<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                                                   49413&#13;
&#13;
                                                 Core Course:&#13;
                                      New Skills in Economic Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Ray C. Rist                        WBI Evaluation Unit World Bank                               William A. Eckert&#13;
Advisor                                                                                         Senior Evaluator&#13;
(202) 458-5625                                                                                   (202) 458-1584&#13;
&#13;
Number 2                                                                                              March 1998&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Araujo, Jorge&#13;
(Notation: The World Bank Institute was formerly called the Economic Development Institute (EDI), as reflected in&#13;
some text)&#13;
&#13;
A Core Course on New Skills in Economic Growth was held in Washington, D.C. from February 9 - 14,&#13;
1998. This was the first of four course sessions planned for presentation during calendar year 1998 by&#13;
EDIMP. The primary goal of these course offerings is to strengthen participants' analytical and research&#13;
skills in the field of economic growth, and to enhance their capabilities to provide sound analysis and policy&#13;
advice for achieving equitable and sustainable growth. Fifty-one participants attended this course session,&#13;
consisting mainly of economists and other key personnel from partner institutions in developing countries.&#13;
The session was evaluated by the EDI Evaluation Unit using an end-of-course questionnaire. The&#13;
questionnaire consisted of two main sections. One section asked participants to rate aspects of the course&#13;
on the extent that the course met standard performance criteria. These performance criteria included the&#13;
level and quality of support provided by course sponsors, the ability of presenters and appropriateness of&#13;
course materials, and the degree to which participants felt they had received suitable training. The second&#13;
main section asked participants to rate their levels of information or knowledge about topics covered in the&#13;
course, before and after completing the course. This attempted to measure achievement through&#13;
participant self-assessment. A 5-point Likert type scale that ranged from 1 = minimum to 5 = maximum&#13;
was used to rate participant response for each item. Following is a summary of these evaluation results:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     ·    Overall ratings for the course's performance in different areas were high. Given that the scale's&#13;
          theoretical mid-point is 3.0, the mean score for all items was above that point. This suggests that&#13;
          on all of the indicators assessed, including content and delivery, participants expressed a high&#13;
          level of satisfaction with the course.&#13;
&#13;
     ·    A key indicator of course performance is the question that asks participants if this course was a&#13;
          worthwhile use of their time. On this indicator, results were very favorable. Participant mean score&#13;
          was 4.35 out of 5.0. This was one of the highest ratings received in this evaluation.&#13;
&#13;
     ·    Highest course ratings were given to support functions. These included the accommodations and&#13;
          administrative support provided. Each of these received a mean score of 4.35 out of 5.0, among&#13;
          the highest scores received in this evaluation.&#13;
&#13;
     ·    Two items stand out for their relatively low mean scores. These were both related to policy issues.&#13;
          One was the extent participants felt they learned about new policies. The other was learning about&#13;
          the consequences of new policies. These areas may be worth reviewing in future offerings and&#13;
          consideration given to why they were not rated as highly as other items.&#13;
&#13;
     ·    Pre/post self-assessment learning questions show substantial gain for ll items. These items were&#13;
          selected as issues that the course attempted to impart to participants. This consistent gain&#13;
          suggests that participants felt they did learn what the course's designers anticipated they would&#13;
          learn.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
· On three items, participants indicated that their pre-course knowledge was relatively low. Each of&#13;
  these areas had a mean score of at or very near 3.0. It may be worth directing additional course&#13;
  time towards these areas, given the relative paucity in information reported by participants. These&#13;
  items also registered some of the greatest gains between pre and post knowledge levels reported&#13;
  by participants.&#13;
&#13;
· Pre-course mean scores were generally in the 3.0-range. This measure can serve as an indicator&#13;
  of how much participants felt they knew about a topic upon entering the course. Its value is that it&#13;
  attempts to assess this level of information only after the course was completed. A high score on&#13;
  the pre-test would suggest that this topic should be reviewed for its contribution to new information&#13;
  for participants. The findings from this course show that these scores were not high enough to&#13;
  suggest that participants felt they knew a great deal about any of the topics upon entering the&#13;
  course.&#13;
&#13;
· The consistent gains in pre/post information reported by participants should be interpreted with&#13;
  caution. These gains were impressive and do reflect the belief by participants that they received a&#13;
  great deal from this course. However, this is not a valid measure of what was actually learned by&#13;
  participants. Future course offerings would benefit from developing and administering cognitively&#13;
  based questions capable of assessing what was truly learned by participants in the course, as&#13;
  opposed to what they feel they gained.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="10905294">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1998/03/10905294/core-course-new-skills-economic-growth
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1998/03/10905294/core-course-new-skills-economic-growth</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1998/03/10905294/core-course-new-skills-economic-growth</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2009/08/04/000334955_20090804040807/Rendered/INDEX/494130WBWP0Cor10Box341953B01PUBLIC1.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2009/08/04/000334955_20090804040807/Rendered/PDF/494130WBWP0Cor10Box341953B01PUBLIC1.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1998-03-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2009-08-04T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Core course : new skills in economic growth
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The primary goal of these course
            offerings is to strengthen participants' analytical and
            research skills in the field of economic growth, and to
            enhance their capabilities to provide sound analysis and
            policy advice for achieving equitable and sustainable
            growth. Fifty-one participants attended this course session,
            consisting mainly of economists and other key personnel from
            partner institutions in developing countries. The session
            was evaluated by the Economic Development Institute (EDI)
            evaluation unit using an end-of-course questionnaire. The
            questionnaire consisted of two main sections. One section
            asked participants to rate aspects of the course on the
            extent that the course met standard performance criteria.
            These performance criteria included the level and quality of
            support provided by course sponsors, the ability of
            presenters and appropriateness of course materials, and the
            degree to which participants felt they had received suitable
            training. The second main section asked participants to rate
            their levels of information or knowledge about topics
            covered in the course, before and after completing the
            course. This attempted to measure achievement through
            participant self-assessment.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Core course : new skills in economic growth
        </docna>
        <display_title>Core course : new skills in
            economic growth</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1998/03/10905294/core-course-new-skills-economic-growth</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>WBI Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Secondary Education,Knowledge for Development,Educational Sciences,Poverty Impact Evaluation,E-Business,Agricultural Knowledge and Information Systems</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Private Sector Development,Poverty Reduction,Agriculture,Education</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Araujo, Jorge;</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000334955_20090804040807</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>WBI working paper core course ; no. 2</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Private Sector Development,Poverty Reduction,Agriculture,Education</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            ability, achievement, administrative
            support, Bank, capabilities, content, contribution, course
            materials, course offerings, Economic Development, Economic
            Growth, Evaluation, indicators, information, institutions,
            Its, knowledge, knowledge levels, learning, materials,
            Notation, participants, performance, policies, policy
            issues, questionnaire, research, results, Senior, Skills,
            standard, text, training, value, worth
        </keywd>
        <owner>Econ. Policy, Poverty &amp; Gender (MNSED)</owner>
        <repnb>49413</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Randomized Control Trials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Green Growth and Sustainability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Green Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Secondary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>