<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                                                    49428&#13;
&#13;
     Evaluation of the Inaugural Banking Supervision Program of the&#13;
        Toronto International Leadership Center for Financial Sector&#13;
                                         Supervision&#13;
&#13;
Ray C. Rist             WBI Evaluation Unit World Bank                             William A. Eckert&#13;
Advisor                                                                    Senior Evaluation Advisor&#13;
(202) 458-5625                                                                      (202) 458-1584&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Number 17                                                                        September 1998&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Ward, Mary Elizabeth&#13;
(Notation: The World Bank Institute was formerly called the Economic Development Institute&#13;
(EDI), as reflected in some text)&#13;
&#13;
The Toronto International Leadership Centre for Financial Sector Supervision held its&#13;
inaugural program in Toronto, Canada, from July 19 - 24, 1998. The Toronto Centre was&#13;
recently created by the World Bank and the Canadian Government, in cooperation with York&#13;
University's Schulich School of Business, the International Monetary Fund and the Bank for&#13;
International Settlements. Its objective is to strengthen financial markets by enhancing the&#13;
leadership capabilities of public sector executives. The target group for the Toronto Centre's&#13;
programs is comprised of the most senior executives whose primary responsibility is banking&#13;
supervision. Individuals from 14 countries participated in the inaugural program session. Of&#13;
these, 3 (21.4%) were women. This inaugural program offering was considered a "pilot" effort&#13;
from which valuable lessons could be learned for future program offerings. A number of&#13;
pedagogical methods were used in this program.&#13;
&#13;
The EDI Evaluation Unit (EDIES) designed and supported the evaluation. The evaluation&#13;
consisted of several components. A rapid response form was used to assess individual&#13;
Program Leaders on the content of their work sessions and on their presentation ability. This&#13;
short form contained 10 questions that used a 5-point Likert type scale along with general,&#13;
open-ended questions. An evaluation form designed to assess general satisfaction with the&#13;
program and to assess learning was also used in the evaluation. This form was administered&#13;
at the end of the course and also used a 5-point Likert type scale. One part of this final&#13;
evaluation form asked questions about the overall performance of the program, including&#13;
accommodations and other means of support. The second part consisted of questions&#13;
designed to assess the perceived level of information gain by participants. This method&#13;
involves asking participants to judge their level of knowledge or information on a set of course&#13;
related topics before and after the course. These measures are taken at the end of the&#13;
course in order to provide a common baseline among participants for making these&#13;
judgments. Comparing the before and after results provides a valid indication of perceived&#13;
growth in knowledge/information among participants. Data from the evaluation were collected&#13;
and processed by EDIRP staff. The analysis of these data were conducted by the EDI&#13;
Evaluation Unit. Following is a summary of the evaluation results.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     l  The rapid response forms showed some variation among Program Leaders on both&#13;
        their presentations and the content of their cases. While this was worth noting to the&#13;
        individual leaders, the amount of variation was not great. Most Program Leaders&#13;
        scored in the high range on both presentation and content.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     l  Combining the results of the rapid response forms shows little variation in the scores&#13;
        for the Program Leaders' presentations and Case content. All items received a score&#13;
        of over 4.0 on a 5-point scale. Within the domain of presentation, the item which&#13;
        received the highest score (4.61) was the view that the course, "imparted useful&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 supervisory advice and skills." The item receiving the lowest score in this area was&#13;
 the view that the course, "treated issues in sufficient depth." The score for this item&#13;
 was 4.34, which still is relatively high on a 5-point scale.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
lFor content of the Case presentations, 2 items received the lowest score. These were&#13;
 the degree to which the course, "covered topics relevant to your country&#13;
 needs," (4.22) and whether the course, "provided enough material to serve as a useful&#13;
 basis for discussion but not too much to overwhelm" (4.23). The highest score, 4.52,&#13;
 was for, "use of English which was easy to understand." It should be noted that these&#13;
 scores were on a 5-point scale and none were low enough to indicate a problem.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
lThe end of program questionnaire consisted of 21 questions that asked about various&#13;
 features of the program, including issues related to the substance of the training and&#13;
 the logistical operations for the event. The first 12 questions used a 5-point scale that&#13;
 measured "intensity" on an issue and ranged from 1=minimum to 5=maximum. On&#13;
 these questions, the average range of scores for all respondents was 4.23 - 4.69 out&#13;
 of 5.0. Overall, these were very high, or positive, scores. The item with the lowest&#13;
 score, 4.23, was the usefulness of the Risk Factor/Core Principles Questionnaire.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
lThe remaining 9 questions on the end of program questionnaire used a 5-point scale&#13;
 that ranged from 1=too little to 5=too much. The mid-point, 3=just right, was&#13;
 considered the ideal score. The number and percentage of score above and below 3.0&#13;
 were also reported as indicators of direction away from the ideal score. All of the&#13;
 scores were 3.0 or higher (3.0 to 3.62), indicating a general inclination for respondents&#13;
 to find the course item "too much" rather than "too little." This is confirmed by&#13;
 observing the percentages above and below 3.0. On only one item, the amount of&#13;
 reading sent in advance, did the percentage responding that it was "too little" exceed&#13;
 the percentage responding "too much." For all other items, there was the general&#13;
 inclination that there was "too much" offered.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
lResults from the pre/post self-assessment showed a substantial gain in information or&#13;
 skills in all areas. The item which showed the highest gain was an increase in the&#13;
 ability to access an international peer network as a resource. This item showed an&#13;
 increase from pre to post of over 71% (71.15%). Since one of the major objectives of&#13;
 the program was to promote this type of networking, this is an important finding. The&#13;
 area which showed the least change was in the ability to, "critically analyze your&#13;
 country environment." This item increased nearly 28% (27.78%), the smallest&#13;
 increase of all items. It appears that respondents may have felt comfortable with this&#13;
 information prior to entering the course.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
lSome valuable information was obtained from the open-ended questions. There were 3&#13;
 questions which asked for 1) the most useful part of the program, 2) the least useful&#13;
 and 3) other advice/suggestions. The most useful items noted were the analytical&#13;
 tools/conceptual approach, interface with program leaders and the Case Studies. This&#13;
 was a mixture of pedagogical methods and content. Found least useful were the&#13;
 amount of time devoted to the Group/Team work and the repetitiveness of some&#13;
 information. A number of respondents felt that time could be saved by more efficient&#13;
 handling of the group presentations. Of the 14 respondents to the question of whether&#13;
 they would recommend this course to others, all responded in the affirmative.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
lThe evaluation, as well as the program, were pilots and intended to provide information&#13;
 that could be used to make changes for later sessions. Based upon this information,&#13;
 there are several limitations to the evaluation that should be considered in future&#13;
 efforts. One major objective is the use of self-assessment as an indicator of&#13;
 knowledge gain. This should be supplemented later with more reliable measures,&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
such as those obtained from using cognitively based questions. More information&#13;
could also be gained by linking the questionnaire responses. An anonymous method&#13;
could be employed to link the end of program questionnaire with the rapid response&#13;
questionnaires. This would provide more extensive data on course topics. Finally,&#13;
some effort should begin on tracking respondents so that information on course&#13;
impact can be collected.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="10920881">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1998/09/10920881/evaluation-inaugural-banking-supervision-program-toronto-international-leadership-center-financial-sector-supervision
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1998/09/10920881/evaluation-inaugural-banking-supervision-program-toronto-international-leadership-center-financial-sector-supervision</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1998/09/10920881/evaluation-inaugural-banking-supervision-program-toronto-international-leadership-center-financial-sector-supervision</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2009/08/07/000333037_20090807000318/Rendered/INDEX/494280WBWP0Cor10Box341953B01PUBLIC1.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2009/08/07/000333037_20090807000318/Rendered/PDF/494280WBWP0Cor10Box341953B01PUBLIC1.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2009-08-07T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1998-09-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Evaluation of the inaugural banking
            supervision program of the Toronto international leadership
            center for financial sector supervision
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Toronto international leadership
            centre for financial sector supervision held its inaugural
            program in Toronto, Canada, from July 19-24, 1998. The
            Toronto centre was recently created by the World Bank and
            the Canadian Government, in cooperation with York
            University's Schulich School of business, the
            international monetary fund and the Bank for international
            settlements. Its objective is to strengthen financial
            markets by enhancing the leadership capabilities of public
            sector executives. The target group for the Toronto
            centre's programs is comprised of the most senior
            executives whose primary responsibility is banking
            supervision. Individuals from 14 countries participated in
            the inaugural program session. Of these, three (21.4
            percent) were women. This inaugural program offering was
            considered a 'pilot' effort from which valuable
            lessons could be learned for future program offerings. A
            number of pedagogical methods were used in this program.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Evaluation of the inaugural banking
            supervision program of the Toronto international leadership
            center for financial sector supervision
        </docna>
        <display_title>Evaluation of the inaugural
            banking supervision program of the Toronto international
            leadership center for financial sector supervision</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1998/09/10920881/evaluation-inaugural-banking-supervision-program-toronto-international-leadership-center-financial-sector-supervision</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>WBI Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>m,E-Business,Education for Development (superceded),Scientific Research &amp; Science Parks,Information Security &amp; Privacy</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Science and Technology Development,Private Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Ward, Mary Elizabeth</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20090807000318</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>WBI working paper core course ; no. 17</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Science and Technology Development,Private Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            capabilities, discussion, domain, Economic
            Development, financial markets, Financial Sector, interface,
            learning, level of knowledge, material, Notation,
            questionnaire, questionnaires, reading, results, Senior,
            Supervision, valuable, worth
        </keywd>
        <owner>CPA Learning Services (CPALS)</owner>
        <repnb>49428</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>