<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                                                   49442&#13;
&#13;
                                          Core Course:&#13;
         Building Knowledge and Expertise in Infrastructure Finance&#13;
&#13;
Ray C. Rist                  WBI Evaluation Unit World Bank                          Fumika Ouchi&#13;
Advisor                                                                          Evaluation Analyst&#13;
(202) 458-5625                                                                      (202) 473-5058&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Number 30                                                                            March 1999&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Dailami, Mansoor&#13;
The Regulatory Reform and Private Enterprise Division of WBI (WBIRP) conducted a core&#13;
course on Building Knowledge and Expertise in Infrastructure Finance in Beirut, Lebanon from&#13;
December 7-18, 1998. This was the third offering of the Infrastructure Finance series in 1998,&#13;
following courses held in Seoul, Korea, in May and in Washington, D.C., in June. The&#13;
objective of the course was to improve participants' understanding of the following areas of&#13;
infrastructure finance: 1) analysis, management, and financing of infrastructure projects; 2)&#13;
international best practices and state-of-the-art techniques in the process of concession&#13;
rights award, contract design, and negotiation; 3) constraints and challenges faced by&#13;
contracting parties; and 4) links between sectoral policy reforms, technologies, regulatory&#13;
structures, and private finances. The course was attended by a total of 40 participants from&#13;
11 countries in the Middle East and North Africa (MENA) region, represented by government&#13;
officials, private executives, and financiers in developing countries who were involved in&#13;
infrastructure development and finance, as well as representatives from the Islamic&#13;
Development Bank and the Arab Fund for Economic and Social Development.&#13;
&#13;
The WBI Evaluation Unit conducted a Level 1 (participants' reaction) evaluation using a&#13;
participants' feedback questionnaire. The questionnaire consisted of three sections. The first&#13;
section asked the extent to which the respondents were satisfied with course content and&#13;
delivery. The second section asked the level of respondents knowledge about course topics&#13;
before and after the course, based on self-assessment. A 5-point Likert type scale that&#13;
ranged from 1=minimum to 5=maximum was used for the first time in this course offering for&#13;
each question. The third section was respondents' open-ended comments about the course.&#13;
The questionnaire was completed by 34 respondents, 85% of the total participants.&#13;
&#13;
In the data analysis, this course was compared with the two previous 1998 course offerings&#13;
that had the same course objectives. Since the courses in Korea and Washington, D. C.&#13;
used a 6-point scale in their course evaluation, results of the Lebanon course were adjusted&#13;
by using the scale adjustment factor described in an WBI's recent technical review (Gaur and&#13;
Eckert, "Evaluating EDI Participant Reactions via Different Response Scales: A Technical&#13;
Review," p.12-13,1998). The scale adjustment factor, 0.78, was added to the mean scores&#13;
measured on a 5-point scale for course content and delivery in the Lebanon course, in order&#13;
to compare scores obtained on a 6-point scale in Korea and Washington. The use of the&#13;
adjustment factor provided comparability between mean scores measured on different scales&#13;
across the three course offerings. Following is a summary of the evaluation findings.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Respondents' Background&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     l  Table 1 summarizes key characteristics of respondents in the three course offerings.&#13;
        The Lebanon course was represented by a larger percentage of respondents from the&#13;
        public sector (91.2%), compared to the two previous courses in Korea (24.2%) and&#13;
        Washington, D.C (65.5%). The Lebanon course also had a higher proportion of&#13;
        respondents with advanced academic degrees. Twenty-eight out of the 34 respondents&#13;
        in Lebanon (82.4%) reported to have had either masters degrees or equivalent (N=23)&#13;
        or doctorate degrees (N=5), whereas 28.8% in Korea and 74.5% in Washington had&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
      the advanced degrees.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    l The Lebanon course was different from the other two courses in another key&#13;
      demographic composition of respondents. Respondents in Lebanon were represented&#13;
      by those with more work experience in the area of infrastructure finance and&#13;
      development. Half of the respondents (50%) in the Lebanon course reported to have&#13;
      had at least 6 years of experience, while 18.2% in Korea and 40% in Washington had&#13;
      the similar length of experience in the area.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    l The number of women respondents remained low for the Lebanon course. In the two&#13;
      previous course offerings, 1 out of 66 respondents (1.5%) in Korea and 10 out of 55&#13;
      (18.2%) in Washington were women. The Lebanon course had 3 women respondents&#13;
      out of the total 34 respondents (8.8%).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            Table 1: Respondents' Backgrounds&#13;
                 Response         Public       Advanced       6 years or       Women2&#13;
                 rate1            Sector2      Degrees3       more&#13;
                                                              Experience2&#13;
&#13;
Lebanon (%)      85.0 (N=34)          91.2          82.4            50.0           8.8&#13;
Korea (%)        79.5 (N=66)          24.2          28.8            18.2           1.5&#13;
Washington       82.1 (N=55)          65.5          74.5            40.0           18.2&#13;
(%)&#13;
&#13;
1. Total number of participants: 40 in Lebanon, 83 in Korea, and 67 in Washington, DC&#13;
&#13;
             2. Percentage (%) of the public sector, advanced degrees, work experience and&#13;
             women are based on the number of total respondents&#13;
&#13;
3. Advanced academic degrees: masters degrees or equivalent, or doctorate degrees&#13;
&#13;
Course Performance&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    l Table 2 shows respondents' ratings of how each course performed on five selected&#13;
      indicators measuring course content and delivery. Mean scores that were adjusted&#13;
      from a 5-point to 6-point scale ("adjusted means") were shown for the Lebanon course,&#13;
      along with the original scores measured on a 5-point scale.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    l The overall usefulness of the course in Lebanon received a mean score of 3.82 on a 5-&#13;
      point scale, or an adjusted mean score of 4.60. This was the highest score among all&#13;
      course performance indicators for the Lebanon course. The usefulness of the lecture&#13;
      presentations (adjusted mean=4.49) and reading materials (adjusted mean=4.57) were&#13;
      also among the highest ratings. The adjusted mean scores fell between the two mean&#13;
      scores of Korea and Washington, indicating that the Lebanon course had a similar&#13;
      performance result with the two previous courses on these three indicators.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    l Compared with the previous courses, the Lebanon course had relatively lower ratings&#13;
      on indicators measuring course content. The extent to which the course provided a&#13;
      variety of viewpoints (adjusted mean=4.22) and the course focused on issues of&#13;
      respondents' needs (adjusted mean=4.08) were reported much lower than the&#13;
      corresponding ratings for Korea (mean=4.50 for viewpoints and 4.42 for focus) and&#13;
      Washington (mean=4.36 and 4.44, respectively). The two ratings of course content&#13;
      were also among the lowest scores in all performance indicators measured in the&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
       Lebanon course.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    l  In their written comments, respondents in the Lebanon course made a number of&#13;
       suggestions on how the course could improve its content and focus. They were: 1)&#13;
       break down the course into major infrastructure subject sector, such as&#13;
       telecommunication, power, and transportation, to concentrate more on each sector&#13;
       (N=7); 2) use more case studies and examples of specific regions (N=8); 3) organize&#13;
       small group sessions for more in-depth discussions of subjects (N=4); and 4) choose&#13;
       instructors from academic or private sector institutions who are specialized in the field&#13;
       (N=3).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Table 2. Course Performance: Mean Scores of Selected Indicators&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   Overall        Presentations Reading          Variety of      Focus on&#13;
                   usefulness of                   materials     viewpoints      issues&#13;
                   course&#13;
&#13;
 Lebanon 5-         3.82 (0.58)3    3.71 (0.63)     3.79 (0.73)     3.44 (0.75)   3.30 (0.73)&#13;
 Point Scale&#13;
&#13;
 Adjusted                    4.60            4.49            4.57            4.22          4.08&#13;
 Mean&#13;
&#13;
 Korea              4.532 (0.93)    4.44 (0.90)     4.55(0.81)      4.50 (0.77)    4.42(0.86)&#13;
 6-point scale&#13;
&#13;
 Washington         4.672 (0.77)    4.55 (0.81)     4.64 (0.87)     4.36 (0.89)   4.44 (0.92)&#13;
 6-point scale&#13;
1. Adjusted Mean: The scale adjustment factor of 0.78 was added to the mean score&#13;
measured on the 5-point scale for each question.&#13;
2. For Korea and Washington, the indicator "overall usefulness of the course" was worded as&#13;
"worthwhile use of time."&#13;
3. Figures in ( ) indicate standard deviation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    l  Pre/post knowledge assessment in Lebanon indicated that the respondents'&#13;
       understanding of all 9 key issues presented in the course improved after the course&#13;
       from the 2.24-3.12 range before the course to the 3.33-3.91 range after the course on a&#13;
       5-point scale. Table 3 summarizes the percentage change between pre- and post-&#13;
       course mean scores of 4 selected topics by course offering. The largest gain in the&#13;
       reported pre/post change in Lebanon was on the "clear systems of risk identification&#13;
       and allocation," which had one of the lowest pre-course mean scores but the rating&#13;
       increased by 64% after the course. This topic was also reported as having the largest&#13;
       positive pre/post gain among respondents in Korea (52.6%) and Washington (57.9%).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    l  The "limited resource project financing as applied to infrastructure transactions" was&#13;
       another topic that had a substantial pre/post gain among all respondents in the&#13;
       Lebanon course (56.8%). The gain was also larger than that observed in Washington&#13;
       (41.6%) and particularly, compared with the gain in Korea (33%). In the Lebanon&#13;
       course, this topic was reported to have had the largest effect on the respondents who&#13;
       had less than 6 years of work experience in infrastructure finance (N=17). Twelve out of&#13;
       the 17 respondents with less than 6 years of experience (71%) reported either 1 or 2&#13;
       on a 5-point scale on this topic, creating the lowest mean score before the course for&#13;
       this group of respondents. Their post-course ratings improved by 61%. This was the&#13;
       largest pre/post gain for the respondents who had relatively fewer years of work&#13;
       experience in the Lebanon course.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    l  Across the three course offerings, respondents reported the smallest pre/post change&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
      Across the three course offerings, respondents reported the smallest pre/post change&#13;
      on the "role of contracting." While the post-course mean score on this topic was&#13;
      among the highest in each course offering, respondents also indicated a high degree of&#13;
      familiarity with the topic before entering the course. This resulted in a small pre/post&#13;
      difference for each course. Another topic on contract, "how to develop a contract," was&#13;
      among the most familiar topics for the respondents in Lebanon before the course. Their&#13;
      pre-course knowledge level of this topic was one of the highest, and the pre/post&#13;
      change was one of the smallest (28.9%).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    l Course organizer should be reminded that the two topics on contract (the "role of&#13;
      contracting" and "how to develop a contract") were also found to be the items that&#13;
      showed the largest knowledge gap between respondents of different work background&#13;
      at the end of the Lebanon course. Results by years of work experience indicated that&#13;
      post-course knowledge levels reported by the respondents with 6 years or more&#13;
      experience were higher than the levels reported by those with less than 6 years of&#13;
      experience across topics (difference in mean scores ranging from +0.19 to +0.46 point&#13;
      on a 5-point scale). Their difference was much larger on two contract issues (difference&#13;
      ranging from 0.8 to 0.9), showing the largest difference in the level of knowledge&#13;
      between the two groups of respondents.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    l Learning gain was based on the respondents' self-assessment in each course offering.&#13;
      The pre/post changes observed in the three courses, therefore, did not reflect how&#13;
      much the respondents actually learned in each course. The course organizer is&#13;
      encouraged to use a measure that could capture the level of respondents' learning,&#13;
      such as the administration of a set of questions on course topics before and after the&#13;
      course.&#13;
&#13;
                 Table 3. Self-Reported Knowledge on Selected Topics&#13;
                           Pre-/Post-Course Percentage Change1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           Risk             Limited            Role of        How to develop&#13;
                     identification        resource          contracting         a contract&#13;
                     and allocation        financing&#13;
&#13;
Lebanon (%)                64.0               56.8               25.2               28.9&#13;
Korea (%)                  52.6               33.0               28.9               35.8&#13;
Washington (%)             57.9               41.6               30.3               46.4&#13;
1. Percentage change: [post mean score ­ pre mean score] / pre mean score x 10&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="10934367">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/03/10934367/core-course-building-knowledge-expertise-infrastructure-finance
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/03/10934367/core-course-building-knowledge-expertise-infrastructure-finance</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1999/03/10934367/core-course-building-knowledge-expertise-infrastructure-finance</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2009/08/11/000333038_20090811003313/Rendered/INDEX/494420WBWP0Cor10Box341953B01PUBLIC1.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2009/08/11/000333038_20090811003313/Rendered/PDF/494420WBWP0Cor10Box341953B01PUBLIC1.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2009-08-11T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1999-03-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Core course : building knowledge and
            expertise in infrastructure finance
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Regulatory Reform and Private
            Enterprise Division of World Bank Institute (WBIRP)
            conducted a core course on building knowledge and expertise
            in infrastructure finance in Beirut, Lebanon from December
            7-18, 1998. This was the third offering of the
            infrastructure finance series in 1998, following courses
            held in Seoul, Korea, in May and in Washington, D.C., in
            June. The objective of the course was to improve
            participants' understanding of the following areas of
            infrastructure finance: 1) analysis, management, and
            financing of infrastructure projects; 2) international best
            practices and state-of-the-art techniques in the process of
            concession rights award, contract design, and negotiation;
            3) constraints and challenges faced by contracting parties;
            and 4) links between sectoral policy reforms, technologies,
            regulatory structures, and private finances. The course was
            attended by a total of 40 participants from 11 countries in
            the Middle East and North Africa (MENA) region, represented
            by government officials, private executives, and financiers
            in developing countries who were involved in infrastructure
            development and finance, as well as representatives from the
            Islamic Development Bank and the Arab Fund for Economic and
            Social Development.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Core course : building knowledge and
            expertise in infrastructure finance
        </docna>
        <display_title>Core course : building knowledge
            and expertise in infrastructure finance</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1999/03/10934367/core-course-building-knowledge-expertise-infrastructure-finance</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>WBI Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Secondary Education,m,Education for Development (superceded),Educational Sciences,Debt Markets</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Education,Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Dailami, Mansoor</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333038_20090811003313</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>WBI working paper core course ; no. 30</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Education,Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            academic degrees, adjustment, advanced
            degrees, best practices, contract design, course content,
            course offerings, developing countries, Development Bank,
            discussions, finances, infrastructure development,
            Infrastructure Finance, instructors, knowledge gap,
            knowledge level, knowledge levels, Learning, level of
            knowledge, questionnaire, regulatory structures, Social
            Development, subjects, variety, work experience
        </keywd>
        <owner>Development Prospects Group (DECPG)</owner>
        <repnb>49442</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Secondary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>