<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                       52236&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 Are your hands&#13;
                                  clean enough?&#13;
                    Study Findings on Handwashing With Soap Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
REPUBLIC OF KENYA&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;      Are your hands&#13;
       clean enough?&#13;
Study Findings on Handwashing With Soap Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   &#13;
&amp;#12; Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
FOREWORD&#13;
EXECUTIVE SUMMARY&#13;
List of Boxes, Figures, and Tables                                                        4-5&#13;
Acronyms and Abbreviations                                                                6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SECTION ONE: INTRODUCTION                                                                 14&#13;
.        Research Background                                                              4&#13;
.        Justification of Research                                                        4&#13;
.        Objectives of the Research                                                       4&#13;
.4       Methodology                                                                      4&#13;
.5       Field Challenges                                                                 5&#13;
.6       Project Learning                                                                 5&#13;
.7       Report Structure                                                                 5&#13;
.0       Background Information                                                           6&#13;
.        Background on Kenya                                                              6&#13;
.        Under-Five Mortality and Incidences of Diarrhea Cases                            6&#13;
.        Kenyan Soap Market                                                               7&#13;
&#13;
SECTION TWO: COMMUNITY STUDY                                                              18&#13;
.0       Methods Used in the Community Study                                              8&#13;
4.0      Results                                                                          0&#13;
4.       Baseline on Handwashing                                                          0&#13;
4.       Procedures of Washing Hands                                                      4&#13;
4.       Perception of Important Junctures of Handwashing with Soap                       5&#13;
4.4      Sanitation Environment in Community                                              5&#13;
4.5      Background of Respondents                                                        7&#13;
4.6      Knowledge and Attitudes towards Handwashing                                      8&#13;
4.7      Motivators and Barriers to Handwashing with Soap (`Why?')                        0&#13;
4.8      Barriers to Handwashing                                                          7&#13;
4.9      Communicating with the Community                                                 40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SECTION THREE:THE SCHOOLS' STUDY                                                          42&#13;
5.0      Sanitation and Hygiene in Kenyan Schools                                         4&#13;
5.       Background                                                                       4&#13;
5.       Handwashing Initiatives in Schools                                               4&#13;
5.       Justification of the School Study                                                4&#13;
5.4      Objectives of the School Study                                                   4&#13;
6.0      Methods Used in the School Study                                                 45&#13;
6..      Overview of Methods                                                              45&#13;
6.       Selection and Description of Schools for Study                                   45&#13;
7.0      RESULTS                                                                          46&#13;
7.       Baseline Behavior of Children in School                                          46&#13;
7.       Handwashing in the Community versus Schools                                      46&#13;
7.       Effect of Placing Soap in Schools                                                46&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   &#13;
&amp;#12;7.4        Knowledge, Perception, and Attitude towards Hygiene and HWWS                     48&#13;
7.5        Motivators for Children Washing Hands                                            49&#13;
7.6        Barriers to Handwashing with Soap in Schools                                     5&#13;
7.7.       Communication with Children                                                      5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SECTION FOUR: CONCLUSIONS AND RECOMMENDATIONS                                               58&#13;
8.         Conclusions                                                                      58&#13;
8.         Recommendations                                                                  59&#13;
Appendix A:        Background Information on Schools in the Study                           60&#13;
Appendix B:        Physical Observations of Hygiene Standards                               6&#13;
References                                                                                  6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
List of Boxes&#13;
Box 4.:            Nurture and Handwashing                                                  &#13;
Box 4.:            Comfort and Handwashing                                                  &#13;
Box 4.:            Disgust and Handwashing                                                  &#13;
Box 4.4:           Fitting in and Handwashing                                               4&#13;
Box 4.5:           Status and Handwashing                                                   5&#13;
Box 4.6:           Purity and Handwashing                                                   5&#13;
Box 4.7:           Attraction and Handwashing                                               6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
List of Figures&#13;
Figure 4.:         Proportion of Households that Experienced Water Shortage in&#13;
                    the last One Year                                                       6&#13;
Figure 7.:         Handwashing Before and After Placing Soap                                47&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
List of Tables&#13;
Table .:           Population and Poverty Incidences across the Study Provinces             6&#13;
Table .:           Main Soap Brands in the Market and Pricing                               7&#13;
Table .:           Summary of Study Methods                                                 8&#13;
Table .:           Summary of Junctures and Persons Observed                                9&#13;
Table 4.:          Consistent Handwashing                                                   &#13;
Table 4.:          Any Handwashing by Primary and Secondary Caregivers across Regions       &#13;
Table 4.:          Handwashing with or without Soap Based on Events Observed&#13;
                   across Regions                                                           &#13;
Table 4.4:         Handwashing with or without Soap Based on Events Observed&#13;
                   across Junctures                                                         &#13;
Table 4.5:         Handwashing with and without Soap by Primary Child Caregiver in Uganda   4&#13;
Table 4.6:         Handwashing with Soap by Primary Caregivers Based on Events Observed&#13;
                   across Junctures and Region                                              4&#13;
Table 4.7:         "What Do You Think are the Key Times When You Must WHWS?"                5&#13;
Table 4.8:         Toilet Facilities at the Household Level                                 6&#13;
Table 4.9:         Main Sources of Water                                                    6&#13;
Table 4.0:         Demographic Characteristics                                              7&#13;
Table 4.:          Summary of Mothers' Aspirations                                          8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 4 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;Table 4.:    Summary of Barriers and Biggest Fears to Realization of Dreams                       9&#13;
Table 4.:    Motivating Factors                                                                   0&#13;
Table 4.4:   Individual Rankings of Handwashing Motivations by Female Focus Group&#13;
             Discussion Participants                                                              0&#13;
Table 4.5:   Access to Water and Cleansing Agents                                                 8&#13;
Table 4.6:   Communication Channels                                                               40&#13;
Table 6.:    School-Based Study Methods                                                           45&#13;
Table 7.:    Handwashing Behavior in Schools Before Placing the Soap                              46&#13;
Table 7.:    Handwashing After Defecation in the Community and School Environment                 46&#13;
Table 7.:    Children's Views on Practising Handwashing with Soap (by District)                   49&#13;
Table 7.4:   Children's Dislikes on Practising Handwashing with Soap (by District)                5&#13;
Table 7.5:   Children's Role Models                                                               54&#13;
Table 7.6:   Perception of `Cool'                                                                 55&#13;
Table 7.7:   Summary of Social Mapping                                                            56&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                               Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   5&#13;
&amp;#12;ACRONYMS AND ABBREVIATIONS&#13;
&#13;
AIDS                         Acquired Immuno-Deficiency Syndrome&#13;
ARI                          Acute Respiratory Infections&#13;
AMREF                        African Medical Research Foundation&#13;
BT                           Behavior Trails&#13;
CARE                         Cooperative for American Relief Everywhere&#13;
CBO                          Community-Based Organization&#13;
CBS                          Central Bureau of Statistics&#13;
FGD                          Focus Group Discussions&#13;
FPE                          Free Primary Education&#13;
GTZ                          German Technical Cooperation&#13;
HIV                          Human Immunodeficiency Virus&#13;
HW                           Hand Washing&#13;
HWWS or WHWS                 Handwashing with Soap&#13;
IDI                          In-Depth Interviews&#13;
IMR                          Infant Mortality Rate&#13;
LC                           Local Council&#13;
Leaky Tins                   Improvised handwashing facilities made from a jerrycan. A stick is inserted into a hole; the&#13;
                             stick is removed while washing hands and replaced to block the water from spilling out&#13;
MoE                          Ministry of Education&#13;
NETWAS                       Network for Water and Sanitation&#13;
NGO                          Non-Governmental Organization&#13;
SES                          Social Economic Status&#13;
TV                           Television&#13;
UNICEF                       United Nation Children's Fund&#13;
WHO                          World Health Organization&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 6 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The Handwashing with Soap Baseline and Consumer study was commissioned by Water and Sanitation Program on&#13;
behalf of Ministry of Public Health and Sanitation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
We would like to acknowledge input and efforts by organizations and individuals who immensely contributed to the&#13;
study at different stages leading to the production of this report. Water and Sanitation Program through Jason Cardosi,&#13;
Japheth Mbuvi and Rufus Eshuchi coordinated and managed the research process implemented by Steadman Kenya Ltd.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
We thank Mr. Kepha Ombacho and Mr. John Kariuki from Ministry of Public Health and Sanitation for their guidance&#13;
and support throughout the process, Ms. Margaret Ndanyi from Ministry of Education and Ms. Rose Ngure from&#13;
Ministry of Water and Irrigation for participating and guiding the preparatory process. Val Curtis and Robert Aunger&#13;
from London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine (LSHTM) and Myriam Sidibe from Unilever Lifebuoy team who&#13;
provided technical assistance to the research agency.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Others who peer reviewed the report were WSPs Sanitation and Hygiene team in East Africa composed of Patrick&#13;
Mwangi, Abdulrazak Badru, Chris Nsubuga-Mugga, Ousseynou Diop, Yolande Coombes, Toni Sittoni, as well as UNICEF&#13;
team composed of Suleiman Malik, Jane Kariuki, Fred Donde and Tobias Omufwoko.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   7&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                   FOREWORD&#13;
&#13;
The National Environmental Sanitation and Hygiene Policy aims to create an enabling environment in which all Kenyans&#13;
can improve hygienic behaviors and environmental sanitation. One among behavioral changes targeted is the practice&#13;
of handwashing with soap, which is considered a better option for disease prevention as a hygiene intervention. Washing&#13;
hands with soap - at the right times - can cut diarrhea risk by half, and respiratory tract infection by a third ­ these are&#13;
two of the largest killers of children under five year olds in Kenya.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
However as demonstrated in this study, handwashing with soap is rarely practiced regularly and at the right times, such as&#13;
before eating or after visiting the latrine. There are many reasons for this, including lack of knowledge on when to wash&#13;
hands, and limited opportunities to do so. In this study, the findings are, while soap is available in 97 percent of households,&#13;
soap for washing hands is uncommon in schools. The only attribute to this is that in Kenya, like elsewhere around the&#13;
world, individuals are simply not motivated to regularly wash hands with soap. .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
To address this situation, several public and private sector organizations have joined the Ministry of Public Health and&#13;
Sanitation to combine state-of the art marketing techniques with public health approaches and institutional structures in&#13;
order to improve and sustain good handwashing behavior. The results of this study serve as a baseline for these efforts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This report provides an opportunity to restate the importance of handwashing with soap promotion and calls on&#13;
stakeholders to renew and broaden their support for the same. It is in this spirit that I believe we can make a difference&#13;
and meet our targets for reductions in child mortality while working together.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
On behalf of the Ministry of Public Health and Sanitation, I am grateful for the support from the Water and Sanitation&#13;
Program ­Africa (WSP-Africa) who commissioned this research, Steadman Research (K) Ltd who carried out the study,&#13;
and the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine and the Unilever Marketing Academy for their technical&#13;
inputs. I am also grateful to the Ministry of Education, Ministry of Water and Irrigation, UNICEF, WHO, NETWAS, Plan&#13;
International, for their helpful contributions. Last but not least we acknowledge the role played by respondents in the&#13;
community as well as schools. You sacrificed your time to participate in various activities that contributed immensely to&#13;
the success of this study.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Mark Bor, EBS&#13;
Permanent Secretary&#13;
Ministry of Public Health and Sanitation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 8 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;                                            Executive Summary&#13;
Washing hands with soap at the right times can reduce instances of diarrhea by 5­50 percent. Evidence also suggests&#13;
that handwashing with soap can reduce acute respiratory infections (ARIs) by 0 percent. Past initiatives in Kenya have&#13;
focused on raising awareness of handwashing with soap but they have not fully translated into behavior. An in-depth&#13;
understanding of motivators and barriers to handwashing at a national level is critical for a behavioral change campaign.&#13;
This study has been designed to provide baseline information on handwashing behavior in detail, by looking at behavior&#13;
practised with regard to handwashing with soap; factors that influence handwashing behavior in schools and in the&#13;
community's context. The study also provides information on preferred and trusted channels of communication.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Methods&#13;
The research utilized both qualitative and quantitative methods of data collection. It was executed at two levels--&#13;
community and schools.&#13;
&#13;
1. Community: It sought to understand handwashing behavior, barriers, and motivators in a community setting. The&#13;
community methods included:&#13;
    a. Structured observations: These involved observing handwashing behavior with or without soap during two&#13;
         key junctures--after contact with feces, and before handling food or eating in households. This was carried out in&#13;
         eight districts and covered 80 households. A total of 5,096 observations were achieved.&#13;
    b. Household interviews: These were carried out with primary caregivers in households where the observations&#13;
         took place. The objective of the household survey was getting the views of the community members on hygiene&#13;
         practises, sources of information and communication channels, and cost of soap or handwashing agents, as well as&#13;
         gathering demographic data of the study respondents.&#13;
    c. Behavioral trials (BT): This involved introducing caregivers of children under five years of age to the behavior&#13;
         of handwashing with soap (HWWS), and later assessing their experiences. A total of 6 trials were achieved.&#13;
    d. Focus group discussions (FGD): These focused on motivators for, and barriers against, handwashing with&#13;
         soap at key junctures and were carried out with both male and female caregivers of children under five years. Eight&#13;
         FGDs were conducted in eight districts.&#13;
    e. In-depth interviews: These were conducted with influential people in the communities of the study; 6 in-&#13;
         depth interviews were carried out in eight districts.&#13;
&#13;
2. School: The school setting targeted children in primary school. This approach sought to understand handwashing&#13;
behavior in school. Previous research in Uganda and Tanzania laid a lot of emphasis on community.The study was conducted&#13;
in  schools. The methods used included:&#13;
    a. Structured observations before and after soap placement: This involved observing handwashing&#13;
         behavior after using the toilet.&#13;
    b. Focus group discussions: FGDs were held with children to understand their way of life, perception of dirt, and&#13;
         attitudes towards handwashing.&#13;
    c. Behavior trials: BTs exposed pupils to handwashing with soap within the school context and later assessed&#13;
         their experience. This was aimed at understanding how easy it is to adopt such behavior, and establishing the&#13;
         barriers that were in the way of such behavior adoption in the school context.&#13;
    d. Drawing: This involved using drawings to identify perceived risky handwashing behavior among pupils in school.&#13;
    e. Social mapping: This required mapping the children's social networks.&#13;
    f. Money game: This was intended to identify what is of value and interest to the children. It involved giving the&#13;
         children a photocopy of a currency note and asking them what they would use it for.&#13;
    g. Diary: This was intended to get an overview of a child's typical day.&#13;
1Hutley, et   al. 1997.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   9&#13;
&amp;#12;      h. Teacher focus group discussions and in-depth interviews: These meant assessing the teachers' opinions&#13;
           on the campaign.&#13;
Qualitative data were analyzed using interpretative analysis through inductive and deductive logic. In addition,&#13;
quantitative data were analyzed through SPSS analysis package using descriptive statistics. Data have been presented&#13;
in charts and tables.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
RESULTS&#13;
Current Handwashing Practises&#13;
Kenyans have a strong culture of washing their face first thing in the morning. Defecation was found to be the first action&#13;
after waking up. Therefore, handwashing after going to the toilet may have been driven more by the need to wash the&#13;
face than the hands. Handwashing behavior was, therefore, looked into from the aspects of: a consistent behavior, any&#13;
handwashing, and based on number of events observed.&#13;
      · Fourteen percent of primary caregivers consistently washed hands at any risky juncture but only 5 percent&#13;
           consistently used soap at all the risky junctures.&#13;
&#13;
Handwashing culture is relatively higher in Mombasa and Nyeri ( percent and  percent consistent handwashing&#13;
with soap) while other regions recorded ­ percent, except Machakos which recorded 4 percent. Unlike other&#13;
regions, Nyeri had good access to water round the year. Mombasa is predominantly Muslim; hence religion may be a&#13;
strong driver of handwashing.&#13;
&#13;
Based on the events observed, caregivers are more likely to wash hands with soap when in contact with stool than when&#13;
handling food.&#13;
      · After suspected self defecation,  percent washed hands with soap.&#13;
      · After other contact with stool, 7 percent washed hands with soap.&#13;
      · After cleaning a child's bottom, 6 percent washed hands with soap.&#13;
      · Before serving or handling food. 5 percent washed hands with soap.&#13;
                                                                       &#13;
      · Before feeding or serving index child,  percent washed hands with soap.&#13;
Caregivers in Kenya are familiar with the concept of handwashing as indicated by any handwashing. Any handwashing in&#13;
this study is defined as `washing hands at least once at any risky juncture'. Primary caregivers recorded handwashing with&#13;
or without soap at 9 percent, and handwashing with soap at 60 percent. Secondary caregivers recorded any handwashing&#13;
with or without soap at 65 percent and 6 percent with soap. The importance of handwashing was emphasized by 94&#13;
percent of caregivers who believe that their family can be healthier if they washed their hands with soap.&#13;
&#13;
Handwashing with soap in school is almost nonexistent--only  percent washed hands with soap and 8 percent washed&#13;
hands in some way. Children are more likely to wash hands at home compared to school. Twenty-three percent of 55&#13;
defecation events observed at the community level washed their hands with soap. Out of the 65 events observed&#13;
among school children at the household level before they ate, 56 percent washed hands but only 8 percent used soap.&#13;
&#13;
Handwashing with soap takes low priority at the household level. It is ranked fourth after bathing; laundry and washing&#13;
dishes are higher priority. Bar soaps have high usage in Kenyan households because of their multiple applications.&#13;
Overall, 97 percent of the households have accessibility to soap. Women are the key decisionmakers on soap usage&#13;
at the household level.&#13;
&#13;
The concept of handwashing at both the community and school level is not separable from the concept of hygiene.&#13;
&#13;
Awareness about the importance of handwashing with soap is high, especially after using the toilet. But awareness&#13;
regarding the relationship between handwashing with soap and diseases, and how this affects the day-to-day lives of&#13;
children and the entire community, is weak.&#13;
2SPSS (originally, Statistical Package for the Social Sciences) is among the most widely used programs for statistical analysis in social science. In addition to statistical analysis, data&#13;
management (case selection, file reshaping, creating derived data) and data documentation (a metadata dictionary is stored with the data) are features of the base software.&#13;
2Index child: Child under five years old on which household selection criteria was based.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
0 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;Motivators for Handwashing&#13;
At the community level, three motivators for handwashing emerged from this study: disgust, comfort and nurture.&#13;
    · Disgust: The strongest motivator where there is strong smell and physical dirt. It is a strong motivator after using&#13;
       the toilet and when in contact with stool.&#13;
    · Nurture: A strong emotional motivator to protect children from illness and see them grow to achieve the&#13;
       dreams parents have for them. Nurture is an effective motivator at junctures that relate to the child, for instance,&#13;
       feeding them or cleaning their bottom.&#13;
    · Comfort: A motivator that gives a mother the flexibility and freedom to continue with her activities.&#13;
&#13;
The motivators of handwashing in a school context were:&#13;
    · Justification: Need to wash away germs that cause disease. This was drawn from the fact that handwashing is&#13;
       covered in the syllabus.&#13;
    · Fun: Handwashing with soap was found to be fun and provided a form of play for the children. This is not a&#13;
       sustainable motivator in the long run but can work at the initial stages of the campaign.&#13;
    · Fitting in: Washing hands after using the toilet is the accepted code of conduct in school. The presence of other&#13;
       children washing hands acted as a trigger to handwashing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Facilitators of Handwashing&#13;
    · Convenient access to soap and water came out strongly as a facilitator at both the community and school level.&#13;
    · The role of teachers as a role model and reminder of the importance of washing hands facilitated the adoption of&#13;
       the behavior. Active participation by teachers in the campaign will be critical to adoption and sustainability of the&#13;
       behavior in schools. The reluctance of teachers to support health clubs in school has reduced the effectiveness of&#13;
       such clubs in promoting hygiene.&#13;
    · Perfumed soap was a facilitator in schools.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Barriers to Handwashing&#13;
Barriers at the community level include:&#13;
    · Lack of soap for handwashing. In poor households, the soap is reserved for high priority usage: laundry, washing&#13;
       dishes, and bathing. Further, poverty minimizes the perceived risk of not washing hands with soap, where the&#13;
       mother has knowledge. Caregivers have many other issues they have to deal with in their lives.This reduces weight&#13;
       given to risks of not washing hands with soap as other issues take priority in her mind.&#13;
    · Poor placement of the soap. Most households keep the soap in places not convenient for handwashing after risky&#13;
       events. Preferred soap locations in rural areas include placing on a shelf in the kitchen or on top of a kitchen&#13;
       cupboard. In urban households, people living in single or two room houses keep soap under the furniture or&#13;
       behind the door. Therefore, soap fails to trigger handwashing behavior.&#13;
    · Lack of a designated place for handwashing in the community. Most communities lack a specific place for washing hands.&#13;
    · Distance between the toilet and source of water is far in most households. This leads to forgetfulness about&#13;
       washing hands after the toilet is finished.&#13;
    · Perfumed soap. Some primary caregivers feel that the perfume of the soap will affect the taste of the food they handle.&#13;
&#13;
Barriers at the school level include:&#13;
    · Placement of the handwashing facilities. The facilities are either very far from the toilets or located in the&#13;
       opposite direction. Children forget to wash hands after the toilet or find it inconvenient to walk to the&#13;
       handwashing facilities.&#13;
    · Level of handwashing facilities. Handwashing facilities in most schools are too high to reach, especially for children&#13;
       in the lower primary classes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   &#13;
&amp;#12;    · Overcrowding at the handwashing facilities.There are limited handwashing facilities to cater for the school population&#13;
       leading to pushing around the facilities. This is a barrier for pupils in lower primary classes and for girls.&#13;
    · Soap disappearance and wastage. Schools that had tried this initiative raised this as the greatest challenge that the&#13;
       initiative faced.&#13;
    · Poor or lack of water drainage of handwashing facilities. This lead to accumulation of dirty water in the trough and&#13;
       spilling around the handwashing site. As a result, the handwashing facilities become muddy and discourage children&#13;
       from washing hands. Bars of soaps fall into the muddy water or disappear in the trough.&#13;
    · Lack of support from teachers. In some schools such an intervention is perceived as an additional workload for&#13;
       teachers who feel they are already overworked. After the introduction of free primary education, the workload&#13;
       for teachers increased drastically. Any additional tasks are likely to face resistance from teachers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Current Channels of Communication&#13;
Overall, radio is the most commonly used and accessible source of information. Television (TV) accessibility is limited to&#13;
urban areas. Health centers and community health workers are the most trusted channel of communication on issues&#13;
to do with hygiene or health. Places of worship, market days, and informal women's group meetings are prime areas to&#13;
capture the mothers' attention.&#13;
&#13;
Access to media for children in rural areas is often limited to radio programs. Urban kids have greater access to TV. But&#13;
children's exposure to any communication through radio and TV is limited to weekends and holidays. Teachers are the&#13;
most trusted channels of communication in the school context.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Conclusions&#13;
    · Handwashing behavior with only water is practiced, especially after contact with stool, but adoption of soap in&#13;
       handwashing needs to be scaled up.&#13;
    · Level of handwashing for primary school children after defecation in school is lower than at home.&#13;
    · Motivators and barriers to handwashing with soap in a school environment are distinct from those at the&#13;
       community level.&#13;
    · Soap and water availability are key facilitators to HWWS. The presence of soap at the handwashing site is of&#13;
       critical importance.&#13;
    · Washing hands with soap takes a lower priority in the hygiene hierarchy.&#13;
    · Radio is the most important form of mass media for mothers. However, men control its listenership most of the time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Recommendations&#13;
There is need for a community- and school-focused campaign. A school-based campaign should consider the following:&#13;
    · Soap used in the school should be in liquid form.&#13;
    · The project should partner with other stakeholders who can prepare dispensers that minimize soap wastage.&#13;
       Practical Action is in the process of developing dispensers that are designed for handwashing in school.&#13;
    · Several other related programs are ongoing in schools. Teachers also relate to handwashing as part of hygiene. In&#13;
       schools children are also taught handwashing as part of the concept of hygiene. Therefore, the HWWS campaign&#13;
       cannot work in isolation; it requires to be integrated into the whole concept of hygiene in school and existing&#13;
       related programs, such as deworming.&#13;
    · The campaign should adopt an integrated approach to incorporate the Ministry of Education, teachers, and&#13;
       parents. This will ensure that soap is incorporated in the school budgets or a provision is made where the parents&#13;
       can be encouraged to contribute. The parents would support this behavior at home.&#13;
    · The communication program should be based on aspiration messages to connect with children and use peer&#13;
       group education. The existing clubs could be utilized to promote adoption of the behavior. However, measures&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;      must be put in place to ensure vibrancy of the clubs. Strategies of keeping the clubs active could be borrowed&#13;
      from the Boy Scout or Girl Guide movement.&#13;
    · The project should consider a reward system, which is not necessarily monetary, for teachers in charge of the&#13;
      campaign in school.&#13;
    · For long-term impact, the campaign should seek to influence the design of sanitation facilities to incorporate&#13;
      appropriate handwashing facilities which are conveniently located.&#13;
&#13;
The community-based campaign should consider the following:&#13;
    · Radio and interpersonal communication methodologies will be key to reaching mothers effectively.&#13;
    · The campaign could consider different execution messages which will promote handwashing behavior at&#13;
      different junctures.&#13;
    · Messages should capture the aspirations and dreams that mothers have for their children.&#13;
    · To reduce the incidence of forgetting to wash hands after the toilet, the campaign could utilize leaky tins which are&#13;
      placed next to the toilet.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   &#13;
&amp;#12;                                               SECTION ONE:&#13;
                                                Introduction&#13;
&#13;
1.1 Research Background                                           soap (for instance: Has soap been used or not? Is the&#13;
The World Bank and development partners recognize                 soap affordable? What kind of soap is used and why?),&#13;
handwashing as one of the most effective means of                 and factors that influence handwashing behavior (both&#13;
preventing diarrheal diseases, along with safe stool disposal,    barriers and motivators).&#13;
as well as safe and adequate household water supply and&#13;
                                                                  Similar studies have been carried out in countries such&#13;
storage. Washing hands with soap at the right times can&#13;
                                                                  as Ghana, Tanzania, and Uganda. However, these studies&#13;
reduce instances of diarrhea by 5­50 percent. Evidence&#13;
                                                                  placed a lot of emphasis on community handwashing&#13;
also suggests that handwashing with soap can reduce&#13;
                                                                  practices. There was need for a Kenyan study with special&#13;
acute respiratory infections (ARIs) by 0 percent.&#13;
                                                                  focus on handwashing behavior in the school context.&#13;
The government of Kenya, together with development&#13;
                                                                  The research findings will input into a national handwashing&#13;
partners, has developed a campaign to raise awareness&#13;
                                                                  with soap (HWWS) campaign. In addition, the research&#13;
of the importance of washing hands with soap. However,&#13;
                                                                  forms a baseline to measure changes in handwashing&#13;
awareness generation alone is unlikely to change behavior&#13;
                                                                  behavior among target groups after the campaign.&#13;
among target consumers. For instance, some consumers&#13;
do have some awareness of the health benefits of&#13;
                                                                  1.3 Objectives of the Research&#13;
handwashing but do not practise it.&#13;
                                                                  The overall objective of this study was to carry out a&#13;
                                                                  baseline survey on handwashing with soap in the&#13;
1.2 Justification of Research&#13;
                                                                  community and in the school environment in urban and&#13;
A number of small-scale approaches have been undertaken&#13;
                                                                  rural areas. The specific objectives of the study were to:&#13;
in the past and though these have had an impact, they do&#13;
                                                                      · Record the current rates of handwashing with&#13;
not give a national picture. Additionally, information on&#13;
                                                                         soap among the target groups at key times:&#13;
current handwashing levels is hard to find: handwashing&#13;
                                                                         o After using the toilet;&#13;
behavior is an emotive issue whose data can mainly be&#13;
                                                                         o Before eating or handling food; and&#13;
collected using observation techniques, yet most national&#13;
                                                                         o After cleaning a child (mothers or caretakers&#13;
surveys have been quantitative in nature, basing their&#13;
                                                                             of children under five years of age).&#13;
reporting on claimed responses. This approach allows&#13;
                                                                      · Obtain a deep understanding of the drivers and&#13;
for neither the verification of a claim nor does it capture&#13;
                                                                         motivations of handwashing behavior.&#13;
certain information critical to handwashing behavior,&#13;
                                                                      · Establish barriers and facilitators of handwashing&#13;
such as where were hands washed with soap, what was&#13;
                                                                         behavior.&#13;
the source of the water, what was the method used for&#13;
                                                                      · Determine the preferred and trusted channel of&#13;
washing hands and what are the key times when hands are&#13;
                                                                         communication.&#13;
washed. It is also indicated that past sanitation activities in&#13;
the country have focused mainly on provision of clean&#13;
                                                                  1.4 Methodology&#13;
water and sanitation facilities, good water storage method,&#13;
                                                                  The study used secondary and primary research data.&#13;
and water treatment.This is an indication that handwashing&#13;
with soap as a preventive sanitation measure against&#13;
                                                                  1.4.1 Secondary Research&#13;
diarrheal diseases has not been addressed in detail.&#13;
                                                                  The focus of secondary research was to review the&#13;
Therefore, a study was needed that would provide                  existing literature that exist on handwashing practices in&#13;
information on handwashing behavior in detail, by looking         other countries, and establish initiatives that have been&#13;
at the behavior practised with regard to handwashing with         undertaken in Kenya towards handwashing with soap.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;        · Identify the knowledge gap and focus the study on    traced following domestic violence. Three in Machakos&#13;
            important areas that were not fully addressed by   dropped out on the basis of superstition that the soap&#13;
            these studies.                                     was meant to bewitch them. At the household level, 0&#13;
        · Gain from the lessons learnt from similar surveys    primary caregivers dropped out on the day of observation,&#13;
            conducted in other African countries.              after confirming their availability the previous day. The&#13;
        · Review the strengths and weaknesses of               study was extended to replace the households.&#13;
            methodologies used and challenges encountered.&#13;
                                                               Lack of cooperation from school management.&#13;
        · Conduct a review of the instruments used.&#13;
                                                               During the time that this study was carried out, other&#13;
        · Build on the strengths of previous and ongoing&#13;
                                                               donors were also carrying out activities in the same urban&#13;
            research.&#13;
                                                               school.There was reluctance to participate in the exercise&#13;
The findings of secondary research have been incorporated&#13;
                                                               on the basis that it was taking too long without a direct&#13;
in the main report.&#13;
                                                               benefit to the school.&#13;
&#13;
1.4.2 Primary Research                                         The project ran out of water in a few schools&#13;
Primary research used two broad approaches: school             during the last days of behavioral trials in&#13;
approach and community approach. Each approach used            school. The project team bought water to complete the&#13;
multiple methodologies. Details on methodologies are           exercise.&#13;
covered under each approach.                                   High rate of soap disappearance in schools. The soap had&#13;
                                                               to be replaced every break time.&#13;
1.4.3 Data Analysis Tools&#13;
Qualitative data were analyzed using interpretative analysis   1.6 Project Learning&#13;
through inductive and deductive logic. Quantitative data       Following this project the following learning can be&#13;
                                   4&#13;
were analyzed through SPSS analysis package using              integrated into future projects:&#13;
descriptive statistics. Data have been presented in charts         · The study should over-sample behavioral trials and&#13;
and tables.                                                           households to factor in drop outs.&#13;
                                                                   · Future projects should budget for more soap.&#13;
1.4.4 Field Work Dates                                             · Future     projects    should     identify   secondary&#13;
The study was carried out between March and May 007.                  caregivers so as to study them as individuals rather&#13;
Data was collected in March 007.                                      than a group.&#13;
                                                                   · Kenyans have a strong culture of washing their&#13;
1.5 Field Challenges                                                  face in the morning.Therefore, washing hands after&#13;
The study experienced a few challenges in the field as                using the toilet first thing in the morning may be&#13;
described below.                                                      driven by this culture.&#13;
Security. The observers in this study were all female.             · Kenyans perceive the concept of handwashing as&#13;
Some of the study sites had security concerns. Project                part of their general hygiene.&#13;
management organized for escorts where necessary and&#13;
observers were encouraged to move in groups.                   1.7 Report Structure&#13;
                                                               The report has been divided into three major sections:&#13;
Drop-outs in behavioral trials and household&#13;
                                                                   · Background information;&#13;
interviews. The study lost four behavioral trials out of&#13;
                                                                   · Community study; and&#13;
the proposed 40. One primary caregiver could not be&#13;
                                                                   · School study.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4&#13;
    See Footnote 2.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   5&#13;
&amp;#12;2. Background Information&#13;
&#13;
2.1 Background on Kenya&#13;
Kenya has an estimated population of .4 million people,          country is divided into eight provinces. A brief background&#13;
of which 65 percent is rural and 5 percent is urban. The         of each of these provinces is given in table ..&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 2.1: Population and Poverty Incidences across the Study Provinces&#13;
&#13;
 Province              Total population               Poverty incidence&#13;
                       according to&#13;
                       1999 Census&#13;
  Central province         ,74,59                     Ranks as the least poor province, with most locations&#13;
                                                      exhibiting a poverty incidence of less than 40 percent.&#13;
                                                      Thika district accounts for 4 percent of the urban poor in&#13;
                                                      Central province, while Nyeri accounts for another  percent.&#13;
  Nairobi province         ,5,88                      Nearly 880,000 people live below poverty line.&#13;
  Coast province           ,487,67                    A rural poor population of roughly 909,000.&#13;
                                                      Two-thirds of the rural poor in Coast province are found in&#13;
                                                      Kilifi and Kwale.&#13;
                                                      The urban poor population is estimated at around 400,000&#13;
                                                      persons, of which two-thirds is concentrated in Mombasa town.&#13;
  Eastern province         4,6,779                    Has a rural population of approximately .5 million people.&#13;
                                                      The rural poor population is concentrated in Kitui, Machakos,&#13;
                                                      Makueni, and Meru North districts.&#13;
                                                      Nearly ,000 urban poor living in Eastern province.&#13;
  Nyanza province          4,9,96                     A rural poor population of .4 million people.&#13;
                                                      It exhibits very high poverty levels across most divisions&#13;
                                                      and locations.&#13;
                                                      Bondo is the poorest district.&#13;
  Rift Valley              6,987,06                   An estimated .7 million rural poor and 450,000 urban poor&#13;
                                                      in this province.&#13;
  Western province         ,58,776                    Nearly .8 million poor people.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2.2 Under-Five Mortality and&#13;
Incidences of Diarrhea Cases&#13;
According to the Demographic Healthy Survey, 00,                 World Health Organization statistics, 006, records that&#13;
the under-five mortality (per ,000 live births) is 5.            diarrheal diseases caused 6 percent of deaths among&#13;
The mortality is higher in rural areas compared to               children under five years of age in 00­0. Prevalence&#13;
urban areas (7 rural and 94 urban). It is high among             of diarrhea among children under five years, measured&#13;
the poor compared to the rich (49 for the lowest                 by the incidence of diarrhea in the last two weeks, was&#13;
wealth quintile and 9 for the highest wealth quintile).          recorded at 6 percent in 00. Coast and Western&#13;
Central province has the lowest under-five mortality at          provinces recorded the highest prevalence at .&#13;
54, followed by Rift Valley at 77. Under-five mortality is       percent and .9 percent, respectively. Central had the&#13;
highest in Nyanza (06); this is followed by Eastern and          lowest prevalence at 7 percent.&#13;
Western (6 and 44, respectively).&#13;
&#13;
6 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;2.3 Kenyan Soap Market                                                                       by urban and rural poor people. The preference for bar&#13;
Soap has proved to be an essential commodity that                                            soaps is driven by their wide application at the household&#13;
individuals cannot do without. It also demonstrates the                                      level to accommodate different needs and low household&#13;
value of hygiene as far as human beings are concerned--it                                    budgets. Bar soap usage cuts across all the socioeconomic&#13;
is ranked the third-most essential need after water and                                      classes in Kenya, with heavier usage in the rural areas and&#13;
food. In the Kenyan market, consumers have a wide range                                      among urban poor people. Powder soaps are preferred&#13;
of choice depending on the preference, perception, and                                       for laundry and used mainly by the middle and upper class.&#13;
prices. There are various types of soaps in the market, for                                  Liquid soap is mainly used by the upper class. The leading&#13;
instance, powdered, bar, toilet, and liquid soaps.                                           soap manufacturers in the Kenyan market are Unilever&#13;
                                                                                             and Bidco Company.&#13;
Bar soaps are the most preferred type of soap. They are&#13;
sold either as bars or small pieces; the latter is preferred&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 2.2: Main Soap Brands in the Market and Pricing&#13;
&#13;
  Detergent                          Weight              Price (in KES)5&#13;
 Bar soaps&#13;
 Ushindi                             00 g                &#13;
 Sunlight                            00 g                &#13;
 Omo                                 00 g                &#13;
 Whitestar                           800 g               58&#13;
 Panga                                kg                 59&#13;
 Kwanga                               kg                 54&#13;
 Toilet soaps&#13;
 Imperial Leather                    00 g                49&#13;
 Geisha                              50 g                48&#13;
 Active                              40 g                44&#13;
 Lux                                 5 g                 45&#13;
 Protex                              00 g                80&#13;
 Pamolive                            5 g                 7&#13;
 Dettol                              00 g                86&#13;
 Flamingo                            5 g                 4&#13;
 Powdered soaps&#13;
 Omo                                 500 g               78&#13;
 Gental                              500 g               69&#13;
 Ariel                               400 g               6&#13;
 Soaftle                              kg                 59&#13;
 Power                               500 g               59&#13;
 Sunlight                            500 g               60&#13;
 Liquid soaps&#13;
 Nivea body wash                     50 ml               45&#13;
 Protex                              50 ml               80&#13;
 Revlon                              00 ml               97&#13;
 Fa body wash                        00 ml               0&#13;
 Biogel handwashing                  500 ml              94&#13;
 Hovid quick clean                   0 ml                99&#13;
 handwashing&#13;
&#13;
5&#13;
 US$1 = KES 68.75 (as of August 30, 2008).Conversion rates are from http://coinmill.com/KES_USD.html;&#13;
all conversions in the text are approximate. (KES stands for Kenyan Shillings.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                        Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   7&#13;
&amp;#12;                                             SECTION TWO:&#13;
                                            Community Study&#13;
The community study sought to understand handwashing                target communities and districts. All behavior trials&#13;
behavior using qualitative and quantitative parameters.             were conducted in villages different from the ones&#13;
The study targeted women who are primary caregivers                 where household interviews were conducted, but they&#13;
of children aged five years and above. The study was                were within the same sub-location. Participants were&#13;
conducted in all the eight provinces. One district was              selected at random using a recruiting questionnaire.&#13;
selected in each province.                                          After recruitment, the respondent was given the&#13;
                                                                    soap and asked to use it at key junctures. However,&#13;
                                                                    the respondent was also free to use the soap in any&#13;
3.0 Methods Used in the                                             other way. Interim visits were made after three days&#13;
Community Study                                                     and more soap was placed where necessary. A debrief&#13;
A summary of the methods used to collect data is                    was conducted after seven days.&#13;
described in table .:&#13;
                                                               b) Focus group discussions (FGDs): The FGDs&#13;
a) Behavioral trials: This is the process of introducing            focused on handwashing with soap (HWWS) at&#13;
   individuals to a behavior and assessing their experiences        key junctures, that is, after contact with feces and&#13;
   with trying to carry out that behavior over a period             while handling food. They sought to establish existing&#13;
   of seven days.This exercise gave insights on how easily          behavior, motivations, and barriers at the functional&#13;
   the new behavior would be adopted, motivators of the             and emotive levels. Each focus group had eight to 0&#13;
   behavior, and barriers to adoption of the behavior.              respondents. Discussions lasted about one-and-a-half&#13;
   In the trials, physical barriers to behavior adoption            hours.&#13;
   were controlled in order to unveil other underlying         c) In-depth interviews: In-depth interviews were&#13;
   adoption barriers. Respondents were given soap and          conducted with key informants who included:&#13;
   encouraged to use it to wash their hands at key times,           · Public health officers;&#13;
   that is, before handling food and after possible contact         · Community health workers;&#13;
   with feces. After seven days the interviewer visited             · Nongovernmental organizations (NGOs) dealing&#13;
   the participants and carried out an in-depth interview              with sanitation;&#13;
   on their experiences between the two visits. The aim             · Assistant chiefs; and&#13;
   of the process is to determine compliance with the               · Influential women group leaders.&#13;
   behavior and barriers hindering compliance.                 d)      Structured observations:           The objectives&#13;
   Forty trials (five in each district) were conducted with         of structured observation were to establish the&#13;
   caregivers of children aged less than five years in the          proportion of times the following occurred:&#13;
   households. The households selected were within the              · Caregivers wash hands with soap (WHWS) after&#13;
                                                                       using the toilet.&#13;
Table 3.1: Summary of Study Methods&#13;
&#13;
  Method                           Target population                   Sample size              Study districts&#13;
  Structured observations and      Caregivers of children below        80 (about 00 per         Nyeri, Nairobi, Kisumu,&#13;
  household interviews             five years                          province )               Bungoma, Mombasa&#13;
  Behavioral trials                Primary caregivers of children      40                       Five in each district&#13;
                                   below five years&#13;
  Focus group discussions          Caregivers of children below        8                        One in each district&#13;
                                   five years&#13;
  In-depth interviews              Community leaders                   6                        Four in each district&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;    · Caregivers WHWS after cleaning up index child.                 household and primary caregiver as well as to book&#13;
    · Caregivers WHWS before feeding a child.                        an appointment for the following day. The study&#13;
    · Caregivers WHWS before handling foods (taken                   objectives were discreetly thought out interviewer&#13;
       raw).                                                         visits and interaction with the respondents. The&#13;
    · School-age children WHWS after using the toilet                study was introduced as one that would be studying&#13;
       at home.                                                      family life, to avoid bias. During the recruitment the&#13;
    · School-going children WHWS before eating.                      primary caregiver and index child were identified. All&#13;
   Structured observations were conducted in eight                   participating households had a child aged less than&#13;
   provinces. These are all provinces in Kenya, except               five years. The interviewers arrived at the household&#13;
   North Eastern province. North Eastern province                    at 5.55 am and strategically positioned themselves to&#13;
   was left out because of logistic problems in carrying             observe handwashing behavior at key junctures. All&#13;
   out the research. Villages in North are far apart. In             observations started at 6.00 am, except where the&#13;
   addition, accessibility of villages very early in the             household woke up late, and ended at 9.00 am. The&#13;
   morning as required in this study is a challenge due              observations also captured the handwashing behavior&#13;
   to security concerns. One district was selected in                of secondary caregivers and school-going children&#13;
   each province using simple random sampling. Two                   at the household level. Table . summarizes the&#13;
   sub-locations (smallest administrative unit in Kenya)             junctures observed.&#13;
   were selected using the probability proportion to&#13;
                                                                     e) Household survey:            The objective of the&#13;
   size (PPS) method.&#13;
                                                                     household survey was to get the views of community&#13;
   A listing of villages was obtained in each sub-location.&#13;
                                                                     members on hygiene practises, sources of information&#13;
   The interviews were spread across several villages in&#13;
                                                                     and communication channels, cost of soap and&#13;
   the same sub-location. Systematic random sampling&#13;
                                                                     handwashing agents, and gather demographic data of&#13;
   was used to select households that participated in&#13;
                                                                     the study respondents.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 3.2: Summary of Junctures and Persons Observed&#13;
&#13;
   Juncture                                                                   Person observed&#13;
                                                       Primary                 Secondary                School-going&#13;
                                                       caregiver                caregiver                 children&#13;
&#13;
   After using the toilet                                                            X                        &#13;
   After cleaning up the bottom of index child                                                                X&#13;
   Other contact with stool                                                                                   X&#13;
   Before feeding the index child                                                                             X&#13;
   Before handling food (taken raw)                                                  X                        X&#13;
   Before eating                                              X                      X                        &#13;
    Juncture was observed.&#13;
   X Juncture was not observed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   the study - this was done by choosing every fourth             The respondents who participated in the structured&#13;
   household on the list of those with children under five        observations were the same sample for household survey.&#13;
   years of age.                                                  Household interviews were conducted with the primary&#13;
   The interviewer visited the participating house one            caregivers immediately after observations. A total of 80&#13;
   day before to seek consent from the head of the                interviews were achieved.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   9&#13;
&amp;#12;0 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;4.0 Results                                                     calculating consistent handwashing, the study eliminated&#13;
                                                                those who washed only one hand. Table 4. summarizes&#13;
4.1 Baseline on Handwashing                                     the findings of those who consistently washed hands the&#13;
Observations at the household level captured primary            correct way.&#13;
caregivers, secondary caregivers, and school-going              Overall, 4 percent of primary caregivers washed hands&#13;
children. This section presents the findings related            with or without soap at all risky junctures. However, only&#13;
to handwashing practises at the household level by              5 percent of primary caregivers washed hands with soap&#13;
secondary and primary caregivers. The results related           at all risky junctures. Handwashing behavior is relatively&#13;
to school-going children have been reported under the           stronger in Mombasa and Nyeri compared to other&#13;
school study in Section Three.                                  regions. Handwashing culture is exceptionally low in Kisii.&#13;
The study established that primary caregivers were, in          Unlike other regions, Nyeri had good access to water&#13;
most cases, the first people to wake up in the household.       round the year. Only  percent said they had experienced&#13;
There was a high incidence of using the toilet first thing      water scarcity. Mombasa is predominantly Muslim. Religion&#13;
after waking up and washing the face immediately after. In      may be a strong driver of handwashing in Mombasa.&#13;
Kenya there is a strong culture of washing one's face first     Note:&#13;
thing in the morning.Therefore in such cases the motivators         · Percent of primary caregivers who consistently&#13;
of handwashing may not be driven by the juncture but the                washed hands with or without soap, or washed&#13;
need to wash their face. This Section presents baseline of              hands with soap at all risky junctures across the&#13;
handwashing at three levels, that is, consistent handwashing,           region (N = 786).&#13;
any handwashing, and handwashing based on incidences.               · Consistent soap use excludes those who washed&#13;
                                                                        only one hand.&#13;
4.1.1 Consistent Handwashing by                                     · Consistent handwashing behavior of secondary&#13;
Primary Caregivers                                                      caregivers was not calculated since secondary&#13;
Consistent handwashing in this study is defined as                      caregivers    in    the   household      were    not&#13;
`washing hands always at any risky juncture'. It determines             differentiated.&#13;
the proportion of caregivers who have fully adopted                 · Observations were carried out over a duration&#13;
this behavior and have made it a habit. A consistent                    of three hours. The study therefore may not&#13;
handwasher washes hands at every risky juncture. This                   objectively   establish   consistent    handwashing&#13;
is what handwashing programs aim to achieve. The                        behavior across junctures.&#13;
recommended way to wash is to rub both hands. When&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 4.1: Consistent Handwashing&#13;
                    Consistent               Washed                    Consistent and                Number of&#13;
                   handwashing             one hand only              correct soap use               primary caregivers&#13;
  Nyeri                 4%                         6%                          %                           98&#13;
  Mombasa               7%                         6%                          %                           99&#13;
  Trans Nzoia           %                          8%                          %                           0&#13;
  Kisumu                0%                         %                           %                           99&#13;
  Bungoma               0%                         %                           %                           00&#13;
  Machakos              9%                         4%                          4%                          98&#13;
  Nairobi               7%                         %                           %                           96&#13;
  Kisii                 %                          0%                          %                           95&#13;
  Overall               4%                         8%                          5%                          786&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya    &#13;
&amp;#12;4.1.2 Any Handwashing Behavior by                                               According to this study caregivers in Kenya are&#13;
Primary and Secondary Caregivers                                                familiar with handwashing. Therefore, the challenge of&#13;
Any handwashing in this study is defined as `washing hands                      this program will be to get them become consistent&#13;
at least once at any risky juncture'. It helps to determine the                 handwashers with soap.&#13;
proportion of people who are familiar with the concept&#13;
of washing hands but who may or may not have put it into                        Note:&#13;
practise. Overall, primary caregivers recorded 9 percent                             · Percentage of primary and secondary caregivers&#13;
of any handwashing with or without soap, and 60 percent                                  who washed hands with or without soap, or&#13;
handwashing with soap. On the other hand, secondary                                      washed hands with soap at least once at any risky&#13;
caregivers recorded 65 percent of any handwashing with                                   juncture across the region.&#13;
or without soap and 6 percent with soap. It is apparent                              · The base of primary caregivers is the respondents.&#13;
that primary caregivers are more likely to wash hands                                    There was only one primary giver in the&#13;
than secondary caregivers.                                                               household.&#13;
                                                                                     · The base of secondary caregivers is events in each&#13;
Trans Nzoia recorded the highest incidence of HWWS.&#13;
                                                                                         household since the secondary caregivers were&#13;
This may indicate the impact of community education&#13;
                                                                                         not differentiated.&#13;
campaigns on handwashing with soap which are being&#13;
carried out in Bungoma and Trans Nzoia. At the time of this&#13;
                                                                                4.1.3 Handwashing Based on&#13;
study there was a sanitation and hygiene campaign, being&#13;
                                                                                Events Observed&#13;
conducted by the Ministry of Health, at the community and&#13;
                                                                                A total of ,87 events (of risky junctures) were observed&#13;
school level triggered by a cholera outbreak in Bungoma.&#13;
                                                                                with primary caregivers and 566 with secondary&#13;
According to interviews with key informants in the area,&#13;
                                                                                caregivers. Out of the total junctures the incidence of&#13;
handwashing with soap had increased compared to what&#13;
                                                                                handwashing with soap is at 5 percent and 57 percent for&#13;
the community was exposed to. However, the behavior has&#13;
                                                                                handwashing with or without soap for primary caregivers.&#13;
not been fully adopted since only  percent of caregivers&#13;
                                                                                Secondary caregivers recorded 9 percent handwashing&#13;
in Bungoma and  percent in Trans Nzoia are consistent&#13;
                                                                                with soap and 6 percent handwashing with or without&#13;
handwashers, as indicated in Table 4..&#13;
&#13;
Table 4.2: Any Handwashing by Primary and Secondary Caregivers across Regions&#13;
&#13;
                              Primary caregivers (N = 786)                                       Secondary caregivers (N = 353)&#13;
                     Any HW             Any HWWS              No. of primary           Any HW           Any HWWS              No. of households&#13;
                                                              caregivers                                                      with a secondary&#13;
                                                                                                                              caregiver&#13;
 Overall                 9%                   60%                   786                    65%                6%                   5&#13;
 Trans Nzoia             00%                  7%                    0                      7%                 9%                   8&#13;
 Nyeri                   97%                  59%                   98                     5%                 7%                   &#13;
 Mombasa                 95%                  54%                   99                     8%                 0%                   47&#13;
 Nairobi                 94%                  67%                   96                     7%                 5%                   55&#13;
 Bungoma                 94%                  74%                   00                     77%                %                    6&#13;
 Kisumu                  9%                   6%                    99                     68%                %                    56&#13;
 Machakos                90%                  5%                    98                     46%                4%                   50&#13;
 Kisii                   78%                  7%                    95                     %                  %                    4&#13;
&#13;
Note: · Percentage of primary and secondary caregivers who washed hands with or without soap, or washed hands with soap&#13;
           at least once at any risky juncture across the region.&#13;
         · The base of primary caregivers is the respondents. There was only one primary giver in the household.&#13;
         · The base of secondary caregivers is events in each household since the secondary caregivers were not differentiated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;soap. Caution must be taken when comparing secondary             hands when they come into contact with stool compared&#13;
and primary caregivers because of the differences in the         to when handling food.&#13;
number of events observed. Comparing all the regions,&#13;
                                                                 Frequency of handwashing with soap by primary caregivers&#13;
handwashing is commonly practised in Mombasa and&#13;
                                                                 at key junctures in Kenya is much higher compared to&#13;
Nyeri. Handwashing with soap is exceptionally low in Kisii,&#13;
                                                                 other countries such as Uganda, as indicated in Table 4.5.&#13;
followed by Machakos.&#13;
                                                                 However, caution must be taken when comparing the&#13;
Table 4.4 summarizes handwashing behavior of primary             Uganda and Kenyan studies directly, because the two&#13;
and secondary caregivers across the junctures: both              studies analyzed the data differently--while Kenya used&#13;
primary and secondary caregivers are more likely to wash         events, Uganda used respondents.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 4.3 : Handwashing with or without Soap Based on Events Observed across regions&#13;
&#13;
                        Primary caregivers (N = 3,387)                        Secondary caregivers (N = 566)&#13;
                  Washed hands       Washed hands       Events          Washed hands       Washed hands          Events&#13;
                  with/without       with soap                          with/without       with soap&#13;
                  soap                                                  soap&#13;
 Total                  57%               5%              87                  6%                 9%                  566&#13;
 Nyeri                  70%               0%              7                   74%                50%                 4&#13;
 Mombasa                69%               9%              70                  75%                %                   75&#13;
 Bungoma                66%               0%              570                 77%                %                   78&#13;
 Trans Nzoia            6%                %               49                  55%                %                   58&#13;
 Nairobi                56%               %               440                 66%                9%                  95&#13;
 Machakos               5%                9%              54                  60%                %                   77&#13;
 Kisumu                 48%               4%              44                  5%                 6%                  99&#13;
 Kisii                  6%                %               456                 4%                 4%                  50&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 4.4: Handwashing with or without Soap Based on Events Observed across Junctures&#13;
&#13;
                                      Primary caregivers                         Secondary caregivers&#13;
                                     Washed         Washed                       Washed          Washed&#13;
                                     hands with/    hands                        hands with/     hands&#13;
                                     without        with                         without         with&#13;
                                      soap          soap             Events       soap           soap             Events&#13;
&#13;
 After cleaning child's bottom        7%                6%           507            6%                %              65&#13;
 After other contact with stool       67%               7%           490             7%               9%             6&#13;
 After suspected self defecation      6%                %            97              N/A              N/A            N/A&#13;
 Before handling food                 47%               5%           8               N/A              N/A            N/A&#13;
 Before feeding or serving&#13;
 index child                          46%               %            66              5%               8%             8&#13;
&#13;
 N/A Juncture was not observed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                       Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya    &#13;
&amp;#12;Table 4.6 summarizes the proportion of events where            4.1.4 Soap used for Handwashing&#13;
primary caregivers washed hands with soap across regions.      Bar soaps were the dominant cleansing agent with 70&#13;
Across all junctures, Kisii records very low incidence of      percent usage except for Mombasa ( percent) and&#13;
soap usage. Although Mombasa has a strong handwashing          Nairobi (48 percent). There was usage of medicated and&#13;
culture, use of soap is not very strong.                       perfumed or scented soaps in Mombasa and Nairobi.&#13;
                                                               The use of bar soaps in rural areas is almost universal.&#13;
Table 4.5: Handwashing with and without Soap by Primary        The dominance of bar soap is further emphasized by the&#13;
Child Caregiver in Uganda                                      fact that, out of 8 households which had a cleansing&#13;
                                  Any HW (%) WHWS              agent at the handwashing site, 76 percent had bar soaps.&#13;
  Event&#13;
                                             any soap          The preference for bar soap is driven by its multiple&#13;
                                             (%)               applications in the household and by its affordability.&#13;
 After self defecation                                         During behavioral trials the soap placed was used not&#13;
 (N = )                              57%             4%        only for handwashing but also for washing clothes, body&#13;
 After cleaning child's                                        washing and, in a few cases, washing dishes. Therefore, bar&#13;
 bottom (N = 85)                     5%              9%        soaps are most appropriate for handwashing campaigns&#13;
 After other contact                                           at the community level.&#13;
 with stool (N = 69)                 8%              %&#13;
 Before feeding or serving                                     4.2 Procedures of Washing Hands&#13;
 index child (N = 4)                 4%               6%       If hands are not washed properly, there is a risk of&#13;
 Before handling food/drink                                    contamination. It is recommended to wash both hands&#13;
 (ready to eat) (N = 97)             4%              8%        with soap under running water and dry them with a&#13;
 Before eating (N = 8)                68%            8%        clean piece of cloth. After the observations, the primary&#13;
 Note: N = 500.                                                caregiver was asked to wash hands the way she normally&#13;
 Source: Uganda Formative and Baseline Survey                  would. The study established that nearly all primary&#13;
 Handwashing Report. 2007.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 4.6: Handwashing with Soap by Primary Caregivers Based on Events Observed across Junctures and Region&#13;
&#13;
                          Total     Kisii   Nyeri    Mombasa   Kisumu Trans Nzoia Machakos Nairobi Bungoma&#13;
 After other contact&#13;
 with stool (N = 490)      7%       8%      7%        44%      4%           45%            5%         40%        %&#13;
 After cleaning child's&#13;
 bottom (N = 507)          6%       8%      47%       0%       48%          8%             7%         4%        54%&#13;
 After suspected self&#13;
 defecation (N = 97)       %        6%      5%        6%       8%           9%             5%         0%        %&#13;
 Before handling&#13;
 food (N = 8)              5%       6%      %         %        %            %              8%         %         %&#13;
 Before feeding or&#13;
 serving index child&#13;
 (N = 66)                  %        5%      %         8%       6%           %              7%         8%        6%&#13;
&#13;
 Note: N = events observed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;caregivers washed hands. However, 0 percent used              4.4 Sanitation Environment in&#13;
recycled water, 50 percent dried hands with the clothes       Community&#13;
they had on and 6 percent preserved the water for later       Pit latrines are the most common types of toilets in Kenya.&#13;
use. This indicates risk of contamination after washing       This implies that the community must get out of the&#13;
hands. The campaign should also sensitize the community       house to go to the toilet. This applied also for those who&#13;
on the proper way of washing and drying hands.                shared the flush toilet. It is important to note that there&#13;
                                                              are  percent households that did not own any toilet and&#13;
                                                              therefore had to go far from their houses to defecate.This&#13;
4.3 Perception of Important                                   was encountered in Mombasa (8 percent), Trans Nzoia (&#13;
Junctures of Handwashing with                                 percent), Bungoma ( percent) and Machakos ( percent).&#13;
Soap                                                          Most households' toilets are located at an estimated&#13;
The study sought to establish community perception            distance of 0 to 50 meters from the handwashing sites.&#13;
about when people think it is important to wash hands.&#13;
                                                              An observation of toilets in the 80 households visited&#13;
Washing hands with soap after using the toilet (7&#13;
                                                              revealed that 59 percent were dirty. This implies that&#13;
percent) and before eating (55 percent) had the highest&#13;
                                                              over half of the household do not prioritize hygiene of&#13;
mention, both top-of-the-mind recall and overall. Most&#13;
                                                              the toilet. It also indicates high chances of contamination&#13;
communities in Kenya have a number of dishes which are&#13;
                                                              after using the toilet. Toilets in Bungoma had the highest&#13;
eaten using the hands, which may explain the high priority&#13;
                                                              mention of poor hygiene.&#13;
of washing hands before meals. Physical dirt and strong&#13;
smells trigger handwashing with soap, indicated by the&#13;
                                                              Sources and Availability of Water&#13;
need to wash hands after contact with sticky or smelly&#13;
                                                              In the HWWS behavioral campaign, access to water is&#13;
material, after coming back from the garden, and after&#13;
                                                              critical. Most households fetch water from outside the&#13;
eating. The campaign should seek to increase awareness&#13;
                                                              compound except in Nairobi, Mombasa, and Nyeri, where&#13;
of handwashing with soap at other key junctures.&#13;
                                                              water is conveniently available in the compound.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 4.7: "What Do You Think are the Key Times When You Must WHWS?&#13;
&#13;
  N = 802                                            1st mention     2nd mention         3rd mention        Total&#13;
  After toilet                                         7%                %                  %                7%&#13;
  Before eating                                        0%                5%                 0%               55%&#13;
  After contact with sticky, oily, smelly material     9%                4%                 4%               7%&#13;
  After coming from the field/garden/work              5%                8%                 6%               9%&#13;
  First thing when you wake up                         4%                %                  %                8%&#13;
  After eating                                         %                 %                  8%               4%&#13;
  After cleaning up a child                            %                 7%                 7%               7%&#13;
  Before cooking food                                  %                 6%                 4%               %&#13;
  Before breastfeeding                                 %                 %                  %                6%&#13;
  Before feeding a baby                                %                 %                  6%               9%&#13;
  Before serving food                                  0%                %                  %                5%&#13;
  After touching animals                               0%                %                  %                5%&#13;
  Before saying prayers                                0%                0%                 %                %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   5&#13;
&amp;#12;When the people were asked whether they had                            of this scarcity across the region reveals that not all regions&#13;
experienced water shortage one year before the                         are affected equally. Water scarcity is severe in Nairobi,&#13;
survey--to an extent of limiting use or recycling water--              Machakos, and Bungoma. Water scarcity may have a&#13;
4 percent responded in the affirmative. A further review               relationship with sanitation in the area. As mentioned&#13;
                                                                       in the previous Section, most toilets in Bungoma were&#13;
                                                                       found to be very dirty. Water scarcity was also found to&#13;
Table 4.8:Toilet Facilities at the Household Level                     be prolonged with 84 percent of those who experienced&#13;
                                                                       water shortage claiming that it took two months or more&#13;
  Type of toilet&#13;
                                                                       for water to be available.&#13;
  Uncovered pit latrine                              %&#13;
  Covered pit latrine: private                       %&#13;
  Covered pit latrine: shared                        %&#13;
                                                                       Table 4.9: Main Sources of Water&#13;
  Flush toilet: shared                               %&#13;
  Flush toilet: private                              9%                  Wells, springs, rivers, dams                       0%&#13;
  Public toilet                                      %                   Tap in the yard                                    6%&#13;
  Bush                                               %                   Communal tap                                       8%&#13;
  Condition of the toilet                                                Tap or piped water in the house                    8%&#13;
  Clean                                              %&#13;
                                                                         Bore hole                                          8%&#13;
  Somewhat dirty                                     44%&#13;
                                                                         Vendor                                             5%&#13;
  Dirty, feces visible, some smell                   4%&#13;
                                                                         Well in the yard                                   %&#13;
  Very dirty, overflowing, very smelly               %&#13;
                                                                         Rain water                                         %&#13;
  No need for observation                            6%&#13;
                                                                         No response                                        %&#13;
  Not mentioned                                      %&#13;
                                                                         Note: N = 80.&#13;
  Note: N = 80.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 4.1: Proportion of Households that Experienced Water Shortage in the last One Year&#13;
&#13;
                                  Did you in the one year experience water shortage?&#13;
 00%                                                    N=802&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 80%&#13;
                           67%&#13;
&#13;
 60%&#13;
                                         53%&#13;
                                                      47%&#13;
 40%&#13;
                                                                    31%&#13;
           34%                                                                     24%&#13;
                                                                                                  22%&#13;
 0%                                                                                                            19%&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                            12%&#13;
 0%&#13;
                            &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    &#13;
                                                     &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                   &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                               0&#13;
                                                                                                97&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                            99&#13;
          al&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      =9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    0&#13;
                                                     0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                             0&#13;
            t&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                           =&#13;
         To&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              ii=&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                          i=&#13;
                      i=&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 ia=&#13;
                                                 a=&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              u=&#13;
                                     s&#13;
                                  ko&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                           r&#13;
                                                                                            Kis&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                          sa&#13;
                      ob&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                        ye&#13;
                                               om&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                            um&#13;
                                                               zo&#13;
                                 ha&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                        ba&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                      N&#13;
                   air&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            ns&#13;
                                 ac&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            ng&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                     om&#13;
                                                                          Kis&#13;
                  N&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                             a&#13;
                             M&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          Bu&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          Tr&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                    M&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;4.5 Background of                                               4.5.3 Challenges Caregivers&#13;
    Respondents                                                 Experience&#13;
                                                                Poverty, HIV/AIDS, family strife, irresponsible husbands,&#13;
4.5.1 Demographic Characteristics&#13;
                                                                and moral decadence in society are the main challenges&#13;
The range age of primary caregivers with children less&#13;
                                                                that caregivers face. Poverty and HIV/AIDS were the most&#13;
than five years are young mothers in the range of 8­5&#13;
                                                                threatening. Most mothers are afraid of contracting HIV/&#13;
years (8 percent). Forty-eight percent have not gone&#13;
                                                                AIDS, leaving their children orphans--and therefore not&#13;
beyond primary school, while 9 percent have little or&#13;
                                                                able to escape the clutches of poverty. This was explicit in&#13;
no formal education. Most (80 percent) are married. The&#13;
                                                                all regions, but mentioned more in Mombasa and Kisumu&#13;
campaign should be designed to also cater for those with&#13;
                                                                districts. These challenges inhibit their ability to nurture&#13;
little or no formal education.&#13;
                                                                the children to the best of their ability. Religion plays an&#13;
                                                                important role in helping these women cope with their&#13;
                                                                challenges and nurture their children.&#13;
4.5.2 Values and Aspirations of&#13;
Primary Caregivers&#13;
Values: The caregivers' core values are family based, with&#13;
                                                                Table 4.10: Demographic Characteristics&#13;
emphasis on family unity. The day-to-day activities are&#13;
therefore family centered. Their nurturing instincts play        Age of the consumers&#13;
an important role. Nurturing is defined as ability to give       Less than 8                                       %&#13;
children a quality life; educate and discipline them (morally    8­4                                               0%&#13;
upright children).They need to be protected from alcohol&#13;
                                                                 5­0                                               9%&#13;
and drug abuse, diseases, and other society vices.&#13;
                                                                 ­5                                                %&#13;
    · "I really fear a kind of situation where children turn&#13;
       up rude and undisciplined even towards me; and            6­40                                              8%&#13;
       towards society such that no one will want to be          4 and above                                       6%&#13;
       associated with them." (Bungoma district)                 No response                                       %&#13;
    · "Recently, there has been an increase in rape&#13;
                                                                 Highest education level attained&#13;
       cases... every time you are afraid for their safety&#13;
                                                                 Never attended school                             %&#13;
       especially when you know you cannot be with&#13;
       them all the time." (Nyeri district)                      Did not complete primary school                   6%&#13;
                                                                 Completed primary school                          9%&#13;
According to the focus group discussions, women                  Did not complete secondary school                 %&#13;
enjoy nurturing their children in addition to doing daily&#13;
                                                                 Completed secondary school                        %&#13;
household chores. Hygiene maintenance plays a great&#13;
                                                                 Beyond secondary school                           %&#13;
role. Religion plays a major role in mothers' lives&#13;
    · " I like taking care of my children, even though they      No response                                       %&#13;
       don't go to school, I have charts, I sit and teach him    Marital status&#13;
       ABC--`A' is for apple, `B' is for banana... and they      Married                                           80%&#13;
       are usually happy... when you meet them you will          Single                                            %&#13;
       think they have started school." (Mombasa district)&#13;
                                                                 Widowed                                           %&#13;
Aspirations: Caregivers' aspirations revolve around their        Cohabiting                                        %&#13;
children and family.They aspire to have financial freedom in&#13;
                                                                 Divorced or separated                             %&#13;
order to contribute to the family's' welfare and guarantee&#13;
                                                                 No response                                       %&#13;
their family a good quality life. They aspire to have well&#13;
educated, disciplined, and socially acceptable children.         Note: N = 80.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   7&#13;
&amp;#12;Table 4.11: Summary of Mothers' Aspirations&#13;
&#13;
         Dream                         Dreams of mothers (Focus Group Discussion participants)&#13;
&#13;
 Best education for their      "I would like to see my children clean and in good health." (Machakos district)&#13;
 children&#13;
&#13;
 High paying career            "I do not have land so I pray my children get a good education and uplift my living&#13;
                               standards. Also I want them to be acceptable in society, and not be despised." (Bungoma&#13;
                               district)&#13;
 Quality lifestyle,            "I want my first-born to have a good certificate with a marketable career." (Nairobi&#13;
 for instance, health          district)&#13;
&#13;
 Children to become            "My dream is to educate my kids, to get jobs, because once they start working, if I am&#13;
 responsible citizens          alive then I will also benefit." (Mombasa district)&#13;
&#13;
                               "I fear early marriages, as they always do not work out. Should my daughter get married;&#13;
                               the husband would not be able to support [her], and she will be forced to come back&#13;
                               home. Or she might leave you with the children to bring them up, yet I am unable to&#13;
                               support her and her child." (Bungoma district)&#13;
&#13;
 Personal (women's)            "I want to have money, so that my children can get a good education, and get jobs; and&#13;
 financial independence        God [will] bless them so they can take care of me in [my] old age." (Bungoma district)&#13;
&#13;
                               "I want to have a sufficient amount of money so that I can support my son on my own."&#13;
                               (Nairobi district)&#13;
&#13;
 Support spouse                "I want to have a progressive business where I can join a merry-go-round so that my&#13;
                               child can go to a boarding school." (Nairobi district)&#13;
 Improve quality of life       "Our husbands tell us not to do business. They don't want us to do anything but be&#13;
                               a housewife... you cannot sell potatoes because the husband will say that you are&#13;
                               shaming him... most of the time they beat you up... most of the time they make us&#13;
                               angry and when the heart is angry doing something is hard." (Mombasa district)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.6 Knowledge and Attitudes                                      hygiene but is perceived to be important from the health&#13;
towards Handwashing                                              perspective.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 Personal care: This is about personal grooming (short&#13;
4.6.1 Perception and Attitudes                                   nails, clean clothes, bathing, short hair, and so on).&#13;
towards Hygiene as a Practise&#13;
                                                                 Psychological: This has to do with purity and peace&#13;
Based on insights from community focus group discussions&#13;
                                                                 of mind. Those observing hygiene are perceived to be&#13;
and in-depth interviews with community leaders, hygiene&#13;
                                                                 people of virtue, and enjoy a good quality life as a result.&#13;
is a holistic concept which is associated with the personal,&#13;
psychological, and physical environment's cleanliness and        Physical environment: It is about hygiene in the&#13;
health. Handwashing falls under the broad concept of             general environment (including sanitation in homes). It has&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;Table 4.12: Summary of Barriers and Biggest Fears to Realization of Dreams&#13;
&#13;
   Barriers                           Description&#13;
&#13;
   Poverty                            · Inability to provide basic needs for children.&#13;
                                      · Retrenchment or unemployment.&#13;
                                      · Lack of start up capital.&#13;
                                      · Denied permission by husbands to be employed or do business.&#13;
&#13;
   Family problems                    · Single parenthood as a result of death of partner; or by choice.&#13;
                                      · Face marital strife, which brings instability in the home and lack of focus.&#13;
                                      · Have irresponsible husbands, for example, drunkards.&#13;
&#13;
   HIV/AIDS                           · Children become orphans or are left with no one responsible to nurture&#13;
                                         them.&#13;
                                      · Infidelity of spouse.&#13;
&#13;
   Permissive society                 · Children are exposed to societal vices such as early marriages, drug abuse,&#13;
                                         rape, crime, and so on.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
to do with daily observation of sanitation issues, especially           · "We have what I call hygiene of the heart... you&#13;
cleanliness in the compound (or playground), and cooking                   might be living together, yet one of us has not&#13;
and dining areas. `Freshness' is the emotional trigger for a               cleaned their heart. Every time you do a good deed,&#13;
clean environment.                                                         one goes behind your back. So hygiene has to be in&#13;
    · "Hygiene requires that you keep yourself clean, your                 everything... we use and we deserve fresh air... So&#13;
       house, children's beddings, my beddings and clothes                 hygiene is to be observed everywhere, even in the&#13;
       should be clean.The compound... and my husband                      environment we live." (FGD: Mombasa district)&#13;
       [also should] be clean." (FGD: Bungoma district)&#13;
                                                                    The main perceived benefits of observing hygiene&#13;
    · "To me cleanliness in general... [is] from your body&#13;
                                                                    standards are:&#13;
       to your environment." (FGD: Kisumu district)&#13;
                                                                        · Preventive measures against diseases, therefore,&#13;
                                                                           save on hospitalization fees and increase one's&#13;
Health: Strongly associated with freedom from germs&#13;
                                                                           productivity as a result.&#13;
and diseases. Health is directly linked to the diet, consuming&#13;
                                                                        · Safeguards and ensures growth of future&#13;
clean water, cleaning hands after toilet, and before and&#13;
                                                                           generations. Growth of future generations is&#13;
after meals.&#13;
                                                                           important in African culture.&#13;
    · "It is... when you wash your hands before handling&#13;
       any food and keeping the kitchen clean." (FGD:&#13;
       Kisumu district)&#13;
                                                                    4.6.2 Beliefs and Knowledge&#13;
    · "You see if there is no hygiene, there will be many&#13;
                                                                    Relating to Handwashing&#13;
       worms... the kid gets worms... typhoid." (FGD:&#13;
                                                                    Overall there is positive attitude towards handwashing:&#13;
       Nyeri district)&#13;
                                                                    8 percent of all caregivers believe that their family would&#13;
    · "Hygiene begins with our bodies, then [in] the&#13;
                                                                    be healthier if they washed hands with soap all the time.&#13;
       environment, which we live in". (FGD: Trans Nzoia&#13;
                                                                    Awareness of handwashing is high as indicated by the&#13;
       district)&#13;
                                                                    following:&#13;
    · "After using the toilets you have to wash your&#13;
                                                                        · 9 percent of caregivers know that hidden germs&#13;
       hands before preparing food--that is hygiene."&#13;
                                                                           cause diarrhea;&#13;
       (FGD: Kisii district)&#13;
                                                                        · 77 percent have been told that it's important to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                           Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   9&#13;
&amp;#12;        wash hands with soap;                                         4.7 Motivators and Barriers to&#13;
     · 9 percent know that there may be unseen                        Handwashing with Soap (`Why?')&#13;
        contamination on their hands; and                              A review of literature from previous studies in Uganda,&#13;
     · 94 percent know that diarrhea can kill.                        Tanzania, and Ghana revealed seven potential motivating&#13;
However, there is a need to increase the depth of                     factors: disgust, fitting in, purity, comfort, status, attraction,&#13;
knowledge about handwashing as indicated by the                       and nurture. This hypothesis was presented to caregivers&#13;
following misconceptions.                                             in a focus group session. Presentations in the form of&#13;
     · 4 percent feel that a child cannot avoid getting               illustrated drawings, representing the motivating factors,&#13;
        diarrhea. It is a normal part of growing up;                  were used to elicit their perceptions and understand&#13;
     · 50 percent do not see any connection between                   motivators and barriers. The definition of each factor as&#13;
        handwashing and children missing school;                      used by the facilitators is shown in Table 4..&#13;
     · 6 percent do not know that if a child is ill less&#13;
        often, he or she will grow to be strong and                   Each group was exposed to these motivators and an&#13;
        healthy; and                                                  individual ranking was obtained. Table 4.4 presents&#13;
     ·  percent can tell if their hands are free of germs             an individual ranking of the motivational concepts by&#13;
        just by looking at them.                                      participants. These rankings are based on head count&#13;
                                                                      and hold no statistical meaning, but rather enhance&#13;
Most primary caregivers know that it is good to wash hands            understanding the positioning of motivational concepts&#13;
with soap but find it is always not possible to do so.                in the mind.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 4.13: Motivating Factors&#13;
&#13;
  Factor                   Description&#13;
  . Disgust                Dirt, contamination, smells--the things people find revolting, horrible, unappealing, and so on.&#13;
  . Purity                 Cleanliness, spiritual purity, feeling untarnished.&#13;
  . Comfort                How you feel and how your hands feel when they're clean.&#13;
  4. Status                Moving up in the world, being admired and respected.&#13;
  5. Attraction            Attracting future partners, being attractive to your current partner. Looking good.&#13;
  6. Nurture               Doing the best for my children, putting them first--rewarding them, teaching them,&#13;
                           helping them develop.&#13;
  7. Fitting in            Being part of the community, being seen to fit in, belonging, doing what others do.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 4.14: Individual Rankings of Handwashing Motivations&#13;
by Female Focus Group Discussion Participants&#13;
&#13;
  Motivator       Ranked        No. of people ranking (64)&#13;
  Nurture                                   &#13;
  Comfort                                   &#13;
  Disgust                                   0&#13;
  Fitting in           4                    8&#13;
  Status               5                    5&#13;
  Purity               6                    7&#13;
  Attraction           7                    &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
0 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;4.7.1 Nurture&#13;
Box 4. has quotes about "nurture and how it relates to&#13;
handwashing". Most caregivers relate strongly to nurture,&#13;
as children are their primary concern now. Other factors&#13;
contributing to this include:&#13;
    · Children (under five years) are more prone to&#13;
       infections than adults.&#13;
    · The society values children.&#13;
    · From a religious perspective, most caregivers&#13;
       believe children are a gift from God.&#13;
    · Handwashing (with soap) as a practise is perceived&#13;
       to be a preventive measure against diseases.&#13;
    · Most mothers have financially and emotionally&#13;
       invested in their children (to help improve quality&#13;
       of life in future).&#13;
                                                                  under five years. Handwashing at other key junctures&#13;
Based on the quotes in Box 4., it is clear that handwashing       did not come through strongly, suggesting a gap in&#13;
is related to nurturing when feeding and handling a child         knowledge.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Box 4.1: Nurture and Handwashing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The following are quotes from focus group discussions:&#13;
    · "Children are my priority even though I do not have the money, but at least I wake up, make porridge for them,&#13;
       and tell them to go to school while I search for food... I care a lot about my children." (Mombasa district)&#13;
    · "My children are my pride and joy. I wash my hands to protect them." (Machakos district)&#13;
    · "The picture is telling me that I have to clean my hands for me to be able to attend to my children. They are&#13;
       my pride and joy and I have to be clean before doing anything for them because they are a blessing from God...&#13;
       children come from far and you struggle to have them. You must pray to God when you see your child looking&#13;
       fine." (Nairobi district)&#13;
    · "I could do anything for my children to protect them." (Nyeri district)&#13;
    · "If you do not have a baby, you are not a person; in a family you must have a baby. It is very important so it is&#13;
       necessary, you protect and make sure you feed her well and make sure she is in good health." (Kisii district)&#13;
    · "Because when you bring up a child from birth, the child needs to be taken care of and all my attention is usually&#13;
       on the child, for example, washing, feeding, and so on." (Mombasa district)&#13;
    · "I chose nurture because when it comes to diseases children are prone to diseases, because when my child fell&#13;
       sick, I could not sleep the whole night thinking about the illness." (Mombasa district)&#13;
    · "I chose nurture because if you touch a child with dirty hands the child can get diarrhea." (Kisumu district)&#13;
    · "I chose nurture because I am a parent. I believe I have to be clean to protect my child. There are diseases like&#13;
       worms because... if I touch food without washing my hands, then my child will be infected, it becomes my&#13;
       problem, thus... I must wash hands to protect them from disease as cholera; vomiting is mostly a result of dirt."&#13;
       (Mombasa district)&#13;
    · "Both you and your child must be clean. As for us, we share the toilet where we live. Every time your child leaves&#13;
       the toilet, you must wash his hands." (Nairobi district)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   &#13;
&amp;#12;4.7.2 Comfort&#13;
Box 4. has quotes about "comfort and how it relates to&#13;
handwashing". This came second after nurture.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Comfort is associated with mothers keeping their hands&#13;
clean most of the time. This gives them flexibility to&#13;
perform multiple tasks such as cooking, handling the baby,&#13;
or even eating. It instills feelings of freedom and ability to&#13;
perform tasks that require high personal hygiene without&#13;
fear. Again, it shows that one adheres to religious beliefs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Box 4.2: Comfort and Handwashing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The following are quotes from focus group discussions:&#13;
Positives&#13;
    · "You cannot give comfort if your hands are not clean or even if you want to do other things that are important,&#13;
       like cooking... it is a must that you wash your hands.You touch almost every thing with the hands, even when you&#13;
       want to eat; you eat with your hands so you must wash your hands." (Bungoma district)&#13;
    · "My hands do not feel comfortable until I have cleaned them." (Kisumu district)&#13;
    · "From the words written there, I understand that personally I have to be clean. You know, when the hands&#13;
       are dirty you cannot eat anything. I must also love myself first to be able to love others. My hands have to be&#13;
       clean for me to be comfortable while eating and serving others. There will be fear of contracting diarrhea."&#13;
       (Machakos district)&#13;
    · "I can also be [doing things] in the house even if am alone, I touch money, even that money is dirty. So I am not&#13;
       comfortable when I have not washed my hands." (Nyeri district)&#13;
    · "That picture which shows that we should wash our hands has touched me. There was a time I had traveled to&#13;
       a certain place and because I was hungry I bought a fruit and ate without handwashing... I was sick afterwards, I&#13;
       had stomachaches." (Trans Nzoia district)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Negatives&#13;
    · "Stains may even remain in between your fingers and [when] you start chopping vegetables you will see the stains&#13;
       on the vegetables." (Bungoma district)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;4.7.3 Disgust&#13;
Disgust is highly associated with germs. This came third&#13;
                                                                Box 4.3: Disgust and Handwashing&#13;
after nurture and comfort. However, disgust was a very&#13;
strong motivator for handwashing where there is strong&#13;
smell or after defecation. Factors contributing to most         The following are quotes from focus group&#13;
people associating germs with feces include:                       discussions:&#13;
    · Most households lack proper toilet facilities. In         Positives&#13;
       urban towns, there is communal sharing, with no          · "I have seen my neighbor... when her&#13;
       proper drainage and water system; in rural areas            children come from the school they start&#13;
       the facilities are lacking and most use the bush.&#13;
                                                                   eating directly without handwashing and even&#13;
    · Cultural issues, like men (head of household)&#13;
                                                                   the utensils are not clean after being used."&#13;
       being the only ones with access to the toilet&#13;
                                                                   (Trans Nzoia district)&#13;
       are still practised, especially in Kisumu and&#13;
       Bungoma districts.&#13;
    · Muslim religious practices on "cleansing self             · "I feel very bad if I come out of the toilet and I&#13;
       with water, and not using tissue" after a visit to          do not wash my hands. I feel like I am smelling&#13;
       the toilet.                                                 just like [the] toilet." (Nyeri district)&#13;
    · Germs from the toilet are believed to be the most&#13;
       dangerous and are likely to cause diarrhea, a killer&#13;
                                                                · "I really feel disgusted when my hands are&#13;
       disease amongst children.&#13;
                                                                   not clean because I cannot greet my friends,&#13;
Disgust relates to both personal and physical cleanliness.&#13;
                                                                   neighbors, you can't touch your vitambaa's&#13;
There is a high association of handwashing with this&#13;
motivational attribute, as it is a key driver to handwashing       in the house... I feel very comfortable when&#13;
with soap. Just like comfort, `disgust' is likely to increase      handling food for my baby and my husband...&#13;
occasions for handwashing with soap.                               you know you cannot do such things if your&#13;
                                                                   hands are dirty. You cannot caress your husband&#13;
                                                                   when your hands are dirty." (Bungoma district)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                · "I choose disgust this is because as a mother,&#13;
                                                                   when you start being clean I also enforced it on&#13;
                                                                   my children, but if you forget doing that then I&#13;
                                                                   am bound to even forget my child. That thought&#13;
                                                                   disgusts me when I think back of what I have&#13;
                                                                   done, like not practising cleanliness... it really&#13;
                                                                   disgusts me." (Mombasa district)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                · I chose that one because most diseases&#13;
                                                                   come and have no cure... There are many&#13;
                                                                   diseases... I should protect [our family] from&#13;
                                                                   this. We should wash our hands with soap&#13;
                                                                   after visiting the toilet, and also make sure it is&#13;
                                                                   clean." (Kisii district)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   &#13;
&amp;#12;4.7.4 Fitting In                                                 serve the community in different areas, such as the church&#13;
Box 4.4 has quotes about "fitting in and how it relates          and at functions.&#13;
to handwashing". This came fourth after nurture, comfort,&#13;
and disgust. Fitting in is associated more with being            Fitting in also has to do with one having a sense of being&#13;
attractive, admired, and respected within the community.         respected, recognized, attractive; a sense of belonging,&#13;
Women have a strong need to feel loved and appreciated           being a hard worker, religious and independent--being&#13;
by their husbands and the larger community. Again, they          "less dependent on others"--and being able to afford the&#13;
                                                                 necessities of life, such as soap.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 As it relates to handwashing, fitting in appears to be a&#13;
                                                                 weak motivator. It is a motivator to more visible elements of&#13;
                                                                 hygiene. In addition, caregivers feel that some factors beyond&#13;
                                                                 their control, such as poverty, make this a less persuasive&#13;
                                                                 motive. It has to do with hygiene maintenance at a physical&#13;
                                                                 and personal level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Box 4.4: Fitting in and Handwashing&#13;
&#13;
 The following are quotes from focus group discussions:&#13;
 Positives&#13;
      · "I would be ashamed if people said I am dirty. Clean people are admired and respected in the community."&#13;
        (Kisumu district)&#13;
      · "You should be clean always... when you are clean you will appeal to everyone but when you are dirty people&#13;
        will avoid you." (Bungoma district)&#13;
      · "The picture is telling me that I must be a hardworking woman and not an idler so that I do not have to visit&#13;
        people all the time and start [saying]: help me with this and that." (Machakos district)&#13;
      · "I am not well [off], so at times I find myself with no money to buy soap. Sometimes I am forced to use&#13;
        porridge flour and a scrubbing sponge to wash off banana stains [and] I feel pain... But [since] I have no way&#13;
        out I try to bear the pain until the dirt comes off." (Mombasa district)&#13;
      · "The story I have is about a certain time we had gone to church. My church is Salvation Army, and we all dress&#13;
        in white. We had visitors in the church, we sang in the choir, the visitors we had were politicians.There was one&#13;
        lady whose dress was discolored, the politician stood up and said that all those whose dresses were sparkling&#13;
        white [should] come and receive some money... the woman with the discolored dress was left with nowhere&#13;
        to fit. It left me feeling that when you are clean you will get respect and you will appeal to people, but when&#13;
        you are dirty, you will just feel odd." (Bungoma district)&#13;
 Negatives&#13;
      · "There are times we lack soap and you still have to bathe, or wash your baby's clothes, and when I have soap&#13;
        I also use it to do all those things. So when I use water only, [only a] little dirt will come out and it will not be&#13;
        as dirty as it was... [but] when I use soap the dirt comes off completely." (Bungoma district)&#13;
      · "Not everyone here belongs to the same social class, and I can't force myself to fit into someone else's living&#13;
        styles." (Bungoma district)&#13;
      · "I cannot wash my hands because someone else has [already] washed." (Kisumu district)&#13;
      · "That shows that you do not have your own way of doing things and you just do things because friends are&#13;
        doing the same, yet they may not be doing [it] in the right way." (Nairobi district)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;4.7.5 Status&#13;
Box 4.5 has a remark about "status and how it relates to&#13;
handwashing".This was fifth after nurture, comfort, disgust&#13;
and fitting in. Status gives one freedom to interact with&#13;
others in society. It is closely related to fitting in.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Box 4.5: Status and Handwashing&#13;
&#13;
     The following is a quote from focus group&#13;
        discussions:&#13;
     · "I have chosen this one of a woman washing&#13;
        her hands, because I like... washing my hands&#13;
        when I come from anywhere... even when I&#13;
        greet somebody I come and wash hands." (Nyeri&#13;
        district)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.7.6 Purity                                                      Box 4.6: Purity and Handwashing&#13;
Box 4.6 has remarks about "purity and how it relates&#13;
to handwashing". This was sixth after nurture, comfort,           The following are quotes from focus group&#13;
disgust, fitting in, and status. Purity has to do with physical   discussions:&#13;
and spiritual cleanliness. It gives one peace of mind, allows     Positives&#13;
one to relax, knowing one is immune from diseases.                    · "I have to clean not only my body but also&#13;
                                                                         my clothes so that my heart can also be pure&#13;
As far as handwashing with soap is concerned, purity                     and... cleanliness is next to Godliness and&#13;
has to do more with physical, personal, and spiritual                    when you live well with the community, it&#13;
cleanliness. This is in harmony with respondents' definition             does you a lot of good." (Machakos district)&#13;
of hygiene. However, the relationship with handwashing                · "Being clean on the outside can make you&#13;
is not direct. This motivational factor is important only as             feel clean on the inside." (Kisumu district)&#13;
far as it highlights secondary benefits to washing hands              · "...when I am clean outside, even inside I feel&#13;
with soap.                                                               clean, even within my spirit and my mind."&#13;
                                                                         (Bungoma district)&#13;
                                                                      · "This picture relates directly to my Christian&#13;
                                                                         way of life. It shows that the outside portrays&#13;
                                                                         what is on the inside for a Born-Again&#13;
                                                                         Christian like me. It befits the Christian of life."&#13;
                                                                         (Bungoma district)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  Negatives&#13;
                                                                      · "At times I may sweat. Just taking a bath&#13;
                                                                         will not completely change the real me."&#13;
                                                                         (Bungoma district)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya      5&#13;
&amp;#12;4.7.7 Attraction&#13;
Box 4.7 has remarks about being "attractive and how it&#13;
relates to handwashing". This was seventh after nurture,&#13;
comfort, disgust, fitting in, status, and purity. It related&#13;
more to personal care, for example, bathing, changing&#13;
clothes, and so on, after a hard day's work; as well as being&#13;
attractive to your partner.&#13;
&#13;
As far as handwashing with soap is concerned, attraction&#13;
has to do with keeping hands clean to attract the opposite&#13;
gender. However, this is perceived to be pseudo, as it is&#13;
not a true reflection of the degree of cleanliness at the&#13;
personal, physical, and spiritual levels.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Box 4.7: Attraction and Handwashing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The following are quotes from focus group discussions:&#13;
    Positives&#13;
         · "There was a time when I was going through a rough time and I was separated from my husband for some&#13;
            time. I found myself begging too much. So now that we are back together, I have seen the importance of&#13;
            taking care of him." (Nairobi district)&#13;
         · "The job which my husband does involves coming into contact with meat and, at times, [it is] meat that is&#13;
            just about to go bad." (Nairobi district)&#13;
         · "It shows that these two people have a good relationship because if the man left in the morning while they&#13;
            were not on good terms, when he came back in the evening the wife would not have extended her hands&#13;
            towards him." (Nairobi district)&#13;
         · "You are the one who has washed your hands. So you are the clean one, that man is not clean, so he would&#13;
            not know if you are clean or not to attract him." (Bungoma district)&#13;
         · "The baby you have, it is the husband who gave you. It is good to look clean to your husband so that both&#13;
            of you can get children." (Kisii district)&#13;
         · "One day I was sitting outside with a friend. A man came where we were, then I left. Later my friend told me&#13;
            the man asked: `Who was this woman sitting with you? Her clothes are clean. Where does she work?' Then&#13;
            my friend told him, `This woman does not work with a mzungu (white man), she just likes to be clean... she&#13;
            just stays in her house'..." (Kisumu district)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;4.7.8 Overall Motivational Concept                                issues affecting sanitation include few toilets or latrines,&#13;
Ranking                                                           poor or no sewage systems, and poor flow of water&#13;
Based on the above insights, emotional benefits have to           leading to use of water believed to be contaminated.&#13;
do with purity, fitting in, status, and comfort. These are        Some comments in this regard were:&#13;
further related to one having "peace of mind, knowing                   · "Toilets must be put up and this has been a&#13;
that by washing hands with soap, they are contributing to                 directive from the Chief.... everyone who has&#13;
the well-being of their family (preventing diseases)". Also               a home or is planning to put up a home must&#13;
when "clean", one feels "attractive, acceptable, recognized,              build a toilet. If they do not have a toilet the&#13;
confident, and earns respect from the community... you                    premises will be pulled [down]. The Chief has&#13;
look rich... many people think you need money to be                       been discouraging flying toilets." (Women's leader,&#13;
clean," said someone in Kisii district. Another comment                   MYWO, Kisumu district)&#13;
was: "At times you might attend a baraza (community                     · "The digging of rubbish pits--people have not done&#13;
meeting); when you are clean and tidy, you will be                        it well." (Maendeleo ya Wanawake Organization&#13;
recognized and you are even given a chance to serve                       leader, Trans Nzoia district)&#13;
visitors." (Mombasa district)                                           · "The main barrier is the shortage of water..." (Chief,&#13;
On the other hand, functional benefits are related more                   Trans Nzoia district)&#13;
to "disgust". Toilets are believed to have the most germs.              · "There is need for sensitization on hygiene in the&#13;
As a result one needs to maintain high hygiene standards                  community...The dogs should also be well taken&#13;
to prevent infections. Water and soap are core tools. The                 care of as they have a tendency of entering the&#13;
use of soap is seen as a preventive measure (disinfecting).               kitchens often..." (Assistant Chief, Nyeri district)&#13;
For instance: "It will be easy to keep diseases away and the            · "We do not have septic tanks... dirty water&#13;
expenditure on treatment will be low. Also, if you get visitors           comes from this compound, goes to the roads...&#13;
you get the required respect from them and you will definitely            what they have not taught us is that each person&#13;
get first priority in many things." (Mombasa district)                    should have a hole dug in his compound to act&#13;
                                                                          like a septic tank to tap dirty water..." (Women's&#13;
"I am reminded mostly of shopkeepers who do not wash&#13;
                                                                          group leader, Kisii district)&#13;
their hands despite the kind of job they do. I remember a&#13;
time when I had gone to buy biscuits from the shop near           Absence of enough toilet facilities has led to sharing of&#13;
[my] home. When I got to the shop the owner was not at            the limited toilets or others opting to use the bush, which&#13;
the counter and two or so minutes [later] she appeared.           are far from the households. Further, water shortages limit&#13;
When she was giving me the biscuits I realized she had            the use of water. This makes behavior change a challenge,&#13;
feces on her hands. In disgust I asked her why she did not        as more people are likely to wash their hands with soap&#13;
wash her hands even after using the toilet.Then she asked         when it is convenient.&#13;
me who told me she had visited the toilet. I did not buy&#13;
the biscuits." (Machakos district)                                (b)     Water shortages&#13;
                                                                  Some areas, as noted earlier, experience prolonged&#13;
                                                                  shortage of water. In Machakos, water is a precious&#13;
4.8 Barriers to Handwashing&#13;
                                                                  commodity and people walk for long distances to&#13;
A wide variety of barriers to the practise of handwashing&#13;
                                                                  fetch water. Others have to buy it from vendors in the&#13;
with soap came through from the behavioral trial&#13;
                                                                  prevailing economic hardships. Therefore, usage of water&#13;
interviews and in-depth interviews of key informants.&#13;
                                                                  for handwashing is considered a waste; recycled water&#13;
Some barriers to handwashing are discussed below.&#13;
                                                                  is used. As one comment shows: "You might have soap&#13;
                                                                  and lack water for use, this might become a hindrance to&#13;
Physical barriers&#13;
                                                                  you... One cannot afford to buy soap although they may&#13;
(a)     Poor sanitation infrastructure&#13;
                                                                  have water..." (Behavioral trials, Bungoma district)&#13;
Overall, there is poor sanitation in most regions. Core&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                          Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   7&#13;
&amp;#12;(c)     Convenience&#13;
Convenience of accessing soap and water is important              HWWS adoption requires presence of soap and water to&#13;
in handwashing. Lack of convenience may arise due to              act as stimuli. During the BT interviews, it was evident that&#13;
location of soap, water shortages, location of toilets in the     the presence of soap and water increased incidences of&#13;
households, and the site where the risky juncture occurs.         usage.This was even more evident during the key junctures&#13;
                                                                  (after a visit to the toilet and before eating). Analysis of&#13;
      · Location of soap&#13;
                                                                  observations at handwashing sites revealed that primary&#13;
       Again, the BHT interviews and observations revealed&#13;
                                                                  caregivers who washed hands were likely to have water&#13;
        that there is no specific location for keeping soap&#13;
                                                                  and soap at the handwashing site.The presence of soap at&#13;
        for handwashing purpose in most households, as&#13;
                                                                  the handwashing site facilitates HWWS.&#13;
        these examples illustrate:&#13;
      · "At first I kept it inside a polythene bag on top of          · Location of toilets in households&#13;
        my box in the bedroom. After it became smaller                      Most toilets in rural areas are located at a&#13;
        I removed it from there, I got a small plate that I              distance from the main house. Handwashing sites&#13;
        do not use and I kept it on top of a wooden shelf                in most households were outside the kitchen or&#13;
        in the bedroom so that the children do not make                  main house. Distance reduces the chances of&#13;
        it dirty. I kept it on top of the box so that I am               handwashing after using the toilet.&#13;
        the only one who could reach it." (BHT, Nairobi&#13;
                                                                      · Lack of water and soap at site of risky&#13;
        district)&#13;
                                                                         juncture&#13;
      · "It stayed in the polythene bag for three days&#13;
                                                                      In rural areas most mothers carry children under five&#13;
        because first I used it for bathing, then I washed&#13;
                                                                         with them to the farm. They change diapers and&#13;
        the baby so it stayed there for a long time but&#13;
                                                                         feed children at the farm. At such junctures there&#13;
        from yesterday I removed it and kept it on the&#13;
                                                                         is no water or soap at site. Therefore, even when&#13;
        plate. The plate is waterproof and other people&#13;
                                                                         the mother knows it is good to wash her hands&#13;
        can easily reach it but I do not want the children&#13;
                                                                         she may not be able to do so due to lack of water&#13;
        to misuse it." (BHT, Nairobi district)&#13;
                                                                         and soap where she is. In other cases, mothers also&#13;
According to the observations during this study,                         change diapers at night. Consider the following&#13;
especially during behavioral trials (BT), the soap is                    comments:&#13;
kept in places which are not visible, such as under the               · "Yes, there were times when I am in the shamba&#13;
bed or other furniture (for people living in one-room                    (farm) with Pati and he defecates... I wipe him and&#13;
houses in urban areas) and on shelves above eye level                    continue digging... Nothing much... I felt guilty for&#13;
for people living in rural areas. This creates a barrier to              sometime... I have been given soap to wash my&#13;
washing hands with soap.                                                 hands but I keep forgetting. But after a while I got&#13;
&#13;
 Table 4.15: Access to Water and Cleansing Agents&#13;
                                                                                        Soap users          Non-soap users&#13;
 Was water available at the handwashing site?&#13;
                                                                Yes                      64%                     5%&#13;
                                                                No                       %                       45%&#13;
                                                                No observation           %                       4%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Was there a cleansing agent at the handwashing site?&#13;
                                                                Yes                      5%                      4%&#13;
                                                                No                       47%                     75%&#13;
                                                                No observation           %                       %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;       used to it." (BHT, Nyeri district)                              Nyeri district)&#13;
    · "In my case, I may have changed the baby during               · "[It was] kept in very special places... like where&#13;
       the night and I did not wash my hands so the                    visitors sit." (BHT, Nyeri district)&#13;
       only time I can do it is when I wake up." (BHT,              · "Soap is for a different social class." (BHT,&#13;
       Kisii district)                                                 Nyeri district)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Psychological barriers                                          (c) Perfumed soap&#13;
                                                                Some women felt perfumed soap was a turn-off for men;&#13;
(a) Cultural beliefs&#13;
                                                                they therefore did not participate with the rest of the family&#13;
Communities in Western Kenya (Kisumu, Bungoma, and&#13;
                                                                in the handwashing activity. Perfumed soap is discouraged&#13;
Kisii) have taboos that restrict sharing of toilets by adult&#13;
                                                                while handling food or handwashing before eating. As one&#13;
male and females. Physical toilet facilities are restricted&#13;
                                                                woman said, "My husband does not like soaps that smell,&#13;
to males (head of household). As a result, most children&#13;
                                                                so he did not use it." (BHT, Nyeri district)&#13;
and mothers end up using the bush. Distance from the&#13;
bush to handwashing facility results to higher incidences&#13;
                                                                (d) Lack of commitment by community leaders&#13;
of forgetfulness.&#13;
                                                                Previous campaigns on public handwashing that involved&#13;
                                                                community leaders showed lack of commitment by&#13;
(b) Value attached to soap&#13;
                                                                leaders as well as lack of transparency in management&#13;
Broadly, across all regions, soap is a valued commodity.&#13;
                                                                of behavior change promotional materials. Consider this&#13;
Use of soap for handwashing takes less priority. Soap is&#13;
                                                                example: "After the visitors came with the promotion on&#13;
preserved for household chores (washing clothes and&#13;
                                                                hygiene, the people of Kaisagat were not happy because&#13;
utensils) and personal care (bathing). Handwashing is&#13;
                                                                there were some conflicts of interest amongst those&#13;
most important before meals and after toilet use to a&#13;
                                                                people, especially the leaders. The other challenge is that&#13;
lesser extent. People are likely to use water only in such&#13;
                                                                when the promoters came with some materials, like soap&#13;
cases. For example, "Let me say it was a hard habit to pick&#13;
                                                                which were to be distributed equally to all households, a&#13;
up because I was not used to washing hands with soap at&#13;
                                                                few leaders took them to their homes and sold [them]...&#13;
all times. Many times I forgot to use the soap but the one I&#13;
                                                                which was not fair. But I liked the promotion because I&#13;
rarely forgot was after using the toilet because... I am used&#13;
                                                                remember even last year they constructed a very nice&#13;
[to that], though I washed with water only. But as days went&#13;
                                                                toilet for me. They were constructing toilets for some&#13;
by I got used to washing with this soap." (BHT, Nyeri)&#13;
                                                                households." (MYWO leader, Trans Nzoia district)&#13;
&#13;
Again, more households are compelled by the need to&#13;
                                                                (e) Beliefs&#13;
"protect the soap" from wastage, damage (excessive heat&#13;
                                                                Some believe handwashing is time consuming and&#13;
from fire or sun) and demand. Many end up hiding the&#13;
                                                                expensive; while others believe that harmful germs&#13;
soap ("under the table", "on the window sill", or "on top&#13;
                                                                are acquired from dirty physical surfaces, such as "soil,&#13;
of a tree trunk"), which makes access difficult. Some other&#13;
                                                                charcoal, feces, hands, toilet walls, brooms, hoes, and so&#13;
comments encountered were:&#13;
                                                                on" (mentioned across all regions).&#13;
    · "[It was] kept on top of the cupboard to avoid&#13;
       wastage... [otherwise] children play with it." (BHT,     Some believe that aloe vera, ash, sand, and stone can&#13;
       Kisumu district)                                         substitute soap. For instance, "They say aloe vera has&#13;
    · "It was the only soap in the bathroom, so I had           anti-bacterial benefits that are useful when bathing."&#13;
       to remove it to prevent wastage... many people           (Nyeri district)&#13;
       have bathed with it... it has washed many dishes&#13;
                                                                There is also a perception that handwashing is only&#13;
       and clothes." (BHT, Kisumu district)&#13;
                                                                important after a long call. For instance: "It is not a must to&#13;
    · "There was always someone touching it." (BHT,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                       Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya    9&#13;
&amp;#12;wash hands after a short call. Men are the ones who must        Radio, health centers, and community health workers are&#13;
wash hands after short call; they easily come into contact      the most credible channels of information on hygiene.&#13;
with many things, but women squat and don't necessarily         Radio has the widest reach among primary caregivers in&#13;
need to wash hands." (BHT, Bungoma district)                    case of national campaigns. Radio listenership is quite high:&#13;
                                                                78 percent claimed to have listened to radio the previous&#13;
Some mothers also believe that the stool of their children is&#13;
                                                                day; 84 percent claimed to own a working radio at the&#13;
not harmful to the mother. For instance:"The stool of a child&#13;
                                                                time of the interview. However, it is important to note&#13;
has never killed the mother." (Nyeri primary caregiver)&#13;
                                                                that according to the field observations, the radios were&#13;
                                                                owned by men and they controlled the channel listened&#13;
Poverty&#13;
                                                                to. This makes it essential to use other channels which are&#13;
Some respondents believe that handwashing with&#13;
                                                                effective in reaching female caregivers.&#13;
soap is a preserve of the rich. The overall majority (97&#13;
percent) of households had soap. However, 6 percent of          Overall TV viewership was  percent--going by previous&#13;
respondents in Bungoma had not used soap the previous           day activities. TV viewership was mainly concentrated&#13;
day due to lack of money. In addition, soap is prioritized      in the cities (Kisumu, Nairobi, and Mombasa). Only 6&#13;
for bathing, laundry and washing dishes. As this comment        percent claimed to own a TV.&#13;
puts it, "Poverty is also another barrier because due to&#13;
                                                                Informal channels that the campaign can consider using,&#13;
lack of money one cannot purchase soap. Most people...&#13;
                                                                especially in the rural areas, are (a) peer influencers; (b)&#13;
depend on the contracts to buy food and not soap." (BH,&#13;
                                                                religious institutions; (c) women's groups; and (d) authorities&#13;
Nairobi district)&#13;
                                                                through barazas. Market places, places of worship, and&#13;
                                                                hospitals are prime areas to reach caregivers&#13;
4.9 Communicating with the&#13;
Community                                                       A campaign carried on in schools can trickle down to&#13;
                                                                the community--7 percent of the women claimed that&#13;
                                                                school children are a source of information. This was high&#13;
4.9.1 What Channels are Effective?                              in Trans Nzoia and Bungoma where the Ministry of Health&#13;
Both informal and formal communication channels are&#13;
                                                                has initiated a hygiene and sanitation program in schools.&#13;
effectively passing information to the communities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 4.16: Communication Channels&#13;
&#13;
  Media vehicles                  Within the community Outside the community            Immunizations            Hygiene&#13;
  Friends and neighbors                  65%                        46%                    6%                       %&#13;
  Radio                                  49%                        60%                    48%                      44%&#13;
  Place of worship                       44%                        8%                     9%                       7%&#13;
  Health centers                         %                          %                      48%                      65%&#13;
  Chief                                  %                          5%                     0%                       0%&#13;
  Village elders                         %                          0%                     %                        7%&#13;
  School children                        %                          9%                     %                        4%&#13;
  Women group meetings                   6%                         %                      5%                       %&#13;
  Television                             9%                         4%                     %                        0%&#13;
  Community health workers               6%                         8%                     %                        %&#13;
  Market vendors                         %                          %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
40 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;4.9.2 Appropriate Campaign                               Only 4 percent claimed that English was their best&#13;
Language                                                 spoken language. At the national level, Kiswahili is the&#13;
The study established that best spoken language is       best campaign language to use--98 percent claimed&#13;
dependent on region. According to the study, 4 percent   that they can understand Kiswahili. It caters for tribal&#13;
claimed that Kiswahili was their best spoken language    differences and illiteracy levels. However, the campaign&#13;
while the rest were split across their mother tongues.   could also consider local languages for informal channels&#13;
                                                         and vernacular FM stations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                               Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   4&#13;
&amp;#12;                                         SECTION THREE:&#13;
                                         The Schools' Study&#13;
&#13;
5.0 Sanitation and Hygiene in                                 Other than the fact that toilet facilities are inadequate and&#13;
Kenyan Schools                                                overstretched, most are dirty. An observation of schools&#13;
                                                              where this study was carried out revealed the pathetic&#13;
5.1 Background                                                conditions of the toilets (see photographs in Appendix&#13;
                                                              C). The toilet floors were soiled with feces and wet with&#13;
Following the implementation of Free Primary Education        urine. Most girls' toilets and urinals had a strong stench.&#13;
(FPE) in 00, sanitation and school infrastructures have       Some had urine collecting in the corners, other had feces&#13;
been severely constrained. According to the Economic          on the walls. This poses a serious health risk for children&#13;
Survey, 006, school enrollment increased from 5.4             considering that some children in rural areas go to school&#13;
million children in 00 to 7.6 million in 005. The             bare-footed.&#13;
expansion of facilities has been slow compared to this        The government has come up with the School&#13;
growth in enrollment. Existing school infrastructure has      Infrastructure Improvement Grant (SIIG) in which ,04&#13;
also been suffering from a lack of investments over a         schools were identified as beneficiaries (00 schools per&#13;
number of years. Most schools have overcrowded                district). The selection of schools was based on current&#13;
classrooms and inadequate water and sanitation facilities.    poverty constituency indices compiled by the Central&#13;
The requirement for additional investment in primary          Bureau of Statistics (CBS) and physical infrastructure&#13;
school infrastructure is particularly acute in urban slums    conditions and enrollment statistics from the Ministry&#13;
and the poorest areas in Kenya                                of Education (MoE). Handwashing facilities have been&#13;
The school toilet standards are way below the                 incorporated in the infrastructure.&#13;
recommended international standards. A rapid assessment       Some schools, as in Kirinyaga district, have water but&#13;
in public schools in Nairobi, Machakos, Kajiado, and Kiambu   poor sanitation. They have received funding from JICA to&#13;
districts in 004 revealed a toilet ratio of :64. The toilet   improve the facilities. WHO and UNICEF are currently&#13;
ratio in Mombasa Municipality public schools is :. This       in the process of providing water facilities to selected&#13;
is way below the international standard of :5 for girls       schools. CARE is also working in Nyanza to improve&#13;
and :5 for boys (with urinal).                                access to water in schools.&#13;
According to discussions with members of the School           According to the MoE, handwashing falls within the scope&#13;
Infrastructure Management Unit (SIMU), there is a             of sanitation and hygiene. It needs to be packaged as such&#13;
lack of comprehensive data on the number of schools           for acceptability, especially amongst MoE stakeholders.&#13;
in Kenya with running water and handwashing facilities.       Therefore, handwashing campaigns in schools need&#13;
However, an audit of the ,04 schools revealed that            to be integrated with other existing programs, such as&#13;
only a negligible proportion had handwashing facilities       deworming.&#13;
(possibly as low as 5 percent). The rapid assessment&#13;
mentioned above revealed that over 90 percent of              5.2 Handwashing Initiatives in&#13;
schools in rural Kenya lack a source of safe water and        Schools&#13;
do not have any handwashing facility. According to the        Network for Water and Sanitation (NETWAS), UNICEF,&#13;
Mombasa Municipality, less than 50 percent in Mombasa         and African Medical and Research Foundation (AMREF)--&#13;
are connected with piped water system while 0 percent         in partnership with other stakeholders such as the Ministry&#13;
must use water from contaminated wells. This is despite       of Health--have established initiatives in schools. These&#13;
the fact that the UNICEF Kenya office has been working        initiatives are, however, not specific to handwashing but to&#13;
with the city council to improve sanitation in schools.       hygiene in general, and have been implemented through&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;the formation of WASH and Hygiene clubs in schools.                     a lack of support by teachers who perceive it as an&#13;
The organizations also coordinate seminars for leaders of               addition to their workload.&#13;
these clubs and teachers. Their initiatives include (a) using&#13;
leaky tins in areas with a shortage of handwashing facilities;&#13;
and (b) asking children to carry water in the morning to         5.3 Justification of the School Study&#13;
cater for water shortage in schools. However, handwashing        Primary school-going children were considered a special&#13;
with soap (HWWS) has not been emphasized, except in              target group in this study. Since habits acquired while&#13;
Olympic Primary School which did try the initiative but          one is young are likely to be carried over to adulthood,&#13;
discontinued it in the face of challenges.                       intervention in handwashing behavior would have a ripple&#13;
                                                                 effect for future generations. Handwashing with soap&#13;
A review of the initiatives provides the following lessons:      is part of the concept of hygiene, which forms part of&#13;
    · Such an initiative should consider soap in liquid          the social studies syllabus in primary schools. Children&#13;
       form rather than as a bar or powder.                      spend most of their active hours in a school environment&#13;
    · There is need for improvised soap dispensers to            and may also have different motivators and barriers to&#13;
       reduce wastage of soap.                                   handwashing.The study, hence, sought to understand their&#13;
    · There is need to involve the Ministry of Education         handwashing behavior in the school environment.&#13;
       to recognize HWWS in schools as an important&#13;
       step towards safeguarding the health of the               5.4 Objectives of the School Study&#13;
       children. Currently, the Ministry has undertaken          The objectives of the school study were to:&#13;
       other initiatives, such as deworming, which has an            · Obtain a baseline of current handwashing practices&#13;
       association with handwashing.                                    in schools;&#13;
    · HWWS cannot work in isolation; it requires to be               · Understand children's perception of dirt;&#13;
       integrated into the whole concept of hygiene.                 · Understand the risky hygiene practises of&#13;
    · Teachers and school administrations need to buy                   children;&#13;
       into the idea in order to continuously promote the            · Learn from a small trial of handwashing in schools;&#13;
       initiative.                                                   · Identify motivators and barriers to handwashing&#13;
    · Teachers supporting the initiative should receive                 with soap; and&#13;
       recognition, not necessarily monetary. Currently              · Determine how best to communicate handwashing&#13;
       the effectiveness of the clubs is decreasing due to              messages to them.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                       Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   4&#13;
&amp;#12;44 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;6.0 Methods Used in the School                                                               6.2 Selection and Description of&#13;
Study                                                                                        Schools for Study&#13;
                                                                                             The school study was carried out in  public schools&#13;
6.1 Overview of Methods                                                                      in the districts selected for the community study. Each&#13;
The study utilized both primary and secondary data                                           district had one school, except the cities which had two&#13;
across several methodologies.The study borrowed heavily                                      schools. The rationale for two schools in the cities was to&#13;
from the methods used in the Uganda study (Formative                                         represent both the middle class and the lower class. The&#13;
and Baseline Survey on Handwashing with Soap, 007). A                                        selection of schools was based on availability of water and&#13;
summary of field methods utilized in this study are listed                                   handwashing facilities. (See Appendix A for a description&#13;
in Table 6..                                                                                 of the schools targeted.)&#13;
&#13;
Table 6.1: School-Based Study Methods&#13;
    Method                          Sample                                                     Description                                       Data&#13;
&#13;
  Participant                 Eight researchers                Two observers (one male and one female) were                                 Field notes&#13;
  observation                                                  attached to one school; their special focus--observe                         (N = 8)&#13;
                                                               the behavior of children and adults, as well as document&#13;
                                                               school facilities, materials, and instruction practices.&#13;
&#13;
  Structured                  First 0 boys and 0 Two observers (one male and one female) observed the                                       Observation&#13;
  observations                girls observed on                handwashing behavior of children after toilet use during                     sheets&#13;
  before placing              one day per school break time on their first day in the schools.                                              (N =  x 0 =&#13;
  the soap                                                                                                                                  440)&#13;
  Structured                  First 0 boys and                 Two observers (one male and one female) observed the                         Observation&#13;
  observations                0 girls observed                 handwashing behavior of children after toilet use during                     sheets&#13;
  after placing               on the last day after break time on their last day in the schools.                                            Pre = 80&#13;
  the soap                    placing the soap                                                                                              Post = 76&#13;
&#13;
  Focus group                 Three groups per                 Focus groups were conducted with children in the study                       FGD transcripts&#13;
                              school                           classes to understand their values, aspirations, perception&#13;
                                                               of dirt, and handwashing in the hygiene hierarchy.&#13;
&#13;
  Baseline on                 The whole class in               A simple one-page questionnaire was administered to&#13;
  student                     upper primary                    the whole study class in upper primary.&#13;
&#13;
  Behavior trials             Whole school but                 Soap was placed for the whole school for one week.                           Debriefing notes,&#13;
                              with special focus on Three different types of soap were placed: perfumed bar; teacher FDG&#13;
                              the study classes     non-perfumed bar; and powder soap.                       transcripts&#13;
  Drawing                     One whole lower                  Children were asked to draw pictures of risky hygiene                        Drawings,&#13;
                              class                            practices; then 0 individuals of each sex from each class                    debriefing notes&#13;
                                                               were selected for debriefings to explain the pictures.                       (N = 80)&#13;
  Money game                  Four children per                Each child was given a photocopied KES ,0006 (US$4) Money form,&#13;
                              school (two boys                 note and was asked to write, on a form, how they    debriefing notes&#13;
                              and two girls from               imagined they would spend it; then a group debriefing                        (N = 48)&#13;
                              upper class)                     was held to talk about the different articles.&#13;
&#13;
  Social mapping              Upper and lower                  A focus group with only one objective of grouping the                        Social maps and&#13;
                              study classes                    social networks.                                                             debrief notes&#13;
6&#13;
 US$1 = KES 68.75 (as of August 30, 2008).Conversion rates are from http://coinmill.com/KES_USD.html;&#13;
  all conversions in the text are approximate. (KES stands for Kenyan Shillings.)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                        Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya    45&#13;
&amp;#12;7.0 Results&#13;
7.1 Baseline Behavior of Children                                Table 7.2: Handwashing After Defecation in the Community&#13;
in School                                                        and School Environment&#13;
The majority of the students observed (7 percent out of                                          School        Community&#13;
80 students) did not wash their hands. Only one school            Did not wash hands         7 (7%)             59 (5%)&#13;
in Nairobi had soap. The students who carried soap to             Handwashing with&#13;
the toilet were mainly girls. Handwashing with soap in            water only                 06 (8%)             (5%)&#13;
this school was influenced by WASH clubs' initiatives.            Handwashing with soap&#13;
Similar initiatives also existed in Bungoma and Trans Nzoia.      and water                        (%)          5 (%)&#13;
However, handwashing in these schools was with water              Total                           80            55&#13;
only. In Mombasa, there is a strong handwashing culture&#13;
after using the toilet, based on Muslim religious practices.&#13;
None of the kids washed their hands at all in Machakos,&#13;
Nyeri, and Kisii.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 7.1: Handwashing Behavior in Schools before Placing the Soap&#13;
                                     Total       Girls   Boys    Bungo Kisii    Kisumu Macha Msa Nbi           Nyeri Tran&#13;
 Did not wash hands                  7 (7%) 4            58               40     74        40       9     4    40     &#13;
 Washed with water only              0 (7%) 58            4        0      0        5        0       8     44    0     4&#13;
 Rinsed one hand with water only       5 (%)                               0       0         0             0    0       0&#13;
 Washed hands with soap and water        (%)                 0     0       0       0         0       0          0       0&#13;
 Total                                  380      176     204      25      40       79       40      39    80   40      37&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
7.2 Handwashing in the                                           7.3 Effect of Placing Soap in&#13;
Community versus Schools                                         Schools&#13;
The levels of handwashing with soap after defecation at          Unlike in Uganda, where soap and handwashing facilities&#13;
home are higher at home than in school, as indicated             were provided to the two study classes, this study provided&#13;
in Table 7.. These findings are a reverse of practices in        the soap to the whole school. No special arrangement was&#13;
Uganda where the level of handwashing was higher in              made for study classes.This was based on the fact that the&#13;
school than at home. The finding is explained further by         behavior needed to be studied in a natural environment.&#13;
the fact that 75 percent of children in upper primary            Soap was placed in the existing handwashing facilities for&#13;
claimed that they washed hands with soap more times at           the whole school. This approach revealed some barriers&#13;
home than in the school environment.This did not change          to adoption of the behavior that would not have been&#13;
after behavioral trials with 75 percent claiming the same.       identified otherwise. The behavioral trials in schools&#13;
                                                                 generated a lot of excitement among the children--some&#13;
The findings suggest that children may be facing unique&#13;
                                                                 washed their clothes! Overall, handwashing improved to&#13;
barriers to handwashing in schools compared to the&#13;
                                                                 55 percent from  percent. This may indicate that such&#13;
home environment. Therefore, there is a need for a&#13;
                                                                 behavior is easy to adopt in the school environment if&#13;
school-focused campaign to raise the levels of HWWS in&#13;
                                                                 access to water and soap supply is maintained.&#13;
the school environment.&#13;
In the community, out of the 65 events observed with              During the exit interviews, the head teachers reported&#13;
school children before they ate, 56 percent did wash their       a positive response towards the campaign, stating that&#13;
hands but only 8 percent used soap.                              more children were washing hands after using the toilet&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
46 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;Figure 7.1: Handwashing Before and After Placing Soap&#13;
&#13;
                                Pre=380                          Post=376&#13;
  00%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  80%&#13;
           72%&#13;
&#13;
  60%&#13;
                                                                                                                          55%&#13;
&#13;
  40%&#13;
                                    27%&#13;
                   23%&#13;
  0%&#13;
                                            16%&#13;
                                                                        3%&#13;
                                                                 1%                               2%              1%&#13;
  0%&#13;
            Did not                Hands washed            Rinsed one hand           Washed one hand          Hands washed with&#13;
           wash hand               with water only         with water only          with soap and water        soap and water&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
and before eating. The following comments are indicative              There was a feeling that the practice of HWWS in&#13;
of the children's attitude:                                           school is likely to trickle down to the community. During&#13;
    · "Before you came it was not very explosive as it is             the debriefing after the study in the school, the pupils&#13;
        now... in the sense that children are now doing it            reported that they had asked their parents to provide&#13;
        with a lot of vigor." (Head Teacher, Kisumu district)         soap for handwashing at home after using the toilet. That&#13;
    · "I have been observing how the children are                     the community will benefit is echoed in the following&#13;
        behaving... I find all they want is to wash hands             comments:&#13;
        even after eating... even before they handle their                · "The school will spread the behavior to the&#13;
        books... the children you picked began to inspire                    community and back home." (Trans Nzoia&#13;
        others." (Head teacher, Mombasa district)                            district)&#13;
    · "I have never seen something like this before, it                   · "They will help the community... improve [it]; by&#13;
        was the first time... I thought of better hygiene                    practising handwashing with soap... we will have a&#13;
        for our children... they were more attentive to                      healthy community." (Bungoma district)&#13;
        the visitors... something implemented here is                     · "They will not forget what they have been taught&#13;
        likely to be practised at home." (Trans Nzoia and                    as they have done it practically... the children are&#13;
        Machakos district)                                                   likely to be role models at home. The practical&#13;
    · "It was an improvement because of the way our                          part of it was good... will have an opportunity&#13;
        children have been brought up... some of them                        to practice it in school... however at home it&#13;
        are not exposed to washing hands with soap...                        may be difficult as the soap is kept away for other&#13;
        it was a new idea [in] the school... initially I was                 purposes. It will make the children become more&#13;
        skeptical it would not work, then day by day I saw                   in control of their hygiene, and agents of change."&#13;
        the children using [it]... especially those in lower                 (Mombasa, Kisumu districts)&#13;
        classes." (Bungoma district)                                      · "... I can see even the windows are now&#13;
    · "Nowadays when the lower primary [children] go                         being cleaned... activity has supported what&#13;
        to the toilet, they really try to ask for soap... more               the UNICEF came and taught the community."&#13;
        kids wash hands than before." (Nairobi district)                     (Nairobi district)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   47&#13;
&amp;#12;7.4 Knowledge, Perception,&#13;
and Attitude towards Hygiene                                       The core driver towards daily observation of hygiene is to&#13;
and HWWS                                                           be acceptable to one's peers and to the rest of the school&#13;
                                                                   community. For example, a child says, "Bad odor can make&#13;
7.4.1 Children's Perception of Dirt                                people avoid you... it is good to avoid smelling [of] sweat&#13;
and Use of Soap                                                    and [avoid] other children laughing at me."&#13;
From the children's perspective, dirt is "physical contact&#13;
with germs or bacteria which are invisible to the naked            The outward indicator as to whether one is observing&#13;
eye". Surfaces where germs are likely to be present are:           hygiene is being well-groomed, that is, "wearing clean&#13;
dirty surfaces, for example, toilet walls, floors (dust or mud);   clothes, maintaining short nails and hair."&#13;
dirty objects, such as brooms, mops, cash notes, writing&#13;
stationery, or contact with feces; working environment, for        On the other hand, the driver towards handwashing is to&#13;
example, on farms; poor personal hygiene standards, for            get rid of disease-causing germs, "though some children&#13;
instance, long nails, dirty hands; and dirty water or food.        still eat while inside the toilet to avoid sharing with friends."&#13;
                                                                   (Toilets are believed to have the most germs.)&#13;
Given the definition of dirt, situations where one is likely&#13;
to wash hands with soap are numerous.                              Insights&#13;
                                                                   For children, motivators for hygiene maintenance are&#13;
Soap is associated with germ removal as it contains "some          related more to attraction, status or fitting in. Handwashing&#13;
chemicals with ability to remove germs". Medicated soaps           with soap is associated more with its functional benefit,&#13;
are top on the list. Other means for germ removal include          that is, removal of germs.&#13;
use of insecticides "to kill insects that carry germs", and&#13;
boiling or treating water.                                         This finding is a true reflection of a child's personality--&#13;
                                                                   at their age, they are seeking recognition, identity, and&#13;
"They say that you should get rid of germs after using the         acceptability. Communications and campaigns on washing&#13;
toilet, and avoid taking in germs before eating."                  hands with soap should emphasize this need.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Despite the high association between soap and the                  7.4.3 Knowledge and Attitude&#13;
removal of "germs from the toilet", soap is used more for          towards HWWS&#13;
hygiene maintenance (personal and physical environment),           Children were asked to respond to `Yes' or `No' statements&#13;
but not for handwashing. Warm water or scrubs (such as             before and after the behavioral trials.This was intended to&#13;
sand and stone) are perceived to be a substitute for soap          asses their knowledge and attitudes towards handwashing.&#13;
by a few people.                                                   Figure 7. summarizes the statements before and after&#13;
                                                                   placing the soap.&#13;
7.4.2 Attitude towards Hygiene&#13;
Behaviors associated with hygiene maintenance include              Although there was little practice of HWWS in schools,&#13;
bathing daily (urban) or washing legs and the face (rural);        knowledge about handwashing was very high. There&#13;
good eating habits; drinking clean water; and a clean              was a slight improvement in children's attitudes towards&#13;
environment, for example, airing beddings (which gives             handwashing after the behavioral trials. However,&#13;
"protection from lice").                                           handwashing is perceived to be practised more at home&#13;
                                                                   than in the school, despite the fact that children spend&#13;
Spontaneously, handwashing is not top-of-the-mind and,             most of their active hours in school as compared to the&#13;
where mentioned, is associated more with "after visits             home environment. This indicates that promotion of&#13;
from the toilet and before eating" (which is practiced by a        HWWS in schools is important.&#13;
few people in urban towns, especially girls).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
48 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;Figure 7.2: Knowledge and Attitude Before and After Placing    excitement! According to the debriefing forms, after&#13;
Soap                                                           behavioral trials 8 percent indicated that handwashing&#13;
                                                               with soap is not a boring activity. Although this is not a&#13;
7.5 Motivators for Children                                    sustainable motivator in the long run, it could work at the&#13;
Washing Hands                                                  initial stages of the campaign to introduce such behavior&#13;
The motivations for children's handwashing can be              in schools.&#13;
determined by examining their debriefing forms after&#13;
                                                               Fitting in: Washing hands after using the toilet is the&#13;
the behavior trials, focus group discussions (FGDs), and&#13;
                                                               accepted code of conduct in school.The presence of other&#13;
drama enactments. The attitude statements which were&#13;
                                                               children washing hands acted as a trigger to handwashing.&#13;
discussed further in focus groups also highlighted some&#13;
                                                               This was raised during the debriefing with children after&#13;
handwashing motivators, which are discussed below:&#13;
                                                               behavioral trials. In addition, 84 percent of the children&#13;
Justification: The need to wash off germs that cause           indicated that they admire clean people, implying the&#13;
disease was the greatest motivator to wash hands,              need to fit in. According to the group panels, children&#13;
especially after using the toilet. This was drawn from the     highlighted that they asked their friends whether they had&#13;
scenario presented in focus groups where children noted        washed hands after using the toilet.&#13;
that those who did not wash hands are likely to fall ill or&#13;
                                                               Status: Clean and smart children are generally admired&#13;
get worms. In addition, a child leaving the toilet was said&#13;
                                                               in the school, according to the social group mapping. This&#13;
to have a lot of germs on her/his hand. About 80 percent&#13;
                                                               need to be liked is transferred to handwashing which is&#13;
or more are aware of the importance of handwashing&#13;
                                                               seen to fit into the concept of hygiene.&#13;
and that soap removes germs that cause diseases, even&#13;
unseen germs, after using the toilet. Handwashing is           Habit: Some children, especially in urban areas, claimed&#13;
covered under hygiene in social studies syllabus in all        to have picked up the habit of washing hands from parents&#13;
lower primary classes and pre-units.                           or elder siblings at home.This is mainly a driver to washing&#13;
                                                               hands before eating food and not after using the toilets.&#13;
Fun: Washing hands with soap was found to be fun&#13;
                                                               Sixty-eight percent of the children indicated in the pre-&#13;
and provided a form of play for the children. Children&#13;
                                                               evaluation forms that parents reminded them to wash&#13;
also washed their clothes with the soap, driven by the&#13;
                                                               hands with soap.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 7.3: Children's Views on Practising Handwashing with&#13;
&#13;
                                               Total    Nairobi Mombasa Kisii       Nyeri      Kisumu Macha Bung&#13;
Likes&#13;
Free from bacteria or germs                    66        7       4           6         9         50        5        5&#13;
Makes hands clean                              4         4       9           0                   7         4        56&#13;
Enjoys washing hands after using the toilet    9         7       7                    0          6         6        0&#13;
Prevents many diseases                         5         9                                       7                  &#13;
Leaves a nice smell on my hands                4         6                            0                    0        0&#13;
Just likes using such kinds of soap            4                             0        0          7         4        0&#13;
Makes me excited after using it                          4       0                               4         0        0&#13;
Feels fresh                                    6                             0                   0                  0&#13;
The soap softens the skin                      4                             0        0          0                  0&#13;
Like the liquid soap                                             0           0        0          0         0        0&#13;
Makes hands shiny                                                            0                   0         0        0&#13;
Soap was given to use for free                           0       0           0                   0                  0&#13;
Removes odor                                             0                   0        0          0         0        0&#13;
Removes stubborn stains                                  0       0                    0          0         0        0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   49&#13;
&amp;#12;Soap (by District)                                           Hygiene Interventions&#13;
Motivators for handwashing at school are emotional and       Interventions by organizations such as UNICEF and&#13;
functional. Functional motivators relate to germ removal     AMREF, through the formation of WASH or HEALTH&#13;
and prevention of diseases as well as having clean hands.    clubs have psychologically prepared the school community&#13;
                                                             to adopt high hygiene standards.This is likely to encourage&#13;
At the emotional level, soap provided excitement and an      high adoption for handwashing with soap.&#13;
opportunity for fun and enjoyment in washing hands. It           · "I believe in it myself. I once attended a course&#13;
also had an effect on the overall hygiene of the students:           which was done by UNICEF and we were told&#13;
in some schools children washed their heads, sweaters,               that we can reduce diseases by 50 percent just&#13;
shirts, handkerchiefs, and socks after the soap was placed           by washing hands. Therefore I insist on that."&#13;
for three days. The behavior was triggered by the need to            (Head teacher, Utange Primary School, Mombasa&#13;
be clean overall. The smell of perfumed soap was also a              district)&#13;
trigger and motivator to wash hands                              · "At times UNICEF comes and takes the children&#13;
                                                                     for hygiene seminars." (Teacher in charge of&#13;
Other motivators to washing hands with soap in schools               cleanliness, Nairobi district)&#13;
include role played by teachers, sensitization campaign by       · "There are drawings on the walls in the school&#13;
organizations such as UNICEF, and religious practices.               that demonstrate how to improve hygiene status."&#13;
                                                                     (Teacher in charge of cleanliness, Nairobi district)&#13;
Role of Teachers&#13;
Head Teachers and other teachers are the main champions      Religious Practices&#13;
of handwashing with soap in the school environment.          Muslims are specifically encouraged to wash their hands&#13;
Teachers act as role models; they also provide leadership    after using the toilet.&#13;
in hygiene related issues within the school.                     · "Muslims do not use toilet paper so it means that&#13;
    · "We are putting a number of fountains for drinking,            they use their hands... and this means [that] they&#13;
       and for washing hands after [using] the toilet."              need to wash their hands with soap. It ensures that&#13;
       (Head teacher, Mombasa district)                              we are also clean. Apart from removing germs and&#13;
    · "When they have played and soiled their hands                  bacteria it ensures that we are coming out of the&#13;
       we tell them to clean them before they go to their            toilet clean. When we wash our hands it is a sign of&#13;
       various classes." (Head teacher, Bungoma district)            cleanliness and it also smells good." (Head teacher,&#13;
    · "There are four handwashing points near the                    Kisauni Primary School, Mombasa district)&#13;
       classrooms and the students are not allowed to&#13;
                                                             Broadly, urban schools are more likely to practise&#13;
       eat before they wash their hands." (Teacher in&#13;
                                                             handwashing with soap compared to rural schools. It is&#13;
       charge of cleanliness, Nairobi district)&#13;
                                                             also important to note that religious practise plays a great&#13;
    · "Hygiene is taught from Class  and is emphasized&#13;
                                                             role in Mombasa.&#13;
       in the Sciences' subject." (Head teacher Kondele&#13;
                                                                 · "...the culture of handwashing is inside them, and&#13;
       Primary School, Kisumu district)&#13;
                                                                     it is part of our religious traditions." (Head teacher,&#13;
    · "I insist on washing hands even in front of Class&#13;
                                                                     Mombasa district)&#13;
       8... I would never eat before I wash my hands.&#13;
       They know I [am the first to] wash hands."            The core drivers towards handwashing during the&#13;
       (Head teacher, Utange Primary School, Mombasa         campaign were availability of soap, involvement of peers,&#13;
       district)                                             practicability, and availability of water.&#13;
    · "Teachers act as examples by washing their hands           · "We always tell them in Home Science, but in the&#13;
       so that the children may follow." (Head teacher,              real sense we do not practise it... presence of&#13;
       Nyeri district)                                               water encouraged the students." (Head teacher,&#13;
                                                                     Kisumu district)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
50 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;Insights                                                          difference between children in rural areas and those&#13;
The insights from teachers further support findings from          in cities. The major cities, Nairobi and Mombasa, had a&#13;
the children. Communication strategies should involve             lower uptake of handwashing with soap that was placed&#13;
teachers as they are children's role models. Teachers             in schools (7 percent of children in each school did not&#13;
champion handwashing by agitating for the construction            adopt the behavior).&#13;
of handwashing facilities; providing leadership through&#13;
example; and teaching the curriculum, which includes              Barriers to handwashing with soap in schools can also&#13;
hygiene.                                                          be derived from debriefing forms, interviews with the&#13;
                                                                  head teachers and focus group discussions with teachers&#13;
Religion is also an influencer of adoption of the habit&#13;
                                                                  and drama sessions. Table 7.4 summarizes the dislikes in&#13;
(especially in Islamic communities).&#13;
                                                                  the debriefing forms. The barriers to adopting the new&#13;
There is need for consistence supply of soap and water            behavior were inadequate handwashing facilities, soap&#13;
(to act as stimulus) for the behavior to be sustained.            disappearance, lack of sustainable supply of soap, water&#13;
Peer pressure is also a motivator.                                shortage, lack of convenience, lack of support by teachers,&#13;
                                                                  and resistance to change.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
7.6 Barriers to Handwashing with                                  Management of Soap: Disappearance and&#13;
Soap in Schools                                                   Wastage&#13;
The barriers to handwashing can be deduced from                   This was a major challenge in the research and soap had&#13;
reasons why children in study classes refused to wash             to be replaced every now and then. A previous study by&#13;
hands with soap. Overall, 8 percent of 587 children in            AMREF in schools had highlighted this as a challenge that&#13;
the study, in upper primary classes, claimed that they            had led to Olympic Primary discontinuing provision of&#13;
used soap after placement while 9 percent did not                 soap.The use of a soap dispenser had been recommended,&#13;
use the soap. This indicates a positive change towards            and Practical Action is working on a design that could be&#13;
the practises of HWWS. However, there was a notable               used for this purpose.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Table 7.4: Children's Dislikes on Practising Handwashing with Soap (by District)&#13;
&#13;
                                                  Total   Nairobi Mombasa Kisii            Kisumu Machakos          Bung&#13;
 Dislikes&#13;
 Bad smell                                         56        6                               5                        7&#13;
 Soap was dirty or placed on a dirty surface       54        0         9            4       0                         0&#13;
 Overcrowding or conflicts due to sharing                    6         5            7       4        0                0&#13;
 People who don't wash their hands with soap       8         5                                       8                0&#13;
 Smell of soap remains on hands                                                     0       6                         0&#13;
 Washing with dirty water                          6                   0            0                                 0&#13;
 Soap was not enough                                         4         0            0       7        0&#13;
 WHWS consumes a lot of time                                 5                              4        0&#13;
 Becoming dirty even after washing                 8                                                 &#13;
 Shortage or disappearance of soap                 6                   0                             &#13;
 Some people misuse it                             5         0                      0                0&#13;
 Water can sprinkle on books                                 0         0                    0        0&#13;
 N=                                               587       129        119          62     117       44&#13;
 Note: N = Number of respondents&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   5&#13;
&amp;#12;    · "One of the problems we encounter is that once soap        Other chores are thus likely to take precedence over&#13;
       is exposed there, some children tend to take it away."    handwashing because of such a scarcity. Some schools&#13;
       (Teacher in charge of cleanliness, Bungoma district)      rely on water supply from vendors, whose source is not&#13;
                                                                 trusted. In instances where diesel-powered water tanks are&#13;
Physical Environment of Handwashing Area                         used, the constant supply of fuel becomes a challenge.&#13;
There was overcrowding at the handwashing area due to                · "We have no money to buy more containers..."&#13;
inadequate facilities, since the population of public schools           (Trans Nzoia district)&#13;
in Kenya is very high and the handwashing facilities are             · "We are dealing with 600 students..." (Mombasa&#13;
limited.There was a lot of pushing during break times, and              district)&#13;
this may have discouraged some children from washing                 · "We need someone to lend us money to dig&#13;
their hands.                                                            boreholes." (Trans Nzoia district)&#13;
                                                                     · "We need washing basins to avoid wasting time."&#13;
In addition, the poor maintenance of handwashing facilities&#13;
                                                                        (Kisumu District)&#13;
is likely to cause accidents because of slippery surfaces.&#13;
                                                                     · "Water is a problem... for example, as far as&#13;
Most handwashing areas were muddy with poor drainage,&#13;
                                                                        drinking water is concerned, we have to go to the&#13;
especially in the rural areas. The soap also got dirty.&#13;
                                                                        plumber to come and repair it as it has broken&#13;
    · "The number of children is high... there is&#13;
                                                                        down." (Head teacher in charge of cleanliness,&#13;
       congestion at the taps." (Head teacher, Kisumu&#13;
                                                                        Utange Primary School, Mombasa district)&#13;
       district, and Head teacher, Kilimani, Nairobi district)&#13;
    · "It could be slippery and therefore dangerous if           Resistance by Teachers&#13;
       they (children) happen to step on it." (Kilimani          The behavior trial experienced resistance by some&#13;
       Primary School, Nairobi district)                         teachers and head teachers in some schools, especially&#13;
                                                                 in the cities. In other schools teachers reserved the right&#13;
Lack or Cost of Soap&#13;
                                                                 to keep the soap for their use. Some headmasters were&#13;
Soap is perceived to be expensive and not catered for in&#13;
                                                                 not in favor of the idea of soap introduction as they felt&#13;
the school budget allocations. Currently, parents believe&#13;
                                                                 it would be a waste of time. Resistance by teachers was&#13;
that primary education is free and it would face a challenge&#13;
                                                                 driven by their perception of this being an addition to&#13;
to ask for contributions from them. This is in spite of the&#13;
                                                                 their workload and possible challenges in sustaining the&#13;
fact that parents also attach value to soap as indicated by&#13;
                                                                 supply of soap in school.&#13;
58 percent of the children (source: pre-evaluation forms)&#13;
who said that parents remind them to take care of soap           Positioning of the Handwashing Area and the&#13;
because it is expensive.                                         Toilets&#13;
    · "It is expensive... sometimes you may not be able          Handwashing facilities in most schools are located far from&#13;
       to afford [it]. Sometimes the handling of soap is a       the toilets, sometimes even in the opposite direction. This&#13;
       problem if any amount is put at the water point."         led to some pupils forgetting to wash hands; they would&#13;
       (Head teacher, Mombasa district)                          rush to class immediately after using the toilet.&#13;
    · "Lack of finance... we have poor parents, if you&#13;
                                                                 Perception of Handwashing as a Bother&#13;
       tell them to buy [then] only a quarter of them will&#13;
                                                                 During the debriefing, a few children felt that handwashing&#13;
       comply, the rest will think that it is a way teachers&#13;
                                                                 is inconvenient because it takes a lot of time. This was&#13;
       have devised to get money from them." (Head&#13;
                                                                 complicated by the queues at the handwashing area. This&#13;
       teacher in charge of cleanliness, Mombasa district)&#13;
                                                                 sentiment was also echoed during focus group discussions&#13;
    · "If the children do not get soap this practice will&#13;
                                                                 where the children said that at times they are too hungry&#13;
       die easily." (Teacher, Kiarithaini Primary School,&#13;
                                                                 to walk to the handwashing area to wash their hands&#13;
       Nyeri district)&#13;
                                                                 before eating. They prefer to eat their food without&#13;
Lack of Consistent Water Supply                                  washing hands. Handwashing is also not considered when&#13;
Most schools do not have a consistent water supply.              the children are running against time, for example, during&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;break time (after using the toilet) and lunch time (before               is most preferred. This should include the local and school&#13;
eating lunch).                                                           communities. For such a campaign to work, endorsement&#13;
                                                                         by the Ministry of Health is vital. There is also a need to&#13;
Adoption of New Behavior: Challenges&#13;
                                                                         construct more handwashing facilities and have a system&#13;
It may take a while for children to fully adopt handwashing with soap.&#13;
                                                                         of maintaining them. This includes provision of soap.&#13;
This is because of many reasons. One is existing preconditioned&#13;
behavior where handwashing is done in a hurry.                           According to headmasters, mobilizing parents to&#13;
     · ".....a culture of just touching the water with the               provide soaps in schools may be a challenge. This is due&#13;
        fingertips, then the children go and eat, is hard to break."     to the parents' belief that education is free; hence the&#13;
        (Head teacher, St. Marks Nyabera, Kisumu district)               government is responsible for providing all the facilities&#13;
                                                                         required. Therefore, consistent supply of soap in schools&#13;
In addition, germs are perceived to be not only on the&#13;
                                                                         may require intervention by the Ministry of Education.&#13;
hands but on other objects, such as pencils and paper, as&#13;
well. Children `eat or chew' these objects. The children's&#13;
habit of buying snacks and eating them on their way home&#13;
from school is also likely to pose a challenge.&#13;
                                                                         7.7. Communication with Children&#13;
     · "They eat paper and biro pens which carry a lot of&#13;
        dirt." (Head teacher, Nyeri district)&#13;
                                                                         7.7.1 Life of a Kenyan Child&#13;
                                                                         During school days, day-to-day activities focus on personal&#13;
     · "They sneak and buy snacks at the fence with&#13;
                                                                         hygiene, studies, and helping in light household chores&#13;
        no supervision and they chew a lot of sugarcane&#13;
                                                                         such as fetching water and washing utensils.&#13;
        on their way to or from home where they have&#13;
        not washed their hands." (Teacher in charge of                   During leisure time, more rural children are involved in&#13;
        cleanliness, Kisii district)                                     household chores in comparison to children in urban&#13;
     · "Whatever has been practised at school will not                   areas where television and playing are prevalent. Most&#13;
        be practiced at home as a result of soap not being               rural children play outdoor games compared to urban&#13;
        there." (Head teacher, St. Marks, Kisumu district)               children who have more indoor games.&#13;
&#13;
Parents as role models do not support teachers when                      In addition, rural children are more involved in farm work such&#13;
it comes to educating children on the importance of                      as looking after livestock and milking, especially boys. Children&#13;
washing hands with soap. This does not apply only to                     engage in religious activities over the weekend (Saturday&#13;
handwashing but to general hygiene and healthy issues.                   madrasa classes for Muslims; Sunday school for Christians). Rural&#13;
Such resistance is experienced mainly in rural areas. After              children are more likely to be engaged in daily observation of&#13;
the introduction of free primary education in 00, most                   religious activities compared to urban children.&#13;
parents are hesitant in contributing towards any project&#13;
                                                                         Insights&#13;
in schools. Some head teachers in rural schools raised&#13;
                                                                         Given the above profile, we can easily conclude that&#13;
challenges they are experiencing in getting parents to&#13;
                                                                         socialization of children into adopting hygiene practices&#13;
cooperate in current health programs such deworming,&#13;
                                                                         is passed on through practical chores. Based on findings&#13;
providing sanitary care for girls, fighting jiggers, and so on.&#13;
                                                                         from this study, it was found that girls in upper primary&#13;
They also fail to provide the basics for children, such as&#13;
                                                                         school have a higher tendency to wash hands with soap&#13;
school uniforms and shoes, among other things.&#13;
                                                                         compared to boys (as evidenced in Mombasa, Nairobi,&#13;
     · "Sometimes parents are not cooperative... there&#13;
                                                                         and Kisii).&#13;
        are some children who come to school from Monday&#13;
        to Friday without even bathing." (Nairobi district)&#13;
                                                                         7.7.2 What Drives the Kenyan&#13;
                                                                         Child?&#13;
Insights&#13;
From the behavior trials and focus groups in schools, we                 Children's Role Models&#13;
have established that a participative learning environment               Children identified their role models and, from the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya      5&#13;
&amp;#12;reasons they gave, we were able to identify their values                                                    income (land or livestock).&#13;
which include: popularity, success, and modernity; ability to&#13;
                                                                                                        · Luxury values (emotional benefits)&#13;
impact positively on other peoples' lives; and to be loved&#13;
                                                                                                        These are items such as new clothes (uniforms&#13;
or nurtured unconditionally.&#13;
                                                                                                            and shoes), toys, electronic or computer games,&#13;
                                                                                                            computers, ornaments and jewelry (Nairobi,&#13;
Tangible Values (What money can buy)&#13;
                                                                                                            Mombasa, and Nyeri), fancy wear, and automobiles&#13;
Children were given a photocopy of KES ,0007 (US$4)&#13;
                                                                                                            (cars and scooters), and bicycles.These items depict&#13;
and were asked to list what they would buy with the&#13;
                                                                                                            an image of being "successful", that is, showing that&#13;
money. The objective of the exercise was to understand&#13;
                                                                                                            "poverty has been conquered".&#13;
tangible values. Based on the findings, tangible values&#13;
range from basic to luxurious. Urban children's values are                                       Broadly, the above tangible values enhance intangible&#13;
skewed towards a luxurious lifestyle.                                                            values associated with role models. The core theme is the&#13;
                                                                                                 need to conquer poverty.&#13;
      · Basic values (functional benefits)&#13;
      These are items related to the basic necessities of&#13;
           life, which include: household items such as utensils                                 7.7.3 Perceptions of `Cool'&#13;
           and food; educational items such as stationery; to                                    Based on insights from focus groups with children, and&#13;
           do with the house (that is, pay rent), source of                                      through the money game, a definition of `being cool' was&#13;
&#13;
Table 7.5: Children's Role Models&#13;
   Role models                                                                           Attributes admired&#13;
&#13;
    Media personalities (for example, Swaleh                                  Depict civilization, western lifestyle, represent success and dress in&#13;
    Mdoe)                                                                     trendy manner (Nyeri and Mombasa districts).&#13;
                                                                              "Big house, car", sophistication... expensive furniture and electronics,&#13;
                                                                              toys", exposure "through lots of travel... education".&#13;
    Politicians (for example, Raila Odinga and                                Command attention, have high social standing.&#13;
    Obama)&#13;
    Administrative officers (for example, D.O.,                               "Always the first people to know what is happening in the&#13;
    Chiefs)                                                                   community".&#13;
    International football stars (for example,                                Command attention, have high social standing.&#13;
    Zinedine Zidane)&#13;
    Professionals such as doctors, teachers,                                  Impact positively on other peoples' lives.&#13;
    engineers, policemen, lawyers, religious                                  Protects or defends the people--"it is a good job when you help&#13;
    leaders                                                                   reduce death".&#13;
                                                                              "Education changes the lives of others... teachers like seeing their&#13;
                                                                              students excelling in exams and making it in life...They dress smartly,&#13;
                                                                              are always clean, teach difficult subjects, live in good houses, and&#13;
                                                                              have power to control children" (rural children).&#13;
    Advertisement models (for example,                                        Nurturing role of the mothers and happy children (urban&#13;
    models in Omo, Sunfill, Dettol, and Jik), for                             children).&#13;
    the role played by the mother and child in&#13;
    the advertisements&#13;
    Parents, other siblings, and relatives                                    They show love and affection.&#13;
                                                                              "Helping each other with difficult sums, for example"; "are generous,&#13;
                                                                              polite, understanding, knowledgeable, and strong".&#13;
&#13;
7&#13;
 US$1 = KES 68.75 (as of August 30, 2008).Conversion rates are from http://coinmill.com/KES_USD.html; all conversions in the text are approximate. (KES stands for Kenyan Shillings.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
54 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;formulated. `Being cool' has to do with good personality                · Antiseptic soaps (Dettol, Protex): Ability of the&#13;
(intelligent, strong, well groomed), good personal and                     soaps to remove germs after playing.&#13;
health care, being materially successful, high interpersonal            · Dental care (Colgate and Close Up): Sensitive to&#13;
skills, and an outgoing nature, especially in games.                       children's hygiene.&#13;
                                                                        · Margarine (Blueband): Healthy product to consume&#13;
For urban children, the definition of `cool' is derived from&#13;
                                                                           as it has vitamins for active children.&#13;
advertisements, especially the ones aired on television.&#13;
                                                                        · Cooking fat (Kimbo): Good food.&#13;
Table 7.6 summarizes the findings.                                      · Mosquito management (Supa net, Power Tab and&#13;
Rural children's definition of `cool' is derived more from                 Doom): Health management.&#13;
the school environment. It includes excelling in studies,&#13;
having great interpersonal skills, and looking smart. Also         Insights&#13;
`cool' is behaving in a morally good way, for instance,            `Cool' has to do with a personality that is intelligent, well&#13;
avoiding alcohol or not going to discos.                           groomed, has high interpersonal skills, and good health&#13;
Advertisements that portray `cool' include Omo, Milo, Jik,         care management. Soap plays an important role in bringing&#13;
Nakumatt, Power tab, Kimbo, Dettol, Blueband (urban                about this image (though this is more at a personal care&#13;
children). Children's perceptions of various advertisements        level as opposed to handwashing). Antiseptic soaps are&#13;
are illustrated below:                                             perceived to be `cool' to use. This follows an emphasis&#13;
    · Detergents (Omo, Ushindi, Toss, and Jik): Perceived          on Dettol Cool communication, especially in Nairobi and&#13;
         to be solutions for dirty and stained clothes.            Mombasa.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 7.6: Perception of `Cool'&#13;
&#13;
  Attribute                                  Definition&#13;
&#13;
  Intelligent in studies                     "In Maths and English".&#13;
  High interpersonal skills                  Express yourself and mingle with other children.&#13;
  Respect                                    Achievements in sports, class.&#13;
  Positive personality                       Being generous, helpful, treats people equally.&#13;
  Ability to defend yourself                 In a fight, especially when fighting bullies.&#13;
  Wealth                                     "You don't have to depend on anyone... have own bedroom with toys,&#13;
                                             video games, computer... good furniture... expensive toys... a car,&#13;
                                             motorcycle, bicycle... winning lottery".&#13;
  Clean, well groomed, smart, and            Boys: "...being well dressed in new clothes that are well fitting and always&#13;
  neat                                       ironed... wearing suits..." (Kanzu).&#13;
                                             Girls: "...wearing trendy clothes such as hipsters, one sleeved- or bare-&#13;
                                             back blouses... wearing jewelry" (more urban).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             Nairobi and Kisumu: trendy/fancy wear.&#13;
                                             Mombasa: modest, that is, long hijab, buibui, low-heeled shoes, well-kept&#13;
                                             hair, polished shoes, clean teeth "gives one confidence", new uniform.&#13;
  Active or outgoing personality             Participating in sports and athletics (football for boys), dancing.&#13;
  Healthy eating habits                      Eating a balanced diet.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                          Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   55&#13;
&amp;#12;The school social mapping echoes similar findings.                discipline, comradeship, and sporty--which are admired.&#13;
                                                                  On the other hand, negative personality traits such as&#13;
7.7.4 Social Mapping in School                                    greed, selfishness, a do-not-care attitude, and lack of&#13;
The social mapping exercise broadly revealed a school             respect for other peoples' property are least valued.&#13;
community that is segmented along personalities.                  Children fitting into different segments also tended to&#13;
Segmentation is along attributes such as pride, intelligence,     form friendship groups. Table 7.7 illustrates this.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 7.7: Summary of Social Mapping&#13;
&#13;
  Pride                 They are like peacocks, "beautiful, neat, tidy and clean", show offs, confident about themselves,&#13;
                        want to be noticed, tend to wear trendy clothes, and eat expensive snacks. They love lifestyle&#13;
                        items (music, trendy clothes or food).&#13;
                        Their pride is not a reflection of their true self as they are "pretenders... for example,&#13;
                        befriending prefects because they are afraid to get into trouble".&#13;
                        Some are not serious in studies, tend to play more, and do things to get noticed, especially in&#13;
                        class. "They walk with a swagger... make noise in class... eat in class... hit desks like drums...&#13;
                        sing and laugh in class... have don't-care attitude".&#13;
                        For others, pride is the result of being gifted, for instance, they may be good in sports or&#13;
                        intelligent.&#13;
                        Within this group, one is likely to have separate groups for boys and girls.&#13;
  Intelligence          These bright students, at the top of their class, enjoy studying and are liked by teachers.&#13;
                        They also enjoy reading, traveling, and sports. To them, being `cool' is working hard in class and&#13;
                        celebrating good performance.They are also health conscious.They like sharing knowledge; are&#13;
                        therefore referred to as "educators".&#13;
                        They have a calm personality and are generally helpful and merciful.&#13;
                        They are anti-social, arrogant, rowdy ("make bad jokes"), and physically strong. They enjoy&#13;
  Bully                 aggressive games such as wrestling.&#13;
                        Tight friendship exists amongst them. They were described as behaving like an army, criminals,&#13;
                        or "like the Armenian brothers".&#13;
                        They are also perceived as being abnormal. They exhibit a stronger tendency of being selfish,&#13;
                        mean, and secretive.&#13;
&#13;
  Sporty                They are good in games, are physically fit, and eat well. Their definition of `cool' is derived from&#13;
                        their love for sports.&#13;
&#13;
  Buddy                 They have a strong sense of friendship and loyalty. The play groups are not gender sensitive.&#13;
                        They protect each other, and enjoy studies and sports. Their definition of `cool' is derived from&#13;
                        enjoying their good performance.&#13;
&#13;
  Thief                 They steal from others, even school stationery; they lack keenness in class.&#13;
  Greed                 They are also known as hyenas or gluttons. They like eating and playing, and are dirty&#13;
                        students.&#13;
  Selfishness           They are also referred to as beggars. They are mean and secretive, and eat in class.&#13;
  Discipline            They are obedient and religious.&#13;
  Fat                   They are bright and clean but fat.&#13;
  Dirty                 They are also referred to as "forgotten ones". They are not presentable, are ill mannered, and&#13;
                        have poor hygiene standards ("don't brush their teeth").&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
56 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   57&#13;
&amp;#12;                                 SECTION FOUR:&#13;
                         Conclusions And Recommendations&#13;
8.1 Conclusions                                                        of the importance of washing hands facilitated the&#13;
    · Handwashing behavior with only water is practised,               adoption of the behavior. Active participation by&#13;
       especially after contact with stool, but the adoption           teachers in the campaign will be critical to the&#13;
       of soap in handwashing needs to be scaled up.                   adoption and sustainability of the behavior in&#13;
    · Awareness regarding the importance of washing                    schools. The reluctance of teachers to support&#13;
       hands with soap, especially after using the toilet, is          the health clubs in schools has reduced the&#13;
       high.There is, however, a weak relationship between             effectiveness of such clubs in promoting hygiene.&#13;
       handwashing with soap (HWWS), diseases, and                  · Perfumed soap was a facilitator in schools.&#13;
       their effects on the day-to-day lives of children and&#13;
       the entire community.                                    Barriers to Handwashing&#13;
    · In Kenya there is a strong culture of washing the         Barriers at the community level include:&#13;
       face in the morning. HWWS in the morning after               · Lack of soap for handwashing. Due to poverty, soap&#13;
       defecation is also combined with washing the face.              is reserved for high priority usage: bathing, laundry,&#13;
       Incidences of washing hands after using the toilet              and washing dishes. Further, poverty minimizes&#13;
       later in the day may be lower.                                  the perceived risk of not washing hands with soap&#13;
    · Overall, 97 percent of the households have                       where the mother has knowledge.&#13;
       accessibility to soap.                                       · Lack of a designated place for handwashing in the&#13;
    · Washing hands with soap takes low priority at the                community.&#13;
       household level. It is ranked fourth after bathing,          · Distance between the toilet and source of water.&#13;
       washing the laundry, and washing dishes.                     · Perfumed soap.&#13;
    · Women are the key decisionmakers on soap usage&#13;
       at the household level.                                  Barriers at the school level include:&#13;
    · Ninety-four percent of caregivers believe that their          · Placement of the handwashing facilities in schools.&#13;
       family can be healthier if they washed hands with               The facilities are either very far from the toilets or&#13;
       soap.                                                           located in the opposite direction.&#13;
    · Level of handwashing for primary school children              · Size of handwashing facilities. They are too high for&#13;
       after defecation at school is lower than at home.               children in the lower primary classes.&#13;
                                                                    · Overcrowding at the handwashing facilities. There&#13;
Motivators                                                             were limited facilities to cater for the school&#13;
    · The motivators and barriers to washing hands with                population. This discouraged lower primary school&#13;
       soap in a school environment are distinct from the              children and girls from washing hands.&#13;
       community level.                                             · Soap disappearance and wastage. Schools that&#13;
    · Disgust, nurture, and comfort are the motivators                 had tried this initiative raised this as the greatest&#13;
       of handwashing at the community level. Justification,           challenge the initiative faced.&#13;
       fun, and fitting in are the motivators in the school         · Poor, or lack of, water drainage of handwashing&#13;
       environment.                                                    facilities. This led to accumulation of dir ty&#13;
                                                                       water in the trough and spilling around the&#13;
Facilitators of Handwashing                                            handwashing site.&#13;
    · Convenient presence of soap and water came out                · Lack of support from teachers. In some schools&#13;
       strongly as a facilitator in both the community and             such an intervention is perceived as an addition&#13;
       school context.                                                 to the workload for teachers who feel they are&#13;
    · The role of teachers as a role model and reminder                already overworked.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
58 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;Potential Challenges in the Campaign                                 behavior at home.&#13;
At the school level the foreseeable potential                     · The communication program should be based on&#13;
challenges are:                                                      aspirational messages to connect with children&#13;
    · Maintaining a consistent supply of water.                      and use peer group education. Existing clubs could&#13;
    · Obtaining a consistent supply of soap.                         be utilized to promote adoption of the behavior.&#13;
    · Managing soap.                                                 However, measures must be put in place to ensure&#13;
    · Maintaining a high level of interest in the new                vibrancy of the clubs. Strategies of keeping the&#13;
       behavior until it becomes a habit.                            clubs active could be borrowed from the Boy&#13;
                                                                     Scout or Girl Guide Movement.&#13;
At the community level, the potential challenges are:&#13;
                                                                  · The project should consider a reward system&#13;
    · Ensuring the campaign is based on the day-to-day&#13;
                                                                     for teachers in charge of the campaign in school,&#13;
       challenges that mothers face&#13;
                                                                     which need not necessarily be monetary.&#13;
    · Facing resistance to change.&#13;
                                                                  · The soap used in school should be in liquid form.&#13;
                                                                  · For long-term impacts, the campaign should seek&#13;
8.2 Recommendations&#13;
                                                                     to influence the design of sanitation facilities to&#13;
There is need for a community- and school-focused                    incorporate appropriate handwashing facilities&#13;
campaign. A school-based campaign should consider the                which are conveniently located.&#13;
following:&#13;
                                                              The community-based campaign should consider the&#13;
    · The project should partner with other stakeholders&#13;
                                                              following:&#13;
       who can prepare soap dispensers that minimize&#13;
                                                                  · The      campaign     should    also   promote      the&#13;
       soap wastage. Practical Action is in the process&#13;
                                                                     recommended way of washing and drying hands.&#13;
       of developing dispensers that are designed for&#13;
                                                                  · Radio       and     interpersonal      communication&#13;
       handwashing in schools.&#13;
                                                                     methodologies will be key in reaching mothers&#13;
    · The handwashing with soap campaign cannot work&#13;
                                                                     effectively.&#13;
       in isolation; it requires to be integrated into the&#13;
                                                                  · The campaign could consider different execution&#13;
       whole concept of hygiene in school and existing&#13;
                                                                     messages which will promote handwashing&#13;
       related programs, such as deworming.&#13;
                                                                     behavior at different junctures.&#13;
    · The campaign should adopt an integrated&#13;
                                                                  · Messages should capture the aspirations and&#13;
       approach to incorporate the Ministry of Education,&#13;
                                                                     dreams that mothers have for their children.&#13;
       teachers, and parents. This will ensure that soap is&#13;
                                                                  · To reduce the incidence of forgetting to wash&#13;
       incorporated in the school budgets or a provision&#13;
                                                                     hands after using the toilet, the campaign could&#13;
       is made where the parents can be encouraged&#13;
                                                                     utilize leaky tins that are placed next to the toilet.&#13;
       to contribute. The parents would support this&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   59&#13;
&amp;#12;Appendix A: Background Information on Schools in the Study&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Districts       Schools         Total            Number of      Water source&#13;
 Mombasa         .               population       toilets        One working water tap, utility connected. Rationing&#13;
                 Kisauni         ,50:             0:             can leave school without water for two or three&#13;
                 Primary         77 girls,        0 for girls,   days. Tank stores up to one day's water supply. Shares&#13;
                                 79 boys          0 for boys     same compound with Mlaleo. Sanitary facilities in&#13;
                                                                 better state.&#13;
                 .               649:             8:             One working water tap, utility connected. One&#13;
                 Utange          69 girls,        4 for girls,   nonfunctioning borehole, which had been used&#13;
                 Primary         0 boys           4 for boys     during periods of water rationing. Security of source&#13;
                                                                 is an issue as surrounding community has little&#13;
                                                                 water and school compound is not fenced. Rural&#13;
                                                                 surroundings.&#13;
 Kisumu          .               ,600                            Has running water from a borehole with an electric&#13;
                 Kondele                                         pump. Unless the pump breaks down, the water runs&#13;
                 Primary                                         4 hours.&#13;
 Nyeri           4.                                              The school had running water from a neighboring&#13;
                 Kiarithaini                                     coffee factory water project. The taps are spoilt and&#13;
                 Primary                                         water runs.&#13;
 Bungoma         5.              78:              0:             Located at the foot of Mt Elgon, the school has&#13;
                 Masaba          40 girls,        6 girls,       running piped water from Cheskaki water project.&#13;
                 Primary         8 boys           4 boys         The school has 4-hour supply as it depends on&#13;
                                                                 gravity.&#13;
 Kisii           6.              70:              0:             The school has two Roto tanks of 90 liters; one is&#13;
                 Amosogo         94 girls;        0 boys;        strategically located at the end of the building, near&#13;
                 Primary         98 boys          0 girls        the toilets. They depend on rain water but there is&#13;
                                                                 sufficient water due to rains.&#13;
 Trans Nzoia     7.              40:              0:             A larger Roto tank has been installed and depends&#13;
                 Gosete          60 girls;        6 girls;       on rain water. Pupils bring water on a daily basis in&#13;
                 Primary         80 boys          4 boys         turns and empty in the tank. There is water on a daily&#13;
                                                                 basis.&#13;
 Machakos        8.              4                :              One tap in compound. Small break in pipe leading&#13;
                 Katine                           5 girls;       from tank occurred three days prior to the school&#13;
                 Primary                          6 boys         audit and has rendered tap inoperative. School has&#13;
                 School                                          funds to pay for repair and local repairman has been&#13;
                                                                 consulted with; work expected soon. The school has&#13;
                                                                 unrestricted access to working tap on adjacent S.A.&#13;
                                                                 Church compound. Water source for both taps is&#13;
                                                                 borehole on church compound.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
60 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;Appendix B: Physical Observations                                unbearable. The floor is clean, though the bowls are&#13;
of Hygiene Standards                                             stained and broken; there is no water for flushing in the&#13;
                                                                 toilets. The handwashing facility is outside the toilet but&#13;
A physical check of the sanitation conditions in the school      there is only one functional tap fitted with a pipe that&#13;
environment revealed poor sanitation and low levels              drains the water in a drum.&#13;
of hygiene. There were inadequate facilities to cater for        Kilimani School: The toilets are relatively clean as they&#13;
the student population. Schools in Kisumu and Bungoma            are washed twice per day. There is no water in the taps&#13;
experience flooding during the rainy season, leading to          so the students wash their hands outside at a facility near&#13;
deterioration in sanitation facilities.                          the canteen.&#13;
(a) Mombasa                                                      (f) Bungoma&#13;
Kisauni: The toilets are not clean and have a foul smell.        Amasago School: The toilets are divided into cubicles&#13;
The handwashing facility has clean running water even            without doors and have an open roof. Some toilets are&#13;
though there is only one tap. The facility is next to the        dirty; with feces on the walls and urine on the floor. The&#13;
toilets "on the outside". Children tend to crowd during          boy's toilets do not have a roof and emit a foul smell. The&#13;
break time, mostly to drink water and to wash their heads        school has two handwashing areas: one tap is located next&#13;
which cools their bodies because of the heat.                    to the head teacher's office while the other is next to the&#13;
Utange: The toilets were under repair at the time of study.      staff room. They are functional, but used by the teachers&#13;
There is a tap outside the toilet with clean water supplied      more. The location of the handwashing areas acts as a&#13;
from a tank. There is no specific water drainage system,         barrier to handwashing by children.&#13;
and water spills all over the ground.                            The school has leaky tins which were introduced following&#13;
(b) Kisii                                                        a cholera outbreak in the area. Handwashing with only&#13;
Masaba DEB: The girls' toilets' floor and wall are not well      water is practised in the school.&#13;
made; they are made of `unfinished' wood, which is not           (g)Trans Nzoia&#13;
covered. Feces is visible and the toilets are wet with urine.    Goseta School: The situation of the toilet construction is&#13;
The boys' toilets have mud walls and have a foul smell.          fairly done as the floor is cemented, the walls are made of&#13;
Leaky tins are used for washing.                                 bricks, and the roof made of iron sheet. The boys' toilets&#13;
                                                                 are not clean. Most opt to urinate outside the latrines,&#13;
(c) Nyeri                                                        leading to a strong stench. The school has one plastic tank&#13;
Kiarithani Primary: The urinals are dirty but the toilets        that rarely has water and therefore students bring water&#13;
are clean. There are two handwashing facilities: one near        from home.&#13;
the toilet and another near the kitchen. The one located&#13;
                                                                 (h) Kisumu&#13;
near the toilet is too high for children in the lower classes.&#13;
                                                                 Kondele School: The toilets are very dirty and the stench&#13;
Further, it is wet and muddy, and has poor drainage.&#13;
                                                                 is strong--such that it "can be felt 50 meters away". The&#13;
The taps are faulty and water runs throughout the day.&#13;
                                                                 floor is dirty and wet with feces and urine. There is no&#13;
Although there is no water shortage in this area, children&#13;
                                                                 clean water for handwashing (except for the dirty, murky&#13;
use the dirty water in the reservoir to clean classrooms.&#13;
                                                                 water in a tank), which some students dip their hands in.&#13;
(d) Machakos&#13;
                                                                 St. Mark School: The toilets are dirty and wet. Most&#13;
Katine Primary: The toilets are well maintained as far as&#13;
                                                                 students urinate outside the urinals (sometimes girls too&#13;
cleanliness is concerned, but have no lids. The toilets are&#13;
                                                                 urinate outside the toilets). This makes the toilets smell&#13;
made of cement and are painted. The handwashing area&#13;
                                                                 foul. The handwashing area, which is near the toilets,&#13;
has only one tap in the school with a small drainage space.&#13;
                                                                 always lacks water.&#13;
(e) Nairobi&#13;
Olympic School: The toilet is filthy and the stench&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                       Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   6&#13;
&amp;#12;Appendix C: Photographs of                                     Hutley, S., S. Morris., and V. Pisana. 997. `Prevention of&#13;
Conditions in Schools                                          Diarrhea in Young Children in Developing Countries.'&#13;
                                                               WHO Bulletin 75 (2): 163.&#13;
References&#13;
Central Bureau of Statistics (CBS) Kenya, Ministry of Health   Ministry of Education, Government of Kenya. 006. Kenya&#13;
(MoH) Kenya, and ORC Macro. 004. Kenya Demographic             Education Sector Support Program: School Infrastructure&#13;
and Health Survey 2003. Calverton, Maryland: CBS, MOH,         Technical Handbook. School Infrastructure Management&#13;
and ORC Macro.                                                 Unit. Version One.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Central Bureau of Statistics (CBS) Kenya, Ministry of          Public Health Department, Municipal Council of Mombasa&#13;
Planning. Economic Survey (006).                               and UNICEF (Kenya Country Office). 006. Proposal for&#13;
                                                               the Improvement of Facilities in Mombasa Municipality Public&#13;
Curtis, V. C., and S. Cairncross. 00. `Effect of Washing       Primary School.&#13;
Hands with Soap on Diarrhea Risk in the Community:&#13;
A systematic Review.' The Lancet Infectious Diseases 3:        World Bank (WSP) and Steadman Uganda. 007. Baseline&#13;
275­281.                                                       and Formative Research on Handwashing with Soap.&#13;
                                                               Unpublished research.&#13;
Environmental Health Project. 004. Activity Report 8.&#13;
Planning Tools for the Nepal Public Private Partnership for    World Bank and TMS International. 006. Understanding&#13;
Handwashing Initiative.                                        the Tanzanian Consumer in Respect to Hand washing with&#13;
                                                               Soap. Unpublished report.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya   6&#13;
&amp;#12;64 Study Findings on Handwashing Behaviour in Kenya&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;                    WSP-Africa Region Office&#13;
                    World Bank, Hill Park Building, Upper Hill&#13;
                    P.O. Box 30577-00100, Nairobi, Kenya&#13;
&#13;
                    Tel: +254-20-3226334&#13;
                    Fax: +254-20-3226386&#13;
                    wspaf@worldbank.org&#13;
                    www.wsp.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
REPUBLIC OF KENYA&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="11529276">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2009/01/11529276/your-hands-clean-enough-study-findings-handwashing-soap-behaviour-kenya
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2009/01/11529276/your-hands-clean-enough-study-findings-handwashing-soap-behaviour-kenya</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2009/01/11529276/your-hands-clean-enough-study-findings-handwashing-soap-behaviour-kenya</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2009/12/18/000334955_20091218022650/Rendered/INDEX/522360WSP0Hand1Box345555B001PUBLIC1.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2009/12/18/000334955_20091218022650/Rendered/PDF/522360WSP0Hand1Box345555B001PUBLIC1.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2009-12-18T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2009-01-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Are your hands clean enough? Study findings
            on handwashing with soap behaviour in Kenya
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Washing hands with soap at the right
            times can reduce instances of diarrhea by 35-50 percent.
            Evidence also suggests that handwashing with soap can reduce
            acute respiratory infections (ARIs) by 30 percent. Past
            initiatives in Kenya have focused on raising awareness of
            handwashing with soap but they have not fully translated
            into behavior. An in-depth understanding of motivators and
            barriers to handwashing at a national level is critical for
            a behavioral change campaign. This study has been designed
            to provide baseline information on handwashing behavior in
            detail, by looking at behavior practised with regard to
            handwashing with soap; factors that influence handwashing
            behavior in schools and in the community's context. The
            study also provides information on preferred and trusted
            channels of communication.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Are your hands clean enough? Study findings
            on handwashing with soap behaviour in Kenya
        </docna>
        <display_title>Are your hands clean enough?
            Study findings on handwashing with soap behaviour in Kenya</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2009/01/11529276/your-hands-clean-enough-study-findings-handwashing-soap-behaviour-kenya</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing,Primary Education,Food &amp; Beverage Industry,Population Policies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Education,Industry,Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>Kenya</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Africa!$!80458</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000334955_20091218022650</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>Water and Sanitation Program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Education,Industry,Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            aged, Availability of Water, baby, Bars,
            basic needs, behavior change, behavioral change, behavioral
            changes, boarding, breastfeeding, Caregivers, child
            mortality, cholera, citizens, clean clothes, clean water,
            cleanliness, Communication Channels, community education,
            community health, cooking, crime, Dates, Diarrhea, diarrheal
            diseases, diet, dirty hands, domestic violence, drug abuse,
            early marriages, Environmental Sanitation, flour, Focus
            Group Discussions, foods, formal education, fruit, future
            generations, germs, girls, Hand Washing, hands with soap,
            Handwashing, Health centers, health workers, HIV, holistic
            concept, hospitalization, hospitals, Household Level, human
            beings, Human Immunodeficiency Virus, husbands, Hygiene,
            illness, Immunodeficiency, Infant, Infant Mortality, Infant
            Mortality Rate, information on hygiene, interpersonal
            communication, intervention, isolation, kids, lack of
            knowledge, Learning, live births, living standards, Marital
            status, marketing, mass media, meat, Medical Research,
            Ministry of Education, Ministry of Health, mother, national
            level, Nongovernmental organizations, old age, orphans,
            peace, Personal care, personal hygiene, physical
            environment, poor hygiene, porridge, potatoes, Primary
            Caregivers, primary classes, Primary Education, primary
            school, primary school children, promotional materials,
            Public Health, quality of life, radio, radio programs, rape,
            religious beliefs, religious institutions, religious
            practices, respect, risk of contamination, Role Models,
            rural areas, rural population, safe stool disposal,
            Sanitation, sanitation activities, sanitation facilities,
            school children, School-age children, SCHOOLS, secondary
            school, Soap, social class, Social Economic Status, social
            networks, social science, Social Sciences, spouse, teachers,
            teaching, technical assistance, Television, toilets, TV,
            typhoid, unemployment, urban areas, vegetables, violence,
            wash both hands with soap, wash hands with soap, Washing
            Hands, waste, water supply, woman, workers, World Health
            Organization, young mothers
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water- Water and Sanit Prgrm (GWASP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>52236</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>AIDS HIV</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV/AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Basic Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>HRH</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Workers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV and AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deworming</ml:concept><ml:concept>Placement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Primary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources for Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drainage</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Kenya</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>