<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>NOTE NUMBER 266&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                              P U B L I C           P O L I C Y           F O R         T H E&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                         privatesector&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                              54118&#13;
DECEMBER 2003&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                             Exchange Rate Risk&#13;
                                                                               Philip Gray and Timothy       Allocating Exchange Rate Risk in Private Infrastructure Projects&#13;
                                                                               Irwin&#13;
                                                                                                             E a c h ye a r d eve l o p i n g c o u n t r i e s s e e k b i l l i o n s o f d o l l a r s o f i nve s t m e n t&#13;
                                                                               Philip Gray (pgray@&#13;
                                                                                                             i n t h e i r i n f r a s t r u c t u re , a n d p r i vat e i nve s t o r s , m o s t l y i n r i c h&#13;
                                                                               worldbank.org) is a senior&#13;
                                                                               private sector development    c o u n t r i e s , s e e k p l a c e s t o i nve s t t r i l l i o n s o f d o l l a r s o f n ew s av i n g s .&#13;
T H E W O R L D B A N K G R O U P PRIVATE SECTOR DEVELOPMENT VICE PRESIDENCY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               specialist, and Timothy&#13;
                                                                                                             P r i vat e f o re i g n i nve s t m e n t i n t h e i n f r a s t r u c t u re o f d eve l o p i n g&#13;
                                                                               Irwin (tirwin@worldbank.&#13;
                                                                               org) a senior economist, at   c o u n t r i e s wo u l d s e e m t o h o l d g re at p ro m i s e . B u t f o re i g n i nve s t o r s&#13;
                                                                               the World Bank. This          m u s t c o p e w i t h vo l at i l e d eve l o p i n g c o u n t r y c u r re n c i e s . M a ny at t e m p t s&#13;
                                                                               Note is a companion to&#13;
                                                                               Philip Gray and Timothy       t o d o s o h ave c re at e d a s m a ny p ro bl e m s a s t h ey h ave s o l ve d . T h i s&#13;
                                                                               Irwin, "Exchange Rate         N o t e p ro p o s e s t h at i nve s t o r s t a ke o n a l l f i n a n c i n g - re l at e d ex c h a n g e&#13;
                                                                               Risk: Reviewing the&#13;
                                                                               Record for Private&#13;
                                                                                                             r at e r i s k , eve n t h o u g h t h i s m ay m e a n h i g h e r t a r i f f s f o r c o n s u m e r s a s&#13;
                                                                               Infrastructure Contracts,"    a p re m i u m f o r b e a r i n g t h at r i s k .&#13;
                                                                               Viewpoint 262 (World&#13;
                                                                               Bank, Private Sector and&#13;
                                                                                                             The standard advice on allocating risk--to                    cost of the service and the risk can be shared&#13;
                                                                               Infrastructure Network,&#13;
                                                                                                             assign it to the party best able to manage it--has            widely to lessen the impact.&#13;
                                                                               Washington, D.C., 2003).      controversial implications for the allocation of                  The allocation of exchange rate risk is often&#13;
                                                                                                             exchange rate risk in a private infrastructure                done through tariff adjustment formulas that&#13;
                                                                                                             project. Three parties can bear the risk of                   implicitly share risk through the way they adjust&#13;
                                                                                                             exchange rate movements in the first instance:                the tariff over time. If indexation is allowed, tar-&#13;
                                                                                                             the private investors (whether foreign or local               iffs can reflect the exchange rate in several ways:&#13;
                                                                                                             equity-holders or creditors), the host country                 Allowed prices or revenue can be fully or par-&#13;
                                                                                                             government (ultimately, its taxpayers), and cus-                  tially indexed to the exchange rate.&#13;
                                                                                                             tomers of the service. Some argue that investors               Input costs that depend on the exchange rate&#13;
                                                                                                             --or at least their ultimate shareholders--                       can be treated as a pass-through, so that cus-&#13;
                                                                                                             should bear the risk because they can diversify                   tomers pay the actual costs of the inputs.&#13;
                                                                                                             away country-specific exchange rate risk. Others               The contract can provide for a renegotiation&#13;
                                                                                                             argue that the government should bear the risk                    of allowed prices or revenue if the exchange&#13;
                                                                                                             because it is responsible for macroeconomic                       rate moves outside a specified band.&#13;
                                                                                                             policies that strongly influence the exchange                     At one extreme of the risk sharing spectrum,&#13;
                                                                                                             rate. Still others argue that customers should                Argentina effectively indexed 100 percent of&#13;
                                                                                                             bear it because they must ultimately pay for the              costs to the dollar. The implications of this are&#13;
&amp;#12;E X C H A N G E R A T E R I S K ALLOCATING EXCHANGE RATE RISK IN PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE PROJECTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 now being fought out by the investors and the              They can influence the underlying source of&#13;
                                 Argentine government, which has prevented                  the risk. Governments, for example, can&#13;
                                 significant tariff increases since the devaluation         reduce the rate of depreciation and the&#13;
                                 of the Argentine peso. Most countries use a                volatility of the exchange rate by keeping&#13;
                                 hybrid approach to tariff adjustment. Part of the          budget deficits small and inflation low.&#13;
                                 tariff is indexed to local inflation, part is           They can influence the sensitivity of the value&#13;
                                 indexed to dollar inflation, and some costs are            of a project or of their interest in it to the risk.&#13;
                                 straight pass-throughs. But there is still much            Project sponsors, for example, can reduce&#13;
                                 debate about what share of the cost base should            the sensitivity of the value of their share-&#13;
2&#13;
                                 be indexed to local inflation and what share to            holding to the exchange rate by reducing the&#13;
                                 international costs. And tariff adjustment mech-           project's reliance on foreign currency debt.&#13;
                                 anisms are not the only approach: governments           They can hedge or diversify away the risk.&#13;
                                 sometimes provide exchange rate guarantees to              Hedging exchange rate risks is possible in only&#13;
                                 cover repayment of foreign currency debt.                  a few developing countries. But most of the&#13;
                                                                                            ultimate foreign shareholders of the project&#13;
                                 Nature and sources of exchange rate risk                   company--individuals with savings in mutual&#13;
                                 To shed more light on the debate requires first            funds, pension plans, and life insurance--can&#13;
                                 looking more closely at the nature and sources             diversify their savings, limiting their exposure&#13;
                                 of the risk. Exchange rate risk, as defined here,          to any one country's exchange rate risk (as&#13;
                                 is variability in the value of a project, or of an         defined).&#13;
                                 interest in the project, that results from unpre-          The principle of optimal allocation can there-&#13;
                                 dictable variation in the exchange rate.               fore be restated as follows: Exchange rate risk&#13;
                                     There are two types of exchange rate risk:         should be allocated according to the parties' abil-&#13;
                                 project and financing related. Project exchange        ity and incentives to influence the exchange rate,&#13;
                                 rate risk arises when the value of a project's         change the sensitivity of the value of the project&#13;
                                 inputs or outputs depends on the exchange              (or of their interest in it) to the exchange rate,&#13;
                                 rate. Typical infrastructure projects sell their       and hedge or diversify away the risk. Because the&#13;
                                 outputs domestically, so, valued in local cur-         principle involves three types of management, its&#13;
                                 rency, revenues usually are not subject to             implications are not clear cut (table 1).&#13;
                                 exchange rate risk. But any input that is trad-            The government's influence over the&#13;
                                 able, even if it is not imported, will have a world    exchange rate is one factor that, other things&#13;
                                 price, so its cost, measured in local currency, will   equal, argues in favor of allocating project and&#13;
                                 vary inversely with the exchange rate. The cost        financing-related exchange rate risk to the gov-&#13;
                                 of fuel, for example, creates exchange rate risk       ernment. But this argument should not carry&#13;
                                 for a thermal electricity generator.                   too much weight. Allocating the risk to the gov-&#13;
                                     Financing choices affect the amount of             ernment is unlikely to improve the quality of its&#13;
                                 exchange rate risk borne by different partici-         decisions affecting the exchange rate--both&#13;
                                 pants in the project (shareholders, creditors,         because the relationship between the exchange&#13;
                                 customers, taxpayers). In particular, loans            rate and the government's financial position is&#13;
                                 requiring repayment in foreign currency expose         affected in complex ways by many factors unre-&#13;
                                 shareholders to exchange rate risk. As a result,       lated to the project and because governments&#13;
                                 shareholders may seek to shape the contractual         do not respond to financial incentives in the&#13;
                                 arrangements to pass on some or all of the risk        same way as firms and individuals do.&#13;
                                 to the government or customers (through                    If the government does not assume the&#13;
                                 exchange rate guarantees or indexation of the          exchange rate risk, the risk must be shared&#13;
                                 tariff to the exchange rate).                          between customers and investors (sharehold-&#13;
                                                                                        ers). Neither can influence the exchange rate,&#13;
                                 Optimal allocation of exchange rate risk               so the choice turns on the other two factors.&#13;
                                 Parties can manage exchange rate risk in three             Consider first project exchange rate risk.&#13;
                                 ways:                                                  Customers can sometimes influence the sensi-&#13;
&amp;#12; Table   Ability of customers, shareholders, and government to manage exchange rate risk&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1        Project risk&#13;
         Influence over exchange rate&#13;
                                                           Customers&#13;
&#13;
                                                           None&#13;
                                                                                     Shareholders&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     None&#13;
                                                                                                                   Government&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                   Great&#13;
         Influence over sensitivity of project             Limited, but can change   Limited, but can              Little&#13;
         to exchange rate                                  consumption in response   sometimes change inputs&#13;
                                                           to changes in the cost    in response to changes in&#13;
                                                           of tradable inputs        the cost of tradable inputs&#13;
                                                                                                                                3&#13;
         Ability to cope with risk by                      Little                    Great                         Little&#13;
         hedging or diversification                                                  (through diversification)&#13;
&#13;
         Financing-related risk&#13;
         Influence over exchange rate                      None                      None                          Great&#13;
         Influence over sensitivity of value of            None                      Great (through choice         None&#13;
         investors' interest in company to exchange rate                             of financial structure)&#13;
         Ability to cope with risk by hedging              Little                    Great                         Little&#13;
         or diversification                                                          (through diversification)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
tivity of a project's value to the exchange rate by                     the project to the exchange rate (they have no&#13;
changing their consumption levels in response                           control over whether the investors decide to use&#13;
to changes in the cost of tradable inputs. When                         financing that creates exchange rate risk).&#13;
the cost of fuel rises as the exchange rate depre-                      Moreover, most customers have no good natural&#13;
ciates, customers may be able to mitigate the                           hedges against the risk of currency fluctuations--&#13;
adverse effect on a power project's value by cut-                       and in most developing countries no realistic&#13;
ting their electricity consumption. In other                            opportunities to acquire hedges or diversify away&#13;
cases investors may be better placed to mitigate                        the risk. Indeed, because exchange rates tend to&#13;
project exchange rate risk. For example, they                           fall during macroeconomic crises, their ability to&#13;
may be able to change the mix of inputs (using                          pay higher tariffs is likely to be lowest just when&#13;
more hydro and less thermal power) to soften                            the exchange rate has fallen.&#13;
the effect of depreciation. Shareholders are also                           Investors, however, choose financing and&#13;
better placed than customers to diversify away or                       thus control the extent of financing-related&#13;
hedge exchange rate risk--because of their abil-                        exchange rate risk. And their ultimate share-&#13;
ity to diversify risk in equity markets and, in a few                   holders are well placed to diversify away much&#13;
developing countries, to hedge risk using                               of the risk they choose to take on.&#13;
exchange rate derivatives.&#13;
    This suggests that project exchange rate risk                       Implications for prices and financing&#13;
should be shared between investors and cus-                             Although investors should generally face some&#13;
tomers according to their ability to respond in                         project and all financing-related exchange rate&#13;
value-enhancing ways to changes in the exchange                         risk, they still need to be able to recoup their&#13;
rate--erring toward investors, given their greater                      costs and make a return that is reasonable given&#13;
ability to hedge or diversify away the risk. For                        the risks they take. Not protecting investors&#13;
many infrastructure projects, however, project                          from exchange rate risk may well imply higher&#13;
exchange rate risk is small. Financing-related                          tariffs. Moreover, if tariffs are not linked to the&#13;
exchange rate risk tends to loom much larger.                           exchange rate, they need to be linked to an&#13;
Should investors or customers bear this risk?                           index of local inflation, possibly adjusted to&#13;
    Customers are in a poor position to manage                          more closely reflect the cost of inputs (for exam-&#13;
the risk because they have no influence over the                        ple, an electricity utility's tariffs might be linked&#13;
sensitivity of the value of shareholders' interest in                   to an index in which the price of fuel has greater&#13;
&amp;#12;E X C H A N G E R A T E R I S K ALLOCATING EXCHANGE RATE RISK IN PRIVATE INFRASTRUCTURE PROJECTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
weight than in the consumer price index). Over          caught up with the exchange rate reduction, AES&#13;
the long term the effect on prices will be similar      Tietê will repay the advances from cash that would&#13;
whether tariffs are linked to local inflation or to     otherwise have gone to shareholders.&#13;
the exchange rate (see the companion Note).&#13;
But with a link to local inflation, currency crises     Conclusion&#13;
will tend not to cause such immediate, politi-          Despite the drawbacks of high levels of foreign&#13;
                                                                                                                       viewpoint&#13;
cally perilous price increases.                         currency debt, the argument for foreign capital&#13;
    What are the implications for financing if nei-     remains. Developing countries need investment&#13;
                                                                                                                       is an open forum to&#13;
ther the host country government nor customers          in infrastructure, and local debt and equity&#13;
                                                                                                                       encourage dissemination of&#13;
protect foreign investors from financing-related        investors may well be unable to meet all the costs&#13;
                                                                                                                       public policy innovations for&#13;
exchange rate risk? Unless the government pro-          of the investment efficiently. The problem with                private sector­led and&#13;
vides explicit subsidies in place of the implicit       many deals is the mix of foreign capital: many                 market-based solutions for&#13;
subsidies in having taxpayers or customers bear         projects have too much dollar-denominated debt,                development. The views&#13;
the exchange rate risk:                                 which drives the demand for allocating exchange                published are those of the&#13;
 Projects may be able to raise less financing,          rate risk to governments and consumers. While                  authors and should not be&#13;
    with shorter terms and higher initial rates.        allocating the risk this way keeps the initial financ-         attributed to the World&#13;
 Traditional project finance deals, with dollar-        ing costs low, it risks a blowup in the longer term.           Bank or any other affiliated&#13;
    denominated debt financing a large share of         Reducing reliance on foreign debt may mean that                organizations. Nor do any of&#13;
    the project cost, may be less feasible, leading     the volumes of private finance mobilized in the                the conclusions represent&#13;
    to greater use of local currency debt and local     1990s for greenfield projects and privatizations in            official policy of the World&#13;
    and foreign equity and therefore higher ini-        developing countries will not be forthcoming--                 Bank or of its Executive&#13;
    tial rates of return and higher project prices.     and that the initial costs of finance will be higher.          Directors or the countries&#13;
&#13;
 In East Asian and other countries with high sav-       But the benefits may be longer-lived and more                  they represent.&#13;
&#13;
    ings rates, the prospects for raising more local    robust investments that can weather the vagaries&#13;
    equity and debt for infrastructure seem prom-       of emerging markets.                                           To order additional copies&#13;
&#13;
    ising. Elsewhere, progress will take longer. But                                                                   contact Suzanne Smith,&#13;
&#13;
    governments can help by facilitating the devel-                                                                    managing editor,&#13;
                                                                                                                       Room I9-009,&#13;
    opment of local capital markets and contrac-&#13;
                                                                                                                       The World Bank,&#13;
    tual savings institutions such as pension funds     Note&#13;
                                                                                                                       1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
    and insurance companies--including by                  For different perspectives on the issue, see Ignacio Mas,&#13;
                                                                                                                       Washington, DC 20433.&#13;
    ensuring that tariff formulas do not implicitly     "Managing Exchange Rate­ and Interest Rate­Related&#13;
    discourage local currency financing.                Project Exposure: Are Guarantees Worth the Risk?" in&#13;
                                                                                                                       Telephone:&#13;
    While foreign debt financing will be scarcer,       Timothy Irwin, Michael Klein, Guillermo E. Perry, and&#13;
                                                                                                                       001 202 458 7281&#13;
innovative financing structures offer solutions.        Mateen Thobani, eds., Dealing with Public Risk in Private&#13;
                                                                                                                       Fax:&#13;
The Tietê project in Brazil illustrates one             Infrastructure, Latin American and Caribbean Studies&#13;
                                                                                                                       001 202 522 3480&#13;
approach to mitigating investors' exposure to           Viewpoint (Washington, D.C.: World Bank, 1997); and Joe&#13;
                                                                                                                       Email:&#13;
financing-related exchange rate risk. To finance        Wright, Tomoko Matsukawa, and Robert Sheppard,&#13;
                                                                                                                       ssmith7@worldbank.org&#13;
the generating facilities, AES (the U.S. parent         "Foreign Exchange Risk Mitigation for Power and Water&#13;
company of the operator, AES Tietê) issued              Projects in Developing Countries," Energy and Mining and       Produced by Communications&#13;
US$300 million in U.S. dollar bonds with an aver-       Water and Sanitation Sector Boards Discussion Paper            Development Inc.&#13;
age maturity of 10 years, at rates less than those      (World Bank, Washington, D.C., 2003).&#13;
paid by the Brazilian government for debt of an                                                                        Printed on recycled paper&#13;
equivalent maturity. The project sells power at&#13;
prices indexed to local inflation with no provision&#13;
for changes in the exchange rate. If the exchange&#13;
rate declines substantially and AES Tietê has insuf-&#13;
ficient cash to pay its debt service, however, it may&#13;
draw on a US$30 million liquidity facility (revolv-&#13;
ing loan) provided by the U.S. Overseas Private&#13;
Investment Corporation. Once local inflation has&#13;
                                                                                  This Note is available online:&#13;
                                                                  http://rru.worldbank.org/Viewpoint/index.asp&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="12120226">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2003/12/12120226/exchange-rate-risk-allocating-exchange-rate-risk-private-infrastructure-projects
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2003/12/12120226/exchange-rate-risk-allocating-exchange-rate-risk-private-infrastructure-projects</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2003/12/12120226/exchange-rate-risk-allocating-exchange-rate-risk-private-infrastructure-projects</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2010/04/20/000334955_20100420053938/Rendered/INDEX/541180VP0266Gr10Box345636B01PUBLIC1.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2010/04/20/000334955_20100420053938/Rendered/PDF/541180VP0266Gr10Box345636B01PUBLIC1.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2003-12-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2010-04-20T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Exchange rate risk : allocating exchange
            rate risk in private infrastructure projects
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Each year developing countries seek
            billions of dollars of investment in their infrastructure,
            and private investors, mostly in rich countries, seek places
            to invest trillions of dollars of new savings. Private
            foreign investment in the infrastructure of developing
            countries would seem to hold great promise. But foreign
            investors must cope with volatile developing country
            currencies. Many attempts to do so have created as many
            problems as they have solved. This note proposes that
            investors take on all financing-related exchange rate risk,
            even though this may mean higher tariffs for consumers as a
            premium for bearing that risk.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Exchange rate risk : allocating exchange
            rate risk in private infrastructure projects
        </docna>
        <display_title>Exchange rate risk : allocating
            exchange rate risk in private infrastructure projects</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2003/12/12120226/exchange-rate-risk-allocating-exchange-rate-risk-private-infrastructure-projects</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Economic Stabilization,Macroeconomic Management,Emerging Markets,Debt Markets,Currencies and Exchange Rates</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Private Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Gray, Philip; Irwin, Timothy;</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000334955_20100420053938</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 266</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Private Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            adjustment mechanisms, adverse effect,
            budget deficits, capital markets, Communications
            Development, consumer price index, contractual savings,
            contractual savings institutions, creditors, currency
            crises, debt financing, debt service, derivatives,
            devaluation, developing countries, dollar bonds, emerging
            markets, equity investors, equity markets, Exchange Rate,
            exchange rate movements, Exchange Rate Risk, exchange rate
            risks, exchange rates, exposure, financial structure,
            foreign capital, foreign currency, foreign currency debt,
            foreign debt, foreign equity, Foreign Exchange, Foreign
            Exchange Risk, foreign investors, hedges, host country,
            implicit subsidies, infrastructure project, Infrastructure
            Projects, innovative financing, insurance companies,
            Interest Rate, Investment Corporation, life insurance,
            liquidity, liquidity facility, loan, local capital markets,
            local currency, local currency financing, local debt, local
            inflation, long term, macroeconomic crises, macroeconomic
            policies, maturity, mutual funds, Optimal allocation,
            outputs, pension, pension funds, pension plans, price
            increases, private finance, Private Infrastructure, Private
            Investment, private investors, private sector, private
            sector development, privatizations, public policy, rate of
            depreciation, rates of return, renegotiation, repayment,
            return, revolving loan, risk sharing, savings rates,
            shareholders, tariff increases, volatility, world price
        </keywd>
        <owner>Financial Solutions Unit (TWIFS)</owner>
        <repnb>54118</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Stabilization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Emerging Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Volatility</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Equity Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>