<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>WATER AND SANITATION PROGRAM: LEARNING NOTE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                       56936&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project                                                                                 Key findings&#13;
Insights from Designing a                                                                                             · Designing a handwashing station&#13;
                                                                                                                        must take user preferences and&#13;
&#13;
Handwashing Station for Rural                                                                                           practices into account.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                      · A universal design for a&#13;
Vietnamese Households                                                                                                   handwashing station may not be&#13;
                                                                                                                        possible.&#13;
February 2010&#13;
                                                                                                                      · Multiple iterations of prototyping&#13;
                                                                                                                        and field-testing of a handwashing&#13;
                                                                                                                        station prior to manufacturing are&#13;
INTRODUCTION                                                PROBLEM STATEMENT                                           critical to identify user preferences&#13;
The Water and Sanitation Program's                          In Vietnam, prior to project implemen-                      and practices.&#13;
(WSP) Global Scaling Up Handwashing                         tation, handwashing rates with water&#13;
Project (HWWS) is testing an array of                       alone were much greater than with                         · The use of a designer experienced&#13;
interventions to promote handwashing                        soap, despite the fact that all house-                      in human-centered approaches is&#13;
with soap among mothers and children                        holds have some form of soap such as                        highly recommended.&#13;
in rural Vietnam. These interventions                       laundry detergent (100 percent), dish-&#13;
include mass media and interpersonal                        washing liquid (88 percent) or bar soap&#13;
communication through organizations                         (60 percent).2 An emerging hypothesis is&#13;
such as the Vietnam Women's Union. Of                       that convenient and easy access to both&#13;
particular and growing interest is the role                 water and soap at critical times is a key&#13;
of handwashing stations. In a household                     behavioral determinant of handwashing&#13;
setting, a handwashing station is a des-                    with soap among women and children.&#13;
ignated space bringing together wa-                         If a busy mother needs to look for soap&#13;
ter and soap to wash hands, ideally in                      before preparing a meal, or a child does&#13;
close proximity to the latrine or the food                  not have easy access to water and soap&#13;
preparation area. Handwashing stations                      after using the latrine, the probability of&#13;
influence individuals' chance to perform                    handwashing with soap actually taking&#13;
a behavior, regardless of their ability                     place is lower. This hypothesis has been&#13;
and motivation to do so.1 While sinks in                    confirmed in other countries where&#13;
kitchens and bathrooms are the norm in                      HWWS is currently being implemented,&#13;
developed nations, they are not in most                     namely Peru and Senegal, where hand-&#13;
resource-scarce countries.                                  washing with soap is positively corre-&#13;
                                                            lated with having a designated place for&#13;
                                                            family members to wash their hands.3&#13;
&#13;
1&#13;
  As part of HWWS, WSP developed a behavior change framework to explain handwashing behavior. The FOAM&#13;
  (Focus, Opportunity, Ability and Motivation), framework identifies the key factors or determinants that influence&#13;
  handwashing. Handwashing stations and other enabling products such as "tippy taps" fall under the Opportunity&#13;
  category of determinants. FOAM is based on Population Services International's PERForM framework.&#13;
2&#13;
  Vietnam National Handwashing Initiative Consumer Research Baseline Survey Final Report. 2007. Indochina&#13;
  Research (Vietnam) Ltd.&#13;
3&#13;
  Galiani, Sebastian. 2009. Draft baseline study. Impact Evaluation of Handwashing with Soap in Peru. Water&#13;
  and Sanitation Program; Kane, Momar Serigne. 2009. Unpublished study. Rapport Etude Lavage des Mains&#13;
  Au Savon Senegal. Water and Sanitation Program.&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;2    Insights from Designing a Handwashing Station                                                                    Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     Step 3: Field Visit (1 day). During a visit to Yun Ben prov-&#13;
      BOX 1: DESIGN BRIEF                                                            ince, the team conducted group interventions with villagers,&#13;
      The Big Idea: Develop rough design for handwashing                             made household visits, and collected observations.&#13;
      station for rural households in Vietnam.&#13;
                                                                                     Step 4: Brainstorming and Prototype Development&#13;
      Users:                                                                         (1.5 days). Prototypes were developed through brainstorm-&#13;
       · Rural household members (adults, children) near                             ing sessions (Illustration 1) and by deconstructing, altering,&#13;
         latrine or food preparation area                                            and re-assembling objects available in local markets. Proto-&#13;
      Essentials:                                                                    types were built to test specific ideas, not to be represen-&#13;
       · Low cost                                                                    tative of actual product designs or future manufacturing&#13;
       · Allows for water to flow on hands (i.e., no dipping)                        methods. Three sets of prototypes were developed to inde-&#13;
       · Inexpensive to produce and distribute                                       pendently test the critical components of the handwashing&#13;
       · Easy to use/operate                                                         station: water dispensing (four options to test hand motions,&#13;
       · Durable                                                                     flow rate, and level styles); soap presentation (five options to&#13;
       · Able to accommodate various types of soap agents                            test hand motions, soap type, and dispensing); and overall&#13;
         or most prevalent one(s) (i.e., not just bar soaps)                         container (six options to test size, shape, and appearance).&#13;
       · Securely holds soap and water to prevent them                               Step 5: Prototype Testing (1 day). During a visit to Hun Yen&#13;
         from being stolen                                                           province, prototypes were shared with a group of about&#13;
       · Capable of being produced locally/regionally                                20 villagers (half male, half female). The villagers were invited&#13;
       · Builds on Peru handwashing station design                                   to come forward and use each set of prototypes (Illustra-&#13;
       · User strategy for waste water generated from use                            tion 2). After each set was tried by a number of villagers, a&#13;
                                                                                     discussion was facilitated during which they were asked to&#13;
                                                                                     share their likes and dislikes, and recommend changes for&#13;
ACTION                                                                               improvement.&#13;
To strengthen mothers' capacity to manage soap and water&#13;
for handwashing and make both soap and water easily ac-&#13;
cessible to household members when and where needed,&#13;
                                                                                     Illustration 1: Brainstorming Handwashing Station&#13;
HWWS contracted a consultant4 to develop rough designs&#13;
                                                                                     Designs&#13;
for a household handwashing station in rural Vietnam. The&#13;
work took place from April 23-30, 2009. Prior to the start of&#13;
work, HWWS developed a design brief (Box 1) to guide the&#13;
design process. This brief outlined key steps and was circu-&#13;
lated for comments and improvement. The design process&#13;
was conducted during a 5-day participatory workshop that&#13;
included meetings, field visits, prototype building and field-&#13;
testing. Key steps included:&#13;
&#13;
Step 1: Mobilization. The consultant mobilized a multi-&#13;
disciplinary team including WSP and key partners includ-&#13;
ing the Ministry of Health, the Vietnam Women's Union and&#13;
PATH, a nongovernmental organization.&#13;
&#13;
Step 2: Kick-off Meeting (2 hours). Team members dis-&#13;
cussed their respective roles and the design brief and                               Prototypes were developed through brainstorming sessions.&#13;
process were explained.                                                              During the initial step, participants sketched features.&#13;
&#13;
4&#13;
    The consultant recruited was an IDEO designer who happened to be on personal leave working on a low-cost latrine in Cambodia. For more information on IDEO, a&#13;
    leading design firm, and human-centered design, see www.ideo.com.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                      www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project                                                                    Insights from Designing a Handwashing Station   3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Illustration 2: Testing Prototypes                                                   KEY LEARNINGS&#13;
                                                                                     The lessons learned during the short consultancy period are&#13;
                                                                                     rich and diverse. The main ones are as follows:&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      · Test, test and re-test: Multiple iterations of prototyping and&#13;
                                                                                        field-testing of a handwashing station prior to manufactur-&#13;
                                                                                        ing are critical to identify user preferences and practices.&#13;
                                                                                      · No one model fits all: A concept similar to a handwashing&#13;
                                                                                        station that was designed and implemented by the HWWS&#13;
                                                                                        team in Peru tested poorly in rural Vietnam, indicating that&#13;
                                                                                        a universal design may not be possible.&#13;
                                                                                      · The mechanics of handwashing stations are complex:&#13;
                                                                                        Field-testing revealed that the mechanics of handwashing&#13;
                                                                                        are more complex than were assumed. Several consider-&#13;
                                                                                        ations, including what part of the hand is used to start the&#13;
During a visit to Hun Yen province, prototypes were shared&#13;
                                                                                        water flow (no finger tips), preferred body position (squat-&#13;
with a group of about 20 villagers. Above, a woman tests a&#13;
prototype that stores the bar of soap in a covered dish.&#13;
                                                                                        ting) and hand motion (extensive rubbing) were not clearly&#13;
                                                                                        known before, and understanding these will help inform&#13;
                                                                                        feature design (Box 2).&#13;
Step 6: Identification of Recommended Directions and                                  · Appearances count: Beyond something utilitarian, users&#13;
Team Debrief. The duration of this consultancy did not allow                            expressed for something that looked nice and new (not&#13;
for the entire design process to be completed. During a team                            using recycled bottles for instance) and would be willing&#13;
debrief, recommended directions and next steps by the con-                              to spend more for a station if installed in a location visible&#13;
sultant were shared and documented.                                                     to other villagers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      BOX 2: THE MECHANICS OF HANDWASHING WITH SOAP IN RURAL VIETNAM&#13;
      Field-testing of an array of prototypes provided meaningful insight5 into critical perceptions and preferences around&#13;
      the mechanics of handwashing with soap. For example:&#13;
       · Tap design: Users strongly preferred a tap that allowed water to run freely over their hands as they rubbed them&#13;
         together to get rid of soap. Having to continuously depress a lever makes rinsing very difficult. An ability to ad-&#13;
         just the flow rate and to control the on-off function with the back of the hand or some other clean body part (to&#13;
         keep the tap clean) was deemed important.&#13;
       · Soap presentation: Both options presenting a soap bar were well liked, with a preference for the hanging bag,&#13;
         which would allow for the bar to dry and prevent it from getting misplaced or stolen, over the covered dish.&#13;
         A powder shaker, which would allow for dispensing of laundry soap, tested poorly as did a liquid (dishwashing&#13;
         soap) bottle with a nipple dispenser. In the latter case, users were unable to divorce the baby bottle used from its&#13;
         intended purpose, providing an important lesson for future prototyping: avoid using products or materials with&#13;
         strong connotations with another use.&#13;
       · Container: Users stated they would mount the handwashing station to a wall or post rather than rest it on a stand&#13;
         because it would seem like a more permanent installation and that they would bring water to the container to refill&#13;
         it rather than bring the container to water. In this light, a clear container allowing them to see the level of water&#13;
         and a capacity of 10 to 15 liters (enough for a projected two to three days of household use) were other important&#13;
         features. Finally, a flip lid was preferred over a removable lid that could be misplaced.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5&#13;
    Chapin, Jeff. 2009. Unpublished presentation. Designing a Handwashing Station for Rural Vietnamese Households. Water and Sanitation Program.&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;4   Insights from Designing a Handwashing Station                                                    Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 · Size does matter: Given that users                  money to build. However, the upside&#13;
   stated they would prefer to bring                   is that in later iterations, the prototypes&#13;
                                                                                                       Acknowledgements&#13;
                                                                                                       With thanks to Nga Kim Nguyen&#13;
   water to the container rather the                   begin to look like a real product and&#13;
                                                                                                       and Minh Thi Nguyen of WSP and&#13;
   other way around, a handwashing                     user affinity increases considerably.&#13;
                                                                                                       Jeff Chapin of IDEO. Photographs&#13;
   with soap station would need to hold            ·   Costing: Users indicated that they&#13;
                                                                                                       by Jeff Chapin.&#13;
   enough water for a few days of use.                 would be willing to pay from 50,000 to&#13;
 · A station as possible cue to action:                70,000 duong for the container. Man-&#13;
   As hoped, the women freely stated                   ufacturing costs and expected mark-             About the project&#13;
   that a well-placed station would                    ups in the distribution chain needs to          The Water and Sanitation&#13;
   help remind them and their family to                be understood. Tooling and other set            Program's Global Scaling&#13;
   handwash with soap.                                 up costs also need to be estimated.             Up Handwashing Project is&#13;
 · Hire a real designer: The enormous              ·   Identification of manufacturing                 learning how to apply innovative&#13;
   amount learned from this process                    partner: The fact that similar plastic          promotional approaches to&#13;
   could not have been obtained with-                  containers and valves can be readily            behavior change to generate&#13;
   out a qualified and experienced                     found in Vietnam, at reasonable prices,         widespread and sustained&#13;
   consultant who is vested in human-                  suggests that manufacturers with the            improvements in handwashing&#13;
   centered design processes.                          required expertise can be found.                with soap at scale. For more&#13;
                                                   ·   Supply chain analysis: The path                 information please visit www.wsp.&#13;
WHAT ELSE DO                                           from a factory to a wall near a house-          org/scalinguphandwashing.&#13;
WE NEED TO KNOW?                                       hold latrine needs to be thoroughly&#13;
Based on the prototype field-testing, the&#13;
consultant was able to document direc-&#13;
                                                       understood. Who are the middle-                 Contact us&#13;
                                                       men? Where are the warehouses?                  For more information please&#13;
tions for the next round of design, includ-&#13;
                                                       What are normal margins? What                   visit www.wsp.org or email&#13;
ing tap and valve design, soap presenta-&#13;
                                                       happens to unsold product? What                 Jacqueline Devine at&#13;
tion, and container features. The HWWS&#13;
                                                       volumes need to be hit to make it a             wsp@worldbank.org.&#13;
team will decide on whether it will under-&#13;
                                                       viable business for someone?&#13;
take suggested next steps:&#13;
                                                   ·   Project budgeting: In addition to the&#13;
                                                       resources required to undertake the&#13;
 · Design iteration: This would involve as&#13;
                                                       preceding research and development&#13;
   many rounds of prototyping and test-&#13;
                                                       steps, manufacturing start-up costs&#13;
   ing as required to "get it right". As the&#13;
                                                       outside the current budget and scope&#13;
   design progresses, each iteration takes&#13;
                                                       of the Project would also be required.&#13;
   longer and the prototypes cost more&#13;
                                                                    --By Jacqueline Devine&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The Water and Sanitation Program (WSP) is a multi-donor partnership created in 1978 and&#13;
administered by the World Bank to support poor people in obtaining affordable, safe, and&#13;
sustainable access to water and sanitation services. WSP's donors include Australia, Austria,&#13;
Canada, Denmark, Finland, France, the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation, Ireland, Luxembourg,&#13;
Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, Switzerland, United Kingdom, United States, and the World Bank.&#13;
For more information please visit www.wsp.org.&#13;
WSP reports are published to communicate the results of WSP's work to the development&#13;
community. The boundaries, colors, denominations, and other information shown on any map in this&#13;
work do not imply any judgment on the part of the World Bank Group concerning the legal status of&#13;
any territory or the endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
                                                                                                                               www.wsp.org&#13;
© 2010 Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="12836518">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2010/02/12836518/vietnam-global-scaling-up-sanitation-project-insights-designing-handwashing-station-rural-vietnamese-households
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2010/02/12836518/vietnam-global-scaling-up-sanitation-project-insights-designing-handwashing-station-rural-vietnamese-households</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2010/02/12836518/vietnam-global-scaling-up-sanitation-project-insights-designing-handwashing-station-rural-vietnamese-households</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-10-06T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2010/10/06/000333037_20101006021515/Rendered/INDEX/569360WSP1Desi10Box353744B01PUBLIC1.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2010/10/06/000333037_20101006021515/Rendered/PDF/569360WSP1Desi10Box353744B01PUBLIC1.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2010-10-06T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2010-02-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Vietnam - Global Scaling Up Sanitation
            Project : insights from designing a handwashing station for
            rural Vietnamese households
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Water and Sanitation Program's
            (WSP) Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project (HWWS) is
            testing an array of interventions to promote handwashing
            with soap among mothers and children in rural Vietnam. These
            interventions include mass media and interpersonal
            communication through organizations such as the Vietnam
            women's union. Of particular and growing interest is
            the role of handwashing stations. In a household setting, a
            handwashing station is a designated space bringing together
            water and soap to wash hands, ideally in close proximity to
            the latrine or the food preparation area. Handwashing
            stations influence individuals' chance to perform a
            behavior, regardless of their ability and motivation to do
            so. While sinks in kitchens and bathrooms are the norm in
            developed nations, they are not in most resource-scarce countries.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Vietnam - Global Scaling Up Sanitation
            Project : insights from designing a handwashing station for
            rural Vietnamese households
        </docna>
        <display_title>Vietnam - Global Scaling Up
            Sanitation Project : insights from designing a handwashing
            station for rural Vietnamese households</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2010/02/12836518/vietnam-global-scaling-up-sanitation-project-insights-designing-handwashing-station-rural-vietnamese-households</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing,Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,E-Business,Water and Industry</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Private Sector Development,Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>Vietnam</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southeast Asia!$!80471</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20101006021515</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Water and sanitation program learning note ; WSP</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Private Sector Development,Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            access to water, behavior change,
            distribution chain, food preparation, handwashing, household
            use, Households, installation, latrine, laundry,
            manufacturing, middlemen, product designs, Prototype,
            Prototypes, results, SANITATION, SANITATION PROGRAM,
            sanitation services, soap, Supply chain, user, user
            preferences, Users
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water- Water and Sanit Prgrm (GWASP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southeast Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>56936</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industrial Cluster</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sector Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sector Value Chain</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supply Chain Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Value Chain Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Randomized Control Trials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research and Development Commercialization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research and Innovation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industrial Clusters and Value Chains</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research, Development and Innovation (RDI)</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Viet Nam</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>