<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>WATER AND SANITATION PROGRAM: PROGRESS REPORT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         56949&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Progress Report:&#13;
Peru, Senegal, Tanzania, and Vietnam&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
July 1­December 31, 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The Water and Sanitation Program is a multi-donor partnership administered&#13;
by the World Bank to support poor people in obtaining affordable, safe, and&#13;
sustainable access to water and sanitation services.&#13;
&amp;#12;By Eduardo Perez, Hnin Hnin Pyne, Catherine Amelink,&#13;
Nathaniel Paynter, Bertha Briceno, Jason Cardosi, Yolande&#13;
Coombes, Rocio Florez de Cilloniz, Jacqueline Devine,&#13;
Christiane Frischmuth, Amy Grossman, Craig Kullmann,&#13;
Nga Kim Nguyen, Seydou Koita, Abdul Badru, Alexandra&#13;
Orsola-Vidal&#13;
Global Scaling Up Handwashing is a Water and Sanitation&#13;
Program (WSP) project focused on learning how to apply&#13;
innovative promotional approaches to behavior change&#13;
to generate widespread and sustained improvements in&#13;
handwashing with soap at scale among women of reproductive&#13;
age (ages 15­49) and primary school-aged children (ages 5­9).&#13;
The project is being implemented by local and national&#13;
governments with technical support from WSP. For more&#13;
information, please visit www.wsp.org/scalinguphandwashing.&#13;
&#13;
WSP is a multi-donor partnership created in 1978 and administered by&#13;
the World Bank to support poor people in obtaining affordable, safe, and&#13;
sustainable access to water and sanitation services. WSP's donors include&#13;
Australia, Austria, Canada, Denmark, Finland, France, the Bill &amp; Melinda&#13;
Gates Foundation, Ireland, Luxembourg, Netherlands, Norway, Sweden,&#13;
Switzerland, United Kingdom, United States, and the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
WSP reports are published to communicate the results of WSP's work&#13;
to the development community. The boundaries, colors, denominations,&#13;
and other information shown on any map in this work do not imply any&#13;
judgment on the part of the World Bank Group concerning the legal status&#13;
of any territory or the endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
&#13;
© 2010 Water and Sanitation Program (WSP)&#13;
&amp;#12;Executive Summary&#13;
&#13;
Introduction                                                     analysis will be shared with clients and partners in the com-&#13;
This reporting period marks the beginning of the final year      ing months, adding a new dimension to the value the proj-&#13;
of implementation of the Global Scaling Up Handwashing           ect can provide to our government clients.&#13;
with Soap (HWWS) project. It represents a critical phase, a&#13;
time for our teams not only to continue intensifying behav-      Evidenced based lessons are being captured and useful&#13;
ior change interventions, but also to establish HWWS pro-        knowledge products are begging to be produced and&#13;
motion as a central component in national and local efforts      disseminated--but overall progress continues to lag in the&#13;
to improve children's health and nutrition in Peru, Senegal,     learning component, with less than 40% of knowledge&#13;
Tanzania, and Vietnam. At present, we are on target to           products completed. A Knowledge Management consul-&#13;
achieve the intended scale of HWWS promotion and with            tant hired in this reporting period worked to establish a&#13;
the project's support, our clients are more committed and        production process and develop tools and several knowl-&#13;
are taking concrete and momentous actions to finance,            edge products were completed or progressed as a result. In&#13;
plan, implement, and monitor HWWS programs at na-                Peru, four monthly Handwashing Bulletin and one HW&#13;
tional and local levels.                                         series were prepared and disseminated; and in DC, two&#13;
                                                                 Working Papers (Global Learning Strategy, and Practical&#13;
Globally, the project is on track to either meet or exceed       Guidelines for Measuring Handwashing Behavior); one Tech-&#13;
expected end-of-project (EOP) targets in each of the coun-       nical Paper (Improving Measures of Handwashing Behavior);&#13;
tries for the reach of behavior change communication inter-      and two Learning Notes (Emergent Learning about Learning&#13;
ventions in each of the three communication channels:            and Insights from Designing a Handwashing Station for Viet-&#13;
interpersonal communication (IPC), direct consumer con-          namese Households) were edited and designed for produc-&#13;
tact (DCC) and mass media. By the end of this reporting          tion. In addition, two reports on project milestones (Annual&#13;
period, about 2.3 million mothers and caretakers have been       Progress Report, Global Annual Meeting Report) were pre-&#13;
engaged through IPC activities (74% of EOP target); about        pared and work on the project Web site--including new&#13;
379,000 women and children have attended DCC events              pages and the addition of presentations and media--has re-&#13;
(56% of EOP target); an estimated 40.7 million people            sulted in significant improvements.&#13;
have been reached by mass media (100% of EOP target);&#13;
and over 26,000 front-line activators (FLAs) have been           Challenges&#13;
trained by the project (85% of EOP target).                      The project has seen considerable progress over the past six&#13;
                                                                 months, but the team recognizes that several challenges&#13;
The project is also on track in strengthening the enabling en-   must be addressed in the coming months. One of the key&#13;
vironment to help sustain HWWS interventions beyond the          challenges is incorporating learning into implementation.&#13;
life of the project. Notable progress has been made around       However, this learning process is expected to improve as&#13;
efforts to integrate HWWS activities into existing national,     teams increase the use of monitoring systems as manage-&#13;
regional and local programs and services, to replicate the ap-   ment tools. The project will continue to reinforce a struc-&#13;
proach within and outside the four countries, and to secure      ture for learning-to-action meetings to help the country&#13;
national and local-level funding for HWWS activities.            teams rapidly adopt lessons into program implementation.&#13;
&#13;
The global performance monitoring system is fully opera-         A related challenge is tied to the transition expected as proj-&#13;
tional and is providing performance data from each country       ect funding ends. The country teams have done good work&#13;
on a regular basis to the global team. The Impact Evaluation     integrating the HWWS approach into national and re-&#13;
achieved key milestones with the completion of baseline          gional institutions but knowledge gained so far needs to be&#13;
surveys in all HWWS countries. As data becomes available         captured and developed into useful tools and documents.&#13;
the team will be better able to revisit some initial assump-     This will be a focus over the coming year and will need to&#13;
tions and recalculate power estimates. Baseline data and         be balanced against the intensifying interventions.&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                   iii&#13;
&amp;#12;     Progress Report   Executive Summary&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Another challenge is measuring reach of mass media. While we       the project will focus on harvesting learning in key areas,&#13;
     can estimate the reach based on the data reported by the imple-    including behavioral determinants, measuring the level of&#13;
     menters, these reports must be independently verified. In the      exposure of through monitoring surveys, and sharing base-&#13;
     next reporting period we will launch community-based sur-          line data with clients and other stakeholders. Knowledge&#13;
     veys to measure prompted and unprompted recall of exposure         management efforts across the country teams and HQ will&#13;
     to provide independent verification directly from the ultimate     focus on prioritizing and producing knowledge products&#13;
     consumers and beneficiaries, the women and caretakers. A           such as Working Papers, Learning Notes, and Technical Re-&#13;
     final challenge comes from the use of scales for measuring de-     ports to facilitate replication and support sustainability, and&#13;
     terminants, such as religious beliefs and social norms: these      strengthening dissemination to effectively reach stakehold-&#13;
     scales require a series of focus groups and qualitative testing    ers through learning events (e.g., workshops, conferences,&#13;
     before piloting on small samples and principal component           brown bag lunches) and print and digital materials.&#13;
     analysis in order to arrive at a final series of questions. This&#13;
     lengthy step requires additional time and resources, for which     Considerable effort will also be undertaken to prepare IE-&#13;
     we intend to adequately budget in the upcoming surveys.            related products, re-estimate sample sizes, procure survey&#13;
                                                                        firms, revise and pilot the questionnaires, strategically de-&#13;
     Expectations for the Next Six Months                               ciding which outcomes should be collected in each country,&#13;
     At the global level, the next six months of implementation         training and standardizing survey personnel.&#13;
     will further scale up the reach and intensity of communica-&#13;
     tions interventions and support our clients and partners to        The expected areas of focus for each country are defined in&#13;
     effectively finance, plan, implement, and monitor HWWS             Annex 1, Country Stories.&#13;
     programs at national and local levels. In addition,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
iv                                                                                                          Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;              Table of Contents&#13;
              Executive Summary ........................................................................... iii&#13;
                I. Achieving Intermediate Outcomes--The Global Story ............ 1&#13;
                     Emerging Intermediate Outcomes .......................................... 1&#13;
               II. Delivering Results--Implementation Progress&#13;
                   and the Project Components .................................................... 3&#13;
                     Component 1: Programming................................................... 3&#13;
                       Country Performance ............................................................. 3&#13;
                       Looking Ahead: Opportunities, Risks and Mitigation&#13;
                       Measures .............................................................................. 7&#13;
                     Component 2: Strengthening the Enabling Environment ........ 7&#13;
                       Handover of PPPHW Secretariat Coordinator Position ............. 8&#13;
                     Component 3: Learning .......................................................... 9&#13;
                       Production of Knowledge Products....................................... 10&#13;
                       Global Learning ................................................................... 10&#13;
                       Emerging Learning ............................................................... 11&#13;
                     Component 4: Monitoring and Evaluation ............................ 12&#13;
                       Monitoring for Performance and Results ................................ 12&#13;
                       Impact Evaluation ................................................................. 13&#13;
              III. Challenges and Project Responses........................................ 15&#13;
                     Global Challenges ................................................................. 15&#13;
                       Performance Monitoring ....................................................... 15&#13;
              IV. Project Management ............................................................... 16&#13;
&#13;
              Box&#13;
                     1: The Senegal Performance Management System ................ 12&#13;
&#13;
              Figures&#13;
                   1:    Progress on Mass Media Reach (% of EOP Target) .............. 4&#13;
                   2:    Progress on IPC and DCC Reach (% of EOP Target) ............ 4&#13;
                   3:    Peru Progress in the Programming Component ................... 5&#13;
                   4:    Senegal Progress in the Programming Component .............. 6&#13;
&#13;
              Tables&#13;
                   1: Emerging Global Results in the Programming Component&#13;
                      by Dec 31, '09 ....................................................................... 4&#13;
                   2: Progress on Enabling Environment ....................................... 9&#13;
                   3: Progress on Production of Knowledge Products ................ 10&#13;
                   4: Status and Schedule of Baseline Surveys ........................... 13&#13;
                   5: Status and Schedule of Longitudinal Surveys..................... 14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                   v&#13;
&amp;#12;     Progress Report   Table of Contents&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           Annexes&#13;
                                               1: Country Stories July 1­December 31, 2009 ........................ 17&#13;
                                               2: Additional Reach Graphs­Peru ........................................... 23&#13;
                                               3: Timeline of Endline Studies ................................................. 24&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
vi                                                                                                                            Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;I.       Achieving Intermediate&#13;
         Outcomes--The Global Story&#13;
&#13;
This reporting period marks the beginning of the final year    and/or radio spots promoting HWWS. Unlike mass media,&#13;
of implementation of the Global Scaling Up Handwashing         IPC is often perceived to be difficult to scale up, but this has&#13;
with Soap (HWWS) project. It represents a critical phase, a    not been the case in this project. To date, through IPC con-&#13;
time for our teams not only to continue intensifying behav-    sisting of face-to-face interactions and exchanges between&#13;
ior change interventions, but also to establish HWWS pro-      trained community-based workers/volunteers and our tar-&#13;
motion as central component in national and local efforts      get group we have supported the engagement of about 2.3&#13;
to improve children's health and nutrition in Peru, Senegal,   million women and caretakers.&#13;
Tanzania, and Vietnam. At present, we are on target to&#13;
achieve the intended scale of HWWS promotion and, with         Each country team has selected implementation partners&#13;
the project's support, our clients are more committed and      that are well-positioned to rapidly expand the reach of IPC:&#13;
are taking concrete and momentous actions to finance,          In Vietnam, scaling up was enabled by a partnership with&#13;
plan, implement, and monitor HWWS programs at na-              Women's Union, a mass organization with a profound pres-&#13;
tional and local levels.                                       ence in every commune; in Senegal, scaling up has been&#13;
                                                               strengthened by the use of existing community-based organi-&#13;
Emerging Intermediate Outcomes                                 zations experienced in delivering behavior change interven-&#13;
In the coming months, more data from impact evaluation         tions through networks of outreach workers; and in Peru and&#13;
baselines, longitudinal, and monitoring surveys will be-       Tanzania, scaling up has been supported by the use of exist-&#13;
come available. Project teams will then be able to quantify    ing service providersin the public and non-governmental sec-&#13;
the relationship between reaching mothers, caregivers, and     tor such as teachers and community development workers.&#13;
children with the message of washing your hands with soap&#13;
at critical times, and shifts in behavioral determinants and   In addition to helping scale up, these partnerships have&#13;
changes in the behavior. The project will not know the full    catalyzed support, created opportunities to forge new and&#13;
extent of this behavior change, or the affect this behavior    diverse partnerships, and have helped leverage national and&#13;
change has on diarrhea and other conditions affecting poor     local investments in sectors such as health, education, and&#13;
health and nutritional status of children, until the comple-   water/sanitation. These investments, in turn, have directly&#13;
tion of the impact evaluation end line surveys in 2011.        contributed to the scaling up of reach.&#13;
&#13;
At this time, however, we can say something meaningful         The following are examples of what has been achieved over&#13;
about the Intermediate Outcomes of the project--the reach      the reporting period. They demonstrate how clients and&#13;
of the behavior change interventions and the extent to         partners are taking concrete actions to scale up and sustain&#13;
which our clients and partners are taking policy and pro-      the reach of HWWS interventions.&#13;
grammatic actions to scale up HWWS and to sustain it               · In seven regions of Peru, local partnerships have ex-&#13;
beyond the life of the project.                                       panded the geographical scope of the HW initiative&#13;
                                                                      to new areas, increasing the size of the target popu-&#13;
Globally, the project is on track to either meet or exceed            lation that will benefit HW behavior change inter-&#13;
expected targets in each of the four countries for the reach          ventions. To be precise, target population increased&#13;
of behavior change communication interventions in each                by 70% in Cajamarca; 30% in Piura; 25% in Lam-&#13;
of the three communication channels (IPC or interpersonal             bayeque; and 70% in Arequipa.&#13;
communication; DCC or direct consumer contacts; and                · In Vietnam, the country team leveraged a World&#13;
mass media). As expected, the use of mass media, be it na-            Bank financed investment project in rural water sup-&#13;
tional or regional, has facilitated the rapid expansion of            ply and sanitation to promote HWWS in the Red&#13;
reach. To date, we estimate that 40.7 million women and               River Delta area. In addition, the National Target&#13;
children across the four countries have been exposed to TV            Program, the government's initiative to speed up&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                  1&#13;
&amp;#12;    Progress Report   Achieving Intermediate Outcomes--The Global Story&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            progress towards MDG targets, expanded HWWS                         in Tanzania to support hygiene and sanitation activi-&#13;
            in three additional provinces of Phu Yen, Dak Nong,                 ties. In addition, the Ministry of Water and Irrigation&#13;
            and Tra Vinh with the support from the project.                     has sent planning and implementation guidelines to&#13;
        ·   In Vietnam, the Women's Union has committed to                      its District Water and Sanitation teams. These teams&#13;
            mainstream HWWS activities in all 63 provinces, as                  consist of representatives from key sectors that are re-&#13;
            laid out in an MOU signed between the World Bank                    sponsible for overseeing sanitation and hygiene inter-&#13;
            and the Women's Union. This is a sizeable increase                  ventions within their wards. The country team is using&#13;
            from 12 provinces initially covered by the project.                 these guidelines as a framework for district-level imple-&#13;
        ·   In Senegal, the partnership with the Ministry of                    mentation with possible opportunities to integrate and&#13;
            Education has helped to expand HWWS into the                        mainstream Scaling Up HWWS project approaches.&#13;
            School Health pilot program. The pilot includes&#13;
            handwashing orientation, training, and materials for          In addition to scaling up HWWS within the four project&#13;
            teachers, developed under the project.                        countries, the Peru team has undertaken efforts to replicate&#13;
        ·   In Tanzania, the country team has helped interna-             HW behavior change in other Latin American countries.&#13;
            tional organizations adopt the project's approach             These efforts have resulted in promising outcomes. Using&#13;
            to HWWS behavior change within several ongoing                Peru's methodology for behavioral change in schools, WHO/&#13;
            program including UNICEF programs in school                   Pan American Health Organization (PAHO) in Guatemala&#13;
            sanitation and in its learning districts; AED's Tan-          are designed its manuals developed to help teachers promote&#13;
            zania Marketing and Communications for AIDS,                  HWWS in their classrooms. In addition, PAHO contacted&#13;
            Reproductive Health, Child Survival and Infec-                DURAPLAST in Peru and ordered 10,000 Super Jaboncin&#13;
            tious Diseases (T-MARC), currently being piloted              HW soap devices that will be distributed in 3,000 primary&#13;
            in Morogoro; and in outreach activities conducted             schools to help combat the spread of the AH1N1 virus.&#13;
            by SNV (Netherlands Development Organisation),&#13;
            WaterAID, and the Water and Sanitation Collabora-             The project has made significant progress in the past six&#13;
            tive Council in their respective districts.                   months towards several Intermediate Outcomes, specifi-&#13;
        ·   In Tanzania, a private sector company, Tarmal In-             cally the reach of behavior change interventions, and policy&#13;
            dustries, has launched a soap brand which includes            and programmatic actions undertaken by clients and part-&#13;
            key Global Scaling Up HWWS messages and the                   ners to support scaling up. These Intermediate Outcomes&#13;
            project logo on the packaging. Tamal Industries is            will be further strengthened as the project moves into the&#13;
            one of the largest soap producers in Tanzania and we          final year of implementation in an effort to meet all the&#13;
            expect this will help increase the penetration of HW          planned targets (particularly for IPC).&#13;
            messages into more households.&#13;
                                                                          Milestones in this reporting period also lay a strong foun-&#13;
    Moreover, during the reporting period, the country teams              dation to accelerate learning and the development of knowl-&#13;
    have laid the groundwork for more partnerships and more               edge products. Learning from the implementation will be&#13;
    opportunities to leverage for scaling up of reach over the            bolstered by data collected through the endline surveys&#13;
    next six months.                                                      scheduled in late 2010. Together, they will support efforts&#13;
       · The Peru team has strengthened its partnership with              in transitioning the project at the conclusion of implemen-&#13;
           the Ministry of Women, which has one of the larg-              tation of behavior change interventions in late 2010. As&#13;
           est social networks in the Peru (reaching close to 5           implementation of the interventions winds down, country&#13;
           million women). This ministry oversees major social            teams will work to supporting national institutions with the&#13;
           programs, including a national nutrition program               necessary tools, documents, and technical assistance to con-&#13;
           that reaches the poorest segments of the population            tinue the work post-intervention. The implementation pro-&#13;
           and our target group.                                          duction tools and a production process achieved during this&#13;
       · In Tanzania, for the first time, the national govern-            reporting period will support new efficiencies to produce&#13;
           ment has allocated annual budgets to all 132 districts         these tools and documents.&#13;
&#13;
2                                                                                                             Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;II.                  Delivering Results--&#13;
                     Implementation Progress&#13;
                     and the Project Components&#13;
&#13;
This section summarizes the results achieved in each com-                                      Given the strong implementation progress of communica-&#13;
ponent of the project: i) Programming, ii) Enabling Envi-                                      tions interventions across the four countries from July to&#13;
ronment, iii) Learning, and iv) Monitoring and Evaluation.                                     December 2009, the team is confident that the project re-&#13;
It assesses the extent to which these project components are                                   mains on track to achieve its overall reach targets at global&#13;
on track to achieve EOP targets defined for each of the key                                    and country levels. The figures below demonstrate the prog-&#13;
indicators under each component. It also highlights exam-                                      ress on mass media (Figure 1) and IPC and DCC (Figure 2)&#13;
ples from the HWWS countries that demonstrate progress                                         reach as a percentage of EOP targets. Mass media progress&#13;
or the achievement of a particular result in support of the                                    is separated from other channels as its reach cannot be ag-&#13;
overall objective of achieving HWWS behavior change at                                         gregated across time periods.&#13;
scale that is sustainable and replicable/adaptable. An&#13;
indepth examination of developments in each of the four                                        Country Performance&#13;
countries is included in Annex 1, Country Stories.                                             Peru&#13;
                                                                                               Peru has made significant progress toward EOP targets in the&#13;
Component 1: Programming                                                                       Programming component in the last six months. IPC, DCC,&#13;
  The Programming Component encompasses the design, de-                                        local mass media, and front line worker trainings have&#13;
  livery, supervision and monitoring of the behavior change                                    reached 174,000, 180,000, 3.8 million, and 14,000 people,&#13;
  communication programs implemented through Interper-                                         respectively (see Figure 3). Implementation now covers the&#13;
  sonal Communication (IPC), Direct Consumer Contact                                           entire country and in seven of the 25 regions in Peru the re-&#13;
  (DCC) and mass media channels. It aims to have a positive                                    sponsibility for implementation has shifted from the project&#13;
  influence on the behavioral determinants defined for each of                                 to local governments. In these seven regions, local munici-&#13;
  the four HWWS countries.                                                                     palities, private institutions and community based organiza-&#13;
                                                                                               tions (CBOs) are now leading HWWS behavior change&#13;
The HWWS project has continued to build on the momen-                                          programs according to the conditions in each unique regional&#13;
tum reported previously. By the end of December 2009, an                                       setting. Accordingly, WSP's role in these regions has evolved&#13;
estimated 2.3 million mothers and caretakers have been en-                                     to one of supporting local authorities directly, providing&#13;
gaged in interpersonal communications, either through                                          technical assistance, capacity building and tools.&#13;
one-on-one or group meetings (74% of EOP target). About&#13;
379,000 women and children have attended DCC or com-                                           Senegal&#13;
munity promotional events (56% of EOP target), and an                                          Since July 2009, Senegal has launched an integrated commu-&#13;
estimated 40.7 million have been reached by mass media, in                                     nications campaign aimed at stimulating and sustaining&#13;
particular radio and TV (100% of EOP target).1 Over                                            handwashing with soap behavior change of about 480,000&#13;
26,000 front line workers responsible for delivering the                                       women of reproductive age and primary school aged children.&#13;
face-to-face interactions have been trained by the project                                     While the mass media channels used cover the entire country,&#13;
(85% of EOP target).                                                                           intensive interventions of local mass media, DCC, and IPC&#13;
                                                                                               through household visits and community meetings have been&#13;
Table 1 shows the Programming progress in the four coun-                                       implemented in 80 communes throughout eight regions of&#13;
tries and at the global level across the four indicators dis-                                  Senegal (Figure 4). Mass media broadcasts completed include&#13;
cussed above.                                                                                  1,496 radio spots and 92 TV spots. The TV spots were&#13;
&#13;
1&#13;
    We do not aggregate the reach numbers across the channels, as exposure is intended to overlap, as the aim of the integrated communications program is to reinforce and&#13;
    complement one intervention with another.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                             3&#13;
&amp;#12;    Progress Report                               Delivering Results--Implementation Progress and the Project Components&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     TABLE 1: EMERGING GLOBAL RESULTS IN THE PROGRAMMING COMPONENT BY DEC 31, '09&#13;
                                                                                                                            Results&#13;
                                                                                       Up to             % of EOP        7/01/09 ­                     % of EOP          Up to               % EOP&#13;
     Performance Indicator                                         EOP Target         6/30/09             Target         12/31/09                       Target          12/31/09           Target Met&#13;
                  Global                                           3,143,000        1,910,210              61%         422,670                           13%          2,332,880                 74%&#13;
     # of target  Peru                                               353,000           55,900              16%         118,300                           34%            174,200                 49%&#13;
     population&#13;
                  Senegal                                            330,000            3,530               1%         145,470                           44%            149,000                 45%&#13;
     reached by&#13;
     IPC programs Tanzania                                           320,000                0               0%         106,000                           33%            106,000                 33%&#13;
                  Vietnam                                          2,140,000        1,850,780              86%          52,900                            3%          1,903,680                 89%&#13;
                  Global                                             676,673           48,900               7%         329,620                           49%            378,520                 56%&#13;
     # of target  Peru                                               249,373           43,600              17%         136,600                           55%            180,200                 72%&#13;
     population&#13;
                  Senegal                                            225,000            1,900               1%         139,820                           62%            141,720                 63%&#13;
     reached by&#13;
     DCC events   Tanzania                                           171,300                0               0%          53,200                           31%             53,200                 31%&#13;
                  Vietnam                                             31,000            3,400              11%               0                            0%              3,400                 11%&#13;
                  Global                                          39,618,078       28,600,000              72%      20,501,300                           52%         40,701,300                103%&#13;
     # of target  Peru                                             5,921,278          577,000              10%       3,234,000                           55%          3,811,000                 64%&#13;
     population&#13;
                  Senegal                                          1,680,000                0               0%       2,734,000                          163%          2,734,000                163%&#13;
     reached by&#13;
     mass media Tanzania                                          14,579,800        8,400,000              58%      14,533,300                          100%         14,533,300                100%&#13;
                  Vietnam                                         17,437,000       19,623,000             113%               0                            0%         19,623,000                113%&#13;
                  Global                                              30,774           14,200              46%          12,083                           39%             26,283                 85%&#13;
     # of front-  Peru                                                15,000            5,200              35%           8,800                           59%             14,000                 93%&#13;
     line workers Senegal                                                139                0               0%             268                          193%                268                193%&#13;
     trained      Tanzania                                               450                0               0%             415                           92%                415                 92%&#13;
                  Vietnam                                             15,185            9,000              59%           2,600                           17%             11,600                 76%&#13;
&#13;
    +: Peru is only implementing local mass media and the numbers across the two time periods can be added because they represent different populations. Senegal, Tanzania and&#13;
    Vietnam, however, use national level media and the numbers cannot be aggregated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      FIGURE 1: PROGRESS ON MASS MEDIA REACH                                                                     FIGURE 2: PROGRESS ON IPC AND DCC REACH&#13;
      (% OF EOP TARGET)                                                                                          (% OF EOP TARGET)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                          Global&#13;
                                                                                                                     number of target&#13;
         number of target population&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                     reached by IPC&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         Global                                    up to Dec. 09&#13;
           reached by mass media&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                       population&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                           Peru&#13;
                                                                                                                        programs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          Peru                                                                                          Senegal&#13;
                                                                                                                                        Tanzania&#13;
                                       Senegal&#13;
                                                                                                                                        Vietnam&#13;
                                                                                                                                          Global&#13;
                                                                                                                     number of target&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                     reached by DCC&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       Tanzania&#13;
                                                                                                                        population&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                           Peru&#13;
                                                                                                                          events&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       Vietnam                                                                                          Senegal&#13;
                                                                                                                                        Tanzania&#13;
                                                  0          50         100        150             200&#13;
                                                                                                                                        Vietnam&#13;
                                                                      percent&#13;
                                                                                                                                          Global&#13;
                                                                                                                     number of front&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                      trained for IPC&#13;
                                                                                                                        line workers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                           Peru&#13;
                                                                                                                                        Senegal&#13;
                                                                                                                                        Tanzania&#13;
                                                                                                                                        Vietnam&#13;
    programmed to air during the broadcast of Latin American                                                                                       0        50          100         150         200&#13;
    soap operas and Senegalese movies--both highly popular                                                                                                            percent&#13;
&#13;
    among women. The total number of participants attend-&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            up to Jun. 09       Jul.­Dec. 09&#13;
    ing DCC eventsrose from 1,400 to 109,000 (62 percent-&#13;
    age point increase). IPC activities are being carried out by&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4                                                                                                                                                                       Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;Progress Report   Delivering Results--Implementation Progress and the Project Components&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 FIGURE 3: PERU PROGRESS IN THE PROGRAMMING COMPONENT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    Target population reached by IPC (,000)                                      Target population reached by DCC (,000)&#13;
    350                                                                         250&#13;
&#13;
    300&#13;
                                                                                200&#13;
    250&#13;
&#13;
    200                                                                         150&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    150&#13;
                                                                                100&#13;
&#13;
    100&#13;
                                                                                 50&#13;
     50&#13;
&#13;
      0                                                                          0&#13;
      Dec. 08 Mar. 09 Jun. 09 Sep. 09 Dec. 09 Mar. 10 Jun. 10 Sep. 10            Dec. 08 Mar. 09 Jun. 09 Sep. 09 Dec. 09 Mar. 10 Jun. 10 Sep. 10&#13;
&#13;
                            projected         reported                                                   projected         reported&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     Target population reached by MM (,000)                                          Cumulative number of FLW trained&#13;
    6,000                                                                      16,000&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               14,000&#13;
    5,000&#13;
                                                                               12,000&#13;
    4,000&#13;
                                                                               10,000&#13;
&#13;
    3,000                                                                        8,000&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 6,000&#13;
    2,000&#13;
                                                                                 4,000&#13;
    1,000&#13;
                                                                                 2,000&#13;
&#13;
       0                                                                              0&#13;
       Dec. 08 Mar. 09 Jun. 09 Sep. 09 Dec. 09 Mar. 10 Jun. 10 Sep. 10                Dec. 08 Mar. 09 Jun. 09 Sep. 09 Dec. 09 Mar. 10 Jun. 10 Sep. 10&#13;
&#13;
                             projected        reported                                                     projected         reported&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
five NGOs that have extensive experience in health pro-                       when it comes to supporting women and caretakers in the&#13;
motion interventions. With the NGO's extensive net-                           family to generate solutions for managing soap and water&#13;
work of community-based organizations and outreach                            (i.e., setting aside soap and water specifically for handwash-&#13;
workers, the reach of IPC has jumped from about 3,500                         ing in convenient places). Concrete options, such as various&#13;
in June 2009 to 149,000 in December 2009 (44 percent-                         types of handwashing stations, are being researched to re-&#13;
age point increase).                                                          move this obstacle.&#13;
&#13;
To date, supervision and quality checks of the face-to-face                   Tanzania&#13;
interactions with the households and community groups                         During this reporting period, the project used mass&#13;
have found that this intervention has been able to improve                    media--airing five different radio spots on three stations--&#13;
knowledge and address obstacles to handwashing with soap.                     to reach an estimated 14.5 million people or 99% of the&#13;
However, the front-line workers are facing a greater challenge                end of project target. The mass media was closely followed&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                                        5&#13;
&amp;#12;    Progress Report        Delivering Results--Implementation Progress and the Project Components&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     FIGURE 4: SENEGAL PROGRESS IN THE PROGRAMMING COMPONENT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   Target &amp; reported mothers and children reached by IPC (,000)               Target &amp; reported mothers and children reached by DCC (,000)&#13;
         40                                                                             80&#13;
         35                                                                             70&#13;
         30&#13;
                                                                                        60&#13;
         25&#13;
                                                                                        50&#13;
         20&#13;
                                                                                        40&#13;
         15&#13;
                                                                                        30&#13;
         10&#13;
                                                                                        20&#13;
          5&#13;
                                                                                        10&#13;
          0&#13;
                                                                                         0&#13;
                          09&#13;
                09&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    09&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     9&#13;
&#13;
                                                     0&#13;
&#13;
                                                    10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    10&#13;
&#13;
                                                    10&#13;
&#13;
                                                    10&#13;
                                                  .0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  .0&#13;
&#13;
                                                  .1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                             Jul. 09 Aug. 09 Sep. 09 Oct. 09 Nov. 09 Mar. 10 Apr. 10 May 10&#13;
                      g.&#13;
              l.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                p.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 r.&#13;
&#13;
                                               ay&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                n.&#13;
&#13;
                                                 l.&#13;
                                               ar&#13;
                                               ov&#13;
                                         ct&#13;
           Ju&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              Ju&#13;
                                             Ap&#13;
                     Au&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             Ju&#13;
                               Se&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             M&#13;
                                             M&#13;
                                         O&#13;
&#13;
                                             N&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                forecasted mothers     reported mothers                                 forecasted mothers        reported mothers&#13;
                                forecasted kids        reported kids                                    forecasted kids           reported kids&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    by the launch of IPC and DCC activities. IPC activities                            implementation team meets with districts/community&#13;
    by trained front line workers reached an estimated                                 leaders to establish the activity plan; Storming, which in-&#13;
    106,000  women and caretakers. These activities pro-                               volves the road shows, including numerous entertainment,&#13;
    vided opportunities for women and children to ask                                  promotional and educational activities; and Celebration, a&#13;
    questions and receive answers to their questions from                              day-long event that is attended by representatives from all&#13;
    trained and informed people, and helped reinforce mes-                             wards and the district level. The events are organized and&#13;
    sages featured in the mass media. During group meet-                               implemented by an experiential marketing firm that works&#13;
    ings, FLWs helped mothers and children learn about the                             closely with local cultural groups. They widely covered by&#13;
    benefits of HWWS, how to make tippy taps, how to                                   local and national media.&#13;
    tackle barriers and how to motivate their family mem-&#13;
    bers to provide a dedicated place for HWWS and ensure                              Vietnam&#13;
    that soap and ensure water are available. Resource Agen-                           While Senegal, Peru, and Tanzania focused on building up&#13;
    cies and District Water and Sanitation Teams supervised                            communications interventions during this reporting&#13;
    and supported the work of the FLWs. The FLW activi-                                period, in Vietnam, the project entered a second phase&#13;
    ties helped create opportunities for communities to cel-                           with the expansion of program activities in four provinces&#13;
    ebrate early successes at DCC events.                                              which are not included in the Impact Evaluation. The&#13;
                                                                                       number of communes in these provinces is relatively&#13;
    During this reporting period, an estimated 200 DCC                                 smaller compared to the number of communes found&#13;
    events took place in seven of the ten project districts, en-                       in  the IE regions, which explains the low numbers for&#13;
    gaging an estimated total of 53,000 participants. DCC will                         reach achieved during this reporting period. Training of&#13;
    be completed in the three remaining districts by April                             community-based workers increased by 17 percentage&#13;
    2010. DCC uses experiential approaches incorporating en-                           point towards the EOP target, and IPC has reached about&#13;
    tertainment and educational techniques to reach and de-                            53,000 women in the new communities. Mass media and&#13;
    liver messages to target audience groups. In Tanzania,                             DCC is scheduled to be re-launched and will take place&#13;
    DCC is staged in three phases: Mobilization, when the                              between April and November 2010.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6                                                                                                                                   Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;Progress Report   Delivering Results--Implementation Progress and the Project Components&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
In the past six months, the Vietnam HWWS program de-                                  in Vietnam) are expected to be launched before&#13;
signed and rolled out a behavior change program targeting                             June 2010.&#13;
school-aged children. Formative research (reported on in&#13;
the 2009 Annual Report) was analyzed using the FOAM&#13;
                                                                              Component 2: Strengthening the Enabling&#13;
behavior change framework adapted for children (FOAM-&#13;
                                                                              Environment&#13;
EM). Among other findings, the research showed that,&#13;
                                                                                 The Enabling Environment component (EE) is designed to&#13;
while Vietnamese children have little free time in their daily&#13;
                                                                                 develop and/or strengthen the institutional and policy/&#13;
lives, they do watch television. Building on this finding, a&#13;
                                                                                 strategy environment in which handwashing with soap&#13;
television program using entertainment-education ap-&#13;
                                                                                 programs can be scaled up and sustained. The EE for the&#13;
proaches was developed to generate interest, enthusiasm,&#13;
                                                                                 HWWS has nine dimensions: Policy, strategy, and direc-&#13;
and promote the practice of HWWS among children. The&#13;
                                                                                 tion; Institutional arrangements; Program methodology;&#13;
program is anchored around the character of Bi, a young&#13;
                                                                                 Implementation capacity; Availability of products and&#13;
boy who acquires special powers by HWWS and integrates&#13;
                                                                                 tools; Financing; Cost-effective implementation; Monitor-&#13;
several channels: an animated series aired during a popular&#13;
                                                                                 ing and Evaluation; and Partnership.&#13;
children's TV show; a comic strip (adapted from the car-&#13;
toon) inserted in the leading children's magazine; and&#13;
                                                                              HW often falls through the cracks of sector silos as there&#13;
school-based extra-curricular activities. The entertainment-&#13;
                                                                              is no clear institutional home or clear leadership to take&#13;
education approach and materials produced under this&#13;
                                                                              the hygiene agenda forward. Peru, Senegal, Tanzania, and&#13;
component have the endorsement of the Ministries of&#13;
                                                                              Vietnam differ significantly in the levels of economic and&#13;
Health and Education and Training, who agreed to let the&#13;
                                                                              human development, institutional capacity, decentraliza-&#13;
materials carry their names along with the Women's Union&#13;
                                                                              tion, fiscal space, and governance. These distinct country&#13;
and WSP. Additionally, IPC training was taken up by the&#13;
                                                                              settings influence implementation approaches and oppor-&#13;
Women's Union and has been well received by schoolmas-&#13;
                                                                              tunities to strengthen the Enabling Environment and&#13;
ters, teachers, and students.&#13;
                                                                              institutionalize HWWS promotion. Despite these differ-&#13;
                                                                              ences, HWWS is now well integrated in all four countries&#13;
Looking Ahead: Opportunities, Risks and Mitigation                            through government-led or private sector initiatives or&#13;
Measures                                                                      programs.&#13;
    · All four countries will continue to work vigilantly                         · In Tanzania, the project has worked to clarify in-&#13;
      to expand the reach. One possible risk to imple-                                stitutional and implementation arrangements for&#13;
      mentation is associated with procurement of new                                 hygiene, particularly handwashing. The Tanzanian&#13;
      implementation partners which will be required if                               Ministries of Health and Social Welfare (MoHSW)&#13;
      current ones are not performing well. To mitigate                               and Water and Irrigation (MoWI) have signed a&#13;
      this risk, the teams have assessed the performance of                           Memorandum of Understanding as a result of inten-&#13;
      partners and undertaken procurement planning and                                sive efforts between WSP, German bilateral partners&#13;
      processing.                                                                     (GTZ and KfW), WaterAid, and UNICEF, and gov-&#13;
    · The figures on reach presented in this report have                              ernment counterparts in the respective ministries.&#13;
      been collected by implementation partners, with                                 The MoU details the national arrangements for sani-&#13;
      quality review by the project teams. The level of in-                           tation and hygiene, and formally establishes a Na-&#13;
      tensity of exposure, which is determined by surveys                             tional Sanitation and Hygiene Steering Committee,&#13;
      of the target audience, will complement and enrich                              a Sanitation and Hygiene Technical Committee, and&#13;
      current information. The next six months present an                             Working Groups. The MoU formalizes the defini-&#13;
      important opportunity to acquire data on exposure,                              tion of sanitation and handwashing, following the&#13;
      as well as changes in HW determinants and behav-                                definitions adopted under the project. The MoHSW&#13;
      ior. Monitoring surveys (i.e., first round in Tanza-                            plans to have the MoU countersigned in 2010 by the&#13;
      nia, second round in Peru and Senegal, third round                              Principal Secretaries from the Ministry of Education&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                             7&#13;
&amp;#12;    Progress Report   Delivering Results--Implementation Progress and the Project Components&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          and the Prime Minister's Office--Regional Admin-                                of the country. Field monitoring and experience has&#13;
          istration and Local Government.                                                 shown that SJ is successful because it provides a con-&#13;
        · In Vietnam, a MoU signed between the World                                      crete solution to the problem of convenient access&#13;
          Bank and the Women's Union--an influential                                      to water and soap: SJ's physical presence in critical&#13;
          mass organization with wide and deep networks--                                 places serves as an important reminder to children&#13;
          secures handwashing as a core component of the                                  to wash their hands properly. This finding is consis-&#13;
          Women's Union programming, extends the reach                                    tent with the global emergent learning on the role&#13;
          of the program to the entire country, and ensures                               of "enabling products" for handwashing (see Com-&#13;
          that handwashing activities will continue beyond                                ponent on Learning). SJ will be scaled up in Central&#13;
          the life of the current project. In addition, the                               America with 10,000 units ordered by WHO for&#13;
          MoU outlines the respective roles and responsi-                                 distribution in Guatemala.&#13;
          bilities for the signees: WSP's role will continue&#13;
          to provide technical assistance on intervention                         Building on the lessons learned from Peru and Vietnam, the&#13;
          design, monitoring, and evaluation in the non-                          Senegal project team has begun to explore how the Scaling&#13;
          project provinces.                                                      Up project can facilitate the National Program on Water&#13;
        · In Peru, HWWS promotion--the behavior change                            and Sanitation (PEPAM) to develop demand-responsive&#13;
          methodology implemented by the project--has                             and affordable HW stations. Currently, HW stations are&#13;
          become a part of the national policy of the Minis-                      provided to households when they obtain a latrine. The&#13;
          try of Education. This action further advances the                      Senegal team will work with PEPAM to determine the level&#13;
          progress and achievements already made to integrate                     of use and responsiveness of these existing HW stations to&#13;
          HWWS into the school curriculum and the training                        meet household needs and propose steps to improve the&#13;
          of teachers.                                                            enabling product.&#13;
&#13;
    In addition to working to secure the institutionalization of                  Other key achievements in the Enabling Environment in&#13;
    HWWS, Peru and Vietnam have also taken firm steps to                          past six months are summarized in Table 2.&#13;
    develop enabling products, in this case, HW stations to fa-&#13;
    cilitate convenient access to water and soap at critical places&#13;
    and times.                                                                    Handover of PPPHW Secretariat Coordinator&#13;
         · In the last progress report, WSP shared the learning                   Position&#13;
            from the development of rough designs of HW sta-                      On December 31, 2009 the position of the Secretariat&#13;
            tions for rural households. As a next step, during this               Coordinator of the Public-Private Partnership for Hand-&#13;
            reporting period, WSP met with WaterSHED Asia,                        washing was rotated to the Academy for Educational De-&#13;
            a Global Development Alliance led by the University                   velopment (AED). Established in 2001, the PPPHW's&#13;
            of North Carolina. At this time, resources are being                  Secretariat was first hosted by the World Bank. In 2003,&#13;
            sought to fund the design and business develop-                       WSP assumed the host functions of the Secretariat, with&#13;
            ment work that would lay the foundation for a com-                    partial funding from the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Founda-&#13;
            mercially produced and distributed HW station.                        tion and USAID. In November 2008, it was agreed to&#13;
         · In Peru, the launch of "Super Jaboncin" (SJ) hand-                     shift the position to a new host in the interest of good&#13;
            washing facility had an enthusiastic response from                    governance. The PPPHW Steering Committee used this&#13;
            public and private partners, resulting in a cost-                     opportunity to evaluate the Secretariat's role and decide&#13;
            sharing arrangement. The HWI produced 36,700                          whether an alternative model should be considered. The&#13;
            units, with partners covering costs associated with                   Steering Committee decided to maintain the current&#13;
            transportation and distribution; promotion; the pro-                  model and, after some consideration, AED was selected as&#13;
            duction of liquid soap; and monitoring of use. SJ                     the new host. A Coordinator has been recruited and is&#13;
            reached 272,000 children and women in 12 regions                      now in place.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8                                                                                                                     Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;Progress Report   Delivering Results--Implementation Progress and the Project Components&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 TABLE 2: PROGRESS ON ENABLING ENVIRONMENT&#13;
 Performance Indicator                                                                     Status 12/31/09&#13;
&#13;
                                                    Progress in Last 6 months:&#13;
                          HWWS integrated            Peru         · MoH has returned as a supporter of the program following&#13;
                          in national policy/                       HW Day&#13;
                          strategy (e.g., water,                  · MoH and MINED budgets allocated for HW promotion.&#13;
                          sanitation, health).                    · HW and soap Stations--Super Jaboncin purchased, distributed&#13;
                                                                    and promoted with regional and local public and private funding.&#13;
                                                                  · HWWS becomes part of national policy on education&#13;
                                                                  · HWWS methodology for BC inserted in regional policy&#13;
                                                                    in Tumbes&#13;
                                                     Senegal      · Technical committee (under the supervision of the Water and&#13;
 Evidence that                                                      Sanitation Sector Program's Steering Committee) to help&#13;
 HWWS is inte-                                                      coordinate the multiple sectors involved in hygiene&#13;
 grated into exist-&#13;
 ing government           HWWS integrated            Tanzania     · MoU signed between MoHSW and MoWI with WSP support&#13;
 or donor budgets         in service delivery                     · Local soap company co-branding their products with HWWS&#13;
 in water, health,        (e.g., water, sanita-                     campaign material&#13;
 education and/or         tion, health).                          · MoWI using HWWS material for work in non-program districts&#13;
 environment.                                                     · MoWI establishes Deputy Directorship of Sanitation and Hygiene&#13;
                                                                  · Budget and sanitation &amp; hygiene plans adopted by MoWI and&#13;
                                                                    distributed to all 132 districts&#13;
                          Handwashing pro-           Vietnam      · MoU signed between WB and VWU&#13;
                          motion/hygiene                          · Partnership with USAID to support development of a commercial&#13;
                          included in budget                        handwashing station&#13;
                          of government or at                     · HWWS training integrated into National Target Program II and Rural&#13;
                          least one additional                      Water and Sanitation projects&#13;
                          donor.                                  · Provincial governments implementing HWWS materials in schools&#13;
                                                                    under their own budget&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
During the period that WSP coordinated the Secretariat,                       PPPHW Web site has been revamped and will be launched&#13;
the PPPHW had several successes: The PPPHW estab-                             in early 2010.&#13;
lished three working groups which are co-chaired by WSP&#13;
staff supported by the BMGF--Schools, Monitoring and                          Looking forward, WSP will continue to be actively engaged&#13;
Evaluation, and Behavior Change. The Schools group                            with the PPPHW as a member of the Steering Committee,&#13;
spearheaded the highly successful Global Handwashing                          through participation in working groups, and by sharing&#13;
Days (October 15) in 2008 and 2009, which was cele-                           lessons from the HWWS project as they become available.&#13;
brated in 80 countries and succeeded in getting 100s of                       WSP sees the PPPHW as a valuable partner in disseminat-&#13;
millions of people to wash their hands. The Monitoring                        ing lessons, testing approaches, and developing new con-&#13;
and Evaluation group established set indicators for hand-                     cepts for the HWWS sector.&#13;
washing, which have been accepted by MICS as core in-&#13;
dicators (observation of soap and water at the handwashing                    Component 3: Learning&#13;
facility). And the Behavior Change group held a Behavior                        The HWWS Learning Component is designed to take a&#13;
Change Think Tank, which lead to work on establishing                           proactive and strategic approach to the learning process to&#13;
an inventory of enabling technologies and related case                          ensure responsive knowledge products are developed and&#13;
studies from two countries, and the development of                              shared with other programmers in the field to encourage&#13;
lighter formative research guidelines. Additionally, the                        knowledge uptake, adaptation and replication.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                              9&#13;
&amp;#12;     Progress Report      Delivering Results--Implementation Progress and the Project Components&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         TABLE 3: PROGRESS ON PRODUCTION OF KNOWLEDGE PRODUCTS&#13;
                                                                      Cumulative              Results         End of Project      % Towards EOP&#13;
         Performance Indicator             Country/Region              Progress            7/1­12/31/09        (EOP) Target           Target&#13;
                                           Senegal                           1                     1                 4                  25%&#13;
&#13;
         Number of knowledge               Tanzania                          0                     0                 5                    0%&#13;
         products completed per            Vietnam                           0                     0                 4                    0%&#13;
         knowledge plan.                   Peru                              3                     2                 5                  60%&#13;
                                           DC                              17                      0               51                   33%&#13;
         Total                                                             21                      3               65                   32%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Production of Knowledge Products                                                 undertaken to provide more information included a new&#13;
     As Table 3 shows, progress on knowledge products has been                        home page and components page.2&#13;
     slow over the duration of the project and in particular the&#13;
     past six months. A Knowledge Management consultant was                           Global Learning&#13;
     hired in this reporting period to implement a production                         As implementation continues to roll out, the teams are in a&#13;
     process. Steps achieved to strengthen the knowledge prod-                        better position to begin documenting their learning. Learn-&#13;
     uct development and dissemination include the develop-                           ing is captured through reporting and information systems,&#13;
     ment and implementation of editorial and design templates,                       performance-based monitoring, knowledge management&#13;
     detailed tracking systems, and the procurement of skilled                        processes and workshops. In the interest of testing and ex-&#13;
     vendors. These steps have established a solid foundation                         panding the lessons from the project, the team has begun&#13;
     through which knowledge products can be consistently and                         engaging with WSP technical staff outside the project.&#13;
     efficiently produced and disseminated.&#13;
                                                                                      The Global Annual Meeting in Vietnam included both&#13;
     During this period two Working Papers (Global Learning                           project team members and five WSP staff working on hy-&#13;
     Strategy and Practical Guidelines for Measuring Handwash-                        giene initiatives in Africa, East Asia, and Central America.&#13;
     ing Behavior), one Technical Report (Improving Measures of                       A key focus was on sharing lessons learned and how to&#13;
     Handwashing Behavior) and two Learning Notes (Emergent                           harvest these lessons to produce tools and resources that&#13;
     Learning about Learning and Insights from Designing a                            will be essential for other countries seeking to replicate the&#13;
     Handwashing Station for Rural Vietnamese Households) were                        project.&#13;
     edited and prepared for production. In addition, four&#13;
     monthly Handwashing Bulletin and one HW series were                              A role-playing exercise ("What Would We Tell Another&#13;
     prepared and disseminated in Peru. With a goal to share                          Country?") helped the team articulate answers and identi-&#13;
     more information with a wider audience, the 2009 Annual                          fied areas to strengthen. Additionally, three rounds of si-&#13;
     Progress Report and a 2009 Global Annual Handwashing                             multaneous peer-learning sessions were held on a wide&#13;
     Meeting Report were produced and disseminated on the                             range of topics from the four countries. In a scenario-based&#13;
     project Web site, and a companion Web page for each re-                          activity, "What does 2015 Look Like," country teams fo-&#13;
     port was also developed. The page with highlights from the                       cused on sustainability and what the sustainability of hand-&#13;
     Global Annual Meeting includes 15 presentations from the                         washing behavior looks like, and then identified the steps&#13;
     meeting, four videos taken at the meeting, and two videos                        and conditions needed to take to make their vision a reality.&#13;
     related to the project. Additional iterations to the Web site                    On the basis of these exercises, the team was in a stronger&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     2&#13;
         2009 Annual Progress Report www.wsp.org/index.cfm?page=page_disp&amp;pid=21250&#13;
         2009 Annual Global Meeting www.wsp.org/index.cfm?page=page_disp&amp;pid=21437&#13;
         Core Components             www.wsp.org/index.cfm?page=page_disp&amp;pid=21214&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10                                                                                                                        Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;Progress Report   Delivering Results--Implementation Progress and the Project Components&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
position to adapt the HWWS lessons to new country con-                        provinces and the number of trained handwashing agents&#13;
texts in an effort to scale up replication.                                   increased by 18%. With the increasing roll out of imple-&#13;
                                                                              mentation in Tanzania, the Ministry of Water and Irriga-&#13;
The Global Annual Meeting also provided an opportunity                        tion (MoWI) saw the effectiveness of handwashing&#13;
to identify key questions and look for shared understand-                     promotion and has incorporated the approach into existing&#13;
ing amongst the global team on the responses to these                         government structures. This not only increases scale and&#13;
questions. There was a consensus that, to help move the                       sustainability, but lends credibility to the initiative among&#13;
sector forward, we must have a shared understanding and                       target population and partners.&#13;
internal consistency on critical issues to successfully pro-&#13;
mote handwashing with soap at national levels. Team&#13;
members developed a list of critical questions or issues in                   National Demand for Baseline Information&#13;
need of alignment and, as a next step, agreed to draft and                    With the completion of the fieldwork for the baselines, dis-&#13;
circulate position statements. Some questions, for exam-                      trict and national governments have been increasingly in-&#13;
ple, include the use of mud/ash and other alternatives                        terested to receive this information. The initial thinking was&#13;
(ABHS) to soap; a definition of handwashing and measur-                       that the baseline data would be of primary interest to re-&#13;
ing behavior change; the involvement of men or others as                      searchers. However, it is now understood that the govern-&#13;
a target population. The teams have begun work on Fre-                        ments will look to the baseline reports to provide essential&#13;
quently Asked Questions (FAQs) and Learning Notes to                          data about their country or districts. To help satisfy this&#13;
address these matters.                                                        demand, the baseline reports will be repackaged and repur-&#13;
                                                                              posed for dissemination with national and local govern-&#13;
                                                                              ments as a key target audience.&#13;
Emerging Learning&#13;
During the past six months, the team has identified four&#13;
areas of learning based on project implementation:                            Institutionalizing through Local Governments. Or Not&#13;
                                                                              At the start of the project, the team assumed that operat-&#13;
                                                                              ing through local governments would prove to be critical&#13;
Reaching Scale and Strengthening Sustainability                               to the success of the project. This has proven to be the&#13;
through Leveraging National Programs                                          case in countries such as Peru and Tanzania, where decen-&#13;
From inception, the project had the goal of reaching scale                    tralization has given the mandate to improve health to&#13;
and improving sustainability by integrating HWWS into                         local governments. By contrast, in Vietnam, local govern-&#13;
national programs. While integration has happened in each                     ment did not emerge asan appropriate vehicle for imple-&#13;
country, the realities of how it happened in each country                     mentation. In Vietnam's more centralized context,&#13;
differed due to the country context. For example, in                          operating through a centralized agency with a national&#13;
Vietnam, time spent working closely with the Women's                          reach has proven to be more effective. Senegal falls be-&#13;
Union--to build their capacity, refine their approach to                      tween Peru and Tanzania on the one hand, and Vietnam&#13;
handwashing, and improve monitoring--lead to the                              on the other: To date, there has been significant emphasis&#13;
signing of a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU)                                on efforts at the national level--focusing in particular on&#13;
between the World Bank and the Women's Union. The                             policy and strategy formulation--in conjunction with ef-&#13;
MoU effectively institutionalizes HWWS into the WU's                          forts undertaken with NGOs working at the community&#13;
national programming, resulting in national scale and on-                     level. The latter is, in large part, driven by the experience&#13;
going implementation. Due to the efforts of the team in                       of behavior change and successful interventions in other&#13;
Peru--they successfully demonstrated the importance of                        areas, such as nutrition and HIV/AIDS. What this learn-&#13;
HWWS to nutrition--JUNTOS, a national nutrition                               ing underscores is the danger of basing project design on&#13;
program, has incorporated the handwashing approach into                       global assumptions without understanding national insti-&#13;
their program. Project coverage expanded to six additional                    tutional contexts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                               11&#13;
&amp;#12;     Progress Report   Delivering Results--Implementation Progress and the Project Components&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Beyond Motivation                                                             Component 4: Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
     Factors that influence individuals' opportunity to HWWS                       Monitoring for Performance and Results&#13;
     have often been overlooked in hygiene promotion initia-                       Performance monitoring systems at the country and global&#13;
     tives, with much of the focus centered on motivation. Find-                   levels continue to provide important data on implementa-&#13;
     ings from WSP's Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project                         tion progress, successes, and opportunities to improve per-&#13;
     and other research (see for example Biran et al 2005 and                      formance. The global Management Information System&#13;
     Luby et al 2009) suggest that convenient access to water                      (MIS), introduced during the last reporting period, is&#13;
     and soap when and where needed, and a designated place                        being used as the basis for global learning and reporting.&#13;
     for HWWS, are also important behavioral determinants.                         Country-level reporting processes and MISs have been in&#13;
     Enabling products such as handwashing stations provide a                      place in Peru and Vietnam for just over a year. The Senegal&#13;
     designated place, an environmental cue to action, and a                       MIS was finalized in this reporting period and is capturing&#13;
     stable context for handwashing--factors highlighted in the                    important implementation and performance data (see&#13;
     research literature as critical for habits to form and be main-               Box  1). With the recent launch of activities in Tanzania,&#13;
     tained (see, for example, Verplanken &amp; Wood, 2006). WSP                       the reporting and data collection systems are being rolled&#13;
     is currently conducting a landscape of enabling products.                     out now and are expected to be fully operational within the&#13;
     Many identified to date are tippy-taps, however, the learn-                   next several months.&#13;
     ing from a design consultancy for a handwashing station for&#13;
     rural Vietnamese households is that appearances may mat-&#13;
     ter and that designing features to take account user prefer-&#13;
                                                                                       BOX 1: THE SENEGAL PERFORMANCE MANAGEMENT&#13;
     ences and usual practices into account is essential. Findings&#13;
                                                                                       SYSTEM&#13;
     from planned case studies on selected enabling products&#13;
                                                                                       The Senegal MIS became fully operational in this&#13;
     and the evaluation of Duraplast in Peru will reveal whether&#13;
                                                                                       reporting period and is tracking all qualitative and&#13;
     mass-produced and commercially distributed products&#13;
                                                                                       quantitative data across the project. The system is&#13;
     have the potential to scale up and sustain handwashing.&#13;
                                                                                       used by implementing agency (IA) staff, supervi-&#13;
     Learning in this area is being shared through several chan-&#13;
                                                                                       sors from the implementing agencies and the WSP&#13;
     nels including the South Asia Hygiene Practitioners' Work-&#13;
                                                                                       M&amp;E and management team. Written reporting&#13;
     shop (in Dhaka in February 2010) and its Proceedings&#13;
                                                                                       forms are used by fieldworkers to record data on&#13;
     Journal as well as through planned Learning Notes.&#13;
                                                                                       IPC and/or DCC activities and indicators. Forms&#13;
                                                                                       are collected by IA supervisors for review and veri-&#13;
     Importance of Champions                                                           fication. Once data is verified, forms are sent to the&#13;
     The HWWS project has benefited from several champions.                            WSP project office, where the project monitoring&#13;
     The team has learned that champions emerge in many                                specialist reviews the forms for quality assurance&#13;
     forms and different contexts. In Vietnam, a champion in                           purposes before data is entered into the Access&#13;
     the Women's Union had advocated for the MoU; once                                 database by a WSP staff member. The WSP MNE&#13;
     drafted, she was able to manage the process to secure final-                      specialist generates monthly reports (Objectives-&#13;
     ization in a few days. In Tanzania, the World Bank's Senior                       Achievements-Gap and Percentage Reports) that&#13;
     Water Specialist long championed handwashing to the na-                           are reviewed at monthly performance meetings with&#13;
     tional government, effectively building the confidence of                         the implementing agencies. A quality assurance&#13;
     the MoW to support an unproven approach and eventually                            monitoring team conducts periodic supervision at&#13;
     integrate it into the national program. Peru found a cham-                        the household level, attending IPC and DCC activi-&#13;
     pion in the Ministry of Education who supported the adop-                         ties to assess the quality and completeness of the&#13;
     tion of handwashing training as a consideration in                                engagement. The results of these "spot checks"&#13;
     promotion of teachers. This strongly improved the incen-                          helps to monitor the quality of delivery and adjust&#13;
     tive among the primary school teachers to participate in                          engagement methods and messages as needed.&#13;
     training and become certified in handwashing promotion.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12                                                                                                                     Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;Progress Report   Delivering Results--Implementation Progress and the Project Components&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Impact Evaluation                                                                    for 2-week recall period) and no significant impacts&#13;
During the last six months, the collection of baseline data                          will be captured on diarrhea and related health out-&#13;
was completed in each of the four countries. In Peru, data                           comes. Thus, no further longitudinal surveys will&#13;
analysis was finalized but a revised report is underway to                           be conducted and the endline survey will be scaled&#13;
include additional tables and information. However, the                              down to measure behavior change outcomes rather&#13;
baseline results have already been shared with some gov-                             than biometric measures.&#13;
ernment counterparts and additional meetings are sched-                            · In Tanzania, resources will be reallocated to con-&#13;
uled with several ministries for mid-February. Vietnam                               duct one survey by a capable and reliable firm, thus&#13;
finalized the collection of baseline data and received the                           relying only in the endline data, rather than having&#13;
data in December. Data analysis is underway and a base-                              repeated but non-credible surveys. This approach&#13;
line report will be drafted by the end of February. In Sen-                          is driven by the lack of transport infrastructure,&#13;
egal, the data collection was finalized but the data has been                        limited capacity of firms in the region, and the&#13;
received. Data analysis is starting and a draft report is ex-                        geographical conditions of Tanzania. An alter-&#13;
pected by early March. In Tanzania, MUHAS finally com-                               native under consideration is to measure height&#13;
pleted the baseline data collection with close monitoring                            rather than diarrhea prevalence if no capable and&#13;
and field support from both the implementation and the                               reliable firms can be found to conduct longitudinal&#13;
country IE teams. The process of entering and coding data                            surveys.&#13;
was also supported by an additional CSPro specialist who&#13;
assisted MUHAS during data entry. The majority of the                         The coming months will be focused in disseminating IE&#13;
data has now been entered, but the process is much slower                     results and knowledge products, and preparing for the&#13;
than anticipated. The baseline data collected by MUHAS                        endline surveys. This will include in-country presenta-&#13;
will not be used for the impact assessment but a baseline                     tions to share baseline data (some already programmed in&#13;
report will be drafted to share with government counter-                      Peru for mid-February), preparing IE-related products,&#13;
parts and other WSP partners.                                                 re-estimating sample sizes, procuring survey firms, revis-&#13;
                                                                              ing and piloting the questionnaires, strategically deciding&#13;
As data becomes available, the IE global team has been re-                    which outcomes should be collected in each country,&#13;
vising some initial assumptions and recalculating power es-                   training and standardizing survey personnel, etc. The&#13;
timates. Actual data will also help to revise some of the                     timelines for the endline surveys in each country are in-&#13;
initial designs, when needed and revisit some of the out-                     cluded in Annex 3.&#13;
comes to be collected. The main issues to consider and re-&#13;
visit are:                                                                    Tables 4 and 5 present the current status and planned ac-&#13;
    · In Vietnam the prevalence of diarrhea among chil-                       tivities for each phase of the baseline and longitudinal&#13;
        dren under age 2 is extremely low (fewer than 2%                      surveys.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 TABLE 4: STATUS AND SCHEDULE OF BASELINE SURVEYS&#13;
                                                    Preliminary Data&#13;
                   Baseline      Data Entered      Analysis Completed                                     Results Shared with Team and&#13;
                    Survey       and Handed         and Shared with           Final Report Completed     Wider Group of Stakeholders and&#13;
 Country          Launched         to WSP            Country Team                and Disseminated             Government Partners&#13;
 Peru                                                                                                                  &#13;
                                                                             (Revised report Feb 2010)      (More meetings Feb 2010)&#13;
 Vietnam                                                                             March 2010                   March 2010&#13;
 Senegal                                               March 2010                     April 2010                   April 2010&#13;
 Tanzania                        Feb­Mar 10             April 2010                    May 2010                     May 2010&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                            13&#13;
&amp;#12;     Progress Report         Delivering Results--Implementation Progress and the Project Components&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         TABLE 5: STATUS AND SCHEDULE OF LONGITUDINAL SURVEYS&#13;
                                                                                        Pre-Intervention&#13;
                                All Necessary                                          Monitoring Survey                  Mid-Term&#13;
                                 Preparation            Pre-Intervention               Data Analyzed and                  Monitoring            Mid-Term Monitoring Survey Data&#13;
                                 for Launch               Monitoring                  Shared with Country                  Surveys                 Analyzed and Shared with&#13;
         Country                 Completed3            Surveys Launched                  Teams by PIs                     Launched                   Country Teams by PIs&#13;
         Peru                                                                             February 2010                                                          Mid 2010&#13;
         Vietnam                                                                             Early 2010                    Mid 2010                          Summer 2010&#13;
         Senegal                                                                              Mid 2010                     Mid 2010                          Summer 2010&#13;
         Tanzania              Due to the problems encountered with the contractor,                                     To be decided                        To be decided&#13;
                               this survey will not be conducted. An additional mid-term&#13;
                               monitoring survey will be conducted in 2010.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     3&#13;
         This includes the following deliverables: firms recruited, questionnaires finalized and translated to local languages, pilots conducted and timeline for the longitudinal set up.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14                                                                                                                                                          Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;III.              Challenges and Project&#13;
                  Responses&#13;
&#13;
Global Challenges                                              norms. These scales require a series of steps--focus groups,&#13;
Performance Monitoring                                         qualitative testing, piloting on small samples, and principal&#13;
In general, routine reporting on project performance           component analysis--to arrive at a final series of questions.&#13;
through the MIS has progressed well over the past six          These steps are lengthy and require additional time and re-&#13;
months. However, the team still faces significant challenges   sources which must be planned for and budgeted.&#13;
in the area of performance monitoring of the behavior&#13;
change interventions. The challenges include:                  Incorporating learning into implementation. With behavior-&#13;
                                                               change interventions gaining momentum across the four&#13;
Measuring reach. We estimate the reach, relying on the re-     countries, numerous implementation lessons are emerging&#13;
ported data from the implementers of the communications        from the field. For example, in Senegal, the project team is&#13;
interventions. What we ideally want is to use community        learning the importance of involving men to facilitate ac-&#13;
based surveys to measure prompted and unprompted recall        cess to women and children in the family, to reinforce&#13;
of exposure. We have included these measures in the moni-      HWWS messages, and to help sustain behaviors. Tanzania&#13;
toring surveys, which we look to for verifying against the     is also learning from implementation experiences in which&#13;
reach reported.                                                consistency and alignment of HW messages in an inte-&#13;
                                                               grated communications program across multiple channels&#13;
Monitoring implementation carried out by partners. While       and implementing partners has proven difficult.&#13;
local implementing partners in Peru have shared data on&#13;
reach, facilitated by a Memorandum of Understanding, we        The challenge facing the teams, at present, involves how&#13;
have found it more challenging at local levels, where au-      best to incorporate these learnings into implementation:&#13;
thorities have limited capacity for monitoring at the house-   mid-way adjustments pose a risk of hampering pace of im-&#13;
hold level, the quality of data varies, and collection less    plementation, particularly at this later phase of the project.&#13;
systematic.                                                    Nevertheless, the teams in Senegal and Tanzania have taken&#13;
                                                               practical and feasible steps, such as adjusting the content of&#13;
Measuring behavioral determinants. Scales are used for mea-    communications material--in particular mass media and&#13;
suring determinants such as religious beliefs and social       IPC--to improve the quality of interventions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                15&#13;
&amp;#12;     IV.             Project Management&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     At headquarters, the Senior Impact Evaluation Specialist,      Education Programs. Ms. Grossman has helped the HWWS&#13;
     Jack Molyneaux, left at the end of September and was           team make significant progress with the development and&#13;
     quickly replaced by Bertha Briceno. Ms. Briceno started in     production of knowledge products, including designing&#13;
     October 2009 and was integrated into the teams by attend-      editorial and design templates, improving WSP's Global&#13;
     ing the global annual meeting of the Global Scaling Up         Scaling Up Handwashing Project Website, editing prod-&#13;
     Handwashing Project (she also attended the global annual       ucts, and formalizing our publishing processes.&#13;
     meeting of the Global Scaling Up Sanitation Project).&#13;
     Previously, Ms. Briceno was the Director of Evaluation of      Our Senior Water and Sanitation Specialist, Ousseynou&#13;
     Public Programs for the Colombian government. In addi-         Diop, who was the overall TTL for the HWWS project&#13;
     tion to her technical skills, she understands the use of im-   in Tanzania and Senegal, passed away unexpectedly in&#13;
     pact evaluation data from the government perspective, is       November, following the global annual meetings. The&#13;
     able to bridge the dialogue between researchers and practi-    regional management team appointed Yolande Coombes&#13;
     tioners, and has the ability to translate impact evaluation    to temporarily fill Mr. Diop's role until a replacement is&#13;
     findings into policy recommendations.                          found. Ms. Coombes has been a technical advisor on&#13;
                                                                    both projects and has a strong background in behavior&#13;
     At headquarters, the project hired Amy Grossman, a knowl-      change and monitoring and evaluation.&#13;
     edge management specialist from National Geographic's&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16                                                                                                   Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;Progress Report   Annex 1: Country Stories July 1­December 31, 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Annex 1: Country Stories&#13;
July 1­December 31, 2009&#13;
Peru Country Story                                                       · Super Jaboncin, the long-awaited "creative tech-&#13;
1. Project Description                                                     nology" to put soap in place in homes and schools&#13;
HWWS, known as the National Handwashing Initiative                         became a reality; designed by a private partner and&#13;
(NHI) in Peru, supports national and regional authorities,                 acquired by diverse public and private partners. The&#13;
the private sector, and civil society organizations to pro-                device reached 272,000 women and children in&#13;
mote HWWS in 23 of 25 regions in the country.                              Peru; an additional 10,000 units for Guatemala were&#13;
                                                                           ordered by WHO and delivered during the period.&#13;
2. Intended Project Outcome                                                Its impact on behavioral change will be evaluated&#13;
Working in collaboration with many partners, NHI will                      during 2010.&#13;
stimulate and sustain 1,279,000 women and children to&#13;
wash their hands with soap at critical times (i.e., after defe-       Scaling Up&#13;
cation, before eating).                                                  · In seven regions, the scope of the program has spread&#13;
                                                                           to new areas due to local partnerships, representing&#13;
3. Highlights for the Reporting Period                                     a geographic growth of 70% in Cajamarca; 30% in&#13;
    · The implementation arrangements map completed                        Piura; 25% in Lambayeque; and 20% in Arequipa;&#13;
      at 100%;                                                           · The Ministry of Women joined at the policy elabo-&#13;
    · A second phase was reached in seven regions where                    ration stage, representing a major opportunity for&#13;
      local entities including governments, municipalities,                scaling up as it represents one of the largest social&#13;
      private institutions, and CBOs are leading the                       networks in the Peru, reaching close to 5m women,&#13;
      process--allocating resources, tapping networks,                     and directs major social programs, in particular a nu-&#13;
      and widening the scope of the intervention--as                       trition program that reaches the poorest segments of&#13;
      originally conceived in the project design;                          the population and our target group.&#13;
    · The Ministry of Health returned and the Ministry of&#13;
      Women emerged as relevant actors. These Ministries              Sustainability&#13;
      direct important national social programs and have                 · National, regional, and local policy: major develop-&#13;
      expressed strong interest to insert HWI into their                   ments in this dimension are analyzed in the attached&#13;
      structures;                                                          chart;&#13;
    · Monthly bulletin delivered to 600 mail recipients                  · The Ministry of Education, the strongest partner in&#13;
      including local stakeholders, partners, authorities,                 the public sector, evaluated the program as it is being&#13;
      universities, media, teachers, implementing agencies                 carried out in 21 regions and 1,884 schools, and has&#13;
      already involved or with potential to join;                          promising results that will be shared with the team&#13;
    · The first issue of the Handwashing Series was deliv-                 in early 2010.&#13;
      ered, complete with guidelines&#13;
    · A consultant was recruited and research initiated to            Replication&#13;
      develop a toolkit for WB Managers to integrate a                   · The OPS in Guatemala adapted our methodologies&#13;
      hygiene component into existing programs;                            for behavioral change in schools­they actually re-&#13;
    · Three longitudinal studies were completed and an                     designed and reproduced the manuals for teachers­&#13;
      Intercept Study was started and reached midpoint;                    you can find them in their web page. They mention&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                     17&#13;
&amp;#12;     Progress Report   Annex 1: Country Stories July 1­December 31, 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           at the beginning of the publication that it is based                 We believe the EE is ready for this as we have evi-&#13;
           on a methodology developed by the Handwashing                        dence of the commitment of these Ministries, but&#13;
           Initiative in Peru;                                                  we must learn about their precise expectations and&#13;
         · To help combat the spread of AH1N1, OPS in                           demand and may need to modify the "BC package"&#13;
           Guatemala contacted DURAPLAST in Peru and                            accordingly;&#13;
           ordered 10,000 Super Jaboncin HW soap devices,                     · Knowledge sharing --Thematic areas have been iden-&#13;
           to distribute at 3,000 primary schools. They repro-                  tified and concept notes are in process. Products will&#13;
           duced the promotion material made in Peru and                        target country demand as well as global.&#13;
           are ready to implement the plan as the products are&#13;
           coming out of customs;&#13;
                                                                           Senegal Country Story&#13;
         · TTLs from Education and Environment Bank Proj-&#13;
                                                                           1. Project Description&#13;
           ects have contacted the team expressing interest to&#13;
                                                                           In Senegal, the Scaling Up HW Project builds on the efforts&#13;
           receive support to integrate hygiene/handwashing&#13;
                                                                           of the Public-Private Partnership on Handwashing with&#13;
           components in projects in Argentina and Pakistan,&#13;
                                                                           soap (PPPHW) which was established in 2003 with assis-&#13;
           respectively. The second case is a result of the&#13;
                                                                           tance the Japanese Social Development Fund (JSDF) and&#13;
           Colombian collaborative experience--the same&#13;
                                                                           WSP. PPPHW, with its Steering Committee under the aus-&#13;
           TTL changed regions.&#13;
                                                                           pices of the Ministry of Health, was responsible for the&#13;
     4. Overall Progress to Date&#13;
                                                                           implementation of the first HWWS campaign that was&#13;
                                                                           structured around two types of communication activities:&#13;
        Target population reached by IPC                        49.3%      (i) direct consumer contact (DCC) events in 4 provinces in&#13;
        Target population reached by DCC                        71.9%      schools, market places, health centers and with women's&#13;
        Target population reached by MM                         64.4%      groups, and (ii) mass media activities through national and&#13;
        Cumulative number of FLW trained                        95.1%      local channels (including local radio and billboards). The&#13;
                                                                           Scaling up project helps to further entrench the HW initia-&#13;
     5. Newly Emerging Questions                                           tive to further scale up promotion and behavior change.&#13;
         · How can we best plan for the end of project? How to             The project deepens mass media interventions at the na-&#13;
           build on lessons learned to date to maximize project            tional and local levels, expands DCC, and introduces inter-&#13;
           impact, replication, and sustainability?                        personal communications in about eighty localities in eight&#13;
         · How to make a case for success before the Impact                regions (Dakar, Diourbel, Fatick, Kaolack, Louga, Thies,&#13;
           Evaluations are completed? We are building the en-              Ziguinchor, and Saint Louis). The size of the target popula-&#13;
           abling environment under the assumption that we                 tion (i.e., women and caretakers and children from 5­13)&#13;
           will succeed at achieving BC objectives;                        in these eighty localities is about 1.5 million.&#13;
         · Who will take over the facilitation of the process in&#13;
           real life?&#13;
                                                                           2. Intended Project Outcome&#13;
                                                                           Stimulate and sustain 493,000 women and children to&#13;
     6. Area of Focus for Next Six Months&#13;
                                                                           wash their hands with soap at critical times (i.e., after defe-&#13;
         · Behavioral Change--to assure we are meeting this&#13;
                                                                           cation, before eating).&#13;
           objective, the project will focus on public sector&#13;
           leadership at regional and local levels. We will revisit&#13;
           our program to maximize scaling-up opportunities                3. Highlights for the Reporting Period&#13;
           working with national networks in four sectors. TA              Scaling Up&#13;
           will also be provided to strengthen local partnerships;            · Launched first phase of implementation in all eight&#13;
         · Sustainability--We aim to insert the program meth-                   intervention areas, starting the last week of June;&#13;
           odology at the operational core of three or four                   · Mass media campaign commenced through televi-&#13;
           sectors: health, education, sanitation and women.                    sion, radio, and billboard displays to prime target&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18                                                                                                             Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;Progress Report   Annex 1: Country Stories July 1­December 31, 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        audience to receive campaign messages and to facili-          initially targeted only mothers/caretakers of children under&#13;
        tate follow-up of IPC and DCC activities;                     five and children from 5­13, reports from fieldworkers re-&#13;
    ·   149,000 women and children reached through IPC                veal a pattern showing that men are very interested by&#13;
        and 104,000 through DCC;                                      HWWS promotion and that they have invited themselves&#13;
    ·   Implementation lessons show that, because of their            to participate in discussions and to commit themselves and&#13;
        multiple roles in the family, men may play a pivotal          their families to handwashing with soap at critical&#13;
        role in handwashing promotion. A Learning Note                junctures.&#13;
        about integration of men in the primary target is in&#13;
        development;                                                  A Management Information System has been put in place,&#13;
    ·   Implementing an integrated communication cam-                 including access to a common database (shared with imple-&#13;
        paign that includes mass media, DCC and IPC                   mentation agencies) and the selection of a team of supervi-&#13;
        shows that mass media is a powerful tool that can             sors to conduct quality assurance monitoring.&#13;
        open household doors and facilitate in terms of&#13;
        reach and exposure;                                           Supervision findings were used as an input to adjust actions&#13;
    ·   Developed Monitoring Information System to pro-               on the ground and assess the performance of five NGOs,&#13;
        vide access to common database and facilitate quality         implementation agencies with regard to the extension of&#13;
        assurance to better assess progress by implementa-            contracts.&#13;
        tion agencies.&#13;
                                                                      The Impact Evaluation baseline study was completed and&#13;
Sustainability                                                        analysis initiated. Two rounds of the longitudinal study out&#13;
    · WSP supported the Ministry of Health in taking a                of ten (2nd step) were completed.&#13;
      more active role in the national handwashing initia-&#13;
      tive, including acting as host for PPPHW Steering               5. Newly Emerging Questions&#13;
      Committee meetings and organizing national cel-                    · How should we best target men--primary or sec-&#13;
      ebrations marking the second Global Handwashing                      ondary audience?&#13;
      Day;                                                               · Under the national rural water and sanitation pro-&#13;
    · With WSP input on the mapping of hygiene inter-                      gram, HW stations are provided to households with&#13;
      ventions, a steering committee has been established                  subsidized latrine. How demand-responsive are these&#13;
      for reviewing the social and environmental impact                    existing HW stations? How can they be improved&#13;
      of water and sanitation projects through PEPAM (a                    and be positioned so that they help habituate the&#13;
      national organization coordinating W&amp;S action for                    HWWS practice in the household?&#13;
      achieving the MDGs). It aims to incorporate a hy-&#13;
      giene component into water and sanitation projects;             6. Area of Focus for Next Six Months&#13;
    · With WSP support on developing of materials and                    · Assess type, convenience, preferences, willingness to&#13;
      training, Task force from the Ministry of Educa-                     pay etc. of handwashing stations in use in Senegal;&#13;
      tion developed a handwashing orientation book                      · Launch a monitoring survey (Doer/Non-doer 2) to&#13;
      for teacher in preparation of the pilot program at                   monitor changes in determinants;&#13;
      schools.                                                           · Launch the 2nd phase of the communication cam-&#13;
                                                                           paign using IPC, DCC and mass media to expand&#13;
4. Overall Progress to Date                                                reach and exposure;&#13;
An integrated HWWS communication campaign has been                       · Monitor the next phase of the communication&#13;
launched in eight intervention areas and has had significant               campaign;&#13;
reach and impact, according to fieldworkers (in IPC and                  · Launch a very large public relations/advocacy cam-&#13;
DCC) who report that the mass media campaign has                           paign to build partnership with medical sector,&#13;
opened household doors for them. While the campaign                        schools, nutrition program, plastic manufacturers etc.;&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                     19&#13;
&amp;#12;     Progress Report   Annex 1: Country Stories July 1­December 31, 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         · Develop knowledge products and tools related to key                  be approved and endorsed by the cabinet and parlia-&#13;
           findings to date such as men's interest in HW promo-                 ment in 2010);&#13;
           tion, impact of integrated communication campaign,                 · Tarmal Industries launched a soap brand with&#13;
           incorporating medical sector in HW promotion;                        HWWS messages and logo on packaging and insert&#13;
         · Assess the demand-responsiveness of the existing                     and distributed in selected markets;&#13;
           HW stations provided under PEPAM and offer                         · GHD and Sanitation &amp; Hygiene Week continued&#13;
           recommendations.                                                     to provide platform for partners and stakeholders to&#13;
                                                                                review and celebrate hygiene achievement.&#13;
     Tanzania Country Story&#13;
     1. Project Description                                                Replication&#13;
     HWWS-Tanzania is implemented in conjunction with                         · Sanitation and hygiene planning and implementa-&#13;
     TSSM-Tanzania and in close collaboration with the Minis-                   tion guidelines finalized and sent to districts for use&#13;
     try of Water and Irrigation's National Water Sector Devel-                 by MOWI. These guidelines provide a framework&#13;
     opment Program (WSDP) and the Ministry of Health and                       for district-level implementation with possible ac-&#13;
     Social Welfare's Health Village Initiative (HVI). The project              tivities using the Scaling Up project approaches.&#13;
     is targeting women of reproductive age and children be-                    More budgets from central government have been&#13;
     tween the ages of 6­14 in ten districts.                                   allocated for hygiene interventions in a few districts&#13;
                                                                                to deepen implementation;&#13;
     2. Intended Project Outcome                                              · Some stakeholders and partners adopted the project&#13;
     Stimulate and sustain 1.25 million women and children to                   approaches to integrate with ongoing interventions:&#13;
     wash their hands with soap at critical times (i.e., after defe-            UNICEF integrated them into school sanitation and&#13;
     cation, before eating).                                                    other learning districts it supports; AED/TMARC&#13;
                                                                                project integrated some training and education&#13;
                                                                                materials into a pilot program in Morogoro; SNV,&#13;
     3. Highlights for the Reporting Period&#13;
                                                                                WaterAID, and WSCC integrated some materials&#13;
     Scaling Up&#13;
                                                                                into outreach activities.&#13;
         · Building on effects started by mass media, rolled out&#13;
           DCC and IPC communication activities to move&#13;
           from awakening to engaging through face-to-face                 4. Overall Progress to Date&#13;
           and group meetings;                                                · Over 14,000,000 people reached through mass&#13;
         · Frontline activators trained and deployed to con-                    media campaign carried on three radio stations (two&#13;
           tinue on the ground HWWS promotions with                             national, one regional);&#13;
           support from professional marketing/promotional                    · 53,000 people reached through DCC activations, in&#13;
           companies and NGOs;                                                  four districts;&#13;
         · Increased project visibility through outdoor paint-                · 106,000 women and children reached through IPC&#13;
           ings and placements in project districts;                            in seven districts;&#13;
         · District teams trained to supervise and monitor                    · IPC training for frontline activators (FLAs) com-&#13;
           IPC activities, materials distribution and DCC                       pleted in seven districts, totaling 415 FLAs trained&#13;
           interventions.                                                       and supervised;&#13;
                                                                              · 26,667 out of 235,000 households, equivalent to&#13;
     Sustainability                                                             11%, have installed HW stations with water and&#13;
         · Annual budgets allocated for all 132 districts to sup-               soap.&#13;
           port hygiene and sanitation activities;&#13;
         · National sanitation and hygiene policy with a frame-            5. Newly Emerging Questions&#13;
           work for implementation and monitoring of all sani-                · How can we create interest from non-traditional&#13;
           tation and hygiene activities nearing completion (to                 private sector partners who can support HW&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
20                                                                                                           Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;Progress Report   Annex 1: Country Stories July 1­December 31, 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      activities by allocating financial resources, includ-           3. Highlights for the Reporting Period&#13;
      ing HWWS messages in their promotions, and in-                  Scaling Up&#13;
      cluding HWWS in corporate social responsibility                    · During the last six months, our efforts on the scal-&#13;
      programs?                                                            ing up component have been focused primarily on:&#13;
    · How to develop durable, low-cost, and culturally-                    1) improving the interpersonal communications ac-&#13;
      appropriate HW technologies such as soap holders/                    tivities and preparing for the expansion of HWWS&#13;
      dispensers, customized washing basins, etc.?                         activities in 240 new communes and 2) development&#13;
    · How to improve the link between below-the-line                       of a HWWS program to reach children through&#13;
      communication activities (i.e., IPC and DCC) and                     multiple channels including television, a children's&#13;
      mass media?                                                          magazine, and interpersonal communications;&#13;
    · How to create and sustain relevant capacities to                   · Training programs for adults have been completed&#13;
      train, supervise and monitor HWWS activities in                      in the four non-Impact Evaluation provinces and&#13;
      the communities and replicating their experiences to                 activities have begun in those provinces;&#13;
      other districts?                                                   · Training courses for the children's program have&#13;
                                                                           been completed.&#13;
6. Area of Focus for Next Six Months&#13;
    · Refresh creative and communication materials to                 Sustainability&#13;
      strengthen link mass media activities and messages                 · A Memorandum of Understanding has been signed&#13;
      with the below-the-line (in particular, interpersonal)               between the World Bank and the Vietnam Women's&#13;
      communication activities;                                            Union that provides a mandate for mainstreaming&#13;
    · Increase and refine monitoring activities, ensure all                of HWWS activities in all 63 provinces in Vietnam;&#13;
      forms are completed, collected, and input within ac-               · At a regional level, two enabling environment kick-&#13;
      ceptable timeframe;                                                  off workshops have been carried out with Women's&#13;
    · Capture and document learning from implementa-                       Union representatives in almost all 63 provinces to&#13;
      tion and enabling environment;                                       introduce HWI and discuss ways that WSP and the&#13;
    · Continue supporting project districts to help other                  central Women's Union can assist the provinces to&#13;
      districts;                                                           integrate HWWS into provincial activities;&#13;
    · Work with government to evaluate and improve                       · Both the Ministry of Health (MoH) and the Minis-&#13;
      planning and implementation guidelines;                              try of Education and Training (MoET) were involved&#13;
    · Identify and recruit more private sector partners to                 in the production of the children's program and both&#13;
      support HWWS with promotional materials, fund-                       ministries have both endorsed the program.&#13;
      ing for additional air time, and outdoor rentals.&#13;
                                                                      Replication&#13;
Vietnam Country Story                                                    · Training and support to other programs to integrate&#13;
1. Project Description                                                     and replicate HWWS activities into water and sani-&#13;
The Vietnam Handwashing Initiative is an integrated pro-                   tation programs continued during this reporting pe-&#13;
gram promoting handwashing with soap in women of re-                       riod, including:&#13;
productive age, caretakers and primary school aged children                · WSP supported six training courses in HWWS&#13;
targeting 600 communes in 12 provinces throughout                              in three provinces (Phu Yen, Dak Nong, and Tra&#13;
Vietnam.                                                                       Vinh) within the National Target Program;&#13;
                                                                           · WSP provided materials and training to integrate&#13;
2. Intended Project Outcome                                                    HWWS into activities in two provinces (Thai&#13;
Stimulate and sustain 2.2 million women, caretakers, and                       Binh and Hai Duong) within the Red River&#13;
primary school aged children to wash their hands with soap                     Delta Rural Water Supply and Sanitation Project,&#13;
at critical times (i.e., after defecation, before eating).                     a World Bank investment project.&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                  21&#13;
&amp;#12;     Progress Report   Annex 1: Country Stories July 1­December 31, 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     4. Newly Emerging Questions                                               into health, food safety, and water and sanitation&#13;
     With a better monitoring tool, would we be able to deter-                 activities;&#13;
     mine the performance of our interventions--in terms of                ·   Harvest lessons learned from the implementation of&#13;
     exposure and its effective on changing the key determinants               a large scale hygiene program from the provincial to&#13;
     of the HWWS--as well as to quantify the resultant behav-                  central levels and producing a learning product to&#13;
     ior change in our project areas?                                          share learning;&#13;
                                                                           ·   Roll out mass media for caretaker's program and pre-&#13;
     5. Area of Focus for Next Six Months                                      pare for DCC activities;&#13;
     The HW team will be focusing our efforts on enabling en-              ·   Provide oversight and technical assistance to the&#13;
     vironment and learning components of the program in the                   provinces, in particular the new communes added&#13;
     next six months including:                                                in Phase II, to ensure that activities are on time and&#13;
         · Increase MoET's willingness to mainstream the chil-                 carried out with quality, as we have done with the&#13;
            dren's program into the national curriculum through                original 260 communes;&#13;
            a workshop (organized by the Women's Union) that               ·   Extend network of partners and build the enabling&#13;
            would introduce the program to larger number of                    environment by organizing integration kickoff&#13;
            MoET's representatives;                                            workshops to engage the Ministry of Agriculture and&#13;
         · Develop Integration Toolkit with practical guidelines               Rural Development in HWI.&#13;
            on how to integrate or improve HWWS messages&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
22                                                                                                         Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                               Am&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                               0&#13;
                                                                                                                                                   5,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                                           10,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                    15,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                             20,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                      25,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                               30,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                        35,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                 40,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                  az&#13;
                                                                                                                                     o&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                  A na&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                Progress Report&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                Ar nca s&#13;
                                                                                                                              C    eq sh&#13;
                                                                                                                                aj ui&#13;
                                                                                                                                  am p&#13;
                                                                                                                                      a a&#13;
                                                                                                                                   C rc&#13;
                                                                                                                                H us a&#13;
                                                                                                                                  ua co&#13;
                                                                                                                                     nu&#13;
                                                                                                                                         co&#13;
                                                                                                                                       I&#13;
                                                                                                                              La J CA&#13;
                                                                                                                            La li un&#13;
                                                                                                                              m be in&#13;
                                                                                                                                ba rta&#13;
                                                                                                                                    ye d&#13;
                                                                                                                                       q&#13;
                                                                                                                              M L ue&#13;
                                                                                                                                oq im&#13;
                                                                                                                                   ue a&#13;
                                                                                                                                       gu&#13;
                                                                                                                                     Pi a&#13;
                 Am                                                                                                                     u&#13;
                                                                                                                                     P ra&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  0&#13;
                                      500&#13;
                                            1,000&#13;
                                                    1,500&#13;
                                                            2,000&#13;
                                                                    2,500&#13;
                                                                            3,000&#13;
                     az&#13;
                        o                                                                                                        Tu un&#13;
                     An nas                                                                                                    Ap mb o&#13;
                  Ap ca                                                                                                            u e&#13;
                      u s                                                                                                   H Ay rim s&#13;
                                                                                                                             ua ac a&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                Annex 2: Additional Reach Graphs­Peru&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   Ar rim h                                                                                                    nc uc c&#13;
                      e a                                                                                                     Sa ave ho&#13;
                  Ay qu c&#13;
                           i                                                                                                      nm lic&#13;
                 C acu pa                                                                                                             ar a&#13;
                   aj c&#13;
                     am ho                                                                                                          Ta tin&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                          FIGURE 2A: TARGET POPULATION REACHED BY IPC&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              H          a                                                                                                             cn&#13;
                ua C rca                                                                                                                  a&#13;
                  nc us&#13;
                     a co&#13;
                   H veli&#13;
                     ua ca&#13;
                        nu&#13;
                             co&#13;
                          IC&#13;
                        J A&#13;
              La Lali un&#13;
                 m be in&#13;
                   ba rta&#13;
                       ye d&#13;
                         q                                                                                                     Am&#13;
                                                                                                                                               0&#13;
                                                                                                                                                   5,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                                           10,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                    15,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                             20,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                      25,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                               30,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                        35,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                 40,000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 M L ue                                                                                                            az&#13;
                   oq im                                                                                                              o&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    FIGURE 2C: FRONT LINE WORKERS TRAINED&#13;
                       ue a                                                                                                        An na&#13;
                         gu                                                                                                      Ar ca s&#13;
                        Pi a                                                                                                   C equ sh&#13;
                           u                                                                                                     aj ip&#13;
                                                                                                                                   am a&#13;
                        Pu ra                                                                                                         a&#13;
                       Ta no                                                                                                        C rc&#13;
                                                                                                                                 H us a&#13;
                    Tu cn                                                                                                          ua c&#13;
                       m a                                                                                                           nu o&#13;
                          be                                                                                                              co&#13;
                              s                                                                                                        IC&#13;
                                                                                                                                La Ju A&#13;
                                                                                                                            La lib n&#13;
                                                                                                                               m e in&#13;
                                                                                                                                 ba rta&#13;
                                                                                                                                    ye d&#13;
                                                                                                                                       qu&#13;
                                                                                                                                     Li e&#13;
                                                                                                                                         m&#13;
                                                                                                                                     Pi a&#13;
                                                                                                                                        ur&#13;
                                                                                                                                     P a&#13;
                                                                                                                                  Tu un&#13;
                                                                                                                            H   Ap mb o&#13;
                                                                                                                              ua ur es&#13;
                                                                                                                                nc im&#13;
                                                                                                                                   a a&#13;
                                                                                                                                Ay ve c&#13;
                                                                                                                                        l&#13;
                                                                                                                               M acu ica&#13;
                                                                                                                                 oq c&#13;
                                                                                                                                    ue ho&#13;
                                                                                                                                       g&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        Annex 2: Additional Reach Graphs­Peru&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                    Ta ua&#13;
                                                                                                                                       cn&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                          FIGURE 2B: TARGET POPULATION REACHED BY DCC&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                           a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
23&#13;
&amp;#12;     Progress Report   Annex 3: Timeline of Endline Studies&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Annex 3: Timeline of Endline Studies&#13;
                                            2010                                            2011&#13;
                                           Jan Feb Mar Apr May Jun Jul Aug Sep Oct Nov Dec Jan Feb Mar Apr May Jun Jul Aug Sep Oct Nov Dec&#13;
      Peru              Baseline&#13;
                        Longitudinal&#13;
                        Endline&#13;
      India             Baseline&#13;
                        Longitudinal&#13;
                        Endline&#13;
      Senegal           Baseline&#13;
                        Longitudinal&#13;
                        Endline&#13;
      Tanzania          Baseline&#13;
                        Longitudinal&#13;
                        Endline&#13;
      Indonesia         Baseline&#13;
                        Longitudinal&#13;
                        Endline&#13;
      Vietnam           Baseline&#13;
                        Longitudinal&#13;
                        Endline&#13;
&#13;
                                                          Longitudinal surveys&#13;
                                                          Endline surveys&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
24                                                                                                               Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="12840757">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2009/12/12840757/peru-senegal-tanzania-vietnam-global-scaling-up-handwashing-project-progress-report-july-1-december-31-2009
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2009/12/12840757/peru-senegal-tanzania-vietnam-global-scaling-up-handwashing-project-progress-report-july-1-december-31-2009</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2009/12/12840757/peru-senegal-tanzania-vietnam-global-scaling-up-handwashing-project-progress-report-july-1-december-31-2009</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-10-07T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2010/10/07/000333037_20101007020834/Rendered/INDEX/569490WP0Progr101public10BOX353742B.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2010/10/07/000333037_20101007020834/Rendered/PDF/569490WP0Progr101public10BOX353742B.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2010-10-07T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2009-12-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Peru, Senegal, Tanzania, and Vietnam -
            Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project : progress report
            (July 1-December 31, 2009)
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This reporting period marks the
            beginning of the final year of implementation of the Global
            Scaling up Handwashing with Soap (HWWS) project. It
            represents a critical phase, a time for the teams not only
            to continue intensifying behavior change interventions, but
            also to establish HWWS promotion as a central component in
            national and local efforts to improve children's health
            and nutrition in Peru, Senegal, Tanzania, and Vietnam. The
            project is also on track in strengthening the enabling
            environment to help sustain HWWS interventions beyond the
            life of the project. Notable progress has been made around
            efforts to integrate HWWS activities into existing national,
            regional and local programs and services, to replicate the
            approach within and outside the four countries, and to
            secure national and local-level funding for HWWS activities.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Peru, Senegal, Tanzania, and Vietnam -
            Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project : progress report
            (July 1-December 31, 2009)
        </docna>
        <display_title>Peru, Senegal, Tanzania, and
            Vietnam - Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project : progress
            report (July 1-December 31, 2009)</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2009/12/12840757/peru-senegal-tanzania-vietnam-global-scaling-up-handwashing-project-progress-report-july-1-december-31-2009</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,ICT Policy and Strategies,Primary Education,E-Business,Population Policies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Private Sector Development,Information and Communication Technologies,Health, Nutrition and Population,Education</teratopic>
        <count>Peru,Senegal,Tanzania,Vietnam</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Perez, Eduardo</author>
            <author>Hnin Pyne, Hnin</author>
            <author>Amelink, Catherine</author>
            <author>Paynter, Nathaniel</author>
            <author>Briceno, Bertha</author>
            <author>Cardosi, Jason</author>
            <author>Coombes, Yolande</author>
            <author>Florez de Cilloniz, Rocio</author>
            <author>Devine, Jacqueline</author>
            <author>Frischmuth, Christiane</author>
            <author>Grossman, Amy</author>
            <author>Kullmann, Craig</author>
            <author>Nguyen, Nga Kim</author>
            <author>Koita, Seydou</author>
            <author>Badru, Abdul</author>
            <author>Orsola-Vidal, Alexandra</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southeast Asia!$!80471</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South America!$!80469</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sahel!$!80468</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>West Africa!$!80474</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Africa!$!80458</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20101007020834</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Africa,Africa,East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Water and Sanitation Program : progress report</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Private Sector Development,Information and Communication Technologies,Health, Nutrition and Population,Education</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            aged, behavior change, Bi, broadcast,
            broadcasts, Bulletin, business development, capacity
            building, caregivers, Child Survival, civil society
            organizations, classrooms, collaboration, communication
            activities, communication campaign, communication channels,
            community development, curricular activities, customs, data
            analysis, data collection, data entry, development of
            knowledge, dissemination, education materials, Education
            Programs, educational activities, enabling environment,
            environmental impact, exercises, families, family members,
            financial resources, Global Development, good governance,
            health centers, health outcomes, health promotion, home
            page, household level, human development, hygiene, impact
            assessment, implementing agencies, implementing agency,
            Infectious Diseases, Information System, information
            systems, institutional capacity, institutionalization,
            international organizations, interpersonal communication,
            interpersonal communications, intervention, interventions,
            inventory, kids, Knowledge Management, knowledge product,
            knowledge products, Knowledge sharing, leadership, learning,
            legal status, local authorities, local governments, local
            municipalities, Management System, manuals, market places,
            Marketing, mass media, material, Ministries of Health,
            Ministry of Education, Ministry of Health, national
            government, national governments, national level, national
            levels, national policy, nutrition, nutritional status,
            opportunities for women, outreach activities, outreach
            workers, Performance Indicator, physical presence, poor
            health, Practitioners, primary school, primary school
            teachers, primary school-aged children, primary schools,
            Private Partnership, private sector, procurement, product
            development, production process, Programming, PROGRESS,
            Project Management, quality assurance, radio, radio
            stations, regional policy, religious beliefs, reproductive
            age, Reproductive Health, result, results, Rural
            Development, SANITATION, school curriculum, School Health,
            service delivery, silos, Social Development, social
            networks, social norms, social programs, Social Welfare,
            supervision, sustainable access, targets, teachers,
            technical assistance, technical skills, technical staff,
            technical support, television, time periods, tracking
            systems, Training courses, training of teachers, Training
            programs, transportation, TV, user, user preferences, uses,
            verification, videos, virus, Web, Web page, Web site, workers
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water- Water and Sanit Prgrm (GWASP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>Southeast Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sahel</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>West Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>56949</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Behavior Change Communication</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Randomized Control Trials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Reproductive Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Reproductive and Women's Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Community Based Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Raising Awareness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tracking Performance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Reproductive and Maternal Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Knowledge Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>