<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                                                                                                                 58575&#13;
 NOTE NUmBER 324&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                          viewpoint                                         PUBLIC POLICY FOR THE PRIVATE SECTOR&#13;
SEPTEmBER 2010&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                       New Firm Creation&#13;
 FINANCIAL AND PRIVATE SECTOR DEVELOPMENT VICE PRESIDENCY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            Leora Klapper and          What Has Been the Effect of the Financial Crisis?&#13;
                                                            Inessa Love&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                       N ew d at a f r o m t h e Wo r l d B a n k G r o u p E n t r e p r e n e u r s h i p S n a p s h ot s&#13;
                                                            Leora Klapper&#13;
                                                            (lklapper@worldbank.org)   s h ow t h at n ew b u s i n e s s e s a r e c r e at e d at a f a s t e r r at e i n c o u n t r i e s&#13;
                                                            and Inessa Love            w i t h g o o d g ove r n a n c e , a s t r o n g l e g a l a n d r e g u l at o r y e nv i r o n m e n t ,&#13;
                                                            (ilove@worldbank.org)&#13;
                                                            are senior economists&#13;
                                                                                       l ow c o r p o r at e t a xe s , a n d l e s s r e d t a p e . T h e d at a a l s o s h ow t h at&#13;
                                                            in the World Bank's        nearly all countries experienced a sharp drop in business entr y&#13;
                                                            Development Research&#13;
                                                                                       d u r i n g t h e f i n a n c i a l c r i s i s . T h e d e c l i n e i n n ew f i r m c r e at i o n w a s&#13;
                                                            Group.&#13;
                                                                                       f a s t e r a n d m o r e s eve r e i n c o u n t r i e s h i t h a r d e r by t h e c r i s i s .&#13;
                                                            More information on&#13;
                                                            the World Bank Group       Entrepreneurial activity can help economic                  the survey--the highest number yet--including&#13;
                                                            Entrepreneurship           growth. For evidence of the economic power of               20 for the first time. The data can help answer&#13;
                                                            Snapshots, as well as      entrepreneurship, we need look no further than              such questions as these:&#13;
                                                            complete data, can be      the United States, where young firms have been               What is the relationship between entrepre-&#13;
                                                            found at http://econ       shown to be a more important source of net job                 neurship and the business environment and&#13;
                                                            .worldbank.org/research/   creation than incumbent firms (Haltiwanger,                    financial development?&#13;
                                                            entrepreneurship.          Jarmin, and Miranda 2009). As millions around                How much did the financial crisis affect&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                       the world feel the impact of the financial crisis              entrepreneurial activity in the formal sector?&#13;
                                                                                       through slower economic growth and job losses,               What factors determine how severely the cri-&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                       understanding regulatory and policy con-                       sis affected new firm creation?&#13;
                                                                                       straints on entrepreneurs wanting to start a for-              The main variable of interest is entry density,&#13;
THE WORLD BANK GROUP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                       mal business has never been more important.                 defined as the number of newly registered cor-&#13;
                                                                                          To measure entrepreneurial activity, a 2010              porations per 1,000 working-age people (those&#13;
                                                                                       survey, the World Bank Group Entrepreneurship               ages 15­64). As in the World Bank's annual&#13;
                                                                                       Snapshots (WBGES), has collected annual data                Doing Business report, the units of measurement&#13;
                                                                                       directly from company registrars on the num-                are private, formal sector companies with lim-&#13;
                                                                                       ber of newly registered firms over the period               ited liability.&#13;
                                                                                       2004­09. The 2010 WBGES builds on earlier&#13;
                                                                                       editions of the data and incorporates improve-              Entry density&#13;
                                                                                       ments in methodology and data from more                     As expected, there is large variation in entry den-&#13;
                                                                                       low-income countries, notably in Sub-Saharan                sity, across both regions and income levels (figure&#13;
                                                                                       Africa. This year 112 countries participated in             1).1 On average, in high-income countries about&#13;
&amp;#12;NEW FiRm CREATiON WhAT hAS BEEN ThE EFFECT OF ThE FINANCIAL CRISIS?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure     Entry density by region, average, 2004­ 09                                                                   four new limited liability firms register annu-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1&#13;
                                                                                                                        ally per 1,000 working-age people; in low- and&#13;
             5&#13;
                                                                                                                        middle-income countries, less than one. Among&#13;
                                                                                                                        developing regions, Europe and Central Asia has&#13;
             4                                                                                                          the highest average entry density (2.26), and Sub-&#13;
                                                                                                                        Saharan Africa and the Middle East and North&#13;
             3                                                                                                          Africa the lowest (0.58 and 0.63). The entry den-&#13;
                                                                                                                        sities translate roughly into national averages of&#13;
             2                                                                                                          55,000 newly registered limited liability firms a&#13;
                                                                                                                        year among high-income countries and about&#13;
                                                                                                                        35,000 in Latin America, 14,000 in South Asia,&#13;
             1&#13;
                                                                                                                        and 9,000 in Sub-Saharan Africa.&#13;
                                                                                                                            Consistent with earlier studies, the data show&#13;
             0&#13;
                                                                                                                        that countries that have higher GDP per capita&#13;
                      High        East Asia &amp;      Europe &amp;      Latin America    Middle East &amp;   South   Sub-Saharan&#13;
                    income          Pacific       Central Asia    &amp; Caribbean      North Africa    Asia      Africa     and greater financial development also have&#13;
                                                                                                                        higher entry density (figure 2).&#13;
         Source: WBGES, 2010 edition.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure     Entry density, income level, and financial development, average, 2004­ 09                                    The business environment and&#13;
                                                                                                                        entrepreneurship&#13;
&#13;
2&#13;
             Entry density&#13;
             5&#13;
                                                                                                                        Two Doing Business indicators on starting a&#13;
                                                                                                                        business show the impact of the business envi-&#13;
                                                                                                                        ronment and barriers to entry on new firm&#13;
             4&#13;
                                                                                                                        registration. The first indicator, cost to start a&#13;
                                                                                                                        business, captures all official fees and fees for&#13;
             3                                                                                                          legal and professional services involved in incor-&#13;
                                                                                                                        porating a company and is measured as a per-&#13;
             2                                                                                                          centage of the economy's gross national income&#13;
                                                                                                                        (GNI) per capita. The second measures the pro-&#13;
                                                                                                                        cedures necessary to start a business. There is a&#13;
             1&#13;
                                                                                                                        strong negative correlation between both these&#13;
                                                                                                                        measures and entry density (figure 3).&#13;
             0&#13;
                       Lowest                                                                             Highest&#13;
                                                                                                                            A formal econometric analysis extends these&#13;
                                        Countries ranked by GDP per capita (2000 US$), quintiles                        simple correlations. To ensure that a better busi-&#13;
                                                                                                                        ness environment is related to subsequent busi-&#13;
             Entry density&#13;
                                                                                                                        ness registration, the cross-country regressions&#13;
             5                                                                                                          average new registrations over 2005­09 and use&#13;
                                                                                                                        the business environment variables from 2004&#13;
             4&#13;
                                                                                                                        as controls. The results show that the initial busi-&#13;
                                                                                                                        ness environment is important for subsequent&#13;
                                                                                                                        new business registrations, which suggests a&#13;
             3&#13;
                                                                                                                        causal relationship. In addition, to ensure that&#13;
                                                                                                                        the results are driven by the business environ-&#13;
             2                                                                                                          ment rather than the overall level of develop-&#13;
                                                                                                                        ment in a country, the analysis controls for GDP&#13;
             1                                                                                                          per capita--which is also significantly and posi-&#13;
                                                                                                                        tively related to entry density (see figure 2). The&#13;
             0                                                                                                          Doing Business indicators remain significant pre-&#13;
                       Lowest                                                                             Highest       dictors of entry density.2&#13;
            Countries ranked by level of financial development (measured by domestic credit as % of GDP), quintiles         To consider the overall economic, politi-&#13;
         Source: WBGES, 2010 edition; World Bank, World Development Indicators database.&#13;
                                                                                                                        cal, and financial conditions of the surveyed&#13;
                                                                                                                        countries over time, the analysis compares&#13;
&amp;#12;entry density with measures of country-level            Figure     Entry density and cost and procedures to start a business, average, 2004­ 09&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        3&#13;
governance. Results show a positive correla-                        Entry density&#13;
tion between entry density and the governance                       6&#13;
&#13;
composite index from Kaufmann, Kraay, and&#13;
                                                                    5&#13;
Mastruzzi (2008). Breaking this index down into&#13;
its subcomponents reveals that the most signifi-&#13;
                                                                    4&#13;
cant factors affecting new business creation are&#13;
regulatory quality and government effectiveness.&#13;
                                                                    3&#13;
Using data from KPMG, the analysis also com-&#13;
pares entry density with the corporate tax rate                     2&#13;
for 77 countries. This shows a negative correla-&#13;
tion between new firm creation and the tax rate.                    1&#13;
The relationships between entry density and&#13;
both governance and the tax rate are statistically                  0&#13;
significant even after controlling for the income                              Lowest                                                                                      Highest&#13;
&#13;
level of the country in a multivariate econometric                                 Countries ranked by cost to start a business (% of GNI per capita), quintiles&#13;
analysis (Klapper and Love forthcoming).&#13;
                                                                    Entry density&#13;
                                                                    6&#13;
The crisis and entrepreneurship&#13;
Data for 95 countries show that nearly all experi-&#13;
                                                                    5&#13;
enced a sharp drop in business entry during the&#13;
crisis (figure 4). Only 20 percent experienced                      4&#13;
growth in business entry between 2008 and&#13;
2009, while 74 percent did between 2006 and                         3&#13;
2007. In general, the speed and intensity with&#13;
which the crisis affected new firm creation var-                    2&#13;
ied by income level and crisis intensity. Richer&#13;
countries, which were more exposed to the                           1&#13;
global financial system, experienced economi-&#13;
cally meaningful drops in business entry in both                    0&#13;
                                                                               Fewest                                                                                          Most&#13;
2008 and 2009. Low-income countries, which&#13;
                                                                                            Countries ranked by procedures to start a business, quintiles&#13;
were less affected by the crisis and introduced&#13;
many reforms modernizing registration, experi-                   Source: WBGES, 2010 edition; World Bank, Doing Business database and World Development Indicators database.&#13;
&#13;
enced no changes in new firm creation. In Spain,&#13;
for example, the number of new firms register-          Figure     Entry density by country income group, 2004­ 09&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        4&#13;
ing dropped by 45 percent, from 145,593 in 2007&#13;
                                                                     6&#13;
to 79,759 in 2009. In Burkina Faso, which intro-&#13;
duced a one-stop shop for registration as part of&#13;
                                                                     5&#13;
a larger reform package, new firm registrations&#13;
increased from 581 in 2007 to 610 in 2009. A                                                                                                                       High income&#13;
                                                                     4&#13;
similar pattern holds for the annual percentage&#13;
change in new firm registrations over time.                          3&#13;
    An important question is whether the crisis&#13;
affected business entry in some countries more                                                                                                     Upper middle income&#13;
                                                                     2&#13;
severely than others. An econometric analysis con-&#13;
                                                                                                                                                          Lower middle income&#13;
firms that countries with higher GDP per capita                      1&#13;
experienced sharper declines in new registrations&#13;
                                                                     0                                                                                             Low income&#13;
during the crisis. This is expected, since the crisis&#13;
                                                                              2004               2005               2006               2007               2008                 2009&#13;
originated primarily in high-income countries.&#13;
Countries in which financial markets play a larger               Source: WBGES, 2010 edition.&#13;
part in the domestic economy (as measured by the&#13;
&amp;#12;NEW FiRm CREATiON WhAT hAS BEEN ThE EFFECT OF ThE FINANCIAL CRISIS?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ratio of domestic credit to GDP) also experienced                             Conclusion&#13;
sharper contractions in new firm creation. One                                The 2010 WBGES data show that dynamic busi-&#13;
plausible channel for this is through firms' access                           ness creation occurs in countries that provide&#13;
to external finance, which is more important in                               entrepreneurs with good governance, a strong&#13;
countries with higher levels of financial develop-                            legal and regulatory environment, and less red             viewpoint&#13;
ment. This channel suggests that countries where                              tape. The data also show that nearly all countries&#13;
start-ups rely more on the banking sector were                                experienced a sharp drop in business entry dur-&#13;
more likely to experience larger contractions in                              ing the financial crisis. But high-income countries        is an open forum to&#13;
new firm creation as a result of the credit crunch                            experienced faster and more severe effects than            encourage dissemination of&#13;
and withdrawal of finance that characterized the                              other income groups. The degree to which the cri-          public policy innovations&#13;
crisis. The analysis also reveals that the ratio of                           sis affected new firm creation is correlated with          for private sector­led and&#13;
domestic credit to GDP is a more powerful predic-                             measures of the severity of the crisis. And countries      market-based solutions for&#13;
tor of the impact of the crisis on new firm creation                          in which financial markets play a larger part in the       development. The views&#13;
than GDP per capita--a notable result, given the                              domestic economy experienced sharper declines              published are those of the&#13;
high correlation between the two measures of                                  in new business registrations. These results can           authors and should not be&#13;
development (Klapper and Love forthcoming).                                   help guide effective policy making and deliver new         attributed to the World&#13;
    The degree to which the crisis affected new                               capabilities for identifying the impact of reforms.        Bank or any other affiliated&#13;
firm creation is highly correlated with measures                                                                                         organizations. Nor do any&#13;
of the severity of the crisis. Using an index from                                                                                       of the conclusions represent&#13;
&#13;
Calderon and Didier (2009) that measures the                                                                                             official policy of the World&#13;
&#13;
crisis-related turbulence in 65 countries (with                               Notes                                                      Bank or of its Executive&#13;
&#13;
lower numbers indicating greater effects from                                 1. Countries classified by the International Monetary      Directors or the countries&#13;
&#13;
the crisis), the analysis shows that countries                                Fund as offshore financial centers are excluded from       they represent.&#13;
&#13;
that were hit harder by the crisis also had larger                            the analysis. For a complete list, go to http://www.imf&#13;
                                                                                                                                         To order additional copies&#13;
shocks to new firm creation (figure 5). For                                   .org/external/np/mae/oshore/2000/eng/back.htm.&#13;
                                                                                                                                         contact Suzanne Smith,&#13;
example, Brazil and Morocco, which were less                                  2. The analysis shows that three other Doing Business&#13;
                                                                                                                                         managing editor,&#13;
affected by the crisis, experienced no decline in                             indicators--time to start a business, cost to close a&#13;
                                                                                                                                         Room F 4K-206,&#13;
new firm creation. But Bulgaria and Lithuania,                                business, and an employment rigidity index--are also&#13;
                                                                                                                                         The World Bank,&#13;
among those most affected because of the near                                 significant predictors of entry density.&#13;
                                                                                                                                         1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
collapse of their financial markets, saw a drastic&#13;
                                                                                                                                         Washington, DC 20433.&#13;
drop in new firm creation.                                                    References&#13;
                                                                              Calderon, Cesar, and Tatiana Didier. 2009. "Severity of&#13;
                                                                                                                                         Telephone:&#13;
                                                                                 the Crisis and Its Transmission Channels." LCR Cri-&#13;
                                                                                                                                         001 202 458 7281&#13;
Figure     Growth in new firms and severity of the crisis                        sis Briefs Series, Latin America and the Caribbean      Fax:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5&#13;
                                                                                 Region, World Bank, Washington, DC.                     001 202 522 3480&#13;
           Growth in new firms, 2007­09 (%)&#13;
           60                                                                 Haltiwanger, John, Ron Jarmin, and Javier Miranda.         Email:&#13;
                                                                                 2009. "Jobs Created from Business Startups in the       ssmith7@worldbank.org&#13;
           40                                                                    United States." Kauffman Foundation Working&#13;
                                                                                 Paper. http://www.kauffman.org/.                        Produced by Communications&#13;
           20                                              Brazil             Kaufmann, Daniel, Aart Kraay, and Massimo Mastruzzi.       Development Incorporated&#13;
                                                     Morocco&#13;
                                                                                 2008. "Governance Matters VII: Aggregate and&#13;
            0                                                                    Individual Governance Indicators, 1996­2007."           Printed on recycled paper&#13;
                      Lithuania                                                  Policy Research Working Paper 4654, World Bank,&#13;
         ­20&#13;
                                                                                 Washington, DC.&#13;
                        Bulgaria                                              Klapper, Leora, and Inessa Love. Forthcoming. "The&#13;
         ­40&#13;
                                                                                 Impact of the Financial Crisis on New Firm Creation."&#13;
                                                                                 Policy Research Working Paper, World Bank, Washing-&#13;
         ­60&#13;
           ­1.5       ­1.0         ­0.5     0.0       0.5         1.0   1.5      ton, DC.&#13;
                                  Crisis turbulence index&#13;
&#13;
         Source: WBGES, 2010 edition; Calderon and Didier 2009.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                       This Note is available online:&#13;
                                                                                        http://rru.worldbank.org/PublicPolicyJournal&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="13264663">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2010/09/13264663/new-firm-creation
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2010/09/13264663/new-firm-creation</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2010/09/13264663/new-firm-creation</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-12-22T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2010/12/22/000334955_20101222021515/Rendered/INDEX/585750VP03241n10BOX353808B01PUBLIC1.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2010/12/22/000334955_20101222021515/Rendered/PDF/585750VP03241n10BOX353808B01PUBLIC1.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2010-09-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2010-12-22T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            New firm creation
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            New data from the World Bank Group
            entrepreneurship snapshots show that new businesses are
            created at a faster rate in countries with good governance,
            a strong legal and regulatory environment, low corporate
            taxes, and less red tape. The data also show that nearly all
            countries experienced a sharp drop in business entry during
            the financial crisis. The decline in new firm creation was
            faster and more severe in countries hit harder by the crisis.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            New firm creation
        </docna>
        <display_title>New firm creation</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2010/09/13264663/new-firm-creation</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Business Environment,E-Business,Competitiveness and Competition Policy,Business in Development,Emerging Markets</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Private Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Klapper, Leora</author>
            <author>Love, Inessa</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000334955_20101222021515</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>View point ; no. 324</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Private Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            barriers to entry, business creation,
            business entry, business environment, Business indicators,
            business registration, business registrations, capabilities,
            Communications Development, corporate tax, domestic economy,
            economic power, external finance, Financial Crisis,
            financial development, financial markets, financial system,
            global financial system, good governance, Governance
            Indicators, income, income group, income groups,
            innovations, job creation, low-income countries,
            middle-income countries, one-stop shop, PRIVATE SECTOR,
            PRIVATE SECTOR DEVELOPMENT, PUBLIC POLICY, red tape,
            regulatory environment, result, results, Startups, tax rate,
            Telephone, Transmission, World Development Indicators
        </keywd>
        <owner>DECRG: Finance &amp; Priv Sec Devt (DECFP)</owner>
        <repnb>58575</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Registration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Regulation for Enterprise Creation and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulation and Business Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Competitiveness and Competition Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Microeconomic and Market Reforms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>AGIs (Actionable Governance Indicators)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Measures of Government Effectiveness, Capacity, Authority, Legitimacy, Legal Framework, Regulations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measures and Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>Econometrics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Environments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Entry and Startup</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Competition Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>