<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>22406&#13;
view point&#13;
Utility Benchmarking&#13;
Bill Kingdon and Vijay   Public  Reporting  of Service  Performance&#13;
Jagannathan&#13;
In some countries regulators routinely publish indicators of utility&#13;
Bill Kingdom isaSenior   service performance through  the local media. Exposing the "worst in&#13;
Water and Sanitation&#13;
Specialist at the World  class" has proven to  be a powerful way of pressuring  utilities to&#13;
Bank. He ismanager of    provide better services to  consumers. By focusing political attention&#13;
the World Bank's water&#13;
utility benchmarking     on service quality, benchmarking can also help to  shield  regulators&#13;
programn. Vijay          from  political interference. This Note reviews the requirements for&#13;
Jagannathan is a Lead&#13;
Water and Sanitation     effective benchmarking: choosing indicators that are unambiguous&#13;
Specialist in the East   and verifiable, consistent with  long-term  incentives for good&#13;
Asian Region of the      performance, and easy for the public to  understand.&#13;
WVorld Bank.&#13;
Benchmarking empowers a broad section of             Scorecard for water and sewerage&#13;
civil society to ask why one service provider has    companies in England and Wales,&#13;
achieved demonstrably better performance    Figure 1999-2000&#13;
than another, or why some companies choose to   1            0 50 100 150 200 250 300 350 400&#13;
ignore effluent discharge standards. Mobilizing  I       Anglian&#13;
consumers in this way is likely to lead to           Northumbrian&#13;
demands on the regulated utilities-whether&#13;
private or public-to improve performance.&#13;
Performance benchmarking has become                  Southern&#13;
standard practice in the regulated utilities of      Severn Trent&#13;
England and Wales-with considerable success.            Thames&#13;
There the water and sewerage companies pro-            South West&#13;
vide the regulator, Ofwat, with indicators of ser-      Yorkshire&#13;
vice performance covering water supply (water&#13;
pressure, hosepipe bans, and quality of drinking      Dvir tymru&#13;
water), sewerage service, customer service (num-       North West&#13;
ber of complaints), and environmental impact&#13;
Note: The scorecard is a composie index of performance far water, sewerage, and&#13;
(leakage, pollution incidents). Ofwat publishes     Sourcerw s.&#13;
the   indicators   annuallv'  in   an   easy-to-digest  Stcrm: Ofwat (wwew.ofweat.goe.ukdpdffilesaso2tf5,pdf.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
UTILITY BENCHMARKING PUBLIC REPORTING OF SERVICE PERfORMANCE&#13;
format accompanied by commentary. Figure 1        that enhance specific agency interests-such&#13;
illustrates Ofivat's total "score" for water supply,  as new investment programs-rather than&#13;
sewerage service, and customer-service perform-   those that will benefit consumers.&#13;
ance by U.K. water and sewerage companies.   * Low consumer expectations. In many countries&#13;
These simple performance scorecards have          basic services such as water supply, sanita-&#13;
helped to pressure the "worst in the class" to    tion, and rural electricity have been pro-&#13;
improve their game and allowed the "best in       vided  at subsidized  prices, and  when&#13;
class" to gain reputation.                        consumers are not charged economic costs&#13;
2                               Some developing countries have adopted per-     for services, their tolerance for inefficiency&#13;
formance benchmarking techniques for sinmilar     and poor service increases-"You get what&#13;
purposes-and with similar results. For examiiple,  you pay for!" Only when services are billed&#13;
in Sao Paulo, since the introduction of pollution  at their true economic value do consumiler s&#13;
tests and public reporting of results in 1991, 95  begin responding to differentials in service&#13;
percent of the industries that had been pumping   quality.&#13;
untreated effluents into the river have installed    * Power/iil vested interests. In most counltries the&#13;
waste treatment units to avoid paying fines and   commercial and indtustrial elite have strotig&#13;
seeing their names published. Indonesia's envi-   lobbying powers. Those powers will be used&#13;
ronmental regulatory agency, BAPPEDAL, has        to resist any public reporting system  that&#13;
developed a simple, color-coded rating systen to  threatens to expose poor-even illegal-&#13;
monitor industry compliance with national envi-   practices and lead to increased costs and&#13;
ronmental standards. Publication of the ratings   adverse public sentiment.&#13;
has brought about spectacular improvements in     C fionflicts of interest. Manly monopoly service&#13;
pollution  abatement  (Woorld  Bank  1999).       providers are either public agencies or parts of&#13;
Procuraduria  Federal  de  Proteccion   al        local goverlnment. They not only provide but&#13;
Ambiente, Mexico's environmental enforce-         also regulate services-supposed(ly in the best&#13;
ment agency, announced last year that it would    interests of the consumer. Publicly reporting&#13;
begin to publish information on the environ-      the agency's performance therefore directly&#13;
mental performance of 3,000 industries to pro-    reflects on the action, or inaction, of the local&#13;
vide incentives to reduce contamination. Ratings  or national government. So there is a tendencv&#13;
will inclu(le recommendations on how to achieve   to cover ulp poor performance.&#13;
acceptable environmental performance.          * Culture of underachievement. Ideally, pointing&#13;
the finger at poor performance should be a&#13;
Barriers                                          wake tip call for an institutioni to do better.&#13;
The power of public reporting seems obvious.      In many developing countries, however,&#13;
So why is it not more widespread? Many of the     poor performance is used by institutions to&#13;
reasons stem from the legacy of decades of pub-   justify demands for more resources. Rather&#13;
lic sector operation of utilities, or from the pres-  than  promoting imiproved  performance,&#13;
ence of vested interests antagonistic to public   public reporting can open a floodgate of&#13;
reporting of performance.                         demands from under-achievers.&#13;
* Insufficient data. The performance of public    * Inconsistencies  in  policy framnework.  The&#13;
sector sernce providers is typically not closely  problems of consumer apathy, conflicts of&#13;
monitored by national policymakers and         interest, and other organizational issues&#13;
donor agencies in a format that identifies the  sometimes arise because the basic rtles of a&#13;
best in the class or the underachievers. Data  sector are inconsistent with rational eco-&#13;
are more likely to reflect either broad policy-  nomic principles. In such cases utilities may&#13;
oriented themes or specific information use-   not be able to do much on their own to lift&#13;
ful for public investment purposes. Sectoral   performance. The policy framework within&#13;
agencies may be unwilling to report or         which the sector operates must be reformed&#13;
record information on the extent of under-     so that pricing, investment, financing, and&#13;
achievement, preferring to focus on actions    operational rules will combine to induce pro-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
clucers to provide services that custollmers             Annual performance measures for&#13;
wvant, are willing to pay for, and arc sustain-          three water utilities in Melbourne,&#13;
Box  Australia&#13;
able in the long term.&#13;
1     Water Quality&#13;
Developing the scorecard                                     * Coliform sampling and testing.&#13;
The basis of an effective performance reporting              * Water quality complaints.&#13;
syste no is good data, the right indicators, clear           * Sewage treatment compliance.&#13;
presentation, and credible public debate.                    * Reuse of effluent and biosolids.&#13;
Choose the right indicators                                  Reliability of Service&#13;
Measuirable and meanringfuil indicators of per-              . Interruptions to, and restoration of, supply.&#13;
*Unaccounted-for water.&#13;
formciance should reflect obvious feattores of the           * 5ewer        water.&#13;
product or service so as to allow customers to               * Sewer blockages and spills.&#13;
untlerstanid variations in service perfornmanice               Response times to emergency phone calls.&#13;
between  different entities  and  over  time.                Affordability&#13;
Indicators may foctLs on  quality. efficiency,               * Use of grant relief scheme.&#13;
affordability,  or  comparative  performance.                * Restrictions for nonpayment.&#13;
Some mav be expressed as indexes acdjusted for               * Use of installment payment plans.&#13;
dlifferent operating con(litions.                            * Legal actions.&#13;
In NVictoria, Austr-alia, the Office of the&#13;
Regulator-General (box 1) publishes annLal per-              Customer Service&#13;
Jormance restolts for the three regutlatedl water            * Complaints.&#13;
distriboution coimipanies in MelbouL-ne. The iiidi-       toorce: Melbourne Retail Water and Sewerage tompanies Performance Report,&#13;
cators include water qualitv (for example, tests          January 2000, Off,ce of the Regulator-General Victoria, Australia.&#13;
per 1,OOO coostoilelrs and the percentage of sam-&#13;
ples meeting guoidelines). the number of inter-&#13;
ruptions  in  service, amotont of water not    resuolts. bhut in most countries newspapers, tele-&#13;
accounlted for bv the utilit, response times to    visiont. anti radio are likely to be more effective&#13;
emergency calls, nutmber of complaints, antI   in bringing the messages to the attentioni of the&#13;
need for payment assistance.                          public.&#13;
Indicators should draw on data that are reli-         The sereice provider is not the only entity&#13;
able. relativelv easy to collect (or of stoch impor-    that will be scrutinized  wheni perfoel-larace&#13;
tance that they ought to be collected anyway),    reports are isstoed. The bodv that prepar-es the&#13;
antI not susceptible tom multiple interpretationis.    report moist also be prepared for media atten-&#13;
TlheT should reflect conditions over whiclh the       tion. It miist be sto-e that its commilentarv is fair&#13;
service providers have control. Ioidicators that    and objective, and that it canl publiclv defelnd its&#13;
offer an indlisputable basis forjoodgimnenit are not    analysis if reqosired.&#13;
easy to find. Even the process of measuring              The ptoblicationi ofdata also may tempt some&#13;
some indicators can lead to disputes. For exam-    participating organizations to cheat on their&#13;
pie, of the various methods of estimatinig water    perfornmance rieports. Routinie or random  inde-&#13;
not accounIted for, whlich should be used?            periclent atudits of the processes of compiling&#13;
Performance results nmust be comml1uLnicated       aiad rieportinig data may be required to solve the&#13;
in a way, that will allow the ptublic to snake an     cheatinig problem.&#13;
informed assessment of relative performance&#13;
and gauge realistically  the extenit to which         Who should compile and report results?&#13;
improvements should be expected. Long lists of    If a formal regLulatory agency already exists, it&#13;
indicators are not necessary: theyt will be expen-    should take the lead. Whiere the regulator is also&#13;
sive to prepare and may obscure the message.          the service provider, however, as in the case of&#13;
Resuolts m.ay be publicized in many ways. The      locally provided services, mesponsibility might&#13;
Web is a convernient place to post performance    fall to a specialized IJlUllicipal periformliianlce&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
UTILITY  BENCHMARKING  PUBLIC REPORTING OF SERVICE PERFORMANCE&#13;
monitoring  nnit or to  citizen  groups. The          their poor performance was due to factors&#13;
organization responsible for data collection and      beyond their control. At the other end of the&#13;
reporting  may change over time. A  private    spectrum  "top of class" agencies shotild be&#13;
organization might start an initiative that is later    rewarded for their superior performance.&#13;
adopted  by  government. Bangalore's  non-&#13;
viewpoint&#13;
governmental Public Affairs Centre, for exam-    Conclusion&#13;
ple, produces a scorecard for performance of    By exposing poor performance public reporting&#13;
the city's public services. The group's presenta-    makes service providers more accountable to the&#13;
is an open forum to&#13;
tions are discussed in well-attended town hall    public and thus increases their motivation for                en    forumito&#13;
meetings and followed up by the local media to    improvement-to the benefit of the end user.    encolicy  ination or&#13;
public policy innovations for&#13;
pressure providers to improve services. The           Governmnent and donor agencies can do more to    private sector-led and&#13;
Public Affairs Centre has now taken the initia-    encourage public performance reporting and to             market-based solutions for&#13;
tive to extend its activities and benchmark the       help guide the effective use of scarce resources.    development. The views&#13;
quality of basic services across 22 major states in    "Worst in the class" performance must not be          published are those of the&#13;
India.                                                seen as a rotute to additional resources but rather    authors and should not be&#13;
Consumer advocates and pressure groups    as a clear challenge to do better.                             attributed to the World&#13;
can play a powerftul role in mobilizing public                                                               Bank or any other affiliated&#13;
opinion in response to published information.                                                               organizations. Nor do any of&#13;
Independent analysis lends punch to the data.                                                               the conclusions represent&#13;
The interinational donor commtnity can also           Note                                                   official policy of the World&#13;
help by compiling and presenting comparative               1. The  Benchmarking Water anici Sanfitationi    Bank or of its Executive&#13;
performiance information. In the water sector    Utilities Project facilitates the sharinig of cost and per-    Directors or the countries&#13;
the Asian Development Bank has published a    forynance information between utilities ani between    they represent.&#13;
comprehensive assessment of utility perform-    counitries by creatinig a network of linked Web sites,&#13;
ance  in  its Second  Water Uttilities Data Book    through global partniership eftirts. Each Web site pies-    To order additional copies&#13;
(Mclntosh and Ynigtuez 1997). The WVorld Bank,    ents saluies for a set of core cost and perforuiance idi-    contact Suzanne Smith,&#13;
working with many partners, recently launched         cators for a utility, or utilities, in that partiCLnlar regioll or    managing editor,&#13;
an  international benchmarking  network for    cottntrv. [http:/ /'wr.wworldbank,org/htmiil/fpdt/water/    Room 19-017,&#13;
water and sanitation utilities on1 the Web.'          topics/bench_network.htrnl]                            The World Bank,&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
Create the right incentives                           References                                            Washington, DC 20433.&#13;
The penalties and incentives of perfoirmance               McIntoslh, Arthur- C. and Cesar E. Ynigtuez. 1997.&#13;
reporting are clear enough in the case of private    Serond  I1'oler a Utilities  Data  Book. Manila: Asian    Telephone:&#13;
00 1 202 458 728 1&#13;
providers: Bad press can affect stock prices and      l)evelopment Bank.                                     Fax:&#13;
public perceptions, and good press can boost              Officc  of  the  Regulator-(General  (Vi(ctor-ia,    001 202 522 3 181&#13;
market share and sometimes ease regulatory            Atistralia). 2000. "Melbourne's Water anid Sewer-age   Email:&#13;
hterdens. But because of the institutional prob-    Companies-Peiformnance  Report, jttly  1998-Jine        ssmith7@worldbank.org&#13;
lems discussed earlier the picture is not so clear    1999."  [vsasss'.reggeix.vic.gov.au/ docs'/water/wr(1121000.&#13;
for the public sector. Certainly, doing well can      pdtl.&#13;
earti good ptiblicity. Doing badly, on the other          World Bank. 1999. Greetntig IndustrD: NVezv Roles for    Printed on recycled paper&#13;
hand, can have several outtcomes, incltuding          Communities, ilorkets, and Goverenments. Watshinigton, D.C.&#13;
requests for more resources.&#13;
In the enid the public sector must shoulder    Bill  Kingdom  (tekiogrdom@u'Sorld6bank.org)  and  1`i;oy&#13;
the butrden of addressing how incentives and          agsannatlhan (o/goagoannoilhatozo;ookl6blnk.org).&#13;
penalties can best be arranged to enhance per-&#13;
formance tising the results of public perform-n_&#13;
ance  reports. How?  "Bottom   of the  class"&#13;
agencies seeking concessional financing from&#13;
national government or international financial&#13;
institutions could be requtired to prove that&#13;
This  Note  is  available  online:&#13;
www.worldbank.orglhtmilfpdinotesl&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1346423">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2001/03/1346423/utility-benchmarking-public-reporting-service-performance
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2001/03/1346423/utility-benchmarking-public-reporting-service-performance</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2001/03/1346423/utility-benchmarking-public-reporting-service-performance</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2001/07/13/000094946_01062804082073/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2001/07/13/000094946_01062804082073/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2001-03-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2001-07-28T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Utility benchmarking : public reporting of
            service performance
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In some countries regulators routinely
            publish indicators of utility service performance through
            the local media. Exposing the "worst in class" has
            proven to be a powerful way of pressuring utilities to
            provide better services to consumers. This Note reviews the
            requirements for effective benchmarking: choosing indicators
            that are unambiguous and verifiable, consistent with
            long-term incentives for good performance, and easy for the
            public to understand.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Utility benchmarking : public reporting of
            service performance
        </docna>
        <display_title>Utility benchmarking : public
            reporting of service performance</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2001/03/1346423/utility-benchmarking-public-reporting-service-performance</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Health Economics &amp; Finance,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Water and Industry</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Environment,Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population,Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Kingdom, Bill</author>
            <author>Jagannathan, Vijay</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_01062804082073</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other Water Supply &amp; Sanitation</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 229</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Environment,Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population,Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Water, sanitation and flood protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Benchmark; Performance indicators; Quality
            of service; Disclosure of information; Conflict of
            interests; Interest groups; Public information
            citizen groups,civil society,economic
            value,effective use,effluent discharge
            standards,effluents,environmental impact,environmental
            performance,financing,investment,pollution,pollution
            abatement,private sector,pumping,regulatory
            agency,sanitation utilities,Sectoral performance,service
            provider,service providers,service quality,Sewage
            treatment,sewerage companies,sewerage
            service,town,utilities,Water Quality,water sector,water
            supply,water utilities,water utility
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <repnb>22406</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Policy Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>