<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>22404&#13;
view point&#13;
Regulating Transmission&#13;
Beatriz Arzu, 11illiam      Why System  Operators Must Be Truly Independent&#13;
H. Dunn Jr., and&#13;
Bernard Tenenbautm          Which  is best for effective  competition  in  power sectors, a separate&#13;
transmission system  operator, a joint owner-operator, or some&#13;
B eatriz Arizu is Director&#13;
of Regulatoiry Studies at   combination  of the  two? This question  is being  hotly  debated  among&#13;
lercados Energdticos        power reformers. The answer?  Both  types of system   operators  can  be&#13;
Buenos Aires, Argentina.&#13;
She has been involved in    made  to  work, singly  or in  combination. What is critical is that the&#13;
establishing transmission   system   operators  be  truly  independent of ownership  and  control by&#13;
system operators and&#13;
power markets in more       market participants-generators, distributors, and  suppliers. But in&#13;
than 10 coutntries.         many  countries  they  have  not been.&#13;
William H. Dunnn r. is&#13;
Vice President of Barker,   Over the past 10 years separate transmission sys-           The job of the transmission system&#13;
Dunn a Rossi, Fairfax,                                                                  Telbo  h   rnmsinsse&#13;
Dunn &amp;Rossi, Fairfax.     tem  operators ("TSOs") have been created or           Box  operator&#13;
Virginia. He has helped     proposed in more than 30 countries reforming&#13;
transmission sestem         their powver sectors. Two kinds of operators dom-           The job of the transmission system operator is to&#13;
transmission sYstem                                         I ~      ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ensure the electrical stability of the interconnected sys-&#13;
operators in Australia,     mate: transcos and independent system opera-                tem so that bulk power can be transported from gen-&#13;
England and Wales, and      tors ("ISOs"). Transcos arejoint owner-operators            erators to distribution networks. The operator-&#13;
the United States.          of the high-voltage grid. Independent system                whether a transco or an independent system&#13;
Bernard Tenenbauno is a     operators are separate operators of grid facilities         operator-provides open access to the transmission&#13;
Principal Energy            owned and maintained by others, such as verti-              system, monitors and controls system operations to&#13;
Specialist at the World     cally integrated power enterprises or stand-alone           ensure a moment-to-moment energy balance, manages&#13;
Bank. Before joining the    o-wners of transmission facilities usually referred         congestion, schedules generation (or reviews the techni-&#13;
Bank, he helped to write   to as wirecos (table 1) 1 To achieve a competitive           cal feasibility of schedules submitted by others),&#13;
the U. S. Feder-al Energy   power sector, a transmission system  operator,              acquires ancillary services such as operating reserves&#13;
Regulatory Commission s     whether a transco or an independent system                  and voltage support, and plans or approves requests&#13;
December 1999 rule on       operator, must act as an impartial policeman, not           for maintenance of transmission and generation facili-&#13;
regional tr-ansmission      as someone's private army.                                  ties. Many system operators also administer spot and&#13;
organpizations.                                                                         real-time balancing energy markets. These operators&#13;
Which kind of operator is best?                         generally perform metering, accounting, settlement, and&#13;
_                   ~~~~~~Which kind of operator Is best?                        biln fo. h mres&#13;
Proponents of independent system  operators&#13;
argue that they are preferable because a transco&#13;
FILE COPY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
REGULATING  TRANSMISSION  WHY SYSTEM OPERATORS MUST BE TRULY INDEPENDENT&#13;
Maintains     Maintains                Owns or leases&#13;
Type of entity                 real-time control  transmission   Controls grid   transmission&#13;
and example                 of system operations     facilities   investments       facilities&#13;
Independent system operator&#13;
Cammesa (Argentina), PJM (U.S.),            *&#13;
ONS (Brazil), NEMMCO (Australia)&#13;
Wireco&#13;
2                                       Transener (Argentina), Transelec (Chile),                 *  &#13;
GPU PowerNet (tictoria, Australia)&#13;
Transco&#13;
National Grid (ompany (England and Wales),  *             *      0                      0&#13;
Statnett (Norway), Polish Power Grid (Poland)&#13;
* Full responsibility. X Shared responsibility.&#13;
Source: Based on unpublished work of Steve Stoft (Unwersity ol talifornia Energy Institute) and tanoyn  Berry o al ina  Economic Research   ssociates).&#13;
will favor its own commercial interests over the    over anotier. Independenice is not jUst a matter&#13;
interests of market participants. They point to    of fairness-it has real conseqtuences. Private&#13;
the difficulties of designing inlcentives to induce    investors will be reluctant to build new genera-&#13;
a transco to minimize the total costs of electric-    tion or distribution facilities or buy existing ones&#13;
ity production rather than just congestion costs.   if they do not believe that the system operator&#13;
They claim that faced with an operating or con-    will be truly independent. Independence has&#13;
gestioni problemn, a transco will almost always    several dimensions.&#13;
choose a solutioni centered on transmission&#13;
(building a new line, for example) even if there    Ownership&#13;
are less costly alternatives (paying a new gener-    Ownership usually convevs control, so there&#13;
ator to build at another location).                 must be restrictions on who ownls the system&#13;
Proponents of transcos clainm that independ-    operator. Ownership restrictions must also go&#13;
ent system operators are inherently inefficient    in the other direction: just as market partici-&#13;
because they are usually nonprofit organiza-    pants canncot have tinanacial interests in the sys-&#13;
tions requiring complex systems of governanice.    tem operator, the system operator cannot have&#13;
They point to the difficulties of writing and    financial interests in market participants.&#13;
enforcing contracts that ensure that an inde-          The first restriction prohibits market partici-&#13;
pendent system  operator will efficiently and    pants from having equity interests in the opera-&#13;
reliably operate transmissioni assets owned by    tor. For example, the corporate charter of the&#13;
others. They argue that transcos are preferable    National (;rid Company, the privately owned&#13;
in the early stages of reform because they are    transco serving England an(d Wales, prohibits&#13;
easier to create from state-owned utilities and     'restricte(d persons" (market participants) from&#13;
may counteract the political power of genera-    owning mnore than 1 percenit of the company's&#13;
tors and distributors.                              voting equity. The second restriction must apply&#13;
No clear-cut evidence has vet emerged that    not only to the operator but also to its directors,&#13;
conclusively supports the arguments of either    managers, and employees.&#13;
group. Properly designed, both types of institu-&#13;
tions can work, singly or in combiniation.          Decisionmaking control&#13;
Control can be achieved even without owner-&#13;
The why and how of independence                     ship if market participants can direct the system&#13;
Key to the success of a transmission system         operator's decisionmaking process. Particularly&#13;
operator-no  matter the type-is independ-    when an operator is a noniprofit or cooperative&#13;
erice from ownership and control by market par-    organization (the typical structures for an inde-&#13;
ticipants, so that the operator does not favor one    pendent system operator), close attention mnust&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
be paid to its governanice-what decisionis are       ent system operator's board has had 25 vot-&#13;
made, whco makes them, how decisions are            ing menibers. Federal atithorities recentix&#13;
enforced, and how disputes arc resolved. The         ordered that it be dissolved because it was too&#13;
key to governance lies in the composition and        large anicl politicizedl.&#13;
voting rulles of the operator-'s governing board.    *  7The voting eldes tust ensure 1l/at onle orar  o c/las ses&#13;
can riot control tIe boards decisions. Rules should&#13;
Governing boards                                     be designed to enstui-e that no one class can&#13;
An operator's governing board can conisist of        block a board action, no two classes can man-&#13;
stakeholders, nonistakelholders, or a combina-       (late board decisions, and no market partici-&#13;
tion of the tvo. The stakeholder board, the          pant can take part in more than one class.&#13;
doininianit model in Latini America, allows each     Until recently thie boarcl of the Chilean&#13;
class of market participants (generators, dis-       market operator  was  limited  to  large&#13;
tributors. suppliers) one or more representa-        generators-virtually  a  cartel-and  each&#13;
tives on  the decisionmaking  board. Board           member hadl veto power. The dominationi by&#13;
memibers are permitted to ctirectlv and openly       large generators was so complete that other&#13;
represent the economic inter-ests of their organ-    market participants did not know the details&#13;
ization or constituenlcy within the operator's       of the board's operational and dispatcl rules.&#13;
regtulatorv frarmework and rules. If n o one enitity    *  '1'1e boardl mii ust have rweal dlecisionniakiang autlio-&#13;
or class can dominate board decisions. inde-        i/v. In Panama the manager of the system&#13;
pendenice can be achieved-an "in)dlependenice        operator locatecl within the transco-both&#13;
through balance of power."                           government owned-was recently removed&#13;
For the nonstakeholder, or "classless," board.    without the approval of the stakeholder&#13;
the dominant modlel in the United States, mem-       boarcl. A board exclucded firom such kes deci-&#13;
bers are choseni to he independent rather than       sions is nmerelv an advisory body.&#13;
to represent stakeholders. Members are prohib-    *  The regulalor 0i.st be alble to step ini and miake a&#13;
itecl fromii having current and soimetimes fuiture iledsion if bo(ard mnemibers are (at a dleadlock. This&#13;
Financial interests in market participants. Board    does not mean that the regulator must for-&#13;
seats may be reserveti for those with particulair    mally approve every board decision or arbi-&#13;
skills (system operations and planninig, finance     trate every dispute. That riequir emenit would&#13;
and accouLntinig, law and regulation). To avoid      slow  relorm, especially  early  on, when&#13;
isolation, the board is usually advised by one or    changes are needcled almost continually. But&#13;
niore conmmilittees of stakeholders.                 the regulator must have the legal riglht to&#13;
A stakeholder board caan be "messy." But for      inters'ene if there is anl appeal by nmarket par-&#13;
countries tiving to privatize and restructure        ticipants or on the regulator's ossin initiative.&#13;
their power sectors it is probably the best          If the governance -sTtelmi is well designed, the&#13;
alternative-for three reasons. First, it gives new   regulator mvill only rarely need to step in, and&#13;
private investors some assuranice that thev will     goverDnmenit  reguLlation  can  be  largely&#13;
be able to influentce decisions that could have a    replaced by industry self-regutlation.&#13;
major financial impact oni their investments.&#13;
Second, finding enough knowledgeable indi-    Functional unbundling-the impossible dream&#13;
VidluislS in the CoLntry who woulcd be perceived    Some refurmers have  proposed  functionial&#13;
as indepenidenit may be impossible. Third, noni-   tnbtulndlinig as a second-best alternative to an&#13;
stakeholders may be susceptible to "icapture"-    indelpenidetnt transmissioni ssstem  operator.&#13;
to bribes or to offers of ftiture employment.     Funictionial unibtumdcling allows the grid operator&#13;
Worltlwide  experience  suggests  seseral   to remaini witlhin a larger power enterpr-ise that&#13;
reqtiiremenits br a successful stakehiolder board:    ownIs generation and dlistributioni facilities, but&#13;
*  7'he boarrd cannot bie too large or it will be ineJfrc-   utses (letailed conduct rules to trs to ensure that&#13;
tine as. a decisionmaking bofdy. Nlost Latin    the grid operator acts as if it were independent.&#13;
American boards are limitedl to 7 or 9 mem-    Thcse rules typically requirc the following:&#13;
bers. In California, however, the indcepenid-    *  Separateaccounits forgridoperations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
_ R EGU LATING  TRANSMISSION  WHY SYSTEM OPERATORS MUST BE TRULY INDEPENDENT&#13;
*  Separate maniagement of grid operations.            knowledgeable people within the couLtry will&#13;
*  Restrictions on information flows between           be perceived, at least initially, as biased because&#13;
the grid operator and other divisions or affil-    of past connections with the indtistiy. Second,&#13;
iates of its parent enterprise.                     the experts must lhavc a broad mandate. They&#13;
*  Nonidiscriminatory provision of transmission        should be charged with assessing not only the          ve&#13;
service to all grid users under a puiblished        perfornmance of the market, but also the per-            i     p&#13;
transmission tariff.                               formanice of the system operator and the regut-&#13;
Ftunctionial unbundlinig has been  tried in    lator. And they should be able to recommiienld    is an open forum to&#13;
Euttope and the United States. But it does not    changes in strticture as well as in rtles.&#13;
work for two reasons. First, it conflicts with the                                                            public policy innovations for&#13;
normilal incenitives of any commercial enterprise      Conclusion                                             private sector-led and&#13;
to try to protect the profits of a parent or affili-    Power sector reform brings different specialists      market-based solucions for&#13;
ated cot)npaniy. In the United States market par-    into close contact-engineers who like to oper-    development. The views&#13;
ticipants  have  widely  alleged  that  system         ate sophisticated  power systems, economists    published are those of che&#13;
operators in vertically  integrated  companies    who like to think about optimal incentives, and             authors and should not be&#13;
have hiur-t conmpetitors by "playing games"-    lawyers who like to write rules and agrcements.    attributed to the World&#13;
issuing biased estimiiates ofavailable tranismissioni    But unless these specialists work together in        Bank or any other affiliated&#13;
capacity, making qttestionable curtailments of    designinlg sustainiable institutions, all of themil    organizations. Nor do any of&#13;
transmission service for "security" reasons, and       will fail at their choseti task. A government that    the conclusions represent&#13;
reserving excessive allocations of transmissioni    wants a co)mpetitive power sector mtist create an         official policy of the World&#13;
import capacitv for themsielves. But proving           independent  transmiiission  system   operator    Bank or of its Executive&#13;
these allegations has been difficult because the       whose decisions are not controlled by market    Directors or the countries&#13;
rules are necessarily general and can be applied       participants. It must also create an institutionial    they represent.&#13;
with discretion.                                       mechanism  that enstires that flawed grid and&#13;
Second, enfor-cinig the rules is virtually impos-    market rules can be chaniged after the initial    To order additional copies&#13;
sible. (Consider the common prohibition against    reforms take effect.                                       contact Suzanne Smith,&#13;
the grid operator sharinig inf)rmation on avail-                                                              managing editor,&#13;
able transmissioni capacity with its power market-                                                            Room 19-017,&#13;
ing division or affiliate before sharing itwith other                                                         The World Bank,&#13;
market participants. Enforcing that rule would         Notes                                                  IIS H Street, NW,&#13;
require a veritable army of regulator-s to IllOIlitOI'     I. Separatesystem operators are osinally r-eferr-ed to  Washington, DC 20433.&#13;
wwho spoke to whonm in the company cafeteria."    as inidepe ndlenit systemii operators in power parlance . htit&#13;
Telephone:&#13;
Anyv tinbuntdling schemiie that requires the regu-    the indepenldence  may be more apparent thani real.&#13;
001 2024587281&#13;
lator to police cotnduct is doome(d to fail.-              2. For  example,  the  U.S.  Federal  Energs'    Fax:&#13;
Regulatoiy Commilission  lias fimi(d it necessary to inter-&#13;
00 1 202 5 22 3 18 1&#13;
Institutionalizing change with outside coaches    pret atid( clarify its 1996 lisiictionial tulu)ttndling lile    Fmail&#13;
The biggest daniger in power sector reform  is    (Order 889) in 79 tollow-np orders covering morc than       ssmith7@worldbank.org&#13;
getting stuck with flawed grid or market rules.    1,300 pages. In Decemhber 1999 the commission (oll-&#13;
Those profiting from  a flawed rtile will ustially     ciUded that Fumnctional ionhoindling sswas iniefficient,&#13;
cir discrimination if anyonie proposes chianiging    umnfair, and difficult to enloice.                       Printed on recycled paper&#13;
it. The challenige is to create a system  that             3. Beamriz Ar-i,t andj ames Barker. a colleague of&#13;
e nsulres efficient rile chatiges. Panama and the      William Dunn's, are two of tde three outsicle experts ill&#13;
United States have adopted similar approaches,    Panama's market surveillance groUp.&#13;
setting up market surveillance grottps of iide-&#13;
pendent otitside  experts to  "institutionalize        BearnZ Anun (br;bi@mcrauhoscningrlia.com.ara Wliham&#13;
change. "" Their experience sttggests two les-    H. Dunno Ir (wrodsB4bdn@det csmi, nb J)et7/        ( Trnrnhumm&#13;
so5s. First, the experts mtist be perceived as    (b/enenbiummi'lr/ld)onk.og.&#13;
independenit and objective. In small and even             _&#13;
mediutn-size counltries that probably means hir-&#13;
ing experts from  otttside the country. Most&#13;
This Note is available online:&#13;
www.worldbank.org/html/fpd/notesI&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1346421">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2001/01/1346421/regulating-transmission-system-operators-must-truly-independent
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2001/01/1346421/regulating-transmission-system-operators-must-truly-independent</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2001/01/1346421/regulating-transmission-system-operators-must-truly-independent</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2001/07/13/000094946_01062804082071/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2001/07/13/000094946_01062804082071/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2001-07-28T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2001-01-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Regulating transmission : why system
            operators must be truly independent
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Which is best for effective competition
            in power sectors, a separate system operator, a joint-owner
            operator, or some combination of the two? The question is
            being hotly debated among power reformers. The answer? Both
            types of system operators can be made to work, singly or in
            combination. What is critical is that the system operators
            be truly independent of ownership and control of market
            participants -- generators, distributors and suppliers. but
            in many countries they have not been.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Regulating transmission : why system
            operators must be truly independent
        </docna>
        <display_title>Regulating transmission : why
            system operators must be truly independent</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2001/01/1346421/regulating-transmission-system-operators-must-truly-independent</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Energy Trade,Access to Markets,Energy Markets,Power &amp; Energy Conversion,Information Technology</subtopic>
        <teratopic>International Economics and Trade,Energy,Information and Communication Technologies</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Arizu, Beatriz</author>
            <author>Dunn, William H, Jr.</author>
            <author>Tenenbaum, Bernard</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_01062804082071</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Distribution &amp; Transmission</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 226</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>International Economics and Trade,Energy,Information and Communication Technologies</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Electric Power &amp; Other Energy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Regulatory framework; Transmissions;
            Ownership; Decision making; Stakeholders
            ancillary services,bulk
            power,congestion,distribution facilities,energy
            balance,energy markets,generators,grid,market
            operator,market
            participants,mii,monitors,networks,power,Power Grid,power
            market,power markets,power sector,Power sector reform,power
            systems,stakeholders,state-owned
            utilities,suppliers,transmission,transmission
            facilities,transmission system,transmission system operators
        </keywd>
        <owner>Energy Unit (SEGEN)</owner>
        <repnb>22404</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Power Systems Technologies and Operations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Thermal Power Generation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal and Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Congestion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Power Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>