<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Viewpoint&#13;
FTII.z, No. 189                                                                                            July  1&#13;
Mitigating Regulatory Risk 2 2 4A0 0&#13;
in Telecommunications&#13;
Peter L. Smnith     In the transition from state-owned monopolies to privately led and increasingly competitive market&#13;
aidc Bjeo/rH        structures in telecommunications, poor performance of regulatory agencies limits the benefits of&#13;
Wellenii is&#13;
reform, especially in countries with a tradition of weak governance. Bearing in mind that the main&#13;
objective is not a successful agency but a well-performing sector, this Note proposes measures for&#13;
establishing a regulatory framework that enables better sector performance even when an effective,&#13;
full-fledged regulatory agency is lacking. These measures reduce the need for agency decisions,&#13;
enhance the credibility of regulation, and generate maximum impact from scarce professional and&#13;
financial resources by using them effectively. Although each of the measures has a primary purpose,&#13;
several contribute to more than one (table 1).&#13;
TABLE 1   REGULATORY STRATEGY CHECKLIST: PRIMARY (0) AND SECONDARY (@) BENEFITS&#13;
Measure                                   __=i&#13;
Accelerate competition                                          0 i&#13;
Prepackage regulatory rules          i :&#13;
Establish rules for interconnection         : &#13;
Keep operators' obligations reasonable                                           0&#13;
Focus licensing on the main operators&#13;
Rebalance prices early .&#13;
Reduce regulation as competition develops  .&#13;
Adopt transparent processes&#13;
Harness public support&#13;
Lock in principles through international&#13;
commitments&#13;
Outsource regulatory functions&#13;
Adopt alternative dispute resolution         *                  *&#13;
Put the operators to work                                       *           :&#13;
Consider multisectoral agencies                                                  0&#13;
Create regional capacity .&#13;
The World Bank Group - Finance, Private Sector, and Infrastructure Network&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2                    Mitigating Regulatory Risk in Telecommunications&#13;
In the transition from state monopoly to private and competitive&#13;
market structures, regulation is needed to promote the public&#13;
interest for several reasons.                                       Regulatory strategy&#13;
Containing abuse of marketpower The former state monopoly is        Most new  regulatorV arrangerients hinge on a&#13;
likely to remain the largest operator for some time. Customers      regulatory agency loosely modeledl on Noith&#13;
should be protected from abuse of this market power, typically      American pullic utility commissions that have&#13;
soletd be    protet e                , ds                           developed  procecdtires  and  credibility  over&#13;
reflected In high prices, insufficient supply, poor service quality  clecales. 'ro woork well, this mocdel of regulation&#13;
and reliability, slow repairs, slow introduction of new services,   reqUil-es certain conclitions: a strong admiinisti-a&#13;
inaccurate and incontestable bills, and corrupt practices in       tive tradition0 the abIility to undertake comimillit-&#13;
allocating scarce service. New service providers must also be       ments that enCdure fiom one govemlinlent to the&#13;
protected.                                                          next, and a jUdicCialy that is impaIrtial. immulline to&#13;
government and political pressures, and alble to&#13;
Fostering competition. This means action on four fronts:            make enforceahle decisions (Levy and Spiller&#13;
U Unless all regulatory barriers to entry and competition are dis-  1996). It also reqcuires sulbstantial professional&#13;
mantled at the outset, someone must decide from time to time      cadres, capable of handling complex regulatory&#13;
concepts and  processes. Teleco-)nlUnicalti( ns&#13;
how many operators can enter the market, who can enter the        regulatorv agencies generally need thirty or nioi-e&#13;
market, and under what conditions.                                professional engineering, accounting, pricing,&#13;
* New entrants need access to scarce resources initially con-       legal, and adlministr.ative staff (rmoie if, as is often&#13;
trolled by the incumbent-most critical, the radio spectrum,       the case in en-lel-ging economies, the regulator0y&#13;
telephone number blocks, and rights of way.                       agency also manages the radlio spectr-um11) and&#13;
- Developing effective competition hinges on new entrants' abil-    sometimes plan on moire than 100 (Nulhy a&#13;
Developing effectiv competition hingesSchneidexevindle 19tl9).&#13;
ity to access the incumbent's customers and to use parts of the&#13;
incumbent's network at prices that reflect costs. Thus intercon-  Whfen these institutiontlI and couintry featuIes are&#13;
nection between new and established operators is at the heart     not in place, regulatory effectiveness, and thiere-&#13;
of the competition agenda.                                        fore sector deevelopment. can be seriously under-&#13;
* Constant vigilance is needed against anticompetitive behavior,    minecd (box 1). In the Philippines, for example,&#13;
particularly by the incumbent (cross-ownership among operat-      friendly ties xvith the goxeinent in  1978-83&#13;
allto,ed the Plhilippinles Long 1)istance Telephone&#13;
ing companies, limitations on resale, conditioning of sales) but  C&#13;
Cormpa-ny (1'11.T), tlle COLintrys (loIiiinzaiit tele-&#13;
also by fast-growing new entrants.                                phone comppany. to raise prices, horrow lheavily,&#13;
limiiit investmient in local facilities, take ovxer othler&#13;
Creating a favorable investment climate. Investors need to be con-  companies, anld channel high  profits to the&#13;
vinced that the rules of the game under which they are investing    accounts of controlling shareholders. 13y 1992. in&#13;
can be relied on. In particular, they need to be confident that their  the wake of changes in the goxeinentt an eco-&#13;
investments will be safe from de facto expropriation through arbi-  new entries in the market, outstandLing applicwa-&#13;
trary changes in prices, taxes, and service obligations.            tions for service exceedlecd teleplhones. Regulaltoly&#13;
failures played a big part, includling large pnice cdis-&#13;
Narrowing developmentgaps. A fully commercial approach to          tortions, the ahsence of effective rare-of-return&#13;
telecommunications will go a long way toward meeting develop-       regulation that might have created incentives for&#13;
ment objectives, including extending access to rural and low-       extending local service, and continuecl protection&#13;
income urban areas. But gaps in meeting universal service goals     of PLDT's dle facto monopoly. Tlese failtures&#13;
are likely to remain, calling for public sector initiatives or financ-  resulted in the \vorst possible outcome: exclusive&#13;
ing to complement or catalyze those of the private sector.          righits for a senrice provided not at all in soimc&#13;
areas and inadequately in most others. Yet the sec-&#13;
tor w,as privately oxvneci anld ecluipleCC withl a meg-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank Group                       3&#13;
BOX 2      UGANDA'S PREPACKAGED RULES&#13;
Network rollout. The bid evaluation criteria for the second&#13;
national operator license included both license bid price and net-&#13;
ulatory agency modeled on public utility corn-           work rollout. The winning bidder proposed to build 89,000 lines&#13;
missions in the United States.                           over five years (more than the 50,000 required), a goal now&#13;
included in its obligations. Regulatory intervention will be limited&#13;
The general steps in setting up effective regula-        to monitoring compliance and establishing approaches to provid-&#13;
tion include establishing an agency with a firm           ing service in unserved areas.&#13;
foundation in law, limiting opportunity for gov-&#13;
ernment intervention, starting up the agency              Price control. The licenses specify a price cap-type price regula-&#13;
wvell before privatization, ensuiring financial and&#13;
wellbeforerivatiatio, ensurin  fin rl ation, which will continue for the five years the duopoly in basic&#13;
administrative autonomy, hiring competent staff,&#13;
establishing a process for appeal, giving the            services is in effect. No further regulatory decisions on prices will&#13;
agency the means to enforce its decisions, and           be needed during this period.&#13;
setting clear boundaries and links with other&#13;
institutions (see, for example, Wellenius forth-         Interconnection. Both licensees are required to negotiate inter-&#13;
coming). But in countries with weak governance           connection agreements. Pending agreement, either licensee can&#13;
ancd  limited  administrative  and  professional         request from the other the immediate application of the prices and&#13;
skills, the regulatory strategy should also focus        terms of a default interconnection agreement appended to the&#13;
on:                                                       licenses.&#13;
* Reducing the need for agency dlecisions.&#13;
* Enhancing regulatory credibility.                      Monopolistic practices. The licensees cannot unduly condition the&#13;
* Using resources effectively by outsourcing some        provision of telephone service on purchase of terminal equipment&#13;
reguilatory tasks and pooling sector knowledge.        and cross-ownership between the companies is prohibited.&#13;
Reduce the need for agency decisions&#13;
RResale. The licensees are obligated to provide basic exchange&#13;
Reform  plans typically expect the regulatory            service for resale for public pay telephone service.&#13;
agency to do too many things too soon. A more&#13;
practical approach is to reduce the need for reg-&#13;
ulatorv action, especially in the early years after    significantly expanding local telephone facilities&#13;
privatization. This can he done in seven main   in regions throughout the country. By 1996 the&#13;
ways.                                               number of lines in service had almost tripled, to&#13;
1.8 million.&#13;
Accelerate competition&#13;
The regulator's job is eased when it can&#13;
Opening the market quickly to new entry and    adjuclicate among several influential players or&#13;
competition not only accelerates the full benefits    constituencies. Multiple players provide the&#13;
from reform but also nmakes the job of the regu-    regulator w ith alternativ e sources of informa-&#13;
lator more manageable. The question is no    tion on sector issues, reduce the risk of regu-&#13;
longer whether to have competition-the tradi-   latorv capture by any one operator, and offset&#13;
tional arguments for exclusivity, even temporary    some of the dominant operators economic&#13;
exclusivity, no longer hold (Smith 1995; Noll   and political power.&#13;
1998). Instead, it is how fast competition should&#13;
be ushered in. Allowing competition in the core    Opening the market to new entry is easiest early&#13;
telephony business creates powerful incentives    in  reform-before  or at thie  same time as&#13;
for the incumbent to perform better. PLDT accel-    privatization-when large unmicet demand allows&#13;
eratedl investment to catch up with demand only    both the incumbent and new entrants to grow.&#13;
after the Philippine government issued licenses    Large initial productivity gains by the incumbent&#13;
in 1993 for mobile service and for several new    followinig privatization will allow it to reposition&#13;
international gateways to consortia committed to   itself for competition, but opening the market&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4                  Mitigating Regulatory Risk in Telecommunications&#13;
early enough can prevent it from using these   impact on new entry is so important, that it is&#13;
gains to entrench its dominant position.       useful to have interconnection rules or guide-&#13;
lines that provide a framework for negotiation&#13;
Prepackage regulatory rules                    and  eventual  regulatory  adjudication-as&#13;
Mexico found when it prepared for competition&#13;
If rights and obligations of an operator or class   in long-distance and international services in&#13;
of operators need to be specified, it is best to   1996. Moreover, the parties often have unequal&#13;
write these into licenses, contracts (such as for   resources, negotiating power, and ability to cope&#13;
the sale of state enterprises), or laws. Then tech-   with delays.&#13;
nical assistance (from multilateral or bilateral&#13;
agencies, for example) can be concentrated up    The authorities can address these issues by estab-&#13;
front to establish a detailed base-case regulatory   lishing up-front default terms of interconnection&#13;
environment.                                   (both price and technical) by which all parties&#13;
must abide while they negotiate or if they fail to&#13;
Uganda provides a good example of this strategy   agree. Alternatively, the dominant company&#13;
(box 2). There, a moderately pro-competitive pol-   could be required to publish a standard inter-&#13;
icy and specification of initial regulatory rules in   connection offering. Guatemala's 1996 telecom-&#13;
the licenses of the main operating companies   munications law sets caps on interconnection&#13;
(along with other elements, discussed later) add    charges for two years following privatization and&#13;
up to a fairly robust regulatory framework. A key   specifies how the regulator should resolve inter-&#13;
part of the strategy was to immediately introduce    connection pricing disputes between operators.&#13;
some competition in all services by authorizing a   And in Uganda the license for the second national&#13;
second national operator to provide local, cellu-   operator includes a detailed default interconnec-&#13;
lar, domestic long-distance, and intemational   tion agreement.&#13;
telephone services alongside Uganda Telecom-&#13;
munications Ltd. (UTL), the state monopoly being    Keep operators' obligations reasonable&#13;
privatized. Before bids were invited for the sec-&#13;
ond license, licenses were prepared for both com-   Imposing tough obligations on operators may&#13;
panies specifying in advance important elements   seem good for the country, but it can force reg-&#13;
of the regulatory regime. This reduced regulatory   ulators into untenable situations. In particular,&#13;
uncertainty for the investors, eased the regulatory   setting stiff rollout obligations, with investments&#13;
commission's burden of establishing a new regu-   that go far beyond what is commercially viable&#13;
latory regime from scratch, and served the public   at the time of privatization, risks forcing compa-&#13;
interest by addressing regulatory issues that often    nies to undertake bad investments, leads opera-&#13;
become problems elsewhere.                     tors to demand special privileges (such as longer&#13;
exclusivity), and creates a need for renegotiation&#13;
There are many other cases of prepackaged rules.  later.&#13;
The 1982 telecommunications law of Chile, for&#13;
example, requires dominant operators' prices to   Focus licensing on the main operators&#13;
be revised every five years using marginal cost&#13;
pricing and to be indexed between revisions.   Many services can be provided without license,&#13;
perhaps subject only to declaration for the pub-&#13;
Establish rules for interconnection           lic record and for statistical purposes. Class&#13;
licenses can be automatically granted to any&#13;
Ideally, interconnection agreements could be   applicant meeting set criteria. Bidding should be&#13;
treated simply as a commercial matter to be   used to allocate any licenses that will be restricted&#13;
agreed between the parties. But interconnection   in number, such as for the use of radio frequen-&#13;
disputes have become so common, and the   cies when demand exceeds supply.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank Group                    5&#13;
That wvas the strategy used by El Salvador in   to rebalance telephone prices to make local ser-&#13;
restructuring its telecommunications sector in   vice profitable-as compensation for reneging&#13;
1997. Licenses are required for using the radio   on license provisions allowing newly privatized&#13;
spectrum but not for operating networks or ser-   telecommunications companies to index their&#13;
vices. Network operators are free to establish    prices to inflation. But it took more than six years&#13;
prices and conditions for the services they pro-   to reach a final decision on the rebalancing.&#13;
vide to end users as well as to each other, but   Meanwhile, business users faced long-distance&#13;
must grant access to essential services on a    prices that were up to fifty times cost, and inter-&#13;
nondiscriminatory basis. Defined by law, essen-   national prices some four times those in neigh-&#13;
tial services are interconnection, signaling, caller   boring  countries. These  distortions created&#13;
identification, billing data, number portability,   artificial incentives to use foreign callback and&#13;
and directory databases.                        calling card services, which may have siphoned&#13;
off about a fourth of Argentina's international&#13;
The regulator in El Salvador is informed of the   telephone  revenues  (Artana, Navajas, and&#13;
terms of access, monitors fairness and compliance    Urbizondo 1998). (The lesson was learned: pri-&#13;
with the law, and resolves disputes if parties fail to   vatizations in gas and electricity were preceded&#13;
agree. The law prescribes in detail the process for   by rate rebalancing.)&#13;
the regulatory agency to follow in all decision-&#13;
making. While the temis of interconnection are to   The experience in Mexico was only somewhat bet-&#13;
be agreed among the parties, disputes are to be   ter. Before privatization in 1990 large taxes on&#13;
settled by the regulator, with the aid of qualified   telecommunications bills were converted to tariff&#13;
external experts and based on long-run average    elements, improving alignment with costs. The&#13;
incremental costs. The regulator also administers   task was left to the privatized operator to complete&#13;
the radio spectrum  and the numbering system    under a timetable linked to its exclusivity period,&#13;
(including codes for customer selection of carriers)   but progress on rebalancing and investment was&#13;
on demand or-for spectrum-using auctions   slower than expected. Near the end of the period&#13;
when demand exceeds available capacity.         the operator argued, unsuccessftilly, for more time&#13;
to rebalance prices before it faced competition in&#13;
Surprisingly, even countries that adopt fairly pro-    1996. By contrast, in Uganda in 1998, prices for&#13;
competitive policies from the start often write into    most telecommunications services were substan-&#13;
law a requirement to license all entrants. This   tially rebalanced and liberalized before the award&#13;
places an excessive burden on the regulator-    of the second national operator's license, con-&#13;
and the operators-and creates oppornunity for   tributing to the high level of investment today. The&#13;
discretion, pressure, and corruption.           number of telephone lines, including cellular,&#13;
increased by more than 48 perc(ent in the year after&#13;
Rebalance prices early                          the license was awarded in April 1998.&#13;
Leaving it to privatized companies to rebalance    Since new entrants will often have little market&#13;
prices invites difficulties for the regulator as well   power, an alternative is to leave prices unregu-&#13;
as for the companies. In Argentina, for example,   lated and allow price competition to lead to rate&#13;
failure to rebalance before privatization, coupled    rebalancing bly the incumbent.&#13;
with broad institutional weaknesses, led to years&#13;
of conflict involving the regulatory agency, reg-   Reduce regulation as competition develops&#13;
ulated companies, the government, opposition&#13;
parties, consumer associations, and various judi-   Because a fundamental rationale for regulation&#13;
cial courts. In 1991, after adoption of a currency   is to respond to operators that have significant&#13;
board svstem made local currency price index-   market power or control scarce resources, regu-&#13;
ing for inflation illegal, the government agreed   lators should be able to reduce or end regulation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6                   Mitigating Regulatory Risk in Telecommunications&#13;
as competition develops, and instead pernmit   a minister attempted to block the reuUlator's taliff&#13;
general commercial rules to apply. Thus in   rebalancing order in 1999, public outcry folloxwed&#13;
Canada the telecommunications regulator is   and the government supportecd the regulator.&#13;
required to forbear exercising its regulatory pow-&#13;
ers where it finds markets to be sufficiently com-    Harness public support&#13;
petitive for regulation to be unnecessary (for&#13;
example. most wireless and long-distance ser-   The sustainability of a regulatory agency will&#13;
vices of all carriers, including the main telephone    eventually depend on public trust and support.&#13;
companies). In Chile the antimonopoly commis-   Thus the agency needs to be seen as addressing&#13;
sion determines what telecommunications ser-   issues important for customers. not just arbitrat-&#13;
vices are to be subject to price regulation. This   ing on highily technical matters. Although the&#13;
trend of treating telecommunications as a trad-   issues valuedC by customers will vxarv froIII COUn-&#13;
ahle service, subject to general commercial and    try to country, they couldl include biilling accuracy&#13;
trading rules, is also seen at the regional level-    and practices. operators terms and conditions of&#13;
notably in the European Union-and tincer the    service (including customer redl-ess), quality of&#13;
World Trade Organization (WTO).                  service, geographic coverage, and access by nOn-&#13;
subscribers to communal facilities, such as pay&#13;
Enhance regulatory credibility                   phones ancl telecenters.&#13;
Elnhancing  credibility can also do much to    Often, telecommunications  reform  involves&#13;
strengthen regulation in an environment of weak    losses for concentrated and influential vested&#13;
governance. Critical steps include ensuring ade-   interests-such as monopoly owners, managers.&#13;
qluate legislative provisions on agency jurisdic-   or employees-ancd gains for hliglhly dispersed&#13;
tion, autonomy, access to information, timeliness   customers. This outcome is typical whlere there is&#13;
of the appeal process, enforceability of decisions,   large unmet demand for selVices anCl OCCulr-S not&#13;
staggerecd terms of office for commissioners, and    only at the time of sector rest-ucturling but also&#13;
inabilitv to remove commissioners except for   later, in a myriad of regulatorwy decisions. Since&#13;
cause. But other measures are also in order.     regulatory agencies in almost all countries oper-&#13;
ate in a political environment. strengthening CulS-&#13;
Adopt open regulatory processes                  tomer associations to adcvocate customler interests&#13;
can help facilitate agency decisions that promote&#13;
Transparency in decisionmaking enhances the    a broad public interest. Thle Canadlian Radio-&#13;
credibility of agencies anci the legitimacy of   television and Telecommutnications Commission&#13;
decisions. This in turn helps ensutre that decisions    for many years lhas arranged funding for cus-&#13;
will not be overturned arbitrarily, increasing    tomer groups that contribute to its proceedings.&#13;
investor conf'idence. Public consultation on major&#13;
regulatory issues adds to transparency by educat-    Undertake international commitments&#13;
ing the regulatory authority and interested parties&#13;
about the facts of an issue and the merits of alter-   Governments can take steps that formiially comI-&#13;
native solutions. tJsing consultative papers has    mit them bheyond the houndaries of their owxn&#13;
several advantages: administrative  simplicity,   legal environments to apply the rules ol' the&#13;
broad reach, and quick decisions. The Tele    game. Countries that subscribed to the 1997&#13;
comnmnications Regulatory Authority of India    NTO agreement on hasic telecommunications&#13;
aclopted  this approach, issuing  consultative    enterect a bindinc international commitmaent to&#13;
papers in 1997 ancI 1998 (for example, on prices.   implemcnt specific reforms, apply a commion set&#13;
sen-ice quality, the numbering plan, anct the    of regulatory principles anct practices, and rec-&#13;
process for determining the license fees) ancd   ognize the XXTO as an axventue for intergovern-&#13;
soliciting comments from interested parties. When    mental appeal. Sovereign loans and credits from&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank Group                    7&#13;
multilateral development organizations such as   There is a risk, however. that alternative dispute&#13;
the World Bank involve formal government   resolution procedures will be used to delay or&#13;
obligations that can be tailored to reduce regu-   sideline difficult decisions that the regulators do&#13;
latory risk, such as the risk that the government   not want to face. The incumbent operator may&#13;
will fail to abide by the pricing rule established    have incentives to let the process drag on. To avoid&#13;
in the license.                                 this, the dispute resolution process should include:&#13;
* Firm deadlines for completing the process.&#13;
Use resources effectively                       * Authority to empower the arbitrator or media-&#13;
tor to obtain information, schedule meetings.&#13;
The skills required by a regulatory agency vary   and recommend a clecision if the process fails.&#13;
widely as the focus of regulatory action shifts   a Regulatory or other sanctions for noncompli-&#13;
from relationships between operators and gov-     ance.&#13;
ernment (licensing) to relationships between&#13;
operators (intercoinnection) to relationships bet-   Put the operators to work&#13;
ween operators and consumers (prices, com-&#13;
plaints). Relying mainly on internal skills is   In most countries the greatest concentration of&#13;
unlikely to be the best way to obtain (and dlis-   telecommunications sector knowledge is in the&#13;
pose of) the wide range of skills needed in a    operating companies. This information asym-&#13;
timely way. There are a number of other options.   metry places the regulator at a disadvantage, but&#13;
it is possible to turn the tables by putting the reg-&#13;
Outsource regulatory functions                  ulated companies to work for the regulator. The&#13;
Chilean telecommunications law requires the&#13;
Many regulatory functions can be contracted out.   regulated  companies-not the regulator-to&#13;
Audit firms can monitor compliance with perfor-   prepare detailed proposals every five years for&#13;
mance commitments in operating licenses, inter-   revising prices along the lines prescribed in the&#13;
connection rules, and tariff rules. In Argentina a   law. The regulator reviews the proposals with&#13;
private contractor monitors use of the radio spec-   the help of consultants and solicits comments&#13;
trum  on behalf of the regulatory agency, keeping    from other interested parties. Once satisfied that&#13;
part of the annual license fees as payment for its   a proposal is consistent with the law and cur-&#13;
services. And external experts can resolve dis-   rent best practice, the regulator approves it, and&#13;
putes among operators and with the regulator,   the proposal remains in force for five years.&#13;
leaving final decisions (such as applying penal-&#13;
ties) in the hands of the regulator.            Consider multisectoral agencies&#13;
Adopt alternative dispute resolution            Many emerging economies cannot afford the&#13;
financial and human resource costs of a separate&#13;
Disputes and conflicts increasingly arise between    regulatoro agency for each sector. Since network&#13;
incumbent operators and new entrants, between   industries-gas, water, electricity, transportation-&#13;
new7 entrants, and betw een operators and regu-   have much in common (but also important differ-&#13;
lators. Regulatory, administrative, and judicial re-   ences), a multisectoral agency can be considered.&#13;
sources may be quickly overwhelmed by the    Such an agency could afford a better core staff&#13;
number and complexity of cases. A broad range    versed in generic regulatory processes, finance,&#13;
of alternative dispute avoidance and resolution   law, and administration than each sector agency&#13;
methods can be used in the telecommunications    could separately (though sector-specific teams&#13;
sector, including negotiation, mediation, and    wtould still be required). And a multisectoral&#13;
arbitration. These methods can be presented in   agency is less likely to be captured by any one&#13;
the telecommunications law, the licenses, or con-   operating company or controlled by any one sec-&#13;
tracts of sale.                                 tor ministry. U.S. public utility commissions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
8                         Mitigating Regulatory Risk in Telecommunications&#13;
typically regulate gas, electricity, local telecommu-           Conclusion&#13;
nications, and sometimes water at the state level,&#13;
but not mail, broadcasting, interstate teleconmimu-             There  is  no  universal  prescription  that  can&#13;
nications, or radio spectrum.                                   guarantee success in launching new  telecommu-&#13;
nications regulatory frameworks, especially in&#13;
A  multisectoral  agency  does  not necessarily                 economies with weak governance. But the ele-&#13;
imply a single agency  for all infrastructure or                ments outlined  in  this Note  can  do  much  to&#13;
public  utility  sectors. Care  must be  taken  to              increase the chances of success even in these&#13;
avoid an overcrowded portfolio of responsibili-                 environments. These elements are being  tried,&#13;
ties and undue concentration of power, and to                   usually a few  at a time, in several countries. It will&#13;
take account of differences in the reform  and                  be some time before we can draw  firm  conclu-&#13;
market development stage of sectors. Further-                   sions on their effectiveness. Nonetheless, given&#13;
more, if regulatory agencies are to be merged or                the limited chances of success for more narrowly&#13;
restructured, it is vitally important to maintain               defined solutions in countries with weak gover-&#13;
credibility  and  effectiveness during the transi-              nance, all these elements should be systemati-&#13;
tion period. Examples of multisectoral commu-                   cally  considered   when   designing  regulatory&#13;
nications regulatory agencies with limited scope                arrangements in  countries now  embarking  on&#13;
are the Canadian Radio-television and Telecom-                  sector reforms.&#13;
munications Commission and the Uganda&#13;
Communications Commission, which is respon-                     References&#13;
forumintended to          sible for mail and radio spectrum  management                   Artana, Daniel, Fernando Navajas, and Santiago Urbizondo. 1998.&#13;
encourage                 as well as telecommunications.                                     'Contractual Adaptation in Regulated Utilities: A Few Observations&#13;
dissemination of and                                                                         from  Argentina." Fundacidn de Investigaciones Economicas&#13;
debate on ideas,&#13;
innovations, and beast   Create regional capacity                                            Latinoamericanas, Buenos Aires.&#13;
levy, Brian, and Pablo T. Spiller. eds. 1996. Regulations, Institutions.&#13;
practices for expanding                                                                      and Commitment, Comparatire Studies in Telecormmunications.&#13;
the private sector The    Countries that have some federalization of gov-                    Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.&#13;
views published are&#13;
those of the authors and  emient functions among them  could share a reg-                 Noll, Roger G. 1998. "Telecommunications Reform in Developing&#13;
1                                               ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~Countries." lorld Banik, Wasbington, D.C.&#13;
should not be attributed  ulatory agency or technical secretariat. The five               Nulty, Timothy E., and Eric Schneidewiinde. 1989. "Regulatory Policy&#13;
to the World Bank or any  countries of the Organization  of Eastern  Carib-                  for Telecommrtnications." In Bjmrn NVellenitts, Peter Stern, Timothy&#13;
of its affiliated organize-  bean  States  are  working  toward  a  common                   E. Nulty, and Richard D. Stern, eds., Restructuting andD   anaging&#13;
tints. Nor do any of the                                             ~~~~~~~~~~~~~the Telecommunications Sector Wasbington, D.C.: World Bank.&#13;
conclusions represent    telecommunications law and a single telecommu-                   Smith, Peter  1995. "Subscribing to Monopoly: The Telecom&#13;
official policy of the    nications regulatory agency much like their com-                   Monopolist's Lexicon-Revisited." Viewpoint 53. World Bank,&#13;
World Bank or of its&#13;
Executive Directors or   mon Central Bank and Civil Aviation Authority.                      Finance, Private Sector, and Infrastructure Network, Washington,&#13;
the countries they        Where a shared agency is politically infeasible, the               D. C.       Wat tbe Transformation of Telecommonications&#13;
represent.               regulatory agency of one country could provide                      Markets Means for Regulation." Viewpoint 121. World Bank,&#13;
To order additional       regulatory services to other countries under con-                  Finance, Private Sector, and Infrastructure Network. Washington,&#13;
D.C.&#13;
copies please call       tract or as part of a regional economic coopera-                 Wellenius, Bjorn. Forthcoming. "Regulating the Telecommunications&#13;
202 458 1111 or contact   tion  agreement such  as  the  Southern  African                   Sector.' In Luigi Manzetti, ed.. Regulation in Post.Privatization&#13;
SuzanneSmlith, editor,   Development Community. Another possibility is                       Entironments: The latin AmericanExperience.&#13;
The World Bank,          to establish core teams of regulatory experts in&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,       regional centers to support countries on demand,                 Peter L. Smith (psmith2@worldbank.org) and&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433,&#13;
or Internet address       as proposed  in the Africa Connection program                   BjoIrn Welleniris (bwellenius@worldbank.org),&#13;
ssmith7@worldbank.org.    and  endorsed  in  1999 by  the  Organization  of                Telecommunications and In]brmatics Division&#13;
The series is also        African Unity. Besides sharing the regulatory load,&#13;
available on line&#13;
lwww.worldbank.org/      all these arrangements aid learning across coun-&#13;
html/fpd/notes/l).       tries and could result in a degree of regulatory uni-&#13;
formity allowing commercial aggregation of small&#13;
paperi                   markets into larger, more viable ones.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1346401">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/07/1346401/mitigating-regulatory-risk-telecommunications
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/07/1346401/mitigating-regulatory-risk-telecommunications</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1999/07/1346401/mitigating-regulatory-risk-telecommunications</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2001/07/06/000094946_01062604121228/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2001/07/06/000094946_01062604121228/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2001-07-06T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1999-07-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Mitigating regulatory risk in telecommunications
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In the transition from state-owned
            monopolies to privately led and increasingly competitive
            market structures in telecommunications, poor performance of
            regulatory agencies limits the benefits of reform. This Note
            proposes measures for establishing a regulatory framework
            that enables better sector performance even when a
            full-fledged regulatory agency is lacking. These measures
            reduce the need for agency decisions -- for example, by
            prepackaging rules and accelerating competition. They
            enhance the credibility of regulation -- for example, by
            locking in principles through international agreements. And
            they generate maximum impact from scarce professional and
            financial resources by using them effectively -- such as by
            contracting out functions and creating multisectoral or
            regional agencies.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Mitigating regulatory risk in telecommunications
        </docna>
        <display_title>Mitigating regulatory risk in telecommunications</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1999/07/1346401/mitigating-regulatory-risk-telecommunications</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,ICT Policy and Strategies,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Access to Markets,Public Sector Economics</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Environment,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Information and Communication Technologies,Public Sector Development,International Economics and Trade</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Smith, Peter L.</author>
            <author>Wellenius, Bjorn</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_01062604121228</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Telecommunications &amp; Informatics</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 189</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Environment,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Information and Communication Technologies,Public Sector Development,International Economics and Trade</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Information and communications</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Telecommunications; Regulatory structure;
            Regulatory agency; Regulatory framework; Market competition;
            Price controls; Monopolistic competition; Licencing;
            Institution building; Contracting
            access to
            information,accounting,auctions,barriers to
            entry,Bidding,Central Bank,communal
            facilities,consumers,decision-
            making,duopoly,electricity,evaluation criteria,financial
            resources,income,inflation,innovations,learning,licenses,marginal
            cost,marginal cost pricing,market power,market
            prices,media,monopolies,outsourcing,phones,political
            power,price competition,Price control,price index,price
            regulation,Private Sector,productivity,provisions,Public
            consultation,public sector,radio,regulatory
            agencies,regulatory agency,regulatory experts,regulatory
            framework,Regulatory Policy,regulatory
            principles,sales,telecenters,telecommunications,telecommunications
            companies,telecommunications law,telecommunications
            reform,telecommunications regulator,telecommunications
            sector,telecommunications services,telephone lines,telephone
            service,telephone
            services,television,Transparency,transparent
            processes,universal service,Utilities,World Trade Organization,WTO
        </keywd>
        <owner>CFO's Finance Functions</owner>
        <repnb>22400</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Generic Name List</ml:concept><ml:concept>Generics</ml:concept><ml:concept>List of Generic Drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Off patent drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Service Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contracting out</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment and Investment Climate</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement of Judgements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Informal Dispute Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>World Trade Organization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Generic Drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adaptation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Outsourcing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Climate</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Dispute Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Dispute Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>