<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                                                               59336&#13;
                                                 The Water and Sanitation Program is an           May 2010&#13;
                                                 international partnership for improving water&#13;
                                                 and sanitation sector policies, practices, and&#13;
                                                 capacities to serve poor people                  Field Note&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Improving Household Drinking Water Quality&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Use of BioSand Filters&#13;
in Cambodia&#13;
The BSF is a robust water treatment technology for use in rural Cambodian households, capable of&#13;
effective removal of bacteria, and significant reduction of diarrheal disease. BSF performance is&#13;
comparable to other recommended household water treatment interventions.&#13;
&amp;#12;       Despite recontamination during storage, the concentration of E. coli as&#13;
       well as turbidity were still lower in BSF-treated and stored water than in&#13;
       untreated water.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Executive Summary                                                                                         95% reduction of E. coli and an 82%&#13;
                                                                                                          reduction in turbidity of untreated source&#13;
                                                                                                          water. Furthermore, BSF-usage in&#13;
Safe water is critical to preventing diarrheal&#13;
                                                                                                          households resulted in a 47% reduction of&#13;
disease, which kills nearly two million&#13;
                                                                                                          diarrheal disease as compared to control&#13;
children annually. A promising household&#13;
                                                                                                          households that did not have BSFs.&#13;
water treatment technology is the BioSand&#13;
                                                                                                          However, a significant proportion of BSF-&#13;
Filter (BSF), an intermittent slow sand filter&#13;
                                                                                                          treated and stored samples became&#13;
that is locally produced in Cambodia and&#13;
                                                                                                          re-contaminated after filtration suggesting&#13;
several other developing countries.&#13;
                                                                                                          the need for additional training and&#13;
However, despite promising laboratory&#13;
                                                                                                          education about safe storage and&#13;
performance, the BSF lacks adequate&#13;
                                                                                                          recontamination. Despite recontamination&#13;
description and epidemiological evidence&#13;
                                                                                                          during storage, the concentration of E. coli&#13;
on its field performance and health impact.&#13;
                                                                                                          as well as turbidity were still lower in BSF-&#13;
                                                                                                          treated and stored water than in untreated&#13;
Cambodia is currently the country with the&#13;
                                                                                                          water.&#13;
largest number of BSFs in the world.&#13;
Although non-governmental organizations&#13;
                                                                                                          The BSF is a robust water treatment&#13;
(NGOs) have conducted internal&#13;
                                                                                                          technology for use in rural Cambodian&#13;
evaluations, no independent evaluations&#13;
                                                                                                          households, capable of effective removal of&#13;
using scientific methods have measured the&#13;
                                                                                                          indicator bacteria, specifically E. coli, and&#13;
performance of these filters to improve&#13;
                                                   Bottled water is an expensive solution; treatment at   significant reduction of diarrheal disease.&#13;
water quality and reduce waterborne&#13;
                                                   home is more sustainable.                              BSF performance is comparable to other&#13;
diarrheal disease in Cambodia. Moreover,&#13;
                                                                                                          recommended household water treatment&#13;
the long-term use and effectiveness of&#13;
                                                                                                          interventions, such as the ceramic water&#13;
BSFs have not been examined and these              households without a BSF (control).&#13;
                                                                                                          purifier; however BSFs provide the&#13;
studies are necessary before further BSF&#13;
                                                                                                          additional advantage of not being prone to&#13;
implementation and scale-up projects can           Results of these studies indicate that 87.5%&#13;
                                                                                                          breakage or needing replacement parts.&#13;
occur.                                             of the households surveyed had BSFs in&#13;
                                                                                                          Overall, the findings of this study provide&#13;
                                                   use. Time in use ranged from six months to&#13;
                                                                                                          evidence that the BSF is a promising&#13;
The purpose of this research was to                eight years, and the percentage of BSFs still&#13;
                                                                                                          household point-of-use (POU) water&#13;
assess: (1) the factors associated with            in use did not decline over the length of&#13;
                                                                                                          treatment option to achieve sustained&#13;
continued BSF use or disuse by using a             time elapsed between BSF installation and&#13;
                                                                                                          access to safe water.&#13;
cross-sectional survey (2) the                     follow up. Water, sanitation, hygiene, and&#13;
microbiological effectiveness of the BSFs          other factors were analyzed for association&#13;
still in use by measuring reduction of             with continued filter use. Households who              Study Background&#13;
Escherichia coli (E. coli) bacteria, and (3) the   reported receiving training in operation and&#13;
health impact of the BSF as determined by          maintenance and those who used deep                    Access to safe water is not only a basic&#13;
a epidemiological study in which diarrheal         wells (more than 10 meters deep) were                  requirement for life, but is also regarded as&#13;
disease incidence was measured among               found to be statistically significantly                a human right. It is estimated that more&#13;
people in households with a BSF                    associated with continued BSF use. In BSF              than 1 billion people, nearly 20% of the&#13;
(intervention) versus people in similar            households, BSF treatment resulted in a                world's total population, do not have&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   2&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                               Use of BioSand Filters in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
access to safe drinking water1. Worldwide,                  technology that is currently being              programs of the BSF in Cambodia. The&#13;
88% of diarrheal disease is due to unsafe                   implemented and promoted internationally.       study was designed as a microbiological&#13;
water, hygiene, and sanitation2. Consuming                  Laboratory studies have examined BSF            and epidemiological assessment of BSF&#13;
unsafe water causes gastrointestinal                        performance, including its ability to reduce    impact on water quality and health after&#13;
illnesses that lead to diarrhea, dehydration,               different classes of microorganisms4,5,6.       introduction into homes beginning in 2001.&#13;
and malnutrition, especially for children in                These studies show reductions ranging           Key study questions were:&#13;
developing countries. Children are more                     from 90% (1 log10) to 99% (2 log10), for&#13;
vulnerable due to undeveloped digestive                     fecal coliforms, including E. coli,             · How long are BSFs being used and what&#13;
and immune systems and experience an                        approximately 90% (1 log10) for viruses, and    factors are related to continued BSF use?&#13;
average of three or more episodes of                        &gt;99.9% (&gt;3 log10) for protozoan parasites.&#13;
diarrheal disease each year3. Of the 1.7                    While these microbial reductions are            · Are those BSFs still in use able to&#13;
million people that die each year from                      encouraging, independent field                  improve household drinking water quality&#13;
diarrheal disease, 90% are children under                   examinations of the BSF to assess long-         by reducing E. coli levels in drinking water?&#13;
the age of five, mostly in developing                       term changes in water quality, health&#13;
countries1.                                                 impact, and sustainability are still lacking.   · Are those BSFs still in use making a&#13;
                                                            The purpose of this study was to conduct        significant impact on household health by&#13;
The BioSand Filter (BSF) is an emerging                     an independent follow-up assessment of          reducing diarrheal disease?&#13;
Point-Of-Use (POU) water treatment                          two large-scale NGO implementation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Even sources classifed as "improved" may provide water that is microbiologically contaminated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                              3&#13;
&amp;#12;    Another factor related to poor surface water quality is low quality or complete&#13;
    lack of sanitation facilities. Nearly 80% of the rural population reports not having&#13;
    a toilet facility and therefore making use of fields or bush areas. A lack of access&#13;
    to sanitation facilities has significant impact on human health as wastes are&#13;
    discharged into surface waters that are also used for drinking.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Box 1: Household Water Treatment in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
    Access to safe water for Cambodians remains a problem throughout the country, especially for the rural population. More than&#13;
    40% of Cambodians use unimproved drinking water sources during the dry season (November to April), with 23% of the&#13;
    population relying on surface waters such as rivers, lakes, ponds, and streams (see table 1). During the rainy season (May to&#13;
    October), when rainwater harvesting is more prominent, use of unimproved drinking water sources decreases to 24%. However,&#13;
    unimproved surface waters are still used by 11% of the total population during this time7. Furthermore, even sources classified as&#13;
    "improved" may provide water that is microbiologically contaminated. In addition, exposure to hazardous chemicals in drinking&#13;
    water is a serious issue in the Mekong region because some groundwater sources are also known to contain high levels of&#13;
    naturally occurring arsenic and other chemical contaminants8,9,10. Surface and shallow ground waters that are of poor&#13;
    microbiological quality are often used as alternatives to arsenic-contaminated deep wells11. The fact that nearly 80% of the rural&#13;
    population do not have a toilet and practice open defecation7 also impacts water quality and health as wastes contaminate&#13;
    surface waters that are used for drinking.&#13;
&#13;
    Water treatment is widely practised at the household level, with boiling the most commonly used method (60% of the total&#13;
    population). Other methods are also used and over 2% of the population uses household filtration (ceramic, sand, or other filter)7,&#13;
    which translates into approximately 55,000 households who make use of this treatment method. Production and promotion of&#13;
    household water treatment technologies have been going on for many years, and Cambodia now serves as an important place&#13;
    for household water treatment research, demonstration, and implementation11.&#13;
&#13;
    Research has shown that POU drinking water treatment is both a technically- and financially effective intervention for provision of&#13;
    safe water to consumers12. Recent systematic reviews of various research studies show that POU technologies can improve&#13;
    water quality and reduce diarrheal disease by 30% to 70%13,14,15. Diarrhoeal disease reduction varies widely however, based on a&#13;
    variety of factors16. Besides being evaluated for the ability to reduce pathogens and disease, household water treatment also&#13;
    needs to be accessible, simple, and inexpensive to operate in order for people to effectively treat and store water in a household&#13;
    setting.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Table 1: Unimproved water sources in rural and urban Cambodia during the dry and rainy seasons&#13;
    (NIPH/NIS 2006)&#13;
&#13;
    Dry Season                                                                           Urban              Rural               Total&#13;
&#13;
    All unimproved water sources                                                          25%                46%                43%&#13;
&#13;
    Surface waters                                                                        12%                25%                23%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Rainy Season                                                                         Urban              Rural               Total&#13;
&#13;
    All unimproved water sources                                                          12%                26%                24%&#13;
&#13;
    Surface waters                                                                         5%                11%                11%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                               Use of BioSand Filters in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                             Figure 1: BSF cross-section&#13;
Box 2: The BioSand Filter&#13;
&#13;
The BioSand Filter (BSF) is a household-scale, intermittently-operated slow sand filter&#13;
invented in its current form by Dr. David Manz in the early 1990s. An estimated&#13;
320,000 BSFs have been installed throughout the world in more than 70 counties17.&#13;
Unlike a traditional slow sand filter, the BSF is specifically adapted for use in the&#13;
home because it is relatively small and does not require constant delivery of&#13;
untreated water. The BSF is a robust technology with no moving parts and can be&#13;
constructed using locally available materials.&#13;
&#13;
The most widely used version of the BSF is a concrete container approximately 0.9&#13;
meters tall and 0.3 meters square, filled with a layer of fine sand below which are&#13;
layers of gravel. The BSF is operated intermittently by pouring untreated water into&#13;
the top, which then flows down the length of the filter bed by gravity. Filtered water&#13;
exits the BSF from a bottom outlet pipe (usually PVC plastic) that is directed upwards&#13;
as a standpipe. Filtered water then flows from the standpipe into a bucket, bottle, or,&#13;
ideally, a safe storage container, which is not included with the BSF, but makes&#13;
usage much easier. Typical BSF flow rate is 0.75 liters per minute, which makes it&#13;
possible to obtain up to 45 liters of water in an hour18.&#13;
&#13;
There are four mechanisms within the BSF responsible for the removal of impurities.&#13;
First, the BSF standpipe exit is at a level that allows for a standing layer of water to&#13;
remain above the sand surface at all times, including the periods between&#13;
intermittent addition of untreated water to the top of the BSF. The maintenance of&#13;
shallow water above the sand bed allows a complex biological layer (or "schmutzdecke") to establish and remain on the surface&#13;
of the sand. This metabolically active microbial community contributes to the filtration mechanisms that trap and/or naturally&#13;
decompose disease-causing microorganisms and other dissolved impurities and particles in the untreated water. A recent study&#13;
has shown that microbial reductions improve as this biological layer matures (or "ripens") and when less than one pore volume of&#13;
water (the volume of water that the BSF is capable of holding) is filtered per day6. A rectangular plate with small holes (diffuser&#13;
plate), located several centimeters above the sand bed and standing water, prevents disruption of the biological surface layer&#13;
when untreated water is added to the BSF.&#13;
&#13;
Second, as the water continues to flow down the sand column, organisms become trapped in fine sand and may stick to sand&#13;
grains due to a static charge (adsorption).&#13;
&#13;
Third, as sand deep within the filter bed acquires a coating over time (referred to as "aged sand"), it becomes more effective at&#13;
absorbing microorganisms and other particles19. Finally and fourth, as water continues farther down the sand column, lack of&#13;
light and nutrients causes microbes to naturally die off.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              5&#13;
&amp;#12;    Success depends on a participatory and integrated approach involving health,&#13;
    hygiene, and sanitation education and promotion, training in BSF operation and&#13;
    maintenance, and continued monitoring of practices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Box 3: BSF Implementation in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
    In 1997, Samaritan's Purse Canada (SPC), an international relief organization, first introduced the BSF into Cambodia through&#13;
    technology workshops. SPC focuses on the BioSand Filter as a main component in improving health and quality of life, but also&#13;
    recognizes that success depends on a participatory and integrated approach involving health, hygiene, and sanitation education&#13;
    and promotion, training in BSF operation and maintenance, and continued monitoring of practices. The household water program&#13;
    employs a partial subsidization model, involving both financial participation and sweat equity, from individuals and communities.&#13;
&#13;
    The program engages local partners, including the NGOs Hagar Cambodia and Cambodia Global Action (CGA; formerly&#13;
    Assemblies of God), in BSF implementation into Cambodian communities. Hagar Cambodia began BSF implementation in 1999,&#13;
    and later trained CGA in the BSF technology. Both organizations target beneficiaries who are considered poor, living in rural&#13;
    communities, and are dependent mostly on contaminated surface and well water for drinking purposes. Hagar Cambodia and&#13;
    CGA work closely with SPC, receiving financial, technical, and managerial support. While some parts of their implementation&#13;
    programs are similar, there are differences as well. Globally, SPC and local partners have implemented more than 100,000 BSFs&#13;
    in the last 12 years and currently implement over 25,000 BSFs per annum.&#13;
&#13;
    Hagar Cambodia BSF Program&#13;
&#13;
    At the time of this study (2005-2007), the Hagar Cambodia BSF program operated in three provinces: Kampong Thom, Svay&#13;
    Rieng, and Kratie. Each province was covered by a construction / community health education team and in addition a mobile&#13;
    team moved to other provinces across the country to implement BSF projects and program activities. Commune leaders from&#13;
    rural communities in the provinces submitted written requests to apply for BSF projects for their community. Community meetings&#13;
    were then held by the Hagar Cambodia team to introduce and promote the BSF to villagers and to invite households to&#13;
    participate in health education meetings and training on the BSF. Priority was given to poor and single parent homes.&#13;
&#13;
    Interested households, who were able to contribute financially, paid 8000 Riel (approximately US$2) to participate in the BSF&#13;
    program. BSFs were constructed in batches of 10, with a member from each of the 10 participating households involved in&#13;
    construction of their BSF. Construction occurred in the morning hours under instruction and supervision from the construction&#13;
    managers. In the afternoon, participating family members prepared filter media by washing pre-sifted sand and gravel extracted&#13;
    from Charam Mountains in the Kompong Speu Province of Cambodia. Each family was required to collect and transport their&#13;
    BSF to their home two days after construction, with the wait allowing for curing of the filter. Each BSF was installed by one of the&#13;
    Hagar Cambodia teams with assistance from an individual in the household. A household caretaker was charged with&#13;
    maintaining the BSF on a daily basis, typically the mother or the elder daughter. Money from the participating households was&#13;
    placed in a fund that was used for the construction of latrines or wells for the community.&#13;
&#13;
    In addition, each household was required to attend a BSF training session and a health education meeting hosted by Hagar&#13;
    Cambodia staff. Households received a printed brochure with pictures portraying BSF use and maintenance. The Hagar team&#13;
    returned one and three months following installation to monitor BSF use and to answer any questions the households may have&#13;
    had. A third follow-up visit was conducted between 6­12 months after the first follow-up visit. The Hagar Cambodia concrete&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                          Use of BioSand Filters in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BSF program has installed the largest&#13;
number of BSFs in Cambodia (more&#13;
than 25,000 at the time of this study;&#13;
approximately 45,000 presently) by an&#13;
NGO.&#13;
&#13;
CGA BSF Program&#13;
&#13;
To target and survey communities that&#13;
would benefit from the BSF program,&#13;
CGA used Participatory Rural&#13;
Appraisal, an approach in which the&#13;
rural community aids in the planning&#13;
and management of development&#13;
projects. Suitability was not only based&#13;
on need for safe water access, but&#13;
was also determined by other factors,&#13;
including support from community&#13;
leaders, agricultural activities and&#13;
practices, community water sources,&#13;
socio-economic status of households&#13;
in the community, and willing&#13;
                                           Having to carry water home over a long distance limits the amount used.&#13;
volunteers to form committees.&#13;
&#13;
A Program Unit (PU) composed of a coordinator, three trainers, the Provincial Department of Rural Development (PDRD), and the&#13;
participating villagers elected Village Development Committees (VDCs) who were trained to manage and coordinate the BSF&#13;
project. The VDC recruited volunteers from the community and trained them about health and hygiene, sanitation, and water.&#13;
Interested households attended weekly meetings about the BSF program prior to receiving a BSF. VDCs were active in the&#13;
community for two months prior to the start of BSF installations. BSF beneficiaries were expected to contribute 8000 to 12,000&#13;
Riel (US$2­$3) for a filter.&#13;
&#13;
Three villagers were recruited to form a Program Management Committee (PMC) to help manage the BSF program in the&#13;
community by monitoring installations, troubleshooting problems with the BSF, and conducting follow up. The PMC was&#13;
responsible for purchasing materials for construction, washing the filter media, assisting with the construction, finding water for&#13;
installation, and conducting follow-up two months post-installation. Households were required to contribute two hours of&#13;
construction labor as well as arrange for transport of the BSF to their house. Each household was also given instructions on BSF&#13;
use and maintenance. Money collected by the PMCs was applied to training materials and activities. PMC members were paid a&#13;
small amount to install the BSFs (2000­3000 Riel or US$0.50­$0.75 per filter).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                         7&#13;
&amp;#12;       The study had two main objectives: To find out about continued use of the BSF&#13;
       as well as factors influencing use or disuse, and to determine the impact of the&#13;
       filter on water quality and diarrhoea.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Table 2: Comparison of BSF implementation programs in Cambodia at the time of the study&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        HAGAR CAMBODIA                                          CGA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Implementation Strategy                                 Community-based, NGO-subsidized                   Community-based, NGO-subsidized&#13;
                                                               intervention projects; sales to NGOs                   intervention projects&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Focus                                               Community-based, provincial construction            Participatory Rural Appraisals, Volunteer&#13;
                                                                     and health teams                            Development Committee (VDC), and&#13;
                                                                                                              Program Management Committees (PMC)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Beneficiary Contribution                                     Financial, labor (sand washing, construction), transportation, attend health&#13;
                                                                                               and hygiene training.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Manufacturing Model                                 Manufactured by participating households,           Constructed by CGA staff, participating&#13;
                                                                 supervised by program staff                         households, and the VDC&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Media                                                                   Media sand is crushed rock pre-sifted using 1 mm mesh&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Quality Control Measures                               Follow up at 1 month, 3 months, 6-12            Follow up at 1 and 2 months, and ongoing&#13;
                                                                   months after filter installation                 at the request of the household&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Unit Production Costa                                               US$15.50b, including plastic storage container for treated water&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Replacement Parts Cost                                      There are no replacement parts; US$2.50 for a new water storage container&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Participation Cost to Users                                                US$2c                         US$1-$3, depending on local costs of&#13;
                                                                                                                            materialsc&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Training                                          BSF training in community groups and at the             BSF training at the household level;&#13;
                                                         household level during installation; community          community health education training&#13;
                                                           health group training sessions hosted by&#13;
                                                                      health trainer (staff)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Total Filters Built to Date                                                45,000                                        8,000&#13;
       (June 2009)&#13;
&#13;
a Not including labor, transportation, education materials, etc.&#13;
b As of 2009 unit production cost is approximately US$19 including water storage container&#13;
c As of 2009, participation cost to users is US$4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   8&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                     Use of BioSand Filters in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Study Design                                     Cambodia and CGA master lists were&#13;
                                                 chosen for the cross-sectional study. Both&#13;
                                                                                                                family or household was living in the original&#13;
                                                                                                                location where they had received the BSF,&#13;
And Materials                                    organizations keep records of BSF recipient                    and (3) willingness to participate in the&#13;
                                                 households for follow-up and quality control                   study. A field staff team was composed of&#13;
The current study was carried out to             programs. While the information gathered                       one study coordinator and six local staff. A&#13;
address the two key questions:                   on BSF communities and households by                           trained field staff member approached&#13;
  1. An initial cross-sectional survey of        each organization differs, their records were                  eligible households for agreement to&#13;
     households previously provided with         considered adequately representative and                       participate in the cross-sectional study. The&#13;
     BSFs to determine continued use and         complete for the purposes of this study.                       cross-sectional study examined the&#13;
     factors that influenced use or disuse.                                                                     continued use of BSFs in households that&#13;
  2. A epidemiological study of a selection      Inclusion criteria for participating                           were part of large-scale BSF&#13;
     of the cross-sectional households still     households in the cross-sectional study                        implementation programs. Data were&#13;
     using the BSF (intervention) and            were: (1) the household had received a BSF                     collected from cross-sectional households&#13;
     similar households not using a BSF          from the implementing organization, (2) the                    for a number of key variables, including BSF&#13;
     (controls) to determine the impact of&#13;
     the BSF on water quality and&#13;
     diarrheal disease.                             Figure 2: Overview of the study approach of the BSF in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Cross-Sectional Study Design&#13;
                                                                                                21,000+ households with BSF&#13;
and Methods&#13;
&#13;
To determine continued use and factors&#13;
that influenced use or disuse of the BSF, a&#13;
master list of all households from both                                 175 randomly selected&#13;
                                                                          Hagar households&#13;
                                                                                                                               175 randomly selected&#13;
                                                                                                                                 CGA households&#13;
Hagar Cambodia and CGA programs was&#13;
compiled. The study population consisted&#13;
of households in communities that had at&#13;
least 20 BSFs. The BSF projects by Hagar                                                 CROSS-SECTIONAL STUDY&#13;
Cambodia were located in 11 provinces                                                          336 households interviewed&#13;
                                                                                           (14 were not qualified to participate)&#13;
throughout Cambodia, where they&#13;
introduced approximately 19,600 BSFs&#13;
between 2001 and 2006. However, the&#13;
majority of their BSFs were installed in three                                              105a BSF intervention households&#13;
provinces: Kampong Thom, Kratie, and                                                      (approximately 50% Hagar/50% CGA)&#13;
&#13;
Svey Rieng. Between 2002 and 2006, CGA&#13;
introduced 2,668 BSFs largely in two                                                      EPIDEMIOLOGICAL STUDY&#13;
provinces: Kandal and Kampong Speu.&#13;
These were the five provinces included in&#13;
the present study (Figure 3).                                                               102 matched control households&#13;
                                                                                                   (without a BSF)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
As depicted in Figure 2, a random selection&#13;
of 175 BSF households from both Hagar            a Two additional households quit prior to the completion of the study&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                     9&#13;
&amp;#12;     All participating households were required to have at least one child under the&#13;
     age of five years living in the household, as differences in diarrheal disease rates&#13;
     in this age group were the main outcome of interest in the longitudinal study.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
operation and maintenance, water source         socio-economic status, water-handling                        The type of study used to determine health&#13;
and sanitation. These variables were            practice, sanitation and hygiene practices,                  impact is properly called a "Longitudinal&#13;
analyzed for association with BSF use and       and other health-related behaviors. Data                     Prospective Cohort Study" (see also the&#13;
are described in detail below. Other            were collected from the months of                            glossary). To determine the impact of the&#13;
technical, behavioral and economic factors      November 2006 to January 2007 and were                       BSF on water quality (E. coli reduction) and&#13;
possibly influencing the decision of BSF use    analyzed to determine factors associated                     diarrheal disease in user (intervention)&#13;
or disuse may also deserve further              with long-term BSF use by utilizing                          households as compared to non-user&#13;
consideration, but were beyond the scope        unadjusted odds ratios.                                      (control) households, households initially&#13;
of this study. Using analysis of "yes/no"                                                                    recruited for the cross-sectional survey were&#13;
outcomes to questions (also called bivariate    Epidemiological Study Design and                             randomly selected for the longitudinal study.&#13;
analysis), unadjusted odds ratios (OR) were     Methods                                                      Fifty-three households were randomly&#13;
generated for each factor and were&#13;
considered statistically significantly            Figure 3: Map of Cambodian provinces included in the study&#13;
associated with continued BSF use if the&#13;
OR was &gt;1 and the 95% confidence&#13;
interval (CI) did not contain any values&#13;
smaller than 1.0. Likewise, a factor was&#13;
considered statistically significantly&#13;
associated with BSF disuse if the OR was&#13;
&lt;1 and the 95% CI did not contain any&#13;
values larger than 1.0 (see glossary for&#13;
further explanation of terminology).&#13;
&#13;
BSFs were considered "in use" if:&#13;
  1. The BSF was in working order. Visual&#13;
     inspection of the top layer of the&#13;
     sand, measurement of the biofilm&#13;
     depth, examination of the diffuser&#13;
     plate placement, examination of the&#13;
     area surrounding the filter outlet,&#13;
     measurement of flow rate, and other&#13;
     indicators consistent with filter use&#13;
     were performed to determine if all&#13;
     filter parts were intact and functional;&#13;
     and&#13;
  2. Households reported that the BSF&#13;
     was used at least once within the             [This map is for illustrative purposes and does not imply&#13;
     previous week.                                the expression of any opinion on the part of the authors&#13;
                                                   or publishers of this report concerning the legal status of&#13;
                                                   any country or territory or concerning the delimitation of&#13;
The study also examined filter use practices       frontiers or boundaries.]&#13;
and user acceptance and collected&#13;
information on household demographics,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   10&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   Use of BioSand Filters in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                filtration was used according to standard&#13;
                                                                                                methods, with substitutions for biological&#13;
                                                                                                media, to assay for total coliform and E. coli&#13;
                                                                                                concentrations (colony forming units per&#13;
                                                                                                100 ml). Turbidity (NTU; see glossary) was&#13;
                                                                                                measured by a Hach® turbidimeter.&#13;
                                                                                                All participating households in the study&#13;
                                                                                                were provided with a household water and&#13;
                                                                                                hygiene kit that included a 20-liter water&#13;
                                                                                                storage container with a sealable lid, multi-&#13;
                                                                                                purpose soap, cleaning brush, and oral&#13;
                                                                                                rehydration sachets at the completion of the&#13;
                                                                                                study (after final surveys and water samples&#13;
                                                                                                collected) as material compensation for their&#13;
                                                                                                willingness to participate in the longitudinal&#13;
Washing the media prior to filling the filter.&#13;
                                                                                                study. The water kits were provided at no&#13;
                                                                                                cost to the household and distributed by&#13;
selected from the cross-sectional list from      per month) between January 2007 and May        the field team in July 2007, after the fifth&#13;
Hagar Cambodia project sites in Kampong          2007. Longitudinal interviews were intended    household visit.&#13;
Thom, Kratie, and Svey Rieng Provinces           to capture information on diarrheal disease&#13;
and 51 households were randomly selected         for each family member based on a 7-day&#13;
from CGA project sites in Kandal and             recall period by the respondent as well as&#13;
Kampong Speu Provinces. Each                     water and hygiene practices, education,&#13;
intervention household recruited for the         and sanitation.&#13;
longitudinal prospective cohort study was&#13;
then matched with a control household            Household drinking water samples were&#13;
located within 1 kilometer from the              also collected from intervention and control&#13;
intervention household. All participating        households. Three types of household&#13;
households were required to have at least        drinking water samples from each BSF&#13;
one child under the age of five years living     household were collected during each visit:&#13;
in the household, as differences in diarrheal    drinking water source prior to treatment,&#13;
disease rates in this age group were the         BSF-treated water (effluent), and stored&#13;
main outcome of interest in the longitudinal     BSF-treated water. Two types of water&#13;
study.                                           samples from each control household were&#13;
                                                 collected during each visit: drinking water&#13;
A trained field staff member approached          source and stored drinking water&#13;
eligible households for consent to               (occasionally treated by another method).&#13;
participate in the longitudinal study. To        Laboratory analyses of water samples were&#13;
account for changes over time in both            conducted in the environmental&#13;
water quality and community diarrheal            microbiology laboratory at Resource&#13;
disease burdens, field staff visited each        Development International Cambodia (RDIC)      More than 300 households were interviewed by&#13;
household five times (approximately once         in Kien Svay (Kandal Province). Membrane       trained field staff.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                   11&#13;
&amp;#12;    Results of this study indicate continued BSF use, in one case up to eight years,&#13;
    as well as significant water quality improvements and a substantial reduction in&#13;
    diarrheal disease.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    BSF Sustainability&#13;
&#13;
    Ultimately, sustainability of POU technologies can be demonstrated if usage becomes part of the daily routine of every household&#13;
    member. Recent publications addressing sustainability have identified the BSF as having the potential to achieve sustained and&#13;
    consistent use, as it involves a one-time purchase, requires little time and effort to use, produces sufficient water for daily use,&#13;
    and improves appearance and often the taste of water21,22. Results of this study indicate continued BSF use, in one case up to&#13;
    eight years, as well as significant water quality improvements and a substantial reduction in diarrheal disease. Additional work&#13;
    examining the sustainability and disease reduction of the BSF in Cambodia should consider how eliminating subsidies may&#13;
    influence these findings. Based on the results here and in other work, future studies in Cambodia should evaluate additional&#13;
    factors related to sustainability of BSF and other technologies such as: seasonal changes in water usage, use of arsenic-&#13;
    contaminated water, technical alterations to the BSF that improve production and distribution, specific implementation models,&#13;
    and possibly other social, behavioral, and economic influences. While opinions regarding scale-up of POU technologies differ,&#13;
    there is general agreement that longer-term studies (such as this one) are required to provide better evidence of continued&#13;
    behavior change, sustained product performance, and health impact.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Results For Cross-                             study, with an average household size of&#13;
                                               5.9 people. Females made up 51% of the&#13;
                                                                                                reported using some form of water&#13;
                                                                                                treatment. When questioned about the uses&#13;
Sectional Assesment                            participants.                                    for treated water, 99% of respondents&#13;
                                                                                                reported for the purpose of drinking, 67%&#13;
Of Contimued Use                               Select Water, Sanitation, and                    for washing or preparing food, 30% for&#13;
Of BSF                                         Hygiene Findings                                 washing dishes and kitchen equipment,&#13;
                                                                                                10% for washing hands, and 7% for&#13;
Out of the 350 randomly selected               In the survey, 47% of households reported        bathing water. The majority (91%) of families&#13;
households from Hagar Cambodia and             traveling less than 10 meters and 45%            reported that their chosen treatment&#13;
CGA master lists, a total of 336 households    traveled between 10 and 100 meters from          method always provided enough drinking&#13;
(96%) completed the cross-sectional survey     home to the water source. These                  water for the family.&#13;
conducted from November 2006 to January        percentages closely resemble findings in the&#13;
2007. Fourteen of the randomly selected        2005 Cambodia Demographic and Health             Of the 336 study households, nearly all&#13;
households did not meet inclusion criteria     Survey (CDHS)7, which reports that 42% of        (99%) reported using a container to store&#13;
and were not included in the study. Of         Cambodians have a drinking water source          water. The majority of storage containers for&#13;
those participating, 40% of households         on the household premises while 40% travel       treated water (66%) were made of plastic,&#13;
were located in Kandal Province, 9% in         less than 30 minutes roundtrip to retrieve       while traditional ceramic or concrete jars&#13;
Kampong Speu Province, 16% in Svay             drinking water.                                  were reported by 11% of the study&#13;
Rieng Province, 18% in Kampong Thom                                                             population. The vast majority of&#13;
Province, and 17% in Kratie Province. More     According to the CDHS, 60% of                    respondents (93%) reported cleaning their&#13;
households were selected from Kandal           Cambodians boil water prior to drinking          water storage containers, while only one-&#13;
Province because it was where the majority     while 2% use some form of filtration. More       half of respondents reported covering their&#13;
of CGA BSFs had previously been installed.     than 30% do not treat drinking water. In the     storage containers. Only 21% of&#13;
Overall, 1986 people participated in the       present study, nearly all study households       households reported using a safe method&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  12&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                     Use of BioSand Filters in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
(tap or pouring) to draw drinking water from&#13;
the water storage container.&#13;
&#13;
When questioned about BSF accessibility&#13;
for purchase either independently or&#13;
through implementing organizations, the&#13;
majority of households (74%) reported that&#13;
they could not be purchased in the area,&#13;
while 15% of respondents did not know. If&#13;
the BSF was broken or had problems, the&#13;
majority of the respondents (65%) said they&#13;
would seek help from the implementing&#13;
organization (CGA or Hagar Cambodia),&#13;
indicating that households recognize the&#13;
implementing organization as the main&#13;
                                                Families play a role in producing their own filter, here filling the mould with concrete.&#13;
resource for technical assistance with filter&#13;
problems.&#13;
                                                households in the cross-sectional study                         respondents, diarrhea can be prevented.&#13;
The 2005 CDHS also reports that only 22%        (60%) had access to sanitation facilities,                      The leading diarrhea prevention measures&#13;
of Cambodians have access to improved           while the remaining reported using grounds,                     reported were boiling water (78%), properly&#13;
sanitation. However, the majority of            fields, or plastic bags as places for                           preparing food (75%), and cleaning hands&#13;
                                                defecation. No households were connected                        (43%).&#13;
                                                to a conventional sewerage system. The&#13;
                                                vast majority of households (96%) had soap                      BSF Use and Disuse&#13;
                                                on the premises. Eighty-one percent of&#13;
                                                cross sectional households reported that                        Of the 336 households in the cross-&#13;
                                                the household members washed their                              sectional study, BSFs were considered "in&#13;
                                                hands with soap. Thirty households (9%)                         use" in 294 (87.5%) of households at the&#13;
                                                reported using other materials, such as                         time of the visit. Households reported using&#13;
                                                sand, to clean hands. Respondents                               an average of 46 liters of water from the&#13;
                                                reported practicing hand-washing after                          BSF per day, with an average of 13.6 liters&#13;
                                                defecation (70%), before preparing food                         per day being used specifically for drinking.&#13;
                                                (56%), after eating (83%), and after                            Households still using the BSF had been&#13;
                                                performing household or caretaking                              using them from six months (n=84) up to&#13;
                                                activities (23%).                                               eight years (n=1). As shown in Figure 4, the&#13;
                                                                                                                percentage of filters still in use (of total&#13;
                                                When households were asked about the                            households interviewed) did not decline&#13;
                                                cause(s) of diarrhea in children,                               over time. The proportion of BSFs in use is&#13;
                                                contaminated water was reported most                            not strongly associated with the length of&#13;
                                                often (70%), followed by food (66%), poor                       time elapsed between BSF installation in&#13;
                                                hygiene (66%), and other causes (23%).                          the household and follow up. When&#13;
Filling the Biosand Filter                      According to 90% of household                                   analyzed statistically, there was not a strong&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                    13&#13;
&amp;#12;    Three factors were statistically significantly associated with BSF disuse:&#13;
    inadequacy of filtered water quantity, boiling water as an alternative treatment&#13;
    method, or consuming water directly from the untreated water container or&#13;
    from the source.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
association between time in use and BSF&#13;
                                                   Figure 4: Percent of households (of total households interviewed, or n)&#13;
use (the OR = 0.99 but lowest CI value is&#13;
                                                   using the BSF at follow-up as a function of time (years) since&#13;
&lt;1.0)).&#13;
                                                   implementation, across all provinces&#13;
&#13;
While 12.5% of households were no longer&#13;
using a BSF, all non-user respondents&#13;
reported having used the BSF at some&#13;
point. Of those no longer using the BSF,&#13;
one-half provided a reason: 13 households&#13;
(62%) cited the dissatisfaction with color,&#13;
taste, or smell of the BSF-treated water; six&#13;
households (29%) reported they were&#13;
unable to fix a problem they encountered or&#13;
felt that the BSF did not work as they had&#13;
expected; and two households (10%)&#13;
reported that they gave the BSF away.                                        0-1    1-2    2-3    3-4    4-5   5-6     6-7     7-8&#13;
                                                                           (n=90) (n=77) (n=59) (n=43) (n=30) (n=6)   (n=8)   (n=1)&#13;
Eighty-three percent of households no&#13;
longer using the BSF reported that they&#13;
used at least one other form of water&#13;
treatment; the majority of these households&#13;
                                                water source were found to have a                   reported use of a dipper to dispense&#13;
reported settling as their primary treatment&#13;
                                                statistically significant association with          water were three times as likely to be&#13;
method.&#13;
                                                continued BSF use (Table 3).                        using their BSF at the time of survey&#13;
                                                                                                    compared to households that poured&#13;
Data were collected from cross-sectional&#13;
                                                · 63% of households using the BSF                   directly from the container or used a tap.&#13;
households for a number of key variables,&#13;
                                                  reported that they had received training&#13;
including BSF operation and maintenance,&#13;
                                                  in operation and maintenance of the             Three factors were statistically significantly&#13;
water source, sanitation, and wealth index.&#13;
                                                  BSF. While all households included in the       associated with BSF disuse: inadequacy of&#13;
These variables are analyzed for association&#13;
                                                  cross sectional study were at one time          filtered water quantity, boiling water as an&#13;
with BSF use and are described in detail&#13;
                                                  provided with BSF training or instruction,      alternative treatment method, or consuming&#13;
below. Other technical, behavioral and&#13;
                                                  these data suggest that 37% of cross            water directly from the untreated water&#13;
economic factors possibly influencing the&#13;
                                                  sectional households do not recall              container or from the source. All other BSF&#13;
decision of BSF use or disuse may also&#13;
                                                  receiving this information. Households          operation and maintenance variables&#13;
deserve further consideration, but were&#13;
                                                  who reported having received training           tested, including number of times the BSF&#13;
beyond the scope of this study.&#13;
                                                  were two times as likely to be using their      was used per day, type of storage&#13;
                                                  BSF at the time of the survey as                container, practices of covering storage&#13;
BSF Operation and Maintenance&#13;
                                                  compared to households who reported             container, cleaning the storage container or&#13;
                                                  they had not received training.                 filter spout, checking flow rate, how to&#13;
Several factors related to BSF operation&#13;
                                                                                                  resume flow rate, or whether the household&#13;
and maintenance practices were analyzed         · The method for dispensing water from&#13;
                                                                                                  had experienced a problem with the filter,&#13;
for association with continued BSF use. Of        the household storage container was&#13;
                                                                                                  were not found to be strongly associated&#13;
these, two factors related to operation and       also found to be strongly associated with&#13;
                                                                                                  with either continued use or disuse of the&#13;
maintenance and one factor related to             continued BSF use. Households that&#13;
                                                                                                  BSF.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  14&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                             Use of BioSand Filters in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Table 3: Factors statistically significant associated with continued BSF use&#13;
&#13;
                                                  Factor                                           BSF Users         Non-users        Unadjusted OR&#13;
                                                                                                    n = 294           n = 42            (95% CIa)&#13;
&#13;
     User reported receiving training on operation and maintenance&#13;
     of the BSFb                                                                                       184               19                 2.04&#13;
         Yes                                                                                           109               23             (1.01 ­ 4.16)&#13;
         No&#13;
&#13;
     Method of drawing water for drinking (observed by interviewer)&#13;
       Dipper or instrument                                                                            241               25                 3.09&#13;
       Pour/Tap                                                                                         53               17             (1.56 ­ 6.13)&#13;
&#13;
     Use of deep wellc as drinking water source&#13;
       Deep well                                                                                       142               11                 2.63&#13;
       All other sources                                                                               152               31             (1.27 ­ 5.40)&#13;
a 95% confidence interval&#13;
b Data missing from one BSF user household&#13;
c Deep well was defined as a well with a depth greater than 10 meters&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Water Source                                               category, households were classified by&#13;
                                                           whether they had or had not used a source&#13;
Cross-sectional study participants reported                in that category during the rainy season. Of&#13;
water source(s) that they used during the                  the water source data analyzed, use of&#13;
rainy season (Table 4). When considering all               deep wells was the only factor found to&#13;
water sources used, rainwater was the                      have a statistically significant association&#13;
most widely used water source for both                     with continued BSF use. Households using&#13;
BSF households (67%) and non-BSF                           deep wells as a drinking water source were&#13;
households (64%), followed by deep wells                   2.6 times as likely to be using the BSF at&#13;
(48% and 26%, respectively), and then                      the time of survey compared to households&#13;
surface waters (38% and 52%,                               using other sources of drinking water (also&#13;
respectively).                                             shown in Table 3)&#13;
&#13;
Water sources that the study households                    Sanitation &amp; Hygiene&#13;
used in the rainy season were examined in&#13;
relationship to continued BSF use. Water                   Nearly 60% of BSF households and 67% of&#13;
source types were grouped according to                     non-BSF households reported having&#13;
three main source categories: vulnerable                   access to sanitation; however no&#13;
water (surface waters including lakes,                     statistically significant association between&#13;
ponds, rivers, streams, channels, and                      continued use or disuse of the BSF and&#13;
shallow wells), protected ground water                     access to sanitation was found. Soap was&#13;
(wells deeper than 10 meters), and                         observed in the vast majority of BSF and&#13;
rainwater. For each main water source                      non-BSF households (97% and 93%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                             15&#13;
&amp;#12;     Access to improved sanitation was 56% for BSF households and 39% for&#13;
     control households, which is higher than the national average of 22% reported&#13;
     in the CDHS.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Table 4: Drinking water sourcesa during the rainy season reported by cross-sectional participants (number of&#13;
   households reporting and percent of all reportedb)&#13;
                        Source                                        No. (%c) Using BSF                           No. (%c) Not Using BSF&#13;
                       Rainwater                                               196 (67%)                                     27 (64%)&#13;
&#13;
               Deep well (&gt;10 meters)                                          142 (48%)                                     11 (26%)&#13;
&#13;
              River, stream, or channel                                        51 (17%)                                      11 (26%)&#13;
                      Shallow well                                             40 (14%)                                       8 (19%)&#13;
&#13;
                     Lake or pond                                               21 (7%)                                       3 (7%)&#13;
                       Tap inside                                                3 (1%)                                       6 (14%)&#13;
&#13;
                      Tap outside                                                3 (1%)                                       0 (0%)&#13;
                Purchased and Other                                             11 (4%)                                       0 (0%)&#13;
a Households could report use of more than one source&#13;
b Percentage based on total households in BSF-usage category (BSF user = 294; BSF non-users = 42)&#13;
c Values may not add up to 100% due to rounding&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
respectively; the presence of soap                      intervention group, resulting in a final total of   19% were children under the age of five&#13;
demonstrated a positive, but not statistically          105 intervention households (Figure 2). Of          years. Other demographic factors of the&#13;
significant association with continued BSF              the households surveyed, there were a total         longitudinal study households are presented&#13;
use. No significant association between                 of 1365 individuals; 53% were female and            in Table 5.&#13;
washing hands with soap and continued&#13;
BSF use or between the belief that diarrhea&#13;
can be prevented and continued BSF use&#13;
                                                              Box 4: Sanitation Access in Study Households&#13;
was found.&#13;
&#13;
                                                              It is noteworthy that sanitation access and the hygiene proxies of soap presence&#13;
Results For                                                   and reported hand washing with soap in the study households were generally&#13;
                                                              high. Access to improved sanitation was 56% for BSF households and 39% for&#13;
Longitudinal Study                                            control households, which is higher than the national average of 22% reported in&#13;
                                                              the CDHS. The reasons for this greater access to sanitation and hygiene are&#13;
Study Participants and Households                             uncertain, but could be related to the promotion of water, sanitation, and hygiene&#13;
                                                              by the two BSF implementing organizations, Hagar Cambodia and CGA.&#13;
A total of 209 households from the cross-                     Furthermore, sanitation coverage in Cambodia varies greatly with household&#13;
sectional study were recruited to take part                   income level, by village, by commune, and by province, so it was not unexpected&#13;
in the longitudinal study. The intervention                   to find such differences from the national average and among provinces in this&#13;
group originally consisted of 107                             study23,24. Important to the results of this study on BSF impact are the findings&#13;
households using BSFs and the control                         that rates for sanitation access, presence of soap, and hand-washing with soap&#13;
group consisted of 102 matched                                were not significantly different between BSF and control households.&#13;
households that had never had BSFs. Only&#13;
two households were lost to follow up in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   16&#13;
&amp;#12;   Table 5: Demographic characteristics of longitudinal study households, by intervention statusa&#13;
                                 Characteristic                                                     BSF group                                     Control group&#13;
&#13;
   Total participants                                                                                722 (53%)                                      643 (47%)&#13;
   Number of females                                                                                 373 (52%)                                      356 (55%)&#13;
   Number of participants &lt; 5 years of age                                                           134 (19%)                                      135 (21%)&#13;
   Total households                                                                                        105                                            102&#13;
   Average household size                                                                                   6.8                                            6.3&#13;
   Province (by household)                                                                              N = 105                                        N = 102&#13;
   Kandal                                                                                              39 (37%)                                       36 (35%)&#13;
   Kampong Speu                                                                                        13 (12%)                                       13 (13%)&#13;
   Svay Rieng                                                                                          17 (16%)                                       17 (17%)&#13;
   Kampong Thom                                                                                        20 (19%)                                       20 (20%)&#13;
   Kratie                                                                                              16 (15%)                                       16 (16%)&#13;
   Formal education (by participants)                                                                  N = 722                                         N=634&#13;
   Has not attended school                                                                           171 (24%)                                      189 (29%)&#13;
   Primary school                                                                                    313 (43%)                                      295 (46%)&#13;
   High school                                                                                       225 (31%)                                      158 (25%)&#13;
   University                                                                                          10 (1%)                                        1 (&lt;1%)&#13;
   Training Courses                                                                                    3 (&lt;1%)                                         0 (0%)&#13;
   Reported receiving health education (by household)b                                                 N = 105                                         N = 102&#13;
   Yes                                                                                               104 (99%)                                        79 (77%)&#13;
   No                                                                                                   0 (0%)                                        23 (23%)&#13;
   Missing data                                                                                         1 (1%)&#13;
   Drinking water source in dry season (by household)d,e                                                N = 105                                        N = 102&#13;
   Surface water                                                                                       48 (46%)                                       51 (50%)&#13;
   Deep well                                                                                           48 (46%)                                       44 (43%)&#13;
   Rainwater                                                                                             4 (4%)                                         2 (2%)&#13;
   Other                                                                                                 5 (5%)                                         5 (5%)&#13;
   Treatment method used (by household)e                                                              N = 105                                          N = 102&#13;
   BSF                                                                                             105 (100%)                                           0 (0%)&#13;
   Boil                                                                                              71 (68%)                                         34 (33%)&#13;
   Settle                                                                                               1 (1%)                                        46 (45%)&#13;
   Chlorine                                                                                             1 (1%)                                        22 (22%)&#13;
   Other filtration method                                                                              0 (0%)                                        14 (14%)&#13;
   Cover water storage (by household)                                                                   N = 105                                        N = 102&#13;
   Yes                                                                                                 55 (52%)                                       48 (47%)&#13;
   No                                                                                                  50 (48%)                                       54 (53%)&#13;
   Observed method of drawing water (by household)                                                      N = 105                                        N = 102&#13;
   Tap / pour                                                                                          18 (17%)                                       28 (27%)&#13;
   Dipper / cup / other instrument                                                                     87 (83%)                                       54 (53%)&#13;
   Missing data/no response                                                                                                                           20 (20%)&#13;
   Access to sanitation (by household)c                                                                 N = 105                                        N = 102&#13;
   Yes                                                                                                 59 (56%)                                       40 (39%)&#13;
   No                                                                                                  46 (44%)                                       62 (61%)&#13;
                                                                                                       N = 105                                         N = 102&#13;
   Soap observed in house (by household)&#13;
                                                                                                     100 (95%)                                        96 (94%)&#13;
   Wash hands with soap (by household)                                                                  N = 105                                        N = 102&#13;
   Yes                                                                                                 82 (78%)                                       53 (52%)&#13;
   No                                                                                                  12 (11%)                                       49 (48%)&#13;
   Missing data/other                                                                                  11 (11%)&#13;
a Percentages may not equal 100% due to rounding or due to reports of multiple answers&#13;
b Health education was reported by participants from different sources including: radio, posters, school, health clinic or hospitals, village committee member, family member,&#13;
  NGO's, local pharmacy, etc. Topics related to health education included water management and use, sanitation and hygiene practices such as hand-washing, HIV/AIDS, food&#13;
  preparation, etc.&#13;
c Access to sanitation was defined has having access to a private or a shared toilet or latrine&#13;
d A well was considered deep if it had a depth of &gt;10 meters. Shallow wells were included in the surface water group&#13;
e Not mutually exclusive&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                              17&#13;
&amp;#12;      The majority of untreated water samples from both BSF and control households&#13;
      were in the high risk category.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Water Quality Analysis                                     determine if they were similar or different.             water that was used for drinking as well as&#13;
                                                           Microbial water quality was evaluated using              treated (by means other than the BSF) and&#13;
In this phase of the study water quality                   E. coli as the fecal indicator microbe. The              stored water. The total number of samples&#13;
analysis was done to determine both                        WHO categorizes drinking water quality into              vary per group depending on total number&#13;
untreated and treated water quality in BSF                 decimal risk levels according to                         of households providing samples at the time&#13;
and non-BSF households. The purpose of                     concentrations of E. coli per 100 ml. Low                of visit and the availability of different&#13;
the analysis was to determine the extent to                risk is considered 10 CFU E. coli per 100                samples at the time of visit. In addition, BSF&#13;
which BSF treatment improved the                           ml, intermediate risk is 11­100 CFU E. coli              household sampling began in December&#13;
microbial quality of water. In both BSF and                per 100 ml, and high risk as &gt;100 CFU E.                 2005 during initial recruitment from the&#13;
non-BSF households, treated water which                    coli per 100 ml25.                                       cross-sectional study whereas control&#13;
was stored was also analyzed for quality. In                                                                        household sampling began in January&#13;
the case of the BSF households the                         During each household visit over the five                2006.&#13;
determination of water quality of BSF-                     month longitudinal study, drinking water&#13;
treated water and BSF-treated and stored                   was collected from the household at the                  Untreated Water&#13;
water made it possible to determine the                    time of visit. Households with BSF&#13;
extent to which BSF-treated water became                   contributed the following samples during                 The majority of untreated water samples&#13;
re-contaminated after treatment and during                 this time: untreated water (before BSF                   from both BSF and control households&#13;
storage and use. In addition, both untreated               treatment), BSF-treated water directly from              were in the high risk category, with 540&#13;
and treated water quality in BSF and control               the BSF and BSF-treated and stored water.                samples from BSF households (73%) and&#13;
(non-BSF) households were compared to                      Control households provided untreated                    364 samples from control households (82%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Table 6: Number (percentage) of household drinking water samples in the longitudinal study by order-of-&#13;
     magnitude categories of E. coli concentration (CFU/100 ml)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                         E. coli Concentration (CFU/100 ml)&#13;
&#13;
                                                               &lt;1                    1 - 10                 11 - 100         101 ­ 1000             &gt;1000&#13;
&#13;
     WHO Microbial Risk Category                                          Low                           Intermediate                       High&#13;
&#13;
     BSF households&#13;
&#13;
     Untreated n=737                                       3 (&lt;1%)                  111 (15%)                 83 (11%)        375 (51%)            165 (22%)&#13;
&#13;
     Directly from BSF n=708                               28 (4%)                 402 (57%)               184 (26%)            72 (10%)              22 (3%)&#13;
&#13;
     BSF treated and stored n=589                          10 (2%)                 157 (27%)               181 (31%)          154 (26%)              87 (15%)&#13;
&#13;
     Control households&#13;
&#13;
     Untreated n=445                                         0 (0%)                    23 (5%)                58 (13%)        247 (56%)            117 (26%)&#13;
&#13;
     Treated and stored n=147                                4 (3%)                  72 (49%)                39 (27%)           24 (16%)               8 (5%)&#13;
&#13;
a E. coli CFU (colony forming units) per 100 ml&#13;
b Treated by some means other than BSF including boiling, chlorination, or other treatment reported by households&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   18&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    Use of BioSand Filters in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
categorized as having &gt;100 E. coli per 100     average 82%.                                      improvement in water quality following BSF&#13;
ml (Table 6; Figure 5). The geometric mean                                                       treatment.&#13;
E. coli concentrations in untreated water of   E. coli concentrations in untreated, BSF-&#13;
BSF and control households were 170 and        treated and BSF-treated and stored waters         BSF-Treated and Stored Water&#13;
355 E. coli per 100 ml, respectively.          from BSF households based on samples&#13;
Average turbidities for water in BSF and       analyzed during the five month intervention       As shown in Table 6 and Figure 5 above,&#13;
control households also were high and          period are summarized as box-and-whisker          29% of BSF-treated and stored water&#13;
above the WHO-recommended maximum              plots in Figure 6b. As seen in this figure, the   samples fell in the low risk category ( 10 E.&#13;
of 5 NTU, at14.2 and 8.6 NTU, respectively.    middle 50% of readings of E. coli for             coli/100ml), while 41% of these samples&#13;
(Table 7). Untreated waters of BSF and non-    untreated water (blue box on left) and BSF-       were in the high-risk category ( 100 E.&#13;
BSF households had similar E. coli             treated water (red box in the middle) do not      coli/100ml). BSF-treated and stored water&#13;
concentrations as can be seen in the plots     overlap, indicating significant improvements      samples had a geometric mean E. coli&#13;
in figure 6a.                                  in quality and reduced concentrations of E.       concentration of 51 CFU E. coli per 100 ml&#13;
                                               coli after treatment. Furthermore, statistical    (intermediate risk) and an arithmetic mean&#13;
Treated Water                                  tests comparing untreated water and BSF-          turbidity of 2.8 NTU. As shown in Table 7,&#13;
                                               treated water confirm significantly different     BSF treated and stored water compared to&#13;
Compared to untreated water, a much            concentrations of E. coli between the two         untreated water has 69% lower average E.&#13;
higher percentage of water samples were        Overall, these reductions in concentrations       coli concentration and an 80% lower&#13;
low or intermediate risk for E. coli after     of E. coli bacteria and turbidity (Table 7,       turbidity.&#13;
either BSF treatment (89% directly from the    Figure 6b) represent a significant&#13;
filter), after BSF treatment and storage&#13;
(60%) and after treatment and storage in&#13;
                                                  Figure 5: Percentage of BSF household untreated, BSF treated and BSF-&#13;
non-BSF households (79%) (Table 6 and&#13;
                                                  treated + stored drinking water samples from the longitudinal study grouped&#13;
Figure 5).                                        by order-of-magnitude categories of E. coli concentration (CFU/100 ml).&#13;
&#13;
BSF-Treated Water&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                             Untreated source water&#13;
As shown in Tables 6 and 7, 61% of BSF-&#13;
                                                                                                             Direct from BSF&#13;
treated water samples collected directly                                                                     BSF treated and stored&#13;
from the BSF outlet pipe were in the WHO&#13;
low risk category and only 13% of these&#13;
samples were in the high-risk category&#13;
(Table 6 and 7; Figure 5). Furthermore, as&#13;
shown in Table 7, treated water samples&#13;
taken directly from the BSF outlet of BSF&#13;
households had a geometric mean of 8.1&#13;
CFU E. coli per 100 ml (WHO low risk&#13;
category) and the arithmetic mean turbidity&#13;
was 2.6 NTU. Overall, the average&#13;
reduction of E. coli concentration following&#13;
BSF-treatment was 95%. Turbidity of the&#13;
BSF-treated water was reduced by an&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                    19&#13;
&amp;#12;      Overall, the average reduction of E. coli concentration following BSF-treatment&#13;
      was 95%. Turbidity of the BSF-treated water was reduced by an average 82%.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                             Figure 6a; Log10 E. coli concentrations of untreated water samples from BSF&#13;
                                                             (n = 737) and control households (n = 445), across five household visits.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
As compared to water samples collected&#13;
directly from the BSF outlet, water that was&#13;
treated by the BSF and then stored had a&#13;
higher percentage of high-risk samples&#13;
(41%) and a decreased percentage of low-&#13;
risk samples (29%) compared to BSF-&#13;
treated water taken directly from the filter&#13;
outlet (13% high risk and 61% low risk,&#13;
respectively) (Table 6; Figure 5). E. coli&#13;
concentrations in BSF-treated and stored&#13;
water were on average 0.8 log10 higher&#13;
than those of BSF-treated water collected&#13;
directly from the outlet pipe. By statistical&#13;
t-test, the E. coli concentrations of these&#13;
groups were statistically significantly&#13;
                                                           The figure shows the median of the distribution of samples (line in box), the interquartile range (25%-75% of results,&#13;
different (p&lt;0.0001).&#13;
                                                           bottom and top of box) and the 95% confidence intervals (upper and lower lines) of the distribution of samples for&#13;
                                                           untreated water. The dots show outliers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The use of cement jars for storage of rain water is very common in Cambodia.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   20&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                              Use of BioSand Filters in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Table 7: Water quality data of intervention and control households and reductions following treatment and storage&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     E. coli                  E. coli LRVa                     Turbidity                     Turbidity&#13;
&#13;
                                                             CFU/100 ml, Geom.                   (% Red.)                 Mean NTU (SD)                      (% Red.)b&#13;
                                                               Mean and (SD)&#13;
&#13;
      BSF households&#13;
&#13;
      Untreated n=737                                              170 (14)                                ---               14.2 (36.8)                           ---&#13;
&#13;
      Directly from BSFc n=708                                       8.1 (9)                      1.3 (95%)                    2.6 (11.7)                        82%&#13;
&#13;
      BSF treated &amp; stored n=589                                     51 (17)                     0.5 (69%)d                       2.8 (6.9)                      80%&#13;
&#13;
      Control households&#13;
&#13;
      Untreated n=445                                                355 (9)                               ---                 8.6 (17.1)                          ---&#13;
&#13;
      Treated &amp; stored n=147                                         12 (12)                      1.2 (94%)                    6.1 (10.2)                        29%&#13;
&#13;
NTU: Nephelometric units&#13;
CFU: colony forming units&#13;
                                                                 Figure 6b: Log10 concentrations of E. coli in the three types of water&#13;
SD: standard deviation&#13;
aLog reduction value of geometric mean                           samples of BSF households across five household visits: untreated&#13;
     10&#13;
bPercent reduction of arithmetic mean                            (n = 737), BSF treated (n = 708) and BSF treated and stored (n = 589).&#13;
cTreated water collected directly from the BSF outlet pipe&#13;
dReduction from untreated water&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
There was a slight (8%) but not statistically&#13;
significant increase in turbidity of BSF-&#13;
treated and stored water as compared to&#13;
BSF-treated water collected directly from&#13;
the BSF outlet. Overall, these results&#13;
indicate that a significant proportion of BSF-&#13;
treated water samples became&#13;
re-contaminated during storage. However,&#13;
despite recontamination during storage, the&#13;
concentrations of E. coli as well as turbidity&#13;
were still lower in BSF-treated and stored&#13;
water than in untreated water, and&#13;
represent a significant improvement in water&#13;
quality.&#13;
&#13;
Treated and Stored Water of Control&#13;
Households and of BSF Households                             The figure shows the median of the samples (line in box), the interquartile range (bottom and top of box) and the&#13;
                                                             95% confidence intervals of the distribution of samples.&#13;
In control households where water was&#13;
often treated by means other than BSF                        water (82%) in these control households                     level) and an arithmetic mean turbidity of&#13;
and then stored, this treated and stored                     (Table 6; Figure 5). The treated and stored                 6.1 NTU that exceeded the WHO-&#13;
water had a substantially lower percentage                   water samples of control households had a                   recommended limit of 5 NTU (Table 7). It is&#13;
of water samples in the WHO high-risk                        geometric mean E. coli concentration of 12                  noteworthy that the levels of E. coli in the&#13;
category (21%) as compared to untreated                      CFU per 100 ml (WHO intermediate risk                       treated and stored water of control&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                             21&#13;
&amp;#12;      In the current study, a wide range of LRVs was found between untreated and&#13;
      BSF-treated or BSF-treated and stored water, including the occurrence of&#13;
      negative LRVs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                               Figure (6c): Log10 E. coli concentrations of treateda and stored water&#13;
                                                               samples from BSF and control households over five visits.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
households at a geometric mean of 12 per&#13;
100 ml were lower than those of BSF-&#13;
treated and stored water at a geometric&#13;
mean of 51 CFU, although both are in the&#13;
WHO intermediate risk category of 10-100&#13;
per 100 ml This difference in E. coli levels is&#13;
also depicted in a box-and-whisker plot&#13;
(Figure 6c) in which median E. coli&#13;
concentrations and their interquartile ranges&#13;
are visibly different, even though they&#13;
overlap. The E. coli concentrations of these&#13;
two groups were also statistically&#13;
significantly different by an unpaired t-test                                                                                                        Direct from&#13;
                                                                                                                                                     BSF&#13;
(p&lt;0.0001).&#13;
&#13;
                                                            The figure shows the median (line in box), the interquartile range (bottom and top of box) and the 95% confidence&#13;
                                                            intervals (upper and lower lines) of the samples of treated water direct from BSF (n=708) and BSF-treated and stored&#13;
                                                            water (589) and treated and stored water from control households (n = 147). aTreatment in control households was&#13;
                                                            by some means other than BSF including boiling, chlorination, or other treatment reported by households.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Pond water is a much preferred drinking water source that can be significantly improved through treatment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   22&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                Use of BioSand Filters in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A Note on Microbial Log10 Reduction Values&#13;
&#13;
A microbial log10 reduction value (LRV) measures the extent of microbial reduction&#13;
when untreated water is subjected to a microbial treatment process, such as the&#13;
BSF. Brown et al.11 have suggested that LRVs alone may be misleading. The LRV is&#13;
a function of both the influent concentration and the effluent concentration of the&#13;
microbes being tested. Therefore, low or non-detectable microbial concentrations in&#13;
the influent sample may lead to an underestimate of the LRV, regardless of the true&#13;
performance capability of the treatment process. Therefore, an uncensored or&#13;
discrete LRV for one sampling event alone cannot accurately document the ability of&#13;
the process to reduce microbes.&#13;
&#13;
In the current study, a wide range of LRVs was found between untreated and BSF-&#13;
treated or BSF-treated and stored water, including the occurrence of negative LRVs.&#13;
These situations, in which there was a higher microbial concentration in the BSF&#13;
effluent water than in the corresponding influent water collected during an individual&#13;
sampling event, may be due to a number of factors:&#13;
&#13;
·   The volume of water that passes through the BSF may not be sufficient to&#13;
    displace the entire volume of water inside the filter bed. Due to fluctuation in&#13;
    source water quality or changes in source water used, treated samples collected          Before and after treatment.&#13;
    from the BSF may have originated from water with a different E. coli&#13;
    concentration than that of the untreated water sample taken on the day of the household visit. Therefore, sampling from the&#13;
    effluent water may not actually be indicative of the current quality of water being applied to the filter and may produce&#13;
    variable results.&#13;
&#13;
·   There may be a presence of high levels of E. coli in the biofilm (schmutzdecke) of the BSF from previously applied water&#13;
    having high E. coli levels. This could lead to the passage of some previously retained E. coli through the sand media and&#13;
    into the treated water.&#13;
&#13;
·   Some bacteria, such as E. coli, may grow in stored water and in storage vessels, which can result in underestimation of the&#13;
    ability of the BSF to reduce these bacteria. In order to reduce post-filtration fecal contamination, a container with a tap or a&#13;
    narrow opening that discourages other objects from being placed into the treated water is recommended . The extent to&#13;
    which E. coli growth that may have occurred in stored water or storage containers was not documented in this study.&#13;
&#13;
·   BSF components that come into contact with the BSF-treated water may be contaminated with E. coli. The water outlet&#13;
    spigot is the only part of the BSF outlet tube that is accessible to the user and it can be a source of contamination if&#13;
    exposed to E. coli from fecal contamination (such as on a person's finger) and is not properly cleaned. This is more likely in&#13;
    households where the BSF is easily accessible to animals, children, and other environmental contamination.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                23&#13;
&amp;#12;    The rates of diarrhea for the intervention households were consistently lower&#13;
    than the rates for the control households over the course of the study,.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Summarizing risk reduction&#13;
&#13;
    Using the relative risk categories of WHO for decimal concentration ranges of E. coli to categorize drinking water quality, we can&#13;
    summarize filter performance by cross tabulating the risk category of water entering the filter against the risk category of water&#13;
    exiting the filter. Results of this cross-tabulation are shown below. The summary only applies to BSF users, and does not take&#13;
    into account changes in water quality due to storage. It is thus a simple summary of the performance of the filters alone. Of the&#13;
    706 samples analyzed, the vast majority (514 or 73%) showed a relative risk reduction in categorical E. coli concentration (the&#13;
    sum of all filters in the light green boxes), only some showed no change in E. coli concentration risk category (136 or 19%; all&#13;
    filters in the dark green boxes), and very few (56 or 8%) were in a higher risk E. coli concentration category than they initially were&#13;
    (indicated by the grey boxes). Thus, BSF filtration generally improved the microbial quality of filtered water based on this&#13;
    comparison of risk categories.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                E. coli in Untreated Water (influent), as No./100 ml&#13;
&#13;
    Risk                                          Low            Intermediate                       High&#13;
&#13;
    E. coli in Treated Water                      &lt; 10               11-100             101-1000              &gt;1000                Total&#13;
    (effluent), as No./100 ml&#13;
&#13;
    &lt;10                                            75                   51                 215                  87                 428&#13;
&#13;
    11-100                                         24                   20                  95                  45                 184&#13;
&#13;
    101-1000                                         9                   7                  35                  21                   72&#13;
&#13;
    &gt;1000                                            2                   1                  13                    6                  22&#13;
&#13;
    Total                                         110                   79                 358                 159                 706&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Health Impact                                   study, although each group experienced            often resulting in correlated cases of&#13;
                                                declining rates of diarrhea over the five-        diarrheal disease. Overall, when adjusting&#13;
Diarrheal Disease                               month observation period. The range of            for clustering and age of participants, there&#13;
                                                cases per person per year was between 4.4         was a clear association between BSF&#13;
Incidence rates of diarrheal disease were       and 6.3 for BSF households and between            households and reductions in cases of&#13;
calculated by dividing the number of            8.0 and 9.9 for control households.               diarrheal disease, as compared to non-BSF&#13;
reported cases by the total number of                                                             control households. Diarrheal disease&#13;
person-time of observation. The cases of        Statistical Analyses of Diarrheal                 reduction was 47%, and is considered&#13;
diarrhea per person-year for each group are     Disease Rates                                     statistically significant.&#13;
presented in Figure 7. The rates of diarrhea&#13;
for the intervention households were            Clustering occurs when participants are           As most diarrhea cases occur in younger&#13;
consistently lower than the rates for the       sampled over time or because multiple             children, an effort was made to estimate&#13;
control households over the course of the       participants live in the same household,          diarrhea disease risks for the years when&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  24&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                   Use of BioSand Filters in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                rates of diarrhea would be most impacted&#13;
   Figure 7: Cases of diarrhea per person per year by household group and&#13;
                                                                                in BSF households. Households were first&#13;
   visit (estimated from averages over five months)&#13;
                                                                                grouped according to age, with the age&#13;
                                                                                categories of less than five years, five to 14&#13;
                                                                                years, and 15 years and older, based on&#13;
                                                                                age at the time of the first household visit.&#13;
                                                                                Stratified odds ratios show a protective&#13;
                                                                                effect of the BSF on diarrhea disease&#13;
                                                                                occurrence, with reductions of 32%, 46%,&#13;
                                                                                and 51%, respectively (data not shown).&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                The data were stratified by the age&#13;
                                                                                categories of less than two years, two to&#13;
                                                                                four years, and five years and older. As&#13;
                                                                                shown in Table 8, the effect of the BSF on&#13;
                                                                                diarrheal disease occurrence in children less&#13;
                                                                                than five years of age was greatest in the&#13;
                                                                                two to four years age category (44%&#13;
                                                                                reduction). The diarrheal disease occurrence&#13;
                                                                                between BSF and control households in the&#13;
                                                                                less than two years age category was not&#13;
                                                                                statistically significantly different, as the 95%&#13;
     Table 8: Odds ratios and 95% confidence intervals for diarrheal disease    confidence interval of the unadjusted odds&#13;
     (filter as referent group)                                                 ratio spans the null value of 1.0. The age&#13;
                                                                                category of five years of age and older&#13;
                                     Unadjusted                  95%            shows a statistically significant association&#13;
                 Group&#13;
                                   Odds Ratio (OR)       Confidence Interval    between BSF and reduced cases of&#13;
                                                                                diarrhea.&#13;
                  Age&#13;
&#13;
                All ages                 0.56                  0.48 - 0.64&#13;
&#13;
                   &lt;2                    0.89                  0.63 - 1.24&#13;
&#13;
                  2-4                    0.56                  0.42 - 0.76&#13;
&#13;
                   5                     0.54                  0.41 - 0.60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      Adjusted                   95%&#13;
                 Group&#13;
                                   Odds Ratio (OR)a       Confidence Interval&#13;
&#13;
             &lt;2, 2 - 4, 5                0.53                  0.36 - 0.75&#13;
aAdjusted for clustering and age&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                   25&#13;
&amp;#12;     Both this BSF study and the previous CWP study documented that stored,&#13;
     treated water was subject to recontamination by E. coli.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DISCUSSION                                                   In the same study, there was a 2% rate of&#13;
                                                             disuse of CWPs each month after&#13;
                                                                                                           Pakistan. Furthermore, continued use of&#13;
                                                                                                           household water chlorination is consistently&#13;
Cross Sectional Study                                        installation, mostly due to ceramic filter    below 75% based on self-reporting and&#13;
                                                             breakage and the unavailability of            only about half that amount (&lt;40%) when&#13;
The cross-sectional study results indicate                   replacement parts, and the average time in    based on measured chlorine residuals in&#13;
that the BSF has a high uptake rate (88%)                    use was about two years. The present          household water21. In contrast, the BSF and&#13;
and sustained usage for as long as eight                     study identified that the BSF does not show   other household water filters are durable&#13;
years since acquisition. Uptake rate and                     the same rate of disuse that the CWP has      goods that require one-time acquisition.&#13;
continued use over time is a major limiting                  shown, likely because it is not prone to&#13;
factor to success of household water                         breakage or the need for replacement parts.   When statistically analyzed, the cross-&#13;
treatment technologies21. An independent                                                                   sectional study found that BSFs are more&#13;
appraisal of ceramic water purifiers in                      Uptake rates are also limited for treatment   likely to be used if:&#13;
Cambodia in 2006 found that ceramic                          methods that rely on consumable material&#13;
water purifiers (CWPs) were more likely to                   that require re-purchase, such as chlorine    · The household reported that they had&#13;
be used in households that had knowledge                     and coagulant-flocculant-disinfectants21.       received training in operation and&#13;
of safe water, sanitation and hygiene                        For example, 5-13% repurchase                   maintenance of the BSF. NGOs and&#13;
practices, purchased the technology, used                    proportions have been reported for the PUR      other implementers, using developed&#13;
surface water sources for drinking water,                    disinfectant treatment product in test          software and education for behavior&#13;
and did not use deep wells11.                                markets in Guatemala, the Philippines, and      modification in implementation programs,&#13;
                                                                                                             have increased the likelihood of&#13;
                                                                                                             continued BSF use after implementation.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                           · The method for dispensing water from&#13;
                                                                                                             the household storage container was by&#13;
                                                                                                             use of a dipping device. This method is&#13;
                                                                                                             considered a less safe practice as&#13;
                                                                                                             compared to using a tap or pouring&#13;
                                                                                                             stored water, as the dipping device may&#13;
                                                                                                             introduce contamination into the stored&#13;
                                                                                                             water26. Use of a dipper may be a reason&#13;
                                                                                                             why BSF-treated and stored water was&#13;
                                                                                                             found to have higher E. coli concen-&#13;
                                                                                                             trations than BSF-treated water taken&#13;
                                                                                                             directly from the outlet pipe. Proper&#13;
                                                                                                             storage and dispensing behaviors are&#13;
                                                                                                             areas that should be focused on in future&#13;
                                                                                                             BSF training programs. Furthermore,&#13;
                                                                                                             future studies and additional statistical&#13;
                                                                                                             tests assessing this phenomenon are&#13;
                                                                                                             required to fully understand the&#13;
                                                                                                             relationship between household water&#13;
There is no shortage of water in Cambodia. It is getting water of good quality that the BSF helps with.      management and BSF usage.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   26&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  Use of BioSand Filters in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              usage resulted in typical reductions of E.&#13;
                                                                                              coli bacteria between 1 and 3 log10 and&#13;
                                                                                              with average reduction of 95%. The CWP&#13;
                                                                                              independent appraisal11 showed similar&#13;
                                                                                              reductions of E. coli (95.1%) in treated&#13;
                                                                                              versus untreated household water.&#13;
                                                                                              However, both this BSF study and the&#13;
                                                                                              previous CWP study documented that&#13;
                                                                                              stored, treated water was subject to&#13;
                                                                                              recontamination by E. coli.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              The reasons for simultaneously declining&#13;
                                                                                              rates of diarrheal disease in intervention and&#13;
                                                                                              control groups over time are uncertain, but&#13;
                                                                                              they may be attributable to seasonal&#13;
                                                                                              fluctuation. Decreases in reported cases of&#13;
· A deep well (&gt;10 meters) was used as a       access during the rainy season. Factors        diarrheal disease have been observed in&#13;
  water source. Other studies have shown       that were found to be associated with BSF&#13;
  that the BSF often removes iron and          disuse include: inadequacy of filtered water&#13;
  therefore may reduce objectionable color,    quantity, boiling water as an alternative&#13;
  taste, and smell. A household may have       treatment method, and consuming water&#13;
  chosen to use the BSF for this reason.       directly from the untreated water container&#13;
  The use of the BSF associated with deep      or from the source.&#13;
  well use may also be related to the belief&#13;
  that deep wells may contain arsenic and      All other BSF variables tested, including&#13;
  that the BSF may have the capability to      those regarding operation and maintenance&#13;
  remove it. Household reasons for use of      and length of time elapsed between BSF&#13;
  the BSF to treat deep ground water were      installation in the household and follow-up,&#13;
  not able to be assessed in this study;       were found to not be strongly associated&#13;
  asking this in future studies may provide    with either continued use or disuse of the&#13;
  valuable information.                        BSF. Overall, the cross-sectional study&#13;
                                               documented high levels of long-term,&#13;
As the cross-sectional study assessing         continued use and acceptability of&#13;
continued BSF use was performed in the         previously implemented BSFs in Cambodia.&#13;
rainy season, one explanation for the disuse&#13;
of the BSF may be that people perceive the     Epidemiological Water Quality and&#13;
quality of rainwater to be higher and          Diarrhea Study&#13;
therefore do not need to filter their water.&#13;
Rainwater is unlikely to contain excessive     This portion of the study demonstrated that&#13;
iron or arsenic as deep ground water may,      use of a BSF improved the microbiological&#13;
so people may choose to use it because of      quality of drinking water at the household     The protective effect of the BSF is highest for children&#13;
its better quality, abundance, and ease of     level compared to control households. BSF      2-4 years old.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                  27&#13;
&amp;#12;    The age group most impacted by the BSF intervention was the group of two to&#13;
    four year olds, who showed a 44% reduction in diarrheal disease occurrence as&#13;
    compared to control households.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
other longitudinal household water              consistent with effects attributable to the   comparison to other studies also measuring&#13;
intervention studies, including a randomized    use of the BSF. However, there was a          health impact based on reduced diarrheal&#13;
controlled trial (RCT) and a post-              difference between the two groups             disease, the reduction of diarrhea by the&#13;
implementation prospective cohort study of      regarding hand-washing with soap. In the      BSF in this study was similar to that&#13;
concrete BSFs in the Dominican                  BSF-user group 83 households (79%)            observed for the ceramic filters, which&#13;
Republic28,29.In the Dominican Republic         washed their hands with soap, while in the    documented a 46% reduction of diarrhea&#13;
RCT, diarrhea rates increased after initially   control (non BSF-user) households, only 54    cases11. Further evidence of the protective&#13;
declining, which appeared to be related to      households (53%) did. These results           effect of the BSF comes from the&#13;
changes in rainfall28. Furthermore, study       suggest that people in BSF households         randomized controlled trial of the BSF in the&#13;
fatigue among the participants as the length    may have more knowledge or awareness          Dominican Republic, where there was a&#13;
of the study increased may have lead to         regarding water treatment and other           47% reduction of diarrheal disease rates for&#13;
less accurate reporting of diarrheal disease    hygiene and sanitation measures than          households using the BSF compared to&#13;
over time.                                      people in non-BSF households in this          control or non-BSF households28.&#13;
                                                longitudinal study.&#13;
Demographic characteristics of the control                                                    As children less than five years of age were&#13;
and the BSF household groups were very          Overall, the use of the BSF in households     a subgroup of interest in this study, data on&#13;
similar, which demonstrates that the            was associated with a 47% reduction in        diarrheal disease was analyzed by age&#13;
comparison of the two household groups          diarrheal disease as compared to              groups. The age group most impacted by&#13;
was appropriate and study results were          households not using the BSF. In              the BSF intervention was the group of two&#13;
                                                                                              to four year olds, who showed a 44%&#13;
                                                                                              reduction in diarrheal disease occurrence as&#13;
                                                                                              compared to control households. For the&#13;
                                                                                              group of less than two years of age, there&#13;
                                                                                              was no statistically significant association&#13;
                                                                                              between filter use and reduced diarrheal&#13;
                                                                                              illness, despite this group showing the&#13;
                                                                                              highest rates of diarrheal disease (15.6&#13;
                                                                                              cases per person per year). This may be&#13;
                                                                                              due to limited or no exposure to water from&#13;
                                                                                              the BSF because mothers may still be&#13;
                                                                                              breastfeeding. Furthermore, boiling water to&#13;
                                                                                              mix with powdered formula for babies may&#13;
                                                                                              be practiced as a more traditional form of&#13;
                                                                                              water treatment.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              Although the BSF may not achieve the&#13;
                                                                                              same level of indicator microorganism&#13;
                                                                                              removal as some other POU technologies, it&#13;
                                                                                              provides substantial reductions of diarrhea&#13;
                                                                                              in intervention households that are&#13;
                                                                                              comparable to the reductions achieved by&#13;
                                                                                              these other POU technologies. Currently, at&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  28&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  Use of BioSand Filters in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              least three review papers document both&#13;
                                                                                              improved drinking water quality and&#13;
                                                                                              reduced diarrheal disease by the use of&#13;
                                                                                              chlorine disinfection, combined chemical-&#13;
                                                                                              coagulation and chlorine disinfection, solar&#13;
                                                                                              disinfection, and ceramic filtration.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              The diarrheal disease reduction results from&#13;
                                                                                              this post-implementation evaluation of the&#13;
                                                                                              BSF in Cambodia are consistent with those&#13;
                                                                                              from this existing literature in documenting&#13;
                                                                                              the positive health impacts of household&#13;
                                                                                              water treatment technology interventions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
What about chemical water quality parameters?&#13;
&#13;
Why look at chemicals in water?&#13;
&#13;
A number of chemical contaminants have been shown to cause harmful health effects in humans as a result of long-lasting&#13;
exposure through drinking-water. Among those are arsenic, fluoride, nitrate and nitrite. Furthermore, iron and manganese are of&#13;
widespread significance because of their effect on acceptability of drinking water.&#13;
&#13;
While the health benefits of using BioSand filters for the reduction of microbiological contamination have been fairly well&#13;
documented, little research has focused on the removal of such chemical contaminants through BioSand filters, or how these&#13;
contaminants may affect the performance of the filters in the field. To address this concern, the performance of a number of&#13;
BioSand filters installed in rural Cambodia was evaluated over a six month period. This case study was carried out independently&#13;
from the main work reported in this field note, and only partial results are reported here.&#13;
&#13;
Background to the case study&#13;
&#13;
The study took place in Kesom and Popeal Kaye villages in Kandal Province, Cambodia, and consisted of two parts: Part 1-&#13;
Initial filter survey and Part 2- Water quality survey of 20 households over time. The initial study consisted of locating all BioSand&#13;
filters currently installed in these two villages: 81 were found, of which 59 were still in use. Once a filter was located, a survey was&#13;
conducted with the household and water samples were collected from the untreated source water for the filter and from the&#13;
treated water leaving the filter spout. From the 59 filters, 20 were chosen to be examined in more detail over a six month period.&#13;
These 20 households were visited once every two weeks to collect water samples and were asked a short questionnaire&#13;
regarding filter operation and maintenance. The household visits took place during the dry season. The dry season was chosen&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 29&#13;
&amp;#12; During the study period, on average 11 source waters exceeded the guideline&#13;
 value for combined nitrate and nitrite, while half the source waters exceeded the&#13;
 acute exposure value for nitrite. After treatment both numbers increased.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 because during this time households generally use water of poorer quality in their filters--such as well and surface water. During&#13;
 the rainy season, many households use rain water for their filters, which is considered of higher quality.&#13;
&#13;
 Water from the filters was analyzed for nitrate, nitrite, ammonia, manganese, iron, fluoride, turbidity, pH, color, total coliforms and&#13;
 E. coli. Arsenic was not considered, but a separate field note on arsenic in BioSand Filters is in preparation.&#13;
&#13;
 Microbiological results for E. coli in this separate study were consistent with the findings from the main study reported in this field&#13;
 note. The most significant findings of this additional research were the results for nitrite and nitrate, and these will be summarized&#13;
 here.&#13;
&#13;
 Why are nitrate and nitrite of concern?&#13;
&#13;
 The primary health concern regarding nitrate and nitrite is methaemoglobinaemia, or so called "blue-baby syndrome". This is a&#13;
 condition which occurs when nitrite oxidizes iron in the blood and limits the ability of oxygen to be transported around the body&#13;
 causing veins and skin to appear blue.&#13;
&#13;
 Bottle-fed infants under 1 year of age are at risk because of the potential intake of nitrate and nitrite from drinking water used to&#13;
 prepare formula, and the relatively high intake of water in relation to body weight.&#13;
&#13;
 Given this risk, WHO has established health-based guidelines for nitrate and nitrite in drinking water. The 2007 WHO Guidelines&#13;
 for Drinking-water Quality give the following guideline values:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              Acute exposure (mg/L)                         Long term exposure (mg/L)&#13;
&#13;
 Nitrate (as NO3-)                            50 mg/L (for bottle fed infants)              -&#13;
&#13;
 Nitrite (as NO2-)                            3 mg/L (for bottle fed infants)               0.2 mg/L (provisional value)&#13;
&#13;
 Combined                                                                                (C is concentration in mg/L)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Elevated levels of nitrate in surface and ground waters typically result from leaching or runoff from agricultural land (nitrate is mainly&#13;
used in inorganic fertilizer) or contamination from human or animal waste. Nitrite is formed (and persists) in water under oxygen-&#13;
poor conditions.&#13;
&#13;
What were the findings?&#13;
&#13;
Results from the 59 filters tested in part 1 of the study are summarized in the table below.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
30&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   Use of BioSand Filters in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 9: Number of filters exceeding the WHO guideline values for nitrate and nitrite (out of 59)&#13;
&#13;
                                                             Source water (in)                               Treated water (out)&#13;
&#13;
Nitrate &gt; 50 mg/L                                                       0                                                 0&#13;
&#13;
Nitrite &gt; 3 mg/L                                                    13                                                17&#13;
&#13;
Nitrite &gt; 0.2 mg/L                                                  22                                                49&#13;
&#13;
Sum of concentration ratios &gt; 1                                     14                                                22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Overall, 39 of the 59 filters saw an increase in nitrate and nitrite after treatment. For the 20 filters studied over a period of 6&#13;
months, average values are reported in the table below.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 10: Number of filters where average nitrate and nitrite concentrations over a six month period exceed WHO&#13;
guideline values (out of 20).&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    Treated water (out)&#13;
&#13;
                                                       Using surface water (N=9)                          Using well water (N=11)&#13;
&#13;
Nitrate  50 mg/L                                                    0                                                 0&#13;
&#13;
Nitrite  3 mg/L                                                     9                                                 8&#13;
&#13;
Nitrite  0.2 mg/L                                                   9                                                 8&#13;
&#13;
Sum of concentration ratios &gt; 1                                     9                                                 8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  During the study period, on average 11 source waters exceeded the guideline value for combined nitrate and nitrite, while&#13;
  half the source waters exceeded the acute exposure value for nitrite (3 mg/L). As can be seen from the table, after treatment&#13;
  both numbers increased. The average values of nitrate and nitrite in treated water hide large fluctuations though; the lower&#13;
  range for all nitrite measurements and for most nitrate measurements includes zero. This means that while on average 85%&#13;
  of the study households use water where nitrite (or combined nitrate/nitrite) values are exceeded, the exceedance is not&#13;
  constant, and long term effects may be hard to evaluate.&#13;
&#13;
  From the findings, it appears that biological nitrification and denitrification may both be taking place in the filter. These are&#13;
  microbially driven processes converting the different forms of nitrogen (ammonia to nitrite and nitrite to nitrate, as well as&#13;
  nitrate to nitrite and nitrite to nitrogen gas). A number of factors could be playing a role in these processes, including source&#13;
  water, frequency of filling and flow rate. However, further work will be required to determine the importance of these and&#13;
  other factors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                   31&#13;
&amp;#12; Building and using latrines to keep waste out of the environment is one step&#13;
 that can be taken to lower the risk of exposure to nitrate and nitrite.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 What are the recommendations?&#13;
&#13;
 In the meantime, a number of&#13;
 recommendations can be made to&#13;
 lower the risk of exposure to high levels&#13;
 of nitrate and nitrite.&#13;
 First to note is that many of the water&#13;
 sources used already have elevated&#13;
 nitrite concentrations prior to treatment;&#13;
 prevention (through awareness raising&#13;
 and following sound construction&#13;
 codes) is an important first step.&#13;
 Keeping waste out of the environment&#13;
 (by building and using latrines, as well&#13;
 as controlling animals) and using well-&#13;
 sited and well protected water sources&#13;
 (e.g. wells sited away from pit latrines&#13;
 and animal pens, constructed with&#13;
 proper lining and using a pump to&#13;
 withdraw water) could prevent many&#13;
 problems.&#13;
                                                      Keeping human and animal waste out of the environment will help protect water sources.&#13;
 For infants, we should remember the&#13;
 slogan "breast is best". Avoiding bottle feeding would avoid exposure of infants to nitrite and nitrate. Where bottle feeding cannot&#13;
 be avoided it may be advisable to rely on a trusted source of bottled water. Boiling water would make matters worse, as&#13;
 concentrations of nitrate and nitrite might increase as some of the water evaporates.&#13;
&#13;
 Where high levels of nitrite are known to be present in water that is consumed, addition of chlorine (or another oxidant) will&#13;
 convert nitrite to nitrate, which is less harmful. While the combined value for nitrate and nitrite may still exceed the guideline value,&#13;
 the nitrite exposure risk will be reduced. Where possible, testing source waters for nitrate and nitrite may be informative. It is&#13;
 important to realize however, that findings from such testing programs need to be acted upon to be useful.&#13;
&#13;
 References&#13;
&#13;
 United States Environmental Protection Agency (USEPA). 2006. Consumer Fact Sheet on Nitrates/ Nitrites. Retrieved August 3, 2009 from: www.epa.gov/OGWDW/&#13;
 contaminants/dw_contamfs/nitrates.html&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 World Health Organization (WHO). 2007. Nitrate and nitrite in drinking-water: Background document for development of WHO Guidelines for Drinking-water Quality.&#13;
 Geneva, Switzerland.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
32&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                              Use of BioSand Filters in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Summary And&#13;
Recommendations&#13;
The BSF is a robust water treatment&#13;
technology for use in rural Cambodian&#13;
households. It is capable of effective&#13;
removal of indicator bacteria, specifically&#13;
E. coli, and BSF-usage in households&#13;
resulted in a 47% reduction of diarrheal&#13;
disease as compared to control&#13;
households. These results are comparable&#13;
to other recommended household water&#13;
treatment interventions such as the ceramic&#13;
water purifier. Moreover, the results of this&#13;
study demonstrate continued usage rates&#13;
are higher for the BSF than some other&#13;
household treatment technologies, which&#13;
may have increased breakage rates or&#13;
require replacement of parts. This study&#13;
also suggests that software programs of&#13;
                                                Rural households with limited access to improved water sources can gain alot from using household water treatment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                the implementing organizations may aid in                 the sustained use, water quality&#13;
                                                the disease-reducing effectiveness of the                 improvement, and health impact of BSFs in&#13;
                                                BSF by providing education on the proper                  Cambodia and other countries is&#13;
                                                use and maintenance of the filter. However,               recommended as a follow up to this study.&#13;
                                                recontamination of stored BSF-treated                     Critical performance and program&#13;
                                                water remains a challenge to maintaining                  evaluations based on marketing models,&#13;
                                                safe drinking water quality at the household              consumer behaviors and preferences, and&#13;
                                                level, as was also previously found for the               business plans for the BSF, along with other&#13;
                                                ceramic water purifier in Cambodia. Overall,              household water treatment technologies,&#13;
                                                the findings of this study provide evidence               will ensure that these interventions are&#13;
                                                that the BSF is a promising household POU                 working effectively to provide safe water,&#13;
                                                water treatment option available in                       protect users from risks of waterborne&#13;
                                                Cambodia and other developing countries                   disease, achieve high coverage, and result&#13;
                                                to achieve sustained access to safe water.                in continued use over long periods of time.&#13;
                                                While results document long-term BSF use                  If these criteria can be met, scaled up&#13;
                                                that is effective in improving water quality              household water treatment and safe&#13;
                                                and reducing diarrheal disease occurrence                 storage technologies can be a potentially&#13;
                                                over a wide range of household and                        important contributor to increase sustained&#13;
                                                community conditions, further evaluation of               access to safe water.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                              33&#13;
&amp;#12;    This study also suggests that software programs of the implementing&#13;
    organizations may aid in the disease-reducing effectiveness of the BSF&#13;
    by providing education on the proper use and maintenance of the filter.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Glossary                                                                   Intervention group the group that has or receives the exposure&#13;
                                                                           of interest (e.g. BSF users).&#13;
95% confidence interval (95% CI) a range of values within&#13;
which the true value of a measurement is expected to occur with            Control group the group that is observed under ordinary&#13;
95% probability.                                                           conditions to provide baseline data to which exposure outcomes&#13;
                                                                           can be compared (e.g. BSF non-users).&#13;
Box-and-whisker plot a graphical representation of a group of&#13;
numerical data through five number summaries: sample minimum               Odds ratio or unadjusted odds ratio (OR) a measure of the&#13;
(smallest observation), lower quartile (cuts off lower 25% of data),       strength of association between two binary outcomes (e.g. using a&#13;
median (cuts data set in half), upper quartile (cuts off upper 25% of      BSF and relying on a deep well for water supply).&#13;
data), and sample maximum (largest observation).&#13;
                                                                           Adjusted OR a type of odds ratio, estimated after any&#13;
Colony forming unit (CFU) a cluster of bacteria growing on the             confounding factors (e.g. age) have been taken into account.&#13;
surface of or within a solid medium; all cells within the colony&#13;
descend from a single cell and are genetically identical.&#13;
                                                                           p-value the probability of obtaining a result at least as extreme as&#13;
                                                                           one that was actually observed in a study, assuming that the null&#13;
Cross-sectional study a type of epidemiological study&#13;
                                                                           hypothesis (i.e. no difference between the groups) is true example:&#13;
performed to determine the association between a health outcome&#13;
                                                                           a p-value of 0.05 corresponds to a 5% chance of a difference&#13;
and several possible exposure variables at a specific point in time.&#13;
                                                                           (between diarrheal disease rates of BSF-users and BSF non-users)&#13;
                                                                           as extreme as the one found, given that there is truly no difference&#13;
Escherichia coli (E. coli) a bacterium that is commonly found in&#13;
                                                                           between the two groups.&#13;
the lower intestine of warm-blooded animals; its presence in water&#13;
indicates the possibility of disease causing microbes and therefore&#13;
a possible risk to human health.                                           Point-of-use (POU) treatment technology a type of&#13;
                                                                           technology that allows people and communities without access to&#13;
Geometric mean the average of the logarithmic values of a data             safe water to improve the water quality by treating it in the home.&#13;
set, converted back to a base 10 number; used to reduce the&#13;
effect of very high or low values which may bias the mean if an            Statistically significant a measure of how unlikely it is that a&#13;
arithmetic mean ("average") were calculated.                               result has occurred by chance alone; often described in terms of&#13;
                                                                           p-values.&#13;
Log10 reduction value (LRV) in this study, a way to describe the&#13;
reduction in bacterial counts between filter influent (untreated) water&#13;
                                                                           Turbidity a measure of cloudiness of the water due to the&#13;
and effluent (BSF-treated) water; for example: a 1 log10 reduction&#13;
                                                                           presence of suspended particulates; it is measured as&#13;
value corresponds to 90% reduction in microbial concentration.&#13;
                                                                           Nephelometric Turbidity Units (NTUs).&#13;
&#13;
Longitudinal prospective cohort study a type of&#13;
epidemiological study that measures the occurrence of disease (e.g.        Unimproved drinking water sources are water sources that&#13;
diarrheal disease) within one or more groups having differing              present a larger risk of providing microbiologically contaminated&#13;
exposures (e.g. consume BSF-treated water); exposure information           water than improved drinking water sources. Unimproved sources&#13;
is recorded initially and the specific period of time at risk is forward   include unprotected dug wells or springs, surface water and&#13;
in time.                                                                   vendor-provided water.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   34&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                   Use of BioSand Filters in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Acknowledgments&#13;
We are grateful to peer reviewers Dr. William Duke at the University&#13;
of Victoria, and the National Institute of Public Health in Japan.&#13;
&#13;
The authors would like to thank Mr. Jan Willem Rosenboom (WSP),&#13;
Mr. Peter Feldman (PLAN International), Mr. John Clayton (SPC),&#13;
Mr. Terrence Thompson (WHO-WPRO), Dr. John Borrazzo (USAID),&#13;
Mr. Yim Viriya (Hagar), Mr. Me Kosal (CGA), Drs. Mao Saray and&#13;
Chea Samnang (Royal Government of Cambodia - Ministry of Rural&#13;
Development), The late Dr. Mickey Sampson and staff at RDI Cambodia,&#13;
staff of Hagar Cambodia and CGA.&#13;
&#13;
Also Mr. Chan Sarik, Mr. Ly Soun, and Mr. Kim Heng and the teams&#13;
in Kampong Thom, Kratie and Svey Rieng.&#13;
&#13;
From CGA, we would like to thank Dr. Guech Hourng and the CGA&#13;
BSF project managers and staff.&#13;
&#13;
For data collection and analysis: Proum Sorya, Project Coordinator,&#13;
Uon Virak, Project Assistant Coordinator, Song Kimsrong, field team&#13;
member, Ken Sreymom, field team member, Um Saravuth, field team&#13;
member, Van Sokheng, GIS specialist, Oum Sopharo, lab team member,&#13;
Peang Sok Heng, lab team member, Heng Seiha, lab team member,&#13;
Monn Pong, lab team, Douglas Wait, UNC environmental microbiology&#13;
laboratory manager.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   35&#13;
&amp;#12;     Overall, the findings of this study provide evidence that the BSF is a promising&#13;
     household POU water treatment option available in Cambodia and other&#13;
     developing countries to achieve sustained access to safe water.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
References                                                              9 Feldman PR, Rosenboom JW, Saray M, Navuth P, Samnang C,&#13;
                                                                        Iddings S. 2007. Assessment of the chemical quality of drinking&#13;
1 WHO/WPRO (World Health Organization/Western Pacific Regional&#13;
                                                                        water in Cambodia. Journal of Water and Health. 5(1):101-116.&#13;
Office). 2009. Water, sanitation, and hygiene [Internet]. Manila,&#13;
                                                                        10Buschmann J, Berg M, Stengel C, Winkel L, Sampson ML, Trang&#13;
Philippines: WHO/WPRO. [cited 2009 May 6]. Available at: http://&#13;
                                                                        PT, Viet PH. 2008. Contamination of drinking water resources in the&#13;
www.wpro.who.int/health_topics/water_sanitation_and_hygiene/&#13;
                                                                        Mekong delta floodplains: arsenic and other trace metals pose&#13;
                                                                        serious health risks to population. Environment International.&#13;
2 WHO (World Health Organization). 2009. Burden of disease and&#13;
                                                                        34(6):756-764.&#13;
cost-effectiveness estimates [Internet]. Geneva, Switzerland: WHO.&#13;
[cited 2009 May 6]. Available at: http://www.who.int/water_&#13;
                                                                        11 Brown J, Sobsey M, Proum S. 2007. Use of Ceramic Water&#13;
sanitation_health/diseases/burden/en/index.html&#13;
                                                                        Filters in Cambodia. Washington, DC: WSP-World Bank Field Note.&#13;
                                                                        Available at: http://www.wsp.org/UserFiles/file/926200724252_&#13;
3 Kosek M, Bern C, Guerrant RL. 2003. The global burden of&#13;
                                                                        eap_cambodia_filter.pdf&#13;
diarrhoeal disease, as estimated from studies published between&#13;
1992 and 2000. Bulletin of the World Health Organization.               12Clasen TF and Haller L. 2008. Water Quality Interventions to&#13;
81(3):197-204.&#13;
                                                                        Prevent Diarrhoea: Cost and Cost-Effectiveness. WHO/HSE/&#13;
                                                                        WSH/08.02. Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization,&#13;
4Palmateer G, Manz D, Jurkovic A. 1999. Toxicant and parasite&#13;
                                                                        2008. 33 p.&#13;
challenge of Manz ntermittent slow sand filter. Environmental&#13;
Toxicology. 14(2):217-225.                                              13 Fewtrell L, Kaufmann RB, Kay D, Enanoria W, Haller L, Colford&#13;
                                                                        JM Jr. 2005. Water, sanitation, and hygiene interventions to reduce&#13;
5 Stauber CE, Elliott MA, Koksal F, Ortiz GM, DiGiano FA, Sobsey        diarrhoea in less developed countries: a systematic review and&#13;
MD. 2006. Characterization of the BioSand filter for E. coli            meta-analysis. Lancet Infectious Diseases. 5(1):42-52.&#13;
reductions from household drinking water under controlled&#13;
laboratory and field use conditions. Water and Science Technology.      14Arnold BF, Colford JM Jr. 2007. Treating water with chlorine at&#13;
54(3):1-7.                                                              point-of-use to improve water quality and reduce child diarrhea in&#13;
                                                                        developing counties: a systematic review and meta-analysis.&#13;
6 Elliott MA, Stauber CE, Koksal F, DiGiano FA, Sobsey MD. 2008.        American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. 76(2):354-364.&#13;
Reductions of E. coli, echovirus type 12 and bacteriophages in an&#13;
intermittently operated household-scale slow sand filter. Water         15 Clasen T, Schmidt WP, Rabie T, Roberts I, Cairncross S. 2007.&#13;
Research. 42(10-11):2662-2670.                                          Interventions to improve water quality for preventing diarrhoea:&#13;
                                                                        systematic review and meta-analysis. British Medical Journal.&#13;
7NIPH/NIS (National Institute of Public Health, National Institute of   334(7597):782.&#13;
Statistics [Cambodia], and ORC Macro. 2006. Cambodia&#13;
Demographic and Health Survey (CDHS) 2005. Phnom Penh,                  16 WHO (World Health Organization). 2007. Household water&#13;
Cambodia and Calverton, Maryland, USA: National Institute of            treatment and safe storage: treatment technologies [Internet].&#13;
Public Health, National Institute of Statistics, and ORC Macro.         Geneva, Switzerland: WHO [cited 2009 May 6]. Available at: http://&#13;
                                                                        www.who.int/household_water/research/technologies_intro/en/&#13;
8Stanger G, Truong TV, Ngoc KS, Luyen TV, Thanh TT. 2005.               index.html&#13;
Arsenic in groundwaters of the Lower Mekong. Environmental and&#13;
Geochemical Health. 27(4):341-357.                                      17   Dyck K, Cantwell RE, Vreeken A. Samaritan's Purse Strategic&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    36&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    Use of BioSand Filters in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Implementation of the BioSand Filter. In: Disinfection 2009              Methods for the Examination of Water and Wastewater, 20th&#13;
Conference Proceedings; 2009 Feb 28-Mar 3; Atlanta GA.                   edition. Baltimore, MD: APHA, AWHA, WEF.&#13;
Alexandria VA: Water Environment Federation; p 787-798.&#13;
                                                                         21 Sobsey MD, Stauber CE, Casanova LM, Brown JM, Elliott MA.&#13;
18Manz DH, Concrete BioSand Water Filter Construction Manual             2008. Point of Use Household Drinking Water Filtration: A Practical,&#13;
Book 7: Installation and Commissioning. May 2008. Website.               Effective Solution for Providing Sustained Access to Safe Drinking&#13;
Available at: http://manzwaterinfo.ca/cmans.htm. Accessed on             Water in the Developing World. Environmental Science and&#13;
January 30, 2010.                                                        Technology. 42(12):4261-7.&#13;
&#13;
19 Elliott MA, DiGiano FA, Fabiszewski AM, Chuang P, Clark LP,           22Schmidt W-P, Cairncross S. 2009. Household Water Treatment in&#13;
Wang A, Sobsey MD. The effect of idle time on reduction of viruses       Poor Populations: Is There Enough Evidence for Scaling up Now?&#13;
in an intermittently operated, household0scale slow sand filter. In:     Environmental Science and Technology. 43(4):986-992.&#13;
Disinfection 2009 Conference Proceedings; 2009 Feb 28-Mar 3;&#13;
Atlanta GA. Alexandria VA: Water Environment Federation; p 616-          23 WSP. 2002. Learning What Works for Sanitation. Revisiting&#13;
628.                                                                     Sanitation Successes in Cambodia. Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
                                                                         East Asia and the Pacific (WSP-EAP) (July, 2002). Jakarta,&#13;
20   Clesceri LS, Greenberg AE, Eaton AD, editors. 1998. Standard        Indonesia. 40 p.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Households have to transport their own filter home after construction.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                   37&#13;
&amp;#12;       Further evaluation of the sustained use, water quality improvement, and health&#13;
       impact of BSFs in Cambodia and other countries is recommended as a follow&#13;
       up to this study.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
24Rosenboom, JW, Ockelford J, Robinson J. 2007. Water Supply                                   Center for Strategic and International Studies; 2005 Mar 9;&#13;
and Sanitation in Cambodia: Poor Access for Poor People.                                       Washington, DC.&#13;
Background paper commisoned for World Bank equity report:&#13;
Water and Sanitation Program / Oxford Policy Management.                                       28Stauber CE, Ortiz GM, Loomis DP, Sobsey MD. 2009. A&#13;
                                                                                               Randomized Controlled Trial of the Concrete Biosand Filter and Its&#13;
25WHO (World Health Organization). 1997. Guidelines for Drinking-                              Impact on Diarrheal Disease in Bonao, Dominican Republic.&#13;
Water Quality, 2nd Edition Volume 3 Surveillance and control of                                American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. 80(2):286-293.&#13;
community supplies. Geneva, Switzerland: World Health&#13;
Organization, 197. Henry Press, 1997. 238 p.                                                   29 Aiken BA. 2008. Sustainability Assessment of the BioSand Filter&#13;
                                                                                               in Bonao, Dominican Republic [technical report]. Chapel Hill:&#13;
26 Brick T, Primrose B, Chandrasekhar R, Roy S, Muliyil J, Kang G.                             University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. 123 p.&#13;
Water contamination in urban south India: household storage&#13;
practices and their implications for water safety and enteric                                  30 Tiwari SS, Schmidt WP,, Darby J, Kariuki ZG, Jenkins MW. 2009.&#13;
infections. International Journal of Hygiene and Environmental                                 Intermittent slow sand filtration for preventing diarrhea among&#13;
Health 2004;207:473-490.                                                                       children in Kenyan households using unimproved water sources:&#13;
                                                                                               randomized controlled trial. Trop Med Intl Health, 2009 Nov; 14(11):&#13;
27   Allgood G. New Business Models for Safe Drinking Water. In:                               1374-82. E Pub 2009. Sep 4.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
There is a long way to go still in improving rural living conditions in Cambodia. Better health through better water is one step in the right direction.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     38&#13;
&amp;#12;What is on the Disc?&#13;
The disc included in the pocket below is of the DVD format.&#13;
It can be played in any DVD player, and on any Windows computer or Apple computer with a DVD drive.&#13;
The DVD contains a video summarizing the findings of the BSF field assessment as described in this field note. One version is in the&#13;
English language, the other is in Khmer. A soft copy of this field note is also contained on it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              Title                            Subject                           Language                           Duration&#13;
&#13;
    Sifting sands: The use of&#13;
                                      Summary of study results                     English                          10 minutes&#13;
    biosand filters in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                   Khmer                            10 minutes&#13;
&amp;#12;       About the series:                                                                                                                      Cambodia Country Office&#13;
                                                                                                                                              113 Norodom Blvd.&#13;
       WSP Field Notes describe and                                                                                                           Phnom Penh, Cambodia&#13;
       analyze projects and activities in&#13;
       water and sanitation that provide                                                                                                      Phone: (+855-23) 217 304 x 103&#13;
       lessons for sector leaders,                                                                                                            Fax: (+855-23) 210 373&#13;
       administrators, and individuals                                                                                                        E-mail: wspeap@worldbank.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Web site: http://www.wsp.org&#13;
       tackling the water and sanitation&#13;
       challenges in urban and rural&#13;
       areas. The criteria for selection of&#13;
       stories included in this series are&#13;
       large scale impact, demonstrable&#13;
       sustainability, good cost recovery,&#13;
       replicable conditions, and&#13;
       leadership.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                              May 2010&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                              WSP MISSION:&#13;
                                                                                                                                              To help the poor gain sustained access to&#13;
                                                                                                                                              improved water and sanitation services.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                              WSP FUNDING PARTNERS:&#13;
                                                                                                                                              The governments of Australia, Austria,&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Belgium, Canada, Denmark, France,&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Ireland, Luxembourg, The Netherlands,&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Norway, Sweden, Switzerland, the United&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Kingdom, the United States of America, the&#13;
                                                                                                                                              United Nations Development Programme,&#13;
                                                                                                                                              the World Bank, and the Bill and Melinda&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Gates Foundation.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                              AUTHORS:&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Kaida Liang, Mark Sobsey, Christine&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Stauber, University of North Carolina. Nitrate&#13;
                                                                                                                                              data provided by Heather Murphy,&#13;
                                                                                                                                              University of Guelph. Edited by Jennifer&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Murphy and Jan Willem Rosenboom. WSP&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Peer reviewed by Dr. William Duke,&#13;
                                                                                                                                              University of Victoria and the National&#13;
                                                                                                                                              institute of Public Health in Japan&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Cover Photos by:&#13;
                                                                                                                                              www.nathanhortonphotography.com&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Other Pictures Credit:&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Samaritan's Purse, Kaida Liang,&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Kathryn Smith, Nathan Horton&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Created by: IMS Consulting Group&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Printed at: Ganad-Khmer Printers co.,ltd.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                              This field note is also available at&#13;
                                                                                                                                              http://www.wsp.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The findings, interpretations, and conclusions expressed are entirely those of the author and should not be attributed in any manner to The&#13;
World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to members of its Board of Executive Directors or the companies they represent.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="13715490">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2010/05/13715490/improving-household-drinking-water-quality-use-biosand-filters-bsfs-cambodia
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2010/05/13715490/improving-household-drinking-water-quality-use-biosand-filters-bsfs-cambodia</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2010/05/13715490/improving-household-drinking-water-quality-use-biosand-filters-bsfs-cambodia</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2011-02-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/02/01/000333037_20110201225322/Rendered/INDEX/593360WP0WSP1b10Box358367B01PUBLIC1.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/02/01/000333037_20110201225322/Rendered/PDF/593360WP0WSP1b10Box358367B01PUBLIC1.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2011-02-01T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2010-05-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Improving household drinking water quality
            : use of BioSand Filters (BSFs) in Cambodia
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Safe water is critical to preventing
            diarrheal disease, which kills nearly two million children
            annually. A promising household water treatment technology
            is the BioSand Filter (BSF), an intermittent slow sand
            filter that is locally produced in Cambodia and several
            other developing countries. However, despite promising
            laboratory performance, the BSF lacks adequate description
            and epidemiological evidence on its field performance and
            health impact. The BSF is a robust water treatment
            technology for use in rural Cambodian households, capable of
            effective removal of indicator bacteria, specifically E.
            coli, and significant reduction of diarrheal disease. BSF
            performance is comparable to other recommended household
            water treatment interventions, such as the ceramic water
            purifier; however BSFs provide the additional advantage of
            not being prone to breakage or needing replacement parts.
            Overall, the findings of this study provide evidence that
            the BSF is a promising household point-of-use (POU) water
            treatment option to achieve sustained access to safe water.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Improving household drinking water quality :
            use of BioSand Filters (BSFs) in Cambodia
        </docna>
        <display_title>Improving household drinking
            water quality : use of BioSand Filters (BSFs) in Cambodia</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2010/05/13715490/improving-household-drinking-water-quality-use-biosand-filters-bsfs-cambodia</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Treatment &amp; Quality,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Water Conservation,Water and Industry</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>Cambodia</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southeast Asia!$!80471</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20110201225322</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Water and Sanitation Program field note</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Access to Safe Drinking Water, access to
            safe water, access to sanitation facilities, adsorption,
            agricultural activities, arsenic, boiling water, channel,
            channels, chemical contaminants, chemical quality,
            chlorination, Chlorine, community groups, community health,
            community leaders, community water, construction,
            contaminated water, denitrification, disinfection, Drinking
            Water, Drinking Water Quality, effluent, effluent
            concentration, Environmental Health, Environmental
            Protection, Environmental Toxicology, Filter, Filtered,
            Filters, gas, gravel, ground water, ground waters,
            groundwater, groundwater sources, hand washing, hazardous
            chemicals, high levels, households, iron, lakes, local
            partners, manganese, Membrane filtration, Microbial water
            quality, microbiological quality, microbiology, moving
            parts, nitrogen, nutrients, outlet pipe, oxygen, particles,
            pathogens, pH, pit latrines, Pond water, ponds, programs,
            Public Health, quality of water, rainwater, rainwater
            harvesting, rainy seasons, rivers, rural communities, rural
            community, safe drinking water, Safe water, sand, sand bed,
            sand grains, sanitation coverage, sanitation facilities,
            sanitation sector, sewerage system, shallow water, slow sand
            filter, slow sand filtration, surface water, surface water
            quality, surface waters, taste, toilet facility, trace
            metals, treatment technologies, turbidity, valuable
            information, washing, Wastewater, Water contamination, water
            filters, Water Filtration, water management, Water Quality,
            Water Quality Analysis, Water quality data, water quality
            improvement, water quantity, Water Research, water
            resources, water samples, water source, water sources, water
            storage, water supply, water treatment, water treatment
            technology, water usage, wells
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water- Water and Sanit Prgrm (GWASP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southeast Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>59336</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>BoD</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Cost of Disease</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Impact of Disease</ml:concept><ml:concept>AIDS HIV</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV/AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Behavior Change Communication</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Chlorination</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Disinfection</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Filtration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Purification</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Models</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>GIS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Geographical Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Land Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Use</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Burden of Disease</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV and AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mountains</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Treatment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications Organizational Design</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Geographic Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Cambodia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>