<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>WATER AND SANITATION PROGRAM: WORKING PAPER                                   59934&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Enabling Technologies for&#13;
Handwashing with Soap:&#13;
A Case Study on the&#13;
Tippy-Tap in Uganda&#13;
Adam Biran&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
February 2011&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The Water and Sanitation Program is a multi-donor partnership administered&#13;
by the World Bank to support poor people in obtaining affordable, safe, and&#13;
sustainable access to water and sanitation services.&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Enabling Technologies for&#13;
Handwashing with Soap:&#13;
A Case Study on the&#13;
Tippy-Tap in Uganda&#13;
Adam Biran&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
February 2011&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;Executive Summary&#13;
Background                                                                                                               The purpose of this study&#13;
Handwashing with soap at key times is believed to be an effective and highly cost-&#13;
effective means of reducing diarrhea incidence.1 However, global rates of hand-                                          was to document the&#13;
washing with soap are frequently low, particularly among the poor, who also face&#13;
the greatest threat from infectious diseases.2 Access to a convenient handwashing&#13;
                                                                                                                         process through which&#13;
station has been found to be associated with higher rates of handwashing3 and                                            tippy-taps were promoted&#13;
decreased fingertip contamination.4&#13;
                                                                                                                         to qualitatively explore&#13;
One such handwashing station is the "tippy-tap," which consists of a small (3 or&#13;
5 liter) jerry can filled with water and suspended from a wooden frame. A string                                         the results and to draw&#13;
attached to the neck of the jerry can is tied to a piece of wood at ground level.&#13;
Pressing on the wood with the foot tips the jerry can, releasing a stream of water&#13;
                                                                                                                         out lessons for future&#13;
through a small hole. Soap is suspended from the frame beside the jerry can. A                                           interventions.&#13;
tippy-tap located close to a latrine provides a cheap and potentially convenient&#13;
means of washing hands after latrine use.&#13;
&#13;
A qualitative case study was carried out May 11­18, 2010 in Uganda to learn&#13;
about two projects, described below, in which health workers and village-level&#13;
volunteers promoted the tippy-tap, provided health education and carried out&#13;
household inspections. The purpose of this study was to document the process&#13;
through which tippy-taps were promoted to qualitatively explore the results and&#13;
to draw out lessons for future interventions. Data were collected through nine&#13;
key informant interviews, forty-seven interviews with householders from model&#13;
and non-model villages, and twenty-two spot-check observations of handwashing&#13;
facilities.&#13;
&#13;
The first project studied, an Agency for Cooperation and Research in Develop-&#13;
ment (ACORD) water and sanitation project, started in 2008 and is scheduled to&#13;
run for a total of three years. The second project studied, a Government of&#13;
Uganda initiative implemented by District Health Authority staff members,&#13;
started in 2007 and is ongoing. This project established model villages in which&#13;
households were encouraged to take up a variety of behavior changes including:&#13;
washing hands with soap at key times; construction of tippy-taps; making and&#13;
using drying racks for kitchen utensils; building bathing shelters; building or&#13;
improving latrines; making and using garbage pits; and growing vegetables.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1&#13;
    Curtis, V., and S. Cairncross. 2003. "Effect of washing hands with soap on diarrhoea risk in the community: a&#13;
    systematic review." The Lancet Infectious Diseases, 3, 275­281, May; and Laxminarayan, R., J. Chow, and S. A.&#13;
    Shahid-Salles. 2006. "Intervention cost effectiveness: Overview of main messages" in Jamison, et al. eds. Disease&#13;
    Control Priorities in Developing Countries. Second edition, 35­86. The World Bank, Washington DC.&#13;
2&#13;
    Scott, B., V. Curtis, and T. Rabie. 2003. "Protecting Children from Diarrhoea and Acute Respiratory Infections:&#13;
    The role of Hand Washing Promotion in Water and Sanitation Programmes." Regional Health Forum, WHO South-&#13;
    East Asia Region, Vol. 7, Number 1.&#13;
3&#13;
    Biran, A., A. Tabyshalieva, and Z. Salmorbekova. 2005. "Formative research for hygiene promotion in Kyrgyzstan."&#13;
    Health Policy and Planning 20 (4) 213­221.&#13;
4&#13;
    Pinfold, J. V. 1990. "Fecal contamination of water and fingertip-rinses as a method for evaluating the effect of&#13;
    low-cost water-supply and sanitation activities on fecooral disease transmission. A case-study in rural North-East&#13;
    Thailand." Epidemiology and Infection 105 (2) 363­375.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                                     iii&#13;
&amp;#12;     A Case Study on the Tippy-Tap in Uganda   Executive Summary&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Changes were promoted through village meetings and               the tippy-tap is the need to replace components annually. It is&#13;
     house-to-house visits carried out by Health Assistants--vis-     possible that over time the need to replace and repair tippy-&#13;
     iting health workers employed by the District Health Au-         taps will lead to a decrease in the number of users if house-&#13;
     thorities--and by village-level volunteers. Households were      holds lack the motivation to carry this out after visits by health&#13;
     also inspected periodically to see if recommendations are        workers and village health committee members cease.&#13;
     being followed.&#13;
                                                                      Dissemination of information about the tippy-tap be-&#13;
     The ACORD project differed from the District Health Au-          tween villages and even between households within vil-&#13;
     thority project in that rainwater-harvesting systems, im-        lages is limited. In non-model villages most respondents&#13;
     proved cooking stoves, tippy-taps and materials for              are unaware of the tippy-tap.&#13;
     upgrading latrines were subsidized. The project worked&#13;
     with women's savings groups to provide members with              While quantitative data on handwashing rates were not&#13;
     credit on a rotating basis, enabling them to access the tech-    collected, households with tippy-taps believed that their&#13;
     nologies being promoted.                                         post-latrine handwashing rates had increased as a result&#13;
                                                                      of the taps. It seems likely that tippy-taps provide both&#13;
     Quantitative data (e.g., rates of handwashing with soap or       convenient water and soap and a salient cue to wash hands.&#13;
     prevalence of tippy-taps in villages) were not collected in      Householders also report that children like using the tippy-&#13;
     this study.                                                      taps. They may therefore play a useful role in nurturing the&#13;
                                                                      handwashing habit in children.&#13;
     Findings&#13;
     Tippy-taps are common, though not universal in model             Respondents in non-model villages were largely unaware&#13;
     villages. Their acquisition seems largely driven by the com-     of the tippy-tap. Scaling up the approach is likely to be&#13;
     bination of educational messages and instructions from the       challenging, since it would need to rely heavily on the in-&#13;
     Health Assistants and the possibility of inspection.             puts of village-level volunteers.&#13;
&#13;
     Awareness of the tippy-tap does not necessarily translate        Conclusions&#13;
     into immediate action to obtain one. Households that             Tippy-taps were an acceptable means of providing a low-&#13;
     were aware of the tippy-tap but had never owned one did          cost enabling technology for handwashing in this popula-&#13;
     not report any barriers to acquisition other than that they      tion. Anecdotally they have increased rates of handwashing&#13;
     either had not lived at their current house for long or that     after latrine use. However, uptake appeared driven by the&#13;
     they were waiting for a package of home improvements to          `push' of the intervention rather than the `pull' of the tech-&#13;
     be funded (through the ACORD project).                           nology and the extent to which spontaneous uptake and&#13;
                                                                      sustained use can be achieved in the absence of intensive&#13;
     Tippy-taps are acceptable to householders and are thought        intervention activities is not known. Respondents in non-&#13;
     to have a number of advantages over using a jerry can. The       model villages had little contact with model villages and&#13;
     most salient of these is that the foot pedal prevents contami-   were largely unaware of the tippy-tap. The interventions&#13;
     nation of the jerry can alone. The main reported drawback of     were labor intensive and probably difficult to scale-up.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
iv                                                                                                          Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;                 Contents&#13;
                        Executive Summary...................................................................iii&#13;
                 I.     Introduction ............................................................................... 1&#13;
                          1.1 Background .................................................................... 1&#13;
                          1.2 The Tippy-Tap ................................................................. 1&#13;
                 II.    Conducting a Qualitative Case Study in Uganda..................... 3&#13;
                          2.1 Study Objectives ............................................................ 3&#13;
                          2.2 Interventions Studied ..................................................... 3&#13;
                          2.3 Methods.......................................................................... 3&#13;
                          2.4 Study Limitations ............................................................ 5&#13;
                 III.   Findings and Discussion ........................................................... 6&#13;
                          3.1 Handwashing Facilities in Households .......................... 6&#13;
                          3.2 Uptake of the Tippy-Tap ................................................. 6&#13;
                          3.3 Advantages and Disadvantages of the Tippy-Tap.......... 8&#13;
                          3.4 Effect of the Tippy-Tap on Handwashing Rates ........... 10&#13;
                          3.5 Implications for Scaling Up .......................................... 11&#13;
                          3.6 Conclusions .................................................................. 12&#13;
&#13;
              Tables&#13;
                           1: Distribution of Household Interviews .................................. 4&#13;
                           2: Distribution of Spot-Check Observations ........................... 4&#13;
&#13;
              Appendices&#13;
                      1: ACORD Project ................................................................. 14&#13;
                      2: Government of Uganda Intervention ................................. 16&#13;
                      3: Terms of Reference ........................................................... 17&#13;
                      4: Schedule of Activities ........................................................ 19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;I.              Introduction&#13;
&#13;
1.1 Background&#13;
The Water and Sanitation Program's (WSP) Global Scaling&#13;
Up Handwashing Project is testing whether innovative pro-&#13;
motional approaches to behavior change can generate wide-&#13;
spread and sustained improvements in household hygiene&#13;
and sanitation practices in Peru, Senegal, Tanzania, and&#13;
Vietnam. Among other learnings, the project is seeking to&#13;
ascertain the key factors that influence handwashing behav-&#13;
ior change (also known as behavioral determinants).&#13;
&#13;
Enabling products and technologies are some of the "ex-&#13;
ternal factors" that influence individuals' likelihood to&#13;
perform a behavior, regardless of their ability and moti-&#13;
vation to take action.5 Availability of enabling products&#13;
and technologies is often overlooked in the design of&#13;
                                                                                         A tippy-tap is easy to use and commonly constructed near&#13;
handwashing initiatives, although it has been well docu-&#13;
                                                                                         latrines.&#13;
mented that behavior change is most successful if the&#13;
behavior is not only intentional, but also feasible for the&#13;
target population to adopt.6 These "external factors" have                               tippy-tap provides a controlled quantity of flowing water&#13;
been shown to facilitate handwashing behavior, in com-                                   for washing hands and is made from locally available ma-&#13;
bination with other behavioral determinants such as at-                                  terials such as gourds or old plastic cooking oil bottles.&#13;
titudes and beliefs about handwashing and knowledge                                      Variants include a design that can be operated by foot,&#13;
about the positive consequences of handwashing, among                                    thereby avoiding contamination of the tap itself. Usual&#13;
others.7                                                                                 methods for promoting and disseminating the tippy-tap&#13;
                                                                                         technology within hygiene promotion interventions are&#13;
In the case of handwashing, the tippy-tap is perhaps the                                 through volunteer outreach workers or community re-&#13;
best-known enabling technology. It is a low-cost, do-it-                                 source persons as well as health club activities in schools.&#13;
yourself technology that has been widely promoted for&#13;
over a decade, notably in Uganda and Madagascar. The                                     While guidelines and "how-to" instructions are available&#13;
                                                                                         about tippy-taps and other enabling products, very few&#13;
                                                                                         evaluations or assessments inform the design of hygiene&#13;
5&#13;
    As part of its Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project, WSP developed a behavior&#13;
                                                                                         promotion programs through the documentation of lessons&#13;
    change framework to explain handwashing behaviour. The FOAM framework                learned, promising practices (including implementation&#13;
    identifies the key factors or determinants that influence Handwashing, organized&#13;
    into four categories--Focus, Opportunity, Ability, Motivation. Enabling products&#13;
                                                                                         models), or successes and challenges (particularly with re-&#13;
    and technologies fall under the Opportunity category of determinants. See            spect to changing behavior at large scale).&#13;
    Introducing FOAM: A Framework to Analyze Handwashing Behaviors to Design&#13;
    Effective Handwashing Programs, available at www.wsp.org/scalinguphandwashing&#13;
6&#13;
    For more information on tippy-taps and other enabling technologies for               1.2 The Tippy-Tap&#13;
    handwashing with soap, see WSP's Enabling Technologies for Handwashing&#13;
    Database at www.wsp.org/scalinguphandwashing/enablingtechnologies.                   The tippy-tap was initially developed in Zimbabwe by Jim&#13;
7&#13;
    Biran, Adam, Anara Tabyshalieva, and Zumrat Salmorbekova, "Formative Research        Watt and Jackson Masawi. It consisted of a small gourd sus-&#13;
    for Hygiene Promotion in Kyrgyzstan," Health and Policy Planning 20, no. 4 (2005):&#13;
    213­21.                                                                              pended on a string. The gourd was filled with water that&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                                        1&#13;
&amp;#12;    A Case Study on the Tippy-Tap in Uganda   Introduction&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    could be dispensed in small quantities if the gourd was         0.5-liter drinking water bottle. A shallow depression filled&#13;
    tipped by means of a string tied to its neck. Soap could be     with gravel or stones acts as a soak-away and prevents a&#13;
    suspended on a string beside the gourd.                         pool of water from forming below the tap.&#13;
&#13;
    Subsequently, the gourd was replaced with a small (3 or         Research shows that a person washing hands under a tippy-&#13;
    5 liter) plastic jerry can with a hole punched in the side. A   tap uses 40-50ml of water as compared with 600ml when&#13;
    more recent addition is a piece of wood at the bottom of        water is accessed by other means.8&#13;
    string tied to the neck of the jerry can. This allows the tap&#13;
    to be operated by foot, avoiding the need for any hand&#13;
    contact with the jerry can. This variant of the tippy-tap       8&#13;
                                                                        Hurtardo E (1993) Dialogue on Diarrhoea Online (54) September­November,&#13;
    was in use at the study site in Uganda. Soap can be pro-            pp 6­7.&#13;
    tected from rain by covering it with the base of an old&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2                                                                                                                  Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;II.           Conducting a Qualitative&#13;
              Case Study in Uganda&#13;
2.1 Study Objectives&#13;
In March 2010, WSP conducted a qualitative case study in&#13;
Uganda to learn about the promotion of specific handwash-&#13;
ing enabling technology (the tippy-tap) through a particu-&#13;
lar approach (the use of visiting health workers and&#13;
village-level volunteers to provide health education and&#13;
carry out household inspections in model villages) in&#13;
Uganda. A schedule of activities is included in Appendix 4.&#13;
&#13;
WSP's overall aim is that these findings will inform both&#13;
WSP's Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project and the&#13;
wider water, sanitation, hygiene promotion, and health&#13;
communities on the potential role, value, and limitations of&#13;
enabling products and provide insights into promising&#13;
practices to maximize scale and sustainability.&#13;
&#13;
Key objectives included:                                       Tippy-taps consist of a jerry can filled with water hung by a&#13;
   · Look for evidence of sustained use of tippy-taps be-      rope next to a container of soap. The stones below the tippy-&#13;
      yond the period of an intervention                       tap act as a soak-away.&#13;
   · Look for evidence of dissemination of tippy-taps be-&#13;
      yond intervention areas                                  Health Authority staff members also worked in non-model&#13;
   · Look for evidence of the reach of the intervention        villages where the same behavior changes were promoted&#13;
      or promotion                                             but at a lower intensity. Each project is described in greater&#13;
   · Understand reasons behind adoption or                     detail in Annexes 2 and 3.&#13;
      non-adoption&#13;
   · Draw out features of the technology and/or the dis-       2.3 Methods&#13;
      semination model that may have contributed signifi-      Data were collected from May 11­May 18, 2010 using&#13;
      cantly to the levels of uptake and sustained use         three qualitative approaches: (1) semi-structured interviews&#13;
   · Consider how these features might help or hinder          with householders, (2) semi-structured interviews with key&#13;
      future attempts to promote the technology at a           informants, and 3) spot-check observations of hand wash-&#13;
      greater scale                                            ing facilities:&#13;
&#13;
2.2 Interventions Studied                                                  Semi-structured interviews with householders: The au-&#13;
The case study research focused on two distinct projects:                  thor worked through either a District Health Inspec-&#13;
one, a project implemented by the Agency for Cooperation                   tor or a Health Assistant who acted as a translator&#13;
and Research in Development (ACORD), a non-govern-                         for the interviews. A total of forty-seven interviews&#13;
mental organization; the other, a Government of Uganda                     were conducted, including in model villages where&#13;
initiative implemented by District Health Authority staff                  the projects had been implemented and in neigh-&#13;
members. Both projects established model villages in which                 boring non-intervention villages from the same sub-&#13;
households were encouraged to take up a variety of behav-                  county.9 Of these interviews, thirty-four were with&#13;
ior changes. The intention was that model villages would&#13;
serve as examples of good practices thereby inspiring and      9&#13;
                                                                   Sub-county is the administrative level below district. Below sub-county are parish&#13;
encouraging changes in neighboring villages. District              and village levels.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                                        3&#13;
&amp;#12;    A Case Study on the Tippy-Tap in Uganda       Conducting a Qualitative Case Study in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    TABLE 1: DISTRIBUTION OF HOUSEHOLD INTERVIEWS                                      TABLE 2: DISTRIBUTION OF SPOT-CHECK OBSERVATIONS&#13;
    (N = 47)                                                                           (N = 22)&#13;
     Village                                                        Interviews          Village                                         Spot-checks&#13;
     ACORD Intervention                                                                 ACORD Intervention&#13;
     Model village, Mwizi sub-county                                      8*            Model village, Mwizi sub-county                       10&#13;
     Non-model village 1, Mwizi sub-county                                8             Non-model village 1, Mwizi sub-county                 10&#13;
     Non-model village 2, Mwizi sub-county                                8             Non-model village 2, Mwizi sub-county                   0&#13;
     District Health Authority Intervention                                             District Health Authority Intervention&#13;
     Model village, Mbarara District                                      8             Model village, Mbarara District                         0&#13;
     Model village, Ibanda District                                       9             Model village, Ibanda District                          0&#13;
     Non-model village, Ibanda District                                   6             Non-model village, Ibanda District                      2&#13;
     Total                                                              47              Total                                                 22&#13;
    *Six respondents were members of savings groups directly involved in the ACORD&#13;
    project; two were non-members.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             female heads of household, eight with male heads of                       from a list of villages in the same sub-county. Households&#13;
             household, and five with male and female heads of                         for interview were selected randomly from a list of all&#13;
             household together (Table 1).                                             households in the villages because there was insufficient in-&#13;
                                                                                       formation available to allow purposive sampling.&#13;
             Semi-structured interviews with key informants: The&#13;
             author worked through either a District Health In-                        Data collection from the District Health Authority inter-&#13;
             spector or a Health Assistant who acted as a transla-                     vention took place in two model villages located in Mbarara&#13;
             tor for the interviews. A total of nine interviews were                   District and Ibanda District respectively and in one non-&#13;
             conducted to learn about the content and nature of                        model village from a neighboring village in Ibanda District.&#13;
             the interventions. Interviews were conducted with:                        The District Health Authority proposed the model villages.&#13;
             one Project Director and Social Worker (ACORD);                           The neighboring non-model village in Ibanda District was&#13;
             two District Health Inspectors; one Volunteer Proj-                       selected randomly from a list of villages within the same&#13;
             ect Coordinator (from the ACORD model village);                           sub-county as the model village. In Ibanda District house-&#13;
             two Village Chairmen from model villages; one                             holds to be interviewed were chosen randomly from a list of&#13;
             Chairman, Village Water and Sanitation Committee                          all households in each of the two villages (model and non-&#13;
             (from a model village); one Deputy District Health                        model). In Mbarara District households to be interviewed&#13;
             Officer; one Health Assistant.                                            were chosen randomly from a list of twenty households&#13;
                                                                                       provided by the village chairman.&#13;
             Spot-check observations. A total of twenty-two spot-&#13;
             check observations of handwashing facilities were                         The average size of the villages studied was estimated to be&#13;
             carried out in a small, convenience sample House-                         one hundred households. In each village, the village chair-&#13;
             holds were not informed in advance that they would                        man or a representative visited selected households in the&#13;
             be visited. The spot checks observations were used to                     late afternoon or early evening of the day before the inter-&#13;
             look for the presence handwashing facilities, soap,                       view with a request that an adult from the household be&#13;
             and water beside household latrines (Table 2).                            available for an interview on the following day. This prepa-&#13;
                                                                                       ration was necessary as the study took place during a busy&#13;
    Data collection from the ACORD project took place in one                           agricultural season and few people were likely to be home&#13;
    model village and two non-model villages from the same                             during daylight hours. Householders were told that the in-&#13;
    sub-county. The model village visited was proposed by                              terview would be about daily domestic life including water&#13;
    ACORD. Two non-model villages were selected randomly                               and sanitation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4                                                                                                                            Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;A Case Study on the Tippy-Tap in Uganda   Conducting a Qualitative Case Study in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
During the Interviews:                                                         2.4 Study Limitations&#13;
                                                                               This study had a number of limitations that should be&#13;
Householders were asked about where they washed their                          borne in mind when interpreting the results:&#13;
hands and what they used for handwashing.                                         1. Despite efforts to focus the fieldwork in areas where&#13;
                                                                                      promotion of the tippy-tap had ceased, interven-&#13;
Householders with a tippy-tap were interviewed about when                             tions were still active in the villages studied. Thus, it&#13;
and why they acquired the tippy-tap, how they learned                                 was not possible to assess the extent to which tippy-&#13;
about it and their opinions of it (including ease of con-                             tap use is sustained in the absence of active promo-&#13;
struction and use, appearance, maintenance, main advan-                               tion efforts.&#13;
tages and problems, and how it compared with their                                2. Introduction to villages and interpretation during in-&#13;
previous practice).                                                                   terviews was done through District Health Inspectors.&#13;
                                                                                      The inspectors appeared to have excellent rapport&#13;
                                                                                      with householders but were probably perceived by&#13;
Householders without a tippy-tap were asked whether they&#13;
                                                                                      householders as associated with the interventions, po-&#13;
knew about tippy-taps, how they knew about them, what&#13;
                                                                                      tentially increasing the possibility of respondent bias.&#13;
they thought of them, and whether they were happy with&#13;
                                                                                  3. In order to ensure that respondents were present for&#13;
their current handwashing practice.&#13;
                                                                                      interviews it was necessary to make arrangements on&#13;
                                                                                      the day prior to interview. Householders were aware&#13;
Households in model villages were asked about their aware-                            that the interview would cover different household&#13;
ness of and contact with the intervention. They were also                             technologies including water and sanitation. It is&#13;
asked about whether they talked about or promoted the                                 therefore possible that householders made efforts to&#13;
tippy-tap to friends and neighbors.                                                   ensure the presence of soap and water at tippy-taps.&#13;
                                                                                  4. A quantitative assessment of handwashing rates or&#13;
Households in non-model villages were asked about their con-                          prevalence of tippy-taps was not included as part of&#13;
tact with the model village in their sub-county.                                      this study.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                                  5&#13;
&amp;#12;    III.               Findings and&#13;
                       Discussion&#13;
    3.1 Handwashing Facilities in Households                         was a blue laundry bar either placed on a rack or soap dish&#13;
    All households that owned tippy-taps had constructed them        on the frame of the tippy-tap or suspended on a cord tied to&#13;
    close to their latrine on the route between the latrine and      the frame and covered with a cut-off plastic drinking water&#13;
    the house. They reported that they used it exclusively for       bottle.&#13;
    washing hands after latrine use. When washing hands at&#13;
    other times, such as before eating, before preparing food, or    Very few respondents from non-model villages had tippy-&#13;
    on returning from the fields hands were washed beside the        taps. In households without tippy-taps, householders re-&#13;
    house or in the kitchen using a jerry can of water and some-     ported washing their hands using soap and a jerry can of&#13;
    times a bowl.                                                    water. Practices varied between individuals and between&#13;
                                                                     households.&#13;
    Not all tippy-taps had water in them at the time of the vis-&#13;
    its. This does not necessarily imply that they were not in use   Sometimes water was poured from the jerry can into a bowl&#13;
    since it may be that they had been emptied through use in        for washing and sometimes it was used directly from the&#13;
    the course of the day (observations took place in the late       jerry can. Some households used a small (3 liter) jerry can&#13;
    mornings and afternoons).                                        for handwashing rather than pouring directly from a&#13;
                                                                     20-liter jerry can. Common practice was to keep the jerry&#13;
    Almost all tippy-taps had soap beside them or contained          cans and water inside the house and to bring them out for&#13;
    small pieces of soap within the water. The type of soap used     handwashing when needed. However, some households&#13;
                                                                     kept a small jerry can with water beside the latrine that was&#13;
                                                                     reported to be specifically for handwashing after latrine use.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     3.2 Uptake of the Tippy-Tap&#13;
                                                                     Householders acquired tippy-taps as the result of hygiene&#13;
                                                                     promotion and inspection efforts or because they came as&#13;
                                                                     part of a package of home improvements (offered in the&#13;
                                                                     ACORD model village only). That is to say they acquired&#13;
                                                                     them because they were told that they should, because they&#13;
                                                                     were told about the need to avoid contamination of the&#13;
                                                                     jerry can and because they knew that there were household&#13;
                                                                     inspections to check on hygiene and sanitation&#13;
                                                                     arrangements.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     That is not to suggest that households were coerced into&#13;
                                                                     acquiring tippy-taps, however there was no suggestion that&#13;
                                                                     tippy-taps are seen as a `must have' technology, nor was it&#13;
                                                                     clear that the benefits of tippy-taps reported by owners were&#13;
                                                                     sufficient to drive adoption without the social pressure re-&#13;
                                                                     sulting from household visits and inspections.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     This qualitative study was not able to assess the true extent&#13;
                                                                     of diffusion of tippy-taps. The impression gained from in-&#13;
                                                                     terviews was that diffusion of tippy-taps to households out-&#13;
    Many households reported increased rates of handwashing&#13;
                                                                     side of the model villages did occur but was very limited.&#13;
    with soap after constructing tippy-taps.&#13;
                                                                     Only one individual interviewed said that she had seen the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6                                                                                                        Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;A Case Study on the Tippy-Tap in Uganda   Findings and Discussion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   REASONS TO GET A TIPPY-TAP&#13;
&#13;
   `I was told to get [a tippy-tap] and there are&#13;
   inspections.'&#13;
                  --Woman, Mbarara District model village&#13;
&#13;
   `I was told to get one because the village is&#13;
   competing.'&#13;
                     --Man, Mbarara District model village&#13;
&#13;
   `We got [the tippy-tap] with the water tank, stove and&#13;
   latrine.'&#13;
                         --Woman, ACORD model village&#13;
&#13;
   `I built [the tippy-tap] yesterday because I knew visitors&#13;
   (i.e. the interview team) were coming.'&#13;
                    --Woman volunteer, Village Health Team,&#13;
                            Ibanda District non-model village&#13;
&#13;
   `We were made aware of the advantage [of avoiding&#13;
   contamination of the jerry can].'                                Tippy-taps are low-cost and can be easily constructed&#13;
                  ­Woman, Ibanda District model village             using available materials.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
tippy-tap and decided to construct one for herself (rather than being told she          Within model villages, respondents&#13;
should have one). The reason given for construction was that she thought it             had acquired tippy-taps as the&#13;
                                                                                        result of direct promotion by health&#13;
looked modern and would be attractive for visitors to use. Two other households&#13;
                                                                                        workers rather than diffusion through&#13;
with tippy-taps were among respondents in non-model villages. One had con-              neighboring tippy-tap users.&#13;
structed a tippy-tap four or five years previously, following health education pro-&#13;
vided by the District Health Authority as part of a cholera prevention campaign.&#13;
The other was a volunteer in the Village Health Team (VHT) who had been&#13;
taught about tippy-taps by the Health Assistant a month earlier but had built the&#13;
tippy-tap the previous day on hearing that she was going to be visited and inter-&#13;
viewed. Within model villages, respondents had acquired tippy-taps as the result&#13;
of direct promotion by health workers rather than diffusion through neighboring&#13;
tippy-tap users.&#13;
&#13;
Two householders were lapsed users. One from a non-model village said his wife&#13;
had found the tippy-tap more difficult to use than a jerry can and therefore they&#13;
no longer have a tippy-tap. He taught adult education classes and had taught a&#13;
class about the tippy-tap. He learned about the tippy-tap when being trained for&#13;
the teaching. He believed that only one of his students had constructed a tippy-&#13;
tap following the lesson and that this was an elderly woman who in his words had&#13;
`enough time and money not to be concerned with other things.' The other&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                7&#13;
&amp;#12;    A Case Study on the Tippy-Tap in Uganda   Findings and Discussion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    `Is it common? I have not                           respondent, also male and from a non-model village, had promoted tippy-taps as&#13;
                                                        a volunteer with the Child Health Uganda campaign in 2006 and was now a&#13;
    heard.'                                             VHT volunteer. He said that parts of his tippy-tap had been stolen and that he&#13;
                 ­Man, Mbarara District,                could see no advantage over simply having a jerry can. In his view people con-&#13;
                      non-model village                 struct tippy-taps during campaigns because there are inspections and they fear&#13;
                                                        fines but subsequently drop them.&#13;
&#13;
                                                        Another male respondent from a non-model village had a tippy-tap at his other&#13;
                                                        home in Mbarara town. He had it constructed after an inspection from the health&#13;
                                                        department. Although he said he liked the tippy-tap he did not see the need to&#13;
                                                        construct one at his home in the village.&#13;
&#13;
                                                        Respondents from households without tippy-taps in non-model villages had not&#13;
                                                        heard of tippy-taps.&#13;
&#13;
                                                        In model villages respondents without tippy-taps offered explanations as to why&#13;
                                                        they did not have one. These responses suggest that respondents believed that the&#13;
                                                        interviewers expected them to have tippy-taps but that constructing them was&#13;
                                                        not a high priority for households: Two respondents from the ACORD model&#13;
                                                        village reported that their tippy-taps had been stolen (although inspection beside&#13;
                                                        the latrine found no evidence of their having been constructed). Other respon-&#13;
                                                        dents who had heard of tippy-taps said that they did not have them because they&#13;
                                                        had only recently moved in (several months ago), were waiting to get the home&#13;
                                                        improvement package (in the ACORD model village), were waiting until they&#13;
                                                        construct a new latrine, or were waiting to hear more about them from the VHT.&#13;
&#13;
                                                        3.3 Advantages and Disadvantages of the Tippy-Tap&#13;
    The most important advantage                        Householders with a tippy-tap reported that it has advantages over using a jerry&#13;
    was considered to be that it avoids                 can in that it avoids contamination of the jerry can, uses less water, and is easier&#13;
    contamination.                                      to use. The most important advantage was considered to be that it avoids&#13;
                                                        contamination.&#13;
&#13;
                                                        The possibility of contaminating the jerry can used for handwashing is something&#13;
                                                        that householders were told about by Health Assistants and VHT volunteers dur-&#13;
                                                        ing health education sessions (either in group meetings or during household vis-&#13;
                                                        its). Through health education sessions householders hear that washing hands&#13;
                                                        after using the latrine is important in preventing disease, that provision should be&#13;
                                                        made for handwashing by the latrine, and that the tippy-tap prevents contamina-&#13;
                                                        tion by avoiding contact between hands and the jerry can. They also are informed&#13;
                                                        that the tippy-tap uses less water. Householders who have not been exposed to&#13;
                                                        these health education messages do not mention the need for a solution to avoid&#13;
                                                        contamination of the jerry can. It is not clear whether householders with tippy-&#13;
                                                        taps now felt a genuine need to avoid contamination of their jerry cans as a result&#13;
                                                        of the hygiene education or whether they were simply repeating an explanation&#13;
                                                        given to them by the health workers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8                                                                                                                 Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;A Case Study on the Tippy-Tap in Uganda   Findings and Discussion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Perhaps unsurprisingly all respondents who had a tippy-tap disagreed with the          `Perhaps it is not modern to&#13;
interviewer's suggestion that some people thought it did not look very modern.&#13;
                                                                                       you but for us it is.'&#13;
However, one male respondent (a lapsed tippy-tap user in a non-model village)                            -- Woman from&#13;
said he thought the tippy-taps did not look attractive and that this was a problem                          model village&#13;
in promoting them.&#13;
&#13;
Households without a tippy-tap generally had no experience of them and were unable     Households without a tippy-tap&#13;
to comment on them. Those that were aware of them said that they believed they are     generally had no experience of them&#13;
better than a jerry can and that they planned to get one soon. One elderly woman       and were unable to comment on them.&#13;
however, reported that she considered the tippy-tap to be childish and unnecessary&#13;
and suggested that people used to live longer before tippy-taps were invented.&#13;
&#13;
Most tippy-tap users interviewed said that they found the tippy-taps easy to refill.&#13;
Refilling rates varied according to the size of the household. Reported rates ranged&#13;
from twice daily to once per week. However, respondents did not want larger&#13;
reservoirs of water in their tippy-taps as it was thought that these would become&#13;
stagnant and would allow algae to grow in them.&#13;
&#13;
Most tippy-tap users interviewed also reported having to replace the jerry can,&#13;
string and wooden frame every year as they wear out and degrade in sunlight. The&#13;
fact that respondents report making these replacements suggests that they were&#13;
motivated to continue using them. It is not known if this is because of the ongo-&#13;
ing hygiene promotion and inspections or because they have adopted the habit of&#13;
handwashing with the tippy-tap.&#13;
&#13;
All respondents with tippy-taps reported that they found them easier to use than&#13;
a plain jerry can. However, all of these respondents continued to use a jerry can&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   REPORTED DISADVANTAGES OF TIPPY-TAPS&#13;
&#13;
   Most tippy-tap users interviewed reported having to&#13;
   replace the jerry can, string, and wooden frame every&#13;
   year as they wear out and degrade in sunlight. One&#13;
   respondent suggested that a frame made of metal&#13;
   would be a useful improvement.&#13;
&#13;
   Other problems associated with tippy-taps were chil-&#13;
   dren playing with them and using all the water and the&#13;
   problem of jerry cans, water, or soap being stolen or&#13;
   used without permission. These problems were par-&#13;
   ticularly acute in villages with severe water shortages&#13;
   and varied depending on the location of the house&#13;
   and the latrine.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                             9&#13;
&amp;#12;     A Case Study on the Tippy-Tap in Uganda   Findings and Discussion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     `It is more difficult to dodge                      for handwashing at times other than after latrine use. When asked why, if they&#13;
                                                         genuinely found the tippy-tap easier to use and a means of saving water they had&#13;
     handwashing.'                                       not constructed an additional tippy-tap beside the house, all respondents reacted&#13;
                       --Woman, ACORD                    with embarrassed laughter followed by an explanation such as `We have not been&#13;
                            model village                told,' `We were not aware of the need,' and `If you tell us to we will construct one&#13;
                                                         tomorrow.'&#13;
&#13;
     The responses again suggest that                    This suggests two possibilities: 1) despite what respondents reported, there are&#13;
     tippy-taps are seen as something                    features of the tippy-tap that make it less convenient to use than a jerry can or&#13;
     that is done to comply with the                     2) that other household handwashing takes place at various locations--meaning&#13;
     recommendations of the Health&#13;
                                                         that a fixed tap in general or a tippy-tap in particular would not be convenient.&#13;
     Assistants and VHTs.&#13;
                                                         The responses again suggest that tippy-taps are seen as something that is done to&#13;
                                                         comply with the recommendations of the Health Assistants and VHTs.&#13;
&#13;
                                                         3.4 Effect of the Tippy-Tap on Handwashing Rates&#13;
                                                         Collecting data on handwashing rates is a challenge and such data are likely to be&#13;
                                                         prone to bias. No data were collected in this study to quantify handwashing. It is&#13;
                                                         likely that the presence of the tippy-tap close to the latrine on the route to the&#13;
                                                         house acts as a salient reminder to wash hands and also facilitates handwashing by&#13;
                                                         providing a convenient source of soap and water. Some households already kept&#13;
                                                         a jerry can beside the latrine to facilitate handwashing but for others the tippy-tap&#13;
                                                         is the first time a handwashing facility has been provided close to the latrine.&#13;
&#13;
                                                         Access to a convenient handwashing station has been found to be associated with&#13;
                                                         higher rates of handwashing10 and decreased fingertip contamination11. However,&#13;
                                                         it is also worth noting findings from rural Bangladesh where the distance from&#13;
                                                         the latrine to the handwashing place was not associated with a decrease in hand-&#13;
                                                         washing rates12 and findings from urban Bangladesh where availability of soap at&#13;
                                                         the handwashing place was found to decrease with increasing distance from the&#13;
                                                         house13. Thus, it may be worth exploring with households the optimal site for a&#13;
                                                         tippy-tap and accepting that this may not be beside the latrine.&#13;
&#13;
                                                         Respondents with tippy-taps reported that handwashing after latrine use had in-&#13;
                                                         creased in their households as a result of having the device.&#13;
&#13;
                                                         Respondents with tippy-taps also reported that children enjoyed using them be-&#13;
                                                         cause of the novelty of the foot pedal. The tippy-tap may thus play a useful role&#13;
                                                         in nurturing the handwashing habit among children.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         10&#13;
                                                            Biran, A., A. Tabyshalieva, and Z Salmorbekova. 2005. "Formative research for hygiene promotion in Kyrgyzstan."&#13;
                                                            Health Policy and Planning 20 (4) 213­221.&#13;
                                                         11&#13;
                                                            Pinfold, J. V. 1990. "Fecal contamination of water and fingertip-rinses as a method for evaluating the effect of&#13;
                                                            low-cost water-supply and sanitation activities on fecooral disease transmission. A case-study in rural North-East&#13;
                                                            Thailand." Epidemiology and Infection 105 (2) 363­375.&#13;
                                                         12&#13;
                                                            Luby, S. P., et al. 2008. "Associations among handwashing indicators, wealth and symptoms of childhood&#13;
                                                            respiratory illness in urban Bangladesh." Trop Med Int Hlth 16 (6) 835­844.&#13;
                                                         13&#13;
                                                            Luby, S. P., et al, 2009. "Household Characteristics Associated With Handwashing With Soap in Rural&#13;
                                                            Bangladesh." Am J Trop Med Hyg 81 (5) 882­887.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10                                                                                                                                        Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;A Case Study on the Tippy-Tap in Uganda             Findings and Discussion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Where homesteads are close together the visibility of tippy-&#13;
taps may also help to encourage handwashing as a social                                    FIVE ATTRIBUTES THAT CONTRIBUTE TO THE&#13;
norm if they become sufficiently common, used, and                                         DIFFUSION OF INNOVATION&#13;
maintained.&#13;
                                                                                           Five attributes of innovations seem to be strongly&#13;
3.5 Implications for Scaling Up                                                            related to the speed with which they diffuse in&#13;
Five attributes of innovations seem to be strongly related to                              populations:&#13;
the speed with which they diffuse in populations. These are                                    1. The ease with which an innovation can be&#13;
not objective attributes of an innovation but rather percep-                                      understood and used;&#13;
tions that the target group holds about it. Additionally up-                                   2. The opportunity to experiment with it on a&#13;
take of innovations is frequently associated with status                                          limited basis;&#13;
seeking.14                                                                                     3. The relative advantage of the innovation&#13;
                                                                                                  over existing practice;&#13;
Interviews with householders suggest that the tippy-tap is                                     4. The ease with which the innovation can be&#13;
easy to understand and use; its low cost should make it easy                                      observed before adoption; and&#13;
to try out on a limited basis; and users of the tippy-tap iden-                                5. Compatibility with existing values and&#13;
tified advantages over previous practices. It should also be                                      needs.&#13;
reasonably easy to observe the tippy-tap prior to uptake.&#13;
The tippy-tap does not seem to conflict with existing values;&#13;
however, the extent to which it addresses a salient perceived&#13;
need is questionable. Promotion of the tippy-tap aims to                                use of face-to-face communication and the provision of re-&#13;
create a need amongst householders to avoid contamina-                                  wards and sanctions are all factors that have been associated&#13;
tion of the jerry can when washing hands, and may be suc-                               with behavior change and indeed this approach seems rea-&#13;
cessful in this. However, it may be more effective to start                             sonably effective, at least in the short term. However there&#13;
with a sound understanding of the existing needs of the                                 are likely to be problems associated with using this ap-&#13;
target group and to think about how best to address these                               proach at scale because it is very labor intensive, requiring&#13;
needs through a facilitating technology. The extent to which                            multiple visits to households over an extended period.&#13;
the tippy-tap is able to deliver status benefits is also not&#13;
                                                                                        Sub-counties vary in size and Health Assistants do not work&#13;
clear.&#13;
                                                                                        on a standard schedule. However, typically a sub-county&#13;
The social networks into which innovations are released in-                             might comprise around fifty villages and a Health Assistant&#13;
fluenced the speed of diffusion. In the Ugandan context                                 might aim to visit a village two or three times during a year.&#13;
there was little contact between model and non-model vil-                               A village may comprise eighty to one hundred households.&#13;
lages and, even within villages, homesteads could be fairly                             In a single day, if households are close together and house-&#13;
isolated from each other. As a result dissemination of                                  holders are at home, a Health Assistant might manage to&#13;
knowledge of the tippy-tap was slow and even within model                               visit thirty households. However, households are often scat-&#13;
villages not all households were even aware of the                                      tered and people are often away from home meaning that&#13;
tippy-tap.                                                                              the actual number of households reached is likely to be&#13;
                                                                                        much lower. Radio achieves wider coverage than Health As-&#13;
The projects rely on health education and instruction by                                sistants and VHTs. Most householders in model and non-&#13;
Health Assistants or VHT volunteers to create demand for                                model villages had some exposure to health and hygiene&#13;
tippy-taps and to give people the skills to make them, and                              education through the radio. However, promoting a new&#13;
on inspections to encourage and enforce continued mainte-                               technology such as the tippy-tap through a non-visual com-&#13;
nance of tippy-taps. The authority of health workers, the                               munication channel is likely to be difficult. This means that&#13;
                                                                                        the task of promoting the tippy-tap currently falls largely to&#13;
14&#13;
     Rogers, E. M. 2003. Diffusion of Innovations. 5th edition. Free Press, New York.   the volunteer VHTs.&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         11&#13;
&amp;#12;     A Case Study on the Tippy-Tap in Uganda            Findings and Discussion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     VHTs are probably reasonably effective at delivering simple                           tippy-tap that looked more attractive and did not wear out&#13;
     health education messages over limited time periods. They                             so rapidly.&#13;
     are probably less suitable for delivering motivational or so-&#13;
     cial marketing messages and would probably be unwilling                               This is not to imply that a commercial handwashing technol-&#13;
     to invest large amounts of time over long periods in pro-                             ogy is a necessity. Social (not for profit) marketing of the&#13;
     moting handwashing and tippy-taps.                                                    tippy-tap might also succeed. However, attempts to market a&#13;
                                                                                           handwashing technology, whether commercially or as part of&#13;
     Another issue related to scale is the sustainability of the in-                       a social marketing or behavior change communication ap-&#13;
     tervention. As tippy-taps were still being actively promoted                          proach are most likely to succeed if the product promoted is&#13;
     in the model villages at the time of this study, it is not pos-                       based on a sound understanding of the needs and preferences&#13;
     sible to comment on the long-term sustainability of their                             of the intended consumers. The promotion of the technology&#13;
     use. However, inspections and the possibility of sanctions                            must also be based on drivers (such as status) or other behav-&#13;
     appeared to play an important role in promoting and rein-                             ioral determinants identified through research. Respondents&#13;
     forcing the use of tippy-taps. It is not clear if tippy-taps                          are only able to judge the usefulness and performance of the&#13;
     alone will deliver sufficient benefits for households to sus-                         tippy-tap relative to other facilitating technologies. In this&#13;
     tain their use once the possibility of inspections subsides.                          study neither households with tippy-taps nor those without&#13;
     This problem may be exacerbated by the need to replace                                had experience of using an alternative technology besides the&#13;
     worn-out components annually since in the absence of in-                              jerry can and they could not tell whether the tippy-tap is the&#13;
     spections householders may lack the motivation to main-                               technology that best addresses their needs.&#13;
     tain tippy-taps in working order. On the other hand, it is&#13;
     possible that inspections over a limited period of time will                          3.6 Conclusions&#13;
     prove sufficient to allow a handwashing habit to develop                              Tippy-taps are a cheap and acceptable enabling technology&#13;
     through repetitions of the behavior, with the presence of                             for handwashing after latrine use in this rural Ugandan&#13;
     the tippy-tap acting as a cue, and that this habit will be suf-                       population.&#13;
     ficiently powerful to motivate maintenance and continued&#13;
     use of tippy-taps. Research on sustainability of hygiene be-                          The tippy-taps probably increased handwashing after la-&#13;
     havior change in schools has found this to be positively cor-                         trine use by providing convenient soap and water, and by&#13;
     related with the duration of the intervention.15 It is not                            acting as a salient cue to wash hands. The tippy-taps were&#13;
     known whether there is an optimal duration for tippy-tap                              also attractive and easy for children to use and may help&#13;
     enforcement after which maintenance of the practice be-                               foster the habit of handwashing among children.&#13;
     comes stable.&#13;
                                                                                           Tippy-tap users perceived benefits of the tippy-tap but it is&#13;
     A commercially marketed enabling technology might be                                  not clear if these perceptions motivated adoption of the&#13;
     able to achieve more widespread coverage in the long run                              technology or if they came about as a result of becoming a&#13;
     avoiding the need to rely on volunteers for promotion and                             tippy-tap user. Perception of the tippy-tap among non-&#13;
     distribution. In view of the low cost and ease with which                             users is unknown as they generally had no knowledge of the&#13;
     households are able to make tippy-taps it is unlikely that                            technology. Some consumer research might be useful to un-&#13;
     they could be commercially marketed in their current form.                            derstand the needs of householders in relation to hand-&#13;
     There might be a market for an improved version of the                                washing and whether the tippy-tap is the technology that&#13;
                                                                                           best meets these needs or whether a different technology,&#13;
     15&#13;
          Cairncross, S. and K. Shordt. 2003. "It Does Last. Some Findings from a Multi-&#13;
                                                                                           either homemade or commercially produced, might be&#13;
          Country Study of Hygiene Sustainability." Waterlines 22: 3 4­7.                  more desirable. Research of this sort carried out recently in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12                                                                                                                             Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;A Case Study on the Tippy-Tap in Uganda             Findings and Discussion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Vietnam was useful in revealing consumer needs such as a                                   because it relies on labor-intensive, repeated visits to villages&#13;
preference for squatting while washing hands and a desire                                  and households. An alternative might be to use radio as a&#13;
to control the flow of water.16                                                            means of stimulating interest and promoting demand for a&#13;
                                                                                           handwashing technology, and then to use a short, intensive&#13;
Although this study did not collect quantitative data on the                               intervention over two or three days in a village in an effort&#13;
prevalence of tippy-taps, diffusion of the tippy-tap beyond                                to get uptake in a majority of households, hoping that visi-&#13;
the model villages in which it was promoted seemed very                                    ble uptake by the majority would create a social norm that&#13;
limited. This may be because the social networks connect-                                  would drive uptake in remaining households and help sus-&#13;
ing villages are relatively few and weak and because addi-                                 tainability. This could be supported by efforts such as dis-&#13;
tional means of promotion are not currently used (radio                                    trict level direct consumer contact events and low-literacy&#13;
may not be a suitable medium for this).                                                    comic strips such as these being used or planned for hygiene&#13;
                                                                                           promotion in Tanzania.17 Radio could again be used to re-&#13;
The `model village' approach in its current form would be                                  inforce the belief that having and using a handwashing&#13;
difficult to scale up to cover an entire district and beyond                               technology is a social norm.&#13;
&#13;
16                                                                                         17&#13;
     Devine, J. 2010. Insights from Designing a Handwashing Station for Rural Vietnamese        Devine, J and Y. Coombes. 2010. Personal communication. WSP. June.&#13;
     Households. WSP Learning Note, February.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                     13&#13;
&amp;#12;     A Case Study on the Tippy-Tap in Uganda Appendix 1: The ACORD Project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Appendix 1: ACORD Project&#13;
     The ACORD water and sanitation project began in 2008                    fortnightly slots on a private radio station. This is funded&#13;
     and is scheduled to run for three years. The project is work-           50 percent by ACORD (as part of a different project) and&#13;
     ing in eight model villages, each in a different sub-county.            50 percent from the radio station's corporate social respon-&#13;
     These villages were selected by ACORD in collaboration                  sibility budget. The talk show slots last for one hour and&#13;
     with the district Department of Health as ones in which the             cover a variety of health topics including water and sanita-&#13;
     project is thought likely to have a reasonable chance of suc-           tion and hygiene issues.&#13;
     cess (i.e., they are not the poorest and they have reasonably&#13;
     well functioning and supportive leadership structures and a             In each model village the project works with three or more&#13;
     need for improvements to water supply).                                 selected women's savings groups. These groups operate as&#13;
                                                                             credit groups and allocate funds to households on a rotating&#13;
     Scope of the Intervention                                               basis to enable them to purchase the promoted technolo-&#13;
     The project is not only promoting hand hygiene but a pack-              gies. Local materials and labor are provided through the&#13;
     age of home improvements including rainwater harvesting,                savings groups. Non-local materials are sourced through the&#13;
     improved pit latrines, improved domestic hygiene (through               project at a 50-percent subsidy through which ACORD&#13;
     use of dish racks, garbage disposal pits, urinals, and bathing          matches each household package of technologies funded by&#13;
     shelters) and fuel efficient stoves.                                    the savings groups. A household package comprises a rain-&#13;
                                                                             water-harvesting tank, an improved latrine (with cement&#13;
     The project uses a combination of community mobilization,               slab, vent pipe, and iron roof ), a fuel-saving stove, and a&#13;
     health education, and social pressure and enforcement along             tippy-tap.&#13;
     with a subsidy for the purchase of materials and technical&#13;
     support for construction. The approach followed by the proj-            The project is working in a water-scarce area in which&#13;
     ect is to establish model villages at the sub-county level in           women report journey time of an hour or more to collect&#13;
     which the interventions are promoted through a process of               water. The experience of ACORD has been that rainwater&#13;
     community mobilization, construction of demonstration                   harvesting systems are a priority for households and that&#13;
     units (latrines, stoves, water tanks, and tippy-taps), technical        provision of these systems serves as an entry point for the&#13;
     training of selected individuals and group meetings, house-             project allowing the opportunity for promotion of hand-&#13;
     hold visits, and community events to promote uptake and                 washing and other household hygiene practices.&#13;
     behavior change. Meetings and community events are open&#13;
     to group members as well as non-group members. Hygiene                  The project works with the district Department of Health&#13;
     promotion focuses on education and raising awareness about              at the sub-county level. In each sub-county one Health&#13;
     diarrhea transmission routes, the importance of handwash-               Assistant from the Department of Health is active in the&#13;
     ing with soap after latrine use and before handling food, and           model village. In the village the Health Assistant is sup-&#13;
     the use of the tippy-tap to avoid contamination of the jerry            ported by a volunteer coordinator who acts as a point of&#13;
     can while handwashing. As described by one ACORD staff                  contact between the project and the savings groups and&#13;
     member this amounts to `telling people the do's and don'ts and          households and who coordinates and facilitates meetings&#13;
     explaining the key times for washing hands.'                            and household visits. The Health Assistants work with the&#13;
                                                                             savings groups to agree on action plans and to arrange for&#13;
     Additional promotion of technologies and health messages                follow-up support visits as needed. Sensitization visits&#13;
     comes from the use of radio by the district health authori-             raise awareness of the project aims and way of working.&#13;
     ties and by ACORD. Since 2009 there have been                           Subsequent visits to households focus on priorities with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14                                                                                                             Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;A Case Study on the Tippy-Tap in Uganda Appendix 1: The ACORD Project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
respect to hygiene and water and sanitation as identified                       · Construction of forty-four household ventilated im-&#13;
by the Health Assistant or village coordinator in discus-                         proved pit (VIP) latrines&#13;
sion with householders. Health Assistants facilitate group                      · Construction of forty-four fuel saving stoves&#13;
meetings with support from ACORD staff as needed.                               · Construction of 300 tippy-taps&#13;
These meetings center on members of the savings groups                          · Household visits to carry out hygiene promotion in&#13;
but are open to all villagers. Progress and plans for imple-                      300 households18&#13;
menting changes in households are reviewed, and also an&#13;
opportunity is provided for the Health Assistant to pro-                There had been no evaluation of the project at the time of&#13;
mote or highlight appropriate health messages. The proj-                the study. Anecdotally, villages vary in how much uptake is&#13;
ect employs two social workers and three technical staff                achieved. It is reported that most success seems to be&#13;
(two civil engineers and one plumber) to provide support                achieved when the village chairman is actively involved and&#13;
in the villages as needed.                                              when the volunteer coordinator at village level is a woman.&#13;
                                                                        Success also depends on the social and political interactions&#13;
Selection of Handwashing Technology                                     that take place at village level.&#13;
There was no formative research to inform design of the&#13;
handwashing technology promoted in the project. The                     The ACORD Project in Mwizi Sub-County&#13;
tippy-tap technology was copied from a UNICEF project                   Model Village&#13;
in Uganda and was regarded by the ACORD project team                    The model village in Mwizi sub-county was visited during&#13;
as being the only suitable handwashing enabling technol-                this study. The village had a population of 108 households.&#13;
ogy available, mostly due to its low cost.                              The project worked with five women's savings groups in this&#13;
                                                                        village (the group members are predominantly but not ex-&#13;
Schools                                                                 clusively women and predominantly but not exclusively&#13;
The project is not working in schools. ACORD would like                 from the model village). There were fifty-seven households&#13;
to include a schools element in subsequent projects if suffi-           that were members of at least one of the savings groups in-&#13;
cient funding is available.                                             volved in the project. The savings groups were selected by&#13;
                                                                        ACORD for involvement in the project on the basis of&#13;
Planning for Sustainability                                             their apparent capacity to collect and distribute funds ef-&#13;
Sustainability is planned for by using existing structures at           fectively among their members. The opportunity for group&#13;
the sub-county and village levels (Health Assistants and sav-           members to obtain rainwater-harvesting systems (water&#13;
ings groups respectively), and by training masons at the vil-           tanks and pipes) was the primary motivation for groups to&#13;
lage level. Health Assistants are already trained in technologies       join the project.&#13;
and basic promotion techniques. The intention is that Health&#13;
Assistants will be able to continue the work, spreading to              A village water and sanitation committee had been formed&#13;
neighboring villages once the project ends.                             from members of the five groups. The committee carried&#13;
                                                                        out home visits to inspect hygiene and sanitation facilities&#13;
Baseline                                                                and can reportedly impose sanctions on households that fail&#13;
A baseline survey of water coverage was conducted at the start          to comply with their recommendations. Sanctions are said&#13;
of the project in 2008. At the time of the visit the consultant         to include the possibility of a fine for not constructing a&#13;
was unable to obtain the report of the baseline survey.                 latrine and the social sanction of the transgressing house-&#13;
                                                                        hold not being used as a meeting place during the rotating&#13;
Monitoring and Evaluation                                               cycle of savings group meetings. Households are reportedly&#13;
The 2008 and 2009 annual reports include the following                  visited approximately every two months.&#13;
among the activities completed per year:&#13;
                                                                        18&#13;
                                                                             The project is working in eight model villages. Assuming that these villages are of&#13;
   · Construction of forty-four domestic rainwater har-                      similar size to those visited during the study, this would equate to a population of&#13;
      vesting tanks                                                          around 800 households.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                    15&#13;
&amp;#12;     A Case Study on the Tippy-Tap in Uganda Appendix 2: Government of Uganda Intervention&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Appendix 2: Government&#13;
     of Uganda Intervention&#13;
     The Government of Uganda intervention started in 2007                        daylight into houses, constructing and maintaining sanitary&#13;
     and is ongoing. This intervention uses essentially the same                  latrines, and construction of bathing shelters. There was no&#13;
     approach as the ACORD intervention, that is, dissemina-                      indication of any strict hierarchy as to the relative importance&#13;
     tion of a variety of health messages through Health Assis-                   of these different messages but rather that Health Assistants&#13;
     tants working with village level volunteers. The main                        were free to use their own judgment as to what was appropri-&#13;
     differences are that materials are not provided and the inter-               ate in order to achieve a suite of changes.&#13;
     vention does not work with savings groups.&#13;
                                                                                  Each village has a Village Health Team (VHT) comprising&#13;
     Each sub-county has a Health Assistant appointed by the                      volunteers trained by the District Health Authority and&#13;
     District Health Authority. Health Assistants visit the vil-                  used to disseminate health messages and carry out inspec-&#13;
     lages within their sub-counties and work with village level                  tions to help encourage and enforce changes at household&#13;
     volunteers to disseminate health messages. In each sub-                      level. These include messages on sanitation and hygiene.&#13;
     county there is a model village in which the work of the                     Prior to the establishment of VHTs the Child Health&#13;
     Health Assistants is concentrated. However, Health Assis-                    Uganda project (a Ugandan Government initiative) oper-&#13;
     tants also carry out similar work to a lesser extent in the                  ated in a similar way, promoting health messages through&#13;
     other villages of the sub-county.                                            village level volunteers and carrying out inspections of sani-&#13;
                                                                                  tary conditions in households.&#13;
     Messages include but are not restricted to the need to wash&#13;
     hands at key times, the need to have a handwashing facility                  A limited number of rainwater-harvesting systems is avail-&#13;
     by the latrine, and the construction and use of tippy-taps.                  able annually through the sub-county municipal authorities&#13;
     Other messages include construction of drying racks for                      at a 50 percent subsidy. In 2010, forty systems were allo-&#13;
     kitchen utensils, growing vegetable gardens, digging garbage                 cated to Mwizi sub-county in Mbarara district by the dis-&#13;
     pits, boiling water for drinking, safe water storage, allowing               trict authorities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16                                                                                                                     Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;A Case Study on the Tippy-Tap in Uganda Appendix 3: Terms of Reference&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Appendix 3: Terms of Reference&#13;
1. Objective and Purpose of Consultancy                                                  only intentional, but also feasible for the target popula-&#13;
The objective of this consultancy is to conduct a case study,                            tion to adopt. These "external factors" noted above have&#13;
delving into the innovation process and framework.                                       been shown to facilitate handwashing behavior, in com-&#13;
                                                                                         bination with other behavioral determinants such as at-&#13;
The purpose of the case study is to investigate the process in                           titudes and beliefs about handwashing and knowledge&#13;
which some of the enabling products have been developed,                                 about the positive consequences of handwashing, among&#13;
what results were obtained, and what lessons can be learned.                             others.&#13;
The results will inform WSP's Global Scaling Up Hand-&#13;
washing Project and the wider water, sanitation, hygiene                                 In the case of handwashing, tippy-taps are perhaps the best-&#13;
promotion, and health communities on the potential role,                                 known enabling product. However, there are many others&#13;
value, and limitations of enabling products and provide in-                              including handwashing stations, soap nets, and soap fea-&#13;
sights into promising practices to maximize scale and                                    tures themselves. A quick online search reveals several&#13;
sustainability.                                                                          guidelines and instructions on how to construct tippy-taps&#13;
                                                                                         or other enabling products. However, very few evaluations&#13;
2. Background                                                                            or assessments, if any, can be found which would document&#13;
The Water and Sanitation Program (WSP) is implementing                                   lessons learned, promising practices (including implemen-&#13;
the Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project with support                                   tation models), successes, and challenges, particularly with&#13;
from the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation. The project will                               respect to changing behavior at large scale, and that might&#13;
test whether innovative promotional approaches to behavior                               inform the design of hygiene promotion programs. This&#13;
change can generate widespread and sustained improvements                                consultancy aims to fill this void and push the learning en-&#13;
in household hygiene and sanitation practices in Peru, Sene-                             velope forward in this area.&#13;
gal, Tanzania, and Vietnam. The project also has a significant&#13;
learning objective, an important component of which is to                                For the purposes of this consultancy, the spectrum of en-&#13;
ascertain the key factors that influence handwashing behavior                            abling products and technologies to be included is limited&#13;
change (also known as behavioral determinants).                                          to those whose primary purpose is to enable handwashing.20&#13;
                                                                                         In this light, technologies that increase water availability,&#13;
Enabling products and technologies are some of the "exter-                               such as rain water harvesting, would be excluded.&#13;
nal factors" that influence individuals' chance to perform&#13;
a behavior, regardless of their ability and motivation to                                Further examples are provided by products and technolo-&#13;
take action.19 Availability of enabling products and tech-                               gies that allow or provide the following:&#13;
nologies is often overlooked in the design of handwash-                                      · Access to water in sufficient quantity to facilitate&#13;
ing initiatives, although it has been well documented that                                      handwashing, such as use of a tippy-tap. Tippy-taps&#13;
behavior change is most successful if the behavior is not                                       are simple and economical handwashing stations&#13;
                                                                                                made with commonly available materials (e.g., a&#13;
                                                                                                gourd, jerry can, and so forth) that allow for release&#13;
19&#13;
     As part of its Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project, WSP developed a behavior&#13;
     change framework to explain handwashing behavior. Called FOAM (Focus on&#13;
     Opportunity, Ability and Motivation), the framework identifies the key factors or&#13;
                                                                                         20&#13;
     determinants that influence handwashing. Enabling products and technologies fall         Both informal and commercially branded products will be considered in the&#13;
     under the Opportunity category of determinants.                                          compilation of the resource guide.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                          17&#13;
&amp;#12;     A Case Study on the Tippy-Tap in Uganda Appendix 3: Terms of Reference&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               of small quantities of water for handwashing, thereby                                      d. How was/were design(s) of enabling product(s)&#13;
               avoiding wasting water.                                                                       developed? What field/pre-testing was con-&#13;
             · Management of soap within a household or institu-                                             ducted? Did design(s) evolve over time?&#13;
               tion (e.g., school, workplace). The end purpose is to                                      e. What was the process of innovation and what can&#13;
               present waste, theft, or spoilage or to facilitate access.                                    be said about its diffusion within the community?&#13;
               Soap nets and dishes are examples.                                                         f. What communication strategy and tools were used&#13;
             · Availability of a handwashing station: a designated                                           to support the rollout or diffusion of the product?&#13;
               or mobile space bringing together water and soap to                                        g. What, other "marketing mix" strategies, if any,&#13;
               wash hands in the household or an institution that,                                           used (e.g., distribution of the product)?&#13;
               ideally, is in close proximity to the sanitation facility                                  h. How is/was sustainability planned for?&#13;
               or the food preparation area.                                                           2. Results and Outcomes22&#13;
                                                                                                          a. What coverage and use were obtained? Were&#13;
     3. Scope of Work                                                                                        these results maintained or have they evolved over&#13;
     Conduct a case study on enabling products for handwashing:                                              time? Why?&#13;
                                                                                                          b. What effect on handwashing rates and behavior&#13;
     The consultant will execute the following tasks:                                                        did they have?&#13;
        1. Develop protocol/framework for a case study based                                              c. What monitoring supported the diffusion efforts&#13;
           on initial research questions to be provided by WSP                                               and what did it consist of?&#13;
           (see attached for partial list), including rationale and                                       d. Was any formative or evaluative research con-&#13;
           justification for country selection, objectives, meth-                                            ducted and if so, what are key findings?&#13;
           ods (including use of knowledge management tools                                               e. Were spillover effects reported/observed (e.g., on&#13;
           such as emerging learning maps), discussion guides,                                               neighboring communities)?&#13;
           timeline and budget, and finalize based on com-                                                f. Were halo effects reported/observed (e.g., inter-&#13;
           ments received from WSP and partners.                                                             est in other innovations such as improved stoves,&#13;
        2. Conduct case study.21                                                                             other improved hygiene practices, etc.)?&#13;
        3. Prepare PowerPoint presentations outlining key                                                 g. Were any other environmental factors present&#13;
           findings and recommendations.                                                                     that would have influenced outcomes (e.g., chol-&#13;
        4. Prepare final report and finalize based on comments                                               era outbreak)?&#13;
           from WSP and partners.                                                                         h. What perspective do local stakeholders have with&#13;
                                                                                                             respect to results and outcomes?&#13;
     Annex&#13;
     Partial List of Research Questions for Case Studies                                               3. Lessons Learned:&#13;
             1. Implementation Strategy:                                                                  a. What are key lessons learned from project de-&#13;
                a. What implementation model was used (e.g.,                                                 sign, implementation, research, and M&amp;E? What&#13;
                   community-based, private sector, etc.)?                                                   could have been done differently, less, more, or&#13;
                b. Was effort part of a stand-alone handwashing ini-                                         better?&#13;
                   tiative or part of an integrated/multiple behaviors                                    b. What limitations to achieving greater scale can&#13;
                   project?                                                                                  be reported and how could these have been over-&#13;
                c. What were roles and responsibilities of organizations/                                    come or overcome in the future?&#13;
                   agencies involved?&#13;
&#13;
     21&#13;
          Peru may be considered as WPS/Peru is currently piloting a handwashing station&#13;
                                                                                               22&#13;
          in collaboration with a plastics manufacturer and soft drink producer. Experiences        As the case study is qualitative, no survey is expected to discuss results and&#13;
          and emergent learning from this innovative implementation model need to be                outcomes. However, it is expected that any secondary data available would be&#13;
          documented.                                                                               examined.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18                                                                                                                                                  Global Scaling Up Handwashing&#13;
&amp;#12;A Case Study on the Tippy-Tap in Uganda Appendix 4: Schedule of Activities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Appendix 4: Schedule of Activities&#13;
&#13;
 Date                                                                            Activities&#13;
 May 10, 2010                      Travel to Uganda&#13;
 May 11, 2010                      Travel to Mbarara District&#13;
                                   Meeting with ACORD&#13;
 May 12, 2010                      Meeting with Chief Administrative Officer Mbarara District&#13;
                                   Interview with volunteer coordinator for ACORD model village&#13;
                                   Interviews with households in ACORD model village in Mwizi sub-county&#13;
 May 13, 2010                      Interviews with households in neighboring village 1, Mwizi sub-county&#13;
 May 14, 2010                      Interviews with households in neighboring village 2, Mwizi sub-county&#13;
 May 15, 2010                      Meeting with Assistant Chief Administrative Officer Ibanda District&#13;
                                   Meeting with Assistant District Health Officer Ibanda District&#13;
                                   Meeting with Health Inspector, Ibanda District&#13;
                                   Interviews with households in Mbarara District model village&#13;
 May 16, 2010                      Travel to Ibanda&#13;
                                   Interviews with households in sub-county model village, Ibanda District&#13;
 May 17, 2010                      Interviews with households in neighboring village, Ibanda District&#13;
                                   Travel to Mbarara&#13;
 May 18, 2010                      Wrap up Meeting in Mbarara District&#13;
                                   Travel to Kampala&#13;
 May 19, 2010                      Travel to UK&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                             19&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;By Adam Biran&#13;
London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine&#13;
&#13;
Acknowledgments                                                      This Working Paper is one in a series of knowledge products designed to&#13;
The author wishes to thank Hannart Nalweysiyo (National              showcase project findings, assessments, and lessons learned in the Global&#13;
                                                                     Scaling Up Handwashing Project. This paper is conceived as a work in&#13;
Handwashing Secretariat) for logistical support throughout           progress to encourage the exchange of ideas about development issues.&#13;
the study; Umar Masereka (District Health Inspector) for&#13;
additional support and translation in Mbarara District; Vincent      WSP is a multi-donor partnership created in 1978 and administered by&#13;
                                                                     the World Bank to support poor people in obtaining affordable, safe, and&#13;
Mugisha (District Health Inspector) and Gerard Yehamye&#13;
                                                                     sustainable access to water and sanitation services. WSP's donors include&#13;
(Health Assistant) for additional support and translation in         Australia, Austria, Canada, Denmark, Finland, France, the Bill &amp; Melinda&#13;
Ibanda District. In addition, the author would like to thank         Gates Foundation, Ireland, Luxembourg, Netherlands, Norway, Sweden,&#13;
WSP, including Harriet Nattabi, Chris Nsubuga-Mugga,                 Switzerland, United Kingdom, United States, and the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
Yolande Coombes, and Jacqueline Devine (Task Manager for             WSP reports are published to communicate the results of WSP's work&#13;
this project) Harriet who helped access information to select        to the development community. Some sources cited may be informal&#13;
a study site, contributed to the study design, and reviewed          documents that are not readily available.&#13;
&#13;
drafts of this report.                                               The findings, interpretations, and conclusions expressed herein are entirely&#13;
                                                                     those of the author and should not be attributed to the World Bank or its&#13;
Photographs courtesy Adam Biran.                                     affiliated organizations, or to members of the Board of Executive Directors&#13;
                                                                     of the World Bank or the governments they represent. The World Bank&#13;
                                                                     does not guarantee the accuracy of the data included in this work.&#13;
Global Scaling Up Handwashing is a WSP project focused on learning&#13;
how to apply innovative promotional approaches to behavior change    The material in this publication is copyrighted. Requests for permission&#13;
to generate widespread and sustained improvements in handwashing     to reproduce portions of it should be sent to wsp@worldbank.org.&#13;
with soap at scale among women of reproductive age (ages 15­49)      WSP encourages the dissemination of its work and will normally grant&#13;
and primary school-aged children (ages 5­9). The project is being    permission promptly. For more information, please visit www.wsp.org.&#13;
implemented by local and national governments with technical&#13;
support from WSP. For more information, please visit www.wsp.org/    © 2011 Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
scalinguphandwashing.&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="13855452">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/02/13855452/enabling-technologies-handwashing-soap-case-study-tippy-tap-uganda
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/02/13855452/enabling-technologies-handwashing-soap-case-study-tippy-tap-uganda</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2011/02/13855452/enabling-technologies-handwashing-soap-case-study-tippy-tap-uganda</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2011-03-03T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/03/03/000356161_20110303012244/Rendered/INDEX/599340WSP0Ugan10Box358302B01PUBLIC1.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/03/03/000356161_20110303012244/Rendered/PDF/599340WSP0Ugan10Box358302B01PUBLIC1.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2011-02-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2011-03-03T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Enabling technologies for handwashing with
            soap : a case study on the tippy-tap in Uganda
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Water and Sanitation Program's
            (WSP) Global scaling up handwashing project is testing
            whether innovative promotional approaches to behavior change
            can generate widespread and sustained improvements in
            household hygiene and sanitation practices in Peru, Senegal,
            Tanzania, and Vietnam. The purpose of this study was to
            document the process through which tippy-taps were promoted
            to qualitatively explore the results and to draw out lessons
            for future interventions. Handwashing with soap at key times
            is believed to be an effective and highly cost effective
            means of reducing diarrhea incidence. However, global rates
            of handwashing with soap are frequently low, particularly
            among the poor, who also face the greatest threat from
            infectious diseases. Access to a convenient handwashing
            station has been found to be associated with higher rates of
            handwashing and decreased fingertip contamination.
            Tippy-taps were an acceptable means of providing a low cost
            enabling technology for handwashing in this population.
            Anecdotally they have increased rates of handwashing after
            latrine use. However, uptake appeared driven by the
            'push' of the intervention rather than the
            'pull' of the technology and the extent to which
            spontaneous uptake and sustained use can be achieved in the
            absence of intensive intervention activities is not known.
            Respondents in non model villages had little contact with
            model villages and were largely unaware of the tippy-tap.
            The interventions were labor intensive and probably
            difficult to scale-up.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Enabling technologies for handwashing with
            soap : a case study on the tippy-tap in Uganda
        </docna>
        <display_title>Enabling technologies for
            handwashing with soap : a case study on the tippy-tap in Uganda</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2011/02/13855452/enabling-technologies-handwashing-soap-case-study-tippy-tap-uganda</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing,Technology Industry,Housing &amp; Human Habitats,Water and Industry</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Resources,Communities and Human Settlements,Industry,Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>Uganda</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Biran, Adam</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Africa!$!80458</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000356161_20110303012244</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>Water and sanitation program working paper ; WSP</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Resources,Communities and Human Settlements,Industry,Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            aged, alternative technology, attributes,
            basic, behavior change, Child Health, cholera, communities,
            components, construction, cost effectiveness, diarrhea,
            Diffusion of Innovations, disease transmission, domestic
            hygiene, drinking water, engineers, Epidemiology, female,
            food preparation, garbage disposal, Hand Washing, hand
            washing facilities, hands with soap, Handwashing, health and
            hygiene, health education, health messages, Health Policy,
            home improvement, household hygiene, household latrines,
            households, houses, hygiene, hygiene behavior, hygiene
            education, hygiene issues, hygiene practices, hygiene
            promotion, hygiene promotion programs, infectious diseases,
            innovations, Intervention, interventions, iron, laundry, new
            technology, pit latrines, promoting health, rainwater
            harvesting, reservoirs, safe water, sanitary latrines,
            SANITATION, sanitation activities, sanitation facilities,
            sanitation practices, sanitation services, shelters, Soap,
            social marketing, social networks, social workers, village
            level, Village Water, villages, washing hands, waste, water
            shortages, water supply, workers
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water- Water and Sanit Prgrm (GWASP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>59934</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Policy Making Policy Coordination</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Behavior Change Communication</ml:concept><ml:concept>Handwashing Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adult Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adult Education, Literacy, and Lifelong Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Continuing Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>HRH</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Workers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Child Survival and Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Early Child and Children's Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Policy Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Policy and Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hygiene Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Elderly</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Lifelong Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources for Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Child Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Knowledge Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>