<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Document of&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Report No. T-7475-COM&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
FOR A PROPOSED CREDIT&#13;
OF SDR 4.8 MILLION (US$ 6 MILLION EQUIVALENT)&#13;
TO&#13;
THE ISLAMIC FEDERAL REPUBLIC OF THE COMOROS&#13;
FOR AN&#13;
EMERGENCY ECONOMIC RECOVERY CREDIT&#13;
JULY 11, 2001&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CURRENCY EQUIVALENTS&#13;
Currency Unit                Comorian Franc&#13;
US$1.00                      580 CF&#13;
SDR 1                        722 CF&#13;
SYSTEM OF WEIGHT AND MEASURES&#13;
Metric System&#13;
FISCAL YEAR&#13;
January 1 - December 31&#13;
ABBREVIATIONS&#13;
ABEDA                    Arab Bank for Economic Development in Africa&#13;
AfDB                     African Development Bank&#13;
CARE                     Cooperative Assistance and Relief Everywhere&#13;
CPPR                     Country Portfolio Performance Review&#13;
DCA                      Development Credit Agreement&#13;
EERC                     Emergency Economic Recovery Credit&#13;
FY                       Fiscal Year&#13;
GDP                      Gross Domestic Product&#13;
GNP                      Gross National Product&#13;
HIPC                     Heavily Indebted Poor Countries&#13;
ICB                      International Competitive Bidding&#13;
IDA                      International Development Association&#13;
IDF                      Institutional Development Fund&#13;
IMF                      International Monetary Fund&#13;
ILO                      International Labor Organization&#13;
I-PRSP                   Interim Poverty Reduction Strategy Paper&#13;
ISS                      Interim Support Strategy&#13;
OAU                      Organization of African Unity&#13;
OIF                      Organization of the Francophonie&#13;
PCF                      Post-Conflict Fund&#13;
PRGF                     Poverty Reduction and Growth Facility&#13;
SAC                      Structural Adjustment Credit&#13;
SMP                      Staff Monitored Program&#13;
SDR                      Special Drawing Rights&#13;
US$                      United States Dollar&#13;
Vice President:                   C. Madavo&#13;
Country Director:                 H. Ghanem&#13;
Sector Manager:                   C. Mills&#13;
Task Team Leader:                 C. Kostopoulos / W. Fengler&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ISLAMIC FEDERAL REPUBLIC OF THE COMOROS&#13;
EMERGENCY ECONOMIC RECOVERY CREDIT&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
A.  Background ................................................                               1&#13;
B.  Recent Political Developments ................................................1&#13;
C.  Recent Economic Developments and Poverty ................................................ 2&#13;
D.  Bank Response and Strategy .........4......................................4&#13;
E.  Detailed Project Description ................................................6&#13;
F.  Role of the IMF and Other Donors ...............................................7&#13;
G.  Institutional Arrangements and Project Implementation .....................................8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ISLAMIC FEDERAL REPUBLIC OF THE COMOROS&#13;
EMERGENCY ECONOMIC RECOVERY CREDIT&#13;
A.   Background&#13;
1.    The Islamic Federal Republic of Comoros comprises three islands in the Indian&#13;
Ocean (Grande Comore, Anjouan, and Moheli), with a population of around 530,000. A&#13;
fourth island, Mayotte, remained under French administration when the Islamic Federal&#13;
Republic of the Comoros became independent. GNP per capita is estimated at US$356 in&#13;
2000, down from about US$500 per capita a decade ago. Comorians living in France&#13;
amount to more than two-thirds of the population of the Republic. They are a source of&#13;
considerable income transfers.&#13;
2.    Since independence, Comoros' politics have been characterized by a high degree&#13;
of political instability including numerous coups d'etat and a period of mercenary&#13;
supported Governments. Even at the time of the referendum for independence ii!&#13;
December 1974, the country was divided when Grande Comore, Anjouan, and Moheli&#13;
voted 96 percent for independence while Mayotte voted 63 percent against. The first&#13;
three islands formed the Islamic Federal Republic of the Comoros and declared their&#13;
independence unilaterally on July 6, 1975, while Mayotte remained under French rule.&#13;
3.    Poor economic performance and continuing poverty through the 1980's were thre&#13;
consequences of the unstable political environment and weak governance. The tirst&#13;
major attempt at reform was the implementation of the first adjustment program in 1991,&#13;
which despite initial delays, led to improvements in public sector manag' ment. This&#13;
contributed to a rise in GDP growth of 1.9 percent per annum. The 1994 devaluatior' of&#13;
the Comorian Franc by 33 percent in foreign currency terms also improveu tht .ullntry's&#13;
competitiveness.&#13;
4.    However, weak fiscal performance and stemmed progress towrels recove.!&#13;
derailed the IMF program. By way of perspective, the Bank's strategy .ti the time&#13;
envisaged the potential for a 6 percent real growth rate based on consolidating the&#13;
benefits of devaluation in export agriculture, deregulation, and public sectot ?ffc3 incv.&#13;
Continued political turmoil and economic management problems delayed preparations&#13;
for a second IDA Structural Adjustment Credit (SAC) and an IMF  ;ai Mon;tored&#13;
Program (SMP) through 1997 when the political crisis in Anjouan erupted.&#13;
5.    The Anjouanese crisis erupted when the island attempted to secede `-frrm the&#13;
Republic in 1997 due to dissatisfaction with an unresponsive central Governm' nt and&#13;
declining living standards. Anjouan contains 45 percent of the country's populatioi. I .1&#13;
Anjouanese secession attempt led to the imposition of an Organization of African Unity&#13;
(OAU) sponsored embargo which severely disrupted trade and exacerbated povertv. A&#13;
Government invasion in 1997 was repulsed but left a legacy of armed militias in Anjouan&#13;
which are a source of local instability.&#13;
B.   Recent Political Developments&#13;
6.    Comoros' political instability results from the twin crises of separatism on&#13;
Anjouan and lack of democratic legitimacy of the central Government. Anjouan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
separatists had refused to accept a compromise agreement negotiated in Antananarivo on&#13;
a new union and dissatisfaction arising from the deteriorating economic situation led to&#13;
unrest in Grande Comore. Riots prompted the army to intervene and take over power in a&#13;
bloodless coup on March 30, 1999.&#13;
7.    Efforts continued to resolve the secessionist crisis and improve the economic&#13;
situation. In December 1999, a civilian Government was named under the leadership of&#13;
Prime Minister Hamada Madi (Bolero), with the support of 22 out of Comoros' 30&#13;
political parties, and promised to carry out elections once the crisis is resolved. An&#13;
agreement on a joint declaration between the President of the Comoros and the head of&#13;
the Anjouan breakaway Government was signed in August 2000. However, the OAU&#13;
would not recognize the agreement as legitimate.&#13;
8.   In February 2001, after a prolonged period of mediation led by the OAU and with&#13;
the assistance of the Organization of the Francophonie (OIF), the representatives of the&#13;
three islands reached an agreement on a national reconciliation process. The agreement,&#13;
signed in Fomboni, Moheli is known as the Fomboni Accord.&#13;
9.    The Fomboni Accord provides for a transition period of one year, from the time&#13;
of its signature until national elections are held under a new constitution. The new&#13;
constitution, which is currently being drafted, would have as a central feature regional&#13;
autonomy for each of the three islands. A referendum on the new constitution would be&#13;
held between July and September 2001.  Upon adoption of the constitution, a&#13;
Government of national unity is expected to govern, for a period of approximately six&#13;
months, and to prepare the country for national elections in early 2002.&#13;
10.   During the transition, the national reconciliation process is being managed by a&#13;
steering committee (Comite de Suivi) consisting of the President of the Republic, two&#13;
members of the Government, two representatives of Grand Comore and Moheli, one&#13;
Anjouanese official and the opposition from the three islands.  The international&#13;
community is represented on the Steering Committee by the OAU and OIF. The&#13;
technical dimensions of the transition process are being managed by a Tri-partite&#13;
Commission consisting of 72 members representing the Government, the opposition, and&#13;
civil society of all three islands. The tasks of the Tri-partite Commission include the&#13;
drafting of the new constitution and the design and implementation of a new financial&#13;
framework.&#13;
11.   The process of reconciliation is still fragile. In late April 2001, the negotiations&#13;
stalled, when Anjouanese representatives withdrew their participation on the Comite de&#13;
Suivi in order to protest OAU's decision to only suspend the embargo; the Anjouanese&#13;
authorities demanded the embargo be lifted.  The Anjouan authorities were also&#13;
dissatisfied with the lack of promised financial transfers from the central Government.&#13;
However, the various parties continue to endorse the reconciliation process. Indeed the&#13;
Tri-partite Commission started its technical work on May 20, 2001.&#13;
C.   Recent Economic Developments and Poverty&#13;
12.   Real GDP in Comoros is estimated to have declined by 1.1 percent in 2000 and&#13;
inflation to have risen by levels close to 5 percent in 2000 due to higher petroleum prices.&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The trade account improved substantially with higher world prices for vanilla, cloves, and&#13;
ylang-ylang, and remittances from abroad rose. The volume of exports continued to&#13;
decline thus offsetting part of the potential benefits of the price rise. Imports rose only&#13;
marginally.&#13;
13.   Public sector management has been proactive during the past year because&#13;
expenditures were reduced following lower than expected revenues. Accordingly, the&#13;
overall fiscal deficit (excluding grants) amounted to 3.8 percent of GDP. The revenue&#13;
decline was due to problems with a new computerized customs administration and tax&#13;
arrears owed by the faltering petroleum company. Current expenditures declined from&#13;
13.8 percent of GDP in 1999 to 12.5 percent in 2000 due mainly to cuts in goods and&#13;
services outlays (see table below). In the absence of foreign budgetary support, the&#13;
resulting deficit was financed by growing external and internal arrears. Civil servants,&#13;
who are owed up to 24 months of salary in total, were paid 11 months in 2000.&#13;
Table 1: Comoros: Key Economic Indicators&#13;
1995   1996   1997   1998   1999   2000   2001&#13;
Estimate projection&#13;
Real GDP growth                3.6   -1.3    4.2    1.2    1.9   -1.1    1.0&#13;
Real GDP per capita growth     0.9   -3.9    1.5   -1.5   -0.8   -3.7   -1.7&#13;
Consumer price index (change)    12.5    2.0    3.0    3.5    3.5    4.8    3.5&#13;
(as percent of GDP)&#13;
Gross domestic fixed          15.5   13.6   13.4   14.7   11.9   10.4   10.2&#13;
investment&#13;
Gross national savings         6.6    4.9   -2.4    8.7    7.8   10.0    9.1&#13;
Fiscal revenue and grants     24.1   20.6   22.6   18.7   18.4   14.4   16.9&#13;
Total expenditure             31.5   26.4   24.9   22.1   19.1   16.3   20.7&#13;
Fiscal balance (with grants)  -7.3   -5.8   -2.2   -3.4   -0.8   -1.9   -3.8&#13;
Current account balance (with  -8.9   -8.7  -15.8   -6.1   -4.1   -0.4   -1.1&#13;
transfers)&#13;
Money supply growth            4.0    6.4    3.1   -3.7    7.0   14.5    5.8&#13;
Source: IMF and World Bank&#13;
14.   Comoros is currently in arrears to its creditors. The country's external debt at&#13;
end-2000 was estimated at US$225 million (113 percent of GDP) of which US$173&#13;
million was owed to multilateral creditors. Interest and principal arrears amounted to&#13;
US$63 million, out of which US$24 million is owed to the Arab Bank for Economic&#13;
Development in Africa (ABEDA), and US$18 million to the African Development Bank&#13;
(AfDB).&#13;
15.   Poverty was already pervasive before the current political crisis took hold.&#13;
According to a 1995 ILO-sponsored household survey, some 47 percent of households&#13;
and 55 percent of individuals lived below the poverty line. Anjouan with 45 percent of&#13;
the population had 56 percent of households and 70 percent of individuals below the&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
poverty line. Moheli with 5 percent ofSthe population had 55 percent of households and&#13;
64 percent of individuals below the poverty line. Grande Comore with 52 percent of the&#13;
population had a third of the households and 41 percent of individuals defined as poor.&#13;
16.   Although surveys and poverty analysis from post-1995 data are not available, the&#13;
level of poverty is expected to have risen as per-capita growth has been negative (see&#13;
table 1). Anjouan has been particularly affected as it was deprived of both imports and&#13;
public services since the effectiveness of the embargo. The decline in economic growth&#13;
has lowered real per capita income by an average of 3 percent a year since 1997, offset in&#13;
part in Grande Comore by rising transfers from abroad. Education was disrupted by&#13;
wage arrears and strikes. Health conditions deteriorated as required social expenditures&#13;
were not made due to persistent budgetary problems. The net primary school enrollment&#13;
rate is 53 percent and only about 58 percent of children under the age of one are&#13;
immunized against prevalent childhood diseases. Only 25 percent of the population has&#13;
access to potable water.&#13;
D.   Bank Response and Strategy&#13;
17.  The Bank resumed disbursements to the Comoros following the clearance of debt&#13;
service arrears in January 2000. At that time the portfolio consisted of five projects with&#13;
US$26 million of undisbursed balances supporting social sectors, private sector&#13;
development, and agricultural services.  Two of these projects (Pilot Agricultural&#13;
Services and Small Enterprise Development) were in the final implementation phases&#13;
and were scheduled to close at end-December 2000 and end-June 2001, respectively.&#13;
T'he Small Enterprise Development Project has been extended.&#13;
18.   A Country Portfolio Performance Review (CPPR) was held in March 2000 to&#13;
assess the appropriateness of the existing portfolio given the country's protracted political&#13;
disputes and two year absence of Bank operations. Effective implementation of existing&#13;
projects was regarded as crucial to reach the economic and social objectives of assisting&#13;
Comoros to emerge from protracted conflict. The CPPR also led to initial discussions&#13;
with the authorities on their national reconciliation and reconstruction strategies. The&#13;
objectives of existing projects were found to be broadly valid but simplification of&#13;
programs and arrangements was recommended. A detailed program of action for the&#13;
following twelve months was agreed upon including acceleration of disbursements,&#13;
restructuring of poorly performing projects, rebuilding project teams and strengthening&#13;
project financial management.  The decision was also taken to assign regional&#13;
coordinators in the three islands for each project to reflect ongoing political concerns.&#13;
19.   Recent progress on national reconciliation has created a new dynamic, which&#13;
suggests a likely solution to the political crisis and provides a basis for the Bretton&#13;
Woods institutions to resume their assistance to Comoros in support of economic and&#13;
social recovery. The resumption of IDA disbursements has allowed projects to resume&#13;
operations on all three islands. In March 2001, the IMF conducted an Article IV mission&#13;
and also negotiated a SMP. A parallel World Bank mission assessed the economic and&#13;
social situation and pre-appraised the proposed operations.&#13;
20.   The World Bank's response to provide an emergency credit to the Comoros&#13;
follows from the Interim Support Strategy (ISS) (IDA/R2000-182) discussed by the&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Board on November 14, 2000. The ISS responded to the volatile political situation and&#13;
then unresolved conflict, which made it imprudent to develop a three-year Country&#13;
Assistance Strategy. Instead, the resumption of Bank activities in Comoros is based on:&#13;
(i) Government commitment to improving economic management and governance, (ii)&#13;
the existence of major poverty problems coupled with inadequate social services, (iii) the&#13;
support the Bank can give to national reconciliation and the avoidance of renewed&#13;
conflict, and (iv) settlement of IDA arrears.&#13;
21.   The ISS contains three scenarios - a low case, a base case and a high case. Under&#13;
the low case, the existence of conflict would make it impossible to implement a coherent&#13;
program, so Bank activities would stop. Under the base case, IDA would supervise the&#13;
existing portfolio and process an infrastructure, water, and environment project.&#13;
22.   At the time of Board presentation of the ISS, the Comoros was in a base case&#13;
scenario. The ISS provides for moving to a high case scenario when Comoros shows&#13;
tangible and decisive progress towards national reconciliation, which is considered a&#13;
necessary pre-condition for emergency assistance to be effective, and substantial&#13;
improvement in public sector management. Triggers in the ISS for the high case scenario&#13;
comprise (i) good perfornance under base case scenario and (ii) preparation of an&#13;
integrated budget with better fiscal management and equitable distribution of resources to&#13;
the three islands.&#13;
23.   Comoros' performance under the base case scenario has been good: the country&#13;
has maintained a socioeconomic environment suitable for development, made progress in&#13;
decentralizing project management to the islands, and has maintained satisfactory&#13;
portfolio performance. An Institutional Development Fund (IDF) grant of US$471,620&#13;
was approved to provide technical assistance for public expenditure management and a&#13;
national development strategy. In March 2001, a new credit (Credit No. 3468-COM) of&#13;
US$11.4 million was approved focusing on infrastructure, water, and environment&#13;
investments. The project is based on decentralized management in each of the three&#13;
islands. The Comoros has also prepared a budget for the current fiscal year which&#13;
integrates transfers between Grande Comore and Anjouan. With additional measures&#13;
taken to improve financial management, Comoros has moved into the high case scenario.&#13;
24.   Given the Comoros' progress on ISS triggers towards a high case scenario, IDA&#13;
moved to pre-appraise the country's request for emergency assistance in March/April&#13;
2001. The mission held discussions with the authorities in Anjouan and Grande Comoros&#13;
and met with representatives of multilateral and bilateral organizations. It confirmed the&#13;
commitment and progress being made towards national reconciliation and the creation of&#13;
a new decentralized state. The mission also concluded that the provision of emergency&#13;
economic assistance was vital to alleviate distress, particularly in Anjouan, to support the&#13;
rehabilitation of the economy and to consolidate the process of reconciliation and nation&#13;
building. At the same time, the Bank approved a post-conflict grant of US$788,000 to&#13;
reintegrate some 650 militias and other at-risk youth into the Anjouanese economy by&#13;
providing training and employment opportunities. The grant will be administered by&#13;
CARE International (see Attachment 2).&#13;
5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
E.   Detailed Project Description&#13;
25.   Comoros is in a transition. The country is emerging from conflict and moving&#13;
towards economic and social rehabilitation, while putting in place the institutions of a&#13;
new decentralized state. The proposed Emergency Economic Recovery Credit (EERC) is&#13;
designed to support the transition until Comoros is prepared to devise and implement a&#13;
medium term poverty reduction program with more conventional financial support. The&#13;
proposed EERC falls within the high case scenario of IDA's ISS. Indeed, time is of the&#13;
essence in this strategy as the transition program cannot be completed without foreign&#13;
financing.&#13;
26.   The proposed EERC is considered an appropriate instrument as it can be quick&#13;
disbursing with no formal tranching. Its objectives are to maintain macroeconomic&#13;
stability and address urgent social needs through financing of import costs associated&#13;
with rebuilding the economy damaged during the emergency. The Government's&#13;
objective is immediate recovery and institutional reforms needed to set the stage for a full&#13;
post transition development program.&#13;
Design of the Credit&#13;
27.   The proposed Credit is designed to be implemented through the financing of a&#13;
positive list of imports which will be disbursed periodically to replenish a foreign&#13;
exchange account in the Central Bank. The foreign exchange will finance eligible private&#13;
and public sector imports (detailed in the Development Credit Agreement). Government&#13;
will request withdrawals through statements of expenditures. World Bank simplified&#13;
procurement procedures as specified in its guidelines will be applied to public and private&#13;
sector imports (see Attachment 5). IDA will conduct a prior review of import contracts&#13;
over US$2 million. Expenditures for a single commodity import such as petroleum will&#13;
not exceed one half of imports financed by the proposed Credit. No proceeds of the&#13;
Credit will be used for food related items for direct consumption.&#13;
28.   The proposed Credit will provide foreign exchange to cover the requirements for&#13;
imports arising from the emergency recovery spending program. Based on retroactive&#13;
financing, up to 20 percent will be released upon signing of the Credit.&#13;
Expenditure Priorities&#13;
29.   The local currency equivalent of the US$6 million EERC would finance&#13;
emergency social and national reconciliation needs. It would cover about 50 percent of&#13;
the estimated budgetary financing gap needed to finance the twelve-month transition.&#13;
The remainder of the US$12.8 million program will be financed by other development&#13;
partners.&#13;
30.   The current budget will be revised by September 2001 in accordance with the&#13;
agreements reached under the SMP in order to incorporate the additional emergency&#13;
social and reconciliation expenditures financed by donors to meet transition needs.&#13;
31.   The Government's program follows the priorities defined by the Comorian&#13;
authorities (in collaboration with authorities of Anjouan and Moheli). The aggregate&#13;
6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
allocations for poverty reduction and decentralization have then been subdivided to&#13;
finance island-specific expenditures. The representatives from the three islands arrived at&#13;
the island-specific allocations by considering the size of the population, the level of&#13;
poverty, and the needs for building decentralized institutions at each island.'&#13;
Table 2: Allocation of Emergency Expenditures&#13;
(in US$ million)&#13;
Anjouan      Moheli    Grande Comore       TOTAL&#13;
Poverty Reduction       1.5          0.3            1.2            3.0&#13;
Decentralization        0.9          0.6            0.3            1.8&#13;
Sub-TOTAL               2.4          0.9            1.5            4.8&#13;
- National                                                          1.6&#13;
Reconciliation&#13;
- Economic                                                          5.6&#13;
Recovery and&#13;
Stabilization&#13;
TOTAL                                                               12&#13;
F.    Role of the IMF and Other Donors&#13;
32.   In March 2001, the IMF conducted an Article IV mission and negotiated a SMP&#13;
for a twelve-month period. The program to be monitored includes measures for&#13;
strengthening central Government finances for the remainder of 2001 and for 2002. The&#13;
program aims at avoiding further accumulation of domestic and external arrears while&#13;
freeing resources to meet debt service obligations. Revenues are to be strengthened and&#13;
tax exemptions eliminated. The IMF estimated that the budgetary financing gap to be&#13;
covered in calendar 2001, including the transition costs, is US$8.3 million. The gap for&#13;
the twelve-month period through June 2002, covering the whole transition, is estimated at&#13;
US$12.8 million.&#13;
33.   In order to assist the Comoros to capitalize on the progression towards national&#13;
reconciliation and to seize this window of opportunity, a conference of the Friends of&#13;
Comoros was held in Paris on July 5 at the Bank's office to confirm pledges to finance&#13;
the transition. IDA will finance half of the transition costs, while other multi-laterals and&#13;
bilaterals will cover the balance. The IMF has prepared an SMP and will present it to its&#13;
Board in later July 2001.&#13;
34.   Comoros' transition out of the present crisis is expected to last until mid-2002.&#13;
The IMF SMP could then be transformed into a Poverty Reduction and Growth Facility&#13;
(PRGF) after a new Government is in place and an Interim Poverty Reduction Strategy&#13;
Paper (I-PRSP) has been prepared.&#13;
' For a detailed description of emergency needs see Government's Letter of Development Policy in&#13;
Attachment 1.&#13;
7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
G.   Institutional Arrangements and Project Implementation&#13;
35.   The Government has created a Office for the Implementation of the Emergency&#13;
Funds which will oversee management of the proposed operation as well as assistance&#13;
from other donors to the National Reconstruction and Reconciliation Program. The&#13;
Office will be coordinated by the Director General for Planning and will have as&#13;
membership representatives of the sectoral departments concerned with the use of the&#13;
funds as well as representatives of the financial departments associated with the&#13;
mobilization and use of the funds. A sub-committee will be responsible for the&#13;
mobilization and control of the funds consisting of the Central Bank, Customs, Treasury,&#13;
and Budget department of the Ministry of Finance. Another sub-committee for&#13;
implementing the use of the funds will consist of representatives from the Ministries of&#13;
Education, Health, Infrastructure and Energy, Agriculture, the Plan Directorate of&#13;
Anjouan, and the coordinator of foreign donor aid.&#13;
36.   The Office will serve as a project implementation unit and will ensure that the&#13;
objectives of the emergency operation are met. It will also provide documentation&#13;
(import bills) to IDA to enable disbursements of the operation to take place, and for&#13;
ensuring their quality in accordance with World Bank procurement and disbursement&#13;
guidelines. The Budget, Planning, and sectoral ministries will manage the use of the&#13;
local currency counterpart of the foreign exchange to support the Government's program.&#13;
37.  IDA has verified that the Government has adequate capacity to control and&#13;
safeguard the use of credit resources and to ensure that the imports for which&#13;
reimbursements will be claimed under the Credit will have been procured following the&#13;
Bank guidelines. The Office and the Central Bank will keep adequate records of (i) all&#13;
IDA funds disbursed under the Credit; (ii) conversion of IDA funds into local currency&#13;
(FC); and (iii) expenditures of local currency in accordance with the agreed allocations&#13;
for various social sectors and for the three islands as specified in Supplemental Letter No.&#13;
3 of the DCA In addition, the Office will submit summary financial statements every&#13;
month and the results of an internal audit conducted quarterly. All transactions under&#13;
EERC will also be audited by an external independent auditor acceptable to IDA as of&#13;
October 2001, January 2002 and a final audit at the end of implementation of the Credit.&#13;
38.   The island of Anjouan will follow the procedures established by the Office in&#13;
implementing emergency expenditures. Representation of the departments on the Office&#13;
would be through their counterpart sectoral ministries and the Secretariat of the Steering&#13;
Committee for National Reconciliation. However, periodic audits, ad hoc surveys and&#13;
site visits will also be at the disposal of the control structures on the island of Anjouan, to&#13;
reinforce local institutions. Anjouanese local budgetary institutions have been managing&#13;
their own expenditures even before the crisis, and will continue to do so.&#13;
39.   Once the constitution has been adopted and the financial institutions of the&#13;
decentralized regional island Government's have been established, the new Government&#13;
will adopt a budget fully integrating revenues and expenditures for all three islands. As&#13;
capacity to manage and verify the use of expenditures related to the EERC is critical to&#13;
ensure program implementation, technical assistance will be provided by France in&#13;
budgetary management and control.&#13;
8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Attachment 1&#13;
Islamic Federal Republic of the Comoros&#13;
Office of the Presidency&#13;
Letter of Policy for National Reconciliation&#13;
July 2001&#13;
A. POLITICAL DEVELOPMENTS AND NATIONAL RECONCILIATION&#13;
The socio-economic difficulties afflicting the Comoros for decades were aggravated&#13;
by a separatist crisis that began in 1997 when the island of Anjouan seceded from the&#13;
Islamic Federal Republic of the Comoros. The crisis had many disastrous consequences&#13;
in terms of political development and impact on development. The secessionist&#13;
disturbances and the persistence of the crisis led the international community to take&#13;
action against the authorities of the island of Anjouan, including suspension of&#13;
cooperation and an economic embargo, which aggravated an already precarious situation.&#13;
The embargo also had a negative impact on the other two islands in the Republic:&#13;
Grande Comore and Moheli.&#13;
The population finds itself without the financial resources essential for imports of&#13;
goods and services and also without the financial support of Comorians living on the&#13;
other islands. The people are demoralized by the trauma resulting from the violence and&#13;
by the disruption of regional and international economic relations, and there has been a&#13;
mass exodus of rural and urban population from the island of Anjouan to the other&#13;
islands. This has affected economic activities in general and contributed to the increase&#13;
in poverty and marked deterioration of social indicators.  For example, rates of&#13;
malnutrition (42.3% in 2000 compared with 33.8% in 1996) and infant mortality are&#13;
rising steadily, while vaccination coverage continues to decline over the same period.&#13;
Steps towards reconciliation&#13;
In the last two years, there have been many political efforts to end the separatist crisis&#13;
affecting the island of Anjouan. On 17 February 2001, under the auspices of the&#13;
international community, the Government, the Anjouan authority, the opposition and&#13;
civil society signed the Framework Agreement for national reconciliation.  The&#13;
Framework Agreement created a structure to promote the national reconciliation process;&#13;
there will be regular evaluations and a timetable for operations.  The national&#13;
reconciliation process is spearheaded by two structures: a seven-member Monitoring&#13;
Committee (with the participation of the international community) and a 72-member&#13;
Tripartite Commission.&#13;
The Tripartite Commission has various technical committees. It is to submit a&#13;
preliminary version of the constitution of the New Comorian Grouping no later than six&#13;
months after the signature of the Framework Agreement and to prepare a referendum on&#13;
this constitution. When the new Constitution is approved, a transition Government will&#13;
prepare the country for national elections to be held six months later.&#13;
9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
B. MACROECONOMIC MANAGEMENT ACTIVITIES&#13;
Economic growth has marked time over the last decade. It is below population&#13;
growth, which is 2.7% a year. During this past decade, private sector investment was&#13;
stagnant, reflecting a difficult economic environment. As a consequence, per capita&#13;
income decreased from US$500 at the beginning of the 1990s to US$356 in 2000. The&#13;
only growth has been in activities connected with trade in imported products.&#13;
In 2000, growth contracted by 1% and inflation reached 4.8%, mainly because of the&#13;
rise in oil prices. However, the trade balance improved considerably, because of higher&#13;
world prices for the main exports (vanilla, cloves, ylang-ylang) and only marginal&#13;
increases in the volume of imports. As a result of improved transfers from the Comorian&#13;
community living abroad, the external deficit decreased from 11% of GDP in 1999 to 5%&#13;
in 2000. Official gross reserves increased to 8 months' imports of goods and non-factor&#13;
services at the end of 2000.&#13;
The current Government's economic policy is designed to create a climate of&#13;
confidence conducive to private investment in order to stimulate production activities.&#13;
The goal is therefore to accelerate real GDP growth, to relieve poverty, to contain&#13;
inflation, to maintain the parity of the fixed exchange rate and to keep a suitable level of&#13;
monetary reserves. Practically speaking, the improvement in the political climate since&#13;
February 2001 and the resumption of public investment activities in Anjouan, as well as&#13;
the recent increase in world prices for revenue products, point to positive real GDP&#13;
growth in 2001.&#13;
As far as public finances are concerned, the Government has concentrated on&#13;
maintaining financial equilibrium. In 2000, public revenue declined slightly but at the&#13;
same time spending also decreased, so that the fiscal deficit remained almost unchanged:&#13;
- 0.1% of GDP. The Government was able to pay 11 months of wages while continuing&#13;
to make scheduled repayments of the public debt, for which 1.1 billion Comorian francs&#13;
(equivalent to 2.5 months' wages) were paid out in 2000. The authorities have also&#13;
improved tax collection, cleaned up the database of govemrnent employees and enhanced&#13;
transparency in the management of the affairs of State.&#13;
Another reason for the fiscal improvements is the restriction on spending financed&#13;
from the State budget (11.2% of GDP in 2000 compared with 12.7% in 1999). In&#13;
particular, spending on goods and services was reduced by an amount equivalent to 0.5%&#13;
of GDP compared with 1999.&#13;
The following table shows changes in the primary balance over the period from 1999&#13;
to the first half of 2002. After showing a small deficit in 2000 (although slightly higher&#13;
than in 1999), the forecast primary balance will improve considerably in the following&#13;
years. It shows a surplus in 2001. In relation to GDP, the primary deficit is 0.0% in 1999&#13;
and 1.12% in the first half of 2002. These favorable changes are attributable to fiscal&#13;
revenue, which alone suffices to cover current government expenditure. Without external&#13;
support, the Comorian State would be able to meet its basic operating expenses thanks to&#13;
real managerial efforts.&#13;
10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Current primary budget balance&#13;
(percentage of GDP)&#13;
1999      2000      2001     2002Q2&#13;
Est. /    Est. 1/   Program   Program&#13;
Income                          11.8      10.2      12.6       6.7&#13;
Current expenditure             13.8      12.5      15.6       5.6&#13;
Salaries and wages             6.3       5.7        5.5       2.6&#13;
Goods and services             4.5       3.9        3.0       1.8&#13;
Transfers                       0.9       0.9       1.1       0.6&#13;
Transition                      0          0        0.4       0.2&#13;
Interregional transfers         0          0        0.2       0.4&#13;
Currentprimarybudgetbalance      0.0       -0.1       2.8       1.12&#13;
Source: Federal Islamic Republic of the Comoros&#13;
In 2001, efforts to improve public finance management are continuing, as&#13;
demonstrated by the regular payment of wages. For the first time in several decades,&#13;
wages have been paid each month since January 2001 and no payments are overdue.&#13;
This regularity in payment of civil service wages is the result of improved control over&#13;
public spending. Economic recovery measures, including elimination of certain&#13;
exemptions and reintroduction of oil import duties amounting to 0.5% of GDP, were&#13;
initiated at the beginning of the year.&#13;
However, in the absence of external financial aid, civil service arrears amount to 24&#13;
months and external arrears have accumulated. Civil service arrears remain a major&#13;
obstacle to government reform and achievement of social stability.&#13;
Aware that the country's sustainable economic development can be achieved only&#13;
after resumption of relations with all its external creditors, the Comorian Government has&#13;
begun discussions to find agreed and appropriate solutions to the external arrears&#13;
problem.&#13;
The improvements in public finance management have been achieved at considerable&#13;
social and economic cost. Since domestic resources alone are not sufficient to maintain&#13;
these efforts and stimulate economic activity, the Comoros is therefore asking through&#13;
this conference for its friends to provide it with exceptional support in its efforts of&#13;
national reconciliation, institution-building and poverty relief.&#13;
B1. Short-Term Strategy&#13;
The strategy of the Comoros during the transition period is to maintain a viable&#13;
macroeconomic situation, in order to meet the most urgent social needs, and to ensure&#13;
that the reconciliation process remains on track.&#13;
Despite the signature of the Framework Agreement, the political situation remains&#13;
very fragile. There is also a social crisis resulting from the accumulation of civil service&#13;
11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
wage arrears, which must be resolved; payment of two months' wages owed from 2000&#13;
could make a real contribution to the settlement of this crisis.&#13;
Support for the reconciliation process has two aspects: support for decentralized&#13;
institutional structures and financing of transition costs. As regards decentralization, the&#13;
priorities are construction and upgrading of administrative buildings in the various&#13;
islands and human resource development.&#13;
With this aim, the Transition Government has embarked on the formulation of a&#13;
strategy designed to stimulate the economy and to promote rehabilitation and&#13;
reconstruction in the social sectors. This strategy is combined with an Emergency&#13;
Reconstruction and National Reconciliation Program, drawn up after sectoral and&#13;
regional technical consultations.&#13;
B2. Financing of the Strategy&#13;
The Comoros will appeal to all its development partners, multilateral and bilateral, for&#13;
support for the national reconciliation process. The Meeting of Friends of the Comoros&#13;
to be held in Paris will enable us to evaluate the strength of our partners' commitment.&#13;
Total financing for the 12 months of transition amounts to US$12.8 million, including&#13;
US$800,000 already obtained for the social and professional re-absorption of young&#13;
militia members in Anjouan. In addition, requirements for a complete transition include&#13;
financing of the cost of the elections, which will be approximately US$1.9 million.&#13;
Financing needed for the&#13;
Emergency Program from 2001 to 2002 Q2&#13;
(millions of US dollars)&#13;
Poverty relief                         3.0&#13;
Economic recovery / financial stabilization  5.6&#13;
Decentralization                        1.8&#13;
National reconciliation *              2.4&#13;
Total                                  12.8&#13;
*Excluding financing of the elections.&#13;
These Funds to support national reconciliation could be used to bolster the Comorian&#13;
authorities' efforts to meet short-term needs, while laying the foundations for widespread&#13;
recovery and a reconstruction program for the post-transition period. They would also be&#13;
distributed in the light of the islands' urgent needs, bearing in mind their respective size.&#13;
This is illustrated in the following matrix.&#13;
Two main areas were considered important: poverty relief, on the one hand, and&#13;
decentralization and national reconciliation, on the other. Poverty affects a large part of&#13;
the population (47% of households), and it has therefore been decided to allocate to&#13;
poverty relief 25% of the- funds to be provided directly by the partners. In view of the&#13;
crucial importance of the principle of power-sharing mentioned in the Framework&#13;
Agreement for national reconciliation, a large share of the total funds should be allocated&#13;
to forceful action to promote decentralization and national reconciliation.&#13;
12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The technical discussions identified the subsectors most affected by poverty in which&#13;
urgent and rapid action was proposed: health, water and fisheries. The expenditure for&#13;
national reconciliation covers the activities of the Monitoring Committee and the&#13;
Tripartite Commission and monitoring of spending under the Credit and spending on&#13;
technical coordination; the latter activities are the responsibility of the General Planning&#13;
Office.&#13;
C. URGENT NEEDS VOICED BY THE POPULATION&#13;
Consultations involving the various technical sectors, civil society and the island&#13;
authorities have identified the needs of the population. The allocation of funds for&#13;
national reconciliation support reflects both the size of the population and the level of&#13;
poverty in each island. In view of the scope of the Program and the resources currently&#13;
available, funds will be allocated only to the priority areas indicated below.&#13;
Poverty was already widespread before the outbreak of the political crisis, with&#13;
almost 47% of households living below the poverty line in 1995, according to surveys&#13;
conducted by the General Planning Office.&#13;
The level of poverty varies from island to island: about 41% for Grande Comore,&#13;
62% for Anjouan and 52% for Moheli. Although there are no recent statistics on poverty,&#13;
negative per capita growth during the crisis and the international embargo against&#13;
Anjouan (since January 2000) undoubtedly had an adverse effect on the living conditions&#13;
of households and the well-being of the three islands. Malnutrition reportedly reached&#13;
42% in 2000, compared with 34% in 1996 (Source: MICS 2000, Statistical Departmnent).&#13;
Health services are inadequate to meet demand. The lack of infrastructures, their&#13;
poor quality and the limited access to medicines, particularly for the rural population, are&#13;
some of the obstacles to the delivery of satisfactory medical services.&#13;
C1. Poverty Reduction, Economic Recovery and Financial Stabilization&#13;
1. Poverty Reduction&#13;
An adjustment was made on the basis of the criteria of population size and incidence&#13;
of poverty, giving the following distribution for the (Poverty reduction)) segment&#13;
Anjouan - 50%, Moheli - 10%, Grande Comore - 40%.&#13;
The consumer budget survey conducted in 1995 showed that rural inhabitants are&#13;
primarily concerned by this phenomenon. Accordingly, the Government's emergency&#13;
program specifies that a large share of the financing will be allocated to activities&#13;
designed to improve the living conditions of these inhabitants. The activities concern&#13;
access to health care and water and development of income-producing activities. This&#13;
segment devoted to poverty reduction will thus finance the most urgent social and&#13;
economic needs for the three islands.&#13;
About 62%, or over half the population, has inadequate access to health care.&#13;
Problems of availability of medicines and inadequacy of health centers (distance) are&#13;
13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
particularly widespread in rural areas. In addition, the population has insufficient access&#13;
to drinking water.&#13;
Poverty Reduction&#13;
(Millions of US dollars)&#13;
Anjouan                  Moheli         Grande Comore   Total&#13;
All Sectors                   1.5                      0.3                     1.2   3.0&#13;
Health                       0.45                      0.3                     0.6   1.25&#13;
-equipment and upgrading of  0.45  Improvement of          Improved access to  0.40&#13;
health posts and centers, gas for  technical facilities    generic medicines in&#13;
medical uses                       in Fomboni              rural areas (PNAC)&#13;
hospital: operating    -Upgrading of&#13;
theater, recovery      subsidiary health&#13;
room, X-ray        0.3  structures in rural   0.2&#13;
equipment,             areas&#13;
ultrasound, lab        -Rehabilitation of&#13;
peripheral health&#13;
structures in rural&#13;
areas (OUZIOINI)2,&#13;
I_medical gas&#13;
Education                    0.75                                                    0.75&#13;
-School supplies             0.25&#13;
-Equipment and upgrading of&#13;
schools                      0.40&#13;
-Retraining of teaching staff  0.10&#13;
Water                        0.15                                             0.36   0.61&#13;
Treatment of drinking water  0.15                          Urgent water&#13;
problems: Makorani 0.36&#13;
system&#13;
Rural development            0.15                                             0.24   0.39&#13;
-Veterinary products         0.05                           Safety at sea:&#13;
-Fishing gear                0.05                           lifeboat &amp;&#13;
-Fish conservation method    0.05                          communication      0.24&#13;
equipment&#13;
Maritime safety&#13;
a) Health sector&#13;
Increased accessibility of generic medicines in rural areas&#13;
In view of the poverty of the inhabitants, the increasing incidence of diarrheal&#13;
diseases and the aggravation of endemic leprosy, access to medicines must be facilitated.&#13;
The fund will be used to increase PNAC stocks of medicines. The upgrading and&#13;
equipment of health posts are considered to be necessary. In general, rural inhabitants are&#13;
facing tremendous difficulties with regard to health infrastructures and often with regard&#13;
to primary health care; this results in very expensive medical evacuations from one&#13;
2 In the event the health structure finds a new short-term financing source, the funds will be reallocated to&#13;
another health structure.&#13;
14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
region to another or from one island to another. In order gradually to remedy this&#13;
situation, urgent measures must be taken to upgrade and equip existing health posts. The&#13;
total amount proposed is US$1.25 million.&#13;
b) Education sector&#13;
It is essential, particularly in the island of Anjouan, to repair damaged schools,&#13;
develop human resources and provide textbooks and teaching materials for schools.&#13;
Primary schools will be the main beneficiaries of these measures. The financing&#13;
requested amounts to US$0.75 million.&#13;
c) Water and environmental sanitation&#13;
Almost 75% of the population has no access to drinking water, and this causes serious&#13;
health problems such as diarrheal diseases. Rapid action must be taken to solve these&#13;
problems. It is planned to create and extend water supply systems, particularly in rural&#13;
areas. The total amount proposed is US$0.61 million.&#13;
d) Rural development&#13;
The great majority of Comorians live off farming and fishing. However, the system&#13;
for marketing the products and the methodology are still rudimentary. This precarious&#13;
situation causes loss of human life (shipwrecks) and spoilage of the catch. The&#13;
Government plans to purchase fish conservation and concentration equipment, lifeboats&#13;
and communications equipment. This will reduce fishing-related risks and accidents.&#13;
The financing for this purpose amounts to US$0.39 million.&#13;
2. Economic Recovery and Financial Stabilization&#13;
a) Domestic arrears&#13;
The Government would like to repay US$2.9 million in arrears in 2001 and the first&#13;
half of 2002. Considerably more arrears are owed by the Government.&#13;
(i) Wages&#13;
Civil servants have lost all confidence in the Government because they are owed&#13;
wages amounting to almost 12 billion Comorian francs (equivalent to 24 months of wage&#13;
arrears). Some 7,200 civil servants on the three islands support almost 10% of the&#13;
population. These arrears problems have discouraged and demotivated civil servants,&#13;
jeopardizing the functioning of the Government. In order to restore the confidence of&#13;
these workers (who are essential for the good governance of the administration) and to&#13;
restore the State's authority in the administration, it is essential for the Government to be&#13;
able to pay at least two months' wages, including one month before the start of the&#13;
school year in October 2001. Two months' wages amount to 750 million Comorian&#13;
francs (equivalent to US$1.5 million) for Grande Comore and Moheli.&#13;
(ii) Suppliers&#13;
The State's domestic debt to its private suppliers amounts to almost US$9 million.&#13;
The private sector, which is suffering considerably because of a very difficult economic&#13;
15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
environment, needs an influx of funds to jump start it. Before June 2002, 700 million&#13;
Comorian francs, equivalent to US$1.4 million, will be paid to suppliers.  The&#13;
Government will thus be starting in June 2002 to pay part of its domestic debt, giving&#13;
priority to suppliers which have complied with their tax obligations, if financing is&#13;
available.&#13;
b) Interregional transfers&#13;
These will be used to finance the equivalent of 4 months' wages, particularly for&#13;
Anjouan. Additional financing (equivalent to US$1 million) is envisaged in the program.&#13;
c) Retrenchment&#13;
The aim is to reduce the wage bill through the retirement or voluntary separation of&#13;
500 persons. This involves expenditure equivalent to 520 million Comorian francs (US$1&#13;
million).&#13;
Economic Recovery and Financial Stabilization&#13;
(Millions of US dollars)&#13;
The three islands                                                  5.6&#13;
Domestic arrears                                                   2.9&#13;
Interregional transfers (to Anjouan)                               1.0&#13;
Retrenchment                                                       1.0&#13;
Central Bank                                                      0.7&#13;
Total                                                              5.6&#13;
d) Central Bank&#13;
The Government had obtained an advance from the Central Bank as part of the&#13;
regular advances (based on average monthly revenues over the last three years). The State&#13;
must repay the sum of 362 million Comorian francs (US$0.7 million) in order to improve&#13;
its cash management. These advances are very useful to the State, allowing it to meet&#13;
essential expenses in the event of a downturn.&#13;
C2. Decentralization and National Reconciliation&#13;
1. Decentralization&#13;
The &lt;&lt; decentralization)&gt; category requires 5.0% of the aid funds requested for the&#13;
institutional requirements of each island. The Comorian State is pursuing a policy of&#13;
administrative and - above all - economic decentralization; the new structures to be&#13;
created should be staffed locally.&#13;
Redeployment of civil servants&#13;
In the context of institution-building and therefore of decentralization, it is essential&#13;
to redeploy government workers and upgrade administrative buildings. Financing for&#13;
staff redeployment in Anjouan amounts to US$0.30 million.&#13;
16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Upgrading and construction&#13;
The financing would be used for basic upgrading and priority equipment of&#13;
administrative premises, particularly with information technology, for the three islands in&#13;
the context of a decentralized Government. The cost is estimated at US$1.4 million.&#13;
Decentralization&#13;
Millions of US dollars)&#13;
Anjoa                 Moheli      Grande Comore Total&#13;
All sectors            0.90                   0.6                0.3   1.8&#13;
Civil service          0.3                                             0.3&#13;
Staff deployments      0.30&#13;
Administrative buildings   0.60               0.3                      0.9&#13;
Upgrading and equipment of    Construction of the&#13;
administrative premises    0.60  central&#13;
administrative  0.3&#13;
building in the&#13;
__________ __  capital    _&#13;
Community buildings and                       0.3                0.30  0.6&#13;
equipment              I&#13;
Construction of      Upgrading:&#13;
administrative       govemorate,   0.204&#13;
buildings in the     prefecture,&#13;
communes:            vital records&#13;
Fomboni,        0.3  center&#13;
Nioumachoi,&#13;
Miringoni, Wanani    Retraining of  0.096&#13;
staff&#13;
2. National Reconciliation&#13;
The &lt;&lt; national reconciliation)) category requires almost 18% of the funds requested&#13;
from the international community. These funds would primarily finance the Tripartite&#13;
Commission, resulting in a new integrated budgetary system and expenditure monitoring&#13;
mechanism, as well as other forms of institutional support. This chapter concerns priority&#13;
activities which cannot be divided among the islands and which are essential for the&#13;
islands and for the Union.&#13;
Monitoring Committee and Tripartite Commission&#13;
The Monitoring Committee and the Tripartite Commission are the two organs&#13;
established under the Fomboni Framework Agreement. The total cost of the activities of&#13;
these two organs is US$0.5 million. The Government will contribute US$0.3 million to&#13;
the expenses. The amount to be obtained is US$0.5 million.&#13;
Creation of a new fiscal and management structure. monitoring of FARN spending&#13;
The Government intends to create a new fiscal structure geared to the requirements of&#13;
decentralization and anticipates expenses for the management and monitoring of the&#13;
National Reconciliation Support Fund (FARN). The amount requested is US$0.4 million.&#13;
17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
National reconciliation&#13;
(Millions of US dollars)&#13;
The three islands                         2.4&#13;
Monitoring Committee and Tripartite Commission                      0.5&#13;
Creation of a new fiscal structure (budget integration) &amp; management and  0.4&#13;
monitoring of emergency plan spending&#13;
Institutional support for coordination (General Planning Office)    0.3&#13;
Other shortfall                                                     0.4&#13;
World Bank: Social and professional reinsertion of young militia members in  0.8&#13;
Anjouan (Post-Conflict Grant recently obtained)&#13;
Financing already obtained&#13;
European Union: Elections                                            1.9&#13;
Institutional support for coordination&#13;
The Government foresees a need for institutional support for the General Planning&#13;
Office, which will coordinate the Reconstruction and National Reconciliation Program&#13;
for the three islands and FARN activities. The financing requested is US$0.3 million.&#13;
Other budgetary shortfall US$0.4 million.&#13;
Post-Conflict US$0.8 million (obtained)&#13;
Since 1999, the process of reconciliation of the three islands has speeded up. In&#13;
February 2001, after a lengthy period of mediation by the Organization of African Unity&#13;
and the International Organization for Francophonie, a peace agreement was signed in&#13;
Fomboni (Moheli) by representatives of the Government and of the opposition in the&#13;
three islands. The proposed plan will seize the opportunity provided by the peace process&#13;
to promote stabilization of the social situation in Anjouan. Because of the lack of&#13;
equipment and international aid, the target group - young members of the Anjouan&#13;
militia - represents a major risk of civil disturbance. At present, this group is supervised&#13;
by ex-soldiers who give them military training and organize sports activities. However,&#13;
there is growing discontent among the young members of the Anjouan militia because of&#13;
the lack of suitable housing and the lack of food and vocational training.&#13;
This project will support CARE International for:&#13;
(i) reintegration of from 600 to 650 former members of the Anjouan militia and young&#13;
people at risk in the Anjouan economy;&#13;
(ii) improvement and expansion of facilities for vocational training in Anjouan; and&#13;
(iii) strengthening of the new Special Civilian Corps, which will organize 1,400 young&#13;
volunteers into &lt;&lt; committees for peace and development &gt;&gt;.&#13;
Elections US$1.9 million (equivalent) obtained from the European Union.&#13;
18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
D. INSTITUTIONAL ARRANGEMENTS FOR THE USE OF EMERGENCY FUNDS&#13;
The General Planning Office is responsible for project coordination and for&#13;
preparation of the Emergency Program for Reconstruction and National Reconciliation.&#13;
The emergency funds will cover certain segments of the program.&#13;
All activities financed by the emergency funds will be supervised by a fund&#13;
management organ - the Office for the Implementation of the Emergency Funds - which&#13;
will be responsible for monitoring disbursements and activities, both at the national level&#13;
and the island level. The General Planning Director will coordinate this Office. He will&#13;
be responsible for coordinating all emergency activities and reporting to the Government&#13;
and development partners. He will provide direct liaison between the Government and&#13;
all donors, sign correspondence and authorize expenditure in the absence of government&#13;
objection. The Office will assume all costs incurred for monitoring, follow-up and&#13;
evaluation of activities.&#13;
Monitoring arrangements:&#13;
An Implementation Unit for the emergency activities will be created (hereinafter&#13;
referred to as ( the Unit &gt;&gt;) coordinated by the General Planning office, with the following&#13;
membership:&#13;
- The Ministry of Education&#13;
- The Ministry of Health&#13;
- The Ministry of Infrastructure and Energy&#13;
- The Ministry of Agriculture&#13;
- The Ministry of National Reconciliation&#13;
- The Representative of Anjouan&#13;
- Donor coordination&#13;
This Unit will be expanded to include the financial sectors responsible for the&#13;
mobilization of funds et financial control. The Office will be composed as follows:&#13;
- The Central Bank&#13;
- The Customs&#13;
- The Treasury&#13;
- The Budget&#13;
The Unit should be composed of permanent official members from the General&#13;
Secretariats or General Offices. The financial oversight section of the Budget Ministry is&#13;
responsible for the commitment of funds, while the "Commission de Wrification des&#13;
Comptes Publics" should ensure that expenses are properly incurred. These two bodies&#13;
would provide close supervision for emergency funds and guarantee correct execution of&#13;
its activities.&#13;
The Unit would be responsible for ensuring that the goals of the emergency aid are&#13;
attained. Based on institutional networks and supported by external auditors, the Unit&#13;
would ensure (i) presentation of eligible invoices and (ii) application of the expenditure&#13;
matrix with tangible and measurable progress in the application of this matrix as&#13;
presented in this Letter of Development Policy.&#13;
A decree signed by the Ministry of Finance, Budget and Privatization will officially&#13;
create this Unit.&#13;
19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Attachment 2&#13;
Social and Professional Reinsertion of the Young Anjouanese Militias&#13;
Because of the genesis of the Comorian crisis, there is a strong need to provide&#13;
targeted assistance to reintegrate young militias and other at-risk youth into the&#13;
Anjouanese economy. Anjouanese militias emerged from the attempt of the national&#13;
Comorian army in September 1997 to bring Anjouan back under its control. At that time,&#13;
Anjouanese authorities distributed arms to defend the island against an offensive by the&#13;
national army. Due to political instability and a deteriorating social situation within&#13;
Anjouan, the militias were involved in internal fighting in December 1998 and August&#13;
1999 with more than 100 people injured and killed.&#13;
In the last year, most of the militias are grouped in a camp close to Patsi&#13;
(Northeastern Anjouan). The group is under the supervision of former military personnel&#13;
who are currently providing military training and organizing sports. However, the&#13;
militias still present a major risk for civil disturbance in Anjouan because of social&#13;
conditions in the camp and lack of a productive future for participants.&#13;
The Bank has made available to the Government of Comoros a grant of its Post-&#13;
Conflict Fund (PCF) of US$788,000 for two years (FY 2002-03) to finance the&#13;
reintegration of young militia and other at-risk youth in the Anjouanese economy. The&#13;
project will feed and house these people during the period of the project. This activity is&#13;
closely linked to the proposed EERC and presents an important component of the&#13;
authorities national reconciliation strategy. CARE International, which has a strong field&#13;
presence in Grande Comore and Anjouan, will administer this project.&#13;
The project aims at:&#13;
(i) reintegrating 600 to 650 Anjouanese ex-militias and high-risk youth into the&#13;
Anjouanese economy;&#13;
(ii) upgrading and extending vocational training facilities in Anjouan; and&#13;
(iii) strengthening the creation of an Adapted Civil Service (Service Civil Adapte,&#13;
SCA) which will organize 1,400 young volunteers within "committees for peace&#13;
and development".&#13;
The project received broad support from all Comorian key stakeholders and&#13;
donors. It will be linked to efforts by the OAU/OIF, assisted by the French Co-operation,&#13;
to recuperate the arms of the militias. To facilitate professional reintegration and arms&#13;
recuperation, CARE has already conducted a survey among the target group to identify&#13;
social background, forrnal skills, expectations for future employment, and the number of&#13;
arms in the hands of the militias. The results of this survey will be incorporated in an&#13;
ongoing ILO study on the labor market for vocationally trained Anjouanese and linked,&#13;
among others, to employment creating projects under the Bank's social fund.&#13;
20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Attachment 3&#13;
Comoros at a glance                                                              6/4101&#13;
Sub-&#13;
POVERT and SOCIAL                                        Saharan      Low.&#13;
Comoat    Affic          t lncom  Development dbamond&#13;
2000&#13;
Poputation mid-year (mison)                        056        643    2,417                 Lifeexpectancy&#13;
GNP per capita (Alis method, USS)                   380       490      420&#13;
GNP (Atlis mnioo USS bilions)                      0,21       316    1t008&#13;
Averge annual groth. 199400                                                                      T&#13;
Population (#J                                      2.5       2.6       1.9&#13;
Laborforce(%)                                       32        2.6       2.4     GNP                             Gross&#13;
per                                  primary&#13;
Moetrecenatlnratestataatytearavallable. 1994.00)                                caia/                       erlmn&#13;
M*NtmObj*"UmaftAlidedyawavadabl*,199440)capita                                          enrollment&#13;
Poverty (A ol poptlabor below na ltpoverV lle)&#13;
Urban populatlon ('A of totat pop Wtion)             32        34       31&#13;
Lte expecta  tbirth (yeams)                          60        47       S9&#13;
lritar mortality (per 1,fO live births)                       92       77&#13;
Child malnuttion % of chdren underS1                 26                              Access to improved water source&#13;
Access to an improved water source (% ofpopulation)            55       76&#13;
Illiteracy (6 ofpopulationage 15+)                   45        39       39&#13;
Gross pimaryenolmett (%of schdof-age population)     75        78       96            -    Comoros&#13;
Male                                                        85       102                 Low-inconme group&#13;
Female                                                       71       86&#13;
KEY ECONOMIC RAT7OS and LONG-TERM TRENDS&#13;
1910    1990      19SS      2000  _        _       _          _  _ _&#13;
EconornIc ratloe&#13;
GOP (USS billons)                          0.12    0.25      0.22      0120&#13;
Gross domesic investmen&amp;GDP                33.2    197       14.8      13.2&#13;
xports of goods and serves/GDP              8.7    14.3      23,1      2856                    Trade&#13;
Gross domestic savingsaiDP                -101      -37 2     2.7       7 0&#13;
Gross national savings/DP                  -0.4    11 0       7.8      10.0&#13;
Curent accountbalancoiG0P                  -7.2    -8.7       4.0      -0.3&#13;
IntarestpaymentsVGOP                        0.2     0.2       1.0       1       Dometic                    Investment&#13;
otal debtfGDP                              35.9    73.8      80.0      77.0    savings&#13;
Total debt semvice/exports                                   20.9      1689&#13;
Present value oJf debttGDP&#13;
Present vaue of debt/exports&#13;
Indebtedness&#13;
1990-90  1990.00    1999     2000  2000-04&#13;
(average &amp;qn1u5glg wth)&#13;
GDP                                2.8      1.1      19       -1.1      2,0            -Comoros&#13;
GNP per capta                      0.1     N 5      04       -3 5      -0.6                 Low-income group&#13;
Exports of goods                   9.3      4.7   -229        4-0       0.2&#13;
STRUCTURE of the ECONOMY&#13;
19B0    1990      199       2000     Growth of investment and GDP (%)&#13;
(% of GOP)                                                                      20&#13;
Agricutture                                34.0    41.4      40.9      40.9&#13;
Industry                                   13,2     8.3      11.9      11.9     o&#13;
Manufacturing                             3.9      42        4.2       42      0&#13;
Services                                   52.8    50.3      47.2      47 2  D&#13;
Private consumption                        79.2    86.7      82.7      79.5    4&#13;
General govemment consumption              30.9    16.5      14.6      13.5             -Ga             GDP&#13;
Imports of goods and services              51.9    37.1      35.2      31.9 9                             0&#13;
19B0-90  1990400     1999     2000      Growth of exports and Imports(%)&#13;
(average annual growth)                                                        z&#13;
Agriculture                                 4.0      1.6      4.4       1.0    40&#13;
Industry                                   -2.9     3.6       2.9      -7.1    30      A       &#13;
Manufacturing                             4.9      0.8       0.0     -7.0    2D -&#13;
Services                                    3.1     0.2      -0.6      -1.6     o  A         .&#13;
Prvate consumption                          3.4     2.6       7.5       4  5      -. o           97 _  \ s  J&#13;
General govemment consimption               0.0     1.2      -1.6      -1.6   -2&#13;
Gross domestc investment                   4.2    -7.2    -20.0    -12.0    40&#13;
Imports of goods and services              -0.2     2.4      -0.1      -2.9           -     Exporls    -*Imports&#13;
Gross nationel product                      2.7      1.1      2.2      -1.0&#13;
Note: 2000 data are preliminary esbmates.&#13;
The diamonds show four key indicators in the country (in bold) compared with its income-group average, If data are missing, the diamond will&#13;
be incomplete. Latest year for improved water source data is 2000.&#13;
21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Attachment 3&#13;
Comoros&#13;
PRICES and GOVERNMENT FINANCE&#13;
1980    1990      1999     2000     Inflaton %)&#13;
Doomesftc prices&#13;
(X change)                                                                    25&#13;
Consumer pnces                                      1.6       3.5      4.8    20&#13;
Implicit GDP deflator                               2.2       5.8      6.1    15&#13;
Govemment finance                                                         9&#13;
(X o0 GOP, incdudes cunent grants)&#13;
Currentm revenue                                   321       184      144&#13;
Current budget balance                              4.8       4.6               -G WP dePtator - t  CPI&#13;
Overati surpiustdeficit                            -0.5      -0.8     -1.9&#13;
TRADE&#13;
(US$ mInhons)                             1980    1S90      1999     2000       Eaxort end Import levls (US$ mill.)&#13;
Totalexports(fob)                                    18       18       20    Wo&#13;
Otherfood                                           9         4        8&#13;
Otherfood                                           1         0        1&#13;
Manufactures&#13;
Total imports (cif)                                  57       73       78&#13;
Food                                               10        22       23&#13;
Fuel and energy                                     6         8        9&#13;
Capital goods                                       .        14       15      o&#13;
94  96  go  57  OR  go  0D&#13;
Export price index (1995=100)                      126        71       72&#13;
Import pnce index (1995=100)                        92       136      140                Exporns    *9m6Ports&#13;
Temns of trade (1995=100)                           137       52       51&#13;
BALANCE of PAYMENTS&#13;
(US$mglions)                             iss1    1990      19919    200       Cununt account balance to GWP 1%&#13;
Exportsoftgoods and services                1 3     36        52       52      o  _         * _&#13;
Imports of goods and services               34      93        78       64      -2  *_&#13;
Resource balance                           -21     -57       -27       -13&#13;
Netincome                                    1       -1        0        0      a        -&#13;
Net current transfers                       1 1     36        18       11    10&#13;
Current account balance                     -9    -22         -9        1&#13;
Financing items (net)                        5       18       13       10&#13;
Changes in net reserves                      4       3         -4      -9&#13;
Memo:&#13;
Reserves including gold (USS millions)       6      31        39       29&#13;
Conversion rate (DEC, bocatlUS$)          211.3   272.3    481.8    534.0&#13;
EXTERNAL DEST and RESOURCE FLOWS&#13;
1980    1990      1999     2000&#13;
(US$ millions)                                                                 Composition of 2000 debtt (US$ mill.)&#13;
Total debt outstanding and disbursed        44      185      210      225&#13;
IBRD                                       0       0         0        0&#13;
IDA                                        4      38        73       71                      13&#13;
Total debt seMce                             0        1        3                                         7&#13;
IBRO                                       0       0         0        0&#13;
IDA                                        0       0         1        2&#13;
Composibon of net resource flows                                                                             2&#13;
Official grants                                             15        9&#13;
Oflica creditors                          13       4         ..       .3 0&#13;
prTvatecreditors                           0                0        0&#13;
Foreign direct investment                                                                             Is ..  1&#13;
Portfolio equity&#13;
World Bank program&#13;
Commiments                                 5       0         0        0      A - IR0                   E - Bilaerml&#13;
Disbursentes                               2        1        2         1     8 -IDA    D - Other mula teral F- Privte&#13;
Prncipal repayments                        0       0         0         1&#13;
Net flows                                  2        1        2        0&#13;
Interest payments                          0       0         1        1&#13;
Net transfers                              2       0         1        -1&#13;
Development Economics                                                                                          6/4/01&#13;
22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Attachment 4&#13;
Comoros - Key Economic Indicators&#13;
National accounts (as % of GDP)&#13;
Gross domestic product                    100      100     100      100      100      100      100      100&#13;
Agriculture                              41       41       41      41        41      41       41       41&#13;
Industry                                 12       12       12       12       12       12      12       12&#13;
Services                                 47       47       47      47       47       47       47       47&#13;
Total Consumption                         107      108      96       97       93       93       94       96&#13;
Gross domestic fixed investment            14       13      15       12       10       11       11       11&#13;
Government investment                     6        6        8       5         4       4        4        4&#13;
Private investment                        8        7        7       7        .7       7        7        7&#13;
Exports (GNFS)b                            18       18      23       23       26       24       23       22&#13;
Imports (GNFS)                             41      43       37       35       32       31       31       31&#13;
Gross domestic savings                     -7       -8       4        3        7        7        6        4&#13;
Gross national savings                      5       -2       9        8       10        9       10        8&#13;
Memorandum items&#13;
Gross domestic product                    230     212      215      223      202      219      231      243&#13;
(US$ million at current prices)&#13;
GNP per capita (US$, Atlas method)        410     400      370      350      380&#13;
Real annual growth rates (%, calculated from 1990 prices)&#13;
Gross domestic product at market prices  -1.3    4.2      1.2      1.9     -1.1      1.0      2.0      2.0&#13;
Gross Domestic Income                   -1.6     4.8      2.1      4.1      0.7      0.2      2.3      2.1&#13;
Real annual per capita growth rates (%, calculated from 1990 prices)&#13;
Gross domestic product at market prices  -3.8     1.6    -1.4    -0.7      -3.6    -1.6    -0.6    -0.6&#13;
Total consumption                       -4.0     5.6   -10.8       3.4     -6.5    -2.5       1.2      1.3&#13;
Private consumption                     -1.0     7.2   -10.5       4.8     -6.9    -3.3       1.5      1.7&#13;
Balance of Payments (US$ millions)&#13;
Exports (GNFS)b                           42      39       49       52       52       52       53       53&#13;
Merchandise FOB                          6       6        6        9       12       10        9        8&#13;
Imports (GNFS)b                          95       91       79      78        64      67       71       74&#13;
Merchandise FOB                         49      48       42       43       38       39       42       44&#13;
Resource balance                         -53     -53      -30      -27       -13     -15      -18      -21&#13;
Netcurrenttransfers                       33       19       17      18        11      13       11       11&#13;
Current account balance                  -20     -33      -13       -9       -I       -3       -6      -10&#13;
Net private foreign direct investment      1        0       0        0        0        0        0        0&#13;
Long-tern loans (net)                     ..       ..       ..       ..       ..       ..      ..&#13;
Official                                  6       4        -4      -6       -8       -6       -6       -5&#13;
Private&#13;
23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Attachment 4&#13;
Comoros - Key Economic Indicators (continued)&#13;
Other capital (net, mcl. errors &amp;          ..       ..       ..      ..       ..&#13;
omissions)&#13;
Change in reserves                         -9       4        3       -4       -9       -4       -1       -1&#13;
Memorandum items&#13;
Resource balance (% of GDP)              -23.1   -24.9   -13.7   -12.0    -6.2    -6.8    -7.7    -8.7&#13;
Real annual growth rates ( YR90 prices)&#13;
Merchandise exports (FOB)               -21.9      5.4      6.2     6.9      7.1      7.4      6.4      6.6&#13;
Primary&#13;
Manufactures&#13;
Merchandiseimports(CIF)                  -6.1      1.3      1.8     2.3      3.5      4.0      4.3      4.6&#13;
Public finance (as % of GDP at market&#13;
prices)'&#13;
Current revenues                         20.6    22.6    18.7    18.4    14.4    16.9    15.5          15.8&#13;
Current expenditures                     20.6    18.9    14.3    13.8    12.5    16.1         14.5     13.2&#13;
Current account surplus (+) or deficit (-)  0.0    3.8     4.4      4.6       1.9     0.8      1.0      2.6&#13;
Capital expenditure                       5.8      6.0      7.8     5.4      3.9      4.7      4.3      4.4&#13;
Foreign financing                         2.9      1.8      1.7    -0.5      0.1       1.3     0.9       1.0&#13;
Monetary indicators&#13;
M2/GDP                                   20.1     19.8    18.0    17.9    19.5    19.5    19.3    19.2&#13;
GrowthofM2(%)                             6.4      3.1    -3.7      7.0    14.5       5.8      6.2      6.5&#13;
Private sector credit growth /&#13;
total credit growth ('%)&#13;
Price indices( YR90 =100)&#13;
Merchandise export price index          165.0   177.1   189.3   185.8   187.9   189.5   193.0   195.3&#13;
Merchandise import price index           78.3    84.1    85.9    87.5    90.2    92.9    94.3    95.9&#13;
Merchandise terms of trade index        210.7   210.7   220.4   212.2   208.2   204.0   204.7   203.7&#13;
Real exchange rate (US$/LCU)f              ..       ..       ..       ..      ..&#13;
Real interest rates&#13;
Consumer price index (% change)           2.0      3.0      3.5     3.5      4.8      3.5      3.0      3.0&#13;
GDP deflator (% change)                   3.2      0.7      1.5     5.8      6.1      4.7      3.2      2.6&#13;
a. GDP at market prices&#13;
b. "GNFS" denotes "goods and nonfactor services."&#13;
c. Includes net unrequited transfers excluding official capital grants.&#13;
d. Includes use of IMF resources.&#13;
e. Consolidated central government.&#13;
f "LCU" denotes "local currency units." An increase in US$/LCU denotes&#13;
appreciation.&#13;
24&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Attachment 5&#13;
Comoros EERC: Procurement and Disbursement Procedures&#13;
The Credit will be disbursed against imports which conform to a positive list of&#13;
ten categories as contained in the Development Credit Agreement (DCA).  The&#13;
disbursements of foreign exchange will be deposited in an account in the Central Bank.&#13;
Government will use the local currency generated from the foreign expenditures to&#13;
finance priority purposes related to poverty alleviation, economic recovery and&#13;
decentralization.&#13;
PROCUREMENT&#13;
General&#13;
The Office for the Implementation of the Emergency Funds (the Office)&#13;
managing the project will be presided over by the Director General of Planning. A sub-&#13;
committee consisting of representatives of the Central Bank and Ministry of Finance will&#13;
collect documents showing proof of shipment and payment for imports included in the&#13;
positive list. A second sub-committee representing the sectoral ministries will be part of&#13;
the process.&#13;
Eligible Imports&#13;
a) Public Sector&#13;
Modified ICB Procedures&#13;
For contracts for eligible goods (excluding commonly traded commodities) above&#13;
US$500,000 equivalent per contract, modified ICB procedures as per Para 2.63 and 2.64&#13;
of the Bank's Procurement Guidelines will apply.&#13;
International Shopping&#13;
Eligible goods procured by the public sector (excluding commonly traded&#13;
commodities) may be procured under contracts awarded on the basis of International&#13;
Shopping, as per Para 3.5 and 3.6 of the Bank's Procurement Guidelines, for imports less&#13;
than the equivalent of US$500,000 per contract.&#13;
b) Private Sector&#13;
Goods imported by the private sector (excluding commonly traded commodities)&#13;
estimated to cost less than US$2 million equivalent per contract may be procured in&#13;
accordance with established commercial practices satisfactory to IDA.&#13;
c) Eligible Commodities&#13;
Imports of commonly traded commodities may be procured through organized&#13;
international commodity markets or other channels of competitive procurement&#13;
acceptable to IDA as per Para 2.65 of the Bank's Procurement Guidelines.&#13;
25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Prior Review&#13;
To the extent practicable, contracts for goods will be grouped in bid packages&#13;
estimated to cost US$2 million equivalent or more each. With respect to each contract for&#13;
goods estimated to cost the equivalent of US$2 million or more, the procedures set forth&#13;
in Para 2 and 3 of Appendix I of the Bank's Procurement Guidelines will apply. All&#13;
other contracts will be subject to post review.&#13;
DISBURSEMENTS&#13;
Documents showing the procurement and payment for goods will be accumulated&#13;
by the Office. On the basis of these documents, the Office will prepare a statement of&#13;
expenditures up to US$2 million per contract for submission to IDA. The documents&#13;
verifying the eligibility of the imports will be held in the Central Bank and may be&#13;
audited by IDA. Once disbursements in foreign exchange are made to the Central Bank,&#13;
the local currency counterpart will be deposited in a Government account. This account&#13;
will be used to finance the agreed priority program of expenditures and will be monitored&#13;
by IDA as part of its supervision of the Credit.&#13;
Retroactive financing, not exceeding 20% of the amount of the Credit (SDR&#13;
960,000) will be accepted for payments made for imports after April 15, 2001, i.e.&#13;
approximately four months prior to the signing of the Credit.&#13;
Imports under a single category may not exceed one half of the Credit amount&#13;
without prior approval by IDA.&#13;
26&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1490145">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2001/07/1490145/comoros-emergency-economic-recovery-credit-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2001/07/1490145/comoros-emergency-economic-recovery-credit-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2001/07/1490145/comoros-emergency-economic-recovery-credit-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2001/08/04/000094946_01071904124227/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2001/08/04/000094946_01071904124227/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <credit_no>3563</credit_no>
        <datestored>2001-08-11T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2001-07-11T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Comoros - Emergency Economic Recovery
            Credit Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Emergency Economic Recovery Credit
            Project will provide emergency assistance to the economy,
            during the transition out of the current secessionist
            crisis, and will address immediate social needs in the
            Comoros, particularly on the island of Anjouan. Priority
            expenditures in the emergency program, will support the
            creation of decentralized institutions, and the
            implementation of the national reconciliation agreement. The
            project aims at maintaining macroeconomic stability, and
            addressing urgent social needs, by financing imports,
            including petroleum, agricultural equipment, construction
            materials, and capital goods, while, foreign exchange will
            be provided to finance increased import requirements arising
            from the spending, generated by the economic recovery
            program. The program will target urgent public expenditures
            needed to alleviate poverty, and support the process of
            national reconciliation. Nonetheless, risks include a) the
            possibility that the national reconciliation process, could
            stall, or be reversed, though careful monitoring of the
            process, and the strong support by stakeholders, development
            partners, and international mediators has been confirmed,
            and, b) the Government's weak capacity to sustain
            economic recovery efforts, but technical assistance
            provision in expenditure management will mitigate this risk.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Comoros - Emergency Economic Recovery Credit Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Comoros - Emergency Economic
            Recovery Credit Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2001/07/1490145/comoros-emergency-economic-recovery-credit-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>KM-Emergency Economic Recovery Credit -- P074054</projn>
        <docty>Technical Annex</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Poverty Assessment,National Governance,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <count>Comoros</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Africa!$!80458</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_01071904124227</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Central government administration</subsc>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Public Administration, Law, and Justice</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Economic recovery; Emergency recovery loan;
            Transitional assistance; Social assistance programs; Public
            expenditures; Decentralization; Financing programs;
            Macroeconomic stability; Import finance; Petroleum imports;
            Agricultural equipment; Construction materials; Capital
            goods; Foreign exchange; Poverty reduction; Risk management;
            Financial management; Technical assistance; Stakeholder
            participation; Partnerships; Development assistance
            accidents,administrative
            buildings,audits,authority,autonomy,budgetary
            institutions,budgetary support,capita growth,central
            Government,civil service,civil society,climate,Competitive
            Bidding,constitution,coups d'etat,Currency Unit,Current
            expenditures,decentralization,deregulation,development
            partners,Development Policy,development strategy,drinking
            water,economic activities,economic activity,Economic
            Development,economic growth,economic management,economic
            situation,employment,equilibrium,exchange
            rate,expenditure,expenditures,external debt,financial
            institutions,financial management,financial
            resources,financial support,financial
            transfers,FISCAL,fiscal deficit,fiscal management,Fiscal
            revenue,FISCAL YEAR,Fish,fisheries,Fishing,foreign
            exchange,GNP,good governance,government reform,Gross
            National Product,growth rate,health care,health
            centers,health problems,Health services,household
            survey,human resource,human resource development,human
            resources,Imports,Improved
            access,income,inflation,Institutional
            Arrangements,Institutional Development,institutional
            reforms,internal audit,legitimacy,leprosy,living
            conditions,living standards,local currency,local
            institutions,MACROECONOMIC MANAGEMENT,macroeconomic
            stability,malnutrition,marketing,medicines,Ministries of
            Education,Ministry of Finance,mortality,national
            elections,oil,oil prices,operating expenses,political
            crisis,political instability,political parties,Poor
            Countries,population growth,population size,poverty
            analysis,poverty line,Poverty Reduction,Poverty Reduction
            Strategy,Presidency,primary health care,primary
            school,Primary schools,priority areas,private sector,private
            sector investment,public debt,public expenditure,public
            expenditure management,public finance,public finances,public
            investment,public sector,Public sector management,public
            services,public
            spending,referendum,rehabilitation,representatives,retirement,rural
            areas,rural inhabitants,rural
            population,Safety,savings,schools,social expenditures,social
            indicators,social sectors,social services,social
            stability,State budget,Structural Adjustment,subsidiary,Task
            Team Leader,tax arrears,tax collection,tax exemptions,tax
            obligations,technical assistance,technical
            dimensions,transition process,transparency,urban
            population,vaccination,violence,wages,water supply,workers
        </keywd>
        <owner>AFT: PREM 1 (AFTP1)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <trustfund>TF038931-COMOROS - CIVIL SERVICE REFORM</trustfund>
        <repnb>T7475</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative and Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Management and Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Lines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Militia</ml:concept><ml:concept>Reconciliation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Comoros</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>