<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿WATER AND SANITATION PROGRAM: RESEARCH BRIEF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                            64771&#13;
The Economic Returns                                                                                  Key messages&#13;
of Sanitation Interventions                                                                           â&#128;¢	 Sanitation	interventions	have	very	&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
in Cambodia&#13;
                                                                                                        favorable	socio-economic	returns	to	&#13;
                                                                                                        households	and	society,	contributing	&#13;
                                                                                                        improved	health,	clean	environment,	&#13;
August	2011                                                                                             dignity	and	quality	of	life,	among	many	&#13;
                                                                                                        other	benefits. Economic returns are&#13;
                                                                                                        potentially highâ&#128;&#148;in excess of US$2 return&#13;
                                                                                                        per dollar investedâ&#128;&#148;especially in rural&#13;
INTRODUCTION                                                                                            areas where low-cost on-site solutions are&#13;
The	 Economics	 of	 Sanitation	 Initia-             percent of the rural population. Urban              feasible.&#13;
tive	 (ESI)	 is	 a	 multi-country	 study	           coverage stands at 81.5 percent, as of&#13;
launched in 2007 as a response by                   2008.ii However, this figure reflects toilet      â&#128;¢	 Economic	efficiency	of	improved	&#13;
the World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s Water and Sanitation               access and not improved management                  sanitation	can	be	optimized	by	&#13;
Program to address major gaps in evi-               of sewageâ&#128;&#148;in urban areas appropri-                  improving	program	performance,	which	&#13;
dence among developing countries on                 ate wastewater management is still                  leads	to	sustained	behavior	change.&#13;
the economic aspects of sanitation. Its             extremely limitedâ&#128;&#148;thus causing health               Future projects should carefully plan and&#13;
objective is to provide economic evi-               risks and widespread pollution to water             implement activities cost-effectively, and&#13;
dence to increase the volumes and ef-               resources.                                          closely monitor project costs and impacts,&#13;
ficiency of public and private spending                                                                 to ensure that the project resources are&#13;
on sanitation. This research brief sum-             Phase	I	of	the	ESI	study estimated the              being appropriately utilized.&#13;
marizes the key findings of Study Phase             overall economic costs of poor sanita-&#13;
IIâ&#128;&#148;cost-benefit analysis of alternative             tion in Cambodia to be US$448 million             â&#128;¢	 High-cost	sanitation	solutions	in	urban	&#13;
sanitation optionsâ&#128;&#148;from Cambodia.i                  per year at 2005 prices, equivalent to              areas	are	difficult	to	justify	economically	&#13;
                                                    7.2 percent of gross domestic product               from	the	perspective	of	health	and	&#13;
PROBLEM STATEMENT                                   (GDP).iii                                           time	benefits	of	the	community	they	&#13;
Sanitation improvement has been in-                                                                     are	serving.	While difficult to quantify&#13;
cluded among Cambodiaâ&#128;&#153;s	 own	                       STUDY AIMS AND METHODS                              in economic terms, the associated&#13;
Millennium	 Development	 Goals	                     The	 purpose	 of	 Phase	 II	 of	 the	 ESI	          environmental benefits are highly valued by&#13;
(CMDG), with the aim of reaching 30                 study is to provide sanitation decision             households, tourists and businesses.&#13;
percent rural coverage and 74 percent               makers with improved evidence on the&#13;
urban coverage by 2015. In rural areas,             costs and benefits of alternative sani-           â&#128;¢	 Improved	hygiene	and	sanitation	&#13;
progress has been slow, with around a               tation options in different contexts in             conditions	in institutions, public places&#13;
one percentage point increase annu-                 Cambodia. The study focuses on hu-                  and tourist sites are	important	to	attract	&#13;
ally between 1997 and 2007, reach-                  man excreta management, including                   more	businesses	and	tourists	to	&#13;
ing little over 20 percent in 2008. Open            data from five selected field sites in ad-          Cambodia.&#13;
defecation is still practiced by about 75           dition to national surveys.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Economic analysis measures the broader welfare benefits of products and services on popula-&#13;
 tions, such as value of life, time use, environmental and social benefits, as opposed to financial&#13;
 analysis, which measures the financial gains only (e.g., changes in income or cash situation).&#13;
&amp;#12;2 The Economic Returns of Sanitation Interventions in Cambodia                                       Economics of Sanitation Initiative&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Figure 1. ESI Field Sites in Cambodia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Surveys	were	conducted in four rural project sites and one           fectiveness ratio, net present value, internal rate of the return,&#13;
  urban site that have recently been the focus of sanitation pro-      and payback period of sanitation options.&#13;
  grams or projects (see Figure 1). Overall 1,180 household&#13;
  questionnaires were undertaken in addition to focus group            Economic	 benefits	 quantified include impacts on health,&#13;
  discussions, physical investigations, water quality assess-          drinking water and sanitation access time. Environmental and&#13;
  ments, market surveys, and health facility surveys conducted         social impacts of poor sanitation were not fully captured in the&#13;
  at each site. Primary data were supplemented with data from          monetary estimates of benefit. Qualitative analyses were con-&#13;
  other national and local surveys.                                    ducted on selected social and broader economic benefits.&#13;
&#13;
  Sanitation	 interventions	 evaluated varied by rural and ur-         Full	 investment	 and	 recurrent	 costs were measured for&#13;
  ban location, comparing open defecation with the two main            each sanitation option.&#13;
  sanitation options currently available to the rural population:&#13;
  dry pit latrines and wet pit latrines (pour-flush). In urban sites   STUDY RESULTS&#13;
  wet pit latrines were compared with a new wastewater man-            Rural Areas: Highly Favorable Economic Returns&#13;
  agement scheme with household sewerage connections.                  on Pit Latrinesâ&#128;&#148;When Used&#13;
&#13;
  Conventional	 techniques	 of	 economic	 analysis were uti-           Benefit-cost ratios (economic return per currency unit invest-&#13;
  lized to generate outputs such as benefit-cost ratio, cost-ef-       ed) and annualized costs per household were compiled for&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                           www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;Economics of Sanitation Initiative                                   The Economic Returns of Sanitation Interventions in Cambodia 3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
the four projects in rural sites, as shown in Figure 2 and Figure      Figure 2. Benefit-Cost Ratios in Rural Sites (economic&#13;
3. Among the sanitation options evaluated, the most favor-             return per unit of currency spent)&#13;
able economic performance was found for wet pits. In the&#13;
two projects delivering wet pits, the benefit-cost ratio varied&#13;
from 2.3 to 2.9, with an annual economic rate of return of at&#13;
least 70 percent, thus requiring less than two years to recover&#13;
the economic value of the initial investment costs. The ben-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Beneï¬?t - Cost Ratios&#13;
efit-cost ratio of dry pits also indicates a positive economic&#13;
return, varying from 1.4 to 2.0, with an annual rate of return&#13;
greater than 8 percent. These resultsâ&#128;&#148;wet versus dry pit la-&#13;
trinesâ&#128;&#148;need to be put into context, however. Under the proj-&#13;
ects evaluated, wet pit latrines were heavily subsidized and&#13;
only reached selected households, thus leaving most house-&#13;
holds in villages without improved sanitation. In contrast, the&#13;
villages where dry pits were evaluated generally reached a&#13;
higher proportion of the community. One of these projects&#13;
was a Community-Led Total Sanitation (CLTS) project with                                     Access Time       Water Access       Health Productivity&#13;
zero hardware subsidy, while the other was a project deliver-                                Water Treatment   Health Mortality   Health Care&#13;
ing longer lasting dry pit latrines with a high proportion of the&#13;
                                                                       Figure 3. Annual Costs per Household in Rural Sites&#13;
hardware cost subsidized by the project.                               (2009 prices, using average exchange rate with US$)&#13;
&#13;
The findings suggest that sanitation technologies appropri-&#13;
ate for rural areas are worth pursuing, in that their economic&#13;
return is positive, and for some interventions it is highly favor-                                                                         Annualized&#13;
                                                                                                                                           Investment&#13;
able. Although wet pit latrines have a high initial investment                                                                             Annualized&#13;
                                                                                                                                           Maintenance&#13;
cost of at least US$170 per household (including both hard-&#13;
                                                                                                                                           Annualized&#13;
ware costs and agency costs to deliver the intervention), a                                                                                Operations&#13;
                                                                                                                                           Investment&#13;
longer expected life of eight years leads to lower annualized&#13;
                                                                      US$&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                           Hardware&#13;
                                                                                                                                           (upfront)&#13;
costs than for dry pit latrines (maximum three years).&#13;
                                                                                                                                           Investment&#13;
                                                                                                                                           Program&#13;
                                                                                                                                           (upfront)&#13;
While the unlined simple pit latrines have a lower benefit-cost&#13;
ratio because they were found to last no more than an av-&#13;
erage of one year, they have a lower upfront cost and thus&#13;
are more affordable to poor households. Also, latrine costs&#13;
include the program costs of the implementing agent: these&#13;
program costs, at US$54 per household adopting a simple&#13;
pit latrine, were higher than is usually the case in other proj-       economic performance of CLTS will improve. Effective CLTS&#13;
ects in Cambodia and in other countries. If program costs per          also leads to all households in a community moving quickly&#13;
household of returning communities to open defecation-free             onto the sanitation ladder, with social pressures for sustain-&#13;
(ODF) status (or maintaining ODF status) actually decline over         ability, and those who start on the lowest rung with dry pits&#13;
time, then the benefit-cost ratio would be more favorable than         progressing up the ladder when they can afford it.&#13;
presented in this analysis.&#13;
                                                                       The most important benefits for all options are time savings&#13;
The lessons from this and other CLTS projects means that               followed by health improvements. The health values estimat-&#13;
future unit costs of changing behavior and achieving basic             ed are based on an assumed 36 percent reduction in mortal-&#13;
sanitation options should be significantly lower, and hence the        ity and disease cases related to poor sanitation. Health care&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;4 The Economic Returns of Sanitation Interventions in Cambodia                                                  Economics of Sanitation Initiative&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  costs are based on actual treatment seeking rates of around           Figure 4. Benefit-Cost Ratios in Urban Site (economic&#13;
  50 percent: if treatment seeking were higher, the associated          return per unit of currency spent)&#13;
  health care savings would also be higher.&#13;
&#13;
  The results presented above are under â&#128;&#156;idealâ&#128;? conditions,&#13;
  where latrine adopters continue to use their latrine for the&#13;
  full-assumed life of the latrine. However, in the projects some&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                       Beneï¬?t - Cost Ratios&#13;
  â&#128;&#156;dropoutâ&#128;? was observed in all project sites, with some or all&#13;
  household members going back to open defecation. This&#13;
  is due partly to force of habit, lack of social pressures and&#13;
  norms to stop open defecation, and partly due to the latrine&#13;
  ceasing to function properly. When dropout was taken into&#13;
  account, the economic performance declined significantly.&#13;
  For simple dry pit latrines benefit-cost ratio dropped from 1.4&#13;
  to 0.8, improved dry pit latrine dropped from 2.0 to 1.3, while&#13;
  wet pit latrine dropped from an average 2.6 to 1.8.&#13;
&#13;
  Urban Areas: Poor Economic Performance of                                                   Access Time       Water Access       Health Productivity&#13;
&#13;
  High-Cost Sanitation Option                                                                 Water Treatment   Health Mortality   Health Care&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        Figure 5. Annual Costs per Household in Urban Site (2009&#13;
  Benefit-cost ratios and annualized costs per household are            prices, using average exchange rate with US$)&#13;
  presented for the urban site, Sihanoukville, in Figure 4 and Fig-&#13;
  ure 5. Given the lack of range of alternative sanitation options&#13;
  practiced by households, only wet pit latrines and sewerage&#13;
  with treatment were compared. A sewerage system without                                                                                  Annualized&#13;
                                                                                                                                           Investment&#13;
  treatment is also still provided in the urban site, with outflow                                                                         Annualized&#13;
                                                                                                                                           Maintenance&#13;
  to the sea. However, given this is a tourist resort, such a prac-                                                                        Annualized&#13;
  tice is not favorable for attracting tourists and therefore the                                                                          Operations&#13;
                                                                      US$&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                           Investment&#13;
  economic performance of this option is not considered. As in                                                                             Hardware&#13;
                                                                                                                                           (upfront)&#13;
  rural areas, the most favorable economic performance was&#13;
  found for wet pit latrinesâ&#128;&#148;in this case, with sedimentation&#13;
  tank made from bricksâ&#128;&#148;with a benefit-cost ratio of 1.8 and&#13;
  an annual return of 27 percent, requiring under three years to&#13;
  recover the economic value of the initial investment. Taking&#13;
  into account non-use of latrines by households, or individual&#13;
  household members, the benefit-cost ratio drops to 1.4.&#13;
&#13;
  Despite their favorable economic returns, pit latrines are not        hence largely ineffective. Hence, the Sihanoukville wastewa-&#13;
  an appropriate sanitation option in most parts of Cambodiaâ&#128;&#153;s          ter treatment plant is considered the first of a new series of&#13;
  fast-growing cities. While access to toilets in urban areas is        wastewater treatment plants to deal with Cambodiaâ&#128;&#153;s urban&#13;
  highâ&#128;&#148;at over 80 percent according to official statisticsâ&#128;&#148;the          waste problem, with more recent investments made in a simi-&#13;
  majority of sewage and wastewater is emptied into water               lar plant in Siem Reap.&#13;
  bodies untreated. Previous wastewater treatment plants con-&#13;
  structed in other cities (such as Battambang) are not cur-            The Sihanoukville plant with improved sewerage network has&#13;
  rently functional, and the natural wetland system serving the         been an expensive undertaking, costing almost US$5,500&#13;
  countryâ&#128;&#153;s capital, Phnom Penh, is seriously overloaded and            per connected household to construct based on its expected&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                     www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;Economics of Sanitation Initiative                                         The Economic Returns of Sanitation Interventions in Cambodia 5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
operating capacity (or US$544 per year, based on a 20-year                     access for all Cambodians. When implementing programs,&#13;
lifespan and discount rate of 8 percent). Given that in the years              special attention should be paid to ensuring the health&#13;
after its construction, only around 20 percent of the house-                   benefits are captured as well as sustaining coverage (i.e.,&#13;
holds have connected (which requires a one-off connection                      avoiding return to open defecation) by focusing on collec-&#13;
fee and a monthly wastewater fee), the actual construction                     tive behavior change. A key to scaling up rural coverage&#13;
cost per household of US$27,500 is five times the planned                      is for communities to achieve total sanitation followed by&#13;
cost per household. This translates to a benefit-cost ratio of                 moving up the sanitation ladder with better latrine structure&#13;
0.14 under full capacity use, and 0.03 under actual capac-                     and design, particularly the slab and underground com-&#13;
ity use. However, the value of the improved environment and                    ponents, at affordable cost. Triggering community social&#13;
seawater quality to residents and tourists, and the associated                 norms and pressures against open defecation, technical&#13;
revenues from tourismâ&#128;&#148;which are potentially substantialâ&#128;&#148;                       guidance to households, and availability of expertise in la-&#13;
have not been included in the calculation (see Box 1).                         trine construction in the community, are also elements of&#13;
                                                                               sustaining coverage.&#13;
KEY FINDINGS AND RECOMMENDATIONS&#13;
This study finds that all rural sanitation interventions have               2. Go beyond basic sanitation provision in urban areas. Deci-&#13;
benefits that exceed costs, when compared with â&#128;&#156;no sanita-                     sion makers should be aware of the full range of sewage&#13;
tion facility.â&#128;? In urban areas, costs of off-site options are not              conveyance and treatment options, and their related costs&#13;
affordable for the majority of the population, and have a very                 and benefits, in order to avoid investing in expensive tech-&#13;
low (unfavorable) benefit-cost ratio. Based on these findings,                 nologies that are difficult and costly to sustain. To achieve&#13;
three major recommendations for decision makers and their                      maximum benefits and efficiencies from the investments,&#13;
partner agencies are proposed here:                                            it will be necessary to ensure incentives and sanction so&#13;
                                                                               that all households connect and use the systems. In many&#13;
1. Intensify efforts to provide broad-based, basic sanitation                  municipalities, funds could be raised that permit more sus-&#13;
&#13;
   BOX 1. SANITATION LINKS TO TOURISM AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT&#13;
&#13;
   A separate tourism survey of 334 holiday and business visitors           sanitation as a contributory reason for their decision not to return.&#13;
   was conducted as part of the study and found that the general&#13;
   sanitation conditions in Cambodia are unfavorable, receiving an          The study also conducted a business survey included 19 firms&#13;
   average 2.5 rating out of a maximum of 5.0. The worst score              around Phnom Penh (six foreign firms, 13 local firms) comprising&#13;
   was for open water sources (e.g., rivers, beach). On the question        five travel agencies, two hotels, three restaurants, four drinking&#13;
   of toilet availability in public areas, bus stations and city centers    water factories, three food producers, and two trading firms. Al-&#13;
   received the worst rating, receiving little more than 2.0 out of a       though sanitation does not have much influence on investment&#13;
   maximum score of 5.0; availability of hand washing facilities re-        decisions, business people admit that they do take into account&#13;
   ceived an even lower score. When asked what the major hygiene            the sanitation conditions in the locations of their investment, as&#13;
   concerns were, the top answers were unsanitary toilets, tap wa-          this would have some impacts on business, especially for food&#13;
   ter, and food safety. One in five (20 percent) of the survey re-         producers and restaurants. Water quality in rivers and toilets&#13;
   spondents said they had gastro-intestinal problems during their          in public places received poor ratings. Workforce health and a&#13;
   stay, incapacitating the tourist for several days. The amount that       pleasant environment for staff are considered very important for&#13;
   they could have spent during those days of illness represents            business, especially travel agencies. Businesses pay to treat their&#13;
   foregone earnings for the tourism industry. Despite the nega-            water on-site, and also to clean up the environment around the&#13;
   tive assessment of environmental sanitation in Cambodia, more            business site. All firms said polluted environment around sales&#13;
   than seven in ten visitors expressed an intention to return to the       offices would have a bad influence on their business operation,&#13;
   country. Of 103 tourists who said they had some doubts about             both for customers and employees. When asked whether they&#13;
   returning, 9 percent of respondents blamed poor sanitation as            plan to move to another location, around half of the firms wish to&#13;
   the main reason for not returning, while 25 percent cited poor           move to new and cleaner locations.&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;6 The Economic Returns of Sanitation Interventions in Cambodia                                                                                     Economics of Sanitation Initiative&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       tained and quality services, which                                      fundamentally target community-&#13;
       better capture the full environmental                                   wide behavior change. Therefore,                                  Acknowledgments&#13;
       and health benefits and respond to                                      relevant evidence to collect includes                             The Research Brief was prepared by Guy&#13;
       the populationâ&#128;&#153;s wish for a clean, liv-                                 assessment of approach, quality                                   Hutton, Kov Phyrum, Isabel Blackett and Almud&#13;
       able environment (see Box 1).                                           of process, and the inclusiveness,                                Weitz based on the full report titled â&#128;&#156;Economic&#13;
                                                                               scale, and speed of getting onto the                              Assessment of Sanitation Interventions in&#13;
  3. Promote evidence-based sanita-                                            sanitation ladder and then moving                                 Cambodiaâ&#128;&#156; prepared by Sam Sok Heng, Poch&#13;
     tion decision making. Variations in                                       up with appropriate sanitation op-                                Kongchheng, Guy Hutton and Kov Phyrum.&#13;
     economic performance of options                                           tions. Further evidence is needed on                              Editing support was provided by Yosa Yuliarsa,&#13;
     and delivery approaches suggests                                          the approachesâ&#128;&#148;and their implied                                  Kara Watkins, and Christopher Walsh.&#13;
     a careful consideration of site con-                                      costsâ&#128;&#148;that help sustain open defe-&#13;
     ditions is needed to select the most                                      cation-free status after initial trigger-&#13;
     appropriate sanitation option and                                         ing, and integrate these findings into                            About us&#13;
     delivery approach. Approaches that                                        future cost-benefit studies. Decisions                            The Water and Sanitation Program (WSP) is a&#13;
     involve the entire community, such as                                     should take into account not only                                 multi-donor partnership created in 1978 and&#13;
     CLTS, have low hardware costs and                                         the measurable economic costs and                                 administered by the World Bank to support&#13;
     although these are not subsidized                                         benefits, but also other key factors                              poor people in obtaining affordable, safe, and&#13;
     from the outside, this approach po-                                       for a decision, including intangible                              sustainable access to water and sanitation&#13;
     tentially achieves higher coverage                                        impacts and socio-cultural issues                                 services. WSP provides technical assistance,&#13;
     rates at low cost. In contrast, more                                      that influence demand and behavior                                facilitates knowledge exchange, and promotes&#13;
     expensive but long-lasting latrine                                        change, availability of suppliers and                             evidence-based advancements in sector dialogue.&#13;
     options with high hardware sub-                                           private financing, and actual house-                              WSP has offices in 24 countries across Africa,&#13;
     sidy will not achieve high nation-                                        hold willingness and ability to pay for                           East Asia and the Pacific, Latin America and&#13;
     wide sanitation coverage and do not                                       services.                                                         the Caribbean, South Asia, and in Washington,&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 DC. WSPâ&#128;&#153;s donors include Australia, Austria,&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 Canada, Denmark, Finland, France, the Bill and&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 Melinda Gates Foundation, Ireland, Luxembourg,&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, Switzerland,&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 United Kingdom, United States, and the World&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 Contact us&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 For more information please visit www.wsp.org or&#13;
  i&#13;
  Economic assessment of sanitation interventions in Cambodia. Heng, S., Poch, K., Hutton, G., Kov, P. World Bank, Water and Sanitation&#13;
  Program. 2011.                                                                                                                                 email Guy Hutton at wsp@worldbank.org.&#13;
  ii&#13;
  The sanitation part of the combined water and sanitation MDG target was to halve by 2015 the proportion of the global population with-&#13;
  out access to basic sanitation in 1990. The figures cited are those those reported by the WHO/UNICEF Joint Monitoring Programme.&#13;
  iii&#13;
     Economic impacts of sanitation in Cambodia. Kov, P., Sok, H., Roth, S., Chhoeun, K., Hutton, G. World Bank, Water and Sanitation&#13;
  Program. 2008. Available for download at www.wsp.org.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Water and Sanitation Program (WSP) reports are published to communicate the results of WSPâ&#128;&#153;s work to the development community.&#13;
  Some sources cited may be informal documents that are not readily available.&#13;
&#13;
  The findings, interpretations, and conclusions expressed herein are entirely those of the author and should not be attributed to the World&#13;
  Bank or its affiliated organizations, or to members of the Board of Executive Directors of the World Bank or the governments they represent.&#13;
  The World Bank does not guarantee the accuracy of the data included in this work. The boundaries, colors, denominations, and other&#13;
  information shown on any map in this work do not imply any judgment on the part of the World Bank Group concerning the legal status of&#13;
  any territory or the endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
&#13;
  The material in this publication is copyrighted. Requests for permission to reproduce portions of it should be sent to wsp@worldbank.&#13;
  org. WSP encourages the dissemination of its work and will normally grant permission promptly. For more information, please visit www.&#13;
  wsp.org.&#13;
&#13;
  Â© 2011 Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="15220010">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/08/15220010/economic-returns-sanitation-interventions-cambodia
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/08/15220010/economic-returns-sanitation-interventions-cambodia</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2011/08/15220010/economic-returns-sanitation-interventions-cambodia</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2011-10-05T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2011-10-05T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/10/05/000020953_20111005091401/Rendered/INDEX/647710wsp0camb00Box361544B00PUBLIC0.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/10/05/000020953_20111005091401/Rendered/PDF/647710wsp0camb00Box361544B00PUBLIC0.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2011-10-05T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2011-08-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The Economic Returns of Sanitation
            Interventions in Cambodia
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Economics of Sanitation Initiative
            (ESI) is a multi-country study launched in 2007 as a
            response by the World Bank's Water and Sanitation
            Program to address major gaps in evidence among developing
            countries on the economic aspects of sanitation. Its
            objective is to provide economic evidence to increase the
            volumes and efficiency of public and private spending on
            sanitation. This research brief summarizes the key findings
            of study second phase, cost-benefit analysis of alternative
            sanitation options, from Cambodia.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The Economic Returns of Sanitation
            Interventions in Cambodia
        </docna>
        <display_title>The Economic Returns of
            Sanitation Interventions in Cambodia</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2011/08/15220010/economic-returns-sanitation-interventions-cambodia</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing,Wastewater Treatment,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,Health and Sanitation,Sanitation and Sewerage</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>Bangladesh</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000020953_20111005091401</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Water and Sanitation Program : research brief</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            access to water, alternative sanitation,
            basic sanitation, behavior change, connection, connection
            fee, drinking water, dry pit, environmental benefits,
            environmental sanitation, hand washing, hand washing
            facilities, Health Care, health risks, human excreta,
            hygiene, latrine, latrine construction, latrine structure,
            pit latrine, pit latrines, pits, pollution, rivers, rural
            population, rural sanitation, safety, SANITATION, sanitation
            access, sanitation coverage, sanitation facility, Sanitation
            improvement, Sanitation Interventions, sanitation options,
            SANITATION PROGRAM, sanitation programs, sanitation
            services, sanitation technologies, sedimentation, sewage,
            sewerage, sewerage connections, sewerage network, toilet,
            toilets, Total Sanitation, treatment plant, urban areas,
            Urban coverage, urban waste, use of latrines, wastewater,
            wastewater management, wastewater treatment, wastewater
            treatment plants, water bodies, water quality, water
            resources, water sources
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water Unit (TWIWA)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>64771</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation and Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Treatment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fescal Sludge Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sludge Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Chlorination</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Disinfection</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Filtration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Purification</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation and Wastewater</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Onsite Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Treatment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wetlands</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Bangladesh</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>