<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿WATER AND SANITATION PROGRAM: RESEARCH BRIEF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                     64773&#13;
The Economic Returns                                                                               Key messages&#13;
of Sanitation Interventions                                                                        â&#128;¢ Improved sanitation has been&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
in Indonesia&#13;
                                                                                                     proven in the study to be a socially&#13;
                                                                                                     profitable investment in Indonesia.&#13;
                                                                                                     In rural areas the economic benefits&#13;
August 2011                                                                                          of pit latrines exceed costs by at&#13;
                                                                                                     least seven times, and in urban areas&#13;
                                                                                                     the economic benefits of improved&#13;
                                                                                                     wastewater management exceed the&#13;
INTRODUCTION                                       Vietnam--access to sanitation facilities          costs by almost two times. Net benefits&#13;
The Economics of Sanitation Initia-                in Indonesia continues to be under par,           from low-cost sanitation options are&#13;
tive (ESI) is a multi-country study                at only 52 percent,ii with large gaps be-         high, offering an affordable option to&#13;
launched in 2007 as a response by                  tween urban (69 percent) and rural ar-            poor households.&#13;
the World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s Water and Sanitation              eas (34 percent) as well as across the&#13;
Program to address major gaps in evi-              33 provinces (30 to 80 percent). At the         â&#128;¢ Better â&#128;&#156;packagingâ&#128;? of and access to&#13;
dence among developing countries on                current pace of progress, Indonesia is            information on costs and benefits of&#13;
the economic aspects of sanitation. Its            unlikely to reach the MDG target of 63            sanitation options is key to rapidly&#13;
objective is to provide economic evi-              percent. Open defecation is still prac-           increasing uptake in Indonesia.&#13;
dence to increase the volume and ef-               ticed by about 60 million Indonesians,            Decision makersâ&#128;&#148;both households&#13;
ficiency of public and private spending            the second highest number of people               and governmentâ&#128;&#148;need to be further&#13;
on sanitation. This research brief sum-            worldwide, with the share of urban                sensitized to the health, economic&#13;
marizes the key findings of Study Phase            open defecation increasing due to mi-             and social benefits associated with&#13;
IIâ&#128;&#148;cost-benefit analysis of alternative            gration of poor rural people into urban           improved sanitation, and the available&#13;
sanitation optionsâ&#128;&#148;from Indonesia.i                slums. Only 2 percent of urban areas in           choice of latrine designs, models, and&#13;
                                                   the country as a whole have sewerage              sanitary options.&#13;
PROBLEM STATEMENT                                  coverage, and the collection, transport&#13;
While Indonesia is on a path to becom-             and disposal of septage from septic             â&#128;¢ Sanitation options that protect the&#13;
ing a middle-income country thanks                 tanks is seriously inadequate, causing            environment are more costly to&#13;
to stable economic growth rates in                 health risks and widespread pollution of          provide, but while the environmental&#13;
recent years, access to and the qual-              water resources.                                  benefits are difficult to quantify in&#13;
ity of public services are closer to that                                                            economic terms, they are essential&#13;
of comparable low-income countries,                Phase I of the ESI study estimated the            to national economic development,&#13;
with Indonesia scoring low marks in                overall economic costs of poor sanita-            and the benefits are highly valued&#13;
several health and infrastructure indi-            tion in Indonesia to be US$6.3 billion            by households, tourists, and&#13;
cators. Compared to other countries                (IDR56 trillion) per year at 2005 prices,         businesses.&#13;
in the region at similar levels of devel-          equivalent to 2.3 percent of gross do-&#13;
opment--such as the Philippines and                mestic product (GDP).iii&#13;
&#13;
  Economic analysis measures the broader welfare benefits of products and services on popu-&#13;
  lations, such as value of life, time use, environmental and social benefits, as opposed to fi-&#13;
  nancial analysis, which measures the financial gains only (e.g., changes in income or cash&#13;
  situation).&#13;
&amp;#12;2 The Economic Returns of Sanitation Interventions in Indonesia                                     Economics of Sanitation Initiative&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Figure 1. ESI Field Sites in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  STUDY AIMS AND METHODS                                             Sanitation interventions evaluated varied by rural and ur-&#13;
  The purpose of Phase II of the ESI study is to provide sani-       ban location, comparing open defecation with the range of&#13;
  tation decision makers with improved evidence on the costs         sanitation facilities currently used by the Indonesian popula-&#13;
  and benefits of alternative sanitation options in different con-   tion: shared and public latrines, dry pit latrines, wet pit latrines&#13;
  texts in Indonesia. The study focuses on human excreta man-        (pour-flush), toilets with septic tank including septage man-&#13;
  agement, and includes data from five selected field sites in       agement, and toilets with sewerage connection and decen-&#13;
  addition to national surveys.                                      tralized treatment.&#13;
&#13;
  Surveys were conducted in two rural and three urban sites          Conventional techniques of economic analysis were uti-&#13;
  that have recently been the focus of sanitation programs or        lized to generate outputs such as benefit-cost ratio, cost-ef-&#13;
  projects (see Figure 1), involving 1,500 household question-       fectiveness ratio, net present value, internal rate of the return,&#13;
  naires, focus group discussions, physical investigations, wa-      and payback period of sanitation options.&#13;
  ter quality assessments, market surveys and health facility&#13;
  surveys conducted in each site. Primary data were supple-          Economic benefits quantified include impacts on health,&#13;
  mented with data from other national and local surveys.            drinking water and sanitation access time. Environmental and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                          www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;Economics of Sanitation Initiative                                   The Economic Returns of Sanitation Interventions in Indonesia 3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
social impacts of poor sanitation were not fully captured in         Figure 2. Benefit-Cost Ratios in Rural Sites (economic&#13;
the monetary estimates of benefits. Qualitative analyses were        return per unit of currency spent)&#13;
conducted on selected social and broader economic ben-&#13;
efits.&#13;
&#13;
Full investment and recurrent costs were measured for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Beneï¬?t - Cost Ratios&#13;
each sanitation option.&#13;
&#13;
STUDY RESULTS&#13;
Rural Areas:&#13;
Substantial Economic Returns on Pit Latrines&#13;
&#13;
Benefit-cost ratios (economic return per dollar invested) and&#13;
annualized costs per household were compiled for the two&#13;
rural sites in Figure 2 and Figure 3. Among the various sanita-&#13;
tion options, the most favorable economic performance was&#13;
for dry and wet pit latrines, both with benefit-cost ratios great-&#13;
                                                                                             Access Time        Water Access       Health Productivity&#13;
er than 7.0. The annual economic rate of return was more&#13;
                                                                                             Water Treatment    Health Mortality   Health Care&#13;
than 100 percent, requiring less than one year to recover the&#13;
economic value of the initial investment costs.                      Figure 3. Annual Costs per Household in Rural Sites&#13;
                                                                     (2009 prices, using average exchange rate with US$)&#13;
&#13;
Due to higher investment and operational costs per house-&#13;
hold, community toiletsiv did not perform as well in rural ar-&#13;
eas as private pit latrines, with a benefit-cost ratio of 3.0 for&#13;
public toilets and 4.6 for shared toilets due to the time taken&#13;
to access them. Septic tanks with wastewater management&#13;
(WWM) have a benefit cost ratio of 3.8. Septic tanks with-&#13;
out WWM had lower costs but also less health benefits, and&#13;
therefore have the same benefit-cost ratio. However, this&#13;
does not fully value the environmental benefits of WWM.&#13;
                                                                     US$&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The major contributor to economic benefits is health care cost&#13;
savings. These savingsâ&#128;&#148;which are largely financial savings to&#13;
householdsâ&#128;&#148;are expected to pay back the investment more&#13;
than two times over for public toilets, rising to almost four&#13;
times for private dry pit latrines. The second most important&#13;
contributor for private latrines is access time savings. Further-&#13;
more, productivity savings are an important benefit for all op-                                    Investment      Maintenance         Operations&#13;
tions analyzed.&#13;
                                                                     pan. Public toilets are also relatively expensive, at an invest-&#13;
The findings suggest that simple technologies, particularly          ment cost of US$400 per household, or US$50 per year per&#13;
improved pit latrines, are the most economic, yielding con-          household.&#13;
siderable benefits with a low unit cost of around US$30 per&#13;
household per year (includes investment and operation and            Under actual program conditions, there is a decline in per-&#13;
maintenance costs). Septic tanks are significantly more ex-          formance for all sanitation options. This is due to non-use by&#13;
pensive at US$70 per year, despite their longer assumed lifes-       some households or household members of the facilities. For&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;4 The Economic Returns of Sanitation Interventions in Indonesia                                                   Economics of Sanitation Initiative&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  example, the benefit-cost ratio of dry pit latrines declines from    Figure 4. Benefit-Cost Ratios in Urban Sites (economic&#13;
  an economic return per currency unit spent of 7.9 to 6.3 and         return per unit of currency spent)&#13;
  for wet pit latrines it declines from 7.1 to 5.6.&#13;
&#13;
  Urban Areas: Off-Site Treatment Options Deliver&#13;
  High Economic Returns&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Beneï¬?t - Cost Ratios&#13;
  Benefit-cost ratios and annualized costs per household were&#13;
  compiled for the three urban sites in Figure 4 and Figure 5.&#13;
  While technology prices are not very different to rural areas,&#13;
  the benefit-cost ratios are less favorable than rural sites due&#13;
  to better baseline health statistics and less access time in&#13;
  urban sites. The most favorable economic performance was&#13;
  found for wet pit latrines, with a benefit-cost ratio of 3.2. The&#13;
  annual return was more than 100 percent, requiring less than&#13;
  one year to recover the economic value of the initial invest-&#13;
  ment cost. All other sanitation options have benefit-cost ra-&#13;
                                                                                             Access Time       Water Access        Health Productivity&#13;
  tios of more than oneâ&#128;&#148;shared toilets 2.3, septic tanks 1.9,&#13;
                                                                                             Water Treatment   Health Mortality    Health Care&#13;
  sewerage with treatment 1.7 and public toilets 1.4â&#128;&#148;thus&#13;
                                                                       Figure 5. Annual Costs per Household in Urban Sites&#13;
  suggesting favorable economic performance and justifying&#13;
                                                                       (2009 prices, using average exchange rate with US$)&#13;
  investment.&#13;
&#13;
  However, pit latrines are not a technically feasible sanitation&#13;
  option in many of Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s densely-populated cities, nor&#13;
  its fast growing peri-urban areas, due to lack of space. While&#13;
  access to household toilets in urban areas is highâ&#128;&#148;at over&#13;
  70 percent according to the latest socio-economic survey in&#13;
  2007 (SUSENAS)â&#128;&#148;the majority of urban households have&#13;
  septic tanks with limited or no septage management. Hence&#13;
  safe septage management is badly needed in Indonesia. The&#13;
  decentralized wastewater treatment system was found to&#13;
                                                                      US$&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  have benefit-cost ratio of 1.7, and cost under US$100 per&#13;
  household per year (including investment costs converted to&#13;
  annual equivalent values as well as operations and mainte-&#13;
  nance). Septic tanks with collection and treatment cost less,&#13;
  at under US$70 per household per year. However, the envi-&#13;
  ronmental benefits of septage management and wastewater&#13;
  treatment were not fully reflected in this study. Hence, the real                               Investment      Maintenance         Operations&#13;
  economic performance of sanitation options that treat waste&#13;
  before disposal or release to the environment will be better         Private options are also preferred by households in terms of&#13;
  than the figures suggest.                                            privacy, security, convenience, and hygienic condition.&#13;
&#13;
  On an annualized cost basis (including both investment and           Under actual program conditions, the economic performance&#13;
  recurrent costs), community and shared toilets cost less than        of all urban sanitation options is lower. The benefit-cost ratio&#13;
  private options. Yet, due to less time savings, their overall        of sewerage declines from 1.7 to 1.1, septic tanks with col-&#13;
  economic performance is less favorable than wet pit latrines.        lection and treatment reduces from 1.9 to 1.4 and wet pit&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                      www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;Economics of Sanitation Initiative                                  The Economic Returns of Sanitation Interventions in Indonesia 5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
latrine from 3.2 to 2.4. The benefit-cost ratio of public toilets   river water quality, poor drainage, poor management of in-&#13;
was reduced to 0.85, i.e., below unity where costs exceed           dustrial solid waste, lack of toilets in public places, and poor&#13;
benefits. This is due not only to non-use by some households        air quality from solid waste.&#13;
or household members of the facilities, but also off-site treat-&#13;
ment facilities being utilized at well below their engineered       KEY FINDINGS AND RECOMMENDATIONS&#13;
capacity. This finding further emphasizes how important it          This study finds that all sanitation interventions have benefits&#13;
is for an effective service delivery to focus on permanently        that exceed costs, when compared with â&#128;&#156;no sanitation facil-&#13;
changing behavior to ensure a sustained use of the sanita-          ity.â&#128;? The high net benefits from low-cost sanitation options,&#13;
tion facilities, that demand assessments are undertaken and         such as pit latrines, suggests these technologies should be&#13;
that the facilities can be adapted if circumstances change          centerpiece to increasing access for rural households. How-&#13;
(e.g., piped water becomes available in the neighborhood).          ever, in densely populated areas, pit latrines have limited fea-&#13;
For community-level facilities, it also emphasizes the impor-       sibility, and to improve quality of life in increasingly populous&#13;
tance of designing appropriate size/volume of the collection        cities, decision makers need to take into account the eco-&#13;
and treatment facilities to ensure there is no significant over-    nomic benefits from improved conveyance and treatment op-&#13;
capacity in the long run.                                           tions. If funding is available, populations prefer options that&#13;
                                                                    transport waste off-site. Appropriate treatment and/or isola-&#13;
Sanitation Links to Tourism and Economic                            tion of waste is key to the future sustainable development of&#13;
Development                                                         Indonesia. Based on these findings, three key recommenda-&#13;
                                                                    tions for decision makers are proposed here:&#13;
The key results of a tourism survey of 254 holiday and busi-&#13;
ness visitors are reported in Box 1.                                1. Intensify efforts to improve access for the entire Indone-&#13;
                                                                       sian population to improved basic sanitation. Indonesia&#13;
A separate business survey was also conducted with ten                 approved a sound community-based sanitation strategy&#13;
firms mostly operating around Jakarta and Bandung, includ-             in 2008 that needs to be implemented, and enough evi-&#13;
ing four restaurants, two hotels, two garment producers, one           dence is available to show that establishing a viable sani-&#13;
food producer and one convention center. The business in-              tation marketâ&#128;&#148;where demand by all income levels meets&#13;
terviewees consider clean air and environment as the most              affordable and good quality supplyâ&#128;&#148;is feasible. For policy&#13;
important factors for companies in locating their businesses,          makers and local governments, this requires special at-&#13;
especially food processing and restaurants. They were con-             tention to ensure demand is triggered, health benefits are&#13;
cerned about the quality of the environment, especially low            captured, and coverage is sustained (i.e., avoiding re-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 BOX 1. KEY RESULTS OF TOURISM SURVEY&#13;
&#13;
  General sanitation conditions in Indonesia are perceived to       Close to one-third of the respondents (31 percent) said they&#13;
  be very poor, scoring 2.5 out of maximum of 5.0. Open             had gastro-intestinal problems during their stay, incapaci-&#13;
  water such as rivers and beaches score the lowest at 2.3,         tating the tourist for an average of two days. The amount&#13;
  with raw sewerage leaking into these.                             they could have spent during those days of illness repre-&#13;
                                                                    sents foregone earnings for the tourism industry.&#13;
  The perception of toilet quality varied by location, scoring&#13;
  from 2.0 (in bus stations and city centers), to 3.0 (airports,    Despite many negative comments about environmental&#13;
  restaurants) to 3.5 (hotels).                                     sanitation in Indonesia, 85 percent of visitors expressed an&#13;
                                                                    intention to return to the country and 74 percent said they&#13;
  When asked about the most serious hygienic concerns,              would recommend the country as a tourist destination to&#13;
  interviewees responded that food hygiene, availability of         friends. Of those reluctant to return, 40 percent of respon-&#13;
  drinking water, and use of sanitary toilets are top concerns.     dents listed sanitation as the main reason.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;6 The Economic Returns of Sanitation Interventions in Indonesia                                                                                    Economics of Sanitation Initiative&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               aware of the full range of conveyance&#13;
                                                                               and treatment options, and their re-                              Acknowledgments&#13;
                                                                               lated costs and benefits, in order to                             The Research Brief was prepared by Guy&#13;
                                                                               avoid investing in expensive technol-                             Hutton, Asep Winara, Isabel Blackett and Almud&#13;
                                                                               ogies that are difficult and costly to                            Weitz based on the full report titled â&#128;&#156;Economic&#13;
                                                                               sustain. In municipalities where fund-                            Assessment of Sanitation Interventions in&#13;
                                                                               ing is sufficient to permit more sus-                             Indonesiaâ&#128;&#156; prepared by Asep Winara, Oktarinda,&#13;
                                                                               tained and quality services, these will                           Edi Purnomo, Koderi Hadiwardoyo, Indon&#13;
                                                                               better capture the full environmental                             Merdykasari, Takdir Nurmadi, Bert Bruinsma,&#13;
                                                                               and health benefits and respond to                                Dedek Gunawan, Dadang Fadilah, Martin Albrecht&#13;
                                                                               the populationâ&#128;&#153;s wish for a clean, liv-                           and Guy Hutton. Editing support was provided&#13;
          turning to open defecation). Sanita-                                 able environment.                                                 by Yosa Yuliarsa, Kara Watkins, and Christopher&#13;
          tion providers, from wholesalers to                                                                                                    Walsh.&#13;
          community-based masons, need to                                  3. Promote evidence-based sanita-&#13;
          improve on affordable, upgradable                                   tion decision-making. Variations in&#13;
          latrine structures and design to en-                                economic performance of options                                    About us&#13;
          sure widespread uptake. Information                                 suggests that careful consideration                                The Water and Sanitation Program (WSP) is a&#13;
          on sanitation options and models for                                of site conditions and local demand                                multi-donor partnership created in 1978 and&#13;
          households everywhere in Indonesia                                  and preferences is needed to select                                administered by the World Bank to support&#13;
          is another key element for rapidly ac-                              the most appropriate sanitation op-                                poor people in obtaining affordable, safe, and&#13;
          celerating and sustaining coverage.                                 tion and delivery approach. Deci-                                  sustainable access to water and sanitation&#13;
                                                                              sions should take into account not                                 services. WSP provides technical assistance,&#13;
  2. Go beyond basic sanitation provision,                                    only the measurable economic costs                                 facilitates knowledge exchange, and promotes&#13;
     where the population demands it and                                      and benefits, but also other key fac-                              evidence-based advancements in sector dialogue.&#13;
     the funding is available. In densely                                     tors for a decision, including intangi-                            WSP has offices in 24 countries across Africa,&#13;
     populated urban areas, only basic                                        ble impacts and socio-cultural issues                              East Asia and the Pacific, Latin America and&#13;
     sanitation provision is no longer fea-                                   that influence demand and behavior                                 the Caribbean, South Asia, and in Washington,&#13;
     sible due to the higher expectations                                     change, availability of suppliers and                              DC. WSPâ&#128;&#153;s donors include Australia, Austria,&#13;
     of populations, space constraints                                        private financing, and actual house-                               Canada, Denmark, Finland, France, the Bill and&#13;
     and risks of groundwater pollution.                                      hold willingness and ability to pay for                            Melinda Gates Foundation, Ireland, Luxembourg,&#13;
     Decision makers should therefore be                                      services.                                                          Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, Switzerland,&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 United Kingdom, United States, and the World&#13;
  i&#13;
  Economic assessment of sanitation interventions in Indonesia. Winara, A., Oktarinda, PE., Hadiwardoyo, K., Merdykasari, I., Nurmadi, T.,&#13;
  Bruinsma, B., Gunawan, D., Fadilah, D., Albrecht, M., Hutton, G. World Bank, Water and Sanitation Program. 2011.                               Bank.&#13;
  ii&#13;
        WHO-Unicef Joint Monitoring Programme in Indonesia. 2010. Progress on Sanitation and Drinking Water: 2010 Update.&#13;
  iii&#13;
   Economic impacts of sanitation in Indonesia. Napitupulu, L., Hutton, G. World Bank, Water and Sanitation Program. 2008. Available for&#13;
  download at www.wsp.org.&#13;
  iv&#13;
    Community toilets are termed SANIMASâ&#128;&#148;Sanitasi Berbasis Masyarakatâ&#128;&#148;translating as Community-based Sanitation. While a range of&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 Contact us&#13;
  technologies are on offer for SANIMAS projects, the one at Tangerang involved a public building with four latrines, underground piping, a&#13;
  sludge treatment unit using Decentralized Wastewater Treatment System (DEWATS), an effluent pipe and a bio-digester.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 For more information please visit www.wsp.org or&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 email Guy Hutton at wsp@worldbank.org.&#13;
&#13;
  Water and Sanitation Program (WSP) reports are published to communicate the results of WSPâ&#128;&#153;s work to the development community.&#13;
  Some sources cited may be informal documents that are not readily available.&#13;
&#13;
  The findings, interpretations, and conclusions expressed herein are entirely those of the author and should not be attributed to the World&#13;
  Bank or its affiliated organizations, or to members of the Board of Executive Directors of the World Bank or the governments they represent.&#13;
  The World Bank does not guarantee the accuracy of the data included in this work. The boundaries, colors, denominations, and other&#13;
  information shown on any map in this work do not imply any judgment on the part of the World Bank Group concerning the legal status of&#13;
  any territory or the endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
&#13;
  The material in this publication is copyrighted. Requests for permission to reproduce portions of it should be sent to wsp@worldbank.&#13;
  org. WSP encourages the dissemination of its work and will normally grant permission promptly. For more information, please visit www.&#13;
  wsp.org.&#13;
&#13;
  Â© 2011 Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="15220047">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/08/15220047/economic-returns-sanitation-interventions-indonesia
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/08/15220047/economic-returns-sanitation-interventions-indonesia</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2011/08/15220047/economic-returns-sanitation-interventions-indonesia</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2011-10-05T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2011-10-05T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/10/05/000020953_20111005092458/Rendered/INDEX/647730wsp0indo00Box361544B00PUBLIC0.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/10/05/000020953_20111005092458/Rendered/PDF/647730wsp0indo00Box361544B00PUBLIC0.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2011-10-05T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2011-08-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The Economic Returns of Sanitation
            Interventions in Indonesia
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Economics of Sanitation Initiative
            (ESI) is a multi-country study launched in 2007 as a
            response by the World Bank's Water and Sanitation
            Program to address major gaps in evidence among developing
            countries on the economic aspects of sanitation. Its
            objective is to provide economic evidence to increase the
            volume and efficiency of public and private spending on
            sanitation. This research brief summarizes the key findings
            of study second phase, cost-benefit analysis of alternative
            sanitation options, from Indonesia.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The Economic Returns of Sanitation
            Interventions in Indonesia
        </docna>
        <display_title>The Economic Returns of
            Sanitation Interventions in Indonesia</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2011/08/15220047/economic-returns-sanitation-interventions-indonesia</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Wastewater Treatment,Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,Health and Sanitation,Sanitation and Sewerage</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>Indonesia</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southeast Asia!$!80471</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000020953_20111005092458</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Water and sanitation program : research brief</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            access to sanitation, access to water,
            alternative sanitation, basic sanitation, behavior change,
            benefits of sanitation, Community toilets, connection,
            drinking water, dry pit, environmental benefits,
            environmental sanitation, food hygiene, groundwater,
            groundwater pollution, health care, health risks, human
            excreta, hygiene, industrial solid waste, latrine, piping,
            pit latrines, poor drainage, public latrines, public
            toilets, range of sanitation facilities, raw sewerage,
            rivers, SANITATION, sanitation access, sanitation
            facilities, sanitation facility, Sanitation Interventions,
            sanitation market, sanitation options, SANITATION PROGRAM,
            sanitation programs, sanitation services, septic tank,
            septic tanks, sewerage, sewerage connection, sludge, sludge
            treatment, toilet, toilets, treatment facilities, urban
            areas, urban households, urban sanitation, urban slums,
            waste, wastewater, wastewater management, wastewater
            treatment, wastewater treatment system, water quality, water resources
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water - Water &amp; Sant. Prgrm-EAP (GWASE)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southeast Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>64773</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation and Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Treatment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Solid Waste Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Solid Waste Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Chlorination</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Disinfection</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Filtration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Purification</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation and Wastewater</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Solid Waste</ml:concept><ml:concept>Airports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Onsite Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Treatment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drainage</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Indonesia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>