<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿ nm                                                                                              1&#13;
&#13;
             NM/AH&#13;
                                                                           64898&#13;
&#13;
                                         INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
&#13;
                                                 INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
                               I&#13;
                              II 
&#13;
                              'I
&#13;
                              II&#13;
                              I&#13;
                              II&#13;
                              II 
&#13;
                              il 
&#13;
                              II&#13;
                              I,&#13;
                              II&#13;
                              Ii&#13;
                                                                   Thursday, December 16, 1993&#13;
                              il&#13;
                              I:&#13;
                                                                   Washington, D.C.&#13;
                                I&#13;
&#13;
                              I,I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              !I               The meeting of the Executive Directors was convened&#13;
                              !'j&#13;
                                I&#13;
                               !&#13;
                              :1     at 10:05 a.m. in the Board Room, 1818 H Street, N.W.,&#13;
                              il 
&#13;
                              Ii&#13;
                              II Washington, D.C.,     Mr. Lewis T. Preston, Chairman, presiding. 
&#13;
                              I! 
&#13;
                              II&#13;
&#13;
                              I' 
&#13;
                              -I&#13;
&#13;
                              "
&#13;
                              i&#13;
                               I&#13;
                              !i&#13;
&#13;
                              II 
&#13;
                              II 
&#13;
                              I&#13;
                              Ii&#13;
                                I
&#13;
                              II 
&#13;
                                I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
W.,h'ngton, D.C.     200{)2&#13;
(202) ;46Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                             2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     CON TEN T S&#13;
&#13;
                              ITEM 	                                    PAGE&#13;
&#13;
                               1	      Governance:   The World Bank's&#13;
                                       Experience                          4&#13;
&#13;
                                        Mr.   de Paiva 	                   7&#13;
                                        Mr.   Syed 	                     11&#13;
                                        Mr.   Kline 	                    13,&#13;
                                        Mr.   Matambo 	                  17.&#13;
                                        Ms.   Jonsdottir 	               23.&#13;
                                        Mr.   Hutagalung 	               27-..&#13;
                                        Mr.   Kaizuka 	                  31&#13;
                                        Mr.   Benhocine 	                36&#13;
                                        Mr.   Cosgrove 	                 41&#13;
                                        Mr.   Stanton 	                  53&#13;
                                        Mr.   Gerber 	                   58&#13;
                                        Mr.   Fischer 	                  66&#13;
                                        Ms.   Cordeiro 	                 78Â·&#13;
                                        Mr.   Zhang 	                    84&#13;
                                        Mr.   Haas 	                     87.&#13;
                                        Mr.   Snoy 	                     96&#13;
                                        Mr.   O'Murchu 	                103&#13;
                                        Mr.   Torres 	                  105&#13;
                                        Mr.   Flano 	                   III&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO.. INC.&#13;
'07 C Street. N .E.&#13;
Washington, D.C.      20002&#13;
(202) WiÂ·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; run                         3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Stt""t, N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C.     20002&#13;
(202) H6-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                           4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    PRO C E E DIN G S&#13;
&#13;
                                          MR. PRESTON:   Good morning, ladies and gentlemen.&#13;
&#13;
                                          The first item this morning is "Governance:   The&#13;
&#13;
                             World Bank's Experience".&#13;
&#13;
                                          Mr. Stevens of the Operations Policy Department&#13;
&#13;
                             will introduce the subject.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Mr. Stevens.&#13;
&#13;
                                          MR. STEVENS:   Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
                                          In introducing the paper entitled "Governance:      The&#13;
&#13;
                             World Bank's Experience", I would just like to make four&#13;
&#13;
                             brief points.&#13;
&#13;
                                          The first is that the present report is not an&#13;
&#13;
                             exercise in further defining what the Bank means by&#13;
&#13;
                             governance.     That was done two years ago by the first report&#13;
&#13;
                             to the Board on governance and by the General Counsel, Mr.&#13;
&#13;
                             Shihata, in his legal memorandum of 1991.&#13;
&#13;
                                          If the definitions are repeated in this report, it&#13;
&#13;
                             is simply to provide the context in which the findings are&#13;
&#13;
                             presented.     The report's purpose is descriptive to set forth&#13;
&#13;
                             what the Bank has been doing in the area of governance for&#13;
&#13;
                             the past two years.     It is an exercise in stocktaking, not in&#13;
&#13;
                             the sense of a mechanical listing of everything that is being&#13;
&#13;
                             done, but a description of the main areas and the type of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street. N,E.&#13;
Washington, D.C, 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                        5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             work being done illustrated by a broad range of lending&#13;
&#13;
                             operations, ESW and research examples.&#13;
&#13;
                                         The second point to emphasize is that, compared&#13;
&#13;
                             with a few years back, a considerable amount of work is being&#13;
&#13;
                             done on governance in the Bank.    The nature of governance&#13;
&#13;
                             makes it hard to measure the exact volume of the work, but it&#13;
&#13;
                             is clear that it has become extensive in many countries and&#13;
&#13;
                             in all regions, in lending operations, in economic and sector&#13;
&#13;
                             work and in research.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Some of this work is substantially or entirely new&#13;
&#13;
                             areas for the Bank.     Examples are assisting governments with&#13;
&#13;
                             legal system reform, participatory approaches to the design&#13;
&#13;
                             and implementation of projects, and strengthening the&#13;
&#13;
                             fundamental accountability mechanisms of governments.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Much of the work is in mainstream areas of&#13;
&#13;
                             governance, such as public sector management, which has long&#13;
&#13;
                             been a concern of the Bank, but within these traditional&#13;
&#13;
                             areas the language changes, methodology is evolving and new&#13;
&#13;
                             approaches are being tried.&#13;
&#13;
                                         The third point I would like to make is that all of&#13;
&#13;
                             this is taking place within the mandate of the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
                             Articles.    As the report makes clear, the Bank's concern with&#13;
&#13;
                             government is exclusively with the contribution it makes to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street, RE.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                        6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             social and economic development and not with the form of&#13;
&#13;
                             political regime.&#13;
&#13;
                                       There are certainly aspects of governance such as&#13;
&#13;
                             military expenditure and the role the Bank is required to&#13;
&#13;
                             playas Chair of the Consultative Group process, which&#13;
&#13;
                             requires sensitive and careful handling in order not to&#13;
&#13;
                             overstep the boundaries of that mandate.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Overall, the economic and social domains of&#13;
&#13;
                             governance have proved to be very broad in practice.    This&#13;
&#13;
                             has provided considerable scope for staff, particularly so&#13;
&#13;
                             when goverrunents have actively sought the assistance of the&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank in analyzing governance issues, bringing to bear the&#13;
&#13;
                             experience of other countries and helping them with the&#13;
&#13;
                             design and implementation of reforms.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The final point I would like to make is a personal&#13;
&#13;
                             observation, the effect of governance work on Bank staff.&#13;
&#13;
                             While it is true that some staff still feel uncomfortable&#13;
&#13;
                             with the governance dimension, many others have seen it as an&#13;
&#13;
                             opportunity for meaningful work.   In turn, this has deepened&#13;
&#13;
                             their understanding of how goverrunents work, the proper role&#13;
&#13;
                             of the public sector, how it can be made more accountable,&#13;
&#13;
                             and how institutional strengthening can be fostered to the&#13;
&#13;
                             benefit of sustainable development.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                         7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        Taking the Bank as a whole, the work of the past&#13;
&#13;
                             two years on governance has undoubtedly broadened our&#13;
&#13;
                             understanding of the development process.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                        MR. PRESTON:    Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Four EDs have circulated their statements.    You may&#13;
&#13;
                             not have received one or two because I just got them as I&#13;
&#13;
                             came in.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Mr. de Paiva.&#13;
&#13;
                                        MR. DE PAIVA:    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                        We consider this is an interesting document, well&#13;
&#13;
                             prepared and it is a good basis for analysis of what should&#13;
&#13;
                             be the World Bank's experience in an area as complex as this&#13;
&#13;
                             area of governance.&#13;
&#13;
                                        My first observation on the document is conceptual.&#13;
&#13;
                             I still think, despite the efforts to identify clearly where&#13;
&#13;
                             the Bank should act and where the Bank should not act, it is&#13;
&#13;
                             very difficult to draw a line between the political and the&#13;
&#13;
                             economic dimensions of governance.&#13;
&#13;
                                        The document stresses one point, that is contained&#13;
&#13;
                             in the Articles of Agreement, that the Bank cannot interfere&#13;
&#13;
                             in a country's internal political affairs.     Nobody doubts&#13;
&#13;
                             that.   The question is whether speaking on some of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street, N,E,&#13;
Washington. D.C, 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                      8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             matters that are in our day-to-day analysis here, such as&#13;
&#13;
                             fiscal policy, balanced budgets, stabilization, we do not&#13;
&#13;
                             touch areas that are political in nature and naturally have a&#13;
&#13;
                             political impact.&#13;
&#13;
                                       To complicate things even further, I doubt whether&#13;
&#13;
                             we can speak of accountability, transparency of information,&#13;
&#13;
                             and the document goes as far as speaking of free press and&#13;
&#13;
                             legal framework without relating them to political aspects&#13;
&#13;
                             and without making explicit reference to the idea of democrac&#13;
&#13;
                             that is not really mentioned in the document.&#13;
&#13;
                                       A very specific point,   I noticed with great&#13;
&#13;
                             interest in Box 3 that the Private Sector Development&#13;
&#13;
                             Department is preparing a study to investigate the&#13;
&#13;
                             relationship between governance capacity and successful&#13;
&#13;
                             economic reform in a few countries.    I still doubt whether&#13;
&#13;
                             this study could be made without going deeply into the&#13;
&#13;
                             analysis of the political system of the countries that were&#13;
&#13;
                             chosen to be analyzed.&#13;
&#13;
                                       But, let me stressed at this point that we just&#13;
&#13;
                             hope that the study will be made in consultation with the&#13;
&#13;
                             countries involved.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Chapter I I of the document selects four areas in&#13;
&#13;
                             which the Bank has been concentrating.    Let me stress public&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12;  run                                                                                             9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   sector management and, in this context, the importance of&#13;
&#13;
                                   institutional-building and the work of the Bank in&#13;
&#13;
                                   institutional-building.    The lack of institutions that are&#13;
&#13;
                                   capable of responding to society's needs are in the last&#13;
&#13;
                                   analysis in the very essence of the question of development.&#13;
&#13;
                                   And, clearly, the Bank has a role to play in this area.&#13;
&#13;
                                              An important question raised by the document is in&#13;
&#13;
                                   paragraph 80, how much further the governance agenda should&#13;
&#13;
                                   be developed.   And, part of the answers are given in paragrap&#13;
&#13;
                                   81.&#13;
&#13;
                                              I have a few comments on the points raised in&#13;
&#13;
                                   paragraph 81.   First, I have doubts whether it would be&#13;
&#13;
                                   advisable to go deep into the profile of governance issues in&#13;
&#13;
                                   the CAS.   The Bank has to be very cautious on that.&#13;
&#13;
                                              I have also some doubts on the conclusion that the&#13;
&#13;
                                   new disclosure policy provides an excellent opportunity to&#13;
&#13;
                                   emphasize the issue of governance.    I think also here the&#13;
&#13;
                                   Bank should be cautious.&#13;
&#13;
                                              Besides that, I think that the document recognizes&#13;
&#13;
                                   that there are a number of aspects of the question of&#13;
&#13;
                                   governance and in the work of the Bank in governance that&#13;
&#13;
                                   need further consideration.&#13;
&#13;
                                              First, there is a question of the Bank's capacity&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C,           20002&#13;
(')1\")\   Utcr..&lt;.t::j(&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                         10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             to deal with governance.   The experience describes in the&#13;
&#13;
                             document shows that there is a huge difference among differen&#13;
&#13;
                             regions, and that those projects will have to be tailor-made,&#13;
&#13;
                             analyzed very deeply on a country-by-country basis.     This&#13;
&#13;
                             will require personnel, staff capacity and expertise.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Staff skills is a point mentioned by the document&#13;
&#13;
                             itself.   We think training is an important point, but we ask&#13;
&#13;
                             ourselves whether engaging the Bank in areas such as the&#13;
&#13;
                             judiciary and the Congress of different countries' activities,&#13;
&#13;
                             whether we have the professional skills in the Bank already&#13;
&#13;
                             prepared to do so or whether there should be radical changes&#13;
&#13;
                             in the Bank's staff if the Bank is going deeper and deeper in&#13;
&#13;
                             this matter.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Third, the type of projects that deal with&#13;
&#13;
                             governance, I tend to believe that they should be projects&#13;
&#13;
                             involving a smaller amount of money, of resources than the&#13;
&#13;
                             regular projects of the Bank! but at the same time very&#13;
&#13;
                             sophisticated expertise.&#13;
&#13;
                                        But, the most important point, I think, in the&#13;
&#13;
                             question is that the Bank has to be cautious, has to go&#13;
&#13;
                             further in close dialogue with borrower countries.&#13;
&#13;
                                        The question of governance in the last analysis&#13;
&#13;
                             involves the capacity of societies to look at themselves and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
)07 C Street. N ,E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
1202\   ~46-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; ~                                                                                            11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             change.   As we all know, Mr. Chairman, self-criticism is a&#13;
&#13;
                             characteristic of mature people.       And, to a large extent,&#13;
&#13;
                             that also happens with countries and societies.&#13;
&#13;
                                          So, that is why we think that the Bank has to be&#13;
&#13;
                             very respectful in dealing with different realities and with&#13;
&#13;
                             different countries and respecting that each country will&#13;
&#13;
                             have its own pace in dealing with the matters covered by the&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
                                          MR. PRESTON:    Thank you, Mr. de Paiva.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Mr. Syed.&#13;
&#13;
                                          MR. SYED:    Mr. Chairman, I welcome this report.        It&#13;
&#13;
                             reflects the Bank's diligent and useful work in a difficult&#13;
&#13;
                             and sensitive area.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Several of my colleagues have circulated papers on&#13;
&#13;
                             the subject.     With the short time available, I hurriedly&#13;
&#13;
                             looked through them.        I found them interesting.&#13;
&#13;
                                          The Bank's work in the several areas, which have&#13;
&#13;
                             been identified in the report, one is public sector managemen&#13;
&#13;
                             and reform.     In this area, the Bank's work has been very&#13;
&#13;
                             extensive.     There is no doubt that the idea of a smaller&#13;
&#13;
                             state, equipped with accountable bureaucracy, is gaining&#13;
&#13;
                             wider and wider acceptance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING COâ&#128;¢â&#128;¢ INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
I'M'   ~4("'~~h('&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                        12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         I am glad that the Bank recognizes need for further&#13;
&#13;
                             work within the Bank, drawing lessons from existing civil&#13;
&#13;
                             service programs.&#13;
&#13;
                                          In financial management, the Bank's advice is now&#13;
&#13;
                             being increasingly sought.       As privatization moves further&#13;
&#13;
                             momentum, there will be increasing demand.       This area needs&#13;
&#13;
                             continually important attention.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Another critical area is legal reforms, a legal&#13;
&#13;
                             system that supplies a framework for rules for the public and&#13;
&#13;
                             private sectors.     There is a crucial need for modernizing&#13;
&#13;
                             commercial laws, strengthening judicial administration and&#13;
&#13;
                             staff.    In this connection, I note the Venezuela Judicial&#13;
&#13;
                             Infrastructure Project, which has indeed been called a&#13;
&#13;
                             landmark project.     I agree.&#13;
&#13;
                                          I am glad to note that similar projects are being&#13;
&#13;
                             prepared for other countries.       I would like greater emphasis&#13;
&#13;
                             on this highly critical and important area.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Finally, Mr. Chairman, another area of great&#13;
&#13;
                             importance is participation.       It is referred to in this&#13;
&#13;
                             report.     The Bank has encouraged it.    And, I was glad to see&#13;
&#13;
                             that the Bank's strategy for sustainable development and&#13;
&#13;
                             sustainable poverty reduction includes this as one of the&#13;
&#13;
                             elements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C SUeet, N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C, 20002&#13;
121m   ~46.6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                        13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       Building channels and institutions for participatio&#13;
&#13;
                             will support all other reform efforts.     In this connection,&#13;
&#13;
                             local government, privatization of selected services and many&#13;
&#13;
                             others will have an important place.&#13;
&#13;
                                       On the whole, Mr. Chairman, I think it is a good&#13;
&#13;
                             report, and I shall look forward that in the future these&#13;
&#13;
                             reports deal with greater depth to some of the important&#13;
&#13;
                             areas which the Bank has highlighted in its strategy for&#13;
&#13;
                             development.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. PRESTON:     Thank you, Mr. Syed.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Mr. Kline.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. KLINE:     Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                       We welcome the opportunity to discuss this paper.&#13;
&#13;
                             We think it is a positive contribution to the implementation&#13;
&#13;
                             of governance issues and we thank staff for its solid work.&#13;
&#13;
                                       In particular, the paper advances the importance of&#13;
&#13;
                             our understanding of institutional and    p~rticipation   issues&#13;
&#13;
                             with respect to governance.     It is clear that the Bank has&#13;
&#13;
                             made important headway on these issues since the governance&#13;
&#13;
                             report of two years ago.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Staff should take comfort in the paper's treatment&#13;
&#13;
                             of these issues by knowing that there has been within the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                      14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank a lot of innovative work done in these areas of&#13;
&#13;
                             governance.    We would like to encourage the more uniform use&#13;
&#13;
                             of these practices throughout the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
                                         We do, however, think that there was room to send&#13;
&#13;
                             stronger signals to staff across the range of implementing&#13;
&#13;
                             governance issues, including participation, military&#13;
&#13;
                             expenditures and human rights.    We recognize that some&#13;
&#13;
                             aspects are sensitive areas, but perception and treatment of&#13;
&#13;
                             the issue has not been stagnant over the years.    It is&#13;
&#13;
                             progressing, and a modern institution has to be responsive to&#13;
&#13;
                             this.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Although the public sector management dimension of&#13;
&#13;
                             governance is highly important, too strongly focused&#13;
&#13;
                             governance problems on this risk being seen as a sheltered&#13;
&#13;
                             approach.&#13;
&#13;
                                         The crucial point for us is that experience&#13;
&#13;
                             continues to demonstrate that governance is essential to&#13;
&#13;
                             development.    We have seen this time and again, that&#13;
&#13;
                             transparency, rule of law, public participation and so on are&#13;
&#13;
                             indispensable to the success of Bank programs.    And here, we&#13;
&#13;
                             especially appreciate Mr. Flano's thoughts in this regard.&#13;
&#13;
                                         That being said, there are a number of more&#13;
&#13;
                             specific comments we would like to make on the paper.      For&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO.â&#128;¢ INC.&#13;
507 C Sueer. N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12;nm                                                                                         15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             one, the reference on page 8 concerning the strengthening of&#13;
&#13;
                             governance through shifting the boundary between the public&#13;
&#13;
                             and private sector is on the mark and deserves considerable&#13;
&#13;
                             attention.&#13;
&#13;
                                          We have had a rather lengthy experience with&#13;
&#13;
                             governance reform going back thirty years or more, and we&#13;
&#13;
                             have found that basically tinkering within a fundamentally&#13;
&#13;
                             inefficient economic government structure does not work.&#13;
&#13;
                                          In addition, at several points in the paper there&#13;
&#13;
                             is an emphasis on raising the professional competence of the&#13;
&#13;
                             public service.     This is, of course, important and, among the&#13;
&#13;
                             many challenges of development, it is probably one of the&#13;
&#13;
                             easiest being accomplished through training.&#13;
&#13;
                                          It seems as if donors are able to do this rather&#13;
&#13;
                             well and it probably requires no fundamental changes in the&#13;
&#13;
                             structure of approach.     The greater difficulty seems to be&#13;
&#13;
                             making those trained professionals responsive to their&#13;
&#13;
                             citizen clientele.     And, this is something we have been&#13;
&#13;
                             struggling with domestically.     That is, a real effort, I&#13;
&#13;
                             think, has to be made to view the citizen as the client and&#13;
&#13;
                             not someone that is to be educated, directed or modernized.&#13;
&#13;
                                          An area where we thought that the paper could be&#13;
&#13;
                             strengthened was on building local ownership of governance&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                          16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               reform.     Helping to develop advocacy groups and public&#13;
&#13;
                               information groups might be possible approaches in this area.&#13;
&#13;
                                            There is also a link between governance reform and&#13;
&#13;
                               structural reform in the economy that needs to be kept in&#13;
&#13;
                               mind.     Those who would benefit most from economic reform are&#13;
&#13;
                               often disorganized, disadvantaged by distorted market forces,&#13;
&#13;
                               excluded from power and, in consequence, not in a position to&#13;
&#13;
                               support the reforms.&#13;
&#13;
                                            We also want to emphasize the point made in the&#13;
&#13;
                               paper in paragraph 60 that military spending, when at high&#13;
&#13;
                               levels, has direct relevance to economic development&#13;
&#13;
                               prospects.     Recognizing this, we think that there are&#13;
&#13;
                               difficult issues involved and judgments, but this is not&#13;
&#13;
                               always the case.     We would like to encourage more work in&#13;
&#13;
                               this area, particularly for the Bank to assist in whatever&#13;
&#13;
                               way possible when called upon by the borrower to do so.&#13;
&#13;
                                            In addition, the paper appropriately points out the&#13;
&#13;
                               scope for pursuing a governance approach to military spending.&#13;
&#13;
                               To that we would add the collection of more reliable data on&#13;
&#13;
                               military spending and assistance for demobilization efforts.&#13;
&#13;
                                            With respect to donor coordination, we note that&#13;
&#13;
                               the paper suggests the importance of CG meetings and providin&#13;
&#13;
                               a context and incentive for policy dialogue on governance&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C.       20002&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                     17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            issues with the countries in question.     We believe that there&#13;
&#13;
                            is room here to structure more interaction among the donors&#13;
&#13;
                            and the international financial institutions on this issue,&#13;
&#13;
                            perhaps under a separate arrangement.&#13;
&#13;
                                        In sum, we welcome the Bank's continued efforts to&#13;
&#13;
                            respond to governance problems and the fact that they are&#13;
&#13;
                            well-documented in this paper.     We would like to encourage&#13;
&#13;
                            staff and managers to take a proactive stance and more&#13;
&#13;
                            systematically explore the boundaries of addressing these&#13;
&#13;
                            problems.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
                                        MR. PRESTON:   Thank you, Mr. Kline.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Mr. Matambo.&#13;
&#13;
                                        MR. MATAMBO:   Thank you very much, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Mr. Chairman, the past two years have indeed been&#13;
&#13;
                            marked by a substantial progress in the way the Bank has&#13;
&#13;
                            approached the subject of governance both in its relationship&#13;
&#13;
                            with its borrowers and in developing its own internal&#13;
&#13;
                            structures and procedures for dealing with the subject of&#13;
&#13;
                            governance.&#13;
&#13;
                                        I, therefore, welcome a discussion of this report,&#13;
&#13;
                            and wish to commend both management and the authors for a&#13;
&#13;
                            well-written and comprehensive review of the activities in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO" INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
WashingWfl, D.C. 20002&#13;
/2(2) 'i4&amp;M6n&#13;
&amp;#12;nm                                                                                          18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             this area.&#13;
&#13;
                                          I wish to note at the outset that most of the&#13;
&#13;
                             concerns that we expressed at the first meeting on the&#13;
&#13;
                             subject two years ago have largely been discussed and, in&#13;
&#13;
                             some cases, fully addressed in the present paper.     In this&#13;
&#13;
                             connection, we think that Chapter II has done a commendable&#13;
&#13;
                             job of reviewing the Bank's experience during the past two&#13;
&#13;
                             years vis-a-vis the four dimensions of governance identified&#13;
&#13;
                             for Bank purposes in the 1991 report, i.e. public sector&#13;
&#13;
                             management, accountability, legal framework and transparency&#13;
&#13;
                             and information.&#13;
&#13;
                                          In particular, the section of Emerging Lessons at&#13;
&#13;
                             the end of the chapter should be useful in guiding the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
                             future activities and in shaping the institution's thinking&#13;
&#13;
                             in this area.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Mr. Chairman, we think that Chapter III is also&#13;
&#13;
                             useful, as it discusses issues that arise in relation to Bank&#13;
&#13;
                             activities.     However, the chapter extends its discussion into&#13;
&#13;
                             controversial areas which are sensitive and could easily be&#13;
&#13;
                             argued to be outside the Bank's mandate, as prescribed by the&#13;
&#13;
                             Articles of Agreement or as defined in the 1991 paper on&#13;
&#13;
                             governance.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Indeed, some of these aspects of governance are&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Wa5hington. D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                     19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             still so sensitive in some developing countries that it is&#13;
&#13;
                             important for the Bank to adopt a measured approach in&#13;
&#13;
                             addressing them.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Of note are those relating to military expenditures&#13;
&#13;
                             and human rights, especially the latter, both of which are&#13;
&#13;
                             usually perceived to be non-economic in nature and, therefore,&#13;
&#13;
                             better handled by other organizations with the mandate to do&#13;
&#13;
                             so.&#13;
&#13;
                                         The report, however, and we congratulate the&#13;
&#13;
                             authors on this, presents cogent arguments for including&#13;
&#13;
                             these two issues in the Bank's dialogue with the borrowers.&#13;
&#13;
                             Now, whether the dialogue on these issues succeeds or not&#13;
&#13;
                             will, in our view, depend on how and who conducts the&#13;
&#13;
                             dialogue.    In this connection, we would like to repeat the&#13;
&#13;
                             point made by this Chair two years ago that, as much as&#13;
&#13;
                             possible, dialogue with authorities in borrowing countries on&#13;
&#13;
                             these sensitive issues should be undertaken by senior Bank&#13;
&#13;
                             staff who have the tact, the experience and necessary skills&#13;
&#13;
                             to separate the economic and social dimensions of governance&#13;
&#13;
                             from their obvious political and national security aspects.&#13;
&#13;
                                         In some cases, Mr. Chairman, as in the case of CG&#13;
&#13;
                             meetings, the Bank's leadership role may require it to&#13;
&#13;
                             discuss such non-economic issues.    We appreciate this.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street, N,E,&#13;
Washington. D,C. 20002&#13;
f?M\   ~d(,_h(,r;r;&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                     20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      However, where it is not necessarily required to&#13;
&#13;
                            discuss them, we would urge the Bank to leave it to bilateral&#13;
&#13;
                            and other organizations to raise these issues with the&#13;
&#13;
                            governments.&#13;
&#13;
                                      Mr. Chairman, we find Chapter IV on Findings and&#13;
&#13;
                            Future Directions to be a useful indication of the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
                            future activities in this area.&#13;
&#13;
                                      While the chapter covers several areas of activity,&#13;
&#13;
                            we would like to comment on only four of these.&#13;
&#13;
                                       First, public sector management and civil service&#13;
&#13;
                            reform:   These are likely to remain at the forefront of the&#13;
&#13;
                            reform process and as key issues in the promotion of&#13;
&#13;
                            development effectiveness and in policy dialogue with&#13;
&#13;
                            borrowing countries.   Indeed, we encourage the Bank to&#13;
&#13;
                            continue with these problems in these areas.&#13;
&#13;
                                       However, we wish to emphasize that as much as&#13;
&#13;
                            possible programs intended to enhance capacity in borrowing&#13;
&#13;
                            countries should be given the highest priority possible.&#13;
&#13;
                            Additionally, safety nets and targeting issues should be&#13;
&#13;
                            further refined so that they reach those segments of the&#13;
&#13;
                            population for whom they are intended.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Second, state enterprise reform and private sector&#13;
&#13;
                            development:   We agree that the results of the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORnNG CO., INC.&#13;
'07 C Street. N .E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
(2D2) ~46-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                         21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             experience in these two areas have not been uniform and in&#13;
&#13;
                             some cases have been disappointing.   In Sub-Saharan Africa,&#13;
&#13;
                             in particular, the process has been slow, although it is now&#13;
&#13;
                             beginning to show some results.&#13;
&#13;
                                       We encourage the Bank to continue with its programs&#13;
&#13;
                             in these two areas.   However, Mr. Chairman, given the&#13;
&#13;
                             difficulties associated with parastatal reforms and the small&#13;
&#13;
                             size of the private sector in many developing countries, we&#13;
&#13;
                             think that the level of public sector involvement in economic&#13;
&#13;
                             activities should be dictated by the conditions prevailing in&#13;
&#13;
                             each individual country.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Now, this position, Mr. Chairman, should not be&#13;
&#13;
                             misconstrued to mean that we advocate a large role for the&#13;
&#13;
                             public sector, far from it.   On the contrary, we completely&#13;
&#13;
                             agree that the private sector should play an important role&#13;
&#13;
                             in economic development, but that the downsizing of the&#13;
&#13;
                             public sector should not be undertaken in a proforma fashion&#13;
&#13;
                             without taking the individual country's   ~nique   conditions'&#13;
&#13;
                             into consideration.   That is the point we are making.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Third, Mr. Chairman, on decentralization:      The&#13;
&#13;
                             report rightly notes the changing attitudes about the role of&#13;
&#13;
                             central governments in developing countries in favor of&#13;
&#13;
                             decentralized structures and strengthened local governance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C.     20002&#13;
1202\   ~46Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                     22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             We agree that the Bank should play an important role in this&#13;
&#13;
                             area through such activities as capacity-building and&#13;
&#13;
                             assisting governments to define the relationship between&#13;
&#13;
                             local and central governments.&#13;
&#13;
                                       However, as I always say, while we endorse&#13;
&#13;
                             decentralization in principle, Mr. Chairman, we would hasten&#13;
&#13;
                             to advise that the Bank should not commit itself with such a&#13;
&#13;
                             major undertaking unilaterally, but should seek the&#13;
&#13;
                             cooperation and involvement of other institutions and&#13;
&#13;
                             particularly bilaterals who may have some experience in the&#13;
&#13;
                             field.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Finally, Mr. Chairman, on popular participation:&#13;
&#13;
                             Obviously, this is an important element of good governance.&#13;
&#13;
                             However, although the principle is acceptable to our&#13;
&#13;
                             countries, we believe that the modalities for promoting it&#13;
&#13;
                             should be developed by the borrowing countries themselves,&#13;
&#13;
                             modalities whose characteristics are shaped by each country's&#13;
&#13;
                             unique circumstances.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The application of these, I dare to say, home-grown&#13;
&#13;
                             modalities would, in our view, go a long way to strengthening&#13;
&#13;
                             the local ownership of development and/or reform programs.&#13;
&#13;
                                       In other words, Mr. Chairman, we consider it&#13;
&#13;
                             appropriate that the Bank should discuss these issues with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Screet. N.E.&#13;
W...,hington, D.C. 20002&#13;
1701\   ~4';.r;('M&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                      23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             authorities of the borrowing countries.     However, we think it&#13;
&#13;
                             would be counterproductive if the Bank staff were to discuss&#13;
&#13;
                             these issues of popular participation outside official&#13;
&#13;
                             sectors.   That is to say, it would be inappropriate in our&#13;
&#13;
                             view for Bank staff to attempt to discuss directly with&#13;
&#13;
                             different sections of the population, be it in towns,&#13;
&#13;
                             villages or districts, unless invited by the official&#13;
&#13;
                             authorities to do so.     That is the point we are making here.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Mr. Chairman, in closing, I wish once again to&#13;
&#13;
                             commend the Bank management for the progress made during the&#13;
&#13;
                             last two years both in their dialogue with borrowing countrie&#13;
&#13;
                             and in refining some governance aspects of the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
                             internal processes.&#13;
&#13;
                                        I would suggest that another progress report in&#13;
&#13;
                             another two years could be produced, following which I hope&#13;
&#13;
                             governance issues would have been fully incorporated into&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank processes and progress reports would then become&#13;
&#13;
                             unnecessary.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Thank you very much, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                        MR. PRESTON:    Thank you, Mr. Matambo.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Ms. Jonsdottir.&#13;
&#13;
                                        MS. JONSDOTTIR:    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                        I join the previous speakers in commending this&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                      24&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             report.   It is comprehensive, well written and systematic in&#13;
&#13;
                             its approach to the Bank's experience since the last Board&#13;
&#13;
                             discussion, which was much more steeped in the principles of&#13;
&#13;
                             the Bank's governance mandate.&#13;
&#13;
                                       On the previously circulated statements of Mrs.&#13;
&#13;
                             Herfkens, Mr. Le Bouder and Mr. Flano, I find that I can&#13;
&#13;
                             generally associate myself with all of them.   It is, in fact,&#13;
&#13;
                             heartening to see the relative consensus on the definitions&#13;
&#13;
                             and importance of the core governance concepts in the&#13;
&#13;
                             development process.&#13;
&#13;
                                       We are beyond the basic arguments on basic&#13;
&#13;
                             principles, though there is still room for healthy debate on&#13;
&#13;
                             the edge of the Bank's mandate.&#13;
&#13;
                                        There should also be room for discussing the&#13;
&#13;
                             relative weight and interpretation given to the governance&#13;
&#13;
                             dimensions within the Bank's mandate.   Here, I wish to&#13;
&#13;
                             comment on the following.&#13;
&#13;
                                        I agree that public sector management is probably&#13;
&#13;
                             the most tangible and quantifiable governance dimension in&#13;
&#13;
                             the Bank's work.   I also agree with the points made in Mrs.&#13;
&#13;
                             Herfkens' statement on this issue, and can strongly support&#13;
&#13;
                             the specific views of caution on civil service reform&#13;
&#13;
                             expressed by Mr. Le Bouder and Mr. Plano.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Ma.LER REPORTING CO.â&#128;¢ INC.&#13;
~07   C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                       25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          The sections on accountability, transparency and&#13;
&#13;
                             legal framework are valuable and interesting as core concepts&#13;
&#13;
                             of governance.     Though often of a more qualitative nature,&#13;
&#13;
                             there is much work left to be done in these areas.     This&#13;
&#13;
                             should also be reflected in the future use of country&#13;
&#13;
                             assistance strategies, portfolio performance reviews and&#13;
&#13;
                             operational policies and procedures.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Box 19 amply illustrates this necessity, especially&#13;
&#13;
                             for governance dimensions beyond the PSM context.&#13;
&#13;
                                          On the legal framework issue, I find not least the&#13;
&#13;
                             question of legal reform in transition economies to be&#13;
&#13;
                             important.     This is well highlighted in Box 14 with valuable&#13;
&#13;
                             emerging lessons described in paragraph 28.&#13;
&#13;
                                          As for the value of the section on participatory&#13;
&#13;
                             development, I again agree with Mrs. Herfkens' observations.&#13;
&#13;
                             This aspect is so important and so intrinsic to governance&#13;
&#13;
                             that I would have liked to see participation or governance as&#13;
&#13;
                             seen from below to be addressed as a core dimension also&#13;
&#13;
                             rather than an issue arising in relation to Bank governance&#13;
&#13;
                             activities.&#13;
&#13;
                                          The two sections on military expenditure and human&#13;
&#13;
                             rights both have an appropriate place in the report.&#13;
&#13;
                             Especially the first offers some important insight and new&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N .E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                           26&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 possibilities.     There is considerable room for the Bank&#13;
&#13;
                                 within its mandate to be more assertive at the appropriate&#13;
&#13;
                                 level in its dialogue with beneficiary countries.&#13;
&#13;
                                              There is no doubt that excessive military&#13;
&#13;
                                 expenditure detracts from the possibilities for developmental&#13;
&#13;
                                 investments.     Also, public sector reviews can help underline&#13;
&#13;
                                 this path.&#13;
&#13;
                                              We find the report's own recommendations useful.&#13;
&#13;
                                 In practice, it seems there is still much to be done within&#13;
&#13;
                                 the boundaries of the Bank's own mandate, boundaries which&#13;
&#13;
                                 have not even been fully explored yet.     We endorse the&#13;
&#13;
                                 report's paragraphs 72, 74 and 80, pointing to the need for&#13;
&#13;
                                 deepening work on the aspects of especially accountability&#13;
&#13;
                                 and transparency, as well as the issue of participation.&#13;
&#13;
                                              Also important are the issues addressed in&#13;
&#13;
                                 paragraphs 81 and 82 relating to systematizing and deepening&#13;
&#13;
                                 understanding of governance throughout the Bank with clear&#13;
&#13;
                                 condoning signals from the side of top management.&#13;
&#13;
                                              One regret, which I share with Mrs. Herfkens' who&#13;
&#13;
                                 points out that the Bank is not acting in splendid isolation.&#13;
&#13;
                                 The report is surprisingly devoid of reference to&#13;
&#13;
                                 collaboration with and experience of other governmental and&#13;
&#13;
                                 non-governmental agencies, a void which is quite unlike many&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
107 C Screet. N .E.&#13;
Washington, D,C.         20002&#13;
11n')\   '\.d~_h:N'1,h&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                       27&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             other thematic policy reports of the Bank.      In this context r&#13;
&#13;
                             what are the prospects for further developing work with such&#13;
&#13;
                             agencies?&#13;
&#13;
                                         And finallYr two more questions.   The skills mix&#13;
&#13;
                             question is one raised by several others.      Can any figures be&#13;
&#13;
                             put to the report's recommendations as far as new recruitment&#13;
&#13;
                             and professional categories are concerned?     And r the question&#13;
&#13;
                             of publishing.    The value of this report to a broader&#13;
&#13;
                             audience would seem evident if perhaps in a slightly edited&#13;
&#13;
                             version.    I would like to know whether such publication is&#13;
&#13;
                             being considered.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Thank your Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                         MR. PRESTON:   Thank your Ms. Jonsdottir.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Mr. Hutagalung.&#13;
&#13;
                                         MR. HUTAGALUNG:   Thank your Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                         First of allr I like others would like to commend&#13;
&#13;
                             the staff for the very comprehensive report before us today.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Governance is a delicate and sensitive subject for&#13;
&#13;
                             the Bank.    The Bank should at all times be aware of the risk&#13;
&#13;
                             of being considered as interfering in the internal politics&#13;
&#13;
                             of the borrowing countries r if it is perceived to be stepping&#13;
&#13;
                             beyond the mandate stipulated in the Articles of Agreement.&#13;
&#13;
                                         In this connection, we would like to take note of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
1101\   ~4~.('('('h&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                      28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             the very clear analysis and guidance on the issue of&#13;
&#13;
                             governance cited in the 1991 legal memorandum of the Vice&#13;
&#13;
                             President and General Counsel.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The consistent observance of the mandate by the&#13;
&#13;
                             staff is very important, bearing in mind the report's&#13;
&#13;
                             conclusion that within the framework of the Articles there is&#13;
&#13;
                             likely to be continued scope for substantial governance work&#13;
&#13;
                             in the future years.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The Bank, in our opinion, has been quite successful&#13;
&#13;
                             in the past to strike the delicate balance between aspects of&#13;
&#13;
                             governance that the Bank is required to do and those that&#13;
&#13;
                             fall beyond its mandate.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Having said that, Mr. Chairman, we would like to&#13;
&#13;
                             make a few comments regarding some specific issues as follows.&#13;
&#13;
                                       We fully agree with the report's conclusion that in&#13;
&#13;
                             the future the bulk of the Bank's governance will continue to&#13;
&#13;
                             be in the area of public sector management.   We think that,&#13;
&#13;
                             given the available resources and expertise of the Bank and&#13;
&#13;
                             taking into account the needs of the majority of the borrowin&#13;
&#13;
                             countries, public sector management is the area where the&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank can contribute most effectively.&#13;
&#13;
                                       We believe that to be productive, Bank's advice as&#13;
&#13;
                             well as financial support to public sector management must be.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07        C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
(")1"1'"    ~dICt:N&lt;t:&#13;
&amp;#12; ~                                                                                       29&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             tailored to the particular circumstances of each country.        A&#13;
&#13;
                             lot still has to be learned by the Bank on the many aspects&#13;
&#13;
                             of public sector management.     It is also difficult to apply a&#13;
&#13;
                             uniform approach to the different aspects related to the&#13;
&#13;
                             public sector management to borrowing member countries.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Second, the report stresses the importance of&#13;
&#13;
                             decentralization as one of the principal ways to strengthen&#13;
&#13;
                             accountability.   The Bank must move very cautiously in this&#13;
&#13;
                             area because for some borrowing member countries it may touch&#13;
&#13;
                             sensitive issues beyond the traditional economic dimension of&#13;
&#13;
                             governance.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Nevertheless, we fully agree that the nature and&#13;
&#13;
                             quality of the relationship between central and local&#13;
&#13;
                             agencies will have very important bearings on the ability of&#13;
&#13;
                             central   gover~ents   to manage the development process.   It&#13;
&#13;
                             should be interesting in this regard to read the final draft&#13;
&#13;
                             of the report on Municipal Development Sector Review, which,&#13;
&#13;
                             as mentioned in paragraph 17, is now under preparation.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Third, related to the above, one particular lesson&#13;
&#13;
                             that emerged from the experience of the Bank so far is the&#13;
&#13;
                             confirmation of the importance of establishing accountability&#13;
&#13;
                             in local processes and institutions.     These findings should&#13;
&#13;
                             guide the Bank in the design of Bank's activities in each&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Sueet, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
1202\   ~46Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                       30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              borrowing member country.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Four, on the legal framework for development, it is&#13;
&#13;
                              important for the Bank staff to proceed with caution when&#13;
&#13;
                              providing assistance in the drafting of any individual law.&#13;
&#13;
                              Any law or regulations should be rooted in the socio-economic&#13;
&#13;
                              realities of the country and the Bank should try to avoid the&#13;
&#13;
                              emergence of perception by the general public of interfering&#13;
&#13;
                              in the internal politics of the country.&#13;
&#13;
                                        We, therefore, strongly endorse the conclusion in&#13;
&#13;
                              the report that the Bank has to recognize and respect the&#13;
&#13;
                              exclusive jurisdictions and responsibility of each country&#13;
&#13;
                              over its own legal and institutional framework.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Fifth, procurement is no doubt one of the most&#13;
&#13;
                              important aspects of governance under the heading of&#13;
&#13;
                              transparency and information in the Bank's relationship with&#13;
&#13;
                              the borrowing member countries.   Transparency through the&#13;
&#13;
                              provision of information to the interested parties in the&#13;
&#13;
                              procurement will enhance the efficiency in the use of the&#13;
&#13;
                              Bank's financial assistance.   We encourage the Bank to&#13;
&#13;
                              strengthen an effective cooperation with all borrowing&#13;
&#13;
                              countries in this field.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Sixth, on military expenditures, we understand the&#13;
&#13;
                              Bank's interest on this sensitive issue.   To be effective,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO" INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D. C.    2000 2&#13;
(202)   ~46-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                       31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              however, the Bank has to avoid double standards in the&#13;
&#13;
                              treatment of member countries in its dialogue with them,&#13;
&#13;
                              especially when a direct relationship between military&#13;
&#13;
                              expenditures and economic growth is difficult to establish.&#13;
&#13;
                                        To conclude, Mr. Chairman, the Bank should&#13;
&#13;
                              continuously improve the efficiency and effectiveness in the&#13;
&#13;
                              delivery of its assistance for the reduction of poverty in&#13;
&#13;
                              member countries.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Poverty reduction strategy embodies the Bank's most&#13;
&#13;
                              important contribution to the promotion of human rights in&#13;
&#13;
                              borrowing countries.     The present Bank's policy on poverty&#13;
&#13;
                              reduction should invest in human resources and the provision&#13;
&#13;
                              of basic social services to the poor and, most importantly,&#13;
&#13;
                              the creation of job opportunities for the poor should be&#13;
&#13;
                              continuously strengthened.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                        MR. PRESTON:     Thank you, Mr. Hutagalung.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Mr. Kaizuka.&#13;
&#13;
                                        MR. KAIZUKA:     Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Like other previous speakers, I welcome the&#13;
&#13;
                              management's high quality paper on the table.     This is a very&#13;
&#13;
                              comprehensive and well-rounded paper which provides us many&#13;
&#13;
                              experiences accumulated after we discussed the governance&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N .E.&#13;
Washington, D.C.      20002&#13;
1202\   ~46-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                        32&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             dimension paper in 1991.&#13;
&#13;
                                          It is also to be noted that the paper challenges to&#13;
&#13;
                             address sensitive issues like military expenditure and human&#13;
&#13;
                             rights in a very practical manner.&#13;
&#13;
                                          The discussion on the governance is a timely one&#13;
&#13;
                             since the development effectiveness has become an area of&#13;
&#13;
                             keen interest of many donor countries, including my country,&#13;
&#13;
                             reflecting the budgetary constraint getting severe and&#13;
&#13;
                             severe, and it has been shared among the international&#13;
&#13;
                             community that without good governance assistance to the&#13;
&#13;
                             developing countries could not be used as originally planned&#13;
&#13;
                             and aimed.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Many donor countries list good governance as a&#13;
&#13;
                             priority criteria in deciding their aid flow to particular&#13;
&#13;
                             countries.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Now, I come to the substance of the paper.   First,&#13;
&#13;
                             public sector management:     I fully agree with Mrs. Herfkens'&#13;
&#13;
                             views on public sector management, which emphasizes that&#13;
&#13;
                             public sector management and private sector development&#13;
&#13;
                             should not be seen as deferring to the one and the other, but&#13;
&#13;
                             as intertwined and equally necessary.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Since successful public sector management would&#13;
&#13;
                             provide an environment in which private sector development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
)07 C Sueet, N,E,&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
1'02\   ~46.6(&gt;il1i&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                      33&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             could be proceeded smoothly, to my opinion private sector&#13;
&#13;
                             development could not succeed without improvement in public&#13;
&#13;
                             sector management.    From a sequential prospect, I think&#13;
&#13;
                             public sector management in certain sectors could provide a&#13;
&#13;
                             good basis for a certain enterprise in this particular sector&#13;
&#13;
                             to be privatized.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Furthermore, I would like to emphasize that ideal&#13;
&#13;
                             balance of public sector management and private sector&#13;
&#13;
                             development should vary from country to country, depending&#13;
&#13;
                             upon its development stage and social and historical&#13;
&#13;
                             background.   I   believe in a certain stage of the development&#13;
&#13;
                             public sector management should be more weighted, so that it&#13;
&#13;
                             could guide the private sector which would not yet be matured&#13;
&#13;
                             and tend to be tracked easily in market failure, since it is&#13;
&#13;
                             commonly shared that private sector development is a rather&#13;
&#13;
                             long-term process.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Secondly, on decentralization, the paper underscore&#13;
&#13;
                             the importance of decentralization and strengthening the&#13;
&#13;
                             local government from the viewpoint of accountability.      Of&#13;
&#13;
                             course, it is reasonable in an advanced stage of development&#13;
&#13;
                             that certain authorities are transferred to local government'&#13;
&#13;
                             hands.&#13;
&#13;
                                       However, we should have a balanced approach which&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
107 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C.     20002&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                      34&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             respects the role of the central government while proceeding&#13;
&#13;
                             with decentralization.    We should be mindful that basic&#13;
&#13;
                             macroeconomic policies should be in the central government/s&#13;
&#13;
                             hands, otherwise the fiscal and monetary policies should not&#13;
&#13;
                             be implemented consistently and thus the macroeconomic policy&#13;
&#13;
                             could not work effectively.&#13;
&#13;
                                       If capable and trained human resources are limited&#13;
&#13;
                             in numbers, those resources should be concentrated to the&#13;
&#13;
                             central government for the time being in order to maintain&#13;
&#13;
                             the unity of a country which is a basis for the economic&#13;
&#13;
                             activities of the country.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Thirdly, I will touch upon the two sensitive issues&#13;
&#13;
                                human rights and military expenditures.    My basic position&#13;
&#13;
                             is, as articulated in the paper, that the Bank's work should&#13;
&#13;
                             concentrate on the economic and social dimension of&#13;
&#13;
                             governance.   However, it is becoming extremely difficult to&#13;
&#13;
                             draw a clear line between economic and political dimensions,&#13;
&#13;
                             since both of them are countries' activities and interrelated&#13;
&#13;
                             in a very complex manner.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Having said so, I will be specific on two issues.&#13;
&#13;
                             First, human rights:     I believe that human rights' issues&#13;
&#13;
                             have several aspects.    What is important here is that&#13;
&#13;
                             absolute poverty itself is a serious human rights' issue.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
S07 C Stroet, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C.     20002&#13;
(202)   ~6Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12;run                                                                                        35&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            Thus, to my opinion, the Bank's approach to the issue of&#13;
&#13;
                            human rights should be limited for the purpose of poverty&#13;
&#13;
                            alleviation.     In this sense, I can go along with the&#13;
&#13;
                            indication of the paper.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Secondly, on military expenditure:   I understand&#13;
&#13;
                            that the level of military expenditure in most cases is&#13;
&#13;
                            decided upon due to the country's relations with its neighbor&#13;
&#13;
                            and the level of military expenditure in its neighboring&#13;
&#13;
                            countries.     Thus, direct intervention to the issue is to be&#13;
&#13;
                            too much politicized and that may be out of the mandate of&#13;
&#13;
                            the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
                                         However, while military expenditure itself is a&#13;
&#13;
                            political issue, the fact of crowding out of the other&#13;
&#13;
                            productive expenditures is an economic issue.      Thus, I would&#13;
&#13;
                            endorse the Bank's approach to address the crowding out&#13;
&#13;
                            issues in its public expenditure review and policy dialogue&#13;
&#13;
                            with the recipient countries.&#13;
&#13;
                                         I think that the Fund is also initiating the study&#13;
&#13;
                            or discussion on military expenditure and the paper indicates&#13;
&#13;
                            the existence of a close collaboration between the Bank and&#13;
&#13;
                            Fund on these issues.     I would welcome the management's&#13;
&#13;
                            explanation on this collaboration.&#13;
&#13;
                                         On the conversion of the defense industry, I also&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MLLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
(202) 546Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                         36&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             support the management approach to address this issue in a&#13;
&#13;
                             broader framework of overall industrial restructuring.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
                                          MR. PRESTON:     Thank you, Mr. Kaizuka.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Mr. Benhocine.&#13;
&#13;
                                          MR. BENHOCINE:     Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Mr. Chairman, this review of the Bank's experience&#13;
&#13;
                             in the field of governance is most welcomed, and I would like&#13;
&#13;
                             to commend the staff and management for the good report&#13;
&#13;
                             before us.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Good governance is among the most fundamental&#13;
&#13;
                             factors conducive to the promotion of both sustainable&#13;
&#13;
                             development and a greater justice.        Bank's activities in this&#13;
&#13;
                             field are already impressive and they should indeed be&#13;
&#13;
                             developed further.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Let me start, Mr. Chairman, by a few general&#13;
&#13;
                             comments before addressing briefly some specific issues.           My&#13;
&#13;
                             first comment is that the report to a large extent is putting&#13;
&#13;
                             to rest some apprehensions expressed by this Chair in July&#13;
&#13;
                             1991 when the first comprehensive paper on government was&#13;
&#13;
                             discussed by this Board.        Our warning at that time was the&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank should not be carried away and enter a field, namely the&#13;
&#13;
                             political field, which clearly is not within its mandate and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C StreÂ¢t. N.E.&#13;
Washingroo. D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12;nm                                                                                       37&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             where it has by no means any so-called comparative advantage.&#13;
&#13;
                                        The present report shows all through the acute&#13;
&#13;
                             consciousness of the Bank not to enter this field.   This&#13;
&#13;
                             attitude, Mr. Chairman, is very much welcomed, not only&#13;
&#13;
                             because it would simply not be right for the institution to&#13;
&#13;
                             go beyond its mandate but also because it will only boost the&#13;
&#13;
                             borrowing country's confidence in Bank action, and has the&#13;
&#13;
                             efficiency of Bank action.&#13;
&#13;
                                        This leads me to my second general comment,&#13;
&#13;
                             confident relations between the Bank and its borrowing&#13;
&#13;
                             members.   A genuine and confident dialogue, supported by good&#13;
&#13;
                             economic and sector work, is by itself the most powerful&#13;
&#13;
                             instrument to promote good governance, more powerful, in my&#13;
&#13;
                             view, and more significant than any single loan or set of&#13;
&#13;
                             loans loaded with conditionality.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Hence, Mr. Chairman, this institution should always&#13;
&#13;
                             be alert not to carry out or to be suspected of carrying out&#13;
&#13;
                             any other agenda but its own.&#13;
&#13;
                                        The third general comment relates to the perception&#13;
&#13;
                             clearly and rightly, in my view, expressed in the report that&#13;
&#13;
                             there is no blueprint approach to the issue of governance.&#13;
&#13;
                             Situations indeed vary between and within regions, and a&#13;
&#13;
                             country focus accompanied with great sensitivity to the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C.     20002&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                      38&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             cultural values and tradition of each country is indeed most&#13;
&#13;
                             needed.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Let me now go briefly to some specific comments.&#13;
&#13;
                             Like Mrs. Herfkens, I do believe that the role of the public&#13;
&#13;
                             sector will remain for a long time in developing countries&#13;
&#13;
                             the main engine or for that matter the main hurdle for the&#13;
&#13;
                             promotion of sustainable development.   I am glad that this&#13;
&#13;
                             report does justice to this notion.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The Bank should continue to step up its operations&#13;
&#13;
                             and its research in this field.   In this connection, I&#13;
&#13;
                             welcome the study made by the Africa Region relating to the&#13;
&#13;
                             civil service reform in Sub-Saharan Africa.   Reforming&#13;
&#13;
                             government, making the civil service more able to respond to&#13;
&#13;
                             the needs of the country and more efficient is one of the&#13;
&#13;
                             most difficult challenges facing many of our countries.&#13;
&#13;
                                       That is why I do totally agree with the report that&#13;
&#13;
                             there is a need for further work within the Bank, drawing&#13;
&#13;
                             lessons from existing service reform programs and for&#13;
&#13;
                             developing new approaches.   And, we are looking forward to&#13;
&#13;
                             seeing soon some specific papers on this subject.&#13;
&#13;
                                       On accountability, decentralization and particularl&#13;
&#13;
                             on the participatory development, here also I can only agree&#13;
&#13;
                             with Mrs. Herfkens and express my satisfaction that the Bank&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N .E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12;run                                                                                       39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             increasingly recognizes the value of the participatory&#13;
&#13;
                             approach and grassroots development project, as illustrated&#13;
&#13;
                             by Box 13 on Matruh Natural Resources Management Project.&#13;
&#13;
                                        I would be more cautious on the decentralization.&#13;
&#13;
                             While I agree that decentralization is by itself a powerful&#13;
&#13;
                             means to improving governance, the purpose would be defeated&#13;
&#13;
                             if significant decentralization is not preceded by means to&#13;
&#13;
                             improve the management capacity at the local level, where it&#13;
&#13;
                             is usually weaker than at the central level.&#13;
&#13;
                                        The same goes for the legal framework.     Passing new&#13;
&#13;
                             laws would be useless if not accompanied by the development&#13;
&#13;
                             and/or the creation of an institution that will enforce these&#13;
&#13;
                             laws.   While recognizing the sensitivity of the issue, I&#13;
&#13;
                             would nevertheless encourage the Bank to help countries that&#13;
&#13;
                             so request to strengthen the judiciary and regulatory&#13;
&#13;
                             institutions.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Let me now address the issue of military&#13;
&#13;
                             expenditure.    We have had an interesting discussion on the&#13;
&#13;
                             subject two years ago.    We addressed the so-called peace&#13;
&#13;
                             dividend, that has not been forthcoming.    We discussed the&#13;
&#13;
                             role and responsibilities of the arms' producing countries.&#13;
&#13;
                             And, last but not least, many of us recognized that most of&#13;
&#13;
                             the time it is easier to get credit for armaments than for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORnNG CO., INC.&#13;
)07 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C.     20002&#13;
(202) H6Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                      40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             development.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I am not going to dwell on this, but I submit, Mr.&#13;
&#13;
                             Chairman, that pressures put on the Bank by donor countries&#13;
&#13;
                             to include military expenditure in its dialogue with IDA&#13;
&#13;
                             countries seems to me somewhat unfair.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Let me reiterate here that the Bank should resist&#13;
&#13;
                             the temptation of imposing its views on the subject, as it is&#13;
&#13;
                             not qualified to determine what should be the right level of&#13;
&#13;
                             defense expenditure for a given country because it cannot&#13;
&#13;
                             analyze for each country the underlying causes of conflict.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Hence, Bank activity in this field should be&#13;
&#13;
                             limited to countries that specifically request Bank's help.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Respect for human rights, Mr. Chairman, is with no&#13;
&#13;
                             doubt the keystone for good governance.     But, I agree totally&#13;
&#13;
                             with the present stand of the Bank, limiting itself to&#13;
&#13;
                             promoting those rights which are economic and social in&#13;
&#13;
                             nature.   The Bank should indeed not try to tackle more&#13;
&#13;
                             political issues that are, by the way, systematically and&#13;
&#13;
                             thoroughly debated in other international fora and in this&#13;
&#13;
                             case namely the Human Commission for Human Rights.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                        MR. PRESTON:    Thank you, Mr. Benhocine.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Mr. Cosgrove.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
)07 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
(202)   ~46-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                     41&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. COSGROVE:    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I agree with my colleagues that this is an importan&#13;
&#13;
                             and a good paper.   It spells out clearly the significance of&#13;
&#13;
                             governance issues in achieving sustained development, as well&#13;
&#13;
                             as the Bank's work in integrating those issues into its&#13;
&#13;
                             activities.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Recent research by the Bank has made it crystal&#13;
&#13;
                             clear that governance issues are of central importance to&#13;
&#13;
                             efforts to assist countries to develop.    So, there is a&#13;
&#13;
                             strong case for a significant deepening of Bank operational&#13;
&#13;
                             work in this area in order to deal with what is called in the&#13;
&#13;
                             paper the crisis of development effectiveness.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Of course, from an operational point of view, this&#13;
&#13;
                             is not an easy area.    The Bank does need to be mindful of its&#13;
&#13;
                             mandate, but on the whole I think the paper presents a well-&#13;
&#13;
                             balanced case for more integrated and comprehensive work by&#13;
&#13;
                             the Bank to improve governance in borrowing countries.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I agree with those who would like to see more in&#13;
&#13;
                             the paper on coordination between the Bank and other donors,&#13;
&#13;
                             especially in terms of policy dialogue with borrowers.&#13;
&#13;
                                       As several speakers have already mentioned, we do&#13;
&#13;
                             need to be careful in the way we handle some issues, such as&#13;
&#13;
                             military expenditure.     I agree with Mrs. Herfkens that staff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street. N .E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                      42&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             are dealing with this issue in a sensible and practical way.&#13;
&#13;
                             It is a field where there is too much waste of resources and&#13;
&#13;
                             the Bank can help to encourage countries to use those&#13;
&#13;
                             resources better.&#13;
&#13;
                                       At the same time though, we should not overlook the&#13;
&#13;
                             fact that military spending often takes the form of imports,&#13;
&#13;
                             including from industrial countries.     So, the supply side has&#13;
&#13;
                             its own governance aspect.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I feel a little uneasy, Mr. Chairman, about the&#13;
&#13;
                             paper's reference to human rights.     This also, I think, is a&#13;
&#13;
                             difficult area.     But, what worries me most is that the&#13;
&#13;
                             subject can mean quite different things to different people.&#13;
&#13;
                             And, it has in the past created important problems for our&#13;
&#13;
                             institution.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The paper uses the phrase human rights in an&#13;
&#13;
                             economic sense, helping to reduce poverty and, of course, I&#13;
&#13;
                             am all in favor of helping to reduce poverty.     I can also&#13;
&#13;
                             understand that we might want to win over some external&#13;
&#13;
                             critics who focus on human rights.     But, we need to avoid I&#13;
&#13;
                             think trying to be all things to all men and women.     In my&#13;
&#13;
                             view, the Bank would be on surer ground in papers like this&#13;
&#13;
                             by focusing on and using phrases such as "improving living&#13;
&#13;
                             standards" or "helping to reduce poverty", rather than on&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
)07 C Stteet, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
(202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                      43&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             using phrases such as "human rights".&#13;
&#13;
                                       If the paper is to be published, as Ms. Jonsdottir&#13;
&#13;
                             earlier asked, I think that would be a worthwhile change.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The paper emphasizes the importance of public&#13;
&#13;
                             participation in governance, and there is no doubt that&#13;
&#13;
                             participation can bring major benefits to project&#13;
&#13;
                             effectiveness.   And, I am glad to see that the Bank is&#13;
&#13;
                             exploring appropriate approaches in that direction.&#13;
&#13;
                                       But again, I think we must not lose sight of the&#13;
&#13;
                             facts that broad participation can also carry with it&#13;
&#13;
                             significant costs and also that there are notable examples&#13;
&#13;
                             within our membership of countries which have experienced&#13;
&#13;
                             rapid and sustained economic growth but which have not&#13;
&#13;
                             adopted a broad participatory approach to development.&#13;
&#13;
                                       On decentralization, I feel here we are addressing&#13;
&#13;
                             a topic which is not amenable to clear-cut prescriptions.        I&#13;
&#13;
                             agree with Mr. Kaizuka on that.   It is obvious that if you&#13;
&#13;
                             make decisions at an appropriate level, that is likely to&#13;
&#13;
                             lead to improved decision-making processes.   But, at the same&#13;
&#13;
                             time, we need to remember that the scarcest resource in many&#13;
&#13;
                             developing countries is skilled human resources.&#13;
&#13;
                                       And, to decentralize decision-making in some&#13;
&#13;
                             countries runs the risk of moving the burdens of government&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
WÂ·.l.Shington, D.C. 20002&#13;
(202) H6Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                      44&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             onto those less able to deal effectively with them.&#13;
&#13;
                                       In our constituency, for example, Mr. Chairman,&#13;
&#13;
                             some countries, in fact, are now recentralizing some&#13;
&#13;
                             government functions, partly in order to make the best use of&#13;
&#13;
                             their scarce skills but also to reverse the growth of large&#13;
&#13;
                             and wasteful bureaucracies at various levels of government.&#13;
&#13;
                                       These are what I see as some important&#13;
&#13;
                             qualifications to the general argument in the paper that need&#13;
&#13;
                             to be covered, Mr. Chairman.    Overall though, the paper is on&#13;
&#13;
                             the right track and within the more integrated and&#13;
&#13;
                             comprehensive approach to governance, I see work on&#13;
&#13;
                             institution-building, the improved public sector management&#13;
&#13;
                             and stronger legal frameworks as remaining very important in&#13;
&#13;
                             our work on governance.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I agree with Mr. Flano's remarks on that, including&#13;
&#13;
                             the need for more staff with practical experience in these&#13;
&#13;
                             fields, but not, of course, more staff in total.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. PRESTON:    Thank you, Mr. Cosgrove.&#13;
&#13;
                                       We might now turn to staff and let them respond to&#13;
&#13;
                             some of the issues raised.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Mr. Stevens, Mr. Choksi.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. STEVENS:    Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING COâ&#128;¢â&#128;¢ INC.&#13;
~07   C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
(202) &gt;46-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                       45&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       If I may, I would like to respond to four comments&#13;
&#13;
                             and questions made by the Chairs.   The first one is the&#13;
&#13;
                             question of the coordination between the Bank and bilateral&#13;
&#13;
                             donors and NGOs, which was raised by the Nordic Chair and I&#13;
&#13;
                             think recently by Mr. Cosgrove.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I would like to make a few points on this.   The&#13;
&#13;
                             first is, although the paper does not explicitly mention it,&#13;
&#13;
                             there is a great deal of both formal and informal consultatio&#13;
&#13;
                             between the Bank and other agencies and NGOs.&#13;
&#13;
                                       In the first instance, there is the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
                             membership of the DAC Subcommittee on Good Governance and&#13;
&#13;
                             Participatory Development, which has been meeting recently to&#13;
&#13;
                             draft an orientation's paper on governance which the Bank has&#13;
&#13;
                             been participating in as an observer.   That is referred to in&#13;
&#13;
                             the report.   This is an ongoing dialogue.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The second is that there are informal exchanges&#13;
&#13;
                             between the Bank and bilateral donors on governance issues,&#13;
&#13;
                             and Bank staff have participated in a range of seminars and&#13;
&#13;
                             training sessions and other activities arranged by bilateral&#13;
&#13;
                             donors to explain the Bank's interpretation of governance and&#13;
&#13;
                             the approach it takes.&#13;
&#13;
                                       And, if I may cite the Africa Region, some of this&#13;
&#13;
                             work has been done on a regional basis within the continent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N,E,&#13;
Washington, D,C,     20002&#13;
(202) 546Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                        46&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             And, there also are annual meetings of the international&#13;
&#13;
                             development banks at the time of the Annual Meetings of the&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank and the Fund.   And, this year the theme of this meeting&#13;
&#13;
                             was, in fact, governance.     And, the Bank, the ADB and the&#13;
&#13;
                             lADB did exchange views and papers on governance topics.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Then, I would say that another point worth&#13;
&#13;
                             mentioning is the importance of the Bank/NGO committee which&#13;
&#13;
                             has been meeting for some time now and has played a key role&#13;
&#13;
                             in the formulation of the Bank's policy on participation.&#13;
&#13;
                             That has been a key factor.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Then, I would also specifically mention SlDA&#13;
&#13;
                             (Phonetic), Swedish SlDA, which has financed the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
                             participation work, helped to finance the Bank's participatio&#13;
&#13;
                             work in the Participation Learning Group.&#13;
&#13;
                                       And finally, I would mention the UNDP where the&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank maintains close contacts on public sector management&#13;
&#13;
                             issues, both in connection with the UNDP's management&#13;
&#13;
                             development program and also in broader areas.     There is, for&#13;
&#13;
                             example, a workshop on technical assistance currently being&#13;
&#13;
                             planned for next year by the UNDP, the Bank and the DAC.&#13;
&#13;
                             This is an example of the collaboration that we pursue.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The second issue I would like to mention is the&#13;
&#13;
                             staff skill one, which has been raised by a number of Chairs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C.     20002&#13;
(202) 546Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                     47&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             and clearly is a crucial one.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The first point I would like to mention is that the&#13;
&#13;
                             President has identified public sector management as one of&#13;
&#13;
                             the areas for specific recruitment emphasis, along with a&#13;
&#13;
                             number of others, in the coming years and targets have been&#13;
&#13;
                             set.&#13;
&#13;
                                        The second point to make is that, although the&#13;
&#13;
                             actual numbers of PSM specialists reported in the report is&#13;
&#13;
                             slightly less than 50 appears to be a relatively modest&#13;
&#13;
                             figure.   This, in fact, is a fraction of the total number of&#13;
&#13;
                             staff currently working on governance issues in the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
                             This is quite a substantial number.&#13;
&#13;
                                        The third point I would make is that recruitment of&#13;
&#13;
                             public sector management specialists is, in fact, increasing&#13;
&#13;
                             in the Bank.   The current figures for this year is that the&#13;
&#13;
                             Personnel Department have filled three additional vacancies&#13;
&#13;
                             and are currently attempting to fill a further three.     So,&#13;
&#13;
                             there is a growth increase of six and the net increase is&#13;
&#13;
                             five in public sector management specialists within the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
                                        The final point I would make on staff skills is&#13;
&#13;
                             that we are currently reviewing the training offerings in&#13;
&#13;
                             public sector management and institutional development with a&#13;
&#13;
                             view to offering next calendar year enhanced courses in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MIUER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C.     20002&#13;
(202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                       48&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             public sector management and in institutional development.&#13;
&#13;
                                          The third pOint that I would like to cover is the&#13;
&#13;
                             question raised about the cooperation between the Bank and&#13;
&#13;
                             the Fund on military expenditure matters.     I would just make&#13;
&#13;
                             three points here to illustrate the cooperation between the&#13;
&#13;
                             two institutions.&#13;
&#13;
                                          First of all, there is now an established&#13;
&#13;
                             arrangement for the sharing of data on both military debt and&#13;
&#13;
                             military budgetary expenditure that has been agreed with with&#13;
&#13;
                             the Fund and is in place. That is the first point to make.&#13;
&#13;
                                          The second point is that there have been now joint&#13;
&#13;
                             operational missions between the Fund and the Bank, which&#13;
&#13;
                             have looked at military expenditure matters.     A case in point&#13;
&#13;
                             is the work that the Bank has done on Argentina at the&#13;
&#13;
                             government's request, and it is cited in the government's&#13;
&#13;
                             progress.     There was a Fund staff member participating in&#13;
&#13;
                             that work.&#13;
&#13;
                                          And finally, there is an agreement with the Fund to&#13;
&#13;
                             carry out joint research on the impact of military expenditur&#13;
&#13;
                             on development.     And, this is something that we will be&#13;
&#13;
                             working on.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Now, the final point that I would like to refer to&#13;
&#13;
                             is the issue of the publication of the report.     Yes, we would&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
(202) 546Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                        49&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             like to publish the report after editing.     We see this as an&#13;
&#13;
                             expression of the Bank's new dissemination policy, and it&#13;
&#13;
                             would be consistent with the publication of the first&#13;
&#13;
                             governance report.&#13;
&#13;
                                       So, we would plan to publish this report after its&#13;
&#13;
                             acceptance by the Board.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. PRESTON:     Thank you, Mr. Stevens.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Mr. Choksi.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. CHOKSI:    I would just like to make one comment,&#13;
&#13;
                             Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I think, Mr. Cosgrove, you raised the issue about&#13;
&#13;
                             how we handled human rights in this report and if we go for&#13;
&#13;
                             publication we use some other term.&#13;
&#13;
                                       We recognize the sensitivity of the issue of human&#13;
&#13;
                             rights, and this report makes this very clear.       However, the&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank has consistently faced this issue in different fora.&#13;
&#13;
                             What is the Bank doing in the area of human rights?       How is&#13;
&#13;
                             it going about it?&#13;
&#13;
                                       And, I am a little concerned that if we go out in&#13;
&#13;
                             the public forum and use some other euphemism for human&#13;
&#13;
                             rights, such as improving the living standards, rather than&#13;
&#13;
                             addressing the issue head-on, as done in this important, I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
(202) 546Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                         50&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             think it is important.&#13;
&#13;
                                        I   think this report makes it very clear and the&#13;
&#13;
                             General Counsel in his various speeches, his various papers&#13;
&#13;
                             has also drawn a very clear delineation between the political&#13;
&#13;
                             dimension of human rights and the economic dimension over&#13;
&#13;
                             here.   And, I think this report makes it explicit, and I&#13;
&#13;
                             think it is important for the outside world to understand&#13;
&#13;
                             that the Bank does and it cannot take into account the&#13;
&#13;
                             political dimensions of human rights.&#13;
&#13;
                                        So, it is my view that, when we go to publication,&#13;
&#13;
                             we do make this explicit because in different fora that I&#13;
&#13;
                             have run into, whether it is with government officials,&#13;
&#13;
                             whether it is with the private sector, whether it is with&#13;
&#13;
                             NGOs, whether it is with academics, this issue of human&#13;
&#13;
                             rights is being raised internationally in all fora.&#13;
&#13;
                                        And, I think that the Bank's view and position&#13;
&#13;
                             needs to be made very clear.&#13;
&#13;
                                        MR. PRESTON:    I was going to calIon Mr. Shihata to&#13;
&#13;
                             respond and then I will go back to Mr. Cosgrove.&#13;
&#13;
                                        MR. SHlHATA:    I don't know if Board members have&#13;
&#13;
                             seen the paper that was submitted by the Bank to the UN&#13;
&#13;
                             Conference on Human Rights and the speech I made there.&#13;
&#13;
                                        There, I made clear that the Bank is, in fact, very&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
(202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                         51&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             involved in the promotion of human rights that fall within&#13;
&#13;
                             its mandate.     Our daily work, after all, whether it is&#13;
&#13;
                             alleviation of poverty, providing assistance for education,&#13;
&#13;
                             health and nutrition, for the protection of the environment,&#13;
&#13;
                             for the improvement of the status of women, for the&#13;
&#13;
                             resettlement and rehabilitation of affected people, for the&#13;
&#13;
                             partiCipation of affected people and local NGOs in the design&#13;
&#13;
                             and implementation of projects, for the protection of the&#13;
&#13;
                             rights of indigenous and tribal people, in all these respects&#13;
&#13;
                             the Bank is indeed promoting very important aspects of human&#13;
&#13;
                             rights.&#13;
&#13;
                                       It has been said that freedom from poverty is&#13;
&#13;
                             probably the freedom needed for the full enjoyment of any&#13;
&#13;
                             other freedom.&#13;
&#13;
                                       To that extent, human rights is part of our work.&#13;
&#13;
                             However, human rights has other dimensions as well.     In fact,&#13;
&#13;
                             in the UN itself there are two separate conventions; they are.&#13;
&#13;
                             called covenants, one for economic, social and cultural human&#13;
&#13;
                             rights and the other one for political and civil human rights.&#13;
&#13;
                                       NOW,    it is the latter that really does not fall&#13;
&#13;
                             within the purposes of the Bank.     And, there are explicit&#13;
&#13;
                             provisions in the Bank's Articles which prohibit it from&#13;
&#13;
                             taking political considerations into account or interfering&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Screet, N.R.&#13;
Washington, D.C.     20002&#13;
(202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                           52&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              in the political affairs of any country or being affected by&#13;
&#13;
                              the political form or orientation of a country.&#13;
&#13;
                                           NOw, as Mr. de Paiva said, the distinction is very&#13;
&#13;
                              difficult.     The political agenda is full of economic&#13;
&#13;
                              questions; the economic agenda is full of political questions.&#13;
&#13;
                              And, certainly, governance in the abstract covers both.&#13;
&#13;
                                           The paper I wrote in 1990 was meant to address that&#13;
&#13;
                              particular issue, how to differentiate.       And, I hope the&#13;
&#13;
                              Executive Directors would have the occasion to read that&#13;
&#13;
                              paper.   In due course, if you are interested, I may read out&#13;
&#13;
                              to you the conclusions of that paper.&#13;
&#13;
                                           But, as far as human rights are concerned, the&#13;
&#13;
                              point to be emphasized is that, yes, we have a role to play&#13;
&#13;
                              in the promotion of human rights but, no, we cannot address&#13;
&#13;
                              the political aspects of human rights because, after all,&#13;
&#13;
                              this is the World Bank, not the world government.&#13;
&#13;
                                           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
                                           MR. PRESTON:    Thank you, Mr. Shihata.&#13;
&#13;
                                           Mr. Cosgrove.&#13;
&#13;
                                           MR. COSGROVE:   Well, Mr. Chairman, what Mr. Choksi&#13;
&#13;
                              and Mr. Shihata have just said, of course, is entirely&#13;
&#13;
                              logical, and I have no problem with that logic at all.&#13;
&#13;
                                           My worry though is that the public debate is not&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING COâ&#128;¢â&#128;¢ INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N .E.&#13;
Washington, D.C.      20002&#13;
(202) 546Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                           53&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               always logical.   And, I feel that if we start going&#13;
&#13;
                               specifically into the area of saying that we are dealing with&#13;
&#13;
                               human rights, however narrowly and precisely we try to tell&#13;
&#13;
                               people outside what we are doing in the field of human&#13;
&#13;
                               rights, we are on a slippery slope.&#13;
&#13;
                                         And, in my view, because of the difficulty of&#13;
&#13;
                               drawing a line between the economic and political aspects of&#13;
&#13;
                               this matter, we will very likely find ourselves in the future&#13;
&#13;
                               being urged by various parties not to have operations with&#13;
&#13;
                               certain countries which might, for example, have some so-&#13;
&#13;
                               called political prisoners in their jails.&#13;
&#13;
                                         This is the worry that I have.     The logic, as I&#13;
&#13;
                               say, is defensible, but I don't think it is always going to&#13;
&#13;
                               win the argument in the public domain.     And, I think we would&#13;
&#13;
                               be wiser to stick to improving living standards and reducing&#13;
&#13;
                               poverty, and to use those phrases in our documents.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
                                         MR. PRESTON:     I saw, I thought, another hand up.&#13;
&#13;
                               Is there another follow-on?&#13;
&#13;
                                         (No response.)&#13;
&#13;
                                         MR. PRESTON:     If not, we will go on.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Mr. Stanton.&#13;
&#13;
                                         MR. STANTON:     Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street. N.E,&#13;
WashioglOo. D,C,       20002&#13;
(202\ ,4(,.(,666&#13;
&amp;#12;nm                                                                                        54&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       Like others, I found much to applaud in this&#13;
&#13;
                             report.   I might say that I was pleased to see that the Bank&#13;
&#13;
                             is not only professional but it is also erudite.     I was&#13;
&#13;
                             grateful to be reminded that governance derives from a Latin&#13;
&#13;
                             word meaning to steer a ship.&#13;
&#13;
                                        I think that this report shows how far we have corne&#13;
&#13;
                             in a short time.   The range of governance issues being&#13;
&#13;
                             addressed by the Bank is impressive, and I think I would also&#13;
&#13;
                             commend the responsiveness that this shows on the part of the&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank.&#13;
&#13;
                                        I think it is also very interesting to note that&#13;
&#13;
                             these issues are proving a good deal less controversial than&#13;
&#13;
                             might have been feared a couple of years ago.&#13;
&#13;
                                        This brings me to the concerns that John Cosgrove&#13;
&#13;
                             has just raised about human rights.     I understand what he is&#13;
&#13;
                             saying, but at the same time, I think that if we didn't make&#13;
&#13;
                             reference in a document of this sort to human rights in those&#13;
&#13;
                             terms, that would be noted.     And, therefore, I think I would&#13;
&#13;
                             agree that it is something that we have to take on the nose;&#13;
&#13;
                             we have to set out our position on this issue.&#13;
&#13;
                                        I very much regret that like you, sir, I didn't&#13;
&#13;
                             have the opportunity to read most of the statements that were&#13;
&#13;
                             circulated by my colleagues before this meeting.     I did read&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Stroot. N.E.&#13;
WashingtOn, D.C.     20002&#13;
(202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                     55&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             Mrs. Herfkens' statement, and on a particular point I agree&#13;
&#13;
                             with her and that is the need to see the Bank's activities in&#13;
&#13;
                             the context of what other agencies are doing.   Governance is&#13;
&#13;
                             an important element in other bilateral programs, other&#13;
&#13;
                             multilateral programs.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I would note, for example, UNDP's redefined mission&#13;
&#13;
                             to focus on capacity-building, which, of course, covers much&#13;
&#13;
                             of the governance agenda.&#13;
&#13;
                                       This brings me to a further point.    I mean, I&#13;
&#13;
                             welcome the consultation, the wide consultation that the b&#13;
&#13;
                             undertakes and which has been referred to again this morning&#13;
&#13;
                             by Mr. Stevens.   But, there is a further question beyond&#13;
&#13;
                             consultation, and that is division of labor.    That is to say,&#13;
&#13;
                             is there, should there be a division of labor between the&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank and the other agencies that operate in this area?      This&#13;
&#13;
                             is a question that is not really addressed in the report in&#13;
&#13;
                             front of us.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I don't have a clear view, but I would welcome any&#13;
&#13;
                             thoughts that you might have on whether the Bank should be&#13;
&#13;
                             attempting to support all the areas of governance that fall&#13;
&#13;
                             within its mandate, or whether there would be merit in a&#13;
&#13;
                             division of labor where other agencies, bilateral or&#13;
&#13;
                             multilateral, are focusing more on certain areas of business.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washil!gton. D.C. 20002&#13;
(202)   ~46Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12;nm                                                                                          56&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       I don't think we should be afraid to say that there&#13;
&#13;
                             are some areas of governance that are better done by others,&#13;
&#13;
                             if that indeed is the case.&#13;
&#13;
                                       This brings us to the question of the effectiveness&#13;
&#13;
                             of Bank assistance.     The report tells us a lot about what the&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank is trying to do.     It tells us less for obvious reasons Â­&#13;
&#13;
                             - we haven't been in the business too long -- about how&#13;
&#13;
                             successful it has been.     And, this is something in due course&#13;
&#13;
                             that we need to get a handle on.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I would expect OED to help us here.     And, indeed, I&#13;
&#13;
                             would be interested to hear a little more about the role of&#13;
&#13;
                             the HRO Vice Presidency in reviewing experiencing and&#13;
&#13;
                             developing new approaches, disseminating best practice in&#13;
&#13;
                             this sort of area.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I would like to say a word about skills mix.     I&#13;
&#13;
                             don't think that we should simply go away with the idea,&#13;
&#13;
                             which is perhaps implicit in the report, that all we need to&#13;
&#13;
                             do is to hire more staff with experience in public sector&#13;
&#13;
                             management.   I mean, this clearly is a very relevant concern.&#13;
&#13;
                                       But, I was struck by Mamadou Dia's paper on civil&#13;
&#13;
                             service reform in Africa, which concluded with the following&#13;
&#13;
                             sentence which I will read, if you will permit me:     "To carry&#13;
&#13;
                             out such operations requires pulling together multi-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
)07 C Sueet. N.E.&#13;
Wash,ngton, D.C. 20002&#13;
(202)   ~46Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                     57&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             disciplinary teams of experts which will include political&#13;
&#13;
                             scientists and sociologists with experience in planned social&#13;
&#13;
                             change, applied behavioral scientists with background and&#13;
&#13;
                             experience in planned organization change, legal specialists&#13;
&#13;
                             with strong background in public and constitutional law,&#13;
&#13;
                             institutional development and public management specialists,&#13;
&#13;
                             public finance and budget specialists".&#13;
&#13;
                                       I would only say, sir, that I think that we need to&#13;
&#13;
                             consider carefully in the Bank what skills mix we need to&#13;
&#13;
                             apply the requisite analytical skills to this complex and&#13;
&#13;
                             difficult question.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Participation:   I agree that participation is an&#13;
&#13;
                             important element in good governance, participation both in&#13;
&#13;
                             defining the development agenda, as well as in the narrower&#13;
&#13;
                             issues of participation in project design.   But, I raise this&#13;
&#13;
                             really to make a budgetary point, and that is that I don't&#13;
&#13;
                             think that I agree with the suggestion that we should&#13;
&#13;
                             replenish the participation Fund to pay for this.   I think&#13;
&#13;
                             rather the costs of it should increasingly be mainstreamed as&#13;
&#13;
                             a normal part of administrative costs.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I mean, in due course, I would like to know more&#13;
&#13;
                             about the cost implications and how staff intensive good&#13;
&#13;
                             governance work is proving to be.   Clearly, we need in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING COâ&#128;¢â&#128;¢ INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
(202)   ~6-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                       58&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             budgetary context to look at the implications for&#13;
&#13;
                             administrative costs of these new types of activities.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Finally! I just would like to say a word of&#13;
&#13;
                             commendation about the valuable role that the Bank has in&#13;
&#13;
                             chairing Consultative Group discussions! which address&#13;
&#13;
                             governance issues.     These are issues that cannot be ignored&#13;
&#13;
                             in any meeting concerned with the mobilization of external&#13;
&#13;
                             resources.    And, I think that the Bank's apolitical status&#13;
&#13;
                             makes it well placed to chair such discussions and to play an&#13;
&#13;
                             honest broker.&#13;
&#13;
                                          I must say that my authorities have found the Bank'&#13;
&#13;
                             role to be very constructive and I commend staff for their&#13;
&#13;
                             sensitive handling of these matters in these fora.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Thank you, sir.&#13;
&#13;
                                          MR. PRESTON:    Thank you, Mr. Stanton.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Mr. Gerber.&#13;
&#13;
                                          MR. GERBER:    Thank you, Mr. President, and thank&#13;
&#13;
                             you to those colleagues who have distributed their texts in&#13;
&#13;
                             advance.&#13;
&#13;
                                          I would like to congratulate both management and&#13;
&#13;
                             staff for this impressive, very informative and interesting&#13;
&#13;
                             progress report.     I encourage the Bank to continue actively&#13;
&#13;
                             promoting the strengthening of good governance in its&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~(}7   C Street. N .E.&#13;
Wuhington. D.C. 2(}OQ2&#13;
(202)   ~46Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                     59&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             operational activities and research work.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The Bank's action on governance focuses attention&#13;
&#13;
                             on state, advocating changes in the structure of government,&#13;
&#13;
                             for instance, through decentralization, changes in the role&#13;
&#13;
                             of the state in the economy, for instance through&#13;
&#13;
                             privatization, and changes in the process by which decision-&#13;
&#13;
                             making and governance takes place, for instance through an&#13;
&#13;
                             increased dialogue with the private sector.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The crucial importance of institutions in economic&#13;
&#13;
                             development has been increasingly recognized in a trend that&#13;
&#13;
                             culminated this year with the attribution of the Nobel Prize&#13;
&#13;
                             for Economics in particularly to one of the two specialists&#13;
&#13;
                             who has extensively worked on this matter.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The Bank is an important actor in putting into&#13;
&#13;
                             practice the message which was conveyed also by the Nobel&#13;
&#13;
                             Prize winner.&#13;
&#13;
                                       And, the report before us illustrates the impressiv&#13;
&#13;
                             effort undertaken by the Bank to better understand and&#13;
&#13;
                             influence its institutional dimension of policies, programs&#13;
&#13;
                             and projects.   The important investment of resources that&#13;
&#13;
                             made this evolution possible is fully justified and augurs&#13;
&#13;
                             well for the future quality and performance of the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
                             work.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N .E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
1202) 546Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                      60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       However, the report puts its emphasis on the&#13;
&#13;
                             activities deployed and is less precise in the presentation&#13;
&#13;
                             of the results achieved so far.     It is, therefore, worthwhile&#13;
&#13;
                             to remember that the recent review of the evaluation results&#13;
&#13;
                             of 1992 in a chapter reserved to the institutional developmen&#13;
&#13;
                             indicated that only one-third of the Bank's projects in this&#13;
&#13;
                             area achieved substantial positive results and that the&#13;
&#13;
                             performance was particularly weak in the areas of technical&#13;
&#13;
                             assistance and in the case of program and policy operations&#13;
&#13;
                             critical for improvement of governance.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The Bank's work on governance has generally&#13;
&#13;
                             expanded in all regions of the developing world and also in&#13;
&#13;
                             the countries that are in transition from socialist to a&#13;
&#13;
                             market economy.     But, some Regional Vice Presidencies have&#13;
&#13;
                             been more active than others.     We understand that Bank work&#13;
&#13;
                             by regions differs depending on the state of development, of&#13;
&#13;
                             public administration and the absorptive capacity of the&#13;
&#13;
                             member countries.&#13;
&#13;
                                       In this context, we have appreciated the impressive&#13;
&#13;
                             work realized by the Latin American and the Caribbean Vice&#13;
&#13;
                             President, including in some difficult areas like&#13;
&#13;
                             decentralization, as well as in some innovative areas like&#13;
&#13;
                             the legislative and judicial reform.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
(202)   ~46-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;run                                                                                       61&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          But, we also encourage the Bank to expand its&#13;
&#13;
                             program aimed at administrative and civil service reform in&#13;
&#13;
                             Asia.&#13;
&#13;
                                          The report stresses influence that the donor&#13;
&#13;
                             policies have on the governance performance of many states in&#13;
&#13;
                             the developing world, which is particularly important and&#13;
&#13;
                             often problematic in the case of the smallest and poorest&#13;
&#13;
                             countries, mainly in Africa.     In this situation, the Bank is&#13;
&#13;
                             one of the most important actors, but it is never in a&#13;
&#13;
                             position to improve alone the way in which foreign assistance&#13;
&#13;
                             is delivered and institutional development is furthered.&#13;
&#13;
                                          On the contrary; other multilateral organizations&#13;
&#13;
                             and, even more, the bilateral development agencies exert&#13;
&#13;
                             through their own operations a substantial influence on the&#13;
&#13;
                             performance of the public sector.     We encourage, therefore,&#13;
&#13;
                             the Bank to pursue with its efforts of coordination as they&#13;
&#13;
                             are conducted in the context of the Special Program for&#13;
&#13;
                             Africa or in the different CG meetings.&#13;
&#13;
                                          In this fora, the way in which the different&#13;
&#13;
                             agencies operate and its impact on governance and&#13;
&#13;
                             institutional development should progressively receive more&#13;
&#13;
                             attention.     Methods to achieve this could be to make bilatera&#13;
&#13;
                             and other agencies participate in the analytical work, which&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C SUeft, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
(2021   ~46-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;nm&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             is realized to understand better the local institutions, in&#13;
&#13;
                             particular through the institutional environment assessment&#13;
&#13;
                             presented in the report on page 14, as well as through the&#13;
&#13;
                             common assessment of the country financial accountability,&#13;
&#13;
                             page 18, that should be generalized following the recent&#13;
&#13;
                             recommendation of the Bank internal task force.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Coming to the touchy subject, Mr. Chairman,&#13;
&#13;
                             military expenditure and human rights.   Given the economic&#13;
&#13;
                             and political impact, the level and the transparency of the&#13;
&#13;
                             military expenditures are in many countries a reason for&#13;
&#13;
                             concern and an unavoidable object of analysis and political&#13;
&#13;
                             dialogue for the Bank.   The report is certainly right in&#13;
&#13;
                             stressing the sensitivity of the issue lying partially&#13;
&#13;
                             outside the Bank mandate.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Nevertheless, when the client governments ask it to&#13;
&#13;
                             do so, the Bank should be in a position to provide useful&#13;
&#13;
                             advice and to measure the progress achieved in the&#13;
&#13;
                             reallocation of resources from the military apparatus to more&#13;
&#13;
                             productive branches of the government.&#13;
&#13;
                                       In particular, we welcome the intellectual and&#13;
&#13;
                             practical involvement of the African Region in support of the&#13;
&#13;
                             demobilization, reintegration schemes prepared and launched&#13;
&#13;
                             in many of the poorest countries of the world to restore&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Sueet, KE.&#13;
Washington, D.C.   20002&#13;
12(2)   ~46.6666&#13;
&amp;#12;nm                                                                                          63&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             peace and scarce resources.&#13;
&#13;
                                          We also consider that the way the Bank has responde&#13;
&#13;
                             to the request of the Government of Argentina to develop&#13;
&#13;
                             options for a reduction in military spending, accompanied by&#13;
&#13;
                             a program to rationalize the Armed Forces, has an exemplary&#13;
&#13;
                             character.&#13;
&#13;
                                          The report tries hard to establish a clear&#13;
&#13;
                             distinction between political and human rights, on one side,&#13;
&#13;
                             and economic and social human rights, on the other.       We&#13;
&#13;
                             understand the rationale for this attempt, but we would like&#13;
&#13;
                             to emphasize that ultimately the human rights are inseparable&#13;
&#13;
                             and that it would be almost impossible to improve transparenc&#13;
&#13;
                             and accountability in states which do not recognize the&#13;
&#13;
                             freedom of speech, to publish and to dissent or which denies&#13;
&#13;
                             independence of the judiciary power and the fair enforcement&#13;
&#13;
                             of the law.&#13;
&#13;
                                          We should, therefore, admit that cases are&#13;
&#13;
                             conceivable in which the abuses exerted by the state power&#13;
&#13;
                             against the human rights are so great that no improvement in&#13;
&#13;
                             the economic and social governance, as defined by the Bank,&#13;
&#13;
                             can be expected, and that the conditions for a continuation&#13;
&#13;
                             or an expansion of the Bank activities are no more warranted.&#13;
&#13;
                                          To a certain extent, Mr. Chairman, I think that the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C.     20002&#13;
(202) )46.6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                      64&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             distinction between political and economic human rights are a&#13;
&#13;
                             wrong problem.   I don't know of one example in the world&#13;
&#13;
                             where you have accountability and transparency and the human&#13;
&#13;
                             rights are not respected; vice versa, I don't know of one&#13;
&#13;
                             example in the world where you have respected human rights&#13;
&#13;
                             and there is no transparency and accountability, which shows&#13;
&#13;
                             that both are practically inseparable.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Mr. Chairman, if one reads the report before us,&#13;
&#13;
                             one sees that governance is dealt with practically only as&#13;
&#13;
                             far as Part II countries are concerned.   But, there is one&#13;
&#13;
                             dimension which is not included at all, that is good&#13;
&#13;
                             government in the Part I countries.   And here, I would like&#13;
&#13;
                             to stress that good governance applies to all countries in&#13;
&#13;
                             the world and I would like to refer to the good governance&#13;
&#13;
                             practices of the Part I countries under the title of coherenc&#13;
&#13;
                             of their economic policy.&#13;
&#13;
                                       It does not make sense to preach competitivity and&#13;
&#13;
                             at the same time tied aid.   It does not make sense to ask for&#13;
&#13;
                             a reduction of military spending and at the same time&#13;
&#13;
                             increase military exports.   It does not make sense to ask for&#13;
&#13;
                             the protection of tropical forests and at the same time to be&#13;
&#13;
                             the major cause in the developed world for C02 fumes.   It&#13;
&#13;
                             does not make sense to preach free trade and take&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washingron. D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                      65&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             protectionist actions.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I think that is a very important issue of governanc&#13;
&#13;
                             which should be addressed also by the Bank.   And, I think it&#13;
&#13;
                             can be addressed, in particular, when we discuss the country&#13;
&#13;
                             assistance strategy and when we discuss in the country&#13;
&#13;
                             assistance strategy the external factors influencing the&#13;
&#13;
                             development process.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Let me also say that the developed countries have&#13;
&#13;
                             to take complementary measures in order to assist the&#13;
&#13;
                             developing countries to implement good governance, for&#13;
&#13;
                             instance, in the area of drugs control, in the area of&#13;
&#13;
                             economic criminality, in the area of trade and weapons.&#13;
&#13;
                                       In this context, and having read the content of Box&#13;
&#13;
                             10 towards an anti-corruption strategy, we are pleased to&#13;
&#13;
                             realize that the Bank's research program for institutional&#13;
&#13;
                             strengthening to improve controls and reduce incentives for&#13;
&#13;
                             corrupt behavior will also include measures that&#13;
&#13;
                             industrialized countries could take to discourage corrupt&#13;
&#13;
                             practices by exporters.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The experience of the Bank has shown many times how&#13;
&#13;
                             these so-called external factors have affected the situation&#13;
&#13;
                             of developing countries as well as the performance of the&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank portfolio.   We think that in the future to be fair, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C.     20002&#13;
(202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                        66&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             international dimension of the problem should be discussed in&#13;
&#13;
                             the periodical reports on governance, as well when addressing,&#13;
&#13;
                             as I said, the condition of country analysis in the country&#13;
&#13;
                             assistance strategy document.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                         MR. PRESTON:   Thank you,   Mr~   Gerber.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Mr. Fischer.&#13;
&#13;
                                         MR. FISCHER:   Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Let me start with the hope that once again we get a&#13;
&#13;
                             summary of sterling quality by the secretariat on this&#13;
&#13;
                             important issue.    And, let me, like others, welcome the&#13;
&#13;
                             occasion to discuss in a timely matter and on the basis of a&#13;
&#13;
                             comprehensive paper before us an issue that is both important&#13;
&#13;
                             and sensitive, and thus requires careful handling.&#13;
&#13;
                                         As others, I would like to underline that this is&#13;
&#13;
                             not only a complex issue that not only concerns a number of&#13;
&#13;
                             bilateral donors and their public, but also the Bank within&#13;
&#13;
                             the framework of its Articles of Agreement.&#13;
&#13;
                                         And, the paper rightly points out that the Bank has&#13;
&#13;
                             moved rapidly in recent years, but it also emphasizes -- and&#13;
&#13;
                             I would like to encourage that -- that there is more room for&#13;
&#13;
                             maneuver.    And, as Mr. Stanton has rightly observed, this&#13;
&#13;
                             issue with all its delicacy and sensitivity seems to be a lot&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C.     20002&#13;
(202) 546Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                         67&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             less controversial than it was only a couple of years ago.&#13;
&#13;
                             And, these are very comforting trends.&#13;
&#13;
                                          I would like to underline what Mr. Kline said, that&#13;
&#13;
                             the experience has shown that good governance is essential&#13;
&#13;
                             for social and economic development, and also this truth, if&#13;
&#13;
                             I may say so, is spreading and gives reasons for hope.&#13;
&#13;
                                          I do appreciate, like others, the very thoughtful&#13;
&#13;
                             advanced statements circulated by some of our colleagues, and&#13;
&#13;
                             I particularly am appreciative of having them share their own&#13;
&#13;
                             experience and insight from the point of view of borrowing&#13;
&#13;
                             countries.&#13;
&#13;
                                          And, more specifically, Mr. Chairman, I welcome&#13;
&#13;
                             that the governance issues will be incorporated increasingly&#13;
&#13;
                             in the country assistance strategy papers.&#13;
&#13;
                                          I felt tempted to respond a little bit to what Mr.&#13;
&#13;
                             Matambo said, but I take comfort from the reaction of the&#13;
&#13;
                             staff.   And, I would simply like to emphasize that with all&#13;
&#13;
                             the understanding that one can have that also in the future&#13;
&#13;
                             the main relations between the Bank and its borrowing&#13;
&#13;
                             countries go through the government, that we as a Board in a&#13;
&#13;
                             consensus way have in the recent past broadened the access to&#13;
&#13;
                             the people affected.&#13;
&#13;
                                          If one just thinks of the prerequisites for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Streer, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C.     20002&#13;
(202) 546Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                          68&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             environmental projects where the affected groups have to be&#13;
&#13;
                             duly consulted, if one thinks of the inspection panel where&#13;
&#13;
                             directly affected groups have access to the Bank, I think we&#13;
&#13;
                             get the right flavor of a more opening of context on both&#13;
&#13;
                             sides.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Mr. Chairman, Mrs. Herfkens elaborated on the&#13;
&#13;
                             participatory development as a necessary prerequisite to&#13;
&#13;
                             advance the sustainability of projects.      And, I would like to&#13;
&#13;
                             underline that and associate myself with this.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Like others l   in this context I the need for increase&#13;
&#13;
                             skill mix comes up, and I am    g~ad   that Mr. Stanton did&#13;
&#13;
                             mention the latest very thoughtful paper of Mr. Dia.          He has&#13;
&#13;
                             written others before where we have largely benefitted from&#13;
&#13;
                             his sensitivity and insight on this part.&#13;
&#13;
                                       We feel in this context that in the area of&#13;
&#13;
                             participatory development there might also be a need for all&#13;
&#13;
                             of us to think of adjusting the instruments that the Bank has&#13;
&#13;
                             in order to supplement the goal orientation that we pursue&#13;
&#13;
                             with more process orientation as well.&#13;
&#13;
                                       With respect to the public sector, a number of&#13;
&#13;
                             colleagues from Holland, Japan, Mr. Benhocine, Mr. Al-Khaled&#13;
&#13;
                             have said a lot about the role of the public sector also in&#13;
&#13;
                             the future.   And l   I can associate myself with it and I am&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C.     20002&#13;
{202} 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                      69&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             grateful that Mr. AI-Khaled reminded us that, inasmuch as&#13;
&#13;
                             privatization is not the panacea for everything and traditions&#13;
&#13;
                             in the different countries, we should always be mindful of&#13;
&#13;
                             having the people available that can manage privatized firms&#13;
&#13;
                             in developing countries.    It is an expression of underÂ­&#13;
&#13;
                             development, and that is an appeal to all of us that in many&#13;
&#13;
                             instances these people are not there and have to be trained&#13;
&#13;
                             accordingly.&#13;
&#13;
                                       With respect to decentralization, I think it is an&#13;
&#13;
                             important feature to advance good governance across the whole&#13;
&#13;
                             country and increase the quality of life, but at the same&#13;
&#13;
                             time I understand the concerns of our Japanese colleague, Mr.&#13;
&#13;
                             Kaizuka, about a certain balance between central government&#13;
&#13;
                             and regional governments.&#13;
&#13;
                                       And, I am also grateful to Mr. Benhocine for having&#13;
&#13;
                             pointed out again the need for the managerial capacities in&#13;
&#13;
                             the regions.   It is not enough that we as Bank or any other&#13;
&#13;
                             organizations advocate this and even sell certain plans to&#13;
&#13;
                             the borrowing countries without taking enough regard to the&#13;
&#13;
                             need for having people on the ground who can pursue this.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I was very grateful for Mr. Shihata's remarks on&#13;
&#13;
                             the human rights' issue and the relation to poverty&#13;
&#13;
                             alleviation.   And, perhaps he will be kind enough to circulat&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILlER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                    70&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            his speech that he made.   And, since Mr. Gerber quoted a&#13;
&#13;
                            Nobel Prize winner, I might have the liberty of referring to&#13;
&#13;
                            another one, a politician in my country, who pOinted out the&#13;
&#13;
                            relativity of human rights and poverty by saying that&#13;
&#13;
                            obviously freedom of speech and freedom of press are not the&#13;
&#13;
                            prime priorities for people who are hungry and don't know how&#13;
&#13;
                            to feed their children and who cannot even read or write.&#13;
&#13;
                                      Mr. Chairman, with respect to military expenditure&#13;
&#13;
                            and corruption, these are both sensitive, delicate issues,&#13;
&#13;
                            but they are also important.   And, Mr. Le Bouder and Mr. AI-&#13;
&#13;
                            Khaled, as well as Mr. Benhocine, Mr. Cosgrove, have pointed&#13;
&#13;
                            out, rightly pointed out that there are two sides to the&#13;
&#13;
                            coin, the suppliers and the receivers.&#13;
&#13;
                                      And, as to corruption more specifically, I&#13;
&#13;
                            understand that OECD -- this is the organization for&#13;
&#13;
                            industrialized countries -- is presently conducting&#13;
&#13;
                            deliberations to contain this on their side.   And, I&#13;
&#13;
                            personally also welcome -- and we all have heard of the&#13;
&#13;
                            Foundation of Transparency International in our future&#13;
&#13;
                            capital in Berlin some time ago by one of the former staff&#13;
&#13;
                            members in the Bank, who I understand also pursues a balanced&#13;
&#13;
                            approach going to both side.&#13;
&#13;
                                      In that context, I was, as many others of us, very&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORnNG CO.â&#128;¢ INC.&#13;
'07 C Str~~[. N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
(202) 546Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                       71&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              impressed by the remarks of Mr. Gerber on the coherence of&#13;
&#13;
                              policies in industrial countries, and I fully agree with him,&#13;
&#13;
                              as it is a very important feature our credibility.   And, I&#13;
&#13;
                              would add to his long convincing list also environment,&#13;
&#13;
                              energy saving, budget deficit, a lot of other issues in this&#13;
&#13;
                              regard.&#13;
&#13;
                                        In the same vein, I think in the context of&#13;
&#13;
                              military expenditure expenditures or arms' reduction, the&#13;
&#13;
                              industrialized countries, both of the former West and the&#13;
&#13;
                              East, have engaged in serious reduction of their armament&#13;
&#13;
                              arsenals and personnel.   But, of course, as we all know,&#13;
&#13;
                              there is the difficulty with the arms' production industry.&#13;
&#13;
                              And, it would be very sad and regrettable if for home&#13;
&#13;
                              consumption the arms' reduction is reduced but in order to&#13;
&#13;
                              keep these people busy and employed, that increaSing arms'&#13;
&#13;
                              exports go to other parts of the world.   It is a very complex&#13;
&#13;
                              issue, as we all know.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Like Mr. Gerber in that context, I very much&#13;
&#13;
                              appreciate the Bank's assistance not only in the case of&#13;
&#13;
                              Argentina that has asked for it, but also in some of the&#13;
&#13;
                              African countries where the Bank has assisted in the&#13;
&#13;
                              demobilization of troops, a subject that against the&#13;
&#13;
                              international change of the scenery which calls for reduction&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N ,E.&#13;
Washington. D.C.      20002&#13;
(202) 546Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12;nm                                                                                        72&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             of military personnel and arms worldwide is of increasing&#13;
&#13;
                             importance. And, I am glad that the Bank has attacked this&#13;
&#13;
                             and lends its assistance in some parts of the world.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Mr. Chairman, Mrs. Herfkens observed that the paper&#13;
&#13;
                             at times gives the impression that the Bank acts in isolation&#13;
&#13;
                             in the area of good governance.    And, like others, I would in&#13;
&#13;
                             the future like to hear more about the experience of other&#13;
&#13;
                             agencies, including NGOs.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Also, the paper gives the impression that only&#13;
&#13;
                             bilateral donors have a more politically oriented approach,&#13;
&#13;
                             human rights and so forth.    And, I would like to submit on a&#13;
&#13;
                             mere factual basis that EBRD in London has these important&#13;
&#13;
                             areas of democratic governments and good governance in its&#13;
&#13;
                             Articles.    And, the Lome-IV Convention between some 65&#13;
&#13;
                             developing countries in three areas of the world, and&#13;
&#13;
                             particularly in Africa, and the twelve members of the&#13;
&#13;
                             European Union have in its preamble several paragraphs on&#13;
&#13;
                             human rights.&#13;
&#13;
                                         So, I would suggest that the Bank takes notice of&#13;
&#13;
                             that.   Something has developed in some of these institutions.&#13;
&#13;
                                         So, all in all, Mr. Chairman, and given the room of&#13;
&#13;
                             maneuver that the Bank paper indicates, we would hope for&#13;
&#13;
                             more coordination and cooperation among donors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Smet. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C.   20002&#13;
(202) 546Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                        73&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         Mr. Flano shared his feeling with us, and I have&#13;
&#13;
                            some sympathy with it, that in the period between the two&#13;
&#13;
                            documents not so many significant gains obviously have been&#13;
&#13;
                            made, as the paper suggests.     Therefore, I would like to&#13;
&#13;
                            support what other colleagues have said that we would like to&#13;
&#13;
                            know more.&#13;
&#13;
                                         I know it is difficult to measure how successful&#13;
&#13;
                            these efforts were.     And, Mr. Flano also reminded us that the&#13;
&#13;
                            research program, which is important, has not yet been&#13;
&#13;
                            addressed as it seems.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Well, Mr. Chairman, Rome was not built in one day&#13;
&#13;
                            and, therefore, we should temper our impatience, however&#13;
&#13;
                            important this subject is.     But, we do encourage the Bank to&#13;
&#13;
                            continue building the edifice of good governance.     And, I&#13;
&#13;
                            support Mr. Flano's plea for a more proactive role in the&#13;
&#13;
                            future.&#13;
&#13;
                                         As to participation, in conclusion, Mr. Chairman,&#13;
&#13;
                            the Wapenhans Report focusing on ownership and the new&#13;
&#13;
                            disclosure policy would certainly advance this important&#13;
&#13;
                            feature in the future.     Therefore, I was delighted to hear&#13;
&#13;
                            that the Bank does envisage to have this report published&#13;
&#13;
                            after some editing, which will be an additional step to&#13;
&#13;
                            portray and inform the rest of the world about the progress&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORnNG CO., INC.&#13;
'07 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
(202) ,46Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                      74&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             that the Bank has been making in this important field and the&#13;
&#13;
                             auspices and the main line of its activities.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. PRESTON:   Thank you, Mr. Fischer.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Mr. Shihata.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. SHlHATA:   I think Mr. Gerber and Mr. Fischer&#13;
&#13;
                             made interesting points that may require some clarification&#13;
&#13;
                             on my point.&#13;
&#13;
                                       First, on human rights, it is true that human&#13;
&#13;
                             rights are indivisible, but in the sense that they are all&#13;
&#13;
                             needed for human progress and development.   But, it is also&#13;
&#13;
                             true that human rights can be divisible for other purposes,&#13;
&#13;
                             like specialization of the organizations which deal with&#13;
&#13;
                             them.   For instance, the UN Commission on Human Rights deals&#13;
&#13;
                             with all aspects of human rights, whereas a financial&#13;
&#13;
                             institution like the World Bank is expected to deal with the&#13;
&#13;
                             aspects of human rights that are relevant to its mandate,&#13;
&#13;
                             because if the Bank acts otherwise, it will be stepping&#13;
&#13;
                             outside its purposes and, therefore, acting ultra vires,&#13;
&#13;
                             without legal powers.&#13;
&#13;
                                        The pOint here is, in fact, that there could be&#13;
&#13;
                             situations where human rights' violations, even political&#13;
&#13;
                             human rights' violations, are of such dimension that they may&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
'07 C Street, N .E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
(2021   ~46-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;run                                                                                         75&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             be relevant to the Bank.     This point has been recognized in&#13;
&#13;
                             the memorandum I circulated in 1990, which said that the&#13;
&#13;
                             degree of respect paid by a government to political and civil&#13;
&#13;
                             rights, as opposed to other human rights, cannot be considere&#13;
&#13;
                             in itself a basis for the Bank's decision to make loans to&#13;
&#13;
                             that government.     Violation of political rights may, however,&#13;
&#13;
                             reach such proportions as to become a Bank concern.     And,&#13;
&#13;
                             there are really two cases for this, either due to significan&#13;
&#13;
                             direct economic effects or if it results in international&#13;
&#13;
                             obligations relevant to the Bank such as those mandated by&#13;
&#13;
                             binding decisions of the UN Security Council.&#13;
&#13;
                                          But, outside that scope, I really believe that the&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank would be acting outside its legal boundaries.&#13;
&#13;
                                          On the question of the military expenditures, I&#13;
&#13;
                             think we should distinguish between two issues.     First, the&#13;
&#13;
                             conversion of military facilities into civil production.&#13;
&#13;
                             This is not only within the Bank's action, but it is provided&#13;
&#13;
                             explicitly in the Articles of Agreement, which, mind you,&#13;
&#13;
                             these Articles were written immediately after the second&#13;
&#13;
                             world war, and one of the purposes of the Bank was to assist&#13;
&#13;
                             countries in what it said the reconversion of facilities for&#13;
&#13;
                             civil use.&#13;
&#13;
                                          If I may read the actual language, "To assist in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
(202) H6Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                        76&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             the reconstruction and development of territories of members&#13;
&#13;
                             by facilitating the investment of capital for productive&#13;
&#13;
                             purposes, including the restoration of economies destroyed or&#13;
&#13;
                             disrupted by warl the reconversion of productive facilities&#13;
&#13;
                             to peace-time needs l and the encouragement of the development&#13;
&#13;
                             of productive facilities and resources in less developed&#13;
&#13;
                             countries".&#13;
&#13;
                                         So, this is the basic objective of the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
                                         The other issue is the level of military&#13;
&#13;
                             expenditures.    And, this matter has been debated here l   and I&#13;
&#13;
                             think you have reached the right conclusion that the Bank can&#13;
&#13;
                             address this issue only in terms of the resources needed for&#13;
&#13;
                             economic development.     And, if the level of expenditure on&#13;
&#13;
                             non-developmental purposes is too high or is rising, it may&#13;
&#13;
                             be a matter of concern for the Bank, and the Bank can take&#13;
&#13;
                             stock but in a sensitive manner at a high level with the&#13;
&#13;
                             officials concerned, addressing the aggregates without going&#13;
&#13;
                             into the details of military requirements.&#13;
&#13;
                                         The last question is the comparison with other&#13;
&#13;
                             institutions.     Each institution has its mandate l and its&#13;
&#13;
                             Articles, et cetera.     For instance, the EBRD has a political&#13;
&#13;
                             mandate I   and it is written in its Articles.   In facti they&#13;
&#13;
                             have a Political Department.     That is very different, almost&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
(202) 546.6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                     77&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             the opposite, of the World Bank situation.    The same may be&#13;
&#13;
                             said about other institutions.    So, this has to be kept in&#13;
&#13;
                             mind.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. PRESTON:    Mr. Fischer.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. FISCHER:    Just to express my greatest&#13;
&#13;
                             appreciation for what Mr. Shihata said and what he has done&#13;
&#13;
                             in the past on this important issue to advance it within the&#13;
&#13;
                             Articles of Agreement.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I   just wonder, Mr. Shihata, if in the re-edited&#13;
&#13;
                             form this reference to the conversion aspect in our Articles&#13;
&#13;
                             that he has reminded us of may not be taken up.&#13;
&#13;
  {&#13;
  '.&#13;
                                       My reference to EBRD, Mr. Chairman, and Lome was,&#13;
&#13;
                             as I explicitly said, a factual one.     And, if you contrast it&#13;
&#13;
                             between the Bank, on the one hand, and bilateral donors, I&#13;
&#13;
                             just wanted to supplement this by saying there are some&#13;
&#13;
                             organizations or agreements already that for whatever reasons&#13;
&#13;
                             put a greater emphasis.&#13;
&#13;
                                       This is not meant to say in any way that I am&#13;
&#13;
                             advocating something similar.    It was merely factual.   And, I&#13;
&#13;
                             said this expressly, but I think for the sake of an exhaustiv&#13;
&#13;
                             description of that situation, it may be good to have that&#13;
&#13;
                             reference somewhere.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C.     20002&#13;
(202) ,46Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                       78&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. PRESTON:    Thank you, Mr. Fischer.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Ms. Cordeiro.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MS. CORDEIRO:   Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                       As many others before us, we also welcome the&#13;
&#13;
                             opportunity to discuss this important matter.       We have before&#13;
&#13;
                             us a very good report, a comprehensive one, well prepared,&#13;
&#13;
                             well documented with specific country cases both at the Bank&#13;
&#13;
                             initiative and at the borrower initiative.&#13;
&#13;
                                       We agree with the definition of the dimensions for&#13;
&#13;
                             the Bank work of governance.    We actually would like to say&#13;
&#13;
                             that we endorse the most controversial area of human rights&#13;
&#13;
                             in the way it has been put forward in the report.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The report itself recognizes, and even experience i&#13;
&#13;
                             the Bank, in the work on governance is also in terms of&#13;
&#13;
                             dimensions, is also in terms of regions.     We hope that this&#13;
&#13;
                             imbalance will be corrected in the future and more attention&#13;
&#13;
                             will be given to more recent areas of work.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Concerning the issue of public sector management,&#13;
&#13;
                             which appears to be the one where the Bank has done more and&#13;
&#13;
                             also feels more comfortable in measuring and identifying both&#13;
&#13;
                             inputs and in some areas outputs, we would like to express&#13;
&#13;
                             our support to the reference made before that public sector&#13;
&#13;
                             management goes hand in hand with private sector development,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
(202)   ~46-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                      79&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             and those links need to be clearly maintained.&#13;
&#13;
                                       In other areas, we welcome the endorsement of&#13;
&#13;
                             further work in areas as participation, decentralization,&#13;
&#13;
                             human rights, military spending.&#13;
&#13;
                                       In the area of participation, we perceive it on a&#13;
&#13;
                             two-fold approach -- building local ownership and&#13;
&#13;
                             strengthening accountability.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Local ownership has been already a dimension of our&#13;
&#13;
                             project-related work, in particular to ensure better&#13;
&#13;
                             implementation.   We think that it can be expanded to other&#13;
&#13;
                             areas and, as others have recommended, participation can be&#13;
&#13;
                             brought into the dialogue on macroeconomic management and&#13;
&#13;
                             into structural adjustment programs.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Concerning the decentralization, we see the subject&#13;
&#13;
                             very linked with the role of state.    And, as the best&#13;
&#13;
                             solution for a balanced and culturally appropriate set of&#13;
&#13;
                             tools, it cannot be decided outside of the country specifics,&#13;
&#13;
                             of the culture, but also of the resources both financially&#13;
&#13;
                             and of human capital available into the country.&#13;
&#13;
                                       So, we believe that the balance between central&#13;
&#13;
                             government and local government is important.    And, as I said&#13;
&#13;
                             before, one can draw a line between macroeconomic management&#13;
&#13;
                             basically at the central level while delivery of service will&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C.     20002&#13;
(202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                       80&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               end at the local level.   However, when it comes to the&#13;
&#13;
                               regulatory functions, a mixed approach might be appropriate.&#13;
&#13;
                               But again, it has to be designed in the context of each&#13;
&#13;
                               country.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Concerning human rights, we agree with those who&#13;
&#13;
                               have expressed that the Bank has to address this in the&#13;
&#13;
                               context of its mandate as contributing to economic and social&#13;
&#13;
                               development.   And, we agree with Mr. Choksi's suggestion that&#13;
&#13;
                               we publish the report and maintain the visible words.     The&#13;
&#13;
                               cost of omitting them will probably be much higher and the&#13;
&#13;
                               Bank should be clearly visible here.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Concerning military spending, our approach is that&#13;
&#13;
                               the Bank should look into that as part of looking for&#13;
&#13;
                               effective and efficient use of public resources.   And, as Mr.&#13;
&#13;
                               Shihata just told us, it is basically the level of resources&#13;
&#13;
                               that we should care about, and basically that is because it&#13;
&#13;
                               affects the resources needed for economic and social&#13;
&#13;
                               development.&#13;
&#13;
                                          We also believe -- and in this aspect in a   differen~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               as others before us -- that the Bank has the right to&#13;
&#13;
                               initiate work in this area.   And, it shouldn't be limited to&#13;
&#13;
                               the initiative taken by the client, by the borrowing country.&#13;
&#13;
                                          In summary, we agree with the recommendations that&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MII.I.ER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C.     20002&#13;
(202) 546Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                       81&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              the report indicates.   We think that this has to be done at&#13;
&#13;
                              the appropriate level and some of the reference indicated in&#13;
&#13;
                              the report point out the sensitive issue and for the need to&#13;
&#13;
                              determine appropriate level from the Bank side, as well as an&#13;
&#13;
                              appropriate forum in the countries.&#13;
&#13;
                                        The findings and lessons emerging in this analysis&#13;
&#13;
                              deserve our support.    The paper is in the right direction,&#13;
&#13;
                              makes a strong attempt to strengthen the Bank's role in the&#13;
&#13;
                              area of governance.&#13;
&#13;
                                        We have a little regret, as others before, that the&#13;
&#13;
                              analysis concentrates on Part II countries.    And, in&#13;
&#13;
                              particular areas I am not going to repeat what namely Mr.&#13;
&#13;
                              Fischer and Mr. Gerber eloquently said that Part I countries&#13;
&#13;
                              have a major responsibility and should also contribute for&#13;
&#13;
                              good governance.&#13;
&#13;
                                        We would like to commend staff for this report, and&#13;
&#13;
                              we basically agree with the suggestions that the report has,&#13;
&#13;
                              as well as the suggestion made before that in two, three&#13;
&#13;
                              years' time to have a follow-up report.&#13;
&#13;
                                        We would like, finally, to address the issue of the&#13;
&#13;
                              implications of governance on Bank operations.    And, there is&#13;
&#13;
                              a particular dimension of this implication that concerns us.&#13;
&#13;
                                        The paper makes a good and strong case for having&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N .E.&#13;
Washington. D.C.      20002&#13;
(202) 546Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12;run                                                                                         82&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             governance issues and concerns based permanently in Bank&#13;
&#13;
                             work.   Good governance is a condition sine qua non for&#13;
&#13;
                             economic and social development.     It is also a critical&#13;
&#13;
                             condition for any kind of aid to be effective.     It is,&#13;
&#13;
                             therefore, extremely important that the issue of governance&#13;
&#13;
                             is taken in full consideration in designing our country&#13;
&#13;
                             assistance strategies and our projects.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Because it is so important and it has to guide the&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank's work, the issue of governance must not be trivialized&#13;
&#13;
                             and approached with an accounting modality of the type how&#13;
&#13;
                             many projects to have a governance component, or even a&#13;
&#13;
                             poorly editorial concern, where is the paragraph on&#13;
&#13;
                             governance.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Governance is not a self-contained issue.     It has a&#13;
&#13;
                             multitude of facets.     It is imbedded in the macroeconomic&#13;
&#13;
                             management.     It is imbedded in the good use of public&#13;
&#13;
                             resources.     It is imbedded in the transparency and&#13;
&#13;
                             accountability of policy choices.     It is imbedded in the good&#13;
&#13;
                             functioning of the markets, enforcement of ownership and&#13;
&#13;
                             exchange rates.     It is imbedded in the full and fair&#13;
&#13;
                             participation of all segments of population to economic and&#13;
&#13;
                             social life.&#13;
&#13;
                                          When a country assistance strategy is a good one,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
'07 C Srf""'. N.E.&#13;
WlI5hingron. D.C. 20002&#13;
(202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                        83&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             the issue of governance comes up clearly from the analysis of&#13;
&#13;
                             the issues, such as those above mentioned, without necessaril&#13;
&#13;
                             mentioning the words of governance.&#13;
&#13;
                                          If a project is a good project, it has taken into&#13;
&#13;
                             consideration all the possible elements that may lead to its&#13;
&#13;
                             good and successful implementation, the ownership of the&#13;
&#13;
                             project, the participation of the beneficiary to the project&#13;
&#13;
                             and so on.&#13;
&#13;
                                          We do not need to have an additional area of&#13;
&#13;
                             special emphasis in order to make sure that governance is&#13;
&#13;
                             handled appropriately.     We do not need to attach yet another&#13;
&#13;
                             objective to those already existing to the individual&#13;
&#13;
                             operations.&#13;
&#13;
                                          We have said that before, and we would like to&#13;
&#13;
                             repeat it again.     The fact that any CAS has a paragraph on&#13;
&#13;
                             each of the items does not mean that it is a good CAS.        The&#13;
&#13;
                             same applies to projects.&#13;
&#13;
                                          If there is a message that we would like to convey&#13;
&#13;
                             at this stage, it is that governance does not mean&#13;
&#13;
                             additionality of objectives to meet our resources to use.           We&#13;
&#13;
                             would like to see better country analysis, better project&#13;
&#13;
                             preparation that faces the key factors and governance will be&#13;
&#13;
                             across many factors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Stteet. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C.     20002&#13;
17M\ '4('.('''{'('&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                          84&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        It might not require any additionality of anything.&#13;
&#13;
                             We agree with Mr. Cosgrove that the issue of skills does not&#13;
&#13;
                             require an increase of staffing as well as an increase of&#13;
&#13;
                             financial resources.&#13;
&#13;
                                        What we perceive is that the issue of governance&#13;
&#13;
                             implies that the Bank will continue to address it in a broad&#13;
&#13;
                             and comprehensive way, in a country focus and in an&#13;
&#13;
                             appropriate manner.      It may be through specific instruments&#13;
&#13;
                             including lending.      We would expect to continue seeing the&#13;
&#13;
                             policy package including aspects to improve good governance.&#13;
&#13;
                             We would expect to see it in project design.         In other cases,&#13;
&#13;
                             free-standing loans might be the appropriate vehicle to&#13;
&#13;
                             strengthen the institution that will contribute to good&#13;
&#13;
                             governance.&#13;
&#13;
                                        But, the wide range of means still remains beyond&#13;
&#13;
                             lending.   The major role in ESW and in the policy dialogue&#13;
&#13;
                             must be given to the issue of governance.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                        MR. PRESTON:     Thank you, Ms. Cordeiro.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Mr. Zhang.&#13;
&#13;
                                        MR. ZHANG:     Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Like others, we welcome the discussion too and&#13;
&#13;
                             commend the staff for the report.      No doubt the subject at&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MIUER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C.     20002&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                        85&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             hand is of a nature that these days can all too easily&#13;
&#13;
                             energize our discussion.&#13;
&#13;
                                       However, I intend not to engage further in general&#13;
&#13;
                             statements.    Rather, with your permission, Mr. Chairman, I&#13;
&#13;
                             would like to make only a couple of specific comments so far&#13;
&#13;
                             as they relate to the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Clearly, governance is essential and important for&#13;
&#13;
                             development.    In principle, we take to such terms as better&#13;
&#13;
                             PSM, greater accountability, better legal framework and&#13;
&#13;
                             greater transparency just like others.     But, it is also a&#13;
&#13;
                             fact as we move from the intended objectives to preferred&#13;
&#13;
                             instruments.&#13;
&#13;
                                       As we move from desired ends to chosen means, it is&#13;
&#13;
                             not all agreement.     Indeed, we substantively differ.   As we&#13;
&#13;
                             all know, there are fundamental reasons both for the agreemen&#13;
&#13;
                             and the differences.    Accordingly, it is our view that in the&#13;
&#13;
                             context of the Bank, our common guidelines should, must and&#13;
&#13;
                             indeed can only be our Articles of Agreement.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I believe the paper is sufficiently clear in this&#13;
&#13;
                             regard, and we would like to embrace it.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Over the past two years, it is always as defined by&#13;
&#13;
                             the Articles of Agreement, the Bank in the area of governance&#13;
&#13;
                             has done a lot.    Achievements are substantial and must be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12;nm                                                                                       86&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             recognized.&#13;
&#13;
                                       However, like quite a few previous speakers made it&#13;
&#13;
                             amply clear, governance as such does not exist in abstract&#13;
&#13;
                             but only does in the broader context of the country's&#13;
&#13;
                             economic and social development.    Indeed, like it or not, it&#13;
&#13;
                             has an inseparable relationship with the country's overall&#13;
&#13;
                             circumstances.   For example, in our view, policies, however&#13;
&#13;
                             high sounding, that lead to the continuation, not to say&#13;
&#13;
                             increase, in poverty will not be sustainable in the long-run&#13;
&#13;
                             and, therefore, not acceptable to the broad people.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Therefore, for our governance work and effort to be&#13;
&#13;
                             effective, which we all want, approaches must be tailored to&#13;
&#13;
                             the country.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Looking ahead, this is a subject where quite a few&#13;
&#13;
                             Executive Directors have already commented on.    For our part,&#13;
&#13;
                             we share the view stated on page 55 that now is not the time&#13;
&#13;
                             to extend or expand our scope; rather, we should confine&#13;
&#13;
                             ourselves to deepening and improving our effort, bearing in&#13;
&#13;
                             mind always what our Articles of Agreement set down in this&#13;
&#13;
                             regard.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Finally, a ,short comment about the question of&#13;
&#13;
                             skills mix.    No doubt the call and the request for that&#13;
&#13;
                             matter has a valid point that we can all easily understand.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12;run                                                                                            87&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    But, I also note this question seems to lately have been&#13;
&#13;
                                    embraced almost without any thinking about the cost and&#13;
&#13;
                                    consequences.&#13;
&#13;
                                              I must quickly confess how this improved or called&#13;
&#13;
                                    for mix can be easily 'done without direct implications from&#13;
&#13;
                                    our budget, on which, as I gather, views appear to point to&#13;
&#13;
                                    the contrary.   Perhaps the budget season has passed or the&#13;
&#13;
                                    budget season has not arrived yet.&#13;
&#13;
                                              Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                              MR. PRESTON:   Thank you, Mr. Zhang.&#13;
&#13;
                                              Mr. Haas.&#13;
&#13;
                                              MR. HAAS:   Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                              Mr. Chairman, there is no doubt in my mind that&#13;
&#13;
                                    governance is a key parameter of all of our day-to-day work&#13;
&#13;
                                    in the Bank.    I would say that we worry about governance as&#13;
&#13;
                                    we breathe, and it would be as awkward to me to wonder&#13;
&#13;
                                    whether we have to talk about it as it would be to wonder&#13;
&#13;
                                    whether we have to talk about economics, and especially from&#13;
&#13;
                                    two points of view.&#13;
&#13;
                                              From an operational one, I think that staff in the&#13;
&#13;
                                    field certainly sometimes feel that the hurdle to correct&#13;
&#13;
                                    implementation of well-designed projects has to do with&#13;
&#13;
                                    governance-linked issues.    And, to that, we have to respond.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C   Str~~t,   N .E.&#13;
Washington, D.C.            20002&#13;
1202) 146.6(,66&#13;
&amp;#12;nm                                                                                        88&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       From the most strategic point of view, I also&#13;
&#13;
                             understand that we might come under the fire of criticism&#13;
&#13;
                             because we did not take sufficiently into account in the&#13;
&#13;
                             design of our projects those issues.    And, to that also,&#13;
&#13;
                             before we maybe come under fire, I think we have to respond.&#13;
&#13;
                                       So, at the same time, it is not a new subject; it&#13;
&#13;
                             is a subject we have discussed already, and there is a frame&#13;
&#13;
                             and, in particular, a legal frame in which we discuss it.&#13;
&#13;
                             The legal frame is the Articles.     Everything has been said; I&#13;
&#13;
                             agree with what Mrs. Herfkens circulated.     I agree with what&#13;
&#13;
                             Mr. Shihata said on that.&#13;
&#13;
                                        I agree, in particular, with what he said on the&#13;
&#13;
                             fact that indirectly we might in our work have an impact on&#13;
&#13;
                             some issues which are not strictly-speaking in the framework&#13;
&#13;
                             of our mandate.   This triggers probably and has to trigger in&#13;
&#13;
                             our action probably even more prudence and caution.     We&#13;
&#13;
                             certainly have to be aware of it, but still, when it comes to&#13;
&#13;
                             our direct influence, to our direct work, then I think we&#13;
&#13;
                             have to focus on what is within our mandates.&#13;
&#13;
                                        It goes without saying.    And, that is extremely&#13;
&#13;
                             wide.   This encompasses certainly, in the first place, public&#13;
&#13;
                             sector management, which also encompasses a broad range of&#13;
&#13;
                             issues, but it also encompasses legal framework, for instance,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C StrÂ«t, N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
(202\ 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;nm                                                                                           89&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             and military expenditures certainly and a wide number of&#13;
&#13;
                             areas that I do not want to expand on now.&#13;
&#13;
                                          What I think is there is no specific autonomy of&#13;
&#13;
                             those subjects.     And, I really believe that there is no&#13;
&#13;
                             evidence that those subjects are self-standing issues to be&#13;
&#13;
                             addressed and that they are, in one way or another, directly&#13;
&#13;
                             and explicitly as recent research has showed it correlated&#13;
&#13;
                             with performance and growth.     I think it is a little bit more&#13;
&#13;
                             complicated than that or more simple.        I don't know.&#13;
&#13;
                                          It is like the oil of the engine, if you will.         It&#13;
&#13;
                             is what makes growth work, what enables development, what&#13;
&#13;
                             makes it possible notably for the Bank's action to be&#13;
&#13;
                             efficient.&#13;
&#13;
                                          So, I think it is probably something that is more&#13;
&#13;
                             practical than conceptual, something that is more material&#13;
&#13;
                             than political and certainly something that is more focused&#13;
&#13;
                             than of a general nature.&#13;
&#13;
                                          And, this is why the question    ~-   and I couldn't&#13;
&#13;
                             agree more here with Ms. Cordeiro -- the question is not to&#13;
&#13;
                             know whether we have to add a new objective to the already&#13;
&#13;
                             extremely long list of ours.     The question is only:       How do&#13;
&#13;
                             we incorporate that concern into our day-to-day work?          That&#13;
&#13;
                             is the only question, I think.     And, I would like not to turn&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                       90&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             to that and to see how we can do that in terms of our goals,&#13;
&#13;
                             our tools and in institutional terms.&#13;
&#13;
                                        In terms of our goals, I would like to put it very&#13;
&#13;
                             simply.   I think, as I said, we want to make our action,&#13;
&#13;
                             let's say our loans and credits, more efficient.    We want to&#13;
&#13;
                             make them work.   That is very close, in fact, to the&#13;
&#13;
                             discussion we had in the Wapenhans Report.    That is, in my&#13;
&#13;
                             view, very much the same one.   What is at stake is the&#13;
&#13;
                             efficiency of the Bank's work, and especially when we have&#13;
&#13;
                             the feeling that it is a key parameter of it.&#13;
&#13;
                                        So, once again, there is in my view, in the first&#13;
&#13;
                             place, a responsibility of the Bank itself.     And, it has been&#13;
&#13;
                             said by others, it is the design of the projects.     We have to&#13;
&#13;
                             tailor them in as realistic manner as possible.     We have to&#13;
&#13;
                             tailor it, as Mr. Zhang said, to the realities of the&#13;
&#13;
                             countries, certainly probably be aware that there are some&#13;
&#13;
                             differences, as Mr. Fischer also said, between poorest&#13;
&#13;
                             countries and others, and be extremely pragmatic, I would say.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Governments and borrowing governments also certainl&#13;
&#13;
                             have their share of responsibility.     They have to commit&#13;
&#13;
                             themselves to increasing the efficiency of, in particular,&#13;
&#13;
                             their public sector and their institutions.     And, probably in&#13;
&#13;
                             that regard, since I was quoting the Wapenhans Report, I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~01   C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
1'01\ ,4.(,.(,(,(,(,&#13;
&amp;#12;run                                                                                        91&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             would like to mention that to help them with the ability to&#13;
&#13;
                             do that and to evaluate how they do that is probably somethin&#13;
&#13;
                             that we should look into and that OED probably could make&#13;
&#13;
                             some proposals on.&#13;
&#13;
                                          In terms of the instruments, I really think that we&#13;
&#13;
                             do not need to add criteria, guidelines.     We have to be&#13;
&#13;
                             extremely cautious.     We have to be cautious everywhere, in&#13;
&#13;
                             particular when it comes to the policy dialogue.     We had&#13;
&#13;
                             extremely precise conclusions two years ago on that.     And, I&#13;
&#13;
                             think they are still valid, about who says what to whom, et&#13;
&#13;
                             cetera.     I don't want to reemphasize; it was clear and put on&#13;
&#13;
                             paper.     I think it remains absolutely valid.&#13;
&#13;
                                         When it comes to the Consultative Groups also, what&#13;
&#13;
                             is said on the Consultative Groups on paper is extremely&#13;
&#13;
                             prudent, cautious, reasonable.     Let's try not to go beyond&#13;
&#13;
                             that.     The Bank is a facilitator in that respect and should&#13;
&#13;
                             not have too much of a proactive role because there is the&#13;
&#13;
                             risk to fall outside the mandate.&#13;
&#13;
                                          More particularly, more specifically, in paragraph&#13;
&#13;
                             81 there are a number of recommendations.     Most of them, I&#13;
&#13;
                             must say, are drafted in a very vague, I should say, careful&#13;
&#13;
                             manner.     I am not sure I understand everything.   Maybe it is&#13;
&#13;
                             good like that.     I guess it can be read in different manners.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Smet. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                        92&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       I would just like for the sake of safety, so to&#13;
&#13;
                             say, to ask if Mr. Shihata could kindly confirm that in his&#13;
&#13;
                             view the way it is drafted and the way it may be implemented&#13;
&#13;
                             will be indeed consistent with our mandate as is stated in&#13;
&#13;
                             our Articles.&#13;
&#13;
                                       But, more generally, let me say that I fully&#13;
&#13;
                             support everything that has been said by Ms. Cordeiro on how&#13;
&#13;
                             to use the heading of governance or rather how not to use it&#13;
&#13;
                             in our documents.   As I said in the beginning, it is somethin&#13;
&#13;
                             that we have to deal with in a permanent manner.    And, it&#13;
&#13;
                             should not be singled out in a way that would add complicatio&#13;
&#13;
                             and certainly not increase efficiency.&#13;
&#13;
                                       And, that leads me to my last point which is more&#13;
&#13;
                             from an institutional point of view, what sort of instruments&#13;
&#13;
                             should we have at hand.   Well, there is no doubt in my view&#13;
&#13;
                             that we should pay more attention to public sector management.&#13;
&#13;
                             We have said that a number of times.     I think that the recent&#13;
&#13;
                             OED report made it clear also, crystal clear.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Institutionally-speaking, it seems to have been&#13;
&#13;
                             somewhat forgotten in the chart of the World Bank. Now, it&#13;
&#13;
                             has been corrected a little bit and there is a department in&#13;
&#13;
                             charge of it or a unit in charge of it.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I am not sure we need experts.     I will be extremely&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Sttcet, N .E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
{1M\ ~4h.hi\('''&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                       93&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             clear on that.     So, I disagree with Mr. Mamadou Dia.   And, we&#13;
&#13;
                             used to say in my country that the specialty of civil&#13;
&#13;
                             servants is not to be specialists.     And, I think the reason&#13;
&#13;
                             is extremely simple, it is because they are supposed to look&#13;
&#13;
                             at things from a broader point of view and not to be&#13;
&#13;
                             technicians only.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I think this has to be looked into.     And,&#13;
&#13;
                             furthermore, what I expect from staff of the Bank, fully&#13;
&#13;
                             aware of the necessity to increase the attention to the&#13;
&#13;
                             public sector management issue, is to be open-minded and not&#13;
&#13;
                             to impose models and ideologies, but, on the contrary, to be&#13;
&#13;
                             able to see what is needed, given the institutions and the&#13;
&#13;
                             culture of the countries concerned.&#13;
&#13;
                                       So, really, here, I would encourage the development,&#13;
&#13;
                             as I think is already the case, of a network of people more&#13;
&#13;
                             in charge of it throughout the regions.     That would be&#13;
&#13;
                             probably something useful so that we have a way to check and&#13;
&#13;
                             monitor how much and how it is taken into account and how&#13;
&#13;
                             much progress is made, but not to separate probably a special&#13;
&#13;
                             unit of experts.&#13;
&#13;
                                       So, Mr. Chairman, in conclusion, let me just say I&#13;
&#13;
                             think that we have already a very heavy agenda.     We are not&#13;
&#13;
                             supposed to solve all problems, not especially those who are&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N,E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                     94&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             supposed to be in the hands of other institutions, notably of&#13;
&#13;
                             the UN.&#13;
&#13;
                                          We don't want to add to the list of our objectives.&#13;
&#13;
                             We don't want to go into the direction that would reduce the&#13;
&#13;
                             universality of our membership now that we have come to it.&#13;
&#13;
                             What we want to do probably is to increase our efficiency and&#13;
&#13;
                             be extremely cautious to pursue not other agendas but really&#13;
&#13;
                             that one.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
                                          MR. PRESTON:   Thank you, Mr. Haas.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Maybe Mr. Shihata would reassure Mr. Haas before we&#13;
&#13;
                             move to the next speaker.&#13;
&#13;
                                          MR. SHlHATA:   I think Mr. Haas is right that the&#13;
&#13;
                             language might lend itself to some misunderstanding, and in&#13;
&#13;
                             the published text we should make it clear that the governanc&#13;
&#13;
                             issues we are speaking of are those which are relevant to the&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank's mandate and do not contradict its Articles of&#13;
&#13;
                             Agreement.&#13;
&#13;
                                          The comment was relevant to the suggestion that in&#13;
&#13;
                             the future country assistance strategy papers, it says here,&#13;
&#13;
                             "will raise the profile of governance" without saying what&#13;
&#13;
                             type of issues, and also that the policies and procedures&#13;
&#13;
                             which replace the Operational Directives will address aspects&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MIUJ!R REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
'07 C Street,   N,c.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
I")n")\ Y{'~Aht:h&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                       95&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             of governance.&#13;
&#13;
                                       We should make it clear what we are speaking of are&#13;
&#13;
                             the relevant aspects to our mandate.&#13;
&#13;
                                       And, of all sources related to emphasizing the nonÂ­&#13;
&#13;
                             political nature of the Bank's work, I would like to quote a&#13;
&#13;
                             document issued by the U.S. Government at the time the&#13;
&#13;
                             Articles of Agreement were prepared, when the draft was&#13;
&#13;
                             prepared in February 1944.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The U.S. Treasury issued a very valuable document&#13;
&#13;
                             explaining the document called "Questions and Answers on the&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank for Reconstruction and Development".   And, at one part,&#13;
&#13;
                             this document reads as follows:&#13;
&#13;
                                       "The Bank is designed to be an international&#13;
&#13;
                             economic agency to facilitate productive international&#13;
&#13;
                             investment without regard to political considerations.       In&#13;
&#13;
                             deciding on loan applications, the Bank is not to be&#13;
&#13;
                             influenced by the political character of the country&#13;
&#13;
                             requesting the credits.   This provision is part of the&#13;
&#13;
                             general requirement that the Bank shall scrupulously avoid&#13;
&#13;
                             interference in the political affairs of member countries.&#13;
&#13;
                                       tiThe greatest assurance that the operations would&#13;
&#13;
                             be based exclusively on economic considerations is given in&#13;
&#13;
                             the provision of the proposal.    No loan can be made to a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C.     20002&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                        96&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             country for other than purely economic purposes and the&#13;
&#13;
                             standards which prospective borrowers must meet are those&#13;
&#13;
                             which protect the economic interests of lender and borrower."&#13;
&#13;
                                       The document ends in this respect by stating that&#13;
&#13;
                             "It remains true that the possibility always exists that&#13;
&#13;
                             pressure will be exerted to induce the Bank to extend foreign&#13;
&#13;
                             credits because they are politically necessary" -- that is on&#13;
&#13;
                             a political account.&#13;
&#13;
                                       "We recognize, however, that no set of rules will&#13;
&#13;
                             of itself completely eliminate political considerations and&#13;
&#13;
                             that proper limitation of the Bank's activities depends&#13;
&#13;
                             ultimately on the character of the men responsible for its&#13;
&#13;
                             operations."&#13;
&#13;
                                       (Laughter.)&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. PRESTON:     I am sorry Mr. Kline wasn't in the&#13;
&#13;
                             room to hear that.     You might want to see if there is an&#13;
&#13;
                             extra copy for the Treasury.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Mr. Snoy.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. SNOY:     Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                       First of all, I would like to thank very much Mr.&#13;
&#13;
                             Shihata for his latest quotation.     And, I would say that I&#13;
&#13;
                             fully concur with Mrs. Herfkens' statement circulated in&#13;
&#13;
                             advance, as well as with those of other colleagues.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
{202l S46Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                        97&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          Like here and like others, I welcome this report&#13;
&#13;
                                and commend the staff for a very good presentation of the&#13;
&#13;
                                progress made by the Bank in a short period of time.     I also&#13;
&#13;
                                very much appreciate the delicate balance -- and everything&#13;
&#13;
                                in this discussion is a question of balance    which has been&#13;
&#13;
                                struck in the report and, more importantly, in the Bank&#13;
&#13;
                                activities between the broad range of issues in governance&#13;
&#13;
                                and those which pertain exactly to the Bank's mandate.     And,&#13;
&#13;
                                that is really the center of our debate.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Given the many aspects which are part of a&#13;
&#13;
                                comprehensive definition of governance, it is rather difficul&#13;
&#13;
                                and perhaps unnecessary to assess Bank interventions in favor&#13;
&#13;
                                of good governance in quantitative terms.&#13;
&#13;
                                          The main thrust of the report conveys the message&#13;
&#13;
                                that Bank commitment to governance is serious and that&#13;
&#13;
                                eventually matters.   Such commitment actually translates in a&#13;
&#13;
                                certain approach which pervades all activities and it should&#13;
&#13;
                                be best reflected in country assistance strategies and&#13;
&#13;
                                portfolio reviews.&#13;
&#13;
                                          We welcome also the research which is underway in&#13;
&#13;
                                the Private Sector Development Department of the Bank to&#13;
&#13;
                                investigate the relationship between governance capacity and&#13;
&#13;
                                successful economic reform in developing countries.    And, I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C St",ct. N .E.&#13;
Washington. D.C.        20002&#13;
&amp;#12;run                                                                                      98&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             have noted that governance in that particular instance is&#13;
&#13;
                             assessed in terms of the capacity of the state to avoid the&#13;
&#13;
                             capture by prominent economic interests and to formulate and&#13;
&#13;
                             implement policy independently in the public interest.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I understand that the results of this research will&#13;
&#13;
                             be presented in a conference in the Bank later in June next&#13;
&#13;
                             year and I hope the Board will be involved.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Let me say also that I am very interested by the&#13;
&#13;
                             import of Mr. Mamadou Dia on the governance approach to civil&#13;
&#13;
                             service reform in Sub-Saharan Africa, and I hope that some of&#13;
&#13;
                             its findings can be discussed in the context of some of our&#13;
&#13;
                             country assistance strategies in Africa.&#13;
&#13;
                                       On many occasions, reference is very rightly and&#13;
&#13;
                             appropriately made in the report to the necessity to take&#13;
&#13;
                             into account country circumstances and interests if governanc&#13;
&#13;
                             is to improve.&#13;
&#13;
                                       To name a few:   Inclusion of the cultural and&#13;
&#13;
                             social settings in the policy advice to public sector&#13;
&#13;
                             management; respect for the social, religious, customary and&#13;
&#13;
                             historical factors in a society for the effectiveness of&#13;
&#13;
                             legal reforms.&#13;
&#13;
                                       In other discussions, we might refer to ownership,&#13;
&#13;
                             with a strong civil society participating in public affairs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Suect, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12;nm                                                                                       99&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             These are indeed very critical aspects that must be taken&#13;
&#13;
                             into account for good governance and development effectiveness&#13;
&#13;
                             altogether.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I insist also, Mr. Chairman, on this idea of&#13;
&#13;
                             strengthening civil society, and I am delighted that it was&#13;
&#13;
                             mentioned several times in our document.&#13;
&#13;
                                       In the same vein, the report also acknowledged that&#13;
&#13;
                             a diversified skill mix is necessary for the Bank to increase&#13;
&#13;
                             its involvement in governance, but I must say that I remain a&#13;
&#13;
                             little bit skeptical.     I am not sure that our recruitment and&#13;
&#13;
                             training efforts in this respect are satisfactory.     I&#13;
&#13;
                             welcome, however, what Mr. Stevens said, and I hope we will&#13;
&#13;
                             follow our discussions on this subject.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Public sector management is the first and basic&#13;
&#13;
                             element of governance, which relates to the Bank mandate, but&#13;
&#13;
                             it is increasingly envisaged by the Bank in a broad and&#13;
&#13;
                             comprehensive approach.     I welcome this evolution, which will&#13;
&#13;
                             help overcome the difficulties encountered so far and the&#13;
&#13;
                             mixed results that have been achieved.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Mr. Plano made very interesting observations on&#13;
&#13;
                             this aspect in his statement, and I share most of them.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The report leaves me the impression that Bank&#13;
&#13;
                             involvement is more frequent and more pronounced in the low-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
(2(m ~,K('('('('&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                     100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             income countries.   I recognize that these countries need more&#13;
&#13;
                             frequently help from the Bank to tackle these problems and&#13;
&#13;
                             also that donors requested IDA to monitor governance&#13;
&#13;
                             performance in that area.&#13;
&#13;
                                       But, middle-income countries also need help, and I&#13;
&#13;
                             would caution against any bias in this respect.   And, I also&#13;
&#13;
                             agree with Mr. Gerber's remarks about the need for good&#13;
&#13;
                             governance in the aid, trade and environmental policies of&#13;
&#13;
                             Part I countries.   And, I am curious, like Mr. AI-Khaled, to&#13;
&#13;
                             see the outcome of the research work underway on measures&#13;
&#13;
                             that industrialized countries could take to discourage&#13;
&#13;
                             corrupt practices by their exporters.&#13;
&#13;
                                       The review of Bank's activities in public sector&#13;
&#13;
                             management provides me with the occasion to reiterate the&#13;
&#13;
                             well-known views of our Chair on the role of the public and&#13;
&#13;
                             private sector in the development process.    The role of the&#13;
&#13;
                             public sector is certainly to provide an enabling environment&#13;
&#13;
                             for the private sector which is the driving force in the&#13;
&#13;
                             economic growth.    And, we are all in favor of private sector&#13;
&#13;
                             development and support the Bank's work on private sector&#13;
&#13;
                             assessments.&#13;
&#13;
                                       But, like Mrs. Herfkens, I objected to the notion&#13;
&#13;
                             in Box 41 page 8, that tax regulations are almost necessarily&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N,E.&#13;
W:ashington. D,C. 20002&#13;
{202l   ~46Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                        101&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             burdensome.     I repeat what I said, taxes are what we pay to&#13;
&#13;
                             live in a civilized world.     And, one of the priorities for&#13;
&#13;
                             the Bank's work in public sector management is surely in the&#13;
&#13;
                             strengthening of revenue collection agencies.&#13;
&#13;
                                          The development of any society must not be reduced&#13;
&#13;
                             to the growth of its economy.     All other aspects of this&#13;
&#13;
                             society must be taken into account and must transform and&#13;
&#13;
                             improve if this society is to achieve socio-politically&#13;
&#13;
                             sustainable development.&#13;
&#13;
                                          The role of the public sector goes beyond fostering&#13;
&#13;
                             the private sector or even to create a strong regulatory&#13;
&#13;
                             framework.     It encompasses the efficient provision of a&#13;
&#13;
                             number of essential public goods, in justice, in collective&#13;
&#13;
                             security, infrastructure, human resource development, safety&#13;
&#13;
                             net and social security, the environment, the preservation of&#13;
&#13;
                             the cultural heritage and other areas with pronounced&#13;
&#13;
                             externalities which can only be determined at the country&#13;
&#13;
                             level.&#13;
&#13;
                                          The Bank's approach of the public sector should&#13;
&#13;
                             thus be comprehensive and it should consider the public and&#13;
&#13;
                             private sector as both equally important for sustainable&#13;
&#13;
                             development but in different roles.&#13;
&#13;
                                          On the questions of military expenditures, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
'07 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
(202) ,46Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12;nm                                                                                      102&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             report puts Bank's intervention in the right perspective.        As&#13;
&#13;
                             for other issues of governance, the institution has made the&#13;
&#13;
                             right balance between different aspects, and I encourage the&#13;
&#13;
                             continuation of its efforts along this same line.&#13;
&#13;
                                          I particularly welcome and support the World Bank's&#13;
&#13;
                             involvement in demobilization and reintegration of military&#13;
&#13;
                             personnel.     Box 22 is particularly useful and demonstrates&#13;
&#13;
                             the peace dividend which may result from demobilization and&#13;
&#13;
                             reintegration programs.&#13;
&#13;
                                          On the broader aspect of governance, I am pleased&#13;
&#13;
                             with the Bank's interventions in support of legislative and&#13;
&#13;
                             judicial branches.     These are indeed a crucial part of the&#13;
&#13;
                             institutional basis for good governance.     The Bank's support&#13;
&#13;
                             to legal reform, the establishment of the legal framework for&#13;
&#13;
                             private sector development and institution building was&#13;
&#13;
                             highly appreciated in the countries in transition represented&#13;
&#13;
                             by this Chair.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Concerning accountability, I was surprised that the&#13;
&#13;
                             report made no reference to the questions of evaluation,&#13;
&#13;
                             capacity development in borrowing countries, which we know to&#13;
&#13;
                             be of great importance further to the Wapenhans Report and&#13;
&#13;
                             our most recent discussion of OED evaluation results.&#13;
&#13;
                                          About transparency, I am pleased with the remarks&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12;nm                                                                                     103&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             in the report that governance also implies transparency in&#13;
&#13;
                             the functioning of the private sector as well.    The&#13;
&#13;
                             requirement to devise a legal and regulatory framework which&#13;
&#13;
                             makes the right balance between general interest and some&#13;
&#13;
                             special interest is a useful reminder.&#13;
&#13;
                                       In conclusion, I would not mind emphasizing again&#13;
&#13;
                             the importance of governance as regards development&#13;
&#13;
                             effectiveness of Bank's projects, as well as the necessity&#13;
&#13;
                             for the Bank to pursue its efforts in helping countries&#13;
&#13;
                             improve their record while broadening its knowledge of the&#13;
&#13;
                             different aspects of the issue.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. PRESTON:    Thank you, Mr. Snoy.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Mr. O'Murchu.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. O'MURCHU:    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I will be very brief, I hope.    I just welcome the&#13;
&#13;
                             general endorsement, the very positive approach of the Board&#13;
&#13;
                             to this paper.   And taking that in the context of the&#13;
&#13;
                             proposed publication of the report, could I take it that the&#13;
&#13;
                             Board's endorsement will go with the report?     I think it is&#13;
&#13;
                             an important signal to the Part I governments and could&#13;
&#13;
                             sustain their support for the international financial&#13;
&#13;
                             institutions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
(202) ,46Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                      104&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          Secondly, I think it could send a good signal from&#13;
&#13;
                             the staff.     I notice from Box 19 that there was considerable&#13;
&#13;
                             reticence on their part on addressing the questions of&#13;
&#13;
                             governance.    And, maybe the fact that a strong signal is&#13;
&#13;
                             going from the Board, it might be useful in that respect.&#13;
&#13;
                                          On the question of the governance and the country&#13;
&#13;
                             assistance strategies, I am not sure that I understand Ms.&#13;
&#13;
                             Cordeiro's point fully.     I think that there is a requirement&#13;
&#13;
                             for the country assistance strategies for IDA countries to&#13;
&#13;
                             address that issue specifically.     And, I welcome the mention&#13;
&#13;
                             in paragraph 38 of this report of the room for a more&#13;
&#13;
                             systematic treatment of governance issues in the CAS.&#13;
&#13;
                                          I think in that respect we don't want to send it&#13;
&#13;
                             out as an objective, but if it is there as a requirement to&#13;
&#13;
                             address specifically, it could have the good effect of&#13;
&#13;
                             focusing people's minds on the issues.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Finally, I would like to say that I do agree with&#13;
&#13;
                             Ms. Cordeiro and Mr. Cosgrove about the issue of costs.       And,&#13;
&#13;
                             in that, I wonder would it be possible, Mr. Chairman, to have&#13;
&#13;
                             a reference in the fourth indent in paragraph 53, which is&#13;
&#13;
                             specifically related to participation and talks about the&#13;
&#13;
                             costs of that, if that could be transposed to the more&#13;
&#13;
                             general section at the end, so that there would be a clear&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12;run                                                                                    105&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             understanding that any of the extra costs involved in the&#13;
&#13;
                             governance work would be met from the existing resources.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. PRESTON:   Thank you, Mr. O'Murchu.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Mr. Torres.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. TORRES:    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I will try to be very brief and, as others, I would&#13;
&#13;
                             like to commend the staff for the excellent job that they&#13;
&#13;
                             have done in preparing this progress report on Bank's&#13;
&#13;
                             governance activities over the last two years.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I agree strongly with the two basic assumptions&#13;
&#13;
                             that underlie the work done: first, that governance issues&#13;
&#13;
                             are extremely relevant for development effectiveness and&#13;
&#13;
                             better portfolio performance; and two, that the Bank has a&#13;
&#13;
                             role to play in assisting our clients' efforts in this domain&#13;
&#13;
                             in a way which is consistent with our mandate, with our&#13;
&#13;
                             Articles of Agreement.&#13;
&#13;
                                       But, I am not going to deal with these issues&#13;
&#13;
                             today, and I am not either going to deal with the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
                             approach in each of the dimensions of governance, which I&#13;
&#13;
                             broadly support.   I am pleased as well with the basic&#13;
&#13;
                             objectives of future work, in particular that the bulk of the&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank's work will continue to be on public sector management,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C.     20002&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                       106&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             and that the major emphasis will be to explore how countries&#13;
&#13;
                             can be assisted to build strong institutions.&#13;
&#13;
                                          I would like instead to take this opportunity to&#13;
&#13;
                             tell you briefly some of the concerns raised after reading&#13;
&#13;
                             the paper.     They have to do basically with how precisely are&#13;
&#13;
                             we defining our objectives and the nature of the constraints&#13;
&#13;
                             in our work.&#13;
&#13;
                                          The first one relates to the need for more focus&#13;
&#13;
                             and specialization in our work in this area.     Governance&#13;
&#13;
                             seems to be a growing industry in the Bank, and the&#13;
&#13;
                             expectation, as was mentioned in the paper, is that it will&#13;
&#13;
                             continue to grow.     But, to me, the work agenda is still too&#13;
&#13;
                             broadly defined.     In extreme, we could think of a situation&#13;
&#13;
                             where the demand on Bank's services in this area can be&#13;
&#13;
                             unlimited.&#13;
&#13;
                                          I have observed, Mr. Chairman -- and it is not the&#13;
&#13;
                             first time that I raised this issue -- that we at the Bank&#13;
&#13;
                             are very good at listing relevant things, but that we have&#13;
&#13;
                             more difficulties at sorting out priorities, of defining what&#13;
&#13;
                             we can do and what we cannot do, and what is done to do it&#13;
&#13;
                             seriously.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Each of the dimensions of governance, take, for&#13;
&#13;
                             instance, public sector management, is so broad that we&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street. N .E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
1202\   ~46-6666&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                       107&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               cannot be good at everything and have intellectual leadership&#13;
&#13;
                               at everything.   Hence, the need for more specialization and&#13;
&#13;
                               focus and the need to deepen our knowledge and efforts in the&#13;
&#13;
                               areas in which we concentrate our work, because this is a&#13;
&#13;
                               must if we want to be effective.   This is one point.&#13;
&#13;
                                         The second point basically refers to supply&#13;
&#13;
                               constraints and has to do with whether we have or not the&#13;
&#13;
                               internal capacity to deal effectively with our work.     And,&#13;
&#13;
                               this brings me to the issues of skill mix and the&#13;
&#13;
                               organizational structure.&#13;
&#13;
                                         I don't want to say anything about skill mix.     I&#13;
&#13;
                               agree with the proposal of the paper, though I think I agree&#13;
&#13;
                               also with those colleagues who have said that we have to be&#13;
&#13;
                               very careful in scaling the number of specialists in this&#13;
&#13;
                               area, and particularly in an environment of a constrained&#13;
&#13;
                               bu'dget or resources within the institution.&#13;
&#13;
                                         With respect to the organizational structure, I was&#13;
&#13;
                               surprised to see that there was not a central unit dealing&#13;
&#13;
                               with that until very recently, though in the past there was a&#13;
&#13;
                               unit but it seems there has been some discontinuation.     I am&#13;
&#13;
                               not sure; I don't know what has happened but in any case, I&#13;
&#13;
                               am glad to see that we have this central unit.   I think that&#13;
&#13;
                               this will be particularly relevant to the need that the paper&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washingroo. D.C.       20002&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                        108&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              raises on the need to draw lessons from the experience across&#13;
&#13;
                              different countries and regions and the need to have some&#13;
&#13;
                              research and intellectual leadership.   I think that this&#13;
&#13;
                              central unit should play an important role.&#13;
&#13;
                                        The third aspect is the specialization and internal&#13;
&#13;
                              capacity are essential.   This brings me also to the need of&#13;
&#13;
                              emphasizing the need to coordinate our efforts with the&#13;
&#13;
                              efforts of other institutions and donors, but this has&#13;
&#13;
                              already been discussed.   This is an important aspect that we&#13;
&#13;
                              have to emphasize.&#13;
&#13;
                                        And fourth, though I understand that it is difficul&#13;
&#13;
                              to provide specific measures or specific indicators of what&#13;
&#13;
                              we achieve in this area, again I encourage staff to work and&#13;
&#13;
                              try to provide us with some qualitative indicators that could&#13;
&#13;
                              be used just to assess which is the progress that is achieved&#13;
&#13;
                              in each of the areas that we work as compared to the resource&#13;
&#13;
                              that we invest in this area.&#13;
&#13;
                                        And, finally, Mr. Chairman, two comments.     The&#13;
&#13;
                              first is on the publication of this report.     I strongly&#13;
&#13;
                              recommend the publication of this report.     And, with respect&#13;
&#13;
                              to the concern raised by Mr. Cosgrove, though I understand&#13;
&#13;
                              his concerns, I think that the risks of not being explicit at&#13;
&#13;
                              expressing our view on this aspect are lower than the risks&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLÂ£fI REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                        109&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             that we may face if we really are not clear at all on what we&#13;
&#13;
                             mean in the field of human rights.&#13;
&#13;
                                       And, second, I am also pleased to see such general&#13;
&#13;
                             concern at this table with respect to how important it is to&#13;
&#13;
                             deal with governance aspects in non-developing countries.&#13;
&#13;
                             Unfortunately, we don't have any mandate to deal with Part I&#13;
&#13;
                             members, but our sister institution, the Fund, has a mandate&#13;
&#13;
                             for surveillance of Part I members.       And, in the context of&#13;
&#13;
                             the Article IV consultations, we could suggest and ask the&#13;
&#13;
                             people who are concerned with that here just to encourage&#13;
&#13;
                             their counterparts on the other side of the street to define&#13;
&#13;
                             an agenda for the Fund to deal with governance issues in&#13;
&#13;
                             industrial countries.       And, I think that this would be really&#13;
&#13;
                             a welcome development.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
                                          MR. PRESTON:    Are there any other comments or&#13;
&#13;
                             questions?&#13;
&#13;
                                          Mr. Gerber.&#13;
&#13;
                                          MR. GERBER:    Yes, Mr. President.&#13;
&#13;
                                          MR. PRESTON:    Our hero.&#13;
&#13;
                                          (Laughter. )&#13;
&#13;
                                          MR. GERBER:    I would appreciate if through you, Mr.&#13;
&#13;
                             President, Mr. Choksi or Mr. Stevens could tell us what they&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street, N.E.&#13;
Wasbington, D.C. 20002&#13;
1?1l?\ \&lt;!h.hhf,1I&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                       110&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             think about the idea of looking in the future into the&#13;
&#13;
                             international dimension, that is the coherence question of&#13;
&#13;
                             good governance.&#13;
&#13;
                                         I have not heard any reaction yet from management.&#13;
&#13;
                             I think I deserve to a certain extent a reaction on this&#13;
&#13;
                             proposal.&#13;
&#13;
                                         I had also the opportunity in the last fifteen&#13;
&#13;
                             minutes to read the statement, the written statement of Mr.&#13;
&#13;
                             Al-Khaled, who made, as a matter of fact, exactly the same&#13;
&#13;
                             points I made.     And, I think we deserve a reaction.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Thank you, Mr. President.&#13;
&#13;
                                         MR. PRESTON:     Thank you, Mr. Gerber.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Mr. Benhocine.&#13;
&#13;
                                         MR. BENHOCINE:     Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Ms. Cordeiro and Mr. Haas have made, in my view, a&#13;
&#13;
                             very convincing point as far as the way the issue of&#13;
&#13;
                             governance should be dealt with in country assistance&#13;
&#13;
                             strategies.&#13;
&#13;
                                         I just would like to request some clarification.       I&#13;
&#13;
                             agree completely with a more systematic treatment of&#13;
&#13;
                             governance.    I agree on the need to raise the profile, but I&#13;
&#13;
                             do understand -- I need clarification -- that there will be&#13;
&#13;
                             no special chapter in the country assistance strategy dealing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; run                                                                                       111&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             with governance because governance issues are in all Bank's&#13;
&#13;
                             activities.&#13;
&#13;
                                          And, the description of the Bank activities and the&#13;
&#13;
                             description of the strategy of the Bank, the priority of the&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank will be self-explanatory as far as governance is&#13;
&#13;
                             concerned.&#13;
&#13;
                                          So, I just would like to be clear on this, that&#13;
&#13;
                             there will be no special chapter in the country assistance&#13;
&#13;
                             strategy and, as it has been said, it will not be another&#13;
&#13;
                             area of emphasis, but it is just an issue that will be more&#13;
&#13;
                             systematically covered in the analysis rather than as a&#13;
&#13;
                             special chapter.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
                                          MR. PRESTON:     Thank you, Mr. Benhocine.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Mr. Flano.&#13;
&#13;
                                          MR. FLANO:     Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                          We had our statement distributed beforehand.     And,&#13;
&#13;
                             given what Mr. Torres said about the internal organization, I&#13;
&#13;
                             have some questions here.        If the staff could refer to the&#13;
&#13;
                             internal organizational structure, and especially what they&#13;
&#13;
                             are thinking in the future with regard to that point.&#13;
&#13;
                                          There was some reference to the staffing of that.&#13;
&#13;
                             I would like to know what is the internal organizational&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street. N.E.&#13;
W""hington, D.C. 20002&#13;
(202l 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;    nm                                                                                    112&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               structure and how much it is going to be centralized and how&#13;
&#13;
                               much is going to be decentralized in the different regions.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                         MR. PRESTON:     Thank you, Mr. Flano.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Are there any other questions or comments?&#13;
&#13;
                                         (NO response.)&#13;
&#13;
                                         MR. PRESTON:     Mr. Stevens, Mr. Choksi.&#13;
&#13;
                                         MR. STEVENS:     Let me, if I may, just pick up on two&#13;
&#13;
                               comments made by the Chairs.     The first is, if I may move to&#13;
&#13;
                               the defense of Box 3, which I think is an important piece of&#13;
&#13;
                               research, it was commented on both by the first speaker, Mr.&#13;
&#13;
                               de Paiva, and Mr. Snoy.&#13;
&#13;
                                         I think it is important to make two points about&#13;
&#13;
                               this particular piece of research.     The first is that&#13;
&#13;
                               research is different to operations.     We are not seeking to&#13;
&#13;
                               influence governance.     What we are seeking to is to understan&#13;
&#13;
                               better the process that is going on.&#13;
&#13;
                                         We recognize that activities in the economic and&#13;
&#13;
                               social sphere do spillover into the political sphere.      And,&#13;
&#13;
                               if we are to better design social safety nets, to advise&#13;
&#13;
                               governments on the sequencing of economic reforms, then it is&#13;
&#13;
                               important to understand the process it plays within countries&#13;
&#13;
                               That is the first point to make.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
$07 C Strttt, N,E,&#13;
Washmgton, D,C.        20002&#13;
I   ?n"   ~&lt;1h_hf"'h&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                      113&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        The second point to emphasize is that this&#13;
&#13;
                             particular research is being planned with the full cooperatio&#13;
&#13;
                             of the governments.     None of those country case studies will&#13;
&#13;
                             go ahead unless there is full agreement and cooperation of&#13;
&#13;
                             the participating governments.     So, this is a cooperative&#13;
&#13;
                             venture.&#13;
&#13;
                                        The second point I would like to touch on is the&#13;
&#13;
                             question by Mr. Stanton as to whether there should be a&#13;
&#13;
                             division of labor of the work of the Bank and bilateral&#13;
&#13;
                             agencies on governance.     My response to that is it depends&#13;
&#13;
                             what form it takes.&#13;
&#13;
                                        I think there are plenty of good examples already&#13;
&#13;
                             of the division of labor on governance in the economic&#13;
&#13;
                             sphere.    I am thinking here of cases where the Bank has&#13;
&#13;
                             provided a public sector management SECAL and yours, as in&#13;
&#13;
                             the case of a number of countries in Africa, have provided&#13;
&#13;
                             technical assistance.     And, the partnership has worked&#13;
&#13;
                             extremely well and there is clearly scope for more of this.&#13;
&#13;
                                         If it means, on the other -- and I hesitate to put&#13;
&#13;
                             it crudely -- but if it means, on the other hand, that there&#13;
&#13;
                             is some strategy coordinated whereby the bilateral agencies&#13;
&#13;
                             might address the political agenda by tacit agreement, the&#13;
&#13;
                             Bank then addresses in some coordinated way the economic and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
'07 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
I7M\   ~4".u,,,,,&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                       114&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             social agenda, then I think certainly the General Counsel&#13;
&#13;
                             would have something to say on that regard.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. PRESTON:    Not just General Counsel.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. STEVENS:    My boss as well.&#13;
&#13;
                                       (Laughter. )&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. PRESTON:    Mr. Stanton.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. STANTON:    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
                                       My point was more division of labor between&#13;
&#13;
                             multilateral organizations such as, in particular, UNDP,&#13;
&#13;
                             rather than division of labor.     I mean, both, of course, but&#13;
&#13;
                             I was particularly focusing on the respective roles of the&#13;
&#13;
                             multilateral organizations here.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
                                       MR. CHOKSI:    We take your point, Mr. Stanton.     I&#13;
&#13;
                             think you did give us a hint earlier on in your first comment&#13;
&#13;
                             as to how tricky this is going to be because governance is&#13;
&#13;
                             inherent to the development process.     And, I think all of you&#13;
&#13;
                             agree to that.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Therefore, to try and bring about a clear-cut&#13;
&#13;
                             division of labor that institutionally handles transparency&#13;
&#13;
                             and handles public sector management I think it is going to&#13;
&#13;
                             be a little bit difficult.&#13;
&#13;
                                       It is intrinsic in our work.       There are dimensions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~07   C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
(102\   ~4('.('(;('('&#13;
&amp;#12; rum                                                                                       115&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             of it that we address.    For example, when we undertake trade&#13;
&#13;
                             liberalization, deregulations, we are addressing issues of&#13;
&#13;
                             transparency in and of themselves.&#13;
&#13;
                                       So, I think it is a tricky issue, and I must&#13;
&#13;
                             confess I don't know exactly how to answer it.     We do have&#13;
&#13;
                             within the broader multilateral institutions an understanding&#13;
&#13;
                             an agreement that, in fact, the UNDP, for example, would&#13;
&#13;
                             focus on issues of institutional development, though we are&#13;
&#13;
                             involved in it as well too.&#13;
&#13;
                                       We work on a bilateral basis with them.     We have&#13;
&#13;
                             the World Health Organization addressing issues, technical&#13;
&#13;
                             issues of health related to poverty.     We are addressing the&#13;
&#13;
                             economic dimensions for it.     So, there are these dimensions.&#13;
&#13;
                                       But, when you talk of governance as a whole, I&#13;
&#13;
                             think it is a little difficult for me to give you a clear-cut&#13;
&#13;
                             answer on how we can cut it apart, because it is an intrinsic&#13;
&#13;
                             part of the development process.&#13;
&#13;
                                       You also raised a question about dissemination, how&#13;
&#13;
                             we are handling this.     Let me tell you firstly that this&#13;
&#13;
                             paper in and of itself, the process of preparing this paper&#13;
&#13;
                             led to a wide level of consultation within the institution,&#13;
&#13;
                             across the institution.     This and of itself was an important&#13;
&#13;
                             activity of disseminating prior, in fact to get into the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N .E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                          116&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              Board.    What you have here is a view that is an institutional&#13;
&#13;
                              view here.&#13;
&#13;
                                           Second, on certain topics within this area, we do&#13;
&#13;
                              undertake best practice papers that are disseminated to the&#13;
&#13;
                              staff.    We have a program within HRO, within the Human&#13;
&#13;
                              Resource Vice Presidency, on what we call HRO working papers.&#13;
&#13;
                              I think you have seen some of those.      Those are papers that&#13;
&#13;
                              are written in very non-technical language, designed for&#13;
&#13;
                              staff to pick up major issues.&#13;
&#13;
                                           We have brief dissemination notes, two-page&#13;
&#13;
                              dissemination notes which really go in bullet form to key&#13;
&#13;
                              issues.    We hold seminars.   We have an annual symposium on&#13;
&#13;
                              public sector management.      That is, in fact, another&#13;
&#13;
                              mechanism.&#13;
&#13;
                                           We do training jointly with the Training Department&#13;
&#13;
                              on issues of public sector management.      And, we have, in&#13;
&#13;
                              fact, started working on using latest computer technology to,&#13;
&#13;
                              in fact, disseminate information and answer questions through&#13;
&#13;
                              the computer network system.&#13;
&#13;
                                           We are beginning to set that process up where&#13;
&#13;
                              individuals can log into the system and ask a question, and&#13;
&#13;
                              somebody else who is logged into the system knows the answer&#13;
&#13;
                              and answers back.     We are doing this in the field of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTIliG CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.B,&#13;
Washington, D,C, 20002&#13;
(202) 546Â·6666&#13;
&amp;#12;run                                                                                     117&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             governance but we are doing this broadly across the field of&#13;
&#13;
                             human resource development itself.     This process has already&#13;
&#13;
                             taken off in the field of population, health and nutrition,&#13;
&#13;
                             and we are going to expand it to all these other fields.&#13;
&#13;
                                        You also raised issues of participation and the&#13;
&#13;
                             budget.   Let me tell you that we had an initial participation&#13;
&#13;
                             fund this year for $300,000.     We expected that for the full&#13;
&#13;
                             year that should be enough.    We had requested matching funds&#13;
&#13;
                             from the regions.&#13;
&#13;
                                        The purpose here was to catalyze the whole process&#13;
&#13;
                             of participation and get it off the ground.     Actually, the&#13;
&#13;
                             catalytic effect was quite tremendous.     Within three months,&#13;
&#13;
                             the entire fund was exhausted.     The replenishment, in fact,&#13;
&#13;
                             is for FY94, not for FY95, as stated in the report, which&#13;
&#13;
                             might have led you to the comment you made.&#13;
&#13;
                                        The intention is, in fact, however, to incorporate&#13;
&#13;
                             it within the regular budget of the regions starting in FY95.&#13;
&#13;
                             But, I think it is worth mentioning that the costs of doing&#13;
&#13;
                             projects with more participation I think will increase.      No&#13;
&#13;
                             doubt the benefits will increase too.&#13;
&#13;
                                        But, I believe that we should keep in mind that&#13;
&#13;
                             bringing in participation right in the early stages through&#13;
&#13;
                             the design and appraisal of a project, important as it is,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
'07 C Street, N.K&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                     118&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             does involve greater time, does involve greater effort, does&#13;
&#13;
                             involve greater resources.   And, within an overall zero&#13;
&#13;
                             budget growth constraint, this has implications for the&#13;
&#13;
                             number of projects that might eventually turn up.&#13;
&#13;
                                       I think the organizational issue has been raised by&#13;
&#13;
                             Mr. Plano and Mr. Torres.    Let me say a few words on that.&#13;
&#13;
                                       We have at the center, at the start of the&#13;
&#13;
                             reorganization of January, in fact, last year, a unit for the&#13;
&#13;
                             issue of public sector management which does address issues&#13;
&#13;
                             of governance, public sector management, the sensitive issues&#13;
&#13;
                             that you see in this document.    And, we work very closely&#13;
&#13;
                             with the legal counsel on issues of human rights as well too.&#13;
&#13;
                                       It is my view, however, that the issues of&#13;
&#13;
                             governance, the issues of public sector management,&#13;
&#13;
                             transparency, all the stuff that we are talking about, is&#13;
&#13;
                             very specific to the culture of the countries concerned, the&#13;
&#13;
                             traditions, the history.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Therefore, I personally am reluctant to build up a&#13;
&#13;
                             large staff in the center.    Whilst I agree with the notion&#13;
&#13;
                             that more attention needs to be paid to it, more staff need&#13;
&#13;
                             to work on this, this should be done at the regional level,&#13;
&#13;
                             not at the center.&#13;
&#13;
                                       At the center, our job is to provide overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
On7l '4(,.(,{,{,(;&#13;
&amp;#12;  nm                                                                                    119&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             documents such as this, provide the dissemination that we&#13;
&#13;
                             talked about, provide the training that we talked about,&#13;
&#13;
                             provide very much a coordinating, facilitating and catalytic&#13;
&#13;
                             role.&#13;
&#13;
                                         I do not believe that staff at the center can, in&#13;
&#13;
                             fact, address the local cultural issues in as much depth as&#13;
&#13;
                             the staff of the regions can.    And, that is the way we are&#13;
&#13;
                             moving actually.&#13;
&#13;
                                         Mr. Benhocine, you have raised issues about the&#13;
&#13;
                             country assistance strategy and you wanted assurance there&#13;
&#13;
                             would not be a special chapter on that.     I can assure you on&#13;
&#13;
                             that.    In fact, I want to draw your attention to the paper&#13;
&#13;
                             that we have distributed to you, and which has passed on a&#13;
&#13;
                             no-objection on the country assistance strategy.     We&#13;
&#13;
                             explicitly said that there will be a section on the Bank&#13;
&#13;
                             Group's assistance strategy.&#13;
&#13;
                                         It will address an assessment of: (a) the status of&#13;
&#13;
                             the Bank, country dialogue on policy; (b) any differences&#13;
&#13;
                             between the Bank's macroeconomic assessment and that of the&#13;
&#13;
                             IMF;    (c) any governance issues related to the government's&#13;
&#13;
                             willingness and capacity to carry out needed reforms; and (d)&#13;
&#13;
                             implications of portfolio performance.&#13;
&#13;
                                         It will be brought in within the context of our&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO., INC.&#13;
~01   C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C, 20002&#13;
1107\ \dr,.h{,fir,&#13;
&amp;#12; nm                                                                                     120&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              overall Bank country assistance strategy.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Mr. Gerber and some of you have raised the&#13;
&#13;
                              interesting question of the international dimensions of&#13;
&#13;
                              governance.   Since there seems to be such an overwhelming&#13;
&#13;
                              support for this type of work, and I think it is a very&#13;
&#13;
                              interesting idea I must say, we have not admittedly done a&#13;
&#13;
                              lot of careful analysis on this, and we will start looking at&#13;
&#13;
                              it and begin some work in this area.&#13;
&#13;
                                        MR. PRESTON:   You better have a referendum.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MILLER REPORTING CO â&#128;¢â&#128;¢ INC.&#13;
507 C Street. N.E.&#13;
Washington. D.C. 20002&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="15274712">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1993/12/15274712/minutes-meeting-executive-directors-held-thursday-16th-december-1993
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1993/12/15274712/minutes-meeting-executive-directors-held-thursday-16th-december-1993</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1993/12/15274712/minutes-meeting-executive-directors-held-thursday-16th-december-1993</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2011-10-11T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2016-01-14T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b0828b23af</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0828b23af</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/10/12/000386194_20111012031504/Rendered/INDEX/648980MIN0Dece00disclosed0100110110.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/10/12/000386194_20111012031504/Rendered/PDF/648980MIN0Dece00disclosed0100110110.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1993-12-16T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <bdmdt>1993-12-16T00:00:00Z</bdmdt>
        <datestored>2011-10-12T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of the meeting of the Executive
            Directors held on Thursday, 16th December, 1993
        </repnme>
        <docna>
            Transcript of the meeting of the Executive
            Directors held on Thursday, 16th December, 1993
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of the meeting of the
            Executive Directors held on Thursday, 16th December, 1993</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1993/12/15274712/transcript-meeting-executive-directors-held-thursday-16th-december-1993</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Banks &amp; Banking Reform,National Governance,Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Governance Indicators,Emerging Markets</subtopic>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Private Sector Development,Public Sector Development,Governance</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000386194_20111012031504</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Board transcript</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Private Sector Development,Public Sector Development,Governance</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            abuses, accountability, accountability
            mechanisms, ADB, administrative costs, advocacy groups,
            anti-corruption, anti-corruption strategy, balanced budgets,
            Bank activities, Bank activity, Bank management, best
            practice, borrower, borrowing, borrowing countries,
            borrowing country, budget deficit, bureaucracy, central
            government, central governments, citizen, civil rights,
            civil service, commercial laws, confidence, consensus,
            constituency, constitutional law, core governance, corrupt,
            corrupt practices, country to country, creation of job,
            criminality, debt, decentralization, decision-making,
            decision-making processes, developing countries, development
            banks, disclosure, districts, dividend, economic
            development, economic growth, economic reform, effect of
            governance, enterprise reform, expenditure, financial
            assistance, financial institution, financial institutions,
            financial management, financial support, fiscal policy,
            foreign assistance, free press, free trade, freedom of
            speech, good governance, governance dimension, governance
            dimensions, governance issues, governance performance,
            governance practices, governance problems, governance
            reform, government officials, governmental agencies, human
            capital, human resources, human rights, improving
            governance, industrial countries, Infrastructure Project,
            initiative, institutional development, institutional
            environment, institutional framework, international
            community, INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT, jails, Judicial
            Infrastructure, judicial reform, judiciary, jurisdictions,
            justice, laws, leadership, legal framework, legal
            frameworks, legal reform, legal system, levels of
            government, living standards, local governance, local
            government, local institutions, macroeconomic management,
            macroeconomic policies, macroeconomic policy, market
            economy, market failure, monetary policies, multilateral
            organizations, Municipal Development, Natural Resources,
            outputs, participatory approaches, particular countries,
            political agenda, political considerations, political
            dimensions, political regime, political rights, political
            system, politician, portfolio, poverty alleviation,
            Presidency, Private Sector Development, privatization,
            procurement, public administration, public expenditure,
            public finance, public information, public management,
            public resources, public sector, public sector management,
            public service, reform programs, regulatory institutions,
            rehabilitation, rule of law, safety nets, social change,
            social development, social services, state enterprise, state
            power, structural adjustment, sustainable development,
            technical assistance, transition economies, transparency
        </keywd>
        <owner>Policy and Operations (SECPO)</owner>
        <repnb>64898</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks and Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business and Commercial Laws and Regulations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative and Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Management and Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Capital</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing People</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Judicial Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Justice Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal and Judicial Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise and Commercial Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks &amp; Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Judicial System Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Rights</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Law and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise and Corporate Law</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>