<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                                                       65046 f&#13;
           Items Discussed at the l27th Regular and&#13;
           Informal Meeting of Executive Directors,&#13;
           held on March 23. 1248.&#13;
&#13;
FORMAL .&#13;
&#13;
Page 759          Approval of Minutes of l26th Regular Meeting&#13;
                  of Executive Directors.&#13;
&#13;
Page 759          Message of condolence on the occasion of the&#13;
                  death of Dr. G. Iv â&#128;¢J. Bruins J Executiva Director&#13;
                  of the Fund.&#13;
&#13;
Page 760          Staff Memorandum on the Report of the Sub-&#13;
                  Commission on Economic Development of the U.N.&#13;
                  Economic and Employment Commission (R-154) -&#13;
                  Consideration postponed.&#13;
Page 767          Agenda of Advisory Council. Draft preliminary&#13;
                  agenda (R-l56) approved for sul::mission to Sir&#13;
                  Arthur Salter for his comments.&#13;
Page 771          Report by Loan Director on progress of Chilean&#13;
                  loan negotiations.&#13;
Page 782         Financial assistance to Latin American Republics.&#13;
                 President proposed reply to l1r. Norman Armour&#13;
                 approved (Sec. Memo 373)                  .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
INFORMAL&#13;
&#13;
Page 782          Currency Clauses in Loan Agreements.     (R-155)&#13;
Page 784         Negotiations Yith B.r.S. re B.l.S. buying from&#13;
                 Bank SF 17,000,000 at interest rate of 2 ~2%.&#13;
&amp;#12;CONFIDJ:-;N1'IAL&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   TRtll':SCRIPr OF l27th RE-GULAR MEETING&#13;
                                   OF THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTORS, HELD IN&#13;
                                   THE BOARD ROOM ON TUESDAY, MJI...RCH 23,&#13;
                                             . 1948 at 10 :30 a.m.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHAIrutMr :        Gentlemen, shall we come to order?         I think we have a quorum.    The first&#13;
(McCloy)&#13;
                   item is the approval of the minutes of the 126th Regular Meeting of the&#13;
&#13;
                   Directors.    You have all had copies.       If there are no conments, I declare&#13;
&#13;
                   them approved.&#13;
&#13;
                   Before   mo\~ng   to the next item, I wanted to note on the record that we&#13;
&#13;
                   have received information of the death of Dr. Bruins who was the&#13;
                   Executive Director of the Fund for the Netherlands and the UniOI: of&#13;
&#13;
                   South Africa.      Dr. Bruins died on March 22nd, and on behalf of the Board&#13;
                   and the Bank, I have written a letter of condolence to both the Fund and&#13;
                   to his widow.      His death was very sudden, I believe.     I understand the&#13;
&#13;
                   Fund are in close touch with Ytrs. Bruins and I would like the minutes to&#13;
&#13;
                   note our regret.&#13;
&#13;
                   Tomorrow, as you know, the officials of the New England insurance companies&#13;
&#13;
                   will be with us.      We have a luncheon arranged and so far four members of&#13;
                   the Board have signified their intention of being present at lunch.            If&#13;
&#13;
                   there . are any others, will you please let Mr. Garner or Mr. Mendels know,&#13;
&#13;
                   so that we can make appropriate arrangements.&#13;
&#13;
                   As you know also, I have asked Dr. Per Jacobssen, who is Economic Advisor&#13;
&#13;
                   of the B.I.S. to talk to us after the meeting this morning.            He wi.ll be&#13;
&#13;
                   here around 12 o.clock or earlier if we are through.         We should be through&#13;
&#13;
                   by then.     Dr. Jacobssen has been conducting a series of talks throughout&#13;
                   the   count~,     and has kept in close touch with the European situation vbile&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    - 759 -&#13;
&amp;#12;            he has been here.    All of you know him, and I am sure you will be glad to&#13;
            hear any pronouncements he can give us on economic conditions there.          The&#13;
&#13;
            second regular item on the agenda is the staff memorandum of comments on&#13;
&#13;
            the report of the Subcommission of the United Nations Economic and Employ-&#13;
&#13;
            ment Commission.    You have seen it.      It has been circulated to you,    We&#13;
&#13;
            received before the report prepared by that        Sub-Co~nission,   and on our&#13;
&#13;
            receiving it, the staff vms instructed to prepare the comments which are&#13;
&#13;
            before you.   We would propose that if those comments are agreeable to you,&#13;
&#13;
            we would send them on to the Commission for consideration by it in con-&#13;
&#13;
            junction with its consideration of the Sub-Commission's report.           Are there&#13;
&#13;
            any comments on the staff memorandum?&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:   vVhat I should like to ask is to postpone the discussion in order that then&#13;
            I could probably read it.       I think we received it too late for this dis-&#13;
&#13;
            cussion.   I could have some remarks later.&#13;
CHAIRMAN:   Anyone else want    to   make any other remarks?&#13;
IU..ANES:   I have read the memorandum, and I think i t is a very important contribution&#13;
&#13;
            to the story of development.       I think I am not quite convinced that it is&#13;
&#13;
            a minor thing, that at the end of page ), it reads !tAt present, the cost&#13;
&#13;
            of capital equipment is unusually high, because of extraordinary demand&#13;
&#13;
            and the low output of many normal producing countries.         New industries&#13;
            developed now, therefore, might be saddled with an exorbitant capital cost&#13;
            which would undermine their economic strength and their ability to compete&#13;
&#13;
            wi th other producers".      I think in the course of time that costs will not&#13;
&#13;
            be much lower.     It is a question of salaries and wages in the cost of pro-&#13;
&#13;
            duction.   They are, I am sure, the most important item, and I do not think&#13;
&#13;
            that we can expect them to be lower in future, so I do not think the cost&#13;
&#13;
            of production would be lower in the future than now, even if production&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             - 760 -&#13;
&amp;#12; JTT lI.NES:     should increase substantially.       I have carefully read the report.     It is&#13;
(c    .;,ld)&#13;
                 a good story and an important contribution.&#13;
 HOPPEJ.'IOT:    I feel that this paper is interesting, and that i t might lead to scme&#13;
&#13;
                 stressing of the   poli~     of the Bank in its future loans, so it seems to&#13;
&#13;
                 me that comments should be made on it.       May I ask if t..l-tis could not be&#13;
&#13;
                 circulated in time so that we can read it and perhaps have a memorandum&#13;
&#13;
                 made of the comments    50   that the staff could put them in order and we&#13;
&#13;
                 might discuss them.    There are a great number of questions raised in the&#13;
&#13;
                 paper; e.g. light industry and heavy industry, development in times of&#13;
&#13;
                 depression, and a lot of interesting things that ought to be discussed&#13;
                 some time.     It seems to me that some day there must be a discussion of&#13;
&#13;
                 what the Bank intends to do regarding the particulars of that paper from&#13;
&#13;
                 the staff and it should be circulated so that we can discuss it.&#13;
      Jl.MAN:    This is the recommendation of the staff, and I do not think any other paper&#13;
                 the staff can prepare    ,~uld   add substantially,to it.&#13;
 HOPPENOT:       No, I mean the comments of the Board.&#13;
 CHAIRl\IAN:     We shall certainly take note of the comments.        We shall not rush the thing&#13;
&#13;
                 through.     fmen is our deadline?&#13;
&#13;
 DEMUTH:         April 19th.&#13;
                                   â&#128;¢&#13;
 BP.ESC IANI :   I have read this report Â¥vith much interest, and I quite agree with the&#13;
&#13;
                 observations made by the Research Department.        I have seen that this&#13;
                 report has been written with a keen sense of economic analysis and knowledge&#13;
                 and I should like to make two observations.        The first point which I think&#13;
&#13;
                 should be enquired into would be some conclusions as to industrialization.&#13;
&#13;
                 There is some danger of industrialization.        I have in mind the case of Italy.&#13;
&#13;
                 Without doubt there is in Italy a lack of capital, which is demonstrated&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  - 761-&#13;
&amp;#12;p' -;CIANI:       by statistics such as those of the amount of iron consumed in relation to&#13;
(\...'-'11t Id)&#13;
                  the number of workers.    This amount of iron can be considered as being the&#13;
                  index of the progress in industrialization.            Statistics shon that the amount&#13;
&#13;
                  of iron cons'llIOOd in July is very little compared with the amount consumed&#13;
&#13;
                  in the United States, France, England and the other great industrial countries.&#13;
&#13;
                  Therefore without doubt, there is a lack of capital in Italy.               Italy needs&#13;
&#13;
                  to develop her industrialization.             Italy needs modernization.    Ho'wever,&#13;
&#13;
                  what might be the consequences?        One of the consequences IJ1.ight be an in-&#13;
&#13;
                  crease in unemployment.     Is this not likely?          rie have seen this happen in&#13;
&#13;
                  Germany, when after the inflation period of 1924-28, a very rapid progress&#13;
&#13;
                  of industrialization of Câ&#130;¬rmany's industry took place.             One of the con-&#13;
&#13;
                  sequences was that Germany vms equipped with the most modern plant, but&#13;
&#13;
                  just the same unemployment increased.             So the problem is very complex.&#13;
&#13;
                  I have in view Italy, the country I know better than any other country.&#13;
&#13;
                  It is not sufficient in the case of Italy to start merely with this problem&#13;
&#13;
                  of industrialization and capital equipment.             It is also absolutely necessary&#13;
&#13;
                  to take into account and. to consider the problem of cost, the problem of&#13;
&#13;
                  man-power, and the problem of immigration.             This is one point.    The second&#13;
&#13;
                  point I make refers, I believe, to what Mr. Hoppenot has said, regarding&#13;
&#13;
                  the policy of the Bank.     It concerns the flow of capital.          I quite agree&#13;
&#13;
                  ~~th   one of the conclusions of the Research Department, accordine to which&#13;
&#13;
                  assistance must come from the profits source and so on; but one problem&#13;
&#13;
                  arises that has not been touched in this memorandum, the problem of the&#13;
&#13;
                  form the flow of foreign capital ought to take.             We nmst distinguish be-&#13;
&#13;
                  tween different forms.    There has been in agricultural countries a great&#13;
&#13;
                  need for foreign capital.     Foreign investments had very great Lmportance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 _   71,.') _&#13;
&amp;#12;Br ~CIANI:      The flaw of foreign capital took the form of capital     e~ipment     for   indust~&#13;
(l. _~lt f d)&#13;
                because many countries did not have an industrial structure, and a sufficient&#13;
                quantity of capital equipment enabled them to construct necessary industrial&#13;
&#13;
                machinery.    For some countries the situation is different, and again I have&#13;
&#13;
                in view Italy.      Italy has also had important industrialization.     Italy has&#13;
&#13;
                an old industrial structure', a.Tld a number of very able technicians.       Italy&#13;
&#13;
                has the people and the equipment to a large part, I would not say all, of&#13;
&#13;
                the capital equipment she needs.      Therefore foreign capital ought to be&#13;
&#13;
                incorporated intoL mainly in the form of food for workers engaged in con-&#13;
&#13;
                struction, and in the meantime unable to produce consumers goods.           I think&#13;
&#13;
                t.~is   problem is very important for our Bank.   As far as I know, our Bank&#13;
                has always stressed the point that we shall finance only for purposes of&#13;
&#13;
                capital equipment.      It seems now, from some news published in the press,&#13;
&#13;
                that this view has been somewhat changed and that it is possible for the&#13;
&#13;
                Bank to    fip~ce   other forms of capital.   I do not know what amount is&#13;
&#13;
                proposed and it would be very interesting to have it cleared.         TheSe are&#13;
&#13;
                my   two points.    I do not know whether i t will be possible to have the&#13;
&#13;
                Research Department make further study so that the department can modify&#13;
&#13;
                a little the emphasis given to capital equipment.&#13;
HOPPENar;       Excuse me for talking again, but I would say that one of the main&#13;
&#13;
                assumptions of this paper is that the basis of financing the flow of&#13;
&#13;
                foreign capital to the countries that need it is through private channels.&#13;
                                                                                       France, Asia&#13;
                Â¥fe all know what has been done in that respect in, America, .Itfrica,/and&#13;
&#13;
                o~~er    countries and all sorts of things have been financed.    It is not&#13;
&#13;
                very clear to me at the present time how foreign investment can be made&#13;
&#13;
                on a large scale only by private investment.       I can agree that technically&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                - 763 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     ')&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
HOPFENOT :   it is the best way of making foreign investments because it permits not&#13;
(   tId)&#13;
             only the export of machinery, but also the export of brains, including&#13;
&#13;
             engineers, technical skills of all kinds, and so on.                     I should like to&#13;
&#13;
             have the staff think about it and tell us how we can put together and&#13;
&#13;
             reconcile the present situation which is not very good for foreign in-&#13;
&#13;
             vestroont         a~d        the policy ,ihich stresses the usefulness of that kind of&#13;
&#13;
             investment.&#13;
&#13;
CfiAIRMAN:   I do not know that we want to collect                  ~~ese   comments now.   A couple&#13;
             rushed to TTJ mind, but I thought i t would be better to reserve them.&#13;
BARANSKI:    I told you that I prefer to postpone the discus_sion, but I still have&#13;
&#13;
             nTY   0'.'111   poL"lts.        I have ma.n.y-, though some "mich I am not prepared to put&#13;
&#13;
             for discussion now.                  There is one I must stress here.      I do not agree&#13;
&#13;
             in some respects with the statements about the controversy between light&#13;
&#13;
             ani heavy industry.                  The statement made on page 3 that the developrlent&#13;
&#13;
             of heavy manufacturing industries may                  p~ve    to be delayed in favor of light&#13;
&#13;
             industries and that many of these require large investment are certainly&#13;
&#13;
             true, but not in all cases.                  They are true in the case \ihen a country is&#13;
&#13;
             not only undeveloped but also over-populated, which is nOt always the same&#13;
&#13;
             thing.           You can have an undeveloped country with sufficient population.&#13;
&#13;
             These statements deal obviously only with the case when there is undevelop-&#13;
&#13;
             mente           There is on the other hand the matter of surplus population which&#13;
&#13;
             from a political and economic point of view should be                     a~ployed   immediately.&#13;
&#13;
             I do not know the situation in Italy, but I know the situation in China&#13;
&#13;
             for instance.                  So the problem'must be followed through to the particular&#13;
&#13;
             case.           There is another thing which is also important.             It is impossible&#13;
&#13;
             to WAke clear poliqr points because the development of any country                        w~st&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        - 764 -&#13;
&amp;#12;lliLi1Ai.'lSKI:   be done by developing harmoniously all kinds of industries ,Yhich are&#13;
     )nt'd)&#13;
                  necessary not only for raising the standard of living, but for the process&#13;
                  of developing itself.    In this respect it must be, for instance, necessary&#13;
&#13;
                  to develop some mechanism and engineering industries Ydthout which the&#13;
&#13;
                  country cannot do the internal work necessary to develop itself.          The&#13;
&#13;
                  development cannot be done only by means of imported or foreign machinery.&#13;
&#13;
                  We can take the example of one larvy industry, the electric power industry.&#13;
&#13;
                  According the terms used in this report, such industry should wait because&#13;
&#13;
                  the unit of capital used for power is extremely great in comparison .lith&#13;
&#13;
                  ~~e   number of people employed.    Nevertheless power must be used in undevelop-&#13;
&#13;
                  ed cOill1tries.   Certain building industries, mining industries, bricks,&#13;
&#13;
                  and cement are other industries requiring a very heaTf capital outlay in&#13;
&#13;
                  comparison with the labor involved.       Nevertheless they are needed in some&#13;
&#13;
                  cotmtries for the simple purpose of developnent.          This one thing is some-&#13;
                  times confusing.     It is necessary to   distin~Jish     between mining and smelt-&#13;
&#13;
                  L~g   industries, mlich are very heavy industries in the respect, that they&#13;
&#13;
                  need a great deal of capital.      an the other   ~~nd,    the engineering industry&#13;
                  requires very much work.     So from the point of viel'f of unemployment, it&#13;
&#13;
                  is sometimes a very econoraic form of producing capital for the people who&#13;
                  need the capital to work on.       For instance, I made some calculations once,&#13;
                  and I   c~e   to the conclusion, according to the statistics, that the outlays&#13;
&#13;
                  of capital in the textile industry, especially in the cotton industry, in&#13;
&#13;
                  looms and so on are heavier than other cases Which are dependent on the&#13;
&#13;
                  skill of labor.     It is sometimes much simpler to delay in the case of&#13;
&#13;
                  engineering'where the necessary labor Skills are impossible to be cleared&#13;
&#13;
                  in the early stages of the industrialization.        I am saying only that this&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 - 765 -&#13;
&amp;#12;B.iUlA.J."lSK I :   problem of heavy versus light industry is very complicated and hard to&#13;
(     It'd)&#13;
                    settle.    We must define what is heavy and what is light and look at&#13;
                    specific cases in which there is the choice for this kind of industry&#13;
&#13;
                    or for the other one.        Certainly this item here on page 3 must be enlarged&#13;
&#13;
                    and made in the form of a separate memorandum dealing with all the subjects&#13;
&#13;
                    .vhich I have stressed here.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:           Does anybody else have any further comments they want to make at this&#13;
&#13;
                    stage?    I would suggest that we put this item on the agenda for next week&#13;
&#13;
                    again to permit further comments to develop_        Then ,vhen they are all put&#13;
&#13;
                    together and we have them, we can have the Staff prepare another paper&#13;
&#13;
                    which we will submit, wit..l1 the idea that, say two weeks off, we would have&#13;
&#13;
                    the final docmnent ready for approval and submission.         Is that satisfactory?&#13;
HOPPENOT:           Would it not take longer?&#13;
r     tRMAN:        Let us    s~J   two weeks.   We can still do it in two weeks and send it off in&#13;
&#13;
                    time so long as it does not go beyond two weeks.&#13;
HOPPENOT:           Even if   we    are not prepared for the 19th of April, I think that for our&#13;
                    ovm use, the ideas that ,muld follow in that paper would be very interest-&#13;
&#13;
                    L~g   and worth considering at length.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:           I think we have to get something up there for the 19th because there are&#13;
                    a number of reasons.         In the first place, we have been asked to comment&#13;
&#13;
                    and I think it is our function to comment on the report they have issued.&#13;
&#13;
                    There are a number of things in the report I would like to see commented&#13;
&#13;
                    on.    I think that if we postpone it, we might lose some of the effect.&#13;
&#13;
                    We can continue discussing the thing.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPENOT:           Are we supposed to report to that Sub-Commission?         Are we supposed to give&#13;
&#13;
                    our advice to the Sub-Commission?&#13;
&#13;
vuAImI.AN!          We are going to give the Commission our comments on the Report of the&#13;
&#13;
                    Sub-Commission.&#13;
&amp;#12;C~I)\_IRl1AN   :   I suppose there is scarcely a paragraph in that letter that you could not&#13;
(tId)&#13;
                   elaborate.    You could even write a book, but our purpose at this stage&#13;
&#13;
                   is not to write a book.     It may be that we ought to have a book somewhere&#13;
&#13;
                   in the library on the subject, but what we want to do n01Y was to have the&#13;
&#13;
                   point of view of the Bank summarized.         It may be that that is an inadequate&#13;
&#13;
                   summary for highly critical purposes or as a definitive pattern of our own&#13;
&#13;
                   procedures.    Certainly something less than a complete pattern I think we&#13;
&#13;
                   can profitably submit before the 18th of April, and I ymuld hope vre could.&#13;
&#13;
                   That doesn't mean that    &gt;VB    could not continue with our o.v.n thoughts as to&#13;
&#13;
                   development throughout the year or throughout the years, for that matter.&#13;
&#13;
                   Are there any other comments?         We will take note of the   cow~ents   thus far.&#13;
DEMUTH:            It would be extremely helpftu if the        ~~ecutive   Directors could put some&#13;
&#13;
                   of their thoughts on paper in specific form and then we can work on the&#13;
&#13;
                   basis of those memoranda, if they would care to do so.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:          Do you want to do that, Dr. Baranski, Mr. Bresciani, :Mr. Hoppenot?&#13;
&#13;
                   (Affirmative nods)&#13;
&#13;
                   The third item is the draft agenda for the first annual meeting of the&#13;
&#13;
                   Advisory Council.    At the last couple of meetines I have asked for suggest-&#13;
                   ions as to what might go on this agenda.         I received very few, but we have&#13;
&#13;
                   put down what we thought might be discussed ard we may have some other&#13;
&#13;
                   things come up as well.         We suggest that the paper is entirely preliminary,&#13;
&#13;
                   that it be sent forward to Sir Arthur Salter to get his comments on it,&#13;
&#13;
                   and that then we circularize it to the members of the Advisory Council.&#13;
&#13;
                   We "would of course have a further discussion of this matter after we had&#13;
&#13;
                   received our reply from Sir Arthur Salter.          Is there any discussion or&#13;
&#13;
                   furth~r   suggestion for the agenda vffiich it is proposed to send to Sir&#13;
&#13;
                   Arthur Salter in this preliminary form, as contained in the confidential&#13;
&#13;
                   draft which has been circulated to you.&#13;
&amp;#12;B    ':.;IAIIT:   The first item IIBank 1 s position in relation to economic development of&#13;
&#13;
                  r,;ember Countries", which refers to the monetary situations, monetary&#13;
&#13;
                  problems, and so on, is a matter for discussion by the fund, but the&#13;
&#13;
                  Bank so to speak has a very large interest in the financial and monetary&#13;
                                    â&#128;¢&#13;
                  stability of the various     c01L~tries      since this   fiP~ncial   and monetary&#13;
&#13;
                  stability is one of the conditions for our            grantin~   loans   ar~   financial&#13;
&#13;
                  stability means security for loans.             I Yionder, taking the opportunity&#13;
&#13;
                  of having toget.'ler such prominent economists vmo will meet next July&#13;
&#13;
                  here, if it is not possible to ask them to give us their opinions as to&#13;
&#13;
                  the monetary situation of the world, and what measures, according to their&#13;
&#13;
                  opinion, ousht to be taken in order to improve the situation.                   There are&#13;
&#13;
                  so many questions; the question of 'whether European currencies, ought to&#13;
&#13;
                  be depreciated, or not; and the question of Sterling, which d.ominates all&#13;
&#13;
                  others.   I think it would be interesting in this first it'3ID to include&#13;
&#13;
                  under conditions required for su:ccensful achievement of these airns, monetary&#13;
&#13;
                  and financial stability of the countries and meas'J.res sugE;ested to improve&#13;
&#13;
                  and to achieve, this    Jl1~tter      of monetary and financial stability.         Ylould it&#13;
&#13;
                  not be proper to do    t.~is?      I repeat that we are not primarily interested&#13;
&#13;
                  in these questions because it is a matter for the Fund, but we have 'a&#13;
&#13;
                  large interest in monetary stability.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRHAN:         Do you think we ought to elaborate l(b)?&#13;
&#13;
BR3SCIANI:        Elaborate l(b) nCondi tions req1..lired for successful achieveraent of these&#13;
&#13;
                  airos ll , by including monetary problems and measures suggested for t1le&#13;
&#13;
                  solution of these problems.&#13;
&#13;
CHAB.MAN:         Do you suppose we would get in trouble with the Fund?&#13;
&#13;
    "PENOT:       We should ask them before       Yfe    do it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     - 768 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                  I must say it seems to me if we are going to ask them 1'ihat their judgments&#13;
&#13;
                  are as to the conditions which would be required to bring about economic&#13;
                  progress that inevitably they will have to consider monetary matters.&#13;
&#13;
                  Perhaps before putting it in the agenda I had better talk to !ionsieur Gutt&#13;
&#13;
                  to see if there is any objection.&#13;
BF:.ESC HI.NI :   I would not miss the opprwtunity to have the opinion of these people.&#13;
&#13;
                  People such as Sir Arthur Salter and Nr. Robbins elaborate for themselves&#13;
&#13;
                  all these problems and possibly solutions.         It would be much more interest-&#13;
&#13;
                  ing than perhaps their opinions      o~   permitting the use of 18% of capital&#13;
&#13;
                  subscription, which is a matter of the future.         It is a problem which&#13;
&#13;
                  does not present itself now.&#13;
EOPPENOT:         Suppose they do not agree "'lith the Ftmd?&#13;
F''''''SCI.A1U:   They come here not in any official capacity.&#13;
CHAIRlvfAN:       I think it is absolutely sound that you cannot consider the general condi-&#13;
&#13;
                  tions here without taking into account monetary conditions.          The question&#13;
&#13;
                  of protocol comes up.    I should talk to Ji.!.:r. Gutt before I put it on the&#13;
                  agenda.    I think it is inevitable that it ,vill come up.&#13;
BRESCHNI:         I would insist on there being something on       mo~etary   problems in order that&#13;
                  these personages 'will be prepared to answer these questions and to give&#13;
                  their opinions.    How to solve the monetary problems is a problem       ,~ich&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  Will be raised ,'lith the application of the 'Marshall Plan and we will have&#13;
&#13;
                  them speak of the Bank1s position in relation to the European Recovery&#13;
                  Program.    Of course monetary problems are one of the most important aspects.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:         W'nat do you think of this, Mr. Madan?&#13;
&#13;
11ADJlli:         I have just come in â&#128;¢&#13;
    â&#128;¢IP..MAN:     Did you not just come from the Fund?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 _   7(.,0 _&#13;
&amp;#12;               I have just returned from the Fund and.am tryinE to pick up the threads&#13;
&#13;
               here.&#13;
&#13;
iiiILSOr{ :    It may help, tIr. Eresciani, to know that the other Sub-Corrunissfon of the&#13;
&#13;
               Econo~~c   and Employment Commission of the U.N. is meeting now on that&#13;
&#13;
               very' set of problems and. it may be a compromise s0111tion to ask the&#13;
&#13;
               AdvisoFf Council to comment on the significance of their report.            They&#13;
&#13;
               are a collection of economists of considerable standi."1g and there may&#13;
&#13;
               be things arising out of their report which would have significance.&#13;
&#13;
               It might be proper to ask the Advisor"'J Council to comment on that report.&#13;
&#13;
C]AIFJL~:      Does the Fund have anything like an advisory council?      ~1h~r   did tc'l8:'I sive&#13;
&#13;
               us one?&#13;
&#13;
               ',Te are issuing bonds; it was set up to create a good Lrnpression.&#13;
&#13;
               I 'I'rill speak to the Fu,'1d people, and depending upon what they say, we "Iill&#13;
&#13;
               send this to Sir   ArL~ur   Salter and raise the point in our letter to tim.&#13;
&#13;
               Vie shall see what his comments are.     B9fore we finalize it, we will have&#13;
&#13;
               a discussion on the final draft.&#13;
&#13;
DASYN:         In cormection with point 3 there is a question 1vhich is gern!8.ne to point 3,&#13;
&#13;
               the question of increasing our operations through the guarantee of t:b..e&#13;
&#13;
               Bank.     I was just wondering vmether this point could not be      sc~~tinized        by&#13;
&#13;
               the AdvisOI"J Council who might advise on the steps the Ban.'k could take.&#13;
&#13;
               I think it is worth while examining.&#13;
&#13;
CHAImIAN:      Well I see no reason why it should not be.       You mean the extent we ought&#13;
&#13;
               to participate in guarantees.       Is that the thought?&#13;
&#13;
BASYN:         The problem itself, why we'should do it, or why we should not do it.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIillW,&gt;/:   Has it not been determined we Should do it by our charter?&#13;
&#13;
B.tIc:YN:      We cannot undertake to do it without a chance of' succeeding.&#13;
&#13;
ca:u RMAN :    We 1rill include that.      Probably put it in item 3.&#13;
&amp;#12;BAri.A.:NSKI:   I have a remark under point 2, "Bank's position in relation to E.R.P."&#13;
&#13;
                We should not say only E.R.P. but other regional plans.             That is because&#13;
&#13;
                it should not be made as a reference to      a~   particular scheme.         It is&#13;
&#13;
                really possible that in Bogota or elsewhere there ,rill be another plan&#13;
&#13;
                proposed.    The question of the Bank1s position    ~~ll    apply in respect to&#13;
&#13;
                all of them.&#13;
CHAIR1IAN:      It is the same thing in respect to China.&#13;
&#13;
BARl-\}iSKI:    The question is regional plans, which are presented as substantial problems&#13;
&#13;
                in relation to what the Bank should do.&#13;
CHAL'Df,AN:     We ought to have some judgments by that time.           It is rather     vaL~e   at the&#13;
&#13;
                moment.     I hope conditions vlill be such when the Advisory Council meets&#13;
&#13;
                that they .vill be able to come to more      defi~ite   conclusions than we have&#13;
&#13;
                been able -to do so far by Â¥forking on itev-ery day.       Vie   'frill include that.&#13;
&#13;
                I think it is a good point.&#13;
&#13;
                We propose to have a special meeting on Thursday to deal ,vi th the problem&#13;
&#13;
                of the Chilean Loan, but some of the papers, particularly the definitive&#13;
&#13;
                agreemarts and the Report of the President and his recommendations, are not&#13;
&#13;
                ready yet.     We hope to get tr.eID ready shortly and certainl:r there will be&#13;
&#13;
                ample opportunity to consider ther.1 before that time.           There may be some&#13;
                aspects of the Chilean Loan we ought     w    talk about wday       in   a preliminary&#13;
                way before we deal with the particular documents.           I have asked }.Ilr. Iliff&#13;
&#13;
                to give us a general report on the Chilean Loan this morning.               It will be&#13;
&#13;
                a brief summary of the negotiations and the proposals, leaving to Thursday&#13;
&#13;
                a more definitive discussion and more definitive action.             k~.   Iliff?&#13;
&#13;
ILIFF:          I propose to tell the Board, Sir, briefly the present status of the Chilean&#13;
&#13;
                Loan, and also to give the Board a short account of the circumstances&#13;
&#13;
                leading up W the situation in which the loan now finds itself.                   This&#13;
&#13;
                application has been before the Bank for a considerable time.               The original&#13;
&amp;#12;request for a loan came on    Septemb~r   )0, 1946, when the Bank was asked if&#13;
&#13;
it would consider granting a loan of $40 million to the Corporacion de&#13;
Fomento and to the Chilean state      F~ilways.   The Corporacion de Fomento is&#13;
&#13;
an official Chilean Gov9rnment Agency established by Chilean law and charged&#13;
&#13;
Â¥dth the responsibility to formulate, to execute; and in certain circum-&#13;
&#13;
stances to finance schemes for the economic development of Chile.        The&#13;
&#13;
authorized negotiator for the loan was Mr. Vergara, who is the representative&#13;
&#13;
in New York of the Fomento Corporacion.       The Chilean Government informed&#13;
&#13;
us very shortly after the original application had been put fOI"\fard that&#13;
&#13;
they themselves were prepared to authorize Fomento to apply for this loan&#13;
and they also indicated that they would be prepared to give a government&#13;
&#13;
guarantee in respect of the loan.       The original application amounted to&#13;
~~40   million, of which $22 million was in respect of Fomento proje'cts, ani&#13;
&#13;
the remaining $18 million for electrification of the Chilean state railways.&#13;
&#13;
So far as the $22 million for which Fomento has asked were concerned, $7t&#13;
&#13;
million were for electric pawer plants, $6 million for forest industries,&#13;
&#13;
$5 million for urban and suburban transportation schemes, $2 million for&#13;
port mechanization, and $lt million for general construction equipment&#13;
&#13;
and contingencies.     As a first stage, and after a certain amolUlt of pre-&#13;
&#13;
l~,rinary   discussion, the Bank sent a mission to Chile to study conditions&#13;
&#13;
on the spot, and also to examine in great detail the projects in respect&#13;
&#13;
of which a loan had been asked.        As a result of that examination by the&#13;
&#13;
Bank, the Bank thought it    ~rould   be desirable to postpone for later con-&#13;
&#13;
sideration certain of the proposals contained in the original application.&#13;
&#13;
These were, first, the forest industries project; secondly, the urban and&#13;
&#13;
suburban transportation project; thirdly, the port mechanization project,&#13;
&#13;
and fourthly, the electrification project for the Chilean state railways.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              - 772 -&#13;
&amp;#12;IJ.1FF:       At the same time" however, we indicated to the Chilean C.avernment and to&#13;
     tt td)&#13;
              Fomento that we were willing in principle to consider an initial loan&#13;
              of a smaller amount than the $40 million which had been asked for.        In&#13;
&#13;
              the meantime, the Chilean authorities had themselves proposed a number&#13;
&#13;
              of minor   ar~ndments   and modifications, in the original application, and&#13;
&#13;
              also one major amendment.     The major aTIJ.endment was put forvlard to us in&#13;
&#13;
              November 1947 and asked .that the Bank should finance t""fO additional&#13;
              electrical generating units and also a programme extending over 1948 for&#13;
&#13;
              the importation of agricultural machinery into Chile.       Subsequently and&#13;
&#13;
              quite recently a further request was made for an increase in the       ~llOunt&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              of the loan to cover the capitalization of the interest during the con-&#13;
&#13;
              struction period of the electrical power projects and also an allowance&#13;
&#13;
              of a small sum for mlforeseen contLl1gencies.     Having reviei"l'8d the whole&#13;
&#13;
              application in the lisht of the light of these modifications that I have&#13;
&#13;
              mentioned, the Bank has now reached the position where it is willing to&#13;
&#13;
              consider an initial loan to Chile amounting in all to $16 million.        This&#13;
&#13;
              $16 million falls into two categories; first, $13~ million in respect of&#13;
&#13;
              the electrical pcw{er projects, and an amount of $2~ million to finance&#13;
&#13;
              the import of agricultural machinery.      The breakdown of the electrical&#13;
              power projects is as follows: about $1,800,000 for hydro-electric plant&#13;
&#13;
              at Los Molles; about $~ million for the hydro-alectric plant at Los&#13;
              Cipreses; $170,000 for one additional generating unit already in existence;&#13;
&#13;
              $980,000 for an additional generating plant to another hydro-electric&#13;
&#13;
              installation already in existence; $300,000 for mechanical irrigation&#13;
&#13;
              equipment; $1,600,000 for general construction equipment; $1,000,000 for&#13;
&#13;
              secondary distribution equipment; an item for capitalization of interest&#13;
&#13;
              of $1,150,000; and $157,000 for contingencies.       For the electrical power&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              - 773 -&#13;
&amp;#12;r'    ..&#13;
     '1&lt;'.&#13;
                projects the borrowers vrould be jointly Fomento and a subsidiary of Fomento&#13;
(&lt;"II..Jnt'd)&#13;
                called Empresa.    For the agricultural machinery project, Fomento itself&#13;
&#13;
                would be the sole borrower.      So far as the guarantee is concerned, the&#13;
&#13;
                Chilean Government has indicated its willingness to guarantee a loan of&#13;
&#13;
                the smaller amount which we are now discussing.          Our proposal muld be&#13;
&#13;
                that for the electric poorer project, the loan should be for a period of&#13;
&#13;
                20 years, amortization to begin at the beginning of the 6th year.            In&#13;
&#13;
                the agr.icultural machinery project, we propose a period of ~ years,&#13;
&#13;
                amortization to begin at the beginning of the third year.           So far as&#13;
&#13;
                interest is concerned,   lVB   have been discussing   3!%   for the hydro-electric&#13;
&#13;
                part of the loan am 2    3/4% for the agricultural machinery part of the&#13;
                loan.    To this will be added the 1% 'which the Bank would devote to reserve&#13;
&#13;
                funds.    The Chilean authorities have expressed their wilJ,ingness to accept&#13;
&#13;
                the terms with regard to the amortization, the commitment charges and the&#13;
&#13;
                commission.    We have alreacw circulated to members of the Board some back-&#13;
&#13;
                ground documents vmich give in two parts, first the description of the&#13;
&#13;
                Chilean economy and secondly     ~he   proposal of the   project~   themselves.    We&#13;
&#13;
                circulated preliminary reports on those subjects about a week ago.              Those&#13;
&#13;
                preliminary reports had been produced in a very great hurry, and I am&#13;
&#13;
                afraid Yie were not very proud of them.       We have now circulated amended&#13;
                versions which are really no more than re-edited versions, and I do not&#13;
&#13;
                think make any alternations in principle, or vary the figures put forward&#13;
&#13;
                in the original reports, but the amended versions I hope vull enable the&#13;
&#13;
                board to follow matters through rather more logically than they would be&#13;
&#13;
                able to if they were restricted'to the original preliminary reports.&#13;
&#13;
                Generally, with regard to this loan, I feel I ought to say this.            In the&#13;
&#13;
                present stage of development of Fomento and Endesa it is not possible&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                - 774 -&#13;
&amp;#12;ILIFF:         for the Bank to rely confidently on these organizations earning a surplus&#13;
(I   ~   'd)&#13;
               of revenues which will produce the pesos necessary to service the loan,&#13;
&#13;
               and it may be necessary for the Chilean GoVerllilient to make good any&#13;
&#13;
               deficiencies in earning capacity of these enterprises.              That obligation&#13;
&#13;
               would fallon the Government directly in         ~he   case of Fomento and indirectly&#13;
&#13;
               in the case of Endesa.     Government responsibility in this reGard is implicit&#13;
&#13;
               in the whole structure of these operations, but beyond that implici ty&#13;
&#13;
               responstbility, a specific responsibility of course would lie on the&#13;
&#13;
               Chilean ;Jovernrnent as a result of t.'1eir guarantee.      So far as the Chilean&#13;
&#13;
               Government's general financial position is concerned, we are satisfied&#13;
&#13;
               that they are   w~king   efforts to achieve and maintain     moneta~1         and financial&#13;
&#13;
               stability.    Those need to be continued and as the Government has ziven&#13;
&#13;
               assurance of their \intentions to do so, !'fe feel that so far as political&#13;
&#13;
               stability and economic a..'1d   fin~'1cial   developments in Chile over long term&#13;
&#13;
               are concerned, mere are reasonable grolmds for confid-::nce in the outlook.&#13;
               We thiT'.k that reliance ca.'} be placed on the ability of the Chilean Govern-&#13;
&#13;
               ment to reet any obligations which may fallon them in respect of the&#13;
&#13;
               G~arantee    for this small loan.    We think the need for the        lo~'1    has been&#13;
&#13;
               amply demonstrated.      tre feel, sir, we ought to say     ~his;    that if the&#13;
&#13;
               International Bank was operating by normal commercial standards, it is&#13;
&#13;
               doubtful if we should be able to make this loan at this tLme.                  I think&#13;
&#13;
               it would probably be judged U'.ore prudent to "'rait a little longer, so that&#13;
&#13;
               'lo-e may have the opportunity to observe the consistency and success with&#13;
&#13;
               which the Chilean Government carries out the necessary measures of fiscal,&#13;
&#13;
               monetary and exchange reform.       On the other hruld, I think it 1vill be&#13;
&#13;
               generally said that the needs of Chilean development a.re urgent, and&#13;
&#13;
               after all, it is the function of the International 'Jank to take calculated&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                - 77S -&#13;
&amp;#12;ILIFF :         risks where they appear to be justified.                  In this particular case, I think&#13;
(    tId)&#13;
                that the risks involved are not substantial enough to run counter to the&#13;
&#13;
                Bank's obligation to safet,"Uard carefully the soundness of its loans.&#13;
&#13;
CHJ~.IIUiAN :   I   thi~~   that we might also say that Chile in this last year has given&#13;
&#13;
                substantial evidence of its desire, intention and will to improve its&#13;
&#13;
                financial and economic position.            It is true they have not reached the&#13;
&#13;
                top of the hill, but they are moving up the 'b..ill in a very definite form,&#13;
&#13;
                and if they were at the top of the hill, they probably would not need any&#13;
&#13;
                bank assistance.        vYe have indicated to the representatives of Chile that&#13;
&#13;
                '{&gt;,e were prepared to move       con(;'~rrently   ,,'1. th   them, and as I say, I th..i.nk&#13;
&#13;
                they have given evidence of their will and determination to :iJnprove their&#13;
&#13;
                pos'ition economically and financially to justify this debt.                      As I have&#13;
&#13;
                said, the details of        ~he   loan will be made available in more concrete&#13;
&#13;
                form at the next meetine, but if there is any general discussion about&#13;
&#13;
                the Chilean loan at this point, we might get it out of the "vay prelLlli-&#13;
&#13;
                narily.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:       Mr. Chairman, it is very difficult to put rn;y question here before the&#13;
&#13;
                Board, because I do not know the substantial elements valich 1vill probably&#13;
&#13;
                be contained in your report.            I do not know whether this loan will be&#13;
&#13;
                long term or short tem and ymether there Yfill be special securities.&#13;
&#13;
                Can you give me an answer?&#13;
&#13;
CHATRMAN:       The length of the loans are 20 years and ~ years.                       The agricultural&#13;
&#13;
                is for      6t   years and the electric is for 20 years.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI;       Any special pledees?&#13;
CHAIRMAN:       No pledges of revenues.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:       AIry foreign exchanr,e E,llara.Tltee?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    - 776 -&#13;
&amp;#12;The only thing we have so far as foreign exchange is concerned, is a&#13;
&#13;
guarantee on Chilean Goverrment revenue.     There is no earmarking of&#13;
&#13;
Chilean foreign exchange.&#13;
&#13;
I think we all may agree that this Chilean loan may be made, either in&#13;
&#13;
theory or perhaps for the reason that the Bank has negotiated the loan&#13;
&#13;
for such a long time.     I certainly agree that the Chilean loan is good,&#13;
&#13;
but I can make some remarks about this loan on the Ba.'1k's part, in the&#13;
&#13;
light of the Bank's general policy.     I have compared the conditions&#13;
&#13;
.::;iven to Chile, with the Bank's offer to Poland.   It strikes me that the&#13;
&#13;
entire Polish loan comprises also items which were negotiated as in the&#13;
&#13;
case of Chile; namely mining and electrical equip!:J.ent "Which ,vera proposed&#13;
&#13;
for Poland to be for    7 years, and for Chile, 20 years. I do not necessarily&#13;
consider that tre Chilean loan should be a shorter one.      On the contrarJ,&#13;
&#13;
I must ask that   ~~e   same principle should be applied to the Polish loan&#13;
&#13;
too.    Then there were special pledges.   1:-e were asked to earmark revenues&#13;
&#13;
from foreign exchange, and put them for the benefit of the service of the&#13;
&#13;
loan.    This was agreed lJ.J the Polish Government, so I think it would be a&#13;
&#13;
dangerous thing for the Bank to apply such a principle in the one case&#13;
&#13;
and in the other, leave absolute freedom from such a pledge.      It may involve&#13;
&#13;
a criticism of the Bank that its policy involves the pri..nciple of such a&#13;
&#13;
pledge in one case; so that liberation of another country from such a&#13;
&#13;
pledge is a special privilege.     We were told several times that the differ-&#13;
&#13;
ence in the conditions put before one country and another may depend on&#13;
&#13;
other things such as political stability, probable repayment of the loan,&#13;
&#13;
and so on.    I have not before me the proposal of the President, so I think&#13;
&#13;
I will postpone m;y final judgment of this until I have it before my eyes.&#13;
&#13;
In this respect the report .Vhich we have before us is not conducive to&#13;
&amp;#12;P' "I\NSKI:     quite clear conclusions.   On   page 20, it is said that the Chilean situation&#13;
    .mt'd)&#13;
                still has an element of instability.      On the other hand, on page )0 of the&#13;
&#13;
                previous report it is said that the present political structure seems to&#13;
&#13;
                be stable.   Stability is referred to in page 1 of Section 1 of Appendix I&#13;
&#13;
                as being the test of the strength of the     C~vernment   composed of various&#13;
&#13;
                parties as tested in September and October     1947 when comraunist and&#13;
                saboteur agitation lVas crushed, 'omen there was martial la,';, and disloyal&#13;
&#13;
                ~~d   high officials imprisoned as well as communist leaders.      I doubt&#13;
&#13;
                v,nether this is a special case for political stability.       Even so, I could&#13;
&#13;
                not agree ,vith the other case, as for instance in the case of my country&#13;
&#13;
                or other countries which I represent, when a lesser degree of political&#13;
&#13;
                pressure was called t.he main factor of political instability.       Therefore,&#13;
&#13;
                I must reserve the right to vote for, or against, or abstain from the&#13;
&#13;
                vote in the Chilean case -when I will have before me the final report of&#13;
                the President.&#13;
CliAIBllA.N :   Before I get any other comments, I would like to reply to one or two&#13;
&#13;
                of the points made by Mr. Baranski..      The matter of the pledge of revenues,&#13;
&#13;
                which is, I think, the ,main point that Mr. Baranski refers to in the com-&#13;
&#13;
                parison with the attitude taken by the Bank in relation to Poland is some-&#13;
                what different.    There is a bit of back ground to it, and although we have&#13;
&#13;
                not as yet made any recommendations to the Board in respect of the Polish&#13;
&#13;
                loan, that application is being held in abeyance by reason of matters&#13;
&#13;
                Â¥mich were laid before the Board some weeks back.         That application the&#13;
&#13;
                Board really has not before it at the moment to support a comparison&#13;
&#13;
                between recommendations of the Management in respect of the Polish loan&#13;
&#13;
                and the recommendations in respect of Chile.       The fact is , as Hr. Baranski&#13;
&#13;
                states, that we did ask for earmarking of certain revenues in that case.&#13;
&#13;
                We considered the matter of the pledge of revenues in the Chilean case&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                - 778 -&#13;
&amp;#12;very carefully.    We went into it quite thoroughly, am were particularly&#13;
&#13;
driven to do that because of our knowledge that there had been some pledge&#13;
of the revenues of Chile in respect one of the Export-Import Bank loans.&#13;
&#13;
That pledge was not a particularly definite form of pledge, but enough&#13;
&#13;
of a pledge to constitute a moral obligation if not a legal one, to ear-&#13;
&#13;
mark funds to secure the loan.    In the negotiations bet'ween Chilean&#13;
&#13;
representatives and the bond holders' representatives, there was a ffilggest-&#13;
&#13;
ion that they should adopt the clause which provided that if there were&#13;
&#13;
any pledge of revenues, bond holders should receive prior position.          The&#13;
&#13;
possibility that there would be a pledge ranking higher than the Sank&#13;
&#13;
meant we Yiould have to take a second position.      Vie objected to that,   am&#13;
suggested to the Chilean Government a general fiscal      a~ency   taking care&#13;
&#13;
of foreign exchange revenue for the service of these loans.        The Chilean&#13;
&#13;
representatives objected to that, but there vms a final compromise to&#13;
the situation.    They obtained the waiver of the Ex-1m Bank of their pledge,&#13;
&#13;
and the approval ,Yhich up to   ~~at   time had not occurred betvreen representa-&#13;
&#13;
tives of Chile and the bond holders was likewise given up.         The result is&#13;
&#13;
all are in the same position in respect to foreign exchange.         Apart from&#13;
&#13;
those considerations, the Bank felt there was a distinction between this&#13;
&#13;
type of loan and the type of loan being discussed      ~~th   Poland, and with&#13;
&#13;
some others.     This loan referred particularly to hydro-electric develop-&#13;
&#13;
ment, a long term loan in respect of a project whieh did not itself&#13;
&#13;
produce foreign exchange, but did improve the general eeonoI1\'{ of the&#13;
&#13;
count~,   whereas in the case of poland and some other cases, there was&#13;
&#13;
a readily available and substantial increase, in tPB foreign exchange in&#13;
&#13;
that country introduced directly by the application of the proceeds of&#13;
&#13;
our loan to the particular project.       Not only was there an increase in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                779-&#13;
&amp;#12;r"- â&#128;¢ IRMAN:   the foreign exchange directly resulting from that loan, and not only was&#13;
. \ ,nt'd)&#13;
               it a tangible, available, worth-while type of security, but also there&#13;
&#13;
               was in all likelihood to be increased production and receipt of foreign&#13;
&#13;
               exchange that would probably not last over a substantial period of time.&#13;
&#13;
               The curve up is very strong the first few years, not only because of any&#13;
&#13;
               particular credit position, although the country does good       ~~siness   and&#13;
&#13;
               sound business but also because of the returns, and then drops.           It did&#13;
&#13;
               not appear unreasonable to take foreign exchange in service of the loan,&#13;
&#13;
               particularly when there was left to the recipient of the loan a       ve~f&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               substantial net increase in its foreign exchange.        It was just, as I say,&#13;
&#13;
               good business for the debtor to payoff when business is good; or at least&#13;
&#13;
               to use part of these proceeds for that purpose.        On ilie other hand there&#13;
&#13;
               are cases where it is more difficult to payoff -wi thin a shorter period.&#13;
&#13;
                  was for these considerations that we felt that a pledge of revenues in&#13;
&#13;
               this case might no:t be desirable or did not fit that situation as ,1911 as&#13;
&#13;
               in the case of Poland.      That does not mean however, we are letting down&#13;
&#13;
               the basic rule or that the size of the loan had something to do with it.&#13;
&#13;
               In a given situation it might be necessary to raise this problem again&#13;
&#13;
               if we saw sudden big foreign exchange earnings rising in the case of&#13;
&#13;
               Chile.   If the credit situation became involved because of loans they&#13;
&#13;
               may have from other sources, we might suggest to them again that they&#13;
&#13;
               set up a fiscal agenC".f   ~"hereby   revenues could be available for amortization&#13;
&#13;
               of these loans if the whole situation required it.         I do not mean to&#13;
&#13;
               categorize our procedures too tightly.         Above all we want to have the&#13;
&#13;
               Bank remain flexible in its procedure so that it can move in an effective&#13;
               way and rapidly to make money available to particular needs.         On   balance,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               - 780 -&#13;
&amp;#12;CP"IRMAN:        after considering all the e1ew&amp;nts of the picture, particularly'the&#13;
    Jnt 'd)&#13;
                 representations which Chile had made concerning the         ne~ative   pledge&#13;
&#13;
                 clause and the type of loans heretofore nade, we came to the conclusion&#13;
&#13;
                 to abandon the revenues pledge on the part of Chile.         Vie felt that we&#13;
&#13;
                 could afford to recommend the loan in this       cas~   without any such pledge&#13;
&#13;
                 on revenues even though we were quite fiIT.1 in requesting it in our dis-&#13;
&#13;
                 cussions with the Polish negotiator.&#13;
&#13;
BAR.u.NSKI:      Your ex.p1anations are not entirely satisfacto:rJ to me.        :CraB your state-&#13;
&#13;
                 ment, it is because the Polish loan is a good one that it needs a pledge.&#13;
&#13;
                 There is a verj" definite conclusion to be dra. . m from that that every&#13;
&#13;
                 loan '.vhich is not so good maybe exempt frOB that pledge.&#13;
&#13;
                 It is flexible and might Change.         If Chile had another loan such as this,&#13;
&#13;
                 there is no assurance we would do it the same 'fray.&#13;
     '0ISKI:     It seems better for a country to have loans which do !lot produce any&#13;
&#13;
                 immediate increase of foreign exchange.&#13;
&#13;
                 I do not think so, because the loan in the case of Poland greatly increases&#13;
&#13;
                 returns from a short period on.       The loan ",Qu1d enormously increase and&#13;
&#13;
                 foreign exchange possibilities and a relatively sliSht         a~ount   would be&#13;
&#13;
                 needed for debt service.      It would have left Poland with 1arse foreign&#13;
&#13;
                 exchange over a period of years and with newest of equipment we would&#13;
&#13;
                 have financed.&#13;
&#13;
BA..'tA.NSKI:    I am not afraid to say that this policy of the Bank can have one of three&#13;
&#13;
                 names; taking the line of least reSistance; or inconsistency; or dis-&#13;
&#13;
                 criIn.3..na tion.&#13;
&#13;
CHA Iill.!AN :   Well, I do not agree Â·with that.      It is very unfair.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:        The   firs~   probably is the case.&#13;
&#13;
CHAlillLAN :     Each one of the three is U!lfair.        Does anybody have anythinÂ£; else?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                - 781 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                         I rur. not supposed to discuss this matter.              Mr. Baranski has considered the&#13;
&#13;
                         Chilean loan good and sO,,-"-"'lo., so I am sure that when he is going to 'Tote&#13;
&#13;
                         he vrill do so according to his conscience.               That is the only thing I can say.&#13;
&#13;
BAr'1.ANSKI:             You can be sure I vrill act according to            nw   conscience.&#13;
&#13;
CrtAIPJL~N :             I tl1ink we can     p~obably   postpone   furthe~    discussions of the Chilean loan&#13;
&#13;
                         until ':'hursday.    There are a nu.rnber of other things I have that perhaps&#13;
&#13;
                         1'18 mit:ht postpone as well.      OEe is a letter to llIr. Norman fti'rlour.             is&#13;
&#13;
                         in response to a letter from him to me on the rnatter of the principles&#13;
&#13;
                         or poltcies of the Bank in respect to Latin l'-1!!erican loans.               Has everybody&#13;
&#13;
                         seen. that?   2e asked for a letter prior to Bogota.               1:r. Baranski, do you&#13;
&#13;
                         have      comm.ents on that ::orman l\.rmour letter?             Is it      ri2:ht to send it&#13;
&#13;
                         off?&#13;
&#13;
BJ:.....J.1l:..i\NSKI:   I have no comments, t;:r. UcCloy.&#13;
&#13;
                         Cnless anyone disagrees then, we vdll send it off.                 The matter of the&#13;
&#13;
                         currency clauses, shall we take that up now, lir. ::,.rcLain?               Suppose you&#13;
&#13;
                         e:-:plain to the Board "mat that situation is.&#13;
&#13;
McUIN:                   Vie circulated    to the Board yesterday a proposed draft of a new set of loan&#13;
&#13;
                         regulations to be called Loan Regulations No.2.&#13;
&#13;
MUNRO:                   It is hardly fair to discuss that just now.                ~~   have not had time to read&#13;
&#13;
                         it.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIPJ,fAN:              We will not discuss it, just        e~)lain    it.&#13;
&#13;
lITJNRO:                 It is hardly fair to explain it, if we have not read it.&#13;
&#13;
McLAIN:                  I can explain it briefly.         Since the first loan agreement, . . .,hen it was&#13;
&#13;
                         decided to include in the Loan Agreement a dollar clause ",lith respect to&#13;
&#13;
                         advances made out of the        ~.nkrs    18% non-dollar capital, there has rer,zined&#13;
                         the possibility of interpretation of Section               9 of   Artic~2    of the Articles,&#13;
&#13;
                         which would have removed the protection of that section from the currency&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            - 782 -&#13;
&amp;#12;McTAIN:   other than dollars that should be out on loan. Approval was given to in-&#13;
C   'd)&#13;
          eluding in tlIe French loan the dollar clause which made the borrower&#13;
&#13;
          obligated in any case for part of the loan repayable in any currency other&#13;
&#13;
          dollars.    Loans to pay again in terms of that currency afford protection&#13;
&#13;
          and maintain the value of the Bank'e capital.        Since the provisions   ~~re&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          put in the French loan, we have fOll.l'1d that they are not adequate, and we&#13;
&#13;
          have been working on re 1rising it for some time, because the suoject is a&#13;
&#13;
          complicated one to deal with in the clauses of loan agreeoents.         Vie have&#13;
&#13;
          therefore prepared Loan regulations i;o. 2 to be approved by the 30ard in&#13;
&#13;
          the same rr.armer as the loan reZlllations Eo. I had been approved by the&#13;
&#13;
          Board.     In the general provisions of Loan regulations No.2, provision is&#13;
&#13;
          made for suitable reference in all loan agreements.        '1'hat is the purpose&#13;
&#13;
          of the loan reEulations No. 2 ani we should like to include them in the&#13;
&#13;
          Chilean loan rather than use the former clause.        They involve one minor&#13;
&#13;
          interpretation of Section 9(a) of Article II.        The purpose actually is&#13;
&#13;
          tris.    If, while we have 18% currency out on loan, there is a Significant&#13;
&#13;
          depreciation in the forei&amp;fl1 exchange concerned, we may immediately when&#13;
&#13;
          that depreciation takes effect or    ~men   we shall so determine it, call for&#13;
&#13;
          additional currency to be paid in.    We have not done that heretofore,&#13;
&#13;
          because it serves no useful purpose, especially when the particular currency&#13;
&#13;
          is in a state of fluctuation.    In order to do that with currency out on&#13;
&#13;
          loan, vre feel we must have an interpretation by Which, i f     we   do not call&#13;
&#13;
          for additional currency, we do not waive the right to call then, as and&#13;
&#13;
          if the situation arises, and that is all      ~hat   interpretation does.   The&#13;
&#13;
          remainder of the regulations is intended, insofar as we can, to extend&#13;
&#13;
          to 18% currency out on loan, the protection afforded when it is ih the&#13;
&#13;
          till, ani to make the borrower responsible for giving this protection.&#13;
&#13;
          We wanted you to have that purpose in mind, because the doc1.unents are&#13;
&#13;
          complicated, and necessarily so.&#13;
&amp;#12;I think you have only just got that paper, but 'with that explanatioIl, they&#13;
may be a little easier to read.&#13;
&#13;
I want to report   inforn~lly   of negotiations with the B.I.S.   Some time ago&#13;
&#13;
we reported to you that there was a possibility that the Bank could&#13;
&#13;
some Swiss franc bonds to B.I.S. and other Swiss Commercial Banks, the&#13;
&#13;
proceeds to be used to re-Lrrrburse the Dutch for ex-pendi tures they wade&#13;
&#13;
in Swiss francs under their $195 million loan.       We have been, since that&#13;
&#13;
time, in close contact vdth the B.I.S., wIll showed a great interest in&#13;
&#13;
the matter and are anxious to help out.      We thought we were going to get&#13;
&#13;
two banks and the B.I.S. to enter into this and raise the      eq~ivalent   of&#13;
&#13;
$8 million, but the two connnercial banks walked out at one point, it was,&#13;
&#13;
at about the point of Snyder's letter to the Senate Committee, but the&#13;
&#13;
B.I.S. proposed that they go ahead on their part of the loar, the equivalent&#13;
&#13;
of $4 million.     If the other banks come in, we could of course discuss the&#13;
&#13;
I!lCttter further with them.    The present status is that they have informally&#13;
&#13;
proposed to buy bonds from us in the principal amount of 17,000,000 S1'liss&#13;
&#13;
francs; the interest rate to be 2i%; the bonds to mature in from       5 to 6&#13;
years; and the maturities to coincide with the first maturities of the&#13;
&#13;
Dutch loan.   We would payoff our bonds with the first amortization pay-&#13;
&#13;
ments received from the Dutch.      We shall have to obtain the agreement of '&#13;
the Dutch to get their first amortization payments in Swiss francs, but&#13;
&#13;
we understand from tentative approaches that they are willing to do that.&#13;
&#13;
The 17,000,000 Swiss francs will not be      n~   money, but will be part of the&#13;
&#13;
$195 million loan.    Vie have indicated to the B.I.S. how we thought from a&#13;
&#13;
technical point of view the operation could be done rather quickly.          It&#13;
&#13;
can be done and they are disposed to do it.       We are not asking you to&#13;
&#13;
approve this operation until you have the exact terms and conditions before&#13;
&amp;#12;          &lt;&#13;
&#13;
CH.P~Â·IRM.AJ:-l" :         you, but I think it would be a pretty good transaction to put through&#13;
        nt1d)&#13;
                           because it would represent our first                   borro~~ng   in other than U.S. dollars,&#13;
&#13;
                           and we should be alert to it, even if the amounts are small.                       I wanted to&#13;
&#13;
                                     that information to you, particular before Dr. Jacobssen spoke to us.&#13;
&#13;
                            Now is there anything else?                   The next meeting will be on Thursday at&#13;
&#13;
                            11   0   I   clock.   We will carry on Yli th           currency clause then and the&#13;
&#13;
                            Chilean m3.tter.          r,i'tr.   :Meyer?&#13;
&#13;
MEYER:                      I vall make a statement on Thursday, as to.what                   ~ight   be done by the Board.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIilliAN :                We will adjourn the meeting and have Dr. Jacobssen in.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     ADJOUENED 12:10 a.m.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="15329691">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1948/03/15329691/transcript-one-hundred-twenty-seventh-regular-meeting-executive-directors-held-tuesday-march-23-1948
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1948/03/15329691/transcript-one-hundred-twenty-seventh-regular-meeting-executive-directors-held-tuesday-march-23-1948</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1948/03/15329691/transcript-one-hundred-twenty-seventh-regular-meeting-executive-directors-held-tuesday-march-23-1948</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2011-09-29T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2016-01-14T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b0828bcbdb</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0828bcbdb</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/10/21/000333038_20111021051751/Rendered/INDEX/650460TRANSCRI061560B0March02301948.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/10/21/000333038_20111021051751/Rendered/PDF/650460TRANSCRI061560B0March02301948.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2011-10-21T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1948-03-23T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of one hundred twenty seventh
            regular meeting of the Executive Directors held on Tuesday,
            March 23, 1948
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This transcript, from the session of the
            Executive Directors held on Tuesday, March 23, 1948 covers
            only the discussion one hundred twenty seventh regular
            meeting and informal meeting.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of one hundred twenty seventh
            regular meeting of the Executive Directors held on Tuesday,
            March 23, 1948
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of one hundred twenty
            seventh regular meeting of the Executive Directors held on
            Tuesday, March 23, 1948</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1948/03/15329691/transcript-one-hundred-twenty-seventh-regular-meeting-executive-directors-held-tuesday-march-23-1948</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Sustainable Land and Crop Management,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Bankruptcy and Resolution of Financial Distress,Access to Finance,Debt Markets</subtopic>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Rural Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333038_20111021051751</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Board transcript</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Rural Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            amortization, Bank loans, bond, bond
            holders, bonds, borrower, capital cost, capital outlay,
            capitalization, Commercial Banks, cost of capital, Currency,
            debt, debt service, debtor, dependent, earning capacity,
            earnings, economic conditions, Economic Development,
            equipment, final judgment, Financial assistance, financial
            position, financial stability, first loan, flow of capital,
            foreign capital, foreign exchange, foreign investment,
            Foreign investments, future loans, government guarantee, Id,
            inflation, initial loan, insurance, insurance companies,
            interest rate, International Bank, judgments, lack of
            capital, Loan, loan agreement, Loan Agreements, maturities,
            monetary stability, moral obligation, negotiations, payoff,
            pledges, political stability, private investment, receipt,
            repayment, reserve, returns, salaries, securities, small
            loan, special pledges, subsidiary, transaction,
            unemployment, wages
        </keywd>
        <owner>Board Operations (SECBO)</owner>
        <repnb>65046</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Land and Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Electric Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textiles</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Land Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary and Financial Stability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forests</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>