<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                                            65047        I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Items Discussed at the l28th Regular Meeting&#13;
           end Informal Meeting of the Executive Direc-&#13;
           tors. on March 25. 12~         ... . .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
FOR}~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Page 786       Approval of }unutes of the 127th Regular&#13;
               Meeting of the Executive Directors.&#13;
&#13;
Page 786       Currency Clauses in Loan Agreements - R-155.&#13;
               Loan Regulations No. 2 included in the proposed&#13;
               loans to Chile excluding paragraph 4 of Article II.&#13;
&#13;
Page 792       Loans to Fomento and Endesa (Endesa Project) and&#13;
               to Fomento (Agricultu~al Machinery Project).&#13;
                  Recommendations of President (R-15S).&#13;
                  Draft Loan P~eements and Related 'Documents (R-157).&#13;
                  Draft Resolutions (R-159).&#13;
&#13;
Page 803       Approval of Loans - Resolutions 78 and 79.&#13;
&amp;#12;    CQ}lFIDENTIAL&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  TRANSCRIPT OF 128tb. REGULAR MEETING&#13;
                                  OF THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTORS HElD IN&#13;
                                  THE BOARD RQCII THURSDAY, llARGH 2$,&#13;
                                          1946 at 4:00 p.m.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHA:IRMAN:     Have we a quorum?     Yes.   Will the meeting come to order?&#13;
(Garner)&#13;
               You bave had the minutes of the last meeting.          Are there any corrections?&#13;
&#13;
               If not, we will consider them approved.&#13;
&#13;
               New loan agreements are being passed round to you containing some marked&#13;
&#13;
               passages which represent some small changes.           \\ben we come to them, Mr. McLain&#13;
&#13;
               will explain the changes whidl, I think, are not of substance, but of wording.&#13;
&#13;
                Before we consider the Loan Agreement,     lie   would like to take up first, the&#13;
&#13;
                problem of currency clauses in Loan Agreements.          A memorandmn explaining the&#13;
&#13;
                reason and purposes accompanies the draft of Loan Regulations No.2, and you&#13;
&#13;
                bave bad a chance to see it.      I would like to ask Mr. McLain to make any&#13;
&#13;
                comments regarding that before we h;ave a discussion of it.&#13;
&#13;
KcLAIN:         Mr. Chainnan, I think I will not attempt         to make a general statement 1fi th regard&#13;
                to it; I would rather answer any questions.          I would like to mention one thing,&#13;
&#13;
                however.     Mr. Figgures came   to me this morning, and suggested that regarding&#13;
                the interpretation which forms part of these regulations, it might be better to&#13;
&#13;
                have the Board give it further consideration, and not attempt to act on it at&#13;
&#13;
                this time.     The general principle of the regulations bas been acted on before&#13;
&#13;
                in connection with other Loan Agreements.          This merely supports it.   I would&#13;
&#13;
                like to say that, so far as the Legal Department is concerned, it would be&#13;
&#13;
                very easy to go forward with the regulations as part of the Loan Agreements,&#13;
&#13;
                without having an interpretation passed on it, i f the Board prefers to put it&#13;
&#13;
                over for further consideration.       It is not absolutely necessary for it to be&#13;
&#13;
                passed for the Chilean Loan, provided it is acted on within a reasonable time&#13;
&#13;
                afterwards, so that we can very well omit it from the re gulations today and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      - 766 -&#13;
&amp;#12;            give it consideration in connection with the interpretations, but in order to&#13;
&#13;
            carry out the Chilean contract, we would like to have t.he rest of the articles&#13;
&#13;
            acted on.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:   The rest of the regulations, excluding the interpretation, aXe what we have&#13;
&#13;
            included in previous loan contracts.&#13;
&#13;
McLAIN: .   They are in substance.       They cover the same points as before but more effectively&#13;
&#13;
            and serve to make the protection of the loan contract        co-extensive nth the&#13;
&#13;
            obligations of the borrower and to give the Bank the same protection for its&#13;
&#13;
            money as i f it were still in the Bank's till.      The regulations themselves are&#13;
&#13;
            subject to amendment at atIiY time by the Board as to aI\Y future loan contract.&#13;
&#13;
            Once incorporated in the Chilean contract of course, that cannot be modified.&#13;
&#13;
BEYEN:      Does this clause in the agreement bave anything to do with the 18%1&#13;
&#13;
IIcLAIN:    No.   All it covers is the following point.       We have found from experience that&#13;
&#13;
            l'fhen there is   00   cha rge in the par value of a currency, but an actual depreciation&#13;
&#13;
            which is changing and not constant in the currency of the territory of the&#13;
&#13;
            member, it is impracticable for the Bank at each cllange to call for more currency.&#13;
&#13;
            There is no practical reason why we should do it.        The clauses in which no inter-&#13;
&#13;
            pretation is intended provide that if there should be actual depreciation in the&#13;
&#13;
            currency of a country today and we should not call for more currency until six&#13;
&#13;
            months from today, we would not have waived the right to call.        If in the mean-&#13;
&#13;
            time the borrower who had borrowed that currency had made payments in that&#13;
&#13;
            currency to the Bank, it woul.d fall back in the till and he would have to make&#13;
&#13;
            good to the extent of the depreciation.        There is no risk in not adopting that&#13;
&#13;
            currency clause for some time as the Bank is not lending currencies likely to&#13;
&#13;
            depreciate in the near future.&#13;
&#13;
BEY""":     I see.   Is it appropriate to ask a question aoout the dollar clause, or do you&#13;
&#13;
            want to postpone it?&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:   Vay I ask one point?        After that diSCUSSion, Mr. Figgures, do you still feel you&#13;
&#13;
            would like to have the position considered further?&#13;
&amp;#12;          I would be very grateful if we could.     In every way we might get ourselves&#13;
&#13;
          involved in a long argument about this, and in the end we might agree with the&#13;
&#13;
          Genera1 Counsel, but as it has taken the General Counsel two months to produce&#13;
&#13;
          it, there are various snags I can see that should be cleared up.       There is the&#13;
&#13;
          question of the obligation on the subscriber to make up the value of its curre~.&#13;
                                                                  they .&#13;
          In this immediate problem of the Chilean Loan Agreement/do not wan:t it put in&#13;
&#13;
          a bit day by day am taken out a bit day by day but there is a problem 'Which is&#13;
&#13;
          of very great concern to us.    Let us ass'lmle, to get the data right, that one&#13;
&#13;
          of our members who has ma.:rks as currency - I do not think there is one actually -&#13;
&#13;
          at par value, one to the dollar, out of 18% lems 100 marks to sa:y Chile.t to&#13;
&#13;
          bu;y 100 marks' worth of equipment.    It is purchased by Chile from that country&#13;
&#13;
          which had a certain obligation 'When it put up.; the capital.     After the purchase&#13;
&#13;
          is made, there is a depreciation of    50%,    the borrower repays 100 marks, the&#13;
&#13;
          equivalent of $50 and the Bank asks it to put up a further 100.       The country&#13;
&#13;
          has in fact provided the whole value or ChUe would not have thought it worth&#13;
&#13;
          while to borrow.    There is the extreme difficulty of drafting suitable provisions&#13;
&#13;
          for this situation and covering adequately the conclusion in relation to this&#13;
&#13;
          money when actually in the hams of the borrowers.        There may well be answers&#13;
&#13;
          to that kind of thing, but I think we might go on for quite a long time, am&#13;
          I   ~uld   like to submit that we can adjust it better when we have more time.&#13;
&#13;
McLAIN:   May I make one thing clear.     I am quite sure that Mr, Figgures is rot un.:ier&#13;
&#13;
          any misapprehension on thiS, but from the way he has stated it, I am a little&#13;
&#13;
          afraid he may be.     Under the regulations, the obligation of the borrower in&#13;
&#13;
          the case of a change of par value would be to pay back.&#13;
&#13;
BEYEN:    The only thing I want to say is we cannot solve one of these proposals without&#13;
&#13;
          objection.     Of course, incidentally, the subscribers might object.     On the other&#13;
&#13;
          hand, i f we follow other principles it may make it practically impossible ever&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                - 788-&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                  (&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             to use the 18% ani might very well have implications.       Borrowers w:lll not feel&#13;
&#13;
             at all inclined to borrcnrgUi.lders from you and be loaded with the dollar clause.&#13;
&#13;
             It is not enough to provide a legal water-tight reaction to it.       We must be very&#13;
&#13;
             careful not to make a decision under which we would make good use of the fullest&#13;
&#13;
             lending facilities.&#13;
&#13;
FIGGURES:    It is a very big problem, and we ought to consider it as a whole rather than&#13;
&#13;
             under the draft resolution which is going to come up later at this meeting.&#13;
&#13;
CHAImIAN:    Since this point has been raised, and a request for postponement of this part&#13;
&#13;
             of it, and because we do not believe it is essential to the business of this&#13;
&#13;
             aftemoon, we are perfectly willing to delete that from the Loan RegulatiOns,&#13;
&#13;
             and give such further time as may be necessary for consideration of it.        Is&#13;
&#13;
             that satisfactory to all?    All right.      Then we will consider the Loan Regulations&#13;
&#13;
             with the deletion of page   4,   paragraph   5.&#13;
FIt   lES:   I am sorry to be, or to seem to be, tiresome on this, but I wonder if I might&#13;
&#13;
             put this to you.    These Loan Regulations we cananend from time to time as we&#13;
&#13;
             wish.   However, they give the impression of something different from lIbat we&#13;
&#13;
             have done in the past as compared with what we may wish to do in relation to&#13;
&#13;
             the Chilean loan.     It will look like general policy for borrowers from the&#13;
&#13;
             bank, providing an exchange guarantee.        Perhaps in the end we have to have it.&#13;
&#13;
             It is perfectly clear we must have a clause dealing with this in relation to&#13;
&#13;
             the Chilean agreement.     It would be possible for us to adopt this loan regulation,&#13;
&#13;
             missing out paragraph    4, not as loan regulations but as a schedule attached to&#13;
             the Chilean loan agreement.      We should then continue our previous policy am&#13;
&#13;
             not bave adopted a set of general rules that produce a certain attitude of mind&#13;
&#13;
             towards this problem, befo re we have a chance to consider it in all its unpleasant&#13;
&#13;
             details.   I do not know i f I have mis-interpreted the General Counsel, but I&#13;
&#13;
             believe it can be done in this way.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    _ ?AO _&#13;
&amp;#12;'(cLATN:       I could add that, if we did, the difficulty of course 18 a mechanical one.&#13;
&#13;
               It is a difficulty in that the regulations are phrased in terma of general&#13;
&#13;
               regulations, but we could fix the Loan Agreement so that it could refer&#13;
&#13;
               to the appropriate schedule and not give it the dignity of a general&#13;
               regulation.       It would not affect the regulations which are agreed to be&#13;
&#13;
               applicable.&#13;
&#13;
CBAIRl4AN:     I think it is a little point but we should have entire agreement on it.&#13;
&#13;
               There is an exception to the form in which we set up the new regulations&#13;
&#13;
               which are similar to those we had before on arbitration.         It. does not,&#13;
&#13;
               8.8   the General Counsel says, commit us a.ny more to change the conditions&#13;
&#13;
               in a loan contract as far as future action goes.&#13;
&#13;
KcLlIN:        On that score, these regulations apply only' to loan agreements which say&#13;
&#13;
               that they    50   apply, and can be modified to fit the terms of a loan agree-&#13;
&#13;
               ment.    We do actually mod.i.i"y loan regulations in alJoost every agreement&#13;
&#13;
               we make to fit the particular case.&#13;
FIGGURES:      Then, if I may take the liberty, it proves mechanics only are involved&#13;
&#13;
               and it is very easy to do it the other way, involving only a word in the&#13;
&#13;
               text here and there because tllB.t form can be used.       It need have no degree&#13;
&#13;
               of permanence and it      10 uld   be an annex.&#13;
&#13;
KcLAIN:        As to the mechanics situation, I gather that it is the intention to have&#13;
               these agreements signed promptly after the meeting, if that should be&#13;
&#13;
               approved and cleared, and that would mean serious mechanism difficulty&#13;
&#13;
               in even changing a few words.          It would require re-printing to do it&#13;
&#13;
               properl;y.    The Loan Agreement refers to Loan Re gulations No.2.      We can&#13;
&#13;
               do it by just marking it up, but it is going to be very difficult.&#13;
&#13;
CHA.I.RMAN :   The thing is that we were rather planning to sign tanoITOW, but tomoITOlJ&#13;
&#13;
               is Good Friday, and the ChUean representatives find it inconvenient to&#13;
&#13;
               do it then, so we set our arrangements up to have it done today.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  - 790 -&#13;
&amp;#12;1i'IoonRES:   We shall have   1:A::&gt;   make a manuscript amendment to put the date in.&#13;
&#13;
C:HAl.KMAN:   Is there an;r further cOlllOOnt?&#13;
&#13;
BEYEN:        I am perfectly happy ldth the solution found, that it come up every time&#13;
&#13;
              in cases that occur in the future.            I just want to sound one warning in&#13;
&#13;
              regard to the interpretation.          It lfOuld be rather dangerous        to have an&#13;
              interpretat,ion one way or the other.          I can very well imagine that in&#13;
&#13;
              future practical cases it might be possible to follow either solution in&#13;
&#13;
              agreement with the subscriber and the borrower.                  I can imagine cases where&#13;
&#13;
              the solution would be for the subscriber to pick up the guarantee and I&#13;
&#13;
              can imagine cases where the borrower can do it.                 We should rather have&#13;
&#13;
              it that way than be bound by interpretations.                 That is for the present.&#13;
&#13;
              I sound my warning for the future.            In any sort of dollar cla.use, it&#13;
&#13;
              will always cause an enormous amount of trouble i f until we are certain,&#13;
&#13;
              we come to aI\Y conclusion.         It would be very much a case of having a&#13;
&#13;
              claar cut decision which might embarrass us where both subscriber and&#13;
&#13;
              borrower might come into conf'lict.&#13;
&#13;
IWlAN:        If a member asks for interpretation, we would have to give one.&#13;
&#13;
BEIEN:        Na one has asked for it.          We do not want   1:A::&gt;   prevent anyone .from asking&#13;
&#13;
              for it.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRW.N:     Well, are there any other comments?            It all boils down 1:.0 the point that&#13;
&#13;
              we are justified in following what we suggested and what the General&#13;
&#13;
              Counsel has worked out as a convenient way of confining this to the&#13;
&#13;
              Chilean loan.       We shall not call these regulations.             I cannot see the&#13;
&#13;
              difference myself.&#13;
&#13;
PARKINSON :   I would like to express my agreement on this.                  Regarding the view taken&#13;
&#13;
              by General Counsel, there are so many problems to be talked over, that&#13;
&#13;
              it would be a pity to delay the development of the Chilean loan while we&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  - 791 -&#13;
&amp;#12;PARKINSON:   talked them over.   One problem suggested itself to me, Kr. :McLain, and that&#13;
C    'd)&#13;
             is, the pOBsiblli ty of a loan to a bolTower under the 18%, UIder which one&#13;
&#13;
             party well might bear the exchange risk; ani the borrowing mxier monies&#13;
&#13;
             fluctuating in the subscribing oount17, in which case there another party&#13;
&#13;
             lIOuld bear exchange risk.   There are two types of obligation in the Bank&#13;
&#13;
             'Wi th a different assumption of exchange risk.   That is just anot.her little&#13;
&#13;
             problem, while it is true that, according to the regulations it is agreed&#13;
&#13;
             they are not permanent, they do have a certain psychological effect.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:    Then you prefer that we have this as an annex?     All right.   We will do it&#13;
&#13;
             on that basis.&#13;
&#13;
McLAIN:      We will change them to constitute Schedule 6 of each of the loan agreements.&#13;
&#13;
             In Section 9 of Article II on page 8 of Endesa, Loan Agreement No.5 CH,&#13;
&#13;
             it will be changed to read as follows, "The provisions of       ~   Regulations&#13;
&#13;
             dated March 25, 1948, annexed hereto as Schedule 6 (in conformed copy&#13;
&#13;
             Schedule 7) shall be   app~cable"   and so forth; aoo then down below we would&#13;
&#13;
             simply refer to the Regulations in two places.     That will do.     We will do&#13;
&#13;
             that in each of the loan agreements and we will simply head it "Regulations"&#13;
&#13;
             and call ita Schedule.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:    All right.   A:ay' question that this currency clause should not be attached to&#13;
&#13;
             the loan agreement?    All right then, we have formal approval on that as part&#13;
&#13;
             of the loan agreement.&#13;
&#13;
             )fay we next. turn to the recommendations of the President on the Chilean&#13;
&#13;
             Loan agreements.    I do not think it is necessary to read them.      You have all&#13;
&#13;
             had them.    Unless saneone requests it they are before the meeting for comments&#13;
&#13;
             am que8tions.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:    Mr. Chairman, I would like to draw your attention and 1;bat of our colleagues&#13;
&#13;
             to a certain discrepancy whim appears between the Ieport of the President&#13;
&#13;
             and the Report of t.he Loan Director to the President, as far as the problem.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             - 792 -&#13;
&amp;#12;A    3KI:    of so-called self-liquidation in local currency is concerned.                The Report&#13;
(Cont1d)&#13;
             of the President on pages 12 and 13 says that although as previousl:y stated&#13;
&#13;
             neither of the two projects involved in the loans under consideration is&#13;
&#13;
             self-liquidating in terms of foreign exchange, it appears that both would be&#13;
&#13;
             self-liquidating in terms of Chilean local. currency.           The Report of the&#13;
&#13;
             Director of the Loan DepartD:ent on Page        4 says that it is evident that at&#13;
             the present stage of development of Fomento and Eniesa, the Bank cannot&#13;
&#13;
             confidently rely upon their earning a surplus of revenues which lfill cover&#13;
&#13;
             the peso cost of servicing the proposed loan.             It appears clearly that the&#13;
&#13;
             President's report accepts the self-liquidation of the loan in the terms&#13;
&#13;
             of the Chilean currency and the Loan Department thinks that as far as the&#13;
&#13;
             long term loan for Endesa is concerned it does not exist.&#13;
&#13;
CHA.IRMAN:   Where is your reference to the Report of the Loan Department?&#13;
&#13;
             Page   4 of   the first section.     That is item   "B"   "Conclusions     wi~h   Regard&#13;
&#13;
             to the Proposed Initial.    Loan".     It is item 13.     The REport says it is&#13;
&#13;
             evident that at the present stage of development of Fomento aDi Endesa the&#13;
&#13;
             Bank cannot confidentl:y rely upon their earning a surplus of revenues which&#13;
&#13;
             will cover the peso cost of servicing the proposed loan.               There is certainly&#13;
&#13;
             a discrepancy here which must be corrected.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:    I think two different things       are referred to here. Perhaps:tlr. niff can&#13;
             clarify them.&#13;
&#13;
ILIFF:       I think the two statements are not inconsistent.             On Page   4   of the Loan&#13;
&#13;
             Director's Report it is true we say it is evident that the Bank cannot&#13;
&#13;
             confidently reJ.:.r on the earnings to cover the peso cost of servicing the&#13;
&#13;
             proposed loan, but 'We go on to point out that the relationship between the&#13;
&#13;
             Fomento Corporation and the Government of ChUe is such that in the event of&#13;
&#13;
             there being a deti ciency of the peso earnings of .the undertakings they will&#13;
&#13;
             be made go od by the Government of ChUe.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   - 793 -&#13;
&amp;#12;            That is perfectly understandable to me, but I would not call i t self-&#13;
&#13;
            liquidation.      That is the result of the government making good any defiCiency&#13;
&#13;
            l'ihich comes into the compa:qy's operations but what we are calling self-&#13;
&#13;
            liquidation is that the project earns itself the currency for the loan&#13;
&#13;
            service wi thout    necessar1~    going to the guarantee.    That is the meaning&#13;
&#13;
            of self-liquidation.&#13;
&#13;
ILIFF:      I think it has said the projects do appear to us to be self-liquidating and&#13;
&#13;
            that on the face of it we could. not say that the projects will not earn&#13;
&#13;
            enough in local currency to service the cost of the loan.          In page   4 of   the&#13;
&#13;
            Loan Director's Report we are saying that in the even that they are not self-&#13;
&#13;
            liquidating the Bank still has the further assurance that the. peculiar&#13;
&#13;
            relationships between the Corporation and the Government should ensure that&#13;
&#13;
            the local. earnings will be provided.&#13;
&#13;
BA   SKI:   But your statement goes further than that. . In :my opinion your statelOOnt is&#13;
&#13;
            not corresponding with the President's Report because in :my opinion the non-&#13;
&#13;
            self-liquidation of the project is much more evident than even in your state-&#13;
&#13;
            ment.    It is said in the report then that all earnings of Endesa are pledged&#13;
&#13;
            to the   ~new   development projects.   They are earmarked   exact~   as a first&#13;
&#13;
            charge on theea.rnings.       Endesa is to use the earnings for new investments&#13;
&#13;
            before allowance for the service of interest on debts has been made.            That&#13;
&#13;
            is contained in the last rtp&gt;rt and in the table annexed,        50   I assume that&#13;
&#13;
            the right thing to do would be first to say that because the loan from t.h.e&#13;
&#13;
            Bank is to Fomento on the sane terms is the Fo:mento loan to t.h.e Endesa.&#13;
&#13;
            Endesa must service this loan to Fomâ&#130;¬mto, Fomento to the Bank.            Through this&#13;
&#13;
            scheme it follows      tha~   Fomento makes either a participation or a grant to&#13;
&#13;
            the Endesa.       Any earnings which Endesa has coming from ita new investnents&#13;
&#13;
            are entirely used for the new investment and not for the servicing of these&#13;
&#13;
            loans.    Therefore I say' that the Bank probably deliberately has agreed to&#13;
&amp;#12;.JA .SKI:     assist them, which means non-self-liquidation.     The Bank has deliberately&#13;
 (Cont'd)&#13;
              accepted the principle that it relies only on the guaranteeoÂ£ the govern-&#13;
&#13;
              ment and has abandoned the possibility of relying on the earnings of Endesa&#13;
&#13;
              as the source for the service of the loan.&#13;
&#13;
BEYEN:        I agree with "What Mr. Baranski says.    I think one should avoid using the&#13;
&#13;
              tam self-liquidating.      The only thing 'Which is self-liquidating is a&#13;
&#13;
              commercial bill because the proceeds are used to pay back the bill.         To&#13;
&#13;
              talk of self-liquidation in connection with a long tem project does not&#13;
&#13;
              make sense.   It is the wrong way to use the expression.    ~ iong tem loan '&#13;
&#13;
              is not self-liquidating.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:     What is here implied by self-liquidating is probably that the earnings of&#13;
&#13;
              the loan 'Will suffice for the service of the loan.&#13;
&#13;
BEYF.N :      Every sound loan would be self-liquidating which is paid back.&#13;
&#13;
BARA.NSKI:    I would like to omit it entirely from the President's report.      I suggest&#13;
&#13;
              that this whole passage about the self-liquidating nature of the loan should&#13;
&#13;
              be omitted.   Mr. Beyan's argument goes further than that again.&#13;
&#13;
McLAIN:       I 'Was ,not inclined to participate in this discussion but your remarks may&#13;
&#13;
              have created a misunderstanding.     Endesa is a party to the loan agreement&#13;
&#13;
              and a direct obligor on the loan and thEDi'ore any earnings of Endesa must&#13;
&#13;
              be pledged to the service of the loan ahead of anything else that is not&#13;
&#13;
              a debt, and ahead of costs of caatruction of new projects.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:     Then the report is wrong because from the report it appears the investments&#13;
&#13;
              will be made first.   I am not criticizing the Bank's standpoint; the&#13;
&#13;
              President's Report is inconsistent.&#13;
&#13;
McLAIN:       There is nothing inconsistent.&#13;
&#13;
BJ.   'SKI:   The Bank cannot rely on the earnings but on the government guarantee.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                - 795 -&#13;
&amp;#12;            There are two different things.     The fact that, as I umerstand it, the&#13;
&#13;
            Government of Chile makes certain guarantees to Bndesa for its operations&#13;
&#13;
            has not anything to do with the guarantee of the Government of Chile on our&#13;
&#13;
            loans.   The situation now exists and will continue to exist, that the Govern-&#13;
&#13;
            ment haa put into Fomento certain tax revenues and other revenues to support&#13;
&#13;
            its program.    I think that is oorrect â&#128;¢. So that process has not anything to&#13;
&#13;
            do with the Government's agreement with the Bank to guarantee the loan and&#13;
&#13;
            see that we are paid in dollars.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:   If there is, as Mr. McLain says, a direct obligation towards the Bank to&#13;
&#13;
            oover the interest, that is satisfactory to me from the point of view of&#13;
&#13;
            the contract.    As mentioned in Section V - "Prospects of Repayment", it&#13;
&#13;
            is said in paragraph   74,   "As has been indicated the long range electrifi-&#13;
&#13;
            cation program to lIbich EDdesa is committed will absorb all its net revenues&#13;
&#13;
            through 1954, even i f no allowance is made for dividends or depreciation".&#13;
&#13;
            And the last paragraph, that is paragraph       78, says "From the above it appears&#13;
            that as matters stand at the moment, the prospect of repayment in local&#13;
&#13;
            currency depends mainly' upon the willingness of the government to appropriate&#13;
&#13;
            pesos for the institutions cited above".        If so, it is   unnecessari~   pessi-&#13;
&#13;
            mistic, because as the Endesa has earnings and is the obligor towards the&#13;
&#13;
            Bank, Mr. McLain has said that it is not necessary to say that it is the&#13;
&#13;
            government guarantee which is the main base of the credit-worthiness of this&#13;
&#13;
            loan.    But that, Mr. Gamer, is not the question of the loan contract, that&#13;
&#13;
            is only an observation on the documents.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:   I presume that the word self-liquidating can be interpreted in various ways&#13;
&#13;
            in aocordance with different terms.         The facts I think are fairly apparent,&#13;
&#13;
            though the summa:r:y may h&amp;ve caused confusion.       I think we all understam,&#13;
&#13;
            as explained in considerable detail in the Loan Departmnt report, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              - 796 -&#13;
&amp;#12;               relationsbip of Fomento and l!ildesa to the Government, and the :tact that it&#13;
&#13;
               is a government-owned corporation that has been starled and carried forward&#13;
&#13;
               with a substantial amount of government revenues is quite clear.      With that&#13;
&#13;
               explanation, is there an.y further comment on that paragraph?&#13;
&#13;
               Do we understand the situation?     As I see it, from the standpoint of this&#13;
&#13;
               President's Report, it is not a question of something to be questioned, but&#13;
&#13;
               of whether we uoo.erstand the situation here before voting on the loan.       Do&#13;
&#13;
               we understand the situation clearly enough?&#13;
&#13;
BA.RAJl5KI I   It is satiefactor.y for me.&#13;
&#13;
BRESCIANl:     I think in paragraph 26 it is clearly explained what is meant by" self-&#13;
&#13;
               liquidating, "Since Fomento itself depeoo.s to a large degree upon funds&#13;
&#13;
               provided by the Government, the Bank must, in the last analysis, depend&#13;
&#13;
               upon the Government of ChUe to provide, directly or indirectly, any local&#13;
&#13;
               currency lVhich Etdesa may require for the pro gram over and above that&#13;
&#13;
               available from its earnings".     Self-liquidating in this sense means that&#13;
&#13;
               either from the earnings of Endesa or through the contribution made by the&#13;
&#13;
               Government the local currency'will be there.        I do affim that this&#13;
&#13;
               expression self-liquidating is appropriate technical langwage.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:      The point is 'Whether we understand 19bat is meant hem am if so is that&#13;
&#13;
               satisfactory?&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:      I think there are two sides of this table and there are two interpretations&#13;
&#13;
               of the 1IOrd self-liquidating.    Therefore I think the best thing will be to&#13;
&#13;
               omit the critical words.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMANz      I think we have clBared. up that point.      AIry- other comments?&#13;
&#13;
PARKINSON:     I have a question to ask.     There bas been a good deal of emphasis placed&#13;
&#13;
               all aJ.ong the line on the copper mining industry.      Emphasis is placed on&#13;
&#13;
               the importance of Anaconda investing $18 million in their plant.       What&#13;
&#13;
               precisely is the position     ot that investnent?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  - 7Q7 -&#13;
&amp;#12;             It is not my question, but I will answer.         We have sane officers of the&#13;
&#13;
             Anaconda Corporation now in Chile studying the investment of that amount.&#13;
&#13;
             I think that it is going to be decided very soon.         They are deciding in&#13;
&#13;
             the field itself the way they are going to invest.         That is the information&#13;
&#13;
             I have.&#13;
&#13;
PARKINSON:   How does the Loan Department feel about that?&#13;
&#13;
ILIFF:       :Mr. Burland, could you answer that?&#13;
&#13;
PARKINSON:   How serious would any delay be of the investment by Anaconda of the $18&#13;
&#13;
             mission that they will put into copper refining, and. how serious would&#13;
&#13;
             tha.t be to Chile I s economic prospects?&#13;
&#13;
BURLAND I    It is a long delay over ma.:Dy' years, probably it would serioUsly curtail&#13;
&#13;
             the production of copper.         I believe the plan is to change from oxide to&#13;
&#13;
             sulphide ores over a period of many years and a delay of the investment&#13;
&#13;
             over a period of years would be serious.         To answer d1rect1:y, i f not made&#13;
&#13;
             by Anaconda and not provided from other sources , it would seriously curtail&#13;
&#13;
             production of copper.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:    I think one might say this is one of the largest copper depoei ts in the&#13;
&#13;
             'WOrld.      One type of copper is running out and they are going to have to&#13;
&#13;
             turn to the other.         It is the biggest thing in Chile, and the biggest&#13;
&#13;
             producer is Anaconda.         It lIOuld seem that they simpl;y have to get together&#13;
&#13;
             on some reasonable basis.          I know discussions have been going on.   It has&#13;
&#13;
             to be done from both parties' standpoint.          It has /pt to be worked out.&#13;
&#13;
             Right     llO'W   the officers of Anaconda are in Chile because they want to realize&#13;
&#13;
             as soon as possible what to do.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:    If there are no more questions I would ask Yr. McLain to point out sane&#13;
&#13;
             slight Cbana'S that have been made in the loan agreements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                - 798 -&#13;
&amp;#12;I may sa::! t.h.at in order to get the dra.rt agreements to you on Monday it&#13;
&#13;
was necessary to serd them to you before they were fully cleared with the&#13;
&#13;
representatives of Olile lIhobad been discussing the matter.            There are a&#13;
&#13;
number of minor typographical changes which need not take up your t:iroe.&#13;
&#13;
The first substantial change is on page          14 of the Agricultural. :Machinery&#13;
project loan.    In Section 1 of Article V, which you see marked in red,&#13;
&#13;
the language that has been inserted there is obviously merely to make it&#13;
&#13;
clear that when the bo:M.s have been executed and delivered, they take the&#13;
&#13;
place of the loan to the exteut of the principal amount of bonds delivered,&#13;
&#13;
and to make it clear that the borrower does not have to pay interest on&#13;
&#13;
both the principal amount of the loan and the principal amount. of bonds.&#13;
&#13;
It was suffiCiently clear before, but it is now doubly clear.            The same&#13;
&#13;
change has been made on page 15 of the other agreement.           The next substantial&#13;
&#13;
cllange is in Section   4 of   Article VI on page 18 of the Agricu1.tural Machinery&#13;
&#13;
agreement and the same page, 18, of the other agreement, at the very end of&#13;
&#13;
the section.    You see marked in red, that words have been inserted to make&#13;
&#13;
it clear "and from and after the date fixed for redemption" if bonds are&#13;
&#13;
paid on that date commission on that part of the loan ceases to accrue.&#13;
&#13;
'!he next change of any substance is in Section 10 of Article VII, which you&#13;
&#13;
will find on page 22 of the End.esa Agreement, it is Section 80f Article VII&#13;
&#13;
on page 21 of the Agricultural Macllinery agreement.          That is the insertion&#13;
&#13;
of a sentence which makes the loan agreement conform to the bonds in respect&#13;
&#13;
of taxation and simply provides that the covenants against taxes on the&#13;
&#13;
income of the bonds do not      aw~     to bonds owned by an individual or corporate&#13;
&#13;
resident of Chile.      It is a usual provision.       We bad in the bonds in the&#13;
&#13;
other loan.     There have been some slight changes, almost entirely formal or&#13;
&#13;
clarif.ying, in descriptions of the projects.          I have not taken your time to&#13;
&#13;
circulate those.     They are purely' formal changes.        The changes of substance&#13;
&#13;
I have given you.&#13;
&#13;
                                    _   '700 _&#13;
&amp;#12;CHJ\TRllAN*   All rigJlt.    A:rry question on any of those?   I think they are mereq clarifying.&#13;
&#13;
McLAIN:       The draft reso1utions have baen circulated with the President I s Report.&#13;
&#13;
MENDEI8.      Separateq.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:     We are ready 1:10 consider the resolutions regarding the loan.    I will read&#13;
&#13;
              them.&#13;
&#13;
                                            RESOLUTION NO. 18&#13;
              RESOLVED&#13;
&#13;
                1.    That the Executive Directors hereby approve the recommendations&#13;
&#13;
                      of the President dated March 24, 1948, that the Bank grant a&#13;
&#13;
                      loan to Corporacion de Fomento de la Produccion (hereina.fter&#13;
&#13;
                      called Fomento) and Empresa Nacional de Electricidad, S. A.&#13;
&#13;
                      (hereinafter called Endesa), to be guaranteed by The Republic of&#13;
&#13;
                      Chile, in the principal amount of $13,500,000 (or the equivalent&#13;
&#13;
                      thereof in currencies other than dollars), maturing on and prior&#13;
&#13;
                      to   Juq 1, 1968,   in accordance with the amortization table set&#13;
&#13;
                      forth in Schedule 1 to the form of Loan Agreement between the&#13;
&#13;
                      Bank and Fomento and Endesa annexed to such recommendations,&#13;
&#13;
                      wi th interest, commission on the amount of the loan disbursed&#13;
&#13;
                      and outstanding, and commitment charge on the undisbursed portion&#13;
&#13;
                      of the loan at the rates specified in the said form of Loan&#13;
&#13;
                      Agreement, and upon such other terms and conditions as a.re contain-&#13;
&#13;
                      ed in said form of LOan Agreement between the Bank    and Fomento&#13;
                      and Ehdesa and the form of Guarantee Agreement between Tbe Republic&#13;
&#13;
                      of Chile am the Bank set forth in Schedule      4 to said form of Loan&#13;
                      Agreement;&#13;
&#13;
                2.    That the form, terms ani conditions of the said forms of Loan&#13;
&#13;
                      Agreement and GuaranteeÂ· Agreement annexed to such recommendations&#13;
&#13;
                      be, and they hereby are, approved;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 - 800-&#13;
&amp;#12;       '(Cont'd)&#13;
                    3. That the President or Vice President of the Bank be, and each&#13;
                        of them hereby is, authorized in the name and on behaJ.f of the&#13;
&#13;
                        Bank (a)   to execute and to deliver a loan agreement wi t.h Fomento&#13;
&#13;
                        and Endesa substantia.lly in the form of the said form oÂ£ Loan&#13;
&#13;
                        Agreement annexed to such recommendations, 'With such changes&#13;
&#13;
                        therein as they or either of them shall approve, the execution&#13;
&#13;
                        of said agreement by either of said officers to be     concl~ive&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        evidence of such approval. of any such changes:; (b)   to execute&#13;
&#13;
                        wi th The Republic of Chile a guarantee agreement substantially&#13;
&#13;
                        in the form of the Guarantee Agreement set forth in Schedule       4&#13;
                        to said rorm 'of Loan Agreement annexed to such recommenlations,&#13;
&#13;
                        wi th such changes therein as they or either of them shall. approve,&#13;
&#13;
                        the execution of said agreement by either of said officers to be&#13;
&#13;
                        conclusive evidence or such approval of any such changes; and&#13;
&#13;
                         (c)   to take any and all such other action and execute any and&#13;
                        all such other documents as they or either of them shall. deem&#13;
&#13;
                         necessary or proper in order to carry fully into effect too&#13;
&#13;
                        purposes of this Resolution.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRL!.AN :       Is that satisfactory.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:          Are we voting now or just discussing.&#13;
&#13;
CHA:rmcA.N :       We nll discuss it before we vote.      We are just putting it before you.&#13;
&#13;
                   There are two resolutions which are identical, except ror the amount.&#13;
&#13;
                   If you desire it, we can consider one and then the other, or consider&#13;
&#13;
                   the two of them togetmr.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:          Better to do the two together.&#13;
&#13;
eH    MAN:         Then I will not read the entire resolution.     It is similar except that&#13;
&#13;
                   the second loan is in the principal amount of $2,500,000.     Otherwise, the&#13;
&#13;
                   two resolutions are the same.     One is Fomento and the other Endesa.      You&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    - 801 -&#13;
&amp;#12;-;1'   "MAN~     have heard these resolutions.     Is there a motion to approve them? .&#13;
(Ct.u~f, f d.)&#13;
BARANSKI:        I wanted to remind the Board that I have made some remarks in the informal&#13;
&#13;
                 meeting about J1.'IY position, and DtV' attitude to these resolutions.     I would&#13;
&#13;
                 not like to repeat them because it was only to bring to your a.ttention J1.'IY&#13;
&#13;
                 views and sentiments towards them.       I want only to say that I shall abstain&#13;
&#13;
                 from voting, because I have views concerning some aspects of the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
                 lending policy, especially in respect of the terms and guara:nt.ees of the&#13;
&#13;
                 loans.     That is my statement, am I would like it to be recorded.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRlIAN :      The resolutions are before you.     Do   I hear a motion?    l4oved.   Seconded?&#13;
&#13;
                 Is there   a~   discussion?&#13;
&#13;
PARKINSON:       I would just like to begin the discussion by" saying that the President and&#13;
&#13;
                 staff are to be congratulated on producing these resolutions.           They have&#13;
&#13;
                 had a long, hard am strenuous job in developing the ,original cpplication&#13;
&#13;
                 into the one before us now.     These are projects the Bank can defend to&#13;
&#13;
                 the public, and, more importantly, to the market.         In the course of the&#13;
&#13;
                 negotiations, it has became clear that a number of internal reforms began&#13;
&#13;
                 at least, i f they were notoarried out completely, in Chile, lIhich I think&#13;
&#13;
                 should help to ensure repayment of the loan.         In particular Chile, I think,&#13;
&#13;
                 has shown a ver.y co-operative attitude in its relationship with the Fund&#13;
&#13;
                 in producing a plan for the eventual devaluation of the peso to a more&#13;
&#13;
                 realistic rate.     The rate as you knaw, was not such as to encourage exports&#13;
&#13;
                 and was not such as to discourage imports.         The plan submitted to the Fund&#13;
&#13;
                 is a good one that can be accepted in that it will mean improvement for&#13;
&#13;
                 the Chilean econOJD1.    We have seen, too, an attempt begun to adopt a program&#13;
&#13;
                 to bring inflation under control.        we   have seen too, that the attitude of&#13;
&#13;
                 the Government of Chile towards outstanding bonds has changed, and that the&#13;
&#13;
                 situation is very much    bri~ter   than it was before.      All these are, I think,&#13;
&#13;
                 steps in the right direction.     They began to take steps during the period&#13;
&amp;#12; A'    '(SON:   in which the loan was being negotiated, and I think for these reasons we&#13;
,Co..... 'd)&#13;
                need not complain too much that some eighteen months have elapsed since&#13;
&#13;
                the first application.     For my part, I am very happy to support the reso-&#13;
&#13;
                lution before us.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRJlAN:      Are there any other comments?     If not, all in favor say aye.    Contrary&#13;
&#13;
                minded?     It is so carried, with a note that Yr. Baranski abst.ained from&#13;
&#13;
                the vote.    :May I say that this is a happy day for us; it is the first loan&#13;
&#13;
                of the Bank in 7 months.     All loans to-date have been in Europe for purposes&#13;
&#13;
                of reconstruction.     This is our first development loan.    As Mr. Parkinson&#13;
&#13;
                has said, we have been working long and hard, and so have the Chileans.&#13;
&#13;
                We are very happy to launch our development program on this beautiful spring&#13;
&#13;
                day, and we hope it will go forward with success.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:       May I say, now that the voting bas been made, that I would like to congratulate&#13;
&#13;
                Chile on the loan.&#13;
&#13;
                I feel that I am almost an interested party, and. I have also something to say.&#13;
&#13;
                I feel very happy on this occasiOn.        I do not say that I feel as happy as&#13;
&#13;
                Mr. nlanes.      That 'WOuld be difficult because I know how much he has worried&#13;
&#13;
                and worked for the successful conclusion of this loan.       He must feel more&#13;
&#13;
                intensely the rejoicing than I, and it is a just reward.       The approval of&#13;
&#13;
                this loan is, in my opinion, a very important landmark in the operations&#13;
&#13;
                of the Bank.     It constitutes the first step taken by this organization in&#13;
&#13;
                the development field, am it has been a very cautious step.       Many obstacles&#13;
&#13;
                and difficulties have been encountered am dealt with fortunately 1n a&#13;
&#13;
                spirit of mutual understanding and co-operation.        This loan will be considered&#13;
&#13;
                as a model to be used as a basis ,. for future development loans, and 1 t is&#13;
&#13;
                understandable that it should have been worked out carefully.        As a member&#13;
&#13;
                of this Bank, I must express satisfaction.        We can soow to the world that we&#13;
&#13;
                are not static, but on the contrary, this is a dynamic organization doing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 - 803 -&#13;
&amp;#12;iEl_.:      something tangible to contribute to the economies of member countries, in&#13;
(Cont'd)&#13;
            spite of the world conditions prevailing today, which are not those envisaged&#13;
&#13;
            at Bretton Woods by the foumers, for which the Bank was created to deal nth.&#13;
&#13;
            As a representative of this Board, of the less developed countries, I must&#13;
                                                                               ,&#13;
            also express my satisfaction.    This loan nll have, I feel, a very definite&#13;
&#13;
            effect on these countries.   They will look to the Bank as a more tangible&#13;
&#13;
            and more hopeful organization for their      Olm   problems.   They hope it will be&#13;
&#13;
            sympathetic.    I ha va both the honor and the task of representing nine&#13;
&#13;
            development countries on this Board, and I am afraid that once the good&#13;
&#13;
            news of the Chilean loan spreads, many more applications nll start coming&#13;
&#13;
            in and increasing m;y work nd.ne-fold.   There are directors representing only&#13;
&#13;
            one country, I may consider this a form of discr1mination.         May I extend to&#13;
&#13;
            Mr. McCloy, you, the staff, and the Chilean representatives, my heartfelt&#13;
&#13;
            congratulations.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:   Thank you for that very nice statement.       I might say your umerstanding of&#13;
&#13;
            the problems involved in this whole development program, and your very&#13;
&#13;
            constructive suggestions many times have been most helpful to us.          Now&#13;
&#13;
            this is another indication of your good spirit.&#13;
&#13;
ILLANESz    In the action taken by the Board in approving the Chilean loan, I am very&#13;
&#13;
            grateful for your work, Mr. Chairman, for Mr. Parkinson'S remarks and the&#13;
&#13;
            congratulations of Mr. Baranski.    I have a third theory about the approval&#13;
&#13;
            of the Chilean loan, which I shall not mention.         I do say the negotiations&#13;
&#13;
            have been long am scmetimes very difficult, but I am. happy to say the&#13;
&#13;
            Chilean representatives have Sways received the fUllest co-operation from&#13;
&#13;
            the Vanagement of the Bank, especially from the President, and at all times&#13;
&#13;
            reconciled a different point of view,        Therefore I wish to avail myself&#13;
&#13;
            of this opportunity to express my sincere thanks to the lIanagement for their&#13;
&#13;
            co-operation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               - 804 -&#13;
&amp;#12;         \   ,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Ii   iAN a            On behalf of the Management, I accept that appreciation.         Are there any&#13;
&#13;
                      further remarks?      If not, the meeting can stand adjourned.&#13;
&#13;
BEYEN:                I have one question to ask.     VIe receive from time to time reports about&#13;
&#13;
                      the disbursements on various loans.      In looking at the last one, I cannot&#13;
&#13;
                      help being struck by Denmark not using the loan quickly.         It seems to mean&#13;
&#13;
                      great hesitation on the part of the worthy Danes.      It might be interesting&#13;
&#13;
                      if not today, then some other day, if we could have some explanation.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:             I think there has been some discussion regarding that.      We have noted the&#13;
&#13;
                       same thing.   Is there any statement you could make on it, Mr. Iliff?&#13;
&#13;
ILm':                 At the moment we are in negotiation with our     wart~Dan1Sb     friends on the&#13;
&#13;
                       subject and on the rate of speed with 'Which they are using the loan.&#13;
&#13;
                       Discussions are now in progress.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:              I hope we get the answer.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 MEETING ADJOURNED   5:10   p.m.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         - 805 -&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="15330221">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1948/03/15330221/transcript-one-hundred-twenty-eighth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-held-thursday-march-25-1948
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1948/03/15330221/transcript-one-hundred-twenty-eighth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-held-thursday-march-25-1948</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1948/03/15330221/transcript-one-hundred-twenty-eighth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-held-thursday-march-25-1948</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2011-09-29T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2016-01-14T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b0828bd153</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0828bd153</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/10/21/000386194_20111021065335/Rendered/INDEX/650470TRANSCRI01560B00March02501948.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/10/21/000386194_20111021065335/Rendered/PDF/650470TRANSCRI01560B00March02501948.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2011-10-21T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1948-03-25T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of one hundred twenty Eighth
            regular meeting of the Executive Directors held on Thursday,
            March 25, 1948
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This transcript, from the session of the
            Executive Directors held on Thursday, March 25, 1948 covers
            only the discussion one hundred twenty Eighth regular
            meeting and informal meeting.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of one hundred twenty Eighth
            regular meeting of the Executive Directors held on Thursday,
            March 25, 1948
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of one hundred twenty
            Eighth regular meeting of the Executive Directors held on
            Thursday, March 25, 1948</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1948/03/15330221/transcript-one-hundred-twenty-eighth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-held-thursday-march-25-1948</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Sustainable Land and Crop Management,Microfinance,Bankruptcy and Resolution of Financial Distress,Debt Markets,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Rural Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000386194_20111021065335</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Board transcript</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Rural Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            amortization, arbitration, bonds, borrower,
            Corporation, credit-worthiness, Currency, debt, debts,
            devaluation, disbursements, dividends, equipment, foreign
            exchange, future loan, future loan contract, General
            Counsel, government guarantee, government revenues,
            inflation, interested party, investing, liquidation, Loan,
            Loan Agreement, Loan Agreements, loan contract, loan
            contracts, loan spreads, local currency, negotiation,
            negotiations, par value, redemption, Repayment, tax, tax
            revenues, taxation
        </keywd>
        <owner>Policy and Operations (SECPO)</owner>
        <repnb>65047</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Land and Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Land Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arbitration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>