<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                                                 65048&#13;
&#13;
             Discussions Held at 195th Regular Meeting&#13;
             of Executive Directors Held in the Board&#13;
             Room on Thursday, October 13, 1949 at&#13;
                            10:00 a.m.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Page 2197   Resignation of Mr. N. Sundaresan; Welcome to Mr. D.K. Nehru;&#13;
             Welcome to Mr. Taghi Naar.&#13;
&#13;
Page 2197   United Nations Administrative Committee on Coordination.&#13;
&#13;
Page 2198   Margin for Bank bonds.&#13;
&#13;
Pa~ 2199    Approval of Minutes of 194th Regular Meeting of   Exe~~tive&#13;
              Directors.&#13;
Page 2199   Timber equipment project loans to Finland am Yugoslavia&#13;
              (R-255),&#13;
            Page 2200 - 2209    Discussion&#13;
            Page 2209           statement by Dr. Baranski&#13;
            Page 2212           Adoption of Resolutions No. 115 and 116.&#13;
Page 2212   Report by Loan Director:&#13;
            Page 2212           U.K. Colonial Development Corporation&#13;
            Page 2213           Turkey&#13;
            Page 2214           Yugoslavia, Brazil, Chile&#13;
            Page 2215           Colombia&#13;
            Page 2216           Cuba, Nicaragua, Guatemala, Costa Rica&#13;
            Page' 2217          El Salvador, Ecuador&#13;
            Page 2218           Mexico&#13;
            Page 2221           Peru&#13;
            Page 2222           Uruguay, Egypt, India, Iran&#13;
            Page 2225           Iraq&#13;
            Page 2226           Thailand&#13;
Page 2227   Announcement of Mr. Gordon's election of Chairman of Canadian&#13;
              National Railways.&#13;
Page 2227   Discussion on Loan Policy:&#13;
            Page 2227           statement by Mr. Hoppenot&#13;
Page 2237   Interpretation of Section 7 Â·0Â£ Article VII:&#13;
&#13;
            Page 2238           Statement by Mr. Hooker&#13;
&amp;#12;        CONFIDENTIAL&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  TRANSCRIPT OF. 195th REGULAR MEETING&#13;
                                  OF EXECUTIVE DIRECTORS . HELD IN THE&#13;
                                  BOARD ROOM ON THURSDAY, OOTOBER 13,&#13;
                                         1949 at 10:00 a.m.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:       Today is the last xooeting at which our good friend Mr. Sundaresan will be&#13;
(Black)&#13;
                present.    I understand that he will resign as of today and will be succeeded&#13;
&#13;
                by Mr. B.l. Nehru, who is here today.          I want to extend to Mr. Sun&lt;iaresan&#13;
&#13;
                our deep regrets on his leaving us - I do not think it will be the same&#13;
&#13;
                wi. thout him.   Also, I want to extend to Mr. Nehru our very hearty welcome&#13;
&#13;
                as the new Director representing India.&#13;
&#13;
                I umerstand that Mr. Nemazee is to resign as Alternate to Mr. Onaran and&#13;
&#13;
                is to be succeeded by Mr. Taghi Nasr.          Is he here?   Dh, yes, Good Morning;&#13;
&#13;
                I want to extend a very hearty welcome to you today â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
 .SR:           The prodigal son'&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:       The day before yesterday I attended     ~      first meeting of the A.C.C.    That&#13;
&#13;
                is the Administrative Coordination Committee of the United Nations.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI I      Not Collaboration?     {Laughter}&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:       This Committee is composed of the Directors General of the F.A.O., W.E.O.,&#13;
&#13;
                Fund, Bank, ICAD - what else?&#13;
&#13;
SU NDARESAN I   UNESCO.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:       We had a meeting and discussed various subjects, the most important of&#13;
&#13;
                which was the probable creation of several new Committees or Boards; one&#13;
&#13;
                Committee is to be called T.A.B. {Technical Assistance Board} am another&#13;
&#13;
                Committee is to be called the T.A.C. (Technical Assistance Committee).&#13;
&#13;
                T.A.C. is to be composed, as I understand it, of 18 members onÂ·a political&#13;
&#13;
                level.     T .A. B. is to be composed of various Specialized Agencies of the&#13;
&#13;
                United Nations and the members of T.A.B. will be probably the Directors&#13;
&#13;
                General of the various organizations or their alternates or deputies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    - 2197 -&#13;
&amp;#12;':HAIRMAN:   The Bank and the Fund advised the A.C.C. that they preferred not to be&#13;
,i::onttd)&#13;
             members of the T .A. B., but we would be willing and glad to ro operate with&#13;
&#13;
             them in any   w~   we could.   While we would not be actual members of T.A.B.,&#13;
&#13;
             we would have representatives at meetings and enter into discussions and&#13;
&#13;
             do everything we could without being actual members of the Board.        The&#13;
&#13;
             T.A.B. is supposed to divide up and allocate various funds voted by&#13;
&#13;
             different Governments for Point IV Technical Assistance and, as the Bank&#13;
&#13;
             ard Fund are not to be recipients of these funds, we did not feel we should&#13;
&#13;
             be members of this particular Board.      Furthermore, T .A.B. is required to&#13;
&#13;
             refer to this Political Committee matters requiring approval.      We felt it&#13;
&#13;
             would not be right for the Bank to be a member of this Committee because&#13;
&#13;
             the Bank is supposed to report to its awn Board of Governors.&#13;
&#13;
             I think the A.C.C. is perfectly satisfied with our decisions but are still&#13;
&#13;
             quite anxious that we work as closely as possible with them which we have&#13;
&#13;
             agreed to do.&#13;
&#13;
             One other matter before I go     to the agenda of this meeting:   I was advised&#13;
&#13;
             by letter today that the New York Stock Exchange, in a meeting on October 11,&#13;
&#13;
             decided that the Stock Exchange member firms who carry International Bank&#13;
&#13;
             bonds for their customers on margin will only require these stock Exchange&#13;
&#13;
             houses   to ask for a 10% margin.     I would like to explain what that means.&#13;
&#13;
             Before the legislation was passed which exempted our bonds from S.E.C.&#13;
&#13;
             registration and which allowed banks to deal in them, i f a man wanted to&#13;
&#13;
             buy International Bank bonds ard then wished to borrow money on them&#13;
&#13;
             through Stock Exchange houses, he would have had to put up a      50%   margin;&#13;
&#13;
             i. e., the Bank's bonds had no priority or preference over common stocks.&#13;
&#13;
             As a result of the legislation enacted this year, our bords became what&#13;
&#13;
             are called exempted securities, which means that they are exempt from&#13;
&#13;
             registration through the S.E.C.; that entitles the bords to have a margin&#13;
&#13;
             fixed by the New York Stock Exchange.      The New York Stock Exchange has&#13;
&#13;
                                                   - 2198 -&#13;
&amp;#12;r:HAIRMAN:   margins of 5% on   u.s.   Government bonds and 15% on state, County and&#13;
  ontld}&#13;
             City bonds.    The Stock Exchange was entitled to require the margin of&#13;
&#13;
             15% for World Bank boms, which would be the same as the margin required&#13;
&#13;
             on state, County and City bonds.       At first we thought tilat we would&#13;
&#13;
             accept tilis although a margin of 10% would give our boms an unusual&#13;
&#13;
             position, i.e., no bonds other than U.S. Government bonds would have a&#13;
&#13;
             lower margin requirement.      We have just been told we have been granted&#13;
&#13;
             this 10% margin by the Stock Exchange and as I said, the Bank's bonds&#13;
&#13;
             have the finest security of anything except U.S. Government bonds.&#13;
&#13;
             I would like to first have approval of the minutes of the 194th Regular&#13;
&#13;
             Meeting.     If tilere are no objections, I de~lare them adopted.     {No objection}&#13;
&#13;
             At about 5:00 p.m. yesterday afternoon you received ~ Report and&#13;
&#13;
             Recommendations concerning the Timber Loans to Finland and Yugoslavia,&#13;
&#13;
             together with Draft Loan Agreements and Draft Resolutions and other&#13;
&#13;
             documents.    We are very glad that we are finally in a position to submit&#13;
&#13;
             these loans to the Board.      I am apologetic for the delay in the   p~   ere&#13;
&#13;
             reaching you and the short period of time you have had to look at them.&#13;
&#13;
             I think it is a mistake that the Board is not given more time to read&#13;
&#13;
             papers in connection with these or aqy other loans.      There is no desire&#13;
&#13;
             on our part at any time to get the Board to rush a decision and we&#13;
&#13;
             certainly do not want to do it in this case.      If my Director feels there&#13;
&#13;
             has been insufficient time to review these papers, we would be glad to&#13;
&#13;
             discuss them here today and call another meeting as soon as possible to&#13;
&#13;
             pass the Resolutions.      There is some hurry about it, particularly in the&#13;
&#13;
             case of Finland.     This loan has been delayed quite a while and it is very&#13;
&#13;
             important to get the machinery into Helsinki before the winter weather&#13;
&#13;
             sets in am each day's delay may be a harmful delay.       However, as I said&#13;
&#13;
             i f any Director feels he would like to have further time to study these&#13;
&#13;
             papers we would be very glad to call a meeting tomorrow, Momay, Tuesday&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                - 2199 -&#13;
&amp;#12;CHAIRMAN:    or whenever it wits you.     Are there any questions to be raised today?&#13;
 ~ont'd)&#13;
clOPPENOT:   There is only a small point, Mr. Chairman.     How will that material be used&#13;
&#13;
             by the receiving countries?    Will they Bell it or rent it or use it through&#13;
&#13;
             governmental agencies.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:    Mr. Schmidt, will you come up to the table and answer that.&#13;
&#13;
SCHMIDT:     In the case of Finland, the material will be used by the privately-owned&#13;
&#13;
             lumber camps and organizations.    The program has been prepared through the&#13;
&#13;
             Central Association of Finnish Woodworkers.&#13;
&#13;
             And in Yugoslavia it is an organization known as Tehnopromet, the Central&#13;
&#13;
             Association for handling the lumber industry.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPENOT:    In Finland, will it be sold?&#13;
&#13;
SCH14IDT:    Yes.&#13;
&#13;
PARKINSON:   I have a few questions, Mr. President, mainly matters of detail about which&#13;
&#13;
             I am always curious.     I will begin by saying I concur in the proposed loan&#13;
&#13;
             and I want first to congratulate the staff of the Bank for the patience&#13;
&#13;
             they have exercised in carrying through what seems to have been the most&#13;
&#13;
             complicated set of arrangements we have entered into for the last two years.&#13;
&#13;
             I think they have been extremely patient.      I hope we have learned from this&#13;
&#13;
             experience how to avoid certain difficulties in the future.      So much work&#13;
&#13;
             for so little in loans leaves a lot to be desired.      Nevertheless, these&#13;
&#13;
             loans are a very sensible kind of arrangement for the Bank to enter into.&#13;
&#13;
             I am glad to see that because of the shortness of the maturity and the&#13;
&#13;
             small amount of the loans the Bank has not seen fit to require a negative&#13;
&#13;
             pledge   clause, or the delivery of bonds and other arrangements of that&#13;
&#13;
             kind.    I am not even sure now, and I do not know if the management is w re ,&#13;
&#13;
             that had they known we would come down to no more than two countries, and&#13;
&#13;
             to such relatively small amounts, whether we would ever have insisted on&#13;
&#13;
             going through with the conclusion of the complicated payments arrangements&#13;
&#13;
             needed to enrure the security of a $2i and $2.7 million loan.      I think we&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 - 2200 -&#13;
&amp;#12;PARKINSON:   might well have dispensed with the payments agreements had we known in&#13;
'Cont'd)&#13;
             advance that we would have ended up with loans on such a relatively small&#13;
&#13;
             scale.    While I do not object, I thought we might note it, and I expect&#13;
&#13;
             the management might keep it in mind.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:    It would have been a lot easier without it.&#13;
&#13;
PARKINSON:   We might keep it in mind for the future - whether we need to worry about&#13;
&#13;
             safeguarding our position to that extent.                             For loans greatly in excess of&#13;
&#13;
             $2 million it might be different.&#13;
&#13;
             Turning now to page   4,   Mr. Chairman, of the President I s Report: "It should&#13;
&#13;
             be noted that because of the existence of so-called negative pledge clauses&#13;
&#13;
             in certain outstanding issues of Finnish bonds, the Bank does not require&#13;
&#13;
             that Finland enter into Timber Payments Agreements as a condition of with-&#13;
&#13;
             drawal of anounts from the Loan Account.                             In order to obtain dollars to&#13;
&#13;
             service the loan, however, representatives of Finland have informed the Bank&#13;
&#13;
             that Finland intends, nevertheless, to enter into such Timber Payments Agree-&#13;
&#13;
             ments in connection with the loan.                       The Bank, however, would not assert 8.DiY&#13;
&#13;
             legal rights under such Agreements."                       I am not sure that I follow the&#13;
&#13;
             meaning of that clause.      I am not sure what the existence of a pledge of&#13;
&#13;
             this kind has to do with the Bank I sloan.&#13;
&#13;
SCHMIDT:     It is a technical, legal point, which perhaps the lawyers could explain&#13;
&#13;
             better than I can.&#13;
&#13;
SOMMERS:     Finland has some outstanding credits, under 1tl ich it has agreed that i t will&#13;
&#13;
             not enter into charges or priorities to secure other foreign debt.                                                                   It is&#13;
&#13;
             something of a oorder line case, but we have taken the position that these&#13;
&#13;
             payments agreements are sufficiently like a pledge that we could not ask&#13;
&#13;
             Finland to violate its previous commitments in ,that regard.&#13;
)ARKINSON:   In the case where Finland undertakes to enter in a payments agreement with&#13;
&#13;
             the purchasers of the timber, who agrees to hani over the dollars to the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
SOMMERS:     Yes.     The situation is that, because of the short term of the loan, Finland&#13;
             would not be willing to undertake repayment of the loan in dollars in so&#13;
                                            â&#128;¢   ..   ......   __ -.    A:,a~~~_   ..1.\ __ ': _ _ .. _-'- ..... _ _ _ ........ _   ~_,   ......&#13;
&amp;#12;SCHMIDT:     And they have reached an agreement on this matter with the Timber importing&#13;
&#13;
             countries.   Finland said her willingness to accept the loan on this short&#13;
&#13;
             term basis would depend upon her ability to provide for repayment with&#13;
&#13;
             timber by means of Timber Payments Agreements.   The only'difference between&#13;
&#13;
             the Finnish and other cases is that the Bank is not requiring Finland to&#13;
&#13;
             sign Timber Payments Agreements but has required it where there is no such&#13;
&#13;
             conflicting pledge.&#13;
&#13;
PARKINSON:   How do they identify the particular timber payments to be made to the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
SCH:MIDT:    That relates to a problem which was difficult to solve.    Neither the&#13;
&#13;
             borrowers nor sellers wanted to contract several years in advance for&#13;
&#13;
             specific lots of timber at specified prices in view of the possible effect&#13;
&#13;
             any such contracts might have had on the future price of lumber.    As a&#13;
&#13;
             consequence, the Timber Payments Agreements will proVide that the importing&#13;
&#13;
             country agrees to import during stated intervals at least specified amounts&#13;
&#13;
             of timber f or which payment will be made by paying to the Bank the dollar&#13;
&#13;
             equivalent of their value.   Such amounts of timber are but a small alOOunt&#13;
&#13;
             of regular imports, and the two countries will agree periodically as to&#13;
&#13;
             which lots are to be selected to be the "dollar timber".&#13;
&#13;
PARKINSON:   This is merely a matter of curiosity, but there has been a good deal of&#13;
&#13;
             reference here and there in the contracts to the assumption that the&#13;
&#13;
             supplying countries will sell timber at "reasonable prices".    Is there any&#13;
&#13;
             likelihood that there will be a dispute between ourselves and suppliers as&#13;
&#13;
             to what are "reasonable prices"?&#13;
&#13;
SCHMJDT:     We do not believe there is any serious likelihood of such a development.&#13;
&#13;
             The primary reason for this qualification is its possible effect upon&#13;
&#13;
             price and the bargaining positions of the bu;,yer ani the seiler.   Without&#13;
&#13;
             that clause, the borrowers fear that timber importing countries might&#13;
&#13;
             contend that the borrower is obliged, unier its Loan Agreement with the&#13;
&#13;
             Bank, to sell at least a stated quantity of timber am could use the&#13;
&amp;#12;SCHMIDT:     position to force down prices.   In order not to jeopardize the position&#13;
'Cont 'd)&#13;
             on either side it was necessary to limit this commitment to "export at&#13;
&#13;
             reasonable prices", but we have no doubt that the exports will take place.&#13;
&#13;
PARKINSON:   There is samething else.   On page   7 of the President I s Report: tlBoth Finland&#13;
             and Yugoslavia will covenant to use their best efforts to procure from&#13;
&#13;
             certain European countries the Additional Equipment listed in Schedules            5&#13;
             and 6 respectively to the Loan AgreementSof'    I am not quite sure of the&#13;
&#13;
             significance of this undertaking of the borrower to get additional eqUipment&#13;
&#13;
             from non-dollar sources.   I take it that the enterprise could not SUCceed&#13;
&#13;
             properly unless the borrowers can acquire this additional equipment as well?&#13;
&#13;
CHAI.RMAN:   That was part of the original deal.      We should supply funds fora certain&#13;
&#13;
             part of the equipment md part is to be obtained in Europe.&#13;
&#13;
SCHMIDT:     It goes back again to the history of the development of this project.&#13;
&#13;
             Initially a suggestion was made to the Bank that the Bank should finance&#13;
&#13;
             the purchase of some $16 million of equipment.      In the course of examining&#13;
&#13;
             the proposal, the question arose as to how much of the equipment could&#13;
&#13;
             come from Europe.   It was found that about one half might be supplied by&#13;
&#13;
             Europe and coold be obtained with financial participation by the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
             Accordingly, the proposal was modified, and the modification was      '10   rked&#13;
&#13;
             out in conjunction with the timber exporting and importing countries, so&#13;
&#13;
             that exporting countries should apply for loans to acquire equipment which&#13;
&#13;
             could not be obtaimd in Europe       ani the balance of the equipment should&#13;
&#13;
             come from Europe.   Accordingly we require the borrowers to use their best&#13;
&#13;
             efforts to procure the complementary equipment from European sources.&#13;
&#13;
PARKINSON:   Suppose they cannot do it, what would happen?&#13;
&#13;
SCHMIDT:     That would raise the question as to whether it would affect the timber&#13;
&#13;
             pledge.   We have not had any indication so far that alV of them vd 11 not&#13;
&#13;
             be able to work out arrangements for obtaining it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           - 2203 -&#13;
&amp;#12;PARKINSON:   I do not see why our loan contract needs to bring up this     ~estion   of other&#13;
&#13;
             equipment to be purchased in Europe.    As I see it, the repayment of the&#13;
&#13;
             loan depends on the use of equipment bought on this continent with our&#13;
&#13;
             loan, and used to produce lumber for export.    Why, then, do we need to tie&#13;
&#13;
             in with another type of transaction not of direct concern to us.        It seems&#13;
&#13;
             to me it will just confuse the issue.&#13;
&#13;
SCHllIDT:    One of the reasons was that the countries entering into Timber Payments&#13;
&#13;
             Agreements want to be sure that the borrowers would make their best&#13;
&#13;
             efforts to get the other equipment from Europe.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:    There is insufficient timber to attract them unless they have this equipment.&#13;
&#13;
PARKINSON:   So the whole scheme might become ineffective if they could not get European&#13;
&#13;
             equipment?   That changes the whole thing, I see.     Is the European equipment&#13;
&#13;
             already ordered, or is it waiting to be ordered?&#13;
&#13;
             In both cases, a substantial part has been ordered.       We started out&#13;
&#13;
             initially with the proposal that we should get copies of all orders and&#13;
&#13;
             contracts, but we finally decided that that was unnecessary, but the loan&#13;
&#13;
             agreement requires them to keep us advised of progress.&#13;
&#13;
PARKINSON:   Where are they buying it?&#13;
&#13;
SCHMIDT:     In the countries listed in the Loan Agreement.&#13;
&#13;
PARKINSON:   I mean the non-European countries.     In this country?&#13;
&#13;
SCHMIDT:     Dollar equipment is being bought in the United States, as far as we knaw.&#13;
PARKINSON:   I think that covers all m:f questions, and I concur in the loan.&#13;
&#13;
BASIN:       Is there a definite relation between amortization of the loans and the&#13;
&#13;
             delive~   of the timber?&#13;
&#13;
SCH1UDT:     There is a set amortization schedule.&#13;
&#13;
BASIN:       Not dependent on the delivery of timber?&#13;
;HAIRMAN:    No.   The schedule of Yugoslavia is on page 23 of the Loan Agreement.        The&#13;
&#13;
             first instalment is due on June 30, 1950, and the last on September 1951.&#13;
&#13;
             The schedule for Finland is on page 18.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               - 2204 -&#13;
&amp;#12;SCHMIDT I     In drawing up the schedule, however, account was taken of their ability&#13;
&#13;
              to export timber.       In the case of Finlam, no amortization payments fall&#13;
&#13;
              due in the winter when the ports are frozen.&#13;
&#13;
 BASYN:       What is the impact of devaluation on the contract?          Will more timber have&#13;
&#13;
              to be delivered for re-imbursement of the loan?&#13;
&#13;
 SCHMIDT:     That is depement on what would happen to prices and it would be worked out&#13;
&#13;
              between the two parties to the agreement.&#13;
&#13;
 PARKINSON:   Prices tem to move up in Finland.&#13;
&#13;
 BASYN:       Devaluation nevertheless affects the whole thing.&#13;
&#13;
 PARKINSON:    It is a little better for the timber exporters.&#13;
&#13;
 POLAK:        Your recommendation on pages 1 and 2 enumerate the different timber commit-&#13;
&#13;
               tees which were held in Geneva in connection with the Timber project, but&#13;
&#13;
               I want to draw your attention to the fact that the last Timber Committee&#13;
&#13;
               in March 1949 is not mentioned here.          It is sure that this committee is&#13;
&#13;
               not in direct relation to the loans in consideration today, but I think it&#13;
&#13;
               might perhaps be of some importaooe in case tl:e Czechoslovak loan would&#13;
&#13;
               come up.      I mention this for the reason that the agreements 1Ibi.ch were&#13;
&#13;
               reached at this Fourth Timber Committee in March 1949 formed the basis for&#13;
&#13;
               the decision of the Czech Government to enter the timber project.&#13;
 CHAIRMANs     We will take note of that.      What do you call that committee?&#13;
 POLAK:        The Fourth Timber Committee, and it was held from March 1 to 10, 1949.&#13;
CHAffiMAN:     In Geneva,?&#13;
&#13;
 POLAK:        Yes, and the agreements which were reached at that committee are the basis&#13;
&#13;
               for the Czech participation.&#13;
&#13;
 CHAIRJIAN:    Is there aqr reason for leaving that 'Committee, out'?&#13;
&#13;
 SCHMIDT:     . The primary reason -was that at the meeti"ng of the Committee in the September&#13;
&#13;
               pt"e'ceding . we had distributed the first working drafts of the Loan&#13;
&#13;
               Agreement and we had indicated to all interested parties from that point&#13;
&#13;
               on that all negotiations should be directly with the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
                                                 - 220t; -&#13;
&amp;#12;POLAK:        The reason why I especially mentioned my point is       tha~   the conditions which&#13;
&#13;
              were fixed in September 1948, are different from those to which the&#13;
&#13;
              Czechoslovak Government agreed to in the Fourth Committee in March 1949.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:     Any questions?   Mr. Baranski?&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:     I remember that originally a loan of $17 million was contemplated and the&#13;
&#13;
              Bank then indicated its willingness to take over sometiling like $7 million.&#13;
&#13;
              The amount of $10 million should be financed in the form of credits or&#13;
&#13;
              otherwise in the framework of trade agreements by the European importing&#13;
&#13;
              countries.   Has tile Bank axw news on this?&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRlLA.N:   Based on the original amount of $8 million.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:     What about the other $9 million?     This amount corresponds to the additional&#13;
&#13;
              purchases of equipment.    How shall they be financed?&#13;
&#13;
SCH14IDT:     It goes back to the question Mr. Parkinson asked.        The equipment which&#13;
&#13;
              had to be paid for in dollars was to be financed by the Bank and is listed&#13;
&#13;
              in Schedule 2 of the Loan Agreements.         The arrangements under which the&#13;
&#13;
              other equipment is to be obtained    are to   be worked out by the parties concerned.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:     What about the credit scheme?      Is the purchase of additional equipment on&#13;
&#13;
              credit or on a compensation basis?&#13;
&#13;
SCHMIIY1':    It was not definitely stated that this additional equipment should be&#13;
&#13;
              obtained on a credit basis.      Inasmuch as the equipment could be obtained&#13;
&#13;
              in Europe, it was felt that it should be obtained on whatever basis was&#13;
&#13;
              suitable to the parties.    In same cases credit would be extended: in other&#13;
&#13;
              cases the balance of payments relations might permit immediate payment.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:     Is the Bank not informed about that?&#13;
&#13;
SCHMIDT:      No.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:     Mr. Chairman, I think too questions have all been put forward.          Before we&#13;
&#13;
              shall proceed to a decision, I would like to make a kind of declaration.&#13;
&#13;
              I would not make it before the discussion is over.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:     Will you please wait for a minute.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               - 2206 -&#13;
&amp;#12;HOPPENOT:    Mr. Chairman, in that loan agreement, some kind of rough agreement has been&#13;
&#13;
             made with the different countries involved, I would not say ties, but&#13;
             connec'b! the use of dollar currency ani use of others; this is when the&#13;
             contract says what amount of other equipment will be sold by the importing&#13;
&#13;
             countries ani even by some which are not member countries, to timber&#13;
&#13;
             exporting countries.   I feel that there has doubtless been a great deal&#13;
&#13;
             of ingenuity and cleverness on the part of the Bank's staff; I hope that&#13;
             the staff will use the same qualities in the further negotiations where&#13;
&#13;
             the use of dollars ani other currencies may be involved, maybe not in the&#13;
&#13;
             present form but in some other form.&#13;
CHAIRMAN:    Any other cpestions?&#13;
PARKINSON:   I do have another question.   I see that the two borrowers agree to deliver&#13;
&#13;
             certain amunts of timber equipment in the next three years including 1949.&#13;
             I think it unlikely that timber agreements can be completed and goods&#13;
             delivered before the end of 1949.     I find it hard to believe that we can&#13;
             expect any particular exports in 1949 relating to this particular loan.&#13;
             Does not this mean we will have to mod1.fy the terms on page 21 of the&#13;
             Finnish Loan?   Am I right in thinking that the borrowers do not get the&#13;
&#13;
             money from the Bank until   th~   have completed payments agreements?   Six&#13;
             to eight of them?&#13;
SCID4IDT:    The number of countries with which payments agreements must be worked out&#13;
                              it is only with&#13;
             is not so large;/three to four for each borrower. A great deal of work&#13;
             has been done on payments agreements and agreement has already been reached&#13;
             between the United Kingdom ani several countries on the text.     The difficult&#13;
&#13;
             part of that work has been done.     That does not mean it is necessarily going&#13;
&#13;
             to be easy but we are well along and given willingness and a little good&#13;
&#13;
             fortune we might have the agreements worked out rather soon.&#13;
PARKINSON:   My other question relates to Mr. Crena de Iongh t 5 department.   In connection&#13;
&#13;
             with disbursements the Bank hands over money on proof of purchase or&#13;
&#13;
                                                - 2207 ...&#13;
&amp;#12;PARKINSON:   intention to purchase.   The borrower does not get the money until he has&#13;
'Cont Id)&#13;
             paid for the goods.   Are we developing aqy standard practice on that?&#13;
             In this case we should not hold Yugoslavia up.&#13;
CRENA DE     We can make camnitments to banks and we can also make credits either by&#13;
  IONGH:&#13;
             the usual cash contracts or letters of commitment.     The Bank can only pay&#13;
             against documents.    Either we repay Finland and Yugoslavia after they have&#13;
&#13;
             paid out cash or commitments to banks in New York.&#13;
&#13;
TANSLEY:     H.M.G. is very anxious to proceed with the signing of the payments agreements&#13;
             and, as the Board will remember, I did speak of payments agreements to be&#13;
             signed by December 31 of this year.     I do not know i f other DiI:ectors can&#13;
&#13;
             indicate whether the payments agreements will be signed by the end of the&#13;
             year, or whether the staff has aqy information.&#13;
SCHMIDT:     We will do everything to assist them in proceeding expeditiously.&#13;
PARKINSON:   Payments agreements are not a welcome feature of international trade.      They&#13;
             generally relate to bilateral as opposed to muJ.ti-lateral trade.&#13;
HOPPENOT:    I feel that these transactions can come under present payments agreements.&#13;
TANSLEY:     Speaking for the United Kingdom, it is a peculi.a.r, form of payments&#13;
&#13;
             agreement.   The opposition is because they concern payment in U.S. dollars.&#13;
BARANSKI:    A small question i f I may interrup:, here.   Why has the Bank abandoned&#13;
&#13;
             50   eaSily the request for the conclusion of payments agreements by Finland?&#13;
             Was it not for the reason that they were not considered as important?&#13;
             My   question is, was it really necessary to ask for the complicated&#13;
&#13;
             payments agreements for these small loans?&#13;
CHAIRMAN:    That is how the deal was originally set up.&#13;
BARANSKI:    But we decided that it was not VIOrthwhile to cancel the whole agreement&#13;
&#13;
             with Finland only because a negative pledge clause in other bonds prevented&#13;
&#13;
             the application of the payments agreement scheme.      So we did not consider&#13;
&#13;
             this scheme as essential or important.&#13;
CHAIRMAN:    We still have payments agreements in Finland.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          - 2208 -&#13;
&amp;#12;BARANSKI:   Not in a legal sense.&#13;
&#13;
            As a practical   ~tter.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:   As a practical   ~tter'   A country can get dollars from many sources.&#13;
&#13;
            Yugoslavia may also get dollars from other sources, not only from timber.&#13;
&#13;
            I think too much time has been spent on this formula, which is in my&#13;
&#13;
            opinion, unsuitable for the use in future contracts.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:   It certainly takes a lot of time, I admit that.    Is there any other&#13;
&#13;
            discussion?&#13;
&#13;
            I propose we vote separately on the two draft Resolutions, i.e., we have&#13;
&#13;
            draft Resolutions covering the loan to Finland and that to Yugoslavia.&#13;
&#13;
            That is the only statement I wanted to make.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:   Mr. Chairman, I must confess that I am in a very awkward position as to&#13;
&#13;
            the-proposed loan.    Speaking frankly, all my views and   fee~ings   are&#13;
&#13;
            clearJ,y against the scheme ani pattern of the loan.    I shall not discuss&#13;
&#13;
            the details, but I should like to stress the fact that in respeot to a&#13;
&#13;
            loan amounting w     5 million dollars, with the average maturity of the&#13;
            credit of a little more than one year, and involving a commodity which&#13;
&#13;
            the respective countries are equally eager w export and w import, the&#13;
&#13;
            discussions ani negotiations lasted almost one and a half years (i.e.&#13;
&#13;
            longer than the proposed average duration of the credit) and were rather&#13;
&#13;
            difficult and complicated.     That proves only that the scheme, although it&#13;
&#13;
            may cover the interests of the Bank, is impractical and unsuitable to be&#13;
&#13;
            used for the benefit of members in this case ani in similar cases.          For&#13;
&#13;
            these reasons I VDuld be disposed to rather vote against the loan so as&#13;
&#13;
            to express my objections against the value of this scheme.&#13;
&#13;
            On the other hand, the fact that both countries which have now accepted&#13;
&#13;
            the terms of the loan belong w the group which elected me w the post&#13;
&#13;
            of the Executive Direcwr, obviously implies my duty not to do anything&#13;
&#13;
            that would be directly hannful to what they consider as being in their&#13;
&#13;
            interest, and to Vthich so much of their energy has been spent.&#13;
&amp;#12;BARANSKI:   But now I come to the crucial point.     There was one important factor&#13;
~Cont'd)&#13;
            underlying the proposed loan which has been originally considered as the&#13;
&#13;
            very reason for which these negotiations have been started.     It was the&#13;
&#13;
            intention of the Bank to demonstrate in a specific way, even if in a token&#13;
&#13;
            form, its willingness to enter into business relations with every country&#13;
&#13;
            irrespecti vely of what the current opinion in this or other country thought&#13;
&#13;
            about its political character, and so to affirm the international character&#13;
&#13;
            of the Bank and the stipulations of Article IV, section 10 of the Articles&#13;
&#13;
            of Agreement.    That would be in my opinion indeed a factor powerful enough&#13;
&#13;
            to justify all the efforts made in bringing about this loan into effect,&#13;
&#13;
            and so to overcome my doubts by offsetting,Â·Â· at least in part, my objections&#13;
&#13;
            raised before.    But this original idea has been frustrated by the fact that&#13;
&#13;
            loans are being proposed now only to two countries - Finland and Yugoslavia.&#13;
&#13;
            I do not blame anybody for this fact, nor do I try to deny the Bank's good&#13;
&#13;
            will to include other Eastern :Eunopean countries into the loan scheme;&#13;
&#13;
            I only regret that two member countries decided to use their dollars for&#13;
&#13;
            payments to both proposed borrowers but so far they did not find it possible&#13;
&#13;
            to do the same in respect to another country with which the timber loan is&#13;
&#13;
            being negotiated.    But the fact is that with loans given to Finland and&#13;
&#13;
            Yugoslavia only, the whole positive psychological effect will be lost, and&#13;
&#13;
            it is even possible that the comments on the Bank's action will be made&#13;
&#13;
            here and there exactly in a sense opposite to the original intention.&#13;
&#13;
            Thus the only motive which could make the credit scheme interesting and&#13;
&#13;
            ove~igh   its shortcomings, has disappeared.&#13;
&#13;
            I trust you will forgive me, Mr. Chairman, for having dealt at length with&#13;
&#13;
            motivesÂ· which are influencing my action in this papticularly difficult&#13;
&#13;
            case.   I think that the only action I can take in view of these conflicting&#13;
&#13;
            motives is to abstain from the vote.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          - 2210 -&#13;
&amp;#12;CHAIRMAN:    . I regret very much that we have been unable to conclude the loan to&#13;
&#13;
              Czechoslovakia, at the same time that we have submitted these loans.&#13;
&#13;
              In your declaration you state that the other countries, import countries,&#13;
&#13;
              have not been willing to enter into agreement.      I do not know whether that&#13;
&#13;
              is correct.   My   impression was that that has never been satisfactorily&#13;
&#13;
              settled.   I told the representatives of the Czech Government that I would&#13;
&#13;
              be ver,y glad personally to use   ~   efforts to settle that question as soon&#13;
&#13;
              as they decide whether they would be willing to export a sufficient amount&#13;
&#13;
              of timber and have an export agreement loan for a similar period of time&#13;
&#13;
              as the others, so I am not sure that it is correct to say that the importing&#13;
&#13;
              countries have not agreed to sign Timber payments Agreements in the case of&#13;
&#13;
              Czechoslova.kia.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:     So I understand that the question is still open?&#13;
&#13;
r:HAIRMAN:    Yes.   We have done ever,ything we can.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:     The conclusion of the loan agreement with Czechosl ovakia would be a most&#13;
&#13;
              important thing, because otherwise the American press here may give to the&#13;
&#13;
              timber loans comments in the sense completely opposite to that which was&#13;
&#13;
              the original intention of the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIR.MAN:    I hope they do not interpret it that way, but I cannot guarantee what the&#13;
&#13;
              press will say'    (Laughter)&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:     I do not blame you for that.&#13;
&#13;
CHANG:        I have listened with great interest to the statement just made by Mr. Baranski&#13;
&#13;
              and the position he has taken in connection with this loan.      May I say we&#13;
&#13;
              are living in a world of great complexity, that sometimes the relationship&#13;
&#13;
              between one country and another is very obscure, and when it involves a&#13;
&#13;
              third country, it becomes even more confused.      I find myself in a similar&#13;
&#13;
              delemma., and I would like to make a statement in connection with this loan.&#13;
&#13;
              The Board is perhaps aware that Yugoslavia has ceased to have normal&#13;
&#13;
              diplomatic relations with the National Government of China, and in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                - ??"    -&#13;
&amp;#12;';HANO:     consequence   of this, I feel there are some legal aspects which have           ~o    be&#13;
,-,onted)&#13;
            taken into consideration, and I therefore feel under these circumstances&#13;
&#13;
            I shall abstain from voting on t le loan to Yugoslavia.            In taking this&#13;
&#13;
            action, I hope the Board will understand that it is done without any&#13;
&#13;
            prejudice to the merl ts of the loan or to the members concerned.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:   Is there any other discussion?      If not, I would like to have a motion to&#13;
&#13;
            approve the draft resolution of the loan to Finland.             Seconded?   All in&#13;
&#13;
            favor please say aye.    Opposed?    I hereby declare the loan of $2,300,000&#13;
&#13;
            to Finland approved.&#13;
&#13;
            Do I hear a motion on the loan to Yugoslavia?          Seconded?     All in favor&#13;
&#13;
            please say aye.   Opposed?    I hereby declare the loan of $2,700,000 to&#13;
&#13;
            Yugoslavia approved.&#13;
&#13;
            I am very glad that we have finally concluded these loans which have&#13;
&#13;
            certainly taken an extraordinary length of t1:me.         I would like particularly&#13;
&#13;
            in this case to compliment the Working Party for their patience and&#13;
&#13;
            ingenuity, and I would like to point out particularly what a fine job&#13;
&#13;
            Mr. Schmidt has done.&#13;
&#13;
TANSLEY:    As the representative of the country. taking the biggest share, I would&#13;
&#13;
            certainly like to compliment the staff on the splendid work they have done.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:   I would like to ask again that nothing is said about this publicly until&#13;
&#13;
            the loans are signed, which will probably be on 1l0nday.&#13;
&#13;
            I now ask the Loan Director to give us a review of the loan applications.&#13;
&#13;
ILIFF:      So far as Europe is concerned, there are only three matters of Significance&#13;
&#13;
            I have to refer   to~   First, with regard to the United Kingdom, we have been&#13;
&#13;
            informed by the   ~.K._?olonial   Development      Corporati~n   that they wish to send&#13;
&#13;
            two authorized representatives to Washington to continue - and we hope&#13;
&#13;
            conclude - the negotiations for a loan from the Bank to the Colonial&#13;
&#13;
            Development Corporation.     The two representatives of the Corporation will&#13;
&#13;
            arrive in Washington next week.      We have no official information at this&#13;
&#13;
                                                  _   ??1? _&#13;
&amp;#12;ILIFF:        point, as to what the probable amo\lllt of the proposed borrowing will be,&#13;
'~ont'd)&#13;
              but we have reason to believe it will be substantially less than the&#13;
               original amount discussed at earlier stages, which was $15 million.&#13;
&#13;
              TURKEY - As the Board know, we have at the moment a number of technicians&#13;
&#13;
               in Turkey, who are examining three projects which the Bank indicated as&#13;
&#13;
               being probably suitable for Bank financing.      In addition, at the request&#13;
&#13;
              . of the Turkish Government, the Bank sent out Harold Johnson to investigate&#13;
&#13;
               the possibility of mobilizing private capital in Turkey, in order that it&#13;
               might be generated into productive investment in that country.      Mr. Johnson&#13;
&#13;
               arrived in Turkey on October 6.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPENOl':     Who is Mr. Johnson?&#13;
CHAIRMAN:      He is employed on a    tempora~   basis.   He was formerly a partner of a law&#13;
&#13;
               firm in Paris, and at the present time is a partner of Merrill Lynch, Pierce,&#13;
               Fenner &amp; Beane and has been engaged on a temporary basis by the Bank.&#13;
 BRESCIANI:    What are the three projects?&#13;
 ILIFF:        A multi-purpose irrigation, hydro-electric, and flood control project - the&#13;
               Seyhan   Dam; second, grain storage facilities; and third, reconstruction of&#13;
               Turkish ports.&#13;
HOPPENOT:      Which ports?&#13;
 ILIFFt        That is what he is there to find out.&#13;
 PARKINSON:    All Government enterprises?&#13;
 ILIFF:        The Turkish Government also asked the Bank to send an overall development&#13;
&#13;
               mission on the Colombia model, to advise the Turkish Government on 1:h e&#13;
               lines along which their economic development ought to proceed.       The Bank&#13;
&#13;
               has selected a Mr. Barker, who was part of the Overseas Consultants team&#13;
&#13;
               that went to Iran.     He was with Overseas Consultants in the capacity of&#13;
&#13;
               financial and economic advisor.      We saw the result of his work there, and&#13;
&#13;
               were extremely impressed with his approach to the problem of an undeveloped&#13;
&#13;
               econoIIl3'.   The Bank asked him to head the mission to Turkey.   Mr. Barker&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    - 2213 -&#13;
&amp;#12;ILIFF:        accepted and will leave for Turkey early in November, to make a preliminary&#13;
 :mt1d)&#13;
              survey and determine wbat, should be the composition of the mission.&#13;
              I also want to mention YUGOSLAVIA.     I refer to the report which Mr.Hoar&#13;
&#13;
              recently made to the Board.   Most of the mission has returned to Washington,&#13;
&#13;
              and are preparing technical reports.    As soon as these are assembled and&#13;
              collated we shall attempt to formulate a policy concerning Yugoslavia at&#13;
&#13;
              staff level.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:     When do you expect to do that?&#13;
&#13;
n.IFF:        It will be a matter of some weeks before all the reports have been collated.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:     So sometime next month.&#13;
&#13;
ILIFF:        LATIN AMERICA - We have today sent a mission to    Brazi~,   consisting of&#13;
              Mr. Demuth, Messrs. Larsen and Parker of the Economic Department, and Mr.&#13;
&#13;
              \flheelock of the Loan Department. We have before us a number of projects&#13;
&#13;
              suggested by the Federal Government and by the State Governments of Brazil,&#13;
&#13;
              as being suitable for Bank financing.     Most of them are in the electric&#13;
              power field.   The Federal Government attach top priority to the extension&#13;
&#13;
              of electric power facilities for Brazil.     We felt that before we could make&#13;
              any recommendations to the Board about the Bank's future investment policy&#13;
&#13;
              in Brazil, we ought to re-appraise the whole Brazilian financial Situation,&#13;
              and it is the purpose of this mission to do so.&#13;
PARKINSotl:   I might make one observation here.     I notice that in missions to Latin&#13;
              America, we never see the name of a Latin American member of the staff.       I&#13;
&#13;
              do not think we have any Latin American members on the staff.       I can recall&#13;
&#13;
              Dr. Lopez-Herrarte, but I cannot think of any other person ina senior&#13;
&#13;
              position. We might give a little thought in trying to attract to the&#13;
&#13;
              staff of the Bank soma senior persons from Latin America â&#128;¢&#13;
..,HAIRMAN:   We have been doing so, and will continue.&#13;
ILIFF:&#13;
               -&#13;
              CHILE - The Board will probably have seen the press announcement by the&#13;
&#13;
              Export-Import Bank, in which they announced that they had recently granted&#13;
&#13;
                                                - 2214 -&#13;
&amp;#12;ILIFF:       a credit of $25 million to Chile.   The need for this credit had arisen on&#13;
~onttd)&#13;
             account of the decline in Chile's dollar income due to the fall in the&#13;
             world price of copper, and a cutback in copper production by Anaconda.&#13;
&#13;
             We have before us a number of projects for further Bank financing, and&#13;
&#13;
             here again, we feel that before we engage in any additional operations in&#13;
&#13;
             Chile, we ought to re-appraise the whole Chilean situation.       A study of&#13;
&#13;
             Chile has just been carried out at working party level in the Bank.       Their&#13;
&#13;
             report will be brought before the Staff Loan Committee next week, and in&#13;
             the light of that, we shall attempt to formulate a policy on Chile. We&#13;
&#13;
             have had some concern about the local currency aspects of the Endesa&#13;
&#13;
             project which we had already undertaken to finance as part of our recent&#13;
&#13;
             loan. ---At-a 'later- stage today, Mr. Crena de Iongh will be talking generally&#13;
             on the subject of end-use supervision, and I shall leave it to him to&#13;
&#13;
             mention the points in connection with the Chilean situation about which we&#13;
             do not feel very happy.&#13;
&#13;
             COLOMBIA - The mission which is now in Colombia unier Dr. Currie is&#13;
&#13;
             expected to conclude its work by the end of this month, and return to&#13;
             Washington ani prepare its reports.      lIeanrrhile, we are still continuing&#13;
&#13;
             our negotiations with respect to the three hydro-electric projects which&#13;
             had been submitted to us by the Colombian authorities some time ago.&#13;
             Difficulties had arisen in connection with the supply of water and we&#13;
&#13;
             had a special study of the water supply made by Carl Flesher, an engineer.&#13;
             It is now reported that sufficient water will be available to ensure that&#13;
&#13;
             the turbines will keep turning at all times of the year, and that difficulty&#13;
&#13;
             that had stood in the way of consideration of these proposals has now been&#13;
&#13;
             disposed of, and negotiations are proceeding.&#13;
PARKINSON:   What projects are these?&#13;
ILIFF:       The Labrija, La Insula and Anchicaya hydro-electric projects.&#13;
PARKINSON:   Run   by whom?&#13;
&#13;
                                           - 2215 -&#13;
&amp;#12;'tLIFF:     The municipalities.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:   What do they total?&#13;
&#13;
ILIFF:      Seven am one-half million dollars for the three.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            -&#13;
            CUBA - OVer the last week or ten days, we tave been holding conversations&#13;
&#13;
            with the Cuban authorities.    The Cuban Ambassador called on the President&#13;
&#13;
            about ten days ago, and subsequently I spent two afternoons with him.&#13;
&#13;
            He brought along with him. three engineers from the Ministry of Public&#13;
&#13;
            Works and an Engineer from the Cuban Ministry of Agriculture; there was&#13;
&#13;
            also a large pile of documents relating to projects which he said he had&#13;
&#13;
            been asked by his Government to bring to the Bank for financing.     The total&#13;
&#13;
            cost of these projects is in the region of $250 million; they range over&#13;
&#13;
            a great variety of subjects.    We have had these projects examined quickly&#13;
&#13;
            by the engineering staff of the Loan Department, and it looks as though&#13;
&#13;
            out of the total, there might perhaps be projects totaling $20 million&#13;
&#13;
            which would be suitable for Bank financing.     However, the question of the&#13;
&#13;
            extent to which the Bank can invest in Cuba gives rise to a number of points&#13;
&#13;
            to which we shall havS"' to give careful consideration before we can forward&#13;
&#13;
            recommendations.    For example, there is the cpestion of the capacity of&#13;
&#13;
            Cuba to :t:'aise money herself in the American market without recourse to the&#13;
&#13;
            Bank, and secondly, there is the difficulty which the Cuban Government&#13;
&#13;
            experiences in raising local capital to marry with the foreign currency&#13;
&#13;
            investment.    The day before yesterday, the President had a communication&#13;
&#13;
            from the President of Cuba, asking for a mission to Cuba as soon as&#13;
&#13;
            possible, to study the whole question, and that request is being considered.&#13;
&#13;
            At the request of the Government of Nicaragua, we are sending a mission to&#13;
&#13;
            NICARAGUA     in the very near future.   Messrs. Consolo of the Loan Department&#13;
&#13;
            and Waterston of the Economic Department, will be members of the mission.&#13;
&#13;
            While Consolo am Waterston are on this trip, they will also take the&#13;
&#13;
            opportunity of calling in at Guatemala am Costa Rica, from which countries&#13;
&#13;
                                               _ ??1f.. _&#13;
&amp;#12;ILIFF:      we have had approaches, although no very definite proposals have come&#13;
 ont 'd)&#13;
            forward from either.&#13;
            The negotiations have been completed in connection with the proposed $12}&#13;
&#13;
            million loan for the Rio Lempa hydro-electric project in El Salvador.&#13;
&#13;
            We are awaiting clearance of the Loan and Guarantee Agreements from San&#13;
            Salvador, and as soon as that has been obtained, it is the intention of&#13;
&#13;
            the President to put the loan formally before the Board.&#13;
&#13;
            ECUADOR - We have been in consultation with the Export-Import Bank with&#13;
&#13;
            regard to the situation in Ecuador.   The Board will remember that the&#13;
&#13;
            President of Ecuador had asked the Bank to interest itself in the financing&#13;
&#13;
            of Ecuadorian development.   At his request, we sent down Mr. Harold B.&#13;
            Hoskins, who is an expert in the textile field, to make an examination of&#13;
&#13;
            the Ecuadorian textile industry.   Mr. Hoskins has submitted his report;&#13;
&#13;
            I have not yet read it, but I understand that the worn-out and obsolete&#13;
            machinery which was regarded by the President as one of the main disadvantages,&#13;
&#13;
            is not the only one, and the whole industry needs a complete overhaul if i t&#13;
            is to make the contribution the President had in mind.      The Export-Import&#13;
&#13;
            Bank Bent a mission to Ecuador to investigate the damage caused by the&#13;
&#13;
            earthquake.   We have not yet seen their report, but they have told us the&#13;
            preliminary conclusion is that the amount of material.damage done is&#13;
            considerably less then first estimated.       I think it is possible there will&#13;
&#13;
            be same Export-Import Bank financing of the reconstruction operations&#13;
&#13;
            necessary to repair damage to the railway, and until we in the International&#13;
            Bank see to what extent the Ecuadorians may find themselves saddled with&#13;
&#13;
            an additional burden of debt arising out of anything they may contract&#13;
&#13;
            with the Export-Import Bank, we will want to delay making any canmitments.&#13;
HOPPENOT:   I feel in connection with Ecuador that without advocating any kind of&#13;
&#13;
            grant and keeping to loan business, if we are going into a loan agreement&#13;
&#13;
            with them, we should take special account of that recent catastrophe that&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               - 2217 -&#13;
&amp;#12;HOPPENOT:   befell them, and I think we might    fin~   either in the rate of interest or&#13;
 'Cont'd)&#13;
            in the conditions of amortization something that wou1d take into account&#13;
&#13;
            what happened to them this year.&#13;
                                  to keep&#13;
CHAIRMAN:   We would be very glad/that in consideration.       I do not know whether we&#13;
&#13;
            should go along with a special rate of interest; it would create considerable&#13;
&#13;
            difficulties, but we shall bear in mind the catastrophe they had.       We have&#13;
&#13;
            had no specific request recently.&#13;
&#13;
ILIFF:      MEXICO - The reorganization of the capital structure of the Mexican Light&#13;
&#13;
            and Power Company, which we made a    pre-re~uisit~   to the long-term credit&#13;
&#13;
            to the Cocpany, has been held up by a delay on the part of the MeXiCan&#13;
&#13;
            Government in the promulgation of the definitive rai:.ep\xoa. for the&#13;
&#13;
            company.    We held conversations with the Mexican authorities last week,&#13;
&#13;
            and also with representatives of the Company, and the .Mexican Government&#13;
&#13;
            informed us that the new rates will be finally promulgated by the 25th of&#13;
&#13;
            November.    However, that date is too late for it to be possible to bring&#13;
&#13;
            the Company's organization plan into effect by the end of 1949, and the&#13;
&#13;
            Company has therefore asked the Bank to consider an extension of the&#13;
&#13;
            maturity of the short-term credit of $10 million.       The Board will remember&#13;
&#13;
            that, so far as the Company was concerned,. the $10 million credit is a&#13;
&#13;
            contract between them and the Mexican authorities, am that the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
            formal relationship is not With the Company but with two .Mexican Government&#13;
&#13;
            agencies, so that i f the Company's credit is to be eKtended, that becomes a&#13;
&#13;
            matter for negotiation between the Company and the Government.       There is&#13;
&#13;
            a further complication, in that certain of the first mortgage bonds fall&#13;
&#13;
            due on February 1st, 1950, and since the new re-organization cannot become&#13;
&#13;
            effective on the date we had contemplated, the bond holders will have to&#13;
&#13;
            be asked to grant an extension of the maturity date.       The Company is&#13;
&#13;
            considering for the moment the steps that ought to be taken.       There is&#13;
&#13;
            another slight complication as a result of devaluation.       The original plan,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             - 2218 -&#13;
&amp;#12;             as approved by the Bank, provided for the conversion of certain securities&#13;
                                                                           )&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             of the Company denominated in Canadian dollars and sterling into U.S.&#13;
&#13;
             dollar securities.   The change in both currencies has created complications&#13;
&#13;
             which they are now attempting to sort out.&#13;
                                                                                 \&#13;
                                            ,             ~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
HOOKER:      Do they have any plans as to when they will be able to proceed 'With the&#13;
&#13;
             re-organization plans assuming the ne~ rates are in effect on the 25th.&#13;
&#13;
ILIFF:       I think, Mr. Hooker, we must assume, first of all, that. the Company cannot&#13;
&#13;
             publish its reorganization plan until after the Mexican Government has&#13;
&#13;
             promulgated the rates.   The timetable then depends on how long it takes&#13;
&#13;
             to call a meeting.   Dave, could you give an estimate?&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:    I think it might be six months.&#13;
&#13;
SOMMERS:     The earliest possible day for closure of local   p."OO~arrl       the most&#13;
&#13;
             optimistic would be around April.&#13;
&#13;
~HAIRMAN:    It might be necessary to have an extension of our one-year loan.        I do not&#13;
&#13;
             think it would be possible to have the/plan of reorganization accepted&#13;
&#13;
             prior to maturity of our one-year loan.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:    Is not there a danger that this postponement of the reorganization will&#13;
&#13;
             affect the credit of the Company in the future and Will do some irreparable&#13;
&#13;
             harm?   We can have before us a company of a quite different standing than&#13;
&#13;
             that which we have contemplated.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:    I do not think so.   Everything being done will help the Company.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:    Such a thing as asking for postponement of maturity' of bonds is not exactly&#13;
&#13;
             a thing which improves a credit of a company.&#13;
&#13;
GARNER:      It is better than having them go into default.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:    I think the Company will come out with a great deal better standing than&#13;
&#13;
             before â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
.aARANSKI:   That is true.   Our ro ndition is that it must improve.   My point is that&#13;
&#13;
             improvement might be smaller than expected and the future standing of the&#13;
&#13;
             Company might not be so high as foreseen.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           - 2219 -&#13;
&amp;#12;CHAIRMAN:   I do not think it would be serious â&#128;¢&#13;
....LIFF:   In connection with our other loan to Mexico, the Treasurerts Department&#13;
            brought to our notice that there would be certain delays in carrying out&#13;
            the program on schedule due to the fact that there T(as a shortage of local&#13;
&#13;
            currency to marry with our dollar investment. We have taken the matter up&#13;
&#13;
            with the Mexican authorities and we have said that the Bank views this&#13;
&#13;
            situation with some concern.  The Mexican Government have taken the matter&#13;
                                                                     for&#13;
            up and we are informed that a plan is now in the course /preparation. The&#13;
&#13;
            plan so far has not been outlined to us in detail but, if it is carried&#13;
&#13;
            through, I think that our worries on the local currency aspect of the&#13;
&#13;
            matter are at an end.   I am going down myself to Mexico City next week to&#13;
            discuss this plan with the Mexican Minister of Finance.       At the same time&#13;
&#13;
            I am going to take the opportunity of impressing on the Mexican Minister&#13;
            of Economy the necessity for adhering to the time schedules for fixing&#13;
            definitive rates for the Mexican Light and Power Company.&#13;
TANSLEY:    Mr. Chairman, may I ask a question.       Ha.ve you any indication as to how&#13;
&#13;
            they propose to raise the local currency?&#13;
ILIFF:      The period of the contract is three years, of which one has already gone&#13;
&#13;
            by.   And so far as there has been a lag in the first yearts program, it&#13;
&#13;
            is Comision's intention to take up the lag in the next two years.       The&#13;
            Mexican Minister of Finance intends to guarantee an appropriation from&#13;
            the Mexican budget of 67 million pesos a year.       That will fall short of&#13;
&#13;
            the local currency needs of the project during the first two years by&#13;
&#13;
            80 million for the first and~60 million for uqe second.       It is proposed&#13;
&#13;
            to make it up by a public bond issue, the proceeds of which will be put&#13;
&#13;
            at the disposal of Comision and without any legal otiligation on the part&#13;
&#13;
            of Comision to repay.&#13;
TANSLEY:    What are the possibilities these days of raiSing money in the Mexican&#13;
&#13;
            market?&#13;
&#13;
                                           - 2220 -&#13;
&amp;#12;CHAIRMAN:    They are not good â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
.J.IFF:      I think that if the Mexican Government decides to issue them, they will&#13;
&#13;
             be taken up.&#13;
&#13;
TANSLEY:     By the Central Bank?&#13;
&#13;
CHAffiMAN:   They charge a high rate of interest,     6%    or   1%.&#13;
ILIFF:&#13;
             -&#13;
             PERU - We have been holding conversations with the Peruvian authorities.&#13;
&#13;
             The Peruvian Ambassador in Washington asked the President of the Bank if he&#13;
&#13;
             would be willing to send a team of Bank technicians to Peru to examine scme&#13;
&#13;
             projects which were under consideration by the Peruvian santa Corporation&#13;
&#13;
             which is a governmental corporation charged with the economic development&#13;
&#13;
             of the Santa Valley.    These projects are a mixed bag, some irrigation,&#13;
&#13;
             some electric power, and there is a steel project.&#13;
&#13;
             When General Wheeler was down in Rio a few months ago at a Congress of&#13;
&#13;
             Latin American engineers, he was much impressed by the quality of the&#13;
&#13;
             engineers of Peruvian nationality, whom he met and he came to the&#13;
&#13;
             conclusion that there was sufficient engineering talent available in Peru&#13;
&#13;
             to make preliminary examination of these projects without calling on the&#13;
&#13;
             Bank technicians at this stage.       We have, therefore, replied to the&#13;
&#13;
             Peruvian authorities saying that at this stage we do not think it necessary&#13;
&#13;
             that Peru calIon Bank technicians when they have their own engineering&#13;
&#13;
             talent available.     We are suggesting that Peruvian engineers pull these&#13;
&#13;
             projects together, so that we may examine them here in Washington and at&#13;
&#13;
             that point the Bank would make up its mind whether it was necessary to&#13;
&#13;
             send Bank technicians to work them over.&#13;
&#13;
             The Ambassador also asked us to indicate whether the Bank would be prepared&#13;
&#13;
             to consider financing of any of these projects if the technicians and&#13;
&#13;
             finance men considered they were suitable.           Vie have informed the&#13;
&#13;
             Ambassador that there were serious difficulties lying in the way in Peru&#13;
&#13;
             at the present time as there is no constitutional assembly in existence&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               -   ???1 _&#13;
&amp;#12;ILIFF:       that could ratify an agreement.    We have said that we would be willing to&#13;
'C:ont Id)&#13;
             consider finaucing some of these projects after elections had been called&#13;
&#13;
             and after the Bank   h~   grounds for believing a constitutional Assembly&#13;
&#13;
             could come together which would be competent to ratify any arrangements&#13;
&#13;
             we might enter into with Peru.&#13;
&#13;
             URUGUA! - Negotiations with the technical representative of U.T.E. have&#13;
&#13;
             now been completed and the amount of the loan which we shall probably&#13;
&#13;
             recommend to the Board will be the full amount of $31 million foreign&#13;
&#13;
             exchange costs of the original program which U.T.E. proposed to us. We&#13;
&#13;
             are awaiting some further details about the financial set-up of U.T.E.&#13;
             and also some subsidiary engineering reports which will be needed before&#13;
&#13;
             we are in a position to put the loan formally up for consideration.&#13;
&#13;
             Now to move to ASIA, AFlUCA and the MIDDLE EAST.&#13;
             I mentioned before that the Egyptian Government had put forward an irrigation&#13;
&#13;
             project at Qena in Middle Egypt.     The dollar component of the foreign&#13;
&#13;
             exchange costs was not very large, a matter of only $3-4 million.     The&#13;
&#13;
             Egyptian Minister of Finance has now informed us that Egypt has come to&#13;
&#13;
             the conclusion that she will not need a dollar loan as she expects that&#13;
&#13;
             all equipment needs can be met from soft currency areas.&#13;
&#13;
             ~     - Having consummated the Kana Grass loan, we have now moved on to&#13;
             discussion of a loan for the Bokaro-Konar Thermal project in the Damodar&#13;
&#13;
             Valley.    The amount involved there will be approximately $25 million.&#13;
             We have been holding conversations with Mr. Keith Roy, Deputy Minister of&#13;
&#13;
             Finance.    He left Washington a few days ago, returning to India to collect&#13;
&#13;
             further material, am as soon as this information has been brought to the&#13;
&#13;
             Bank, discussions and negotiations will be resumed probably about the&#13;
&#13;
             middle of November.&#13;
&#13;
             -&#13;
             IRAN - I reported to the Board the arrangements which had been entered into&#13;
&#13;
             between the Iranian C'lOvernment on the one hand and Overseas Consultants,&#13;
             Inc., on the other.    OVerseas Consultants have now produced their report&#13;
&amp;#12;ILIFF:      on the Iranian Seven-Year Plan and the Government of Iran have put copies&#13;
 :mt'd)&#13;
            of this report at the disposal of the Bank.      It is now being studied by&#13;
&#13;
            our engineering experts.   About a fortnight ago, the Iranian Ambassador&#13;
&#13;
            here brought to us a list of projects which had been reconnnended by O.C.I.&#13;
&#13;
            in their report.   The total amount of the foreign exchange cost was aoout&#13;
&#13;
            $35 million and they asked us to indicate which of these projects the Bank&#13;
            would regard as suitable for Bank financing and which the Bank would not&#13;
            regard as coming into that category.      We have indicated to the Iranians&#13;
&#13;
            those projects which we do not think the Bank could consider financing.&#13;
&#13;
            With regard to the rest we have said we would be prepared to consider them&#13;
&#13;
            when they have been shaped up technically and economically.       The Iranian&#13;
&#13;
            Government have asked us to send a mission to Iran early in the new year&#13;
            to take a general look at the financial and economic situation and, also,&#13;
&#13;
            at their development plans.&#13;
BARANSKI:   What is the amount of those projects you would consider as suitable?&#13;
ILIFF:      About half of the $35 million.&#13;
HOPPENOT:   I have read in different papers a   ve~   long report on what O.C.I. has made&#13;
&#13;
            in Iran.   What is the exact relationship, I do not say between the Bank&#13;
&#13;
            and O.C.I., but between the kind of work that O.C.I. has made and the kind&#13;
            of approach the Bank is disposed to do in the way of loans to Iran, Le.,&#13;
            do we feel that we can take that O.C.I. report as a basis for a general&#13;
&#13;
            development program of Iran on which we might adjust our own loan policy&#13;
&#13;
            to some extent, or do we feel we must go and see for ourselves what kind&#13;
&#13;
            of loan, if any, we could make to Iran?&#13;
IT..IFF:    In all our conversations with Iran, we have preserved complete freedom of&#13;
&#13;
            action for the Bank, and the mere fact that a project has been recommended&#13;
&#13;
            by Overseas Consultants as a suitable project for the Iranian Government&#13;
&#13;
            to develop is not to be taken by the Iranian Government as any indication&#13;
&#13;
            that the Bank is prepared to finance it.       However, i f our own examination&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                - 2223 -&#13;
&amp;#12;NASR:       O.C.I.     The Iranian Government is not committed to follow the O.C.I.&#13;
'iont Id)&#13;
            proposal but I have no doubt that it will try to take advantage of it&#13;
&#13;
            as much as it seems possible in taking into consideration all other&#13;
&#13;
            relative factors.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPENar:   The Iranian Government expects to make a plan of its own which, to some&#13;
&#13;
            extent, will have the Overseas. report as a starting point.   Do you feel&#13;
&#13;
            the Iranian Government will have a general plan by the end of this year?&#13;
&#13;
NASR:       To avoid long delays in the execution of the Plan, a law passed about four&#13;
&#13;
            months ago, has authorized to start the execution of same projects of its&#13;
            own   choice subject to the approval of the Council of Ministers.   At the&#13;
&#13;
            end of the year (based on the date of the approval of the law) the Plan&#13;
            organization is required to present to the Parliament a report on its&#13;
&#13;
            activities during the first year together with a plan for the six following&#13;
&#13;
            years.    This plan accordingly should be ready in the next six: or seven&#13;
&#13;
            months.&#13;
CHAIRMAN:   Thank you.&#13;
 ILIFF:     IRAQ - We have before us a request from the Government of Iraq for financial&#13;
&#13;
            assistance, first to meet the costs of two flood control and irrigation&#13;
&#13;
            projects which are being promoted by the Government, and secondly for&#13;
&#13;
            financial assistance in connection with the remainder of their railway&#13;
            development program.    The Government of Iraq told us they are prepared&#13;
            to undertake that the costs of these projects would be met out of the&#13;
&#13;
            Iraq oil royalties.    In present circumstances, there are quite considerable&#13;
            doubts as to what the amount of these royalties is likely to be over the&#13;
                                                       that&#13;
            next few years. On the worst assumptions,/!f the Haifa pipe-line is not&#13;
&#13;
            reopened and that no new arrangements for increased royalties are put&#13;
&#13;
            into effect, the Iraqi Government will not obtain from the royalties a&#13;
&#13;
            sufficient amount to finance undertakings.    On the other hand, on the&#13;
&#13;
            assumption that the pipeline is reopened, it would not be necessary for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              - 2225 -&#13;
&amp;#12;ILIFF:      Iraq to borrow at all except in one respect.      However, underlying the&#13;
 ont Id)&#13;
            whole situation there are two other points.      First, there is a substantial&#13;
            budgetary deficit this year which is likely to be repeated next year.&#13;
&#13;
            As   far as we can see, that budgetary deficit can be met only by diverting&#13;
&#13;
            some of the oil royalties into the budget.       The second consideration is&#13;
&#13;
            that at the moment, the Iraq State Railways have floating obligations&#13;
&#13;
            amounting to   2!   million pounds, part in sterling and part in Iraq dinars.&#13;
&#13;
            We have told the Iraq Government that it is not in accord with Bank policy&#13;
&#13;
            to fund floating debts and that we would wish to see the floating debt&#13;
            situation cleared up.&#13;
BARANSKI:   Who are the holders of these bonds?&#13;
&#13;
ILIFF:      They are not bonds, but obligations.&#13;
            We also told the Iraq Government we would not be disposed to enter into&#13;
&#13;
            the railway situation until they had taken steps to clear up this debt.&#13;
&#13;
            So far as the flood control project is concerned, and assuming for the&#13;
&#13;
            moment they have enough sterling at their disposal from the royalties to&#13;
            finance the costs of this project, there still remains the need for&#13;
&#13;
            financing the dollar component of the foreign exchange costs of these&#13;
&#13;
            projects.    That is about $~ million, so that in any event, Iraq V(ould&#13;
&#13;
            probably wish to borrow that amount from the Bank.       The whole situation&#13;
&#13;
            is under examination at the moment, and we hope to have it at the Staff&#13;
&#13;
            Loan Committee level next week, so that we may form a policy.&#13;
&#13;
            The only other point I wish to mention is that Prince Viwat, the      TI:!!1&#13;
            Minister of Finance who was over here at the Board of Governors Meeting,&#13;
&#13;
            called on the President and said that the Government of Thailand would&#13;
&#13;
            wish the Bank to consider financing the foreign currency requirements&#13;
&#13;
            for a five-year railway rehabilitation program.       The amount involved was&#13;
&#13;
            $33 million, and also $22 million for the foreign exchange costs of a&#13;
&#13;
            five-to seven-year program for irrigation, drainage, power and navigation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  - 2226 -&#13;
&amp;#12;ILIFF:       in what is called the Chao Phya River Plain.    We are, at the moment,&#13;
 ont1d)&#13;
             examining the data which the Thais submitted to us.    The Minister asked&#13;
&#13;
             us if we would send a mission to Thailand as soon as possible to study&#13;
&#13;
             the general situation and discuss with the Thai Government the general&#13;
&#13;
             lines of economic development programs to follow.     Incidentally, I heard&#13;
&#13;
             yesterday that Prince Viwat had resigned as Minister of Finance, to become&#13;
&#13;
             the Governor of the Central Bank, and had been succeeded by another very&#13;
&#13;
             competent Thai who is himself a close personal friend of Prince Viwat,&#13;
&#13;
             and we regard that as quite a healthy step.&#13;
&#13;
             That is all that I have to report.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:    In connection wi. th the resignations of Mr. Sundaresan and Mr. Nemazee, I&#13;
&#13;
             failed to mention at the beginning of the meeting that there is an item&#13;
&#13;
             in today I s paper that Mr. Donald Gordon, our Director-representing Canada,&#13;
&#13;
             has been elected President of the Canadian National Railways system.       I&#13;
&#13;
             understand he Will probably take office in January.     That is quite an&#13;
&#13;
             honor and a very big job to have been given.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPENaI':   I would like to say just a few words, taking as an example the EI Salvador&#13;
&#13;
             application, on underdeveloped countries.     If I talk about Salvador it is&#13;
&#13;
             not because I think Salvador is extremely different from others, but it&#13;
&#13;
             is because in the general situation of El Salvador, as we see from the&#13;
&#13;
             papers submitted to the Board, the technical aspect of the project seems&#13;
&#13;
             to be very promising.   Salvador has been a very prosperous country for a&#13;
&#13;
             long period; its public finances are in good order and Salvador seems&#13;
&#13;
             in a position to easily repay the kind of loans the Bank intends or&#13;
&#13;
             considers to make.   And the project itself looks very well conceived and&#13;
&#13;
             studied from an engirieering point of view.&#13;
&#13;
             What I would like to say of such a project is that it is of the type that&#13;
&#13;
             any banking institution would have been glad to consider in times when&#13;
&#13;
             international lending was more or less active in a number of countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               - 2227 -&#13;
&amp;#12;HOPPENOT:   As we do not meet very often and as decisions are made rather rapidly,&#13;
tCont'd)&#13;
            the question I would like to put to the Board and which I do not expect&#13;
&#13;
            to be answered today, is the International Bank to be satisfied only by&#13;
&#13;
            such standards as we find in the Salvador loan?   At the past meeting of&#13;
&#13;
            the Board of Governors the Governor for France said: " â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢ But now comes&#13;
&#13;
            another problem which is related to the choice between specific projects.&#13;
&#13;
            As we are not able to realize everything immediately, we are obliged to&#13;
&#13;
            face the question of urgency and of priority.     It is obvious that in the&#13;
&#13;
            first few years of its activity, the Bank had more or less to examine&#13;
&#13;
            loan applications from member countries as and lIhen they came, and to&#13;
&#13;
            judge them on their own merits Without being able to place them in&#13;
&#13;
            complete comparison with others which might perhaps have required prior&#13;
&#13;
            attention from the Bank.   We hope that in the future, keeping in mind its&#13;
&#13;
            limited resources, the Bank will be able to judge not only if such or such&#13;
&#13;
            country is able to carry the future burden of the Bank's loan and if a&#13;
&#13;
            certain project is worthy of attention, but also if, in a particular&#13;
&#13;
            country, an intended loan will be used for the most urgent and useful work.&#13;
&#13;
            For instance, it has been generally said that in many, if not most, under-&#13;
&#13;
            developed countries, agricultural projects should have a priority.     At&#13;
&#13;
            the same time, i f we go through the list of outstanding Bank loans, we&#13;
&#13;
            see that out of the general amount of $200 million granted to underdeveloped&#13;
&#13;
            countries, maybe only $10 million or so is intended for agricultural&#13;
&#13;
            purposes.   We strongly hope the general survey actually made in some of&#13;
&#13;
            the member countries will enable the Bank in the future to strengthen its&#13;
&#13;
            lending policy in that respect ...&#13;
&#13;
            Most of the time when we hear of loans, arrl just a few minutes ago when&#13;
&#13;
            we hear of loans to urrlerdeveloped countries, we hear about electrification.&#13;
&#13;
            We lent a few million cb liars to Chile for agricultural machinery and then&#13;
&#13;
            there was that extremely interesting project in India on Kans Grass; we&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 - 2228 -&#13;
&amp;#12;HOPPENOT:    lent for electrification in Brazil &amp;ld today first priority is being given&#13;
'':!ont'd)&#13;
             by the Brazilian Government to new electrification projects.     This makes&#13;
             me remember what was said in the Bank's report at the Governors' Meeting&#13;
&#13;
             that when asking for loans many Governments have a tendency to bring forward&#13;
&#13;
             spectacular projects, projects that look well in the picture.     Electrification&#13;
&#13;
             is of that type.     It is much more glamorous to build a dam than to improve&#13;
&#13;
             the general   w~   of raising corn or wheat or whatever is the chief or basic&#13;
&#13;
             product of certain countries.&#13;
&#13;
             So there is a second point and, I talk about Salvador just because the&#13;
&#13;
             Salvador project is a very good one and I do not expect to discuss it&#13;
&#13;
             itself.   It is not in any way a criticism against the Salvadorian project,&#13;
&#13;
             but rather a general thought on the Bank's policy with regard to underdeveloped&#13;
             countries.&#13;
&#13;
             As I said before, our re60urces are limited and we consider a loan of, say&#13;
&#13;
             $10 million, to    Salvado~.   If the Bank feels that it should lend $10 million&#13;
&#13;
             to such -a SInal-I w:r:lerdeveloped country, what might the amount be which other&#13;
             larger countries should expect to apply for?     We see in the papers which&#13;
&#13;
             have been circulated, that there are about two million people in Salvador&#13;
&#13;
             who are very poor and not very well paid.      If the figure for a small&#13;
&#13;
             country like Salvador is $10 miD.ion, what would be the amount for much&#13;
             larger and no more developed countries?&#13;
COPETE:      Do you consider that the amount of the loan is a very big burden for Salvador?&#13;
HOPPENOT:    I do not want to discuss the question of lending an amount of $10 million&#13;
&#13;
             to El Salvador as such; in my opinion if such a loan is part of a general&#13;
&#13;
             lending policy it may mean that other underdeveloped countries may expect&#13;
&#13;
             loans of a much higher amount considering their size and needs.      I would&#13;
&#13;
             like to know what is the Bank's thinking on that point.&#13;
                           in connection with El Salvador,&#13;
CHAIRMAN:    First of all/the loan is $12.5 million and not $10.&#13;
HOPPENOT:    $11.5 million.&#13;
&#13;
                                               - 2229 -&#13;
&amp;#12;SOMMERS:    $12.5 million.    It is expected that, when the bids are in, it will be cut&#13;
&#13;
            down.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:   As to your statement that the Bank's resources are limited, that is true,&#13;
&#13;
            but I think we can say that we are not concerned today as to our ability&#13;
&#13;
            to raise money.        I have made that statement on a number of occasions and&#13;
&#13;
            I feel very definitely that we can get money.           I think it is more difficult&#13;
&#13;
            to find loans of the type we are allowed to make wrler the Articles of the&#13;
&#13;
            Bank.   The problem we had a year or so ago to raise money is gone.          While,&#13;
&#13;
            of course, we have always to say our resources are limited, so far as the&#13;
&#13;
            priority of a technical project is concerned, that is determined both&#13;
&#13;
            by the borrowing country and the staff of the Bank.           We determine on our&#13;
&#13;
            own whether or not we feel that the priority should be either an electrical&#13;
&#13;
            or an agricultural project.        As you know, we have to get the guarantee of&#13;
&#13;
            the Government and we have to get their acceptance of the proper priority&#13;
&#13;
            of the project.&#13;
&#13;
            In Brazil the loan was applied for by the Brazilian Government who was&#13;
&#13;
            willing to guarantee the loan and at the present time the Brazilian Govern-&#13;
&#13;
            ment know which are the most pressing projects.&#13;
&#13;
            So far as El Salvador is concerned, while it is a small country, we think&#13;
&#13;
            it is a country in good shape financially, with a good record and well&#13;
&#13;
            able to service a debt of $12 million.            In El Salvador, as in any country&#13;
&#13;
            we go into,   Ura~;x   U   the first thing the staff tries to ascertain is the&#13;
&#13;
            ability of the country to service a debt.           The fact that we lend El Salvador&#13;
&#13;
            $10-12 million does not mean that we will not make loans to other under-&#13;
&#13;
            developed countries.           I think, as   Mr. Iliff has pointed out, we are&#13;
            talking to a good many countries and are applying the same measures.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:   I may raise three questions in connection with          Mr. Hoppenot's remarks.&#13;
            I think it is a very dangerous thing to consider the amount of loans in&#13;
&#13;
            proportion with the size of the country.           You heard today that Britain&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   - 2230 -&#13;
&amp;#12;BARANSKI:   will approach us with quite a small loan, $12-15 million, and they do not&#13;
'Cont'd)&#13;
            consider the size of the loan out of proportion with Britain's colonial&#13;
            empire.&#13;
            I remember that in the very great infancy of the Bank somebody in the Bank&#13;
&#13;
            had the idea that the proportion of loans granted to various countries&#13;
&#13;
            should be in direction relation to their subscriptions.    That was absolute&#13;
&#13;
            nonsense.   AQy proportions that could be established would be certainly&#13;
            more suitable than a proportion based on the subscribed capital.    It is&#13;
&#13;
            believed sometimes that a loan is good i f it is big am on very long term,&#13;
&#13;
            but very often quite the opposite is true.    Such simplified ideas can be&#13;
&#13;
            found also in seeking relationship between foreign loans and the magnitude&#13;
&#13;
            of one country.&#13;
            The second subject is the priority of electrification.    It is true, we have&#13;
&#13;
            made many loans for electrical projects but I think we have done that with&#13;
&#13;
            right.    Electrification in modern times has indeed a high priority.   Without&#13;
            electricity you cannot develop anything.     If you industrialize a country&#13;
&#13;
            it obviously causes the increase in consumption of electricity.    The con-&#13;
&#13;
            sumption of electric power goes up in a developing country even at a&#13;
&#13;
            higher rate than the average rate of development.    We may have a case that&#13;
&#13;
            the overall production increases by say, 20-25%, and in connection with&#13;
            that the electric power output must go up 50% or more.     Therefore, much&#13;
            more must be spent on electricity than on other development schemes.&#13;
&#13;
            The last point is the role of the private capital. My question is:      how&#13;
&#13;
            to explain that private capital does not seem to be willing to enter into&#13;
&#13;
            a business which, before the war was considered very suitable for foreign&#13;
&#13;
            investments.    I remember that the bulk of the development of the electrical&#13;
&#13;
            power plants in Polam between the wars, has been made with British, Belgian&#13;
            and Swedish capital.    But in the case of Salvador, it seems that nobody&#13;
&#13;
            wants to invest capital in electric plants in Salvador, despite the fact&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              - 2231 -&#13;
&amp;#12;liARANSKI:     that the demand is not saturated and consumption of the current is artificially&#13;
  ':::ont'd)&#13;
               restricted and regulated.    Something is wrong here am needs to be explained&#13;
               am elucidated.    Maybe conditions in the 'World have changed so profoundly&#13;
&#13;
               that even in the discussed case it is impossible to attract foreign capital&#13;
&#13;
               to a country having a balanced budget, a favorable balance of payments, no&#13;
&#13;
               exchange restrictions, possibilities of unrestricted transfer of profits -&#13;
&#13;
               and electricity in short supply ,       How can we expect an expans ion of&#13;
&#13;
               private foreign capital to underdeveloped countries i f it lacks willingness&#13;
               even in such   a~particularly   advantageous situation1     It was said in the&#13;
&#13;
               report on Salvador that what is lacking there - is the proper "economic&#13;
&#13;
               climate".   This can be understood    ~only   in the sense that Salvador lacks&#13;
&#13;
               the atmosphere of a properly developed country which attracts new enterprises.&#13;
&#13;
               But in orderto have this atmosphere or climate, the country must already&#13;
               be developed and not just expected to be developed.         In my opinion, the&#13;
               Bank is entitled to substitute the lacking private capital in such cases,&#13;
               but if so, 'What about the whole program of financing underdeveloped countries&#13;
&#13;
               by the afflux of private foreign capital, and .the views in this respect&#13;
               presented in our annual rep ort 1 ,&#13;
&#13;
BRESCIANI:     I do not y,now what the situation is in Salvador; I do not know why private&#13;
               capital does not invest in electric power development projects in Salvador,&#13;
               but I can answer this question as concerns Italy.         One   of the causes&#13;
&#13;
               preventing investment of private capital is simply the fact that even now,&#13;
               after the Italian Government has granted to our electric companies an&#13;
&#13;
               increase of the level of tariffs, our tariffs are very far from the level&#13;
&#13;
               reached by costs and prices, so that the expected return on invested capital&#13;
&#13;
               is so low that it cannot attract private capital.          However, there might be&#13;
&#13;
               some important reasons which prevent the Italian Government from bringing&#13;
&#13;
               tariffs to the general level of prices. We must recognize that a practical&#13;
               economic problem has not only an economic aspect, but many other social and&#13;
&amp;#12;BRESCIANI:   political aspects, which might be more important than the economic aspect,&#13;
'Cont'd)&#13;
             and that might be therefore some social important reason which induces&#13;
             Government to be cautious when they raise tariffs.     In this case, an&#13;
&#13;
             intervention of the International Bank, which according to its Articles of&#13;
&#13;
             Agreement grants loans when private capital cannot be attracted is justified.&#13;
&#13;
HOOKER:      I just want to emphasize that in the report the need for power is streesed.&#13;
&#13;
             I also want to secood Mr. Baranski' 5 statement that because Salvador has&#13;
&#13;
             only a small subscription in the Bank it is no reason why they cannot get&#13;
&#13;
             a loan they urgently need.&#13;
&#13;
BARREDA-     Mr. Hoppenot1s statement con"{eys the idea that he considers convenient that&#13;
  MOLLER:                                                                 it&#13;
             the Bank should establish now a policy on what kind of loans/should ake&#13;
&#13;
             to the underdeveloped countries, in other words what kind of projects it&#13;
&#13;
             should accept for consideration.    To set a policy is always very important&#13;
             and more when it is regarding the very purposes of the Bank.     He has tm.de&#13;
             three remarks that we may consider three objections to what the Bank has&#13;
&#13;
             been doing until now.   First, he raises the question whether the Bank&#13;
             should make loans to underdeveloped countries at the present moment; .&#13;
&#13;
             second he considers these countries are bringing to the Bank projects which&#13;
&#13;
             only "look well", to use his awn words, but have no economic justification&#13;
             such as the hydroelectric projects; ani finally, considers" that the loans&#13;
&#13;
             made so far to the underdeveloped countries, or under consideration, are&#13;
&#13;
             too big, mainly i f we consider the available resources of the Bank and the&#13;
&#13;
             need of other countries.     I think that as a member of this Board and a&#13;
&#13;
             representative of nine underdeveloped countries, I must express my points&#13;
&#13;
             of view on these matters.&#13;
&#13;
             It seems to me that i f it is convenient for any institution to have a clear&#13;
&#13;
             policy on what should it do or not do, such policy must not be so narrow&#13;
&#13;
             as to leave outside questions or problems of importance to the institution&#13;
&#13;
             without giving them a chance to be considered.     I do not think the Bank&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               - 2233 -&#13;
&amp;#12;BARREDA-&#13;
 MOLLER:    should set a policy on vbat kind of projects it must consider for financing&#13;
"~ont Id)&#13;
            going so far in detail as to say: we shall consider irrigation projects&#13;
            but not ports and harbor facilities; we shall consider railroads but not&#13;
&#13;
            highways and so forth.   On the other hand it would be perfectly correct&#13;
&#13;
            to establish a policy on much broader terms as to consider self liquidating&#13;
&#13;
            projects only and not others that are not self liquidating.       In other words,&#13;
&#13;
            each particular and specific project must be considered by its own merits.&#13;
&#13;
            For instance, Mr. Hoppenot has referred to the hydroelectric projects as&#13;
&#13;
            non-suitable for the underdeveloped countries, and I think it is a      ve~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            serious mistake.    I agree with Messrs. BÂ±esd!aDiand Baranski that electric&#13;
&#13;
            energy is essential for economic development am a "must" in any program&#13;
&#13;
            of that kind.   Furthermore, I can say that electricity is useii    rl01F3~Y'::&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            in the largest factories and by the heavy industry of the well developed&#13;
&#13;
            countries but is essential everywhere for multiple purposes from home&#13;
&#13;
            lighting to treatment of raw materials as the different minerals.&#13;
&#13;
            For instance, let us take the case of Peru.       In this country there is a&#13;
&#13;
            Corporation building a hydroelectric plant in Chimbote and which has&#13;
&#13;
            already approached the Bank for technical advice.       The electric energy&#13;
&#13;
            produced by this plant will be used for treatment of zinc of which Peru&#13;
&#13;
            is one of the largest producers.       Today the zinc produced in Peru is&#13;
            shipped to this country and to Europe in form of concentrates with only&#13;
&#13;
            50%   of the metal and therefore pays in freight twice as much as it would&#13;
&#13;
            have to pay if the metal were shipped after refining.       Today freight&#13;
&#13;
            absorbs almost 60% of the value of the mineral and, therefore, Peru is&#13;
&#13;
            wasting millions of dollars each year because she has not had, until&#13;
&#13;
            now an electric plant for treatment of the mineral.       Part of the energy&#13;
&#13;
            to be produced by that project wil1 be used to refine aluminum.       The bauxite&#13;
&#13;
            wil1 be brought from the GuillalB.s and after treatment, the alumirrum will be&#13;
&#13;
            exported.    Therefore, Peru wil1 be lIexporting" electric energy and will&#13;
&#13;
                                               -   ')?~I, -&#13;
&amp;#12;BARREDA-&#13;
  MOUER:     profit from the service rendered and obtain foreign exchange.         There are&#13;
.';ont'd)&#13;
             ma~   other cases like this to prove that electric energy is essential for&#13;
             any program of economic development and not only for highly advanced forma&#13;
             of industrial development.&#13;
             Regarding the size of loans to be made to the different countries, I do not&#13;
&#13;
             think that the loan under consideration for Salvador is very large and I&#13;
             do not think it is possible to establish a policy on size of loans to be&#13;
             made.   I do not think we could find a reasonable rule to follow in this&#13;
             respect.   Should we consider the size of the country according to the&#13;
             square miles it has?    In this case, i f we consider appropriate the loan&#13;
             to India we could not lend much to France or Belgium.      Or   should we&#13;
             consider the population?     In this case, a loan of 10 million dollars to&#13;
             Salvador, as it is being considered, would represent only       5 dollars   per&#13;
             inhabitant for this country which is the most populated of all, with&#13;
             exception perhaps of Haiti, when we have lent to France 250      millio~which&#13;
&#13;
             represents more than   5 dollars per inhabitant and this was done only for&#13;
             general purposes and not for capitalization.&#13;
             I should not like to raise a discussion here about which countries have&#13;
             received preferential treatment ani what I have said has been only to&#13;
                                                                              it&#13;
             illustrate my points, but this will prove how inconvenient/could be to&#13;
             set a rule on the kind of projects to be considered or on the size of loans&#13;
             to be made to the different countries.&#13;
             The policy of the Bank should be to consider each project only on its own&#13;
&#13;
             merits.&#13;
HOPPENOl':   First, i f I took aa an example the Salvador project, it is because it is a&#13;
&#13;
             very good project, and as I said, of the type that    a~   banking institution&#13;
             would have been glad to consider in times past when international lending&#13;
             was a normal activity; but m;r question was, is the International Bank to be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 - 2235 -&#13;
&amp;#12;HOPPENOT:   sa tisfied with that approach only?     Mr. Barreda' s answer is "Yes II , and my&#13;
  ant'd)&#13;
            answer is slighly different.   If we feel,   aff   Mr. Barreda does what is our&#13;
&#13;
            reason for sending a mission to Brazil, Turkey, Cuba, and I hope other&#13;
            countries, if we do not feel that such missions will come back with a general&#13;
            survey which will enable the Bank to have a policy, a lending policy, and i f&#13;
&#13;
             it is not able to finance by itself, KHcmgKt,r it may show the way to others.&#13;
             Secondly,               .&#13;
            Ii! tomorrow the Bank is asked for a $500 million loan for a very good project,&#13;
             I am not sure it would be able to raise it in five minutes, or even six&#13;
            months, so that establishing priorities is the purpose of our mission, and&#13;
             I think the purpose of our thought.    What I said on agriculture and&#13;
            spectacular projects, we all said it.      It was said by the former President;&#13;
            it was said in the report we discussed, that one of the troubles with&#13;
            missions to under-developed countries was to have sound and good and helpful&#13;
             loans made, and loans that did not lead to projects that were more of the&#13;
            political kind, so the basic question is, and I see some of my colleagues&#13;
            and myself are of very different views, is the Bank going on to examine&#13;
             applications on their merits only, or considering both its      own   lending&#13;
&#13;
            policy and the leadership it has to take in private lending and advice.&#13;
CHAIRMAN:    I would like to make a statement.     You mean the management of the Bank plans,&#13;
             or tries, to make loans throughout the world only fordlear specific projects&#13;
&#13;
             and that is the only conSideration.     I do not think that is the policy of&#13;
             the management of the Bank.   I think we should take into consideration all&#13;
             factors relating to a country and not merely whether a project will produce&#13;
                                      not&#13;
             a bankable loan. It has/been the policy of the Bank in the past, and it is&#13;
             certainly not the intention, as far as I am concerned, that we can only look&#13;
&#13;
             around for favorable propositions throughout the world.       I am sure that is&#13;
&#13;
            what you mean.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  - 2236 -&#13;
&amp;#12;r.HAIRMAN:   loans we have made.   We plan to do that periodically, so that you can keep&#13;
 ;ont'd)&#13;
             posted as to what is going on.&#13;
HOOKER:      I think the Board will remember that sometime ago we circulated an   ~r:rled&#13;
&#13;
             brief which was filed with the Federal Communications Commission in regard&#13;
             to the complaint which had been raised by the Fund am Bank with regard to&#13;
             rates.   The companies wanted to raise the rates they charge.&#13;
&#13;
             In this connection, my Government wishes to request the Executive Directors&#13;
&#13;
             to make an interpretation of' Article VII, Section 7, insofar as it may relate&#13;
             to the rates which may be charged by cable companies for the official&#13;
             communications of the Bank.   The Section involved is in general terms.    The&#13;
             precise scope of the obligations of the member governments .can best be&#13;
&#13;
             determined by an interpretation by the Executive Directors in accordance&#13;
             with the provisions of the Articles of Agreement.   The questions of&#13;
             interpretation l'lhich have been raised involve not only the obligations of&#13;
&#13;
             the United States, but also of all other members, and it is desirable that&#13;
             an interpretation be rendered under which the obligations.of all the members&#13;
             will be uniform.&#13;
             In this connection, when the interpretation is made by the Board, i t would&#13;
             be forwarded to the Chairman of the National Advisory Council; who would&#13;
             in turn transmit it to the Federal Communications Commission. c The U.S.&#13;
             Director in the Fund is asking the Fund to make a similar interpretation&#13;
             of this section as the two sections in the two institutions are identical&#13;
             and the two cases before the Federal Communications Commission are identical.&#13;
             In this regard you must recognize that the Federal CommUhications Commission&#13;
&#13;
             is a quasi-judicial agency of the Government and we cannot give any absolute&#13;
&#13;
             assurance that whatever interpretation the Boards of the Fund and Bank make,&#13;
&#13;
             it will necessarily settle the case before the Federal Communications Com-&#13;
             mission, but it certainly will be of great assistance.   I do not know what&#13;
&#13;
             procedure you wish to follow.&#13;
&#13;
                                              - 2238 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                              ,&#13;
                                                                  )&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:   I think in view of the fact that we are raising this point both here and&#13;
&#13;
            in the Fund the Committee on Interpretation of the Bank should work very&#13;
&#13;
            closely with the similar committee of the Fund.       Possibly a joint committee&#13;
&#13;
            or sub-coounittee could be formed to try to settle this matter.       I think it&#13;
&#13;
            might be well, as long as the United states is not represented on this Inter-&#13;
&#13;
            pretations Committee to add the United states to the Committee i f there are&#13;
&#13;
            no objections.   Mr. Hooker will be rewarded for bringing up this point by&#13;
&#13;
            being put on this Committee.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:   I think this procedure of Directors making interpretations not only would&#13;
&#13;
            be applicable for the United states but for all members.        But one question&#13;
&#13;
            of procedure is certainly involved.  There must be a distinction between&#13;
                                                       an&#13;
            Directors acting in an impartial way as in/international body, and the Bank&#13;
&#13;
            itself being a party in a controversy with the United states Government or&#13;
&#13;
            same agencies of it.   Obviously the duties of the administration of the Bank&#13;
&#13;
            consist in claiming for the Bank as many   advantag~s     as is possible.   The&#13;
&#13;
            Bank cannot be at the same time a party and a judge, therefore, i f the&#13;
&#13;
            Committee on Interpretation convenes and recommends the       inte~)retation   to&#13;
&#13;
            the Directors, everything must be avoided in the work of the Committee which&#13;
&#13;
            can give the impression that the Directors themselves are influenced by&#13;
&#13;
            the   standpoint of the Bank staff.&#13;
&#13;
            MY warning   is only that the Committee on Interpretation Should not have&#13;
&#13;
            actual briefing for its work from the Legal Counsel's office, because he&#13;
&#13;
            is acting for the Bank as a party.&#13;
HOOKER:     I think he is needed for assistance in technical points.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:   For evidence of course, but not for writing the proposal.&#13;
SOMMERS :   I think i t is true that the Ex.ecuti ve Directors have to consider both sides&#13;
&#13;
            of the question.    They must not only consider the meaning of the provision&#13;
&#13;
            of the Articles of Agreement in the light of the reasonable requirements&#13;
&#13;
            of the Bank's operations, but they must consider the reasonable needs of&#13;
&amp;#12;    SOMMERS:    the member countries.    I disagree with Dr. Baranski in looking at it only&#13;
     iont Id)&#13;
                from one side, the side of a member country.                     The interests of the Bank as&#13;
&#13;
                an institution must be considered also.&#13;
&#13;
1   BARANSKI:   Yes, I missed that.&#13;
&#13;
    CHAIRMAN:   Any other comments?     (No response)&#13;
&#13;
                One of the Directors has made a suggestion that we might wire to Donald&#13;
&#13;
                Gordon the congratulations of the Board on his new position.                     Could I hear&#13;
&#13;
                a motion am second. to this?&#13;
&#13;
                (Moved and seconded)&#13;
&#13;
    BARANSKI:   We once decided to give a g1.ft for Mr. McLain.                    What about that?&#13;
&#13;
    CHAIRMAN:   We did.&#13;
&#13;
    BARANSKI:   But I have not subscribed'&#13;
&#13;
    CHAIRMAN:   At the next meeting of the Board, I would like to make a change in the&#13;
&#13;
                seating arrangements.    We have found. in some information conferences that&#13;
&#13;
                acoustics are better i f the speaker sits at the head of the table.                    I find.&#13;
&#13;
                it rather difficult, bobbing I'I\V head back and forth, and I would like to have&#13;
&#13;
                my seat at the end of the table wi!-h the Secretary and. Mr. Garner and the&#13;
&#13;
                General Counsel on the other sides.            The Directors would have various places&#13;
&#13;
                aroum the table and the staff at tha far end of the room.                      We have got&#13;
&#13;
                seating arrangements worked out on which there is no protocol or priority&#13;
&#13;
                involved.   We tried to fix seating of the various Directors either by&#13;
&#13;
                their voice or their hearing capacitye                      If there is anyone who would like&#13;
&#13;
                to look at the plan after the meeting, we would be glad to show it.                         If it&#13;
&#13;
                does not work and if we find that I'I\V voice does not carry, we may try a&#13;
&#13;
                loudspeaker.   We are giving some thought to that.&#13;
&#13;
    GIORDANI:   I would suggest the same disposition as in the Board Room of the Fund.&#13;
&#13;
                They have an oval table which helps very much.                      (Shows how oval table&#13;
&#13;
                might be placed in Bank Board Room)&#13;
&#13;
    CHAIRMAN:   We paid something like one thousand dollars for this table.                      We will study&#13;
&#13;
                the oval question if this does not work, and the loudspeaker.&#13;
                                                        "" ...... \ .....&#13;
&amp;#12;,.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     TiNSLEY:       I would be interested in your estimate of our various physical infirmities.&#13;
     vHAIRMAN:      That was done by the Secretaryl&#13;
                    If there is no other business, the next meeting will be held next Tuesday,&#13;
&#13;
                    October 25, unless in the meantime we find it necessary to call a meeting&#13;
&#13;
                    for El Salvador.&#13;
                    I would like the members of the Pension Committee to remain after this&#13;
&#13;
                    meeting.     They are Messrs. Tansley, Copete, Eriksen.&#13;
&#13;
                    Otherwise the meeting stands adjourned.&#13;
     SUNDARESAlI:   I would like to say Goodbye.       It has been one of the most wonderful periods&#13;
&#13;
                    of   my   life.   I will be carrying the most cherished memories of the four&#13;
                    years I spent here.       (Applause)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 ADJOURNED AT 12:40 p.m.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    - 2241 -&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="15330223">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1949/10/15330223/transcript-one-hundred-ninety-fifth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-held-thursday-october-13-1949
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1949/10/15330223/transcript-one-hundred-ninety-fifth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-held-thursday-october-13-1949</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1949/10/15330223/transcript-one-hundred-ninety-fifth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-held-thursday-october-13-1949</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2011-09-29T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2016-01-14T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b0828bb54a</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0828bb54a</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/10/21/000386194_20111021065643/Rendered/INDEX/650480TRANSCRI0560B0October01301949.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/10/21/000386194_20111021065643/Rendered/PDF/650480TRANSCRI0560B0October01301949.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2011-10-21T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1949-10-13T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of one hundred and ninety fifth
            regular meeting of the Executive Directors held on Thursday,
            October 13, 1949
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This transcript, from the session of the
            Executive Directors held on Thursday, October 13, 1949
            covers only the discussion one hundred and ninety fifth
            regular meeting.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of one hundred and ninety fifth
            regular meeting of the Executive Directors held on Thursday,
            October 13, 1949
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of one hundred and
            ninety fifth regular meeting of the Executive Directors held
            on Thursday, October 13, 1949</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1949/10/15330223/transcript-one-hundred-ninety-fifth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-held-thursday-october-13-1949</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Debt Markets,Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Bankruptcy and Resolution of Financial Distress,Access to Finance</subtopic>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <teratopic>Public Sector Development,Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000386194_20111021065643</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Board transcript</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Public Sector Development,Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            amortization, amortization schedule, amount
            of loans, balance of payments, Bank bonds, Bank financing,
            Bank loans, Bank policy, banking institution, banks, bids,
            bond, bond holders, bond issue, borrower, borrowing,
            budgetary deficit, business relations, capital structure,
            capitalization, Central Bank, common stocks, complaint,
            credit scheme, credits, debt, debts, delivery of bonds,
            dependent, devaluation, developing country, Development
            Corporation, disbursements, disposition, economic climate,
            economic development, economic problem, economic situation,
            equipment, exporters, Federal Government, financial
            assistance, financial Situation, floating debt, floating
            debts, foreign capital, foreign currency, foreign debt,
            foreign exchange, foreign investments, foreign loans, form
            of credits, future contracts, General Counsel, Government
            bonds, holding, Id, immediate payment, interested parties,
            International Bank, international lending, international
            trade, investment policy, judge, judicial agency, lawyers,
            leadership, legal rights, legislation, lending policy, Loan,
            Loan Account, Loan Agreement, Loan Agreements, loan
            amounting, loan applications, loan contract, Loan Policy,
            local currency, margin requirement, maturity, maturity date,
            Minister, Ministers, mortgage, mortgage bonds,
            municipalities, negative pledge clause, negative pledge
            clauses, negotiation, negotiations, original amount,
            outstanding Bank loans, outstanding credits, payments
            agreements, payments arrangements, Pension, preferential,
            preferential treatment, prejudice, private capital, private
            lending, productive investment, public finances,
            rehabilitation program, reorganization, reorganization plan,
            repayment, return, securities, small loan, small loans,
            State Governments, Stock Exchange, Stock Exchange member,
            subsidiary, Technical Assistance, term credit, transaction,
            water supply, withdrawal
        </keywd>
        <owner>Policy and Operations (SECPO)</owner>
        <repnb>65048</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks and Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Flood Control</ml:concept><ml:concept>Flood Control and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Flood Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Flood Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Flood Protection and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Flood Rehabilitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Floods and Droughts</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Electric Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks &amp; Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textiles</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Flood Protection</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Balance of Payments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drainage</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>