<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                                                   65045 I&#13;
&#13;
           Items Discussed at the l26th Regular jÂ·leeting&#13;
           and Informal Heeting of the Executive Direc-&#13;
           iÂ£!:.Â§l. qn lfu.rch 17. 19.,4:k.,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Page 759        Introduction of Dr. Roland Wilson, Alternate&#13;
                Executi ve Director to Nr. S. G. !vlcFarlane.&#13;
&#13;
Page 759        Approval of I1dnutes of 125th Regular Heeting&#13;
                of8xecuti ve Directors.&#13;
&#13;
Page 759        Chilean Loan k,:oHcation - Consideration&#13;
                postponed. (Secretary's Memorandum 365)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Page 761        Brazilian   1o~l   Application.&#13;
&#13;
     76J        Report by Professor Varvaressos on the pros-&#13;
                pects of European R.ecovery under the t'iarshall&#13;
                Plan - Discussion postponed. (Secretaryts&#13;
                Hemorandurn. 364)&#13;
&amp;#12;       GO NFIDEIITIAL&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         TRAHSGRIPr OF 126th REGULAR 'MEETING&#13;
                                         OF THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTORS HELD IN&#13;
                                         BOARD ROOM ON WEDl'JESDAY MARCH 17,&#13;
                                                1948, at 11:00 a.m.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
GHAIR1JiAN :            Viill the meeting come to order, please.     Dr. Wilson, Mr. McFarlane's&#13;
&#13;
                        Alternate, from Australia, is with us this morning.      Will you stand up&#13;
&#13;
                        and take a bow, Dr. Wilson?    What kind of Doctor is that?    Is tllat a&#13;
&#13;
                        Doctor of Economics, or a real doctor, or What?&#13;
&#13;
SUNDARES.AN :           Not of human diseases.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:               You have the minutes of the 125th Regular Meeting.      Are there any comments?&#13;
&#13;
                        If not, I will declare them approved.      Item No. 2 on the agenda is a report&#13;
&#13;
                        on the loan application of Chile.       I want to tell you a little about that,&#13;
&#13;
                        why I put it on the agenda, and in the end why I am taking it off for this&#13;
&#13;
                        morning.   As you know, I contemplate taking a trip to Latin America, South&#13;
&#13;
                        America particularly, commencing the first of the month, to be gone about&#13;
&#13;
                        a month.   I am going first to the Republic of Colombia, shall be there&#13;
                        just a little after the commencement of the Bogota Conference and shall&#13;
&#13;
                        then spend a few days in Bogota am elsewhere in Colombia.        I then go on&#13;
&#13;
                        to Ecuador, Peru, Chile, Argentina, Brazil, Uruguay and Venezuela, and&#13;
                        home.   I am not going down to attend the Bogota Conference in any sense as&#13;
&#13;
                        a participant.    My invitation in fact is from the Republic of Colombia and&#13;
&#13;
                        not from any official of the Conference.       I do hope, however, to take&#13;
                        advantage of the opportunity "which will be afforded to meet in one spot&#13;
&#13;
                        before I proceed on my way a number of the Finance Ministers and others&#13;
&#13;
                        who are interested in the economic development of Latin America.       Being&#13;
&#13;
                        away for that length of time, I would have liked to have been able to clear&#13;
&#13;
                        up some of our proposed Latin American financing.       It would be a little&#13;
&#13;
                        embarrassing to turn up in Santiago the day the Directors approve a loan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      - 759 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                             (&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
to Chile, or the day I arrive in Bogota.     That is an embarrassment, but&#13;
&#13;
not fundamental.     I made inquiries to find out where we stood on two of&#13;
&#13;
these loans, particularly to determine Whether we could not take action&#13;
&#13;
in principle on these loans some time not in too close juxtaposition on&#13;
&#13;
my trip.   It was indicated to me that we were probably close enough to&#13;
&#13;
justify that action and it would be a comfort to me to go off' with one or&#13;
&#13;
possibly two of those loans on the track, subject to further completion in&#13;
&#13;
due course as papers could be drawn up and details worked out.       I am not&#13;
&#13;
entirely sure, however, that we are at a point, although I think we are&#13;
&#13;
fairly close, where that type of action can be taken.      Rather than be&#13;
&#13;
uncertain about it I suggest that we postpone consideration of the report&#13;
&#13;
on Chile at ttlis time and be prepared to be able to discuss it next week,&#13;
&#13;
unless intervening circumstances make it clear that that would not be&#13;
&#13;
adVisable, or perhaps hold ourselves available for a special meeting some&#13;
&#13;
time before next week.     Next week's meeting, as you know, has been ante-&#13;
&#13;
dated from l'fednesday to Tuesday, due to the fact that a number of officials&#13;
&#13;
are corning to visit the Bank from the New England area.      It would be a&#13;
&#13;
matter of greater convenience if we could have the meeting on Tuesday&#13;
&#13;
rather than Wednesday, because I am anxious that these gentlemen should&#13;
&#13;
meet as many of the Executive Directors as possible.      It would probably&#13;
be easier to   ~~e   appointments throughout the day if we had the Directors'&#13;
&#13;
Meeting the day before.     If "..'e can arrive at a point where we feel that&#13;
&#13;
this action in respect of Chile would be desirable, we would call a special&#13;
&#13;
meeting, though I do not know that we can have one, on account of suggest-&#13;
&#13;
ions already made to me by some of the directors as to their commitments&#13;
&#13;
towards the end of the ".eek.    At any rate, we will postpone it today.        I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 760 -&#13;
&amp;#12;C}   .MAN:   want to say that the report that you have before you is really no more&#13;
&#13;
             at this time than a draft report.         We may make some corrections in it.&#13;
&#13;
             The substance probably will remain the same, but there may be additions&#13;
&#13;
             and corrections we will want to make.         If so, we will substitute pages&#13;
&#13;
             before the next meeting, when we will consider the report.          There is also&#13;
&#13;
             in that report a number of matters relating to the Chilean financial&#13;
&#13;
             Situation, which of course are confidential.         I hope they will be treated&#13;
&#13;
             as such.   Is there anything else?        Did I cover that situation fully?&#13;
&#13;
IlLANES:     Yes, Mr. Chairman; the only point I would like to make is that there be&#13;
&#13;
             added after the first paragraph, of the report, a memorandum we sent to&#13;
&#13;
             you on June 6, 1947 concerning the points that are mentioned in the first&#13;
             paragraph under "History of the Negotiations ll â&#128;¢      CoW of that memorandum&#13;
&#13;
             I will give to the Secretary in order that it can be added to the Report.&#13;
&#13;
CHA.lRMAN:   I meant to make reference to that.&#13;
&#13;
             The other loan vmich was pretty close to consideration by the Board was&#13;
&#13;
             the Brazilian loan.   There, however, are also some complications which&#13;
&#13;
             I think would make it unwise for us to consider it now, much as vre might&#13;
&#13;
             like to.   I might suggest at this time though,       ~~thout   any further dis-&#13;
&#13;
             cussion, because I do not know enough to report to the Board facts to&#13;
&#13;
             justify a discussion, that the fundamental problem there is going to be&#13;
&#13;
             that we shall have to determine vmat our attitude in regard to Brazil will&#13;
&#13;
             be in the event that Brazil's situation with the Fund is not cleared up.&#13;
&#13;
             Now so much for Item 1';0. 2.     I have nothing else on the formal agenda.        I&#13;
&#13;
             thought I might mention Professor Varvaressos t report and tell you that&#13;
&#13;
             the Loan andR.esearch Department people are putting together comments on&#13;
&#13;
             that report and I hope to have that to you in due time if the Directors&#13;
&#13;
             would like it and have a discussion about that report and those comments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             - 161 -&#13;
&amp;#12;HDPPENOT:   Mr. Chairman, I must tell you quite frankly that I do not know if I am&#13;
            entitled or qualified as a member of the Board to discuss or even to hear&#13;
&#13;
            about Pro fessor Varvaressos t report.     I read it carefully yesterday, but&#13;
&#13;
            there is a very large number of personal opinions on England and on France&#13;
&#13;
            that I will not be able to diSCUSS, such as on the political situation,&#13;
&#13;
            history of the country, and so forth.      Matters have been discussed at the&#13;
&#13;
            Sixteen Nations t Meeting that may have been discussed here when we went&#13;
&#13;
            into the French Loan.      Really I do not feel able to discuss   ~t   and I do&#13;
&#13;
            not feel entitled to.&#13;
&#13;
CHAIRMAN:   I certainly am not going to require anybody to discuss anytMng they do&#13;
&#13;
            not want to discuss, and I am not putting it fOITfard as any sort of&#13;
&#13;
            official item on the agenda.      I think the whole question of European re-&#13;
&#13;
            covery is something in which the Board is vitally interested and I would&#13;
&#13;
            think that if we could not discuss that in the Board we would scarcely be&#13;
&#13;
            doing our duty.    VIe   have already had discussions on European Recovery&#13;
&#13;
            problems and perhaps it vrould be unwise, inappropriate or ineffective to&#13;
&#13;
            discuss it as an item of an agenda, but I wonder 'whether it could not be&#13;
&#13;
            considered as a continuation of some of the informal meetings which we&#13;
&#13;
            have had on general world recovery problems.       Don't you think that is&#13;
            the way to do it?&#13;
&#13;
lillNRO:    I have not yet had the opportunity of studying it closely.        I have glanced&#13;
&#13;
            through i t and my feelings are that I am in sympathy with my French&#13;
&#13;
            colleague.     I do rather question how embarrassing it might be for certain&#13;
&#13;
            members.     Certain questions and opinions brought into the thing may be&#13;
&#13;
            inappropriate for us to discuss as a Board when it will not have a direct&#13;
&#13;
            bearing on any course of action we might adopt.       I agree that it is a&#13;
&#13;
            valuable report and controversial, as many valuable things are.          I agree&#13;
&#13;
            however, that we might wish the whole subject discussed sooner or later.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             - 762 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                I must say I had never tllOUght of this thing.    I get at first blush that&#13;
&#13;
                there mie;ht be some hesital1cy to discuss a report of this nature.      Let me&#13;
&#13;
                talk off the cuff.    I do feel in some form or other this Board ought to&#13;
&#13;
                feel free from all its international representation to discuss frankly&#13;
&#13;
                what conditions are throughout the world, vd.thout having it spread on the&#13;
&#13;
                record.    The political views affect the economic and the economic views&#13;
&#13;
                aIfect the political.    If we can only discuss certain s.exless types of&#13;
&#13;
                report we will not be getting and we vall not have the general freedom ani&#13;
&#13;
                objectivity that I think and organization of this type ought to have.&#13;
&#13;
                This is my first reaction.&#13;
&#13;
BEYEN:          I think that i t would be regrettable i f the fact that Professor Varvaressos&#13;
&#13;
                has uttered his opinions on political matters with frankness of view would&#13;
&#13;
                bar us from discussion of the economic aspects of his report.        I think it&#13;
&#13;
                is our duty to do so and I lIould very much like to do it for various&#13;
&#13;
                reasons.    First, I think we could have, as promised, a report from the&#13;
&#13;
                Research Department on it, but, quite apart from the political angles,&#13;
&#13;
                there are various stater:Jents of economic character.      Many of them are&#13;
&#13;
                economic in character and wholesome, but some of them I think are at least&#13;
&#13;
                open to doubt.    I think ,{fe could be given an opportunity to discuss those&#13;
&#13;
                angles at any rate.&#13;
&#13;
BARANSKI:       I am absolutely impartial and objective because I have not yet read it.&#13;
&#13;
                So I cannot say what are either the advantages or disadvantages of the&#13;
&#13;
                discussion, but if the matter is controversial it is better to have a&#13;
&#13;
                discussion and stress the controversial points.         Otherwise we will give&#13;
&#13;
                the impression, even with the comments of the Research and of the Loan&#13;
&#13;
                Departments, that Prr)fessor   Varva~ssos   is right.&#13;
&#13;
CH}l.l RMAN :   Anybody else?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               - 763 -&#13;
&amp;#12;CF    U:I!AH:    Let me go on and finish by saying that the representatives of the insurance&#13;
(CL.dt'd)&#13;
                 companies, according to IlliY schedule, will be here on March 24th from&#13;
&#13;
                 Massachusetts, and on the 26th from the Commonwealth of Virginia.         Mr.&#13;
                 1iachado?&#13;
&#13;
MACHADO:         This is st. Patrick's Day, and Saint Patrick brought to Ireland a lot of&#13;
&#13;
                 courage and faith and music and poetry.      A year ago it brought us McCloy.&#13;
&#13;
                 Since we have survived a year under McCloy we ought to recognize that fact&#13;
&#13;
                 and go on record with our appreciation of our good association with him,&#13;
&#13;
                 and the expectation that he will carry us forward to great accomplishments.&#13;
&#13;
CEAI 'Th'lAN :   I am ver.r touched by that.     Certainly I am glad that St. Patrick brought&#13;
&#13;
                 me here.    I look back on this year with a great deal of satisfaction.         I&#13;
&#13;
                 shall long remember that first meetLTlg I had with the Board when I came,&#13;
&#13;
                 after the stress and strain of many newspaper comments.      It was a very&#13;
&#13;
                 awh'''ward time for us all.   He have gotten some roots down this year.     I&#13;
&#13;
                 hope that the next year vdll find deeper and finner roots embedded in the&#13;
&#13;
                 soil.   I am absolutely confident that they will be so embedded, and am the&#13;
&#13;
                 more certain in my feeling about that by reason of the fact that I now&#13;
&#13;
                 know so thoroughly that the Board of Directors have the objectives of the&#13;
&#13;
                 Bank deeply rooted in their own convictions and have shO\m such rnagnificent&#13;
&#13;
                 cooperation with the manageJrent in conducting this institution.     It has&#13;
&#13;
                 been a very pleasant association indeed.      Although the next year looks&#13;
&#13;
                 from this particular point as being another one of stress and strain, we&#13;
&#13;
                 can look forward so far as the Bank is concerned, with confidence in the&#13;
&#13;
                 knowledge that we have a good and loyal institution to cope .dth the&#13;
&#13;
                 difficult problems that are bound to arise.&#13;
                                                 (APPLAUSE)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 - 764 -&#13;
&amp;#12;cr    1MAN:        I understand there is a radio set up here so that anyone who 'wants to&#13;
(CtJtlt1d)&#13;
                   can listen to the President's speech at 12:30.       I think the connection is&#13;
                   good.   The meeting is closed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              ADJOURNED 11 :25 a.m.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   Sir Gordon, you had something to say.&#13;
&#13;
1.'1JNRO:          Thank you very much.    I want to make at the outset, a few remarks not in&#13;
&#13;
                   my capacity as Executive Director of this Bank.       I am speaking merely as&#13;
&#13;
                   a Scotsman on st. Patric}c's Day, I suppose, and since I am not speaking&#13;
&#13;
                   as a Director of this Board, perhaps it would be appropriate if I rose&#13;
                   for this occasion.     I have been charged, Mr. President and Directors,&#13;
&#13;
                   with a most pleasant   du~,   by the Governor of the Bank of Eneland, Lord&#13;
&#13;
                   Catto, and the Court of the Bank of England.       They heard that the Bank&#13;
&#13;
                   bad started a Luncheon Room, similar to their own, and they are very&#13;
&#13;
                   anxious to give some small expression of their friendliness and esteem,&#13;
&#13;
                   by making some token gift to the President and Directors of this Bank,&#13;
&#13;
                   ri.hich they hoped would be used in the Luncheon Room.     This is the small&#13;
&#13;
                   gift they wanted to f,ive.       They send this wooden box from the Bank of&#13;
                   England.   They were   any~ous    to make the presentation a personal one and&#13;
&#13;
                   wished to give some small token.        This box is made from one of the piles&#13;
&#13;
                   on which the Bank of England was built in 1797.        They hope very much it&#13;
&#13;
                   vnll be welcomed, and that you vall appreciate it.        I have a letter from&#13;
&#13;
                   the Governor, which I would like, if I may, Mr. President, to read:&#13;
&#13;
                   "Dear Mr. President, It has come to my knowledge that you and your&#13;
&#13;
                   colleagues are starting a Luncheon Room rather on the lines of our own.&#13;
&#13;
                   I am pleased to hear this     becaus~   I am sure that it will prove a pleasant&#13;
&#13;
                   and informal way of cementing your contacts with visitors from Central&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     - 765 -&#13;
&amp;#12;ML_._..O:     Banks and others from allover the world.           We are, as you know, always&#13;
(Cont'd)&#13;
              happy to see our friends at our luncheon table and we have already had&#13;
&#13;
              the pleasure of so entertaining representatives of the International Bank.&#13;
&#13;
                   As a token of our good wishes I am sending you on behal,f of my&#13;
&#13;
              colleagues and myself one of the cigarette boxes which were made from the&#13;
&#13;
              piles on which the Bank was built in 1797.          I hope that you will use it&#13;
&#13;
              at your luncheon table and that it will remind you of the interest and&#13;
&#13;
              sympathy which the Old Lady bears toward your Institution.&#13;
&#13;
                                         I am, Dear Mr. President,&#13;
&#13;
                                             Yours Sincerely,&#13;
&#13;
                                                    CATTO   II&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              On behalf of the Governor, I would like to hand this over as a small&#13;
&#13;
              token of esteem and affection.&#13;
&#13;
CiiAIRMAN :   This is a very warming, and highly appreciated gift we have received from&#13;
&#13;
              the Mother of Banks, and it )'.rill, I am sure, gi ve us inspiration as we&#13;
&#13;
              are diJling at our board, to have the cigarettes passed from this box.            The&#13;
&#13;
              thoughtfulness of Lord Catto, and of the Governor and Court of the Bank of&#13;
&#13;
              England is deeply appreciated, and I hope that we will have an occasion,&#13;
              or many occasions, on which we' can welcome them to sit at our board when&#13;
&#13;
              they visit this country.     Thank you very much indeed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             - 766 -&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="15330132">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1948/03/15330132/transcript-one-hundred-twenty-sixth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-bank-held-wednesday-march-17-1948
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1948/03/15330132/transcript-one-hundred-twenty-sixth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-bank-held-wednesday-march-17-1948</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1948/03/15330132/transcript-one-hundred-twenty-sixth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-bank-held-wednesday-march-17-1948</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2011-09-29T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2016-01-14T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b0828bee28</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0828bee28</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/10/21/000386194_20111021064204/Rendered/INDEX/650450TRANSCRI061560B0March01701948.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/10/21/000386194_20111021064204/Rendered/PDF/650450TRANSCRI061560B0March01701948.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2011-10-21T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1948-03-17T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of one hundred twenty sixth
            regular meeting of the Executive Directors of the Bank, held
            on Wednesday, March 17, 1948
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This transcript, from the session of the
            Executive Directors held on Wednesday, March 17, 1948 covers
            only the discussion one hundred twenty sixth regular meeting
            and informal meeting.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of one hundred twenty sixth
            regular meeting of the Executive Directors of the Bank, held
            on Wednesday, March 17, 1948
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of one hundred twenty
            sixth regular meeting of the Executive Directors of the
            Bank, held on Wednesday, March 17, 1948</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1948/03/15330132/transcript-one-hundred-twenty-sixth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-bank-held-wednesday-march-17-1948</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Sustainable Land and Crop Management,Corporate Law,Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Debt Markets,Gender and Law</subtopic>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <teratopic>Rural Development,Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Gender</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000386194_20111021064204</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Board transcript</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Rural Development,Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Gender</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Banks, confidence, Court, economic
            development, home, insurance, insurance companies,
            International Bank, Loan, loan application, Ministers, Will
        </keywd>
        <owner>Policy and Operations (SECPO)</owner>
        <repnb>65045</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Land and Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Land Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>