<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿NOTE NUMBER 326                                                                                                                                                                                  65598&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                            viewpoint                                          PUBLIC POLICY FOR THE PRIVATE SECTOR&#13;
FEBRUARy 2011&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          Water in Bucharest&#13;
 FINANCIAL AND PRIVATE SECTOR DEVELOPMENT VICE PRESIDENCY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            David Earhardt,              A Utilityâ&#128;&#153;s Efficiency Gains under a Concession&#13;
                                                            MelissaÂ Rekas, and&#13;
                                                            MartinaÂ Tonizzo              I n M a r c h 20 0 0 B u c h a r e s t e n t e r e d i n t o a c o n c e s s i o n c o n t r a c t f o r i t s&#13;
&#13;
                                                            David Earhardt is&#13;
                                                                                         w at e r u t i l i t y w i t h t h e a i m of t u r n i n g a r o u n d t h e u t i l i t y â&#128;&#153;s f a l t e r i n g&#13;
                                                            chief executive, and         p e r f o r m a n c e . U n d e r t h e p r i v at e o p e r at o r t h e u t i l i t y h a s r a i s e d&#13;
                                                            Martina Tonizzo an&#13;
                                                                                         s e r v i c e q u a l i t y a b ove Ro m a n i a n s t a n d a r d s a n d t ow a r d We s t e r n&#13;
                                                            analyst, at Castalia,&#13;
                                                            an advisory firm             E u r o p e a n l eve l s . B y 20 0 8 e f f i c i e n c y g a i n s h a d p r o d u c e d c o s t s av i n g s&#13;
                                                            specializing in governance&#13;
                                                                                         t ot a l i n g U S $349 m i l l i o n . T h e c o n c e s s i o n a i r e h a s f i n a n c e d U S $259&#13;
                                                            and regulation of&#13;
                                                            infrastructure services.     m i l l i o n i n i nve s t m e n t , w i t h o u t p u b l i c s u b s i d y, w h i l e ke e p i n g t a r i f f s&#13;
                                                            Melissa Rekas was            we l l b e l ow t h e Ro m a n i a n ave r a g e . N ot a l l w at e r c o n c e s s i o n s h ave&#13;
                                                            formerly a manager at the&#13;
                                                            firm. Castalia carried out   b e e n a s s u c c e s s f u l . W h at a c c o u n t s f o r t h e g a i n s u n d e r t h i s o n e?&#13;
                                                            an evaluation of the water&#13;
                                                            concession in Bucharest.     After Romaniaâ&#128;&#153;s communist dictatorship fell                   on tariff level, was concluded in 2000. The win-&#13;
                                                                                         in 1989, responsibility for water service in                  ning bidder, Apa Nova Bucuresti, a subsidiary&#13;
                                                            Comments and questions       Bucharest was transferred to RGAB, a munici-                  of the international water operator Veolia, took&#13;
                                                            may be directed to           pal water utility. By the late 1990s service was              over the operation in November 2000.&#13;
                                                            Chiaki Yamamoto&#13;
                                                                                         intermittent, water pressure was low, water qual-&#13;
                                                            (cyamamoto@ifc.org).&#13;
                                                                                         ity fell short of health standards, and there were            Benefits for Bucharest&#13;
                                                                                         outbreaks of waterborne disease. The system                   Apa Nova improved service markedly over the&#13;
                                                                                         needed more than US$1 billion in investment,                  first 10 years of the concession while keeping&#13;
THE WORLD BANK GROUP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                         but neither the municipality nor the national                 the connection rate high (93 percent in 2007)&#13;
                                                                                         government was able to finance an investment                  and only moderately increasing the typical&#13;
                                                                                         of this size.                                                 household bill.&#13;
                                                                                             The municipality decided to bring in a pri-&#13;
                                                                                         vate firm to manage the system and finance                    Faster gains in service quality&#13;
                                                                                         improvements. The World Bank helped pave                      Water quality tests went from less than 70 per-&#13;
                                                                                         the way by developing a public-private partner-               cent compliance before the concession to 100&#13;
                                                                                         ship strategy, and the International Finance                  percent by 2006. Water supply is now continu-&#13;
                                                                                         Corporation (IFC) supported the municipal-                    ous and at good pressure, and water quality&#13;
                                                                                         ity as the transaction adviser between 1998 and               exceeds Romanian and European Union stan-&#13;
                                                                                         2000. The competitive bidding process, based                  dards. Complaints fell to less than a seventh of&#13;
&amp;#12;WATER IN BUCHAREST A UTILITYâ&#128;&#153;S EFFICIENCY GAINS UNDER A CONCESSION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                            their previous level, while customer satisfaction                        the period averaged 11 percent a year. While&#13;
                                                                                            with overall service climbed from less than 50                           the increase seems large, tariffs in Bucharest&#13;
                                                                                            percent to 75 percent.                                                   remain well below the average for the 10 other&#13;
                                                                                                Service also improved in a group of 10                               Romanian cities as well as for European capitals&#13;
                                                                                            Romanian municipal utilities without a public-                           such as Rome (US$1.40) or London (US$3.60).&#13;
                                                                                            private partnership. But Bucharestâ&#128;&#153;s utility,                            Moreover, unlike the other Romanian utilities,&#13;
                                                                                            under the concession, improved faster and                                Apa Nova financed all its operations and invest-&#13;
                                                                                            reached better levels than most of these utili-                          ment without subsidies. And the tariff increases&#13;
                                                                                            ties on four of six key service indicatorsâ&#128;&#148;water                         were tied to improvements in service.&#13;
2&#13;
                                                                                            coverage, sewerage coverage, water quality, and&#13;
                                                                                            customer complaint level (figure 1). On two                              Gains in efficiency&#13;
                                                                                            indicatorsâ&#128;&#148;sewer blockages and pipe breaksâ&#128;&#148;                              Significant efficiency gains allowed Apa Nova&#13;
                                                                                            the Bucharest utilityâ&#128;&#153;s level of performance was                         to generate the operating cash flow needed to&#13;
                                                                                            still below average in 2007. But on all the service                      service the utilityâ&#128;&#153;s loans and provide a return&#13;
                                                                                            indicators reviewed, its performance improved                            on equity invested. From 2000 to 2007 Apa Nova&#13;
                                                                                            faster than the average rate for the 10 other                            kept its operating cost increases below the aver-&#13;
                                                                                            Romanian utilities.                                                      age for the other Romanian utilities. Indeed,&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                     Bucharestâ&#128;&#153;s utility has the fourth lowest unit&#13;
                                                                                            Low tariffsâ&#128;&#148;and no subsidies                                             operating costs among the 11 utilities for which&#13;
                                                                                            Before the concession, the average combined                              data were available.&#13;
                                                                                            water and wastewater tariff in Bucharest was                                The biggest factor in Apa Novaâ&#128;&#153;s ability to&#13;
                                                                                            around US$0.18 per cubic meter. By 2009 the                              contain operating costs was the gain in labor&#13;
                                                                                            combined tariff had reached US$1.08. In local                            productivity achieved by the new managers.&#13;
                                                                                            currency terms the real price increase over                              Bucharestâ&#128;&#153;s utility went from being one of the&#13;
&#13;
Figure     Service quality and improvement in Bucharest compared with other Romanian cities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1                                                             2&#13;
                                                                      Above-average level,&#13;
                                                                      below-average improvement&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                          Above-average level&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                            and improvement&#13;
           Level in 2007 (standard deviations from average)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                             Sewerage coverage&#13;
                                                              1&#13;
                                                                                                                                                     Water quality                                Customer complaints&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                     Water coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                              0       Average&#13;
                                                                                                                                                   Sewer blockages&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                              1&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                        Pipe breaks&#13;
                                                                                                                                         Average&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                              2&#13;
                                                                      Below-average level                                                                                                            Below-average level,&#13;
                                                                      and improvement                                                                                                         above-average improvement&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  3                         2                     1                        0                                1                       2                                3&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                          Average annual change in 2000â&#128;&#147;07 (standard deviations from average)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Source: Authorsâ&#128;&#153; calculations based on data from the International Benchmarking Network for Water and Sanitation Utilities (IBNET) and Apa Nova.&#13;
         Note: Averages are based on available data for 10 Romanian utilities operating without a public-private partnership in municipalities with more than 80,000 inhabitants. The averages do not include Bucharestâ&#128;&#153;s utility.&#13;
&amp;#12;least efficient in the use of labor in Romania to   Impact on costs&#13;
one of the most efficient as staff per thousand     To test the total impact of the concession on&#13;
connections fell from 75 in 2000 to 20 in 2007.     costs, a financial simulation model of Bucharestâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
   Clearly, labor force reductions of this          water utility was constructed. The model shows&#13;
magnitude were traumatic for all concerned.         that if the utility had made the same investments&#13;
Relations between Apa Novaâ&#128;&#153;s management             in improved service, but with the efficiencies&#13;
and staff were difficult between 2000 and 2003.     observed in Romanian utilities that do not have&#13;
The management wanted to reduce the work-           a public-private partnership, the total cost of ser-&#13;
force rapidly, and unions led several strikes       vice provision over the period 2000â&#128;&#147;08 would&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                     3&#13;
in response. But relations improved after the       have been US$349 million higher.&#13;
first three years as Apa Nova started delegat-          The people of Bucharest would have borne&#13;
ing more responsibility to the staff and also       this additional cost, through either higher taxes&#13;
invested in new equipment that increased            (if the municipality had been called on to sub-&#13;
employee safety and productivity. In addition,      sidize the company) or higher bills. Indeed,&#13;
as part of the social plan included in the con-     under continued public management, achiev-&#13;
cession contract, Veolia sold 10 percent of Apa     ing the same investment levels that Apa Nova&#13;
Novaâ&#128;&#153;s shares to staff in 2007. This sale brought   did would have required almost doubling the&#13;
staff members into a partnership with Veolia as     bills for a typical household. Instead, compared&#13;
equity holders and improved relations between       with a scenario with no concession (and no sub-&#13;
management and the staff. Workers now feel          sidy), the concession reduced household bills by&#13;
they are better off than before, according to       33 percent on average between 2000 and 2008&#13;
Apa Novaâ&#128;&#153;s federation of unions.                    (figure 2). And the savings keep growing. The&#13;
   Apa Nova also achieved other efficiencies:       2009 bill for a typical household was just over&#13;
â&#150; â&#150;  Energy efficiency. Bucharestâ&#128;&#153;s utility had       half what it would have been in the scenario&#13;
   the second slowest rate of unit energy cost      with no concession.&#13;
   increases in the sample.                             These estimates are based on conservative&#13;
â&#150; â&#150;  Collection efficiency. In 2007 Apa Nova col-     assumptions. For example, the calculations&#13;
   lected 98 percent of bills, compared with an     assume that the utility under public manage-&#13;
   average for the 10 other utilities of about 95   ment is just as efficient as the private company&#13;
   percent.                                         in capital expenditure. But studies of public -&#13;
â&#150; â&#150;  Reduced waste. A demand-side management          private partnership projects show that publicly&#13;
   campaign involving customer awareness,           run projects tend to have higher capital expen-&#13;
   expanded metering, and more cost-reflective      diture (Duffield 2010).&#13;
   tariffs reduced consumption toward Western&#13;
   European levels. Water consumption in 2009       Figure     Average monthly household bill with and without the concession, 2000â&#128;&#147; 08&#13;
   was 40 percent of the 1999 level of 571 liters&#13;
   per capita a day.&#13;
â&#150; â&#150;  Reduced nonrevenue water.1 Bucharestâ&#128;&#153;s utility&#13;
&#13;
   cut the level of nonrevenue water by nearly&#13;
                                                    2            Lei&#13;
                                                                70&#13;
&#13;
                                                                60&#13;
                                                                                                                                     Without concession (counterfactual)&#13;
   half, from almost 350 cubic meters per kilo-&#13;
   meter of network a day in 2000â&#128;&#148;the high-                     50&#13;
&#13;
   est in the sampleâ&#128;&#148;to 176 in 2007. While the                  40&#13;
   10 other utilities reduced nonrevenue water&#13;
   by 6 percent a year on average, Bucharestâ&#128;&#153;s                  30&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                 With concession&#13;
   reduced it by 10 percent a year.&#13;
                                                                20&#13;
   Over the first nine years of the concession&#13;
Apa Nova invested US$66 million in pipe                         10&#13;
replacement and other measures to reduce leak-&#13;
                                                                  0&#13;
age. In the short term this pushed up the cost of&#13;
                                                                        2000          2001         2002         2003         2004          2005        2006        2007       2008&#13;
service. But over the long term this investment&#13;
will help keep costs and tariffs down.                       Source: Authorsâ&#128;&#153; calculations based on Apa Nova financial statements.&#13;
&amp;#12;WATER IN BUCHAREST A UTILITYâ&#128;&#153;S EFFICIENCY GAINS UNDER A CONCESSION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   The estimates also assume that investment           Mechanisms for regulation, monitoring, and&#13;
and service improvements would have been            dispute resolution were also key to success. The&#13;
possible without a concession. This is doubt-       technical regulator created within the munici-&#13;
ful. RGAB had difficulty mobilizing finance         pality was innovative and did its job well. An&#13;
because it was making losses and lacked any         international expert panel (whose selection                   viewpoint&#13;
credible commitment to turn itself around.          was agreed to by both the municipality and the&#13;
Investments made while the company was              concessionaire) has been crucial in maintain-&#13;
under public management often failed to yield       ing the relationship between the contracting                  is an open forum to&#13;
the intended results. All this suggests that the    parties. Because the expert panel is neutral                  encourage dissemination of&#13;
estimated savings are a lower-bound estimate        (the contract requires that the members be                    public policy innovations&#13;
of the value that the concession has brought        neither from Romania nor from the country of                  for private sectorâ&#128;&#147;led and&#13;
to the citizens of Bucharest. Over the lifetime     the investor, in this case France), accepted, and             market-based solutions for&#13;
of the concession (2000â&#128;&#147;25) the public-private      readily available, the parties have turned to it              development. The views&#13;
partnership will save citizens a total of US$1.38   before disagreements become conflicts.                        published are those of the&#13;
billion (present value as of 2008).                                                                               authors and should not be&#13;
                                                    Conclusion                                                    attributed to the World&#13;
Insights from project implementation                The concession of Bucharestâ&#128;&#153;s water utility                   Bank or any other affiliated&#13;
All the evidence points to the concession con-      has brought its citizens higher-quality water                 organizations. Nor do any&#13;
tract as the root cause of the improvements in      services, at a lower cost, than they could have               of the conclusions represent&#13;
&#13;
service and efficiency in Bucharestâ&#128;&#153;s water and     had under continued municipal provision.                      official policy of the World&#13;
&#13;
wastewater services. Yet not all concession con-    The credit for this goes to the leadership of the             Bank or of its Executive&#13;
&#13;
tracts have been as successful. In Argentina,       municipality and the municipal utility in the                 Directors or the countries&#13;
&#13;
for example, concession contracts for Buenos        late 1990s, which saw that private finance and                they represent.&#13;
&#13;
Aires and several other cities and provinces ran    management were needed to reverse the cycle&#13;
                                                                                                                  To order additional copies&#13;
into serious difficulties and were canceled. In     of poor performance. Credit also goes to the&#13;
                                                                                                                  contact Suzanne Smith,&#13;
Manila, where two concession contracts were         managers and staff of Veolia and Apa Nova, who&#13;
                                                                                                                  managing editor,&#13;
awarded, the concessionaire for the west zone       have made the utility work; the union leaders,&#13;
                                                                                                                  Room F 4K-292,&#13;
went into default and had to be financially         who were able to chart a course through the&#13;
                                                                                                                  The World Bank,&#13;
restructured. Are there distinctive features in     labor force reductions; and the municipal tech-&#13;
                                                                                                                  1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
the design and implementation of Bucharestâ&#128;&#153;s        nical regulator, which ensured that the public&#13;
                                                                                                                  Washington, DC 20433.&#13;
concession that contributed to its success?         interest was protected throughout.&#13;
   The teams involved played a key part in that                                                                   Telephone:&#13;
success. Senior officials in the municipality                                                                     001 202 458 7281&#13;
and utility were committed to a public-private                                                                    Fax:&#13;
partnership. In particular, the head of the         Note                                                          001 202 522 3480&#13;
municipal utility, convinced that it could not      1. Nonrevenue water consists of leakage and commer-           Email:&#13;
operate effectively under direct government         cial losses due to underbilling, theft, and other deficien-   ssmith7@worldbank.org&#13;
management, championed the reforms. While           cies in the commercial system.&#13;
most of the IFC team was based in Washington,                                                                     Produced by Communications&#13;
DC, the team brought on board a Romanian            Reference                                                     Development Incorporated&#13;
adviser with strong reform credentials who was      Duffield, Colin. 2010. â&#128;&#156;Report on the Performance of&#13;
known and trusted by senior officials in the           PPP Projects in Australia When Compared with a             Printed on recycled paper&#13;
government. His role was to ensure that the            Representative Sample of Traditionally Procured&#13;
advisory teamâ&#128;&#153;s technical expertise could be           Infrastructure Projects.â&#128;? University of Melbourne.&#13;
effectively communicated to the right people           Available at http://www.partnerships.vic.gov.au.&#13;
in government and to stay on top of the man-&#13;
agement of the complex and fluid transaction&#13;
process.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                            This Note is available online:&#13;
                                                             http://rru.worldbank.org/PublicPolicyJournal&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="15476286">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/02/15476286/water-bucharest-utilitys-efficiency-gains-under-concession
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/02/15476286/water-bucharest-utilitys-efficiency-gains-under-concession</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2011/02/15476286/water-bucharest-utilitys-efficiency-gains-under-concession</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2011-11-15T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2011-11-15T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/11/15/000333037_20111115233624/Rendered/INDEX/655980BRI00PUB0arest0water00PUBLIC0.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/11/15/000333037_20111115233624/Rendered/PDF/655980BRI00PUB0arest0water00PUBLIC0.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2011-02-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2011-11-15T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Water in Bucharest : a utility's
            efficiency gains under a concession
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In March 2000 Bucharest entered into a
            concession contract for its water utility with the aim of
            turning around the utility's faltering performance.
            Under the private operator the utility has raised service
            quality above Romanian standards and toward Western European
            levels. By 2008 efficiency gains had produced cost savings
            totaling US$349 million. The concessionaire has financed
            US$259 million in investment, without public subsidy, while
            keeping tariffs well below the Romanian average. Not all
            water concessions have been as successful. What accounts for
            the gains under this one? The concession of Bucharest's
            water utility has brought its citizens higher-quality water
            services, at a lower cost, than they could have had under
            continued municipal provision. The credit for this goes to
            the leadership of the municipality and the municipal utility
            in the late 1990s, which saw that private finance and
            management were needed to reverse the cycle of poor performance.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Water in Bucharest : a utility's
            efficiency gains under a concession
        </docna>
        <display_title>Water in Bucharest : a
            utility's efficiency gains under a concession</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2011/02/15476286/water-bucharest-utilitys-efficiency-gains-under-concession</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Infrastructure Economics,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Water and Industry</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Resources,Infrastructure Economics and Finance,Water Supply and Sanitation</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20111115233624</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>View point ; no. 326</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Resources,Infrastructure Economics and Finance,Water Supply and Sanitation</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            capital expenditure, cash flow, Collection
            efficiency, competitive bidding, competitive bidding
            process, concession, concession contract, concession
            contracts, connection, connection rate, connections, cost of
            service, cubic meter, cubic meters, customer satisfaction,
            Energy efficiency, Infrastructure Projects, infrastructure
            services, International Finance, international water
            operator, leakage, Low tariffs, metering, municipal
            utilities, municipal utility, municipal water,
            municipalities, pipe breaks, pipe replacement, present
            value, public management, quality Water, responsibility for
            water, Sanitation, Sanitation Utilities, service
            improvements, service provision, service quality, sewerage,
            tariff level, utilities, wastewater, wastewater services,
            wastewater tariff, Water consumption, water coverage, water
            quality, water service, Water supply, water utility
        </keywd>
        <owner>PPP Transaction AS (CASPP)</owner>
        <repnb>65598</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shared Rivers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Diplomacy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Conservation &amp; Efficiency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Conservation and Efficiency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Investment Plan</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement of Judgements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Informal Dispute Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transboundary Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Efficiency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Investment Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Dispute Resolution</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>