<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
                                                65771&#13;
   INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 Monday, December 20, 1999&#13;
&#13;
                                 Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           The informal meeting of the Executive Directors&#13;
&#13;
 of the Bank and IDA convened at 10:10 a.m., on Monday,&#13;
&#13;
 December 20, 1999, in the Board Room, 700 Eighteenth&#13;
&#13;
 Street, N.W., under the chairmanship of Mr. James&#13;
&#13;
 Wolfensohn.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                             Page1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
                       C O N T E N T S&#13;
&#13;
 AGENDA ITEM:                     PAGE&#13;
&#13;
 1.   Poverty Reduction Strategy Papers:         Operational&#13;
      Issues                   10&#13;
&#13;
           Mr.   Hubloue.................24&#13;
           Mr.   Holden..................31&#13;
           Mr.   Haque...................35&#13;
           Mr.   Kamitomai...............43&#13;
           Mr.   Singh...................47&#13;
           Mr.   Alyahya.................53&#13;
           Ms.   Hollifield..............58&#13;
           Mr.   Zhu.....................62&#13;
           Mr.   Meyer...................72&#13;
           Mr.   Balduino................77&#13;
           Mr.   Pesme...................85&#13;
           Mr.   Reinermann..............94&#13;
           Mr.   Al-Saad.................96&#13;
           Mr.   Toure...................99&#13;
           Mr.   Passacantando..........101&#13;
           Mr.   Abraham................105&#13;
           Ms.   Piercy.................107&#13;
           Mr.   Pickford...............126&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                               Page2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
                    P R O C E E D I N G S&#13;
&#13;
           MR. WOLFENSOHN:    Good morning.&#13;
&#13;
           I will first call on Mr. Ferrer to comment on&#13;
&#13;
 the present situation in Venezuela.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. FERRER:   Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           By now, you can see that this catastrophe in&#13;
&#13;
 Venezuela is probably worse than in Honduras.      The figures&#13;
&#13;
 which have been confirmed are 5,000 people dead and 10,000&#13;
&#13;
 missing, but unofficially, they are already talking about&#13;
&#13;
 25,000 people dead--&#13;
&#13;
           MR. WOLFENSOHN:    Twenty-five thousand?&#13;
&#13;
           MR. FERRER:   That is what has been said.     It has&#13;
&#13;
 not been officially confirmed.      But they are talking about&#13;
&#13;
 25,000, most of them buried alive in mud or swept away to&#13;
&#13;
 the sea by the landslides and the water.&#13;
&#13;
           And as to people who have lost their homes, the&#13;
&#13;
 estimate is by now 150,000 and is probably substantially&#13;
&#13;
 larger.   So it is a very serious catastrophe, and it is&#13;
&#13;
 regrettable that so little was known of it until, I&#13;
&#13;
 believe, Friday, maybe even Saturday, because all that&#13;
&#13;
 happened Wednesday and Thursday.       It is amazing how little&#13;
&#13;
 attention the media paid to what was going on over there.&#13;
                                                                   Page3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
            Maybe--and I am not trying to put the blame on&#13;
&#13;
 anyone--maybe the Venezuelan authorities also tried to&#13;
&#13;
 play down the situation at the beginning, and that may&#13;
&#13;
 also be at the root or the origin of what little amount of&#13;
&#13;
 attention has been devoted to it.&#13;
&#13;
            What can the Bank do for Venezuela?      I suppose I&#13;
&#13;
 shouldn't answer that question.        I have been talking&#13;
&#13;
 already with the Country Director and so on on Friday, and&#13;
&#13;
 they have already gotten in touch with the Venezuelan&#13;
&#13;
 authorities.    The most obvious measure that the Bank may&#13;
&#13;
 take, and I believe it is already on its way, is to&#13;
&#13;
 disburse quickly the loans which have still not been&#13;
&#13;
 disbursed.   I believe there are five of them which could&#13;
&#13;
 be disbursed very quickly, and all of them total about&#13;
&#13;
 $400 million.   This could probably be of some help.&#13;
&#13;
            In this respect, I must admit that there has&#13;
&#13;
 been a change in the attitude of the Venezuelan&#13;
&#13;
 authorities.    Before Friday, they would not admit their&#13;
&#13;
 need for some outside help, but by now, they admit that&#13;
&#13;
 any help that may come from any country or any institution&#13;
&#13;
 is welcome, because certainly the catastrophe is very&#13;
&#13;
 serious.&#13;
                                                                   Page4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           The Bank has already gotten in touch with them.&#13;
&#13;
 We have here always the same problem when catastrophes&#13;
&#13;
 take place--the Bank puts itself at the disposal of the&#13;
&#13;
 authorities, but the authorities are normally in a&#13;
&#13;
 terrible mess and don't know what to ask the Bank or&#13;
&#13;
 anybody else, for that matter, to do.         So I wonder if we&#13;
&#13;
 could start to think in the future of having some kind of&#13;
&#13;
 menu of possibilities on the Bank side to be able to react&#13;
&#13;
 under those circumstances.&#13;
&#13;
           At this stage, that is all I want to say.        I&#13;
&#13;
 just wanted you to be aware that this is a very serious&#13;
&#13;
 catastrophe.   I also want to tell you that I have already&#13;
&#13;
 been working with the Bank, and the Venezuelan authorities&#13;
&#13;
 are already in touch with the staff.        I simply believe&#13;
&#13;
 that this is another opportunity to reflect on what can be&#13;
&#13;
 done for the future and how can the Bank be more proactive&#13;
&#13;
 or do something more target-oriented in the case of these&#13;
&#13;
 kinds of catastrophes.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. WOLFENSOHN:    Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
           I think the Bank's crisis team has actually&#13;
&#13;
 demonstrated in the past that we are very responsive.          As&#13;
&#13;
 soon as we knew about this, we told the Venezuelan&#13;
                                                                     Page5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 authorities that we were ready.       I instructed on the&#13;
&#13;
 weekend that we go directly to the President and tell him&#13;
&#13;
 that whatever he wants, we will do.        I don't believe there&#13;
&#13;
 is any holding back, but it is very hard to find someone&#13;
&#13;
 in authority to talk to who is fully informed.       I think&#13;
&#13;
 you'd have to say there has been some crisis in government&#13;
&#13;
 in the way in which they have been able to handle this.&#13;
&#13;
           Within the context of what we can do, I believe&#13;
&#13;
 that we are doing everything we can.        Certainly, I think&#13;
&#13;
 the Board would want to know that we have told them that&#13;
&#13;
 funding is available and that we are ready to be&#13;
&#13;
 responsive as we have been in Honduras and in every other&#13;
&#13;
 case.   And I think it is fair to say that in the other&#13;
&#13;
 natural catastrophes which have occurred, the Bank has&#13;
&#13;
 emerged as being the most responsive and the leading&#13;
&#13;
 factor in terms of both immediacy of response and&#13;
&#13;
 consistency of response.&#13;
&#13;
           It would be my hope, Mr. Ferrer, that we will do&#13;
&#13;
 the same in Venezuela, and if there are any things that&#13;
&#13;
 you think we should be doing that we aren't doing, we&#13;
&#13;
 would be very glad to hear them.       But I do believe that&#13;
&#13;
 our office is doing everything we can, and we are working&#13;
                                                                    Page6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 on it on an hour-to-hour basis.         This is not a casual&#13;
&#13;
 activity.&#13;
&#13;
             If there is anything you think we should be&#13;
&#13;
 doing, I would be very glad to hear from you.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. FERRER:   I'm sorry, that was not a criticism&#13;
&#13;
 toward the Bank.    I believe the Bank is acting correctly.&#13;
&#13;
 I was just wondering if, in the future, the Bank should&#13;
&#13;
 have some quick or fast-deployment unit to act with&#13;
&#13;
 emergency or aid relief--&#13;
&#13;
             MR. WOLFENSOHN:    But we do have that.         It is in&#13;
&#13;
 action.   We do have a catastrophe unit which comes into&#13;
&#13;
 play right away.    I'll make doubly sure that it is active.&#13;
&#13;
 We operate on a 24-hour basis at the moment there is a&#13;
&#13;
 crisis, and we have done it many times in the last period,&#13;
&#13;
 provided we have a counterparty to deal with.             But I will&#13;
&#13;
 double check on it and make sure we inform the Board&#13;
&#13;
 tomorrow and on Thursday of exactly what is happening.&#13;
&#13;
             It is a terrible thing, and the number of 25,000&#13;
&#13;
 really shocks me.    I am very, very upset to hear that.&#13;
&#13;
 That would be more than the catastrophe in Honduras and&#13;
&#13;
 Guatemala.    It would be terrible.&#13;
&#13;
             The second item I want to report on is that I&#13;
&#13;
 did attend the G-20 meetings last week.              I think most of&#13;
                                                                        Page7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 you have had reports on these meetings, but they were&#13;
&#13;
 important, I think, as much for the fact that they took&#13;
&#13;
 place as for the substance.     I would have to say that&#13;
&#13;
 substantially, I don't believe any great new ground was&#13;
&#13;
 traversed, but there was at least a coming together of a&#13;
&#13;
 new group known as the G-20 which covered 85 percent of&#13;
&#13;
 the world's population and which was perceived to have&#13;
&#13;
 greater political legitimacy from a global point of view&#13;
&#13;
 in that the G-7/G-8 was effectively added to by other&#13;
&#13;
 major countries, still with some gaps in representation at&#13;
&#13;
 the meeting, but in the opinion of those who put it&#13;
&#13;
 together, as good a group as they could get.        Several&#13;
&#13;
 important areas were not represented, but within the&#13;
&#13;
 European context I think were perceived to be adequately&#13;
&#13;
 covered.&#13;
&#13;
            The substance of the meeting was around&#13;
&#13;
 international financial architecture again, about the&#13;
&#13;
 development process and issues which are facing the global&#13;
&#13;
 community.   A press release was issued, a copy of which if&#13;
&#13;
 you don't have it, I'll be very glad to make sure comes to&#13;
&#13;
 each of you.   It traverses basically just what I have&#13;
&#13;
 said, adding that the WTO is extraordinarily important to&#13;
&#13;
 the architectural and development process.         They welcomed&#13;
                                                                    Page8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 the work done by the Bretton Woods institutions.        They&#13;
&#13;
 asked us to examine ways to reduce vulnerabilities to&#13;
&#13;
 crises in the future, much as we have addressed in the&#13;
&#13;
 past, and they recognized that sound national economic and&#13;
&#13;
 financial policies are central to the building of an&#13;
&#13;
 international financial system--again, something which I&#13;
&#13;
 believe has been commented on before.         Each nation was&#13;
&#13;
 admonished to strengthen its management and its sovereign&#13;
&#13;
 debt management particularly, and there was some&#13;
&#13;
 discussion that unsustainable exchange rate regimes bring&#13;
&#13;
 with them the prospect of vulnerability and crash.&#13;
&#13;
           So there was a broad general debate, as I said,&#13;
&#13;
 in which I don't believe any brand new areas were&#13;
&#13;
 traversed, but the fact was that this was a meeting that&#13;
&#13;
 was important because of the participants.         I believe that&#13;
&#13;
 little more than that happened, but if anybody has any&#13;
&#13;
 questions, I would be glad to observe on them.&#13;
&#13;
           There was some commentary elliptically on the&#13;
&#13;
 Larry Summers statement which had come out the day before,&#13;
&#13;
 but there was no central debate, and there was some&#13;
&#13;
 discussion in the corridors as to who would be the new&#13;
&#13;
 head of the International Monetary Fund, but I was unable&#13;
                                                                     Page9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 to discern anything that I thought I could report to you&#13;
&#13;
 on the results of those observations.&#13;
&#13;
            So it was an important meeting that we&#13;
&#13;
 participated in that substantially was more a beginning&#13;
&#13;
 than an end of the discussions.&#13;
&#13;
            If anybody has any other perceptions of the&#13;
&#13;
 meeting, I'd be glad if they could perhaps throw them on&#13;
&#13;
 the table.   It was a useful meeting; Mr. Martin was very&#13;
&#13;
 happy to chair the meeting.&#13;
&#13;
            Well, that brings you up-to-date.       Let me now&#13;
&#13;
 pass on to this Board meeting in which I have&#13;
&#13;
 uncharacteristically been programmed by my colleagues to&#13;
&#13;
 read a short opening statement so that I don't get beyond&#13;
&#13;
 the context of the meetings that have already been held&#13;
&#13;
 and so that I don't create problems.        So let me just read&#13;
&#13;
 this, which is approved by my colleagues, and if I&#13;
&#13;
 disagree later, I'll come in and say so, but they have&#13;
&#13;
 asked me to read this.&#13;
&#13;
            It says:   "Our meeting today is to discuss the&#13;
&#13;
 joint Bank/Fund paper on "Poverty Reduction Strategy&#13;
&#13;
 Papers."   This reflects a major commitment on the part of&#13;
&#13;
 our two institutions to work closely together to focus on&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction in low-income countries.&#13;
                                                                   Page10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
             I have followed progress over the past few weeks&#13;
&#13;
 and days closely, and I have been particularly heartened&#13;
&#13;
 by the large degree of support indicated for the general&#13;
&#13;
 thrust of our analysis and the valuable views you have&#13;
&#13;
 provided.&#13;
&#13;
             The directions we are proposing involve&#13;
&#13;
 empowerment of our client countries, major changes in our&#13;
&#13;
 operational direction and thereby in our own roles in the&#13;
&#13;
 development community, and last but not least in&#13;
&#13;
 analytical content.&#13;
&#13;
             The road we propose to take will not be smooth&#13;
&#13;
 but will be bumpy, with many twists and turns, but the&#13;
&#13;
 rationale for moving in this direction has become&#13;
&#13;
 increasingly clear to Michel and myself.            We have become&#13;
&#13;
 increasingly worried that despite the remarkable progress&#13;
&#13;
 we have seen in developing outcomes over the past 25&#13;
&#13;
 years, poverty and social inequities remain deeply&#13;
&#13;
 entrenched.    Moreover, we are facing a population increase&#13;
&#13;
 of 2 billion over the next 25 years from the current 6&#13;
&#13;
 billion, most of which will be in the developing and&#13;
&#13;
 transition economies.     It is therefore no longer an option&#13;
&#13;
 but an imperative that we scale up the effectiveness of&#13;
&#13;
 our efforts, qualitatively and quantitatively.           Unless we&#13;
                                                                      Page11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 make this commitment together, we will surely lose more&#13;
&#13;
 ground against achieving the international development&#13;
&#13;
 goals to reduce poverty.&#13;
&#13;
           As we prepare to move in this direction, I&#13;
&#13;
 cannot help but be impressed by the convergence of views&#13;
&#13;
 across the development community on what should be the key&#13;
&#13;
 principles that should guide us as a compass.        Familiar as&#13;
&#13;
 you are with these, let me list them here:         country&#13;
&#13;
 ownership; a comprehensive approach to development; a&#13;
&#13;
 clear focus on development outcomes and working in&#13;
&#13;
 partnership.&#13;
&#13;
           In particular, you will recall that at the&#13;
&#13;
 September Annual Meetings, Ministers recommended that&#13;
&#13;
 these same principles embedded in the CDF be applied in&#13;
&#13;
 the preparation of PRSPs.     I am very appreciative of this&#13;
&#13;
 clear direction given by the Ministers and support for&#13;
&#13;
 these principles received from our bilateral partners,&#13;
&#13;
 NGOs, and colleagues from other multilateral institutions.&#13;
&#13;
 These shared and generic principles reflect our clear&#13;
&#13;
 understanding that unless the country itself takes&#13;
&#13;
 responsibility for its own long-term development, no&#13;
&#13;
 amount of outside assistance will be effective.        This&#13;
&#13;
 means that governments will have to define their&#13;
                                                                    Page12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 priorities, make the hard choices, ensure that they&#13;
&#13;
 generate wide support from representative voices of their&#13;
&#13;
 societies.   The Bretton Woods institutions, as the&#13;
&#13;
 countries' key development partners, should be ready to&#13;
&#13;
 offer all effective assistance in this process.&#13;
&#13;
           But given the enormity of the poverty challenge&#13;
&#13;
 facing us, I am also convinced that the Bank and the Fund&#13;
&#13;
 working closely together will be necessary but not&#13;
&#13;
 sufficient for the job that needs to be done.      We have to&#13;
&#13;
 rationalize and scale up the records of all the countries'&#13;
&#13;
 development partners to make a real difference.&#13;
&#13;
           We have tried to give operational expression to&#13;
&#13;
 these principles in the approach to poverty reduction that&#13;
&#13;
 we have outlined in the papers.       This will require that we&#13;
&#13;
 work differently but more effectively with development&#13;
&#13;
 partners and learn from each other as we follow the lead&#13;
&#13;
 of the countries' poverty strategy.&#13;
&#13;
           Finally, let me also observe that our focus on&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction also draws on a deep and analytical&#13;
&#13;
 understanding that we can no longer afford to view the&#13;
&#13;
 process of growth and poverty reduction in non-directional&#13;
&#13;
 terms.   As the recent Fund/Board paper on the Poverty&#13;
&#13;
 Reduction and Growth Facility notes, "The new approach&#13;
                                                                   Page13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 recognizes that not only is growth essential for poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction, but entrenched poverty and severe inequality in&#13;
&#13;
 economic opportunities and asset endowments can themselves&#13;
&#13;
 be impediments to growth.&#13;
&#13;
           The interlinkages between these processes are&#13;
&#13;
 explicitly recognized in the approach that we are&#13;
&#13;
 proposing in these papers, and I look forward to a very&#13;
&#13;
 stimulating discussion.&#13;
&#13;
           I also want to thank Ms. Piercy, Messrs.&#13;
&#13;
 Abraham, Niemi, Pickford, Stek and Wan Abdullah for their&#13;
&#13;
 statements which were circulated in advance.       Mr. Abraham&#13;
&#13;
 has revised his statement, and copies are being made.&#13;
&#13;
           Before proceeding to the discussion of the&#13;
&#13;
 Operational Issues paper, I'd like to take a moment to&#13;
&#13;
 review where we are in terms of the discussion of the&#13;
&#13;
 other papers related to PRSPs.      In addition to the&#13;
&#13;
 Operational Issues paper, we also discussed the "Update on&#13;
&#13;
 Costing the Enhanced HIP Initiative" at the Informal&#13;
&#13;
 Meeting of the Joint Boards of the IMF and Bank on&#13;
&#13;
 December 15th.   As the Update is an information, no&#13;
&#13;
 further discussion is needed.&#13;
&#13;
           On Thursday, December 16th, we met in an&#13;
&#13;
 Informal Meeting to discuss the "International Guidance&#13;
                                                                  Page14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 Note for PRSPs."   After Thursday's full discussion, no&#13;
&#13;
 further discussion is needed.&#13;
&#13;
           Also on December 16th, we discussed "HIPC - Note&#13;
&#13;
 on Modalities for Implementing HIPC Debt Relief under the&#13;
&#13;
 Enhanced Framework."    This Informal Meeting was resumed on&#13;
&#13;
 Friday, December 17, and we will meet formally to discuss&#13;
&#13;
 this paper sometime in January.&#13;
&#13;
           With this review, I think we can proceed to the&#13;
&#13;
 discussion of Operational Issues.        Ann Duncan, who is the&#13;
&#13;
 Adviser on Poverty Reduction Strategy Papers in the PREM&#13;
&#13;
 Network, will begin.    We also have with us Masood Ahmed;&#13;
&#13;
 Sarwar Lateef, who is a Senior Adviser; Mike Walton from&#13;
&#13;
 PREM; John Page, Peter Fallon, Joanne Salop, Ms. Montoliu-&#13;
&#13;
 Munoz, Axel van Trotsenburg and Sudhir Shetty.       So we have&#13;
&#13;
 enough people to answer all of your questions.&#13;
&#13;
           Let me ask Ann to start, please.&#13;
&#13;
           MS. DUNCAN:    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
           Management and staff would like to thank you for&#13;
&#13;
 the very constructive and supportive comments you have&#13;
&#13;
 made during our discussions on Poverty Reduction Strategy&#13;
&#13;
 Papers of the last few days.       We are very encouraged by&#13;
&#13;
 the level of your support for an approach which has the&#13;
&#13;
 potential to substantially improve the way the Bank and&#13;
                                                                   Page15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 Fund intend to support reducing poverty in the developing&#13;
&#13;
 world.&#13;
&#13;
            In addition to the comments you have made in the&#13;
&#13;
 Board meetings and the bilateral meetings we have held&#13;
&#13;
 with Executive Directors, we have also received written&#13;
&#13;
 comments, as Mr. Wolfensohn noted, from Messrs. Abraham,&#13;
&#13;
 Pickford, Stek, Niemi, Abdullah, and Ms. Piercy, for which&#13;
&#13;
 we thank you.&#13;
&#13;
            Most of the issues you have raised relate to&#13;
&#13;
 inherent tensions which are due to the competing&#13;
&#13;
 objectives set for the PRSP approach.           What we need,&#13;
&#13;
 therefore, is to find the right balance between these&#13;
&#13;
 objectives, both in design and more importantly in the&#13;
&#13;
 early implementation cases.       We seek your guidance on the&#13;
&#13;
 right balance or approach on the following issues that&#13;
&#13;
 have been raised.&#13;
&#13;
            First is the relationship between growth and&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction.     A number of Executive Directors&#13;
&#13;
 stressed the importance of ensuring that growth is pro-&#13;
&#13;
 poor.    While sustained poverty reduction will not be&#13;
&#13;
 possible without economic growth, the benefits of growth&#13;
&#13;
 have to be felt by the poor.&#13;
                                                                  Page16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           As the recent Fund/Board paper on the PRGF&#13;
&#13;
 notes, not only is growth essential for poverty reduction,&#13;
&#13;
 but entrenched poverty and severe inequality in economic&#13;
&#13;
 opportunities and asset endowments can themselves be&#13;
&#13;
 impediments to growth.&#13;
&#13;
           Assuring pro-poor growth will involve dealing&#13;
&#13;
 with the inequalities in assets that influence the extent&#13;
&#13;
 to which the poor participate in the growth process--for&#13;
&#13;
 example, inequalities in education, in land ownership, in&#13;
&#13;
 access to infrastructure that are in turn often related to&#13;
&#13;
 weak influence or lack of voice of the poor.&#13;
&#13;
           Although much of our analytical work has&#13;
&#13;
 recognized these relationships, we plan to be more&#13;
&#13;
 systematic in helping countries take account of these&#13;
&#13;
 interactions as they design the strategies, learning from&#13;
&#13;
 experience and incorporating the findings of the WDR&#13;
&#13;
 2000/2001.&#13;
&#13;
           Second is endorsement of the PRSP by the two&#13;
&#13;
 Boards.   A number of chairs have asked for more clarity on&#13;
&#13;
 exactly what this means.    The PRSP is a government&#13;
&#13;
 document which is considered by the two Boards because it&#13;
&#13;
 sets the context for the concessional assistance programs&#13;
&#13;
 of the Bank and the Fund.     Given the integrated nature of&#13;
                                                                Page17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 the country's poverty reduction strategy, the two Boards&#13;
&#13;
 would likely want to review the overall approach set out&#13;
&#13;
 in the PRSP, and they would be informed by the joint staff&#13;
&#13;
 assessment which would accompany the PRSP when it is&#13;
&#13;
 circulated to the Boards.&#13;
&#13;
            However, as the joint paper notes in paragraph&#13;
&#13;
 3, each Board would be asked to "endorse the PRSP insofar&#13;
&#13;
 as it relates to policies and programs supported by each&#13;
&#13;
 institution in its area of responsibility."        It is&#13;
&#13;
 important to emphasize that the word "endorsement" is not&#13;
&#13;
 intended in the legal sense of "approval" but rather to&#13;
&#13;
 provide guidance to Management and to provide an&#13;
&#13;
 opportunity for Board views to be taken fully into&#13;
&#13;
 account.&#13;
&#13;
            Next is the issue of speed of delivery of HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 debt relief or PRGF funding versus country ownership of a&#13;
&#13;
 participatory and effective PRSP.       As Directors have&#13;
&#13;
 noted, there is a tension between preparing participatory&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP documents which are country-owned and well-designed&#13;
&#13;
 versus avoiding delays for HIPC debt relief and PRGF&#13;
&#13;
 funding.&#13;
&#13;
            It is for this reason that staff have proposed a&#13;
&#13;
 transition period which will allow a country to reach its&#13;
                                                               Page18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 decision point provided that it can demonstrate a&#13;
&#13;
 commitment to poverty reduction.       This can be done through&#13;
&#13;
 an "interim" PRSP.&#13;
&#13;
           For the retroactive cases, there is a broad&#13;
&#13;
 sense that we should move forward expeditiously.      At last&#13;
&#13;
 week's Informal Meeting, staff suggested moving forward on&#13;
&#13;
 the basis of Option 2 described in paragraph 55, namely,&#13;
&#13;
 that a country could reach its completion point as early&#13;
&#13;
 as the adoption of a participatory PRSP, depending, of&#13;
&#13;
 course, on progress in policies and poverty reduction&#13;
&#13;
 strategies.&#13;
&#13;
           Key poverty outcomes prior to the completion&#13;
&#13;
 point could be specified in the interim PRSP against which&#13;
&#13;
 progress could be judged, and interim assistance could&#13;
&#13;
 again be provided.&#13;
&#13;
           A number of Executive Directors have called for&#13;
&#13;
 even faster delivery of enhanced debt relief, moving&#13;
&#13;
 toward Option 3 in the paper.      We would welcome further&#13;
&#13;
 guidance on this issue.&#13;
&#13;
           On our current plans, we hope to bring three&#13;
&#13;
 countries to their decision point in January--Bolivia,&#13;
&#13;
 Mauritania, and Uganda--with Mozambique brought to its&#13;
&#13;
 decision point shortly thereafter. We would also hope to&#13;
                                                                   Page19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 bring perhaps another four countries, depending on&#13;
&#13;
 progress in policies and implementation, to their decision&#13;
&#13;
 points in the subsequent quarter.&#13;
&#13;
           Next is the question of how can the adequacy of&#13;
&#13;
 the participatory process be judged.        Some Executive&#13;
&#13;
 Directors want the staff to make an explicit assessment,&#13;
&#13;
 while others judge this to be an essentially political&#13;
&#13;
 process that staff should not undertake.           Based on these&#13;
&#13;
 comments, we will explore whether the staff assessment&#13;
&#13;
 could go somewhat further by giving a somewhat more&#13;
&#13;
 structured description of the participatory process of the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP to inform the Board's judgment, drawing on advice on&#13;
&#13;
 good practice we are developing for the toolkit on&#13;
&#13;
 participatory processes.&#13;
&#13;
           However, I would stress that this is an area in&#13;
&#13;
 which early experience will be of great value in helping&#13;
&#13;
 to define precisely how far the staff assessment can&#13;
&#13;
 feasibly and usefully go.&#13;
&#13;
           Next is the issue of country ownership of the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP versus weak capacity in many poor countries.&#13;
&#13;
 Directors emphasized the demands that the introduction of&#13;
&#13;
 PRSPs impose on the already strained institutional&#13;
&#13;
 capacity of poor countries.     This has two implications.&#13;
                                                                     Page20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 First, it is crucial that a poverty reduction strategy be&#13;
&#13;
 embedded in the country's delivery systems.        In&#13;
&#13;
 particular, it should be incorporated into the&#13;
&#13;
 government's budget system.     Second, the Bank is aware of&#13;
&#13;
 the needs for capacity-building that this program would&#13;
&#13;
 generate; by proposing a gradual approach, starting with&#13;
&#13;
 interim PRSPs, and by offering to provide as much support&#13;
&#13;
 as needed and encourage the support from others, the Bank&#13;
&#13;
 expects that the potential pressure on countries would be&#13;
&#13;
 eased.&#13;
&#13;
           The role of Bank and Fund staff, as well as of&#13;
&#13;
 other donors, should be of a supportive nature.         As the&#13;
&#13;
 paper states, this implies a culture shift for Bank and&#13;
&#13;
 Fund staff, and it also implies a change in the way staff&#13;
&#13;
 would be evaluated.&#13;
&#13;
           Next is the issue of the role of other donors.&#13;
&#13;
 A number of Executive Directors welcomed the PRSP as a&#13;
&#13;
 potential instrument on which other donors could also base&#13;
&#13;
 their programs of assistance and which would facilitate&#13;
&#13;
 donor coordination.   We will encourage other partners and&#13;
&#13;
 aid agencies to participate and even take the lead where&#13;
&#13;
 they are better placed to do so.&#13;
                                                                  Page21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           Recipient countries should be free to choose on&#13;
&#13;
 whom to draw for assistance to produce the PRSP--for&#13;
&#13;
 example, the UNDP, bilateral agencies, regional&#13;
&#13;
 development banks, the EU.     As an example, this is a&#13;
&#13;
 central part of the agenda of the Working Group on Poverty&#13;
&#13;
 of the International Financial Institutes.         The Bank and&#13;
&#13;
 Fund met with the RDBs a week ago to discuss how to&#13;
&#13;
 cooperate on PRSP-related work.&#13;
&#13;
           Next is the issue of the costs of PRSPs.        It is&#13;
&#13;
 clear that the preparation of PRSPs is costly for the&#13;
&#13;
 countries concerned as well as for the Bank and Fund and&#13;
&#13;
 other donors supporting the process.        The countries will&#13;
&#13;
 need to collect data, set up consultation processes, and&#13;
&#13;
 build capacity wherever these are not adequate.        It is&#13;
&#13;
 therefore imperative to bring other partners into the&#13;
&#13;
 process early so they can assist the countries to meet&#13;
&#13;
 these additional costs.&#13;
&#13;
           Regarding the costs for the Bank, Management&#13;
&#13;
 plans to focus on redeployment this fiscal year, including&#13;
&#13;
 aligning ESW more closely with the PRSP work.        As noted in&#13;
&#13;
 the informal meeting, we will be monitoring the costs of&#13;
&#13;
 the initiative in the coming months and will report back&#13;
                                                                    Page22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 if we need to revisit the initial expectations about&#13;
&#13;
 redeployment.&#13;
&#13;
             For FY01 and beyond, we will return to this&#13;
&#13;
 subject as part of the Strategic Directions discussions in&#13;
&#13;
 the coming months.&#13;
&#13;
             Finally is the issue of IMF/Bank cooperation&#13;
&#13;
 versus undermining country ownership and the perception of&#13;
&#13;
 "ganging up" on countries.      We cannot have inconsistent&#13;
&#13;
 views between the Bank and the Fund, yet at the same time,&#13;
&#13;
 a firm, common initial position could undercut the&#13;
&#13;
 domestic process in developing a country-owned strategy.&#13;
&#13;
             We propose to manage this by getting a common&#13;
&#13;
 perspective that lays out the principles and issues as&#13;
&#13;
 seen by the Bank and the Fund, without laying out a&#13;
&#13;
 specific position.&#13;
&#13;
             You have also raised a number of other points of&#13;
&#13;
 guidance which we will take into account in the&#13;
&#13;
 implementation process and in any future revisions to&#13;
&#13;
 guidance for staff.&#13;
&#13;
             Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. WOLFENSOHN:   Thank you very much for&#13;
&#13;
 reviewing the issues that have come out of recent&#13;
&#13;
 meetings.&#13;
                                                                Page23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           Let me also welcome Tony Boote, an Assistant&#13;
&#13;
 Directors; Russell Kincaid, Assistant Director of the&#13;
&#13;
 Policy Development and Review Department; and David&#13;
&#13;
 Andrews, Senior Economist, who are joining us from the&#13;
&#13;
 Fund.   We are very   happy to see you here.&#13;
&#13;
           Let me now start the list.&#13;
&#13;
           Mr. Hubloue, please.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. HUBLOUE:   Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
           I am happy that on the basis of the excellent&#13;
&#13;
 staff preparations, and after last week's informal&#13;
&#13;
 discussions, we are today in a position to give our formal&#13;
&#13;
 support to the launch of the PRSP process.&#13;
&#13;
           While the discussions of last week indicated&#13;
&#13;
 that the link between the PRSP and many of our existing&#13;
&#13;
 processes and instruments--CDF, CAS, and so on--will have&#13;
&#13;
 to be clarified as we learn from experience, I believe&#13;
&#13;
 these discussions have also highlighted that we may here&#13;
&#13;
 before us have the so-called missing link between the CDF&#13;
&#13;
 process based on principles now widely endorsed by the&#13;
&#13;
 international development community and, on the other&#13;
&#13;
 hand, the operational programs which should translate&#13;
&#13;
 these principles into effective and sustained poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction.&#13;
                                                              Page24&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
             From that perspective, I think we should expect&#13;
&#13;
 that there should be serious commitment and even a good&#13;
&#13;
 deal of enthusiasm to make this challenging approach work.&#13;
&#13;
 Our task will be to mobilize that positive energy and to&#13;
&#13;
 sustain it over a sufficiently long period of time.       I&#13;
&#13;
 think that that is important because, as you said in the&#13;
&#13;
 introductory remarks which were prepared for you, it is&#13;
&#13;
 going to be a bumpy road, but I would almost say that I&#13;
&#13;
 hope it will be a bumpy road, because the main risk for me&#13;
&#13;
 would be that the process would soon elapse into a kind of&#13;
&#13;
 bureaucratic process in which it will be impossible to&#13;
&#13;
 meet the expectations that we all have for this new&#13;
&#13;
 approach.&#13;
&#13;
             In that connection, let me make three brief&#13;
&#13;
 comments on the following issues--first, on transitional&#13;
&#13;
 arrangements; second, on resource implications; and third,&#13;
&#13;
 on the role of the Board.&#13;
&#13;
             On transitional arrangements, it is clear to me&#13;
&#13;
 that an early start soon to be followed by visible results&#13;
&#13;
 will be a critical factor in establishing the initial&#13;
&#13;
 credibility of the whole process.        I agree with everything&#13;
&#13;
 that Pieter Stek has said in that connection in his&#13;
&#13;
 written statement under the heading "Substance of&#13;
                                                                    Page25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 Process."    Indeed, I believe that countries with a good&#13;
&#13;
 track record on the implementation of a comprehensive&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction strategy should not be requested to&#13;
&#13;
 start everything all over again according to the book.      A&#13;
&#13;
 credible commitment to further deepening of their strategy&#13;
&#13;
 based on satisfactory past performance should for these&#13;
&#13;
 countries be a sufficient condition to unlock the&#13;
&#13;
 international support that goes with a strong PRSP.&#13;
&#13;
             More specifically, it should not be ruled out&#13;
&#13;
 that a number of the retroactive HIPC cases meet these&#13;
&#13;
 conditions.    Subject to the availability of sufficient&#13;
&#13;
 funding resources, these cases should have access to&#13;
&#13;
 retroactive HIPC financing upon production of their&#13;
&#13;
 interim PRSP.&#13;
&#13;
             All in all, we can therefore support Option 3 in&#13;
&#13;
 paragraph 56 of the document and propose that for as many&#13;
&#13;
 countries as possible, we try to proceed by following the&#13;
&#13;
 proposals laid out in that option.&#13;
&#13;
             Second, on resource implications, there, I&#13;
&#13;
 believe we will from the outside commit ourselves to&#13;
&#13;
 keeping this aspect of the whole process under review,&#13;
&#13;
 with an open mind.    Frankly, I cannot imagine that during&#13;
&#13;
 the start-up phase of the initiative, especially the&#13;
                                                                 Page26&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 Africa Region and most of the African countries, would not&#13;
&#13;
 face significant resource and capacity constraints.&#13;
&#13;
 Without proper and constructive monitoring of this&#13;
&#13;
 situation, these constraints may either affect the quality&#13;
&#13;
 of the PRSP process, especially the ownership of it, or&#13;
&#13;
 they may erode the pipeline of future lending operations&#13;
&#13;
 which should follow the presentation of a valid PRSP.&#13;
&#13;
           Specifically, I would propose that soon after&#13;
&#13;
 next month's consultations with the African governments on&#13;
&#13;
 the PRSP process, we have an informal follow-up meeting on&#13;
&#13;
 this critical aspect with the Africa Region, so that from&#13;
&#13;
 the outset, we can learn and have a fairly good perception&#13;
&#13;
 of what we are up to.&#13;
&#13;
           Donor resources to support the process,&#13;
&#13;
 especially the in-country process, will have to be&#13;
&#13;
 mobilized to the maximum extent.       I believe Pieter Stek&#13;
&#13;
 has also made a number of valid comments there.&#13;
&#13;
           I also would perhaps propose, or would not rule&#13;
&#13;
 out, that at some point, it may be useful that especially&#13;
&#13;
 for the limitations that the countries themselves are&#13;
&#13;
 going to meet, a sufficient share of resources which are&#13;
&#13;
 being allocated under the PACT Initiative may have to be&#13;
&#13;
 reallocated or devoted especially to help the countries&#13;
                                                                Page27&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 build up the necessary capacity to participate in that&#13;
&#13;
 process.   Indeed, I believe there are potentially&#13;
&#13;
 important synergies between, let's say, the countries'&#13;
&#13;
 participation in the PRSP process and the whole spirit of&#13;
&#13;
 the PACT Initiative which was approved a couple of months&#13;
&#13;
 ago.&#13;
&#13;
            Third, on the implications of the PRSP process&#13;
&#13;
 for the Board, these implications may seem of little&#13;
&#13;
 significance compared to the efforts that are going to be&#13;
&#13;
 expected from all other players in the game, I believe we&#13;
&#13;
 should also as a Board from the beginning learn from&#13;
&#13;
 experimentation and be fully aware of how we are expected&#13;
&#13;
 to participate in the whole process.&#13;
&#13;
            I believe indeed that the quality of the&#13;
&#13;
 dialogue in the Board which should take place at the&#13;
&#13;
 occasion of the Board presentation of the PRSP process&#13;
&#13;
 will over time become a significant element in sustaining&#13;
&#13;
 the momentum of the whole process, because it is at that&#13;
&#13;
 level that institutional signals are being given about&#13;
&#13;
 what we expect and how this whole process should fit into&#13;
&#13;
 the Bank's program.&#13;
&#13;
            On this point, I believe it is fair to&#13;
&#13;
 acknowledge that this Board has no culture of formulating&#13;
                                                             Page28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 strong collective views on the validity of countries'&#13;
&#13;
 development programs, especially if they are not directly&#13;
&#13;
 related to the scenarios and triggers for Bank lending&#13;
&#13;
 programs.    We can, I believe, in this respect not ignore&#13;
&#13;
 the experience from the PFP process on which in 1995, it&#13;
&#13;
 was decided that the Board should no longer discuss these&#13;
&#13;
 papers, probably because the Board had already lost&#13;
&#13;
 interest in doing so for a number of years.&#13;
&#13;
             The challenge to do different at this time is&#13;
&#13;
 even bigger, because the substance to be covered is so&#13;
&#13;
 much more complex.    We have to learn to listen carefully&#13;
&#13;
 to what countries have to tell us in their PRSPs before&#13;
&#13;
 speaking up on their validity, and our discussions will&#13;
&#13;
 need to be focused in order to be productive.&#13;
&#13;
             I would not rule out that soon after we have&#13;
&#13;
 discussed the first series of PRSPs in the Board that it&#13;
&#13;
 would be useful to take stock also at the level of the&#13;
&#13;
 Board and develop progressively in consultation with&#13;
&#13;
 Management a reference list of those topics on which it is&#13;
&#13;
 felt that we as a Board can make the most productive&#13;
&#13;
 collective contribution to the whole process.&#13;
&#13;
             Let me end with two more specific comments on&#13;
&#13;
 the final stages of the PRSP process.          First, I note from&#13;
                                                                     Page29&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 paragraph 34 of the document that in general, PRSPs will&#13;
&#13;
 be finalized for presentation to the Board only after they&#13;
&#13;
 have been refined or modified to the point at which&#13;
&#13;
 Management feels comfortable to recommend them for&#13;
&#13;
 endorsement.    This is the way we usually proceed.   I can&#13;
&#13;
 live with that approach, but I believe that it will also&#13;
&#13;
 be consistent with the whole spirit of the exercise,&#13;
&#13;
 especially with our desire to maintain ownership of the&#13;
&#13;
 country all along the process and that these discussions&#13;
&#13;
 on final negotiations on how the PRSP will be prepared at&#13;
&#13;
 these discussions will be reflected in the documents&#13;
&#13;
 presented to the Board.&#13;
&#13;
             Second--and there, it has become clear that we&#13;
&#13;
 still have some issues to be discussed from the&#13;
&#13;
 introductory remarks--I am indeed not convinced that we&#13;
&#13;
 should adopt the proposal to have the Board make judgments&#13;
&#13;
 on the quality of the participatory process without&#13;
&#13;
 benefitting from the staff's assessment of this aspect of&#13;
&#13;
 the PRSP.    If the quality of the participation is&#13;
&#13;
 considered to be among the key factors of a sustained and&#13;
&#13;
 comprehensive poverty reduction, I believe the Board's&#13;
&#13;
 views on it will certainly benefit from a balanced,&#13;
&#13;
 country-based Management perspective.&#13;
                                                               Page30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           If Management feels that it is not in a position&#13;
&#13;
 to give that perspective because the issue is in its view&#13;
&#13;
 too political, I think we should refrain from involving&#13;
&#13;
 the Board in it, because then it is certainly going to be&#13;
&#13;
 political.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. WOLFENSOHN:      Thank you for those thoughtful&#13;
&#13;
 comments, Mr. Hubloue.&#13;
&#13;
           Mr. Holden?&#13;
&#13;
           MR. HOLDEN:     I am on the whole very supportive&#13;
&#13;
 of the proposed approach even if quite nervous about&#13;
&#13;
 whether we will be able to meet the enormous challenge of&#13;
&#13;
 achieving what is a very multifaceted objective for a&#13;
&#13;
 strategy that is at the same time useful, focused and&#13;
&#13;
 genuinely country-owned.&#13;
&#13;
           I want to reiterate the comments that are&#13;
&#13;
 already in the written statements and Luc's comments and&#13;
&#13;
 discussion last week, that we do need to be flexible and&#13;
&#13;
 accommodating as we move forward and must in that context&#13;
&#13;
 very much accept the "learning-by-doing," iterative nature&#13;
&#13;
 of this exercise.&#13;
&#13;
           I think we have also got to accept the reality&#13;
&#13;
 of highly subjective judgments in terms of both the&#13;
                                                                 Page31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 process, including the participatory process by which&#13;
&#13;
 PRSPs are formulated, and the content of them.       There is a&#13;
&#13;
 real discipline, I think, for all of us here to avoid&#13;
&#13;
 being too quick to substitute our values for those of our&#13;
&#13;
 member countries.&#13;
&#13;
             I want very much to focus my comments this&#13;
&#13;
 morning on the issue of endorsement and of the nexus&#13;
&#13;
 between the completed or interim PRSP and the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
 assistance program, because I think that is the part that&#13;
&#13;
 I am least comfortable with that we have gotten the&#13;
&#13;
 clarity we need.&#13;
&#13;
             As many people have noted, there is a real&#13;
&#13;
 tension between the principle of genuine ownership and the&#13;
&#13;
 notion of multilateral or bilateral endorsement of a&#13;
&#13;
 strategy.    I take the comments about not meaning&#13;
&#13;
 "endorsement" here in the strict legal sense, but the word&#13;
&#13;
 certainly carries a lot of baggage with it, I think.&#13;
&#13;
             To a large extent, of course, the tensions are&#13;
&#13;
 inevitable.    It is both inevitable and, I think,&#13;
&#13;
 ultimately quite desirable that donors will determine the&#13;
&#13;
 nature and quantum of the assistance they are prepared to&#13;
&#13;
 offer on the basis of country actions and intentions.&#13;
                                                                   Page32&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
            I would also say that armed with our new, richer&#13;
&#13;
 sense of the importance of adopting a comprehensive&#13;
&#13;
 approach to development, it seems to me both impractical&#13;
&#13;
 and undesirable to try and narrow our focus to some notion&#13;
&#13;
 of the Bank's or the Fund's particular concerns.       I agree&#13;
&#13;
 with Jan Piercy's comments on that point.&#13;
&#13;
            But we must also recognize that highly&#13;
&#13;
 prescriptive approaches to conditionality and so on, with&#13;
&#13;
 the implications of genuine ownership, have largely been&#13;
&#13;
 ignored in practice and have not been successful.       On the&#13;
&#13;
 one hand, countries have not taken real responsibility for&#13;
&#13;
 the policies proposed, and equally as important on the&#13;
&#13;
 other, the donor community has been understandably very&#13;
&#13;
 reluctant to deliver on the threat that conditionality&#13;
&#13;
 implies.&#13;
&#13;
            I think the proposed approach to endorsement of&#13;
&#13;
 PRSPs and the assistance that might flow from is&#13;
&#13;
 vulnerable on at least two counts.        First, endorsement&#13;
&#13;
 with its implication of grading country efforts may I&#13;
&#13;
 think undermine our efforts to turn over a new leaf with&#13;
&#13;
 respect to the notion of ownership.&#13;
&#13;
            Second and somewhat paradoxically, the to date&#13;
&#13;
 somewhat fuzzy link between endorsement and our specific&#13;
                                                                  Page33&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 lending and nonlending program could be both too loose and&#13;
&#13;
 too rigid--too loose in that if consideration of a PRSP&#13;
&#13;
 takes place without a very clear sense of the consequences&#13;
&#13;
 in terms of the quality and quantity of assistance, then I&#13;
&#13;
 think both the country and the Bank or the Bank Board may&#13;
&#13;
 be uncertain about the relevance of the PRSP exercise, and&#13;
&#13;
 it may fall into the kind of neglect that previous&#13;
&#13;
 attempts have--put bluntly, both the country and the Board&#13;
&#13;
 may see the real action as in another place and another&#13;
&#13;
 time--and too rigid in that countries may also see&#13;
&#13;
 endorsement of their PRSP as both a necessary and a&#13;
&#13;
 sufficient condition for access to the high-lending case&#13;
&#13;
 nirvana.   I don't think we would see the PRSP in any sense&#13;
&#13;
 as the end of the road.&#13;
&#13;
            Now, in many respects, this is an issue of&#13;
&#13;
 semantics, but I wonder if both of the problems I have&#13;
&#13;
 outlined might be ameliorated to some extent were we to&#13;
&#13;
 desist from endorsing PRSPs as such and instead, rather,&#13;
&#13;
 note them, while at the same time using the joint&#13;
&#13;
 assessment that is proposed to more formally respond to&#13;
&#13;
 the country's PRSP.   In a sense, I think this is what is&#13;
&#13;
 meant anyway, but I think it is a case where terminology&#13;
&#13;
 is going to be quite important.&#13;
                                                               Page34&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           It seems to me that the assessment might indeed&#13;
&#13;
 be seen as a core or significant part of the Bank's CAS&#13;
&#13;
 but would in any event give them a much more concrete&#13;
&#13;
 sense of the Bank's program going forward.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. WOLFENSOHN:    Well, thank you very much, Mr.&#13;
&#13;
 Holden.&#13;
&#13;
           Mr. Haque?&#13;
&#13;
           MR. HAQUE:   Mr. Chairman, thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
           The Poverty Reduction Strategy Papers in my view&#13;
&#13;
 mark an exceedingly significant landmark in our endeavors&#13;
&#13;
 to translate into operational reality our central mission&#13;
&#13;
 and overarching vision.&#13;
&#13;
           It was said long ago that a tree is not really&#13;
&#13;
 known by its roots, but by its fruits.         What shape our&#13;
&#13;
 aspirations assume in terms of attainment is a real test.&#13;
&#13;
 Promises, Mr. Chairman, remain academic unless transformed&#13;
&#13;
 into performance, and performance is possible only if&#13;
&#13;
 there is a well-thought-out road map.         Preparation of this&#13;
&#13;
 road map in the context of poverty reduction is indeed&#13;
&#13;
 important and significant.     The Bank and Fund staff&#13;
&#13;
 deserve our sincerest thanks and appreciation for this&#13;
&#13;
 collaborative effort, for this productive joint venture.&#13;
                                                                     Page35&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           I should also like to thank the management of&#13;
&#13;
 both these institutions for providing leadership and&#13;
&#13;
 guidance to staff and a refreshing willingness to join&#13;
&#13;
 hands in this crusade against poverty.          Convening the&#13;
&#13;
 joint meetings of the Boards of the Bank and Fund was a&#13;
&#13;
 very welcome manifestation of this new order, this new&#13;
&#13;
 dispensation.&#13;
&#13;
           It should, however, be realized that this is an&#13;
&#13;
 ongoing process.   There can be no finality claimed for it.&#13;
&#13;
 It is a matter, as Pieter Stek says, of continuous debate.&#13;
&#13;
 Moreover, it must be viewed in the overall context of the&#13;
&#13;
 Comprehensive Development Framework.         I have read&#13;
&#13;
 somewhere it has been stated that the strategy papers, or&#13;
&#13;
 the thinking behind them, are consistent with the&#13;
&#13;
 Comprehensive Development Framework.         I don't think this&#13;
&#13;
 is the right way of putting it.        We may say that it is a&#13;
&#13;
 manifestation of the CDF and not mere consistency with it.&#13;
&#13;
           It has been realized and I think it will&#13;
&#13;
 continue to be realized that the PRSP is not a blueprint;&#13;
&#13;
 it is not a detailed prescription but a process or&#13;
&#13;
 compass, and it will be built on existing thinking.&#13;
&#13;
           The principles set out in Box 1 appear to be as&#13;
&#13;
 sound and acceptable, and I don't propose any change at&#13;
                                                                   Page36&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 this moment.   Let us learn by doing and modify whatever we&#13;
&#13;
 want to do in the area of the principles in light of&#13;
&#13;
 experience on the ground and further analytical work.&#13;
&#13;
           I therefore think that reviewing this&#13;
&#13;
 periodically, with the first review in 2001, is a very&#13;
&#13;
 sound idea, although I agree with Stephen Pickford that we&#13;
&#13;
 must recognize the importance of such strategy reflected&#13;
&#13;
 in the country's delivery system.&#13;
&#13;
           I find one of the most important features of the&#13;
&#13;
 strategy is the clear option by both institutions for pro-&#13;
&#13;
 poor growth as against mere growth.        Of course, growth&#13;
&#13;
 must be shared, and benefits must go to the poor.       Of&#13;
&#13;
 course, it need not be emphasized that without sustained&#13;
&#13;
 growth, there can be no reductio of poverty, but as has&#13;
&#13;
 been pointed out, poverty itself is an impediment in the&#13;
&#13;
 path of growth.&#13;
&#13;
           I also find that sound principles like the&#13;
&#13;
 participation of civil society, the interim PRSPs, the&#13;
&#13;
 need for flexibility, and above all, the country-driven&#13;
&#13;
 nature, are welcome and commendable.&#13;
&#13;
           I propose, Mr. Chairman, to briefly touch on two&#13;
&#13;
 or three points in specific.      One is the issue of&#13;
                                                                Page37&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 ownership; second is the role of the two Boards; and the&#13;
&#13;
 third is conditionality.&#13;
&#13;
           Coming to the question of ownership, Mr.&#13;
&#13;
 Chairman, I have been hearing this phrase not only in this&#13;
&#13;
 Board, but I have come across this rubric long ago when I&#13;
&#13;
 was in the field.    But when I contrasted the reality of&#13;
&#13;
 this, I was always disappointed.         Ownership most of the&#13;
&#13;
 time has been an optical illusion.          It has not been real.&#13;
&#13;
 It has not been genuine.&#13;
&#13;
           I would like to be reassured that now we are&#13;
&#13;
 going ahead with the transformation of this idea, that&#13;
&#13;
 this will be a genuine ownership.         We should not have&#13;
&#13;
 ownership which is sort of a product of paternal guidance,&#13;
&#13;
 not a manifestation of what I would call Confucian&#13;
&#13;
 syndrome, which syndrome is that we know better, that we&#13;
&#13;
 are wiser than the people.       That has to be given up, and&#13;
&#13;
 it requires great effort, Mr. Chairman; it is not easy.&#13;
&#13;
 This is ingrained.     People who know more or think they&#13;
&#13;
 know more are naturally not going to give up this idea, so&#13;
&#13;
 this requires humility, and it also requires an&#13;
&#13;
 appreciation that there can be more than one way of doing&#13;
&#13;
 things.   And this would require a continuous effort to&#13;
&#13;
 change the culture of poverty.        I do realize, Mr.&#13;
                                                                     Page38&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 Chairman, that you have a genuine commitment to this, but&#13;
&#13;
 I hope this genuine commitment will percolate down to the&#13;
&#13;
 staff of both institutions when they are dealing with the&#13;
&#13;
 problems.&#13;
&#13;
             On the ownership, again, I find it a little&#13;
&#13;
 problematic.    There is a danger which I expressed the&#13;
&#13;
 other day at the joint meeting, that when two powerful&#13;
&#13;
 institutions like the World Bank and the IMF come&#13;
&#13;
 together, it is like two gladiators coming together,&#13;
&#13;
 trying to teach a small pygmy how to improve body-&#13;
&#13;
 building.    The whole process can be very, very difficult--&#13;
&#13;
 overpowering and overwhelming.       So we will have to ensure-&#13;
&#13;
 -and this can be done by a continuous drilling in the&#13;
&#13;
 minds of people that, look, ownership has to be&#13;
&#13;
 recognized.    Without genuine ownership, I am afraid these&#13;
&#13;
 strategies will never see that sort of fruition and&#13;
&#13;
 completion which we require.&#13;
&#13;
             Then, we come to the role of the two Boards.&#13;
&#13;
 This question was also raised by the senior Deputy&#13;
&#13;
 Managing Director of the Fund, and I find that we must try&#13;
&#13;
 to answer it, but questions have been raised very rightly&#13;
&#13;
 by my colleague, Wan Abdullah, in this when he said:       "In&#13;
&#13;
 terms of Board presentation, we wonder how the&#13;
                                                                   Page39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 arrangements will work in the event the views of the two&#13;
&#13;
 Boards differ.   Which Board makes the primary decision,&#13;
&#13;
 thereby setting the overriding framework?"&#13;
&#13;
           And similarly, Jan Piercy also very wisely&#13;
&#13;
 raised this point and talked about whether the strategy is&#13;
&#13;
 an integral strategy or if we can take it as a segmented&#13;
&#13;
 thing.&#13;
&#13;
           Mr. Chairman, in this context also is the&#13;
&#13;
 question of endorsement.    I have been very happy and a&#13;
&#13;
 little bit reassured by learning that endorsement is not&#13;
&#13;
 being used in terms of a technical approval, because that,&#13;
&#13;
 I think, would be very unfortunate.        That would be&#13;
&#13;
 striking at the concept of ownership from the very&#13;
&#13;
 beginning.&#13;
&#13;
           So endorsement could be sort of a support, one&#13;
&#13;
 might say, and we may live with this phrase unless a&#13;
&#13;
 better phrase is thought of.&#13;
&#13;
           But what can be done about the endorsement by&#13;
&#13;
 two Boards?   May I come along with an idea which is&#13;
&#13;
 somewhat unorthodox, something which represents a change&#13;
&#13;
 in my own thinking?   My feeling would be that endorsement&#13;
&#13;
 could be done--we call it "endorsement," within inverted&#13;
&#13;
 commas--by a meeting of joint Boards.         The Boards of IMF&#13;
                                                                   Page40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 and the World Bank, as they met the other day, should come&#13;
&#13;
 together.    We must make the deliberation manageable, and&#13;
&#13;
 it can be done so that there is only one intervention from&#13;
&#13;
 one constituency.    We are represented both in the Fund and&#13;
&#13;
 in the Bank, so both of the Executive Directors need not&#13;
&#13;
 speak; one of them can speak.        That would also bring about&#13;
&#13;
 a unity of thinking of shareholders.&#13;
&#13;
             So I would submit it for consideration that this&#13;
&#13;
 sort of endorsement--and this will become more informal&#13;
&#13;
 also, because if you do it in separate Boards, it will&#13;
&#13;
 become more formal--it will become less formal as well.&#13;
&#13;
 So this is something which I would just present as food&#13;
&#13;
 for thought.&#13;
&#13;
             Thank you very much, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. WOLFENSOHN:    I think that that last&#13;
&#13;
 suggestion is one that the Board should consider and&#13;
&#13;
 deliberate on, on the issues of a joint meeting with your&#13;
&#13;
 colleagues at the Fund.       I think they are done informally,&#13;
&#13;
 and I think it is for you to consider.           On the question of&#13;
&#13;
 ownership, I think we do have a long way to go in terms of&#13;
&#13;
 seeing how it works.     I think ownership is important.       It&#13;
&#13;
 does not mean that any requirements that the Bank or Fund&#13;
&#13;
 might perceive to be necessary to get an appropriate&#13;
                                                                       Page41&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 strategy need to be thrown out the window.         What it means&#13;
&#13;
 is that we should not have in cement what it is we want&#13;
&#13;
 but that there should be a dialogue with the countries and&#13;
&#13;
 that the countries absolutely free, and it is appropriate&#13;
&#13;
 that they should conduct their reviews of the poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction strategy in their own way and with complete&#13;
&#13;
 ownership.   If, however, they were to come up with a--this&#13;
&#13;
 is my personal perception--if they were to come up with&#13;
&#13;
 something that was new and innovative that we hadn't&#13;
&#13;
 thought of, and we want to accept, that would be great.&#13;
&#13;
 On the other hand, if they leave gaping holes in things&#13;
&#13;
 that this Board might want to be included, we would be&#13;
&#13;
 entitled to go back and on an equal basis say to them we&#13;
&#13;
 think that this approach is fascinating, interesting, but&#13;
&#13;
 it doesn't meet the requirements of the Board.        That is&#13;
&#13;
 something that I think is the logic of the negotiation.&#13;
&#13;
 It doesn't mean that the Board has to accept whatever it&#13;
&#13;
 is that the country brings forward.        They may bring&#13;
&#13;
 forward a fantastic and innovative and remarkable&#13;
&#13;
 response; they may bring forward something that is&#13;
&#13;
 lamentable and doesn't meet our needs.         I think that that&#13;
&#13;
 is perfectly appropriate that we should be able to take&#13;
&#13;
 the judgment of the Board.     I think that what is important&#13;
                                                                    Page42&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 is that the country should be in the driver's seat to try&#13;
&#13;
 to conduct their strategy, and it is our intent that we&#13;
&#13;
 should help them do that and be supportive.&#13;
&#13;
           So I think the question of ownership is&#13;
&#13;
 something that we are going to have to feel our way into.&#13;
&#13;
 I think the motion that you put forward of two gladiators&#13;
&#13;
 coming in and crushing a pygmy is certainly not my concept&#13;
&#13;
 of how this is, nor is my concept that we have to throw&#13;
&#13;
 away any ideas that we have about what is important in a&#13;
&#13;
 Poverty Reduction Strategy Paper.&#13;
&#13;
           I think it is a question of having equal&#13;
&#13;
 dialogue but being clear that the ownership and control&#13;
&#13;
 and direction of the strategy paper should be in the hands&#13;
&#13;
 of the government concerned.      I think that that is&#13;
&#13;
 something that we will learn about as we move forward.&#13;
&#13;
           Mr. Kamitomai?&#13;
&#13;
           MR. KAMITOMAI:    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
           We would like to join other colleagues in&#13;
&#13;
 commending the staff of both institutions for this&#13;
&#13;
 excellent work.   We also welcome a series of informal&#13;
&#13;
 discussions, including the joint Board discussion, to help&#13;
&#13;
 us deepen our understanding.      We are supportive of the&#13;
&#13;
 thrust of the proposal.&#13;
                                                              Page43&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
            Since we already had the occasion to discuss the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP, I would like to limit my comments to the following&#13;
&#13;
 five issues.     The first is on the nature of the PRSP and&#13;
&#13;
 the way forward.&#13;
&#13;
            As I have pointed out in a previous statement,&#13;
&#13;
 there still seems to be no clear consensus on the nature&#13;
&#13;
 of the PRSP and what the Board is supposed to endorse&#13;
&#13;
 and/or approve.    While we consider that we can go forward,&#13;
&#13;
 we hope that we can make this issue clearer in our&#13;
&#13;
 exercises.&#13;
&#13;
            In discussing the PRSP at the Board, we think it&#13;
&#13;
 is useful to discuss implications to Bank operations at&#13;
&#13;
 the same time.    Hence, it is desirable to discuss the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP, to     ?    its assessment paper and the CAS that&#13;
&#13;
 stems from the PRSP.     In this vein, we would like to ask&#13;
&#13;
 Management to make efforts in gradually integrating this&#13;
&#13;
 document into the overall process.          In forming the PRSP,&#13;
&#13;
 consultation with the recipient government is&#13;
&#13;
 indispensable, but we hope that the work will proceed&#13;
&#13;
 promptly so that we can provide the expanded HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 Initiative without delay.&#13;
&#13;
            We also hope that non-HIPC countries would also&#13;
&#13;
 demonstrate strong ownership in the PRSP process.&#13;
                                                                    Page44&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           Second is on judging the adequacy of the&#13;
&#13;
 participatory process.     Participation is at the core of&#13;
&#13;
 the PRSP framework and takes place at its design,&#13;
&#13;
 implementation and monitoring stage.         It is obviously the&#13;
&#13;
 key to the success of the framework.         The Bank has&#13;
&#13;
 substantial experience in participation through conducting&#13;
&#13;
 participatory CG and the CAS, and we hope that the&#13;
&#13;
 Management will provide advice to the recipient government&#13;
&#13;
 drawing from its best practices.&#13;
&#13;
           Given the importance of participation and the&#13;
&#13;
 fact that Management is well-informed of the process in&#13;
&#13;
 the field, we think that Management can effectively&#13;
&#13;
 provide comments on the participatory process in the PRSP&#13;
&#13;
 assessment.   However, in doing so, we think it is&#13;
&#13;
 important to take into account the country-specific&#13;
&#13;
 circumstances and not apply an in-home standard.&#13;
&#13;
           Third is regarding the PRSP and the enhanced&#13;
&#13;
 HIPC Initiative.   In order to ensure the linkage between&#13;
&#13;
 debt relief and poverty alleviation, we believe it is&#13;
&#13;
 important for the HIPCs to have at least an interim PRSP&#13;
&#13;
 at the decision point and demonstrate progress on the&#13;
&#13;
 implementation of the PRSP by the completion point.         For&#13;
&#13;
 such viewpoint, we think it is necessary to have at least&#13;
                                                                    Page45&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 a satisfactory first annual progress report before the&#13;
&#13;
 completion point, as stated in the paper.           However, in the&#13;
&#13;
 case of retroactive countries that continue to demonstrate&#13;
&#13;
 strong performance, adoption of the PRSP will be a&#13;
&#13;
 sufficient condition for the completion point.          In other&#13;
&#13;
 words, we rather favor Option 2 in the staff paper.&#13;
&#13;
           Fourth is on links to Bank lending.          This chair&#13;
&#13;
 supports the idea of linking performance and the PRSP and&#13;
&#13;
 Bank lending.    However, IDA lending has been allocated&#13;
&#13;
 based on performance ratings such as portfolio performance&#13;
&#13;
 assessment and CPIA.    We hope that such methodology will&#13;
&#13;
 be reflected in the design of the PRSP of each country.&#13;
&#13;
           Fifth is regarding the importance of ownership&#13;
&#13;
 of the recipient government.&#13;
&#13;
           Finally, I understand that this PRSP framework&#13;
&#13;
 in front of us was created under the Bank and Fund&#13;
&#13;
 initiative, but in order for this framework to be owned by&#13;
&#13;
 the recipient government, the Management needs to put most&#13;
&#13;
 emphasis on consultation with the recipient government in&#13;
&#13;
 coming months.   Along with ownership of the recipient&#13;
&#13;
 government, the work by regional development banks and&#13;
&#13;
 other donor agencies could be efficiently integrated into&#13;
&#13;
 the process of PRSP formulation.&#13;
                                                                       Page46&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. WOLFENSOHN:    Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           Mr. Singh?&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SINGH:    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
           We really welcome this opportunity        to discuss&#13;
&#13;
 this imaginative and well-thought-out document on poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction.   We welcome this because we do feel that&#13;
&#13;
 despite the commendable efforts by national governments,&#13;
&#13;
 the Bank, the Fund, the NGOs, the private sector and&#13;
&#13;
 others, the number of people living on a dollar a day is&#13;
&#13;
 on the rise, and therefore, they need to have a fresh and&#13;
&#13;
 imaginative look at the arrangements.         This PRSP paper&#13;
&#13;
 will help us in that direction.&#13;
&#13;
           I would like to confine my comments to four&#13;
&#13;
 aspects of the paper.    The first is country ownership; the&#13;
&#13;
 second is the need for flexibility of approach; the third&#13;
&#13;
 is the cost of preparation of PRSP papers; and the fourth&#13;
&#13;
 is the relationship between the CAS and the PRSP and&#13;
&#13;
 between the CAS, the CDF and PRSP.&#13;
&#13;
           Mr. Chairman, we support that PRSPs should be&#13;
&#13;
 country-driven, and the contents and the strategies to&#13;
&#13;
 reduce poverty should be left to the government concerned.&#13;
&#13;
 Although in many countries, the national governments do&#13;
                                                                  Page47&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 have a well-defined strategy for government--we may call&#13;
&#13;
 it a five-year plan or a strategic plan or a vision&#13;
&#13;
 document--the Poverty Reduction Strategy Paper will enable&#13;
&#13;
 the government to focus its attention sharply to wage a&#13;
&#13;
 decisive war against poverty.&#13;
&#13;
           Each country, Mr. Chairman, thus has a vision--a&#13;
&#13;
 history with strong points and shortcomings.       It also has&#13;
&#13;
 limited or extended room for the private sector and NGOs,&#13;
&#13;
 and it also has, in the majority of countries, certain&#13;
&#13;
 democratic institutions, parliament, legislative bodies,&#13;
&#13;
 and so on.&#13;
&#13;
           Therefore, the preparation of this paper should&#13;
&#13;
 be left to the country concerned.       The joint missions from&#13;
&#13;
 the Bank and Fund would give advice to the government and&#13;
&#13;
 would also involve themselves in the preparation of the&#13;
&#13;
 document--subject, naturally, to that concerned&#13;
&#13;
 government's approval.    The mission could also give its&#13;
&#13;
 comments on the content and effectiveness of the strategy&#13;
&#13;
 prepared by the government, as well as the nature of the&#13;
&#13;
 participatory process involved in preparing the document.&#13;
&#13;
           Having emphasized this dialogue between the&#13;
&#13;
 national government and Bank and Fund mission, it may not,&#13;
&#13;
 however, be appropriate for the staff to recommend&#13;
                                                                   Page48&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 endorsement or rejection of the paper prepared by a&#13;
&#13;
 sovereign government.    It may be submitted to the Board&#13;
&#13;
 with the observation of the members of the joint mission.&#13;
&#13;
 The Board, after detailed discussion, may convey to the&#13;
&#13;
 concerned government its views, suggestions and&#13;
&#13;
 apprehensions, if any, which may or may not lead to&#13;
&#13;
 modification of the PRSP paper.&#13;
&#13;
           If it is really a country-driven strategy, then&#13;
&#13;
 the final say should rest with the national government&#13;
&#13;
 concerned, and they should be fully responsible for the&#13;
&#13;
 implementation.   Experience has shown that strategies that&#13;
&#13;
 lack ownership and are perceived to have been imposed from&#13;
&#13;
 above are not successful in implementation.&#13;
&#13;
           Once the PRSP is final, the Bank and Fund should&#13;
&#13;
 effectively monitor it and should also visualize that&#13;
&#13;
 whatever may be the degree of commitment and ownership,&#13;
&#13;
 things may go wrong for regions outside the control of the&#13;
&#13;
 government.   Under such circumstances, the Bank/Fund&#13;
&#13;
 should step in and give appropriate advice and help to&#13;
&#13;
 come out of the drift quickly.      For this, an appropriate&#13;
&#13;
 advance warning system and outcome indicators have to be&#13;
&#13;
 developed.&#13;
                                                                Page49&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
             Regarding the publication of the PRSP, it should&#13;
&#13;
 be widely publicized both by the government and the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
 Transparency itself will lead to wide debate and will&#13;
&#13;
 force the government to correct itself and incorporate&#13;
&#13;
 appropriate strategies in the best interest of the people.&#13;
&#13;
             To sum up, poverty reduction strategies must be&#13;
&#13;
 domestically owned and internally driven.            This is only&#13;
&#13;
 possible if the respective governments themselves decide&#13;
&#13;
 priorities in program objectives.         This is especially true&#13;
&#13;
 for those countries which have democratic institutions in&#13;
&#13;
 place at national, subnational and district levels and&#13;
&#13;
 have set up their developmental priorities and decided the&#13;
&#13;
 pace and scope of their implementation based upon&#13;
&#13;
 constitutional provisions and participatory consultations.&#13;
&#13;
 Such programs should not be constrained by&#13;
&#13;
 conditionalities.&#13;
&#13;
             My second comment is about the flexibility of&#13;
&#13;
 approach.    Several of my colleagues--Stephen, Jan, Pieter&#13;
&#13;
 and others--have already highlighted in the written notes&#13;
&#13;
 that there should be flexibility in approach, and we&#13;
&#13;
 should not be, to use my own phrase, prisoners of our own&#13;
&#13;
 critical models.&#13;
                                                                     Page50&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           What is required, therefore, is that we can have&#13;
&#13;
 an approach related to a particular country, and it is not&#13;
&#13;
 necessary that the same strategy must ipso facto be made&#13;
&#13;
 applicable to another country.      There, the Country&#13;
&#13;
 Directors of the Bank in particular will play a very&#13;
&#13;
 important role.&#13;
&#13;
           My third comment, Mr. Chairman, is in relation&#13;
&#13;
 to the cost of PRSP paper preparation.         I thought that for&#13;
&#13;
 very informal consultations between the Bank and the Fund&#13;
&#13;
 and the national government, and also for removing any&#13;
&#13;
 doubts about it, we should offer to meet the cost.        It is&#13;
&#13;
 for the national government to accept it or not to accept&#13;
&#13;
 it.&#13;
&#13;
           My last comment, Mr. Chairman, is about the&#13;
&#13;
 relationship between CAS and PRSP and between CAS, CDF and&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP.   I had said the other day that we must not get&#13;
&#13;
 confused between the contradictions of one document and&#13;
&#13;
 another, because if the two documents are prepared at&#13;
&#13;
 different periods of history by different teams, such&#13;
&#13;
 confusion is possible.    Therefore, an integrated view is&#13;
&#13;
 necessary, and in having that integrated view, I think&#13;
&#13;
 what is required is that the CAS, which is the generic&#13;
&#13;
 document, should have the PRSP also fully taken into&#13;
                                                                     Page51&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 account once the CAS is revised, after the PRSP has been&#13;
&#13;
 prepared.    For countries which have accepted the&#13;
&#13;
 Comprehensive Development Framework, the requirement in my&#13;
&#13;
 view is very sensitive between the CAS, the CDF, and the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP, and this is an area on which further thought it&#13;
&#13;
 possible, but as we go along, we would improve upon it.&#13;
&#13;
             What is therefore crucial is that we should have&#13;
&#13;
 full information about who is doing what in a particular&#13;
&#13;
 country, in a particular region of a country, in regard to&#13;
&#13;
 the removal of poverty, and it is there that the donor&#13;
&#13;
 agencies and the monitoring by the Bank would be of help&#13;
&#13;
 in telling the national government and the donor agencies&#13;
&#13;
 in particular about the need to avoid duplication and to&#13;
&#13;
 have full advantage of the synergy of the different&#13;
&#13;
 organizations.&#13;
&#13;
             Again, Mr. Chairman, the success of the PRSP&#13;
&#13;
 lies not in the beauty of its document but in what it&#13;
&#13;
 actually does.    Are we going to reduce the number of&#13;
&#13;
 people, the 1.3 billion people who are living on one&#13;
&#13;
 dollar a day, and how soon?      We are all committed to&#13;
&#13;
 working toward that end.&#13;
&#13;
             Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. WOLFENSOHN:   Thank you very much.&#13;
                                                                Page52&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
            Mr. Alyahya.&#13;
&#13;
            MR. ALYAHYA:    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
            We made a number of comments on this paper&#13;
&#13;
 during last Wednesday's Informal Meeting, and today, I&#13;
&#13;
 will reiterate some of these points, but I will also make&#13;
&#13;
 some references to the internal guidance note.&#13;
&#13;
            First, on ownership and capacity-building, while&#13;
&#13;
 the intention is to let the country prepare the PRSP, it&#13;
&#13;
 is clear that many of the targeted poor countries lack the&#13;
&#13;
 capacity to undertake such a complex task by themselves.&#13;
&#13;
 The Bank and the IMF will, of course, have to provide&#13;
&#13;
 significant support.      In doing so, the two institutions&#13;
&#13;
 should aim at creating sufficient local capacity to enable&#13;
&#13;
 countries to truly prepare homegrown PRSPs.&#13;
&#13;
            It would therefore be important for the two&#13;
&#13;
 Boards to know at one point what kind of technical&#13;
&#13;
 assistance was provided in the preparation of the PRSP and&#13;
&#13;
 by whom.   This could be attached as an annex to the staff&#13;
&#13;
 assessment.&#13;
&#13;
            In my view, unless we take capacity-building&#13;
&#13;
 more seriously and improve the delivery of technical&#13;
&#13;
 assistance, many of these countries will continue to rely&#13;
                                                               Page53&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 on donors for the preparation of the PRSP, which in itself&#13;
&#13;
 will underline ownership.&#13;
&#13;
            As for the participatory approach, we agree with&#13;
&#13;
 the staff that participatory processes need to reflect the&#13;
&#13;
 culture, practices and institutions of countries.&#13;
&#13;
 Participatory processes are not easy; they are costly and&#13;
&#13;
 require time and careful preparation.           As the paper points&#13;
&#13;
 out, meeting HIPC and other deadlines puts a limit on this&#13;
&#13;
 time frame.   Financial and technical support will be&#13;
&#13;
 needed.    However, the government should determine the&#13;
&#13;
 modality of the process.&#13;
&#13;
            As for timing of the PRSP rollout, we welcome&#13;
&#13;
 the flexibility provided in the paper for the timing of&#13;
&#13;
 the PRSP rollout.    Given the differences in country&#13;
&#13;
 circumstances, a transition period is needed.          A period of&#13;
&#13;
 two years for some countries, as suggested in the paper,&#13;
&#13;
 would also give countries, donors and international&#13;
&#13;
 institutions time to learn and adapt.           This would also&#13;
&#13;
 prevent interruption of the normal lending program to the&#13;
&#13;
 country.&#13;
&#13;
            As for Bank/Fund collaboration, there has been&#13;
&#13;
 considerable progress between the Bank and Fund.          I am&#13;
&#13;
 particularly pleased to note that we already have&#13;
                                                                       Page54&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 procedures for resolving differences of view between the&#13;
&#13;
 two institutions.    As indicated in Footnote 10 of the&#13;
&#13;
 joint paper, remaining differences will be, and I quote,&#13;
&#13;
 "reflected in reports on the country to the Executive&#13;
&#13;
 Boards of the two institutions."&#13;
&#13;
           Since PRSPs are expected to be homegrown, we&#13;
&#13;
 should also expect differences in view between the two&#13;
&#13;
 institutions and the country.        It will be important for&#13;
&#13;
 the two Boards to have an opportunity to hear the&#13;
&#13;
 country's case, perhaps giving the country an opportunity&#13;
&#13;
 to comment on staff assessment, especially when such an&#13;
&#13;
 assessment is negative.      Country comments could be&#13;
&#13;
 included as an attachment to the staff assessment.&#13;
&#13;
           While we would want the Bank and the Fund to&#13;
&#13;
 continue strengthening their collaboration in the interest&#13;
&#13;
 of client countries, we would not encourage the&#13;
&#13;
 introduction of cross-conditionality.           In this context, it&#13;
&#13;
 would be important to ensure that Bank/IMF PRSP missions&#13;
&#13;
 be separate from missions for lending programs.           This&#13;
&#13;
 would also ensure greater objectivity.&#13;
&#13;
           As for the links with IDA operations, the paper&#13;
&#13;
 states in paragraph 42 that, and I quote:            "A Board-&#13;
&#13;
 endorsed PRSP, interim PRSP, or PRSP progress report will&#13;
                                                                       Page55&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 be a necessary condition for a high-case lending scenario&#13;
&#13;
 and adjustment lending except in special circumstances&#13;
&#13;
 such as emergency or crisis situations."&#13;
&#13;
           I would like to know if this precludes&#13;
&#13;
 adjustment lending in the base case.        I am aware of the&#13;
&#13;
 note on adjustment lending that Management circulated last&#13;
&#13;
 week, but I would like a clear answer, yes or no.        If&#13;
&#13;
 there is going to be flexibility, how would we ensure&#13;
&#13;
 consistency and equal treatment?&#13;
&#13;
           On the endorsement by the Board, I agree that&#13;
&#13;
 the joint staff assessment accompanying the PRSP should&#13;
&#13;
 recommend to the Board endorsement and not approval, as&#13;
&#13;
 suggested by some during the meeting last week, of the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP.   I also agree that the assessment should not&#13;
&#13;
 recommend to the Board approval or rejection of the&#13;
&#13;
 participatory approach.    Of course, Board members may have&#13;
&#13;
 their own views on this, but such views should not&#13;
&#13;
 influence the endorsement of the PRSP.         The quality of the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP should be judged by the quality of the diagnosis and&#13;
&#13;
 the policy content of the matrix.&#13;
&#13;
           On the link to the HIPC Initiative, I agree that&#13;
&#13;
 an interim PRSP should be in place by decision point and&#13;
&#13;
 that the country should have adopted a PRSP and made&#13;
                                                                     Page56&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 progress in its implementation by completion point.         I&#13;
&#13;
 also agree that this requirement should be relaxed for&#13;
&#13;
 retroactive HIPCs.   They should be required to have only&#13;
&#13;
 adopted a PRSP.&#13;
&#13;
           On Bank preparedness, it is not clear whether&#13;
&#13;
 the Bank is internally fully-prepared to launch this new&#13;
&#13;
 initiative.   My concern is that we rush into this while&#13;
&#13;
 unprepared, as has been the case with other initiatives.&#13;
&#13;
 Clearly, for many countries, the quality of their PRSPs&#13;
&#13;
 will largely depend on the quality and timeliness of the&#13;
&#13;
 Bank's support.&#13;
&#13;
           On administrative, budget and staffing, the&#13;
&#13;
 resource implications of Bank/Fund support of countries in&#13;
&#13;
 the preparation of PRSPs are substantial.          I am pleased to&#13;
&#13;
 note that from the Bank side, the budgetary implications&#13;
&#13;
 for the remainder of FY00 will be made available through&#13;
&#13;
 redeployment.   I am not sure, however, whether such&#13;
&#13;
 redeployment will be carried out within the relevant&#13;
&#13;
 regions or across the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
           I note the budgetary implications for FY01, and&#13;
&#13;
 of course, further deployment could be needed, but too&#13;
&#13;
 much redeployment could adversely affect other programs.&#13;
                                                                      Page57&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 This should be avoided.     In any case, this will need to be&#13;
&#13;
 considered in the overall context of the post-Compact.&#13;
&#13;
           Finally, the PRSPs will have important&#13;
&#13;
 implications to the Executive Directors Work Program.      We&#13;
&#13;
 are confident that Mr. Toure's committee will take a&#13;
&#13;
 careful look at this and advise the Board.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. WOLFENSOHN:    Thank you very much, and we&#13;
&#13;
 will respond to your question in a moment.&#13;
&#13;
           Ms. Hollifield?&#13;
&#13;
           MS. HOLLIFIELD:    Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
           The PRSP is an entirely new way of relating to a&#13;
&#13;
 wider range of countries.     As such, it does seem to be a&#13;
&#13;
 natural extension of the CDF, with the focused common goal&#13;
&#13;
 of poverty reduction.    The approach and documents&#13;
&#13;
 themselves must be explicitly pro-poor, and we would&#13;
&#13;
 welcome additional discussion at some point on how to&#13;
&#13;
 mobilize an enhanced relationship between growth and&#13;
&#13;
 equity.&#13;
&#13;
           The challenge for all international development&#13;
&#13;
 players is how to operationalize a new style of&#13;
&#13;
 constructive engagement.    Our authorities are most&#13;
&#13;
 intrigued by the proposed PRSP approach and, depending on&#13;
                                                                 Page58&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 the country and their skill set, stand ready to&#13;
&#13;
 participate both in the analytical policy work and with&#13;
&#13;
 implementation and monitoring.       As with the Bank and&#13;
&#13;
 Fund's engagement, they are aware of the difficult balance&#13;
&#13;
 between donor participation and support and country&#13;
&#13;
 ownership.&#13;
&#13;
             We believe that a strong and inclusive&#13;
&#13;
 partnership standing alongside the client should decline&#13;
&#13;
 the PRSP style.&#13;
&#13;
             The role of the Board must also change in&#13;
&#13;
 parallel.    It is best if we are engaged earlier and&#13;
&#13;
 informally in the PRSP process.        In fact, we hope that the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP will demand lots of our time.         Therefore, we will&#13;
&#13;
 need timely documentation for our own consultations.        But&#13;
&#13;
 we will need to be open and flexible, both on&#13;
&#13;
 documentation and on ideas.      We will need to be open to&#13;
&#13;
 new approaches and innovative ideas even when they are in&#13;
&#13;
 contrast with conventional wisdom.&#13;
&#13;
             The interface with the changing CAS will have to&#13;
&#13;
 be carefully managed.     We need a strong effort to create a&#13;
&#13;
 unified process.    While there may be many distinct&#13;
&#13;
 building blocks, we want them to be designed or redesigned&#13;
&#13;
 as necessary to be mutually reinforcing rather than&#13;
                                                                    Page59&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 replicating efforts.     In particular, we would want to see&#13;
&#13;
 the PRSP and the CAS explicitly linked, another seamless&#13;
&#13;
 transition.&#13;
&#13;
           The cost issues worry us.          We agree with a&#13;
&#13;
 number of speakers last week who asked that these costs&#13;
&#13;
 not be considered as marginal costs to the Bank, since the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP clearly offers the opportunity for the institution to&#13;
&#13;
 substantively change the approach to client countries and&#13;
&#13;
 to poverty alleviation.      What is more complex and&#13;
&#13;
 interesting, however, are the potential implications for&#13;
&#13;
 countries themselves in terms of their relations with&#13;
&#13;
 donors and their role in their own development dialogue.&#13;
&#13;
 In-country impact is the heart of the matter.          We would be&#13;
&#13;
 very interested to see additional work on the potential&#13;
&#13;
 cost to borrower countries and on the Bank's proposed&#13;
&#13;
 approach for facilitating donor involvement and financing.&#13;
&#13;
           In-country impact extends far beyond costing and&#13;
&#13;
 financing, though.     If the process is to be truly country-&#13;
&#13;
 driven, governments themselves are the key stakeholders&#13;
&#13;
 and must be fully involved in all stages of a poverty&#13;
&#13;
 strategy process.    Mr. Abraham has provided an important&#13;
&#13;
 warning that space must be left for ownership.          We would&#13;
&#13;
 welcome comments from staff on the process that has been&#13;
                                                                      Page60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 followed so far to include the borrowers.          The interests,&#13;
&#13;
 experiences and capabilities of the PRSP clients are&#13;
&#13;
 essential inputs into the overall PRSP design.&#13;
&#13;
           We would hope that the Bank and Fund will&#13;
&#13;
 systematically seek their input over the months to come,&#13;
&#13;
 not just on country-specific matters but on the emerging&#13;
&#13;
 shape of the PRSPs more generally.&#13;
&#13;
           Finally, I would like to reiterate our position&#13;
&#13;
 on the PRSP-HIPC linkages.     We strongly believe that only&#13;
&#13;
 Option 3 is consistent with the timely provision of&#13;
&#13;
 enhanced debt relief for retroactive countries.         These&#13;
&#13;
 countries should not have to convince us all over again on&#13;
&#13;
 their commitments to the HIPC principles.          We should not&#13;
&#13;
 be setting up additional hurdles for countries that need&#13;
&#13;
 our support.   We must work alongside them on their long&#13;
&#13;
 road to achieve sustained growth and poverty reduction.&#13;
&#13;
           We would also suggest that interim PRSPs be used&#13;
&#13;
 where appropriate in other cases, both HIPC and otherwise.&#13;
&#13;
 We don't think we can overstate the enormity of the PRSP&#13;
&#13;
 challenge in countries with constrained capacity.         Our&#13;
&#13;
 concessional lending program should not be slowed as&#13;
&#13;
 countries work toward the development of a strong PRSP--a&#13;
&#13;
 goal that we share.&#13;
                                                                     Page61&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           This brings me back to the implications for the&#13;
&#13;
 staffs and the Boards of the two institutions.      We will&#13;
&#13;
 need to be open and willing to take some difficult&#13;
&#13;
 judgment calls.   At the end of the day, we will have to&#13;
&#13;
 ascertain whether countries are truly committed to reform&#13;
&#13;
 and have developed strong and credible development&#13;
&#13;
 strategies with broad civil society support.       This is the&#13;
&#13;
 key to success.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. WOLFENSOHN:    Thank you, Ms. Hollifield.&#13;
&#13;
           Mr. Zhu?&#13;
&#13;
           MR. ZHU:   Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
           While we had two discussions about PRSP-related&#13;
&#13;
 issues last week, I welcome the formal Board discussion&#13;
&#13;
 today and would like to make the following observations&#13;
&#13;
 and comments.&#13;
&#13;
           On ownership, I appreciate the emphasis in the&#13;
&#13;
 paper on country ownership and country-specific approach.&#13;
&#13;
 Government ownership is critical to the success of the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP process.   But Mr. Chairman, in my view, the real&#13;
&#13;
 issue is how to secure genuine and full ownership, or&#13;
&#13;
 rather, how to avoid an imposed or cosmetic ownership&#13;
                                                                  Page62&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 which to a large extent may lead to the dominance of a&#13;
&#13;
 Washington consensus.&#13;
&#13;
           If the proposed approach in terms of&#13;
&#13;
 accountancy, format and process is too complicated, then I&#13;
&#13;
 will be very nervous that the ownership will be easily&#13;
&#13;
 lost in the process.&#13;
&#13;
           Also, the PRSP should not shy away from&#13;
&#13;
 presenting differences in the government concerned and the&#13;
&#13;
 two institutions.    What we want to see at the end of the&#13;
&#13;
 day is a candid and honest paper--not a polished one on&#13;
&#13;
 so-called consensus, where eventually there is no&#13;
&#13;
 ownership.   The lack of differences possibly indicates in&#13;
&#13;
 some cases lack of ownership by the government.&#13;
&#13;
           It seems difficult but very important to avoid&#13;
&#13;
 making PRSP a "Christmas tree," trying to cover too many&#13;
&#13;
 areas together at the same time, especially for those not-&#13;
&#13;
 yet-CDF pilot countries.&#13;
&#13;
           Poverty-related agendas also need to be&#13;
&#13;
 consolidated and selective, addressing the focal points,&#13;
&#13;
 particularly the concerns where each of the governments&#13;
&#13;
 select as a top priority external resources support being&#13;
&#13;
 most relevant.&#13;
                                                              Page63&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           If the PRSP is a country's own document, then&#13;
&#13;
 the final say definitely should be on the country side.&#13;
&#13;
 The country view should prevail wherever there are&#13;
&#13;
 differences, particularly over timing, sequencing, and the&#13;
&#13;
 pacing of the reform program.      The Bank and the Fund role&#13;
&#13;
 in PRSP preparation should be limited to partners rather&#13;
&#13;
 than as a substitute.&#13;
&#13;
           Special attention at the outset should be&#13;
&#13;
 explicitly paid to the asymmetries between the country, on&#13;
&#13;
 the one hand, and international financial organizations&#13;
&#13;
 and donor communities at large on the other in terms of&#13;
&#13;
 institutional capacity, resource availability, and ways of&#13;
&#13;
 voices particularly for small and independent member&#13;
&#13;
 countries.&#13;
&#13;
           The PRSP logically and legally should be&#13;
&#13;
 regarded as a    ?      document, so it's not appropriate, I&#13;
&#13;
 believe, for the Board to endorse it.         As Mr. Pieter Stek&#13;
&#13;
 rightly pointed out, endorsement might take away the sense&#13;
&#13;
 of ownership in the countries involved, and might alienate&#13;
&#13;
 our partners in the field from what is seen as a&#13;
&#13;
 Washington document.&#13;
&#13;
           On cost implications, I appreciate the&#13;
&#13;
 management's intention to redeploy resources internally in&#13;
                                                                    Page64&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 the first year, but inevitably there will be additional&#13;
&#13;
 costs in the process.     In this regard, I hope that we can&#13;
&#13;
 discuss it in the context of the Strategic Compact, and&#13;
&#13;
 also better attention should be paid to the possible&#13;
&#13;
 least-cost solutions.&#13;
&#13;
             And to the extent possible, I would like to call&#13;
&#13;
 for using more experts and consultants from developing&#13;
&#13;
 countries themselves.     In this way, PRSP may technically&#13;
&#13;
 less articulate or perfect, but more cost-effective and&#13;
&#13;
 feasible.    Also, in such a process of involvement of the&#13;
&#13;
 consultants or experts from developing countries&#13;
&#13;
 themselves, borrowing countries may also have a better&#13;
&#13;
 chance to share each other's experiences.&#13;
&#13;
             On the participation process, the Bank and the&#13;
&#13;
 Fund should be cautious with participating, respecting the&#13;
&#13;
 rights of the governments to draw the line on their&#13;
&#13;
 engagement.    PRSP should not create the impression that it&#13;
&#13;
 is open to unrealistic public access if the governments do&#13;
&#13;
 not think so.&#13;
&#13;
             How to ensure a meaningful not a biased&#13;
&#13;
 participation is indeed a challenge.         Years of experience&#13;
&#13;
 have proved that civil society is not a homogeneous&#13;
&#13;
 building block, and some special interest groups'&#13;
                                                                    Page65&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 participation may not truly represent the interests of the&#13;
&#13;
 poor in the field.   Their participation may not benefit&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction, and sometimes unfortunately even go to&#13;
&#13;
 the country.   Therefore, a better definition of the&#13;
&#13;
 composition of civil society is urgently needed, given the&#13;
&#13;
 tendency nowadays to lump all organizations outside&#13;
&#13;
 government together without due regard to their diversity&#13;
&#13;
 and their relevance to poverty reduction.&#13;
&#13;
           Another dimension, Mr. Chairman, is that&#13;
&#13;
 participation can be expensive and time-consuming, if&#13;
&#13;
 poorly handled, and may compound the problem of cost of&#13;
&#13;
 doing business with the Bank and the Fund.         So&#13;
&#13;
 participation selectivity must be ensured.&#13;
&#13;
           It makes more sense to focus on working more&#13;
&#13;
 directly with grass-roots participation and reflecting&#13;
&#13;
 local communities' interests rather than going through the&#13;
&#13;
 variety of international NGOs as an intermediary in the&#13;
&#13;
 process of PRSP consultation, and Bank staff assessment in&#13;
&#13;
 this regard must be of neutrality politically.&#13;
&#13;
           Mr. Chairman, it's a little bit confusing to me&#13;
&#13;
 how the Board could comment or judge the PRSP&#13;
&#13;
 participation process.    Executive Directors do not have&#13;
&#13;
 the legal right, as such, or the responsibility, even the&#13;
                                                              Page66&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 comparative advantage, in doing so.        How could we make a&#13;
&#13;
 reasonable judgment in this area?       I'd like to hear from&#13;
&#13;
 the management and staff some thoughts.&#13;
&#13;
           On Bank and Fund collaboration, the challenge of&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction is daunting.      It requires concerted&#13;
&#13;
 effort by all players based on their comparative&#13;
&#13;
 advantage.   As mentioned above, the Board's role in PRSP&#13;
&#13;
 endorsement may result, unfortunately in some cases, in&#13;
&#13;
 cross-conditionality, and even loss of country ownership,&#13;
&#13;
 especially if each Board has to endorse the overall PRSP&#13;
&#13;
 which includes areas of primary responsibility of the&#13;
&#13;
 other side of 19th Street.&#13;
&#13;
           We are all aware of the risk of further blurring&#13;
&#13;
 the division of labor of the two institutions which has b&#13;
&#13;
 been increasingly less clear-cut.       In this regard, it may&#13;
&#13;
 be advisable to prepare a new matrix to set up detailed&#13;
&#13;
 respective responsibilities of the two institutions in the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP process.&#13;
&#13;
           Joint missions is a good concept, but in&#13;
&#13;
 practice may be difficult to work out.         Efforts also need&#13;
&#13;
 to be made to forge a real team between the Bank and&#13;
&#13;
 staff, with different emphasis, culture, even work cycle.&#13;
                                                                    Page67&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 How to ensure the synergy of the two institutions in terms&#13;
&#13;
 of time frame dynamics is indeed a challenge.&#13;
&#13;
           The country, Mr. Chairman, rather than the Bank&#13;
&#13;
 and the Fund should take the lead with all donor&#13;
&#13;
 coordination and be responsible for defining the division&#13;
&#13;
 of labor among donors.    In this regard, I again endorse&#13;
&#13;
 Mr. Pieter Stek's point.    Let me quote: "Let recipient&#13;
&#13;
 countries be free to choose whom they want to turn to for&#13;
&#13;
 assistance in writing their PRSP.       This will not only&#13;
&#13;
 strengthen ownership, but also trust in partnership."&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. WOLFENSOHN:    Well, thank you very much, Mr.&#13;
&#13;
 Zhu.   I think you raise a number of questions which have&#13;
&#13;
 been touched on by some earlier speakers.&#13;
&#13;
           Certainly, there is no desire to make this a&#13;
&#13;
 cosmetic document.     In fact, the provision is that the&#13;
&#13;
 countries would develop the PRSP and then there will be&#13;
&#13;
 staff commentary on the PRSP.      But I do not believe that&#13;
&#13;
 there is a desire on the part of the Bank or Fund to push&#13;
&#13;
 the PRSP into some particular form or to have it as a&#13;
&#13;
 cosmetic document which is agreed.&#13;
&#13;
           I certainly agree with you about the use of&#13;
&#13;
 local consultants.     It's something that we have been&#13;
                                                                Page68&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 supporting for some time.     But on the issue of&#13;
&#13;
 participation and how you judge it, and on how the Board&#13;
&#13;
 can most effectively decide on the participation issue, I&#13;
&#13;
 think we're going to have to deal with that on a case-by-&#13;
&#13;
 case basis.&#13;
&#13;
           I raised this matter this morning in our&#13;
&#13;
 internal meeting, and I doubt that we could give a&#13;
&#13;
 guideline that would be suitable for every country.    I&#13;
&#13;
 think manifestly there may be differences in approaches&#13;
&#13;
 between countries and that you may bring a different&#13;
&#13;
 approach to the issues than some other countries yourself.&#13;
&#13;
 I think all the countries would probably want us to take a&#13;
&#13;
 country-by-country approach.&#13;
&#13;
           But, again, this issue is in the hands of the&#13;
&#13;
 government.   It's going to be country-led, and then it has&#13;
&#13;
 to come to our Board to take a view as to whether we&#13;
&#13;
 regard it as a Board as having been a satisfactory process&#13;
&#13;
 for the Board.   No doubt, we will all have, over time,&#13;
&#13;
 some judgments that might be useful, but I will ask my&#13;
&#13;
 team to try and see if we can come up with some&#13;
&#13;
 guidelines.   But, frankly, I think it would be very&#13;
&#13;
 difficult to do so, even acknowledging the distinction you&#13;
                                                               Page69&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 are making between international NGOs and local NGOs.         But&#13;
&#13;
 perhaps practice will determine that.&#13;
&#13;
           And so far as the Bank and the Fund is&#13;
&#13;
 concerned, I think it's clear that there are a number of&#13;
&#13;
 areas that we need to work together on to clarify our&#13;
&#13;
 operating procedures.    I'd be surprised if we could come&#13;
&#13;
 up with a matrix, or would maybe even want to.&#13;
&#13;
           What I think is important is that the Managing&#13;
&#13;
 Director and I have agreed that we should seek to work&#13;
&#13;
 together in developing this, and that there are some areas&#13;
&#13;
 of apparent strengths and weaknesses on either side of&#13;
&#13;
 19th Street, and that what I have learned already from my&#13;
&#13;
 colleagues is that the initial efforts and the initial&#13;
&#13;
 discussions are being done in a very flexible and a very&#13;
&#13;
 communal way between the two of us.&#13;
&#13;
           And I think it may be better to let it develop&#13;
&#13;
 rather than trying to impose something on it that we would&#13;
&#13;
 discuss in advance at the Board.       I think so far it is&#13;
&#13;
 working rather well in terms of the cooperation and in&#13;
&#13;
 terms of the flexibility that we're seeking.       It is&#13;
&#13;
 something that is rather new for both of us, but I would&#13;
&#13;
 counsel the Board that we should let it move forward and&#13;
&#13;
 learn as we go.&#13;
                                                                     Page70&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
             I think our teams have a pretty good idea of&#13;
&#13;
 what is needed, and I think putting too fine a point on it&#13;
&#13;
 might lead us to a bureaucratic discussion that we all&#13;
&#13;
 want to avoid.    So my instinct would be that we should let&#13;
&#13;
 it develop and review it regularly, but not review it so&#13;
&#13;
 regularly that we kill something that is emerging and&#13;
&#13;
 where each side is getting some sense of the other.&#13;
&#13;
             At the moment, I'm rather happy with the way&#13;
&#13;
 things are going, and I believe that is the view of the&#13;
&#13;
 Managing Director as well.       And my instinct would be to&#13;
&#13;
 let it move forward and review it as we move forward in&#13;
&#13;
 particular cases.    And then the Board can--we can all&#13;
&#13;
 learn together.    It is something different for the Board&#13;
&#13;
 as well, for both Boards, as evidenced by the fact that&#13;
&#13;
 the Boards feel the need to talk together and meet&#13;
&#13;
 together.&#13;
&#13;
             So we're on new territory, but I find it&#13;
&#13;
 exciting.    It's a new millennium, maybe a new day for all&#13;
&#13;
 of us, and I suggest that we move slowly, but cautiously&#13;
&#13;
 and effectively together.&#13;
&#13;
             Mr. Meyer?&#13;
&#13;
             MR. MEYER:   Thank you, Chair.           I think you're&#13;
&#13;
 right.   There is a new day and a new millennium.             Also,&#13;
                                                                       Page71&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 we're starting out the new millennium with an overload, I&#13;
&#13;
 think, which is maybe healthy.&#13;
&#13;
           I would like to associate myself to a lot of&#13;
&#13;
 what has been said, and we would like to associate&#13;
&#13;
 ourselves particularly with Mr. Pickford's statement, I&#13;
&#13;
 think, which expresses best our--we might call it in&#13;
&#13;
 French sensibilite, or our sensitivity which I think is,&#13;
&#13;
 in fact, what we should be talking about.          Most of us have&#13;
&#13;
 very similar views, but then some of us are more&#13;
&#13;
 judgmental than others, and some of us have more&#13;
&#13;
 confidence in local processes than others.&#13;
&#13;
           And so this is a very soft kind of discussion&#13;
&#13;
 which we can have right now because, in fact, in terms of&#13;
&#13;
 substance we don't know anything right now, because we're&#13;
&#13;
 basically dealing with the maybe most difficult problem in&#13;
&#13;
 our work, which is what is the right development and what&#13;
&#13;
 is the right theory for development, and how is growth&#13;
&#13;
 related to inequality in poverty reduction.&#13;
&#13;
           As others, I do hope that this process in terms&#13;
&#13;
 of the substance of what will become PRSPs, and so on, can&#13;
&#13;
 be heavily inspired by the discussion on the WDR&#13;
&#13;
 2000/2001.   In terms of process, I think we all have ahead&#13;
&#13;
 of us a relatively long interim period where we have to do&#13;
                                                                      Page72&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 a lot of cost planning, and at the same time not create&#13;
&#13;
 any undue burden for successful HIPC countries because of&#13;
&#13;
 this new process.&#13;
&#13;
            And in that sense, I think one of the things we&#13;
&#13;
 should be doing is exactly to look at how successful&#13;
&#13;
 countries do maybe present models in terms of ownership&#13;
&#13;
 and in terms of participatory processes.             I think one of&#13;
&#13;
 the things we should be doing very clearly is, since we do&#13;
&#13;
 not have at the present time any way to judge that&#13;
&#13;
 process, is to have in place kind of a monitoring and&#13;
&#13;
 evaluation system when the first PRSPs are being presented&#13;
&#13;
 to the Board.   I think we do have to have common ground in&#13;
&#13;
 terms of how we want to monitor the process and what are&#13;
&#13;
 the essential elements of success and failure in the&#13;
&#13;
 process.&#13;
&#13;
            Relating to ownership, obviously everybody likes&#13;
&#13;
 to talk about this.     We just this morning thought about&#13;
&#13;
 ownership of long-term strategies in the case of Poland,&#13;
&#13;
 in the case of Switzerland.       We couldn't discover any&#13;
&#13;
 written document which goes beyond four years, and&#13;
&#13;
 certainly we couldn't discover any document which is being&#13;
&#13;
 taken seriously in the political system.             So this is just,&#13;
&#13;
 you know, a hint of how maybe difficult it is, or maybe&#13;
                                                                         Page73&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 how such long-term strategies and processes are not&#13;
&#13;
 necessarily very transparent or very rational to the&#13;
&#13;
 outside world in any countries.&#13;
&#13;
            Now, here, when we talk about ownership, I think&#13;
&#13;
 one of the important things is not to dream.       HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 countries are the poorest countries in the world and if&#13;
&#13;
 they are going to do a PRSP, it's not just because they&#13;
&#13;
 would like to do that; it's also because they have a very&#13;
&#13;
 heavy debt burden and they expect financing.       And so they&#13;
&#13;
 obviously will do this in the context of high dependency&#13;
&#13;
 and in expectation that such a PRSP is going to lead to&#13;
&#13;
 support.   And that, of course, to some extent might limit&#13;
&#13;
 the real autonomy of that process.&#13;
&#13;
            So I think it's better maybe to accept that such&#13;
&#13;
 a process is not totally autonomous and that it has to&#13;
&#13;
 serve a purpose internationally.       And what concretely&#13;
&#13;
 means, I think, is that we should probably endorse a PRSP.&#13;
&#13;
 I think what Bank management proposes is a correct&#13;
&#13;
 compromise.   And clearly, as Lewis Holden said, this&#13;
&#13;
 process and the PRSP has to be relevant for support later&#13;
&#13;
 on.   In other words, the CAS will become some kind of a&#13;
&#13;
 business plan.&#13;
                                                                  Page74&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           In that sense, although I share a lot of what my&#13;
&#13;
 Chinese colleague just said and what Pieter Stek said in&#13;
&#13;
 his statement, I do not concur with their conclusion which&#13;
&#13;
 I consider not to be realistic as part of a process where&#13;
&#13;
 we expect should lead to major contributions from the&#13;
&#13;
 international community to local processes.&#13;
&#13;
           Now, in terms of the Bank, what this reflection&#13;
&#13;
 implies, I think, is that the Bank has to be interested in&#13;
&#13;
 the first stage in the analysis and the participatory&#13;
&#13;
 process for creating a PRSP.      I think the Bank and other&#13;
&#13;
 institutions should provide support, strong support.               And&#13;
&#13;
 I would like to reiterate that this is not just a question&#13;
&#13;
 of capacity-building.    This goes well beyond some kind of&#13;
&#13;
 a very general concept of capacity-building.            It implies&#13;
&#13;
 methods of support and of analysis which are not very&#13;
&#13;
 common in the past of the Bank and which so far have not&#13;
&#13;
 been very explicit.&#13;
&#13;
           Whenever we talk in CASs about whether a&#13;
&#13;
 participatory process was a good one or a bad one, we&#13;
&#13;
 always hear that it was very good.        And how do we measure&#13;
&#13;
 it?   Well, there were so many workshops, and these and&#13;
&#13;
 these and these circles were consulted.            We never hear&#13;
&#13;
 anything about the real content of those consultations,&#13;
                                                                          Page75&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 about who was active or passive in those consultations,&#13;
&#13;
 and how this contributed to reinforce existing local&#13;
&#13;
 processes of checks and balances and consultations.&#13;
&#13;
           And clearly, again, how this works, how far this&#13;
&#13;
 process can go depends a lot on the local circumstances,&#13;
&#13;
 depends a lot on the specific systems.         And that means&#13;
&#13;
 that the Bank itself will have to learn a lot about how to&#13;
&#13;
 judge and how to move in local political systems.        And&#13;
&#13;
 that is a difficult task, but it is a learning task for&#13;
&#13;
 the Bank, and I would not just like to stay at the level&#13;
&#13;
 of saying this is just a question of capacity-building.&#13;
&#13;
           Links with HIPC.     We are clearly for Option 3.&#13;
&#13;
 We feel that here Jan Piercy is taking too tough of a&#13;
&#13;
 stance.   We do have confidence that in retroactive cases&#13;
&#13;
 that we have important poverty strategies, poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction strategies and planning in place, and we should&#13;
&#13;
 not unduly lengthen that process.&#13;
&#13;
           We also feel that the whole planning of&#13;
&#13;
 countries should be very transparent, and in that sense we&#13;
&#13;
 would like to know at the present time, when Bank staff&#13;
&#13;
 talks about four countries, in addition to the three or&#13;
&#13;
 four mentioned, which are the countries which are&#13;
&#13;
 presently anticipated to come forward and at what time.&#13;
                                                                 Page76&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
             Finally, staffing.    We think that this might&#13;
&#13;
 present a problem, exactly because I think the challenge&#13;
&#13;
 is substantial.    I think there will be a question of&#13;
&#13;
 staffing in the Fund and in the Bank.          We think that to&#13;
&#13;
 have as a basis a redeployment option both in the Fund and&#13;
&#13;
 the Bank is probably a correct assumption.          But we have to&#13;
&#13;
 revisit this, as it was said, very closely and look into&#13;
&#13;
 the cost question, all this related to clearly a much&#13;
&#13;
 stronger role and a more participatory role of the Bank in&#13;
&#13;
 the first stage.&#13;
&#13;
             Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. WOLFENSOHN:   Thank you, Mr. Meyer.&#13;
&#13;
             Mr. Balduino?&#13;
&#13;
             MR. BALDUINO:   Thank you very much, Mr.&#13;
&#13;
 Chairman.    There are a number of points mentioned in the&#13;
&#13;
 document that we fully agree with and very much welcome.&#13;
&#13;
 Let me start by mentioning them briefly.&#13;
&#13;
             First, the recognition that rapid and&#13;
&#13;
 sustainable economic growth is necessary, although not a&#13;
&#13;
 sufficient condition for poverty reduction, and that, in&#13;
&#13;
 turn, sound macroeconomic policies and management and a&#13;
&#13;
 thriving private sector which is actively investing in&#13;
&#13;
 sound sectoral policies are all necessary conditions for&#13;
                                                                      Page77&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 sustainable growth, and therefore necessary conditions for&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction, too.&#13;
&#13;
           Second, the recognition that there are wide&#13;
&#13;
 differences among countries in terms of the determinants&#13;
&#13;
 of poverty, their type of governments and their&#13;
&#13;
 representative nature, the possibilities for actively&#13;
&#13;
 involving civil society, local capacity, and available of&#13;
&#13;
 data, and that because of all these differences we need to&#13;
&#13;
 be realistic about what can be achieved, recognizing that&#13;
&#13;
 there will be differences in the content and nature of the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSPs and the way that they are prepared.            There is no&#13;
&#13;
 blueprint or ideal model for a PRSP or of participatory&#13;
&#13;
 processes that can be suited to all, and over-ambition in&#13;
&#13;
 this case may lead to paralysis.&#13;
&#13;
           And, third, we very much welcome the notion that&#13;
&#13;
 the preparation of the PRSP has to be country-driven, and&#13;
&#13;
 we hope that we're not going to pay just lip service to&#13;
&#13;
 this notion.&#13;
&#13;
           Fourth, there are many things that we simply&#13;
&#13;
 still do not know and therefore should be subject to&#13;
&#13;
 further analysis.    Also, we have to be careful on the&#13;
&#13;
 advice we extend to these areas and avoid being too&#13;
&#13;
 prescriptive.&#13;
                                                                    Page78&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           The first of these issues on which there is not&#13;
&#13;
 yet firm knowledge ranges from the very major ones, such&#13;
&#13;
 as what are the determinants of poverty, given the&#13;
&#13;
 national situation, to what are the links between higher&#13;
&#13;
 spending and the desired intermediate indicators and&#13;
&#13;
 outcomes, and what these indicators and outcomes could be.&#13;
&#13;
 These are all very important points that the document&#13;
&#13;
 spells out and with which we fully agree.&#13;
&#13;
           Let me make some additional points on four&#13;
&#13;
 issues on participatory process, the role of the Bank and&#13;
&#13;
 the Fund, the transitional arrangements, and the role of&#13;
&#13;
 the Board and external partners.&#13;
&#13;
           On participatory process, there is an innovation&#13;
&#13;
 proposed that the PRSP should be prepared by governments,&#13;
&#13;
 with broad participation of elected institutions, civil&#13;
&#13;
 society, and external partners.       The idea is that this&#13;
&#13;
 participatory process would enhance design and&#13;
&#13;
 implementation.   The document makes the point with which&#13;
&#13;
 we agree that there can be no ready guidelines or general&#13;
&#13;
 models for the participatory process.         We also agree with&#13;
&#13;
 the proposal that the staff should not try to access the&#13;
&#13;
 quality of the participatory process in the joint staff&#13;
&#13;
 assessment.&#13;
                                                                    Page79&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           There are no general models on how this should&#13;
&#13;
 be conducted.   The process should be coordinated and&#13;
&#13;
 conducted by the government and other elected political&#13;
&#13;
 institutions, and they should always have the last word in&#13;
&#13;
 the decisionmaking process.      That's why we think it's note&#13;
&#13;
 necessary to have a feedback process on the strategy&#13;
&#13;
 adopted to those that are consulted, especially in a legal&#13;
&#13;
 sense and especially where these are not provided for&#13;
&#13;
 within the country's legal framework.&#13;
&#13;
           And we think that in the end, a well-established&#13;
&#13;
 political system based on free and fair elections which&#13;
&#13;
 possesses itself mechanisms for consultation of interested&#13;
&#13;
 parties in the form of public hearings and consultations&#13;
&#13;
 is the best participatory process that we could have.&#13;
&#13;
           On the role of the Bank and the Fund, we think&#13;
&#13;
 that there should be not a provision of technical analysis&#13;
&#13;
 by staff too early in the process, but perhaps at an&#13;
&#13;
 intermediate stage.    There is a true risk that we come out&#13;
&#13;
 with not a very consistent document, but this is the price&#13;
&#13;
 of learning.    We may have to choose between a good process&#13;
&#13;
 and a good document, and there may be many countries that&#13;
&#13;
 have received so much advice in past years that they have&#13;
                                                                  Page80&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 just not become accustomed to think for themselves on&#13;
&#13;
 their own priorities and their own development needs.&#13;
&#13;
            On the role of the Boards, it is suggested that&#13;
&#13;
 the PRSP could become the basis for concessional lending&#13;
&#13;
 by the Bank and the Fund.     It is important, however, to&#13;
&#13;
 avoid cross-conditionality, and the two Boards should&#13;
&#13;
 focus only on those parts of the PRSP that relate directly&#13;
&#13;
 to the programs of each institution, and the different&#13;
&#13;
 mandates should be really maintained.&#13;
&#13;
            Let me add that we are really concerned with the&#13;
&#13;
 legal implications of this whole question of endorsement.&#13;
&#13;
 Maybe the suggestion made by Lewis Holden is a good one&#13;
&#13;
 that the Board would only take notice of the PRSP, but&#13;
&#13;
 instead of endorsing that document, just endorse whatever&#13;
&#13;
 strategy that the different staffs propose.        Since the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP could be some part of the CAS process, the Boards&#13;
&#13;
 would then be endorsing the strategy rather than the CAS&#13;
&#13;
 again and not the document itself.        And we would urge that&#13;
&#13;
 a legal clarification be made because this can have&#13;
&#13;
 implications for international law beyond the Bretton&#13;
&#13;
 Woods institutions, depending on how this issue is&#13;
&#13;
 phrased.&#13;
                                                                    Page81&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
            On transitional issues, we think that the&#13;
&#13;
 transitional arrangements between the present situation&#13;
&#13;
 and the new approach that is being proposed--to say that&#13;
&#13;
 we fully support the orientation suggested that the new&#13;
&#13;
 approach should be implemented without interrupting or&#13;
&#13;
 reducing the present flow of concessional financing&#13;
&#13;
 provided to low-income countries.        To do otherwise would&#13;
&#13;
 be like depriving a patient from an existing medicine&#13;
&#13;
 under the argument that a better one would be developed&#13;
&#13;
 soon.    This is particularly important in the case of the&#13;
&#13;
 HIPC countries, and therefore we fully support Option 3&#13;
&#13;
 that envisages the possibility of a collapse of the&#13;
&#13;
 decision and completion points for the retroactive cases.&#13;
&#13;
            On the role of external donors, the document&#13;
&#13;
 claims that donors should actively participate and&#13;
&#13;
 indicate their preferences during the design phase of the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSPs.   The argument is that if they do that, then they&#13;
&#13;
 would make a medium-term financial commitment in support&#13;
&#13;
 of the strategy.   That is in paragraph 57.&#13;
&#13;
            We would like to listen from staff what kind of&#13;
&#13;
 preferences they are talking about here.            Is it just&#13;
&#13;
 preferences about which of the components they would like&#13;
&#13;
 to choose to finance, and if that is the case, why they&#13;
                                                                  Page82&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 should be involved in the design phase and not to wait&#13;
&#13;
 until the strategy is finalized.       Or is it the preferences&#13;
&#13;
 about what should be done, in which case they would have&#13;
&#13;
 indeed been involved in the design phase.           But then this&#13;
&#13;
 raises very serious problems of legitimacy and the danger&#13;
&#13;
 that ownership would not be transformed into donorship, as&#13;
&#13;
 has been mentioned in other meetings here at this forum.&#13;
&#13;
           I would like to ask staff how firm these&#13;
&#13;
 financial commitments by external donors would be done.&#13;
&#13;
 Would there be a formal mechanism to bind these external&#13;
&#13;
 donors to their commitments?      What if they participate&#13;
&#13;
 actively in the design, exert influence, and then shy away&#13;
&#13;
 from the financing?   What would happen then?&#13;
&#13;
           The document also mentions in paragraph 59 that&#13;
&#13;
 external partners will have to reinforce their actions by&#13;
&#13;
 increasing aid flows, unrestricted market access.           We&#13;
&#13;
 mostly support these ideas, but again I would like to know&#13;
&#13;
 what is the plan for how to make these ideas firm&#13;
&#13;
 commitments.&#13;
&#13;
           In terms of review and publication, let me&#13;
&#13;
 finally say that we agree with the proposal to have a full&#13;
&#13;
 review of the program by the year 2001.            And we think that&#13;
&#13;
 in addition to the one to be prepared jointly by both&#13;
                                                                        Page83&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 staffs, there also should be one done by independent&#13;
&#13;
 external evaluators, like those we had on surveillance&#13;
&#13;
 indicators of the Fund.&#13;
&#13;
             The PRSP documents, as we understand them, will&#13;
&#13;
 be documents fully written by the countries concerned.       So&#13;
&#13;
 it should be up to them to decide the best moment for&#13;
&#13;
 publication.    If they decide to publish them before Board&#13;
&#13;
 discussion, we would not object.        And as to the document&#13;
&#13;
 that we are considering, we would favor that first we make&#13;
&#13;
 the changes in the document that would emerge from both&#13;
&#13;
 Boards before going public on them.&#13;
&#13;
             Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. WOLFENSOHN:   Well, thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
             Before calling on Mr. Pesme, I'll just explain&#13;
&#13;
 that I was unable to put off a 12:15 date that I have.&#13;
&#13;
 Mr. Sandstrom has been sitting right through these&#13;
&#13;
 meetings with me and we have been in contact through the&#13;
&#13;
 meetings.    We have already prepared a current summary&#13;
&#13;
 which will be amended by subsequent observations on which&#13;
&#13;
 we have agreed.&#13;
&#13;
             I have asked him if he would continue with this&#13;
&#13;
 meeting.    I apologize for the fact that I cannot put off&#13;
&#13;
 this 12:15 date, but I was very grateful to be able to&#13;
                                                                   Page84&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 participate in this part of the discussions.         And if I&#13;
&#13;
 may--since this evening I'm going to leave for vacation,&#13;
&#13;
 if I could take this chance to wish you all a happy&#13;
&#13;
 holiday season, and I look forward to seeing you in the&#13;
&#13;
 next millennium and hope that you have a great time with&#13;
&#13;
 your families and safe travel and no Y2K problems for the&#13;
&#13;
 end of the year.&#13;
&#13;
           So thank you all very much.         I'll ask Mr.&#13;
&#13;
 Sandstrom to take over.     Mr. Pesme, you are next.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. PESME:    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.      Happy&#13;
&#13;
 holidays to you, also, and I think I can say it on behalf&#13;
&#13;
 of all my colleagues.     And I think all of us deserve&#13;
&#13;
 vacations, given the workload in the recent weeks.           But&#13;
&#13;
 happy holidays.&#13;
&#13;
           On the specific subject, at the outset I would&#13;
&#13;
 like to sincerely commend IMF and Bank management and&#13;
&#13;
 staff for the preparation in such a short time frame of&#13;
&#13;
 the set of papers before us which provide a very sound&#13;
&#13;
 basis to respond to the challenging objectives for poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction agreed during the Annual Meetings.&#13;
&#13;
           What is proposed is indeed a fundamental step&#13;
&#13;
 forward toward enhanced efficiency and effectiveness in&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction, following a comprehensive and&#13;
                                                                    Page85&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 integrated approach which we very much welcome.     As noted&#13;
&#13;
 by several previous speakers, the discussion today is only&#13;
&#13;
 a first step in this endeavor, given the needed ambition&#13;
&#13;
 of the approach, but also the necessity to be successful&#13;
&#13;
 to involve all parties at stake.&#13;
&#13;
           I would like to comment on three aspects:&#13;
&#13;
 substance of the PRSPs, ownership and participatory&#13;
&#13;
 processes, and implementation.&#13;
&#13;
           On substance, we strongly believe that two&#13;
&#13;
 pitfalls must be avoided.      On the one hand, any attempt to&#13;
&#13;
 set a rigid framework would lead to undue delays, in&#13;
&#13;
 particularly in the context of HIPC II which calls for&#13;
&#13;
 faster debt relief.    On the other hand, the absence of a&#13;
&#13;
 minimal content is very likely to undermine the&#13;
&#13;
 effectiveness of the PRSP process and to give room to&#13;
&#13;
 arbitrariness and unfair treatment among countries.&#13;
&#13;
           On balance, we therefore believe that a minimal&#13;
&#13;
 framework is needed, which we expect to be implemented&#13;
&#13;
 with pragmatism.   Such a minimal framework seems to be&#13;
&#13;
 necessary to ensure that general lessons are applied where&#13;
&#13;
 appropriate, that no major block of poverty reduction is&#13;
&#13;
 forgotten, and finally in the HIPC context that the&#13;
                                                                  Page86&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 appropriate basis for comparison between countries is in&#13;
&#13;
 place.&#13;
&#13;
           Of course, two major principles must lead the&#13;
&#13;
 implementation of such a framework.        First, PRSPs are&#13;
&#13;
 designed to be and must be country-driven.         Second, as&#13;
&#13;
 emphasized in the WDR outline, more and more attention has&#13;
&#13;
 to be paid to country specifics, likely leading to very&#13;
&#13;
 different emphasis on the building blocks of this minimal&#13;
&#13;
 framework in each country.&#13;
&#13;
           At this stage, the set of questions in Box 3 of&#13;
&#13;
 the document provides a useful basis for such a framework,&#13;
&#13;
 but we believe that much more could be said, in&#13;
&#13;
 particular, on dimensions which are potentially more&#13;
&#13;
 difficult at the country level.&#13;
&#13;
           Let me be more specific.       First, we strongly&#13;
&#13;
 support the emphasis in the document on the need to ensure&#13;
&#13;
 consistency between macroeconomic, structural and social&#13;
&#13;
 policies and the goals of poverty reduction.        Growth&#13;
&#13;
 remains crucial, and no sustainable outcome will be&#13;
&#13;
 achieved without some macro policies, not to mention that&#13;
&#13;
 essential elements of these macro policies, such as&#13;
&#13;
 inflation and tax policies, for instance, have a direct&#13;
&#13;
 impact on distribution patterns.&#13;
                                                                 Page87&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           Second, we welcome the multi-dimensional&#13;
&#13;
 approach of poverty reduction laid in the paper, but such&#13;
&#13;
 a comprehensive approach must not undermine the need for&#13;
&#13;
 sharpness.   The document puts, in our view, an appropriate&#13;
&#13;
 emphasis on the determinants of poverty, which applies&#13;
&#13;
 that the IMF and the World Bank must provide early enough&#13;
&#13;
 in the process support for broad-based assessment, not&#13;
&#13;
 shying away from potentially contentious issues, such as&#13;
&#13;
 good governance and budget transparency, for instance.&#13;
&#13;
           This process is crucial, in our view, to make&#13;
&#13;
 sure that we do not rush into easy and short-sighted&#13;
&#13;
 solutions.   If each country will have to determine its own&#13;
&#13;
 solutions, in particularly in the determination of the&#13;
&#13;
 appropriate pressure points, we also have the&#13;
&#13;
 responsibility to help them tackle the complexity of the&#13;
&#13;
 issues.&#13;
&#13;
           As mentioned by several speakers in the last&#13;
&#13;
 days, we cannot avoid facing the weaknesses of the&#13;
&#13;
 analysis on causal relationships.       By contrast, it calls,&#13;
&#13;
 in our view, for strong attention to encompass at the&#13;
&#13;
 country level all the dimensions of poverty.       In this&#13;
&#13;
 respect, we also welcome the proposal to establish&#13;
&#13;
 stronger links between the IMF and the Bank lending&#13;
                                                                  Page88&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 programs on the basis of the PRSP implementation so that&#13;
&#13;
 this comprehensive approach is reflected in the dialogue&#13;
&#13;
 between the country and the two institutions.&#13;
&#13;
           This being said, each institution will have to&#13;
&#13;
 maintain a strong focus on its areas of primary&#13;
&#13;
 responsibility, as proposed by staff, and will have to&#13;
&#13;
 rely heavily on the other's expertise.         It implies that&#13;
&#13;
 appropriate attention has to be paid to delivery on each&#13;
&#13;
 side, and that a very strong ongoing dialogue will have to&#13;
&#13;
 take place between the IMF and the Bank to avoid delays in&#13;
&#13;
 any problem resolution process.&#13;
&#13;
           To summarize on this point, we concur with the&#13;
&#13;
 main thrust of the paper, but we think it puts so far too&#13;
&#13;
 much emphasis on the processes at the expense of the&#13;
&#13;
 substance.   Pragmatism and judgment calls will be of the&#13;
&#13;
 essence, but we remain convinced that there is room for&#13;
&#13;
 further work on a minimal framework.&#13;
&#13;
           On ownership and participatory processes, we&#13;
&#13;
 strongly welcome the attention paid in the paper to these&#13;
&#13;
 two dimensions which have proven crucial in long-term&#13;
&#13;
 sustainability of poverty reduction efforts.        Pieter Stek&#13;
&#13;
 makes interesting comments on participation as an end in&#13;
                                                                   Page89&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 his written statement, and we concur with the need to&#13;
&#13;
 implement bottom-up approaches to a greater extent.&#13;
&#13;
           This being said, it is also very likely that the&#13;
&#13;
 dialogue on policies will also have to rely on some top-&#13;
&#13;
 down aspects at the country level, in particular to make&#13;
&#13;
 sure that appropriate distance is taken between assessment&#13;
&#13;
 and design of public policies.&#13;
&#13;
           The obvious solutions are not always the most&#13;
&#13;
 efficient in the long run, even if it is crucial that we&#13;
&#13;
 do not force solutions.    This will clearly be one of the&#13;
&#13;
 trickiest aspects of the PRSP, and one has to be careful&#13;
&#13;
 not to be prescriptive at the outset.         And we agree that&#13;
&#13;
 we will have to learn from experience.&#13;
&#13;
           But, on balance, in the short run we also have&#13;
&#13;
 to remain very aware that additional financing provided&#13;
&#13;
 under HIPC II will have to be actually supportive of&#13;
&#13;
 efficient and effective policies.       More generally, we have&#13;
&#13;
 to maintain the IMF and the Bank and other donors' ability&#13;
&#13;
 to express comments and, when necessary, strong&#13;
&#13;
 disagreements on the priorities and timetables set at the&#13;
&#13;
 country level.&#13;
&#13;
           This being said, it is crucial, in our view, for&#13;
&#13;
 the Bretton Woods institutions to respect each country's&#13;
                                                                   Page90&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 internal political and representative mechanisms.      We must&#13;
&#13;
 not enter into a process in which we would establish any&#13;
&#13;
 norm or standard regarding participatory approach.      And we&#13;
&#13;
 call for great caution in the development of the tool kits&#13;
&#13;
 from this standpoint.    We would not support any request to&#13;
&#13;
 have the staffs of the institutions commenting on these&#13;
&#13;
 processes beyond the existing mechanisms in each country;&#13;
&#13;
 i.e., beyond, among others, involvement of parliaments and&#13;
&#13;
 legitimate local authorities.&#13;
&#13;
           On implementation, we globally concur with staff&#13;
&#13;
 proposals regarding implementation, including the interim&#13;
&#13;
 PRSPs.   We would nevertheless appreciate staff's further&#13;
&#13;
 comments on the time frame for the exit of the interim&#13;
&#13;
 period beyond the case-by-case approach proposed.       And I&#13;
&#13;
 would like to make four additional comments on&#13;
&#13;
 implementation.&#13;
&#13;
           First, on the relationship with the HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 Initiative, we believe it important, in steady state, to&#13;
&#13;
 link the decision point to a fully-fledged PRSP and&#13;
&#13;
 completion point to satisfactory implementation of the&#13;
&#13;
 strategy for at least one year.       We are ready to accept&#13;
&#13;
 some flexibility for the early cases on the basis of&#13;
&#13;
 Option 2 proposed by staff.&#13;
                                                                  Page91&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
            For some exceptional cases where retroactive&#13;
&#13;
 countries have so far demonstrated strong progress in the&#13;
&#13;
 implementation of their national poverty reduction&#13;
&#13;
 strategy, we do not exclude up front to cut off the&#13;
&#13;
 completion and decision points, but a case-by-case&#13;
&#13;
 discussion will have to take place to justify such an&#13;
&#13;
 exceptional measure.   The additional debt relief provided&#13;
&#13;
 by HIPC II must be strongly embedded in the recipient&#13;
&#13;
 country's fight against poverty, and we would have to&#13;
&#13;
 measure that for each country upcoming.&#13;
&#13;
            Two, we support the idea of both IMF and Bank&#13;
&#13;
 Board endorsement of the PRSP because of the very strong&#13;
&#13;
 link with the two institutions' lending program which we&#13;
&#13;
 support.   We are reluctant to limit this endorsement to&#13;
&#13;
 the Bank and IMF elements, since in itself the PRSP must&#13;
&#13;
 represent a comprehensive and integrated approach of&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction.&#13;
&#13;
            Our own selective business plan reflected in the&#13;
&#13;
 CAS must be built on a broad-based agreement with the&#13;
&#13;
 overall strategy, informed by the joint assessment&#13;
&#13;
 provided by staff of the two institutions.         As I mentioned&#13;
&#13;
 last Thursday, we also see some room for improvement in&#13;
&#13;
 the articulation between PRSPs and CASs, including on the&#13;
                                                                     Page92&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 definition of conditionality and triggers for lending&#13;
&#13;
 scenario.    And I would like to associate myself with the&#13;
&#13;
 comments made by Lewis on these points, including on the&#13;
&#13;
 role of the joint assessment.&#13;
&#13;
             Third, we support the proposal for disclosure of&#13;
&#13;
 the various documents, and reiterate our request to make&#13;
&#13;
 publicly available a timetable for the up to 11 countries&#13;
&#13;
 likely to come to the Boards before the spring meetings,&#13;
&#13;
 assuming reasonably progress on macro stability and&#13;
&#13;
 structural reform.       And as mentioned on Wednesday, Table 2&#13;
&#13;
 in the costing paper provides, in our view, a good basis&#13;
&#13;
 for such communication.&#13;
&#13;
             Four, we support the proposal to review the PRSP&#13;
&#13;
 process in 2001 if we have a feeling that further&#13;
&#13;
 discussion might be warranted on the scope of this review.&#13;
&#13;
 Like others, we favor some independence in the review,&#13;
&#13;
 including through strong endorsement of OED.        We&#13;
&#13;
 nevertheless have to be careful on the role of NGOs in&#13;
&#13;
 such a process, and further discussion seems needed on&#13;
&#13;
 this last point.&#13;
&#13;
             Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you very much, Jean.&#13;
                                                                   Page93&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           I have four more names on my list--Reinermann,&#13;
&#13;
 Al-Saad, Toure, and Passacantando.&#13;
&#13;
           Dirk, please.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. REINERMANN:    Thank you, Chairman.     The&#13;
&#13;
 discussion of both Boards last week and today were very&#13;
&#13;
 helpful to give the Boards comfort to give the start&#13;
&#13;
 signal for a PRSP rollout today and to start&#13;
&#13;
 implementation.&#13;
&#13;
           Certainly, many open questions remain and staff&#13;
&#13;
 gave a very good summary initially of those open questions&#13;
&#13;
 and tensions.   But our opinion is one can only take this&#13;
&#13;
 discussion on general tension so far and there comes a&#13;
&#13;
 point when one must take this discussion to a country&#13;
&#13;
 level, and we feel that this time is now and we need to&#13;
&#13;
 revisit the issue once we have some more country-based&#13;
&#13;
 experience.&#13;
&#13;
           I would just like to mention some points that&#13;
&#13;
 would need attention up front.      The first is the issue of&#13;
&#13;
 how the Boards treat PRSPs, the question of endorsement,&#13;
&#13;
 and we believe this is more than a housekeeping issue,&#13;
&#13;
 this is more than a semantic issue.        This probably goes to&#13;
&#13;
 the core of what is intended through PRSP, and in that&#13;
&#13;
 sense it could be a symptom of a deeper issue.&#13;
                                                                    Page94&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
             We appreciate staff's clarification that by&#13;
&#13;
 endorsement it is not meant to find a legal synonym for&#13;
&#13;
 approval.    That's very good, but we believe that given the&#13;
&#13;
 discussion around the table, "endorsement" might be the&#13;
&#13;
 wrong word.    At least we should reconsider the term and&#13;
&#13;
 the concept behind it.&#13;
&#13;
             The deeper issue is probably the issue of&#13;
&#13;
 letting go, and we seem to have a little bit of a problem&#13;
&#13;
 of letting go.    Letting go is very hard, but as I said,&#13;
&#13;
 it's at the heart of the new process, and this is true for&#13;
&#13;
 the staff, for management, and for the Boards.      In that&#13;
&#13;
 sense, we have great sympathy for the proposal by Lewis&#13;
&#13;
 Holden, which I believe is a three-fold proposal for the&#13;
&#13;
 Boards to take note of the PRSPs, to assess the quality of&#13;
&#13;
 the PRSPs as basis for our lending, and then, thirdly, to&#13;
&#13;
 endorse the CAS.    I hope I represent that correctly, but&#13;
&#13;
 we believe that would be a sensible way to proceed.&#13;
&#13;
             The second comment on the CDF-PRSP relationship,&#13;
&#13;
 there was a bit of discussion on this last week.     We&#13;
&#13;
 appreciate very much the clarification offered by you,&#13;
&#13;
 Chairman, and others, and we believe those explanations&#13;
&#13;
 are quite clear and the relationship is quite clear.      And&#13;
&#13;
 we're happy to see both initiatives' progress&#13;
                                                                 Page95&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 simultaneously, as we believe those initiatives are, in&#13;
&#13;
 fact, complementary.&#13;
&#13;
             The third comment is just to support, or&#13;
&#13;
 reiterate and support the request by the UK, the U.S. and&#13;
&#13;
 France today in this meeting for a timetable to be&#13;
&#13;
 published by Bank and Fund of HIPCs likely to come to the&#13;
&#13;
 Board before the spring meetings.        And if I may, I'd like&#13;
&#13;
 to diplomatically ask management for a response to that&#13;
&#13;
 request during this meeting.&#13;
&#13;
             Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. SANDSTROM:    You'll get a response.    Thank&#13;
&#13;
 you.&#13;
&#13;
             Khalid, please.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. AL-SAAD:   Thank you, Chairman.     I'm not sure&#13;
&#13;
 whether we're providing guidance or providing confusion to&#13;
&#13;
 the staff on this exercise.      You know, the issues are&#13;
&#13;
 complex and it's not easy, and we might want to go forward&#13;
&#13;
 with this exercise but with caution and to overburden poor&#13;
&#13;
 countries with many processes that fall beyond their&#13;
&#13;
 capacity.&#13;
&#13;
             As the paper notes, this process is learning by&#13;
&#13;
 doing, and during our Wednesday discussion one speaker&#13;
&#13;
 said he would prefer learning before doing.         But I'm not&#13;
                                                                    Page96&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 sure here whether we can learn before we do in this&#13;
&#13;
 exercise.&#13;
&#13;
             But the question that I have--I don't mind&#13;
&#13;
 learning by doing, but learning by whose money?     Is it the&#13;
&#13;
 poor countries' money or the Bank or donors' money?      So&#13;
&#13;
 that's why it's not clear to me whether we are learning&#13;
&#13;
 with poor country money in order to help them alleviate&#13;
&#13;
 poverty.&#13;
&#13;
             I don't have very much to say to what I said on&#13;
&#13;
 Wednesday regarding the paper, maybe one or two points.&#13;
&#13;
 Basically, it seems clear after our discussion of the&#13;
&#13;
 other two papers that there is a close link between the&#13;
&#13;
 operational issues, the guidelines, and the modalities&#13;
&#13;
 aspect.&#13;
&#13;
             It also seems clear, as many colleagues have&#13;
&#13;
 said, that we need to come back to this issue for a much&#13;
&#13;
 more careful look than the short notice allowed us during&#13;
&#13;
 this week.    The strategies proposed have far-reaching&#13;
&#13;
 implications for many countries well beyond the HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 countries.    This became more evident when we discussed the&#13;
&#13;
 Internal Guidance Note, as we noted that the PRSP will, in&#13;
&#13;
 fact, be expected to be eventually prepared for over 70&#13;
&#13;
 countries.&#13;
                                                                 Page97&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           This involves a more complex process of more&#13;
&#13;
 papers, more staff missions, and clear linkage with CDF,&#13;
&#13;
 culminating finally in more costs for the institution and&#13;
&#13;
 the low-income borrowing countries they are trying to&#13;
&#13;
 help.   Of course, there is the positive outcome that is&#13;
&#13;
 expected from more focus on poverty reduction, but we need&#13;
&#13;
 to avoid the new burden and complexity involved.&#13;
&#13;
           What also became clear from our discussion of&#13;
&#13;
 the modalities for implementation is that the funding of&#13;
&#13;
 the strategy is far from certain.       The concern here is&#13;
&#13;
 that many countries might embark on the new, costly and&#13;
&#13;
 complex exercise without firm assurance that the needed&#13;
&#13;
 financing contribution will be secured.&#13;
&#13;
           Finally, I wish to reiterate the concern I&#13;
&#13;
 mentioned last week on management's intention to cover the&#13;
&#13;
 additional resources by redeployment.         Despite staff&#13;
&#13;
 assurances, I hope this will not turn out to be another&#13;
&#13;
 unfunded mandate, and I share what Pieter Stek said in his&#13;
&#13;
 written statement.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
           Bassary Toure, please.&#13;
                                                               Page98&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
            MR. TOURE:    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.    Most of my&#13;
&#13;
 points were already made during the informal briefings&#13;
&#13;
 that preceded today's meeting.        At this stage, I will try&#13;
&#13;
 to be very brief.    I have two or three points.&#13;
&#13;
            First, on the country ownership, I welcome the&#13;
&#13;
 qualitative move by the Development and Interim&#13;
&#13;
 Committees, and which are stressed in the papers before&#13;
&#13;
 us, to put countries in the driver's seat of the PRSP&#13;
&#13;
 process.   In fact, as frequently advocated by this Chair,&#13;
&#13;
 there is no other alternative to that move which can&#13;
&#13;
 warrant success to development strategies.&#13;
&#13;
            My plea here would consist only in having the&#13;
&#13;
 following concern in mind as we are preparing to adopt&#13;
&#13;
 this approach.   First, the time issue and the related need&#13;
&#13;
 to be flexible in linking the PRSP to the HIPC support;&#13;
&#13;
 second, the issue of administrative and financial&#13;
&#13;
 resources needed to engage and complete quality PRSPs.       In&#13;
&#13;
 that regard, let me reiterate my suggestion to have a&#13;
&#13;
 second look at the issue of resources of the Africa&#13;
&#13;
 Region.    It is my view that this region needs additional&#13;
&#13;
 resources to carry out its duties in our countries under&#13;
&#13;
 the proposed approach.      The third issue is one of&#13;
                                                                   Page99&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 capacity-building in countries where that is needed to&#13;
&#13;
 fully own the process of the preparation of the PRSPs.&#13;
&#13;
           My second point is on the CAS and the PRSPs.&#13;
&#13;
 The CAS is a Bank document and therefore cannot be merged&#13;
&#13;
 with the PRSP.   In fact, if we see the PRSP as a&#13;
&#13;
 comprehensive framework in which the development and&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction priorities and strategies would be&#13;
&#13;
 crafted and implemented, I see no reason why it should be&#13;
&#13;
 different from the CAS chapter on government strategies.&#13;
&#13;
 Furthermore, I just cannot imagine our authorities&#13;
&#13;
 launching two different consultation processes nationwide&#13;
&#13;
 for the purpose of the preparation of PRSPs, on the one&#13;
&#13;
 hand, and the CASs on the other hand.&#13;
&#13;
           In short, we see room for finding a way to&#13;
&#13;
 rationalize the many papers that exist today, and most&#13;
&#13;
 importantly to also establish an operational link with the&#13;
&#13;
 CDF.   I think that we can easily merge these two papers.&#13;
&#13;
           Third, on the endorsement of the PRSPs, we see&#13;
&#13;
 the endorsement of PRSPs the same way as Pieter Stek put&#13;
&#13;
 it in his written statement, for example, for the support&#13;
&#13;
 that we will decide to provide.                              Page100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           Finally, as regards the three options relating&#13;
&#13;
 to HIPC, our preference goes to Option 2, complemented by&#13;
&#13;
 Option 3 and the instances described in that option.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
           Franco Passacantando, please.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. PASSACANTANDO:     Thank you.        I like the tone&#13;
&#13;
 of this document and the emphasis on the realism about&#13;
&#13;
 what can be achieved, which is the most important thing to&#13;
&#13;
 be reminded at this stage, I think, because we have to be&#13;
&#13;
 aware of not raising excessive expectations, you know, on&#13;
&#13;
 simply what is a new document and a new procedure, and&#13;
&#13;
 also the flexibility and the multiplicity of approaches&#13;
&#13;
 that should be followed to poverty reduction.&#13;
&#13;
           I think that many of the issues that have been&#13;
&#13;
 addressed in this document have been discussed not only in&#13;
&#13;
 the past days, but in recent years.        So I don't think we&#13;
&#13;
 have to once again state our position on what we mean by&#13;
&#13;
 ownership and participation.      But, you know, since we are&#13;
&#13;
 here, I think I'll do it again, trying to be as brief as&#13;
&#13;
 possible, and to refer specifically to the issue that is&#13;
&#13;
 at stake now.&#13;
                                                                      Page101&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           On the participatory process, I think that&#13;
&#13;
 Pieter Stek phrased it in a very good way that&#13;
&#13;
 participation can be an end in itself, and should be&#13;
&#13;
 therefore systematically encouraged by the Bank.            At the&#13;
&#13;
 same time, we all agree now that there is not an optimum&#13;
&#13;
 participatory process that can be applied to any&#13;
&#13;
 circumstance, so we should look with some humility and&#13;
&#13;
 open mind to the participatory process that each country&#13;
&#13;
 decides to adopt.&#13;
&#13;
           In this respect, the staff should refrain from&#13;
&#13;
 expressing a judgment, but it should provide the Board&#13;
&#13;
 with full and clear information in order for the Board to&#13;
&#13;
 make an informed judgment on this issue.             And on this&#13;
&#13;
 aspect, I think if we can be very specific, and more&#13;
&#13;
 specific from what we have been in the past about the&#13;
&#13;
 participatory process, I think that could be very helpful.&#13;
&#13;
           On ownership, I think that in recent months we&#13;
&#13;
 have made progress in defining what we mean by ownership.&#13;
&#13;
 And also we now recognize that there will always be a&#13;
&#13;
 tension when we discuss this concept, some tension that is&#13;
&#13;
 inevitable and perhaps welcome.         It's clear that ownership&#13;
&#13;
 means, I think, like Luc said, that a country should take&#13;
                                                                      Page102&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 full responsibility for its actions, and that is crucial&#13;
&#13;
 for the success of any development strategy.&#13;
&#13;
           It does not mean that it should not take into&#13;
&#13;
 account the knowledge and the experience of the&#13;
&#13;
 international community.    We also agree on that now, and&#13;
&#13;
 we also agree, but it is more controversial, that it does&#13;
&#13;
 not mean that the country should not refrain from taking&#13;
&#13;
 advantage from the pressure that the international&#13;
&#13;
 community could exert to implement reforms that are widely&#13;
&#13;
 recognized as being needed but that meet internal&#13;
&#13;
 resistance.&#13;
&#13;
           So it is a matter of balance, it is a matter of&#13;
&#13;
 judgment, and it is a matter of implementation.        And I&#13;
&#13;
 think the most important fact is how the Bank keeps itself&#13;
&#13;
 to have the ability and the sensitivity of presenting its&#13;
&#13;
 knowledge and its experience, and at the same time&#13;
&#13;
 listening to what the specific conditions of a country&#13;
&#13;
 are.   Let me state in this respect the importance that we&#13;
&#13;
 attach to the public expenditure reviews that are an&#13;
&#13;
 important technical instrument that the Bank can provide&#13;
&#13;
 to improve the overall strategy of poverty reduction.&#13;
&#13;
           Let me mention now two other aspects, the point&#13;
                                                                    Page103&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 of endorsement and the link with HIPC.         On endorsement, I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 think that I agree with others that endorsement should not&#13;
&#13;
 mean formal approval.     However, I do not share the opinion&#13;
&#13;
 of those who think that endorsement is inconsistent with&#13;
&#13;
 country ownership.    In fact, I think that a full and open&#13;
&#13;
 discussion on this Board of the PRSP could be beneficial&#13;
&#13;
 for the quality of the product and could avoid the risk&#13;
&#13;
 that Luc appropriately mentioned that the PRSP becomes&#13;
&#13;
 another bureaucratic process, like a document that the PFP&#13;
&#13;
 that ends up being not greatly used.&#13;
&#13;
             Again, also in this respect it is important that&#13;
&#13;
 the Board itself develop a new approach in discussing this&#13;
&#13;
 issue to avoid the risk of a bureaucratic approach.          But I&#13;
&#13;
 think that the Board should be involved in the discussion&#13;
&#13;
 of the PRSP.&#13;
&#13;
             Finally, the link with HIPC.        We are in favor of&#13;
&#13;
 Option 2.    For retroactive countries, I'm sure that,&#13;
&#13;
 again, a proper balance can be found between the need to&#13;
&#13;
 proceed expeditiously and the opportunity that the new&#13;
&#13;
 emphasis on poverty reduction can offer to these countries&#13;
&#13;
 to improve and to fine-tune their own poverty reduction&#13;
&#13;
 strategy.    So I think on this again there is a judgment,&#13;
&#13;
 and I think that by working within Option 2 we can achieve&#13;
                                                                      Page104&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 this balance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you very much, Franco.&#13;
&#13;
           Mr. Abraham, please.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. ABRAHAM:    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.   I have&#13;
&#13;
 circulated my statement, and therefore I will be brief&#13;
&#13;
 just to say, Mr. Chairman, that the issues of ownership&#13;
&#13;
 and endorsement, as explained and presented by management,&#13;
&#13;
 was well with us because as long as endorsement does not&#13;
&#13;
 mean that the Boards have the power to reject the poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction strategy of countries, but like Mr.&#13;
&#13;
 Passacantando said that they have a very positive input&#13;
&#13;
 into them, I think that's very, very positive.&#13;
&#13;
           In terms of ownership, Mr. Passacantando also&#13;
&#13;
 explained very well.     I don't think ownership from our&#13;
&#13;
 part means that exclusively these countries will not&#13;
&#13;
 entertain or benefit from the expertise of the&#13;
&#13;
 international community.    It should not mean that.     What&#13;
&#13;
 it should not mean is that the countries have very little&#13;
&#13;
 to do with that strategy and it comes here and is&#13;
&#13;
 approved, and therefore in the end we don't get the&#13;
&#13;
 results that we're after.     So I think I am, from my&#13;
&#13;
 viewpoint, quite happy today with the clarifications on&#13;
                                                                 Page105&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 endorsement and ownership.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           The other issue is the good policy kind of&#13;
&#13;
 thing.   I very much endorse what Pieter Stek and Stephen&#13;
&#13;
 Pickford have stated in the sense that we should recognize&#13;
&#13;
 those countries that are really performing well.         I always&#13;
&#13;
 think of myself the classroom example that if you give&#13;
&#13;
 every student a C, regardless of that performance, that's&#13;
&#13;
 not a good policy.    Or if you give every student an A, it&#13;
&#13;
 doesn't make sense either.&#13;
&#13;
           I think we ought to recognize policy, whether&#13;
&#13;
 it's in lending, whether it's in peace policy.         In&#13;
&#13;
 everything that we do, we should not treat countries the&#13;
&#13;
 same, and I think our weakness has been that we treat them&#13;
&#13;
 fairly the same.   I'd like to state that.&#13;
&#13;
           And then a point, why we chose Option 2.          Option&#13;
&#13;
 2 simply does not shut the door on other countries who may&#13;
&#13;
 have the same problems of debt burden right now.         Option 3&#13;
&#13;
 simply excludes those.     So I think Option 2, with some&#13;
&#13;
 modification to include countries, meaning part of Option&#13;
&#13;
 3, is something that we would support.          And that goes very&#13;
&#13;
 well with our African Chair and the French Chair, and I&#13;
&#13;
 think we would be not totally fair to say those who have&#13;
&#13;
 made it so far, that's it, and we shut the door.&#13;
                                                                      Page106&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
           Are there any other comments at this point?        Jan&#13;
&#13;
 is hesitating.   Her arm went up.&#13;
&#13;
           Jan?&#13;
&#13;
           MS. PIERCY:   Some of the interventions raised&#13;
&#13;
 some legal questions, and I wonder if at some point in the&#13;
&#13;
 staff comment they might--I'm not sure if I--I was trying&#13;
&#13;
 to sort of frame those questions in my own mind, but I'm&#13;
&#13;
 not sure I could do so with precision.         But I think that&#13;
&#13;
 is an area that would be worth getting some enlightenment&#13;
&#13;
 on in the response.&#13;
&#13;
           And an area that we didn't so much in the&#13;
&#13;
 discussion today touch on but some of the written&#13;
&#13;
 statements did has to do with the role of WBI, and I think&#13;
&#13;
 that that is something that since not much has been said&#13;
&#13;
 about it, and given the hour, let's just perhaps say I&#13;
&#13;
 think that is something we should flag and probably will&#13;
&#13;
 return to in certain committee discussions because I think&#13;
&#13;
 that is an issue that is linked to resources and linked to&#13;
&#13;
 where responsibility resides.      And in our statement, we&#13;
&#13;
 did ask the question that we would appreciate an answer to&#13;
&#13;
 with respect to where responsibility will reside in the&#13;
                                                                    Page107&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Bank in the follow-through on this.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
             Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
             Matthias, please.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. MEYER:   I'm sorry.     I just forgot one very&#13;
&#13;
 practical aspect which I'd like to submit, since this&#13;
&#13;
 question of endorsement or how the Board deals with PRSP&#13;
&#13;
 is pretty much at the center of the debate.          One&#13;
&#13;
 possibility would be to have a summary of the Board's&#13;
&#13;
 discussion and consensus on PRSP made public the same way&#13;
&#13;
 as the PRSP and put it on the Web site, put it on the&#13;
&#13;
 Internet.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
             Other thoughts?&#13;
&#13;
             [No response.]&#13;
&#13;
             MR. SANDSTROM:    Masood, will you organize, start&#13;
&#13;
 the response?&#13;
&#13;
             MR. AHMED:   Thank you, Sven.       I think perhaps&#13;
&#13;
 the way to take this is there is a set of specific&#13;
&#13;
 questions on the paper which I'd like to get Ann to pick&#13;
&#13;
 up on.&#13;
&#13;
             There were a couple of questions about the&#13;
&#13;
 redeployment.    Is it going to be within-region, across&#13;
                                                                   Page108&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 regions, how are we going to manage that?           Can we come&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 back and have some discussion of it?        And I was hoping&#13;
&#13;
 that Joanne would be able to come and talk about that, and&#13;
&#13;
 also about the specific question that was raised by, I&#13;
&#13;
 believe it was Mr. Alyahya about do we preclude adjustment&#13;
&#13;
 lending in the base case.     So we'll come back to that&#13;
&#13;
 question, as well.&#13;
&#13;
           Then I think given the time, I would suggest&#13;
&#13;
 that we leave aside a set of issues, but happy to come&#13;
&#13;
 back to them indeed even now, which relate to more&#13;
&#13;
 information on what the substantive content might be, how&#13;
&#13;
 to do beyond what is in Box 3, the work that is underway&#13;
&#13;
 on tool kits that is essentially trying to flesh that out.&#13;
&#13;
           And I had suggested in the meeting, I believe,&#13;
&#13;
 on Thursday that in January, when we had the first cut of&#13;
&#13;
 those tool kits, we would be happy to organize a workshop&#13;
&#13;
 and anybody who is interested, you know, is more than&#13;
&#13;
 welcome to participate in that.       So my sense is that we&#13;
&#13;
 take note of all of those issues.       They are important&#13;
&#13;
 points, and unless people want to discuss them now,&#13;
&#13;
 including the link between growth and poverty reduction,&#13;
&#13;
 we'll come back to that.&#13;
&#13;
           And that is also linked to the question of the&#13;
                                                                Page109&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 role of WBI in terms of the whole effort of how do we take&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 those tool kits and what do we do with them.       Let's come&#13;
&#13;
 back to that later.   Similarly, I think there is a set of&#13;
&#13;
 questions about what more can we say about the&#13;
&#13;
 participatory process in terms of how can we structure it.&#13;
&#13;
 I think Mr. Wolfensohn gave what, in a sense, is our&#13;
&#13;
 current thinking on it.    We have to develop it case by&#13;
&#13;
 case.&#13;
&#13;
           There is Box 4 which lays out some questions&#13;
&#13;
 that might be considered in reviewing that.        I think what&#13;
&#13;
 Ann mentioned in her opening statement was that we are&#13;
&#13;
 proposing that the staff assessment would do a little more&#13;
&#13;
 structured discussion of the participatory process using&#13;
&#13;
 those questions, and those questions themselves will&#13;
&#13;
 evolve and be refined as we move forward.&#13;
&#13;
           So I take on board the different views, some&#13;
&#13;
 suggesting that we might go a bit further still, others&#13;
&#13;
 cautious about whether even that is too far, and we'll try&#13;
&#13;
 that out in the first few cases.       And, again, we're happy&#13;
&#13;
 to come back to it if people want to have more of a&#13;
&#13;
 discussion.&#13;
&#13;
           And then what I'd like to perhaps come back to,&#13;
&#13;
 which is really the issue that I think we need to spend a&#13;
                                                                   Page110&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 bit of time on, is the question of how we are going to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 move forward now on this link in terms of what does&#13;
&#13;
 endorsement mean, how do we link it to the lending&#13;
&#13;
 strategies, because that is clearly the issue on which we&#13;
&#13;
 do need to spend a few minutes trying to get clarity.&#13;
&#13;
             And I'll then also clarify that I think on the&#13;
&#13;
 HIPC timetable, Ann mentioned the state of our current&#13;
&#13;
 thinking on it in her introductory comments, and our&#13;
&#13;
 intention is to reflect that both in the summing-up and&#13;
&#13;
 once these documents are put out, subject to the Fund&#13;
&#13;
 Board's agreement tomorrow, onto the Web, at the same time&#13;
&#13;
 to issue a press brief which would have that information&#13;
&#13;
 in it.   But we'd be happy to provide more information on&#13;
&#13;
 that.&#13;
&#13;
             So let me turn to Ann first and then ask Joanne&#13;
&#13;
 to pick up, and then we'll come back to the question of&#13;
&#13;
 what does endorsement and linkage with lending mean.&#13;
&#13;
             MS. DUNCAN:   Thank you, Masood.        Well, as Masood&#13;
&#13;
 has indicated, there have been a lot of different comments&#13;
&#13;
 on the question of endorsement which I think we'll come&#13;
&#13;
 back to.&#13;
&#13;
             There were a number of suggestions that the&#13;
&#13;
 question of ownership should not be cosmetic or an optical&#13;
                                                                       Page111&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 illusion.    I think that is well-recognized in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 principles of the paper.      I think a lot of this will be--&#13;
&#13;
 the proof of the pudding will be in the eating, and it&#13;
&#13;
 will be a question of how we help the countries with the&#13;
&#13;
 early cases and a lot of it will be based on the behavior&#13;
&#13;
 of Bank and Fund staff.      So I hope that that cultural&#13;
&#13;
 shift will actually take place throughout the&#13;
&#13;
 organization.&#13;
&#13;
           Another question was on whether Bank and Fund&#13;
&#13;
 missions to support the PRSP would be separate from&#13;
&#13;
 lending missions.    I believe that is the intention that&#13;
&#13;
 they should be separated in terms of time, but obviously&#13;
&#13;
 not in terms of content.&#13;
&#13;
           There was another question about the governments&#13;
&#13;
 being fully involved at all stages and what is the process&#13;
&#13;
 being followed so far.      A number of cases we have before&#13;
&#13;
 us--Bolivia and Uganda, for example--in Uganda, as many of&#13;
&#13;
 you probably know, this was very much a government-owned&#13;
&#13;
 process from the beginning.       In Bolivia, similarly the&#13;
&#13;
 government has been involved from a very early stage.         So&#13;
&#13;
 I think we would like to use those models and have the&#13;
&#13;
 government fully involved at all stages and, in fact, not&#13;
&#13;
 proceed until the government is clearly committed to&#13;
                                                                    Page112&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 proceeding and take the lead there.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
            There were a few questions on how to judge the&#13;
&#13;
 participatory approach and process.         I think Masood has&#13;
&#13;
 touched on that.   We'll come back to that in the early&#13;
&#13;
 cases.   As somebody pointed out, a lot of the judgments&#13;
&#13;
 we'll have to make on a case-by-case basis.&#13;
&#13;
            On the list of which of the countries we'll be&#13;
&#13;
 considering in addition to those mentioned, I think Axel&#13;
&#13;
 may want to take up the question of the countries to be&#13;
&#13;
 considered under the HIPC Initiative.&#13;
&#13;
            On the question of how firm would be the&#13;
&#13;
 commitment of the external partners, what if they get&#13;
&#13;
 involved to influence the PRSP but don't then come through&#13;
&#13;
 in terms of financial commitment, I think it would be hard&#13;
&#13;
 for us to make a determination on that.             I think it would&#13;
&#13;
 just be a question of the partners taking the full&#13;
&#13;
 responsibility when they do participate and coming&#13;
&#13;
 through.   And if they don't intend to come through with&#13;
&#13;
 support, then perhaps sitting back and letting others be&#13;
&#13;
 more involved.&#13;
&#13;
            On the question of the interim PRSP and at what&#13;
&#13;
 point would we, quote, "exit" from the interim PRSP and&#13;
&#13;
 into the full PRSP, I think the interim PRSP is seen very&#13;
                                                                        Page113&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 much as the first stage for any country as the launch of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 the process.   So, by definition, there would only be one&#13;
&#13;
 interim PRSP, and thereafter we would expect to see a&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP.&#13;
&#13;
           I think that is based on the recognition that&#13;
&#13;
 each country will be starting from a different starting&#13;
&#13;
 point.   And so one would actually expect to see progress&#13;
&#13;
 over the years.   By year one, one would expect to see a&#13;
&#13;
 certain amount of progress in key dimensions, and I think&#13;
&#13;
 those dimensions would be, first of all, the diagnostics&#13;
&#13;
 and analysis of poverty; second, the government getting&#13;
&#13;
 together a shared vision in the society of what the&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction objectives are.       Obviously,&#13;
&#13;
 participation will be key to that process.&#13;
&#13;
           The third key dimension would be linking the&#13;
&#13;
 poverty outcomes with priority public actions in terms of&#13;
&#13;
 action implementation and really focus on those things&#13;
&#13;
 that are going to make a big difference to the lives of&#13;
&#13;
 the poor, and finally making sure that the implementation&#13;
&#13;
 of the strategy is monitored in an open, transparent and&#13;
&#13;
 participatory way with the key stakeholders.&#13;
&#13;
           So I think the vision is to expect that&#13;
&#13;
 countries will make progress on each of those dimensions&#13;
                                                             Page114&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 over time, not that one will go from zero to a quote,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 "perfect PRSP" overnight or between the interim PRSP and&#13;
&#13;
 the PRSP, but rather a continual progression on key&#13;
&#13;
 dimensions.&#13;
&#13;
           Those are the questions I had from the paper.&#13;
&#13;
 Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MS. SALOP:     Good afternoon.       Three questions I'm&#13;
&#13;
 going to address.    One is the budget issues that several&#13;
&#13;
 speakers raised; two, the adjustment links that Mr.&#13;
&#13;
 Alyahya raised; and then, three, CAS links with PRSP which&#13;
&#13;
 a number of speakers raised.&#13;
&#13;
           First, on the budget issues, as you saw in the&#13;
&#13;
 Internal Guidance Note, we have done some analysis of what&#13;
&#13;
 the incremental budget costs are to the Bank of rolling&#13;
&#13;
 out the PRSP process.      And as you know, we came forward&#13;
&#13;
 with the idea that we would not ask for a supplementary&#13;
&#13;
 appropriation at this time, but rather try to meet the&#13;
&#13;
 expenses with respect to redeployment from within.&#13;
&#13;
           That said, we are keeping a very close watch on&#13;
&#13;
 the situation.   The message has gone out to the staff and&#13;
&#13;
 to the country directors in the countries, particularly in&#13;
&#13;
 the Africa Region, that the incremental funding, should it&#13;
&#13;
 be needed, is there.     In the first instance, we have&#13;
                                                                      Page115&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 talked to the teams about their redeploying within&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 programs to the extent that is necessary; secondly, within&#13;
&#13;
 the region to the extent that that is appropriate; and&#13;
&#13;
 then, third, within the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
           Shengman Zhang is overall looking at the&#13;
&#13;
 resource picture, and we have this amount of redeployed&#13;
&#13;
 resources which we can then channel back to the country&#13;
&#13;
 teams or the regions should that prove necessary.    So we&#13;
&#13;
 do want to assure you that we are keeping a very close&#13;
&#13;
 watch on it, particularly for the Africa Region, as&#13;
&#13;
 Messrs. Toure and Hubloue have raised those particular&#13;
&#13;
 points.&#13;
&#13;
           For next year, we're also looking, and as Sven&#13;
&#13;
 mentioned the other day and as was mentioned this morning,&#13;
&#13;
 we will be looking at that picture very closely in the&#13;
&#13;
 context of the budget discussions for FY01 and the&#13;
&#13;
 Strategic Directions.&#13;
&#13;
           Now, in terms of this year, just one very quick&#13;
&#13;
 word on that.   Clearly, there are going to be incremental&#13;
&#13;
 costs in the PRSP program.     The question that we face,&#13;
&#13;
 though, is in some sense the adding-up question.     While we&#13;
&#13;
 can put together the incremental costs and give funding&#13;
&#13;
 for those programs, at the end of the day we're also going&#13;
                                                                 Page116&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 to need staff and staff resources to step forward to do&#13;
&#13;
 the work underlying those programs.&#13;
&#13;
           What we're not totally sure is how much on the&#13;
&#13;
 incremental staff side we can pull into the programs&#13;
&#13;
 within the year.   That lies behind the question of the&#13;
&#13;
 softness in the budgetary forecasts for this year.         If we&#13;
&#13;
 are successful in pulling in incremental staff and&#13;
&#13;
 resources, say, from short-term consultants to do the&#13;
&#13;
 work, the overall costs of the program will end up being&#13;
&#13;
 higher.   We'll have less net redeployment.         If it's lower,&#13;
&#13;
 we will end up redeploying more within the program.&#13;
&#13;
           So as I say, we're keeping a very close watch on&#13;
&#13;
 this situation both on the resource side and the overall&#13;
&#13;
 staff side.   The staffing side is being managed through&#13;
&#13;
 the network, through the PREM network, who is, of course,&#13;
&#13;
 managing the substantive work on the program overall.         So&#13;
&#13;
 that is on the budget.&#13;
&#13;
           Second, on the question of the adjustment&#13;
&#13;
 lending that Mr. Alyahya raised and whether, in fact--in&#13;
&#13;
 the paper, particularly in the Internal Guidance Note,&#13;
&#13;
 we've indicated that PRSP would be a necessary condition&#13;
&#13;
 for high-case lending and for adjustment lending within&#13;
                                                                      Page117&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 the base case.   And I think the question was specifically&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 with respect to the adjustment in the base case, and he&#13;
&#13;
 referred to a note that we put out last week on adjustment&#13;
&#13;
 lending and the Bank policy and practice with respect to&#13;
&#13;
 consulting with the IMF in the context of adjustment&#13;
&#13;
 lending.   And it's exactly that point which is relevant&#13;
&#13;
 here.&#13;
&#13;
            Here, our thinking was the following, and that&#13;
&#13;
 is for a country which is already in the PRSP program, if&#13;
&#13;
 there is not a PRSP in place, a satisfactory&#13;
&#13;
 implementation in place, then it has two possible reasons.&#13;
&#13;
 One, either the macro is off track, in which case per the&#13;
&#13;
 note we put out we would typically not be going ahead with&#13;
&#13;
 adjustment lending.   Or, alternatively, the Bank-supported&#13;
&#13;
 program is not on track.    In that case, as well, we&#13;
&#13;
 typically would not be going forward with adjustment&#13;
&#13;
 lending.&#13;
&#13;
            So from both sides of the house, we came to the&#13;
&#13;
 conclusion that within the base case we would not be doing&#13;
&#13;
 adjustment lending for countries who are otherwise&#13;
&#13;
 eligible for the PRSP program in the short run unless the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP is in place and on track.      So I hope you find that a&#13;
&#13;
 satisfactory explanation.     I'm happy to follow up in&#13;
                                                                 Page118&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 bilateral discussions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
            The third point: Many speakers raised the&#13;
&#13;
 questions about the links between the CAS, the PRSP, and&#13;
&#13;
 the CDF.   Just very quickly, one word on that overall&#13;
&#13;
 architecture.   As some of you may have seen, but you may&#13;
&#13;
 not have seen, given the abundance of papers before you in&#13;
&#13;
 recent days and weeks, we were to have had a discussion&#13;
&#13;
 last Friday on the CAS retrospective, and          that paper&#13;
&#13;
 deals with many of these issues in terms of the&#13;
&#13;
 relationship between the emerging PRSP process, the CDF&#13;
&#13;
 process, and the CAS process.&#13;
&#13;
            In terms of vision, I think what we very much&#13;
&#13;
 see is an interconnected process of these various papers.&#13;
&#13;
 And right now, what the CAS involves is basically three&#13;
&#13;
 main building blocks; one, a statement of the country&#13;
&#13;
 strategy and vision; two, a Bank assessment of the country&#13;
&#13;
 strategy and the constraints to development; and, three, a&#13;
&#13;
 statement of the Bank Group program, why it is the program&#13;
&#13;
 is what it is and what are the benchmarks by which&#13;
&#13;
 performance will be measured.&#13;
&#13;
            Essentially, what we have before us is an&#13;
&#13;
 opportunity to really unbundle, or as we have said in the&#13;
&#13;
 retrospective, unpack the CAS process, with the PRSP&#13;
                                                                 Page119&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 and/or CDF being really that first part of it standing on&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 its own and very much clearly underpinned and led by the&#13;
&#13;
 country itself; the second piece, the staff assessment, in&#13;
&#13;
 this case being a joint Bank/Fund assessment; and then the&#13;
&#13;
 third piece which will be the kernel of what is now the&#13;
&#13;
 CAS, the Bank Group business strategy going forward.          And&#13;
&#13;
 several speakers this morning, I think, have used the&#13;
&#13;
 vocabulary there.&#13;
&#13;
           Now, while that is the vision of these three&#13;
&#13;
 pieces--and I think the vision is also one of an&#13;
&#13;
 integrated vision, and an integrated discussion of the&#13;
&#13;
 three of them at the same time would be the best--in the&#13;
&#13;
 near term we will also have transition issues with respect&#13;
&#13;
 to that, also with respect to timing.           And it may well be&#13;
&#13;
 that the PRSP time frame is driven by considerations with&#13;
&#13;
 respect to HIPC, with respect to the PRGF, and may not be&#13;
&#13;
 exactly on the same time frame as the Bank program.&#13;
&#13;
           So it's in that context that we were looking for&#13;
&#13;
 flexibility with respect to the timing of these various&#13;
&#13;
 components.   But certainly--and to my neighbor, Mr. Toure,&#13;
&#13;
 I would like to reassure him that our thinking is very&#13;
&#13;
 much the idea to try to harmonize the overall timing and&#13;
&#13;
 to reduce duplication and certainly to eliminate any&#13;
                                                                      Page120&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 sources of contradiction, so that in the end we would have&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 these three pieces which currently are bundled up in the&#13;
&#13;
 CAS to be much more separated, and also then to give&#13;
&#13;
 greater voice to the country, of course, in laying out the&#13;
&#13;
 country vision, aspirations, objectives, and strategy.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you very much, Joanne.&#13;
&#13;
           Should we move on to the word "endorse" and&#13;
&#13;
 maybe hear first from Daoud.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. KHAIRALLAH:    It seems that this word has&#13;
&#13;
 given us a lot of difficulties, although management has&#13;
&#13;
 tried to explain by that we don't mean a formal legal&#13;
&#13;
 endorsement.   Notwithstanding that, difficulties persist.I&#13;
&#13;
 want to make it clear that neither the Bank nor the Board&#13;
&#13;
 has legal authority, standing, to endorse a document that&#13;
&#13;
 is issued and provided by a country.&#13;
&#13;
           What we mean by endorsement here--the word&#13;
&#13;
 "noted" was mentioned, which is a good contribution.       The&#13;
&#13;
 Board would note, would assess, would give input and&#13;
&#13;
 guidance, and basically would feel comfortable with this&#13;
&#13;
 strategy that would help the Board in taking whatever&#13;
&#13;
 decision with respect to a particular investment.&#13;
&#13;
           So the word "endorsement"--unfortunately, we&#13;
                                                                  Page121&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 couldn't find a better word that would engulf all this--is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 not meant to mean more than the Board would feel&#13;
&#13;
 comfortable with a strategy adopted by a country.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    Masood?&#13;
&#13;
           MR. AHMED:   I think that the way that Daoud has&#13;
&#13;
 laid it out is, in my mind, a sensible way to think about&#13;
&#13;
 it.   I don't think there's any real substantive&#13;
&#13;
 disagreement about what it is that we're trying to achieve&#13;
&#13;
 in the sense that I think the reason why the PRSP, which&#13;
&#13;
 is a country strategy document prepared by the country, is&#13;
&#13;
 being discussed by the Boards is because we are linking it&#13;
&#13;
 to the actions that the Bank will take.            It's a context&#13;
&#13;
 for the country assistance strategy and the lending&#13;
&#13;
 operational program contained therein for us.&#13;
&#13;
           And I think what we're struggling with is what's&#13;
&#13;
 the best way to characterize the two levels of engagement.&#13;
&#13;
 The reason why we're reviewing the PRSP is, as Daoud&#13;
&#13;
 pointed out, to take note of it, to provide feedback and&#13;
&#13;
 guidance, and to be comfortable that as a backdrop to what&#13;
&#13;
 we are going to be doing as a context for the Bank's own&#13;
&#13;
 subsequent actions, it provides a good way to go forward.&#13;
&#13;
           Then there is a more specific feedback in terms&#13;
&#13;
 of the links with the CAS.     I think that's the point that&#13;
                                                                     Page122&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Lewis was raising, also.    And there I think that there are&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 two points, specific ones, that were raised.          In some&#13;
&#13;
 sense, is it necessary and sufficient to have a PRSP, to&#13;
&#13;
 have a high-case?    It's not just necessary and sufficient&#13;
&#13;
 to have a PRSP, but it's the content of the PRSP which&#13;
&#13;
 sets the framework.     And ultimately we come back to this&#13;
&#13;
 discussion of substance over process.           We are saying it is&#13;
&#13;
 necessary because in some sense we're trying to structure&#13;
&#13;
 that discussion, but not sufficient.&#13;
&#13;
           And, secondly, then the guidance that we would&#13;
&#13;
 get from the Board would then enable us to look at the&#13;
&#13;
 specific lending scenarios within the CAS and the overall&#13;
&#13;
 framework of the CAS.      So I think that's how we see it.&#13;
&#13;
 Now, the question really is how does one formulate it in a&#13;
&#13;
 way that gets to the heart of that two-level relationship.&#13;
&#13;
           I think it's difficult to find an alternative&#13;
&#13;
 term for "endorse."     Maybe "take note" is an option, but&#13;
&#13;
 in some ways it's more than just simply taking note of&#13;
&#13;
 what is in there.    It's actually saying that what is in&#13;
&#13;
 there is a satisfactory basis on which to provide a&#13;
&#13;
 context for our operations, and that's why we came up with&#13;
&#13;
 this term "endorse."     So we're struggling to see if we can&#13;
&#13;
 find a better term, but that is really what has driven us&#13;
                                                                       Page123&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 to where we are now.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
             MR. SANDSTROM:      Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
             Any further thoughts or should we see where we&#13;
&#13;
 come out?&#13;
&#13;
             Lewis Holden, please.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. HOLDEN:     I suppose the difficulty I still&#13;
&#13;
 have with that, though, is that it almost implies a binary&#13;
&#13;
 situation where we either are comfortable or not.            And it&#13;
&#13;
 seems to me that more often than not, there are going to&#13;
&#13;
 be aspects of the PRSP that we're comfortable with and&#13;
&#13;
 aspects that we're less comfortable with, and that will be&#13;
&#13;
 reflected in the type and the level of our engagement.            So&#13;
&#13;
 that is what I'm still a little bit uncomfortable with.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. SANDSTROM:      Further comments.&#13;
&#13;
             Please.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. ALYAHYA:     There are just two clarifications.&#13;
&#13;
 One is about having an annex or table showing the role of&#13;
&#13;
 donors in the preparation--or giving technical assistance&#13;
&#13;
 to the country in the preparation of that.             The other one&#13;
&#13;
 is right now in the CAS, if there is a major disagreement&#13;
&#13;
 between the government and the Bank, we allow them to put&#13;
&#13;
 detail on that, and whether if there is a major&#13;
&#13;
 disagreement or the staff assessment is negative, we&#13;
                                                                        Page124&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 should allow the country an opportunity to comment on the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                       MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                             507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                           Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                               (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 staff assessment and therefore attach that for information&#13;
&#13;
 to the Board.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. SANDSTROM:   Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
             Luc, please.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. HUBLOUE:   Yes, Chairman.       I don't want to&#13;
&#13;
 prolong the discussion on this issue of terminology, but&#13;
&#13;
 if there is one thing I would like to caution against, it&#13;
&#13;
 is that the words just "take note of" would slip into the&#13;
&#13;
 whole approach of dealing with this because then I'm&#13;
&#13;
 afraid we are going to open the door to the PFP kind of&#13;
&#13;
 approach.    They are also distributed for us to take note&#13;
&#13;
 of and that is what we do with them.&#13;
&#13;
             The other thing is I think we don't have to have&#13;
&#13;
 illusions about all that.      I'm perfectly happy to live&#13;
&#13;
 with another word than "endorse," but if we are not going&#13;
&#13;
 to endorse it, someone else is going to do it for us.             And&#13;
&#13;
 that is probably going to be management when it enters&#13;
&#13;
 into the final discussion with the government on how it&#13;
&#13;
 feels that really the final product should look like&#13;
&#13;
 before it is ready for being a basis for Bank lending.&#13;
&#13;
             So, you know, we may be perfectly happy to live&#13;
&#13;
 with that situation, but I'm not necessarily sure that it&#13;
                                                                         Page125&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 is the most transparent one.       So I think the discussion&#13;
&#13;
 should continue to be very open on that.&#13;
&#13;
            MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you, Luc.&#13;
&#13;
            Is there any better word in your language,&#13;
&#13;
 Stephen?&#13;
&#13;
            MR. PICKFORD:    I can't think of one, but then&#13;
&#13;
 I'm not sure we ought to spend that much more time trying&#13;
&#13;
 to find a better word.&#13;
&#13;
            I think the discussion has actually brought out&#13;
&#13;
 some quite useful aspects; I think the concept of a&#13;
&#13;
 spectrum that Lewis introduced, although it will be multi-&#13;
&#13;
 dimensional.   The idea of building a degree of comfort is&#13;
&#13;
 also a useful one.&#13;
&#13;
            Like Luc, I think "take note" is probably too&#13;
&#13;
 passive and doesn't really reflect the richness.      I think&#13;
&#13;
 it is also worth injecting the sense that there is--while&#13;
&#13;
 it's not formal approval, nevertheless the degree of&#13;
&#13;
 comfort derived from the PRSP, about the PRSP, will&#13;
&#13;
 influence decisions about the degree of lending under&#13;
&#13;
 other programs.&#13;
&#13;
            And I suspect that all of those elements will be&#13;
&#13;
 always imperfectly couched in one word, but I can't think&#13;
                                                                 Page126&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 of a better one.   And as long as we know what we mean,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 then that is really all that matters.         I suspect also what&#13;
&#13;
 we mean by it will evolve as we get through the first few&#13;
&#13;
 cases and we'll decide whether the process is working or&#13;
&#13;
 not.&#13;
&#13;
            You know, we'll reach a degree of comfort about&#13;
&#13;
 the process, as well as about the PRSPs, I suspect.        And&#13;
&#13;
 one suggestion--I can't remember who made it--which I&#13;
&#13;
 think is useful is that we should really use the&#13;
&#13;
 opportunity of the discussion to producing a summing-up&#13;
&#13;
 that reflects the sort of comments and views and richness&#13;
&#13;
 of the discussion.      And I don't see any reason why that&#13;
&#13;
 shouldn't be publicly available as a commentary, if you&#13;
&#13;
 like, on the PRSP.&#13;
&#13;
            One way, I suspect, of avoiding or getting&#13;
&#13;
 around the problem that people feel about this is, as I&#13;
&#13;
 suggested, trying as hard as possible to harmonize the&#13;
&#13;
 timing of the discussion between, on the one hand, the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP which is country-driven, on the other hand the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
 response to that, which is why what Joanne said was very&#13;
&#13;
 helpful.   And I think we should try hard to, if you like--&#13;
&#13;
 use another unfortunate word--we should collapse those&#13;
&#13;
 discussions.&#13;
                                                                     Page127&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           MR. AHMED:    Sorry, not to prolong it, but just&#13;
&#13;
 to make two points.    I think, one, to confirm that I think&#13;
&#13;
 the notion that the role that donors have played in&#13;
&#13;
 providing technical assistance and attaching that to the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP is certainly a very good idea, and we would certainly&#13;
&#13;
 be happy with that and encourage it.&#13;
&#13;
           Similarly, from our perspective, I don't think&#13;
&#13;
 we see any difficulty with the notion that if there is a&#13;
&#13;
 continuing disagreements about assessments or about&#13;
&#13;
 policies, then that should be flagged in the document, so&#13;
&#13;
 not an issue on that.&#13;
&#13;
           And, finally, just to make one point that I&#13;
&#13;
 think the valuable addition of the last few minutes in&#13;
&#13;
 helping to think this through is also not to think of it&#13;
&#13;
 as a binary process, but rather that, in a sense, the&#13;
&#13;
 guidance from the Boards would be very much also on areas&#13;
&#13;
 of weaknesses, the extent to which there was complete&#13;
&#13;
 endorsement of some issues that were still there.     And&#13;
&#13;
 that would then drive the nature and scope of the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
 assistance strategy as well.      So I think thinking of it as&#13;
&#13;
 a more graduated process certainly helps in doing that.&#13;
&#13;
           And just to close with the point that it's also&#13;
                                                                  Page128&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 important not to think of this as a "one of" process.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 What we are saying is that this is an ongoing exercise&#13;
&#13;
 that the country is undertaking in which this kind of&#13;
&#13;
 feedback from the Boards on a particular iteration of a&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP is very useful input for them as they think about&#13;
&#13;
 where they go next in terms of issues.&#13;
&#13;
           So I don't necessarily see the PRSP discussion&#13;
&#13;
 by the Board as being the end of the exercise.     It's&#13;
&#13;
 really an important end point in a cycle, but it is a&#13;
&#13;
 continuing exercise in which the country will be embarked,&#13;
&#13;
 and successive iterations of PRSPs done by the country&#13;
&#13;
 would benefit from this and other discussions in other&#13;
&#13;
 institutions which would also be using that strategy as a&#13;
&#13;
 framework for their own actions.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           Matthias?&#13;
&#13;
           MR. MEYER:   I mean, of course, I like this&#13;
&#13;
 discussion very much because we're trying to find a&#13;
&#13;
 practical way to determine what the Board should be doing,&#13;
&#13;
 and this is a general problem we have in the Board and I&#13;
&#13;
 hope we address that now through this new committee and&#13;
&#13;
 determine much better what do we really mean when we&#13;
&#13;
 discuss something and what is the output we expect and how&#13;
                                                              Page129&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 is this output being put into some form which represents a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 consensus.   I think we have not been very good at this in&#13;
&#13;
 many areas, and maybe if I might add that note, we have&#13;
&#13;
 not always maybe also been given the support by management&#13;
&#13;
 to reach very clear conclusions and consensus.&#13;
&#13;
           Now, here, I think we're being a little bit too&#13;
&#13;
 nice with each other this morning, in the sense that this&#13;
&#13;
 discussion on PRSP, although it is, of course, the basis&#13;
&#13;
 for a CAS and then it could lead to different lending&#13;
&#13;
 scenarios, and so on, it is also the basis for a decision&#13;
&#13;
 on whether a country is being included in HIPC or not.&#13;
&#13;
           In other words, it's a yes or no decision, and&#13;
&#13;
 once a country is included, this not only means that it&#13;
&#13;
 gets important financial support over a period of time,&#13;
&#13;
 but it also means that as the Initiative, as we know, is&#13;
&#13;
 not totally funded, it means probably that in each case,&#13;
&#13;
 at least after the first three or four cases, that there&#13;
&#13;
 is going to be a funding drive.       And we will have to&#13;
&#13;
 convince donors and the international community to fund&#13;
&#13;
 this program which is expressed in part through this PRSP.&#13;
&#13;
           So, you know, we do not have a gradual scenario&#13;
&#13;
 where we can agree or not agree, or agree on some aspects,&#13;
&#13;
 not agree on other aspects.     At the end, we have to&#13;
                                                              Page130&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 endorse the PRSP as the basis for very important support&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 by the international community to a specific country.         And&#13;
&#13;
 so in that sense the significance of that endorsement&#13;
&#13;
 might be a little bit bigger than what some people would&#13;
&#13;
 like to have it.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:     Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
           Why don't I try the key paragraph in the&#13;
&#13;
 summing-up the way we have it now, and then later I'll com&#13;
&#13;
 back to the full summing-up.&#13;
&#13;
           Directors agreed that the PRSP would provide a&#13;
&#13;
 context for concessional lending to support countries and&#13;
&#13;
 for debt relief under the HIPC Initiative.          They agreed&#13;
&#13;
 that while the Board would consider and comment on the&#13;
&#13;
 overall approach set out in the PRSP, it would endorse the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP and provide guidance to management insofar as the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP relates to the policies and programs within the areas&#13;
&#13;
 of the Bank's responsibility.       The PRSP and the Board's&#13;
&#13;
 guidance would then the guidance for the CAS and the CAS&#13;
&#13;
 lending scenarios.&#13;
&#13;
           So we've divided it into two parts.         First, the&#13;
&#13;
 Board would consider and comment on the overall approach.&#13;
&#13;
 Secondly, it would endorse the PRSP and provide guidance&#13;
&#13;
 to management insofar as the PRSP relates to the Bank's&#13;
                                                                     Page131&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 policies and programs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           Mr. Balduino?&#13;
&#13;
           MR. BALDUINO:    Yes, thank you very much.    I&#13;
&#13;
 think the language is very interesting, but the question&#13;
&#13;
 is whether we would not be freezing the fact that the PRSP&#13;
&#13;
 and the consideration of the CAS would not be collapsible&#13;
&#13;
 because then we would be making really two--because I&#13;
&#13;
 think the intention is to make the two even come together,&#13;
&#13;
 so the CAS would--&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    No.    We would keep the two&#13;
&#13;
 distinct, but we would streamline them so they fit&#13;
&#13;
 together better than the CAS has related to other&#13;
&#13;
 documents in the past.&#13;
&#13;
           But on the endorsement, does it work?      Should we&#13;
&#13;
 simply move ahead on this basis?       We still have to listen&#13;
&#13;
 to the Fund Board tomorrow, and then over time we can&#13;
&#13;
 adjust this as we learn.&#13;
&#13;
           Mr. Singh?&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SINGH:   This summary has a very fascinating&#13;
&#13;
 aspect.   Possibly for the first time, we have the&#13;
&#13;
 deliberations of the Board to be viewed in two parts.       One&#13;
&#13;
 is a part which deals statistically with national&#13;
&#13;
 governments, and the other is the part which will deal&#13;
                                                                   Page132&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 directly with the management.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           We largely function through the management, so&#13;
&#13;
 whatever we say or whatever we do not say are the&#13;
&#13;
 components of our directions or guidance to the&#13;
&#13;
 management.   Now, here one part is not meant for that.         So&#13;
&#13;
 what we are trying to endorse is endorse things which will&#13;
&#13;
 constitute guidance to the management.&#13;
&#13;
           The comments that we are making would constitute&#13;
&#13;
 something which is related to the national government.          I&#13;
&#13;
 think there is a dichotomy between the two.         So what I&#13;
&#13;
 will suggest, Mr. Chairman, is that if the draft summary&#13;
&#13;
 could be given to us for a look before you circulate it,&#13;
&#13;
 because this can be liable to interpretations and will put&#13;
&#13;
 the deliberations of the Board on totally a new path which&#13;
&#13;
 is not intended.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:     Okay.    We need to get this over&#13;
&#13;
 to the Fund by the end of the day, so we don't have much&#13;
&#13;
 time.&#13;
&#13;
           Any other thoughts?       I should read the whole&#13;
&#13;
 summing-up, also, but Stephen?&#13;
&#13;
           MR. PICKFORD:     I'm still not all that&#13;
&#13;
 comfortable with this dichotomy which is actually rather&#13;
&#13;
 starker even than the paper itself between, on the one&#13;
                                                                      Page133&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 hand, commenting on the overall strategy and then&#13;
&#13;
 endorsing in the areas of the Bank's own responsibilities.&#13;
&#13;
           I heard the discussion around the table.          I&#13;
&#13;
 don't think there's that very stark element here.          I mean,&#13;
&#13;
 realistically, the PRSP is one of the inputs into the&#13;
&#13;
 Board's judgments about lending operations, and indeed the&#13;
&#13;
 HIPC decisions.   And I don't think realistically we can&#13;
&#13;
 ignore, for instance, in this Board whether there is a&#13;
&#13;
 sound and sustainable macro framework in place.          So I&#13;
&#13;
 think the distinction in the wording is rather too stark.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:      Okay.    I think we're eating into&#13;
&#13;
 your lunch hour and several EDs have left.           What we may&#13;
&#13;
 want to do is take some time and work on the language,&#13;
&#13;
 come back to you, as Mr. Singh suggested, in the afternoon&#13;
&#13;
 and see if we can't reconcile these views.           And that would&#13;
&#13;
 also give us a chance to consult with the Fund colleagues.&#13;
&#13;
 So let's do that.    We'll try to do it within an hour or&#13;
&#13;
 two, depending on when we can get a hold of people.&#13;
&#13;
           But should I read the overall summing-up, also,&#13;
&#13;
 so you get that, and then we'll circulate the full piece.&#13;
&#13;
           First of all, this summing-up will try to&#13;
&#13;
 capture the main themes.      The richness of the discussion&#13;
                                                                       Page134&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 we'll capture separately and build on as we move forward,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 but these are the main themes that are important also for&#13;
&#13;
 the Fund tomorrow.&#13;
&#13;
           First, Directors endorsed the overall approach&#13;
&#13;
 set out in the paper, and welcomed the progress made in&#13;
&#13;
 operationalizing the PRSP concept.        There was general&#13;
&#13;
 agreement with the principles underlying the PRSPs, namely&#13;
&#13;
 that they should be country-driven with broad&#13;
&#13;
 participation of civil society and development partners;&#13;
&#13;
 that they should reflect the country-specific nature and&#13;
&#13;
 determinants of poverty; and that they should be results-&#13;
&#13;
 oriented and link public actions to poverty outcomes,&#13;
&#13;
 especially through faster and broad-based growth.&#13;
&#13;
 Directors noted that these principles characterize the&#13;
&#13;
 Comprehensive Development Framework.&#13;
&#13;
           Directors emphasized that flexibility should be&#13;
&#13;
 built into the process to reflect diversity in country&#13;
&#13;
 context and capacity, and to develop and implement poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction strategies.    Many Directors stressed that this&#13;
&#13;
 approach would likely result in greater variation in both&#13;
&#13;
 substance and form across the future country programs&#13;
&#13;
 considered for support by the Bretton Woods institutions.&#13;
&#13;
           Directors stressed that many countries would&#13;
                                                               Page135&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 need assistance to prepare such comprehensive and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 participatory strategies, and called for the Bank and&#13;
&#13;
 other bilateral and multilateral agencies to treat such&#13;
&#13;
 assistance as a matter of high priority.           They emphasized&#13;
&#13;
 the importance of countries reaching out early to other&#13;
&#13;
 development partners so that the PRSP initiative could&#13;
&#13;
 gain from their perspective and support at both the&#13;
&#13;
 country and agency level.&#13;
&#13;
           Most Directors agreed that the joint staff&#13;
&#13;
 assessment which would accompany the PRSP to the Boards&#13;
&#13;
 should focus on the evaluation of substantive policies and&#13;
&#13;
 only describe the participatory process used to define key&#13;
&#13;
 anti-poverty actions and monitoring procedures.&#13;
&#13;
           Some Directors, however, also recommended that&#13;
&#13;
 staff assessment should go a step further and give an&#13;
&#13;
 evaluation of the participatory process, or at least&#13;
&#13;
 provide a more structured description of the participatory&#13;
&#13;
 process that had been followed in each country case.&#13;
&#13;
           Then would follow the paragraph on endorsement&#13;
&#13;
 which I mentioned earlier which we will work on.&#13;
&#13;
           And then Directors stressed that to ensure&#13;
&#13;
 country ownership, poverty reduction strategies will take&#13;
&#13;
 time to establish.   They were also concerned, however,&#13;
                                                                      Page136&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 that unnecessary delays should not be created in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 provision of debt relief under the HIPC Initiative, and&#13;
&#13;
 welcomed the concept of interim PRSPs as a means of&#13;
&#13;
 avoiding such delays in the transition period.&#13;
&#13;
           With respect to retroactive cases under the&#13;
&#13;
 Enhanced HIPC Initiative, most Directors recommended that&#13;
&#13;
 the adoption of a participatory PRSP should be a&#13;
&#13;
 sufficient requirement for the completion point, subject&#13;
&#13;
 to progress in policies and poverty reduction measures.&#13;
&#13;
           Some Directors indicated that they support even&#13;
&#13;
 faster progress toward the provision of debt relief, and&#13;
&#13;
 asked that the period between decision and completion&#13;
&#13;
 points for these countries be kept relatively short or&#13;
&#13;
 collapsed altogether.&#13;
&#13;
           Directors took note of the expected timetable&#13;
&#13;
 for processing HIPC cases in the coming months.&#13;
&#13;
 Specifically, they welcomed that under current plans and&#13;
&#13;
 subject to country progress, it was expected that three&#13;
&#13;
 countries would reach their decision points in January--&#13;
&#13;
 Bolivia, Mauritania and Uganda--with Mozambique following&#13;
&#13;
 shortly thereafter.   It was further expected that four&#13;
&#13;
 additional countries would reach their decision points in&#13;
&#13;
 the subsequent quarter.&#13;
                                                             Page137&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
            There was general agreement that the PRSP&#13;
&#13;
 process would need careful review.        Directors welcomed the&#13;
&#13;
 proposal of a status report by the time of the spring&#13;
&#13;
 meetings, a progress report in the fall of 2000, and a&#13;
&#13;
 full review at the end of 2001.&#13;
&#13;
            Finally, Directors commended the staff of the&#13;
&#13;
 Bank and the Fund for their continued strong collaboration&#13;
&#13;
 on the PRSP exercise and for their work in preparing the&#13;
&#13;
 paper.   They agreed that, subject to the outcome of the&#13;
&#13;
 Fund Board discussion tomorrow, the joint paper and this&#13;
&#13;
 summing-up should be posted on the Bank's Web site as&#13;
&#13;
 drafts for consultation.&#13;
&#13;
            Hein, please.&#13;
&#13;
            MR. BOGAARD:    A very good summary, I think.    At&#13;
&#13;
 one point in the beginning of the summary, you put a lot&#13;
&#13;
 of emphasis on the demands about flexibility toward&#13;
&#13;
 countries.   Whereas we have not discussed the substance of&#13;
&#13;
 guidance yet, there was a clear call of a number of&#13;
&#13;
 Directors, I think, to put some more guidance in the&#13;
&#13;
 framework, in several boxes in the paper, for instance, in&#13;
&#13;
 the tool kits.&#13;
&#13;
            MR. SANDSTROM:   I think the views were quite&#13;
                                                                    Page138&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 diverse.   I thought there was quite a range of views&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 stressing the flexibility and diversity.            But we'll take&#13;
&#13;
 another look at the language.&#13;
&#13;
             I don't want to get into debate on each point.&#13;
&#13;
 We'll take your points and we'll then work on it.&#13;
&#13;
             Mr. Haque?&#13;
&#13;
             MR. HAQUE:   Mr. Chairman, I made a somewhat&#13;
&#13;
 radical suggestion which I thought would merit a mention,&#13;
&#13;
 which was that in order to resolve the question which&#13;
&#13;
 Board would be competent, whether the strategy is a&#13;
&#13;
 segmented strategy or integrated strategy, I had suggested&#13;
&#13;
 that the endorsement, if we use the word "endorsement" or&#13;
&#13;
 some other word, must be done by the joint meeting of both&#13;
&#13;
 Boards.&#13;
&#13;
             This was meant to resolve one or two specific&#13;
&#13;
 problems.    One was that, as I said earlier, the question&#13;
&#13;
 was what will be the competence of the Board, whether one&#13;
&#13;
 Board will be only confining itself to its own mandate or&#13;
&#13;
 not.&#13;
&#13;
             And, second, as I said, the question was whether&#13;
&#13;
 it is an integrated strategy or not.         And, thirdly, even&#13;
&#13;
 the question will be this will, in my view, as stated&#13;
&#13;
 earlier, make even less formal the word "endorsement."&#13;
                                                                      Page139&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           So I suggest that my suggestion may very well&#13;
&#13;
 find a mention when you are making a summing-up.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:     Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           Mr. Abraham?&#13;
&#13;
           MR. ABRAHAM:    Just a short note, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
 I think that was an excellent summary as far as I can&#13;
&#13;
 tell.   Just one thing that was really mentioned by a&#13;
&#13;
 number of Chairs, and that is the recognition of good&#13;
&#13;
 policy and whether somehow we would incorporate it there&#13;
&#13;
 because that is at the heart of a lot of programs that we&#13;
&#13;
 do recognize this if we want to make progress.          So I&#13;
&#13;
 thought maybe somehow it could be included.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:     Thank you; good point.&#13;
&#13;
           Jean Pesme?&#13;
&#13;
           MR. PESME:    Thank you, Sven.        Very briefly, and&#13;
&#13;
 not to open a discussion on these specific points, you&#13;
&#13;
 mentioned several countries which could come before the&#13;
&#13;
 spring meetings.   And if I refer to Table 2 in the costing&#13;
&#13;
 exercise, I had the feeling there were more countries than&#13;
&#13;
 the number you mentioned, so just to draw your attention&#13;
&#13;
 on this point.&#13;
                                                                     Page140&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
             MR. SANDSTROM:   Stephen?&#13;
&#13;
             MR. PICKFORD:    The same point.        I thought last&#13;
&#13;
 Wednesday we were told up to five.         The number has gone&#13;
&#13;
 down now.    And to pick up on the point that Mr. Haque&#13;
&#13;
 made, I think it is worth injecting some sense about the&#13;
&#13;
 way in which the two Boards are going to have to work out&#13;
&#13;
 some method of proceeding.&#13;
&#13;
             Personally, I think perhaps a joint informal&#13;
&#13;
 session first and then the two Boards go away and formally&#13;
&#13;
 consider, and also take decisions about the issues that&#13;
&#13;
 are relevant to the two institutions might be the way&#13;
&#13;
 forward.    But we're going to have to work these procedures&#13;
&#13;
 out.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. SANDSTROM:   Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
             Other advice?&#13;
&#13;
             If not, we'll work on this.       These were good&#13;
&#13;
 additions.    So we'll work on this and focus on this&#13;
&#13;
 paragraph on endorsement.      We'll circulate, then, the&#13;
&#13;
 revised summing-up later in the afternoon.            Hopefully, we&#13;
&#13;
 don't need a meeting tonight, but we'll see how it goes.&#13;
&#13;
             Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
             [Whereupon, at 1:33 p.m., the informal meeting&#13;
                                                                       Page141&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 of the Executive Directors was concluded.]&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="15512614">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/12/15512614/transcript-meeting-executive-directors-bank-ida-held-monday-december-20-1999
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/12/15512614/transcript-meeting-executive-directors-bank-ida-held-monday-december-20-1999</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1999/12/15512614/transcript-meeting-executive-directors-bank-ida-held-monday-december-20-1999</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2011-11-28T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2016-01-14T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b0828cf732</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0828cf732</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/11/30/000386194_20111130003835/Rendered/INDEX/657710TRANSCRI00disclosed0110280110.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/11/30/000386194_20111130003835/Rendered/PDF/657710TRANSCRI00disclosed0110280110.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2011-11-30T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1999-12-20T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of meeting of the Executive
            Directors of the Bank and IDA, held on Monday, December 20, 1999
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This transcript, from the session of the
            Executive Directors of the Bank and the International
            Development Association held on Monday, December 20, 1999,
            covers poverty reduction strategy papers and the operational issues.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of meeting of the Executive
            Directors of the Bank and IDA, held on Monday, December 20, 1999
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of meeting of the
            Executive Directors of the Bank and IDA, held on Monday,
            December 20, 1999</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1999/12/15512614/transcript-meeting-executive-directors-bank-ida-held-monday-december-20-1999</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Country Strategy &amp; Performance,Corporate Law,Poverty Monitoring &amp; Analysis,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Knowledge for Development</subtopic>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <teratopic>Education,Law and Development,Poverty Reduction,Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000386194_20111130003835</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Board transcript</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Education,Law and Development,Poverty Reduction,Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            adjustment, adjustment lending, assistance
            program, assistance programs, autonomy, best practices,
            Board meeting, Board meetings, Board members, CAS, CASs, CG,
            collaboration, collective, common ground, communities,
            COMPANY, concessional assistance, concessional lending,
            debt, Debt Relief, development strategies, discussion,
            discussions, documents, economic growth, equal treatment,
            ESW, experimentation, financial policies, flexibility, good
            practice, HIPC, idea, ideas, income, incorporated,
            innovation, intermediate indicators, international
            development goals, intervention, joint venture, land
            ownership, leading, learning, limited, little attention,
            logic, missions, negotiation, outcome indicators,
            participatory approach, participatory process, partnership,
            portfolio performance, poverty alleviation, poverty
            outcomes, Poverty Reduction, poverty reduction strategies,
            regional development, regional development banks, semantics,
            shareholders, societies, society, stakeholders, technical
            assistance, thinking, transition economies, transitional
            arrangements, Transparency, variety, vision, wisdom
        </keywd>
        <owner>Policy and Operations (SECPO)</owner>
        <repnb>65771</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pro-Poor Growth and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Country Strategy and Performance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Strategy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Generic Name List</ml:concept><ml:concept>Generics</ml:concept><ml:concept>List of Generic Drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Off patent drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIPC</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pro-Poor Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Country Strategy &amp; Performance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Financial Architecture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Generic Drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Policy Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Relief</ml:concept><ml:concept>Heavily Indebted Poor Countries (HIPC)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>