<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
                                              65772&#13;
   INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
&#13;
           INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 Thursday, September 9, 1999&#13;
&#13;
                                 Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           The meeting of the Committee of the Whole&#13;
&#13;
 was convened at 12:32 p.m., in the Board Room, 700&#13;
&#13;
 Eighteenth Street, N.W., Washington, D.C., Mr. Sven&#13;
&#13;
 Sandstrom, presiding.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                               Page1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
                       C O N T E N T S&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 ITEM                                                PAGE&#13;
&#13;
  1       Enhancing the Poverty Focus of the Bank's&#13;
          Work                                         3&#13;
            A. Building Poverty Reduction Strategies&#13;
               in Developing Countries [SecM99-604]&#13;
            B. Heavily Indebted Poor Countries [HIPC]&#13;
               Initiative: Strengthening the Link&#13;
               Between Debt Relief and Poverty&#13;
               Reduction [IDA/SecM99-545]&#13;
            C. Social and Structural Reviews -&#13;
               Progress and Lessons [SecM99-556]&#13;
            Opening Remarks by Mr. Masood Ahmed        4&#13;
            Opening Remarks by Mr. Michael Walton      6&#13;
            Opening Remarks by Mr. Peter Fallon       12&#13;
&#13;
              Mr.   Al-Saad                           17&#13;
              Mr.   Bachmayer                         21&#13;
              Mr.   Schaeffer                         27&#13;
              Mr.   Ako-Adjei                         35&#13;
              Mr.   Ghattas                           39&#13;
              Mr.   Alvarez                           43&#13;
              Mr.   Sinclair                          49&#13;
              Mr.   Hyden                             56&#13;
              Mr.   Pesme                             61&#13;
              Mr.   Kamitomai                         70&#13;
              Ms.   Cordeiro                          74&#13;
              Mr.   Bogaard                           84&#13;
              Mr.   Pandian                           89&#13;
              Mr.   Binkert                           94&#13;
              Mr.   Garcia                            98&#13;
              Ms.   Zou                              101&#13;
              Ms.   Piercy                           106&#13;
&#13;
 Chairman's Summary                                   140&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            Page2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
                     P R O C E E D I N G S&#13;
&#13;
             MR. SANDSTROM:    I think we should at least start&#13;
&#13;
 before we break for lunch so let's get moving.           We, as Jim&#13;
&#13;
 said, we will be discussing three papers.           First, Building&#13;
&#13;
 Poverty Reduction Strategies in Developing Countries;&#13;
&#13;
 secondly, the HIPC Initiative: Strengthening the Link&#13;
&#13;
 between Debt Relief and Poverty Reduction.          That paper, as&#13;
&#13;
 you know, was prepared jointly by the IDA and Fund staff.&#13;
&#13;
 And thirdly, Social and Structural Reviews - Progress and&#13;
&#13;
 Lessons.&#13;
&#13;
             You've also received for information a parallel&#13;
&#13;
 IMF paper on the "Review of Social Issues and Policies in&#13;
&#13;
 IMF-Supported Programs," and this paper together with a&#13;
&#13;
 joint HIPC linked paper will be discussed by the Fund&#13;
&#13;
 board on September 13.&#13;
&#13;
             And I believe we have colleagues from the IMF&#13;
&#13;
 here, Russell Kincaid, David Andrews and Christian&#13;
&#13;
 Schiller.    They are here.    Great.    Welcome.    And we have a&#13;
&#13;
 number of statements from Anna Brandt, Godfrey Gaoseb,&#13;
&#13;
 Stephen Pickford, Mr. Toure and Mr. Wan Abdullah.          And&#13;
&#13;
 Masood will give a brief introduction first providing the&#13;
&#13;
 connections between the three papers and then Mike Walton&#13;
&#13;
 will give the introduction on the poverty reduction&#13;
                                                                       Page3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 strategy paper and then Peter Fallon on the HIPC link&#13;
&#13;
 paper.   So Masood, please.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. AHMED:   Thank you very much, Sven.   Just&#13;
&#13;
 very briefly, to pick up on the point that we left off at&#13;
&#13;
 the end of July when we briefed you on the overall board&#13;
&#13;
 program leading up to the poverty action plan or the&#13;
&#13;
 different elements of it.     You'll recall that we had&#13;
&#13;
 talked about one set of papers that we would be working on&#13;
&#13;
 which would be trying to strengthen the link between the&#13;
&#13;
 poverty focus of country specific work, and that's where&#13;
&#13;
 we were going to talk about the work that we were going to&#13;
&#13;
 do to build greater links between our own country programs&#13;
&#13;
 and country strategies and their impact on poverty, and&#13;
&#13;
 how we wanted to ensure that the same approach was also&#13;
&#13;
 consistent with what was being done in the HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 enhancements.   And that's why those two papers in some&#13;
&#13;
 sense are very much dovetailed because the underlying&#13;
&#13;
 approach that we want to apply in the HIPC cases is really&#13;
&#13;
 a way of moving forward rapidly with the same approach&#13;
&#13;
 that we want to generalize and apply more broadly to all&#13;
&#13;
 of our country assistance strategies.&#13;
&#13;
           The Social and Structural Reviews came up at&#13;
&#13;
 that time and we mentioned that we saw these as a key&#13;
                                                              Page4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 building block in terms of identifying the main obstacles&#13;
&#13;
 that impeded the poverty reduction and development&#13;
&#13;
 objectives in each country and so we wanted to circulate&#13;
&#13;
 that status report on the early social and structural&#13;
&#13;
 reviews as background for today's discussion because again&#13;
&#13;
 that's one of the building blocks that leads into it.&#13;
&#13;
            I just want to say one more word that in&#13;
&#13;
 addition to the paper that Sven referred to that is the,&#13;
&#13;
 if you like, the corollary paper in the Fund in some ways&#13;
&#13;
 that's being done on social aspects of the Fund's&#13;
&#13;
 programs, which we circulated to you for background&#13;
&#13;
 information, our paper on building poverty reduction&#13;
&#13;
 strategies at the country level is also being circulated&#13;
&#13;
 for background to the Fund board's discussion because&#13;
&#13;
 again we do see all of these three pieces as being very&#13;
&#13;
 much an integrated and joined up approach to moving&#13;
&#13;
 forward on making poverty more central to our collective&#13;
&#13;
 efforts.&#13;
&#13;
            And a final point I want to make is that on&#13;
&#13;
 Tuesday, we talked about the social aspects of crisis,&#13;
&#13;
 financial crisis, and a number of executive directors&#13;
&#13;
 raised the question of how that particular effort fitted&#13;
&#13;
 into this overall framework for enhancing the poverty&#13;
                                                              Page5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 focus of our work, and when Mike talks about the approach&#13;
&#13;
 here, we will try and pick up on making that connection&#13;
&#13;
 clearer because we see that as being again one of the how-&#13;
&#13;
 to efforts dealing with one specific source of&#13;
&#13;
 vulnerability that affects poverty outcomes in certain set&#13;
&#13;
 of countries.   So again the connection there is one that&#13;
&#13;
 we would like to make explicitly.        So that's just to try&#13;
&#13;
 and put it in terms of context, but the next thing would&#13;
&#13;
 be to get more introduction on the specific papers&#13;
&#13;
 themselves.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:     Thanks, Masood.        Mike, please.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. WALTON:    Thank you very much.        The proposed&#13;
&#13;
 approach to incorporating poverty into country strategies&#13;
&#13;
 is very much a follow-up to a number of discussions that&#13;
&#13;
 we've had with the board in the past.          It is a central&#13;
&#13;
 element of our corporate strategy to develop practical&#13;
&#13;
 actions to systematically link all of our work to poverty&#13;
&#13;
 and it is, of course, a key aspect of the&#13;
&#13;
 operationalization of the Comprehensive Development&#13;
&#13;
 Framework.    Our interactions with executive directors have&#13;
&#13;
 been most useful to this process and we specifically&#13;
&#13;
 appreciate the comments we have received on these papers.&#13;
                                                                     Page6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
             The approach laid out in these papers is&#13;
&#13;
 fundamentally about how we integrate poverty into country&#13;
&#13;
 strategy.    This is based, of course, on a body of&#13;
&#13;
 substantive work on the determinants of poverty reduction&#13;
&#13;
 and, as Masood noted, it is complementary to the work on&#13;
&#13;
 good practices in managing social dimensions of crises.&#13;
&#13;
 That work that we reported on the progress on Tuesday, we&#13;
&#13;
 see as the material on good practice for advising on one&#13;
&#13;
 important aspect of the relationship between country&#13;
&#13;
 strategy and poverty which would constitute the&#13;
&#13;
 ingredients to be incorporated into the framework laid out&#13;
&#13;
 here.&#13;
&#13;
             I'd also emphasize that in terms of substance,&#13;
&#13;
 the framework draws on the initial thinking in the World&#13;
&#13;
 Development Report for the coming year.             In particular, it&#13;
&#13;
 emphasizes the importance of security and of empowerment&#13;
&#13;
 within any country based poverty reduction strategy.            We&#13;
&#13;
 see action in these two areas as necessary complements to&#13;
&#13;
 measures that enhance the material opportunities of the&#13;
&#13;
 poor, and this is something that needs to be made&#13;
&#13;
 explicit.&#13;
&#13;
             The board will be having an opportunity for&#13;
&#13;
 further discussion of these, the substantive thinking for&#13;
                                                                         Page7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 the WDR, in the discussion of the WDR outline on the 17th&#13;
&#13;
 of September.&#13;
&#13;
           And in this introduction, I would just like to&#13;
&#13;
 emphasize four points, largely in response to some of the&#13;
&#13;
 comments received.   First point is that participatory&#13;
&#13;
 processes and country ownerships are central features of&#13;
&#13;
 the process, as has been emphasized in the comments by Ms.&#13;
&#13;
 Brandt, Mr. Gaoseb and Mr. Pickford.        This applies at the&#13;
&#13;
 level of the definition of country goals, to the&#13;
&#13;
 monitoring of delivery of services, and also to the&#13;
&#13;
 analysis of an interpretation of progress.         And we see&#13;
&#13;
 this very much again as an application of the principles&#13;
&#13;
 that underpin the Comprehensive Development Framework.&#13;
&#13;
           I'd just like to take note of one issue, an&#13;
&#13;
 issue raised by Mr. Wan Abdul Aziz, and this is that the&#13;
&#13;
 structure of civil society engagement has to be worked out&#13;
&#13;
 at a country level and it is in particular important in&#13;
&#13;
 designing this that we work out mechanisms or the country&#13;
&#13;
 works out mechanisms that assure the involvement of civil&#13;
&#13;
 society institutions that genuinely represent the poor and&#13;
&#13;
 indeed work out mechanisms for strengthening and involving&#13;
&#13;
 organizations of the poor themselves.         This we see as one&#13;
                                                                    Page8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 important element of the emerging WDR strategy that we'll&#13;
&#13;
 be discussing in the future.&#13;
&#13;
             Second, the approach has important implications&#13;
&#13;
 for the diagnostic and information basis for country&#13;
&#13;
 strategy formulation and implementation.            As the progress&#13;
&#13;
 report on social and structural reviews lays out, we are&#13;
&#13;
 moving towards a more systematic approach to linking the&#13;
&#13;
 macroeconomic social and structural agenda to poverty&#13;
&#13;
 outcomes.&#13;
&#13;
             A couple of issues I'd like to respond to that&#13;
&#13;
 were raised in comments.     First is that the diagnostic&#13;
&#13;
 work has to be within a comprehensive frame.           This doesn't&#13;
&#13;
 mean diluting sectoral analysis, as a point made by Mr.&#13;
&#13;
 Wan Abdul Aziz, but it does mean systematically linking&#13;
&#13;
 sectoral work to poverty outcomes and recognizing the&#13;
&#13;
 intersectoral linkages that are both often powerful and&#13;
&#13;
 have largely or significantly been neglected in both our&#13;
&#13;
 work and those of other institutions.&#13;
&#13;
             In this context, we would very much agree with a&#13;
&#13;
 point made by Mr. Pickford that this should include&#13;
&#13;
 explicit assessment of the distributional consequences of&#13;
&#13;
 macroeconomic choices, and not just an analysis of the&#13;
                                                                       Page9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 effects of what have been traditionally labeled as social&#13;
&#13;
 policies.&#13;
&#13;
             We'd also take note of Ms. Brandt's point that&#13;
&#13;
 if we go ahead and introduce poverty notes, that we must&#13;
&#13;
 ensure that these strengthen and not weaken what is the&#13;
&#13;
 central endeavor, and that is to put poverty at the center&#13;
&#13;
 of country strategies.     We've not reached closure on this.&#13;
&#13;
 We are actually now working through how best to reshape&#13;
&#13;
 our poverty assessment process in a fashion that will&#13;
&#13;
 underpin the enhanced poverty focus and we'll be coming&#13;
&#13;
 back to you on that with specific recommendations for&#13;
&#13;
 discussion in the context of the poverty progress report&#13;
&#13;
 in the next couple of months.&#13;
&#13;
             Second general point is undertaking this&#13;
&#13;
 diagnosis and shifting to a genuinely outcome-based&#13;
&#13;
 process of monitoring and implementation has significant&#13;
&#13;
 implications for the production and availability of&#13;
&#13;
 information.    Many countries will not initially have an&#13;
&#13;
 optimal information base.      We don't think that this means&#13;
&#13;
 you have to delay moving towards an outcome-oriented&#13;
&#13;
 approach.    We don't need to a have perfection in order to&#13;
&#13;
 start on this process, but it does mean in these cases&#13;
&#13;
 that it will be important to have a clear approach to&#13;
                                                                 Page10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 developing the information system as an integral component&#13;
&#13;
 of a country strategy.&#13;
&#13;
             This leads to our third point, that in many&#13;
&#13;
 countries moving in the direction advocated will need to&#13;
&#13;
 be complemented by quite major efforts in capacity&#13;
&#13;
 building, a point noted by both Mr. Gaoseb and Mr.&#13;
&#13;
 Pickford.    This will certainly apply to statistical&#13;
&#13;
 systems, but is also very much broader.             It implies&#13;
&#13;
 developing the capacity in governments, in think tanks,&#13;
&#13;
 and in civil society to analyze and interpret progress and&#13;
&#13;
 participate in informed country level dialogue.            This&#13;
&#13;
 will, of course, often require support from the&#13;
&#13;
 international donor community.&#13;
&#13;
             Fourth, and perhaps most important, that while&#13;
&#13;
 the approach very much builds on ongoing country&#13;
&#13;
 experiences, it will involve over time a really quite&#13;
&#13;
 substantial shift in the way in which we work.            And this&#13;
&#13;
 does imply quite a major challenge in implementation, both&#13;
&#13;
 for the country teams that will be supporting countries&#13;
&#13;
 and framing outcome oriented programs and for the networks&#13;
&#13;
 in providing the technical support and the international&#13;
&#13;
 experience on the links between public action and&#13;
&#13;
 outcomes.     We see this as an effort that will need to be&#13;
                                                                      Page11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 phased over time, as emphasized by Mr. Gaoseb, with a very&#13;
&#13;
 important role for systematically sharing experience as we&#13;
&#13;
 go along.    So we look forward to reactions to the proposed&#13;
&#13;
 approaches.    Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. SANDSTROM:   Thank you very much, Mike.&#13;
&#13;
 Peter.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. FALLON:   Thank you very much.      The paper I'm&#13;
&#13;
 discussing looks at some of the implications of applying&#13;
&#13;
 the poverty reduction strategy framework laid out in the&#13;
&#13;
 paper discussed by Michael to the HIPC Initiative&#13;
&#13;
 countries.    We believe that the conclusions apply to a&#13;
&#13;
 rather wider set of countries than the HIPCs and have&#13;
&#13;
 similar implications for other IDA countries and even&#13;
&#13;
 perhaps for IBRD countries.      The paper as noted is jointly&#13;
&#13;
 written by Bank and IMF staff.       It's worth pointing out it&#13;
&#13;
 draws on extensive consultation with civil society&#13;
&#13;
 undertaken as part of Phase II of the review of the HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 Initiative.    A compendium of views received under this&#13;
&#13;
 consultation has been circulated to the executive&#13;
&#13;
 directors.&#13;
&#13;
             In applying the framework to the HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 Initiative, the paper suggests I think two main&#13;
&#13;
 principles.    First, as a poverty reduction strategy is a&#13;
                                                                     Page12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 long-term effort spanning say 15 years or more, HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 programs should be seen as applying only to the first few&#13;
&#13;
 years of this long effort.&#13;
&#13;
           Second, the best way of ensuring a strong link&#13;
&#13;
 between debt relief and poverty reduction is to deploy all&#13;
&#13;
 resources including domestic revenue and debt relief&#13;
&#13;
 towards the goal of poverty reduction.         HIPC decisions&#13;
&#13;
 would then be integrated into a comprehensive effort to&#13;
&#13;
 reduce poverty.   Debt relief would be seen as only one&#13;
&#13;
 element in the financing of the long-term poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction strategy.&#13;
&#13;
           The need for closer cooperation between the&#13;
&#13;
 coauthors, that's the Bank and the Fund, will be&#13;
&#13;
 accentuated under the new framework.        The main elements of&#13;
&#13;
 the strategy it's proposed would be published in a&#13;
&#13;
 tripartite document, which we're calling for now "The&#13;
&#13;
 Poverty Reduction Strategy Paper," or PRSP, for short.&#13;
&#13;
 This would be endorsed by the government, the Bank and the&#13;
&#13;
 Fund.   It would show how Bank and Fund lending supports&#13;
&#13;
 the strategy and it would require approval by the boards&#13;
&#13;
 of both institutions.&#13;
&#13;
           The IMF paper that Sven referred to on the&#13;
&#13;
 "Review of Social Issues and Policies in IMF-Supported&#13;
                                                                    Page13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 Programs" clearly sees the PRSP as a stimulus to improved&#13;
&#13;
 collaboration by, for example, better integrating&#13;
&#13;
 macroeconomic and social objectives, policy measures and&#13;
&#13;
 related work agendas.     The Bank CAS would fully reflect&#13;
&#13;
 the strategy and use performance under this framework as&#13;
&#13;
 the basis for setting the various lending envelopes.&#13;
&#13;
             As Ms. Brandt noted very aptly in her statement,&#13;
&#13;
 overall consistency of IDA and ESAF-supported programs is&#13;
&#13;
 a key to successful strengthening of the poverty focus in&#13;
&#13;
 all work and specifically in the enhanced HIPC.&#13;
&#13;
             For the Fund, the ESAF would continue to play&#13;
&#13;
 its present role but would now be seen as supporting the&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction strategy as a whole and not just the&#13;
&#13;
 macroeconomic and structural components.            This may affect&#13;
&#13;
 IMF time-tabling as processes of developing strategies are&#13;
&#13;
 likely to be lengthy and it's likely that achieving&#13;
&#13;
 overall consistency will require some iteration between&#13;
&#13;
 the macroeconomic targets and other components of this&#13;
&#13;
 strategy.&#13;
&#13;
             For the Bank, I won't say much.         My colleague&#13;
&#13;
 went into this.    This means deepening and extending work&#13;
&#13;
 using outcome-based criteria and participatory processes.&#13;
&#13;
 This is a major task that will take time.           Nevertheless,&#13;
                                                                       Page14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 we propose as a first step establishing poverty reduction&#13;
&#13;
 strategies along the lines suggested.&#13;
&#13;
           We are very grateful for responses received thus&#13;
&#13;
 far from the executive directors and we're encouraged by&#13;
&#13;
 the rather strong sense of support that their comments&#13;
&#13;
 convey.   Let me expand briefly on some of the points.&#13;
&#13;
           We share the concerns raised by Ms. Brandt and&#13;
&#13;
 by Messrs. Pickford and Kelmanson that there should be no&#13;
&#13;
 undue delay in the provision of additional debt relief in&#13;
&#13;
 countries already having a well-defined poverty strategy.&#13;
&#13;
 The suggestion in the paper is that while it is desirable&#13;
&#13;
 that an appropriate poverty reduction strategy be in place&#13;
&#13;
 at the decision point, it has to be recognized that this&#13;
&#13;
 will not always be possible as building a strategy takes&#13;
&#13;
 time.   For retroactive countries, the paper suggest that&#13;
&#13;
 each country be treated on a case-by-case basis.&#13;
&#13;
           We agree fully with Mr. Toure's comment that we&#13;
&#13;
 should be careful not to believe that investing in the&#13;
&#13;
 social sectors is the only key that warrants the success&#13;
&#13;
 of poverty alleviation strategies.        A related concern was&#13;
&#13;
 expressed by Mr. Gaoseb.    The need for sound macroeconomic&#13;
&#13;
 policies, better governance and better structural policies&#13;
&#13;
 is as great as ever.   Without these, growth will falter&#13;
                                                                   Page15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 and strategies will fail.     It also may sometimes by the&#13;
&#13;
 case that social sector investment is not actually the top&#13;
&#13;
 priority for poverty alleviation.       As one example, better&#13;
&#13;
 access to safe drinking water is likely to be a priority&#13;
&#13;
 in many countries.   Achieving this actually requires in&#13;
&#13;
 general better infrastructure.&#13;
&#13;
           We note the concerns expressed by Mr. Gaoseb and&#13;
&#13;
 Mr. Wan Abdul Aziz regarding the proposed PRSP.          Our view&#13;
&#13;
 is that the PRSP would be a stronger document than the&#13;
&#13;
 existing PFP as it would tighten the focus on poverty&#13;
&#13;
 alleviation by laying out the strategy and the targets in&#13;
&#13;
 detail.   Our view is that retaining both is likely to&#13;
&#13;
 result in needless duplication, however.           The CAS would&#13;
&#13;
 remain the Bank's business document as at present, but&#13;
&#13;
 would draw on the government's strategy as laid out in the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP.&#13;
&#13;
           Finally, we note Mr. Toure's point that there is&#13;
&#13;
 now a lot of experience on how to improve development&#13;
&#13;
 effectiveness and we take his point that we are saying&#13;
&#13;
 nothing really very new in the paper.         We do hope,&#13;
&#13;
 however, that by moving further along the lines suggested&#13;
&#13;
 in the paper will make a contribution to worldwide poverty&#13;
&#13;
 alleviation.   Thank you.&#13;
                                                                     Page16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you very much, Peter.&#13;
&#13;
 Later on in the afternoon, we may want to ask Fund staff&#13;
&#13;
 also to come in and comment on this from their side, but I&#13;
&#13;
 would first like to hear from some of you.         I have seven&#13;
&#13;
 names on my list so far.    It's almost one o'clock.      Should&#13;
&#13;
 we at least get started?    And Mr. Al-Saad will have the&#13;
&#13;
 honor, please.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. AL-SAAD:   Thank you.      It's always good to&#13;
&#13;
 start before lunch.   Well, I will restrict my remarks to&#13;
&#13;
 the first paper and I see this paper as a first step in a&#13;
&#13;
 process of taking a hard look at the Bank's poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction strategy.   The record in the past decade has&#13;
&#13;
 been disappointing, to say the least, with poverty&#13;
&#13;
 increasing by a lot instead of decreasing.         In looking at&#13;
&#13;
 the proposed enhanced framework, I wish we had had enough&#13;
&#13;
 time to look at it carefully.      I didn't even have enough&#13;
&#13;
 time to digest the outline of the new poverty WDR which I&#13;
&#13;
 received yesterday, though I noted it's a new and&#13;
&#13;
 interesting vision based on empowerment, security and&#13;
&#13;
 opportunity.&#13;
&#13;
           I understand, however, the urgent need to&#13;
&#13;
 consider the new framework in the view of its relevance to&#13;
&#13;
 the HIPC discussion and since it seems to have&#13;
                                                                    Page17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 incorporated the main thrust of the forthcoming WDR.&#13;
&#13;
 Basically I am in broad agreement with the framework focus&#13;
&#13;
 on poverty outcome and the link between policy and&#13;
&#13;
 outcomes.    The three elements of the enhanced framework&#13;
&#13;
 seem fairly logical starting with understanding of poverty&#13;
&#13;
 and its determinants, choosing the policy actions that&#13;
&#13;
 have the highest poverty impact, then monitoring outcome&#13;
&#13;
 on the basis of indicators widely endorsed.           My concern is&#13;
&#13;
 that actual implementation of such enhanced framework will&#13;
&#13;
 burden the capacity of many poor developing countries,&#13;
&#13;
 especially the HIPC countries who are expected to be the&#13;
&#13;
 first target of the new approach.&#13;
&#13;
             On this, I wish to hear more from my colleagues.&#13;
&#13;
 I welcome the framework commitment to work for the&#13;
&#13;
 achievement of the international development goals of&#13;
&#13;
 cutting poverty in half by the year 2015 and other&#13;
&#13;
 targets.    I wonder, however, if this is still realistic&#13;
&#13;
 given the setbacks in the past two years.            I certainly&#13;
&#13;
 hope it still is.    One aspect that I wish the document&#13;
&#13;
 brought to light is how much the poverty policy in the&#13;
&#13;
 bulk of the countries was donor driven, whether by&#13;
&#13;
 international and regional institutions or bilaterals?&#13;
&#13;
 This clearly means that all major participants, not only&#13;
                                                                       Page18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 the Bank and the Fund, should be adequately committed to&#13;
&#13;
 the new concept and its operational requirements.&#13;
&#13;
             Coming to the question addressed to us on the&#13;
&#13;
 operational implication, I can only give my preliminary&#13;
&#13;
 reaction.    On the first question, I do agree that outcome&#13;
&#13;
 based approach would provide a good basis for further&#13;
&#13;
 improvement of CASs.    Support for countries, however,&#13;
&#13;
 should not be mechanically based on achievement of these&#13;
&#13;
 outcomes.    As paragraph 35 points out, this might depend&#13;
&#13;
 on factors beyond the control of the country.&#13;
&#13;
             On the second question, I have no problem&#13;
&#13;
 working with governments to promote transparency and broad&#13;
&#13;
 participation of civil society in this selection and&#13;
&#13;
 monitoring of outcomes.     This should improve realism and&#13;
&#13;
 relevance of outcomes targeted and enhance ownership.&#13;
&#13;
             On the third question, I think there should&#13;
&#13;
 still be a balance between program-based lending and the&#13;
&#13;
 project lending.    Some countries may already have very&#13;
&#13;
 large program lending and others much less.         Outcome-based&#13;
&#13;
 strategies should not mean across the board increase in&#13;
&#13;
 the share of program lending.&#13;
&#13;
             Finally, on the last question, I am not sure it&#13;
&#13;
 is appropriate to apply the new framework when there is&#13;
                                                                     Page19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 inadequate knowledge about the link between determinants&#13;
&#13;
 of poverty and policy action.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you very much.      With that,&#13;
&#13;
 I suggest we break for lunch and I have not six more names&#13;
&#13;
 on my list, I have 12 more names now.         And we'll start at&#13;
&#13;
 2:30 with Ruth and then Helmut and we'll take it from&#13;
&#13;
 there.   Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           [Whereupon, at 1:00 p.m., the board recessed to&#13;
&#13;
 reconvene at 2:30 p.m., this same day.]&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    Page20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
                      AFTERNOON SESSION&#13;
&#13;
                                                      [2:34 p.m.]&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    All right.      Welcome back.    I&#13;
&#13;
 think we have to start if we are going to finish.           So,&#13;
&#13;
 let's get going again.&#13;
&#13;
           Ruth, please.    It is your turn.&#13;
&#13;
           MS. BACHMAYER:    Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           I want, first of all, to commend management and&#13;
&#13;
 staff for the excellent documents which reflect the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
 long and rich theoretical and practical experience in&#13;
&#13;
 struggling to reduce poverty.      The building of poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction strategies paper provides a very comprehensive&#13;
&#13;
 and at the same time concise strategic framework for the&#13;
&#13;
 operational work, and the two other documents complement&#13;
&#13;
 it by perhaps the most important links to the operational&#13;
&#13;
 work done by the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
           The papers implicitly make clear how&#13;
&#13;
 underestimated and inadequately developed is the area of&#13;
&#13;
 diagnostics and monitoring of social developments compared&#13;
&#13;
 to purely economic development, including, in particular,&#13;
&#13;
 the financial sector.     Any social targeting has for this&#13;
&#13;
 reason been somewhat blind-shooting with the high risk&#13;
&#13;
 outcomes in terms of efficiency.&#13;
                                                                    Page21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           For this reason, we much welcome the progress&#13;
&#13;
 that has been made in the attempts to root social and&#13;
&#13;
 social policies in a more solid and well-defined round.&#13;
&#13;
           We believe that the ultimate goal of the&#13;
&#13;
 policies is the effect in preventing or reducing poverty,&#13;
&#13;
 not the speed of action alone.      I particularly welcome the&#13;
&#13;
 outcome-based approach and I support the suggestion that&#13;
&#13;
 the poverty reduction framework should provide an umbrella&#13;
&#13;
 for the Bank's work in developing and it should also, of&#13;
&#13;
 course, be the basis for CASs.&#13;
&#13;
           In this respect, I welcome the social and&#13;
&#13;
 structural reviews as a systematic and structured way to&#13;
&#13;
 approach the CAS process.     We were very satisfied with the&#13;
&#13;
 report on the progress in and lessons from the SSRs and&#13;
&#13;
 consider them as an excellent diagnostic and efficient&#13;
&#13;
 tool.&#13;
&#13;
           Nevertheless, even the excellent documents&#13;
&#13;
 cannot hide the fact that some challenges and difficult&#13;
&#13;
 questions remain ahead of us.      I see, in particular, three&#13;
&#13;
 issues.&#13;
&#13;
           First, we would appreciate to learn more about&#13;
&#13;
 the management's views on the concept of the client in the&#13;
&#13;
 driver's seat in the context of the SSRs.          The SSRs will&#13;
                                                                    Page22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 provide a single perspective or a single scenario, which&#13;
&#13;
 may not necessarily be the only one, or even not the most&#13;
&#13;
 relevant one.   There is nothing like a single set of&#13;
&#13;
 generally-accepted paradigms in the area of social and&#13;
&#13;
 structural policies.&#13;
&#13;
           We hope that management prepares a framework&#13;
&#13;
 which is really conducive for substantive inputs and&#13;
&#13;
 feedbacks from the governments and from civil society and,&#13;
&#13;
 of course, also for public discussion of the SSRs.       It&#13;
&#13;
 would be very disappointing if the implementation of the&#13;
&#13;
 desired social and structural policies took a form or were&#13;
&#13;
 felt as imposing ultimate prescriptions and give the&#13;
&#13;
 feeling of too much power by international institutions or&#13;
&#13;
 the donor community.&#13;
&#13;
           Second, we consider it important to keep enough&#13;
&#13;
 realism in the strategy and in the intentions.     The&#13;
&#13;
 requirements that the social and structural strategy for&#13;
&#13;
 many countries would impose may be far too ambitious given&#13;
&#13;
 their capacity.   I will come back to this observation in&#13;
&#13;
 the context of the HIPC paper.&#13;
&#13;
           We should not forget that building of the&#13;
&#13;
 proposed institutional arrangements, for instance,&#13;
&#13;
 information systems, has been a major challenge for&#13;
                                                               Page23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 development economies too and it took us tens of years to&#13;
&#13;
 come to the point where we are now, we as industrial&#13;
&#13;
 countries.&#13;
&#13;
            The third point related to the relationship with&#13;
&#13;
 the IMF.   The Bank's cooperation with the IMF in the area&#13;
&#13;
 of social and structural policies remains an important&#13;
&#13;
 open issue.   The Bank has done most of its work in this&#13;
&#13;
 area, and has core competence and a competitive advantage&#13;
&#13;
 in it.   But parts of the Article IV consultations by the&#13;
&#13;
 Fund deal with social and structural issues at least with&#13;
&#13;
 their fiscal aspects.&#13;
&#13;
            For this reason, the areas of overlap seem to be&#13;
&#13;
 a natural field for shared responsibilities between the&#13;
&#13;
 two institutions.    We would welcome management's thoughts&#13;
&#13;
 on the future cooperation and sharing responsibility with&#13;
&#13;
 the Fund on the very operational level, in particular with&#13;
&#13;
 respect to the SSRs, with the structural part of the SSRs,&#13;
&#13;
 in particular.&#13;
&#13;
            I commend management for the inspiring thoughts&#13;
&#13;
 that were put to the operationalizing of the poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction programs on each stage of the Bank's work.   Many&#13;
&#13;
 elements of the proposed approach have not yet been&#13;
&#13;
 tested, and we know little on how they would work.    It&#13;
                                                               Page24&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 refers to all stages of the operational work from the&#13;
&#13;
 better coordination and communication between the regions&#13;
&#13;
 and sectors within the Bank to the use of different&#13;
&#13;
 instruments.&#13;
&#13;
           I have to say also as a footnote, I find it a&#13;
&#13;
 bit premature to include budget support lending in the set&#13;
&#13;
 of instruments.   It may have a big rationale in the&#13;
&#13;
 context of poverty-focused work of the Bank, but I think&#13;
&#13;
 it is really premature to include it in a proposal right&#13;
&#13;
 now.   We have not finished our discussion.        We have not&#13;
&#13;
 come to a conclusion on this proposal.&#13;
&#13;
           Before turning to the implications for HIPC, I&#13;
&#13;
 would like to conclude my remarks on the poverty reduction&#13;
&#13;
 strategy by saying that I believe that the next logical&#13;
&#13;
 step is to pilot the approach and carefully review the&#13;
&#13;
 experiences.&#13;
&#13;
           We also support that it would be appropriate for&#13;
&#13;
 the Board to return to the review of experience from the&#13;
&#13;
 implementation of the poverty reduction strategy and the&#13;
&#13;
 outcome-based approach in more than a year from now.&#13;
&#13;
           Turning now to "Strengthening the Link Between&#13;
&#13;
 Debt Relief and Poverty Reduction" in the context of an&#13;
&#13;
 enhanced HIPC framework, it is indeed desirable that&#13;
                                                                  Page25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 resources freed up by debt relief should lead to an&#13;
&#13;
 increase in social investment.      But it could be&#13;
&#13;
 counterproductive if a mechanistic linkage between both&#13;
&#13;
 were to be established.&#13;
&#13;
           Debt relief is not the only source of external&#13;
&#13;
 finance in support of poverty reduction efforts, as you&#13;
&#13;
 said and as we all know.&#13;
&#13;
           While it is important for HIPC countries to have&#13;
&#13;
 a viable and comprehensive poverty reduction strategy in&#13;
&#13;
 place as soon as possible, preferably before the decision&#13;
&#13;
 point, speed should not be the over-arching objective but&#13;
&#13;
 rather sufficient attention should be given that the&#13;
&#13;
 strategy is well-balanced, that it takes into account the&#13;
&#13;
 country-specific resources and implementation constraints,&#13;
&#13;
 and that it is fully shared by all relevant stakeholders.&#13;
&#13;
           I see some merit in tying the relevant length of&#13;
&#13;
 the second stage of HIPC to progress achieved in the areas&#13;
&#13;
 of structural and social reform and poverty reduction,&#13;
&#13;
 provided the actions to be undertaken by the country can&#13;
&#13;
 be monitored and not formulated in such a way that it&#13;
&#13;
 would over-burden the reform agenda.&#13;
&#13;
           This could result in a delay instead of faster&#13;
&#13;
 delivery of debt relief.    Given the fact that many HIPCs&#13;
                                                              Page26&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 are highly vulnerable to external shocks, which might lead&#13;
&#13;
 to setbacks in that implementation of the reform agenda, I&#13;
&#13;
 believe that some form of judgment should be retained as&#13;
&#13;
 to whether a critical mass of reforms and improvements in&#13;
&#13;
 the delivery of social services to the poor had been met.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you very much, Ruth.&#13;
&#13;
           Helmut Schaffer, please.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SCHAFFER:    Thank you, Sven.&#13;
&#13;
           In my view, these papers are milestones in the&#13;
&#13;
 poverty orientation of the Bank, and in the realization of&#13;
&#13;
 the Bank's own mission.    Especially the joint Bank-Fund&#13;
&#13;
 paper is a big step in the right direction and a success&#13;
&#13;
 for the enhanced debt relief initiative per se.&#13;
&#13;
           This paper also is very close to the thinking&#13;
&#13;
 expressed at the Utstein [phonetic] declaration of the&#13;
&#13;
 four Development Ministers of Great Britain, the&#13;
&#13;
 Netherlands, Norway and Germany from August this year.&#13;
&#13;
           Consequently, I would like to express my sincere&#13;
&#13;
 thanks to the management of both institutions for this&#13;
&#13;
 tremendous job to give a new spirit of the poverty focus&#13;
&#13;
 of the World Bank's work.&#13;
                                                              Page27&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
            Let me make some comments and start with the&#13;
&#13;
 first paper, "Building Poverty Reduction Strategies in&#13;
&#13;
 Developing Countries", as it has been a key input to the&#13;
&#13;
 second paper on the HIPC Initiative.&#13;
&#13;
            This is a good and very useful paper and I agree&#13;
&#13;
 with all its key issues and recommendations.       It is&#13;
&#13;
 absolutely correct that the paper's underlying assumption&#13;
&#13;
 is based on a multi-dimensional definition of poverty and&#13;
&#13;
 its causes, paragraph 7.    Hence, as poverty is not only&#13;
&#13;
 seen in its economic context, the paper proposes a multi-&#13;
&#13;
 sectoral approach and comes to a varied set of strategies.&#13;
&#13;
            I also fully agree with paragraph 20 that it is&#13;
&#13;
 significant to analyze the multiplicity of causal factors&#13;
&#13;
 of poverty.   The paper does not explicitly mention the&#13;
&#13;
 vast differences in power and interest which lead to&#13;
&#13;
 poverty or conserve it and the consequence of strong&#13;
&#13;
 political will is a significant precondition to alleviate&#13;
&#13;
 poverty.&#13;
&#13;
            Paragraph 16 strengthens the importance of a&#13;
&#13;
 detailed analysis of poverty.      I quote, "Policy&#13;
&#13;
 formulation should start from a disaggregated&#13;
&#13;
 understanding of who the poor are, where they live and&#13;
&#13;
 their source of livelihood".      I want to add that this&#13;
                                                               Page28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 analysis should be also carried out with a specific gender&#13;
&#13;
 focus.&#13;
&#13;
           Coming to a more strategic consideration, I&#13;
&#13;
 support the idea that poverty alleviation has to be based&#13;
&#13;
 on the specific situation of each country.          We could even&#13;
&#13;
 go further and speak of an area-specific approach, as, for&#13;
&#13;
 example, homogeneous-looking countries, like my own&#13;
&#13;
 Germany, can actually be quite diverse in nature.             There&#13;
&#13;
 is no blueprint for poverty alleviation.           I really&#13;
&#13;
 appreciate that the World Bank integrates this aspect into&#13;
&#13;
 its new focus on poverty.&#13;
&#13;
           It also makes sense to focus on the question of&#13;
&#13;
 distribution, participation and empowerment of the poor,&#13;
&#13;
 as stated in paragraphs 11 and 26, but we should not&#13;
&#13;
 forget that any empowerment of one group leads&#13;
&#13;
 simultaneously to diminishing the power of others and said&#13;
&#13;
 power structures might change to the now powerful, a&#13;
&#13;
 typical scenario of conflict.      The paper does not reflect&#13;
&#13;
 whether the World Bank should play a role in this&#13;
&#13;
 empowerment process for the poor.&#13;
&#13;
           I was also delighted to notice that the World&#13;
&#13;
 Bank is now more careful about the role of economic&#13;
&#13;
 growth.   Economic growth is still necessary, but it is not&#13;
                                                                       Page29&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 seen as a guarantee for poverty alleviation anymore.           Past&#13;
&#13;
 experiences have shown that the trickle-down effect did&#13;
&#13;
 not work out the way it was expected.&#13;
&#13;
           Paragraph 23 mentions ways to go about poverty&#13;
&#13;
 alleviation, even in times of less economic growth, but&#13;
&#13;
 obviously do not exist in addition to economic growth, as&#13;
&#13;
 stated in the paper.   Each way has its value in itself.&#13;
&#13;
           In paragraph 11, the paper raises the important&#13;
&#13;
 topic of broadly-based growth, which is directly linked to&#13;
&#13;
 the equality of income distribution, as the paper later on&#13;
&#13;
 rightly points out by stating poverty payoff to growth&#13;
&#13;
 will be high but only if the distribution of income and&#13;
&#13;
 the quality of governance are improved.            This has my full&#13;
&#13;
 sympathy and the facts that this aspect will even form&#13;
&#13;
 part of the forthcoming WDR shows the great importance it&#13;
&#13;
 also has for the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
           Only one question remains:        How can the World&#13;
&#13;
 Bank support these activities, for example, the&#13;
&#13;
 distribution of land, as mentioned in paragraph 23?&#13;
&#13;
           The role of indicators is another important&#13;
&#13;
 subject the paper deals with.      How difficult it is to find&#13;
&#13;
 right or useful indicators shows, as the example given in&#13;
&#13;
 paragraph 32, where the rising rate of primary enrollment&#13;
                                                                       Page30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 does not necessarily say something about a better quality&#13;
&#13;
 of learning.    In addition, it would also be important to&#13;
&#13;
 look at the rate of dropouts after several months or even&#13;
&#13;
 years.   Otherwise, the wrong evaluation about the success&#13;
&#13;
 of the undertaken measures would be made.&#13;
&#13;
             Table 1 gives a good starting point for the&#13;
&#13;
 development of adequate indicators but again, as pointed&#13;
&#13;
 out earlier already, the design of indicators and their&#13;
&#13;
 quantification has to be country-specific.&#13;
&#13;
             To conclude my remarks on this paper, I would&#13;
&#13;
 like to give some brief answers to the issues for&#13;
&#13;
 discussion outlined in paragraph 73 at the end of the&#13;
&#13;
 paper.&#13;
&#13;
             The first point, I agree that outcome-based&#13;
&#13;
 approaches would provide a good basis for further&#13;
&#13;
 improvements in the CAS selectivity and the articulation&#13;
&#13;
 of more comprehensive and robust links between poverty&#13;
&#13;
 outcomes and Bank activities.       Developing countries should&#13;
&#13;
 design their own national plans and strategies for poverty&#13;
&#13;
 alleviation and to develop an appropriate indicator system&#13;
&#13;
 for monitoring and evaluation of the different proposed&#13;
&#13;
 measures.&#13;
                                                                   Page31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
             Secondly, I also support the second aspect to&#13;
&#13;
 promote transparency and broad participation of civil&#13;
&#13;
 society.    Let me just give one suggestion.        The close&#13;
&#13;
 relationship of poverty and gender aspects should be&#13;
&#13;
 worked out in more detail.      In the Committee of the Whole&#13;
&#13;
 paper on Tuesday we discussed the same problem for the&#13;
&#13;
 social policy already.&#13;
&#13;
             The third point concerning the third question,&#13;
&#13;
 lending support type, lending instruments appear as a&#13;
&#13;
 logical consequence of better national policies and&#13;
&#13;
 strategies for poverty alleviation, but an uncertainty&#13;
&#13;
 remains how the majority of bilateral and multilateral&#13;
&#13;
 donors are ready for it.&#13;
&#13;
             In regard to the fourth question, a gradual and&#13;
&#13;
 slow process on a case-by-case basis seems to be adequate.&#13;
&#13;
 The immediate start for a widespread introduction of the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSPs is not realistic.&#13;
&#13;
             Let me now come to the second paper,&#13;
&#13;
 "Strengthening the Link Between Debt Relief and Poverty&#13;
&#13;
 Reduction".    The paper is a clear statement by the World&#13;
&#13;
 Bank and the IMF that the debt relief initiative should&#13;
&#13;
 form a part of a comprehensive poverty alleviation&#13;
&#13;
 strategy.    Consequently, all available resources and not&#13;
                                                                 Page32&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 only those from the HIPC Initiative should be used for&#13;
&#13;
 this purpose.&#13;
&#13;
           Both organizations underline the necessity to&#13;
&#13;
 integrate sector and macroeconomic policies and, in doing&#13;
&#13;
 so, good governance becomes significant and important to&#13;
&#13;
 this broad-based concept.&#13;
&#13;
           I fully agree that poverty alleviation should be&#13;
&#13;
 seen as a long-term and multi-sectoral approach, as, for&#13;
&#13;
 example, pointed out in Box 7 on page 24.          But the paper&#13;
&#13;
 gives so far no answer to relevance and priority of the&#13;
&#13;
 various parameters for each individual country.&#13;
&#13;
           Furthermore, there is an inherent danger once we&#13;
&#13;
 try to include all the different parameters of poverty and&#13;
&#13;
 its alleviation in a cross-sectoral manner that the design&#13;
&#13;
 of strategies becomes too complex and, accordingly, rather&#13;
&#13;
 difficult for the country to efficiently implement them.&#13;
&#13;
           On the other hand, ownership and the inclusion&#13;
&#13;
 of the HIPC funds into the country's general policies for&#13;
&#13;
 poverty alleviation remains crucial.        Consequently, with&#13;
&#13;
 respect to HIPC, the outlined strategy might be somehow&#13;
&#13;
 too ambitious and on a case-by-case basis a more pragmatic&#13;
&#13;
 approach should be also taken into consideration.&#13;
                                                                    Page33&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
            The role of ownership and poverty reduction&#13;
&#13;
 strategy papers are also interlinked.         As pointed out in&#13;
&#13;
 the papers, these PRSPs are agreed upon jointly by the&#13;
&#13;
 three players -- the partner countries, the World Bank and&#13;
&#13;
 the IMF.   Hence, a lack of ownership is a prevalent danger&#13;
&#13;
 to this concept in a similar way as to the former&#13;
&#13;
 structural adjustment programs.&#13;
&#13;
            The paper further stresses on poverty funds as&#13;
&#13;
 an important instrument, as positive examples of the&#13;
&#13;
 Poverty Action Fund of Uganda is mentioned; also on a more&#13;
&#13;
 rather general basis, positive criteria for the&#13;
&#13;
 establishment for these kind of funds are transparency in&#13;
&#13;
 the allocation of resources, their fast disbursement and&#13;
&#13;
 their immediate disposal.&#13;
&#13;
            But the paper also rightly points out a&#13;
&#13;
 significant danger in relation to the experiences with&#13;
&#13;
 social funds.   These funds can become separated from the&#13;
&#13;
 general national policy and the national budget which&#13;
&#13;
 could be very detrimental to an overall approach to&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction.&#13;
&#13;
            Therefore, more information and detailed&#13;
&#13;
 analysis of their usefulness are needed.           But let me&#13;
&#13;
 conclude by stating that in my view this paper is a very&#13;
                                                                   Page34&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 good basis for further discussions of a very complicated&#13;
&#13;
 but very important matter, but, of course, much remains to&#13;
&#13;
 be clarified and much remains to be reflection upon.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:     Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
           Mr. Ako-Adjei, please.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. AKO-ADJEI:     Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
           First of all, I would like to take the three&#13;
&#13;
 papers together.   I will begin by saying I endorse the&#13;
&#13;
 outline and the policies set out in the papers, and others&#13;
&#13;
 have devoted some time to that.        So, I am not going to&#13;
&#13;
 devote any more time to that.       I would want to take what&#13;
&#13;
 Ms. Bachmayer has called challenges that are ahead of us.&#13;
&#13;
           And the first challenge I see is the&#13;
&#13;
 relationship with the Fund, because this new arrangement&#13;
&#13;
 is going to raise the level of our relationship and our&#13;
&#13;
 cooperation with the Fund to another level.         I would want&#13;
&#13;
 to sincerely request that the burden relationship that is&#13;
&#13;
 being built up here at headquarters should be extended to&#13;
&#13;
 the field, where in most of our countries the two&#13;
&#13;
 institutions are seen to be working at cross purposes most&#13;
&#13;
 of the time.&#13;
                                                                    Page35&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
            If this attitude continues or this perception&#13;
&#13;
 continues, it would completely derail the very good&#13;
&#13;
 intentions that we plan to put in place here.&#13;
&#13;
            The second point is the role of the government&#13;
&#13;
 itself.    I see more of a role at the regional and the&#13;
&#13;
 district levels where a lot of the studies are going to be&#13;
&#13;
 done, where a lot of implementation is going to be done,&#13;
&#13;
 where a lot of the operationalization of the whole poverty&#13;
&#13;
 program is going to be done.        But this is where the&#13;
&#13;
 difficulties are.&#13;
&#13;
            The central governments are weak; the districts&#13;
&#13;
 are weaker.   And I would prefer that we strengthen&#13;
&#13;
 capacity at the regions and at the districts before we&#13;
&#13;
 start throwing in money at these programs, because&#13;
&#13;
 otherwise we would end up throwing a lot of money at these&#13;
&#13;
 programs, but without institutional setup to create&#13;
&#13;
 accountability, to create transparency, to create the&#13;
&#13;
 mobilization, you need a mobilization not only of&#13;
&#13;
 resources but you need a mobilization of the people&#13;
&#13;
 involved, the poor themselves to really get into the whole&#13;
&#13;
 program.   And I think the success depends upon that&#13;
&#13;
 mobilization and what the papers call the empowerment and&#13;
                                                              Page36&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 participation.   So, I urge that we pay special attention&#13;
&#13;
 to that.&#13;
&#13;
            Then, the next challenge I see really is the&#13;
&#13;
 issue of the poor themselves.      We need to build a whole&#13;
&#13;
 program around the poor themselves, around their own&#13;
&#13;
 responses, around their own interests.         We need to make&#13;
&#13;
 sure that the key resources of the poor, which is their&#13;
&#13;
 labor, is going to be utilized.       We need to create equal&#13;
&#13;
 opportunities and avenues for the poor to participate and&#13;
&#13;
 have access to all the institutional prerogatives that the&#13;
&#13;
 state creates.&#13;
&#13;
            We need to be able to create access to the&#13;
&#13;
 resources that have been channeled.        We need to create&#13;
&#13;
 access for them to generate their own incomes, to be able&#13;
&#13;
 to grow out of poverty.    I think they have to grow out of&#13;
&#13;
 poverty; we don't have to get them out of poverty.        But if&#13;
&#13;
 we provide the opportunities, the access and the&#13;
&#13;
 resources, they themselves could take the opportunities&#13;
&#13;
 and create and participate seriously for the success of&#13;
&#13;
 the program.   That is the way I see it.&#13;
&#13;
            Then the next challenge I see is with the NGOs.&#13;
&#13;
 And this is also where you are going to have to play a lot&#13;
&#13;
 at the level of the regional and the districts.        And let's&#13;
                                                                    Page37&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 accept it; I think the NGOs are better situated than both&#13;
&#13;
 the Bank and the Fund in most of the developing countries.&#13;
&#13;
 And I don't think we are going to be able to duplicate or&#13;
&#13;
 excel in a lot of areas to what the NGOs are doing.&#13;
&#13;
           So, I would urge that wherever possible, we get&#13;
&#13;
 them involved to the utmost and to the maximum.           There are&#13;
&#13;
 some of that we can work with.        There are some of them&#13;
&#13;
 that we can all work with.       Those we can all work with, we&#13;
&#13;
 leave them aside.    Those we can work with, we go along&#13;
&#13;
 with them and use the expertise.&#13;
&#13;
           Finally, taking a look at donors, the role of&#13;
&#13;
 donors, that is also going to be crucial.            But the need&#13;
&#13;
 also for donors is also to strengthen coordination both at&#13;
&#13;
 the regional level, the district and at the center in our&#13;
&#13;
 countries.   And this is going to involve a bit of a spread&#13;
&#13;
 in the countries.    And if donors are going to pick and&#13;
&#13;
 choose their own pet projects and so on and there is not&#13;
&#13;
 going to be any coordination from the center, we are going&#13;
&#13;
 to have a lot of a mess.&#13;
&#13;
           And I would urge that the Bank plays a key role&#13;
&#13;
 in coordination and the donors would also see themselves&#13;
&#13;
 as an integral part of the whole program and coordinate&#13;
                                                                       Page38&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 both with the Bank and the Fund and the other donors to&#13;
&#13;
 make sure that we succeed.&#13;
&#13;
            This is a worthwhile effort, and I am sure that&#13;
&#13;
 if can galvanize the people, we can galvanize the&#13;
&#13;
 institutions, the government, the donors and the NGOs, the&#13;
&#13;
 poor themselves will grow out of poverty.&#13;
&#13;
            Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
            MR. SANDSTROM:   Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
            Mr. Ghattas, please.&#13;
&#13;
            MR. GHATTAS:   Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
            Before we convened, Mr. Page asked me to be&#13;
&#13;
 briefed.   As one of my former bosses, I better listen to&#13;
&#13;
 him.&#13;
&#13;
            I will, therefore, discuss the two papers,&#13;
&#13;
 "Building Poverty Reduction Strategies in Developing&#13;
&#13;
 Countries" and "Social and Structural Reviews", focusing&#13;
&#13;
 mainly on the former.     But I will refer to the IMF paper&#13;
&#13;
 as well.&#13;
&#13;
            We have had a very useful and informative&#13;
&#13;
 bilateral discussion with staff.       I can, therefore, be&#13;
&#13;
 selective in my comments.&#13;
&#13;
            We can support the comprehensive framework for&#13;
&#13;
 reducing poverty as underpinned by the three elements -- a&#13;
                                                               Page39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 thorough understanding of poverty and its determinants;&#13;
&#13;
 choosing public actions that have the highest poverty&#13;
&#13;
 impact; and participatory setting of targets and&#13;
&#13;
 monitoring outcome indicators.&#13;
&#13;
           This framework seems to build on the experience&#13;
&#13;
 with the approach outlined in the 1993 Poverty Reduction&#13;
&#13;
 Handbook by utilizing new knowledge and lending&#13;
&#13;
 instruments.   The international development goals for 2015&#13;
&#13;
 that the proposed framework is designed to achieve are&#13;
&#13;
 very ambitious.   The Bank, as well as other donors, needs&#13;
&#13;
 to be modest and realistic in applying the framework.&#13;
&#13;
           Nonetheless, it is perhaps better to sets one&#13;
&#13;
 sight in fighting poverty too high than too low.      The&#13;
&#13;
 framework needs to be applied flexibly and be tailored to&#13;
&#13;
 the country circumstances.     How we proceed in an&#13;
&#13;
 individual country will depend on the initial conditions.&#13;
&#13;
 Where we want to end by 2015 will also depend on&#13;
&#13;
 government ownership, resource availability and&#13;
&#13;
 institutional capacities.&#13;
&#13;
           In this regard, the paper broadly states that&#13;
&#13;
 there is a potential tradeoff between external assistance&#13;
&#13;
 to expedite the process and ultimate ownership.       This&#13;
&#13;
 seems to be a fact that is often ignored when we announced&#13;
                                                               Page40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 that the government should always be in the driver's seat.&#13;
&#13;
 This tradeoff or tension could slow down progress towards&#13;
&#13;
 achieving the international development goals.&#13;
&#13;
           Implementation of the proposed framework puts&#13;
&#13;
 pressure on the Bank to deliver.       It also has operational&#13;
&#13;
 and perhaps organizational implications to the Bank that&#13;
&#13;
 the paper does not adequately discuss.         I can think of two&#13;
&#13;
 aspects related to this.&#13;
&#13;
           First, the challenge of making units and staff&#13;
&#13;
 move from sectoral-based analysis and interventions to an&#13;
&#13;
 overall framework centered on poverty outcomes.        Staff may&#13;
&#13;
 want to explain how we can make this change across the&#13;
&#13;
 Bank.&#13;
&#13;
           The second is Bank collaboration with the IMF.&#13;
&#13;
 The proposed poverty strategy paper that could replace the&#13;
&#13;
 PFP will put additional pressure on the Bank to deliver.&#13;
&#13;
 The IMF paper states in a number of places that the Bank&#13;
&#13;
 is sometimes unable to provide social policy analysis on a&#13;
&#13;
 timely basis because of either staff resource constraints&#13;
&#13;
 or mismatched Bank-Fund work cycles.        The paper goes on to&#13;
&#13;
 pose the question to the IMF Directors whether they think&#13;
&#13;
 that the IMF should increase staff resources and hire new&#13;
&#13;
 specialized staff to meet the needs.        In fact, some units&#13;
                                                                     Page41&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 may have already started hiring specialized staff.          Of&#13;
&#13;
 course, poverty reduction, if it is not already, should be&#13;
&#13;
 the bread and butter of the bank.        Inability to deliver&#13;
&#13;
 should be a major concern for management.&#13;
&#13;
             I have two more technical points on the poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction paper.    First, the paper seems to put too much&#13;
&#13;
 emphasis on slow growth as a major cause of poverty.          My&#13;
&#13;
 understanding is that growth policies are very effective&#13;
&#13;
 when the income distribution is fairly egalitarian.          But&#13;
&#13;
 when the income distribution is highly skewed,&#13;
&#13;
 redistribution policies are more effective.         This&#13;
&#13;
 highlights the importance of understanding and starting&#13;
&#13;
 with the initial conditions in the country.&#13;
&#13;
             My second technical point concerns the use of&#13;
&#13;
 poverty lines.    It is always preferable to use a range of&#13;
&#13;
 poverty lines and measures that capture the depth and&#13;
&#13;
 severity of poverty as opposed to using a single poverty&#13;
&#13;
 line.   These will indicate how many households or&#13;
&#13;
 individuals hover around the poverty line and whether the&#13;
&#13;
 profile of poverty changes with different lines.           This is&#13;
&#13;
 extremely important for policy and for the design of&#13;
&#13;
 projects.&#13;
                                                                      Page42&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
             It is possible that with this kind of approach,&#13;
&#13;
 we would not have been, quote, "unprepared for the&#13;
&#13;
 dimensions of the social crisis in Asia".&#13;
&#13;
             Mr. Chairman, I have the following final comment&#13;
&#13;
 on the social and structural reviews.          If delivered, as&#13;
&#13;
 indicated in Annex Table 1, we would have made good&#13;
&#13;
 progress on completing these papers for the pilot&#13;
&#13;
 countries.    By then, we would have acquired sufficient&#13;
&#13;
 experience to evaluate whether we should move forward from&#13;
&#13;
 the pilot phase to broader implementation.&#13;
&#13;
             This is not specifically discussed in the paper,&#13;
&#13;
 and we should return to the subject at an opportune time.&#13;
&#13;
             Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. SANDSTROM:   Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
             Jaime Alvarez, please.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. ALVAREZ:   Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
             Let me first acknowledge staff for very&#13;
&#13;
 comprehensive papers, especially the HIPC one.         Without&#13;
&#13;
 diminishing the importance of the earlier two papers, we&#13;
&#13;
 would like to concentrate our comments on the HIPC one,&#13;
&#13;
 given that it is a very good analysis of the different&#13;
&#13;
 approaches being used to tackle poverty to targeted&#13;
&#13;
 programs.&#13;
                                                                   Page43&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
             In general, we found that the paper is well-&#13;
&#13;
 balanced, making use of good policy analysis, while&#13;
&#13;
 blending the views of many interested parties.      Trying to&#13;
&#13;
 accommodate different, often conflicting, views is a&#13;
&#13;
 difficult task and staff of both institutions should be&#13;
&#13;
 commended for their efforts.&#13;
&#13;
             The first point that caught our attention in the&#13;
&#13;
 paper is the recognition by staff that increasing budget&#13;
&#13;
 spending along may not have effect in poverty programmed&#13;
&#13;
 outcomes.    This recognition is important for at least two&#13;
&#13;
 reasons, both of which we have mentioned in different HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 discussions.&#13;
&#13;
             The first one has to do with efficiency and&#13;
&#13;
 public expenditure.    Increases in budget expenditure alone&#13;
&#13;
 should not be taken as a measure for commitment to poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction, much less as an indicator of poverty&#13;
&#13;
 alleviation.    It is important to remember that in some&#13;
&#13;
 cases HIPC assistance will provide just for breathing&#13;
&#13;
 space to pay external commitment; thus, the effect on&#13;
&#13;
 spending should not be expected.&#13;
&#13;
             Furthermore, in a country with a weak delivery&#13;
&#13;
 system of social services, an increasing expenditure for&#13;
&#13;
 social services would create wasteful programs.     One can&#13;
                                                                 Page44&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 always argue, as several commentators did, an&#13;
&#13;
 institutional capacity needs to be strengthened.     But&#13;
&#13;
 capacity building for service delivery does not guarantee&#13;
&#13;
 efficient outcomes.&#13;
&#13;
           Educational outcomes in areas with among the&#13;
&#13;
 best teacher training, salaries, infrastructure and&#13;
&#13;
 equipment in the world are comparable with those countries&#13;
&#13;
 that spend much less.&#13;
&#13;
           A second reason why budget expenditure alone is&#13;
&#13;
 misleading has to do with individual's spending patterns,&#13;
&#13;
 patterns that could greatly affect the efficiency of&#13;
&#13;
 providing social services.     If a country, due to debt&#13;
&#13;
 relief scheme, allows their citizens to use more&#13;
&#13;
 disposable income to purchase social services that affect&#13;
&#13;
 poverty indicators, then poverty alleviation could take&#13;
&#13;
 place.&#13;
&#13;
           Regardless of spending levels, one might find&#13;
&#13;
 outcomes of providing service more efficient in some&#13;
&#13;
 societies more than in others.      Outcome could be closer&#13;
&#13;
 linked to the competitive environment under which services&#13;
&#13;
 are provided.   One suggestion to staff, while another is&#13;
&#13;
 in poverty, is to consider social services being financed&#13;
&#13;
 and provided by both the public and private sectors.&#13;
                                                               Page45&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
             Staff could expand on the role of private sector&#13;
&#13;
 provision of social services, especially in light of the&#13;
&#13;
 part that delivery capacity in HIPC countries could be&#13;
&#13;
 weak.&#13;
&#13;
             To follow up on the point Mr. Fallon made this&#13;
&#13;
 morning about the impact of poverty and poverty that&#13;
&#13;
 access to water may have, we could only add that recent&#13;
&#13;
 research by Bank staff points out the desirability of&#13;
&#13;
 deregulated private provision of services in that sector.&#13;
&#13;
             We are of the opinion that, at this point in&#13;
&#13;
 time, no option should be disregarded.&#13;
&#13;
             The Bank presented results of poverty funds,&#13;
&#13;
 Section 47, being used to target poverty.           The paper&#13;
&#13;
 identifies several shortcoming of such funds in reaching&#13;
&#13;
 the poor.    While mentioning the shortcomings of poverty&#13;
&#13;
 funds in some developing countries, the paper disappoints&#13;
&#13;
 us for not revealing similar problems with poverty funds&#13;
&#13;
 in industrialized countries.&#13;
&#13;
             By extending the analysis to identify&#13;
&#13;
 shortcomings of poverty programs, two experiences in&#13;
&#13;
 industrialized countries, one could get generalization for&#13;
&#13;
 such type of programs, thus avoiding the perception that&#13;
&#13;
 if we correct this or by improving in some areas, like,&#13;
                                                                 Page46&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 for example, capacity building, one may get efficient&#13;
&#13;
 outcomes.&#13;
&#13;
             Competition in the provision of public services,&#13;
&#13;
 as well as consumer empowerment in the selection of&#13;
&#13;
 providers, could have a great impact in poverty service&#13;
&#13;
 outputs.    Staff should be mindful of the proposals that&#13;
&#13;
 limit competition for the provision of social services,&#13;
&#13;
 and in that respect we are glad that, although many&#13;
&#13;
 commentators brought up such approaches, they were&#13;
&#13;
 somewhat disregarded.&#13;
&#13;
             Another point worth mentioning again has to do&#13;
&#13;
 with representation in the policy formulation process.&#13;
&#13;
 Like increases in budget expenditure, increases in the&#13;
&#13;
 number of entities that participate in the political&#13;
&#13;
 dialogue do not guarantee ownership or the desired&#13;
&#13;
 reforms.    Representation is something that has to be&#13;
&#13;
 defined within the political process of each individual&#13;
&#13;
 HIPC country.    Like in all areas, an appropriate measure&#13;
&#13;
 should be identified for each desired outcome.&#13;
&#13;
             To the extent that the desired outcome is a wide&#13;
&#13;
 participatory process, the matrix to evaluate performance&#13;
&#13;
 has to be chosen according to it.        If we are monitoring&#13;
&#13;
 process, let us measure it.&#13;
                                                                 Page47&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           The proposal for improving debt management in&#13;
&#13;
 HIPC countries is a good.     Recommendation along the lines&#13;
&#13;
 of improving accountability and transparency should be&#13;
&#13;
 properly assessed.   The World Bank started technical&#13;
&#13;
 assistance work recently in this area.         This work, along&#13;
&#13;
 with the work being performed by other institutions, would&#13;
&#13;
 enhance management capability in borrowing countries.&#13;
&#13;
           The literature is reaching and analyzing the&#13;
&#13;
 role of different actors in the budget process, including&#13;
&#13;
 parliaments and interest groups.       The Bank and the Fund&#13;
&#13;
 should be mindful of such analysis and should weigh the&#13;
&#13;
 pros and cons the proposals that could work against the&#13;
&#13;
 aim for economic reforms that could bring sustainable&#13;
&#13;
 growth to HIPC countries.&#13;
&#13;
           Finally, going back to the other two papers, in&#13;
&#13;
 our opinion they focus on the traditional poor.         Recent&#13;
&#13;
 research of the Bank has presented a clear link between&#13;
&#13;
 poverty and lack of access to employment.          This lack of&#13;
&#13;
 access to employment is limited to the traditional poor or&#13;
&#13;
 limits access to the traditional poor and to the new poor.&#13;
&#13;
 We think the Bank in a revision paper should properly&#13;
&#13;
 reflect the analysis that the Bank has performed.&#13;
                                                                   Page48&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           In summing up, we can go along with most of the&#13;
&#13;
 questions posed by staff, but in echoing Mr. Schaffer we&#13;
&#13;
 think that each country deserves case-by-case attention,&#13;
&#13;
 taking into consideration the points that were mentioned.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:     Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
           John Sinclair, please.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SINCLAIR:     Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
           I think we found these papers very&#13;
&#13;
 comprehensive, thoughtful and sensitive.            In fact, I think&#13;
&#13;
 together they serve as a key set of stepping stones&#13;
&#13;
 towards a very different sense of priority for the poor in&#13;
&#13;
 all of our work.   They represent a critical coming&#13;
&#13;
 together of the Bretton Woods institutions, and I know&#13;
&#13;
 that is happening all the time.        But I think, most&#13;
&#13;
 importantly, they demand a sustained operational level of&#13;
&#13;
 collaboration between those institutions.&#13;
&#13;
           And picking up my Ghanaian colleague's&#13;
&#13;
 challenge, I think that is going to be a very, very&#13;
&#13;
 difficult and very important dimension of this work,&#13;
&#13;
 especially bringing the client government to the center of&#13;
&#13;
 that process.&#13;
                                                                        Page49&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           We agree that any new poverty reduction&#13;
&#13;
 framework needs to be rooted in the four elements that are&#13;
&#13;
 mentioned -- broad-based participatory process; improved&#13;
&#13;
 transparency and accountability for government -- and I&#13;
&#13;
 think in that dimension I would mention the desirability&#13;
&#13;
 of greater efforts of monitoring and analyzing some of the&#13;
&#13;
 extra budgetary spending elements that sometimes confuse&#13;
&#13;
 our interpretations of that level -- most fundamentally,&#13;
&#13;
 the understanding that poverty is indeed a multi-&#13;
&#13;
 dimensional phenomenon, that it is not just something&#13;
&#13;
 about income; and finally, that there is a reminder that&#13;
&#13;
 sustained poverty reduction is impossible for sure without&#13;
&#13;
 quality economic growth, but also that trickle-down is&#13;
&#13;
 rarely enough.&#13;
&#13;
           Implicitly, I think we are reconfirming that&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction should be the new underpinning, not of a&#13;
&#13;
 few but, of all of our interventions.         Under the enhanced&#13;
&#13;
 HIPC paper in front of us, we are adding debt relief to&#13;
&#13;
 that list of supportive instruments.        I think in the&#13;
&#13;
 vocabulary CDF, we are again seeing the interplay between&#13;
&#13;
 the social and the economic in an organic whole.&#13;
&#13;
           I think the Bank paper sees these new poverty&#13;
&#13;
 goals being mobilized around an instrument called the&#13;
                                                                    Page50&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction strategy paper.         And in that light, I&#13;
&#13;
 would add some words my Director reminded me to mention&#13;
&#13;
 that her sincere hope is that this will be one paper that&#13;
&#13;
 we know by its title rather than by an acronym, especially&#13;
&#13;
 since the acronym is hard to pronounce.&#13;
&#13;
           I think we support that poverty strategy and its&#13;
&#13;
 proposed role as the core instrument for assessing&#13;
&#13;
 eligibility under the enhanced HIPC.          I already mentioned&#13;
&#13;
 some of the key elements we saw as important to the&#13;
&#13;
 poverty strategy.    I would add that, as drafted, it is&#13;
&#13;
 rather thin on implicit concerns for gender and the&#13;
&#13;
 environment.&#13;
&#13;
           I think we agree very strongly that the&#13;
&#13;
 insistence that ownership is crucial is a correct one.&#13;
&#13;
 Any meaningful poverty strategy has to be home-grown.&#13;
&#13;
           As others have mentioned, the preparation of&#13;
&#13;
 these strategies are going to be complex and demanding&#13;
&#13;
 and, in that context, I think we will need to finesse the&#13;
&#13;
 situation where the addition of this focus for HIPC could&#13;
&#13;
 be seen, especially in its early days, not as a new burden&#13;
&#13;
 of conditionality for the countries concerns, a new set of&#13;
&#13;
 goal posts which have moved.        We would rather like to see&#13;
                                                                     Page51&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction as replacing, not adding to, some&#13;
&#13;
 conditionalities.&#13;
&#13;
             In that sense, especially for the existing&#13;
&#13;
 HIPCs, we may need process-type targets, are they putting&#13;
&#13;
 place an effective poverty strategy.&#13;
&#13;
             Realistically, key to the longer term, we don't&#13;
&#13;
 expect poverty outcome indicators to be available&#13;
&#13;
 meaningfully in the first two or three years of new HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 decisions.    I think we would be intrigued to understand&#13;
&#13;
 how staff see these early cases being handled.        I think we&#13;
&#13;
 had a little bit of an impression of that at the beginning&#13;
&#13;
 but it may be useful to reconfirm that.&#13;
&#13;
             Most importantly, whether within a HIPC or just&#13;
&#13;
 as a new normal IDA activity, the existence of a poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction strategy should radically change the rules of&#13;
&#13;
 the game.    For sure, they will crucially become central&#13;
&#13;
 elements within a CDF scenario.         Their thinking should be&#13;
&#13;
 a central influence on a CAS.        Indeed, one would hope and&#13;
&#13;
 assume that their consultative processes would largely&#13;
&#13;
 overlap and flow into the CG process.&#13;
&#13;
             We assume that the poverty strategy will become&#13;
&#13;
 a central feature of the new guidance to CAS authors, that&#13;
&#13;
 we heard being mentioned a couple of days ago before.        And&#13;
                                                                    Page52&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 I suppose in the context of Question 3, we certainly would&#13;
&#13;
 support a steady expansion of the range of countries being&#13;
&#13;
 covered.&#13;
&#13;
            I must also assume that the same strategies will&#13;
&#13;
 significantly condition the framework of an ESAF.       And I&#13;
&#13;
 think this is clearly the challenge for our colleagues&#13;
&#13;
 across the street in recognizing that future fiscal&#13;
&#13;
 framework recommendations should proactively seek to leave&#13;
&#13;
 space for pro-poor for social expenditures.&#13;
&#13;
            The Trican [phonetic] surveys used in Uganda&#13;
&#13;
 would seem to be an important and useful monitoring&#13;
&#13;
 mechanism.    And, as my Irish colleagues have suggested,&#13;
&#13;
 there could be much merit in protecting core social&#13;
&#13;
 expenditures via the concept of ring-fencing in budgetary&#13;
&#13;
 frameworks.&#13;
&#13;
            Conceptually, we favor the outcome focus&#13;
&#13;
 thinking of the poverty strategy.        However, I think we&#13;
&#13;
 would have to caution against false expectations.       We were&#13;
&#13;
 only discussing yesterday the realities in the Strategic&#13;
&#13;
 Compact that output targets are very hard to define and,&#13;
&#13;
 at best, have been now embodied in the CAS frameworks&#13;
&#13;
 themselves.   I think we will have to rely more on&#13;
&#13;
 intermediates and encourage governments and countries to&#13;
                                                                   Page53&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 align their national goals around the framework of the key&#13;
&#13;
 international development goals.&#13;
&#13;
            In that spirit, the Bank and other donors will&#13;
&#13;
 need to stand ready to support capacity building in those&#13;
&#13;
 areas, in data collection, enhanced budgetary design, in&#13;
&#13;
 many dimensions, as others have mentioned.&#13;
&#13;
            I think on the positive side of an outcomes&#13;
&#13;
 discussion, we would hope that the strategy is intimately&#13;
&#13;
 linked and quickly linked in the CAS or the CDF or&#13;
&#13;
 whatever to an action plan.     I think we need very clear to&#13;
&#13;
 see this as something related to the whole programmatic&#13;
&#13;
 process.&#13;
&#13;
            A word of caution:    We see all this process as&#13;
&#13;
 part of a master plan, a well-conceived master plan,&#13;
&#13;
 hopefully to take poverty reduction to the heart of the&#13;
&#13;
 development process.   And in that spirit, just as our&#13;
&#13;
 Nordic colleagues alluded to, I think we are a little&#13;
&#13;
 worried that the idea of a stand-alone poverty note, even&#13;
&#13;
 if it is a CAS annex, will have the spirit of an&#13;
&#13;
 independent perspective.&#13;
&#13;
            I think we would rather see the mind set goal&#13;
&#13;
 being one of making the CAS into a totally holistic&#13;
&#13;
 document and, in that sense, at least for poverty&#13;
                                                                 Page54&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 mainstreaming, it should be mandatory, rather than an&#13;
&#13;
 annex poverty note.&#13;
&#13;
           We were talking briefly yesterday about a&#13;
&#13;
 version of question of proliferation, which I thought was&#13;
&#13;
 supposed to end with the Cold War.        However, I think we&#13;
&#13;
 are seeing it still today, not in the military sense.       We&#13;
&#13;
 are seeing it in terms of the numbers of documentations,&#13;
&#13;
 the different sort of approaches we have to these agendas.&#13;
&#13;
           We have SSRs, rightly complaining that some ESW&#13;
&#13;
 building blocks were missing.      We have encouraged a new&#13;
&#13;
 generation of participatory PERs.       I was at a presentation&#13;
&#13;
 in which I learned a great deal about NIRs, and they&#13;
&#13;
 seemed very, very important also.       And just a few weeks&#13;
&#13;
 ago, we were in a room and we were talking about PSLs and&#13;
&#13;
 PAPs, though I understand PAPs was considered to be a&#13;
&#13;
 little offensive as an acronym.&#13;
&#13;
           All in all, I think these could be worthy&#13;
&#13;
 elements in an evolution of a sound poverty reduction&#13;
&#13;
 strategy, but I think they also risk the potentiality of&#13;
&#13;
 being like those mysterious disconnected files we get&#13;
&#13;
 warned about as cluttering our hard drives.        And I suppose&#13;
&#13;
 we would put in a small quiet plea for some consolidation.&#13;
                                                                    Page55&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           I think we are moving the pieces together, but&#13;
&#13;
 let's not, in a sense, have too much dispersal of that&#13;
&#13;
 energy.&#13;
&#13;
           Finally, to conclude then, I think we would have&#13;
&#13;
 to say we very strongly welcome these efforts to add flesh&#13;
&#13;
 and bones to the commitment of poverty reduction that is&#13;
&#13;
 at the heart of this institution's mandate.        It is, in a&#13;
&#13;
 sense, very, very appropriate that the chosen instrument,&#13;
&#13;
 the poverty strategy, will also be a critical bridge to&#13;
&#13;
 strengthen in the work on the HIPC and our relationship&#13;
&#13;
 with the Fund across the way.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you very much, John.&#13;
&#13;
           Neil Hyden, please.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. HYDEN:   Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
           I join with other Directors in welcoming these&#13;
&#13;
 papers and the framework that they present.        This is a&#13;
&#13;
 marked advance, perhaps even an historic one, and we very&#13;
&#13;
 warmly support it, and support the broad elements that are&#13;
&#13;
 in it.&#13;
&#13;
           I wanted really just to take up two points or&#13;
&#13;
 two issues at this stage.     One links to the point that Mr.&#13;
&#13;
 Sinclair was just making about the burdens that are placed&#13;
                                                                  Page56&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 on countries in trying to meet all of our requirements,&#13;
&#13;
 and the variety of forms and reports and whatever they&#13;
&#13;
 have to fill in.&#13;
&#13;
           Many of our countries don't have capacity to put&#13;
&#13;
 huge resources into these sorts of exercises, and that&#13;
&#13;
 applies certainly to some of my constituents.        So,&#13;
&#13;
 consolidation will clearly help.&#13;
&#13;
           But even so, the requirements we are putting on&#13;
&#13;
 them is formidable.    My advice to them in those&#13;
&#13;
 circumstances, when they ask, well, if we cannot do the&#13;
&#13;
 whole job, which bit is most important, I think the most&#13;
&#13;
 important bit is the framework; that is, the broad&#13;
&#13;
 elements that are set out here of identifying the national&#13;
&#13;
 objectives, of the country itself having ownership of&#13;
&#13;
 that, of identifying the means and options for pursuing&#13;
&#13;
 those objectives, having some measurement of outcome,&#13;
&#13;
 coordination of the efforts between the various supporters&#13;
&#13;
 and donors.&#13;
&#13;
           So, the key elements of this framework are&#13;
&#13;
 really the most important elements.         The detail of how it&#13;
&#13;
 is implemented I think can be done flexibly and tailored&#13;
&#13;
 to the circumstances of individual countries.&#13;
                                                                    Page57&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
            If they get the questions right, then it is much&#13;
&#13;
 easier to get the answers right, even if you don't have&#13;
&#13;
 such sophisticated analyses and report writing as we would&#13;
&#13;
 like.&#13;
&#13;
            The second question I would like to refer to is&#13;
&#13;
 the treatment of governance and empowerment in the papers.&#13;
&#13;
 Governance is very important.       We discussed this with the&#13;
&#13;
 President last night at our dinner, and he made the point&#13;
&#13;
 that governance was central to almost all things that&#13;
&#13;
 countries were trying to do.       If you don't have good&#13;
&#13;
 governance, then it is pretty hard to have good economic&#13;
&#13;
 performance, if the budget doesn't operate, if monetary&#13;
&#13;
 policy doesn't operate, if the court systems don't&#13;
&#13;
 operate.&#13;
&#13;
            Yet, in the frameworks we are presented with,&#13;
&#13;
 governance is not seen as something which affects&#13;
&#13;
 everything.   It is put into a category of its own.     In the&#13;
&#13;
 paper on "Building Poverty Reduction Strategies", in Table&#13;
&#13;
 1 on page 9, we see that good governance is linked to the&#13;
&#13;
 objective of empowerment and participation in decision-&#13;
&#13;
 making.    But it is really much more than that.    It relates&#13;
&#13;
 also to economic opportunities; it relates to the heading&#13;
                                                                  Page58&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 of capabilities, of literacy, education, health; it&#13;
&#13;
 relates to security.&#13;
&#13;
           One example:   In one of the countries I&#13;
&#13;
 represent, teachers have not been paid for six months.       It&#13;
&#13;
 is because of a breakdown in governance in the central&#13;
&#13;
 government.   It is not an isolated example.&#13;
&#13;
           Infrastructure programs, capital works programs,&#13;
&#13;
 also completely chaotic because of inadequate governance.&#13;
&#13;
 So, unless governance is dealt with as a central concern,&#13;
&#13;
 most of these other objectives are so much more difficult&#13;
&#13;
 to achieve.&#13;
&#13;
           If, as in this table, we link good governance to&#13;
&#13;
 empowerment, we risk downgrading it to something,&#13;
&#13;
 something which is less important than economic growth,&#13;
&#13;
 less important than education and health, less important&#13;
&#13;
 than security.&#13;
&#13;
           In many countries, empowerment I think is&#13;
&#13;
 something which is not so readily endorsed as an objective&#13;
&#13;
 as some of the other objectives of this strategy --&#13;
&#13;
 economic growth, education, social objectives.     That is&#13;
&#13;
 because empowerment takes countries into difficult&#13;
&#13;
 questions of representative arrangements, parliamentary&#13;
&#13;
 processes, public dialogue, and one can understand why&#13;
                                                                   Page59&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 many countries need to tailor what they do to their&#13;
&#13;
 capacities and circumstances.&#13;
&#13;
            I, therefore, am concerned that if we link&#13;
&#13;
 governance to an empowerment objective, we are in danger&#13;
&#13;
 of seeing it given inadequate attention because of the&#13;
&#13;
 reservations that some countries will inevitably attach to&#13;
&#13;
 empowerment as an objective as such.        And if we are giving&#13;
&#13;
 countries ownership and we believe in that, then we have&#13;
&#13;
 to follow their preferences.&#13;
&#13;
            In the paper on HIPC and "Strengthening the Link&#13;
&#13;
 Between Debt Relief and Poverty Reduction", the comparable&#13;
&#13;
 table, which is Box 7 on page 27, treats the issues&#13;
&#13;
 differently.   There is no reference there to empowerment&#13;
&#13;
 as such.   The heading becomes transparency, accountability&#13;
&#13;
 and budget management, which is clearly a subsector of&#13;
&#13;
 good governance but it is not all of good governance.&#13;
&#13;
            So, this area I think needs some closer&#13;
&#13;
 attention.   I would like to see good governance made as a&#13;
&#13;
 separate heading, probably a chapeau across the top that&#13;
&#13;
 applies to all.   One can keep the section on empowerment&#13;
&#13;
 and perhaps attach to that the issues relating to&#13;
&#13;
 participation, participatory processes, information and&#13;
                                                                    Page60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 public dialogue.   So, it is still there, but it doesn't&#13;
&#13;
 compete with good governance.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:     Thank you very much, Neil.&#13;
&#13;
           Jean Pesme, please.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. PESME:    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
           I would also like to commend the IMF and Bank&#13;
&#13;
 staff for these very impressive pieces of paper.         I must&#13;
&#13;
 say it is sometimes difficult to comment on them because&#13;
&#13;
 they are very comprehensive and well reflect the&#13;
&#13;
 complexity of the issue, which also means that when we&#13;
&#13;
 come to make them operational, it may be quite tricky&#13;
&#13;
 because we will have to lose part of this complexity to&#13;
&#13;
 make sure that we are doing something.          But I will come&#13;
&#13;
 back on that later.&#13;
&#13;
           On the substance, we are in global agreement&#13;
&#13;
 with the main thrust of all the papers and we welcome the&#13;
&#13;
 opportunity taken to somehow scale up the commitment of&#13;
&#13;
 the two institutions to fight against poverty at the&#13;
&#13;
 occasion of this momentum linked to the HIPC Initiative.&#13;
&#13;
           I agree with Bassary Toure that nothing is&#13;
&#13;
 really new, but we understand the proposal of the&#13;
&#13;
 framework as a way to try to rationalize and be more&#13;
                                                                   Page61&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 systematic in our approach for poverty alleviation.       And&#13;
&#13;
 we very much appreciate this proposal from this&#13;
&#13;
 standpoint.&#13;
&#13;
           Now some features of the proposal we would like&#13;
&#13;
 to particularly welcome.    The first one is the strong&#13;
&#13;
 interlinkage between growth and social progress and the&#13;
&#13;
 emphasis on distribution of growth.        And we think it is a&#13;
&#13;
 very important part of the proposal.&#13;
&#13;
           The second one is that placing poverty reduction&#13;
&#13;
 at the center of our involvement must be a criteria for&#13;
&#13;
 selectivity.   And the fact that we have been able to try&#13;
&#13;
 to tackle with all the issues why putting selectivity at&#13;
&#13;
 the forefront is very important.&#13;
&#13;
           The proposal to add a long-term and multi-&#13;
&#13;
 sectoral approach is also very welcomed, as well as the&#13;
&#13;
 efforts not to remain only in the HIPC context but to&#13;
&#13;
 broaden the approach.&#13;
&#13;
           This being said, there are three points on which&#13;
&#13;
 we will pay attention.    The first one is that this&#13;
&#13;
 approach should not undermine the macroeconomic&#13;
&#13;
 conditionality of IMF programs, in particular in the HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 context, which means that sometimes we will have make some&#13;
&#13;
 balance and make more explicit some of the social&#13;
                                                                   Page62&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 consequences of this macroeconomic program, which is very&#13;
&#13;
 welcome, but not at the expense of the core issues of the&#13;
&#13;
 IMF program.&#13;
&#13;
           The second point is that strong political will&#13;
&#13;
 from the authorities of the beneficiary countries will be&#13;
&#13;
 very important in the implementation.         And this approach&#13;
&#13;
 should not only be Bank and IMF approach but really have a&#13;
&#13;
 sense of ownership, not in the country in general -- I&#13;
&#13;
 will come back on the participatory process -- but at&#13;
&#13;
 really the political level in these countries.&#13;
&#13;
           The third issue relates to what has just been&#13;
&#13;
 mentioned by Mr. Hyden on governance.         I would just add to&#13;
&#13;
 that, that the more we are going towards a multi-&#13;
&#13;
 dimensional approach, assessment of outcomes, et cetera,&#13;
&#13;
 the more necessary it will be to make sure that we know&#13;
&#13;
 exactly what is the use of the resources we are providing,&#13;
&#13;
 that accountability and transparency is there.        So, we&#13;
&#13;
 must pay great attention to that, so that we know at each&#13;
&#13;
 stage what is going on.&#13;
&#13;
           Second, on the methodology which is proposed, we&#13;
&#13;
 agree with what we see as three key elements -- the&#13;
&#13;
 emphasis on determinants of poverty; selectivity in the&#13;
&#13;
 choice of public action; and the focus on outcome&#13;
                                                                     Page63&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 indicators, both in the context of the international&#13;
&#13;
 development targets and having some short and medium-term&#13;
&#13;
 intermediate objectives.&#13;
&#13;
            Once more, it is not fully revolutionary and it&#13;
&#13;
 has proved in the past to be a robust approach, but what&#13;
&#13;
 we very much appreciate is the fact that it is now&#13;
&#13;
 systematic and we expect this to be put in place very&#13;
&#13;
 quickly.&#13;
&#13;
            But, as mentioned by several other speakers, it&#13;
&#13;
 should not become a straitjacket, and we will have to have&#13;
&#13;
 the right balance between a country-by-country approach&#13;
&#13;
 and also, which will be very important in the HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 context, I think appropriate fairness between the&#13;
&#13;
 countries, which sometimes might be very difficult.&#13;
&#13;
            But we think case-by-case, yes, but making sure&#13;
&#13;
 that across-the-board we will treat every country the same&#13;
&#13;
 way.   That is something I will come back on a bit later on&#13;
&#13;
 Nicaragua.&#13;
&#13;
            The second point in this process is being&#13;
&#13;
 careful -- it has been mentioned by other speakers -- on&#13;
&#13;
 the participatory process.     Each country has somehow its&#13;
&#13;
 own political economy, and we must make sure that the way&#13;
&#13;
 that we will be discussing with the country will be fully&#13;
                                                               Page64&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 taken into account.   And there are some representative&#13;
&#13;
 bodies.   There are now processes of legitimacy in each&#13;
&#13;
 country, to which we will have to pay attention and in&#13;
&#13;
 which we would have to fit our approach.&#13;
&#13;
           We must remain very careful not to convey a kind&#13;
&#13;
 of across-the-board participatory process.         This will be,&#13;
&#13;
 in our view, a very important condition for ownership but&#13;
&#13;
 also for this very strong political involvement at the&#13;
&#13;
 highest level, so that everybody in each country will be&#13;
&#13;
 committed to the poverty reduction strategies.&#13;
&#13;
           On implementation, there are three levels of&#13;
&#13;
 challenges on implementation, and somehow at this stage we&#13;
&#13;
 are still with a very general framework and we will need&#13;
&#13;
 to know more on what it means operationally.&#13;
&#13;
           At the country level, I want to come back on&#13;
&#13;
 what has been said the capacity building, the difficulty&#13;
&#13;
 with statistical issues when defining the intermediary&#13;
&#13;
 outcomes, and just to take the table which is in the annex&#13;
&#13;
 of the paper, there are some figures which show that we&#13;
&#13;
 may have big holes in our assessment of what is going on&#13;
&#13;
 in many of the HIPC countries, in particular.&#13;
&#13;
           But it also means that we will have&#13;
&#13;
 implementation challenges at the Bank level.        I won't come&#13;
                                                                    Page65&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 back on the discussion we have had some months ago on the&#13;
&#13;
 poverty progress report, which has shown that, yes, we&#13;
&#13;
 have made progress but, on the other hand, doing it on a&#13;
&#13;
 day-by-day basis and making sure that each country team is&#13;
&#13;
 fully involved in that process and really puts that at the&#13;
&#13;
 forefront, at the center of the relationship with the&#13;
&#13;
 country is not always very easy.&#13;
&#13;
           I am not sure that we currently have all the&#13;
&#13;
 skills to put in place the proposed framework and, in&#13;
&#13;
 particular, this attention to political economy in each&#13;
&#13;
 country, that we have the skills to assess poverty in all&#13;
&#13;
 its dimensions.   We had a discussion some time ago on the&#13;
&#13;
 urban strategy which shows that we were weak on that side.&#13;
&#13;
           So, the question of also scaling up our&#13;
&#13;
 mobilization of internal skills and resources will be very&#13;
&#13;
 important in the way we implement the proposed framework.&#13;
&#13;
           But another important issue of implementation&#13;
&#13;
 would be the way we present it towards outside&#13;
&#13;
 stakeholders.   We fully concur with staff that the impact&#13;
&#13;
 of our involvement in poverty reduction will have to be&#13;
&#13;
 assessed on the long-term, but there are very strong&#13;
&#13;
 expectations, in particular in the HIPC context, in the&#13;
&#13;
 shorter term.   So, the way we balance that will be very&#13;
                                                              Page66&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 important, and we must be very clear on how actually our&#13;
&#13;
 involvement in the HIPC context will demonstrate that we&#13;
&#13;
 are focused on poverty reduction.&#13;
&#13;
           On implementation, John Sinclair was very&#13;
&#13;
 eloquent in coming back to all the acronyms.        Making sure&#13;
&#13;
 that somehow we aggregate all of our assessments, papers,&#13;
&#13;
 et cetera will be very important in clarifying what is&#13;
&#13;
 center to our dialogue with the countries.         And so far the&#13;
&#13;
 way the link would be made between these poverty programs&#13;
&#13;
 and the CASs or the CDF, where the CDF is tested, is not&#13;
&#13;
 very clear, in our view.    And maybe this will be part of&#13;
&#13;
 the upcoming discussion for the Annual Meetings on&#13;
&#13;
 implementation.&#13;
&#13;
           One point more specific to the HIPC context.        We&#13;
&#13;
 believe that these poverty reduction programs must be&#13;
&#13;
 linked with the decision point.       And somehow we will have&#13;
&#13;
 to balance the willingness to accelerate the process and&#13;
&#13;
 the fact that we must make sure that in the new context we&#13;
&#13;
 can demonstrate that there is strengthening of the link&#13;
&#13;
 between debt relief and poverty alleviation.        So, we will&#13;
&#13;
 have to make some tradeoffs, and we are not clear at this&#13;
&#13;
 stage on how we should make these tradeoffs, in particular&#13;
&#13;
 in the context of retroactive countries.&#13;
                                                                     Page67&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           This was part of the discussion we had in early&#13;
&#13;
 August and, frankly, we are not very clear on how both the&#13;
&#13;
 IMF and the Bank staff intend to handle this issue of&#13;
&#13;
 balancing between the need to demonstrate and the need to&#13;
&#13;
 be quite quick in the process.&#13;
&#13;
           This will have also consequences in terms of&#13;
&#13;
 fairness of the process between the various countries and,&#13;
&#13;
 in particular, the way we treat the retroactive country.&#13;
&#13;
 So, once more, yes, for case-by-case approach, but we must&#13;
&#13;
 make sure that all of this is consistent.&#13;
&#13;
           One point on the link with the IMF.           Several&#13;
&#13;
 speakers mentioned that operational collaboration between&#13;
&#13;
 the two institutions will be crucial in achieving the&#13;
&#13;
 objectives we are setting to ourselves.            We believe that&#13;
&#13;
 in this sector the Bank should have the leadership and&#13;
&#13;
 that the expertise on the social sector must be on the&#13;
&#13;
 Bank side, and that the two institutions should be in the&#13;
&#13;
 position to complement each other from this standpoint.&#13;
&#13;
           The British chair has invented the notion of&#13;
&#13;
 intelligent customer, which is very interesting, and it is&#13;
&#13;
 a very good way of presenting it.       But we have to be very&#13;
&#13;
 clear from the Bank side on what it means.           It means that&#13;
&#13;
 we must have the capacity to deliver.         And there are some&#13;
                                                                      Page68&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 tough sentences in the IMF paper on the Bank from this&#13;
&#13;
 standpoint.   But we will be able to justify that we have&#13;
&#13;
 the expertise and we should contribute to the ESAF program&#13;
&#13;
 only if we are able to deliver, which means that, first,&#13;
&#13;
 we may have to modify some of our way of doing business,&#13;
&#13;
 but also adapt our timetables to the IMF ones sometimes.&#13;
&#13;
            And really, there is an issue there.      We have&#13;
&#13;
 been able to solve it after some difficulties in the&#13;
&#13;
 financial sector.    We must be able to do it in the social&#13;
&#13;
 sectors also now.&#13;
&#13;
            One final word on the social and structural&#13;
&#13;
 reviews.   I don't want to open the discussion with Masood&#13;
&#13;
 we had in July on that.      I share the view expressed&#13;
&#13;
 earlier that we are not really in a position to evaluate&#13;
&#13;
 what has been done, but we agree with the fact that these&#13;
&#13;
 two will be very important in implementing this framework.&#13;
&#13;
            On the other hand, we must not lose sight of&#13;
&#13;
 what was the initial purpose of this instrument.       Yes, it&#13;
&#13;
 was created in post-crisis situation and we must expand it&#13;
&#13;
 to more normal business.      But we must really maintain the&#13;
&#13;
 focus on the structure on the identification of structural&#13;
&#13;
 weaknesses and somehow not just focus on social and losing&#13;
&#13;
 sight of that.&#13;
                                                                  Page69&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           And the link between the two will be very&#13;
&#13;
 important.    In the initial paper, as far as I remember,&#13;
&#13;
 the poverty dimension was only one part, what I understand&#13;
&#13;
 as somehow trying to have a chapeau, but only if the other&#13;
&#13;
 building blocks are still there.        And maybe some&#13;
&#13;
 additional comments on that could be useful.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:     Thank you very much, Jean.&#13;
&#13;
           Akira Kamitomai, please.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. KAMITOMAI:     Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
           I would like to join other colleagues to commend&#13;
&#13;
 the staff for their excellent work.         It comprehensively&#13;
&#13;
 presents a strategy for this important challenge.&#13;
&#13;
           We consider the HIPC Initiative as one of the&#13;
&#13;
 important mechanisms to address poverty, and we welcome&#13;
&#13;
 the opportunity to discuss ways to enhance such&#13;
&#13;
 mechanisms.&#13;
&#13;
           Links between debt reduction and poverty&#13;
&#13;
 alleviation must be owned by the HIPC countries&#13;
&#13;
 themselves.   And in this regard, we think it is extremely&#13;
&#13;
 appropriate that the HIPC poverty paper is discussed&#13;
&#13;
 together with the poverty reduction strategy paper that&#13;
                                                                  Page70&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 will be useful for HIPC countries in designing such&#13;
&#13;
 strategy.&#13;
&#13;
             Many of the efforts to strengthen debt relief&#13;
&#13;
 and poverty alleviation is relevant to the Bank's overall&#13;
&#13;
 effort to address poverty.      But I will focus my&#13;
&#13;
 intervention on the HIPC paper, which touches on the two&#13;
&#13;
 related papers as well.&#13;
&#13;
             First of all, as proposed by the management, we&#13;
&#13;
 support the integration of the HIPC Initiative into the&#13;
&#13;
 comprehensive effort to enhance the poverty impact of&#13;
&#13;
 Bank-Fund supported framework.       In implementing the&#13;
&#13;
 comprehensive strategy, we believe that a country-based&#13;
&#13;
 approach is appropriate since each HIPC country is unique&#13;
&#13;
 in its social and economic condition, level of poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction effort, government capacity and in resources&#13;
&#13;
 freed up from debt relief.&#13;
&#13;
             We believe that the CAS will be the most&#13;
&#13;
 important vehicle in the implementation and, hence,&#13;
&#13;
 improving the quality of the CAS would be essential.&#13;
&#13;
             As we have learned from the last poverty&#13;
&#13;
 progress report, we still have a lot of room to improve&#13;
&#13;
 the quality of poverty assessment and to strengthen the&#13;
&#13;
 link between the assessment and the CAS.            We hope that the&#13;
                                                                        Page71&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 Bank will redouble their efforts in these areas, since&#13;
&#13;
 they are important in successful implementation of this&#13;
&#13;
 strategy.&#13;
&#13;
             Secondly, on outcome-oriented approach, we&#13;
&#13;
 believe that this is extremely appropriate since the Bank&#13;
&#13;
 is focusing more on outcomes rather than inputs to assess&#13;
&#13;
 performance of its operations.       We also believe that&#13;
&#13;
 participation of the civil society is important to the&#13;
&#13;
 effectiveness of the strategy, since it enhances&#13;
&#13;
 ownership, transparency and accountability.&#13;
&#13;
             However, up until now, the civil society that&#13;
&#13;
 has made a contribution to the discussion on the debt&#13;
&#13;
 relief and poverty was mainly international advocacy NGOs.&#13;
&#13;
 We hope that as we move towards implementation of this&#13;
&#13;
 strategy, the broader civil society in the field should&#13;
&#13;
 participate in this effort.&#13;
&#13;
             Third, on replacing PFP to PRSP, we are still&#13;
&#13;
 unclear of the added value of this exercise.        We would&#13;
&#13;
 imagine that addressing poverty reduction strategy more&#13;
&#13;
 comprehensively in the CAS, while maintaining full&#13;
&#13;
 consistency with PFP, could be also effective in&#13;
&#13;
 addressing poverty.    We would appreciate staff's comments&#13;
&#13;
 on this point.&#13;
                                                                Page72&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           We also notice that there are similar ESWs&#13;
&#13;
 lately and think it would be useful to streamline some of&#13;
&#13;
 them.   For example, in relation to poverty, there are ESWs&#13;
&#13;
 such as poverty assessment, social assessment and social&#13;
&#13;
 and structural review and the role of these documents are&#13;
&#13;
 not always so clear.&#13;
&#13;
           Other donors are also actively engaged in doing&#13;
&#13;
 similar assessments, and we hope that the Bank will&#13;
&#13;
 coordinate with other donors in order to avoid duplication&#13;
&#13;
 and enhance efficiency.&#13;
&#13;
           Lastly, we can support the idea of having a&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction strategy in place by the decision point,&#13;
&#13;
 but in order for this strategy to be sustainable, even&#13;
&#13;
 after the completion point, it is important that the&#13;
&#13;
 strategy is fully owned by the government.&#13;
&#13;
           In designing such a poverty alleviation&#13;
&#13;
 strategy, we believe that closer collaboration between the&#13;
&#13;
 Bank and the Fund is critical, since the strategy has to&#13;
&#13;
 be fully consistent with the ESAF program.         Therefore, we&#13;
&#13;
 urge strengthened collaboration between these two&#13;
&#13;
 institutions in the operations and for the Bank, as the&#13;
&#13;
 French chair mention, strengthening of the capacity to&#13;
&#13;
 deliver timely is an urgent task.&#13;
                                                                    Page73&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           In addition, strategic benchmarks up to the&#13;
&#13;
 completion points should be the ones that are central to&#13;
&#13;
 the development of the country, and should not be&#13;
&#13;
 compromised for early completion point.&#13;
&#13;
           We believe an early completion point should be&#13;
&#13;
 warranted only in the case of strong performance, and we&#13;
&#13;
 hope such a mechanism will serve as an incentive for HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 countries to achieve the goal.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you very much, Akira.&#13;
&#13;
           Helena Cordeiro, please.&#13;
&#13;
           MS. CORDEIRO:    Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
           At this stage of the debate, I will try to be&#13;
&#13;
 very brief, because a lot of what has been said is&#13;
&#13;
 definitely shared by us and I will try to move it forward,&#13;
&#13;
 if possible.&#13;
&#13;
           I would like to stress immediately that a lot&#13;
&#13;
 what Jean Pesme has said is very much in the same line of&#13;
&#13;
 our thinking, and the need to balance the different&#13;
&#13;
 dimensions of all of this.&#13;
&#13;
           Very briefly, I would like, as many others, to&#13;
&#13;
 welcome these papers, while recognizing that they are&#13;
&#13;
 different; they are different in scope, in quality and in&#13;
                                                              Page74&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 stage of preparation.    And I think a word comes out&#13;
&#13;
 immediately from my side on the concerns that the social&#13;
&#13;
 structural reviews still pose to us -- again, Jean just&#13;
&#13;
 mentioned, and we had a discussion with Masood before -- I&#13;
&#13;
 still want to come back at the right time because I think&#13;
&#13;
 they are one important piece, and a poverty chapeau is&#13;
&#13;
 needed.   But we cannot eliminate or dilute the importance&#13;
&#13;
 of key blocks that have to be there.        And they were the&#13;
&#13;
 core nature of those studies.&#13;
&#13;
           So, I see the paper as a progress report with&#13;
&#13;
 some important lessons, I think the integration, the&#13;
&#13;
 building blocks that have to come up.          But, in my view,&#13;
&#13;
 it has to remain with a very clear focus.&#13;
&#13;
           The other two papers definitely come as nothing&#13;
&#13;
 new but very important value-added of the World Bank&#13;
&#13;
 agenda.   And I hope it will be beyond the World Bank, and&#13;
&#13;
 I think it will be a tripartite effort, although it raises&#13;
&#13;
 certainly a lot of issues.&#13;
&#13;
           So, we see from this approach a consolidation of&#13;
&#13;
 a lot of aspects, of tools, of instruments.        And we attach&#13;
&#13;
 a lot of important to what now is called -- and I agree&#13;
&#13;
 the title may need to be rethought -- the poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction strategy paper.     And we would view it as the key&#13;
                                                                    Page75&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 long-term framework for Bank intervention, and I hope it&#13;
&#13;
 will be Bank-Fund intervention.&#13;
&#13;
           The fact that it came out in the context of the&#13;
&#13;
 HIPC Initiative does not diminish its importance.       It is&#13;
&#13;
 the opposite; it gives it more meaning, and I think it is&#13;
&#13;
 relevant for the HIPC.    We agree with those that said that&#13;
&#13;
 as much as possible it has to be part of the HIPC process&#13;
&#13;
 of decision, which means that on the decision point we&#13;
&#13;
 want to have as much as we can towards a strategy owned by&#13;
&#13;
 the country, produced on a participatory approach.       But we&#13;
&#13;
 know that reality will not allow us the ideal situation&#13;
&#13;
 when we may have to compromise.       But the compromise cannot&#13;
&#13;
 be by losing the focus on poverty.        And I think that is&#13;
&#13;
 definitely an important aspect that we see at this stage.&#13;
&#13;
           We see the PRSP will become crucial but common&#13;
&#13;
 for all IDA countries.    We would see it as being the real&#13;
&#13;
 base framework, and it is a long-term approach.&#13;
&#13;
 Certainly, it will have to be updated, it will have to be&#13;
&#13;
 improved, but it should be the underpinning document, the&#13;
&#13;
 underpinning process more than document, of the&#13;
&#13;
 relationship between the Bank, the Fund, the country and&#13;
&#13;
 within the country.   So, we see it that it will be the key&#13;
&#13;
 departing point for the CAS.&#13;
                                                                   Page76&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           The CAS may need to be adjusted.         It should&#13;
&#13;
 remain; it should allow us to focus much more on how are&#13;
&#13;
 we going to deliver and assist the country objectives&#13;
&#13;
 spelled out in the strategy, what are the risks, what are&#13;
&#13;
 the tradeoffs, what is our business strategy to deliver,&#13;
&#13;
 what are the costs, what are the outcomes.         And I think&#13;
&#13;
 the accountability will be part of that.&#13;
&#13;
           So, I envisage adjustments in the CAS but not&#13;
&#13;
 change in the importance of the CAS, but I believe the CAS&#13;
&#13;
 would certainly benefit from the introduction from this&#13;
&#13;
 new framework.&#13;
&#13;
           I think one aspect that somehow has been&#13;
&#13;
 referred to but I think that has to be brought out is the&#13;
&#13;
 issue of resources.   So, the public finance framework in&#13;
&#13;
 the medium-term at least -- because I think there it is&#13;
&#13;
 more difficult to go on a long-term -- has to be part of&#13;
&#13;
 the exercise.&#13;
&#13;
           The experience that the Bank had with the public&#13;
&#13;
 expenditure review has been mixed because of different&#13;
&#13;
 things, but I think we have to move beyond the public&#13;
&#13;
 expenditure review with a broad approach including&#13;
&#13;
 resources.   And I think the resources have to be there,&#13;
&#13;
 and I agree with those that make the emphasis that we are&#13;
                                                                  Page77&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 looking to the overall resources, external and domestic&#13;
&#13;
 generated, towards improving the situation.&#13;
&#13;
            So, I think there another area of cooperation&#13;
&#13;
 with the Fund will be necessary in terms of developing&#13;
&#13;
 appropriate medium-term fiscal framework if one can use&#13;
&#13;
 that simple word.&#13;
&#13;
            One aspect that also has been mentioned by Jean&#13;
&#13;
 Pesme lately is in fact the centrality of macro stability&#13;
&#13;
 which comes up as a key aspect of the ESAF program, but it&#13;
&#13;
 is also an aspect for us.       And so, we have to make sure&#13;
&#13;
 that the consistency between the macro objectives and the&#13;
&#13;
 social and poverty strategy emphasis have to be taken into&#13;
&#13;
 account.   And I assume that the ESAF process and approach&#13;
&#13;
 has to suffer some adjustment too, because the consistency&#13;
&#13;
 will have to start from that point.&#13;
&#13;
            I haven't read the IMF paper.             I only looked at&#13;
&#13;
 the issues for discussion, because I only got the paper&#13;
&#13;
 today.   And I agree with the comment made that it is a&#13;
&#13;
 very different way of looking to the issue than what we&#13;
&#13;
 are doing.   It is very tough on the Bank.             I don't know if&#13;
&#13;
 it is totally warranted, but it puts a challenge on us.&#13;
&#13;
 And I agree with the line of action that Jean just&#13;
&#13;
 mentioned.   We should do our best to maintain our&#13;
                                                                          Page78&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 expertise and responsibility on the social policies and&#13;
&#13;
 cooperate with the Fund, adjusting the timetable, if&#13;
&#13;
 possible.    But basically, we cannot deliver, we should not&#13;
&#13;
 engage ourselves.&#13;
&#13;
             But I hope that we will be able to do it.        And I&#13;
&#13;
 think if we take, in fact, the proposal that this new&#13;
&#13;
 framework is, in fact, a tripartite government, Fund and&#13;
&#13;
 Bank, it should be possible to eliminate a lot of&#13;
&#13;
 difficulties that have been mentioned.&#13;
&#13;
             At least, I think there are underlying issues in&#13;
&#13;
 the Fund paper that we may have to come back on among&#13;
&#13;
 ourselves.&#13;
&#13;
             Another aspect that we very much support but are&#13;
&#13;
 cautious about how ambitious we can be on the delivery is&#13;
&#13;
 on the results outcome-based programs.           Definitely we all&#13;
&#13;
 agree with the importance but we all know the&#13;
&#13;
 difficulties.    It should not prevent us to move ahead, but&#13;
&#13;
 I think it makes us conscious of the limitations.&#13;
&#13;
             And I think one particular aspect that we have&#13;
&#13;
 to keep in mind, that it is not only the design, the&#13;
&#13;
 measurement and the monitoring, but it is the time factor&#13;
&#13;
 that really is so important in assessing poverty impact.&#13;
&#13;
 That sometimes is inconsistent with our own cycles.          Of&#13;
                                                                      Page79&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 course, in the case of the HIPC Initiative, there is a&#13;
&#13;
 very, very conflicting message because we want debt relief&#13;
&#13;
 quicker, but we want it in a very strong linkage with&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction.&#13;
&#13;
           I think that we are going to deal with this&#13;
&#13;
 aspect in the near future, particularly when we start&#13;
&#13;
 implementing the enhanced initiative.         But it is a reality&#13;
&#13;
 and it is going to raise the issues of fairness and&#13;
&#13;
 consistency across countries that certainly should be on&#13;
&#13;
 our minds.&#13;
&#13;
           Many people have spoken and I fully agree with&#13;
&#13;
 the ownership by countries and the participatory process.&#13;
&#13;
 But it is very difficult.     And I think it is not only&#13;
&#13;
 difficult because of the capacity, but it is difficult&#13;
&#13;
 because of motivation.    And I think Neil and Jean have&#13;
&#13;
 referred to precisely the political commitment that is&#13;
&#13;
 necessary, and it goes beyond the technical limitation.&#13;
&#13;
           And I think we should avoid to fall in the trap&#13;
&#13;
 that in my mind the PFP is an example, that really does&#13;
&#13;
 not help in building ownership and commitment from&#13;
&#13;
 authorities.&#13;
&#13;
           But after saying all of this, I would like&#13;
&#13;
 basically to ask management with the strong support that&#13;
                                                                     Page80&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 has been given in this Board on the enhanced framework and&#13;
&#13;
 the several elements, I think definitely we have to move&#13;
&#13;
 towards a strategy or master plan, as I think Jean&#13;
&#13;
 mentioned, how to operationalize it.        And definitely at&#13;
&#13;
 least three levels will be very crucial.&#13;
&#13;
            One is the cooperation and collaboration with&#13;
&#13;
 the IMF.   And there again, I think we will hear about the&#13;
&#13;
 how the IMF Board addressed the questions that are on the&#13;
&#13;
 table.   I don't know even if this Board fully agrees with&#13;
&#13;
 all the questions and analysis, but definitely we have to&#13;
&#13;
 be very firm about how we are going to address this issue.&#13;
&#13;
            We know that what is being proposed -- and I&#13;
&#13;
 think this morning it was clearly emphasized by both Mike&#13;
&#13;
 and Peter, I guess -- this approach is a dramatic shift in&#13;
&#13;
 the way we work, inside the Bank but the way we work with&#13;
&#13;
 other partners.   And I think the Fund here is critical.&#13;
&#13;
            I think flexibility can exist in exercising the&#13;
&#13;
 complementarity between the two institutions, but I think&#13;
&#13;
 we have to have a very clear line where the management and&#13;
&#13;
 the Board see this process to go forward in order to&#13;
&#13;
 position us as an equal -- in this case maybe more than&#13;
&#13;
 equal, because the Bank has the expertise and has the&#13;
                                                                 Page81&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 experience, and I hope that we will be able to have the&#13;
&#13;
 necessary skills on time to deliver this.&#13;
&#13;
           The second level for personalizing all this plan&#13;
&#13;
 is, in fact, the internal apparatus of the Bank that has&#13;
&#13;
 to be adjusted.   I mean, the word "consolidation" comes to&#13;
&#13;
 mind immediately, but before consolidation I think we&#13;
&#13;
 really have to look at the wide array of instruments that&#13;
&#13;
 we are using.   The ESW is the best umbrella but it doesn't&#13;
&#13;
 tell us anything.    When we go down and disintegrate the&#13;
&#13;
 ESW, we have a multiplicity and also in terms of what that&#13;
&#13;
 means in our relationship with the country.          I will come&#13;
&#13;
 to that issue under the umbrella of the countries.&#13;
&#13;
           But the references that have been made on the&#13;
&#13;
 country teams, networks and skills are very important, but&#13;
&#13;
 I think they have to go beyond that in terms of the&#13;
&#13;
 strategic documents, strategic papers.           For us, I believe&#13;
&#13;
 the Board still attaches the maximum importance to the&#13;
&#13;
 CAS, but recognizes that there are underpinnings of the&#13;
&#13;
 CAS that have to remain.&#13;
&#13;
           So, consolidation, yes, eventually elimination&#13;
&#13;
 of separate pieces but not undermining what we are&#13;
&#13;
 accomplishing by enlarging and broadening our approach.&#13;
                                                                      Page82&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           And the third level for the road map is, in&#13;
&#13;
 fact, in countries and our relationship with countries.&#13;
&#13;
 And I think again we have to go beyond the words of&#13;
&#13;
 partnership, ownership, political commitment, but in&#13;
&#13;
 reality how we are going to assist the countries in taking&#13;
&#13;
 the lead of that potential.&#13;
&#13;
           I fully agree with the dimension that Neil Hyden&#13;
&#13;
 gave to the governance issue.      And I think that is very,&#13;
&#13;
 very important, precisely in our relationship with the&#13;
&#13;
 countries.   I think he is absolutely right that it is part&#13;
&#13;
 of empowerment but it is higher than empowerment, and I&#13;
&#13;
 think we have to bring it across the higher level.&#13;
&#13;
           One final comment on the retroactive application&#13;
&#13;
 of the new framework for the HIPC countries.         I think we&#13;
&#13;
 have to be cautious about bringing additional requirements&#13;
&#13;
 at this stage without ignoring the emphasis on poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction.   But I think timing, fairness has to be part of&#13;
&#13;
 the way we look on specifics.&#13;
&#13;
           I think the issue is simplified.         If we look at&#13;
&#13;
 the poverty reduction strategies as permanent frameworks&#13;
&#13;
 for action, it will be possible, as we move along, to&#13;
&#13;
 refine its elaboration on each country and IDA will remain&#13;
&#13;
 the key player in these countries.        Unfortunately, we are&#13;
                                                                    Page83&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 not in a position of imagining that it will be out of the&#13;
&#13;
 playing field.   So, we have an opportunity to bring back&#13;
&#13;
 all these countries in a more, I would say, deeper and&#13;
&#13;
 broader approach that now may be possible in other&#13;
&#13;
 countries.&#13;
&#13;
           So, we are really pleased with what we are&#13;
&#13;
 seeing.   We are cautious about how we go about&#13;
&#13;
 implementation, and we encourage management to move ahead&#13;
&#13;
 and start spelling out precisely in these two or three&#13;
&#13;
 dimensions how we will move ahead.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:     Thank you, Helena.&#13;
&#13;
           Hein Bogaard, please.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. BOGAARD:    Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           I am in a bit of trouble at this time, because I&#13;
&#13;
 would like to be short; I don't like to repeat people and&#13;
&#13;
 I also want to give a comprehensive view on these very&#13;
&#13;
 good papers.   So, I have to find some balance here.&#13;
&#13;
           I think it is clear that paragraph 15 of the&#13;
&#13;
 paper on poverty strategy more or less defines the basic&#13;
&#13;
 outlines of the approach -- good analysis, prioritization&#13;
&#13;
 of policies and participation.       We are very much in&#13;
&#13;
 support of that.&#13;
                                                              Page84&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           In the past year, we have focused on pro-poor&#13;
&#13;
 growth, moving beyond a single focus on social protection&#13;
&#13;
 and increasing social expenditure.         And in this document,&#13;
&#13;
 staff rightly stresses the importance of taking a broad&#13;
&#13;
 view on poverty, including empowerment and in general&#13;
&#13;
 reducing barriers throughout the economic and social&#13;
&#13;
 system to poverty reduction.&#13;
&#13;
           I think in view also of disturbing trends in&#13;
&#13;
 poverty, our CAS documents and everything basically we do&#13;
&#13;
 should focus on the issue of poverty.&#13;
&#13;
           We also appreciate the attention paid to gender&#13;
&#13;
 in the document.   It is both morally right I think to take&#13;
&#13;
 this into account and economically sound.           It also comes&#13;
&#13;
 out of recent research on the link between poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction and gender in the Africa Region.&#13;
&#13;
           In practical terms, the suggested approach&#13;
&#13;
 implies that we need to take a holistic view I think on&#13;
&#13;
 both the inputs to debt relief, tax revenues, also human&#13;
&#13;
 capital as an input and, at the same time, a holistic view&#13;
&#13;
 on policy outputs and outcomes more specifically.&#13;
&#13;
           In this regard, if we look at public policies,&#13;
&#13;
 countries should try and develop a medium-term expenditure&#13;
&#13;
 framework, and they would also greatly benefit if they&#13;
                                                                     Page85&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 could complement such a framework with medium-term&#13;
&#13;
 commitments from donors, not only in the CAS of the World&#13;
&#13;
 Bank or in a three-year ESAF program but also from other&#13;
&#13;
 donors.&#13;
&#13;
           In relation to the medium-term framework, I&#13;
&#13;
 would also like to draw attention to the work that is&#13;
&#13;
 ongoing on the Special Program for Africa, where they try&#13;
&#13;
 to work from a balance of payments approach to a budgetary&#13;
&#13;
 gap approach, which facilitates the connection between aid&#13;
&#13;
 and policies and between inputs and results.       This might&#13;
&#13;
 also be a way to refocus our discussions with the IMF on a&#13;
&#13;
 macroeconomic framework.&#13;
&#13;
           It is obvious -- almost everybody has said this&#13;
&#13;
 so far -- that the biggest challenge, if we agree on the&#13;
&#13;
 framework, is implementation and in order to make the&#13;
&#13;
 approach work, we need to foster partnerships outside the&#13;
&#13;
 Bank, and this goes broader I think than only the IMF and&#13;
&#13;
 the country.   We have been talking about a tripartite&#13;
&#13;
 effort.   I think it should be even broader, including&#13;
&#13;
 other donors, other regional development banks.&#13;
&#13;
           I think the poverty reduction strategy papers&#13;
&#13;
 could be a very useful element of these partnerships.      And&#13;
&#13;
 we hope to begin with, they are more than a joint effort&#13;
                                                                  Page86&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 than the almost Fund-only policy framework papers that we&#13;
&#13;
 currently have.   So, we fully support the replacement of&#13;
&#13;
 the PFPs with the PRSPs, as proposed.&#13;
&#13;
           What I also felt compelling about the proposal&#13;
&#13;
 was the idea to make the PRSP process an iterative process&#13;
&#13;
 during which all policy targets, including the IMF targets&#13;
&#13;
 are up for discussion, in which all structural,&#13;
&#13;
 macroeconomic policies are being related to poverty.&#13;
&#13;
           In this respect, if one compares the Bank paper,&#13;
&#13;
 which is very comprehensive in its approach to poverty,&#13;
&#13;
 with the IMF paper, I found it a bit disappointing that&#13;
&#13;
 the Fund presents the PRSP in a paper with a title which&#13;
&#13;
 refers to social policies only and not to the broader set&#13;
&#13;
 of poverty reduction policies.&#13;
&#13;
           We also need to foster partnerships inside the&#13;
&#13;
 Bank, especially within the matrix management.       I think&#13;
&#13;
 that the responsibilities of networks need to be&#13;
&#13;
 clarified, and they should be allocated resources to match&#13;
&#13;
 their roles and possibly regions should try to communicate&#13;
&#13;
 with each other more to learn from each other.&#13;
&#13;
           Finally, one small point on instruments:       I&#13;
&#13;
 think that we should not presume that countries with PRSP&#13;
&#13;
 receive more program-based support.        I can imagine a&#13;
                                                                Page87&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 situation in which a country has a PRSP and still not has&#13;
&#13;
 the implementation capacity to work with program-based&#13;
&#13;
 instruments.&#13;
&#13;
           Quickly, on the relation to HIPC, I think for&#13;
&#13;
 countries that have qualified for debt relief already and&#13;
&#13;
 are expected to qualify for debt relief in the short-term,&#13;
&#13;
 we should take a somewhat flexible approach.          But&#13;
&#13;
 hopefully, they could have as much of a poverty strategy&#13;
&#13;
 in place as possible by the time they reach their decision&#13;
&#13;
 point and certainly when they reach the completion point.&#13;
&#13;
           This requirement should also be applied flexibly&#13;
&#13;
 to retroactive countries, but good policies to reduce&#13;
&#13;
 poverty I think should be a requirement to qualify for&#13;
&#13;
 additional debt relief.&#13;
&#13;
           With regard to the structural policy reviews, we&#13;
&#13;
 several times stressed the need for better selectivity&#13;
&#13;
 management, a systemization of economic and sector work,&#13;
&#13;
 and I think John Sinclair made it clear that also we not&#13;
&#13;
 only have the acronym ESW, but we also have a huge number&#13;
&#13;
 of acronyms which fall under the umbrella of ESW, and we&#13;
&#13;
 hope that some streamlining can be done.&#13;
&#13;
           Those are all my points.       Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you very much, Hein.&#13;
                                                              Page88&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
             Mr. Pandian, please.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. PANDIAN:   Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
             Like others, we also welcome the papers, which&#13;
&#13;
 really put their heart and soul on poverty reduction,&#13;
&#13;
 which is the main mandate of this Bank.&#13;
&#13;
             To begin with regarding paper one, "HIPC:&#13;
&#13;
 Strengthening the Link Between Debt Relief and Poverty&#13;
&#13;
 Reduction", we welcome the suggestion that all resources&#13;
&#13;
 should be put in position to fight poverty, not only debt&#13;
&#13;
 relief but also domestic resources.&#13;
&#13;
             But our question is whether there will be enough&#13;
&#13;
 domestic resources available to achieve a desired result.&#13;
&#13;
 So, we may go beyond that and to generate additional&#13;
&#13;
 resources, the government may have to invest in new&#13;
&#13;
 infrastructure.    How are we going to balance this&#13;
&#13;
 question?&#13;
&#13;
             Number two, we also welcome to build on the&#13;
&#13;
 existing framework to build a new strategy.         But at the&#13;
&#13;
 same time, we have certain reservations about involving&#13;
&#13;
 the civil society in the formulation, selection and&#13;
&#13;
 monitoring of output indicators.        It is a problem in&#13;
&#13;
 selecting civil society when the country and government is&#13;
&#13;
 infested with a number of civil society organizations.&#13;
                                                                  Page89&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 How are we going to discriminate between a good civil&#13;
&#13;
 society group and a bad civil society group?        Everybody&#13;
&#13;
 has a vested interest.&#13;
&#13;
           In this connection, again ownership should be&#13;
&#13;
 given to the country.    If the government is comfortable&#13;
&#13;
 with the civil group, it can go ahead.         If it is not&#13;
&#13;
 comfortable, then the democratically-elected process&#13;
&#13;
 should not be undermined, because a number of countries do&#13;
&#13;
 have local authorities, local elected governments and we&#13;
&#13;
 should make use of those institutions.         In fact, if they&#13;
&#13;
 do not have the capacity to plan, to monitor, that&#13;
&#13;
 capacity should be built, and the World Bank Institute in&#13;
&#13;
 association with other local and regional organizations&#13;
&#13;
 can arrange a number of programs to build the capacity at&#13;
&#13;
 the grassroots level.&#13;
&#13;
           We also welcome the poverty reduction strategy&#13;
&#13;
 paper.   In fact, we very much appreciate the participatory&#13;
&#13;
 approach being adopted in preparing this.&#13;
&#13;
           But one thing we would like to point out that in&#13;
&#13;
 a number of countries, at least particularly in the&#13;
&#13;
 constituencies we represent, there are planning&#13;
&#13;
 ministries, democratically-elected representatives, that&#13;
&#13;
 do prepare the local plan, regional plan and the country&#13;
                                                                   Page90&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 plan.   I think that these things also cannot be&#13;
&#13;
 undermined.    They should be given proper importance and&#13;
&#13;
 proper role.&#13;
&#13;
           What is needed is how civil society can be&#13;
&#13;
 involved in these processes.       Perhaps in collaboration&#13;
&#13;
 with the poor people, in collaboration with the local&#13;
&#13;
 people, they should see whether these projects are&#13;
&#13;
 properly implemented at the implementation stage.      As my&#13;
&#13;
 colleagues pointed out, the question of governance, the&#13;
&#13;
 question of commitment, the question of delivery comes&#13;
&#13;
 into the picture; it is here the civil society can&#13;
&#13;
 associate to see that the desired results are achieved and&#13;
&#13;
 it is being distributed.&#13;
&#13;
           As far as questions number four and five are&#13;
&#13;
 concerned, already the HIPC activity is delayed very much.&#13;
&#13;
 So, we would like to agree with the staff that instead of&#13;
&#13;
 waiting for the completion point we can go ahead with the&#13;
&#13;
 relief; probably the government is committed for a poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction strategy.&#13;
&#13;
           Now coming to the second paper, Mr. Chairman,&#13;
&#13;
 the poverty reduction strategy, we also welcome the&#13;
&#13;
 outcome-based approach.     Definitely, this will give a&#13;
                                                                Page91&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 clear-cut improvement in the CAS process.          We welcome&#13;
&#13;
 that.&#13;
&#13;
            But again, this cannot be a straitjacket&#13;
&#13;
 approach; it varies from country to country, because, as&#13;
&#13;
 the paper itself has pointed out, the countries which have&#13;
&#13;
 massive poverty like India and Bangladesh, we had growth.&#13;
&#13;
 We concentrated on growth in the 1990s, in the early 1990s&#13;
&#13;
 but still poverty was stagnant.       We concentrated on the&#13;
&#13;
 income redistribution in the late 1970s and 1980s but the&#13;
&#13;
 growth was stagnant.   What we need is both.        We need&#13;
&#13;
 growth as well as fairly distributed income.&#13;
&#13;
            If you take India, Pakistan, Bangladesh, nearly&#13;
&#13;
 40 percent of the people are living below the poverty&#13;
&#13;
 line.   And these countries face a different unique&#13;
&#13;
 problem.   In fact, rather than concentrating on growth or&#13;
&#13;
 huge investment in infrastructure, if you spend a small&#13;
&#13;
 amount in improving our tax collection system, that will&#13;
&#13;
 create more wealth, and the distribution definitely should&#13;
&#13;
 be given importance.&#13;
&#13;
            So, the strategy may vary from country to&#13;
&#13;
 country, particularly if you want to bring down the&#13;
&#13;
 poverty in a massive level and these countries where the&#13;
&#13;
 poverty is massive should be given due importance.         We&#13;
                                                                 Page92&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 feel that this paper seems to be a little more Africa-&#13;
&#13;
 based.   No doubt, a number of poor countries are in the&#13;
&#13;
 Africa Region, but, at the same time, there are few&#13;
&#13;
 countries in other regions where a number of people are&#13;
&#13;
 poor.&#13;
&#13;
            Again, we find it a little discouraging to note&#13;
&#13;
 that there is no mention of technology, taking technology&#13;
&#13;
 to fight poverty.    Like the Industrial Revolution, today&#13;
&#13;
 is the Technological Revolution, and to what extent we can&#13;
&#13;
 use the technology to fight poverty.          It may be disease or&#13;
&#13;
 it may be quality education or it may be building economic&#13;
&#13;
 assets which can be easily accessible by the poor people.&#13;
&#13;
 So, I think the Bank should do some research how&#13;
&#13;
 effectively technology can be used to fight poverty and to&#13;
&#13;
 do global common good.&#13;
&#13;
            Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
            MR. SANDSTROM:     Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
            Mr. Binkert, please.&#13;
&#13;
            MR. BINKERT:    Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
            Like all the other speakers, I would also like&#13;
&#13;
 to commend staff, and I guess I have decided that I will&#13;
&#13;
 not do justice with those papers but try to be brief&#13;
&#13;
 instead.&#13;
                                                                      Page93&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
             I have a few points and the main message from&#13;
&#13;
 all the following points is that on a conceptual level, we&#13;
&#13;
 like very much the proposals for the enhanced framework,&#13;
&#13;
 but we are very concerned that this may contradict the&#13;
&#13;
 objective of speedy debt relief, that we are just&#13;
&#13;
 overloading the initiative.      But I will go in step-by-&#13;
&#13;
 step.&#13;
&#13;
             First, we fully agree that actually the overall&#13;
&#13;
 framework is important for poverty reduction, not just for&#13;
&#13;
 HIPC.    So, whatever criteria we use for quick-disbursing&#13;
&#13;
 funds, it will be the same ones for HIPC.           It is the same&#13;
&#13;
 thing.   And, therefore, all the necessary measures, in&#13;
&#13;
 particular on improving the quality of budget management&#13;
&#13;
 and accounting, all of those things have to be applied to&#13;
&#13;
 HIPC as well, and that will take time.          We will not be&#13;
&#13;
 able to do that in twelve to eighteen months.&#13;
&#13;
             The second point, of course, conceptually we&#13;
&#13;
 like very much the move towards outcome-oriented&#13;
&#13;
 objectives and impact indicators.        Our experience from the&#13;
&#13;
 field is very clear that this is the key thing that we&#13;
&#13;
 ought to be monitoring rather than traditional policy&#13;
&#13;
 measures.    At the same time, we have learned very much in&#13;
&#13;
 the SPA, the Special Program for Africa exercise, of how&#13;
                                                                      Page94&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 complicated it is to define, measure and monitor such&#13;
&#13;
 outcome indicators.&#13;
&#13;
           So, we think this is going to be a very big&#13;
&#13;
 challenge, even though conceptually it is the right thing.&#13;
&#13;
           Similarly, with the poverty reduction strategy&#13;
&#13;
 paper, again this sounds like an excellent exercise.      It&#13;
&#13;
 is very consistent with our objective, with what we would&#13;
&#13;
 like to achieve, but it may be a very complex exercise to&#13;
&#13;
 do, particularly if we want to have a highly participatory&#13;
&#13;
 process to develop -- as John said, it cannot be reduced.&#13;
&#13;
 So we always have to say poverty reduction strategy paper.&#13;
&#13;
 It doesn't go by the acronym.&#13;
&#13;
           It is going to be very complicated.      We are not&#13;
&#13;
 quite sure when we will be ready to use this framework&#13;
&#13;
 paper or strategy paper and substitute that for the PFP.&#13;
&#13;
 And also, we are not quite clear whether it makes sense to&#13;
&#13;
 require countries to do this every three years in a fully&#13;
&#13;
 participatory way.    This may be asking too much; it may&#13;
&#13;
 not be the proper thing to do.      And this, of course, is a&#13;
&#13;
 comment that goes beyond HIPC.&#13;
&#13;
           Similarly, some of the innovations in the new&#13;
&#13;
 framework are the floating completion points and the&#13;
&#13;
 frontloading.   And we attach great importance to this.     We&#13;
                                                                  Page95&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 are strong supporters of those two features and,&#13;
&#13;
 therefore, urge really that we be very careful in how much&#13;
&#13;
 we load the enhanced framework with conditions that may&#13;
&#13;
 slow us down.&#13;
&#13;
           The last point is with regard to the countries&#13;
&#13;
 that have already reached the decision point under the&#13;
&#13;
 current framework or the completion point even.           It is&#13;
&#13;
 very important that they be treated equally and that we&#13;
&#13;
 don't really introduce sort of a third stage to the HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 implicitly with retroactive conditions.            So, we really&#13;
&#13;
 have to strike a balance here.&#13;
&#13;
           As I said, to sum up, the main concern is that&#13;
&#13;
 we continue with a speedy program, a speedy HIPC program.&#13;
&#13;
 We fully agree with the overall framework to enhance&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction as the key objective, but this should be&#13;
&#13;
 the objective for all of our activities.           And we have to&#13;
&#13;
 find a balance.&#13;
&#13;
           I would just like to make one last comment on&#13;
&#13;
 the other paper, on the paper for the building poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction strategies.    On the outcome table on page 9, it&#13;
&#13;
 mentions here that private consumption, poverty incidence&#13;
&#13;
 and inequality should be sort of key indicators for&#13;
&#13;
 economic opportunities.    If one could not include also an&#13;
                                                                     Page96&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 indicator for employment conditions, this would be a proxy&#13;
&#13;
 for many other things that go on in the poverty field or&#13;
&#13;
 in the vulnerability of people.         Maybe by including&#13;
&#13;
 employment indicators, that might be a very useful thing&#13;
&#13;
 to monitor as well, of course, in the various instruments&#13;
&#13;
 that the Bank has, such as CASs or whatever reviews we&#13;
&#13;
 get.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:      Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
           Mr. Garcia, please.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. GARCIA:     Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
           I would also like to commend Mr. John Page, Mr.&#13;
&#13;
 Walton and their team for an excellent paper.            I am&#13;
&#13;
 talking about "Building Poverty Reduction Strategies in&#13;
&#13;
 Developing Countries".&#13;
&#13;
           I have a couple of suggestions.            I think the&#13;
&#13;
 paper will gain or it may be worthwhile looking at&#13;
&#13;
 different strategies to fight absolute poverty and&#13;
&#13;
 relative poverty.    I think they bring up two complete sets&#13;
&#13;
 of issues, and the strategy may well be totally different.&#13;
&#13;
           Economic growth probably will reduce absolute&#13;
&#13;
 poverty and will increase relative poverty.            Now, to fight&#13;
&#13;
 relative poverty is very, very difficult because it is in&#13;
                                                                        Page97&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 the nature of our policies that we carry to our countries&#13;
&#13;
 deregulation, competitive policy, change.           And things&#13;
&#13;
 change today in one year more than they used to change&#13;
&#13;
 before in 50 years.    So, it is in the nature of the&#13;
&#13;
 business that people are going to get more poor on&#13;
&#13;
 relative terms.    Even though their income may have&#13;
&#13;
 doubled, if the income of the whole society has tripled,&#13;
&#13;
 they are poorer.    So, that is an issue I would suggest to&#13;
&#13;
 look at because I think it is very important.&#13;
&#13;
             Also, there is an issue of picking up&#13;
&#13;
 priorities.    And the difficulty of this issue is clearly&#13;
&#13;
 in Table 1 on page 9, because there is a large inventory&#13;
&#13;
 of issues, but we have to be always aware that there is a&#13;
&#13;
 tradeoff.    And when we tell a country or a country decides&#13;
&#13;
 that it is going to invest more on microfinance, it really&#13;
&#13;
 invests less in education, it is investing less in health.&#13;
&#13;
 So, the whole budgetary process is crucial.&#13;
&#13;
             In that sense, I am very skeptical about this&#13;
&#13;
 participatory process, of empowering people in order to&#13;
&#13;
 reach a list of items, because the thing gets very&#13;
&#13;
 political instead of getting more technical, with the&#13;
&#13;
 economic rate of return and with good data to help the&#13;
&#13;
 budgetary process in the countries.         So, my position would&#13;
                                                                     Page98&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 be that we should not look so much at all of this&#13;
&#13;
 participatory process but we should look a little bit more&#13;
&#13;
 on the internal rate of return, on how the budgetary&#13;
&#13;
 process plays in these countries.&#13;
&#13;
           Just to finish, let me say that I think that in&#13;
&#13;
 these priorities trade and education are real crucial.      If&#13;
&#13;
 we look, for example, at Africa, the participation of&#13;
&#13;
 total world exports in Africa 1980 it was 6 percent, and&#13;
&#13;
 today it is less than 2 percent.       So, that is a question:&#13;
&#13;
 Why is that?   And I think that is an important question to&#13;
&#13;
 which we should try to give some answers.&#13;
&#13;
           The other issue is I think we should be more of&#13;
&#13;
 an education bank, because education is the only tool that&#13;
&#13;
 we have that, at the same time, growth is improved, it&#13;
&#13;
 diminishes relative poverty; it gives more equity, more&#13;
&#13;
 opportunity, and I think we should focus more on that.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
           A two-handed.    Jan.&#13;
&#13;
           MS. PIERCY:   I was just going to ask when you&#13;
&#13;
 anticipated having staff come back, because I have heard a&#13;
&#13;
 number of questions that, rather than repeat them, we&#13;
&#13;
 might at some point want to have an intervening comment&#13;
                                                                  Page99&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 round which might shorten the comments of some of us who&#13;
&#13;
 have not yet spoken.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    We had planned to listen.   We&#13;
&#13;
 have only two speakers left, at least right now on the&#13;
&#13;
 list, Ms. Zou and yourself.     I didn't want to lose too&#13;
&#13;
 many of you before you had heard each other and then have&#13;
&#13;
 staff to come back with a very full response.&#13;
&#13;
           Ms. Zou, please.&#13;
&#13;
           MS. ZOU:   Thank you, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
           I think it is difficult to be a late speaker,&#13;
&#13;
 but I will still try to be brief and to minimize the&#13;
&#13;
 repetitions.&#13;
&#13;
           We too would like to commend the staff for&#13;
&#13;
 preparing these three interrelated papers, and each&#13;
&#13;
 contains very useful thinking.      Let me start with the&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction strategies.      Basically, we appreciate&#13;
&#13;
 the outcome-based approach.     We find it is appropriate for&#13;
&#13;
 this approach to serve as a policy base for the enhanced&#13;
&#13;
 HIPC framework.&#13;
&#13;
           However, we feel that this framework needs to be&#13;
&#13;
 further refined before it could be widely adapted to all&#13;
&#13;
 the borrowers.&#13;
                                                                 Page100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           Regarding the overall approach, we find that&#13;
&#13;
 Table 1 is very interesting.      All the elements listed in&#13;
&#13;
 Table 1 are relevant to poverty reduction.         However, if&#13;
&#13;
 these elements need to be operationalized by the Bank, I&#13;
&#13;
 would again call for the selectivity, because if we look&#13;
&#13;
 at Table 1, there are four categories listed here.&#13;
&#13;
           My feeling is that probably the first two&#13;
&#13;
 categories gear mostly to the Bank's comparative advantage&#13;
&#13;
 and capacity, while the last two categories, some of the&#13;
&#13;
 items listed in the last two categories are obviously&#13;
&#13;
 beyond the Bank's mandate and internal capacity.        For&#13;
&#13;
 example, actions to reduce violence, the community&#13;
&#13;
 policing and something like this, obviously it must be&#13;
&#13;
 done by the government instead of the Bank.        So, I think&#13;
&#13;
 the Bank has to be selective in those areas.&#13;
&#13;
           Regarding the issue of governance, I fully agree&#13;
&#13;
 on the points made by Mr. Hyden that governance should be&#13;
&#13;
 more related to the way the government manages the&#13;
&#13;
 economy, instead of to link solely to the gray area of&#13;
&#13;
 empowerment, where we are not sure whether the Bank can&#13;
&#13;
 really make a difference.&#13;
&#13;
           Regarding the participation, we are in favor of&#13;
                                                                  Page101&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 the idea that the Bank should work directly with the poor&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 and to reflect the interest of those final stakeholders.&#13;
&#13;
 Probably we feel that this might be a more effective way&#13;
&#13;
 of participation than going through NGOs as an&#13;
&#13;
 intermediary.&#13;
&#13;
           NGOs, however, could be helpful if the&#13;
&#13;
 participation of NGOs could be managed in a pragmatic way&#13;
&#13;
 and avoid potential political conflicts.             I would echo&#13;
&#13;
 those points made by Mr. Garcia in this regard.&#13;
&#13;
           And we also feel that the Bank needs to develop&#13;
&#13;
 certain guidelines and criteria for the NGO participation&#13;
&#13;
 so as to ensure accountability.         The Bank should choose&#13;
&#13;
 those NGOs with a good track record to work on the&#13;
&#13;
 development business as its partners.&#13;
&#13;
           Regarding the monitoring indicators, we feel&#13;
&#13;
 that indicators should be technically mature and avoid&#13;
&#13;
 using subjective judgment, particularly when involving the&#13;
&#13;
 qualitative indicators in social-related aspects.&#13;
&#13;
           Regarding the analytical tools on poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction, we feel that those tools need to be simple and&#13;
&#13;
 straight-forward.    My feeling is that the poverty notes&#13;
&#13;
 probably could be one section of the CAS, when necessary,&#13;
&#13;
 instead of being a new and independent tool.&#13;
                                                                     Page102&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           Now let me turn to the paper of HIPC.      We feel&#13;
&#13;
 that poverty reduction is the ultimate goal of the HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 Initiative.   Therefore, we support to strengthen the&#13;
&#13;
 linkage between debt relief and poverty reduction.      We&#13;
&#13;
 have three brief observations here.&#13;
&#13;
           We feel that strengthening the linkage to&#13;
&#13;
 poverty should not delay the debt relief process.      Our&#13;
&#13;
 desire is that the qualified HIPC countries should get as&#13;
&#13;
 soon as possible all the potential benefits from the HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 Initiative.   In this regard, we have no problem with the&#13;
&#13;
 transitional approach that the decision-making point could&#13;
&#13;
 take place even before the completion of the poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction strategy.&#13;
&#13;
           Number two, we believe that poverty reduction&#13;
&#13;
 cannot be delinked with financial resources.       Therefore,&#13;
&#13;
 we feel that we need to have a detailed country-specific&#13;
&#13;
 calculation on how much financial resources are actually&#13;
&#13;
 released by the enhanced framework on a cash flow basis.&#13;
&#13;
 And the performance target for the poverty alleviation&#13;
&#13;
 should be commensurate with the cash flow impact and&#13;
&#13;
 should not be over-ambitious.&#13;
&#13;
           In this regard, we also are worried a little bit&#13;
                                                                 Page103&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 about the possible imbalanced way of processing this&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 enhanced framework, because we find that, on the one hand,&#13;
&#13;
 there are proactive, dynamic discussions on the poverty&#13;
&#13;
 linkage to this HIPC enhanced framework.           However, on the&#13;
&#13;
 other hand, the financial resources are still pending in&#13;
&#13;
 the air.   So, we would like to caution our colleagues on&#13;
&#13;
 this potential three-fold approach will definitely not&#13;
&#13;
 work.&#13;
&#13;
            Certainly, on the tripartite poverty strategy&#13;
&#13;
 paper, PRSP, we find this is a useful tool for HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 countries.   However, we are not yet convinced whether this&#13;
&#13;
 should be introduced to as wide a range of countries as&#13;
&#13;
 possible, because, like many other speakers mentioned,&#13;
&#13;
 this again evolved into a division of labor issue of the&#13;
&#13;
 Bank's and Fund's respective role in poverty reduction.&#13;
&#13;
 We need to avoid the risk of further blurring the division&#13;
&#13;
 of labor between the two institutions.&#13;
&#13;
            Finally, let me come to the paper of "Social and&#13;
&#13;
 Structural Reviews".   We appreciate the progress made and&#13;
&#13;
 the lessons learned over the one year's pilot for six&#13;
&#13;
 countries.   However, we are skeptical on the expansionary&#13;
&#13;
 way suggested in this paper.      We still remember that one&#13;
&#13;
 year ago, when we discussed to introduce the new tool of&#13;
                                                                      Page104&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 SPR, at the time there were a lot of concerns and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 hesitation from many chairs due to the complexity of the&#13;
&#13;
 issues the SPR is going to address.&#13;
&#13;
           And now, we have already expanded into the&#13;
&#13;
 social policy areas.     Although we have already had one&#13;
&#13;
 year's experience for the pilot, I believe we are still at&#13;
&#13;
 the beginning of the learning curve.        So, as the paper&#13;
&#13;
 also mentions, if we are going to expand into an effective&#13;
&#13;
 and useful one, we need more building blocks and&#13;
&#13;
 intellectual support from the ESW in different sector&#13;
&#13;
 issues.&#13;
&#13;
           However, obviously, we find the quality of the&#13;
&#13;
 ESW itself is still in question today.         So, given the&#13;
&#13;
 limited internal capacity of the Bank, as well as the&#13;
&#13;
 complexity and demanding nature of these structural and&#13;
&#13;
 social policy issues, we would be in favor of the idea&#13;
&#13;
 that the SSR will continue the pilot and still concentrate&#13;
&#13;
 on the structural issues and the social policies, when&#13;
&#13;
 necessary, and we make it better focused and do it better.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
           And now Jan.&#13;
&#13;
           MS. PIERCY:    Thank you.&#13;
                                                                Page105&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           I will try at this stage to be down right&#13;
&#13;
 elliptical and simply signal support because I think all&#13;
&#13;
 of the issues have been well elaborated.           I have great&#13;
&#13;
 sympathy at this stage with the team and look forward to&#13;
&#13;
 answers to some of the questions.       But I think some of the&#13;
&#13;
 questions we have posed are real conundrums; they are not&#13;
&#13;
 ones you are going to be able to settle today but simply&#13;
&#13;
 kind of take into account in weighing as we go forward.&#13;
&#13;
           Let me start by simply saying that we can&#13;
&#13;
 support the broad thrust of the papers all taken together,&#13;
&#13;
 and especially single out a few areas for underscoring --&#13;
&#13;
 one, the emphasis on the comprehensive PRSP as a common&#13;
&#13;
 framework for Bank-Fund programs replacing the PFP.&#13;
&#13;
           I also agree with statements others have made on&#13;
&#13;
 the need for an emphasis on gender, particular focus on&#13;
&#13;
 gender in poverty analyses and strategies.          I think our&#13;
&#13;
 work over the years has documented very dramatically the&#13;
&#13;
 impact of our failure to understand gender differentiated&#13;
&#13;
 impacts, and we have a long way to go in that area, but we&#13;
&#13;
 must really integrate it in very carefully.&#13;
&#13;
           Also, the emphasis on outcomes is quite&#13;
&#13;
 important to us, on monitoring, on performance linkages,&#13;
                                                                   Page106&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 including governance and anti-corruption in triggers, and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 better and more participatory analysis of the incidence&#13;
&#13;
 and causes of poverty, although I certainly take the point&#13;
&#13;
 about how difficult it is to design effective&#13;
&#13;
 participatory approaches.      I think those complications&#13;
&#13;
 have been well elaborated in the interventions around this&#13;
&#13;
 table today.    Also, transparency and accountability are&#13;
&#13;
 likewise very critical.&#13;
&#13;
           I would make just four particular points on&#13;
&#13;
 these papers.   First, the need for Bank-Fund cooperation:&#13;
&#13;
 I think our lengthy discussion in the Steering Committee&#13;
&#13;
 yesterday of how trying to set up a single meeting to talk&#13;
&#13;
 about the HIPC framework because of the overlap in the&#13;
&#13;
 Bank and the Fund and getting it right, should be evidence&#13;
&#13;
 to us that this is easy to call for but will require of us&#13;
&#13;
 a great deal of work going forward.         And indeed, the&#13;
&#13;
 Fund's paper -- I didn't entirely appreciate the reference&#13;
&#13;
 to the Bank speed -- I think that may reflect perhaps a&#13;
&#13;
 bit of a lack of understanding of how complex it is when&#13;
&#13;
 you move into the social parameter design.          So, I just&#13;
&#13;
 underscore that and the need for cooperation.&#13;
&#13;
           I think the recently started joint committee is&#13;
&#13;
 helpful to at least begin to create greater symmetry in&#13;
                                                                  Page107&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 what a common set of shareholders is signalling in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 Fund and the Bank, because I recall Stan Fischer saying&#13;
&#13;
 that he often finds it hard to believe that, in fact, it&#13;
&#13;
 is a virtually identical set of shareholders, as he&#13;
&#13;
 follows the discussion of the same issues on both sides of&#13;
&#13;
 the street.   So, that is critical and we have a role to&#13;
&#13;
 play in that.&#13;
&#13;
           Second, I would like to caution that we not too&#13;
&#13;
 quickly dismiss, as the Bank's papers appear to do, the&#13;
&#13;
 possibility of directing HIPC savings and special stand-&#13;
&#13;
 alone poverty reduction or human development funds or&#13;
&#13;
 windows as some have called for.       I think properly&#13;
&#13;
 implemented in the context of transparent overall budget&#13;
&#13;
 procedures that are built on public expenditure reviews&#13;
&#13;
 and medium-term expenditure frameworks and that include&#13;
&#13;
 safeguards to ensure true additionality, such forums can&#13;
&#13;
 provide an important and a rational entry point for civil&#13;
&#13;
 society into decision-making that overcomes some of the&#13;
&#13;
 problems which have been cited in terms of when you open&#13;
&#13;
 it up to participation what structures that participation&#13;
&#13;
 and who are the legitimate participants.&#13;
&#13;
           So, I would just caution that we not too quickly&#13;
&#13;
 dismiss those vehicles, which in at least a couple of&#13;
                                                              Page108&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 instances have proven viable.      So, I think it would be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 inappropriate for us to dismiss them too arbitrarily,&#13;
&#13;
 which links I think directly to another point, that the&#13;
&#13;
 success of this framework requires tremendous leadership&#13;
&#13;
 from Bank management.    I think we have got to be&#13;
&#13;
 forthright in saying that the incentives are not in place&#13;
&#13;
 yet fully in the Bank.    And in our examination of the&#13;
&#13;
 balance in the matrix structure between the networks and&#13;
&#13;
 over-arching corporate priorities -- and I would say&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction in that sense is an over-arching, cross-&#13;
&#13;
 cutting corporate priority -- vis-a-vis the immediate&#13;
&#13;
 priorities of a Country Director at a given point in time,&#13;
&#13;
 we have all acknowledged that we don't have that balance&#13;
&#13;
 yet entirely well calibrated or honed.&#13;
&#13;
           That becomes especially critical as a constraint&#13;
&#13;
 when we talk about strengthening our poverty reduction.     I&#13;
&#13;
 think we simply have to keep it on the list as something&#13;
&#13;
 that, if we are going to do this, we are going to have to&#13;
&#13;
 accelerate the effort to do some pragmatic problem solving&#13;
&#13;
 on how to assure that this kind of a commitment translates&#13;
&#13;
 into direct incentives and performance evaluation measures&#13;
&#13;
 for staff in country units as well as in the networks.&#13;
&#13;
           This chair would explicitly want to say that we&#13;
                                                                 Page109&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 think it is too soon to agree on budget support lending&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 instruments and, since the paper anticipates that, we want&#13;
&#13;
 to make it clear that we don't think the case has yet&#13;
&#13;
 effectively been made.&#13;
&#13;
           I also want to recognize that the development&#13;
&#13;
 and implementation of PRSPs will take time.        This is going&#13;
&#13;
 to require capacity building in governments and in the&#13;
&#13;
 Bank.   This shouldn't be though an excuse for delays.      We&#13;
&#13;
 need to begin this urgently, and I thought the paper&#13;
&#13;
 perhaps overstressed a bit the complexity at the cost of&#13;
&#13;
 recognizing the essentiality of really moving with&#13;
&#13;
 dispatch to do this, because we have all committed to HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 relief based on performance, not promises.&#13;
&#13;
           And unless we can identify at least some&#13;
&#13;
 proxies, recognizing that results will take time and there&#13;
&#13;
 is an inherent tension between the desire for upfront debt&#13;
&#13;
 relief, on the one hand, and the time required to realize&#13;
&#13;
 results, on the other, in a results-based approach, I&#13;
&#13;
 think part of the way around that is country-specific&#13;
&#13;
 input-based measures as a kind of interim proxy.       And I&#13;
&#13;
 think we really have got to struggle further to find those&#13;
&#13;
 imperfect but workable measures.&#13;
&#13;
           In this regard, I would urge that we all&#13;
                                                                    Page110&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 integrate into the discussion the tremendous work that OED&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 has done.    And I think in some of their evaluations that&#13;
&#13;
 we sometimes insufficiently integrate into our operational&#13;
&#13;
 design, there is a lot of material which is directly&#13;
&#13;
 relevant to what selections we make on indicators going&#13;
&#13;
 forward.    So, I would commend that to all of our&#13;
&#13;
 attention.&#13;
&#13;
             Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. SANDSTROM:   Thank you very much, Jan.&#13;
&#13;
             Does anyone else want to come in at this stage&#13;
&#13;
 or should we first hear from staff?&#13;
&#13;
             [No response.]&#13;
&#13;
             MR. SANDSTROM:   So, why don't we hear from staff&#13;
&#13;
 and then you can come back with any further comments or&#13;
&#13;
 statements.&#13;
&#13;
             Masood will organize the answers, organize the&#13;
&#13;
 questions and answers and lead off.         We will also call on&#13;
&#13;
 IMF staff to react and respond to the questions that have&#13;
&#13;
 been raised and to give their perspective.&#13;
&#13;
             So, Masood.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. AHMED:    Thank you very much, Mr. Chairman.&#13;
&#13;
             Thank you all for those comments.       And what I&#13;
&#13;
 might do is really pick up on one general point which I&#13;
                                                                    Page111&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 think comes through in a lot of interventions.         And then,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 I thought that what I would do is ask our colleagues from&#13;
&#13;
 the Fund, particularly Russell Kincaid, to come and talk&#13;
&#13;
 specifically about a couple of issues that were raised,&#13;
&#13;
 the balancing of macro and the social objectives and how&#13;
&#13;
 we can do that while preserving the macro stability&#13;
&#13;
 objective, and also the issue of collaboration, and in&#13;
&#13;
 terms from their perspective, how do see that.     A number&#13;
&#13;
 of people have raised that.&#13;
&#13;
           I think it was Helena who said that this would&#13;
&#13;
 imply a sort of dramatic change in the way in which the&#13;
&#13;
 Bank works.   I think certainly from my interactions in&#13;
&#13;
 talking to my colleagues in the Fund, they will come and&#13;
&#13;
 tell you that in some ways it also implies pretty dramatic&#13;
&#13;
 difference in the way in which the Fund will be working.&#13;
&#13;
 It will be useful to get that perspective.&#13;
&#13;
           And I thought I would ask Peter to pick up on&#13;
&#13;
 some of the specific HIPC-related issues, in particular&#13;
&#13;
 whether or not the points that have been raised about&#13;
&#13;
 whether this new approach will be too burdensome for some&#13;
&#13;
 the HIPC countries to apply, and how do we balance the&#13;
&#13;
 speed, the desire that is coming through that you don't&#13;
&#13;
 delay debt relief and yet begin to phase in this new&#13;
                                                               Page112&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 approach in a pragmatic way, and also the link between the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 PFP, the PRSP and the CAS and how these things fit&#13;
&#13;
 together, it would be good to get that.&#13;
&#13;
           Then, I think I will ask John to pick up on the&#13;
&#13;
 questions related to the SSRs which a number of you have&#13;
&#13;
 raised, what their focus is, how poverty overlays the core&#13;
&#13;
 content and how they relate to other building blocks, as&#13;
&#13;
 well as to this issue of the proliferation of various&#13;
&#13;
 products and how we try and consolidate them.      And I will&#13;
&#13;
 ask him to be brief in response to Mr. Ghattas because&#13;
&#13;
 that is what John asked him to do and then Mike to pick up&#13;
&#13;
 on the other issues that relate to it.&#13;
&#13;
           The general point I wanted to make though is&#13;
&#13;
 really the following.    What you have before you is an&#13;
&#13;
 approach that has conceptually I think now been laid out.&#13;
&#13;
 Maybe I shouldn't be saying this, but in my own mind, if I&#13;
&#13;
 look back six months and look at what we have today, I&#13;
&#13;
 think this conceptual approach represents a significant&#13;
&#13;
 advance not only in terms of pulling together our own&#13;
&#13;
 material but also in terms of pulling together the way in&#13;
&#13;
 which the Bank and the Fund and other partners can support&#13;
&#13;
 countries in moving towards a common objective in a much&#13;
&#13;
 more concerted, coherent framework.&#13;
                                                                 Page113&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           So, I think on the conceptual level the elements&#13;
&#13;
 of it have been thought through and are laid out for you,&#13;
&#13;
 and I think we have had broad endorsement of it.    But it&#13;
&#13;
 is still very much at the conceptual level in many places.&#13;
&#13;
           And, as we move forward over the next couple of&#13;
&#13;
 years, I think you will find that it is in at least three&#13;
&#13;
 different ways going to have to be fleshed out.    First,&#13;
&#13;
 the analytics of it, as we operationalize, this whole idea&#13;
&#13;
 of what constitute the relevant set of indicators, how do&#13;
&#13;
 you use outcome indicators and what kind of proxy&#13;
&#13;
 indicators work or don't work well; how do you actually&#13;
&#13;
 try and look at the content, the points that were raised&#13;
&#13;
 by Mr. Hyden and others about how do play certain&#13;
&#13;
 elements, you know, is governance one part of it or is it&#13;
&#13;
 over-arching.&#13;
&#13;
           All of these things we are going to have to work&#13;
&#13;
 through and some of those rough edges are not only there&#13;
&#13;
 now, but my sense is that this is a new frontier for a lot&#13;
&#13;
 of people, trying to work through those relationships.&#13;
&#13;
           Secondly, in terms as we move forward to apply&#13;
&#13;
 it, it is going to be a function of capacity, the capacity&#13;
&#13;
 in countries to be able to develop this kind of&#13;
                                                              Page114&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 participative process and the content and the dialogue on&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 it, the capacity in civil society to play the role that&#13;
&#13;
 many of you are saying it ought to be playing and that we&#13;
&#13;
 I think are suggesting it plays in the design of this, the&#13;
&#13;
 capacity inside the Bank and in our partners who work with&#13;
&#13;
 it to try and follow through in supporting countries in&#13;
&#13;
 these areas.   We don't have that kind of range of&#13;
&#13;
 expertise yet onboard and we will be building and training&#13;
&#13;
 capacity there.&#13;
&#13;
           The third dimension is behavior, culture.   But&#13;
&#13;
 in some ways this is about a different way of relating and&#13;
&#13;
 doing business.   And there is a set of behavioral changes&#13;
&#13;
 implied in this in the way in which different parties&#13;
&#13;
 interact in the design of country strategies within the&#13;
&#13;
 country, in the way in which we, the Bank and the Fund,&#13;
&#13;
 not only work with each other but, much more importantly,&#13;
&#13;
 actually make our processes and our products in some sense&#13;
&#13;
 in timetables contingent upon the pace at which countries&#13;
&#13;
 are able to move forward.&#13;
&#13;
           I think much of the discussion about whether we&#13;
&#13;
 have been timely in responding to the Fund, you know, we&#13;
&#13;
 can talk about it, I am happy to come back to that.   But I&#13;
&#13;
 think a much more interesting question is going to be:&#13;
                                                               Page115&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 How will we both be timely in responding to the pace at&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 which countries move?    And that timely means not only&#13;
&#13;
 being too slow but being too fast.        Because I think the&#13;
&#13;
 real behavioral change that we will have to work through&#13;
&#13;
 is recognizing that in some cases pushing for speed at our&#13;
&#13;
 timetable will undermine the very process of ownership&#13;
&#13;
 that we are trying to foster through this.&#13;
&#13;
           So, I think there is a whole set of behavioral&#13;
&#13;
 issues there and internal behavioral issues which are&#13;
&#13;
 going to be partly related to the respective roles of&#13;
&#13;
 center and Country Directors, incentives that reinforce&#13;
&#13;
 those behavioral changes.&#13;
&#13;
           I don't have today any kind of simple rules of&#13;
&#13;
 thumb or options that I can say this is how we are going&#13;
&#13;
 to really ensure that those behavioral changes take place&#13;
&#13;
 within the Bank except to say the things that you have&#13;
&#13;
 pointed out, that you can work on a number of levers to&#13;
&#13;
 push on those.   The are incentives, the way in which we do&#13;
&#13;
 evaluations, it is the management attention, it is the&#13;
&#13;
 celebration of those who are moving forward more quickly&#13;
&#13;
 than others.&#13;
&#13;
           I think what you will see over the next year or&#13;
&#13;
 two is a messy, patchy, uneven process coming to you.&#13;
                                                                 Page116&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Some of the country strategies that will come to you will&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 be much stronger in terms of being grounded in this&#13;
&#13;
 framework than others.     I say that now because I think it&#13;
&#13;
 is very important that, while we adhere firmly to the&#13;
&#13;
 objectives of where we are trying to go with this&#13;
&#13;
 framework, if you endorse it, we recognize that the&#13;
&#13;
 process of getting there for these very reasons is going&#13;
&#13;
 to be an uneven and sort of phasing-in process.         And we&#13;
&#13;
 will have two systems in some ways running in parallel for&#13;
&#13;
 a period.&#13;
&#13;
             I mean, in some countries you may see a PFP and&#13;
&#13;
 in others a PRSP, and you might legitimately ask why do&#13;
&#13;
 you have these two still coexisting.         And I think the&#13;
&#13;
 answer will be that one was just ready to go and the other&#13;
&#13;
 wasn't.&#13;
&#13;
             So, I say this as a prelude to getting specific&#13;
&#13;
 answers because in some ways some of the answers you will&#13;
&#13;
 get will still show the same rough edges that the papers&#13;
&#13;
 themselves show in terms of where we are and how we begin&#13;
&#13;
 to phase in this approach over the next year and eighteen&#13;
&#13;
 months.&#13;
&#13;
             So, with that, I thought I might ask Russell to&#13;
&#13;
 sort of say from his perspective, from the Fund, how&#13;
                                                                  Page117&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 things look on those issues.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           MR. KINCAID:     Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           Let me say at the outset that the Fund staff&#13;
&#13;
 that has been working on both the HIPC Initiative but also&#13;
&#13;
 the social sector questions and ESAF arrangements and&#13;
&#13;
 policies more generally work quite closely with their Bank&#13;
&#13;
 counterparts in commenting on the Bank's papers that are&#13;
&#13;
 before you today, but also in reacting and accommodating&#13;
&#13;
 the Bank's comments on their own papers.             And this has&#13;
&#13;
 been I think a very fruitful collaboration.&#13;
&#13;
           We have come a long way in the last six months.&#13;
&#13;
 And there, I very much share Masood's remarks on that.&#13;
&#13;
           I would also like to say that several Directors&#13;
&#13;
 here have commented that the poverty reduction strategy&#13;
&#13;
 papers imply a shift in the way the Bank works, a very&#13;
&#13;
 fundamental shift.     And I think that is right.         They also&#13;
&#13;
 imply a very fundamental shift in the way the Fund works&#13;
&#13;
 and works not only internally but with the Bank.            And that&#13;
&#13;
 I think is recognized at all levels within the two&#13;
&#13;
 institutions.&#13;
&#13;
           I don't think we have answers to all the&#13;
&#13;
 questions about how the processes need to change, but I&#13;
&#13;
 think there is a very clear means of communication going&#13;
                                                                        Page118&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 on at this stage.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                           507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                         Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                             (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           In that context, let me share with you something&#13;
&#13;
 which our management, the Managing Director has said to&#13;
&#13;
 our Board, which will be part of the dialogue and the&#13;
&#13;
 discussion the Fund's Executive Board will have on Monday.&#13;
&#13;
 That is that it is recognized that the ambitious proposals&#13;
&#13;
 that are put forward for the HIPC countries have&#13;
&#13;
 implications for how the Fund supports all low-income&#13;
&#13;
 developing countries; that is, how the Fund's ESAF&#13;
&#13;
 programs work, in general.&#13;
&#13;
           And therefore, the management of the Fund has&#13;
&#13;
 talked about the need to adapt ESAF arrangements.      In&#13;
&#13;
 fact, it was even proposed that the whole facility be&#13;
&#13;
 renamed to reflect the fact that this will be a reformed&#13;
&#13;
 ESAF that is going to come out of this process.&#13;
&#13;
           We are in the opening stages of that discussion&#13;
&#13;
 within the Fund.   So, it is really not possible for me to&#13;
&#13;
 go into great detail.     But I think it is clear from our&#13;
&#13;
 perspective and I think from the Bank's that the PFP&#13;
&#13;
 process has not worked well.       There are weaknesses there&#13;
&#13;
 and it needs to be replaced.       And the poverty reduction&#13;
&#13;
 strategy paper I think is the instrument that we think&#13;
&#13;
 would be a useful replacement.       And I will leave my Bank&#13;
                                                                 Page119&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 colleagues to expand about that.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           But that is the perspective that certainly is&#13;
&#13;
 shared on the Fund side, and we are looking very much&#13;
&#13;
 forward to seeing more input from the Bank in this&#13;
&#13;
 process, not only in terms of what I would say would be&#13;
&#13;
 the medium-term budgetary strategies of these countries&#13;
&#13;
 but in the annual budgetary processes and in terms of the&#13;
&#13;
 priorities, the quality of spending.        This is where the&#13;
&#13;
 Fund staff sees the greatest need at the moment for Bank&#13;
&#13;
 staff input, because that is really the nitty-gritty&#13;
&#13;
 choices that a country faces each year.            And particularly&#13;
&#13;
 if there is an external shock and there is a need for&#13;
&#13;
 budgetary adjustments, different than had been expected in&#13;
&#13;
 the medium-term plan, well, what is going to give?&#13;
&#13;
           And here, I think the authorities and the Fund&#13;
&#13;
 staff in a participatory process want to have greater&#13;
&#13;
 input at a technical level as well as in a social,&#13;
&#13;
 political context.&#13;
&#13;
           It is both of these aspects that we want to see&#13;
&#13;
 strengthened -- the expertise coming from the Bank but&#13;
&#13;
 also a more open and consultative process.           This is very&#13;
&#13;
 much I think in line with what you are talking about here&#13;
&#13;
 at the Bank.&#13;
                                                                       Page120&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
            From our own side, we recognize that the setting&#13;
&#13;
 of macroeconomic objectives, fiscal targets needs to be an&#13;
&#13;
 iterative process, a process that takes onboard what the&#13;
&#13;
 objectives are for poverty reduction in the social area,&#13;
&#13;
 but more broadly development objectives.           But what the&#13;
&#13;
 Fund needs and what the authorities need I think are a&#13;
&#13;
 clearer idea of what the costs are, the resource costs,&#13;
&#13;
 the budgetary costs of all of these programs are, and also&#13;
&#13;
 the priorities that need to be assigned.&#13;
&#13;
            And that is a very important part of this&#13;
&#13;
 process.   And there, there is scope in the fiscal envelope&#13;
&#13;
 and in the macro framework to make adjustments.          Now how&#13;
&#13;
 much, that will have to be decided in each individual&#13;
&#13;
 case.   But what we see as going on is an iterative process&#13;
&#13;
 -- Bank, Fund and the authorities trying to work out what&#13;
&#13;
 is optimal for this country, recognizing that macro&#13;
&#13;
 stability and low inflation have positive effects on&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction and on growth.&#13;
&#13;
            Many of these countries, particularly HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 countries, became highly indebted because they had&#13;
&#13;
 unsustainable fiscal policies.      So, we want to make sure&#13;
&#13;
 that fiscal policies are sustainable.         And that is I think&#13;
                                                                     Page121&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 a common framework.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           I guess in responding to the two questions that&#13;
&#13;
 were put to me, we see a need for these changes at the&#13;
&#13;
 Fund.   We are going to work very hard in the days ahead to&#13;
&#13;
 come up with some of the -- I won't call them answers --&#13;
&#13;
 but come up with some of the processes, some of the&#13;
&#13;
 approaches that allow some the ragged edges that we now&#13;
&#13;
 have before us to become smooth.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. AHMED:    Peter.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. FALLON:   Okay.    Thank you very much.   And&#13;
&#13;
 let me say again how much we very much appreciate the&#13;
&#13;
 comments from the Executive Directors on our papers.      This&#13;
&#13;
 is really very encouraging and a very nice position to be&#13;
&#13;
 in.&#13;
&#13;
           I am just going to talk about two things.      One,&#13;
&#13;
 I think was -- and this came out from several speakers --&#13;
&#13;
 about the burdensome nature or will all of this business&#13;
&#13;
 over-burden poor countries and perhaps the HIPC countries&#13;
&#13;
 which tend to be particularly poor.&#13;
&#13;
           And I think in a way the answer has partly&#13;
&#13;
 actually come out of the comments of various Executive&#13;
&#13;
 Directors.   I mean, in a way, at the very end this is&#13;
                                                                  Page122&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 going to be a tradeoff situation.       On the one hand, yes,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 we don't want to delay getting relief and helping these&#13;
&#13;
 countries.   On the other hand, to put it rather crudely&#13;
&#13;
 and in a rather English way, we don't want to give&#13;
&#13;
 something away totally for nothing.        We do want to see&#13;
&#13;
 this as integrated into a poverty reduction strategy which&#13;
&#13;
 is long-term and going to have long-term benefits.&#13;
&#13;
           Now quite clearly, when you are dealing with a&#13;
&#13;
 situation like this, you are looking for some form of&#13;
&#13;
 compromise, though I suspect the nature of the compromise&#13;
&#13;
 will probably change as we move through.&#13;
&#13;
           Let me just make two or three comments on being&#13;
&#13;
 burdensome, over-burdening I find easier to pronounce.&#13;
&#13;
 First of all, in fact, it relates to another question and&#13;
&#13;
 that is, in some sense, will HIPC be enough?       Will there&#13;
&#13;
 be enough resources?    Well, the answer is even with HIPC,&#13;
&#13;
 with domestic resources, these remain very poor countries&#13;
&#13;
 and the amount of investments that can be placed on&#13;
&#13;
 various poverty reduction actions are obviously limited.&#13;
&#13;
           That forces the pragmatism in one way.       With&#13;
&#13;
 limited resources, this tends to mean, of course, that you&#13;
&#13;
 tend to seek a few really key priorities and to&#13;
&#13;
 concentrate on those.    That is one kind of constraint that&#13;
                                                                 Page123&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 comes across.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
            A second one I think is the participatory&#13;
&#13;
 process.   We have reflected in the documents, and I&#13;
&#13;
 reflected this this morning, we expect this actually to&#13;
&#13;
 help.   One of the problems we have, particularly in the&#13;
&#13;
 poorer countries, we often don't know what NGOs or what&#13;
&#13;
 various donor agencies are actually doing.          One thing this&#13;
&#13;
 might do is actually put this information basis together&#13;
&#13;
 to design the process and then later easier to implement&#13;
&#13;
 the process as it unfolds.&#13;
&#13;
            Thirdly, this point was made very well I think&#13;
&#13;
 by the Dutch chair, the World Bank and the IMF probably&#13;
&#13;
 just cannot do all of this on their own.           We are hoping,&#13;
&#13;
 in fact, that the design and the monitoring and all of&#13;
&#13;
 these things will be shared between the Bank, the Fund and&#13;
&#13;
 other relevant agencies.    In that sense, the burden we see&#13;
&#13;
 as being shared and spread rather more perhaps than at the&#13;
&#13;
 present time.&#13;
&#13;
            The compromise, as I said, will shift over time.&#13;
&#13;
 It is definitely then going to be a transitional process,&#13;
&#13;
 and John Sinclair said, well, he would like to know&#13;
&#13;
 staff's view on how the new HIPCs will be handled.          I&#13;
&#13;
 don't think staff really have a clear view right at this&#13;
                                                                      Page124&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 point on a case-by-case kind of basis.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
             Initially, the compromise will have to be -- if&#13;
&#13;
 we think of it -- on a scale a bit towards the idea of,&#13;
&#13;
 look, we don't want to create unnecessary delay; we&#13;
&#13;
 recognize that a good strategy will take time to&#13;
&#13;
 formulate; it will take time to put into place.       And we&#13;
&#13;
 don't want to hold people up.&#13;
&#13;
             As we move along the scale over time, I suspect&#13;
&#13;
 that we will begin to tighten.       I suspect that, as we have&#13;
&#13;
 said, today that, while it is desirable basically that a&#13;
&#13;
 strategy be in place at the decision point but it is not&#13;
&#13;
 really absolutely essential, I predict -- it is just a&#13;
&#13;
 personal prediction -- that a few years down the road it&#13;
&#13;
 will be the case that it will have to be in place at the&#13;
&#13;
 decision point.    In other words, I anticipate that this&#13;
&#13;
 will tighten gradually over time in what we hope is a&#13;
&#13;
 demonstrated success of what we are trying to do.&#13;
&#13;
             The point about transition and moving over time&#13;
&#13;
 I think also applies to the question of the PRSP and the&#13;
&#13;
 PFP.   We do recognize that the PFP is not going to die&#13;
&#13;
 tomorrow.    There will be countries that will have PFPs and&#13;
&#13;
 gradually bringing PRSPs in.&#13;
&#13;
             But let me just address perhaps briefly the&#13;
                                                                   Page125&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 question of why trying to do it.        Remember, we are trying&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 to introduce a new enhanced framework, which is going to&#13;
&#13;
 be participatory, it is going to have a consistency for&#13;
&#13;
 the first time we believe between the macro, the&#13;
&#13;
 structural and what sometimes is called the social -- I&#13;
&#13;
 would rather say other poverty reduction components.&#13;
&#13;
           The idea of the PRSP is this is going to be, if&#13;
&#13;
 you like, a flagship document, which is going to be&#13;
&#13;
 published, it is going to be a tripartite document, owned&#13;
&#13;
 by the government.   It is going to basically contain all&#13;
&#13;
 of the indicators that are used, largely perhaps&#13;
&#13;
 intermediate indicators.    As we stressed and some speakers&#13;
&#13;
 have stressed, we are looking at initially short time&#13;
&#13;
 frames and we, of course, have to work with intermediates&#13;
&#13;
 rather than outcomes for purely practical reasons.&#13;
&#13;
           A big point about this is we expect -- and this&#13;
&#13;
 is the linkage to the CAS -- the CAS would take the&#13;
&#13;
 strategy and basically would judge progress under the&#13;
&#13;
 strategy for its lending instruments.         We also hope -- it&#13;
&#13;
 may not happen -- that other institutions would start to&#13;
&#13;
 use this document in much the same way.&#13;
&#13;
           Our comparators with the PFP, I have written&#13;
&#13;
 three PFPs -- I won't say for which country -- some time&#13;
                                                                    Page126&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 ago at the World Bank, and I regarded it then as&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 fundamentally a shadow document to what was then the SAF&#13;
&#13;
 and later the ESAF.    The PFP was a document really without&#13;
&#13;
 any particular kind of teeth.&#13;
&#13;
           I understand over time it has become an even&#13;
&#13;
 paler shadow.   It is taken not terribly seriously by Bank&#13;
&#13;
 staff.   There have been surveys of this.          We suspect there&#13;
&#13;
 is not much ownership on the part of governments.&#13;
&#13;
           Now, we could do all the things in the PRSP and&#13;
&#13;
 still call it a PFP and just make this change.          We&#13;
&#13;
 suggested this idea.    There was a feeling though that,&#13;
&#13;
 since we are making a real discrete change at the present&#13;
&#13;
 time, we really need a change in the title to signal this,&#13;
&#13;
 much the same way as my colleague from the Fund said          they&#13;
&#13;
 may change the title of the ESAF, because that is changing&#13;
&#13;
 its particular nature.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. PAGE:    Well, I have been given the task of&#13;
&#13;
 trying to be brief in addressing the relationship between&#13;
&#13;
 our diagnostic instruments in country strategies --&#13;
&#13;
 unfortunately, Marcos is not here to grade me on my&#13;
&#13;
 performance; so I hope you will report back to him later.&#13;
&#13;
           The first set of issues really have to do with&#13;
                                                                       Page127&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 the role of the SSR and how we see this fitting into these&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 poverty-focused country assistance strategies.          Put very&#13;
&#13;
 simply, we see these as the tools by which Country&#13;
&#13;
 Directors and country teams can achieve a more systematic&#13;
&#13;
 analysis of the issues in their countries and a better&#13;
&#13;
 strategic focus.&#13;
&#13;
             In a way, it is answering the first question of&#13;
&#13;
 good strategic planning, which is where do we want to go.&#13;
&#13;
 It is a help for that particular purpose.           We do not see&#13;
&#13;
 these instruments really in a sense as ends in themselves.&#13;
&#13;
 And I want to assure Directors that we don't see a poverty&#13;
&#13;
 note substituting for a poverty-focused CAS, nor do we see&#13;
&#13;
 a social and structural review as in any way undermining&#13;
&#13;
 the need to have then a well-focused country strategy and,&#13;
&#13;
 within that, a well-focused Bank country assistance&#13;
&#13;
 strategy.    These are tools to do the job.&#13;
&#13;
             The second question, of course, in strategic&#13;
&#13;
 planning is:    How do we get there?       And that question is&#13;
&#13;
 really the one in which we have to bring the array of&#13;
&#13;
 matrix services that we have discussed today, the role of&#13;
&#13;
 the networks in really supporting the regions and Country&#13;
&#13;
 Directors in setting strategic priorities within the&#13;
&#13;
 broader country assistance framework.&#13;
                                                                     Page128&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           That brings us, of course, to the question of&#13;
&#13;
 the role of instruments.     Which instruments do we deploy?&#13;
&#13;
 Those are I think very much a country-based set of&#13;
&#13;
 decisions that have to be made.        We note some Directors'&#13;
&#13;
 concerns with respect to budgetary support instruments,&#13;
&#13;
 but please note that there is nothing in this strategy&#13;
&#13;
 that presupposes any selection of instruments.       The tools&#13;
&#13;
 have to befit the task.&#13;
&#13;
           It also speaks to the issue of capacity building&#13;
&#13;
 in our own analytical and advisory services.        And here,&#13;
&#13;
 let me take a slight exception with our colleague from the&#13;
&#13;
 Fund.   One of the things that I think we have tried to&#13;
&#13;
 demonstrate to you in the past two years is that,&#13;
&#13;
 particularly in the critical area of public expenditure,&#13;
&#13;
 which in some ways is one of the key links between public&#13;
&#13;
 actions and poverty outcomes, the Bank is moving well&#13;
&#13;
 beyond the mere certification of public expenditure&#13;
&#13;
 programs, if you like, the old traditional shooting of&#13;
&#13;
 white elephants.&#13;
&#13;
           To answer the question that I always got when I&#13;
&#13;
 was a Chief Economist:     How do we keep from making the&#13;
&#13;
 same bad decisions the next time?        The issue is really to&#13;
                                                                   Page129&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 create the capacity within countries to have better&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 selectivity and better prioritization of the public&#13;
&#13;
 expenditure programs.     Certification is a part of that but&#13;
&#13;
 it is not the end of that.      And I wouldn't like to leave&#13;
&#13;
 an impression with Directors that we are simply going to&#13;
&#13;
 be engaged in a process of certifying public expenditure&#13;
&#13;
 programs.    That is not the objective of our work in public&#13;
&#13;
 sector development and public expenditure.&#13;
&#13;
             To come to the role of the SSR, the fundamental&#13;
&#13;
 concept of the SSR is systematic coverage of a set of&#13;
&#13;
 questions dealing with the underpinnings of the market&#13;
&#13;
 economy -- social and structural -- but within an&#13;
&#13;
 integrating framework, the integrating framework being the&#13;
&#13;
 objective of poverty reduction.&#13;
&#13;
             So, it is not that we are trying to create a&#13;
&#13;
 poverty instrument or a poverty reduction instrument in&#13;
&#13;
 the SSR, but to actually provide an over-arching framework&#13;
&#13;
 within which we can understand structural and social&#13;
&#13;
 issues and be more selective in the process of answering&#13;
&#13;
 the question of where do we want to go.&#13;
&#13;
             It is a very interesting case that in the six&#13;
&#13;
 pilot studies the question of ownership has evolved.       It&#13;
&#13;
 is no secret to many of you that some countries were&#13;
                                                                 Page130&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 deeply concerned about how social and structural reviews&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 would be used.   What we have found is that, as these&#13;
&#13;
 social and structural reviews have been undertaken, as&#13;
&#13;
 governments have been engaged in the process of design, as&#13;
&#13;
 we would do with any process of economic and sector work,&#13;
&#13;
 we have had substantially greater buy-in over the course&#13;
&#13;
 of the pilot period than in the initiation of the social&#13;
&#13;
 and structural review process.      That is seen by the fact&#13;
&#13;
 that we now have I think received clearance from all&#13;
&#13;
 governments to bring those documents to the Board.         They&#13;
&#13;
 are now formally parts of ESW.&#13;
&#13;
           When we began, we said to them you can choose,&#13;
&#13;
 and many of them said let's wait and see.          The answer has&#13;
&#13;
 been we are quite satisfied with this process and believe&#13;
&#13;
 it has taken onboard our concerns about balance and about&#13;
&#13;
 perspective, many of those concerns expressed by the&#13;
&#13;
 Chinese chair today.&#13;
&#13;
           Given that evolving relationship, it is also&#13;
&#13;
 interesting to ask what have they been used for?         And here&#13;
&#13;
 I would like to call your attention to the Dominican&#13;
&#13;
 Republic SSR which is a particularly interesting example&#13;
&#13;
 of an SSR in a CDF country.     The current proposal on the&#13;
&#13;
 table from government is to actually use that as one of&#13;
                                                                     Page131&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 the fundamental underpinnings of a set of dialogues to be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 undertaken among all the parties within the Dominican&#13;
&#13;
 Republic -- political and civil society organizations --&#13;
&#13;
 on forming a vision, but a national vision of where the DR&#13;
&#13;
 wants to go.   So, this has become a document which is not&#13;
&#13;
 only in some sense owned by government and the Bank but is&#13;
&#13;
 going to be used to try to build a new level of consensus&#13;
&#13;
 at the level of the society in terms of a country strategy&#13;
&#13;
 focused on poverty reduction, incorporating the&#13;
&#13;
 underpinnings of the market economy.&#13;
&#13;
           I think that is where we would like to go with&#13;
&#13;
 SSRs, a tool which can help in this process of forming a&#13;
&#13;
 vision of where countries wish to go.&#13;
&#13;
           Where will we go in practice?            We have eight to&#13;
&#13;
 ten country teams who have asked for further work on SSRs&#13;
&#13;
 in the coming year.   We will begin by supporting those.&#13;
&#13;
 As we learn more from that process and as we learn from&#13;
&#13;
 this process of developing poverty-focused country&#13;
&#13;
 strategies, we will come back to you with further&#13;
&#13;
 recommendations as to whether management wishes to move&#13;
&#13;
 further in the implementation of this particular tool.&#13;
&#13;
           Finally, let me very briefly address the&#13;
&#13;
 alphabet soup of analytical acronyms.         You are right,&#13;
                                                                       Page132&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 there are too many of them; they are too confusing; they&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 change all the time.   Even I cannot keep track of them.&#13;
&#13;
 It makes me feel like I am back in the U.S. Navy.&#13;
&#13;
            We will try in the course of the coming year to&#13;
&#13;
 do what Joanne Salop calls "business-ify" our ESW program.&#13;
&#13;
 In doing that, what we will do is reduce the number of&#13;
&#13;
 standard ESW products which we offer both to country teams&#13;
&#13;
 and to client countries, to develop a set of network&#13;
&#13;
 support services to those to ensure greater coherence and&#13;
&#13;
 comparability among them and greater quality assurance&#13;
&#13;
 from the network side.&#13;
&#13;
            At the same time, let me point out that, as we&#13;
&#13;
 do that, and reduce the range of these products, which&#13;
&#13;
 would be in a sense the building blocks identified by the&#13;
&#13;
 SSR type product of critical areas that are constraints to&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction, we will also have to maintain a&#13;
&#13;
 balance.&#13;
&#13;
            Because, as many of you know, much of our&#13;
&#13;
 analytical and advisory work today is not done in the form&#13;
&#13;
 of formal ESW products but just in-time policy notes and&#13;
&#13;
 other responses to emerging needs.        And while we move&#13;
&#13;
 toward greater standardization, on the one hand, I think&#13;
&#13;
 we also have to maintain a balance to be sure that we are&#13;
                                                               Page133&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 responsive to the client, on the other.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
             Nevertheless, I hope that within a year's time&#13;
&#13;
 we can come back to you and assure you that we have&#13;
&#13;
 reduced the number of alphabetical combinations, and that&#13;
&#13;
 you can also have greater confidence that when you look at&#13;
&#13;
 one of these particular acronyms, you know more or less&#13;
&#13;
 what it is going to contain and you have a better sense of&#13;
&#13;
 what its quality will be and what its content will be.&#13;
&#13;
             So, I think in that sense we hear you, we share&#13;
&#13;
 the same concern and we are trying to respond.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. WALTON:   Thank you very much.      I will be&#13;
&#13;
 really quick.    People get nervous when you say that.&#13;
&#13;
             First, to reaffirm we have got two processes&#13;
&#13;
 going on.    What we are really talking about today is a&#13;
&#13;
 very practical process of how you do business in countries&#13;
&#13;
 and in sectors.    I would like to reaffirm that what we are&#13;
&#13;
 building on today is a lot of what is beginning in&#13;
&#13;
 different countries, different sectors in the Bank but it&#13;
&#13;
 needs to be extended and that, of course, will take time.&#13;
&#13;
             I want to pick up one issue within that, and&#13;
&#13;
 that was raised by a number of Directors, and that is&#13;
&#13;
 goals, how they are set, and just to reaffirm that we see&#13;
&#13;
 a strong complementarity between participative processes&#13;
                                                                 Page134&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 at the societal level to set goals and use indicators that&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 are relevant to that society, and a technical process&#13;
&#13;
 which will define the tradeoffs and define what works and&#13;
&#13;
 does not work from international experience.       Often that&#13;
&#13;
 will involve, and we take note, issues of employment,&#13;
&#13;
 issues of poverty lines, but that will have to be defined&#13;
&#13;
 on a country-by-country basis.&#13;
&#13;
           The next point, we certainly take note of a lot&#13;
&#13;
 of substantive issues that were raised about how we can&#13;
&#13;
 continue to learn about what is important and what matters&#13;
&#13;
 in poverty reduction strategies.       Just to cite a few,&#13;
&#13;
 there is a lot of resonance with the central issue of&#13;
&#13;
 distribution, questions of how you confront issues of&#13;
&#13;
 asset inequality, what is really meant by empowerment, how&#13;
&#13;
 that may relate to issues of conflict, the fact that&#13;
&#13;
 governance is certainly not just about empowerment but it&#13;
&#13;
 cuts across everything, and that there is a powerful&#13;
&#13;
 interrelation about issues that gender is central both in&#13;
&#13;
 terms of the dimensions of poverty and its process.&#13;
&#13;
           The only thing I will say about this is this&#13;
&#13;
 will be a central part of the debate over the coming year.&#13;
&#13;
 And this forum will start next Friday -- or the next phase&#13;
&#13;
 will be next Friday in the discussion of the WDR.      So, I&#13;
                                                                 Page135&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 am going to postpone any discussion of that till then.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
           The only thing I would underline which is part&#13;
&#13;
 of that process is the difficult question of understanding&#13;
&#13;
 the types of institutions and the types of processes that&#13;
&#13;
 genuinely represent the interests of poor people.          That is&#13;
&#13;
 something we are only beginning to work with.          It is what&#13;
&#13;
 the poor communities themselves are saying is a major&#13;
&#13;
 missing link, and that governments are failing them, even&#13;
&#13;
 when there are formal structures of voting.          But that is a&#13;
&#13;
 central challenge which we will again be discussing in the&#13;
&#13;
 future.&#13;
&#13;
           The final thing, we take note of the concerns of&#13;
&#13;
 the poverty notes and the need to link them with the CAS.&#13;
&#13;
 And, as I said before, we will get back to you to discuss&#13;
&#13;
 how to achieve the common end I think that we all mutually&#13;
&#13;
 understand and avoid the risks.&#13;
&#13;
           Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
           Good answers to good questions.          Now are there&#13;
&#13;
 any further comments?    Jan.&#13;
&#13;
           MS. PIERCY:   I risk the wrath of my colleagues&#13;
&#13;
 at this hour.   One point, going back to Masood Ahmed's&#13;
&#13;
 opening -- this is a point I make through the lens of the&#13;
                                                                      Page136&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Ad Hoc Committee on Board Policies and Procedures -- when&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 Masood made the point that if we endorse this framework,&#13;
&#13;
 then, of course, we have to see that it is consistently&#13;
&#13;
 applied across CASs and how countries are held to it.&#13;
&#13;
             The point I want to make is that the Board has a&#13;
&#13;
 role to play here.    Part of our role -- and that is part&#13;
&#13;
 of why it is important that we debate this and that we do&#13;
&#13;
 fully elaborate the points of agreement and the points of&#13;
&#13;
 difference -- because it should mean something if we in&#13;
&#13;
 the end endorse the framework, and that then should mean&#13;
&#13;
 that we consistently apply it across the CASs.      And we are&#13;
&#13;
 a part of how you begin to achieve that consistency.&#13;
&#13;
             And I want to say that management can hold the&#13;
&#13;
 Board accountable, just like the Board holds management&#13;
&#13;
 accounts.    This is part of what we had begun discussing in&#13;
&#13;
 this Ad Hoc Committee.     So, I think we shouldn't shy away&#13;
&#13;
 from envisioning the role of the Board when management has&#13;
&#13;
 its conversations going up to the Strategic Forum, where&#13;
&#13;
 this will be discussed, because I think that is really&#13;
&#13;
 critical.    And that also translates into how we orient in-&#13;
&#13;
 coming members of the Board, so they know there is a&#13;
&#13;
 framework, and it was adopted and this are its&#13;
&#13;
 implications, so that we over time become an active&#13;
                                                                  Page137&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 partner in this process.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
            Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
            MR. SANDSTROM:    Thank you, Jan.        You are right;&#13;
&#13;
 it is very helpful.     We all need to focus on this and be&#13;
&#13;
 disciplined and just work together and get it done.&#13;
&#13;
            And we need also to disseminate this to staff,&#13;
&#13;
 and that is the next challenge now also, to work with&#13;
&#13;
 them.   We have a number of teams who are actually doing&#13;
&#13;
 it, and they are cross-fertilizing within and across&#13;
&#13;
 regions.   But we need at the corporate level to do much&#13;
&#13;
 more.&#13;
&#13;
            Part of that is to develop an operational plan&#13;
&#13;
 to implement this.      So, that is the next challenge.&#13;
&#13;
            Are there any further comments, any further&#13;
&#13;
 statements?&#13;
&#13;
            [No response.]&#13;
&#13;
            MR. SANDSTROM:    You know what we need to do now.&#13;
&#13;
 This is the Board discussion in the Bank.           The Fund will&#13;
&#13;
 be discussing the same sets of issues on the HIPC link&#13;
&#13;
 paper on Monday.   So, as usual, what we would like to do&#13;
&#13;
 is to transmit the formal summary to the Fund Board of&#13;
&#13;
 this discussion.&#13;
&#13;
            So, if you have some more patience with us, I&#13;
                                                                      Page138&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 will read out the draft of a summary of this discussion,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 which will try to highlight the major themes of what came&#13;
&#13;
 out.   I will do that and then, if you have any further&#13;
&#13;
 comments or changes, additions to this, if you could give&#13;
&#13;
 it to us now and then we will work on it, clean it up and&#13;
&#13;
 get it out quickly.    So, let me try this.&#13;
&#13;
             Directors strongly welcomed the thrust of both&#13;
&#13;
 documents and the effort they reflect to enhance the&#13;
&#13;
 impact of Bank and Fund activities and the role of&#13;
&#13;
 external assistance, more generally, including debt relief&#13;
&#13;
 in poverty reduction.&#13;
&#13;
             Directors endorsed the emphasis on outcome-based&#13;
&#13;
 indicators, the international development goals,&#13;
&#13;
 participatory process and country ownership of a poverty-&#13;
&#13;
 oriented development strategy.&#13;
&#13;
             Directors supported the joint proposal by Bank&#13;
&#13;
 and Fund staffs to move to tripartite poverty reduction&#13;
&#13;
 strategy papers as a basis for integrating policies and&#13;
&#13;
 programs.&#13;
&#13;
             On the paper, "Building Poverty Reduction&#13;
&#13;
 Strategies in Developing Countries", Directors welcomed&#13;
&#13;
 the comprehensive approach to poverty reduction.    They&#13;
&#13;
 stressed that sustained poverty reduction is not possible&#13;
                                                                Page139&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 without economic growth.     Consequently, macroeconomic&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 stability and structural reforms that allow sustained&#13;
&#13;
 growth are an essential part of any poverty reduction&#13;
&#13;
 strategy.&#13;
&#13;
             But to maximize the poverty-reducing impact of&#13;
&#13;
 growth requires a determined focus on the determinance of&#13;
&#13;
 poverty and related public action.         As poverty is multi-&#13;
&#13;
 dimensional, the poverty response would also need to be&#13;
&#13;
 multi-dimensional, relating not only to more spending in&#13;
&#13;
 social sectors but also to other reforms that improve the&#13;
&#13;
 access of the poor to the benefits of economic growth.&#13;
&#13;
             Directors emphasized the need to be pragmatic in&#13;
&#13;
 the application of this approach, taking into account the&#13;
&#13;
 circumstances of each country.       They also cautioned that&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction is a long-term process and we should&#13;
&#13;
 avoid creating unrealistic expectations which do not take&#13;
&#13;
 into account capacity constraints, including those related&#13;
&#13;
 to statistical information and poverty monitoring.&#13;
&#13;
             Directors agreed that broad-based participation&#13;
&#13;
 is needed at the design, implementation and monitoring&#13;
&#13;
 stages of a successful poverty reduction strategy.&#13;
&#13;
 Directors also supported the use of a clear set of&#13;
&#13;
 outcome-oriented goals and intermediate indicators to&#13;
                                                                   Page140&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 ensure that poverty reduction strategies are well-designed&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                          507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                        Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                            (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 and provide a feedback mechanism to ensure that they are&#13;
&#13;
 implemented effectively.&#13;
&#13;
            The selection and monitoring of such indicators&#13;
&#13;
 would be a good vehicle for broad participation of civil&#13;
&#13;
 society.   Directors agreed that in the context of the HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 Initiative and given the irrevocable nature of debt&#13;
&#13;
 relief, transparency and accountability were important&#13;
&#13;
 features of any poverty reduction strategy and would help&#13;
&#13;
 ensure effective use of debt relief after the completion&#13;
&#13;
 point.&#13;
&#13;
            In this context, they suggested that governance&#13;
&#13;
 be given higher priority among the levers for public&#13;
&#13;
 action in the poverty reduction strategies.&#13;
&#13;
            Finally, Directors urged management to move&#13;
&#13;
 quickly to operationalize the approach and to ensure&#13;
&#13;
 effective implementation.&#13;
&#13;
            On the paper, "Strengthening the Link Between&#13;
&#13;
 Debt Relief and Poverty Reduction", Directors endorsed the&#13;
&#13;
 broad and open consultative process undertaken to solicit&#13;
&#13;
 the views of interested parties in the second stage of the&#13;
&#13;
 review of the HIPC Initiative.      They welcomed the wide&#13;
&#13;
 range of comments and proposals received from NGOs,&#13;
                                                               Page141&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 religious groups, international organizations and others.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 These extensive contributions, which have been conveyed in&#13;
&#13;
 full to the Executive Boards of the World Bank and IMF and&#13;
&#13;
 summarized in the HIPC link paper, provide valuable inputs&#13;
&#13;
 into strengthening the link between debt relief and&#13;
&#13;
 poverty reduction.&#13;
&#13;
           Directors fully endorsed the integration of HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 debt relief into comprehensive efforts to reduce poverty&#13;
&#13;
 and the introduction of the poverty reduction strategy&#13;
&#13;
 paper to this effect.    Directors noted that poverty funds&#13;
&#13;
 could provide a vehicle to foster the link between debt&#13;
&#13;
 relief and poverty reduction.      However, they stressed the&#13;
&#13;
 need to ensure that all resources, including amounts&#13;
&#13;
 released by debt relief and new inflows of external&#13;
&#13;
 assistance, were integrated in a transparent, well-managed&#13;
&#13;
 and accountable resource allocation process.&#13;
&#13;
           Directors noted that resources other than debt&#13;
&#13;
 relief would continue to provide the bulk of resources&#13;
&#13;
 available to finance spending on poverty reduction and&#13;
&#13;
 cautioned against poverty funds that were not integrated&#13;
&#13;
 into the wider budgetary process.&#13;
&#13;
           Directors agreed that the poverty reduction&#13;
&#13;
 strategy paper as a tripartite document of the&#13;
                                                                 Page142&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 authorities, the World Bank and the IMF could be a very&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 effective vehicle to ensure the poverty impact of Bank and&#13;
&#13;
 Fund assistance, to link debt relief and poverty reduction&#13;
&#13;
 and to ensure ownership, transparency and broad-based&#13;
&#13;
 participation.&#13;
&#13;
           They noted that moving to the PRSP would take&#13;
&#13;
 time and should be phased in, depending part on the pace&#13;
&#13;
 at which countries can build the relevant capacity.&#13;
&#13;
           Directors also supported the proposal that the&#13;
&#13;
 PRSP should be discussed by the Executive Boards of the&#13;
&#13;
 World Bank and the IMF.&#13;
&#13;
           Directors stressed the importance of the early&#13;
&#13;
 provision of debt relief under the enhanced HIPC&#13;
&#13;
 framework.   They agreed in principle that the poverty&#13;
&#13;
 reduction strategy should be in place when a country&#13;
&#13;
 reached its decision point under the HIPC Initiative, but&#13;
&#13;
 supported the need for flexibility so that the decision&#13;
&#13;
 point could take place while the poverty reduction&#13;
&#13;
 strategy is being formulated, provided the government is&#13;
&#13;
 committed to a firm timetable for the formulation and&#13;
&#13;
 implementation of the strategy which should be in place&#13;
&#13;
 well before the completion point.&#13;
&#13;
           Directors agreed that in HIPCs that have already&#13;
                                                              Page143&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 reached their decision or completion points under the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;[--- Unable To Translate Graphic ---]&#13;
&#13;
 current framework, the timing of the proposed additional&#13;
&#13;
 debt relief should be determined, inter alia, on an&#13;
&#13;
 assessment of their progress in the signing and&#13;
&#13;
 implementing their poverty reduction strategies.&#13;
&#13;
           And finally, Directors supported broad&#13;
&#13;
 dissemination of the two papers.&#13;
&#13;
           Is there anything you want to add, delete or&#13;
&#13;
 change?&#13;
&#13;
           [No response.]&#13;
&#13;
           MR. SANDSTROM:    If not, we will go through this&#13;
&#13;
 and clean it up and make sure that it is clear, not too&#13;
&#13;
 repetitive, and that we have really captured the main&#13;
&#13;
 points.   But I think this is a fair summary.&#13;
&#13;
           We have gone through the written statements as&#13;
&#13;
 well as listened carefully today.&#13;
&#13;
           So, thank you very much.       These have been four&#13;
&#13;
 good hours.   Thank you.   Thanks to the team also.&#13;
&#13;
           [Whereupon, at 5:35 p.m., the meeting was&#13;
&#13;
 adjourned.]&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 Page144&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   MILLER REPORTING COMPANY, INC.&#13;
                         507 C Street, N.E.&#13;
                       Washington, D.C. 20002&#13;
                           (202) 546-6666&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="15512537">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/09/15512537/transcript-meeting-executive-directors-ibrd-ida-held-thursday-september-9-1999-transcript-meeting-executive-directors-ibrd-ida-held-thursday-september-9-1999
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/09/15512537/transcript-meeting-executive-directors-ibrd-ida-held-thursday-september-9-1999-transcript-meeting-executive-directors-ibrd-ida-held-thursday-september-9-1999</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1999/09/15512537/transcript-meeting-executive-directors-ibrd-ida-held-thursday-september-9-1999-transcript-meeting-executive-directors-ibrd-ida-held-thursday-september-9-1999</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2011-11-28T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2016-01-14T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b0828baa59</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0828baa59</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/11/30/000333037_20111130000057/Rendered/INDEX/657720TRANSCRI00disclosed0110280110.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2011/11/30/000333037_20111130000057/Rendered/PDF/657720TRANSCRI00disclosed0110280110.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2011-11-30T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1999-09-09T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of meeting of the Executive
            Directors of the IBRD and IDA, held on Thursday, September
            9, 1999
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This transcript, from the session of the
            Executive Directors of the International Bank on
            Reconstruction and Development and the International
            Development Association held Thursday, September 9, 1999,
            covers only the discussion on meeting of the committee.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of meeting of the Executive
            Directors of the IBRD and IDA, held on Thursday, September
            9, 1999
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of meeting of the
            Executive Directors of the IBRD and IDA, held on Thursday,
            September 9, 1999</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1999/09/15512537/transcript-meeting-executive-directors-ibrd-ida-held-thursday-september-9-1999</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Rural Poverty Reduction,Poverty Monitoring &amp; Analysis,Governance Indicators,Achieving Shared Growth,Regional Economic Development</subtopic>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Governance</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20111130000057</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Board transcript</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Governance</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            access to employment, access to safe
            drinking water, accountability, capacity building, CAS, CG,
            citizens, civil society, country assistance strategies,
            country level, country specific, crises, data collection,
            Debt Relief, determinants of poverty, Developing Countries,
            Development Report, distribution of land, economic
            development, economic growth, economic opportunities,
            economic performance, economic reforms, external shocks,
            financial crisis, financial sector, good governance, growth
            policies, Heavily Indebted Poor Countries, HIPC, income,
            income distribution, indicator of poverty, individual
            countries, industrialized countries, institutional
            arrangements, institutional capacity, INTERNATIONAL
            DEVELOPMENT, international development goals, intervention,
            learning, livelihood, macro stability, macroeconomic
            policies, national policies, operational level, operational
            work, outcome indicators, participatory approach,
            participatory process, participatory processes, policy
            analysis, policy measures, political economy, poverty
            alleviation, poverty alleviation strategies, poverty
            alleviation strategy, poverty assessment, poverty changes,
            poverty goals, poverty impact, poverty indicators, poverty
            line, poverty lines, poverty outcomes, poverty programs,
            Poverty Reduction, poverty reduction efforts, poverty
            reduction programs, Poverty Reduction Strategies, poverty
            reduction strategy, Poverty Reduction Strategy Paper,
            poverty reduction strategy papers, pro-poor, Programs,
            public expenditure, redistribution policies, reducing
            poverty, regional institutions, regional level, service
            delivery, social assessment, social policies, social
            services, structural adjustment, structural adjustment
            programs, structural policies, sustainable growth,
            targeting, transparency, understanding of poverty
        </keywd>
        <owner>Policy and Operations (SECPO)</owner>
        <repnb>65772</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Poverty Reduction Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Strategy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIPC</ml:concept><ml:concept>Measurement and Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Diagnostics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Impact Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Monitoring &amp; Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Monitoring and Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Lines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education and Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Relief</ml:concept><ml:concept>Heavily Indebted Poor Countries (HIPC)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Measurement and Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>