<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>FILE COPY XSWP609&#13;
Shadow Prices for Economic Appraisal&#13;
of Projects&#13;
An Application to Thailand&#13;
Sadiq Ahmed&#13;
WOIRLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 609&#13;
' 1                     1&#13;
_  I~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WRKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 609&#13;
Shadow Prices for Economic Appraisal&#13;
of Projects&#13;
An Application to Thailand&#13;
Sadiq Ahmed&#13;
,tMATIOAL MONETARY FUND&#13;
W4TERNArTOtA~LGAM(Foll&#13;
WASHING   . D.C, 20431&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright ® 1983&#13;
The Intemational Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development / THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
First printing September 1983&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To&#13;
present the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has&#13;
not been prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal&#13;
printed texts, and the World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The&#13;
publication is supplied at a token charge to defray part of the cost of&#13;
manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to&#13;
any individual acting on their behalf. Any maps used have been prepared&#13;
solely for the convenience of the readers; the denominations used and the&#13;
boundaries shown do not imply, on the part of the World Bank and its affiliates,&#13;
any judgment on the legal status of any territory or any endorsement or&#13;
acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications is described in the Catalog of World&#13;
Bank Publications; the continuing research program of the Bank is outlined in&#13;
World Bank Research Program: Abstracts of Current Studies. Both booklets are&#13;
updated annually; the most recent edition of each is available without charge&#13;
from the Publications Distribution Unit of the Bank in Washington or from the&#13;
European-Office of the Bank, 66, avenue d'Iena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Sadiq Ahmed is a country economist in the Europe, Middle East, and North&#13;
Africa Regional Office of the World Bank; he was formerly with the Programs&#13;
Department of the East Asia and Pacific Regional Office.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Ahmed, Sadiq.        ,*C   ,&#13;
Shadow prices for eco       ic;'a}a-isaof proJects,&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 609)&#13;
Includes bibliographical references.&#13;
1. Economic development projects--Thafl-ans--Evalnatioan&#13;
2. Shadow ;rices--4hnlad.p. I'. Title.       II. Series.&#13;
HC445.A55   1983           33805- 2-JAA          83-14620&#13;
ISBN o-82313-C244-2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Abstract&#13;
The study reviews past estimates of shadow prices in Thailand&#13;
and their use in World Bank appraisals. Applying the Squire-van der Tak&#13;
methodology, it proceeds to estimate conversion factors for project analysis&#13;
in Thailand. Efficiency conversion factors were estimated for broad&#13;
categories of commodities, as well as for selected sub-categories, including&#13;
construction, electricity, transportation and rice. Estimates were also&#13;
made of the shadow wage rate and of the opportunity cost of capital and&#13;
land, drawing on an assessment of factor markets in Thailand. An annex&#13;
also provides estimates of social conversion factors allowing for growth&#13;
and income distribution considerations.&#13;
Besides providing up-to-date estimates of shadow prices (conversion&#13;
factors) for use in economic (and social) analysis of projects in Thailand,&#13;
the study provides a case study of application of the Squire-van der Tak&#13;
methodology. It also confirms the findings of other studies that Thailand&#13;
is a country with relatively undistorted prices, as indicated by the fact&#13;
that there is relatively little dispersion in conversion factors and that&#13;
most of them are close to unity.&#13;
Acknowledgments&#13;
This paper is an outcome of my stay in the Thailand/Indochina&#13;
Division of the East Asia and Pacific Programs Department as a Young&#13;
Professional. The study benefitted from comments by Piyasvasti Amranand,&#13;
Dhananjaya Kumar, Johannes Linn, Roy Pepper, and Dusan Vujovic. Cooperation&#13;
from the Department of Customs and the Bank of Thailand during field work&#13;
in Bangkok is gratefully acknowledged.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
I.  INTRODUCTION . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .     1&#13;
Role of Cost-Benefit Analysis   . . . . . . . . . . . . . .    2&#13;
Project Evaluation in Practice .. .   . . . . .  . . . . . .   3&#13;
Scope and Methodology of the Present Study . . . . . . . .     4&#13;
11. REVIEW OF EXISTING SHADOW PRICING STUDIES FOR THAILAND&#13;
AND SUMMARY OF RESULTS . .Ae .RE.T.S. .    ..................  4&#13;
Review of Existing Studies wof  xistinagSa.................    4&#13;
Summary of Results Based on the Present Study  . . . . . .     7&#13;
Limitations of the Present Study.. . . . . . . .. . . .       10&#13;
III.  ESTIMATION OF EFFICIENCY PARAMETERS  . . . . . . . . . . . .    11&#13;
Functioning of Commodity Markets: History   . . . . . . . .    11&#13;
Functioning of Commodity Markets: Efficiency Issue . . . .    12&#13;
Distortionary Effects of Government Policies . . . . . . .     13&#13;
Numerical Estimates of General Conversion Factors   . . . .    16&#13;
Non-Traded Goods Conversion Factor . . . . . . . . . . . .     25&#13;
IV.  ESTIMATION OF ECONOMIC RETURNS TO FACTORS  . . . . . . . . .    30&#13;
The Labor Market: Review of Existing Theories of Wage&#13;
Determination in Developing Countries   . . . . . . . . .    30&#13;
Characteristics of Labor Markets in Thailand . . . . . . .     32&#13;
The Capital Market ...      o .  ....a..a......................  35&#13;
Government Intervention in Financial Markets . . . . . . .     37&#13;
Estimation of Marginal Productivity of Capital . . . , . .     39&#13;
V. ESTIMATION OF CONVERSION FACTOR FOR RICE . . . . . . . . . .      45&#13;
Government Intervention in Rice Trade   . . . . . . . . . .    45&#13;
Estimation of Conversion Factor for Rice . . . . . . . . .     47&#13;
ANNEXES&#13;
A. ESTIMATION OF SOCIAL PARAMETERS   .       .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  . .  . ..  53&#13;
Introduction . .. ... . . . .......................a........     53&#13;
The Government Policy Towards Income Distribution and&#13;
Growth ..................a.............a............ ..C..     53&#13;
Value Judgements: The Consumption Rate of Interest,&#13;
Pure Time Preference, Elasticity of Social Marginal&#13;
Utility of Income  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .    .      55&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Page No.&#13;
The Consumption Distribution Weight . . . . . . . . . . . . . 56&#13;
The Summary Distribution Measure   .  *.......         .. ..      57&#13;
Derivation of Value of Public Income   . . . . . . . . . . . .    59&#13;
The Critical Consumption Level   .     . . .. .. ..... .          61&#13;
The Accounting Rate of Interest . .    . . . .. .... ..      .    64&#13;
The Social Price of Labor ...    ...............                  64&#13;
B.  DATA SOURCES     . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .  66&#13;
C.  ESTIMATION OF TAX EQUIVALENCE OF RICE RESERVE REQUIREMENT . . .     67&#13;
D. ESTIMATION OF SPECIFIC CONVERSION FACTORS USED IN DERIVING&#13;
CONVERSION FACTORS FOR NONTRADED GOODS   . . . . . . . . . . .    68&#13;
Eo AVERAGE CONVERSION FACTORS FOR EXPORTED AND IMPORTED GOODS&#13;
CONSIDERED SEPARATELY ... .      .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .  69&#13;
F. ESTIMATION OF CONVERSION FACTOR FOR RICE WITH LESS THAN&#13;
PERFECTLY ELASTIC WORLD DEMAND FOR RICE AND ALLOWING FOR&#13;
DOMESTIC CONSUMPTION   ... .     .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  o. .  .  .  .   .  70&#13;
G. DATA FOR ESTIMATION OF MARGINAL PROPENSITY TO SAVE .        . . .    71&#13;
H. ECONOMIC VALUE OF LAND    .......           . ........      ..      .  73&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. INTRODUCTION&#13;
1.        Adam Smith,/1 writing in the eighteenth century, argued that under&#13;
a competitive environment individual entrepreneurs left to themselves would&#13;
tend to maximize social welfare at the same time as they seek to maximize&#13;
their own individual welfare. Later, Pareto /2 laid down conditions under&#13;
which individuals' welfare would be maximized. Other classical economists&#13;
pointed out that a perfectly competitive economy would satisfy these&#13;
conditions. Stronger advocates of the market mechanism extended the Pareto&#13;
approach to argue that under a competitive system not only would private&#13;
welfare be maximized, but also social welfare would be maximized. By&#13;
implication, the set of prices generated by a competitive economy would be&#13;
'optimal.'&#13;
2.        Pigou was one of the earliest critics of the optimality of market&#13;
solution./3 He pointed out that the competitive solution would not be optimal&#13;
since it does not take into account the 'externalities in the system.    Other&#13;
criticisms include, neglect of the issue of income distribution, indeter-&#13;
minacy in the Pareto approach, i.e., a large number of soluti.ns, presence&#13;
of natural monopolies and public goods, and absence of perfect information.&#13;
Further complications arise when the issue of deducing the social welfare&#13;
function is raised. One line of argument is that the social welfare&#13;
function can be formulated through the political voting procedure. But in a&#13;
powerful work Arrow /4, himself a firm believer in the efficiency of the&#13;
market economy, came up with the paradoxical result that majority decisions&#13;
need not be consistent. Thus, a social welfare function generated by&#13;
majority decisions would not necessarily satisfy the consistency property -&#13;
a characteristic necessary to obtain meaningful results. Hence, the&#13;
quantities and prices obtaining in the market solution are not necessarily&#13;
the optimal ones.&#13;
3.        A second type of problem with the market solution is that in&#13;
practice all countries of the world have government interventions in the&#13;
economy. Such interventions have often created further distortions in the&#13;
economy. This is another reason why market solution may yield inoptimal&#13;
prices and quantities.&#13;
/1 Adam Smith, An Inquiry into the Nature and Causes of the Wealth of&#13;
Nations, Vol. 1, Dent., 1933.&#13;
/2 Vilfredo Pareto, Manual d'economie publique, Girard, Paris 1909.&#13;
/3 A.C. Pigou, The Economics of Welfare, Macmillan, 4th ed. 1932.&#13;
/4 K.J. Arrow, Social Choice and Individual Values, Wiley, 1951.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2-&#13;
Role of Cost-Benefit Analysis&#13;
4.        Critics of the market solution have provided justification for&#13;
government investment in the economy. But investible resources are limited&#13;
relative to the number of activities possible and market prices are inappro-&#13;
priate, hence some decision rules for public investment are required.&#13;
Economists have, therefore, devised techniques for making investment&#13;
decisions. Such techniques, broadly known as Cost-Benefit analysis, have&#13;
two main parts: identifying benefit and cost streams, and devising appro-&#13;
priate value weights for determining social profitability. While the&#13;
objective of Cost-Benefit analysis is fairly simple and convincing-maximize&#13;
net social welfare from any project, the welfare base of the appropriate&#13;
weights (prices) and methodology for deriving these weights remain highly&#13;
controversial issues.&#13;
5.        A more serious issue raised by a number of critics of Cost-Benefit&#13;
analysis concerns its logic. If all distortions in the economy are&#13;
corrected, then prices derived from this simulated competitive economy are&#13;
called the 'first best shadow prices.' Cost-Benefit analysis does not seek&#13;
to derive these set of prices because it recognizes that in practice all&#13;
distortions cannot be corrected. What it aims at is deriving the second&#13;
best shadow prices by assuming some constraints as fixed and correcting for&#13;
other distortions. In 1956 Lipsey and Lancaster/l derived a devastating&#13;
theorem known as the "general theory of second best" which says that any&#13;
move which corrects for some distortions but leaves unchanged other&#13;
distortions does not necessarily constitute an improvement in welfare. A&#13;
related criticism made by Rudra /2 is that optimal projects and optimal&#13;
prices are interdependent and can only be derived simultaneously. Hence,&#13;
prices derived separately from the choice of optimal projects will not&#13;
necessarily be optimal. Both arguments are valid in a puristic sense. The&#13;
defense of supporters of Cost-Benefit analysis is that it is a pragmatic&#13;
approach to planning and in practice corrections for some distortions, even&#13;
if other distortions remain uncorrected, are more likely to result in an&#13;
improvement rather than further deterioration in welfare. As Sen /3 has&#13;
/1  R.G. Lipsey and R.K. Lancaster, "The General Theory of Second Best,"&#13;
Review of Economic Studies, Vol. XXIV(1), 1956-7.&#13;
/2 A. Rudra, "Use of Shadow Prices in Project Evaluation," paper presented&#13;
at the World Econometric Congress, Cambridge 1970.&#13;
/3 A.K. Sen, "Interrelations Between Project, Sector and Aggregate&#13;
Planning," Economic Bulletin for the Asia and Pacific, UN, ESCAP,&#13;
Bangkok, 1970.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
argued: "Even in many-commodity models it is not at all obvious why these&#13;
improvements will not operate, but it is possible to think of a complex of&#13;
relationships that would make these corrections have a negative impact on&#13;
social welfare. What is at issue in all these cases is the practical&#13;
relevance of rules that work with sure-fire efficacy in models involving&#13;
some abstraction, the real world does have features that do not figure in&#13;
these models. This is a general problem to which all analytical planning&#13;
techniques are exposed, and the use of shadow prices in project evaluation&#13;
is no exception."&#13;
project Evaluation in Practice&#13;
6.        A large number of economists have contributed to the development&#13;
of analytical tools of Cost-Benefit analysis. Most studies have, however,&#13;
dealt with one aspect or another in isolation. Three well known and&#13;
complete works on project evaluation in developing countries are those of&#13;
Little and Mirrlees /1, Dasgupta, Sen and Marglin /2 and Squire and van der&#13;
Tak./3 Since 1971 the first two groups of authors have been pitched against&#13;
each other in a series of debates concerning the proposal made by Little and&#13;
Mirrlees (L-M) that world prices be used as appropriate shadow prices. The&#13;
main objection raised by Dasgupta, Sen and Marglin (UNIDO) is that use of&#13;
world prices assumes that the project evaluator can persuade governments of&#13;
developing countries to follow trade policies such that there are no&#13;
quantitative restrictions - a questionable assumption for most developing&#13;
countries.&#13;
7.        The Squire and van der Tak (S-T) method is essentially an exten-&#13;
sion of the L-M approach, going one step forward. Like the L-M approach, it&#13;
also advocates use of world prices as appropriate shadow prices, but takes&#13;
into account the criticism of the trade policy assumption by arguing that&#13;
should project evaluator fail to influence the government to remove&#13;
quantitative restrictions, such commodities be treated as nontraded and&#13;
valued differently i.e., according to their social marginal cost or social&#13;
marginal benefit or a weighted average of the two. The S-T approach goes&#13;
further by explicitly introducing income distribution consideration in&#13;
/L  I.M.D. Little and J.A. Mirrlees, Project Appraisal and Planning for&#13;
Developing Countries, Basic Books, Inc., New York, 1974.&#13;
/2  UNIDO, Guidelines for Project Evaluation, written by P.S. Dasgupta,&#13;
A.K. Sen, and S.A. Marglin, United Nations, New York 1968.&#13;
/3  Lyn Squire and H. G. van der Tak, Economic Analysis of Projects,&#13;
John Hopkins University Press, Baltimore, 1975.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
deriving shadow prices. The authors suggest a two-step procedure. In step&#13;
one the "efficiency prices" are derived - so called because these are&#13;
obtained on the basis of resource allocation considerations only. In step&#13;
two considerations of income distribution are introduced and efficiency&#13;
prices are converted into "social prices." The implicit assumption is that&#13;
the resultant income redistribution does not have significant feed-back&#13;
effects on the efficiency component of the shadow prices. Apart from this&#13;
innovation, the other advantage of the S-T approach is that it is relatively&#13;
simple and less demanding in practical work.&#13;
Scope and Methodology of the Present Study&#13;
8.        The objective of this paper is to apply the S-T methodology for&#13;
deriving conversion factors (ratio of shadow prices to domestic prices) for&#13;
Thailand. Following the S-T classification, distinction is made between&#13;
efficiency prices and social prices. Further, estimation of conversion&#13;
factors relevant for the economy as a whole - known as national level&#13;
parameters, is the main topic of discussion. Conversion factors by specific&#13;
commodities, except rice, are not considered here.&#13;
9.        The study is organized as follows.   In Part II, earlier works on&#13;
shadow prices in Thailand are briefly discussed and the summary results of&#13;
the present study are presented. Estimation of efficiency conversion&#13;
factors is considered in Part III. The discussion in this Part is divided&#13;
into two sections. In the first section, estimation of general conversion&#13;
factors for traded and nontraded goods is considered, while in the second&#13;
section, the estimation of marginal productivity of capital and shadow wage&#13;
rate is discussed. Derivation of conversion factor for rice is discussed in&#13;
Part IV. This commodity is given special attention in view of the contro-&#13;
versy over the Thai government's rice trade policy. Social parameters are&#13;
considered in Annex I. Other annexes containing data and sources and&#13;
additional notes follow the presentation of the discussion on social&#13;
parameters.&#13;
II. REVIEW OF EXISTING SHADOW PRICING STUDIES&#13;
FOR THAILAND AND SUMMARY OF RESULTS&#13;
Review of Existing Studies&#13;
10.       There are at least three studies directly concerned with the esti-&#13;
mation of shadow prices in Thailand. The first work was undertaken by&#13;
McCleary /1 in 1973. The study derived shadow prices based on the UNIDO&#13;
methodology. The second study was prepared by the Mekong Secretariat under&#13;
/1 W.A. McCleary, Equipment Versus Employment: A Social Cost-Benefit&#13;
Analysis of Alternative Techniques of Feeder Road Construction of&#13;
Thailand, ILO, Geneva, 1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
the sponsorship of UN ESCAP./1 This is a fairly elaborate piece of work&#13;
based on the L-M methodology, and it derived general conversion factors as&#13;
well as a fairly large number of specific conversion factors. The study,&#13;
however, did not attempt any social pricing exercise. The third work was&#13;
done by Collin Bruce /2 as a part of World Bank sponsored studies on the&#13;
application of the S-T methodology in a number of countries. The results&#13;
are summarized in Table 1.&#13;
Table 1:  SUMMARY OF CONVERSION FACTORS DERIVED IN EARLIER STUDIES&#13;
Colin Bruce's Study    Lower Mekong   Mccleary's&#13;
Alt.    Alt.    Alt.    Basin Study     study&#13;
1       2       3&#13;
Standard Conversion&#13;
Factor (SCF)                  0.918   0.878   0.79       0.791         0.87&#13;
Consumption Goods Conver-       0.881   0.923   0.96       0.96           -&#13;
sion Factor (CGCF)&#13;
Intermediate Goods Conver-&#13;
sion Factor (IGCF)              -       -       -        0.86           -&#13;
Capital Goods Conversion&#13;
Factor (KGCF)                 0.942   0.866   0.82       0.82           -&#13;
Construction Conversion&#13;
Factor (CCF)                    -       -       -        0.74           -&#13;
Electricity Conversion&#13;
Factor (ECF)                  0.93    0.871  1,276      1.276           -&#13;
Labor Conversion Factor for&#13;
Unskilled Workers (LCF)         -       -       -       0.380        0.91-1.15&#13;
Marginal Productivity of&#13;
Capital (q)                   0.15    0.15    0.15       N.A.           0.225&#13;
Rice Conversion Factor (RCF)      -       -       -        1.482            -&#13;
/1  UN ESCAP, Guidelines for the Economic Appraisal of Projects in the&#13;
Lower Mekong Basin, Vol. II: Calculation of Conversion Factors for&#13;
Thailand, Bangkok 1975 (Draft).&#13;
/2  Collin Bruce, Social Cost-Benefit Analysis:   A Guide for Country and&#13;
Project Economists to the Derivation and Application of Economic and&#13;
Social Accounting Prices; World Bank Staff Working Paper, No. 239, 1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
11.       Alternatives 1 and 2 in Bruce's work were derived independently of&#13;
the Mekong study. Alternative 3 is based on the Mekong Basin study. The&#13;
main reason for differences between alternatives 1 and 2 is use of number of&#13;
years for which the trade data were averaged to derive the conversion&#13;
factors, ranging from 5 to 8 years for alternative 1, and 3 to 5 years for&#13;
alternative 2. The differences between Bruce's results and Mekong results&#13;
are partly explained by differences in time period, and partly by the fact&#13;
that the later study involved a higher level of disaggregation. The&#13;
differences are particularly large in the cases of electricity conversion&#13;
factor and standard conversion factor (SCF). In the Lower Mekong Basin&#13;
study the SCF was derived as a weighted average of a large number of&#13;
conversion factors for traded and nontraded items, whereas in Bruce's work&#13;
(for both alternatives) the SCF is based entirely on traded goods. The high&#13;
value of conversion factor for electricity derived in the Mekong study&#13;
appears implausible. The authors overestimated the border price value of&#13;
"profit and other value added" component of the input-output coefficient&#13;
structure of electricity by using a conversion factor greater than unity.&#13;
If this component is converted into border price terms by applying the SCF,&#13;
the conversion factor for electricity falls dramatically to 0.776.&#13;
12.       In McCleary's work, the ratio of shadow exchange rate to the&#13;
official exchange rate (SER/OER), obtained as a weighted average of the&#13;
effective tariff rates on imports and tax rates on exports, was estimated&#13;
1&#13;
as 1.15. The value of SCF (SER/OER) is, therefore, very close to Bruce's&#13;
estimate. The significant difference in the marginal productivity of&#13;
capital (q) estimates is explained by the fact that while McCleary esti-&#13;
mated q by using various sources of information, Bruce simply assumed a&#13;
value for q. The results for labor conversion factor (LCF) obtained by&#13;
McCleary and the Lower Mekong Basin study are not directly comparable&#13;
because they are based on different methodologies. Nevertheless, it should&#13;
be noted that the later study assumed significant labor market imperfections&#13;
while McCleary took the view that labor market imperfections were small.&#13;
13.       Apart from these three studies, some information on shadow&#13;
prices in Thailand is also available from various Bank project appraisal&#13;
reports. These reports shed some light on three conversion factors which&#13;
are of interest for this study. These are LCF, SCF and rice conversion&#13;
factor (RCF). The information is summarized in Table 2.&#13;
14.       In most appraisal reports, estimates of SCF and consumption goods&#13;
conversion factor (CGCF) are based on Bruce's work i.e., SCF = 0.79 and&#13;
CGCF = 0.96. The values of 0.91-0.92 for SCF used in a number of reports&#13;
are based on the assumption that the exchange rate is overvalued by 9-10&#13;
percent. The source of this latter assumption is not mentioned. The two&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 2: SUMMARY OF CONVERSION FACTORS USED IN VARIOUS&#13;
BANK APPRAISAL REPORTS&#13;
Bank Report No.        Date          CGCF      SCF          LCF          RCF&#13;
(unskilled)&#13;
No. 867-TH       March 1976            -       0.91          1.00&#13;
No. 1530-TH       September 1977       -         -           0.50          -&#13;
No. 1412-a-TH     June 1977          0.96      0.79          0.40        1.27&#13;
No. 2622-TH       November 1979      0.96      0.79          0.96          -&#13;
No. 2269-TH      May       1979        -       0.92          0.90        1.36&#13;
No. 2704-TH       February 1980        -       0.92          0.90        1.40&#13;
No. 2568a-TH     October   1979        -       0.91          0.50          -&#13;
No. 1901-TH      October 1978        0.96      0.79          0.50        1.19&#13;
No. 3223-TH      January 1981          -       0.79          0.96          -&#13;
No. 3277-TH       June 1981          0.96      0.79          0.96        1.41&#13;
No. 3040a-TH      July 1981          0.96      0.79          0.96          -&#13;
Staff Working&#13;
Paper No. 385   April 1980            -         -           1.16        1.68&#13;
main reasons for differences in the RCF are the number of adjustments made&#13;
and the timing of calculations.   In all reports it is implicitly assumed&#13;
that Thailand has a perfectly elastic world demand curve for rice. But some&#13;
reports did not consider the effect of reserve requirement, and, therefore,&#13;
obtained a lower value for RCF. There is a big difference in the treatment&#13;
of unskilled labor. Some reports assumed efficient labor markets and set&#13;
the LCF equal to the CGCF. Others assumed presence of labor market imperfec-&#13;
tions and as such derived LCF in the range of 0.4 to 0.5. The one study&#13;
which reported LCF exceeding unity assumed that the marginal productivity&#13;
of labor in agriculture is underestimated by the market wage rate due to&#13;
divergence between world price of rice and domestic price of rice caused by&#13;
the Thai government's rice trade policy. This logic is entirely different&#13;
from the logic behind McCleary's estimate of LCF greater than unity.&#13;
Summary of Results Based on the Present Study&#13;
15.       The central values of parameters and the sensitivity range&#13;
estimated in the present study are summarized in Table 3. There are a&#13;
number of differences between these results and earlier results presented in&#13;
Table 1. We would first compare the present results with those obtained in&#13;
Collin Bruce's study, since both studies follow the same methodology and the&#13;
main difference is time period. The Bruce study assumed that Thailand is a&#13;
price taker in the world market for all exports and imports. If we make the&#13;
same assumption, then a comparison of the SCF shows that the present estimate&#13;
(0.94) is closer to unity than the estimates obtained by Bruce (0.92 under&#13;
alternative I and 0.88 under alternative II), implying that the average level&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
of distortion is lower now than in the past. The CGCF estimate also&#13;
reflects the liberalization tendency. The value of CGCF, under small&#13;
country assumption, obtained in this study is 0.98, which is higher than&#13;
0.88 under alternative I and 0.92 under alternative II obtained by Bruce.&#13;
The KGCF estimate, however, does not provide a clear indication. If we&#13;
exclude imported vehicles from the category of capital goods, as was done in&#13;
the other study, the value of KGCF is 0.874 (not shown in Table 3) which is&#13;
Table 3: SUMMARY OF OWUNTRY PARAMETERS FOR THAILAND (1980)&#13;
Central      Sensitivity&#13;
Efficiency Pricing Parameters                    value           range&#13;
Standard Conversion Factor (SCF)                  0.92       0.91  -   0.94&#13;
Consumption Goods Conversion Factof (CGCF)        0.95       0.77   -  0.98&#13;
Intermediate Goods Conversion Factor (IGCF)       0.94        0.90  -  1.09&#13;
Capital Goods Conversion Factor (KGCF)            0.84        0.83  -  0.96&#13;
Construction Conversion Factor (CCF)              0.88        0.86  -  0.92&#13;
Electricity Conversion Factor (ECF)               0.90        0.88  -  0.93&#13;
Transportation Conversion Factor (TCF)            0.87        0.85  -  0.90&#13;
Labor Conversion Factor (LCF)                     0.92        0.91  -  0.94&#13;
Marginal Productivity of Capital (q)              0.16        0.12  -  0.20&#13;
Rice Conversion Factor (RCF)                      1.11        0.92  -  1.49&#13;
slightly higher than 0.866 under alternative II but lower than 0.942 under&#13;
alternative I in the Bruce study. The value of q obtained in this study is&#13;
also higher than the value given in the other study. The comparison,&#13;
however, does not provide any useful information because the other study&#13;
simply assumed a value of q equal to 0.15 which, incidentally, turned out to&#13;
be close to the value of 0.16 derived in this study.&#13;
16.       When the results of this study are compared with the results of&#13;
the Lower Mekong Basin study, the differences are partly due to timing and&#13;
partly attributable to the higher level of disaggregation followed in the&#13;
latter study. For example, the lower value of SCF obtained in the Mekong&#13;
study is partly due to the fact that it was estimated as a weighted average&#13;
of a large number of traded and nontraded specific commodity conversion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 - -&#13;
factors, whereas in this study the SCF is based entirely on traded goods. The&#13;
value of ECF is lower in this study because of differences in calculation&#13;
referred to above. The low value of LCF obtained in the Mekong study is based&#13;
on the assumption that agricultural labor markets are highly imperfect in&#13;
Thailand. The present study takes the position that labor markets are&#13;
reasonably efficient and the only reason why LCF is not equal to unity is&#13;
because of distortions in the product market as reflected by the average&#13;
conversion factors. In this study the SCF is taken as a proxy for the&#13;
accounting ratio required to convert labor's marginal product in efficiency&#13;
price terms. The value of LCF for a specific project may also be greater than&#13;
unity. This would happen for example, if labor is withdrawn from a sector&#13;
which has high export taxes that cannot be justified as optimal. In this case&#13;
the accounting factor for converting labor's marginal product into efficiency&#13;
units would be greater than unity. This is the logic used in Staff Working&#13;
Paper No. 385 in deriving LCF equal to 1.16 (Table 2).&#13;
17.       The results in the McCleary study are based on different&#13;
methodology. The value of SCF and q are, however, comparable. The higher&#13;
value of SCF in the present study reflects a lower level of average distor-&#13;
tion. So far as the value of q is concerned, the lower estimate obtained in&#13;
this study is partly due to the fact that q is expressed in border price terms&#13;
whereas in the McCleary study q was expressed in domestic currency unit, and&#13;
partly because the estimation procedure is somewhat different. The LCF value&#13;
obtained in this study is not comparable with the McCleary study because of&#13;
differences in methodology.&#13;
18.       Neither the Bruce study nor the Mekong study allowed for the&#13;
possibility that Thailand may have some monopoly power in its major export -&#13;
rice. This is done in the present study. The central values of SCF and CGCF&#13;
are based on this more realistic assumption. The assumption is critical, in&#13;
particular, for the estimation of RCF and LCF specific to the rice sector. As&#13;
shown in Table 3, under small country assumption, the value of RCF is 1.49.&#13;
When it is assumed that the world demand elasticity for Thai rice is (-) 4.0&#13;
(based on an empirical study), rather than infinity, the RCF falls&#13;
dramatically to 1.11. Although a more careful study is required to obtain a&#13;
firm estimate for the world demand elasticity for Thai rice and the estimate&#13;
would need to be revised from time to time, the assumption of perfectly&#13;
elastic world demand for Thai rice is not satisfactory.&#13;
19.       It may also be useful to see how the important parameter values&#13;
for Thailand compare with corresponding estimates for other developing&#13;
countries. The inter-country comparisons are conducted in terms of the SCF&#13;
and the LCF (Table 4). In a crude sense, other things being equal, the&#13;
higher the SCF, the smaller the distorting-influence of trade tariffs and&#13;
subsidies. Thus, Thailand may be regarded as the least protected economy in&#13;
this sample and Turkey as the most protected. Although the estimates do not&#13;
correpond to the same time period, these results are in accord with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
preconceived notions. Similarly, the higher the LCF, the more likely it is&#13;
that the labor market works efficiently. Once again, the value of the LCF&#13;
indicates that the labor market in Thailand is relatively more efficient&#13;
than labor markets in other countries in the sample.&#13;
Table 4: CROSS-COUNTRY COMPARISON OF IWO IMPORTANT NATIONAL PARAMETERS&#13;
Parameters/country          SCF        LCF&#13;
Turkey (1980)              0.59       0.39&#13;
Morocco (1979)             0.60       0.51&#13;
Ghana (1975)               0.75        NA&#13;
Tanzania (1974)            0.77       0.45&#13;
Ivory Coast (1977)         0.83       0.83&#13;
Malaysia (1976)            0.85       0.42&#13;
Colombia (1979) /a         0.90       0.58&#13;
Philippines (1976)         0.91        NA&#13;
Thailand (1981)            0.92       0.92&#13;
/a  Based on trade data approach for&#13;
comparability.&#13;
Limitations of the Present Study&#13;
20.       There are a number of limitations of the present study.    First,&#13;
the conversion factors are based on current and past data. The values,&#13;
therefore, reflect the present distortions. No attempt is made to project&#13;
future distortions. The justification for use of these parameters in the&#13;
economic analysis of projects in the future is based on the assumption that&#13;
the government would continue to pursue the present policies, mainly in&#13;
respect of trade policies, for a number of years. Any major policy change&#13;
affecting the present trade regime would require a re-estimation of most&#13;
conversion factors. Second, it was not possible to check on the accuracy of&#13;
the CGCF by using a more disaggregated approach, since relevant income-&#13;
expenditure data for consumers were not available. Third, the estimation of&#13;
q involves a number of approximations which may have an adverse effect on&#13;
the accuracy of this estimate. Fourth, the values for CFR are based on the&#13;
present rice export tax structure and available evidence on the relevant&#13;
elasticity parameters. Since the Thai government's rice export policy has&#13;
undergone frequent changes in the past, it is expected that there would be&#13;
changes in the future as well. Moreover, the elasticity estimates are&#13;
illustrative rather than definitive. Hence, for both reasons, the value of&#13;
CFR would need to be estimated in the context of specific projects.&#13;
Finally, the SCF is used in this study as a proxy for the accounting ratio&#13;
required to convert labors marginal product at market prices into border&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-11 -&#13;
price terms. In actual project analysis the accounting ratio would depend on&#13;
the distortions specific to the sector from which labor is withdrawn.&#13;
III. ESTIMATION OF EFFICIENCY PARAMETERS&#13;
Functioning of Commodity Markets: History&#13;
21.       Any discussion on the structure of commodity markets in Thailand and&#13;
the role of government therein would be incomplete without reference to past&#13;
economic history. Since the early times, the market mechanism has been the&#13;
dominant force in the evolution of the Thai economy. The Thai government did&#13;
not attempt to impede the functioning of the market mechanism; on the&#13;
contrary, it helped promote active competition in the economy.&#13;
22.       From the point of view of development of commodity markets, the&#13;
signing of the Bowring Treaty in 1855 between King Mongkut of Thailand and&#13;
Great Britain probably marks a watershed. The treaty not only exposed&#13;
Thailand to the west, it also imposed a regime of free trade - both internally&#13;
as well as externally. The mobility of goods across borders also had a&#13;
favorable impact on the extent of monetization in the economy.&#13;
23.       Two other developments during the reigns of Mongkut and his son&#13;
Chulalongkorn - know as the "modern monarchs", had significant impact on the&#13;
economy. The first development was the abolishment of 'Corvee'/2 and slavery&#13;
systems.  This measure had two types of effects.   First, the Thai farmers&#13;
became free to engage themselves fully on their own land as well as to explore&#13;
new lands and second, the demand for wage labor increased rapidly which&#13;
attracted new streams of Chinese migrants. The later effect increased the&#13;
competition in internal and external trading as the new immigrants sought to&#13;
exploit the available opportunities while at the same time internal mobility&#13;
of goods and services was promoted through increased monetization and the&#13;
development of transportation system.&#13;
24.       The second important development during this period was the crea-&#13;
tion of a government structure to administer the nation. In the absence of&#13;
/1 The discussion on Thailand's economic history is based on the following&#13;
works: Dole A. Anderson, Marketing and Development: The Thailand&#13;
Experience, Michigan State University, International Business and&#13;
Economic Studies, East Lansing, 1970; T.H. Silcock, The Economic&#13;
Development of Thai Agriculture, Cornell University Press, 1970.&#13;
/2 A system of compulsory labor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
an administrative machinery, the government was forced to "farm out" the&#13;
collection of taxes. The introduction of direct collection by the govern-&#13;
ment in 1892 increased tax collections three-fold in a decade even without&#13;
imposition of new taxes. At the same time the Thai government became&#13;
increasingly concerned about the growing power of the Chinese community.&#13;
Beginning in the 1930's a number of laws were passed which attempted to&#13;
restrict the Chinese economic power. Such laws included the requirement to&#13;
employ a minimum proportion of Thai citizens in certain activities and&#13;
barring alien participation in a number of important activities, including&#13;
rice cultivation. The impact of these controls, however, was rather limited&#13;
due to the enforcement problem. This, however, provided incentives to the&#13;
aliens to get assimilated in the Thai society by becoming citizens.&#13;
25.       A second type of response of the government was the creation of&#13;
State-owned enterprise, on a limited scale, to provide competition to the&#13;
private sector and to provide employment to Thai nationals. But once&#13;
created, unfortunately, these public enterprises increasingly became&#13;
important sources of income and patronage to the politicians and bureaucrats&#13;
associated with the management of these enterprises.&#13;
26.       Apart from these small-order interventions, traditionally the&#13;
government's role in the economy has been to create an environment favorable&#13;
to the growth of private enterprises. Moreover, the objective of the above&#13;
interventions was to limit the economic power of any one group so that more&#13;
competition may be possible. But, beginning in the early 1960s, the&#13;
government decided to play a more active role in the economy. The concern&#13;
was generated by a rather unsatisfactory progress in the industrial sector.&#13;
The first development plan was launched in 1961. Although the stated&#13;
objectives in this Plan and other successive Plans, maintained that the&#13;
government's role is to promote private enterprise through profit incentives&#13;
and more efficient functioning of the market mechanism, these Plans mark the&#13;
beginning of the period of significant government interventions in the Thai&#13;
economic history. Even now, however, direct participation in economic&#13;
activity is very small relative to most developing countries of the world.&#13;
Functioning of Commodity Markets: Efficiency Issue&#13;
27.       Marketing Channels in Industry. In the Industry sector there are&#13;
three distribution channels - wholesalers, retailers and direct consumers.&#13;
Although distribution through wholesalers and retailers is dominant relative&#13;
to direct sales to consumers, there is no clear evidence on the relative&#13;
ranking of wholesale distribution versus retail distribution. There is some&#13;
evidence that smaller industrial firms sell less of their outputs to&#13;
wholesalers and more to retailers or directly to consumers than do larger&#13;
firms. There are however no documented allegations concerning inefficiency&#13;
in the distribution of industrial goods. The number of firms engaged in&#13;
trading (wholesale or retail) is sufficiently large to ensure significant&#13;
competition amongst traders.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
28.       Marketing Channels in Agriculture.   The first transaction in the&#13;
agricultural channel occurs on the farm or in the village. The farmer does&#13;
not transport his crop to the market, rather, the middleman seeks out the&#13;
farmer and purchases his produce. The first middleman collects small&#13;
quantities from individual farmers and transports them to the district or&#13;
provincial centers where he sells to the second middleman or to the&#13;
processing mill.&#13;
29.       In view of the presence of a chain of middlemen, concern has been&#13;
raised about the efficiency of agricultural marketing system. A number of&#13;
critics believe that farmers are exploited. There is, however, very little&#13;
evidence to support this allegation./l There are some problems with the&#13;
distribution of fertilizer. But marketing of agricultural output is&#13;
reasonably efficient. The two main reasons why exploitation is unlikely to&#13;
be significant are: first, there are a large number of traders competing&#13;
with each other and second, there is an excellent transportation network in&#13;
Thailand.&#13;
30.       Special Role of Development of Transportation. Few other govern-&#13;
ment programs have had as large a role in integrating the Thai economy as the&#13;
development of a network of roadways. The effect on the operation of the&#13;
commodity markets has been dramatic. Wrote Anderson, "the resulting revolu-&#13;
tion in mobility has made possible for the first time in Thailand's history&#13;
a national market for a variety of consumers goods. It is true that for&#13;
centuries imported goods have been carried to all parts of the Kingdom by&#13;
itinerant traders, but the high cost of transportation by animals, bicycles,&#13;
and human backs restricted the flow of goods to a trickle. What has changed&#13;
with lower-cost, year-round road transport is the volume of the flow and in&#13;
consequence, the roles of the existing marketing agencies and sectors"&#13;
(p. 139)./2   And further, "evidence suggests that for consumer goods the&#13;
traditional pattern of higher prices with increasing distance from Bangkok&#13;
is giving way to uniform prices to retailers throughout the national&#13;
territory" (p. 145) ./2&#13;
Distortionary Effects of Government Policies&#13;
31.       While the government's transportation program has helped promote&#13;
competition, a number of government policies have introduced distortion in the&#13;
/1 In particular see: Millard F. Long and Channond Aranjakonda, "Rice&#13;
Marketing in Thailand," Bangkok Bank Monthly Review, Vol. 4, July&#13;
1963, pp. 19-25; and also: William I. Baldwin, "The Thai Rice Trade&#13;
as a Vertical Market Network: Structure, Performance and Policy&#13;
Implications," Economic Development and Cultural Change, Vol.22, No. 2,&#13;
January 1974; pp. 79-97.&#13;
/2 Anderson, op. cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
commodities market. These policies are classified into four groups: (1)&#13;
Trade taxes, (2) domestic taxes, (3) quantitative restrictions and (4)&#13;
price controls and subsidies.&#13;
32.       Trade Taxes.   The two categories of trade taxes are (1) taxes on&#13;
imports and (2) taxes on exports: On the export side only agricultural&#13;
commodities are subject to export taxes.&#13;
33.       Agricultural Export Taxes.   The distortionary impact of agricul-&#13;
tural export taxes has been hotly debated, mainly in respect of Thailand's&#13;
major agricultural product 'rice.' At the one extreme there is the view&#13;
that "the most important form of government intervention in the rural&#13;
economy has been through restricting access to world markets for the major&#13;
agricultural products, mainly via export taxation of rice and rubber."/1 On&#13;
the other side there is the view that "Thailand is in the rather peculiar&#13;
position of being one of the largest rice exporters but not amongst the&#13;
largest producers. Although under free trade Thailand could not be expected&#13;
to have any appreciable influence on world prices, it does exercise some&#13;
monopoly power under existing conditions in the international market. The&#13;
export premium could therefore be justified as an optimal export tax on&#13;
rice."/2 Since the concern is only in respect of rice taxation, it will be&#13;
discussed in some greater detail in the section dealing with conversion&#13;
factor for rice. For the present, the issue of optimal tax on rice export&#13;
is ignored and it is assumed that agricultural taxation introduces&#13;
distortion by driving a wedge between world prices and domestic prices of&#13;
taxed commodities.&#13;
34.       Only two major agricultural crops are subject to export taxes -&#13;
rice and rubber. The main types of explicit taxes on rice are: (1) The&#13;
export tax and (2) the rice premium. In addition, there is an important&#13;
form of implicit taxation on rice which is known as the 'rice reserve&#13;
requirement'. The main tax on rubber is the export tax. There is also a tax&#13;
called the 'cess.' The proceeds of the cess goes to the Rubber Replanting&#13;
Aid Fund to finance rubber replanting. Hence, in effect the cess does not&#13;
constitute a tax.&#13;
/1 Trend Bertrand, Thailand: Case Study of Agricultural Input and Output&#13;
Pricing, World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 385, Washington, April&#13;
1980, p. 39.&#13;
/2 George S. Tolley et. al. Agricultural Price Policies and the Developing&#13;
Countries.  The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1982, pp. 96-97.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
_ 15 _&#13;
35.       Tariff Policy.   On the import side the main type of government&#13;
intervention is impositon of tariffs on different categories of imports.&#13;
As a rule all types of imports are subject to taxation. However, imported&#13;
inputs entering manufactured exports are allowed exemptions through the&#13;
'Export Tax Rebate' and the 'Import Drawback Scheme.'&#13;
36.       Domestic Taxes.   The three main domestic taxes are (1) excise&#13;
tax, (2) business tax and (3) municipal tax. Since the excise tax is&#13;
imposed on both domestically produced goods as well as imported goods and&#13;
part of the objective is to correct for externalities (i.e. tax on liquor&#13;
and tobacco), it is rather difficult to determine its distortionary effect.&#13;
Therefore, following L-M suggestion, it is assumed that these taxes are&#13;
"corrective" rather than distortionary./l Most goods, whether imported or&#13;
domestically produced, are subject to business and municipal taxes. In&#13;
addition, there are some local taxes which, however, are ignored in this&#13;
study as negligible.&#13;
37.       Quantitative Restrictions.   In general, quantitative restrictions on&#13;
trade are selective and, for most items, of limited duration.   The aggregate&#13;
impact is not likely to be significant. The main quantitative restriction&#13;
is in the form of export and/or import quotas. The export quota restriction&#13;
has played an important role only for cassava exports, the quota restriction,&#13;
in the first instance, being imposed by the main importing bloclc - the&#13;
EEC./2 On the import side, the two most important quantitative restriction&#13;
are the ban on imports of fully assembled cars and the requirement to have a&#13;
minimum domestic input content in car manufacturing./3&#13;
38.       Three other forms of nonprice intervention are: the government to&#13;
government (G to G) sales of rice, the restriction on the establishment of&#13;
sugar mills, and restrictions on private slaughterhouses. The distortionary&#13;
effects of these policies are rather difficult to measure. But, the&#13;
aggregate distortionary impact is not likely to be significant.&#13;
/1  Little-Mirrlees take an even stronger view.   "In general we would&#13;
regard taxes on goods sold to final consumers as 'corrective:' meaning&#13;
by this that the net-of-taxes price is a better measure of the social&#13;
value of the good than market price." See Little-Mirrlees, op. cit,&#13;
p. 224.&#13;
/2  For detailed discussion on quantitative restrictions on export, see&#13;
Trent Bertrand, op. cit.&#13;
/3  See:  Back round Paper:   Thailand's Industrial Sector:  The Changing&#13;
Role ot Poicies to the    eport:  Thailand - Toward a Development Strategy&#13;
of Full Participation, World Bank Country Study, March 1980.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
39.       Price Controls and Subsidies:   From time to time the Thai Government&#13;
has imposed price controls on a number of consumer goods. The scope of price&#13;
controls has decreased recently. At present only six products are under price&#13;
control at the retail level./l The main implication of price controls for&#13;
shadow pricing is that domestic prices of items with price controls can no&#13;
longer be used as a measure of consumer's willingness to pay. Thus, if a&#13;
commodity which is to be shadow priced on the basis of social marginal product&#13;
falls in the controlled price group, a direct estimate of consumers&#13;
willingness to pay will have to be made to obtain the appropriate shadow&#13;
price.&#13;
40.       In order to promote manufactured exports the Thai Government has&#13;
devised a number of incentive schemes, including various tax reimbursements on&#13;
inputs. The channels of tax reimbursements are: the "Import Drawback Scheme"&#13;
and the "Export Tax Rebate". On the agricultural export side, some indirect&#13;
subsidy is provided through cheap credit policy and through the "Farmer's Aid&#13;
Fund". These subsidies tend to only partially offset the impact of various&#13;
taxes. Hence, in the aggregate there is no net subsidy on either agricultural&#13;
exports or manufactured exports.&#13;
Numerical Estimates of General Conversion Factors&#13;
41.       In this section numerical estimates of general conversion factors&#13;
and a number of specific nontraded goods conversion factors will be derived.&#13;
The general conversion factors include: the standard conversion factor (SCF),&#13;
the consumption goods conversion factor (CGCF), the intermediate goods&#13;
conversion factor (IGCF) and the capital goods conversion factor (KGCF);&#13;
non-traded items include: construction conversion factor (CCF), transporta-&#13;
tion conversion factor (TCF) and electricity conversion factor (ECF). Before&#13;
presenting the numerical estimates, the logic and use of these conversion&#13;
factors in actual project appraisal are discussed briefly.&#13;
42.       As mentioned earlier, the S-T approach advocates use of world prices&#13;
for all actually traded goods and most tradeables which are not presently&#13;
traded due to quantitative restrictions but for which the project evaluator&#13;
has some assurance that such restrictions are temporary or that the government&#13;
can be pursuaded to modify its' policies. For nontradeables and all such&#13;
tradeables which are rendered nontraded by government policy and project&#13;
evaluator has no assurance that these restrictions will be removed, world&#13;
prices are not appropriate. Such commodities are to be shadow priced on the&#13;
basis of marginal social benefit (MSB), marginal social cost (MSC) or a&#13;
weighted average of the two, as appropriate. The MSC is decomposed, through&#13;
various iterations using input-output table, into tradeables and labor. The&#13;
tradables are to be shadow priced in terms of border prices directly, while&#13;
labor is to be converted into border price term by using the shadow price of&#13;
labor. The MSB is to be derived based on consumer's willingness to pay.&#13;
/1 Information provided by the Bank of Thailand.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 .&#13;
43.       In actual project appraisal it is usually feasible to obtain&#13;
specific shadow prices for only a few major commodities, either due to lack&#13;
of information or because there are a large number of small items and&#13;
estimating shadow prices for each item is a lengthy process. In such cases&#13;
it is sufficient normally to use general conversion factors for all such&#13;
items for which direct shadow prices cannot be obtained. In the case of&#13;
nontraded goods, also, it is sufficient normally to decompose SMC into&#13;
first or second rounds of disaggregation using input-output tables. Since&#13;
input-output tables themselves are generally fairly aggregative, the common&#13;
practice is to apply general conversion factors to these first and second&#13;
round decomposed inputs, rather than to try to reach the stage where&#13;
specific conversion factors can be applied to each individual input.&#13;
44.       The Standard Conversion Factor.    The simplest way of calculating&#13;
the SCF is to use what is known as the trade-data approach. The formula&#13;
for estimating SCF under this approach is:&#13;
M + X&#13;
SCF =&#13;
M(l+t m) + X(l-t x)&#13;
where        M   = c.i.f. value of imports&#13;
X   - f.o.b. value of exports&#13;
t m = average tax on imports&#13;
t x = net average tax on exports&#13;
45.       The practical usefulness of this approach is that it requires&#13;
knowledge of mainly aggregate trade data which are relatively easily avail-&#13;
able and, moreover, the actual computation is very simple. The simplicity&#13;
of the formulation is also its main limitation. A number of special&#13;
assumptions are required for its validity. These are: (a) the country&#13;
does not have monopoly power in trade; (b) marginal changes in expenditure&#13;
on nontradeables can be neglected; (c) income effects can be ignored or&#13;
that all income elasticities of spending are roughly equal to one; (d) share&#13;
of imports and exports adequately reflect the relative importance of traded&#13;
goods in nontraded production and consumption; and (e) quantitative&#13;
restrictions on trade can be ignored as relatively small.&#13;
46.       When these assumptions are inappropriate, this formulation may&#13;
yield misleading results. A more accurate, though fairly elaborate&#13;
procedure is to derive specific conversion factors for a large number of&#13;
traded and nontraded commodities and derive the SCF as a weighted average&#13;
of these conversion factors. The choice of estimation procedure,&#13;
therefore, depends both on the criteria of convenience and relevance.&#13;
47.       In the case of Thailand the estimation of SCF and all other&#13;
general conversion factors are based on the trade data approach. Apart from&#13;
its' convenience, the underlying assumptions also are not likely to be very&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
inappropriate./I One questionable aspect, though, is the assumption of&#13;
perfectly elastic world demand for Thai rice exports. There is some&#13;
evidence that Thailand may have some monopoly power in the world market for&#13;
rice. The approach adopted here is to first obtain the value of SCF based&#13;
on the standard model and subsequently do some sensitivity tests by&#13;
relaxing the assumption of perfectly elastic world demand for rice.&#13;
48.       The data for estimation of SCF is contained in Table 4.   The&#13;
value of SCF obtained on the basis of 5-year average data is 0.937 which is&#13;
fairly high indicating that the average level of distortion is on the low&#13;
side. This result, however, is quite consistent with large deviations from&#13;
this average conversion factor for individual commodities.&#13;
Table 4: DATA FOR ESTIMATION OF STANDARD CONVERSION FACTOR (SCF)&#13;
(in million Bhats/current price)&#13;
5-year&#13;
Items                      1976       1977       1978        1979        1980       average&#13;
1.  Total value of imports       72,877.0   94,177.0   106,899.0   146,161.0   188,686.0   121,760.0&#13;
2.  Total value of export        60,797.0   71,198.0    83,065.0   108,179.0   133,252.0    91,298.2&#13;
3.  Import duty                   9,378.0   12,216.0    14,536.0    16,938.0    18,894.0     14,392.4&#13;
4.  Business tax on import        3,586.5    4,185.5     4,471.4     4,862.2     5,574.3     4,536.0&#13;
5.  Municipal tax on import         358.6      418.6       447.1       486.2       557.4       453.6&#13;
6. Total tax on import&#13;
(3+4+5)                             -          -           -           -    25,025.7    19,382.0&#13;
7. Average tax on import&#13;
(6/1)                               -          -           -           -      0.1326      0.1592&#13;
8.  Export duty                   1,296.0    1,685.0     1,951.0     3,057.0     3,372.0     2,272.1&#13;
9.  Export premium                  346.4      847.9     1,025.4     1,031.2     1,705.0      1,045.2&#13;
10. Implicit tax rate through&#13;
rice reserve requirement          -          -           -           -        2.7%        2.7%&#13;
11. Business tax on exports         575.2      740.6       780.3       924.8     1,237.7       851.7&#13;
12. Export tax rebate                64.7      109.9       112.3       281.9       255.1       164.8&#13;
13. Municipal tax on exports         57.5       74.1        78.0        92.5       123.8        85.2&#13;
14. Import duty drawback            N.A        N.A.        N.A.        800.0       800.0       800.0&#13;
15. Farmers aid fund                N.A.       N.A.        N.A.       N.A.         758.3       758.3&#13;
16. Total Net Tax on Export&#13;
(8+9+11+13-11-14-15)                -          -           -           -     4,625.1     2,531.1&#13;
17. Average net tax on export           -          -           -           -      0.0617      0.0547&#13;
Source: See Annex A.&#13;
/1 Thailand is a fairly open economy both in terms of flow of goods and&#13;
services as well as capital. Quantitative restrictions are quite small.&#13;
Further, it is likely to be a small trader in the world market for most&#13;
traded goods, except rice.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
49.       The SCF bears a close relationship to the concept of the shadow&#13;
exchange rate (SER) suggested in the UNIDO methodology./l The relationship&#13;
between the two is given by:&#13;
SCF = OER/SER&#13;
where OER is the official exchange rate. Thus, the reciprocal- of the SCF&#13;
gives the premium on foreign exchange. The premium, on the basis of 5-year&#13;
average data, is 6.73%. A direct estimate of SER was made by Chunanuntathum&#13;
in 1976./2 He obtained a foreign exchange premium ranging from 3% to 8.8%.&#13;
The two results are, therefore, reasonably close.&#13;
50.       If, however, it is assumed that Thailand has some monopoly power&#13;
in rice trade, the value of SCF is then overestimated. To get some idea on&#13;
the possible magnitude of overestimation, an alternative estimate of SCF is&#13;
derived by taking a weighted average of SCF excluding rice and the conversion&#13;
factor for rice derived under the assumption of less than perfectly elastic&#13;
world demand for Thai rice (see Part V). The result is shown below. The&#13;
precentage variation is not very large, i.e., only 3% at the lower end.&#13;
This implies that the estimated value of 0.937 is not wide off the mark.&#13;
Nevertheless, since presently available evidence does not justify an&#13;
assumption of perfectly elastic world demand for rice, the central value of&#13;
SCF is chosen as 0.92 corresponding to the case of elasticity of world&#13;
demand for Thai rice (nw) of (-) 4.0 and Thai rice supply elasticity (ed)&#13;
of 0.3.&#13;
/1 In the UNIDO methodology it is suggested that in practice the SER may&#13;
be derived by using the following formula:&#13;
M          X&#13;
SER - OER (1 + M+X (t ) + M+X (-t ) )&#13;
m           x&#13;
It is clear that SER/OER * 1/SCF. This formulation has also been advo-&#13;
cated by E.J. Mishan, Cost Benefit Analysis, New York, Praeger&#13;
Publishers, 1971; D.M. Schydlowsky, On the Choice of a Shadow Price for&#13;
Foreign Exchange, Economic development report, No.108, Cambridge, Mass.,&#13;
Development Advisory Service, Harvard University, revised Oct. 1968.&#13;
/2 S. Chunanuntathum, Trade and Balance of Payments of Thailand, Unpublished&#13;
Discussion Paper No. 72, Faculty of Economics, Thammasat University,&#13;
Bangkok, March 1979.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
Table 5: SENSITIVITY OF STANDARD CONVERSION FACTOR&#13;
TO RICE CONVERSION FACTOR&#13;
Case 1      Case 2&#13;
Conversion factor for rice         1.11           0.92&#13;
Standard conversion factor         0.925          0.912&#13;
51.       The Consumption Goods Conversion Factor:    Data for estimation of&#13;
consumption goods conversion factor are presented in Table 6. Based on&#13;
average of 5 year trade data, the CGCF value is derived as 0.985. This result&#13;
may appear a little surprising, since it implies that the average distortion&#13;
for consumption goods is almost nonexistent whereas it is commonly known that&#13;
the average rate of protection is relatively large in the imported consumption&#13;
goods sector. The reason for this apparently paradoxical result is that in&#13;
Thailand most of the exported goods are consumption goods and the average&#13;
share of consumption goods exports in total trade of consumption goods is&#13;
about 80%. Export taxes on rice, the major consumption goods export, tends to&#13;
offset the impact of the average import tax on consumption goods. The conver-&#13;
sion factors for imported and exported consumption goods taken separately are&#13;
0.773 and 1.052 respectively. Further, the CGCF is overestimated because it&#13;
is assumed that the world demand curve for Thai rice is perfectly elastic.&#13;
52.       To get some idea on the possible extent of overestimation, the CGCF&#13;
is also derived as a weighted average of the conversion factor for consumption&#13;
goods excluding rice and the conversion factor for rice under monopoly power&#13;
in rice trade assumption. The result is shown in Table 7. As is obvious, the&#13;
estimated value of CGCF is fairly sensitive to the assumption of the nature of&#13;
world demand for Thai rice. At the lower end i.e., CFR = 0.92 corresponding&#13;
to nw = (-) 2.0 and ed - 0.3, the sensitivity is about 7%. The value of&#13;
0.985 is, therefore, on the high side. As in the case of SCF, the central&#13;
value of CGCF is chosen to correspond to the case of nw     (-) 4.0 and&#13;
ed - 0.3, which is 0.95.&#13;
Table 7: SENSITIVITY OF CONSUMPTION GOODS CONVERSION&#13;
FACTOR TO RICE CONVERSION FACTOR&#13;
Conversion factor for rice                         0.92      1.11&#13;
Consumption goods conversion factor                0.922     0.954&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
Table 6: DATA FOR ESTIMATION OF CONSUMPTION GOODS CONVERSION FACTOR&#13;
Average&#13;
1976       1977       1978      1979      1980    5-year&#13;
1.   Value of Consumption Goods&#13;
Import                     10,359.0  12,525.0  14,426.0  18,289.0   23,550.0  15,829.8&#13;
2.   Value of Consumption Goods&#13;
Export                     47,369.9  54,014.0  59,717.1  77,199.2  96,560.9   67,025.6&#13;
3.   Import Duty on Consumption&#13;
Goods                       2,802.3   3,385.3   3,753.0   3,883.0    4,549.0   3,658.5&#13;
4.   Business Tax on Imported&#13;
Consumption Goods             N.A.      748.6     N.A.      N.A.     1,035.6     892.1&#13;
5.   Municipal tax on Imported&#13;
Consumption Goods             N.A.       74.9     N.A.      N.A.       103.6      89.2&#13;
6.   Total Import Tax on&#13;
Consumption Goods (3+4+5)   4,639.8   4,639.8   4,639.8   4,639.8.   4,639.8   4,639.8&#13;
7.   Average Tax on Imported&#13;
Consumption Goods (6/1)       0.293     0.293     0.293     0.293      0.293     0.293&#13;
8.   Export Duty on Consumption&#13;
Goods                         443.0     682.0     566.0     699.0      940.0     666.0&#13;
9.   Export Premium on Consumption&#13;
tion Goods                    364.4     847.9   1,025.4   1,031.2    1,705.0   1,045.2&#13;
10.   Implicit Tax Rate through&#13;
Rice Reserves                 3.68%     3.68%     3.68%      3.68%     3.68%     3.68%&#13;
11.   Business Municipal Tax in&#13;
Export of Consumption Goods 1.002%     1.002%    1.002%     1.002%    1.002%    1.002%&#13;
12.   Import Duty Drawback in&#13;
Consumption Goods Export      N.A.      N.A.      N.A.      592.0      638.0     615.0&#13;
13.   Tax Rebate on Consumption&#13;
Goods                          57.4      96.4      96.9     241.1      187.5     135.9&#13;
14.   Farmers Aid Fund                N.A.      N.A.      N.A.      N.A.       758.3     758.3&#13;
15.   Net Total Tax Rate on&#13;
Exported Consumption Goods&#13;
(8+9-12-13-14/2)+10+11)      0.0498    0.0498    0.0498    0.0498    0.0498     0.0498&#13;
Source: See Annex A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
_ 22 _&#13;
53.       Intermediate Goods Conversion Factor.   The conversion factor for&#13;
intermediate goods is estimated on the basis of data contained in Table 8.&#13;
Using 5-year average data the IGCF value is obtained as 0.941. If imported&#13;
and exported intermediate goods are considered separately, the respective&#13;
conversion factors are 0.90 and 1.098.&#13;
Table 8: DATA FOR ESTIMATION OF INTERMEDIATE&#13;
GOODS CONVERSION FACTORS&#13;
(in million Bhat/Current Price)&#13;
1976     1977     1978        1979     1980     Average&#13;
1.    Import of Intermediate&#13;
Goods                     37,567.3  48,758.3  53,718.0  78,341.0 108,131.3    65,303.2&#13;
2.    Export of Intermediate&#13;
Goods                     11,806.0  15,265.0  20,221.0  26,411.0   28,330.6   20,406.6&#13;
3.    Import Duty on Inter-&#13;
mediate Goods              2,852.3   3,716.3   4,260.0    6,033.3   7,029.2    4,778.2&#13;
4.    Business and Municipal Tax&#13;
on Imported Intermediate&#13;
Goods                        N.A.    1,943.3     N.A.      N.A.     2,469.5    2,206.4&#13;
5.    Total Taxes on Imported&#13;
Intermediate Goods         6,948.6   6,984.6   6,984.6   6,984.6   6,984.0     6,984.6&#13;
6.    Average Tax on Imported&#13;
Intermediate Goods (5/1)       -         -         -         -         -        0.1069&#13;
7.    Export Tax on Intermediate&#13;
Goods                        853.0   1,003.0    1,385.0  2,387.0    2,432.     1,612.0&#13;
8.    Business and Municipal&#13;
Taxes on Intermediate&#13;
Goods                          -         -         -         -         -          1.02%&#13;
9.    Average Tax on Exported&#13;
Intermediate Goods ((7/2)+8)   -         -         -         -         -         0.089&#13;
Source: See Annex A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23&#13;
54.       Capital Goods Conversion Factor.  Two values of KGCF are derived,&#13;
the first including imported vehicles (other than passenger cars) and the&#13;
second excluding imported vehicles (other than passenger cars). The data base&#13;
is given is Table 9. In each case 5-year average is used. The numbers are:&#13;
KGCF 1 = 0.844 and KGCF 2 = 0.874. If imported and exported capital goods are&#13;
considered separately, the respective conversion factors are:&#13;
KGCFlM -   0.834&#13;
KGCF M =   0.866&#13;
KGCF*  =   0.962&#13;
55.       A Comparison of Different General Conversion Factors.   To facili-&#13;
tate comparison, the estimated conversion factors for the three categories of&#13;
goods - consumer goods, intermediate goods and capital goods, are summarized&#13;
in Table 10. If average conversion factors are compared, then capital goods&#13;
show the highest average distortion followed by intermediate goods. Consump-&#13;
tion goods show the least average distortion (small country assumption). When&#13;
the small country assumption is relaxed in the case of rice, the ranking is&#13;
changed between intermediate goods and consumption goods, but the capital&#13;
goods conversion factor still shows the highest average distortion. When&#13;
imported and exported goods are considered separately, the conversion factor&#13;
for imported consumption goods show the highest average distortion, with or&#13;
without the small country assumption, while the intermediate imported goods&#13;
conversion factor shows the lowest average distortion. On the export side,&#13;
the conversion factor for exported consumption goods indicates lowest average&#13;
distortion, under the assumption of monopoly power in rice trade, whereas the&#13;
intermediate exports conversion factor shows the highest average distortion&#13;
(due to high export tax on rubber - a commodity in which Thailand does not&#13;
have monopoly power in international trade).&#13;
Table 10: A COMPARISON OF GENERAL CONVERSION FACTORS&#13;
Consumption Goods Conversion Factor  Intermediate ICapital goods&#13;
Composition   Small country Monopoly power          goods conver-I conversion&#13;
of Goods      assumption    in rice trade         Ision factor  I   factor&#13;
assumption          l&#13;
Average           0.985          0.938                0.941          0.843&#13;
Only imports      0.773          0.773                 0.900         0.834&#13;
Only exports      1.052          0.984                 1.088         0.962&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
Table 9: DATA FOR ESTIMATION OF CAPITAL GOODS&#13;
CONVERSION FACTOR&#13;
(In million Bhat/Current Price)&#13;
Items                               1976     1977     1978        1979     1980     Average&#13;
1.   Import of Capital Goods         24950.3  32836.3  39921.0    49060.0  40754.3    40756.3&#13;
2.   Export of Capital Goods          1354.1   1918.6   3126.9     4568.8   8361.9     3865.9&#13;
3.   Import Duty on Capital Goods     3753.3   5113.3   6523.0     7017.3   7315.3     5944.4&#13;
4.   Business &amp; Municipal Tax on&#13;
Capital Goods                    N.A.   1827.3     N.A       N.A     2523.1     2180.2&#13;
5.   Total Taxes on Imported&#13;
Capital Goods                    -        -        -         -                  8124.6&#13;
6.   Average Tax on Imported&#13;
Capital Goods                    -        -        -         -                  0.1994&#13;
7.   Business &amp; Municipal Taxes on&#13;
Exported Capital Goods           -        -        -         -                   1.02%&#13;
8.   Tax Rehate on Exported Capital&#13;
Goods                             7.3     13.5     15.6       40.8     67.6       28.9&#13;
9.   Import Duty Drawback for Capital&#13;
Goods                            N.A.     N.A.     N.A.        116      208      162.0&#13;
10. Net Tax on Capital Goods&#13;
Export (7-(8+9/1)                -        -        -          -          -   (-)0.0392&#13;
Source: See Annex A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
56.       These results have two important implications for project evalua-&#13;
tion. First, they clearly indicate that disaggregation makes a big differ-&#13;
ence in the values of conversion factors. Thus, the average conversion&#13;
factors are only imperfect substitutes for specific conversion factors and,&#13;
hence, should not be used when specific conversion factors can be estimated.&#13;
Second, where use of general conversion factors is unavoidable, it is desir-&#13;
able that the items be identified as exported or imported goods and conver-&#13;
sion factors applied accordingly. When such identification is not possible,&#13;
sensitivity analysis should be undertaken, using the separate conversion&#13;
factors for imported and exported items as the two bounds.&#13;
Nontraded Goods Conversion Factor&#13;
57.       Estimation of conversion factors for three nontraded items will be&#13;
considered here. These are: construction, electricity and transportation.&#13;
The methodology followed in each case is to use input/output coefficients&#13;
expressed in domestic price terms, obtained from the 1975 Input-Output Table&#13;
for Thailand /1, and convert these coefficients into border price terms by&#13;
applying relevant conversion factors.   The implicit assumption behind this&#13;
methodology is that these items are produced at constant cost. The results&#13;
are shown in Tables 11, 12 and 13. Although it is not possible to breakdown&#13;
all inputs into specific commodity terms, a number of major specific inputs&#13;
are shown separately. For these inputs specific conversion factors have&#13;
been used./2 For other traded inputs average conversion factors derived&#13;
above are used. For nontraded inputs the SCF is used. The SCF is also&#13;
applied to the profits component, whereas in the case of depreciation KGCF&#13;
is used. Finally, salaries and wages are converted into border price terms&#13;
by applying the labor conversion factor./3 The estimated conversion factors&#13;
are:&#13;
Construction Conversion Factor    (CCF) - 0.88&#13;
Electricity Conversion Factor     (ECF) = 0.90&#13;
Transportation Conversion Factor (TCF) = 0.87&#13;
These estimates are not very sensitive to alternative values for average&#13;
conversion factors. Hence, these are regarded as central values. The&#13;
sensitivity results are shown in Table 14.&#13;
/1 Input-output table of Thailand for Analytical Uses, 1975, NESDB, IDE&#13;
and NSO joint publication.&#13;
/2 These are calculated in Appendix A.2.&#13;
/3 See Part IV.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
Table 11: DERIVATION OF CONVERSION FACTOR FOR CONSTRUCTION&#13;
Input                           Input&#13;
Co-efficient     Magnitude of   co-efficient&#13;
Sector                        (Conversion         at market        Conversion   at efficiency&#13;
Factor used)/a         price           factor        prices&#13;
Agriculture                    (CGCFx)              0.00689            1.05         0.00723&#13;
Mining &amp; quarrying             (IGCF)                0.04967          '0.94         0.04669&#13;
Textile &amp; textile products     (TGCFm)               0.00094           0.75         0.00071&#13;
Manufacture of wood products   (IGCFm)               0.00294           0.92         0.00270&#13;
Chemicals, rubber &amp; petro-&#13;
products                     (IGCF)               0.03929            0.94         0.03693&#13;
Nonmetallic mineral products   (KGCF)               0.08914            0.84         0.07488&#13;
Iron and steel                 (ISCF)               0.10690            0.91         0.09728&#13;
Other metal and products       (KGCF)               0.06133            0.84         0.05152&#13;
Machinery                      (MCFm)                0.04371           0.85         0.03715&#13;
Other manufacturing            (SCF)                0.00006            0.92         0.00006&#13;
Public utilities               (SCF)                0.00414            0.92         0.00381&#13;
Construction                   (SCF)                0.00028            0.92         0.00026&#13;
Trade                          (SCF)                0.07816            0.92         0.07191&#13;
Transport &amp; communication      (TCF)                0.06272            0.87         0.05457&#13;
Services                       (SCF)                0.02179            0.92         0.02005&#13;
Unclassified                   (SCF)                0.00421            0.92         0.00387&#13;
Total intermediate inputs                         0.63184                         0.56509&#13;
Wages &amp; salaries               (LCF)                 0.09868           0.92         0.09079&#13;
Operating surplus              (SCF)                0.21181            0.92         0.19486&#13;
Depreciation                   (KGCF)               0.03899            0.84         0.03275&#13;
Net indirect tax               (ZERO)               0.01868            0.00         0.00000&#13;
Total value added                                   0.36816                         0.31840&#13;
Sector Total                                      1.00000                         0.88349&#13;
/a Source: See Annex C for specific conversion factors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
_27 -&#13;
Table 12: DERIVATION OF CONVERSION FACTOR FOR ELECTRICITY&#13;
Input            Magnitude          Input&#13;
co-efficient        of          co-efficient&#13;
(Conversion        at market        Conversion     at efficiency&#13;
Sector                      factor used)/a    prices             factor          prices&#13;
Mining and Quarrying           (IGCF)           0.00394          0.94            0.00370&#13;
Textile &amp; products             (TGCF)           0.00064          0.75            0.00048&#13;
Paper &amp; paper products         (IGCFm)          0.00052          0.92            0.00048&#13;
Chemical industry              (IGCF)           0.00373          0.94            0.00351&#13;
Petroleum refineries           (PCFm)           0.37811          0.95            0.35920&#13;
Plastic ware                   (IGCF)           0.00017          0.94            0.00016&#13;
Machinery                      (MCFm)           0.06888          0.85            0.05855&#13;
Motor vehicles &amp; parts         (VPCFp)          0.00145          0.73            0.00106&#13;
Other manufacturing            (SCF)            0.00060          0.92            0.00055&#13;
Public utilities               (SCF)            0.02505          0.92            0.02305&#13;
Construction                   (CCF)            0.00294          0.88            0.00259&#13;
Transport &amp; communication      (ICF)            0.01946          0.87            0.00256&#13;
Trade                          (SCF)            0.07872          0.92            0.07242&#13;
Services                       (SCF)            0.02576          0.92            0.02370&#13;
Unallocable                    (SCF)            0.00466          0.92            0.00429&#13;
Total intermediate inputs                    0.61461                          0.55630&#13;
Wages                          (LCF)            0.06167          0.92            0.05674&#13;
Operating surplus              (SCF)            0.25107          0.92            0.23098&#13;
Depreciation                   (KGCF)           0.06641          0.84            0.05578&#13;
Net indirect tax               (ZERO)           0.00624          0.00            0.00000&#13;
Total valued added                              0.30539                          0.34350&#13;
Sector Total                                 1.00000                          0.89980&#13;
/a Source: See Annex C for specific conversion factors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
Table 13: DERIVATION OF CONVERSION FACTOR FOR TRANSPORTATION&#13;
Conver-    Input co-     Magnitude      Input co-&#13;
sion      efficient        of          efficient&#13;
factor     at market    conversion      at effic-&#13;
Sector                        used /a     price        factor      iency prices&#13;
Agriculture                    (CGCFX)     0.00048        1.05        0.00051&#13;
Food manufacturing             (CGCF)      0.00256        0.94        0.00241&#13;
Textile and products           (TGCFm)     0.01069        0.75        0.00802&#13;
Paper and products             (IGCFm)     0.00389        0.92        0.00359&#13;
Chemical, rubber &amp; products    (IGCF)      0.00757        0.94        0.00712&#13;
Petroleum and products         (PCFm)      0.21606        0.95        0.20526&#13;
Nonmetalic products            (KGCF)      0.00042        0.84        0.00035&#13;
Metallic products              (KGCF)      0.00128        0.84        0.00108&#13;
Machinery                     (MCFm)      0.00210        0.85        0.00179&#13;
Motor vehicles &amp; parts         (VPCFT)     0.08555        0.73        0.06211&#13;
Other manufacturing            (SCF)       0.00044        0.92        0.00041&#13;
Public utilities               (SCF)       0.00454        0.92        0.00418&#13;
Construction                   (SCF)       0.00536        0.92        0.00484&#13;
Trade                          (SCF)       0.04867        0.92        0.04478&#13;
Transport &amp; Communications     (SCF)       0.03029        0.92        0.02787&#13;
Services                       (SCF)       0.03303        0.92        0.03039&#13;
Unallocable                    (SCF)       0.01016        0.92        0.00952&#13;
Total Intermediate Input                0.46249                    0.41403&#13;
Wages and salaries             (LCF)       0.19979        0.92        0.18381&#13;
Operating surplus              (SCF)       0.21237        0.92        0.19538&#13;
Depreciation                   (KGCF)      0.08991        0.84        0.07552&#13;
Indirect taxes                 (ZERO)      0.03545        0.00        0.00000&#13;
Total Value Added                       0.53751                    0.45471&#13;
Sector Total                            1.00000                    0.86874&#13;
/a Source: See Annex C for specific conversion factors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
_ 29 _&#13;
Table 14: SENSITIVITY OF NON-TRADED GOODS CONVERSION&#13;
FACTORS TO GENERAL CONVERSION FACTORS&#13;
General conver-                    Non-traded conversion factors&#13;
sion factors           Construction       Electricity       Transportation&#13;
Case I&#13;
SCF   - 0.92              0.88              0.90                0.87&#13;
IGCF = 0.94&#13;
KGCF = 0.84&#13;
Case II&#13;
SCF     = 0.91            0.86              0.88                0.85&#13;
IGCF  - 0.90&#13;
KGCF - 0.83&#13;
Case III&#13;
SCF   = 0.94              0.92              0.93                0.90&#13;
IGCF  = 1.09&#13;
KGCF  = 0.96&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
IV. ESTIMATION OF ECONOMIC RETURNS TO FACTORS&#13;
58.       The two main factors traded in the factor market are labor and&#13;
capital. Estimation of economic returns to these two factors - the shadow&#13;
wage rate and social marginal productivity of capital, would be considered&#13;
here.&#13;
The Labor Market&#13;
59.       Review of Theories of Wage Determination in Developing Countries.&#13;
The determination of wage rates in the rural and urban centers of developing&#13;
countries has been extensively discussed in the literature, following the&#13;
lead from the works of Lewis /1, Fei-Ranis /2, and Harris-Todaro /3.&#13;
The common characteristic of these models is the assumption that there is&#13;
dualism in the labor market - either in the rural sector or in the urban&#13;
sector, in the sense that the price of labor exceeds the marginal product&#13;
of labor. In the Lewis-Fei-Ranis model dualism prevails in the traditional&#13;
rural sector, while in the Harris-Todaro model dualism prevails in the modern&#13;
urban sector. These works have dominated economic thinking in this area for&#13;
quite sometime and have been frequently used as a basis for classifying&#13;
actual labor markets in developing countries as following either of the two&#13;
schemes but, unfortunately, often without a strong empirical justification.&#13;
60.       Dualism in the Traditional Sector.    Lewis' basic argument is that&#13;
in developing countries the traditional sector is characterized by a large&#13;
surplus of underemployed labor with close to zero marginal product of&#13;
labor. But labor earnings are positive and significantly greater than&#13;
marginal product. As a result, private cost of employment exceeds its social&#13;
cost. The policy implication of this model is that the government should&#13;
initiate a process of labor transfer from rural sector to the urban sector.&#13;
For project analysis purpose, the Lewis model implies that not only labor's&#13;
social marginal product is zero but also its utilization is socially&#13;
costless; hence labor's shadow price, both in efficiency terms as well as&#13;
social terms, is zero.&#13;
/1 W. A. Lewis, "Economic Development with Unlimited Supplies of Labor,"&#13;
Manchester School, Vol. 22, 1951.&#13;
/2  J.C.H. Fei and G. Ranis, "A Theory of Economic Development," American&#13;
Economic Review 51, September 1961.&#13;
/3 J. R. Harris and M. P. Todaro, "Migration, Unemployment and Development:&#13;
a Two-Sector Analysis," American Economic Review, Vol. 60, 1970.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
61.       Dualism in the Urban Center.   The main argument of urban sector&#13;
dualism, as developed by liarris and Todaro, is that, due to prevalence of&#13;
minimum wages, wages in the urban organized labor market exceeds correspond-&#13;
ing marginal product as well as wages in the rural sector. This wage gap&#13;
induces a process of rural-urban migration, causing the presence of a large&#13;
pool of underemployed urban workers as well as a reduction in agricultural&#13;
output due to withdrawal of labor from rural areas. The main policy impli-&#13;
cation of this model is that the government should remove the minimum wage&#13;
clause. For project analysis purpose this model implies that shadow price&#13;
of labor in the urban organized sector is less than the market price. Thus,&#13;
labor conversion factor for organized sector is less than one and labor&#13;
conversion factor in the efficiency sense is different from labor conversion&#13;
factor in the social sense.&#13;
62.       Justification of Labor Market Dualism.    The most complete state-&#13;
ment on the implication of dual agriculture was provided by Sen./l There&#13;
are two major propositions:&#13;
(a) Agricultural households may be classified into two groups - small&#13;
farmers who employ only family labor and maximize utility and&#13;
large farmers who use hired labor and maximize profit.&#13;
(b) Supply price of family labor is lower than that of hired labor.&#13;
A number of arguments have been given in support of the second proposition.&#13;
One line of argument is that labor - at least female and child labor - is&#13;
not fully mobile due to various forms of social impediments. A second view&#13;
forwarded by Mazumdar /2 and Marbo /3, is that family employment is certain&#13;
while wage employment is uncertain. The probability of finding a job&#13;
outside family farm is less than one and, as such, a family worker would want&#13;
to be compensated for the search cost incurred in obtaining a nonfamily&#13;
employment. A closely related argument is that in inflationary economies&#13;
wages tend to lag behind price increase while in family farm an increase in&#13;
output price is transformed into an increase in nominal income as well in&#13;
the same period. A third argument is that it may be impossible for the&#13;
family to send income supplement to the worker transferred. Fourth, there&#13;
might be a preference for work on the family farm as work in someone else's&#13;
farm (for prestige reasons). A more powerful argument is based on the&#13;
/1  A. K. Sen, "Peasants and Dualism With or Without Surplus Labor,"&#13;
Journal of Political Economy, Vol. 74, 1966.&#13;
/1 D. Mazumdar, "Size of Farms and Productivity: A problem of Indian&#13;
Peasant Agriculture," Economica, Vol. 32, May 1965.&#13;
/2 Robert Marbo, "Employment and Wages in Dual Agriculture," Oxford&#13;
Economic Papers, No. 3, November 1971.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
seasonal pattern of agricultural prodSction and employment.   Marbo,/1&#13;
pointed out that due to seasonality there may be certain indivisibility in&#13;
the demand for labor. During slack seasons employers would typically be&#13;
interested in very short contract on a day-to-day or even hourly basis,&#13;
while in busy seasons due to relative scarcity of labor supply and urgency&#13;
of work employers would want to enter into longer contracts. There is no&#13;
adjustment problem for landless laborers, but for family farm workers&#13;
contractual arrangements during the peak period may not be acceptable&#13;
because the arrangements may be in conflict with their own family farm&#13;
interests. This argument, therefore, provides a logic for prevalence of a&#13;
gap between supply prices of family and hired workers even in peak periods.&#13;
63.       Critique of Dualism Assumption.   The assumption that family farm&#13;
and capitalist farm are dichotomous has been challenged recently by&#13;
Rosenzweig./2 Citing evidence from Indian agriculture, he has argued that&#13;
this assumption is unnecessarily restrictive and counterfactual. Once the&#13;
possibility that capitalist farmers may also use family labor and family&#13;
farms may hire labor from outside (permanent or temporary) is allowed, the&#13;
dichotomy as well as surplus labor assumptions fall apart. As Lal /3 has&#13;
pointed out "if a family hires a permanent worker or at least one casual&#13;
laborer on all or most family farm operations, then there cannot be surplus&#13;
labor in such farms even in the slack seasons."&#13;
Characteristics of Labor Markets in Thailand&#13;
64.       The above discussion implies that the model underlying the&#13;
determination of wage rates in actual labor markets should be based on the&#13;
characteristics of the labor market being analyzed. The functioning of&#13;
labor markets in Thailand has been extensively discussed, based on existing&#13;
census and survey data, by a number of authors./4 The main findings are&#13;
as follows:&#13;
/1 Marbo, op cit.&#13;
/2 M.R. Rosenzweig, "Rural Wages, Labor Supply and Land Reform" in&#13;
American Economic Review, Vol. 68, No. 5, December 1978&#13;
/3 D. Lal, "Supply Price of Surplus Labor: Some Indian Evidence," in&#13;
World Development, Vol. 4, No. 10/11, 1976, p.894.&#13;
/4 See Trent Bertrand, op, cit.; Lyn Squire and Trent Bertrand, "The&#13;
Relevance of the Dual Economy Model: A Case Study of Thailand,"&#13;
Oxford Economic Paper, Vol. 32, No. 3, November 1980; Employment&#13;
Aspects of Thailand Development, World Bank, Working Paper No. 3,&#13;
East Asia and Pacific Programs Department, Nov. 1978, Rural Non-Farm&#13;
Employment Study; World Bank, Research Report in Progress, 1981; Fred&#13;
Arnold and Susan Cochrane, Economic Motivation versus City Lights:&#13;
Testing Hypotheses About Inter-Changwat Migration in Thailand, World&#13;
Bank Staff Working Paper No. 6, Sept. 1980.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
_ 33 -&#13;
65.       Characteristics of Rural Labor Market:&#13;
(a) There is no evidence of significant open unemployment in rural&#13;
Thailand. Unemployment for all regions of the country and for&#13;
both the wet and dry seasons has been typically well below one&#13;
percent of the labor force.&#13;
(b) There is a significant change in utilization patterns between the&#13;
peak and slack agricultural seasons. This variation is most&#13;
pronounced in the Northeast.&#13;
(c) The labor force expands in response to heavy demands for labor&#13;
in on-farm activities during the rainy season by drawing on&#13;
females and children who in the great majority of cases are&#13;
not engaged in dry season off-farm employment by choice.&#13;
(d) In the dry season, the labor force contracts with a large decline&#13;
in the participation by females and children, a shift to off-farm&#13;
employment by members of farm families, and a substantial&#13;
reduction in work hours.&#13;
(e) Labor utilization is characterized by considerable off-farm and&#13;
nonagricultural employment that account for large part of money&#13;
income and significant shares of total income.&#13;
(f) Available data on the movement of real wages in the rural areas&#13;
indicate that real wages are responsive to forces of demand and&#13;
supply.&#13;
66.       Characteristics of Labor Markets in Urban Areas&#13;
(a) Wage rates have in general remained subject to forces of supply&#13;
and demand.&#13;
(b) Urban labor markets have expanded rapidly and have been&#13;
characterized by low unemployment rates.&#13;
(c) The very active informal sector in Bangkok provides employment&#13;
at terms competitive with the wage-sector and cannot be charact-&#13;
erized as a residual labor market providing low income employment&#13;
to those unable to enter the wage labor market.&#13;
67.       Rural-Urban Labor Mobility&#13;
(a) Regional and sectoral wage differentials of unskilled workers&#13;
are not very great and certainly not as large as those in many&#13;
developing countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
_34 -&#13;
(b) The available evidence on migration flows indicates that the Thai&#13;
rural population is relatively stable and that the rate of&#13;
urbanization is relatively low.&#13;
(c) There is, however, significant mobility of labor within rural&#13;
and urban areas.&#13;
(d) Migration has taken place mainly in response to economic factors.&#13;
For example, there is empirical support for the following&#13;
hypotheses: the higher the per capita income, the lower the&#13;
unemployment; the lower the proportion of land farmed in the&#13;
destination relative to the origin, the greater the flow of&#13;
migration between areas holding population size and distance&#13;
constant.&#13;
(e) Male and female migration streams seem to respond to per capita&#13;
income and unemployment in the same way. Males, however, are&#13;
more responsive than female to the scarcity or availability of&#13;
farmland.&#13;
(f) Participation rates of Bangkok migrant workers have been&#13;
generally very high and there is some evidence that the job&#13;
search procedure has not been very difficult.&#13;
68.       Government Intervention in the Labor Market:   Role of Minimum&#13;
Wages&#13;
(a) Minimum wages legislated for rural sector are largely ineffective&#13;
in the private labor markets either because in some cases they&#13;
are below market wages or because in some other cases they are&#13;
not enforced.&#13;
(b) In the past minimum wages have been effective only in narrow&#13;
segments of the urban labor market - mainly large scale manu-&#13;
facturing, and for short duration of time.&#13;
(c) Minimum wages are certainly ineffective for unskilled workers&#13;
in general since a recent survey shows that for all categories&#13;
of unskilled workers actual wages have exceeded minimum wages&#13;
(Annex G, Table A.2).&#13;
69.       All these characteristics indicate that dualistic labor market&#13;
models are irrelevant for describing the'Thai labor markets. Available&#13;
evidence indicates that in Thailand labor markets work quite effectively&#13;
with significant labor mobility in response to wage incentives and wages in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
turn respond to forces of demand and supply. The level of nonmarket&#13;
intervention is very small and confined to small segments of the labor&#13;
market. It is, however, possible that the importance of government&#13;
intervention may gain significance in the future. As of now the impact of&#13;
trade unions on the determination of wage rate is only marginal. But it is&#13;
possible that trade unions may gain more political influence in the future.&#13;
Since these changes are difficult to predict, the conclusion at present is&#13;
that the wages are roughly equal to marginal products in most occupations&#13;
and in most regions of Thailand.&#13;
70.       Implication for Efficiency Labor Conversion Factor.    In general&#13;
the market wage for most sectors can be regarded as good measure of the&#13;
marginal product of labor./f In view of product market imperfections, we need&#13;
to estimate an accounting ratio (8) to convert market wage rate into&#13;
efficiency units. Since, at the margin, labor can be withdrawn from any&#13;
sector of the economy, the SCF may be used as a proxy for e. Thus, the&#13;
labor conversion factor (LCF) is given by the SCF, i.e., LCF - 0.92./2&#13;
71.       The only exception is in the case of large-scale urban based manu-&#13;
facturing industries. Depending upon the effectiveness of minimum wages in&#13;
these activities, project specific conversion factors for labor may need to&#13;
be estimated. If minimum wages are effective, the wages in these activities&#13;
would overestimate the marginal product of labor and a separate estimate of&#13;
marginal product of labor would be required. If labor is withdrawn from&#13;
sectors where minimum wages are not effective (as is likely to be the case),&#13;
then that sector's wages can be used as a measure of labor's marginal product.&#13;
The Capital Market&#13;
72.       As in the case of commodity and labor markets, it is useful to get&#13;
some insights on the functioning of the financial market in Thailand and the&#13;
nature of government intervention in its operation.&#13;
/1 The wage rate in the rural areas may, of course, vary over the year due&#13;
to seasonality of agricultural production. Hence, for a project&#13;
providing year-round employment to agricultural labor, the wage rate&#13;
at any particular point in time should not be used as a measure of&#13;
labor's marginal product in agriculture or for other rural activities&#13;
affected by seasonality. A weighted average of monthly wage rates&#13;
should be used in such cases.&#13;
/2  Choice of accounting ratio (e) for specific projects would depend on&#13;
the sector from which labor is withdrawn. If labor is actually withdrawn&#13;
from rice production, then e should be set equal to RCF rather than SCF.&#13;
This was assumed in Staff Working Paper No. 385 (page 12 above). If it&#13;
is not possible to identify precisely the sector from which labor is&#13;
withdrawn, then e should be set equal to SCF.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
_36 _&#13;
73.       The structure of financial markets in Thailand evolved mostly in&#13;
response to the need of the time and the opportunities to earn profit from&#13;
financial activities./1 There has been little conscious attempt by the&#13;
government to develop a financial structure geared directly to the objective&#13;
of fostering economic development in the country.&#13;
74.       The organized money market in Thailand, concentrating mostly in&#13;
urban areas, is dominated by commercial banks. The role of foreign banks&#13;
has gradually decreased in importance, and at present locally owned&#13;
commercial banks account for most of the financial asests and lending&#13;
operations. The "Finance Companies", though relatively new, are second in&#13;
line of importance in the organized financial market hierarchy. Other&#13;
categories of financial institutions are the life insurance companies,&#13;
agricultural cooperatives, savings cooperatives, pawn shops and credit&#13;
foncier companies. Apart from these institutions, there are a number of&#13;
specialized financial institutions: Government Savings Banks, the Bank for&#13;
Agriculture and Agriculture Cooperatives, the Industrial Finance Corporation&#13;
of Thailand, the Government Housing Bank, and the Small Industries Finance&#13;
Office.&#13;
75.       In the early sixties, the financial needs of the largest segment of&#13;
the Thai economy, the rural sector, were predominately served by the&#13;
unorganized money market; so called because such financial transactions do&#13;
not go through legally registered financial institutions. For example, the&#13;
sample survey of agricultural credit in Thailand for 1962-63 indicated that&#13;
94.5% of total volumes of loans to farmers came from non-institutional&#13;
sources./2 Begining in the seventies the situation improved significantly&#13;
due to the government's efforts to channel institutional loans to agriculture.&#13;
For example, in 1978, according to the Bank of Thailand, financial institu-&#13;
tions provided about 67% of total farm credit./3 Non-institutional sources of&#13;
credit now cater mainly to the needs of small borrowers who cannot take&#13;
advantage of institutional credit due to collateral requirements.&#13;
/1 The discussion here is based on the following works: A.A. Rozenthal,&#13;
Finance and Development in Thailand, published by Prager, New York,&#13;
1970; "Financial Insitutes in Thailand" prepared by Money &amp; Finance&#13;
Section, Department of Economic Research, Bank of Thailand, and&#13;
published in BOT Quantity Bulletin Vol. 21, No. 1 March 1981 (pp. 13-58)&#13;
/2 Millard Long, et.al., Agricultural Credit in Thailand, Theory Data&#13;
and Policy, Kasetsart University, Bangkok, 1965, p. 35.&#13;
/3 Bangkok Bank Monthly Review, December 1979, p. 467.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37&#13;
76.       So far as the distribution of credit is concerned, there is some&#13;
evidence that in the past the financial markets, both organized and unorga-&#13;
nized, tended to favor the traders over manufacturers. The bias was more&#13;
prominent for unorganized markets./l Information on the present situation,&#13;
unfortunately, is not available. The government's special credit&#13;
institutions, such as IFCT, have, however, sought to correct this imbalance.&#13;
77.       Although the major financial institutions are owned and operated by&#13;
the private sector, there are significant imperfections in the credit&#13;
market./2 Apart from distortions in the system introduced by government&#13;
regulations, there is a major imperfection in the market itself. The bulk of&#13;
agricultural producers are smallholders with significant credit requirements&#13;
but inadequate creditworthiness in the legal sense. Hence these producers&#13;
have to depend on noninstitutional sources by paying a "high price" for their&#13;
"creditworthiness". Since lack of creditworthiness is a private risk, rather&#13;
than social risk, the payment of risk premium creates a divergence between&#13;
private profitability and social profitability in agriculture. By lowering&#13;
effective private profit, investible resources are diverted away from&#13;
agriculture into other relatively less socially profitable activities,&#13;
primarily trading.&#13;
Government Interventions in the Financial Markets&#13;
78.       The Government has intervened in the operation of financial markets&#13;
in two ways:&#13;
(a) by enacting various rules of operations; and&#13;
(b) by directly participating in various market operations.&#13;
The rules of operations are enforced through the Central Bank - known as the&#13;
Bank of Thailand (BOT). The BOT is authorized to regulate the activities of&#13;
the commercial banks through the following measures:&#13;
(a) adjust the amount of loan extended to commercial banks and&#13;
vary its loan rate;&#13;
(b) vary the legal cash reserves requirement in relation to the&#13;
volume of deposits or the volume of borrowing;&#13;
(c) prescribe a liquidity ratio;&#13;
/1 See Rozenthal, op. cit.&#13;
/2 The financial markets in Thailand, however, are possibly more&#13;
competitive than those in many developing countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
(d) vary the ratio of capital risk assets;&#13;
(e) prescribe the ratios of capital to specified assets;&#13;
(f) set maximum interest rates on loans and various types of&#13;
deposits;&#13;
(g) regulate the proportion of loans to any one borrower.&#13;
79.        The activities of other financial companies may be regulated by&#13;
use of the following:&#13;
(a) the prescription of a liquidity ratio;&#13;
(b) the prescription of a capital to risk assets ratio;&#13;
(c) the fixing of minimum registered capital;&#13;
(d) the fixing of minimum amount for promissory note;&#13;
(e) the fixing of maximum amount of loans to any one person;&#13;
(f) the prescription of terms and conditions for hire purchase&#13;
finance;&#13;
(g) the imposition of selective credit control;&#13;
(h) the fixing of maximum interest rate on loans;&#13;
(i) the fixing of maximum interest rate on promissory notes.&#13;
80.        It appears from this list of regulations that the government's aim&#13;
in seeking to influence the operation of financial markets is to achieve the&#13;
following objectives;&#13;
(a) regulate the supply of money and credit;&#13;
(b) obtain a desired distribution of credit;&#13;
(c) reduce the cost of credit either in general or selectively or&#13;
both.&#13;
The main distortion is induced through the third objective. Even without&#13;
government intervention, there may be substantial difference between average&#13;
rate of interest charged by institutional sources and average rate of&#13;
interest charged by non-institutional sources. When government intervenes&#13;
by imposing a maximum ceiling on rates of interest that may be charged by&#13;
registered financial institutions, the normal result is an excess demand for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
institutional credit which in turn implies credit rationing in some form or&#13;
another.&#13;
81.       The other type of government intervention in Thailand is direct&#13;
operation of government controlled financial institutions. These are special-&#13;
ized institutions operating on a relatively limited scale. The government's&#13;
main objective is to provide incentives through access to cheap credit to&#13;
certain activities, such as manufacturing export industries and certain&#13;
agricultural activities, on economic development ground. To the extent that&#13;
there is divergence between social and private profitability in these&#13;
activities and subsidized credit helps narrow the gap, such interventions&#13;
are corrective rather than distortive. In practice, however, the main&#13;
problem is proper administration of this policy and the associated misuse of&#13;
the facility.&#13;
Estimation of Marginal Productivity of Capital /&#13;
82.       In "perfect" capital markets, with no government interventions,&#13;
the market rate of interest would reflect the social time preference rate&#13;
as well as the social marginal productivity of capital, provided there is&#13;
perfect competition in all other markets and there are no externalities.&#13;
In Thailand not only are capital markets not perfect, other conditions&#13;
required to equate the market rate of interest to the social marginal produc-&#13;
tivity of capital are not likely to be satisfied, i.e. perfect knowledge of&#13;
every individual's investment plans, knowledge about future demand pattern&#13;
and prices of all goods, to name only two conditions. Thus, the market rate&#13;
of interest is only of limited value in judging the level of the marginal&#13;
productivity of capital.&#13;
83.       Direct estimation of the marginal productivity of capital is not&#13;
an easy task. There are numerous conceptual and empirical problems&#13;
associated with this./2 In practice most of these issues are side-tracked&#13;
and an estimate of SMP of capital is obtained by comparing estimates from a&#13;
number of alternative approaches./3 These alternatives are:&#13;
/1 See the excellent articles on this issue by M.S. Feldstein, "The Social&#13;
Time Preference Rate", Economic Journal, Vol. 74, 1964 and by J.&#13;
Hirshleifer, "On the Theory of Optimal Investment Decision", Journal&#13;
of Political Economy, Vol. 66, 1958.&#13;
/2 For a good flavor of the nature of conceptual difficulties see:&#13;
G.C. Harcourt, Some Cambridge Controversies in the Theory of Capital,&#13;
Cambridge, Cambridge University Press 1972.&#13;
/3 See Squire and van der Tak, op. cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
(a) the marginal output-capital ratio approach;&#13;
(b) the marginal output-capital ratio modified to reflect&#13;
labor's contribution;&#13;
(c) aggregate production function approach;&#13;
(d) micro-level estimates.&#13;
84.       Marginal Output-Capital Ratio:   In economies characterized by&#13;
surplus labor with marginal product of labor close to zero, the marginal&#13;
productivity of capital (q) may be approximated by calculating the incre-&#13;
mental output-capital ratio (k) which is simply the reverse of the familiar&#13;
incremental capital output ratio (ICOR). Data for the necessary calculation&#13;
is presented in Table 15. The value of q is estimated as 0.36. This&#13;
approach over estimates q for at least three reasons. First, it is obtained&#13;
as an average estimate rather than a truly marginal estimate. Second, the&#13;
assumption of zero marginal productivity of labor is invalid. Third, no&#13;
allowance is made for technical progress.&#13;
85.       Adjusted Marginal Output - Capital Ratio.   One crude way of&#13;
allowing for labor's contribution in net incremental output is to subtract&#13;
the increase in real national wage bill per unit of net investment (6RW/I)&#13;
from the incremental net output capital ratio (k) thus&#13;
- k - ARW - 0.36 - 0.11 = 0.25&#13;
I&#13;
The new value of q is 0.25 which, although a better estimate than the previous&#13;
one, is still on the high side due to first and third reasons&#13;
mentioned above, and also because national wage data underestimate the&#13;
actual total national wage bill.&#13;
Aggregate Production Function Approach&#13;
86        When reliable national accounts data are available, a direct&#13;
estimate of j may be obtained by estimating an aggregate production&#13;
function. Although Thailand's national accounts data base is better than&#13;
many developing countries, there are numerous problems with such data./l In&#13;
/1 See National Accounts of Thailand, NESDB, Mimeo, 1978.&#13;
particular, aggregate capital stock, employment and capital consumption data&#13;
are very weak. An alternative solution is to assume a Cobb-Douglas production&#13;
function and estimate g by using the "factor share approach", that is,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 15: DATA FOR ESTIMATION OF INCREMENTAL OUTPUT-CAPITAL RATIO&#13;
(million Baht/1972 constant price)&#13;
Net&#13;
Cross     Cross    capital Net        Net         Net      Incremental                 Incremental   Incremental&#13;
national  invest-  consump- national  incremental invest-  output/capital   Net real   real wage     real wage&#13;
Year  output    ment     tion     output    output      ment     ratio            wage bill   bill        Net Investment&#13;
1972  162,071   32,268    9,358   152,713&#13;
1973  180,146   43,217   12,289   167,857     15,144    30,928      0.49           42,139&#13;
1974  189,191   46,141   12,531   176,660      8,803    33,610      0.26           44,449     2,310.4          0.069&#13;
1975  203,751   51,356   14,199   189,552     12,892    37,157      0.35           49,360     4,911.1          0.146&#13;
1976  222,225   49,526   15,848   205,377     15,825    33,678      0.47           53,606     4,245.4          0.126&#13;
1977  237,173   63,860   17,381   219,756     14,379    46,479      0.31           56,995     3,388.7          0.073&#13;
1978  261,097   69,978   19,244   241,853     22,097    50,734      0.43           63,997      7,002.7         0.138&#13;
1979  276,907   76,009   20,850   256,057     14,204    55,159      0.26           68,521     4,523.5          0.082&#13;
1980  297,376   76,765   22,231   272,145     16,088    54,534      0.29           76,437     7,916.6          0.145    t&#13;
Average                                                             0.36                                       0.11&#13;
Source: See Annex A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
kY-A.&gt; Aeh^L'-i&#13;
d.Y       A tkL,&#13;
dS            -A&#13;
Ja, =  g  k&#13;
The coefficient '4' is the share of capital in total national product. The&#13;
value of 'J' may be obtained from national accounts data on distribution of&#13;
national income amongst factors of production.&#13;
87.       There is a practical problem in calculating 'o4'. Thailand's&#13;
national accounts data distributes private national product into three&#13;
categories.&#13;
(1) compensation of employees : wage payments&#13;
(2) income from unincorporated enterprises&#13;
(3) income from property&#13;
The income from property includes: interest earnings, rents and dividends.&#13;
If we add (2) and (3), we obtain oL = 0.76. This is obviously not&#13;
correct.  The problem is that income of unincorporated enterprises includes&#13;
return to entrepreneurship (profit) as well as return to entrepreneur's labor&#13;
(wages). Hence, the sum of property income and income from unincorporated&#13;
enterprises overestimates capitals' income. Some indication of the nature of&#13;
over-estimation may be obtained by considering estimates of ;C' in other&#13;
middle income developing countries and historical experience in developed&#13;
countries.&#13;
88.       Simon Kuznets' study of the historical behavior of national income&#13;
in developed countries shows that labor's share in national income rises from&#13;
a little over 50% in the early stages to about 75-80% at the late stages,&#13;
corresponding to high levels of development./l Harberger supports the&#13;
/1  Simon Kuznets, Modern Economic Growth:    Rate Structure and Spread,&#13;
New Haven, Connecticut, Yale University Press, 1965; also&#13;
"Quantitative Aspects of Economic Growth of Nations: IV Distribution&#13;
of Income by Factors Shares", in Economic Development and Cultural&#13;
Change, Chicago, University of Chicago Press, April 1959, Part II.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43-&#13;
view that labors' share cannot be greater than 60-65 percent at Colombia's&#13;
stage of development./1 In a recent work on shadow prices in Turkey, the&#13;
net share of capital in national income is estimated as 35%./2 These&#13;
findings indicate that a share of capital above 60% is highly implausible.&#13;
Even 60% appears to be on the high side and an estimate of 50% is more&#13;
reasonable.&#13;
89.       Assuming d - 0.5, the value of q is derived as&#13;
q - 0.5 x 0.36 - 18.0%&#13;
90.       Micro Level Estimates:   One micro level estimate is based on the&#13;
estimated rates of return on projects financed by Industrial Financial&#13;
Corporation of Thailand (IFCT). The distribution of economic and financial&#13;
rates of return on IFCT projects is shown in Table 16. The average (1977-79)&#13;
economic rate of return is 21%.&#13;
Table 16: DISTRIBUTION OF RATES OF RETURN ON IFCT PROJECTS&#13;
Year                             1977    j   1978        1979&#13;
Rates of Return (%)      IFRR   ERR   FRR   ERR    FRR   ERR&#13;
I&#13;
Below 10                        -     -     -     -      -     4&#13;
10-19                     -    19     5    26      7    27&#13;
20-39                    10    22     9    19     11    20&#13;
40 and over               5     1     4     -      6     2&#13;
Weighted average ERR             23           21           21&#13;
Source: Fourth Industrial Finance Corporation of Thailand:&#13;
February 1981. Bank Staff Appraisal Report.&#13;
/1  A.C. Harberger, "On Estimating the Rate of Return to Capital in&#13;
Colombia", in Project Evaluation: Collected Papers, Chicago,&#13;
Markham Publishing Company, 1973.&#13;
/2  Shadow Prices for Prolect APpraisal in Turkey, World Bank Staff&#13;
Workng paper No. 392, i9a0.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
91.       The other source of information is the rate of return estimated&#13;
for recent World Bank financed projects in Thailand. Some examples of rates&#13;
of return are:&#13;
Project Name                                 Economic Rate of Return&#13;
Irrigation XI (1980)                                  32%&#13;
Agricultural Credit (1980)                            35%&#13;
Irrigation XII (1981)                                 23%&#13;
Second National Gas Pipeline (1980)                 40-53%&#13;
Khao Laen Hydroelectric Project (1979)                16%&#13;
Inland Waterways and Coastal Ports (1980)             26%&#13;
The range is quite large, but most projects show rates of return exceeding&#13;
20%.&#13;
92.       Central Value for Marginal Productivity of Capital.   The main&#13;
conclusion that emerges from examining the different methods of estimating&#13;
q is that this number is likely to be greater than the traditional cut-off&#13;
value of 12% used in Bank financed projects. Although there are numerous&#13;
problems with estimation techniques and the range of values are quite large,&#13;
macro and micro estimates indicate that a value of 15-20 percent for q is&#13;
more reasonable than 12%. Considering 18% as central value for q in&#13;
domestic price terms, the value of q in border price terms is obtained as&#13;
q - 0.18 x KGCF - 16%&#13;
SCF&#13;
For sensitivity purposes q - 12% and q - 20% constitute a plausible range.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
V. ESTIMATION OF CONVERSION FACTOR FOR RICE&#13;
93.       In this chapter the conversion factor for rice will be estimated.&#13;
There are three main reasons for giving special attention to this specific&#13;
commodity. First, rice is the single most important consumption item in&#13;
the country. Second, rice is also the single most important export good.&#13;
Its share in total exports is about 15% (1976-1980 average). And thirdly,&#13;
there is strong disagreement on the nature of world demand for Thai rice.&#13;
One view is that Thailand faces a perfectly elastic world demand for rice.&#13;
The other view is that the demand curve is less than perfectly elastic&#13;
implying that Thailand has some monopoly power in world rice trade. This&#13;
latter characteristic has important implications for deriving aggregate&#13;
conversion factors in general and conversion factors for rice in particular.&#13;
Before we go into the estimation process, we present a brief discussion on&#13;
the different types of government intervention in rice trade.&#13;
94.       Government Intervention in Rice Trade may be classified into six&#13;
categories:&#13;
(a) Export Duty;&#13;
(b) Rice Premium;&#13;
(c) Rice Reserve Requirements;&#13;
(d) Business and Municipal Tax;&#13;
(e) Government to Government Sales of Rice; and&#13;
(f) Quantitative Restrictions&#13;
The first four categories fall under "price interventions", while the last&#13;
two may be termed "non-price interventions".&#13;
Price Interventions                  /&#13;
95.       Export Duty.  The export duty was introduced in 1952.   This is an&#13;
ad-valorem tax on rice export collected by the Customs Department and the&#13;
revenue accrues to the government treasury. At present the tax rate is 5%&#13;
of the export price.&#13;
96.       Rice Premium.   The use of "Rice Premium" is by far the most&#13;
controversial government policy in the history of the rice trade./l Until&#13;
1974 this was the most important form of government intervention in rice&#13;
exports. The term "premium", unlike its usual connotation, is a tax on&#13;
rice and has an interesting history which dates back to the Second World&#13;
/1  See:  Ammar Siamwalla, A Ristory of Rice Policies in Thailand, Food&#13;
Research Institute Stu5Ies, L975.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
War./1 The rice premium originated with the compulsory post-war deliveries&#13;
of rice to the UN as a war reparation contribution. The government set up the&#13;
Rice Bureau under the Ministry of Commerce to buy rice from millers and&#13;
traders to fulfill the treaty obligation. But, once established, the Rice&#13;
Bureau continued to exist even after the obligation was fulfilled.&#13;
97.       The Rice Bureau monopolized the rice export trade. All rice to be&#13;
exported had to be sold to the Rice Bureau which dictated the price to the&#13;
domestic sellers. The price was fixed below the export price and the monopoly&#13;
profit thus derived went to the government exchequer. The significant&#13;
divergence between world price and domestic price encouraged large scale&#13;
smuggling which forced the government to relax its control over rice exports.&#13;
Private export of rice was permitted with proper licensing. As a "price" for&#13;
access to export license the government introduced a rice premium in 1950.&#13;
98.       In 1955 the Rice Bureau was abolished and most of rice export,&#13;
except Government to Government sales, was left to the private traders. The&#13;
rice premium was also significantly reorganized and since then, until 1974,&#13;
the rice premium has been used as a major policy tool to regulate rice trade.&#13;
99.       Initially, the primary objective of the rice premium was to raise&#13;
revenue for the government. Subsequently, the rice premium came to be used as&#13;
a means of ensuring adequate domestic supply and to stablize rice prices. As&#13;
a result of the price stabilization objective, rice price became a function of&#13;
world price of rice, increasing when world price is very high and decreasing&#13;
when world price is very low. After the rice crisis of 1973, this objective&#13;
became the primary concern. Further, since 1975 the premium revenue accrues&#13;
to the Farmers' Aid Fund rather than to the government treasury.&#13;
100.      The rice premium, unlike the export tax, is not a uniform tax. The&#13;
rate varies according to the quality of rice. The present and historical&#13;
structure of rice premium is shown in Annex G, Table A.1.&#13;
101.      Rice Reserve Requirement. The rice reserve requirement policy dates&#13;
back to 1962, but it gained prominence after 1973. Since then, this has&#13;
replaced rice premium as the major government policy tool in the rice export&#13;
market.&#13;
/1  See:  (a)  T. H. Silcock, The Economic Development of Thai Agriculture,&#13;
Cornell University Press, 1970;&#13;
(b) S. C. Yang, A Multiple Exchange Rate System: An Appraisal&#13;
of Thailands' Mperience 1Y4b-55, university or Wisconsin&#13;
Press, 1957;&#13;
(c) A. Lew Chalermwong, Taxation and Tax Reforms in Thailand,&#13;
Krushapa Ladprao Press, Bangkok, 1972.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-47 -&#13;
102.      Unlike the export tax or the rice premium, the rice reserve&#13;
requirement is not a tax yielding revenue to the government, but a commodity&#13;
levy, since all rice exporters receiving export licenses must surrender to the&#13;
Public Warehouse Organization (PWO) an amount of rice in proportion to their&#13;
export order./l The Ministry of commerce decides the quality of rice and the&#13;
price to be paid for this compulsory surrender. The price is always fixed&#13;
below the actual export price resulting in a tax on the rice exporter - the&#13;
implicit tax amount and rate depending on the divergence between export price&#13;
and the price paid by PWO. The government does not get any direct tax revenue&#13;
because rice collected by the PWO is sold to the consumers at a price close to&#13;
the purchase price through the "cheap rice" program designed to reach poor&#13;
urban consumers.&#13;
103.      Business and Municipal Taxes.   Like other business activities,&#13;
rice trade, whether internal or for export, is also subject to a business&#13;
and a municipal tax. This tax is paid by the rice millers.&#13;
Nonprice Interventions&#13;
104.      Government-to-Government Sales.   Even though the Rice Bureau was&#13;
abolished long ago, a significant part of rice exports is channeled through&#13;
the government. This is in the form of contractual sales between the Thai&#13;
government and other foreign governments. The G-to-G sales, as this is&#13;
known, has in the recent years accounted for 27 to 45 percent of total rice&#13;
export. The mechanism works as follows. The Ministry of Commerce announces&#13;
to the private traders the type and quantity of rice it wants to buy and&#13;
also the price it is willing to pay. Unlike reserve requirement, this&#13;
transaction between government and private traders is voluntary.&#13;
105.      Licensing and Quota Policies.   All potential private rice exporters&#13;
are required to obtain an export license. Further, they are also required&#13;
to obtain an export permit for each shipping period. Through this policy the&#13;
government seeks to regulate the distribution of total rice production&#13;
amongst exports and domestic consumption. When the domestic market situation&#13;
is tight, the conditions for issuing export permit are also tightened. In&#13;
crisis situations the government has also issued export quotas to limit&#13;
exports and ensure adequate domestic supply.&#13;
Estimation of Conversion Factor for Rice&#13;
106.      Tax Equivalence of Government Interventions.    The nominal export&#13;
duty on rice is 5X of value, but the effective average tax rate, obtained&#13;
as the ratio of tax revenue collected and value of exports over a five-year&#13;
period, is 4.62X (Table 17). The five-year average tax rate on rice export&#13;
due to the rice premium comes to about 9.0%. Data on the amount of business&#13;
L As in August 1980, this was one half ton for every ton exported.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
tax collected in rice export is not available. The five-year average effec-&#13;
tive business tax on exports in general is 0.93% (see Table 4). Using&#13;
this estimate and adding 10% as municipal tax, the percentage business and&#13;
municipal taxes work out to be 1.02. The calculation of tax equivalence of&#13;
rice reserve requirement is not an easy task in view of the wide varieties&#13;
of rice exported and frequent changes in the mixture of reserve requirement.&#13;
A precise estimate would, therefore, be quite involved and goes beyond the&#13;
scope of this report. A less precise, but plausible estimate is obtained in&#13;
Annex C. The average "tax burden" works out as 18.3%.&#13;
Table 17: DATA FOR ESTIMATION OF CONVERSION FACTOR FOR RICE&#13;
(in million Baht/current price)&#13;
5-year&#13;
1976    1977      1978     1979     1980    average&#13;
1. Total value of&#13;
rice exports         8,603   13,382   10,425    15,592    19,505  13,501.4&#13;
2. Duty collected&#13;
on rice exports        391      622      524       670       910     623.5&#13;
3. Average export&#13;
duty (2/1)               -        -        -         -         -    0.0462&#13;
4. Rice export&#13;
premium              423.7  1,003.1  1,510.2   1,533.6   1,517.0   1,213.5&#13;
5. Average rice export&#13;
premium (4/1)            -        -        -        -          -     0.090&#13;
Source: See Annex A.&#13;
107.      The two forms of nonmarket intervention have different implications&#13;
for induced tax burden on rice. So far as Government-to-Government (G-to-G)&#13;
sales are concerned, this does not involve any additional tax burden of rice&#13;
surrender over and above what is implied by the rice reserve requirement since&#13;
traders get a price close to the prevailing domestic price./l In the case of&#13;
/1 It is possible that G-to-G sales may involve a lower tax burden either&#13;
because the explicit taxes are less strictly applied or because such&#13;
contracts involve transactions at a lower than world price for&#13;
noneconomic reasons. In this case the average tax burden for the&#13;
private sector, derived on the basis of total rice exports, will be&#13;
underestimated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-49 -&#13;
licensing, the amount of rice exported is)reduced and unsatisfied potential&#13;
exporters get the domestic market price rather than the export price. But&#13;
there is a spill-over effect of reduced exports in the domestic market,&#13;
since the domestic price of rice would be lower than what it would be if the&#13;
quota is not applied. In principle the implicit tax effect of the quota can&#13;
be calculated by taking a ratio of average export price to average domestic&#13;
price and comparing the implied tax rate to the rate that obtains from price&#13;
interventions. The problem is that the difference between export price and&#13;
domestic price also includes trading costs and exporters margin. Further,&#13;
export quotas for rice have been used only temporarily and very infrequently&#13;
in the recent periods, so that the average effect (over 5-year period) is&#13;
not likely to be very significant./l&#13;
108.      Conversion Factor for Rice with Perfectly Elastic World Demand&#13;
for Thai Rice. If the world demand for Thai rice is perfectly elastic, then&#13;
the world price gives the shadow price for rice. The conversion factor in&#13;
this case is simply the ratio of world price of rice to its domestic price.&#13;
The relationship between world price and domestic price is given by the&#13;
formula: /2&#13;
Pjkbut    4:    AOt,o C4ost fr4U.. of rs*ce&#13;
kW.d    pti(e Of r'49&#13;
mo- Av C      t to\  ,de 'Op fcrCcc C#G/otXS&#13;
The coversion factor is given by:&#13;
pd iXt --e 2-&#13;
The conversion factor for rice will be greater than, equal to or less than&#13;
uniti depending upon whether tR is positive, zero or negative. The value&#13;
of t derived above is&#13;
tR _ 0.0462 + 0.090 + 0.0120 + 0.1830 - 0.3312&#13;
/1 For an interesting theoretical model of rice market under various price&#13;
and nonprice Interventions seet C. Nakajima, "Theoretical Analysis&#13;
of the Rice Export System in Thailand", The Developing Economies,&#13;
Vol. 15, No. 2, June 1977.&#13;
/2 Cost of exporting and traders margin are ignored here. These have to be&#13;
considered in specific projects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 _&#13;
Hence, the conversion factor is&#13;
1&#13;
-  1.49&#13;
1 - 0.3312&#13;
108.      Conversion Factor for Rice with Less than Perfectly Elastic&#13;
World Demand for Thai Rice: Simple Case (Exports only). If the world demand&#13;
for Thai rice is less than perfectly elastic, this means Thailand has some&#13;
monopoly power in rice trade. In this case the world price is no longer the&#13;
relevant shadow price. Following the familiar textbook monopoly model, we&#13;
have to distinguish between average revenue and marginal revenue. The shadow&#13;
price is now given by the marginal revenue and the conversion factor is given&#13;
by the ratio of marginal revenue from an additional unit of rice export to&#13;
its domestic price. Using the well-known relationship between average&#13;
revenue and marginal revenue, the formula for conversion factors becomes:&#13;
R'F = it (' r^sl)&#13;
?g ( I-_t R)&#13;
where nw    price elasticity of world demand for Thai rice.    It is clear&#13;
that R F is greater than, equal to or less than unity as tR is greater&#13;
than, equal to or less than nw. When tR and nw are equal, we have a case&#13;
of 'optimal rice tax'./l&#13;
110.      A host of econometric work has been done on the empirical&#13;
characteristics of the domestic and world market for Thai rice. Three&#13;
elasticities particularly relevant for this study are:&#13;
(a) the elasticity of world demand for Thai rice (nw);&#13;
(b)  domestic demand elasticity for rice (nd);&#13;
(c) domestic supply elasticity for rice (ed).&#13;
Most studies agree that, at least in the short-run, the world demand&#13;
elasticity for Thai rice is less than infinity. There is, however,&#13;
/1 The optimal tax concept used here is based on a very simple model. In&#13;
practice we have to distinguish between long-run and short-run&#13;
elasticities of demand for rice. See Robert Reppeto, "Optimal Export&#13;
Taxes in the Short and Long Runt An Application to Pakistan's Jute&#13;
Export Policy", Quarterly Journal or Economics, Vol. 86, No. 3, Aug.&#13;
1972.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-51 -&#13;
disagreement on the magnitude of the elasticity estimate. One study derived a&#13;
value of (-)4.0/1, while another work obtained a value of (-)1.7/2. Regarding&#13;
domestic demand elasticity, two estimates are (-)0.45/1 and (-)OUI8/3; while&#13;
short-run domestic supply estimates are 0.3/4 and 0.17-2.  For the&#13;
present study we would assume a world demazndelastieity of (-)4.0. Using&#13;
this assumption the RCF in the simple case becomes&#13;
1 -  1/4.0      0.75&#13;
RCF    -              -         -  1.12&#13;
1 -  0.3312     0.6688&#13;
If we use nw - (-)2.0, the value of CFR becomes&#13;
1 - 1/2.0      0.50&#13;
RCF -       0                   -  0.75&#13;
1 - 0.3312     0.6688&#13;
111.      Allowing for Domestic Consumption: More Complex Case:    When we&#13;
allow for the Impact of domestic consumption of rice, the simple formula&#13;
above is no longer adequate. It can be shown that the relevant efficiency&#13;
conversion factor for rice becomes:/5&#13;
AcF =0e4              -a       -&#13;
/1 Wong Chung Ming, "A Model Evaluating the Effects of Thai Government&#13;
Taxation of Rice Exports on Trade and Welfare", American Journal of&#13;
Agricultural Economics, Vol. 60, No. 1, February 1978.&#13;
/2 Supote Churranantathun; An Econometric Analysis of Demand and Supply&#13;
Elasticities of Thai White Rice, Ph.D. dissertation, Univeriety of&#13;
Oregon, 1977.&#13;
/3 Olarn Chaiprawat, AgRreaate Structures of Production and Domestic&#13;
Demand for Rice in Thailead: A Time Series Analysis, 1951-1973, Bank&#13;
of Thailand,, 1975.&#13;
/4 J. R. Behrman, Supply Response in Underdeveloped Agriculture: A Case&#13;
Study of Four Major Agricultural Crops In Thailand, North. Holland&#13;
Publishing Company, Amsterdam, 1977.&#13;
/5  Lynn Squire and van der Tak, op. cit., p. 144.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
Where           -  SCF&#13;
B  -  CGCF&#13;
a  -  share of domestic consumption of rice in total&#13;
production&#13;
(1-a)     share of exports in total rice production&#13;
tR  - average net tax in rice&#13;
nw  = elasticity of world demand for Thai rice&#13;
nd  = elasticity of domestic demand for rice&#13;
ed  = elasticity of domestic supply for rice.&#13;
This formula in essence allows for the impact of changes in the rice price&#13;
on domestic consumption and the consequent induced changes in the economy.&#13;
Using different values of the underlying parameters, the values of RCF are&#13;
shown in Table 18./I&#13;
Table 18: SENSITIVITY OF CONVERSION FACTOR FOR&#13;
RICE IN nw AND ed&#13;
ed            nw       (-)4.0     (-)2.0&#13;
0.1                       1.13       0.94&#13;
0.3                       1.11       0.92&#13;
112.      The conclusion which emerges from the above discussion is that the&#13;
assumption regarding the elasticity of world demand for Thai rice is of&#13;
crucial importance, both for estimation of conversion factor for rice as well&#13;
as for policy purpose. Evidence available at present does not support the&#13;
assumption of a perfectly elastic world demand curve for Thai rice. However,&#13;
more careful empirical work is required to obtain a more definite range for&#13;
the elasticity estimate. The main implication for project analysis is that&#13;
where rice is a major project output or input and specific conversion factor&#13;
for rice is required, it is not sufficient to take the ratio of world price to&#13;
domestic price. The consequence of less than perfectly elastic world demand&#13;
for Thai rice has to be considered in obtaining the relevant shadow price or&#13;
conversion factor for rice.&#13;
/1 Details are shown in Annex E.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX A&#13;
Page 1&#13;
ESTIMATION OF SOCIAL PARAMETERS&#13;
1.        Introduction.  Apart from the growth objective, another justifica-&#13;
tion for government intervention in the economy is that income distribution&#13;
obtaining in a free market economy is considered socially undesirable and&#13;
the government is expected to improve the income distribution through&#13;
various measures. Economists, however, recognize that in practice there may&#13;
be a trade-off between growth and income distribution objectives. The&#13;
government may, therefore, need to balance one against the other.&#13;
2.        A number of instruments are available to the government to pursue&#13;
the income distribution objective. One suggested approach is to use projects&#13;
as a possible mechanism for income redistribution. The idea is that if, due&#13;
to political and administrative constraints, it is not possible to use fiscal&#13;
or other policy instruments to achieve the desired income distribution&#13;
directly, it may be possible to attain this objective by building income&#13;
distribution considerations in the project design or selection process. This&#13;
may be achieved by identifying the various beneficiaries and putting different&#13;
"weights" on benefits accruing to different beneficiaries in deriving the&#13;
measure of total "social profitability." The derivation of income distribu-&#13;
tion weights for a particular group, in turn, involves estimation of a number&#13;
of national level parameters which are called "social parameters" in the S-T&#13;
approach because they relate to both income distribution and growth&#13;
objectives, as distinguished from the efficiency parameters which relate to&#13;
only the growth objective. These parameters would be estimated in this Annex.&#13;
3.        Thai Government Policy Towards Income Distribution and Growth.&#13;
Historically, the Thai goverment's basic attitude has been to create an atmos-&#13;
phere favorable for the growth of economic activity in the private sector.&#13;
The government has considered its main role as providing infrastructure&#13;
facilities for promotion of private economic activities. Conscious attempts&#13;
to promote either growth or equity or both, are very recent phenomena. Even&#13;
the First Plan (1961-67) was launched at the urging of the World Bank and&#13;
other international financial institutions. The Plan's basic objective was&#13;
to encourage a diversification of economic activities from agriculture&#13;
towards industry. It sought to achieve this objective through heavy&#13;
investment in infrastructure as well as through development of service&#13;
industries and mining activities. The Second Five-Year Plan was a&#13;
continuation of the task set in the First Plan. In both these Plans there&#13;
was very little concern for the promotion of equity.&#13;
4.        Income distribution as a social objective was first recognized in&#13;
the Third Plan, and it gained prominence in the Fourth and Fifth Plans.&#13;
The Fifth Plan (1982-86), in particular, has expressed a very serious concern&#13;
for improving income distribution in the country. Two of the five major&#13;
objectives of the Fifth Plan ares L&#13;
/1 Outline of the Fifth National Economic and Social Development Plan&#13;
(1982-86), NESDB, January 1981, pp. 4-5.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX A&#13;
Page 2&#13;
(a) "to reduce absolute poverty and accelerate rural development&#13;
in backward areas;" and&#13;
(b) "to adjust social structure in order to make it more stable and&#13;
disciplined, fair and safe, as well as to provide more educa-&#13;
tional and employment opportunities for the poor."&#13;
5.         The goveriment's present policy, therefore, is to balance the need&#13;
for high economic growth with the social need for a more equitable distri-&#13;
bution of income. In view of the fact that Thailand is presently going&#13;
through a process of structural change in the economy, the government will&#13;
need to concentrate its attention on this task which implies that the govern-&#13;
ment may not be able to pursue its equity objective with as much enthusiasm&#13;
as the stated objectives indicate. Hence, in choosing subjective parameters&#13;
relating to equity and growth objectives, the Thai Government's attitude&#13;
towards income distribution may be considered as "moderate" compared to&#13;
"radical" and "no concern" positions.&#13;
6.        The above view is also supported by actual government policies&#13;
pursued so far to improve income distribution. The interest in improving&#13;
income distribution is reflected by a number of programs undertaken by the&#13;
government. These include:&#13;
(a) legislation of minimum wages;&#13;
(b) providing subsidized rice to consumers;&#13;
(c) increasing the tax exempt income level and a mildly pro-&#13;
gressive income tax rate;&#13;
(d) the desire to reduce the impact of agricultural taxation on in-&#13;
centives through various special programs such as Farmer's Aid&#13;
Funds, price supports to farmers and greater access to cheap&#13;
credit;&#13;
(e) creation of special programs to aid poverty pockets; and&#13;
(f) developing regional cities to reduce concentration of income and&#13;
economic activities in Bangkok.&#13;
At the same time, a critical examination of these programs shows that some&#13;
of these measures are not very effective in improving income distribution.&#13;
There is no attempt to change the asset distribution in the country, neither&#13;
is there a major effort to reduce the concentration of wealth and income&#13;
through large increases in wealth and property taxes and a highly progressive&#13;
income tax structure, both enforced strictly.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX A&#13;
55 -                           PasPe 3&#13;
Value Judgements: The Consumption Rate of Interest (CRI), Pure Time&#13;
Preference Rate (P) and the Elasticity of Social Marginal Utility of Income&#13;
() v&#13;
7.        The CRI is defined as the rate of discount to be used in deriv-&#13;
ing the present value of future consumption. In the S-T formulation the&#13;
CRI is given by&#13;
CRI- i ng + P                                    {S-T  page 691&#13;
Where P - rate of pure time preference;&#13;
n - elasticity of social marginal utility of income;&#13;
g - rate of growth of per capita consumption.&#13;
Estimation of CRI, therefore, involves estimation of two value Judgements&#13;
(P, n) and an objective parameter (g). The value of g can be obtained from&#13;
national accounts data (see Annex F Table Al). The trend growth rate of per&#13;
capita real consumption over an 11 year period, 1970-1980, is 4.25%. The&#13;
value of P depends on society's preference between present consumption and&#13;
future consumption due to difference only in timing of'consumption. In a&#13;
democratic society individuals' time preference may be used to obtain some&#13;
guidance on the possible range for P./1 For an individual P will certainly&#13;
be greater than zero because of future uncertainty. There is also some&#13;
evidence that a Thai may have a relatively high preference for present over&#13;
future consumption. One such evidence is the observed "low levels of&#13;
ownership of insurance and financial assets and relatively high levels of&#13;
ownership of consumer goods in comparison with other Asians./l But, some&#13;
allowance should also be made in respect of the government's desire to have&#13;
a reasonable rate of growth as well as its responsibility towards future&#13;
generations which are not being represented now. Based on these considera-&#13;
tions, the S-T approach suggests use of a low value for P between 0 to 5%.&#13;
In this work a value of 3% is selected, and for sensitivity purpose a range&#13;
of 2-4% is used.&#13;
/1 The idea of society having a ,pure time preference other than zero&#13;
has been hotly debated in the literature. Critics argue that indivi-&#13;
dual time preference due to future uncertainties cannot serve as a&#13;
basis for society's time preference because such uncertainties reflect&#13;
mostly private rather than social risks. Supporters argue that in a&#13;
democratic society the government should reflect to some extent the&#13;
individual's preference. For an excellent discussion see S. Chakravarty,&#13;
Capital and Development Planning, MIT Press, Cambridge, Mass. 1969.&#13;
/2 Anderson, op cit., p. 138.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -                             ANNEX A&#13;
- 56 -                   ~~~~~Page 4&#13;
8.        The value of n depends on government's concern for improving&#13;
income distribution in the country. There have been a number of attempts to&#13;
derive n objectively. In an interesting work, Fellner/l found that a&#13;
reasonable range of values for n is given by n - 1.0 to n - 2.5. In their&#13;
work S-T suggest values of n - 0.5 to n - 2.0 for countries with mild&#13;
interest and strong interest in income distribution objective respectively.&#13;
In the case of Thailand we suggest a sensitivity range of n - 1.0 and&#13;
n - 1.5. The value of CRI implied by these numbers and its sensitivity to&#13;
P and n is shown in Table 19.&#13;
Table 19: ALTERNATIVE VALUES OF CRI (i)&#13;
WITH "g" = 4.25%&#13;
n = 1.0              n = 1.5&#13;
P - 0.02           0.0625               0.0838&#13;
P - 0.03           0.0725               0.0938&#13;
P - 0.04           0.0825               0.1038&#13;
The central value of CRI is selected as 0.0938 or 9.4%, based on P - 0.03&#13;
and n - 1.5.   For sensitivity we suggest values of 6.3% and 10.4% as lower&#13;
and upper bounds.&#13;
The Consumption Distribution Weight (d)&#13;
9.        The consumption distribution weight (d) is defined as the value&#13;
of a marginal increase in consumption at domestic prices to someone at a&#13;
certain consumption level relative to the value of a marginal increase in&#13;
consumption at domestic prices obtaining to someone at the average consump-&#13;
tion level. Thus, d will be greater than one for all individuals who&#13;
have consumption levels below the average and less than one for all indivi-&#13;
duals who have consumption levels above the average.&#13;
10.       The formula for estimating d depends on the nature of the utility&#13;
function assumed. Also in the S-T approach a distinction is made between&#13;
marginal changes in consumption and nonmarginal changes in consumption.&#13;
Where nonmarginal changes are involved, the value of d will normally have&#13;
to be estimated in the context of specific project. But where only marginal&#13;
changes are involved, it is sufficient to refer to a country specific table&#13;
for d.&#13;
/1 W.J. Fellner, "Operational Utility: The theoretical background and a&#13;
measurement," in W.J. Fellner et. al. Ten Economic Studies in the Tradi-&#13;
tion of Irving Fisher, Wiley, 1967.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX A&#13;
57 -                           Page 5&#13;
11.       Assuming a utility function characterized by diminishing marginal&#13;
utility of consumption, the formula for estimating d is obtained as&#13;
d - (C/C)n                                             {S-T   page 63)&#13;
Where C - average level of consumption&#13;
C - consumption level corresponding to any individual or group&#13;
n - elasticity of marginal utility of consumption (income).&#13;
Given data on the distribution of consumption (income) amongst households, a&#13;
table of consumption distribution weights may be estimated by assuming&#13;
different values for n.&#13;
12.       In the case of Thailand, unfortunately, data on the distribution&#13;
of consumption (income) for the whole Kingdom is not available. Data is&#13;
available only for the distribution of income classified into regions -&#13;
North, North-East, Central and South, and further subdivided into Municipal&#13;
areas, Sanitary districts, Villages, and Greater Bangkok, i.e. 16 categories&#13;
in all. A country specific table of consumption distribution weights canr&#13;
not, therefore, be calculated at present. Project evaluators would need to&#13;
use project specific income (consumption) distribution weights, should&#13;
income distribution consideration be judged important.&#13;
The Summary Distribution Measure (D)&#13;
13.       When the effects of a project on consumption is too small or too&#13;
general requiring examination of all income classes, the S-T approach&#13;
suggests use of a summary distribution weight (D), defined as the increase in&#13;
welfare resulting from a distribution of an additional unit of consumption&#13;
such that the existing distribution is unaffected. D would be greater&#13;
than "unity" if government shows considerable concern for income distribution,&#13;
whereas if government is indifferent, D would be equal to unity. The&#13;
formula for D is given by:&#13;
b _  6  6 -I) tS-T.                            page 1381&#13;
( JJ   6-I)&#13;
Where d Is the parameter of the Pareto distribution.&#13;
The parameter d bears a close relationship to the more familar income&#13;
inequality measure - Olni coefficient (O), and it can be estimated from the&#13;
formula:&#13;
X = ;C6I&#13;
- 1/2  c Ih)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX A&#13;
- 58 -                        Page 6&#13;
14.       Once again, a basic problem is tnat estimation of G requires&#13;
income distribution data for the Kingdom as a whole which is not presently&#13;
available. However, it is possible to get some idea about G from esti-&#13;
mates obtained by a number of researchers, based on past data and making a&#13;
number of adjustments, and comparing these global estimates of G with a&#13;
more reliable and recent estimate for rural areas only. The estimates of G&#13;
for the country as a whole are shown in Table 20./i&#13;
Table 20: GINI COEFFICIENT FOR THAILAND&#13;
Ex ante          Ex ante           Ex past&#13;
Year              money income    broad income      broad income&#13;
1963              0.56277         0.4559           0.4529&#13;
1969              0.5550          0.4822           0.4819&#13;
1972              0.6025          0.5371           0.5348&#13;
Source: An Analysis of Fiscal Activity is Thailand, Background&#13;
working paper No. 6, World Bank East Asia and Pacific&#13;
Programs Department, September 1978.&#13;
15.       A recent estimate of G, obtained on the basis of a survey of income&#13;
distribution in certain rural areas,is shown in Table 21. The survey was&#13;
carried out as a part of a study to evaluate government's rural&#13;
Table 21: GINI COEFFICIENT FOR RURAL THAILAND (1980)&#13;
North        Central      North-east        South      Whole Kingdom&#13;
0.4607      0.4797        0.4377           0.4389      0.4690&#13;
Source: Evaluation of Rural Job Creation Program, Methi Krong Kaew,&#13;
et. al, Thammasat University, Bangkok, 1980.&#13;
employment program. Hence, it covered only those villages which actually&#13;
participated in the program. The magnitude of G for the whole Kingdom&#13;
(rural and urban) would be higher than this estimate for at least two reasons.&#13;
/1 These studies do not, however, present the data used in estimating G.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX A&#13;
- 59 -                            Page 7&#13;
First, the survey included only workers who participated in the works pro-&#13;
gram. Those who did not participate constitute mostly the richer segment of&#13;
the population. Second, it is generally believed that interregional or&#13;
rural-urban income inequality is more severe than within regions or within&#13;
rural and urban areas considered separately.&#13;
16.       Despite the weakness of the data base for the aggregative estimates&#13;
of G in Table 20, the more reliable sample survey estimate in Table 21&#13;
tends to support the result that there is considerable relative inequality&#13;
in Thailand./l For the present study we assume a central value of G - 0.5&#13;
and consider    = 0.45 and G = 0.55 as lower and upper bounds for sensi-&#13;
tivity analysis. The numbers are presented in Table 22. The central&#13;
Table 22: SENSITIVITY OF SUMMARY DISTRIBUTION MEASURE (D)&#13;
TO GINI-COEFFICIENT (G) AND n&#13;
G =0.45            G - 0.50        G - 0.55&#13;
6- 1.6              6- 1.5         6- 1.40&#13;
n - 1.0                    1.0                1.0             1.0&#13;
n - 1.5                    1.23              1.32             1.37&#13;
value for D is 1.32 which corresponds to G - 0.5 and n - 1.5.&#13;
Derivation of Value of Public Income XV)&#13;
17.       The value of public income (V) is defined as the present value of&#13;
consumption stream generated by an additional unit of investment in the&#13;
public sector. Since government may invest in a wide variety of fields, in&#13;
principle the value of V would be different for different sector. But,.&#13;
for simplicity, it is assumed that all uses are equally valuable in prospect&#13;
so that we can concentrate on one kind of investment project and talk about&#13;
one V rather than a number of Vs.&#13;
L/ This conclusion doei not necessarily conflict with the earlier result&#13;
that labor markets in Thailand are quite efficient. A priori, the&#13;
two features can coexist if income inequality is caused by a&#13;
highly uneven distribution of assets (real and financial) and human&#13;
capital, and income from wage employment is a relatively small&#13;
proportion of total factor income.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX A&#13;
-60 -                           Page 8&#13;
18.       The estimation of V depends on the assumption made about the&#13;
distribution of income, obtained from public investment in each period,&#13;
amongst savings and consumption. The simplest case is one where it is&#13;
assumed that the entire income in each period is consumed. In this case,&#13;
the value of V is given by V - q/Bi.&#13;
Where B - consumption goods conversion factor.&#13;
Using B - 0.95, the values of V for different values of q and i are&#13;
shown in Table 23.&#13;
Table 23: VALUE OF PUBLIC INCOME: SIMPLE CASE&#13;
V = q/Bi, B = 0.9 5&#13;
6.3       9.6     10.4&#13;
12.0        2.03      1.36    1.23&#13;
16.0        2.70      1.81     1.64&#13;
20.0        3.34      2.26     2.06&#13;
19.       A more realistic valuation of V would result from taking&#13;
reinvestment into account. A part of income generated by public investment&#13;
in each period may be reinvested. In this case, V may be calculated by&#13;
using the formula./l&#13;
q - sq /&#13;
i~Tq    /                        {S-T  page 105}.&#13;
Where s - marginal propensity to save (reinvest) of the private sector.&#13;
The value of s may be estimated from national accounts data. In this&#13;
study we estimate a by using a standard text book formulation of real&#13;
private savings being a function of real income and real money balance. The&#13;
estimated equation, using time series data for 1970-1980 is:&#13;
RPS - 46094.6 + 0.2925 RINC - 3.76 RHNY (-1)&#13;
(2.74)     (5.43)        (-3.04)&#13;
D.W. - 2.199    , R2 - 0.8583,  SEE - 2790&#13;
/1 This formula is based on a number of simplifying assumptions. These are:&#13;
(a) q, i, a and B remain constant over time.&#13;
(b) i &gt; sq.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX A&#13;
- 61 -                            Page 9&#13;
The estimated value of s given by the coefficient of RINC , is 0.2925 or 29%.&#13;
The values of V for s = 0.29 and B - 0.94 and using different values of i and&#13;
q, are presented in Table 24.&#13;
Table 24: VALUE OF PUBLIC INCOME: MORE COMPLEX CASE&#13;
q - sq&#13;
V -             B          ,   B= 0.95    ,s a= 0.29&#13;
i&#13;
6.3                 9.4                     10.4&#13;
12.0           3.21                 1.53                    1.31&#13;
16.0           7.28                 2.54                    4.20&#13;
20.0          30.20                 2.18                    3.28&#13;
20.       As is clear from the above, the value of V depends on the values&#13;
of the underlying parameters (P, n, g, q, B, a) and the formulation used to&#13;
calculate V.  Since some of the parameters are based on value Judgements&#13;
and can only be determined within a reasonable range, the value of V also&#13;
becomes somewhat subjective and, further, the range of V could be quite&#13;
wide. Fortunately, it is possible to narrow down the range of V and also&#13;
reduce the subjectivity element by using some cross checks suggested in the&#13;
S-T approach.&#13;
Use of Cross-Checks: The Critical&#13;
Consumption Level (C*)&#13;
21.       The critical consumption level is defined as the level of consump-&#13;
tion at which the government is indifferent as hetween additional income&#13;
accruing to it and additional income allocated to the private consumption,&#13;
both expressed in terms of the numeraire. It can he shown that the estima-&#13;
tion of V implies a value for C* and vice versa. Hence, an independent&#13;
estimation of C* would provide a useful cross-check on the plausibility of V&#13;
estimates obtained. The precise relationship between C* and V is given by:&#13;
-./n&#13;
C* *  (VE)     C               {S-T  page 107; footnote }&#13;
22.       We will first obtain the values of C* implied by values of V&#13;
obtained above. From the national accounts data the average per capita con-&#13;
sumption for 1980 is Baht 9,199 in current price terms. Given this value of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 62 -                            ANNEX A&#13;
Page 10&#13;
C the different values of C* for selected range of values of V and n are shown&#13;
in Table 25.&#13;
Table 25: VALUES OF CRITICAL CONSUMPTION LEVEL&#13;
IMPLIED BY DIFFERENT VALUES OF "V AND "n"&#13;
(in Baht)&#13;
n = 1.0                 n = 1.5&#13;
V = 1.26                       7862                    8380&#13;
V   1.80                       5443                    6472&#13;
V = 2.54                       3833                    5117&#13;
V = 4.20                       2329                    3665&#13;
V = 7.28                       1344                    2535&#13;
23.       Information on the possible range of values for an independent esti-&#13;
mate of C* may be obtained from a number of sources.    A minimum value for&#13;
C* is given by estimated poverty level income. The poverty level income for&#13;
1976 was estimated as Baht 1,980.4 and Baht 2,q60.6 for rural and urban areas&#13;
respectively./l The corresponding income levels for 1980 may be obtained&#13;
by using the cost of living index for the whole Kingdom for inflating urban&#13;
income, and cost of living index for Northern region for inflating rural&#13;
income. These are Baht 4,521 for urban areas and Baht 2,881.5 for rural&#13;
areas. Next, the subsistence income for the country as a whole may be&#13;
obtained by taking a weighted average of the two incomes, using distribution&#13;
of population as weights. The relevant estimate is Baht 3,160.&#13;
24.       A second possibility is to look at the government's program.to&#13;
attain regional balance. The North-East is generally regarded as a relatively&#13;
poorer region and the guvernment has been making efforts to improve the income&#13;
of people in this region. Hence, the average consumption level in this region&#13;
can provide somne insight on the possible value of C*. Published data on gross&#13;
regional product only are available up to 1978. To obtain per capita income&#13;
for 1980, we take the ratio of gross per capita income for North-East to gross&#13;
per capita income for the whole Kingdom for 1978, and apply this ratio to the&#13;
1980 per capita net national product of the country as a whole.&#13;
/1 See World Bank Report No. 2566-TH: Income Growth and Poverty Alleviation&#13;
in Thailqnd, Jtune 1980.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 63 -                            ANNEX A&#13;
Page 11&#13;
The number thus derived is Baht 5,050. Next, allowintg for the price differ-&#13;
ential between North - East, and the whole Kingdom and using the relation-&#13;
ship between average income and average consumption for the country in&#13;
general, we obtain a value of C* equal to Baht 3,241. Thib is quite close&#13;
to the value obtained as poverty level income.&#13;
25.       A third source of information is the government's payment of con-&#13;
sumption and production subsidies. In general consumption subsidy is not&#13;
significant in Thailand./l The main consumption subsidy policy is cheap&#13;
rice distribution programs. Rice reserved from exporters is sold to urban&#13;
consumers, primarily in Bangkok area, at a price close to the procurement&#13;
price. Although the government's stated objective is to benefit the poor,&#13;
there is no "target income" group and access is almost free. Hence, cri-&#13;
tical consumption level cannot be identified from this scheme. Other con-&#13;
sumption subsidies are given in the form of lower price for electricity,&#13;
water and transport facilities./2 Once again these are open to all consumers&#13;
irrespective of income level.   Production subsidies are intended to&#13;
encourage certain economic activities. Income distribution effects are&#13;
mostly incidental and benefits are not directed to any target group.&#13;
Hence, no insight for C* is available from production subsidy schemes&#13;
either.&#13;
25.       An upper limit for C* can be obtained by considering the legal tax&#13;
exempt income level. Before 1980 the minimum income required for a person&#13;
to file tax return was Baht 7,000. The ceiling was raised to Baht 10,000 in&#13;
May 1980. If we assume that the marginal savings rate is equal to 29% at&#13;
this income level, the corresponding consumption level is Baht 7100. This&#13;
overestimates C* because, in setting tax exempt income, the government is&#13;
influenced by income distribution consideration as well as collection cost,&#13;
consideration.&#13;
26.       The range of values obtained for an independent estimate of C* i.e.,&#13;
Baht 3,160 - Baht 7,100, can be used to narrow down the range for V. Thus&#13;
V - 1.24 and V - 7.28 may be eliminated from consideration since these imply&#13;
values of C* outside the range obtained independently. The central value of&#13;
V - 2.54, suggested ealier, appears quite reasonable since it implies a&#13;
value of C* which is almost half-way between the two ranges for C* obtained&#13;
independently. By implication, the central values of the subjective&#13;
parameters - n-l.5 and P - 0.03, also appear reasonahle.&#13;
/1 See: An Analysis of Fiscal Activity in Thailand, op. cit.&#13;
/2 The scope of subsidization from these facilities has been narrowed down&#13;
considerably since late 1980.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-64 -                             ANNEX A&#13;
Page 12&#13;
The Accounting Rate of Interest (ARI)&#13;
133.      The accounting rate of interest is defined as the rate of fall of&#13;
value of public income measured in terms of foreign exchange. The ARI may&#13;
be estimated from the following formula:/1&#13;
ARI = sF + (l-s) s/VB                  {S-T      page 114}&#13;
The values of ARI are shown in Table 26. Choice of a central value for ARI&#13;
may be made with reference to the relationship between ARI, CRI and V. It&#13;
can be shown that the following relationship holds between the three&#13;
parameters./2&#13;
ARI = CRI -1/V dV                                   {S-T    page 142}&#13;
dt&#13;
Table 26: SENSITIVITY OF ARI TO s AND q&#13;
q '= 0.12            q = 0.16            q = 0.20&#13;
s   0.22         0.0656               0.0876              0.1093&#13;
s = 0.29         0.0785               0.0960              0.1175&#13;
S G 0.35         0.0767               0.0996              0.1264&#13;
In the typical case ARI is expected to be greater than CRI implying that&#13;
V is expected to fall over time. This is based on the logic that the&#13;
inoptimality of the savings rate and income inequality are both expected to&#13;
fall over time resulting in a fall in V. The central value for ARI is,&#13;
therefore, assumed to be 0.104, corresponding to s - 0.29, q - 0.16, V - 4.2&#13;
and B - 0.94. The upper limit for ARI is set by the value of "q", that is,&#13;
ARI - 0.1600. As a lower hound we assume ARI - 0.0656 which corresponds to&#13;
q - 0.12, s - 0.22, V - 2.54 and B - 0.95.&#13;
The Social Price of Labor&#13;
28.       In economies where the market wage rate does not reflect labor's&#13;
marginal product, the efficiency price of labor is different from the market&#13;
wage rate. In this situation further adjlustments are required to derive the&#13;
A   Use of this formula lmplies that V is constant even through q changes.&#13;
A poasible justification for this is that the value of V implied by&#13;
independent estimate of C* is unaffected by changes in.q.&#13;
/2  See Lyn Squire and van der Tak, op.cit, p. 142.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 65-                              ANNEX A&#13;
Page 13&#13;
social price of labor. A general formulation for shadow wage rate, suggested&#13;
in the S-T approach, is&#13;
SWR = m e +(w-m) (B-d/V)&#13;
+ (w-m) 0 ed/V                       {S-T      page 83}&#13;
Where m = lahors marginal product at market prices&#13;
e = accounting ratio to convert "m" into efficiency units&#13;
w - market wage rate&#13;
d = income distribution weight&#13;
V - social value of income&#13;
0 = ratio of social to private evaluation of disutility of effort&#13;
e - ratio of wage earners own evaluation of the disutility of&#13;
effort to his additional income.&#13;
This forumula simply adjusts the efficiency price of labor (m 0) for the&#13;
disutility of effort and income distribution effects. As is obvious, when&#13;
labor markets work reasonably efficiently so that the market wage rate re-&#13;
flects labor's marginal product, i.e, m - w, the formula reduces to:&#13;
SWR - m ie&#13;
which is the efficiency price of labor.&#13;
29.       In the case of Thailand, we have shown that the available evi-&#13;
dence suggests that labor markets function reasonably efficiently implying&#13;
that w - m. Rence in Thailand, the efficiency price of labor and its&#13;
social price are the same./l&#13;
/1 The only exception, as pointed out earlier, is in the case of projects&#13;
in large-scale manufacturinR sector with effective minimum wages. Social&#13;
price of labor will be different from the efficiency price.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 66 -                        ANNEX B&#13;
DATA SOURCES&#13;
1.        Data used in this report are obtained from a number of sources.&#13;
Specifically, these are as follows. Data on the value of aggregate imports&#13;
and exports are obtained from the Bank of Thailand (BOT). Disaggregated&#13;
data on value of imports - classified into four groups: consumer goods,&#13;
intermediate goods, capital goods, and other imports, are also obtained&#13;
from BOT. The "other import" group includes vehicles and parts, fuels and&#13;
lubricants and a miscellaneous category. We reclassified imports in terms&#13;
of first three groups only by reassigning other imports. Passenger cars&#13;
are included in the category of consumer goods. All other vehicles are&#13;
considered as capital goods. Fuels and lubricants are assigned to&#13;
intermediate goods. Finally, the miscellaneous category is equally divided&#13;
amongst the three groups.&#13;
2.        A similar classification for exports is not available.   However,&#13;
disaggregation of exports into broad commodity groups is available. This&#13;
is used to obtain economic classification of exports. The methodology&#13;
followed in deriving this classification is broadly similar to the&#13;
methodology followed by BOT in obtaining economic grouping for imports.&#13;
3.        Data on import duties and export taxes are obtained from BOT.&#13;
Information on business taxes on imports and exports are obtained from the&#13;
Cutoms Departments. Municipal taxes are calculated as 10% of business&#13;
taxes. Unfortunately, disaggregated data on business taxes for exports&#13;
could not be obtained. Hence, it is assumed that all categories of exports&#13;
have uniform business tax. Data on rice premium is obtained from the Ministry&#13;
of Commerce, while information on agricultural subsidy administered through&#13;
the Farmer's Aid Fund is obtained from the Comptroller Office. Finally,&#13;
information on export subsidy administered through the "Export Rebate" and&#13;
"Import Drawback Scheme" are obtained from the Ministry of Finance.&#13;
4.        National accounts data are available in various World Bank reports&#13;
on Thailand as well as in different official publications of the Thai Govern-&#13;
ment. The two main official publications consulted are: Bank of Thailand,&#13;
Quarterly Bulletin published by BOT, and National Accounts of Thailand&#13;
published by NESDB. In addition, a large amount of information processed by&#13;
BOT for the IMF and made available to the SAL mission of the World Bank, is&#13;
used to supplement data from other sources./l&#13;
/1 Six months after this Report was complete, the author was informed that&#13;
data on economic classification of exports and income distribution&#13;
for the Kingdom as a whole have been compiled and are now available in&#13;
computer tapes in Thailand. These data would be useful in updating&#13;
the parameters of this study.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 67 -                          ANNEX C&#13;
ESTIMATION OF TAX EQUIVALENCE OF RICE RESERVE REqUIREMENT&#13;
1.        The Bank of Thailand has estimated the implicit tax involved in&#13;
rice reserve requirements for six varieties of rice for the months&#13;
June and July 1981. The six varieties are: white rice (5%), white&#13;
rice (15%), broken rice (A1 super), broken rice (A1 special), parboiled&#13;
rice (5%) and parboiled rice (15%). Aggregating these six varieties into&#13;
three categories - white rice, broken rice super and parboiled rice, the&#13;
implicit export tax rate (June-July average) on these three categories work&#13;
out as 19.8%, 6.9% and 22.2% respectively. An examination of rice trade&#13;
structure reveals that on an average (1979-80) white rice accounts for 63%,&#13;
parboiled rice 14% and broken super rice 17% of the total rice exports from&#13;
Thailand. The remaining 6% is comprised of glutinous rice (4%), cargo rice&#13;
(2%) and other rice (negligible). The average tax equivalence of reserve&#13;
requirement is, therefore, obtained as a weighted average of implicit rice&#13;
export taxes on the 3 varieties - the weights being share of each variety in&#13;
total export of rice. The magnitude comes to about 18.3%.&#13;
2.        To convert this implicit rice export tax into a tax rate on total&#13;
exports, the 18.3% tax rate is multiplied by the average value weight of&#13;
rice exports in total export, i.e., 0.1479, based on five-year average&#13;
(1976-1980). Hence, the average rate of export tax implied by rice&#13;
reserve requirement policy is 2.7% (calculated in terms of total exports&#13;
as base).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68 -                          ANNEX D&#13;
ESTIMATION OF SPECIFIC CONVERSION FACTORS USED IN DERIVING&#13;
CONVERSION FACTORS FOR NONTRADED GOODS&#13;
A number of specific conversion factors were used in obtaining&#13;
conversion factors for construction, transportation and electricity.&#13;
Estimates of these specific conversion factors are presented here. In each&#13;
case the conversion factor is obtained by using the formula&#13;
CF-       I&#13;
1 + tm&#13;
where tm   average import tax on the item.&#13;
The import tax is obtained as the sum of import duty, business&#13;
and municipal taxes. The relevant data, 1979-80 FY basis, was obtained&#13;
from the Customs department.&#13;
(1) Textile and Textile Goods Conversion Factor&#13;
(TGCFm)&#13;
1    = 0.7546&#13;
1.*3252&#13;
(2) Wood and Products Conversion Factor (WCPm)&#13;
1      0.9278&#13;
1.*0778&#13;
(3) Iron and Steel Conversion Factor (ISCFm)&#13;
Ir   '  0'905&#13;
(4) Nachinery Conversion Factor (MCFm)&#13;
'  0.851&#13;
(5) Petroleum Converslon Factor (PCFm)&#13;
1     ' 0.951&#13;
(6)  Vehiclee and Parts Conversion Factors (VPCFm)&#13;
I     - 0.726&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-69 -                           ANNEX 1&#13;
AVERAGE CONVERSION FACTORS FOR EXPORTED AND IMPORTED&#13;
GOODS CONSIDERED SEPARATELY /1&#13;
1.  SCF0      1.1592  =  0.863&#13;
1.9&#13;
2.  SCFX   - 0.9433   =  1.060&#13;
3. CGCFn =    1.2931     0.773&#13;
4. CGCFx'        1        1.052&#13;
0.9 502&#13;
5.  IGCFm     1.107      0.90&#13;
6.  IGCFX        1       1.088&#13;
0.9 189&#13;
7. KGCFm         1    -  0.834&#13;
1. 1993&#13;
8. KGCFX         1    '  0.962&#13;
1.0 392&#13;
/1 Source: See Tables 49 5 and 6 in the text.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 70 -                            ANNEX F&#13;
ESTIMATION OF CONVERSION FACTOR FOR RICE WITH LESS THAN PERFECTLY&#13;
ELASTIC WORLD DEMAND FOR RICE AND ALLOWING FOR DOMESTIC CONSUMPTION&#13;
The formula for rice conversion factor, under the general case of&#13;
less than perfectly elastic world demand curve for rice and allowing for&#13;
domestic consumption as well as exports, reported in the text is&#13;
e'( +  C-I  )t1  - +      ij&#13;
Numerical estimation is illustrated here for the case of In.1 - 4.0,&#13;
ed - 0.03 and Indl = 0.4. We already know the values of .' ,B, and tR&#13;
i.e., 0.937, 0.985 and 0.31 respectively./l We only need to estimate&#13;
a - the share of domestic consumption of rice in total production.&#13;
Using data for 1976-80, the average share of exports in total domestic&#13;
production of rice is 30%. Hence, a - 0.7 or 70%. Thus&#13;
Rcj F    °3' ?( 0°3 -(o*3))L I36              g o*q9-s:-o.c,&#13;
o 3 -+ C  C1-t 7) Ai  o   x. o &#13;
RCF                1./1&#13;
L1 The value of SCF and CGCF used here corresponds to the assumption that&#13;
Thailand does not have monopoly power in rice trade.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-'71-                          ANNEX G&#13;
Page 1&#13;
Table Al: DATA FOR ESTIMATION OF MARGINAL PROPENSITY TO SAVE&#13;
Estimated    Total nominal    Total nominal     Nominal money   Implicit&#13;
population    consumption    personal savings      balance      price&#13;
Year   (million)    (Billion Bhat)   (Billion Bhat)   (Million Bhat)   deflator&#13;
1970      36.4          108.0           13,803            18,718         93.4&#13;
1971      37.5          116.0           13,082            20,447         92.5&#13;
1972      38.6          128.1           18,949            23,138        100.0&#13;
1973      39.7          159.3           37,008            27,384        120.2&#13;
1974      40.8         203.4            37,616            31,572        142.0&#13;
1975      41.9          229.5           37,815            34,095        146.8&#13;
1976      43.0          262.1           42,071            37,805        151.7&#13;
1977      44.0          302.2           44,062            42,462        164.6&#13;
1978      45.0         354.1            62,529            48,601        178.9&#13;
1979      45.9         420.2            69,456            57,076        200.9&#13;
1980      46.5          522.7           75,986                 -        228.9&#13;
Source:  (a)  Bank of Thailand:   Quarterly Bulletin, BOT; and&#13;
(b) National Accounts of Thailand, NESDB.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A2 : AVERAGE BASIC WAGES PER MONTH OF UNSKILLED WORKERS&#13;
AS OF 1980/81 AND CHANGE IN WAGES BEIWEEN 1980/81&#13;
1980                           1981              Z change in basic wage&#13;
Average wage of     As % of    Average wage of     As % of      between 1980/81&#13;
unskilled workers    minimum   unskilled workers   minimum               Higher than&#13;
(Baht)        wage rate        (Baht)        wage rate   Unskilled   unskilled&#13;
Bangkok Metropolitan Tbtal             1,349           1.20           1,537           1.14        13.9         12.1&#13;
Salaried workers                     1,541           1.37           1,762           1.31        14.3        12.0&#13;
Permanent daily wage earners         1,312           1.17           1,499           1.11        14.3         13.0&#13;
Temporary daily wage earners         1,236           1.10           1,367           1.01        10.6         9.7&#13;
C.Ratract iwr;kers                   1,601           1.42           1,761           1.30        10.0          5.8&#13;
Central Total                          1,207           1.27           1,384           1.18        14.7         11.2&#13;
Salaried workers                     1,338           1.41           1,494           1.27        11.7        11.6&#13;
Permanent daily wage earners         1,187           1.25           1,370           1.17        15.4         9.0&#13;
Temporary daily wage earners         1,136           1.20           1,322           1.13        16.4        11.7&#13;
Contract workers                     1,429           1.50           1,592           1.35        11.4        11.5&#13;
North Total                            1,171           1.34           1,301           1.18        11.1         9.3&#13;
Salaried workers                     1,282           1.47           1,451           1.32        13.2         9.5&#13;
Permanent daily wage earners         1,196           1.37           1,300           1.18         8.7         6.3&#13;
Temporary daily wage earners         1,006           1.15           1,127           1.02        12.0        20.0&#13;
Contract workers                     1,192           1.36           1,323           1.20        11.0        24.7&#13;
Northeast Total                        1,036           1.18           1,193           1.08        15.2         9.3&#13;
Salaried workers                     1,165           1.33           1,271           1.16         9.1         9.2&#13;
Permanent daily wage earners           979           1.12           1,181           1.07        20.6         9.0&#13;
Temporary daily wage earners           948           1.08           1,079          0.98         13.8        19.8&#13;
Contract workers                     1,319           1.51           1,477           1.34         1.1        16.5&#13;
South Total                            1,231           1.30           1,394           1.19        13.2        13.2&#13;
Salaried workers                     1,310           1.38           1,492          1.27         13.9        13.8&#13;
Permanent daily wage earners         1,145           1.21           1,307           1.11        14.1         8.5&#13;
Temporary daily wage earners         1,207           1.27           1,269          1.08          5.1        11.2&#13;
Contract workers                     1,475           1.55           1,637          1.39         11.0        15.4&#13;
All Regions                            1,277                          1,456                       14.0        12.0&#13;
Salaried workers                     1,413                          1,599                       13.2        11.9&#13;
Permanent daily wage earners         1,262                          1,445                       14.5        12.3&#13;
Temporary daily wage earners         1,143                          1,296                       13.4        10.4&#13;
Contract workers                     1,458                          1,614                       10.7        10.6&#13;
Note: Comparison between the above figures and findings of 1979/80 survey should be done with reservation. Th&#13;
definition of miniumum wage earners in the two surveys has been revised.                                 T&#13;
Source: Survey conducted by the Bank of Thailand, early 1981.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
73                           ANNEX H&#13;
Page 1&#13;
ECONOMIC VALUE OF LAND&#13;
A. The Opportunity Cost of Land&#13;
1.        mhe general principle underlying the determination of the economic&#13;
value of land is the same as for any other resource - the value of the&#13;
resource depends on the "opportunity cost" of using the resource in any&#13;
particular project. The opportunity cost in turn depends on the "real&#13;
choices" available for the use of land. The choices open may preclude&#13;
employing land in the most profitable project or in its most efficient use.&#13;
Hence, the opportunity cost depends on the alternative "best available use"&#13;
rather than the "best technically possible use" of land. For example,&#13;
suppose it is technically possible to use land in A, B, C, D and E and we&#13;
are trying to determine the opportunity cost of using land as an input in&#13;
B. Suppose also that land is most productive if used in A, but environment,&#13;
policy or custom precludes using land for A. The opportunity cost of using&#13;
land in B cannot be determined by calculating the net profitability of land&#13;
in A. The real alternatives are C, D and E and the opportunity cost&#13;
depends on the maximum net economic profitability foregone by not using&#13;
land in *C, D or E.&#13;
2.        Measuring the opportunity cost of land, therefore, involves&#13;
calculating the net economic profitability of land in the best available use&#13;
without the project. This requires a knowledge of not only what alternative&#13;
uses of land are available, but also knowledge of different input-output and&#13;
price configurations. Since alternative possible uses of land depends on&#13;
location, the opportunity cost of land would differ from project to project&#13;
and no general conversion factor or shadow price of land can be derived.&#13;
B. Project Interaction and Opportunity Cost&#13;
3.        One very important point which is often overlooked in determining&#13;
the opportunity cost of land is that there are two opportunity cost&#13;
concepts - one without the project and the second with the project completed.&#13;
Which measure is relevant? On first thought it may appear that the oppor-&#13;
tunity cost of land without the project is the relevant measure. If the&#13;
project is using "X" amount of land, the society is losing whatever net&#13;
economic benefit the beot available alternative use would have yielded.&#13;
However, this provides only a partial answer. Let us elaborate a little&#13;
more.&#13;
4.        Before a project is undertaken, a tract of land may have little&#13;
scope for alternative uses, But once the project is installed, the alter-&#13;
native uses of the land may increase dramatically. The low value oppor-&#13;
tunity cost of land before the project may be far below the high value&#13;
opportunity cost of land after the project is completed. Thus, there are&#13;
two decisions that have to be takent first, should the project be undertaken&#13;
and second, what is the optimal mix of land and other inputs. If land can&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 74 -                            ANNEX H&#13;
Page 2&#13;
be used only for the project due to "use restrictions", or if the amount of&#13;
land available is the minimum required for the project, the substitution&#13;
issue is irrelevant and consideration of before-project opportunity cost is&#13;
sufficient. But, if the substitution of land for other inputs is possible,&#13;
determining the optimal mix of land and other inputs requires that the&#13;
opportunity cost of land be measured under the assumption that the project&#13;
is installed. In other words, both measures are relevant - the&#13;
without-project measure is required to decide whether the project should be&#13;
undertaken or not, and the with-project measure is required to determine the&#13;
optimal mix of land and other inputs.&#13;
C. Measurement of Opportunity Cost of Land in Practice&#13;
5.        In practice it is possible to obtain only an approximate measure&#13;
of the opportunity cost of land. First, it is not often possible to know&#13;
for sure all the alternative uses. When land is diverted from an existing&#13;
use, the usual practice is to consider this as the best alternative avail-&#13;
able use and measure economic profitability based on the existing input-&#13;
output configuration. Second, the opportunity cost of land would vary over&#13;
time. The best available use of one tract of land today is likely to be&#13;
different from the best available use of the same tract of land 5 or 10 years&#13;
later. But there is no way this can be predicted correctly. Therefore, in&#13;
determining opportunity cost a constant alternative use pattern over the&#13;
life of the project is assumed. Finally, the productivity of land in any&#13;
existing or assumed alternative use depends on (a) price of output&#13;
relative to the general price level, (b) prices of inputs relative to the&#13;
general price level, (c) technology and (d) laws and regulations and&#13;
other constraints on land use. Any or all of these may vary over the life&#13;
of the project, which would change the productivity of the alternative use&#13;
and, hence, the opportunity cost of land from year to year. In practice,&#13;
these factors are assumed to remain constant in measuring opportunity cost.&#13;
D. The Market Rent as a Measure of Opportunity Cost&#13;
6.        If a number of assumptions are satisfied, then the market rent&#13;
would also reflect the opportunity cost of land. These assumptions are:&#13;
(a)  the market rent is competitively determined;&#13;
(b)  individuals are free to trade contractual agreements on&#13;
land use and state laws protect such voluntary contracts;&#13;
(c)  market prices fully reflect social scarcities;&#13;
(d)  there are no externalities associated with land use, or&#13;
alternatively, all externalities are fully internalized&#13;
through government policies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 75-                             ANNEX H&#13;
Page 3&#13;
The market rent obtained under these assumptions is called the "true" or&#13;
"economic" rent.   It is clear that the set of assumptions is fairly restric-&#13;
tive. It is commonly believed that in many developing countries landlords&#13;
exert some monopoly power in the rent determination process. Further, zoning&#13;
laws and use restrictions are frequently imposed by the governments of both&#13;
developed and developing countries which imply that individuals are not&#13;
always free to trade contractual rights. Even if rents are competitively&#13;
determined and individuals are reasonably free to enter into contractual&#13;
agreements on land use, market prices are likely to diverge from the&#13;
corresponding shadow prices. Moreover, the problem of externality is&#13;
particularly pervasive in the case of land use.&#13;
7.        A final point is that, given that the above assumptions are&#13;
satisfied, the "market price" of land (present value of annual rents) would&#13;
reflect the "ecottomic price" only if the market rate of interest reflects&#13;
the opportunity cost of capital. We have already pointed out why the market&#13;
rate of interest may not reflect the opportunity cost of capital./l Hence,&#13;
in practice rarely would it be appropriate to measure the opportunity cost&#13;
of land by referring to its market price.&#13;
E.  Valuation of Land in Previous Bank Projects in Thailand&#13;
8.        There are at least two Bank projects undertaken in Thailand in&#13;
the past in which the services of land entered as a major input or output.&#13;
These are:&#13;
(a) National Sites and Services Project (1980);&#13;
(b) Lat Krabang Industrial Estate Project (1977).&#13;
In the National Sites and Services project the benefit from construction&#13;
of dwellings is measured in terms of imputed rents based on existing market&#13;
rent in comparable units. Cost of land used in the project is also measured&#13;
in market price terms. We pointed out above that the conditions required to&#13;
use market rent or market price of land to measure the opportunity cost of&#13;
land are quite stringent and a careful analysis would be required for the&#13;
specific tracts of land to establish whether or not these conditions are in&#13;
fact satisfied. The extent to which such an analysis has been carried out&#13;
cannot be discerned from the appraisal report.&#13;
9.        In the Lat Krabang Industrial Estate Project the opportunity cost&#13;
of land is measured on the basis of net value of output lost from diverting&#13;
land from its previous use. More specifically, land was previously used as&#13;
/1 See the discussion on the marginal productivity of capital in the&#13;
text.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-76-                            ANNEX H&#13;
Page 4&#13;
a paddy field.   Net annual value of output is measured by calculating&#13;
annual value of rice production and subtracting an assumed value as cost of&#13;
production. The net present value is derived by assuming that the net&#13;
annual benefit remains constant throughout the project life and using an&#13;
assumed discount rate to reflect the time preference rate. This is&#13;
definitely an improvement over the practice of using the market value of&#13;
land. Nevertheless, two problems remain. First, the output of rice is&#13;
valued in terms of the domestic market price. Since rice is a tradeable and&#13;
is actually exported, the relevant measure and output value is the marginal&#13;
revenue from exporting rice. Secondly, use of time preference rate as the&#13;
discount rate implies that the project evaluator is undertaking social&#13;
analysis. Since this does not appear to be the case, i.e. only economic&#13;
analysis is undertaken, the opportunity cost of capital is the appropriate&#13;
discount rate.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
World      Bank                       Italian: AnalLsi economica del progettl  The Effects of Population&#13;
dl lnuestimento"in Analisi del progetti  Growth, of the Pattern of&#13;
Publications                         di investimento: iI metodo della Banca  Demand, and of Technology&#13;
Mondiale. Marsillo Editorl. s.p.a.,  on the Process of Urbaniza-&#13;
of Related                            S. Croce 518/A, 30125 Venice,        tion: An Application to India&#13;
Interest                             Italy. 1978.                         Rakesh Mohan&#13;
ISBN 10-4108-8. L8,800.              This paper uses a non-linear, three-&#13;
Portuguese: Analise econ6mica de pro-  sector, two-region wage-and-price&#13;
jetos. LTC-Liuros T4cnicos e Clenttficos.  endogenous dynamic general&#13;
S. A., Au. Venezuela. 163, 20.220-Rio de  equilibrium model to study the effect&#13;
Approaches to Purchasing             Janelro, R J, Brazil. 1979.          of populaton growth, the pattern of&#13;
demand, and of technological change&#13;
Power Parity and Real                ISBl 85-216-0017-8, $8.00 equivalent.  on urbanization In the context of a&#13;
Product Comparisons                  paperback.                           low-income developing country start-&#13;
Using Shortcuts and                  SpanishI AnMisis economico de proyec-  Ing at a low level of urbanization.&#13;
Reduced Information                  tos. Editorial Tecnos, 1977.         World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
Sultan Ahmad                         ISBN 84-309-0719-X, 435 pesetas.     No. 520. 1982. 47 pages.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.                                        ISBN 0-8213-0008-3. $3.00.&#13;
418. September 1980.11 + 60 pages&#13;
(including 14 tables, bibliography).  Economic and Social&#13;
Stock No. WP-0418. S3.00.            Analysis of Projects and of              NEW&#13;
Price Policy: The Morocco&#13;
Fourth Agrcultural                   Financing of Investment in&#13;
Comparative Study of the             Credtt Priuect u                     India, 1975-1985: A&#13;
Management and Organoza-             Kevin M. Cleaver                     Sources and Uses of Funds&#13;
tion of Irilgation Projects                   *                           Approach&#13;
Anthony E Bottrall                   World Bank Staff Working Paper NO.   Armando Pinell-Slles and&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper Mo.   369. January 1980. 59 pages (includ-  VUJ. Ravishankar&#13;
458. May 1981. 274 pages (Includi i nS     a   table69.                   This paper presents sources and uses&#13;
3 appendixes).                       Stock No, WP-0369, S3,00.            of funds accounts Integrated in a&#13;
Stock Mo. WP-0458. $10.00.                                                 macroeconomic framework for&#13;
Economy-Wide Models and              analyzing flnancing patterns and&#13;
Development Planningeconomic interdependence among&#13;
Deveopment Planning                  sectors In India, contrasting the&#13;
Economic Analysis                    Charles R. Blitzer,                  period 1975-80 with the Sixth Plan&#13;
of Projects                          Peter B. Clark, and                  period. 1980-85.&#13;
Lyn Squire and                       Lance Taylor, editors                World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
hierman G. van der Tak               Surveys the specification and uses of  543.1982. 92 pages.&#13;
Reconsiders project appraisal and    medium-term and perspective          ISBN 0-8213-0205-5. $3.00.&#13;
recommends a more systematic and&#13;
consistent estimation and application  Oxford Uniuersity Press, 1975; 4th  General Equilibrium Models&#13;
of shadow prices and a calculation of  printing, 1982. 382 pages (including  for Development Policy&#13;
rates of return that take explicit   selected additional readings, bibliogra-  KemaI D     J      de Me1&#13;
account of the project's impact on the  phy, subject and author Index),      eman S erms, aime      e   o,&#13;
distribution of Income.LC7297.IB0199072,adSemnRbso&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Pmess,  LC 74-29171. 15BN 0-19-920074-2,     Provides a comprehensive study of&#13;
1975; 4th printing, 1981. 164 pages                                        multisector. economywide planning&#13;
models with particular emphasis on&#13;
(including appendi, glossary,                                             issues of trade, distribution, growth,&#13;
bibliography).                                                            and structural change. Theoretical&#13;
LC 75-40228. ISBN 0-8018-1818-4,                                          discussion of the properties of&#13;
$6.50 (2. 75) paperback.                                                  multisector, appiled general&#13;
equilibrium models is combined with&#13;
French: Analyse economique                                                 numerical applications to particular&#13;
des projets. Economica, 1977; 2nd                                         countries and problems. The models&#13;
printing, 1981.                                                            considered range from input-output&#13;
ISBN 2-7178-0014-X, 29 francs.                                            and linear programming to the more&#13;
recent nonlinear computable general&#13;
equilibrium (CGE) models. The&#13;
authors consider how these modeis&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
can be used to analyze questions of   Human Resource Develop-             Phae 1: A System of Inter-&#13;
growth and structural change. the     ment and Economic Growth            n   onal Comparisons of&#13;
selecdon of foreign exchange regime.  In Developing Countries: A          Gross Product and&#13;
and the Impact of alternative develop-&#13;
ment strategies on the distribution of  Simultaneous Model                Purct  asing Power&#13;
Income. The empirical applications    David Wheeler                       Irving B. Kravis,&#13;
are based both on cross-country       World Bank Staf Working fpar No.    Zoltan Kenessey, Alan Hleston,&#13;
analysIs and on the experience of par-  40.Jl 18-3         paes icuig     adRbr        u   mr&#13;
ticular countries and demonstrate     407 July 1980.130pages (Including     an  oeresue       rs&#13;
how such models provide a useful      8 appendixes, biblography).         Establishes the methodology and pre-&#13;
framework for policy analysis. Particu-  Stock lo. WP-0407. $5.00.        sents comparisons of gross domestic&#13;
lar attention is focused on the                                           product per capita and currency&#13;
problems of planning and policy for-                                      purchasing power for ten countries In&#13;
mulation in mixed-market economies                                        1970 and six of the same countries&#13;
and on the nature of models required      NEW                             In 1967.&#13;
to capture the Important mechanisms                                       The Johns 11opkins Unioersity Press,&#13;
that constrain policy markets.        Incorporating Uncertainty           1975. 306 pages (including&#13;
Cambridge Uniuersity Prems 32 East    Into Planning of Industrial-        glossary, index).&#13;
57th Street Nlew York, N1.Y. 10022.   Ization Strategies for              LC 73-19352. 15B11 0-8018-1606-8.&#13;
1982. xvll + 526 pages.               Developing Countries                $27.50 (X16.50) hardcover,&#13;
LC 81-12307. ISBNS 0-521-24490-0,     Alexander H. Sarris and             15Bt 0-8018-1669-6, $8.95 (5.50)&#13;
$42.50 hardcouer; ISBl 0-521-27030-8,  Irma Adelman                      paperback.&#13;
$17.95 paperback.                     This survey of existing literature on&#13;
planning under uncertainty focuses&#13;
on issues of international trade and  Phase 1l: Intamtonal CoM-&#13;
NYEW                              Investment allocation. Various ways of  parsons of Real Product&#13;
Incorporating uncertainty Into target-  and Purhasing Powver&#13;
The GlobalFi FratewoIk                planning models are discussed and   Irving B. Kravis, Alan Heston,&#13;
The GloM   Fmmework.,proposals for possible empirical            and Robert Summers&#13;
An Update                             applications are outined.&#13;
Brian Nolan                           World Bank Staff Working Paper Plo.  Updates Phase I and adds six new&#13;
Worl Ban Staf WokingPape No. countries, comparing the flgures for&#13;
This paper presents the methodologi-  503. January 1982. 58 pages (ircluding  the sixteen countries for the years&#13;
cal background to the Global Model-   appendfx. references).               1970 and 1973.&#13;
ling Framework used In the World&#13;
Development Report exercises of the   Stock llo. WP-0503. $3.00.           The Johns Hopkins Uniuersity Press,&#13;
World Bank. It gives an overall view of                                   1978. 274 pages (including&#13;
this framework and discusses In                                             l       fndex'&#13;
some detail the data base supporting  Interdependence In                  giossary. nd).&#13;
the global analysis and the methods   Planning: Multilevel                LC 77-17251. ISBII 0-8018-2019- 7,&#13;
of reconciling data from various      Programming Studies of the           $25.00 (415.00) hardcover; ISBN&#13;
sources.                              Ivory Coast                          0-8018-2020-0, $8.50 (f5.00)&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper        Louis M. Goreux                     paperback.&#13;
rio. 533.1982. 58 pages.              Provides a system for analyzing each&#13;
ISBN5 0-8213-0047-4. $3.00.           component of a country's economy     Phase III: World Product and&#13;
Independently and relates the interde-  Income: International Com-&#13;
pendencues between the components.  parisons of Real GDP&#13;
Human FacitorsrIn            The Johns Hopkins University Press,  Irving B. Kravis, Alan Heston,&#13;
Project Work                          1977. 448 pages (including bibliogra-  and Robert Summers&#13;
Hei Perrett                           phy, index)&#13;
and Francis J. Lethem                 py        '                          This report restates and extends the&#13;
LC 77-4793. 15BN 0-8018-2001-4.     methodology set out in the flrst two&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper {to.   $27.00 (I16.20) hardcover;           volumes. Particular attention is given&#13;
397. June 1980. 85 pages (including   15B1N 0-8018-2006-5, $9.95           to the problem of comparing services&#13;
3 annexes, 5 charts, bibliography).   (X6.00) paperback.                   and to the conlicting demands of&#13;
Stock Yo. WP-039 7. $3.00.                                                 parisons are given of prices, real per&#13;
The International                   capita quantities, and flnal expendi-&#13;
Comparlson Project                  ture components of GDP for thirty-&#13;
four countries for 1975. By reiating&#13;
Three volumes that establish a&#13;
worldwide system of international&#13;
comparisons of real product and of&#13;
the purchasing power of currencies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
the results to certain widely available  A Model of an Agricultural     used to estimate the projects effects&#13;
naUonal Income accounUng data and   Household: Theory and               on key national variables, thus per-&#13;
reiated variables, the authors develop  Evidence                        mitting a full social cost-benefit&#13;
extrapolating equations to estmate       encr                           analysis of the project.&#13;
per capita GDP for the thirty-four  THoward e. Barnum                   Th Johns Hopkins UniuersIty Pess.&#13;
countrIes for 1.950 to 1978. In addi-  and Lyn Squire192                      3pae(icuIgmsan&#13;
tion, the 1975 distribution of world  Innovative model of short-run     lndand&#13;
product by region and per capita    behavior that combines producton&#13;
Income class Is estimated. The      and consumption decisions In a      LC 81-48173. 15BI( 0-8018-2802-3,&#13;
1975 results confirn relations      theomtically consistent fashion for an  S30.00 hardcover.&#13;
between both quantities and prices  agricultural household.&#13;
and per capita income found In the&#13;
earlier volumes.                    The Johns Hopkins UnIuersity Prs,   Rediotribution with Growth&#13;
The Johns Hopkins UnIuersity Press,  1980. xi + 107 pages (Including    Haolis Chenery,&#13;
1982. 398 pages.                    appendx references).MontekS Ahluwal&#13;
LC 81-15569. ISB1N 0-8018-2359-5,   LC 78-21397. ISBN1 0-8018-2225-4,   Clive Bell John H. Duloy,&#13;
$35.00 hardcouer; ISBN1 0-8018-2360-9,  $6.95 (04.75) paperback.        and Richard Jolly&#13;
$15.00 paperback.                                                       Describes existing Inequality In&#13;
The Polltical Economy of           incomes In developing countries and&#13;
Landsat Index Atlas of the          Specalized Farm Credit              proposes a reorientation of develop-&#13;
Developing Countries            Institutions in Low-Income          ment policy to achieve more equitable&#13;
Df the Worid                        Countries                           distribution.&#13;
Fourteen four-color maps, applica-  J. D. Von Pischke,                  Oxford University Pss. 1974; 4th&#13;
tons of Loandsat lmagery reading and  Peter J. ileffeman, and           printing, 1981. 324 pages (including&#13;
uses of the Index maps, and pro-     Dale W. Adams                      annex, bibliography).&#13;
cedure for securing Imagery.                                            ISBNt 0-19-920070-X, $9.95 (15.00)&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper (1o.  paperback.&#13;
The Johns Hopkins UnIversity Press,  446. April 1981. Ill + 99 pages.&#13;
1976.17 pages, 1312" x 21", spiral  Stock No. WP-0446. $5.00.           french: Redistribution et croissance.&#13;
bound.                                                                  P'esses Universitaires de France, 108,&#13;
LC 76-46190. ISBN1 0-8018-1923-7,                                       bouleuard Salnt-Germaln, 75006 Paris,&#13;
$12.00 (1725) paperback.                MEW                             France, 1977.&#13;
ISBN1 22403102, 5820 francs.&#13;
Methodologies for Measur.           Project Evaluation in               Spanish: Redlstribucl6n con creci-&#13;
ing Agricultural Price              Regional Perspective: A             miento. Editorlal Tecnos, 1976.&#13;
Intervention Effects                Study of an Irrigation              ISBNl 84-309-0624-X, 880 pesetas.&#13;
Project In N4orthwest&#13;
Pasquale L. Scandizzo               Malaysia&#13;
and Colin Bruce                     Clive Bell, Peter Hlazell, and&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper tNo.  Roger Slade&#13;
394. June 1980: x + 96 pages        This Innovative study develops quan-&#13;
(Including 4 appendixes, references).  titative methods for measuring the&#13;
Stock (1o. WP-0394. $5.00.          direct and Indirect effects of&#13;
agricultural projects on their sur-&#13;
rounding regional and national&#13;
economies. These methods are then&#13;
applied to a study of the Muda Irriga-&#13;
tion project in northwest Malaysia. A&#13;
linear programming model is used to&#13;
analyze how a project changes the&#13;
farm economy, and a social account-&#13;
Ing matrix of the regional economy Is&#13;
then estimated. This provides the&#13;
basis for a semi-input-output modeL&#13;
which Is used to estimate the Indirect&#13;
effects of the project on Its reglon.&#13;
Thereafter, a similar methodology is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Risk Analysis in                      Techniques for Project                WRIrNs&#13;
Project Apprai"sa                     Appraial under Uncertainty            The Meaning of Technological Mastery&#13;
LusY. PuqenShlomo Reutlinger                                             In Relation to Tmaasfer of Technolo&#13;
LouisY   Pouliquen                    Slm        etnerCarl J.Dahiaun and Larry r. westpa&#13;
Discusses methodological problems     Presents a method of evaluating risk  World Bank Reprmnt Serrs: Eumber 217.&#13;
and the usefulness of simulation;    In Investment projects and means for   Reprinted m Annals of the AmNrican Acad my&#13;
Illustrated by three case studies.    using quantitative measures of risk in  of Political and Social Science. wol. 458 (tlouem-&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press5   decisionmaking.                       ber 1981).12-26.&#13;
1970; 4th printing, 1979. 90 pages.   The Johns Hopkins University Press,   Stock (1o. RP-0217. free of charge.&#13;
LC 79-12739. ISBI5 0-8018-1155-4.     1970; 4th printing, 1979.108 pages&#13;
$5.50 (£3.25) paperback.              (including annex, bibliography).      The Model of an Agricultural&#13;
LC 74-94827. ISBN1 0-8018-1154-6      llousehold In a Multl-Crop Econonoi&#13;
French: L'appreciation du risque dans  S5.9S (S.50) paperback.              The Came of Korea&#13;
Ievaiuation des projets. Dunod Editeur,                                     Choonrg Yong Ahn. lnderjit Slngh,. and&#13;
24-26, bouleuard de '116pltal, 75005                                        Lyn Squire&#13;
Parls, France, 1972.                                                        World Bank Reprint SEries: Number 222.&#13;
What Is a SAM? A Layman's             Reprinted ftom The Review of Economics and&#13;
21 francs.                            Guide to Social Accounting            Statistics, uol. 63. no. 4 (Nlovember 1981:520-25.&#13;
Matrices                              Stock Nio. RP-0222. Free of charge.&#13;
Shadow Prices for Project             Benjamin B. King                      The Relevance of the Dual Economy&#13;
Appraisal In Turkey                   World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    Model: A Case Study of Thaland&#13;
Afsaneh Mashayekhi                    463. June 1981. 59 pages (including   Trent Bertrand and Lyn Squire&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    references).                          World Bank ReprlntI Series: Nfumber 219.&#13;
World                                                    ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~Reprinted from Oxford Economic Papers, uol. .52&#13;
392. May 1980. 57 pages.              Stock No. WP-0463. $3.00.             (1980):480-5L.&#13;
Stock No. WP-0392. $3.00.                                                   Stock /Yo. RP-0219. free of charge.&#13;
Social Cost-Beneflt Analysis:&#13;
A Guide for Country and&#13;
Project Economists to the&#13;
Derivation and Application&#13;
of Economic and Social&#13;
Accounting Prices&#13;
Colin Bruce&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper llo.&#13;
239. August 1976. ii, iil + 143 pages&#13;
(including 6 annexes).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0239. $5.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBUCATIONS&#13;
ORDER FORM&#13;
SEND TO:&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS                                                       WORLD BANK PUBUCATIONS&#13;
P.O. BOX 37525                                            or                  66, AVENUE D'IENA&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013                                                         75116 PARIS, FRANCE&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Name:&#13;
Address:&#13;
Stock or ISBN #                            Author, Title                       Qty.        Price         Total&#13;
Sub-Total Cost:______&#13;
Postage &amp; handling fee for more than two free items ($1.00 each):&#13;
Total copies: _____       Air mail surcharge ($2.00 each):&#13;
TTAL PAYMENT ENCLOSED:&#13;
Make checks payable: WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
Prepayment on orders from individuals is requested. Purchase orders are accepted from booksellers, library suppliers, libraries, and institutions.&#13;
All prices include cost of postage by the least expensive means. The prices and publication dates quoted in this Catalog are subject to change&#13;
without notice.&#13;
No refunds will be given for items that cannot be filled. Credit will be applied towards future orders.&#13;
No more than two free publications will be provided without charge. Requests for additional copies will be filled at a charge of US 51.00 per&#13;
copy to cover handling and postage costs.&#13;
Airmail delivery will require a prepayment of US f2.00 per copy.&#13;
Mall-order payment to the World Bank need not be in U.S. dollars, but the amount remitted must be at the rate of exchange on the day the&#13;
order is placed. The World Bank will also accept Unesco coupons.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                      * European Office                Tokyo Office                       U&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                  66, avenue d'I6na             Kokusai Building,&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.       75116 Paris, France           1-1 Marunpuchi 3.chorne&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234            Telephone: (1) 723-54.21      Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100 Japan&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK           Telex: 842-620628             Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                           Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0244-2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554834">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/09/1554834/shadow-prices-economic-appraisal-projects-application-thailand
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/09/1554834/shadow-prices-economic-appraisal-projects-application-thailand</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1983/09/1554834/shadow-prices-economic-appraisal-projects-application-thailand</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/12/000178830_98101903421467/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/12/000178830_98101903421467/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-07-12T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1983-09-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Shadow prices for economic appraisal of
            projects : an application to Thailand
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The study reviews past estimates of
            shadow prices in Thailand and their use in World Bank
            appraisals. Applying the Squire-van der Tak methodology, it
            proceeds to estimate conversion factors for project analysis
            in Thailand. Efficiency conversion factors were estimated
            for broad categories of commodities, as well as for selected
            sub-categories, including construction, electricity,
            transportation and rice. Estimates were also made of the
            shadow wage rate and of the opportunity cost of capital and
            land, drawing on an assessment of factor markets in
            Thailand. An annex also provides estimates of social
            conversion factors allowing for growth and income
            distribution considerations. Besides providing up-to-date
            estimates of shadow prices (conversion factors) for use in
            economic (and social) analysis of projects in Thailand, the
            study provides a case study of application of the Squire-van
            der Tak methodology. It also confirms the findings of other
            studies that Thailand is a country with relatively
            undistorted prices, as indicated by the fact that there is
            relatively little dispersion in conversion factors and that
            most of them are close to unity.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Shadow prices for economic appraisal of
            projects : an application to Thailand
        </docna>
        <display_title>Shadow prices for economic
            appraisal of projects : an application to Thailand</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1983/09/1554834/shadow-prices-economic-appraisal-projects-application-thailand</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Access to Markets,Markets and Market Access</subtopic>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>International Economics and Trade</teratopic>
        <count>Thailand</count>
        <authors>
            <author>AHMED, S.</author>
            <author>EM1</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southeast Asia!$!80471</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903421467</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Macro/non-trade</subsc>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 609</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>International Economics and Trade</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0244-2</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Case studies; Cost-benefit analysis;
            Economic analysis; Project appraisal; Shadow prices; Shadow
            wages; Sociological analysis
            Accounting,affiliates,agricultural
            output,agriculture,Bank of Thailand,Benefit Analysis,border
            price,Capital Goods,classical economists,consumers,cost of
            capital,country comparisons,demand curve,demand
            elasticity,development projects,Development
            Strategy,Distortionary Effects,economic activity,Economic
            Analysis,Economic development,economic history,economic
            power,ECONOMIC VALUE,Elasticity,Employment,exchange
            rate,exploitation,exports,externalities,Financial
            Markets,free trade,Government Intervention,import
            quotas,imports,income,income
            distribution,inefficiency,Intermediate Goods,Labor
            Market,Labor Markets,laws,marginal cost,marginal
            product,Marginal Productivity,MARGINAL PROPENSITY TO
            SAVE,Marginal Utility,market economy,market mechanism,market
            prices,Marketing,middlemen,natural monopolies,opportunity
            cost,perfect information,price control,price controls,Price
            Policies,producers,profitability,public enterprises,public
            goods,RESERVE REQUIREMENT,resource
            allocation,retail,sales,Shadow prices,SHADOW PRICING,social
            marginal cost,social prices,social pricing,streams,tax
            rates,taxation,trade policies,Trade taxes,transport,value
            added,Wage Determination,watershed,Wealth,welfare
            function,wholesalers,willingness to pay,world markets
        </keywd>
        <owner>EAC</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southeast Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP609</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Employment and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Improving Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Market Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets, Job Creation and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textiles</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Minimum Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Price Controls</ml:concept><ml:concept>Price Controls </ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Thailand</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>