<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP698&#13;
The Potential Impact of Changes in Fertility&#13;
on Infant, Child, and Maternal Mortality&#13;
James Trussell&#13;
Anne R. Pebley&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 698&#13;
POPULATION AND DEVELOPMENT SERIES&#13;
Number 23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page&#13;
I.      Introduction .....  ......  ..*........................................ 1&#13;
II.     Sources ............................................... .    . .. 5&#13;
III.    Impact on Mortality of Changing Maternal Age,&#13;
Parity, and Birth Spacing Patterns ...................... 11&#13;
Infant and Child Mtortality      ..     .. 0.     ........ ..... . 11&#13;
Maternal Mortality .............. ................. .*..*..*.~......23&#13;
IV.    Actual Impact of Family Planning Programs ................ 26&#13;
V.      Summary and Conclusions ...........     ..     ............... 29&#13;
Notes .... . . . .  . . . . .  . . . .  . .  . . 31. .. .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. Introduction&#13;
Certain aspects of reproductive behavior, such as the maternal age and&#13;
parity at the time a child is born and child spacing, have long been&#13;
thought to affect both a mother's and a child's chance of survival.'&#13;
During the transition from high to low fertility, as contraceptive use&#13;
increases, these variables change in ways which may alter child and&#13;
maternal mortality rates.      For example)   the proportion of    live births&#13;
occurring to women at high parities and older ages is likely to decline&#13;
significantly.   Reduction in maternal and child mortality is frequently one&#13;
of  the   stated  objectives  of   family  planning   programs  in  developing&#13;
countries. Nevertheless, there are relatively few estimates of the size of&#13;
the mortality reductions thought to accompany changes in fertility.&#13;
In this paper, we explore the relation between changes in the timing&#13;
and quantity of fertility, such as those that may result from an effective&#13;
family planning program in developing countries, and changes in child and&#13;
maternal mortality.    First, we outline mechanisms through which reproduc-&#13;
tive behavior may influence the levels of child and maternal mortality in a&#13;
population.    Next, we use results from recent      studies to estimate the&#13;
changes in mortality which might result from hypothetical alterations in&#13;
maternal age, birth order and birth spacing distributions of live births.&#13;
Finally, we discuss the problem of predicting how these distributions would&#13;
actually change as the result of implementing effective family planning&#13;
programs or, more generally, increasing contraceptive use in populations of&#13;
developing countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
We corisidler three ways in which the implementation oE a successful&#13;
family planning program may affect child mortality:        1) by changing the&#13;
ages at wh:.ch women have childrern, 2) by reducing the proportion of births&#13;
which occur at high parities     and 3) by lengthening the spacing between&#13;
births.   Previous research suggests that all three changes would reduce&#13;
infant and child mortality.2&#13;
When examined one at a time, both maternal age at the time of a birth&#13;
and a child's birth order are consistently found to be relat:ed to the risk&#13;
of infant and child mortality, usually in a J-shaped pattern [Nortman,&#13;
1974; Omram,   1976 and 19811.    That is, the risk is moderately high for&#13;
infants of very young mothers and for first births, declines for infants of&#13;
mothers in their twenties and of birth orders 2 and 3, and then rises with&#13;
further increases in maternal age and birth order.       Maternal age seems to&#13;
be related to the risk of mortaLity even when parity is controlled, and&#13;
vice versa;    there is, moreover,    likely to be an important interaction&#13;
between the two.&#13;
Nortman [1974:4] argues that the basic curvilinear relationship&#13;
between infant mortality, birth order, and maternal age results from&#13;
underlying biological factorsl.    Very young women's reproductive systems,&#13;
for example, may not be adequately prepared for the stress of a pregnancy,&#13;
while advanced aging seems to reduce the efficiency of the entire&#13;
reproductive process.    Higher orcler births may be at greater risk because&#13;
of general exhaustion of a woman's reproductive resources, whereas a first&#13;
birth may be riskier because the body is undergoing partuition for the&#13;
first time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
Observed maternal age and birth order differentials in infant and&#13;
child mortality may be exaggerated, however, for at least two reasons.&#13;
First, socioeconomic status may be a confounding factor. Poorer women, who&#13;
experience higher child mortality, contribute disproportionate shares of&#13;
higher order births and births at very early and late maternal ages.&#13;
Second, the effect of high parity, or of high age when parity is not&#13;
controlled, may reflect the harmful impact on child survival of closely&#13;
spaced  births.    Hence,   it  is  essential  to  control  for  socioeconomic&#13;
correlates of child mortality and for birth spacing patterns when trying to&#13;
isolate the real effects of maternal age and parity.3&#13;
Most discussion about the ways in which close spacing of births may&#13;
contribute   to   higher   child  mortality   center   around   two  principal&#13;
mechanisms. One possibility is that competition for limited maternal and&#13;
familial resources among closely spaced children [Omram, 19811 may&#13;
jeopardize the health of both the older and younger sibling.      For example,&#13;
the beginning of another pregnancy shortly after a previous birth may&#13;
result in early weaning of the first child.      Similarly, the younger child&#13;
may also receive less adult attention because of competition from a&#13;
slightly older sibling with similar needs. The second hypothesis suggests&#13;
that a mother's nutritional status is eroded by a rapid sequence of&#13;
pregnancies and periods of lactation [Jelliffe and Jelliffe, 1978].       Poor&#13;
maternal nutritional status increases the risk of premature births and low&#13;
birth weight (small-for-date) babies, who have a poorer chance for survival&#13;
[Fedrick and Adelstein,    19731.    Malnourished mothers may also be less&#13;
successful at breastfeeding their children either because of diminished&#13;
quantity or quality of breastmilk or because low birth weight infants have&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
a harder time breastfeedingl.    Hence, taken together, the two mechanisms&#13;
suggest that close spacing of two births may result in poorer survival&#13;
chances of both, and therefore thai: we might expect that lengthening birth&#13;
intervals wc,uld increase the overall likelihood of child survival.&#13;
Increased use of contraception may also lower the riskl of maternal&#13;
death  per  birth  (the  maternal   mortality  ratio4)  by:  1)  reducing  the&#13;
proportion o-f births occurring to youngest and oldest women; 2) reducing&#13;
the  proport:ion  of  births  at   high  parity;  and   3)  lengthening  birtl&#13;
intervals. As a consequence of these changes, the maternal raortality rate&#13;
is further Lowered because chiLdbearing is less frequent.5     AIs in the case&#13;
of infant and child mortality, there is evidence that the risk of maternal&#13;
mortality is higher for women under 20 and over 35, and for women at parity&#13;
C and very high parities (see, for example, Nortman [19741 and Tietze&#13;
[19771).  Bv contrast, little is known about the effect of birth spacing on&#13;
maternal mortality, although it is likely that maternal depletion (if it&#13;
exists) wou'Ld increase the risk oF maternal mortality among women with very&#13;
short birth intervals.    An additional effect on maternal mortality of an&#13;
increase in contraceptive use would be a reduction in the overall level of&#13;
fertility.   Thus, a smaller fraction of women would be exposed to the risk&#13;
of maternal mortality in any given year.       In summary, increased contra-&#13;
ceptive use is likely to result Ln lower maternal mortality because of a&#13;
reduction in both the number of deaths per birth and the number of births.&#13;
How large an impact could changes in fertility resulting from a family&#13;
planning program have on irLfant, child and maternal mortality? In the next&#13;
section we describe recent studies which explore the relation between&#13;
fertility variables and mortality.      We then employ results    from these&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
studies to estimate the magnitude of changes in mortality which might be&#13;
expected from different types of fertility changes.&#13;
II. Sources&#13;
We draw on the results of five studies to assess the potential impact&#13;
of increased contraceptive use on infant and child mortality.        The first&#13;
two, by Martin et al. [19831 and Trussell and Hammerslough [1983], employ&#13;
hazard models to estimate the effects of several covariates, including&#13;
maternal age and parity, on mortality in Indonesia, Pakistan, the&#13;
Philippines, and Sri Lanka. Both studies find significant effects of these&#13;
two variables on the risk of dying.      In the third study, Holland [19831&#13;
also uses hazard models to assess the effect of breastfeeding on infant&#13;
mortality in Malaysia.     To avoid confounding his estimates, he includes&#13;
several other covariates as controls, including the length of the prior&#13;
birth interval.    This variable is constructed by combining it with birth&#13;
order so that first births can be included in the analysis.6&#13;
A fourth study by Hobcraft et al. [1983] focuses specifically on the&#13;
effects of birth spacing.    The investigators are interested in estimating&#13;
the relationship between mortality of an "index" child and the number of&#13;
other births which occurred within certain time periods before and after&#13;
that child's birth.     The periods they select are: 2-6 years before the&#13;
birth of the index child, 0-2 years before, and 0-17 months (for 1ql) or 0-&#13;
29 months (for 3q2) after the birth of the index child.7 By separating the&#13;
effects of prior intervals from the effects of those subsequent, they hoped&#13;
to determine whether short child spacing is harmful because of maternal&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-0-&#13;
depletion or because of sibling competition for resources.          Since they&#13;
find a negative association betweea survival probabilities of the index&#13;
child  and  closely   spaced  subsequent  siblings,   they  conclude  that  the&#13;
competition   effect  is  strong  since   the  principal  impact   of  maternal&#13;
depletion syndrome is thought to operate through a short prior interval.&#13;
They also find that prior close spacing has a substantial negative impact&#13;
on survival probabilities, but they are unable to distinguish possible&#13;
competition effects from the possibLe maternal depletion syndrome.        Since&#13;
the study is a cross-national analysis involving 26 countries, only one&#13;
control variable (mother's education) was included, to reduce costs.&#13;
Finally, Cleland and Sathar [1983] use a sample of births occurring&#13;
between one   mnd fifteen years prior to the Pakistan Fertility Survey to&#13;
explore the relation between birth spacing and infant and child mortality&#13;
in greater depth.     They calculate   infant  (1q0), early childhood    (1qj),&#13;
and later childhood (3q2) mortality rates by the length of the preceding&#13;
birth  interval and by whethler or not the previous child survived until&#13;
his/her second birthday.     Their results indicate that a strong positive&#13;
relation between the length of the preceding interval and child survival&#13;
generally persists even when the survivorship of previous child, maternal&#13;
education, rural-urban residence, sex of the child, maternal age, and&#13;
parity are held constant.8     One possible explanation for this association&#13;
would be that women breastfed all children for similar lengths of time;&#13;
those women who lactate     for short periods,   therefore, would have short&#13;
interbirth intervals and also higher infant and child mortality.         If so,&#13;
then  the  association   between   interval  length  and  mortality   would  be&#13;
spurious.   Cleland and Sathar conclude, however, that early weaning of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page&#13;
I.     Introductio-n .................................................... l&#13;
II.     Sources.................................................   *.. .5&#13;
III.    Impact on Mortality of Changing Maternal Age,&#13;
Parity, and Birth Spacing Patterns ............. l    l&#13;
Infant and Child Mortality            ......... .11&#13;
Maternal Mortality ......... o......................... .o........... 23&#13;
IV.    Actual Impact of Family Planning Programs ..................26&#13;
V.      Summary and Conclusions ......... . ...... o....... ........ 29&#13;
Notess  o o s .  . ....    ,..  oo o , * * * . .  ... .,. o o o. .  .  .  31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. Introduction&#13;
Certain aspects of reproductive behavior, such as the maternal age and&#13;
parity at the time a child is born and child spacing, have long been&#13;
thought to affect both a mother's and a child's chance of survival.1&#13;
During the transition from high to low fertility, as contraceptive use&#13;
increases, these variables change in ways which may alter child and&#13;
maternal mortality rates.      For example,   the proportion of    live births&#13;
occurring to women at high parities and older ages is likely to decline&#13;
significantly. Reduction in maternal and child mortality is frequently one&#13;
of the stated objectives of family planning programs in developing&#13;
countries. Nevertheless, there are relatively few estimates of the size of&#13;
the mortality reductions thought to accompany changes in fertility.&#13;
In this paper, we explore the relation between changes in the timing&#13;
and quantity of fertility, such as those that may result from an effective&#13;
family planning program in developing countries, and changes in child and&#13;
maternal mortality.    First, we outline mechanisms through which reproduc-&#13;
tive behavior may influence the levels of child and maternal mortality in a&#13;
population.    Next, we use results from recent      studies to estimate    the&#13;
changes in mortality which might result from hypothetical alterations in&#13;
maternal age, birth order and birth spacing distributions of live births.&#13;
Finally, we discuss the problem of predicting how these distributions would&#13;
actually change as the result of implementing effective family planning&#13;
programs or, more generally, increasing contraceptive use in populations of&#13;
developing countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
We consider three ways in which the implementation of a successful&#13;
family planning program may affect child mortality:        1) by changing the&#13;
ages at which women have children,    2) by reducing the proportion of births&#13;
which occuc at high parities and 3) by lengthening the spacing between&#13;
births.   Previous research suggeSts that all three changes would reduce&#13;
infant and child mortality. 2&#13;
When examined one at a time, both maternal age at the t:ime of a birth&#13;
and a child's birth order are consistently found to be related to the risk&#13;
of infant and child mortality, usually in a J-shaped pattern [Nortman,&#13;
1974; Omram,   1976 and 1981].    That is, the risk is moderately high for&#13;
infants of very young mothers and for first births, declines for infants of&#13;
mothers in their twenties and of birth orders 2 and 3, and then rises with&#13;
further increases in maternal age and birth order.       Maternal age seems to&#13;
be related to the risk of mortality even when parity is controlled, and&#13;
vice versa;    there is, moreover,    likely to be an important interaction&#13;
between the two.&#13;
Nortman [1974:4] argues that the basic curvilinear relationship&#13;
between infant mortality, birth order, and maternal age results from&#13;
underlying biological factors.     Very young women's reproductive systems,&#13;
for example, may not be adequately prepared for the stress of a pregnancy,&#13;
while advanced aging seems to reduce the efficiency of the entire&#13;
reproductive process.    Higher order births may be at greater risk because&#13;
of general exhaustion of a woman"s reproductive resources, whereas a first&#13;
birth may be riskier because the body is undergoing partuition for the&#13;
first time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
Observed maternal age and birth order differentials in infant and&#13;
child mortality may be exaggerated, however, for at least two reasons.&#13;
First, socioeconomic status may be a confounding factor. Poorer women, who&#13;
experience higher child mortality, contribute disproportionate shares of&#13;
higher order births and births at very early and late maternal ages.&#13;
Second, the effect of high parity, or of high age when parity is not&#13;
controlled, may reflect the harmful impact on child survival of closely&#13;
spaced  births.    Hence,   it  is  essential  to  control  for  socioeconomic&#13;
correlates of child mortality and for birth spacing patterns when trying to&#13;
isolate the real effects of maternal age and parity.3&#13;
Most discussion about the ways in which close spacing of births may&#13;
contribute   to   higher   child  mortality   center   around   two  principal&#13;
mechanisms.   One possibility is that competition for limited maternal and&#13;
familial resources among closely spaced children [Omram, 1981] may&#13;
jeopardize the health of both the older and younger sibling.      For example,&#13;
the beginning of another pregnancy shortly after a previous birth may&#13;
result in early weaning of the first child.      Similarly, the younger child&#13;
may also receive less adult attention because of competition from a&#13;
slightly older sibling with similar needs. The second hypothesis suggests&#13;
that  a   mother's nutritional    status  is eroded by a rapid sequence of&#13;
pregnancies and periods of lactation [Jelliffe and Jelliffe, 19781.       Poor&#13;
maternal nutritional status increases the risk of premature births and low&#13;
birth weight (small-for-date) babies, who have a poorer chance for survival&#13;
[Fedrick and Adelstein,    19731.   Malnourished mothers may also be      less&#13;
successful at breastfeeding their children either because of diminished&#13;
quantity or quality of breastmilk or because low birth weight infants have&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-.4-&#13;
a harder tirne breastfeeding.     Hence, taken together, the two mechanisms&#13;
suggest that cLose spacing of two births may result in poorer survival&#13;
chances of both, and therefore that we might expect that lengthening birth&#13;
intervals would increase the overalL likelihood of child survival.&#13;
Increased use of contraception may also lower the risk of maternal&#13;
death  per   birth  (the  maternal  mortality   ratio4)  by:  1)  reducing   the&#13;
proportion of bfirths occurring to youngest and oldest women; 2) reducing&#13;
tae   proportion  of   births  at  h[gh   parity;  and   3)  lengthening   birth&#13;
intervals.   As a consequence of these changes, the maternal mortality rate&#13;
is further lowered because childbearing is less frequent.5 As in the case&#13;
of infant and child mortality, there is evidence that the risk of maternal&#13;
mortality is higher for women under 20 and over 35, and for women at parity&#13;
0 and very high parities (see, for example, Nortman [1974] and Tietze&#13;
[19771).  By contrast, little is known about the effect of birth spacing on&#13;
maternal mortality, although it is likely that maternal depletion (if it&#13;
exists) would increase the risk oE maternal mortality among women with very&#13;
short birth intervals.    An additional effect on maternal mortality of an&#13;
increase in contraceptive use would be a reduction in the overall level of&#13;
fertility. Thus, a smaller fraction of women would be exposed to the risk&#13;
of maternal mortality in any given year.        In summary, increased contra-&#13;
ceptive use is likely to result in lower maternal mortality because of a&#13;
reduction in both the number of deaths per birth and the number of births.&#13;
How large an impact could changes in fertility resulting from a family&#13;
planning program have on infant, child and maternal mortality?     In the next&#13;
section we describe recent studies which explore the relation between&#13;
fertility  variables  and mortality.     We then employ results     from these&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
studies to estimate the magnitude of changes in mortality which might be&#13;
expected from different types of fertility changes.&#13;
II. Sources&#13;
We draw on the results of five studies to assess the potential impact&#13;
of increased contraceptive use on infant and child mortality.        The first&#13;
two, by Martin et al. [1983] and Trussell and Hammerslough [1983], employ&#13;
hazard models to estimate the effects of several covariates, including&#13;
maternal age and parity, on mortality in Indonesia, Pakistan, the&#13;
Philippines, and Sri Lanka. Both studies find significant effects of these&#13;
two variables on the risk of dying.      In the third study, Holland [1983]&#13;
also uses hazard models to assess the effect of breastfeeding on infant&#13;
mortality in Malaysia.     To avoid confounding his estimates, he includes&#13;
several other covariates as controls, including the length of the prior&#13;
birth interval. This variable is constructed by combining it with birth&#13;
order so that first births can be included in the analysis.6&#13;
A fourth study by Hobcraft et al. [1983] focuses specifically on the&#13;
effects of birth spacing.    The investigators are interested in estimating&#13;
the relationship between mortality of an "index" child and the number of&#13;
other births which occurred within certain time periods before and after&#13;
that child's birth.     The periods they select are: 2-6 years before the&#13;
birth of the index child, 0-2 years before, and 0-17 months (for lq1) or 0-&#13;
29 months (for 3q2) after the birth of the index child.7 By separating the&#13;
effects of prior intervals from the effects of those subsequent, they hoped&#13;
to determine whether short child spacing is harmful because of maternal&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6-&#13;
depletion or because of sibling competition for resources.        Since they&#13;
find a negative association between survival probabilities of the index&#13;
child and closeLy spaced subsequent siblings, they conclude that the&#13;
competition effect is strong since the principal impact of maternal&#13;
depletion syndrome is thought: to' olperate through a short prior interval.&#13;
They also find that prior close spacing has a substantial negative impact&#13;
on survival probabilities, but they are unable to distinguish possible&#13;
competition effects from the possible maternal depletion syndrome.      Since&#13;
the study is a cross-nationail analy'sis involving 26 countries, only one&#13;
control variable (mother's education) was included, to reduce costs.&#13;
Finally, Cleland and Sathar [19831 use a sample of birthls occurring&#13;
between one and fifteen years prior to the Pakistan Fertility Survey to&#13;
explore the relation between birth spacing and infant and child mortality&#13;
in greater depth.     They calculate infant (lq0), early childhood     (lql),&#13;
and later childhood (3q2) mortality rates by the length of the preceding&#13;
birth interval and by whether or not the previous child survived until&#13;
his/her second birthday.     Their results indicate that a strong positive&#13;
relation between the length of the preceding interval and child survival&#13;
generally persists even when the survivorship of previous child, maternal&#13;
education, rural-urban residence, sex of the child, maternal age, and&#13;
parity are held constant.8    One possible explanation for this association&#13;
would be that women breastfed all children for similar lengths of time;&#13;
those women who lactate for shLort periods, therefore, would have short&#13;
interbirth intervals and also higher infant and child mortality.       If so,&#13;
then the association between interval length and mortality would be&#13;
sparious. Cleland and Sathar conclude, however, that early weaning of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
index child cannot, in general, explain the association. They also examine&#13;
the effect of subsequent interval length on child mortality and find that&#13;
short subsequent intervals have a negative effect on child survival,&#13;
principally   because  of  earlier weaning.     They  conclude   that  maternal&#13;
depletion is a more plausible explanation for the relation between child&#13;
spacing and infant and child mortality since this association is not&#13;
diluted by inclusion of information on the survivorship of the previous&#13;
child.&#13;
All the analysts except Holland use World Fertility Survey data.&#13;
Holland's results come from the Malaysian Family Life Survey (MFLS),&#13;
conducted by the Malaysian Department of Statistics, Survey Malaysia, and&#13;
the Rand Corporation. The MFLS and WFS data sets that have been evaluated&#13;
have been shown to be of high quality.        The variables included in each&#13;
study for each country are shown in Table 1.         This table also includes&#13;
estimates of 1qO and 4q1 for each population from Hobcraft et al. [1983].&#13;
In the next section of this paper, we assess the likely proportionate&#13;
changes in these indices of child mortality rates that would be induced by&#13;
changing observed distributions     of births by maternal age, birth order,&#13;
and spacing patterns.&#13;
Information on the levels, trends, and correlates of maternal&#13;
mortality in developing countries is far rarer, and measurement is much&#13;
more difficult, than for infant and child mortality. Part of the reason is&#13;
that reproductive complications are only one of the many causes of death&#13;
among women of reproductive ages.       Thus,  an accurate classification of&#13;
deaths by cause is required to determine the level of maternal mortality.&#13;
Even in the United States, maternal mortality is believed to be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
TABLE  1. AnaLyses employed in asse!ssing     the effect of famiLy planning on&#13;
inf.ant and child mortality.    Countries are listed by region, and&#13;
within region by descending value of 5q0 (not shown).&#13;
Factor-s        Birth       Reference    Reference&#13;
COUNTRY          Source a    in model1b      cohorts        lq0 c         q,c&#13;
Africa&#13;
Senegal            I         M,PB,SB        1963-73        120           151&#13;
Lesotho            1         M,PB,SB        1962-72        132           054&#13;
Ken'ia             1         M,PB,SB         1962-73       095           064&#13;
Sud.ln             1         M,PB,SB        1963-74        076           063&#13;
Ghana              1         M,PB,SB        1964-75        075           058&#13;
Americas&#13;
Haiti              1         M,PB,SB         1962-72       147           082&#13;
Peru               1         M,PB,:SB        1962-73       107           064&#13;
Ecu.ador           1         M,PB,SB         1964-74       085           052&#13;
MexLco             1         M,PB,SB         1961-72       075           036&#13;
Colombia           I         M,PB,SB         1961-71       068           042&#13;
Costa Rica         1         M,PB,SB        1961-71        071           019&#13;
Guyana             1         M,,PB,SB        1960-70       055           014&#13;
Panarna            1         M, PB,SB       1960-71        044           018&#13;
Jamaica            1         MN PB,SB       1960-71        041           014&#13;
Asia&#13;
Nepal              1         M,PB,SB         1961-71       168           096&#13;
Bangladesh         1         M,PB,SB         1960-71       136           080&#13;
Pakistan           1         M,PB,SB         1960-70       130           077&#13;
Pakistan           3         M,F,TP,A,S,&#13;
BO,R,U         -1941-75       130           077&#13;
Pakistan           5         M,A,PB,SB,&#13;
S,BO,U,BF,SS   -1960-75       130           077&#13;
Indonesia          1         M,PB,SB        1961-71        106           081&#13;
Indonesia          3         M,F,TP,A,S,&#13;
BO,R,U        -1972-76        106           081&#13;
Thailand           1         M,PB,SB         1960-70       079           034&#13;
Jordan             1         M,PB,SB         1961-71       069           026&#13;
Syria              1         M,PB,SB        1963-73        067           025&#13;
Philippines        1         M,PB,SB         1963-73       055           012&#13;
Philippines        3         M,F,TP,A,W,L,&#13;
S,BO,T,R,U    -1944-78        055           012&#13;
Sri Lanka          1         M, PB,SB        1960-70       055           024&#13;
Sri Lanka          4         M,F,TP,A,W,S,&#13;
B0,T,E,U       -1941-75       055            024&#13;
Korea              1         M,PB,SB         1959-69       053           021&#13;
Malaysia           1         M,PB,SB         1959-69       043           009&#13;
Malaysia           2         BF,M,BW,BO,&#13;
PB,TP,S,,ET?,W,A '-1942-76   043           009&#13;
a) Sources: 1) Hobcraft et al., 11983]; 2) Holland [1983]; 3) Martin et al.,&#13;
[1983]; 4) Trussell anT H[ammerslough     [1983];    5) Cleland  and  Sathar&#13;
[19831.&#13;
b) Factors:    M-mother's education; F-father's    education; TP--time period   of&#13;
birth; A-age of mother; PB-previous birth interval; SB-subsequent birth&#13;
interval; W-water supply; L-lighting source; S-sex; BO-birth order;&#13;
T-toilet facilities; R-region; E-ethnicity; U-urban/rural; BF-breast-&#13;
feeding; BW-birth weight; SS-survival status of previous child.&#13;
c) Reference lq0 and 4q:      pertains to the birth cohorts for each country&#13;
listed for source (1).   Values taken from Hobcraft et al. [1983], Table 1.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9-&#13;
underestimated by at least 25 percent [Sachs et al., 19821.       Furthermore,&#13;
even in high mortality and fertility settings, maternal mortality is a rare&#13;
occurrence.    For  example,   Chen et al.    [19771 report   a high maternal&#13;
mortality ratio (maternal deaths per 1,000 live births) for Matlab Thana,&#13;
Bangladesh of 5.7 deaths per 1000 live births.       By  contrast, the infant&#13;
mortality rate in Matlab for the same period was 124 deaths per 1000 live&#13;
births.   The maternal mortality rate was 0.9 maternal deaths per 1000 women&#13;
years of exposure between the ages of 15 and 49, indicating that the&#13;
probability of a woman dying from a maternity-related cause was small&#13;
indeed.&#13;
The majority of studies of maternal mortality in LDCs concern the&#13;
experience of women who enter a maternity hospital for delivery and/or&#13;
treatment of pregnancy complications.     One example is given by Chi et al.&#13;
[1981] using data from admissions to 12 teaching hospitals in Indonesia.&#13;
The obvious problem with generalizing from such results, particularly in a&#13;
poor country, is that only a select sample of women deliver in a hospital&#13;
and, furthermore, that women who are suffering serious complications are&#13;
more likely to be hospitalized.&#13;
By contrast, Chen et al. [19741 were able to follow an entire popula-&#13;
tion of women in Matlab Thana, Bangladesh. Their results by age and parity&#13;
are shown in Table 2.    To our knowledge, this is the only population-based&#13;
study available that reports rates cross-classified by age and parity. In&#13;
the next section, we consider the possible consequences for maternal&#13;
mortality of altering distributions of births by either maternal age or&#13;
parity and of lowering the fertility level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-10-&#13;
TABIIE 2. Maternal mortality ratio lper thousand live births by maternal age and&#13;
maternal parity, Matlab Thana, 1968-1970 study.&#13;
Parity&#13;
Maternal                                                                     All&#13;
age (years)                    0-1        2-3         4-5     6 or more   parities&#13;
10-19                         8.8         3.1        45.4        0.0         8.6&#13;
(4,069)       (323)       (22)         (2)    (4,416)&#13;
20-29                          4.5        3.6         5.8        4.5         4.5&#13;
(2,449)     (4,439)    (3,072)     (1,326)   (11,286)&#13;
30-39                         12.8        2.5         2.5         7.4        5.8&#13;
(78)       (396)    (1,212)     (2,981)    (4,667)&#13;
40-49                          0.0        0.0         0.0         8.0        6.7&#13;
(7)        (13)       (54)       (373)      (447)&#13;
All Ages                       7.2        3.5         5.0         6.6        5.7&#13;
(6,603)     (5,171)    (4,360)     (4,682)   (20,816)&#13;
Source: Adapted from Chen et aL., [19771&#13;
( ) = Figures in parentheses are the numbers of live births.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
III.  Impact on Mortality of Changing Maternal Age,&#13;
Parity and Birth Spacing Patterns&#13;
Infant and Child Mortality&#13;
To estimate the effect on mortality of changes in fertility, we must&#13;
assume that maternal age, parity and birth spacing are causally related to&#13;
infant and child mortality when the effects of potentially confounding&#13;
variables are controlled, as in the studies described above. We can, then,&#13;
use the results of statistical models reported in these studies to&#13;
predict how large a mortality change would result from a specific fertility&#13;
pattern change. The methods employed to quantify the impact of a change in&#13;
the fertility variables are briefly outlined below and are described fully&#13;
in the Appendix. The reader is warned that assumptions described in the&#13;
Appendix are essential to a full understanding of the results.&#13;
Our calculations are based on parameter estimates and sample&#13;
characteristics reported in the studies described above.       In each study,&#13;
the analysts estimated the parameters (or coefficients) of equations&#13;
linking the probability of surviving to individual characteristics of the&#13;
child -- such as the age of his/her mother and birth order.          To give a&#13;
simple example, we might estimate the coefficients a and b in the&#13;
equation:&#13;
Pi = a + b xi + error,&#13;
where pi takes on the value one if the child died and zero otherwise and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-L2-&#13;
xiLs the birtlh, order of the child.  Once a and b have been estimated, using&#13;
staindard statistical  procedures   (such as regression), we coald use the&#13;
equation    to   predict   the probability p.that the jth child died&#13;
(p.   a + bx.).   We could also predict the average probability of dying if&#13;
the average birth order of the sample, for example, was 3.      In this simple&#13;
model, p would then equal eL + b(3). We could further estimate the change&#13;
in p   that would result from reducing average birth order from 7 to 3.&#13;
Clearly, all these results depends both on the values of the estimated&#13;
parameters a and b and on the magnitude of the hypothesized change in the&#13;
independent   rariable,  x.   In the calculations   that  follow, we consider&#13;
precisely this type of change, except that the prediction equations are&#13;
more complex than the linear function shown above and include several&#13;
independent variables.&#13;
Results from this type of calculation using equations from Martin et&#13;
al. [1983] and Trussell and Hammerslough [19831, shown in Table 3, indicate&#13;
that the children of young mothers (&lt;20 years of age) suffer much higher&#13;
mortality  than the children of older mothers.         In this and subsequent&#13;
tables, the proportionate changes indicate how much mortality rates would&#13;
change if independent variables were changed from their present values to&#13;
new hypothetical values.    Hence, the results shown are relative to actual&#13;
values of the independent variables in the samples.      To determine how much&#13;
change   would  occur   if  explanatory   variables  were   altered   from  one&#13;
hypothetical distribution to another, a simple calculation is required.&#13;
Fcr example, if all births9 in Sri Lanka occurred to women under 20, infant&#13;
mortality would rise by 22 percent, as shown in Table 3, and if all births&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-13-&#13;
TABLE   3.  Effects of Changing Maternal Age (A) at Birth and Birth Order (BO) on lq0&#13;
and 4q,.&#13;
Effect of changes in percent&#13;
A=20-34&#13;
Reference                                   No BO    and no&#13;
COUNTRY        Sourcec     lq0    4q,      A&lt;20    A=20-34    A&gt;35      4+b     BO 4+b&#13;
Pakistan         3          130   077       36        -5       -19      -7        -12&#13;
Indonesia        3         106    081       38       -6        -15      -11       -16&#13;
Philippines      3         055    012       28       -2        -1       -9        -11&#13;
Sri Lanka        4         055    024       22       -5         15      -5         -9&#13;
a.  Values of all other variables held constant at means.          Only changes in lq0&#13;
presented; changes in 4q, differ slightly.&#13;
b. Births at orders 4 and higher are distributed proportionately to the categories&#13;
birth order = 1 and birth order = 2 and 3.&#13;
c.  Source:   3) Martin et al., [19831, 4) Trussell and Hammerslough [19831.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-14-&#13;
occurred to women 20-34, infant mortality would fall by five percent.&#13;
Hence, if we moved from a situation where births occurred only to women&#13;
under 20 to another circumstance in which births occurred only to women 20-&#13;
34, infant mortality would faLl by 1--(.95/1.22)=22.1 percent.      Though the&#13;
prime reproductive ages are generally considered to be between 20 to 34,&#13;
the hazard model results reported in the original paper for Pakistan and&#13;
Indonesia indicate that children of older women (35+) have lower mortality&#13;
tharL the chilclren of women in these "prime" reproductive ages.        Only in&#13;
Sri Lanka does the expected IJ-shaped pattern with respect to age emerge.&#13;
In all four countries, the estimated effect of eliminating childbearing&#13;
before 20 and after 34 is relatively small (averaging roughly five&#13;
percent)  because most   childbearing is already concentrated      in this age&#13;
span, so moving the remainder of births to this maternal age range has&#13;
little effect on overall child mortality. Furthermore, as mentioned above,&#13;
only in Sri lanka does eliminating childbearing above age 35 have a net&#13;
positive impact on the level of child mortality.&#13;
In fact, the mortality impact of changes in maternal age due to an&#13;
increase in contraceptive use is likely to be even smaller than indicated&#13;
by the estimates shown in Table 3.      The reason is that while the fraction&#13;
of children born to old mothers is likely to decline, the under--20 fraction&#13;
of childbearing is not in most countries.       It is this under-20 fraction&#13;
that contributes most to the small iimpact shown in Table 3.      Increases in&#13;
age at first birth and reductions in teenage fertility are like'Ly to result&#13;
only from changes in age at marriage accompanying general socioeconomic&#13;
development and changes in the status of women.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-15-&#13;
The estimated impact on child mortality of stopping childbearing at&#13;
three children is also shown in Table 3.         On average across the four&#13;
countries, child mortality rates would be lowered by eight percent if&#13;
higher  order   births  were  eliminated.     The  estimated  effect  of   both&#13;
concentrating childbearing in the age range 20-34 and eliminating births&#13;
beyond the third is shown to be approximated very closely by simply summing&#13;
the separate effects; on average, mortality would decline by 12 percent.&#13;
Since the role of family planning in helping couples to reduce higher order&#13;
births is well documented, there is likely to be more of an impact on&#13;
mortality from increased contraceptive use through reducing parity than&#13;
through lowering maternal age at birth.     As discussed earlier, this parity&#13;
effect may be large by a spacing effect in disguise.&#13;
Hobcraft et al. [19831, Holland [1983], and Cleland and Sathar [1983],&#13;
have shown that birth spacing has a large impact on child mortality.         In&#13;
Table 4, we consider the impact on lqO and 4q, of changing spacing patterns&#13;
in three ways.    In this table, the convention proposed by Hobcraft et al.&#13;
is used:   spacing patterns are represented by the format SZ.L; S denotes&#13;
the number of children born 2-6 years before the index child, Z denotes the&#13;
number born 0-2 years before the index child, and L denotes the number born&#13;
0-17 (if estimating lql) or 0-29 (if estimating 3q2) months after the birth&#13;
of the index child.      The patterns we examine are SZ.L=10.0,      11.0, and&#13;
21.1+.   In words, these three patterns are:      1) 10.0 = only one sibling&#13;
born within 2-6 years before the index child, and none born 0-2 years&#13;
before or 0-17 (or 0-29) months after; 2) 11.0 = one born 2-6 years before,&#13;
one born 0-2 years before, and none born 0-17 months after; and 3) 21.1+&#13;
two born 2-6 years before, one born 0-2 years before, and at least one born&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-16-&#13;
TABIE 4. Effects of Changing SpacingC Patterns on lq0 and 4qj.&#13;
lqO                                  4q,&#13;
% change if all                      % change if all&#13;
ReEerenbe      births spaceda       Referenbe      births spaceda&#13;
COUNTRY        Value    10.0     11,0    21.1+     Value      10.0     11.0    21.1+&#13;
Africa&#13;
Senegal         120       0       12       4        151        14      -13     -29&#13;
Lesotho         132        2      -7      15        054        -7       14     117&#13;
KenvaL          095     -25      -15     -13        064       -13       21      39&#13;
Sudan           076     -28      -'9      -1        063       -14       17      59&#13;
Ghana           075     -30      -16       8        058       -11       15     134&#13;
Americas&#13;
Haiti           147     -23       -6      16        082          1       6      25&#13;
Peru            107     -27        4      18        064       -33       10     109&#13;
Ecuador         085     -23       -9       1        052       -14       36      95&#13;
Mexico          075     -22       -5       0        036       -18       11      79&#13;
Colombia        068     -28        4       5        042        -9       40      17&#13;
Costa Rica      071     -33        8      31        019       -28      -15      24&#13;
Guyana          055     -24        6      10        014       -25      -14     111&#13;
Panama          044     -11       -9      -2        018          1       6      21&#13;
Jamaica         041      -5        5       8        014         0       14      41&#13;
Asia&#13;
Nepal           168     -27       -9      15        096       -20       24     106&#13;
Bangladesh      136     -23      --2      -1        080       -29        9     151&#13;
Pakistan        130     -23      -18     -18        077       -22       26     111&#13;
Indonesia       106     -24      --6      -2        081       -33        7     207&#13;
ThaLiland       079     -28      -19     -23        034       -34       28     242&#13;
Jordan          069     -37      --6       0        026       -32       39      80&#13;
Syzia           067     -31      -25     -18        025       -18       37      87&#13;
Philippines     055     -23       22      24        012        -1       97     154&#13;
Sri Lanka       053     -10        7      -6        024       -20       -2      44&#13;
Korea           043     -26      -19      -1        021       -20       42     336&#13;
Malaysia        043     -13       -2      -6        009         16      45      59&#13;
a.  Spacing is defined by the notation SZ.L, where S = number of previous births&#13;
2-6 years before index child, Z = number previous births 0-2 years before&#13;
index child and L = number subsequent births 0-17 months for lql or 0-29&#13;
months for 3q2 after birth of index child.&#13;
b. See Table 1, footnote c, for description.&#13;
c.  Calculated from Hobcraft et al. [1983].&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-17-&#13;
0-17 months after. Of the three, the first, SZ.L=10.0, is expected to be&#13;
the most favorable, and 21.1+, the last, the least favorable by far. The&#13;
results generally bear out these expectations: as we move across the rows&#13;
labeled 10.0, 11.0 and 21.1+, the percent change generally rises,&#13;
indicating successively higher mortality. Moreover, switching universally&#13;
to the "ideal" pattern SZ.L=10.0, implying a prior birth interval of at&#13;
least two years, would lower lq0 in all but two countries         (Senegal and&#13;
Lesotho) and would lower 4q1 in all but five countries (Senegal, Haiti,&#13;
Panama, Jamaica, and Malaysia).l0&#13;
The variation across countries in the estimates in Table 4 is&#13;
mainly mechanically caused by differences in the parameter estimates in the&#13;
original study; instability in the parameter estimates reflects primarily&#13;
small sample sizes in many of the covariate categories. Other sources of&#13;
variability in the parameter estimates are differences in data quality&#13;
across country and in the extent of date imputation in the data.           (see&#13;
Trussell, 1984) Fortunately, we do not have to rely on estimates from a&#13;
single country.    Instead, we can examine the distribution of estimates&#13;
generated  for many populations.      These distributions are displayed      in&#13;
Figure 1, using box plots.11 Examination of these box plots confirms our&#13;
expectation that the spacing pattern 10.0 is superior to 11.0 which in turn&#13;
is superior to 21.1+.     These estimates indicate that if all births were&#13;
spaced in the "ideal" pattern (10.0), the median reductions in 1q0 and&#13;
would be 24% and 13%, respectively.&#13;
These results are misleading, however, for at least three reasons.&#13;
First, it is logically impossible for all births to have the ideal spacing&#13;
pattern of one birth 2-6 years before and no births 0-2 years before.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
--18-&#13;
Obviously, first births could not.. Thus, our ideal spacing pattern applies&#13;
only to second and higher order births.   For first births, SZ by definition&#13;
would equal CO and L would ideally equal 0.     Hence, the ideal pattern for&#13;
first births wouLd be SZ.L = 00.0. 'Figure 1 shows that if first births and&#13;
subsequent births each were ideally spaced, then lq0 would be reduced by an&#13;
average across countries oF 10 percent and 4q, by an average of 21&#13;
percent.12   Because first births cannot be explicitly distinguished from&#13;
higher order births in the Hobcraft et all study, however, the predicted&#13;
mortality rate for first births is likely to be biased.    Examination of the&#13;
results convinces us that the estimates of mortality for first births are&#13;
biased upward and therefore the estimated changes in overall mortality&#13;
resulting from the adoption of the ideal spacing pattern are biased&#13;
downward.&#13;
Even with this adjustment, it would be highly optimistic to believe&#13;
that changing spacing patterns alone, for example through the use of&#13;
contraception, would have an effect of this magnitude. The reason is that&#13;
these "child spacing effects" are almost certainly due, in part, to the&#13;
effects of breastfeeding in both delaying resumption of menstruation and&#13;
improving child health. A spurious spacing effect would result if a woman&#13;
tends to breastfeed each of her children for the same length of time.&#13;
Tlen,  a short prior interval reflects early weaning of the prior child&#13;
which in turn is associated with early weaning of the index child.&#13;
Lengthening birth intervals through breastfeeding would have a greater&#13;
positive impact on child survival than would increasing birth intervals&#13;
through contraceptive use, other things being equal.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
0~~~~~0&#13;
'.0 ~ ~ ~ ~~~.&#13;
o~~~&#13;
so~~~~.&#13;
0       0&#13;
0          :3 03  .JO&#13;
o       0 &#13;
C'4      0 X0g. 3  X &#13;
co rC-4                                                        W o&#13;
_w%                                          s0  C           4D0   Ci&#13;
*~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~t ,  NCo )n&#13;
la                                       :3~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~*-  034  0&#13;
04~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0&#13;
.0                                                         '1-4 0J  0  cO&#13;
C) C          o      0o&#13;
Q~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0 CD o4         n -4   *&#13;
-     0    .40h   0&#13;
Al                                              0.4                co&#13;
4i                                                    (U~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~  i0&#13;
$4                                               I                 hi&#13;
*                                               -0    0&#13;
Oa ww4X 03   r &#13;
0o                                                          .   . j.&#13;
du 60                                                  cd~~~~~~~~~~~'.  00.03 h&#13;
4.0  C                                                0     .0  a,&#13;
-,*                                               *,   ,4 &gt;  K { &#13;
00                                              .0    0    04 w0hi  0&#13;
u  0.                  I          -zt  w~~          ~~~~~~~~ 44  0  "  O&#13;
'1)00                                                w-           CO4  &#13;
00                      0                             *44  Ai  0)4  00&#13;
.00~~~                             ~    ~    ~~~~~~~ If U  O0 O  C-&#13;
CO -A                                   .~ ~ ~~   ~~~~~~~~~~~0 '4  .0  4 0&#13;
00                                03    0    hi~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~4   - '.4  IJ 4&#13;
X u   X    Ai,E &#13;
030.. o                                                       o   *4&#13;
CU'44                                    .0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C  -A  44&#13;
1-'n                               .n~h&#13;
040  I~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~$&#13;
0   44  03~4  4J0&#13;
*         I  I          0                  Co  Ai&#13;
I  *                 hi   *~~~~~~~~~~~-4oor  003&#13;
'-0  C14  0C.&#13;
'44  I  I  I                            hi           003~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~'444&#13;
u   .440"la 0 oo &#13;
_ _ _ C'                                                a) &gt; &#13;
0  4 -  0  030o&#13;
I                    44~~~~~~~~~~~~~~6 co .  ..&#13;
0W&#13;
+  -4   4'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-A  - &#13;
0  0  -  0  jO  0  -4  0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0  . &#13;
4  -4          C'4 -4  .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
--20-&#13;
Hence, it is important to establish whether spacing effects persist&#13;
after the effects of breastfeeding of the index child are controlled.&#13;
Cleland and Sathar provide a partial answer.     Because of the coding of age&#13;
at   death  in   the  Pakistan   survey and    imprecision  of   retrospective&#13;
breastfeeding reports, it is impossible in most cases to decide whether&#13;
ternmination of breastfeeding was caused by death or vice versa. Therefore,&#13;
Cleland and Sathar could control for breastfeeding only when analyzing&#13;
mortality after the first year.    They present results only for early child&#13;
mortality and conclude that the negative association between birth interval&#13;
length and lql cannot be explained by the timing of weaning.&#13;
Holland used a different methodology in his Malaysia study and the&#13;
coding of age at death was more precise in the MFLS. As a consequence, the&#13;
difficulty in separating cause and effect in the weaning/death association&#13;
was  largely   eliminated.    He found that previous     interval  length was&#13;
negatively related to lqO even when the effect of breastfeeding was&#13;
controlled.    If breastfeeding duration is held constant but short prior&#13;
birth intervails are eliminated, the estimated change in lqO is a reduction&#13;
of 16 percent.     In comparison, the estimate implied by the Hobcraft, et&#13;
al., study for Malaysia is a reduction of lqO by 9.3 percent (not shown),&#13;
after allowing for first births.       Although we might have expected the&#13;
Hobcraft, et al., study to produce a larger estimated reduction since the&#13;
effects of breastfeeding are not controlled, the two studies are not&#13;
directly comparable because they emiploy different data sets and different&#13;
specificationis of spacing effects.&#13;
Even the Holland estimate, however, is potentially biased.        When a&#13;
breastfeeding child dies, ovulation is likely to resume more quickly.       In&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-21-&#13;
the absence of contraception, the consequence would be a more rapid next&#13;
conception.    Some short prior intervals are likely to be caused by the&#13;
death of the previous child. The death of the index child is more probable&#13;
if  the  previous  child died.     Thus,  the  childspacing   variable  may be&#13;
spuriously capturing an intra-family correlation in the propensity for&#13;
children to die.   To avoid this potential bias, the survival status of the&#13;
previous birth must be controlled.       Cleland and Sathar found a strong&#13;
spacing effect regardless of whether the preceding child survived for two&#13;
years  or died before    the age of two.     They did not, however,    control&#13;
simultaneously   for  the   survival  status   of  the  preceding   child   and&#13;
breastfeeding   of  the  index  child.    They  estimate  that  the  universal&#13;
adoption of the "ideal" spacing pattern discussed above would reduce lqO by&#13;
15 percent in Pakistan. Unfortunately, it is not clear whether the effects&#13;
of any confounding variables were controlled or how first births were&#13;
handled in this calculation.&#13;
Producing a "best" estimate of the mortality reducing impact of&#13;
adopting the "ideal" spacing pattern is difficult.        No single study has&#13;
controlled   for  all  obvious  confounding  variables  simultaneously.     The&#13;
estimates from the Hobcraft et al. study are probably slightly overstated&#13;
because they do not control for the effects of breastfeeding and survival&#13;
of the previous child, but they are likely to be understated because the&#13;
estimated mortality rates of first births are probably exaggerated.      These&#13;
two effects will, on average, tend to compensate for each other.        Hence,&#13;
our preferred estimate is the median change for the 25 countries in the&#13;
Hobcraft, et al., study; if all births are spaced at least two years apart,&#13;
we might expect reductions in lqO by 10 percent and in 4qO by 21 percent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-22-&#13;
nC                                  41&#13;
c U- 'A 0             do Z   0 &#13;
V .4-.o  .  .    .     .-&#13;
&gt; _ ~UU4    O O                             U &#13;
* .Z _s u S -  _ _ D0&#13;
O  O Q * O D   _s 0.0&#13;
C          1.*@ &#13;
.0                                            0&#13;
I..     .H                                  0fl&#13;
.0                                         0~~~&#13;
:.Z   Z4                                 -I _  e  O&#13;
'S     ~~~ ~~V cv  In  eq &lt;n        m&#13;
g  ..41.. 1.4.1.  41. 04&#13;
..4    ,,14  f  . 1  Ne g &#13;
v  e_s B~~~~r_                            C04 D   s @  &#13;
s !4.&lt;  al   .;  .    .     .     .      ..4o&#13;
2  w  @D&gt;-  CD   a         O     o&#13;
004100.e-&#13;
O                                  C0&#13;
to                                            a Wo&#13;
1.       *4.   N          N                   4o&#13;
e   ,,  ~      N.   p.    N           04 &#13;
.^  _ " b W W * - S                      n I~~,  W &#13;
'.      41'U  N O4       N D  *&#13;
0.41                                 0 S y o _u _&#13;
1.                        .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0&#13;
'.4                               ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0.&#13;
C~~~~~~~~~~~~~c                  on a     In1# &#13;
r.      041  0 &#13;
41I~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~4&#13;
U  -           I&#13;
a,        0          o                    *   I C&#13;
0         41I'.-.                        F.   e 0  0.  1&#13;
C.       UU.41       .     .     .    .11 0&#13;
C ~ ~ ~ 1                                   0&#13;
*    _                                        4 *_ 0&#13;
.00&#13;
41.04.                        4.~~~~~~~~~~~~a.  ~00 0I&#13;
*   .1   41                           0 _I&#13;
C  14  *  VC oe4   .  .    .     .            .0 e&#13;
0   1...'*i..Wbu_ OOO &#13;
U  4.41                        0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~l 4.41&#13;
o.4     e40                               4 _   A&#13;
41        *1''       - _  o           N .   c* &#13;
1.l      u1. u       -s   C     -$  e  _       A"C &#13;
o        v1o         - _              N  0'  *e u   i&#13;
II v                           *   u1 &gt;  U &#13;
.0                               -~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.  uG  , 0  &#13;
GI    1    0                                c  &gt;.  P.,&#13;
a,     I..4U.        06  a    -A 0   a C0   a  el"'C&#13;
B~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0 0 AM a. e- ". -     . "lC'&#13;
O       * D                               _ r0 , o .. C  w a&#13;
1.   0                              0    gel~~~~~~~~A  -  -  .4  1 &#13;
e         4 _       o           .f   -       * o  o4&#13;
4141..-.  0   fl           CU  *~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~I &#13;
I.                           l aN  g 0  -  41.0  1.4..o-&#13;
41             -          04    -     N         e1.&#13;
*i                              .D4&#13;
a~~~~~~~ -1         o1 -      e1. e   4o10"&#13;
-,~~~~~~~~~~~~ e.1  41* 44      ,, o. .4 4 0 ,. . .&#13;
~~~~' ,   ^b * * &#13;
c:~~~~           ~~~              - V 4 ,eOC U.D ,0 U.W-&#13;
|1          Ps    D fS ^0~~~~~1..  4.0  *.4 D  4  _e.  ccc&#13;
4*                        410 C C1     O  nS"" &#13;
O                 41    LI|  0      U D"  SOCCw *&#13;
II~~~ e       -  C-  -          -a  *1OU4 *   4co  4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-23-&#13;
Maternal Mortality&#13;
To estimate the size of a change in maternal mortality which would&#13;
result from a hypothetical change in the age and parity distribution of&#13;
births, we use maternal mortality ratios and distributions of live births&#13;
by maternal age and parity from the Chen et al. study [1974].13         In the&#13;
first column of Table 5, we show changes in maternal mortality ratios which&#13;
might occur in four hypothetical situations, plus the ratio which was&#13;
actually observed in the Matlab population.     In each case, we have altered&#13;
the observed distribution of live births by maternal age and/or parity and&#13;
then used the age and parity distribution of maternal mortality ratios for&#13;
the Matlab population to calculate new ratios.       In Row B, we change the&#13;
maternal age distribution of live births by eliminating all births to women&#13;
under 20 and over 39.     In this case, we ignore the fact that the age and&#13;
parity distributions of births are closely linked in this and other&#13;
populations.    Therefore,  the  figure 4.9 maternal deaths per 1000 live&#13;
births is calculated from the proportions of live births to women 20-29 and&#13;
30-39 and the ratios for these two age groups. In this case, the reduction&#13;
in the maternal mortality ratio would be 14 percent.&#13;
Next, we consider the analogous exercise for parity:       elimination of&#13;
births at parities 6 and above, ignoring any interaction between maternal&#13;
age  and parity.     For convenience,   the rates   for primagravida and 0-1&#13;
multigravida in Table 2 are combined into a single rate.        This change in&#13;
the parity distribution reduces the maternal mortality ratio to 5.5, for a&#13;
reduction in mortality of only 3.5 percent. Eliminating all births beyond&#13;
the third parity also has little effect in this population:     the ratio (not&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-24-&#13;
shown) in this case is 5.6 deaths per 1000 births, or a reduction of only&#13;
1.8 percent.   The reason is that naternal mortality is greatest in the 0-1&#13;
parity group, and simply reclistributing births away from the higher parity&#13;
groups shifts proportionately more iinto the high risk 0-1 pariity.&#13;
Clearly, it. is unrealistic to pretend that the distributions of births&#13;
b) maternal age and parity are unrelated.        For example, among 10 to 19&#13;
year-olds, there are likely to be more first births than higher order&#13;
births.   Since maternal mortality is related to both age and parity, and,&#13;
most probably, to their interaction, it is important to consider how the&#13;
parity distribution of births by, age might change if we eliminate births at&#13;
ycungest  and oldest ages.     In Row D we have, therefore, calculated the&#13;
maternal  mortality   ratio  elimi.natring births  under  20 and  over  39  and&#13;
rearranging the parity distributions for the age groups 20 to 29 and 30 to&#13;
39  as   described  in   Table  5  to   compensate   for  the  change   in  age&#13;
distribution.   The redistribution procedure chosen is arbitrary, and other&#13;
methods may yield slightly differenit results.      As might be expected, the&#13;
amount of reduction in maternal mortality resulting in this case is&#13;
somewhat less than that resulting from eliminating births at youngest and&#13;
oldest ages alorne.  Over all, the reduction expected would be approximately&#13;
11 percent.&#13;
Finally,, in Row E we take the age-parity distribution of- live births&#13;
in Row D and eliminate all births at parities 6 and above.       T'he effect is&#13;
tc reduce the maternal mortality ratio further from 5.1 to 4.5.        Thus, if&#13;
nc births occurred in this population below age 20 and above age 39 and&#13;
there were no births beyond parity 6, the maternal mortality ratio might&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-25-&#13;
drop from 5.7 reported by Chen et al. to something like 4.5, a decline of&#13;
21 percent.&#13;
In the last eight columns of Table 3, we consider the impact of these&#13;
changes in the maternal mortality ratio on the maternal mortality rate&#13;
(maternal deaths per 1000 women 15 to 49) and the total death rate for&#13;
women of reproductive ages.     The maternal mortality rate as used here is&#13;
the product of the maternal mortality ratio and the general fertility rate&#13;
(GFR)--the number of live births per 1000 women of reproductive age.&#13;
Obviously, if fewer women are exposed to pregnancy in a given period, the&#13;
maternal mortality rate will be lower.     The effects of our four changes in&#13;
the age and parity distribution on the maternal mortality rate are&#13;
evaluated in two ways.     First, we consider the unlikely circumstance in&#13;
which the age and parity distribution of live births changes but the GFR&#13;
remains constant.    Second, we assume that the changes in age and parity&#13;
distribution of live births result in a 25 percent decline in the GFR.14&#13;
In this case, the maternal mortality rate in column 7 is simply 75% of the&#13;
rate in column 3.      As is clear in Table 5, changes      in the age/parity&#13;
distribution of live births and in their number may have an important but&#13;
generally small impact on the fraction of women of reproductive ages who&#13;
die.15 The largest effect, which comes from eliminating births below 20&#13;
and above 39 and to women at parity 6 and above while the GFR is reduced by&#13;
25 percent, is a reduction in the maternal mortality rate by a third.       The&#13;
overall mortality rate for women of reproductive ages in this population&#13;
would change from 3.4 per 1000 to 3.2, for a reduction of about 6 percent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
IV. Actual Impact of Family Planning Programs&#13;
As is apparent from the' previous sections, to determine how much of an&#13;
impact a change in reproductive behavior (induced perhaps by a family&#13;
planning program) might actLLally have on mortality, we need to know how the&#13;
change   would   affect  the   maternal  age,   parity,   and  birth   interval&#13;
distributions of live births.&#13;
For illustrative purposes, we have attempted to make some reasonable&#13;
guesses about the types of changes which might take place:        higher order&#13;
births and short birth intervals would be less common, women would be less&#13;
likely to have births below the age of 20 and after their thirties, and&#13;
fertility would decline.     It is important to bear in mind that although&#13;
these are changes that may reflect the goals of a family planning program,&#13;
whether or not they would actually occur in a particular country is another&#13;
matter.   For example, it is unlikely that a family planning program will&#13;
reduce the number of births occurring to women under 20 unless there is&#13;
also an increase in the age at marriage.     Even if contraceptives were made&#13;
widely avaiLable to young, newly married women, very few might want to&#13;
deLay their first birth.&#13;
To obtatin a more realistic picture than provided in this paper of the&#13;
impact of a family planning program on mortality, we need to know not only&#13;
what type of changes in reproductive behavior may take place, but also the&#13;
magnitude  of those changes.      In other words,   rather than assuming all&#13;
births at birth orders 5 and above are eliminated, we would like to know&#13;
what proportion of births would occur at each birth order.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-27-&#13;
There are two ways in which we might attempt to determine how the&#13;
distribution of births by maternal age, parity, and birth spacing would&#13;
actually change. First, we might compare the distribution of births at two&#13;
or more periods of time in countries which have implemented successful&#13;
family planning programs.   Such a comparison could in principle be readily&#13;
made using maternity history data from surveys at different points in time.&#13;
The major problem with this approach is that it would be nearly impossible&#13;
to attribute the observed changes solely to the activities of the family&#13;
planning program, as the continuing debate about the relative roles of&#13;
family planning programs and economic and social development in reducing&#13;
fertility suggests [Lapham and Mauldin, 19841.&#13;
A second approach would be to use a simulation to determine what&#13;
effect   a  family   planning   program,   or  more   generally,   increased&#13;
contraceptive use, would have on the distribution of births by maternal&#13;
age, parity, and birth spacing occurring each year. Through simulation, we&#13;
could assess the potential impact of a family planning program in a&#13;
population rather than in documenting what has happened in the past.      Two&#13;
types of simulations have been developed for answering exactly this type of&#13;
question.    The  first  group  are macro-simulations,   such as TABRAP and&#13;
CONVERSE [Nortman et al., 1978], designed to project a population, with&#13;
annual variations in fertility depending on the number of new contraceptive&#13;
acceptors and the rate at which contraceptive use is discontinued.      These&#13;
simulations are usually based only on age-specific fertility calculations,&#13;
and therefore they cannot provide the necessary information about resulting&#13;
parity  distributions  or birth   spacing.    The  second  group  are micro-&#13;
simulations or family building models, such as POPSIM and POPREP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-. 28 -&#13;
[Lachenbruch, Sheps and Sorant, 1973; Horvitz et al., 1971].     These programs&#13;
sirnulate actual maternity histories of individual women in a population using&#13;
Monte Carlo techniques.   Although they are fairly complicated and expensive to&#13;
use, they have the potential of producing the type of results we need.&#13;
The obvious difficulty with using simulations is that It is necessary&#13;
to make asuroptions about the way in which contraceptive use diffuses&#13;
throughout a population and how effectively couples who adopt contraception&#13;
will use it    While there is considerable research concerning the impact of&#13;
family planning programs on t:he level of fertility (see, for example, Mauldin&#13;
[1982], Mauldin and Berelson [1978], and Lapham and Mauldin [1984], we know&#13;
considerably less about how the imrplementation of family planning programs&#13;
actually alters reproductive beha,vior. Furthermore, there is undoubtedly&#13;
substantial intercountry variation in the way in which a program affects&#13;
fertility;.   For example,   in the Republic of Korea and in Taiwan, China,&#13;
fertility rates started to decline E:Lrst among older women, but in Costa Rica,&#13;
thE fertility decline began among younger women [Stycos, 1982].      Thus, while&#13;
the estimates of changes in a population's fertility pattern generated by a&#13;
sinmulation may be more realisitic than the changes we have considered, they&#13;
would still depend heavily on the assumptions made about the implementation&#13;
anc effectiveness of a family plaLnniLng program.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
V. Summary and Conclusions&#13;
In this paper, we have discussed several mechanisms by which wide-&#13;
spread adoption of contraception could lower infant, child, and maternal&#13;
mortality.   We have also generated quantitative estimates that show how&#13;
much mortality in developing countries would be reduced under hypothetical&#13;
changes in the distributions of maternal age at birth, birth order, and&#13;
birth spacing patterns.     Our results indicate that if childbearing were&#13;
confined to the "prime" reproductive ages 20-34, the infant and child&#13;
mortality rate would fall by about five percent. Limiting childbearing to&#13;
ages 20-39 could reduce the maternal mortality ratio by about 11 percent.&#13;
Eliminating fourth and higher order births would reduce infant and child&#13;
mortality by about eight percent.        The maternal mortality ratio would&#13;
decline by about four percent if fifth and higher order births were&#13;
eliminated.   Simultaneously, eliminating fourth and higher order births and&#13;
confining childbearing to ages 20-34 would reduce 1q0 by 12 percent.&#13;
Alternatively, an improvement in birth spacing patterns, so that all&#13;
births subsequent to the first are spaced at least two years apart, is&#13;
estimated to reduce lq0 by an average of 10 percent and 4q1 by an average&#13;
of 21 percent    among the 25 countries studied.       Hence,  improving birth&#13;
spacing patterns and eliminating births to women at highest risk ages and&#13;
parities are expected to lower mortality by approximately the same amount.&#13;
Unfortunately, we are unable to estimate the combined effect of changing&#13;
age, parity and birth spacing simultaneously because there are no studies&#13;
that report results when all three factors are included in the same&#13;
multivariate model.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-30-&#13;
Thus,  there is definite potential    for reducing infant, child, and&#13;
maternal mortality through increased use of contraception.     Whether or not&#13;
family planning programs can effect the types of changes in behavior&#13;
discussed  in  this  paper  is  another matter.     We  discuss  problems  in&#13;
estimating likely effects of family planning programs in reproductive&#13;
behavior but do not attempt to resolve them.&#13;
In absolute magnitude, the potential effects on infant and child&#13;
mortality oE changing feritility patterns appear to be modest, though&#13;
certainly important.    We can apply the same methodology to estimate the&#13;
effect on infant and child mortality of raising levels of maternal&#13;
education in order to assess relative magnitudes.        In the 25 countries&#13;
included in the comparative study by Hobcraft et al.       [19831, giving all&#13;
mothers  7 or more years of education is estimated to lower 1q0 by an&#13;
average of 41 percent and ,ql by an average of 60 percent, other things&#13;
equal.   In the more intensive studies by Martin et al. [1983] and Trussell&#13;
and Hammerslough [1983], in which the effects of a much larger number of&#13;
socioeconomic variables are controlled, the implied reduction in 1qO is&#13;
still large, averaging 25 percent for Indonesia, Pakistan, the Philippines,&#13;
and Sri Lanka.&#13;
It would appear, therefore,, that educating girls lowers mortality to a&#13;
greater extent than altering reproductive behavior.    The costs of reducing&#13;
mortality through female education or implementing family planning programs&#13;
wcould surely diEfer. Reducing infant and child mortality, however, is not&#13;
the   primary   rationale   for   either   type  of   social   intervention.&#13;
Nevertheless, our results indicate that either approach may have the side&#13;
effect of lowering mortality.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
NOTES&#13;
For reviews of this literature, see Nortman, 1974; Gray, 1981; Omram,&#13;
1976 and 1981; Wray, 1971, and Winikoff, 1983.&#13;
2   It is also possible that a family planning program emphasizing oral&#13;
contraceptives may increase infant and child mortality.      The use of the&#13;
pill appears to reduce the quantity of breastmilk a woman can produce,&#13;
although it is less certain whether there is any change in the quality of&#13;
the milk [Hull, 1981].    Because breastmilk is important to the survival&#13;
of infants in many developing countries, a reduction in breastmilk due to&#13;
pill use could result in increased mortality. However, results from the&#13;
World Fertility Survey indicate that, even in developing countries with&#13;
large fractions of women using the pill, there is very little overlap&#13;
between pill use and lactation [Pebley, et al., 19821.&#13;
3   The real effect of parity may, in fact, not be an entirely biological&#13;
effect, but may also represent competition for limited resources.&#13;
4   Maternal mortality is generally measured in two ways:       1) the maternal&#13;
mortality ratio relates deaths due to maternity-associated causes to the&#13;
number of live births; 2) the maternal mortality rate relates these&#13;
deaths to the number of women of reproductive age.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-32-&#13;
5 Another irnportant effect of a family planning program on maternal mor-&#13;
tality is the reduction of mortality resulting from induced abortions&#13;
(see,  for example, Rochat et al., [1981]).      If women who want to avoid&#13;
pregnancy adopt contraception, they are far less likely to have to resort&#13;
to abortion (often available only under unsafe conditions in developing&#13;
countries).     We  do not   attempt  to  estimate   directly  the  amount  of&#13;
maternal mortality caused by abortions which may be eliminated by&#13;
contracept.ive use, since it is virtually impossible to obtain adequate&#13;
data on induced abortion in many countries.&#13;
6  Each birth is assigned to one of five categories:       (1) first; (2) second&#13;
or third, short prior interval; (3) second or third, long prior interval;&#13;
(4)  fourth or higher,    short  interval;   or (5)  fourth or higher,    long&#13;
interval.&#13;
7  The symbol    q   is defined as the probability of dying between exact ages&#13;
x and x+n.&#13;
8   These variables are held constant sequentially, or in groups, but not&#13;
simultaneously.&#13;
9,ote that only the distribution of births across the categories of the&#13;
independent variables, not the absolute number of births, affects the&#13;
estimated mortality rates.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-33-&#13;
10 We do not mean to indicate by our choice of the word ideal that even&#13;
longer intervals would not yield lower mortality.      The evidence on this&#13;
point is mixed.   Hobcraft, et al., originally had divided the period two&#13;
to six years before the survey into two subintervals, two to four and&#13;
four to six years.   On the basis of exploratory work, they concluded that&#13;
their models fit no better with the more complicated specification.       The&#13;
implication is that spacing births more than four years apart does not&#13;
result  in any further reductions     in mortality.   The Hobcraft et al.,&#13;
study is silent on the question of whether spacing births three to four&#13;
years apart is superior to spacing them two to three years apart.&#13;
Cleland and Sathar, however, found that for neonatal mortality, there&#13;
appears to be a threshold of about three years, above which no further&#13;
advantage is conferred on the index child.      For post-neonatal and early&#13;
child (1q0) mortality, an approximately linear decline occurs up to four&#13;
years. Note that our definition of the "ideal" spacing pattern allows&#13;
only one birth in the four-year interval two to six years before the&#13;
birth of the index child. Hence the implied spacing pattern is really a&#13;
birth every four (not two) years.&#13;
11 The median of the distribution is plotted as a single dot.      The lines on&#13;
either side of the median extend from the quartiles to the eighths.&#13;
Fifty percent of the observations lie above, and fifty percent lie below,&#13;
the median. One fourth and one eighth of the observations, respectively,&#13;
lie above (below) the upper (lower) quartiles and eighths.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-34-&#13;
12 In these calculations, we assume that one-sixth of births are first&#13;
births, since the exact distribution of births by birth order is&#13;
inavailable (see the Appendix).    Thus, we compute the expected change as&#13;
5/6 of the change if all births were spaced SZ.L = 10.0 plus 1/6 of the&#13;
change if all births were spaced SZ.L = 00.0.      In every case, the change&#13;
to SZ.L = 00.0C raises 1qO, but in all except three countries lowers 4qj.&#13;
As a consequence, the overall change, when first births are explicitly&#13;
included, is smaller for lqO than the corresponding figure in Table 4 but&#13;
Larger for 4qj.   Note that births with a spacing pattern of 00.0 include&#13;
two very different groups: first births and higher order births with&#13;
extremely long prior interbirth intervals.      There is some evidence that&#13;
the latter group experiences higher mortality than the former.&#13;
13 It is important to note that Chen et al. do not control for potentially&#13;
confounding variables, as the child mortality analyses in the last&#13;
section do.    Thus, the assumption that Chen et al.'s figures represent&#13;
coefficients of causal relaLtionships may be less tenable than in the case&#13;
of the child mortality studies.      Nevertheless, these are the only such&#13;
data available.&#13;
14 The change is instantaneous.       The women in Matlab Thana are assumed&#13;
simply to have had 25 percent fewer births during the two-year&#13;
observation period.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-35-&#13;
15 Because maternal mortality is likely to be underreported, even in the&#13;
Matlab population, the effect may well be larger than our estimates&#13;
indicate.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
APPENDIX&#13;
Calculation of q, and Lq,&#13;
Two measures of childhood mortality are used in this paper, lqO and&#13;
Lql.   To calculate these rates -- either for the actual sample or for a&#13;
1ypotheticaL population -- we use estimated parameters and a set of average&#13;
characterist:ics from each study.     In the models on which our results are&#13;
based, mortalit:y rates are nonlinear functions of these parameters and the&#13;
distributions of these characterist:ics in the sample. The set of parameters&#13;
can be divided into two subsets, consisting of the set of coefficients of&#13;
the indepencdent variables (hereafter denoted by the vector a) and other&#13;
parameters (hereafter denoted by the vector a). The purpose of the original&#13;
papers was   to estimate   the  values of a and a given information on the&#13;
covariates such as age, education of the mother, birth order and sex of the&#13;
infant. We, on the other hand, want to predict the probability of dying for&#13;
various hypothetical values of the covariates or independent variables&#13;
(hereafter clencted by the vector of characteristics X), given the estimated&#13;
parameters.      In symbols, nqx       f( 'X,ca), where   q   is the predicted&#13;
probability of dying between exact ages x and x+n; 'X is the linear&#13;
combination of the covariates, each multiplied by its estimated coefficient;&#13;
and a is the vector of other parameters estimated in the model.          Because&#13;
dii-ferent st:atistical procedures are used, we describe the calculation of&#13;
Lan and 4q, separately for each study.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
Martin et al. [1983] and Trussell and Hammerslough [1983] both use a&#13;
hazards model approach, described in detail by Trussell and Hammerslough&#13;
[19831. Both studies use the same age categories, of which only the first&#13;
six (through age five) are needed for our calculations.        We denote the set&#13;
of covariates by the vector X and the associated parameter estimates,&#13;
including the intercept, by the vector a.     The symbols al, al,...,a6, denote&#13;
the age parameters and the width, in years, of each category. Then,&#13;
lqa  =  1.0 - exp(-(wie al + w2ea2 + w3ea3 + w4ea4)e X)         (Al)&#13;
and&#13;
4q, =    1.0 - exp(-(w5ea5 + w6ea6)+eS X)                       (A2)&#13;
The values of wl, w2,...,w6 in these studies are 1/12, 2/12, 3/12, 6/12,&#13;
1, and 3. Values of 5 are taken from Table 3 of Trussell and Hammerslough&#13;
and Tables   1, 2, and 3 of Martin et al.        Our calculations   consisted of&#13;
substituting in a set of X values and, using the parameter estimates from&#13;
the original studies, solving the equations for      q .&#13;
Holland [1983] also used hazards models, but estimated separate&#13;
equations for each of four sub-intervals in the first year, so that there&#13;
are four sets of $'s, denoted $ ks k=l, 2, 3, 4.          Since his analysis is&#13;
limited to infant mortality, only lq0 can be calculated.&#13;
1kx&#13;
lq0  =   1.0 - IT exp(-wke k                      (A)&#13;
k&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-38-&#13;
Because expc,sure is measured in months (not years), the values of wk are&#13;
2, 2, 3, End 5.  The values of fk are taken from Holland's T'able 17.&#13;
Hobcraft et al. [19831 used probability models, not hazard models, so&#13;
the equations are simpler.  S'ee Hobcraft et al. for further details.    There&#13;
are four separate equations Eor aeonatal, post-neonatal, toddler, and child&#13;
mnortality.  T'he associated parameter vectors are denoted Skj k=l, 2, 3, 4.&#13;
lqO  =  1.0 - (1.0 - e iX) (1.0 - e$2X)               (A4)&#13;
4q, =   1.0 - (1.0 - e OX) (1.0 - eO IX)              (A5)&#13;
'Values of O's were supplied by John McDonald of WFS.    Exponentiated O's are&#13;
shown in T'ables 3, 4, 5, and 6 of Hobcraft et al.&#13;
Evailuating the effect of a change in the characteristics of a&#13;
population on lq0 and hql&#13;
We are interested in assessing what would happen to lqO or 4q, if&#13;
certain  characteristics   of births   in a population were     changed.    For&#13;
example, other things equal, what would happen to predicted mortality rates&#13;
if all women had 7+ years of education.     To carry out this calculation, we&#13;
need  to know the distribution of characteristics       before  and after   the&#13;
change.   To get the predicted rate before the change, we should calculate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-39-&#13;
the predicted rate for each cell in the covariate matrix and then find the&#13;
weighted average, where the weights are the fractions of births in each&#13;
cell in the covariate matrix.&#13;
We do not, however, have the proportions in the covariate matrices.&#13;
In fact, there are approximately 500,000 cells in some of these matrices.&#13;
We only have the marginals, which are printed in the various studies.&#13;
Hence, we are forced to evaluate the predicted mortality rate for a baby&#13;
with average characteristics.     We do this calculation by substituting X for&#13;
X in the equations above.      The overall level predicted by the equations&#13;
will not be the correct one, since the functions are highly nonlinear (the&#13;
function of an average is not the average of functions) and since (having&#13;
only the marginals) we in effect must assume that all covariates are&#13;
uncorrelated.      Even   though  levels   are   incorrect,   however,   implied&#13;
proportional changes caused by substituting a hypothetical distribution&#13;
(say, X*) instead of X are generally close to the answers that would be&#13;
obtained   in  the  correct  manner.    Econometricians  have recognized    this&#13;
property in logit and tobit regressions; the predicted Y when the X's are&#13;
set at their means is not Y (as it would be with OLS), but the derivatives&#13;
with respect to the parameters, estimated at the means of the X's, are&#13;
generally close to the OLS parameter estimates.        When we tried adjusting&#13;
the constants to give the correct level, the implied proportional changes&#13;
(when X* was substituted for X) were nearly identical to those obtained&#13;
without adjusting the constants.     Hence, we are confident that the implied&#13;
proportional impacts that we estimate are reasonably accurate.&#13;
Of far more concern is the fact that we do not have the appropriate&#13;
X's, except for the Hobcraft et al. study.     Hobcraft et al. estimated their&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-40-&#13;
models on a sample consisi:ing of all births 5 to 15 years before the WFS&#13;
survey, and the marginals for covariates are available.       The other three&#13;
studies, however, have a sample of all births to women in the surveys.&#13;
Thus, the narginals do not refer to any period.        For exarnple, since the&#13;
3Urveys pertain to women L5-49 at the time of the survey, births to older&#13;
women are grossly under-represented and those to younger women are over-&#13;
represented (relative to what a distribution of births in a given period&#13;
would be) since all women can contribute births when young but only a few&#13;
when old.   Means of almost all covariates, calculated from the marginals,&#13;
are distorted and thus require adjustment before we can determine how the&#13;
riortality rate would change if the X's change.     Information on the current&#13;
period   is  clearly   unavailable.     We  could,   in  princ-iple,  get  the&#13;
characteristics of births near the time of each WFS survey, but most of&#13;
these surveys were conducted 5-10 years ago.       Since the Hobcraft et al.&#13;
means do apply to a particular period, they are not distorted by sample&#13;
selection bias.    The means, rhowever, pertain to a period on averge more&#13;
than 15 years ago.    Though in principle we could obtain means for a time&#13;
closer to the present from the IW'S standard recode files, in fact we have&#13;
access only to a few of those used in these studies.&#13;
Thus we were forced to resort to cruder adjustments. The means for the&#13;
H[obcraft et al. study were not adjusted.   For the other studies we adjusted&#13;
only  the  natErnal   age  and  birth  order  means  because  these  were   the&#13;
variables  we   altered  when  assessing  the   potential  effects  of  family&#13;
planning on mortality.    Adjustment of the means of other variables would&#13;
have  far   less  impact  on  our  estimates   because  they  remain  constant&#13;
throughout.    Maternal  age distributions were adjusted by estimating the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-41-&#13;
births for age groups of women during the three years before the survey,&#13;
with age-specific fertility rates taken from Hannenberg [1980] and number&#13;
of women married and proportion married taken from Goldman and Hobcraft&#13;
[19821. The distribution of births by birth order (one, two-three, four+)&#13;
was much harder to adjust, since data on the distribution of births by&#13;
birth order have seldom been published by WFS.      Some of the evaluations of&#13;
individual WFS Surveys include total fertility rates, total first birth&#13;
rates,  and total   fourth-and-higher  birth rates.     These reports   indicate&#13;
that during the five years before the surveys, first births constituted&#13;
about  14 percent   of births when the TFR was high       (5.5)   and about   18&#13;
percent when the TFR was      lower  (4.5).    The proportion of second- and&#13;
third-order births was generally about twice the proportion of first order&#13;
births. Information for Malaysia was available directly from Yatim [19821,&#13;
and indicates a distribution split 17 percent for first births; 30 percent&#13;
for second and third births; and 53 percent for fourth and higher order&#13;
births. Based on these findings, we split the births in the Philippines&#13;
and Indonesia in the proportions 18/36/46, in Pakistan in the proportions&#13;
14/28/58,  and   in  Sri  Lanka  20/40/40.    These   latter  estimates  almost&#13;
certainly are not correct, but they are equally certain to be better than&#13;
those "observed" from the entire sample.        For example,  in the Malaysian&#13;
Survey used   by Holland,   the births were    split  20/17/63.*   Within each&#13;
parity for Malaysia, the observed distribution of births by short and long&#13;
prior birth intervals was not adjusted since there was insufficient&#13;
information.&#13;
* This result seems quite implausible, but it is the one reported.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
Chen, Lincoln C., Melita C. Gesche, Shamsa Ahmed, A.I. Chowdhury and&#13;
Wittenry  Mc,sely, (1974).    Maternal Mortality  in Rural Bangladesh,&#13;
Studies in Family Planning 5(l11):334-341.&#13;
Clii, I-Cheng, Tina Agoestine and Joe Harbin (1981).  Maternal Mortality at&#13;
Twelve l'eaching Hospitals in Indonesia--An Epidemiologic Analysis.&#13;
International Journal of Gynaecology and Obstetrics 19:259--266.&#13;
Cleland, John and Zeba Satlhar (1983).     The Effect of Birth Spacing on&#13;
Childhoocd Mortality  in Pakistan.    WFS/TECH  2163.   London:    World&#13;
Fertility Survey.&#13;
Fedrick, J. and P. Adelstein (1973).     Influence of Pregnancy Spacing on&#13;
Outcome of Pregnancy. British Medical Journal 4:753-756.&#13;
Goldman, Nore-en and John Hobcraft (1982). Birth Histories. WFS Comparative&#13;
Studies, No. 17. London: World Fertility Survey.&#13;
Hannenberg, Robert (1980).    Current Fertility.   WFS Comparative Studies,&#13;
No. 11. London: World Fertility Survey.&#13;
Hobcraft, John, John McDonald and Shea Rutstein (1983).        Child-Spacing&#13;
Effects  on  Infant  and  Early  Child   Mortality.    Popul.ation  Index&#13;
49(4):585-618.&#13;
Holland, Bart (1983).   Breastfeeding and Infant Mortality: A Hazards Model&#13;
Analysis of the Case of Malaysia.       Ph.D. Dissertation,    Princeton&#13;
University.  Available from University Microfilms, Ann Arbor, MI.&#13;
Horvitz, D.G. et al., (1971). POPSIM: A Demograhic Microsimulation Model.&#13;
Monograph Series, No. 12. Chapel Hill: Carolina Population Center.&#13;
Jelliffe, D.B. and E.F.P. JelliEfe (1978).    The Volume and Composition of&#13;
Human Milk in Poorly Nourished Communities: A Review. American Journal&#13;
of Clinical Nutrition 31:492-515.&#13;
Lachenbruch, P.A., M.C. Sheps, and A.M. Sarant (1973).      Applications of&#13;
POPREP, A Modification oE POPSIM, in D. Dyke and J.W. MacCluer (eds.),&#13;
Computer Simulation in Human Population Studies.    New York:   Academic&#13;
Press.&#13;
Lapham, Robert J. and W. Parker Mauldin (1984).    Contraceptive Prevalence:&#13;
The Influence of Organized Family Planning Programs.     Paper presented&#13;
at the PAAk Annual Meetings.&#13;
Le Bolt, Scot A., David A. Grimes, Williard Cates, Jr., (1982). Mortality&#13;
from Abortion and Childbirth: Are the Populations Comparable? Journal&#13;
of the Amierican Medical Association 243(2):188-191.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-43-&#13;
Martin, Linda, James Trussell, Florentina Reyes Savail and Nasra M. Shah&#13;
(1983).   Co-variates of Child Mortality in the Philippines, Indonesia,&#13;
and Pakistan:   An Analysis Based on Hazard Models.     Population Studies&#13;
37(4):417-432.&#13;
Mauldin,  W.  Parker   (1982).   The Determinants    of Fertility Decline    in&#13;
Developing Countries: An Overview of the Available Empirical Evidence.&#13;
International Family Planning Perspectives 8(3):116-121.&#13;
Mauldin, W. Parker and Bernard Berelson (1978).        Condition of Fertility&#13;
Decline in Developing Countries, 1965-75.      Studies in Family Planning&#13;
9:89-147.&#13;
Nortman, Dorothy (1974). Parental Age as a Factor in Pregnancy Outcome and&#13;
Child Development. Reports on Population/Family Planning, No. 16.&#13;
Nortman, Dorothy L., Robert G. Potter, Sharon W. Kirmeyer, John Bongaarts&#13;
(1978).    Birth Rates   and Birth Control   Practice.    New York:    The&#13;
Population Council.&#13;
Omram,  Abdul  R.  (1976).    Review of Evidence,    in A.R.   Omram and C.C.&#13;
Standley   (eds.),  Family  Formation   Patterns  and   Health.    Geneva,&#13;
Switzerland: World Health Organization.&#13;
Omram, Abdul R. (1981).    Review of Evidence--An Update, in A.R. Omran and&#13;
C.C. Standley (eds.), Further Studies on Family Formation Patterns and&#13;
Health. Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization.&#13;
Pebley, A.R., Howard I. Goldberg, and Jane Menken (1982).        Prevalence of&#13;
Contraceptive Use During Lactation in Developing Countries.      Presented&#13;
at the WHO-NAS Symposium on Breastfeeding and Contraception.       Geneva,&#13;
February, 1982.&#13;
Rochat, Roger, Suraiya Jabeen, Michael J. Rosenberg, Anthony R.       Measham,&#13;
Atigur R. Khan, M. Obaidulla and Patrick Gould (1981).        Maternal and&#13;
Abortion-Related Deaths in Bangladesh, 1978-1979, International Journal&#13;
of Gynaecology and Obstetrics 19:155-164.&#13;
Sachs, Benjamin P., Peter M. Layde, George L. Rubin and Roger Rochat&#13;
(1982). Reproductive Mortality in the United States, in Journal of the&#13;
American Medical Association 247(20):2789-2792.&#13;
Stycos, J.M. (1982).    The Decline of Fertility in Costa Rica:      Literacy,&#13;
Modernization and Family Planning, Population Studies 36(1):15-30.&#13;
Tietze,   Christopher   (1977).     Maternal   Mortality   Excluding  Abortion&#13;
Mortality, World Health Statistics Report 39(4):312-339.&#13;
Trussell, James (1984).    Evaluation of Data Imputation in World Fertility&#13;
Surveys. WFS/Tech 2318.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-44-&#13;
Trussell,  James   and  CharLes  R.  Hammerslough   (1983).    A Hazard-Model&#13;
Analysis of the Covariates of Infant and Child Mortality in Sri Lanka,&#13;
Demography 20(1):1-26.&#13;
VTinikoff,  Beverly (1983).    The Effects of Birth Spacing on Child and&#13;
Maternal HIealth, Studies in Family Planning 14(10):231-245.&#13;
Wlray, Joe D). (1971).   Poplulation Pressure on Families:    Family Size and&#13;
Childspacirig.  Reports on Population/Family Planning, No. 9.    New York:&#13;
The Population Council.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
W   orld   Bank                          value of these findings and provides      Demographic Aspects of&#13;
valuable insights into possiblithes for  Migration in West Africa-&#13;
Publications                             implementing mass programs for           K. C. Zachanah and others&#13;
needy people in villages throughout&#13;
of Related                               the world                                Volume 1&#13;
Interest                                                                          Staff Working Paper 'No 414 September&#13;
1980 369 pages (including statistical an-&#13;
Volume 1 Integrated Nutrition            nexes, bibliography)&#13;
and Health Care                          Stock No WP 0414 515&#13;
Arnied A. Kielmann and others&#13;
This volume provides detailed data       Volume 2&#13;
suggestng that synergism between         Staff Working Paper No 415 September&#13;
malnutntion and infecton is probably     1980 391 pages (including statistical an-&#13;
the greatest cause of mortality, mor-    nexes, bibliography)&#13;
The African Trypanosomiases:             bidity, and retarded growth and devel-   Stock No WP 0415 515&#13;
Methods and Concepts of                  opment in children In an expenment       (These Working Papers are background&#13;
over a penod ot four vears, villagers    sThes torhngrapers   We    ac nd&#13;
Control and Eradication in               received nutntion care, general health   studies tor Mhicgrason i West Afnica:&#13;
Relation to Development                  care to control infectons, or both Dra-  Demographic Aspects, descrbed in this&#13;
C. W. Lee and J. M. Maurice              matic improvements, including a 40%-     secton)&#13;
Here is a practical cost-benefit ap-     50o decline in mortality, a 20%o reduc-  Economic Motivation versus&#13;
proach to an age-old problem affecting   creases in height and weight. In addi-   City Lights: Testing&#13;
humans and livestock alike, the Afn-     tion, detaied informanion on  adi -     Hypotheses about Inter-&#13;
can Trypanosomiases. Descnbes new        presented that permuts the most com-     Changwat Migration in&#13;
techniques that offer tsetse control     plete analysis of cost-effectiveness and  Thailand&#13;
without destroying game animals.         program relevant costs and benefits      Fred Arnold and Susan H.&#13;
Also summanzes current research in       yet avaglable r  this hnd of held re-C&#13;
genetic control, the use of traps and    search. The study focuses directly on      ochrane&#13;
screens, attractants, and pheromones     practical program implications and        Staff Working Paper No 416. September&#13;
Technical Paper No. 4 1983. 107 pages    ways in which such integrated services    1980 41 pages (includtng footnotes, refer-&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0191-8 Stock No BK 0191      can be applied under field conditions     ences)&#13;
$5                                        The Johns Hopkins University Press 1984.  Stock No WP 0416. 53&#13;
Analyzing the Impact of                  288 pages.                                Experiments in Family&#13;
Health Services: Project                   C 82-2395. ISBN 0-808-3064-8 Stock      Planning: Lessons from     the&#13;
Experiences from    India,               No. 'H 3064 $24.50                        Developing World&#13;
Ghana, and Thailand                                                                Roberto Cuca and Catherne S.&#13;
Rashid Faruqee                           Volume II.          a    Family           Pierce&#13;
Staff Workig Paper .No. 546 1982 44                   Integrated                   A comprehensive review of expen-&#13;
pages.                                    Planning and Health Care                 mental efforts in the developing world&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0117-9 Stock No. WP 0546      Carl E. Taylor and others               to determine more effectve ways of&#13;
53                                       To vllUage people, politcians, and in-    providing family planning services.&#13;
temational health planners, health and   The Johns Hopkins University Press, 2978&#13;
family planning have always seemed       276 pages (including bibliography, index of&#13;
NEW                                   to fit naturally together But in the     experiments)&#13;
early 1960s, when intemational aware-    LC 77-16596. ISBN 0-8018-2013-8, Stock&#13;
Child and Maternal Health                 ness of the social and economic conse-   No IH 2013, $19.50 hardcover; ISBN 0-&#13;
r * . - ~~~~~~~~~quences of surging population growth                   8018-2014-6, Stock No. IH 2014, 58.95&#13;
Services in India: Tne                    moved famly planning into a position     paverback&#13;
Narangwal Experiment                      of high pnonrty, some intemational&#13;
What can pnmary health care and           agencies began to advocate separation    Family Planning Programs: An&#13;
:amily planning do for women and         of family planning from health serv-      Evaluation of Experience&#13;
:hildren in the poor and depnved         ices. In intemational policy discussions  Roberto Cuca&#13;
ireas of the world? Some of the most     the question continues to be impor-&#13;
ipecific evidence available today to     tant. This volume analyzes this ques-     Staff Working Paper No 345 1979 146&#13;
;upport the benefits of these services   tion and provides arguments and evi-      pages (including 2 annexes, reqerences)&#13;
s contained in these two studies,         dence to support integraton of health    Stock No WP 0345 55&#13;
vhlch represent the findings of re-      care and family planning; it outlines&#13;
iearch camed out dunng 1967-74 in        the purposes underlying the research      Fertility and Education: What&#13;
wenty-six vlllages in Punjab, India.      in this area; and it proposes policy     Do We Really Know?&#13;
questions regarding the effectiveness,   Susan H. Cochrane&#13;
vlembers of the research staff, whichefcec,adeut               fsch  a  ne&#13;
;tarted with 15 people and grew to       efrfciency, and equity of suc an nte-     A model identifying the many chan-&#13;
Lbout 150 by the end of the project,     graon.                                    nels through whlich education might&#13;
pent many years working with, and        The Johns Hopkins University Press 1984&#13;
haring the lives of, vlllagers. The      256 pages.&#13;
.epth of understanding that came         LC 83-23915. ISBN 0-8018-2830-9 Stock     Prices subject to change without notice&#13;
rom this type of sharng enhances the     No JH 2830. $22 50.                       and may vary by country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
act to determine fertlitv and a review    Hlealth Issues and Policies in           Kenya.: Population and&#13;
ot the evidence of the relation between  the Developing Countries                  Development&#13;
education and the intervenirg vana-       Frednck Gclladav                         (See description under Countrv&#13;
bles in he model that aftect fertilltv&#13;
The Johrs Hopkins University P3ress, 1979  S'aff Working Paper No 412 1980 55      Studies listing.)&#13;
138 pages (including biblicgrapity, index)  pages&#13;
LC 78-26070 ISBN 0-801E-27140-1. Stock    Stock N'o W-' 0412 53.&#13;
No IH .'140, 56 95 paperoack.             Health, Nutrition, and Family            Migration in West Africa:&#13;
Planning in India: A Survey of            Demographic Aspects&#13;
Experiments and Special                  K. C. Zachanah and Juhen Conde&#13;
Fertility and Its Regalation in           Projects                                  The first study of the large-scale move-&#13;
Bangladesh                                Rashid Faruqee and Ethna Johnson          ment of people in nine West Afncan&#13;
R. Anumn and Rashid F'aruclee                                        9 an8          countnes Discusses the volume and&#13;
StaffWo7*ng PperN   3.3 1190 54Siaff Working Paper No 507 19218          direction of internal and extemnal flows&#13;
Staff Working Paper eNo 333 1980          pages (including references)              and the economic and social cha-acter-&#13;
pStoc  (inlPin r03erence3  3Slock No WP 0507 55                                    istics of migrants.&#13;
Stock NVo WP 0383 53                                                                A joznt World Bank-OECD study Oxford&#13;
Infant and Child Mortality as a           University Press, 1981 166 pages (ncldud-&#13;
Dleterminant of Fertility: The            ing 22 maps, bibliography, index)&#13;
Health                                    Policy Implications                       LC 80-21352. ISBN 0-19-520186-8, Stock&#13;
Frednc. Golladay, cocirdinating           Susan Hill Cochrane and K. C.             No OX 520186, 519 95 hardcover; rSBN&#13;
author                                    Zachariah                                 0-19-520187-6, Stock No. OX 520187,&#13;
Draws oi expenence gamed irom             An illustrative analysis that suggests    58.95 paperback.&#13;
health comrrponents of seventy World      infant mortality may be an important&#13;
Bank projects in forty-four countnes      component of a fertlity reduction pro-&#13;
between 1975 and 1978. z_mphasLzes        gram irn counttnes where mortality is&#13;
the dispioportionately high expendi-      high arid few couples are able to have    Population and Famdly&#13;
tures incurTed on curative medicine,      the nurnber of surviving children they    PlanniS  g in Bangladesh: A&#13;
mamtenance of expensive hospitals,        desire.                                   Study of the Research&#13;
and sophisticated trainung of medical     World Bank Siaff Working Paper No 556     Mohammad Alauddin and Ratshid&#13;
personnel at the cost of preventtve&#13;
care for the ma;ontv of the people.       1983. 44 pages.                           Faruqee&#13;
Points ouit that low-cost healtn care     ISBN 0-8212-0147-0. Stock No WP 0556      Reviews major studies on family plan-&#13;
systems are feasible and recommends       $3.                                       mng and on fertility trends, profales,&#13;
t,at the   ,,nk begin regular and direct                                            and determinants. Evaluates results of&#13;
lending t or health, in adr iora to hav-  Integrating Family Planning               such studies and cntiques their rneth-&#13;
ing health components as part of pro-     with Health Services: Does It             odology and applicaton. Underscores&#13;
jects in other sectors  Help?             need for continued study and suggests&#13;
Sector in ,ot  setr 1ehel                                                           directions for future research to im-&#13;
Sector Poticy Paper 1980 30 pages (in-     sashid Faruqee                           prove the Bangladesh population&#13;
cluding 8 annexes, 4 fgures, map)         Staff Working Paper No 515. 1982. 47      problerm.&#13;
Stock Nos BK 9066 (Arabic), BK 9067       pages.                                    World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 557&#13;
(English), BK 9068 (French), BK 9069      IS3N 0-8213-6003-2. Stock No. WP 0515.    1983 176 pages.&#13;
(Spanish) S5 -                            S3                                        ISBN 0-8213-0150-0. Stock No WF' 0557&#13;
55&#13;
\I   7       Visit the World Bank&#13;
Z        ~      ~      ~        \j &lt;ookstore&#13;
_   K Street  '  -   when      you are in               Population and Poverty in the&#13;
K Street  whe      you are inDeveloping World&#13;
[I I                  rn      Washington, D.C.                 Nancy Bidsall&#13;
Staff Wcrking Paper No 404. 1980. 96&#13;
Street XP   spages (including 2 appendixes, inbilog-&#13;
r B 1 sD E v- ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~raphy).&#13;
&lt;   =   :           e       \   '\                            ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~Stock No. WP 0404. S3&#13;
H Street&#13;
H Street       Pe~                            Lafayette Square           Population Policy and Fanmily&#13;
[I]                        1                  Urts&gt;__Planning Programs: Trends in&#13;
.   Avenue                                       Policy and Administration&#13;
F_  _   &gt;   _                   I        Kandiah Kanagaratnam and&#13;
G Street                    The White House             Catherne S. Pierce&#13;
r   W   W  r       ]                                           ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~Staff Wrrking Paper NMo 447. 1981. 80&#13;
L_ll, I     I    I             I   _     _L.]pages (mcluding bibliography, appendixes).&#13;
World Bank Bookstore                                                            Stock No. WP 0447 53.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-39-&#13;
the predicted rate for each cell in the covariate matrix and then find the&#13;
weighted average, where the weights are the fractions of births in each&#13;
cell in the covariate matrix.&#13;
We do not, however, have the proportions in the covariate matrices.&#13;
In fact, there are approximately 500,000 cells in some of these matrices.&#13;
We only have the marginals, which are printed in the various studies.&#13;
Hence, we are forced to evaluate the predicted mortality rate for a baby&#13;
with average characteristics.     We do this calculation by substituting X for&#13;
X in the equations above.      The overall level predicted by the equations&#13;
will not be the correct one, since the functions are highly nonlinear (the&#13;
function of an average is not the average of functions) and since (having&#13;
only the marginals) we in effect must assume that all covariates are&#13;
uncorrelated.      Even   though  levels   are   incorrect,   however,   implied&#13;
proportional changes caused by substituting a hypothetical distribution&#13;
(say, X*) instead of X are generally close to the answers that would be&#13;
obtained   in  the  correct  manner.    Econometricians  have  recognized   this&#13;
property in logit and tobit regressions; the predicted Y when the X's are&#13;
set at their means is not Y (as it would be with OLS), but the derivatives&#13;
with respect to the parameters, estimated at the means of the X's, are&#13;
generally close to the OLS parameter estimates.        When we tried adjusting&#13;
the constants to give the correct level, the implied proportional changes&#13;
(when X* was substituted for X) were nearly identical to those obtained&#13;
without adjusting the constants.     Hence, we are confident that the implied&#13;
proportional impacts that we estimate are reasonably accurate.&#13;
Of far more concern is the fact that we do not have the appropriate&#13;
X's, except for the Hobcraft et al. study.     Hobcraft et al. estimated their&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-40-&#13;
models on a sample consisting of all births 5 to 15 years before the WFS&#13;
survey, and the marginals for covariates are available.       The other three&#13;
studies, however, have a sample of all births to women in the surveys.&#13;
Thus, the marginals do not refer to any period.        For example, since the&#13;
surveys pertain to women 15-49 al: the time of the survey, births to older&#13;
women are grossly under-represent:ed and those to younger women are over-&#13;
represented (relative to what a distribution of births in a given period&#13;
would be) since all women can contribute births when young but only a few&#13;
when old.   Means of almost all covariates, calculated from the marginals,&#13;
are distorted and thus require adjustment before we can determine how the&#13;
nortality rate would change if the X's change.     Information on the current&#13;
Deriod   is  clearly  unavailable.      We  could,   in  principle,   get  the&#13;
characteristics of births near the time of each WFS survey, but most of&#13;
:hese surveys were conducted 5-l) years ago.       Since the Hlobcraft et al.&#13;
means do apply to a particular period, they are not distcirted by sample&#13;
selection bias.    The means, however, pertain to a period on averge more&#13;
than 15 years ago.    Though in principle we could obtain means for a time&#13;
closer to t:he present from the WI'S standard recode files, in fact we have&#13;
access only to a few of thc,se used in these studies.&#13;
Thus we were forced to resort to cruder adjustments. The means for the&#13;
Hobcraft et al. study were not acljusted.   For the other studies we adjusted&#13;
only  the  maternal   age  and  birth  order  means  because  these  were   the&#13;
variables we altered when assessing the potential effects of family&#13;
planning on mortality.    Adjustment of the means of other variables would&#13;
Fave far Less impact on our estimates because they remain constant&#13;
throughout.    Maternal  age distributions  were adjusted by estimating the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-41-&#13;
births for age groups of women during the three years before the survey,&#13;
with age-specific fertility rates taken from Hannenberg [1980] and number&#13;
of women married and proportion married taken from Goldman and Hobcraft&#13;
[1982].   The distribution of births by birth order (one, two-three, four+)&#13;
was much harder to adjust, since data on the distribution of births by&#13;
birth order have seldom been published by WFS.      Some of the evaluations of&#13;
individual WFS Surveys include total fertility rates, total first birth&#13;
rates,  and total   fourth-and-higher  birth rates.     These reports   indicate&#13;
that during the five years before the surveys, first births constituted&#13;
about 14 percent of births when the TFR was high (-5.5) and about 18&#13;
percent when the TFR was      lower  (-4.5).   The proportion of second- and&#13;
third-order births was generally about twice the proportion of first order&#13;
births. Information for Malaysia was available directly from Yatim [1982],&#13;
and indicates a distribution split 17 percent for first births; 30 percent&#13;
for second and third births; and 53 percent for fourth and higher order&#13;
births.   Based on these findings, we split the births in the Philippines&#13;
and Indonesia in the proportions 18/36/46, in Pakistan in the proportions&#13;
14/28/58,  and   in  Sri  Lanka  20/40/40.    These   latter  estimates   almost&#13;
certainly are not correct, but they are equally certain to be better than&#13;
those "observed" from the entire sample.        For example, in the Malaysian&#13;
Survey used   by Holland,   the births were    split  20/17/63.*   Within each&#13;
parity for Malaysia, the observed distribution of births by short and long&#13;
prior birth intervals was not adjusted since there was insufficient&#13;
information.&#13;
* This result seems quite implausible, but it is the one reported.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
Chen, Lincoln C., Melita C. Gesche, Shamsa Ahmed, A.I. Chowdhury and&#13;
Wittenry  Mosely,   (1974).   Maternal Mortality   in Rural Bangladesh,&#13;
Studies in Family Planning 5(11):334-341.&#13;
Chi, I-Cheng, Tina Agoestinea and Joe Harbin (1981).    Maternal Mortality at&#13;
Twelve Teaching Hospitals in Indonesia--An Epidemiologic Analysis.&#13;
International Journal of Gynaecology and Obstetrics 19:259-266.&#13;
CLeland, John and Zeba Sathar (1983).       The Effect of Birth Spacing on&#13;
Childhood  Mortality  in Pakistan.     WFS/TECH 2163.    London:    World&#13;
Fertility Survey.&#13;
Fedrick, J. and P. Adelstein (1973).      Influence of Pregnancy Spacing on&#13;
Outcome of Pregnancy.   British Medical Journal 4:753-756.&#13;
Goldman, Noreen and John Hobcraft (L982). Birth Histories. WFS Comparative&#13;
Studies, No. 17.   London:  World Fertility Survey.&#13;
Hannenberg, Robert (1980).     Current Fertility.   WFS Comparal:ive Studies,&#13;
No. 11. London: World Fertilil:y Survey.&#13;
Hc,bcraft, John, John McDonald and Shea Rutstein (1983).        Child-Spacing&#13;
Effects  on   Infant  and  Earl,  Child  Mortality.     Population  Index&#13;
49(4):58'5-618.&#13;
Holland, Bart (1983).   Breastfeeding and Infant Mortality: A Hazards Model&#13;
Analysis of the Case of Malaysia.        Ph.D.  Dissertation,   Princeton&#13;
University. Available from University Microfilms, Ann Arbor, MI.&#13;
Horvitz, D.G. et al., (1971).   POPSIM:  A Demograhic MicrosimuLation Model.&#13;
Monograph Series, No. 12. Chapel Hill: Carolina Population Center.&#13;
Jelliffe, D.B. and E.F.P. Jelliffe (1978).     The Volume and Composition of&#13;
Human Milk in Poorly Nourished Communities: A Review. American Journal&#13;
of Clinical Nutrition 31:492-5]5.&#13;
Laclhenbruch, P.A., M.C. Sheps, and A.M. Sarant (1973).       Applications of&#13;
POPREP, A Modification of POPSIM, in D. Dyke and J.W. MacCluer (eds.),&#13;
Computer Simulation in Human Population Studies.     New York:   Academic&#13;
Press.&#13;
Lapham, Robert J. and W. Parker Mauldin (1984).     Contraceptive Prevalence:&#13;
The Influence of Organized Family Planning Programs.      Paper presented&#13;
at the PAA Annual Meetings.&#13;
Le Bolt, Scot A., David A. Grimes, 'Williard Cates, Jr., (1982). Mortality&#13;
from Abortion and Childbirth: Are the Populations Comparable? Journal&#13;
of the American Medical Association 243(2):188-191.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-43-&#13;
Martin, Linda, James Trussell, Florentina Reyes Savail and Nasra M. Shah&#13;
(1983).   Co-variates of Child Mortality in the Philippines, Indonesia,&#13;
and Pakistan:   An Analysis Based on Hazard Models.     Population Studies&#13;
37(4):417-432.&#13;
Mauldin,  W.  Parker   (1982).   The  Determinants   of Fertility Decline    in&#13;
Developing Countries: An Overview of the Available Empirical Evidence.&#13;
International Family Planning Perspectives 8(3):116-121.&#13;
Mauldin, W. Parker and Bernard Berelson (1978).        Condition of Fertility&#13;
Decline in Developing Countries, 1965-75.      Studies in Family Planning&#13;
9:89-147.&#13;
Nortman, Dorothy (1974). Parental Age as a Factor in Pregnancy Outcome and&#13;
Child Development. Reports on Population/Family Planning, No. 16.&#13;
Nortman, Dorothy L., Robert G. Potter, Sharon W. Kirmeyer, John Bongaarts&#13;
(1978).    Birth Rates   and Birth Control   Practice.    New York:    The&#13;
Population Council.&#13;
Omram,  Abdul  R.  (1976).    Review of Evidence,    in A.R.   Omram and C.C.&#13;
Standley   (eds.),  Family  Formation   Patterns  and   Health.    Geneva,&#13;
Switzerland: World Health Organization.&#13;
Omram, Abdul R. (1981).    Review of Evidence--An Update, in A.R. Omran and&#13;
C.C. Standley (eds.), Further Studies on Family Formation Patterns and&#13;
Health.   Geneva, Switzerland:   World Health Organization.&#13;
Pebley, A.R., Howard I. Goldberg, and Jane Menken (1982).        Prevalence of&#13;
Contraceptive Use During Lactation in Developing Countries. Presented&#13;
at the WHO-NAS Symposium on Breastfeeding and Contraception.       Geneva,&#13;
February, 1982.&#13;
Rochat, Roger, Suraiya Jabeen, Michael J. Rosenberg, Anthony R.       Measham,&#13;
Atigur R. Khan, M. Obaidulla and Patrick Gould (1981).        Maternal and&#13;
Abortion-Related Deaths in Bangladesh, 1978-1979, International Journal&#13;
of Gynaecology and Obstetrics 19:155-164.&#13;
Sachs, Benjamin P., Peter M. Layde, George L. Rubin and Roger Rochat&#13;
(1982). Reproductive Mortality in the United States, in Journal of the&#13;
American Medical Association 247(20):2789-2792.&#13;
Stycos, J.M. (1982).    The Decline of Fertility in Costa Rica:      Literacy,&#13;
Modernization and Family Planning, Population Studies 36(1):15-30.&#13;
Tietze,   Christopher   (1977).     Maternal   Mortality   Excluding  Abortion&#13;
Mortality, World Health Statistics Report 39(4):312-339.&#13;
Trussell, James (1984).    Evaluation of Data Imputation in World Fertility&#13;
Surveys. WFS/Tech 2318.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-44-&#13;
Trussell,   James  and  Charles  R.  Hammerslough   (1983).    A  Hazard-Model&#13;
Analysis of the Covariates of Infant and Child Mortality in Sri Lanka,&#13;
Demography 20(l):1-26.&#13;
Winikoff,  Beverly   (1983).   The Effects of Birth Spacing on Child and&#13;
Matern.al Health, StudLes in Family Planning 14(10):231-245.&#13;
Wray, Joe D. (1971).     Population Pressure on Families:     Family Size and&#13;
Childspacing. Reports on Population/Family Planning, No. 9. New York:&#13;
The Population Council..&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
W   orld   Bank                          value of these findings and provides      Demographic Aspects of&#13;
valuable insights into possibilities for  Migration in West Africa-&#13;
Publications                             implementing mass programs for           K. C. Zachanah and others&#13;
needv people in villages throughout&#13;
of Related                               the world                                Volume 1&#13;
Interest                                                                          Staff Working Paper No 414 September&#13;
1980 369 pages (including statistical an-&#13;
Volume 1: Integrated Nutrition           nexes, bibliography)&#13;
and Health Care                          Stock No WP 0414 $15&#13;
Amfned A. Kielmann and others&#13;
This volume provides detailed data       Volume 2&#13;
suggesting that synergism between        Staff Working Paper No 415 September&#13;
malnutntion and infection is probably    1980 391 pages (including statistical an-&#13;
the greatest cause of mortality, mor-    nexes, bibliography)&#13;
The African Trypanosomiases:             bidity, and retarded growth and devel-   Stock No WP 0415 515&#13;
Methods and Concepts of                  opment in children. In an expenment      (These Working Papers are background&#13;
over a penod of four Years, villagers    sThes Work    in       We  aca&#13;
Control and Eradication in               received nutntion care, general health   studies m or Mgrahion i West Afnica&#13;
Relation to Development                  care to control infectons, or both. Dra-  Demographic Aspects, descrbed in this&#13;
C. W   Lee and J. M. Maunce              matic Lmprovements, Lncluding a 40%-     section)&#13;
Here is a practical cost-benefit ap-     50% dechne in mortality, a 20% reduc-     Economic Motivation versus&#13;
proach to an age-old problem affectng    creases in  heght and weight. In addi-   City Lights: Testing&#13;
humans and livestock alike, the Af-      tion, detailed information on costs is    Hypotheses about Inter-&#13;
can Tryupanosomases. Describes new       presented that perrmts the most com-      Changwat Migration in&#13;
technques that offer tsetse control      plete analysis of cost-effectiveness and  Thailand&#13;
wlthout destroyngurrent research l       program relevant costs and benefits      Fred Arnold and Susan H.&#13;
genetic control, the use of traps and    yet available in this kind of hteld re-   Cochrane&#13;
screens, attractants, and pheromones     praccal program  mplcatons and            Staff Working Paper No 416. September&#13;
Technical Paper No 4 1983. 107 pages      ways in which such integrated services   1980 41 pages (including footnotes, refer-&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0191-8 Stock No. BK 0191     can be applied under field conditions     ences)&#13;
$5.                                       The fohns Hopkins University Press 1984  Stock No WP 0416 53&#13;
Analzingthe Impact of                 288 pages.                                Experiments in Family&#13;
Health Servicesg Proect                  LC 82-23915. ISBN 0-8018-3064-8 Stock     Planning: Lessons from     the&#13;
Experiences from    India,                                                         Developing World&#13;
Ghana, and Thailand                                                                Roberto Cuca and Catherne S.&#13;
Rashid Faruqee                            Volume II. Integrated Family             Pierce&#13;
Staff Workzng Paper Nfo 546. 1982 4-4     Volannin    and Hnegalted Care           A comprehensive review of expen-&#13;
StaffgWorkingePapersNo.546. 2982 4Planning and Health Care                         mental efforts in the developing world&#13;
1513N 0-8213-0117-9 Stock No. WP 0546     Carl E. Taylor and others               to determune more effective ways of&#13;
53                                        To vllUage people, poiticians, and in-   providing family planning services&#13;
ternational health planners, health and  The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1978&#13;
family planning have always seemed       276 pages (including bibliography, Index of&#13;
NEW                                   to fit naturally together But in the     experiments)&#13;
early 1960s, when international aware-   LC 77-16596 ISBN 0-8018-2013-8, Stock&#13;
Child and Maternal Health                 ness of the social and economic conse-   No JH 2013, $19.50 hardcover; ISBN 0-&#13;
Services in India: The         quences of surging population growth     8018-2014-6, Stock No JH 2024, $8.95&#13;
Services in India: The                    moved family planning into a position    paperback.&#13;
Narangwal Experiment                      of high pnonrty, some international&#13;
What can pnmary health care and           agencies began to advocate separation    Family Planning Programs: An&#13;
family planning do for women and          of family planning trom health serv-     Evaluation of Experience&#13;
children in the poor and depnved         ices. In international policy discussions  Roberto Cuca&#13;
areas of the world7 Some of the most     the question contnues to be impor-&#13;
specific evidence availabie today to     tant. This volume analyzes this ques-     Staff Working Paper No 345 1979 146&#13;
support the benefits of these services    tion and provides arguments and evi-     pages (inciuding 2 annexes, reJerences)&#13;
Is contained in these two studies,        dence to support integraton of health    Stock No WP 0345 55&#13;
which represent the findings of re-       care and family planning; it outlnes&#13;
search camed out dunng 1967-74 m          the purposes underlying the research     Fertility and Education: What&#13;
twenty-six vllUages in Punjab, India.     in this area, and it proposes policy     Do We Really Know?&#13;
questions regarding the effectiveness,   Susan H   Cochrane&#13;
Members of the research staff, which      efficiency, and equity of such an inte-  A&#13;
started with 15 people and grew to          tion                                   A model identfvig the manv chan-&#13;
about 150 by the end of the project,                                               nels through which education might&#13;
spent many years working with, and        The Johns Hopkins University Press 1984&#13;
sharing the lives of, villagers. The      256 pages.&#13;
depth of understanding that came          LC 83-23925 ISBN 0-8018-2830-9 Stock      Prices subject to change without notice&#13;
from this type of sharng enhances the     No JH 2830 522 50                         and may vary by country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
act to determine tertihti ancd a review   Hlealth Issues and Policies in           Kenya: Population and&#13;
of the rvidence of the relaton between   the Developing Countries                  Devellopment&#13;
educatonem and the interv eniig vana-     Eredrnck Golladav                        (See description under Country&#13;
bles in the model that aFEfect fertilitv  'taff Workzmsy Paper No 412. 1980 .7S    Studies lisang.)&#13;
The Johis Hopkins University Press. 1979  pa es&#13;
138 pages (including bibliigraphy, index)   c Nge1&#13;
LC 78-.6070 ISBN 0-80)`8-2140-1, Stock    '&#13;
No IH 2140, 56 95 paper back             Hlealith, Nutrition, and Family           Migration in West Africa:&#13;
I'lanning in India: A Survey of           Demographic Aspects&#13;
Frt..ih~ and.its           .          Experim,ents and Special                 K. C. Zachanah and Julien Conde&#13;
Fertility and Its Regulation in           Erojects                                 The first study of the large-scale move-&#13;
Bangladesh                                Rashld Faraqee and Ethna Johnson          ment of people in nine West Ahrican&#13;
R. Anl=i and Rashid --aruqee                       arie    n      n   osn           countrnes. Discusses the volume and&#13;
Staff Working Paper No 507 1982 108       direction of internal and extemal flows&#13;
Staff Wcrking Paper No 283. 1980 54       pages (including references)              and the economic and social character-&#13;
pages (trcludzng references)              Stock No. WVP 0507 55                    istics of migrants.&#13;
Stock Nc WP 0383 S3                                                                 A joint World Bank-OECD study Oxford&#13;
Infant andc Child Mortality as a          University Press, 1981. 166 pages (includ-&#13;
Determinant of Fertility: The             ing 22 maps, bibliography, index)&#13;
Healti                                    P'olicy Implications                      LC 80-21352. ISBN 0-19-520186-8. Stock&#13;
Frednck Golladay, coordinating            Susan Hill Cochrane and K. C              No OA: 520186, 529 95 hardcover; ISBN&#13;
author                                    Zachanah                                  0-19-520187-6, Stock No OX 520187,&#13;
Draws cin expenence gamed from            A.n illustraiave analysis that suggests   $8 95 paperback.&#13;
health cornponents of seventy World       infant mortiaUty may be an Lmportant&#13;
Bank proJects in forty-four countnes      componeni of a fertilty reduction pro-&#13;
betweer 1975 and 1978 Emphasizes          gram Ln countnes where mortality is&#13;
the disprcportionately high expendi-      high and few couples are able to have     Population and Family&#13;
tures incurred on curative medicine,      the number of surviving children they     Planning in Bangladesh: A&#13;
maintenance of expensive hospitals,       desire.                                   Study of the Research&#13;
and sophusticated traLnirg of medical     World 3ank Staff Working Paper No 556     Mohainmad Alauddin and Rashid&#13;
personnel at the cost of preventive       2983. 44 pages.                           Faruqee&#13;
care for the majontv of the people&#13;
Points out that low-cost health care      I_'BN 0-8213-0147-0. Stock No WP 0556     Reviews major studies on family plan-&#13;
svstems are feasible and recommnnends     5-3rning arid on fertility trends, profiles,&#13;
systhe Bar feaiblegan   d rcm  end                                                  and determinants. Evaluates results of&#13;
lendit g for healthn in additron to hav-  Integrating Family Planning               such studies and cntiques their meth-&#13;
ing health components as part of pro-     with Health Services: Does It             odology and applicaton. Underscores&#13;
)ects inX. other sectors.  Helpneed fcor continued study and suggests&#13;
Sectsr .i Pther sectors.                   helpe                                    directions for future research to irn-&#13;
Sector Policy Paper 1980 90 pages (in-    wRashicl Faruqee                          prove the Bangladesh populatoni&#13;
cluding 8 annexes, 4 figures, map).       Staff Working Paper No. 515 1982. 47      problern&#13;
Stock Nos BK 9066 (Arabic), BK 9067       pages                                     World Eank Staff Working Paper No 557&#13;
(English) BK 9068 (French), BK 9069       ISBN 0--8213-0003-2. Stock No WP 0515.    1983 1.76 pages.&#13;
(Spanish) .155 -                                                                    ISBN 0- 8213-0150-0. Stock No. WIP 0557&#13;
55&#13;
m           X  e   |  |    \   7   ]   Visit the World Bank&#13;
I  |  I        I   __I  _       \_\               Bookstore&#13;
K Street              when you are in                 Population and Poverty in. the&#13;
K Street  whe      you are inDeveloping World&#13;
[ I   I I  NWashington, D.C.                    Bill&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 404. 1980 96&#13;
7  1 I Street  7,                                      pages (including 2 appendixes, bibliog-&#13;
raphy)&#13;
zW                E              5L     x     Z                              Stock No. WP 0404 $3.&#13;
H Street&#13;
H Street                                      Lafayette Square           Population Policy and Farnily&#13;
f__I__-_______               Planning Programs: Trends in&#13;
Avenue                                       Policy and AdministrationL&#13;
Kandiah Kanagaratnam and&#13;
G Street                    The White House             Catherine S. Pierce&#13;
F      7    1             I                    . r   |Staff Working Paper No. 447. 1981. 80&#13;
LE_x          W      I   I              I        _                                   pages (including bibliography, appendixesi.&#13;
World Bank Bookstore                                                            Stock No. WP 0447 S3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG 3881.5 .W57 W67 NO.698&#13;
c .3&#13;
TRUSSELL, JAMFS.&#13;
THF POTENTIAL IMPACT OF&#13;
_ _'-' TM CCDTTI TT Y nN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headcuarters                          Eurolpean Office              Tokyo Office                                        z&#13;
1818 Ii Strect, N W                   60, a,'cnuc d'16n,:           Kokusai B3uilding                C&#13;
Washington l) C 20433, U S A          751 lo Paris, Francc          I-I Nlarunouchi 3-choric &#13;
Felephone (202) 477-1234             Telephone (1) 7.3-5421         Chiyoda-ku Tokyo 100 Japan&#13;
I dCx   L'UI 04 15 WORI [1I3ANK      lelex 842-6200218              Iclephone (03) 214-5001                              \&#13;
RCA 248423 WOIRLDBK.                                          Telcx 781-2o838 &#13;
Cable ,ddrcss (INI BAF tAD&#13;
M\SHIll.C,l'\DC&#13;
0&#13;
'-9.&#13;
0&#13;
E.g&#13;
O&#13;
E.g&#13;
0-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554764">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/12/1554764/potential-impact-changes-fertility-infant-child-maternal-mortality
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/12/1554764/potential-impact-changes-fertility-infant-child-maternal-mortality</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1984/12/1554764/potential-impact-changes-fertility-infant-child-maternal-mortality</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/06/14/000178830_98101903425061/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/06/14/000178830_98101903425061/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-06-14T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1984-12-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The potential impact of changes in
            fertility on infant, child, and maternal mortality
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper explores the relation between
            changes in the timing and quantity of fertility, such as
            those that might result from an effective family planning
            program in developing countries, and changes in child and
            maternal mortality. It uses the results from recent
            multivariate studies to estimate the changes in mortality
            that might result from altering maternal age, birth order,
            and birth spacing distributions of livebirths. The results
            indicate that if childbearing were confined to the prime
            reproductive ages of 20 to 34, then infant and child
            mortality rates would fall by about 5 percent. Limiting
            childbearing to ages 20-39 may also reduce the maternal
            mortality ratio by about 4 percent. Universal adoption of an
            ideal spacing pattern in which all births subsequent to the
            first are spaced at least two years apart may reduce infant
            mortality by about 10 percent and child mortality by about
            21 percent.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The potential impact of changes in fertility
            on infant, child, and maternal mortality
        </docna>
        <display_title>The potential impact of changes
            in fertility on infant, child, and maternal mortality</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1984/12/1554764/potential-impact-changes-fertility-infant-child-maternal-mortality</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Early Child and Children's Health,Early Childhood Development,Reproductive Health,Adolescent Health</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Education</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Trussel, J.</author>
            <author>Pebley, A.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903425061</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Primary health, including
            reproductive health, child health and health</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 698</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Education</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Health, Nutrition &amp; Population</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0453-4</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Mortality; Fertility; Child welfare;
            Maternal welfare; Family planning; Birth spacing; Birth
            order; Age; Mothers
            age at marriage,aging,babies,birth
            intervals,birth order,Birth Spacing,birth
            weight,births,breastfeeding,breastfeeding duration,child
            health,child mortality,child mortality rates,child
            spacing,child survival,chiLdbearing,contraceptive use,early
            childhood,Family Planning,Family Planning Programs,first
            birth,hospitals,infant mortality,infants,live births,low
            birth weight,low birth weight infants,Maternal Age,maternal
            death,maternal deaths,maternal mortality,maternal mortality
            rate,maternal mortality rates,maternal mortality
            ratio,maternal nutritional status,maternity
            hospital,menstruation,mortality rates,nutritional status,old
            mothers,older mothers,older
            women,pregnancies,pregnancy,pregnancy
            complications,reproductive behavior,reproductive
            process,sex,siblings,teenage fertility,use of
            contraception,World Fertility Survey,young mothers,young women
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP698</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>IMR</ml:concept><ml:concept>Maternal and Child Mortality</ml:concept><ml:concept>U5MR</ml:concept><ml:concept>Birth Spacing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock and Animal Husbandry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Child Survival and Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Early Child and Children's Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition  Community Based Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition  Raising Awareness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition  Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Breastfeeding</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infant and Child Mortality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Family Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contraceptives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Animal Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Child Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>