<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP719&#13;
The Training and Visit Extension System&#13;
An Analysis of Operations and Effects&#13;
Gershon Feder&#13;
Roger H. Slade&#13;
Anant K. Sundaram&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 719&#13;
inkE           OP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 719&#13;
The Training and Visit Extension System&#13;
An Analysis of Operations and Effects&#13;
Gershon Feder&#13;
Roger H. Slade&#13;
Anant K. Sundaram&#13;
RiNATIOHAL MONETARY FUND&#13;
JOINT LIBRARY&#13;
l4LNATIONAL N1¶I FO&#13;
,LCOrn UCCIlON Al, D 4r LLOpIZNT&#13;
v71F'2-.llGTGil" D.C.  31&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright (© 1985&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing January 1985&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To present&#13;
the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been&#13;
prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed texts, and&#13;
the World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a&#13;
token charge to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The World Bank does not accept responsibility for the views expressed herein, which&#13;
are those of the authors and should not be attributed to the World Bank or to its&#13;
affiliated organizations. The findings, interpretations, and conclusions are the results&#13;
of research supported by the Bank; they do not necessarily represent official policy of&#13;
the Bank. The designations employed, the presentation of material, and any maps used&#13;
in this document are solely for the convenience of the reader and do not imply the&#13;
expression of any opinion whatsoever on the part of the World Bank or its affiliates&#13;
concerning the legal status of any country, territory, city, area, or of its authorities, or&#13;
concerning the delimitation of its boundaries, or national affiliation.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications, both free and for sale, is described in the&#13;
Catalog of Publications; the continuing research program is outlined in Abstracts of&#13;
Current Studies. Both booklets are updated annually; the most recent edition of each is&#13;
available without charge from the Publications Sales Unit, Department T, The World&#13;
Bank, 1818 H Street, N.W., Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A., or from the European&#13;
Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'1ena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Gershon Feder is an economist in the Research Unit of the Agriculture and Rural&#13;
Development Department, and Roger H. Slade an economist in the Projects Depart-&#13;
ment of the South Asia Regional Office, both in the World Bank. Anant K. Sundaram&#13;
is a consultant to the Bank.&#13;
Library of Congreas CE inloging in Publiomn Dz/g&#13;
Feder, Gershon, 1947-&#13;
The training and visit extension system.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no, 719)&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
1. Agricultural extension work-°India, I. Slade,&#13;
Roger,    1941=          ,   IIo  Sundaram,      Anant   K. (Anant     Kumar),&#13;
19540         ,   III. Title.        IV. Series.&#13;
S544150I5F42        1985         630'.7'15054              84-29945&#13;
ISBN   08213-0497-6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-iii-&#13;
ABSTRACT&#13;
The paper analyzes several aspects of the operation and effects of&#13;
the T&amp;V extension system. Specific questions related to the supply of, and&#13;
demand for, extension agents (VEW) visits, the presence or absence of farm&#13;
size bias in VEW visits, seasonal and longer-term variations in the pattern&#13;
of VEW visits, the relative importance of the VEW as a source of information&#13;
to farmers, and the crop yields obtained by farmers in relation to their main&#13;
sources of agricultural advice are addressed in detail.&#13;
The analysis is based on extensive empirical evidence from India.&#13;
In particular, data collected and reported by several state government&#13;
monitoring and evaluation units are used in conjunction with data collected&#13;
during a detailed case study of T&amp;V extension conducted by the World Bank in&#13;
collaboration with the Haryana Agricultural University at Tissar.&#13;
The paper draws the following main conclusions. Most (85%) contact&#13;
farmers are visited regularly, and the majority of noncontact farmers also&#13;
have some interaction with VEWs, suggesting that the supply of extension&#13;
services is adequate. Although a statistically significant bias in favor of&#13;
larger farmers is detected in the pattern of VEW visits, the absolute size of&#13;
this bias is very small. VEWs appear to be more active in the dry season&#13;
than in the rainy season, which may be attributable to the past tendency of&#13;
the research system to concentrate on irrigated crop technology. As&#13;
experience with the T&amp;V system increases, contact farmers appear to receive&#13;
fewer visits from VEWs, but visits to noncontact farmers increase. Overall&#13;
there is an increase in the absolute number of farmers receiving visits from&#13;
extension agents. VEWs play a more important role as disseminators of&#13;
information in areas operating the T&amp;V system than in areas relying on the&#13;
older community development system of extension. The role of the VEW also&#13;
increases in importance the more expensive or costly the recommended cropping&#13;
practice. Finally, crop yields of farms that rely on the VEW as the main&#13;
source of information are higher than of farms that rely mainly on other&#13;
sources of information. The yields in farms that depend on other sources do&#13;
not appear to differ greatly from one another, but information from any&#13;
source, in terms of crop yields, appears to be better than none.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-iv-&#13;
CONDENSE&#13;
Le present document analyse plusieurs aspects du fonctionnement&#13;
et des effets du systeme de vulgarisation base sur la methode de formation&#13;
et de visites. I1 examine en detail les questions sp6cifiques concernant&#13;
l'offre et la demande de visites d'agents de vulgarisation, la presence ou&#13;
l9absence, au cours de ces visites, de distorsions fondees sur la taille&#13;
de 19exploitation9 les fluctuations saisonnieres et a long terme et la&#13;
structure des visites , l'importance relative de ces dernieres en tant que&#13;
source de renseignements pour les exploitants9 ainsi que les rendements de&#13;
cultures obtenus par les exploitants par rapport a leurs principales&#13;
sources de conseils agricoles.&#13;
L'analyse se fonde sur l'examen d'un grand nombre d'exemples&#13;
empiriques pris en Inde. En particulier, les renseignements rassembles et&#13;
publi6s par plusieurs organismes publics de suivi et d'evaluation sont&#13;
utilis6s en conjonction avec des donnees reunies au cours d'une 6tude de&#13;
cas detaillee portant sur la vulgarisation par la m6thode de la formation&#13;
et des visites, et realis6e par la Banque mondiale en collaboration avec&#13;
l'Universite agricole d'Haryana, a Hissar.&#13;
Le document pr6sente plusieurs conclusions dont voici les&#13;
principales. La plupart des agriculteurs de contact (85 %) recoivent des&#13;
visites regulieres et la majorite des autres agriculteurs sont egalement&#13;
en rapport avec les agents de vulgarisation effectuant les visites, ce qui&#13;
tend a suggerer que l90ffre de services de vulgarisation est ad6quate.&#13;
Bien que les statistiques fassent apparaitre dans la structure des visites&#13;
une distorsion marquee en faveur des gros exploitants, cette distorsion&#13;
est minime. I1 semble que les agents de vulgarisation effectuant les&#13;
visites soient plus actifs au cours de la saison seche qu'au cours de la&#13;
saison des pluies, en raison peut-etre de la tendance qu'avait dans le&#13;
passe le systeme de recherche a se concentrer sur la technologie des&#13;
cultures irrigu6es. A mesure qu'augmentent l'application du systeme de&#13;
formation et de visites et l'exp6rience acquise, il semble que le nombre&#13;
des visites aux agriculteurs de contact diminue, alors que les visites aux&#13;
autres agriculteurs deviennent plus nombreuses. Dans l1ensemble, on note&#13;
un accroissement du nombre absolu d'agriculteurs recevant des visites&#13;
d9agents de vulgarisation. Ces derniers jouent un r6le plus important&#13;
dans la diffusion de renseignements dans les zones oui a 6te mis en place&#13;
le systeme de formation et de visites que dans celles oiu le systeme de&#13;
vulgarisation plus ancien, ax6 sur le d6veloppement communautaire, est&#13;
utilis6. L'importance du role des agents de vulgarisation effectuant les&#13;
visites augmente aussi en proportion du cout et de I9ampleur des pratiques&#13;
culturales recommand6es. Enfin, le rendement des cultures est plus eleve&#13;
sur les exploitations qui s'en remettent, comme principale source&#13;
d'information, aux conseils prodigues par les agents de vulgarisation au&#13;
cours des visite que sur les exploitations qui comptent surtout sur&#13;
d'autres sources de renseignements. Pour ces derni6res, le rendement ne&#13;
parait pas fluctuer de facon sensible d'une exploitation a l'autre, mais&#13;
il semble que, en termes de rendement des cultures, une information,&#13;
quelle qu'en soit la source, vaut mieux que l'absence totale de&#13;
renseignements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
EXTRACTO&#13;
En este documento se analizan varios aspectos del funcionamiento&#13;
y efectos del sistema de extensi6n agricola mediante capacitaci6n y visitas.&#13;
En 61 se abordan en forma detallada cuestiones especificas relativas a la&#13;
oferta y demanda de visitas de los agentes de extensi6n, a la existencia o&#13;
ausencia de un sesgo relacionado con el tamanio de las explotaciones&#13;
agricolas en las visitas de los agentes, a las variaciones estacionales y a&#13;
mas largo plazo en la modalidad de las visitas, a la importancia relativa&#13;
de los agentes como fuentes de informaci6n para los agricultores y a los&#13;
rendimientos agricolas obtenidos por los mismos en relaci6n con sus&#13;
principales fuentes de asesoramiento.&#13;
El analisis se basa en abundantes datos empiricos provenientes de&#13;
la India. En particular, los datos recopilados y transmitidos por las&#13;
unidades de seguimiento y evaluaci6n de varios gobiernos estatales se han&#13;
usado juntamente con la informaci6n recogida durante un minucioso estudio&#13;
prActico de servicios de extensi6n mediante capacitaci6n y visitas llevado&#13;
a cabo por el Banco Mundial en colaboraci6n con la Haryana Agricultural&#13;
University, en Hissar.&#13;
En el documento se llega a las siguientes conclusiones&#13;
principales. Casi todos (85%) los agricultores de enlace son visitados&#13;
regularmente, y la mayoria de los demas tambi6n tienen cierto contacto con&#13;
los agentes de extensi6n, lo que indica que la oferta de servicios de&#13;
extensi6n es suficiente. Aunque en las visitas de los agentes de extensi6n&#13;
se observa un sesgo estadisticamente significativo en favor de los&#13;
agricultores mas grandes, la magnitud absoluta de ese sesgo es muy&#13;
pequeiia. Los agentes de extension parecen ser mas activos en la estaci6n&#13;
seca que en la lluviosa, lo que puede atribuirse a la tendencia anterior&#13;
del sistema a concentrarse en la tecnologia de la agricultura de regadio.&#13;
A medida que aumenta la experiencia con el sistema de capacitaci6n y&#13;
visitas, al parecer los agricultores de enlace reciben menos visitas de los&#13;
agentes de extensi6n, en tanto que aumentan las visitas a los demas. En&#13;
general, hay un incremento en el ntunero absoluto de agricultores que&#13;
reciben visitas de los agentes, los que desempeiian una funci6n mAs&#13;
importante en la difusi6n de informaci6n en las zonas con servicios de&#13;
capacitaci6n y visitas que en las que dependen del sistema de extensi6n mas&#13;
antiguo del desarrollo comunitario. Ademas, la funci6n de los agentes es&#13;
mAs importante cuanto mas costosa o riesgosa es la practica de cultivo&#13;
recomendada.  Por ultimo, los rendimientos en las granjas cuya principal&#13;
fuente de asesoramiento son los agentes de extensi6n son mayores que los de&#13;
las que dependen principalmente de otras fuentes de informaci6n. Los&#13;
rendimientos de estas ultimas no parecen variar mucho de una a otra, pero,&#13;
en t6rminos de dichos rendimientos, es evidente que el disponer de alguin&#13;
tipo de asesoramiento es mas eficaz que el no disponer de ninguno.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-vii-&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Section                                                                   PaRe No.&#13;
I.   INTRODUCTION ........................................               1&#13;
II.   THE FOCUS OF THE PAPER ..............................               2&#13;
III.   SUPPLY OF AND DEMAND FOR EXTENSION AGENT VISITS           .....     7&#13;
IV. EXTENSION AGENTS IN RELATION TO OTHER SOURCES&#13;
OF INFORMATION ......................................              18&#13;
V.   INFORMATION SOURCES AND FARM PRODUCTIVITY ....          .......    27&#13;
VI.   CONCLUSIONS .........................................              32&#13;
FOOTNOTES ...........         ........................................       34&#13;
REFERENCES ...........         .......................................       35&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. INTRODUCTION&#13;
Agricultural extension has long been the handmaiden of agricultural&#13;
research and usually a poor one. To some extent this has been due to the&#13;
lack of conviction regarding the ability of extension to bring about the&#13;
sharp increases in agricultural productivity heralded by the growing quantity&#13;
of new or modified technology emerging from agricultural research institu-&#13;
tions. Accordingly, increasing attention has been given, in recent years, to&#13;
ways of improving the management and efficiency of extension systems. One&#13;
result has been the emergence of the Training and Visit (T&amp;V) Extension&#13;
System which was originally tested in Turkey in the late sixties. This&#13;
system which is comprehensively described in Benor and Baxter (1984) is being&#13;
introduced in a number of developing countries often with the assistance of&#13;
the World Bank. 1/ It has been most widely adopted, since 1977, in India&#13;
where it has progressively replaced the prevailing system of multipurpose&#13;
village level workers.&#13;
Our purpose in this paper is to analyze several aspects of the opera-&#13;
tion of the T&amp;V extension system and sore of the resulting effects. In the&#13;
next section we delineate a number of questions worthy of study. In par-&#13;
ticular, we discuss three related matters: (i) the supply of, and demand&#13;
for, extension services, (ii) the role of extension agents relative to other&#13;
sources of agricultural information, and (iii) farm productivity in&#13;
-1-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
relation to sources of information. The subsequent three sections of the&#13;
paper address these issues in order and in some detail, drawing or. a rich&#13;
data base provided by Monitoring and Evaluation reports on the implementation&#13;
of T&amp;V extension issued by several states in India and a study undertaken by&#13;
two of the authors in conjunction with the HaryAna Agricultural Unliversity at&#13;
Hissar, India.   Finally, in section six we summarize our principai conclu-&#13;
sions.&#13;
110 THE FOCUS OF THE PAPER&#13;
The early literature on T&amp;V extension (von Blanckenburg et0al. 1980;&#13;
von Blanckenburg 1982; Cernea 1981; Cernea et.al. 1983; Howell 1982a, 1982b;&#13;
Jaiswal 1983; Moore 1984, Shingi et.a10, 1982; Singh 1983) has been mainly&#13;
qualitative in nature and more often than not, a review of first experienceso&#13;
Hence, there are several issues worthy of further study and we have chosen&#13;
three0&#13;
First is the supply of and demand for extension services as measured&#13;
by the frequency of VEW visits0 2/ Specific questions are:&#13;
(a) Is the supply of extension services close to its potential?&#13;
Is demand as high as supply?&#13;
(b)  Is there a difference in the extension agents' interaction&#13;
with farmers belonging to different farm-size categories?&#13;
(c) Is there a difference in the pattern of visits between the&#13;
two major cropping seasons, namely, kharif, (rainy season)&#13;
and rabi (dry season)?&#13;
(d) How does the pattern of interaction change as the newv form&#13;
of extension becomes more established?&#13;
Regarding the questions in (a), we presume that when the 'T&amp;V system&#13;
functions properly, there should be a high supply of extension services since&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
the system allows inter alia for effective supervision. Technically, we&#13;
define "high supply" as being close to the designed frequency of agents&#13;
interaction with contact farmers. Demand, as measured by extension agent&#13;
interaction with non-contact farmers, is bound to be lower than the observed&#13;
level of interaction with contact farmers, since such farmers are less aware&#13;
of the availability of extension services. Demand should, however, be higher&#13;
in areas with T&amp;V extension than in non-T&amp;V areas. This is due to the fact&#13;
that the cost to the farmer of information search and acquisition will be&#13;
lower in an area of intensive extension coverage because agents are more&#13;
numerous (Feder and Slade, 1984b).    There may, however, be a demand-reducing&#13;
effect because non-contact farmers under the T&amp;V system are supposed to&#13;
obtain information passed on from contact farmers and this could weaken their&#13;
motivation to meet with the VEW (i.e., lower their apparent demand for exten-&#13;
sion services). In areas without T&amp;V extension however, there are no&#13;
formally designated contact farmers and hence this demand reducing tendency&#13;
may not exist.&#13;
In examining question (b), evidence suggests that extension agents&#13;
are traditionally biased towards the more wealthy and influential farmers&#13;
(see for example, Howell 1982a; p. 10). The factors and motivations gener-&#13;
ating such a bias in the supply of extension services could still be present&#13;
under the reformed extension system. On the demand side, tVe economics of&#13;
information-acquisition suggest that demand by smaller farmers will be less&#13;
than that by larger farmers (Feder and Slade 1984b).&#13;
Concerning (c) above, it is expected that the VEW will play a more&#13;
significant role in the dry season (i.e., rabi) if there are a significant&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
number of farmers with access to irrigation0 This is because agricultural&#13;
research in countries like India has traditionally been directed towards&#13;
improv.ing technology for irrigated rather than rainfed crops. Hence, for&#13;
irrigated crops there is a greater quantum of proven technology available for&#13;
delivery to farmers by t1he extension service. However, as we hypothesize&#13;
below, the greater riskiness of rainfed agriculture could serve to increase&#13;
the demand for accurate and proven information during the wet (Inarif)&#13;
season.&#13;
In relation to question (d), it is conceivable that as initial&#13;
enthusiasm and institutional support diminish, various aspects of extension&#13;
operations, such as visits to farmers, slackien. On the demand side, any&#13;
favorable experience with extension advice and increased awareness of exten-&#13;
sion availability wjill tend to increase farmers' interaction with extension,&#13;
while disappointment with recommended practices may result in diminished&#13;
demand.&#13;
These four questions are explored further in Part III below0&#13;
The second set of questions concerns the VEW as an information source&#13;
in relation to other sources of information (e.g., other farmers, radio,&#13;
etc.) and the extent to which the VEW is a preferred source for more expen-&#13;
sive or complex agricultural practices0   Specifically, we ask ti'e following&#13;
questions.&#13;
(e) How important is the extension agent as a source of information&#13;
in relation to other sources in areas covered by T&amp;V extension?&#13;
How does this compare with the role of an extension agent in a&#13;
non-T&amp;V extension system?&#13;
(f) What is the nature of the interaction betw-Jeen extension agents&#13;
and other sources of information?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
(g) Is the T&amp;V agent more important than other (non-personal and&#13;
non-specialized) sources of information the more expensive/riskier&#13;
an agricultural practices become?&#13;
Concerning (e), we expect the VEW, if the training and upgrading of&#13;
staff skills called for under the T&amp;V system are effective, to be the most&#13;
important source of information, since he is a personalized and specialized&#13;
means of information transmission to farmers while also being more readily&#13;
available due to the schedule of frequent visits. We also hypothesize that&#13;
the importance of the agent under the T&amp;V system outweighs that of an exten-&#13;
sion agent in a non-T&amp;V setting, because of superior training, more frequent&#13;
availability and higher visibility.&#13;
In considering issue (f), our approach is exploratory. We attempt&#13;
to examine other information sources as either complements to or substitutes&#13;
for personalized extension. For example, Orivel (in Perraton et al, 1983, p.&#13;
31) quoting another study related to India (Shore, 1980) states that although&#13;
radio was the medium most equitably distributed, its use had no impact on the&#13;
introduction of agricultural innovations. He suggests that it could,&#13;
however, be complementary and if used as a means of transmitting information&#13;
to VEWs it might also reduce training costs.&#13;
Finally, regarding question (g), the expected answer is positive,&#13;
since the value of specific and accurate information should increase for&#13;
riskier, more expensive, or complicated practices. Hence, risk, cost and&#13;
complexity should increase the importance of the VEW, as he is a specialized&#13;
and personal information source, with access to subject matter specialists in&#13;
case of doubt or to assist him to answer additional enquiries from farmers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6-&#13;
The three questions reviewed above are explored further in Part IV&#13;
below0 Our third and final set of questions relates to farm productivity.&#13;
Specifically:&#13;
(h) Are yields higher for farmers who report the extension agent&#13;
to be their main source of information? Does this hold for&#13;
irrigated as well as non-irrigated farms?&#13;
If extension is delivering a flow of proven and acceptable technology&#13;
then the adoption of that technology is likely to be greatest amongst those&#13;
farmors who depend most heavily on extension for information. Hence there&#13;
should be a discernible and positive effect on crop yields for such farmers.&#13;
Folloving the arguments above, we also expect this effect to be greater in&#13;
irrigated than in rainfed farms. Moreover, we hypothesize that this will hold&#13;
even if the information provided by extension in rainfed and irrigated areas&#13;
had equal expected value as the inherent riskiness of rainfed agriculture is&#13;
greater than that of irrigated agriculture0 This question is explored fur-&#13;
ther in Part V0&#13;
The data for our analysis pertain to India and are drawn from two&#13;
main sources: primary data collected by the Haryana Agricultural University&#13;
(HAU) in a case study in North India, sponsored and supervised by the World&#13;
Bank between 1981 and 1983, 3/ and the Monitoring and Evaluation (M&amp;E)&#13;
reports produced by twelve of the thirteen states in India where T&amp;V has been&#13;
progressively instituted since 1977. Wherever relevant we indicate w^lhich&#13;
source we have used.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
III. SUPPLY OF AND DEMAND FOR EXTENSION AGENT VISITS&#13;
The interactions of the VEW with contact farmers can be viewed as a&#13;
system determined "supply" of extension services. "Supply" is a relevant&#13;
concept because the T&amp;V system requires the VEW to provide these services&#13;
to contact farmers regularly. Contact farmers, in turn, are expected to&#13;
disseminate this information to non-contact farmers. Thus for non-contact&#13;
farmers, the interactions between farmers and extension agents are likely to&#13;
be "demand" determined -- i.e., non-contact farmer meetings with the exten-&#13;
sion agent may reflect the farmer "demanding" the information, since it is&#13;
not a system imperative that the VEW visit regularly farmers other than&#13;
contact farmers. 4/ The VEW is expected, however, to accommodate requests&#13;
for information from all farmers. It is also expected that non-contact&#13;
farmors will occasionally attend meetings between the VEW and contact&#13;
farmers.&#13;
For the purpose of examining the broad differences in the quantum&#13;
of visits by the extension agent to contact and non-contact farmers, data&#13;
from M&amp;E reports from seven states in India over a number of years are sum-&#13;
marized in Table 1. These reports have been produced more-or-less regularly&#13;
by the states where T&amp;V has been instituted. The data are comparable across&#13;
states because all M&amp;E units use the same sampling design, definitions and&#13;
questionnaire (for details, see Slade and Feder, 1981). The reference period&#13;
for visit frequencies as reported in the Table is one month, but it is pos-&#13;
sible that non-contact farmers, since they do not receive regular visits, had&#13;
a longer time horizon in mind, thus generating an exaggerated per mensem&#13;
visit frequency.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The critical indicator is the percentage of farmers who report not&#13;
seeing extension agents. For contact farmers, this ranges from lo2 to 34.7&#13;
percent, while for non-contact farmers, it ranges from 2104 to 5902 percent.&#13;
Across all seven states the average percentage of 'no-visits reported by&#13;
contact farmers is 15.4 percent (i.e., about 85 percent of contact farmers&#13;
were visited at least once in the reference month), Dwyhile 34.5% of the&#13;
non-contact farmers reported no interaction with extension (see Table 2)o&#13;
The demand for T&amp;V extension services as measured by non-contact farmers&#13;
interaction with extension agents thus appears significant. Considering that&#13;
some share of 'no-visits' must be due to factors such as agent illness,&#13;
vacant posts, contact farmer non-availability, etc. (factors that SFeder and&#13;
Slade, 1984a, PO15D refer to as "normal friction") the actual supply of T&amp;V&#13;
extension services seems adequate relative to the potential supply.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9-&#13;
Table 1:         FREQUENCY OF VEW VISITS AND FARM SIZE&#13;
C ONTACT FARMRS                         NO-OTACT FARMRS---&#13;
states/seasonsa   i Monltoring or      Sample I No, of Visits Within      ISample I Me00. iof Visits Within&#13;
anLd opera ted   I Konitoring         I Size  I  the   atFu       ek        Stane  I the Past Four Weeks &#13;
Farm Size        I  u    valuatiLon   I       I   0      1     2 or morel          I    0     1      2 or note I&#13;
I    I ---- percent -     -               -  --    trerent &#13;
Rahi    1981-82          H&#13;
Snail Farme !/                          251   17.1   14.0   68.9            333      48.6   27.9      23.5&#13;
Large Fatus                             202   15.9   12.8   71.3            138     45.7    29.7      24.6&#13;
Ilharif 1982-83          H&#13;
Small Faetu                             232   16.4' 17.2    66.4            309      40.4   35.9      23.7&#13;
Large Farms                             219   10.0   20.1   69.9            138      45.6   21.0      33.3'&#13;
Kharif 1982-83           McE&#13;
Small farms                              64    7.8   21.9    70.3           658      52.3   24.5      23.2&#13;
Large Farms                              64    6.2   17.2   76.6            267      49.8   21.3      28.9&#13;
flbhi   1981-82          N&#13;
Small Farms                           2024    15.4* 17.3    67.3           1482      30.2   21.8      48.0*&#13;
Large Farms                            1143   12.3   20.6    67.1           530      32.6   26.4      41.0&#13;
Rebi    1981-82          MCI&#13;
Small Farms                              86   17.4   16.3   66.3            395      40.3   21.8      37.9&#13;
Large farms                             159   11.4   17.6    71.0           493      40.2   25.8      34.0&#13;
Ibarif 1982-83           N&#13;
Snall Fakrms                          1499    10.1   10.8    79.1*         1869      28.0   16.2      35.8*&#13;
Large Farus                            1133   10.9   14.7    74.4           760      25.8   25.8      4.8.4&#13;
[harnf 1982-83           McE&#13;
Small farms                             307   13.0   24.1    62.9          2065      50.7   19.7      29.6&#13;
Large Fetus                             235    8.9   27.2   63.8            712      50.6   20.5      28.9&#13;
Rabi    1982-83          N&#13;
Small Farms                           1280    13.0   21.6   65.4           1621      28.2   24.6      47.2&#13;
Large Farms                             988   14.0   15.0   71.0'           698      27.8   22.7      49.3&#13;
Rahi    1982-83          MCI&#13;
Small Farms                              69   18.8   23.2    38.0           606      579*9   18.0     24.1&#13;
Large Farms                             168   11.3   17.3    71.4*          544      48.7   20.8      30.5*&#13;
[h&amp;rif 1983-84           H&#13;
Small Farms                           1157    20.4* 13.9    65.7           1593      36.4'  18.8      44.8&#13;
Large Farms                             944   15.4   18.6   66.0            648      31.3   19.4      49.3&#13;
Kharnf 1981-82           H&#13;
Small Farms                             503   33.2   19.9    46.9           -          0 .a - - .     &#13;
LArge Forms                             328   28.6   21.6    49.7                      n . a -. &#133;--- &#13;
[harnf 1981-82           MC!&#13;
Small Farms                             298    8.0   19.5    72.5           -          o . a -. &#133;--- &#13;
Large Farms                             237    8.0   20.7    71.3           -          n-- . a -. &#133;--- &#13;
Rtabi   1981-82          M&#13;
Small Farms                             527   23.9   17.5    58.6&#133;-                    n.--  a -. &#133;--- &#13;
Large Farms                             308   20.1   14.0    65.9'         &#133;o---        . a -.  &#133;--- &#13;
Rab&amp;    1981-82          MC!&#13;
Small Farme                             208    8.6   14.9    76.5&#133;-----a. a -.                  &#133;--- &#13;
Large Farms                             184   12.0   20.1    67.9           -----a. a -.        &#133;--- &#13;
[harnf 1982-83           M&#13;
Small farms                             498   24.3   14.3    61.4&#133;---                  a . a -. &#133;--- &#13;
Large Farms                             337   19.3   14.2    66.5&#133;---                  0 . a -. &#133;--- &#13;
Kharif 1982-83           NCR&#13;
Small farin                             394   12.4   15.0   72.6&#133;---                   a . a -. &#133;--- &#13;
Large Farms                            375    13.1   20.3   66.6&#133;-----n. a -.                   &#133;--- &#13;
Rabi    1982-83          M&#13;
Small Farms                            481    21.9   18.8    59.3                      n . a -. &#133;--- &#13;
Large Farms                            354    20.2   22.1   37.7                       n . a -. &#133;--- &#13;
Kharnf 1982-83           MC!&#13;
Small Farms                            394    27.3'   9.6   63.0            423      48.0'  22.7      29.3&#13;
Large Farms                            332    11.2   18.0    70.8*          308      21.4    9.1      69.5'&#13;
m4bargebtra&#13;
Labi    1983-84          M&#13;
Small Farms                           1200    14.0', 12.2   73.8                       n . a -. &#133;--- &#13;
Large Farms                            735    10.2   11.4   78.4'             --     -. a      -. &#133;-- &#13;
Bihar&#13;
Kharnf 1983-84           M&#13;
small Forms                            734    32.2   17.5   50.3            854      59.2   15.2      25.6&#13;
Large Farms                            352    34.7   16.8    48.5           249      55.0   16.1      28.9&#13;
Summer 1982              M&#13;
Small Farms                            347     2      4.6   A3.1            -          a.-  a -. &#133;--- &#13;
Large Farms                              83    1.2    8.4   90.4                       n.--  - a -. &#133;--- &#13;
Khanif 1982-83           M&#13;
Snell Farms                           1317     3.4    2.8   93.8            -          a.--  a -. &#133;--- &#13;
Large Farms                            248     2.8    3.6   93.6            -a.--         a -.  &#133;--- &#13;
*Significant at 5 percent probability level&#13;
n.a. - not available&#13;
Small farms were defined as less than 5.1 hectares in Haryana and Gujarat&#13;
4.1 hectares in Tamil nadu and Karnataka, 3.1 in Madhya Pradesh and Bihar&#13;
and 2.1 hectares in Assam.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-o1-&#13;
Table 2:  FREQUENCY OF VEW VISITS TO CONTACT AND NOW-CONTACT FA2aiERS:&#13;
ALL STATES AND ALL CROPPING SEASONS /a&#13;
Contact Farmers               Non-contact Farmers&#13;
One or More                      One or More&#13;
No Visits        Visits         No Visits         Visits&#13;
&#133;=--------------------   --Percent--&#13;
15.39          84.61           34.49            65.51&#13;
(3,321) Lb    (18,219)         (4,268)          (8,117)&#13;
La  During the four weeks preceding the interview for contact&#13;
farmers. For non-contact farrers the reference period may&#13;
be longero&#13;
/b Figures in parentheses indicate sample sizes,&#13;
Source: Nonitoring and evaluation reports of State&#13;
Governments in India.&#13;
As expected, the demand for extension services (measured by agent's&#13;
interaction with non-contact farmers) is significantly lower than the supply&#13;
(measured by agent visits to contact farmers)0 But the actual supply avail-&#13;
able to non-contact farmers must be less than that which is available to&#13;
contact farmers, thus there is not necessarily a significant level of unused&#13;
capacity. Further, the demand for extension services in a T&amp;V area is far&#13;
higher than the demand in a non-T&amp;V area -- data for a section of Huzaffar-&#13;
nagar district in the State of Uttar Pradesh, which is not covered by the T&amp;V&#13;
system, show that between 89 and 97 percent of the farmers were not visited&#13;
by (or did not seek out) the extension agent during the reference period&#13;
(Feder and Slade, 1984c, po 16)o Because a distinction cannot be drawn&#13;
between contact and non-contact farmers in non-T&amp;V areas, this could be the&#13;
result of either low demand or low supply0   It is know^m however that the&#13;
extension agent/farmer ratio is lowder in non-T&amp;V areas than in areas ewith T&amp;V&#13;
and that in the former areas agents have many duties other than eKtension.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-11-&#13;
Hence it is possible that in areas without T&amp;V extension the low supply of&#13;
extension increases the cost to the farmer of acquiring information from&#13;
extension and thereby reduces the amount of interaction between farmers and&#13;
extension agents.&#13;
As a partial check on the accuracy of the data from tile M&amp;E reports&#13;
we compared the M&amp;E results with those from the HAU/World Bank study.&#13;
Specifically, we compared the incidence of 'no-visits to large and small,&#13;
contact and non-contact farmers, in the whole of Haryana (all 12 districts)&#13;
with those from the HAU/World Bank study in Jind and Karnal districts of&#13;
Haryana for Rabi 81-82, the only season for which comparable data are avail-&#13;
able. The M&amp;E reports indicate (see Table 1) that 17 percent of small con-&#13;
tact farmers and 16 percent of large contact farmers are not visited, while&#13;
the HAU/World Bank data (see Feder and Slade, 1984c, p. 16) show 17 and 14&#13;
percent, respectively. For non-contact farmers, the M&amp;E figures are 49&#13;
percent for small farmers and 46 percent for large farmers, while the&#13;
HAU/World Bank figures are 69 and 52 percent, respectively. These are com-&#13;
parable results although in the HAU/World Bank study area it seems that small&#13;
non-contact farmers are visited significantly less frequently than their&#13;
counterparts elsewhere. In addition, the definition of the reference period&#13;
was quite strict in the HAU/Bank study, while it may have been less so in M&amp;E&#13;
reports.&#13;
Table 3 summarizes data on visits and 'non-visits by farm size.&#13;
Prima facie, there is remarkable similarity between large and small farms&#13;
amongst both contact and non-contact farmers. Amongst contact farmers, 15.9&#13;
percent of the small farms and 14.5 percent of the large farms are not&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-120&#13;
visited, a difference of 14 percent. Similarly, for non-contact farmers,&#13;
the difference is only 3.2 percent. While these differences are statisti-&#13;
cally significant at the 99 percent level (see Table 3), their ai^e indicates&#13;
that the bias in favor of large farmers is not grzet enough to wiarzant&#13;
serious concern. 5/ Moreover, since non-contact farmers' interactions with&#13;
extension agents are probably demand-driven, the difference between large and&#13;
small farmers may merely indicate, as ?redicted by theory (Feder and Slade&#13;
1984b), the tendency of larger farmers to invest more in information&#13;
gathering.&#13;
Table 3: FARM SIZE AND VEW VISITS TO CONTACT AND NON-CONTACT :ARNERS:&#13;
ALL STATES AND ALL SEASONS la&#13;
Contact Farmers               Non-contact Farmers&#13;
One or More                      One or More&#13;
No Visits        Visits         No Visits         Visits&#13;
-----------------------Percent&#133;-----------&#133;---------------&#13;
Small /b      15.91            84.09          35044             64o56&#13;
(2,098) /c     (11,000)         (3,038)          (5,532)&#13;
Large         14049            85.51          32017             67.83&#13;
(1,223)         (7,219)         (l,230)          (2n594)&#13;
/a  See footnote /a in Table 20&#13;
lb  See footnote la in Table lo&#13;
/c Figures in parentheses indicate sample sizes0&#13;
Tests of Significance for 'No-visits' (Large vs Small Farmers)&#13;
"t" Value&#13;
Contact Farmers                2o823)&#13;
) Botn significant at 99 percent&#13;
Non-contact Farmers            3.535)&#13;
Source:  Monitoring and evaluation reports of State Governments&#13;
in India.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-13-&#13;
Further corroboration of the lack of substantial farm size related&#13;
discrimination is provided by Feder and Slade (1984c). Using Logit analysis,&#13;
they exam'ined factors that explain the probability that a contact farmer will&#13;
be visited by an extension agent. Amongst others "area of land owned" was&#13;
entered as an independent variable and was found to be a positive though not&#13;
significant explanator of the probability that a contact farmer would be&#13;
visited.&#13;
Earlier, we hypothesized that visit frequencies would be greater in&#13;
the dry (rabi) season compared to the kharif. Data for both contact and&#13;
non-contact farmers (Table 4) indicate that the incidence of no-visits during&#13;
the rabi season is significantly lower than in the kharif, although the&#13;
absolute difference is small. This result is consistent with an analysis&#13;
conducted by Feder and Slade (1984c, pp. 30-32), which shows that knowledge&#13;
diffusion rates tend to be higher for dry season crops than for rainy season&#13;
crops. These findings support the hypothesis that the extension agent plays&#13;
a greater role in the dry season although the cause may be more closely&#13;
associnted with the available technology and the riskiness of rainfed&#13;
agriculture than the efficiency of the extension system. Another explanation&#13;
may be that the rainy season reduces the mobility of extension agents.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-14-&#13;
Table 4:  CPOPPING SEASON AND VISITS OF VEW TO CONTACT&#13;
AND NON-CONTACT FARMERS:   ALL STATES /a&#13;
Rabi           Kharif&#13;
(dry season)   (rainy season)&#13;
-- - - --  -Percent--- -- - -&#13;
No visits                14045           16025&#13;
Contact                                (3.522) lb      (l0799)&#13;
Farmers&#13;
One or more visits       85.55           830i5&#13;
(9,038)         (9,231)&#13;
No visits                32.60           36.00&#13;
(2,854)         (2D414)&#13;
Non-contact&#13;
Farmers&#13;
One or more visits       67.40           64.30&#13;
(3,836)         (4,290)&#13;
la See footnote /a in Table 20&#13;
lb  Figures in parentheses indicate sample size.&#13;
Tests of significance for 'no-visits' (Iharif vs Rabi)&#13;
"t" values&#13;
Contact farmers:       144 (significant at 90 percent)&#13;
Non-contact farmers: 2.31 (significant at 99 percent)&#13;
Source: Monitoring and evaluation reports of State&#13;
Governments in India.&#13;
We next examine the trend in extension visits as experience with the&#13;
ThV system increases. The results, summarized in Table 5 and Figure 1, form&#13;
a mixed picture0 The proportion of contact farmers not visited goes up&#13;
significantly: amongst projects which are four or more years old nearly one&#13;
in five contact farmers are not visitedo This may, in part, be due to the&#13;
VEW replacing those contact farmers who are deemed inadequate with other&#13;
farmers without formally notifying the original contact farmers of the&#13;
change0 On the other hand, the proportion of non-contact farmers not visited&#13;
declines equally significantly, from about 48 to 36 percent0 This may be due&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-15-&#13;
to the fact that as projects mature, knowledge about the availability of&#13;
regular extension visits spreads and more non-contact farmers take advantage&#13;
of the service. As mentioned earlier, in the T&amp;V extension system the VEW is&#13;
expected to respond to all farmers who approach him with queries (Benor and&#13;
Baxter, 1984). Remembering that contact farmers form only about 10 percent&#13;
of the farming community, the most important finding is that the proportion&#13;
of farmers visited is the greater, the older is the project. 6/&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
D~~~~~~~~c 0&#13;
-16-~~~~~~~~~~~~~~E&#13;
':4 &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-17-&#13;
Table 5: PROJECT LIFE, FARM SIZE AND VEW VISITS: /a&#13;
ALL SEASONS AND ALL STATES /b&#13;
Project                                                                 All&#13;
Life                      Visits      Small Farms /c    Large Farms    Farms&#13;
Sample            Sample&#13;
Percent    Size   Percent   Size   Percent&#13;
Contact           0      5.01       96     7.50      40     5.74&#13;
&gt; 1     94.99    1,819    92.50     493    94.26&#13;
&lt; 1 year&#13;
Non-contact       0     48.65      162    45.65      63    47.81&#13;
&gt; 1     51.35      171    54.35      75    52.19&#13;
Contact           0     17.13      830    13.93     431    16.04&#13;
&gt; 1     82.87    4,016    86.07   2,663    83.96&#13;
2 years&#13;
Non-contact       0     32.34      607    36.27     371    33.83&#13;
&gt; 1     67.66    1,270    63.73     652    66.17&#13;
Contact           0     14.26      592    14.06     448    14.17&#13;
&gt; 1     85.74    3,560    85.94   2,739    85.83&#13;
3 years&#13;
Non-contact       0     28.08      980    26.75     390    27.70&#13;
&gt; 1     71.92    2,510    73.25   1,068    72.30&#13;
Contact           0     22.18      344    14.26     186    19.44&#13;
&gt; 1     77.82    1,207    85.74   1,094    80.56&#13;
&gt; 4 years&#13;
Non-contact       0     38.83      783    28.14     269    36.09&#13;
&gt; 1     61.17    1,233    71.86     687    63.91&#13;
/a  See footnote /a in Table 2.&#13;
/b  Excludes Bihar because of great diversity in project initiation dates for&#13;
different districts. For all other states, the most predominant starting&#13;
date (in terms of number of districts covered) has been chosen.&#13;
/c  See footnote /a in Table 1.&#13;
Source: Monitoring and evaluation reports of State Governments in&#13;
India.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
=18-&#13;
IV. EXTENSION AGENTS IN RELATION TO OTHER SOURCES OF INFOR-ATION&#13;
It is reasonable to presume that farmers tend to prefer &amp;irect9&#13;
specialized, personal and easily accessible sources of information, provided&#13;
that they see such sources as being reliable and professional. Therefore; in&#13;
areas with a large supply of professional entension agents wie expect the role&#13;
of extension as a means of information dissemination to increase. Thus9 we&#13;
pose the following questions (i) are T&amp;V agents the most important informa-&#13;
tion source in areas covered by T&amp;V extension? and (ii) do extension agents&#13;
play a more important role in such settings compared to those operating where&#13;
a less intensive system of extension iS present?   We also wish to examine how&#13;
the role of the extension agent changes in relation to other information&#13;
sources as farmers gain increasing "access" to extension0 Finally, we&#13;
hypothesize that extension becomes more important to the farmer the riskier,&#13;
the more complex or the more expensive an agricultural practice becomes.&#13;
We first examine how important the extension agent is as a source&#13;
of information, in ThV and non-TIV areas. Table 6 summarizes primary data&#13;
from the RAU/World Bank study which was collected from geographically con-&#13;
tiguous T&amp;V and non-T&amp;V areas in 1982.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-19-&#13;
Table 6: RELATIVE IMPORTANCE OF SOURCES OF AGRICULTURAL INFORMATION&#13;
Karnal District (State of Haryana)&#13;
T&amp;V District                       Muzaffarnagar District&#13;
Non-Contact         (State of Uttar-Pradesh)&#13;
Main            Contact Farmers           Farmers               Non T&amp;V District&#13;
Information&#13;
Source     Small    Large/a  All    Small    Large/a All      Small    Large/a All&#13;
(N=59) (N=101) (N=160)   (N=93) (N=73) (N=166)     (N=45) (N=45) (N=90)&#13;
&#133;----------------&#133;Percent-------------------     ---------Percent--------&#13;
Extension&#13;
Personnel       42     45      44        11     16     13           0      3      2&#13;
Demonstra-&#13;
tion Days        2      5       4         1      1      1          13      9     11&#13;
Other&#13;
Farmers         27     20      22        48     43     46          49     42     46&#13;
Radio           16     17      16        18     22     20          20     25     23&#13;
Sales&#13;
Personnel        9      7       8        15     11     13          12      8     10&#13;
Research&#13;
Personnel        2      2       2         2      2      2           0      0      0&#13;
Other /b         2      4       4         5      5      5           6     13      8&#13;
All            100    100     100       100    100    100         100    100    100&#13;
/a  Larger farmers were defined as those owning ten or more acres.&#13;
lb Includes written materials, demonstrations, group meetings and miscellaneous.&#13;
Source: HAU/World Bank Study, 1982.&#13;
There is a dramatic difference between the two districts. In Karnal&#13;
(a T&amp;V district) 44 percent of the contact farmers and 13 percent of the&#13;
non-contact farmers indicate that extension agents are the main source of&#13;
information. In Muzaffarnagar (a non-T&amp;V district) only 2 percent of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-20-&#13;
farmers (all large farmers) are of the same opinion. For non-contact farmers&#13;
in Karnal, and for all farmers in Muzaffarnagar, "other farmers" are the most&#13;
important source of information, followed by the radio. "9Other farmers0' are&#13;
an important source of information for contact farmers as well; slightly more&#13;
so than radio. Sales personnel of firms marketing agricultural inputs also&#13;
constitute a significant source of information for all farmers.&#13;
Since other farmers are the most frequently cited source of agricul-&#13;
tural information, and given the impracticality of reaching all farmers&#13;
directly by extension, it is logical to base an information dissemination&#13;
strategy on the principle of a two-step flow, wuhereby some farmero initially&#13;
get continuous and frequent extension visits. Through the natural process of&#13;
information diffusion, these farmers may subsequently be expected to transmit&#13;
this information to other farmers.&#13;
These data also reveal the relative shares of different information&#13;
sources (see Figure 2). Ranking farmer categories by access to the TMV agent&#13;
we see that the share of the VEW goes up from 2 to 44 percent with increasing&#13;
access to T&amp;V extension.   It is then of interest to know which sources&#13;
decline in importance0 Among contact farmers, as the importance of the VEW&#13;
increases the importance of "other farmers0° declines sharply. This is as&#13;
expected, since contact farmers are in a pocition to obtain informatioa&#13;
first-hand rather than through intermediaries0 Among non-contact farmers,&#13;
however, "other farmers"0 continue to play a significant role, w^hich is again&#13;
as expected0  This relationship betw-ieen VEWs and "other farmera" aS cources&#13;
of information is consistent with the two-step communication flow charac-&#13;
terizing the T&amp;V system.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-21-&#13;
The share of radio remains more-or-less constant regardless of access&#13;
to extension services. This is compatible with the hypothesis that radio is&#13;
a source of information that complements the role of the VEW (as suggested by&#13;
Orivel in Perraton et. al., 1983).&#13;
The lowest ranked sources of information are "sales personnel" and&#13;
"demonstration days". The former seem to be an important source for farmers&#13;
in non-T&amp;V areas suggesting that they serve as a partial substitute for&#13;
visits by extenbion agents. These five sources of information account for a&#13;
little over 90 percent of the information needs of all classes of farmers.&#13;
To examine whether there may be differences related to farm-size, a&#13;
similar analysis was conducted for large and small farmers separately. As&#13;
can be seen from Figure 3, the results are almost exactly the same for both&#13;
classes. There is a slightly higher preference among larger farmers for&#13;
information from extension agents (irrespective of whether they were contact&#13;
or non-contact farmers in T&amp;V areas or farmers in non-T&amp;V areas) but the&#13;
differences are not statistically significant.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-22--&#13;
o~~~~t&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-tc&#13;
T~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~O&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-23-&#13;
Figure 3&#13;
100Z    O   t h  e  rs__ ___________100%________&#13;
0                                     0&#13;
a) CUMULATIVE SHARE OF INFORMATION SOURCES - LARGE FARMERS&#13;
100%                                                  100%&#13;
Farmers                 Farmers               Farmers&#13;
b) CElAIESROF INFORMATION SOURCES - SMALL FARMERS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
We also examine data on the T&amp;V system drawn from seven atateo in&#13;
India. These data are taken from the ME reports produced by the State&#13;
Governments and record the main source of informa-tio, namely the "VEW",&#13;
DOother farmero", "gother sources", and "no advice" for contact and non-contact&#13;
farmers0  We preoume that the category "no advice" meano "inimal advice" or&#13;
the acquiaition of information through observation or casual converzation.&#13;
From Table 7, we see that 80 percent of contact farmers and 54 per-&#13;
cent of non-contact farmers claim eatension agents to be their maia source of&#13;
informationo  Those who claim to take "no advice", comprice about 9 percent&#13;
of contact farmers and nearly 19 percent of non-contsct farmeras "Other&#13;
fazme-os"° age the main source of information for 20 perceat of non-contact&#13;
farmers, but less than 7 percent of contact farmeroo These data support the&#13;
finding that eatension agents are the most iapoztant source of agricultural&#13;
information in areas 'aith T&amp;V eatenaion0&#13;
Table 7:  FARMER'S HAIN SOURCE OF INFOLM2ATIOZ .1 STATES&#13;
WITH THE T&amp;V EXTENSION SYSTEN&#13;
Main Sources              Contact          Non-contact&#13;
of Information           Farmers             Farmers&#13;
-----      ercent-    &#133; - - 7°°&#13;
vyE                       79.66               53.58&#13;
Other farmera               6o87              l5992&#13;
Other sources              4o66                7061&#13;
Wo advice                   8o8l              18.69&#13;
All                       100000             100000&#13;
Source:  Nonitoring and evaluation reports of&#13;
State Governments in India.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-25-&#13;
In contrast, data from a study in a non-T&amp;V setting on the&#13;
socio-economic constraints to rainfed agriculture in Thailand (Hutanuwatr&#13;
et. al., 1982) indicate that extension officers are the 4th ranked source of&#13;
information -- the most important being "relatives and neighbors" (equivalent&#13;
to our category of "other farmers") followed by radio programs and community&#13;
leaders. The authors also report that "... more than half of the farmers&#13;
sampled felt that extension officers could not help them solve any agricul-&#13;
tural problems" (p. 25).&#13;
We next examine the question of whether extension agents become more&#13;
important as information sources the more expensive or complicated a practice&#13;
becomes, by calculating "information source ratios" for two increasingly&#13;
expensive categories of agricultural practices. 7/ "Expensive" means the&#13;
opportunity loss resulting from wrong application of the practice as well as&#13;
the simple financial cost. The information source ratio is an indicator of&#13;
the relative importance of two information sources: the VEW and "other&#13;
farmers" (i.e., first-hand versus second-hand sources).&#13;
Relevant data are shown in Table 8. We note that in areas without&#13;
T&amp;V extension the VEW plays a very minor role in relation to both groups of&#13;
practices -- the ratios for less expensive practices and more expensive&#13;
practices are 0.04 and 0.09 respectively. In areas with T&amp;V extension the&#13;
comparable ratios for non-contact farmers are 0.27 and 0.47, while those for&#13;
contact farmers are much higher at 3.98 and 5.14. Reflecting the more&#13;
favorable "supply" conditions, the ratios become higher as access to exten-&#13;
sion increases.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-26&#13;
Table 8: WEIGHTED AVERAGE INFORLATION SOURCE RATIOS FOR UHEAT PRACTICES /a&#13;
Non-T&amp;V Farmers            T6V Non-contact Farmers         T6V Contact Farmers&#13;
Less           More           Less           M9ore          Less           More&#13;
Expensive lb   Expensive      Expenoive      Expensive      Expensive      Eupensive&#13;
Practices /c   Practices /d   Practices tc   Practices /d   Practices /c   Practices /d&#13;
Small    0000             000           0.20          0.28           3.51           4,43&#13;
Large    0.07             0.16          0.36           0.58          4.27           7.50&#13;
All      0.04             0.09          0.27           0.47          3.98           5.14&#13;
la  The "Source Ratio" is the ratio of the number of times that a VEW is cited as the main&#13;
source of information to the number of times that "gother farmers" is cited.&#13;
Lb  "Expensiveness" refers to the opportunity loss resulting from the incorrect appli-&#13;
cation of the agricultural practices as well as their cost, or complextity0&#13;
/c  Less expensive (variety choice, seeding rate and spacing).&#13;
/d  More expensive (use of phosphate, potash and %inc, seed treatment against termites, seed&#13;
treatment against disease, timing of nitrogen application).&#13;
Source: RAU/World Bank Study, Rabi 1982/83.&#13;
There is also a distinct pattern with respect to farm size -- the&#13;
source ratios are consistently higher for larger farms. This may result from&#13;
larger contact farmers having somewhat greater access to the VEW (see Table&#13;
3) and larger non-contact farmers investing more in information acquisition.&#13;
Moreover the VEW is likely to be a more expensive source (in terms of time&#13;
taken to locate and meet him) than "other farmers". In short, irrespective&#13;
of farm size the data show that all classes of farmers prefer to receive&#13;
advice about the more "expensive" practices from the VEW, Similar viewzs are&#13;
expressed by Howell [1984, pp. 174, 175].&#13;
We also examined evidence contained in a detailed report on a study&#13;
of ThV extension operations in the indian State of Madhya Pradesh conducted&#13;
by the National Council for Applied Economic Research (NCAER, 1983). Data&#13;
in the report (pp. 49-51) generally support the contention that VZWs play&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-27-&#13;
an important role as sources of knowledge about recommended practices for&#13;
both contact and non-contact farmers. Further, the NCAER data suggest that&#13;
the importance of the VEW rises as the riskiness or complexity of agricul-&#13;
tural practices increases.&#13;
V. INFORMATION SOURCES AND FARM PRODUCTIVITY&#13;
The process by which extension influences crop yields involves a wide&#13;
range of intervening variables. The effect is indirect and not easily&#13;
measured. However, if extension efforts are successful, this success must&#13;
eventually result in an increase in output per unit input and/or reduced&#13;
costs per unit of product.&#13;
Since the contact point between the extension system and the farmer&#13;
is the village extension worker, it is essential that the VEW, as a&#13;
first-hand information source, be "better" than other second-hand or&#13;
non-personal sources of information. It would be hard to justify the expense&#13;
of an intensive agricultural extension system under any other circumstances.&#13;
A testable hypothesis is therefore implied, namely, that farmers whose main&#13;
information source is the extension agent will have higher productivity than&#13;
those who rely on other information sources, ceteris paribus. Of course,&#13;
there may be some systematic relationship between farmers who are more&#13;
inclined to utilize extension as a main source of information and other&#13;
inherent attributes (e.g. intelligence) which make them better farmers who&#13;
obtain higher yields. Unfortunately, the data do not permit all other&#13;
relevant attributes to be held constant and therefore the analysis below is&#13;
suggestive rather than definitive.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2 8-&#13;
Drawing again on the state ,i&amp;E reports in India, we use data on crop&#13;
yields in the kharif and rabi seasons disaggregated by informatioa source.&#13;
For kharif, we use rice yields and for rabi, wiheat, under both irrigated and&#13;
unirrigated conditions.&#13;
State average yields were calculated by applying weights based on the&#13;
sample sizes for irrigated and unirrigated farms and contact and non-contact&#13;
farmers. The resulting overall average for each etate was set equal to 1000&#13;
Subsequently, each subset of yields was expressed as an index numhaer relative&#13;
to the overall state average. This conversion permits rice and wheat yields&#13;
to be compared (since they differ in absolute magnitudes) and heavily damps&#13;
differences in agro-climatic and socio-economic factors between states. The&#13;
net result of this conversion is a series of inAde2 numbers that is comparable&#13;
across states, crops and cropping seasons0   A summary of the data for&#13;
irrigated, unirrigated and all farms, disaggregated by main source of farmer&#13;
information, is shown in Table 9o&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-29-&#13;
Table 9: YIELD INDICES BY MAIN SOURCE OF INFORMATION /a&#13;
Main Source of Information&#13;
Other          Other          No&#13;
VEW        Farmers       Sources        Advice&#13;
116.25       89.52         92.64          93.22&#13;
Irrigated         (13) /b     (13)          (13)           (13)&#13;
114.75      101.90        103.29 /c       79.88&#13;
Unirrigated       (13)        (13)          (13)           (13)&#13;
114.50       99.08         95.77          86.11&#13;
All               (15)        (15)          (15)           (15)&#13;
La The actual sample base in terms of numbers of farmers is more&#13;
than 1,500; the sample sizes in the table refer to the number&#13;
of average yield index figures and hence represent a mean of&#13;
means.&#13;
/b  Figures in parentheses indicate sample size.     Sample sizes&#13;
differ because, for two states, data disaggregated by&#13;
irrigated and unirrigated farms were not available.&#13;
/c One state, in one cropping season, had an unduly high yield&#13;
figure and the sample base was extremely low in relation to&#13;
the rest and hence was insignificant in the computation of&#13;
weighted average yields for "all" farms. However, in&#13;
computing the average across unirrigated farms in all states,&#13;
this number receives equal weighting. Hence this particular&#13;
figure should be considered an overestimate.&#13;
Source: Monitoring and evaluation reports of State Governments&#13;
in India.&#13;
Farmers whose main source of information is the VEW have the highest&#13;
yield index of 114.5. This is followed by those whose source is "other&#13;
farmers" and their yield index is close to the average. "Other" sources&#13;
(e.g., radio, demonstration days, sales personnel, etc.) have a lower yield&#13;
index of 95.77 and those farmers who receive "no advice", 86.11. Prima&#13;
facie, it would appear that those using the VEW as the main source of infor-&#13;
mation have yields that differ substantially from all other sources, but the&#13;
difference between "other farmers" and "other sources" is much less marked.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
--30-&#13;
All three, however, appear to be better compared to those farmers receiving&#13;
"rno advice".a&#13;
'e test these results more rigorously in a multiple regression&#13;
framework (equivalent to an analysis of variance since all explavatory vari-&#13;
ables are categorical), suppressing the variable against which we test for&#13;
significance. We specify the dependent variable (yield) in its logarithm as&#13;
conventionally done in production analysis0 8/ The first set of results, for&#13;
irrigated and unirrigated farms and all farms,, are show:n separately in Table&#13;
10. In these results we have controlled for 'other sources', that is to say&#13;
the coefficients of the remaining explanatory variables represent deviations&#13;
from the effect of 'other sources'.&#13;
Table 10: YIELD INDEX AND INFORIVATION SOURCES,&#13;
CONTROLLING FOR "OTHER SOURCES"&#13;
Dependent Variable: Log (YIELD INDEX)&#13;
Parameter Estimate&#13;
Independent                   (t' values in parentheses)&#13;
Variable&#13;
All             IrKiRated&amp;  Ujj    irrEg ed&#13;
Intercept      -0.061 (-10419)    -00003 (-0O55)      4.584  (66A8O9)&#13;
VEW             MolO ( 3.119)      O.R41] ( 2.1140)   0.151  ( ,.552&#13;
Other Farmers  0044 ( 0M721)     -3.119 (lI02)       Oo010  ( 00105)&#13;
No Advice      -0.107 (-1750)    o-0.90  (°o.303)  -00223   (20296)&#13;
F                    8.4l8             6.425              5.053&#13;
R2                   00266             002953             002402&#13;
All three regressions have significant F values (at &gt; 99 percent&#13;
levels), suggesting reasonable overall explanatory power0   As suraised,&#13;
y4elds for farmers receiving information from VEWs are significantly higher&#13;
than those for farmers who depend on "other sources". There is significant&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-31-&#13;
difference at the 99 percent level for all farms; for unirrigated farms the&#13;
difference is significant at a little less than 90 percent and for irrigated&#13;
farms at 95 percent. "Other farmers" do not constitute a source of informa-&#13;
tion that has a productivity effect significantly different from "other&#13;
sources" for all farms and unirrigated farms. Receiving "no advice" is&#13;
significantly worse than receiving advice from "other sources" for all&#13;
farmers and unirrigated farmers, but not significantly worse (though the&#13;
direction of the relationship is negative) in the case of irrigated farms.&#13;
Table 11: YIELD INDEX AND INFORMATION SOURCES,&#13;
CONTROLLING FOR "NO ADVICE"&#13;
Dependent Variable: Log (YIELD INDEX)&#13;
Parameter Estimate&#13;
Independent                   (t   values in parentheses)&#13;
Variable&#13;
All             Irrigated        Unirrigated&#13;
Intercept      -0.168 (-1.536)    -0.076 (-1.536)    4.361   (63.561)&#13;
VEW              0.297 ( 4.870)    0.215 ( 3.193)     0.373  ( 3.848)&#13;
Other Farmers    0.151 ( 2.471)   -0.055 (-0.826)     0.233  ( 2.401)&#13;
Other Sources    0.107 ( 1.750)    0.073 ( 1.072)     0.223  ( 2.296)&#13;
F2                   8.418             6.641              5.059&#13;
0.3039             0.3022            0.2402&#13;
Similar results, when "no advice" is the control variable, are&#13;
presented in Table 11. In this set of regressions the coefficients of the&#13;
explanatory variables represent deviations from the productivity effect of&#13;
Ino advice'. VEW advice is significantly better than "no advice" in all&#13;
three cases. "Other farmers" and "other sources" come out significantly&#13;
better than "no advice" for all farms and unirrigated farms, and better, but&#13;
not significantly so for irrigated farms. 9/&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
VI. CONCLUSIONS&#13;
The foregoing analysis of an extensive set of aggregate &amp;nd farm&#13;
level data mostly pertaining to T&amp;V extension operations in India permits the&#13;
following conclusions to be drawn.&#13;
(a)  Approximately 85 percent of contact farmers are visited at least&#13;
once a month, suggesting that "supply" of extension serv2.cesD&#13;
taking normal "friction" into accountD, is reasonable. A&amp;nongst&#13;
non-contact farmers 65 percent have interacted with extencion&#13;
workers at least once during the reference period, suggeoting&#13;
that demand is substantial0&#13;
(b) The data indicate that there is a statistically significant bias&#13;
in favor of visits to large farmers; however, the absolutfe size&#13;
of this bias is very small.&#13;
(c)  T&amp;V agents appear to be more active and in higher demand ia the&#13;
dry as opposed to the rainfed cropping season; this is probably&#13;
explainable by the fact that research has traditionally emphasized&#13;
dry-season cropping technology and this has resulted in more&#13;
reliable advice in the rabi season0&#13;
(d) Visits to contact farmers decrease with the age of the p-oject,&#13;
while they increase for non-contact farmerso lith lengthening&#13;
project life, there is a sizeable increase in the absolute number&#13;
of farmers meeting with extension agents0&#13;
(e)  VEWs play a more important role in the dissemination of iaform-&#13;
ation in areas covered by TIV extension than they do in non-T&amp;V&#13;
settings; in both situations they are relatively more important&#13;
to large farmers than to small0&#13;
(f)  The VEW and radio are probably complementary information sources0&#13;
(g)  "Other farmers" qua information sources appear to play a role&#13;
consistent with a two-step communication flowo In a nor-T&amp;V&#13;
setting they are the most important information source0 In&#13;
areas covered by T&amp;V extension they are the major information&#13;
source for non-contact farmers and a relatively minor one for&#13;
contact farmers0 These results hold for both large and small&#13;
farmers0&#13;
(h) VEWs become increasingly important information sources the more&#13;
expensive or complicated an agricultural practice becomeos; their&#13;
role is somewhat greater in the case of large farmso&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-33-&#13;
(i) Yields in farms that rely on the VEW as the main source of&#13;
information are higher than in farms that rely mainly on other&#13;
sources of information. The other sources do not appear to&#13;
differ greatly from one another, but any source of information&#13;
appears to be better than receiving no advice.&#13;
As more information starts to emerge from T&amp;V projects in other&#13;
countries, future research should focus on comparisons between experiences&#13;
in differing socio-economic and cultural environments. Such comparisons may&#13;
provide insights into the ways in which extension systems may be further&#13;
adapted and improved.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-34-&#13;
F OOTNOTES&#13;
1/ By 1984, it had been adopted by about 40 countries in Eastern and&#13;
Western Africa, South and Southeast Asia, the Middle East, Europe,&#13;
Central and South America (Benor and Baxter, 1984, po 4).&#13;
2/  The terms "0extension agent" and "village e2tension workers 'SVEW)` are&#13;
used interchangeably throughout the remainder of the paper.&#13;
3/  Two geographically adjacent areas    one w^ith T&amp;V and one&#13;
without - in the Indian states of Haryana and Uttar Pradech,&#13;
respectively, were chosen. A sample survey amongst 972 farmers&#13;
was conducted. For details, see Feder and Slade, i984a, ppo7-8o&#13;
4/  In a recent case study of ettension in India [Howell (1984)iL a&#13;
similar distinction between supply and demand is made. Powever, the&#13;
indicators used' for supply and demand are different, and no&#13;
distinction is maintained between contact farmers and other farmers0&#13;
5/ The statistical test used is based on the large sample normality of&#13;
the test statistic:&#13;
Z     I X  P2)/      (1 ')°[(J/N) 4 (l/E )&#13;
where  P. is the proportion of farmers with a certain characteristic&#13;
within sample i, Ni is the sample sizes, y the population&#13;
proportion.&#13;
6/ This can be verified by calculating the weighted average for all&#13;
farmers (contact and non-contact) of the proportion of farmers with&#13;
°ino visit00, using the weights .2 and .9 for contact and non-contact&#13;
farmers, respectivelyo&#13;
7/  The "information source ratio" ia merely the ratio of the number of&#13;
times a VEW is cited as the main source of information to the number&#13;
of times °°other farmers°° is cited0&#13;
8/  This transformation does not at all alter our results; the same&#13;
regressions run for non-logarithmic data produced ident-ical results,&#13;
9/ A test of the difference between the mean yield indices from farmero&#13;
who depended on the VEW and farmers who depended on °°other farmers00&#13;
for advice produced a 't' statistic of 3.14, which was significant&#13;
at 99 percent, suggesting that yields are significantly higher&#13;
for farmers who depend on VZhs as opposed to °°other farmers000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-35-&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
1. Benor, Daniel and Michael Baxter, 1984, "Training and Visit Extension",&#13;
Washington, D.C.: The World Bank.&#13;
2. von Blanckenburg, P., C. Sivayoganathan, M.W.A.P. Jayatilake and&#13;
K.K. Navaratnam, 1980, "Some Observations on Agricultural Extension:&#13;
The Training and Visit System in Sri Lanka", Faculty of Agriculture,&#13;
University of Perdenia, Mimeo.&#13;
3. von Blanckenburg, Peter, 1982, "The Training and Visit System of&#13;
Agricultural Extension - A Review of First Experiences",&#13;
Quarterly Journal of International Agriculture, Vol. 21, No. 1.&#13;
4. Cernea, Michael M., "Sociological Dimensions of Extension Organization:&#13;
The Introduction of the T&amp;V System in India", Extension Education&#13;
and Rural Development Vol. 2: International Experience in Strategies&#13;
for Planned Change, Bruce R. Crouch and Shankarian Chamala, eds.,&#13;
John Wiley and Sons, Ltd., Chichester, 1981.&#13;
5. Cernea, Michael M., J.K. Coulter, and J.F.A. Russell, eds., 1983&#13;
"Agricultural Extension by Training and Visit. The Asian Experience."&#13;
A World Bank and UNDP Symposium.   Washington, D.C.   The World Bank.&#13;
6. Feder, Gershon and Roger Slade, 1984a, "Contact Farmer Selection and&#13;
Extension Visits - The Training and Visit Extension System in&#13;
Haryana, India", Quarterly Journal of International Agriculture.&#13;
Vol. 23. No. 1.&#13;
7.                                 , 1984b, "Acquisition of Information and&#13;
Adoption of New Technology", American Journal of Agricultural&#13;
Economics, Vol. 66, No. 3.&#13;
8.                                 , 1984c, "Aspects of the Training and&#13;
Visit System of Agricultural Extension in India: A Comparative&#13;
Analysis". Staff Working paper No. 656, The World Bank,&#13;
Washington, D.C.&#13;
9. Howell, John, 1982a, "Managing Agricultural Extension: The T&amp;V System&#13;
in Practice", Overseas Development Institute (London), Agricultural&#13;
Administration Unit Discussion Paper No. 8.&#13;
10.               , 1982b, "Strategy and Practice in the T&amp;V System of&#13;
Agricultural Extension", Agricultural Administration Unit, Overseas&#13;
Development Institute (London). Discussion Paper No. 10.&#13;
11.               , 1984.  "Small Farmers Services in India:   A Study of Two&#13;
Blocks in Orissa State", Overseas Development Institute (London),&#13;
Agricultural Administration Paper No. 13.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-36-&#13;
120 Hutanuwatr, Narong, Suchint Simaraks, Rrirkkiat Phipatseritham,&#13;
Chalong Bunthamcharoen, Arnone Yamtree, l982. "Socio-economic&#13;
Constraints in Rain-fed Agricultural Production in the Lower&#13;
North-East Thailand", Faculty of Agriculture, Rohn Kaen University,&#13;
Thailand.&#13;
130  Jaiswal, NOKO, 1983, "Transfer of Technology under T&amp;V - Problem&#13;
Identification", Background Papers:   Workshop on Mianagement of&#13;
Transfer of Farm Technology under the Tranin&amp; and Visit System,&#13;
National Institute of Rural Development, Hyderabad.&#13;
140 Noore, Michael, 1984, "Institutional Development, The World 3ank and&#13;
India's New Agricultural Extension Programme", The Journal of&#13;
Development Studies, Vol 20, No. 4.&#13;
15. National Council of Applied Economic Research (NCAER), 1983,&#13;
"Evaluation of the Training and Visit EZtension Service in Madhya&#13;
Pradesh'8, New Delhi.&#13;
l6o Perraton, Hilary, D.T. Jamison, J0 Jenlins, 7. Orivel and LEurence&#13;
Wolff, 1983, "Basic Education and Agricultural Extension    Costs,&#13;
Effects, Alternatives", Staff Working Paper, Noo 564, The World&#13;
Bank, Washington, D.C.&#13;
170 Reports on Monitoring and Monitoring-cum-Evaluation Surveys of T&amp;V&#13;
System0 Various State Governments, India, 1979-l9830&#13;
l80 Shingi, Prakash M., Sanjay Wodx^walar and Gurindar Iaun, 1982, "Management&#13;
of Agricultural Extension: Training and Visit System in Rajasthan0"&#13;
CoMoAo Monograph, No0 96, Indian Institute of Management, Ahmedabad.&#13;
19o Singh, R0N0, 1983, "T&amp;V in Chambal Command Area (Kota District): Some&#13;
Observations" in Background Papers: Workshop on Mianagement of&#13;
Transfer of Farm Technology under the Trainina and Visit Svstem,&#13;
National Institute for Rural Development, Hyderabad.&#13;
200  Slade, Roger and Gershon Feder, 1981, "The Mionitoring and Evaluation of&#13;
Training and Visit Extension in India: A Manual of Instruction."&#13;
The World Bank, Washington, D.C. Mimeo&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
W   orld   Bank                          The Agricultural Development            their productivity. Valuable to policy-&#13;
Experience of Algeria,                  makers, project designers, rural sociol-&#13;
Pub        licaO   W                     Morocco, and Tunisia: A                 ogists, extension workers, and other&#13;
of   Rdated                              Comparison of Strategies for            agncultural researchers.&#13;
of Reated                   ~   ~~~~Growthf                           1984. 176 pages.&#13;
Interest                                Kevin M. Cleaver                        ISBN 0-8213-0301-5.Stock No. BK 0301.&#13;
Compares agncultural expenence of       $  50.&#13;
Algena, Morocco, and Tunisia. Pro-&#13;
vides insights into the importance of&#13;
food and agnculture for development,&#13;
and determinants of agncultural             NEW&#13;
Adoption of Agricultural                 growth.                                 Agricultural Extension: The&#13;
Innovations in Developing                Staff Working Paper No 552. 1983 55    Training and Visit System&#13;
Countries: A Survey                      pages.                                  Daniel Benor, James Q. Harrison,&#13;
Gershon Feder, Richard Just,and          ISBN 0-8213-0120-9 Stock No. WP 0552.   and Michael Baxter&#13;
David Silbermnan                         $3.&#13;
David Silberman     $3.                                    ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~Contains guidelines for reform of agri-&#13;
Staff Working Paper No 542 1982. 65                                              cultural extension services along the&#13;
pages.                                                                          lines of the training and visit system.&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0103-9 Stock No. WP 0542                                             The central objective-making the&#13;
$3                                       The Agricultural Economy of             most efficient use of resources avail-&#13;
Northeast Brazil                        able to governments and farmers-is&#13;
Agrarian Reform as Unfinished            Gary P. Kutcher and Pasquale L.         achieved through encouraging and fa-&#13;
Scandizzo                               ciitating feedback from farmers to re-&#13;
Business-the Selected Papers            This study, based on an agricultural     search workers through extension per-&#13;
of Wolf Ladejinsky                       survey of 8,000 farms, assesses the ex-  sonnel who visit and advise farmers&#13;
Louis J. Walinsky, editor                tent and root causes of pervasive rural  on a regular, fixed schedule, thus&#13;
Studies in agranan pohcy and land re-    poverty in northeast Brazil. The au-    helping research to solve actual pro-&#13;
form spanning four decades, grouped     thors review a number of policy and      ductfon constraits ced by the&#13;
chronologically according to Ladejin-    project options; they conclude that     fanner.&#13;
sky's years in Washington, Tokyo, and    courageous land reform is the only ef-  Explains the complex relationships in&#13;
Vietnam and while at the Ford Foun-      fective means of dealing with the       training and visit extension and draws&#13;
dation and the World Bank.Oxford         problem                                 attenhon to the range of considera-&#13;
University Press, 1977 614 pages (in-    The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1982  bons that are important to implement-&#13;
cluding appendixes, index).              288 pages.                             ing the system.&#13;
LC 77-24254 ISBN 0-19-920095-5, Stock    LC 8147615. ISBN 0-8018-2581-4, Stock   1984 95 pages&#13;
No OX 920095, $32.50 hardcover, ISBN     No. IH 2581. $25 00 hardcover          ISBN 0-8213-0140-3. Stock No. BK 0140.&#13;
0-19-920098-X, Stock No OX 920098,                                               S5.&#13;
$14 95 paperback&#13;
Agrarian Reforms in                                                              Agricultural Land Settlement&#13;
Developing Rural Economies                  NEW                                  Theodore J. Goering, coordinating&#13;
Characterized by Interlinked                                                     author&#13;
Credit and Tenancy Markets               Agricultural Extension by               Examines selected issues related to the&#13;
Avishay Braverman and T.N.               Training and Visit: The Asian           World Bank's lending for land settle-&#13;
Srinivasan                               Experience                              ment and gives estimates of the global&#13;
Staff  orkingPaper o 433  980 32Edited by Michael M. Cermea,          rate of settlement andthe world's ulti-&#13;
Staff Working Paper No 433 1980 32      JonKC         e,adJh          .mate potentiaey aranbdle lan        ld. sub&#13;
pages (ncludig refeTnces).John K. Coulter, and John F A.maeptnilyraelnd&#13;
RusseUl                                 A World Bank Issues Paper. 1978. 73&#13;
Stock No WP-0433. $3                    Captures nearly ten years of expen-      pages (including 4 annexes). English,&#13;
ence with the Training and Visit Ex-    French, and Spanish.&#13;
Agricultural Credit                     tension System  Addresses five issues.   Stock Nos. BK 9054 (English), BK 9055&#13;
Outlines agncultural credit practices    farmer participation, the research-ex-  (French), BK 9056 (Spanish) $5 paper-&#13;
and problems, programs, and policies    tension Imkage, traimng, system man-     back.&#13;
in developing countnes and discusses     agement, and monitoring and evalua-&#13;
their implications for World Bank op-   tion. Within this framework, extension&#13;
erations.                                system managers and evaluators from     Agricultural Price Management&#13;
A Word Ban Pa pr. 175 85pages(in- six Asian countries and six discussants  in Egypt&#13;
Al dWirld Bank Papexr 1975 85 pages (tn-  present their experience and analyses.  William Cuddihy&#13;
cluding 14 annex tables)Notes the World Bank's strong corn-&#13;
Stock No BK 9039 (English), BK 9052      mitment to agricultural development     Staff Working Paper No. 388 1980. 174&#13;
(French), BK 9053 (Spanish) $5 paper-   in its member countries and to helping   pages (including annex, bibliography).&#13;
back.                                   least advantaged farmers to improve      Stock No WP-0388 $5.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
AACURquR 1nce IPoMeo is ad              Stock Nos. BK 9074 (English),BK 0160&#13;
e llDeveRopin, Counties                (French), BK 0161 (Spanish). $5 paper-     _     -&#13;
George Tolley, Vinod Thomas, and        bck.&#13;
Chung Ming Wong                           ,                D     AnnRyoio&#13;
This book first considers price policies  James E. Austin                           A     f,   I..- Oc 7F ia t&#13;
in Korea, Bangladesh, Thailand, and     Provides and illustrates a framework&#13;
Venezuela, bringing out the conse-      for analyzing and designing agro-in-                       I.,&#13;
quences for govemment cost and reve-    dustyial projects.&#13;
nue, farm income, and producer and      E   S      i  c       D                                           \ 1&#13;
consumer welfare. Other effects, in-    EDI Series in Economc Development.&#13;
cluding those on agricultural diversifi-  The Johns Hopkiz.s University Press,            |&#13;
cation, inflation, economic growth,     1981.2nd printing, 1983. 224 pages (in-&#13;
and the balance of payments are also    cluding appendixes, bibliography, and&#13;
discussed The second part of the book   index).&#13;
provides a methodology for estimating   LC 80-550. ISBN 0-8018-2412-5,Stock            '1       T   I&#13;
these effects in any country Opera-     No JH 2412, $16 50 hardcover; ISBN 0-                         I&#13;
honal tools for measunng the effects    8018-2413-3, Stock No. IH 2413, $7.50        I                i      jI&#13;
on producers, consumers, and govern-    paperback.                                 v,&#13;
ment are developed and applied.         French: L'Analyse des p7olets agroindus-   L         k&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press 1982  trnels. Economica, 1982. ISBN 1-7178-&#13;
256 pages                               0480-3, Stock No. IB 0537 $7.50 paper-&#13;
LC 81-15585 ISBN 0-8018-2704-3, Stock   back                                    l©ir lo1ir: A Mzuiai            r&#13;
No IH 2704, $25 hardcover, NEW  ISBN    Spanish: Analisis de proyectos agroindus-  Q¢t.lII1 L&#13;
0-8018-3124-5, Stock No IH 3124, $9 95  triales. Editorial Tecnos, 1981 ISBN 84-  lntemnaton?l Fiinance Corp.&#13;
paperback                               309-0882-X, Stock No. IB 0520, $7 50 pa-  Decisionmal&amp;ng tool for entrepreneurs&#13;
perback.                                and project rranageLs considering in-&#13;
vestments in integrated poultry pro-&#13;
NErW                               jects. Use thti guide to conduct on-site&#13;
AgricluniRMa  IDrces iin Ciina ivestigation of proposed project. Fig-&#13;
Nicholas R. Lardy                       All   nativ AS     zfrliR WITfLmEIflm   ure production costs and determine&#13;
Analyzes recent adjustments to          PoRid6e in &amp;e Repinilc o                fixed asset and worling capital for&#13;
China's agricultural pncing systems     NoI eL: The@iz FM91RACZHon0 §v          broiler operetions. Analyze market and&#13;
and its effects on urban consumers      GefvesAenll             llnec(Dme       accurately forecast market pnces This&#13;
and overall production pattems. De-                        lMnna      e         comprehensive guide tells how to&#13;
fines price ratios from key inputs and                                          manage inteErated broiler operations,&#13;
outputs and examines prnce/cost rela-   ?ramenms                                gives specifications for broiler and&#13;
hons in view of the institutional set-  Avishay Braverman, Choong Yong          breeder houses and summanzes pro-&#13;
brng for price policy.                  Ahn, Jeffrey S. Hammer                  duction costs.&#13;
Staff Working Paper No 606 1983 84      Develops a two-s2ctor multimarket       Technical Papez No. 10. 1983 110 pages.&#13;
pages                                   model to evaluate agricultural pricing  ISBN 0-8213-0165-9.Stock No BK 0165&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0216-7 Stock No WP 0606.    policies, replacing insufficient standard  $5&#13;
$3*                                     operational methods. Measures the&#13;
impact of altemative pncing policies    The         f- C(rHAC:&#13;
Alfn6l11luraR Iteseadllri             on production and consumption of rice                  G D  ite   ley&#13;
Points out that developing countnes     and barley, real income distnbution,                           FH A?nnaI I?OIIy&#13;
must invest more in agncultural re-     import levels of rice, self-sufficiency in  Edited by .oger D. Norton&#13;
search if they are to meet the needs of  rice, and public budget. Provides a&#13;
their growing populations. Notes that   valuable synthesis of the work that has  andLeopolc:o Solis M.&#13;
studies in Brazil, India,Japan, Mexico,  been done to date on agricultural      The pnncipal tool of analysis is the&#13;
and the United States show that agn-    household models. Helps economists      sector model CHAC, named after the&#13;
cultural research yields a rate of return  evaluate the impact of alternative pnc-  Mayan rain god. This model can be&#13;
that is more than two to three times    ing policies aimed at reducing deficits.  used throughIout the sector to cover&#13;
greater than retums from most alter-    Based on the experience of the Grain    short-cycle cr-ops, their inputs, and&#13;
native investments and cites some of    Management Fund and the Fertilizer     their markets. It can also be broken&#13;
the successes of the high-yielding van-  Fund in Korea.                         down into submodels for partcular lo-&#13;
eties of rice and wheat that were de-   Staff Working Paper No. 621. 1983. 174  calities if more detailed analysis is re-&#13;
veloped in the mid-1960s. Discusses     pages.                                  quired. The model helps planners&#13;
the World Bank's plans to expand its    ISBN 0-8213-0275-2.Stock No. WP 0621.   weigh the costs among policy goalIs,&#13;
lending for agncultural research and    $5                                      which can vary from region to region.&#13;
extension, particularly for the produc-                                         This volume :eports the expernence of&#13;
hon of food and other commodities       AleliaL: coumzffy Cnsme ZUy             using the CHAC model and also pre-&#13;
that are of importance to low-income    of A  llc6wallk2is  1 S 1               sents purely methodological material.&#13;
consumers, small farmers, and re-       and su$ndns                             The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1983&#13;
source poor areas.                      Lucio G. Reca                           624 pages (including maps, bibliographies,&#13;
Sector Policy Paper 1981 110 pages (in-  Staff Working Paper No.386. 1980. 72  index)&#13;
cluding annexes) English, French, and   pages (including 3 annexes).            LC 80-29366. ISBN 0-8018-2585-7, Stock&#13;
Spanish                                 Stock No. WP-0386. $3.                  No. IH 2585. 535 hardcover.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Building National Capacity to            The Design of Rural                      Economic Aspects and Policy&#13;
Develop Water Users'                     Development: Lessons from                Issues in Groundwater&#13;
Associations: Experience from            Africa                                  Development&#13;
the Philippines                          Uma Lele                                Ian Carruthers and Roy Stoner&#13;
Frances F. Korten                        Analyzes new ways of designing rural    Staff Working Paper No 496 1981. 110&#13;
Staff Working Paper No 528 1982 v +      development projects to reach large     pages (including annex, bibitography)&#13;
69 pages (including references)          numbers of low-income subsistence       Stock No. WP-0496 $5&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0051-2 Stock No WP 0528      populations. The third paperback        Economic Retum to Investment&#13;
$3                           ~~~~~~~~printing contains a new chapter by the EcnmcRtrtoIvs             et&#13;
author updating her findings             in Irrigation in India&#13;
Bureaucratic Politics and                The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1975,  Leslie A. Abbie, James Q.&#13;
Incentives in the Management             3rd printing, 1979 260 pages (including  Harrison, and John W. Wall&#13;
of Rural Development                     glossary, appendix, maps,bibliography, in-  Staff Working Paper No. 536 1982 52&#13;
Richard Heaver                           dex)                                    pages&#13;
ISBN 0-8018-1769-2, Stock No JH 1769,   ISBN 0-8213-0083-0 Stock No WP 0536&#13;
Analyzes management problems in          $9 95 paperback                         $3&#13;
implementing rural development from&#13;
a bureaucratic polihcal standpoint       French Le developpement rural l'experi-  Farm Budgets: From Farm&#13;
Emphasizes the need to take account      ence Africa7e Economica, 1977 ISBN 2-    ncome Analysis to&#13;
of informal interests in managing pro-   7178-0006-9, Stock No lB 0545, $9 95     Icm        nlsst&#13;
grams Suggests possible methods for      paperback                                Agricultural Prow ect Analysis&#13;
assessing incentives                     Economic Analysis of                     Maxwell L. Brown&#13;
Staff Workgng Paper No 537 1983 74       Agricultural Projects                    farmn income analysis and the broader&#13;
Pages                                    Second edition, completely revised       field of agncultural project analysis&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0084-9. Stock No WP 0537     and expanded                             and emphasizes the more practical as-&#13;
$3                                       J. Price Gittinger                       pects of project preparation Gives&#13;
Sets out a careful and practical meth-   guidance to those responsible for plan-&#13;
NEW                                  odology for analyzing agncultural de-    ning in agnculture.&#13;
velopment projects and for using these   EDI Senes in Economic Development.&#13;
The Common Agricultural                  analyses to compare proposed invest-     The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
Policy of the European                   ments. It covers what constitutes a      1980 154 pages.&#13;
Community: A Blessing or a               "project," what must be considered to    LC 79-3704. ISBN 0-8018-2386-2,Stock&#13;
Curse for Developing                     identify possible agncultural projects,  No IH 2386, $15 hardcover, ISBN 0-&#13;
the life cycle of a project, the strengths  8018-2387-0, Stock No IH 2387, $6 50&#13;
Countries?                               and pitfalls of project analysis, and the  paperback&#13;
Ulrich Koester and Malcolm D.            calculations required to obtain financial  Spanish Presupuestos de fincas Editoral&#13;
Bale                                     and economic project accountsSpns:PeuetodefcaEiorl&#13;
Baleand economic r oject  accounts  Tecnos,  1982   ISBN   84-309-0886-2,  Stock&#13;
Examines the importance of the Euro-     The methodology reflects the best of     No. IB 0522, $6 50 paperback&#13;
pean Community (EC) in global agn-       contemporary practice in govemnment&#13;
cultural trade Points out that the EC    agencies and international develop-      Fishery&#13;
is the leading importer of agricultural  ment institutions concemned with in-     Highlights the importance of fishenes&#13;
goods and is the dominant exporter of    vesting in agnculture and is accessible  to the economies of developing coun-&#13;
a number of agncultural products Em-     to a broad readership of agricultural   tnes and recommends that the World&#13;
phasizes that policymakers in develop-   planners, engineers, and analysts        Bank provide assistance to those coun-&#13;
ing countnes must understand the im-     This revision adds a wealth of recent    tnes that have the fishery resources&#13;
plications of the EC's common            project data, expanded treatment of      and are willing to develop them fur-&#13;
Agncultural Policy Spells out how this  farm budgets and the efficiency pnces     ther&#13;
policy operates and categorizes impor-   to be used to calculate the effects of an  Sector Policy Paper 1982&#13;
tant commodities                         investment on national income, a glos-   ISBN 0-8213-0138-1 Stock No BK 0138,&#13;
Staff Working Paper No 630. 1984 64      sary of technical terms, expanded ap-    $5 paperback&#13;
pages                                    pendixes on preparing an agncultural&#13;
Stock No WP 0630 $3                      project report and using discounting     Forestry&#13;
tables, and an expanded, completely      Graham Donaldson, coordinating&#13;
The Design of Organizations              annotated bibliography.                  author&#13;
for Rural Development                    EDI Series in Economic Development.      Examines the significance of forests in&#13;
Projects: A Progress Report              The Johns Hopkins University press July  economic development and concludes&#13;
William E. Smith, Francis J.             1982 2nd printing, March 1984 528       that the World Bank should greatly in-&#13;
Lethem, and Ben A. Thoolen              pages (including appendixes and glossaryl  crease its role in forestry development,&#13;
Staff Working Paper No 375 1980. 48     index)                                    both as a lender and adviser to gov-&#13;
pages English and French                 LC 82-15262 ISBN 0-8018-2912-7, Stock    ernments&#13;
Stock Nos WP 0375 (English), BK 9241     No. iH 2912, $37 50 hardcover, ISBN 0-   Sector Policy Paper 1978 63 pages (in-&#13;
(French) $3                  ~~~~~8018-2913-5, Stock No JH 2913, $13 50  cluding 7 annexes) English, French, and&#13;
paperback                                Spanish&#13;
Spanish Analisis economico de proyectos  Stock Nos. BK 9063 (English), BK 9064&#13;
Prices subject to change without notice  agricolas Editorial Tecnos, S A. ISBN 84-  (French), BKL 9065 (Spanish) $5 paper-&#13;
and may vary by country.                 309-0991-5 $13 50                        back&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
major policy options open to the        pages (including 3 annexes, appendix,&#13;
ThEW                                 World Bank in this field.               map).&#13;
7Q)Tes$z$   Tema--lrminoRogie            A World Bank Paper 1975. 73 pages (in-  Stock No. WP-0332. $5.&#13;
(&amp;IDTys2oah                              cluding 2 annexes).                      mnA$zilg 3 m&amp; EVhnaHn        ol&#13;
English-French; Francais-                Stock No. BK 9042. $5 paperback.        AcpaUT         Em(1 LmzaR&#13;
Anglais.                                 LEFd Yemze Syotema aml&#13;
Presents terminology related fo for-     5oCA1        Cao          IF $zS07      Dennis J. Casley and Denis A.&#13;
estry development and erosion control    Deekpmenl eZOTLMO                       Lury&#13;
in arid and semiand lands. Since fuel-   Michael M. Cernea                       This book pzovides a how-to tool for&#13;
wood problems and deserification                                                the design and implementaoon of&#13;
have become serious, particularly in     Staff Working Paper No 452. 1981 35     motitonng and evaluation systems in&#13;
Western Afnca, the World Bank has        pages (including references, bibliography).  rural development projects Because&#13;
become increasingly involved in wood-    Stock No WP-0452 $3                    rural development projects are com-&#13;
based energy and erosion-control and                                             plex, they seek to benefit large num-&#13;
in forest-management projects. Assists       jEW                                 bers of peop!e in remote rural areas,&#13;
translators and researchers who work                                            and they involve a variety of invest-&#13;
in this field.                                                                   ments. Tre need for monitonng and&#13;
A World Bank Glossary-Glossaire de                                               evaluating tirem dunng implementa-&#13;
la Banque mondtale                               ,7-      -,                     tion has been accepted in principle,&#13;
1984. 48 pages                                                                  but effective systems have not hereto-&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0175-6. Stock No BK 0175.                       ~~~~fore been formnulated. The concepts of&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0175-6. Stock No BK 0175.                                            monitoring and evaluation are differ-&#13;
$5  t)rt X  SgLoentiated and issues that need to be&#13;
EmpZav,An=ageed I                                                               considered in designing systems to&#13;
4zm seliltra?  Ln$2nklizoFainX  *  1 W l  m onitor  and   evaluate  specific  projects&#13;
At~~~r~~~: ~~n~~~ifruLional ~~~~~~are outlined, emphasizing the timeli-&#13;
LIT   D     airz &amp;he S1mgl lFazrmeir                                            ness of the monitoring functions for&#13;
Daniel W. Bromley                                --                             effective management Elaborates on&#13;
Staff Working Paper No 531 7982. 96                              -              such techn-cal issues as selection of in-&#13;
pages.                                                                          dicators, selection of survey methodol-&#13;
ogy data analysis, and presentation. It&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0064-4 Stock No WP 0531                                             i E  is directed primnarily to those working&#13;
53                                       D9elze61a&amp;iovn Anrt AgyAculii&amp;rnA       with specific projects and will be use-&#13;
Irait: Il t)e~1 mar ti1 §n SUply          nt  L;Dgegllg ]?Zcj $                  Mi to project appraisal teams, to de-&#13;
Plruope¢&amp;s Icy AgRCM&amp;Me                  John Seidensticker                     signers of monitonng and evaluation&#13;
James Q. Harrison, Jon A.                Outhnes precedures for managing ele-       systems, and to pro.ect staff who work&#13;
Hitchings, and John W. Wall              phants in and around project areas as             Y&#13;
Staff Working Paper No 500 1981 133      part of the project design. Helps proj-  The Johns Hopkins University Press 1982&#13;
ptages (incluing 5Pappendixes, r1erences  ect designers plan activities that will  145 pages&#13;
pages (including 5 appendixes, references,  protect wildlife and prevent financial  LC 82-7126 ISBN 0-8018-2910-0, Stock&#13;
annex).                                 loss from damage by animals. Illus-     No. JH 2910. $8.50 paperback.&#13;
Stock No WP-0500 $5.                    trates methods used to investigate ele-&#13;
phant behavior and ecology. Notes&#13;
that careful scheduling of project activ-  An EZS 5&#13;
ities is required to ensure that ele-  Guido Debo2ck and Ronald Ng&#13;
C1h¢xtinn: A R   w sf t1he               phants are not isolated in production  Staff Workirg Paper No. 439 1980. 91&#13;
areas.                                 pages (including annexes).&#13;
James E. Nickum                          Technical Paper No. 16 1984.50 pages.  Stock No WP-0439 53&#13;
Analyzes irrigation management in the   ISBN 0-8213-0297-3.&#13;
People's Republic of China. Major top-   Stock No. BK 0297 $3                      IVEWA&#13;
ics covered are the institutional envi-&#13;
ronment, the organizational structure,  nmammin                                 monnaenltO  ff   syrt2eE   anm&#13;
water fees and funding, and water al-   RU ZR DeVe?                          EMenq- AIC9&#13;
location The report is based on&#13;
Chinese-language materials published     Om    Snsrem Al?Om the&#13;
in China and now available in the       Guido Deboeck znd Bill Kinsey&#13;
United States.                          Staff Working Paper No. 379. 1980. vio +  Agncultural economists, planners, and&#13;
Staff Working Paper No 545. 1983. 106   70 pages (including 5 annexes, index)   field workers will find this 19S3 case&#13;
pages                                    Stock No WP-0379 $3.                   study report a practical guide for de-&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0110-1. Stock No. WP 0545                                           signing efficient monitonng and evalu-&#13;
$5.                                     MeEMUzaMP LFZCD-eCR LMRICt              ation systems for imahon and similar&#13;
moniawnslane 1EwaRw2flan An             projects. It illustrates the practical ap-&#13;
La2ndl lRelm                            the HIIID1EIR LIW2 DevekpmemR           plication of the principles covered in&#13;
Examines the characteristics of land re-  Piru~eca-mezi(=                       the 19S2 publication Monitoring and&#13;
Evaluation of Agriculture and Rural De-&#13;
form, its implications for the econom-  Mchael M. Cernea                        velop;ment Projects. Highlights the prob-&#13;
ies of developing counties, and the     Staff Working Paper No. 332. 1979. 137  lems as well as the successes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
1983 162 pages.                           World Bank Staff Working Paper No 387    permitting a full social cost-benefit&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0059-8 Stock No BK            1980 108 pages                           analysis of the project&#13;
0059 $5.                                  Stock No WP-0387 $5                      The Johns Hopkins University Press. 1982&#13;
336 pages (including maps and index)&#13;
NEW                                   Project Evaluation in Regional           LC 81-48173 ISBN 0-8018-2802-3, Stock&#13;
Perspective: A Study of an               No. IH 2802, $30 hardcover&#13;
Opportunities for Biological             Irrigation Project in Northwest&#13;
Control of Agricultural Pests in         Malaysia                                  Rethinking Artisanal Fisheries&#13;
Developing Countries                     Clive Bell, Peter Hazell, and Roger       Development: Western&#13;
D J Greathead and J. K. Waage            Slade                                     Concepts, Asian Experiences&#13;
Descnbes how to use living organisms     This innovative study develops quanti-    Staff Working Paper No 423 1980 107&#13;
as pest control agents, either alone or  tative methods for measunng the di-       pages (including references)&#13;
as one component of pest manage-          rect and indirect effects of agncultural  Stock No. WP-0423 $5.&#13;
ment. Biological control offers hope of   projects on their surrounding regional&#13;
long-term-permanent-results, causes       and nahonal economies. These meth-       Rural Development&#13;
no pollution, poses no nsk to human       ods are then applied to a study of the   Discusses strategy designed to extend&#13;
health and is often cheaper than          Muda irngation project in northwest     the benefits of development to the ru-&#13;
chemical controls Gives methods and       Malaysia A linear programming            ral poor and outlines the World Bank's&#13;
costs Specifies controls for specific     model is used to analyze how a project   plans for increasing its assistance in&#13;
crops found in developing countnes        changes the farm economy, and a so-      this sector.&#13;
Technical Paper No 11 1983 55 pages       cial accounting matrnx of the regional   Sector Policy Paper, 1975, 89 pages (in-&#13;
ISBNO-823-014-0  tockNo B0164  economy is then estimated This pro-      cluding 14 annexes)&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0164-0 Stock No BK&lt; 0164      vides the basis for a semi-input-output&#13;
$3                                        model, which is used to estimate the     Stock No. BK 9036 $5 paperback&#13;
indirect effects of the project on its re-&#13;
Prices, Taxes, and Subsidies in           gion Thereafter, a similar methodol-&#13;
Pakistan Agriculture,1960-1976            ogy is used to estimate the project's        NEW&#13;
Carl Gotsch and Gilbert Brown             effects on key national vanables, thus&#13;
Rural Financial Markets in&#13;
Developing Countries&#13;
NEW                                                                         J. D. Von Pischke, Dale W.&#13;
Adams, and Gordon Donald&#13;
Rural Development in China                                                      Selected readings highlight facets of&#13;
Rural Development in China                                                   rural financial markets often neglected&#13;
Dwight H. Perkins and Shahid Yusuf                                              i                    , o&#13;
in discussions of agricultural credit in&#13;
developing countries Considers the&#13;
Looks at China's rural development   China's rural development policy.          performance of rural financial markets&#13;
expenence,as a whole since 1949 Ana- Helps clanfy both the strengths and        and ways to improve the quality and&#13;
lyzes China's agncultural performance  weaknesses of a self-reliant strategy    range of financial services for low-in-&#13;
and traces it back to the technology  of rural development.                     come farmers Also reflects new think-&#13;
and other sources that made that per-                                           ing on the design, administration,&#13;
formance possible. Goes beyond the                                              evaluation, and policy framework of&#13;
conventional sources of growth analy-                                           rural finance and credit programs in&#13;
sis to examine the political and organi-                                        developing countres&#13;
zational means that enabled the                                                 The Johns Hopkins University Press 1983&#13;
Chinese to mobilize so much labor for                                           430 pages.&#13;
development purposes                                                            ISBN 0-8018-3074-5 Stock No lH 3074&#13;
Descnbes the successes and failures of                                          $32 50 hardcover&#13;
Rural Poverty Unperceived:&#13;
Problems and Remedies&#13;
Robert Chambers&#13;
Staff Working Paper No 400 1980 51&#13;
-0 8  w8   pages (including references)&#13;
Stock No WP-0400 $3&#13;
Rural Projects through Urban&#13;
Eyes: An Interpretation of the&#13;
World Bank's New-Style Rural&#13;
Development Projects&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press. 1984.  . -                                  Judith Tendler&#13;
232 pages                                                                       World Bank Staff Working Paper No 532&#13;
LC 83-049366 ISBN 0-8018-3261-6 Stock a     '                                   1982 100 pages.&#13;
No lH 3261 $25 hardcover.                                                       ISBN 0-8213-0028-8 Stock No WP 0532&#13;
$3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANEW                                 most important determinant of overall  ISBN 0-8213-0268-3 Stock No WP 0561&#13;
economic growth, has been sluggish in   (English) $3&#13;
She: anad Gca     in                   Sub-Saharan Afnocan countries dunng      ISBN 0-8213-0269-8. Stock No. BK 0269&#13;
e                         ~~~~~~~~~the past two decades. This overview  (French) $3&#13;
Ceve olpilan  COGUInes: Thenzr          takes a three-pronged approach to un-&#13;
WFTeOen2 anMd lFo enfRlRolle            derstanding the problems of aggncul-&#13;
Winrock Intemational Livestock           tural productio:r in the 47 countnes&#13;
Research and Training Center            that make up the region It outlines          NEW&#13;
Sheep and goats are viewed as an in-     domestic and global constraints; sum-&#13;
tegral component of complex agricul-     manzes price, trade, and consumption    7yain:no aind V$a       ni&#13;
tural systems. This comprehensive       forecasts for major agricultural exports;  Daniel Benor and Michael Baxter&#13;
analysis leads to recommendations on     and project trends.                     Contains a comprehensive explanation&#13;
the need for a balanced production       Staff Working Paper No 608 1983 172     of the organization and operation of&#13;
system approach for research, training,  pages (including more than 75 tables and  the training and visit system of agn-&#13;
and development programs Assesses       charts).                                 cultural extension Emphasizes sim-&#13;
the role of sheep and goats in food      ISBN 0-8213-0221-3 Stock No WP 0608     plicity and decisiveness. Defines or-&#13;
production systems by examining ad-      $5                                      ganization and mode of operation and&#13;
vantages and disadvantages, aid/donor                                            allows continuous feedback from farm-&#13;
support, constraints on contnbuhons,                                             ers to exteiision and research workers.&#13;
and overcoming constraints. Empha-       A Sys$em 01 MDiiwi         a            This method has been adopted in&#13;
sizes the need for a combination of      EvaMflna M3 AgHCUiRUTaIR               some 40 countnes in Asia, Afnca, Eu-&#13;
support activities and marketing and            .       .                        rope, and Central and South Amerca.&#13;
pricing policies for small ruminants     Mcal     M. Crica                       Useful to extension staff at all levels,&#13;
and their products Reviews ongoing       Mihe      .Cre      n     ejmnagricultural research personnel, train-&#13;
projects.                               J. Tepping                               ers, and staff of agncultural organiza-&#13;
Technical Paper No. 15 1983 109 pages.  Staff Working Paper No. 272. 1977 121   tions, as well as universities and train-&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0272-8.                      pages (including 9 annexes, bibliography)  ing institutions involved in agncultural&#13;
Stock No BK 0272. $5                     Stock No. WP-0272 $5                    and rural development and public ad-&#13;
ministration.&#13;
§SCEiD£Es]1Z;g                                             2 n$2 O6t             1984. 214 pages.&#13;
ofDeVeRojpnrg §                          Thnal1: m     .se    ln  Ouy           ISBN 0-8213-0121-7 Stock no BK 0721.&#13;
IFAn$eirne$:ID   nves:   eies            Aal6sl:ff&amp;l llri     md D3vp'rRre       $15&#13;
Richard B. Pollnac                       Trent Bertrand&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 490. 1981 64     Staff Working Paper No 385. 1980 243    War       rn l he §&#13;
pages (including references)             pages (including 2 appendixes)          se6c2ir: 7?,C1M(n3   a&#13;
Stock No. WP-0490 $3.                    Stock No WP-0385 $5 NEW                 and HsuzehoM&#13;
llD¢nncginzHn HeIRL r&#13;
Some AspecQs ol Wheaa a¢ad               Yailotnzlnai 1L.az,, 7enmze ?a&amp;         Meena Acharya and Lynn Bennett&#13;
6e Einic¢e Policy in Ilcndia            Land Use Syr2ems nn Hie                 Fascinating analysis of the complex so-&#13;
Raj Krishna and G.S.                     llDesnsne sD: Am6uRhraX IRzoDe62$       cial, demographic,and economic fac-&#13;
Raj Krishna and G.S.  ~esigr off AopkuaEl~ lpoe2                       tors that affect women's decisionmak-&#13;
Raychaudhun                              Raymond Noronha and Francis J.          ing role in the subsistence sector. Data&#13;
Staff Working Paper No 381. 1980 62      Lethem                                  collected from seven villages show&#13;
pages (including 2 appendixes, 6 tables,  The feasibility of agncultural projects  women piay a major role in agncul-&#13;
bibliography)                            and their intended impact are often     tural production, both as laborers and&#13;
Stock No WP 0381. $3.                    determined by traditional patterns of   managers. Bringing women into the&#13;
tenure and land use This paper pro-     market economy would make better&#13;
NVEW                                 vides agricultural project designers    use of local resources and improve&#13;
with an analytical basis and rationale  their status and economic secunty in&#13;
for examining svstems and suggests      Nepal.&#13;
§nna°S~itaharan Airn6aRlre:              how to use such information in de-      Staff Working Paper No. 526 1983. 160&#13;
Syzahesis and Tadle Pospecas             signing projects                        pages&#13;
Shamsher Singh                           Staff Working Paper No 561 1983 54      ISBN 0-8213-0024-5 Stock No WP 0526.&#13;
Agricultural production, the single      pages.                                  $5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Publications Order Form&#13;
SEND TO: YOUR LOCAL DISTRIBUTOR OR TO WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
(See the other side of thts form)         P.O. BOX 37525&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013 U.S.A.&#13;
Date&#13;
Name                                                Ship to: (Enter if different from purchaser)&#13;
Title                                               Name&#13;
Firm                                                Title&#13;
Address                                             Firm_&#13;
City              State_       Postal Code          Address&#13;
Country    .Telephone (             )               City             State_      Postal Code_&#13;
Purchaser Reference No.                             Country             Rilephone&#13;
Check your method of payment.&#13;
Enclosed is my Fl Check L International Money Order fi Unesco Coupons L International Postal Coupon.&#13;
Make payable to World Bank Publications for U. S dollars unless you are ordering from your local distributor.&#13;
Charge my O VISA O MasterCard fi American Express Li Choice. (Credit cards accepted only for orders addressed&#13;
to World Bank Publications.)&#13;
Credit Card Account Number           Expiration Date                     Signature&#13;
3l Invoice me and please reference my Purchase Order No&#13;
Please ship me the items listed below&#13;
Customer lniernd&#13;
Stock Number  Author/ Title                                      Routing Code  Quantity  Unit Price  Total Amount S&#13;
All prices subject to change.  Prices may vary by country.  Allow 6-8 weeks for delivery.&#13;
Subtotal Cost  $&#13;
lbtal copies      Air mail surcharge if desired ($2.00 each)  $&#13;
Postage and handling for more than two complimentary items ($2.00 each)  $S&#13;
Thtal  S&#13;
IBRD0053                                                         Thank you for your order.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IDis6CrAbutzs of Wad                     Attn Mr Giancarlo Bigazzi                Attn Mr J M  Hernandez&#13;
'via Lamarmora 45                        Castello 37&#13;
lkn    P?ubHafons                        50121                                    Madrid&#13;
ARGENTINA                                Florence                                 SRI LANIA AND THE MALDIVES&#13;
Carlos Hirsch, SRL,                      JAPAN                                    Lake House Bookshop&#13;
Attn Ms Monica Bustos                    Eastern Book Service                     Attn Mr Victor Walatara&#13;
Florida 165 4° piso                      Attn. Mr Tertimasa Hirano               41 Wad Ramanavake Mawatha&#13;
Galeria Guemes                           37-3, Hongo 3-Chome, Bunkvo-ku 113       Colombo 2&#13;
Buenos Aires 1307                        Tokyo                                    SWEDEN&#13;
AUSTRALIA, PAPUA NEW GUINEA,             KENYA                                    ABCE Fritzes Kungi, Hovbokhandel&#13;
FAUI, SOLOMON ISLANDS                    Africa Book Services (E A ) Ltd          Attn Mr Eide Segerback&#13;
FIJI,RSOLOMON     , ISANDS,              Attn Mr M B. Dar                         Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356&#13;
WESTERN SAMOA, AND                       P O Box 45245                            S-1 03 2/ Stockholm&#13;
VANUATU&#13;
The Australian Financial Review          Nairobi                                  SWITZERLAND&#13;
Information Service (AFRIS)              KOREA, REPUBLIC OF                       Libraine Pavot&#13;
Attn Mr. David Jamieson                  Pan Korea Book Corporation               Attn. Mr Hlenri de Perrot&#13;
235-243 Jones Street                     Attn Mr Yoon-Sun vlm                     6, rue Grenus&#13;
Broadway                                 P 0 Box 101, Kwanghwamun                 1211 Geneva&#13;
Sydney. NSW 20001                        Seoul                                    TANZANIA&#13;
BELGIUM                                  MALAYSIA                                 Oxford University Press&#13;
Publications des Nations Unies           University of Malava Cooperative         Attn Mr Anthony Theobold&#13;
Attn. Mr Jean de Lannoy                  Bookshop Ltd                             Maktaba Road, P 0 Box 5299&#13;
av du Roi 202                            Attn. Mr. Mohammed Fahim Htj             Dar es Salaam&#13;
1060 Brussels                            Yacob                                   THAILAND&#13;
CANADA                                   P 0 Box 1127, Jalan Pantai Baru          Central Department Store, Head Office&#13;
Le Diffuseur                             Kuala Lumpur                             Attn Mrs   atana&#13;
Attn Mrs. Suzanne Vermette               MEXICO                                   306 Silom Road&#13;
C P 85, Boucherville J4B 5E6             INFOTEC                                  Bangkok&#13;
Quebec                                   Attn, Mr Jog Ce peda                     Thailand Management Association&#13;
COSTA RICA                               San Lorenzo 1 53 11, Col del Valle       Attn Mrs Sunan&#13;
COSTA RICA                   ~~~~~Deleg Benito Juarez                  308 Silom Road&#13;
Librena TreOs        eran03100 Mexico, D F                                        Bangkok&#13;
Attn Mr H ugo Chamberlain&#13;
Calle 11-13, Av Fernandez Guell          MIDDLE EAST                              TUNISIA&#13;
San Jose                                 Middle East Marketing Research           Societe Tunisienne de Ditfusion&#13;
DENMARK                       ~~~~~~~Bureau                            Attn Mr Slaheddine Ben Hamida&#13;
SanfundsMitteratur                       Attn NMr George Vassilou                 5 Avenue de Carthage&#13;
Sanfundslitteratur             Mitsis Bldg 3                           Tunis&#13;
Attn Mr Wilfried Roloff                  Makarios I Avenue                        TU&#13;
Rosenderns Alle 11                       Nicosia                                  TURKEY&#13;
DK-1970 Copenhagen V                     Cvprus                                   Haset Kita pevi A S&#13;
EGYPT, Arab Republic of                  (granch offices in Bahrain, Greece,      Attn Mr Izzet Izerel&#13;
Al Ahram                                NMorocco, Kuwait, United Arab            469, Istekal Caddes&#13;
Al Galaa Street                          Emirates, Jordan)                        Bevoglu-lstanbul&#13;
Cairo                                    NETHERLANDS                              UNITED KINGDOM AND&#13;
MBE BV                                   NORTHERN IRELAND&#13;
FINLAND                                  Attn Mr Gerhard van Bussell              Microinfo Ltd&#13;
Akateeminen Klakauppa                    Noorderwal 38,                           Attn Mr Rov Selwyn&#13;
Attn. Mr Kari Ltmanen                    7241 BL Lochem                           Newman Lanie, P.O Box 3&#13;
Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100                   NORWAY                                   Alton, Hampshire GU34 2PG&#13;
Helsinki 10                             Johan Grundt Tanum A S                    England&#13;
FRANCE                                   Attn Ms Randi Mikkelborg                 UNiTED S17ATES&#13;
World Bank Publications                  P O Box 1177 Sentrum                    The World Bank Book Store&#13;
66, avenue dclena                        Oslo 1                                   600 19th Street, N W&#13;
75116 Paris                              PANAMA                                   Washington, D C 20433&#13;
GERMANY, Federal Republic of             Ediciones Libreria Cultural Panamena     (Postal address. P 0. Box 37525&#13;
UNO-Verlag                               Attn Mr Luis Fernandez Fraguela R.       Washington, D C 20013, U S A&#13;
Attn. Mr Joachim Krause                  Av 7, Espana 16                          Baker and Taylor Company&#13;
Simrockstrasse 23                        Panama Zone 1                            501 South Gladiola Avenue&#13;
D-5300 Bonn I                            PHILIPPINES                              Momence, Illinois, 60954&#13;
HONG KONG, MACAU                         National Book Store                     380 Edison Wav&#13;
Asia 2000 Ltd                            Attn. Mrs Socorro C Ramos                Reno, Nevada, 89564&#13;
Attn Ms Gretchen Wearing Smith           701 Rizal Avenue                         50 Kirbv Avenue&#13;
6 Fl., 146 Pnnce Edward Road             Manila                                   Somerville, New Jersey, 08876&#13;
Kowloon                                  PORTUGAL                                 Commerce, Georgia 30599&#13;
INDIA                                    Livrarna Portugal                        Bernan Associates&#13;
UBS Publishers' Distributors Ltd         Attn. Mr Antonio Alves Martins          93-     erePle        iha&#13;
Attn Mr. D P Veer                        AtDo Cr    mo 70-7  s                    Lanham, Maryland, 20761&#13;
5 Ansan Road. Post Box 7015                ba                                             Nr&#13;
New Delhi 110002                         Li,bon                                   Blacwell North Amenca, Inc&#13;
(Branch offices in Bombav, Bangalore,    SAUDI ARABIA                             1001 Fnes Mill Road&#13;
Kanpur, Calcutta, and Madras)            Jarir Book Store                        Blackwood, New Jersey 08012&#13;
INDONESIA                                Attn Mr Akram Al-Agil                   Sidney Kramer Books&#13;
Pt Indira Limited                        P.O Box 3196                            1722 H Street, N W&#13;
Attn Mr. Bambang Wahyudi                 Riyadh                                   Washington, D C. 20006&#13;
JI, Dr. Sam Ratulangi No 37              SINGAPORE, TAIWAN, EURMA                 United Nations Bookshop&#13;
Jakarta Pusat                            Information Publications Pnvate, Ltd.    United Nations Plaza&#13;
IRELAND                                  Attn Ms Janet David                     New York, N Y IC017&#13;
TDC Publishers                           02-06 1st Floor, Pei-Fu lndustnal        VENEZUELA&#13;
Attn: Mr James Booth                       Building                               Librena del Este&#13;
12 North Frederick Street               24 New Industnal Road                    Attn. Mr. Juan Pencas&#13;
Dublin I                                 Singapore                                Avda Francisco de Miranda, no 52&#13;
ITALY                                   SPAIN                                     Edificio Galipan, Aptdo 60 337&#13;
Licosa Commissionaria Sansoni SPA       Mundi-Prensa Libros, S A.                Caracas 1%0-A&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG 3881.5 .W57 W67 NO.719&#13;
c.3&#13;
FFDFR, GFRSHON. 1947&#13;
THE TRAINING AND VISIT&#13;
FXTENSION SYSTEM&#13;
DATE   NAME AND EXTENSION  ROOM&#13;
NUMBER&#13;
_~~~~~ &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The WoIld Ban&#13;
rojpe~~~~~~~~t  'lPc2~~~~~~~~~~yo ~~~~~ff1Ce ~~ ~  ~       r&#13;
Headlganzreers                     lEuropean Mice               7cHsyu C'eie                                        z ° &#13;
1818 H Street, N W                 66, avenue d'lena            Kokusai Building&#13;
Washington, D.C 20433, US.A         75116 Pans, France          1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone (202) 477-1234            Telephone (1) 723-54.21     Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex WUI 64145 WORLDBANK           Telex. 842-620628           Telephone (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                        Telex. 781-26838                                    \0&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
0&#13;
0&#13;
1¢3&#13;
CO&#13;
ISSN 0253-2I15/iSBN 0-8213-0497-6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554738">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/01/1554738/training-visit-extension-system-analysis-operations-effects
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/01/1554738/training-visit-extension-system-analysis-operations-effects</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1985/01/1554738/training-visit-extension-system-analysis-operations-effects</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/06/21/000178830_98101903430383/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/06/21/000178830_98101903430383/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1985-01-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-06-21T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The training and visit extension system :
            an analysis of operations and effects
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The paper analyzes several aspects of
            the operation and effects of the T&amp;V extension system.
            Specific questions related to the supply of, and demand for,
            extension agents (VEW) visits, the presence or absence of
            farm size bias in VEW visits, seasonal and longer-term
            variations in the pattern of VEW visits, the relative
            importance of the VEW as a source of information to farmers,
            and the crop yields obtained by farmers in relation to their
            main sources of agricultural advice are addressed in detail.
            The paper draws the following main conclusions. Most (85
            percent) contact farmers are visited regularly, and the
            majority of noncontact farmers also have some interaction
            with VEWs, suggesting that the supply of extension services
            is adequate. VEWs appear to be more active in the dry season
            than in the rainy season, which may be attributable to an
            emphasis on irrigated crop technology. As experience with
            the T&amp;V system increases, contact farmers appear to
            receive fewer visits from VEWs, but visits to noncontact
            farmers increase. VEWs play a more important role as a
            disseminators of information in areas operating the T&amp;V
            system than in areas relying on the older community
            development system of extension.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The training and visit extension system : an
            analysis of operations and effects
        </docna>
        <display_title>The training and visit extension
            system : an analysis of operations and effects</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1985/01/1554738/training-visit-extension-system-analysis-operations-effects</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Crops and Crop Management Systems,Agriculture and Farming Systems,Agricultural Knowledge and Information Systems,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Agricultural Research</subtopic>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Agriculture</teratopic>
        <count>India</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Feder, Gershon</author>
            <author>Slade, Roger</author>
            <author>Sundaram, A.</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903430383</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Agricultural extension</subsc>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 719</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Agriculture</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Agriculture, fishing, and forestry</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0497-6</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Training &amp; visit systems; Agricultural
            productivity; Supply &amp; demand; Agricultural extension;
            Agricultural information
            Agricultural extension,agricultural
            information,agricultural inputs,agricultural
            practices,agricultural productivity,agricultural
            research,Agriculture,crop,crop yields,cropping,cropping
            seasons,crops,dates,dry season,economics,economics of
            information,empirical
            evidence,exploitation,extension,extension services,farm,FARM
            PRODUCTIVITY,farmer,farmers,farming,farms,fur,hay,indica,Karnal,marketing,rainfed
            agriculture,Rural Development,small farmers,Small
            farms,T&amp;V system
        </keywd>
        <owner>SAR</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP719</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Extension &amp; Research</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Irrigated Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Extension</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research and Extension</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forest and Forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Basic Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops and Crop Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Irrigation and Drainage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rainfed Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Credit</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT and Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Primary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>India</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>