<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Pirate Subdivisions and the Market for&#13;
Residential Lots in Bogota&#13;
FILE COPY                                                          SWP435&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 435&#13;
October 1980&#13;
Prepared by: Alan Carrol&#13;
Urbai&#13;
Deve     OF             Co&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.Vh.&#13;
rgton, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
ws and interpretatiors in this doaunent are those of the author&#13;
oid not be attributed to the Ubrld Bank, to its affiated&#13;
ations, or to any indvka acting in their behalf.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author&#13;
and should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated&#13;
organizations, or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Working Paper No. 435&#13;
October 1980&#13;
PIRATE SUBDIVISIONS AND THE MARKET FOR&#13;
RESIDENTIAL LOTS IN BOGOTA&#13;
Residential lots developed illegally by entrepreneurs and sold with&#13;
rudimentary or no public services account for between one third and one&#13;
half of the residential land developed to date in Bogota, Colombia. As&#13;
one alternative to these so-called "pirate" subdivisions, legally approved&#13;
"minimum norm" developments with minimum levels of public services have&#13;
been instituted in Bogota in the past few years. Analysis of data from&#13;
135 pirate and 14 minimum norm developments shows that developers of&#13;
minimum norm lots spend about twice as much on infrastructure per lot as&#13;
do pirate developers, and sell their lots for about eighty percent more&#13;
per square meter. The total cost of minimum norm lots are only a third&#13;
greater than pirate lots because they are only three-fourths as large as&#13;
pirate lots. Median rates of return for pirate developments, calculated&#13;
to be 33 percent per annum in nominal terms, indicate that the development&#13;
of pirate lots is competitive. Median rates of return for minimum norm&#13;
developments, calculated to be 78 percent per annum in nominal terms,&#13;
suggest the presence of significant restrictions on the supply of land&#13;
zoned for minimum norm development. Increasing the land available for&#13;
minimum norm development would likely reduce its profitability to a&#13;
competitive level and lower the price of minimum norm lots, but it would&#13;
be unlikely to eliminate pirate development completely. The higher prices&#13;
of minimum norm lots relative to pirate lots are mainly attributable to&#13;
the greater quantity of infrastructure provided with minimum norm lots.&#13;
Prepared by:  Alan Carroll&#13;
Urban and Regional Economics Division         C° O&#13;
Development Economics Department&#13;
Copyright Q 1980                                         sc,  &lt;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington-, D. C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Page No.&#13;
PREFACE&#13;
SUMMARY                                                                          i&#13;
I.    INTRODUCTION .................................................             1&#13;
A.    Background            .............................................   1&#13;
B.   The Study ..............................................               5&#13;
C.   Data Validity ..........................................               7&#13;
D.    Pirate vs. Normas Minimas Subdivisions .............     ....         7&#13;
E.    Affordability of Lots .............   ..   ...................       11&#13;
F.    Services and Profits ...................................             16&#13;
II.    GENERAL CHARACTERISTICS OF SUBDIVISIONS ...                               18&#13;
A.    Basic Features .........................................             18&#13;
B.   Purchase of Tracts .....................................              27&#13;
C.    Infrastructure and Development Costs ...............     ....        30&#13;
D.    Sale of Lots ...........................................             41&#13;
E.   Total Costs of Development .....         ........................     45&#13;
III.    RATES OF RETURN TO SUBDIVIDERS ..............................             51&#13;
A.    Background .......   .................     .....................     51&#13;
B.   Rates of Return in the Sample ............     ..    ............     53&#13;
C.   Determinants of Rates of Return .........     ..    .............     57&#13;
D.    Real vs. Nominal Rates of Return ...........    ..    ..........     60&#13;
E.    Summary and Conclusions ...............    ..    ...............     62&#13;
IV.   THE DETERMINANTS OF TRACT PRICES ............................              64&#13;
A.    Analytical Framework ...................................             64&#13;
B.   Results for Subdivision Tracts ............     ..    ...........     66&#13;
V.    THE DETERMINANTS OF LOT PRICES ....................     ..........        70&#13;
A.    Background and Model Specifications ....................             70&#13;
B.   Aggregated Sample Results ..............     ..    ..............     72&#13;
C.   Disaggregated Sample ...................................              82&#13;
VI.    POLICY ISSUES:   NORMAS MINIMAS AND THE SUPPLY OF&#13;
SERVICED LOTS ..........................................             89&#13;
A.    Improving the Quality of Lots .............    ..    ...........     89&#13;
B.   Restrictions on Normas Minimas            .........................   92&#13;
C.    Policy Conclusions .................. ...................            96&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS (Contiaued)&#13;
Page No.&#13;
APPENDIX I     -  List of Variables in Superintendencia Bancaria&#13;
Pirate Subdivision Survey, 1977 ....       .............     99&#13;
APPENDIX II    -  Calculation of Internal Rates of Return for&#13;
Subdivisions ...... 0 ..                                   101&#13;
APPENDIX III   -  Hedonic Prices in Competitive Markets .       ..........    104&#13;
APPENDIX IV    -  Hedonic Price Indexes with Infrastructure&#13;
Expenditures ......       ..............................    108&#13;
REFERENCES                                                                    114&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
LIST OF TABLES&#13;
Page No.&#13;
1.    Basic Average Data for Pirate and Normas Minimas Subdivisions          9&#13;
2.    Bogota Household Income Distribution 1977                            12&#13;
3.    Distribution of Monthly Installment Payments for Lots                14&#13;
4.    Distribution of Subdivisions by Number of Lots                        19&#13;
5.    Number of Subdivisions by Initiation Year                             20&#13;
6.    Total Lots Sold by Year in Sample                                     25&#13;
7.    Average Land Uses Within Subdivisions                                26&#13;
8.    Extent of Infrastructure Installaition in Subdivisions                32&#13;
9.    Sources of Financing for Infrastructure   in Pirate Subdivisions     34&#13;
10.    Average Quantities of Infrastructure Installed per Hectare&#13;
Usable Area                                                           36&#13;
11.    Average Costs of Infrastructure Installation per Unit                37&#13;
12.    Average Expenditure on All Infrastructure per M2 Usable Area          39&#13;
13.    Average Professional Services, Publicity, and Administrative&#13;
Expenditures per Lot                                                 40&#13;
14.    Average Rates of Lateness in Payments Among Lot Buyers               42&#13;
15.    Distribution of Major Cost Components                                 48&#13;
16.    Average Total Development Costs Per Lot                               49&#13;
17.    Alternative Average Nominal Rates of Return to Subdividers            55&#13;
18.    Relation Between Rate of Return for Low-Income Subdivisions&#13;
and Subdivision Characteristics                                      58&#13;
19.    Comparison Between Average Nominal and Real Rates of Return&#13;
to Subdividers                                                       61&#13;
20.    Relation Between Tract Price and Tract Characteristics in&#13;
Low-Income Subdivisions                                               67&#13;
Relation Between Lot Price And&#13;
Subdivision Characteristics&#13;
Observations are Subdivisions&#13;
21.    Linear Hedonic  rice inaex witH infrastruccure Quantity -&#13;
Average Lot Price Dependent                                           75&#13;
22.    Linear Hedonic Price Index with Infrastructure Quantity -&#13;
Average Lot Price per Square Meter Dependent                          76&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
LIST OF TABLES (Continued)&#13;
Page No.&#13;
Relation Between Lot Price and&#13;
Lot Characteristics -&#13;
Observations are Lots&#13;
23.    Linear Hedonic Price Index with Infrastructure Quantity -&#13;
Total Lot Price Dependent                                             84&#13;
24.    Linear Hedonic Price Index with Infrastructure Quantity -&#13;
Lot Price Per Square Meter Dependent                                  85&#13;
25.    Normas Minimas Subdivision Proposals Submitted and Given&#13;
Final Approval 1973-1977                                              93&#13;
LIST OF FIGURES&#13;
1.     Location of Pirate and Normas Minimas Developments in Sample           22&#13;
2.     Average Tract Size Across Rings and Sectors of Bogcta                 23&#13;
3.     Average Tract Prices per M   Across FRings and Sectors of Bogota      29&#13;
4.     Average Tract Price per M2 Over Time                                   31&#13;
5.     Average Lot Prices per M   Over Time                                  44&#13;
6.     Average Lot Prices per M   Across Rings and Sectors of Bogota         46&#13;
7.     Average Lot Size Across Rings and Sectors of Bogota                   47&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PREFACE&#13;
This paper is part of a program of urban development research&#13;
being conducted by The World Bank on Bogota and Cali, Colombia. The&#13;
goal of the program is to increase our understanding of the workings&#13;
of five major urban sectors--housing, transport, employment location,&#13;
labor markets, and the public sector--in order that the impacts of&#13;
policies and projects may be assessed more accurately. Another project&#13;
paper that deals with housing in this series is Rafael Stevenson,&#13;
"Housing Programs and Policies in Bogota: An Historical/Descriptive&#13;
Analysis", Project Paper No. 3 (June 1978).&#13;
The author is grateful to Gregory Ingram, Director of the&#13;
City Study, for overall guidance on this paper. He is indebted as&#13;
well to Ricardo Paredes and Luis Guillermo Martinez, formerly of the&#13;
Superintendencia Bancaria in Bogota, for making the data available&#13;
and for their advice on many topics. The author also thanks Luis&#13;
Carlos Jimenez of the Departamento Administrativo de Planeacion&#13;
Distrital for providing important information on normas minimas&#13;
subdivisions and Jose Fernando Pineda, local coordinator of the City&#13;
Study, for furnishing useful contacts and comments on the analysis.&#13;
The paper has benefitted greatly from first-draft comments made by&#13;
Andrew Hamer, Kyu Sik Lee, Johannes Linn, Rodrigo Losada and Rakesh&#13;
Mohan. Finally,the author gratefully acknowledges the computer&#13;
programming help received from Yoon Joo Lee, Jeffrey Lewis and&#13;
Manfred Wagner, and the manuscript editing of Marcia Fernald.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. INTRODUCTION&#13;
A. Background&#13;
The "pirate subdivisions" of Bogota, Colombia differ from&#13;
squatter settlements in that land changes hands through purchase. Modest-&#13;
income families buy small lots from entrepreneurs who acquire tracts&#13;
of land and subdivide them without conforming to zoning laws, subdivision&#13;
regulations, or service provision standards -- hence the term "pirate".&#13;
The subdivisions spring up where land is inexpensive, generally on the&#13;
periphery of the city. The lots usually provide only a bare minimum&#13;
of services, often nothing more than some bulldozed streets and a&#13;
few water standpipes. Buyers typically make down payments of between&#13;
a quarter and a third of the lot value and pay monthly installments&#13;
over one to four years. Families build their houses, often incrementally,&#13;
according to their capacity to pay.&#13;
The small amount of research done so far suggests that pirate&#13;
subdivisions account for a very large proportion of the residential&#13;
land supply in Bogota. One study (Vernez, 1973) estimated that, of the&#13;
total residential area of the city within the urban perimeter in 1970,&#13;
almost one-third had been developed as pirate subdivisions. Another&#13;
study found the fraction to be around 38 percent (Borrero and Sanchez,&#13;
1973). In addition, Vernez reported that in 1970 about 45 percent of&#13;
Bogota's 451,000 families were living on land originally developed by&#13;
pirate subdividers. The proportion of families living in illegal&#13;
developments is much lower in current terms, however. For years the&#13;
city government has been granting legal status to well-established&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
pirate subdivisions, thus allowing residents to obtain better public&#13;
services and clear tenure. One study (Fuentes and Losada, 1978)&#13;
estimated that about 13 percent of Bogota's families lived in illegal&#13;
subdivisions in 1972-73.-/&#13;
The extent of the pirate land business in Bogota reflects&#13;
a high demand for inexpensive residential land and the lack of alter-&#13;
natives available to lower-income people. Commercial and government&#13;
housing in the city is generally occupied by families with incomes&#13;
at least twice those of pirate subdivision dwellers.(Lopez and&#13;
Jimenez; Bender 1975). In addition, land invasion, a widespread&#13;
solution for the poor in other Latin American cities, has not been&#13;
practiced to a significant extent in Bogota.-/&#13;
Two basic conditions have allowed pirate subdivisions to&#13;
flourish in Bogota: the existence of a large supply of inexpensive,&#13;
privately-owned land close to the city and a history of lax enforcement&#13;
of land use and subdivision regulations.    While the authorities have&#13;
11 The foregoing figures are about the best available on the extent of&#13;
illegal land development in Bogota. There appear to be no accurate or&#13;
up-to-date records in any agencies on the total land area occupied by&#13;
pirate subdivisions.&#13;
2/ Bogota is unusual in that invasion accounts for a very tiny proportion&#13;
of lower-income land development: somewhere between one or two percent of&#13;
residential land. The reasons usually given are (1) the scarcity of the&#13;
type of land preferred for invasion, that is, public land or land whose&#13;
ownership is unclear; (2) the history of strong police action in Bogota&#13;
against squatters on private property; and (3) the need for durable,&#13;
solid shelter due to Bogota's cool, rainy climate and the consequent&#13;
disincentive for invasion if the risk of eviction is high after substantial&#13;
housing investments by families (Vernez, 1973).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
traditionally used strong measures to suppress land invasions, they have&#13;
exerted little effective control over land sales between private&#13;
1/&#13;
individuals.-&#13;
Several reasons may motivate a land owner to sell to a pirate&#13;
subdivider. First, a pirate may simply offer the highest price. Land&#13;
in certain parts of the city may be unattractive to legitimate&#13;
developers for the middle-class market because the neighborhood is un-&#13;
desirable, the parcel is too small, drainage is bad, or the land cannot&#13;
be serviced properly. In addition, pirate subdividers are often&#13;
willing to buy land whose development value is otherwise restricted&#13;
by zoning laws. As a result pirate subdivisions have sprung up in&#13;
areas of the city where there should be no development, such as flood&#13;
zones and steep slopes. A third problem that encourages illegal land&#13;
subdivision is the long delay -- often one or two years -- posed by&#13;
the legal development approval process. Pirate subdividers are known&#13;
for the speed with which they transact business, and a parcel on the&#13;
margin -- one that could be developed legally or illegally -- may be&#13;
tipped in the latter direction if the owner is in a hurry to liquidate&#13;
his property. A fourth factor is that not all tracts of land become&#13;
pirate subdivisions in arm's length transactions. Pirate subdividers&#13;
have sometimes coerced land owners to sell by hiring squatters or&#13;
making plysical threats.&#13;
1/ While land development regulations have been tightened in the last&#13;
decade (beginning with Law 66 of 1968), officials in Bogota tend to&#13;
feel that a crackdown on the large pirate subdivision business would&#13;
invite more land invasions, a prospect deemed far worse than pirate&#13;
development.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
While the purchase of the original tract is usually a legal&#13;
transaction, the sale of lots is always illegal. Because pirate&#13;
subdividers ignore zoning laws as well as minimum lotsize and servicing&#13;
standards, the ownership documents (escrituras) given to lot buyers&#13;
are invalid and cannot be legalized until the District government&#13;
"regularizes" the subdivision.-/ This may take many years. It is&#13;
not clear, however, how much of a burden illegal tenure imposes on lot&#13;
buyers. There is evidence, for example, that it does not prevent&#13;
pirate lots, with or without houses, from being resold.-/&#13;
Public officials and the press often portray pirate sub-&#13;
dividers as exploiters and criminals. They are blamed for cheating the&#13;
poor and creating slums. The findings of this and other studies suggest&#13;
that, whatever their motives, pirate subdividers fulfill a useful&#13;
function by providing tens of thousands offamilies with plots of land&#13;
that they could not otherwise obtain without resorting to invasion.&#13;
Buyers rarely lose their lots, despite their illegal tenure. Families&#13;
build homes on the lots, often upgrading them substantially over the&#13;
years. Missing services gradually arrive, and over time some barrios&#13;
begin to take on a middle-class appearance. On the other hand,&#13;
it is not uncommon for lot buyers to be left without&#13;
1/ The principal laws governing lower-income subdivisions are Special&#13;
District Acuerdo 25 of 1975, Acuerdos 20, 21, and 22 of 1972, Decretos&#13;
1259 and 1260 of 1973, and Law 66 of 1968.&#13;
2/ According to data from a 1978 survey of 212 proprietor households&#13;
in pirate subdivisions in Bogota, 43 percent of the lots in the sample&#13;
had been purchased directly from previous owners. Of these, two-thirds&#13;
were bought with houses on them. See Andrew Hamer, Lower-Income Home-&#13;
owner Households in the Developing Metropolis, Part II, October 1979.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
promised services, for services to fail due to faulty construction, or&#13;
for lots to become uninhabitable because of poor drainage. Indeed,&#13;
the social costs of uncontrolled development by pirate subdividers are&#13;
probably large. These include installing services in unsuitable&#13;
places such as steep slopes or flood zones; building service networks&#13;
for inefficient lot layouts; providing transportation services to&#13;
inaccessible areas; revising street and utility construction programs&#13;
to take account of unauthorized development; and coping with erosion,&#13;
pollution, and destruction of natural amenities as a result of&#13;
development in ecologically sensitive areas.&#13;
B. The Study&#13;
This paper deals with the market for pirate subdivision lots.&#13;
Examining the pirate subdivision business is instructive because&#13;
it is a unique case of a large-scale, competitive land market for modest&#13;
income families. This study seeks to apply some basic analytical methods&#13;
to the following questions: 1) what are the rates of return to pirate&#13;
subdividers, and do they indicate the presence of excess demand for&#13;
lots? 2) what are the relationships between prices and characteristics&#13;
of lots, and what do they suggest about the willingness of lot buyers&#13;
to pay for different lot attributes? and 3) what are the differences&#13;
between pirate and legal "minimum norms" (normas minimas) subdivisions,-/&#13;
and is there a potential for expanding the supply of better-serviced,&#13;
better-planned subdivisions?Z/&#13;
1/ Normas minimas refers to a legally-set package of minimum standards for&#13;
services such as water, electricity, and streets (as well as for lot and&#13;
dwelling size) which developers of low-income subdivisions must meet. The&#13;
normas minimas law, first passed in 1972 (Acuerdo 20 of the Bogota Special&#13;
District), was designed to lower the cost oT required infrastructure and&#13;
thus encourage the creation of legal subdivisions for the lower-income market.&#13;
2/ No attempt is made to treat the pirate market's role within the overall&#13;
housing or land markets of Bogota. These topics are not unimportant, but&#13;
they could not conveniently be incorporated into the scope of this study.&#13;
For background information and broader perspectives on pirate subdivisions,see&#13;
Vernez (1973a), Doebele (1975), Losada and Gomez (1976), and Blaesser (1979).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6-&#13;
The analysis covers 149 subdivisions developed over the last&#13;
ten years. In 1977 the Superintendencia Bancaria in Bogota collected&#13;
data on 135 pirate subdivisions as well as 14 normas minimas developments.&#13;
The Housing Division sent out questionnaires to 200-odd subdividers&#13;
whose names were in their files and in records of the District Planning&#13;
Department (DAPD). The respondents were informed that they were legally&#13;
bound to supply the information and that their subdivisions could be&#13;
"regularized" if they cooperated. Data requested for each subdivision&#13;
included the size of the original tract, its price and date of acquisition;&#13;
the number of lots; the total street and open space areas; the amounts&#13;
and costs of services installed (sewer, water, telephone, electricity,&#13;
and paving); and, for each lot sold, its size,price, terms, and date&#13;
of sale (see Appendix I for a complete list of variables included in&#13;
the survey). The 149 pirate and normas minimas subdivisions for which&#13;
completed questionnaires were returned represent the efforts of 121&#13;
individual subdividers.-/&#13;
The paper is divided into six parts. This introductory chapter&#13;
is followed by a descriptive overview covering the general characteristics&#13;
of the subdivisions studied, the purchase of tracts, infrastructure and&#13;
development costs, and the sale of lots. The third chapter deals with&#13;
rates of return to pirate and normas minimas developers. The fourth&#13;
and fifth chapters are devoted to an analysis, based on hedonic price&#13;
1/ No data on dwelling units or on the characteristics of families buying&#13;
lots were collected, hence the focus of this study on the supply side of&#13;
the lot market. The data do permit inferences to be made about demannd,&#13;
however.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
indexes, of the determinants of tract and lot prices, respectively.&#13;
The final chapter presents conclusions and discusses policy issues&#13;
related to the effectiveness of the normas minimas laws.&#13;
C. Data Validity&#13;
The question arises of whether figures obtained from illegal&#13;
subdividers by the authorities can be believed. One would expect sub-&#13;
dividers to exaggerate their costs and understate their revenues so as&#13;
to minimize their apparent profit rates. Checked against the available&#13;
information, however, the magnitudes of all the important variables&#13;
-average tract and lot prices, unit costs of infrastructure, lot sizes,&#13;
and infrastructure quantitites - were found to be reasonable. Sources&#13;
of verification are cited in this paper where appropriate.&#13;
Only one item in the data seems invalid: average overhead&#13;
costs per lot (subdivider expenditures on professional services,&#13;
administration, and publicity) are too high for both pirate and normas&#13;
minimas subdivisions.    Owing to the nature of these items and the&#13;
design of the questionnaire, overhead costs were clearly the most&#13;
difficult to verify. Some subdividers apparently took this opportunity&#13;
to overstate their expenditures. The study attempts to correct for&#13;
this in the rate of return analysis.&#13;
D. Pirate vs. Normas Minimas Subdivisions&#13;
Normas minimas subdivisions are essentially planned and&#13;
approved sites and services projects. Special District Acuerdo 20&#13;
of 1972 permitted not only the lowering of minimum design standards&#13;
for residential developments but also the participation of the private&#13;
sector. The example of pirate subdividers undoubtedly influenced&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
the drafting of Acuerdo 20, which makes it possible for lots to be sold&#13;
as soon as infrastructure plans are approved, thereby allowing sub-&#13;
dividers to realize immediate returns on investment. Anuerdo 20 was&#13;
followed in 1973 by Decretos 1259 and 1260, which set out detailed&#13;
design and engineering specifications for vehicular and pedestrian&#13;
access, lot sizes, open and communal areas, and public services.&#13;
In practice the chief problem with normas minimas subdivisions has&#13;
been the failure of many developers to install the required services&#13;
after lots are sold.- A number of reasons have been suggested for this,&#13;
including underestimation of infrastructure costs by both public&#13;
agencies and developers, excessive delays for developers caused by&#13;
government red tape, and sheer dishonesty. Whatever the real causes,&#13;
the fact is that most normas minimas developments, including the 14&#13;
in this study, do not meet legal service standards, although they&#13;
are generally of significantly higher quality than pirate subdivisions.-/&#13;
Table 1 presents separate figures for pirate subdivisions&#13;
inside and outside Bogota's urban perimeter and for the 14 normas&#13;
minimas subdivisions. Pirate subdivisions outside the perimeter are&#13;
much larger and cost less, as might be expected, than those inside the&#13;
perimeter. In general, land development outside the perimeter is&#13;
subject to different regulations and institutional forces. Where it&#13;
1/ Most lot buyers are probably unaware of this pattern because&#13;
too few normas minimas subdivisions have been developed so far&#13;
(see Chapter VI).&#13;
2/ As evidenced by the Superintendencia Bancaria data and visits to&#13;
several normas minimas subdivisions in Bogota.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9-&#13;
Table 1&#13;
BASIC AVERAGE DATA FOR PIRATE AND NORMAS MINIMAS SUBDIVISIONS&#13;
(all prices in 1976 Col $)&#13;
Pirate Inside        Normasl/     Pirate Outside&#13;
Average:                         Urban  Perimeter     Minimas-    Urban Perimeter&#13;
2/          2                        5                 41&#13;
Tract Price per m                         50               64              18&#13;
2&#13;
Tract size (m )                       35,528           98,700         84,758&#13;
Number of lots                           156              585             150&#13;
Lot size                                 125               92             315&#13;
Lot price per m 2                        253              456            109&#13;
3/&#13;
Total lot price-                      31,625           41,952         23,008&#13;
Subdivider expendituEe.on&#13;
infrastructure per m salable (usable)     22               64              9&#13;
area&#13;
Subdivider expenditure on&#13;
infrastructure per lot                 3,256            5,955          3,695&#13;
Percent subdivision in open space         10               22             10&#13;
Open space per lot (m2)                   26               39             38&#13;
Total number of subdivisions             109               14             24&#13;
Total number oflots subdivided        16,994            8,191          3,604&#13;
Total number oflots with sale data    11,540            5,916          2,099&#13;
1/  All normas minimas subdivisions are inside the urban perimeter.&#13;
2/ The term "tract" refers to the whole parcel of lanrd that is purchased&#13;
for subdivision.&#13;
3/ Total lot price here is the sum of undiscounted installments plus&#13;
the down payment, as per standard practice in the pirate subdivision&#13;
business.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
seems appropriate in the analysis, subdivisions inside and outside&#13;
the perimeter are treated separately. Because all normaA minimas&#13;
subdivisions are (by law, and hence by definition) inside the urban&#13;
perimeter, it is more accurate to compare them only with pirate&#13;
subdivisions located inside.&#13;
The first two columns of Table 1 show that normas minimas&#13;
developers pay an average of about 28 percent more per square meter&#13;
initially for their tracts of land than pirate subdividers. This&#13;
reflects the fact that the normas minimas subdivisions are better&#13;
located, on flat land in the near western zone of the city. It is&#13;
also due to the legal requirement that normas minimas subdivisions&#13;
be built on land zoned for residential use and accessible to public&#13;
utility connections.    Normas minimas developers spend a greater&#13;
proportion of their total costs on infrastructure than do pirates.&#13;
They also spend almost twice as much on infrastructure per lot in&#13;
absolute terms, and their subdivisions are better-serviced (see&#13;
Table 9). Thus, the average normas minimas buyer pays about one-&#13;
third more than he would in the pirate market for a lot that is&#13;
about 25 percent smaller; he receives however, more services, a&#13;
better-than-average location, more open space, and a greater&#13;
probability of acquiring legal tenure.l/&#13;
1/ The lot prices and sizes calculated from this data set are&#13;
consistent with earlier observations by Borrero and Sanchez (1973),&#13;
Losada and Gomez (1976), Doebele (1975), and DAPD (1978).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
According to this data sample, the average pirate lot buyer&#13;
makes a down-payment of about 30 percent of the lot price and then pays&#13;
36 monthly installments. The average down-payment for a pirate lot is&#13;
about Col$9500 and the average monthly installment is Col$615 (1976 prices).&#13;
An average normas minimas lot buyer faces a down-payment of&#13;
about 35 percent and a term of 39 months. The normas minimas down-&#13;
payment averages Col$14,700 and the installment Col$700. Term length&#13;
among all subdivisions varies from as few as 12 or 20 months to as many&#13;
as 50 or 60. While interest rates are rarely explicit in lot purchase&#13;
terms, buyers within the same subdivision may pay from two to 30&#13;
percent more per square meter if they buy on installment than if they&#13;
pay in one lump sum. On average this "implicit" finance charge is&#13;
approximately 1.0 percent per month or 13 percent per year on the total&#13;
1/&#13;
lot price. -&#13;
E. Affordability of Lots&#13;
According to the 1977 Bogota Household Survey (DANE EH15),&#13;
median monthly household income in that year was slightly less than&#13;
Col$5,000, and 26 percent of households had monthly incomes under&#13;
Col$2,500 (1977 prices, see Table 2).&#13;
This means that for a family at the median income level, the&#13;
down-payment for an average lot would cost between two and three monthly&#13;
incomes. For a family at the first quartile, earning around Col$2,500&#13;
1/ This figure is well below the prevailing interest rates in Bogota's&#13;
financial markets (see Chapter III, p. 51), but it is the best&#13;
estimate available from the data. See Chapter V, page 80 for an&#13;
explanation of how the implicit finance charge was calculated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
Table 2&#13;
BOGOTA HOUSEHOLD INCOME DISTRIEJTION. 1977&#13;
Categories of Monthly                                     Cumulative&#13;
Income (pesos)                   Percentage               Percentage&#13;
0 - 499                       6.2                       6.2&#13;
500 - 1499                      7.7                     13.9&#13;
1500 - 2499                     11.9                     25.8&#13;
2500 - 4999                     27.5                     53.3&#13;
5000 - 7499                     15.6                     68.9&#13;
7500-- 9999                      9.9                     78.8&#13;
10,000 - 14,999                    4.4                     83.2&#13;
15,000 - 24,999                    7.5                     90.7&#13;
25,000 +                           9.3                    100.0&#13;
Total Number of Households (expanded) = 685,424&#13;
Source: DANE 1977 Bogota Household Survey, EH15. Figures compiled by&#13;
N. Hartline and R. Mohan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
per month, the down-payment would equal four to six months' income.&#13;
Becoming a homeowner in this market thus means having access to a&#13;
large lump sum, which suggests that families without savings may be&#13;
largely excluded.&#13;
The affordability of shelter based on a pirate or normas&#13;
minimas lot also depends on the cost of building a structure. Since&#13;
not even the highest-quality lots come with core dwelling units, lot&#13;
buyers must spend substantial additional sums to provide themselves&#13;
with minimal shelter. The cost of a basic dwelling ranges from one&#13;
to four times the cost of a lot, depending on quality.-/ A good&#13;
estimate of the affordability range for housing on pirate and normas&#13;
minimas lots is provided by the distribution of monthly installment&#13;
payments made by lot buyers in the Superintendencia Bancaria sample&#13;
(Table 3). The median monthly installment is roughly Col$625 for&#13;
all subdivisions, slightly less than Col$600 for pirate, and around&#13;
Col$660 for normas minimas. About one quarter of the pirate lots&#13;
require monthly payments of less than Col$400, while only about two&#13;
percent of normas minimas lots can be had at that price. The&#13;
distribution overall is compact, with 60 percent of the installment&#13;
values falling in the Col$400 to 800 range.&#13;
Assuming the conventional though somewhat arbitrary standard&#13;
that 25 percent of income is a reasonable amount to spend on housing,&#13;
1/ See, for example, W. Paul Strassman, Basic Shelter in an Urban&#13;
Framework: The Experience of Carpagena, Colombia. World Bank,&#13;
URBOR Report, Nov. 1978, p. 118.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
Table 3&#13;
DISTRIBUTION OF MONTHLY INSTALLMENT PAYMENTS FOR LOTS&#13;
1976 Col$&#13;
Percentages&#13;
Installment              All                                   Normas&#13;
Value (pesos)            Subdivisions         Pirate           Minimas&#13;
1-199                     2.3                3.1              0.7&#13;
200-399                    15.2               21.6              1.5&#13;
400-599                    28.5               27.4             31.7&#13;
600-799                    31.2               24.7             44.9&#13;
800-999                    11.4               11.9             10.3&#13;
1000-1999                    8.7                8.9              8.1&#13;
2000+                       2.7                2.2              3.8&#13;
Lots counted               16,543             11,247           5,296&#13;
Zero installment&#13;
(paid cash)             2,741             2,131              610&#13;
No information                271                261              10&#13;
Total lots                 19,555            13,639            5,916&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
families at the median income level can afford the monthly payments for&#13;
almost all the lots on the market. If the cost of a dwelling unit&#13;
is taken into account, however, pirate or normas minimas solutions&#13;
are much less affordable. If the absolute minimum structure-to-land cost&#13;
ratio is 1:1, the total median housing expenditure would be about&#13;
1/&#13;
Col$1,250 per month.  This is within range of families at or above&#13;
the median income level in Bogota. Conversely, a family earning&#13;
the median income could afford only about half the lots on the&#13;
market -- including about a third of the normas minimas lots --&#13;
if it uses half its monthly housing expenditure for a structure.&#13;
Assuming the same 1:1 structure-to-land split, a family at the first&#13;
quartile in the income distribution, earning Col$2,500 per month,&#13;
could afford only the cheapest 20 percent of pirate lots offered&#13;
and would be barred entirely from purchasing a normas minimas lot.&#13;
Families in the lowest 20 percent of the income distribution would&#13;
effectively be shut out of the ownership market. If the assumption&#13;
of a 1:1 structure-to-land cost ratio is raised to a more realistic&#13;
level of, say, 3:1,the affordability picture worstens considerably.&#13;
Under th&amp;se circumstances ownership is difficult for any family below&#13;
the median income level, unless an unusually large share of income --&#13;
30-35 percent or higher -- is devoted to housing.&#13;
1/ This calculation assumes that families would make monthly payments&#13;
for structures. This is not necessarily realistic, because house&#13;
construction expenditures are often erratic due to income fluctuations.&#13;
It does give a valid indication, however, of the long-term financial&#13;
burden of building a structure.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
In general, home ownership through purchase of a pirate&#13;
or normas minimas lot seems accessible to families around the median&#13;
income level, but not to those in the lowest third of the income&#13;
distribution. This conclusion is supported by a 1978 survey of 212&#13;
households in illegal barrios on the periphery of Bogota, which found&#13;
that the median income of homeowning families matched the median&#13;
income for the city as a whole.-/&#13;
F. Services and Profits&#13;
Although the figures in Table 1 suggest that lot buyers&#13;
are willing to pay more for services even if it means getting a&#13;
smaller lot, two caveats are in order. First, in many of the sub-&#13;
divisions studied, the lot buyers or the government - not the sub-&#13;
divider - paid directly for a large proportion of the services. This&#13;
indicates that, in practice, lot buyers may not expect or be willing&#13;
to pay for more than a bare minimum of services at the outset.&#13;
Second, in most of the 149 subdivisions studied, infrastructure&#13;
installation, whether by the subdivider or others, occurred after&#13;
the sale of lots had begun. This casts some doubt on the extent to&#13;
which the marginal costs of infrastructure may be fully reflected&#13;
in the observed variations in lot prices. It depends on whether lot&#13;
buyers are willing to pay only for infrastructure "on the ground"&#13;
at the time of sale, or additionally, for services "promised" in the&#13;
future.&#13;
1/ Andrew M. Hamer, Lower Income Homeowner Households in a Developing&#13;
Metropolis, World Bank, City Study Paper, Oct. 1979.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
The descriptive figures in Table 1 also suggest that on&#13;
average, subdividers make good profits, and that the normas minimas&#13;
subdividers make higher profits than their pirate counterparts. While&#13;
the normas minimas pay more for raw land and infrastructure, they&#13;
also create much larger subdivisions, supply smaller lots, and sell&#13;
them at higher prices.&#13;
This study tests the hypothesis that pirate subdividers&#13;
make "exorbitant" profits. Doebele (1975) and others have suggested&#13;
that if pirate subdividers do earn huge profits (sometimes put at&#13;
hundreds of percent per year), public policy could be designed eo&#13;
encourage legitimate private developers to supply lots with higher&#13;
service levels while still allowing them to obtain good returns.&#13;
This was, in fact, an argument in favor of the normas minimas laws.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
II. GENERAL CHARACTERISTICS OF SUBDIVISIONS&#13;
This chapter is a descriptive overview of subdivisions and lots&#13;
sold, with particular attention to differences between pirate and normas&#13;
minimas subdivisions.&#13;
A. Basic Features&#13;
Size and Density: The 149 subdivisions in the sample range widely&#13;
in area, the smallest being around 0.1 hectare and the largest 43.5 hectares.&#13;
2&#13;
The average gross subdivision size overall is 49,475 m , or about 5 hectares&#13;
or 12.2 acres. The subdivisions in the sample contain as few as five and as&#13;
many as 2,000 lots (Table 4); the overall average is 196 lots per sub-&#13;
division. Most of the subdivisions are not large, however; half have less&#13;
than 100 lots and over one-third have fewer than 50. On the average, pirate&#13;
subdivisions outside the urban perimeter have the same number of lots as&#13;
those inside, but their average lot size is about 2.5 times larger (125m2&#13;
vs. 315 m2).&#13;
The average lot size of 125 m in pirate subdivisions inside the&#13;
urban perimeter implies a density of about 56 lots per hectare, taking into&#13;
account average street and open space area. Normas minimas density works&#13;
out to an average of about 62 lots per hectare. Some subdivisions in the&#13;
sample have densities as high as 100 lots per hectare. Assuming six persons&#13;
per lot, gross residential densities are in the range of 300 to 600 persons&#13;
per hectare.&#13;
When Developed: Four-fifths of the subdivisions in the sample&#13;
were initiated after 1967, and half of these sprang up during the last five&#13;
years (see Table 5). There appears to be little relationship between size&#13;
and age among the pirate subdivisions studied.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
Table 4: DISTRIBUTION OF SUBDIVISIONS BY NUMBER OF LOTS&#13;
Size Category           Number of           Percent of          Cumulative&#13;
(Number of Lots)        Subdivisions         Subdivisions           Percent&#13;
1-24                  23                   15.4                15.4&#13;
25-49                  33                   22.2                37.6&#13;
50-99                  20                   13.4                51.0&#13;
100-199                 26                   17.4                68.4&#13;
200-299                 19                   12.8                81.2&#13;
300-399                  8                    5.4                86.6&#13;
400-499                  5                    3.4                90.0&#13;
500-749                  7                    4.7                94.7&#13;
750-999                  5                    3.4                98.1&#13;
1000 +                   3                    2.0               100.0&#13;
TOTAL                  149                  100.00&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
Table 5: NUMBER OF SUBDIVISIONS BY INITIATION YEAR&#13;
Age Category of Subdivision          Number of                 Percent&#13;
Based on Initiation Year           Subdivisions           of Subdivisions&#13;
Old (pre 1967)                           28                     18.8&#13;
Middle-aged (1967-72)                    60                     40.3&#13;
Young (1973-77)                          61                      40.9&#13;
TOTAL                                  149                     100.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
Amount of Land Developed in Bogota: The 125 subdivisions that&#13;
are within the urban perimeter represent a total of 534 hectares or about&#13;
1,318 acres of residential land, in gross terms. Using Borrero and Sanchez's&#13;
estimate of Bogota's total residential area of 14,162 hectares (1973), the&#13;
sample subdivisions comprise approximately 3.8 percent. Assuming, for rough&#13;
estimation, that pirate land is one-third of total residential area in&#13;
Bogota, the sample represents about 12 percent of pirate land area in the&#13;
city.&#13;
Location: Twenty-four of the pirate subdivisions studied (16%)are&#13;
located outside the 1973 urban perimeter of Bogota. Most of these are within&#13;
the Special District of Bogota, but a few are located in towns some distance&#13;
away in the adjacent Department of Cundinamarca. Eight subdivisions are in&#13;
Soacha, about four kilometers beyond the city limits to the southwest.&#13;
Several subdivisions are in the far north-northwest, two of these in Funza,&#13;
six kilometers from the perimeter; one in Mosquera, seven kilometers away;&#13;
one in Madrid, ten kilometers away; and one in Bojaca, even further distant.&#13;
Ten subdivisions in the sample are beyond the urban perimeter to the south,&#13;
seven of these along the highway to Villavicencio.&#13;
As Figure 1 shows, pirate subdivisions cluster in the far southern&#13;
and western areas of Bogota, with a significant but much smaller number&#13;
located in the north-northwestern zone. The newest subdivisions are in the&#13;
west, the older ones in the south. Figure 2, which depicts the relationship&#13;
between location and tract size, indicates that subdivisions outside the&#13;
urban perimeter are substantially larger overall. The large average size of&#13;
subdivisions in the near west is due to the clustering there of eight normas&#13;
minimas developments which average 12.6 hectares in size, twice the average&#13;
for the zone as a whole.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
Figure 1&#13;
LOCATION OF PIRATE AND NORMAS&#13;
MINIDAS DEVELOPMENTS IN SAMPLE&#13;
0~~~~&#13;
Madrid7  Funza&#13;
BojacaN    o*                                                I-_&#13;
amosquera*&#13;
* Pre sb    o vionY&#13;
ran oiter rubi- &#13;
00~~2@°e&gt; IYO OO&#13;
ONrasMndma outerding    00 Qub   8 &#13;
O   1  2   3  4                       ¢to &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
Figure 2&#13;
AVERAGE TRACT SIZES ACROSS RINGS AND SECTORS OF BOGOTA&#13;
1200&#13;
SOUTH&#13;
1000&#13;
NORTH/NCRTHWEST&#13;
800.&#13;
Average    600\&#13;
Tract&#13;
Size&#13;
(lOOs of&#13;
m2)     400/                                                              WEST&#13;
(without normas minimas)&#13;
200L&#13;
First                    Second                    Outside&#13;
Ring                      Ring                     Perimeter&#13;
5-10 km                 11-20 km                   over 20 km&#13;
(Kilometers from center)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-24-&#13;
There is no hard evidence on why normas minimas subdividers create&#13;
much larger subdivisions than pirates. One possible explanation is that&#13;
normas minimas subdividers are likely to have better access to financing,&#13;
enabling them to obtain more capital and to invest in larger tracts of land.&#13;
Another possibility is that normas minimas subdividers are more efficient;&#13;
that is, they may be more apt to take advantage of potential economies of&#13;
scale in the subdivision business.&#13;
Lots Sold: The Superintendencia Bancaria's questionnaire asked&#13;
subdividers to submit data on all lots sold in each subdivision. The data&#13;
set includes figures on 19,555 lots in 147 of the 149 subdivisions, or about&#13;
68 percent of the total number of lots subdivided in the sample. The re-&#13;
mainder are lots unsold and a small residual of lot sales not reported. Of&#13;
those lots sold, 13,639 are in pirate subdivisions and 5,916 in normas&#13;
minimas developments. It has not been possible to estimate what fraction&#13;
this represents of the universe of pirate lots sold in Bogota in recent&#13;
years. Listed in Table 6 are the number of sample lots sold by year: 87&#13;
percent were sold since 1970; three-quarters in the last five years;&#13;
one-third in 1976-77.&#13;
Land Uses in Subdivisions: Across all subdivisions an average&#13;
of 70 percent of the area is devoted to salable lots, 11 percent to communal&#13;
area and green zones, and 19 percent to streets (see Table 7). Because of&#13;
the legal standards they must meet, normas minimas subdivisions provide about&#13;
twice as high a proportion of communal and green space, at the expense of&#13;
about 20 percent less salable area, than pirate subdivisions. The proportion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
Table 6: TOTAL LOTS SOLD BY YEAR IN SAMPLE&#13;
Years of Sale         Number of         Percent of         Cumulative&#13;
of Lots               Lots             Total              Percent&#13;
Pre-1960                 109               0.6                 0.6&#13;
1960-64                   56               0.3                 0.9&#13;
1965-69                 2398              12.3                13.2&#13;
70                  436               2.2               15.4&#13;
71                  654               3.3                18.7&#13;
72                 1135               5.8               24.5&#13;
73                 1610               8.2               32.7&#13;
74                 3156              16.2               48.9&#13;
75                 3594              18.4               67.3&#13;
76                 3526              18.1               85.4&#13;
77                 2827              14.5              100.0&#13;
Sub-total              19506             100.0&#13;
No Date                   49&#13;
TOTAL                  19555&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
Table 7&#13;
AVERAGE LAND USES WITHIN SUBDIVISIONS&#13;
(Percent of tract)&#13;
Average Percent of                  All          Pirate Inside     Pirate Outside     Normas&#13;
Tract Devoted to:               Subdivisions       Perimeter          Perimeter       Minimas&#13;
Usable (salable) Area               70                71                 74             56&#13;
Conmunal and Green Area             11                10                 10             22&#13;
Street Area                         19                19                 16             22&#13;
Average Communal + Green&#13;
Area per Lot (m2)                29                26                 38             39&#13;
Average Street Area&#13;
per Lot (m2)                     47                43                 70             37&#13;
Number of Subdivisions             147               109                 24             14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
of usable area in most of the normas minimas developments is between&#13;
50 and 60 percent. Among pirate subdivisions, however, the fraction&#13;
varies from over 80 percent to 100 percent of the tract surface.&#13;
Regarding the fraction of land devoted to streets, the average is&#13;
19 percent in pirate subdivisions and 22 percent in normas minimas.&#13;
The figures on space per lot in Table 7 also show that&#13;
normas minimas subdividers offer greater amounts of open and&#13;
communal area. The somewhat lower average street area per lot in&#13;
normas minimas subdivisions reflects their smaller average lot size.&#13;
B. Purchase of Tracts&#13;
In 76 of the 149 subdivisions, works were initiated less&#13;
than 12 months after the tract was acquired. Twenty-nine other sub-&#13;
divisions-- six of which were normas minimas -- were actually begun&#13;
before the official acquisition of the tract, although for half&#13;
of these these the period was less than one year. This is a&#13;
reflection of the loose, clandestine nature of the business.-/ In&#13;
contrast, 40 subdivisions were not initiated for two or more years&#13;
following acquisition, and in 28 of these cases -- one-fifth of the&#13;
sample -- the subdivider waited six years or more before proceeding.&#13;
These patterns suggest that while most pirate subdividers behave&#13;
like businessmen with discount rates -- they want to obtain returns&#13;
as soon as possible -- a substantial number seem to be either&#13;
1/ According to the Superintendencia Bancaria, most normas minimas&#13;
developers are former pirate subdividers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
inexperienced or in no hurry to develop their parcels of land. Comments&#13;
on the questionnaires indicate that many subdividers had owned the&#13;
tracts for long periods and a few had even inherited the land, suggesting&#13;
that some fraction of pirate subdividers are one-time entrepreneurs.&#13;
The tendency for some pirate subdividers to wait, perhaps&#13;
for a-rise in land prices, is also reflected in the relationship between&#13;
the dates of official tract acquisition and the beginning of lot sales.&#13;
In 64 of the 149 cases, this period is less than one year; in 12 more,&#13;
it is between one and two years. In 43 subdivisions more than two&#13;
years passed before any lots were sold, and in 30 of these the delay&#13;
was over six years. At the same time, there are 28 subdivisions,&#13;
including six normas minimas in which lots were sold before the&#13;
tract was officially acquired, in most cases less than one year before.&#13;
This is another indication that the business often involves unorthodox&#13;
transactions, including the use of receipts from lot sales to meet&#13;
payments for the tract.&#13;
A majority of subdividers in the sample paid for their&#13;
tracts in a lump sum. In 39 cases, 42 percent of those with information&#13;
available, the subdivider made a down-payment and paid installments on&#13;
the tract. The down-payments averaged about 35 percent of the total&#13;
tract price. In only 23 cases was an interest charge - ranging from&#13;
0.3 percent to 7.0 percent annually - reported to be part of the tract&#13;
acquisition contract.&#13;
Figure 3 presents average prices of subdivision tracts in&#13;
Bogota for the northwest, west, and south.-/ Within the urban&#13;
1/ These land price measurements are consistent with those of McCallum&#13;
(1974) and Villamizar (1979).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
Figure 3&#13;
AVERAGE TRACT PRICES PER M2 ACROSS RINGS AND SECTORS OF BOGOTA&#13;
144&#13;
128&#13;
112 &#13;
96 *&#13;
80 -&#13;
Average Tract&#13;
Prices per m2&#13;
(constant&#13;
1976 Col$)   64&#13;
48&#13;
32                                                           WEST&#13;
NORTH/NORTHWE!&#13;
16&#13;
SOUTH&#13;
First                    Second                  Outside&#13;
Ring                     Ring                  Perimeter&#13;
5-10 km                 11-20 km               Over 20 km&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
perimeter the average price per square meter of tracts is&#13;
consistently highest in the north, Bogota's higher income&#13;
area.     land prices are about twice as high in the west&#13;
as in the south.       In all sectors land prices decline with distance&#13;
from the center of the city, although in the southern zone the gradient&#13;
is small.&#13;
As Figure 4 illustrates, peripheral tract prices per&#13;
square meter in Bogota have been rising in real terms, particularly&#13;
between 1974 and 1977. While price increases have been relatively&#13;
gradual in the west and south, the northern periphery has recently&#13;
experienced spectacular land price growth. The combination of&#13;
lower relative prices and lower real price growth helps explain&#13;
why pirate subdivisions are concentrated in the west and south.&#13;
C. Infrastructure and Development Costs&#13;
Because the questionnaire failed to ask about planned&#13;
infrastructure investments, the data on expenditures and quantities&#13;
of services may be, on an absolute per-subdivision basis, lower than&#13;
eventual levels. Nonetheless, this does not interfere with either&#13;
comparisons of relative magnitudes or the hedonic lot price analysis&#13;
later on. Of the 149 subdivisions studied, 20 reportedly had no&#13;
infrastructure--water, sewer, electricity, telephone, streets, side-&#13;
walks, and curbs-- installed at all; the rest had at least one type&#13;
installed. As Table 8 indicates, the most frequent infrastructure&#13;
types present are streets (three-quarters of the subdivisions),&#13;
water (two-thirds), and electricity (almost two-thirds). All but&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
Figure 4: AVERAGE TRACT PRICES PER M2 OVER TIME&#13;
(Constant 1976 Col$)&#13;
220-&#13;
North-northwest&#13;
180-&#13;
140&#13;
Average&#13;
Tract Prices&#13;
Per M2&#13;
100                                                                      West&#13;
South&#13;
60 -&#13;
20&#13;
I              i              II&#13;
Pre-         1970-71         1972-73       1974-75         1976-77&#13;
1970&#13;
Time Periods&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
Table 8: EXTENT OF INFRASTRUCTURE INSTALLATION IN SUBDIVISIONS&#13;
Percent of Subdivisions Having Services&#13;
at Time of Survey&#13;
All Subdivisions      Pirate     Normas Minimas&#13;
Sewer                              46.9             46.7           50.0&#13;
Water                              68.5             65.2           100.0&#13;
Electricity                        63.8             61.5            85.7&#13;
Telephone                          20.8             17.0            57.1&#13;
Streets                            73.2             70.3          100.0&#13;
Sidewalks                          16.1             16.3           14.3&#13;
Curbs                              27.5             23.7           64.3&#13;
No Services Whatsoever             20               20               0&#13;
%                             13.4             14.8            0.0&#13;
Total Number of Subdivisions      149              135             14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
two of the normas minimas subdivisions have water, electricity, and&#13;
streets, while half of them have sewer service.&#13;
While in the normas minimas subdivisions all the infra-&#13;
structure was paid for by the subdividers, in the pirate subdivisions&#13;
some infrastructure was financed by other sources.     Indeed, the&#13;
data in Table 9 demonstrate that lot buyers themselves often endup&#13;
paying for the installation of services.&#13;
Infrastructure investments usually occur well after&#13;
acquisition of the tract and initiation of the subdivision. In&#13;
over three-fourths of the cases a delay of one year or more occurred&#13;
between the sale of lots and the installation of any infrastructure.&#13;
Of 93 subdivisions for which the installation date of at least one&#13;
type of infrastructure is given, only 18 had a service or services&#13;
installed prior to the sale of the first lot. In 39 cases, infra-&#13;
structure was not installed until two or more years after the sale&#13;
of the first lot, and in 17 the delay was more than five years.&#13;
In 41 of the subdivisions -- 44 percent of those reporting -- infra-&#13;
structure provision. was delayed until after 50 percent,of the lots&#13;
had been sold; in 28 of these - five of which are normas minimas -&#13;
the infrastructure was not installed until after 90 percent of lots&#13;
had been sold. Streets and water standpipes tend to be installed&#13;
earlier relative to lot sales than water and sewer lines.&#13;
The lag in infrastructure provision suggests that: (1)&#13;
subdividers generally cannot afford to make infrastructure expenditures&#13;
"up front"; hence they wait until after returns from lot sales come&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
Table 9: SOURCES OF FINANCING FOR INFRASTRUCTURE&#13;
IN PIRATE SUBDIVISIONS&#13;
Percentage of pirate subdivisions in which service was paid by:&#13;
Both sub-                N- Number of&#13;
Sub-                   divider and               Subdivisions&#13;
divider   Community      community   Government   with service&#13;
Sewer               43.5        32.2           16.1        8.1        62&#13;
Water               62.8        23.2            5.8        8.1        86&#13;
Electricity         48.8        31.7            6.1       13.4        82&#13;
Telephone            4.8        61.9            4.8       28.6        21&#13;
Streets             81.4        12.8            2.3        3.5        86&#13;
Sidewalks           21.0        47.4            5.3       26.3        19&#13;
Curbs               53.3        30.0            3.3       13.3        30&#13;
Note: In all 14 normas minimas subdivisions 100 percent of all services were&#13;
financed by the subdividers. The normas minimas subdivisions are&#13;
excluded from this table.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
in; (2) some subdividers are unwilling to install infrastructure at&#13;
all and do so only after lot buyers and/or the municipal authorities&#13;
force them to at a later time; (3) Lot buyers who are unable to&#13;
convince or coerce the subdivider into installing infrastructure&#13;
at his own expense often choose to compromise by sharing costs&#13;
with him,paying for the services themselves, or obtaining services&#13;
financed directly by the public sector.&#13;
Pirate subdividers most frequently finance sewer,&#13;
standpipes, electric lines, streets, and curbs. Lot buyers pay&#13;
more often than pirate subdividers for telephone lines and side-&#13;
walks, although about one-third of the time they pay for sewer and&#13;
electric lines. The public sector plays a minor role and does not&#13;
seem to finance certain infrastructure types more often than others.&#13;
Average quantities of each infrastructure type installed,&#13;
presented in Table 10, represent only completed - not planned -&#13;
investments. While the amounts of infrastructure vary widely across&#13;
subdivisions, normas minimas subdividers clearly provide more than&#13;
do pirates.&#13;
The average prices of different infrastructure types per&#13;
unit, shown in Table 11, were obtained by dividing expenditures by&#13;
quantities of works completed. The prices vary greatly across sub-&#13;
divisions and should be interpreted cautiously. On the average&#13;
one would expect normas minimas subdividers to pay higher prices,&#13;
assuming that they supply higher quality infrastructure. At the&#13;
same time, pirate subdividers may pay higher prices for some types&#13;
of infrastructure because they purchase inefficiently. According to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 10: AVERAGE QUANTITIES OF INFRASTRUCTURE INSTALLED PER HECTARE USABLE AREA&#13;
All Sub-                        Normas         Maximum    Minimum*&#13;
Infrastructure Type         Units           divisions         Pirate         Minimas        Amount     Amount&#13;
Sewer                   Lineal Meters       186(128)          168(115)       340(13)         1166         89&#13;
Electricity             Lineal Meters       292(104)          279(98)        496(6)          2255         38&#13;
Telephone               Lineal Meters        11(127)            6(118)        57(9)           510         15&#13;
Streets                 M2                 2041(121)             (115)      3045(6)          6100        330&#13;
Sidewalks              M12                     (36)            4(122)        87(14)          1060        180&#13;
Curbs                   Lineal Meters        97(132)           9 (123)       178(9)          1337         66&#13;
Note:  Figures in parentheses are the number of cases.    Specific quantities  of infrastructure were not&#13;
reported for some subdivisions even though the services were present.&#13;
* Figures based only on cases where quantity is greater than zero.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 11:   AVERAGE COSTS OF INFRASTRUCTURE INSTALLATION PER UNIT&#13;
(Constant 1976 Col$)&#13;
Verification&#13;
Infrastructure      Unit of           All                    Normas             (Including Labor and Materials)&#13;
Type          Measurement     Subdivisions    Pirate     Minimas         Item                  Price     Source*&#13;
Sewer             Lineal meter          407         399        456           8" Pipe                262        (2)&#13;
Drainage Conduit      2969        (2)&#13;
Manhole               8568        (2)&#13;
Water Pipes       Lineal meter          398          422       253           8" Pipe                237        (1)&#13;
10" Pipe               291       (1)&#13;
Manhole               4610       (1)&#13;
Pilas             Unit               21,560      23,688     13,993                     (not available)&#13;
Electricity       Lineal meter          342          359       203                     (not available)&#13;
Streets           m                      83          72        165           Macadam with base      106        (1)&#13;
Macadam with base     65-86       (2)&#13;
Asphalt                166       (2)&#13;
Crushed stone,sand,&#13;
gravel 15 cm.         52       (2)&#13;
* Sources for price verification:&#13;
(1)  Contracts between subdivider and contractors for infrastructure installation, 1977, supplied by&#13;
Superintendencia Bancaria.&#13;
(2)  Estudio de Precios Unitarios, Ministry of Public Works, 1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
the data, normas minimas developers do in fact pay more than pirates&#13;
for sewer and street construction, but pay less - by about two-thirds&#13;
to three quarters - for water pipes, standpipes, and electric lines.&#13;
Since inefficient purchasing probably does not account for this large&#13;
a difference, the high figures for pirate subdividers may reflect&#13;
some instances of erroneous reporting on the questionhaires. Never-&#13;
theless, the price figures in Table 11 are reasonable in overall&#13;
magnitude.-/&#13;
Total expenditures by subdividers, lot buyers and govern-&#13;
ment on infrastructure per square meter of usable area, shown in&#13;
Table 12, average around Col$38 at 1976 prices for all subdivisions.&#13;
Infrastructure investments in normas minimas developments are&#13;
considerably higher than in pirate subdivisions (Col$57 vs. Col$36).&#13;
Expenditures reported in this sample seem reasonable in comparison&#13;
with other sources; for example, the amount spent in pirate sub-&#13;
divisions in Bogota is about one-quarter to one-third the amount&#13;
budgeted by the World Bank for infrastructure in low-income urban&#13;
upgrading projects in El Salvador.&#13;
Table 13 shows average subdivider expenditures for&#13;
professional services, publicity, and administration, calculated on&#13;
a per-lot basis. As explained in Chapter I, some of these figures&#13;
1/ Documentation on prices for construction of sewer and water&#13;
lines and streets was made available by the Superintendencia Bancaria.&#13;
These verification figures, which also appear in Table 11, are close&#13;
to the averages given by the data. However, because details on the&#13;
types of infrastructure installed are missing, it is difficult to&#13;
say what level of quality lot buyers are receiving at these prices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
Table 12:   AVERAGE EXPENDITURE ON ALL INFRASTRUCTURE PER M   USABLE AREA&#13;
(Constant 1976 Col$)&#13;
Col$ Per m          Number of&#13;
Usable Area          Subdivisions&#13;
All Subdivisions                             38.5                116&#13;
Pirate                                       36.0                102&#13;
Normas Minimas                               56.9                 14&#13;
Average for 4 squatter&#13;
upgrading projects in&#13;
El Salvador  I/                            92.6&#13;
Average for World Bank&#13;
El Salvador Second Urban&#13;
Development  Project  2/                  130.2&#13;
"Urbanization Primer" Mi-&#13;
nimum Level, Layout No. 2  3/              91.0&#13;
1/ EDURES, A Program for the Integrated Development of Critical&#13;
Metropolitan Areas in El Salvador, Document No. 25, Vol. 1, May 1978.&#13;
2/ World Bank, El Salvador Second Urban Development Project, unpublished&#13;
data.&#13;
3/ Horacio Caminos and Reinhard Goethert, Urbanization Primer, World&#13;
Bank Urban Projects Department, October 1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
Table 13:  AVERAGE PROFESSIONAL SERVICES, PUBLICITY,AND ADMINISTRATIVE&#13;
EXPENDITURES PER LOT&#13;
(Constant 1976 Col$)&#13;
Expenditures per Lot&#13;
Categories of over-        Pirate Subdivisions     Normas      Pirate Subdivisions&#13;
head expenditures          Inside Perimeter        Minimas     Outside Perimeter&#13;
Professional Services           2,150*               833              940&#13;
Publicity                         218                498             257&#13;
Administration                  3,819*             3,419*           1,866&#13;
Number of Subdivisions          (148)               (134)            (14)&#13;
*Absolute value probably exaggerated as reported.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
are overstated. For pirate subdivisions the means for professional&#13;
services and administration costs are unduly high; for normas minimas&#13;
the administration cost mean is exaggerated. According to Superintendencia&#13;
Bancaria officials, many subdividers (including the normas minimas&#13;
developers, most of whom had not complied with all legal norms at&#13;
the time of the survey) attempted to overstate their costs to reduce&#13;
their apparent profit rates.&#13;
D. Sale of Lots&#13;
According to the sample data, it takes an average of 47&#13;
months to sell 90 percent of the lots in:a pirate subdivision. For&#13;
normas minimas the period is 17 months. This large difference may&#13;
reflect excess demand for normas minimas lots. It also may suggest&#13;
that normas minimas subdividers are more efficient salesmen.&#13;
It is widely believed that buyers of pirate lots are&#13;
unreliable in their payments. This is offered as one reason why&#13;
"legitimate" developers are reluctant to go into the lower-inoome&#13;
housing market.&#13;
The payment rates displayed in Table 14 indicate that&#13;
an average pirate subdivider working within the urban perimeter can&#13;
expect about 30 percent of his lot buyers to fall behind in their&#13;
payments. Of these, more than half will eventually lag six months&#13;
or more. A normas minimas subdivider can, on the average, expect&#13;
a slightly higher rate of late payments as well as a somewhat larger&#13;
proportion of serious delays. Pirate subdividers operating outside&#13;
the urban perimeter seem to have much graver problems; on the average&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
Table 14&#13;
AVERAGE RATES OF LATENESS IN PAYMENTS AMONG LOT BUYERS&#13;
Lot Buyers In&#13;
Pirate Subdivisions       Normas Minimas        Pirate Subdivisions&#13;
Inside Urban Perimeter       Subdivisions       Outside Urban Perimeter&#13;
Percent late                     30.5                    33.7                      50.9&#13;
Percent late more than&#13;
six months                       18.2                    22.1                      42.8&#13;
Late more than six months&#13;
as percent of all late           59.6                    65.4                      84.0&#13;
Total number of lot&#13;
buyers                       11,540                   5,916                     2,099&#13;
Total number of sub-&#13;
divisions                       109                      14                        24&#13;
Average number of&#13;
lot buyers per sub-&#13;
division                        106                     423                        87&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
half their buyers end up late in payments, and 84 percent of these&#13;
fall behind six months or more. Clearly the problem of lateness in&#13;
payments and long-term default is significant in the lower-income&#13;
lot business. On the one hand, these results do seem to reflect&#13;
the riskiness of the business from the subdivider's point of view.&#13;
On the other hand, given that many pirate subdividers do not&#13;
deliver what they promise, it is understandable that lot buyers&#13;
may have good reasons to stop their payments. In fact, the experience&#13;
of the Superintendencia Bancaria and comments on the questionnaires&#13;
indicate that lot buyers deliberately hold up payments in response&#13;
to a subdivider's failure to make improvements or install services.&#13;
Although it is not possible to determine how many cases like this&#13;
occur, an educated guess might be 25 percent of the late debtors.&#13;
The prices of both pirate and normas minimas lots have&#13;
been rising faster than consumer prices overall in Bogota, as&#13;
shown in Figure 5. The real rate of increase in pirate lot prices&#13;
has been especially high since 1973. The average inflation rate&#13;
for the 1973-77 period was about 24 percent, while the average&#13;
annual nominal growth rate in prices per square meter of pirate&#13;
lots was about 111 percent. At the same time, the average size&#13;
of pirate lots has gradually been decreasing. From 1972 to 1977&#13;
the average pirate lot had diminished in size from an average of&#13;
2                2&#13;
about 180 m  to about 105 m . This reflects increasing costs of&#13;
land development, as well as continuing high demand for pirate lots.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Figure 5&#13;
AVERAGE LOT PRICES PER M2 OVER TIME&#13;
600-&#13;
500                                                                    1Average lot prices (nominal)&#13;
I&#13;
400                                                                   I&#13;
Average                                                                            I Average lot prices (constant&#13;
lot price                                                                                                1976 Col$)&#13;
(Col$ per mn)&#13;
300/&#13;
20C. -&#13;
100I&#13;
52   54   56   58  60    62   64   66   68   70   72    74  76   78&#13;
Years&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
Average lot prices per square meter decline with distance&#13;
from the center of the city, as Figure 6 illustrates. Prices are&#13;
highest in the northwestern- zone within the perimeter, lower by&#13;
about one-fifth in the west, and lower by about one-third in the&#13;
south. Average lot sizes within the urban perimeter, shown in&#13;
Figure 7, vary little with distance from the center, and even&#13;
2&#13;
across sectors  the range is only between 100 and 140 m . The&#13;
greatest variations in average lot size occur outside the urban&#13;
perimeter.&#13;
E.  Total Costs of Development&#13;
The distribution of major costs in total expenditures&#13;
for pirate and normas minimas subdivisions, shown in Table 15,&#13;
indicate that both types of subdividers spend about the same proportion&#13;
of total outlays on land, but normas minimas subdividers devote a&#13;
greater percentage of resources to infrastructure. Pirate sub-&#13;
dividers report spending a much larger fraction on overhead.&#13;
Compared with 19 World Bank sites and services projects around the&#13;
globe, Bogota subdivisions are more land-intensive.&#13;
Average total expenditures per lot appear in Table 16.&#13;
While normas minimas subdividers pay about 28 percent more per&#13;
square meter of land than pirates, their land costs per lot are&#13;
actually lower on average because they develop smaller lots.&#13;
There is almost no difference between development costs per lot for&#13;
pirate subdivisions inside the perimeter and normas minimas sub-&#13;
divisions. Even if the likely exaggeration of overhead expenditures&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
Figure 6&#13;
AVERAGE LOT PRICES PER M2 ACROSS RINGS AND SECTORS OF BOGOTA&#13;
500 &#13;
400.&#13;
Average lot    300\&#13;
prices per&#13;
in2                                                                           WEST&#13;
(constant&#13;
1976 Col$)&#13;
200\&#13;
100 -&#13;
NORTH/NORTHWESI&#13;
SOUTH&#13;
First                     Second                  Outside&#13;
Ring                     Ring                   Perimeter&#13;
5-10 km                   10-20 km              20 km and over&#13;
(Kilometers from center)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
Figure 7&#13;
AVERAGE LOT SIZE ACROSS RINGS AND SECTORS OF BOGOTA&#13;
400-&#13;
SOUTH&#13;
300 -   NORTH/NORTHWESI&#13;
300&#13;
Average&#13;
lot&#13;
sizes&#13;
(m2)&#13;
200 -&#13;
WEST&#13;
100-&#13;
_                        I                        I&#13;
First                   Second                   Outside&#13;
Ring                     Ring                  Perimeter&#13;
5-10 km                 10-20 km               20 km and over&#13;
(Kilometers from center)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
Table 15&#13;
DISTRIBUTION OF MAJOR COST COMPONENTS&#13;
(Percentages)&#13;
Pirate             Normas         World Bank&#13;
Component                  Subdivisions       Minimas        ProJects&#13;
Land                            39              42              21&#13;
Infrastructure                  22              32              33&#13;
Professional Services           15               3              13 &#13;
Publicity                        2               2&#13;
Adcinistration                  lh              13&#13;
Unspecified/Miscellaneous        8               8&#13;
Plot Development)                                               33&#13;
100             100             100&#13;
Number of Subdivisions         133              lh              19&#13;
Source: Praful C. Patel, Sites and Services Projects: Survey and Analysis&#13;
of Urbanization Standards and On-Site Infrastructure. World Bank,&#13;
August 197h, Annex A, p. 11.&#13;
In the World Bank projects this is "site preparation; topo/survey work ."&#13;
Construction of sanitary cores or dwelling shells.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
Table 16&#13;
AVERAGE TOTAL DEVELOPMENT COSTS PER LOT&#13;
1976 Col$&#13;
Pirate Subdivisions    Normas      Pirate Subdivisions&#13;
Cost Per Lot Of:       Inside Perimeter      Minimas      Outside Perimeter&#13;
Land                      11,387              10,798            10,171&#13;
Infrastructure             3,256               5,955             3,695&#13;
Overhead'                   6,187              4,750             3,063&#13;
Total                     20,830              21,503            16,929&#13;
Number of Subdivisions        109                 1                 24&#13;
*Probably exaggerated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
is taken into account, by reducing pirate overhead by about half&#13;
and normas minimas overhead by about one third, the total development&#13;
costs per lot are still practically the same (roughly Col$17,700 for&#13;
pirate inside the perimeter vs. Col$18,300 for normas minimas).&#13;
These figures add to the evidence that normas minimas subdividers&#13;
make higher profits on average than pirates. Normas minimas sub-&#13;
dividers spend only marginally more per lot, but they sell at a&#13;
substantially higher markup and sell four times the number of lots&#13;
on the average per subdivision.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
III. RATES OF RETURN TO SUBDIVIDERS&#13;
A. Background&#13;
Using data from the Superintendencia Bancaria sample, this&#13;
chapter will examine the magnitude of rates of return to subdividers&#13;
and discuss the policy implications of the findings. Some observers&#13;
have suggested that, since pirate subdividers make large profits, the&#13;
public sector should attempt to capture the excess profits and divert&#13;
them to the provision of adequate levels of services (Doebele, 1975).&#13;
This could be accomplished either by forcing subdividers to install&#13;
infrastructure or by providing incentives to legitimate developers&#13;
to supply legal lots with services.&#13;
There is some difficulty here in defining what constitutes&#13;
an exorbitant rate of return. An annual profit rate of 30 percent&#13;
may seem large until one takes into account that inflaction in&#13;
Bogota averaged around 24 percent yearly between 1972 and 1977.&#13;
Moreover, a 30 percent nominal rate of return is only slightly better&#13;
than the yields offered by most of the major financial instruments&#13;
currently available in Colombia (see below). Finally, nominal&#13;
Effective Annual Rates of Return, June 1979&#13;
UPAC (indexed savings andloan) ordinary deposits      19.30&#13;
UPAC savings accounts                                 24.95&#13;
UPAC savings certificates six months                  26.14&#13;
one year                   27.33&#13;
Term deposit certificates three months                26.82&#13;
six months                 28.07&#13;
Savings accounts                                      19.00&#13;
Agro-industrial Titulos (bonds) three months          27.50&#13;
six months           28.00&#13;
Bonos Cafeteros (coffee bonds)                        22.00&#13;
Titulos de Ahorro Cafetero (coffee savings&#13;
bonds) @ 65% and 2-year term                      51.29&#13;
Certificates of exchange                              35.60&#13;
Source:  Estrategia Economica y Financiera, Bogota, June 1979,&#13;
No. 23, page 1U.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52-&#13;
profit rates in high-standard housing development ventures during the&#13;
1977-78 period were reported to be in the range of 50 to 100 percent&#13;
annually.-/&#13;
Losada and Gomez (1976) calculated net benefits for two of&#13;
the subdivisions they studied. In both cases, the subdivider's&#13;
expenditures consisted of the tract cost, office costs, commissionists'&#13;
fees, and expenses for grading of streets. Revenues came from the&#13;
sale of lots. The calculations yield net benefits of 229 percent and&#13;
227 percent over five years in constant prices, with the cash flow&#13;
discounted at 10 percent annually. -/ These figures are equivalent&#13;
to an average annual real net benefit of about 27 percent (compound),&#13;
a good but not unusually high profit margin. Doebele (1975) offers&#13;
rougher profit figures estimated from Superintendencia Bancaria records&#13;
for six pirate   subdivisions      of widely varying size and quality.&#13;
Doebele estimates "presumptive" profits, based on several assumptions,&#13;
as low as 35 and as high as 1,300 percent. 3/           Doebele&#13;
suggests that lot sales occur over two or three years, which is&#13;
consistent with the sales periods observed in this study. At three&#13;
years, the average annual net profit for the six subdivisions is 98.5&#13;
1/ Based on background information supplied by several middle and upper-&#13;
middle class development firms in Bogota, February 1979.&#13;
2/ Losada and Gomez, pp. 52-55.&#13;
3/ The assumptions are: 67 percent of the tract area is salable and&#13;
5 percent of the tract value covers overhead costs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
percent (compound). One difficulty with these figures is that they&#13;
are based on undiscounted cash flows. Discounting over the lot&#13;
sale period would lower the present value of benefits and net&#13;
benefit margins. In addition, it can be argued that Doebele's&#13;
estimates are maximum possibilities because the expenditures do not&#13;
include any infrastructure. Finally, the prices used in Doebele's&#13;
calculations are current, not constant values. Real net benefits&#13;
would be significantly lower. It is worth noting that Doebele's&#13;
figures do reflect the great variation in performance among sub-&#13;
dividers. Some make enormous profits, while others barely scrape by&#13;
or even lose money.&#13;
B. Rates of Return in the Sample&#13;
The Superintendencia Bancaria data provide the first&#13;
opportunity to measure the profitability of a large number of sub-&#13;
divisions using a consistent criterion. The measure employed here&#13;
is the internal rate of return (IRR). The IRR is the discount&#13;
(interest) rate at which the present value of a net cash flow equals&#13;
zero. -/ Two attributes make the IRR a better way to measure&#13;
profitability than discounted net benefits. One is that there is&#13;
no need to choose a discount rate. The other is that the IRR is&#13;
1/ See E.J. Mishan, Cost-Benefit Analysis. New York: Praeger, 1976;&#13;
pp. 183-195&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54 -&#13;
conceptually analogous to the periodic percent return an entre-&#13;
preneur may obtain from other investments such as bonds. The IRR&#13;
is essentially the compound interest rate at which the initial&#13;
investment grows over a given period. The IRR does have one sig-&#13;
nificant disadvantage. Given a cash flow with unusual characteristics,&#13;
particularly substantial outlays late in the period, the equation&#13;
for the IRR may yield more than one root. In this case it is common&#13;
practice to use the first root as the "correct" IRR. In the results&#13;
presented below, between 10 and 19 (depending on the assumptions&#13;
underlying the calculations) of the 147 subdivisions with lot sale&#13;
data presented multiple IRRs and were omitted from the analysis.-/&#13;
Table 17 summarizes average rates of return across all&#13;
subdivisions in the sample. The "medium" average IRRs are based&#13;
on the data "as is"; i.e., expenditures and revenues reported&#13;
by subdividers are unmodified and all lots are assumed to be paid&#13;
for on time. The "payment default" averages take into account a&#13;
percentage of failure in lot payments, and the "favorable" rates of&#13;
return assume that subdividers exaggerated some of their overhead&#13;
1/ Appendix II provides an explanation of the assumptions used&#13;
in the alternative IRR calculations. An IRR for each sub-&#13;
division was calculated using a computer program that assembled&#13;
a net cash flow and then computed the IRR by successive ap-&#13;
proximations (see Appendix II for details). The program&#13;
allowed the testing of the IRR's sensitivity to various&#13;
assumptions, such as the degree of lateness in lot payments,&#13;
and permitted easy substitution of real for nominal prices. The&#13;
program could not, however, calculate IRRs for unusual cadiflows.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
Table 17&#13;
ALTERNATIVE AVERAGE NCMINAL RATES OF RETURNI TO SUBDIVIDERS-/&#13;
(Figures are monthly; yearly figures in parentheses; rates are unadjusted for inflation)&#13;
Pirate Subdivisions       Normas      Pirate Subdivisions&#13;
Inside Urban Perimeter     Minimas    Outside Urban Perimeter&#13;
Monthly rates of return:&#13;
Payment default assumptions-/&#13;
Median                              1.9 (25)           2.8 (39)                (33)&#13;
Mean                                 2.7 (38)          6-0 (101)           3-  (55)&#13;
Standard deviation                  3.0 (42)           5.7(94)             4.8 (75)&#13;
N                             101                 14                  21&#13;
Medium assumptions3/&#13;
Median                               2.4 (33)               (78)               (41)&#13;
Mean                                3.6 (53)                (125)              (64)&#13;
Standard deviation                  3.6 53)            5.6 (92)                (78)&#13;
N                             102                 14                  21&#13;
Favorable assumptions4/&#13;
Median                               3.2 (46)               (146)          4.0 (60)&#13;
Mean                                4.6 (72)          10.9 (246)           5-5 (90)&#13;
Standard deviation                  5.(80)            126 (315)            62 (106)&#13;
N                              95                 13                  20&#13;
1/  Rates of return here are averages over internal rates of return calculated for individua.&#13;
subdivisions. Calculations are based on complete revenue and expenditure figures, with&#13;
dates, for each subdivision. Basic assumptions in all IRR calculations: All lots in th(&#13;
subdivision are sold; if the total number of lots is greater than the number of lots for&#13;
which sale data is given, the "excess" lots are counted as sold at the average size and&#13;
price (in 1977 pesos) and on the last date of sale among the lots listed.&#13;
2/  Payment default assumptions:   A certain proportion of defaulting lot buyers is given per&#13;
subdivision in the data; this incidence of default is assumed to occur randomly over the&#13;
period of lot sales; defaulting lot buyers are assumed to pay only the down payment.&#13;
3/  Medium assumptions:   No default; all lots are fully paid for on time.&#13;
4/  Favorable assumptions:   Overhead costs are limited to one standard deviation above the&#13;
mean of figures for normas minimas developments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
costs. These alternative estimates are intended to bound the results&#13;
within a valid range by accounting for the most serious sources of&#13;
uncertainty in the data.&#13;
Table 17 shows that profits in both pirate and normas&#13;
minimas subdivisions are good on the average. The median rates of&#13;
return are substantially lower than the means, indicating that there&#13;
are a few enormously lucrative subdivisions in the sample. Because&#13;
of the presence of these high-value "outliers" that skew the mean&#13;
upward, the median is a better measure of central tendency here.&#13;
While median nominal rates of return for pirate sub-&#13;
divisions are are well below 100 percent annually ( a range of 25&#13;
to 60 percent), they are much higher for normas minimas, up to 146&#13;
percent under favorable assumptions. This confirms what was&#13;
suggested by the averages in Table 1. Although normas minimas sub-&#13;
dividers pay more for land and spend more on the provision of infra-&#13;
structure, they earn larger profits than their pirate counterparts&#13;
because they sell lots at a higher price, they sell more of them, and&#13;
they sell them faster.&#13;
Two features of the absolute magnitudes of the IRRs are&#13;
noteworthy. One is that the medians for pirate subdivisions are&#13;
modest. According to these data, pirates earn a nominal IRR of&#13;
30 to 40 percent annually, which is much lower than earlier estimates.&#13;
Second, there is a very large amount of variance in IRRs among both&#13;
pirate and normas minimas subdivisions. Standard deviations exceed&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
means in almost all cases. This supports the idea that subdividers&#13;
in this market are a heterogeneous group. -/&#13;
C. Determinants of Rates of Return&#13;
What accounts for the large variation in subdivider's profits?&#13;
To help answer this question, a simple linear and additive regression&#13;
model was constructed with the nominal rate of return as a function&#13;
of subdivision characteristics, expenditure levels, and lot prices.&#13;
Although the model, presented in Table 18, accounts for less than a&#13;
third of the variation in rates of return, some inferences can be drawn.&#13;
Increments in tract prices seem to have strong negative&#13;
effects on rates of return, all else held constant, while marginal&#13;
expenditures on infrastructure and overhead have weak negative effects.&#13;
The coefficient for the number of lots in the subdivision is weak and&#13;
negative, contrary to expectations raised by the large and lucrative&#13;
normas minimas examples.    Average lot price is positive and has a&#13;
fairly strong effect: a Col$1,000 increase in average lot value yields&#13;
around a 0.5 percent increase in monthly nominal IRR. Profitability&#13;
also seems to improve markedly with how recently the subdivisions ws&#13;
developed, with the extent to which lot buyers are paying an install-&#13;
ment terms (prices are higher on installment), and with how soon the&#13;
subdivider begins selling lots after he acquires the tract. Dummy&#13;
1/ Background information collected by Bogota officials shows that&#13;
they are a mix of large and small-scale operators, of the educated&#13;
and the nearly illiterate, and of experienced and naive entre-&#13;
preneurs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 58 -&#13;
Table 18&#13;
RELATION BETWEEN RATE OF RETURN FOR&#13;
LOW-INCOME SUBDIVISIONS AND SUBDIVISION CHARACTERISTICS&#13;
Linear Estimation of Form:&#13;
IRR = A + BIVar1 + B2Var2 ...&#13;
Variable Definitions:&#13;
INPLOT                =         Expenditures by subdividers on infrastructure per lot.&#13;
BUYPLOT               =         Expenditures by lot buyers on    infrastructure per lot.&#13;
WAIT                  =         Number of years between tract acquisition and sale of&#13;
first lot in subdivision.&#13;
NNW                   =         Dummy variable equal to 1 if subdivision located in north-&#13;
northwest zone of city (north of Avda. Las Americas),&#13;
O otherwise.&#13;
WEST                  =         Dummy variable equal to 1 if subdivision located in&#13;
western zone of city (industrial corridor/Bosa),&#13;
O otherwise.&#13;
DIST                  =         Kilometers between DANE barrio in which subdivision is&#13;
located and CDB (defined as intersection of Avda. Caracas&#13;
and Calle 26).&#13;
LOTS                  =         Total number of lots in subdivision.&#13;
ALVL                  =         Average lot price in subdivision in lOOs of 1976 Col $.&#13;
TIME                  =         Year of sale of first lot indexed as 1950 = 1, 1951      2,&#13;
etc.&#13;
2&#13;
ALSZ                  =         Average lot size in subdivision (m ).&#13;
TRPM2                 =         Tract price per m   in 1976 Col $.&#13;
APDP                  =         Average down payment as a percent of average lot&#13;
price for the subdivision.&#13;
NM                    =         Dummy variable equal to 1 if subdivision is normas&#13;
minimas, 0 otherwise.&#13;
PROL                  =         Subdivider expenditure on professional services per&#13;
lot in 1976 Col $.&#13;
PUBL                  =         Subdivider expenditure on publicity per lot in 1976 Col $.&#13;
ADML                  =         Subdivider expenditure on administration per lot in&#13;
1976 Col $.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 59 -&#13;
Table 18 (Continued)&#13;
Dependent Variable = Internal Rate of Return 1/&#13;
in 10ths of Percent Per Month&#13;
Coefficients for Subsamples:&#13;
(Prices in 1976 Col $)&#13;
Pirate&#13;
Tract            Inside        Inside        Profitable&#13;
All Sub-       Acquisition        Urban        Perimeter      Subdivision&#13;
Variable          divisions     1970 or Later      Perimeter       (w/o NM)         Only&#13;
INPLOT             -.00126          -.0014          -.00106       -.00106          -.0014&#13;
BUYPLOT            -.00003            .00107         .00005         .00009         -.00011&#13;
WAIT               -.0674           -.0599          -.0855         -.0615          -.078&#13;
NNW               -2.22             1.13            6.12           5.57              .098&#13;
WEST              11.19            19.44           16.17          11.59           14.77&#13;
DIST                .138              .543          1.69           2.029           -.105&#13;
LOTST              -.00847          -.0193          -.00014        -.026           -.0056&#13;
ALVL                .0497             .0714          .0408          .022             .055&#13;
TIME               1.54               .353          1.47           1.62            2.88&#13;
ALSZ                .0207           -.00921         -.044          -.056             .016&#13;
TRPM2              -.142            -.231           -.136        -1.21             -.159&#13;
APDP               -.390            -.598           -.309          -.273           -.375&#13;
NM                17.73            11.37&#13;
PROL               -.00254          -.00713         -.0023         -.0021          -.0030&#13;
PUBL               -.00367          -.0055          -.0013          .0028          -.0074&#13;
ADML               -.00106          -.0034          -.0009         -.00067         -.0011&#13;
Constant          21.65            72.08           10.67         10.86             -.77&#13;
R 2                 .295              .351           .311           .312            .313&#13;
2                  .206             .201            .213           .198            .227&#13;
Std. Error&#13;
of Est.           37.53            43.64           36.34         32.95            37.06&#13;
Number of&#13;
Observations       (135)             (81)           (114)          (100)           (127)&#13;
Note::  Underlined coefficients are significant at the two-tail .05 level.&#13;
1/  Internal rate of return used here is "medium assumptions" figure.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 60 -&#13;
variables for location in the western part of the city and for&#13;
normas minimas subdivisions yield extremely high but non-significant&#13;
coefficients.&#13;
Among the explanatory variables omitted from the model&#13;
are the speed of lot sales and the subdividers' experience and&#13;
organizational ability, which probably account for a good part&#13;
of the unexplained two thirds variation in rates of return. It&#13;
is likely that the most lucrative subdivisions are developed by&#13;
subdividers who are well-organized, experienced, and well-connected&#13;
to government officials,subcontractors, and sources of credit.&#13;
D. Real vs. Nominal Rates of Feturn&#13;
Real rates of return (calculated with constant prices) are&#13;
compared with nominal rates in Table 19. For pirate subdivisions&#13;
real medians are about one-third (median assumptions) to one-half&#13;
(default assumptions) lower than nominal. For normas minimas,&#13;
however, median real and nominal rates of return hardly differ.&#13;
This suggests that normas minimas subdividers are more skilled than&#13;
their pirate counterparts at manipulating their expenditures, prices&#13;
and sales in such a way as to keep abreast of inflation.-/&#13;
In addition, while both pirate and normas minimas subdividers&#13;
earn real profits, normas minimas subdividers'real rates of return&#13;
are much higher. Interestingly the proportion of subdivisions that&#13;
fail, e.g. earn negative rates of return, is about the same for pirate&#13;
and normas minimas subdivisions. In nominal terms roughly one sub-&#13;
division in 15 fails under medium assumptions, while one in eight&#13;
1/   In an inflationary market the real IRR of a cash flow can be&#13;
increased by obtaining income as early as possible and postponing&#13;
expenditures. This is what normas minimas subdividers probably&#13;
do more successfully than pirates. See Chapter II, Pp. 33-34, for&#13;
evidence that cash flows in the pirate and normas minimas&#13;
business are often not typically "well-behaved", i.e. having&#13;
most expenditures occur before receipt of revenues.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 61 -&#13;
Table 19&#13;
1/&#13;
COMPARISON BETWEEN AVERAGE NOMINAL AND REAL RATES OF RETURN TO SUBDIVIDERS&#13;
(Figures are monthly; yearly figures in parentheses)&#13;
Rates of Return&#13;
Pirate Subdivisions Inside       Normas Minimas&#13;
Urban Perimeter            Subdivisions&#13;
Nominal     Real           Nominal    Real&#13;
Payment Default Assumptions&#13;
Median                                   1.9 (25)  10(13)               (41)     (41)&#13;
Mean                                     2.7       2.0              6.0       5.1&#13;
(38)       (27)             (101)    (82)&#13;
Standard Deviation                       3.0 (42   28 5(37 (94)                  (80)&#13;
Number of Subdivisions&#13;
with Negative IRR                       12        25                2         3&#13;
Total N                                  101       102               14        14&#13;
Medium Assumptions&#13;
Median                                   241.7                      49        4.7&#13;
2.4(33)       (22)             (78)     (74)&#13;
Mean                                     3.6(53)   3.1(44)          7.0(125) 6.0(101)&#13;
Standard Deviation                       3.6(53    4.6(72)          5.6(92)  5   (80)&#13;
Number of Subdivisions&#13;
with Negative IRR                        6        15                1         2&#13;
Total N                                  102       102               14        14&#13;
1/   See Table 17 for explanation of calculations and alternative assumptions.&#13;
Nominal figures are based on current Col$, and real figures are based on&#13;
constant 1976 Col$.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 62 -&#13;
fails under default assumptions. In real terms the failure rate&#13;
doubles, going as high as one subdivision in four or five under default&#13;
assumptions.-/&#13;
E. Summary and Conclusions&#13;
In general, both pirate and normas minimas subdivisions appear&#13;
to offer high real rates of return to subdividers who operate efficiently.&#13;
Although the rates of return observed here are not "exorbitant," a&#13;
small number of subdividers do apparently earn very large profits.&#13;
Average nominal rates of return in the pirate market are below those&#13;
that have prevailed recently in the middle and upper-middle class&#13;
development business and about on par with returns in financial markets.&#13;
The much higher average real rates of return to normas minimas&#13;
subdivisions indicate that excess demand exists for better-serviced&#13;
lots in Bogota. The demand has gone unmet because the controversial nature&#13;
of normas minimas -- involving both technical and political arguments&#13;
over how low the standards should be set -- have caused the District&#13;
government to approve relatively few normas minimas subdivision&#13;
proposals (32 approvals as of early 1979) since the laws were passed&#13;
in 1973.&#13;
1/ It is worth noting here that defaulting lot buyers do more damage,&#13;
on the average, to the rates of return of pirate subdivisions than&#13;
to normas minimas.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 63 -&#13;
The analysis indicates that pirate subdividers do not earn&#13;
a margin of "excess" profits large enough to be tapped for greater&#13;
infrastructure investments. Considering the risks inherent in the&#13;
business, the poorly-serviced pirate lots seem to be priced&#13;
competitively. The excess profits earned by itormas minimas sub-&#13;
dividers are apparently due to restrictions on the granting of&#13;
normas minimas permits, which are necessary for subdividers to connect&#13;
to utility networks and give legal titles to lot buyers. (see Chapter VI).&#13;
The permits are, in effect, licenses to market a scarce product and&#13;
thereby earn high profits.-/ Without these restrictions, the normas&#13;
minimas business would become more nearly competitive, lot prices would&#13;
fall somewhat, and rates of return for normas minimas subdivisions would&#13;
drop to around the level of those in the pirate market.&#13;
1/ Eleven of the 14 normas minimas subdivisions in the sample had&#13;
obtained resoluciones at the time of the survey. The other&#13;
three had received approval of their final designs. See Chapter&#13;
VI for a description of the normas minimas approval process.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 64 -&#13;
IV. THE DETERMINANTS OF TRACT PRICES&#13;
A. Analytical Framework&#13;
In a competitive land market like Bogota's one would expect&#13;
to observe certain spatial and behavioral regularities. Market prices&#13;
are the key to tracing these patterns. This chapter will introduce&#13;
a technique for analyzing the determinants of land prices - the&#13;
hedonic price index - and apply it to the prices of subdivision tracts.&#13;
In the next chapter the same technique will be used to analyze lot&#13;
prices.&#13;
Traditional theory in urban land economics posits that the&#13;
price of an undeveloped parcel of land is determined by various factors,&#13;
the most important being: topography, nearness to facilities or&#13;
amenities, distance from the central business district, the quality&#13;
of the neighborhood, and the timing of the purchase. All of these&#13;
can be thought of as "attributes" of the parcel. Ideally one might&#13;
construct a model in which the price of land is a function of its&#13;
attributes:&#13;
P = f [A1,A2,A3 *. An]&#13;
where P is the price of the land parcel and A1,A2, etc. are measures&#13;
of its attributes. This is the structure of a hedonic price index.&#13;
The technique assumes that each item or product (in this&#13;
case a tract or lot) has a market price that is associated with a&#13;
fixed set of quantities of attributes. The standard method is to&#13;
regress prices on a vector of attributes. The approach is related&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 65 -&#13;
to the idea of product differentiation; that is, thinking in terms&#13;
of one generic good (e.g. houses) with different component characteristics&#13;
(e.g. one bathroom or three) rather than in terms of many related&#13;
generic goods. The hedonic price is an implicit price whose validity&#13;
depends on the assumption that the market is in short-run equilibrium.-/&#13;
The regression coefficient of each explanatory variable is a mneasure&#13;
of the contribution of that variable to the variation in the price of&#13;
the good, holding constant the values of the other explanatory variablesA./&#13;
In this study the hedonic price index is used to reveal the&#13;
behavior of buyers and sellers. On the demand side, the regression&#13;
coefficients measure buyers' willingness to pay, on the margin, for&#13;
quantities of the corresponding attributes. On the supply side, the&#13;
coefficients indicate whether attributes make productive or unproductive&#13;
contributions, on the margin, to the supplier's return.&#13;
1/ See Rosen (1974) for an excellent treatment of the theory of hedonic&#13;
price indexes. An abstract of Rosen's model appears in Appendix III.&#13;
A basic work on the subject is Griliches (1971).&#13;
2/ The other key assumptions besides short-run equilibrium that underlie&#13;
the hedonic price index are: (1) buyers and sellers behave in&#13;
economically rational ways (maximizing utility and profit);&#13;
(2) consumers have access to information on the variation of&#13;
attributes and prices of goods; and (3) a sufficiently large number&#13;
of products with different attributes is available so that the&#13;
range of choice among combinations is virtually continuous.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 66 -&#13;
B. Results for Subdivision Tracts&#13;
As an introduction to the workings of the hedonic price&#13;
index, Table 20 presents the results of a simple model of the determinants&#13;
of prices of tracts purchased for pirate and normas minimas development.&#13;
Coefficients were calculated for seven explanatory variables in a linear&#13;
and additive specification. The equation was estimated for four groups&#13;
of subdivisions: the whole sample, tracts purchased in 1970 or after,&#13;
pirate subdivisions only, and tracts within Bogota's urban perimeter.&#13;
This specification explains no more than a third of the&#13;
variation in tract prices. This is not surprising, since the&#13;
independent variables cover only three explanatory concepts - tract&#13;
size, location, and date of acquisition - out of many possible ones.&#13;
While certain independent variables, such as the dummies for location&#13;
in the northwestern or western zones of the city, may pick up the&#13;
effects of more specific variables, there are a number of explanatory&#13;
variables completely missing, including the public services avail-&#13;
able on or near the tract, the tract's natural amenities and topography,&#13;
the legal status of the tenancy, and the zoning of the tract and&#13;
surrounding area.&#13;
The other major limitation of this specification is the linear&#13;
and additive form. Linearity implies constant returns to scale;&#13;
that is, price must vary in a constant ratio to the quantity of&#13;
each explanatory variable throughout the entire range of values of&#13;
that variable. A more sophisticated model might have included&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 67 -&#13;
Table 20&#13;
RELATION BETWEEN TRACT PRICE AND TRACT CHARACTERISTICS IN LOW-INCOME SUBDIVISIONS&#13;
Linear Hedonic Price Index of Form:   Price = A + B Var1 + B 2Var2 ....&#13;
(Prices in 1976 Col $)&#13;
Variable Definitions:&#13;
NNW;                      =         Dummy variable equal to 1 if tract is located in north-&#13;
northwest zone of the city (north of Avda. Las Americas),&#13;
O if otherwise.&#13;
WEST                                Dummy variable equal to 1 if tract is located in western&#13;
zone of the city (industrial corridor/Bosa), 0 if&#13;
otherwise.&#13;
AQYR                                Year of tract acquisition by subdivider.&#13;
DIST                                Number of kilometers between DANE barrio in which tract&#13;
is located and CBD (defined as intersection of Avda.&#13;
Caracas and Calle 26).&#13;
DISTSQ                              Square of DIST.&#13;
AQYRSQ                              Square of AQYR.&#13;
2&#13;
TRACTSZ                   =         Gross size of the tract in lOOs of m&#13;
Dependent Variable = Tract Price per m&#13;
Coefficients for Subsamples:&#13;
All             Tract Acquisition           Pirate   1/     Inside Urban&#13;
Variable        Subdivisions         1970 or Later          Subdivisions-        Perimeter&#13;
TRACTSZ            -.0088                -.0176                  -.0093             -.0066&#13;
NNW               29.73                  51.91                  30.88              30.61&#13;
WEST              23.15                  28.95                  18.06              20.94&#13;
AQYR              -3.04                   3.09                  -2.22              -1.89&#13;
AQYRSQ              .038                                           .031              .034&#13;
DIST              -3.93                 -5.15                   -2.49             -13.79&#13;
DISTSQ              .048                  -.102                    .0095             .54&#13;
Constant          94.68               -132.79                   62.35              83.66&#13;
R2                  .302                   .351                    .269              .348&#13;
R                   .266                   .302                    .228              .308&#13;
Std. Error&#13;
of Est.           34.44                 36.29                   34.71              34.43&#13;
Number of&#13;
Observations       (144)                  (87)                    (130)             (120)&#13;
Note: Underlined coefficients are significant at the two-tail .05 level.&#13;
1/ Excludes normas minimas.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68 -&#13;
non-linear transformations of certain variables (such as tract size).&#13;
This model attempts to account for the probable non-linear effects&#13;
of two variables - tract acquisition year and distance to the CBD -&#13;
by including their squares as additional independent variables.&#13;
The results show that the zone in which the tract is&#13;
located has the strongest effect on price. For all tracts, prices&#13;
in the west average about Col$20 per square meter higher than in&#13;
the south; prices in the northwest are around Col$30 higher than in&#13;
the south, other variables held constant. The data also indicate&#13;
that the desirability of the north-northwest and the west seems to&#13;
have increased over time. Limiting the sample to tracts acquired&#13;
since 1970 increases the coefficient for the west by roughly Col$10&#13;
and the one for the north-northwest by about Col$20. What accounts&#13;
for the strength of these variables? The zones are proxies for a&#13;
number of more specific explanatory factors, including access to&#13;
non-CBD employment (particularly in the "industrial corridor" to&#13;
the west between Calle 26 and Avenida Las Americas); the perceived&#13;
higher social status or quality of the areas, especially of the&#13;
northwest; and general topography, the south being hilly and erosion-&#13;
prone, the west being flat but containing certain flood areas, and&#13;
the northwest being the most desirable.&#13;
The other location variables in the model, distance in&#13;
kilometers to the CBD and the square of this distance, yield&#13;
coefficients of the expected signs and magnitudes. The high&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 69 -&#13;
concentration of jobs in Bogota's center makes accessibility valuable.-&#13;
For all tracts the price per square meter decreases by about Col$4&#13;
with each additional kilometer's distance from the center. The distance&#13;
coefficient rises sharply for tracts inside the urban perimeter only,&#13;
which corresponds to theoretical expectations that the land price&#13;
gradient should be steeper with proximity to the CBD.&#13;
The negative coefficient for tract size indicates that&#13;
there are "quantity discounts" in purchasing tracts. For every 100&#13;
square meters added to the size of the tract, sellers tend to lower&#13;
the unit price by about Col$l per square meter. The discount is&#13;
higher for subdivisions developed since 1970. Finally, the year&#13;
variable by itself and the combined effect of the year and its&#13;
square produce the expected results: since 1970 real tract prices&#13;
have been increasing by about Col$3 per square meter annually.&#13;
An important point in using hedonic price indexes is that&#13;
the coefficients of the independent variables express relationships&#13;
that are relevant to buyers and sellers emultaneously, given competitive&#13;
short-term equilibrium. The next chapter presents a similar but&#13;
more elaborate analysis of lot prices with particular attention to the&#13;
revealed preferences of lot buyers.&#13;
1/ According to data of the Instituto Colombiano de Seguro Social,&#13;
25 to 30 percent of all employment is concentrated in the CBD,&#13;
defined as DANE comuna 31, the old downtown south of Calle 25 and&#13;
east of Avenida Caracas. See K.S. Lee, Spatial Distribution of&#13;
Establishments and Employment in Bogota, 1978. World Bank,&#13;
City Study paper, January 1979, p. 5.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 70 -&#13;
V. THE DETERMINANTS OF LOT PRICES&#13;
A. Background and Model Specifications&#13;
Although the data set used in this study contains no inform-&#13;
ation about the characteristics of lot buyers, it is possible to&#13;
draw some inferences about their behavior. One way to do this is to&#13;
create a hedonic price index for lots sold in pirate and normas&#13;
minimas subdivisions. The Superintendencia Bancaria survey offers&#13;
the opportunity to test a number of different specifications and&#13;
subsamples. The analysis presented here was done first with sub-&#13;
divisions as observations, using mean values per subdivision for lot&#13;
price, lot size, and percent down-payment. Afterwards a sample of&#13;
lots was drawn and a new group of equations was estimated. This&#13;
chapter reports results for both the "aggregated" or subdivision&#13;
sample and for the "disaggregated" or lot sample.&#13;
The focus is on what the regression coefficients reveal&#13;
about lot buyers' willingness to pay for particular lot characteristics.&#13;
Do lot buyers pay higher prices for additional amounts of services,&#13;
all other things being equal? Or do they prefer to spend their&#13;
incremental pesos on other attributes, such as greater lot area or&#13;
better locations in the city? If the analysis shows that there is a&#13;
strong willingness to pay for well-serviced lots, it would suggest&#13;
that facilitating an increase in the supply of normas mininas lots&#13;
may be good public policy. If such willingness is lacking, it would&#13;
indicate that the attractiveness of normas minimas lots is based on&#13;
other characteristics, perhaps location.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 71 -&#13;
Different specifications were possible for several variables&#13;
in the hedonic price indexes. First, the dependent variable, lot price,&#13;
could take two forms: total price or price per square meter. Second,&#13;
the infrastructure variables could be expressed in terms either of&#13;
quantities (lineal meters of water, sewer, and electric lines, numbers&#13;
of standpipes, square meters of streets) or of expenditures. The most&#13;
useful results come from the equations which use quantities of infra-&#13;
structure,in that they reveal the value of additional units of services&#13;
installed rather than the effect of additional sums spent on services.&#13;
Further, the expenditure variables may give biased results to the&#13;
extent that subdividers may, due to inefficiency, install similar&#13;
levels of infrastructure at widely varying costs.-/&#13;
The linear and additive form of these equations limits the&#13;
interpretation of the results. While a more complex specification for&#13;
some terms might be desirable, the intention of this exercise is not&#13;
to obtain a "best fit" model; rather, it is to demonstrate a sense&#13;
of the direction and magnitude of the relationships between the various&#13;
lot attributes and the lot price.&#13;
1/ The infrastructure expenditure equations do provide a rough check&#13;
on the validity of the2data, however. The results they give are&#13;
reasonable,including R s, which are about the same as in the quantity&#13;
equations. (See Appendix IV).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 72 -&#13;
B. Aggregated Sample Results&#13;
The effects of the independent variables on lot prices,&#13;
presented in Tables 21 and 22, are summarized below.&#13;
Quantities of sewer, water, electricity, and streets: Using&#13;
infrastructure quantities clarifies the concept of hedonic price index&#13;
coefficients as measures of lot buyers' willingness to pay for&#13;
increments of these attributes. For example, the coefficient of 20.64&#13;
for the variable QSEWLT in the first column of Table 21 means that,&#13;
according to this model and this sample, one additional lineal meter&#13;
of sewer line per lot raises the average total lot price by Col$2,064,&#13;
holding all other lot attributes constant. In other words, Col$2,064&#13;
is what lot buyers are willing to pay, on the margin, for a unit&#13;
(linear meter) of this service. The results indicate that the number&#13;
of standpipes also has a strong positive effect on lot prices.&#13;
Installing one standpipe for every 10 lots raises the average lot&#13;
price by around Col$5,000. Demand for electric lines, water pipes,&#13;
and paving, however, seems much lower.    It is likely that buyers&#13;
are willing to pay substantially more for lots with access to standpipes&#13;
but not with waterpipes because standpipes are a large marginal improve-&#13;
ment over trucked-in water or none at all. While individual water&#13;
pipes are better still, buyers are not willing to pay extra for them&#13;
because, at the time of lot acquisition, the marginal benefits over&#13;
standpipes probably do not exceed the marginal costs. Moreover, lot&#13;
buyers have learned to expect that the District government will&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 3 -&#13;
Tables 21 and 22&#13;
RELATION BETWEEN LOT PRICE AND SUBDIVISION CHARACTERISTICS&#13;
Linear Hedonic Price Index of Form:&#13;
Price = A + B Var1 + B2Var2 ...&#13;
(Observations are subdivisions; all prices in constant 1976 Col $)&#13;
Variable Definitions:&#13;
ALSZ                 =         Average lot size in subdivision (m ).&#13;
DIST                 =         Kilometers along major streets from midpoint of DANIE&#13;
barrio in which subdivision is located to CBD (defined&#13;
as intersection of Avda. Caracas with Calle 26).&#13;
TIME                 =         Year of sale of first lot indexed as 1950 = 1,&#13;
1951 = 2, etc.&#13;
NNW                  =         Dummy variable equal to 1 if subdivision located in&#13;
north-northwest zone of city (north of Avda. Las&#13;
Americas), 0 if elsewhere.&#13;
WEST                 =         Dummy variable equal to 1 if subdivision located&#13;
in western zone of city (industrial corridor/Bosa),&#13;
0 if elsewhere.&#13;
OPLOT                          Square meters of open space per lot in subdivision.&#13;
STPLOT               =         Square meters of street area per lot in subdivision.&#13;
NM                   -         Dummy variable equal to 1 if subdivision is legal&#13;
normas minimas, 0 otherwise.&#13;
TRPM2, TRPLOT                  Price of original tract of land per m    and per lot.&#13;
PROM, PROL           =         Expenditure on professional services per m2 of usable&#13;
(salable) area and per lot.&#13;
PUBM, PUBL           =         Expenditure on publicity per m   of usable (salable)&#13;
area and per lot.&#13;
ADMM, ADML                     Expenditure on administration per m    of usable&#13;
(salable) area and per lot.&#13;
PERIM                =         Dummy variable equal to 1 if subdivision is within&#13;
the Bogota urban perimeter, 0 if not.&#13;
APDP                 =         Average down payment as a percent of average lot&#13;
price for the subdivision.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 74 -&#13;
QSEWM2, QSEWLT       =         Lineal meters of sewer lines installed per m    of&#13;
usable area and per lot.&#13;
PILPM2, PILPLT       =         Number of pilas (water taps) installed per m    of&#13;
usable area and per lot.&#13;
QWATM2, QWATLT       =         Lineal meters of water lines installed per m    of&#13;
usable area and per lot.&#13;
QELEM2, QELELT       =         Lineal meters of electric lines installed per m    of&#13;
usable area and per lot.&#13;
QSTRM2, QSTRLT       =         Square meters of street area installed per m    of&#13;
usable area and per lot.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 75 -&#13;
Table 21&#13;
LINEAR HEDONIC PRICE INDEX WITSTNFRASTRUCTURE QUANTITY&#13;
Coefficients for Subsamples:&#13;
(Observations are Subdivisions)&#13;
Dependent Variable = Average Lot Price per Subdivision in 100s&#13;
(All prices in 1976 Col $)&#13;
All               Inside Urban           Profitable          Profitable In-&#13;
Variable          Subdivisions            Perimeter          Subdivisions          side Perimeter&#13;
ALSZ                   .183                    .662                 .134                    .776&#13;
DIST                 -7.16                  -13.05               -6.71                  -15.77&#13;
TIME                  1.96                    3.98                 1.10                    3.89&#13;
NNW                 160.10                  191.76              157.46                  178.81&#13;
WEST                117.97                  117.34              103.09                  100.26&#13;
OPLOT                  .293                    .262                 .217                    .042&#13;
STPLOT               -2.82                    -.278               -.247                   -.059&#13;
NM                  155.61                  176.87              168.77                  191.73&#13;
TRPLOT                 .0076                   .0074                .0084                   .0080&#13;
PROL                   .0123                   .0092                .0124                   .0089&#13;
PUBL                   .0134                   .0053                .0085                   .0058&#13;
ADML                   .0015                   .00094               .0012                   .00007&#13;
PERIM                25.69                                         6.56&#13;
APDP                 -1.30                   -1.67               -1.28                   -1.25&#13;
QSEWLT               20.64                   18.18               20.11                   16.04&#13;
PILPLT              618.16                  421.82              555.26                  490.87&#13;
QWATLT               -4.98                  -10.68               -6.45                  -14.61&#13;
QELELT                8.13                    9.49                9.15                   12.22&#13;
QSTRLT                -.234                    .274              -1.77.                     .378&#13;
Constant            172.43                  166.68              211.19                  167.98&#13;
R2                     .659                    .673                 .668                    .686&#13;
R2                     .583                    .583                 .592                    .597&#13;
Std. Error&#13;
of Est.             133.90                  141.65              133.13                  140.07&#13;
Number of&#13;
Observations          (100)                   (80)                 (97)                    (78)&#13;
Note: Underlined coefficients are significant at the two-tail .05 level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 76 -&#13;
Table 22&#13;
LINEAR HEDONIC PRICE INDEX WIt1t-4*F1N:STRUCTURE QUANTITY&#13;
Coefficients for Subsamples:&#13;
(Observations are Subdivisions)       2&#13;
Dependent Variable = Average Lot Price per m per Subdivision&#13;
(All prices in 1976 Col $)&#13;
A 1l              Inside Urban           Profitable          Profitable In-&#13;
Variable          Subdivisions            Perimeter          Subdivisions          side Perimeter&#13;
ALSZ                  -.245                   -.974                -.275                  -.891&#13;
DIST                 -6.53                   -9.47               -6.60                  -11.19&#13;
TIME                  9.15                    8.86                 8.22                   8.71&#13;
NNW                  96.96                  155.01                94.11                 146.51&#13;
WEST                110.55                  112.32                98.54                 101.17&#13;
OPLOT                 -.0027                   .327                -.074                    .179&#13;
STPLOT                 .134                    .022                 .177                    .142&#13;
NM                   76.50                   95.95                83.96                 102.95&#13;
TRPM2                  .667                    .605                 .738                    .656&#13;
PROM                   .807                    .595                 .782                    .549&#13;
PUBM                  2.16                     .369                2.12                     .664&#13;
ADMM                   .632                    .591                 .539                    .502&#13;
PERIM                 8.11                                       -5.72&#13;
APDP                  -.940                  -1.39                 -.858                 -1.09&#13;
QSEWM2             1683.3                  1676.1              1636.5                  1521.2&#13;
PILPLT             605.20                  484.7                660.14                   580.61&#13;
QWATM2           -1017.5                   -705.5             -1123.6                  -1058.1&#13;
QELEM2              354.8                   136.5                478.6                   332.5&#13;
QSTRM2                6.84                  -15.36                11.12                   -4.42&#13;
Constant             59.29                  221.25               95.19                  222.05&#13;
R2                     .684                    .677                 .687                    .678&#13;
R2                     .614                    .589                 .614                    .586&#13;
Std. Error&#13;
of Est.             108.51                  112.97              107.50                  112.29&#13;
Number of&#13;
Observations          (100)                   (80)                 (97)                    (78)&#13;
Note: Underlined coefficients are significant at the two-tail .05 level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 77 -&#13;
eventually install water lines at lower costs than pirate subdividers.-/&#13;
At the same time, lot buyers are willing to pay significantly more&#13;
for sewer lines. Although this service is expensive, the demand exists&#13;
because (1) sewer pipes are an enormous improvement over the feasible&#13;
alternative, pit latrines, (2) septic tanks are unworkable on the small&#13;
pirate and normas minimas lots-/; and (3) there is no alternative&#13;
supplier as in the case of water connections. The low willingness&#13;
to pay for electric lines exists because legal connections are readily&#13;
obtained from the public electric company and, if not, illegal taps&#13;
are easy to install. Willingness to pay for street construction&#13;
appears to be noneexistent because virtually all subdivisions have&#13;
graded, unpaved streets, and the cost of paving is very high relative&#13;
to the added benefits.&#13;
Tract price: As an explanatory variable, tract price is a&#13;
proxy for neighborhood quality, including factors like the social&#13;
class of the residents, access to shops and services, the attractive-&#13;
ness of the landscape, and the presence or absence of nuisances such&#13;
1/ Since 1976 the Special District of Bogota has offered individual&#13;
water connections to lot owners in illegal subdivisions on very&#13;
favorable terms: a 30 percent down-payment on the household's&#13;
share of the network cost and a connection fee equivalent to 3&#13;
percent of the land value, plus installation costs. Both the&#13;
balance of the network charge and the whole connection fee are&#13;
financed at 12 percent over ten years.&#13;
2/ Even if septic tanks were an alternative, they are no less ex-&#13;
pensive than sewer pipes. In fact, the cost to the user of septic&#13;
tanks may be greater because sewer installation is often subsidized.&#13;
For a comparison of economic costs per unit of various sanitation&#13;
technologies, see Johannes Linn, Policies for Efficient and&#13;
Equitable Growth of Cities in Developing Countries, World Bank Staff&#13;
Working Paper No. 342, July 1979, p. 255.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 78 -&#13;
as noise or pollution. The tract price may also pick up the effect of&#13;
how readily the land can be serviced with public utility connections&#13;
(e.g. the elevation and proximity of sewer and water mains) and the&#13;
quality of access roads. The coeficcient for tract price is&#13;
consistently positive and significant across subsamples, though its&#13;
1/&#13;
value is below unity.-&#13;
Location: Dummy variables for subdivision location in the&#13;
northwest or west turn out to be among the strongest explanatory&#13;
variables in the lot price analysis. The coefficients are always&#13;
significant and have high values. Holding all other characteristics&#13;
constant, a lot in the west costs about Col$10,000 more than a lot&#13;
in the south, while a lot in the northwest costs Col$16,000 to&#13;
Col$18,000 more. In other words, controlling for the level of&#13;
infrastructure, tract price, lot size, and distance to the CBD,&#13;
lot buyers are willing to pay 10 to 20 thousand pesos for location&#13;
in these zones alone. As in the tract price analysis of the last&#13;
chapter, access to non-CBD employment, social status, and topo-&#13;
graphical desirability make the zone dummy variables strong&#13;
determinants of land prices.&#13;
Distance to the center: The coefficient of distance in&#13;
kilometers from the subdivision to the center of Bogota has the&#13;
expected negative sign. In most subsamples it is not statistically&#13;
1/ Tract price is in this case an explanatory variable together&#13;
with some of the Iame independent variables used in Chapter IV's&#13;
model. The low R produced by the tract price equation --&#13;
around .3 -- permits this maneuver without raising serious&#13;
collinearity problems.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 79 -&#13;
significant because it interacts with other accessibility and location&#13;
variables such as the zone and tract price. The coefficient behaves&#13;
well, however, having a larger absolute value for subdivisions inside&#13;
1/&#13;
the urban perimeter.-   Linearly, total lot price declines by about&#13;
Col$700 to Col$1,500 per kilometer and the lot price per square&#13;
meter by about Col$6 to Col$ll.&#13;
Average lot size: Results differ depending on the specification&#13;
of the dependent variable. Using total lot price, the coefficient is&#13;
positive across all subsamples; with lot price per square meter, however,&#13;
it is consistently negative showing that unit price decreases with lot&#13;
size. For both specifications, though,the absolute values of the&#13;
coefficients are much larger for subdivisions inside the urban perimeter,&#13;
where an additional square meter of lot area costs an average of about&#13;
Col$70 to Col$80. Outside the perimeter one finds very large, low-&#13;
value lots.&#13;
Year of sale of first lot: The coefficients for this variable&#13;
has the expected positive sign in all equations and its absolute size&#13;
is quite stable. The results indicate that average total lot prices&#13;
have been increasing in real terms by several hundred pesos per year.&#13;
Average lot prices per square meter have been going up by about 8 to&#13;
10 pesos per year, with a higher annual increase of up to 15 pesos&#13;
in the last several years.&#13;
1/ In Appendix Tables A6 and A7 (equations using infrastructure&#13;
expenditure variables), the slope is substantially lower among&#13;
recently-developed subdivisions, indicating a flattening of the&#13;
price-distance gradient over time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 80 -&#13;
Average percent down-payment: Using the average percent&#13;
down-payment as an independent variable measures the implicit finance&#13;
charge to lot buyers who pay on installment. Pirate subdividers seldom&#13;
give lot buyers an explicit interest rate as part of the terms of&#13;
sale. The general practice is to charge a higher total price (computed&#13;
as the sum of the installments plus the down-payment).     The expectation&#13;
is for the coefficient of this variable to be negative, since it is&#13;
hypothesized that the smaller the percent down-payment, the higher&#13;
the total lot price, all else being equal.    The sign is in fact&#13;
consistently negative and the absolute value is stable over the&#13;
various specifications and subsamples; indeed, the variable appears&#13;
to be quite strong. For an average lot, the price increase from&#13;
paying in full (100 percent down) to paying 30 percent down is about&#13;
Col$9,000. In terms of average lot price per square meter, this&#13;
increment is around Col$70. Using these results and the average lot&#13;
price figures in Table 1, the average implicit finance charge on the&#13;
balance is about 46 percent yearly for all lots in the sample.-/&#13;
1/  As will be shown later, however, this figure is an overestimate. The&#13;
method of calculation is the following: The coefficient for the&#13;
percent down-payment variable from the hedonic price equation is&#13;
the amount by which the subdivider is willing to reduce the lot price&#13;
for each additional percentage point added to the down-payment. This&#13;
coefficient multiplied by 100 (percent) is the maximum price reduction&#13;
available to a buyer who pays in one lump sum (100 percent down) in&#13;
comparison with another who pays entirely on installment (zero percent&#13;
down). In other words, the subdivider is indifferent between receiving&#13;
the lot price minus this reduction immeeiately or being paid installments&#13;
that add up to the lot price over a certain term. The implicit finance&#13;
charge may be calculated by setting the former as the present value&#13;
and solving for the discount rate which makes the latter installment&#13;
stream equal to it.   Example: Average lot price = Col$31,000; percent&#13;
down-payment coefficient from aggregated equation = 1.30; maximum&#13;
price reduction = (130 X 100) = Col$13,000; average term length = 37&#13;
months; average installment at zero down-payment = (31,000/37) =&#13;
Col$838; setting present value of 18,000 (31,000 - 13,000) equal to&#13;
838 over 37 months, the monthly discount rate = 3.2 percent (46 percent&#13;
yearly).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 81 -&#13;
Overhead expenditures: The subdivider's expenditures for&#13;
professional services, publicity, and administration were included&#13;
to test if lots are priced to recover marginal increases in these&#13;
cost categories. The professional services expenditure coefficient&#13;
oscillates around unity across the various equations, while publicity&#13;
expenditures have coefficients above unity in most cases (especially&#13;
in the specifications in Appendix IV). One possible explanation for&#13;
the productivity of publicity expenditures is that they are a proxy&#13;
for the subdivider's organizational ability or business acumen.&#13;
Administration expenditures yield weak coefficients and seem to be&#13;
unproductive.&#13;
Open space and street area: Although the amount of open&#13;
space and street area were expected to have positive effects on lot&#13;
prices, the coefficients for these variables are consistently low in&#13;
value, are never statistically significant, and have unstable signs.&#13;
Simple correlations of these variables with lot price are also not&#13;
sigfiificant.&#13;
Normas Minimas: Table 21 shows that a normas minimas&#13;
lot costs between Col$15,000 and Col$20,000 more than a pirate lot,&#13;
controlling for location, services, and other attributes. One&#13;
possible reason that buyers seem to be willing to pay more for a&#13;
normas minimas lot is that there is a higher probability of having&#13;
infrastructure installed; another possibility is that normas minimas&#13;
buyers are paying for the greater likelihood of obtaining full legal&#13;
title.&#13;
Urban perimeter: A dummy variable for the urban perimeter&#13;
was included in some equations to pick up the effect of laws prohibiting&#13;
public service connections outside the perimeter. While these laws&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 82 -&#13;
are not strictly enforced, their existence probably does delay the&#13;
provision of infrastructure in the outside areas. The coefficient&#13;
for this variable is not statistically significant, and its absolute&#13;
size and sign are unstable. The ambiguity of the results is due&#13;
largely to the interaction of this variable with the distance to CBD,&#13;
zone, and infrastructure variables.&#13;
C. Disaggregated Sample&#13;
The above results, based on subdivisions as observations,&#13;
tell a useful story about the key features of pirate lots. There is&#13;
something more to be learned, however, from estimating these equations&#13;
using a set of observations of individual lots. The use of subdivisions&#13;
as observations creates potential for "aggregation bias." This can&#13;
occur when the variables in regression equations are averages over&#13;
individual observations that are grouped in some way. A common&#13;
example is the use of averages across census tracts for variables like&#13;
household income or family size. A key condition for introducing&#13;
aggregation bieas is that the data be grouped non-randomly according&#13;
to values of the dependent variable. If this is done, the absolute&#13;
values of the coefficients of the explanatory variables will be biased&#13;
upwards.-   In the preceeing analysis the d4ependent varil1ele (eotU&#13;
forms of it) and two independent variables - lot size and percent down&#13;
1/ This was demonstrated by Smith and Campbell, who aggregated the&#13;
data for a housing expenditure estimation in three ways: randomly,&#13;
according to one independent variable, and according to the dependent&#13;
variable. The parameters in the first two estimations were&#13;
consistent with those based on the original disaggregated data;&#13;
the third set were higher. This was termed "pure" aggregation&#13;
bias. See Barton, Smith and J.M. Campbell, Jr. Aggregation Bias&#13;
and the  Demand for Housing,         Paper presented at the Annual&#13;
Meet'ing of the Econometric Society, Atlantic City, New Jersey,&#13;
September 1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 83 -&#13;
payment - are averages across all the lots sold in each subdivision.&#13;
Since lots within a subdivision are more homogeneous in price than&#13;
the total universe of lots, using lot price averages as observations&#13;
implicitly groups the sample into higher-price and lower-price&#13;
categories; in other words, it stratifies along the dependent variable.&#13;
In addition, using lots as observations permits a more&#13;
realistic approach to the infrastructure variables. In the aggregate&#13;
equations infrastrubture was counted as being available no matter when&#13;
it was installed. Since the lot price was an average across all lots,&#13;
there was no way to differentiate between those lots sold before or&#13;
after the installation of a given infrastructure type. In the disag-&#13;
gregated equations, one specification parallels that used in the&#13;
aggregate sample, with the infrastructure variable interpreted as&#13;
"installed ever". The other specification contains separate variables&#13;
for infrastructure installed before and after the sale of the lot.&#13;
The latter assumes that the presence or absence of infrastructure at&#13;
the date of sale is reflected in lot price but allows for the&#13;
possibility that the expectation of receiving infrastructure may raise&#13;
the lot price.&#13;
Tables 23 and 24 present the coefficients for hedonic price&#13;
indexes based on a random sample of lots drawn from the 19,555 in&#13;
the Superintendencia Bancaria data. The tables present equations&#13;
containing infrastructure quantity variables like those set out in&#13;
Tables 21 and 22. Lot sample coefficients for equations with infra-&#13;
structure expenditures appear in Appendix IV. In general the results&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 84 -&#13;
Table 23&#13;
LINEAR HEDONIC PRICE INDEX WITH INFRASTRUCTURE QUANTITY&#13;
Coefficients for Subsamples:&#13;
Observations are Lots&#13;
DeDendent Variable = Total Lot Prlce in 100s&#13;
(All prices in 1976 ColS)&#13;
Variable                       All Lots                  Profitable Subdivisions     Inside Urban Perimeter    Pirate Subdivisions&#13;
Infra-                     Infra-                    Infra-                      Infra-&#13;
Infra-     structure       Infra-     structure      Infra-      structure      Infra-      structure&#13;
Aggregate    structure    Before or    structure    Before or     structure    Before or    structure     Before or&#13;
Model        Ever       After Sale     Ever        After Sale     Ever       After Sale     Ever        After sale&#13;
LSZ                .183        .113          .103         .115        .103          1.60         1.61         .104          .095&#13;
LYS               1.96         3.53         2.41          .744        -.907        11.04        11.44         .475           .715&#13;
"0--DP           -1.30         -.545        -.538        -.432        -.407         -.559        -.613       -.689          -.640&#13;
NM              155.61      -142.44      -121.18       -126.73     -107.18        -587.68      -99.28&#13;
NNW4            160.10       158.34       149.76       148.54       141.08        153.14       127.94      109.44         123.22&#13;
WEST            117.97       171.32       156.59        131.45      112.18        153.69      143.31        171.87        161.96&#13;
TRPM2              .0076       1.16         1.28         1.33         1.51          1.41        1.40         1.73           1.45&#13;
DIST             -7.16        -5.71        -4.92        -3.66        -2.32         -2.65       -4.27        -3.81          -4.52&#13;
PROL               .0123       -.0031       -.0007       -.00036       .0025         .0041       .0082        .0032         .0021&#13;
PUBL               .0134        .0753        .0723        .0826        .0808         .055        .058         .101          .087&#13;
ADML               .0015        .0069        .0066         .0065       .0057         .0046       .0025         .0035         .0048&#13;
BEFORE&#13;
QSEWLT           20.64         7.95         5.11         7.42         5.12          7.14        1.49         2.12           2.60&#13;
QWATLT           -4.98        -4.24        -6.11        -4.82        -8.36        -23.08      -15.69         4.55          -3.87&#13;
QELCLT            8.13         -.135        2.59         2.29         4.45          1.19        1.61         -1.11          6.73&#13;
QSTRLT            -.234        -.288        -.466        -.309        -.497         -414        -527         -.243          -.463&#13;
PILPT           618.16      1569.72      2328.9       1700.3       2359.23        683.23     1530.7       1183.7        2419.7&#13;
AFTER&#13;
QSEWLT                                      6.37                      4.65                      845                    .    3.58&#13;
QWATLT                                     -5.45                     -3.49                    -23.08                       -3.41&#13;
QELCLT                                      -.726                     2.27                       .0077                      -.561&#13;
QSTRLT                                      2.49                      2.67                      2.32                        2.19&#13;
PILPLT                                    357.49                    483.52                    326.31                     -846.31&#13;
Constant        172.43       -46.91        27.58       114.80       221.64       -782.17     -790.51        155.24        151.57&#13;
R2                 .659        .609          .642         .615        .654          .665         .697         .504          .539&#13;
R                  .583         .604         .636         .609        .647          .659         .689         .496          .529&#13;
Std. Error&#13;
of Est          133.90       131.95       126.63       131.49       125.08        126.76      120.89       130.68         126.09&#13;
Number of&#13;
Observations      (100)       (1,129)      (1,129)      (1,033)     (1,033)        (912)       (912)        (1,009)       (1,009)&#13;
Note: Underlined coefficients are significant at the two-tail .05 level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 85 -&#13;
Table 24&#13;
LINEAR HFDONIC PRICE INDEX WITH INFRASTRUICTURE QUANTITY&#13;
Coefficients for Subsemples:&#13;
Observations are Lots&#13;
Dependent Variable = Lot Price per M2&#13;
(All prices in 97f Col$S)&#13;
Variable                        All Lots                   Profitable Subdivisions      Inside Urban Perimeter     Pirate Subdivisions&#13;
Infra-                        Infra-                  Infra-                      Infra-&#13;
Infra-      structure      Infra-       structure      Infra-     structure      Infra-       structure&#13;
Aggrega':c   structure     Before or     structure     Eefc.re or   structure    Before or    structure      Before or&#13;
Model        Ever        After Sale     Ever         After Sale     Ever       After Sale     Ever         After Sale&#13;
LSZ                -.245        -.136        -.126         -.142          -.129        -.729       -.635         -.122          -.116&#13;
LYS                9.15         8.07         8.63          6.24           6.15        10.46       11.41          7.35           8.33&#13;
PCDP              -9.40         -.425        -.456         -.334          -.345        -.341       -.402         -.562          -.534&#13;
NM                76.80      -119.61       -139.01      -122.58        -149.19       -94.22     -117.46&#13;
NNW               96.96       131.12        124.90       127.59         119.93       132.10      105.27         93.61         114.44&#13;
WEST             110.55       145.56        125.67       125.53          98.56       138.72      120.42        155.46         136.35&#13;
TRP12               .667        1.30         1.57          1.39           1.74         1.36        1.39          1.73           1.51&#13;
DIST              -6.53        -6.63       -6.29          -5.27          -4.40        -1.41       -2.59         -8.14          -8.41&#13;
PROM                .807        1.37         1.85          1.28           1.72          .718       1.39          1.02           1.41&#13;
PUBM               2.16          .340         .599         1.63           2.20         2.83        2.51          5.09           2.77&#13;
ADoMM               .632        1.71         1.46          1.62           1.30         1.26          .844        1.37           1.42&#13;
BEFORE&#13;
QsEWIZ2          168.33       271.48       -494.53       288.79        -444.20       198.12     -478.41         92.64        -358.98&#13;
QWALN2         -1017.5       -953.03      -823.88       -976.99       -1068.2     -2782.2       -1262.7       -327.87        -371.62&#13;
QELCM2           358.4       -721.72       -409.35      -506.15        -218.99      -547.04     -500.81       -357.44        -129.63&#13;
QSTRX23            6.84       -26.01       -43.62        -23.57         -42.28       -40.64      -59.95        -32.03         -53.00&#13;
PILPLT           605.20     2071.6        1927.37       2352.6         2046.6       1111.26     1516.0          -3.14        -516.43&#13;
AFTER&#13;
QSEWM2                                     670.97                       502.58                   431.47                       668.81&#13;
QWALM2                                     -719.51                     -521.91                 -3409.9                       -917.66&#13;
QELCM2                                     -535.91                     -245.23                  -481.37                      -294.63&#13;
QSTR'12                                    267.22                       313.52                   320.28                       246.66&#13;
PILFLT                                    1637.35                      1990.9                    746.65                      1477.98&#13;
Constant          59.29      -367.17       -417.83      -259.96        -270.67      -494.82     -557.90       -290.75        -364.95&#13;
R2                 ,.684         .709         .752          .679           .737         .693        .742          .718           .753&#13;
RT                  .614         .705         .748          .674           .731         .688        .736          .714           .748&#13;
Std. Error&#13;
of Est.          108.51       105.57        97.65        106.12          96.37       107.83       99.16        101.68          95.46&#13;
Number of&#13;
Observations      (100)       (1,129)       (1,129)      (1,033)        (1,033)       (912)       (912)        (1,009)         (1,009)&#13;
Note: Underlined coefficients are significant at the two-tail .05 level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 86 -&#13;
of the individual lot sample do not differ dramatically from those of&#13;
the subdivision (aggregated) sample. R s remain around .6 to .7; all&#13;
but a few coefficeints have the same sign and similar values. In&#13;
addition to supporting the results of the subdivision equations, the&#13;
lot sample coefficients indicate the following:&#13;
Ingrastructure quantity: Tables 23 and 24 show two&#13;
consistent differences from the aggregated subdivision sample&#13;
equations. First, while the coefficient for quantity of sewer lines&#13;
is still positive and mostly significant, its absolute value is&#13;
substantially lower. Instead of costing about Col$2,000 per lot, an&#13;
additional lineal meter of sewer line is estimated here to cost&#13;
about Col$700 - 800. Second, the coefficient for standpipes goes&#13;
up by a factor of two to three. Installing one standpipe for every&#13;
ten lots adds about Col$15,000 to the price of an average lot,&#13;
compared to Col$5,000 as estimated with the aggregated sample. The&#13;
other infrastructure quantity relationships remain more or less un-&#13;
changed.&#13;
Regarding infrastructure quantities installed before and&#13;
after lot sale, the equations give mixed results. The expectation&#13;
is that the "before" coefficients should be stronger, based on the&#13;
premise that people are willing to pay more for lots with infra-&#13;
structure already installed. Standpipes and electric lines, however,&#13;
are the only services whose coefficients are consistently higher&#13;
before lot sale than after. Sewer lines installed before lot sale&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 87 -&#13;
give stronger coefficients in Table 24, but in Table 23 the before and&#13;
after coefficients for sewer are about the same. Water pipes yield&#13;
small and unstable coefficients whether before or after lot sale.&#13;
Square meters of streets constructed after lot sale give positive and&#13;
significant coefficients, while those for streets built before sale are&#13;
weak and negative. The reason may be that subdivisions where street&#13;
construction occurs after the sale of lots are those in which the&#13;
greatest marginal benefits accrue to lot buyers. In sum, while services&#13;
installed prior to lot sale do tend to have stronger effects on lot&#13;
prices, buyers appear to be willing to pay additional sums for promised&#13;
services.&#13;
Lot size and percent down-payment: Although the coefficient&#13;
for lot size does not change appreciably in the disaggregated equations,&#13;
the percent down-payment coefficient is lower in absolute value by&#13;
about half than in the aggregated specifications. The extra cost of&#13;
paying on installment thus amounts to about Col$4,200 for an average&#13;
lot rather than the Col$9,000 estimated originally (assuming a 30 percent&#13;
down-payment). The average implicit finance charge, which was over-&#13;
estimated using the coefficient from the aggregated equation, is&#13;
calculated here to be about 13 percent per year on the balance for all&#13;
lots paid by installment.&#13;
Normas minimas: In the aggregated equation the coefficient&#13;
for the normas minimas dummy variable is positive but not statistically&#13;
significant. In the disaggregated runs, however, the coefficient&#13;
is consistently negative and significant for the equations with&#13;
infrastructure quantity. The change of sign is not clearly due to&#13;
interaction effects or outliers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 88 -&#13;
Distance to the CBD: All coefficients in the lot&#13;
sample equations have smaller absolute values than in the sub-&#13;
division equations. The decline in total lot price per kilometer&#13;
is estimated here (linearly) to be about Col$300 to Col$500, less&#13;
than half that in the aggregated.&#13;
In summary, the disaggregated sample does seem to&#13;
help correct bias in the estimates of the effects of sewer lines,&#13;
standpipes, the percent down-payment on the lot, and distance to&#13;
the CBD. The equations explain between half and two-thirds of&#13;
the variance in lot prices. Adjusted R s range from around .6 for&#13;
the equations in which total lot price is the dependent variable&#13;
to about .7 for those in which lot price per square meter is&#13;
dependent. These R s are about as large as can be expected and&#13;
permit a high degree of confidence in the results.&#13;
D. Summary&#13;
Two types of samples were used to estimate the effects, via&#13;
hedonic price indexes, of varying lot characteristics on lot prices: an&#13;
aggregated sample of subdivisions using mean lot prices and a disaggregated&#13;
sample of lots using individual prices. The results from the two samples&#13;
are similar, though the disaggregated sample yields more reliable estimates&#13;
of the effects of some variables. The equations show that there is a&#13;
willingness to pay among lot buyers for additional amounts of sewer lines&#13;
and standpipes, for location in the north and west of Bogota, for closeness&#13;
to the center of the city, and for larger lot area. Little willingness to&#13;
pay is found for additional amounts of water pipes, electric lines, or&#13;
street construction. While people undoubtedly place some value on these&#13;
services, the low willingness to pay probably results from the availability&#13;
of cheaper alternatives (such as standpipes or clandestine electricity&#13;
connections).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 89 -&#13;
VI. POLICY ISSUES: NORMAS MINIMAS AND THE SUPPLY OF SERVICED LOTS&#13;
A. Improving the Quality of Lots&#13;
The key policy issue addressed by this study is how&#13;
to encourage the private sector to increase the supply of adequately&#13;
serviced lots for the lower and moderate income market. The&#13;
Bogota District has pursued this goal in two ways: bringing sanctions&#13;
against the most exploitative pirate subdividers to force them to&#13;
provide services and making it possible for the private sector to enter&#13;
the legal lots-with-services business by way of the normas m.inimas&#13;
standards.&#13;
The first approach has involved freezing the assets of&#13;
pirate subdividers, a procedure known as intervencion, which is&#13;
analogous to the U.S. practice of placing a venture in receivership.&#13;
Law 66 of 1968 (Article 12) empowers the Housing Division of the&#13;
Superintendencia Bancaria to seize (though not confiscate) the assets&#13;
of illegal subdividers and to turn over the administration of their&#13;
subdivisions to the Instituto de Credito Territorial (ICT), Colombia's&#13;
public housing agency. To help implement the intervencion, a lien&#13;
is normally placed on the land and on the subdivider's bank accounts.&#13;
The goal is to hold the property until the subdivider upgrades services&#13;
to a satisfactory level, or, if this fails, to arrange for upgrading&#13;
by the public sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 90 -&#13;
The problem with this approach is that violations are&#13;
too widespread. In effect, any illegal subdivision is eligible to be&#13;
seized under Law 66. The practical result is that intervencion is&#13;
used only in extreme cases, which one former head of the Housing&#13;
Division defines as situations where the subdivider and buyers are&#13;
deadlocked over the continuation of lot payments versus the installation&#13;
of services. Between 1976 and 1978 only about 30 intervenciones were&#13;
carried out in Bogota. In addition the ICT has reportedly done little&#13;
to upgrade the pirate subdivisions it has taken over under Law 66.&#13;
The agency is paid to lack the administrative capacity to absorb this&#13;
responsibility.l/&#13;
Even if intervencion were an effective tool, most pirate&#13;
subdividers do not earn excess profits that could be diverted to raising&#13;
the quality of lots without increasing lot prices. The evidence presented&#13;
in Chapter III demonstrates that rates of return to pirate subdividers&#13;
are similar to those in Bogota's financial markets. Further, the lot price&#13;
analysis in Chapter V shows that, because buyers are willing to pay for&#13;
larger quantities of services, better-serviced pirate lots would be more&#13;
expensive. For these reasons stricter enforcement is not likely to succeed&#13;
in forcing pirate subdividers to install more services. For the most part&#13;
1/ As of the end of 1978, ICT had over 100 seized subdivisions under&#13;
its authority, about 80 percent of them located in Bogota.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 91 -&#13;
the pirate market successfuly and competitively supplies a relatively low-&#13;
quality good for which there is a high demand at a modest price and for&#13;
which there is no satisfactory alternative.&#13;
The qualifier to this conclusion is that a few pirate&#13;
subdividers do make very large profits. The top 25 percent of pirate&#13;
subdivisions in the sample earned a mean nominal rate of return of 166&#13;
percent annually, compared with a mean of 55 percent for all the&#13;
pirate subdivisions studied.I- Whether these high profits are due to&#13;
the subdividers' greater efficiency, to favorable timing, or to some&#13;
other factors, intervencion could in fact improve the quality of services&#13;
they provide. The proportion of pirate lots eligible for upgrading&#13;
through legal action against subdividers remains small, however; the most&#13;
profitable 25 percent of pirate subdivisions studied accounts for only 17.3&#13;
percent of the total supply of pirate lots in the sample.&#13;
The second approach, encouraging the private sector to&#13;
supply higher-quality lots through normas minimas, has produced mixed&#13;
results. According to the analysis in Chapter III the lower-income sub-&#13;
division business is lucrative enough to interest legitimate private developers.&#13;
Moreover, this study's finding that lot buyers are willing to pay for additional&#13;
services confirms that there is demand for higher-standard normas minimas lots&#13;
at higher prices. Private entrepreneurs demonstrated their interest in normas&#13;
minimas investment by submitting 253 normas minimas subdivision proposals&#13;
to the District Planning Deparment between 1973 and 1977. At the same time,&#13;
the District government has strongly restricted the supply of normas minimas&#13;
lots (see below) by granting few final permits. This restriction probably&#13;
accounts for the very high normas minimas profit rates--on average two to&#13;
three times higher than for pirate subidivisions in real terms--presented in&#13;
Chapter III.&#13;
1/ Figures based on "medium" rates of return. See Chapter IIJ.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 92 -&#13;
B. Restrictions on Normas Minimas&#13;
Between 1973 and 1977 the District Planning Department&#13;
(DAPD) granted final permits (resoluciones) to 28 normas minimas sub-&#13;
divisions averaging 10 -hectares in gross area each, as shown in Table&#13;
2&#13;
25.  Assuming 60 percent salable area and an average lot size of 80 m&#13;
the supply works out to about 4,200 legal lots annually over the five-&#13;
year period. Only four more normas minimas subdivisions were given&#13;
final approval between the beginning of 1978 and April 1979.&#13;
The approval process consists of two stages, a preliminary&#13;
review (consulta previa) which results in either rejection or clearance&#13;
to begin drafting formal plans, and a final design (proyecto general)&#13;
which results in either final approval (resolucion) or denial of the&#13;
proposal. Preliminary and final approval are awarded by the Public&#13;
Services Committee (Comite de Servicios Publicos), a group composed&#13;
of representatives from DAPD and the public utility companies plus&#13;
members of the City Council. If a resolucion is granted, the normas&#13;
minimas subdivider must still obtain permission from the Housing&#13;
Division of the Superintendencia Bancaria (permiso de venta) before&#13;
he can begin to sell lots.&#13;
DAPD records show that, of a total of 253 normas minimas&#13;
applications received over the 1973-77 period, 28 were given resoluciones&#13;
(11 percent), 97 were rejected (38 percent), and 128 were given preliminary&#13;
clearance only (51 percent). The three major reasons for rejection&#13;
related to location:    (1) the tract was outside the urban perimter;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 93 -&#13;
Table -25&#13;
NORMAS MINIMAS SUBDIVISION PROPOSALS SUBMITTED AND GIVEN&#13;
FINAL APPROVAL 1973 - 1977&#13;
Number of          Number of Final&#13;
Year                           Proposals          Permits (Resoluciones)-/&#13;
1973                               12                      1&#13;
74                              62                       9&#13;
75                              63                       6&#13;
76                              66                       5&#13;
77                              54                       7&#13;
2/&#13;
Total                             257-2                   28&#13;
/ Proposals receiving resoluciones in a given year were not necessarily&#13;
submitted in the same year.&#13;
2/&#13;
There is a discrepancy of four proposals in the DAPD report between this&#13;
figure and the sum of proposals rejected and accepted with and without&#13;
resolucion (253).&#13;
Source: Departamento Administrativo de Planeacion Distrital,&#13;
Aplicacion de las Normas Minimas de Urbanizacion y&#13;
de Servicios, Unidad de Mejoramiento y Coordinacion&#13;
de Barrios, Bogota, February 1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 94 -&#13;
(2) the tract was in a restricted development zone (e.g. a flood area);&#13;
and (3) the tract was in an area zoned for industrial use.&#13;
It is not clear, though, why 128 proposals, about half, received only&#13;
preliminary approval. It is very probable that some of these sub-&#13;
divisions -- no one knows how many -- have gone on the market illegally.&#13;
Interviews with public officials and private developers suggest the&#13;
following reasons why the supply of legal normas minimas lots has been&#13;
restricted:&#13;
Lack of land: According to the regulations, normas&#13;
minimas subdivisions may be built only on land with the proper&#13;
residential zoning classification ("high density"). DAPD reports that&#13;
over the last two years the supply of this type of land has practically&#13;
dried up in Bogota. Although the city's Planning Board (Junta de&#13;
Planeacion) may rezone land, so far it has not increased the supply of&#13;
high density areas. Apparently a significant number of normas minimas&#13;
proposals have been submitted for tracts on residential land having&#13;
the wrong zoning class; these have tended not to be rejected outright,&#13;
but to remain in limbo.&#13;
Delay in official approval: The normas minimas approval&#13;
process takes at least one year and often two, which is viewed as&#13;
excessive by most developers, especially when coupled with the uncertainty&#13;
over whether a resolucion will be granted. This gives the normas minimas&#13;
system the character of a lottery; subdividers lucky enough to win approval&#13;
are rewarded with permission to earn high profits. The odds of winning,&#13;
are low, however, and it appears that other types of investments.,, mostly&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 95 -&#13;
speculative but including the pirate subdivision business, currently&#13;
provide the opportunity for faster turnover of funds by investors.&#13;
Technical and financial objections: These have been&#13;
raised against the normas minimas   concept itself.  The Bogota Water&#13;
and Sewerage Company (EAAB), for example, reportedly has not been&#13;
comfortable with the lower-than-standard engineering specifications&#13;
for water supply and drainage under the normas minimas regulations.&#13;
The company feared that the infrastructure would be of inferior&#13;
quality and create excessive maintenance expenditures in the future.&#13;
Under current practice, water company clients pay installation and&#13;
connection fees, but all subsequent maintenance costs are borne by&#13;
EAAB.&#13;
Social opposition: Some argue that the normas minimns&#13;
concept implies giving official approval to substandard development&#13;
("legitimizing slums"), thus undermining the normal subdivision and&#13;
building codes. It has been difficult to promote the idea that&#13;
lowering standards through normas minimas produces significant benefits,&#13;
namely lower unit costs and hence wider affordability for lower-income&#13;
families, in addition to more efficient use of land and public resources&#13;
as a result of planned development. The normas minimas label has not&#13;
eliminated the fears that tend to segregate income groups in Bogota.&#13;
Opposition from neighboring land owners and residents may have&#13;
defeated several normas minimas subdivision proposals, based on the&#13;
belief that the presence of a normas minimas subdivision would lower&#13;
property values and reduce neighborhood quality.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 96 -&#13;
C. Policy Conclusions&#13;
This study finds that there is demand in Bogota for residential&#13;
lots at a variety of quality and price levels. While the biggest supply&#13;
gap is in higher-quality lots, there remains a large segment of&#13;
families who cannot afford lots with adequate service levels. These&#13;
families will continue to buy poorly serviced pirate lots as long as&#13;
the supply can be maintained at prices well below those in the normas&#13;
minimas market.&#13;
Since most pirate subdividers do not earn excess profits,&#13;
stronger legal action to force them to upgrade services would be&#13;
effective on only a small proportion of the pirate lot market. A&#13;
better approach to increasing the supply of well-serviced lots would&#13;
be for the District government to allow more normas minimas sub-&#13;
divisions to be developed. While normas minimas may replace a portion&#13;
of the pirate market, it will not eliminate pirate subdivisions&#13;
entirely. The extent of the inroads normas minimas can make depends&#13;
on the degree to which the supply restrictions are lessened and on&#13;
how low the service standards--and hence lot prices--can be set. The&#13;
price and income figures cited in Chapter I suggest that up to three&#13;
quarters of pirate lot buyers might be able to afford normas minimas&#13;
lots if they were available.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 97 -&#13;
If normas minimas subdividers make high profits selling&#13;
better-serviced lots, why don't more pirate subdividers mimic them by&#13;
developing higher-quality illegal subdivisions? One possible explanation&#13;
is that pirate subdividers cannot obtain connections to the public&#13;
service networks. Both the Bogota Water and Sewerage Company (EEAB)&#13;
and the Bogota Electric Power Company (EEEB) require subdividers to&#13;
have official approval before they allow connections to be made.&#13;
This is circumvented only in cases where established illegal subdivisions&#13;
are "regularized." Another reason pirate subdividers may be unable&#13;
to supply unauthorized duplicates of the normas minimas product is&#13;
that they cannot offer legal tenure. While the lack of legal documents&#13;
does not seem to impede the sale and resale of pirate lots, it may be&#13;
a problem for buyers willing to pay higher prices for normas minimas&#13;
lots.&#13;
In summary, pirate subdividers successfully fill the&#13;
demand for modestly-priced, low-quality residential lots in Bogota.&#13;
The demand for modestly-priced, adequately-serviced, and legal lots is&#13;
largely unsatisfied. The normas minimas regulations, designed to permit&#13;
the private sector to supply higher-quality lots, are being applied very&#13;
restrictively, resulting in excess profits to the few normas minimas&#13;
subdividers able to obtain permits.&#13;
Removing the restrictions on normas minimas development&#13;
could generate significant benefits. The market for legal, serviced lots&#13;
would become more competitive, the supply of higher-quality lots would&#13;
rise, and lot prices would drop. Buyers would have a wider choice of lots.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- .9,8 -&#13;
An increase in the amount of normas minimas development would probably&#13;
give greater numbers of families adesiitat-ji&amp;o electricity,&#13;
and drainage services, as well as security of tJengrte.' Expanision of&#13;
normas minimas' may also reduce the cost's o-f upoad'ing' po6`r1jyplanned-&#13;
and serviced subdivisionrs, 'bring imiore la-nd'developmentf int`6 hartiony&#13;
with local land use riegulatiobns and infds'trulcturie fl3ang', "and mitigate&#13;
the environmental probli4ms associated'with"'un'ohfr'oitdbl'd'evel-opTiieTit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 99 -&#13;
Appendix I&#13;
List of Variables in Superintendencia Bancaria&#13;
Pirate Subdivision Survey, 1977&#13;
(coded from questionnaires)&#13;
A.  Subdivision Variables&#13;
1. Name of subdivision&#13;
2. Name of DANE (census) barrio of subdivision&#13;
3. ID number of DANE barrio (1973 codes)&#13;
4. Date of initiation of physical works&#13;
5. Number of lots&#13;
6. Date of DAPD approval, if any&#13;
7. Date of Superintendencia Bancaria approval, if any&#13;
8. Size of tract (m )&#13;
9. Date of acquisition of tract&#13;
10. Date of tract acquisition document&#13;
11. Price of tract&#13;
12. Value of installments (up to five) for tract&#13;
13. Dates of installments&#13;
14. Interest rate on tract installments&#13;
15. Number of bus routes within ten minutes walk&#13;
16. Existence of neighboring subdivision with water net-&#13;
work&#13;
17. Subdivision inside or outside urban perimeter?&#13;
18. Subdivision above or below water company elevation&#13;
limit?&#13;
19. If above, source of water supply&#13;
20. For the following types of infrastructure: sewer,&#13;
water pipes, stand pipes, electricity, telephone,&#13;
streets, sidewalks, and curbs&#13;
(a) quantity installed&#13;
(b) cost of installation&#13;
(c) source of financing&#13;
(d) date of installation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 100 -&#13;
21.  Other infrastructure installed:   type, cost, fin-&#13;
ancing, date&#13;
22. Usable (salable) area of subdivision (m )&#13;
23.  Communal area (m )&#13;
24. Green zones (m2)&#13;
25. Street area (m2)&#13;
26. Expenditure on professional services&#13;
27. Expenditure on publicity&#13;
28. Expenditure on administration&#13;
29. Other expenditures: type, value&#13;
30. Date of sale of first lot&#13;
31. Months taken to sell 50 percent of lots&#13;
32. Months taken to sell 90 percent of lots&#13;
33. Type of publicity used, if any, to sell lots&#13;
34. Commissionists' fees, if any, paid per lot&#13;
35. Number of buyers to date&#13;
36. Number of buyers behind in payments; number&#13;
behind less and more than 6 months&#13;
37. Value of outstanding payments&#13;
38. Value of outstanding late payments&#13;
39.  Number of legal actions initiated by buyers&#13;
against subdivider&#13;
40. Number of legal actions initiated by subdivider&#13;
against buyers&#13;
41. Number of lots sold to date.&#13;
B.   Lot variables (for lots sold)&#13;
1. Date of sale&#13;
2.  Area (m2)&#13;
3. Type of sale and property documents&#13;
4. Price&#13;
5. Value of down payment&#13;
6. Term of balance (months)&#13;
7. Value of monthly installments&#13;
8. Value of installments paid to date&#13;
9. Does original buyer live on lot?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 101 -&#13;
Appendix II&#13;
Calculation of Internal Rates of Return for Subdivisions&#13;
I. Assumptions in Alternative IRR Calculations&#13;
A. Basic Assumptions&#13;
1) All payments for lots are made on time, and all lots are fully&#13;
paid for.&#13;
2) If no infrastructure installation date is given (missing ob-&#13;
servation) it is assumed to occur on the date of sale of the&#13;
first lot.&#13;
3) Overhead costs are assumed to occur at the initiation date.&#13;
4)   If the sale date of the lot is missing, it is assumed to be&#13;
the date of sale of the first lot.&#13;
5) All cost and price figures are taken as is.&#13;
6) All lots in the subdivision are sold.&#13;
7)  Lots not having individual sale data (unsold at time of survey)&#13;
are assumed sold at the average size and price (in 1977 pesos)&#13;
and on the last date of sale among the lots with data.&#13;
B. Payment Default Assumptions&#13;
1) Items 2 through 7 in A above.&#13;
2) A proportion of defaulting lot buyers is given per subdivision&#13;
in the data; this incidence of default is assumed to occur random-&#13;
ly over the period of lot sales; subdividers are assumed to receive&#13;
only down payments for defaulting lots.&#13;
C. Favorable Assumptions&#13;
1) All items in A above except 5.&#13;
2) Item 5 is modified in that the three overhead cost types -- pro-&#13;
fessional services, publicity, and administration -- are limited&#13;
in value to one standard deviation above the means for overhead&#13;
in normas minimas subdivisions.&#13;
II. Method for Calculating Internal Rates of Return&#13;
A. Using the expenditure and revenue figures and dates, a net cash flow&#13;
in monthly intervals is assembled for each subdivision.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 102 -&#13;
B. The cash flow is summed to check whether the present value is pos-&#13;
itive at a zero discount rate. If it is negative, the value is stored&#13;
and work begins on the next subdivision. If it is positive, the&#13;
process,,,continues.&#13;
C. A series of simple iterative linear algebra calculations are performed&#13;
to estimate the internal rate of return. The routine is based on the&#13;
inverse relationship between the discount rate and the presenp value&#13;
in any "well-behaved" cash flow.   This is shown in   the figure Ae)ow.&#13;
The steps are:&#13;
1)  Choose an arbitrary discount rate (R1) as a starting point&#13;
2) Compute the present value of the cash flow at this discount&#13;
rate (PVI)&#13;
3) Calculate the slope of line PVoA given PVO, PV1, and R1.&#13;
4) Compute a new discount rate (R2) given PVO and the slope of&#13;
PVOA.&#13;
5) Calculate the new present value (PV2) given R2.&#13;
PV0&#13;
blX&#13;
PV1,         A&#13;
Present&#13;
value    P                \    B&#13;
PS2&#13;
PV   ,           \          "     \  C        /present value function (PV as&#13;
3                                                  discount rate varies)&#13;
M~~~~~~~&#13;
Ri       R2               R3          R4      IRR&#13;
Discount rate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 103&#13;
6)  Determine the slope of line AB and use it to compute the new&#13;
intercept bl.&#13;
7)  Given the slope of AB and bl, obtain R3.&#13;
8)  Continue until PVn approaches zero within a given margin&#13;
(in this case + 500 pesos)&#13;
D.  Since the internal rate of return is the discount rate at which the&#13;
present value equals zero, the Rn that causes the PVn to fall within&#13;
the desired interval around zero is stored.&#13;
E.  A "badly-behaved" cash flow -- one with no unique IRR -- is indicated&#13;
by the appearance of a negative PVn or a positive slope in the course&#13;
of an iteration. If this happens the calculations are stopped and a&#13;
new subdivision is started.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 104 -&#13;
Appendix III&#13;
Hedonic Prices in Competitive Markets&#13;
A hedonic price index is an equation in which the price of a good&#13;
or product is regressed on a vector of quantities of its attributes. As&#13;
Rosen (1974) describes it,&#13;
Each product has a quoted market price&#13;
and is also associated with a fixed value&#13;
of the vector z [of quantities of attributes3,&#13;
so that products markets implicitly reveal&#13;
a function p(z)= p(z ,Z    ..Zn) relating&#13;
prices and characteristics. This function&#13;
is the buyer's (and seller's) equivalent of&#13;
a hedonic price regression, obtained from&#13;
shopping around... (p. 37)&#13;
The hedonic price index describes behavior in competitive markets in short-&#13;
run equilibrium. The key assumptions underlying the model are:&#13;
- buyers and sellers behave in economically rational&#13;
ways, maximizing utility and profit, respectively.&#13;
- consumers have good information on the available&#13;
choices among variants of the generic good with&#13;
different characteristics and different prices.&#13;
- a sufficiently large number of products with dif-&#13;
ferent attributes is available so that the range&#13;
of choice among combinations is virtually continuous.&#13;
In Figures A-1 to A-5 the relationships between prices and quantities&#13;
are shown graphically (after Rosen). The diagrams demonstrate how the hedonic&#13;
price model describes "a space in which both buyers and seller locate" and&#13;
how the price function is reached through the equalization of quantities supplied&#13;
and demanded of each attribute.&#13;
Figure A-1 shows a traditional budget line with the quantity of&#13;
attribute z plotted against the quantity of all other goods (or income).&#13;
The budget line is the opportunity set available to consumers as the quantity&#13;
of z varies. Figure A-2 depicts the same space but with the Y axis flipped&#13;
over to measure total expenditure on attribute z 1    Buyer B purchases a pro-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 105 -&#13;
HEDONIC PRICES AND COMPETITIVE EQUILIBRIUM&#13;
Y&#13;
(all other         A&#13;
goods or&#13;
income)                        bid function (indifference curve)&#13;
budget line P(zl,z2*, * . . z&#13;
n&#13;
Fig. A-1                          \&#13;
(                            I            zl (quantity of attribute zl)&#13;
Flip over Y axis&#13;
p1z1                                      DEMAND SIDE&#13;
B purchases a product&#13;
(expenditure           I                           containing more of&#13;
on attri-                                         attribute z  than A does.&#13;
bute z )&#13;
demand price&#13;
line             A&#13;
amount of income foregone by A&#13;
in purchasing quantity q1 of z&#13;
Fig. A-2 &#13;
qI        q2    z1&#13;
I         I&#13;
l         l&#13;
I 0  D         SUPPLY SIDE&#13;
p1 1             I         I   /            D has a comparative advan-&#13;
iso-profit curve                   tage over C in producing&#13;
(amount of             I          I                larger quantities of z )&#13;
firm's                 I   C&#13;
resources              I&#13;
spent in&#13;
producing              I         supply-price line&#13;
z)&#13;
/  I          I&#13;
Fig. A-3  /&#13;
z&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 106-&#13;
HEDONIC PRICES AND COMPETITIVE EQUILIBRIUM&#13;
(cont'd)&#13;
p1 1                             D         MARKET-CLEARING JOINT ENVELOPE&#13;
/ ~~implicit price function--&#13;
//  B  maximum price obtainable&#13;
in the market for different&#13;
c   -                 models with varying amounts&#13;
of attribute z1.&#13;
Fig. A-4   /&#13;
'  .  I    I   zi&#13;
derivative of iso-profit curve&#13;
P1           \  |  /    \l       &lt;        (supply curve)&#13;
trace of short-run equilibrium&#13;
points (demand=supply)&#13;
derivative of indifference&#13;
curve (compensated demand&#13;
curve)&#13;
Al&#13;
Fig.  A-5   _ _ _ _ _  _ _ _ _  _ _ _&#13;
z&#13;
1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 107 -&#13;
duct containing more of attribute z than buyer A. He may do this because&#13;
he has a different utility function, a different income, or both. In&#13;
Figure A-3 the same price line is shown, with iso-profit curves for two&#13;
producers, C and D. The price line is a supply-price, and producer D&#13;
has a comparative advantage, because of his technology and cost conditions,&#13;
in producing larger quantities of z than producer C.&#13;
Figure A-4 shows the buyers' and sellers' indifference curves&#13;
together and all tangent to the price line. The latter is the implicit&#13;
price function -- the hedonic price -- in equilibrium. The price line is&#13;
essentially a joint envelope created by one group of bid function and another of&#13;
offer functions.&#13;
In Figure A-5 the relationships are depicted in price-quantity rather&#13;
than expenditure - quantity space. The bid functions are transformed into&#13;
compensated demand curves (from which the income effect has been removed) and&#13;
the iso-profit curves into short-run supply or marginal cost curves.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 108 -&#13;
APPENDIX IV&#13;
Tables A6 through All&#13;
HEDONIC PRICE INDEXES WITH INFRASTRUCTURE EXPENDITURES&#13;
Coefficients for Subsamples&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 109 -&#13;
Table A6&#13;
LINEAR HEDONIC PRICE INDEX WITH INFRASTRUCTURE EXPENDITURE&#13;
CTefficients -or Subsarnles:&#13;
(Observations are Subdivisions)&#13;
Dependent Variable = Average Lot Price per Subdivision in 100s&#13;
(All prices in 1976 Col $)&#13;
All          Tract Acquisition     Inside Urban      Profitable     Profitable In-&#13;
Jariable    Subdivisions       1970 or After         Perimeter      Subdivisions     side Perimeter&#13;
kLSZ             .156                 .056                .834             .114             .849&#13;
)IST          -7.76                -2.97              -13.18            -6.31           -15.96&#13;
rIME            4.73                 5.54                9.03            6.18             9.45&#13;
SNW          212.25               171.81              239.03           198.79           236.16&#13;
WEST         100.78                 99.58               90.24          111.21            97.59&#13;
OPLOT           -.173                 .148               -.089           -.287            -.140&#13;
STPLOT          -.053                 .236               -.016             .096             .076&#13;
srM            43.29                45.95               53.36           63.82            62.02&#13;
rRPM2            .613                1.52                 .530             .263             .514&#13;
PROL             .0092                .013                .0059            .010             .0054&#13;
PUBL             .0542                .041                .059             .037             .055&#13;
ADML             .0024                .0040               .0024            .0023            .0030&#13;
PERIM          52.68                                                    63.07&#13;
APDP           -1.84                -3.18                -2.05          -1.62            -1.55&#13;
INPLOT           .0091                .0066               .0085            .0099            .0080&#13;
BUYPLOT          .0041                .0039               .0039            .0036&#13;
Constant      144.23               117.74               85.78           94.92            92.04&#13;
R2               .561                 .623                .586             .539             .578&#13;
R2               .508                 .550                .529             .477             .523&#13;
Std. Error&#13;
of Est.       141.30               140.18              143.40          136.37           145.14&#13;
Number of&#13;
Observations   (145)                (87)                (118)           (127)            (113)&#13;
Note: Underlined coefficients are significant at the two-tail .05 level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 110 -&#13;
Table A7&#13;
LINEAR. HEDONIC PRICE INDEX WITH-T WRASTRUCTURE EXPENDITURE&#13;
Coefficients for Subsamples:&#13;
(Observations are Subdivisions)         2&#13;
Dependent Variable = Average Lot Price per m per Subdivision&#13;
(All prices in 1976 Col $)&#13;
All          Tract Acquisition    Inside Urban      Profitable      Profitable In-&#13;
Variable     Subdivisions      1970 or After         Perimeter      Subdivisions    side Perimeter&#13;
ALSZ            -.239               -.194               -.859            -.321            -.954&#13;
DIST           -8.80               -5.71              -11.39            -8.21          -12.76&#13;
TIME           10.81               16.91               10.29            11.86           11.33&#13;
NNW           135.28              122.02              188.14           126.66          179.25&#13;
WEST           88.51               94.45               96.43            89.09           93.69&#13;
OPLOT           -.159               -.124                .092            -.207             .011&#13;
STPLOT           .147                 .197               .083             .209             .195&#13;
NM             81.99               81.10               51.42           102.77           72.91&#13;
TRPM2            .380                 .856               .297             .234             .305&#13;
PROM             .684               2.19                 .453             .745             .385&#13;
PUBM            3.99                1.38                3.68             2.71            3.12&#13;
ADMM             .433                 .506               .499             .434             .567&#13;
PERIM          27.96                                                    27.32&#13;
APDP           -1.60               -2.73               -1.68            -1.28           -1.12&#13;
INPM2            .813                 .720               .768             .847            .542&#13;
BUYPM2           .164                 .305               .151             .137&#13;
Constant       72.48              -86.49              218.79            50.14          214.13&#13;
R2               .675                 .726               .664             .670             .672&#13;
2               .636                 .672               .618             .625             .629&#13;
Std. Error&#13;
of Est.       109.80              109.39              112.02           108.41          110.69&#13;
Number of&#13;
Observations   (145)                 (87)               (118)            (127)            (113)&#13;
Note:  Underlined coefficients are significant at the two-tail .05 level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 111-&#13;
Table A8&#13;
LINEAR HEDONIC PRICE INDEX WITH 'rELAS5fUCTURE EXPENDITURE&#13;
Coefficients for Subsamples:&#13;
(Observations are Subdivisions)&#13;
Coefficients for Individual Infrastructure Expenditures:&#13;
Sewer, Water, Electricitv. Streets&#13;
(These variables replace INPLOT and INPM2 in preceding tables;&#13;
all other variables remain the same, all prices in 1976 Col $)&#13;
All       Tract Acquisition   Inside Urban    Profitable   Profitable In-&#13;
Variable  Subdivisions     1970 or After       Perimeter   Subdivisions   side Perimeter&#13;
Snecifica-   SEWLT          .0256             .0257            .0160         .0373            .017&#13;
tion A&#13;
Dependet A   WATLT          .0018           -.0045            -.0022         .0002          -.0005&#13;
Dependent&#13;
Variable:     ELELT         .0209             .0377             .0163        .0152            .012&#13;
Average lot   STRLT        -.0012            -.0280             .0051        .0028            .0059&#13;
price in&#13;
loos of&#13;
Col $        Constant     17.17             99.13            84.14        108.04.          85.97&#13;
R2             .569             .665              .582         .561             .576&#13;
R              .506              .583             .511          .488            .505&#13;
Std. Error&#13;
of Est.     141.61           135.05            146.33       134.89           147.82&#13;
Specifica-   SEWM2         1.87              2.45             1.72          2.91            2.44&#13;
tion B       WATM2         -.579           -1.87             -1.03         -.415            -.409&#13;
Dependent&#13;
Variable:    ELEI2        1.74              3.06             1.17           .755             .086&#13;
Average lot   STRP12        .444            -1.12               .373         .854             .435&#13;
p5ice per&#13;
m- in Col $&#13;
Constant     88.03          -115.97            219.34        42.58           204.74&#13;
R              .671             .737              .659         .675             .680&#13;
R              .623             .673              .601          .621            .627&#13;
Std. Error&#13;
of Est.     111.8            109.34            114.46       109.11           111.02&#13;
Number of&#13;
Observations (145)              (87)             (118)         (127)          (113)&#13;
Note:  Underlined coefficients are significant at the two-tail .05 level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A9&#13;
IINEAR ItEDONIC I'RICE INDEX WETII INFRASTRPJCCURE EXPENDITURE&#13;
Coefficients for Subsamples:&#13;
Observations are tots&#13;
Dependent Variable = Total lot Price in tOOs&#13;
(All prices in 1976 Cot$)&#13;
Variable                  All Lots                      Profitable Subdivisions      Inside Urban Perimeter         Pirate Subdivisions&#13;
Infra-                      Infra-                       Infra-                        Infra-&#13;
infra-      struettire      inifra-    structtire         Infra-     struicture       iifra-      structure&#13;
Aggregate     structure     Before or       structure    Before or       struicture   Before or      structure     Before or&#13;
Model         Ever        After Sale        Ever      After Sale         Ever       After Sale       Ever        After SaLe&#13;
LSZ            .156          .111          .111           .108          .112            .931         .935           .094          .089&#13;
l.YS          4.73          4.51         4.51           4.46           4.34           10.03         9.94           3.95          4.58&#13;
PCDP         -1.84          -.847        - .847         -.622          -.618          -1.09        -1.09           -.908         -.906&#13;
NM           43.29         17.09        17.09          25.89         20.12            27.73        27.46&#13;
NNW         212.25        153.32       153.32          147.56        150.35          138.54       138.52         153.26        146.32&#13;
WEST        100.78        133.88        133.88         121.04        124.17          121.69       121.89         151.92        158.81&#13;
TRI'M2         .613          .015         .0152           .039          .032            .042         .042          -.0014        - .014&#13;
DrST         -7.76         -7.58        -7.58          -7.79         -7.96            -3.51        -3.54          -7.43         -8.12&#13;
PROL           .0092         .0031        .0031          .0009          .0007           .0072        .0074         -.0009        -.0034&#13;
PIIRL          .0542         .081         .081           .079           .082            .067         .068           .113          .115&#13;
ADMIl          .0024         .0035         .0035          .0032         .0031           .0009        .0009          .0033         .0035&#13;
INPLOT(before) .0091         .0071        .0071           .0091        .0081            .0071        .0068          .0068         .0096&#13;
INPl'LT(after)                             .0071                        *0110                        .0074                        .0035&#13;
Constant    144.23        -56.39       -56.34          -60.76        -52.03         -571.92      -566.25         -15.26        -49.18&#13;
R2             .561          .519          .519           .536          .537           .543          .543           .441          .446&#13;
R7             .508          .516         .516           .533           .534            .540         .540          /,636          .441&#13;
Std. Error&#13;
of Est.     141.30        119.01       119.03          117.46        117.37          115.08       115.10         127.59        127.07&#13;
Ntmiber of&#13;
Observatiotis  (145)      (2,399)       (2,3991         (2,226)       (2,226)         (2,172)      (2,172)        (1,477)       (1,477)&#13;
Note:  Ihnderlinied coefficients are significant nt the two-Lail .05 level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 113 -&#13;
Table A10&#13;
LINEAR nZDONIC PRICE INDEY. WITH INFRASTRUCTURE EXPENDITURB&#13;
Coefficients for Stubsamples:&#13;
Observations are Lots&#13;
Dependent Variable - Lot Price per M&#13;
(All prices in 1976 Col$)&#13;
Variable                 All Lots                     Profitable Subdivisions        Inside Urban Perimeter        Pirate Subdivisions&#13;
Infra-                        Infra-                       Infra-                        Infra-&#13;
Infra-     structure         Infra-      structure        Infra-      structure         Infra-      structure&#13;
Aggregate      structure    Before otr     structure     Before or       structure     Before or      structure     Before or&#13;
Model          Ever       After Sale       Ever        After Sale         Ever       After Sale       Ever        After Sale&#13;
SZ            -.239         -.217        -.212           -.245         -.233           -.703        -.698           -.159         -.159&#13;
,YS          10.81         14.07        13.50           14.16         13.71           13.54        13.42           12.58         12.48&#13;
CDP          -1.60          -.846        -.846           -.614         -.604           -.930        -.932           -.745         -.745&#13;
M            81.99         80.71        78.23           80.42         63.04           46.81        46.61&#13;
'NW         135.28        143.42       144.31          139.32        145.29          144.56       144.40          140.86        141.78&#13;
EST          88.51        143.27       145.00          135.63        145.69          148.04       148.36          175.85        174.77&#13;
'RPH2          .380          .144         .141            .155          .135            .089         .089            .122          .125&#13;
IST         -8.80          -9.68        -9.63          -9.65         -10.18           -2.61        -2.67          -12.04        -11.92&#13;
'801           .684         1.02         1.08             .729          .693            .488          .507           .114          .159&#13;
UBM          3.99            .300         .761           .303           .968           2.43         2.52           8.43           8.38&#13;
D1MM           .433          .216         .211            .133          .087            .122          .121           .457          .456&#13;
NPM2(before)   .813          .393         .184            .679          .389            .349          .302           .255          .194&#13;
NPH2(after)                               .565                         1.18                          .386                          .298&#13;
onetant      72.48          -.693.16     -.655.09        -.706.46      -672.89         -.651.08     -.642.59        -.583.94      -578.48&#13;
2              .675          .672         .673           .680           .686            .650         .650            .649          .649&#13;
?              ..636         .670         .672            .679          .684            .648         .648            .646          .646&#13;
td. Error&#13;
f Est.     109.80         107.91       107.70         106.23         105.39          106.61       106.63         106.57         106.59&#13;
'umber of&#13;
bservations   (145)        (2,399)      (2,399)         (2,226)       (2,226)         (2,172)      (2,172)         (1,477)       (1,477)&#13;
ote: Underlined coefficients are significant at the two-tail .05 level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table All&#13;
LINEAR HEDONIC PRICE INDEX %nTH INFRASTRUCTURE EXPENDITURE&#13;
Coefficients for Subsaisples:&#13;
Observations are Lots&#13;
Coefficients for Individual Infrastructure Types: Sewer, Water, Electricity, Streets&#13;
(These variables replace INPLOT and INPM2 in preceding tables; all other variables remain the same; all&#13;
prices in 1976 Col$)&#13;
Dependent Variable - Total Lot Price in lOOs&#13;
Variata,e                       All Lots                               Profitable Subdivisions                  inside Urban Perimeter                   Pirate Subdivisions&#13;
Irfra-          Infrastructure Before    Infra-         Infrastructure Before     Infra-      Infrastructure Before     InfrS-      Infrastructure  Before&#13;
Aggregate   structure             or After           strLcture             *r After          etructure           or After           rtructure         or After&#13;
M,.del      Ever                  Sale               Ever                  Sale              Ever                Sale               Ever              Sale&#13;
S"'ELT        .0256       .0123          .0153          .008Q      .019           .022          .024       .0057        .0077          .0088     .0112       .0126           .0101&#13;
IWATLT        .0018       .0064          .0066         -.0009      .0038          .0003        -.0026      .019         .021           .0013      .0095       0106           .0035&#13;
ELECLT        .0209       .0035          .0106          .0038      .0090          .013          .0106      .0038        .013           .0041     -.0093      .005          -.0102&#13;
STaLT        -.0012       .0061          .0031          .0113      .0059          .0038         .013       ,0055        .0027         ,0104       .012t      .0092           .0108&#13;
Coastant    17.17      -68.07                  -40.79           -74.30                  -64.36         -541.01                -529.07          -85.55               -81.09&#13;
2 2           .569        .519                    .522             .538                     .541           .544                   .547            .445                 .449&#13;
RZ2           .506        .517                    .519             .535                     .537           .541                   .543            .440                 .442&#13;
Std. Error&#13;
of Est.    141.61      118.97                  118.72           117.25                   116.95         115.02                 114.76          127.17               126.95&#13;
NSuber cf&#13;
Observations  (145)      (2,399)               (2.399)          (2,226)                  (2,226)        (2,172)                (2,172)         (1,477)              (1.477)&#13;
Specification J: Dependent Variable - Lot Price per M2&#13;
1.17       -1.24           -1.49          -.823      -.541          -.995          1.07      -.536        -.735           .0042     -.178       -.244            .653&#13;
'iA.T.2      -.579        .532            .141          .357       .322          -.489           .270       .421        .805          -.866       .883       1,18           -.348&#13;
ZZ-{2        1.74        1.19           1.15           1.03       1.76           1.41          1.73        .505        1.04            .485     -1.14       -1.19          -1.34&#13;
STP-M2        .444        .725           .637          1.25        .831           ,798          1.56       .649         .505          1.05       1.17         .745          1.67&#13;
Constant    88.03      -653.78                -630.82          -655.7                   -668.81        -661.87                -654.35         -624.35               -608.51&#13;
R2           .671          .678                   .680             .684                     .691           .652                   .654            .652                  .655&#13;
R2            .623         .676                   .677             .682                     .688            .650                  .651            .649                  .651&#13;
Std. Error&#13;
of Eat.    111.8       107.00                  106.75           105.62                   104.65         106.40                 106.25          106.20                105.89&#13;
lcber of&#13;
Observations  (145)    (2,399)                 (2,399)          (2,226)                  (2.226)        (2,172)                (2.172)         (1,477)               (1,477)&#13;
Noce: Underlined coefficients are significant at the two-tail .05 level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 115 -&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
Bender, Stephen A. "Low-Income Housing Development in Bogota," Rice&#13;
University Studies, Issues in Income Distribution, Houston, Texas,&#13;
Vol. 61, No. 4, Fall 1975.&#13;
Blaesser, Brian. The Private Market and the Process of Lower Income&#13;
Urbanization in Colombia: The Pirate Housing Submarket of Medellin.&#13;
Master's Thesis, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Department&#13;
of Urban Studies and Planning, June 1979.&#13;
Borrero, Oscar and Sonia Sanchez. Mercadeo de Tierras en Barrios&#13;
Clandestinos de Bogota, Bogota: Departamento Administrativo de&#13;
Planeacion Distrital, April 1973.&#13;
Departamento Administrativo de Planeacion Distrital. Aplicacion de las&#13;
Normas Minimas de Urbanizacion y de Servicios. Bogota: Unidad de&#13;
Mejoramiento y Coordinacion de Barrios, February 1978.&#13;
Doebele, William A. The Private Market and Low-Income Urbanization in&#13;
Developing Countries: The "Pirate" Subdivisions of Bogota.&#13;
Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Department of City and&#13;
Regional Planning, Discussion Paper No. D75-11, October 1975.&#13;
Fuentes, Alfredo L. and Rodrigo Losada. "Implicaciones Socio-Economicas&#13;
de la Ilegalidad en la Tenencia de la Tierra Urbana en Colombia,"&#13;
Coyuntura Economica, Vol. VIII, No. 1, April 1978.&#13;
Gauhan, Timothy 0. Some Economic and Political Characteristics of&#13;
Low-Income Housing Market in Bogota, Colombia and Their Implications&#13;
for Public Policy Alternatives. Rice University, Program of&#13;
Development Studies, Paper No. 64, Spring 1975.&#13;
Griliches, Zvi, ed. Price Indexes and Quality Change. Cambridge,&#13;
Massachusetts: Harvard University Press, 1971.&#13;
Lopez Trujillo, Anibal and Fernando Jimenez Mantilla. El Estado de la&#13;
Actividad de Vivienda en Bogota; mimeo, source and date unknown,&#13;
16 pages.&#13;
Losada Lora, Rodrigo and Hernando Gomez Buendia. La Tierra en el Mercado&#13;
Pirata de Bogota. Bogota: FEDESARROLLO, June 1976.&#13;
McCallum, David. "Land Values in Bogota, Colombia," Land Economics,&#13;
Vol. 82, No. 1, August 1974.&#13;
Nelson, Joan M.  Public Housing, Illegal Settlements, and the Growth of&#13;
Colombia's Cities. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Agency for International&#13;
Development, December 1973.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 116 -&#13;
Paredes, Luis Ricardo and Luis Guillermo Martinez. Alternativa para la&#13;
Solucion del-Problema de;la'Vivienda para Grupos2'de Bajos Ingresos:&#13;
El, Sectox Prrivado Tradicional y las Normas: MiMnimas.  Docum:ent prepared&#13;
for INTERHABITAT 1977, VI Inter-American Conference on Housing,&#13;
Medellin, Colombia, November 1977.&#13;
Rosen,, Sherwin. '!'Hedonic Prices and Implicit Majrket:  Product,Diffetentia-&#13;
tion in Pure Compet'ition," Journal,of Politifcaal-'Eco'ibmy-, Vol. 82, No. 1&#13;
January 1974.                               II&#13;
Smith, Barton,, and J.M. Campbell, Jr.  Aggregation.. Bd.as.-an'd the^Demand for&#13;
Housting;. Paper presented at; the- annual meetingS'of the, Econometric&#13;
Society, Atlantic City, New Jersey, September 19176.&#13;
Valenzuela,, Jaime and George Vernez.  La'Actividad-Co-nstruetora Popular:&#13;
Ana.-i'sis, Gener,a-l y Elementos-.para una PoilitiDaL'ade Ap'o .j fDocumento !I,&#13;
Departamento.Nacional d&amp;'Planeacion, Bogota-:' hVrifl 1972.&#13;
Vernez ,George.-,Bogota'sJwPira,te Settlements: -An-Oppqrtunity-for&#13;
Metropol1itan:Develo,pment..' Behk!eley, CAlifbrni1'; i8T- h Unlv!rsity: of&#13;
Calif odnia,; -Doctoral -Dissertation; ;April 1973 '(a).&#13;
Vernez, George. Pirate Settlements, Housing Construction by Incremental&#13;
Dev,elopment, and Low-Incbmex'Hbusing4Policies' in Bogota, .Colombia.&#13;
NewO York: 'The New;Y'ork' City-Rand Institut6,4 ay-197Z3?(b.).'&#13;
Villamizar, Rodrigo. Land Prices in Bogota Between 1955 and 1978: A&#13;
Descriptive,Analysis. 'Paper ,prepared for World-)"Eak - CCRP "City Study"&#13;
Workshop,ipBogota,'&gt;Colonb,ia,_July '197-9.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
RECENT PAPERS IN THIS SERIES&#13;
No.                      TITLE OF PAPER                                AUTHOR&#13;
419       Employment Patterns and Income Growth:                    J. Stern&#13;
An Application of Input-Output Analysis                   J. Lewis&#13;
420       The Evaluation of Human Capital in Malawi                 S. Heyneman&#13;
421       A Conceptual Approach to the Analysis of External         R. Aliber&#13;
Debt of the Developing Countries&#13;
422       Estimating Total Factor Productivity Growth in            A. Krueger&#13;
a Developing Country              .                       B. Tuncer&#13;
423       Rethinking Artisanal Fisheries Development:               D. Emmerson&#13;
Western Concepts, Asian Experience                        (consultant)&#13;
424       Transition toward More Rapid and Labor-Intensive          B. de Vries&#13;
Industrial Development: The Case of the Philippines&#13;
425       Britain's Pattern of Specialization in Manufactured       V. Cable&#13;
Goods with Developing Countries and Trade Protection      I. Rebelo&#13;
426       Worker Adjustment to Liberalized Trade:    Costs and      G. Glenday&#13;
Assistance Policies                                       G. Jenkins&#13;
J. Evans&#13;
427       On the Political Economy of Protection in Germany         H. Glismann&#13;
F. Weiss&#13;
428        Italian Commercial Policies in the 1970s                 E. Grilli&#13;
429       Effects of Non-Tariff Barriers to Trade on Prices,        C. Hamilton&#13;
Employment, and Imports: The Case of the Swedish&#13;
Textile and Clothing Industry&#13;
430       Output and Employment Changes in a "Trade Sensitive"      J. Mutti&#13;
Sector:  Adjustment in the U.S. Footwear Industry         M. Bale&#13;
431       The Political Economy of Protection in Belgium            P. Tharakan&#13;
432       European Community Protection Against Manufactured        E. Verrydt&#13;
Imports from Developing Countries:   A Case Study         J. IWaelbroeck&#13;
in the Political Economy of Protection&#13;
433       Agrarian Reforms in Developing Rural Economies             A. Braverman&#13;
Characterized by In,terlinked Credit and Tenancy           T.N. Srinivasan&#13;
Markets                                                    (consultant)&#13;
434       How Segmented is the Bogota Labour Market?                 G. Fields (consultant)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
JLC l1G38815    57 W67 noD  A&#13;
C.3&#13;
C.3 oll, Alan-&#13;
pirate susdi   Sions and the&#13;
market for residential lo&#13;
i-n Boqota.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554988">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1980/10/1554988/pirate-subdivisions-market-residential-lots-bogota
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1980/10/1554988/pirate-subdivisions-market-residential-lots-bogota</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1980/10/1554988/pirate-subdivisions-market-residential-lots-bogota</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/12/000178830_98101903405889/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/12/000178830_98101903405889/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-07-12T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1980-10-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Pirate subdivisions and the market for
            residential lots in Bogota
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Residential lots developed illegally by
            entrepreneurs and sold with rudimentary or no public
            services account for between onethird and one-half of the
            residential land developed to date in Bogota, Colombia. As
            one alternative to these pirate subdivisions, legally
            approved minimum norm developments with minimum levels of
            public services have been instituted in Bogota in the past
            few years. Analysis of data from 135 pirate and 14 minimum
            norm developments shows that developers of minimum norm lots
            spend about twice as much on infrastructure per lot as do
            pirate developers, and sell their lots for about eighty
            percent more per square meter. The total cost of minimum
            norm lots are only a third greater than pirate lots because
            they are only three-fourths as large as pirate lots. Median
            rates of return for pirate developments indicate that the
            development of pirate lots is competitive. Median rates of
            return for minimum norm developments suggest the presence of
            significant restrictions on the supply of land zoned for
            minimum norm development.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Pirate subdivisions and the market for
            residential lots in Bogota
        </docna>
        <display_title>Pirate subdivisions and the
            market for residential lots in Bogota</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1980/10/1554988/pirate-subdivisions-market-residential-lots-bogota</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Urban Housing and Land Settlements,National Urban Development Policies &amp; Strategies,Urban Services to the Poor,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Urban Development</teratopic>
        <count>Colombia</count>
        <authors>
            <author>CARROLL, A.</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South America!$!80469</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903405889</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Urban housing</subsc>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 435</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Urban Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Urban Development</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Data analysis; Entrepreneurs; Housing;
            Income distribution; Infrastructure; Land development; Land
            resources; Land tenure; Public services
            Average Costs,barrios,cities,Competitive
            Markets,discount rates,economies of
            scale,employment,Expenditures,housing,Income,Income
            Distribution,interest rates,labor markets,land
            development,land markets,land sales,land use,marginal
            costs,neighborhood,overhead costs,pollution,Price
            Indexes,private property,savings,slums,social costs,squatter
            settlements,subdivision
            regulations,subdivisions,towns,Urban,urban development
        </keywd>
        <owner>LCS</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP435</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Generic Name List</ml:concept><ml:concept>Generics</ml:concept><ml:concept>List of Generic Drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Off patent drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Process Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Mapping</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Chains</ml:concept><ml:concept>Service Fees</ml:concept><ml:concept>Service Standards</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Capital</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing People</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Employment and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Improving Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Market Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets, Job Creation and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing Finance &amp; Real Estate Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Housing and Land Settlements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Econometrics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Middle-class</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Generic Drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Highways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adminstrative Simplification</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adminstrative Simplification </ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drainage</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Colombia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>