<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP697&#13;
Schooling and Demand for Children&#13;
Historical Perspectives&#13;
Jee Peng Tan&#13;
Michael Haines&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 697&#13;
POPULATION AND DEVELOPMENT SERIES&#13;
Number 22&#13;
iL a      *rr&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS                              -      7&#13;
Number 697                                      w67&#13;
POPULATION AND DEVELOPMENT SERIES                         '@'    Q"17&#13;
Number 22&#13;
Schooling and Demand for Children&#13;
Historical Perspectives&#13;
Jee Peng Tan&#13;
Michael Haines&#13;
tNTft-NALTIONAL MONETARY FUND&#13;
JOINT LIBRA8Y&#13;
JA.I 9) 1935&#13;
I;lTENNAnONAL BAN% FOR&#13;
teECONlSTfUCTiOI4 AND MVELOMM'&#13;
WASIII'r1 ON. ) C. 'rt3&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright CC) 1984&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
18 18 H Street, N W.&#13;
Washirtgton, D C. 20433, U S A&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First piunting November 1984&#13;
This is a working docunent published informally by the World Bank. To present&#13;
the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been&#13;
prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal pnnted texts, and&#13;
the World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a&#13;
tolken (harge to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The World Bank does riot accept responsibility for the views expressed herein, which&#13;
are those of the authors and should riot be attributed to the World Bank or to its&#13;
affiliated organizations. The findings, interpretations, and conclusions are the results&#13;
of research supported by the B,ank; they do not necessarily represent official policy of&#13;
the Bank. The designatiors employed, the presentation of material, and any maps used&#13;
in :his document are solely for the convenience of the reader and do not imply the&#13;
expression of any opinion whatsoever on the part of the World Bank or its affiliates&#13;
conceming the legal status of any country, territory, city, area, or of its authorities, or&#13;
concerning the delimitation of its boundaries, or national affiliation.&#13;
The full range of World Bankc publications, both free and for sale, is described in the&#13;
Catalog of Publications; the continuing research program is outlined in Abstracts of&#13;
Current Studies. Both booklets are updated annually; the most recent edition of each is&#13;
available without charge from the Publications Sales Unit, Department T, The World&#13;
Bank, 1818 H Street, N.V, Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A., or from the European&#13;
Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'Iena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
fee Peng Tan is a staff member of the Education and Training Department of the&#13;
World Bank. Michael Haines, a consultant to the Bank, is associate professor of&#13;
economics at Wayne State University (Detroit, Michigan, U.S.A.)&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Tan, Jee Peng, 19'54-&#13;
Schooling and clemand for children.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 697)&#13;
Bibliography: F'.&#13;
1. Fertility, Human--Economic aspects. 2. Fertility,&#13;
Human--Economic aspects--Developing countries. 3. Educa-&#13;
tion--Demographic aspects. 4. Education--Demographic&#13;
aspects--Developinig countries. I. Haines, Michael R.&#13;
II. Title. III. 'Series.&#13;
HB901.T36    1984        304.6'32        84-26944&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0450-Y&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FOREWORD&#13;
This paper is one in a special series of World Bank Staff&#13;
Working Papers on population change and development.     Prepared as&#13;
background papers for the World Development Report 1984, they&#13;
provide more detailed treatment and documentation of the issues&#13;
dealt with in Part II of the Report. The papers cover a range of&#13;
topics, including the effects of population growth and change on&#13;
economic development, the determinants of fertility and mortality,&#13;
the links between population growth and internal and international&#13;
migration, and the management, financing, and effectiveness of&#13;
family  planning  programs.     They  include  several  country  and&#13;
regional studies of fertility change and population policy.&#13;
The background papers draw on a large number of published&#13;
and unpublished studies of individual researchers, on Bank policy&#13;
analysis and research, and on reports of other organizations&#13;
working on population and development programs and issues.       The&#13;
papers   are   the  work   of   individuals   and   the  views   and&#13;
interpretations expressed in them do not necessarily coincide with&#13;
the views and interpretations of the Report itself.&#13;
I hope these detailed studies will supplement the World&#13;
Development Report 1984 in furthering understanding of population&#13;
and development issues among students and practitioners of&#13;
development.&#13;
Nancy Birdsall&#13;
Staff Director&#13;
World Development Report 1984&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Some of the Papers in the Population and Development Series&#13;
ALnsworth, Marthia. Family Planaing Programs: The Clients' Perspective. World Bank&#13;
Staff Working Paper no. 676.&#13;
Boulier, Bryan L. Evaluatirg Unmet Need for Contraception: Estimates for Thirty-&#13;
six Developing Countries. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 678.&#13;
Builatao, Rodolfo A. Expenditures on Population Programs in Developing Regions:&#13;
Current Levels and Future R,pqirements, World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 679.&#13;
Bullatao, Rodolfo A. Reducing Fertility in Developing Countries: A Review of&#13;
Determinants and Policy Levers. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 680.&#13;
Builatao, Rodolfo A. and Anne ElTwan. Fertility and Mortality Transition in&#13;
Developirs Countries:   Patterns, Projections, and Interdependence.   World&#13;
Bank Staff Wor ing Paper no. 681.&#13;
Cain, Mead. Women's Status and Fertility in Developing Countries: Son&#13;
Preference and Economic Security. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 682.&#13;
Gwatkin, Davidson. Mortality Reduction, Fertility Decline, and Population&#13;
Growth: Toward a More Relevant Assessment of Relationships Among Them.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 686.&#13;
Herz, Barbara. Official Developmnt Assistance for Population Activities: A&#13;
Review. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 688.&#13;
McNicoll, Geoffrey. Consequencies of Rapid Population Growth: An Overview.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 691.&#13;
Merrick, Thomas W. Recent Fertility Declines in Brazil, Colombia, and Mexico.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 692.&#13;
Muiscat, Robert and others.  Rapid Population Growth and Human Carrying Capacity:&#13;
Two Perspectives. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 690.&#13;
Sapir, Andre. Some Aspects of Population Growth, Trade, and Factor Mobility.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 694.&#13;
Standing, Guy.  Population Mobility and Productive Relations:   Demographic Links&#13;
and Policy Evolution. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 695.&#13;
Tan, Jee-Peng and Michael Ha,ines. Schooling and Demand for Children: Historical&#13;
Perspectives. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 697.&#13;
Trussell, Janes and Anne R. Pebley. The Potential Impact of Changes in Fertility on&#13;
Infant, Child, and Maternal Mortality. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 698.&#13;
Zachariah, K,C. and Sulekha Patel. Determinants of Fertility Decline in India:&#13;
An Analysis. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 699.&#13;
Zachariah, K.C. The Anomoly of the Fertility Decline in India's Kerala State:&#13;
A Field Investigation. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 700.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Summary&#13;
This paper focuses on one of the factors thought to be important in&#13;
explaining changes in fertility over time, namely the schooling of children.&#13;
Theory predicts that it exerts a negative effect on parental fertility. The&#13;
mechanisms by which this relationship occurs at the micro-level have been&#13;
elaborated by Becker in this quantity-quality trade-off model, and by Caldwell&#13;
in his intergenerational transfer model. In the Becker model, an increase in&#13;
quantity decreases demand for quality, both through the shadow income&#13;
constraint, and by raising the shadow price of quality. An increase in the&#13;
demand for quality decreases the demand for close quantity by a similar&#13;
mechanism. Although quantity and quality need not be close substitutes, an&#13;
increase in the demand for one will decrease the demand for the other. In the&#13;
Caldwell model, fertility decline sets in only when the direction of net&#13;
wealth flow changes from children to parents, over to parents to children.&#13;
The (mass) education of children is seen as a primary determinant in changing&#13;
the direction of the wealth flow between generations. First, the child's&#13;
potential for work both inside and outside the family is reduced; not only&#13;
because of the hours needed for school attendance and homework, but also&#13;
because of the changing attitudes of the child and family toward traditional&#13;
work at home. Second, education increases the direct costs of children to the&#13;
family. The institution of mass education also changes the position of the&#13;
child in the family and in society, and accelerates cultural change and the&#13;
creation of new (western middle-class) cultural values.&#13;
The results of empirical studies are mixed, with some studies finding&#13;
positive, others negative, and still others no relationship between quantity&#13;
and quality. This paper extends the existing discussion by evaluating the&#13;
evidence from a historical perspective. The time-series data for five&#13;
presently developed countries and eighteen developing countries show that,&#13;
prior to the attainment of primary gross enrollment ratios of about 70 or 80&#13;
percent, there appeared to be little relationship between levels or change in&#13;
primary school enrollments and fertility. There were exceptions, but overall&#13;
a fairly high level of educational development, as indicated by the level of&#13;
primary enrollments, seemed to be important for a decline in fertility to take&#13;
place.&#13;
It is suggested in this paper that costs and financing arrangements,&#13;
and parental aspirations for children's education may be important reasons&#13;
behind the observed historical relationship. At early stages of development,&#13;
parental aspirations are likely to be low, so that for most children parents&#13;
desire only a few years of primary schooling. At this level of education, the&#13;
costs, both direct and indirect, are also low. Moreover, the social organiza-&#13;
tion in traditional societies is likely to be such that parents do not expect&#13;
to bear the full cost of their children's schooling since they can usually&#13;
rely on relatives and even older children for financial support. As a society&#13;
modernizes, however, the inverse relationship between child schooling and&#13;
parental fertility is likely to become stronger. The high level of primary&#13;
school enrollments characteristic of such societies is probably symptomatic of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
rising returns to education, which :Lmplies a corresponding rising pay-off to&#13;
inrestment in child quality.   Parents are likely to plan for more years of&#13;
education for their children, including possibly secondary and even higher&#13;
education. This is likely to imply an escalating economic burden, since the&#13;
opportunity cosst of children's eclucalt:ion at the post-primary ages is&#13;
substantially higher than at the younlger ages. Also, as the process of&#13;
development often weakens kinship tLes and sibling obligations, the cost of&#13;
firancing schooling is likely to fall more fully on parents.&#13;
Acknowledgements&#13;
We are grateful to Nancy B:Lrdsall, Rodolfo Bulatao, Dennis DeTray and&#13;
William McGreevey for their comments on an earlier draft. We alone are,&#13;
however, solely responsible for the views expressed in this paper.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
R6sume&#13;
Cette etude examine un des facteurs qui, croit-on, contribue&#13;
largement a expliquer les variations de la f6condit6, a savoir la scolari-&#13;
sation des enfants. Selon la theorie, elle exerce un effet negatif sur la&#13;
fecondite des parents. Les mecanismes de cette causalit6 ont 6t6 pr6cises&#13;
par Becker dans son modele d'interaction entre la quantite et la qualit6&#13;
et par Caldwell dans son modele de transfert intergen6rationnel. Dans le&#13;
modele de Becker, une augmentation de la quantit6 amene une diminution de&#13;
la demande de qualite, en comprimant le revenu virtuel et en accroissant&#13;
le prix virtuel de la qualit6 et une augmentation de la demande de qualit6&#13;
amene une diminution de la demande de quantite. Bien que la quantite et&#13;
la qualite ne soient pas exactement des produits substituables, lorsque la&#13;
demande d'un de ces facteurs augmente, celle de l'autre diminue. Selon le&#13;
modele de Caldwell, la f6condit6 ne baisse que lorsque la direction du&#13;
flux net de richesses (des enfants aux parents) s'inverse (pour aller des&#13;
parents aux enfants). L'enseignement (de masse) des enfants est consid6r6&#13;
comme un facteur d6terminant dans le renversement de la direction de ce&#13;
flux entre les generations. Premierement, le potentiel de travail de&#13;
l'enfant, tant a l'interieur qu'a l'exterieur de la famille, diminue; cela&#13;
ne tient pas simplement au fait que l'enfant doit passer un certain nombre&#13;
d'heures a l'6cole et a faire ses devoirs, mais egalement a une modifica-&#13;
tion de la maniere dont l'enfant et la famille envisagent le travail tra-&#13;
ditionnel a la maison. Deuxiemement, l1'ducation augmente le coat direct&#13;
de 1'enfant pour la famille. L'education de masse modifie la place de&#13;
l'enfant dans la famille et dans la soci6te, acc6lere le changement cultu-&#13;
rel et la creation de nouvelles valeurs culturelles de la classe moyenne&#13;
occidentale.&#13;
Les r6sultats d'6tudes empiriques ne sont pas probants, cer-&#13;
taines 6tudes concluant qu'il existe un rapport positif, d'autres un rap-&#13;
port n6gatif, d'autres encore aucun rapport entre la quantite et la qua-&#13;
lit6. La pr6sente etude reprend la question en examinant les donn6es dans&#13;
un contexte historique. Les donn6es de s6ries chronologiques de cinq pays&#13;
developpes et de dix-huit pays en d6veloppement montrent que tant que les&#13;
ratios bruts d'inscription a l'ecole primaire n'ont pas atteint 70 ou&#13;
80 %, il ne semble guere y avoir d'interaction entre les niveaux d'ins-&#13;
cription a l'6cole primaire et la fecondit6. I1 y a des exceptions mais&#13;
dans l'ensemble, il semble que le d6veloppement de l'education (exprime&#13;
par le taux d'inscriptions primaires) doive avoir atteint un niveau rela-&#13;
tivement elev6 avant qu'on puisse noter une baisse de la fecondit6.&#13;
D'apres cette 6tude, il semblerait que l'on peut, dans une&#13;
grande mesure, expliquer ces phenomenes par le coat de l'enseignement des&#13;
enfants, les modalites de son financement et les aspirations des parents.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Pendant les premiers stades dii d6veloppement, les aspirations des parents&#13;
sont en g6n6ral relativement modtestes, ce qui fait qu'ils ne souhaitent,&#13;
dans la pliupart des cas, que quelques ann6es d'enseignement primaire. A&#13;
ce niveau d1inistruction, les couts directs et indirects sont faibles. En&#13;
outre, la structure sociale des societes traditionnelles est en gen6ral&#13;
telle que les parents n'ont pas a supporter tout le coat de 1'education de&#13;
leurs enfants.   Ils peuvent obtenir un soutien financier de leur famille&#13;
et meme de leuirs enfants plus ages.  N6anmoins, a mesure que la societe se&#13;
modernise, il est probable que le rapport inverse entre l'6ducation des&#13;
enfants et la fecondit6 parentale se renforce. Le fort niveau d'inscrip-&#13;
tions dans les ecoles primnaires, qui est caract6ristique de ces soci6t6s,&#13;
est probabLement symptomatique de la rentabilit6 accrue de l'education,&#13;
qui implique line augmentation proportionnelle des ben6fices de l'investis-&#13;
sement dans la qualit6 des enfants. Les parents envisagent d'6tendre la&#13;
scolarite de leurs enfants, peut-etre de les envoyer a l'6cole secondaire&#13;
ou meme a L'universit6. II en r6sultera un fardeau economique plus 6leve,&#13;
puisque le cofit d'opportunit6 de L'enseignement des enfants est sensible-&#13;
mient plus elev6 une fois qu'i:Ls ont d6passe l'age de l'ecole primaire.&#13;
Comme, en meme temps, le processus de d6veloppement affaiblit souvent les&#13;
liens familiaux et les obligations entre freres et soeurs, une partie plus&#13;
importante du coat du financernent de l'6ducation retombe sur les parents.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Resumen&#13;
El presente estudio se centra en uno de los factores que se con-&#13;
sideran importantes a la hora de tratar de explicar las variaciones en la&#13;
fecundidad a trav6s del tiempo, a saber, la educaci6n de las hijos. La&#13;
teoria sostiene que 6sta ejerce un efecto negativo en la fecundidad de los&#13;
padres. Los mecanismos por los cuales esa relaci6n tiene lugar en el&#13;
micronivel han sido estudiados detalladamente por Becker en su modelo de&#13;
las compensaciones reciprocas entre cantidad y calidad, y por Caldwell en&#13;
su modelo de las transferencias intergeneracionales. En el modelo de&#13;
Becker, un aumento de la cantidad hace que disminuya la demanda de cali-&#13;
dad, tanto a trav6s de la limitaci6n del ingreso de cuenta como a trav6s&#13;
del aumento del precio de cuenta de la calidad.    Un aumento de la demanda&#13;
de calidad reduce la demanda de cantidad por medio de un mecanismo ana-&#13;
logo.  Aunque no es preciso que la cantidad y la calidad se sustituyan&#13;
entre si exactamente, todo aumento de la demanda de una harA que disminuya&#13;
la demanda de la otra.   En el modelo de Caldwell, la disminuci6n de la&#13;
fecundidad se produce s6lo cuando el sentido de la corriente neta de&#13;
patrimonio, de los hijos hacia los padres, se invierte y va de los padres&#13;
hacia los hijos. La educaci6n (universal) de los ninos se considera un&#13;
factor determinante primario del cambio de sentido de la corriente patri-&#13;
monial entre las generaciones. En primer lugar, las posibilidades del&#13;
niino para trabajar dentro y fuera del ambito familiar se reducen, no s6lo&#13;
debido a la cantidad de horas necesarias para asistir a la escuela y estu-&#13;
diar en la casa, sino tambi6n debido a la evoluci6n de las actitudes del&#13;
nino y de la familia con respecto al trabajo tradicional en el hogar. En&#13;
segundo lugar, la educaci6n incrementa los costos directos de los hijos&#13;
para la familia.   La instituci6n de la educaci6n universal, hace que cam-&#13;
bie la posici6n que el niiio ocupa en la familia y en la sociedad, y ace-&#13;
lera el cambio cultural y la generaci6n de nuevos valores culturales (de&#13;
la clase media occidental).&#13;
Los resultados de estudios empiricos han sido diversos: en&#13;
algunos han sido positivos, en otros negativos y en otros se ha hallado&#13;
que no hay ninguna relaci6n entre la cantidad y la calidad.    En este tra-&#13;
bajo se amplia el anAlisis en curso evaluando las pruebas desde una pers-&#13;
pectiva hist6rica. Los datos de las series cronol6gicas elaboradas para&#13;
cinco paises actualmente desarrollados y 18 paises en desarrollo indican&#13;
que antes de alcanzarse coeficientes brutos de matricula primaria de alre-&#13;
dedor de 70% u 80% parecia existir poca relaci6n entre los niveles o las&#13;
variaciones de la matricula escolar primaria y la fecundidad.    Habia&#13;
excepciones, pero, en terminos generales, para que se produjera una dis-&#13;
minucion de la fecundidad parecia ser importante lograr un grado bastante&#13;
elevado de desarrollo educacional, tal como el indicado por el alto nivel&#13;
de la matricula primaria.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
En el presente estudio se seniala que los costos y los mecanismos&#13;
cde financiarnierito, asi como las aspiraciones de los padres con respecto a&#13;
la educaci6n de sus hijos, pueden ser razones importantes de la relaci6n&#13;
hist6rica observada. En las etapas iniciales del desarrollo es probable&#13;
cue las aspiraciones de los pac[res sean modestas, de modo que, en lo que&#13;
atanie a la mayor parte de sus descendientes, los padres s6lo deseen unos&#13;
rocos ainos cle educaci6n primaria. A este nivel, los costos, tanto direc-&#13;
tos como inclirectos, son tambi6n pequenios. Mas adn, es probable que la&#13;
crganizaci6n scicial de las sociedacles tradicionales sea tal que los padres&#13;
no esperan tener que sufragar el costo total de la educaci6n de sus hijos,&#13;
ya que generalmente pueden recurri.r a los parientes e incluso a los hijos&#13;
mayores para obtener apoyo financiero. A medida que una sociedad se&#13;
modlerniza, s in embargo, es probab]e que la relaci6n inversa entre la edu-&#13;
cacion de los hijos y la fecundidad de los padres se refuerce.   El alto&#13;
coeficiente de la matricula escolar primaria caracteristico de esas socie-&#13;
dades probablemente sea sin toma de un rendimiento creciente de la educa-&#13;
ci6Sn, que a su vez supone una rentabilidad creciente de la inversi6n en la&#13;
calidad de los hijos. Es probable que los padres planeen mas anios de edu-&#13;
caci6n para estos, incluida tal vez la educaci6n secundaria y aun la uni-&#13;
versitaria.  Esto probablemente represente un aumento de la carga econo-&#13;
mica, ya que el costo de oportunidad de la educaci6n de los h-ijos en eda-&#13;
des posprimarias es mucho maLyor que el de la educaci6n de los hijos mAs&#13;
j6venes. Ademas, como el proceso de desarrollo a menudo debil.ita los&#13;
lazos familiares y las obligaciones para con los hermanos, es probable que&#13;
el costo de financiar la educaci6n recaiga mas de lleno en los padres.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Contents&#13;
Page&#13;
1.   Introduction ---------------------------------------------------    1&#13;
2.   Children's Schooling and Fertility Change ----------------------    1&#13;
2.1 Preliminary Considerations -------------------------------------     1&#13;
2.2  Theoretical Relationship and Supporting Evidence ---------------    2&#13;
3.   The Historical Experience of Developed Countries ---------------   16&#13;
3.1 Fertility and Mortality Trends ---------------------------------    16&#13;
3.2 Enrollment Rates -----------------------------------------------    20&#13;
3.3 Graphical Relationships Between Fertility and&#13;
School Enrollment, 1950-1960 ---------------------------------   22&#13;
3.4  The Cost of Education ------------------------------------------   26&#13;
3.5 Private Returns to Schooling -----------------------------------    34&#13;
3.6  Other Considerations:  Child Labor Laws ------------------------   37&#13;
4.   The Experience of Less Developed Countries ---------------------   39&#13;
4.1 Fertility and Mortality Trends ---------------------------------    39&#13;
4.2 Enrollment Trends ----------------------------------------------    42&#13;
4.3 Graphical Relationships Between Fertility and&#13;
Enrollment, 1950-1980 ----------------------------------------   45&#13;
4.4  The Private Cost of Education ----------------------------------   52&#13;
4.5 Private Returns to Schooling   ----------------------------------   64&#13;
4.6 Other Influences   ----------------------------------------------   68&#13;
5.   Conclusions:  Children's Schooling and Fertility Change --------   71&#13;
Appendix A. The Becker-Lewis Quantity-Quality Tradeoff&#13;
Fertility Model                              ------------  75&#13;
Tables&#13;
1 Some Empirical Studies of the Quantity-Quality Model of Fertility - 10&#13;
2 Share of Education in Total Family Expenditures by Family&#13;
Composition in 11 Latin American Cities                ------------- 12&#13;
3 Relationship Between Gross School Enrollment Rates and&#13;
Fertility Decline, Five Developed Countries            ------------- 25&#13;
4 Expenditures on Education in the United States,&#13;
1840-1900 (Current Dollars)                            -----------   27&#13;
5 Relative Educational Expenditure: US, UK, and Germany,&#13;
1860-1900 (Current Dollars)                            ------------- 28&#13;
6 Gross Enrollment Levels at the Start of Fertility&#13;
Decline in Selected LDCs                               ------------- 50&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Page&#13;
Tables A.1.-A.5.  Fertility, Mortality and Enrollment Data&#13;
for Five Developed Countries, 1800-1900     ------ 77-82&#13;
Table A.6,.       Coale's IndiceS of Overall Fertility,&#13;
Marital Fertility, and Proportions Married ------     83&#13;
Tables B.1.-B.18. Fertility, Mort.ality and Enrollment Data&#13;
for 18 LDCs 1950-1980                        ----  85-94&#13;
Figures&#13;
1   Fertility and Enrollment Trends in Five Developed&#13;
Countries, 1800-1960                                   ------     24&#13;
2   Fertility and Enrollment Trends in Latin America,&#13;
1950-1980                                              ------     46&#13;
3   Fertility and Enrollment Trends in Asia, 1950-1980      ------    47&#13;
4   Fertility and Enrollment Trends in Africa, 1950-1980    ------    49&#13;
Bibliography               -----------------------------------------     95&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
1. Introduction&#13;
The purpose of this paper is to study the relationship between the&#13;
schooling of children (as opposed to that of parents) and fertility change.&#13;
Some attention will be paid to mortality change, although that is more likely&#13;
to be a cause than an effect of changes in children's education. There&#13;
already exists a strong body of evidence which notes a negative relation of&#13;
mother's education to fertility and to child mortality [Cochrane, 1979, 1980;&#13;
Behm, 1979; United Nations, 19821. The focus here will be less on&#13;
differentials and more on trends over time, with attention being paid to&#13;
declines in fertility and changes in school enrollment, schooling costs,&#13;
compulsory schooling, costs and benefits of children and their schooling, and&#13;
some other relevant factors, such as child labor laws, which affect fertility&#13;
through the child.&#13;
2. Children's Schooling and Fertility Change&#13;
2.1 Preliminary Considerations&#13;
The education or schooling of children is generally regarded as an&#13;
investment in human capital, or child quality [Becker, 1975, 1981; Schultz,&#13;
1981]. Associated with this investment process are direct costs (e.g.,&#13;
expenditures on school fees, books, supplies, subsistence costs) and indirect&#13;
costs, particularly foregone earnings (opportunity cost) of the child.&#13;
Benefits are to be expected. They are not so easy to measure, but would&#13;
include enhanced future welfare of the child, especially because of higher&#13;
wages or earnings, as well as increased income to the family, if the child&#13;
contributes to the family when he or she eventually enters the labor force.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
Several important questions must be approached in the course of the inquiry:&#13;
Who makes schooling decisions?  Wrho finances schooling (i.e., parents or the&#13;
government)? Why would parents or children invest in child q[uality? What is&#13;
the relationship of school[ng to fertility and child mortality?  What has been&#13;
the historical and contemporary record on this? These topics form the basis&#13;
for the present paper.&#13;
2.2 Theoretical Relationships and Supporting Evidence&#13;
The literature on the demographic transition has often mentioned&#13;
edcucation as an important aspect of the transition process [Notestein, 1954;&#13;
3eaver, 1975; Coale, 1973] Much attention has been paid to the existence of&#13;
a negative relationship between parental education (especially education of&#13;
i:he mother) and fertility ICochrane, 1979; Graff, 1979]. Much of the&#13;
empirical work has dealt wi-th cross-sectional results, but some evidence&#13;
irndicates that secular change in education may influence fertility decline&#13;
[Stycos, 1977]. Education of parents also appears to affect differential&#13;
childhood mortality [Cochrane, 1980; United Nations, 1982; Behm, 1979].&#13;
Another aspect operates through the education process by affecting&#13;
:he costs and benefits of children. The fertility behavior of the parents,&#13;
and possibly child mortalit:y in their families, are influenced by the costs of&#13;
eclucating their children and by the perceived benefits of thatt education&#13;
[Arnold, et. al., 1975; Ca]dwell, 1982, ch. 10].  Schooling has been&#13;
associated witn modernizati-on and the demographic transition. Ansley Coale,&#13;
in his discussion of the demographic transitions, notes:&#13;
"[A] society was modern, in 1960, if at least 50&#13;
percent of the population lived in urban settlements&#13;
of more than 20,000 persons, if more than 90 percent&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
of the female population at ages 6 to 13 was enrolled&#13;
in school, and fewer than 30 percent of the labor&#13;
force was engaged in agriculture, fishing and&#13;
forestry. A society was traditional if less than 30&#13;
percent of its population lived in urban settlements&#13;
of more than 20,000 persons, if fewer than 50 percent&#13;
of females 6 to 13 were enrolled in school, and if&#13;
more than 60 percent of the labor force was engaged in&#13;
agriculture, fishing, or forestry." [Coale, 1973,&#13;
p. 641&#13;
A modern society is one with low birth and death rates and a&#13;
traditional society is one with high fertility and mortality. One problem&#13;
with this viewpoint is that "threshold values" of these indicators seem to&#13;
have changed over time. For example, Germany and Scandinavia had very high&#13;
levels of literacy by 1870, but had undergone no sustained fertility decline.&#13;
Examining historical evidence, Knodel and van de Walle [1979] found no&#13;
evidence of a correlation between level of literacy and the date of onset of&#13;
the fertility decline.&#13;
Nevertheless, Caldwell has advanced the theory that fertility decline&#13;
only sets in when the direction of net wealth flow changes from children to&#13;
parents over to parents to children. "It is argued that the primary deter-&#13;
minant of the timing of the onset of the fertility transition is the effect of&#13;
mass education on the family economy. The direction of the wealth flow&#13;
between generations is changed with the introduction of mass education. . .&#13;
[Caldwell, 1982, p. 301]. He cites five mechanisms for this impact of mass&#13;
education on parents' fertility behavior. First, the child's potential for&#13;
work both inside and outside the family would be reduced (i.e., indirect costs&#13;
to the family are increased). This is not only because of hours needed for&#13;
school attendance and homework, but also changing attitudes of the child and&#13;
the family toward traditional work at home. Second, education increases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
direct costs to the family.   These costs often go beyond fees, books, uniforms&#13;
and supplies into improved general levels of clothing, nutrition, etc. Third,&#13;
schooling, or rather the philosophy which underlies the instil:ution of mass&#13;
education, changes the position of the child in the family andL in society.&#13;
Rather than being regarded as a present productive resource within the family,&#13;
the child is regarded as a future productive resource by society and,&#13;
eventually, by the family.   The status of dependent is reinforced and&#13;
increased, and society passes laws to protect children (e.g., child labor and&#13;
compulsory schooling laws). Fourth, mass education accelerates cultural&#13;
change and the creation of new cultural values, particularly because the&#13;
working class can now be reached th,rough their children. And finally, the&#13;
schools serve as a major instrument for propagating Western m],ddle-class&#13;
values [Caldwell, 1982, pp. 303-305]. In general, the first two mechanisms&#13;
(via indirect and direct costs) are widely cited; whereas education as a means&#13;
of creating, changing and diffusing values and norms is often considered, but&#13;
n3t very systematically. Caldwell indeed believes that it is the last three&#13;
value-related mechanisms wh-ich are more influential in turning the family&#13;
economy from one in which childrenL are perceived as a net benefit to one in&#13;
w-xich they are seen as a net cost.&#13;
Another approach has been taken in recent years by economists who&#13;
have constructed micro-economic, household decision-making moclels which&#13;
incorporate a quantity-quality trade-off in childbearing [Becker, 1960, 1981,&#13;
cla. 5; Becker and Lewis, 1973; Becker and Tomes, 1976; Willis, 1973; DeTray,&#13;
1973].  This literature draws on the notions of household procLuction functions&#13;
anid human capital theory [Schultz, 1981; Becker, 1975; Michael and Becker,&#13;
1973].  In the simplest type of model [Beclker, 1981, pp. 103-104], the demand&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
for number of children (quantity) and child quality depends both on the shadow&#13;
prices of quantity, quality, and other commodities, and "shadow income".&#13;
Quantity and quality (the amount of human capital) of children interact&#13;
inversely in demand functions, depending upon market prices and income. That&#13;
is, an increase in quantity decreases demand for quality, both through the&#13;
shadow income constraint and by raising the shadow price of quality. An&#13;
increase in quality decreases demand for quantity by a similar mechanism.&#13;
(See Appendix A for a brief description in more formal terms.) Although&#13;
quantity and quality need not be close substitutes (and indeed cannot be if&#13;
the system is to be stable in a range of plausible values), an increase in&#13;
demand for one will decrease the demand for the other. This offers a probable&#13;
reason for historical fertility decline in developed countries.&#13;
"Several alternative explanations for large&#13;
changes in fertility have been suggested, including&#13;
the contraceptive revolution ushered in by the pill.&#13;
. , but this cannot explain the large decline in&#13;
births in the United States during the twenties or in&#13;
Japan during the fifties. I am convinced that the&#13;
most promising explanation is found in the interaction&#13;
between quantity and quality of children, for it&#13;
implies that the demand for children is highly&#13;
responsive to price and perhaps to income, even when&#13;
children have no close substitutes." [Becker, 1981,&#13;
pp. 106-107]&#13;
A basic conclusion of this model is that economic development and&#13;
modernization, which usually increase demand for skilled labor relative to&#13;
unskilled labor, raises rates of return on education and training, especially&#13;
in urban areas. This lowers the marginal cost (and hence the shadow price) of&#13;
child quality. As a consequence, demand for child quality increases, which&#13;
interacts with quantity to reduce fertility. In addition, reductions in child&#13;
mortality can reduce the marginal cost of child quality, which can, in turn,&#13;
reduce fertility via the same mechanisms (see below).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6-&#13;
In general, the basic model can be extended to anything which reduces&#13;
the costs ol' child quality or increase the returns, including various&#13;
governmental policies such as schooling, which affect human capital&#13;
investments. Becker cites evidence [1981, p. 1111 that the empirical&#13;
relationship between quantity and quality is usually negative, especially for&#13;
developed countries. Tomes [1978]., DeTray [19781 and Rosenzweig and Wolpin&#13;
[1980] also found evidence for this for the contemporary United States.&#13;
Rosenzweig and Wolpin [1982] demonstrate theoretically that a compulsory&#13;
schooling law which forces parents to educate their children beyond a level&#13;
which they would have chosen in the absence of the law will have a negative&#13;
effect on feirtility. In another paper, Rosenzweig notes, howlever, that the&#13;
basic economic maximization model "cannot predict how a subsidy to health or&#13;
education will influence fertility or even investments in health or schooling;&#13;
it can only predict total resources allocated to children. . . will rise,&#13;
since investments in both numbers and the quality of children are made cheaper&#13;
by subsidization of basic needs." I-Rosenzweig, 1981, p. 57] Empirical results&#13;
for rural India and urban Colombia indicate, however, that health programs&#13;
lowered both fertility and child rnortality. "Basic needs subsidies to&#13;
fertility control, to health and to schooling thus appear to have the same&#13;
joint outcomes--smaller family size and more investments in each child."&#13;
[Rosenzweig, 1981, p. 59]&#13;
It should be noted that this economic model can also be extended to&#13;
include childhood mortality [Becker, 1981, pp. 111-112]. For example, an&#13;
exogenous decline in childhood mortality caused by a public health program can&#13;
free parental resources which had been devoted to child mortality prevention,&#13;
while at the same time increasing the expected rate of return on child&#13;
investments. This would lower the shadow price of child quality and increase&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
demand for child quality (and hence induce a reduction in quantity). Thus&#13;
mortality decline during the demographic transition could induce greater&#13;
demand for schooling.    Preston [1980, pp 324-326] notes, however, that the&#13;
effect of mortality decline on rates of return from education is not likely to&#13;
be very large.&#13;
This model seems most appropriate for urban, high-income societies in&#13;
which fertility is low or declining, and where investment per child is already&#13;
high. Eva Mueller (1983) has argued that in less developed, rural societies&#13;
the relationship between children's education (and child quality generally)&#13;
and fertility may be only weakly negative, null, or even positive. She notes&#13;
that the quantity-quality trade-off assumes tastes (preferences) as given, and&#13;
also that quality is more income elastic and more price elastic than&#13;
quantity. This is true only when education is assigned a great importance in&#13;
the household utility function, which is a condition that is unlikely to&#13;
prevail at early stages of development in rural, agrarian regions. With high&#13;
child mortality and with relatively low rates of return on education, price&#13;
and income elasticities of demand for child quality may be relatively low. In&#13;
addition, education costs may not be substantial, even including indirect&#13;
costs of foregone labor. If children are sent to school for only 3-4 years,&#13;
or even the 6 years to complete primary education, the direct costs may not be&#13;
especially burdensome. Further, children attending school only up to ages&#13;
11-13 are not as much missed in terms of labor or income contributions to the&#13;
family as would children aged 14 and over. School years may be short (several&#13;
months only) and hence children may even be able to make significant economic&#13;
contributions to the family while continuing to attend school. It may be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
that older siblings help pay for the direct schooling costs of younger&#13;
children, and so increased demand for quality might even have a positive&#13;
relationship to the demand for quality.&#13;
In general, Mueller notes that child quantity and quality could be&#13;
positively related under a regime of natural fertility (e.g., if rising income&#13;
might make possible both increased fertility and increased children's&#13;
education), if the opportunity cost of school attendance is seen as being&#13;
lower in larger than in smaller families; if net rates of return to parents&#13;
from educating their children are perceived as positive; or if siblings or&#13;
relatives assist in educating children.   Even if the quantity-quality relation&#13;
is negative, it may well be weak if the family does not accord a high priority&#13;
to education and child qua-Lity.&#13;
The empirical evidence on this is mixed, with some studies finding&#13;
positive, others negative, and still others no relationship between quantity&#13;
and quality. Table 1 contains the results of some recent studies on the&#13;
quantity-quality model of i.ertility. In the three African case studies&#13;
listed, the relationship between number of children and per child investment&#13;
is positive in five of the six regressions cited. For Botswana, Chernichovsky&#13;
found that&#13;
"The larger the numlber of school-age children in the&#13;
household, the higher the probability of their school&#13;
enrollment and the higher their levels of education.&#13;
This finding can be in part explained by the falling&#13;
productivity of labor in the household with any given&#13;
amount of assets that reduce the indirect cost of&#13;
schooling. The fall in productivity may lead to role&#13;
assignment in the hcusehold; some children are kept&#13;
for household and farm activities, while others are&#13;
'assigned' to school and allowed to concentrate on&#13;
this activity." [Chernichovsky, 1981]&#13;
Snyder's study of Sierra Leone revealed a positive and statistically signifi-&#13;
cant relationship between quantity and quality. His explanaLtion is that&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9-&#13;
"Tropical African parents often regard a child as ao&#13;
investment good, a device for attaining income&#13;
security in old age, and an educated child has more&#13;
earning power and hence more "social security valne"&#13;
than an uneducated one. Furthermore, the parents&#13;
often do not bear the full cost of educating the child&#13;
under the extended family system: relatives, friends,&#13;
and older children sometimes chip in, expecting to&#13;
reap further benefits when the child completes school&#13;
and starts to earn. Either or both of these factors&#13;
may cause parents to seek large families and high&#13;
education per child. . ." [Snyder, 1974]&#13;
Evidence for a third African country comes from Kelly's [19801&#13;
analysis of the economic and demographic behavior of households in urban&#13;
Kenya. Although his study does not deal directly with the quantity-quality&#13;
trade-off question, his data and regression results offer some hints. In&#13;
particular, household investment in education increases as the number of&#13;
children in the household increases, but the per child investment tends to&#13;
decline.-I     In a study of India using district and village level data,&#13;
Sahota and Sahota [1980] found an interesting relationship between schooling&#13;
and fertility. If investment in child quality is measured simply by the&#13;
enrollment rate, the relationship is positive, contrary to theory's&#13;
prediction; on the other hand, if it is measured by schooling quality&#13;
(proportion of non-repeaters in class), the relationship is negative. In a&#13;
situation where tuition is free, out-of-pocket expenses low, and opportunities&#13;
for child labor have been declining, as happened in the Punjab in the period&#13;
under review, the family bears a relatively small cost to keep a child in&#13;
1/  In all his regressions, dIe/dCs is statisically significant at the 5%&#13;
level or above and ranges from 6.3 to 8.9 shillings, where Ie is&#13;
household investment in education, and Cs the number of surviving&#13;
children. At the mean of le, 29.3 shillings, the percentage increase in&#13;
le corresponding to an additional qurviving child is between 11 and 15&#13;
percent. Even standardizing for age and sex profiles, the per child&#13;
investment in large families is likely to be lower than in smaller&#13;
families.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 1: Some Empirical Studies of the Quantity-Quality Model of Fertility&#13;
Sample                                                              Relationship    Statistical&#13;
Authors           Country         Year   Characteristics                Regression Variable Definitions         between q and n   Significance&#13;
Quantity (n)             Quality (g)&#13;
Chernichovsky     Botswana        1974   National sample           No. of children      (1) child in school            +               5Z&#13;
(1981)                                   of 1,000 rural            aged 7-14                dummy&#13;
households                                     (2) level of cniid             -             n.a.&#13;
education of&#13;
those who stopped&#13;
(3) level of schooling         +               5Z&#13;
of those currently&#13;
enrol led&#13;
(4) time spent in school       +             n.a.&#13;
DeTray (1978)     USA              1967  Subsample of 1163          No. of children     Average educational level       -               5X&#13;
white households          living at home       of children not living at&#13;
drawn from the National   and elsewhere as     home, this is assumed to be&#13;
Longitudinal Survey       reported by the      the completed level of&#13;
husband             schooli-ng&#13;
Snyder (1974)     Sierra Leone    1966-  Subsample of 717 urban    No. of live          Educational attainment of      +               5X&#13;
1968   households from the       births fathered     the oldest child, EC-Ec,&#13;
Western Area Household    by the household     defined as the residual for&#13;
head                            Of yeas of&#13;
acoL4n~g on the child';&#13;
age, i.e. the portion of                                             C&#13;
the child's educational&#13;
attainment not attrib-&#13;
utable to age&#13;
Rosenzweig and    India           1969-  1,633 rural households    Multiple births      Age standardized schooling&#13;
Wolpin (1980)                      1971   from the Additional       per pregnancy       index&#13;
Rural Incomes Survey                           (1) including twins            -             n.a.&#13;
of 2939 households                             (2) excluding twins            -             n.a.&#13;
Birdsall (1980)   Colombia         1967-  1433 households in 4      (1)  No. of         Ratio of current actual        -                52&#13;
1968   major cities              children of wife    household expenditure on&#13;
currently alive     education to its pre-&#13;
(2)  Fertility      dicted expenditures             +             n.a.&#13;
measure based on    based on sex and age of&#13;
children ever       enrolled children&#13;
born standardized&#13;
for the age-&#13;
fertility rela-&#13;
tionship using a&#13;
natural fertility&#13;
schedule&#13;
Sahota and        India           1964-  Combined time series      Birth rate           (1) Total school enroll-       +              10X&#13;
Sahota (1980)                     1971   and cross section data                             ment as percent of&#13;
from 18 districts and                              total population&#13;
30 villages, yielding                          (2) Ratio of pupils            -              102&#13;
75 observations at the                            spending one year or&#13;
district level; 155                                less in a class to&#13;
at the village level                               total pupils in the&#13;
class&#13;
(3) mean age of pupils in      -              10X&#13;
various classes&#13;
Kelley (1980)     Kenya            1968- C0l house.hold 1 mostly    No. o  e            Total houehl1   e&#133;   Ad-       *               lot&#13;
1969   African nuclear from      children            tures on education (school&#13;
3 urban areas (Nairobi,                        fees, school uniform, books,&#13;
Kisuma and Mombassa)                          etc.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
school. However, the cost to the family rises as the quality of schooling&#13;
desired for the child increases. Thus, one is more likely to observe a&#13;
negative relationship between fertility and child investment when the latter&#13;
is associated not merely with enrollment, but rather with schooling quality.&#13;
However, in the study by Rosenzweig and Wolpin [1980] for another Indian&#13;
sample, the negative relationship predicted by theory is borne out by the&#13;
data, although it is statistically not significant. Another study by&#13;
Rosenzweig [1982] found that, in India, farm households that have been exposed&#13;
to the new technologies of the "green revolution" reduced fertility and&#13;
increased level of schooling investment. The mere proximity of schools, in&#13;
the absence of technical change, had little impact on either schooling or&#13;
family size.&#13;
Birdsall [19801 presents some data for Colombia which show the&#13;
inverse relationship between number of children and investment in their&#13;
schooling. The result is, however, sensitive to the definition of the&#13;
fertility variable. For other Latin American countries, evidence on the&#13;
quantity-quality trade-off comes indirectly from Mugrove's [1977] analysis of&#13;
household expenditure on education in 11 cities. In general, the share of&#13;
education in total family expenditure increases as the number of children in&#13;
the family increases, but the relative rates of increase imply that investment&#13;
per child is probably lower in larger than in smaller families.&#13;
Evidence on the effect of educational subsidies on fertility has&#13;
become available recently [Rosenzweig and Wolpin, 1982; Rosenzweig, 1982; and&#13;
Rosenzweig and Schultz, 1983]. In these studies, educational subsidies are&#13;
proxied by a variable indicating the presence or availability of schooling&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
Table 2: 'Share of Education in Total Family Expenditures by Family&#13;
Composition in L]L Latin American Cities&#13;
Percent&#13;
Families with children          No. of children in family&#13;
Ciur              7 or less   8-18   19 or more     0     1-2    3-5    6 or more&#13;
Bogota              2.11      7.75       1.98      4.12   4.70   3.15      5.92&#13;
Barranquilla        1.95      5.44      1.74       1.85   3.41   4.17      3.65&#13;
Cali                1.40      4.17      1.51       1.73   2.24   2.91      3.84&#13;
Medellin            1.64      5.69       0.93      2.10   3.00   4.06      4.52&#13;
Santiago            0.49      1.12      0.55       0.50   0.87   0.82      0.74&#13;
Quito               0.94      2.12       0.81      0.84   1.43   1.59      1.91&#13;
Quayaquil           1.22      2.71       1.04      1.33   1.83   2.01      1.90&#13;
Azuncion            1.30      2.93       0.92      1.80   1.82    2.01     3.01&#13;
Lima                1.00      2.48       0.99      1.62   2.01   1.54      1.11&#13;
Caracas              --        ---       --        2.13   3.30   4.62      3.54 /1&#13;
Maracaibo           0.93      2.35       1.01      1.16   1.81   1.49      0.58&#13;
/1 Based on less than 40 observations.&#13;
Source:   (Musgrove, 1978), pp. 350-360.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
facilities; this variable is a valid proxy in so far as the presence of a&#13;
school, say in a village, implies a reduction in the price for schooling for&#13;
that village. Presumably this price reduction is associated with reductions&#13;
in the time and travel cost of attending school [Rosenzweig, 1982]. The&#13;
empirical results provide partial support for a positive relationship between&#13;
educational subsidies and schooling on the one hand; and a negative&#13;
relationship between subsidies and fertility on the other. In other studies&#13;
(see Birdsall [1982] for a partial listing) which focus more on the&#13;
determinants of school attendance, the effect on attendance of educational&#13;
subsidies as proxied by the same types of variables (presence of school,&#13;
distance to school) turns out to be statistically insignificant in a&#13;
surprisingly large number of regressions; and in some of those regressions for&#13;
which the effect is statistically significant, the sign of the coefficient is&#13;
negative instead of positive.&#13;
Among studies of developing countries not mentioned in Table 1, a&#13;
recent monograph by Anker and Knowles [1982] looks at the quantity-quality&#13;
issue for rural and urban areas in Kenya. They find that higher educational&#13;
attainment is positively related to fertility in rural areas; but, in urban&#13;
areas, neither enrollment rates nor wife's expectations regarding children's&#13;
education had a signficiant effect on fertility. Children were evidently seen&#13;
as a "good investment" in rural areas. A doctoral dissertation by Carol Clark&#13;
[1979] on schooling decisions in rural Guatemala notes that there is an&#13;
increase in work time and a reduction in school attendance for children when&#13;
there are one or more siblings aged 15-18 in the household. Evidently,&#13;
quality and quantity in this instance are negatively related; she attributes&#13;
this to the lower income per capita associated with larger numbers of children&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
which induces greater labor supply despite the reduced opportunity cost of&#13;
children's time. A study oi families in the rice farming areas of central&#13;
Thailand by Ron and Shutjer [1982] also finds a negative relationship between&#13;
quantity and quality within a simultaneous equations framework. The income&#13;
elasticity of expected childrents education is also greater than the income&#13;
elasticity of children born, which is also in accord with the Becker model.&#13;
The value of child studies conducted at the East-West Center, based&#13;
oa surveys in the U.S., the Philippines, and the Republic of Korea found that&#13;
financial costs, including schooling, figured prominently in inducing couples&#13;
to limit their family size [Bulatao and Arnold, 1977]. Earlier research by&#13;
Eva Mueller [1972] on Taiwan, China in 1969 concluded that economic considerations&#13;
associated with costs and benefits of children, rising education and income&#13;
levels, and availability of new consumer goods all led to smaller family size&#13;
preferences and increased use of contraception. Educational aspirations of&#13;
parents for children were important.&#13;
For developed countries, the conclusion seems to be that the quantity&#13;
trade-off is negative and significant. This accords with the evidence cited&#13;
in Becker 11981, p. 111].   One of those studies, by Dennis DeTray [1978], is&#13;
noted in Table 1. Using the! data ware drawn from the 1967 round of the&#13;
National Longitudinal Survey, it found a significant negative coefficient&#13;
relating average educational level of children at home to number of living&#13;
chiildren in the family.&#13;
Some !historical eviden:ce for the presently developed countries&#13;
indicates that this negative trade-off was true once significant development&#13;
anic structural change had occurred,  Francine van de Walle [1980] studied&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
Switzerland in 1870, 1888 and 1910, and found a strong negative correlation by&#13;
cantons between marital fertility and the literacy and schooling level of&#13;
military recruits from those cantons. Peter Lindert [1978, 1980] believes&#13;
that the fertility decline in the United States (since 1800) was brought about&#13;
partly by increased relative costs of children, including educational costs.&#13;
Avery Guest and Stewart Tolnay [1981] found that fertility differentials&#13;
across states in the United States in 1870 and 1900 were strongly negatively&#13;
related to proportion of eligible children attending secondary school. The&#13;
results were less clear, however, 'or micro-data. Hashimoto [1980], in a&#13;
study of the fertility decline in Japan between 1900 and 1962, found that&#13;
child quality, as measured by the proportion of primary school graduates going&#13;
on to secondary school, was negatively related to the birth rate. The&#13;
regression coefficients were significant, however, only for a cross-sectional&#13;
analysis of prefectures in 1920 and 1935, and not for the time series&#13;
equations. W4hile the historical record on the relation of schooling to&#13;
fertility is ambiguous [e.g., Easterlin, 1976; Graff, 1979; and Knodel and van&#13;
de Walle, 1979], there is evidence of an increasingly strong quantity/quality&#13;
trade-off as development proceeds. Eva Mueller [1983] concludes that the&#13;
Becker type quantity/quality trade-off applies more to industrial societies&#13;
than to low income, rural, agrarian developing groups or regions. WIhen&#13;
education is extensive and prolonged, and when incomes are high, the negative&#13;
trade-off can be found [e.g., DeTray, 1978]. But in less developed rural&#13;
areas, the relation may be only weakly negative, zero, or even positive. The&#13;
same conclusion was also reached in a study by Birdsall and Cochrane [1982].&#13;
The evidence cited above tends to confirm it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
One additional consideration should be made in closing.   The whole&#13;
issue of children's education and parental fertility and child care behavior&#13;
involves an interchange between generations.   Economic theory has been moving&#13;
in recent years to a study oE multiple generation models. Two examples are&#13;
Birdsall and Cochrane [1982] and Willis [1982].   This paper, however, will&#13;
remain largely on a descriptive level and will examine some historical and&#13;
contemporary evidence on schooling, fertility and mortality to see what the&#13;
patterns have been.&#13;
3. The Historical Experience of Developed Countries&#13;
3.1 Fertility and Mortality Trends&#13;
The development process has, as one of its major characteristics, the&#13;
transition from high to low Levels of fertility and mortality [Kuznets, 1966,&#13;
pp. 40-56]. As a consequence, by definition all presently developed nations&#13;
have achieved a demographic transition. From that developed group (Western&#13;
and Northern Europe, Spain, Italy, the Soviet Union, Eastern Europe, the U.S.,&#13;
Canada, Australia, New Zealand, Israel and Japan), five countries were&#13;
selected for description here: the United States, England and Wales, Germany,&#13;
Sweden and Japan. The selection, was based on a desire to obtain good data for&#13;
reasonably long time periods for relatively large countries. Japan is of&#13;
interest as the most developed "non-Western" nation, while the United States&#13;
is distinguished for its early fertility transition. Britain experienced the&#13;
first industrial revolution [Landes, 1969, ch.2], Germany had a rapid&#13;
fertility decline [Knodel, 1974] arLd Sweden had a long history of excellent&#13;
demographic data. Other casess clearly could have been chosen, but those&#13;
seemed to give a good range of experiences and contexts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
The basic data are presented in Appendix Tables A.1 to A.5. A number&#13;
of measures of fertility and mortality are included. For fertility, these&#13;
include Coale's indices of overall fertility (If), marital fertility (I ),&#13;
proportions married (I ), and illegitimate fertility (Ih); the crude birth&#13;
rate (live births per 1000 population per annum); the total fertility rate&#13;
(TFR) (the sum of age-specific birth rates for women aged 15 to 44); and the&#13;
net reproduction rate (NRR) (the sum of age-specific female birth rates for&#13;
women aged 15-49, adjusted for the mortality of women between birth and the&#13;
child-bearing ages). A definition of the Coale indices is given in Table&#13;
A.6. Basically, If measures the number of births generated by a female&#13;
population relative to the number of births they would have generated were&#13;
they to experience the age-specific marital fertility rates of U.S. Hutterite&#13;
women in the 1920s (the highest fertility group ever observed).    I gives&#13;
the same ratio for married women in a given population. So, for example,&#13;
total women in England and Wales in 1851 produced 35% (I = .349) as many&#13;
births as they would have if they had experienced Hutterite fertility rates.&#13;
Similarly, married women in England and Wales in 1851 produced almost 68%&#13;
(I = .675) as many births as they would have with Hutterite fertility.&#13;
g&#13;
I is a ratio of age-weighted married women to age-weighted total women, the&#13;
weights being the Hutterite age-specific fertility rates.    Finally, Ih is&#13;
the ratio of illegitimate births to the births that non-married women would&#13;
have produced with Hutterite fertility. The total fertility rate (TFR)&#13;
basically gives the number of births a woman would have if she experienced the&#13;
current period fertility rates over her reproductive lifetime. The net&#13;
reproduction rate gives the number of girls surviving to adulthood that a&#13;
woman produces. A replacement level of NRR is 1.0. The mortality measures&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
include q(l5), the proportion of children dying between birth and age 15 (from&#13;
period life tables); the infant mortality rate (IMR), or deaths before age one&#13;
per 1000 live births; and the cru(de! death rate (CDR), or deaths per 1000&#13;
population per annum.&#13;
The data are of reasonable quality, particularly those from Germany&#13;
and Sweden |Knodel, 1974; Hofsten and Lundstrom, 1976].    The early English&#13;
birth data suffer from some underregistration, but it is not overly serious&#13;
[Teitelbaum, 19I74]. The U.S. data consist of a large number of estimates,&#13;
because of the absence of vital registration in most states prior to the early&#13;
20th century. The Japanese data are quite reliable after 1920, but are of&#13;
lesser quality prior to that date ITaeuber, 1958].&#13;
In general, England (TabLe A.1) experienced its demographic&#13;
transition ifrom the 1870s onward, with a sustained decline in fertility&#13;
beginning then from a TFR of about 4.7 Mortality appears to have declined&#13;
from the 1860s, but only had a sustained decline from the 1890s. The&#13;
fertility decline was largely caused by reductions in fertility within&#13;
marriage (I ) and not by changes in nuptiality (I ).    Germany (Table A.2)&#13;
followed a similar pattern, with a sustained decline in fertility dating from&#13;
roughly the 1870s and mortality beginnnng its decline at about the same time.&#13;
The data for Germany do not furnish a TFR, but the If of .428 in 1875 would&#13;
correspond to a TFR of about 5 to 6. Again, marital fertility was the source&#13;
of the change, since nuptiality (I ) remained virtually unchanged between&#13;
Y in&#13;
1875 and 1925. The third European country considered, Sweden (Table A.3),&#13;
also did nol: undergo a fertililty transition until the latter half of the&#13;
nineteenth cenlury. Fertility did not begin to decline until the 1860s, as&#13;
measured by If, and the TFE diii not commence its sustained decline until&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
after 1880. Mortality seems to have begun its irreversible reduction during&#13;
the period 1860-1880. With the notable exception of France [van de Walle,&#13;
19741, the countries of western and northern Europe underwent their fertility&#13;
declines period between 1880 and 1914 [Lesthaeghe, 1977, p. 4]. Mortality&#13;
frequently declined concurrently, or with a lag of a decade or two.&#13;
The United States (Table A.4) was somewhat different. Fertility (as&#13;
measured by the TFR or CBR) declined in the United States throughout the&#13;
nineteenth century from very high levels, e.g., a TFR of 7-8 in 1800 for the&#13;
white population. This decline is, in fact, historically quite unusual, since&#13;
the United States was not urban or industrial to any significant extent until&#13;
the latter half of the century. (France is another exceptional case of&#13;
sustained pre-industrial fertility decline.) The U.S. experience has prompted&#13;
a fairly considerable literature on the role of land availability and child&#13;
costs as factors in the fertility decline [Yasuba, 1962; Forster and Tucker,&#13;
1972; Easterlin, 1971, 1976]. Mortality, by contrast, did not seem to exhibit&#13;
a sustained downward trend until after about 1880.&#13;
Japan (Table A.5) was, in contrast to the United States, a later&#13;
participant in the demographic transition. As indicated by the CBR, the&#13;
fertility decline began only after about 1920. There is, however, reason to&#13;
suspect the accuracy of the numbers prior to 1920 [Mosk, 1977, pp. 657-658;&#13;
Taeuber, 1958, pp. 40-44]. Nonetheless, after 1920, fertility decreased&#13;
consistently, from a TFR of nearly 5.5 to 2.0 in 1959/61. Mortality also&#13;
declined after 1920, concurrently with fertility. Japan thus appears to have&#13;
had simultaneous mortality and fertility declines, unlike the United States,&#13;
where fertility declined before mortality.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
These historical demographic levels and trends from developed&#13;
countries can be contrasted with the contemporary experience of developing&#13;
nations.  Several points stancl out. First, levels of fertil ity prior to the&#13;
onset of the fertility transition were, with the exception oF the&#13;
land-abundant United States, relat:ively moderate (with TFRs in the range of&#13;
4-6). Many LDCs have (or had)l TFRs above 6 (see section 4 below). Second,&#13;
the pace of decline was slower h:istorically for the developed countries.&#13;
Third, unlike the experience of rnost developing nations since World War II,&#13;
mortality clecline did not necessarily precede the fertility transition.&#13;
Mortality reduLCtion was either sirnultaneous with or later than the fertility&#13;
declines in all five cases presented here.  Fourth, mortality levels&#13;
historically were high, even during the transition. Life expectancy&#13;
corresponding to the q(15)s in Tables 3-7 ranged from about 37 to 48 years for&#13;
the pre-transition period, in contrast to 50-70 years in most LDCs today.&#13;
Finally, as a result of lower fertility and higher mortality, the proportion&#13;
of children (below age 15) was historically lower in developing countries&#13;
(30-40 percent) than in tcday's LDCs (with 40-50 percent below age 15). Thus,&#13;
historically, the demographic transitions of the developed countries were&#13;
rather different from those of today's LDCs [see Kuznets, 1954; Teitelbaum,&#13;
1975].&#13;
3.2 Enrollment Rates&#13;
Tables A.1 to A.5 also present data on school enrollment, using gross&#13;
enrollment rates (GERs). For each of the five countries, information was&#13;
collected on primary and secondary school enrollment (however defined by the&#13;
country). Census data on the school age population was also sought, but these&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
were only approximate since the census data appeared in the standard reference&#13;
sources in quinquennia 5-9, 10-14, and 15-19. Most primary schooling takes&#13;
place between the ages 6-13 and most secondary schooling between the ages&#13;
14-18. As a compromise in the computation of GERs, primary enrollment was&#13;
related to children 5-14, secondary enrollment to children 10-19, and primary&#13;
plus secondary enrollment to children 5-19. While this may create some&#13;
variations due to differences in compulsory school ages, age structures, and&#13;
age misreporting, it was felt that use of the same age categories for the&#13;
denominators for all countries would facilitate comparisons. Probably greater&#13;
error is introduced by variations in attendance rates or in differing lengths&#13;
of school year. Another problem associated with school enrollment figures is&#13;
that they do not always cover the whole period of the demographic transition&#13;
(e.g., for the United States). This was especially true for data on secondary&#13;
schools.&#13;
Bearing these qualifications in mind, it appears that, as of the&#13;
mid-nineteenth century, there were considerable differences among these five&#13;
countries in degree of educational participation. In 1850 in the United&#13;
States, 47 percent of the total population aged 5-19 and 56 percent of the&#13;
white population in the same age group were enrolled in primary and secondary&#13;
school. This contrasts with a mere 8 percent of children aged 5-14 enrolled&#13;
in primary school in England and Wales in 1851. By 1870, the primary GER had&#13;
risen in England to 26 percent, but by that date it was 74 percent in the&#13;
United States, 64 percent in Germany and 57 percent in Sweden. Even&#13;
late-comer Japan had achieved a primary GER of 35 percent by 1888. In&#13;
England, Germany, Sweden and Japan the primary GER peaks out at about 70-80&#13;
percent. In Germany, the peak was reached in 1939, in England in 1931, in&#13;
Sweden in 1910, and in Japan in 1940. Niot too much can be made of these&#13;
differences, since they likely reflect differences in compulsory schooling&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
a;es.  This is indicated by the U.S. data, with primary GER's peaking at 97&#13;
percent in 1940 but whose population was no more literate than the other&#13;
developed nations at that ti-me.&#13;
Secondary GERs are, as one would expect, much lower. Initial&#13;
observations for these range from C.86 percent for the United States in 1870&#13;
to 1.44 percent for England in 1904. The secondary GERs increase in relative&#13;
terms much faster, reflecting the growing importance of extencded human capital&#13;
investment during modernization and industrialization. By 1970, the secondary&#13;
GER was 54 percent for England ancL Wales; 61 percent for Sweden; 52 percent&#13;
for the Federal Republic of Germany; 50 percent for the U.S.; and 53 percent&#13;
for Japan. Secondary gross enrollment rates have thus continued to grow,&#13;
while primary rates have leveled off, reflecting the very high levels of&#13;
primary enrollment which had been achieved in all five of those developed&#13;
countries by the time of the First World War. Increases in secondary&#13;
enrollment have continued past the mid-point of the twentieth century.&#13;
3.3 Graphical Relationships Between Fertility and School Enrollment,&#13;
1850-1960&#13;
Somae patterns appear in the data, graphed in Figure 1.  First, there&#13;
was not a particularly good correlation between the level of the primary&#13;
school enro'Llment rate and the date of fertility decline. This may perhaps be&#13;
better seen in Table 3. The level of the primary GER at the onset of&#13;
fertility decline ranged from 38 percent (England and Wales) to 65-66 percent&#13;
(Germany and Japan). Sweden's was probably below 57 percent, although&#13;
sustained decliLne in TFR (as opposed to If and CBR) began only in 1880, when&#13;
the primary GE11 was about 59 percent. For the decade during which the CBR&#13;
fell below 30, never to rise above it again, there was a range of primary GERs&#13;
of 65-92 percent.  Finally, for the date at which marital fertility (I )&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
fell irreversibly by 10%, there was a range of primary GERs of 60-74 percent.&#13;
The conclusion seems to be that a substantial level of primary GER had to be&#13;
attained (e.g. above 50-60 percent of population aged 5-14) before significant&#13;
fertility declines would occur. The U.S., with its early fertility decline,&#13;
was probably an exception. England and Wales was likely not an exception,&#13;
since its late fertility decline did not accelerate until primary GER was&#13;
above about 60 percent.&#13;
A second conclusion is that secondary GERs also showed considerable&#13;
variation with respect to the dates of fertility decline, but that they did&#13;
not have to rise above 5-6 percent of population aged 10-19 before significant&#13;
declines would occur. The primary GER did not rise too much after fertility&#13;
decline had become significant (e.g., a 10 percent decline in marital&#13;
fertility), but the secondary GER continued to rise through the very low&#13;
fertility rates of the present. It seems that the quantity-quality trade-off&#13;
was related to the trend in the secondary GER, but not much to the trend in&#13;
primary GER. A substantial initial level of primary GER seems to have been a&#13;
prerequisite for substantial irreversible fertility declines, however.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-24 -&#13;
ENGLAND AND WALES&#13;
Figure 1: Fertility and Enrollment&#13;
N X \           .                         Trends in Five Developed&#13;
......'  -                               Countries, 1800-1960&#13;
,@   J        -  z                                 FSS~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~RMARY&#13;
28  /                                          ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~------- SECON,DARY&#13;
TOTAL FERTILITY RATE&#13;
Mi-  1M1I  1;7!   .sm;   llB1  19111  iI   1021   1131   1941   1391  CCI&#13;
GERMANY                                               JAPAN&#13;
1W r                                                  1W :7 &#13;
70-                                                  70 3-                 /.-2&#13;
60-~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
2e~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~- - I22 &#13;
ml-                                                    leg&#13;
N WDE                                              NNTDSAE&#13;
3-           N                                                               N .   .   .   .   .   ,   ,   ,   . -   ,   ,  &#13;
1_9  1e1  w6  I9                                                                 '. 13 - _1 k1  91 1 1  @}1 11   8   17   _11  #  &#13;
N                         Z &#13;
of  40804                                                0&#13;
209                                       92         20&#13;
1887  1877  188  197  1 987  1917  1927  1937  1947  1997  1888  99  988 19 18 al  1928  1938  1948  958s&#13;
YEAR                                                 YEAR&#13;
SWEDEN                                            UNITED STATES&#13;
s- &#13;
73  --  \~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~NN                 73~3  m--&#13;
N~~~~~~&#13;
N~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.. ...&#13;
lesIislii  s~Iss I'M i, Iss Ii   I;   ei   ~   I9   '   m   Il   1is o   a'   911Illlll~~1,   e~   gm  B~Ne  IisS~ Ii   s&#13;
N                                              N YE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
Table 3:  Relationship between Gross School Enrollment Rates&#13;
and Fertility Decline, Five Developed Countries&#13;
Gross Enrollment Rate (%)&#13;
Country                   Event/Date                      Primary    Secondary&#13;
1. England &amp;      (a)  Date of onset of fertility&#13;
Wales               decline:   ca. 1875.                   38      below 1.4&#13;
(b) Decade in which CBR falls&#13;
below 30 (never to rise&#13;
above it again): 1890's.               65      below 1.4&#13;
(c) Date at which marital&#13;
fertility declines 10%:   1892         60      below 1.4&#13;
2. Germany        (a)  Date of onset of fertility&#13;
decline: ca. 1875                      66             2.3&#13;
(b) Decade in which CBR falls&#13;
below 30 (never to rise&#13;
above it again.): 1880's               72             4.7&#13;
(c) Date at which marital&#13;
fertility declines 10%:   1890         74             3.6&#13;
3. Sweden         (a)  Date of onset of fertility&#13;
decline.   ca 1860               below 57      below 1.3&#13;
(b) Decade in which CBR falls&#13;
below 30 (never to rise above&#13;
it again):   1880's                    69             1.4&#13;
(c) Date at which marital&#13;
fertility declines 10%: 1900           69             1.8&#13;
4. U.S.A.         (a)  Date of onset of fertility&#13;
decline:   ca 1800               below 74      below 1.3&#13;
(b) Decade in which CBR falls&#13;
below 30 (never to rise&#13;
above it again):   1910's              92             9.1&#13;
(c)  Date at which marital                  -               -&#13;
fertility declines 10%: n.a.&#13;
5. Japan          (a)  Date of onset of fertility&#13;
decline:   1920?                       65             2.6&#13;
(b) Decade in which CBR falls&#13;
below 30 (never to rise above&#13;
it again):   1930's                    70             5.6&#13;
(c) Date at which marital&#13;
fertility declines 10%: 1932           69             5.4&#13;
Sources: Tables A.1 - A.5.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
3.4 The Costs of Education&#13;
Costs of education, as mentioned above, would include direct and&#13;
indirect costs. Direct costs would comprise school fees, books, supplies,&#13;
school uniforTns, etc.  Caldwell [1982, ch. 10] also contends that children&#13;
who attend school receive more andi better quality resources than if they were&#13;
not attending school.   The indirect costs would he the opportunity cost of&#13;
the child's time in terms of foregcne labor.    Opportunity cost of the&#13;
rnother's t-ime, while definitely important in the cost of the child, would&#13;
seem to have less bearing directly on education cost. One exception might be&#13;
the de facl:o child care services furnished by schools.    Another possible&#13;
influence is the positive correlation between mother's education, and hence&#13;
the opportunity cost of her time, and her educational aspirations for the&#13;
child. Some of the difficulties in defining the cost of children have been&#13;
discussed in Birdsall, Cochrane and van der Gaag [1983] and in Espenshade&#13;
[1972].&#13;
It is not especially easy to obtain information on historical&#13;
education costs. One area for which data are available is the United&#13;
States.   (Fishlow, 1966; Solmon &amp; Tierney, 1980; Solmon, 1975.1     Some&#13;
information on this appears in TabLes 4 and 5. There it is evident that&#13;
educational expenditures grew over the period 1840 to 1900, with expenditures&#13;
per pupil and expenditures as a share of GNP rising. The share of government&#13;
spending rose from 47 percent of total direct costs (expenditures) in 1850 to&#13;
79 percent in 1900.   Thus total direct cost per pupil rose frorm $6.25 to&#13;
$16.78 in current dollars (or about $7.11 to $16.78 in dollars of 1900). Of&#13;
this, private expenditure per pupil rose from only $3.31 in 1850 to $3.52 in&#13;
1900 in current dollars, and it actually fell from $3.77 to $3.52 in dollars&#13;
of 1900. The government was clearly picking up a much larger share of the&#13;
total direct burden of eduzation over time. This burden only amounted to 1.7&#13;
percent of GNP by 1900 and of that the government was assuming 80%.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
Table 4:  Expenditures on Education in the United States, 1840-1900 (currenit dollars)&#13;
PublIc         Public           Direct&#13;
Direct      %                   Total      Direct      Resource    Outlays        Outlays           Expend.&#13;
Direct    Public      Direct   Opport.    Resource   Expend.     Costs       Relative to    Relative to       Per&#13;
Expend    Outflows    Expend.  Cost       Coqt       Relative    Relative    Total Govt.    State &amp; Local     Pupil&#13;
Year   ---.( million)----    Public   ---( million)----     to GNP      to GNP      Spending       Expenditures      (3)&#13;
1840     9.2        n.a.       n.a.                            .006&#13;
1850    16.2        7.6       47                               .007                                                     6.25&#13;
1860    34.7       19.9       57       24.8       59.5         .008         .014        .13            .21             6.39&#13;
1870    95.4       61.7       65                               .013                     .10            .22            13.19&#13;
1880   106.4       81.5       77       72.1      178.5        0.11          .018        .14            .26             9.89&#13;
1890   187.3      147.4       79                               .015                     .17            .26            14.52&#13;
1900   289.6      229.9       79      213.9      503.5         .017         .029        .16a           .25a           16.78&#13;
a   1902.&#13;
Source: Fishlow (1966).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
Table 5:   RelatiVe Educational Expenditures:&#13;
U.S., U.K., andL Germany 1860-1900 (Current ;)&#13;
Expenditure              Income       Expendisture&#13;
GCuntry               Year     ($ million)  % of GNP    per capita  per pupil&#13;
($)          ($)&#13;
United States         1860          35            .8         126         6.39&#13;
1880         106          1.1          197         9.89&#13;
1900         290          1.7          227        16.78&#13;
United Kingdom        1860          -             -            -&#13;
1880          59            .9         186        15.49&#13;
1900         124           1.3         241        16.40&#13;
Germany               1860          24           1.0 /a       60         5.95 /b&#13;
1880          70           1.6 /a       94         9.91&#13;
1900         160           1.9 /a      144        14.57&#13;
/a % of NNP; /b 1867&#13;
Source:   Fishlow (1966).   Estimates of income per capita prior to 1900(a)&#13;
U.S.: Berry (1978), Table 1B.    United Kingdom:   Mitclhell (1975).&#13;
Germany, Hoffmann (1965). Pupils: Banks (1971) adjusted in 1880 for&#13;
the U.K. for secondary enrollment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
Indirect costs (i.e. opportunity cost of children's work foregone)&#13;
were considerably larger, and amounted to 42 percent of total resource costs&#13;
in 1860, 40 percent in 1880, and 42 percent in 1900. A somewhat higher&#13;
fraction for indirect costs was found by Solmon for 1880 and 1890, being 58&#13;
and 57 percent respectively. [Solmon, 1975; and Solmon &amp; Tierney, 1980]. The&#13;
ratio of indirect to direct costs were .715, .678, and .739 for the three&#13;
years, respectively. If one adds together opportunity cost and total private&#13;
direct cost, one finds that the proportion of total private cost (direct and&#13;
indirect) which was due to opportunity cost rose from .626 in 1860 to .743 in&#13;
1880 to .782 in 1900. In the United States in the late nineteenth century, it&#13;
was clearly becoming increasingly expensive to educate children, not because&#13;
direct private out-of-pocket costs were great (they were not), but because the&#13;
opportunity cost of a child not working was becoming greater. Opportunity&#13;
cost per child was rising (from $4.52 in 1860 to $6.72 in 1880 to $11.43 in&#13;
1900 in current dollars) for a number of reasons: longer school attendance&#13;
per year, longer number of years in school per student, rising child wages,&#13;
and an increased number of pupils in urban, industrial employment where the&#13;
opportunity cost of education was much higher. The much lower opportunity&#13;
cost of education, particularly primary education, in rural areas was apparent&#13;
in the United States in the late nineteenth century and probably played a role&#13;
in the differentially higher fertility of rural areas, and particularly in the&#13;
South, in the late 19th century [Tolnay, Graham, and Guest, 1982].&#13;
In the other countries for which data are readily available, Table 10&#13;
indicates that Germany systematically spent a higher proportion of its&#13;
national product on education while England (in this case taken as the United&#13;
Kingdom) spent somewhat less than the United States. In terms of expenditure&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
per pupil in relationship to GNP, Germany seems to have had a ratio of per&#13;
pupil spending to national product: per capita in the range .09 to .10, while&#13;
the U.K. hacl a ratio in the rarLge cf .7 to .8 and the U.S. had a range of .5&#13;
to .75.  In Germany, much of the spending on education seemed to have been&#13;
governmental, Germany having had widespread compulsory, free public education&#13;
by the early part of the nineteenth century [Levasseur, 1897].  In Prussia,&#13;
the largest state in Germany, literacy was quite high, for example. In 1850,&#13;
only about 10 percent of bridegroonis were unable to sign the rnarriage&#13;
register, or,ly 5 percent of military recruits could not read, and an estimated&#13;
20 percent of the whole adult population (male and female) was illiterate. As&#13;
of 1871, only 12 percent of the adult population was enumerated as illiterate&#13;
[Cipolla, 1969]. Germany was thus, prior to the demographic transition, a&#13;
relatively well educated society.&#13;
With respect to education, Germany was similar to the United States&#13;
which, in 1850, recorded adult illiteracy of only about 10-15 percent among&#13;
the total white population aged 10 and over. This fell to 6 percent by 1900&#13;
and 3 percent by 1930. This came about in the United States without the&#13;
benefit of compulsory free public schooling. The first state to enact a&#13;
compulsory education law was Massachusetts, in 1852. Only one other state&#13;
(Vermont) had enacted a similar law by 1870, but thereafter progress in&#13;
achieving some compulsory education laws in the northern and western states&#13;
was rapid. By 1918, all states had some such laws. Many of the laws did not&#13;
enforce attendance for more than 3--5 months and common attendance ages were&#13;
set at 8-14 years [Landes and SolTnon, 1972, Table 1]. This illustrates the&#13;
diversity of the legislative environment within the United States and also the&#13;
relative lateness of legislative compulsion to primary education. (Secondary&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
education was rarely made compulsory until well into the 20th century.) It&#13;
has indeed been argued that compulsory schooling laws only came into effect&#13;
when there was already a substantially high primary enrollment rate on a&#13;
voluntary basis [Landes and Solmon, 1972].&#13;
England and Wales were a case of less governmental intervention. A&#13;
substantial role of the state in education did not come about until 1870 and&#13;
legal requirements on parents for the education of their children not until&#13;
1876 [West, 1970a]. A spate of further restrictions on parents and children&#13;
followed [Caldwell, 1982, p. 311]. Although this coincided closely with the&#13;
rise of compulsory education, there is evidence that private education had&#13;
achieved considerable success in the earlier part of the century. By 1851,&#13;
about 65-70 percent of the adult population was literate and significant&#13;
progress in private schooling was apparent [West, 1970b. Cipolla, 1969].&#13;
This belies the low enrollment rates given in Table A.1. By 1880, a&#13;
considerable amount per student was being spent in the United Kingdom. One&#13;
might compare this to an estimate by West [1970b, pp. 86-87] of about 1&#13;
percent of net national product being spent privately on education in 1833&#13;
amounting to about $6.18 per pupil. After 1870 the share of spending shifted&#13;
rapidly to the government, at least for primary education.&#13;
Sweden was rather more similar to Germany with regard to education.&#13;
It had a compulsory school system by 1842 [Jorberg, 1973, p. 386] and, in&#13;
1850, only about 10 percent of the population aged 10 and over was illiterate&#13;
[Cipolla, 1969]. Sandberg [1979] has noted the extraordinarily high level of&#13;
human capital formation relative to its level and stage of economic&#13;
development. "By the late 1860's, at the latest, Sweden had a system of&#13;
universal elementary education, and the supporting structure of teacher&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
training institutions, in full operation." [Sandberg, 1979, p. 230.] Between&#13;
1870 and 1914, primary enroLlments increased little, but educational&#13;
expenditures (largely government expenditures) per pupil increased. Sweden&#13;
also seemed t:o have had a "taste" for high secondary and university&#13;
enrollments. During the period 1870 to 1900, enrollment ratios in secondary&#13;
schools increased only modestly, but they were still among the highest in&#13;
Eu rope, indicating a strong commitment to secondary education already in the&#13;
middle of the nineteenth century.  It is significant, however, that Swedish&#13;
secondary enrollment rates and expenditures (again largely governmental) on&#13;
secondary education began a strong increase after 1900 [Sandberg, 1979, p.&#13;
231], a period coincident with its fertility decline.&#13;
Finally, there is the interesting case of Japan. Prior to the Meiji&#13;
restoration of 1868, it has been argued that there was a considerable level of&#13;
literacy and school enrollment [Dore, 1965; Rosovsky, 1966, pp. 104-106]. By&#13;
1868, about 40-50 percent of boys and 15 percent of girls were believed to&#13;
receive some schooling [Dore, 19651. Most of the pre-Meiji education was&#13;
privately funded. When the state clid begin to fund education, local&#13;
governments had to pick up most. of the burden [Rosovsky, 1966]. Private fees&#13;
continued to be a significant burden and a deterrent to attendance,&#13;
particularly in rural areas. They were abolished in 1898 and then progress&#13;
toward universal primary education resumed [Landes, 1965, p. 108]. Although,&#13;
prior to 1868, education was fairly widespread among samurai, merchants, and&#13;
richer farmers, and was reasonably secular, reforms were introduced. The&#13;
alphabet was simplified.  A Ministry of Education was established in 1871 and&#13;
the basic education system law was promulgated in 1872. The system was&#13;
standardized nationally and four years of elementary schooling were made&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
compulsory in 1886, extended to six years in 1907. Primary and secondary&#13;
school enrollment as a percentage of population 5-19 was perhaps 10 percent in&#13;
1868 [Rosovsky, 1966, p. 106] and rose to 26 percent by 1888 and 42 percent by&#13;
1908. The Japanese state began to spend heavily on education after 1900. (As&#13;
an example, in real terms [in 1910 million yen], expenditures were 1880, 10.7;&#13;
1896, 19.3; 1900, 50.2; 1910, 90.9.) [Oshima, 1965; price index from Kelley&#13;
and Williamson, 1974, Appendix 1.] The expansion of education was, however,&#13;
selective and moderately paced. [Maddison, 1969, pp. 16-17.] In 1880, 31&#13;
percent of children 5-19 were in primary and two secondary levels. This rose&#13;
to 63 percent by 1915, 86 percent by 1950, and 94 percent by 1963. In upper&#13;
secondary education, only 1 percent of the population aged 15-19 were enrolled&#13;
in 1880, but this rose to 21 percent in 1915, 71 percent in 1950, and 92&#13;
percent in 1963. [Maddison, 1969, Table 6.] Increasingly costs were borne by&#13;
the government, but private spending, particularly at the secondary and&#13;
university levels, still continued to be important. [See, for example,&#13;
Yamamura and Hanley, 1975.]&#13;
In general, from these fragmentary data one can draw some tentative&#13;
conclusions. First, for these five presently developed countries, educational&#13;
costs generally rose (in real terms) from the mid to late nineteenth century&#13;
onward. Second, government spending appeared to have taken over an increasing&#13;
share of direct costs, although this varied by country. Third, as a&#13;
consequence, direct private costs rose only slowly, if at all. Fourth,&#13;
private indirect costs rose over time for a number of reasons. Among these&#13;
were rising wages and a shift of the population from agriculture to&#13;
urban-industrial locations where opportunity costs of education at higher&#13;
levels tended to be higher. Fifth, primary school education did not seem to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
constitute much of an econonic burclen, especially after the government began&#13;
Froviding all cr part of the fees (e.g. in England after 1870 and Japan after&#13;
1898). And, sixth, the direct anc' indirect costs of secondary (and higher)&#13;
education were increasingly of consequence and so the growth of enrollments in&#13;
secondary eclucation was associated with greater parental burdens. The&#13;
evidence on this last point is, however, not abundant.&#13;
3.5 Private Returns to Schoolin&#13;
The other side of the calculation from costs is beneEits or returns.&#13;
Enfortunately, there is a distinct paucity of information on this directly.&#13;
One can infer, in the face of rising indirect private costs, that private&#13;
returns to education must have kept pace with the rise in costs in order to&#13;
keep an acceptable rate of return. Some time series data for the United&#13;
States are available [Becker, 1975, ch. VI] and indicate that since the 1930's&#13;
the private returns to a high school education have been well above 10 percent&#13;
and generally well above that of a college education. Some scanty evidence&#13;
points to a decline during the period 1900 to 1940 and then a rise in the&#13;
rates of returrn between 1940 and 1960. Other work on the U.S. [Carnoy and&#13;
Marenbach, 197';; Hlansen, 1963; Mincer, 1962] and Britain [Ziderman, 1973;&#13;
Morris and Ziderman, 1971] tend to confirm a rate of return above 10 percent&#13;
to completed secondary and completed college education. [See Blaug, 1972, pp.&#13;
224-234.]&#13;
Historical information tiends to be even more scanty, since a&#13;
relatively small proportion of aduLts had completed secondary school or&#13;
university prior to 1900, even in the industrial countries.    Schools above thei&#13;
primary level were few and smaLl, iand often specialized in subjects such as&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
preparation for the ministry, rather than in technical training. In the 19th&#13;
century (and earlier), many technicians and professionals (e.g. physicians,&#13;
lawyers) were educated on the job and/or through apprenticeships.&#13;
An important benefit of children is clearly the contribution they&#13;
make to their families.   W4hile schooling keeps children out of the labor force&#13;
at an early age, it enhances their earning potential when they eventually&#13;
enter the labor force.   Some historical research with micro-data for working&#13;
class families in the United States and Europe from the 1889/90 U.S.&#13;
Commissioner of Labor Survey [Haines, 1979a, ch. 6, 1979b, 1981, 1983] reveals&#13;
that late nineteenth century families relied heavily on the earnings of&#13;
children to make up for declining earnings of the family head. For example,&#13;
only about four percent of total income for families with household heads aged&#13;
30-39 was from children. For families with heads aged 50-59 (with older&#13;
children, on average), this proportion had risen to 33 percent. Children&#13;
often remained in the home, worked, and contributed to the family before they&#13;
left for marriage and their own household formation. This was noted for&#13;
Lancashire in England in 1851 [Anderson, 1971], for Hamilton in Canada in 1861&#13;
and 1871 [Katz and Davey, 1978], for late nineteenth century Philadelphia&#13;
[Haines, 1981; Goldin, 1979, 1981; Modell, Furstenburg, and Hershberg, 1981]&#13;
for the nineteenth century, United States generally by Kett [1973]; for&#13;
England in Pinchbeck and Hewitt [1973, ch. XIV]. The importance of children&#13;
to the family economy in Japan in the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries&#13;
has been the subject of comment [e.g. Taeuber, 1958, ch. V; Lockwood, 1954,&#13;
pp. 556-5593. Some evidence points to the fact that historically children did&#13;
indeed make substantial transfers to their parents and families. This was&#13;
noted in the report of the U.S. Commissioner of Labor on "Working Women in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
Large Cities" IU.S. Commissioner oiE Labor, 1889], which found that about half&#13;
cf single working women living at home in U.S. cities gave up their entire&#13;
Earnings to their parents. There is also support for the view that parents&#13;
kept their children in school longer if their incomes were higher, thus&#13;
investing their higher "savings" in human capital [Raines, 1979, 1983].     This&#13;
confirms the observed historical trade-off between child labor and schooling&#13;
[Ensign, 1921] and suggests, at: least by the late nineteenth century in urban,&#13;
industrial areas, that parents preferred extended children's education to&#13;
early child corLtributions to the family economy. This supports the view that&#13;
the net benefits of children to farailies were declining as parents opted in&#13;
increasing numbers to keep childrern in secondary school. Such benefits as did&#13;
occur were greatly delayed and usually reduced. For example, Modell,&#13;
Furstenberg, and Hershberg [1981, p. 335] report for Philadelphia in 1880 that&#13;
a young man or woman would spend an average of seven years in the labor force&#13;
while in their family of birth and that they would contribute to family&#13;
income.&#13;
In contrast, by 1970, children would remain only 2.5 years in their&#13;
home while working and would contribute relatively little to the family&#13;
income. Anderson [1971] and Katz and Davey [1979] indicate that this&#13;
prolonged earning period in the natal family was more a development of urban,&#13;
industrial society historically, since earlier in rural areas children had&#13;
often been sent off as servants.   Nevertheless, the shift from a substantial&#13;
benefit to family income from children's earnings (or at least the benefit of&#13;
reduced consumption requirements fromn an early child departure) to prolonged&#13;
secondary and university schooling has marked developed countries since the&#13;
Late 19th or early 20th centuries.   The ratio of benefits to costs has fallen,&#13;
and the net flow of resources appears to have shifted in favor of children as&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
the quantity-quality tradeoff operated. One further consequence of this loss&#13;
of children's income has been to create pressure for married women to enter&#13;
the labor force. This has been happening in developed countries since about&#13;
1900 and has placed additional downward pressure on fertility by raising the&#13;
shadow price of quantity (via the opportunity cost of women's time). [Tilly&#13;
and Scott, 1979; Oppenheimer, 1982.]&#13;
As a final note, it should be pointed out that the demographic&#13;
transition in those developed countries has also been accompanied by large&#13;
reductions in childhood mortality [e.g. q (15)] (see Tables A.1 to A.5).&#13;
These reductions reduced risks associated with investing in child quality and&#13;
hence reduced the cost (and price) of child quality. Although this raised&#13;
potential benefits associated with child quality, it ultimately was probably&#13;
of secondary importance to changes in demand for skilled labor which induced&#13;
increased demand for child quality by reducing its shadow price.&#13;
3.6 Other Considerations: Child Labor Laws&#13;
In general, there has been a negative correlation observed between&#13;
schooling and child labor laws [e.g. Haines, 1979. Ensign, 1971]. The&#13;
question is, however, whether the child labor laws were a major cause of&#13;
increased schooling by reducing the opportunity cost of children's time (i.e.&#13;
indirect schooling costs) and hence reducing the shadow cost (and price) of&#13;
child quality. Given the timing of these laws relative to changes in&#13;
schooling, however, it appears that compulsory education and child labor laws&#13;
rather ratified changes in demand for quality. The laws may have served to&#13;
accelerate the process to universal primary schooling but, in general, they&#13;
did not seem to cause it. This could be seen in the United States in the late&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
nineteenth century where variations in child labor were indeed negatively&#13;
correlated with child labor restrictions [liaines, 1979], but landes and Solmon&#13;
[1972] found no significant effect of child labor laws on school enrollments&#13;
in a multiple regression analysis of U.S. states in the late 19th century.&#13;
Caldwell [l1'62, p. 311] notes a number of child labor laws in 19th century&#13;
Britain [1833, 1844, 1847] which relstricted hours of work that seemed to have&#13;
little effect on fertility until they were supplemented by a rnovement to mass&#13;
education. In Germany, child labor- in mines was not severely restricted until&#13;
1903. It appears the employment of children in factories and mines (as&#13;
opposed to agriculture and domestic service) was on the declile in Europe in&#13;
the late 19th century because children became less useful [Stearns, 1967, p.&#13;
1301. An analysis of the British experience in the 19th century by Nardinelli&#13;
11980] concluded that rising real incomes and technological change were the&#13;
main causes of decline in child labor. Child labor laws only accelerated a&#13;
process already taking place. This would have created an environment&#13;
favorable to child labor legislation.   In Japan, despite some efforts to&#13;
protect children, still 23 percent of children aged 10-14 were gainfully&#13;
employed in 1920 [Taeuber, 1958, Table 27]. In sum, child labor laws did not&#13;
seem historically to have had a dramatic initial causal role in promoting&#13;
schooling by reducing the cost of child quality, although they may well have&#13;
had an effect on it once p-rimary schooling had become widespread.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
4. The Experience of Developing Countries&#13;
4.1 Fertility and Mortality Trends&#13;
For present purposes, we focus on the demographic experience of&#13;
18 LDCs, including six from Latin America, eight from Asia, and four from&#13;
Africa. These countries encompass a broad range of fertility and mortality&#13;
levels and trends over the last twenty to thirty years; some of them may be&#13;
characterized as having undergone the demographic transition to varying&#13;
degrees, while, in the others, this transition has occured only very&#13;
slightly, if at all.&#13;
Before proceeding, it is useful to bear in mind the considerable&#13;
differences in data quality of the countries chosen, a shortcoming that&#13;
largely reflects differences in methods of estimation and also coverage of&#13;
data collection. Among the countries presented below, the fertility data&#13;
are judged to be reliable only for Egypt and Tunisia in Africa; Costa Rica,&#13;
Mexico and Chile in Latin America; and Hong Kong, Singapore, Sri Lanka, and&#13;
Taiwan in Asia [UN, 1979a]. The reliability of the mortality data are&#13;
similarly weak, but since these data are presented here only for the&#13;
purpose of completing the demographic picture, this shortcoming poses no&#13;
serious problems. Despite the data flaws, however, it can be argued that,&#13;
in looking at broad changes of relationships over time, even the rough data&#13;
available to us now can provide some insights.&#13;
The simplest measures of fertility/mortality are the crude birth&#13;
and death rates.3/ In conjunction, they provide an indication of the&#13;
rapidity of population growth, but when used to compare fertility or&#13;
mortality between countries and over time they present a problem because of&#13;
3/ Defined as number of births or deaths per 1000 population.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
:heir dependence on the population age structure. Thus variations could&#13;
Lndicate a change in fertility/mortality, or a change in the age sructure,&#13;
or both. A better indicator for fertility is the total fertility rate&#13;
(TFR)4/; for mortality it is the expectation of life at birth (eO).&#13;
Si'nce this paper is not pr:imarily concerned with population growth as such,&#13;
,we can use the TFR measure for fertility; and e for mortality.&#13;
Tables B.1 to B.:L8 in Appendix B contain the fertility, mortality&#13;
and enrollment data for countries included in this study.   Orn average,&#13;
African fertility exceeds that in any other continent; within Africa,&#13;
fertility In the Eastern and Western regions are the highest, The&#13;
estimated 1980 TFR for Ghana (7.0) and Kenya (8.0) are illustrative;&#13;
moreover, f'ertility in these countries has remained stable at these high&#13;
levels for most of the last two to three decades. In Egypt and Tunisia,&#13;
fertility is somewhat lower with estimated 1980 TFR's of 4.9 and 5.3&#13;
respective:Ly. Between 1950 and L980 both countries experienced declines in&#13;
the TFR of about 20 to 25 percent. Some authors have tentatively&#13;
attributed the decline in Tunisia to government policies in the late&#13;
1960's, including family planning and improvement in the status of women.&#13;
In terms of mortality, lif'e expectancy has improved considerably since the&#13;
1950's for most of Africa, but it remains low in comparison to other parts&#13;
of the developing world; 45 years compared to 49 years in South Asia; and&#13;
62 years in East Asia and Latin America. The 1980 life expectancy in the&#13;
four countries included here exceeds the average for Africa; in Egypt,&#13;
Ghana and Kenya, it is around 55 years while in Tunisia, it is about 60&#13;
years.&#13;
4/  Definetd as the total number of children that would be born per&#13;
woman among a group passing through life subject to given age specific&#13;
fertility rates.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
In Asia, the fertility experience encompasses a wider range of&#13;
levels and trends. For Hong Kong, Singapore, the Republic of Korea and in&#13;
Taiwan, China, the estimated 1980 TFR does not exceed 3.0; thus in these&#13;
countries, fertility is comparable to the level characteristic of Western&#13;
industrialized countries. On the other hand, India and the Philippines&#13;
continue to experience high fertility although the level is not nearly as&#13;
high as in parts of Africa. For Sri Lanka and Thailand, fertility is at&#13;
moderate levels. In terms of trend, the most dramatic declines took place&#13;
in the first four East Asian countries listed above; from 1950 to 1980, the&#13;
TFR fell by between 49 and 72 percent, the largest decline having occurred in&#13;
Singapore. The remaining Asian countries have also experienced declines in&#13;
this period, although the rate of decline had been slower, averaging 20 to&#13;
40 percent. As with fertility, mortality conditions in the four Asian&#13;
countries with the lowest fertility compare favorably with that in Western&#13;
countries; in 1980, life expectancy ranges from 74.5 years in Hong Kong to&#13;
65.4 years in the Republic of Korea. In the remaining countries, it is over&#13;
60 years in Thailand, Philippines, and Sri Lanka, but only 51.8 years in India.&#13;
Among Latin America countries considered, only Barbados and Chile&#13;
have a 1980 TFR not exceeding 3.0. Of the six countries included, Mexico&#13;
probably has the highest fertility with a TFR of 5.1 in 1980. All six&#13;
countries, however, share the common experience of a fertility decline in&#13;
the three decades preceding 1980; the decline is over 40 percent in Colombia&#13;
and Costa Rica; over 30 percent in Barbados, Chile and Brazil; but only 25&#13;
percent in Mexico. As with the Asian countries, life expectancy is generally&#13;
high in Latin America. In Barbados and Costa Rica, it exceeds 70 years,&#13;
while in none of the remaining four countries does it fall below 62 years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
4.2 Enrollment Trends&#13;
Gross Enrollment rates (GERs) for primary and secondary schools&#13;
are used as indicators of the level of children's schooling Ln this study.&#13;
They are defined as the ratio of school enrollment at a given educational&#13;
level to the total population in the corresponding age range.5/   The&#13;
reliability of these statistics for time series and cross country&#13;
comparisons depends on the re]Liab;ility of both the denominator and&#13;
numerator in each case; the former is likely to be inaccurate because of&#13;
age-misreporting, and the latt:er, because of incomplete coverage of the&#13;
school population, a problem which arises, for example, when privately&#13;
enrolled students are omitted through lack of information on them. Thus,&#13;
differences between countries and trends within countries probably cannot&#13;
be entirely attributed to genuine differences or change in enrollment.    In&#13;
some countries, even assuming data reliability, comparisons are difficult&#13;
to make because of changes in the age range corresponding to school&#13;
enrollment at a given level; for example, in Brazil, the erratic movements&#13;
in the primary school GER betweeni 1965 and 1975 is partly due to this&#13;
problem.&#13;
A peculiarity of the GEEL is that theoretically it does not have a&#13;
well-defined upper limit, since its numerator, is not confined to the same&#13;
age range aLs its denominator.6!/ Thus a GER that exceeds 100 percent not&#13;
5/ For most countries, the age range for primary enrollment is 6 to&#13;
11; and 12 to 17 for secondary enrollment.&#13;
6/ The net enrollment ratio is EL better statistic to use, siLnce the&#13;
age range is the same for both its numerator and denominator.&#13;
However, it requires more information to construct, and is thus&#13;
not readily available for all the years and countries included in&#13;
this study. For this reason, we have chosen the gross enrollment&#13;
rate as the indicator.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
only means that enrollment is high but also that some of the pupils at that&#13;
level of schooling are overage. For the purpose of this paper, the GER is&#13;
used to indicate the extent to which parents invest in their children by&#13;
schooling them. A GER greater than 80 percent may be interpreted as&#13;
corresponding to a situation where the tradition of sending children to&#13;
school is fairly well-established, although by no means pervasive. For a&#13;
country to be described as having attained universal education at a given&#13;
level would probably require a GER exceeding at least 110 pecent.&#13;
Among the four African countries, Kenya and Tunisia boast a&#13;
primary school GER of around 100 percent in the late seventies compared to&#13;
around 70-75 percent in Egypt and Ghana. Considering the level from which&#13;
these countries started two to three decades ago, the gains in enrollment&#13;
are especially remarkable; for example, the primary school GER was merely&#13;
32 percent for Ghana in 1950 and Kenya in 1955. Similar gains in secondary&#13;
school enrollment have been made; for example by the late 1970's the GER in&#13;
Egypt was three times the level in 1960; in Ghana it was 36 times the 1950&#13;
level. However, in Kenya and Tunisia, the secondary school enrollment&#13;
appears to have grown at a slower rate, possibly reflecting the greater&#13;
emphasis of public policies on the first level of education compared to the&#13;
second level.&#13;
In Asia, primary school enrollment has been at a high level since&#13;
the 1950's for most of the countries in our sample. For example, the&#13;
primary school GER in 1955 exceeded 80 percent in the Philippines,&#13;
Singapore, the Republic of Korea, Taiwan, China and possibly also Sri&#13;
Lanka; however, enrollment has increased steadily, and by the late&#13;
1970's, many of the Asian countries in this study had attained or are&#13;
close to attaining universal primary education; the only exceptions are&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
India and Thailand, where the GER is around 80 percent.  At the secondary&#13;
level, enrollment in no part of Asia, except perhaps in Taiwan, China&#13;
and in the Republic of Korea, are at the level characteristic of the&#13;
more developed countries. Nevertheless, in terms of growth, enrollment&#13;
has shot up dramatically in all of them in the last three decades.&#13;
Around 1980, the secondary school. GER was below 60 percent only for&#13;
Thailand (29 percent) and 'India (27 percent).&#13;
The six Latin American countries included in this study all&#13;
boast high levels of primary school enrollment; not only do the statistics&#13;
indicate that there is a well-established norm of schooling c:hildren,&#13;
but they also suggest that by the late 1970's, almost all school-age&#13;
children attend primary school.  However, at the secondary level,&#13;
enrollment is high only in Barbac[os, which in 1978 had a GER of 72 percent,&#13;
For the remaining countries, the secondary GER in the late 1970's was&#13;
below 50 percent, except in Chile where it was 55 percent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
4.3 Graphical Relationships Between Fertility and Enrollment, 1950-1980&#13;
Figures 2 to 4 graph the fertility and enrollment trends for the&#13;
18 countries included in this study. These graphs reveal several&#13;
interesting patterns:&#13;
(i) with rare exceptions, the primary school GER is at least 75 percent&#13;
before a sustained decline in fertility can be discerned;&#13;
(ii) the decline in fertility is most significant in countries in which&#13;
the primary GER has already stabilized beyond the 100 percent level, for&#13;
example in Chile, Costa Rica, Barbados, Singapore, the Republic of Korea,&#13;
Taiwan, China and Hong Kong;&#13;
(iii) as the primary GER increases it is possible for fertility to&#13;
increase at the same time as was the case between 1950 and 1960 in Costa&#13;
Rica, Chile and Hong Kong;&#13;
(iv) in quite a few countries, increases in the primary GER has not been&#13;
accompanied by reductions in the total fertility rate, particularly when&#13;
enrollment was rising from low levels. This relationship is apparent for&#13;
various time periods in Colombia, Mexico, India, Egypt, Tunisia, and most&#13;
notably in Kenya and Ghana;&#13;
(v) a downward trend in the total fertility rate is sometimes&#13;
unaccompanied by increases in primary school enrollment, as in Thailand and&#13;
Egypt; and finally;&#13;
(vi) a negative relationship between schooling and fertility trends is&#13;
more frequently observed when the schooling indicator is secondary rather&#13;
than primary enrollment; note especially the experience of Singapore, the&#13;
Republic of Korea, Chile, Taiwan and China,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
Figure 2: Fertility aid Enrollment Trends in Latin America, 1950-1980&#13;
COLOMBIA                                         BRAZIL_&#13;
I-    __           -              -  8          lSa&#13;
7                                               7&#13;
tt~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ -                    - &lt;  -   -   - i  - 3  -   -   -   -   -   - -&#13;
129&#133;-..                                         -'25&#13;
ae                 '      |N                                         . . e   e       e&#13;
75  e4                                          76 Ie                                4&#13;
se'-                                             e--&#13;
2                                               2&#13;
25         ...                      ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~25-.-&#13;
a -i'- ' '- ' - - -   ' '-'-I- *  *, I,*.,,,,  .   r                                 S1 -llllllll-&#13;
low   9     9e . . .ees  1e 979  t975   9       ,6.            .5 9   965  . 97. . 975  98e&#13;
YEAR                                            YEAR&#13;
C  RICA                                         CHILE&#13;
12 15 55--                                                                            S8&#13;
8      T X |~~~                 e          e &#13;
N~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
leDe   55   1n    9|    ee   ses   1a          tsee   l5     9e   ss    9e   95    Xe&#13;
--'' 5,.                  ----.-  N&#13;
- 4           7Y                                   4&#13;
5  5                            .-........~~~~~~~~~~~~~~...... &#13;
25-               ....2.             . .......   r &#13;
lose  9S   199  65   7         lo7 w         INS I99  99  99e9  ;969  197q  1975  9ose&#13;
YEAR                                            YEARt&#13;
MEXICO                                         BARBADOS&#13;
7~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
25&#133;-.25-.&#13;
-- -- - .  . .. . .. N&#13;
ID"9.          ~ 711  175   lowI=               95                          o&#13;
YER               P3:AR                      YA&#13;
.... SEODR&#13;
N   _ TTLFR3_TYRT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
Figure 3: Fertility and Enrollment Trends in Asia, 1950-1980&#13;
SINGAPORE                                            INDIA&#13;
6e-                                     _|         1s- &#13;
-7                                    -~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~7&#13;
1267  _125-&#13;
|3g" p        0\0             10Q5;                     /                   00&lt;2~~~~~~-5100&#13;
PHILIPPINES~~~                                SR8AK&#13;
We-   . .  -6&#13;
.- .2 ........&#13;
-2~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
I6e   1      I      6    i97 1s6      gs           1   se  975  s1Q78 8            s7s   ls&#13;
YEAR                                               YEAR&#13;
PHILIPPINES                                         SRI LANKA&#13;
------ SECONDARY&#13;
2-                                        T25R&#13;
76     . . . . . . . .&#13;
110;8'  1965  960  1Q65  1979  17     1Q8  1956 as  ls    1Q5   Iwe    Q6   1979   1975  1lo8&#13;
YEAR                                  ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~YEAR&#13;
PRIMARY&#13;
.----SECOlNDARY&#13;
- -. TOTAL FERTnLITY RATE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-48 -&#13;
Figure 3: Continued&#13;
THAILAND                                           HONG KONG&#13;
-7                                                 -7&#13;
163::                                    12S i               '1&#13;
25_                              . .......         25- || ! |l} w   "B,-&#13;
tesit   lssb I gele  low  I ss7e  tl475  low     lb    lE    le    Iss    Is7e  1 97S  low&#13;
YER                                                YE&#13;
SOUTH KOREA                                           TAIWAN&#13;
-e                                    ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-e&#13;
N~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
7e-                                                71                                       -4 |-l_f &#13;
-2 ~   ~    - &#13;
sse   lsEs   rsilse   low  M9e  1s7b  sto"     lo   low    to"e   lows  ise   1s7s   sto"&#13;
YER                                                YEAR&#13;
PRIMARY&#13;
....SECONDARY&#13;
*--* TOTAL FEKRTnrrY RATE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
Figure 4: Fertility and Enrollment Trends in Africa, 1950-1980&#13;
EGYPT                                             TUNISIA&#13;
III.                    Si                          158                                     IS&#13;
-7&#13;
t                                                 -&#13;
tt;@-~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.. _,                     -2 ,&#13;
I.                                        kI.&#13;
IOSS         IS     5          1975  to"S          lSow  tt5   ISS   9985   1978  t9l Wm  lose&#13;
YEAR                                              YEAR&#13;
KENYA                                              GHANA&#13;
115~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0&#13;
1Om                                               158 onlw In   Io     m    178   17     o&#13;
....    SECONDAY&#13;
- -* TOTAL FERTtLr RATE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 --&#13;
Table 6: Gross Enrollment Levels at the Start&#13;
of Fertility Decline in Selected LDCs.&#13;
Start of Fertility GER at Start of Fertility Decline&#13;
Decline 1/          Primary         Secondary&#13;
American Samoa              1964                 92                85&#13;
Bahamas                     1970                153                76&#13;
Bahrain                     1966                118                42&#13;
Barbados                    1963                 80                36&#13;
Brazil                      1962                108                15&#13;
Kampachea (Cambodia)        1968                 84                10&#13;
Cape Verde                  1961                 70                 8&#13;
Chile                       1961                105                25&#13;
Taiwan                      1957                100                24&#13;
Colombia                    1962                 83                14&#13;
Costa Rica                  1961                100                27&#13;
Cuba                        1967                 118               25&#13;
Dominican Republic          1966                 91                15&#13;
Fiji                        1966                 85                20&#13;
Grenada                     1964                156                21&#13;
Guadeloupe                  1968                 148               37&#13;
Guam                        1961                100                90&#13;
Guyana                      1961                 117               44&#13;
Hong Korg                   1961                 92                30&#13;
Jamaica                     1971                 85                59&#13;
S. Korea                    1959                 96                27&#13;
Lebanon                     1965                104                22&#13;
Malaysia                    1962                 84                27&#13;
Martinique                  1969                 146               47&#13;
Mauritius                   1960                 98                24&#13;
Mexico                      1971                 104               22&#13;
Panama                      1968                103                39&#13;
Philippines                 1969                114                50&#13;
Puerto Bico                 1961                114                70&#13;
Reunion                     1960                 126               20&#13;
Singapore                   1955                 94                18&#13;
Sri Lanka                   1963                 94                31&#13;
Surinam                     19372               100                38&#13;
Thailand                    1968                 81                13&#13;
Trinidad &amp; Tobago           1960                128                14&#13;
Tunisia                     1968                107                20&#13;
Turkey                      1972                106                29&#13;
Venezuela                   1963                 95                30&#13;
AVERAGE                      --                  105               33&#13;
1/ Source: Bulatao, R.A. (1983) "Mortality Thresholds For Fertility&#13;
Transition in Developing Countries". World Bank mimeograph.&#13;
2/ Source: Unesco Statistical Yearbook 1970 and 1977.&#13;
Some data do not correspond exactly to the start of the fertility&#13;
decline. They refer to one year earlier for Kampachea, Cape Verde,&#13;
Chile, Costa Rica, Fiji, Hong Kong, Jamaica, Martinique andi Mexico;&#13;
two years earlier for Bahamas, and Surinam; one year later for&#13;
Barbados, S. Korea, Philippines, and Turkey; two years later for&#13;
Venezuela; three years later for Malaysia; four years later for Guyana&#13;
and E'aerto Rico; between 1955-60 for Taiwan, China; and between&#13;
1960--65 for Brazil and Sri Lanka,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
Table 6 provides corroborating evidence supporting the idea that&#13;
a threshold in primary school enrollment is usually reached before a&#13;
sustained decline in fertility takes place. The dates at which fertility&#13;
start declining have been derived by Bulatao (1983) based on assessment of&#13;
the level and rate of decline. The data show that at the onset of decline,&#13;
most LDCs were either fairly well on their way to attaining universal&#13;
primary education, or had already attained it. Thus only eight of the 39&#13;
LDCs had a primary GER below 90 percent at the time of fertility decline,&#13;
and the lowest GER among these countries was 70 percent, for Cape Verde.&#13;
At the secondary level however, a threshold condition is much less&#13;
apparent, given the greater variation in enrollment ratios. If it exists,&#13;
the threshold would be lower since the average secondary GER at the start&#13;
of fertility decline was only 33 percent compared to 103 perent at the&#13;
primary level.&#13;
To summarize, there is some indication that in the LDCs the&#13;
quantity-quality trade-off exists at best weakly in the early stages of&#13;
development when child-quality investments refer mainly to primary&#13;
schooling. However, in the more advanced LDCs where universal primary&#13;
education has been more or less established, declines in fertility are&#13;
invariably associated with rising secondary school enrollment. This&#13;
pattern of relationships probably reflects various characteristics of&#13;
schooling at the primary and secondary levels, including cost&#13;
considerations. In addition, differences in financial arrangements and in&#13;
parental aspirations for children's education at various stages of&#13;
development are also likely to affect the nature of the quantity-quality&#13;
relationship. Some of these factors are discussed below.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
4.4  The Private Cost of Education&#13;
What economic burden is borne by families when children are sent&#13;
to school? To answer thiis question, we need at least to know the unit&#13;
private c:ost of education, that. is, the cost to households of each child -&#13;
year of schooling at different levels of education. Some of this&#13;
information is given below; however, since there are many gaps in the&#13;
available data, we can atz best only develop some generalisations on private&#13;
costs which are possibly applicable to LDCs as a whole. Clearly, the&#13;
results require confirmation by more detailed study. The data presented&#13;
below pertain solely to primary and secondary schooling, as enrollment at&#13;
those levels represent the bulk of the school population in LDCs.&#13;
(i) Direct Costs&#13;
In public primairy schools, the available data indicate that&#13;
students are normally requiried to pay only a nominal fee, if at all. For&#13;
example, in 1983 Malawian primary students pay annually between US$3 to&#13;
US$5 in the lower grades and between US$6 to US$7.50 in the upper grades,&#13;
depending on urban-rural locality. These rates represent an increase of&#13;
about 15 to 50 percent from the rates in 1982 which have been unchanged&#13;
since 1975 [Thobani, 1982]. In liaiti, annual tuition fees at the primary&#13;
level have remained at US$2.50 f'or at least 10 years.7/ In some&#13;
countries, students are exempt from fees; for example, in Indonesia, fees&#13;
were abolished in 1977 for grades I to III, and in 1978 for grades IV to VI&#13;
[Meesook, 1983].  Similarly, in Francophone African countries, students not&#13;
only attend school free-oE-charge (at least theoretically), but they are&#13;
7/ Personel communication from M. Ainsworth.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
also given free books and writing supplies [Ainsworth, 1983], and sometimes&#13;
even free school meals. There seem to be no data on the cost of other&#13;
school-related items 8t, but at the primary level, these are likely to be&#13;
small, since students normally use few books, walk to school, and eat at&#13;
home. Moreover, the cost of uniforms is probably also low, since they are&#13;
not always required, and, if required, the rule is not always enforced.&#13;
Thus students who cannot afford uniforms can still attend school in clothes&#13;
worn at other times. Another schooling cost item is parents' contribution&#13;
to parent-teacher associations or similar organisations; these&#13;
contributions, usually used to maintain school buildings or to erect new&#13;
ones, are often voluntary,and may be made in the form of cash, labor or&#13;
materials.&#13;
In most countries, the low private cost of public primary&#13;
schooling reflects governments' deliberate policy to encourage enrollment.&#13;
Widespread primary education is viewed not only as a desirable social goal,&#13;
but also as essential to economic growth [Psacharopoulos, 19821. Indeed,&#13;
there is a feeling that as a basic right in life, education should be&#13;
completely free-of-charge. For example, at the United Nations'&#13;
thirty-seventh session in March, 1983, the General Assembly urged "all&#13;
states to consider the adoption of appropriate legislative, administrative&#13;
and other measures, including material guarantees in order to ensure full&#13;
implementation of the right to universal education, through, inter-alia&#13;
free and compulsory primary education, universal and gradually&#13;
free-of-charge secondary education...&#13;
8/ Some data for Malawi have been gathered in early 1983; they are&#13;
currently being analyzed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The material cost of public primary education is thus borne&#13;
largely by public expendit:ure. On average, in 1975, more than 15 percent&#13;
of the natLonal budget in LDCs that was allocated to education went to&#13;
primary schooling [World Bank, 1980]. Nevertheless, even with this level&#13;
of spending, the public school system cannot absorb all students wishing to&#13;
enroll. There is thus some tendency to stretch the available resources by&#13;
spending less per student. The resulting low school quality, together with&#13;
lack of places, probably :Leads some parents to enroll their children in&#13;
private schools.   Where these are subsidized by the government, the private&#13;
cost of attending is kept low; but usually private schools charge high fees&#13;
and require students to purchase all their schooling needs. However, at&#13;
the primary level private school enrollment in LDCs is small, except in&#13;
Eastern Africa, and declining over time since 1965 [Tan, 1983a]9/.&#13;
At the secondary level, the private cost of public schooling&#13;
varies widely from country to country. In general, however, it is at least&#13;
as high as for primary schooling,, but more usually it is much higher. In&#13;
terms of fees alone, students pay substantially more; for eKample, in&#13;
Indonesia in 1981, these amount to about US$9 for lower secondary students,&#13;
and about US$18 for upper secondary students whereas in primary schools, no&#13;
fees are charged [Meesook, 1983]. Similarly, tuition charges range from&#13;
US$15 to IJS$75 for secondary students in Botswana, Burundi, Lesotho,&#13;
Malawi, Sierra Leone, and Zimbabwe, whereas primary students either pay no&#13;
tuition (Botswana, Burundi, Lesotho, and Zimbabwe) or pay only a nominal&#13;
9/   In 1975, private enrollment at the primary level in LDCs was 43&#13;
percent in Eastern Africa, 18 percent in Western Africa, 13&#13;
percent in Asia and Latin America and Caribbean, and 6 percent in&#13;
Europe, Middle East and North Africa.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-55 -&#13;
fee - US$1 in Sierra Leone, and less than US$8 in Malawi.-O/ In Korea,&#13;
the difference in secondary and primary school fees is even larger; in&#13;
1980, tuition for middle school ranges from US$100 to US$189, and for&#13;
general high school from US$166 to US$293 compared to US$5 to US$8 at&#13;
primary school.&#13;
Secondary students in some countries are not required to pay&#13;
tuition, such as in Guinea, Mali, Mauritania, Mauritius, Swaziland,&#13;
Tanzania, Upper Volta and Yemen Arab Republic; but there are other&#13;
expenses. In Tanzania, a 1981 survey of 4,181 students in the last year of&#13;
secondary schools revealed that those attending tuition-free state schools&#13;
spent US$139 per student for books, writing supplies, equipment,&#13;
transportation, uniforms, bedding and incidentals [Tan, 1983b]. Another&#13;
1981 survey of Colombian students in secondary schools showed that feesll/&#13;
account only for approximately 20 percent of total student expenditure&#13;
[Hinchliffe, 1983]. A study of 1,832 Indonesian students [Tjiptosamito and&#13;
Cummings, 1981] indicates that tuition charges make up only 13 to 15&#13;
percent of the total private direct cost of attending secondary school.&#13;
Moreover, since the relative scarcity of secondary schools&#13;
requires many students to board at school, additional expenses are often&#13;
incurred; for example, in 1981 boarding fees amounted to about US$83-290 in&#13;
Zimbabwe, and about US$83-110 in Malawi. In both countries, these charges&#13;
10/ The data for most of these countries are found in (Ainsworth,&#13;
1983). The author has graciously made available data&#13;
which have been painstakingly collected.&#13;
11/ Including registration, tuition, insurance and parent association&#13;
contributions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
were at le.3st two and a half times tuition fees.  Indeed, of the 23&#13;
countries i'or which data are available, only in Mauritania do students&#13;
truly enjoy nearly free public education, since the government provides&#13;
textbooks, notebooks, pens, transportation, boarding and medlcal care&#13;
[Ainsworth, 1983, Appendix A]. Thvere is also some evidence from the&#13;
Indonesian study cited above that non-fee expenses are higher for older&#13;
secondary students. For example, upper secondary pupils spent about twice&#13;
as much as their lower secondary ;peers. Their expenditure is higher, not&#13;
only on average, but also for every item of expenditure. Although the&#13;
findings cannot form a strong basis for generalization, it is probably true&#13;
that as a student progresses to higher grades in the first two levels of&#13;
education, the annual private direct cost of schooling also increases.&#13;
The preceeding paragraphs show that students incur significant&#13;
expenses in public secondary school; but if their expenses are high, they&#13;
are even higher for students attending private schools. For example, in&#13;
Colombia, private school fees in 1981 were six to fourteen times as high as&#13;
in public schools at the same level of instruction [Hinchliffe, 1983]. In&#13;
addition, the cost of most: other schooling needs are also higher; as a&#13;
result,,tbe overall expenses of private secondary students can be many&#13;
times that at public schools. In Colombia, the total private cost is about&#13;
two to three times higher, and in Tanzania, it is over three times higher.&#13;
Despite the large cost difference, however, private schools in&#13;
LDCs absorb a large proportion of the secondary school enrollment compared&#13;
to primary enrollment.12/ The dominance of private schools partly&#13;
12/ In 15175, private enrollment: at the secondary level in LDCs was 45&#13;
percent in Eastern AErica; 30 percent in Western Africa; 29&#13;
percent in Asia; 33 percent in Latin America and Caribbean; and 8&#13;
percent in Europe, Middle East and North Africa [Tan, ]L983a].&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 5 7 -&#13;
reflects the insufficiency of places in the state system, and partly also&#13;
the public's demand for an alternative system which they consider to be&#13;
superior. Whatever it reflects, however, the dominance of private schools&#13;
implies that secondary schooling is very expensive for a substantial number&#13;
of students. When compared with primary schooling, our data indicate that&#13;
even for those attending the relatively cheaper public systems, the private&#13;
direct cost of secondary schooling represents a significantly larger&#13;
financial outlay.&#13;
To return to the question of economic burden on families, there&#13;
is some indication that enrollment at the primary level probably implies&#13;
only modest increases in family expenditure on education, given the&#13;
generally low level of unit private costs. However, as educational&#13;
aspirations increase, and as families begin sending their children to&#13;
secondary school, the private financial burden of education is likely to&#13;
increase substantially, although households can still minimise the burden&#13;
by choosing different amounts of education for different children in the&#13;
family. As mentioned before, however, the direct cost of school is only&#13;
part of the cost consideration; perhaps a more important cost is the value&#13;
of the labor forgone by children attending school.&#13;
(ii) Opportunity Costs&#13;
To understand the opportunity costs involved in schooling, it is&#13;
necessary to examine the economic activities of school-age children.&#13;
Attendance at school involves an opportunity cost only if it is&#13;
incompatible with a child's work, either in terms of amount of time spent&#13;
working, or types of work activity.&#13;
According to official statistics, about four percent of the&#13;
world's population aged 15 or less participated in the labor force in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 58 -&#13;
1975 13/; most of these wor]cing ch,ildren lived in developing countries&#13;
[Mandelievich, 1979]. Children normally work as unpaid family workers,&#13;
helping on the family farm or in parents' small workshops and commercial&#13;
establishments. It is also commonly reported that even when children work&#13;
for third parties outside the family, employers frequently payr wages not to&#13;
the working child, but to his or her parents; in 1975, an estimated 80&#13;
percent of working children worldwide were unpaid family workers&#13;
[Mandelievich, 1979]. Data for the same year for Thailand show that this&#13;
arrangement is almost the sole basis on which children of all ages in the&#13;
rural areas work. In the urban areas, it is confined largely., but by no&#13;
means exclusively, to children below age ten.&#13;
Children can be found working in almost all sectors of the&#13;
economy. A relatively small proportion live in urban areas where they&#13;
normally firLd employment in the manufacturing and service seclors. Often&#13;
working in small, informal and unregistered enterprises, their range of&#13;
activities include packing, labelling, cleaning shoes, guarding parked&#13;
cars, loading and unloading goods, carrying messages and selling on the&#13;
streets. But the majority of children who work live in rural areas; hence&#13;
most working children are engaged iin agriculture.  In the early 1970's, for&#13;
example 87 percent of all working children in India were in this sector;in&#13;
Peru, the corresponding statistic was 57 percent [Mandelievich, 1979]. The&#13;
following paragraphs discuss in mor-e detail the work of childlren working&#13;
in agriculture.&#13;
13/ This figure is probably an underestimate since labor force&#13;
statistics in many countries (i) omit young workers; (ii) exclude&#13;
those who work and study; (iii) include only full-time workers;&#13;
and (iv) exclude unpaid family workers. Moreover, the data suffer from&#13;
reportiag problems, since child labor, being clandestine in most&#13;
countries, is usually concealed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 59 -&#13;
Cain's [1979] study of a village in Bangladesh provides a&#13;
detailed analysis of the kinds of rural work that children are capable of&#13;
performing at different ages. Children aged around six work at tasks which&#13;
do not require physical maturity, such as gathering fuel, picking chilies,&#13;
carrying messages, fetching water, and caring for younger children. Boys&#13;
around age eight or nine assume responsibility for herding cattle and&#13;
fishing; at age eleven, they begin agricultural work, and by age 14, they&#13;
are capable of the most demanding types of adult work, for example&#13;
transplanting paddy. Owing to the sexual division of labor in Bangladesh,&#13;
girls perform different tasks from boys. In general, Cain's data show that&#13;
they are active in adult female work such as rice processing and food&#13;
preparation by age nine or ten.&#13;
Although children are initiated into working life in early&#13;
childhood, their lack of physical stamina prevents them from working the&#13;
same hours as adults. Cain's study indicates that at age 4-6, children&#13;
work about one-fifth as long as adults, increasing to one-half as long by&#13;
ages 7-9, and to three-quarters as long by ages 10-12. Children beyond age&#13;
12 work, on average, at least the same hours as adults. There is also some&#13;
indication that it is only beyond age 12 or 13 that children's work&#13;
efficiency reaches the level of adults. Most children work on own family&#13;
farms, owing to the lack of wage employment opportunities. Their labor&#13;
contribution frees adult family members for off-farm work, but this&#13;
substitution for male adult work is probably limited in the case of young&#13;
children below age 12. However, children in the 6-9 age group can and do&#13;
substitute for women in child care duties.&#13;
Hart [1980] presents similar but less detailed data on children's&#13;
time-use patterns in a rice-growing area in Java, Indonesia. As in rural&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 60 -&#13;
BSangladesh, ch:Lldren perform work as early as at six years old. In&#13;
contrast, however, the time spent by children is not as high; for example,&#13;
in both the peak and slack sea3ons children aged 10 to 15 work on average&#13;
only 40 to 60 percent as many houris per month as do adults. Among the&#13;
poorest agricuLtural families however, children's labor participation is&#13;
higher, particularly for females, probably reflecting the lower school&#13;
attendance rate of children in this socio-economic class.   For children&#13;
aged 6 to 9 the time spent on work, including income-earning activities and&#13;
housework,is almost negligible compared to adults; this result is true in&#13;
all households, whether rich or poor, thus suggesting that at these young&#13;
ages, children's low labor participation is probably associated more with&#13;
their physical incapacity for adult work than with school attendance. Nag&#13;
et. al. [1980] also provide data on the average daily time input by&#13;
children in Nepal and anotlher village in Java. As before, children begin&#13;
participating in the family's work at early ages, but work only a fraction&#13;
of the time adults put in, particularly below age eleven. Moreover, their&#13;
tasks are concentrated in animal care (feeding), child care, and other&#13;
housework.&#13;
Evidence on the compiatibility of child labor and schooling is&#13;
provided in Caldwell et. al. [198J]X; their study is based on data from&#13;
Bangladesh for Dacca, the capital city, and Manikganj, a rural rice growing&#13;
area. In Manikganj, girls between age seven and eight who attend school&#13;
work nearly as many hours as those who do not; while for boys, the number&#13;
of work hours is actually longer for those who attend school. Between ages&#13;
ten and fourteen, however, children in school work only about half as long&#13;
as those not in school. However, beyond age fourteen, girls work just as&#13;
long, while boys work 80 percent as long.   In Dacca, the compatibility of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 61 -&#13;
child labor and schooling is very low for all children below age fourteen,&#13;
possibly reflecting differences in the kinds of work that urban and rural&#13;
economies generate for children. Beyond age fourteen, however, the work&#13;
time of children attending school is comparable to those of children not&#13;
attending school.&#13;
In looking at children's pattern of time use, it is also useful&#13;
to examine the effect of number of siblings on children's work input. Nag&#13;
et. al. [1980] present data from Java and Nepal which show that time spent&#13;
on work was higher for children with two or more siblings than for those&#13;
with fewer. They suggest that possibly in larger families, (i) the&#13;
presence of elder siblings encourage other children's work participation,&#13;
and (ii) younger siblings are expected to take over household chores so as&#13;
to free older siblings for directly productive activities.&#13;
The findings for Java and Nepal are however, contradicted by the&#13;
result of studies in two other LDCs. Mueller [1981] found that in&#13;
Botswana, as the sibling number increases, the economic work of each child&#13;
is reduced, while average school hours increases; in the author's view,&#13;
this finding is consistent with the possibility that children in large&#13;
families can provide the needed work input, and still have time left for&#13;
school.&#13;
Presumably, the demand for child labor on the family farm does not&#13;
increasein proportion with increases in the number of children in the&#13;
household. In another study, De Tray [1982] showed that in Malaysia, the&#13;
larger the number of children aged over ten in the family, the less each&#13;
child in the 5 to 14 age group engages in economic and housework; however,&#13;
his analysis also showed that the larger the number of children under 10,&#13;
the more each child age 5 to 14 works.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 62 -&#13;
At this point,the available data provide no convincing evidence&#13;
either for a negative or posiltive relationship between number of siblings&#13;
and work per child. Clearly some of the differences in research findings&#13;
may be attributed to definitionaL or methodological differences, for&#13;
example, using different age groupings.   For the present purposes, however,&#13;
the central result of time-use studies is that children perform a&#13;
significani: amount of work, which suggests that sending them to school&#13;
involves some opportunity costs to the family. However, these costs are&#13;
low for younger children, say below ten years old, since the kinds of work&#13;
done by these children are probably not incompatible with attending school;&#13;
moreover, ciwing to their lack of physical strength, they typically spend&#13;
only a few hours working, so that even if time from work is lost, the&#13;
sacrifice is relatively small. Clearly, these remarks are not applicable&#13;
in the case of older children. In terms of level of education, the&#13;
opportunity costs of primary schooling, particularly in the first few&#13;
grades is low, but increase as the child enters higher grades; and entry&#13;
Lnto secondary school usually entails a dramatic cost increase.&#13;
What do the data on private direct and opportunity costs of&#13;
schooling suggest for the relationship between fertility and child&#13;
investments?  It probably depends to some extent on parent's aspirations&#13;
for their children's education. At low levels of development and in rural&#13;
populations, these aspirations may only mean a desire to see their children&#13;
able to read and write.   Thus in reckoning the cost of child quality&#13;
Investments, parents probably focus largely on the cost of primary&#13;
schooling.  Since this cost is relatively small, the decision to enroll&#13;
children in school may not have any appreciable effect on the number of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 63 -&#13;
children parents choose to have. Over time as the general level of&#13;
education in the population rises, and as parents recognize the need for&#13;
their children to have at least completed primary school, the cost&#13;
consideration of child quality investments becomes increasingly important.&#13;
Thus it is probably only at this stage that households, in making fertility&#13;
decisions recognise a trade-off between number of children and schooling&#13;
per child. Clearly, cost is not the only consideration, as many&#13;
researchers have emphasized. In particular, if parents can rely on some of&#13;
the older children for financial help to send younger children to school,&#13;
the quantity-quality trade-off model may not be the appropriate framework&#13;
for describing fertility decision-making in such households; some evidence&#13;
for such financial arrangements are briefly discussed below.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 64 -&#13;
4.5 Privatte Returns to Schooling&#13;
Having considered the private cost of education, we now turn to&#13;
examine its private returns to iLndividuals and their families.  In&#13;
calculating these returns, economists have generally used individuals'&#13;
earnings as the yardstick of benefits associated with attending school.&#13;
Clearly this approach is flawed,, as it discounts the fact that education&#13;
provides a host of other not-easi.ly-quantified benefits, such as ability to&#13;
appreciate literature and art better. However, since the focus of this&#13;
paper is not on measurement, we shall merely note that rates of return&#13;
calculated on the basis of earnings data represent lower bound evaluations&#13;
of the total benefits to schooling.&#13;
That individuals gain from attending school is hardly debatable;&#13;
research findings corroborate casual observation that educated individuals&#13;
earn more than those who are not. In a recent study, Psacharopoulos [1981]&#13;
provided a compilation of rate-of-return data for over 40 countries. These&#13;
data reveal that everywhere in the developing world, the private returns to&#13;
education, particularly for primary schooling are generally high, and,&#13;
almost without fail, exceed the 10 percent commonly associated with the&#13;
opportunity cost of capital. Moreover, time series data, which are&#13;
available only for USA ancL Colombia, indicate that these returns remain&#13;
highly attractive over time despite the rapid expansion of education. The&#13;
reason is because with development and technological change, the demand for&#13;
educated labor keeps pace with the rapidly growing supply.&#13;
Although individuals galn personally from being educated, the&#13;
decision to enroll, particularly at the primary and secondary levels, is&#13;
probably made by their parents, and not the individuals themselves. What&#13;
are parents' motivations in sending a child to school?   Clearly at one&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 65 -&#13;
level, it is because education is perceived to be a viable vehicle of&#13;
upward social mobility for the child. Even if parents are less altruistic,&#13;
the fact is that as society becomes technologically more complex, and as&#13;
more people rely on urban employment for a livelihood, it becomes a&#13;
necessity for children to be at least literate in order to survive&#13;
economically. As one Indian agricultural laborer explained, "...Nobody&#13;
needed an illiterate villager...nowadays you need to read and write even&#13;
for a coolie's job..."[Vlassoff and Vlassoff, 1980]. Over time, it is thus&#13;
probable that parents' educational aspirations for their children will&#13;
rise. For example, in a study of a poor rural area in Kerala State in&#13;
India, Zachariah [1983] found that the average desired years of schooling&#13;
for children had risen rapidly in all socio-economic groups; even parents&#13;
who have had no education now wanted their children to obtain some&#13;
secondary schooling.&#13;
The effect of rising educational aspirations on the number of&#13;
children parents choose to have is not immediately apparent in the context&#13;
of LDCs. This is because the private returns to schooling typically accrue&#13;
not only to the individual who went to school, but also to his/her parents&#13;
and siblings. If education improves employment opportunities and earning&#13;
power, and if children remit part of their earnings to parents, then it is&#13;
rational for parents to have and educate many children [Mueller, 1983]. In&#13;
many developing countries, the custom of remitting earnings to parents is&#13;
quite common. For example in India, Zachariah's [1983] data indicated that&#13;
96 percent of children who worked contributed to the household income.&#13;
That parents expect financial help from children is also apparent from the&#13;
data presented in Bulatao [1979]; over 60 percent of sample fathers interviewed&#13;
in Turkey, the Republic of Korea, thes Philippines and Taiwan, China expected&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 66 -&#13;
to have a share in their son's salaries. The corresponding percentage was a&#13;
slightly over 50 percent :Ln Indonesia and Thailand, whereas in Singapore and&#13;
the USA, it was only 29 and 19 percent respectively. In the longer run,&#13;
children are also expected to provide old age support. Vlassoff and&#13;
Vlassoff [1980] showed that in India, over 40 percent of elderly men in&#13;
their sample indicated that "educated sons help more" when asked to&#13;
evaluate the support given by educated and uneducated sons. In general, if&#13;
parents can benefit from having educated children, we may not observe a&#13;
quantity-quality tradeoff.&#13;
Part of the firLancial help that working children make available&#13;
to parents typically goes to pay for the cost of educating younger&#13;
children. In Bulatao's 11979] study, such help is expected from sons by&#13;
over 80 percent of fathers in the Philippines, Turkey, Indonesia, and&#13;
Thailand; 79 percent in Taiwan, China; 60 percent in the Republic of Korea;&#13;
35 percenit in Singapore; compared to only 16 percent in the USA. Expectations&#13;
of help from daughters were expressed by only slightly lower proportions of&#13;
the respondents. Moreover, :if the sample was separated into&#13;
high-parity-nonlimiters (HPN) and low-parity-limiters (LPL), the proportion&#13;
expecting help from sons for siblings' education was always significantly&#13;
higher among HPN than among LPL, except in Indonesia where it was only&#13;
slightly :Lower. These expectations reflect the financial relationships&#13;
within families which character:Lse most of Asia and Africa; parents usually&#13;
pay for the oldest child's education in the expectation that he or she will&#13;
contribute towards the schooling expenses of the next sibling, who in turn&#13;
pays for yet a younger sibling [Mueller, 1983]. It should lbe noted,&#13;
however, that this dependence oii sibling resources is effective only if the&#13;
older children start working after a few years of schooling; with rising&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 67 -&#13;
educational expectations, and as the normal stay in school lengthens, older&#13;
children would probably still be in school when their younger siblings&#13;
reach schooling age. In these circumstances, the financial burden would&#13;
fall back on the parents, at least until the o:Lder children begin working.&#13;
The web of financial obligations and expectations commonly also extends&#13;
beyond the nuclear family; it is thus usual to rely on relatives in better&#13;
circumstances to help with the cost of schooling.&#13;
What are the implications of the system of financing described&#13;
above for the relationship between number of children and their education?&#13;
Clearly, as long as parents do not expect to bear the full cost of child&#13;
quality investments, the quantity-quality trade-off will probably be weak&#13;
if it exists at all. However, with rising educational goals and as kinship&#13;
ties and family obligations weaken, as they are likely to with&#13;
modernisation and industrialisation, this tradie-off will tend to become&#13;
stronger as the choice between quantity and quality becomes increasingly&#13;
inescapable when the cost of child quality investment cannot be shifted&#13;
elsewhere.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68 -&#13;
4.6 Other Influences&#13;
So far we have discussed parents' decision to enroll children in&#13;
school on the assumption that: it is a voluntary decision, motivated largely&#13;
by the attractiveness of private returns to schooling.   What happens when&#13;
legislation compels parents to send their children to schooL and keep them&#13;
there beyond the age they would have chosen themselves?   Would such&#13;
legislation also indirectly persuade parents to lower their fertility; if&#13;
so, by whaLt mechanism?&#13;
In most LDCs, compulsory schooling laws apply to children of&#13;
primary school age.   These laws are generally marked by several&#13;
characteristics. Firstly, there are serious enforcement problems,&#13;
particularly in rural areas where the population is dispersed and the&#13;
transportation system, weak. Even where the personnel exists to enforce&#13;
compliance, the lack of school facilities frequently present.s an obstacle&#13;
to accomplishing enrollment goals.   As in MDCs, enforcement becomes&#13;
effective only in an environment where enrollment is already high and&#13;
rising.  In other words, the main effect seems to be to bring a&#13;
recalcitrant minority into compliance with the general view among parents&#13;
that children ought to attend school. Secondly, compulsory schooling&#13;
]Legislation often contains special provisions to excuse fromt school&#13;
children whose parents need them to work; the authorities either tolerate&#13;
frequent and long absenteeism, or permit non-enrollment in some cases.&#13;
MIoreover, school holidays are normally arranged so that they coincide with&#13;
harvest and other busy periods during which children are expected to help.&#13;
These provisions thus minimize the opportunity cost of school attendance.&#13;
ALt the same time, to encourage attendance further, the financial cost is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 69 -&#13;
also kept low through the provision of free or nearly free services14/.&#13;
Compulsory schooling legislation often goes hand in hand with&#13;
child labor legislation, since each requires the other for reinforcement.&#13;
Here again, the question is whether these laws lead or lag behind the&#13;
movement away from child labor usage; do these laws cause a decrease in the&#13;
demand for child labor, or are they a consequence, formalized as law to&#13;
compel the compliance of a minority who still profit from the use of child&#13;
labor? Child employment is caused "most fundamentally [by] the extent and&#13;
nature of poverty" [Rodgers and Standing, 1981]. As such, a mere piece of&#13;
legislation, by itself, cannot hope to have much effect. Moreover, whether&#13;
or not children work depends on "cultural constraints, social relations of&#13;
production, the industrial and occupational structure, [and] the nature of&#13;
available technology..."&#13;
To summarize, it is probably true that legal provisions at best&#13;
speed up existing trends in enrollment and child employment. Under a&#13;
compulsory education law, some parents would undoubtedly be forced to&#13;
school their children beyond the level they would have chosen. The&#13;
increase in child quality investment would, however, have an uncertain&#13;
effect of parents' fertility. Compulsory education is frequently enforced&#13;
by minimizing both the private direct and opportunity cost of attending&#13;
schools. If the economic burden is thus shifted away from parents, would&#13;
they still balance quantity against quality? Since parents nevertheless&#13;
still bear some cost, the trade-off probably exists, but is likely to be&#13;
14/ For a description of the experience with compulsory schooling&#13;
legislation in LDCs, see Unesco's series of Studies on Compulsory&#13;
Education, covering countries such as India, the Philippines,&#13;
Thailand, The Arab States, and Indonesia.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 70 -&#13;
weak. As for laws against: employing children, the main mechanism by which&#13;
t:hey have an effect is through reduction in the economic value of children&#13;
t:o parents, which in turn presumably leads to a reduction in fertility.&#13;
HIere reduction in fertilit.y can only be partly attributed to the effect of&#13;
child labor legislation since such legislation is not totally responsible&#13;
for the reduction in chilcl labor practices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 71 -&#13;
5. Conclusions: Children's Schooling, Demand for Children, and&#13;
Fertility Change.&#13;
This paper has attempted several things. First, the connections&#13;
between the education of children and the demand for chldren have been&#13;
explored both in theory and in previous empirical work. Second, the&#13;
relationship between changes in schooling and changes in fertility has also&#13;
been studied. Finally, the association between education of children and&#13;
fertility decline has been viewed, on a basic empirical level, historically&#13;
for five presently developed countries and also for 18 developing countries&#13;
since 1950.&#13;
Some of the theory predicts a negative association of children's&#13;
education and fertility. This stems largely from two directions, the human&#13;
capital, quantity-quality tradeoff, extensively elaborated by Gary Becker,&#13;
and the intergenerational transfer model of J.C. Caldwell. While these&#13;
models are useful, they need to be subjected to modification based on&#13;
specific circumstances. (See, for example, the qualifications noted by&#13;
Mueller (1983)). The effect of schooling of children operates through&#13;
direct and indirect (opportunity) costs as well as changes in expected&#13;
future returns to education. The process of economic development and&#13;
modernization generally raises the undiscounted returns to education.&#13;
Direct private costs (in real terms) often decline, due to increased&#13;
government intervention and financing of education. Indirect costs&#13;
(foregone earnings of children) may rise, although compulsory schooling&#13;
laws and child labor legislation can reduce these costs.&#13;
In the earliest stages of development, during which investment in&#13;
children is mainly primary schooling, there may be only a weak negative&#13;
relationship, or even a positive relationship, between children's education&#13;
and fertility. If price and/or income elasticities for child quality are&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 72 -&#13;
smaller than those for child quantity, if direct or indirect education&#13;
costs are low, (e.g. if on:Ly young children attend primary school); if&#13;
there are economies of scale in financing of education within the&#13;
household (e.g. older children paLying for younger children); if child&#13;
mortality i.s high; or if returns to education are relatively low, then the&#13;
relationship can weaken or turn postitive. These conditions are more&#13;
likely to prevail in low income agrarian societies than in hLgher income&#13;
urban environnients.&#13;
The data presented iLn tthis paper are consistent with the&#13;
theory. Historically for developed countries and more recently for&#13;
developing countries there seemed to have been little relationship between&#13;
levels or change in primary school enrollments until primary gross&#13;
enrollment ratios (GER's) reached a level of about 70-80% of children in&#13;
the relevant age categories. There were exceptions (such as the United&#13;
States in the nineteenth century and Thailand since 1960), but, overall, a&#13;
high level of primary GER seems important to a decline in fertility. At&#13;
earlier stages of developrment, with lower parental aspirations for&#13;
education, most schooling consisting of only a few years of primary&#13;
education, low direct ecoaomic burdens per child year of schooling, low&#13;
opportunity costs for young children in school, and with older children or&#13;
relatives often sharing direct costs, the relationship of schooling to&#13;
fertility is likely to be weak. The direction and strength of the&#13;
relationship depends both on economic and cultural conditions.&#13;
When, however, a sociely reaches a certain level of development,&#13;
with accompanying rising incomes and levels of urbanization, then the&#13;
relationship seems to strengthen. It is likely that high levels of&#13;
primary GER's are symptomatic of rising returns to education (and a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 73 -&#13;
consequent decline in the price of child quality). At this point, many&#13;
parents begin to plan for more years of children's education. The longer&#13;
gestation period, together with rising unit costs at higher levels of&#13;
education, imply that anticipated child quality investments involve an&#13;
escalating economic burden. Kinship ties and sibling obligations often&#13;
change and weaken in the process of development, placing the direct costs&#13;
of children more fully on parents. Factors leading to declining costs of&#13;
education, such as compulsory schooling and child labor laws (operating on&#13;
indirect costs) as well as increased public support of education&#13;
(operating on direct costs), would most likely operate at the primary&#13;
level than at the secondary level. Once parents begin to demand greater&#13;
amounts of education for their children, which is more likely to occur at&#13;
higher levels of income and development, the conflict between large&#13;
families and child quality becomes greater. Education costs increase&#13;
rapidly, particularly because the opportunity cost of children's education&#13;
is much higher for children in secondary school ages, but also because&#13;
direct secondary school costs are more likely to fall on parents and&#13;
families. Alternatively, under Caldwell's model, as children begin to&#13;
obtain more secondary education, the direction of the net flow of&#13;
resources between parents and children changes in favor of children, and&#13;
parents begin to reduce fertility. This is again consistent with the data&#13;
which indicate fertility decline associated with rising secondary GER's,&#13;
in a situation in which universal primary education was either already&#13;
established or being approached.&#13;
A recent study by Anker (1978) has produced results consistent&#13;
with the quantity-quality tradeoff. The study used country level data&#13;
from 69 LDC's for 1968-70, measured child quality investment as the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 74 -&#13;
secondary school enrollment rate, and estimated a simultaneous structural&#13;
model. His two stage leasi: squares estimates of the model indicated that,&#13;
ceteris paribus, a ten percent rise in the secondary school enrollment&#13;
ratio would be accompanied by a 1.2 percent drop in fertility. This&#13;
relationship was statistically significant at a ten percent level. The&#13;
study also noted that, at early stages of development, rising life&#13;
expectatiorn at birth and falling female labor force participation tended&#13;
partially to offset the negative effect on fertility of rising adult&#13;
literacy, school enrollment, aLnd non-agricultural employment. At&#13;
intermediate levels of development, these relationships became more&#13;
uniformly negative.&#13;
This paper has been exploratory and descriptive in nature. It&#13;
attempts to delineate the relationship of demand for children and&#13;
fertility to the education of children, both at the primary and the&#13;
secondary levels. Although the present findings are tentative, they are&#13;
suggestive and indicate a strategy for additional research on this topic.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 75 -&#13;
Appendix A&#13;
The Becker-Lewis Quantity-Quality Tradeoff Fertility Model&#13;
Let a family have a utility function, which it seeks to maximize.&#13;
(1)     U = U (n, q, ZI, Z2 ..... Zm)&#13;
where U is family utility; n is number of children; q is expenditures per&#13;
child, called total child quality per child; and Zl's are the quantities of&#13;
other "commodities" (which are actually outputs of household production&#13;
functions which themselves use marketed goods and services). The Zl's can&#13;
be written as a composite commodity Z for convenience. Thus&#13;
(1.1)   U = U (n, q, Z)&#13;
This utility function is maximized subject to a full income budget&#13;
constraint.&#13;
(2)     I = Pc.q.n +   TzZ&#13;
where I is full income, Pc is the constant cost of a unit of quality, H z&#13;
is the cost of Z, and Pc.q n is the total amount spent on children. It is&#13;
non-linear in n and q, and it is this non-linearity which creates the&#13;
quantity-quality interaction.&#13;
Maximizing (1.1) subject to (2) yields the following first order&#13;
equilibrium conditions.&#13;
aU  =  MU   =AXP q    =  Al&#13;
n        n=       c        n&#13;
(3)   at  =  MU    =  XP n  =  XTI&#13;
~~q    q        c        q&#13;
au_=&#13;
=  MU  =  AN&#13;
9z       z        z&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 76 -&#13;
where 1In is the shadow price oE n and IT q is the shadow prLce of q.&#13;
What is interesting is that ]Tn depends on q (i.e. the shadow price of&#13;
quantity depends on total quality per child) and that TI depends on n&#13;
(i.e. the shadow price of quality depends on total quantity). In&#13;
particular, this means that an increase in quality per child (q) will raise&#13;
the price of quantity ( Irl) by raising the cost of each child. From (2)&#13;
and (3), demand functions for n, q, and Z can be derived as a function of&#13;
shadow prices and income.&#13;
n  d    JI    R     I,  R)&#13;
d   (      [q,  TI   R)&#13;
(4)   q=    dq (1      II n  s  Zq'   Rz &#13;
z=  z  n( n 'q  z,  R&#13;
where R is full shadow income (i.e. the shadow amounts spent on the&#13;
different commodities).&#13;
R  =( Pcn ) q     +  ( PCq )     +   Z&#13;
=  nqq  +   IInN  +  IZ&#13;
In general,   - &lt; 0   becauase  an     &lt; 0  and      &gt; 0&#13;
n&#13;
Economic development can raise rates of return on education and&#13;
training, particularly in urban areas. This, in turn, lowers the marginal&#13;
cost of quality (MCq = nq, in conpetitive equilibrium), and hence raises&#13;
demand for quality which, in tur-ni, lowers demand for quantity of children.&#13;
In fact, In this system, anything which reduces the marginal cost (and&#13;
price) of child quality, such as schooling subsidies, can reduce the demand&#13;
for quantity [Becker, 1981, ch. 5].&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 77 -&#13;
Appendix Tables A.1 - A.5 /1&#13;
(Fertility, Mortality and enrollment data for five developed countries).&#13;
1 The rates are generally calculated for a three year average around the&#13;
census data. Symbols in the tables have the following definitions:&#13;
If        Coale's index of overall fertility.&#13;
Ig     =  Coale's index of marital fertility.&#13;
Im        Coale's index of proportions nmarried.&#13;
Ih   =    Coale's index of illegitimate fertility.&#13;
TFR  =    Total fertility rate.&#13;
NRR  =    Net reproduction rate.&#13;
CBR  =    Crude birth rate (per 1000).&#13;
q(15)=    Probability of death between birth and age 15.&#13;
IMR  =    Infant mortality rate (per 1000).&#13;
CDR  =    Crude death rate (per 1000).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 78 -&#13;
Table A.1:  Demographic: and School Lnrollinent Data:  England &amp; Waleq, 1851-1971&#13;
Gross Enrollment Rates (per 100)&#13;
Primary          Primary 6        Secondarv&#13;
Fertility                             Mortality           Enrollment/      Secondary/       Enrollment/&#13;
Date     I:     I      Ia     fh     TFR     NRR     CBR    q(15)     IMR     CUR    Children 5-14     Children 5-19   Childreni 10-19&#13;
1851   .34S9   .675   .483   .045   4.663      -    34.08       -    157.7    21.77      8.06             -                   -&#13;
1861   .3',9   .670   .502   .046   4.524    1.363i 34.59   .30829   178.1    21.61    18.0               -                   -&#13;
1871   .3io9   .686   .509   .041   4.670    1.41   34.98   .31103   182.4    22.59     26.3              -                   -&#13;
1881   .3'5    .674   .501   .034   4.552    1.54   33.92   .24991   145.8    18.88     50.5              -                   -&#13;
1891   .310    .621   .477   .026   4.080    1.36   31,42    .27040  176.7    20.21     59.0              -                   -&#13;
1901   .2,3    .553   .476   .021   3.449    1.21   28.51    .24907  176.6    16.91     71.9             49.7                1.44&#13;
1911   .2:4    .467   .479   .019   2.897    1.07')  24.40   .21434  146.5    14.61     74.7             52.6                2.44&#13;
1921   .193    .375   .489   .018   2.685    1.09   22.40    .13933   88.4    12.10     72.1             51.7                4.87&#13;
1931   .154    .292   .503   .014   1.882    0.79   15.80    .11089   70.1     12.29    76.5             54.4                6.44&#13;
1941   .147      -      -      -    1.736    0.745  14.95    .09565   63.0    13.54      -                -                  -&#13;
1951    .174   .251   .658   .025   2.170    1.01   15.59    .03866   29.5     11.85    70.6             68.8               31.S&#13;
1961   .217    .292   .699   .043   2.777    1.30'  17.58    .02883   22.4    11.81     59.2             68.2               40.6&#13;
19'71    -      -       -     -       -       -       -         -      -         -      69.4             82.1               53.2&#13;
Sources:   (1) If, Ig, 1m  Ih:  1851-1931:   Data from the Euiropean Fertility Project, Princeton Uliversity.&#13;
1941:  CalciLatea from data in Keyfitz &amp; Flieger (1968).&#13;
1951-1961:  Calculated from data in Mitchell &amp; Jones (1974).&#13;
(2) TFR &amp; .RR:   1851.  Glass (1939).&#13;
1861-1961: Keyfitz &amp; Flieaer (1968).&#13;
(3) CBR:   1851: Mitchell (1975).&#13;
1861-1961   Keyfitz &amp; Flieger (1968).&#13;
(4) q(15), DIR, CDR    1851:  Mitchell (1975).&#13;
1861-1961: Keyfitz &amp; Flieger (1968).&#13;
(5) School enro'.lment data:  Mitchell (1975).   U,S. Bujreau of the Census (1974, 1976).&#13;
(6) School age population:   Mitchell (1975).&#13;
United Nations (1979b).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 79 -&#13;
Table A.2:   Demograpihic and School Enrollment Data:   Germany, 1867-1970&#13;
Gross Fnroll,ient Rates (per 100)&#13;
Secondary         Primary         Prim. &amp; Second.&#13;
Fertility                      Mortality               Enrollment/      Enrollment/      Enrollment/&#13;
Date     If     i      I.       Ih    CBR    q(15)     IMR       CDR      Children 10-19   Children 5-14    Children 5-19&#13;
1867    .389    .761   .454     .079   37.2     -        307      28.1           -             -                -&#13;
1871   .396     .760   .472    .071    37.5     -        310      28.7         1.31          64.1              45.9&#13;
1875   .428     .791   .495     .073   4D.5   .37600     256      26.9           -             -                -&#13;
1880   .404     .735   .501    .072    38.2     -        227      25.7         2.57          69.5              50.3&#13;
1885    .395    .726   .494     .073   37.1   .36200     232      26.0           -            -                 -&#13;
1890    .389    .706   .497    .070    36.4     -        224      23.8         3.59           74.0             53.8&#13;
1895    -        -      -        -     36.1   .32000     219      21.7           -            -                -&#13;
1900   .373     .664   .513     .066   35.7      -       217      21.4         4.53          72.6              53.5&#13;
1905    -        -      -        -     33.4   .26600     195      19.2           -           -                 -&#13;
1910   .312     .542   .524     .059   29.8   .23500     175      16.9         4.87          71.2              52.6&#13;
1925    .185    .334   .490     .041   20.3   .14300     105      11.9         6.16          75.9              51.0&#13;
1933    .157    .264   .534     .033   15.9   .10800      74      11.0         7.52          71.9              57.4&#13;
1939    .202    .316   .590     .038   20.1      -        65      12.2         5.58          82.1              55.4&#13;
t950   .173     .791   .537    .035    16.2      -        56      10.6        12.2           78.0             62.6&#13;
1961   .200     .301   .625     .032   17.8   .04328      15      11.4        16.7           69.8              58.2&#13;
1970 a/  -       -      -       -       -        -        -        -         52.1            67.9             80.1&#13;
a/ Federal Republic of Germany.&#13;
Sources: (1)   If. Ig, I,. Ih:   1867-1939:  Knodel (1974) 1950-1961:   Data provided by European Fertility Project,&#13;
Princeton University.&#13;
(2) CBR: Mitchell (1975).&#13;
(3) q(15): 1875-1933: Knodel (1974).&#13;
1961:  Keyfitz &amp; Flieger (1968).&#13;
(4) IMR, CDR: Mitchell (1975).&#13;
(5)  School enrollment data:   lanks (1971), U.S. Bureau of the Census (1974).&#13;
(6) School age population: Mitchell (1975), United Nations (1979b).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 80 -&#13;
Table A.3:  Demographic and School Enrollment Data:     Sveden, 1800-1970&#13;
Gross Enrollment Rates (per 103)&#13;
Secondary        Primary          Prim. &amp; Second,&#13;
Fertility                        Mortality           Enrollment/      Enrollment/       Enrollment/&#13;
Date     If      I      Im     th    rFR   NRR    CBR     q(15)    IMR     CDR    ChLldren 10-19, Children 5-14     Children 5-19&#13;
1800    .334    .688   .458  .034  4.164   1.15   31.21   .36867   249.0  25.88        -               -                   -&#13;
1810   .323     .676   .447  .038  4.275   1.32   32.23   .42915   260.1  33.09        -               -                   -&#13;
1820    .355    .714   .463  .046  4.519   1.31   34.29   .33446   206.7   24.90       -               -                   -&#13;
1830   .357     .671   .498  .045  4.523   1.346  32.52   .31999   204.0  25.82        -               -                   -&#13;
1840    .324    .678   .441  .044  4.405   1.38   30. 54  .28666   184.6  21.73        -               -                   -&#13;
1850   .315     .673   .425  .050  4.305   1.39   31.46  .27384    165.6  20.54        -               -                   -&#13;
1860   .343     .709   .440  .055  4.558   1.46   34.10   .28376   150.1  19.87        -               -                   -&#13;
1870   .329     .709   .416  .058  4.120   1.33   29.15  .27564    157.7  19.40        -             56.8                  -&#13;
1880   .321     .704   .409  .055  4.317   1.43   29.52  .25962    131.3  17.56       1.34a          69.34               47.5a&#13;
1890   .316     .674   .421  .057  4.098   1.44   27.92  .21359    115.9  16.75       1.52           68.2                48.8&#13;
1900   .297     .639   .411  .059  3.984   1.43   26.79  .19144    106.9  16.19       1.77           68.9                48.6&#13;
1910    .268    .560   .409  .066   3.574  1.39   24.72  .13533     69.8  14.11       2.26           69.8                49.5&#13;
1920   .213     .440   .413  .053  2.852   1.11   20.99  .12393     46.4  14.19       2.96           60.7               ,43.0&#13;
1930    .151    .301   .422  .041   1.913  0.813  15.20   .08638    42.6  12.01       3.80           62.6                43.7&#13;
1940   .194     .294   .586  .044  1.916   0.86   15.76  .05756     31.3  11.14       6.42           63.0                43.7&#13;
1950   .187     .269   .628  .049  2.312   1.08   16.64  .03133     18.9   9.85     14.3            62.3                 53.0&#13;
1960    .178    .252   .626  .053  2.227   1.052  14.02  .02328     15.6   9.82     23.8            67.6                 151.0&#13;
1970     -        -      -     -     -              -       -        -       -      60.9            55.8                 77.0&#13;
a/ 1982.&#13;
Sources: (1)   If, Ig, Im, Ih:  Data furniqhed bY tIhe Lsiropean Fertility Project, Princeton University.&#13;
(2)  TFR, NiR, CBR, q(15), IMR, CtR:   Keyfiti, snd Flieger (1968).&#13;
(3)  School enrollment data:   Mitchell (1975), BAnks (1971), U.S. Bureau of the Census (1974).&#13;
(4)  School age population:   Mitchell (1975), tIn^id Nations (1975).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 81 -&#13;
Table A.4:  Demographic and School Enrollment Data: tlnited States, 1800-1970&#13;
Enrollment Rates (per 100)&#13;
Secondary       Primnary       Prxm. &amp; Second.&#13;
Fertility                           Mortality          Enrollment/     Enrollment/     Enrollment/&#13;
I)ate  TFR 1   TFR II   rFR fIt   NU1   CBh    CBR   _q(5)     LIR     CUR    Children 10-19  Children 5-14  Children 5-19&#13;
a    (Whites) (Whites)  (Total)  (Total)(Total)(Whitea)    (Total)&#13;
1800   8.02     7.04        -     -      -     55.0      -      -        -          -             - &#13;
1810   7.92     6.92        -     -      -     54.3      -      -        -          -             -                  _&#13;
1820   7.42     6.73        -     _    55.2    52.8      -      -        -          -             -                  -&#13;
1830   6.93     6.55        -     _      -     51.4      -      -        -          -             -                  _&#13;
1840   6.56     6.14        -      -   51.8    48.3      -      -        -          -             -                46.9 Lc&#13;
1850   6.03     5.42        -     _      -     43.3   .34736  229.5      -          -             -                47.2&#13;
1860   5.52     5.16        -     -    44.3    41.4   .30457  197.4      -          -             -                50.6&#13;
1870   5.13     4.56        -      -     -     38.3   .28455  185.0   (23) /a      0.86          74.0              52.6&#13;
1880   4.67     4.25        -      -   39.8    35.2   .33777  225.1      -         3.82         77.5               57.3&#13;
1890   4.40     3.93        -     -      -     31.5   .25902  160.9   (19) /b      1.49         85.7               60.1&#13;
1900   3.75     3.50        -      -   32.3    30.1   .24234  120.2    16.8        3.27         88.2               63.1&#13;
1910   3.61     3.41        -     -    30.0    21.2   .18494  114.6    14.3        5.03         89.4               63.7&#13;
1920   3.31     3.14      3.378  1.334  27.3   26.5   .13718   88.8    12.91     13.1           95.4               75.2&#13;
1930    -      2.41      2.547  1.072  20.9    20.2  .10202    68.1    11.43     21.0           95.5               78.7&#13;
1940    -      2.20      2.312  1.026  19.5    18.7  .07317    54.5    10.64     28.6           97.1               82.5&#13;
1950    -      3.04      3.153  1.459  24.5    23.5  .04440    33.9    9.64      31.9           87.9              81.0&#13;
1960    -      3.52      3.690  1.732  23.7    22.6  .03484   26.8     9.39      35.7           84.3              83.4&#13;
1970    -       -          -       -     -       -     -        -       -        49.9           78.3              86.6&#13;
/a 1870/80;    /b 1l91/1900;     /c Whites.&#13;
Sources: TFR I:  Sanderson (1979).&#13;
TFR II: Coale &amp; Zelnick (1963).&#13;
TFR III &amp; NRR:  Keyfitz and Flxeger (1968).&#13;
CDR:    U.S. Bureatu nf the Cenqus (1975).&#13;
q(15) &amp; IMR: 1850-1900:  Hiines (1979). Preston &amp; Haines (1981)&#13;
1910: Glover (1921).&#13;
1920-1960: Keyfitz &amp; Flieger (1968).&#13;
CDR:    1870,1890: Kuznets (1966).&#13;
1900-1910: U.S. Bureau of the Census (1975).&#13;
1920-196n:  Keyfitz &amp; Flieger (1968).&#13;
School enrollment data:  1840-1850:  U.S. Censtuses of Populatiion, 1840. 1850, 1860.&#13;
1870-1960:  Banks (1971).&#13;
1970:       U.S. Bureau of the Census (1974).&#13;
School age poPulation: U.S. Bureau of the Census (1975). United Nations, (1979b).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 82 -&#13;
Table A.5   DOcoogrophic ito1 School FollmI,ent Iota  Japan, 1875-1970&#13;
School Enrollment Rates (per 100)&#13;
Secondary       Pr-oary          trio.   Secnd&#13;
Period/                        fertility                                  Mortnlity               Enrolle,rnt/     Enrollment/     Enrrollment/&#13;
Year        If             L       th      fFR     N        Ch CBR  q(lS)        LMR      CDR     Children 10-19   Children 5-14   Children 5-19&#13;
1875/79    -       -        -      -        -       -       25.2       -          -       18.0&#13;
1880/84    -       -        -      -        -       -       26.3      -           -       19.5         -               -             -&#13;
1885/89    -       -        -      -        -       -       28.3       -          -       21.5       1.31            35.1 /a       25.9 L&amp;&#13;
1890/94    -       -        -      -        -       -       28.4      -           -       21.1         -              -              -&#13;
1895/99    -       -        -      -        -       -       30.6   .28290/e    157.9/e    20.7       2.74 /e        47.1 /e        33.6 6.e&#13;
1900/04    -       -        -      -        -       -       32.0      -           -       20.4         -              -              -&#13;
190 5 I    _9  -   -        -      -        -       -       32.0   .28101/f    162.1/f    20.9       5.82/f         54.8/f         42.4/f&#13;
1910/14    -       -        -      -        -       -       33.6      -           -       20.2         -              -              _&#13;
1915/19    -       -        -      -        -       -       32.4      -           -       22.5         -              -              _&#13;
1920/25  .423/a  .590/a    597/, .054/a     -       -       36.7      -        164.7      23.0       2.63/a         65.1/a         47.6/a&#13;
1925/30    -       -        -      -      5.342/c   -       34.7      -        140.8      19.8         -              -              -&#13;
1930/35  .376/b  .534/b    n77/1- .045/b  4.929/b   -       32.6      -        124.3      18.1       5.23/b         68.7/b         50.8/b&#13;
1935/b0    -       -        -      -      4.929/d   -       29.3      -        110.4      17.3         -              -              _&#13;
1939/41    -       -        -      -      4.134    1.435    29.01  .19138       98.14     16.49      5.89/h         70.3/h         53.0/h&#13;
1950/52  .299    .496    .588    .018     3.297    1 393    25..42  .0950'.     55.95      9.93     41.8/i          61.0/1         69.1/i&#13;
1953/55  .199    .346     .5.6   .008     2.511    1.1t    20.34  .0;288       44.56      8.29     42.0/1          58.8/j         68.4/i&#13;
1959/61  .170    .290    .578    .005     2.013    0 922    17.24  .n4722       31.01      7.48     41.4            59.7           69.2&#13;
1970       -        --                       -      -          -             -                      53.1            59.3           73.7&#13;
/a  1920,  /b  1910,   /c  1925,  /d  113?739,   e  1899,  /f 1108, /g   1888,   /h  1940;  /i  1950;     P155-&#13;
Sourcer:  (I) lh, r;,    i   1/'k (1q9O).&#13;
(2) TFR, NRR, CFR, CLt: 1875-1940     T.ei ,er (1959)&#13;
1934/41- 1959/61   Keyfictz  Flieger (1968).&#13;
(3) q(l5), lMR    180', 1908   Preston, Ke ficz b Scho-n (197')&#13;
1921./24-1935/40  lan-e- '(!153)&#13;
1931'/41 - 1950/61  Kev[Llc  b&#13;
FI,eger (19b3).&#13;
(4) School enr-. lment itr.  Panks (1971), U S. B.ren,, of the Ce&amp;-ss&#13;
(1974) .&#13;
(5) School aRe pop7l Cicn:  1888, 192C-1955    T,ocbec (1q58)&#13;
1899, 1908   PresCon, Keyliti,  .na Schoen (1972)&#13;
1959/61   Kevtit. &amp;  Frile,- tl968)&#13;
1970:  United Nations d19,'9b).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 83 -&#13;
Table A.6: Coale's Indices of Overall Fertility, Marital&#13;
Fertility, and Proportions Married&#13;
Births per married Hutterite woman,&#13;
Standard Schedule        Aqe groups       W)                     1921-1930.   (F&#13;
15-19                                    .300&#13;
20-24                                    .550&#13;
25-29                                    .502&#13;
30-24                                    .447&#13;
35-39                                   .406&#13;
40-44                                    .222&#13;
45-49                                   .061&#13;
if= index of overall fertility                       rh= index of illegitimate fertility&#13;
Bt                                                      BI&#13;
-  t                                                f~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
L F w                                                    E F &#13;
I    index of .marital fertillty                    I   = index of proportions married&#13;
Fw&#13;
t                                                        1&#13;
I F=                                            I       )F&#13;
f    g      m       h        m&#13;
Bt   =  total births at time t in the population studied&#13;
L   =   legitimate births at time t in the population studied&#13;
S   =   lllegitimate births at time t in the population studied&#13;
w = total women in the ith age group in the population studied&#13;
(using five year a:e qroupings)&#13;
m = total marr-ed women in the ith age group in the population studied&#13;
(using five year aqe groupings)&#13;
u = total unmarried women in the ith age group in the population studied&#13;
.us nq five year age qroupings)&#13;
F   =   births per .oman in the "standard" population in the ith aqe -nteral&#13;
Source    Ansley J   Coale, "Factors Associated with the Development of Low&#13;
Fertility    An Historic Summary," United Nations., World Popuiatlon&#13;
-onference    1965, Vol. II (New York     United Nations, 1967),&#13;
pp 205-209.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 85 -&#13;
Appendix Tables B.1 to B.18 Li&#13;
(Fertility, Mortality and School Enrollment&#13;
Data for 18 LDCs)&#13;
/-   Source:  Data on Crude Birth Rate (CBR), Total Fertility Rate (TFR),&#13;
Crude Death Rate (CDR) and Life Expectancy at Birth (e0) are from&#13;
(World Bank, 1983). Enrollment Data are from UNESCO Statistical&#13;
Yearbook, 1970, 1977 and 1982. For Taiwan, enrollment data for&#13;
1960 onwards are from (Republic of China, 1981 and 1982).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 86 -&#13;
Table B.l: Barbados&#13;
Gross Eviroll-rent Pate&#13;
Year        CBR         TFR        CDR         e0         Primary /'      Secondary&#13;
1950        32.9I      4.1         14.4        54.8          -&#13;
1955        32.2       4.1         11.9        60.1           -                _&#13;
1960        30.7       4.1         10.2        64.3         95               39 /2&#13;
1965        26.3        3.7         9.4        66.8        106                61 /2&#13;
1970        22.3       3.2          9.0        68.3        1C8                71 /3&#13;
1975        22.3       2.8          8.9        69.5         101               77 A&#13;
1976                                -           -             -                _&#13;
1977                                -           -             _&#13;
1978                                -                         _ -&#13;
1979                                -           -                                /3&#13;
1980        22.9       2.6          8.6        70.8         117               85  -&#13;
/1  age (5-10)             age (11-L7)&#13;
/2  age (11-18)         -  age (11-16)&#13;
Table B.2: Brazil&#13;
Gross Enrollment Rate&#13;
Year         CBR         TFR         CDR        e         Primar"          Secorndarv&#13;
1950         45.3       6.1         15.9        49.8          68                6 /5&#13;
1955         44.0        6.1        14.0        52.2          76                8 /-&#13;
1960         42.7       6.1         12.9        54.7          95 /2            11 /5&#13;
1965         39.3       5.7         11.5        56.9          72 /3            17 /6&#13;
1970         35.0       5.0         10.3        58.9          76 .4            24 /&#13;
1975         32.8       4.5          9.3        60.8          87 A             31 /-7&#13;
1976          -          -           -           -             -&#13;
1977          -          -           -           _             _&#13;
1978          -          -     -        _        _&#13;
1979          -          -           -           _             _&#13;
1980         30.9       4.0          8.4        63.1          84 A             36 /7&#13;
age (7-12); /2   age (7-10); /3   age (6-il); A    age (6-;3); /5   age (11-17);&#13;
A   age (12-13); /7   age (L4-17).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 87 -&#13;
Table B.3:   Chile&#13;
Gross Enrollment Rate&#13;
Year        CBR         TFR         CDR        e          Primary         Secondary&#13;
1950        34.0       4.6         13.9        53.1         93 /1            14 /3&#13;
1955        36.3 ,     5.0         13.2        55.1        101 /1            21 /3&#13;
1960        36.6       5.1         12.3        56.9        109 /I            24 /3&#13;
1965        32.8       4.5         10.9        59.1        124 /I            34 /3&#13;
1970        28.0       3.7          9.2        62.4        107 /2            39 /4&#13;
1975        25.7       3.2          8.2        64.9        118 /2            48 A&#13;
1976         -          -           -           -&#13;
1977         -          -           -           -           _&#13;
1978                    -           -           -&#13;
1979         -          -           -           -           _&#13;
1980        25.1       3.0          7.6       67.1         117 /2            55 A&#13;
/-  age (7-12);   -  age (6-13); /3   age (13-18);   -  age (14-17).&#13;
Table B.4: Colombia&#13;
Gross Enrollment Rate&#13;
Year         CBR         TFR        CDR         e          Primary         Secondary&#13;
1950         48.3       6.7         19.3       46.5          60                5&#13;
1955         46.9       6.7         15.9       50.3          69                7&#13;
1960         45.7       6.7         13.6       53.1          77               12&#13;
1965         42.3       6.3         11.6       55.9          85               17&#13;
1970         36.8       5.4          9.7       58.9         103               25&#13;
1975         32.3       4.4          8.6       60.8         114               39&#13;
1976                     -            -         -&#13;
1977                                  -         -             -                _&#13;
1978&#13;
1979          ---                                - &#13;
1990         30.0       3.8          7.8       62.9         128 /-            46  2&#13;
Li  age (6-10).   In previous years, it is 7-11 years;&#13;
/2 age (11-16). In previous years, it is 12-17 years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 88 -&#13;
Table B.5: Costa Rica&#13;
Gross l,nrollment Rate&#13;
Year       CBR         TFR        CDR        e0         Primary        Secondary&#13;
1950       47.2       6.5        13.1         55.8        78               7 14&#13;
1955       47.9       6.9        11.6         58.7        96              18 L4&#13;
1960       40.8       7.0          9.9        61.6        96 /2           21 /5&#13;
1965       41.8       6.4          8.1        64.3       106 /2           24&#13;
1970       34j.6      5.2          6.5        66.9       110 /3           28 /6&#13;
1975       30.8       4.2          5.2        69.8       107 /3           43 /6&#13;
1976                                           -           -&#13;
1977                   -     -                 -           _&#13;
19'78                                                      -&#13;
1979                         -                 - &#13;
1980       30.0       3.6          4.4        72.2       107  --          48 t6&#13;
L]- age (6-11); a- ge (12-17).&#13;
Table B.6: Mexico&#13;
Gross Enrollment Rate&#13;
Year         CBR        TFR        CDR         e        Primary- /i econda,ry/2&#13;
1950        47.1        6.8        17.7       48.4          62               5&#13;
1955         46.3       6.8        14.7       53.1          69               6&#13;
1960         45.4       6.8        12.2       57.0          80              11&#13;
1965         44.6       6.7        10.8       59.5          92              17&#13;
1970         43.4       6.6         9.7       61.3         104              22&#13;
1975         40.1       5.9         8.5       63.1         109              35&#13;
1976          -          -          -          -             -&#13;
1977          _          _          _                                        _&#13;
1978          -        . _                                                   _&#13;
1979          _          _          _                                        _&#13;
1980         32.7       5.1         7.2       65.2         120              37&#13;
/1 age (6-11); /2 age (12-17).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 89 -&#13;
Table B.7: Hong Kong&#13;
Gross Enrollment Rate&#13;
Year        CBR        TFR         CDR        e          Primary        Secondary&#13;
1950       35.6        4.3         11.6       60.8          -              _&#13;
1955       36.3        4.9          9.6       64.0         61 /1          32 /3&#13;
1960       34.5        5.3          7.8       66.7         87 /2          24 '&#13;
1965       27.0        4.6          6.6       68.9        ]03 /-          34 A&#13;
1970       20.4        3.5          5.9       70.9        117 /1          36 t5&#13;
1975       18.3        2.7          5.5       72.6        120 '1-         49 /5&#13;
1976        -           -                      -            -              _&#13;
1977        -           -                      -            -              _&#13;
1978        -           -                      -            _              _&#13;
1979        -           -           -          -                           _&#13;
1980       18.6        2.2          5.3       74.5        109 LI          62 /5&#13;
A age (6-11); /2 age (5-10); /3 age (12-17); /4 age (11-17); /5 age (12-18).&#13;
Table B.8: India&#13;
Gross Enrollment Rate&#13;
Year         CBR        TFR         CDR        e        Primary         Secondary&#13;
1950        40.7        5.9        27.6       37.2          28 /1            4 /3&#13;
1955        42.8        6.0        24.7       40.2          34 /1            7 /3&#13;
1960        43.7        6.0        21.8       43.2          61 /2           10 /A&#13;
1965        42.3        5.9        19.0       45.9          74              36&#13;
1970        40.0        5.6        16.7       48.1          73              26&#13;
1975        37.4        5.3        14.9       49.9          76              26&#13;
1976          -          -          -          -             -               -&#13;
1977         -           -          -          -             _               _&#13;
1978          -          -          -          -            76              28&#13;
1979         -                      -          -             -               _&#13;
1980         35.6       4.9        13.6        51.8&#13;
/1 age (6-12); /2 age (5-9); for all years after 1960&#13;
/3 age (13-17); /A age (10-15) for all years after 1960.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 90 -&#13;
Table B.9: Philjp Tines&#13;
Gross Enrollment Rate&#13;
Year        CBR        TFR         CDR        e          Priarv          Seconda   /2&#13;
1950       50.3        7.3        21.2        45.8         -                _&#13;
1955       48.4        7.1        17.8        49.3        91               27&#13;
1960       46.7        7.0        14.6        52.8        95               26&#13;
1965       45.6        6.8        11.9        56.0       113               41&#13;
1970        44.0       6.4         9.8        59.0       108               46&#13;
1975        39.5       5.6         8.3,       61.1       108               54&#13;
1976&#13;
1977                          -           -&#13;
1978                          -                 -             -&#13;
1979                                -           -&#13;
1980        34.6       4.7          7.4       62.8        110              63&#13;
/- age (7-12); /- age (13-16).&#13;
Table B.10: Singapore&#13;
Gross Enrollment Rate&#13;
o                 /                  /2&#13;
Year         CBR        TFR         CDR         e         Primary -        econdary   -&#13;
1950         45.8       6.5        11.6        59.0         80                 8&#13;
1955         43.0       6.1         9.6        61.8         94               i8&#13;
1960         37.8       5.4         7.8        64.5        111               32&#13;
1965         29.5       4.2         6.4        66.9        105               45&#13;
1970         23.1       3.C         5.4        68.7        106               46&#13;
1975         19.2       2.2         5.1        70.2        111               53&#13;
1976          -                      - -        -                              _&#13;
1977          -                      -          -&#13;
1973                                            -&#13;
1979          -&#13;
1980         17.6       1.e         5.1        71.5        107               55&#13;
/i age (6-11): /-- age (12-17).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 91 -&#13;
Table B.ll: Republic of Korea&#13;
Gross Enrollment Rate&#13;
Year        CBR        TFR         CDR        e          Primary -      Secondary/2&#13;
1950         -          -          -           -            83            16&#13;
1955       45.3        5.9        14.4       53.2           89            29&#13;
1960       42.7        5.6        13.4       54.4           94            27&#13;
1965       35.6        4.8        11.0       57.3          101            35&#13;
1970       30.3        4.2         9.1       60.3          103            42&#13;
1975       26.2        3.6         8.0       62.8          107            50&#13;
1976        -                       -          -            -              -&#13;
1977        -                       -         -             _              _&#13;
1978        -           -           -         -             -              -&#13;
1979        -           -           -          -            -              _&#13;
1980        23.8       3.0         7.1        65.4         109            80&#13;
1958&#13;
/2 age (6-11); /3 age (12-17).&#13;
Table B.12: Sri Lanka&#13;
Gross Enrollment Rate&#13;
Year         CBR        TFR         CDR        e0         Primary        Secondary&#13;
1950         39.5       5.9        12.3       54.6&#13;
1955         37.6       5.6        10.7       58.5          -                 -&#13;
1960         35.7       5.3         9.2        62.0        95 /1             27 /3&#13;
1965         33.2       4.9         8.2        63.9        93 I'             35 /3&#13;
1970         29.4       4.4         7.5        63.6        99 /2             47 /4&#13;
1975         27.8       4.0         8.5        64.0        77               48&#13;
1976          -                     -           -           _                 _&#13;
1977          -          -          -           -           _&#13;
1978          -          -          -           -           _&#13;
1979          -                     -           -           _                 _&#13;
1980         27.6       3.6         6.1        68.0       100                51&#13;
/1 age (5-12); /2 age (6-10) for all years after 1970.&#13;
/3 age (13-16); age (11-17) for all years after 1970.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 92 -&#13;
Table B.13: Taiwan, China&#13;
Gross Enroliment Rate&#13;
Year       CBR         TFR        CDR        e          Primary t2     Secondary /3&#13;
1950       46.6"1      6.7"       9.9/1      57.7/1       79              11&#13;
1955       45.3        6.3        8.6         61.6        97              19&#13;
1960       39.5        5.7        7.0        64.7         96              30&#13;
1965       32.7        4.8        5.5        66.6         97              38&#13;
1970       27.2        3.8        4.9         68.7        98              54&#13;
1975       23.0        3.0        4.7         70.9        99              66&#13;
1976&#13;
1977                               -           -           -&#13;
1978&#13;
1979&#13;
1980       23.4        2.7        4.8         72.4       100              80&#13;
/1 ]L952&#13;
/2 age (6-11)&#13;
/3 age (10-17)&#13;
Table B.14: Thailand&#13;
Gross Enrollment Rate&#13;
Year         CBR        TFR        CDR         e         Primary -      Secondary&#13;
1950          -         -             -         -          76&#13;
1955          -         -             -         -          79               -&#13;
1960        43.6       6.4          1L4.9     52.3         83              12&#13;
1965        4 2.4      6.3          L2.6      55.4         78              14&#13;
1970        39.7       5.8          10.8      57.9         83              17&#13;
1975        34.5       4.9           9.2      60.2         84              26&#13;
1976          -         -             -         -           -               _&#13;
1977          -         -             -         -           _&#13;
1978          --                      -         -           _&#13;
1979          -         -             -         -           -               _&#13;
1980         0.1       4.0           7.9      62.6         96              29&#13;
/3age (7-13);/-2 age (14-18).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 93 -&#13;
Table B.15: Egypt&#13;
Gross Enrollment Rate&#13;
Year        CBR        TFR        CDR         e0        Primary  -2 Secondarv&#13;
1950       45.4        6.2        22.4      41.1          41               17&#13;
1955       44.4        6.1        20.8      43.6          52               16&#13;
1960       43.5        6.1        19.0      46.1          66               16&#13;
1965       41.7        5.9        17.0      48.6          75               26&#13;
1970       38.L,       5.6        15.1      51.3          72               34&#13;
1975       37.6        5.3        13.6      54.3          73               43&#13;
1976                         -                 -             -&#13;
1977        -           -          -         -&#13;
1978        -           -          -         -&#13;
1979         -          -          -         -&#13;
1980        36.6       4.9        12.1      56.6          76               52&#13;
- age (6-11)&#13;
/- age (12-17)&#13;
Table B.16: Ghana&#13;
Gross Enrollment Rate&#13;
Year         CBR        TFR        CDR       e_          Primary        Secondary&#13;
1950         50-.2      7.0        24.2      39.6           32               1&#13;
1955         50.2       7.0        22.4      42.2           52               6&#13;
1960         50.2       7.0        20.3      44.8           59               8&#13;
1965         50.2       7.0        18.2      47.4           79              15&#13;
1970         50.2       7.0        16.8      49.9           64 '1           14 /2&#13;
1975         49.8       7.0        15.5      52.2           70              36&#13;
1976          -          -          -         -&#13;
1977          -          -          -         - &#13;
1978          -          -          -         -             71              36&#13;
1979          -          -          -         _&#13;
1980         49.4       7.0        13.7       54.5&#13;
/1  Before 1970, age is (6-11), after 1970, it is (6-15).&#13;
/-  Before 1970, age is (12-19), after 1970, it is (16-19).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 94 -&#13;
Table B.17:  Kenya&#13;
Gross Enrollment Rate&#13;
YoaLr      CBR        TFR        C'DR        e         Primary        Secondary&#13;
1950       54.7       8.0        27.7      36.3           -&#13;
1955       54.7       8.0        25.6      38.8          32 /]:           1 -&#13;
1960       54.7       8.0        23.6      41.3          47 /2            2 /-&#13;
1965       54i.7      8.0        20.8      44.8          54               4&#13;
1970       54.7       8.0        17.8      48.7          61               9&#13;
1975       54.7       8.0        15.4      51.9         100              13&#13;
19176&#13;
1977                                        -&#13;
19I78                                                    99              18&#13;
1979                                                      -                -&#13;
1980       54.7       8.0        13.3      55.3&#13;
/--age (6-12'); - age (5-11) after 1960.&#13;
/2-age (13-18); A age (12-17) after 1960.&#13;
Table B.18: Tunisia&#13;
Gross Enrollment Rate&#13;
Year        CBR        TFR         CDR        e        Primary  -     Secondary  -&#13;
1951               -          -              -            35               8&#13;
1955         -          -                    -            47               9&#13;
1960        43.8       7.1       :21.0      48.1          66              12&#13;
1965        46.1       7.0        17.7      51.2          91              16&#13;
1970        40.6       6.5        14.6      54.2         101              23&#13;
1975        316.0      5.9         11.2     57.2          97              21&#13;
1976i        -          -                    -                              _-&#13;
1977         --                     -        -_&#13;
19 78        -          ---                  -&#13;
1979         -          -          ..         -&#13;
1980(        34.4      5.3          9.1      60.2         103              27&#13;
/1 age (6-11);  - age (12-18).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 95 -&#13;
BIBLIOGRAPHY&#13;
Ainsworth, 1983, "User Charges for Cost Recovery in the Social&#13;
Sector: Current Practice". mimeo.&#13;
Anderson, Michael, 1971, Family Structure in Nineteenth Century&#13;
in Lancashire. Cambridge, England: Cambridge University Press.&#13;
Anker, Richard, 1978. "An Analysis of Fertility Differentials in Developing&#13;
Countries". Review of Economics and Statistics. Vol. LX, No. 1.&#13;
Anker, Richard and James C. Knowles, 1982, Fertility Determinants&#13;
in Developing Countries: A case Study of Kenya. International Labour&#13;
Office. Liege: Ordinary Editions.&#13;
Arnold, Fred, et al. 1975, The Value of Children: A Cross National Study&#13;
Vol. 1 "Introduction and Comparative Analysis" Honolulu: The East-West Center.&#13;
Banks, Arthur S., 1971. Cross-Polity Time Series Data, Cambridge, Mass:&#13;
MIT Press.&#13;
Beaver, l-ephen, 1975.   Demographic Transition Theory Reinterpreted.&#13;
Lexington, Mass.: Lexington Books.&#13;
Becker, Gary S. 1960. "An Economic Analysis of Fertility" in&#13;
Universities-National Bureau of Economic Research. Demographic and&#13;
Economic Change in Developed Countries.    Princeton:   Princeton&#13;
University Press.&#13;
Becker, Gary S. 1975. Human Capital. 2nd edition. New York:&#13;
Columbia University Press for NBER.&#13;
Becker, Gary S. 1981. A Treatise on the Family. Cambridge, Mass.&#13;
Harvard University Press, 1981.&#13;
Becker, Gary S. &amp; H. Gregg Lewis.    1973.  "On the Interaction between the&#13;
Quantity and Quality of Children". Journal of Political Economy. Vol.&#13;
81, No. 2, Pt. 2, pp. 5279-5288.&#13;
Becker, Gary S., and Nigel Tomes, 1976. "Child Endowments and the Quantity&#13;
and Quality of Children". Journal of Political Economy. Vol. 84, No. 4,&#13;
Pt. 2, pp. 5143-5162.&#13;
Behm, Hugo. 1979. "Socioeconomic Determinants of Mortality in Latin&#13;
America." in United Nations/World Health Organization. Proceedings of&#13;
the Meeting on Socioeconomic Determinants and Consequences of&#13;
Mortality. El Cologio de Mexico, Mexico City, 19-25 June 1979. pp.&#13;
139-165.&#13;
Berry, Thomas S. 1978. "Revised Annual Estimates of American Gross National&#13;
Product" Bostwick Paper No. 3. Richmond, Va.: The Bostwick Press.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 96 -&#13;
Blaug, Mark. 1972. An Introduction to the Economics of Education&#13;
London: Penguin.&#13;
Birdsall, Nancy, 1980. "A Cost of Siblings: Child Schooling in Urban&#13;
Colombia".  In J.L. Simon and J. Da Vanzo (eds.) Research in Population&#13;
Economics. Vol. 2, pp. 115-150.&#13;
Birdsall, Nancy and Susan Hlill Cochrane. 1982.  "Education and Parental&#13;
Decision Making:  A Two-Generation Approach."  In Lascelles Anderson and&#13;
Douglas Windham, (eds.) Education and Development. Lexington, MA:&#13;
Lexington Books. pp. 175-210.&#13;
Birdsall, Nancy; Susan H. Cochrane; and Jacques van der Gaag, 1983. "The&#13;
Cost of Children". Unpublished paper.&#13;
Branson, William, 1968. "Social Legislation and the Birth Rate in&#13;
Nineteenth Century Britain". 'Western Economic Journal, March 1968,&#13;
pp. 134-144.&#13;
Bulatao, RodolEo A. and Fre-d Arnold. 1977. "Relationship between the&#13;
Value and Cost of Children and Fertility:  Cross-Cultural Evidence."&#13;
IUSSP, International Pc,pulation Conference, Mexico City. Vol. 1.&#13;
Liege: IUSSP pp. 141-155.&#13;
Bulatao, RodolFo  ,1979. On the Nature of the Transition in the Value of&#13;
Children. Papers of the East-West Population Institute, No. 60-A.&#13;
Bulatao, Rodolfo   1983.  "'Mortality Thresholds for Fertility Transition&#13;
in Developing Countries". World Bank Mimeograph.&#13;
Cain, Mead r.  1977.  "The Economic Activities of Children in a Village in&#13;
Bangladessh". Populaticin and Development Review. Vol. 3, No. 3.&#13;
Caldwell, J. C. 1982.  Thecry  f Fertility Decline.  New York: Academic&#13;
Press.&#13;
Caldwell, J. C.; Jalaluddirn, A.K.M.; Caldwell, P.; and Cosford, W. 1981.&#13;
"The Control of Activity in Bangladesh". Paper presented at the IUSSP&#13;
Seminar on Individuals and Families and Income Distribution, Honolulu,&#13;
April 6-9.&#13;
Carnoy, M. and D. Marenbach. 1975. "The Returns to Schooling in the U.S.,&#13;
1939-1969." Journal of Human Resources.   Vol. 10.&#13;
Chernichovsky, Dov. 1981. "Socioeconomic and Demographic Aspects of School&#13;
Enrollment and Attendance in Rural Botswana". Population and Human&#13;
Resources Division. Discussion Paper No. 81-47. The World Bank.&#13;
Cipolla, Carlo M. 1969. Literacy and Development in the West.&#13;
Baltimore:  Penguin Books.&#13;
Clark, Carol. 1979. "Relattion of Economic and Demographic Factors to&#13;
Household Decisions Regarding Education of Children in Guatemala."&#13;
Unpublished Ph.D. Thesis. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 97 -&#13;
Coale, Ansley.   1973.  "The Demographic Transition"   IUSSP International&#13;
Population Conference, Liege.   Vol I. Li&amp;ge:   International Union for&#13;
the Scientific Study of Population pp. 53-72.&#13;
Cochrane, Susan 1979. Fertility and Education: What Do We Really&#13;
Know? World Bank. Staff Occasional Paper, No. 24, Baltimore: The&#13;
Johns Hopkins University Press.&#13;
Cochrane, Susan H. 1980. "Educational Differences in Child Survival&#13;
in Developing Countries." Paper presented at the annual meetings of the&#13;
Popularion Association of America, April 10-12, 1980, Denver, Colorado.&#13;
Cremin, Lawrence, A. 1980. American Education: The National Experience&#13;
1783-1876. New York: Harper and Row.&#13;
De Tray, Dennis N. 1973. "Child Quality and the Demand for Children."&#13;
Journal of Political Economy. Vol 81, No. 2, Part II. (March/April).&#13;
pp. 570-595.&#13;
De Tray, Dennis, 1976. Population Growth and Educational Policies: An&#13;
Economic Perspective in Ridker, Ronald, ed. Population and&#13;
Development: The Search for Selective Intervention. Baltimore: Johns&#13;
Hopkins University Press (published for Resources for the Future).&#13;
De Tray, Dennis (1978). Child Schooling and Family Size. R-2301-NICHD,&#13;
Santa Monica: Rand Corporation.&#13;
DaVanzo, Julie, 1972. The Determinants of Family Formation in Chile, 1960.&#13;
R-830-AID. Santa Monica, California: The Rand Corporation.&#13;
Dore, Ronald P. 1964. "The Legacy of Tokugawa Education" in Marius B.&#13;
Jansen, (ed.) Changing Japanese Attitudes Towards Modernization.&#13;
Princeton: Princeton University.&#13;
Dore, Ronald P. 1965. Education in Tokugawa Japan. Berkeley: University&#13;
of California Press.&#13;
Easterlin, Richard A. 1971. "Does liuman Fertility Adjust to the Environment?"&#13;
American Economic Review, Vol. 61 No. 2 (May). pp. 399-407.&#13;
Easterlin, Richard A. 1976. "Population Change &amp; Farm Settlement in&#13;
the Northern United States." The Journal of Economic History, Vol.&#13;
XXXVI, No. I (March). pp. 45-75.&#13;
Easterlin, Richard A. 1981. "Why Isn't the Whole World Developed?". The&#13;
Journal Economic History. Vol. 41, No. 1 (March) pp. 1-19.&#13;
Ensign, Forest C. 1969. Compulsory School Attendance and Child Labor.&#13;
American Education:   Its men, Institutions and Ideas Series.    New York:&#13;
Arno Press reprint of 1921 edition.&#13;
Espenshade, Thomas J.   1973.  "The Cost of Children in the Urban United&#13;
States". Population Monograph Series. No. 14. University of&#13;
California, Berkeley.&#13;
Espenshade, Thomas J. 1977. "The Value and Cost of Children." Population&#13;
Bulletin. (32)(1). Washington, D.C. Population Reference Bureau.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 98 -&#13;
Fishlow, Albert. 1966. "rhe American Common School Revival: Factor or&#13;
Fancy?" In Henry Rosozskey, ed. Industrialization in TWo Systems: Essays&#13;
in Honor of Alexander Gershenkson. New York.&#13;
Fishlow, Albert. 1966. "Levels cf Nineteenth Century American Investment in&#13;
Education." The Journal of Economic History. Vol. 26, Nlo. (4) pp.&#13;
418-436.&#13;
Forster, Colin &amp; Tucker, W.S.L. 1972. Economic Opportunity &amp; White American&#13;
Fertility Ratios, 1800-1860. New Haven: Yale University Press.&#13;
3lass, D.V.  1938. "ChangeS in Fertility in England and Wales, 1851-1931."&#13;
In Lancelot Hoyben, ed Political Arithmetic. London: Geroge Allen and&#13;
Unwin. pp. 173-191.&#13;
1G]over, James W. 1921.  United States Life Tables.   1890, 1901, 1910&#13;
and 1901-10.   Washington, D.C.: G.P.O.&#13;
Goldin, Claudia. 1979. "Hlousehold and Market Production of Families in&#13;
a Late Nineteenth-Century City" Explorations in Economics History. Vol.&#13;
16. pp. 111-131.&#13;
Goldin, Claudia. 1981. "Family Strategies and the Family Economy in the&#13;
Late Nineteenth-Century: The Role of Secondary Workers.'' In Theodore&#13;
Hershberg,(ed.) PhiladElphia: Work, Space, Family and Group Experience in&#13;
the Nineteenth Century. New York: Oxford University Press. pp. 277-310.&#13;
Graff, Harvey. "Literacy, Education and Fertility, Past and Present:&#13;
A Criticial Review". Population and Development Review 5 No. 1 (March)&#13;
pp. 105-140.&#13;
Guest, Avery M. and Stewart E. Tolnay. 1981. "Children's Roles and&#13;
U.S. Fertility in the Late Nineteenth Century." Unpublished paper.&#13;
Center Eor Studies in Demograph~y and Ecology. University of Washington,&#13;
Seattle. (August).&#13;
Hlaines, Michae-L R. 1979a.  FertLility and Occupation:  Population Patterns&#13;
in InduStrialization. New York: Academic Press.&#13;
Haines, Michael R. 1979b.   "Industrial Work and the Family Life&#13;
Cycle, L889-1890"   Research in Economic History.   Vol. 4, pp. 289-356.&#13;
Haines, Michael R. 1981.   "Poverty, Economic Stress, and the Family&#13;
in a Late Nineteenth-Century   American City.    Whites in Philadelphia,&#13;
1880. [n Theodore Hershberg, (ed.) Philadelphia: Work, Space, Family,&#13;
and Group Experience in the Nineteenth Century.    New York:  Oxford&#13;
University Press. pp. 240--2715.&#13;
Faines, Michael R. 1983.   "The Life Cycle, Savings, and Demographic&#13;
Adaptation:  Some Historical/EVidence for the United States and Europe."&#13;
Paper presented at the annual Tneetings at the American Sociological&#13;
Association. Detroit, MI. 31 August-3 September.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 99 -&#13;
Hansen, W. Lee 1963. "Total and Private Rates of Return to Investment&#13;
in Education." Journal of Political Economy. Vol. 71, No. 2, (April).&#13;
pp. 128-140.&#13;
liart, Gillian. 1980. "Patterns of Household Labour Allocation in a&#13;
Javanese Village" in Binswanger, H.P.; Everson, R.E., Florencis, C.A.,&#13;
and White, B.N.F. (eds.) Rural Household Studies on Asia.&#13;
Hashimnoto, Masanori. 1980. "Demand for Children in Japan During&#13;
Modernisation" in Julian Simon and Julie Davanzo, eds. Research on&#13;
Population Economics. Vol. 2 pp. 295-320.&#13;
Hauser, Philip M. 1979. World Population and Development: Challenge and&#13;
Prospects.   Syracuse, New York: Syracuse University Press.&#13;
dinchliffe, K. 1983.   "Cost Structures of Secondary Schooling in Tanzania&#13;
and Colombia." World Bank Mimeograph, Education Department.&#13;
Hoffmann, Walther W. 1965. Das Wachstaan der deutschen Wirtschaft&#13;
seit der Mitte des 19 Jahrhundants. Berlin: Springerverlag.&#13;
Hofsten, Erland and lians Lundstrbm. 1976. Swedish Population History:&#13;
Main Trends from 1750 to 1970. Stockholm:    National Central Bureau of&#13;
Statistics.&#13;
Jorberg, Lennart.  1973.   "The Nordic Countries 1850-1914."  In Carlo M.&#13;
Cipolla, (ed.) the Fontana Economic lHistory of Europe.    Vol. 4, Part&#13;
2. London: Fontana. pp. 375-485.&#13;
Katz, Michael and Ian Dany. 1978. "Youth and Early Industrialization in&#13;
a Canadian City."   In John Demos and Sarane Spence Boocock, eds. Turning&#13;
Points: Historical and Sociological Essays on the Family. Chicago:&#13;
University of Chicago Press. pp. 581-5119.&#13;
Kelley, Allen C. 1980. "Interactions of Economic and Demographic Household&#13;
Behavior." in Richard Easterlin, (ed.) Population and Economic Change&#13;
in Developing Countries. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, pp.&#13;
403-448.&#13;
Kelley, Allen C. and Jeffrey C, Williamson. 1974. Lessons from&#13;
Japanese Development: An Analytical History. Chicago, University of&#13;
Chicago Press.&#13;
Kett, Joseph.  1973.    "Adolescence and Youth in Nineteenth-Century&#13;
America." In Theodore K. Rabb and Robert I. Rotberg, (eds.) The&#13;
Family in llistory: Interdisciplinary Essays. New York: liarper and Row.&#13;
Keyfitz, Nathan and Wilhelm Flieger. 1968. World Population: An Analysis&#13;
of Vital Data. Chicago: UIniversity of Chicago Press.&#13;
Knodel, John.  1974.   The Decline of Fertility in Gernany, 1871-1939.&#13;
Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press.&#13;
Knodel, John and Etienne van de Walle. 1979. "Lessons from the Past:&#13;
Policy Implications of {Sistorical Fertility Studies." Population and&#13;
Develop,nent Review.  Vol. 5, No.2 (June) pp. 217-245.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 100 -&#13;
Kuznets, Simon.   1954.  "Underdeveloped Countries and the Pre-Industrial&#13;
Phase in the Advanced Countries: an Attempt at Compariscin." United&#13;
Nations.  Proceeding oE the Wcld Population Conference:    1954.  Vol 5.&#13;
New York: United Nations.&#13;
Kuznets, Simon A. 1966. Modern Economic Growth: Rate, Structure, and&#13;
Spread. New Haven: Yale University Press.&#13;
Landes, David S. 1965. "Japan and Europe Contrasts in Industrialization"&#13;
in W. W. Lockwood, (ed.) The State and Economic Enterprise in Japan.&#13;
Princeton, N.J.: Princeton Ulniversity Press. pp. 93-182&#13;
Landes, David S. 1969. The Unbound Promotheus: Technological Change&#13;
and Industrial Development in Western Europe from 1750 to the Present.&#13;
Cambridge, England. Cambridge University Press.&#13;
Landes, William M., and So]mon, Lewis C.    1972.  "Compulsory Schooling&#13;
Legislation: An Economic Analysis of Law and Social Change in the&#13;
Nineteenth Century." rournal of Economic History. Vol. 32, No. 1&#13;
(March), pp. 54-91.&#13;
Lesthaeghe, Ron J. 1977. The Decline of Belgium Fertility, 1800-1970.&#13;
Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press.&#13;
Levasseur, E. 1897. L'enseiRnement primaire dans les pays civilises.&#13;
Paris-Nancy.&#13;
Lindert, Peter H. 1978. Eertility and Scarcity in America. Princeton:&#13;
Princeton lJniversity Press.&#13;
Lindert, Peter H. 1980. "Child Costs and Economic Development" in Richard&#13;
A. Eastarlin, (ed.) Lopulation and Economic Change in Developing&#13;
Countries. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.&#13;
L.ockwood, William W. 1954. The Economic Development of Japan: Growth&#13;
and Structural Change 1868-1938.   Princeton, N.J.:   Princeton University&#13;
Press.&#13;
Maddison, Angus. 1969. Economic Growth in Japan and the U.S.S.R. New York&#13;
Nanton&#13;
Meesook, O.A. 1983. "Financing and Equity in the Social Sectors in&#13;
Indonesia." World Bank CPD Discussion Paper #1983-5 May.&#13;
Mendelievich, Elias. (ed.). 1979. Children at Work. Geneva:&#13;
International Labor Office.&#13;
Michael, Robert T. and Gary S. Becker. 1973. "On the New Theory of&#13;
Consumer Behavior." Swedish Journal of Economics. Vol. 75, No. 4. pp.&#13;
378-396.&#13;
1Mincer, Jacob. 1962. "On-the--Job Training: Costs, Returns, and Some&#13;
Implicat:ions." Journal of Political Economy. Vol. 70, No. 5, Part 2,&#13;
Supplement (October) pp. 550-579.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 101 -&#13;
Mitchell, Brian R. 1975. European Historical Statistics: 1750-1970.&#13;
New York: Columbia University Press.&#13;
Mitchell, B. R. and H. G. Janes. 1971. Second Abstract of British&#13;
Historical Statistics. Cambridge, England Cambridge University Press.&#13;
Modell, John, Frank F. Furstenberg, Jr., and Theodore Hershberg. 1981.&#13;
"Social Change and Transitions to Adulthood in Historical Perspective."&#13;
In Theodore Hershberg, (ed.)   Philadelphia:   Work,  Space, Family, and&#13;
Group Experience in the 19th Century. New York: Oxford University&#13;
Press. pp. 311-341.&#13;
Morris, V. and A. Zidermaan. 1971. "The Economic Return on Investment in&#13;
Higher Education in England and Wales." Economic Trends. (May)&#13;
London: HMSO.&#13;
Mosk, Carl. 1977. "Demographiic Transition in Japan." The Journal of&#13;
Economic History. (Dec.) pp. 655-674.&#13;
Mosk, Carl. 1980. "Rural-Urban Fertility Differences and the Fertility&#13;
Transition."   Population Studies.   Vol. 34, No. 1 (March), pp. 77-90&#13;
Mueller, Eva. 1972.   "Economic Motives for Family Limitation".&#13;
Population Studies. Vol. 26, No. 3 (Nov.) pp. 383-403.&#13;
Mueller, Eva. 1976. "The Economic Value of Children in Peasant&#13;
Agriculture." in Ronald Ridker, (ed.) Population and Development: The&#13;
Search for Selective Intervention.   Baltimore:   The Johns Hopkins&#13;
University Press.&#13;
Mueller, Eva.   1981.  "The Value and allocation of Time in Rural Botswana."&#13;
The World Bank, Population and Ituman Resources Division Discussion Paper&#13;
No.81-44.&#13;
Mueller, Eva. 1983. "Income, Aspirations and fertility in Rural Areas of&#13;
Less Developed Countries." Paper presented at the Conference on Rural&#13;
Development and Human Fertility, The Pennsylvania State University, May.&#13;
Musgrove, Philip.   1978.  "La Contribucion Familiar Al Financiamiento de La&#13;
Educacion en America Latina" in Mario Brodersohn and Maria Ester&#13;
Sanjurjo (eds.) Financiamiento de la Eduicacion en Anerica Latina.&#13;
Fondo de Cultura Economica and Banco Interamericano de Desarrollo,&#13;
Mexico.&#13;
Nag, Mori; White, Benjamin N.F.; and Peet, R. Creighton. 1980. "An&#13;
Anthropological Approach to the Study of the Economic Value of Children&#13;
in Java and Nepal." in Binswanger, H.P.; Evenson, R.E.; Florencio, C.A.;&#13;
and White, B.N.F.,(eds.) Rural Household Studies in Asia.&#13;
Nardinelli, Clark. 1980. "Child Labor and the Factory Acts." The Journal&#13;
of Econoimic History. Vol. 40, No. 4 (Dec) pp. 739-755.&#13;
Notestein, Frank W. 1953. "The Economics of Population and Food Supplies.&#13;
I.  The Economic Problems of Population Change."    Proceedings of the&#13;
Eighth International Conference of Agricultural Economists, London:&#13;
Oxford University Press.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 102 -&#13;
O(ppenheimer, VaLerie K. 1982.  Work and the Family:   A Study in Social&#13;
Demograpby.  New York:   Academic Press.&#13;
Oshima, Harry C. 1965. "Meiji Fiscal Policy and Economic Progress."&#13;
In W. W. Lockwood, (ed.) The State and Economic Enterprise in Japan.&#13;
PrincetDn, N.J. Princeton University Press. pp. 353-390.&#13;
'inchbock, Ivy and Margaret Hewitt.   1973.  Children in English Society.&#13;
Vol. II.. "From the 18th Century to the Children Act 1948".   London:&#13;
Routledge i Kegan Paul.&#13;
'otter, Joseph E., and Miriam G. Ordenez and Anthony R. Measham.    1976.&#13;
"The Rapid Decline in Colombian Fertility." Population and Development&#13;
Review. Vol. 2 #4, pp. 509-28.&#13;
Preston, Samuel H. 1980. "Causes and Consequences of Mortality Declines&#13;
in Less Developed Countries during the Twentieth Century." In Richard&#13;
A. Easterlin, (ed.) Population and Economic Change in Developing&#13;
Countries.   Chicago:   University of Chicago Press.   pp. 289-341.&#13;
'lreston, Samuel H., Nathan Keyfitz, and Robert Schoen. 1972. Causes&#13;
of Death: Life Tubles for National Populations. New York: Seminar&#13;
Press.&#13;
Preston, Samuel H. and Michael R. Haines.   1981.   "New Estimates of&#13;
Childhood Mortality in the United States in 1900." Wayne State&#13;
University Dept. of Economics Working Paper No. 142 (16 October).&#13;
Psacharopoulos, George.   1981.  "'Returns to Education: an Updated&#13;
International Comparison."   Comparative Education.   vol. 17, #3.&#13;
Psacharopoulos, George.   1982.  "Education as an investment."   Finance and&#13;
Development. vol. 19, #3.&#13;
Republic of China.   Statistical Yearbook of the Republic of&#13;
China 1981 and 1982. )irectorate-General of Budget, Accounting and&#13;
Statistics.&#13;
Ron, Zvi ard Wayne Schutjer. 1982. "An Econometric Analysis of Fertility,&#13;
Schooling, and Time Allocating among Thai Agricultural Households."&#13;
Bulletin 840. Pennsylvania State College of Agriculture, University&#13;
Park, E'A.&#13;
Rodgers, G. and Standing, '. 1981. (eds.) Child Work, Poverty and&#13;
Underdevelopment. Geneva: [nternational Labour Office.&#13;
Rosenzweig, Mark R. 1981. "Redistribution, Population Policies and&#13;
Household Behavior: Implication for Population Growth and Economic&#13;
Development." In Proceedings of the IUSSP International Conference 1981&#13;
Manila, Philippines. Liege: LUSSP.&#13;
Rosenzweig, Mark R. 1982. "Educational Subsidy, Agricultural Development,&#13;
and Fertility Change." The liarterly Journal of Economics. (Feb.) pp.&#13;
67-88.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 103 -&#13;
Rosenzweig, Mark R. and Robert Evenson. 1977. "Fertility, Schooling and&#13;
the Economic Contribution of Children in Rural India:    An Econometric&#13;
Analysis." Econometrica. Vol. 45. No. 5 (July). pp. 1065-1080.&#13;
Rosenzweig, Mark and Schultz, T.P. 1983 "Child Mortality and Fertility in&#13;
Colombia: Individual and Community Effects." Health Policy and&#13;
Education. February.&#13;
Rosenzweig, Mark R. and Wolpin, K.I. 1980. "Testing the quantity-quality&#13;
Fertility Model: The use of twins as a natural experiment."&#13;
Econometrica. Vol. 48, No. 1 pp. 227-240.&#13;
Rosenzweig, Mark R. and Wolpin, K.I. 1982 "Governmental interventions and&#13;
Household Behavior in a Developing Country." Journal of Development&#13;
Economics Vol. 10, No. 2, 209-225.&#13;
Rosovsky, Hlenry. 1966. "Japan's Transition to Modern Economic Growth,&#13;
1868-1885." In Henry Rosovsky, (ed.) Industrialization in Two Systems:&#13;
Essays in lIonor of Alexander Gerschankron. New York: Wiley. pp. 91-139.&#13;
Saiyidain, K.G., Naik, J.P.; and Husain, S.A. 1966. Compulsory Education&#13;
in India. Delhi: Universal Book and Stationary Company.&#13;
Sahota, C. K. and G. S. Sahota. 1980. "Educability-Fertility Trade Off&#13;
in Punjab."  The Indian Economic Journal.   Vol 27, lNo. 4 (April-June).&#13;
pp. 70-90.&#13;
Sandburg, Lars.   1979.  "The case of the Impoverished Sophisticate - Human&#13;
Capital and Swedish Economic Growth before World War I." The Journal of&#13;
Economic History.   vol. 39, 41  (March).&#13;
Schultz, T.W.   1981.  Investing in People, The Economics of Population&#13;
Quality. Berkeley: University of California Press.&#13;
Smith, Richard. 1981. "Three Centuries of Fertility, Economy and Household&#13;
Formation in England." Population and Development Review. Vol. 7, #4,&#13;
(Dec) pp. 595-622.&#13;
Snyder, Donald. 1974. "Economic Determinants of Family Size in West&#13;
Africa." Demography. Vol. 11, No. 4 (N4ov.) pp. 613-628.&#13;
Solmon, Lewis C. 1970. "Estimates of the Costs of Schooling in 1880 and&#13;
1890." Explorations in Economic History. Supplement Vol. 7, #4.&#13;
Solmon, Lewis C. 1970. "Opportunity Costs and Models of Schooling in the&#13;
Nineteenth Century." The Southern Economics Journal. Vol. 37, #1&#13;
(July) pp. 66-&#13;
Solmon, Lewis. 1975. Capital Formation by Expenditures on Formnal&#13;
Education. New York.&#13;
Solmon, Lewis, C. and Michael Tierney. 1980. "Education". In Glen&#13;
Porter, (ed.) Encyclopedia of American Economic History. Vol. 3. New&#13;
York:  Scribnor's.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 104 -&#13;
Stearns, Peter N. 1967.  1_uropean Society in Upheaval:  Social History&#13;
Since 1800. New York: M4acnillan.&#13;
Stycos, J. Mayone.  1978. "Recent Trends in Latin American Fertility."&#13;
Population Studies. Vol. 32, No. 3 (Nov.) pp. 407-425.&#13;
Tan, Jee-Peng.  1983(a).   "Private Education: Some Macro Trends on&#13;
Enrollment and Expenditure."  World Bank, mimeo.&#13;
Tan, Jee-Peng.  1983(b).   "The Willingness to pay for Public Secondary&#13;
Education.  Evidence from Tanzania."   World Bank, -aimeo.&#13;
Taeuber, Irene B. 1958. The Population of Japan. Princeton: Princeton&#13;
University Press.&#13;
Teitelbacrn, Michael S. 1974.  "Birth Under-registration in the Constituent&#13;
Counties of England and Wales; 1841-1910." Population Studies. Vol.&#13;
28, Mo. 2 (July). pp. 329-343.&#13;
Teitelbaum, Michael S. 1975.   "Relevance of Transition Theory for Developing&#13;
Countries." Science. Vol. L88 (2 May). pp. 420-425.&#13;
Thobani, Mateen. 1983. "Charging User Fees for Social Services: The Case&#13;
of Ecducation in Malawi."  World Bank Staff Working Paper #572.&#13;
Tilly, Louise A. and Joan W. Scott.   1979.  Women, Work, and Family.&#13;
New York:  Holt, Rinehart and Winston.&#13;
Tjiptosasmito, W. and Cumlrmings W;.K. 1981. "The Status and Deployment of&#13;
Teachers in Indonesia." Report prepared for World Bank Education&#13;
Project '&amp;5. (kugiist),&#13;
Tolney, ,tewart, Stephen Graham, and Avery Guest. 1982. "Owrn Child Estimates&#13;
of U.S. White Fertility, 1866-1899." Historical Methods. Vol. 15, No. 3&#13;
(Sumner), np. 127-133.&#13;
Tomes, Nigel.  1981.  "The Family, Inheritance, and Intergenerational&#13;
Transmission of Inequality."   Journal of Political Econcmy. Vol. 89, #&#13;
pp. q28-958.&#13;
UNESCO. Studies on Compulsory Education. (series begins in 1954). New&#13;
York, United Nations.&#13;
United Nations. 1975. rhe Population Debate: Dimension and Perspectives.&#13;
Papers af the World Populatiori Conference.  B3ucharest, 1974.  Population&#13;
Studies, #57, New York.&#13;
United Nations. 1979(a). Worlcl Population Trends and Policies. 1977:&#13;
Monitoring Report. Vol. 1.   Population Trends.  Population Studies #62,&#13;
New York.&#13;
United Nations.  1979(b).   Demographic Yearbook: Hlistorical Supplement&#13;
Special Issues. New York. United Nations.&#13;
United Nations.  1982.   T,evels and Trends of hMortality since 1950.&#13;
New York: United Nations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 105 -&#13;
U.S. Bureau of the Census. 1974. Statistical Abstract of the United&#13;
States, 1974. Wash. D.C. G.P.O.&#13;
U.S. Bureau of the Census. 1975. Historical Statistics of the United&#13;
States, Colonial Times to 1970. Washington D.C.: GPO.&#13;
U.S. Bureau of the Census. 1976. Statistical Abstract of the&#13;
United States, 1976. Wash. D.C.: GPO.&#13;
U.S. Commissioner of Labor. 1889. Fourth Annual Report of the&#13;
Commissioner of Labor: 1888. Working W4ornen in Large Cities. Wash.&#13;
D.C.: GPO.&#13;
van de Walle, Etienne. 1974. The Female Population of France in the&#13;
Nineteenth Century: A Reconstruction of 82 Departements. Princeton,&#13;
N.J. Princeton University Press.&#13;
van de Walle, Francine.   1980.   "Edducation and the Demographic&#13;
Transition in Switzerland." Population and Development Review. Vol. 6&#13;
No. 3 (Sept.) pp. 463-472.&#13;
Vlassoff, M. and Vlassoff, C., 1980. "Old Age Security and the Utility of&#13;
Children in Rural India." in Population Studies. November.&#13;
West, E. G. 1970(a).   Education and the State:    A  Strategy in Political&#13;
Economy. Second edition. London: The Institute of Economic Affairs.&#13;
West, E. G. 1970(b). "Resource Allocation and Growth in Early Nineteenth&#13;
Century British Education." Economic History Review. Second series.&#13;
Vol 23, No. 1 (April) pp. 68-95.&#13;
Willis, Robert 1973. "A New Approach to the Economnic Theory of Fertility&#13;
Behavior." Journal of Political Economy. Vol. 81, No. 2, Part II&#13;
(March/April). pp. 514-564.&#13;
Willis, Robert J. 1982. "The Direction of Intergenerational Transfers and&#13;
Demographic Transition." In "Income Distribution and the Family."&#13;
Supplement to Vol. 8.   Population and Development Paper.&#13;
World Bank, 1980. Education Sector Policy Paper. Washington, D.C.&#13;
World Bank, 1983. EPD Social Indicators. May. mimeo.&#13;
Yamamuna, Kozo and Susan Hanley. 1975. "Ichi himo, ni Taro: Educational&#13;
Aspirators and the Decline of Fertility in Postwar Japan." Journal of&#13;
Japanese Studies. Vol 2. ( Autumn). pp. 83-125.&#13;
Yasuba, Yasukichi. 1962. Birth Rates of the White Population of the United&#13;
States, 1800-1860:   An Economic Analysis.   Baltimore:    Johns Hopkins&#13;
Press.&#13;
Zachariah, K.C.   1983.  "Anomaly of the Fertility Decline in Kerala."    The&#13;
World Bank, PHN Technical Notes. RES 2 (July).&#13;
Ziderman, A. 1973. "Does It pay to Take a Degree?" Oxford Economic&#13;
Papers. Vol. 25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
W   orld    Bank                          value of these findings and provides     Demographic Aspects of&#13;
valuable insights into possibilities for  Migration in West Africa-&#13;
Publications                             implementing mass programs for           KC       ahnhadohr&#13;
needy people in villages throughout      K C Zachanah and others&#13;
of Related                               the world                                 Volume I&#13;
Interest                                                                          Staff Working Paper No 414 September&#13;
1980 369 pages (including statistical an-&#13;
Volume 1: Integrated Nutrition           nexes, bibliography)&#13;
and Health Care                          Stock No WP 0414 $15&#13;
Amfned A Kielmann and others&#13;
This volume provides detailed data       Volume 2&#13;
suggesting that synergism between        Staff Working Paper No 415 September&#13;
malnutntion and infechon is probably     1980 391 pages (including statistical an-&#13;
the greatest cause of mortality, mor-    nexes, bibliography)&#13;
The African Trypanosomiases:             bidity, and retarded growth and devel-   Stock No WP 0415 $15&#13;
Methods and Concepts of                  opment in children In an expenment       (These Working Papers are background&#13;
over a penod of four years, villagers&#13;
Control and Eradication in               received nutntion care, general health   studies for Migration in West Afnca&#13;
Relation to Development                  care to control infections, or both Dra-  Demographic Aspects, described in this&#13;
C. W. Lee and J. M. Maunce               matic improvements, including a 40%-     section )&#13;
Here is a practical cost-benefit ap-     50% decline in mortality, a 20% rediic-  Economic Motivation versus&#13;
proach to an age-old problem affecting   creases in  height and weight In addi-   City Lights: Testing&#13;
humans and livestock alike, the Afn-     tion, detailed information on costs is   Hypotheses about Inter-&#13;
can Trypanosomiases Descnbes new         presented that permits the most com-     Changwat Migration in&#13;
techniques that offer tsetse control     plete analysis of cost-effectiveness and  Thailand&#13;
without destroying game animals          program relevant costs and benefits      Fred Amold and Susan H&#13;
Also summarizes current research in      yet avial nti      ido il     e&#13;
genetic control, the use of traps and    search The study focuses directly on       ochrane&#13;
screens, attractants, and pheromones     practical program implications and       Staff Working Paper No 416 September&#13;
Technical Paper No 4. 1983. 107 pages    ways in which such integrated services   1980 41 pages (including footnotes, refer-&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0191-8 Stock No BK 0191      can be applied under field conditions    ences)&#13;
$5                                       The Johns Hopkins University Press 1984  Stock No WP 0416 $3&#13;
Analyzing the Impact of                  288 pages                                Experiments in Family&#13;
Health Services: Project                 LC 82-23915 ISBN 0-808-3064-8 Stock      Planning: Lessons from     the&#13;
Experiences from    India,                                                        Developing World&#13;
Ghana, and Thailand                                                               Roberto Cuca and Cathenne S.&#13;
Rashid Faruqee                                                                    Pierce&#13;
Staff Working Paper No 546 1982 44       Volume II. Integrated Family             A comprehensive review of expen-&#13;
0a-es                                   Planning and Health Care                 mental efforts in the developing world&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0117-9 Stock No WP 0546      Carl E. Taylor and others                to determine more effective ways of&#13;
$3                                       To village people, politicians, and in-  providing family planning services&#13;
temational health planners, health and   The fohns Hopkins University Press, 1978&#13;
family planning have always seemed       276 pages (including bibliography, index of&#13;
NEW                                  to fit naturally together But in the     expertments).&#13;
early 1960s, when international aware-   LC 77-16596 ISBN 0-8018-2023-8, Stock&#13;
Child and Maternal Health                ness of the social and economic conse-   No JH 2013, $19 50 hardcover, ISBN 0-&#13;
Services in India: The                   quences of surging population growth     8018-2014-6, Stock No IH 2014, $8 95&#13;
moved family planning into a position    paperback&#13;
Narangwal Experiment                     of high prionty, some internahonal&#13;
What can pnmary health care and          agencies began to advocate separation     Family Planning Programs: An&#13;
family planning do for women and         of family planning from health serv-     Evaluation of Experience&#13;
children in the poor and deprived        ices In intemational policy discussions  Roberto Cuca&#13;
areas of the world7 Some of the most     the question continues to be impor-&#13;
specific evidence avadable today to      tant This volume analyzes this ques-     Staff Workng Paper No 345 19,9 24b&#13;
support the benefits of these services   bon and provides arguments and evi-      pages (including 2 annexes, referetices)&#13;
is contained in these two studies,       dence to support integration of health   Stock No WP 0345 55&#13;
which represent the findings of re-      care and family planning, it outlines&#13;
search carned out dunng 1967-74 in       the purposes underlying the research     Fertility and Education: What&#13;
twenty-six villages in Punjab, India     in this area, and it proposes policy     Do We Really Know?&#13;
Members of the research staff, which     questions regarding the effectiveness,   Susan H   Cochrane&#13;
started woth 15 people and grew to       efficiency, and equity of such an inte-  A model identifying the manv chan-&#13;
about 150 by the end of the project,     gration                                  nels through whlich education might&#13;
spent many years working with, and       The Johns Hopkins University Press 1984&#13;
shanng the lives of, villagers The       256 pages.&#13;
depth of understanding that came          LC 83-23915 ISBN 0-8018-2830-9 Stock    Prices subject to change without notice&#13;
from this type of shanng enhances the    No. JH 2830 $22 50                        and may vary by country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
act to determine fertilitv and a review   Health Issues and Policies in            Kenya: Population and&#13;
of the evidence of the relation between   the Developing Countries                 Development&#13;
education and the intexenin: vana-        Fredrick Golladay                        (See descnption under Country&#13;
Thebhes inhemopklns at affeterntitPrss  979 Staff Working Paper No 412 1980 55     Studies listing.)&#13;
The Johrss Hopkotis Univerirtt Pness. 1979&#13;
188 pages (including bibliokraphy, index)  pages&#13;
LC 78-2 5070 ISBN 0-801,-2140- 1. Stock   Stock No WI' 01412 53&#13;
No IH 2140, 56 95 paperbiack              Health, Nutrition, and Family            Migration in West Africa:&#13;
Planning in India: A Survey of           Demographic Aspects&#13;
Experiments and Special                  K. C Zachanah and Julien Conde&#13;
Fertility and Its Regulation in           Projects                                 The first study of the large-scale move-&#13;
Fertilid:ys                               PRojects Faruqe and   thna Jhnson        ment of people in nine West Afncan,&#13;
Bangl.desh                                Rashid Faruqee and Ethna Johnson         countnes Discusses the volume and&#13;
R. Amin and Rashid Faruqee                Staff Working Paper No 507 1982 108      direction of internal and external flows&#13;
Staff Acrking Paper .No 3F3 1 380 54      pages (includ!ng references)             and the economic and social character-&#13;
pages (1? cluding references) IStock No W,7 9507 $5                                istics of migrants&#13;
Stock No, WP 0383. 53                                                               A joint World Bank-OECD study Oxfcrd&#13;
Infant and Child Mortality as a           University Press, 1981 166 pages (includ-&#13;
Determinant of Fertility: The             ing 22 maps, bibliography, index)&#13;
Health                                    Policy Implications                       LC 80-21352 ISBN 0-19-520186-8, Stock&#13;
Fredrick Golladay, cooDrditating          Stisan Hill Cochrane and K. C             No OX 520186, $19 95 hardcover, ISBN'&#13;
author                                    Zachariah                                 0-19-520187-6, Stock No OX 520187,&#13;
Draws on expenence gained from            An illustrative analysis that suggests    $8 95 paperback.&#13;
health (omponents of seventv World        infant nmortalitv may be an important&#13;
Bank pi o]ects in fortv-fcur ccuntnes     component of a fertilitv reduction pro-&#13;
between 1975 and 1978 Emphasizes          gram in countres wheFre mortaity s&#13;
the disproportionately high expendi-      gram             where   ality is         Population and Family&#13;
tures irctirred on curative medicine,     high and few couples are able to have     Planning in Bangladesh: A&#13;
the number of surviving children they     Std    afheRsrc&#13;
maintenance of expensive hcsspitals,      desire                                    Study of the Research&#13;
and sophisticated training of medical     World Bank Staff Working Paper No 556     Mohamrnad Alauddin and Rashid&#13;
personnel at the cost of preventve        15983 44 pages                            Faruqee&#13;
care fox the majontv of the people&#13;
Points out that low-cost health care      ISBN 0-8213-0147-0 Stock No WP 0556       Reviews major studies on family plan-&#13;
svstem, are feasible anc recommends       5-                                        ning and on fertility trends, profiles,&#13;
tem; t   re,feasibleean reg, m  e nds                                              and determinants Evaluates results of&#13;
that th, Bank begith. n regar and direct-  Integrating Family Planning              such stuclies and cntiques their melh-&#13;
lending; for health, in adidition to hav-odlg                                                 ndapitonU        erc-s&#13;
ing he2lth components as part of pro-     with Health Services: Does It             odology ond appincahton Underscores&#13;
Zects In other sectors  Help?                                 ~~~~~~~~need for continued study and suggests&#13;
jects in other sectors                    Help?                                     direchons for future research to im-&#13;
Sector Policy Paper 1980 90 ,,ages (in-   Rashid Faruqee                            prove the- Bangladesh population&#13;
cluding 8 annexes, 4 figuies. map)        Staff Working Paper No 515 1982 47        problem&#13;
Stock .%os BK 9066 (Arahtc). BK 9067      pages                                     World Bank Staff Working Paper No 557&#13;
(English). BK 9068 (French). BK 90b9      ISBN 0-8213-0003-2 Stock No WP 0515       1983 176 pages&#13;
(Spanis i) $8 -                           5 3                                       ISBN 0-8213-0150-0 Stock No IVP 0557&#13;
$5&#13;
1D  \I~~J  F            Visit the World Bank&#13;
K Street           wh yBookstore                   Population and Poverty in the&#13;
K Street          When you are in                 Developing World&#13;
1        3         [             I    g      Washington, D.C.                 Nancy 131rdsall&#13;
Staff Working Paper No 404 1980 96&#13;
IStreet                                               pages (including 2 appendixes. bibliog&#13;
7-  3            bi .              8      \ I                                 raphy)&#13;
91 ~i                                                    Stock No WP 0404 $3&#13;
H Street&#13;
~~~~7H                             SLfaetree lsquare             Popula,tion Policy and Family&#13;
X &lt; __ | ~~~~~~~~~~~~~Planning Programs: Trends in&#13;
CIi^  Avenue                                    Policy and Administration&#13;
_-1 _ I  )_Kandiani Kanagaratnam and&#13;
G Street                    The White House             Cathenne S. Pierce&#13;
FF IFI                                I        I                                    Staff Working Paper No 447 1981 S0&#13;
L_    L........J          L....J IJ                   t ___________________         pages (including bibliography, appendixes).&#13;
WVoild Bank Bookstore                                                          Stock No. WP 0447 $3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NEW                                  publhshed as World Population Projec-    falling mortality, and urbanization-&#13;
tlions: Short- and Long-term Projections by  factors that tend to lower fertility else-&#13;
Short-term  Population                   Age and Sex for All Countries, with Re-  where. Calls for a viable population&#13;
Projection, 1980-2020 and Long-          lated Demographic Statistics             policy and programs appropriate to&#13;
term Projection, 2000 to                 1983 391 pages                           the culture&#13;
Stationary Stage by Age and              ISBN 0-8213-0355-4. $30 paperback.       Staff Working Paper No 559 1983. 116&#13;
Sex for All Countries of the&#13;
World                                        NEW                                  ISBN 0-8213-0152-7 Stock Nos WP&#13;
My T. Vu, under the supervision          Rapid Population Growth in&#13;
of K. C. Zachariah                       Sub-Saharan Africa: Issues and           Regional Aspects of Family&#13;
This report gives detailed population    Policies                                 Rgoa        set      fFml&#13;
projections by age and sex for each       o      icies                            Planning and Fertiliq Behavior&#13;
country at five-year intervals from 1980  Rashnd Faruqee and Ravi Gulhah           ln Indonesia&#13;
to 2020 and at twenty-five year inter-   No other country has higher fertility    Dov Chernichovsky and Oey Astra&#13;
vals from 2000 to the year in which      than Kenya and its neighbonng coun-      Meesook&#13;
population becomes stationary in each    tnes in Sub-Saharan Africa. This&#13;
country The implied fertility and mor-   Working Paper examines the reasons       Staff Working Paper No. 462. 1981 62&#13;
tality measures are also given. Revised  for fertility rates staying high, even   pages (including appendix, references).&#13;
annually The 1984 edition will be        rising in the face of greater education,  Stock No WP 0462. $3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
,       The World Bank&#13;
Publications Order Form&#13;
SEND TO: YOUR LOCAL DISTRIBUTOR OR TO WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
(See the oilher uh,e ol Mto lorot          P.O. BOX 37525&#13;
WASHINGTON, D C 20013 U.S.A.&#13;
Date&#13;
Name                                                 Ship to: (Enter if different from purchaser)&#13;
Title                                                Name&#13;
Firm                                                 Title&#13;
Address                                              Firm&#13;
City               State_      Postal Code           Address&#13;
Country             Telephone l                      City             State_      Postal Code&#13;
Purchaser Reference No.                              Country             TeIlephone&#13;
Check your method of payment.&#13;
Enclosed is my C Check w International Money Order O Unesco Coupons E7 International Postal Coupon.&#13;
Make payable to World Bank Publications for U. S. dollars unless you are ordering from your local distributor&#13;
Chaige my D VISA E: MasterCard E American Express C Choice. (Credit cards accepted only for orders addressed&#13;
to World Bank Publications.)&#13;
Credit Card Account Number            Expiration Date                     Signature&#13;
C Invoice me and please reference my Purchase Order No.&#13;
Please ship me the items listed below.&#13;
Customer Internal&#13;
Stock Number  Author/ Title                                       Routing Code  Qusntity  Lnit Price  rotal Amount S&#13;
All prices subject to change.  Prices may vary by country.  Allow 6-8 weeks for delivery.&#13;
Subtotal Cost  $&#13;
Thtal copies_.     Air mail surcharge if desired 1$2.00 each)  $&#13;
Postage and handling for more than two complimentary items )S2.00 each)  S&#13;
Total   S_&#13;
BRD40053                                                          Thank you for your order.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Distributovi of World                    %ttri Mr Uiani.ailo Big,zzi             Attn Mr I NI Hernandez&#13;
i ,  amerrnora 45                       Castello 37&#13;
Bank Publications                        5()121                                  Madrid&#13;
ARGENTINA                                Florene                                 SRI LANKA AND THE MALDIVES&#13;
Carlis Hirsch. SRL                       JAPAN                                   Lake House B3ookshop&#13;
Attn Ms Monica Bustos                    Eastern Book Service                    Attn Mr Vxitor Walatara&#13;
Florida 165 4- pl.O                      Attrn Mr lerumaba Hirano                41 Wad Ramanavake Mawatha&#13;
Galeria Guemes                           37-3, HongD 3-Chome, Bunkvo-ku 113      Colombo 2&#13;
Buenos Aires 1307                        Tokvo                                   SWEDEN&#13;
AUSTRALIA, PA.PUA NEW GUINEA,            KENIYA                                  ABCE Fritze, Kungl, Ho% bokhandel&#13;
FIJI, SOLOMON ISLANICS,                  Atnra Bool, Ser% ices (E A I Ltd        Attn Mr Eide hegerback&#13;
WESTERN SAOLOMOA AND                    rAtn Mr \l B Dar                         Regennrsgatan 12. BOx lt35h&#13;
WESUTER   SAO,ADO Box 4-'245                                                     S-103 2. Stockholm&#13;
The Australian -inanLial Re%ieA          Nairebi                                 SWITZERLAND&#13;
Intormation Serx we (AFRISI              KOREA, REPUBLIC OF                      Librairie ['avit&#13;
Attn Mlr Dasid lamiesoni                 Pan Korea 3ook Corporation              Attn .Mr Henri de Perrot&#13;
235-243 Jones Stieet                     Attn Mr Yoon-Sun Kim                   hs, rue Grenus&#13;
Broadwav                                 P 0 Box 101 Kwanghwamun                 1211 Geneva&#13;
Svdnev, NSW 20001                        Seoul                                   TANZANIA&#13;
BELGIUM                                 MAILAYSIA                                Oxtord Uni% ersitv Press&#13;
Piblications des Naticn, Lmies          Uni%ersit, it Malava Cooperative         Attn Mr Anthonv Fheobold&#13;
Attn Mr Jean di Lannos                  Bookshop Ltd                             Maktaba Road P o Box 5299&#13;
as du Roi 202                            Attn Mr Mohammed Fahim Htl              Dar e Salaarn&#13;
1060 Brussels                           Xaccb                                    THAILAND&#13;
CANADA                                   P 0 Box 1127, Jalan Pantai Baru         Central Department Store. Head Ottice&#13;
Le Ditfuseur                            Kuala Lumpur                             Attn Mrs Ratana&#13;
Attn Mrs Suzanne Vermette                MEXICO                                  30tb Silom Road&#13;
C P 8;, Bouwheiville J4B SEt,           INFOTEC                                  Bangkok&#13;
Quebec                                   Attn Mr orge Ce peda                    Thailand Management Association&#13;
C Ran Lorenzo t;3-le. Col del Valle,     Attn Mrs Stinan&#13;
COSTA RICA                               D)eleg Benito Juarez                    308 Silom Road&#13;
Libreria frelos                         03100 Mesimo. D F                        Bangkok&#13;
Attn Mr Hugo Chamberlain&#13;
Calle 11-13, Av Fernandez Guell          MIDDLE EAST                             TUNISIA&#13;
San Jose                                 Middle Easi Marketing ResearLh         So,iite funisienne d.L Dittubion&#13;
DENMARK                                  BUlreau                                 Attn .Mr Slaheddine Ben Hamida&#13;
DENMARK                       ~~~~~~~~-\ttn MIr Coorge '.assiloo'  ~      A%enue de Carthage&#13;
Santundslitteratir                       Mlit is Bld  1 I                        Funis&#13;
Attn Nlr WiltriLd Rolott                 Mlik.rini 17,[ Asenue&#13;
Rosenderns Alle 11                       \iuos1a                                 TURKEY&#13;
DK-1970 Copent-agen V                    Ls F Li                                 Ha set Kitarpei A S&#13;
EGYPT, Arab Republic of                 13ran)h otfices in Bahrain, Greeue.     Attn Mr zzet Izerel&#13;
Al Ahram                                 Miro.co, Kussait. Lnited Arab           4th9 [stiklal (addesi&#13;
Al Galaa Street                          I mnirates, lordan)                     Be%oglu-lstanibul&#13;
Cairo                                    NETHERLANDS                             UNITED KINGDOM AND&#13;
%IBE BV                                  NORTHERN IRELAND&#13;
FINLAND                                  Attn Mr Cerhard van Bussell             Microinto Ltd&#13;
Akateeminen Kiilakauppa                  'oorderwal 38.                          Attn Mr Rov Selwvn&#13;
Attn Mr kari Litmanen                   7241 BL L0(hem                           Newmdn Lane, Pr    Box 3&#13;
Keskuskatu 1. Sl'-00100                  NORWAY                                  Alton, Hampshire GU34 2PG&#13;
Helsinki 10                             lohan Grundt Tanum A S                   England&#13;
FRANCE                                   Attn .Ms Randi Mikkelborg               UNITED STATES&#13;
World Bank Publications                 PrC) Box 1177 Sentrum                    The World Bank Book Store&#13;
66, asenue d lena                        Oslo I                                  ht00 19th Street. N W&#13;
,;116 Paris                              PANAMA                                  Washington. D C 20433&#13;
GERMANY, Federal Republic of             Edic,ones Libreria Culturai Panaimena   (Postal addrebs P 0 Box 37525&#13;
UNO-Verlag                               Attn Mr Luob Fernandez Fraguela R       Wvahington D C 20013, L S A&#13;
Attn Mr Joachim Krause                   An    E   na Zon                        Baker and Tavlor Companv&#13;
Simrockstrasse 23                        I na a    le I                          501 South Glc,idiola Avenue&#13;
D-5300 Bonn I                            PHILIPPINES                             Momence llinoib, ht)9N4&#13;
HONG KONG, MACAU                         National Book Store                     380 Fdison WVav&#13;
AHNa 2000 Ltd                            Attn Mrs Socorro C Ramos                Renu, Ne\ada, 89;t4&#13;
Attn Ms Gretchen Wearing Smith           701 Rizal A,enue                        5O Kirbv Avenue&#13;
h Fl . 146 Prince Edward Rodd            Manila                                  Somersille New Jersev, 0887,&#13;
Koswloon                                 PORTUGAL                                Commerce, Georgia 30599&#13;
INDIA                                   L[I rerna Portugal&#13;
LBS Publishers' Distributors Ltdi        \ttn NMr Antonio Alses Martins          B7rnan Asoriates&#13;
LBS Pulisher' Disributos LtdRto,:IDo Carmo 70-74                       9730-E George Palmer Highway&#13;
Attn Mr D P Veer                         'iOLanham, Maryvlandi, 20761&#13;
i Ansari Road, Post Box 701;              Ia,&#13;
Ne', Delhi 11OW2                         1'bon                                   Blackwell North Amenca Inc&#13;
(BranLh oftices i Bomba' Bangalore       SAUDI ARABIA                            1001 Fries Mill Road&#13;
Kanpur Calcutta, and Vadras)             larr Book Store                         Blackwood New Jersev 08012&#13;
INDONESIA                                Attn .Mr Akram Al-Agil                  Sidnev Kramer Books&#13;
Pt Indira Limited                        P 0 Box 3196                            1722 I Street N W&#13;
Attn Mr Bambang Wahvudi                  Risadh                                  Washington, D C 20006&#13;
Jl, Dr Sam Ratulangi No 37               SINGAPORE, TAIWAN, BURMA                Lnited Nationb Bookshop&#13;
Jakarta Pusat                            Intormation Publications Private. Ltd   United Nations Plaza&#13;
IRELAND                                  Attn Ms lanet David                     New York, N Y 10017&#13;
TDC Publishers                          02-0) Ist Floor, Pet-Fu Industrial       V&#13;
Attn Mr James Booth                       Building                               LENEZUELA&#13;
12 North Frederi,k Street               24 New Industrial Road                  LAbrena del E    rte&#13;
Dublin I                                Singapore                                Attn Mr Juan PernLas&#13;
Dublin I            Singapore                               ~~~~~~~~~~~~Av'da Francisco de Miranda, no 32&#13;
ITALY                                   SPAIN                                    Edificio Galiaan, Aptdo 60 337&#13;
I ILOsa Commissmin,iri,, Sansoni SPA     Mundli-Prensa Libros, S A               Caracas 1060-A&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG 3881.5 .W57 W67 NO.697&#13;
c.3&#13;
TAN, JEE PENG, 1954-&#13;
SCHOOLING AND DFMAND FOR&#13;
CHILDRFN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The WVorld Bank&#13;
Headcluarters                        European Office               Tokyo Office&#13;
1818 11 Street, N W.                 66, avenue d'1ena            Kokusai Building&#13;
Washimgton, DC 20433, USA.           75116 Pans, Frarce            1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephonie: (202) 477-1234           TeleFhone: (1) 723-54.21      Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex. WUI 64145 WORI.DBANK          Telex 842-620623              Telephone (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                          Telex 781-26838&#13;
Cable iddress. INTBAFIAD&#13;
WASHINGTCNDC&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0450-X&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554763">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/11/1554763/schooling-demand-children-historical-perspectives
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/11/1554763/schooling-demand-children-historical-perspectives</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1984/11/1554763/schooling-demand-children-historical-perspectives</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/06/14/000178830_98101903424960/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/06/14/000178830_98101903424960/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-06-14T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1984-11-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Schooling and demand for children :
            historical perspectives
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Theory predicts that schooling of
            children exerts a negative effect on parental fertility.
            Results of empirical studies related to this are mixed. This
            paper extends the existing discussion by evaluating the
            evidence from a historical perspective. The time-series data
            for five presently developed countries and eighteen
            developing countries show that, with some exceptions,
            overall a fairly high level of educational development
            seemed to be important for a decline in fertility to take
            place. It is suggested that costs and financing arrangements
            and parental aspirations for children's education may
            be important reasons behind the observed historical
            relationship. As a society modernizes the inverse
            relationship between child schooling and parental fertility
            is likely to become stronger. The high level of primary
            school enrollments characteristic of such societies is
            probably symptomatic of rising returns to education, which
            implies a corresponding rising payoff to investment in child quality.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Schooling and demand for children :
            historical perspectives
        </docna>
        <display_title>Schooling and demand for children
            : historical perspectives</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1984/11/1554763/schooling-demand-children-historical-perspectives</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Early Child and Children's Health,Gender and Social Development,Primary Education,Teaching and Learning</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Gender</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Tan, J.</author>
            <author>Haines, M.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903424960</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Primary health, including
            reproductive health, child health and health</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 697</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Gender</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Health, Nutrition &amp; Population</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0450-X</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Rate of return; Fertility rate; Cost of
            education; Case studies; Schooling
            aged,basic needs,Birth rate,child
            mortality,childbearing,childhood,childhood
            mortality,Cs,cultural values,distance to school,economic
            development,educational development,enrollment
            rate,Enrollment Rates,families,family
            planning,Fertility,generations,gross enrollment,gross
            enrollment ratios,homework,investment in
            education,Laws,level of education,levels of
            education,literacy,Maternal
            Mortality,media,migration,Mobility,mortality,Multiple
            births,norms,nutrition,PAPERS,parents,pill,population
            growth,power,pregnancy,primary education,primary
            school,primary school enrollments,primary
            schooling,productivity,public health,pupils,rates of
            return,repeaters,rural areas,schools,siblings,societies,twins
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP697</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>IMR</ml:concept><ml:concept>Maternal and Child Mortality</ml:concept><ml:concept>U5MR</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographic Transition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Investment in Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Provision of Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Provision of Education Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private School</ml:concept><ml:concept>School Fees</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Returns to Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forest and Forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Basic Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Capital</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing People</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Employment Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infant and Child Mortality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographic Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>User Fees in Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Child Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Returns to Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Primary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Secondary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor and Employment Laws and Regulations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>