<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>foDr Doe3 t'ne2t( ResourlJce$ MobiRizafti¢on&#13;
The Case off the Republic of Ko-r-&#13;
Shahid Yusuf            SWP628&#13;
R. Kyle Peters&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 628&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 628&#13;
Savings Behavior and Its Implications&#13;
for Domestic Resource Mobilization&#13;
The Case of the Republic of Korea&#13;
Shahid Yusuf&#13;
R. Kyle Peters&#13;
INTERNATIONAL MONETARY FUM&#13;
JOINT LIBRARY&#13;
APR 1 Ci 1984&#13;
INTEINATIONAL BANK FOR&#13;
RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOP?CNT&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20431&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright ( 1984&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development / THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
First printing April 1984&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To&#13;
present the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has&#13;
not been prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal&#13;
printed texts, and the World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The&#13;
publication is supplied at a token charge to defray part of the cost of&#13;
manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to&#13;
any individual acting on their behalf. Any maps used have been prepared&#13;
solely for the convenience of the readers; the denominations used and the&#13;
boundaries shown do not imply, on the part of the World Bank and its affiliates,&#13;
any judgment on the legal status of any territory or any endorsement or&#13;
acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications is described in the Catalog of World&#13;
Bank Publications, the continuing research program of the Bank is outlined in&#13;
World Bank Researchi Program: Abstracts of Current Studies. Both booklets are&#13;
updated annually; the most recent edition of each is available without charge&#13;
from the Publications Sales Unit of the Bank in Washington or from the&#13;
European Office of the Bank, 66, avenue d'Iena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Shahid Yusuf is an economist and R. Kyle Peters an economic support&#13;
systems analyst with the East Asia and Pacific Regional Office of the World&#13;
Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Yusuf, Shahid, 1949-&#13;
Savings behavior and its implications for domestic&#13;
resource mobilization.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 628)&#13;
1. Saving and investment--Korea. I. Peters, R.&#13;
Kyle, 1954-       .   II. Title.   III. Series.&#13;
HC470.S3Y87    1984        339.4'3'095195         83-26016&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0304-X&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Abstract&#13;
This paper focuses on the path of domestic resource mobilization&#13;
in the Republic of Korea, over the past twenty years, and on the probable&#13;
medium term trend.&#13;
To achieve the investment targets of the Fifth Five Year Plan&#13;
(FYP), within the confines of the current environment of the world capital&#13;
markets, will require a strong recovery of national savings from the depressed&#13;
level which followed the second oil-price shock. The first section of this&#13;
paper briefly reviews the underlying behavioral relationships which have&#13;
been identified in the theoretical literature as affecting savings. From&#13;
this, a number of potential explanatory variables are selected, which are&#13;
tested empirically in the second part of the paper. Our empirical analysis&#13;
reveals that savings behavior, in the Republic of Korea, is explained by&#13;
current income, the growth of income, the rate of inflation, and the real&#13;
time deposit rate. After establishing the responsiveness of savings to this&#13;
set of variables, the course of domestic resource mobilization in the Korean&#13;
economy is simulated according to the movements of these variables as&#13;
envisioned in the Fifth FYP. The result of these simulations reveal a need&#13;
for additional foreign savings, if the growth targets of the Fifth plan are&#13;
to be met.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Acknowledgements&#13;
We would like to thank Mr. Parvez Hasan for his perceptive comments.&#13;
The burden of programming was ably shouldered by Ms. Y. Hirao. All errors&#13;
remain our sole responsibility.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page no.&#13;
I. Overview .... .      .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .  1&#13;
11.  Savings Performance in Comparative Perspective . . . . . . .  7&#13;
III.  Savings Hypothesis ....            ...... .   .  .  .  .  .  .   .  10&#13;
IV.  Data  .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .  13&#13;
V.  Estimation Results . . .....    ... .    .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .  20&#13;
VI.  Future Implications. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .  24&#13;
VII.  Evaluating the Projections . ...                             26&#13;
Appendix A. Savings As Defined in the Korean National Accounts&#13;
and the World Bank Statistical Manual&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. OVERVIEW&#13;
There was a time when the analysis of savings behavior was one of&#13;
the central concerns of development economists. Since growth required the&#13;
accumulation of capital and few countries could rely to any large extent on&#13;
foreign sources, economic expansion was regulated by the availability of&#13;
domestic savings. By the mid 70s, however, interest in the subject of&#13;
domestic savings was beginning to wane for a variety of reasons./1 Whereas&#13;
capital was once the fulcrum of development, it had to a degree been&#13;
overshadowed by technology which promised much the same if not superior&#13;
results with far less effort and self-abnegation. Further, after years of&#13;
refinement and testing, the most popular theories explaining saving behavior&#13;
showed signs of exhaustion. New ideas were scarce and the paucity of data&#13;
on the developing countries rendered somewhat futile the activity of&#13;
empirically verifying hypotheses, forged within the institutional context of&#13;
the industrial nations.&#13;
Perhaps most important was the sudden increase in the availability&#13;
of foreign savings, primarily in the form of petro-dollars, following the&#13;
first oil crisis in 1973. Unable to find borrowers for all funds which&#13;
the adjustment in energy prices placed at their disposal, the major western&#13;
banks evinced a growing willingness to lend to developing nations, consider-&#13;
ed poor risks in the past./2 The moderate pace of economic activity in the&#13;
OECD countries, throughout the latter part of the 70s, which dampened the&#13;
demand for loans at a time when savings were registering a modest increase,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
increase, induced smaller banks to throw in their lot with the major&#13;
international institutions. As a result, those developing nations whose&#13;
prospects appeared favorable, either because of their performance as&#13;
exporters or by virtue of their resource endowment, found that adding to the&#13;
capital stock was no longer tied rigidly to the saving propensities of&#13;
their citizens /3.&#13;
While the need to mobilize more resources locally remained on the&#13;
agenda of planners and the lips of development advisers, the analysis of&#13;
savings behavior became less urgent. Most people assumed that so long as&#13;
economic growth could be sustained, through a combination of exporting,&#13;
encouraging domestic business activity and overseas borrowing, savings would&#13;
keep on expanding, eventually obviating the need to look abroad. Thus, the&#13;
Korean Fourth Five Year Plan (FYP) which commenced in 1977, assumed that by&#13;
1981 Korea would be able to finance all of her investment from domestic&#13;
savings. In fact, during the first two years of the Plan it seemed as though&#13;
this goal might be realized. As shown in Table 1 and Figure 1, Gross&#13;
National Savings (GNS), as a ratio of GNP, rose from 19.7% in 1975 to 27.4%&#13;
in 1978 while the ratio of foreign savings to GNP fell from 9.3% to 2.3%.&#13;
But the decline in business activity, which followed on the heels of the&#13;
second oil price adjustment in 1979, brought savings down to 20.7% in 1980&#13;
from 27.3% in the previous year and forced Korea to rely upon foreign&#13;
borrowing. Two years later, in 1982, the level of savings was still only&#13;
22%.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
Since the country may need to invest, annually, an average of 30% or&#13;
more of GNP over the next four years in order to attain the target growth of&#13;
7.5% to 8%,domestic savings will have to increase since the flow of capital to&#13;
countries such as Korea, by way of the international banks, may be curtailed:&#13;
as the problems cf Poland, Mexico, Brazil and Argentina lead to a return of&#13;
conservative lending policies; the need for financing large public sector&#13;
deficits in the Western economies increases greatly the demand for these&#13;
funds; and, a revival of business in the OECD countries multiplies the range&#13;
of less risky options./4&#13;
For macroeconomic objectives to be realized, national savings must&#13;
increase by at least 9% over a four year period. Since government savings,&#13;
which reached 6.6% in 1981 may not grow by more than 1% of GNP, the entire&#13;
increment in resources will have to come from the household and corporate&#13;
sectors. Is this within the realm of possibility? How much reassurance can be&#13;
derived from econometric analysis, given the character of savings data, and&#13;
the possibility that some critical parameters might have been altered by a&#13;
change in expectations and economic opportunities in recent years? These are&#13;
the questions which are tackled in this paper.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
Table 1: GROSS NATIONAL SAVINGS AND FOREIGN SAVINGS&#13;
(% of GNP at current prices)&#13;
Gross National Savings (GNS) /a&#13;
House-  Corpo-    Gov-      Composition of GNS       Foreign&#13;
Total     hold    rate  ernment      GDS     NCT     NFI      savings&#13;
/b      /c       /d      /e         /f             /h         /i&#13;
1953        13.5     6.5     4.9     2.1        7.6    4.7      1.2       1.7&#13;
1954        10.2     4.7     5.4     0.2        5.6     3.6     1.0       1.1&#13;
1955         9.2     3.6     4.8     0.7        4.0    3.9      1.2       1.4&#13;
1956         7.3    -2.6     4.8     5.1       -2.9    9.3      0.9      -0.8&#13;
1957        13.5     4.8     4.9     3.7        4.8     7.9     0.7       0.0&#13;
1958        12.4     3.6     5.5     3.3        4.2     7.5     0.7      -1.1&#13;
1959        10.7     1.7     6.2     2.8        3.6    6.4      0.7      -0.4&#13;
1960         8.4    -1.8     5.9     4.4        0.1    7.5      0.7      -0.4&#13;
1961        11.4    -0.2     6.4     5.2        1.9    8.5      0.9      -1.4&#13;
1962        11.4    -0.9     7.8     4.5        2.4    8.1      0.9       2.0&#13;
1963        15.2     3.4     7.5     4.3        8.0    6.5      0.7       3.7&#13;
1964        14.8     3.5     6.8     4.5        8.0    6.1      0.7       0.7&#13;
1965        14.1     0.2     8.1     5.8        6.4    6.7      0.9      -0.3&#13;
1966        17.6     4.1     7.8     5.7       10.6     5.7     1.3       2.7&#13;
1967        16.1     1.3     8.2     6.6        9.7    4.8      1.7       4.1&#13;
1968        18.9     2.9     8.1     7.8       13.7     3.8.    1.4       7.4&#13;
1969        22.1     7.1     8.0     7.0       17.7     3.3     1.2       7.3&#13;
1970        19.4     4.5     7.7     7.3       16.9     2.1     0.4       7.2&#13;
1971        17.1     3.6     7.7     5.8       15.5     1.8    -0.1       8.9&#13;
1972        17.4     4.2     9.4     3.8       16.1     1.7    -0.4       3.6&#13;
1973        25.0     9.1     11.7    4.2       24.3     1.4    -0.7       2.4&#13;
1974        21.7     7.0    12.4     2.4       21.4     1.2    -0.9      11.2&#13;
1975        19.7     4.1    11.5     4.1       20.2     1.1    -1.6       9.3&#13;
1976        24.3     6.7    11.2     6.4       23.7     1.3    -0.6   ~   1.1&#13;
1977        25.8     9.1    11.2     5.5       25.7     0.6    -0.6       0.0&#13;
1978        27.4    10.9    10.1     6.3       26.9     1.0    -0.5       2.3&#13;
1979        27.3    10.3    10.0     7.0       27.6.    0.7    -1.0       6.9&#13;
1980        20.7     6.2     8.6     5.9       23.0     0.8    -3.1       9.4&#13;
1981        20.4     5.3     8.5     6.6       23.3     0.8    -3.7       7.1&#13;
1982 p      22.2     6.0     9.4     6.7       25.0     0.8    -3.6       -&#13;
/a  Gross National Savings = GNP + net current transfers from the rest of the&#13;
world (ROW) - consumption. This differs from the definition used by the&#13;
Bank of Korea (BOK) for "National Savings" (see Appendix A).&#13;
/b  Total may not equal sum of the components due to rounding errors.&#13;
7T   Includes private households and nonincorporated private enterprises.&#13;
Depreciation on nonincorporated private enterprises is included under&#13;
corporate savings because disaggregated data were not available.&#13;
/d  Includes private and public enterprises, depreciation of private and&#13;
public enterprises, and depreciation of nonincorporated private enter-&#13;
prises as noted above.&#13;
/e  Includes government savings and depreciation expenses for general&#13;
government.&#13;
/f  Gross Domestic Savings = GDP - consumption.&#13;
H NCT = Net current transfers from ROW.&#13;
NFI = Net factor income from ROW.&#13;
7T   Foreign savings are "net borrowings from the rest of the world"; net cur-&#13;
rent transfers are included in GNS. The BOK definition includes NCT (see&#13;
Appendix A).&#13;
Source: National Income in Korea, (1982) BOK.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 1: GROSS NATIONAL SAVINGS AND FOREIGN SAVINGS&#13;
(AS X OF GNP)&#13;
40-&#13;
TOTAL SAVINGS&#13;
- - GROSS NATIONAL SAVINGS&#13;
3---FOREIGN SAVINGS&#13;
30-&#13;
E&#13;
R&#13;
C&#13;
E&#13;
N&#13;
10    I                                              1%. l l l l l l l l &#13;
0-~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
1953        1958        1963        1968        1973        1978&#13;
SOURCE: BANK OF KOREA, THE NATIONAL INCOME IN KOREA C1982)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
II. Savings Performance in Comparative Perspective&#13;
Korea is a relative newcomer to the ranks of countries whose&#13;
savings rates are above the average. Early in the sixties the level of Gross&#13;
Domestic Saving (GDS) was negligible, and investment was financed largely&#13;
through net current transfers from the rest of the World (ROW) (see Table&#13;
1 and Figure 2). A turnaround apparently occurred in the middle of the decade&#13;
with GDS increasing from about 2% of GNP in 1962 to 17% in 1970. A number of&#13;
economists, among them McKinnon, have argued that this spurt can be ascribed&#13;
to the policy of posting positive real interest rates on time and savings&#13;
deposits. Our own results, discussed later, suggest that savings are interest&#13;
elastic, but some allowance should also be made for improvements in accounting&#13;
practices in the second half of the sixties which made the measurement of&#13;
income and expenditure more accurate. Furthermore, the intractability of&#13;
evaluating savings in the form of real assets, as against financial savings,&#13;
might have led to an underestimate of savings in the earlier years. The large&#13;
outlays by Korean families on the education of children also includes elements&#13;
of savings passed over by conventional definitions (see Table 2). After&#13;
making due allowance for these factors, it remains that the mobilization of&#13;
domestic resources proceeded at a respectable clip over the following ten&#13;
years. Gross domestic savings reached 24.3% of GNP in 1973 and six years&#13;
later peaked at 27.6%. Much of this increase resulted from the growth in&#13;
Private savings which went from 8.3% in 1966 to 20.8% in 1973, but Government&#13;
savings also increased from under 4.5% in the early 1960's to 7.0% by the end&#13;
of the decade. After averaging 4% during the early 70s, they once again rose&#13;
to above 6.4% in 1976 and have fluctuated around that level since.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 2: COMPOSITION OF GROSS NATIONAL SAVINGS&#13;
C% OF GNP AT CURRENT PRICES)&#13;
30-_-&#13;
GROSS DOMESTIC SAVINGS&#13;
2S-    -- NET FACTOR INCOME&#13;
----NET CURRENT TRANSFERS&#13;
p 2 IS&#13;
E1&#13;
R&#13;
C&#13;
E&#13;
T            P.&#13;
N~~~ ~~ 10-    ...&#13;
0-S&#13;
1953         1958         1963         1968         1973        1978&#13;
SOURCE: BANK OF KOREA, THE NATIONAL INCOME IN KOREA C1982)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
Table 2: EDUCATIONAL EXPENDITURES&#13;
(in Won) /a&#13;
Urban households                            Rural households&#13;
Education                            Education&#13;
expenses      Income       %         expenses      Income        %&#13;
1965      5,160      112,560      4.6         4,482        112,200      4.0&#13;
1966      8,040      161,520      5.0         6,350        130,176      4.9&#13;
1967     12,600      248,640      5.1         7,945        149,472      5.3&#13;
1968     19,800      285,960      6.9         9,732        178,956      5.4&#13;
1969     19,440      333,600      5.8        11,432        217,872      5.2&#13;
1970     23,760      381,240      6.2        14,185        255,804      5.5&#13;
1971     30,120      451,920      6.7        18,363        356,388      5.2&#13;
1972     39,120      517,440      7.6        20,382        429,396      4.7&#13;
1973     43,560      550,200      7.9        24,111        480,708      5.0&#13;
1974     43,080      644,520      6.7        27,838        674,448      4.1&#13;
1975     50,880      859,320      5.9        38,443        872,928      4.4&#13;
1976     67,680    1,151,760      5.9        58,404      1,156,260      5.1&#13;
1977     71,880    1,405,080      5.1        79,252      1,432,812      5.5&#13;
1978     84,720    1,916,280      4.4       105,358      1,884,192      5.6&#13;
1979    120,396    2,629,596      4.6       146,483      2,227,488      6.6&#13;
1980    135,288    3,205,152      4.2       200,283      2,693,100      7.4&#13;
1981    166,524    3,817,224      4.4       253,348      3,687,852      6.9&#13;
/a  731 W = 1 US$, average 1982 (line rf from International Financial&#13;
Statistics).&#13;
Survey:  Economic Planning Board, EPB, The Family Income and Expenditure&#13;
Survey.&#13;
Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries, The Farm Household Economy&#13;
Survey.&#13;
Source:  Social Indicators In Korea, 1982:    p. 52 and 135.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
A gross national savings ratio of over 25% is very respectable by&#13;
any standards, but is well below that of some of the economies with which&#13;
Korea is most frequently compared e.g., Japan and Singapore. As Table 3&#13;
shows, savings in these countries were appreciably in excess of 30%&#13;
throughout much of the 70's even though the Korean economy expanded&#13;
considerably faster than Japan's and maintained a slight edge over that of&#13;
Singapore. If we assume that savings behavior in these nations is broadly&#13;
similar and that Korea will eventually draw abreast, then it would be&#13;
reasonable to expect a sustained growth in savings in the course of the&#13;
1980s as stated in the Fifth FYP. On the other hand, if we take the gap&#13;
between Korean savings performance and that of the other two countries as&#13;
evidence of a structural difference in attitudes towards accumulation, a&#13;
plausible hypothesis, based on movements during the 1970s, one would expect&#13;
a recovery of savings within the next 3-4 years to a 27% level, as occurred&#13;
after the first oil shock in 1973/74, and little further increase,&#13;
thereafter. The implications of these two rather divergent hypotheses for&#13;
growth, BOP deficits, and foreign borrowing are quite profound.&#13;
Doubts and disagreements can be resolved through recourse to&#13;
beliefs concerning the future actions of Korean households and governments.&#13;
Alternatively, an attempt can be made to model savings behavior as depicted&#13;
in the annual time series data stretching back to the early 1950s, and the&#13;
course of future accumulation derived from parameters brought to the surface&#13;
by statistical tests.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
Table 3: GROSS NATIONAL SAVINGS RATIOS: VARIOUS ASIAN ECONOMIES /a&#13;
(% of GNP at current prices)&#13;
Year             Korea /b               Japan /c           Singapore&#13;
1952                -                     25.6                -&#13;
1953               13.5                   25.4                -&#13;
1954               10.2                   22.0                -&#13;
1955                9.2                   26.2                -&#13;
1956                7.3                   29.0                -&#13;
1957               13.5                   31.1                -&#13;
1958               12.4                   28.7                -&#13;
1959               10.7                   32.1                -&#13;
1960                8.4                   35.2                -&#13;
1961               11.4                   38.6                -&#13;
1962               11.4                   34.9                -&#13;
1963               15.2                   35.1                -&#13;
1964               14.8                   35.1                -&#13;
1965               14.1                   33.0                -&#13;
1966               17.6                   34.7                -&#13;
1967               16.1                   36.3                -&#13;
1968               18.9                   38.1               19.7&#13;
1969               22.1                   39.1               19.1&#13;
1970               19.4                   39.7               19.3&#13;
1971               17.1                   38.0               18.4&#13;
1972               17.4                   37.8               24.1&#13;
1973               25.0                   37.9               27.3&#13;
1974               21.7                   35.1               25.1&#13;
1975               19.7                    32.5              25.5&#13;
1976               24.3                   32.1               27.7&#13;
1977               25.8                   32.4               28.8&#13;
1978               27.4                   32.4               28.3&#13;
1979               27.3                   32.1               28.9&#13;
1980               20.7                    31.7              28.9&#13;
1981               20.4                   32.2               29.8&#13;
1982               22.0&#13;
/a  Gross National Savings is defined as Gross National Product +&#13;
net current transfers from the ROW - consumption.    See The&#13;
World Bank Statistical Manual for a more complete definition.&#13;
/b This differs from national savings as shown in National Income&#13;
in Korea; the Korean definition of national savings does not&#13;
include net current transfers from the ROW (See Appendix A).&#13;
/c Japan changed its SNA in 1965.&#13;
Sources: Korea: BOK, National Income in Korea (1982);&#13;
Japan: Economic Planning Agency, Annual Report on&#13;
National Accounts;&#13;
Singapore: Statistical Yearbook (1982).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
III. Savings Hypothesis&#13;
Theories of saving have been frequently surveyed and there is&#13;
little need for an exhaustive listing. We will only touch upon those that&#13;
promise to cast a ray or two on attitudes toward savings and for which the&#13;
necessary data can be mustered.&#13;
Among Keynesian economists the very first rung in a theory of&#13;
savings, is the level of current income. How much a nation might save,&#13;
depends, quite appropriately, on total earnings./5 This formulation is the&#13;
fundamental building block of most aggregate savings functions. But for all&#13;
its considerable explanatory power, the level of income is but one of many&#13;
variables impinging on the decision to save. Hence other candidates must&#13;
also be canvassed. So called, "ratchet" theories of spending have proven to&#13;
be a very fruitful source of ideas./6 They assume that by virtue of habit,&#13;
or out of sense of caution, individuals are slow to increase their consump-&#13;
tion as their incomes grow. Therefore, the more swiftly incomes expand, the&#13;
greater will be the volume of savings in an economy. One very famous variant&#13;
of this notion, identified with Milton Friedman, assumes that by looking at&#13;
the trend in their earnings over the recent past and by making educated&#13;
guesses as to their future incomes, people derive a sum they treat as their&#13;
"permanent income," a much stabler aggregate than their actual earnings./7&#13;
What is spent or saved is determined by reference to their permanent income.&#13;
An unexpected increase in income is treated as transitory and frequently&#13;
saved. A full-blown test of the permanent income hypothesis, requires a&#13;
considerable volume of data. Adding the rate of growth of GNP to the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
estimating equation can, at a pinch, suffice. It is a crude proxy for the&#13;
many sophisticated ideas underlying the "ratchet" theories but an adequate&#13;
one, nonetheless. Another surrogate for permanent income which we also&#13;
tried, was a three-year moving average of current income.&#13;
The rate of growth is not the only way of capturing, empirically,&#13;
the inertia of spending patterns. A second possibility is to take the ratio&#13;
of actual GNP to its three-year moving average (which can be considered as&#13;
an indicator of potential GNP), the assumption being that when this ratio&#13;
exceeds one by a significant margin, the growth of income is likely to be&#13;
well above what most people expect, leading to a rise in savings.&#13;
Decisions to save are guided not only by income but also by the&#13;
stock of assets./8 As people become wealthier, the utility from postponing&#13;
consumption in the current period for the sake of higher consumption in later&#13;
years is likely to diminish, with the result that savings are cut back.&#13;
Individuals might also have a target level of savings, which once achieved&#13;
discourages them from accumulating further. This line of argument points&#13;
toward a negative relationship between savings and wealth. Unfortunately,&#13;
an aggregate assets variable is difficult to construct for the period of&#13;
time being investigated. A rather weak alternative, for use in the household&#13;
savings function, was provided by individual financial assets outstanding at&#13;
the end of each year, obtained from the flow of funds tables. While we&#13;
realize that this does not do justice to the hypothesis, the alternative was&#13;
to proceed with the chores of model building, ignoring wealth altogether.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
For years, a spirited debate has swirled around the effects of&#13;
inflation on savings./9 At one level, there is the pure theorist who cannot&#13;
understand why the rate of increase in prices should influence the trade-off&#13;
between current and future consumption. From his perspective, savings&#13;
behavior remains unaltered although the composition of savings might change.&#13;
More empirically minded practitioners argue, however, that inflation by&#13;
disturbing relative prices, increasing uncertainty about employment and&#13;
income in the future, and in particular, reducing the value of financial&#13;
assets, could lead to a spurt in savings, especially where financial assets&#13;
occupy a large share in total household wealth./10 Savings would also rise,&#13;
following an unanticipated surge in inflation, if individuals respond to the&#13;
increasing costliness of certain items by cutting purchases, without taking&#13;
account of the actual or anticipated growth of their own incomes./ll Also,&#13;
monetary policies which lead to accelerating inflation can result in a trans-&#13;
fer of resources from moneyholders to the state, thereby raising government&#13;
savings./12 On the other hand, under conditions of persistent inflation,&#13;
people expecting goods to grow ever costlier, might advance their purchases,&#13;
by eating into their savings. They may also restructure their asset&#13;
portfolios, with housing and real estate edging out financial holdings.&#13;
Since prices of such items often increase more than proportionately during&#13;
inflationary times, the wealth effect can serve to depress new savings.&#13;
Finally, periods of high inflation, by redistributing income to those with&#13;
greater saving propensities, because of the lag in wages behind prices and&#13;
the transfers between creditors and debtors, can be accompanied by a growth&#13;
in accumulation.&#13;
Thus, there is some ambiguity in the relationship on the theor-&#13;
etical plane which is echoed by the diversity of the empirical results.&#13;
Alongside research, which was unable to discern any significant relationship,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
there are papers claiming a positive association, while still others conclude&#13;
that in fact, inflation lowers saving propensities. Since Korea has&#13;
experienced a high rate of inflation for nearly three decades, it seemed&#13;
appropriate to include the annual change in inflation as an explanatory&#13;
variable in our model.&#13;
There is widespread faith among economists that the real interest&#13;
rate should affect saving decisions by altering the trade-off between present&#13;
and future consumption. But uncovering empirical traces of a rational&#13;
response on the part of savers to changes in interest rates, has turned out&#13;
to be maddeningly difficult. On occasion, by selectively excluding certain&#13;
other variables that might mask the effects of interest rates, some assiduous&#13;
researcher will discover a positive relationship, but by and large it has&#13;
been hard going for the true believers. Thanks to the efforts of Edward&#13;
Shaw and Ronald McKinnon,/13 the importance of interest rates for Korean&#13;
savings has received much attention and a measure of econometric support,&#13;
although the strength of their findings has not been convincingly reaffirmed&#13;
by subsequent research./14 Another attempt at verification seemed long&#13;
overdue. Hence, we incorporated interest rates into our model.&#13;
Foreign savings offered us another opportunity of adding to our&#13;
theoretical menu, but the link between foreign and national saving lacks&#13;
conceptual foundations, being built largely on ad hoc rationalizations which,&#13;
on occasion, have been sustained by tests. It is thought that the avail-&#13;
ability of foreign capital flows discourages government from strenously&#13;
promoting domestic resource mobilization and can displace private&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
savings./15 For these reasons and because Korea has attracted large flows&#13;
of capital over the past thirty years, it seemed worthwhile determining&#13;
whether the hypothesized negative association was sustained in the Korean&#13;
case.&#13;
Lastly, since we are dealing with an economy which has plumbed the&#13;
secrets of export-led growth, we attempted to test the validity of one&#13;
additional view. It has been proposed by Maizels, Lee, Laumas, Papanek and&#13;
others /16, that rapidly expanding exports can raise savings, because of a&#13;
higher propensity to save in the export sector; the importance of export&#13;
taxes for government revenues; the positive influence the tradeable goods&#13;
sector can exert on marginal saving propensities in other sectors that&#13;
benefit as a result of linkages; and the indirect effects arising from a more&#13;
efficient allocation of resources. Although export taxes have never been a&#13;
large source of government revenue in Korea, we reasoned that custom duties&#13;
on imports are far from negligible /17 and as export growth is directly&#13;
associated with changes in imports, it was a variable meriting inclusion in&#13;
our tests. Our attempt at explaining the behavior of savings in Korea&#13;
encompassed the eight variables listed above.&#13;
IV. Data&#13;
Savings behavior can be examined at several levels. Gross National&#13;
Savings (GNS) represent the highest level of aggregation, including public and&#13;
private savings, depreciation, net current transfers from the ROW and net&#13;
factor income from the rest of the world (ROW). By excluding net current&#13;
transfers and net factor income, one is left with Gross Domestic Savings&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
(GDS). GDS provides the best estimate of the domestic savings effort in&#13;
Korea, as GNS is dominated by net current transfers from the ROW in the&#13;
1950s and 1960s. Furthermore, in the early eighties, GNS was several&#13;
precentage points below GDS because of the large factor payments needed to&#13;
service Korea's debt obligation (Table 2). As these transfers must be&#13;
financed from domestic savings; excluding them would result in an under-&#13;
estimate of domestic resource mobilization. For this reason, the emphasis&#13;
of our projections has been on GDS rather than GNS, although both were used&#13;
in our estimating equations. Savings can be further disaggregated into&#13;
three categories: government, households, and corporations. Finally, it is&#13;
possible to estimate household savings, independently by netting out&#13;
agriculture stocks, a large and variable item.&#13;
The National Income in Korea (1982) published by the Bank of Korea&#13;
(BOK) provides annual time series on the national accounts for the period&#13;
1953-82. It includes data based on Korean definitions for national, house-&#13;
hold, government, and corporate savings, but we have conformed to the stand-&#13;
ard World Bank definitions for those items (see Appendix A, for a complete&#13;
description of the savings data published by the Korean authorities and the&#13;
World Bank definitions of savings). We also found it necessary to limit our&#13;
econometric tests to the period 1965-82 as there was an apparent shift&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
in savings patterns after the mid-60s which made it risky to use the&#13;
statistics for the first ten years. To determine whether this shift&#13;
represented a structural change in savings behavior, we used the Chow Test&#13;
to compare the period, 1953-65, with the period, 1965-82. Since the null&#13;
hypothesis of no structural change in the parameters could not be sustained,&#13;
all regressions were limited to the period, 1965-82./18&#13;
The question of whether or not to include the annual change in&#13;
agricultural stocks, a volatile and climate related item, in the savings&#13;
statistics also had to be settled empirically. There can be little&#13;
conceptual disagreement with treating grain inventories as a form of saving,&#13;
but they could introduce noise into the statistics, obscuring the influence&#13;
of the independent variables being used. After estimating various domestic&#13;
and household savings functions with and without agricultural stocks, it&#13;
became clear that including inventories improved the fit and imparted&#13;
stability to the coefficients.&#13;
To derive savings in real terms, we have followed the World Bank&#13;
Statistical Manual: real GDS equals gross domestic income /19 minus&#13;
consumption; and, real GNS equals GDS plus net current transfers and net&#13;
factor income. This procedure yields a more suitable measure of real income&#13;
than the more conventional approach where savings in current prices are&#13;
deflated by the GDP deflator. This can be justified when one considers the&#13;
changes in relative prices following the first and second oil shocks.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
To convert other nominal amounts into real magnitudes, it was&#13;
necessary to choose from the GDP deflator, the Consumer Price Index (CPI)&#13;
and the Wholesale Price Index (WPI). Since the latter is dominated by&#13;
tradeables and intermediate products, we excluded it in the first round.&#13;
After considering the weighting scheme used for the CPI and taking into&#13;
account both the small share of housing and the significant share of food&#13;
and other items whose prices are regulated by the Government, we elected to&#13;
use the GDP deflator. While its broad coverage has certain drawbacks, the&#13;
GDP deflator does adequately reflect movements in the prices of services,&#13;
whose share of the national product is large and growing. However, these&#13;
deflators do tend to undervalue savings from a developmental perspective.&#13;
As shown in Table 4, the fixed investment deflator rose more slowly than the&#13;
GDP deflator from 1975 onwards. Thus, a given volume of real savings&#13;
arrived at by using the GDP deflator would support a larger amount of fixed&#13;
investment as measured by the cost of accumulating capital goods. On&#13;
balance, however, it seemed more appropriate to stay with the GDP deflator,&#13;
since from 1965 to 1975, the rate of change of the two indexes is nearly&#13;
identical.&#13;
By the standards of most developing countries, Korean economic&#13;
data are both abundant and of relatively high quality. As mentioned above,&#13;
the national account statistics were obtained from the National Income in&#13;
Korea (1982). The Economic Statistics Yearbook (1982) was the source of the&#13;
time series on deposit rates, while for exports and the CPI we relied on the&#13;
International Finance Statistics (IFS) issued by the IMF. All the&#13;
regressions were run using ordinary least squares (OLS) unless auto-&#13;
correlation necessitated a recourse to Generalized Least Squares (GLS).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
Table 4: GROSS DOMESTIC PRODUCT AND FIXED INVESTMENT DEFLATORS&#13;
GDP deflator                 Fixed investment deflator&#13;
Index            Rate of             Index            Rate of&#13;
(1975             change             (1975             change&#13;
= 100)             (%)               = 100)             (%)&#13;
1960                8.63             11.2               10.90              2.9&#13;
1961                9.77             13.2               13.61             24.8&#13;
1962               11.57             18.4               15.00             10.2&#13;
1963               15.02             29.9               16.48              9.9&#13;
1964               19.50             29.8               21.70             31.7&#13;
1965               20.70              6.1               24.99             15.1&#13;
1966               23.67             14.3               27.61             10.5&#13;
1967               27.49             16.2               29.47              6.7&#13;
1968               31.96             16.2               32.31              9.6&#13;
1969               36.69             14.8               34.79              7.7&#13;
1970               42.32             15.3               40.55             16.6&#13;
1971               47.45             12.1               42.98              6.0&#13;
1972               54.82             15.5               48.30             12.4&#13;
1973               62.03             13.1               57.88             19.8&#13;
1974               80.36             29.5               80.39             38.9&#13;
1975              100.00             24.4              100.00             24.4&#13;
1976              117.86             17.9              108.01              8.0&#13;
1977              137.29             16.5              119.63             10.8&#13;
1978              165.87             20.8              136.30             13.9&#13;
1979              197.43             19.0              167.30             22.7&#13;
1980              246.69             25.0              225.87             35.0&#13;
1981              286.16             16.0              258.59             14.5&#13;
1982              309.20              8.1              270.58              4.6&#13;
Annual rate (1960-82)               17.7%                                15.7%&#13;
Source:  National Income in Korea, Bank of Korea (1982).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
Estimation Results&#13;
We began by modelling real gross national savings behavior in&#13;
logarithmic form over the period 1965-81. - Various "theories" of savings&#13;
behavior were tried by varying the definition of the income variable:&#13;
a Keynesian model with savings as a function of current income; a simple&#13;
permanent income hypothesis with savings as a function of permanent income&#13;
(measured by a 3-year moving average of current income); and, a "ratchet"&#13;
model with savings as a function of the ratio of current income to a three-&#13;
year average of current income. This latter definition did not perform well&#13;
in any of our equations and was excluded from subsequent tests. All nine&#13;
variables - income (current and permanent), the growth rate, the inflation&#13;
rate, financial assets (as a proxy for wealth), the real time deposit rate,&#13;
the level of exports, and the amount of foreign savings - were included in our&#13;
initial regression. The level of exports and the income variable were highly&#13;
correlated and hence, we eliminated the export variable to avoid problems with&#13;
multicollinearity. Financial assets was also discarded as it was insignifi-&#13;
cant. To capture the unusual circumstances created by the second oil shock&#13;
and Korea's first serious recession in two decades, we experimented with a&#13;
dummy for the period 1980-81. The results are shown in Table 5; all equations&#13;
have been corrected for first-order serial correlation.&#13;
The level of Gross National Income (GNY), and our measure of per-&#13;
manent income are highly significant, in all equations. Current income&#13;
(GNY) performs slightly better than our measure of "permanent" income,&#13;
especially in terms of the standard error of the regression. Foreign&#13;
savings, which is estimated as a semi-elasticity because of negative values&#13;
during the sample period, has a negative coefficient as expected, but it is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 5: GROSS NATIONAL SAVINGS: 1965-1981&#13;
(Logarithmic Estimates)&#13;
Income&#13;
Average   GNY     Infla-  Real TD  Foreign    Dummy              -2&#13;
GNY       GNY    growth  tion       rate   savings   80/81    Constant   R     SER     DW    rho&#13;
(3 yr)&#13;
1.    1.576             0.974    1.092   1.082   -.521E-3            -7.04    0.975   0.065  1.75  0.494&#13;
(18.31)            (3.09)  (1.87)   (2.50)   (0.92)              (9.36)&#13;
2.              1.595   1.604    1.444   1.419   -.408E-5            -7.37    0.969   0.087  1.68  0.329&#13;
(15.25)   (3.84)  (1.85)  (2.54)   (0.01)              (8.29)&#13;
3.     1.537            1.051    1.284   1.188                       -6.75    0.976   0.065  1.64  0.486&#13;
(20.85)            (3.49)  (2.36)   (2.86)                      (10.04)&#13;
4.              1.601   1.578    1.640   1.644                       -7.46    0.972   0.083  1.68  0.331&#13;
(18.44)  (4.41)   (2.41)  (3.02)                       (9.27)&#13;
5.     1.570            0.849    1.189   1.209             -0.081    -7.01    0.976   0.065  1.72  0.482&#13;
(19.65)            (2.38)  (2.17)   (2.92)             (1.04)    (9.84)&#13;
6.              1.639   1.339    1.306   1.445              -0.117   -7.70    0.968   0.082  1.75  0.400&#13;
(16.38)   (3.01)  (1.86)  (2.75)              (1.19)   (8.58)&#13;
Abbreviations:&#13;
GNY = Gross National Income&#13;
TD = Time Deposit&#13;
SER = Standard Error of Regression&#13;
DW = Durbin-Watson statistic&#13;
rho = coefficient for first order autocorrelation correction&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
not significant (see equations 1 and 2). The dummy for 1980-81 is also&#13;
insignificant, indicating no structural changes during the 1980-81 recession&#13;
(see equations 5 and 6). Therefore, the best equations include an income&#13;
variable, the growth rate of income, the rate of inflation and the real time&#13;
deposit rate (see equations 3 and 4).&#13;
The importance of the income growth variable is heartening because&#13;
it lends support to the ratchet theories that have been applied with&#13;
considerable success to data drawn from the advanced industrial nations.&#13;
Even though a positive relationship between inflation and savings was a&#13;
possibility the size and significance of the coefficients was nevertheless&#13;
surprising. They confirmed the importance of the Government's occasional&#13;
reliance on the inflation tax to increase the flow of resources into invest-&#13;
ment and the tendency of individuals holding large savings deposits to over&#13;
compensate for the erosion of real /20 balances when inflation accelerates.&#13;
In addition, the real time deposit rate is significant in all equations,&#13;
signifying the importance of the real rate of return to savings behavior./21&#13;
The relationship between GNS, and the two primary dependent valuables, current&#13;
income and the real time deposit rate are shown graphically in Figure 3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-23-&#13;
FIGURE 3: SAVINGS, INCOME AND INTEREST RATES&#13;
e'0ssT&#13;
GROSS NATIONAL SAVINGS&#13;
B 4,990                                               //&#13;
I&#13;
N&#13;
N/&#13;
1965    1967    198es   1871   1973    1976    1977    1979    1981&#13;
20-                                                                    -18,0880&#13;
15-                       -     REAL TIME DEPOSIT RATE  - -&#13;
---- GROSS NATIONAL INCOME           . ' '- 15 ,0&#13;
-le_;"                                                                   .e&#13;
p                                                       ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~12, 999 &#13;
E  S- ~ ~ ~    ~     ~    ~    ~     &#13;
-15-    |                                                                3,000&#13;
108e    1967    1969    1971    1973   1975    1977    1979    1961&#13;
SOURCE  BANK OF KOREA, THE NATIONAL INCOME IN KOREA C1982)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
Table 6: GROSS NATIONAL SAVINGS: 1965-1982&#13;
(Logarithmic estimates)&#13;
GNY                 Real   Foreign   Dummy&#13;
GNY   growth   Inflation  TD rate  savings   1980-82  Constant   R2    SER      DW      rho&#13;
7     1.584   0.933     0.907      1.104   0.265E-3            -7.10   0.980   0.066    1.75   0.395&#13;
(19.52)  (2.87)    (1.60)     (2.59)  (0.53)              (9.99)&#13;
8     1.590    0.814    0.930      1.166             -0.066    -7.14   0.980    0.065   1.76   0.406&#13;
(21.39)  (2.25)    (1.89)     (2.87)            (0.87)   (10.65)&#13;
9     1.559    1.001    1.071      1.157                       -6.91   0.981    0.064   1.75   0.405&#13;
(24.11)  (3.44)    (2.33)     (2.88)                     (11.34)&#13;
Table 7: GROSS DOMESTIC SAVINGS: 1965-1982&#13;
(Logarithmic estimates)&#13;
GDY                 Real   Foreign   Dummy&#13;
GDY   growth   Inflation  TD rate  savings   1980-82  Constant   R2     SER     DW     rho&#13;
10    1.887    1.504    1.162      0.450   0.26E-3            -10.46   0.99    0.063    1.75  -0.604&#13;
(41.04)  (3.95)    (2.41)     (1.72)  (0.72)             (18.11)&#13;
11    1.875    1.618    1.315      0.487             -0.019    -9.98   0.99     0.064   1.85  -0.548&#13;
(92.56)  (4.02)    (2.73)     (1.80)            (0.31)   (24.43)&#13;
12   1.869     1.712    1.416      0.503                       -9.95   0.99     0.061   1.87   0.515&#13;
(50.59)  (6.87)    (3.80)     (1.90)                     (27.31)&#13;
Abbreviations:&#13;
GDY = Gross Domestic Income&#13;
GNY = Gross National Income&#13;
GD  = Time Deposit&#13;
SER = Standard error of Regression&#13;
DW  = Durbin-Watson Statistic&#13;
rho = coefficient for first-order autocorrelation correction&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
Because of our definition of permanent income, a three-year&#13;
moving average centered at year t, we were unable to regress it over the&#13;
longer period, 1965-82. The results over this time period for our best&#13;
equations, using current income, are shown in Table 6. Comparing equation 3&#13;
(1965-81, Table 5) and equation 8 (Table 6), the coefficients are unchanged&#13;
even with the introduction of another year; this is important when one&#13;
considers that savings only recovers from the 1980 recession in 1982.&#13;
We next turned to Gross Domestic Savings (GDS) which excludes&#13;
net current transfers and net factor income from the rest of the world.&#13;
As previously indicated, GDS is a more accurate measure of the domestic&#13;
savings effort, since, the large interest payments due on Korea's foreign&#13;
debt calls for an effort at resource mobilization appreciably in excess&#13;
of investment needs. It also provides us with a useful check on the tests&#13;
conducted with GNS; all the independent variables identified above, except for&#13;
exports, were used to explain the movements in GDS (see Table 7). The level&#13;
of GDY, the real TD rate, the rate of inflation, and the growth rate are&#13;
significant (see equations 10, 11 and 12); the level of foreign savings has&#13;
the correct sign, but is not significantly different from zero (see equation&#13;
10). The results of these regressions are similar to the ones that we&#13;
obtained from GNS although the elasticities - with the exception of the&#13;
interest elasticity - are slightly higher.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
VI. Future Implications&#13;
Having established the responsiveness of savings in Korea to a&#13;
set of variables with respectable theoretical credentials and isolated&#13;
a couple of equations with a good "fit", we thought it useful to try and&#13;
predict the course of domestic resource mobilization in the Korean&#13;
economy during the remainder of the Fifth FYP period. Table 8 shows the&#13;
elasticities of the independent variables with respect to both GNS and GDS.&#13;
Table 8: HISTORICAL SAVINGS ELASTICITIES: 1965-1982&#13;
GNS                       GDS&#13;
(Eqn 9)                  (Eqn 12)&#13;
Current income               1.56                      1.87&#13;
Growth                       1.00                      1.71&#13;
Inflation                    1.07                      1.42&#13;
Real TD rate                 1.16                      0.50&#13;
In projecting future rates of saving for the period 1983-86, we&#13;
assumed that: the economy will maintain a growth rate of 8%; the government&#13;
will continue to be successful in controlling inflation; and, it will not&#13;
depart from the policy of posting positive real interest rates. These&#13;
assumptions are reflected in the base scenario, shown as Table 9.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
Table 9: BASE SCENARIO&#13;
1983         1984        1985         1986&#13;
GDP growth                  8%            8%         8%          8%&#13;
Terms of trade index        99.2          100.1      99.6        99.0&#13;
Real time deposit rate      4%            4%         4%          4%&#13;
Inflation rate              4%            5%         6%          6%&#13;
Simulation of equation 12 for the 1983-86 period yields an annual growth&#13;
rate of savings of 12-13%. This is 4-5% higher than our projected GDP&#13;
growth and implies about a 1.5% increase in the average savings rate for the&#13;
remainder of the Fifth FYP.&#13;
Evaluating the Projections&#13;
Although with equation 12, we are able to track the actual savings&#13;
pattern very closely throughout the sample period, the projected savings&#13;
through 1986 must still be treated with a measure of caution for econometric&#13;
as well as conceptual reasons. On the econometric front, there is the&#13;
concern arising out of our reliance on single equation estimates. As Leff&#13;
and Sato have pointed out,/22 savings and investment are determined&#13;
simultaneously and estimating savings with a single equation approach risks&#13;
introducing simultanity bias into the parameter estimates. Further, we&#13;
cannot claim conclusively to have identified a savings function. Our&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
structural parameters might just possibly be capturing an investment&#13;
relationship or an amalgam of savings and investment. Our hunch is that the&#13;
latter is the more serious of the two.&#13;
At the conceptual level, the performance of several variables&#13;
tested was noteworthy. It is hardly suprising to find that the income&#13;
level plays such a prominent role; our preference for current income&#13;
over "permanent" income stems from only a slightly better peformance by the&#13;
former over the latter. Given the rate at which Korea's GNP has risen over&#13;
the past two decades, the significance of the economy's rate of growth was&#13;
expected. Of greater interest was the clear association between savings and&#13;
the real rate of interest. But the low elasticity (.5) with respect to GDS&#13;
suggests that the benefits for resource mobilization of higher real interest&#13;
rates will be outweighed by their negative effect on investment.&#13;
Since we assume that the real time deposit rate will change no&#13;
more than a percent or two in the next three years and inflation will&#13;
decline, these variables, will contribute little to the savings rate.&#13;
Almost all the growth arises from the rising level of income. As a&#13;
consequence, we see savings climb back to the ratios prevailing in the late&#13;
1970s, the difference between the high growth scenario (8.0%) shown in the&#13;
previous section and a low growth scenario (6.5%) being probably less than 1%.&#13;
The figure of 28-29% would seem to be very much an upper bound, but how far it&#13;
has to be shaved in order to arrive at a true point estimate, calls for very&#13;
finely balanced judgment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
What other factors might impinge upon the savings propensities of&#13;
households and the Government? For the period 1970-81 the marginal propen-&#13;
sity to save (MPS) from household disposable income was 20% which is very&#13;
close to that prevailing in Japan during 1972-79. Compared with marginal&#13;
propensities in other countries, developed or developing, these rates are&#13;
quite high. For Korean savings to increase yet more would call for changes&#13;
in: (a) the age structure of the population and in family ties that&#13;
fundamentally alter post-retirement expectations; (b) the scale of expenditure&#13;
on consumer durables and the mode of financing; (c) the variance of bonus&#13;
payments to wage earners;/23 and (d) the demand for education and the outlays&#13;
involved. However, no major changes in age structure and family ties are in&#13;
the offing over the coming four years. Since consumer financing is rather&#13;
scarce, an easing of supply would if anything reduce the need for households&#13;
to save in anticipation of a purchase. Thus the likely growth in the demand&#13;
for household goods and cars might be balanced by the emergence of new&#13;
financial arrangements. Somewhat in contrast to Japan, bonus payments to&#13;
workers in Korea have tended to vary little from one year to the next and&#13;
probably have affected household savings only minimally. With the Korean&#13;
economy becoming more susceptible to the international business cycles this&#13;
might change, but even if bonuses do start to fluctuate there is no saying&#13;
whether workers will treat them as transitory income and deposit them in&#13;
savings accounts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
Government savings rose in the late 60s as a result of improved&#13;
fiscal policies and the introduction of new tax laws. While they have&#13;
occasionally climbed above 6%, the experience of the past decade suggests&#13;
that 6-6.5% may be the upper limit, given the "tax effort" the Government is&#13;
prepared to make. No doubt, the plans to improve the efficiency of public&#13;
sector bodies will lower administrative expenses but at the same time&#13;
current revenues will expand more slowly for two reasons. First the much&#13;
lower rate of inflation that has been forecast for the period 1983-86 will&#13;
dampen the States' income from direct taxes. Second, the "supply side"&#13;
policies adopted by the Regime has led to a lowering of tax rates, whose&#13;
effects will begin to be felt from 1984 onwards. Improvements in collection&#13;
will provide a partial offset, but nevertheless, the trend in revenues is&#13;
not strongly upwards, and with Assembly elections scheduled for 1986, a tax&#13;
increase in 1985 would appear unlikely.&#13;
Some preliminary projections that we obtained from revenue and&#13;
expenditure functions indicate that government savings should average 5.0%&#13;
between 1983-86. However, this does not include the savings which will&#13;
accrue, in the short-term, from the policy of absorbing a part of the fall in&#13;
oil prices through import duties and taxes; from improved tax administration;&#13;
and, from the removal of a variety of tax loopholes. Possibly as much as 0.3%&#13;
of GNP could be added to government savings by way of the energy stabilization&#13;
fund over the next two years. Even after making these assumptions we can&#13;
still only project government savings in the region of 7%.&#13;
What other changes might have a bearing on savings propensities?&#13;
Only two factors come to mind. One is the continuing migration of people to&#13;
the urban areas./24 A decrease in inflation is a second. Both will have a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
negative influence on aggregate household savings, although a minor one.&#13;
Since farmers whose incomes are more variable than those of wage earners in&#13;
the cities, save more, a fall in their number will work its way into the&#13;
savings rate. With the redistributive effects of inflation much less marked,&#13;
profit earners and rentiers, with high saving propensities, may find their&#13;
share of the national income, stabilizing if not falling, with some modest&#13;
consequences for domestic savings.&#13;
Taking all these into account, there is scant reason to expect&#13;
national savings to exceed 28% even in the event of a strong and sustained&#13;
upswing in business activity. Matched against the investment ratio of 31%&#13;
contained in the FYP, this would presuppose an unacceptably high level of&#13;
foreign borrowing, since a portion of the GDS will be diverted to finance the&#13;
high level of interest costs on foreign debt. But the Fifth Plan projections&#13;
are based on an incremental capital-output ratio (ICOR) which assumes a&#13;
pattern of infrastructural investment which is unlikely to prevail given the&#13;
recent changes in the Government's program. If the expansion of the&#13;
manufacturing sector resumes with the anticipated upswing in international&#13;
business activity, a growth rate of 7.5-8.5% could conceivably be attained&#13;
with investment averaging between 29-30%. Should the manufacturing sector&#13;
fail to recover its leading role in the economy, and growth continue to rest&#13;
upon the expansion of social-overhead capital and services, the expected&#13;
increase in savings coupled with the international borrowing circumstances&#13;
will limit Korea's growth rate to about 7.0%.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Appendix A: SAVINGS AS DEFINED IN THE KOREAN&#13;
NATIONAL ACCOUNTS AND THE WORLD BANK&#13;
STATISTICAL MANUAL&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Appendix A&#13;
-35-&#13;
The manner in which Korean aggregate savings data -- both national&#13;
and foreign -- are constructed differs from the standard Bank definitions&#13;
for these variables, as outlined in the World Bank Statistical Manual Note&#13;
6.20. The purpose of this Appendix is: (i) to explain the difference between&#13;
the Korean definition of savings and the Bank's operating definitions; and&#13;
(ii) to establish a crosswalk between the two definitions for analytical&#13;
purposes.&#13;
For operational purposes, three definitions are employed by the&#13;
World Bank for Gross Domestic Savings (GDS) and Gross National Savings (GNS).&#13;
Conceptually, these definitions do not differ; however, in practice,&#13;
variations in the level of savings can arise as a result of a country's&#13;
accounting practices. The three definitions are presented in: (i) the&#13;
Operational Manual; (ii) the CPP/UN SNA system; and (iii) the World Tables&#13;
(see Appendix Table 1).&#13;
Table 1: GROSS NATIONAL SAVINGS (GNS)/GROSS DOMESTIC SAVNGS (GDS)&#13;
(in current prices)&#13;
Operational Manual          CPP/UN SNA               World tables&#13;
GNS = GDI + CAB          GNS = GDP - C + NFI + NCT    GNS = GDI + net exports&#13;
of all goods and services&#13;
+ NCT&#13;
GDS = GNS -NFI - NCT     GDS = GNS - NFI -NCT&#13;
where; GDI:   Gross Domestic Investment&#13;
CAB: Current Account Balance&#13;
C:    Consumption&#13;
GDP: Gross Domestic Product&#13;
GDY: Gross Domestic Income&#13;
NFI: Net Factor Income&#13;
NCT: Net Current Transfer&#13;
Source: World Bank Statistical Manual&#13;
Note: 6.20, p. 3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Appendix A&#13;
-36-&#13;
From the definitions in Appendix Table 1 and the data contained in&#13;
the National Income in Korea (NIK) published by the BOK, one can easily&#13;
construct GNS and GDS in current prices for Korea using any one of these&#13;
methods. Appendix Table 2 shows these data for the period 1977-81. For&#13;
GNS, the Operational Manual and the World Tables produce an identical level of&#13;
savings, whereas the CPP/UN SNA method produces a different result. This&#13;
difference arises from the treatment of the statistical discrepancy; since&#13;
the Korean national accounts are constructed by industrial origin, the expen-&#13;
diture side of the accounts contain a statistical discrepancy. The CPP/UN&#13;
SNA method uses GDP minus consumption and the statistical discrepancy is&#13;
included in savings. In the other two methods, savings is calculated directly&#13;
from the expenditure components of GDP and therefore, does not include the&#13;
statistical discrepancy. As GDS equals GNS minus NCT and NFI, in each of the&#13;
three methods the same difference shows up there as well.&#13;
In the Korean presentation of savings, they are divided into two&#13;
categories -- National Savings and Foreign Savings. Appendix Table 3 shows&#13;
the standard Korean presentation of these savings data. NCT are considered to&#13;
be part of Foreign Savings and therefore are not included in National Savings;&#13;
the statistical discrepancy is included in savings. Thus at the aggregate&#13;
level, National Savings, as defined by the BOK, and GNS, as defined by the&#13;
Bank, differ in two respects:&#13;
(a) the treatment of NCT (the only divergence between the CPP/UN SNA&#13;
method and the Korean definition); and,&#13;
(b) the treament of the statistical discrepancy (since the Operational&#13;
Manual and the World Tables do not include it).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-37-                         Appendix A&#13;
The National Savings data, that are shown in Appendix Table 3,&#13;
are derived from more disaggregated data at this household, corporate,&#13;
and government level. Appendix Table 4 shows this detailed data. The&#13;
savings data for households and private non-profit institutions are the&#13;
difference between current receipts, including transfers from the ROW,&#13;
and current expenditures, including transfers to the ROW (see lines 1 and&#13;
2, Appendix Table 4). Corporate savings for public and private enterprises,&#13;
as shown in the distribution of national income (see line 3, Appendix Table&#13;
3), plus the depreciation of unincorporated enterprises, and public and&#13;
private enterprises (see line 4, Appendix Table 4) together constitute&#13;
corporate savings. Private savings is the sum of corporate and household&#13;
savings. Government savings, derived by subtracting current expenditure,&#13;
excluding transfers to the ROW, from current revenue, excluding transfers&#13;
from the ROW, when added to the depreciation of general government and&#13;
government enterprises' equals the savings of the public sector. National&#13;
savings, as defined by the BOK, is the sum of Private savings and Government&#13;
savings.&#13;
In the main body of this paper, we have used the CPP/UN SNA&#13;
definition of savings, since it only differs from the Korean concept of&#13;
national savings in the classification of NCT. In addition, our definition of&#13;
Foreign Savings is "net borrowings from the ROW" (or Foreign Savings as&#13;
defined by the BOK minus NCT). By adhering to the CPP/UN SNA definition of&#13;
savings in converting nominal savings into real savings, we have adjusted&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Appendix&#13;
-38-                           Table 2&#13;
KOREA&#13;
GROSS NATIONAL SAVINGS AND GROSS DOMESTIC SAVINGS.   1977-1981&#13;
(in billion won)&#13;
1977      1978         1979      1980      1981&#13;
Consumption                 12,743.05  16,873.25  21,343.64  27,489.39   34,085.41&#13;
Private consumption       10,754.44  14,238.73  18,106.47  23,042.61   28,532.89&#13;
Government consumption     1,988.61   2,634.52   3,237.17    4,446.78   5,552.52&#13;
Gross domestic investment    4,644.95   7,137.74  10,293.50   10,812.68  12,030.40&#13;
Fixed capital formation    4,420.88   7,023.07   9,458.18   11,240.03  12,087.17&#13;
Increase in stocks           224.07     114.67     835.32    -427.35      -56.77&#13;
Exports of goods &amp; svcs.     5,966.79   7,714.77   8,808.61   12,945.15  17,543.58&#13;
Imports of goods &amp; svcs.     5,967.43   8,355.58  10,745.28   15,385.90  19,326.73&#13;
Statistical discrepancy       -264.70    -339.85    -343.41    -480.82     -358.46&#13;
Gross domestic product      17,122.66  23,030.33  29,357.06   35,380.50  43,974.20&#13;
Net factor income             -101.29    -112.73    -284.98   -1,058.95  -1,577.08&#13;
Gross national product      17,021.37  22,917.60  29,072.08   34,321.55  42,397.12&#13;
Memo items:&#13;
Current account balance        5.96    -525.29  -2,009.18  -3,224.32   -3,018.38&#13;
Net current transfers        107.89     228.25     212.47      275.38     341.85&#13;
Gross national savings&#13;
Operational manual         4,650.91   6,612.45   8,284.32    7,588.36   9,012.02&#13;
CPP/UN SNA                 4,386.21   6,272.60   7,940.91    7,107.54   8,653.56&#13;
World tables               4,650.91   6,612.45   8,284.32    7,588.36   9,012.07&#13;
Gross domestic savings&#13;
Operational manual         4,644.31   6,496.93   8,356.83    8,371.93  10,247.25&#13;
CPP/UN SNA                 4,379.61   6,157.08   8,013.42    7,891.11   9,888.79&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Appendix A&#13;
-39-&#13;
GDP by the income terms of trade, yielding Gross Domestic Income (GDY)./25&#13;
Real GNS equals GDY minus real consumption;/26 this definition of real&#13;
savings was used for the econometric work in the later section of the paper.&#13;
Consequently, we used GDY as our measure of income rather than GDP.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Appendix&#13;
Table 3&#13;
-40-&#13;
KOREA&#13;
NATIONAL SAVINGS AND FOREIGN SAVINGS&#13;
(in billion won)&#13;
1977       1978      1979         1980     1981&#13;
National Savings     4,278.32   6,044.35   7,728.44   6,832.16    8,311.71&#13;
Private            3,323.84   4,563.12   5,623.69   4,710.32    5,475.01&#13;
Government           954.48   1,481.23   2,104.75   2,121.84    2,836.70&#13;
Foreign Savings        101.93     753.54   2,221.65   3,499.70    3,360.23&#13;
NCT                  107.89     228.25     212.47      275.38     341.85&#13;
Net borrowings&#13;
from ROW           -5.96      525.29   2,009.18   3,224.32    3,018.38&#13;
Memo Items&#13;
GDI               4,644.95    7,137.74  10,293.50   10,812.68  12,030.40&#13;
Statistical&#13;
discrepancy    -264.70      -339.85     -343.41    -480.82     -358.46&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Appendix&#13;
-41-                             Table 4&#13;
KOREA&#13;
NATIONAL SAVINGS: SECTORAL BREAKDOWN&#13;
(in billion won)&#13;
1977       1978         1979       1980      1981&#13;
1. Household &amp; private non-&#13;
-profit institutions/a       1,553.73  2,509.44     3,001.11    2,130.89    2,258.27&#13;
2. (of which NCT) /a               (82.53)   (210.20)     (192.87)    (244.98)    (287.53)&#13;
3. Corporate savings /b             548.26    709.18       772.31       33.39       40.63&#13;
4. Depreciation (unincorporated&#13;
enter., private &amp; public&#13;
corporations) /c             1,304.38   1,554.70     2,043.14   2,791.02    3,463.64&#13;
5. Govenment savings/d              901.40   1,404.05     1,997.51   2,001.97    2,693.52&#13;
6. (of which NCT) /c                (25.36)     (18.05)     (19.60)    (30.40)     (54.32)&#13;
7. Depreciation: Govt. enter-&#13;
prices/c                        49.37      57.88        79.96     113.31       99.72&#13;
8. General government /c             29.07      37.35        46.88      36.96       97.78&#13;
Memo Items:&#13;
9. Private savings (1+3+4-2).     3,323.84   4,563.12     5,623.69   4,710.32    5,475.01&#13;
10. Govt. savings (5+7-6)            954.48   1,481.23     2,104.75   2,121.84    2,836.70&#13;
11. National savings (9+10)        4,278.32   6,044.35     7,728.44   6,832.16    8,311.71&#13;
12. NCT (2+4)                        107.89     228.25       212.47     275.38      341.85&#13;
13. GNS (11+12)                    4,386.21   6,272.60     7,940.91   7,107.54    8,653.56&#13;
/a  "Current receipts and expenditures of households and private non-profit institutions,"&#13;
National Income in Korea (NIK), (1982) p. 205.&#13;
/b "Distribution of National Income," NIK, (1982) p. 173.&#13;
7T Line items: Provisions for the consumption of fixed capital. "The Finance&#13;
of Gross Domestic Capital Formation," NIK (1982), p. 177.&#13;
/d "General Government Revenue and Expenditure," NIK, p. 209.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-42-&#13;
Footnotes&#13;
1.        The most recent comprehensive survey was the following: Mikesell, R.&#13;
and Zinser, J., "The Nature of the Savings Function in Developing Countries:&#13;
A Survey of the Theoretical and Empirical Literature," Journal of Economic&#13;
Literature, March 1973. A search through the literature on savings in&#13;
developing countries that has accumulated during the past five years&#13;
suggests both a marked easing in the flow of papers and the absence of major&#13;
new developments.&#13;
On Korea, only a handful of papers can be found. See Kim, Mahn Je&#13;
&amp; Park, Yung Chul, "A Study on the Savings Behavior, 1953-1972," and Kim,&#13;
Kwang Suk. "Household Savings Behavior," both in Kim, Chuk Kyo, et. al.,&#13;
Planning Model and Macroeconomic Policy Issues, Seoul (Korea Development&#13;
Institute) 1977; Sundararajan, V. and Thakar, S., "Public Investment,&#13;
Crowding Out, and Growth: A Dynamic Model Applied to India and Korea,"&#13;
IMF Staff Papers, Vol. 27, No. 4 (December 1980); and notes 12 and 13.&#13;
2.        See N.C. Hope, "Developments in and Prospects for the External&#13;
Debt of the Developing Countries: 1970-80 and Beyond," World Bank Staff&#13;
Working Paper, No. 488, August 1981, Washington, D.C.; A. Fleming, "Private&#13;
Capital Flows to Developing Countries and their Determination: Historical&#13;
Perspectives, Recent Experience and Future Prospects," World Bank Staff&#13;
Working Paper, No. 484, August 1981, Washington, D.C.; R. O'Brien, "Private&#13;
Bank Lending to Developing Countries," World Bank Staff Working Paper, No.&#13;
482, August 1981, Washington, D.C.&#13;
3.        As a ratio of GNP, foreign savings were negligible in 1977, but in&#13;
1979 they had risen to 6.9% and to over 9% in 1980. Economic Management&#13;
Plan for 1981, Economic Planning Board, ROK, January 1981.&#13;
4.        The Economic Management Plan for 1983 (EPB, February 1983) projects&#13;
an investment-GNP ratio of 30.9% in 1986 (p. 22). This may be somewhat of&#13;
an overestimate. See note on "Investment in Korea," by S. Yusuf and R.K.&#13;
Peters, mimeo, World Bank, May 1983.&#13;
5.        See, for instance, Evans, M.K. (1969), Macroeconomic Activity, New&#13;
York: Harper &amp; Row, Chapters 2 and 3.&#13;
6.        Duesenberry, J.S. (1949), Income, Saving, and the Theory of&#13;
Consumer Behavior.   Cambridge, MA:  Harvard University Press.&#13;
7.        Friedman, M. (1957), A Theory of the Consumption Function.&#13;
Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press.&#13;
8.        Modigliani, F. and Ando, A.K. (1957), "Tests of the Life Cycle&#13;
Hypothesis of Savings." Bulletin of the Oxford University Institute of&#13;
Economics Statistics, 19 pp. 99-124.&#13;
9.        Howard, D. (1978), "Personal Savings Behavior and the Rate of&#13;
Inflation," Review of Economics and Statistics, Nov. 1978; and Thirlwall, A.&#13;
(1979), "Inflation and the Savings Ratio Across Countries," Journal of&#13;
Development Studies, Jan. 1979.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- -43-&#13;
10. Shinohara, Miyohei (1981), Industrial Growth Trade and Dynamic Patterns&#13;
In the Japanese Economy, University of Tokyo Press, Chapter 10. United&#13;
Nations, Savings for Development of the International Symposium Resource&#13;
Mobilization of Personal Savings in Developing Countries, United Nations,&#13;
NY (1981).&#13;
11.       Deaton, A. and Muelbauer, J. Economics and Consumer Behavior,&#13;
Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.&#13;
12.       Mundell, Robert A., "Growth, Stability, and Inflationary Finance,"&#13;
Journal of Political Economy, 73, no. 2 (April 1965), p. 97-109.&#13;
Aghevli, Bijan B., "Inflationary Finance and Growth," Journal of&#13;
Political Economy, 85, no. 6 (1977),- p. 1295-1307.&#13;
./&#13;
Gordon, Robert J., "The Demand for and Supply of Inflation,"&#13;
The Journal of Law and Economics, vol. XVIII (3), December 1975, p. 807-857.&#13;
Calvo, Guillermo A., and David A. Peel, "Growth and Infationary&#13;
Finance: Variations on a Mundellian Theme," Journal of Political Economy,&#13;
vol. 91, no. 5, (1983), p. 880-900.&#13;
13.       McKinnon, R. (1976), "Savings Propensities and the Korean Monetary&#13;
Reform in Retrospect," in Money and Finance in Economic Growth and Develop-&#13;
ment. New York, Marcel Dekker, Inc.&#13;
14.       Williamson, J., "Why Koreans Save 'So Little'?," Journal of Devel-&#13;
opment Economics, 6 (1979) p. 343-362.&#13;
15.       Chenery, H.C., and Eckstein, P., "Development Alternatives for&#13;
Latin America," Journal of Political Economy, 78, no. 4, pt. 1 (July/August&#13;
1970), pp. 966-1006.&#13;
Rahman, A., "Foreign Capital and Domestic Savings: A Test of&#13;
Haavelmo's Hypothesis with Cross-Country Data," Review of Economics and&#13;
Statistics, February 1968.&#13;
But some economists are doubtful of the negative effect of foreign&#13;
capital inflow on domestic savings. See Papanek, G. (1972), "The Effect of&#13;
Aid and Other Resource Transfers on Savings and Growth in Less Developed&#13;
Countries," The Economic Journal, Sept. 1972, pp. 934-950.&#13;
16.       Chenery and Eckstein, ibid.&#13;
Laumas, P. "Exports and the Propensity to Save," Economic Develop-&#13;
ment and Cultural Change, July 1982.&#13;
Lee, J.K., "Exports and the Propensity to Save in LDCs," The Eco-&#13;
nomic Journal, June 1971, pp. 341-351.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Maizels, A. (1968), Exports and Economic Growth in Developing&#13;
Countries, Cambridge: Harvard University Press.&#13;
Papanek, G. (1973) "Aid, Foreign Private Investment, Savings, and&#13;
Growth in Less Developed Countries." Journal of Political Economy, p. 120-&#13;
130.&#13;
17.       Import duties as a share of total tax revenue averaged around 11.0%&#13;
during the period 1962 to 1969, 11.8% during the 1970s, and 11.7% for the&#13;
years 1980 and 1981. (Source: Economic Planning Board, Major Statistics of&#13;
Korean Economy, 1982.)&#13;
18.       The Chow tests were performed on our best equation for real gross&#13;
national savings yielding an F value of 9.74. Therefore, we rejected the&#13;
hypothesis of stable coefficients throughout the 1953-81 period.&#13;
19.       Gross domestic income (GDY) equals gross domestic product plus an&#13;
adjustment for the income effect of changes in the terms of trade (see the&#13;
World Bank Statistical Manual, Note 6.20).&#13;
20.       Sato, K. (1982), "Japan's Savings and Internal and External&#13;
Macroeconomic Balance", in Policy and Trade Issues of the Japanese Economy.&#13;
21.       Substituting the curb rate for the TD rate for the period 1965-81&#13;
yields results that are slightly inferior in terms of R2 and the standard&#13;
error of equation. When the TD rate and curb rate are combined in one&#13;
equation, both are reduced to insignificance. Finally in logarithmic&#13;
equations the curb rate is insignificant while the TD rate is not.&#13;
22.       Leff, N. and Sato, K., (1975) "A Simultaneous Equations Model of&#13;
Savings in Developing Countries," Journal of Political Economy, Dec. 1975.&#13;
23.       Shinohara, M., The Determinants of Japan's High Savings Ratio&#13;
and Its Behavior Pattern, The Asian Club, Occasional Paper A-4.&#13;
Mizoguchi, T. (1970), Personal Savings and Consumption in Postwar&#13;
Japan. Tokyo: Kinokuniya.&#13;
Blumenthal, T. (1970), Saving in Postwar Japan. Cambridge, MA:&#13;
Harvard East Asian Monograph.&#13;
24.        Song, Byung-Nak, "Empirical Research on Consumption Behavior",&#13;
Economic Development and Cultural Change, April 1981.&#13;
25.       For further information, see the World Bank Statistical Manual.&#13;
26.       The BOK does not publish savings data in real terms amounts only&#13;
nominal.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
World Bank                          Aggregate Demand and                  Capital Market Imperfec-&#13;
Macroeconomic Imbalances             tions and Economic&#13;
Publications                        in Thailand: Simulations             Development&#13;
of Related                     with the SIAM 1 Model                Vinayak V Bhatt and&#13;
of Related                          Wafik Grais                          Alan R. Roe&#13;
Interest                            Focuses on the demand-side adjust-   World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
ments of the Thai economy to lower   No. 338. July 1979. 87 pages&#13;
agricultural growth and to higher    (including footnotes).&#13;
energy prices. Discusses policy&#13;
measures and structural changes that  Stock Mo. WP-0338. $3.00.&#13;
might enable the economy to over-&#13;
come these problems and continue to&#13;
maintain high GDP rates of growth.    The Changing aNature of&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    ImplctFinance and Its&#13;
448. April 1981. 70 pages (including  Counictions    frDvlpn&#13;
2 appendixes).                        Countries&#13;
Stock No. WP-0448. $3.00.             Albert C. Cizauskas&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
409. July 1980. 43 pages (including&#13;
An Analysis of                        3 annexes).&#13;
Developing Country                    Stock No. WP-0409. $3.00.&#13;
Adjustment Experience and            Adjustment Experiences in&#13;
Growth Prospects of the              the 1970s: Low-Income Asia&#13;
Semi-Industrial Countries            Christine Wallich                    Compounding and Df        s&#13;
Frederick Jaspersen                  This background study for World      counting Tables for&#13;
This background study for World      Development Report 1981 examines      Project Evaluation&#13;
Development Report 1981 examines     low-income South Asia's adjustment   J. Price Gittinger, editor&#13;
the successful process of adjustment  to the external shocks of the 1970s,  Easily comprehensible, convenient&#13;
to external "shocks" of the 1970s    especially those factors that helped  tables for project preparation and&#13;
(rising prices of oil imports, reduced  make the effects of these external  analysis.&#13;
demand for exports, slower economic  developments less severe In theanls.&#13;
growth in the OECD countries) in the  region than In other parts of the    The Johns tlopkins University Press,&#13;
semi-industrial developing countries,  developing world.                   1973; 7th printing, 1982.143 pages.&#13;
Presents an analytical framework for  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   LC 75-186503. ISBN 0-8018-1604-1,&#13;
quantifying the effects of demand    487. August1981. iu + 39 pages        $6.00 paperback.&#13;
management and structural awjust-    (including references).              Arabic: World Bank, 1973. (Available&#13;
ment in forty-two countries, with par-&#13;
ticular reference to Uruguay, Brazil,  Stock No. WP-0487. $3.00.           from ILS, 1715 ConnecticutAvenue,&#13;
Republic of Korea, and Turkey.                                             N.W., Washington, D.C. 20009, U.S.A.)&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   Aspects of Development                $4.00 paperback.&#13;
477. August 1981. 132 pages (including  Bank Management                    French: Tables d'interts composes et&#13;
3 appendixes).                       William Diamond and                   d'actualisation. Economica, 4th print-&#13;
Stock No. WP-0477. $5.00.             V S. Raghavan                        ing, 1979.&#13;
Deals exclusively with the manage-   ISBN 2-7178-0205-3, 36 francs.&#13;
Adjustment in                         ment of development banks. The       Spanish: Tablas de interes compuesto y&#13;
Low-income Africa                     book is divided into eight sections,  de descuento para evaluacion de proyec-&#13;
Robert Liebenthal                     each dealing with one aspect of      d  ecet     aaeauc6       epyc&#13;
management of its problems. and      tos. Editorial Tecnos, 1973; 4th print-&#13;
This background study for World       of the various ways of dealing       Ing, 1980.&#13;
Development Report 1981 aualyzes      with them.                           ISBN 84-309-0716-5, 380 pesetas.&#13;
the adjustment to external shocks&#13;
during the 1970s made by a group      EDI Series in Economic Development.&#13;
of middle-income and low-income       The Johns Hopkins University Press,  A Conceptual Approach to&#13;
African countries, with partJcular    1982. 311 pages.                     the Analysis of External Debt&#13;
reference to Kenya an.  zLC 8-48174. ISB             0-8018-2571-7,        of the Developing Countries&#13;
Senegal, and Sudan.                   $2.9 hardcover; IBN 0-8018-25 72-5,   Robert Z. Aliber&#13;
S29.95 hardcover, ISBN 0-8018-2572-5. ,&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    $12.95 paperback.                    World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
486. August 1981. vi + 56 pages                                            421. October 1980. 25 pages (including&#13;
(Including bibilography).                                                  appendix, references).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0486. $3.00.                                                  Stock No. WP-0421. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Development Banks                    Developments In and                  Food Policy Issues in&#13;
William Diamond                      Prospects for the External           Low-Income Countries&#13;
Operating experiences that serve as a  Debt of the Developing             Edward Clay and others&#13;
practical guide for developing coun-  Countries: 1970-80                  A background study for World&#13;
tries, with a selected list and      and Beyond                           Development Report 1981. Discusses&#13;
summary description of some          Nicholas C. Hope                     food distribution-especially its&#13;
development banks.                   T                                    insecurity in the face of external&#13;
This background study for World      economic pressures and potential&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University PNess,  Development Report 1981 analyzes     conolicts with inter al production&#13;
1957; 5th printing, 1969.141 pages   the debt situation artd its implica-  conceris-in general and with&#13;
(including 2 appendixes, index).     tions for future borrowing.         reference to Bangladesh, Zambia,&#13;
LC 57-13429. ISBN 0-8018-0708-5,     World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   and India.&#13;
$5.00 (£3.50) paperback.             488. August 1981. 70 pages (including  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
2 annexes, references).              473. August 1981. vii + 115 pages.&#13;
Development Finance Com-             Stock No. WP-0488. $3.00.            Stock No. WP-04 73. $5.00.&#13;
panies: Aspects of Policy&#13;
and Operation                        Energy Prices, Substitution,         A General Equilibrium&#13;
William Diamond, editor;             and Optimal Borrowing in             Analysis of Foreign&#13;
essays by E. T. uiper,               the Short Run: An Analysis           Exchange Shortages in a&#13;
Douglas Gustafson, and               of AdUustment in Oil-                Developing Economy&#13;
P M. Mathew                          Importing Developing                 Kemal Dervis, Jaime de Melo,&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press,  Countries                            and Sherman Robinson&#13;
1968.130 pages (including appendix,  Ricardo Martin and                   Examines the consequences of alter-&#13;
index).                              Marcelo Selowsky                     native adjustment mechanisms to&#13;
LC-68-27738. ISBIY 0-8018-0166-4,    Develops a short-term model for      foreign exchange shortages in semi-&#13;
$5.00 (£3.25) paperback.             evaluating the adjustment (par-      industrial economies. Compares&#13;
French: Les societes flnancieres de  ticularly, external borrowing) of oil-  devaluation to two forms of import&#13;
developpement: quelques aspects de   importing developing countries to the  rationing and finds that adjusting by&#13;
leur politique et de leurs actiitesd  increases in oil prices during the.  rationing is much more costly In&#13;
leurapoitiqfree from the World Bank  1970s. Discusses the borrowing       terms of lost gross domestic product.&#13;
(Available  D. C)                    strategies that can be expected in the  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Washington, D. C-                    future and the demands that will be  443. Januaiy 1981. 52 pages (Includ-&#13;
Spanish: Las compaifas financieras   made on multilateral institutions.   in references).&#13;
de desarrollo: algunos aspectos de su                                     ing reerences).&#13;
polftica y de sus actividades. Editorial  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  Stock No. WP-0443. $3.00.&#13;
Tecnos, 1969.                        466. July 1981. 77 pages (including&#13;
300 pesetas.                         footnotes, references).&#13;
Stock /lo. WP-0466. $3.00.               NYEW&#13;
Development Prospects&#13;
of Capital Surplus Oil-              Exchange Rate Adjustment             Growth and Structurai&#13;
Exporting Countries: Iraq,           under Generalized Currency           Adjustment in Eas Asia&#13;
Kuwait, Libya. Qatar,                Floating: Comparative                 arvez   asan&#13;
Saudi Arabia. UAE                    Analysis among Developing            Analyzes the economic performance&#13;
Saudi Arabia. UAE           Countiries                           of the five large market economies of&#13;
Rudolf llablutzel                                                         East Asia-orea, Thailanc, the&#13;
This background study for World      Romeo M. Bautista                    Philippines, Malaysia,.and&#13;
Development Report 1981              Examines the experiences of twenty-  Indonesia-during the last two&#13;
discusses the production strategies  two developing countries in adapting  decades; focuses on the key factors&#13;
and the development policies of the  to the generalized floating of the   explaining their remarkable economic&#13;
capital-surplus oil-exporting        world's major currencies since 1973  and social progress; and identifles the&#13;
countries.                           and discusses the implications that  main economic issues for the 1980s.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   currency floating has on policymaking  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
in these countries and indicates direc-  59 92  2pgs&#13;
483. August1981. 53 pages (including  tions for further research.         529.1982. 42 pages.&#13;
statistical tables).                 World Bank Staff Working Paper Plo.  ISBN 0-8213-0102-0. $3.00.&#13;
Stock No. WP-0483. $3.00.            436. October 1980. 99 pages (including&#13;
appendix).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0436. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
International Adjustment in         Notes on the Mechanics of            ect appraisal. To give substance to&#13;
the 1980s                           Growth and Debt                      the applied and policy dimensions,&#13;
Joshi         Benjamin B. l'~~~~~~~ing            many of the readings are drawn from&#13;
Vijay Joshi                         Benjamin B. King                     the experience of development prac-&#13;
A backgound study for World         A practical model to explore the way  titioners and relate to such important&#13;
Development Report 1981. Analyzes    in which capital inflow from abroad  sectors as agriculture. Industry,&#13;
the macroeconomics of intemational  affects economic growth.             power, urban services, foreign trade,&#13;
adjustment. Highlights potential                                         and employment. The principles&#13;
market failures and areas for       The Johns Hopkins Unuersity Priess,  outlined are therefore relevant to a&#13;
intervention.                       1968. 69 pages (including 4 annexes).  host of development problems.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  LC 68-8701. ISBN 0-8018-0338-1, $5.00  The Johns Hopkins University Press.&#13;
485. August 1982. 57 pages.         (iS.00) paperback.                   February 1983. About 304 pages.&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0062-8. $3.00.                                               LC 82-7716. ISBN 0-8018-2803-1,&#13;
The Policy Experience of             $35.00 hardcover, ISBN 0-8018-2804-X,&#13;
Twelve Less Developed                $12.95 paperback.&#13;
NEW                             Countries, 1973-1978&#13;
Bela Balassa                        Private Bank Lending to&#13;
The Nature of Credit                Uses the methodology applied in the  Developing Countries&#13;
Markets in Developing               author's "The Newly Industrializing  Richard O'Brien&#13;
Countries: A Framework              Developing Countries after the Oil&#13;
for Policy Analysis                 Crisis" (World Bank Staff Working   A background study for World&#13;
Paper No. 473, October 1980) to     Development Report 1981.&#13;
Arvind Virrnani                     examine the policy experience of     Describes the evolution of relation-&#13;
The central purpose of the paper is to  twelve less developed countries in  ships between private banks and&#13;
analyze various forms of government  the period following the quadrupling  developing countries.&#13;
intervention in the loan market in  of oil prices in 1973-74 and the     World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
terms of their effect on efficiency.  world recession of 1974-75.        482. August 1981. vi + 54 pages&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  (Including appendix, bibliography).&#13;
524.1982. 204 pages.                449. April 1981. 36 pages (including  Stock No. WP-0482. $3.00.&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0019-9. $5.00.          appendix).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0449. $3.00.            Private Capital Flows to&#13;
The Newly- Industrializing                                               Developing Countries and&#13;
Developing Countries after          The Political Structure of          Their Determinations:&#13;
the Oil Crisis                      the New Protectionism                Historical Perspective.&#13;
Bela Balassa                        Douglas R. Nelson                    Recent Experience, and&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  This background study for World      Future Prospects&#13;
437. October 1980. 57 pages (including  Development Report 1981          Alex Fleming&#13;
appendix).                          presents a political-economicAbakonstdfrWrl&#13;
analysis of what has been called the  A backgound study for World&#13;
Stock No. WP-0437. $3.00.           "new protectionism."                 Development Report 1981.&#13;
Discusses the nature and determina-&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  tion of recent private capital flows to&#13;
Notes on the Analysis of            471. July 1981. 57 pages (including  developing countries. Focuses on&#13;
Capital Flows to Developing         references).                        those flows passing through the&#13;
Nations and the                     Stock No. WP-0471. $3.00.            prospects for and cmnstranes the&#13;
"Recycling" Problem                                                      developing countries' continuing&#13;
Ralph C. Bryant                                                          access to the intemational capital&#13;
A backgound study for World              NEW                             markets.&#13;
Development Report 1981.                                                 World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Summarizes and criticizes the con-   Pricing Policy for Develop-         484. August 1981. 41 pages.&#13;
ventional analysis of the interrela-  ment Management                    Stock No. WP-0484. $5.00.&#13;
tions between flnancial markets in   Gerald M. Meier&#13;
the industrialized countries and capi-&#13;
tal flows to the developing nations.  Presupposing no formal training in&#13;
economics, it explains the essential  P'rivate Direct Foreign&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   elements of a price system, the     Investment in Developing&#13;
476. August 1981. 67 pages.         functions of prices, the various     COUntri&#13;
Stock Io. WP-04 76. $3.00.           policies that a government might   KC Billerbeck and Y. Yasugi&#13;
Stock flo.                 ~~~~~~pursue. In cases of market failure,  K  ilrel  n   .Ysg&#13;
and the principles of public pricing of  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
goods and services provided by       348. July 1979. iu + 97 pages (includ-&#13;
government enterprises. It also pro-       Y&#13;
vides the would-be practitioner with  ng  annexes).&#13;
an appreciation of the underlying    Stock No. WP-0348. $5.00.&#13;
logical structure of cost-beneflt proj-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NEW                             Structural Adjustment               implications In terms of income&#13;
Policies In Developing              generation, extemal deficit, and&#13;
Short-Run Macro-Economic            Economies                          inflation.&#13;
Adjustment Policies in              Bela Balassa                        World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
South Korea: A Quantitative         Examines structural adjustment      513. June 1982. 93 pages (including&#13;
Analysis                            policies (policy responses to extemal  appendix).&#13;
Sweder van Wijnbergen               shocks, such as the quadrupling of  ISBN 0-8213-0023-7. $3.00.&#13;
oil prices and the world recession of&#13;
An analysis of the startling reversal of  the 1970s) of developing countries.&#13;
performance of the South Korean     Considers reforms in production     World Debt Tables&#13;
economy in 1979 and 1980 compared   incentives, incentives to save and to    p      &#13;
with the preceding fifteen years, and  invest, public investments, sectoral Acopltnofdaonhexerl&#13;
an exploration of the short-run     policies, and monetary policies, and  public a3nd publicly-guaranteed debt&#13;
miacro-economic policy options      comments on the interdependence of  of 101 developing countries plus&#13;
available to Korea in 1981. Highlights  thie various policy measures and on  eighteen additional tables of private&#13;
the role of commercial banks, foreign  the intemational environment in  and nonguaranteed debt from the&#13;
capital inflows, and money markets  which they operate.                 World Bank Debtor Reporting&#13;
and the use of credit obtained from                                     System. Describes the nature, con-&#13;
these sources to flnance flxed and  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  tent, and coverage of the data,&#13;
working capital.                    464. July 1981. 36 pages.           reviews the external debt of 101&#13;
countries through 198L contains&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  Stock No. WP-0464. $3.00.          tables on extemal public debt out-&#13;
510. November 1981. iv + 178 pages                                      standing, commitments, disburse-&#13;
(Including 3 appendixes).                                               ments, service payments, and net&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0000-8. $5.00.              NEW                             borrowings of 101 developing coun-&#13;
tries, by country, 1972-1981.&#13;
Structural Aspects of               (EC-167/81). December 1982. Annual.&#13;
NEW                             Turkish Inflation:                  About 300 pages.&#13;
1.950-1979                         ISSN 0253-2859. $75.00.&#13;
State Finances in India             M. Ataman Aksoy                     Computer tapes containing the data&#13;
A three-volume set of papers that   Inflation has been one of the major  bases for the World Debt Tables are&#13;
explores a range of issues relating to  problems of the Turkish economy  available from the Publications&#13;
the nature of intergovemmental flscal  during the.postwar period. This paper  Distribution Unit, World Bank. The&#13;
relations in India.                 develops altemative inflation models  tapes are available to intemational&#13;
and analyzes their performance in   agencies and offlcial nonprofit agen-&#13;
light of the Turkish experience in  cies of member govemments at a&#13;
VoL 1:- Revenue Sharing             order to provide a framework on     nominal fee. For inforrnation concem-&#13;
in India                            which a more realistic macro model  ing fees for other organizations,&#13;
Christine Wallich                   can be developed.                   please write to the addressee listed&#13;
Deals speciflcally with the principles  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  aboue.&#13;
of revenue sharing in India.        540. 1982. 718 pages.               Supplements to World Debt Tables are&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0098-9. $5.00.          issued periodically as information&#13;
VOLZ H1: IndfaStudfe:s in                                               becomes available; the current&#13;
State Finances                                                           updates are Included with orders for&#13;
Christine Wallich                       NEW                             World Debt Tables.&#13;
Examines in detail the implications of&#13;
revenue sharing for project flnance.  Thailand: An Analysis of            Thea&#13;
Structural and Non-                 The Impact of Contmctuaj Saigs on&#13;
Stmctural and Mon-        ~Resource MobIlizatIon and Allocation:&#13;
VoL 111: The Measurement of         Structural A4justments              The Experience of Malaysia&#13;
abx Effort of State Govern-         Ame Drud, Wafilk Grais, and         Soi Sec        un    In Singapore&#13;
ments, 1973-1976                     Dusan Vujovic                      and the PhilippInes: Ramlflcatlons of&#13;
Raja J. Chelliah and                This study was prepared as a         Instment Poldes&#13;
Narain Sinha                        background paper for the preparation  Investments of Social Security Funds&#13;
of a trucuraladjutrnet lon to In India and Sri Lank.a: Legislation&#13;
Attempts to evaluate the tax perfor-  of a structural-adJustment loan to  and Experience&#13;
mance of particular states in terms of  Thailand and is a follow-up to a pre-  Parthasarathi Shome and&#13;
the average tax effort of all states.  vious paper entitled "Aggregate  Katrine Anderson Salto&#13;
Demand and Macroeconomic            World Bank Reprint Series: Nlumber 144.&#13;
World Bank Working Paper No. 523.   Imbalances in Thailand." Comparative  Reprinted fBom The Malayan Economic Revie, uol.&#13;
September 1982. vol. 1, 85 pages, vol. II,  statistics are used, within the frame-  23. no. 1 (April 1978):54-72; Labour and Society.&#13;
186 pages, uol. III, 85 pages.      work of a four-sector macroeconomic  vol. 5. no. 1 (January 1980):9-30: and The Indian&#13;
ISBN1 0-8213-0013X uol. 1 $3.00, ol 11 modeL to assess alternative ways of  Journal of Economics, uol. 60. patt, no. 238&#13;
ISB  0-213001-X.vol 1,$3.0, ot.11, macroeconomic adjustment in the  (Januany 1980):-349-60.&#13;
$5.00, vol. Ili, $3.00.             Thai economy. Discusses speciflcally  Stock Nlo. RP-0144. fre of charge.&#13;
flsca! policy !nterventions, rnarilpua-&#13;
tions of the exchange rate, and pro-&#13;
ductivity improvements and their&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Policy Responses to External Shocks In&#13;
Selected Latin American Countries&#13;
Bela Balassa&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Nlumber 221.&#13;
Reprinted from Quarterly Review of Economics and&#13;
Business. vol. 21, no. 2 (Summer 1981):131-64.&#13;
Stock No. RP-0221. free of charge.&#13;
Restructuring the Worid Econoniry&#13;
Round 11&#13;
Hlollis Chenery&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Number 204.&#13;
Reprinted from Foreign Affairs&#13;
(Summer 1981).1102-L120.&#13;
Stock No. RP-0204. Free of charge.&#13;
Risk Assessments and Risk Premiunis&#13;
In the Eurodoflar Market&#13;
Gershon Feder and Kinud Ross&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Nlumber 220.&#13;
Reprinted fiom The Joumal of Finance, vol. 37.&#13;
no. 3 (June 1982):679-91.&#13;
Stock No. RP-0220. Free of charge.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
ORDER FORM&#13;
SEND TO:&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS                                                        WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
PO. BOX 37525                                              or                   66, AVENUE D'IENA&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013                                                          75116 PARIS, FRANCE&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Name:&#13;
Address:&#13;
Stock or ISBN #                             Author, Title                       Qty.        Price          Total&#13;
Sub-Total Cost:     .       -&#13;
Postage &amp; handling fee for more than two free items ($1.00 each):&#13;
Total copies: _     _       Air mail surcharge ($2.00 each):&#13;
TOTAL PAYMENT ENCLOSED:&#13;
Make checks payable: WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
Prepayment on orders from individuals is requested. Purchase orders are accepted from booksellers, library suppliers, libraries, and institutions.&#13;
All prices include cost of postage by the least expensive means. The prices and publication dates quoted in this Catalog are subject to change&#13;
without notice.&#13;
No retunds will be given for items that cannot be filled. Credit will be applied towards future orders.&#13;
No more than two tree publications will be provided without charge. Requests for additional copies will be filled at a charge of US S1.00 per&#13;
copy to cover handling and postage costs.&#13;
Airmail delivery will require a prepayment of US $2.00 per copy.&#13;
Mail-order payment to the World Bank need not be in U.S. dollars, but the amount remitted must be at the rate of exchange on the day the&#13;
order is placed. The World Bank will also accept Unesco coupons.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
ORDER FORM&#13;
SEND TO:&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS                                                       WORLD BANK PUBUCATlONS&#13;
PO. BOX 37525                                             or                  66, AVENUE D'ItNA&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013                                                         75116 PARIS, FRANCE&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Name:&#13;
Address:&#13;
Stock or ISBN #                            Author, Title                       Oty.        Pnce          Total&#13;
Sub-Total Cost:&#13;
Postage &amp; handling fee for more than two free items ($1.00 each):&#13;
Total copies: _      _     Air mail surcharge ($2.00 each):&#13;
TOTAL PAYMENT ENCLOSED:&#13;
Make checks payable: WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
Prepayment on orders from individuals is requested. Purchase orders are accepted from booksellers, library suppliers, libraries, and institutions.&#13;
All prices include cost of postage by the least expensive means. The prices and publication dates quoted in this Catalog are subject to change&#13;
without notice.&#13;
No refunds will be given for items that cannot be filled. Credit will be applied towards future orders.&#13;
No more than two tree publications will be provided without charge. Requests for additional copies will be filled at a charge of US $1.00 per&#13;
copy to cover handling and postage costs.&#13;
Airmail delivery will require a prepayment of US $2.00 per copy.&#13;
Mail-order payment to the World Bank need not be in U.S. dollars, but the amount remitted must be at the rate of exchange on the day the&#13;
order is placed. The World.Bank will also accept Unesco coupons.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
rII&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-         .                __l1~~-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                         European Office               Tokyo Office&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                  66, avenue d'1ena            Kokusai Building                                     Z&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A        75116 Paris, France           1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234            Telephone: (1) 723-54.21      Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK           Telex: 842-620628             Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                           Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC                                                                                             oo&#13;
-.-&#13;
0&#13;
Cl)&#13;
0&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0304-X&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554828">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/04/1554828/savings-behavior-implications-domestic-resource-mobilization-case-republic-korea
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/04/1554828/savings-behavior-implications-domestic-resource-mobilization-case-republic-korea</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1984/04/1554828/savings-behavior-implications-domestic-resource-mobilization-case-republic-korea</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/08/000178830_98101903422288/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/08/000178830_98101903422288/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-08-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1984-04-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Savings behavior and its implications for
            domestic resource mobilization : the case of the Republic of Korea
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper focuses on the path of
            domestic resource mobilization in the Republic of Korea over
            the past twenty years, and on the probable medium term
            trend. Achievement of the investment targets of the Fifth
            Five Year Plan within the confines of the current
            environment of the world capital markets will require a
            strong recovery of national savings from the depressed level
            which followed the second oil-price shock. The first section
            of this paper briefly reviews the underlying behavioural
            relationships which have been identified in the theoretical
            literature as affecting savings. From this, a number of
            potential explanatory variables are selected, which are
            tested empirically in the second section. The analysis
            reveals that Korean savings behaviour is explained by
            current income, growth of income, rate of inflation, and the
            real time deposit rate. The course of domestic resource
            mobilization in the Korean economy is simulated according to
            the movements of these variables as envisioned in the Fifth
            Plan. The result of these simulations reveal a need for
            additional foreign savings, if the growth targets of the
            Plan are to be met.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Savings behavior and its implications for
            domestic resource mobilization : the case of the Republic of Korea
        </docna>
        <display_title>Savings behavior and its
            implications for domestic resource mobilization : the case
            of the Republic of Korea</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1984/04/1554828/savings-behavior-implications-domestic-resource-mobilization-case-republic-korea</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Rural Poverty Reduction,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Financial Intermediation,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <count>Korea, Republic of</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Yusuf, Shahid</author>
            <author>Peters, R.</author>
            <author>AEA</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Asia!$!80460</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903422288</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Macro/non-trade</subsc>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 628</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0304-X</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Domestic resources mobilization; Simulation;
            Savings behavior
            accounting,accounting
            practices,affiliates,Agriculture,assets,Bank of
            Korea,borrowing,capital goods,capital markets,Consumer Price
            Index,CPI,current prices,debt,deficits,deflators,econometric
            analysis,economic activity,economic expansion,economic
            growth,Economic Statistics,elasticities,elasticity,empirical
            analysis,employment,equations,EXPENDITURES,export
            growth,exports,financial assets,Fisheries,foreign capital
            flows,GDP,GDP deflator,GNP,GROSS DOMESTIC PRODUCT,Gross
            National Product,Gross National Savings,growth
            rate,housing,imports,income,inflation,inflation
            rate,interest rates,international
            banks,inventories,Keynesian economists,monetary
            policies,National Income,oil,permanent income,permanent
            income hypothesis,poor,portfolios,propensity to save,public
            enterprises,real income,real interest rate,resource
            mobilization,Savings,Savings behavior,savings
            deposits,savings rates,savings ratio,structural change,Terms
            of trade,time series,wages,wealth,Wholesale Price Index
        </keywd>
        <owner>EAC</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP628</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Poverty Reduction Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Political Economy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Political Economy Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Econometrics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Political Economy of Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>