<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Integrating Family Planning with Health Services&#13;
Does It Help?           SWP515&#13;
Rashid Faruqee&#13;
.vv.- llwllAMa uLJVLLUPMENT&#13;
WASHINGTON. D.C. 2O4aI&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 515&#13;
FILE CP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 515&#13;
Integrating Family Planning with Health Services&#13;
Does It Help?&#13;
Rashid Faruqee&#13;
Development Research Department&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright © 1982&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development / THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
This is a working document published informally by The World Bank. To&#13;
present the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has&#13;
not been prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal&#13;
printed texts, and The World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The&#13;
publication is supplied at a token charge to defray part of the cost of&#13;
manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to The World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to&#13;
any individual acting on their behalf. Any maps used have been prepared&#13;
solely for the convenience of the readers; the denominations used and the&#13;
boundaries shown do not imply, on the part of The World Bank and its&#13;
affiliates, any judgment on the legal status of any territory or any endorsement&#13;
or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of The World Bank publications is described in the Catalog of&#13;
World Bank Publications; the continuing research program of the Bank is outlined&#13;
in World Bank Research Program: Abstracts of Current Studies. Both booklets are&#13;
updated annually; the most recent edition of each is available without charge&#13;
from the Publications Distribution Unit of the Bank in Washington or from the&#13;
European Office of the Bank, 66, avenue d'Iena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Faruqee, Rashid, 1938-&#13;
Integrating family planning with health services--does&#13;
it help?&#13;
(World Bank staff working paper ; no. 515)&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
1. Maternal haealth services--India--Narangwal.&#13;
2. Child health services--India--Narangwal.       3. Birth&#13;
control clinics--India--Narangwil. I. Title. II. Series.&#13;
RG965.I42N373    1982      362010o425     82-8405&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0003-2 (pbk.)                 AACR2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ABSTRACT&#13;
Narangwal is more than the name of a village In Punjab, India. It has become&#13;
associated with one of the best known and well documented field experiments in&#13;
health care and family planning anywhere in the world. In that experiment,&#13;
groups of villages were provided with combinations of services for health,&#13;
family planning, and nutrition between 1968 and 1974. The households in each&#13;
group were then followed through extensive data gathering. The World Bank has&#13;
been collaborating with Johns Hopkins University in analyzing this rich set of&#13;
data to study policy questions relating to systems for the delivery of&#13;
services. Two monographs on the findings of this research--one dealing with&#13;
population, one with nutrition--are forthcoming.&#13;
One important question addressed in the population monograph is whether the&#13;
integration of health and family planning services helps in attaLning family&#13;
planning and health objectives. This paper focuses on the findings on this&#13;
question.&#13;
The findings show that integration was more effective in recruiting family&#13;
planning acceptors than was the provision of family planning alone. They also&#13;
show that integration was more cost effective than separate services and more&#13;
equitable in distributing family planning services to all socioeconomic&#13;
groups. Integration also produced better contraceptive protection.&#13;
These results were not obtained by sacrificing health benefits. The findings&#13;
show that health benefits were also impressive--in effectiveness, in effi-&#13;
ciency, and in equLty.&#13;
The life of the experiment was too short to produce a perceptible fertility&#13;
decline, yet the results generally suggest that integration can help in&#13;
reducing fertility, too.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CONTENTS&#13;
Page no.&#13;
Introduction ..................................... .           1&#13;
Description of Services and Variables ........al       ....    2&#13;
Use of Family Planning ..       .    ................ .. ..    7&#13;
Effecttveness     .    ......... ..........  .................. .  7&#13;
Efficiency ....................................           20&#13;
Equity ........................................           23&#13;
Use of Health Services ..........................              25&#13;
Effectiveness             .       .....     ......... .   25&#13;
Efficiency..................                ....29&#13;
Equity ............................................... 34&#13;
Decline in Fertility ........................    .   .... .    36&#13;
Effectiveness           .    .    .........    ...... .   36&#13;
Efficiency                  .      .       ..     .... . 39&#13;
Equity ............................................... 40&#13;
Conclusion                       .....                        41&#13;
References ........................................            42&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
LIST OF TABLES&#13;
Page no.&#13;
Table 1         Summary of Service Inputs                                 5&#13;
Table 2        Preproject Use of Modern (Permanent and&#13;
Temporary) and Traditional Methods among&#13;
Experimental Groups                                       9&#13;
Table 3        Percentage Distribution of Current Users&#13;
of Family Planning, by Method                             16&#13;
Table 4         Multiple Regression Results:  Effects of&#13;
the Volume of Service Contacts in 1969-1973&#13;
and other Variables on Use or Nonuse of&#13;
Family Planning at Any Time During the&#13;
Project 1969-73                                           19&#13;
Table 5        Mean Number of Services and Associated&#13;
Regression Coefficients from the&#13;
Regression Analysis in Table 4                            21&#13;
Table 6        Preproject Use (modern, temporary, and&#13;
permanent methods) Project Use Rates,&#13;
Project Recruits from Nonusers among&#13;
Sociodemographic Groups                                   24&#13;
Table 7        Effects of Children's Services on Mortality&#13;
Rates, by Age, Caste and Experimental Group,&#13;
1970-73                                                   27&#13;
Table 8         Effects of Children's Services on Morbidity&#13;
Levels, 1970-73                                           30&#13;
Table 9         Comparative Efficiency of Narangwal Services             32&#13;
Table 10       Percentage of Women Who had a Live Birth, by&#13;
Practice of Family Planning in the Preceding&#13;
Year and by Experimental Group                            38&#13;
Table 11        Mean Number of Service Contacts and Percentage&#13;
Decline in Fertility                                      40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
LIST OF FIGURES&#13;
Page no.&#13;
Figure 1       Experimental Design for the Narangwal&#13;
Population and Nutrition Projects                          3&#13;
Figure 2       Percent Currently Married Women Age 13-19&#13;
Who Were Acceptors of Modern Family Planning&#13;
Methods at Specified Periods in Time by&#13;
Experimental Group                                        10&#13;
Figure 3        Cumulative Rates of Project Acceptors in&#13;
Experimental Groups                                       12&#13;
Figure 4       Percent Currently Married Women Aged 15-49&#13;
Who were Practicing Family Planning by&#13;
Experimental Group                                        13&#13;
Figure 5       Trends in Contraceptive Practice Rates in&#13;
Experimental Groups                                       14&#13;
Figure 6       Percent Currently Married Women Age 15-49&#13;
Who were "Effective-Users" of Family&#13;
Planning at Specified Points in Time by&#13;
Experimental Group                                        17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INTEGRATING FAMILY PLANNING WITH HEALTH SERVICES:&#13;
DOES IT HELP?&#13;
Whether family planning and health services should be integrated to increase&#13;
the effectiveness of family planning services is no longer a subject of&#13;
debate. Most countries and international agencies favor integration because&#13;
of the efficiency of using health personnel for family planning. But it still&#13;
is important to ask, does integration increase the impact of services? The&#13;
question can be addressed by studying the experience of a controlled experi-&#13;
ment at Narangwal in the Indian state of Punjab.     The Department of Interna-&#13;
tional Health of Johns Hopkins IJniversity conducted a field experiment there&#13;
between 1968 and 1974. In that experiment, different groups of villages were&#13;
provided with different combinations of services for health, nutrition, and&#13;
family planning. The experiment had two parts. The population study examined&#13;
the outcome of integrating health services with those for family planning.&#13;
The nutrition study considered the interaction between malnutrition and infec-&#13;
tions in children under three years of age.&#13;
Timothy King gave the valuable comments on an earlier draft of this paper,&#13;
which is     drawn from Carl Taylor, Rashid Faruqee, Robert Parker, William&#13;
Reinke and R.S.S. Sarma, Benefits of Integrating Family Planning and Health&#13;
Services: the Narangwal Experience (Washington, D.C.: World Bank, forth-&#13;
coming). That source contains the details of the experimental design,&#13;
services, and findings.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
In the population study, five experimental groups of villages were&#13;
matched as closely as possible for comparability. Each group of villages&#13;
received a different service package:&#13;
10   Family planning, women's services, and child care services (FPWSCC)&#13;
2.   Family planning and women's services (FPWS)o&#13;
3.   Family planning and child care services (FPCC).&#13;
4.   Family planning and family planning education services (FPED)0&#13;
5.   Control group (CONT-P).&#13;
In the nutrition study, which covered all children under three, each of four&#13;
groups of villages received a different service package:&#13;
10   Child care services:   nutritional supplementation, and health care&#13;
(NUTHC)o&#13;
2.   Nutritional supplementation (NUT)0&#13;
3.   Health care (HC)0&#13;
4.   Control group (CONT-N)&#13;
The NUTHC experimental group was the FPCC group of the population study (see&#13;
figure 1).&#13;
Description of Services and Variables&#13;
As services developed in the course of the experiment, care was taken to&#13;
ensure that the intensity of services in each experimental group was roughly&#13;
the same0 The project services are summarized in table 10 Never static, the&#13;
services continued to evolve, so that activities would become more relevant&#13;
and realistic0 Services did not start at the same time in all experimental&#13;
groups; this complicated the analysis, as will be noted later0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Figure 1&#13;
EXPERIMENTAL DESIGN FOR THE NARANGWAL&#13;
POPULATION AND NUTRITION PROJECTS&#13;
t                   &#133; -   -   -   -   -   -   _&#13;
HC          I       CONT-N&#13;
Child Health Care  ' Nutrition Project&#13;
Control&#13;
I (Health Care only)       (No services)&#13;
2 Villages            2 Villages&#13;
FPEd            i FPCC (NUTHC)                  NUT&#13;
Family Planning       Family Planning      IChild Nutrition Care&#13;
Educatio         and Child Care      I&#13;
Education         I ,                                          I&#13;
,(Health Care and        (Nutrition only)&#13;
I   Nutrition)                               X&#13;
4 Villages            3 Villages         1     3 Villages&#13;
FPWS                 FPWSCC&#13;
Family Planning      Family Planning &amp;&#13;
and            Women's Services&#13;
Women's Services        &amp; Child Care&#13;
4 Villages            4 Villages&#13;
CONT-P&#13;
Population Project&#13;
Control&#13;
(No Services)&#13;
4 Villages                               __&#13;
Population    Nutrition&#13;
Project       Project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
The project services can be described as follows:&#13;
o    Women's illness care, which included visits or contacts related to&#13;
women's illnesses usually initiated by ill women or their families&#13;
and most often occurring in the village clinic.&#13;
o    Women's other care, which included contacts initiated by project&#13;
health workers through routine home visits to women for fertility&#13;
surveillance, health education, family planning motivation, and&#13;
preventive care.&#13;
o    Children' illness care, which included visits or contacts for&#13;
curative purposes to children of women in the study villages, usually&#13;
at family initiative and in the village clinic.&#13;
o    Children's other care, which included routine contacts initiated by&#13;
project health workers for prevention and surveillance (but including&#13;
early diagnosis and treatment in the home) for children of women in&#13;
the study villages.&#13;
o    Family planning services and follow-up, which included contacts with&#13;
both women and men involving the provision of modern family planning&#13;
methods or the follow-up of users.&#13;
o    Family planning motivation, which included contacts by male family&#13;
planning workers with husbands of women in the study villages (these&#13;
contacts involved general rapport generating activities, health&#13;
related advice, specific family planning and population education,&#13;
and motivation to use contraceptives)0&#13;
The first two categories constituted women's services (WS), the second two&#13;
children's services (CC), and the third two family planning (FP) and family&#13;
planning education (ED).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 1:  SUMMARY OF SERVICE INPUTS&#13;
Kind of service                        Description of service&#13;
FAMILY PLANNING&#13;
Education and motivation          Intense educational efforts were provided in&#13;
FPED villages; education was well integrated&#13;
with health care delivery in FPWSCC and FPWS&#13;
villages, and less adequately integrated in&#13;
FPCC villages.&#13;
Contraceptive services            Condoms, pills, IUDs, injectable Depo-&#13;
provera, vasectomies, and tubectomies were&#13;
provided under similar conditions in all&#13;
experimental groups.&#13;
Follow-up                         The same method-specific patterns of&#13;
follow-up were established for all groups.&#13;
WOMEN'S SERVICES&#13;
Monitoring fertility and          Routine in FPWSCC, FPWS, and FPCC villages;&#13;
early diagnosis of pregnancy      carried out in simplified fonn in FPED&#13;
villages.&#13;
Prenatal and postnatal care       Well-developed pattern in FPWSCC and FPWS&#13;
and supervision of deliveries     villages; modified prenatal care provided in&#13;
done by dais (indigenous mid-     FPCC to protect the child.&#13;
wives)&#13;
CHILD CARE&#13;
Periodic health surveillance      Weekly monitoring of morbidity status in&#13;
and education to three years      FPCC villages, much less frequent (about&#13;
every two months) home visiting in FPWSCC&#13;
villages.&#13;
Periodic measurement of           Routine ranged from every month for&#13;
weight and height                 infants to every three months at three&#13;
years of age for FPWSCC and FPCC villages.&#13;
Immunization                      Routine smallpox, OPT, BCG, polio, and&#13;
measles in FPWSCC and FPCC villages.&#13;
Nutrition supplementation         Selective provision of supplements to mal-&#13;
and education                     nourished or faltering children, and&#13;
education of mothers of all children in&#13;
FPWSCC and FPCC villages.&#13;
Diagnosis, treatment, and         Early care emphasized in FPWSCC and FPCC&#13;
referral of illness               villages.&#13;
Note: All services in the health care villages were provided by family health&#13;
workers, who were auxiliary nurse-midwives with two years' hospital&#13;
training beyond high school plus an intensive six to eight weeks re-&#13;
training period in the project. They were supervised on weekly visits&#13;
by a doctor and by a public health nurse or lady health visitor.&#13;
Family planning educators were the peripheral workers in the FPED&#13;
villages. They were village teachers whose training and supervision&#13;
paralleled the level and intensity of the family health workers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
A large number of input-output-outcome variables were measured in the&#13;
many surveys and studies during the project. Detailed data on services were&#13;
collected to provide a basis for using quantitative measures of services as&#13;
independent variables in input-output-outcome analysis and for detailed&#13;
studies of cost-effectiveness. To identify the background factors that&#13;
lnfluenced project results, many variables were measured. The variables can&#13;
be categorized as follows: i) demographic; ii) socioeconomic; iii) attitudes&#13;
and beliefs; iv) family planning knowledge and practice; v) fertility and&#13;
mortality; and vi) morbidity and growth of children.&#13;
In evaluating the benefits of integration, three outcomes of the ex-&#13;
periment were examined: the use of family planning, selected indicators of&#13;
health, and the decline in fertility0 Three criteria were used to assess the&#13;
value of services: effectiveness, efficiency, and equity0 Effectiveness was&#13;
judged by looking at the outcome: for example, whether integrated health and&#13;
family planning services increased the use of family planning without sacri-&#13;
ficing health benefits0 I/ Efficiency cost-effectiveness was judged by re-&#13;
lating outcome to input, equity by examining the dtstribution of services&#13;
among socioeconomic groups.&#13;
The results of the Narangwal experience are summed up in the follow-&#13;
ing table0&#13;
1/ Outcome and output can be defined in many ways0 Reduced Infant mortality&#13;
or fertility are the ultimate outcomes of project services, but there are&#13;
also such lntermedLate variables as the number and duration of service&#13;
contacts0 .Similarly, input can be measured in many ways0     Here It is&#13;
defined as the time of the personnel and the cost of services0 Note that&#13;
no attempt is made to distinguish the quality of output on the basis of&#13;
whether services are provided separately or in combination with others0&#13;
Nor is the quality of a unit of output distinguished on the basis of who&#13;
uses it0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7-&#13;
Criteria for            Family planning          Health           Fertility&#13;
evaluation                    use              improvement         decline&#13;
Effectiveness                 Yes                  Yes               Yes&#13;
Efficiency                    Yes                  Yes                ?&#13;
Equity                        Yes                  Yes                ?&#13;
I turn now to the results.&#13;
Use of Family Planning&#13;
The experience of many developed countries shows that with socioeconomic&#13;
development, there is a decline in fertility because of the greater use of&#13;
family planning. This does not mean that a fertility decline is possible only&#13;
through socioeconomic development. Recent experience in China, Sri Lanka, and&#13;
in the Indian state of Kerala shows that a country can achieve a substantial&#13;
fertility decline by intervening with family planning programs, even without&#13;
reaching higher income levels. But socioeconomic development alone will not&#13;
increase the use of family planning programs. It is therefore important for&#13;
policymakers to know what kinds of services and what approaches to the&#13;
delivery of services will increase the use of family planning.&#13;
Effectiveness&#13;
The effectiveness of integrated services in increasing the use of&#13;
family planning was looked at in four ways. The first was to observe changes&#13;
in the use of both modern and traditional methods during the project (the&#13;
ever-use rate). This would not exactly capture how much of the change was&#13;
contributed by the project, which only provided modern methods. So, the second&#13;
was to observe only the increases in the use of modern methods (the new-&#13;
acceptor rate of modern method). Acceptance rates do not capture the&#13;
continuation of use. Therefore, the third was to observe changes in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
proportion of women contracepting (the continuing-use rate) at a given point&#13;
of time. The fourth was to observe changes in the methods of contraception&#13;
(the effective-use rate). -&#13;
Acceptors of project contraception fall into three categories: those&#13;
who had used modern contraceptives, those who had used traditional methods of&#13;
contraception, and those who had not used contraception. The distinctions are&#13;
important because they show how great an effect the project had. For example,&#13;
the biggest shift in use was from nonuse before the project to the use of&#13;
modern methods under the project; the smallest, from prior use of modern&#13;
methods to the use of modern methods under the project0 The second was merely&#13;
a shift in the source of supply, but it may also have been a shift to more&#13;
effective methods0&#13;
A comparison of preproject use of permanent, temporary, and tradi-&#13;
tional methods of family planning is shown for the four experimental groups in&#13;
table 20 Considering both modern and indigenous methods, the ever-use rates&#13;
were similar in the villages where family planning services were offered (49.4&#13;
percent of eligible women, that is, married women in the age group 15-49) and&#13;
in those where no family planning services were offered (52 percent of&#13;
eligible women)0 The ever-use rates in the four experimental groups ranged&#13;
from 46.4 to 51.2 percent, but the differences were not significant0&#13;
The overall preproject use of modern methods was 17.6 percent of&#13;
eligible women but varied greatly among the four groups:     the ever-use rate of&#13;
modern methods was 26.0 percent in the FPED group, 19.1 percent in the FPWS&#13;
group, 1801 percent in the control group, 1109 percent in the FPCC group, and&#13;
11.7 percent in the FPWSCC group0 Modern contraceptives accounted for about&#13;
half the prior contraception in the FPED group and more thAn a third in the&#13;
FPWS group and control groups0 In the FPWSCC and FPCC groups, modern&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
contraception was used by only a fourth of those who had practiced family&#13;
planning, and the use of traditional methods was correspondingly greater.&#13;
Thus, if the prior use of family planning is considered with its mix of&#13;
contraceptives, the biggest impact is expected in the FPWSCC and FPCC groups,&#13;
followed by the FPWS group. The least is expected from the FPED group.&#13;
Table 2: PREPROJECT USE OF MODERN (PERMANENT AND TEMPORARY)&#13;
AND TRAD[TIONAL METHODS AMONG EXPERIMENTAL GROUPS&#13;
FPWSCC         FPWS          FPCC         FPED&#13;
Method                       villages     villages      villages      villages&#13;
Permanent                      1.0          5.1           2.8           7.3&#13;
Modern-temporary               10.7        14.0           9.2          18.6&#13;
Traditional                    39.1        29.9          34.5          25.1&#13;
None                           49.2        51.0          53.6          48.8&#13;
Total                         100.0       100.0         100.0         100.0&#13;
In Narangwal villages during the project, the acceptance (ever-use)&#13;
rates of modern family planning methods rose to between 51 and 54 percent of&#13;
eligible women (see figure 2). Those in FPCC and FPED villages rose to 45 and&#13;
37 percent. These increases relate to all acceptors.&#13;
A better indicator of the effect of the project is the new-acceptor&#13;
rate--for those who used modern methods for the first time as a result of&#13;
project activities. Cumulative new acceptor rates in FPWSCC, FPWS, FPCC, and&#13;
FPED villages respectively were 45 percent, 42 percent, 39 percent and 22&#13;
percent by the end of the project (see figure 3). In comparing these rates,&#13;
one has to bear in mind that services started at different times in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
Figure 2&#13;
PERCENT CURRENTLY MARRIED WOMEN AGE 15-49 WHO WERE ACCEPTORS OF&#13;
MODERN FAMILY PLANNING METHODS AT SPECIFIED POINTS IN TIME&#13;
BY EXPERIMENTAL GROUP&#13;
60&#13;
|FPWSC&#13;
50                                          0D~  o Fwsc&#13;
10 _                                            0&#13;
40  J  |  |                                 00000000 1   I I   _   I t&#13;
30  969   1 970   1 97 1    19721973        1974FPCC&#13;
40~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
10  OoooooOOoOOoO ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ 10&#13;
M = March&#13;
i = June&#13;
S = September&#13;
o  December&#13;
World Bank-23899&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
different service groups; FPED services, for example, started nearly two and a&#13;
half years later than FPWSCC services. These rates are useful, however, to&#13;
indicate the trend of project acceptance rate and they somewhat modify the&#13;
picture in figure 2. Cumulative project acceptor rates show that although the&#13;
overall acceptor rates were higher in FPWS villages than in FPWSCC villages,&#13;
the present acceptor rates were higher in the FPWSCC villages. In addition,&#13;
the gap between the curves for FPCC and FPED villages, which widened during&#13;
the project period in figure 2, remained essentially the same in figure 3.&#13;
The much greater source-substitution by prior users in FPWS and FPED villages&#13;
accounts for the differences between figure 2 and figure 3. Figure 3 more&#13;
accurately portrays the project results. 1/&#13;
Figure 3 shows that acceptance curves in all the four groups of&#13;
villages are roughly parallel, implying that the project succeeded in getting&#13;
couples to start contraception more or less at the same rate in all the&#13;
experimental groups. More important, however, is a comparison of trends in&#13;
continuing-use rates, measured by the proportion of eligible women practicing&#13;
contraception at a given time. Ftgure 4 presents the fluctuating continuing-&#13;
use rates in the four experimental groups. A trend line (constructed by&#13;
fitting quadratic equations to smooth the curves) shows a somewhat different&#13;
picture (see figure 5). The smoothed curves show that in all the experimental&#13;
groups except FPCC, the practice rates were still rising. However, the rate&#13;
of rise in FPED villages was considerably slower. In FPCC villages, even a&#13;
decline in the practice rate seemed to have started. One possible reason for&#13;
the observed trend in FPCC villages is that there may be a lag period between&#13;
1/ These results at Narangwal are comparable with the achievements in family&#13;
planning by other experiments and special projects in India.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
Figure 3&#13;
CUMULATNVE RATES OF PROJECT ACCEPTORS 0N EXPERDMENTAL GROUPS&#13;
60&#13;
50 -&#13;
FPWSCC&#13;
00 F PWS&#13;
40  -7                                             0&#13;
0r BPC0&#13;
w&#13;
w~~~~~~ 30&#13;
o 0~~~~~o&#13;
L)                       0/~~~0 &#13;
20~~~~~&#13;
0~~~~~~0&#13;
19917017                         92       9317&#13;
M =  March&#13;
J  =  June&#13;
S  =September&#13;
D =  December&#13;
World Bank-23900&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
Figure 4&#13;
PERCENT CURRENTLY MARRIED WOMEN AGE 15-49 WHO WERE PRACTICING&#13;
FAMILY PLANNING BY EXPERIMENTAL GROUP&#13;
60&#13;
50s&#13;
40                                                        /  FPWS&#13;
0                                                               FPWSCC&#13;
WU 30&#13;
F PCC&#13;
w&#13;
a.~~~~~~~~~~.&#13;
20&#13;
Z          #     /          / /            a&#13;
10                                      /&#13;
0                                      I A ----ii  tii   t  Ii&#13;
M  J S D M     J S D   M  J S D M    J S D M J S D M&#13;
1969      1970        1971       1972       1973     1974&#13;
M = March&#13;
J = June&#13;
S = September&#13;
D = December&#13;
WVorld Bank-23901&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
Figure 5&#13;
TRENDS IN CONTRACEPTIVE PRACTfCE RATES IN EXPEROlMENTAL GROUPS&#13;
(Smooth Curve Obtained by Fitting Quadrate) Equations to Continuing - Us' Ratt)&#13;
60&#13;
50&#13;
40                                                                       FPWS&#13;
0                                                                0 &#13;
z                                                             O&#13;
I-                                                     O             Ooo°   FPWSCC&#13;
rr  30                                               0&#13;
z&#13;
Z                                      0        g       ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~FPCC&#13;
w&#13;
20&#13;
10~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
20&#13;
0        I  I  I   I  I         I  l  I  I   I  I  ,1I1      I  1  1&#13;
M  J   S  D  M  J  S   D  M  J   S D   M  J   S  D  M  J   S D     M&#13;
1969        1970          1971         1972         1973      1974&#13;
M = March&#13;
J = June&#13;
S = September&#13;
D = December&#13;
World Bank-23902&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
the use of services and a rise in family planning (because it would take time&#13;
for the reduced infant and child mortality to have an effect on desired family&#13;
size).&#13;
The demographic impact of family planning depends on what kinds of&#13;
contraceptives are used. 1/ Obviously, the use of condoms or pills cannot be&#13;
as effective as sterilization. So, further adjustments in contraceptive prac-&#13;
tice rates are needed. The mix of contraceptives differed greatly for the&#13;
four experimental groups and changed from beginning to the end (see table 3).&#13;
Toward the end of the project (1974) almost half those practicing contracep-&#13;
tion in FPED group were still only using condoms. At the other extreme, more&#13;
than 40 percent of those practicing contraception at the end of the project in&#13;
FPCC group were sterilized. The expectations for demographic impact thus are&#13;
reduced for the FPED group and increased for the FPCC group. The continuing-&#13;
use rates were adjusted for effectiveness of the methods to give effective-use&#13;
rates (see figure 6). In general, the integration of family planning and&#13;
health services helped in the movement from less effective methods to more&#13;
effective methods.&#13;
To be considered next is the effect of the various health services on&#13;
the practice of family planning. This is best done by reviewing results among&#13;
the different categories of prior practice of family planning. Because prior&#13;
nonusers of family planning started with the zero practice rates, they showed&#13;
the greatest increases in family planning practices. Children's other&#13;
services tripled the use of modern methods by prior users of traditional&#13;
1/ The relative effectiveness of various methods (measured by the pregnancy&#13;
rate of noncontracepting women) was measured as follows: condom, 34 per-&#13;
cent; oral pills, 28 percent; tubectomy, 97 percent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
Table 3: PERCENTAGE DISTRIBUTION OF CURRENT USERS OF&#13;
FAMILY PLANNING, BY METHOD&#13;
Method                  FPWSCC          FPWS            FPCC            FPED&#13;
1970  1974      1970  1974     1970  1974     1970   1974&#13;
Condom                18.0  34.8     20.6  28.7       OoO  30.7      5.5  47.7&#13;
Pill                   3.8   5.5      1.9  09        000   4o7     00    04&#13;
IUD                   18.8   8.2     13.5  25.1       OoO   3.3     18.2   7.0&#13;
Injectable&#13;
Depo-provera       308  29.9     27.7  200       00  19.8      1.8   19.4&#13;
Vasectomy              9.8   6.7     25.2   13.7     58.6  23.6     32.7   12.8&#13;
Tubectomy             18.8  14.9     110   1106     41.4  17.9     41.8   12.9&#13;
Total                 100   100      100    100      100   100      100    100&#13;
methods0 1/  No significant effect was observed among prior users of modern&#13;
methods0 Similar but less dramatic effects were observed for women's other&#13;
services0 Children's illness care more than doubled family planning practice&#13;
rates among prior nonusers. Effects less dramatic but still significant were&#13;
observed for both children's and women's illness care for other categories of&#13;
use0 In contrast with other care, illness care for both women and children&#13;
produced a significant increase in the practice of family planning by prior&#13;
users of modern methods0 Because these other services were more project-&#13;
initiated than patient-initiated, the results indicate that services have the&#13;
potential of being targeted on those who have never used family planning or&#13;
who have used only traditional methods0 People with prior experience of&#13;
family planning tended to respond spontaneously to the availability of family&#13;
planning and health services; therefore, project initiative seemed to be less&#13;
important for them, and illness care had the greater impact0&#13;
1/ See page 4 for a description of illness services and other services0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
Figure 6&#13;
PERCENT CURRENTLY MARRIED WOMEN AGE 15-49 WHO WERE "EFFECTIVE-USERS"&#13;
OF FAMILY PLANNING AT SPECIFIED POINTS IN TIME BY EXPERIMENTAL GROUP&#13;
60&#13;
so _&#13;
50_&#13;
40 -&#13;
cn&#13;
&gt; 30 L                                                      FPWS&#13;
I-&#13;
LU&#13;
we&#13;
FPWSCC&#13;
20                                                       F P Ed&#13;
10   -  -  0   *&#13;
a              i                I  I    I I  I  I I  I&#13;
M  J S D   M J SD0 M J S D       M J S D   M J S D M&#13;
1969     1970       1971       1972      1973    1974&#13;
M = March&#13;
J  =  June&#13;
S = September&#13;
D = December&#13;
World Bank-23903&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
The project-initiated other services for surveillance and prevention&#13;
had much more universal coverage and showed less of a direct concurrent rela-&#13;
tion with the use of family planning than did illness services. The only&#13;
apparent association was that new recruits to family planning late in the pro-&#13;
ject seem to have received (somewhat) more children's other services during&#13;
the period of successful recruitment to family planning. A converse rela-&#13;
tion--early acceptance of family planning leading to greater use of health&#13;
services--was not demonstrated.&#13;
A regression model was used to assess the net effect of services on&#13;
contraceptive practice. Table 4 presents the results0 The coefficients in&#13;
the regression equation are small because service inputs are expressed as&#13;
individual contacts0 The coefficients can be interpreted as approximate in-&#13;
creases in the percentage of contraceptive users in the population given an&#13;
increased input of one unit (contact or visit) of service per woman0 In this&#13;
context, one contact with women's other services is seen to have almost nine&#13;
times the effect of one contact with children's other services; a visit for&#13;
women's illness services is about twice as effective as a visit for child's&#13;
illness services0&#13;
But when the effect of services is examined in relation to the mean&#13;
number of services received, the picture is somewhat different (table 5). If&#13;
the coefficient for each service variable is multiplied by the mean number of&#13;
service contacts, the effect of children's other services in the project is&#13;
shown to be as strong as women's illness services, but still not as strong as&#13;
women's other services0 Women's other services were assocLated with a 14.4&#13;
percent increase in the probability of accepting family planning, compared&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
Table 4: MULTIPLE REGRESSION RESULTS: EFFECTS OF THE VOLUME&#13;
OF SERVICE CONTACTS IN 1969-1973 AND OTHER VARIABLES ON USE OR NONUSE&#13;
OF FAMILY PLANNING AT ANY TIME DURING THE PROJECT 1969-73&#13;
(DICHOTOMOUS DEPENDENT VARIABLE)&#13;
Regression                            Level of&#13;
Independent variable                            coefficient           t-value        significance&#13;
Education of husband                                  .0337                2.1            &lt;.05&#13;
Occupation of husband:   Labor                        .0082                0.2            n.s.&#13;
Farming                      .0543                 1.3           n.s.&#13;
Other                           *                   *             *&#13;
Religion-caste:  Jat-Sikh                           -.0800                 1.8            n.s.&#13;
Ramdasia and other low castes      -.0474                 1.1           n.s.&#13;
Other                                  *                   *             *&#13;
Living children and wife's age: &lt;3 and &lt;35            .1810                3.4            *.001&#13;
&lt;3 and &gt;35              *                  *              *&#13;
&gt;3 and &lt;35           .2568                4.4            &lt;.001&#13;
&gt;3 and &gt;35           .0885                1.7            n.s.&#13;
Number of children dead                              -.0234                 1.6           n.s.&#13;
Awareness of modern contraception                    -.0296                0.6            n.s.&#13;
Prior use of contraception                            .0704                3.5            &lt;.001&#13;
Belief about child mortality                          .0112                0.7            n.s.&#13;
Talk with husband                                     .0671                2.4            &lt;.02&#13;
Attitude toward family planning:   Approval           .0799                2.1            &lt;.05&#13;
Uncertain             *                  *              *&#13;
Disapproval        .0307                0.8            n.s.&#13;
Service contacts:  Women's illness                    .0026                5.0            &lt;.001&#13;
(1969-1973)        Women's other                      .0071                5.8            &lt;.001&#13;
Children's illness                .0012                 2.7           &lt;.01&#13;
Children's other                  .0008                 4.8           &lt;.001&#13;
Male motivation                  -.0025                 0.9           n.s.&#13;
R2 , 0.24&#13;
* Suppressed category; effect included in constant term (-0.0373).&#13;
n.s. = not significant (p &gt;.05)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
Table 5: MEAN NUMBER OF SERVICES AND ASSOCIATED REGRESSION COEFFICIENTS&#13;
FROM THE REGRESSION ANALYSIS IN TABLE 4&#13;
Mean number                      (B) x (X)*        Beta&#13;
Service variable     of contacts (X) Coefficients     (B) x 100    coefficients&#13;
(X)&#13;
Women's illness          1801             oO026           4.7         0.1472&#13;
Women's other            20.3             oO071          14.4         0.1729&#13;
Children's illness       21.6            oO012            2.6         0.0866&#13;
Children's other         60.3            o0008            4.2         0.0973&#13;
*?~  Estimated percentage increase in likelihood of family planning acceptance&#13;
with average services use.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
with an increase of somewhat less than 5 percent associated with women's&#13;
illness and children's other services. In this case the relative importance&#13;
of the variables in explaining differences in contraceptive use is about the&#13;
same as the ranking of the "t" values (table 4) and the beta coefficients,&#13;
normalized coefficients that take into account differences in standard&#13;
deviations of the variables (see also table 5).&#13;
Di ;'tn: Combined and integrated services for health and family&#13;
planning were more effective in getting women to practice family planrilig than&#13;
were services for family planning alone. But integrated services (FPWSCC)&#13;
were less effective than one of the two combined services (FPWS). Of the&#13;
health services, women's services were more effective than children's services&#13;
in getting women to practice family planning. That may explain why the&#13;
services in FPWS villages were more effective than those in FPWSCC villages.&#13;
Efficiency&#13;
Integrated health and family planning services at Narangwal were&#13;
efficient because, by combining various activities in a single visit,&#13;
economies were significant in both time and money. In addition, because the&#13;
combinations made sense in the village home, there appeared to be more rapport&#13;
and greater changes in behavior.&#13;
By the last year of the project (1974) the input of family planning&#13;
workers and family planning educators averaged six to eight hours of direct&#13;
service time a week. For family planning activities the weekly distribution&#13;
of time was 37 minutes in FPWSCC villages; 57 minutes in FPCC villages; 83&#13;
minutes in FPWS villages; and 249 minutes in FPED villages. The time taken to&#13;
maintain friendly relations and rapport took 113 minutes in FPED villages,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
compared with 43-49 minutes by family health workers in the other experimental&#13;
villages. Further evidence on the relative increase in efficiency is provided&#13;
by the time per average service contact in 1973-74, which was shortest where&#13;
integration was greatest: 4.4 minutes in FPWSCC villages; 5.7 minutes in FPWS&#13;
villages and FPCC villages; 14.3 minutes in FPED villages. When time per&#13;
family planning contact was estimated separately, the averages were found to&#13;
be about 4 minutes in FPWSCC villages, 8 minutes in FPWS villages, 19 minutes&#13;
in FPCC villages, and 16 minutes in FPED villages.&#13;
What was the relative cost-effectiveness of different service&#13;
packages? The cost per new family planning acceptor was $12.27 in FPWSCC&#13;
villages, twice that amount in FPWS villages, three times that amount in FPCC&#13;
and FPED villages. The cost per couple-year family planning was $1027 in&#13;
FPWSCC villages, 1.7 times that amount in FPWS villages, 2.5 times that amount&#13;
in FPCC villages, and three times that amount in FPED villages0 The cost per&#13;
family planning contact was $051 in FPWSCC villages, $077 in FPWS villages,&#13;
$1.45 in FPED villages, and $1.92 in FPCC villages0 The cost in FPWSCC&#13;
villages approached the 1968-69 cost per family planning contact in the&#13;
government's primary health centers ($033).&#13;
One explanation for the FPCC contacts being least efficient is that&#13;
family planning services in these villages were started several years after&#13;
child care services had been well established, thus requiring a big&#13;
readjustment in the work patterns of family health workers0 It appears that&#13;
child care services will be always somewhat more difficult to Integrate with&#13;
family planning services than with women's services0 But when family planning&#13;
was combined with both women's and children's services, family health workers&#13;
made much more efficient use of their work time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
Equity&#13;
There were significant differences in preproject rates of ever-use of&#13;
modern contraceptives among religion-caste groups, among education groups,&#13;
among occupation groups, among age groups, and among family-size groups (table&#13;
6). The general pattern was that people of higher caste, higher education,&#13;
higher occupation, and larger family size groups had greater rates of&#13;
contraceptive use. The group aged 25-34 had the highest rate, the group under&#13;
twenty-five the lowest.&#13;
The differences in rates of contraceptive use during the project&#13;
became less significant than the differences in preproject use. The exception&#13;
was the age of wife: there was a reversal of the difference between the&#13;
youngest (under twenty-five) and the oldest (over thirty-five). The reversal,&#13;
which was demographically more advantageous, was so great that the age&#13;
difference became even more significant than the preproject difference.&#13;
Couples recruited by the project were from three prior-use&#13;
categories: users of traditional methods, users of modern methods, and&#13;
nonusers. There were no socioeconomic differences in acceptors recruited from&#13;
preproject users of traditional methods and of modern methods. More important&#13;
than eliminating differences in the recruitment of prior users was narrowing&#13;
differences among new recruits.&#13;
The sociodemographic characteristics of new recruits were distinctly&#13;
different from those of preproject users: the low-caste group had a&#13;
recruitment rate greater than did the high-caste group. Differences by the&#13;
occuipation of the husband, highly significant for preproject users, were&#13;
eliminated. Education of husband maintained the same pattern of distribution&#13;
as that for preproject users, with higher education being associated with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
Table 6:   PREPROJECT USE (MODERN, TEMPORARY, AND PERMANENT METHODS),&#13;
PROJECT USE RATES, PROJECT RECRUITS FROM NONUSERS&#13;
AMONG SOCIODEMOGRAPHIC GROUPS&#13;
Preproject users&#13;
of modern,&#13;
temporary, and                                  Percentage&#13;
Sociodemographic          permanent method        Project users        recruited by project&#13;
group                    (percent)              (percent)             from nonusers&#13;
Religion-Caste:&#13;
Jat-Sikh              20.6                   45.8                   32.4&#13;
Sch-Sikh              12.9                   47.0                   38.9&#13;
Others                18 4  X2 =  21.88      47.5  x2=    049       35.6  x2=    5001&#13;
(2)                    (2)                    (2)&#13;
p =   &lt;oOO1             n.s.                  p =     oO84&#13;
Education of Husband:&#13;
0                     15.2                   46.0                   35.7&#13;
1-5                   17.4                  44.2                   32.4&#13;
6-10                  21.5                   53.8                   45.1&#13;
11+                   32 4  x2 =  49oO       60o2  x2 =  17.40     40O0      =   9o8&#13;
(3)                    (3).                   (2)&#13;
p=    &lt;o001            p=    &lt;o001            p=      oO20&#13;
Occupation of Husband:&#13;
Farming               17.9                   48.8                   38.4&#13;
Labor                 1100                   47oO                   38o7&#13;
Service               27.0                   4922                   36.4&#13;
Other                 206  X2 =  42.85      48.0  x      0.68      34.7  x=     12&#13;
(3)                    (3)                    (3)&#13;
P =   &lt;0001            n.s.                   p =     o750&#13;
Age of Wife:&#13;
&lt;25                   12.3                   52.1                   46.8&#13;
25-34                 22.6                   5701                   45.3&#13;
35+                   17.9  x2 =  23.48      34.5  x2=    068       19.8  x2 =  82.9&#13;
(2)                    (2)                    (2)&#13;
p =   &lt;(001            p =   &lt;o001            p =   &lt;o001&#13;
Living Children:&#13;
&lt;3                    11.8                   41.5                   33.8&#13;
3-5                   21.6   2               51.2                   38.4&#13;
6+                    24.2  x     42.25      49.7  X2=   19.50      33.5  x      2.6&#13;
(2)                    (2)                    (2)&#13;
p =   &lt;.001            p =   &lt;.001            p =     .282&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
higher family planning rates but at considerably lower levels of&#13;
significance. In contrast to preproject users, who mainly were older women,&#13;
the project was able to get fresh acceptors at a considerably higher rate from&#13;
among women under thirty-five. Only about 20 percent of the women over&#13;
thirty-five became users of family planning for the first time; but about 46&#13;
percent of women under thirty-five did. The relation between preproject use&#13;
and number of living children was significant. In contrast, fresh recruitment&#13;
ranged from 33.5 percent for couples with six or more children to 38.4 for&#13;
couples with three to five children.&#13;
Use of Health Services&#13;
The integration of family planning with health services increased the&#13;
efficient and equitable use of family planning. These results in family&#13;
planning were not obtained by sacrificing health benefits. The findings show&#13;
that health benefits were substantial and commensurate with the health&#13;
services provided.&#13;
Effectiveness&#13;
The effectiveness of integrated services in improving health was&#13;
examined by observing changes in the mortality, morbidity, and growth of&#13;
children under the different packages of services. At Narangwal, the death&#13;
rate of children under three years of age was analyzed because the children's&#13;
health services were largely concentrated on children of that age. Changes in&#13;
maternal mortality rates would have been an important measure of the effec-&#13;
tiveness of women's health services, but the analysis of maternal mortality&#13;
was not feasible because of there being few maternal deaths.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
Rates were calculated for stillbirths, infant mortality (neonatal&#13;
under one month and postneonatal from 1 to 12 months), and children's deaths&#13;
between one and three years of age (see table 7). The stillbirth rate roughly&#13;
measures the probable effect on the fetus of prenatal care for the mother,&#13;
especially the effect of providing iron, folic acid, and tetanus toxoid to all&#13;
mothers and nutritional supplementation to poorly nourished mothers. 1/ This&#13;
rate was 57 per 1,000 live and still births in the control villages and was 23&#13;
to 35 percent lower in the villages with services.&#13;
The effects of services on still births were comparable for the low-&#13;
caste group in both FPWSCC and FPCC villages. Only in the FPCC villages was&#13;
there some effect among the high-caste families. This possibly implies that&#13;
the more intensive child care services in FPCC villages covered all caste&#13;
groups, and that workers in FPWSCC villages, with less available time, may&#13;
have concentrated their prenatal care efforts on low-caste mothers. It also&#13;
is likely that low-caste mothers accepted supplementation more readily than&#13;
high-caste mothers in FPWSCC villages0&#13;
Infant mortality rates were disaggregated into neonatal death rates&#13;
(for the first month of life) and postneonatal death rates (for the next&#13;
eleven months)0 The difference in the neonatal death rates was significant:&#13;
the rate was 78 per 1,000 live births in control villages, 64 in FPWSCC&#13;
villages, and 47 in FPCC villages0 This variable also differed by caste0 In&#13;
neonatal suvrival rates, the high-caste children in FPWSCC villages were&#13;
affected by the services, but the low-caste children were not0 This contrasts&#13;
1/ Full prenatal and postnatal care were provided in FPWSCC and FPWS&#13;
villages; modified prenatal care was provided in FPCC villages to protect&#13;
the child. See table 10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
Table 7:    EFFECTS OF CHILDREN'S SERVICES ON MORTALITY RATES, BY AGE,&#13;
CASTE, AND EXPERIMENTAL GROUP, 1970-73&#13;
Infant mortality b              Child (1-3)&#13;
Experimental        Stillbirths a       ( 1 month          1-12 months        mortality C&#13;
group              High       Low      High      Low      High       Low      High       Low&#13;
Caste       Caste   Caste      Caste   Caste       Caste   Caste       Caste&#13;
Control villages d   47         71       81        84       52          52       7          26&#13;
(57)                (78)              (51)                (19)&#13;
FPWSCC villages      52          39      58        86       40          66       3          10&#13;
(44)                (64)              (54)                ( 7)&#13;
Percentage&#13;
difference e      +10.6       -45.1   -28.4     +2.4     -23.1      +26.9    -57.1       -61.5&#13;
(-22.8)              (-18.0)           (+5.9)             (-63.2)&#13;
FPCC villages        27          37      67          48     28          33      12          18&#13;
(37)                (47)              (34)                (13)&#13;
Percentage&#13;
difference e      -63.8       -47.9   -17.3     -42.9    -46.2      -36.5    +71.4       -30.8&#13;
(-35.1)              (-39.7)          (-33.3)             (-31.6)&#13;
Note:     "High" caste were the Jat Sikhs, the landowning farmers, and "Low" caste were the&#13;
scheduled Sikhs, predominately landless laborers. These castes made up 75 to 85&#13;
percent of the population. Total mortality rates including other castes are&#13;
shown in parentheses.&#13;
a.       Rate per thousand live and stillbirths combined.&#13;
b.        Rate per thousand live births.&#13;
c.       Rate per 1,000 children 1-3 years of age.&#13;
d.        Combined rates from the control villages of the Population and Nutrition studies.&#13;
e.        b (or c) - a x 100 = % Difference.&#13;
a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
sharply with the results for still bLrths, for which prenatal care is critical&#13;
and the prenatal care could have been provided to low caste in FPWSCCo      As for&#13;
the neonatal death rate, In villages where services were less intensive in&#13;
their outreach (FPWSCC), high-caste families perhaps sought care from the pro-&#13;
ject or other sources, and neonatal mortality was moderately reduced. Low-&#13;
caste children were significantly affected by services in FPCC villages, show-&#13;
ing a reduction of 43 percent in the neonatal death rate. In FPCC villages,&#13;
home visits were much more intensive (weekly, compared with monthly or bi-&#13;
monthly visits in FPWSCC villages after the immediate postpartum period).&#13;
Basically the same pattern held for children in the postneonatal period, with&#13;
high-caste children in FPWSCC villages and all children in FPCC villages being&#13;
significantly affected by the child care services.&#13;
Although there were fewer deaths among children aged 1-3, the effect&#13;
of services on these deaths was as important as it was in deaths at an earlier&#13;
age. The mortality rates for children aged 1-3 in FPWSCC and FPCC villages&#13;
were 7 and 13 per 1,000 children, compared with 19 in control villages. The&#13;
effect was greatest in FPWSCC villages, which had a mortality rate 63 percent&#13;
lower for this age group than controls, but services for this population had&#13;
an equal effect on all castes. Interestingly, services for older children in&#13;
FPCC villages had no effect on high-caste children0 This may reflect that the&#13;
high-caste older children did not participate in the nutrition supplementation&#13;
program0&#13;
To measure morbidity at Narangwal, FPCC and control villages were&#13;
surveyed weekly0 The morbidity indicator is the average duration of episodes&#13;
of seven illness:   fever, cough, pneumonia, diarrhea, vomiting, eye infection,&#13;
and skin infection0 These were selected because of their frequency and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
importance for children under three. For each illness, the average duration&#13;
was less in the FPCC villages than in the control villages (see table 8). The&#13;
differences ranged from 14 to 33 percent.&#13;
The measures were further refined. The total annual days of illness&#13;
per chtld were estimated for infants under one and for children aged 1-3 by&#13;
using the duration and average incidence rates for each illness.      The analyses&#13;
show that services in FPCC villages reduced the amount of illness by twenty-&#13;
two days a year in each group (table 8): the reductions were 16 percent for&#13;
those under a year and 21 percent for those aged 1-3.&#13;
The differences in another indicator of effectiveness of child health&#13;
services--child growth--were also significant. Growth increased dramatically,&#13;
with average weight dLfferences of 0.5 kilogram and height differences of 2&#13;
centimeters between children in study villages and control villages. The&#13;
effect of sex and caste on growth added to the effects of project services:&#13;
high-caste male child from a study village was 2 kilograms heavier and 6&#13;
centimeters taller at age three than a low-caste female child from a control&#13;
village. The number of living siblings also added to the effect:     a child with&#13;
two male and two female siblings was on the average 0.5 kilograms lighter than&#13;
a child with one living brother or none. This is a powerful argument for the&#13;
health benefits of family planning.&#13;
Efficiency&#13;
The efficiency of health services at Narangwal was measured by&#13;
service contacts per capita, by the time spent per service contact, by the&#13;
service cost per capita, and by the cost per service contact. The integrated&#13;
services in FPWSCC villages generated more contacts than those in FPCC&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
Table 8:    EFFECTS OF CHILDREN'S SERVICES&#13;
ON MDRBIDITY LEVELS, 1970-73&#13;
FPCC     Percentage&#13;
Kind of illness                    Control villages   villages     reduction&#13;
Average days per episode&#13;
Fever                                      3.9            2.9         -25.6&#13;
Cough                                     11.4            8 5         -25.4&#13;
Pneumonia                                  3.6            3.1         -13.9&#13;
Diarrhea                                   6.3           5S1          -19 1&#13;
Vomiting                                   5.2            3.5         -32.7&#13;
Eye infection                              8.3            6.3         -24.1&#13;
Skill infection                            8.7            7.2         -17.2&#13;
Average annual&#13;
days of illness per child&#13;
Total for those under one year             135             113        -16.3&#13;
Total for those aged 1-3                   105             83         -21.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
villages. The different patterns of time inputs and service contacts were&#13;
compared by calculating the average time per contact. In 1971 the average&#13;
time per contact in FPWSCC villages was 5.4 minutes. This figure combines all&#13;
services in the home and clinic into one average. The corresponding averages&#13;
were 6.9 minutes in FPWS villages and 7.6 minutes in FPCC villages.      The&#13;
greater efficiency of the integrated services Is indicated by the averages for&#13;
child care: 4.6 minutes per contact in FPWSCC villages, where they were&#13;
combined with women's services, but 6.7 minutes in FPCC villages. Another&#13;
fact contributing to the differences in child care services between FPWSCC and&#13;
FPCC villages was the greater use of home visiting, which required more time&#13;
per contact in FPCC villages.&#13;
For both women's services and child care, the costs per capita in&#13;
FPWSCC villages were consistently lower than in FPWS and FPCC villages&#13;
indicating the greater efficiency of integrated services (table 9). The&#13;
average annual cost of children's services was $0.56 per capita in FPWSCC&#13;
villages and $1.07 in FPCC villages. This difference is another indication of&#13;
the difference in intensity of surveillance in the two experimental groups.&#13;
Nutritional supplementation, primarily oE children aged 1-3, also cost more in&#13;
FPCC villages ($0.87 per capita) than in FPWSCC villages ($0.60 per capita).&#13;
The cost of women's services other than maternity care was $0.60 in FPWSCC&#13;
villages and $0.88 in FPWS villages; that of maternity care was $0.23 and&#13;
$0.43 for these two experimental groups.    The cost per capita of limited&#13;
services to women in FPCC villages was much less.&#13;
Table 9 also shows the cost per service contact. The cost per unit&#13;
of service for children's and women's services at Narangwal ranged from $0.19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
Table 9: COMPARATIVE EFFECIENCY OF NARANGWAL SERVICES&#13;
(U.S. dollars = 7.5 rupees)&#13;
Control      FPED       FPWS        FPCC      FPWSCC     Governmnent&#13;
villages   villages    villages   villages    villages    services&#13;
Annual cost per capita&#13;
Child care           -          -          005 a      107        056&#13;
Nutrition care       -          -           -         0.87        060b&#13;
Women's services     -         007 a      0.88      013 a       0.60        008 b&#13;
Maternity care       -         001 a      0.44       0011 a      0.23         -&#13;
Cost per service contact&#13;
Women's services     -          -          0.36       0.29        0.29       021 c&#13;
Child care           -          -           -         0.23        0.19        0.13 d&#13;
Maternity care       -          -          1031       1.21        0.79&#13;
Expenditure per capita&#13;
Private services    2.12       3.05        2.09       2.20        1.76         -&#13;
Government&#13;
services e        0.89       0.45        0.39       0.20        0.20        0.25&#13;
a. These reflect cost for supportive services (related to either the main&#13;
services or incurred to maintain rapport).&#13;
bo This figure is for curative and maternal child health care combined.&#13;
c. This figure is for care of illness0&#13;
do This figure is for care of maternal and child health.&#13;
e. This is the average cost of government health services within a primary&#13;
health center area (Johns Hopkins 1976).&#13;
-   Not available or not applicable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
to $0.36; the cost in government primary health centers in 1968-69 was $0.21&#13;
per patient visit and $0.13 per maternal-and-child-health contact. There were&#13;
major differences in the achievements of Narangwal and those of primary health&#13;
center services, but the costs per contact for both services were remarkably&#13;
close.&#13;
Despite government and project expenditure on health care services,&#13;
the villagers still spent a large amount of money on private health care.&#13;
Information on such out-of-pocket spending was collected during the sample&#13;
household survey and combined wtth data on project and government expenditure&#13;
to estimate total expenditure on health care per capita in project villages,&#13;
including control areas. The findings in table 9 show that the provision of&#13;
project services permitted a reduction in the amount of money spent on health&#13;
care by the villagers and by the government. Nonproject health care expendi-&#13;
ture was $1.96 in FPWSCC villages, which had the most project services,&#13;
compared with $2.96 in control villages and $3.51 in FPED villages, which had&#13;
no project health care services. When the second two amounts are compared&#13;
with the expenditure per capita (project and nonproject) in FPWSCC villages,&#13;
it is clear that introducing the comprehensive package of women's and&#13;
children's services (excluding nutrition) in Punjab villages cost only&#13;
slightly more than the existing pattern of government and private services--&#13;
$3.59 per capita a year, compared with $2.96 and $3.51. In contrast, the&#13;
total expenditure on each of the other service packages--FPWS, FPCC, and&#13;
FPED--shows them to be somewhat more expensive alternatives.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
Equity&#13;
Surveys conducted before the project demonstrated a significant&#13;
direct relation between income and the use of health services. Low-income&#13;
people used health services less than high-income people. Narangwal services&#13;
were designed, however, for all people in the study villages, with special&#13;
concern for those in the greatest need. It was therefore important to find&#13;
out whetlher the Narangwal project overcame preexLsting disparities and&#13;
improved equity in the use of project services.&#13;
The use of services was categorized in three ways: no use during the&#13;
project, use early (1969-71) or late (1972-73) in the project, and use&#13;
throughout the project0 The families were characterized by socioeconomic&#13;
measures, including caste, income, ownership of land, education of husband or&#13;
father, and the possesston of radios, bicycles, or sewing machines. The&#13;
project services attracted all types of women and children almost equally0&#13;
Women from land-owning families and those whose husbands were better educated&#13;
used women's illness services significantly more than other women0 Other than&#13;
that, there were no significant differences in use between different socio-&#13;
economic groups0 But there was a small, consistent trend for women of higher&#13;
socioeconomic status and children of lower socioeconomic status (except for&#13;
education) to use services more0&#13;
Cross-sectional household surveys measuring the use of different&#13;
sources of care also confirmed the equitable distribution of project curative&#13;
services and the removal of disparities between women and children of high&#13;
caste and those of low caste0 The data from these surveys showed that 38&#13;
percent of the illnesses of high-caste children were treated by project&#13;
personnel, compared with 39 percent of those of low-caste children0 Among&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
women the proportion of illnesses receiving project services was 28 percent&#13;
for high-caste families and 29 percent for low-caste families. But Ln project&#13;
villages, high-caste families (20 percent) continued to use outside sources of&#13;
services much more than low-caste families (7 percent), producing a use rate&#13;
significantly higher for high-caste children (56 percent) than for low-caste&#13;
children (45 percent). Thus project services in many cases tended to supple-&#13;
ment outside sources of care for high-caste children, but they substituted for&#13;
most outside sources for low-caste children. The pattern of displacement of&#13;
other sources of care by project services among high-caste woman and low-caste&#13;
women was similar to that observed in their children. The data therefore&#13;
indicate that the project delivered services equitably, but that the demand&#13;
for continued use of other sources of care varied significantly by socio-&#13;
economic level.&#13;
The provision of curative services required a visit to the family&#13;
health worker's village clinic and were mainly initiated by patients. Most&#13;
services other than curative services were initiated by the project. They&#13;
included prevention and surveillance, usually in the home. Except [or&#13;
differences by caste, the proportion of women using these services varied&#13;
slightly but not significantly by socioeconomic classification. In general, a&#13;
greater proportion of low-caste women used them, making these even more&#13;
equitable than curative services.&#13;
To sum up: The use of curative services was essentially equalized&#13;
for the different socioeconomic groups. It appears that the provision of&#13;
curative services by the Narangwal project made it possible for the low-caste&#13;
group to shift to project services while the high-caste group continued to use&#13;
private services, but the disparity in total use of the services by caste was&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
reduced. Project-initiated preventive and surveillance activities promoted&#13;
equity because thetr allocation was based on need. For children's other&#13;
services, differences in use were shifted in favor of low-caste children, low-&#13;
income families, landless families, and those with the fewest material&#13;
possessions. The coverage by women's other services was similar.&#13;
Decline in Fertility&#13;
The fertility data disaggregated by experimental groups do not permit firm&#13;
inferences about trends in annual fertility rates or about the effect of&#13;
services on these rates0 The period was too short to observe a secular trend&#13;
or to calculate moving averages to correct fluctuations0 In addition, the&#13;
births in a year, on which the fertility rates were based, were few in number,&#13;
and fluctuations were accentuated because the births were to different groups&#13;
of women0 There also was variation in the quality of birth data gathered in&#13;
the various groups: villages that had the most extensive services had the&#13;
least underreporting0&#13;
Effectiveness&#13;
The fluctuation in fertility rates from year to year was consider-&#13;
able, partly because of the small sizes of the experimental groups0 The&#13;
largest decline was in FPWS villages (21 percent), followed by FPWSCC villages&#13;
(15 percent)0 The decline in FPED villages was 7 percent, that in the control&#13;
villages 12 percent0   The FPCC villages registered a rise of 2 percent0   Thus,&#13;
two of the groups (FPWS and FPWSCC) had declines significantly greater than&#13;
the control group. The crude birth rates reflect the same patterns.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
The use of family planning had the greatest effect in FPWS villages:&#13;
differences were highly significant in all three years (table 10). Reductions&#13;
in births were also significant in FPWSCC villages, but the effect was less&#13;
than in FPWS villages. These results establish the link between the use of&#13;
services and the reductions in fertlity through contraceptive use.&#13;
As noted earlier, the fertility decline was greatest in FPWS&#13;
villages, next greatest in FPWSCC villages. The results indicate that such&#13;
declines were achieved by contraceptive use from project sources. In FPCC and&#13;
FPED villages, the reductions in births were, not significant, partly because&#13;
of a smaller number of contraceptive users.&#13;
Because of the limitations of fertility data based on groups, an&#13;
attempt was made to assess the effect of services on fertility, primarily&#13;
through relating changes in the fertility of individual women to the use of&#13;
service inputs. The individual-level variable was constructed by measuring&#13;
the percentage change in the annual probability of birth for each woman&#13;
exposed to pregnancy during the project. 1/&#13;
1/  This was constructed as follows:    by using the information on duration of&#13;
marriage (D1) and the total number of live births (B1) up to the end of&#13;
1969, the average annual probability of birth (P1 = B1/D1) was computed&#13;
for each woman to indicate preproject fertility. Similarly, by using the&#13;
duration of the project (D ) and total live births (B2) during the project&#13;
up to the time the women withdrew from project exposure (outmigration,&#13;
dissolution of marriage, or end of project, whichever happened first),&#13;
another average annual probability of birth (P - R /D ) was computed.&#13;
The absolute decline (P1 - P2) in the probability of birth was then&#13;
expressed as a percentage of the initial level (P1). The percentage&#13;
decline in fertility was&#13;
l00(Pl - P2)/P1l&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
Table 10:    PERCENTAGE OF WOMEN WHO HAD A LIVE BIRTH, BY&#13;
PRACTICE OF FAMILY PLANNING IN THE PRECEDING&#13;
YEAR AND BY EXPERIMENTAL GROUP&#13;
Percentage of women who had a live birth&#13;
Calendar     Nonusers of family    Users of family&#13;
year           planning              planninga         X    P-Value&#13;
FPWSCC    1971  22.9               14 4                  5.17           oO24&#13;
1972  25.8               14.7                 10.03         &lt;oO05&#13;
1973  20.5               14.3                  3.57           oO62&#13;
FPWS      1971  26.3               9.6                  19.42         &lt;oO05&#13;
1972  29.1               12.7                 18.79         &lt;oO05&#13;
1973  21.2               103                 1080         &lt;oO05&#13;
FPCC      1971  26oO               6.1                   5o57          oO20&#13;
1972  208               15.9                  1.39           o243&#13;
1973  22.9               20f6                   0.26          o636&#13;
FPED      1971  200 oO             f                     3.O7          oO84&#13;
1972  25.2                9.1                  3.56           o062&#13;
1973  20o5               12 o9                 2 o97          .088&#13;
a   These births occurred presumably because of the faLlure of contraceptive&#13;
method used or because of inefficient or irregular use.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
Of the 2,298 cases examined during the project, about 18 percent had&#13;
an increase in the probability of birth, and about 4 percent had no change.&#13;
But 78 percent of women in the sample had a decline, though low. More than&#13;
half had a decline in probability of less than 20 percent; about a fifth more&#13;
than 20 percent. As would be expected, age is significantly related to the&#13;
dependent variable.&#13;
The relationship between the use of services and the individual-level&#13;
fertility decline appears to be complex. Table 11 presents the mean number of&#13;
service contacts of various types by the groups with varying ratios of&#13;
fertility decline. The table shows that in all instances the least use of&#13;
services was related to a moderate decline in fertility. Those who had no&#13;
decline, or even a negative decline, were heavy users of services, as were&#13;
those who had high declines in fertility. These results suggest that some&#13;
heavy users were families to which services were rendered in response to&#13;
health needs generated by high fertility. The most relevant finding is that&#13;
the remaining group of heavy users of services had a substantial decline in&#13;
fertility (16 percent and more), and these couples may be those for whom the&#13;
fertility impact of services was beginning to be evident. The relation&#13;
between service inputs and the dependent variable (the percentage decline in&#13;
the average probability of birth per year of exposure to the project) is&#13;
therefore nonlinear.&#13;
Efficiency&#13;
The cost-effectiveness of the Narangwal services in causing a decline&#13;
in fertility cannot be ascertained because of the ambiguity observed in the&#13;
relationship between the use of services and a decline in fertility. The&#13;
indirect evidence is of course provided through the observed link between the&#13;
practice of family planning and fertility at the group level (see table 11)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
Table 11:   MEAN NUMBER OF SERVICE CONTACTS&#13;
AND PERCENTAGE DECLINE IN FERTILITY&#13;
Percentage                          Mean number of contacts&#13;
decline in                                                    Family     Family&#13;
average annual   Women's   Women's  Children's   Chtldren's   planning    planning&#13;
probability     illness    other      illness     other     motivation  service &amp;&#13;
of birth      services  services  services     services    services   follow-up&#13;
Negative        11.7       15.9      18.4        69.6        12.1         5.9&#13;
0        13.7      19.4      26.6         92.6        13.5         8.1&#13;
1-10        17.1      18.5      25.4        59.7         11L8         8.4&#13;
11-15        14.1      1101       9.5        20.6          6.3         3.4&#13;
16-20        13.1      13.5      14.2        27.4          8.8         7.3&#13;
21-30        17.9      16.8      20.6        43.6          8.8         9.5&#13;
30+        12.9      16.4      15.4        61.3          9.2         8.0&#13;
Total        14.2      14.8       16.5        45.0         9.4         6.5&#13;
and the cost-effectiveness of integrated services in increasing family&#13;
planning use. As noted before, the duration of the project was not long&#13;
enough to have the full effect on fertility. This makes the analysis of the&#13;
project's efficiency in causing a decline in fertility tenuous.&#13;
Equity&#13;
The evidence on equity is also ambiguous. The earlier discussion&#13;
indicated that equity was achieved in the practice of family planning from&#13;
project sources0 An analysis of the fertility decline by income groups&#13;
indicates, however9 that the proportion of women who experienced either an&#13;
increase or no change in the annual probability of birth decreased with&#13;
income9 but that a greater proportion of women in higher income groups had&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
declines in fertility measured by the annual probability of birth. 1/ The&#13;
association is significant.&#13;
Caste is the most important indicator of social status in Punjab.&#13;
For Jat-Sikhs (high caste) the proportion of women who experienced an increase&#13;
in the annual probability of birth was lowest and the proportion who exper-&#13;
ienced reductions was highest. The findings were reversed for scheduled Sikhs&#13;
(low caste). The others were in between. The husband's education was&#13;
associated differently with declines in the individual level fertility of&#13;
women. The women with better educated husbands (sixth grade or higher) fell&#13;
predominantly into two extreme groups--one experiencing no fertility decline&#13;
and the other experiencing a decline of more than 20 percent during the&#13;
project. The less educated group had a higher proportion with a moderate (up&#13;
to 20 percent) decline in fertility. These findings indicate that the objec-&#13;
tive of equity was at least partially achieved because a moderate decline was&#13;
achieved among the less educated group and not all in the higher educated&#13;
group experienced a decline in fertility.&#13;
Conclusion&#13;
The Narangwal data provides some of the most important evidence recorded any-&#13;
where on the benefits of integrating family planning with health services.&#13;
The results show that the benefits can be great--in effectiveness, in effic-&#13;
iency, and in equity, whether measured by health or by family planning. Even&#13;
for a decline in fertility, for which the project life was too short to be&#13;
evident, the results generally show that integration helps.&#13;
1/ See page 37 for a description of this individual level fertility variable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
Antia, N. H. Annual Report of Foundation for Research in Community Health.&#13;
Bombay: Ohokwade/Uran, 1979.&#13;
Arole, M., and R. Arole. "The Comprehensive Rural Health Project in Jamkhed,&#13;
India," in K0 W. Newell (ed.), Health by the People. Geneva: World&#13;
Health Organization, 1975.&#13;
Coale, A0 J. "The Demographic Transition," IUUSP, International Population&#13;
Conference at Liege, Belgium, vol0 1, no0 2 (1973), spo 53-72.&#13;
Coyaji, B0 J. Annual Report on Nadu Rural Health Project. Pune, India: KEM&#13;
Research Center, 1979.&#13;
DeSweemer, C., N0 K0 Sengupta, and S. B0 Takulia. Manual for Child Nutrition&#13;
in Rural India0 New Delhi: Voluntary Health Association and Concept Pub-&#13;
lishing, 1978.&#13;
Esterlin, R. "The Economic and Sociology of Fertility: A Synthesis," in C0&#13;
Tilly (ed0), Early Industrialization: Shifts in Fertility and Changes in&#13;
Family Structure0 Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1974.&#13;
Grant, J. Disparity Reduction Rates in Social Indicators: A Proposal for&#13;
Measuring and Targeting Progress in Meeting Basic Needs0 Monograph no.&#13;
110 Washington, D.C.: Overseas Development Council, 1978.&#13;
Renry, Louis0 "Some Data on Natural Fertility," Eugenics Quarterly, vol0 8,&#13;
no0 2 (1971)o&#13;
Indian Council on Medical Researcho   National Conference on Evaluation of Pri-&#13;
mary Health Care Programs0 Proceedings of a conference held in New Delhi,&#13;
April 21-23, 1980. New Delhi, 1981.&#13;
International Council for Educational Development0 The Lampang Health Develo-&#13;
pment Project: Thailand's Fresh Approach to Rural Primary Health Care0&#13;
Case study no0 7. Essex, Conn., 1979.&#13;
Johns Hopkins University, Department of International Health0 Functional&#13;
Analysis of Hlealth Needs and Services0 New Delhi: Asia Publishing House,&#13;
1976.&#13;
Kendall, M. "The World Fertility Survey: Current Status and Findings.'" Popu-&#13;
lation Reports, series M, no0 3 (July 1979)o&#13;
Kielmann, A0, C0 E. Taylor, and others0 "The Narangwal experiment on interac-&#13;
tion of nutrition and infection: 11 Morbidity and mortality effects0"&#13;
Indian Journal of Medical Research, vol0 68 supplement (December 1978)o&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
Mauldin, P., and B. Berelson.    "Conditions of Fertility Decline in Developing&#13;
Countries," Studies in Family Planning, vol. 9, no. 5 (1978).&#13;
McCord, C.   "The Companiganj Rural Health Project:    A Joint Venture between&#13;
Government and Voluntary Agency," Contact, vol. 34 (1974).&#13;
Misra, B.D., R. Simmons, A. Ashraf, and G. Simmons, "Family Planning in Uttar&#13;
Pradesh:   Final Report of the Kenyan Project."    Ann Arbor:  University of&#13;
Michigan, May 1975 (processed).&#13;
Nortmann, D.L. and E. Hofstatter. Population and Family Planning Programs; A&#13;
Compendium of Data through 1978. 19th ed. New York: Population council,&#13;
1978.&#13;
Omran, A. R. The Health Theme in Family Planning. Monograph no. 16.&#13;
Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina, Carolina Population Center,&#13;
1971.&#13;
Omran, A. R., and C. C Standley, eds. Family Formation Patterns and Health.&#13;
Geneva: World Health Organization, 1976.&#13;
Park, C. B., S. H. Han, and M. K. Choe. "The Effect of Infant Death on&#13;
Subsequent Fertility in Korea and the Role of Family Planning," American&#13;
Journal of Public Health, vol. 69 (1970).&#13;
Parker, R. L., C. E. Taylor, and others. "The Narangwal experiment on&#13;
interactions of nutrition and infection: III. Measurement of services&#13;
and costs and their relation to outcome." Indian Journal of Medical&#13;
Research, vol. 68 supplement (December 19781.&#13;
Preston, S., ed. The Effects of Infant and Child Mortality on Fertility. New&#13;
York: Academic Press, 1978.&#13;
Ratcliffe, J. "Social Justice and the Demographic Transition: Lessons from&#13;
India's State," International Journal of Health Services, vol. 8, no. 1&#13;
(1978), pp. 123-44.&#13;
Ridker, R.G. Population and Development: The Search for Selective Interven-&#13;
tions. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1976.&#13;
Shah, P. M. "The Kasa Project." Speech at International Health Conference&#13;
held for the National Council for International Health, New York, May&#13;
1977.&#13;
Taylor, C. E. and H. Takulia. "Integration of Health and Family Planning in&#13;
Village Subcenters: Report on the Fifth Narangwal Conference."&#13;
Narangwal, Punjab: Narangwal Rural Health Research Center, November 1970.&#13;
Taylor, C. E., J. S. Newman, and N. U. Kelly. "The Child Survival&#13;
Hypothesis." Population Studies, vol. 30, no. 2 (1976), pp. 263-78.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
Taylor, C. E., and others. Doctors for the Villages0     Delhi:  Asia Publishing&#13;
House, 1976.&#13;
Taylor, C0 E., A0 Kielmann, and others. "The Narangwal experiment on interac-&#13;
tions of nutrition and infections: I. Project design and effects upon&#13;
growth0" Indian Journal of Medical Research0 Vol0 68 supplement&#13;
(December 1978)o&#13;
Taylor, C0 E., and others0   Benefits of Integrating Family Planning and Health&#13;
Services: the Narangwal Experience0 Washington, D.C.: The World Bank,&#13;
forthcoming0&#13;
Uberoi, I. S0. and others0   Child Health Care in Rural Areas:   A Manual for&#13;
Auxiliary Nurse Midwives0 New York and Delhi: Asia Publishing House for&#13;
the Narangwal Rural Health Resear Center, 1974.&#13;
United Nations Fund for Population Activities0 Inventory of Population&#13;
Projects in Developing Countries Around the World, 1979-80 New York:&#13;
UNFPA, 1980O&#13;
University of Ghana, Department of Community Health0 Danfa Project Final&#13;
Report: The Danfa Comprehensive Rural Health and Family Planning Project,&#13;
Ghana0 Accra and Los Angeles: University of Ghana Medical School,&#13;
Department of Community Health, and UCLA School of Public Health, 1979.&#13;
Wolfson, M. Changing Approaches to Population Problems0 Paris: OECD, 1977.&#13;
World Bank0 World Development Report, 1980 New York: Oxford University&#13;
Press, 1980O&#13;
World Health Organization and UNICEF0 Primary Health Care0 Joint report on&#13;
an international conference on Primary Health Care at Alma-Ata, UoSoSoRo,&#13;
September 1978. Geneva and New York, 1978.&#13;
Wyon, J. B0 and J. E. Gordon0 The Khanna Study: Population Problems in Rural&#13;
Punjab. Cambridge, Mass0: Harvard University Press, 1971.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 5 -&#13;
World Bank                            Measuring Urban Malnutri-            The Costs and Benefits of&#13;
publications                          tion and Poverty: A Case             Family Planning Programs&#13;
Ublications                       Study of Bogota and Cali,             George C. Zaidan&#13;
of Related                           Colombia                              A technique for measuring the&#13;
Rakesh Mohan,                        economic returns from investing in&#13;
Interest                              M. Wilhelm Wagner,                   population control, with an appraisal&#13;
and Jorge Garcia                     of inherent assumptions and&#13;
Attempts to measure the extent of    limitations.&#13;
malnutrition and poverty in the cities  The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
of Bogota and Cali, Colombia. One    1971. 62 pages (including&#13;
of five papers resulting from a      bibliography).&#13;
research program entitled "City&#13;
Study," a study of the workings of   LC 70-155166. ISBN 0-8018-1317-4,&#13;
five major urban sectors in          $4.00 (f2.40) paperback.&#13;
Colombia.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
447. April 1981. 80 pages (including&#13;
Economics of Supplemental            bibliography, appendixes).&#13;
Feeding of Malnourished              Stock No. WP-0447. $5.00.             Demographic Aspects of&#13;
Children: Leakages, Costs,                                                 Migration in West Africa&#13;
and Benefits                          Regional Aspects of Family           -Volume 1&#13;
Odin K. Knudsen                       Planning and Fertility               K. C. Zachariah&#13;
Analyzes some of the economic         Behavior in Indonesia                and others&#13;
issues involved in the supplemental   Dov Chernichovsky and                Background data on migration in&#13;
feeding of malnourished children.     Oey Astra Meesook                    four English-speaking countries:&#13;
Demonstrates that supplemental        Discusses the recent decline in      Ghana, Sierra Leone, Liberia, and&#13;
feeding programs are economically     Indonesia's population growth rate   The Gambia. A regional analysis&#13;
justified if minimum improvements     despite that country's relatively low  based on these studies is presented&#13;
in mortality rates and more substan-  level of income and socioeconomic    in Migration in West Africa:&#13;
tial increases in productivity take   development. Reviews the history     Demographic Aspects, page 43.&#13;
place.                               and organization of the family plan-  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   ning program and attempts to iden-    414. September 1980. vi + 363 pages&#13;
451. April 1981. iv + 76 pages.      tify those factors that have been     (including statistical annexes,&#13;
Stock No. WP0451. $5.00.responsible for its success and           bbigah)&#13;
Stock No. WP-0451. $5.00.             assesses its prospects for the future.  bibliography).&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   Stock No. WP-0414. $5.00.&#13;
462. May 1981. 62 pages (including&#13;
appendix, references).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0462. $3.00.&#13;
Malnourished People:&#13;
A Policy View                        Confronting Urban                     Demographic Aspects of&#13;
(See description under Development   Malnutrition: The Design of           Migration in West Africa&#13;
listing.)                            Nutrition Programs                    -Volume 2&#13;
James E. Austin                       K. C. Zachariah&#13;
Describes a framework for            and others&#13;
systematically carrying out urban     Background data on migration in&#13;
nutrition programs that examines     four French-speaking countries: Ivory&#13;
Malnutrition: Some                   several key considerations in nutri-  Coast, Upper Volta, Senegal, and&#13;
tion education, on-site feeding, take-  Togo. A regional analysis based on&#13;
Measurement and                       home feeding, nutrient-dense foods,  these studies is presented in&#13;
Policy Issues                         ration shops, food coupons, fortifica-  Migration in West Africa:&#13;
T.N. Srinivasan                       tion, direct nutrient dosage, and food  Demographic Aspects, page 43.&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Number     processing and distribution.         World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
178. Reprinted from Journal of        The Johns Hopkins University Press,  415. September 1980. vi + 385 pages&#13;
Development Economics, vol. 8         1980. 136 pages.                     (including statistical annexes,&#13;
(1981):3-19.                         LC 79-3705. ISBN 0-8018-2261-0,       bibliography).&#13;
Stock No. RP-01 78. Free of charge.   $6.50 (S4.50) paperback.             Stock No. WP-0415. $5.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
416 &#13;
lunmonnflc mfotatrln&amp;Ma  wre$un      ing variables in the model that affect  H-1mmtnn Ufoimnn amnnd WFvewIr(&amp;y&#13;
(Cfl&amp;y ILg0&amp;0le&amp;ngfertility.                                             Hmgmltuu&amp;e&amp;    minnf IFaDRfl(y&#13;
lMypote$e$ ailD       Io l nteir-    The Johns Hopkins University Press,  OPU0inn&#13;
Cnnnhran&amp; At RwM&amp;uO Ann              1979. 188 pages (including bibliogra-  Shlomo Reutlinger and&#13;
lDnhaifilanndnl                      phy, index).                        Marcelo Selowsky&#13;
Fred Arnold and                      LC 78-26070. ISBN 0-8018-2140-1,    The first large research effort in the&#13;
Susan lill Cochrane                  $6.95 (S4.75) paperback.            World Bank to determine the global&#13;
dimension of malnutrition.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
416. September 1980. 41 pages        r&amp;floAty rmad E&amp;$ 1 Regmflolm       The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
(including footnotes, references).                                       1976; 2nd printing, 1978. 94 pages&#13;
Stock No. WP-0416. $5.00.            nrm lmnm   d$o                      (including 5 appendixes).&#13;
R. Amin and                         LC 76-17240. ISBN 0-8018-1868-0,&#13;
lne lnoimon: IrNeory of fae          5E Faruqee                          $4.75 (£2.85) paperback.&#13;
INomoD©n15D k   d umpmet             World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  Spanish: Desnutrici6n y pobreza:&#13;
Hemnmne:ment off NleAoim            383. April 1980. iv + 50 pages       magnitudes y opciones de politica.&#13;
annndl Re0an(Bler  IDeaS&amp;0h          (including references).             Editorial Tecnos, 1977.&#13;
L5Prc:Drg!.=mm                      Stock No. WP-0383. $5.00.            ISBN 84-309-0726-2, 380 pesetas.&#13;
Don Chemichovsky&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Number   lltlln&#13;
121. Reprinted from Evaluating the   Fredrick Golladay,                   Dg    n    n nKfeot AnC&#13;
Impact of Nutrition and Health       coordinating author                 Demoomnhk kopectz&#13;
Programs (1979):227-267.            Draws on experience gained from      K. C. Zachariah and&#13;
Stock No. RP-0121. Free of charge.   health components of seventy World  Julien Conde&#13;
Bank projects in forty-four countries&#13;
Ezm2zmesnnf iinn IFzmnily      between 1975 and 1978.               The first study of the large-scale&#13;
[fmnfngn:gng  LeooDms giroi m       Emphasizes the disproportionately    movement of people in nine West&#13;
high expenditures incurred on cura-  African countries. Discusses the&#13;
IDwLll©e'Yeoflme n  T             tive medicine, maintenance of e:xpen-  volume and direction of internal and&#13;
Roberto Cuca and                    sive hospitals, and sophisticated    external flows and the economic and&#13;
Catherine S. Pierce                 training of medical personnel at the  social characteristics of migrants.&#13;
A comprehensive review of experi-    cost of preventive care for the     A joint World Bank-OECD study. Oxford&#13;
mental efforts in the developing     majority of the people. Points out  University Press, 1981. 166 pages&#13;
world to determine more effective   that low-cost health care systems are  (including 22 maps, bibliographya&#13;
feasible and recommends that the     (icung2masbblorpy&#13;
ways of providing family planning    Bankbe      and       direct le       d )&#13;
services.                            Bank begin regular and direct lend-  Index).&#13;
ing for health, in addition to having  LC 80-21352. ISBN 0-19-520186-8,&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press,  health components as part of        $19.95 (£.10.50) hardcover;&#13;
1978. 276 pages (including bibliogra-  projects in other sectors.        ISBN 0-19-520187-6, $8.95 (f4.50)&#13;
phy, index of experiments).          Sector Policy Paper. February 1980.  paperback.&#13;
LC 77-16596. ISBN 0-8018-2013-8,     90 pages (including 8 annexes,&#13;
$19.50 (-11.50) hardcover;           4 figures, map). English, French,&#13;
ISBN 0-8018-2014-6, $8.95 (£4.00)   Japanese and Spanish. Arabic&#13;
paperback.                           (forthcoming).                      F&amp;dnDzn nsl IFad       Need$&#13;
Stock Nos. PP-8001-E, PP-8001-F,    RiM DeN¢eDOfing CODnnMM   e$&#13;
IFimnlly flnannninfg Firogiramo:     PP-8001-J, PP-8001-S, PP-8001-A.    Odin K. Knudsen and&#13;
Amn zvmnuGalafion of EM;ineunc¢      $5.00.                               Pasquale L. Scandizzo&#13;
Roberto Cuca                                                             World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.                        wonn328. May 1979. 73 pages (including&#13;
345. July 1979. xii + 134 pagesappendxes)&#13;
(including 2 annexes, references).   Hmt &amp;    e¢  pa IlD¢lw3AThm&amp;        Stock No. WP-0328. $3.00.&#13;
Stock No. WP-0345. $5.00.            Fredrick Golladay&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
IFeitflMfy aiand IEdcmnnUoan in:     412. August 1980. ii + 53 pages.    IR   UDII&amp;nuD mlmd IFOBrty flin&#13;
UM2&amp; DoD W1¢e nnDDy imnow?           Stock No. WP-0412. $5.00.           the DeVeDOPRIM0 TJOAd&#13;
Susan Hill Cochrane                                                      Nancy Birdsall&#13;
A model identifying the many chan-&#13;
nels through which education might   Ke~nya: Wlonflaftiogn                World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
act to determine fertility and a review  ainnd  De Done&amp;n                404. July 1980. 96 pages (including&#13;
of the evidence of the relation      (See description under Country      2 appendixes, bibliography).&#13;
between education and the interven-  Studies listing.)                   Stock No. WP-0404. $5.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-47 -&#13;
The Population of Thailand:&#13;
Its Growth and Welfare&#13;
Susan Hill Cochrane&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
357. June 1979. 4, iv + 73 pages&#13;
(including bibliography).&#13;
Stock No. WP-033 7. $5.00.&#13;
Population Policies and&#13;
Economic Development&#13;
Timothy King and others&#13;
The English-language edition is&#13;
out of print.&#13;
Spanish: Poifticas de poblaci6n y&#13;
desarrollo econ6mico. Editorial&#13;
Tecnos, 1975.&#13;
ISBN 84-309-0605-3, 440 pesetas.&#13;
Population Policy and&#13;
Family Planning Programs:&#13;
Trends in Policy and&#13;
Administration&#13;
Kandiah Kanagaratnam and&#13;
Catherine S. Pierce&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
411. August 1980. iii + 22 pages&#13;
(including footnotes).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0411. $3.00.&#13;
The Prevalence of Calorie-&#13;
Deflcient Diets in&#13;
Developing Countries&#13;
Shlomo Reutlinger and&#13;
Harold Alderman&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Number&#13;
158. Reprinted from World Develop-&#13;
ment, vol. 8 (1980):399-411.&#13;
Stock No. RP-0158. Free of charge.&#13;
Sources of Fertility Decline:&#13;
Factor Analysis of Inter-&#13;
Country Data&#13;
Rashid R. Faruqee&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
318. February 1979. 48 pages (includ-&#13;
ing bibliography, appendix).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0318. $3.00.&#13;
Target Group Oriented&#13;
Food Programs: Cost Effec-&#13;
tiveness Comparisons&#13;
Marcelo Selowsky&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Number&#13;
127. Reprinted from American Journal&#13;
of Agricultural Economics, vol. 61,&#13;
no. 5 (December 1979):988-994.&#13;
Stock No. RP-0127. Free of charge.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG3881.5 .W57 W67 no.515 c.3&#13;
Faruqee, Rashid, 1938-&#13;
Integrating family planning&#13;
with health services--does&#13;
it help? /&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters:&#13;
1818 H Street, N W.&#13;
Washington, D C 20433, U S A.&#13;
Telephone (202) 477-1234&#13;
Telex. WUI 64145 WORLDBANK&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK&#13;
Cable address INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
European Office:&#13;
66, avenue d'lena&#13;
75116 Paris, France&#13;
Telephone: 723 54 21&#13;
Telex. 842-620628&#13;
Tokyo Office:&#13;
Kokusai Building&#13;
1-1, Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telephone- 214-5001&#13;
Telex 781-26838&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/TSBN 0-8213-0003-2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554923">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1982/01/1554923/integrating-family-planning-health-services
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1982/01/1554923/integrating-family-planning-health-services</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1982/01/1554923/integrating-family-planning-health-services</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/06/30/000178830_98101903413076/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/06/30/000178830_98101903413076/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1982-01-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-06-30T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Integrating family planning with health services
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Narangwal is more than the name of a
            village in Punjab, India. It has become associated with one
            of the best known and well documented field experiments in
            health care and family planning anywhere in the world. In
            that experiment, groups of villages were provided with
            combinations of services for health, family planning, and
            nutrition between 1968 and 1974. The households in each
            group were then followed through extensive data gathering.
            The World Bank has been collaborating with Johns Hopkins
            University in analyzing this rich set of data to study
            policy questions relating to systems for the delivery of
            services. Two monographs on the findings of this
            research--one dealing with population, one with
            nutrition--are forthcoming. One important question addressed
            in the population monograph is whether the integration of
            health and family planning services helps in attaining
            family planning and health objectives. This paper focuses on
            the findings on this question. The findings show that
            integration was more effective in recruiting family planning
            acceptors than was the provision of family planning alone.
            They also show that integration was more cost effective than
            separate services and more equitable in distributing family
            planning services to all socioeconomic groups.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Integrating family planning with health services
        </docna>
        <display_title>Integrating family planning with
            health services</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1982/01/1554923/integrating-family-planning-health-services</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Adolescent Health,Housing &amp; Human Habitats,ICT Policy and Strategies,Agricultural Knowledge and Information Systems</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>India</count>
        <authors>
            <author>FARUQEE, R.</author>
            <author>DEDPH</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903413076</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Primary health, including
            reproductive health, child health and health</subsc>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 515</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Health, Nutrition &amp; Population</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Family planning; Fertility; Health services;
            Nutrition; Population
            Aged,Birth control,births,care
            services,Child health,Child health services,child
            mortality,clinics,Condoms,contraception,Contraceptive
            Practice,contraceptive protection,Contraceptive
            services,contraceptive use,contraceptives,data
            gathering,death rate,educators,families,family
            planning,family planning education,family planning
            services,farmers,fertility decline,folic acid,health,health
            care,health education,health services,health
            workers,households,Immunization,infants,integration,iron,IUDs,malnutrition,maternal
            deaths,maternal mortality,measles,modern
            contraception,modern
            contraceptives,Morbidity,Mortality,mothers,motivation,neonatal
            death,nurse-midwives,nutrition,nutrition,nutritional
            supplementation,older women,Pill,polio,postnatal
            care,pregnancy,pregnancy rate,prenatal care,programs,public
            health,services for family
            planning,sterilization,stillbirth,teachers,tetanus,use of
            condoms,use of contraception,Use of Health Services,Vasectomy,villages,workers
        </keywd>
        <owner>SAR</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP515</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery of Health Care</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Care Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Service Management and Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Preventive Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Primary and Secondary Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutritional supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vitamins</ml:concept><ml:concept>Birth Spacing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vaccines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Higher Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tertiary Education – Enhancing Access, Equity and Quality</ml:concept><ml:concept>HRH</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Workers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Child Survival and Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Early Child and Children's Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Community Based Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Raising Awareness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Services Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Preventive Care</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Family Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contraceptives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Immunizations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tertiary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources for Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Child Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>India</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>