<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Assessing the Performance of Infant Industries&#13;
Martin Bell     I&#13;
Bruce Ross-Larson&#13;
Larry E. Westphal       SW   P666&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 666&#13;
- FILE CPY l&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 666&#13;
Assessing the Performance of Infant Industries&#13;
Martin Bell&#13;
Bruce Ross-Larson&#13;
Larry E. Westphal&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright ©D 1984&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing September 1984&#13;
This is a working document publishe 'informally by the World Bank. To present the&#13;
results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been prepared&#13;
in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed texts, and the&#13;
World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a&#13;
token charge to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to any&#13;
individual acting on their behalf. Any maps used have been prepared solely for the&#13;
convenience of the readers; the denominations used and the boundaries shown do&#13;
not imply, on the part of the World Bank and its affiliates, any judgment on the&#13;
legal status of any territory or any endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications, both free and for sale, is described in&#13;
the Catalog of Publications; the continuing research program is outlined in Abstracts of&#13;
Current Studies. Both booklets are updated annually; the most recent edition of each&#13;
is available without charge from the Publications Sales Unit, Department T, The&#13;
World Bank, 1818 H Street, N.W., Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A., or from the&#13;
European Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'1ena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Martin Bell, a senior fellow in the Science Policy Research Unit of the University of&#13;
Sussex, and Bruce Ross-Larson are consultants to the Productivity Division of the&#13;
World Bank's Development Research Department. Larry E. Westphal is chief of that&#13;
division.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Bell, Martin (R. Martin N.)&#13;
Assessing the performance of infant industries.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 666)&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
1. New business enterprises--Developing countries.&#13;
2. Industrial productivity--Developing countries.&#13;
3. Technological innovations--Developing countries.&#13;
I. Ross-Larson, Bruce Clifford, 1942-                .   II. Westphal,&#13;
Larry E. III. Title. IV. Series.&#13;
HD2346.5.B45     1984           338.09172'4           84-17416&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0413-5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Abstract&#13;
This paper reports findings from a literature survey to learn about the&#13;
performance of infant industries in less developed countries. Remarkably&#13;
little direct evidence was uncovered about the costs and benefits of&#13;
developing these industries. But the findings indicate that infant firms have&#13;
experienced relatively slow productivity growth. Thus many infants started&#13;
quite some time ago apparently have so far failed to achieve international&#13;
competitiveness. The findings suggest tentative conclusions about the causes&#13;
of the failure. Insufficient productivity growth to achieve and maintain&#13;
competitiveness seems to reflect the absence of sustained efforts to acquire&#13;
and use the capabilities necessary for continuous technological change. Far&#13;
more than stemming from experience alone, these capabilities appear to&#13;
increase to needed levels only through consciously allocating resources to&#13;
acquire them.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Abrege&#13;
Le present document expose les conclusions de toute une s6rie d'ouvrages&#13;
quant aux performances des industries de creation recente dans les pays en&#13;
developpement. On a d6couvert peu d'61ements probants sur les coats et&#13;
avantages d'un developpement de ces industries mais il apparait que leur&#13;
productivite augmente relativement lentement. C'est ainsi que de&#13;
nombreuses societes creees depuis un certain temps deja ne sont&#13;
apparemment pas encore devenues comp6titives au plan international et&#13;
plusieurs hypotheses sont avancees pour expliquer cet echec. Le fait que&#13;
leurs gains de productivite soient insuffisants pour leur permettre de&#13;
devenir durablement competitives semble tenir a l'absence d'efforts&#13;
soutenus en vue d'acqu6rir et d'utiliser les moyens n6cessaires pour&#13;
s'adapter a l'evolution constante des techniques. L'experience ne suffit&#13;
pas a elle seule et, pour parvenir a disposer des moyens voulus, il est&#13;
indispensable de proc6der a une affectation rationnelle des ressources.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Extracto&#13;
En este documento se detallan los resultados de un estudio de los trabajos&#13;
publicados sobre el desempenio de las industrias nacientes en los paises&#13;
menos desarrollados. Es sorprendente que se haya obtenido tan poca&#13;
informaci6n directa sobre los costos y beneficios que comporta el&#13;
desenvolvimiento de estas industrias. Sin embargo, los resultados indican&#13;
que las empresas nacientes han experimentado un crecimiento de la&#13;
productividad relativamente lento. De este modo, muchas industrias&#13;
iniciadas hace bastante tiempo no han logrado aparentemente hasta la fecha&#13;
alcanzar un grado de competitividad internacional. Se sugieren algunas&#13;
conclusiones tentativas acerca de las causas de esto uiltimo. El&#13;
insuficiente aumento de la productividad para alcanzar y mantener la&#13;
competitividad parece reflejar la ausencia de esfuerzos sostenidos a fin&#13;
de adquirir y utilizar las capacidades necesarias para un continuo cambio&#13;
tecnol6gico. Mucho mas que derivarse s6lo de la experiencia, estas&#13;
capacidades parecen incrementarse a los niveles necesarios s6lo mediante&#13;
una asignaci6n consciente de los recursos para adquirirlos.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Acknowledgements&#13;
Alan Gelb and Mieko Nishimizu helped oversee and guide the&#13;
research underlying this paper. Thanks are also due to Bela&#13;
Balassa, Carl Dahlman, Anne 0. Krueger, Simon Teitel, and&#13;
especially to Howard Pack and Don Scott-Kemmi.s for comments on&#13;
earlier versions of this paper.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Contents&#13;
1.  Introduction    ....................................................         1&#13;
2.  Concepts and line of argument           .........................            2&#13;
2.1.   Costs, benefits, and productivity growth .....         ..............  3&#13;
2.2.  Maturity and maturation     .........      ..........................  10&#13;
2.3.   Productivity and capability     .......     ........................  13&#13;
2.4.  Outline of what follows     .........      ..........................  16&#13;
3.  Evidence about performance        ..................  ....................  16&#13;
3.1.   Changing productivity    ..........     ...........................  17&#13;
3.2.   Duration of infancy    ...........     ............................  22&#13;
4.  Maturation of firms     .............................................       26&#13;
4.1.   Stimuli for technological change     ......      ....................  27&#13;
4.2.   Resources for technological change     ......      ..................  30&#13;
5.  Accumulating technological capability      ......      .....................  32&#13;
6.* Conclusion    ....................................................          35&#13;
References   ....................................................           40&#13;
Figure&#13;
1.  The Cost, Benefit, and Duration of Infancy       .....     .................  5&#13;
Table&#13;
1.  Productivity Growth in Industries in Less Developed Countries         ...   19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Summary&#13;
The general view in the literature about infant industries is that only a&#13;
short period is needed for them to become competitive at international&#13;
standards of cost and product specifications. For the right industry and the&#13;
right technique -- that is, for an industry and a production method that&#13;
conform to the country's relative factor endowment -- catching up merely&#13;
entails productivity growth by overcoming initial technical inefficiencies&#13;
through the straightforward accumulation of experience. The essence of this&#13;
model of maturation is that the required increase in productivity is achieved&#13;
passively, effortlessly, and almost automatically. Common expectations about&#13;
the duration of infancy are that it will take about three to five years,&#13;
perhaps stretching to seven or eight.&#13;
The evidence from our survey suggests a different model, one in which&#13;
maturation is achieved by explicit efforts to manage technological change.&#13;
The literature provides few estimates, however, of the duration of infancy in&#13;
today's less developed countries. The studies we surveyed show wide variation&#13;
in rates of productivity change, but they do imply two reasonably clear&#13;
conclusions. First, productivity growth in infant industries appears to be&#13;
highly variable, even in apparently similar economic conditions. Second, few&#13;
of the infant enterprises studied in less developed economies appear to have&#13;
demonstrated the high and continuous productivity growth needed to achieve and&#13;
maintain international competitiveness.&#13;
Given that infant industrial activities experience modest&#13;
productivity growth and that the initial productivity gap is wide, the&#13;
duration of infancy must be long. Long periods of infancy may in part be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
explained by a dynamic aspect that usually is neglected. Productivity may be&#13;
growing not only for infant enterprises, it may also be growing for mature&#13;
enterprises in other countries where the industry is well established. Thus&#13;
industrial maturation may and often does require becoming competitive in&#13;
relation to international standards of cost and product specifications that&#13;
are changing because of continuing advances in productivity in mature&#13;
enterprises. For a newly established industry that begins without being&#13;
internationally competitive, maturity is impossible without productivity&#13;
growth that is faster paced than that in countries where the industry is&#13;
already internationally competitive. This fact may be obvious, but it appears&#13;
frequently to be forgotten.&#13;
The central conclusion is that infant enterprises cannot mature&#13;
unless they accumulate the capability for technological change. The process&#13;
of accumulating that capability is commonly described as learning, but what&#13;
this learning involves is not clear.     The term has often been used merely to&#13;
refer to what is thought to underlie rising productivity. Thus, a path of&#13;
falling unit costs, with an apparently unchanging production system, is often&#13;
simply described as the result of "learning." Such learning refers to the&#13;
feedback of information about industrial production; production in one period&#13;
generates a flow of information and understanding that allows improvements in&#13;
a subsequent period. But the evidence indicates that the flow of information&#13;
does not take place without a conscious effort to monitor performance. And&#13;
the learning from such flows is not effortless; nor is it without cost.&#13;
Costless learning-by-doing thus has limited relevance for the accumulation of&#13;
technological capability.&#13;
Although all enterprises can take advantage of a vast body of&#13;
existing technology, maturity depends on the ability to use this technology&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
effectively. From the evidence it seems that the firm-level absorption of&#13;
technology for infant industrial activities involves modifying and adapting&#13;
the technology. Absorption and the accompanying improvements require specific&#13;
technological changes and the resources to accomplish them. In this respect&#13;
the technological effort needed to master a technology is difficult to&#13;
distinguish from that associated with managing technological change more&#13;
generally. To achieve and maintain international competitiveness thus&#13;
requires developing the capability to manage continuous technological&#13;
change. In other words, maturation takes conscious efforts to develop a&#13;
technological strategy, to invest in resources for technological changes, and&#13;
progressively to accumulate technological capability.&#13;
The apparent failure of many infant industries to attain&#13;
international competitiveness may be due to any of several causes. The one&#13;
that has probably received the most attention in previous discussions is the&#13;
promotion of the wrong infant industries by governments, whether through&#13;
explicit selection or through the implicit effects of trade and other policies&#13;
that differ in their combined incidence on incentives across industries.&#13;
Another possible cause that has received much attention is the use of the&#13;
wrong production methods. Production would be internationally competitive&#13;
given the choice of technique that minimizes cost, but it is not competitive&#13;
because of the choice of a suboptimal technique that leads to permanently&#13;
higher production costs.&#13;
The selection of industries and production methods that do not&#13;
conform to a country's relative factor endowment have undoubtedly been&#13;
important factors inhibiting the attainment of internationally competitive&#13;
production. But given the selections made, what is of at least equal concern&#13;
is the evidence that many infant enterprises have failed to exert needed&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
technological efforts and have thus failed to realize the beneficial&#13;
productivity gains possible. Perhaps of even more concern, this applies to&#13;
many firms in infant industries that do have the potential for international&#13;
competitiveness on factor intensity grounds.&#13;
Governments have often instituted policies that are ill-advised --&#13;
and failed to institute policies that are well-advised -- in relation to&#13;
fostering rapid and efficient maturation. But the effects of different&#13;
policies acting in combination with each other -- and with other social,&#13;
political, and economic factors in the environment -- are far from well enough&#13;
understood to enable unarguable recommendations for optimal policy packages&#13;
designed to foster rapid and efficient maturation. We do know that infants&#13;
can mature. Moreover, the experience in some rapidly industrializing&#13;
countries suggests that they can even mature very quickly. But reflecting our&#13;
general ignorance of the maturation process, there is little general agreement&#13;
on the factors ultimately responsible for the rapid maturation in these&#13;
countries.&#13;
Finding out more about these factors, and how they operate on firms,&#13;
is urgent business -- particularly if our conclusion about the slow maturation&#13;
of most infants in most developing countries is correct. Of equal importance&#13;
is finding out why some firms perform well, whatever the environment, while&#13;
others do not.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ASSESSING THE PERFORMANCE OF INFANT INDUSTRIES&#13;
1. Introduction&#13;
Infant industries are industrial activities that are being undertaken for the&#13;
first time in an economy. The startup costs for plants in a less developed&#13;
country's infant industries are thought to exceed those for identical plants&#13;
in economies where these industries are well established. These higher&#13;
startup costs do not argue against establishing an infant industry if they are&#13;
expected to be offset by the eventual benefits of lower production costs and&#13;
positive externalities. The critical question is whether performance matches&#13;
expectation. Are the startup costs higher? how much higher? Do production&#13;
costs eventually fall to levels below those in well established industries?&#13;
after how long? What are the elements of maturation -- that is, of achieving&#13;
international competitiveness? These are the questions that concern us in&#13;
this paper. They are questions sidestepped in much of the discussion about&#13;
infant industries that has focused on establishing criteria for selecting the&#13;
industries to be nurtured and on determining the policies to promote them.&#13;
Historical plant-level estimates of the social costs and benefits&#13;
associated with infant industrial activities are needed to address these&#13;
questions. With such estimates it would be possible to analyze differences in&#13;
infant-industry performance across firms, sectors, and economies - to examine&#13;
how maturation is influenced by the industrial base, the policies adopted for&#13;
infant activities, and the characteristics of firms and technologies. It&#13;
would also be possible to spell out the various aspects of maturation and to&#13;
determine what is needed to reduce the cost of infancy and increase the&#13;
benefit. Such information should enable better prescriptions for the central&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
choices in designing industrial development strategies and formulating&#13;
policies for their realization; choices about what industries to promote --&#13;
and how to promote them.&#13;
The foregoing framework was our starting point in surveying the&#13;
literature to learn more about the maturation of infant industries in the less&#13;
developed countries.L/ But the survey turned up remarkably little&#13;
quantitative evidence about the cost and benefit of infancy. What we have&#13;
ended up with is very little idea of the cost, some idea of the rate of&#13;
productivity growth for the firms covered in the studies surveyed, an&#13;
impression that there is not much maturation of infants in very many&#13;
developing countries, and some conclusions about the technological effort&#13;
needed for industrial maturation.&#13;
2. Concepts and line of argument&#13;
In this section we lay the groundwork for the following sections on the&#13;
results of the survey. We first consider the relationship between cost-&#13;
benefit analysis and productivity measurement as approaches to assessing the&#13;
performance of infant industries. We do this because the most relevant&#13;
empirical studies give indicators of productivity but not cost and benefit.&#13;
We also do this to underscore the importance of the link between productivity&#13;
growth and maturation. We go on to make a connection between maturation and&#13;
technological efforts to acquire technological capability. Then we consider&#13;
whether productivity growth must always reflect -- or be due to --&#13;
technological effort. We conclude the section with a reader's guide to the&#13;
rest of the paper.&#13;
1/  Martin Bell carried out the survey.      The findings are given in full in&#13;
Bell (forthcoming), from which many of the arguments and conclusions in&#13;
this paper are drawn.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
2.1. Costs, benefits, and productivity growth&#13;
A complete assessment of the performance of an infant industry&#13;
requires social cost-benefit analysis.-/ Nonetheless, very useful diagnostic&#13;
information can be obtained by measuring the infant's productivity growth. A&#13;
brief sketch of the application of cost-benefit analysis will help in&#13;
understanding both the relevance and the limitations of productivity&#13;
measurement.&#13;
The net benefit of an infant industry's development is properly&#13;
measured by starting with the difference between the cost of domestic&#13;
production and the value of that production. The cost of domestic production&#13;
is obtained by valuing inputs at their appropriate shadow prices (or&#13;
accounting values).-/ The simplest approach to placing a value on production&#13;
is to multiply the quantity produced by the unit cost of imports, the latter&#13;
measured using the shadow price of foreign exchange. This approach assumes&#13;
that all production simply replaces imports.4/    It correspondingly overvalues&#13;
any production that satisfies demands in excess of the quantity demanded at a&#13;
price equal to the unit import cost. It equally overvalues any production&#13;
2/ Such analysis applies the Mill-Bastable test for allocative efficiency&#13;
(see Corden 1974, ch. 9).&#13;
3/ Following Bruno (1972), the appropriate measure of unit production cost is&#13;
equal to the ex post domestic resource cost of nontraded inputs plus the&#13;
value of traded inputs per unit of production.       Domestic resource costs&#13;
are measured in shadow prices (or accounting values).       Traded inputs are&#13;
valued by multiplying marginal border prices by the shadow price of&#13;
foreign exchange. As Bruno discusses, the government's policy regime and&#13;
the circumstances of the industry in relation to other industries are&#13;
important determinants of the tradable inputs that are to be counted as&#13;
traded.&#13;
4/ The approach cannot be used if the output produced by the infant industry&#13;
differs in its characteristics from products that can be imported.         The&#13;
implications of product innovation by an infant industry are discussed at&#13;
the end of the section.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
that is exported. The simple approach thus overstates the net benefit..5/ We&#13;
will nonetheless use the simple approach here, because our purpose is only to&#13;
demonstrate that productivity growth may generally be a necessary condition&#13;
for a positive net benefit.L/&#13;
Following this approach, the social cost of developing an infant&#13;
industrial activity is equal to the cumulative discounted value of the&#13;
difference between domestic and import costs from the initiation of production&#13;
to the time of maturation, when domestic production and import costs are the&#13;
same. The gross social benefit includes, correspondingly, the cumulative&#13;
discounted value of the difference between domestic production and import&#13;
costs after the time of maturation, when the average domestic production cost&#13;
is lower than the import price. To this benefit must be added the&#13;
externalities typically invoked in the infant-industry argument and not&#13;
captured in measuring the gross benefit in the foregoing manner.&#13;
In figure 1, OA represents the initial unit cost of infant&#13;
production. OF is the unit cost of importing the product. ABC is the path of&#13;
falling unit production costs as the productivity of the industrial infant&#13;
increases.-/ FG is the path of the unit costs of imports. The figure has two&#13;
5/ The net benefit may also be overstated as a result of neglecting possible&#13;
efficiency losses from protectionist or other measures to promote the&#13;
infant.&#13;
6/ Note that a necessary condition for a positive value with respect to an&#13;
overstatement of the net benefit is equally a necessary condition for a&#13;
positive value of the net benefit.&#13;
7/ The relationship of the path of ABC to the path of the product's market&#13;
price depends on how government policies (especially those affecting trade&#13;
in the product) and the industry's market structure affect price in&#13;
relation to the unit cost of production in shadow prices.      In this paper,&#13;
however, we leave this relationship unexplored, since we are not concerned&#13;
with the distribution of costs and gross benefits between producers and&#13;
consumers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Fig. 1. The Cost, Benefit, and Duration of Infancy&#13;
Unit values&#13;
A&#13;
P~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
F                    B&#13;
I~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
Q       I&#13;
IC&#13;
Cumulative output or time&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
interpretations corresponding to whether the horizontal axis represents&#13;
cumulative output or time. Each interpretation is used below according to its&#13;
relative merit as the vehicle for exposition.&#13;
With the horizontal axis representing cumulative output, the areas&#13;
FAB and CBG have straightforward interpretations. FAB indicates the&#13;
undiscounted total cost of infancy. CBG represents the readily measurable&#13;
undiscounted total benefit of the infant's development, to which must be added&#13;
the externalities not reflected in its measurement.8/ Those benefits are&#13;
gross benefits. To obtain the net benefit, costs and gross benefits must be&#13;
properly time-discounted before deducting the former from the latter. As can&#13;
be seen from the figure, the net benefit can be positive -- leaving&#13;
externalities aside -- only if the infant's unit production cost eventually&#13;
falls below the unit import cost. Indeed, for the discounted equivalent of&#13;
CBG (extended to an infinite horizon) to exceed the discounted equivalent of&#13;
FAB, the production cost must fall enough relative to the import cost to&#13;
overcome the compounding effect of time-discounting.-/     In sum:   to realize a&#13;
positive net benefit in the absence of any externalities, not only must the&#13;
infant mature, the gross benefit achieved after maturation must also be&#13;
sufficient to recoup the cost incurred as the infant matures.&#13;
With the horizontal axis representing time, OT gives the duration of&#13;
infancy. Unit values are then averages with respect to the total quantity for&#13;
each period. The slope of ABC is the real rate of change of unit production&#13;
8/ If measured at the firm level, costs and benefits as measured here fail to&#13;
capture the externalities generated by the firm, though the path of ABC&#13;
will reflect externalities transmitted to it by other firms, both in the&#13;
industry and outside it.     If measured at the industry level, the path of&#13;
ABC will capture the externalities that are internal to the industry.&#13;
9/ This does not mean that the average rate at which domestic costs fall over&#13;
time relative to import costs must be greater than the discount rate.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
costs with respect to time.    It is equal to the rate of change of productivity&#13;
of all inputs combined -- that is, to the rate of change of output minus the&#13;
rate of change of total inputs, where the latter rate of change is equal to&#13;
the weighted sum of the rates of change of all inputs (capital, labor, raw&#13;
materials, energy, and so on), using appropriate weights that vary with&#13;
time.-L2 As can be inferred from the figure, the net benefit of the infant's&#13;
development can be positive -- again leaving externalities aside, and assuming&#13;
an initial cost disadvantage (A greater than F) together with no increase in&#13;
the unit import cost over time -- only if the infant experiences some&#13;
productivity growth. But as can also be inferred from the figure, there is a&#13;
more stringent necessary condition than this for realizing a positive net&#13;
benefit. The slope of FG is the real rate of change of unit import costs,&#13;
which is equal -- assuming the shadow exchange rate remains constant -- to the&#13;
rate of change of productivity for the foreign supplier(s). Thus the net&#13;
benefit of the infant's development can be positive -- assuming no&#13;
externalities, an initial cost disadvantage, and a constant shadow exchange&#13;
rate -- only if the infant experiences faster productivity growth than its&#13;
foreign competitor(s) during some period.&#13;
Suppose -- as may typically be the case -- that the cost of infancy&#13;
exceeds the value of any externalities generated by the infant. Further&#13;
suppose -- as is probably most often true -- that changes in the shadow&#13;
exchange rate over time, if any, do not compensate for this difference.&#13;
Faster productivity growth during some period is then a necessary condition&#13;
10/ For references on measurement, see the citations in Nishimizu and Robinson&#13;
(1984).&#13;
11/ Note that changes in the shadow exchange rate would generally affect the&#13;
unit cost of production as well as the unit cost of imports.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
for the realization of a positive net benefit from the infant's development.&#13;
(Whether faster productivity growth is sufficient to ensure a positive net&#13;
benefit depends on how long it is maintained.) Thus the relationship of&#13;
productivity measurement to cost-benefit analysis is this: productivity&#13;
measurement provides information to test whether a condition that may&#13;
generally be necessary for the economic justification of the infant's&#13;
development has been met, cost-benefit analysis focuses directly on the&#13;
sufficient condition.&#13;
Up to this point we have implicitly assumed that the infant industry&#13;
produces a single unchanging product that is identical to an importable&#13;
variety. This assumption affects the measurement of productivity change, but&#13;
it does not fundamentally alter the relationship of productivity measurement&#13;
to cost-benefit analysis. With many products, the composition of output is&#13;
reflected in the measurement of productivity by measuring it with respect to&#13;
the total real value of output. Changes in productivity then include the&#13;
effects of changes in the composition of output. Thus an infant's relative&#13;
productivity growth depends -- among other things -- on changes over time in&#13;
the variety of products produced. Correspondingly, an infant may experience&#13;
faster productivity growth by shifting the composition of output among an&#13;
unchanged set of products or by changing product characteristics or&#13;
introducing new products.&#13;
Import prices cannot be used to value outputs that are innovative or&#13;
that otherwise differ in their characteristics from those of products that can&#13;
be imported. Indeed, the inappropriate use of import prices -- by failing to&#13;
pay adequate attention to differences in product characteristics -- may result&#13;
in seriously understating the value of an infant's production as well as the&#13;
changes over time in its productivity. This does not, however, mean that&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9-&#13;
import prices can be totally neglected. Outputs that differ from importable&#13;
products are valued through directly estimating the benefits derived by the&#13;
infant's customers.-L-   But these benefits are not independent of the unit&#13;
import costs of close substitutes. Thus the net benefit of the infant's&#13;
development does depend on changes in its productivity relative to changes in&#13;
foreign productivity -- that is, foreign productivity in producing closely&#13;
substitutable imports. The net benefit similarly depends on product&#13;
innovations made overseas. In sum: though differentiation among many&#13;
products makes the measurement of productivity more complex, the relevance of&#13;
productivity measurement remains.&#13;
Even rough estimates of productivity change would help in answering&#13;
several fundamental questions. For example, in figure 1, with ABC now the&#13;
time path of the average (over the outputs produced) total production cost&#13;
(per period) and FG the path of the corresponding average total output value&#13;
-- it being recognized that changes in output composition and product mix&#13;
toward higher value products may cause both of these paths to trend upwards&#13;
during some intervals: What tends to be the gap between A and F for different&#13;
industries and technologies in different countries? What is the general shape&#13;
and average slope of the cost reduction path ABC? How do these relate to&#13;
startup costs in industrial countries? At the very least, it would help to&#13;
know the average duration, OT, for different industries. Is this short, such&#13;
that the cost of infancy is small? Or is it long, such that the cost is&#13;
large? And how does the duration differ in different environments? Is it, as&#13;
might be expected, shorter if the initial industrial base is large? if the&#13;
12/ The measurement problems here are similar to those encountered -- for&#13;
products that have identical importable substitutes -- in measuring the&#13;
value of production that satisfies demands in excess of the quantity&#13;
demanded at a price equal to the unit import cost.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
technology is similar to other technologies already in use? if the policy&#13;
frame is more outward-looking than protectionist?&#13;
2.2. Maturity and maturation&#13;
Maturity is the condition of being internationally competitive -- of&#13;
being at or to the right of T in figure 1. Maturation is the process of&#13;
becoming internationally competitive -- of going from A to B. We use these&#13;
terms because they are the metaphorical counterparts of "infancy." Maturity&#13;
in the sense of achieving and maintaining international cost-competitiveness&#13;
should not be confused with using the most recent vintage of technology or&#13;
being at the global frontier in innovating new technology.13/ In many&#13;
industries neither of these conditions is necessary for achieving maturity as&#13;
we define it. Also to be recognized is that maturity, once gained, can be&#13;
lost. The metaphor can thus be extended to geriatric, even senile,&#13;
industries, but such uncompetitive old industries are not of concern here.&#13;
The basic problem of maturation is accumulating the technological&#13;
capability to become and remain competitive at international standards of cost&#13;
and product specifications. This follows from the observation that sustained&#13;
increases in productivity are the result of efforts to acquire and use&#13;
technological capability. That said, a few definitions are in order.&#13;
o    Technology refers to a collection of physical processes that&#13;
transform inputs into outputs, to the specifications of the inputs&#13;
and the outputs, and to the procedural and organizational&#13;
arrangements for carrying out the transformations. Sometimes the&#13;
term refers only to a production technique, such as the use of a&#13;
13/ Nor should it be confused with achieving particular single-factor (say,&#13;
labor) productivities comparable with levels attained in industrially more&#13;
advanced countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
basic oxygen furnace for making steel in one plant at one time.&#13;
Other times it is extended to embrace a range of similar techniques,&#13;
such as basic oxygen furnaces generally -- or all steel-making&#13;
techniques, including open hearth and electric arc furnaces.&#13;
Sometimes the term refers only to operational expressions of&#13;
technological information, such as steel-making furnaces and the&#13;
tasks involved in their operation. Other times the term is extended&#13;
to embrace the technological information, such as the blueprints and&#13;
operating manuals for steel-making furnaces.&#13;
o    Technological capability is the ability to make effective use of&#13;
technology.-!4/ Capability in choosing technology and in operating&#13;
processes and producing products is essential for attaining&#13;
international competitiveness. Capability in managing changes in&#13;
products, processes, and the procedural and organizational&#13;
arrangements in plants is essential for maintaining international&#13;
competitiveness in an industry.&#13;
o    Technological effort is conscious exertion to use technological&#13;
information and to accumulate technological knowledge to choose,&#13;
assimilate, adapt, or create technology. Effort is needed to&#13;
evaluate and choose technology; to acquire and operate processes and&#13;
produce products, to manage changes in products, processes,&#13;
procedures, and organizational arrangements; and to create new&#13;
technology.&#13;
In emphasizing technological effort and capability, we do not mean to imply&#13;
that relative factor endowments or the imperatives of the product cycle are&#13;
14/ Westphal (1982) and Dahlman and Westphal (1982) use the term "mastery" in&#13;
much the same sense that "capability" is used here.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
inconsequential in determining the potential either for achieving or for&#13;
maintaining international competitiveness. We simply mean to focus on what is&#13;
involved in realizing the potential for competitiveness -- the growth of&#13;
productivity.&#13;
The requirements of infant-industry development are seen differently&#13;
by different people, depending on their focus.    Some economists and policy&#13;
makers conceive of infant industrial activities as being akin to operating an&#13;
espresso machine. As they would have it, all that one needs to enter the&#13;
competitive fray is to buy an espresso machine and to become proficient in&#13;
preparing inputs and running the machine. This conception may be correct for&#13;
some infant activities. But many other infant industrial activities may be&#13;
more akin to running a good restaurant, for which entering the competitive&#13;
fray is much more complex. One not only needs a kitchen with an array of&#13;
equipment, ingredients, and possibilities for what can be produced. One also&#13;
needs an array of recipes for various dishes and the broader training and&#13;
specialization associated with each input and product -- and with their&#13;
interrelations. The difference between operating the espresso machine and&#13;
running the good restaurant is this: the first involves using a machine that&#13;
requires a small number of inputs according to a standard recipe to produce a&#13;
standardized product; the second involves using a variety of equipment in&#13;
combination with a broad array of inputs according to highly variable recipes&#13;
to produce a changing array of products. Corresponding to this difference,&#13;
far more time and effort are needed to achieve proficiency in running a good&#13;
restaurant than in operating an expresso machine.&#13;
Some economists and policy makers would also have it that the&#13;
efficient operation of an infant industrial plant -- whether akin to an&#13;
espresso machine or a restaurant -- is something that comes (solely and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
automatically) from growing experience in operation. Once again, this may be&#13;
so for some industries. But in many instances even getting up to capacity at&#13;
international standards of cost and quality may require various technological&#13;
efforts. And the output from a given plant rarely increases beyond its&#13;
nominally rated capacity without explicit technological efforts. The&#13;
achievement of greater output without commensurate changes in the value of&#13;
physical capital seems almost always to require changes in processes,&#13;
procedures, and organizational arrangements. It often requires changes in&#13;
specifications for inputs and outputs as well. None of these changes can take&#13;
place without the requisite technological capability.&#13;
Maintaining international competitiveness is not merely a matter of&#13;
efficient operation according to original design standards. It is a matter&#13;
both of efficient operation and of developing the capability to keep up with&#13;
ever changing standards in the world. In addition, the efforts needed to&#13;
achieve efficient operation apparently are generally similar to the efforts&#13;
needed to manage technological changes that enable the producer to maintain&#13;
international competitiveness in a changing world.&#13;
2.3. Productivity and capability&#13;
Technological effort by infant industries is not the only possible&#13;
source of growth in their productivity. This fact complicates research on the&#13;
performance of these industries because greater productivity cannot always be&#13;
associated with increased technological capability. Observed changes in&#13;
productivity often include cyclical components related to variations in the&#13;
intensity of factor use due to fluctuations in demand and in the availability&#13;
of intermediate inputs. Secular changes may reflect similar variations: for&#13;
example, firms that overinvest to exploit economies of scale will experience&#13;
increasing productivity as excess capacity falls with the growth of demand.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
But changes in productivity that are unrelated to changes in technological&#13;
capability can be detected by using information at the firm level to uncover&#13;
the sources of productivity change.&#13;
Changes in productivity, if measured at the industry level, may&#13;
reflect structural shifts in the composition of output among firms having&#13;
different productivity, shifts that include the exit of some firms and the&#13;
entry of others. Indeed, separating the sources of productivity growth into&#13;
structural shifts and firm-level changes is an important area for empirical&#13;
investigation (Carlsson 1981). This is particularly so for analyzing the&#13;
effects of policy -- because policies affecting the acquisition of&#13;
technological capability by individual firms can be distinguished from&#13;
policies affecting the exit and entry of firms and the growth of the market&#13;
shares held by the more productive firms.&#13;
But it is important to recognize where the higher productivity of the&#13;
more productive firms comes from. It may come from greater and better&#13;
directed technological effort by the firm to master and adapt the same&#13;
technology that is used by its local competitors. Or a firm's higher&#13;
productivity may come from its having chosen to use more productive elements&#13;
of technology -- "superior" machines, material inputs, or product designs, for&#13;
instance. Serendipity sometimes accounts for the use of "superior"&#13;
elements. But more generally the choice of such elements is the result of a&#13;
search that involves technological effort and must be counted as part of the&#13;
firm's technological capability.&#13;
It also needs to be realized that infant firms may experience cost&#13;
reductions owing to technological efforts undertaken elsewhere. Over time&#13;
they may benefit from "improvements" -- in machines, material inputs, or&#13;
product designs, for example -- sold to them by other firms. Through labor&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
mobility and other means of information diffusion, they may also benefit from&#13;
transfers of technological capabilities initially acquired elsewhere. These&#13;
benefits are externalities resulting from the technological efforts of other&#13;
firms, which may be local or foreign. In a careful estimation of productivity&#13;
change, such externalities -- which would be reflected in figure 1 as downward&#13;
shifts of the cost reduction path ABC -- would show up as abrupt increases in&#13;
the infant's productivity which could not be attributed -- that is, not fully&#13;
-- to its efforts. Whether such externalities produce an increase in the&#13;
infant's international competitiveness depends on the extent of their&#13;
diffusion to foreign competitors who could also benefit from them.&#13;
To assess the full effect of firm-level technological efforts on an&#13;
infant industry's productivity over time requires detailed analysis of&#13;
historical information across firms -- among other things to evaluate&#13;
externalities generated by or transmitted to other local firms whether in the&#13;
same industry or not. With rare exceptions, such information is not available&#13;
for today's less developed countries.-k5    Correspondingly, our survey is&#13;
largely confined to evidence pertaining to individual firms, whose&#13;
technological capabilities are generally considered apart from the activities&#13;
of other firms. Externalities from other firms that benefit the firm, as well&#13;
as those from the firm that benefit other firms, are thus neglected.      This is&#13;
very unfortunate in view of the frequent appeal to externalities as being an&#13;
important, if not the principal, social benefit to be derived from the&#13;
promotion of infant industries.&#13;
15/ Research to uncover and analyze such information is under way at the World&#13;
Bank, in. the project on "Productivity Change in Infant Industry" (Ref. No.&#13;
672-86) under the direction of Mieko Nishimizu and John M. Page, Jr.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
2.4. Outline of what follows&#13;
In the following pages we first examine the evidence about the cost&#13;
and duration of industrial infancy, focusing mainly on the growth of&#13;
productivity. We look next at evidence of the continuity of technological&#13;
change: that is, at the interplay between radical technological change (the&#13;
introduction of a new technology) and incremental technological change (the&#13;
modification of an existing technology). We then speculate about the&#13;
requirements for accumulating the technological capability needed for the&#13;
continuous technological change that characterizes maturity. Far more than&#13;
stemming from experience alone, that capability appears to increase to needed&#13;
levels only through conscious technological effort. We end by summarizing the&#13;
evidence and by assessing the importance of productivity growth in relation to&#13;
other forces that affect international competitiveness -- which prompts us to&#13;
reemphasize the importance of conscious efforts by infants to build up their&#13;
stock of technological resources and to develop strategies for technological&#13;
change.&#13;
3. Evidence about performance&#13;
The general view in the literature on infant industrial activities is that&#13;
only a short period is needed in an optimal environment for enterprises to&#13;
move from low productivity to internationally competitive production. For the&#13;
right industry and the right technique, catching up merely requires overcoming&#13;
initial technical inefficiencies through the straightforward accumulation of&#13;
experience. The essence of this model of maturation is that the required&#13;
increase in productivity is achieved passively, effortlessly, and almost&#13;
automatically. The evidence from our survey suggests a different model, one&#13;
in which maturation is achieved by explicit efforts to manage technological&#13;
change.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
There do not appear to be any readily available, systematic&#13;
compilations of empirical estimates of the cost, benefit, and duration of&#13;
infancy. Nor can such compilations be easily constructed from case studies&#13;
available in the literature or from the mental and physical files of&#13;
institutions that plan, approve, finance, and implement investment projects.&#13;
Several well-known empirical studies have investigated the costs of protection&#13;
in various industrial sectors in developing economies. See, for example,&#13;
Balassa and Associates (1971) and Little, Scitovsky, and Scott (1970);&#13;
numerous similar studies have followed in the wake of these pioneering&#13;
explorations. But almost all these have been cross-sectional studies, which&#13;
only provide information about the distance between ABC and FG at one time.&#13;
Needed is information over time, not just at one time (PQ in figure 1).&#13;
Moreover, these studies are principally concerned with issues of allocative&#13;
efficiency that are considered important from the perspective of the&#13;
conventional paradigm of static comparative advantage. For several reasons,&#13;
then, the studies throw little light on the issues being considered here.&#13;
3.1. Changing productivity&#13;
Most of the reliable information about productivity change in&#13;
developing countries derives from data pertaining to individual firms. Many&#13;
estimates measure single-factor productivity, though some measure the&#13;
productivity of several inputs combined. Nearly all of the latter estimates&#13;
pertain to capital and labor inputs and thus neglect changes in productivity&#13;
associated with changes in intermediate input use. And it is not always clear&#13;
that adequate account is taken of product innovations and changes in output&#13;
composition. Only a few firm-level studies examine productivity trends for&#13;
infant industries over long periods. Moreover, none of the studies surveyed&#13;
reveals anything definite about how far the observed productivity is from&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
internationally competitive levels:   they give information about the slope of&#13;
ABC in figure 1, but not the distance of ABC from FG.&#13;
The data from the studies surveyed show wide variation in rates of&#13;
productivity change (table 1). At one extreme is the Usiminas steel plant in&#13;
Brazil (Dahlman and Fonseca 1978). The plant took four years (1962-66) to&#13;
reach its rated capacity. Then, constrained by the lack of capital for&#13;
expansion, it more than doubled its productivity over the ensuing six years.&#13;
During a subsequent period of capital expansion, productivity continued to&#13;
improve, though more slowly than before. By the end of that expansion,&#13;
sixteen years after the infant's birth, Usiminas appears to have achieved&#13;
international competitiveness. Moreover, it was exporting some of its&#13;
technological adaptations to steel producers in other developing countries.&#13;
At the opposite end of the spectrum represented in table 1 are&#13;
several negative rates of productivity change. Perhaps the most striking of&#13;
these are derived from Mlawa's (1983) study of productivity change in the&#13;
textile industry in Tanzania during 1973-79. A number of the mills had&#13;
declining productivity for both capital and labor over this period, and the&#13;
declines were from levels of productivity already well below those expected of&#13;
the technology involved.&#13;
Between the rapid productivity increase at Usiminas and the examples&#13;
at the other extreme lie cases showing modest rates of productivity growth.&#13;
None of the studies generating this evidence makes comparisons with&#13;
established firms and industries producing similar products. But in one case&#13;
a crude comparison can be made to illustrate two general points: modest&#13;
productivity growth may be insufficient to ensure maturation; even rapid&#13;
productivity growth -- if not sustained -- may also be insufficient. The&#13;
performance of an Argentine rayon plant studied by Katz and others (1978) can&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
Table 1. Productivity Change in Industries in Less Developed Countries&#13;
Average annual percentage change&#13;
of productivity&#13;
Country             Industry         Period    Source     Labor        Capital      Totala&#13;
Brazil        Steel                  1966-77     (1)         14.0         13.0           -&#13;
Argentina     Electrical machinery   1960-68     (2)            -            -        10.6&#13;
Puerto Rico   Garments               1951-61     (3)          9.5            -           -&#13;
Argentina     Metals                 1960-68     (2)            -            -         9.3&#13;
Argentina     Chemicals              1960-68     (2)           -             -         9.1&#13;
India         Steel                  1914-26     (7)         6.0          -0.4           -&#13;
Argentina     Machinery              1960-76     (4)          5.8            -         2.8&#13;
Turkey        Electrical machinery   1963-76     (5)            -            -         5.8&#13;
Turkey        Apparel and footwear   1963-76     (5)            -            -         5.2&#13;
Zambia        Mining                 1954-66     (6)          4.9            -         2.7&#13;
India         General engineering    1951-59     (8)         4.1             -           -&#13;
Argentina     Oil refining           1960-68     (2)            -                      4.1&#13;
Argentina     Textiles               1960-68     (2)            -            -         3.0&#13;
Argentina     Rayon                  1941-67      (9)         2.3            -           -&#13;
India         Nonelectrical&#13;
machinery            1960-65    (11)     2.3/2.7     -1.6/3.3      0.7/1.3&#13;
Turkey        Basic metals           1963-76     (5)            -            -         2.2&#13;
Turkey        Nonmetallic&#13;
mineral products     1963-76     (5)           -             -         1.6&#13;
India         Cotton spinning        1961-69     (8)          1.4            -           -&#13;
India         Cotton weaving         1961-69     (8)          1.0            -           -&#13;
Turkey        Textiles               1963-76     (5)            -            -         0.7&#13;
Brazil        Machinery              1938-79    (10)         0.5             -         0.1&#13;
Turkey        Food                   1963-76     (5)           -             -         0.3&#13;
India         Metal products         1960-65    (11)   -0.8/-0.3       0.1/1.5    -2.1/2.3&#13;
Turkey        Chemicals              1963-76     (5)            -            -        -0.0&#13;
Turkey        Metal products         1963-76     (5)            -            -        -0.1&#13;
Turkey        Wood and cork          1963-76     (5)            -            -        -3.3&#13;
India         Iron and steel         1913-56     (8)        -2.0             -           -&#13;
India         Chemicals              1960-65    (11)    -1.1/3.9    -13.1/-0.1    -2.0/6.0&#13;
India         Electrical machinery   1960-65    (11)    -2.8/0.9     -12.0/9.2    -3.1/4.3&#13;
Tanzania      Cotton spinning        1973-79    (12)   -9.6/-5.5      -6.9/2.3           _&#13;
Notes:  A few of the estimates pertain to individual firms; most pertain to groups of&#13;
firms. In turn, most of the latter estimates are simple averages of firm-specific&#13;
productivity growth rates, but a few are estimates of the growth of aggregate&#13;
productivity. Productivity growth estimates joined by a slash indicate the range of&#13;
estimates for individual firms or subgroups of firms within the respective sectors.&#13;
Estimates from source (5) are for periods of unspecified length greater than five years&#13;
within the overall period 1963-76. Estimates for capital and total productivity from&#13;
source (11) use different measures of capital: in the former case, fixed capital; in the&#13;
latter, total assets.&#13;
Sources: (1) Dahlman and Fonseca (1978); (2) Katz (1973); (3) Reynolds and Gregory&#13;
(1965); (4) Castano, Katz, and Navajas (1981); (5) Krueger and Tuncer (1980); (6) Moody&#13;
and Kessel (1972); (7) Dhar and Seth (1962); (8) Ghosal and Ghosh (1964); (9) Katz and&#13;
others (1978); (10) Da Cruz and Da Silva (1981); (11) Balasubramanyam (1973); (12) Mlawa&#13;
(1983).&#13;
a. Total productivity refers to the productivity of several inputs combined. The&#13;
measures vary between the studies. Most neglect inputs other than capital and labor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
be set against the performance of two very similar Dupont rayon plants in the&#13;
United States studied by Hollander (1965).-L6k/   Because of differences in the&#13;
measurements reported in the two studies, only the roughest comparisons of&#13;
changes in labor productivity are possible.&#13;
Of the comparisons that can be made (over different periods and&#13;
making different adjustments for comparability), nearly all -- and all of the&#13;
more sensible ones -- show considerably greater average rates of labor&#13;
productivity increase in the two plants in the United States than in the&#13;
Argentine plant. Nonetheless, labor productivity in the Argentine plant grew&#13;
at an average annual rate of about 3.6 percent over its life (1937-75). But&#13;
productivity growth, like the underlying technological effort, was not&#13;
continuous. Labor productivity roughly doubled during the first three years&#13;
after start-up and again during 1963-73, but there was almost no productivity&#13;
growth during the interim. Whether the plant was able to achieve&#13;
international cost competitiveness during the initial burst of productivity&#13;
growth is unknown, but it must have suffered progressively deteriorating&#13;
competitiveness through the early 1960s, by which time the Dupont plants had&#13;
been abandoned in the face of continuing technological progress in the&#13;
industrially more advanced countries. Thus the plant could hardly have&#13;
remained competitive even if it had once become so.&#13;
16/ The Argentine plant was owned and operated by a Dupont subsidiary.      Thus&#13;
the comparison also illustrates another point:     foreign-owned firms seem&#13;
to be no more successful (or no less unsuccessful) in accumulating&#13;
technological capability than locally-owned firms. Or, to state the point&#13;
in other words, the technological behavior of infant enterprises appears&#13;
to vary for reasons that are not necessarily related to differences&#13;
between local and foreign ownership.       This is the rationale for our&#13;
neglect of ownership distinctions throughout the text.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
This very rough comparison centers on labor productivity only, but&#13;
productivity change in established industries in industrial economies appears&#13;
to follow a multidirectional path. In such economies, the productivity of a&#13;
wide range of inputs is pushed in different directions and at different rates&#13;
by a welter of different efforts at technological change (Carter 1970).&#13;
Various studies of established industries have examined some of these&#13;
dimensions of productivity growth. Some studies have examined reductions in&#13;
the cost of both labor and materials: these have often found substantial&#13;
savings in the cost of materials, though unit material costs usually fall more&#13;
slowly than unit labor costs.1-7   Other studies have shown increased&#13;
productivity in the use of energy, especially after sharp rises in energy&#13;
prices. Still other studies indicate important increases in productivity that&#13;
originate in changes or modifications in products, though the problem of&#13;
assessing such increases is notoriously difficult.&#13;
There is no basis for assessing the significance of these kinds of&#13;
productivity growth in infant industries. But from several studies that&#13;
describe patterns of technological change without reporting associated&#13;
productivity changes, we have the impression that few of the enterprises&#13;
studied were undertaking multidirectional efforts, manipulating their&#13;
production technology to reduce the cost of capital, labor, energy, and&#13;
materials. If real, this failure would retard the growth of productivity and&#13;
imply the limited evolution of techniques appropriate to conditions in&#13;
developing economies. In turn, the available evidence about changes in&#13;
products precludes even an impression of what typically happens, except in the&#13;
17/ For example, Asher (1956) suggests that each doubling of cumulative output&#13;
in  aircraft  production   tends  to  be  associated   with  materials  cost&#13;
reductions of around 4 to 10 percent, compared with around 15 to 30&#13;
percent for labor costs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
metalworking sector where these kinds of changes appear to be widespread (Katz&#13;
1984).&#13;
We can therefore draw only two reasonably clear conclusions. First,&#13;
productivity growth in infant industries appears to be highly variable, even&#13;
in apparently similar economic conditions. Second, few of the infant&#13;
enterprises studied in less developed economies appear to have demonstrated&#13;
the high and continuous productivity growth needed to achieve and maintain&#13;
international competitiveness.&#13;
3.2. Duration of infancy&#13;
If infant industrial activities experience modest productivity growth&#13;
and if the initial productivity gap is wide, the duration of infancy must be&#13;
long. For example, an infant industry that experiences 5 percent average&#13;
annual productivity growth will require 23 years to achieve maturity if its&#13;
unit costs are initially twice the competitive level and if its mature&#13;
competitors experience 2 percent average annual productivity growth over the&#13;
same period.-!! The literature provides few estimates, however, of the&#13;
duration of infancy in today's less developed countries.&#13;
Some studies -- of manufacturing in Nigeria (Kilby 1969) and of shoe&#13;
production in Puerto Rico (Reynolds and Gregory 1965) -- report relatively&#13;
rapid productivity growth in the first years of operation. The cost&#13;
reductions are consistent with what seem to be common expectations and beliefs&#13;
about the duration of infancy: that it will take about three to five years,&#13;
perhaps stretching to seven or eight. The Indian Tariff Board in the 1920s&#13;
and 1930s usually set the protection of infant industries at five to eight&#13;
18/ The following formula applies:    OT = [ln (OA/OF)I/(g - g').    OT, OA, and&#13;
OF are as defined in reference to figure 1; g and g' respectively denote&#13;
the annual rates of productivity growth in the infant industry and in its&#13;
mature competitors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
years (Government of India Tariff Board 1932). Casual familiarity with views&#13;
elsewhere in more recent years suggests the common belief that similar periods&#13;
are adequate to overcome industrial infancy.    So does some of the current&#13;
literature on trade: for example, Balassa (1975) prescribes that the extra&#13;
protection of infant industries should be lifted after five to eight years.&#13;
There is perhaps a fivefold to tenfold discrepancy between the&#13;
duration of infancy commonly expected and the time that often appears to be&#13;
needed to become internationally competitive. On the basis of fragments in&#13;
the historical literature, it can be said that the cotton textile industry in&#13;
Japan took two to three decades to mature (Smith 1955; Sen 1979); the&#13;
automobile industry in Japan, somewhere between three and six decades,&#13;
depending on when the date of birth is set (Ono and Odaka 1979; Adachi, Ono,&#13;
and Odaka 1981); the textile industry in Korea, about four decades (Mizoguchi&#13;
1981; Mizoguchi and Yamamoto 1981).19/&#13;
Long periods of infancy may in part be explained by a dynamic aspect&#13;
that usually is neglected. Productivity may be growing not only for infant&#13;
enterprises; it may also be growing for mature enterprises in other countries&#13;
where the industry is well established. Industrial maturation may thus&#13;
involve more than becoming competitive at international standards of cost and&#13;
product specifications prevailing in the world market at the time of the&#13;
infant's birth (catching up with a horizontal FG in figure 1). It may and&#13;
19/ These inferences are based on taking the point of maturity as the time at&#13;
which  the industry   begins   to exhibit   sustained export   growth.    This&#13;
approach has the advantage of requiring only trade data that are&#13;
relatively easy to obtain. However, it is not flawless. It may overstate&#13;
the period of infancy; for example, international competitiveness vis-a-&#13;
vis  imports may be achieved without exports.         In turn,   exports give&#13;
evidence of having reached international standards of price and quality,&#13;
but exports do not necessarily imply cost competitiveness; exports may&#13;
benefit differentially from government incentives or they may be priced in&#13;
a discriminatory manner.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
often does involve becoming competitive in relation to standards that are&#13;
changing because of continuing advances in productivity in mature enterprises&#13;
(catching up with a downward-sloping FG in figure 1).2L/&#13;
Evidence is accumulating to suggest that industries in the developed&#13;
countries experience increases in productivity that range between 1 and 3&#13;
percent a year, with the average across industries appearing to be around 2&#13;
percent [see Nishimizu and Robinson (1984), for references]. Roughly half the&#13;
cases summarized in table 1 appear to have experienced productivity growth&#13;
higher than this. Depending on the rate of productivity growth for the same&#13;
industry in the developed countries, these cases may show some maturation --&#13;
though perhaps at widely different rates and with correspondingly differing&#13;
durations of infancy.21/&#13;
For the other firms there may have been no catching up at all. But&#13;
the validity of this inference is questionable because of the lack of&#13;
sufficient comparability -- with respect to measurement methodology and level&#13;
20/ The trend of FG also depends on the trend of the shadow exchange rate,&#13;
which in turn depends on rates of productivity change in other industries,&#13;
both domestically and internationally, and on pricing behavior in relation&#13;
to productivity changes.    Our focus on global productivity trends in the&#13;
same industry neglects productivity changes in other industries and&#13;
assumes -- for an unchanging product -- that the world market for it- is&#13;
competitive, so that productivity changes in other countries are reflected&#13;
inversely in its world price.     Alternatively, one could assume that all&#13;
world prices remain constant, so that productivity changes in other&#13;
domestic industries are reflected inversely in changes in the shadow&#13;
exchange rate -- and so focus on productivity trends in other domestic&#13;
industries.    This alternative   approach is the one Krueger and Tuncer&#13;
(1982) take. A full analysis would have to take all these influences into&#13;
account.&#13;
21/ The inference that some maturation may have occurred is subject to&#13;
qualification because the measures of productivity growth given in table I&#13;
do not necessarily reflect relative scarcities.     The measures use market&#13;
prices rather than shadow prices, so that the productivity growth may&#13;
overstate -- or understate, though this is less likely -- the true rate of&#13;
progress toward international competitiveness.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
of aggregation -- in the estimates being used. Nevertheless, the inference is&#13;
supported by the one reasonably direct comparison that can be made. Recall&#13;
the differences in productivity growth for rayon plants in Argentina and the&#13;
United States. As that comparison illustrates, productivity growth in infant&#13;
industries is not sufficient for maturation. Moreover, product innovations&#13;
and changes in output composition -- not considered in that comparison but&#13;
relevant in some cases -- do not in themselves indicate that maturity is being&#13;
achieved, since product change is a central focus of technological efforts in&#13;
corresponding industries in the industrial economies. In sum, for a newly&#13;
established industry that begins without international competitiveness,&#13;
maturity is impossible without productivity growth that is faster paced than&#13;
that in countries where the industry is already internationally competitive.&#13;
This fact may be obvious, but it appears frequently to be forgotten.&#13;
Other information about past industrial performance gives further&#13;
indirect evidence about the duration of infancy. The rapid industrialization&#13;
and diversified export achievements of such newly industrializing countries as&#13;
Brazil and Korea imply that infants can mature rapidly. But the implication&#13;
deserves scrutiny. Information obtained in the research underlying Westphal,&#13;
Rhee, and Pursell (1981) shows that maturation periods for Korean industries&#13;
can be as long as four decades (as for textiles, see above) or as short as a&#13;
year or two (as for shipbuilding). At best, there are only ill-informed&#13;
speculations to explain the differences across industries in Korea. There&#13;
appears to have been a trend toward shorter maturation periods for Korean&#13;
infants, but it again is sheer speculation whether the apparent trend is due&#13;
to the general broadening and deepening of Korea's industrial base or to other&#13;
factors, such as continuing changes in the policy regime.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
Even if the experience of the very rapidly industrializing countries&#13;
demonstrates that the duration of infancy can be brief, the fact remains that&#13;
the industrial performance of most developing countries falls far short of&#13;
that of countries like Brazil and Korea. This implies that for many&#13;
industries in most developing countries the duration of infancy has been long&#13;
-- with many industries started quite some time ago still remaining in their&#13;
infancy.22/ Ill-advised policies for selecting the infants to be .promoted and&#13;
for nurturing their development undoubtedly share part of the blame. The&#13;
firm-level evidence does not address this issue; instead, it deals extensively&#13;
with another side of infant-industry maturation, a side we now turn to.&#13;
4. Maturation of firms&#13;
Technological progress at the global frontier in industry is often conceived&#13;
as comprising (a) radical innovations and (b) subsequent adaptations of those&#13;
23/&#13;
innovations.L- From the evidence it seems that the firm-level absorption of&#13;
technology for infant industrial activities, making modifications and&#13;
adaptations in the process, is not unlike the adaptation process that follows&#13;
innovations at the global frontier (Dahlman and Westphal 1982). At least&#13;
there is persuasive evidence that absorption and improvement involve&#13;
technological effort. They require the implementation of specific&#13;
technological changes (in the broad sense used in this paper) and the use of&#13;
particular kinds of resources to accomplish them. In this respect the&#13;
technological effort needed to master a technology is difficult to distinguish&#13;
from that associated with managing technological change more generally. Below&#13;
22/ For direct evidence about Turkish infants -- albeit on a different but&#13;
complementary criterion (see note 20) -- see Krueger and Tuncer (1982).&#13;
23/ For the classic and influential study organized around this distinction&#13;
between original innovation and subsequent adaptation of new processes,&#13;
see Enos (1962).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
we examine the significance and nature of both the stimuli which seem to&#13;
prompt change in infant enterprises and the resources which are used to&#13;
respond to those stimuli.&#13;
4.1.  Stimuli for technological change 24/&#13;
Technological change in infant industries is often a specific&#13;
response to stimuli that impinge on firms from product markets and from input&#13;
markets. For example, a Korean polyethylene plant (Seoul National University&#13;
1980), stimulated by higher energy prices, introduced a sequence of process&#13;
adaptations that reduced unit energy use 18 percent over three years. Most&#13;
cases suggest that stimuli in input markets, unless dramatic, may need to be&#13;
matched by pressure in product markets to induce efforts at technological&#13;
change.  For example, the Argentine rayon plant, after fifteen years of little&#13;
productivity increase, suddenly boosted its labor productivity, changed&#13;
product quality, substituted material inputs, and increased efficiency in the&#13;
use of materials (Katz and others 1978). Why? To defend its market share,&#13;
which began to erode after two new producers entered its previously secure and&#13;
growing market and as nylon began to challenge rayon.&#13;
What seems usual is that the response is a one-time effort that flags&#13;
after pressure eases in product and input markets. Rare is the formulation of&#13;
a conscious strategy for technological change: for example, a strategy that&#13;
enables responding to a third kind of stimuli -- one that emanates from&#13;
systematically monitoring the performance of the technology in use. The&#13;
24/ See Katz (1984) and Teitel (1984) for more comprehensive reviews of what&#13;
is known about stimuli for technological change.          In addition to the&#13;
stimuli discussed here, they also consider other factors which might be&#13;
thought to affect the predispositon of firms to engage in technological&#13;
change activities, including the size and ownership of the firm, the scale&#13;
of the domestic industry, and the characteristics of the industry's&#13;
technology.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
Acindar steel company in Argentina was saddled with a plant at Rosario that&#13;
was losing money at its current capacity and was constrained from undertaking&#13;
major investments by the government's licensing authorities. This situation&#13;
led to technological efforts to overcome bottlenecks and production problems&#13;
and to exploit perceived opportunities for engineering improvements (Maxwell&#13;
1982). In essence, monitoring the production system enabled the&#13;
identification and breaking of bottlenecks, which led to the identification&#13;
and breaking of other bottlenecks.-?5/ The company embarked on this path of&#13;
technological change to reduce its losses, but the sequence of changes was in&#13;
large part determined by the characteristics of the plant's technology. Thus&#13;
the monitoring of the technology in use is what provided the proximate&#13;
stimulus for the successive changes.&#13;
Because of its inherently dynamic nature, performance monitoring&#13;
moves beyond simple responses to external stimuli, but it can still fall short&#13;
of being a fully effective strategy for technological change. The Rosario&#13;
plant had a strategy, but it was only for sequential bottleneck-breaking --&#13;
through its own efforts and based on its technology already in use. What&#13;
often is needed for an effective strategy is to search outside the firm. In&#13;
the face of a situation similar to that at Rosario, the managers of the&#13;
Usiminas steel plant in Brazil adopted a conscious strategy to reduce costs&#13;
and increase capacity without major investment. They did this by&#13;
25/ One should not be misled by our use of a simple rubric, "monitoring," into&#13;
thinking that what is involved is either passive or a single activity.&#13;
Quite the contrary, the systematic monitoring of performance requires&#13;
active technological efforts in various directions: to design performance&#13;
indicators for elements of the production system; to determine feasible&#13;
targets for improving the performance of each; to devise and implement the&#13;
changes that could be expected to achieve these targets; to monitor&#13;
subsequent performance to check progress toward the targets and to revise&#13;
the targets on the basis of the experience gained; and from there to&#13;
devise further changes, and so on.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
experimenting with modifications of products and processes (Dahlman and&#13;
Fonseca 1978). But what distinguishes their strategy is that the&#13;
modifications came not only from experience, but from a worldwide search for&#13;
steel technology -- with some modifications requiring investments in&#13;
licensing, consulting services, and specialized equipment (Maxwell 1982, ch.&#13;
6). The Rosario and Usiminas plants both greatly improved their performance,&#13;
but Usiminas went on to become a technological leader in the Latin American&#13;
steel industry.&#13;
So, some firms have a strategy, but most apparently do not. The&#13;
pressure to pursue some form of change seems generally to be necessary, but&#13;
the response to pressure seems to be variable and to depend on the stimuli and&#13;
on the firm. In most of the cases studied, the external stimulus evoked only&#13;
a transitory response. It seems merely to have temporarily jolted enterprises&#13;
from prevailing patterns of low or nonexistent activity for change. Effort at&#13;
technological change was thus a defensive reaction to periodic threats, not an&#13;
offensive activity driven by a conscious strategy, except in the few firms&#13;
that had such a strategy. Conscious strategies may involve changes in&#13;
products as well as changes in processes. (In fact, changes of one kind&#13;
typically require changes of the other kind.) We focus on process changes&#13;
because they are better documented in the literature surveyed. But there are&#13;
a few cases of enterprises that appear to have had strategies for product&#13;
improvement -- for example, strategies based on monitoring feedback from&#13;
customers about product performance. A conscious strategy for changes in&#13;
processes and products, augmented by responses to intermittent stimuli, is&#13;
what generally distinguishes successful firms in established industries from&#13;
infants in the less developing countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
4.2. Resources for technological change&#13;
Detailed empirical studies suggest that technological change arises&#13;
from the explicit allocation of resources to innovative activities that&#13;
produce technological change -- to the specialized activities of seeking,&#13;
defining, and implementing major and minor changes.&#13;
Consider again the experience at Usiminas, where the introduction of&#13;
a standard cost system was a driving force for technological change (Dahlman&#13;
and Fonseca 1978). The flow of performance feedback pointed to problems&#13;
around which the firm could focus its resources on an effort to define and&#13;
implement change. Regular monitoring of the system's performance thus&#13;
provided a basis for understanding how and why performance varied. Such&#13;
monitoring can generate "understanding of why certain things work and others&#13;
not," which Nelson (1979) suggests cannot be acquired through other means. It&#13;
can thus help in the effort to identify the adaptations, improvements, and&#13;
incremental changes that can be made. But an industrial plant can run for&#13;
years without generating any of this understanding. Nor is this flow of&#13;
information a function of time or cumulative output. Instead, it depends on&#13;
the allocation of resources to an effort that can generate, interpret, and act&#13;
upon that flow.&#13;
This example and others suggest that sustained productivity growth&#13;
has its roots in a demand for technological change that (i) originates in the&#13;
firm and (ii) has to be specified in operational terms by the firm. As a&#13;
consequence, sustained productivity growth is unlikely without the&#13;
specialization of some of the firm's resources on technological effort. But&#13;
in many of the infants studied, the efforts at technological change were&#13;
accomplished by temporarily assigning to them resources that were ordinarily&#13;
allocated to production activities. This finding reinforces other indications&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
of the general lack of strategies for technological change and of the&#13;
likelihood that change is limited to intermittent responses to external&#13;
stimuli.&#13;
But in some case histories the firm's growth was accompanied by an&#13;
increasing specialization of resources in the firm. Individuals, groups, and&#13;
items of physical capital become allocated more or less continuously to the&#13;
efforts at change. When that happens, the incidence of technological change&#13;
becomes correspondingly more continuous and autonomously driven from within&#13;
the firm, rather than being intermittent and driven only by pressing external&#13;
stimuli. How this increasing specialization in the firm interacts with the&#13;
creation of a strategy is likely to depend in part on the scale of the&#13;
enterprise. In consequence, the improved performance of infant firms that is&#13;
observed to accompany their growth may in part be traced to the increased&#13;
specialization of the firm's resources for change.&#13;
This emphasis on the firm as the focal point for technological effort&#13;
obviously does not mean that outside resources play only a minor role in&#13;
accomplishing technological changes. On the contrary, machinery suppliers,&#13;
outside consultants, input suppliers, and customers are all noted as supplying&#13;
important technological elements. But the integration of these elements with&#13;
the structure of the firm's existing systems requires complementary adjustment&#13;
and change by resources in the firm. The firm thus has the central role in&#13;
the management of technological change. At the very least, it must recognize&#13;
the potential value of changes and absorb them. Doing this requires managing&#13;
its own resources for change. In sum, not everything is done in the firm, but&#13;
very little can be done for the firm without its efforts in absorbing, if not&#13;
initiating, and managing change.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
5. Accumulating technological capability&#13;
The central point is thus that infant enterprises cannot mature unless they&#13;
accumulate the capability for technological change. The process of&#13;
accumulating that capability is commonly described as learning, but what this&#13;
learning involves is not clear.    The term has often been used merely to refer&#13;
to what is inferred to underlie rising productivity. Thus, a path of falling&#13;
unit costs, with an apparently unchanging production system, is often simply&#13;
described as the result of learning. The term has also been used to refer&#13;
generally to the acquisition of increased skill and knowledge by people,&#13;
enterprises, and even economies -- regardless of how that skill and knowledge&#13;
are obtained. And "learning" has been used to refer to the feedback of&#13;
information about industrial production: production in one period generates a&#13;
flow of information and understanding that allows improvements in a subsequent&#13;
period. But as we have argued, that flow does not take place without a&#13;
conscious effort to monitor performance. The learning from such flows of&#13;
information thus is not effortless; nor is it without cost. Costless&#13;
learning-by-doing thus has limited relevance for the accumulation of&#13;
technological capability.&#13;
How far can infant firms progress along the path of maturation by&#13;
relying on the technological capability they acquire from monitoring&#13;
performance? Probably not very far. Recall the difference between the&#13;
Rosario plant, which stayed within the confines of its technology and&#13;
operations, and Usiminas, which went beyond those confines by purchasing&#13;
information and specialized equipment. A priori reasoning, and some evidence,&#13;
suggests that continuing progress along the path of infant maturation requires&#13;
explicit investment in technological capability -- that is, in human and&#13;
(firm-specific) institutional capital.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
Training is a driving force for technological change -- if it is&#13;
active, explicit, and directed to more than routine plant operations. Case&#13;
studies of Korean firms (Seoul National University 1980) show that although&#13;
various kinds of experience in production played some role in augmenting the&#13;
technological capability of firms, the effort to undertake explicit training&#13;
probably was much more significant. This effort created much of the&#13;
capability needed to exploit what were only potential opportunities for&#13;
learning, such as taking part in the technological aspects of investment&#13;
projects or executing subsequent minor changes. But at a steel galvanizing&#13;
plant in Thailand, where little training was undertaken to do more than impart&#13;
basic operating skills, there was little technological change over nine years&#13;
(Bell, Scott-Kemmis, and Satyarakwit 1982). The same was true of textile&#13;
producers in Tanzania (Mlawa 1983).&#13;
Hiring technically skilled specialists is also important in&#13;
accumulating the human capital needed for technological change. And it often&#13;
is simpler than training, if trained people can be hired. For example,&#13;
activities for technological change at the previously mentioned rayon plant in&#13;
Argentina were associated with distinct peaks in spending on technicians and&#13;
engineering staff (Katz and others 1978). Such hiring also appears to have&#13;
been important for several machinery producers in Brazil and Argentina (Da&#13;
Cruz 1980; Da Cruz and Da Silva 1981; Castano, Katz, and Navajas 1981), as&#13;
well as for those in Korea (Seoul National University 1980).&#13;
The formation of human and institutional capital is thus important&#13;
for continuing progress along the path of maturation. It is especially&#13;
important when encountering discontinuities in that path. The reason is that&#13;
operating experience in one area of technology -- however intensive and&#13;
prolonged -- is unlikely to provide the full capability needed for changing to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
and absorbing another technology. And doing one technological task is&#13;
unlikely to contribute much to the specific capability for carrying out other,&#13;
different tasks. Thus, despite the evident importance of experience in some&#13;
phases, maturation may grind to a halt if the technological effort is limited&#13;
to the technology in use and to adapting it through localized changes.&#13;
The discontinuities in the path of technological change seem to take&#13;
two forms. First, maturation may involve shifting between different tasks in&#13;
relation to a given general type of technology. For example, product-centered&#13;
technological change may move through successive phases based on replicative&#13;
copying, the specification of minor improvements and modifications, formalized&#13;
overall redesign, and innovation through R &amp; D. Similarly, cost-reducing&#13;
change may require the successive mastery of different kinds of technological&#13;
tasks -- production scheduling versus quality control, for example -- even&#13;
though the general type of technology remains the same.h-L Second, maturation&#13;
periodically requires firms to shift to different types of technology. At&#13;
these points, continuing competitive performance requires the use or&#13;
production of substantially different processes or products -- often much more&#13;
complex or sophisticated -- that embody technological knowledge substantially&#13;
different from that embodied in existing processes and products.&#13;
Several firm-level studies have shown the persistence of various&#13;
kinds of incremental technological change after the start-up of new industrial&#13;
facilities. But the rate of productivity increase for a given technology&#13;
seems to fall over time. Crossing major discontinuities in the path of infant&#13;
maturation is important because the associated investment in new technology&#13;
26/ Recent studies have elaborated such stages of technological evolution in&#13;
developing  economies.    Progression  through those stages    is variously&#13;
described as learning or as being due to learning. See, for example, Lall&#13;
(1980).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
often opens opportunities that substantially increase the returns to&#13;
incremental changes. Indeed, in the technologically capable firms, the&#13;
sequential adaptations that follow an investment in a new technology seem&#13;
typically to have a cumulative impact in changing productivity that exceeds&#13;
the immediate change from the investment.&#13;
A striking feature of the historical record, then, is that firms --&#13;
if they are to progress along the path of maturation -- must go beyond the&#13;
experience accumulated in production. Experience in production, if monitored,&#13;
is one mechanism for augmenting the capability of infant enterprises for&#13;
change. It appears to be the dominant mechanism in some phases of change&#13;
between major discontinuities. But it does not seem to be sufficient to&#13;
achieve and maintain international competitiveness. Crucially important for&#13;
crossing technological discontinuities is investment in technological&#13;
capability -- especially in the human and institutional capital needed to&#13;
initiate, absorb, and manage technological change. Indeed, as a study of the&#13;
Taiwan machine-tool industry suggests, exclusive dependence on experience in&#13;
production may retard the progressive development of an industry (Amsden&#13;
1977). Major discontinuities may sometimes be crossed only by the takeover of&#13;
existing enterprises by a younger generation of entrepreneurs who introduce&#13;
new technological strategies -- or by the entry of new firms that introduce&#13;
new technologies to the industry.&#13;
6. Conclusion&#13;
There is little evidence about productivity growth among infant industries in&#13;
today's less developed countries. But the evidence does suggest that many&#13;
infant firms have failed to reach international competitiveness -- or if they&#13;
have once reached it, have failed to maintain it. This inference is&#13;
consistent with the record of overall industrial performance in these&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
countries. It is also consistent with findings from various studies of the&#13;
costs of protection in developing countries.&#13;
In looking for causes of the failure, we have emphasized the lack of&#13;
technological capability. The case studies convey a pervasive impression that&#13;
explicit investment in technological capability often is a faltering,&#13;
intermittent, and low priority use of resources. Although all enterprises can&#13;
take advantage of a vast body of existing technology, maturity depends on the&#13;
ability to use this technology effectively. The evidence shows that&#13;
maturation is not automatic or instant: reaching and maintaining&#13;
international competitiveness is not simply a matter of developing the right&#13;
industry or industries, given the existing (aggregate) relative factor&#13;
endowment. It takes more than effortless learning-by-doing and requires the&#13;
capability to manage continuous technological change. Maturation takes&#13;
conscious efforts to develop a technological strategy, to invest in resources&#13;
for technological changes, and progressively to accumulate technological&#13;
capability.&#13;
The apparent failure of many infant industries to attain&#13;
international competitiveness may be due to any of several causes. The one&#13;
that has probably received the most attention in previous discussions is the&#13;
promotion of the wrong infant industries by governments, whether through&#13;
explicit selection or through the implicit effects of trade and other policies&#13;
that differ in their combined incidence on incentives across industries. Thus&#13;
it is argued that governments have promoted infant industries that are not in&#13;
line with relative factor endowments and that therefore lack the potential for&#13;
international competitiveness. The promotion of the wrong infants has&#13;
undoubtedly been an important causal factor, though its precise significance&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
is at issue (Westphal 1982). But given that these industries have been&#13;
promoted, what is of at least equal concern is the evidence that many firms in&#13;
these industries have failed to exert needed technological efforts and have&#13;
thus failed to realize the beneficial productivity gains possible. Perhaps of&#13;
even more concern, the same can apparently be said about firms in infant&#13;
industries, that do have the potential for international competitiveness on&#13;
factor intensity grounds.&#13;
Another possible cause of the apparent failure to attain&#13;
international competitiveness has also received much attention: the choice of&#13;
production methods not in line with relative factor endowments (White 1978).&#13;
Production would be internationally competitive given the choice of technique&#13;
that minimizes cost, but it is not competitive because of the choice of&#13;
suboptimal techniques that lead to permanently higher production costs.&#13;
Inappropriate techniques may be chosen because governments pursue policies&#13;
that distort relative input prices, or because producers lack complete&#13;
technological information or have objectives other than cost-minimization.&#13;
Suboptimal choices of technique have no doubt been an important causal factor&#13;
in some settings, but they cannot explain slow or nonexistent productivity&#13;
growth. Moreover, there is evidence in some settings that the increased costs&#13;
associated with the choice of suboptimal techniques are much less than the&#13;
increased costs associated with the failure to achieve best-practice levels of&#13;
productivity (Page 1980).&#13;
Ill-advised government policies that contribute to the failure to&#13;
achieve international competitiveness can take many forms and have ultimate&#13;
effects on productivity that go beyond those of having selected the wrong&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
industries and production methods.1--   In their ultimate effects, such&#13;
policies may interfere with achieving potential levels of productivity, as is&#13;
often the case with badly designed and implemented administrative controls&#13;
that limit capacity utilization. Alternatively, they may inhibit&#13;
technological effort and thus slow the growth of productivity. Or they may&#13;
retard the relative growth of firms having higher productivity or faster&#13;
productivity growth. Such policy effects have been uncovered even in rapidly&#13;
industrializing countries, such as Korea (Rhee and Westphal 1977). In turn,&#13;
policies affecting the inducements that condition the nature of technological&#13;
efforts may lead to efforts in the wrong direction.-LY    Where technological&#13;
changes have occurred, they have not always increased productivity at prices&#13;
that would properly reflect relative scarcities, even if they have increased&#13;
productivity at existing market prices and conditions (Teitel 1981).&#13;
Governments can also be at fault for not formulating or effectively&#13;
implementing policies to overcome market failures that may constrain the&#13;
development of infant industries. Particularly important in relation to the&#13;
growth of productivity are externalities involving transfers of technological&#13;
capabilities across firms through various means of information diffusion.&#13;
These externalities may lead firms to allocate too few resources to&#13;
27/ Nishimizu and Robinson (1984) present and discuss evidence about possible&#13;
differences between outward-looking and inward-looking strategies of&#13;
industrialization in their effects on productivity growth at the sector-&#13;
level. Pack (1984) evaluates the productivity of Philippine textile firms&#13;
in comparison with international norms.     In looking for sources of their&#13;
low productivity, he examines the importance of firm-level technological&#13;
capability in relation to policy-related macro and sectoral influences.&#13;
28/ By drawing attention to the need for technological effort, we clearly have&#13;
not meant to imply that all technological effort is equally valuable or&#13;
that technological effort is its own reward. Such an interpretation would&#13;
not   be  consistent   with   our   continued  emphasis   on   international&#13;
competitiveness as the measure of maturity.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
technological efforts -- for example, to underinvest in acquiring&#13;
technological capability through labor training. In fact, the low priority&#13;
that many infant enterprises apparently give to investments in technological&#13;
capability suggests that externalities do precisely that. In turn, the lack&#13;
of international competitiveness implies -- to the degree it is due to&#13;
inadequate technological capability -- that these externalities are not being&#13;
adequately offset by policies specifically designed to address them.&#13;
Governments have often instituted policies that are ill-advised and&#13;
failed to institute policies that are well-advised in relation to fostering&#13;
rapid and efficient maturation. But the effects of different policies acting&#13;
in combination with each other -- and with other social, political, and&#13;
economic factors in the environment -- are far from well enough understood to&#13;
enable unarguable recommendations for optimal policy packages designed to&#13;
foster rapid and efficient maturation. We do know that infants can mature.&#13;
Moreover, the experience in some rapidly industrializing countries suggests&#13;
that they can even mature very quickly.    But reflecting our general ignorance&#13;
of the maturation process, there is little general agreement on the factors&#13;
ultimately responsible for the rapid maturation in these countries. Finding&#13;
out more about these factors, and how they operate on firms, is urgent&#13;
business -- particularly if our conclusion about the slow maturation of most&#13;
infants in most developing countries is correct. Of equal importance is&#13;
finding out why some firms perform well -- whatever the environment -- while&#13;
others do not.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
References&#13;
Adachi, Fumihiko, Keinosuke Ono, and Konosuke Odaka, 1981, Ancillary Firm&#13;
Development in the Japanese Automobile Industry -- Selected Case Studies&#13;
(II), Discussion paper series no. 42, Processed (Institute of Economic&#13;
Research, Hitotsubashi University, Tokyo).&#13;
Amsden, Alice H., 1977, The Division of Labour is Limited by the Type of&#13;
Market: the Case of Taiwanese Machine Tool Industry, World Development 5,&#13;
217-233.&#13;
Asher, Harold, 1956, Cost-Quantity Relationships in the Airframe Industry (The&#13;
Rand Corporation, Santa Monica, California).&#13;
Balassa, Bela and Associates, 1971, The Structure of Protection in Developing&#13;
Countries (Johns Hopkins Press, Baltimore and London).&#13;
Balassa, Bela, 1975, Reforming the System of Incentives in Developing&#13;
Countries, World Development 3, 365-382.&#13;
Balasubramanyam, V. N., 1973, International Transfer of Technology to India&#13;
(Praeger, New York).&#13;
Bell, R. Martin, (forthcoming), Technological Change in Infant Industries: A&#13;
Review of the Evidence, (World Bank, Washington, D.C.).&#13;
Bell, Martin, Don Scott-Kemmis, and Wit Satyarakwit, 1982, Limited Learning in&#13;
Infant Industry: A Case Study, in: Frances Stewart and Jeffrey James,&#13;
eds., The Economics of New Technology in Developing Countries (Frances&#13;
Pinter Limited, London) 138-156.&#13;
Bruno, Michael, 1972, Domestic Resource Costs and Effective Protection:&#13;
Clarification and Synthesis, Journal of Political Economy 80, 16-33.&#13;
Carlsson, Bo, 1981, The Content of Productivity Growth in Swedish&#13;
Manufacturing, Research Policy 10, 336-354.&#13;
Carter, Anne P., 1970, Structural Change in the American Economy (Harvard&#13;
University Press, Cambridge, Mass).&#13;
Castano, Angel, Jorge Katz, and Fernando Navajas, 1981, Etapas Historicas y&#13;
Conductas Tecnologicas en una Planta Argentina de Maquinas Herraminenta,&#13;
IDB/ECLA/UNDP/IDRC Research Program on Scientific and Technological&#13;
Development in Latin America [hereafter: Research Program] Working Paper&#13;
no. 38 (Economic Commission for Latin America, Buenos Aires).&#13;
Corden, W. M., 1974, Trade Policy and Economic Welfare (Clarendon Press,&#13;
Oxford).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
Da Cruz, Helio Nogueira, 1980, Mudanca Tecnologica no Seto Metal Mecanico: Um&#13;
Estudo de Caso de Maquinas para Processar Cereais, Research Program,&#13;
Processed (Fundacao Instituto de Perquisas Economicas, Sao Paulo).&#13;
Da Cruz, Helio Nogueira and Marcos Engino Da Silva, 1981, Mundanca Tecnologica&#13;
no Setor Metal Mecanico: Relatocio Parcia, Parte II, Research Program,&#13;
Processed (Fundacao Instituto de Perquisas Economicas, Sao Paulo).&#13;
Dahlman, Carl J. and Fernando Fonseca, 1978, From Technological Dependence to&#13;
Technological Development: The Case of USIMINAS Steel Plant in Brazil,&#13;
Research Program Working Paper no. 21 (Economic Commission for Latin&#13;
America, Buenos Aires).&#13;
Dahlman, Carl and Larry E. Westphal, 1982, Technological Effort in Industrial&#13;
Development -- an Interpretative Survey of Recent Research, in: Frances&#13;
Stewart and Jeffrey James, eds., The Economics of New Technology in&#13;
Developing Countries (Westview Press, Boulder, Colo.) 105-137.&#13;
Dhar, P. N. and Om Kar Seth, 1962, The Rate of Technical Progress in the Tata&#13;
Iron and Steel Company in 1913-56, Indian Economic Review VI, 1-19.&#13;
Enos, John, 1962, Invention and Innovation in the Petroleum Refining Industry,&#13;
in: National Bureau of Economic Research, The Rate and Direction of&#13;
Inventive Activity: Economic and Social Factors (Princeton University&#13;
Press, Princeton, N.J.) xxx-xxx.&#13;
Ghosal, A. and S. N. Ghosh, 1964, A Study of Productivity in Important&#13;
Industries in India, Productivity Measurement Review 38, 23-37.&#13;
Government of India Tariff Board, 1932, Report of the Indian Tariff Board on&#13;
the Glass Industry (Calcutta).&#13;
Hollander, Samuel, 1965, The Sources of Increased Efficiency:    A Study of Du&#13;
Pont Rayon Plants (The MIT Press, Cambridge, Mass.).&#13;
Katz, Jorge, 1973, Industrial Growth, Royalty Payments and Local Expenditure&#13;
on Research and Development, in: Victor Urquidi and Rosemary Thorp, eds.,&#13;
Latin America in the International Economy (Macmillan, London) 197-224.&#13;
Katz, Jorge and others, 1978, Productivity, Technology and Domestic Efforts in&#13;
Research and Development (the Growth Path of a Rayon Plant), Research&#13;
Program Working Paper no. 14 (Economic Commission for Latin America,&#13;
Buenos Aires).&#13;
Katz, Jorge, 1984, Domestic Technological Innovations and Dynamic Comparative&#13;
Advantage: Further Reflections on a Comparative Case-Study Program,&#13;
Journal of Development Economics (forthcoming).&#13;
Kilby, Peter, 1969, Industrialization in an Open Economy: Nigeria 1945-1966&#13;
(Cambridge University Press, London).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
Krueger, Anne 0. and Baran Tuncer, 1980, Microeconomic Aspects of Productivity&#13;
Growth Under Import Substitution: Turkey, National Bureau of Economic&#13;
Research Working Paper Series no. 532 (National Bureau of Economic&#13;
Research, Cambridge, Mass.).&#13;
Krueger, Anne 0. and Baran Tuncer, 1982, An Empirical Test of the Infant&#13;
Industry Argument, American Economic Review 72, 1142-52.&#13;
Lall, Sanjaya, 1980, Developing Countries as Exporters of Industrial&#13;
Technology, Research Policy 9, 24-52.&#13;
Little, Ian, Tibor Scitovsky, and Maurice Scott, 1970, Industry and Trade in&#13;
Some Developing Countries: A Comparative Study (Oxford University Press,&#13;
London).&#13;
Maxwell, Philip, 1982, Steelplant Technological Development in Latin America,&#13;
Research Program Working Paper no. 55 (Economic Commission for Latin&#13;
America, Buenos Aires).&#13;
Mizoguchi, T., 1981, Economic Growth of Korea Under the Japanese Occupation --&#13;
Background of Industrialization of Korea, 1911-1940, in: Mataji Umemura&#13;
and Toshiyuki Mizoguchi, eds., Quantitative Studies on Economic History of&#13;
Japan Empire, 1890-1940, Processed (Institute of Economic Research,&#13;
Hitotsubashi University, Tokyo).&#13;
Mizoguchi, T. and Y. Yamamoto, 1981, Colonial Investments of Japan Empire, in:&#13;
Mataji Umemura and Toshiyuki Mizoguchi, eds., Quantitative Studies on&#13;
Economic History of Japan Empire, 1890-1940, Processed (Institute of&#13;
Economic Research, Hitotsubashi University, Tokyo).&#13;
Moody, C. E., Jr. and Norman Kessel, 1972, Productivity Change in Zambian&#13;
Mining, The South African Journal of Economics 40, 61-69.&#13;
Mlawa, Hasa Mfaume, 1983, The Acquisition of Technology, Technological&#13;
Capability and Technical Change: A Study of the Textile Industry in&#13;
Tanzania, Unpublished Ph.D. Dissertation (University of Sussex).&#13;
Nelson, Richard, 1979, Innovation and Economic Development: Theoretical&#13;
Retrospect and Prospect, Research Program Working Paper no. 31 (Economic&#13;
Commission for Latin America, Buenos Aires).&#13;
Nishimizu, Mieko and Sherman Robinson, 1984, Trade Policies and Productivity&#13;
Change in Semi-Industrialized Countries, Journal of Development Economics&#13;
(forthcoming).&#13;
Ono, Keinosuke and Konosuke Odaka, 1979, Ancillary Firm Development in the&#13;
Japanese Automobile Industry - Selected Case Studies (I), Discussion&#13;
Paper Series no. 24, Processed (Institute of Economic Research,&#13;
Hitotsubashi University, Tokyo).&#13;
Pack, Howard, 1984, Productivity and Technical Choice: Applications to the&#13;
Textile Industry, Journal of Development Economics (forthcoming).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
Page, John M., Jr., 1980, Technical Efficiency and Economic Performance: Some&#13;
Evidence from Ghana, Oxford Economic Papers (New Series) 32, 319-339.&#13;
Reynolds, Lloyd G. and Peter Gregory, 1965, Wages, Productivity, and&#13;
Industrialization in Puerto Rico (Richard D. Irwin Inc., Homewood,&#13;
Illinois).&#13;
Rhee, Yung W. and Larry E. Westphal, 1977, A Micro, Econometric Investigation&#13;
of Choice of Technology, Journal of Development Economics 4, 205-237.&#13;
Sen, Asim, 1979, The Role of Technological Change in Economic Development:&#13;
The Lessons of Japan for Presently Developing Countries, Unpublished Ph.D.&#13;
Dissertation (Rutgers University, New Brunswick, N.J.).&#13;
Seoul National University, 1980, The Absorption and Diffusion of Imported&#13;
Technology in Korea, Draft (Institute of Economic Research, Seoul National&#13;
University, Seoul, Korea).&#13;
Smith, Thomas C., 1955, Political Change and Industrial Development in&#13;
Japan: Government Enterprise, 1868-1880 (Stanford University Press,&#13;
Stanford).&#13;
Teitel, Simon, 1981, Towards an Understanding of Technical Change in Semi-&#13;
Industrial Countries, Research Policy 10, 127-147.&#13;
Teitel, Simon, 1984, Technology Creation in Semi-Industrial Economies, Journal&#13;
of Development Economics (forthcoming).&#13;
Westphal, Larry E., Yung W. Rhee, and Garry Pursell, 1981, Korean Industrial&#13;
Competence: Where It Came From, World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 469&#13;
(World Bank, Washington, D.C.).&#13;
Westphal, Larry E., 1982, Fostering Technological Mastery by Means of&#13;
Selective Infant-Industry Protection, in: Moshe Syrquin and Simon Teitel,&#13;
eds., Trade, Stability, Technology, and Equity in Latin America (Academic&#13;
Press, New York) 255-279.&#13;
White, Lawrence J., 1978, The Evidence on Appropriate Factor Proportions for&#13;
Manufacturing in Less Developed Countries: A Survey, Economic Development&#13;
and Cultural Change 27, 27-60.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
World       Bank                       The Construction Industry:             Employment and Development&#13;
Issues and Strategies in               of Small Enterprises&#13;
Publications                          Developing Countries                    David L. Gordon, coordinating&#13;
of Related                             Ernesto E. Henriod, coordinating       author&#13;
author                                 Examines the potential role of the&#13;
Interest                              Presents a profile of the construction  World Bank in encouraging developing&#13;
industry. Points out that construction  countries to assist small enterprises&#13;
work represents 3 to 8 percent of the  and suggests that efficient substitution&#13;
gross domestic product of developing   of labor for capital is possible in a&#13;
countries. Fostering a domestic capa-  broad spectrum of small-scale manu-&#13;
bility in construction, therefore, is im-  facturing and other activities that are&#13;
A Brief Review of the World            portant. Discusses problems and con-   able to absorb a rapidly growing labor&#13;
Lube Oils Industry                     straints of the industry and formulates  force.&#13;
A. Ceyhan, H. Kohli, L.                strategies for future actions. Draws   Sector Policy Paper. 1978. 93 pages (in-&#13;
Wijetilleke and B.R. Choudhury         heavily from the experience of the     cluding 3 annexes).&#13;
Wijetilleke,                 World Bank in supporting domestic      Stock Nos. BK 9060 (English), BK 9061&#13;
This report assesses the structure,    construction industries over the past  (French), BK 9062 (Spanish). $5.&#13;
background, and outlook for the world  ten years. Useful to contractors, engi-&#13;
lube oils industry. Presents the histori-  neers, and administrators in construc-  Estimating Total Factor&#13;
cal and projected lube oils demand     tion industry.&#13;
and trends in manufacturing technolo-  1984. 120 pages.                       Productivity Growth in a&#13;
gies and production capacity and pro-                                         Developing Country&#13;
vides an indicative assessment of the  ISBN 0-8213-0268-X. Stock No. BK 0268.  Anne O       Krueger and Baran&#13;
economics of lube oil production with  $5.                                    Anne      er&#13;
detailed market and economic data.                                            Tuncer&#13;
Enetaily mnuarkeseot Snd eooies Not.   Cost-Benefit Evaluation of             Staff Working Paper No. 422. 1980. 64&#13;
1982. 48 pages (including 13 annexes   LDC Industrial Sectors Which           pages (including references, appendix).&#13;
erences).                       rep    Have Foreign Ownership                 Stock No. WP 0422. $3.&#13;
ISBN 0-8213 0054-7. Stock No. BK 0054  Garry G. Pursell                       Financing Small-Scale Industry&#13;
$3                                     Staff Working Paper No. 465. 1981. 45  and Agriculture in Developing&#13;
pages.                                 Countries: The Merits and&#13;
Capital Utilization in                 Stock No. WP 0465. $3.                 Limitations of "Commercial"&#13;
Manufacturing: Colombia,                                                      Polici&#13;
Israel, Malaysia, and the              Development Finance                    Dennis Anderson and Fanda&#13;
Philippines                            Companies                              Khambata&#13;
Romeo M. Bautista, Helen               Examines the role of development fi    Staff Working Paper No. 519. 1982. 41&#13;
Hughes, David Lim, David               nance companies as major mechanisms    pages (including references).&#13;
Morawetz, and Francisco E.             for assisting medium-scale productive  ISBN-0-8213007-5. Stock No. WP 0519.&#13;
Thoumi                                 industries, assesses their potential for  ISN081330-. tc        o.W    59&#13;
The authors surveyed 1,200 manufac-    aiding small enterprises in meeting so-&#13;
turing firms in four developing coun-  cioeconomic objectives of developing   Fostering the Capital-Goods&#13;
tries to establish actual levels of capital  countries, and discusses the evolution  Sector in LDCs: A Survey of&#13;
utilization. The information collected  of World Bank assistance to them.     Evidence and Requirements&#13;
was the first and remains the only     Sector Policy Paper. 1976. 68 pages (in-  Howard Pack&#13;
data base available for the study of   cluding 7 annexes).                    Staff Working Paper No. 376. 1980 64&#13;
capital utilization. It was found that  Stock Nos. BK 9040 (English), BK 9058  pages (including references).&#13;
capital utilization is not as low as had  (French), BK 9041 (Spanish). $5.    Stock No. WP 0376. $3.&#13;
been supposed. The study is con-&#13;
cerned with factors that cause differ-  Empirical Justification for           Incorporating Uncertainty into&#13;
ences in levels of capital utilization  Infant Industry Protection            Planning of Industrialization&#13;
and the policies that might be used to  Larry E. Westphal                     Strategies for Developing&#13;
increase it.&#13;
Oxford University Press, 1982. 288 pages  Staff Working Paper No 445. 1981. 38  Countries&#13;
(including bibliography, index).       pages (including references).          Alexander H. Sarris and Irma&#13;
LC 81-9526. ISBN 0-19-520268-6, Stock  Stock No. WP 0445. $3.                 Adelman&#13;
No. OX 520268. $22 hardcover.                                                 Staff Working Paper No. 503. 1982. 58&#13;
pages (including appendix, references).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0503. $3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Industrialization and Growth:           Macroeconomic Implications of           Managing State-Owned&#13;
The Experience of Large                 Factor Substitution in                  Enterprises&#13;
Countries                               Industrial Processes                    Mary M. Shirley&#13;
Hollis Chenery                          Howard Pack                             Discusses efficiency of state-owned en-&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 539. 1982. 38   Staff Working Paper No. 377. 1980. 67   terprises. Gives the nature and size of&#13;
pages.                                  pages (including bibliography).         this sector, including industrial and&#13;
ISB   0-213007-0 StckNo. WP 0539.  Stock No. WP 0377. $3.                 commercial firms, mines, utilities,&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0.097  Stock                                                       transport companies, and financial in-&#13;
termediaries controlled to some extent&#13;
Industrial Prospects and                                                        by govemment. Tells how to increase&#13;
Policies in the Developed                        ^MA    injasnia               the sector's efficiency by defining ob-&#13;
Countries                                                                       jectives, controlling without interfer-&#13;
Countries                                               ,       _-              ence, holding managers accountable&#13;
Bela Balassa                                            .                       for results, and designing managerial&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 453. 1981. 30                '         .                skills and incentives. Includes bar&#13;
pages (including appendix).                                                     graphs and charts of information for&#13;
Stock No. WP 0453. $3.                               .~ f       -24 developing and developed coun-&#13;
tries.&#13;
Industrial Strategy for Late                                                    Staff Working Paper No. 577. 1983. 116&#13;
Starters: The Experience of                          .                          pages.&#13;
Kenya, Tanzania and Zambia                                                     ISBN 0-8213-0241-8. Stock No. WP 0577.&#13;
Ravi Gulhati and Uday Sekhar                      M                             $5.&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 457. 1981. 63   Made in Jamaica: The                    Manufacture of Heavy&#13;
pages (including references, annex).     Development of the                     Electrical Equipment in&#13;
Stock No. WP 0457. $3,                   Manufacturing Sector                   Developing Countries&#13;
Korean Industrial Competence:           Mahrnood Ali Ayub                      Ayhan (ilingiroglu&#13;
Where It Came From                      This book, the first detailed study of  Analyzes growth and competitiveness,&#13;
Larry E. Westphal, Yung W. Rhee,        Jamaica's manufacturing sector, pro-   comparing prices and costs with those&#13;
and G3arry G. Pursell                   vides a comprehensive assessment of    in the intemational market.&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 469. 1981. 76   sector and of its structure It relates  The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1969.&#13;
pages (inclu'ding references).          the development of the sector during   235 pages (including 2 annexes).&#13;
Stock No. WP 0469. $3.                  the past two decades, describes the ex-  LC 76-89962. ISBN 0-8018-1097-3, $5.50&#13;
tent of protection provided to the sec-  paperback.&#13;
tor in 1978, and examines the pros-    Spanish: Fabricacidn de equipo electrico pe-&#13;
NEW                                 pects for growth of manufactured       sado en los pafses en desarrollo. Editorial&#13;
exports during the coming years. Pol-  Tecnos, 1971. $5.50 paperback.&#13;
Location Factors in the                  icy recommendations are made on the&#13;
Decentralization of Industry: A         basis of this analysis.                 The Mining Industry and the&#13;
Survey of Metropolitan Sao              The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1981.  Developing Countries&#13;
Paulo, Brazil                           144 pages.                              Rex Bosson and Bension Varon&#13;
Peter M. Townroe                        LC 80-27765. ISBN 0-8018-2568-7, Stock  An overview of the world's nonfuel&#13;
No. rH 2568, $6.50 paperback.          mining industry, its structure and op-&#13;
Focuses on decisionmaking procedures                                            eration, and the major factors bearing&#13;
for industrial companies that are estab-  Managerial Structures and             on them.&#13;
lishing new plants or relocating their  Practices in Manufacturing              Oxford University Press, 1977; 3rd print-&#13;
plant sites. Some 581 industrial com-&#13;
panies in Brazil participated in a 1980  Enterprises: A Yugoslav Case           ing, 1984. 304 pages (including 12 appen-&#13;
survey to determine company motives      Study                                  dixes, bibliography, index).&#13;
for seeking a new site or building. Ap-  Martin Schrenk                         LC 77-2983. ISBN 0-19-920096-3, Stock&#13;
pendixes include nine detailed tables   Staff Working Paper No. 455. 1981. 104  No. OX 920096, $29.50 hardcover; ISBN&#13;
useful to industrial planners and com-  pages (including 4 appendixes).         0-19-920099-8, Stock No. OX 920099,&#13;
pany plant developers.                  Stock No. WP 0455. $5                   $24.95 paperback.&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 517. 1983. 112                                          French: L'industrie miniere dans le tiers&#13;
pages.                                                                          monde. Economica, 1978. ISBN 2-7178-&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0005-9. Stock No. WP 0517.                                          0030-1, Stock No. IB 0538, $14.95.&#13;
$5.                                                                             Spanish: La industria minera y los paises&#13;
en desarrollo. Editorial Tecnos, 1978.&#13;
ISBN 84-309-0779-3, Stock No. IB 0521,&#13;
$14.95.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Occupational Structures of            Policies for Industrial Progress       Oxford University Press, 1980; 2nd print-&#13;
Industries                            in Developing Countries                ing, 1982. 325 pages (including bibliog-&#13;
Manuel Zymelman                       John Cody, Helen Hughes, and           raphy, index).&#13;
Eighty-four tables profile the occupa-  David Wall, editors                  LC 79-24786. ISBN 0-19-520176-0, Stock&#13;
tional composition of industries in   Analysis of the principal policy issues  No. OX 520176, $24.95 hardcover; ISBN&#13;
each of twenty-six countries. Data    that influence the course and pace of  0-19-520177-9, Stock No. OX 520177,&#13;
show the structure of employment by   industrialization in the developing    $9.95 paperback.&#13;
sectors and industries for each coun-  countries. The text, organized along&#13;
try; cross-classify 120 occupations with  lines of governmental administrative  Pollution Control in Sao Paulo,&#13;
fifty-eight industries; and provide in-  responsibility for various industrial  Brazil: Costs, Benefits, and&#13;
formation about productivity (value   pokcies, includes chapters on trade, fi-  Effects on Industrial Location&#13;
added per person engaged), energy     nance, labor-technology relations, tax-  Vinod Thomas&#13;
consumption per person engaged, and   ation, licensing and other direct pro-&#13;
employment.                           duction controls, public enterprises,  Staff Working Paper No. 501. 1981. 127&#13;
1980; second printing, 1982. 211 pages.  infrastructure and location, industry-  pages (including annex, references).&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0126-8. Stock No. BK 0126.  agriculture linkage, and the interna-  Stock No. WP 0501. $5.&#13;
$20.                                  tional environment.&#13;
The Process of Industrial&#13;
Development and Alternative&#13;
The Planning of Investment Programs                                        Development Strategies&#13;
Alexander Meeraus and Ardy J.       cesses of relevance to fertilizer produc-  Bela Balassa&#13;
Stoutjesdijk, editors               tion and a systematic description of   Staff Working Paper No. 438. 1980. 42&#13;
Series comprising three volumes (to  the planning problems that need to be  pages (including appendix).&#13;
date) that describe a systematic ap-  addressed during the project identifi-  Stock No. WP 0438. $3.&#13;
proach to investment planning, relying cation phase.&#13;
primarily on mathematical program-  The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1980.  Public Subsidies to Industry:&#13;
ming techniques. Includes both gen-  320 pages.                            The Case of Sweden and Its&#13;
eral methodological volumes and stud- LC 78-8436. ISBN 0-8018-2138-X, Stock  Shipbuilding Industry&#13;
ies dealing with specific industrial  No. JH 2138, $25 hardcover; ISBN 0-  Carl Hamilton&#13;
subsectors.                         8018-2153-3, Stock No. JH 2153, $15 pa-  Examines the reasons for the high&#13;
Volume 1: The Planning of           perback.                               govemment subsidies given to the&#13;
Industrial Investment                   NEW                                Swedish shipbuilding industry during&#13;
Programs: A Methodology                                                    the recession period of the 1970s. Swe-&#13;
David A. Kendrick and Ardy J.       Volume 3: The Planning of              den's approach to the shipbuilding&#13;
Stoutjesdijk                        Investment Programs in the             problem is compared with the adjust-&#13;
The analytical approach with special  Steel Industry                       ment made by Japan when it faced a&#13;
similar situation. Concludes that a sta-&#13;
emphasis on the complications arising  David A. Kendrick, Alexander        bilization policy is important in achiev-&#13;
from economies of scale; a helpful in-  Meeraus, and Jaime Alatorre        ing the objective of full employment.&#13;
troduction to  linear and mixed-integer  As a suppher of both capital equip-  Staff Working Paper No. 566. 1983. 52&#13;
programming, facilitating understand-  ment and materials for further proc-  pages.&#13;
ing of subsequent volumes in the se-  essing, the steel industry has a sub-  pag g&#13;
nies..                                                                     ISBN 0-8213-0196-9.Stock no. WP 0566.&#13;
TheJohns.  Hopin Uivrsty res,199.stantial effect on the cost structure and&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1979. competitiveness of other economic ac-&#13;
144 pages (including index).        tivities. Its own cost structure, how-&#13;
LC 78-8428. ISBN 0-8018-2139-8, Stock  ever, depends to a large extent on the  Restructuring of&#13;
No. IH 2139, $18.50 hardcover; ISBN 0-  efficiency of past investments.    Manufacturing Industry: The&#13;
8018-2152-5, Stock No. JH 2152, $12 pa-  Provides an overview of the technol-  Experience of the Textile&#13;
perback.                             ogy of steel production, and the prob-  Industry in Pakistan,&#13;
French: La programmation des investisse-  lems of investment analysis in this in-  Philippines, Portugal, and&#13;
ments industriels: methode et etude de cas. dustry, and contains an application of  Turkey&#13;
Economica, 1981. (Combines translation of investment analysis to the Mexican  Barend A. de Vries and Willem&#13;
this book with that of the case study of the  steel industry. Introduces a new eco-  Brakel&#13;
fertilizer industry in Volume 2, below.)  nomic modeling language, GAMS,&#13;
ISBN 2-7178-0328-9, Stock No. IB 0544,  which decreases the time and effort re-  Views the restructuring and modemi-&#13;
$12.                                quired to construct and use industrial  zation of manufacturing from the per-&#13;
Volume 2: Th  Planning of  sector models.                         spective of World Bank assistance in&#13;
Volume    2T he Programsning th     The Johns Hopkins University Press. 1984.  the textile industry. Evaluates the roles&#13;
Investment Programs in the          Th8paeJhs.HpisUiesiyPes         94     of government, the financial systemn&#13;
Fertilizer Industry                 L832187page. IB0818390,Sok             and the private sector in restructuring.&#13;
Armeane M. Choksi, Alexander        No IH 31972 $30IhardNo808397-I Stock   World Bank Working paper No. 558.&#13;
Meeraus, and Ardy J. StoutJesdijk   8018-3198-9, Stock No. IH 3198, $15 pa-  1983. 59 pages.&#13;
Discusses the main products and pro-  perback.                             ISBN 0-8213-0151-9. Stock No. WP 0558.&#13;
-J____  $3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Small Enterprises and                            Suoe_aq                            NEW&#13;
Development Policy in the                                 tpWmna&#13;
Philippines: A Case Study                             _dEa                      Technological Change and&#13;
Dennis Anderson and Farida                           T    wU  Ca                Industrial Development: Issues&#13;
Khambata                                                                        and Opportunities&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 468. 1981. 239                                          Frederick T. Moore&#13;
pages (including bibliography, annex).           .. _    4       7.i            Identifies principal issues relating tech-&#13;
Stock No. WP 0468. $10.                                                         nological change to growth in indus-&#13;
trial development. Draws upon the&#13;
Small Industry in Developing                      .       -     0              theoretical and empirical literature for&#13;
Countries: Some Issues                                                         an economic analysis of effective pro-&#13;
Dennis Anderson                                                                gram designs. Projects underway in&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 518. 1982. 77                     ~~~the engineering and capital goods in-&#13;
Staff Wor(ing Paper No. 518.1982. 77                                           dustries suggests methods for revising&#13;
pages (including references).                         U          ;,            policies and promoting new technolog-&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0006-7. Stock No. WP 0518.                                         ical information in industry.&#13;
$3.                                     State Manufacturing Enterprise         Staff Working Paper No. 613. 1983. 96&#13;
in a Mixed Economy: The                 pages.&#13;
Small-Scale Enterprises in              Turkish Case                           ISBN 0-8213-0257-4. Stock No. WP 0613.&#13;
Korea and Taiwan                        Bertil Waistedt                        $3.&#13;
Sam P.S. Ho                             Traces the historic roots of "etatism"  T           t&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 384. 1980. 157  and reviews the performance of six     Transiton toward More Rapid&#13;
pages (including 4 appendixes).         major state industries in Turkey.      and. Labor-Intensive Industrial&#13;
Stock No. WP 0384. $5.                  The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1980.  Development: The Case of the&#13;
354 pages (including appendixes, index).  Philippines&#13;
LC 78-21398. ISBN 0-8018-2226-2, Stock  Barend A. de Vries&#13;
NE_ W                               No. JH 2226, $30 hardcover; ISBN 0-    Staff Working Paper No. 424. 1980. 32&#13;
8018-2227-0, Stock No. IH 2227, $13.50  pages (including references, 12 tables).&#13;
Sources of Industrial Growth            paperback.                              Stock No. WP 0424. $3.&#13;
and Structural Change: The&#13;
Case of Turkey&#13;
Merih Celasun&#13;
Considers-the role of Turkey's public&#13;
and private sectors in the industrial&#13;
transition since the 1950s. Compares&#13;
Turkey's trade prospects in the 1980s&#13;
with growth in earlier periods of de-&#13;
velopment as well as growth in other&#13;
semi-industrial countries.&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 614. 1983. 188&#13;
pages.&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0283-2. Stock No. WP 0614.                                          Prices subject to change without notice&#13;
$5.                                                                             and may vary by country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
U Publications Order Form&#13;
SEND TO: YOUR LOCAL DISTRIBUTOR OR TO WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
(See the other sitd of thisform.)        P.O. BOX 37525&#13;
WASHNGTON, D.C. 20013 U.S.A.&#13;
Date&#13;
Name                                               Ship to: (Enter if different from purchaser)&#13;
Title                                              Name&#13;
Firm                                               Title&#13;
Address                                            Firm&#13;
City              Statek     Postal Code. .        Address&#13;
Country             Telephone l    )               City            State     Postal Code&#13;
Purchaser Reference No.                            Country             Teiephone I&#13;
Check your method of payment.&#13;
Enclosed is my O Check LU International Money Order O Unesco Coupons Ol International Postal Coupon.&#13;
Make payable to World Bank Publications for U S. dollars unless you are ordering from your local distributor.&#13;
Charge my El VISA O MasterCard Ol American Express n Choice. (Credit cards accepted only for orders addressed&#13;
to World Bank Publications.)&#13;
Credit Card Account Number          Expiration Date                    Signature&#13;
Cl Invoice me and please reference my Purchase Order No.&#13;
Please ship me the items listed below.&#13;
Ctmi lnternal&#13;
Stock NuMh  Authbr/ Tide                                       Routing Code  Quatity  Unit Prke Total Amou n&#13;
All prices subject to change.  Prices may vary by country.  Allow 6-8 weeks for delivery.&#13;
Subtotal Cost  S&#13;
Total copies      Air mail surcharge if desired ($2.00 each)  S&#13;
Postage and handling for more than two complimentary items (52.00 each)  S -&#13;
Tbtal  S_&#13;
IwORcO                                                          Thank you for your order.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Distributors of World                   Attn: Mr. Giancarlo Bigazzi             Attn: Mr. I.M. Hemandez&#13;
D X ,,. . ~~~~~~~~Via Lamarmora 45                                    Castello 37&#13;
Bank Publications                       50121                                   Madnd&#13;
ARGENTINA                               Florence                                SRI LANKA AND THE MALDIVES&#13;
Carlos Hirsch, SRL.                     JAPAN                                   Lake House Bookshop&#13;
Attn: Ms. Monica Bustos                 Eastem Book Service                     Attn: Mr. Victor Walatara&#13;
Florida 165 4e piso                     Attn: Mr. Terumasa Hirano               41 Wad Ramanayake Mawatha&#13;
Galerta Guemes                          37-3, Hongo 3-Chome. Bunkyo-ku 113      Colombo 2&#13;
Buenos Aires 1307                       Tokyo                                   SWEDEN&#13;
AUSTRALIA, PAPUA NEW GUINEA,            KENYA                                   ABCE Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel&#13;
FIJI, SOLOMON ISLANDS,                  Africa Book Services (E.A.) Ltd.        Attn: Mr. Eide Segerback&#13;
WESTERN SAMOA, AND                      Attn: Mr. M.B. Dar                      Regenngsgatan 1Z, Box 16356&#13;
VANUATU                                 P.O. Box 45245                          5-10327 Stockholm&#13;
The Australian Financial Review         Nairobi                                 SWITZERLAND&#13;
Information Service (AFRIS)             KOREA, REPUBLIC OF                      Librairie Payot&#13;
Attn: Mr. David Jamieson                Pan Korea Book Corporation              Attn: Mr. Henn de Perrot&#13;
235-243 Jones Street                    Attn: Mr. Yoon-Sun Kim                  6, rue Grenus&#13;
Broadway                                P.O. Box 101. Kwanghwamun               1211 Geneva&#13;
Sydney, NSW 20001                       Seoul                                   TANZANIA&#13;
BELGIUM                                 MALAYSIA                                Oxford University Press&#13;
Publications des Nations Unies          University of Malaya Cooperative        Attn: Mr. Anthony Theobold&#13;
Attn: Mr. Jean de Lannoy                Bookshop Ltd.                           Maktaba Road. P.O. Box 5299&#13;
av. du Roi 202                          Attn: Mr. Mohammed Fahim Htj            Dar es Salaam&#13;
1060 Brussels                           Yacob                                   THAILAND&#13;
CANADA                                  P.O. Box 1127, Jalan Pantai Baru        Central Department Store, Head Office&#13;
Le Diffuseur                            Kuala Lumpur                            Attn: Mrs. Ratana&#13;
Attn: Mrs. Suzanne Vermette             MEXICO                                  306 Silom Road&#13;
C.P. 85. Boucherville J4B 5E6           INFOTEC                             -   Bangkok&#13;
Quebec                                  Attn: Mr. Jorge Cepeda                  Thailand Management Association&#13;
COSTA RICA                              San Lorenzo 53-1, Col. del Valle,       Attn: Mrs. Sunan&#13;
Libreria T e os                         Deleg- Benito Juarez                    308 Silom Road&#13;
Attn. Mr. Hugo Chamberlain              031     Mexico, D.F.                    Bangkok&#13;
Calle 11-13. Av. Femandez Guell         MIDDLE EAST                             TUNISIA&#13;
San Jose                                Middle East Marketing Research          Societe Tunisienne de Diffusion&#13;
DENMARK                                 Blureau                                 Attn: Mr. Slaheddine Ben Hamida&#13;
Sanfundslitteratur                      Attn: Mr. George Vassilou               3 Avenue de Carthage&#13;
Attn: Mr. Wilfried Roloff               Makais   fi Avenue.                     TU&#13;
Rosenderns Alle 11                      Nicosia                                 TURKEY&#13;
DK-1970 Copenhagen V.                   Cvprus                                  Haset Kitapevi A.S.&#13;
EGYPT, Arab Republic of                 (Branch offices in Bahrain, Greece.     Attn: Mr Izzet lzerel&#13;
Al Ahram                                Morocco, Kuwait, United Arab            469. Istiklal Caddesi&#13;
Al Galaa Street                         Emirates, Jordan)                       bevoglu-Istanbul&#13;
Cairo                                   NETHERLANDS                             UNITED KINGDOM AND&#13;
MBE BY                                  NORTHERN IRELAND&#13;
FINLAND                                 Attn: Mr. Gerhard van Bussell           Microinfo Ltd.&#13;
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa                 Noorderwal 38,                           Atn: '   r°&#13;
Attn: Mr. Kan Litmanen                  7241 BL Lochem                          Newman Lane, P.O. Box 3&#13;
Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100                  NORWAY                                  Alton, Hampshire GU34 2PG&#13;
Helsinki 10                             Johan Grundt Tanum A.S.                 England&#13;
FRANCE                                  Attn: Ms. Randi Mikkelborg&#13;
World Bank Publications                rPo. Box 1177 Sentrum                    UNITED STATES&#13;
66, avenue d'lena                       Oslo                                    The World Bank Book Store&#13;
75116 Pans                              PANAMA                                  600 19th Street, N.W.&#13;
75116 Pans                   ~~~~~~PANAMA                             Washington. D.C. 20433&#13;
GERMANY, Federal Republic of            Ediciones Libreria Cultural Panamena    (Postal address: P.O. Box 37525&#13;
UNO-Verlag                              Attn: Mr. Luis Femandez Fraguela R.     Washington, D.C. 20013, U.S.A.)&#13;
Attn: Mr. Joachim Krause                Av. 7, Espana 16                        Baker and Taylor Company&#13;
Simrockstrasse 23                       Panama Zone 1                           501 South Gladiola Avenue&#13;
D-5300 Bonn I                           PHILIPPINES                             Momence, lflinois, 60954&#13;
HONG KONG, MACAU                        National Book Store                     380 Edison Way&#13;
Asia 2000 Ltd.                          Attn: Mrs. Socorro C. Ramos             Reno, Nevada. 89564&#13;
Attn: Ms. Gretchen Wearing Smith        701 Rizal Avenue                        50 Kirby Avenue&#13;
6 Fl., 146 Pnnce Edward Road            Manila                                  Sumervyllene&#13;
Kowloon                                 PORTUGAL                                Somerville, New Jersey. 08876&#13;
INDIA                                   Livrana Portugal                          ommerce, Georgia 30599&#13;
UBS Publishers' Distributors Ltd.       Attn: Mr Antonio Alves Martins          Beman Associates&#13;
Attn: Mr. D.P. Veer                     Rua Do Carmo 70-74                      9730-E George Palmer Highway&#13;
Attn: Mr. OP. Veer           ~~1200                                   Lanham, Maryland. 2076&#13;
5 Ansan Road, Post Box 7015             1L                                           a      yn    2&#13;
New Delhi 110002                        Lisbon                                  Blackwell North America, Inc.&#13;
(Branch offices in Bombay, Bangalore,   SAUDI ARABIA                            1001 Fries Mill Road&#13;
Kanpur, Calcutta, and Madras)           larir Book Store                        Blackwood, New Jersey 08012&#13;
INDONESIA                               Attn: Mr. Akram AI-Agil                 Sidney Kramer Books&#13;
Pt. Indira Limited                      P.O. Box 31%                            1722 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Attn: Mr. Bambang Wahyudi               Riyadh                                  Washington, D.C. 20006&#13;
JI, Dr. Sam Ratulangi No. 37            SINGAPORE, TAIWAN, BURMA                United Nations Bookshop&#13;
Jakarta Pusat                           Information Publications Private, Ltd.  United Nations Plaza&#13;
IRELAND                                 Attn: Ms. Janet David                   New York, N.Y. 10017&#13;
TDC Publishers                          02-06 Ist Floor, Pei-Fu Industnal&#13;
Attn: Mr. James Booth                     Building                              VENEZUELA&#13;
12 North Frederick Street               24 New Industnal Road                  LAbreria del Este&#13;
Dublin I                                Singapore                               Attn. Mr. Juan Pericas&#13;
ITALY                                   SIN                                     Avda Francisco de Miranda, no. 52&#13;
iTosa CommissionriaSansoiSPAMund-PrensaLbros,S.ASPAIN                           Edificio Gal'pan, Aptdo. 60.337&#13;
Licosa Commissionaria Sansoni SPA       Mundi-Prensa Libros. S.A.               Caracas 1010A&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG 3881.5 W57 W67 NO.666&#13;
c.3&#13;
BELL. IIARTIN&#13;
ASSESSING THE PERFORMANCE Of&#13;
INFANT INDUSTRIES&#13;
DATE   NAME AND EXTENSION  ROOM&#13;
__________________  ____________NUMBER&#13;
JUN ~  UN    h   .3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                                  European Office            Tokyo Office                  Di&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                           66, avenue d'lena          Kokusai Building                          z&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.                75116 Paris, France         1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan      &#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234                     Telephone: (1) 723-54.21       o       T      1&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK                    Telex: 842-620628          Telephone: (03) 214-5001                  0&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                                 Telex: 781-26838                           \&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
fb&#13;
r'&#13;
0&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0413-5    ~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554779">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/09/1554779/assessing-performance-infant-industries
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/09/1554779/assessing-performance-infant-industries</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1984/09/1554779/assessing-performance-infant-industries</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/23/000178830_98101903423628/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/23/000178830_98101903423628/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-08-23T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1984-09-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Assessing the performance of infant industries
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper reports findings from a
            literature survey to learn about the performance of infant
            industries in less developed countries. Remarkably little
            direct evidence was uncovered about the costs and benefits
            of developing these industries. But the findings indicate
            that infant firms have experienced relatively slow
            productivity growth. Thus many infants started some time ago
            apparently have so far failed to achieve international
            competitiveness. The findings suggest tentative conclusions
            about the causes of the failure. Insufficient productivity
            growth to achieve and maintain competitiveness seems to
            reflect the absence of sustained efforts to acquire and use
            the capabilities necessary for continuous technological
            change. Far more than stemming from experience alone, these
            capabilities appear to increase to needed levels only
            through consciously allocating resources to acquire them.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Assessing the performance of infant industries
        </docna>
        <display_title>Assessing the performance of
            infant industries</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1984/09/1554779/assessing-performance-infant-industries</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Municipal Financial Management,Industrial Management</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Bell, M.</author>
            <author>Ross-Larson, B.</author>
            <author>Westphal, L.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903423628</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Other finance</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 666</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Finance</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0413-5</isbn>
        <keywd>
            New industry; Industrial productivity;
            Competitiveness; Technological capacity
            accounting,affiliates,allocative
            efficiency,Basic metals,benefit analysis,comparative
            advantage,competitiveness,competitors,consumers,developed
            countries,development strategies,discount rate,discounted
            value,economic conditions,economic factors,economic
            justification,economies of scale,economists,effective
            use,empirical studies,exchange rate,foreign
            exchange,furnaces,imports,industrial countries,industrial
            development,industrial production,Industrial
            productivity,input use,intermediate inputs,labor inputs,less
            developed countries,Maturity,Metals,new products,Oil,policy
            makers,positive externalities,producers,production
            costs,Productivity,productivity growth,Science Policy,shadow
            prices,social costs,technological change,total output,value
            of output
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP666</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technological Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Capital</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing People</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Econometrics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textiles</ml:concept><ml:concept>Construction Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technology Transfer and Diffusion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adaptation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>