<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP567&#13;
The Political Economy of Protection in Italy&#13;
Some Empirical Evidence&#13;
Enzo Grilli&#13;
Mauro La Noce&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 567&#13;
HG&#13;
3881.5&#13;
.W57&#13;
W67&#13;
no. 567&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
A Set of Related&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Public Subsidies to Industry&#13;
The Case of Sweden and Its Shipbuilding Industry&#13;
Number 566&#13;
The Political Economy of Protection in Italy&#13;
Some Empirical Evidence&#13;
Number 567&#13;
Bureaucracies and the Political Economy&#13;
of Protection&#13;
Reflections of a Continental European&#13;
Number 568&#13;
Economics and the Politics of Protection&#13;
Some Case Studies of Industries&#13;
Number 569&#13;
Public Assistance to Industries&#13;
and Trade Policy in France&#13;
Number 570&#13;
The Structure of International Competitiveness&#13;
in the Federal Republic of Germany&#13;
An Appraisal&#13;
Number 571&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 567&#13;
The Political Economy of Protection in Italy&#13;
Some Empirical Evidence&#13;
Enzo Grilli&#13;
Mauro La Noce&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright © 1983&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development / THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
First printing July 1983&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To&#13;
present the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has&#13;
not been prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal&#13;
printed texts, and the World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The&#13;
publication is supplied at a token charge to defray part of the cost of&#13;
manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to&#13;
any individual acting on their behalf. Any maps used have been prepared&#13;
solely for the convenience of the readers; the denominations used and the&#13;
boundaries shown do not imply, on the part of the World Bank and its affiliates,&#13;
any judgment on the legal status of any territory or any endorsement or&#13;
acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications is described in the Catalog of World&#13;
Bank Publications; the continuing research program of the Bank is outlined in&#13;
World Bank Research Program: Abstracts of Current Studies. Both booklets are&#13;
updated annually; the most recent edition of each is available without charge&#13;
from the Publications Distribution Unit of the Bank in Washington or from the&#13;
European Office of the Bank, 66, avenue d'Iena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Enzo Grilli, now secretary of planning with the Italian Ministry of Planning,&#13;
was with the Economic Analysis and Projections Department of the World Bank&#13;
when the report was written. Mauro La Noce is an economist with the Research&#13;
Department of the General Confederation of Italian Industry in Rome and a&#13;
consultant to the Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Grilli, Enzo R.&#13;
The political economy of protection in Italy.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 567)&#13;
Bibliography: p.*&#13;
1. Tariff-Italy. 2. Italy--Commercial policy.&#13;
3. Free trade and protection--Protection. I. La Noce,&#13;
Mauro, 1952-       .  II. Title.    III. Series.&#13;
HF2126.G74    1983        382.7'3'0945    83-10230&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0197-7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ABSTRACT&#13;
This report is part of an inquiry undertaken by the World Bank&#13;
in conjunction with scholars from 12 industrial countries into the&#13;
penetration of the markets of industrial countries by exports of&#13;
manufactures from developing countries. The project sought to establish&#13;
the shares of industrial country markets held by the developing&#13;
countries, changes in such shares in the 1970s, and why they vary among&#13;
industry groups and countries.      The aim is to assist developing and&#13;
industrial   countries  to   improve  their  policies   through  a  better&#13;
understanding of trade patterns and protectionist pressures.&#13;
To date, the work on decision-making with respect to commercial&#13;
policy has produced three principal models:       the adding machine, the&#13;
interest group and the national policy.    The explanatory power of these&#13;
models at the country level depends critically on the prevailing&#13;
political and institutional realities.    For example, the members of the&#13;
European Community (EC) have given considerable authority to EC's&#13;
administrators to determine tariff policy.    At the same time, the member&#13;
countries can use a substantial number of non-tariff measures to protect&#13;
domestic interests.    Thus, in analyzing protection policy in EC member&#13;
countries, it is the sum of EC tariff and national non-tariff measures&#13;
that must be considered.     Moreover, the ensuing explanation of trade&#13;
policy cuts across all three models rather than fitting any one.&#13;
This paper looks at the political economy of protection in&#13;
Italy using a model that specifies the demand side of the market,&#13;
despite the limitations of that approach.      It addresses protection as&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
embodied in the EC's rate of tariff protection and Italy's rate of&#13;
domestic  subsidy  assistance.     The  rate  of  tariff   protection  was&#13;
explained  by   import  penetration   variables  that  reflected  the   EC&#13;
countries' exposure to import competition from non-EC countries, while&#13;
the rate of subsidy assistance used variables that reflected more direct&#13;
determinants of domestic demand. The empirical findings from the cross-&#13;
section analysis of 35 industrial subsectors conformed quite well to the&#13;
assumptions.&#13;
Effective tariff rates have protected Italian exports in the EC&#13;
markets and only to a lesser extent have guarded against the penetration&#13;
of  non-EC  exports  of  final  goods  into  the domestic market.      The&#13;
allocation of subsidies has been strongly affected by the labor&#13;
intensity of the production processes and by the size of the value-added&#13;
share of the output.   The overall structure of protection has also been&#13;
directed to ensure relatively low prices for industrial inputs purchased&#13;
from non-EC countries.   It seems that industries in the poorer regions&#13;
of southern Italy were protected by both tariffs and subsidies, although&#13;
this issue warrants further investigation.    The analysis also verified&#13;
the substitution relationship between tariff protection at the EC level&#13;
and subsidy assistance at the national level.      Finally, the economic&#13;
agents have reacted more strongly to the effective than to the nominal&#13;
rates of tariff protection.&#13;
A topic needing further investigation is the supply side of&#13;
protection. Moreover, it would be useful to have a dynamic examination&#13;
of  protection   across  industries   rather  than  the  static   analysis&#13;
conducted here.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS&#13;
The authors wish to thank Helen Hughes of the World Bank and&#13;
Jean Waelbroeck of the Free University of Bruxelles for their comments&#13;
on the various drafts of this paper, as well as the Italian Statistical&#13;
Office (ISTAT) for making available the 1975 input-output matrix and&#13;
related data. They also acknowledge with gratitude?the help received in&#13;
the preliminary stages of the research from many of their former&#13;
colleagues in the General Confederation of Italian Industries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Page&#13;
I      THE POLITICAL ECONOMY OF PROTECTION:          ADAPTING THE&#13;
STANDARD MODELS TO THE ITALIAN CASE          ....................       .     I&#13;
Limitations of the Standard Models........................ &#13;
Adopting the Standard Models for the Italian Case......4&#13;
II      THE STRUCTURE OF PROTECTION FOR THE MAJOR INDUSTRIAL&#13;
SECTORS IN ITALY      ..........................................             9&#13;
III       THE DETERMINANTS OF THE INTER-INDUSTRY STRUCTURE OF&#13;
PROTECTION IN ITALY       .....       ...................          ...      20&#13;
IV      CONCLUSIONS ......                     ................                     28&#13;
REFERENCES.....                                                                       31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
LIST OF TABLES&#13;
Page&#13;
1    Nominal Tariffs and Product Coverage of Quantitative&#13;
Restrictions in Italy, 1975 ................................. .. 13&#13;
2    Nominal Rate of Tariff Protection (NT), Effective Rate&#13;
of Tariff Protection (ERTP) and Effective Rate of&#13;
Subsidy Assistance (SUB) in Italy, 1975 ....................... 16&#13;
3    Cumulative Effect on Sector ERTP of a Uniform One&#13;
Percentage Point Change in the Nominal Tariff ................. 19&#13;
4    Determinants of the Effective Rate of Assistance in Italy ..... 23&#13;
5    Determinants of the Effective Rate of Tariff Protetion&#13;
(ERTP) and of the Effective Rate of Subsidization (SUB)&#13;
in Italy ...................................................... 25&#13;
6    A Recursive Specification of the Effective Rate of&#13;
Assistance Model for Italy .................................... 27&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 1 -&#13;
Chapter I&#13;
THE POLITICAL ECONOMY OF PROTECTION: ADAPTING THE STANDARD&#13;
MODELS TO THE ITALIAN CASE&#13;
Limitations of the Standard Models&#13;
Only recently has the political economy of protection, probably as&#13;
old as protection itself, become the subject of systematic analysis.        Pre-&#13;
occupied with the task of showing the "welfare inferiority" of import&#13;
restrictions, neoclassical and modern trade economists have long failed to&#13;
address the economic and political reality of protection from the standpoint&#13;
of the process of choice.    This process varies among countries, depending on&#13;
the political framework in which it develops, the institutional framework of&#13;
trade, and basic economic characteristics.&#13;
Although traditionally attention has been paid to the rationales for&#13;
import protection (or, in a neoclassical sense, for the "demand" for&#13;
protection), typically the level of analysis has been quite abstract. It has&#13;
been assumed that government objectives (e.g., industrialization) reflect&#13;
underlying community preferences; proposed policies (e.g., protection of an&#13;
"infant" sector) have been analyzed in terms of their welfare rationality&#13;
and/or national development effectiveness.     Especially in certain developing&#13;
countries, other "non-economic" objectives of government have been taken at&#13;
face value and criticized or defended in political terms, a discussion in&#13;
which  trade  economists   very  often  have  not  participated.    The  obvious&#13;
illustration is the issue of "dependency," which has generated substantial&#13;
literature.&#13;
With the development of the theory of public choice, economic&#13;
analysis has begun to focus on the political processes that lead to decisions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
on  commercial  policies.   1/   In recent   years,  several models   have been&#13;
developed and tested to explain, first, the inter-industry structure of import&#13;
restrictions, especially tariffs, and, subsequently, that of other forms of&#13;
government assistance to domestic producers. 2/&#13;
These models have several shortcomings.     Some assume implicitly or&#13;
explicitly that the choice of policy is something that takes place in liberal-&#13;
democratic political systems.    Yet it is quite conceivable that when choice&#13;
takes place in an authoritarian system, some of the determinants of import&#13;
protection will be different from those in a democracy.         Thus it must be&#13;
questioned to which countries explanatory hypotheses such as those of the&#13;
"adding machine model," which postulates that governments       "supply"  import&#13;
protection to maximize their chances of re-election, are applicable. Strictly&#13;
speaking, they would seem to be most applicable to industrial democracies, and&#13;
in particular to those in which elected representatives and voters have a&#13;
direct relationship, rather than to developing economies in which different&#13;
political systems and consensus-generating mechanisms are at work.&#13;
1/ See, for example, W. A. Brock and S. P. Magee, "The Economics of Special&#13;
Interest Politics:    The Case of the Tariff," American Economic Review&#13;
68(2)(May 1978):246-55; Anne 0. Krueger, "The Political Economy of the&#13;
Rent-Seeking Society," American Economic Review 64 (June 1974):291-303; J.&#13;
J. Pincus, "Pressure Groups and the Patterns of Tariffs," Journal of&#13;
Political Economy 83(2)(August 1975):757-78; R. E. Caves, "Economic Models&#13;
of Political   Choice:   Canada's Tariff Structure," Canadian Journal of&#13;
Economics 19(2)(May 1976):278-300; R. E. Baldwin, "The Political Economy&#13;
of Postwar U.S. Trade Policy," The Bulletin (1976-4), New York University&#13;
Graduate School of Business Administration; K. Anderson, "The Political&#13;
Market for Government Assistance to Australian Manufacturing Industries,"&#13;
a paper presented at the Conference of Economists, Macquarie University,&#13;
Sydney, Australia, August 1978; and W. A. Brock and S. P. Magee, "An&#13;
Economic Theory of Politics: The Case of the Tariff," mimeo, 1974.&#13;
2/ A most useful comparative analysis of these models can be found in Caves,&#13;
ibid., which also provides excellent bibliographical references.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
With respect to the "interest group model," it presumes, on the&#13;
demand side, a functioning productive sector articulated into well-defined&#13;
categories of agents capable and free to exert influence on decision-makers&#13;
with respect to the protection of a sector. Interest groups,will organize for&#13;
action as long as the benefits they seek from protection exceed (at the&#13;
margin) the costs incurred in obtaining it.     While this analytical framework&#13;
does not necessarily require a political democracy, it does presuppose private&#13;
enterprise or, at least, a mixed economic system, within which interest groups&#13;
can form, function openly and try to influence government decision-makers.&#13;
The model, therefore, is again more applicable to industrial democracies and&#13;
their processes for choosing policies, and to a select group of developing&#13;
countries, than to the universe of countries with their widely differing&#13;
selection mechanisms.&#13;
Of the various models, the "national policy" one is probably the more&#13;
broadly applicable.     It seeks  to identify and take into account national&#13;
preferences with regard to industrial structure in order to explain the inter-&#13;
industry make-up of import protection and government assistance in a country&#13;
at a given time.&#13;
A priori reasoning strongly suggests that the determinants of the&#13;
structure of import protection in a given country actually cut across single&#13;
model lines.   On the supply side, consider, for example, the use of import&#13;
protection and/or direct government assistance to maximize employment in a&#13;
given industry or sector.     This approach is consistent with both the re-&#13;
election objective of elected representatives which is at the core of the&#13;
"adding machine" model, and the "national policy" goal of industrialization in&#13;
a system where decisions are made not by elected representatives but by&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
appointed planners.    On the demand side, it can be reasonably hypothesized&#13;
that the geographic concentration of an industry is positively related to the&#13;
rate of protection (or assistance) it receives within the context of an&#13;
"interest group" model.    This is so because geographic concentration should&#13;
improve an industry's capacity to organize and lobby successfully for&#13;
protection.    The   notion  of  an  inverse  relationship   between  geographic&#13;
concentration and protection (or assistance) is, on the other hand, more&#13;
tenable within the framework of the "adding machine" model, according to which&#13;
geographically dispersed seekers of protection may be able to influence a&#13;
larger number of elected representatives.&#13;
In these as well as in other cases, the empirical test results&#13;
provide the "answers."    However, even where the common practice is to test&#13;
hybrid variants of individual models, it is still essential that both the&#13;
broad conformity of the explanatory model to the underlying political reality,&#13;
and the institutional framework within which the process of choice takes&#13;
place, be carefully addressed. Further, the applicability of these models to&#13;
different countries needs to be carefully scrutinized.        The choice of the&#13;
left-hand side variable of these models -- either the inter-industry structure&#13;
of tariff and non-tariff protection or the inter-industry structure of trade&#13;
protection plus other government assistance -- becomes critical, depending on&#13;
the specific institutional framework for trade.&#13;
Adapting the Standard Models for the Italian Case&#13;
In the case of Italy -- and of the other members of the EC -- a&#13;
critical factor is that national authorities have given up a good deal of&#13;
autonomy over trade policies.    Tariffs, and more recently import quotas, are&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
now centrally managed by the EC, which sets a common structure for tariff&#13;
protection.   That structure could hardly be taken as reflecting fully the&#13;
domestic determinants of any single country.     As it is the result of intra-&#13;
country bargaining, the structure of tariff protection can only be expected to&#13;
reflect the minimum common denominator of interests among the seekers of&#13;
protection.   They, in turn, can be either national governments who want to&#13;
protect "national policy" interests, or firms lobbying as interest groups at&#13;
the national or Community level.&#13;
In   this   institutional   context,  the   assumption   of   a  direct&#13;
relationship between the re-election objectives of elected representatives and&#13;
tariff protection to industry breaks down.       Even the concept of "national&#13;
policy" objectives needs to be modified, if it is to fit an institutional&#13;
framework   in  which   the  search   for  and   achievement  of   consensus   is&#13;
transnational.   Presumably, it might be easier for the Community to achieve&#13;
consensus on commercial policy in reaction to a certain situation (a sectoral&#13;
crisis, for example) as opposed to the pursuit of longer term structural&#13;
changes or developmental objectives (regional or industry-oriented).&#13;
On the other hand, since the member countries of the EC still have a&#13;
large degree of autonomy over non-tariff measures, it is likely that they will&#13;
resort to these instruments to protect domestic interests either at variance&#13;
with perceived "Community" interests or too "specific" to become "Community"&#13;
interests.   Because the quantitative analysis of non-tariff protection is so&#13;
difficult, this aspect of protection cannot usually be fully incorporated in&#13;
the models.   However, it is possible to take into account direct and indirect&#13;
government assistance to industry, which is also more freely granted at the&#13;
national level, even if the data limitations create serious difficulties.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
Direct and indirect subsidies to industry can be thought of as&#13;
substitutes for the tariff protection set at the Community level. The greater&#13;
the autonomy that national authorities have in deciding which sectors to&#13;
protect, the more closely the determinants of the intersectoral structure of&#13;
assistance will conform to the models that explain tariff protection in&#13;
countries whose national authorities have a freer choice between tariff&#13;
protection and subsidies.    Then, for countries like Italy that belong to an&#13;
economic union, it is the "sum" of the tariff protection granted at the&#13;
Community level and of government assistance granted at the national level&#13;
across industrial sectors that becomes the more relevant structure to explain.&#13;
Finally, the standard models of the determinants of protection have&#13;
often lacked a clear theoretical specification. The "adding machine" model is&#13;
in essence a supply side model, while the "interest group" model is basically&#13;
a demand side model: the former focuses primarily on the determinants of the&#13;
supply of protection, while the latter focuses on the determinants of&#13;
demand. Yet often the two sides of the market are not clearly differentiated.&#13;
The empirical literature on the subject is clear evidence of this confusion:&#13;
sometimes the same variables are used to represent both sides of the market&#13;
for protection, such that their impact is decided ex post, according to the&#13;
signs of the estimated coefficients.&#13;
It is quite appealing to start, as the most recent literature&#13;
suggests, 1/ from the theoretical premise that there is a political market for&#13;
protection, in which the suppliers and demanders of protection behave in terms&#13;
1/ See K. Anderson and R. E. Baldwin, "The Political Market for Protection in&#13;
Industrial Countries: Some Empirical Evidence," World Bank Staff Working&#13;
Paper No. 492, Washington, D.C., October 1981.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
of (net) benefit maximization (re-election benefits for the suppliers and&#13;
economic benefits for the demanders). The market model implies that there is&#13;
an "equilibrium" structure of protection to be explained and that demand and&#13;
supply factors can be more clearly differentiated and accounted for. However,&#13;
at the empirical stage, identification has been a problem.      This problem is&#13;
common with models that assume a market mechanism in which both the quantity&#13;
offered and the quantity demanded depend on the market price. The only&#13;
solution is to specify a model that incorporates both sides of the market.&#13;
In this analysis of the political market for protection in Italy,&#13;
rather than specifying and estimating a complete model, the approach was to&#13;
adopt a specification that emphasizes the demand side of the market and to&#13;
test it empirically, with clear recognition of its limitations.      Protection&#13;
was addressed in its two basic dimensions:       the rate of tariff protection&#13;
afforded at the EC level, and the rate of subsidy assistance afforded at the&#13;
national  level.    The rate of tariff protection was explained       by import&#13;
penetration variables that reflect the degree of the EC countries' exposure to&#13;
import competition from non-EC sources and therefore, by proxy, the factors&#13;
that are likely to trigger a common demand for protection. On the other hand,&#13;
the rate of subsidy assistance (the more endogenous component of industrial&#13;
protection)   was  explained   by  variables   that   reflect  domestic   demand&#13;
determinants more directly.&#13;
Even this model relies on the signs of the estimated coefficients of&#13;
the variables used to explain the rate of subsidy assistance to the domestic&#13;
industry to interpret the overall function as a demand one.        However, the&#13;
implicit assumption that a supply of assistance automatically responds to&#13;
changes in demand did not seem a priori to be out of line in the Italian&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
context.   Given the lack of transparency of the commercial policy decision-&#13;
making process, the absence of an organized consumer movement that protects&#13;
consumers from the "hidden" costs of industrial assistance, and the ever-&#13;
present, officially sanctioned free trade posture of the economic and&#13;
political establishment, 1/ the political costs of disguised protectionist&#13;
measures seem to be very limited.&#13;
1/  See E. R. Grilli, "Italian Commercial Policies in the 1970s," World Bank&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 428, Washington, D.C., October 1980.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
Chapter II&#13;
THE STRUCTURE OF PROTECTION FOR THE MAJOR INDUSTRIAL&#13;
SECTORS IN ITALY&#13;
To quantify the structure of industrial protection in Italy, it was&#13;
first necessary to estimate the nominal and effective rates of tariff&#13;
protection, as well as the rates of subsidy assistance granted to the&#13;
industrial sectors included in the sample.       The effective tariff rate was&#13;
estimated using the sector breakdown and technical coefficients provided in&#13;
the 1975 input-output matrix of the Italian economy.     The effective rates of&#13;
subsidy assistance to the same sectors were also estimated, using data on the&#13;
direct and indirect subsidies (including export subsidies) granted by the&#13;
government that were contained in the inter-industry table.        The effective&#13;
rates of tariff protection (ERTP) and of subsidy assistance (SUB) were&#13;
estimated for 35 of the 58 industrial subsectors included in the 1975 table.&#13;
Among those excluded from the sample were energy and food products. 1/&#13;
The effective rates of tariff protection (ERTP) were computed using&#13;
the standard techniques developed in this field.    The simplest version of the&#13;
ERTP formula was used, after modifying it to allow for a differentiation&#13;
between exportables and non-traded input.     As to the former, it was assumed&#13;
that the sectoral output competes abroad at the international "free-trade"&#13;
prices, since only the internal market is being protected. Italy's membership&#13;
1/ In addition, in calculating the effective rates of protection for the 35&#13;
sectors considered here, the nominal tariffs on imports of petroleum&#13;
products and gas were put at zero because the Italian tariff legislation&#13;
provides domestic industrial users with a great many exemptions.        More&#13;
precise treatment was impossible because of the complexity of the&#13;
legislation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
in the EC means, however, not only that tariff protection is no longer being&#13;
determined at the national level, but also that tariffs are being levied only&#13;
on imports originating in non-EC countries and, similarly, that exports to EC&#13;
countries are duty-free.     The "internal" market was therefore defined      to&#13;
include the entire Community, so that the concept of exportables became&#13;
applicable to goods sold to non-EC countries and that of importables to goods&#13;
bought from outside the EC.&#13;
Non-traded goods were treated according to the Balassa method 1/ by&#13;
assuming that the tariffs on output equalled zero.         It followed that by&#13;
decomposing a non-traded input into its value-added, non-traded input and&#13;
traded input components, only the protection afforded the latter would affect&#13;
the price of the non-tradable.     In other words, only the coefficient of the&#13;
tradable inputs into non-tradables needed to be corrected according to their&#13;
relative tariffs. Although this correction should have been iterated through&#13;
a multi-stage procedure, it was possible to get a good approximation by&#13;
considering only the first two stages of the computation.&#13;
Thus the formula used to calculate the effective rate of tariff&#13;
protection (ERTP) was:&#13;
1/ See B. Balassa, The Structure of Protection in Developing Countries,&#13;
Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1971.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
ERTP                                                                             -1&#13;
j    l-E j      NC _     amj      E v  a     E Z,a    ,a ,     E     mn  n;      (1)&#13;
1 + t + El M m         1+t  - n  n  nj  n n  nn   n'j  -imn     1 + t&#13;
j                  m                                            m&#13;
where:    aij  =  input-output coefficient; 1/&#13;
ENC  =   share of production exported to non-EC countries;&#13;
j&#13;
tj  =  nominal tariff on the jth product;&#13;
m  =  traded inputs;&#13;
v  =  value-added coefficient; and&#13;
n, n'  =  non-traded inputs.&#13;
Of the non-tariff protective devices used by Italy, of which the most&#13;
important have been quantitative restrictions and subsidies, only the latter&#13;
were considered directly.     Because of the lack of suitable price data, the&#13;
"tariff-equivalent" implicit in the quantitative restrictions in force in 1975&#13;
outside the agricultural sector could not be calculated. However, to gain at&#13;
least a qualitative      appreciation  of the   importance  of the quantitative&#13;
restrictions   in the 35 industrial sectors considered here, a computation of&#13;
the percentage shares of the items included in each sector covered by a&#13;
quantitative restriction was made. 2/&#13;
1/  The aii coefficients were computed from the 84 sectors of the 1975 Italian&#13;
inter-sectoral table, which is available only at producers' prices.       The&#13;
inter-industry flows therefore include taxes but exclude subsidies.       The&#13;
implicit assumption made in using this formula was that the tax structure&#13;
did not affect the "free trade" coefficients (ail)&#13;
l+t&#13;
2/ More specifically, this procedure was applied to the more than 7,000&#13;
products included in the Italian version of the NIMEXE classification.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
The results are shown in Table 1, which also contains the nominal&#13;
tariff rates.   A clear shortcoming of these coverage indicators is that they&#13;
do not take into account the importance and effectiveness of the restrictions.&#13;
On the whole, however, outside the textile, clothing and motor vehicle&#13;
industries, the quantitative import restrictions do not seem to have been&#13;
particularly important in Italy in the mid-1970s.&#13;
Government subsidies to all the 35 industrial sectors included in the&#13;
sample were taken into account, instead, and their effective importance&#13;
estimated.   The data on the subsidies, derived from the 1975 inter-industry&#13;
table, included public contributions to production as well as to exports. The&#13;
formula used to quantify the effective rate of subsidy assistance (SUB) to&#13;
industry was analogous to the previous one:&#13;
S.&#13;
SUBj  NC     3                                            ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~(2)&#13;
j  E  E   NC       - a      v   anv  - a   £,a               amnanj&#13;
1 +    t   j    m l + t   n           n n  n n    n  j    m n  l + t&#13;
where:        =  the ratio of subsidies to production;&#13;
ENC = share of production exported to non-EC countries;&#13;
i&#13;
ti  =  nominal tariff on the jth product;&#13;
m  =   traded inputs;&#13;
v  =  value-added coefficient; and&#13;
n, n'  =   non-traded inputs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
Table 1: NOMINAL TARIFFS AND PRODUCT COVERACE OF QUANTITATIVE&#13;
RESTRICTIONS IN ITALY, 1975&#13;
Product                              Within Sector&#13;
Nominal               Nominal              coverage of         Number of         coefficients of&#13;
tariffs               tariffs              quantitative        products       correlation between&#13;
Sectors                                         (simple average)    (weighted average) /a     restrictions     in each sector    nominal tariffs and&#13;
Import values&#13;
&#133;     ---------------------- (S) --------------------------&#13;
Ferrous metals (extraction and&#13;
preliminary processing)                             7.07                  5.90                  21.99              302                 -.183&#13;
Non-ferrous metals (extraction and&#13;
preliminary processing)                             5.18                  2.03                   4.50              240                  -.128&#13;
Non-metalliferous minerals (extraction&#13;
and preliminary processing)                         2.32                  0.56                   0.68              117                  -.154&#13;
Cement and related products                            6.17                  6.90                   4.21               38                   .104&#13;
Clay products and ceramics                             7.81                  8.09                  14.40               75                   .043&#13;
Class and glassware                                    8.65                  9.24                   5.05               99                   .077&#13;
Primary chemicals (excluding fibers)                  10.40                 10.61                   5.92              804                   .015&#13;
Secondary chemicals                                    9.20                 10.75                   7.08              305                   .129&#13;
Pharmaceutical products                                9.05                  9.19                   5.61               57                   .010&#13;
Manmade fibers                                         8.75                  9.02                  23.05               59                   .097&#13;
Metal products (excluding machinery&#13;
and transport equipment)                            7.50                  7.90                   5.00              392                   .078&#13;
Agricultural machinery                                 6.32                  9.44                   9.18               61                   .394&#13;
Machine tools                                          6.14                  6.40                  23.66              584                  -.059&#13;
Office machinery (including data processing&#13;
and instrument engineering)                         8.70                  8.27                  10.04              251                  .045&#13;
Electric machinery                                     9.99                  13.10                 15.60               50                   .320&#13;
Electrical and telecommunication machinery             7.60                  8.90                  11.60              338                   .216&#13;
Motor vehicles (including parts and&#13;
accessories)                                       12.52                  12.54                 43.21               56                   .001&#13;
Cycles and motorcycles (including parts&#13;
and accessories)                                    8.71                  9.92                  22.86               28                   .206&#13;
Railway equipment                                      5.65                  5.28                   0.00               24                 -.284&#13;
Shipbuilding                                           1.52                  0.77                   0.80               25                 -.233&#13;
Aerospace equipment                                    6.75                  5.43                   9.00               20                 -.372&#13;
Spinning and weaving of textile fibers&#13;
(including upholstery and carpets)                 11.26                  9.81                  35.59              562                 -.082&#13;
Knitting goods                                        16.46                  15.71                 48.61              144                  -.139&#13;
Clothing                                              13.81                  13.71                 42.87              223                 -.007&#13;
Tanning and dressing of leather                        3.87                  4.55                   5.13               39                   .133&#13;
Leather products                                       8.60                  9.04                   0.00               31                   .127&#13;
Footwear                                              12.40                  11.55                 16.57               35                  -.101&#13;
Timber and wooden products (excluding&#13;
furniture)                                          6.66                   1.96                  2.17              120                 -.184&#13;
Wooden furniture                                       8.33                  8.33                   0.00               23                   .008&#13;
Pulp and paper                                         9.22                  3.78                  12.09               91                  -.383&#13;
Paper and board products                              12.15                  8.51                   0.86               70                  -.457&#13;
Printing and publishing                                5.67                  3.59                   0.00               23                 -.211&#13;
Rubber products                                        7.62                  8.35                  13.02               63                   .098&#13;
Plastic products                                      15.57                  16.76                  9.46              112                   .146&#13;
Miscellaneous manufactures                             7.98                  9.37                   2.50              168                   .133&#13;
/a Import values used as weights.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
Before analyzing in some detail the sectoral structure of the ERTP,&#13;
it is worth commenting briefly on the t'ariff-averaging method used here to&#13;
aggregate the nominal tariffs of the more than 7,000 items (corresponding to&#13;
the Italian version of the NIMEXE classification)       of relevance to the 35&#13;
industrial sectors considered here. Because import data were available at the&#13;
same level of detail as that of the nominal tariffs, it was possible to choose&#13;
between two methods of averaging: simple or weighted, in which the weights&#13;
would be the relative imports. 1/ Either of these averaging methods, however,&#13;
would still have introduced some bias in the aggregation. 2/&#13;
Simple averaging is preferable where the correlation between the&#13;
height of nominal tariffs and the value of the imports is negative. To weigh&#13;
the nominal rates by import shares would, in this case, seriously bias the&#13;
estimates.   On the other hand, if economic operators react to the effective&#13;
and not to the nominal rates of tariff protection, the sign of the correlation&#13;
between the height of nominal tariffs and import values should not be&#13;
systematically negative.&#13;
The data allowed for some interesting statistical checks. In most of&#13;
the 35 industrial sectors included in the sample, no systematic inverse cor-&#13;
relation was found between the nominal tariffs and import values (Table 1).&#13;
There was some evidence, even if not decisive, of a negative correlation in&#13;
metals and minerals, railway, shipbuilding and aerospace, and paper and&#13;
1/ The "optimal" averaging procedure would have involved weighting the mean&#13;
of the tariffs by domestic consumption.      It could not be used because&#13;
consumption data were not available at the same level of disaggregation as&#13;
those for the tariffs.&#13;
2/ See G. Basevi, "Aggregation Problems in the Measurement of Effective&#13;
Protection," in M. G. Grubel and H. G. Johnson, eds., Effective Tariff&#13;
Protection, Geneva: Graduate Institute of International Studies, 1971.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
printing. This lack of a significant inverse correlation in most sectors led&#13;
to a preference for weighted as opposed to simple averages in the tariff&#13;
aggregation. The weights were the import shares from all sources, including&#13;
those from EC countries to which no tariffs were applicable.&#13;
The estimates of the average nominal tariff rates, effective tariff&#13;
rates and effective rates of subsidy assistance are summarized in Table 2. In&#13;
addition to textiles and clothing, the sectors that appear to have been&#13;
protected the most were those that produced primary and secondary chemicals,&#13;
plastics and pulp paper.      The effective rates of subsidy assistance were&#13;
highest in the shipbuilding and manmade fibers sectors, both of which are&#13;
largely controlled by state-owned enterprises. On the other hand, as shown in&#13;
Table 1, non-tariff protection measures appeared to have been most numerous in&#13;
textiles and clothing, reflecting the effects of the Multi-Fibre Arrangement&#13;
and in the motor vehicle sector.     Imports of ferrous metals, manmade fibers&#13;
and machine tools were also subject to a fairly high number of quantitative&#13;
restrictions in the mid-1970s.&#13;
Nominal and effective rates of protection were found to be fairly&#13;
strongly correlated (with a rank correlation coefficient of 0.853). In 23 of&#13;
the 35 industrial sectors considered here, the effective rates of tariff&#13;
protection turned out to have been higher than the corresponding nominal&#13;
rates, thus revealing that the tariffs had the typical "escalation" effect:&#13;
final goods were more protected than intermediate products (Table 2).       This&#13;
difference is most evident in building materials, chemicals, textiles and&#13;
clothing, and in some other final products such as furniture, paper and board&#13;
products and plastic manufactures.&#13;
In only two cases -- shipbuilding and leather tanning and dressing --&#13;
was there significant "negative protection." Shipbuilding, as previously&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 2:  NOMINAI. RATE OF TARIFF PROTECTION (NT),/a EFFECTIVE RATE OF TARIFF PROTECTION (ERTP)&#13;
AND EFFECTIVE RATE OF SUBSIDY ASSISTANCE (SUB) IN ITALY, 1975&#13;
(percent)&#13;
Sectors                                                                                  NT             ERTP         SUB&#13;
Ferrous metals (extraction and preliminary processing)                                  5.90             9.30        0.43&#13;
Non-ferrous metals (extraction and preliminary processing)                              2.03            3.61         1.00&#13;
Non-metalliferous minerals (extraction and preliminary processing)                      0.56           -0.30         0.46&#13;
Cement and related products                                                             6.90           14.31         0.90&#13;
Clay products and ceramics                                                              8.09            13.09        0.72&#13;
Glass and glassware                                                                     9.24            14.86        0.77&#13;
Primary chiemicals (excluding fibers)                                                  10.61            20.96        2.61&#13;
Secondary chemicals                                                                    10.75            16.87        0.51&#13;
Pharmaceutical products                                                                 9.19            10.66        0.53&#13;
Manmade fibers                                                                          9.02             8.59       34.79&#13;
Metal products (excluding machinery and transport equipment)                            7.90             9.30        1.05&#13;
Agricultural machinery                                                                  9.44             9.73        1.77&#13;
Machine tools                                                                           6.40             2.39        0.89&#13;
Office machinery (including data processing and instrument engineering)                 8.27             7.12        1.57&#13;
Electric machinery                                                                     13.10            14.83        0.53&#13;
Electrical and telecommunication machinery                                              8.90             9.61        0.69&#13;
Motor vehicles (including parts and accessories)                                       12.54            13.77        0.81&#13;
Cycles and motorcycles (including parts and accessories)                                9.92           12.08         0.75&#13;
Railway equipment                                                                       5.28             5.17        0.02&#13;
Shipbuilding                                                                            0.77           -6.39        16.18&#13;
Aerospace equipment                                                                     5.43             1.86        0.01&#13;
Spinning and weaving of textile fibers (including upholstery and carpet)                9.81           11.88         1.05&#13;
Knitttng goods                                                                         15.71           22.57         0.31&#13;
Clothing                                                                               13.71            19.86        0.91&#13;
Tanning and dressing of leather                                                         4.55           -9.06         1.94&#13;
Leather products                                                                        9.04             7.70        1.48&#13;
Footwear                                                                               11.55           13.83         1.82&#13;
Timber and wooden products (excLuding furniture)                                        1.96            0.89         0.90&#13;
Wooden furniture                                                                        8.33           12.04         1.00&#13;
Pulp and paper                                                                          3.78            4.98         4.55&#13;
Paper and board products                                                                8.51            16.73        0.73&#13;
Printing and publishing                                                                 3.59            3.34         0.29&#13;
Rubber products                                                                         8.35            7.92         0.23&#13;
Plastic products                                                                       16.76           28.44         0.36&#13;
Miiscellaneous mantifactures                                                            9.32           13.03         2.91&#13;
/a Nominal tariff weighted by import values.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
observed, has been subsidized strongly in Italy, while the output of the&#13;
leather tanning and dressing sector represents an intermediate input into the&#13;
leather products and footwear sectors, which exhibited a relatively high&#13;
degree of effective tariff protection. A negative, if weak, protection effect&#13;
was evident in the case of manmade fibers, a sector that is dominated by&#13;
state-owned or state-controlled enterprises and for which the effective rates&#13;
of subsidy assistance have been very high. In the machine tool sector, the&#13;
effective rates of protection appear to have been significantly lower than the&#13;
nominal rates.&#13;
In general, then, for all the sectors that produced capital goods,&#13;
the effective rates of protection were either lower or only marginally higher&#13;
than the nominal rates, an outcome that is not unusual. A similar pattern of&#13;
results was obtained in earlier calculations of the effective rates of&#13;
protection for the investment goods industries of Great Britain and the&#13;
Federal Republic of Germany. 1/&#13;
The interpretation of these last results is not straightforward,&#13;
however.    A partial   explanation  is the relatively    low degree   of  price&#13;
competitiveness in these sectors. Further, if it can be assumed that there is&#13;
a relatively high degree of non-homogeneity of products and of vertical&#13;
integration of production processes in these sectors, it follows that&#13;
entrepreneurs might have relatively little concern for the tariff structure.&#13;
In the case of non-homogeneous products, non-price factors could per se&#13;
protect domestic production from similar, but qualitatively different, foreign&#13;
1/ See W. M. Corden and G. Fels, eds., Public Assistance to Industry:&#13;
Protection and Subsidies in Great Britain and Germany, London: MacMillan,&#13;
1976. In the case of Great Britain, this phenomenon has been particularly&#13;
evident when the ERTP formula has been modified to take exportables into&#13;
account, according to the method adopted here.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
goods.   In addition, the likely existence of "'breaking-up costs' resulting&#13;
from separating vertically related processes" should reduce, to some extent,&#13;
the production costs in an integrated industry relative to the cost of&#13;
processing imported inputs. 1/&#13;
The analysis of the sensitivity of the ERTP to changes in the nominal&#13;
tariffs revealed another pattern specific to the capital good sectors.       The&#13;
variations of the effective rate of protection in each sector were calculated&#13;
by assuming a change of 1 percentage point in the nominal tariff of each of&#13;
the 35 sectors (Table 3).    The results showed that the capital goods sectors&#13;
would have suffered a loss in effective protection when there was a uniform&#13;
increase in the nominal tariffs:     the increases in the costs of the inputs&#13;
would have more than compensated for the higher protection given to the&#13;
output.   The sensitivity analysis also indicated that a uniform reduction in&#13;
the tariff structure would have had a relatively minor effect on the&#13;
mechanical and engineering industry, but would have reduced more strongly the&#13;
effective protection provided to the other sectors (namely, chemicals and&#13;
plastics, building materials and the sectors that supply intermediate inputs&#13;
to the leather, footwear, clothing and printing industries).        The opposite&#13;
result would have held in the case of a uniform increase in the tariff&#13;
structure.&#13;
1/  See W. M. Corden, The Theory of Protection, Oxford:        Oxford University&#13;
Press, 1971.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
Table 3: CUMULATIVE EFFECT ON SECTOR ERTP OF A UNIFORM ONE PERCENTAGE&#13;
POINT CHANGE IN THE NOMINAL TARIFF /a&#13;
% change in&#13;
Sectors                                                              sector ERTP&#13;
Ferrous metals (extraction and preliminary processing                    1.678&#13;
Non-ferrous metals (extraction and preliminary processing)               1.594&#13;
Non-metalliferous minerals (extraction and preliminary&#13;
processing)                                                            1.032&#13;
Cement and related products                                              1.712&#13;
Clay products and ceramics                                               1.366&#13;
Glass and glassware                                                      1.484&#13;
Primary chemicals (excluding fibers)                                     1.998&#13;
Secondary chemicals                                                      1.611&#13;
Pharmaceutical products                                                  1.338&#13;
Manmade fibers                                                           0.858&#13;
Metal products (excluding machinery and transport equipment)             0.920&#13;
Agricultural machinery                                                   0.589&#13;
Machine tools                                                            0.449&#13;
Office machinery (including data processing and instrument&#13;
engineering)                                                           0.869&#13;
Electric machinery                                                       0.923&#13;
Electrical and telecommunication machinery                               0.882.&#13;
Motor vehicles (including parts and accessories)                         0.568&#13;
Cycles and motorcycles (including parts and accessories)                 0.691&#13;
Railway equipment                                                        1.103&#13;
Shipbuilding                                                             1.075&#13;
Aerospace equipment                                                      0.524&#13;
Spinning and weaving of textile fibers (including&#13;
upholstery and carpet)                                                 1.331&#13;
Knitting goods                                                           0.918&#13;
Clothing                                                                 1.163&#13;
Tanning and dressing of leather                                          2.255&#13;
Leather products                                                         0.799&#13;
Footwear                                                                 1.541&#13;
Timber and wooden products (excluding furniture)                         1.340&#13;
Wooden furniture                                                         1.083&#13;
Pulp and paper                                                           1.793&#13;
Paper and board products                                                 1.187&#13;
Printing and publishing                                                  1.209&#13;
Rubber products                                                          1.072&#13;
Plastic products                                                         1.245&#13;
Miscellaneous manufactures                                               0.672&#13;
/a Nominal tariff weighted by import values.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
Chapter III&#13;
THE DETERMINANTS OF THE INTER-INDUSTRY STRUCTURE&#13;
OF PROTECTION IN ITALY&#13;
The overall rate of protection afforded Italian industry can be&#13;
thought of as the sum of three components:        the effective rate of tariff&#13;
protection (ERTP), the "rate" of non-tariff protection (RNTP) and the&#13;
effective rate of subsidy assistance (SUB). Since only ERTP and SUB could be&#13;
quantified, the left-hand side variable of the model used only a proxy for the&#13;
inter-industry structure of effective assistance. On the whole, however, the&#13;
evidence suggested that the distortions that would result from the lack of&#13;
RNTP information should not be too great, particularly since the cross-section&#13;
analysis on the determinant of the inter-industry rates of effective&#13;
assistance   was  performed   for  1975,   at  the   very  beginning   of  "neo-&#13;
protectionism.." 1/&#13;
Of the two basic components of industrial protection, ERTP can be&#13;
considered as relatively "exogenous."      As tariff rates are set at the EC&#13;
level, the inter-industry structure of tariff protection is in essence&#13;
given.    Italy can resort only to substitute measures, such as non-tariff&#13;
protection and direct or indirect government assistance to industry. SUB then&#13;
became the "autonomous" component of the total.      This key characteristic of&#13;
protection in a country like Italy, which belongs to an economic union, has to&#13;
be taken into account in specifying the determinants of the overall structure&#13;
of effective assistance to industry. These can be thought of as belonging to&#13;
two different sets: the first related to the EC market (the "enlarged" sales&#13;
1/ See Grilli, op. cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
outlet for Italian industrial products), the second having to do more with the&#13;
structural traits of the domestic industry.&#13;
The effective rate of tariff protection can be assumed to be&#13;
responsive to both sets of factors only to the extent that there exists a&#13;
similarity of interest among EC members as to the sectors that need tariff&#13;
protection,   or,  more  specifically,  to   the  extent  that  the   industrial&#13;
structures of the various member countries share common characteristics.     The&#13;
community of interests is likely to be stronger wherever imports from non-EC&#13;
countries "encroach" upon domestic industrial production.       From the single&#13;
country standpoint, the variables that were hypothesized as proxies for this&#13;
aspect of the demand for protection were the share of domestic production&#13;
exported to other EC countries (EXEECSH) and the penetration of domestic&#13;
markets by non-EC exporters (defined as the share of non-EC country exports in&#13;
domestic consumption). The import penetration variable was in turn split into&#13;
two components to reflect the degree of processing of imports:     intermediate&#13;
inputs (IMNEECISH) and final goods (IMNEECFSH).&#13;
The escalation characteristic of the tariff structure suggested that&#13;
IMNEECISH should be negatively related to the ERTP, while IMNEECFSH should be&#13;
positively related   to it.    EXEECSH,  which reflects the importance of EC&#13;
markets for Italian producers and, hence, their incentive to ask for tariff&#13;
protection at the EC level, should also be positively related to the ERTP.&#13;
The effective rate of subsidy assistance was assumed to depend on the&#13;
labor intensity of production, proxied by labor's share of the value added&#13;
(LSH)  and  on  the value-added   share of output    (VASH);    these variables&#13;
represent the willingness of workers and entrepreneurs, respectively, to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
contribute to the lobbying efforts of their industry.       1/   Because of the&#13;
weight of the trade unions in Italy, normally there should be a strong degree&#13;
of political and social support for workers' demand for assistance, and even&#13;
more so in those sectors where the importance of labor is greater.      LSH was,&#13;
therefore, hypothesized to be positively related to the level of protection&#13;
received by a sector.     It was further assumed that the lower the share of&#13;
value added in production, the higher would be the gains that entrepreneurs&#13;
would receive from a lobbying effort that resulted in government assistance.&#13;
As such, VASH was expected to be negatively related to the left-hand side&#13;
variable of the model.&#13;
It was hypothesized that the effective rate of subsidy assistance to&#13;
industry  in  Italy  depended on some additional     factors.   Because of the&#13;
dualistic nature of the Italian economy -- with a relatively less developed&#13;
industrial structure in the southern areas -- the regional location of&#13;
industrial activity was thought to have some influence on the level of&#13;
protection through subsidy assistance.    The variable used as a proxy for the&#13;
regional distribution of industrial activity was the share of workers employed&#13;
in the poorer southern regions in each industrial sector (POORREGSH).       This&#13;
variable should account for the additional strength in the demand for&#13;
protection   deriving  from   the  physical   location  of  production   in  the&#13;
economically weaker regions.&#13;
The results of the cross-section analysis using this model are shown&#13;
in Table 4.     The  empirical  findings  seem to conform quite well      to the&#13;
assumptions. All the variables included in the "demand" equation showed&#13;
1/ See Anderson and Baldwin, op. cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 4: DETERMINANTS OF THE EFFECTIVE RATE OF ASSISTANCE IN ITALY&#13;
\    ExplanatoryTetsaiic&#13;
variables                                                                                                              Tetsaitc&#13;
\               ~~~~~Constant  IMNEECFSH   IMNEECISH     EXEECSH         ISH          VASH      POORREGSH          R      SEE       F&#13;
Dependent &#13;
variables\&#13;
ERTP + SUB                      .042         .067        -.365 /a        .231         .399 /a       -.306 /a                  .495    .0638    7.67&#13;
(.58)       (1.10)      (-3.09)         (1.68)       (4.20)         (2.50)&#13;
ERTP + SUB                      .065                     -.365 /a        .224         .387 /a       -.330 /a                  .491    .0641    9.21&#13;
(.94)                  (-3.08)          (1.63)       (4.09)        (-2.72)&#13;
ERTP + SUB                      .196         .067        -.423 /a        .297 /a      .396 /a       -.284 /a      .206 /a     .562    .0595    8.26&#13;
(2.08)       (1.19)      (-3.75)         (2.27)       (4.47)        (-2.47)       (2.32)&#13;
ERTP + SUB                      .219                     -.423 /a        .290 /a      .384 /a       -.307 /a      .206 /a     .555    .0599    9.49&#13;
(2.35)                   (-3.72)         (2.20)       (4.33)        (-2.70)       (2.31)&#13;
/a Significant at the 5Z level.&#13;
Note: The t values are in parentheses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
the expected sign at acceptable levels of statistical significance, except for&#13;
IMNEECFSH. The results suggest that, overall, the structure of protection has&#13;
been more directed to ensuring low prices for industrial inputs from non-EC&#13;
countries than to protecting the domestic market from the competition of final&#13;
goods originating in the same countries.     The demand side interpretation of&#13;
this equation also seems to have been confirmed by the good performance of the&#13;
variables representing the labor intensity and value-added share of the&#13;
turnover (LSH and VASH). Finally, the structure of protection in Italy seems&#13;
to have favored production by the southern industries, as shown by the&#13;
significance of the regional concentration variable (POORREGSH).&#13;
To test whether the attribution of the two sets of determinants to&#13;
the two main protective devices considered here -- tariffs and government&#13;
subsidies -- -was correct, the same model was re-estimated with ERTP and SUB as&#13;
the separate left-hand side variables.    The results (Table 5) seem to confirm&#13;
the a priori hypothesis.     More specifically,  the two variables that mostly&#13;
reflect the sectoral structure of the domestic industry (LSH and VASH) do not&#13;
seem to have played any significant role In the explanation of the effective&#13;
rates of tariff protection granted at the EC level. However, they have a high&#13;
explanatory power in the equation concerning the effective rates of subsidy&#13;
assistance  granted   at  the  national  level.     Conversely,  the  trade  and&#13;
penetration variables (IMNEECISH and EXEECSH) that are most significant in&#13;
explaining the effective rates of tariff protection do not seem to have played&#13;
the same role in explaining the effective rates of subsidy assistance.&#13;
Instead, the relative weight of the locational variable was more dubious:&#13;
POORREGSH consistently showed the expected positive sign, but was never&#13;
significant in explaining either ERTP or SUB; Its contribution to the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 5: DETERMINANTS OF THE EFFECTIVE RATE OF TARIFF PROTECTION (ERTP)&#13;
AND OF THE EFFECTIVE RATE OF SUBSIDIZATION (SUB) IN ITALY&#13;
\       ~~Explanatory&#13;
\   variables                                                                                                  Test statistics&#13;
\               ~~~~~Constant  IMNEECFSH  IMNEECISH      EXEECSH      LSH        VASH      POORREGSH      R2     SEE       F&#13;
Dependent\&#13;
variables &#13;
ERTP                            .257 /a     .063       -.317 /a        .303 /b   -.027       -.100        .148        .146   .0714    1.97&#13;
(2.27)        (.95)     (-2.33)         (1.93)     (-.26)      (-.73)     (1.38)&#13;
ERTP                            .206 /a     .074       -.319 /a        .300 /b                            .154        .186   .0697    2.94&#13;
(2.43)       (1.14)     (-2.43)         (1.99)                            (1.48)&#13;
ERTP                            .200 /a     .075       -.274 /a        .252                                           .155   .0711    3.07&#13;
(2.41)       (1.14)     (-2.11)         (1.68)&#13;
SUB                           -.061         .004       -.106          -.006        .424 /a   -.184 /a     .059        .640    .0374  11.11&#13;
(-1.03)        (.11)     (-1.50)         (-.08)     (7.59)     (-2.55)     (1.05)&#13;
SUB                           -.080                                               .413 /a    -.183 /a     .040        .649   .0370   21.99&#13;
(-1.44)                                             (7.74)     (-2.60)      (.76)&#13;
SUB                           -.109 /a                                             .413 /a   -.187 /a                 .654    .0367  33.14&#13;
(-2.78)                                             (7.79)     (-2.70)&#13;
/a Significant at the 5% level.&#13;
/b Significant at the 10 level.&#13;
Note: The t values are in parentheses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
explanation   of  the   structure   of  assistance   to  Italian   industry  was&#13;
statistically significant only at the aggregate level.&#13;
To test the validity of the assumption that the subsidy component of&#13;
the overall rate of assistance to industry in Italy was relatively endogenous,&#13;
a final check was performed by testing a recursive formulation of the model in&#13;
which ERTP was introduced directly as an explanatory variable of SUB.       This&#13;
was equivalent to subsuming under ERTP the effect of the import penetration&#13;
and "enlarged" market variables (IMNEECFSH, IMNEECISH and EXEECSH).&#13;
The results of this test appear in Table 6.      The effective rate of&#13;
tariff protection is shown to have influenced significantly, and in the&#13;
expected direction, the effective rates of subsidy assistance to industry:&#13;
the higher the ERTP, the lower the SUB.    Moreover, the sign and the values of&#13;
the coefficients of both the LSH and VASH variables were invariant to the new&#13;
specification.   While the POORREGSH variable continued to exhibit the right&#13;
sign,  the level of statistical significance was weak.        Finally, when the&#13;
nominal rate of tariff protection (NT) was used instead of the effective rates&#13;
(ERTP) as a right-hand side variable, the regression lost some explanatory&#13;
power.&#13;
These results seem to lend some empirical support to the hypothesis&#13;
that economic agents react more to the effective than to the nominal rates of&#13;
tariff protection.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 6: A RECURSIVE SPECIFICATION OF THE EFFECTIVE RATE OF ASSISTANCE&#13;
MODEL FOR ITALY&#13;
Explanatory&#13;
variables                                                                                                Test statistics&#13;
-2&#13;
Constant           NT          ERTP           LSH         VASH         POORREGSH        R      SEE      F&#13;
Dependent&#13;
variables&#13;
SUB                           -.083 /a                      -.156 /b       .408 /a      -.207 /a                    .683   .0352   25.40&#13;
(-2.09)                       (-1.97)        (8.03)       (-3.08)&#13;
SUB                           -.080 /b      -.278 /b                       .415 /a      -.206 /a                    .674   .0356   24.51&#13;
(-1.91)        (-1.74)                       (8.07)       (-3.02)&#13;
SUB                           -.048                         -.161 /a       .408 /a      -.203 /a       .047         .681   .0353   19.17&#13;
(-.87)                       (-2.03)        (8.01)       (-2.99)         (.92)&#13;
SUB                           -.060         -.267                           .415 /a     -.202 /a       .029         .667   .0360   18.06&#13;
(-1.07)       (-1.64)                         (7.98)      (-2.91)         (.56)&#13;
/a Significant at the 5% level.&#13;
7T Significant at the 10% level.&#13;
Note: The t values are in parentheses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
Chapter IV&#13;
CONCLUSIONS&#13;
The results of this analysis support the notion that, in Italy, the&#13;
dichotomous nature of the assistance variable, defined as the sum of ERTP and&#13;
SUB, is of critical importance. Civen the rate of tariff protection (which is&#13;
fixed at the EC level), the demand for subsidy assistance at the national&#13;
level assumes rather clearcut autonomous contours.&#13;
Two different sets of determinants could be assigned to the two&#13;
components of overall assistance to industry. Specifically, it was found that&#13;
the effective tariff rates have protected Italian exports in the EC markets&#13;
and guarded to a lesser extent against the penetration of non-EC exports of&#13;
final goods into the domestic markets.      It was also found that the subsidy&#13;
assistance to industry granted at the national level has been significantly&#13;
influenced by the labor intensity of the production processes, as well as by&#13;
the  size  of   the  value-added  share   of  output.    Both  variables   reflect&#13;
endogenous impulses toward industrial protection.       The output of industries&#13;
located in the underdeveloped regions of the south was found to have been&#13;
protected by both tariffs and subsidies.       The lack of significance of the&#13;
regional variable (POORREGSH) in explaining the effective rate of subsidy&#13;
assistance in the recursive version of the model may well be attributable more&#13;
to its statistical inadequacy than to the protection tariffs afforded the&#13;
industrial sectors that were relatively more concentrated in the southern&#13;
regions.   Without excluding, on the basis of the evidence, the existence of a&#13;
bias in the EC tariff structure toward the protection of industrial output&#13;
located in the weak regions of the Community, it still seems that the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
importance of domestic subsidy assistance to the southern industry of Italy&#13;
needs further investigation.&#13;
Also verified empirically was the substitution relationship between&#13;
the tariff protection determined at the EC level and the subsidy assistance&#13;
determined at the national    level:    this relationship was implicit in the&#13;
definition of the overall assistance variable as the algebraic sum of ERTP and&#13;
SUB.   National authorities can take substitute measures       to protect their&#13;
industries, and indeed have done so.       What gets done in Brussels can get&#13;
undone in Rome.   The results confirmed that this substitution has taken place&#13;
in Italy. 1/&#13;
The characterization of the estimated model as a demand model implies&#13;
that Italy automatically adjusts its supply of assistance to changes in&#13;
demand. While this assumption may not be untenable on a priori grounds, given&#13;
the institutional features of this market up to the mid-197Cs, it is not&#13;
clearly tenable ad infinitum.   Even if there were no serious concern over the&#13;
specification biases exhibited by a demand equation estimated on such a basis,&#13;
the supply side of the market for protection requires more specific&#13;
attention. The rationale of public intervention in "granting" assistance to&#13;
industry needs to be made explicit.&#13;
As a final point, the lack of complete data series on subsidies to&#13;
industry made it impossible to analyze changes in the inter-industry structure&#13;
of assistance in Italy over time.     While the results of the static analysis&#13;
presented here are encouraging and interesting, a dynamic analysis of&#13;
industrial protection could provide additional insights.     It is important to&#13;
1/ This phenomenon was also noticed in West Germany. See H. P. Clismann and&#13;
F. 0. Weiss, "Evidence on the Political Economy of Protection in Germany,"&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 427, Washington, D.C., October 198C.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3C -&#13;
understand, inter alia, what factors trigger, over time, the demand for&#13;
assistance and determine its changes, how important the existing stock of&#13;
assistance is in determining its modifications, the nature and relative&#13;
importance of the instruments used to achieve various obJectives, and,&#13;
finally, the importance of the different forms of frictions that influence the&#13;
adiustment of supply to changes in protectionist pressures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
Anderson, K.     "The  Political Market for Government Assistance     to&#13;
Australian Manufacturing Industries." A paper presented to the&#13;
VII Conference of Economists, Macquarie University, Sydney,&#13;
Australia, August 1978. (A revised version appears in Economic&#13;
Record 56(153)(June 1980):132-144.)&#13;
Anderson, K. and R. E. Baldwin. "The Political Market for Protection in&#13;
Industrial Countries:   Empirical Evidence."   World Bank Staff&#13;
Working Paper No. 492. Washington, D.C., October 1981.&#13;
Balassa, B.    The Structure   of Protection in Developing Countries.&#13;
Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1971.&#13;
Baldwin, R. E. "The Political Economy of Postwar US Trade Policy." The&#13;
Bulletin (New York University Graduate School of Business&#13;
Administration), 1976-4, 1976.&#13;
Basevi, C.     "Aggregation Problems in the Measurement of Effective&#13;
Protection." In Effective Tariff Protection. Edited by H. G.&#13;
Grubel and H. G. Johnson. Geneva:        Graduate Institute of&#13;
International Studies, 1971.&#13;
Brock, W. A. and S. P. Magee.       "The Economics of Special Interest&#13;
Politics:   The Case of the Tariff." American Economic Review&#13;
Papers and Proceedings 68(2)(May 1978):246-55.&#13;
" An Economic Theory of Politics:     The Case of the Tariff."&#13;
Mimeo. 1974.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
Caves, R. E.    "Economic Models of Political Choice:      Canada's Tariff&#13;
Structure."   Canadian Journal of Economics 9(2)(May 1976):278-&#13;
300.&#13;
Corden, W. M. The Theory of Protection. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971.&#13;
Corden,  W.  M.  and G.   Fels,  eds.    Public  Assistance  to Industry:&#13;
Protection and Subsidies in Britain and Germany. London:&#13;
Westview Press, 1976.&#13;
Glismann, H. H. and F. D. Weiss. "Evidence on the Political Economy of&#13;
Protection in Germany."     World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
427. Washington, D.C., October 1980.&#13;
Grilli, E. R.    "Italian Commercial Policies in the 1970s." World Bank&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 428. Washington, D.C., October 1980.&#13;
Krueger, A. O.    "The Political Economy of the Rent-Seeking Society."&#13;
American Economic Review 64(June 1974):291-303.&#13;
Pincus, J. J. "Pressure Groups and the Patterns of Tariffs." Journal of&#13;
Political Economy 83(2)(August 1975):757-78.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
World Bank&#13;
Publications&#13;
of Related&#13;
Interest&#13;
Adjustment Policies and             Britain's Pattern of Special-        Capital-importing Ol&#13;
Problems in Developed               ization in Manufactured              Exporters: A4justment&#13;
Countries                           Goods with Developing                Issues and Policy Choices&#13;
Martin Wolf                         Countries and Trade                 Alan 11. Gelb&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  Protection                          A background study for World&#13;
349. August 1979. 236 pages (includ-  Vincent Cable and                  Development Report 1981. Uses a&#13;
Ing references).                    Ivonia Rebelo                       simple two-sector model involving&#13;
ing references).               Rebelo                       traded and nontraded goods as a&#13;
Stock lo. WP-0349. $10.00.          World Bank Staff Working Paper       conceptual framework to compare the&#13;
No. 425. October 1980. 61 pages      evolution of critical macro and sec-&#13;
(including 3 appendixes).           toral variables for a number of oil&#13;
Adjustment to External              Stock Nog WP50425 $3.00              economies after 1974 and discusses&#13;
Shocks in Developing                S      .              *              government responses to the oil&#13;
Economies                                                                crisis and the effects of these&#13;
Bela Balassa                                                            responses of the nonoil economies.&#13;
A background study for World                                             World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Development Report 1981. Analyzes                                        475. August 1981. 38 pages (including&#13;
adjustments to external shocks, In                                       9 tables).&#13;
the form of changes In the terms of                                     Stock N1o. WP-0475. $3.00.&#13;
trade and the slowdown in foreign&#13;
export demand, in twenty-eight&#13;
developing economies, classified&#13;
according to the character of extemal&#13;
shocks, the level of industrial devel-&#13;
opment, and the policies applied.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper IYo.&#13;
472. July 1981. 31 pages (including&#13;
appendix).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0472. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NEW                               The Export Experience of             Oxford University Press. 1982.&#13;
Developing Countries                  224 pages (including index).&#13;
The Developing Countries              Barend A. de Vries                    LC 82-6309. ISBN 0-19-520211-2,&#13;
and International Shipping            The English-language edition is      $22.50 (410.50) hardcover. (A specially&#13;
Hlarald Hansen                        out of print.                        priced edition will be available in India&#13;
Considers whether developing coun-    French: Resultats obtenus en mati6e  from Oxford University Press branches.)&#13;
tries can benefit from investments in  d'exportation par les pays en voie de&#13;
international shipping and discusses  developpement. Dunod Editeur, 24-26,  Industrial Country Policy&#13;
the circumstances under which such    boulevard de l'lM6pital, 75005 Paris,  and Adjustment to Imports&#13;
investment might be favorable.        France. 1969.                        from   Developing Countries&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   LC 67-28942, 10 francs.               J. M. Finger&#13;
502. November 1981. iii + 148 pages&#13;
(including 12 annexes, .38 tables,   Spanish: La experiencia de los pafses  A background study for World&#13;
en desarrollo en materia de exporta-  Development Report 1981. Reviews&#13;
bibliography).                        ciones. Editorial Tecnos, 1969.       and interprets recent analyses of the&#13;
Stock No. WP-0502. $5c00.                                                   policies established by industrial&#13;
200 pesetas.                          countries in response to increasing&#13;
imports from developing countries.&#13;
Effects of Non-Tariff Bar-            Export Promotion Policies             World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
riers to Trade on Prices,             Barend A. de Vries                    470. July 1981. ii + 20 pages (includ-&#13;
Employment, and       Imports:        World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   ing references).&#13;
Textile and Clothing S313. January 1979. v + 75 pages.                      Stock No. WP-0470. $3.00.&#13;
Industry                              Stock No. WP-0313. $3.00.&#13;
Carl Hamilton                                                               Italian Commercial Policies&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.        NEW                               in the 1970s&#13;
429. October 1980. ii + 61 pages                                            Enzo R. Grilli&#13;
(including appendLx, bibliography).   On Exports and                        World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Stock No. WP-0429. $3.00.             Economic Growth                       428. October 1980. 47 pages.&#13;
Gershon Feder                         Stock No. WP-0428. $3.00.&#13;
An analytical framework is developed&#13;
Energy, International Trade,          to analyze the sources of growth dur-&#13;
and Economic Growth                  ing the period 1964-73 for a group of  On the Political Economy of&#13;
Alan S. Manne and                     semi-industrialized developing coun-  Protection in Germany&#13;
Sehun Kim                            tries. Discusses the relationship      H. H. Glismann and&#13;
A background study for World          between export performance and        F D. Weiss&#13;
economic growth and concludes that&#13;
Development Report 1981.              growth can be generated not only by   World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Constructs a small-scale international  increases in the aggregate levels of  427. October 1980. 30 pages (includ-&#13;
trade model that focuses on issues   labor and capital but also by the      ing bibliography).&#13;
related to energy and economic        reallocation of existing resources&#13;
growth in order to determine the     from the less-efficient nonexport sec-  Stock No. WP-0427. $3.00.&#13;
extent to which increasing energy     tor to the higher-productivity export&#13;
prices impose constraints on          sector.&#13;
economic growth.                                                            Output and Employment&#13;
WoldBan Pape No.   World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    Changes In a "Trade Sensi-&#13;
Word4  an Agstaff81 Worin paper (no.uin  508. February 1982. 24 pages (includ-  tive" Sector: Adjustment In&#13;
474 August 1981. 30 pages (including  ing appendix, references).            the U.S. Footwear Industry&#13;
Stock No. WP-0474. $3.00.             Stock No. WP-0508. $3.00.             John H. Mutti and&#13;
Malcolm D. Bale&#13;
European Community                        NEW                               World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Purotetion    agaiunstyIndia'sExports                                       430. October 1980. 21 pages&#13;
Protection against                    India's Exports                       (including footnotes, references).&#13;
Manufactured Imports                  Martin Wolf                           Stock No. WP-0430. $3.00.&#13;
from  Developing Countries:           Despite improved performance, the&#13;
A Case Study in the Politi-           growth of India's exports continues to&#13;
cal Economy of Protection             lag behind need, potential, and the&#13;
E. Verreydt and                       achievements of several of its com-&#13;
J. Waelbroeck                         petitors. This study examines India's&#13;
overall export performance in the&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    1960s and 1970s, with emphasis on&#13;
432. October 1980. 25 pages.          the central role of incentives. The&#13;
Stock No. WP-0432. $3.00.             major problems and policies are&#13;
discussed, as well as current strategic&#13;
options.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NEW                               Prospects for Partnership:            The Structure of Protection&#13;
Industrialization and Trade           In Developing Countries&#13;
Patterns of Barriers to               Policies in the 1970s                 Bela Balassa and others&#13;
Trade in Sweden: A Study in           Helen Hughes, editor                  The Johns Hopkins Uniuersity Press,&#13;
the Theory of Protection              The Johns Hopkins University Press,  1971, 394 pages (including 5 appen-&#13;
Lars Lundberg                         1973. 310 pages.                      dixes, index).&#13;
This report is part of an inquiry being  LC 72-12369. ISBN 0-8018-1498-7,   LC 77-147366. ISBN 0-8018-1257-7,&#13;
undertaken by the World Bank in con-  $20.00 (£12.00) hardcover.            $25.00 (15.00) hardcover&#13;
junction with scholars from twelve&#13;
industrial countries into the penetra-  ISBN 0-8018-1500-2, $6.95 (f 4.25)  Spanish: La estructura de la protecci6n&#13;
tion of the markets of industrial     paperback.                            en paises en desarrollo. CEMLA, Depar-&#13;
countries by exports of manufactures  Spanisht Las perspectivas detcomercio  Mento de Publicaciones, Durango 54,&#13;
from developing countries.            Spns:Lsprpcia          e  oeco        Mexico 7, D.F., Mexico. 1972.&#13;
intemacional: industrializaci6n y&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    politicas comerciales en la d&amp;cada de&#13;
494. October 1981. 35 pages (including  los 70. Editorial Tecnos, 1974.     The Tokyo Round: Results&#13;
3 appendixes).                       ISBN 84-309-0497-2, 575 pesetas.       and Implications for&#13;
Stock No. WP-0494. $3.00.                                                   Developing Countries&#13;
Ria Kemper&#13;
The Political Economy of                  NEW                               World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Protection in Belgium                 On Protectionism      In              372. February 1980. iii + 35 pages&#13;
P K. M. Tharakan                      the Netherlands                       (including annex).&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper        K.A. Koekkoek. J. Kol, and            Stock No. WP-03 72. $3.00.&#13;
No. 431. October 1980. 22 pages       L.B.M. Mennes&#13;
(including statistical appendix,      This report is part of an inquiry being  Trade Adjustment Policies&#13;
references).                          undertaken by the World Bank in con-  and Income Distribution In&#13;
Stock No. WP-0431. $3.00.             junction with scholars from twelve    Three Archetype Developing&#13;
industrial countries into the penetra-  Economies&#13;
tion of the markets of Industrial     Jaime de Melo and&#13;
NEW                               countries by exports of manufactures  SherMman Robinson&#13;
from developing countries.&#13;
The Political Market for              World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Protection in Industrial              493. October 1981. ii + 68 pages      442. December 1980. 91 pages&#13;
Countries: Empirical                  (including 3 annexes, references).    (including appendixes, references).&#13;
Evidence                              Stock No. WP-0493. $3.00.             Stock No. WP-0442. $3.00.&#13;
Kym Anderson and&#13;
Robert E. Baldwin                         NEW                               Trade among Developing&#13;
This report is part of an inquiry being                                     Countries: Theory,&#13;
undertaken by the World Bank In con-&#13;
junction with scholars from twelve    Shadow Prices for Trade                Policy Issues, and&#13;
industrial countries into the penetra-  Strategy and Investment             Principal Trends&#13;
tion of the markets of industrial     Planning in Egypt                     Oli Havrylyshyn and&#13;
countries by exports of manufactures  John Page, Jr.                        Martin Wolf&#13;
from developing countries.                     g    '&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    This papdr presenats ccounting prices  Development Report 1981. Presents&#13;
492. October 1981. 28 pages (including  for commodities and factors of pro-  the results of empirical work on trade&#13;
references).                          duction in Egypt that are appropriate  among developing countries. Based&#13;
Stock No. WP-0492. $3.00.             for the period 1979-1985.             thirty-three developing countries&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    that account for about 60 percent of&#13;
521. October 1982. 212 pages.         developing countries' exports to&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0009-1. $5.00.            one another.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
479. August 1981. iv + 12 pages&#13;
Structural Change in Trade            (including 2 appendixes, references).&#13;
In Manufactured Goods                 Stock No. WP-0479. $5.00.&#13;
between Industirial and&#13;
Developing Countries&#13;
Bela Balassa&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
396. June 1980. 46 pages.&#13;
Stock No. WP-0396. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NEW                              Trade Policy for Developing          '-e'ms"&#13;
Countries                            Can Developing-Country Exports Keep&#13;
Trade and Employment                 Donald B. Keesing                    Growing In the 1980s7&#13;
Policies for Industrial              World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   World Bank Reprint Series: Number 194.&#13;
Development                         353. August 1979. vii + 264 pages     Reprinted from The World Economy (June&#13;
Keith Marsden                        (Including references).             1981J:127-47.&#13;
In the last decade, the developing  Stock No. WP-0353. $10.00.           Stock tio. RP-0194. free of charge.&#13;
countries have proved that they can&#13;
compete internationally in exporting                                      Questions on International Trade In&#13;
manufactured goods, as well as pri-  Trade Policy Issues for the          Textiles and Clothing&#13;
mary products and services. This     Developing Countries in              Donald B. Keesing and Martin Wolf&#13;
paper examines three sets of issues:  the 1980s                           World Bank Reprint Series: Number 202.&#13;
(a) whether good export performance  Isaiah Frank                         Reprinted from The World Economy, vol. 4 (March&#13;
is attributable to special characteris-                                   1981):79-101.&#13;
tics of the most successful countries  Explores the relation between trade  Stock No. RP-0202. Free of charge.&#13;
or whether their success can be      policy and "industrial policy" and&#13;
readily replicated in other countries;  calls attention to points of conflict&#13;
(b) whether the penetration of the   and compatability. Reviews the       Trade Policy and Resource&#13;
markets of industrial countries has  recently completed multilateral trade  Allocation In the Presence of Product&#13;
reached, or will soon reach, a limit;  negotiations and assesses the policy  Differentiation&#13;
and (c) whether trade in manufactures  significance for the developing coun-  Jaime de Melo and Sherman Robinson&#13;
among the developing countries can  tries during the 1980s. Takes a new   Reprinted from The Review of Economics and&#13;
expand further. Concludes with a     look at industrial policy and struc-  Statistics. vol. 63. no. 2 (May 1981):169-177.&#13;
discussion of the contribution of    tural adjustment, fair labor stan-   Stock No. RP-0214. Free of charge.&#13;
small enterprises to the creation of  dards, trade among the developing&#13;
employment and the alleviation of    countries, and trade in services.&#13;
poverty.                             World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
1982. vi + 64 pages (Including annex).  478. August 1981. 52 pages.&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0017-2. $5.00.           Stock No. WP-04 78. $3.00.&#13;
Trade in Non-Factor                  Worker Adjustment to&#13;
Services: Past Trends and            Liberalized Trade: Costs&#13;
Current Issues                       and Assistance Policies&#13;
Andre Sapir and                      Graham Glenday,&#13;
Ernst Lutz                           Glenn R Jenkins, and&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   John C. Evans&#13;
410. August 1980. iii + 137 pages    World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
(including 4 annexes).               426. October 1980. i + 86 pages&#13;
Stock No. WP-0410. $5.00.            (including 2 appendixes.&#13;
bibliography).&#13;
Trade in Services: Economic          Stock No. WP-0426. $3.00.&#13;
Determinants and Develop-&#13;
ment-Related Issues                  World Trade and Output of&#13;
Andre Sapir and                      Manufactures: Structural&#13;
Ernst Lutz                           Trends and Developing&#13;
A background study for World         Countries' Exports&#13;
Development Report 1981. Finds that  Donald B. Keesing&#13;
trade theories can help explain the  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
patterns of trade in services in spite  '316. January 1979. v + 69 pages&#13;
of varying and often substantial&#13;
degrees of protectionism. Represents  (including statistical annex).&#13;
the second stage of a research       Stock No. WP-0316. $3.00.&#13;
project on trade in services.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
480. August 1981. 38 pages (including&#13;
appendix, references).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0480. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
ORDER FORM&#13;
SEND TO:&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS                                                       WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
P.O. BOX 37525                                            or                  66, AVENUE D'IENA&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013                                                        75116 PARIS, FRANCE&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Name:&#13;
Address:&#13;
Stock or ISBN #                            Author, Title                       Oty.        Price          Total&#13;
Sub-Total Cost:&#13;
Postage &amp; handling fee for more than two free items ($1.00 each):&#13;
Total copies: _     _      Air mail surcharge ($2.00 each):&#13;
TOTAL PAYMENT ENCLOSED:&#13;
Make checks payable: WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
Prepayment on orders from individuals is requested. Purchase orders are accepted from booksellers, library suppliers, libraries, and institutions.&#13;
All prices include cost of postage by the least expensive means. The prices and publication dates quoted in this Catalog are subject to change&#13;
without notice.&#13;
No refunds will be given for items that cannot be filled. Credit will be applied towards future orders.&#13;
No more than two free publications will be provided without charge. Requests for additional copies will be filled at a charge of US $1.00 per&#13;
copy to cover handling and postage costs.&#13;
Airmail delivery will require a prepayment of US $2.00 per copy.&#13;
Mail-order payment to the World Bank need not be in U.S. dollars, but the amount remitted must be at the rate of exchange on the day the&#13;
order is placed. The World Bank will also accept Unesco coupons.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PUB HG3881.5 .W57 W67 no.567&#13;
Grilli, Enzo R.&#13;
The political economy of&#13;
protection in Italy   some&#13;
empirical evidence /&#13;
DATE    NAME AND EXTENSION  NUOMBER&#13;
PUB HG3881.5.W57 W67 no.567&#13;
Grilli, Enzo R.&#13;
The political econany of&#13;
protection in Italy : some&#13;
empirica&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters:                                                                                    _D&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                                                                                                z&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK&#13;
Cable address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
European Office:&#13;
66, avenue d'1ena&#13;
75116 Paris, France&#13;
Telephone: (1) 723-54.21                                                                                           r&#13;
Telex: 842-620628&#13;
0&#13;
Tokyo Office:&#13;
Kokusai Building&#13;
1-1, Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
Telex: 781-26838&#13;
(D&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0197-7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554879">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/07/1554879/political-economy-protection-italy-some-empirical-evidence
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/07/1554879/political-economy-protection-italy-some-empirical-evidence</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1983/07/1554879/political-economy-protection-italy-some-empirical-evidence</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/11/28/000178830_98101903415327/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/11/28/000178830_98101903415327/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1983-07-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2002-11-28T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The political economy of protection in
            Italy : some empirical evidence
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            To date, the work on decision making
            with respect to commercial policy has produced three
            principal models: the adding machine, the interest group,
            and the national policy. The explanatory power of these
            models at the country level depends critically on the
            prevailing political and institutional realities. This paper
            looks at the political economy of protection in Italy using
            a model that specifies the demand side of the market,
            despite the limitations of that approach. It addresses
            protection as embodied in the EC's rate of tariff
            protection and Italy's rate of domestic subsidy
            assistance. The empirical findings from the cross-section
            analysis of 35 industrial subsectors conformed quite well to
            the assumptions. It seems that industries in the poorer
            regions of Southern Italy were protected by both tariffs and
            subsidies. The analysis also verified the substitution
            relationship between tariff protection at the EC level and
            subsidy assistance at the national level. Finally, the
            economic agents have reacted more strongly to the effective
            than to the nominal rates of tariff protection.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The political economy of protection in Italy
            : some empirical evidence
        </docna>
        <display_title>The political economy of
            protection in Italy : some empirical evidence</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1983/07/1554879/political-economy-protection-italy-some-empirical-evidence</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Free Trade,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Export Competitiveness,Water and Industry</subtopic>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>Italy</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Grilli, Enzo</author>
            <author>La Noce, Mauro</author>
            <author>EPD</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe!$!80461</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903415327</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Other finance</subsc>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 567</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Finance</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0197-7</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Cross section analysis; Economic models; Protectionism
            autonomy,capital good,capital
            goods,comparative analysis,consumers,country
            markets,Cumulative Effect,domestic consumption,domestic
            demand,domestic industry,domestic market,domestic
            producers,domestic production,Economic Analysis,Economic
            Models,Economic Theory,economists,empirical
            evidence,employment,equilibrium,export
            subsidies,exports,final goods,Free trade,gas,Government
            subsidies,import competition,import penetration,import
            protection,import quotas,import
            restrictions,imports,industrialization,intermediate
            inputs,International Competitiveness,legislation,market
            mechanism,Metal products,metals,political
            economy,producers,production costs,production
            processes,protection measures,protectionist
            measures,protectionist pressures,Public
            Assistance,Quantitative Restrictions,rates of
            protection,static analysis,tariff policy,tariff
            protection,tariff rate,tariff rates,Tariff
            Structure,Timber,trade patterns,trade policies,Trade
            Policy,trade protection,voters
        </keywd>
        <owner>ECS</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP567</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Medical Supplies, Drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pharmaceutical Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation Equipment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Political Economy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Political Economy Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Free Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textiles</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pharmaceuticals</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport Equipment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Political Economy of Reform</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Europe</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Italy</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>