<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP-596&#13;
Prospects for Food Production and Consuinption&#13;
in Developing Countries&#13;
Malcolm D. Bale&#13;
Ronald C. Duncan&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 596&#13;
k**&#13;
JD&#13;
L4 17&#13;
.B34&#13;
1983&#13;
c2&#13;
HD1417 .B 198 c.2&#13;
Prospects for food prodUction and consumption in developing&#13;
SLC026832&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WC)RLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 596&#13;
Prospects for Food Production and Consumption&#13;
in Developing Countries&#13;
Malcolm D. Bale&#13;
Ronald C. Duncan&#13;
SECTORAL LIBRgARY&#13;
INTERANATIONAL BANK&#13;
vO-CR E°LP NlEN T&#13;
R,EC0NSTRUCTIO0N AN4D DEELPMN&#13;
pirnl 9084&#13;
INTERNATIONAL MONETARY FUND&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyrigntt igt?i&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development / THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
First printing May 1983&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
This is a working document published informally bv the World Bank. To&#13;
present the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has&#13;
not been prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal&#13;
printed texts, and the World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The&#13;
publication is supplied at a token charge to defrav part of the c(st of&#13;
manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to&#13;
any individual acting on their behalf. Anm maps used have been prepared&#13;
solely for the convenience of the readers; the denominations used and the&#13;
boundaries shown do not imply, on the part of the World Bank and its affiliates,&#13;
any judgment on the legal status of znv territory or any endorsement or&#13;
acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range o-f World KBnk publications is described in the CatahNlo of W.&#13;
RBatnk Publicatiow&gt;: the continuing research program of the Bank is outlined in&#13;
l'iirld Bank Rc~. arciv Pr(W.ranI,,r , l- tr ,wto (it Crrc utf Nfg,- lth hooklets are&#13;
updated annuallv; the most recent edition o.f each is av'ail,iblt' without charge&#13;
from the Puhli cations Distribution Lniiit (}f the ki nk in Washington or fromn the&#13;
European OTfice of the Banik. oo .avenut d lnria. -l It, l'Varl-. Fr lee.-C&#13;
NIa'llcoll 1)  1ale  iv ,111 tan   VIeIIbilli l I%   it hie  ( o'trlII  lI'rtgt.ini..  I 1k', r'trf eIt t  Hihl i&#13;
)i;aI. !  C  .  I )ule.a   aI   dwI ,  Ii  t' l  It'  III   tilt  I  o'I)  III  \a.1i   .1IIf Pri  e' W'tk'.i)&#13;
)  rt'1'.fI'tl'lt  ,I llit, ~\orld  Bank&#13;
Library of Convre%s Cataloving in Publication l)ata&#13;
Bale, Malcolm D.&#13;
Prospects for food production and consumption in&#13;
developing countries.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 596)&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
1. Underdeveloped areas--Agriculture and state.&#13;
2. Underdeveloped areas--Nutrition policy. 3. Under-&#13;
developed areas-Food consutmption. 4. Underdeveloped&#13;
areas-Food supply. 5. Underdeveloped areas--Food&#13;
prices.   I. Duncan, Ronald C., 1936-          .  II. Title.&#13;
III. Series.&#13;
HD1417.B34    1983       338.1'9'1724         83-6875&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0194-2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Abstract&#13;
This Paper analyzes recent trends in world food production and con-&#13;
sumption with special reference to developing countries. It continues by&#13;
outlining the World Bank's approach to projections of food production and&#13;
consumption providing results to the year 1995. It is shown that levels of&#13;
consumption of various food items have improved in developing countries and&#13;
are expected to continue to improve. Moreover, the results indicate favorable&#13;
prospects for food production in developing countries. The paper comments&#13;
throughout on areas whe;re further work is required to refine the projection&#13;
method and qualifies the generally optimistic outlook by identiEying the types&#13;
of actions that will be needed to accelerate food consumption and production&#13;
in developing countries. Pricing policies in agriculture are seen as being&#13;
particularly critical to the optimal development of the agricultural system in&#13;
tovpl nn ino rniintriejq.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Page No.&#13;
Introduction ..................................................             3&#13;
Historical Growth of Income and Food Consumption .......................... 4&#13;
World Bank Forecasts of' Food Consumption by 1995 ......................... 14&#13;
Price Developments ...................................................      20&#13;
Production Yields ........................................................ 24&#13;
Other Factors ..................                                           35&#13;
Table No.&#13;
1: Per Capita Food Supplies by Major Economic Regions and by Food&#13;
Category, 1961-65 (Average), and 1977 ................................ 11&#13;
2:  Foodstuffs - Projections of Apparent Consumption, by Economic&#13;
Regions ................................................................ 17&#13;
3: Projected Real GDP Growth and Population Growth, by Major Economic&#13;
Region, 1983-95 ........................................................ 18&#13;
4: Growth in Production 1961-80 (Actual) and 1980-95 (Projected), Area&#13;
Harvested and Yields 1961-80, in Main Developing Countries .26&#13;
5: Cereals - Growth in Production, Area Harvested and Yields, 1961-80.. .28&#13;
6:  Average Yields for Major Crops in Regions of the World, 1970-80 .      28&#13;
7: Nominal Protection Coefficients Calculated for Grains Production&#13;
in Developing Counl:ries                      ..                       37&#13;
Figure No.&#13;
1:  Income and Consumption Growth - 1960s Developing Countries ............ 7&#13;
2:  Income and Consumpition Growth - 1970s Developing Countries ............ 8&#13;
3: Wheat Price Indexes, 1900-1982                     ..                   21&#13;
4: Rice Price Indexes, 1900-1982                     ..                    22&#13;
5: Maize Price Indexes, 1900-1982                     ..                   23&#13;
6:  Wheat - Yield Growth Rates in Selected Major Producing Countries ... 30&#13;
7:  Coarse Grains - Yield Growth Rates in Selected Producing Countries...31&#13;
8:  Rice - Yield Growt'h Rates in Major Producing Countries       .   .     32&#13;
References: .............................................................. 40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PROSPECTS FOR FOOD P'RODUCTION AND CONSUMPTION IN DEVELOPINC COUNTRIES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
Introduction&#13;
1.       The available evidence indicates that, in aggregate, the growth in&#13;
world food production over the past two decades has more than kept pace with&#13;
the growth in population. Improvements in per capita consumpt:ion among the&#13;
developing countries have been widespread. The important exceptions have&#13;
included many of the countries of sub-Saharan Africa. Associated with this&#13;
improvement has been the adoption and success of improved technologies,&#13;
increased investment in infrastructure vital to increased agricultural pro-&#13;
duction and, for some countries, a diminishing of the price distortions which&#13;
have disadvantaged agricultural production. Substantial production increases&#13;
have been recorded particularly in the case of rice and wheat, leading to&#13;
declining actual and expected prices for grains.&#13;
2.       We believe it is likely that these improvements in food availability&#13;
in the developing countries will continue, but that any such improvements&#13;
would be considerably erthanced by widespread adoption in developing countries&#13;
of pricing policies which remove the existing distortions under which&#13;
agricultural production labors.&#13;
3.       In this paper we illustrate the changes that have occurred in food&#13;
consumption in developing countries over the past 20'years and compare them to&#13;
changes in the industrial countries. We then present the forecasts of food&#13;
consumption growth which have recently been assembled in the World Bank and&#13;
briefly outline their implications for per capita consumption, production and&#13;
prices in developing cotntries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
4.       We are not directly concerned here with the question of hunger,&#13;
whether chronic or periodic. We agree with the view that hunger is not&#13;
directly related to the level of world food availability, but is more a ques-&#13;
tion of income level, or as Sen puts it, the "entitlement" to sufficient&#13;
resources to purchase enough food to live. The many studies which the World&#13;
Bank for one has done on the cost effectiveness of programs to meet chronic&#13;
hunger among specific groups and periodic hunger due to sharp reductions in&#13;
food supplies have recently been summarized by Reutlinger, (1981/82).&#13;
Historical Growth of Income and Food Consumption&#13;
5.       The last 20 years has been a period of substantial growth for some&#13;
developing countries. The concentration of this growth can be shown as&#13;
follows: of the 68 developing countries (World Bank definition) for which&#13;
there are purchasing-power-parity (PPP) estimatesl/ of GDP/capita available,&#13;
only 19 countries recorded GDP/capita growth, in real terms, in excess of 2%&#13;
p.a. for both the 1960-70 decade and the period 1970-79. 2/ There are no PPP&#13;
estimates available for them, but to this list should probably be added Hong&#13;
Kong, Republic of Korea, Singapore and perhaps the Peoples' Republic of China.&#13;
1/ Purchasing-power-parity estimates of national income, (i.e., estimated in&#13;
terms of a set of international prices) are preferred to traditional&#13;
exchange rate adjusted GDP estimates because they better reflect the pur-&#13;
chasing power of income in each country. The PPP estimates flow from the&#13;
United Nations/World Bank project on International Comparisons of Real&#13;
Product carried out by Irving Kravis, et. al.&#13;
2/ The countries are: Barbados, Brazil, Costa Rica, Cyprus, Egypt, Gabon,&#13;
Guatemala, Indonesia, Iraq, Malaysia, Malta, Nigeria, Portugal, Sri Lanka,&#13;
Saudi Arabia, Thailand, Tunisia, Turkey and Yugoslavia.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 5 -&#13;
Of this group of 68 developing countries, another 15 recorded GDP/capita&#13;
growth in excess of 2% p.a. for the 1970-79 period only. 1/ By comparison, of&#13;
the 23 industrial countrLes for which similar national income data are avail-&#13;
able only seven countries (Australia, Luxembourg, Netherlands, New Zealand,&#13;
Sweden, Switzerland and United Kingdom) did not grow at rates in excess of 2%&#13;
p.a. for either one of these two periods, and only New Zealand grew at less&#13;
than 2% p.a. for both periods. 2/&#13;
6.       How has this growth, or lack of growth, of the per capita incomes of&#13;
developing countries affected food consumption in those countries? To give a&#13;
broad picture of the impact, growth in per capita calorie consumption of all&#13;
foodstuffs has been plotted against growth in income (PPP) for the developing&#13;
countries in Figures 1 and 2. In Figure 1 each developing cotntry-s average&#13;
income/capita growth for the 1960-70 period is plotted against its growth rate&#13;
of total per capita calorie consumption for the period 1963-70 (end-point&#13;
growth estimates). In Figure 2 income/capita growth for the period 1970-79 is&#13;
plotted against calorie growth for the period 1970-77. 3/ In using this&#13;
measure of improvements in food consumption we recognize the difficulties&#13;
1/  The   countries  are:  Algeria,   Bolivia,   Cameroon,  Colombia,  Dominican&#13;
Republic,   Ecuador,    Gambia,   Kenya,   Mauritius,   Mbrocco,   Paraguay,&#13;
Philippines, Sudan, Surinam, and Trinidad and Tobago.&#13;
2/ The industrial country group includes Greece, Israel and Spain--countries&#13;
that have until recently been classified as developing countries.&#13;
3/ Fbr calorie consumption, the periods 1963-70 and 1970-77 are the closest&#13;
approximations we can get, given the available data, to the decades of the&#13;
1960s and 1970s. Tle figures for calorie consumption in 1963 are the&#13;
averages of the years 1961 to 1965 while the figures for 1970 and 1977 are&#13;
the averages of the three years about these mid-points. The data on per&#13;
capita calorie consumption are taken from FAQ, 1980.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
associated with the measurement of "adequate" diets. 1/ All that is being&#13;
implied in our use is that at these levels of food consumption, growth in&#13;
calorie consumption does represent an improvement in living standards.&#13;
7.       In Figures 1 and 2 the north-east quadrant represents an increase in&#13;
both per capita income and food consumption. The south-west quadrant repre-&#13;
sents a decline in both. There is a positive correlation between per capita&#13;
income and food consumption growth in both periods. In the 1960s all but four&#13;
of this group of developing countries registered growth in income/capita,&#13;
while eight registered a decline in per capita food consumption. When a&#13;
country at these levels of food consumption registers growth in per capita&#13;
income but declining per capita food consumption, as most of these eight did,&#13;
the answer must lie in the shape of the income distribution of the new income&#13;
generated (i.e., it is so unevenly distributed in favor of the already wealthy&#13;
that demand for food is affected little) or in the food-pricing policies of&#13;
the country (i.e., relative prices are so distorted that food consumption is&#13;
seriously disadvantaged).Fbur of those countries which had declining food&#13;
consumption in the 1960s (Algeria, Colombia, Guyana, and Upper Volta) were&#13;
able to reverse the situation in the 1970s--even though in the case of Guyana&#13;
and Upper Volta they experienced declining income/capita in the latter period.&#13;
India, the Ivory Coast, Niger and Nigeria, along with many others, suffered&#13;
declining food/capita levels in the second period. In this latter period there'&#13;
1/ Fbr a critique of the estimation of basic food needs see Eberstadt.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FiGkE i: !NrUME AND CONSUrMPIOUN GROUWTIi i-   8&#13;
DEVELOPING COUNTRIES&#13;
LMAA&#13;
INCOME - 15.9&#13;
CONSUMPTION - 5.0&#13;
3&#13;
JAMAICA&#13;
*CYPRUS&#13;
*PAIISTAN                *POTUM&#13;
2 _&#13;
x                     I                              *TUNEI&#13;
*SUDAN4     8M*&#13;
D F 9 ~~~~~~* p *Sz&#13;
2                   Ivasn2     *USAKDA * *COSTA RICA&#13;
*          ~~~~*IRAO  PAPUA NEWl StJI4EA&#13;
L                        ZAIIA     *oRUNLt   *DUO                  *PANAMA&#13;
r I            _              .                            THAI *A P&#13;
Z    DOIR                  *MHLAYSZNOLTVI*SAUDI ARABIA&#13;
CEN/AFRICAN tEP.                TANZ=4IAARS8rJ1A&#13;
* CWN I REP   C        SUATEKALA * S          SAO *    *YUOSLAVIA&#13;
KALI DOMIWNCAN RPU     *   *SAC&#13;
qOMALIA           *            *  TRINID=ATOBA6d'R&#13;
_SEN i***      L3 RX     YA *KEA&#13;
t .     S.AURIT11UUUTNJS     * *  E TIYPT TOWY *SMAUR4 TAt0*NIA&#13;
0   __________           ZAAE     EL  IA                          *  &#13;
0               *MDOIA                IV&gt;Y COAST&#13;
WJAYMA  UPER VOLTA   *MXSERIA&#13;
_1  _ _ __ _ _   I       I          I           I           I          ii;t&#13;
-1          0           1           2          3           4           5          6           7          16&#13;
INCOME GROWTH CXp.a)&#13;
SOURCES: INCOME GROWTH, WORLD BANK ESTIMATES; CONSUMPTION GROWTH DERIVED FROM FAO, FOOD&#13;
BALANCE AVERAGE AND PER CAPITA FOOD SUPPLIES 1961-1965 AVERAGE 1967-1977.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 2: INCOME AND CONSUMPTION GROWTH - 1970s&#13;
DEVELOPING COUNTRIES&#13;
3 _     UYA&#13;
2 _a.v                                                *&#13;
a.                                                       * &#13;
I  * _                        *                   c IBeama *                  *&#13;
CD I0D -             CS tR V8.TA*                          *A *'A                        *&#13;
TAI"                          VDMM *  *^Lt &#13;
to   U"= VMTA*~~~~~~~~~~~~W.                          VMAUJAY&#13;
** "&#13;
*~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~*R~&#13;
PM WIA&#13;
-2 __ _ * ,&#13;
-3l&#13;
-3                -1                                  3&#13;
INCOME GROWTH (X p.o.)&#13;
SOURCES: INCOME GROWTH, WORLD BANK ESTIMATES: CONSUMPTION GROWTH DERIVED FROM FAO, FOOD&#13;
BALANCE AVERAGE AND PER CAPITA FOOD SUPPLIES 1961-1965 AVERAGE 1967-1977.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
seems to have been a worsening of the factors which have led to the countries&#13;
appearing in the south-east quadrant. 1/&#13;
8.        The obvious dLfference in the developing countries       performance in&#13;
the two time periods is that the 1970s gave rise to much more dispersed&#13;
behavior than the 1960s. The increased number of countries registering lower&#13;
per capita incomes in the 1970s explains part of this dispersion; with the&#13;
countries in the north-west quadrant more likely to be t;hose with food&#13;
policies favoring low-income consumers than those countries in the south-west&#13;
quadrant. Increased agricultural instability in the 1970s together with&#13;
pricing policies descriminating against agricultural production are likely&#13;
causes of the large number of countries in the south-east quadrant. 2/&#13;
1/ We tried, without success, to explain these differences in performance in&#13;
terms of income distribution and relative price distortion measures. To&#13;
measure distortions in consumer prices nominal protection coefficients on&#13;
grains production, which measure the distortions in producer prices, were&#13;
assembled for 18 of these countries. Nominal protection coefficients are&#13;
probably not a gocid measure of distortions in consumer prices, but no&#13;
other measures are available. Gini coefficients were used as one measure&#13;
of income distribution. These are available for about 30 oE these develop-&#13;
ing countries. Like the nominal protection coefficients the Gini coeffi-&#13;
cients have been estimated at different periods of time over the last two&#13;
decades. Further, t:he quality of the data on which they have been esti-&#13;
mated is extremely varied. Neither of these variables could explain any of&#13;
the variation in equations in which the growth of calorie consumption was&#13;
to be explained by the growth of per capita income, the level of per&#13;
capita income, income distribution and distortions in consumer prices.&#13;
Life expectancy in 1960 and 1980 was tried as a proxy for income distribu-&#13;
tion, but it also gave insignificant results. The results for this last&#13;
equation were as follows:&#13;
C = 0.17 Y + 0.003 LE + 0.0003 YCAP, R2(adj) = 0.42&#13;
(4.5)      (0.12)     (3.0)&#13;
t statistics are in parentheses&#13;
Fbr this equation the observations for both periods were combined; also,&#13;
the constant is constrained to zero.&#13;
2/ Barr shows that the variability of world food production was higher in the&#13;
1960s than in the 1950s and higher again in the 1970s.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
Reutlinger has shown that, in the face of reductions in domestic production,&#13;
developing countries have been unwilling to compensate for the shortfall by&#13;
increasing food imports. Therefore, artificially low food prices in developing&#13;
countries (a widespread practice,often aimed at the politically more powerful&#13;
urban consumers) do not necessarily mean increased consumption. Besides the&#13;
restriction on imports, artificially low producer prices (also a widespread&#13;
practice, particularly in African countries) mean lower incomes and hence&#13;
lower consumption in the rural areas--where most of the population and most of&#13;
the poor often reside.&#13;
9.       To give an idea of what these changes in food consumption have meant&#13;
in aggregate terms for the developing countries we have constructed Table 1.&#13;
These figures show the improvement in per capita food supplies in the&#13;
developed and developing market economies (FAO definition) over the period&#13;
between 1961-65 (average) and 1977 and the sources of the calories and protein&#13;
consumed. Over this approximately 15-year period the per capita consumption of&#13;
calories in developing countries has increased by 4.1% and the consumption of&#13;
protein by 2.8%. 1/ Both in absolute and percentage terms the developed market&#13;
economies have done much better--with per capita calorie consumption increas-&#13;
ing by 6% and per capita protein consumption increasing by 7.6%. During this&#13;
period food production actually increased more slowly in industrial countries&#13;
than in developing countries, but their rate of population increase was much&#13;
slower than that of developing countries, giving rise to the higher per capita&#13;
gains. 2/&#13;
1/ These are average figures which convey little information about how well&#13;
the different income groups in the developing countries have fared.&#13;
2/ See Barr, op. cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE 1:   PER CAPITA FOOD SUPPLIES BY MAJOR ECONOMIC REGIONS /A AND BY FOOD CATEGORY, 1961-65 (AVERAGE), AND 1977&#13;
PER CAPITA CALORIE SUPPLY                    PER CAPITA PROTEIN SUPPLY&#13;
DEVELOPED MARKET     DEVELOPING MARKET      DEVELOPED MARKET     DEVELOPING MARKET           PERCENTAGE OF&#13;
ECONOMIES            ECONOMIES              ECONOMIES             ECONOMIES          WORLD CALORIE SUPPLY&#13;
FOOD CATEGORY              1961-65      1977    1961-65       1977      1961-65     1977     1961-65      1977       1961-65         1977&#13;
-----------(calorie/day)(-------------      -------------(ram/day)&#133;--------------        --------()---------&#13;
CEREALS                      961         891    1,229        1,274      27.3        25.1      29.5        30.8        51.4           51.1&#13;
WHEAT                      642         592      290          372      20.7        19.0       8.5        10.9       18.1            18.6&#13;
RICE                       192         171      545          544       3.4         3.1      10.4        10.3       19.3            20.2&#13;
MAIZE                       71          86      175          178       1.7         1.9       4.4         4.5        5.9             5.8&#13;
MILLET &amp; SORGHUM             2           2      175          147       0.1                   5.0         4.2        4.7             4.1&#13;
ROOTS AND TUBERS              148        123      147          143        3.2        2.8       1.5         1.5         8.0            6.4&#13;
SUGARS AND HONEY             384         444      182          209                             0.2         0.2        8.5             9.4&#13;
PULSES                         35         28      115           92       2.3         1.8       7.0         5.6         3.5            3.1&#13;
NUTS AND OILSEEDS              53         58       48           44        2.6        2.7        1.6        1.6         2.1            1.9&#13;
VEGETABLES                     57         64       26           29        3.1        3.4        1.5        1.6         1.6            1.6&#13;
FRUIT                         89          98       63           66        1.1        1.3       0.7         0.8         2.2            2.4&#13;
MEAT AND OFFALS              420         525       63           67      22.3        29.0       4.7         5.0         7.3            8.2&#13;
EGGS                           50         54        4            7       4.0         4.4       0.3         0.5         0.8            0.8&#13;
FISH AND SEAFOOD              40          49       11           15        5.9        6.9       1.8         2.4        0.8             1.0&#13;
MILK                         279         289       66           67      16.2        17.3       3.9         4.0         5.0            4.6&#13;
OILS &amp; FATS                   440        510       129         154       0.2         0.2                               8.4            9.0&#13;
VEGETABLE OILS &amp; FATS        256         359      100          123       0.1         0.1                               5.4            6.4&#13;
ANIMAL OILS &amp; FATS           '184        151       29           31       0.1         0.1                               3.0            2.6&#13;
TOTAL VEGETABLE PRODUCTS   2,151       2,280    1,940        2,016      41.4        39.3      42.6        42.9        83.5           83.1&#13;
TOTAL ANIMAL PRODUCTS        977       1,073      173          188      48.6        57.7      10.8        12.0        16.5           16.9&#13;
GRAND TOTAL&#13;
(EXCL. ALCOHOL)            2,977       3,156    2,092        2,178      89.4        96.2      53.3        54.°&#13;
/A FAO COUNTRY CLASSIFICATION.&#13;
SOURCE: CONSTRUCTED FROM FOOD BALANCE SHEETS 1975-77 AVERAGE AND PER CAPUT FOOD SUPPLIES 1961-65 AVERAGE 1967 TO 1977,&#13;
FAO ROME 1980.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
10.      When examined in terms of the sources of these food supplies there&#13;
have been some marked changes for some food categories and for others a dis-&#13;
appointing lack of change. While the total per capita direct supply of calo-&#13;
ries and protein obtained from the cereals group by people in developing&#13;
countries has increased slightly over the period, there have been sharp&#13;
changes for individual cereals. The amount of wheat consumed directly, mea-&#13;
sured in terms of calories, increased by 28% while the per capita calorie&#13;
supply of millet and sorghum fell by 16%. On a geographical basis the regions&#13;
responsible for these changes were Africa and Asia. In per capita terms wheat&#13;
consumption rose by 44% in Asian countries and by 32% in African countries.&#13;
Millet and sorghum consumption fell by 11% in Asian countries and by 16% in&#13;
African countries. Within the developing countries there have generally been&#13;
the kinds of changes in food sources that would be expected with improved&#13;
living standards, but just as the total increase in food consumption has been&#13;
small over this period, most of the changes observed have been small. Fbr&#13;
example, we would expect per capita consumption of roots and tubers and pulses&#13;
to decline and consumption of fruit, vegetables, meat, eggs, fish and seafoods&#13;
and milk to increase. These changes have indeed taken place, and in percentage&#13;
terms some of the changes are large, but in absolute terms the only signifi-&#13;
cant change has been the decline in pulses (20%).&#13;
11.      At the world level (see the last two columns in Table 1) the percen-&#13;
tages of total calorie consumption supplied by these various categories of&#13;
foodstuffs have also changed little. Cereals still account for 51% of the&#13;
total, with wheat and rice becoming more important and maize and millet and&#13;
sorghum relatively less important. The decline in per capita consumption of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
roots and tubers in both developed and developing countries is the most&#13;
significant change. The improvement in meat consumption is absolutely and&#13;
proportionately mostly a result of the increase in developed countries. The&#13;
declining importance of milk products and animal fats and their substitution&#13;
by vegetable fats and oils, shows up here, even in developing countries.&#13;
12.      If we take the present consumption levels of the developed countries&#13;
as the norm towards which developing countries are moving we can see that the&#13;
major changes that wi:Ll take place in the pattern of food consumption, and&#13;
which will be reflected in production and trade patterns, will be in terms of&#13;
considerable decreases in the importance of cereals and roots and tubers, and&#13;
considerable increases in the importance of sugars and honey, meat, milk, and&#13;
vegetable oils and fats. Of course, when allowance is made fcor both livestock&#13;
feed as well as direct human consumption, the net impact on cereals consump-&#13;
tion in total may well be an increase in importance in absolute and per capita&#13;
terms.&#13;
13.      But such conjectures can only give a guide to the products which can&#13;
be expected to be more or less important over the very long run. More to the&#13;
point, what are the changes we are likely to see in the next 20 years in terms&#13;
of the levels of food consumption reached in the developing countries and the&#13;
changes in importance of the various categories of foodstuffs? Further, what&#13;
will the expected deveLopments in food consumption mean for the future pattern&#13;
of production and prices of foodstuffs?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
World Bank Fbrecasts of Fbod Consumption by 1995&#13;
14.      Within the Commodities Division of the World Bank we have recently&#13;
carried out an exercise which in part led to forecasts to the year 1995 of&#13;
world (and regional) production, consumption, trade and prices of many primary&#13;
commodities of importance to developing countries. The commodities included do&#13;
not cover the entire food basket of developing countries, but represent about&#13;
70% of the total.&#13;
15.      Fbr the most part these long-term projections were derived using&#13;
comparative-static equilibrium models, disaggregated by region, where prices&#13;
are used to achieve a unique equilibrium solution. Since the models are long-&#13;
run, stock level changes are ignored. The models are demand-determined and the&#13;
consumption projections were made first by applying income elasticities of&#13;
demand by region to projected per capita GDP and population. Given a set of&#13;
regional price elasticities of supply and demand and productivity growth&#13;
rates, prices were adjusted such that through successive iterations global&#13;
production and consumption converged to equilibrium. The models assume an&#13;
absence of shocks on both the consumption and production sides. Information&#13;
concerning production developments in key countries and likely changes in&#13;
factors affecting the market such as international'commodity agreements were,&#13;
incorporated at the appropriate level. Income and price elasticities are&#13;
assumed to change over time with the evolution of a region's income level.&#13;
16.      The basic position that we take on projections of food consumption is&#13;
that the amount and composition of food is, in the aggregate and in the long&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
run, determined by aggregate demand. In this we differ from those who take a&#13;
physical capacity-cum-productivity possibility approach. That is, we believe&#13;
that the resources allocated to food production, including resources allocated&#13;
to productivity-enhancing research, are endogenous. We acknowledge that in&#13;
some countries the food-producing sector is so large a proportion of total&#13;
national product that it cannot be regarded as not being simultaneously deter-&#13;
mined with aggregate demand. Further, there are also distortions of prices&#13;
which disturb food production from the levels that would otherwise be deter-&#13;
mined by aggregate demand. However, while these influences are important,&#13;
often extremely important for individual countries, for this exercise we chose&#13;
to assume that they are captured in the projections of income growth.&#13;
17.      In looking at the level and composition of food consumption,         our&#13;
focus on aggregate demand implies that both at the world level and at the&#13;
country level access to food is not determined by physical cconstraints on food&#13;
production either within individual countries (because a country can import&#13;
whatever food it can pay for) or at a world level (because production will&#13;
respond to price incentives). Thus, it follows that we do nol: see the solution&#13;
of any "food problem" at the world level or within a particular country as a&#13;
question of overcoming food production problems on a world basis or within a&#13;
country, but as a problem of obtaining the maximum economic growth--within the&#13;
economic constraints. However, distortions of relative prices within a country&#13;
which tax food production and consumption may well reduce national income&#13;
growth and make the itask of improving food consumption levels more difficult&#13;
than it otherwise would be.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
18.      The long-term forecasts shown in Table 2 are conditional in nature.&#13;
On the demand side they rest critically on the assumptions made about the&#13;
world economy in the 1980s and 1990s. The forecasts, moreover, are positive&#13;
rather than normative. They are based on the most likely assumptions concern-&#13;
ing government policies affecting production and trade, the likely market&#13;
structures and demand conditions. Given the use of the resulting price fore-&#13;
casts in project and balance of payments analyses by the World Bank Group,&#13;
trying to determine what is most likely to happen, as opposed to what would&#13;
happen if desirable changes in policies and market structure were to take&#13;
place, becomes inescapable and appropriate.&#13;
19.      The assumptions adopted about growth in the world economy and in the&#13;
industrial, centrally planned and developing economies, represent the mid-&#13;
point of the High and Low scenarios described in the World Bank's World&#13;
Development Report, 1982. The population projections are also those of World&#13;
Development Report, 1982. These projections of income and population are shown&#13;
in Table 3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE 2: FOODSTUFFS - PROJECTIONS OF APPARENT CONSUMPTION, BY ECONOMIC REGIONS /A&#13;
------------------------------------------------------------------ _---------__-----------------------------------------------------------------__---------__----O--D&#13;
INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES                        CENTRALLY PLANNED ECONOMIES                    DEVELOPING COUNTRIES            GROWrH KATES&#13;
1980         1985    1990    1995           1980          8    19       15            191985                1990       1995  1961-80  1980-95&#13;
/B                          /C             /B                            /C           /B                           /C      /B     /C&#13;
WHEAT                           89.3 (1.7)  94.8    104.2   114.5 (1.7)   145.9 (3.1)   158.7  175.2    193.4 (1.9)  208.5 (4.7)   260.9  319.8   390.1 (4.3)    3.4     3.1&#13;
RICE                             9.5(-0.6)  10.0    10.3     10.5 (0.7)    14.5 (1.9)    16.0   17.7    19.0 (1.8)   236.1 (3.0)   269.5  313.0   363.5 (2.9)    2.7     2.8&#13;
COARSE GRAINS /D               252.6 (2.1) 252.9   260.3    270.4 (0.5)   161.7 (4.0)   198.4  215.4    249.0 (2.9)  297.5 (2.8)   348.3  411.6   481.8 (3.3)    2.8     2.3&#13;
SUGAR                           25.1 (1.3)  25.6    26.2     26.8 (0.4)    17.7 (2.3)    18.5   19.4    20.4 (1.0)    54.8 (3.6)   63.9    74.4    84.6 (2.9)    2.6     2.0&#13;
BEEF AND VEAL                  20.6 (2.1)   22.4    24.2     27.0 (1.8)     9.5 (4.1)    10.5   12.1    14.0 (2.6)    16.5 (2.6)   18.9    21.2    24.7 (2.7)    2.6     2.3&#13;
FRESH CITRUS FRUITS             26.1 (4.5)  28.7    31.1     34.0 (1-8)     1.7 (6.9)     1.9    2.3     2.7 (3.1)    28.6 (5.1)   34.6    41.0    48.5 (3.6)    4.8     2.8&#13;
VEGETABLE FATS AND OILS&#13;
- SOYBEANS (OIL EQUIVALENT       6.8 (5.7)   7.6      8.6     9.6 (2.3)     0.7 (7.9)     0.8    1.0      1.2 (3.7)    7.3 (6.0)     8.9   11.7    16.2 (5.5)    5.9     4.1&#13;
- PALM OIL                       1.0 (6.9)   1.1      1.2     1.3 (1.7)     0.1(19.8)     0.1    0.2      0.2 (2.9)    3.8 (8.1)     4.9    6.3     8.5 (5.6)    7.9     4.9&#13;
- COCONUTS (OIL EQUIVALENT)      1.0 (0.6)   1.1      1.2     1.3 (1.7)     0.1 (3.9)     0.2    0.2     0.2 (2.7)     1.7 (1.7)     1.9    2.2     2.6 (2.9)    1.4     2.5&#13;
/A WORLD BANK CLASSIFICATION OF COUNTRIES, SEE WORLD DEVELOPMENT REPORT, 1982. NOTE THAT CHINA IS INCLUDED.&#13;
/B  THE NUMBERS IN THIS COLUMN ARE THE ACTUAL GROWTH RATES (LEAST SQUARES TREND) FOR THE PERIOD 1961-80.&#13;
/C THE NUMBERS IN THIS COLUMN ARE THE PROJECTED GROWTH RATES (END POINTS) FOR THE PERIOD 1980-95.&#13;
/D  COARSE GRAINS HERE INCLUDE MAIZE, BARLEY, OATS, KYT, GKAIN SoRGHUiM AND fLLET.&#13;
SOURCE: FAO, PRODUCTION YEARBOOK, 1981, TRADE YEARBOOX, 1981 (ACTUAL 1980 DATA); WORLD BANK (PROJECTIONS).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
TABLE 3: PROJECTED REAL GDP GROWTH AND POPULATION GROWTH,&#13;
BY MAJOR ECONOMIC REGION, 1983-95&#13;
(% CHANGE PER ANNUM)&#13;
REAL GDP GROWTH            POPULATION GROWTH&#13;
1983-90    1990-95      1960-80   1980-90   1990-95&#13;
INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES         3.7        3.5          0.9       0.5       0.5&#13;
CENTRALLY PLANNED ECONOMIES                          1.3       1.2       1.0&#13;
EAST EUROPE                3.5        3.5          1.0       0.9       0.7&#13;
DEVELOPING COUNTRIES*        4.9        5.3          2.2       2.0       1.9&#13;
OIL EXPORTERS              6.1        6.4          2.6       2.6       2.4&#13;
OIL IMPORTERS              4.6        5.1          2.2       1.9       1.8&#13;
- LOW INCOME               3.2        3.8          2.1       1.8       1.7&#13;
SUB-SAHARAN AFRICA                                 2.6       3.1       2.9&#13;
ASIA                                               2.1       1.7       1.6&#13;
- MIDDLE INCOME            4.8        5.4          2.3       2.2       2.0&#13;
CHINA                        4.9        5.0          1.9       1.3       1.2&#13;
WORLD                        3.9        3.8          1.9       1.7       1.6&#13;
* EXCLUDES PEOPLES   REPUBLIC OF CHINA IN THE GDP DATA BUT INCLUDES IT IN THE&#13;
POPULATION DATA.&#13;
SOURCE: WORLD BANK, ECONOMIC ANALYSIS AND PROJECTIONS DEPARTMENT, INTERNA-&#13;
TIONAL TRADE AND CAPITAL FLOWS DIVISION AND ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL DATA&#13;
DIVISION.&#13;
20.      Looking at the growth rates in world consumption for the period 1961-&#13;
80 (Table 2) we can see that the importance of industrial countries in world&#13;
consumption of these foodstuffs *has declined in the past 20 years. Growth in&#13;
consumption of these commodities has been faster in the centrally planned eco-&#13;
nomies and the developing countries, reflecting their lower levels of income,&#13;
and their faster income and population growth. However, as we have seen&#13;
earlier, on a per capita basis food consumption has grown much faster in&#13;
industrial countries than in developing countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
21.      Overall, the growth in total consumption of these commodities is&#13;
expected to be lower in the period 1980-95 than in the period 1961-80 except&#13;
for rice and coconuts (see growth rates in last two columns). 1/ The decline&#13;
in the expected rate of growth of wheat consumption is largely a function of&#13;
the expected much slower growth in the centrally planned economies; and the&#13;
expected slowdown in growth of coarse grains consumption is a result of the&#13;
expected  slowing of growth    in industrial countries and centrally planned&#13;
economies and the consequent adverse effect on the demand for meats and feed-&#13;
stuffs. The developing countries are expected to maintain their historical&#13;
growth in grains consumiption. This, together with the expected slower growth&#13;
in population in developing countries should mean a slightly faster growth in&#13;
per capita grains consumption in developing countries than in the past 20&#13;
years. Bringing together the consumption growth rates of Table 2 and the&#13;
population growth ratesi of Table 3, it can be seen that the per capita con-&#13;
sumption of wheat, rice and coarse grains by the developing countries was&#13;
2.5%, 0.8% and 0.6% per annum, respectively, over the 1961-80 period. The&#13;
projected per capita consumption growth rates for these grains in the period&#13;
1980-95 are 2.3%, 0.9% and 1.3% respectively. The much higher rate of growth&#13;
of coarse grains is a reflection of the expected increase in the consumption&#13;
of animal products.&#13;
22.      In its major study of future food availability scenarios for develop-&#13;
ing countries the FAO imade the following projections. If, in the period 1980&#13;
to 2000, the GDP of developing countries grows at much the same rate as in the&#13;
1/ A large part of this increase in coconut product consumption will be for&#13;
non-edible uses, particularly soaps and detergents.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
past 20 years per capita food demand is projected to average 0.44% p.a.&#13;
growth. This is a faster rate of growth in per capita consumption of develop-&#13;
ing countries than the 0.3% p.a. rate achieved in the 1963-77 period (see&#13;
Table 1). Under an assumption of much higher GDP growth, coincident with&#13;
greater investment in agriculture and relaxation of trade distortions within&#13;
developing   countries   and  between   developing   countries   and  industrial&#13;
countries, it was projected by FAQ that per capita food demand could grow by&#13;
0.75% p.a. The projections of the first FAO scenario appear compatible with&#13;
our expectations of a slightly faster growth in per capita grains consumption&#13;
in the next 15-20 years.&#13;
Price Developments&#13;
23.      The cereals price forecasts to which this exercise led show a contin-&#13;
uation of the long-term declining trend in real terms (see Figures 3, 4 and 5&#13;
for long-term price series for wheat, rice and maize). 1/ Even though incomes&#13;
are increasing, and the growth of incomes in the developing countries is&#13;
having a larger impact in terms of total food demand, food demand remains&#13;
essentially price and income inelastic. Supply will respond to any increase in&#13;
demand with improvements in technology. The result will be a fall in prices.&#13;
The events of the past decade seem to bear this out. With an expansion of&#13;
demand for cereals for human consumption and for feed grains--from the fast-&#13;
growing developing countries and the centrally planned economies--supply has&#13;
I/ The maize price has shown a different pattern than wheat and rice prices&#13;
with a period of higher prices in the post-World War II period than in the&#13;
period prior. As maize is the premium feed grain, this is consistent with&#13;
the fact that beef prices were significantly higher also during the post-&#13;
World War II period.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 3: WHEAT PRICE INDEXES, 1900-1982&#13;
(1975-100)&#13;
cult=~~&#13;
i-                                               S~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~r&#13;
o~~~~~~~~~ _&#13;
8    12  It   24   30   38   42   40   54   60   60   72   78&#13;
SOURCE: COMPILED AND SUPPLIED BY ENZO GRILLI AND MAW-CHENG YANG, ECONOMIC&#13;
ANALYSIS AND PROJECTIONS DEPARTMENT, WORLD BANK, THE PRICE SERIES&#13;
IS CANADIAN NO. 1 NORTHERN, IN STORE PORT WILLIAM/FORT ARTHUR FOR&#13;
1900-47; CANADIAN NO. 1 WESTER RED SPRING IN STORE THUNDER BAY FOR&#13;
1948-82 AND THE DEFLATOR IS US WHOLESALE PRICE INDEX.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 4: RICE PRICE INDEXES, 1900-1982&#13;
(1975-100)&#13;
r-                    I&#13;
8    12   18  24    3    38   42   48   54   60   88   72   78&#13;
YEtR&#13;
SOURCE:  COMPILED AND SUPPLIED BY ENZO GRILLI AND MAW-CHENG YANG, ECONOMIC&#13;
ANALYSIS AND PROJECTIONS DEPARTMENT, WORLD BANK. THE PRICE SERIES IS&#13;
BOAT PADDY, RANGOON FOR 1900-47; THAI 5% BROKEN, FOB BANGKOK FOR&#13;
1948-82. THE DEFLATOR IS THE US WHOLESALE PRICE INDEX.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 5: MAIZE PRICE INDEXES, 1900-1982&#13;
(1975-100)&#13;
_ I  -.-.-.  OUA&#13;
C:t &#13;
4                                              A                     A        A&#13;
0&#13;
0-&#13;
B-       12   l      4   w    3     2    t      t   Z    6         17&#13;
z&#13;
8    12 tO      24   30   38    42   48   54    80   88   72    78&#13;
Y1RW&#13;
SOURCE: COMPILED AND SUPPLIED BY ENZO GRILLI AND MAW-CHENG YANG, ECONOMIC&#13;
ANALYSIS AND PROJECTIONS DEPARTMENT, WORLD BANK. THE PRICE SERIES&#13;
IS US NO. 2 YELLOW FOB GULF PORTS FOR 1948-82; US NO. 3 YELLOW FOR&#13;
1900-47. THIE DEFLATOR IS THE US WHOLESALE PRICE INDEX.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
responded. Much of this supply response has been in the grain growing areas of&#13;
North America and Oceania, which have a comparative advantage in production of&#13;
grains.&#13;
24.       Our analysis indicates that the increase in the per capita growth&#13;
rate for rice consumption (the staple food of the major proportion of low-&#13;
income people) through the projection period will be accompanied by a substan-&#13;
tial reduction in price and in trade in rice. Among the developing countries,&#13;
Indonesia (historically the largest importing country) has displayed the most&#13;
remarkable growth in consumption and production, with both increasing at 5%&#13;
p.a. over the past 20 years. This has resulted in an increase in self-suffi-&#13;
ciency and the likelihood of smaller imports in most years, as in 1981. Other&#13;
developing country importers (such as Republic of Korea, India and Bangladesh)&#13;
have also become less reliant on trade, one of the consequences of the Green&#13;
Revolution. Together with a continuation of the expansion of rice production&#13;
in the United States (since 1975 when acreage controls were relaxed) and&#13;
production subsidies in Japan, it is anticipated that world prices on the&#13;
relatively small international market will face continuing downward pressure.&#13;
Production and Yields&#13;
25.      Grains occupy by far the largest part of land under agricultural pro-&#13;
duction. Continuing increases in area harvested similar to those experienced&#13;
in the past are unlikely. 1/ Reliance on yield increases will probably rise.&#13;
1/ However, the FAO, ibid. estimated that there was still considerable&#13;
potential for area expansion in developing countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
The potential for such increments exists and past experience, particularly in&#13;
developing countries is encouraging.&#13;
26.      Over the 1980-95 period world production growth for the major food-&#13;
crops is projected as follows: rice 2.8% p.a. wheat 3.1% p.a. and coarse&#13;
grains 2.3% p.a. If yields of wheat and coarse grains were to continue to grow&#13;
at recent rates these production increases would be achieved with little&#13;
increase in area harvested. Attainment of the rice production projections,&#13;
however, will necessitate just as much reliance as in the past on increases in&#13;
area harvested, or more likely, a faster rate of growth in rice yields than in&#13;
past years. Such a possLbility exists as the major rice growing countries are&#13;
envisaged to increase the use of fertilizer, continue to develop water control&#13;
systems, as well as adopt other improved production practices. Unlike indus-&#13;
trial countries, where wheat, coarse grains and rice yields are already grow-&#13;
ing at best at a constant rate, and in some cases at a declining rate, yields&#13;
in developing countries are generally growing at an increasing rate. In other&#13;
words, in both rice and wheat, developing countries appear to be on the way to&#13;
catching up to the industrial countries in yields. Fbr coarse grains the pic-&#13;
ture seems similar but perhaps not so strong. The exception to this encourag-&#13;
ing performance by the developing countries has been in Africa, where produc-&#13;
tion of grains has lagged as improvements in yields have been much slower than&#13;
in other developing areas. This has been particularly evident in rice and&#13;
coarse grains (see Table 4 below). In Table 4 we also provide our developing&#13;
countries projections on a regional basis; these indicate that African coun-&#13;
tries will fall even further behind other developing countries in the years&#13;
ahead. Domestic price distortions which reduce incentives for agricultural&#13;
production may well be a leading factor in reducing the incentives to adopt&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
new technology in these countries. Under these circumstances the pay-off to&#13;
agricultural research and to other public investments such as roads and dams&#13;
will not be as profitable as they otherwise would be.&#13;
TABLE 4: GROWTH /A IN PRODUCTION 1961-80 (ACTUAL) AND 1980-95 (PROJECTED),&#13;
AREA HARVESTED AND YIELDS 1961-80, IN MAIN DEVELOPING COUNTRIES&#13;
--------------------------------------------------------__-------------------_&#13;
PRODUCTION   3       AREA HARVESTED          YIELDS&#13;
1961-80     1980-95           1961-80              1961-80&#13;
RICE (PADDY)&#13;
ASIA                   2.9         2.9               0.8                 2.1&#13;
AFRICA                 2.7         2.0               2.5                 0.2&#13;
LATIN AMERICA          3.4         3.4               2.8                 0.6&#13;
WHEAT&#13;
ASIA                   5.9         4.1               1.7                 4.2&#13;
AFRICA                 2.5         N.A.              0.9                  1.6&#13;
LATIN AMERICA          1.9         1.3               1.3                 0.5&#13;
COARSE GRAINS&#13;
ASIA                   1.8         2.2              -1.1                 3.0&#13;
AFRICA                 2.1         1.7               1.6                 0.5&#13;
LATIN AMERICA          3.6         2.6               1.3                 2.8&#13;
/A LEAST SQUARES TREND GROWTH RATES FOR 1961-80, END-POINT GROWTH RATES FOR&#13;
1980-95.&#13;
SOURCE:  FAO,   PRODUCTION  YEARBOOK,   VARIOUS  ISSUES   (ACTUAL);  WORLD  BANK&#13;
(PROJECTIONS).&#13;
27.      Considerable expansion of wheat, coarse grains, and even rice produc-&#13;
tion is possible in the industrial countries, if warranted by global demand.'&#13;
Currently, agricultural policies in the United States and Canada, two of the&#13;
largest wheat exporters, restrict wheat output in order to maintain farm&#13;
prices and incomes. If world prices rise, as they did in 1972-74, acreage&#13;
currently held out of production can be readily brought back into use; though&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
this response cannot be as great in terms of area as it was in the 1970s when&#13;
there was a 20% increase in the area under wheat and coarse grains--land that&#13;
farmers had been paid to hold out of production. Further, the livestock herds&#13;
of these two countries may be regarded as an enormous bufferstock of grains.&#13;
As grain prices rise livestock on feed falls thus releasing for export and&#13;
human consumption quantities of grain formerly destined to be consumed by&#13;
livestock. This indeed occurred during the 1972-73 crop shortfalls. Supply&#13;
elasticities for wheat and coarse grains in the United States, Canada, the&#13;
European Community and Australia indicate that the production response to&#13;
increased price is quit:e elastic. Export supply elasticities are considerably&#13;
larger than supply elasticities.&#13;
28.      The grains projections have been based largely on a continuation of&#13;
1961-80 rates of growth of yields. Since many developing counitries are mount-&#13;
ing successful efforts to increase yields, it is believed that the yields&#13;
assumptions used are conservative. Shown in Table 5 below are the historical&#13;
rates of growth of production, area harvested and yield for the cereals, dif-&#13;
ferentiated by main eccnomic regions. Table 6 gives average 1970-80 yields for&#13;
the grains by major regions. As the growth rates of area harvested and yield&#13;
sum to the growth rate of production, the relative contribut:Lon of yield and&#13;
area harvested to the changes in production that have occuretd can be easily&#13;
inferred. World wheat yields have been growing at the rate of 2.5% p.a.,&#13;
implying that 80% of output growth during the 1961-80 period has been due to&#13;
yield improvements. Wheiat yields have been increasing most rapidly in develop-&#13;
ing countries, especially China (5.5% p.a.), yet yields in developing&#13;
countries are still 402 below those of industrial countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
TABLE 5: CEREALS - GROWTH /A IN PRODUCTION, AREA HARVESTED&#13;
AND YIELDS, 1961-80&#13;
AREA               SHARES IN WORLD&#13;
PRODUCTION    HARVESTED   YIELDS  PRODUCTION, 1980&#13;
&#133; ----     (Z p.a.)&#133;------------      --&#13;
RICE&#13;
INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES            0.5        -0.6        1.1            5.1&#13;
CENTRALLY PLANNED ECONOMIES     1.8         0.0        1.8            5.1&#13;
DEVELOPING COUNTRIES            2.9         1.0        2.0           89.8&#13;
WORLD                           2.7         0.9        1.8&#13;
WHEAT&#13;
INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES            2.7         0.9        1.8           34.5&#13;
CENTRALLY PLANNED ECONOMIES     2.7        -0.6        3.3           28.7&#13;
DEVELOPING COUNTRIES            4.6         1.2        3.3           36.8&#13;
WORLD                           3.4         0.6        2.8&#13;
COARSE GRAINS&#13;
INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES            3.0         0.5        2.5           42.9&#13;
CENTRALLY PLANNED ECONOMIES     3.0         1.6        2.3           19.1&#13;
DEVELOPING COUNTRIES            2.4         2.2        2.4           38.0&#13;
WORLD                           2.8         0.3         2.5&#13;
/A LEAST SQUARES TREND GROWTH RATES.&#13;
SOURCE:  DERIVED FROM FAO, PRODUCTION YEARBOOK, VARIOUS ISSUES.&#13;
TABLE 6:  AVERAGE YIELDS FOR MAJOR CROPS IN REGIONS OF THE WORLD,&#13;
1970-80 AVERAGE&#13;
(KG/HA)&#13;
-------------------------------------------------------------__-------------&#13;
WHEAT          RICE        COARSE GRAINS /A&#13;
(PADDY)&#13;
------------------------------------------------------------------__--------&#13;
WORLD OF WHICH:                     1,771          2,576             1,993&#13;
INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES             2,298           6,565             3,943&#13;
CENTRALLY PLANNED ECONOMIES      1,748           3,557             1,943&#13;
DEVELOPING COUNTRIES OF WHICH:   1,345           1,970             1,091&#13;
ASIA                           1,523           2,541             1,261&#13;
AFRICA                         1,024           1,773               882&#13;
LATIN AMERICA                  1,456           1,834             1,631&#13;
-----------------------------------------------------------------__----------&#13;
/A COARSE GRAINS INCLUDE BARLEY, MAIZE, RYE, OATS, MILLET, SORGHUM.&#13;
SOURCE: FAO, PRODUCTION YEARBOOK, VARIOUS ISSUES.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
29.      World yields of coarse grains have been growing at 2.3% p.a., imply-&#13;
ing that almost 90% of output growth has been due to yield increases. Coarse&#13;
grains yields have been growing most rapidly in industrial countries as a&#13;
rule, although again China has achieved very good yield increases in sorghum&#13;
(5% p.a. for 1961-80). Two-thirds of the growth in the world production of&#13;
rice in the past 20 years has been due to increases in yields.. Over the last&#13;
few years, rice yields in the United States have averaged 5,000 kilograms per&#13;
hectare and in Japan 6,000 kilograms per hectare. The average for developing&#13;
countries has been about: 2,000 kilograms per hectare. Clearly there exists a&#13;
great potential for "catching up."&#13;
30.       Figures 6, 7 and 8 present yield growth rates in selected countries&#13;
for wheat, rice and coarse grains over the past 32--year period. The vertical&#13;
axis are logarithmic in order that yield data can be interpret:ed directly as&#13;
growth in yields. The conclusions that can be drawn from these figures are&#13;
that yields are increasing at a constant or diminishing rate in industrial&#13;
countries while they are increasing at an increasing rate in developing&#13;
countries. This is a very favorable indication of the future productive poten-&#13;
tial of developing countTies; especially when the differences between yields&#13;
in industrial countriese and    developing countries   are considered.   Even if&#13;
developing countries never achieve yields of the same magnitude as industrial&#13;
countries, merely approaching current yields in industrial countries would&#13;
represent a substantial improvement and would have a significant effect on&#13;
production. Since achieving yields similar to those now common in industrial&#13;
countries involves adopting well-developed technologies, the l:echnical chal-&#13;
lenge is not difficult. The main difficulty is an organizational one that&#13;
involves providing correct incentives and removing obstacles to production&#13;
increases.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
FIGURE 6: WHEAT - YIELD GROWTH RATES IN&#13;
SELECTED MAJOR PRODUCING COUNTRIES /A&#13;
('00 KG/HA)&#13;
CANADA                                 AMENTINA&#13;
w idt                                   ad'&#13;
46  ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~646  II 4 V    a  a&#13;
UNITED KINGDOM                        SNDIA&#13;
'c 'Si 'is 'Il 3u u I* is  tbd.        .       .*       ais,&#13;
UNIED STATES                           PAKISTAN&#13;
ad',                              id&#13;
/A THE VERTICAL AXIS IS LOGARITHMIC SO THAT YIELD DATA ARE INTERPRETED&#13;
DIRECTLY AS GROWTH IN YIELDS.&#13;
SOURCE: FAO, PRODUCTION YEARBOOK, VARIOUS ISSUES.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
FIGURE 7: COARSE GRAINS - YIELD GROWTH RATES IN SELECTED PRODUCING COUNTRIES /A&#13;
('00 KG/HA)&#13;
ARGENTINA : HAIZE                              FRANCE : MUIZE&#13;
1   ii.l,                                      i.'&#13;
INDIA : SORGHUM                              UNITED STATES   MAIZE&#13;
a  $I at   1i uI                                                                    2 e * a&#13;
/A THE VERTICAL AXIS IS LOCARITHMIC SO THAT YIELD DATA&#13;
IS INTERPRETED DIRECTLY AS GROWTH IN YIELDS.&#13;
SOURCE: FAO, PRODUCTION YEARBOOK, VARIOUS ISSUES.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
FIGURE 8: RICE - YIELD GROWTH RATES IN&#13;
MAJOR PRODUCING COUNTRIES /A&#13;
('00 KG/HA)&#13;
UNITED STATES                                     PHILIPPINES&#13;
&gt;t; | S ss ~~~~~~~~~v                                 S "oi' '4   am  a21 n@  , id".-1&#13;
JAPAN                                             PARISTAN&#13;
3       .l Si *4 Dw6 ' u* a                        i d n  i  7o  l      a'      ' u   n' i  sd&#13;
CHINA                                             THAILAND&#13;
usa 3W5511  a~emnisis      id ii              B I IfI I4 pi  * vie I I is* Is   0&#13;
t@;  i-U- 7-  a $''I'' 43 a w  'N  W   -ld 97- IS                                    Pe " "'"'&#13;
/A THE VERTICAL AXIS IS LOGARITHMIC SO THAT YIELD DATA ARE INTERPRETED DIRECTLY&#13;
AS GROWTH IN YIELDS.&#13;
SOURCE: FAO, PRODUCTION YEARBOOK, VARIOUS ISSUES.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
31.      World wheat yields grew at an annual rate of 3.1% from 1961 to 1970,&#13;
and at the much slower rate of 1.7% over the 1970-79 period. The slow growth&#13;
in the 1970s was entirely due to almost negligible growth in Canada, the&#13;
United States and the IJSSR. It is evident from Figure 6 that: the 1970s saw&#13;
some disturbing fluctuations in yields in the United States due to weather.&#13;
There were sharp reductions in 1974 due to the cold, wet spring and early fall&#13;
freeze, and in 1976-77 due to the extended drought. All three industrial&#13;
countries shown in Figure 6 exhibit a slowing down in the historical growth of&#13;
wheat yields. The sudden increase in the United Kingdom in the late 1970s&#13;
probably represents the partial changeover from bread wheat to higher-yielding&#13;
feed wheat. In many developing countries, as exemplified by the three examples&#13;
in Figure 6, wheat yields are growing at an increasing rate. It is hard to see&#13;
why there might be a sudden change from these recent trends.&#13;
32.      In examining( coarse grains' yields,    it is important to split the&#13;
total into maize and Dther coarse grains (where "other" include sorghum,&#13;
millet, rye, oats and barley). There are large differences in production and&#13;
yields between the othe:r coarse grains and maize, which has received the bulk&#13;
of research and develolment expenditures and which is more often irrigated&#13;
than the other coarse grains. As a result, there has already been a substan-&#13;
tial shift from sorghum and millet to the higher yielding maize. Maize&#13;
production is now more l:han half of total coarse grains production.&#13;
33.      The industrial countries have maize yields two to three times greater&#13;
than those of the rest of the world, mainly as a result of greater irrigation&#13;
and fertilizer inputs. 'he United States has, by far, the highest yields, pro-&#13;
ducing over 6.5 tons of maize per hectare. This is twice the yields achieved&#13;
in Argentina and four times the yields achieved in Brazil. Yields in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
centrally planned economies are only about half those of the United States.&#13;
Yields in the United States, producer of about half the world's total, grew&#13;
strongly in the 1961-80 period. Argentina, one of the more important develop-&#13;
ing country producers, recorded growth rates in maize yields during the 1970s&#13;
of 4.4% p.a. However, growth in maize yields in the industrial countries has&#13;
been slowing down while in the developing countries growth rates are still&#13;
increasing (Figure 7).&#13;
34.      Yields of other coarse grains are generally less than one-half of the&#13;
yields of maize. Yields in the United States, the second largest producer, are&#13;
around 2.5 tons per hectare. The USSR, the largest producer, has yields less&#13;
than half those of the United States. France and Canada are other major indus-&#13;
trial coarse grain producing countries. India, Argentina and Mexico are impor-&#13;
tant developing country producers. Data on the other coarse grains generally&#13;
show constant growth in industrial countries yields, a sharp slowdown in&#13;
growth in centrally planned economies yield growth during the 1970s by com-&#13;
parison with the 1960s, and yields in the developing countries growing faster&#13;
in the latter period (see, for example, India's sorghum yields in Figure 4).&#13;
35.      In the United States and Japan, the only major industrial country&#13;
rice producers, yields grew at an increasing rate throughout the 1950s and&#13;
early 1960s, slowing down in the late 1960s, and growing at a constant rate'&#13;
during the 1970s (Figure 8). Recent yields (1978-80 average) of rice in the&#13;
United States and Japan have been 5 and 5.8 tons per hectare, respectively,&#13;
and in industrial countries yield increases have accounted for all of the&#13;
production increases as area harvested has actually declined. The contrasting&#13;
experience of developing countries is striking. In China and the Philippines,&#13;
for example, and to a lesser extent in Thailand and Pakistan, growth rates of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-35 -&#13;
yields are still increasing (Figure 8). In China, growth in yields has&#13;
increased at a fairly sl:eady rate over the last 30 years to 4.2' tons/ha in the&#13;
period 1978-80. In the l'hilippines the rate of growth in yields; since 1957 has&#13;
been much greater than in China, but is still only 2.1 tons/ha. Yields over&#13;
the period 1978-80 averaged 2.4 tons/ha in Pakistan and 2.0 tons/ha in&#13;
Thailand. In Pakistan, growth in yields, after being stagnant during the 1950s&#13;
and early 1960s, accelerated greatly during the late 1960s and early 1970s and&#13;
has since flattened off; though yields are still increasing. Thailand displays&#13;
a similiar pattern to Pakistan, though the changes have been more moderate&#13;
than in Pakistan. Over the most recent decade, increasing yields in China and&#13;
the Philippines have contributed to approximately 80% of the output increase,&#13;
while in Pakistan and Thailand increasing yields have only conl:ributed 57% and&#13;
39%, respectively, of the increased output. Considerable area expansion has&#13;
taken place in the latter two countries.&#13;
Other Factors&#13;
36.      The projections of food consumption to 1995 leave oul: some important&#13;
components of the food basket, such as eggs, milk, vegetables and other meats.&#13;
Besides changes in income, population and the income elasticii:y of demand for&#13;
food, other factors aff'ecting food consumption may also change over time. Two&#13;
factors that could be important are the distribution of income and the age&#13;
distribution of the population. Allowance was made in the above projections&#13;
for changes in income elasticity of demand over time. However, these were the&#13;
result of educated guesses. No allowance was made for change in income distri-&#13;
bution and population distribution. 'We need to get a better idea of how income&#13;
elasticities change with changes in income for different comaodities and for&#13;
this we need extensive time-series and cross-section studies. The age distri-&#13;
bution of the population should also affect food consumption patterns,&#13;
especially for commodities such as milk and meat. With developing countries&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
expected to experience some significant changes in population distribution as&#13;
their population growth slows in the years ahead, there is also room for work&#13;
on this aspect of demand.&#13;
37.      As   we  noted  earlier  it   is  likely  that  within  many   developing&#13;
countries growth in food consumption has been affected, negatively, by&#13;
distorted prices and income distribution which is biased against the poor.&#13;
From data assembled by the World Bank, nominal protection coefficients (NPCs)&#13;
have been calculated for agricultural production in various countries. 1/ In&#13;
Table 7 we have presented NPCs for 19 developing countries, calculated in most&#13;
cases for the most important grain grown in each country. 2/ Bearing in mind&#13;
the qualifications attached to these estimates, it is obvious that food&#13;
production faces severe implicit or explicit taxes in many developing&#13;
countries. It is our opinion that this factor has been the most important&#13;
disincentive to the adoption of improved agricultural production performance&#13;
in Africa, the region of most persistent concern about human nutrition, and&#13;
that there would be a marked improvement if these disincentives were removed.&#13;
And to reiterate, the pay-off to public investment in research and infras-&#13;
tructure designed to assist agriculture will not be as effective as it could&#13;
be, so long as such distortions remain.&#13;
1/ The nominal protection coefficient measures the incentives or disincen-&#13;
tives faced by producers by comparison with prices they would receive if&#13;
there were free trade. The NPCs take account of tariffs, quotas and non-&#13;
tariff barriers which protect farmers as well as export taxes or other&#13;
restrictions that may penalize them. These NPC estimates are also adjusted&#13;
for exchange rate under- or over-valuation, but they are not adjusted for&#13;
the protection given to tradable inputs such as fertilizer or machinery.&#13;
Fbr an evaluation of the effects of such price distortions for several&#13;
industrial and developing countries, in terms of income transfers and&#13;
welfare reductions, see Bale and Lutz.&#13;
2/ Fbr a larger set of NPC estimates refer to World Bank, 1982, pp. 48-9.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
TABLE 7: NOMINAL PROTECTION COEFFICIENTS CALCULATED FOR GRAINS&#13;
PRODUCTION IN DEVELOPING COUNTRIES&#13;
COUNTRY                             GRAIN                     NCP ESTIMATE /A&#13;
AFRICA&#13;
EGYPT                              MAIZE                          0.67&#13;
IVORY COAST                        RICE                           0.97&#13;
KENYA                              MAIZE                          0.91&#13;
SENEGAL                            RICE                           0.70&#13;
SUDAN                           SORGHUM                           0.50&#13;
TANZANIA                           MAIZE                          0.13&#13;
TUNISIA                            WHEAT                          0.99&#13;
ZAMBIA                            MAIZE                           0.62&#13;
ASIA&#13;
INDIA                              RICE                           0.65&#13;
PAKI STAN                         WHEAT                           0.76&#13;
PHILIPPINES                         RI CE                         0.73&#13;
THAILAND                           RICE                           0.58&#13;
EUROPE&#13;
TURKEY                            WHEAT                           0.94&#13;
YUGOSLAVIA                         WHEAT'                         0.38&#13;
LATIN AMERICA&#13;
ARGENTINA                          WHEAT                          0.64&#13;
BRAZIL                             RICE                           0.57&#13;
COLOMBIA                           RI CE                          0.92&#13;
MEXICO                            WHEAT                           0.89&#13;
URUGUAY                           WHEAT                           1.25&#13;
/A A VALUE GREATER THAN 1.0 INDICATES A SIUBSIDY ON PRODUCTION AND A VALUE&#13;
LESS THAN 1.0 INDICATES A TAX. THESE ESTIMATES HAVE BEEN MADE AT DIFFERENT&#13;
POINTS OF TIME AND NOW MAY WELL BE OUT OF DATE: MDREOVER, THE ESTIMATES DO&#13;
VARY WIDELY FROM YEAR TO YEAR WITHIN A COUNTRY.&#13;
SOURCE: WORLD BANK, 1982.&#13;
38.      World Bank and other estimates of Gini coefficients and other mea-&#13;
sures of income distriLbution suggest that incomes are generally much more&#13;
unevenly distributed in developing countries than in industrial countries. A&#13;
redistribution of incomes in these countries would certainly improve access to&#13;
food supplies by the poor in those countries. However, we would not argue&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
therefore for massive redistribution programs. Our opinion is that improved&#13;
pricing policies would, by encouraging agricultural production, raise the&#13;
levels of incomes of farmers and landless rural people who rely on farming for&#13;
their income. This would improve income distribution in favor of the sector in&#13;
which most of the poor are found, more effectively than any direct&#13;
intervention to change the distribution of incomes.&#13;
39.      Two final points.   The creation and development of a "world food&#13;
system" that has occurred since World War II has greatly alleviated the&#13;
possibility of widespread food shortages. At this time, virtually the entire&#13;
population of the world has access to the world food markets. Vastly improved&#13;
communications, lower surface and air transportation costs, the availability&#13;
of shipping, the construction of storage facilities, and the development of&#13;
infrastructure at dockside and in the hinterlands have all contributed to the&#13;
creation of this complex. Food merchants receive worldwide market reports on a&#13;
daily and sometimes hourly basis such that arbitrage opportunities largely&#13;
equalize the price of food commodities across the world (net of transportation&#13;
costs, government intervention activities, quality differences, and the like).&#13;
Because of these developments it is now possible to eliminate food shortages&#13;
caused by natural events. 1/&#13;
40.      And finally, it is well-known that projections of economic behavior&#13;
are notoriously unreliable (or are notoriously misinterpreted). All we know&#13;
about the future is what we hav,e observed in the past. We know that the future&#13;
will be similar to the past because in the past the future has been similar to&#13;
1/ D. Gale Johnson observed this development to one of the authors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
the past. Given this dictum we interpret the information provide!d here of over&#13;
30 years of declining agricultural prices and over 30 years of increasing crop&#13;
yields (now increasing al: an increasing rate in developing countries) as prima&#13;
facie evidence of the robustness of the world food system and of the likely&#13;
continuation of such trends. We feel that it is incumbent on those who view&#13;
the global food situation in a pessimistic way to provide a strong case of why&#13;
trends that have been in existence for at least thirty-five years will be&#13;
suddenly reversed. While we are cautiously optimistic about the continued&#13;
improvement of food consumption and food output throught the world, there is&#13;
no room for complacency. As Johnson has observed, "if circumstances are to&#13;
improve it is because efforts are made to make the improvement occur and at&#13;
least some of the hinderences that exist, such as trade restrict:ions, low farm&#13;
prices due to government constraints, and inadequate provision of farm inputs,&#13;
are ameliorated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
Bale, Malcolm and Ernst Lutz, "Price Distortions in Agriculture and Their&#13;
Effects: An International Comparison" Am. J. Agr. Econ., 63(1981): 8-22.&#13;
Barr, T.N., "The World Fbod Situation and Global Grain Prospects," Science,&#13;
214 (1981) :1087-95.&#13;
Eberstadt, Nick, "Hunger and Ideology" Commentary, July 1981, pp. 40-49.&#13;
Food and Agriculture Organization, Agriculture: Toward 2000, July 1979, FAO,&#13;
Rome.&#13;
, Food Balance Sheets 1975-77 Average and Per Capita Food&#13;
Supplies 1961-65 Average 1967 to 1977, Rome 1980.&#13;
Johnson, D. Gale, "The Current World Food Situation," Conference Proceedings,&#13;
The Role of Markets in the World Food Economy, Minneapolis, October 1982.&#13;
Kravis, I.S., A. Heston and R. Summers, International Comparisons of Real&#13;
Product and Purchasing Power, Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore,&#13;
1978.&#13;
Reutlinger, Shlomo, "World Bank Research on the Hunger Dimension of the Fbod&#13;
Problem," Research News, 3(1), Winter 1981/1982, World Bank, Washington,&#13;
D.C.&#13;
, "Food Insecurity: Magnitude and Remedies," World Devel.,&#13;
6(1978): 797-811.&#13;
Sen,   Amartya,    "Ingredients    of    Famine   Analyses:    Availability    and&#13;
Entitlements," Quart. J. Econ., 96 (1981): 433-64.&#13;
World Bank, World Development Report 1982, pp.48-9, Oxford University Press,&#13;
1982.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WiDrid     Bank                      Confronting Urban                    these studies is presented in&#13;
Malnutrition: The Design of          Migration in West Africa:&#13;
Piblications                         Nutrition Programs                   Demographic Aspects.&#13;
of' Related                          James E. Austin                      World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Describes a framework for            415. September 1980. vi + 385 pages&#13;
Interest                             systematically carrying out urban    (including .itatistical annexes,&#13;
nutrition programs that examines     bibliography).&#13;
several key considerations in nutri-  Stock No. W'P-0415. $15.00.&#13;
tion education, on-site feeding, take-&#13;
home feeding, nutrient-dense foods,&#13;
ration shops, food coupons, fortiflca-  Economic Motivation versus&#13;
tion, direct nutrient dosage, and food  City Lights: Testing&#13;
processing and distribution.         Hypotheses about Inter-&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press,  Changwat Migration in&#13;
1980. 136 pages.                     Thailancl&#13;
LC 79-3705. ISBN 0-8018-2261-0.      Fred Arnold and&#13;
$6.50 (£4.50) paperback.             Susan H. Cochrane&#13;
NlEW                                                                   World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
The Costs and Benefits of            416. September 1980. 41 pages&#13;
Analyzing the Impact of              Family Planning Programs              (including footnotes, references).&#13;
He;lth Services: Project             George C. Zaidan                      Stock No. WP-0416. $3.00.&#13;
Experiences from     India,          A technique for measuring the&#13;
Ghana, and Thailand                  economic returns from investing in   Economics of Supplemental&#13;
Rashid Faruqee                       population control, with an appraisal  Eedng     of a    uppsed&#13;
of inherent assumptions andFedn                ofMl      urs     d&#13;
Reviews four categories of health    limitations.                         Children: Leakages, Costs,&#13;
indi-ators (environment, services                                         and Benefits&#13;
offered, services received, and      The Johns Hopkins University Press,  On     enuds&#13;
changes in morality, morbidity, and  1971. 62 pages (including            Odin K. Knudsen&#13;
nutritional status) in order to evaluate  bibliography).                  Analyzes some of the economic&#13;
the impact of health projects in India  LC 70-155166. ISBN 0-8018-1317-4  issues involved in the supplemental&#13;
Ghana, and Thailand.                  40024)paebc.feeding of malnourished children.&#13;
$4.00 (£2.40) paperback.             Demonstrates that supplemental&#13;
Wor.d Bn     S a   g  Pae                                                 feeding programs are economically&#13;
No.N 546.-18213-01-. 44 p .          DemographAc Aspects of               justified if minimum improvements&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-011,7-9. $3.00.                                               in mor-tality rates anld mnore substan-&#13;
Migration in West Africa             tial increases in productivity take&#13;
-Volume 1                            place.&#13;
K. C. Zachariah                      World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
NVEW/                            and others                            451. April 1981. iv + 76 pages.&#13;
-- W                             Background data on migration in       Stock No. WP-0451. $3.00.&#13;
Beitiefits and Costs of Food         four English-speaking countries:&#13;
Ghana, Sierra Leone, Liberia, and&#13;
Dis,tribution Policies: The          The Gambia. A regional analysis       Experiments in Family&#13;
Indlia Case                          based on these studies is presented   Planning: Lessons from&#13;
Pasquale L. Scandizzo and            in Migration in West Africa:&#13;
Gurushri Swamy                       Demographic Aspects.                  the    Developing World&#13;
Analyzes some of the characteristics  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   Catherine S Fierce&#13;
and the main consequences of the     414. September 1980. vi + 363 pages   ac    hene     reviewoe&#13;
food distribution policies followed by  (including statistical annexes,    A comprehensive review of experi-&#13;
the Indian government and provides   bibliography).                        mental efforts in the developing&#13;
a qtiantUflcation and a cost-beneflt                                       world to determine more effective&#13;
ana. ysis of their effects on con-   Stock No. WP-0414. $15.00.            ways of provi ding family planning&#13;
surriers. producers, and the govern-                                       services.&#13;
merit budget.                        Demographic Aspects of                Ti- Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
Wor'd Bank Staff Working Paper       Migration in West Africa              1918. 276 pages (including bibliogra-&#13;
No. 509. August 1982. 54 pages.      -Volume 2                             phy, index of experiments).&#13;
ISBI/ 0-8213-0011-3. $3.00.           K. C. Zachariah                      LC 77-16596. ISBN 0-8018-2013-8,&#13;
and others                            $19.50 (11.50) hardcover;&#13;
ISBN 0-8018-2014-6, $8.95 (f4.00)&#13;
BSackground data on migration in     pprak&#13;
four French-speaking countries: Ivory  paperback.&#13;
Coast, Upper Volta, Senegal, and&#13;
Togo. A regional analysis based on&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Family Planning Programs:            Health                                  NYEW&#13;
An Evaluation of Experience          Fredrick Goiladay, &#13;
Roberto Cuca                         coordinating author                  Integrating Family Planning&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   Draws on experience gained from     with Health Services: Does&#13;
345. July 1979. xii + 134 pages      health components of seventy World   It Help?&#13;
(including 2 annexes, references).   Bank projects in forty-four countries  Rashid Faruqee&#13;
Stock No. WP-0345. $5.00.            Emphasizes the disproportionately    Analyzes the findings of an experi-&#13;
high expenditures incurred on cura-  ment carried out in Narangwal, a&#13;
tive medicine, maintenance of expen-  village in Punjab, India, between 1968&#13;
Fertility and Education:             sive hospitals, and sophisticated    and 1974 related to health care and&#13;
What Do We Really Know?              training of medical personnel at the  family planning. The World Bank col-&#13;
Susan H. Cochrane                    cost of prevent4ve care for the      laborated with The Johns Hopkins&#13;
A modl idetifyig themany han- majority of the people. Points out  University in analyzing this data from&#13;
A model identifying the many chan-   that low-cost health care systems are  one of the best known and well-docu-&#13;
nets through which education might   feasible and recommends that the     mented field experiments in health&#13;
act to determine fertility and a review  Bank begin regular and direct lend-  (.are and family planning in the world.&#13;
Of the evidence of the relation      ..&#13;
between education and the interven-  ing for health, in addition to having  World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
betwen ducaionand he nteren- health components as part of&#13;
ing variables in the model that affect                                   No. 515. September 1982. 47 pages.&#13;
fertility.                                                               ISBN 0-8213-0003-2. $3.00.&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press,  Sector Policy Paper. February 1980.&#13;
1979. 188 pages (including bibliogra-  90 pages (including 8 annexes,&#13;
phy, index).                         4 figures, map). English, French,    Kenya: Population&#13;
LC 78-260y70.5BN 0-8018-2140-1,      Japanese, Spanish, andArabic.       and Development&#13;
$6.95 (74.75) paperback.             Stock Nos. PP-8001-E, PP-8001-F,     (See description under Country&#13;
PP-8001-J, PP-8001-S. PP-8001-A.     Studies listing.)&#13;
$5.00.&#13;
Fertility and Its Regulation                                              Malnourished People:&#13;
In Bangladesh                        Health Issues and Policies          A Policy View&#13;
R. Amin and                          in the Developing Countries          (See description under Development&#13;
Rashid Faruqee                       Fredrick Golladay                   listing.)&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
383. April 1980. iv + 50 pages       412. August 1980. ii + 53 pages.     Malnutrition and Poverty:&#13;
(including references).              Stock No. WP-0412. $3.00.            Magnitude and Policy&#13;
Stock No. WP-0383. $3.00.                                                 Options&#13;
______W__                        Shlomo Reutlinger and&#13;
NEW                                  MEW                              Marcelo Selowsky&#13;
Health, Nutrition, and               The first large research effort in the&#13;
Food Distribution and                Famil Planning In India: A           World Bank to determine the global&#13;
Nutrition Intervention: The          Survey of Experiments and            dimension of malnutrition.&#13;
Case of ChiFle                       Special Projects                     The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
Lloyd Harbert and                    Rashid Faruqee and                   1976; 2nd printing, 1978. 94 pages&#13;
Pasquale L. Scandizzo                Ethna Johnson                        (including 5 appendixes).&#13;
The impact of Chile's Complementary  Surveys fourteen experiments and     LC 76-17240. ISBN 0-8018-1868-0,&#13;
Feeding Program (CFP), both on the   special projects in health, nutrition,  $4.75 (f2.85) paperback.&#13;
direct and indirect beneficiaries, is  and family planning in India and pro-  Spanish: Desnutrici6n y pobreza:&#13;
analyzed. Describes Chile's major    poses guidelines for future Bank     magnitudes y opciones de polftica.&#13;
nutrition intervention programs and  projects on the basis of the survey.  Editorial Tecnos, 1977.&#13;
establishes the relative importance of&#13;
the CFP in terms of budgetary expen-  World Bank Staff Working Paper     ISBN 84-309-0726-2, 380 pesetas.&#13;
ditures and number of beneficiaries  No. 507. February 1982. xi -- 97 pages&#13;
reached. Reviews briefly the pro-    (including references).              Measuring Urban Malnutri-&#13;
grams past limitations, recent       Stock No. WP-0507. S5.00.            tion and Poverty: A Case&#13;
reforms, and potentala effectiveness.                                     Study of Bogota and Call,&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.                                        Colombia&#13;
512. May 1982. v + 45 pages (including                                    Rakesh Mohan,&#13;
bibliography. annex).                                                     M. Wilhelm Wagner,&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0001-6. $3.00.                                                and Jorge Garcia&#13;
Attempts to measure the extent of&#13;
malnutrition and poverty in the cities&#13;
of Bogota and Cali, Colombia. One&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
of five papers resulting from a       Population Policies and               REPRllf5&#13;
research program entitled "City       Economic Development                  Health Care In the Developing World:&#13;
Stucly," a study of the workings of   Timothy King and others               Problems; of Scarcity and Choice&#13;
five major urban sectors in                                                 (Shattuck Lecture)&#13;
Colcmbia.                             The English-language edition is       John R. Evans, ISaren Lashman Hall, and&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    out of print.                         Jeremy J. Warford&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Number 209.&#13;
447. April 1981. 80 pages (including  Spanish: Poifticas de poblaci6n y     Reprinted from New England Journal of Medicine,&#13;
bibliography, appendixes).            desarrollo econ6mico. Editorial       vol. 305 (November 1981:L11 7-27.&#13;
Stoc t No. WP-0447. $3.00.            Tecnos, 1975.                         Stock No. RP-0209. Free of charge.&#13;
ISBN 84-309-0605-3, 440 pesetas.&#13;
West  *                                       'l~~~~~~~~~~~~easuremnent of Deprivation and&#13;
Mig ration in West Afnca:                                                    Poverty Based on the Proportion&#13;
Demnographic Aspects                  Population Policy and                  Spent on Food: An Exploratory&#13;
K. C. Zachariah and                  Population Policy and                 Exercise&#13;
JulienC.Z hariad   n                  Family Planning Programs:              V.V. Bhanoji Rao&#13;
Juli en Conde                         Trends in Policy and                   World Bank Reprint Series: Number 193.&#13;
The first study of the large-scale    Administration                         Reprinted fiom World Development. vol. 9. no. 4&#13;
movement of people in nine West       Kandiah Kanagaratnam and               (1981):337-53.&#13;
African countries. Discusses the      Cathein     S.nagarce                  Stock No. RP-0193. Free of charge.&#13;
volu -ne and direction of internal and  Catherine S. Pierce&#13;
extei nal flows and the economic and   World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    Nutrition, Health, and Education: The&#13;
sociali characteristics of migrants.  411. August 1980. iii + 22 pages       Economic Significance of&#13;
footnotes).          ~~Complenientaritics at Earty Age&#13;
A joi rit World Bank-OECD study. Oxford  (including footnotes).              Marcelo elowskay&#13;
Uniumrsity Press, 1981. 166 pages     Stock No. WP-0411. $3.00.              World Bank Reprint Series: Number 218.&#13;
(including 22 maps, bibliography,                                            Reprinted fiom Journal of Development&#13;
inder).                                                                      Economics, vol. 9 (1981):331-46.&#13;
LC 80-21352. ISBN 0-19-520186-8,      Regional Aspects of Family             Slock No. FP-0218. free of charge.&#13;
$19095                                P10.50) hardcover  Panning and Fertility&#13;
ISBN 0-19-520187-6, $8.95 (h4.50)      Behavior in Indonesia&#13;
paperback.                             Dov Chernichovsky and&#13;
Oey Astra Meesook&#13;
Discusses the recent decline in&#13;
Nutrition and Food Needs               Indonesia's population growth rate&#13;
in Cleveloping Countries               despite that country's relatively low&#13;
Odill K. Knudsen and                   level of income and socioeconomic&#13;
Pasqluale L. Scandizzo                 development. Reviews the history&#13;
and organization of the family plan-&#13;
Worldl Bank Staff Working Paper No.    ning program and attempts to iden-&#13;
328. Nay 1979. 73 pages (including     tify those factors that have been&#13;
4 appendixes).                        responsible for its success and&#13;
Stock tNo. WP-0328. $3.00.             assesses its prospects for the future.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Population and Poverty In              462. May 1981. 62 pages (including&#13;
theDevelopioang Woverld      In       appendix, references).&#13;
the Developing World                   Stock No. WP-0462. $3.00.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
$04. July 1980. 96 pages (including&#13;
? appendixes, bibliography).&#13;
3tocl: No. WP-0404. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
World      Bank                       Agrcultural Credit                  Agricultural Price&#13;
Fpi Ub4tl(L tbONS                    Outlines agricultural credit practices  Management in Egypt&#13;
and problems, programs, and         William Cuddihy&#13;
oA  Kelated                           policies in developing countries and  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
interest                             discusses their implications for World  388. April 1980. x + 164 pages (includ-&#13;
.uterest                            Bank operations.                    ing annex, bibliography).&#13;
A World Bank Paper. May 1975. 85    Stock No. WP-0388. $5.00.&#13;
Adoption of Agricultural              pages (including 14 annex tables).&#13;
Innovations in Developing             English. French, and Spanish.      Agricultural Price Policies&#13;
Countries: A Survey                   Stock Nos. PP-7502-E, PP-7502-F,    and the Developing&#13;
Gershon Feder, Richard Just,          PP-7502 -S. $5.00 paperback.        Countries&#13;
and David Silberman                                                       George Tolley, Vinod Thomas,&#13;
Reviews various studies that have pro-  The Agricultural Economy of       and Chung Ming Wong&#13;
vided a description of and possible   Northeast Brazil                    This book first considers price&#13;
explanation for patterns of innovation  Gary R Kutcher and                policies in lKorea, Bangladesh, Thai-&#13;
adoption in the agricultural sector.  Pasquale L. Scandizzo               land, and Venezuela, bringing out th4&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper        This study, based on an agricultural  consequences for government cost&#13;
and revenue, farm income, and pro-&#13;
No. 542. 1982. 65 pages.              survey of 8,000 farms, assesses the  ducer and consumer welfare. Other&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0103-9. $3.00.            extent and root causes of pervasive  effects, including those on agri-&#13;
rural poverty in northeast Brazil. The  cultural diversification, inflation,&#13;
arian Reform as                   authors review a number of policy   economic growth, and the balance 0'&#13;
Agrarian                              and project options; they conclude  payments are also discussed. The&#13;
Unfinished Business-                 that courageous land reform is the   second part of the book provides a&#13;
the Selected Papers of                only effective means of dealing with  methodology for estimating these&#13;
Wolf Ladejinsky                       the problem.                        effects in any country. Operational&#13;
Louis J. Walinsky, editor             The Johns Hopkins University Press,  tools for measuring the effects on&#13;
Studies in agrarian policy and land   1982. 288 pages.                    producers, consumers, and govern-&#13;
reform spanning four decades,         LC 81-47615. ISBN 0-8018-2581-4,    ment are developed and applied.&#13;
grouped chronologically according to  $25.00 (17.50) hardcover.           The Johns Hopkins dniuersity Press,&#13;
Ladejinsky's years in Washington,                                         1982. 256 pages.&#13;
Tokyo, and Vietnam and while at the&#13;
Ford Foundation and the World Bank.   Agricultural Extension: The         LC 81-15585. ISBN 0-8018-2704-3,&#13;
oxford University Press, 1977. 614    Training and Visit System           $25.00 (S17.50) hardcover.&#13;
pages (including appendixes. index).  Daniel Benor&#13;
and James Q. Harrison               Agricultural Project&#13;
LC 77-24254.15SBN 0-19-920095-5       Describes the Training and Visit    Analysis: Case Studies and&#13;
$32.50 (i14.95) hardcover;            System of extension developed by    Exercises&#13;
ISBN 0-19-920098-X, $14.95 (S5.25)    Daniel Benor and introduced in a    Case studies and exercises on&#13;
paperback.                            number of projects assisted by the  agricultural project preparation and&#13;
Agrarian Reforms in                   World Bank in developing countries.  analysis, developed for, and used in.&#13;
Developing Rural                      May 1977. 55 pages (including annex).  EDI's rural development and rural&#13;
Economies Characterized by            English. French, and Spanish.       credit courses.&#13;
Interlinliked Credit and              Stock Nos. PM-7701-E, PM-7701-F,    World Bank (EDI), 1979, v.1-viii&#13;
Tenancy Markets                       PM-7701-S. $3.00 paperback.         711 pages. u.2-iu + 113 pages. v.3&#13;
Avishay Bravermanl                                                        -iv + 15 7 pages. (Available from ILS,&#13;
and T. t'1. Srinivasan              Agricultural Land                   1715 ConnecticutAvenue, N.W.,&#13;
and T N. Srinivasan                   Settlement                          Washington, D.C. 20009, U.SA.)&#13;
World Bank.Staff Working Paper No.    Theodore J. Goering, coor-          $9.00 paperback.&#13;
433. October 1980. 32 pages (including  dinating author&#13;
references).ArclualRsac&#13;
Examines selected issues related    Agricultural Research&#13;
Stock No. IP-0433. $3.00.             to the World Bank's lending for land  Points out that developing countries&#13;
settlement, and gives estimates of  must invest more in agricultural&#13;
the global rate of settlement and   research if they are to meet the&#13;
the world's ultimate potentially    needs of their growing populations.&#13;
arable land.              '         States that studies in Brazil, India,&#13;
Japan, Mexico, and the United States&#13;
A World Bank Issues Paper. January  show that agricultural research yields&#13;
1978. 73 pages (including 4 annexes).  a rate of return that is more than two&#13;
English, French, and Spanish.       to three times greater than returns&#13;
Stock Nlos. PP-7801-E, PP-7801-F,   from most alternative investments&#13;
PP-7801-S. $5.00 paperback.         and cites some of the successes of&#13;
the high-yielding varieties of rice and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
wheat that were developed in the    Farm Budgets: From Farm                  NEW&#13;
mid-19'60s. Discusses the World     Income Analysis to&#13;
Bank's plans to expand its lending for  Agricultural Project Analysis    Improving Irrigated Agricul-&#13;
agricu.tural research and extension,  Maxwell L. Brown                   ture: Institutionaf Reform&#13;
particularly for the production of&#13;
food and other commodities that are  Clarifies the relation between simple  and the Small Farmer&#13;
of importance to low-income con-    farm income analysis and the broader  Daniel W. Bromley&#13;
sumers, small farmers, and resource-  field of agricultural project analysis  A model of farmer interdependence is&#13;
poor areas.                         and emphasizes the more practical      del      o providepens       is&#13;
Sector Policy Paper. June 1981. 11  aspects of project preparation and   ivproving exdstinode ugigestions for&#13;
pages (including annexes). English.  gives guidance toriculture.         as well as for designing new ones.&#13;
French,. andt Spanish.              for planning in agriculture.&#13;
EDI Series in Economic Development.  World Bank5Staff Working Paper&#13;
Stock Yo. PP-8101-E, PP-8101-F,     The Johns Hopkins University Press.  No 531.198. 96pg&#13;
P?-81CI1-S. $5.00 paperbrack.       1980. 154 pages.                    ISBN 0-8213-0064-4. S3.00.&#13;
LC 79-3704. ISBN 0-8018-2386-2,&#13;
A De'relopment Model for             $15.00 (flO.50) hardcover,&#13;
the APgrcultural Sector             ISBN 8-8018-2387-0, $6.50                NEW&#13;
of Pcbrtugal                          4.0paebc&#13;
Alvin C. Egbert                     (i4S50) paperback.                   Increasing Agricultural&#13;
and lIyung M. Kim                   Spanish: t resupuestos de fincas.    Productivity&#13;
Spatia mathematical programming is                                       (Proceedings of the Third Annual&#13;
used to develop comprehensive and   ISBN 84-309-0886-2. 725 pesetas.     Agricultural Sector Symposium)&#13;
quantitative methods to suggest                                          Ted J. Davis, editor&#13;
develcpment strategies in Portugal's  Fishery                            These proceedings are the third in a&#13;
agriculture sector.                IHighlights the importance of fisheries  series of records of Agricultural Sec-&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press,  to the economies of developing coun-  tor Symposia presented at the World&#13;
1975. 110 pages (including          tries and recommends that the World  Bank each January since 1980. Con-&#13;
biblioc.raphy).                     Bank provide assistance to those     tains the papers presented by the&#13;
countries that have the fishery      speakers, chairpersons' statements.&#13;
LC 75-26662. ISBN 0-8018-1793-5,    resources and are willing to develop  and summaries of the discussions&#13;
S6.50 If4.00) paperback.            them further.                        prepared by the rapporteurs.&#13;
Economic Aspects and                Sector Policy Paper. December 1982.  1982. 307 pages (including index).&#13;
Policy Issues in Ground-            ISBN 0-8213-0138-.1. $5.00 paperback.  ISBN 0-8213-0099-7. S15.00.&#13;
wate,r Development&#13;
Ian Carruthers and Roy Stoner       Food Security in Food                    NEW&#13;
Examiines a wide range of economic  Deficit Countries&#13;
and. p&lt;,licy issues related to develop-  Shlomo Reutlinger               India: Demand and Supply&#13;
ment of groundwater for irrigation.  and Keith Knapp                     Prospects for Agriculture&#13;
World 3ank Staff Working Paper      World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   James Q. Harrison,&#13;
Yo. 49%i. October 1981. 110 pages   393. June 1980. 39 pages (including  Jon A. Hitchings,&#13;
'inclucing annex, bibliography).    appendix, references).               and John W. Wall&#13;
itock Ito. WP-0496. $5.00.          Stock No. WP-0393. $3.00.            Contains four papers that report on&#13;
the World Bank's economic work in&#13;
the agricultural sector in India and&#13;
MErW                            Forestry                             the implicat:ions of this development&#13;
Qraham   Donaldson, coordi-          both for foodgrains and for other&#13;
Economic Return to Invest-          nating author                        major agricultural commodities.&#13;
Focuses on the demand for&#13;
meni: in Irrigation in India        Examines the significance of forests  agricultural commodities through the&#13;
Leslie A. Abbie,                    in economic development and con-     year 2000, the foodgrain economy,&#13;
James Q. Harrison,                  cludes that the World Bank should    the vegetable oil economy, and the&#13;
3nd John W. Wall                    greatly increase its role in forestry  sugar economy.&#13;
development, both as a lender and&#13;
tepons on an investigation into the  adviser to governments.             World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
mfflcie lcy of investment in surface                                     No. 500. October 1981. 133 pages&#13;
ind gioundwater irrigation in India.  Sector Policy Paper. February 1978. 63  (including 5 appendixes. references,&#13;
pages (including 7 annexes). English,  a nnex).&#13;
4'orld 3ank Staff Working Paper     French, and Spanish.                     no.&#13;
Yo. 535. 1982. 52 pages.            Stock Nos. PP-7804-E, PP-7804-F,      tock No. 14'P-0500. 55.00.&#13;
SBN 0-8213-0083-0. $3.00.           PP-7804-S. $5.00 paperback.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Agricultural Research and               NEW                             Casos y Ejercicios Sobre&#13;
Productivity                                                            Proyectos Agrcolas&#13;
Robert E. Evenson                   The Book of CliAC:                  Edited by Orlando T. Espadas&#13;
and Yoav Kislev                     Programming Studies for             Three case studies prepared in con-&#13;
Examines the role of scientific     Mexican Agricultural Policy         junction with the EDI's Agricultural&#13;
research and technological change in  Edited by Roger D. Norton and     Projects Courses in Spanish and&#13;
increasing agricultural productivity.  Leopoldo Solis M.                intended primarly for teachers of&#13;
project analysis.&#13;
Yale University Press. 302 Temple Street,  The principal tool of analysis is the&#13;
New Hauen, Connecticut 06520, U.S5A.  sector model CHAC, named after the  World Bank (EDI). March 1974; revised&#13;
1975. xi + 204 pages (including 10  Mayan rain god. This model can be   January 1975. 480 pages (Available&#13;
appendixes, references. index).     used throughout the sector to cover  from ILS, 1715 Connecticut Avenue,&#13;
short-cycle crops, their inputs, and  N.W., Washington, D.C. 20009, U.S.A.)&#13;
LC 74-15210. ISBN 0-300-01815-0,    their markets. It can also be broken  $5.00 paperback.&#13;
$15.00 hardcover, ISBN 0-300-01877-0,  down into submodels for particular&#13;
$3.95 paperback.                    localities if more detailed analysis is&#13;
Spanish: Investigacon agricola y pro-  required. The model helps planners  The Design of Organiza-&#13;
Spansh:Invstigci6 agicol y ro- weigh the costs among policy goals,&#13;
ductividad. Editorial Tecnos, 1976.  which can vary from region to region.  tions for Rural Development&#13;
ISBN 84-309-0641-X, 420 pesetas.    This volume reports the experience of  Projects-a Progress&#13;
using the CllAC model and also pre-  Report&#13;
sents purely methodological material.  William E. Smith,&#13;
Agroindustrial Project              The Johns ilopkins University Press,  Francis J. Lethem, and&#13;
Analysis                            1983. 632 pages.                    Ben A. Thoolen&#13;
James E. Austin                     LC 80-29366. ISBN 0-8018-2585-7,    World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Provides and illustrates a framework  $35.00 (f24.50) hardcover.        375. March 1980. 48 pages. English&#13;
for analyzing and designing agro-&#13;
industrial projects.                                                    and French.&#13;
EDI Series in Eco,nomic Development.     NEW                            Stock No. WP-0375-E. WP-0375-F.&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
1981. 224 pages (including appen-   Building National Capacity&#13;
dixes, bibliography, and index).    to Develop Water Users'              The Design of Rural&#13;
LC 80-550. ISBN 0-8018-2412-5,      Associations: Experience             Development: Lessons&#13;
$16.50 (210.00) hardcover; ISBN     from the Philippines                 from Africa&#13;
0-8018-2413-3, $7.50 (24.25)        Frances F Korten                     Uma Lele&#13;
paperback.                          Over a flve-year period, the Niational  Analyzes new ways of designing rural&#13;
French: L'Analyse des projets agro-  Irrigation Administration (NIA) of the  development projects to reach large&#13;
industriels. Economica, 1982.       Fhilippines has been building its    numbers of low-income subsistence&#13;
ISBNl 2-7178-0480-3, 49 francs.     capacity to develop water users      populations. The paperback reprint-&#13;
associations on small-scale irrigation  ing in 1979 contains a new chapter by&#13;
Spanish: Analisis de proyectos agro-  systems. This paper details the    the author updating her findings.&#13;
industriales. Editorial Tecnos, 1981.  changes that have been made within  The Johns tiopkins University Press,&#13;
ISBN 84-309-0882-X, 600 pesetas.    the agency as a result of the develop  1975; 3rd printing, 1979. 260 pages&#13;
ment of these associations prior to&#13;
the construction of the physical    (including glossary, appendix, maps,&#13;
Argentina: Country Case             system and the involvement of       bibliography, index).&#13;
Study of Agricultural Prices,       association members in the planning  ISBN 0-8018-1769-2, S9.95&#13;
Taxes, and Subsidies                and construction stages. It also     paperback&#13;
examines the nature of the learning  paerck.&#13;
Lucio Gi. Reca                      process that has led to these changes  French: Le developpement&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  and discusses the implications for   rural: 1'experience Africaine.&#13;
386. April 1980. 72 pages (including  donor support of other small-scale  Economica, 1977.&#13;
3 annexes).                irrigation programs and more        ISBN 2- 7178-0006-9, 39 francs.&#13;
3 annexes).                         generally for programs involving&#13;
Stock No. WP-0386. $3.00.           village-level work.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
No. 528. July 1982. u + 69 pages&#13;
(including references).&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0051-2. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Land Reform                           and they involve a variety of invest-  Rethinking Artisanal Fish-&#13;
Examiiies the characteristics of land  ments. The need for monitoring and   eries Development: Western&#13;
reform, its implications for the      evaluating them during implementa-    Concepts, Asian Experiences&#13;
economies of developing countries,    tion has been accepted in principle.  Donald K. Emmerson&#13;
and th~ major policy options open to  but effective systems have not&#13;
the Wcrld Bank in this field.         heretofore been formulated. The con-  World Bank .Staff Working Paper lo.&#13;
cepts of monitoring and evaluation    423. October 1980. x - 97 pages&#13;
A World( Bank Paper. May 1975. 73     are differentiated and issues that    (including references).&#13;
pages X including 2 annexes).         need to be considered in designing&#13;
English. French, and Spanish.         systems to monitor and evaluate       Stock No. WP-0423. $5.00.&#13;
specific projects are outlined,&#13;
Stock lfos. PP-7503-E, PP-7503-F,     emphasizing the timeliness of the     Rural Development&#13;
PP-7503-S. $5.00 paperback.           monitoring functions for effective&#13;
management. Elaborates on such        Discusses strategy designed to extend&#13;
technical issues ds selection of indica-  the benefits of developrnent to the&#13;
Land Tenure Systems and               tors, selection of survey methodology  rural poor and outlines the World&#13;
SociiLi Implications of               data analysis, and presentation. It is  Bank's plans for increasing its assis-&#13;
Fore:stry Development                 directed primarily to those working  tance in this sector.&#13;
Programs                              with specific projects and will be use-  Sector PolicL/ Paper, February 1975, 89&#13;
Michael 11. Cernea          ~~ful to project appraisal teams, to             -&#13;
Michael M. Cernea                     ful todesigners of monitoring and evalua-  pages (including 14 annexes). English.&#13;
World Blank Staff Working Paper NIo.  tion systems, and to project staff who  French, Spanish. and Arabic.&#13;
452. April 1981. 35 pages (including  work with these systems.              Stock Nos. PP-7501-E, PP-7501-F,&#13;
referen:es, bibliography).            The Johns Hopkins Uniuersity Press.   PP-7501-S. PP-7501-A. $5.00&#13;
Stock {lo. WP-0452. $3.00.            1982.145 pages. French and Spanish    paperback.&#13;
forthcoming.&#13;
Managing Information for              LC 82-7126. ISBN 0-8018-2910-0, S850  Rural Poverty Unperceived:&#13;
Ruana.gin Development: L     son      (f6.50) paperback.                    Problems and Remedies&#13;
Rurafl Development: Lessons                 P r                             Robert Chambers&#13;
from  Eastern Africa&#13;
Guido Deboeck and Bill Kinsey         Monitoring Rural Develop-             World 3ank .Staff Working Paper Yio.&#13;
World l5ank Staff Working Paper NIo.  ment in   East Asia                   400. July 1980. 51 pages (including&#13;
379. March 1980. vii + 70 pages       Guido Deboeck and Ronald              Stock o. W-0400. 3.00.&#13;
(incluoing 5 annexes, index).         World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Stock 11o. WP-0379. $3.00.            439. October 1980. 91 pages (including  R     P         Through&#13;
annexes).                             Rural Prcojects Through&#13;
Urban Eyes: An Interpreta-&#13;
Measuring Project Impact:             Stock rio. WP-0439. $5.00.            tion of the World Bank's&#13;
Monlitoring and Evaluation                                                  New-Style Rural Develop-&#13;
In th4e PIDER Rural Develop-          Nutritional Consequences              ment Projects&#13;
ment Project-Mexico                   of Agricultural Projects:             Judith Tendler&#13;
Michael M. Cernea                     Conceptual Relationships              This paper (describes the Bank's new-&#13;
World fank Staff Working Paper No.    and Assessment                        style rural development projects,&#13;
332. June 1979. ui + 131 pages        Approaches                            including some of the things that hap-&#13;
(including 3 annexes, appendix, map).  Per Pinstrup-Andersen                project when govoernensir,nment of a&#13;
Stock i o. WP-0332. $5.00.            World Bank Staff Working Paper Nlo.   by the Bank, redirect their public-sec-&#13;
456. April 1981. 93 pages (including  tor services and subsidies to the rural&#13;
bibliography, appendix).              poor.&#13;
NllW                              Stock Nio. WP-0456. $3.00.            World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
Monil:orlng and Evaluation                                                  No. 552. 1982.100 pages.&#13;
of Agriculture and Rural              Prices, Taxes, and Subsidies          ISfIri 0-8215-0028-8. $5.00.&#13;
Devellopment Projects                 inP     s                             Sociocultural Aspects of&#13;
Dennis J. Casley                       WO1976&#13;
and lenis A. Lury                     Carl Gotsch and Gilbert Brown         Developing Small-Scale&#13;
Ban Stff  oringPapr ro.  Fisheries:. Delivering&#13;
This book provides a how-to tool for  World Bank Staff Working Paper o.ies                   e&#13;
the design and implementation of      387. April 1980. 108 pages.           Seices to the Poor&#13;
monitc ring and evaluation systems in  Stock Nio. WP-0387. $5.00            Richard B. Pollnac&#13;
rural development projects. Because                                         World Bank Staff Working Paper l/o.&#13;
rural dclvelopment projects are com-                                        490. October 1981. iii + 61 pages&#13;
plex, they seek to benefit large num-                                       (including references).&#13;
bers of peop!e in remote rural areas,&#13;
Stock lio. WPD-0490. $5.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Some Aspects of Wheat and                          Credit and Sharecropping in Agrairlan&#13;
Rice Price Policy in India                         Societies&#13;
Raj Krishna and G. S.                              Avishay Braverman and TN. Srinivasan&#13;
Raychaudhuri                                       World Bank Reprint Series: Number 216.&#13;
Reprinted from Journal of Development&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.                 Economics, uol. 9 (December 1981): 289-312.&#13;
381. April 1980. 62 pages (including               Stock no. RP-0216. Free of charge.&#13;
2 appendixes, 6 tables, bibliography).&#13;
Stock Mo. WP-0.381. ~~~                farm Size and the Diffusion of Green&#13;
Stock Nlo. WP-0381. S3.00.                         Revolution Technology On Information&#13;
and Innovation Diffusion: A Bayesian&#13;
Approach&#13;
A System     of Monitoring and                     Gershon Feder and Gerald T. O'Mara&#13;
Evaluating Agricultural                            World Bank Reprint Series: Number 207.&#13;
Extension Projects                                 Reprinted from Economic Development and&#13;
Michael M. Cernea and                              Cultural Change, vol. 30. no. I (October&#13;
~~~~  ,. ~~~~~~~~~~~~1981):59-76:- and American Journal of Agricultural&#13;
Benjamin J. Tepping                                Economic5, uol. 64. no. I (February 19821:145-47.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.                 Stock No. RP-0207. Free of charge.&#13;
272. December 1977. vi + U15 pages&#13;
(including 9 annexes, bibliography).               Sociological Dimensions of Extension&#13;
Stock No. WP-02 72. S5.00.                          Organization: The Introduction of the&#13;
Ta&amp;V System In India&#13;
Michael M. Cernea&#13;
Thailand-Case Study of                              World Bank Reprint Series: Naumber 196.&#13;
Agricultural Input and                ~~~~~Reprinted from Extension Education and Rural&#13;
Agriicultural Input and                             Development. uol. 2. (1981):221-35. 281.&#13;
Output Pricing                                      Stock no. RP-0196. Free of charge.&#13;
Trent Bertrand&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
.385. April 1980. ix + 134 pages                        NEW&#13;
(including 2 appendixes).                           Economic Analysis of Agricultural Projects&#13;
Stock No. WP-0.385. $5.00.                          Second edition, completely revised and&#13;
expanded&#13;
REPRPINTS                                           J. Price Gittinger&#13;
This entirely new edition of the World Bank's best-selling&#13;
Adoption of Interrelated Agricultural               book sets out a careful and practical methodology for&#13;
Innovations: Complementarity and the                analyzing agricultural development projects and for using&#13;
Gershon Feder                                       these analyses to compare proposed investments. It&#13;
covers what constitutes a "project," what must be con-&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Number 206.              sidered to identify possible agricultural projects, the life&#13;
Reprinted from American Joumnal of Agricultural     cycle of a project, the strengths and pitfalls of project&#13;
Economics. uol. 64. no. I (February 1982):94-101.   analysis, and the calculations required to obtain financial&#13;
Stock No. RP-0206. Free of charge.                  and economic project accounts.&#13;
In the ten years since its publication, the first edition has&#13;
AgiriculturaJ Policies and Developiment:            been accepted widely as a standard reference and text. The&#13;
A Socioeconomic Investigation Applied               methodology reflects the best of contemporary practice in&#13;
Martha H. de Melo                                   government agencies and international development&#13;
Warth Bank deprint Series. Number 191.              institutions concerned with investing in agriculture and is&#13;
Word Bank Reprint Series: J lumber 191.             accessible to a broad readership of agricultural planners,&#13;
Reprinted from The Jounal of Policy Modeling.       engineers, and analysts.&#13;
vol. 1. no. 2 (May 1979J:217-34.                      This revision adds a wealth of recent project data;&#13;
Stock (to. RP-0191. Free of charge.                 expanded treatment of farm    budgets and the efficiency&#13;
prices used to calculate the effects of an investment on&#13;
Choice of Technique in Sahellan Rice                national income; a glossary of technical terms; expanded&#13;
Production                                          appendixes on preparing an agricultural project report and&#13;
Charles P 11umphreys and Scott R. Pearson           using discounting tables: and an expanded, completely&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Nlumber 199.             annotated bibliography.&#13;
Reprinted from Food Research Studies. vol. 17D&#13;
no. 3 (1979-80J:235-77.                              EDI Series in Economic Development.&#13;
Stock No. RP-0199. Free of charge.                   The Johns Htopkins Uniuersity Press. July 1982. 528 pages&#13;
(including appendixes and glossary/index).&#13;
LC 82-15262. ISBN 0-8018-2912-7. $37.50 (.22.50) hardcover;&#13;
ISBN 0-8018-2913-5, $13.50 (48.75) paperback.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WIORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
ORDER FORM&#13;
SEND TO:&#13;
W'ORLD BANK PUBLICATIONIS                                                       WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
P.O. BOX 37525                                              or                  66, AVENUE D'IENA&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013                                                          75116 PARIS, FRANCE&#13;
U S.A.&#13;
N;me:&#13;
Address:&#13;
Stock or ISBN #                             Author, Title                        Qty.        Price          Total    1&#13;
_.~~~~~~~~~~.&#13;
___                                                                                                         l   -&#13;
Sub-Total Cost:&#13;
Postage &amp; handling fee for more than two free items ($1 00 each): -_&#13;
Total copies: _     _       Air mail surcharge ($2.00 each):&#13;
TOTAL PAYMENT ENCLOSED: _                   -&#13;
Miake checks payable: WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
Propayment on orders from individuals is requested. Purchase orders are accepted from booksellers, library suppliers. libraries. and institutions.&#13;
All prices include cost of postage by the least expensive means. The prices and publication dates quoted in this Catalog are subject to change&#13;
witiout notice.&#13;
No refunds will be given for items that cainnot be filled. Credit will be applied towards future orders.&#13;
No more than two free publications will be provided without charge. Requests for additional copies will be fille?d at a charge of US $1.00 per&#13;
colpy to cover handling and postage costs.&#13;
Airmail delivery will require a prepayment of US $2.00 per copy&#13;
Mail-order payment to the World Bank need not be in U.S. dollars, but the amount remitted must be at the rate of exchange on the day the&#13;
orcier is placed. The World Bank will also accept Unesco coupons.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
*** HD 1417 .B34 1933 c.2&#13;
Bale, Malcolm D.&#13;
Prospects for food production&#13;
and consumption in developing&#13;
countries /&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank'&#13;
Headquarters:&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK&#13;
Cable address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
European Office:&#13;
66, avenue d'Ina&#13;
75116 Paris, France&#13;
Telephone: (1) 723-54.21&#13;
Telex: 842-620628&#13;
Tokyo Office:&#13;
Kokusai Building&#13;
1-1, Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
Telex: 781-26838&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0194-2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554855">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/05/1554855/prospects-food-production-consumption-developing-countries
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/05/1554855/prospects-food-production-consumption-developing-countries</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1983/05/1554855/prospects-food-production-consumption-developing-countries</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/07/09/000178830_98101903420554/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/07/09/000178830_98101903420554/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1983-05-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2002-07-19T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Prospects for food production and
            consumption in developing countries
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The available evidence indicates that,
            in aggregate, the growth in world food production over the
            past two decades has more than kept pace with the growth in
            population. This paper analyzes recent trends in world food
            production and consumption and outlines the Bank's
            approach to projections of food production and consumption
            providing results to the year 1995. It is shown that levels
            of consumption of various food items have improved in
            developing countries and are expected to continue to
            improve. Moreover, the results indicate favorable prospects
            for food production in developing countries. The paper
            comments throughout on areas where further work is required
            to refine the projection method and qualifies the generally
            optimistic outlook by identifying the types of actions that
            will be needed to accelerate food consumption and production
            in developing countries. Pricing policies in agriculture are
            seen as being particularly critical to the optimal
            development of the agricultural system in developing countries.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Prospects for food production and
            consumption in developing countries
        </docna>
        <display_title>Prospects for food production and
            consumption in developing countries</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1983/05/1554855/prospects-food-production-consumption-developing-countries</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Crops and Crop Management Systems,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Inequality,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Consumption</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Bale, Malcolm</author>
            <author>Duncan, R.</author>
            <author>CPD</author>
            <author>EPD</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903420554</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>AY</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 596</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Agriculture, fishing, and forestry</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0194-2</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Food consumption; Food prices; Food
            production; Food technology; Price distortions; Price
            policy; Projections; Trends
            aggregate demand,agricultural
            production,Agriculture,animal fats,ANIMAL OILS,ANIMAL
            PRODUCTS,Average Yields,balance of payments,BARLEY,capita
            consumption,CAPITAL FLOWS,CD,CENTRALLY PLANNED
            ECONOMIES,Cereals,CITRUS FRUITS,Coarse
            Grains,coconut,COCONUTS,commodity,comparative
            advantage,consumer prices,consumers,consumption,Consumption
            Growth,consumption levels,cost effectiveness,country
            level,crop,Crops,demand side,developed countries,developing
            areas,developing countries,ECONOMIC ANALYSIS,economic
            constraints,economic
            growth,EGGS,elasticities,equilibrium,exchange
            rate,FAO,farm,farmers,fertilizer,FISH,food consumption,food
            demand,food imports,food policies,food production,Food
            supply,Forecasts,fruit,grain,grain prices,Grains,Green
            Revolution,growth,growth rate,Growth Rates,Historical
            Growth,imports,Income,income data,income distribution,income
            groups,income level,increasing rate,individual
            countries,International Comparisons,Life expectancy,living
            standards,LOW INCOME,Maize,market
            economies,MEAT,MILLET,national income,net
            impact,OATS,OIL,OIL EXPORTERS,OILS &amp;
            FATS,OILSEEDS,PADDY,PALM OIL,per capita consumption,per
            capita consumption growth,per capita growth,per capita
            growth rate,per capita income,per capita incomes,POPULATION
            DATA,Population Growth,positive correlation,price
            elasticities,Price Indexes,production
            increases,productivity,productivity
            growth,PULSES,purchasing,Real GDP,relative prices,Rice,Rice
            Price,rice prices,rice production,rice
            yields,SORGHUM,SOYBEANS,SPRING,static
            equilibrium,SUGAR,total consumption,TUBERS,vegetable
            fats,VEGETABLE OILS,VEGETABLES,vegetables,Wheat,WHOLESALE
            PRICE INDEX,wto,Yields
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP596</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Extension &amp; Research</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Birth Spacing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock and Animal Husbandry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Community Based Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Raising Awareness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops and Crop Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Family Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Animal Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>