<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>The Gross Domestic Product of Czechoslovakia,&#13;
1970-1980&#13;
Peter Havlik          SWP772&#13;
Friedrich Levcik&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 772&#13;
A Background Study&#13;
for&#13;
Dollar GNPs of the U.S.S.R. and Eastern Europe&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS                        jjj Y 5g&#13;
Number 772&#13;
A Background Study                            W57&#13;
for&#13;
Dollar GNPs of the U.S.S.R. and Eastern Europe         WC 7&#13;
n?. 77.2&#13;
The Gross Domestic Product of Czechoslovakia,&#13;
1970-1980&#13;
Peter Havlik&#13;
Friedrich Levcik&#13;
'MrOL 4ST 'EAi Iu r&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright (© 1985&#13;
The Intemational Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THiE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing November 1985&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To present the&#13;
results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been prepared&#13;
in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed texts, and the World&#13;
Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a token charge&#13;
to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The World Bank does not accept responsibility for the views expressed herein, which&#13;
are those of the authors and should not be attributed to the World Bank or to its&#13;
affiliated organizations. The findings, interpretations, and conclusions are the results&#13;
of research supported by the Bank; they do not necessarily represent official policy of&#13;
the Bank. The designations employed, the presentation of material, and any maps used&#13;
in this document are solely for the convenience of the reader and do not imply the&#13;
expression of any opinion whatsoever on the part of the World Bank or its affiliates&#13;
conceming the legal status of any country, territory, city, area, or of its authorities, or&#13;
concerning the delimitation of its boundaries, or national affiliation.&#13;
The most recent World Bank publications are described in the annual spring and fall&#13;
lists; the continuing research program is described in the annual Abstracts of Current&#13;
Studies. The latest edition of each is available free of charge from the Publications Sales&#13;
Unit, Department T, The World Bank, 1818 H Street, N.W., Washington, D.C. 20433,&#13;
U.S.A., or from the European Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'lena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Peter Havlik is an economist at, and Friedrich Levcik director of, the Vienna Institute&#13;
for Comparative Economic Studies; both are consultants to the World Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging-in-Publication Data&#13;
Havlik, Peter.&#13;
The gross domestic product of Czechoslovakia,&#13;
1970-1980.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 772)&#13;
Includes bibliographical references.&#13;
1. Gross national product--Czechoslovakia.&#13;
2. Czechoslovakia--Economic conditions--1945-&#13;
I. Levcik, Friedrich. II. Title. III. Series.&#13;
HC270.295.I5H38      1985          339.3437           85-22725&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0634-0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FOREWORD&#13;
Centrally planned economies (CPEs) account for a significant share of&#13;
the world's production and income.     In view of their importance in the world&#13;
economy, and to facilitate international comparative analysis, for many years&#13;
the World Bank has included statistical data on these countries in those of&#13;
its publications that aim for universal coverage, such as The World Bank&#13;
Atlas.   Among these data, those relating to gross national product (GNP) and&#13;
to GNP per capita are the most important, and the Bank also needs them for&#13;
operational purposes for its member countries, which now include some CPEs.&#13;
In the CPEs prices are generally set administratively and are often&#13;
loosely or not at all related to the relative scarcity and costs of production&#13;
of goods and services.    This is particularly true of the exchange rate.      The&#13;
World Bank normally uses exchange rates for converting GNP figures from&#13;
national   currencies   into   dollars  (or   into  any   other   numeraire),   an&#13;
indispensable   step   for  international   comparisons.     The  choice   of  an&#13;
appropriate conversion factor therefore poses particularly difficult problems&#13;
for most CPEs.   A further difficulty arises because the national accounts of&#13;
the CPEs are based on the concept of net material product (NMP), which differs&#13;
from the concept of GNP used in market economies.      To derive the GNP numbers&#13;
of those CPEs that compile only NMP accounts, various adjustments must be&#13;
made.   The data required for making these adjustments are not always fully&#13;
available.   Finally, a separate set of issues arises in relation to year to&#13;
year comparisons within the same CPE.      For these too and the corresponding&#13;
growth rates, official data are not strictly comparable to growth rates of the&#13;
market economies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
In early 1982 a research project sponsored and financed by the World&#13;
Bank was undertaken to assess alternative methods of computing the per capita&#13;
dollar GNP levels and growth rates of CPEs.        It covered eight countries:&#13;
Bulgaria, Cuba, Czechoslovakia, the German Democratic Republic, Hungary,&#13;
Poland, Romania and the U.S.S.R.    The purpose of this research project was to&#13;
define the best among known methods that could be applied to CPEs as a group&#13;
and make use of available data.     It was not its aim to establish and define&#13;
new computation methods whose application would have required many more years&#13;
of effort, even if data had been available.&#13;
-    This  research   project  has  produced   eleven  reports,  which   are&#13;
published   simultaneously.    The  main   report  authored  by   the  principal&#13;
researcher for the project, Paul Marer, is published as a book, Dollar GNPs of&#13;
the USSR and Eastern Europe (Johns Hopkins University Press, 1985). The eight&#13;
country studies and two background papers are published separately in the&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper series.        The main report provides highly&#13;
valuable insights into the problems related to the estimation and comparison&#13;
of the GNPs and GNP growth rates of the CPEs. It also gives the author's best&#13;
estimates of the actual values of these indicators for the majority of CPEs&#13;
covered by the project, that is those for which there was some statistical&#13;
basis for computing estimates or choosing between those already available.&#13;
The main report on the Research Project on CPEs concludes that&#13;
adequate GNP data in national currencies can be derived for most CPEs by&#13;
adjusting official information about net material product in the light of&#13;
statistical  and other information known to country experts.         It further&#13;
concludes that the best method generally applicable to CPEs for converting&#13;
such GNP data from local currencies into dollars would use conversion rates&#13;
based upon purchasing power parity (PPP) information.       For comparison with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
corresponding World Bank data on other World Bank members, these conversion&#13;
rates should be adjusted to correct for the expected differences between the&#13;
PPP rates and the actual official exchange rates (the "exchange rate deviation&#13;
index"). The needed adjustments are estimated econometrically from the actual&#13;
differences observed at each level of per capita GNP among the thirty-one&#13;
market economies participating in Phase III (1975) of the International&#13;
Comparison Project (ICP).    For Hungary, Romania, and Poland, PPP information&#13;
is derived from Phase III (1975) of the ICP, while for Czechoslovakia, the&#13;
German Democratic Republic, and the U.S.S.R., it is derived from private&#13;
bilateral comparisons chain-linked to the ICP data.       This method yields a&#13;
range of per capita GNP estimates: for example, $2,700 to $5,700 with a&#13;
midpoint of $4,190, for the U.S.S.R. in 1980.    No PPP estimate was available,&#13;
and no GNP per capita figure in US dollars calculated, for Bulgaria and Cuba.&#13;
The main report also concludes that the official estimates of growth&#13;
rates of the CPEs "tend to yield varying degrees of upward bias."        For all&#13;
countries except Hungary, the experts lean toward preferring alternative&#13;
indices, constructed by outside experts with partial information, although&#13;
these too present problems (especially for countries other than the U.S.S.R.)&#13;
and the experts therefore fell short of endorsing them.       The author of the&#13;
study on Hungary leans toward preferring the official index at this time.&#13;
The country studies and background papers that are being issued in&#13;
the World Bank Staff Working Paper series provide additional details on the&#13;
CPEs studied and their exchange rates.     Some of the country studies include&#13;
the respective authors' estimates of per capita GNP in U.S. dollars.       These&#13;
estimates, however, are the individual authors' experimental computations,&#13;
based on methods that may not be consistently applicable to CPEs generally.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
There remain major uncertainties about GNP conversions by means of&#13;
"adjusted PPPs." In addition to numerous remaining theoretical .and practical&#13;
problems  associated   with  calculating  PPPs  within   the  framework  of  the&#13;
centrally coordinated ICP, private estimates such as those used in this study&#13;
for three CPEs still appear to be subject to a wide margin of error.&#13;
Furthermore, there is no other way to estimate the exchange rate deviation&#13;
index than to derive it from observation of the countries covered by the ICP&#13;
(almost all of which are market economies).      The applicability of an index&#13;
derived in this fashion to the CPEs, whose economic structures are very&#13;
different, remains subject to reservations.&#13;
The present study used ICP Phase III data relating to the year 1975,&#13;
extrapolated to 1980.    Phase IV ICP data already published shows estimates&#13;
directly relating to 1980 for European countries, including Hungary and&#13;
Poland; Romania, a participant in early phases of the ICP, has not pr9vided&#13;
the data needed for participation in Phase IV. It is noteworthy that Phase IV&#13;
estimates of Hungary's and Poland's per capita GNP in 1980 are lower than the&#13;
1975 results extrapolated to 1980, used by the Research Report on CPEs. These&#13;
differences are partly due to the greater attention paid in Phase IV to&#13;
quality differences and to other methodological advances.&#13;
During the course of 1983 the Bank, with the help of a distinguished&#13;
panel of experts, 1/ undertook a review of the methodological problems and&#13;
issues related to the estimation of internationally comparable per capita GNP&#13;
figures for all countries. The preliminary results of the research project on&#13;
CPEs constituted an important input into that review, whose findings and&#13;
1/ Abram Bergson, Harvard University, Chairman; Andre Vanoli, Institut&#13;
National de la Statistique et des Etudes Economiques; and Parmeet Singh,&#13;
Commonwealth Secretariat.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
recommendations were approved by the panel of experts.         In light of the&#13;
review; the Bank has decided that. for the time being (that is, at least until&#13;
data availability and other problems related to PPP information are resolved),&#13;
official GNP information converted at official exchange rates should generally&#13;
continue to provide the basis of the per capita GNP estimates published in The&#13;
World Bank Atlas.   Exceptions to this rule are to be made only when official&#13;
GNP data, in national currency, is exceptionally bad or compiled in ways which&#13;
diverge in an exceptionally large measure from the usual methods and&#13;
standards, or when the official exchange rate is exceptionally far removed&#13;
from the rate effectively governing foreign payments transactions. When there&#13;
is a reason to believe that such exceptional circumstances prevail, and&#13;
adequate information exists, appropriate adjustments are to be made.        When&#13;
adequate information does not exist and cannot be obtained, no estimates are&#13;
to be published.   At the time of writing this foreword, it seems likely that&#13;
lack of information will for some time prevent the Bank from making estimates&#13;
of the per capita GNP of most CPEs.     Thus The World Bank Atlas published in&#13;
early 1985 contains an estimate of the values of GNP and GNP per capita for&#13;
only one European CPE, Hungary.&#13;
Following the review endorsed by the panel of experts, the World Bank&#13;
has adopted calculation methods and obtained results which, for a few&#13;
countries, are different from those of the research project of CPEs.         The&#13;
Bank's general methodology must be applicable to all its member countries,&#13;
including most market economies and only a few CPEs; the Bank could demand&#13;
that its member countries provide additional information when needed; and it'&#13;
could, and did, decide not to estimate the per capita GNP of countries for&#13;
which a minimal, but still fairly extensive set of information could not be&#13;
obtained.   As noted earlier, however, the research project on CPEs has aimed&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
at defining a method consistently applicable to all CPEs and one that could&#13;
make use of available information.    These differences in aims and constraints&#13;
readily explain the differences in results.&#13;
The research project on CPEs, whose major findings are published in&#13;
the main report, has greatly enhanced the understanding of the CPEs' unique&#13;
macroeconomic accounting frameworks and pricing systems.        It has provided&#13;
insight into many substantive issues, in particular the relationship of&#13;
domestic and international prices.    The individual country reports, published&#13;
separately, shed much light on many important country-specific issues.       The&#13;
Bank will continue to build upon the valuable findings of the research project&#13;
on CPEs in its future efforts to understand these important components of the&#13;
global economy.&#13;
Jean Baneth&#13;
Director&#13;
Economic Analysis and Projections Department&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Background Studies for&#13;
Dollar GNPs of the U.S.S.R. and Eastern Europe&#13;
Issued as World Bank Staff Working Papers&#13;
A Study of Cuba's Material Product System, Its Conversion to the&#13;
System of National Accounts, and Estimation of Gross Domestic&#13;
Product per Capita and Growth Rates.&#13;
National Accounts Statistics and Exchange Rates for Bulgaria.&#13;
The Gross Domestic Product of Czechoslovakia, 1970-1980.&#13;
The Estimation of Gross Domestic Product and Its Growth Rate for&#13;
the German Democratic Republic.&#13;
National Accounts and the Estimation of Gross Domestic Product and&#13;
Its Growth Rates for Romania.&#13;
The Gross National    Product of Hungary:     Important Issues for&#13;
Comparative Research.&#13;
National Income Statistics for Poland, 1970-1980.&#13;
The Conversion of National Income Data of the U.S.S.R. to Concepts&#13;
of the System of National Accounts in Dollars and Estimation of&#13;
Growth Rates.&#13;
Exchange   Rates  in  Eastern   Europe:    Types,  Derivation,   and&#13;
Application.&#13;
Exchange Rates, Foreign Trade Accounting, and Purchasing-Power&#13;
Parity for Centrally Planned Economies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
A b s t r a c t&#13;
The paper considers the theoretical and practical problems connected with&#13;
the estimation of Gross Domestic Product for the centrally planned&#13;
economy of Czechoslovakia. In the methodological part the basic differen-&#13;
ces between the SNA and MPS accounting systems are discussed and several&#13;
transformation procedures are presented. The price formation used in&#13;
Czechoslovak MPS aggregates is briefly described before the problem of&#13;
converting-the data in national currency to US dollars is highlighted.&#13;
Alternative GDP estimates, exchange rates and growth rates are compared.&#13;
Own estimates, based on the purchasing parity type comparison with&#13;
Austria, are presented in comparison with official Czechoslovak indexes.&#13;
The appendices contain the detailed description of MPS/SNA transformation&#13;
procedures as well as the statistical tables illustrating the process of&#13;
GDP reconstruction based on Czechoslovak data for the period 1970-1980.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
S u m m a r y&#13;
The paper analyses the problem of obtaining estimates of the Gross&#13;
Domestic Product for the centrally planned economy of Czechoslovakia&#13;
which would be comparable with Western statistics. The Czechoslovak&#13;
authorities publish only a part of the system of balances of the national&#13;
economy, drawn up according to the MPS (Material Product System) methodo-&#13;
logy. The system differs from the SNA (System of National Accounts)&#13;
concept mainly in that it excludes the so called non-productive services&#13;
which - according to the MPS system - do not contribute to the generation&#13;
of new value and are treated basically as redistribution. In order to&#13;
obtain the SNA indicator of GDP, a rather straightforward method was&#13;
selected: the standard form of MPS Global Financial Balance is presented&#13;
in a more detailed form and items differentlv treated within the SNA are&#13;
regrouped appropriately. Although theoretically relatively simple, the&#13;
reconstruction of SNA indicators still poses a difficult problem as only&#13;
a part of the Global Financial Balance is generally published. Because of&#13;
the lacking data and the use of estimates, the deviations of the GDP in&#13;
current national currency units obtained by this method oscillate very&#13;
probably within a range of about + 3-4 % (of the actual GDP if all&#13;
required statistical information would be available).&#13;
The transformation procedure adopted, based as far as possible on the&#13;
official statistical data, does not leave much room for adjustments&#13;
allowing for the distorted relative prices (mainly subsidized personal&#13;
transport and housing, heavily taxed industrial consumer goods, etc.). A&#13;
brief description of the Czechoslovak price patterns (producer, consumer&#13;
and foreign trade prices) sheds some light on the impact of pricing on&#13;
the structure of GDP aggregates.&#13;
A separate problem is the selection of a realistic exchange rate to be&#13;
used for the conversion of GDP expressed in national currency to US&#13;
dollars. Six different conversion coefficients are discussed and the&#13;
scant economic meaning of the official exchange rate is illustrated. Even&#13;
if no ultimate solution for the realistic exchange rate is presented, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
alternative, purchasing power parity type conversion coefficients are&#13;
clearly more appropriate. The decisive impact of selecting the correct&#13;
conversion coefficient on obtaining the comparable GDP estimate in US&#13;
dollars is stressed: the relative differences of various GDP estimates in&#13;
national currency are negligible in comparison with the range of possible&#13;
GDP estimates in US dollars. Future research should therefore be focused&#13;
either on more plausible ways of assessing the real purchasing power of&#13;
currencies used in centrally planned economies or on to some other method&#13;
of obtaining comparable GDP estimates requiring no exchange rate conver-&#13;
sions. A volume of GDP per capita of about US $ 4500 in 1980 is the&#13;
authors' assessment.&#13;
The last part of the paper evaluates the real growth of the Czechoslovak&#13;
economy in 1970-1980. The upward bias in aggregates given at official&#13;
constant prices in the centrally planned economies is present also in the&#13;
case of Czechoslovakia. The estimated index of realistic price increases&#13;
in the field of consumption is derived from the comparison of relative&#13;
changes in purchasing power parities between the Czechoslovak and Austrian&#13;
currencies. Application of this index to the whole GDP gives an approxi-&#13;
mate lower boundary to the probable overall real price movements: the&#13;
estimated inflation in Czechoslovakia was about two times as high as the&#13;
officially reported one.&#13;
The paper contains two appendices: the first one describes in detail the&#13;
MPS/SNA GDP transformation algorithms, the second presents 21 statistical&#13;
tables illustrating all estimations using the Czechoslovak data for the&#13;
period 1970-1980.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
I.  Derivation of GDP and Comparison of Alternative&#13;
Estimation (in National Currency) ........................ 1&#13;
Inventory of the Main National Income Aggregates Published&#13;
by the Federal Statistical Office of Czechoslovakia ....... l&#13;
Method used for Transformation of MPS to SNA concept ......... 2&#13;
Adjustments Necessary for Transformation...... .................3&#13;
Derivation of GDP from Transformation Matrices .............*..4&#13;
Differences between CMEA and Czechoslovak MPS&#13;
Methodologies .....*.....  ........... .... ......................... 5&#13;
Derivation of Czechoslovak GDP Based on Available Data      .   . 6&#13;
Comparison with Alternative GDP Estimates in National&#13;
Currency ....              ...........           o..*o  ..o.l.................. 7&#13;
II.  Price Formation Used in Czechoslovak MPS Aggregates. ...... 20&#13;
Producer Prices.....                              o.o..oo.22&#13;
Retail Trade (Consumer) Prices......o.............. ,  -    25&#13;
Foreign Trade Prices....o... ....... ....o....... ......... 28&#13;
III.  Conversion from KCS to US Dollars..     ............oo28&#13;
IV.  Assessment of the Real Growth of the Czechoslovak&#13;
Economy in 1970-1980....... .............*00* ...        .... 32&#13;
Appendix A:   Conversion of MPS Data to SNA Indicators......e........39&#13;
Appendix B:   Statistical Tables with Calculations and Notes........ 62&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. DERIVATION OF GDP AND COMPARISON OF ALTERNATIVE&#13;
ESTIMATES (IN NATIONAL CURRENCY)&#13;
Inventory of the Main National Income Aggregates Published by the Federal&#13;
Statistical Office of Czechoslovakia&#13;
The Federal Statistical Office of Czechoslovakia (FSO) publishes only&#13;
a part of its system of balances of the national economy, drawn up according&#13;
to the MPS methodology. In essence, only the aggregates Gross Material Output&#13;
(GMO) and Net Material Product (NMP) are regularly published in the Statis-&#13;
tical Yearbooks. The most important balance, the so-called "Global Financial&#13;
Balance", or more precisely the "Balance of the Production, Distribution,&#13;
Redistribution and Use of the GMO and NMP" is considered classified informa-&#13;
tion and is not published. The incomes generated in the productive sphere are&#13;
linked, in the redistribution part of this balance, via the budget (comprising&#13;
both the state and national committees budgets), with the non-productive&#13;
sphere (excluded according to the MPS methodology from the national&#13;
accounts). The balance equates the final incomes of the population and of the&#13;
enterprises of the productive sphere and of the enterprises and institutions&#13;
of the non-productive sphere (including depreciation) with the means of pro-&#13;
duction and consumption goods generated at home and imported and destined for&#13;
consumption, gross capital formation and exports. No doubt the publication of&#13;
the Global Financial Balance would greatly facilitate the transformation of&#13;
the aggregates according to the MPS methodology into the national accounts&#13;
based on the SNA concept.&#13;
In recent years the FSO has published more statistical information on&#13;
the non-productive sphere, e.g. the "Balance of Money Incomes and Expenditure&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
of the Population", and, in a very aggregated form, the "Incomes and Outlays&#13;
of the Non-Productive Sphere", but this information cannot make up the gap&#13;
created by withholding the Global Financial Balance data.&#13;
Method Used for Transformation of MPS to SNA Concept&#13;
There is no information whether the Federal Statistical Office has&#13;
made computations of the Czechoslovak national accounts according to the SNA&#13;
concept for internal purposes. The Research Computing Centre of the UN&#13;
(Vyskumne vypoctov6 stredisko OSN) in Bratislava, Czechoslovakia has made such&#13;
a computation for 1970/1 using rules and procedures recommended by the&#13;
Conference of European Statisticans of the UN/ECE, Geneva./2&#13;
The present country study is using Bratislava (1972) as a point of&#13;
departure for our own computations. The main advantages of using such an&#13;
approach are: a) the conversion matrices (presented in Appendix A) can be&#13;
used for transformation to GDP based on primary incomes, final use and by&#13;
origin of social product; furthermore the GDP aggregate may be disaggregated&#13;
into major components, b) a time series 1970-1980 can be computed,/3 c) the&#13;
actual results of Bratislava (1972) for 1970 can be utilized (with some&#13;
additional modifications) and some of the data not presented in the published&#13;
official statistical materials can be estimated for later years on the basis&#13;
of the computation results of the Czechoslovak investigators (who had access&#13;
/1  Transformation of Indicators from Czecholovak MPS System to the SNA (in&#13;
Slovak). Research Report 48, VVS OSN, Bratislava, December 1972.&#13;
/2 Rules for Conceptual Adjustments Between the Systems of National Accounts&#13;
and Balances in Use in Europe. Conf. Eur. Stats. /WG.22/Gr.l/l, March&#13;
1965.&#13;
/3 All relevant statistical tables with detailed calculations and notes - see&#13;
Appendix B.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
to statistical sources not usually published - e.g. the Global Financial&#13;
Balance).&#13;
A disadvantage of the procedure selected may be that there is not&#13;
much room to depart from the pricing procedures actually used in Czechoslova-&#13;
kia (e.g. subsidized personal transport and housing). This may have an impact&#13;
on the structure of the GDP, but as the main aim of the World Rank project is&#13;
to obtain figures on the volume of the GDP aggregate only, this disadvantage&#13;
does not seem to be decisive. A short discussion on this subject and its&#13;
implication on a possible understatement of the GPD will be given in the part&#13;
discussing pricing problems.&#13;
Adjustments Necessary for Transformation&#13;
The adoption of the procedure developed in Bratislava, 1972 (and&#13;
based on Conf. Eur. Statis, 1965) requires presentation of the MPS data in a&#13;
form allowing for regrouping individual items treated differently in the&#13;
indicators adopted in SNA. For this purpose the standard form of MPS Global&#13;
Financial Balance must be presented in a more detailed way and items with&#13;
different treatment within the SNA concept must be regrouped appropriately.&#13;
The resulting Transformation Matrix I (see Appendix A) may be used as a&#13;
vantage point for the construction of SNA indicators. Presentation of this&#13;
matrix, based in principle on Bratislava (1972) is somewhat different from&#13;
that presented in Conf. Eur. Stats. mainly because the chief purpose is the&#13;
transformation from MPS to SNA only and MPS standards are taken as a base for&#13;
the necessary adjustments.&#13;
In the Transformation Matrix I all items subject to different&#13;
treatment in MPS and SNA are indicated. As the number of differences is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
rather numerous, only the most important ones (especially from the&#13;
quantitative point of view) are taken into account.&#13;
Derivation of GDP from Transformation Matrices&#13;
Although the number of non-zero elements in the Transformation Matrix&#13;
I is relatively low, the reconstruction of a matrix with real data still poses&#13;
a serious problem. The main source of data - Global Financial Balance - is&#13;
not generally available as it is not published in complete form in accessible&#13;
statistical materials. However, if our aim is to construct global indicators&#13;
only (i.e. GDP), the number of data needed for transformation can be even more&#13;
reduced. Yet in some cases estimation of missing items is necessary as well.&#13;
GDP Based on MPS Data on Primary Incomes&#13;
GDP may be calculated from MPS data by several alternative methods.&#13;
The first possibility is to start with Net Material Product and primary&#13;
incomes generated within the non-material sphere. In this case the NMP must&#13;
be adjusted mainly for wages and salaries and private incomes in the non-&#13;
material sphere, travel expenses, depreciation, etc. The adjustment&#13;
procedure, using the elements indicated in Transformation Matrix II, is&#13;
described in Appendix A.&#13;
GDP Based on MPS Data on Final Use&#13;
GDP may also be derived from MPS data on final use of NMP. MPS' Net&#13;
Material Product (National Income) must be adjusted for incomes and costs&#13;
within the non-material sphere, for balance of exports and imports and some&#13;
other minor transfers. The adjustment procedure uses the elements of&#13;
Transformation Matrix III (see Appendix A).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
GDP Based on NMP (MPS) by Origin&#13;
Finally, MPS data on the origin of Global Output and Net Material&#13;
Product may be used as a starting point for the derivation of GDP. This time,&#13;
NMP must be adjusted mainly for net output of non-material services (net of&#13;
material consumption and depreciation), costs of dwelling services, cost of&#13;
business travels, depreciation in the productive sphere, etc. (Appendix A).&#13;
Differences Between CMEA and Czechoslovak MPS Methodologies&#13;
The transformation procedures presented in this study are based on&#13;
MPS/SNA links (Conf. Eur. Stats. 1965) using standard CMEA concepts./4 Unfor-&#13;
tunately, each CMEA country uses a slightly different variation of its MPS&#13;
standard. Most of these variations are of a minor character (e.g. shifts&#13;
between industries, etc.), having no impact on the transformation of global&#13;
indicators, some of them however need to be taken into account. In the case&#13;
of Czechoslovakia, differences of this kind are mainly the following:&#13;
(a) The Czechoslovak methodology does not include in the productive&#13;
(material) sphere personal transport and the non-material part of communica-&#13;
tion services. While total production of communication services may be rela-&#13;
tively easily estimated, it is not so with the value of production of personal&#13;
transport. The CSSR study (Bratislava, 1972) approximates both values by&#13;
incomes of the non-material sphere from non-material services.&#13;
(b) Analogous with (a), productive (intermediate) consumption should be&#13;
adjusted.&#13;
/4 The Basic Methodological Principles on Construction of Statistical&#13;
Balances of National Economy (in Russian). CMEA, Moscow, 1969.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
(c) Net Material Product should be adjusted for "net output" of personal&#13;
transport and non-material communications.&#13;
(d) Adjustments in (b) should reduce the consumption of institutions&#13;
providing services.&#13;
(e) Gross output of personal transport should be included in personal&#13;
consumption.&#13;
(f) Output of non-material communications should be split into three&#13;
parts and added to:&#13;
-    private consumption&#13;
-    consumption of institutions providing services&#13;
-    collective consumption of standard MPS (CMEA) aggregates.&#13;
Derivation of Czechoslovak GDP Based on Available Data&#13;
Even if we limit ourselves to the transformation of global indicators&#13;
only, the search for necessary data still poses a serious problem. The task&#13;
given according to the agreed outline of the country studies is, however, far&#13;
more ambitious. In addition to the global indicator of GDP derived from NMP,,&#13;
also the structural components within this aggregate:&#13;
(a) by sectors of origin,&#13;
(b) by primary incomes (by distributive shares),&#13;
(c) by final use,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
are to be computed. This multiplies the difficulties to obtain, from offi-&#13;
cially published Czechoslovak statistical materials, the necessary data./5 In&#13;
many cases estimates had to be used--as can be seen from detailed notes to the&#13;
individual transformation tables--either because a certain statistical&#13;
information was available only for a limited number of years and for the other&#13;
years of the time series own extrapolations and estimations had to be made, or&#13;
the necessary data were missing altogether and certain proxies had to be used,&#13;
taking the benchmark data used by the Czechoslovak researchers (Bratislava,&#13;
1972) for 1970 as far as possible as a point of departure. Because of the&#13;
lacking data and the use of estimates, the deviations in our estimates of the&#13;
GDP in current prices very likely oscillate within a range of plus/minus 3 to&#13;
4% (of the actual GDP) if computed with precise statistical information.&#13;
Adjustment of Czechoslovak NMP to the CMEA Methodology&#13;
One of the aims of the World Bank Project is to make the National&#13;
Accounts aggregates of the CPEs mutually comparable. For that reason national&#13;
peculiarities have to be eliminated and the original data presented in the&#13;
standard MPS (CMEA) form. In the case of Czechoslovakia this means primarily&#13;
to include personal transport and non-material communications into the NMP&#13;
aggregate.&#13;
Net output of non-material communications is easily obtained from&#13;
statistical yearbooks. It is equal to the published value of net output of&#13;
material communications which itself in Czechoslovak statistical practice is&#13;
estimated as 50% of net output of total communications (both material and non-&#13;
5/ The Czechoslovak authorities did not respond to the World Bank request to&#13;
cooperate in the effort of deriving GDP/GNP data according to the SNA&#13;
concept.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
material)./6 A more complicated procedure is necessary to estimate the net&#13;
output of personal transport. In Czechoslovakia output of material transport&#13;
is computed on the basis of data on incomes of transport enterprises (from&#13;
transportation of material goods, see SNTL/ALFA, 1969). We used a similar&#13;
approach for estimating the net output of personal transport. From published&#13;
data on the performance of different types of personal transport the total&#13;
value of net output in personal transport was estimated and inserted in Table&#13;
1 (Appendix B). As the costs of personal transport are greater than incomes&#13;
(personal transport in Czechoslovakia is heavily subsidized) the resulting&#13;
aggregate - Net Material Product according to the standard MPS methodology -&#13;
is lower than that published in Czechoslovak statistics./7 The relative&#13;
difference between the two versions of Net Material Product is almost constant&#13;
during the whole period.&#13;
DEVELOPMENT OF CZECHOSLOVAK AND CMEA VERSIONS OF NMP&#13;
(mil. Kcs., current prices)&#13;
Average rate&#13;
of growth&#13;
1970         1975          1980        1970-1980&#13;
NMP (CSSR)              312.345      409.970      480.107&#13;
in %                   100.00       131.26        153.71           4.4&#13;
NMP (CMEA)              307.835      404.322      474.980&#13;
in %                   100.00       131.34       154.30            4.3&#13;
Ratio of CSSR/CMEA&#13;
NMP versions (in %)     101.47       101.40       101.08&#13;
/6 J. Kaspar, J. Jilek, M. Matejka, V. Roubicek: Economical Statistics (in&#13;
Czech). SNTL/ALFA, Prague 1969, p. 110.&#13;
/7 This is also the finding of Bratislava (1972) for 1970 and R. Wintrova,&#13;
The Balance of National Economy: The Tool for Analyzing the Process of&#13;
Reproduction in Czechoslovakia (in Czech). Academia, Prague 1979, p. 96.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
The more detailed results of the adjustment of the Czechoslovak version of NMP&#13;
to the standard CMEA MPS concept are presented in Table 1 (Appendix B).&#13;
Derivation of GDP from Data on NMP According to Primary Incomes&#13;
The division of the NMP according to primary incomes (which is a&#13;
point of departure for the transformation) distinguishes the so-called fund of&#13;
individual distribution (primary incomes of population) and the fund of socie-&#13;
tal (collective) distribution (primary income of enterprises), both limited to&#13;
the material sphere only. In the aggregate of primary incomes of the popula-&#13;
tion not only wages and salaries generated in the material sphere, but also&#13;
the money incomes and incomes in kind of cooperative farmers from cooperative&#13;
activity and the private incomes of the population (from different heteroge-&#13;
neous activities within the material sphere) are included. The category of&#13;
private incomes according to the Czechoslovak methodology includes the net&#13;
incomes from private plots of cooperative farmers, the net incomes of private&#13;
peasants (40,000 persons in 1980), and the net incomes of a small number of&#13;
persons working as self-employed in the material sphere. On the other hand,&#13;
in the SNA methodology, the following types of primary incomes can be&#13;
distinguished: compensation of employees; operating surplus including&#13;
indirect taxes; and consumption of fixed capital.&#13;
In the transformation procedure, the incomes of cooperative farmers&#13;
from cooperative activity are treated in the same way as wages and salaries of&#13;
othe&amp;r workers in the material sphere, while, according to the SNA, private&#13;
incomes (including those from private plots of cooperative farmers) are&#13;
shifted from the primary incomes of the population to the primary income of&#13;
enterprises (operating surplus). This procedure takes into account the&#13;
ambivalent role of cooperative farmers with respect to their social&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
standing. In their cooperative activity they play essentially the same role&#13;
as any other wage earner in the material sphere. They get a monthly&#13;
remuneration and participate in the enterprise results of the cooperative only&#13;
by end of the year premia. But this type of remuneration is also applied in&#13;
state-owned enterprises. From private plots, on the other hand, the&#13;
cooperative farmers receive an income from the sale of agricultural products&#13;
after deduction of the production costs.&#13;
Further in the course of transformation procedure, private incomes&#13;
originating from the non-material sphere have to be added to NMP.    This figure.&#13;
is not directly available and our estimate is based on the benchmark informa-&#13;
tion from Bratislava (1972). An alternative way of assessment (based on the&#13;
aggregate money incomes and outlays of the population data) would lead to&#13;
somewhat higher results: for 1980 about 3 bill.Kcs higher than our estimate&#13;
found on line 3 of Table 2 (App. B). On the other hand, travel expenses of&#13;
employees in the material sphere, treated in the MPS concept as a part of&#13;
primary incomes of the population, should be deducted according to the SNA&#13;
methodology as here they form part of intermediate consumption of&#13;
enterprises. There was no possibility of estimating this item from available&#13;
statistical material. It is likely that the above-mentioned possible&#13;
underestimation of private incomes originating from the non-material sphere is&#13;
compensated by omitting the deduction of the travel expenses. Further, losses&#13;
on stocks have been estimated as a difference of total losses and losses on&#13;
fixed capital stock, both available from published statistical data. All&#13;
other steps of the transformation procedure are sufficiently explained in the&#13;
notes to Table 2 in Appendex B. The GDP derived from data according to&#13;
primary incomes increases over time in relation to the NMP (CMEA version) from&#13;
about 117% in 1970 to 120% in 1980.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
DEVELOPMENT OF GDP DERIVED FROM DATA ON PRIMARY INCOMES&#13;
(mil. Kcs, current prices)&#13;
Average rate&#13;
1970        1975         1980       of growth&#13;
1970-1980&#13;
GDP                     360.894     476.944     569.604&#13;
in %                  100.00      132.16      157.83          4.7&#13;
NMP (CMEA)              307.835     404.322     474.980&#13;
in %                 100.00       131.34      154.30          4.4&#13;
Ratio of GDP&#13;
to NMP (CMEA)             1.172       1.180       1.199&#13;
As to the structure of GDP by primary incomes, under labour incomes&#13;
(according to SNA diction: compensation of employees) the following items were&#13;
summarized: the primary incomes according to the NMP concept (compensations&#13;
of wage and salary earners in the material sphere and earnings of cooperative&#13;
farmers from cooperative activity) minus private incomes in the material&#13;
sphere plus compensations of wage and salary earners in the non-material&#13;
sphere plus the employers' contributions to social security in both material&#13;
and non-material spheres. The non-labour incomes (operating surplus including&#13;
net indirect taxes) are calculated as the difference between GDP and the&#13;
labour incomes plus depreciation in the material and non-material spheres.&#13;
The distribution according to labour and non-labour incomes and depreciation&#13;
remains fairly constant during the observed time period 1970-1980 (Tables 3&#13;
and 4 in Appendix B).&#13;
For comparative purposes the structure of the Net Material Product&#13;
(according to MPS) by primary incomes is also given (Tables 5 and 6). As the&#13;
NMP aggregate is net of depreciations, labour and non-labour incomes only are&#13;
distinguished. In this aggregate the proportion of non-labour incomes is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
increasing over time: a development to be expected since employment in the&#13;
non-material sphere is increasing faster than that in the material sphere and&#13;
the costs of the faster growth of the non-material sphere have to be covered&#13;
from the non-labour incomes generated in the material sphere. The faster&#13;
growth of the non-material sphere results also in the slightly greater average&#13;
annual rate of growth of GDP than NMP (4.7 vs 4.4% p.a. in 1970-1980).&#13;
Derivation of GDP from Data on NMP According to Data on Final Use&#13;
The aggregate of the NMP is composed of the final (material) consump-&#13;
tion of the population, other final (material) consumption, net fixed capital&#13;
formation and capital formation in stocks. After an adjustment for losses on&#13;
fixed capital and stocks and for the foreign trade surplus or deficit we&#13;
obtain the NMP produced as given in Table 1, Appendix B (after further adjust-&#13;
ments for personal transport and non-material communications). In the trans-&#13;
formation procedure we have firstly to add purchases of nonmaterial services&#13;
by households. This item has to be estimated as explained in notes 2-5 of&#13;
Table 7 in Appendix B, because the published statistical materials do not&#13;
distinguish household expenditures on services by the nature of services&#13;
purchased (material and non-material).&#13;
A second adjustment item, and one of the most troublesome, are the&#13;
expenditures on housing. As in the other CPE countries, so also in&#13;
Czechoslovakia, housing is heavily subsidized by the state and the rents paid&#13;
by the population do not cover the operating costs and depreciation of&#13;
housing. An additional difficulty in obtaining the necessary data on housing&#13;
arises from the fact that the only available data source (the published table&#13;
on money incomes and outlays of the population) gives no separate data on&#13;
housing but treats it together with communal services. Nor do direct data&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
exist for estimating the imputed rent for owner-dwellers. By adding household&#13;
expenditures on dwelling and communal services (combined) to the NMP under No.&#13;
6 of Table 7 a certain overestimation of the household expenditures on non-&#13;
material services takes place, as only a part of the communal services has&#13;
non-material character. On the other hand, no item for the imputed rent was&#13;
taken into account./8&#13;
We assume that the over- and under-estimation cancel each other&#13;
out. Moreover, under the methodology used there is no room for increasing the&#13;
household expenditures on housing by the value of the housing subsidies. In&#13;
addition to these purely technical reasons it is also conceptually debatable&#13;
whether it is correct to increase the relative price of one expenditure item&#13;
in the national accounts (as for instance the Alton group is doing) but to&#13;
leave other relative prices (e.g. for public transport, but also for the&#13;
overpriced durables and many other manufactured goods) unchanged.&#13;
/8 There are more approaches in assessing the value of imputed rents. One&#13;
may, for instance, take the data on privately owned houses (data from the&#13;
population census - see SY 1981/93) - in 1980 there were 2441 th. of&#13;
dwellings in private houses in Czechoslovakia - and assume the same&#13;
average rent as that charged in state-owned houses: 1695 Kcs in 1980 (SY&#13;
1981/553). An assumption about identical average rents in private and&#13;
public houses would be justified if the quality of both types of houses&#13;
were approximately the same. Such an assumption may hold if one takes into&#13;
account that the lower quality of some of the private houses in rural&#13;
areas is compensated by the higher standard of private houses in towns&#13;
(owned largely by upper strata in the society). This procedure would lead&#13;
to an estimate of the value of imputed rents amounting to 4137.5 mil. Kcs&#13;
in 1980 (approx. 0.7 % of GDP). Another possibility is to take the share&#13;
of the value of private houses in the value of the total housing stock&#13;
(amounting to 31 % in 1975 - see Academia, 1979 p.83) and estimate the&#13;
imputed rents proportionally to the costs of state owned dwellings (9.614&#13;
mil. Kcs in 1980 - see SY 1981/553). This procedure leads to a somewhat&#13;
lower estimate for the value of imputed rents: 2.980 mil. Kcs in 1980&#13;
(0.5 % of GDP).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
The next item to be deducted from NMP are the material costs in&#13;
business travel expenditures. Also on this item no data exist in the&#13;
published statistical materials. We used an estimate suggested in Bratislava,&#13;
1972 (see note 7 to Table 7).&#13;
The lines 8 and 9 in Table 7 from Appendix B, comprise the material&#13;
costs of institutions from the non-material sphere which have to be deducted&#13;
as they are already included in the collective consumption of the NMP.&#13;
The other costs of services provided by budgetary institutions (to be&#13;
added after deduction of incomes from these services) had to be estimated&#13;
because the published material again lacks this information. The procedure&#13;
used was to take the total budgetary expenditures from the consolidated state&#13;
and national committee budgets, to deduct from this item the budgetary&#13;
expenditures for productive purposes, deduct the transfers from the state&#13;
budget to the budget of national committees (to avoid double counting), and&#13;
lastly, to deduct the own incomes of the budgetary institutions providing&#13;
services.&#13;
The other items are sufficiently explained in the notes. As to the&#13;
omission of the external balance arising from exports and imports of non-&#13;
material services, one can assume that the figure - especially in the later&#13;
ye rs - may have been a negative one, because of the net outflow of the&#13;
payments for licences and royalties and for servicing the external debt./9&#13;
The only figure available (for 1970) amounted to excess of imports over&#13;
exports by 780 mill.Kcs (Bratislava, 1972).&#13;
/9 F.L. Altmann, Wachstumspause oder Krise. Tschechoslowakei 1981/82.&#13;
Working Paper 85, March 1982, Osteuropa-Institut Mtlnchen, p. 26.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
The GDP calculated from data on final use is greater by 17 % than the&#13;
NMP in 1970 and its share is steadily increasing over time. For 1980, the&#13;
estimate of the GDP, (derived mainly from provisional data) seems to be biased&#13;
upwards. The GDP exceeds the NMP by almost 24 %; it may be that the figures&#13;
for 1980 will have to be adjusted if definite statistical information would be&#13;
available.&#13;
Tables 8 and 9 in Appendix B, give the structure of the GDP by final&#13;
use. Notes 1 and 2 to the Table 8 explain the computations leading to the&#13;
sub-aggregates of residential households' consumption expenditures and&#13;
government final consumption expenditures. Paragraphs 3 and 4 of the notes&#13;
explain how we arrived at the gross capital formation and at the balance of&#13;
exports minus imports. Also in this table the balance of external transac-&#13;
tions in non-material services had to be omitted owing to the lack of data.&#13;
As to the structure of the GDP by final use, the share of final consumption&#13;
expenditures of government is increasing over time from 14 to 17%, the share&#13;
of gross capital formation is increasing in the first half of the seventies&#13;
from 34 to 36% and declining with decelerating economic development in the&#13;
second half of the 1970s, reaching 32% in 1980. The share of consumption&#13;
expenditures by residential households is fairly constant during the period&#13;
with the exception of the years 1977 and 1978. The sudden increase of this&#13;
share in these two years is connected with the reform of producer prices (see&#13;
further discussion on pricing).&#13;
For comparative purposes the structure of the NMP by final use is&#13;
given as well (Tables 10 and 11, Appendix B). The tendencies of development&#13;
are the same as described for the GDP above. It should, however, be pointed&#13;
out that according to the MPS methodology the NMP used domestically has a dif-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
ferent value and meaning in comparison with the NMP produced, as the latter&#13;
aggregate has to be adjusted for losses and for the balance of merchandise&#13;
trade. Up to 1975 and again in 1979 and 1980 the NMP used was smaller than&#13;
the NMP produced owing to these adjustments.&#13;
GDP Derived from Data on Gross Material Output and NMP by Origin&#13;
Only rough approximations are possible for the computation using this&#13;
method because the most essential statistical information - the gross output&#13;
of on-budgetary enterprises providing services - is missing (Table 12,&#13;
Appendix B). Also, the data on costs of services provided by budgetary&#13;
organizations are not directly available. In Table 12 similar procedure as in&#13;
Table 7 is used for assessing the gross output of non-material services in&#13;
both budgetary and non-budgetary institutions from the consolidated state and&#13;
national committees' budget expenditures (see Notes 2 and 3 to Table 12). The&#13;
material consumption in the non-material sphere (Note 4) has to be deducted&#13;
likewise as the payments for nonmaterial services, as they are already&#13;
included in the gross output of the non-material services. For the other&#13;
entries see the remaining notes./10&#13;
Tables 13 and 14 in Appendix B give the structure of the Gross&#13;
Product divided into intermediate consumption and GDP. The notes explain the&#13;
procedure of computation sufficiently. The structure reveals a steady growth&#13;
of the share of intermediate consumption till 1977. In the last years the&#13;
share of intermediate consumption is slightly declining. For illustration,&#13;
/10 The costs of private dwellings, which are to be deducted from the NMP&#13;
have been omitted. According to the computations made by the Czecho-&#13;
slovak researchers (Bratislava, 1972), these costs amounted to Kcs 880&#13;
mill. or less then 0.25 % of GDP in 1970.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
the analogous structure according to the MPS concept (of the Gross Material&#13;
Output) is given in Tables 15 and 16. The tendencies between shares of&#13;
productive consumption and NMP in GMO are similar as in the case of SNA&#13;
aggregates.&#13;
Comparison with Alternative GDP Estimates in National Currency&#13;
In Table 17 from Appendix B, the three different GDP estimates&#13;
(according to primary incomes, final use and activity by origin) are compared&#13;
and it is suggested to use an average of the three estimates for the&#13;
conversions to US$. It may be interesting to compare our result with other&#13;
available estimates of Czechoslovak GDP computed by Western scholars:&#13;
COMPARISON OF VARIOUS GDP ESTIMATES&#13;
(1977, mil. Kcs)&#13;
GDP as x of NMP&#13;
Type of GDP                                CSSR concept        CMEA concept&#13;
estimate                GDP                  of NMP              of NMP/a&#13;
Alton/b                565.937                  136.4                138.4&#13;
Krejci I/c             530.429                  127.7                129.6&#13;
Krejci II/c            525.656                  126.7                128.6&#13;
Our average&#13;
estimate/d             486.719                  117.3                119.0&#13;
/a Our estimate of NMP.&#13;
/; T. Alton et al., Eastern Europe: Domestic Final Uses of Gross Product&#13;
Selected Years 1965, 1970 and 1975-1980. OP-66, 1981, p. 26.&#13;
/c J. Krejci, National Income and Outlay in Czechoslovakia, Poland and&#13;
Yugoslavia. The Macmillan Press Ltd., 1982, p. 90 (unfortunately&#13;
this source became available to us only after our computations were&#13;
completed).&#13;
/d See Table 17 in Appendix B.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
As can be seen from the above table, the Alton's estimate of GDP for&#13;
1977 in current prices is more than 36% higher than the officially reported&#13;
NMP. The two alternative estimates of Krejci are higher by 26.7 % and 27.7%&#13;
respectively. According to our estimate the GDP exceeds the volume of NMP by&#13;
17.3% only. If the Czechoslovak NMP is recalculated according to the CMEA&#13;
standard, the distance of estimated GDP from NMP becomes even wider, approach-&#13;
ing in the case of Alton's estimate almost 40%. Taking into account that the&#13;
non-material services in Czechoslovakia--perhaps with the exception of health&#13;
and education--are notoriously underdeveloped, the share of the non-material&#13;
services according to Alton and perhaps even according to Krejci seems to be&#13;
high when compared with Western industrialized countries. If we compare the&#13;
ratios of GDP to NMP for Czechoslovakia with that given for Hungary in&#13;
1976,/11 we obtain an index of 119.2 which is practically identical with our&#13;
result. It may be interesting to note that the GDP of Austria (1974) is 28 %&#13;
higher than a computed NMP aggregate (Studies in Methods, Series F. No. 20,&#13;
Part II, 1981). R. Wintrova even claims that the value of Czechoslovak GDP&#13;
according to the SNA concept would be only 11% larger than the NMP (Academia,&#13;
1979).&#13;
The GDP aggregates of Krejci are probably higher because some double-&#13;
counting is likely within the assessment of capital formation. The probable&#13;
upper bias of the Alton GDP estimate is due mainly to his imputations of value&#13;
/11 Comparisons of the System of National Accounts and the System of Balances&#13;
of the National Economy: Conversion of Aggregates of SNA to MPS and vice&#13;
versa for Selected Countries. Studies in Methods, Series F, No.20 (Part&#13;
II), U.N., New York, 1981.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
of dwellings and returns to land. On the other hand, his aggregate at so-&#13;
called adjusted factor costs does not take into account the turnover tax&#13;
(amounting to 71 bill. of Kcs in 1977 - see SY 1981/159) and the amount of&#13;
subsidies. Thojugh no accurate estimate of the value of subsidies is&#13;
available, there seems to be no doubt that the yield of the turnover tax is&#13;
higher than the amount of subsidies. It follows that the GDP aggregate at&#13;
factor costs (Alton) ought to be lower than the one at market prices (our&#13;
estimate).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
II. PRICE FORMATION USED IN CZECHOSLOVAK MPS AGGREGATES&#13;
The prices in the Czechoslovak national accounts are a mixture of&#13;
market prices and producer prices. The two systems of prices developed rela-&#13;
tively independently of each other not only with regard to the change in price&#13;
levels, but also to the relative changes of prices within each system.&#13;
Producer Prices&#13;
The producer prices are formed by the costs of production and a&#13;
certain amount of profit. Up to 1967 the producer prices were determined on a&#13;
cost-plus basis (taking as a basis for the rate of profit total unit costs&#13;
calculated on the branch or product-group level). In 1967 a price reform of&#13;
producer prices was carried out, introducing the so-called two-channel type of&#13;
prices. Profit was calculated separately in fixed proportions to wages and to&#13;
the value of fixed capital and stocks. In 1977, a new reform of producer&#13;
prices was adopted and the basically applied production price model included a&#13;
profit rate which was charged proportionally to the value of fixed capital and&#13;
stocks. In both cases, that means in the 1967 and 1977 price reforms, the&#13;
overall producer price level was also affected. In 1967 the rate of profit&#13;
was considerably increased while in 1977 the rate of profit was lowered, but&#13;
the overall level of producer prices was lowered to a lesser degree. These&#13;
across-the-board price reforms interrupted the "normal" development of current&#13;
prlces. e.g., a comparison of the NMP and GDP estimates for 1977 with those&#13;
for 1976, both at current prices (see Table 17, Appendix B) should not be&#13;
Interpreted to mean that the level of economic activity in 1977 was lower than&#13;
the year before. When comparing the NMP data for 1976 at current prices with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
DEVELROEMB AND SRDUUhRE OF SaECtED 021MENI     OF aIUr IN     aSO      ( IW-DT     ) ORCANI7ATION&#13;
(KcS. xilU., current producer prices)&#13;
Cam*nsation           Profit before&#13;
(lutput           Vterial Costs          Depreciation         of employees               taxes              Residual/a&#13;
1970       1980       1970      1980        1970      1980        1970      1980       1970       1980       1970       1980&#13;
All organizations    698,920   1,196,349    320,274   564,045      28,071    56,646     127,624    186,641    125,447   131,492      97,504    257,525&#13;
100.0)      100.0       45.82     47.15        4.02      4.73       18.26      15.60     17.95      10.99      13.95       21.53&#13;
of which:&#13;
in Matertal sphere   680,731   1,124,168    316,207   555,023      26,175    51,866     121,348    174,760    125,027   113,348     91,974     229,171.&#13;
Z             100.00      100.00      46.45     49.37        3.84      4.61       23.44      15.55      24.15     10.oR       13.51      2n.39&#13;
of %ich:&#13;
IrdLustry        446,671     734,983    240,815   420,441      15,881    30,523      61,942     90,400     79,142    74,262     48,891     119,397&#13;
Z             100.00      100.00      53.91     57.20        3.56      4.16       13.87      12.30      17.72     10.10       1r).95     16.24&#13;
Agriclture        62,050     109,754     24,929    47,651       3,227     6,349      18,433     25,006      9,484     8,098       5,982     22,560&#13;
Z             100.00      100.00      40.18     43.42        5.20       5.87      29.71      22.78      15.28      7.34        9.f64     20.56&#13;
in nomaterial&#13;
sphere              18,189      72,181      4,067     9,022       1,896     4,780       6,276     11,881       420     18,144      5,530      28,354&#13;
%             100.00      100.00      22.36     12.50       10.42      6.62       34.50      16.46       2.31     25.14       30.40      39.28&#13;
La  Ehergy,  anyents for nonm terial services, taxes (excludirg turnover tax) and other financial costs, etc.&#13;
Source:  SY 1981/163-166, SY 1971/184 and awn calculations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
the same data valued at 1977 official constant prices, a price difference of&#13;
minus 4.2% appears which is due precisely to the new valuation of producers'&#13;
prices (see SY 1981/142). Some insight into the structure of producer prices&#13;
may provide the table for Khozraschot (state and cooperative) organizations.12&#13;
Retail Trade (Consumer) Prices&#13;
The retail trade prices, applied to consumption goods in the national&#13;
balances, are not tied to production costs but are determined by a mix of&#13;
social preferences and by the demand and supply situation on the market. The&#13;
difference between the producer price (charged by enterprises) and the retail&#13;
price (paid by the population for consumer goods) is made up of the trade&#13;
mark-up and the turnover tax, the rate of which varies greatly, not only by&#13;
commodity groups but also within each commodity group. In some cases (as in&#13;
public transport and housing, but also with some cultural goods and services)&#13;
price subsidies make up the difference between the price charged to the&#13;
private consumers and the higher producer price.&#13;
It must be noted that the turnover tax is levied on population&#13;
purchases of consumption goods only, while intermediate products, investment&#13;
goods and changes in stock as well as purchases of consumer goods by "social-&#13;
ist" organizations are priced mainly at producer prices. Producer prices are&#13;
those charged by production enterprises in industry, procurement prices of&#13;
agricultural products, prices of construction works, transport rates a.s.o.&#13;
All these prices have in common that, unlike with consumer goods, no turnover&#13;
/12 Khozraschot (non-budgetary) organizations have their own financial&#13;
accounting and are linked to the state budget by profits or losses only.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
tax is levied on them. This applies also to foreign trade prices (actual&#13;
transaction prices converted into national currency from rouble and dollar&#13;
values at internal conversion rates); here, however, the prices are formed on&#13;
the external market, outside the control of the planning authorities.&#13;
In the national accounts the turnover tax is always accounted for by&#13;
the branch in which the taxed commodities are produced, notwithstanding the&#13;
fact that the turnover tax is levied on the retail level and paid by the&#13;
consumer in the act of purchase from a trade organization. As in fact the&#13;
bulk of consumer goods is produced by industry - perhaps with the exception of&#13;
fresh fruits and vegetables - the turnover tax is apportioned in the national&#13;
accounts, overwhelmingly to industry, giving to this branch a higher propor-&#13;
tion when priced at final realization prices (including turnover tax) than if&#13;
the aggregates would be priced at producer prices. The following table shows&#13;
the branch structure of the NMP in 1967 at various valuations (see Academia,&#13;
1979, p.106). However, in the course of attempted economic reforms, the&#13;
amount of turnover tax was lowered and the difference between producer and&#13;
market prices diminished somewhat.&#13;
Thus, for instance, the turnover tax yielded to 50.1 bill. Kcs in&#13;
1970 and 85.5 bill. Kcs in 1980 while subsidies (granted to Khozraschot&#13;
organizations only) amounted to 29.2 bill. Kcs in 1980 (data on subsidies for&#13;
1970 not available) - see SY 1981/159, 162. However, this leaves out the&#13;
amount of subsidies in budgetary organizations (e.g. in personal transport)&#13;
where subsidies are higher. No comparable data exist for the amount of&#13;
turnover tax and subsidies by branches. The turnover tax amounted presumably&#13;
to 80% of the difference between producer and market prices in industry until&#13;
the price reform of 1967. After an increase of the profit rate in 1967 the&#13;
share of the turnover tax dropped to 44% only (see Academia, 1979, p. 104).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
STRUCTURE OF CZECHOSLOVAK NMP BY BRANCHES IN 1967 (%)*&#13;
(Various Types of Prices)&#13;
Final       Wholesale     Value        Cost     Production&#13;
Branch               realization   trade (pro-   prices/a    prices/b    prices/c&#13;
prices        ducer)&#13;
prices&#13;
Industry              61.6            53.6        46.7         56.6        49.8&#13;
Construction          11.2            13.2        11.0          9.3         7.6&#13;
Agriculture&#13;
and Forestry          11.2            13.5        25.4         20.9        19.9&#13;
Material Communi-&#13;
cation and Trans-&#13;
port                   7.0           9.1           8.9          7.0        16.3&#13;
Other                  9.0          10.6           8.0          6.2         6.4&#13;
Total                100.0         100.0         100.0        100.0       100.0&#13;
/a Value prices:  model prices with profits distributed proportionally to labor&#13;
costs.&#13;
/b Cost prices: model prices with profits distributed proportionally to unit costs.&#13;
/c Production prices: model prices with profits distributed proportionally to fixed&#13;
assets and inventories.&#13;
* See Academia (1979), p. 106.&#13;
Globally, the yield from the turnover tax exceeded the amount of subsidies&#13;
granted to Khozraschot organizations by 61.5 bill. Kcs in 1980 or by about 5 %&#13;
of output of these organizations expressed at producer prices (see SY&#13;
1981/162-164; the data for budgetary organizations are not available). In&#13;
assessing the difference between the level of producer and market (retail)&#13;
prices one may compare the data on personal consumption taken from national&#13;
accounts statistics (at market prices) with those from input-output tables (at&#13;
producer prices). In 1977, the personal consumption at market prices amounted&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
to 229.7 bill. Kcs (SY 1980/132) but valued at producer prices it amounted to&#13;
182.6 bill. Kcs. only (SY 1980/131). The level of retail prices thus exceeded&#13;
that of producer prices by 25.8% (in 1973 it was by 23.1% - see SY 1976/151-&#13;
152; the input-output tables are available for 1973 and 1977 only) made up by&#13;
the mark up of the trade organizations and the turnover tax.&#13;
The "final realization prices" of the national accounts are formed by&#13;
a mix of:&#13;
(a) market prices (retail prices for consumer goods, with the exception&#13;
of public consumption and consumption in kind),&#13;
(b) producer prices (for capital formation and changes of stocks),&#13;
(c) foreign trade prices.&#13;
From the structure of NMP follows that its greater part is expressed in market&#13;
prices (see Table 9, Appendix B).&#13;
Foreign Trade Prices&#13;
The Statistical Yearbook is very vague about the prices used for the&#13;
export and import figures in the national accounts. It only explains that&#13;
"foreign trade prices used in the actual settlements" are used, but it is&#13;
nowhere indicated that the data in the foreign trade part of the Statistical&#13;
Yearbooks are expressed in different foreign trade prices (at official&#13;
exchange rates of either Western currencies or transferable rouble). On the&#13;
other hand, the foreign trade data used in the National Income part of the&#13;
Statistical Yearbooks are expressed in domestic currency by using the official&#13;
exchange rate adjusted by the special internal conversion coefficients which&#13;
are not published and are considered to be classified information. The&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
foreign trade statistics published in different parts of the yearbook are thus&#13;
not comparable./13&#13;
There is also no explanation that the concept of imports and exports&#13;
used in the national account statistics differs from the concept used in the&#13;
foreign trade statistics. The national accounts use an enlarged concept which&#13;
includes, in addition to merchandise trade, also the value of freight trans-&#13;
port, communications and middlemen trade. It is a somewhat crude concept of&#13;
the current account but as the MPS concept excludes the non-productive sphere,&#13;
the export and import figures do not include incomes and outlays vis-a-vis the&#13;
outside world derived from interest, royalties, transfer payments and tourist&#13;
trade (i.e. the trade in the non-material services).&#13;
As to the character of the foreign trade prices converted to the&#13;
national currency at internal conversion coefficients, one can roughly compare&#13;
them with the average level of producer prices. The coefficients have been&#13;
fixed originally at the level of the so-called re-production costs expressing&#13;
the number of units of national currency necessary to earn one dollar or one&#13;
rouble respectively in exports. The procedure was to value the bundle of&#13;
commodities exported to the West in dollars and those exported to the CMEA in&#13;
transferable roubles and to compare the sum with approximately the same basket&#13;
valued in domestic producer prices. This system can be compared with the&#13;
multiple exchange rate system, where subsidies are granted for some commodi-&#13;
ties (if the price achieved in foreign trade would be too low) to guarantee to&#13;
the production enterprise the producer price valid in the domestic economy&#13;
/13 Moreover, since 1975 foreign trade transactions at domestic prices are&#13;
not entered any more separately for imports and exports, but only the net&#13;
balance is given.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
while a system of additional charges payable to the government is introduced&#13;
for the other commodities (where the use of the conversion coefficient could&#13;
lead to windfall gains). But, on average, all production enterprises were&#13;
supposed to achieve from exports (converted at the internal conversion&#13;
coefficient into domestic currency) the "average" producer price.&#13;
The different valuation of the national accounts aggregates at a mix&#13;
of producer prices, retail prices and foreign trade prices affects naturally&#13;
not only the structure of the NMP but its rate of growth as well (see&#13;
Academia, 1979, p. 107).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
III. CONVERSION FROM KCS TO US DOLLARS&#13;
Six different conversion coefficients can be used:&#13;
(1) the official exchange rate;&#13;
(2) a purchasing power parity computation elaborated by the Statistical&#13;
Office of the Federal Republic of Germany (Wiesbaden);&#13;
(3) our purchasing power parity estimate (computed by P. Havlik);&#13;
(4) the tourist exchange rate applied officially to Western visitors of&#13;
Czechoslovakia;&#13;
(5) a conversion factor derived from comparing imports and exports in&#13;
domestic currency and foreign trade Kcs (J. Krejci, 1982).&#13;
(6) the so-called realistic exchange rate between US$, rouble and Kcs/14&#13;
In the case of the first PPP (Wiesbaden), the second PPP (Havlik) as&#13;
well as in the case of tourist exchange rate the exchange relations expressed&#13;
in DM and AS were converted to US $ using the official exchange rates between&#13;
US dollar and DM or AS (see Table 19). The results expressed as the quanti-&#13;
ties of Kcs per 1 US$ are given in Table 19 from Appendix B. The different&#13;
conversion factors vary between 4.273 Kcs per 1 US $ to 21.067 Kcs per 1 US$&#13;
in 1980.&#13;
The official exchange rate has no real economic meaning but it is&#13;
used in the official Czechoslovak foreign trade statistics. Formally, it is&#13;
based on the collection of laws on the monetary reform Nr. 41/1953. Till the&#13;
early seventies the official exchange rate was kept unchanged, but later on it&#13;
was frequently adjusted, taking into account the devaluation of the US&#13;
/14 J. Vanous, The Real Facts About Czechoslovak Foreign Trade. The ACEs&#13;
Bulletin, Vol. XXIV, No. 1, Spring 1982.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
dollar.  Since all foreign commercial transaction with the West are settled in&#13;
foreign currencies and the values expressed in foreign currencies are&#13;
converted to foreign exchange Kcs using the official exchange rates, one can&#13;
vice versa reconvert the export (import) values expressed in foreign exchange&#13;
Kcs into US $ by using the official exchange rate. Thus the official exchange&#13;
rate can be safely used to get dollar-values of imports and exports to non-&#13;
socialist countries officially reported in the Czechoslovak statistical&#13;
yearbooks in their Foreign Trade Part.   The implicit unit prices derived by&#13;
using this exchange rate have, however, no connection with actual domestic&#13;
prices applied in the whole economy. To link the domestic price level more&#13;
J&amp;f!alistically to prices achieved on the foreign markets or to prices charged&#13;
t by foreign suppliers the internal conversion coefficients reflecting the value&#13;
of US dollar and transferable rouble were introduced at the end of the sixties&#13;
(see the Government degree number 189/1966). The internal coefficients were&#13;
fixed at 27.0 Kcs per 1 US $ and to 18 Kcs per 1 TR-Rouble. The relation in TR//:(-47&#13;
respect to the US dollar was almost 4 times higher than the official exchange&#13;
rate (Kcs 7.20 per 1 US $). The same coefficient was two and a quarter times&#13;
higher than the official exchange rate of Kcs and the Soviet Rouble (8.00 Kcs&#13;
per 1 Soviet Rouble). Since the time of its first introduction the internal&#13;
conversion coefficients were no longer officially reported and they are today&#13;
considered classified information. However, it is known that they remained&#13;
unchanged till the end of 1976 and new internal conversion coefficients were&#13;
established from the beginning of 1977. Apparently these coefficients too&#13;
were kept stable till 1980, not taking into account the violent fluctuations&#13;
of exchange rates between the currencies of the market economies. For the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
years 1981 and 1982 new coefficients were fixed;/15 their level was, however,&#13;
not reported.&#13;
The exchange rate listed in Table 19 at line 9 (Appendix B) is in&#13;
essence the average of the internal conversion coefficients with respect to&#13;
the US$ and the transferable Rouble. Used as weights are the different shares&#13;
of the trade (with the rouble-area and the non-rouble area) and the exchange&#13;
rate is computed as the weighted average:&#13;
Exchange rates                  Internal conversion     Share of the&#13;
with:                              coefficient          foreign trade&#13;
(Kcs)          (approximately)&#13;
Non-rouble area                        27                    0.33&#13;
Rouble area                            18                    0.66&#13;
Total                                  20.8                  1.00&#13;
The exchange rates applicable for foreign trade (lines 9 and 10 in&#13;
Table 19) undervaluate, in our opinion, the real exchange relations in com-&#13;
parison with realistic exchange rates, as only the commodities traded in&#13;
international trade are here taken into account and not all goods and services&#13;
produced and domestically used. The point has been argued at length by&#13;
Marer./16 According to our judgement a realistic exchange-rate should lie&#13;
somewhere between our calculated purchasing power parity (line 7) and the&#13;
/15 E. Hlavaty, The control of the foreign exchange economy in Czechoslovakia&#13;
(in Slovak). Alfa, Bratislava, 1982, p. 84.&#13;
/16 P. Marer, Background paper prepared for the 1st workshop.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
tourist exchange rate (line 8). The GDP per capita figures in US$ converted&#13;
with the alternative exchange rates are given in Table 20, Appendix B. The&#13;
use of various exchange rates also affects the nominal growth rate of the GDP&#13;
in current prices as well as the real growth rate of GDP in constant Kcs (see&#13;
Table 21, Appendix B).&#13;
A volume of GDP per capita of about 4,500 US$ (resp. 3,500 US$ if an&#13;
adjustment for Czechoslovak inflation is considered) in 1980 seems to be a&#13;
realistic assessment.&#13;
After completing the study and assessing its results one finding of&#13;
great importance for future possible research must be stressed: while the&#13;
various GDP estimates at national currency oscillate within a range 487-566&#13;
bil. Kcs in 1977, the GDP per capita estimates in U.S. dollars fluctuate from&#13;
1580 to 5737 U.S. dollars in the same year. The relative difference in GDP&#13;
estimates at national currency is thus 16.2% while the relative difference of&#13;
GDP estimates expressed in U.S. dollars amounts to 263.1%! This large&#13;
fluctuation of dollar estimates is due to the great variations in possible&#13;
exchange rates.&#13;
It seems to us that future research should be focused either on more&#13;
plausible ways of assessing the real purchasing power of CPEs national&#13;
currencies or into some other method requiring no exchange rate conversions in&#13;
an estimation procedure (i.e. PIG, etc) since the use pf a particular exchange&#13;
rate has a decisive effect on the estimate of the dollar value of the GDP.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
IV. ASSESSMENT OF THE REAL GROWTH OF THE CZECHOSLOVAK ECONOMY&#13;
IN 1970-1980&#13;
The Czechoslovak statistical office measures the growth of the NMP by&#13;
using constant prices fixed to certain base years. In the time period observed&#13;
constant prices fixed to the year 1967 were used till 1976, and from 1977 up&#13;
to 1980 prices of 1977 are being applied. The two price levels are supposedly&#13;
linked by chaining of the respective price indixes (see SY 1981/134). The&#13;
Czechoslovak economists and statisticians are themselves aware of the fact&#13;
that the price indices deflate the indicators only to a limited extent./17&#13;
Just to illustrate this feature the following table presents selected value,&#13;
volume and price indexes taken directly or calculated from data in different&#13;
parts of the Czechoslovak Statistical Yearbook 1981. The paradoxical result--&#13;
namely the growth rate of NMP at official constant prices is faster than the&#13;
growth rate computed from data at current prices, in spite of the fact that&#13;
some inflation is officially admitted-was achieved mainly by a simple statis-&#13;
tical procedure: together with the change of price levels in 1976 a branch&#13;
classification reform was performed. The effects of actual price changes thus&#13;
cannot be traced at all from official statistical sources.&#13;
The reasons for the upward bias in aggregates given at official&#13;
constant prices in the centrally planned economies are well known and a more&#13;
detailed discussion is not possible within the frame of this study. According&#13;
to Academia (1979) the probability of an upward bias not reflected in the&#13;
offical price indices is greater for the non-standard production, especially&#13;
/17 See Academia (1979), p. 103 and V. Nachtigal, The National Income of&#13;
Czechoslovakia (in Czech). Research Report 59, EU-CSAV, Prague, 1969,&#13;
p.92.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
SELECTED VOLUME, VALUE AND PRICE INDICES,&#13;
1970-1980&#13;
Average rate&#13;
1970       1975          1976            1980        of growth&#13;
1970-1980&#13;
NMP at official&#13;
constant prices&#13;
(mil. Kcs)/a          280.807     370.800   384.357   394.076   453.123&#13;
(1967    (1977&#13;
prices)   prices)&#13;
Official growth&#13;
of NMP (%) at&#13;
constant prices/b     100.0       132.0          137.5          158.1            4.7&#13;
NMP at current&#13;
prices (mil. Kcs)/c   312.345     408.399        418.182        480.107&#13;
NMP value indices/d   100.0       130.8          133.9          153.7/*           4.4&#13;
Official index of&#13;
producer prices&#13;
in industry/e         100.0        99.7           99.9          107.5            0.7&#13;
Official index of&#13;
retail prices/f       100.0       100.7          101.6          111.8            1.1&#13;
Procurement prices&#13;
of agricultural&#13;
products/g            100.0       103.7          105.7          119.4            1.8&#13;
/a SY 1981/142&#13;
/1 SY 1981/143&#13;
/c SY 1981/138&#13;
/d own calculation based on 3)&#13;
/e SY 1981/256&#13;
/I SY 1981/257&#13;
SY 1981/257&#13;
*)   The value index is to a small extent influenced by the price reform of 1977.&#13;
Taking this factors into account the value index for 1980 would be 157.6 and the&#13;
rate of growth for 1970-1980 4.7%.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
in case of construction and investment goods. But the probability of price&#13;
increases not sufficiently reflected in the price index is high also with&#13;
consumer prices, even if to a lesser extent. From such an assessment it can&#13;
be deduced that the construction of an index of realistic price increases in&#13;
the field of consumption and application of this index to all the sub-&#13;
aggregates of the GDP would give us a lower boundary of the probable overall&#13;
real price development. One approach to assess the actual price development&#13;
(at least for consumption) is to compare the purchasing power parity between&#13;
Czechoslovakia and some Western market economy (Austria) at two different&#13;
points of time under the assumption that, in the Western country, the price&#13;
development is correctly reflected in the official consumer price index. This&#13;
procedure was used in order to estimate the actual Czechoslovak development of&#13;
consumer prices for the period from 1970 to 1980./18 For 1964 the purchasing&#13;
power parity is based on the results of a Czechoslovak study. As can be seen&#13;
from the table, the PPP of 1 AS equals 0.5232 Kcs in 1980 while in 1964 it&#13;
amounted to 0.70 Kcs./19&#13;
The individual price indexes for 1980 were calculated on the basis of&#13;
roughly 130 items at prices taken from official statistics of both countries;&#13;
in the case of CSSR some quality adjustments were taken into account (analo-&#13;
/18 The comparison of purchasing power parities between Czechoslovakia and&#13;
Austria in 1980 is the topic of a separate study of one of the co-authors&#13;
(Mr. Havlik) of this report. See P. Havlik, A Comparison of Purchasing&#13;
Power Parity and Consumption Level in Austria and Czechoslovakia.&#13;
Research report No. 87, May 1983, Vienna Institute for Comparative&#13;
Economic Studies.&#13;
/19 Comparable Analysis of Living Standards in Czechoslovakia, West Germany&#13;
and Austria (in Czech). Research Report No. 37. EU-CSAV, Prague, 1967,&#13;
p. 32.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
gous to those made in the original Czechoslovak study/19 estimating the PPP&#13;
for 1964).&#13;
The resulting PPP in 1980 is thus comparable with PPP calculated for&#13;
1964 (1 AS = 0.70 Kcs). Both PPP's were used for estimating the actual growth&#13;
of consumer prices in CSSR (officially reported consumer price index 80/64 was&#13;
124.7% - see SY 1981/257, 1972/486). Knowing the Austrian inflation in the&#13;
period (227.14%) we estimate actual inflation (consumer price index in CSSR)&#13;
through the relative change of PPPs:&#13;
I   = I .     1980 = 2.2714 0-52 = 1.69&#13;
cs    appp                 0.70&#13;
The estimated consumer price index 1980/1964 for CSSR is thus 169% (about 3.3%&#13;
per year) instead of the officially reported 124.7% (1.4% per year).&#13;
Assuming the constant degree of bias in the official reporting of&#13;
Czechoslovak price indexes (during the whole period 1964-1980) we assigned&#13;
47.9% of the total estimated price increment to the period 1970-1980 (offi-&#13;
cially reported price increment in 1970-1980 is 11.85%, i.e. 47.9% of the&#13;
total reported price increment in period 1964-1980 - see SY 1972/486,&#13;
1981/257).&#13;
For the period .1980/1970 we obtain the estimated consumer price&#13;
index: 1.33 (47.9% of the total estimated price increment in 1964-1980).&#13;
Since the value index of our average estimate of GDP 1980/1970 is 1.58 (Table&#13;
17) we get, for the estimated real growth of GDP: 1.58/1.33 = 1.19 for the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
period 1970-1980./20 Decomposing this global growth rate to the individual&#13;
years (proportionaly to the official growth rates of NMP) we obtain our&#13;
estimates of real growth as given in line 3 of Table 18 (Appendix B). In&#13;
PURCHASING POWER PARITIES BETWEEN CSSR AND AUSTRIA&#13;
(In 1980)&#13;
Part of            Partial PPPs/a&#13;
consumer basket       calculated   with:           Weights/b          Fisher's&#13;
CSSR      Austrian        CSSR     Austrian      index&#13;
1 Kcs = x AS         weights     weights     Kcs(mil)        AS      1 Kcs=x AS&#13;
Food &amp; beverages       1.3732     1.7175      119655       2715.70      1.5357&#13;
(1 AS = x Kcs)       (0.7282)    (0.5823)    (39.4 %)     (26.5 %)     (0.6512)&#13;
Industrial consumer&#13;
goods                  1.2158     1.1915      135470       4975.80      1.2036&#13;
(1 AS = x Kcs)       (0.8225)    (0.8393)    (44.6 %)      (48.5 %)    (0.8308)&#13;
Services               6.8838     6.9802       48446       2561.96      6.9318&#13;
(1 AS = x Kcs)        (0.1453)   (0.1433)    (16.0 %)     (25.0 %)     (0.1443)&#13;
Total                  2.1824     1.6743      303571      10253.46      1.9116&#13;
(1 AS = x Kcs)        (0.4582)   (0.5973)   (100.0 %)    (100.0 %)     (0.5232)&#13;
/a   For detailed calculations and sensitivity analysis see P. Havlik, A Com-&#13;
parison of Purchasing Power Parity and Consumption Level in Austria and&#13;
Czechoslovakia. Research Report No. 87, May 1983, Vienna Institute for&#13;
Comparative Economic Studies.&#13;
/b   Czechoslovak weights: retail trade turnover (food &amp; beverages and&#13;
industrial consumer goods), money expenditures of the population in 1980&#13;
(services) - see Czechoslovak Statistical Yearbook (SY) 1981, pp. 502-&#13;
503, 525.&#13;
Austrian weights: households' monthly expenditures - survey of 6674&#13;
households from 1974 - see Austrian SY 1980, p. 326-327.&#13;
/20 It is interesting to note that the officially reported volume index on&#13;
NMP produced is also 1.58 - see p. 33.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
essence, we deflated the annual official growth rates by our estimate of an&#13;
assumed constant rate of bias (1.029)./21 Further calculations are explained&#13;
in notes to Table 18 from Appendix B.&#13;
The line 4 in Table 18 gives the volume of GDP in national currency&#13;
at estimated real "constant prices". The real growth of GDP in the period&#13;
1970-1980 was estimated by 19% with an average yearly growth rate of 1.7%. A&#13;
second possibility is to measure the real growth rate based on data on final&#13;
use (lines 5 to 8 in Table 18, Appendix B) giving a slightly lower growth rate&#13;
(1.2% p.a.).&#13;
COMPARISON OF DIFFERENT ALTERNATIVE GROWTH MEASURES&#13;
(Index 1975 = 100)&#13;
1970     1975      1976     1977      1978     1979    1980&#13;
GNP (GDP) produced&#13;
Alton/a              84.8    100.0     101.7    105.8     107.6    108.6    110.4&#13;
Our estimate/b       87.5    100.0     101.2    102.5     103.7    104.0    104.0&#13;
GNP (GDP) used&#13;
Alton/c              83.7     100.0    103.1    105.3     106.0    105.5    106.8&#13;
Our estimate/d       85.8    100.0     100.2     98.9      98.7     97.0     96.4&#13;
/a   GNP at 1977 adjusted factor cost - see OP-70, p. 9.&#13;
71    Calculated from Table 18, line (4), Appendix B.&#13;
Ic   GNP at 1977 adjusted market prices - see OP-72, p. 8.&#13;
7Wd Calculated from Table 18, line (8), Appendix B.&#13;
When comparing the different available alternative growth rates of Czechos-&#13;
lovak GDP (Alton's vs. our estimates) it can be seen that the difference is&#13;
negligible in the first half of the period (1970-75) while in the second half&#13;
/21 Obtained as: official volume index of NMP (1.58) divided by our estimate&#13;
of GDP real growth (1.19) gives the total bias of the real growth 1,33&#13;
for 1970-80. The average annual bias is thus 1.029.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
(1975-80) Alton's growth rates are considerably higher. Thus according to our&#13;
estimate average annual real growth in the second half of the decade amounted&#13;
to 1.0 %, Alton's to 2.0 % for GNP (GDP).&#13;
The differences follow first of all from the various estimation&#13;
procedures used. While our estimates are in essence deflated official "real"&#13;
rates of NMP growth (and therefore do not take into account the slightly&#13;
higher growth rates of the non-material sphere), Alton's estimates are based&#13;
on estimates of growth rates of the various production and service branches&#13;
(aggregating the sectoral indexes into an index of GNP with weights reflecting&#13;
the estimated sectoral contributions in terms of 1977 weights).&#13;
The higher growth rates of Alton thus may result mainly from:&#13;
- higher growth rates of non-material sectors,&#13;
- own estimates of rent and imputed rent from private dwellings,&#13;
- neglecting the increasing losses of personal transport,&#13;
-  use of a different price level.&#13;
It is also possible that our assumption about the constant rate of bias in&#13;
official statistical reporting does not hold and the quality of official price&#13;
indexes improved after 1977. However, the exact source of differences in&#13;
alternative growth rates is very difficult to trace.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
APPENDIX A&#13;
CONVERSION OF MPS DATA TO SNA INDICATORS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
Elements Needed for Conversion of MPS Data to SNA Indicators&#13;
in Transformation Matrices I-IV&#13;
(Description of Rows and Columns of the Transformation Matrices)&#13;
Production&#13;
1.   Products and Services net of depreciation&#13;
2.   Depreciation&#13;
3.   Activities in the material sphere&#13;
Value added&#13;
4.   National Income (Net Material Product)&#13;
5.   Net incomes of private enterprises&#13;
6.   Travel expenses in the material sphere&#13;
7.   Other primary incomes of the population&#13;
8.   Primary incomes of enterprises (profits)&#13;
Redistribution&#13;
9.   Employers' contributions to social security&#13;
10.   Provision of free services for employees&#13;
11.   Material costs of dwelling facilities&#13;
12.   Other transfers&#13;
13.   Non-material services financed from travel expenses&#13;
14.   Other non-material services&#13;
15.   Net incomes of private enterprises&#13;
16.   Travel expenses in the non-material sphere&#13;
17.   Other wages and salaries&#13;
Incomes and Outlays&#13;
18.   Financial assets&#13;
19.   Enterprises in the material sphere&#13;
20.   Institutions financed by the State serving the population&#13;
21.   Dwelling facilities provided by non-material institutions&#13;
22.   Other non-budgetary institutions serving the population&#13;
23.   Budgetary institutions serving collective purposes&#13;
24.   Non-budgetary institutions serving collective purposes&#13;
25.   Inhabitants living in private houses&#13;
26.   Other population&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
Consumption of National Income&#13;
27.   Material products financed from travel expenses&#13;
28.   Material costs of dwelling facilities&#13;
29.   Other private consumption&#13;
30.   Consumption of non-mat. institutions serving the population&#13;
31.   Consumption of non-mat. institutions serving to collective purposes&#13;
32.   Net fixed capital formation&#13;
33.   Non-finished construction&#13;
34.   Accumulation of stocks&#13;
35.   Losses from abandoned construction&#13;
36.   Other losses on fixed capital&#13;
37.   Losses on stocks&#13;
External transactions&#13;
38.   Material products and services&#13;
39.   Direct import and export by population&#13;
40.   Non-material services and other transactions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
M  x                           x     x  x&#13;
K&#13;
v x rx Yx                          i&#13;
K&#13;
x&#13;
t~ y  X  X&#13;
IC~~~~~~~~~~ K&#13;
K~~~~     &#13;
XXXx     XX     XXX      tI&#13;
IC~~~~~~~~~~~t&#13;
x ~ ~ ~ ~~      X&#13;
x        x  x &#13;
IC           XX  K  XX  X X X~~~~~~~~~'I          Iii &#13;
IC~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~e&#13;
K                      I~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~'&#13;
x  K  XSXi&#13;
K      i1&#13;
x~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
XK   X  XX Y   X   KK  I K X  X&#13;
XI xi~ew uoaeuiIoISujiL&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
GDP Based on MPS Data on Primary Incomes&#13;
8&#13;
Net Material Product:        E     n    = n&#13;
i = 5     i,4    4,3&#13;
add wages and salaries in the non-material sphere:&#13;
24&#13;
E    n&#13;
j=20   17,1&#13;
add     private incomes in the non-material sphere:&#13;
n15,22 + nl15,24&#13;
deduct profits of non-budgetary institutions in the non-material sphere:&#13;
22,13    22,14    24,14   9,22    10,22   14,22  n16,22&#13;
n17,22    30,22  9,24  10,24   14,24  16,24  17,24&#13;
n 31,24&#13;
add     employers' contributions to the social security in the nonmaterial&#13;
sphere:&#13;
24&#13;
E n&#13;
j=20 9,j&#13;
deduct travel expenses in enterprises of material sphere:&#13;
n6,4&#13;
deduct payments of productive enterprises for non-material services:&#13;
nl4,19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
add depreciations:&#13;
31&#13;
n    +   E   n&#13;
2,3   j=28   2,j&#13;
deduct costs of provision of free services for employees in productive&#13;
sphere:&#13;
n1O,19&#13;
deduct losses on stocks;&#13;
n37,19&#13;
The result is equal to the GDP according to the SNA concept. It must be&#13;
noticed that some transformation items (n9,22; n9,24; n17,22; n17,24) are&#13;
ommitted in Transformation Matrix II as they vanish during the conversion. In&#13;
practice, as the detailed itemizing of data was often not possible, the actual&#13;
transformation procedures used were somewhat adjusted.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
i x   x                             X  x                ml&#13;
xx x x x x&#13;
xxxxx&#13;
x&#13;
xv x xx x x                        it&#13;
x                                 f&#13;
* x&#13;
XX&#13;
xxIx     Kx     x .       R&#13;
i       x xT&#13;
!~~~~~~~~~~~~ x                                  t7&#13;
!                       x x x x  x x   ~~~~~x  x  x  ztr&#13;
x                nT&#13;
I~~~~~~~~~~~~~ x                     X            t&#13;
x        x  x&#13;
I~~~~~                              ~~           ~~~~~~ I I|  &#13;
x             x          *&#13;
I  ~~~~~~~~XIx                     Y    Y&#13;
I x            ~~~~~~x  x x x x x x                  t&#13;
x a 3x&#13;
i  x x  x                         1:&#13;
x x  xx x x&#13;
!  x'&#13;
I  X X'               X   -X ' XX  X   X                 r&#13;
I~~~~~Eu X3.&#13;
x  x a x x&#13;
I xvt&#13;
x    t&#13;
;  x X S u  t                           w   T~~~~~~~~~~~~~~u &#13;
x x Y x w x A x  v x x xx&#13;
^ ',  ri kt ES  41 CC , "   i, 11 IT  Ir r,  r. El  r aT  Wl 81  t*l  Si " I tl   Iot  TO s t&#13;
IIxTIIeR uojlem-lo;suPell&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
GDP Based on MPS Data on Final Use&#13;
38&#13;
Net Material Product:     E   n    - n    - n     = n&#13;
1=27  1,j    38,1    2,3    4,3&#13;
add households expenditures on non-material services (less expenditures on&#13;
dwelling services)   n14,26 - n2l,14&#13;
add   value of dwelling services provided by&#13;
- institutions in non-material sphere:&#13;
n9,21 + n10,21+ n14,21+ n16,21+ n17,21+ n28,26&#13;
-   owners of private houses:&#13;
n14,25 + n29,25&#13;
deduct material costs in business travel expenses:&#13;
n27, 26( = nl,27)&#13;
deduct material costs of dwelling services provided for the population:&#13;
n29,25 + n28,26&#13;
deduct costs of final consumption in institutions of the non-material&#13;
sphere:&#13;
30,20    30,22   n31,23    n31,24   n29,26&#13;
add     costs of services provided by institutions financed from State Budget&#13;
n9,20 + n10,20 + n14,20 + n16,20 + n17,20 + n30,20 +&#13;
n9,23   n10,23 "14,23 + n16,23 + n17,23 + n31,23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
add depreciations:&#13;
n2,3 + n2,28 +n2,29 +n2,30 + n2,31&#13;
deduct losses on stocks:&#13;
n1,37&#13;
add balance of exports and imports of non-material services:&#13;
nl4,40 - n40,14&#13;
deduct all transfers to the non-material sphere connected with provision&#13;
of free services for employees&#13;
24&#13;
E n&#13;
j=19 10,j&#13;
The result is again equal to the Gross Domestic Product according to the SNA&#13;
concept. When comparing the reconstruction procedure with data needed for&#13;
transformation, it can be seen that some elements (namely n28,26; n29,25;&#13;
n30 20; n31,23) were ommitted in Transformation Matrix III as they again&#13;
vanish during the calculations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
x&#13;
x                 . &#13;
Xx X X XX X                         t&#13;
X                           ST&#13;
X Y YX X X &#13;
X                           tt&#13;
YX XC 'X X X X&#13;
x                                  tT&#13;
x        x&#13;
X        Y   X            CZ&#13;
X~~ fl&#13;
X        X     Y          b&#13;
x  X  X x X   x x X&#13;
x        x x&#13;
x        X                 *t&#13;
X~~~~ X &#13;
|~~~~~~~~~~~ x X* x x x x                             m&#13;
x  xxxt&#13;
x UxUIt&#13;
x X            X  X ~~~~~X  X X5 XT&#13;
X   x&#13;
x  x x x Y E                         o&#13;
'Xx            X  X  XXXX  X &#13;
x                              r&#13;
x&#13;
x~~~ ~ ~ ~ ~                9 &#13;
t&#13;
X  S&#13;
x~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~x*&#13;
X ilK Y x X x x Y X               X x&#13;
r, it it  ir hi  ti T  i . I . :  1i 5 it 3  n VT C   61  rt tt  s 951  Sim CO  li  l  L   I '  7   ; T I os&#13;
III XTlluw uoTILeeaOJSUelL&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
GDP Based on NMP Data by Origin&#13;
8&#13;
Net Material Product:      E n    = n&#13;
i=5  i,4   4,3&#13;
add  costs of services provided by budgetary institutions:&#13;
n9,20 + n16,20 + n17,20 + n30 20 +&#13;
n9,23 + n16,23 + n17,23 + n31,23&#13;
add  costs of dwelling services provided by institutions of the non-material&#13;
sphere&#13;
n9,21 + n16 21 + n17,21 + n28,26&#13;
deduct  material consumption in the non-material sphere (net of depreciation):&#13;
1,28    1,30     1,31&#13;
deduct payments for non-material services in the material sphere:&#13;
n14,19&#13;
deduct payments for non-material services in the non-material sphere:&#13;
n14,22 + 14,24&#13;
deduct material costs in business travel expenditures&#13;
nld27&#13;
add depreciation in the material sphere:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
deduct     payments for non-material services in the material sphere:&#13;
nl14,19&#13;
deduct payments for non-material services in the non-material sphere:&#13;
nl4,22 + 14,24&#13;
deduct material costs in business travel expenditures&#13;
nl,27&#13;
add   depreciation in the material sphere:&#13;
n2,3&#13;
deduct     transfers to the non-material sphere connected with the provision&#13;
of free services for employees:&#13;
n10,19 +n10,22     10,24&#13;
deduct losses on stocks:&#13;
n1,37&#13;
The resulting aggregate is equal to the GDP. The reconstruction procedure&#13;
requires the data on items indicated in Transformation Matrix IV.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
Transformation Matrix Iv&#13;
1   3 L   I  S   I I  i 01  1  z1s  Is 11 tt  lo 14 11 'D   14 :;  J;.   II: ^&gt;   1 }   14 I; IL II'  ] &#13;
4                                         RRXvu)rXyxK3K&#13;
I    X                                    *  * X  wx   x  x xX *&#13;
I  x&#13;
'4U&#13;
S.    X&#13;
C C &#13;
x~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
I     X                                 X&#13;
X, X aX XX&#13;
,.X XX X&#13;
II                               X&#13;
Ii                           IX X XXX    X&#13;
X~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
tt      X     ~   ~~X  X&#13;
11            ~~~~X X   X&#13;
Iii                X         U  XDXX X  X&#13;
3s            X    X        X&#13;
1~~~~~ x X               x&#13;
X X        X&#13;
Lr                ,XY&#13;
b     ~X X X   X X    X X X X&#13;
xxx  X~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
X         '    X    X&#13;
31XXX X                           XX XX&#13;
21                            X&#13;
I.         .                        * x&#13;
IL                            X X X X X X&#13;
II                            X&#13;
Ua                            X X X X X~ X&#13;
3SXX&#13;
E;                    ~~~~~~~X X X X t. X&#13;
1                  X&#13;
No                                                             I&#13;
I.                 X  X     XX&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
Detailed Description of Elementary Flows in Transformation Matrices&#13;
(based on MPS concept)&#13;
Individual non-zero elements in transformation matrices have the fol-&#13;
lowing meaning (element of i-th row and j-th column: i/j):&#13;
1/3       Products and material services (net of depreciation) used for&#13;
production in material sphere&#13;
2/3       Depreciation in material sphere&#13;
1/27-29   Private consumption of products and material services&#13;
2/28      Depreciation from public dwellings&#13;
2/29      Depreciation from private dwellings&#13;
1/30      Products and material services (net of depreciation) consumed by&#13;
institutions providing services to population (in non-material&#13;
sphere)&#13;
2/30      Depreciation of institutions providing services to population (in&#13;
non-material sphere)&#13;
1/31      Products and material services (net of depreciation) consumed by&#13;
institutions serving collective purposes (in non-material sphere)&#13;
2/31      Depreciation of institutions serving collective purposes (in non-&#13;
material sphere)&#13;
1/32      Net fixed capital formation&#13;
1/33      Increment of non-finished construction&#13;
1/34      Increment of stocks&#13;
2/32      Negative value of all depreciations&#13;
1/35      Abandoned construction&#13;
1/36      Other losses on fixed capital&#13;
1/37      Losses on stocks&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
1/38      Exports of material products and services&#13;
3/1       Products and services in material sphere (Global Material Output)&#13;
4/3       Net Material Product&#13;
5/4       Net product of private enterprises in material sphere&#13;
6/4       Travel expenses of employees in material sphere&#13;
7/4       Wages and salaries in material sphere&#13;
8/4       Gross profits of enterprises in material sphere&#13;
9/19      Employers' contributions to the social security in material sphere&#13;
9/20      Employers' contributions to social security in institutions financed&#13;
from State Budget serving population&#13;
9/21      Employers' contributions to social security in institutions&#13;
providing dwelling facilities&#13;
9/22      Employers' contributions to social security in non-budgetary&#13;
institutions serving population (in non-material sphere)&#13;
9/23      Employers' contributions to social security in institutions financed&#13;
from State Budget serving collective purposes (in non-material&#13;
sphere)&#13;
9/24      Employers' contributions to social security in non-budgetary&#13;
institutions serving collective purposes (in non-material sphere)&#13;
10/19     Provision of free services to employees in enterprises of the&#13;
material sphere&#13;
10/20     Provision of free services to employees in institutions financed&#13;
from State Budget providing services for the population (in non-&#13;
material sphere)&#13;
10/21     Provision of free services to employees in institutions providing&#13;
dwelling facilities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54 -&#13;
10/22     Provision of free services to employees in other non-budgetary&#13;
institutions providing services for the population (in non-material&#13;
sphere)&#13;
10/23     Provision of free services for employees in institutions financed&#13;
from State Budget serving collective purposes (in non-material&#13;
sphere)&#13;
10/24     Provision of free services for employees in non-budgetary in-&#13;
stitutions serving collective purposes (in non-material sphere)&#13;
11/21     Imputed transfers. from dwelling facilities (material costs of&#13;
dwelling facilities)&#13;
12/19     Transfers of institutions in material sphere&#13;
12/20     Transfers of institutions financed from State Budget providing&#13;
services for population (in non-material sphere)&#13;
12/21     Other transfers from dwelling facilities&#13;
12/22     Transfers of non-budgetary institutions providing services for the&#13;
population (in non-material sphere)&#13;
12/23     Transfers of institutions financed from State Budget serving&#13;
collective purposes (in non-material sphere)&#13;
12/24     Transfers of non-budgetary institutions serving collective purposes&#13;
(in non-material sphere)&#13;
12/26     Transfers from population&#13;
12/39     Consumption of non-residential households&#13;
12/40     Other transfers from abroad&#13;
14/19     Expenditures of material enterprises on non-material services&#13;
14/20     Expenditures on non-material services of institutions financed from&#13;
State Budget serving the population&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
14/21     Expenditures on non-material services of institutions providing&#13;
dwelling facilities for the population&#13;
14/22     Expenditures on non-material services of non-budgetary institutions&#13;
from non-material sphere serving the population&#13;
14/23     Payments for non-material services of institutions in non-material&#13;
sphere financed from State Budget&#13;
14/24     Payments for non-material services of non-budgetary institutions in&#13;
non-material sphere serving collective purposes&#13;
13/26     Individual payments for non-material services financed from business&#13;
travel expenses&#13;
14/25     Payments of inhabitants living in own houses for non-material&#13;
services&#13;
14/26     Other individual payments&#13;
14/40     Exports of non-material services&#13;
15/22     Net income of private enterprises from the non-productive sphere&#13;
serving the population&#13;
15/24     Net income of private enterprises from the non-productive sphere&#13;
serving collective purposes&#13;
16/20     Travel expenses of institutions financed from State Budget (in the&#13;
non-material sphere) providing services for the population&#13;
16/21     Travel expenses of institutions providing dwelling facilities&#13;
16/22     Travel expenses of non-budgetary institutions (in the non-material&#13;
sphere) providing services for the population&#13;
16/23     Travel expenses of institutions financed from State Budget(in the&#13;
non-material sphere) serving collective purposes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
16/24     Travel expenses of non-budgetary institutions (in non-material&#13;
sphere) serving collective purposes&#13;
7/20     Wages and salaries in institutions financed from State Budget&#13;
providing services for the population&#13;
17/21     Wages and salaries in institutions providing dwelling facilities&#13;
17/22     Wages and salaries in non-budgetary institutions (in non-material&#13;
sphere) providing services for the population&#13;
17/23     Wages and salaries in institutions financed from State Budget&#13;
serving collective purposes&#13;
17/24     Wages and salaries in non-budgetary institutions (in non-material&#13;
sphere) serving collective purposes&#13;
18/19     Current transfers and saldo of debts of material enterprises to the&#13;
government&#13;
18/20     Current transfers from institutions financed from State Budget (in&#13;
non-material sphere) to the government&#13;
18/21     Current transfers from institutions providing dwelling facilities to&#13;
the government&#13;
18/22     Current transfers from non-budgetary institutions (in non-material&#13;
sphere) to the government&#13;
18/23     Current transfers and saldo of debts of institutions financed from&#13;
State Budget (in non-material sphere) serving collective purposes to&#13;
the government&#13;
18/24     Current transfers and saldo of debts of non-budgetary institutions&#13;
(in non-material sphere) serving collective purposes to the&#13;
government&#13;
18/26     Current transfers and saldo of debts of population to the government&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
18/40     Current transfers and saldo of debts from abroad to the government&#13;
19/8      Primary incomes of material enterprises&#13;
19/12     Transfers to material enterprises&#13;
19/18     Transfers to the government and saldo of)credits obtained from&#13;
enterprises in the material sphere&#13;
20/10     Payments to non-material institutions for providing services for&#13;
employees&#13;
20/12     Other transfers to non-material institutions providing services for&#13;
the population&#13;
21/12     Transfers to institutions providing dwelling facilities&#13;
22/12     Transfers to other non-budgetary institutions providing services for&#13;
the population&#13;
21/14     Rents from dwellings&#13;
22/13     Payments for non-material services paid by employees in business&#13;
travel expenses&#13;
22/14     Other payments for non-material services&#13;
20/18     Transfers from government and saldo of credits to institutions&#13;
financed from State Budget (in non-material sphere) providing&#13;
services for the population&#13;
21/18     Transfers from government to institutions providing dwelling&#13;
facilities&#13;
22/18     Transfers from government and saldo of credits to other nonbudgetary&#13;
institutions (in non-material sphere)&#13;
23/9      Employers' contributions to social security paid to institutions&#13;
financed from State Budget (in non-material sphere) serving&#13;
collective purposes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 58 -&#13;
23/12     Other transfers to institutions financed from State Budget (in non-&#13;
material sphere)&#13;
24/12     Other transfers to institutions (in non-material sphere) financed&#13;
from other sources&#13;
24/14     Incomes of non-budgetary institutions (in non-material sphere)&#13;
serving collective purposes from non-material services&#13;
23/18     Transfers from government and saldo of credits to institutions&#13;
financed from State Budget (in non-material sphere) serving&#13;
collective purposes&#13;
24/18     Transfers from government and saldo of credits to non-budgetary&#13;
institutions (in non-material sphere) serving collective purposes&#13;
26/5      Incomes (output) of private enterprises&#13;
26/6      Travel expenses of employees in enterprises of the material sphere&#13;
26/7      Other primary incomes of population (wages and salaries in the&#13;
material sphere)&#13;
25/12     Costs connected with ownership of private dwellings&#13;
26/11     Transfers connected with redistribution of material costs of&#13;
dwellings to private consumption in institutions providing dwelling&#13;
facilities&#13;
26/12     Other transfers to population&#13;
26/15     Net incomes of private enterprises in non-material sphere&#13;
26/16     Travel expenses paid by employees in institutioats of non-material&#13;
sphere&#13;
26/17     Other wages and salaries in non-material sphere&#13;
26/18     Transfers from government and saldo of credits from population&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 59 -&#13;
27/26     Expenditures on material products and services financed from&#13;
business travel expenses&#13;
28/26     Material costs of institutions providing dwelling facilities&#13;
included in private consumption&#13;
29/25     Material products and services needed for private dwelling&#13;
facilities&#13;
29/26     Other expenditures on material products and services included in&#13;
private consumption&#13;
30/20     Consumption of institutions financed from State Budget (in non-&#13;
material sphere) providing services for the population (excluding&#13;
institutions providing dwelling services)&#13;
30/22     Consumption of non-budgetary institutions (in non-material sphere)&#13;
providing services for the population&#13;
31/23     Consumption of institutions financed from State Budget (in non-&#13;
material sphere) serving collective purposes&#13;
31/24     Consumption of non-budgetary institutions (in non-material sphere)&#13;
serving collective purposes&#13;
32/19     Net fixed capital formation in material sphere&#13;
33/19     Non-finished construction in material sphere&#13;
34/19     Net acummulation of stocks&#13;
32/20     Net fixed capital formation in institutions financed from State&#13;
Budget (in non-materi-a-l sphere) providing services for the&#13;
population&#13;
34/20     Net acummulation of stocks in institutions financed from State&#13;
Budget (in non-material sphere) providing services for the&#13;
population&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 60 -&#13;
32/21     Net fixed capital formation in institutions providing dwelling&#13;
facilities&#13;
34/21     Net acummulation of stocks in institutions providing dwelling&#13;
facilities&#13;
32/22     Net fixed capital formation in other institutions (in non-material&#13;
sphere) providing services for the population&#13;
34/22     Net acummulation of stocks in other institutions (in non-material&#13;
sphere) providing services for the population&#13;
32/23     Net fixed capital formation in institution financed from State&#13;
Budget (in non-material sphere) serving collective purposes&#13;
34/23     Net acummulation of stocks in institutions financed from State&#13;
Budget (in non-material sphere) serving collective purposes&#13;
32/24     Net fixed capital formation in non-budgetary institutions (in non-&#13;
material sphere) serving collective purposes&#13;
34/24     Net acummulation of stocks in non-budgetary institutions (in non-&#13;
material sphere) serving collective purposes&#13;
32/25     Net fixed capital formation by owners of private dwellings&#13;
35/19     Losses on abandoned construction in material sphere&#13;
36/19     Other losses on fixed capital in material sphere&#13;
37/19     Losses on stocks in material sphere&#13;
36/20     Losses of institutions financed from State Budget (in non-material&#13;
sphere) providing services for the population&#13;
36/21     Losses of institutions providing dwelling facilities&#13;
36/22     Losses of other non-budgetary institutions (in non-material sphere)&#13;
providing services for the population&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 61 -&#13;
36/23     Losses of institutions financed from State Budget (in non-material&#13;
sphere) serving collective purposes&#13;
36/24     Losses of non-budgetary institutions (in non-material sphe-re)&#13;
serving collective purposes&#13;
38/1      Imports of goods and material services&#13;
39/12     Consumption of residential households abroad&#13;
40/12     Other transfers from population to abroad&#13;
40/14     Imports of non-material services&#13;
40/18     Saldo of foreign debts&#13;
40/38     Saldo of imports minus exports in goods and material services&#13;
40/39     Saldo of residential households' expenditures abroad and non-&#13;
residential households' expenditures at home&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 63 -&#13;
APPENDIX B&#13;
STATISTICAL TABLES WITH CALCULATIONS AND NOTES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 64 -&#13;
Table 1: ADJUSTMENT OF NET MATERIAL PRODUCT OF CZECHOSWVAKIA TO THE&#13;
STANDARD MPS (CMEA) CONCEPT&#13;
(Mil. Kcs)&#13;
1970       1971        1972       1973       1974       1975        1976       1977       1978      1979       1980&#13;
(1)        312.345    327.915     346.333    363.204    390.440    409.970     418.182    414.990    438.015    460.667   480.107&#13;
(2)          1.547       1.676      1.671      1.712      1.901       2.011      2.008      2.193      2.465      3.050     4.125&#13;
(3)          1.712      1.690       1.672      1.737      1.725      1.858       1.679      1.730      1.677      1.693     1.684&#13;
(4)          6.426       6.759      7.093      7.448      8.108       8.483      8.726      9.062      9.436      9.643    10.126&#13;
(5)           .942        .934       .905       .907       .933        .941      1.094      1.090      1.081      1.051     1.041&#13;
(6)           .966       1.045      1.143      1.182      1.340       1.499      1.489      1.379      1.453      1.610     1.670&#13;
(7)           .591        .649       .718       .769       .839        .896      1.014      1.120      1.187      1.241     1.313&#13;
(8)         10.637     11.077      11.531     12.043     12.945     13.677      14.002     14.381     14.834    15.238     15.834&#13;
(9)        -16.694    -17.280     -17.988    -18.787    -20.194    -21.336     -21.843    -22.436    -23.230   -24.215    -25.176&#13;
(10)        -6.057     -6.203      -6.456     -6.744     -7.249     -7.659      -7.841     -8.055     -8.395    -8.977     -9.342&#13;
80&#13;
(11)       307.835    323.388     341.547    358.172    385.092    404.322     412.349    409.128    432.084   454.740    474.968&#13;
Sources and Methods:&#13;
(1)   Net Material Product (NMP) produced (CSSR methodology).    (See SY 1975/162, 1979/130, 1981/138).&#13;
(2)   NMP produced in non-material communications.   Taken to be equal to the NMP produced in material communications (see SY&#13;
1976/152, 1981/138) since, in CSSR methodology, income from material communications is estimated as 50% of incomes from&#13;
communications (both material and non-material). See SNTL/ALFA (1969), p.110.&#13;
(3)   Incomes from personal rail transport.&#13;
(4)   Incomes from bus transport aitside towns.   Estimated via number of persons transported per mil. km and average price of&#13;
1 bus ticket for 10 km - 3 Rcs (see SY 1981/263).&#13;
(5)   Incomes from tramway transport in towns.&#13;
(6)   Incomes from personal airline transport.&#13;
(7)   Incomes from bus transport in towns. All data on personal transport see SY 1974/371-383, 1975/385, 1976/375, 1977/413,&#13;
1979/420-434, 1980/425-446, 1981/420-444.&#13;
(8)   Incomes from personal transport:   (3)+(4)+(5)+(6)+(7).&#13;
(9)   Cts of per         t      rt (see SY 1979/516, 1980/529, 1981/529).   For 1970-76 estimated as well as for 1980.&#13;
(10)  Net income (loss) of personal transport:   (8)+(9).&#13;
(11) NMP produced (CMEA methodology): (1)+(2)+(10).&#13;
| Because of subsidized personal transport, NMP according to the CMEA methodology is lower, in spite of the broader&#13;
concept of material sphere.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 65 -&#13;
Table 2: GDP DERIVED FRCM DATA ON NMP ACCORDING TO PRIMARY INCOMES&#13;
(Mil. Kcs)&#13;
1970       1971       1972        1973       1974       1975       1976        1977       1978      1979      1980&#13;
(1)        307.835    323.388     341.547    358.172    385.092    404.322     412.349    409.128    432.084   454.740    474.890&#13;
(2)         32.240      33.919     36.332     38.644     40.534     42.482      44.730     47.381     49.246     51.305    53.450&#13;
(3)          4.630      4.864       4.723      4.908      4.387      3.910       3.739      3.922      3.836     3.629      4.556&#13;
(4)          -.801      -.155       -.208      -.185      -.099      -.105       -.760       .131       .293     -.823     -1.913&#13;
(5)           .700        .700       .800       .900      1.000      1.100       1.200      1.207      1.278     1.261      1.270&#13;
(6)        -17.673    -18.530     -19.386    -19.975    -21.770    -22.815     -21.148    -18.981    -20.299   -21.185   -22.315&#13;
(7)         26.850     30.477      31.881     33.433     35.585     38.608     40.909      40.393     43.752    46.915    50.221&#13;
(8)         10.468     10.879      11.302     11.741     12.392     13.103     13.799      13.482     14.700    15.805    15.418&#13;
(9)         -1.200     -1.300     -1.476      -1.631     -1.754     -1.965     -2.112      -3.179     -3.367    -3.631    -3.927&#13;
(10)        -5.300     -6.407      -5.791     -5.221     -6.403     -5.936      -5.384     -4.378     -4.457    -4.721    -5.116&#13;
(11)         3.145      3.691       3.845      3.328      4.603      4.239       3.854      2.425      3.014     2.953      3.070&#13;
(12)       360.894    381.526    403.570     424.115    453.567    476.944     491.177    491.530    520.081   546.248    569.604&#13;
(13)         1.172      1.180       1.182      1.184      1.178      1.180       1.191      1.201      1.204     1.201      1.199&#13;
Sources and methods:&#13;
(1)   Net Material Product (CMEA concept) - see Table 1.&#13;
(2)   Wages and salaries in the non-material sphere (SY 1975/485, 1977/506, 1978/511, 1979/514, 1980/526, 1981/526).    Data for&#13;
1970-75 were transformed to the new classification of the NM sphere introduced in 1974. Data for 1980 estimated.&#13;
(3)   Private incomes in the NM sphere.   Data not available:  estimate based on published data on private incomes in the&#13;
material sphere (SY 1975/171, 1981/147) and an assumption of the constant ratio between private incomes in material and&#13;
NM spheres was used (in 1970, the private incomes in the NM sphere were 4663 mil. Rcs - see Rratislava (1972).&#13;
(4)   Profits of non-budgetary organizations in the non-material sphere.   Organizations operating on the "Kchozraschot"&#13;
principle are taken to be non-budgetary organizations. Profits of financial and insurance institutions were excluded&#13;
(SY 1971/184, 1972/184, 1973/170, 1974/181, 1975/186, 1976/173, 1977/151, 1978/150, 1979/157, 1980/158, 1981/166).&#13;
(5)   Employers' contributions to social security in the NM sphere (SY 1979/516, 1980/529, 1981/529).    Data for 1970-76 and&#13;
1980 were estimated.&#13;
(6) Payments of enterprises in the material sphere for non-material services (SY 1971/184, 1972/183, 1973/169, 1974/180,&#13;
1975/185, 1976/172, 1977/151, 1978/150, 1979/157, 1980/158, 1981/166).&#13;
(7)   Depreciation in the material sphere (SY 1975/221, 1981/142).   Transformed to current prices with the official price&#13;
index for inveatments (SY 1975/427, 1981/256).&#13;
(8) Depreciation in the non-material sphere. Data for 1977-1979 (SY 1975/221, 1979/516, 1980/529, 1981/529). Data for&#13;
1970-76 and 1980 (estimated based on the value of fixed capital stock in the NM sphere and analogous rate of&#13;
depreciation as in 1977-79).&#13;
(9)   Provision of free services for employees in enterprises of the material sphere.    Data reported as non-investment&#13;
payments from "funds for social and cultural development" in non-budgetary organizations (SY 1975/184, 1976/171,&#13;
1977/147, 1978/146, 1979/153, 1980/154, 1981/162).&#13;
(10) Total losses (SY 1972/159, 1977/123, 1980/132, 1981/138).&#13;
(11) Losses on fixed capital (SY 1973/142, 1974/159, 1975/164, 1976/154, 1978/125, 1979/132, 1980/134, 1981/139). (10)-(11)&#13;
used as an estimate of losses on stocks which must be deducted from NMP.&#13;
(12) GDP based on data on primary incomes.&#13;
(13) The ratio of GDP to NMP (12):(l).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 66 -&#13;
Table 3: DEVELOPMENT OF GDP BY DISTRIBUTIVE SHARES (SNA)&#13;
(Mil. Kcs and aTmual percentage changes)&#13;
1970       1971       1972        1973       1974       1975       1976       1977       1978       197Q      19R8&#13;
(1)        173.273    182.374    196.723     206.392    215.393    224.351    235.519     242.490    251.744   260.052   268.752&#13;
5.3%       7.9%       4.9%       4.4%        4.2%       5.0%       3.0%       3.8%      3.3%       3.3%&#13;
(2)        150.304    157.796    163.664     172.548    190.197    200.R81    200.949    195.165     209.885   223.476   235.213&#13;
*         5.0%       3.7%       5.4%       10.2%       5.62        .0%      -2.92       7.5%       6.5%      5.3X&#13;
(3)         37.317     41.357     43.183      45.175     47.977     51.712     54.709     53.875      5R.452    62.720    65.639&#13;
*        10.8%       4.4Z       4.6%        6.2%       7.8%       5.8%      -1.5%       8.5%       7.3%      4.7%&#13;
(4)        360.894    381.526     403.570    424.115    453.567    476.944    491.177     491.530    520.081   546.24R   569.604&#13;
*         5.7%       5.8%        5.1%       6.9%       5.2%       3.0%       1%          5.R2      5.0%      4.3%&#13;
Sources and methods:&#13;
(1) Compensation of employees. Obtained as a sum of: primary incomes of population in NMP (SY 1976/160, 1981/147) - private&#13;
incomes in the material sphere (see Table 2) + employers' contributions to social security (see Table 2 for the NM sphere&#13;
and SY 1976/184, 1977/148, 1978/148, 1979/155, 1980/156, 1981/164 for the material sphere).&#13;
(2) Operating surplus and indirect taxes (net). Obtained as a difference between (4) and ((1) + (3)).&#13;
(3) Depreciation (both material and non-material - see Table 2).&#13;
(4) GDP derived from data an primary incomes (by distributive shares) (see Table 2).&#13;
Table 4: STRUCTURE OF GDP BY DISTRIBUTrVE SRARES (SNA)/a&#13;
1970    1971    1972    1973     1974    1975    1976    1977    1978   1979   1980&#13;
(1)      .480     .478    .487    .487    .475    .470    .479    .493    .484   .476    .472&#13;
(2)      .416    .414    .406     .407    .419    .421    .409    .397    .404   .409    .413&#13;
(3)      .103    .108    .107     .107    .106    .10S    .111    .110    .112   .115    .115&#13;
(4)     1.000   1.000   1.000   1.000    1.000   1.000   1.000   1.000   1.000  1.000  1.000&#13;
/a  See Table 3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 67 -&#13;
Table 5:  MVELPMENT OF NET MAiERIAL PRODUCT BY PRDMAFY INC4ES (MPS)&#13;
(Mil. Kcs and annual percentage changes)&#13;
1970     1971     1972     1973     1974     1975     1976     1977     1978     1979     1980&#13;
(1)       135.241  140.999  148.805  155.587  160.473  166.015  171.074  177.726  184.055  189.817  196.304&#13;
4.3%     5.5%     4.6%     3.1%     3.5%     3.0X     3.9%     3.6%     3.1%     3.4%&#13;
(2)       172.594  182.389  192.742  202.585  224.619  238.307  241.275  231.402  248.029  264.923  278.586&#13;
.       5.7%     5.7X     5.1%    10.9%     6.1%     1.2X    -4.1%     7.2%     6.8%     5.2X&#13;
(3)       307.835  323.388  341.547  358.172  385.092  404.322 412.349   409.128  432.084 454.740   474.890&#13;
*       5.1%     5.6%     4.9%     7.5%     5.0%     2.0X     -.8%     5.6%     5.2X     4.4%&#13;
Sources and methods:&#13;
(1)  Primary incomes of population (SY 1976/160, 1981/147).&#13;
(2) Primsry incocs of enterprises adjusted for losses in personal transport (see Table 1).    (Obtained&#13;
as a difference between NMP and primary incomes of population.)&#13;
(3) Net Material Product (see Table 1).&#13;
Table 6: STRDCIURE OF NMP (MPS)/a&#13;
1970     1971     1972     1973     1974     1975     1976     1977     1978     1979     1980&#13;
(1)          .439     .436     .436     .434     .417     .411     .415     .434     .426     .417     .413&#13;
(2)          .561     .564     .564     .566     .583     .589     .585     .566     .574     .583     .587&#13;
(3)         1.000    1.000    1.000    1.000    1.000    1.000    1.000    1.000    1.000    1.000    1.000&#13;
/a See also Table 5.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68 -&#13;
Table 7: GDP BASED ON DATA ON FINAL USE&#13;
(Mil. Kcs)&#13;
1970       1971        1972       1973       1974       1975        1976       1977       1978       1979        1980&#13;
(1)     307.835    323.388     341.547    358.172    385.092     404.322    412.349    409.128    432.084     454.740    474.890&#13;
(2)       3.999      4.092       4.331      4.670      5.026       5.302      5.602      5.733      5.958       6.161      6.338&#13;
(3)       1.171      1.183       1.146      1.115      1.142       1.161      1.093      1.104      1.162       1.162      1.157&#13;
(4)       1.321       1.327      1.431      1.526      1.673       1.792      1.899      1.944      2.102       2.180      2.486&#13;
(5)       1.347      1.444       1.510      1.504      1.582      1.628       1.705      1.826      1.930       1.962      2.036&#13;
(6)       7.259      7.544       8.085      8.654      9.345      10.098     11.322     11.685     12.344      13.542     16.230&#13;
(7)      -3.620     -3.946     -4.112      -4.544     -4.933     -5.091      -5.309     -5.726     -5.820     -5.803      -5.850&#13;
(8)      -4.382     -4.811      -5.087     -5.373     -5.160     -5.462      -5.625     -6.160     -6.432      -6.668     -6.663&#13;
(9)     -40.943    -43.000    -45.700     -47.00O    -48.646    -51.855     -55.897    -58.350    -60.652    -62.826     -65.078&#13;
(10)     194.313    212.632     216.569    237.200    259.185    273.774     290.071    278.301    283.912     292.403    304.182&#13;
(11)     -87.648   -101.755     -97.150   -109.737   -126.872   -133.876    -141.757   -127.847   -126.555   -128.382    -130.515&#13;
(12)     -13.291    -15.217     -16.716    -14.849    -15.595    -14.507     -15.689    -17.492    -12.556    -11.564     -11.801&#13;
(13)     -38.799    -37.582    -46.383     -45.452    -49.486    -52.666     -51.897    -51.817    -55.602    -57.954     -56.098&#13;
(14)      37.317     41.357      43.183     45.175     47.977      51.712     54.709     53.875     58.452      62.720     65.63q&#13;
(15)      -5.300     -6.407      -5.791     -5.221     -6.403     -5.936      -5.384     -4.378     -4.457     -4.721      -5.116&#13;
(16)       3.145      3.691       3.845      3.328      4.603       4.239      3.854      2.425      3.014       2.953      3.070&#13;
(17)      -2.800     -3.000      -3.150     -3.300     -3.660     -4.032      -4.100     -5.317     -5.607     -6.008      -6.327&#13;
(18)     360.925    380.939     397.559    425.869    454.871    480.604     496.946    488.935    523.278     553.897    588.580&#13;
(19)       1.172      1.178       1.164      1.189      1.181       1.189      1.205      1.195      1.211       1.218      1.239&#13;
Sources and methods:&#13;
(1)  Net Material Product (see Table 1).&#13;
(2)  Households' expenditures on personal services (50% taken as non-material).    (SY 1974/463, 1977/505, 1980/525,&#13;
1981/525).&#13;
(3)  Households' expenditures on sport, cultural and entertainment services (SY 1974/463, 1975/484, 1980/525, 1981/525).&#13;
(4)  Households' expenditures on recreational and health services (SY 1974/463, 1975/484, 1980/525, 1981/525).&#13;
(5) Households' expenditures on miscellaneous services (50% taken as non-material). (SY 1974/463, 1975/484, 1980/525,&#13;
1981/525). (2)+(3) + (4)+(5) taken as an estimate of households' expenditures on the non-material services&#13;
(excluding comnmnal services).&#13;
(6)  Households' expenditures on dwelling and communal services (SY 1974/463, 1975/484, 1980/525, 1981/525).&#13;
(7) Material costs in husiness travel expenses.    Data not available:   estimated at 30% of "other incomes" of population&#13;
(SY 1974/463, 1977/148, 1978/510, 1981/525).&#13;
(8)  Material costs of dwelling services provided for the population (SY 1972/183, 1973/169, 1974/180, 1975/185, 1976/172,&#13;
1977/150, 1978/149, 1979/156, 1980/157, 1981/165).&#13;
(9) Material costs in the non-material sphere (SY 1977/506, 1979/514, 1981/526). Data for 1970-73 and 1980 not&#13;
available: extrapolated.&#13;
(10)  Total budgetary (State budget and budgets of National Committees) expenditures.    (SY 1975/178, 1980/148, 1981/156.)&#13;
(11)  "Productive" budgetary expenditures (SY 1975/178, 1980/148, 1981/156).&#13;
(12)  Incomes of institutions financed from State budget (SY 1980/149, 1981/157).&#13;
(13)  Transfers from State budget to National Committees.   (SY 1975/179, 1980/149, 1981/157).   (10)-(11)-(12)-(13) used as&#13;
an estimate of costs of services provided by budgetary institutions less incomes from these services.&#13;
(14) Depreciation in both material and non-material spheres (see Table 2).&#13;
(15)  Total losses (see Table 2).&#13;
(16)  Losses on fixed capital (see Table 2).   (15)-(16) used as an estimate of losses on stocks.&#13;
(17) All transfers to the non-material sphere connected with the provision of free services for employees of enterprlses&#13;
in both material and non-material spheres. (Equals to non-investment payments from "funds for social and cultural&#13;
development". See SY 1977/506, 1978/511, 1981/526 for the non-material sphere and Table 2 for the material sphere.)&#13;
(18)  GDP based on data on final use.&#13;
(19)  The ratio of GDP to NMP:(18):(1).&#13;
Remark: data on exports-imports of non-material services are omitted as we failed to obtain a reasonable estimate.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 69 -&#13;
Table 8: DEVEIOPMENT OF GDP BY FINAL USE CATEGORIES (SMA)&#13;
(Mil. Kcs and annual percentage changes)&#13;
1970       1971        1972       1973       1974       1975       1976        1977       1978       1979       1980&#13;
(1)      182.177    192.914     202.712    216.221    232.681    243.557    250.919     258.156    272.746    284.076    297.285&#13;
*         5.9Z       5.1%       6.7%        7.6%       4.7Z       3.0%       2.9%        5.7%       4.2%       4.6Z&#13;
(2)       51.775     55.078      53.170     63.862     63.572     68.693     76.628      75.828     83.592     88.495     99.441&#13;
*         6.4%      -3.5Z      20.1%       -.5%        8.1%      11.6%      -1.0%      10.2%        5.9%      12.4%&#13;
(3)      121.285    124.724    132.016     142.566    161.797    172.749    178.132     159.639    168.571    176.636    186.704&#13;
*         2.81       5.8Z       8.0%       13.5%       6.8%       3.1%     -10.4%        5.6%       4.8%       5.7%&#13;
(4)        5.687      8.224       9.661      3.220     -3.179     -4.395     -8.732      -4.688     -2.176      3.690       5.212&#13;
44.6%      17.5%     -66.7%     -198.7%     -38.3%     -98.7%     +46.3%     +53.6%     +269.6%      41.2%&#13;
(5)      360.925    380.939     397.559    425.869    454.871    480.604    496.946     488.935    523.278    553.897    588.580&#13;
5.5%       4.4%       7.1%        6.8%       5.7%       3.4%      -1.6%       7.0%        5.9%       6.3%&#13;
Sources and methods:&#13;
(1) Expenditures on the final use of residential households. Obtained as a sum of private consumption (SY 1975/162,&#13;
1977/122, 1981/138 - enlarged for subsidies in personal transport - see Table 1), households' expenditures on&#13;
dwelling and other non-material services (see Table 7), excluding the material costs of dwelling services provided&#13;
for the population (see Table 7), material costs in business travel expenses (see Table 7) and the balance of direct&#13;
households' external transactions (SY 1975/484, 1977/505, 1981/525).&#13;
(2) Final consumption expenditures of government. Estimated by the costs of services provided by budgetary institutions&#13;
less incomes from these services (see Table 7) less transfers to the non-material sphere connected with the provision&#13;
of free services for employees in enterprises of both material and non-material spheres (see Table 7).&#13;
(3) Gross capital formation. Obtained as a sum of net accumulation of fixed capital and changes in stocks (SY 1975/162,&#13;
1977/122, 1981/138), depreciation in both material and non-material spheres (see Table 7) and losses on fixed capital&#13;
(see Table 2).&#13;
(4) Balance of exports minus imports. Obtained as a sum of the balance of merchandize trade (SY 1976/152, 1977/123,&#13;
1980/132, 1981/138) and the balance of direct households' external transactions (SY 1975/484, 1977/505, 1981/525).&#13;
The balance of non-material services' external transactions is omitted.&#13;
(5) Gross Domestic Product (see Table 7).&#13;
Table 9: STRUCTURE OF GDP BY FINAL USE (SNA)/a&#13;
1970       1971        1972       1973       1974       1975       1976        1977       1978       1979       1980&#13;
(1)         .505        .506       .510       .508       .512       .507        .505       .528       .521       .513        .505&#13;
(2)         .143       .145        .134       .150       .140       .143        .154       .155       .160       .160        .169&#13;
(3)         .336        .327       .332       .335       .356       .359        .358       .327       .322       .319        .137&#13;
(4)         .016        .022       .024       .008      -.007      -.009       -.018      -.010      -.004       .007        .009&#13;
(5)        1.000      1.000       1.000      1.000      1.000      1.000       1.000      1.000      1.000      1.000       1.000&#13;
/a See also Table S.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 70 -&#13;
Table 10: DEVEIOPMENT OF NMP ACCXORDING TO DATA ON FINAL USE CAT¶ 0RIES (MPS)&#13;
(Mil. KeS and anrual percentage changes)&#13;
1970       1971       1972        1973       1974       1975       1976        1977       1978       1979       1980&#13;
(1)      174.565    185.960    196.116     209.584    225.126    235.488    241.659     249.294    263.332    273.962    283.515&#13;
*         6.5%       5.5%       6.9%        7.4%       4.6%       2.6%       3.2%        5.6%       4.0%       3.5%&#13;
(2)       40.943     43.000      45.700     47.000     48.646     51.855      55.897     58.350     60.652     62.826     65.078&#13;
*         5.0%       6.3%        2.8%       3.5%       6.6%       7.8%       4.4%        3.9%       3.6%       3.6%&#13;
(3)       80.823     79.676      84.988     94.063    109.217    116.798    119.569     103.339    107.650    111.963    117.933&#13;
*        -1.4%       6.7%      10.7%       16.1%       6.9%       2.4%     -13.6%        4.2%       4.0%       5.3%&#13;
(4)      296.331    308.636     326.804    350.647    382.989    404.141     417.125    410.983    431.634    448.751    466.526&#13;
*         4.2%        5.9%       7.3%       9.2%       5.5%        3.2%      -1.5%       5.0%       4.0%       4.0%&#13;
(5)        5.300      6.407      5.791       5.221      6.403      5.936      5.384       4.378      4.457      4.721      5.116&#13;
20.9%      -9.6%      -9.8%       22.6%      -7.3%      -9.3%     -18.7%       1.8%        5.°%       8.4%&#13;
(6)        6.204      8.345       8.952      2.304     -4.300     -5.755    -10.160      -6.233     -4.007      1.268      3.248&#13;
34.5%       7.3%     -74.3%     -286.6%     -33.8%     -76.5%     +38.7%     +35.7%     +131.6%     156.2%&#13;
(7)      307.835    323.388     341.547    358.172    385.092    404.322     412.349    409.128    432.084    454.740    474.890&#13;
5.1%       5.6%       4.9%        7.5%       5.0%       2.0%       -.8%        5.6%       5.2%       4.4%&#13;
Sources and methods:&#13;
(1)  Private consumption (SY 1975/162, 1977/122, 1981/138, adjusted for subsidized personal transport - see Table 1).&#13;
(2)  Other consumption.  Estimated by the costs of final consumption in the non-material sphere (see Table 7).&#13;
(3)  Accumulation (net of depreciation) of fixed capital and stocks (material).    (SY 1975/162, 1977/122, 1981/138.)&#13;
(4)  Net Material Product used.  Sum of (1)+(2)+(3).&#13;
(5)  Total losses (see Table 2).&#13;
(6)  Balance of exports minus imports (material).   (SY 1976/152, 1977/123, 1980/132, 1981/138.)&#13;
(7)  Net Material Product produced (see Table 1).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 71 -&#13;
Table 11: STICCTURLE OF NET MATERIAL PtODUCT (MPS)/a&#13;
(Il. KCS)&#13;
1970    1971     1972    1973    1974     1975    1976--  1977     1978    1979     1980&#13;
(1)        .567    .575    .574     .585    .585     .582    .586    .609     .609    .602     .597&#13;
(2)        .133    .133     .1'34   .131    .126     .128     .136    .143    .140    .138     .137&#13;
(3)        .263    .246    .249     .263    .284     .289    .290    .253     .249    .246     .248&#13;
(4)        .963    .954    .957     .979    .995    1.000   1.012    1.005    .999     .987    .982&#13;
(5)        .017    .020     .017    .015    .017     .015    .013     .011    .010     .010    .011&#13;
(6)        .020    .026    .026     .006   -.011    -.014   -.025    -.015   -.009     .003    .007&#13;
(7)       1.000   1.000    1.000   19000   1.000    1.000   1.000    1.000   1.000   1.000    1.000&#13;
/a See Table 10.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 72 -&#13;
Table 12: GDP DERIVED FROM DATA ON GROSS MATFRIAL 0UWPUT AND NMP BY ORIGIN&#13;
(Mil. Kcs)&#13;
1970       1971       1972        1973       1q74       1975       1976       1977        197R       1979       1980&#13;
(1)     307.835    323.388     341.547    358.172    385.092    404.322    412.349     409.12R    432.084    454.740    474.P90&#13;
(2)     194.313    212.632     216.569    237.200    259.185    273.774    290.071     278.301    283.912    292.403    304.182&#13;
(3)     -87.648   -101.755    -97.150    -109.737   -126.872   -133.R76   -141.757   -127.847    -126.555   -128.382   -110.515&#13;
(4)     -37.655    -41.043    -44.748     -48.764    -53.153    -57.937    -63.151     -70.278    -72.814    -76.499    -80.371&#13;
(5)     -17.673    -18.530    -19.386     -19.975    -21.770    -22.815    -21.148     -18.981    -20.299    -21.185    -22.315&#13;
(6)     -11.998    -13.401     -14.272    -14.055    -16.263    -16.834    -17.822     -18.027    -18.719    -1Q.639    -20.601&#13;
(7)      -3.620     -3.946     -4.11?      -4.544     -4.933     -5.091     -5.309      -5.726     -5.820     -5.803     -5.8so&#13;
(8)      26.850     30.477      31.881     33.433     35.585     38.608     40.qO9      40.393     43.752     46.915     50.221&#13;
(9)      -2.800     -3.000     -3.150      -3.300     -3.660     -4.032     -4.100      -5.317     -5.607     -6.008     -6.327&#13;
(10)      -5.300     -6.407     -5.791      -5.221     -6.403     -5.936     -5.384      -4.378     -4.457     -4.721     -5.116&#13;
(11)       3.145      3.691      3.845       3.328      4.60i      4.239      3.854       2.425      3.014      2.953      3.070&#13;
(12)     365.449    382.106    405.234     426.538    451.411    474.422    488.513     479.693    50A.491    534.774    561.268&#13;
(13)       1.187      1.182      1.186       1.191      1.172      1.173      1.185       1.172      1.177      1.176      1.182&#13;
Sources and methods:&#13;
(1)  Net Material Product (see Table 1).&#13;
(2) Total budgetary (State budget and budgets of National Committees) expenditures. (SY 1975/178, 1980/148. 1981/156).&#13;
(3) "Productive" budgetary expenditures. (SY 1975/178, 1980/148, 1981/156). (2)-(3) used as an estimate of gross output&#13;
of institutions providing non-aterial services (including dwelling services).&#13;
(4) Material consumption in the non-material sphere (net of depreciation). (SY 1979/516, 1980/529, 1981/529). For 1970-&#13;
76 and 1980 data not available: extrapolated.&#13;
(5)  Payments for non-material services in the material sphere.   (SY 1971/184, 1972/183, 1973/169, 1974/180, 1975/1R5,&#13;
1976/172, 1977/148, 1978/150, 1979/159, 1980/158, 1981/166).&#13;
(6) Payments for non-material services in the non-material sphere. (SY 1976/466, 1977/506, 1978/511, 1980/526,&#13;
1981/526). Data for 1970-73 and 1980 not available: extrapolated.&#13;
(7) Material costs of business travels. Data not available: estimated (see Table 7).&#13;
(8)  Depreciation in the productive sphere (see Table 2).&#13;
(9) Transfers to the non-material sphere connected with the provision of free services for employees (see Table 7).&#13;
(10) Total losses (see Table 2).&#13;
(11) Losses on fixed capital (see Table 2). (10)-(11) used as an estimate of losses on stocks.&#13;
(12) GDP derived from data on Gross Material Output and NMP by origin.&#13;
(13) The ratio of GDP to NMP. (12):(1).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 73 -&#13;
Table 13: DEVELQPMNT OF GROSS PRODLET (SNA)&#13;
(1Xl. Kes and annual percentage changes)&#13;
1970       1971       1972       1973       1974       1975       1976       1977       1978       1979       1980&#13;
(1)      854.403    902.191    957.678  1,012.162  1,079.744  1,146.884  1,192.208  1,236.327  1,300.446  1,347.750' 1,426.084&#13;
*         5.6%       6.22       5.7%       6.7%       6.2%       4.02       3.7%       5.2%       3.6%       5.8%&#13;
(2)      488.954    520.085    552.444    585.624    628.333    672.462    703.695    756.634    791.955    812.976    864.816&#13;
*         6.4%       6.22       6.0C       7.3Z       7.02       4.6%       7.52       4.7%       2.72       6.4%&#13;
(3)      365.449    382.106    405.234    426.538    451.411    474.422    488.513    479.693    508.491    534.774    561.268&#13;
*         4.6%       6.1%       5.3Z       5.8%       5.1%       3.0Z      -1.8%       6.0%       5.%        5.0%&#13;
Sources and methods:&#13;
(1) Gross Product.   Obtained as a sun of Gross Material Output (SY 1975/162, 1981/138, adjusted for personal transpDrt&#13;
and non-osterial cammunications - see Table 1), gross autput of institutions providing the non-material services (see&#13;
Table 12) less trangfe7rs to the non-mterial sphere connected with the provision of free services by enterprises for&#13;
employees (see Table 7).&#13;
(2)  Intermediate consumption (net of depreciation).  Obtained as a difference between Gross Prodict (1) and GDP (see&#13;
Table 12).&#13;
(3) GDP derived fran data on gross output and ?W by origin (see Table 12).&#13;
Table 14: STRUCTURE OF (ROSS RODUCT (SNA)/a&#13;
1970       1971       1972       1973       1974       1975       1976       1977       1978       1979       1980&#13;
(1)        1.000      1.000      1.000      1.000      1.000      1.000      1.000      1.000      1.000      1.000      1.000&#13;
(2)         .572       .576       .577       .579       .582       .586       .590       .612       .609       .603       .606&#13;
(3)         .428       .424       .423       .421       .418       .414       .410       .388       .391       .397       .394&#13;
/a See Table 13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 74 -&#13;
Table 15:  DEVELOPMENT OF GROSS MATERLAL OUTPTIT (MPS)&#13;
TMil. Rcs and annual percentage changes)&#13;
1970       1971       1972        1973       1974       1975       1976        1977       197P       1979       1980&#13;
(1)      750.538    794.314    841.409     887.949    951.091  1,011.018  1,047.994   1,091.190  1,14R.696  1,189.737  1,25R.744&#13;
*         5.8%       5.9%       5.5%        7.1%       6.3%       3.7%       4.1%        5.3%       3.6h       5.R%&#13;
(2)      442.703    470.926    499.861     529.827    565.999.   606.h96    635.645     682.062    716.611    734.497    7P3.R54&#13;
*         6.4%       6.1%        6.0%       6.82.      7.2%       4.82       7.3X        5.1%       2.6%       6.6!&#13;
(3)      307.835    323.388     341.547    358.172    385.092    404.322    412.349     409.128    432.0e4    454.740    474.89n&#13;
*         5.1%       5.6%       4.9%        7.5%       5.0%       2.0%       -.8%        5.6%       5.2%       4.4%&#13;
Sources and methods:&#13;
(1)  Gross Material Output.   (SY 1975/162, 1981/138 and adjustments for non-zaterial comunications and personal transport&#13;
- see Table 1).&#13;
(2)  Productive consumption (material).   Obtained as a difference between Gross Material Output (1) and Net Material&#13;
Product (3).&#13;
(3)  Net Material Product (see Table 1).&#13;
Table 16: STRUCTURE OF GROSS MATERI.AL OUTIPUT (MPS)/a&#13;
1970       1971       1972        1973       1974       1975       1976        1977       1978       1979       1980&#13;
(1)        1.000      1.000      1.000       1.000      1.000      1.000      1.000       1.000      1.000      1.000      1.000&#13;
(2)         .590       .593        .594       .597       .595       .600        .607       .625       .624       .61R       .623&#13;
(3)         .410       .407        .406       .403       .405       .400        .393       .375       .376       .382       .377&#13;
/a  See also Table 15.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 75 -&#13;
Table 17:  SUfMARY RESULTS: NlP AND CDP AT CUQRENT RCS (MIL.) AND ANNUAL PERcENTAIE CIwEU  S&#13;
1970       1971       1972        1973       1974       1975       1976       1977       1978        1979       1980&#13;
(1)      312.345    327.915     346.333    363.204    390.440    409.970    418.182    414.990    438.015     460.667    480.107&#13;
*         5.0%       5.6%       4.9%        7.5%       5.0%       2.0%       -.8%       5.5%        5.2%       4.2%&#13;
(2)      307.835    323.388    341.547     358.172    385.092    404.322    412.349    409.128    432.084     454.740    474.890 '&#13;
*         5.1%       5.6%       4.9%        7.5%       5.0%       2.0%       -.8%       5.6%        5.2%       4.42&#13;
(3)         .986       .986        .986       .986       .986       .986       .986        .986       .986       .987       .989&#13;
(4)      360.894    381.526    403.570     424.115    453.567    476.944    491.177    491.530     520.081    546.248    569.604 -&#13;
5.7%       5.8%       5.1%       6.9%        5.2%       3.0%        .1%       5.8%       5.0%        4.3%&#13;
(5)      360.925    380.939    397.559    425.869     454.871    480.604    496.946    488.935    523.278     553.897    588.5R0 -&#13;
5.5%       4.4%       7.1%       6.8%        5.7%       3.4%      -1.6%       7.0X       5.9%        6.3%&#13;
(6)      365.449    382.106    405.234     426.538    451.411    474.422    488.513    479.693    508.491     534.774    561.268 -&#13;
4.6%       6.1%       5.3%        5.8%       5.1%       3.0%      -1.8%       6.0%        5.2%       5.0%&#13;
(7)      362.423    381.524    402.121     425.507    453.283    477.323    492.212    486.719    517.283     544.973    573.151-'&#13;
5.3%       5.4%       5.8%        6.5%       5.3%       3.1%      -1.1%       6.3%       5.4%        5.2%&#13;
1. J;b     /. &amp;,)     J..S ,17               1./4/      /./n       1- /77     /0173       ).t is     1-/4       /' /511&#13;
(8)        1.177      1.180      1.177       1.188      1.177      1.181      1.194      1.190      1.197       1.198      1.207&#13;
Sources and methods:&#13;
(1)  Net Material Product, CSSR concept (see Table 1).                                        C             a o .S1&#13;
(2)  Net Material Product, CMEA concept (see Table 1).&#13;
(3)  The ratio of (2):(1).&#13;
(4)  GDP based on data on primary incomes (see Table 2).&#13;
(5)  GDP based on data on final use (see Table 7).&#13;
(6)  GDP based on data on Gross Material Output and NMP by origin (see Table 12).&#13;
(7)  "Average" estimate of GDP:   ((4)+(5)+(6))/3.  This estimate is used in conversions to US dollars (see Table 20).&#13;
(8)  The ratio of (7):(2).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 76 -&#13;
Table 18: ESTIMATES OF GDP'S REAL rR(WTH RATES&#13;
1970       1971       1972        1973       1974       1975       1976       1977       1978        1979       1480&#13;
(1).     360.894    381.526     403.570    424.115    453.567    476.944    491.177    491.530     520.n81    546.248    569.604&#13;
5.77       5.8%       5.1%        6.9%       5.27       3.0%        .1%       5.8%       5.0%        4.3%&#13;
(2)        1.000      1.055      1.057       1.052      1.059      1.062      1.041      1.042      1.041       1.031      1.029&#13;
(3)        1.000      1.025       1.027      1.022      1.029      1.032      1.012      1.013       1.012      1.002      1.000&#13;
(4)      360.894    369.916     379.904    388.262    399.521    412.306    417.253    422.67R     427.750    428.605    428.605&#13;
(5)      360.925    380.939    397.559     425.869    454.871    480.604    496.946    488.935     523.278    553.897    588.580&#13;
5.5%       4.4%       7.1%        6.8%       5.7%       3.4%      -1.6%       7.0%        5.9%       6.3%&#13;
(6)        1.000      1.049      1.057       1.073      1.081      1.045      1.031       l.016      1.027      1.011      1.023&#13;
(7)        1.000      1.019      1.027       1.043      1.051      1.016      1.nO2        .9R7       .998       .983        QQ4&#13;
(8)      360.925    367.783     377.713    393.954    414.046    420.671    421.512     416.032    415.200    408.142    405.693&#13;
Sources and methods:&#13;
(1)  GDP based on data on primary incomes, current Kcs (mil). (See Table 2).&#13;
(2)  Official growth rates of Net Material Product (produced).   (SY 1981/143.)&#13;
(3)  Estimated real growth rates.  Our estimate is based on the asumption of an upward bias in the official growth rates;&#13;
the bias being constant and proportional to the official reported growth rate. Thel degree of bias we estimated in&#13;
the following way: we start with comparing the purchasing power parities between Czechoslovakia and Austria in 1964&#13;
(1 Austrian shilling - 0.70 Kcs) and in 1980 (1 Austrian shilling - 0.5232 Kcs) - see table in text. The Austrian&#13;
consumer price index 1980/1964 was 2.2714; officially reported consumer price index in Czechoslovakia was 1.2470 (SY&#13;
1972/486, 1981/257). From the relative change of PPP's and Austrian consumer price index In the period we obtained&#13;
an estimate of "real" Czechoslovak consumer price index for 1964-1980: 1.69. 47.9% of this price increment was&#13;
ascribed to the period 1970-1980 (proportionally to the officially reported consumer price index) giving an estimated&#13;
price index for 1980/70:1.33. The value index of GDP 1980/70 (1.58) was deflated by the estimated price index (1.33)&#13;
and the real growth of GDP is thus: 1.58/1.33 - 1.19 (approximately). This overall real GDP growth rate was&#13;
decomposed to the individual years proportionally to the official growth rates (2).&#13;
(4)  GDP based on data on primary incomes at constant (1970) prices.   (Estimated growth rate indexes (3) applied to the&#13;
value of GDP in 1970).&#13;
(5) GDP based on data on final use (see Table 7).&#13;
(6)  Official growth rates of Net Material Product (used).   (SY 1981/143.)&#13;
(7)  Estimated real growth rates for GDP based on data on final use.   The estimation procedure has the same logic as above&#13;
by (3). We deflated the official growth rates (6) by our estimate of bias (1.029).&#13;
(8)  GDP based on data on final use at constant (1970) prices.   (Estimated growth rates indexes (7) applied to the value&#13;
of GDP in 1970.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 77 -&#13;
Table 19: DIYFERENT EXCHANGE RATES USED FOR CONVERSION OF KCS TO U.S. DOLLARS&#13;
1970       1971        1972       1973       1974        1975       1976        1977       1978       1979        1980&#13;
SJ 8   (1) °11    7.200      7.200      6.610       5.860      5.860      5.580       5.770      5.670      5.430       5.320      5.380&#13;
I 4    (2)       25.830     23.660     23.140      19.850     17.130     18.510      16.770     15.130     13.370      12.430     13.810&#13;
,/Ke3 (3) 7;&gt; 1..605         1.528       1.562      1.522      1.577       1.753      1.808      1.706       1.555      1.465       1.347&#13;
t/'KeS (4) {f0     .287        .304       .323       .343       .367        .386       .401        .411       .415       .417        .426&#13;
4    (5)       3.650       3.480      3.190      2.660       2.590      2.460      2.520       2.320      2.010      1.830       1.820&#13;
i/J2 $  (6) P    12.704     11.462       9.876      7.744      7.063       6.375      6.291       5.645      4.845      4.387       4.273  J&#13;
5   (7) /p'/9..608        8.108      8.129       8.108      8.067      8.027       7.954      7.856      7.723       7.431         24&#13;
(8)      16.092     15.485      14.818     13.041     10.860      10.560      9.274       8.870      8.599      8.403      10.253&#13;
(9)      21.600      22.183     20.915     19.043     19.557      19.125     20.310      20.497     20.160     20.285      21.067&#13;
(10)   - 17.408      12.696      13.616     16.192      20.056     16.744     15.456      16.008     13.376     13.528      13.680&#13;
Sources and methods:&#13;
-~ /(1)      Official exchange rate 1 US$ - xKcs - yearly averages (SY 1981/185).&#13;
(2)  Official exchange rate 1 US$ - xAS (Monthly Bulletin of Statistics).&#13;
(3)  Tourist exchange rate 1 Kcs - xAS (Austrian National Bank).&#13;
(4)  Purchasing Power Parity 1 Kcs - xDM (Internationaler Vergleich der Preise fur    Lebenshaltung 1980, Statistisches&#13;
Bundesamt Wiesbaden, Reihe 10/1981).&#13;
(5)  Official exchange rate 1 US$ - xDM (see (4)).&#13;
(6)  Wiesbaden's PPP 1 USS - xXcs ((5):(4)).&#13;
-   (7)  Our estimate of PPP 1 Kcs - 1.9116 AS in 1980 (see text) converted to US$ with the official exchange rate (2) and&#13;
moved to the previous years with our estimate of Czechoslovak consumer price index (1.33 for 1970) (see text).      The&#13;
estimated consumer price index is proportional to the officially reported index of retail prices (SY 1975/497,&#13;
1981/297); the average coefficient of bias is again 1.029 (see notes to Table 18). The result is thus PPP of one&#13;
1980 US$ in relation to constant (1970) Kcs.&#13;
(8) Tourist exchange rate 1 US$ - xKcs ((2):(3)).&#13;
(9)  Exchange rate based on the estimated difference between domestic and foreign trade Kcs (1 foreign trade Kcs = 3&#13;
domestic Kcs - see J. Krejci, National Income and Outlay in Czechoslovakia, Poland and Yugoslavia. The Macmillan&#13;
Press Ltd., 1982, p. 57 and also K.Dyba. The change of Czechoslovak terms of trade with capitalist countries and the&#13;
saldo of Czechoslovak trade balance in 1967-1974 (in Czech), Finance a uver 10/1976, p.675). This exchange rate is&#13;
thus 3 times the official one (1).&#13;
(10)  Exchange rate 1 US$ - xKcs obtained via the "realistic exchange rate between USS and transferable rouble" (see&#13;
J. Vanous, The Real Facts about Czechoslovak Foreing Trade. The ACES Bulletin, Vol. XXIV, No. 1, Spring 1982 p.l2),&#13;
the official exchange rate between Kcs and Soviet rouble (SY 1981/185) and the multlplicators for the non-commercial&#13;
exchange rates between the transferable and Soviet rouble (see P. Spacek, The Non-commercial payments and exchange&#13;
rates of the CMEA countries (in Czech), SocialistickA economicka integrace 1/1979, p.21).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 78 -&#13;
Table 20: GDP PER CAPITA IN CURRENT PRICES AT DIFFERENT EXCHANGE RATES&#13;
(Current U.S. dollars)&#13;
Average&#13;
annual groowth&#13;
1970    1971     1972    1973     1974    1975    1976     1977    1978     1979    1980    rate (%)&#13;
1970 - 1980&#13;
(1) 5     3.512    3.682   4.206   4.987    5.267   5.779    5.718   5.711    6.293   6.723   6.95R      7.1&#13;
(2) fPtI/)I1.990   2.313   2.815   3.774    4.370   5.059    5.245   5.737   7.054    8.152   8.759     16. l&#13;
(3)l etjk2.788     3.270   3.420   3.604    3.826   4.017    4.148   4.122   4.425    4.813   5.181       6.4&#13;
(4)     1.571     1.712   1.876   2.241    2.842   3.054    3.558   3.651    3.974   4.216   3.651       8.8&#13;
(5)       1.171    1.195   1.329   1.535    1.578   1.686    1.625   1.580    1.695   1.763   1.777       4.2&#13;
(6)       1.452    2.088   2.042   1.805    1.539   1.926    2.135   2.023    2.555   2.644   2.736       6.5&#13;
Sources and methods:&#13;
(1) "Average" estimate of GDP (see Table 17) converted to U.S.$ with the official exchange rate (Table 19).&#13;
(2) "Average" estimate of GDP (see Table 17) converted to U.S.S with Wiesbaden PPP (see Table 19).&#13;
(3) "Average" estimate of GDP (see Table 17) converted to U.S.$ with our estimate of PPP, at 1980 ll.S.S, (see Table&#13;
19).&#13;
(4) "Average" estimate of GDP (see Table 17) converted to U.S.S with tourist exchange rate (see Table 19).&#13;
(5) "Average" estimate of GDP (see Table 17) converted to U.S.S with domestic/foreign Kcs difference exchange rate (see&#13;
Table 19).q&#13;
(6) "Average" estimate of GDP (see Table 17) converted to U.S.S with "realistic" exchange rate between U.S.S - rouble -&#13;
KRs (see Table 19).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-79-&#13;
Table 21: GDP PER CAPITA IN CONSTANT PRICES AT DIFFERENT EXCHANCE RATES&#13;
(Current U.S. dollars)&#13;
Average&#13;
anrmal grcwth&#13;
1970     1971    1972     1973    1974     1975     1976    1977     1978     1979    1980     rate (%)&#13;
1970 - 1980&#13;
(1)       3.497    3.578    3.991   4.581    4.683    5.046   4.908    5.030   5.286    5.381    5.305      4.3&#13;
(2)       1.982    2.248    2.671   3.467    3.885   4.417    4.502    5.052   5.925    6.524    6.679     12.9&#13;
(3)        2.620   3.171    3.231   3.289    3.372    3.470   3.516    3.579    3.659   3.785    3.874      4.0&#13;
(4)       1.565    1.664    1.780   2.058    2.526   2.666    3.054    3.215   3.338    3.374    2.784      5.9&#13;
(5)       1.166    1.161    1.261   1.410    1.403   1.472    1.394    1.391   1.424    1.411    1.355      1.5&#13;
(6)       1.446    2.029    1.937   1.658    1.368   1.682    1.832    1.781   2.146    2.116    2.086      3.7&#13;
Sources and methods:&#13;
(1) GDP in constant (1970) Kcs (see Table 18, line (4)), converted to US$ with the official excharge rate (Table 19).&#13;
(2) GDP in constant (1970) Kcs (see Table 18, line (4)), converted to US$ with Vlesbaden PPP (see Table 19).&#13;
(3) GDP in constant (1970) Kcs (see Table 18, line (4)), converted to US$ with our estimate of PPP, at 1980 US$, (see&#13;
Table 19).&#13;
(4) GDP in constant (1970) Kes (see Table 18, line (4)), converted to US$ with tourist excharge rate (see Table 19).&#13;
(5) GDP in constant (1970) KRs (see Table 18, line (4)), converted to US$ with doistic/foreign Kcs difference exchange&#13;
rate (see Table 19).&#13;
(6) GDP in constant (1970) Kcs (see Table 18, line (4)), coriverted to US$ with "realistic" excharge rate between US $ -&#13;
rouble - Kcs (see Table 19).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG 3881.5 .W57 W67 NO.772&#13;
C.3&#13;
HAVLIK, PETER.               I&#13;
THE GROSS DOMESTIC PRODUCT&#13;
OF CZECHOSLOVAKIA, 1970&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                         European Office              Tokyo Office&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                  66, avenue d'lena            Kokusai Building&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.       75116 Paris, France          1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234            Telephone: (1) 723-54.21     Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK           Telex: 842-620628            Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                          Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0634-0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554689">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/11/1554689/gross-domestic-product-czechoslovakia-1970-1980
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/11/1554689/gross-domestic-product-czechoslovakia-1970-1980</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1985/11/1554689/gross-domestic-product-czechoslovakia-1970-1980</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/16/000178830_98101903433735/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/16/000178830_98101903433735/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1985-11-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-09-23T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The gross domestic product of
            Czechoslovakia, 1970-1980
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The paper considers the theoretical and
            practical problems connected with the estimation Gross
            Domestic Product (GDP) for the centrally planned economy of
            Czechoslovakia. In the methodological part the basic
            differences between the SNA (System of National Accounts)
            and MPS (Material Product System) accounting systems are
            discussed and several transformation procedures are
            presented. The price formation used in Czechoslovak MPS
            aggregates is briefly described before the problem of
            converting the data in national currency to US dollars is
            highlighted. Alternative GDP estimates, exchange rates and
            growth rates are compared. Own estimates, based on the
            purchasing parity type comparison with Austria, are
            presented in comparison with official Czechoslovak indexes.
            The appendices contain the detailed description of MPS/SNA
            transformation procedures as well as the statistical tables
            illustrating the process of GDP reconstruction based on
            Czechoslovak data for the period 1970-1990.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The gross domestic product of
            Czechoslovakia, 1970-1980
        </docna>
        <display_title>The gross domestic product of
            Czechoslovakia, 1970-1980</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1985/11/1554689/gross-domestic-product-czechoslovakia-1970-1980</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,ICT Policy and Strategies,Inequality,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Information Technology</subtopic>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <count>Czech Republic</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Havlik, Peter</author>
            <author>Levcik, Friedrich</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Eastern Europe!$!107233</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe!$!80461</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903433735</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Macro/non-trade</subsc>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 772</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0634-0</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Accounting systems; Centrally planned
            economies; Exchange rates; Gross domestic product; Growth
            rate; Statistical tables
            Abstracts,algorithms,annual rate,average
            annual,Average rate,basic,benchmark,benchmark data,capital
            formation,Centrally planned economies,centrally planned
            economy,communication services,comparative
            analysis,computing,constant prices,consumer
            goods,consumption expenditures,country reports,debt,Economic
            Analysis,Economic conditions,economic development,economic
            structures,Economic Studies,employment,exchange
            rate,exchange rates,expenditures,exports,Foreign
            Trade,Future research,GDP,GDP per capita,global
            economy,GNP,GNP per capita,gross domestic product,Gross
            Domestic Product per Capita,Gross national product,Growth
            Rate,growth rates,imports,income,Income
            Data,incomes,indexes,inflation,international
            comparisons,market economies,member countries,MPS,National
            Income,national peculiarities,net output,official
            estimates,population data,power parity,PPPs,price
            increases,private consumption,production costs,productive
            sphere,public transport,purchasing power,purchasing power
            parities,purchasing power parity,real growth,relative
            prices,statistical data,time series,wages
        </keywd>
        <owner>ECS</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Eastern Europe</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP772</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>GMO</ml:concept><ml:concept>GMOs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Genetically Modified Organisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Price Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rail Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Genetically Modified Organisms (GMOs)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing Subsidies</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Europe</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Czech Republic</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>