<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP-61 2&#13;
Financing State and Local Government in Brazil&#13;
Recent Trends and Issues&#13;
Dennis J. Mahar&#13;
William R. Dillinger&#13;
WOiRLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 612&#13;
HJ&#13;
925&#13;
. M24&#13;
1983&#13;
c.2 &#13;
SLC018237&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 612&#13;
Financing State and Local Government in Brazil&#13;
Recent Trends and Issues&#13;
Dennis J. Mahar&#13;
William R. Dillinger&#13;
p,lJG  I 98I&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright © 1983&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development / THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
First printing September 1983&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To&#13;
present the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has&#13;
not been prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal&#13;
printed texts, and the World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The&#13;
publication is supplied at a token charge to defray part of the cost of&#13;
manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to&#13;
any individual acting on their behalf. Any maps used have been prepared&#13;
solely for the convenience of the readers; the denominations used and the&#13;
boundaries shown do not imply, on the part of the World Bank and its affiliates,&#13;
any judgment on the legal status of any territory or any endorsement or&#13;
acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications is described in the Catalog of World&#13;
Bank Publications; the continuing research program of the Bank is outlined in&#13;
World Bank Research Program: Abstracts of Current Studies. Both booklets are&#13;
updated annually; the most recent edition of each is available without charge&#13;
from the Publications Distribution Unit of the Bank in Washington or from the&#13;
European Office of the Bank, 66, avenue d'Iena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Dennis J. Mahar is a senior economist in the Latin America and Caribbean&#13;
Regional Office and William R. Dillinger an urban economist in the Urban&#13;
Development Department, both at the Wozld Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Mahar, Dennis J.&#13;
Financing state and local government in Brazil.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 612)&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
1. Intergovernmental fiscal relations-Brazil.&#13;
I. Dillinger, WilliLam R., 1951-        .  II. Title.&#13;
III. Series.&#13;
HJ925.M275   1983       336.1'85'0981        83-17074&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0255-8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Page No.&#13;
GLOSSARY OF ACRONYMS                                                     v&#13;
CURRENCY EQUIVALENTS                                                  viii&#13;
MAP                                                          follows text&#13;
I.  INTRODUCTION ............................                          I&#13;
II.  HISTORICAL BACIKGROUND TO 1968 .....................2&#13;
Dual Federa:Lism:  1889-1930 ..........................        2&#13;
Decentralized Unitary Government:     1930-45 ...........      2&#13;
Cooperative Federalism:    1946-64 .....................       3&#13;
The Fiscal Reforms of 1965-67 ........................         4&#13;
III.  CURRENT INSTITUTIONAL FRAMEWORK .........................          5&#13;
Administrative Structure .............................          5&#13;
State and Local Revenue Sources ............6&#13;
State and Local Functional Responsibilities .....13&#13;
IV. CORRESPONDENCE OF REVENUES AND EXPENDITURES:&#13;
THE QUESTION OF VERTICAL BALANCE .....        ................  16&#13;
The "Conventional Wisdom" ..       ............................  16&#13;
Saving and Investment .......................     .........   17&#13;
Deficit Financing ..................................          17&#13;
Principal Causes of the States' Fiscal Problems               19&#13;
Problems of Municipal Resourc-e Mobilization ............     25&#13;
V. SPATIAL VARIATIONS IN REVENUES AND EXPENDITURES:&#13;
THE QUESTION OF HORIZONTAL BALANCE           ....................  29&#13;
Regional Economic Disparities    .......................      29&#13;
Revenues, Expenditures and Public Service Indicators          30&#13;
Sources of Variation in State Revenues .         ........     33&#13;
Sources of Variation in Municipal Revenues                    38&#13;
Revenue Sharing ............................................ .  40&#13;
Regional Distributon of Direct Federal Expenditures ...       43&#13;
VI.  SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS ...........................               45&#13;
Vertical Balance ... .... .. .................................  46&#13;
Horizontal Balance ..   ..   ............................. ...  48&#13;
Final Considerations ........       .   .........    ......   50&#13;
REFERENCES .       .............................................  53&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
LIST OF TABLES&#13;
Table                                                                  Page&#13;
Number                                                                Number&#13;
1        Structure of the Public Sector, 1975 .................        7&#13;
2        State and Municipal Revenues by Source, 1978.......           9&#13;
3        Summary of Principal Revenue-sharing Mechanisms&#13;
(1   1-81........................                           11-&#13;
4        Public Expenditures by Function and Level of&#13;
Government, 1975. ...................... . ...... ....       15&#13;
5        Selected Indicators of State and Municipal&#13;
Finances, 1968-80......... ............. oo*.. ...........   18&#13;
6        Structure of State Debt at Year End, 1977-81 .......         19&#13;
7        Buoyancy of Revenues by Level of Government,&#13;
1968-80**..*... .......................  e .o  .9.....      20&#13;
8        Annual Growth Rates of State Revenues and&#13;
-Expenditures and GDP, 1968/69-1979/80 .............         21&#13;
9        Impact of CIATA on Municipal Revenues, 1976-78.....          27&#13;
10        Hypothetical Impact of Doubled Property Tax Effort&#13;
on Municipal Current Revenues....         ..........         28&#13;
11        State and Municipal Revenues and Public Service&#13;
Indicators by Region, mid-1970s ...............              31&#13;
12        State and Municipal Expenditures on Education&#13;
and Health by Region, 1975 .......................           32&#13;
13        Gross Regional Product and ICM Revenues, 1970 ......         33&#13;
14        Sectoral Composition of ICM Revenues and Taxable&#13;
Gross State Product, 1970-       oo.... ..................   36&#13;
15        Regional Pattern of State Revenue Sources, 1978 ....         37&#13;
16       Municipal Taxes:    Concentration of Base and Yield&#13;
in Large Cities, 1975 ...... .... .... ... ......... ...    38&#13;
17        Regional Pattern of Municipal Revenue Sources,&#13;
1975...............                                         39&#13;
18        Impact of Revenue Sharing on Regional Disparities,&#13;
mid-1970s ................... * ..**O**...... O... ......     41&#13;
19        Non-capital Municlpios:    Average Population and&#13;
Revenues, mid-1970s ........rt  u   .......b.............    42&#13;
20        Federal Direct Expenditures by Region, 1975 ............................45&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
GLOSSARY OF ACRONYMS&#13;
BNH                 Banco Nacional de Habitas,ao&#13;
(National Housing Bank)&#13;
CIATA               Convanios de Incentivos ao Aperfeicoamento&#13;
TLcnico-Administrativo das Municipalidades&#13;
(Agreements on Incentives for the&#13;
Technical-Administrative Improvement of&#13;
Municipalities)&#13;
CIBRAZEM            Companhia Brasileira de Armazenagem&#13;
(Brazilian Storage Company)&#13;
CMN                 Conselho Monetario Nacional&#13;
(National Monetary Council)&#13;
DNAEE               Departamento Nacional de Aguas e Energia Eletrica&#13;
(National Department of Water and Electric Energy)&#13;
DNER                Departamento Nacional de Estradas de Rodagem&#13;
(National Highways Department)&#13;
DNPM                Departamento Nacional de Producao Mineral&#13;
(National Department of Mineral Production)&#13;
ELETROBRAS          Centrais El'etricas Brasileiras S. A.&#13;
(Brazilian Electric Company)&#13;
EMBRATER            Empresa de Assist8ncia Tgcnica e Extensn'o Rural&#13;
(Federal Technical Assistance and Rural Extension&#13;
Company)&#13;
FAS                 Fundo de Assistencia Social&#13;
(Social Development Fund)&#13;
FDTU                Fundo de Desenvolvimento dos Transportes Urbanos&#13;
(Urban Transport Development Fund)&#13;
FE                  Fundo Especial&#13;
(Special Fund)&#13;
FFDF                Fundo Federal do Desenvolvimento Ferroviario&#13;
(Federal Railroad Development Fund)&#13;
FGTS                Fundo de Garantia do Tempo de Servigo&#13;
(Time of Service Guarantee Fund)&#13;
FGV                 Fundacao Getulio Vargas&#13;
(GetAlio Vargas Foundation)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FND                 Fundo Nacional de Desenvolvimento&#13;
(National Development Fund)&#13;
FNDU                Fundo Nacional de Apoio ao Desenvolvimento Urbano&#13;
(National Urban Development Fund)&#13;
FNM                 Fundo Nacional de Minerac,o&#13;
(National Mining Fund)&#13;
FPE                 Fundo de Participaqa1o dos Estados, DF e Territorios&#13;
(States, Federal District and Federal Territories&#13;
Participation Fund)&#13;
FPM                 Fundo de Participa'ao dos Municfpios&#13;
(Municipal Participation Fund)&#13;
FRN                 Fundo Rodoviario Nacional&#13;
(National Road Fund)&#13;
GRP                 Gross Regional Product&#13;
GSP                 Gross State Product&#13;
IBAM                Instituto Brasileiro de Amininistra,cao Municipal&#13;
(Brazilian Institute of Municipal Administration)&#13;
ICM                 Imposto sobre Circulac,ao de Mercadorias&#13;
(Value-added tax)&#13;
INCRA               Instituto Nacional de Coloniza,cao e Reforma Agraria&#13;
(National Institute for Colonization and Agrarian&#13;
Reform)&#13;
IPI                 Imposto sobre Productos Industrializados&#13;
(Manufacturers' sales tax)&#13;
IPTU                Imposto Predial e TerriLorial UrbanO&#13;
(Urban property tax)&#13;
IR                  Imposto sobre a Renda e Proventos de Qualquer Natureza&#13;
(Income tax)&#13;
ISS                 Imposto sobre Servigos&#13;
(Tax on services)&#13;
ITBI                Imposto de Transmissao&#13;
(Property transfer tax)&#13;
ITR                 Imposto Territorial Rural&#13;
(Rural property tax)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IUCL                Imposto dnico sobre Lubricantes e Combustiveis Liquidos&#13;
e Gasosos&#13;
(Fuels tax)&#13;
IUEE                Imposto dnico sobre a Energia Elltrica&#13;
(Electricity tax)&#13;
IUM                  Imposto dnico sobre Minerais&#13;
(Minerals Tax)&#13;
IVC                 Imposto sobre Vendas e Consignacoes&#13;
(Turnover tax)&#13;
PASEP                Programa de Formacao do Patrimonio de Servidor Pdblico&#13;
(Public Employees Financial Reserve Fund)&#13;
PIS                  Programa de Integragao Social&#13;
(Social Integration Program)&#13;
PME                  Programa de Mobilizagao Energetico&#13;
(Energy Mobilization Program)&#13;
SAREM                Secretaria de Articulags'o com os Estados e Munic6pios&#13;
(Secretariat for Coordination with the Stal.es and&#13;
Municipalities, Federal Planning Secretar:Lat)&#13;
SE                   Salario Educassao&#13;
(Ed,ucation Salary tax)&#13;
SEF                  Sec:retaria de Economia e Finangas&#13;
(Secretariat for Economics and Finance, Ministry of&#13;
Finance)&#13;
SEPLAN               Secretaria de Planejamento&#13;
(Federal Planning Secretariat)&#13;
TELEBRAS             TeJLecomunicago8es Brasileiras, S. A.&#13;
(Brazilian Telephone Company)&#13;
TRU                  Taxa Rodoviaria Unica&#13;
(Vehicle Registration Tax)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CURRENCY EQUIVALENTS&#13;
Yearly Average of Cruzeiros/US$&#13;
1968     3.40                   1975     8.13&#13;
1969     4.07                   1976    10.67&#13;
1970     4.59                   1977    14.14&#13;
1971     5.29                   1978    18.08&#13;
1972     5.93                   1979    26.82&#13;
1973     6.13                   1980    52.81&#13;
1974     6.79                   1981    93.34&#13;
1982   178.89&#13;
Source:  Central Bank Bulletins&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ABSTRACT&#13;
Brazil's system of intergovernmental fiscal relations has, with some&#13;
ninor exceptions, remained unchanged for almost two decades. Economic, social&#13;
and political conditions :in the country, however, have undergone profound&#13;
transformations during the same period.  This paper investigates whether the&#13;
mechanisms, established during the 1960s, for financing state and local&#13;
governments are still.adequate in the environment of the 1980s. The main&#13;
conclusion is that they are not, and that certain fiscal adjustments are&#13;
called for in order to bring resource availability at the subnational level&#13;
more into line with functional responsibilities. Given the extreme intra- and&#13;
interregional economic disparities prevailing in Brazil, special attention is&#13;
given to the fiscal problems of governments in poorer regions.&#13;
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS&#13;
This report is based on the findings of a World Bank mission which&#13;
visited Brazil in 1981. It consisted of Dennis J. Mahar, (mission leader),&#13;
William Dillinger (urban economist), and Woo Sik Kee (fiscal economilst).&#13;
Mr. Jacques Cellier (transport economist) participated in a followup mission&#13;
in June 1982. In Washington, additional research and statisticELl support&#13;
were provided by Joan Ahern (research assistant).&#13;
,An earlier version of this paper was presented at a seminar held&#13;
in Brasilia during February 1983. The authors gratefully acknowledge the&#13;
useful comments provided by Brazilian colleagues, in particular Jose Teofilo&#13;
Oliveira, Fernando Rezende, Ricardo Varsano, Osmundo Rebou9as, Ibrahim Eris,&#13;
and Celsius Lodder.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. INTRODUCTION&#13;
During the period from 1965 to 1967, Brazil enacted a comprehen-&#13;
sive set of fiscal reforms affecting all levels of government. The&#13;
principal aims of these reforms were to increase domestic resource mobil-&#13;
ization, eliminate fiscally-induced distortions in the production and&#13;
distribution processes, promote capital formation and economic growth, and&#13;
reduce interregional disparities in the financial capacities of state and&#13;
local governments.l/ ToD these ends, new taxes were created and others&#13;
abolished; the tax administration apparatus was improved; the rights to&#13;
collect specific taxes were reallocated among the federal, stat:e and local&#13;
governments; and an expanded, and more regionally redistributive, system of&#13;
intergovernmental revenue-sharing was put in place.&#13;
Since the mid-1960s, frequent changes have been introduced to the&#13;
fiscal system, most related to tax rates and the criteria for revenue-&#13;
sharing. To a large extent, however, the main features of the original&#13;
fiscal reforms have remLained intact. But Brazil is not the same country it&#13;
was in the mid-1960s -- between 1970 and 1980, for example, th,e real GD)P&#13;
more than doubled, the proportion of the population living in urban areas&#13;
rose from 55% to 68%, and a gradual political opening (abertura) was&#13;
initiated -- and many have voiced the opinion that the fiscal system has&#13;
failed to adapt to the new economic, demographic and political realities.&#13;
One importani: line of thought holds that the public sector has&#13;
become "overly central:Lzed" during the past 15 years, and that the time has&#13;
come to increase the flscal roles and autonomy of the state and local&#13;
governments.2/ This poLnt of view has been expressed repeatedly in&#13;
academic circles and in pronouncements by politicians. Moreover, fiscal&#13;
decentralization is included as one of the objectives of Brazil's Third&#13;
National Development Plan (1980-85).3/ The question of whether the&#13;
Brazilian public sector is indeed "overly centralized", however, is fraught&#13;
with definitional uncertainties and is, at any rate, only partially&#13;
economic in nature. This study takes the present system of&#13;
intergovernmental fiscal relations as given and evaluates the recent&#13;
performance of state and local finances.&#13;
Methodologically, attention is focused on the extent to which the&#13;
intergovernmental fiscal system has achieved and maintained vertical&#13;
balance (the balance between resource availability and functional respon-&#13;
sibilities at each of the various levels of government) and horizontal&#13;
1    R. Varsano, "O Sistema Tributario de 1967: Adequado ao Brasil de 80?",&#13;
Pesquisa e Plane'jamento Econ8mico, XI, 1 (1981), 208-21.&#13;
2/   This is distinct from the argument that the Brazilian public sector as&#13;
a whole has becolne overextended (estatizacao), an issue which is not&#13;
addressed in the present report.&#13;
3/   Brasil, Presidencia da Republica, Secretaria de Planejamento,&#13;
III Plano Nacional de Desenvolvimento, 1980-85 (Brasflia, September&#13;
1980), pp. 47 and 84.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
balance (the balance between resources and responsibilities at given levels&#13;
of government in different parts of the country). The report will also&#13;
explore ways and means through which the roles of the states and munici-&#13;
palities as revenue-raisers and providers of public services might be&#13;
enhanced in the future. Before undertaking these tasks, however, it is&#13;
useful to discuss briefly the historical background and current institu-&#13;
tional framework of Brazil's intergovernmental fiscal system.&#13;
II.   HISTORICAL BACKGROUND TO 1968&#13;
The nature of the fiscal relationships among the various levels&#13;
of government in Brazil has evolved continually over the years, roughly&#13;
paralleling changes in social, political and economic conditions. For&#13;
discussion purposes, this historical evolution may be conveniently divided&#13;
into four more or less distinct phases: 1889-1930, 1930-45, 1946-64, and&#13;
1965-67. 4/&#13;
Dual Federalism: 1889-1930&#13;
Between 1889 and 1930, the period of Brazilian history known as&#13;
the "First Republic" or "Old Republic", most public functions were assumed&#13;
initially by the central government. This was undoubtedly a result of the&#13;
centralized political structure prevailing under the Empire (1822-89) and&#13;
the fact that Brazil became a federation by disaggregation rather than by&#13;
aggregation as occurred, for example, in the U. S.. As the central govern-&#13;
ment proved to be weak in relation to the states, power soon decentral-&#13;
ized. This transformation was closely related to the rapid growth of agri-&#13;
cultural and industrial activity in southeast Brazil,which generated both&#13;
new revenues and demands for public services, and was reflected in the&#13;
Constitution of 1891, which reserved all residual powers to the states.&#13;
The states, principally Sao Paulo, Minas Gerais and Rio Grande do&#13;
Sul, took advantage of their political autonomy and increasing revenues by&#13;
assuming such non-traditional responsibilities as coffee stabilization and&#13;
the promotion of immigration, and by embarking upon ambitious public works&#13;
programs. This is reflected in the fiscal data of the period which show&#13;
the states' share of total public expenditures rising from 36% to 46%&#13;
between 1907 and 1930. A distinguishing characteristic of this era was the&#13;
existence of "dual federalism", a system in which the federal and state&#13;
governments operated quite independently of each other in the planning,&#13;
financing and execution of public functions.&#13;
Decentralized Unitary Government: 1930-45&#13;
In the 1930-45 period, government as a whole assumed new respon-&#13;
sibilities, and the fundamental federal relationships were irrevocably&#13;
altered. More specifically, the "dual federalism" of the First Republic&#13;
4/   Details on the historical evolution of intergovernmental fiscal&#13;
relations in Brazil may be found in: D. J. Mahar, "Federalismo Fiscal&#13;
no Brasil: A Experiencia Historica", Revista ABOP, II, 2 (1976),&#13;
29-82.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3-&#13;
was replaced by a centra:Lized system sharing few characteristics with&#13;
"classical" federalism.&#13;
Two national Constitutions were promulgated during the period --&#13;
one in 1934 and the other in 1937. The first of these documents,&#13;
influenced by Germany's Weimar Constitution of 1919, had an economic and&#13;
social content that stood in sharp contrast to the purely political content&#13;
of its predecessor. Although it assigned a greater role to the central&#13;
government, the 1934 Constitution also clearly defined mumicipal. autonomy.&#13;
Municpipos (units of government somewhat resembling North American&#13;
counties were granted exclusive revenue sources for the first time and&#13;
were expected to become viable members of the federal system. Elowever, the&#13;
Constitution of 1934 was short-lived and replaced by a distinctly&#13;
centralist Constitution in 1937.&#13;
Building on the legal basis provided by the Constitul:ions of&#13;
1934 and 1937, and reacting to the impacts of the Great Depression and&#13;
rising economic nationalism, the central government, which prior to 1930&#13;
had performed only minimal functions, considerably expanded its range of&#13;
activities (especially in the areas of commodity controls, education and&#13;
labor) at the expense of the previously-powerful states. In addition, it&#13;
entered fields which hadt never before involved any level of government.&#13;
These new areas of government activity, often administered through extra-&#13;
budgetary institutes and enterprises, included a greatly expanded social&#13;
security system and the establishment of public enterprises in the steel,&#13;
energy and capital goodEi sectors.&#13;
Cooperative Federalism: 1946-64&#13;
At the end of World War II, Brazil gained a new government, a&#13;
new Constitution and new ways of dealing with intergovernmntal fiscal&#13;
problems. An important aspect of the Constitution of 1946 was its emphasis&#13;
on revitalizing local government. Direct contacts between the federal&#13;
government and the munit:pios were formalized in response to widespread&#13;
"municipalist" sentimenit in the Constituent Assembly.  The new&#13;
Constitution, however, did not provide "equal partnership" for local&#13;
government. It aimed only at curbing encroachments of the states within&#13;
the sphere of the munictpios. Nevertheless, the elaborate revenue-sharing&#13;
schemes utilized after 1948 theoretically provided local government with&#13;
the resources necessary to realize the political autonomy guaranteed by the&#13;
Constitution.&#13;
The revenue-sharing mechanisms established in the late 1940s&#13;
were quite complex and involved all three levels of government., Most&#13;
importantly, the municipios were to receive shares of the federal income&#13;
tax, excise tax and "sole taxes" (impostos utnicos) on fuels, electric&#13;
energy and minerals; 30% of all state taxes collected in a munlcipio which&#13;
exceeded the total own-source revenues of that municipio; and 40% of the&#13;
revenues from any new federal or state taxes.&#13;
If only the shares from the federal income and excise taxes had&#13;
been duly transferred to the local governments, they would have, by the&#13;
early 1960s, raised munricipal revenues by over 70%. However, the actual&#13;
impact of these provisions was greatly reduced by an "equal-shares per&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
municfpio" distribution formula (which led to a proliferation of local&#13;
governments), inflation, and nonpayment of quotas by the federal govern-&#13;
ment. During 1962-64, for example, less than 10% of the authorized federal&#13;
shares were actually disbursed to the municipios. 5/ Thus, the expansion&#13;
of government activity at the local level foreshadowed in the 1946&#13;
Constitution never materialized and, as of 1964, the municipal share of&#13;
total public sector revenues stood at the same level (7.5%) as it did in&#13;
1950.&#13;
The Fiscal Reforms of 1965-67&#13;
The present revenue structures of the state and local governments&#13;
were largely defined by the fiscal reforms of 1965-67. The principal&#13;
impetus for these reforms was the need to reduce the large public sector&#13;
deficits of the mid-1960s and the inflationary pressures caused by them.&#13;
There was at the time also a general perception that the revenue-sharing&#13;
schemes established in the 1940s were not having the salutary effects on&#13;
municipal finances originally envisaged. The government brought to power&#13;
in 1964 took immediate steps to deal with these problems. A general reform&#13;
of the fiscal system was outlined in Constitutional Amendment 18 (December&#13;
1965), detailed in Law 5172 (October 1966) and included virtually intact in&#13;
the Constitution of 1967. The main effects of the reforms were to redefine&#13;
the tax bases available to each level of government, concentrate control&#13;
over tax bases and rates at the federal level and vastly expand the impor-&#13;
tance of federal transfers in the revenues of the state and municipal&#13;
governments.&#13;
Before the reforms, the main source of state government revenues&#13;
was a turnover-type sales tax (IVC). Tax rates and assessment practices&#13;
varied according to the policies of each state government. The states also&#13;
collected export, property transfer and stamp taxes as well as fixed shares&#13;
of the federal "sole taxes". The yields of state taxes, other than the&#13;
IVC, were relatively low. Delays and cancellations in the distribution of&#13;
shares of the federal taxes also limited their importance.&#13;
Prior to 1967, local governments relied on two principal taxes:&#13;
a tax on urban property and a tax on industrial production and professional&#13;
services. The latter lacked a clearly-defined base (i.e., "movimento&#13;
economico"), and was often imposed as a surcharge on the IVC, particularly&#13;
in poorer states. Yields of the urban property tax were limited by the&#13;
difficulties of reassessing local real estate values during a period of&#13;
high inflation. Municipal governments also collected stamp and license&#13;
taxes, and taxes on entertainment, all with relatively low yields. Like&#13;
the states, the municipios were entitled to fixed shares of the federal&#13;
"sole taxes".   They were also to benefit from shares of the federal income&#13;
and excise taxes, though, as pointed out previously, the implementation of&#13;
this scheme was flawed.&#13;
5/   D. J. Mahar, "The Failures of Revenue Sharing in Brazil and Some&#13;
Recent Developments", Bulletin for International Fiscal Documentation,&#13;
XXV, 3 (1971), 71-80.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
The fiscal reforms abolished all state taxes except for the&#13;
relatively minor property transfer tax.   In place of the IVC, the reform&#13;
legislation substituted a value-added tax (ICM). By establishing the ICM,&#13;
the reformers sought to eliminate the economic distortions and wi.despread&#13;
evasion fostered by the turnover tax. All municipal taxes were likewise&#13;
abolished with the exception of the urban property tax. To replace the tax&#13;
on industry and professions, and the other miscellaneous local taxes, the&#13;
new fiscal legislation authorized municipios to impose a tax on services,&#13;
and to share in the collections of the ICM. An additional feature of the&#13;
reforms was to give the federal government exclusive authority to establish&#13;
any new taxes,that is, taxes not explicitly contemplated in the reform&#13;
legislation.&#13;
The reforms sought to compensate the state and local governments&#13;
for the restriction of their own-source tax bases by expanding the system&#13;
of intergovernmental transfers. The mechanism for sharing federal income&#13;
and excise taxes was revised and expanded to include the states. The&#13;
principal aims of the new system were to augment the revenues of state&#13;
governments in poorer regions and to channel increased federal funds to&#13;
municlpios with limited tax bases and administrative capacities. The&#13;
nature of the post-1967 revenue-sharing schemes, as well as the other major&#13;
components of the state and local revenue bases (taxes and credit&#13;
operations), are described in greater detail in the following section.&#13;
III. CURRENT INSTITUTIONAL FRAMEWORK&#13;
Administrative Structure&#13;
At present, the Brazilian public sector is comprised of a federal&#13;
(central) government, three federal territories, 23 states and about 4,000&#13;
local governments (municipios).   In addition, a large number of decentral-&#13;
ized semiautonomous agencies (e.g., autarquias, fundac'es) and public&#13;
enterprises (.e.g., empresas pu'blicas, sociedades de economia mista)&#13;
operate at the federal,state and local levels.   This "parastatal sector"&#13;
had its origins in the 1930s (see para. 10) and has since expanded&#13;
rapidly. 6/&#13;
The data presented in Table 1 illustrate some of the basic fiscal&#13;
interrelationships among the federal, state and municipal governments. Two&#13;
characteristics are ev-Ldent. First, the federal government clearly&#13;
dominates the system, accounting for over 70% of both revenues and expendi-&#13;
tures. Second, the states and municlpios are more important as providers&#13;
of public services, particularly investments, than they are as revenue-&#13;
raisers. This is explained by the existence of various intergovernmental&#13;
revenue-sharing and grant schemes. A third characteristic of the Brazilian&#13;
fiscal system, obscured by the level of aggregation in Table 1, is the&#13;
6/   For an historical, account of this development, see:  T.J. Trebat,&#13;
Brazil's State-Owmed Enterprises: A Case Study of the State as&#13;
Entrepreneur (Cambridge:   Cambridge University Press, 1983).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6-&#13;
extensive fragmentation of spending authority between the federal govern-&#13;
ment, states and municfpios and their respective decentralized&#13;
agencies. 7/ This administrative feature has interfered with the ability&#13;
of budget authorities at all levels of government to control the size and&#13;
sectoral allocation of public expenditures.&#13;
The relative importance of the federal government is undoubtedly&#13;
far greater than implied in Table 1. This is because the data shown are&#13;
from the "fiscal budget", and hence exclude public enterprises and the&#13;
so-called "monetary budget" (orcamento monetario). 8/ (The latter refers&#13;
to the revenues and expenditures of the Banco Centr:L and Banco do Brasil&#13;
which include a large volume of essentially fiscal operations). Public&#13;
enterprises (though not "monetary budgets") also exist at the state and&#13;
municipal levels, but fragmentary data suggest that they are less important&#13;
relative to the respective "fiscal budgets" than at the federal level.&#13;
Moreover, many subnational public enterprises (including many of those&#13;
operating in the energy, telecommunications and agricultural sectors) are&#13;
subsidiaries of federal holding companies (e.g., Eletrobras, Telebras,&#13;
EMBRATER, CIBRAZEM, etc.) and subject to varying degrees of central&#13;
control.&#13;
While given units of government are essentially treated as equals&#13;
under Brazilian Constitutional law, the states and municlpios constitute a&#13;
highly heterogeneous lot. This heterogeneity stems, inter alia, from the&#13;
particular pattern of the country's settlement and from wide spatial&#13;
variations in natural resource bases and economic structures. Thus, one&#13;
finds states as different as Sto Paulo (densely populated and highly&#13;
industrialized, with a per capita income almost twice the national&#13;
average), Alagoas (densely populated and agrarian, with a per capita income&#13;
perhaps half that of the nation) and Mato Grosso (a sparsely-populated,&#13;
relatively poor frontier area, with incipient agricultural and industrial&#13;
development taking place); and municlpios as dissimilar as Vicosa, Rio&#13;
Grande do Norte (population 1,150) and S o Paulo (population 8.5 million).&#13;
These spatial differences clearly suggest caution when generalizing from&#13;
fiscal data aggregated to the national level.&#13;
State and Local Revenue Sources&#13;
State taxes. Taxes account for about 60% of total state revenues&#13;
(see Table 2). Though the states are permitted to tax transfers of real&#13;
property (ITBI), for all intents and purposes the only meaningful tax&#13;
available at this level is the ICM. In recent years, ICM collections have&#13;
comprised about 95% of the states' total tax revenues.&#13;
7/   In 1975, for example, state decentralized agencies accounted for about&#13;
34% of expenditures at the state level, but only 8% of the revenues.&#13;
8/   The full dimensions of the federal public sector are quantified in:&#13;
Carlos von Doellinger, "Estatizacao, Financas Publicas e suas&#13;
Implicacoes", Camara de Estudos e Debates Econ8micos e Sociais -&#13;
CEDES, Relatorio de Pesquisa No. 1 (December 1981).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7&#13;
Table 1&#13;
Structure of the Public Sector, 1975 a/&#13;
(Cr.$ millions)&#13;
Federal       State    Municipal    All Governments&#13;
1. Current Revenues           202,699.7    70,735.4 b/ 9,767.5        283,202.6&#13;
(X)                    (71.6)      (25.0)      (3.4)          (100.0)&#13;
2. Capital Revenues c/           2,275..8     653.4       220.1         3,149.3&#13;
(%)                    (72.3)      (20.7)      (7.0)          (100.0)&#13;
3. Total Revenues (1) + (2)   204,975.5    71,388.8    9,987.6        286,351.9&#13;
(X)                    (71.6)      (24.9)      (3.5)          (100.0)&#13;
4. Current Expenditures       162,420.1    55,082.9     6,210.1       223,713.1&#13;
(%)                    (72.6)      (24.6)      (2.8)          (100.0)&#13;
5. Capital Expenditures d/      27,734.9   26,305.1     6,142.7        60,182.7&#13;
(%)                    (46.1)      (43.7)     (10.2)          (100.0)&#13;
6. Total Expenditures&#13;
(4) + (5)              190,155.0    81,388.0   12,352.8        283,895.8&#13;
(%)                    (67.0)      (28.7)      (4.4)          (100.0)&#13;
7. Current Surplus/Deficit&#13;
(1) - (4)            40,279.5   15,652.5     3,624.8         59,489.5&#13;
8. Total Surplus/Deficit&#13;
(3) - (6)             14,820.5   -9,999.2    -2,365.2         -2,456.1&#13;
a/  Data include decentralized agencies, but exclude public enterprises;&#13;
intergovernmental transfers have been deducted to avoid double-counting.&#13;
b/ All of ICM collections attributed to states.&#13;
c/ Net of borrowing.&#13;
d/ Excludes debt amortization.&#13;
Source : Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatlstica (IBGE), unpublished.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The states' freedom to levy the ICM is restricted by the federal&#13;
government's authority to determine the tax base and rates. In its present&#13;
form, the ICM is not a true tax on global value-added because of the wide&#13;
range of exemptions from the tax base. Among the more important of these&#13;
exemptions are certain essential foodstuffs (e.g., milk, eggs, fresh&#13;
vegetables), manufactured exports, industrial machinery and equipment,&#13;
agricultural inputs, fuels, minerals and services. From time to time, the&#13;
federal government has also granted additional exemptions to promote&#13;
priority objectives of national economic policy. At present, the ICM tax&#13;
rate is set at a uniform 16% for all intrastate transactions. (In the&#13;
past, rates had been set higher in the relatively poor North and Northeast&#13;
to help compensate for the lower state tax bases in these regions). The&#13;
rates are lower on interstate transactions (11% on sales originating in the&#13;
North, Northeast and Center-West and 9% on sales originating in the&#13;
Southeast and South), which are taxed according to the origin of sales.&#13;
Municipal taxes.   The Brazilian Constitution limits municipios to&#13;
two tax bases: urban property and "services of any type". The urban&#13;
property tax (IPTU) applies to land and buildings in areas of each&#13;
municfpio defined according to federal guidelines as "urban." To be&#13;
classified as urban for fiscal purposes, a lot must be served by at least&#13;
two services constructed or maintained by the municipal government (among&#13;
them sidewalks, water supply, sewers, street lighting, a primary school, or&#13;
health post). While this definition exempts much of the tax base of rural&#13;
municlpios, it is in practice a fairly generous definition of an urban&#13;
area. Unlike state taxes, property tax rates are federally unrestricted.&#13;
A recent Supreme Court decision has upheld the power of municipal govern-&#13;
ments to "correct" the assessed value of all urban property for inflation,&#13;
up to a ceiling established by the treasury bond index (ORTN), without any&#13;
assessment based on actual field data.&#13;
The service tax (ISS) is similarly limited to a federally-&#13;
defined base. Types of services liable to the tax are specified by federal&#13;
legislation. The legal base of the ISS is the gross value of the service&#13;
performed, but in the case of some self-employed professionals federal&#13;
courts have approved the power of municipal governments to assess the tax&#13;
on a "per worker" basis in the interest of administrative convenience.&#13;
Under this system, each municipio is permitted to set a reference value for&#13;
tax purposes; a given worker's tax bill is equal to this reference value,&#13;
or some fixed fraction thereof. Unlike the property tax, the maximum rates&#13;
of the service tax are set by the federal government.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 2&#13;
State and Municipal Revenues by Source, 1978 a/&#13;
S T A T E S                                         M U N I C I P I O S&#13;
Cr$ 106     %                                               Cr$ 106    X&#13;
Exclusive Sources          173,884.2    67.8     Exclusive Sources                     22,992.1     48.5&#13;
Value-Added Tax&#13;
(ICM) b/               151,865.0     59.2     Service Tax (ISS)                      7,768.6    16.4&#13;
Transfer Tax (ITBI)         4,099.7      1.6     Property Tax (IPTU)                    7,834.5     16.5&#13;
Non-Tax C/                  17;919.5     7.0     Non-Tax c/                             7,389.0     15.6&#13;
Transfers                  50,367.2     19.6     Transfers                             18,804.2     39.7&#13;
Participation Fund&#13;
(FPE + FE)              15,769.2      6.1     Federal: Participation Fund (FPM)      1,233.4     2.6&#13;
Fuels Tax (IULC)             7,562.5     2.9               Fuels Tax (IULC)               597.4      1.3&#13;
Electricity Tax (IUEE)      4,158.8      1.6               Electricity Tax (IUEE)          60.5      0.1&#13;
Vehicle Registration                                       Vehicle Registration&#13;
Tax (TRU)                   3,324.6      1.3               Tax (TRU)                      222.0      0.5&#13;
Ed. Salary Tax (SE) d/      4,647.6      1.8               Grants e/                    1,713.6      3.6&#13;
Grants e/                   9,469.3      3.7               Others t/                      810.9      1.7&#13;
Others f/                   5,435.2      2.1&#13;
Credit Operations          32,218.7     12.6     State:    Value-Added Tax             13,725.7     29.0&#13;
(ICM) Grants e/                446.7      0.9&#13;
TOTAL REVENUES            256,470.0    100.0     Credit Operations                      5,569.3     11.8&#13;
TOTAL REVENUES                        47,365.6   100.0&#13;
a/  Central budgets only; municipal data refer to state capitals only.&#13;
b/ .State share (80%).&#13;
c/  Includes fees, property income, asset sales, "miscellaneous" and taxes (ISS, IPTU) collected in&#13;
the Federal District.&#13;
di  Includes share transferred through the National Educational Development Fund (FNDE).&#13;
e/  Transfers not linked to specific taxes.&#13;
f/  Includes transfers from decentralized agencies and public enterprises; shares from minerals tax&#13;
(IUM) and "miscellaneous".&#13;
Source : IBGE, Estatlsticas Economicas do Governo Estadual e Municipal, 1978 (Rio de Janeiro,&#13;
1980).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
Federal revenue sharing. Intergovernmental transfers constitute&#13;
important sources of revenue for some of the poorer states and for the&#13;
majority of local governments (see Table 2). The present revenue-sharing&#13;
system contemplates flows of funds between the federal government and the&#13;
states, the federal government and the municlpios, and the states and the&#13;
municlpios. As shown in Table 3, a variety of federal taxes are currently&#13;
shared with the states and municfpios. 9/ The most important of these are&#13;
the income tax (IR), manufacturers' sales tax (IPI), the "sole taxes" on&#13;
fuels and electric energy (IUCL and IUEE, respectively), the automobile&#13;
registration tax (TRU) and the education salary tax (SE). In 1981, these&#13;
six taxes accounted for about 80% of total federal tax revenues.&#13;
Shares from the IR and IPI are transferred to the state and local&#13;
governments through "Participation Funds" (Fundos de Participacao - FPs).&#13;
Overall responsibility for the FPs rests with the Secretaria de Articulacao&#13;
cor os Estados e Munictpios (SAREM) of the Federal Planning Secretariat&#13;
(SEPLAN), an agency which also provides technical assistance to state and&#13;
local governments. The percentages of the IR and IPI to be deposited in&#13;
the FPs have varied considerably over the years. The figure for 1982 is&#13;
23% (see Table 3) and is scheduled to rise to 24% in 1984. At present,&#13;
there are three FPs: 10.5% of each tax goes to the State Fund (FPE), a like&#13;
amount goes to the Municipal Fund (FPM), and 2% is deposited in a "Special&#13;
Fund" (FE). The latter is reserved for the northern and northeastern&#13;
states and for Esplrito Santo, Goias, Mato Grosso and Santa Catarina.&#13;
The criteria employed for determining individual shares from the&#13;
FPs are broadly based on the concept of "need". That is, a given state or&#13;
municfpio's land area, population and per capita income are all taken into&#13;
account (see Table 3). There are two exceptions to this rule: (i)&#13;
municlpios other than state capitals (entitled to 90% of the FPM) receive&#13;
their shares based on population alone; and (ii) the FE is distributed&#13;
according to criteria determined annually by SEPLAN. In order to enhance&#13;
further the regionally redistributive impact of the FPs, a special reserve&#13;
fund for states in the relatively poor North and Northeast was established&#13;
in 1975. This reserve is constituted through 20% shares of the FPs and is&#13;
received by the beneficiaries as an addition to their normal FP and FE&#13;
quotas.&#13;
Originally, shares from the FPs were to be transferred to the&#13;
states and municipios with a number of "strings attached". During most of&#13;
the 1970s, both levels of government were required to earmark 30-50% of&#13;
their shares for expenditures on certain functions (education, health and&#13;
sanitation, agriculture and the formation of "development funds").&#13;
Moreover, at least half of the total proceeds were to be allocated to&#13;
capital expenditures. In order to help ensure that this earmarking would&#13;
be carried out, spending plans were to be submitted for federal government&#13;
approval prior to the release of individual shares.&#13;
9/   It should be noted that funds transferred through institutionalized&#13;
tax-sharing schemes do not account for all intergovernmental&#13;
transfers.. As shown in Table 2, some funds are transferred as ad hoc&#13;
grants and/or emanate from the decentralized sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 3&#13;
SunLry of ?rincipal Revenue-Sharing Mechanisms&#13;
(As of Januar 1, 1982)&#13;
Total                Division (X)&#13;
Shared Taesa a/                        Collections, 1981                                        Distribution&#13;
r(C   T bfiio      States       Municipios              Criteria                   Earmarking&#13;
1. Income Tax (IR)                           965.3            12.50 b/     10.50          Land area (52);              PASEP (2%); education&#13;
population and inverse       sector (20X) (municipios&#13;
2. Manufacturers' Sales Tax (IPI)           613.5            12.50 b/      10.50          of state per capita          only)&#13;
income (95Z). c/&#13;
3. Fuels '"ax (IULC)                         60.1            30.72          8.00          Land area (202);             Transport sector (1002); in&#13;
population (402);            accordance with National&#13;
consumption (402). d/        Highway Plan.&#13;
i. Vehicli Registration Tax (TRU)            61.2            45.00          -             Origin basis; municipal      Programa de&#13;
quotas at discretion of      Mobilirco Energetico&#13;
etaten.   ~          ~~~~ -, PME(3X) Programa&#13;
states.                          .Z65&#13;
Especial de Vias&#13;
Expressas - PROGRES&#13;
(28.5X) road&#13;
improvements (35.52).&#13;
S. Interstate and Intermanicipal&#13;
Highway Transport Tax (ISTR)               19.8            20.00         -             Origin (502); length of      Transport sector (1002); for&#13;
highway network (302);       road maintenance,&#13;
population (202).            rehabilitation and&#13;
improvements, traffic safety,&#13;
and construction of passenger&#13;
and cargo terminals.&#13;
i. Electlicity Tax (IUEE)                    60.6            50.00         10.00          Land area (202);             Investment in energy sector&#13;
population (602);            (1002).&#13;
production (22) and&#13;
consumption (152) of&#13;
electric energy; area&#13;
inundated by&#13;
hydroelectric projects&#13;
(32).&#13;
Minerils Tax (IUM)                         18.1            70.00         20.00         Origin basis.                In direct or indirect benefit&#13;
of mining sector (states);&#13;
priority to education, social&#13;
assistance, roads and&#13;
electric energy (municipios).&#13;
1. Education Salary Tax (SE)                 62.6            66.67           -            Origin basis.               Basic education (1002).&#13;
1. Rural Land Tax (ITR)                      14.0 (eat)       -            80.00          Origin basis.               None.&#13;
O.Valu.-Added Tax (ICM)                   1,209.2            80.00         20.00         Origin (752); at             None.&#13;
discretion of states&#13;
(25X).&#13;
I.Prop4!rty Transfer Tax (ITBI)              lO.(,  e/      50.00         50.00          Origin basis.                None.&#13;
a/T'Taxes 1-9 are federal; 10 and 11 are state,,&#13;
b/   Lwo percent allocated to "Special Fund" (FYI).&#13;
c/  3hares to non-state capitals (90X of municipal quota) distributed on basis of&#13;
)opulation only.&#13;
d/  Refers to imported fuels.&#13;
e/  1980 data.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
In response to criticism that the earmarking provisions and&#13;
burdensome bureaucratic procedures were interfering with state and local&#13;
political autonomy and the efficient allocation of public resources, the&#13;
*strings" on shares from the FPs were substantially eliminated during&#13;
1979-81. 10/ The only earmarking that remains are the provisions that 2%&#13;
of the FPEiand FPM be deducted for the Public Employees' Financial Reserve&#13;
Fund (PASEP), and that 20% of the FPM be devoted to education. Prior&#13;
federal approval of budgets is no longer required, and shares are trans-&#13;
ferred automatically to the recipient governments by the Bank of Brazil as&#13;
the taxes are collected.&#13;
The manner in which the other major federal taxes (i.e., IULC,&#13;
IUEE, TRU and SE) are shared with the states and municipios differs concep-&#13;
tually from that of the Participation Funds. One difference is that the&#13;
distribution criteria for these taxes do not explicitly promote the reduc-&#13;
tion of interregional disparities. 11/ In fact, the relative weights&#13;
given to such factors as population, production, consumption and motor&#13;
vehicle ownership (see Table 3) suggests that the benefits from these&#13;
revenue-sharing mechanisms would tend to be concentrated in the densely&#13;
populated and highly industrialized Southeast. Another difference is that&#13;
the transfers from the "sole taxes", TRU and the SE are fully earmarked to&#13;
the transport, (IUCL, TRU) energy (IUEE) or education (SE) sectors.&#13;
State revenue sharing.    State taxes shared with the municfpios&#13;
include the value-added tax (ICM) and, starting in 1981, the property&#13;
transfer tax (ITBI).    Shares of the ICM constitute the    single most impor-&#13;
tant source of revenue for many local governments. Through the 1965-67&#13;
reforms, a mechanism was established whereby the states would collect the&#13;
ICM and distribute 20% of the proceeds to the municfpios on an origin&#13;
basis, gross of state exemptions. Such shares are transferred&#13;
automatically to the recipient governments and are not subject to&#13;
earmarking.    However, owing to the particular sectoral incidence of the&#13;
ICM, the main beneficiaries of this tax-sharing mechanism tend to be the&#13;
more industrialized municfpios. 12/ This peculiarity has had some&#13;
negative distributional consequences in a spatial sense, which has prompted&#13;
the passage of new legislation permitting the states to transfer up to 25%&#13;
of the municipal share according to discretional criteria.&#13;
10/ For an early critique of the earmarking provisions, see: A. Barboza&#13;
de Araujo, M.H.T. Taques Horta and C.M. Considera, Transferencias de&#13;
Impostos aos Estados e Municipios (Rio de Janeiro: IPEA/INPES, 1973).&#13;
11/ It should be noted, however, that the federal share of the education&#13;
salary tax (33%) is transferred back to the states on need-based&#13;
criteria through the National Educational Development Fund (FNDE).&#13;
12/ For a discussion of the sectoral incidence of the ICM, see:&#13;
F. A. Rezende da Silva and M. da Concei'ao Silva, 0 Sistema Tributario&#13;
e as Desigualdades Regionais: Uma Analise da Recente Controvdrsia&#13;
Sobre o ICM (Rio de Janeiro: IPEA/INPES, 1974), Ch. IV.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
Credit operations. In recent years, credit has become increas-&#13;
ingly important as a source of state and municipal revenues. The sources&#13;
of this credit have taken many forms, including bond placements and loans&#13;
loans from official and commercial (domestic and foreign) banks. Though&#13;
expressly forbidden by 1kw, it would appear that "arrearages" have also&#13;
been increasingly used as a means of financing state and local government.&#13;
The general rules governing the domestic indebtedness of the&#13;
states and municfpios are contained in two resolutions of the Federal&#13;
Senate Resolution 62 of October 28, 1975 and Resolution 93 of October 11,&#13;
1976. 13/ The first of these resolutions sets limits on both total and&#13;
annualfindebtedness. The basic rules are: (i) the total debt outstanding&#13;
in any given year may not exceed 70% of a given state or municlpio's total&#13;
revenues (adjusted for inflation) of the previous fiscal year; (ii) the&#13;
amount of debt contracted in any year may not exceed 20% of the total&#13;
revenues of that year; and (iii) debt service (interest plus amortization)&#13;
in any year may not exceed 15% of the total revenues (adjusted for infla-&#13;
tion) of the previous fLscal year. For purposes of establishing these&#13;
limits, credit operations are excluded from the concept of "total state or&#13;
municipal revenues".   Funds obtained under the rules of Resolution 62 are&#13;
known as "intralimit" credit.&#13;
Resolution 93 broadens the rules established under Resolution 62&#13;
by freeing certain credit operations from pre-set limits. Such operations,&#13;
known as "extralimit" credit, apply only to funds obtained from the&#13;
National Urban Development Fund (FNDU), the Social Development Fund (FAS)&#13;
and the National Housing Bank (BNH). However, states and municfpios seek-&#13;
ing credit from these sources must obtain the approval of SEPLAN, the&#13;
National Monetary Council (CMN) and the Federal Senate. Prior approval by&#13;
SEPLAN and the Senate Ls also required in the case of all foreign borrow-&#13;
ing, even when a given state or municlpio is below its legal debt&#13;
limit. 14/&#13;
State and Local Functional Responsibilities&#13;
In contrast to the strict separation of revenue sources, the law&#13;
is vague when it comes to allocating functional responsibilitLes to the&#13;
states and municfpios. Legally, the states are permitted to engage in any&#13;
activity not explicitly or implicitly forbidden to them by the Federal&#13;
Constitution. Since few functions are assigned to any level of government&#13;
on an exclusive basis., this has theoretically given the states considerable&#13;
13/ These rules apply to state and municipal governments proper and to&#13;
their decentralized agencies (autarquias. .or fundagoes), but not to&#13;
public enterprisies.  This is said to be an important loophole.&#13;
14/  Through a ruling by the Central Bank (Circular 648 of August 5, 1981),&#13;
the states and municdpios may circumvent prior Senate approval of&#13;
foreign credit cperations by sub-borrowing in local currency from&#13;
loans obtained abroad by financial intermediaries (generally state or&#13;
regional development banks) under the provisions of Resolution 63 (of&#13;
August 21, 1967). These types of operations, however, still require&#13;
the approval of SEPLAN.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
freedom. The Constitution is at its vaguest when referring to the func-&#13;
tions of the munic4pios, which are held responsible only for the organiza-&#13;
tion of "local public services".&#13;
In practice, the lack of a strict delineation of functions has&#13;
led to a situation in which a wide range of public services are provided by&#13;
more than one level of government. This is clearly illustrated in&#13;
Table 4. The federal government quite logically maintains a virtual&#13;
monopoly over national defense and foreign affairs, but almost all other&#13;
services are jointly provided to some extent. However, certain levels of&#13;
government have tended to specialize in specific functional areas. At the&#13;
state and local levels, this specialization is most clearly observed in&#13;
some of the social services. In 1975, for example, the states and&#13;
municfpios combined accounted for significant portions of public spending&#13;
(after transfers) in the following social sectors: housing and urban&#13;
services (99%), education (74% overall, and 98% at the primary level) and&#13;
health and sanitation (47%). The state-municipal share of total public&#13;
expenditures in the same year was about 33%.&#13;
The data in Table 4 also give some idea of the de facto division&#13;
of responsibilities between the state and local governments. In broad&#13;
terms (keeping in mind that the level of aggregation masks important inter-&#13;
regional differences in the spending patterns), states tend to be rela-&#13;
tively more involved in the "economic services" (agriculture, energy,&#13;
industry and commerce) than are the nunicipios. The opposite appears to be&#13;
true in the case of the "social services". However, it may be observed&#13;
that the relative importance of local government in providing social&#13;
services is attributable almost solely to their intensive activity in the&#13;
area of housing and urban services. Education, on the other hand, is&#13;
mainly a state function, although the municdpios do play an important role&#13;
in providing education services at the primary level. T5/ In 1975, about&#13;
70% of total municipal expenditures on education were alTocated to the&#13;
primary system.&#13;
15/ The Education Reform Law (Law 5692 of August 11, 1971) holds that&#13;
education services are provided "most satisfactorily by local&#13;
administrations" and calls for the progressive transferral of this&#13;
function to the municipios. Although practices vary from state to&#13;
state, rural primary education is usually the responsibility of the&#13;
municfpios, and urban primary education the responsibility of the&#13;
states. See: Instituto Brasileiro de AdministraSa4o Municipal (IBAM),&#13;
Pesquisa Sobre as Relacoes Intergovernamentais: 0 Estado e o&#13;
Municfpio (Rio de Janeiro, 1974), pp. 246-47.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 4&#13;
Public Expenditures by Function and Level of Government, 1975 *&#13;
Federal                State               Municipal       -All Governments&#13;
Functional Categories                 Cr.$106       %      Cr.$106        %       Cr.$100      %      Cr.$100      X&#13;
GENERAL GOVERNMENT                    45,748.7    63.4     23,931.5     33.2      2,487.8    3.4      72,168.0   100.0&#13;
Administration                        32,121.7    62.8     16,541.2     32.A      2-461.5     4.8     51,124.8   100.0&#13;
Defense &amp; Foreign Affairs              9,432.8   100.0        -           -          -        -        9OO..&#13;
Police                                 4,194.2    36.1      7,390.3     63.7         26.3    0.2      11,610.8   100.0&#13;
ECONOMIC SERVICES                     43,644.1    65.8     20,159.1     30.4      2,533.5     3.8     66,336.7   100.0&#13;
Agriculture &amp; Natural Resources        6,650.8    73.4      2,407.2     26.6          1.9     0.0      9,059.8   100.0&#13;
Energy                                 3,281.3    43.3      4,293.9     56.7          3.7    0.9       7,578.9   100.0&#13;
Transport &amp; Communications            20,639.2    59.6     11,601.3     33.5      2,368.0     6.8     34,608.5   100.0&#13;
Industry &amp; Commerce                   13,072.8    86.4      1,896.8     12.5        159.9     1.1     15,129.5   100.0&#13;
SOCIAL SERVICES                      101,513.3    69.4     37,257.4     25.5      7,331.5    5.0      14,102.2   100.0&#13;
Education                              6,541.0    26.2     16,913.1     67.8      1,475.6     5.9     24,929.7   100.0&#13;
Housing &amp; Urban Services                  81.2     1.4      1,868.2     33.3      3,669.1    65.3      5,618.5   100.0&#13;
Health &amp; Sanitation                   10,746.1    53.0      8,177.5     40.3      1,306.5     6.7     20,284.1   100.0&#13;
Labor &amp; Welfare                       84,145.0    88.3     10,298.6     10.8        826.3    0.9      95,269.9   100.0&#13;
TOTAL                          190,155.0     67.0     81,388.0     28.7     12,352.8    4.3     283,895.8   100.0&#13;
* Data include decentralized agencies, intergovernmental transfers have been deducted.&#13;
Source: IBGE (unpublished)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
IV. CORRESPONDENCE OF REVENUES AND EXPENDITURES:&#13;
THE QUESTION OF VERTICAL BALANCE&#13;
In order to maintain the fiscal stability of a federation, it is&#13;
necessary that there be broad correspondence between resource availability&#13;
and functional responsibilities (whether de jure or de facto) at each level&#13;
of government in the system. This ideal balance may be achieved at a given&#13;
point in time, but in most federations it has proven difficult to maintain&#13;
in the long run. Various hypotheses have been put forward to explain this&#13;
phenomenon. Some authors attribute vertical imbalances simply to poor&#13;
fiscal management. The majority view, however, is that such imbalances are&#13;
inherent to federations. Proponents of the latter argument hold that the&#13;
most productive modern taxes (especially those on income and value-added)&#13;
are collected efficiently only at the national level, while optimal scale&#13;
in the provision of most public services is reached at the subnational&#13;
level. There is, thus, a tendency for subnational governments to be&#13;
chronically underfinanced.&#13;
When vertical imbalances become evident, adjustments in the&#13;
intergovernmental fiscal system are called for--on the revenue side, expen-&#13;
diture side, or both. Solutions have varied from country to country,&#13;
ranging from the establishment of revenue sharing and grant mechanisms, to&#13;
shifts from one level of government to another of authority over specific&#13;
taxes or spending functions. The purpose of the present section is to&#13;
discuss the extent to which vertical balance has been achieved and main-&#13;
tained in Brazil, and to assess the efficacy of the present adjustment&#13;
mechanisms. Owing to data limitations, the quantitative analysis of more&#13;
recent years is mainly confined to the states.&#13;
The "Conventional Wisdom"&#13;
It is commonly asserted in Brazil that state and local finances&#13;
have deteriorated significantly in recent years. 16/ Through the 1965-67&#13;
fiscal reforms, it is argued, the federal government assumed control over&#13;
the most elastic revenue sources, leaving the rest to the states and&#13;
municfpios. The principal effect has been for the subnational governments&#13;
to become less and less capable of covering expenditures with their own&#13;
revenue sources. This has led to increasing deficits and more frequent&#13;
recodrse to outside sources of funds such as revenue-sharing, grants and&#13;
borrowing. The latter tendency has been interpreted by some as evidence of&#13;
an increasing fiscal (and by implication, political) dependence of the&#13;
states and municfpios on the federal government. In order to assess the&#13;
validity of the scenario sketched above, several basic fiscal indicators&#13;
were calculated for the period 1968-80. These include calculations of&#13;
current account saving ratios, investment rates and the extent to which&#13;
state and local governments have engaged in deficit financing.&#13;
16/  See, for example, "Reflexos da Reforma Tributaria de 1966 nas&#13;
Finangas Estaduais," Revista de Finangas Publicas, XXXVIII, 336&#13;
(1978), 47-80; and "Reflexos da Reforma Tributaria de 1966 nas&#13;
Finan9as Municipais ", Revista de FinanEas Pdblicas, XXXIX, 337&#13;
(1979), 43-60.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
Saving and Investment&#13;
The saving and investment indicators presented in Table 5 show a&#13;
deteriorating trend over the 1968-80 period. During the first seven years&#13;
of the series, the states were able to cover current expenditures and to&#13;
invest on the basis of t:heir own revenues from taxes and fees, but this&#13;
proved impossible after 1974. If intergovernmental transfers are added to&#13;
the states' own current revenues, positive saving rates may be observed in&#13;
all years of the series (see Table 5, column I [D]). However, during the&#13;
post-1974 period, these rates behave erratically and are, on the average,&#13;
lower than those prevailing in 1968-74. The growing dependence on outside&#13;
financial assistance is illustrated by the ratio of federal transfers to&#13;
total state revenues (net of borrowing), which rose from 14% in 1968-69 to&#13;
22% in 1979-80.&#13;
Generally declining saving rates have quite clearly reduced the&#13;
states' capacity to invest. Capital expenditures as a proportion of total&#13;
expenditures, which rose from 26.8% in 1968 to 37.6% in 1974, subsequently&#13;
fell to 30.6% in 1980 (see Table 5, column II). Moreover, of the invest-&#13;
ment spending which did occur, only a part was financed through current&#13;
saving. The rest was covered by miscellaneous capital receipts (e.g.,&#13;
property sales, rents and participation in industrial enterprises), arrear-&#13;
ages and, most importantly, by borrowing.&#13;
Deficit Financing&#13;
The growing imbalance between state revenues and expenditures has&#13;
led to an increasing reLiance on deficit financing. Deficits in relation&#13;
to total expenditures appear to have worsened at the state level (and local&#13;
level as well) starting in 1974 (see Table 5, column III). The relative&#13;
size of the states' deficit peaked in 1977 but has since remained at high&#13;
levels by historical standards (see Table 5, column III). In aLbsolute&#13;
terms, the cumulative deficit of the states amounted to Cr.$868 billion&#13;
(1980 prices), or US$16.4 billion equivalent at the average official&#13;
exchange rate. About 70% of this total was realized after 1974.&#13;
During the 1968-80 period, approximately 95% of the states'&#13;
deficits (Cr.$819 billion in 1980 prices) were covered by credit operations&#13;
of various types. (It must be assumed that the remainder was financed&#13;
through arrearages). Among the factors facilitating borrowing of this&#13;
magnitude were the introduction of indexed debt instruments in the&#13;
mid-1960s; the establis'hment and subsequent growth of compulsory savings&#13;
funds such as PASEP, the Social Integration Program (PIS), and the Time of&#13;
Service Guarantee Fund (FGTS); the passage in 1976 of Senate Resolution 93,&#13;
which freed certain credit operations from pre-set limits (see page 13);&#13;
and the availability of a multitude of official, frequently subsidized,&#13;
credit lines for financing activities in water supply and sanit:ation, urban&#13;
transport, housing, social services, pre-investment studies, and so&#13;
forth. 17/&#13;
17/ The nature and terms of these credit lines are conveniently&#13;
summarized in two publications of the Ministry of Finance: Fontes de&#13;
Financiamentos aos Estados (Brasilia, November 1980) and Fontes de&#13;
Financiamentos aos Municipios (Brasflia, September 1980).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
Table 5&#13;
Selected Indicators of State (S) and Municipal (M) Finances, 1968-80&#13;
(%)&#13;
II. Investment     III. Deficit&#13;
I. Current Saving Ratio                Ratio            Ratio&#13;
Year           (a)                 (b)&#13;
S       M           S      M         S      M         S      M&#13;
1968      4.5   -147.5       17.2    33.6     26.8   44.7       -4.0   -5.9&#13;
1969      0.7   -147.7       12.7    27.7     29.1   41.1       -8.5   -7.1&#13;
1970      1.4   -135.5       16.4    30.5     30.2   41.0       -8.0   -2.1&#13;
1971      2.8   -137.3       15.8    28.1     29.4   40.0       -5.3   -1.1&#13;
1972      2.4   -145.7       14.7    25.3     32.4   39.3       -9.6   -7.4&#13;
1973      6.4   -143.6       19.5    26.0     34.7   37.7       -7.9   -5.3&#13;
1974      7.2   -134.8       20.4    28.7     37.6   44.7      -10.8  -13.4&#13;
1975     -5.0   -126.3       13.7    29.9     36.3   46.2      -16.6  -14.3&#13;
1976     -9.7      n.a.       8.9    n.a.     34.7    n.a.     -17.1    n.a.&#13;
1977     -2.5      n.a.      17.1     n.a.    35.6    n.a.      -9.2    n.a.&#13;
1978     -6.0      n.a.      13.7     n.a.    34.5    n.a.     -13.3    n.a.&#13;
1979    -14.6      n.a.       7.8     n.a.    29.0    n.a.     -12.8    n.a.&#13;
1980     -5.8      n.a.      15.2     n.a.    30.6    n.a.      -9.9    n.a.&#13;
Definitions:&#13;
Current Saving&#13;
Ratio          (a) = Own current revenues less current expenditures&#13;
divided by own current revenues.&#13;
(b) = Total current revenues less current expenditures&#13;
divided by current revenues.&#13;
Investment Ratio     = Capital expenditures divided by total expenditures.&#13;
Deficit Ratio        = Total revenues (excluding credit) less total&#13;
expenditures divided by total expenditures.&#13;
Note:  Data exclude decentralized agencies and public enterprises.&#13;
Only state share of ICM (80%) included in state "own current&#13;
revenues "*.&#13;
Source : Raw data provided by MinistArio da Fazenda, Secretaria de&#13;
Economia e Financas (MF/SEF).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
As of October 1931, the states' (excluding decentralized agencies&#13;
and public enterprises) total medium and long-term debt outstanding stood&#13;
at Cr.$952.5 billion (US$8.3 billion equivalent). The evolution cf this&#13;
debt since December 1977 is shown in Table 6. It may be observed that&#13;
state indebtedness increased by about 10% per year in constant prices&#13;
during the period, a rate considerably above the 3% annual rate of increase&#13;
in state revenues (net of borrowing). Though this would imply a rising&#13;
cebt service ratio, it is not possible, on the basis of the available data,&#13;
t.o judge conclusively whether future service payments will seriously impair&#13;
the states' capacity to meet other expenditure commitments. In addition to&#13;
projections of state revertues, such an analysis would require detailed&#13;
information on the terms of the debt outstanding (average maturities and&#13;
:nterest rates) and the nature of the projects for which the debt was&#13;
:Lncurred (e.g., whether these projects are self-financing, give rise to&#13;
siignificant recurrent cost:s).&#13;
Table 6&#13;
Structure of State Debt at Year End, 1977-81 a/&#13;
(Percent)&#13;
Components                1977     1978    1979     1980    1981&#13;
(Oct.)&#13;
Foreign                                 28.2    24.4     33.3    33.0     29.1&#13;
Domestic                                71.8    75.6     66.7    67.0     70.9&#13;
of which:&#13;
"Intralimit" b/                      (73.1)  (68.1)  (67.7)   (66.3)  (64.8)&#13;
"Extralimit" c/                      (26.9)  (31.9)   (33.3)  (33.7)  (35.2)&#13;
Total                                  100.0    100.0   100.0   100.0    100.0&#13;
(Cr.$ billions, Dec. 1980 prices)      361.1   425.7    542.9   465.4   533.6&#13;
a/ Excludes decentralized agencies and public enterprises.&#13;
b/ Contracted under rules of Senate Resolution 62 (1975).&#13;
c/ Contracted under rules of Senate Resolution 93 (1976).&#13;
Source : Banco Central&#13;
Principal Causes of the States' Fiscal Problems&#13;
Macroeconomic conditions. Owing to their dependence on taxes&#13;
related to production, sales and income (e.g., ICM, ISS, shares from the&#13;
IPI and IR), the revenue structures of both the states and munidcpios are&#13;
sensitive to changes in macroeconomic conditions. "Buoyancy coefficients"&#13;
calculated for the 1968-30 period (1968-75 in the case of the local&#13;
governments) are near unity (see Table 7 below). That is, for each&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
percentage-point change in GDP, state and local revenues changed by close&#13;
to a like amount. 18/&#13;
Table 7&#13;
Buoyancy of Revenues by Level of Government, 1968-80 a/&#13;
(Coefficients)&#13;
Level of                    Tax             Total&#13;
Government                 Revenues         Revenues b/&#13;
Federal                      0.97             0.95&#13;
State                        0.92             0.95&#13;
Municipal c/                  1.08            0.98&#13;
a/ Estimated on the basis of simple double logarithmic functions relating&#13;
revenues to GDP.&#13;
b/ Excludes borrowing.&#13;
c/ Data are for 1968-75 period.&#13;
Source: Raw data from MF/SEF.&#13;
As shown in Table 8, national economic growth rates were consid-&#13;
erably higher in the 1968/69-1973/74 period than in the latter part of the&#13;
1970s. Not surprisingly, this led to a reduction in the annual growth of&#13;
state revenues from an average of 9.8% in the late 1960s and early 1970s to&#13;
5.5% in the latter half of the decade. The states responded to this short-&#13;
fall in revenues by sharply curtailing total expenditures. However, the&#13;
data indicate that the states were far more successful at cutting invest-&#13;
ments than current expenditures (see Table 8).&#13;
Investment expenditures are, by their nature, easier to postpone&#13;
than current expenditures. But the two are frequently related. That is,&#13;
public investments made in one period give rise to associated recurrent&#13;
costs (e.g., salaries, maintenance) in a subsequent period. It may be&#13;
hypothesized, therefore, that the states' inability to cut current expendi-&#13;
tures in the latter part of the 1970s was related to the recurrent costs&#13;
gen&amp;rated by the high rates of investment observed earlier in the decade.&#13;
Though highly aggregated, the data in Table 8 generally support this hypo-&#13;
18/ The calculations presented in Table 7 suggest that the "conventional&#13;
wisdom" regarding the intergovernmental division of tax sources is&#13;
essentially correct ( page 16)--since 1968, federal taxes have been&#13;
more buoyant with respect to GDP than those allocated to the states.&#13;
Municipal taxes tended to be highly buoyant during the 1968-75 period,&#13;
but owing to a lack of data for recent years, a direct comparison with&#13;
the federal coefficient could not be made.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
thesis. The available data do not permit a linkage of operating costs to&#13;
specific types of investtaents. However, it seems reasonable to assume that&#13;
the burden of recurrent 0ost financing has been mst severe in states&#13;
emphasizing the social sectors, as investments in this area (e.g.,&#13;
education and health) are normally characterized by high&#13;
recurrent-to-investment cost ratios, and low levels of cost recovery. 19,&#13;
Table 8&#13;
Annual Growth Rates of State Revenues and Expenditures&#13;
and GDP, 1968/69 - 1979/80   a/&#13;
(%)&#13;
1968/69-      1968/69-     1973/74-&#13;
1979/80       1973/74      1979/80&#13;
Total Revenues   b/                          7.4           9.8          5.5&#13;
ICM Revenues                                 6.9           9.1         5.0&#13;
Total Expenditures                           8.0          10.5           5.9&#13;
Current Expenditures                         7.7           7.8           7.6&#13;
- Operating Costs (custeio)                7.3           6.3          8.1&#13;
- Transfers C/                             8.5          10.3          7.0&#13;
Capital Expenditures                         8.6          16.3           2.5&#13;
GDP                                          8.8          11.3           6.8&#13;
a/ Adjusted with GDP implicit deflator; data exclude decentralized&#13;
agencies and public enterprises.&#13;
b/  Excludes borrowing.&#13;
c/  Excludes transfer of ICM share (20%) to municlpios.&#13;
Source : Fiscal data are from MF/SEF; GDP data are from Getulio Vargas&#13;
Foundation (published in Conjuntura Economica)&#13;
In this respect, it is interesting to cite the case of Parana'&#13;
where, in the face of declining rates of revenue growth, chronic deficits&#13;
and recourse to borrowing have been largely avoided by a deliberate policy&#13;
of concentrating investments in physical infrastructure (mainly transport&#13;
and energy) so as to minimize subsequent pressures on current expendi-&#13;
tures. 20/ It is difficult to see, however, how this policy could have&#13;
19/  This issue is further explored in F.A. Rezende da Silva, "O&#13;
Financiamento da Polltica Social," Pesquisa e Planejamento Economico,&#13;
X, 1 (1980), 12:3-46.&#13;
20/  See Fundagao IPARDES, "Participa,a`o do Setor Pu'blico na Economia&#13;
Paranaense", Relatorio de Pesquisa No. 1 (Curitiba, January 1980).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
22 -&#13;
been emulated by many other states, especially the poorer ones. In&#13;
contrast to the poorer states, Parana has maintained a low dependence on&#13;
federal transfers (7.8% of total revenues in 1978 versus about 20% for all&#13;
states), which has given the state considerable freedom to determine its&#13;
own sectoral allocation of investment expenditures, coupled with a very low&#13;
rate of population growth (0.96% p.a. in 1970-80 versus 2.48% p.a. for&#13;
Brazil as a whole), which has restrained the demand for social services.&#13;
Legislative changes. The erosion of the ICM base through a&#13;
series of legislative reforms has compounded the adverse effect on state&#13;
and local finances. 21/ One of these reforms was the decision of the&#13;
federal government tColower gradually the rate of the ICM. Starting in&#13;
1970, the rate on intrastate transactions was reduced by 0.5% per year from&#13;
17% in the Center-South (18% in the North/Northeast) to 14% in 1976 (15% in&#13;
the North/Northeast). It stayed at these levels until 1980 when the rate&#13;
was raised by one percentage point. In 1982, the ICM rate on intrastate&#13;
transactions was set at a uniform 16% for all regions.&#13;
Another source of tax base erosion has been the intensive use of&#13;
the 1CM for purposes of stimulating exports and for subsidizing certain&#13;
projects of "national interest". Incentives of the first type were&#13;
established during the late 1960s and early 1970s. Until 1979, they were&#13;
comprised of three elements: direct exemption, indirect exemption and a&#13;
subsidy. 22/ Direct exemptions from the ICM for manufactured exports were&#13;
provided for in the 1967 Constitution, but these were limited to the final&#13;
stage of production. Starting in 1971, however, exporting firms were&#13;
permitted a direct exemption, plus a credit (which could be applied to the&#13;
firms' other ICM liabilities) equal to the ICM paid at previous stages of&#13;
production. In the same year, the incentive mechanism was further expanded&#13;
to include a subsidy element (the so-called credito-pr^mio) in the form of&#13;
an additional ICM credit expressed as a percentage of the firm's FOB export&#13;
value. 23/ The subsidy to projects of "national interest" was established&#13;
in 19757. In essence, it provides that inputs to projects deemed high&#13;
priority by the federal government are exempt from the ICM. During recent&#13;
years, such projects have been concentrated in the telecommunications,&#13;
power and steel sectors.&#13;
21/ Some legislative changes passed during the 1970s directly benefitted&#13;
the states and munic:pios. The portions of the IR and IPI to be&#13;
deposited in the Participation Funds, for example, increased from 12%&#13;
to 20% between 1970 and 1979, and the earmarking of shares from these&#13;
funds was virtually eliminated in the latter part of the period (see&#13;
pages 10-12).&#13;
22/ W.G. Tyler, Manufactured Export Expansion and Industrialization in&#13;
Brazil (J.C. B. Mohr: Tubingen, 1976), pp. 210-12.&#13;
231 Until 1977, the states were expected to bear the full fiscal burden&#13;
of the cr6dito-premio. In 1977, the federal government absorbed 50%&#13;
of the burden, and in the following year the ICM credito-premio was&#13;
abolished.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
A quantification of ICM revenues foregone as a result of legis-&#13;
Lative changes is difficult because of data limitations and methodological&#13;
,roblems.  However, such an exercise was carried out for Sao Paulo (which&#13;
accounts for about 45% of total ICM collections) by the state's Finance&#13;
Secretariat. 24/ Accord:Lng to these calculations, about Cr$ 761 billion&#13;
in 1980 prices TUS$14.4 billion) were lost through ICM rate changes and&#13;
various exemptions during the 1972-80 period. This is equivalent to about&#13;
37% of the total ICM revenues effectively collected in Sao Paulo.     The&#13;
revenue losses via exemptions (Cr$513 billion) were found to be consider-&#13;
ably more important than those accounted for by changes in the IM rate&#13;
(Cr$248 billion).&#13;
Though declines in the ICM rates mDst likely resulted in real&#13;
revenue losses for the states, the purported shortfall caused by export&#13;
incentives and the exemptions given to inputs to priority projects is&#13;
probably exaggerated. First, the Sao Paulo study implicitly assumes that&#13;
all tax-exempt products would have been exported even in the absence of the&#13;
fiscal incentives. This is a dubious assumption. Second, the study does&#13;
not take into account the multiplier effects of increased production&#13;
(either for export or for use in priority projects) which induce economic&#13;
activity and hence help raise the tax base in other segments of the&#13;
economy. These same criticisms also apply to the argument that reductions&#13;
in the income tax and IP'E awarded to exporting firms have adversely&#13;
affected state and local finances by reducing the funds available for&#13;
redistribution through the Participation Funds.&#13;
Administrative aspects. Another aspect of the current fiscal&#13;
problems of the states, closely linked to macroeconomic conditions and&#13;
legislative changes, is the process of budgetary fragmentation. 25/ The&#13;
central argument here is that the responsibility for investment E-s become&#13;
increasingly assumed by state-level decentralized agencies and public&#13;
enterprises, leading to a loss of control over expenditures by the state&#13;
finance secretariats. The growing relative importance of the decentralized&#13;
sector is attributed to the decline in the states' capacity to finance&#13;
investments from their own-source revenues, and the consequent need to&#13;
secure resources through federally-controlled grants and credit lines.&#13;
Rather than pass these funds to the state budgets, the federal government&#13;
has preferred to channe]. them to state-level decentralized agencies or&#13;
enterprises (state road departments-DERs, power companies, housing&#13;
companies-COHABs, rural extension companies-EMATERs, collective transport&#13;
companies, etc.) with counterparts at the national level (DNER,&#13;
24/  A.C. Pastore, "Avaliac,o Critica da Reforma Tributaria de 1965,"&#13;
Revista de Financas Publicas, XLI, 348 (1981), 4-32.&#13;
25/ This issue is mDre fully explored in: F.A. Rezende da Silva,&#13;
"Autonomia Polftica e Depende^ncia Financeira:   Uma Analise das&#13;
Transforma,es Recentes nas Relap"es Intergovernamentais e seus&#13;
Reflexos sobre a Situa,co Financeira dos Estados", Pesquisa e&#13;
Planejamento Econc,mico, XII, 2 (1982), 489-540.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
ELETROBRAS, BNH, EMBRATER, EBTU, respectively). 26/    Through this process,&#13;
effective control over investment decisions in many sectors has passed from&#13;
the states to the federal government.&#13;
What are the major implications of the administrative transforma-&#13;
tions described above? First, they have significantly modified the tradi-&#13;
tional concept of planning at the state level. Ideally, planning requires&#13;
reasonably accurate projections of available investment funds, and a selec-&#13;
tion of various investment options based on their respective economic rates&#13;
of return. In constrast, the present system revolves around negotiations&#13;
for federal funds--negotiations in which the states, because of their&#13;
precarious fiscal situations, find themselves in inferior bargaining posi-&#13;
tions. The amount of investment funds to be available, therefore, has&#13;
become difficult to predict, and specific sectors or projects to benefit&#13;
from these funds are more apt to reflect national priorities than those of&#13;
the states.&#13;
Second, the loss of control by the states over investment deci-&#13;
sions has reduced their control over recurrent costs. In agreeing to&#13;
accept federal funds for investments, the states assume responsibility for&#13;
the subsequent operation and maintenance of the resulting projects. Since&#13;
the operational revenues of many decentralized agencies do not cover their&#13;
expenditures, this implies increasing levels of intragovernmental trans-&#13;
fers, not only to cover these agencies' operating and maintenance costs,&#13;
but to service their debt as well. 27/ This, in turn, sets the stage for a&#13;
further deterioration of the states' central budgets on current account,&#13;
and the continuation of the present dependence on the federal government&#13;
for new investment funds.&#13;
26/ The data indicate that, while the growth of investment expenditures&#13;
made through the state budgets declined abruptly after 1974 (see&#13;
Table 8), the opposite occurred with respect to the state decentral-&#13;
ized agencies. Investment expenditures of the latter grew at 2.9%&#13;
p.a. in the 1970-75 period, accelerating to 19.8% p.a. during&#13;
1975-78. Ibid. p.77.&#13;
27/ The summary fiscal accounts of state-level decentralized agencies&#13;
(fundacoes and autarquias) for 1978 are as follows (millions of 1978&#13;
cruzeiros):&#13;
(a)  Total Non-Debt Revenues                 Cr$ 97,123.4&#13;
(b)  (operational revenues)                     (30,302.3)&#13;
(c)  (state budget transfers)                   (58,494.7)&#13;
(d)  (other transfers)                          ( 8,326.4)&#13;
(e)  Total Expenditures                         106,454.7&#13;
(f)  Operational Deficit (b)-(e)               - 76,152.4&#13;
(g)  Net Deficit (a)-(e)                       -  9,331.3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
Problems of Municipal Resource Mobilization&#13;
Municipal governments are financially the weakest of Brazil's&#13;
three levels of government, accounting for only about 4% of public sector&#13;
tax collections. However, municipal own-source tax revenues grew rapidly&#13;
during the years of the: Brazilian economic "miracle". Property tax&#13;
revenues averaged 17% real growth per year between 1968 and 1975; service&#13;
tax revenues grew by 28% annually. Relative to growth in GDP, the buoyancy&#13;
of tax revenues was above unity, as shown in Table 7. (Data on revenue&#13;
growth during the subsequent economic downturn are not available).&#13;
Despite the Lmpressive gains of the 1968-75 period (albeit&#13;
reflecting to some extent the low bases upon which the revenue growth rates&#13;
were calculated), Brazil's relative dependence on property taxation is&#13;
still the lowest of any country in Latin America (comparable data on the&#13;
taxation of services are not available). As of the late 1970s, only 0.13%&#13;
of total public revenues came from this source. This may be compared with&#13;
the analogous ratios for Argentina (2.25%), Chile (2.49%), Mexico (0.89%)&#13;
and Peru (5.58%). 28/ Brazil, with a per capita GDP of US$1,160 in 1975,&#13;
collected just US$5.00 per capita in property taxes from its urban popula-&#13;
tion. Excluding the country's seven largest municipios, which dominate&#13;
local tax collections, property tax revenues averaged US$2.70 per urban&#13;
resident.&#13;
There are three potential barriers to further increases in&#13;
property taxation: (i) federal legal restrictions, (ii) municipal&#13;
administrative capacit:y, and (iii) political pressures. The case for&#13;
federal restrictions as a major constraint on the yield of the property tax&#13;
is weak. Though the exemption of rural property reduces the tax base&#13;
accessible to rural municipios, there are few other controls on the&#13;
taxation of property ( page 8). 29/ The cause of the low yield of the&#13;
property tax lies more in'-the inability or unwillingness of municipal&#13;
governments to exploit the tax bases at hand.&#13;
Tax administration. The low yield of the property tax is, to a&#13;
large extent, attributable to poor tax administration. Property cadastres&#13;
often fail to include recent subdivisions, building improvements or new&#13;
construction, and land and building assessments are frequentLy years out&#13;
of date. (Municfpios as large as Campinas--with a population of 660,000--&#13;
make no systematic attempt to update their property cadastres; relying&#13;
instead upon requests for building permits or subdivision approvals to&#13;
trigger a reassessment.) Uncollected tax bills also reduce the effective&#13;
revenues from the property tax. In Campinas, the value of unpaid property&#13;
28/ International Monetary Fund, Government Finance Statistics Yearbook,&#13;
VI (1982).&#13;
29/ Municipal governments are entitled to an 80% share of the federal&#13;
graduated tax on rural property (imposto territorial rural - ITR).&#13;
However, the prLmary function of this tax is to promote more intensive&#13;
cultivation of Idle or underutilized land, not to raise revenue. The&#13;
potential contribution of the ITR to local finances is therefore&#13;
limited.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
tax bills exceeds the annual revenues of the tax. Revenues are also kept&#13;
low for political reasons (pp. 27-28).Nominal tax rates are typically 1%&#13;
on land, and 0.5% on buildings. The ratio of assessed value to market&#13;
value is often deliberately kept low (if it is known at all), resulting in&#13;
effective rates of taxation of a few tenths of a percent.&#13;
In an effort to improve municipal tax administration, the federal&#13;
Finance Ministry in 1974 established Project CIATA (Convenio de Incentivo&#13;
ao Aperfei,oamento Tecnico-Administrativo das Municipalidades), a joint&#13;
federal-state-municipal program of technical assistance. The program&#13;
focuses on smaller municipalities, selected by mutual agreement of the&#13;
state and municipal governments, and consists of five components:&#13;
(i) revision of the municipal tax code (based on model&#13;
legislation prepared by the federal government);&#13;
(ii) creation or revision of the municipal property cadastre to&#13;
include all land and buildings subject to property&#13;
taxation, and identify lots served with public lighting,&#13;
garbage collection or other municipal services subject to&#13;
user charges;&#13;
(iii)  creation or revision of the municipal economic cadastre,&#13;
identifying business as subject to service taxation and&#13;
municipal licensing fees (optional);&#13;
(iv) property assessment based upon locally derived land and&#13;
building value assessment factors; and&#13;
(v) processing of cadastre and assessment actions, preparation&#13;
of bills, processing of tax returns and fines for late&#13;
payments.&#13;
The first four components are funded largely by grants from the federal&#13;
Finance Ministry. Data processing, billing, supervision and collection of&#13;
debt--as well as subsequent maintenance of the cadastre--are the financial&#13;
responsibility of municipal, and in some cases, state governments. Staff-&#13;
ing typically consists of a team of federal technicians, with counterparts&#13;
from the municipal government involved for purposes of training.&#13;
CIATA has had an immediate and dramatic effect on municipal&#13;
revenues. As shown in Table 9, revenues from the urban property tax and&#13;
related surcharges averaged a real increase of over 100% in municfpios&#13;
taking part in the program between 1976 and 1978. Though comprehensive&#13;
data on the impact of CIATA are not available, there is general agreement&#13;
among Brazilian sources that the program's principal product is a more&#13;
comprehensive and accurate property cadastre and a mDre efficient billing&#13;
system. The effective taxation of property owners who previously evaded&#13;
the IPTU through unrecorded building improvements or increases in land&#13;
values, or by administrative errors in billing, is the principal source of&#13;
revenue growth attributable to CIATA.&#13;
CIATA does not induce an increase in nominal tax rates. Yields&#13;
per capita, therefore, remain relatively low after CIATA assistance. As&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
ahown in Table 9, revenues per urban resident averaged only US$3.32 among&#13;
aunic1pios having received CIATA assistance in 1978.      Relative to the&#13;
yield of the tax, the cost of CIATA assistance is high. CIATA officials&#13;
estimate that revisions of property cadastres cost about US$11.00 per unit&#13;
cadastred. The impact of the technical assistance is also reportedly&#13;
short-lived. Federal officials report they are already returning to&#13;
municfpios covered in the mid-70s to repeat the entire process. In Paranl,&#13;
where the state now pays for processing costs, local officials reported&#13;
they would not be able tc sustain the present level of tax administration&#13;
if state aid were withdrawn.&#13;
Table 9&#13;
Impact of CIATA on Municipal Revenues, 1976-78&#13;
-----Year of Program&#133;-----&#13;
1976       1977       19713&#13;
Yield in preceding year (US$000)        376.00      522.00   1,107.00&#13;
Yield per capita (US$)                    0.95        0.87       1.53&#13;
Yield in year of program (US$000)       749.00    1,234.00   2,397.00&#13;
Yield per capita (US$)                    1.89        2.08       3.32&#13;
Percent increase in yield                98.9%      139.0%     117.0%&#13;
Municipios in program (no.)              21          21         35&#13;
Notes:    Yield includes only property tax and related surcharges.     Data&#13;
are for municfpios listed in Minist£rio da Fazenda, "Projeto&#13;
CIATA" (mimeo). Per capita figures are calculated from 1980&#13;
urban population. Cruzeiros converted by average official&#13;
exchange rates.&#13;
Given the low nominal rates that prevail even after ClATA, and&#13;
the rapid decay in its effect, the cost effectiveness of the program is&#13;
questionable. Data are not available to permit an accurate calculation of&#13;
the rate of return for the program as a whole. Using the existing data on&#13;
average cost per unit and average increase in yields, it is difficult to&#13;
arrive at a positive internal rate of return for the program with any&#13;
reasonable assumptions regarding duration of impact and costs and yields&#13;
without CIATA, even counting all increases in municipal revenues as net&#13;
social benefits.&#13;
Political constraints. The above discussion suggests that&#13;
technical assistance alone is not a solution to the low yield of municipal&#13;
taxes. Political constraints discourage municipal tax effort, even when&#13;
technical problems are resolved. Three factors put the municfp i at a&#13;
disadvantage in the competition for public resources:&#13;
(i)  The imayor and city council are directly elected officials&#13;
and are the most accessible targets for complaints over&#13;
high taxation. State governors (until November 1982) and&#13;
the president have been appointed or indirectly elected,&#13;
in contrast, and are politically more isolat:ed from the&#13;
taxpayers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
(ii)  The property tax is a direct tax in a country with a&#13;
tradition of indirect taxation. Two thirds of federal&#13;
taxes, and 98% of state taxes are indirect; part of their&#13;
incidence being passed from the point of collection on to&#13;
consumers in the form of higher prices. To the extent&#13;
consumers remain unaware of the source of higher prices,&#13;
indirect taxation is a politically innocuous source of&#13;
revenues. The municipal services tax is also an indirect&#13;
tax, which partly accounts for its rapid growth. The&#13;
property tax, as a direct tax (except when passed on by&#13;
landlords and businesses in the form of higher rents or&#13;
product prices), is a conspicuous exception to the&#13;
Brazilian tax system and is therefore politically&#13;
difficult to impose.&#13;
(iii)  Because of municipal dependence on transfers, an increase&#13;
in tax effort has little impact on the ability of&#13;
municipal governments to provide services. Property taxes&#13;
account for only 11% of non-debt revenues of all Brazilian&#13;
municfpios, and only 7% of the revenues of municipios with&#13;
populations of under one million. As none of the transfer&#13;
formulas reward tax effort, a doubling of property tax&#13;
effort would increase municipal current revenues by only&#13;
11% (Table 10). Excluding municfpios with over a million&#13;
inhabitants, a doubling of local tax effort, with its&#13;
political costs, would only increase the funds available&#13;
by 7%.&#13;
Table 10&#13;
Hypothetical Impact of Doubled Property Tax Effort&#13;
on Municipal Current Revenues&#13;
(millions of 1975 cruzeiros)&#13;
All           Large          Smaller&#13;
Municipios     Municfpios a/  Municfpios&#13;
Property tax revenues b/              5,265.0         3,191.4        2,073.6&#13;
Service tax revenues                  2,597.1         1,792.2          804.9&#13;
Charges                               1,814.1           724.6        1,089.5&#13;
All other local current revenue       2,580.2           819.0        1,760.9&#13;
Transfers                            14,358.0         4,319.5       10,038.8&#13;
Total                                26,614.4        10,846.7       15,767.7&#13;
Percent increase c/                     11%             17%            7%&#13;
a/ Seven municfpios with populations over 1 million in 1975.&#13;
b/ Represents twice the amount actually collected in 1975.&#13;
c/ Increase of hypothetical total current revenues over actual revenues.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
V. SPATIAI VARIATIONS IN REVENUES AND EXPENDITURES:&#13;
TEE QUESTION OF HORIZONTAL BALANCE&#13;
Regional variations in the correspondence between revenue bases&#13;
and expenditure requirements exist in all federal systems. Wealthy tax&#13;
bases are often concentrated in industrial areas, while expenditure&#13;
requirements can be higher in rural areas where the population is&#13;
dispersed, and where greater backlogs exist in the provision of physical&#13;
and social infrastructure. Ideally, interregional flows of labor and&#13;
capital would eliminate regional disparities. However, the persistence of&#13;
such disparities in most parts of the world testifies to the inadequacy of&#13;
these flows as a short- or medium-term solution to the problem. Most&#13;
federal systems are, therefore, forced to use intergovernmental transfers&#13;
as a means to assure an adequate level of public services in poor regions.&#13;
The problem of horizontal balance is particularly iraportant in&#13;
Brazil, owing to the scale of economic disparities. The revenue bases of&#13;
state governments vary widely between the country's major economic&#13;
regions. The revenue bases of municipal governments vary not only among&#13;
economic regions, but between industrial and rural areas of each state.&#13;
This section examines two issues of horizontal balance: (i) the impact of&#13;
public policy in reducing regional disparities in state and local tax&#13;
collections; and (ii) the effectiveness of federal intergovernmental&#13;
transfers in reducing spatial disparities in total resources available to&#13;
state and local governments.&#13;
Regional Economic Disparities 30/&#13;
Regional economic disparities are wide in Brazil. The&#13;
Southeast's highly urbanized, industrialized economic base dominates the&#13;
rest of the country. With 60% of the national population, the Southeast&#13;
accounts for over 80% of Brazil's GNP. Gross regional product (GRP) per&#13;
capita is more than twice the national average. Sixty percent of south-&#13;
easterners live in cities of over 20,000 and nearly 40% live in metropo-&#13;
litan agglomerations of over a million. The labor force in engaged primar-&#13;
ily in services (43%) and manufacturing, construction and utilities (28%).&#13;
Northeast B3razil, in contrast, is predominantly rural, agricul-&#13;
tural, and poor. Two-thirds of the population live in rural areas or in&#13;
towns with less than 20,000 inhabitants. Fifty-five percent of the labor&#13;
force is engaged in agriculture, and only 16% in manufacturing, construc-&#13;
tion, and utilities. Labor productivity is low in all sectors of the&#13;
economy, but particularly in agriculture, where it is less than a third of&#13;
that of the Southeast. Per capita gross regional product (1970 US$138) is&#13;
well under half the national average.&#13;
30/  For purposes of the present analysis, Brazil is divided into three&#13;
regions: "Southeast" (comprised of Minas Gerais, Espfrito Santo, Rio&#13;
de Janeiro, Sa'o Paulo, Paranl, Santa Catarina and Rio Grande do Sul);&#13;
"Northeast" (Maranhao, Piaui, Cearl, Rio Grande do Norte, Paralba,&#13;
Pernambuco, Alagoas, Sergipe and Bahia); and "Frontier" (Rond8nia,&#13;
Acre, Amazonas, Roraima, Pare, Amapd, Mato Grosso and Goias). See&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
The interior of Brazil -- the Frontier -- is sparsely populated.&#13;
Like the Northeast, the Frontier is predominantly rural and agricultural.&#13;
Roughly one-third of the population live in towns of over 20,000; a figure&#13;
which falls to 25% with the exclusion of Brasflia. Two-thirds of the labor&#13;
force is engaged in agriculture, and only 10% in manufacturing, construc-&#13;
tion and utilities.    Population pressures are much less severe in the&#13;
Frontier than in the Northeast, however, and per capita indicators of&#13;
economic activity are generally higher. Gross regional product per capita&#13;
is (1970 US$221); well below the per capita GRP of the Southeast, but above&#13;
that of the Northeast. Average labor productivity in agriculture and&#13;
services also falls between the figures for the Northeast and Southeast,&#13;
though industrial productivity in the Frontier region is about equal to&#13;
that of the Northeast.&#13;
Revenues, Expenditures and Public Service Indicators&#13;
Wide variations in the economic conditions of different parts of&#13;
Brazil are paralleled by disparities in the revenues and expenditures of&#13;
their respective state and local governments. However, the impact of&#13;
regional disparities in government finances on the quality of public&#13;
services is difficult to document statistically. The available indicators&#13;
-- school attendance, infant mortality, levels of access to certain&#13;
services -- reflect the ability of residents to exploit public services as&#13;
well as the ability of governments to provide them. Particularly in&#13;
functions that are financed in part through user charges, low levels of use&#13;
may reflect the inability of residents to pay fees, as much as the poverty&#13;
of their governments. The complex nature of the Brazilian fiscal system&#13;
also limits any simple correlation between state and local finances on the&#13;
one hand, and public service quality on the other. Nevertheless, a link&#13;
between the two is evident in Table 11.&#13;
The marked regional disparities in per capita revenues are shown&#13;
at the top of the Table. State governments in the richest region, the&#13;
Southeast, take in three times as much per capita as the state governments&#13;
of the poorest region, the Northeast. The disparity in revenues between&#13;
state capitals and the interior municlpios of each region is equally wide.&#13;
The southeastern capitals take in 2.8 times the per capita revenues of&#13;
northeastern capitals; and southeastern interior municlpios, over four&#13;
times the revenues of their northeastern counterparts. Within each region,&#13;
the per capita revenues of interior municipios are well below the average&#13;
of each region's capitals. The poorest class of municfpios is, therefore,&#13;
the interior municfpios of the Northeast; the richest, the capital&#13;
municipios of the Southeast. These disparities are reflected to varying&#13;
degrees in the list of public service indicators.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
Table 11&#13;
State and Municipal Revenues and Public Service Indicators by Region,&#13;
Hid-1970s&#13;
Indicator                  --------- -Region--------------&#13;
Southeast   Northeast   Frontier&#13;
Revenues per capita, 1975 Cr$&#13;
State government                        Cr$ 1025    Cr$   312    Cr$ 717&#13;
Municipal government&#13;
Capitals                                    703         248        244&#13;
Interior                                    243          57         84&#13;
Percent eligible populatlion,&#13;
1976, attending:&#13;
Primary school&#13;
Urban                                        69          57         63&#13;
Rural                                        52          27        n.a.&#13;
Secondary school&#13;
Urban                                        20          12         12&#13;
Rural                                         3           1        n.a.&#13;
Percent qualified primry school&#13;
teachers - , 1978&#13;
Urban                                        99          93         95&#13;
Rural                                        75          31         34&#13;
Hospital beds per thousand&#13;
population, 1976&#13;
Capitals                                      9.7         1.3        6.7&#13;
Interior                                      3.6         1.2        1.4&#13;
Infant mortality, 1978, per thousand&#13;
Metro and non-metro capitals                   70         124        n.a.&#13;
All other municfpioa;                          63         127        n.a.&#13;
Percent urban househo'lds, 1978 with:&#13;
Water network connection&#13;
Metro                                        77          52         85&#13;
Non-metro                                    79          57         58&#13;
Sewer network connection&#13;
Metro                                        50          20         35&#13;
Non-metro                                    49           8         10&#13;
Electricity&#13;
Metro                                        95          81.        58&#13;
Non-metro                                    90          68        n.a.&#13;
Frequent garbage collection b/&#13;
Metro                                        62          23         58&#13;
Non-metro                                    53          16        n.a.&#13;
a/ Defined as having at least primary school degree.&#13;
b/  Defined as 3 or more times per week.&#13;
n.a. - not available.&#13;
Sources:  Revenues per capita:  MF/SEF, unpublished computer listings.&#13;
Education:            Ministerio de Educacao e Cultura, Ensino de&#13;
Primeira Grau-Sbntese Retrospectiva, 1981.&#13;
Hospitals:            IBGE, Estatisticas da Sadde, 1976.&#13;
Infant Mortality:     IBGE, Anudrio Estatistico, 1980.&#13;
Householda:           IBGE, Metodologia da PNAD, 1981.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-32 -&#13;
State and local per capita expenditures on social services are&#13;
closely correlated with per capita revenues. The Northeast, with the&#13;
lowest per capita revenues (and poorest public service indicators) among&#13;
the regions, also lags well behind the rest of Brazil with regard to the&#13;
volume of public resources devoted to education and health. As shown in&#13;
Table 12, per pupil education expenditures and per capita health&#13;
expenditures in this region are only about 45% of the national average, and&#13;
35% of the Southeast average. Although the cost of providing health and&#13;
education services undoubtedly differs among the regions, it is certain&#13;
that most of the variation in expenditure levels represents differences in&#13;
service quality, coverage or both. 31/ The federal government, by&#13;
targeting its own education and health expenditures on the poorer regions,&#13;
could help narrow these qualitative and quantitative gaps. The available&#13;
data, however, suggest that the regional distribution of such expenditures,&#13;
by favoring the Southeast, might have widened them.&#13;
Table 12&#13;
State and Municipal Expenditures on Education&#13;
and Health by Region, 1975 a/&#13;
(current Cr$)&#13;
b/&#13;
Education                        Health-&#13;
Region                Cr$           Index             Cr$              Index&#13;
(per pupil)    (Brazil=100)    (per capita)     (Brazil=100)&#13;
Southeast           1,196.1          126             111.1             133&#13;
Northeast             418.5           44              37.8               45&#13;
Frontier              642.0           68              49.7               60&#13;
BRAZIL                951.3          100              83.5              100&#13;
a/   After intergovernmental transfers.&#13;
Includes sanitation.&#13;
Sources: MF/SEF, Finan,as do Brasil, Vol. XXIII (Brasilia, 1981) for&#13;
expenditures; IBGE, Metodologia da Pesquisa Nacional por Amostra&#13;
de Domicflios na DScada de 1970 (Rio de Janeiro, 1981) for&#13;
enrollment data; 1975 population estimated from 1970-80 trends.&#13;
31/ In 1975, the minimum wage (a crude proxy for regional differences in&#13;
the cost of living) prevailing in the Southeast was only 40% higher&#13;
than that prevailing in the Northeast.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
Sources of Variation in State Revenues&#13;
Value-added l:ax (ICM). Economic disparities explain most of the&#13;
variation in the per capita yield of the ICM. Table 13 compares ICM&#13;
revenues with gross regional products, aggregating the states into three&#13;
economic regions. (All regional averages are weighted by population). As&#13;
these data show, the states of the Southeast take in over five times as&#13;
much per capita as the states of the Northeast, and roughly four times as&#13;
much as the frontier states. This represents a considerably wider varia-&#13;
tion than exists in per capita GRP where the ratio among the t:hree regions&#13;
is roughly 1-to-3.5-to-2.5. The yield of the ICM is equal to 8% of GRP in&#13;
the Southeast, but only 5% of GSP in the Northeast and the Frontier.&#13;
Table 13&#13;
Gross Regional Product (GRP) and ICM Revenues, 1970&#13;
(Current Cr$)&#13;
Region&#13;
Southeast    Northeast   Frontier&#13;
GRP per capita (Cr.$)                       2,218         622         872&#13;
ICM revenues per capita (Cr.$)                174          33          44&#13;
ICM revenues as percent of GRP                7.9%        5.3%        5.2%&#13;
Note:      Table excludes Federal District and Territories.    ICM revenues&#13;
include only state government share, and were adjusted from raw&#13;
SEF data based on the accounting practices of each state as&#13;
indicated in the 1975 data.&#13;
Sources : Regional Accounts: Fundarlo Getulio Vargas.&#13;
ICM Revenues: MF/SEF.&#13;
Federal policy is a major determinant of ICM yields and should,&#13;
in principle, explain the disproportionately low yield of the tax in poorer&#13;
states. In broad terms, the federal government defines the legal base of&#13;
the ICM as the value added in agriculture, industry and commerce. This&#13;
definition works against the states of the poorer regions. In excluding&#13;
services and transportation from the definition, the ICM base excludes&#13;
sectors that constitute a relatively large share of the economies of the&#13;
northeastern and frontier states. Sectors taxable by the ICM constitute&#13;
about 60% of the economy of the Southeast, but only about 54% of the&#13;
economy of the Northeast and 56% of the Frontier economy.&#13;
The higher proportion of taxable sectors in the economy of the&#13;
Southeast is partly compensated for by a quirk in Brazil's t:ax system.&#13;
Brazil uses the "credit" method to calculate ICM liabilities. That is, a&#13;
firm's ICM bill is equal to the tax rate applied to the total value of&#13;
sales, minus a credit equal to the ICM paid by suppliers on inputs&#13;
purchased by the firm. This method is equivalent to the traditional sub-&#13;
traction method (tax rate applied to the difference between sales receipts&#13;
and input costs), as long as all inputs are taxed at the same rate. If an&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
input is tax exempt, however, the firm has fewer credits to apply to its&#13;
tax liability. In this way, a part of the value of sectors legally exempt&#13;
from the ICM are captured by overtaxation of other sectors, but not all of&#13;
the exempted tax base is fully recovered. Services provided to final&#13;
demand, rather than as inputs to agriculture, industry, or commerce remain&#13;
exempt. Silva and Silva's study of the ICM estimated the taxable&#13;
value-added in industry and commerce to be about 20X higher than the true-&#13;
value added in these sectors, however suggesting that a large share of&#13;
exempted value-added is recaptured. 3_/&#13;
The federally-decreed ICM tax rates also fail to explain the&#13;
disproportionately low yields in the Northeast and Frontier. The schedule&#13;
of ICM rates now applies uniformly to all states, although in earlier&#13;
periods slightly higher rates were applied in poorer regions. The rate&#13;
schedule is, however, differentiated according to the destination of sales&#13;
in a way that increases the revenues of Northeast and Frontier states.&#13;
Current ICM legislation requires that sales across state lines be taxed at&#13;
rates substantially below the rate for intrastate sales. This reduces the&#13;
ICM paid by exporting firms to their respective state governments for&#13;
interstate sales. By the same token, it reduces the amount importing firms&#13;
can credit to their gross ICM liability.   As Sao Paulo is usually the only&#13;
net exporter of ICM-taxable goods, it is the government of this state which&#13;
bears the loss in potential revenues from the lower tax rate applied to&#13;
interstate trade. The Northeast and Frontier regions, as well as net&#13;
importing states in the Southeast, experience proportionate gains.&#13;
Given data constraints, it is not possible to calculate the&#13;
degree to which the differential taxation of interstate trade inflates the&#13;
tax base of states that are net importers. The size of the trade deficits&#13;
in the Northeast and Frontier regions, and the substantial difference in&#13;
rates (interstate rates in the poorer regions are now 45% higher than rates&#13;
for interstate sales originating in the Southeast), suggests that the&#13;
contribution of differential taxation to the revenues of governments in&#13;
poorer regions is substantial. 33/ Nevertheless, it has been estimated&#13;
that between 1969 and 1974 the Wortheastern states had their ICM&#13;
collections reduced by 20% because of the essentially origin-based&#13;
criterion for assessing this tax. 34/&#13;
Problems of tax administration appear to explain best the dispro-&#13;
portionately low yield of the ICM in the Northeast and Frontier. The&#13;
predominance of sectors that are inherently difficult to tax, and the&#13;
"slippery" nature of the northeastern and frontier economies in general,&#13;
limit the effective tax base of poorer states. Silva and Silva, describe&#13;
it) in effect, as a tax on industrial production and the distribution of&#13;
industrial products. Though the legal tax base extends to agricultural&#13;
products and their distribution, agricultural value-added has proved&#13;
extremely difficult to tax. The low taxation of agriculture is partly due&#13;
to federally-required exemptions that carry through to final demand. Milk,&#13;
eggs, and fresh fruits and vegetables, for&#13;
32/ Silva and Silva, op. cit., Ch. IV.&#13;
33/ In 1978, the Northeast ran a deficit of Cr$55 billion on taxable trade&#13;
of Cr$131 billion with the Southeast; the Frontier's deficit with the&#13;
Southeast totalled Cr$28 billion out of a total Cr$94 billion.&#13;
34/ C.A. Longo, "Controvgrsias sobre o ICM no Comercio Interstadual:&#13;
Uma Resenha", Pesquisa e Planejamento Economico, XI, 1 (1981), p. 246.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
example, are all exempt 1rom the ICM at all stages of production and&#13;
distribution. The share of farmers' crops consumed on farm are also, de&#13;
facto, exempt. The small scale and often non-mon_=t4zed nature of Brazilian&#13;
agriculture also makes il: subject to evasion.&#13;
The relatively low yield of ICM taxation of agri( ilture is&#13;
illustrated in Table 14. The table compares the percentage oi 1CM&#13;
collected from agriculture, industry, and commerce with the share of each&#13;
sector in gross state product (GSP). (In calculating shares of gross state&#13;
product, sectors not subject to the ICM are excluded). In four of the five&#13;
states for which data are available, the share of ICM collections from the&#13;
agricultural sector are below agriculture's share of taxable GSP. In Sao&#13;
Paulo -- the extreme case -- agriculture represents 8% of the GSP, but only&#13;
0.1% of ICM revenues. More typically, agriculture's share of D2M revenues&#13;
is only half its share cf taxable GSP. The difficulty of taxing agricul-&#13;
ture is particularly onerous to the northeastern and frontier states. In&#13;
the Southeast, agriculture is a relatively small proportion of the taxable&#13;
base. In the poorer states, however, it represents roughly 40% of the tax&#13;
base eligible for ICM taxation. The loss from untaxed agriculture thus&#13;
falls disproportionately on the poorer states.&#13;
Industry, on the other hand, is more readily taxed and, with the&#13;
exception of Mato Grosso, is consistently overrepresented in ICM revenues.&#13;
The share of industry in ICM revenues is roughly 5% higher than its share&#13;
of gross state product in the Northeast, and 15% higher than its share of&#13;
state product in the Southeast. Commerce, similarly, is overrepresented in&#13;
the ICM revenues of most states, excluding Mato Grosso and Sawo Paulo.&#13;
The tax collection problems of the Northeast and Frontier may be&#13;
institutional as well as sectoral. Silva and Silva's analysis suggests&#13;
that the yield of ICM per cruzeiro of value-added is lower in Lndustry and&#13;
commerce as well as agriculture in the Northeast and Frontier, compared to&#13;
the Southeast. They attribute the lower yield in the poor reg:lons partly&#13;
to the nature of taxpaying units there: the higher proportion of subsis-&#13;
tence farmers, small-scale manufacturers, informal street vendors, and so&#13;
forth. They also attribute variations in the ratio of ICM collections to&#13;
industrial value-added to varying degrees of industrial tax exemptions,&#13;
though it is unclear which region sacrifices more of its industrial tax&#13;
base to exemptions.&#13;
In summary, :it is clear that the relatively low per capita yield&#13;
of the ICM in poorer regions is primarily a reflection of the low produc-&#13;
tivity of their economLes. Federal restriction of the tax base to agricul-&#13;
ture, industry and commerce appears to be only slightly detrimental to the&#13;
poorer regions, and they are able to recover some of the exempted tax base&#13;
as a result of the way tax liabilities are calculated. Federal policies&#13;
regarding the taxation of interstate trade explicitly favor the governments&#13;
of poorer regions. Thus, the available data supports the conclusion that&#13;
the inability of state governments to raise ICM revenues at least propor-&#13;
tionate to their gross state output is primarily due to problems of tax&#13;
administration.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
Table 14&#13;
Sectoral Gopositimg&#13;
of IOI 1W ners and Table Gross State Product, ((GP) 1970&#13;
(percent of each sector in IM aid taxable GSP)&#13;
State&#13;
Ariculture                  Industry                   GQmmrce&#13;
IRl    GSP ICI/GSP         ICQI  GSP    ICH,/GSP       I(M     GSP  IaI/GSP&#13;
Nbrtbeast&#13;
Parafba            18.3   43    0.4           36.2   24      1.5          45.5 33       1.4&#13;
Pernambuc          17.6   23    0.8           40.7   39      1.0          41.6  38      1.1&#13;
Soutaast&#13;
Minas Gerais       13.6   26    0.5           50.4  43       1.2          36.0 31       1.2&#13;
S;o Paulo           0.1   8     0.0           80.3  68       1.2          19.2 24      0.8&#13;
Frmntier&#13;
Mito Grosso        63.5   53     1.2           8.7   16      0.5          27.8 31       0.9&#13;
NDte: 1CM revenues in P    crnanb3  and Paraiba exclude 12.6% and 5.0%, respectiwely, classified as&#13;
"other". Gross state product (GSP) ewcludes public uti]ities and civil constructicn and is&#13;
therefore consistent with the legally defined I1M industrial tax hae. Commerce, as defined in&#13;
gross state product, excludes sales of merchaidise In bars, restaurants, and similar&#13;
service-type locations, where sals of anDrchandise are subject to IQC taxation. Iba share of&#13;
merce, as defined for ICM purposes, is therefore larger in gross state product than&#13;
Indicated in the table.&#13;
Source: 1CM Revenmes: SIlva and Silva (1974).&#13;
State product: FIzuoda  Getulio Vargas, Contas kclonais, 1974.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
Property transfer tax (ITBI). The federal Constitution permits&#13;
the states only one tax base other than the ICM--a tax on the transfer of&#13;
real property (ITBI). The legal tax base of the ITBI includes both the&#13;
sale of property and ithe transfer of property at death. Maximum tax rates&#13;
are fixed by federal law. As shown in Tables 2 and 15, revenues from the&#13;
ITBI are a relatively minor component of state receipts. Low rates partly&#13;
explain the tax's low yield. The maximum rates range from 0.5% to 2.0% of&#13;
market value according to the type of property transferred. Spatial varia-&#13;
tions in per capita ITBI revenues are highly correlated with variations in&#13;
ICM revenues per capita (r = 0.80 in 1980), reinforcing the concentration&#13;
of state tax revenues in the Southeast.&#13;
Other state revenue sources.   The federal Constitut:ion also&#13;
permits state governuLents to charge fees for licenses and permits and for&#13;
services performed by the state. In order to prevent states from using&#13;
this power to raise revenues for general expenditures, federal legislation&#13;
requires that the charge not exceed the cost of the function performed.&#13;
Per capita revenues from licenses and service charges are highly correlated&#13;
with per capita ICM revenues (r = 0.83 in 1980). In contrast, the yields&#13;
from rentals or sales; of state property, fines and penalties, and dividends&#13;
on state-owned stock,, vary erratically from year to year, and from state to&#13;
state. However, the lack of correlation with ICM revenues does not (at&#13;
least in 1980) imply that this revenue source counteracts the overall&#13;
concentration of public revenues in the Southeast. Aggregated by region,&#13;
the yield of "miscellaneous revenues" is still significantly higher in the&#13;
Southeast than in the poorer regions of Brazil (see Table 15).&#13;
Table 15&#13;
Regional Pattern of State Revenue Sources, 1978&#13;
(current Cr$ per capita)&#13;
Source                            -------------Region&#133;------------&#13;
Northeast    Southeast   Frontier&#13;
Value-added tax (ICM)                          475        1,853        601&#13;
Transfer tax (ITBI)                             10           49         30&#13;
Charges and Misc.                               65          202         75&#13;
Subtotal:   local sources                    550       2,104         706&#13;
Transfers                                      453          366        613&#13;
Borrowing                                      106          389        131&#13;
TOTAL                                      1,110        2,858      1,449&#13;
Notes:   Table excludes Federal District and territories.     ICM figure&#13;
excludes nmunicipal share.&#13;
Source:   IBGE,  Estatfsticas Economicas do Governo Estadual e&#13;
Municipal, 1978 (Rio de Janeiro, 1980).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
Borrowing. Federal legislation regulates the borrowing of state&#13;
governments (see  page 13).    The legislative controls over borrow-&#13;
ing, in principle, exaggerate regional disparities in revenues, though it&#13;
is not clear that the controls have that effect in practice. In linking&#13;
borrowing to tax revenues, the formula allows a considerably higher&#13;
absolute level of borrowing in the relatively wealthy southeastern states&#13;
than in the northeastern or frontier states. Though the restrictions of&#13;
Resolution 62 can be circumvented, there remains a fairly high correlation&#13;
between per capita borrowing and total per capita revenues. The value of&#13;
borrowing varies from year to year. Taking a five-year average (adjusted&#13;
for inflation), revenues from official borrowing account for about 11% of&#13;
state revenues in the Southeast and Northeast, and about 7% of the revenues&#13;
of the frontier states. The correlation between per capita revenues from&#13;
borrowing and per capita non-debt revenues is 0.80.&#13;
Sources of Variation in Municipal Revenues&#13;
Regional disparities in per capita tax collections are wider at&#13;
the municipal level of government than at the state level. In 1975,&#13;
property and service tax collections in the Southeast were seven times&#13;
higher than in the Northeast, and ten times higher than in the municfpios&#13;
of the Frontier region. Disparities in municipal tax collections are also&#13;
substantial within regions. Large cities dominate local tax collections&#13;
throughout Brazil. As shown in Table 16, the munfcipio of Sa'o Paulo, with&#13;
7% of Brazil's population, collects almost 40% of all municipal taxes. The&#13;
seven municfpios with populations of one million or more together collect&#13;
nearly two-thirds of all local taxes, though they account for less than 20%&#13;
of national population. The tax collections of smaller municApios are thus&#13;
almost insignificant, particularly in poorer regions. The average yield of&#13;
local taxes in the Frontier region in 1975 was Cr$8.1 (US$1) per capita.&#13;
In the Northeast, excluding the major cities of Fortaleza, Recife, and&#13;
Salvador, the average yield of local taxes was the equivalent of US$0.41&#13;
per capita.&#13;
Table 16&#13;
Municipal Taxes: Concentration of Base and Yield in Large Cities, 1975&#13;
Percent of National Total&#13;
Manufacturing&#13;
Value                    Property   Service     Total&#13;
Municipio           Added      Population     Tax         Tax    Municipal&#13;
(IPTU)      (ISS)      Taxes&#13;
Sao Paulo            24%            7%        39%          38%       39%&#13;
Rio de-Janeiro       8              5         12           19        15&#13;
Other municipios&#13;
of over one&#13;
million a/           4             6         10           12        11&#13;
Total               36            18         61           69        65&#13;
a/  Fortaleza, Recife, Salvador, Belo Horizonte, Porto Alegre.&#13;
Sources:  Tax Revenues:  MF/SEF, unpublished computer listings;&#13;
IBGE, Estatisticas Econ8micas do Governo Estadual&#13;
e Municipal, 1979&#13;
Value added:   IBGE, Pesquisa Industrial, 1980&#13;
Population:    IBGE, Sinopse Preliminar do Censo Demografico,&#13;
1981 (1975 population estimated based on 1970-80&#13;
growth rate).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
Unlike states, mnunicipal governments have the authority to set&#13;
tax rates. Variations in revenues therefore reflect political factors, the&#13;
strength of the local tax base, and local administrative capacity. There&#13;
are no precise indicators of the property and service tax bases of each&#13;
municfpio, and it is therefore difficult to separate the effect of tax&#13;
bases from other factors in explaining regional variations in tax yield.&#13;
Using formal sector manufacturing value added as a rough index suggests&#13;
that tax base variations are not the sole explanation for varying yields in&#13;
local taxes.   As shown in Table 16, the large cities' share of t;ax collec-&#13;
tions far exceeds their share of manufacturing value added. The seven&#13;
municipios with populations over one million account for 36% of manufactur-&#13;
ing value-added, but 65% of tax collections.&#13;
There is some evidence that the legal, administrative and&#13;
political constraints on local tax collections (see pages 25-27 ) apply&#13;
most stringently to smaller municlpios, particularly in poorer, rural&#13;
regions. The federal restriction of the IPTU to urban areas clearly&#13;
constrains the tax base of rural areas more than that of urban municfpios.&#13;
Administrative capacity :is also more limited in poorer regions. Moreover,&#13;
political factors appear to have greater impact in smaller municfpios.&#13;
Brazilian sources frequently cite the day-to-day contact between a mayor&#13;
and his constituents as a major obstacle to increased tax effort in small&#13;
towns. The federal revenue-sharing system also confers larger amounts, per&#13;
capita, on smaller municpios, reducing the incentive for increa,sed tax&#13;
effort.&#13;
Given present low levels of municipal revenue effort, spatial&#13;
variations in local tax yields are not the major source of variation in&#13;
municipal revenues. Taxes account for only 20% of local current: revenues.&#13;
As shown in Table 17, revenues from charges for municipal services,&#13;
licenses, and miscellaneous sources nearly equal tax collections in each&#13;
region. The principal source of variation is not local revenues, but the&#13;
distribution formulas of intergovernmental transfers. The effect of&#13;
transfers on spatial variation in revenues is discussed in the Eollowing&#13;
paragraphs.&#13;
Table 17&#13;
Regional Pattern of Municipal Revenue Sources, 1975&#13;
(Current Cr$ per capita)&#13;
Source                                         Region&#13;
Northeast         Southeast         Frontier&#13;
Property Tax (IPTU)               4.5               41.1             4.6&#13;
Service Tax (ISS)                 6.5               39.7             3.5&#13;
Charges and Misc.                 8.8               56.0            14.8&#13;
Subtotal:   local sources      19.8             136.8             22.9&#13;
Transfers                        59.4            _198.8             69.1&#13;
Borrowing                         3.9              49.3             11.1&#13;
Unclassified                      1.1                9.7             4.5&#13;
Total                          84.3             394.6            107.6&#13;
Note: Table excludes Federal District and territories.&#13;
Sources: MF/SEF, unpublished computer listings;&#13;
Finangas Publicas (Jan, Feb, March 1981).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
Revenue Sharing&#13;
Revenue sharing is a major component of the Brazilian system of&#13;
intergovernmental fiscal relations. The federal government shares the&#13;
revenues from 12 of its taxes with state and municipal governments, and&#13;
requires the states to share fixed proportions of their tax revenues with&#13;
their respective municdpios. The revenue-sharing system is primarily aimed&#13;
at closing the "vertical gap". The federal government, having monopolized&#13;
most tax bases, permits state and local governments a share of the revenues&#13;
collected in their respective jurisdictions. Eight of the shared taxes are&#13;
thus distributed largely or entirely on the basis of origin. Two others,&#13;
the fuels (IUCL) and energy taxes (IUEE), are distributed according to&#13;
population and consumption, mixing origin and need criteria. Only the&#13;
Participation Funds, financed from the income and manufacturers' sales&#13;
taxes, use "need" as a primary distribution criterion.&#13;
The impact of shared taxes and non-formula intergovernmental&#13;
transfers on regional disparities in current revenues is shown in&#13;
Table 18. At the state level, the redistributive effect of the Participa-&#13;
tion Funds is partly counteracted by origin-based shared revenues, as well&#13;
as by non-formula grants. The net effect of federal intergovernmental&#13;
transfers is a substantial increase in total state revenues (about 30%),&#13;
but a fairly modest decrease in regional revenue disparities. With the&#13;
addition of transfers, state revenues per capita in the Southeast drop from&#13;
139% to 128% of the national average, and levels in the Northeast and&#13;
Frontier regions rise correspondingly.&#13;
Consistent data on federal and state transfers to the municfpios&#13;
are not available. The figures in Table 18, based on aggregate data&#13;
supplied by the Finance Ministry, show virtually no net regional redistrib-&#13;
ution via federal transfers (combining Participation Funds, origin based&#13;
transfers and non-formula transfers). Federally-mandated transfers of the&#13;
ICM clearly favor municfpios in the Southeast. The net effect of federal&#13;
and state transfers to local governments is a slight narrowing of regional&#13;
disparities. Including transfers in municipal revenues reduces municipal&#13;
revenues in the Southeast from 153% to 141% of the national average, with&#13;
corresponding increases in the Northeast and Frontier region.&#13;
The question of how much the transfer system should attempt to&#13;
reduce regional disparities is largely a political one, outside the scope&#13;
of the present report. however, two technical aspects of the system of&#13;
transfers require comment. The first, already discussed, is the need to&#13;
design transfer formulas to reward, rather than discourage, the reci-&#13;
pients' own tax effort. The second concerns the targeting of transfers.&#13;
In two respects, the present system of transfers mistargets its recipients&#13;
-- these cases are discussed below.&#13;
Small population as an indicator of weak tax base. The share of&#13;
the federal Participation Fund distributed to state governments, and the&#13;
municipal governments of state capitals, is distributed according to&#13;
population and the inverse of per capita state income. The share of&#13;
non-capital municlpios is distributed only on the basis of population. In&#13;
all cases, population is measured according to a formula that gives greater&#13;
per capita weight to less populous municpios. Thus, Espfrito Santo, with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
Table 18&#13;
Impact of Revenue Sharing on Regional Disparities, Mid-1970s&#13;
(Current Cr$)&#13;
Region&#13;
Revenue Source                       Northeast       Southeast      Frontier&#13;
State Government:&#13;
Cr$ per capita, 1978&#13;
Participation Fund                   273              50            251&#13;
Origin-based transfers*              106             225            237&#13;
Non-formula transfers                 73              91            125&#13;
Total                              452            366             613&#13;
Local revenues                       550          2,104             706&#13;
Total non-debt revenues            1,002          2,470           1,319&#13;
As % of national average&#13;
Transfers                            109              88            147&#13;
Local revenues                        37             139             47&#13;
Total non-debt revenues               52             128             69&#13;
Municipal Government:&#13;
Cr$ per capita, 1975&#13;
Federal formula transfers             29              33             31&#13;
Federal other transfers                4              10              7&#13;
State transfers                       27             155             31&#13;
Total                               60             198             69&#13;
Local revenues                        20             137             23&#13;
Total non-debt revenues               80             335             92&#13;
As % of national average&#13;
Transfers                             42             139             48&#13;
Local revenues                        22             153             26&#13;
Total non-debt revenues               34             141             39&#13;
*   Includes TRU, XUM, ITR, SE and federal tax on incomes of state&#13;
employees withlield at source.&#13;
Sources: IBGE, Estatfsticas Economicas do Governo Estadual e&#13;
Municipal, 1978 (Rio de Janeiro, 1980); MF/SEF, unpublished&#13;
computer listings.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
a population of 1.6 million in 1970, received 2.5 times as much per capita&#13;
as Minas Gerais, with a population of 11.6 million and an approximately&#13;
equal income level. Under the present distribution formula, a non-capital&#13;
municfpio of 10,000 would receive twice as much per capita as a non-capital&#13;
municipio of 100,000.&#13;
The distribution criteria of the Participation Funds were&#13;
apparently intended to assist state and local governments whose revenues&#13;
from local sources were low owing to weak tax bases and poor administrative&#13;
capacities. This intent is explicit in the inclusion of state income per&#13;
capita in the distribution formulas of the FPE, FE, and the capitals share&#13;
of the FPM. However, the success of population as a tax capacity indicator&#13;
is questionable. At the state level, the per capita tax and charge reve-&#13;
nues of governments are positively correlated with their population (r =&#13;
0.60) only when income per capita is ignored. Regressing per capita tax&#13;
and charge revenues on state income per capita and state population renders&#13;
the influence of population not significantly different from zero. Income&#13;
per capita is, in contrast, significant (at a 0.01 level of significance)&#13;
with, or without the inclusion of population. As an indicator of tax&#13;
capacity at the state level, the use of population is at best redundant and&#13;
appears to over-compensate less populous states.&#13;
The problem at the municipio level is more complicated, since&#13;
there are no indicators of the tax capacity of each of Brazil's approxim-&#13;
ately 4,000 municfpios. The earlier discussion of local taxation lends&#13;
some support to the present distribution formula. Very large municipios&#13;
appear to be far more successful in collecting taxes than the average of&#13;
all municfpios. Nevertheless, population alone is a poor indicator of tax&#13;
yield, and probably, of tax capacity. Though detailed municipal revenues&#13;
by region and size class are not available, the regional averages shown&#13;
below in Table 19 indicate that regional variations in municipio population&#13;
size are relatively small, compared to regional variations in local reve-&#13;
nues from taxes and charges. The FPM transfer formula, intending to&#13;
compensate municfpios with weak administrative capacities, succeeds in&#13;
concentrating revenues at the lower end of the population scale, but fails&#13;
to compensate for regional variations in tax capacity within a given&#13;
size-class.&#13;
Table 19&#13;
Non-Capital Municipios: Average Population and Revenues,Mid-1970s&#13;
(Current Cr$)&#13;
Southeast    Northeast   Frontier&#13;
Average population                          24,590       20,303       18,106&#13;
Average tax and charge revenues,                186          22          41&#13;
per capita, 1975&#13;
Average FPM per capita, 1978                Cr$ 124      Cr$ 150     Cr$ 146&#13;
Sources: MF/SEF, unpublished computer listings; Revista de Financas&#13;
Publicas, XLI, 345 (Jan-March 1981); IBGE, Estatfsticas&#13;
Econ8micas do Governo Estadual e Municipal, 1978 (Rio de Janeiro,&#13;
1980).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
"Value-added" collections as an indicator of origin. The second&#13;
technical issue concerns the federally-mandated transfer of revenues from&#13;
jtates to municfpios. Federal law requires that states return 20% of their&#13;
ICM revenues to municipal governments; 75% on the basis of origin, and 25%&#13;
at the discretion of the state government. Regionally, the result is a&#13;
concentration of resourcei; in the Southeast, as noted earlier. At the sub-&#13;
regional level, the result is a concentration of funds in industrial&#13;
areas. The concentration is most apparent in metropolitan regions, where&#13;
industrial municipios, with relatively large tax bases, coexist with&#13;
"dormitory suburbs", with relatively small tax bases. Owing to the&#13;
jurisdictional segregation of tax bases and population, wide variations in&#13;
per capita ICM transfers occur. In metropolitan Sao Paulo, for example,&#13;
the industrial city of Sio Bernardo received ICM transfers equal to US$147&#13;
per capita in 1975, while the "dormitory suburb" of Francisco Morate&#13;
received the equivalent of US$0.61 per capita. 36,&#13;
The intent of using origin as a distribution criteriorL is to&#13;
return a share of taxes collected to the local jurisdiction where they are&#13;
paid. Because the ICM is an indirect tax, its incidence is partly shifted&#13;
forward from the point of collection to the point of consumption. The&#13;
origin of the tax may, therefore, correspond more to the geographic pattern&#13;
of consumption of taxable goods than to the pattern of value-added. A&#13;
transfer system based on actual origin--approximated by population--would&#13;
more uniformly distribute the ICM transfer without doing violence to its&#13;
intended distribution objectives.&#13;
Regional Distribution of Direct Federal Expenditures&#13;
A recent study of the spatial distribution of the federal budget&#13;
suggests that the pattern of the federal government's own revenues and&#13;
expenditures leads to aL transfer of resources from the Southeast to the&#13;
poorer regions. 37/ In 1975, according to this study, the southeastern&#13;
states contributeT 32% more to federal revenues than they received in&#13;
federal expenditures. The Northeast, in contrast, received 70% more in&#13;
federal expenditures than it paid in federal taxes, and the Frontier nearly&#13;
three times as much. The study concluded that regional redistribution&#13;
implicit in the federa1l budget far outweighs the effect of official system&#13;
of intergovernmental transfers.&#13;
There are a number of conceptual problems with this type of&#13;
analysis, particularly as it applies to Brazil. On the revenue side, the&#13;
federal government relies heavily on indirect taxes where incidence is to&#13;
varying degrees shifted across state boundaries through interstate trade.&#13;
Revenues collected in the Southeast may, therefore, be paid in part by&#13;
consumers in poorer regions, reducing the magnitude of the apparent&#13;
transfer. On the expenditure side, there are problems in treating federal&#13;
36/ In 1975, transfers were distributed entirely on the basis of origin.&#13;
The disparity would be less under the distribution formula adopted by&#13;
Sao Paulo in 1981 which takes population into account.&#13;
37/  C.A. Longo and A.E. Muller, "Impacto Regional das Finanpas Federais",&#13;
in Proceedings of the IX Encontro Nacional de Economia, Olinda&#13;
(Pernambuco), Deicember 8-11, 1981; Vol. 4, pp. 1663-83.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
expenditures as equivalent to transfers to state or local governments.&#13;
Owing to externalities, the benefits of a given federal expenditure are not&#13;
always limited to the region in which the expenditure occurs. Federal&#13;
expenditures on "public goods", for example, benefit the nation as a whole,&#13;
though the expenditures may be concentrated in certain regions. Expendi-&#13;
tures on general administration and national defense are obvious cases in&#13;
point.&#13;
Certain federal expenditures can be considered comparable to&#13;
federal intergovernmental transfers, however, to the extent that they&#13;
replace or supplement the expenditures of state or local governments. This&#13;
approach is particularly appropriate to Brazil. Because the division of&#13;
functional responsibilities between levels of government is vague, federal&#13;
direct expenditures often take the place of what would be intergovernmental&#13;
grants under a wmre rigid division of functions.&#13;
The most recent regionalization of federal expenditures, by&#13;
function, is only for 1975. Table 20, below, shows federal per capita&#13;
expenditures on selected functions. The table excludes federal&#13;
expenditures on general administration, defense, social security,&#13;
agriculture, energy, industry, and foreign relations, which together&#13;
account for 78% of federal expenditures. Federal expenditures in the&#13;
Federal District (Brasilia) are also excluded. Owing to the level of&#13;
aggregation, it was not possible to separate official intergovernmental&#13;
transfers from the functional categories. The total of selected sectors&#13;
may therefore include state and municipal shares of some taxes, most likely&#13;
the fuels tax (IUCL) and the motor vehicle registration tax (TRU).&#13;
On a per capita basis, federal expenditures in the selected func-&#13;
tional areas clearly favor the Southeast. The federal government.spends&#13;
roughly Cr$500 per capita on the selected functions in this region,&#13;
compared to Cr$310 in the Frontier and Cr$163 in the Northeast. The bias&#13;
toward the Southeast is particularly great in transportation and health&#13;
expenditures. The value of federal expenditures on the selected functions&#13;
is more than twice the value of official transfers (assuming no double&#13;
counting). The Southeast bias in direct expenditures is therefore suffi-&#13;
cient offset the bias of official transfers toward poorer regions. Combin-&#13;
ing federal expenditures on the selected functions and official transfers&#13;
(and ignoring any double-counting) the federal government spends Cr$640 per&#13;
capita in the Southeast, nearly twice what it spends in the Northeast, and&#13;
20% more than its expenditures per capita in the Frontier states.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
Table 20&#13;
Federal Direct Expenditures by Region, 1975&#13;
(Current Cr$ per capita)&#13;
Region&#13;
Function                   Frontier    Northeast   Southeast&#13;
Transportation                             Cr$ 164    Cr$    53    Cr$ 327&#13;
Education                                       61           55         65&#13;
Housing and Urban Services                       2            0          0&#13;
Health                                          84           55        116&#13;
Total (selected functions)                     310          163        510&#13;
Official transfers                             239          153        134&#13;
Total (direct expenditures plus&#13;
official transfers)                       549         317         634&#13;
Source : Fundacao Getdlio Vargas/Centro de Estudos Fiscais, Regionalizacao&#13;
das Transagcces do Setor Publico - 1975 (Rio de Janeiro, 1980).&#13;
VI. SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS&#13;
State and Local governments already play important roles in the&#13;
provision of essential services such as education, health, housing, and&#13;
urban development. Since the demand for these types of services tends to&#13;
be highly elastic wii:h respect to GDP, one would expect that pressures on&#13;
the financial resources of the states and municfpios will continue to&#13;
increase rapidly in the future. 38/ This tendency should be reinforced,&#13;
moreover, by the gradual political opening now underway.&#13;
Will the states and municipios be able to meet future demands for&#13;
expanded services? rhe experience of the past decade raises doubts in this&#13;
respect. The basic conclusion of the present report is that means need to&#13;
be devised to increase the level of resources available to the states and&#13;
municipios generally, and to subnational governments of poor regions in&#13;
particular. In order to achieve this objective, both vertical and hori-&#13;
zontal fiscal adjustments are indicated. but these adjustments need not&#13;
entail a comprehensive reform encompassing the creation of new taxes, nor a&#13;
significant increase, in the national tax burden. 39/ A series of measures&#13;
aimed at improving the efficiency and equity of t1ie system as it now exists&#13;
would be sufficient.. A recapitulation of the findings of the present&#13;
report concerning the fiscal situation of the states and munidpios, as&#13;
well as some suggestions as to how this situation might be iraproved,&#13;
follows.&#13;
38/ Calculations of historical income-elasticity coefficients for various&#13;
public expenditure categories are presented in:    D. J. Mahar and&#13;
F. A. Rezende da Silva, "The Growth and Pattern of Public Expenditure&#13;
in Brazil, 1920-1969", Public Finance Quarterly, III, 4 (October&#13;
1975), 380-99.&#13;
39/ During the 1972-76 period, Brazil had the second highest (after Iran)&#13;
tax effort index among a sample of 47 developing countries. See:&#13;
A.A. Tait, W.L.M. Gratz and B.J. Eichengreen, "International&#13;
Comparisons of Taxation for Developing Countries, 1972-76", IMF Staff&#13;
Papers, 26, 1 (March 1979), 130.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
Vertical Balance&#13;
Principal findings. Over the past decade, state finances have&#13;
been characterized by declining saving and investment ratios, chronic&#13;
budgetary deficits and increasing levels of indebtedness. Though the&#13;
fiscal data for the municipios are fragmentary after 1975, it is likely,&#13;
given the strong links between state and local finances (particularly with&#13;
respect to intergovernmental transfers of the ICM), that local finances&#13;
have behaved similarly. The causes of this financial deterioration are&#13;
varied. The most important, however, is probably the slower growth of&#13;
economic activity observed after the "oil shock" of 1973-74. One effect of&#13;
this slowdown was a substantial reduction in the rate of public revenue&#13;
growth. In response, many states sharply curtailed their spending for&#13;
investment programs, at least those financed through central state&#13;
budgets. Current expenditures, in contrast, could not be cut back to the&#13;
same extent owing to commitments to finance general administrative costs,&#13;
and the operation and the maintenance of investments made in previous&#13;
years.&#13;
Though the subnational governments could not have foreseen the&#13;
shortfall in their revenues, certain legal and administrative factors have&#13;
exacerbated their financial situations and interfered with their ability to&#13;
adjust to the new economic environment. Foremost among these factors are&#13;
the federally-mandated controls over the rates and/or bases of some&#13;
important state and local taxes. The ICM, in particular, has been increas-&#13;
ingly utilized as an instrument of national economic policy, as evidenced&#13;
by periodic changes in the tax rate and the exemptions given to manufac-&#13;
tured exports, inputs to projects of "national priority", and so forth.&#13;
This has contributed to the instability of ICM revenues and the erosion of&#13;
state and local tax bases.&#13;
With little latitude for adjusting their own sources of revenues&#13;
to demands on the expenditure side, the state and local governments have,&#13;
by necessity, become more dependent on the federal government for financial&#13;
assistance. In recent years, this assistance has increasingly taken the&#13;
form of transfers and special credit lines to help finance the investments&#13;
of state-level decentralized agencies. This process has reduced the&#13;
control of state finance secretariats over investment decisions, thereby&#13;
interfering with medium and long-term planning and efforts to contain&#13;
recurrent costs. The situation described above contrasts sharply with the&#13;
positive steps taken in 1979-81 to eliminate the earmarking of shares from&#13;
the Participation Funds.&#13;
Recommendations. The Government is cognizant of the general need&#13;
to strengthen state and local finances and has included this among the&#13;
objectives of the third National Development Plan. This is a laudable&#13;
goal, which should be pursued vigorously. Given its high revenue-raising&#13;
potential, a good place to start would be enactment of legislation to&#13;
reform the ICM. Here the principal objective should be to broaden the base&#13;
of this tax by eliminating most of the present exemptions. 40/&#13;
40/ To avoid possible negative effects on the balance-of-payments, it&#13;
would be preferable not to abolish the present exemption for manufac-&#13;
tured exports. Instead, federal compensation to the states for all,&#13;
or part of, the revenue loss caused by this provision should be&#13;
considered.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
By including such items as fuels, industrial equipment, agricul-&#13;
tural inputs, and servicefs in the ICM base, both state and municLpal reve-&#13;
nues would be greatly increased. If services were to be included in the&#13;
ICM base, it would be advisable to abolish the municipal ISS. Though this&#13;
would undoubtedly cause local own-source revenues to fall, some important&#13;
benefits could be achieved. For example, existing conflicts between the&#13;
states and municipios over the taxation of certain bases (e.g., publishing&#13;
and food services) would be eliminated. Also, there would undoubtedly be&#13;
efficiency gains in the collection process. The munictpios could be&#13;
compensated for the loss of the ISS through adjustments in the state-to-&#13;
local tax-sharing system.&#13;
In addition to broadening the states' tax base, steps should be&#13;
taken to improve the-control of the state governments over the activities&#13;
of their decentralized agencies and enterprises. The recognition of the&#13;
need for such coordination in urban areas has led to the creation of&#13;
metropolitan planning agencies, which in some cases have been successful in&#13;
integrating the efforts of a large number of state and municipal. entities&#13;
within their areas of influence. A similar process could take place at the&#13;
state level, with guidelines being drawn up to ensure appropriate balance&#13;
between the sectorial investment plans of the various decentralized&#13;
agencies. The states should also insist on improvements in pricing and on&#13;
greater efficiency to reduce the need to support the agencies from state&#13;
budgets.&#13;
At the municipal level, efforts to improve the productivity of&#13;
the IPTU should be continued. As the experience of CIATA has shown,&#13;
considerable revenues are foregone because of poor administrative prac-&#13;
tices. However, in order for property taxation to increase significantly&#13;
in importance as a source of municipal revenue, the traditional reluctance&#13;
of locally-elected officials to tax their own constituents must be over-&#13;
come. This change of mentality could, in principle, be promoted by linking&#13;
federal and state transfers to local tax effort. In practice, this is not&#13;
an easy task.&#13;
The simplest way to reward tax effort is the matching grant.&#13;
Under this system, the amount transferred would be based upon the amount of&#13;
counterpart funds raised by a given municipio; the transfer would be set at&#13;
a fixed fraction of the amount raised. However, matching grants only&#13;
reward tax effort when per capita tax bases are roughly equal among the&#13;
eligible governments. Otherwise, a municipio with a rich tax base and a&#13;
low tax effort could raise as much, or more, money as a poor municipality&#13;
with a high tax effort. Given the extreme diversity in wealth among&#13;
Brazil's local governments, matching grants alone would not provide an&#13;
acceptable vehicle for intergovernmental transfers.&#13;
In the Brazilian context, tax effort would have to be measured&#13;
directly. Two approaches may be suggested. The first is the direct&#13;
measurement of the tax base itself, i.e., the assessed value of property in&#13;
each jurisdiction. This approach requires a uniform definition of the tax&#13;
base in each jurisdiction, and some assurance that no jurisdiction is&#13;
underestimating its base.   Either direct assessment or regular auditing by&#13;
a higher level of govercnment is therefore required. The second approach is&#13;
to use indicators. A large number of possible indicators are now generated&#13;
annually by the transfer system itself. State governments monitor value&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
added and the value of property transactions by municipio. The federal&#13;
government collects statistics on electric energy and fuel consumption, and&#13;
motor vehicle registrations. Data are also available decenially from the&#13;
demographic census, and quinquenially from the sectorial censuses&#13;
(industry, commerce, services), allowing periodic verifications of the&#13;
reliability of selected indicators. While no single indicator will&#13;
perfectly reflect spatial variations in property and service tax bases, the&#13;
available data would permit a reasonable approximation. Despite the&#13;
obvious administrative problems, a change in the incentives embodied in the&#13;
system of intergovernmental transfers is required if locally-administered&#13;
taxes are to make a major contribution to public sector revenues in&#13;
Brazil. Technical asssistance, while necessary, is not sufficient to&#13;
ensure the exploitation of the large revenue potential of the property tax.&#13;
Benefit taxation (recovering the costs of public works from the&#13;
direct beneficiaries) is another underexploited source of local revenue.&#13;
This is mainly because legislation specifying the means for calculating&#13;
individual charges has never been enacted. Some municipal governments&#13;
recover the costs of street paving, sidewalks, gutters and similar works by&#13;
charging their costs directly to owners of abutting property according to&#13;
the front footage of each lot. This practice has been halted in some&#13;
cases, however, owing to uncertainties over whether municipal governments&#13;
have the legal authority to charge property owners for public works&#13;
performed without their consent. The law must be clarified on this point&#13;
before the full potential of benefit taxation can be realized.&#13;
Horizontal Balance&#13;
Principal findings. Wide disparities exist in the financial&#13;
situation of states and munictpios in Brazil, and these are reflected in&#13;
the quality (as measured by per capita expenditures) of publicly-supplied&#13;
services in different parts of the country. Varying economic conditions&#13;
largely explain the extent of the disparities. The impact of local govern-&#13;
ment policy is small, as federal policies discourage or prohibit local&#13;
differences in own-source revenues. The federal government's various&#13;
revenue-sharing programs work at cross purposes and have only a small net&#13;
equalizing effect, at least interregionally.&#13;
Though state and municipal autonomy is limited, problems of tax&#13;
administration exacerbate the poverty of governments in poorer regions.&#13;
The predominance of small-scale agriculture and "informal" manufacturing&#13;
and retailing reduces the tax base that can be effectively captured by&#13;
state and municipal governments in poorer regions. Federal legislation&#13;
does permit governments in poorer regions to impose higher taxes on inter-&#13;
state imports. However, this does not compensate for the difficulty&#13;
governments in poorer regions have in collecting taxes. Despite federal&#13;
policy, the proportion of economic activity effectively taxed is higher in&#13;
rich regions than in poor ones.&#13;
In addition to regional disparities, there are marked differences&#13;
in the per capita revenues of municipal governments of different sizes.&#13;
Locally-generated revenues are particularly dominated by larger&#13;
municfpios. Brazil's most populous municipios (Sao Paulo and Rio de&#13;
Janeiro), for example, collect more than half the locally-administered&#13;
taxes collected in the nation. Lack of both administrative capacity and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
incentive are explanatory factors. Many small municpios are operating&#13;
with obsolete tax codes and property cadastres, owing to a lacI: of&#13;
sufficiently trained staff. At the same time, municipal tax effort is&#13;
discouraged by federal laws granting municfpios fixed shares of federal and&#13;
state taxes. A municipio's incentive to raise funds locally is also&#13;
discouraged by the ambiguous nature of its responsibilities. Direct&#13;
participation by the federal or state government is an alternative to local&#13;
tax effort as a means of financing many public services. Though the&#13;
evidence is not strong either way, these disincentives to loca:L tax effort&#13;
appear to be more influential in smaller municlpios than in ma;jor cities.&#13;
Wide disparities in per capita revenues also occur among the&#13;
municpios of Brazil's metropolitan regions. In this case, the disparity&#13;
is largely due to federal regulations which permit municipal governments to&#13;
retain a fixed share of the ICM collected within their boundarLes. As the&#13;
growth of metropolitan areas has been characterized by the segregation of&#13;
industrial plants from residential areas, municlpios with high concentra-&#13;
tions of industry collect a disproportionate amount of ICM revenues, while&#13;
the municdpios housing their work force collect relatively little.&#13;
The federal government distributes shares of 12 of its taxes to&#13;
the states and municipios; nine of them according to fixed formulas. Only&#13;
two, comprising the system of Participation Funds, are distributed accord-&#13;
ing to explicitly equalizing formulas.    Participation Funds are distributed&#13;
to states and municipios of state capitals largely on the basis of state&#13;
per capita income and population. Funds are distributed to interior&#13;
municipios only on the basis of population. In both cases, population is&#13;
weighted so that less populous municfpios receive higher per capita&#13;
transfers. At the stat:e and state capital levels, the weighting of popula-&#13;
tion appears redundant as an equalizing factor, and penalizes large poor&#13;
states and their capitals. The lack of any income indicator in the&#13;
distribution formula for non-capital municipios eliminates any element of&#13;
regional equalization among the interior municipios.&#13;
The remaining shared taxes are distributed according to formulas&#13;
that, to varying degrees, contradict the equalizing intent of the&#13;
Participation Funds. B3ecause of the higher level of funding in the&#13;
Participation Fund, fe,ieral transfers to state governments are, in aggre-&#13;
gate, higher per capita in poorer regions. Considering state capitals and&#13;
interior municipios, together federal transfers to local governments are&#13;
roughly equal per capita among regions. Intraregionally, the Participation&#13;
Fund formula compensates smaller municfpios for their relatively low tax&#13;
revenues, though only Dn a small scale. No federal program addresses the&#13;
problem of intra-metropolitan disparities, though recent changes in federal&#13;
legislation allow state governments greater flexibility in distributing ICM&#13;
revenues among municfpios.&#13;
Recommendations. Brazil's Third National Development Plan calls&#13;
for the reduction of regional social and economic disparities. Given the&#13;
size of economic variations between regions, complete equalization through&#13;
the public sector would be impossible, short of a radical centralization of&#13;
public sector expenditures or a massive increase in intergovernmental&#13;
transfers. Neither alternative is compatible with the curreni: political&#13;
pressure for increased state and local autonomy. The problem of the&#13;
inability of governments in poor regions to provide a level of- services&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
consistent with Brazil's overall level of development has to be addressed&#13;
in the long run through instruments designed to encourage factor mobility,&#13;
e.g., promoting investment in poor regions and encouraging labor migration&#13;
to rich regions.&#13;
In the short run, the extent of regional disparities in public&#13;
services might be reduced by:&#13;
(i) improving state and municipal tax administration, since&#13;
governments in the poorest areas generally have the worst&#13;
records in this respect (this would need to be accompanied&#13;
by measures to ensure that administrative improvements would&#13;
be maintained);&#13;
(ii) targeting state and municipal Participation Funds more&#13;
effectively to jurisdictions with limited tax capacities&#13;
(particularly the interior municipios of poorer regions);&#13;
(iii) introducing an equalization element into the other taxes&#13;
shared by the federal government (though at a cost to each&#13;
program's own objectives); and&#13;
(iv) increasing direct federal social expenditures in poorer&#13;
regions.&#13;
These four "top-down" measures would be more effective if comple-&#13;
mented by better performance by the recipient governments in poorer&#13;
regions. The municipal level particularly has room for improvement.&#13;
Municipal performance is discouraged by the present system of ambiguous&#13;
functional responsibilities and readily available aid from higher levels of&#13;
government, both in the form of transfers and as direct participation. The&#13;
definition of what functions are appropriate to the municipal level of&#13;
government and what revenue sources would be adequate, would require exten-&#13;
sive study, given the enormous diversity of Brazilian municfpios. An&#13;
investigation of the present functions and problems of a particular class&#13;
of municfpios -- particularly rural municfpios and secondary cities in&#13;
poorer regions -- would be a good place to start.&#13;
Final Considerations&#13;
An Interministerial Working Group, comprised of representatives&#13;
of SEPLAN and the Ministry of Finance, was established in 1982 for the&#13;
purpose of proposing a new fiscal reform. One of the major tasks of this&#13;
Group is to identify ways to increase the fiscal autonomy of the states and&#13;
municipios. In this regard, a working assumption of the Group is that&#13;
fiscal autonomy can be most effectively promoted through an expansion in&#13;
the volume of own-source revenues available to these governments, rather&#13;
than by altering the present system of intergovernmental transfers. A&#13;
second assumption is that any reform of the tax system should be designed&#13;
to benefit disproportionately subnational governments in the poorer regions&#13;
of the country. A final assumption is that the devolution of taxing&#13;
authority from the federal to the state and local levels will need to be&#13;
compensated for by a similar shift in the responsibility for public&#13;
services like education, health and transport.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
The Interministerial Working Group has not yet submitted its&#13;
forLal fiscal reform proposal for consideration by the national Congress.&#13;
A preliminary proposal, however, was made public in mid-1982, and its five&#13;
main features may be summarized briefly.    l/ First, it was proposed that&#13;
the ICM rate on interstate sales be reduced to zero.   This feature would,&#13;
in effect, change the assessment of the ICM from an origin to a destination&#13;
basis. By chiefly benefitting poorer net importing states, it would help&#13;
to redress horizontal fiscal imbalances. Second, it was proposed to expand&#13;
the list of essential food items exempted from the ICM. This proposal&#13;
would reduce the regresisivity of the tax, although at the expense of&#13;
further circumscribing the state and local tax base. Third, it was&#13;
proposed that the IPI be abolished and that its present base, with the&#13;
exception of vehicles, tobacco products and alcoholic beverages, be&#13;
incorporated into the base of the ICM. This measure would incr,ease total&#13;
state revenues by roughly 15%; the revenue gain to an individual state&#13;
being determined by the3 production or (in the case of production exported&#13;
to other states) consumption of taxable goods. Fourth, it was proposed&#13;
that the federal income tax burden be increased for upper-income groups.&#13;
This proposal is mainly intended to compensate the federal government for&#13;
the loss of the IPI, w'hile improving the overall progressivity of the tax&#13;
system. However, it would also assist the states and municfpios to the&#13;
extent that it offset the decline in the volume of resources transferred&#13;
through the FPs caused by the elimination of the IPI. Finally, it was&#13;
proposed that a special fund be created to compensate states for revenue&#13;
losses due to the exeniption of manufactured exports from the ICM. This&#13;
measure would have the macroeconomic advantage of motivating states to&#13;
promote exports. The revenue gains, however, would mainly accrue to the&#13;
wealthier industrial Etates of the Southeast which, in 1980, accounted for&#13;
about 85% of Brazil's total exports.&#13;
To some extent, the preliminary proposals of the Interministerial&#13;
Working Group paralleL the recommendations of the present report. The&#13;
Group has quite right:Ly concentrated its efforts on reforming the ICM,&#13;
proposing an expansion in its base (proposal 3) and the formation of a fund&#13;
to compensate states for revenue losses caused by the exemption of&#13;
manufactured exports (proposal 5). However, the Group's proposals do not&#13;
addrcss directly the need for fiscal reform at the municipal level, the&#13;
defects of the intergovernmental revenue-sharing system, nor the problems&#13;
of fiscal administration. Our analysis has shown that these are all areas&#13;
deserving close attention. The proposal to tax interstate sales on a&#13;
destination basis (proposal 1), for example, while clearly intended to&#13;
benefit the poorer states, would only result in additional revenues to the&#13;
extent that these states possess the administrative capacities to identify&#13;
and effectively tax the myriad retail establishments operating within their&#13;
borders..&#13;
Since the proposals of the Interministerial Working Group are&#13;
still preliminary, and not fully detailed, it is difficult to assess&#13;
quantitatively their net effect on state and local finances. According to&#13;
representatives of the Group, all states would benefit through increased&#13;
revenues, with the relatively largest gains accruing to the poorer states.&#13;
(The change in the overall fiscal situation of the states, however,&#13;
would be largely determined by the expenditure implications of transferring&#13;
certain functional responsibilities from the federal to subnational&#13;
levels). This revenue-enhancing aspect of the proposed fiscal reform&#13;
41/ C. Viacava, "Reforma Tributaria," Revista de Finangas Publicas, LXII,&#13;
351 (1982), 4-7.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
package has been generally well received by the states, although individual&#13;
states, or regional blocs of states, have expressed dissatisfaction with&#13;
the working assumptions of the Interministerial Group or with one or more&#13;
of the preliminary proposals. The governments of the northeastern states,&#13;
for example, citing their underdeveloped economies and relatively weak&#13;
administrative capabilities, appear to favor an expansion of federal-state&#13;
transfers more than a devolution of taxing authority. 42/ Similarly, the&#13;
government of Minas Gerais has noted that it would gain relatively little&#13;
through the proposal to transfer some of the IPI base to the states&#13;
(proposal 3), since about 84% of the IPI now collected in Minas is&#13;
accounted for by bases (i.e., vehicles, tobacco products and alcoholic&#13;
beverages) that would be retained by the federal government. 43/&#13;
Finally, the Sao Paulo state government has objected to the proposal to&#13;
change the assessment of the ICM on interstate sales from an origin to a&#13;
destination basis (proposal 1), arguing that its treasury should be&#13;
compensated for the benefits of public services (e.g., education, health,&#13;
transport, energy) accruing (through "spillovers") to residents of other&#13;
states, as well as for social costs (e.g., congestion and pollution)&#13;
associated with the production of exported goods.&#13;
The national debate concerning the Interministerial Working&#13;
Group's preliminary proposals illustrates well the economic and political&#13;
difficulties of designing a fiscal reform for a country characterized by&#13;
extreme regional disparities. Because of the direct elections for national&#13;
congressional seats and most state and local offices held in November 1982&#13;
(which brought the issue of fiscal reform to the forefront), and the&#13;
continuing recession in Brazil (which has caused state and local finances&#13;
to deteriorate still further), however, there is considerable pressure for&#13;
a compromise fiscal reform package to be enacted into law. The major&#13;
question mark at this point is whether the federal government will be&#13;
willing and able to transfer some of its revenue base to the subnational&#13;
governments during a period when, as a part of an austerity program,&#13;
it is making a strong effort to reduce its own fiscal deficit. 44/ To&#13;
transfer additional responsibilities to the subnational governments,&#13;
without making adequate allowance for their financing, of course, would&#13;
only make matters worse.&#13;
42/  C.M.P. de Albuquerque and J.D. de M. Gomes, "Reforma Tributaria:&#13;
Uma Visa'o Consolidada das Propostas Estaduais," Fundasao JP; Analise&#13;
e Conjuntura, XIII, 13 (1983), 72-78.&#13;
43/ A.K. Gomes and C.M.P. de Albuquerque, "Reforma Tributaria: Aspectos&#13;
Economicos da Proposta do Grupo Interministerial", Fundagco JP;&#13;
Analise e Conjuntura, XIII, 13 (1983), 79-83.&#13;
44/ This dilemma is discussed in P.R. Haddad, Bases Para a Reforma&#13;
Tributaria no Brasil (Belo Horizonte, 1982).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
Albuquerque, C. M. Pontes de, and&#13;
J. D. de Magalhaes Gomes. "Reforma&#13;
Tributaria: Uma Visao Consolidada das&#13;
Propostas Estaduais", Fundaago JP;&#13;
Analise e Conjuntura, XIII,&#13;
(1983), 72-78.&#13;
Aradjo, A.B. de, M. H. T. Taques Horta, and&#13;
C. M. Considera. Transferencias de Impostos&#13;
aos Estados e Municipios. Rio de Janeiro:&#13;
IPEA./INPES, 1973.&#13;
Brasil, Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e&#13;
EstELtisticd (IBGE). Estatlsticas Econ8micas do&#13;
Governo Estadual e Municipal, 1978. Rio de&#13;
Janeiro, 1980.&#13;
Metodologia da Pesquisa Nacional par Amostra de&#13;
DomLcilios na D6cada de 1970. Rio de Janeiro,&#13;
1981.&#13;
Brasil. Ministifrio da Fazenda. Secretaria de&#13;
Economia e Financas. Fontes de Financiamento&#13;
aos Estados. Brasflia, 1980.&#13;
Brasil. Ministfrio da Fazenda. Secretaria de&#13;
Economia e Finanqas. Fontes de Financiament:os&#13;
aos Municdpios. Brasflia, 1980.&#13;
Brasil. Ministfrio da Fazenda. Secretaria de&#13;
Economia e Finantas. Finangas do Brasil, XLII&#13;
(1.981).&#13;
Brasil.. Presid#ncia da Republica. Secretaria de&#13;
Plmnejamento. III Plano Nacional de&#13;
De_senvolvimento, 1980-85. Brasilia, 1980.&#13;
DoellLnger, C. von. "Estatizacao, Finanqas Putblicas&#13;
e suas Implicacoes", Camara de Estudos e Debates&#13;
Econ6micos e Sociais - CEDES, Relatorio de&#13;
Pesquisa 1 (1981).&#13;
Fundagao Getulio Vargas. Centro de Estudos Fisicais.&#13;
Regionaliza ao das Transap3es do Setor P4blico -&#13;
1975. Rio de Janeiro, 1980.&#13;
Fundagao IPARDES. "Participagavo do Setor P¢blLco na&#13;
Economia Paranaense", Relatorio de Pesquisa I&#13;
(1.980).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54 -&#13;
Gomes, A.K., and C.M. Pontes de Albuquerque.&#13;
"Reforma Tributaria: Aspectos Econ6micos&#13;
da Proposta do Grupo Interministerial",&#13;
Fundacao JP; Analise e Conjuntura, XIII, (1983),&#13;
79-83.&#13;
Haddad, P.R. Bases para a Reforma Tributaria no&#13;
Brasil. Belo Horizonte, 1982.&#13;
Instituto Brasileiro de Administracao Municipal&#13;
(IBAM). Pesquisa Sobre as Relacoes Inter-&#13;
governamentais: 0 Estado e o Municipio. Rio de&#13;
Janeiro, 1974.&#13;
International Monetary Fund. Government Finance&#13;
Statistics Yearbook, VI (1982).&#13;
Longo, C.A. "Controversias Sobre o ICM no Comercio&#13;
Interstadual: Uma Resenha, Pesquisa e Planejamento&#13;
Econ8mico, XI, 1 (1981), 229-49.&#13;
Longo, C.A., and A.E. Muller. "Impacto Regional das&#13;
Financas Federais", in Proceedings of the IX&#13;
Encontro Nacional de Economia, Olinda, Pernambuco,&#13;
Dec. 8-11, 1981; Vol 4, pp. 1663-83.&#13;
Mahar, D.J. "Federalismo Fiscal no Brasil:&#13;
A Experigncia Historica", Revista ABOP, II, 2,&#13;
(1976), 29-82.&#13;
Mahar, D.J. "The Failures of Revenue Sharing in&#13;
Brazil and Some Recent Developments", Bulletin&#13;
for International Fiscal Documentation, XXV, 3&#13;
(1971), 71-80.&#13;
Mahar, D.J., and F.A. Rezende da Silva. "The Growth&#13;
and Pattern of Public Expenditure in Brazil, 1920-&#13;
1969", Public Finance Quarterly, III, 4 (1975),&#13;
380-99.&#13;
Pastore, A.C. "Avaliacao Critica da Reforma&#13;
Tributaria de 1965", Revista de Finansas P'blicas,&#13;
XLI, 348 (1981), 4-32.&#13;
Reflexos da Reforma TributSria de 1966 nas Financas&#13;
Estaduais", Revista de Finangas Publicas, XXXVIII,&#13;
336 (1978), 47-80.&#13;
"Reflexos da Reforma Tributaria de 1966 nas Financas&#13;
Municipais", Revista de Finangas Publicas, XXXIX,&#13;
337 (1979), 43-60.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
Silva, F.A. Rezende da. Autonomia Polltica e&#13;
Depend6ncia Financeira: Uma Andlise das&#13;
Transformagses Recentes nas Rela8o'es&#13;
Intergovernamentais e seus Reflexos Sobre&#13;
a Situaca"o Financeira dos Estados," Pesquisa e&#13;
Planelamento Econ8mico, XII, 2 (1982), 489-540.&#13;
Silva, F.A. Rezende da. "0 Financiamento da Politica&#13;
SociaL", Pesquisa e Planejamento Econ8mico, X, 1&#13;
(1980), 123-46.&#13;
Silva, F.A. Rezende da and M. da Concei,ao Silva. 0&#13;
Siste1na Tributario e as Desigualdades Regionais:&#13;
Uma Analise da Recente Controversia Sobre o ICM.&#13;
Rio de Janeiro, IPEA/INPES, 1974.&#13;
Tait, A.A., W.L.M. Gratz, and B.J. Eichengreen.&#13;
International Comparisons of Taxation for&#13;
Developing Countries, 1972-76", IMF Staff Papers,&#13;
XXVI, 1 (1979).&#13;
Trebat, T.J. Brazil's State-Owned Enterprises: A Case&#13;
Study of the State as Entrepreneur. Cambridge&#13;
University Press, 1983.&#13;
Tyler, W.G. Manufactured Export Expansion and&#13;
Indus;trialization in Brazil. J.C.B. Mohr:&#13;
Tiibingen, 1976.&#13;
Varsano, R. "0 Sistema Tributario de 1967: Adequado&#13;
ao Brasil de 80?", Pesquisa e Planejamento&#13;
Econ;5mico, XI, 1 (1981), 203-27.&#13;
Viacava, C. "Reforma Tributaria", Revista de Finansas&#13;
Pdblicas, XLII, 351 (1982), 4-7.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I BRD-15685&#13;
'b.                     '.o.;7N              .      '*                         o               APRIL  1981&#13;
(VENEZUELA      ,         .-      (FREr      s.AL&#13;
j~  !SURINAME\UIA&#13;
C O L O M B I A , -          BooVista 7j&#13;
-A. RORAP'A (RAMAPA&#13;
Ry  ~~~~~ ~-TERRITORY&#13;
0'    f           /O   C'~A    E    A          ARANHAO                       A&#13;
TeresrnaoCEARA 1Rio GRA E DO NORTE&#13;
l.  PA?AiB,b Jo6o Pessoa&#13;
E  /  _;  r   r,&gt;x.  A0  j \  &gt;A  I t        } g   1  / P ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~I A U I  &gt;&lt;=t  {&#13;
.PAO5JR ,_&lt;erlth°tt tt &lt;-*-&lt; ................ _ ) . 1.  toR NfAMBU                    R efB&#13;
P E R U                                         TERTRX 0                   4                         (  ( ;jEGPE&#13;
i          \_,    } G  R \OSs   5 / OG  0  G O     A 5 2  i?/S/lao&#13;
O                                                      Sob uabJ   J   RA iIs&gt;+&gt;   ,Sa,hF  -A  GOAS&#13;
\   (  B O L I V I A                        Goldnij   )&#13;
I~NMA      OMOOSSO                 INA5     r A I    ,r&#13;
P A C /F I                                        Cao Grande f    hei               EPiIO AT&#13;
Conp Irne        M,      St Belo   XESP] ITO SANTO&#13;
DO SU   f1~Horizo.r &#13;
/                                       ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~Vitai  A T I A Nt r  C&#13;
-20                I !  &gt;_-. r's           l . ^        ,or32J SAO PAULO:                                       201&#13;
OCEAN  1/n           \.PARAGUAY                           t_   RIO DE   EIro       0 C E A N&#13;
HILE                       4                   Sao           Rio de Janeiro&#13;
/   &lt;      ~~~~~~Curitiba""i&#13;
. == = 2                                   _______   SANTA CATARI A&#13;
I  SOT R ZII orian' i,                                                              Ct DA 711&#13;
(. eeAZL    )            A R G E N T I     °ig AForofi --- @= NationaRl ci&#13;
IOGRANDE DO SUL&#13;
t AME(ItCAJ     (                     0,  +/@                                            aiorlcp&#13;
:  {   J   hin. ,ph fls beeo, p,eP,a410,. ts\  Porto Alegre            *  State and territory capitals&#13;
O  {   . a A JANT/I  ;. :: :-  :  ......., "   9xp/  I   \&lt;,  Petg KILOMETERS 0  100 200 300 400 500  __  _  .  State and territory boundaries&#13;
-.  OCEAN J- _  dono  o  .nihponos'the  |                   MILES O  10  200  300  .   International boundaries&#13;
SOnGS  S  pl onts   the br  l  I a t , o  U R U G U A Y                   Rivers&#13;
1k 1  K   dmyrcuiS M wny#ndorsamdnI         Y 6                         40                    30&#13;
_ or eeepeensc Ctl= bo/dlS 6000.0   AVOO&amp;50 , 30-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MWord Bank                         Aggregate Demand and                  Capital Market Imperfec-&#13;
Macroeconomic Imbalances             tions and Economic&#13;
Publications                       in Thailand: Simulations             Development&#13;
of Related                         with the SIAM 1 Model                Vinayak V. Bhatt and&#13;
Waflk Grais                          Alan R. Roe&#13;
Initerest                          Focuses on the demand-side adjust-   World Bank 'Staff Working Paper&#13;
ments of the Thai economy to lower   No. 338. July 1979. 87 pages&#13;
agricultural growth and to higher    (including footnotes).&#13;
energy prices. Discusses policy&#13;
measures and structural changes that  Stock No. WP-0338. $3.00.&#13;
might enable the economy to over-&#13;
come these problems and continue to&#13;
maintain high GDP rates of growth.   The Changing Nitature of&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   Export Finance and Its&#13;
448. April 1981. 70 pages (including  Implications for Developing&#13;
2 appendixes).                       Countries&#13;
Stock No. WP-0448. $3.00.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No..&#13;
409. July 1980. 43 pages (including&#13;
An Analysis of                      .3 annexes).&#13;
Developing Country                   3 ane.&#13;
Adjustment Experience and            Adjustment Experiences In            Stock No. WP-0409. $3.00.&#13;
Grcowth Prospects of the             the 1970s: Low-income Asia&#13;
Seinl-Industrial Countries           Christine Wallich                   Compounding and Dis-&#13;
FredJerick Jaspersen                This background study for World      counting Tables for&#13;
This background study for World      Development Report 1981 examines     Project Evaluation&#13;
Devulopment Report 1981 examines     low-income South Asia's adjustment   J. Price Gittinger, editor&#13;
the successful process of adjustment  to the external shocks of the 1970s,  Easily comprehensible, convenient&#13;
to extemal "shocks" of the 1970s     especially those factors that helped  tables for project preparation and&#13;
(rising prices of oil Imports, reduced  make the effects of these external  analysis.&#13;
demand for exports, slower economic  developments less severe in the&#13;
groiAth in the OECD countries) In the  region than in other parts of the  The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
semi-industrial developing countries.  developing world.                  1973; 7th printing, 1982.143 pages.&#13;
Presemts an analytical framework for  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  LC 75-186503. ISBN 0-8018-1604-1,&#13;
quaritifying the effects of demand   487. August 1981. iu + 39 pages      $6.00 paperback.&#13;
mana3gement and structural adjust-  (including references).              Arabic: World Bank.1973. (Available&#13;
men;: In forty-two countries, with par-                                  Aai:WrdBn,17.(vial&#13;
ticul.ar reference to Uruguay, Brazil,  Stock No. WP-0487. $3.00.         from ILS, 1715 Connecticut Avenue,&#13;
Republic of Korea, and Turkey.                                            N.W., Washington, D.C. 20009, U.S.A.)&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   Aspects of Development               $4.00 paperback.&#13;
477. A4ugust 1981. 132 pages (including  Bank Management                  French: Tables d'interets composes et&#13;
3 appendixes).                       William Diamond and                  d'actualisatioil. Economica, 4th print-&#13;
Stock No. WP-0477. $5.00.            V. S. Raghavan                      ing, 1979.&#13;
Deals exclusively with the manage-   ISBN 2- 71 78-0205-3, 36 francs.&#13;
Aju-Istment in                        ment of development banks, The      Spanish: Tablas de interes compuesto y&#13;
Low-Income Africa                    book Is divided Into eight sections,  de descuento para evaluaci6n de proyec-&#13;
Robert Liebenthal                    each dealing with one aspect of      ds ditora enos.1973 4t print-&#13;
management of its problems, and      tos. Edito1al Tecnos,91973 4th print-&#13;
This 3ackground study for World      of the various ways of dealing      Ing, 1980.&#13;
Deve!opment Report 1981 analyzes     with them.                           ISBN 84-309-0716-5, 380 pesetas.&#13;
the a iJustment to external shocks&#13;
during the 1970s made by a group     EDI Series in Economic Development.&#13;
of middle-income and low-income      The Johns Hopkins University Press,  A Concepitual Approach to&#13;
Afriain countries, with particular   1982. 311 pages.                     the Analysis of External Debt&#13;
reference to Kienya, Tanzania,&#13;
Senegal, and Sudan.                  LC 81-48174. ISBN 0-8018-2571-7,     of the Deireloping Countries&#13;
$29.95 hardcover: ISBN 0-8018-2572-5,  Robert Z. Aliber&#13;
Worl; Bank Staff Working Paper No.   $12.95 paperback.                    World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
486.ungust1981. vibliogr 56ppage421. October 1980. 25 pages (including&#13;
(incIl ding bibliography).                                                apni.rfrne)&#13;
Stock No. WP-0486. $3.00.                                                 Skappendox, references).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0486. $3,00.                              S~~~~~~~~~tock No. WP-0421. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
fll  sopment Banks                   Developjments In and                Food Policy Issues In&#13;
William Diamond                      Prospects for the External          Low-income Countries&#13;
Operating experiences that serve as a  Debt off the Developing           Edward Clay and others&#13;
practical guide for developing coun-  Countries: 1970-80                 A background study for World&#13;
tries, with a selected list and      and Beyond                          Development Report 1981. Discusses&#13;
summary description of some          Nicholas C. Hope                    food distribution-especially its&#13;
development banks.                                                       insecurity in the face of external&#13;
This background study for World      economic pressures and potential&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press,  Development Report 1981 analyzes    conflicts with internal production&#13;
1957; 5th printing, 1969.141 pages  the debt situation and its implica-  concerns-in general and with&#13;
(including 2 appendixes, index).    tions for future borrowing.          reference to Bangladesh. Zambia.&#13;
LC 57-13429. ISBN 0-8018-0708-5,     World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  and India.&#13;
$5.00 (£3.50) paperback.             488. August 1981. 70 pages (including  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
2 annexes, references).              473. August 1981. vii + 115 pages.&#13;
UDellDpment Finance Com-             Stock No. WP-0488. $3.00.           Stock No. WP-04 73. $5.00.&#13;
pmm A(eAspects of Policy&#13;
nd1 Operation                        Energy Prices, Substitution,        A General Equilibrium&#13;
William Diamond, editor;             and Optimal Borrowing in            Analysis of Foreign&#13;
essays by E. T. Kuiper,              the Short Run: An Analysis          Exchange Shortages In a&#13;
Douglas Gustafson, and               of Adjustment in Oil-               Developing Economy&#13;
P M. Mathew                          Importing Developing                Kemal Dervis, Jaime de Melo,&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press,  Countries                           and Sherman Robinson&#13;
1968.130 pages (including appendix,  Ricardo Martin and                   Examines the consequences of alter-&#13;
index).                              Marcelo Selowsky                     native adjustment mechanisms to&#13;
LC-68-27738. ISBN 0-8018-0166-4,     Develops a short-term model for      foreign exchange shortages in semi-&#13;
$5.00 (£3.25) paperback.             evaluating the adjustment (par-     industrial economies. Compares&#13;
French: Les societes financieres de  ticularly, extemal borrowing) of oil-  devaluation to two forms of import&#13;
developpement: quelques aspects de  importing developing countries to the  rationing and finds that adjusting by&#13;
leur politique et de leurs activites.  increases in oil prices during the  rationing is much more costly in&#13;
(Available free from the World Bank  1970s. Discusses the borrowing       terms of lost gross domestic product.&#13;
Washington, D. Cf)                   strategies that can be expected in the  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Washington, D.C.)          ~~future and the demands that will be  445. January 1981. 52 pages (includ-&#13;
Spanish: Las compafias financieras   made on multilateral institutions.  4ng r   ences).&#13;
de desarrollo: algunos aspectos de su                                    ing references).&#13;
politica y de sus actividades. Editorial  World Bank Staff Working Paper No. Stock No. W-0443. $3.00.&#13;
Tecnos, 1969.                        466. July 1981. 77 pages (including&#13;
300 pesetas.                         footnotes, references).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0466. $3.00.                NEW&#13;
DeDelopment Prospects                                                     Growth and Structural&#13;
off Capital Surplus On-              Exchange Rate Adjustment            AGoustment In East Asia&#13;
E&amp;poirtng Countries: Iraq,           under Generalized Currency           Parvez  nlis  in&#13;
lnw2At, ILibya, Qatar.               Floating: Comparative&#13;
Sam&amp;di Arabia, UAE                   Analysis among Developing           Analyzes the economic performance&#13;
Rudolf Hablutzel                     Countries                           of the five large market economies of&#13;
Rudolf HablutzeiRomo M                   ButitaEast Asia-Korea, Thailand, the&#13;
This background study for World      Romeo M. Bautista                    Philippines, Malaysia, and&#13;
Development Report 1981              Examines the experiences of twenty-  Indonesia-during the last two&#13;
discusses the production strategies  two developing countries in adapting  decades; focuses on the key factors&#13;
and the development policies of the  to the generalized floating of the   explaining their remarkable economic&#13;
capital-surplus oil-exporting        world's major currencies since 1973  and social progress; and identifies the&#13;
countries.                           and discusses the implications that  main economic issues for the 1980s.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   currency floating has on policymaking  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
483Bn AgStaff81. Workin Pages (iNcl g  in these countries and indicates direc-  529. 1982. 42 pages.&#13;
485. August 1981. 55 pages (including  tions for further research.&#13;
statistical tables).                 World Bank Staff Working Paper Po.  ISBN 0-8213-0102-0. $3.00.&#13;
Stock No. WP-0483. $3.00.            436. October 1980. 99 pages (inciuding&#13;
appendix).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0436. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Inlernational Adjustment in         Notes on the Mechanics of            ect appraisal. To give substance to&#13;
the 1980s                           Growth and Debt                      the applied and policy dimensions,&#13;
Vij ay Joshi                       Benjamin B. .K.,.many of the readings are drawn from&#13;
Vi ay Joshi                         Boenjamin B. Ki,ng                   the experience of development prac-&#13;
A backgound study for World         A practical model to explore the way  titioners and relate to such important&#13;
Deuelopment Report 1981. Analyzes   in which capital inflow from abroad  sectors as agriculture, industry,&#13;
the macroeconomics of intemational  affects economic growth.            power, urban services, foreign trade,&#13;
adjustment. Highlights potential    The Johns Hopkins      .Press,      and employment. The principles&#13;
market failures and areas for                       University          outlined are therefore relevant to a&#13;
interventIon.                       1968. 69 pages (including 4 annexes).  host of development problems.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  LC 68-8701. ISBN 0-8018-0338-1. $5.00  The Johns Hopkins University Press.&#13;
485. August 1982. 57 pages.         (3.00) paperback.                    February 1983. About 304 pages.&#13;
ISBY 0-8213-0062-8. $3.00.                                               LC 82-7716. ISBN 0-8018-2803-1,&#13;
The Policy Experience of             $35.00 hardcouer: ISBN 0-8018-2804-X,&#13;
Twelve Less Developed                $12.95 paperback.&#13;
NEW                             Countries, 1973-1978&#13;
Bela Balassa                        Private Bank Lending to&#13;
The Nature of Credit                Uses the methodology applied in the  Developing Countries&#13;
Mairkets in Developing              author's "The Newly Industrializing  Richard O'Brien&#13;
Co'untries: A Framework             Developing Countries after the Oil&#13;
for Policy Analysis                 Crisis" (World Bank Staff Working   A background study for World&#13;
Anind Virmani                       Paper No. 473, October 1980) to     Development Report 1981.&#13;
examine the policy experience of     Describes the evolution of relation-&#13;
Thc central purpose of the paper Is to  twelve less developed countries in  ships between private banks and&#13;
anEzlyze various forms of government  the period following the quadrupling  developing countries.&#13;
Intcrvention in the loan market in  of oil prices in 1973-74 and the     World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
tenns of their effect on efflciency.  world recession of 1974-75.       482.     St191 virki54 Pages&#13;
482. August 1981. ui + 54 pages&#13;
Would Bank Staff Working Paper No.  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  (including appendix. bibliography).&#13;
524. 1982. 204 pages.               449. April 1981. 36 pages (including  Stock No. WP-0482. $3.00.&#13;
ISB,Y 0-8213-0019-9. $5.00.         appendix).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0449. $3.00.&#13;
Private Capital Flows to&#13;
The Newly Industrializing                                                Developing Countries and&#13;
Developing Countries after          The Political Structure of          Their Determinations:&#13;
the OH Crisis                       the New Protectionism                Historicali Perspective,&#13;
Bela Balassa                        Douglas R. Nelson                   Recent Experience, and&#13;
Woi Id Bank Staff Working Paper No.  This background study for World    Future Prospects&#13;
43 7. October 1980. 5 7 pages (including  Development Report 1981       Alex Flem ing&#13;
appendix).                          presents a political-economic&#13;
analysis of what has been called the  A backgound study for World&#13;
Stocxk No. WP-0437. $3.00.          "new protectionism."                 Development Report 1981.&#13;
Discusses the nature and determina-&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  tion of recent private capital flows to&#13;
Notes on the Analsis of             471. July 1981. 57 pages (including  developing countries. Focuses on&#13;
Caipital Flows to Developing        references).                        those flows passing through the&#13;
internationail banks and examines the&#13;
Nations and the                     Stock No. WP-04 71. $3.00.           prospects for and constraints on&#13;
Riecycling" Problem                                                      developing countries' continuing&#13;
Ralph C. Bryant                                                          access to the international capital&#13;
A backgound study for World              NEW                             markets.&#13;
Deuelopment Report 1981.                                                 World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Summarizes and criticizes the con-  Pricing Policy for Develop-          484. August 1981. 41 pages.&#13;
vend:ional analysis of the interrela-  ment Management&#13;
tions between financial markets In  Gerald M. Meier                      Stock No. WP-0484. $3.00.&#13;
the Industrialized countries and capi-&#13;
tal flows to the developing nations.  Presupposing no formal training in&#13;
economics, it explains the essential  Prvate Direct Foreign&#13;
Wor!d Bank Staff Working Paper No.  elements of a price system, the      Investment in Developing&#13;
476. August 1981. 67 pages.         functions of prices, the various     Countri&#13;
Stock No. WP-04 76. $3.00.          policies that a government might     K. Billerieck and Y. Yasugi&#13;
pursue In cases of market failure,K.BlebcanY.asg&#13;
and the principles of public pricing of  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
goods and services provided by      348. July 1979. iv t  97 pages (includ-&#13;
govemment enterprises. It also pro-   .&#13;
vides the would-be practitioner with  ing 2 annexes).&#13;
an appreciation of the underlying   Stock No. Wi'-0348. $5.00.&#13;
logical structure of cost-benefit proj-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NEW                             Structural Adjustment               implications in terms of income&#13;
Policies in Developing              generation. external deficit, and&#13;
Short-Run Macro-Economic            Economies                           inflation.&#13;
Adjustment Policies in              Bela Balassa                        World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
South Korea: A Quantitative         Examines structural adjustment      513. June 1982. 93 pages (including&#13;
Analysis                            policies (policy responses to external  appendix).&#13;
Sweder van Wijnbergen               shocks, such as the quadrupling of  ISBN 0-8213-0023-7. $3.00.&#13;
oil prices and the world recession of&#13;
An analysis of the startling reversal of  the 1970s) of developing countries.&#13;
performance of the South Korean     Considers reforms in production     World Debt Tables&#13;
economy In 1979 and 1980 compared   incentives, incentives to save and to Acopltnofdaonhexerl&#13;
with the preceding fifteen years. and  invest, public investments, sectoral  A compilation of data on the external&#13;
an exploration of the short-run     policies, and monetary policies, and  public and publicly-guaranteed debt&#13;
macro-economic policy options       comments on the Interdependence of  of 101 developing countries plus&#13;
available to Korea in 1981. ilighlights  the various policy measures and on  eighteen additional tables of private&#13;
the role of commercial banks, foreign  the international environment in  and nonguaranteed debt from the&#13;
capital inflows, and money markets  which they operate.                 World Bank Debtor Reporting&#13;
and the use of credit obtained from                                     System. Describes the nature, con-&#13;
these sources to finance fixed and  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  tent, and coverage of the data;&#13;
working capital.                    464. July 1981. 36 pages.           reviews the external debt of 101&#13;
World Bank Staff Wiorking Paper No.  Stock No. WP-0464. $3.00.          countries throetrnalh public debt out-&#13;
510. November 1981. iv + 178 pages                                      standing, commitments, disburse-&#13;
(including 3 appendixes).                                               ments, service payments, and net&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0000-8. $5.00.              NEW                             borrowings of 101 developing coun-&#13;
tries, by country, 1972-1981.&#13;
Structural Aspects of               (EC-167/81). December 1982. Annual.&#13;
NEW                             Tuirkish Inflation:                 About 300 pages.&#13;
ISSN 0253-2859. $75.00.&#13;
State Finances In India             M. Ataman Aksoy                     Computer tapes containing the data&#13;
A three-volume set of papers that   Inflation has been one of the major  bases for the World Debt Tables are&#13;
explores a range of issues relating to  problems of the Turkish economy  available from the Publications&#13;
the nature of intergovemmental fiscal  during the postwar period. This paper  Distribution Unit, World Bank. The&#13;
relations in India.                 develops altemative inflation models  tapes are available to intemational&#13;
and analyzes their performance in   agencies and official nonprofit agen-&#13;
VoL. I: Revenue Sharing         light of the Turkish experience in  cies of member governments at a&#13;
VoL I., Revenue Sharing             order to provide a framework on      nominal fee. For information concem-&#13;
in India                            which a more realistic macro model   ing fees for other organizations,&#13;
Christine Wallich                   can be developed.                   please write to the addressee listed&#13;
Deals specifically with the principles  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  aboue.&#13;
of revenue sharing in India.        540.1982.118 pages.                  Supplements to World Debt Tables are&#13;
ISBN1 0-8213-0098-9. $5.00.         issued periodically as information&#13;
Vol. Il: India-Studies in                                                becomes available; the current&#13;
State Finances                                                           updates are included with orders for&#13;
Christine Wallich                       NEW                              World Debt Tables.&#13;
Examines in detail the implications of&#13;
revenue sharing for project finance.  Thailand: An Analysis of           REPRNTS&#13;
Structural and N1on-                The Impact of Contractual Savings on&#13;
Structural and Non-  ~     Resource Mobilization and Allocation:&#13;
Vol. III: The Measurement of        Structural Adjustments               The Experience of Malaysia&#13;
Tax Effort of State Govern-         Arne Drud, Wafik Grais, and          Social Security Funds in Singapore&#13;
ments, 1973-1976                     Dusan Vujovic                       and the PhIlippines: Ramifications of&#13;
Raja J. Chelliah and                This study was prepared as a         Investment Polides&#13;
Narain Sinha                        background paper for the preparation  Investments of Socdal Security Funds&#13;
Attempts to evaluate the tax perfor-  of a structural-adjustment loan to  and Experience&#13;
mance of particular states in terms of  Thailand and is a follow-up to a pre-  Parthasarathi Shome and&#13;
the average tax effort of all states.  vious paper entitled "Aggregate  lKatrine Anderson Saito&#13;
Demand and Macroeconomic            World Bank Reprint Series: Nlumber 144.&#13;
World Bank Working Paper No. 523.   Imbalances in Thailand:' Comparative  Reprinteld from The Malayan Economic Review, vol.&#13;
September 1982. vol. I, 85 pages, vol. II,  statistics are used, within the frame-  23, no. 1 (April 1978):54-72; Labour and Society,&#13;
186 pages, vol. III, 85 pages.      work of a four-sector macroeconomic  vol. 5. no. I (January 1980):19-30: and The Indian&#13;
ISBN0-813-013-. vl. 1 $300, ol.11, model, to assess alternative ways of  Joumnal of Economics, vol. 60, part .3. no. 2.38&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0013 X. vol. I, $5.00, vol. Il,  macroeconomic adjustment in the  (January 1980).349-60.&#13;
$5.00, vol. III, $3.00.             Thai economy. Discusses specifically  Stock N1o. RP-0144. Free of charge.&#13;
fiscal policy interventions, manipula-&#13;
tions of the exchange rate, and pro-&#13;
ductivity improvements and their&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Policy Responses to External Shocks in&#13;
Selected Latin American Countries&#13;
Bela Balassa&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Number 221.&#13;
Reprinted from Quarterly Review of Economics and&#13;
Business. vol. 21. no. 2 (Summer 1981)P.131-64.&#13;
Stock Nlo. RP-0221. Free of charge.&#13;
Restructuring the World Economy:&#13;
Round If&#13;
Holils Chenery&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: (lumber 204.&#13;
Reprinted from Foreign Affairs&#13;
(Summer 1981):d02-U20.&#13;
Stock Nlo. RP-0204. Free of charge.&#13;
Rsk Assessments and Risk Premiums&#13;
in the Eurodoflar Market&#13;
Gershon Feder and Knud Ross&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: (umber 220.&#13;
Reprinted from The Journal of Finance. vol. 3 7,&#13;
no. 3 (June 1982):679-91.&#13;
Stock (lb. RP-0220. Free of charge.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WlVORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
ORDER FORM&#13;
SEND TO:&#13;
WNORLD BANK PUBLICATIONIS                                                      WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
l'O. BOX 37525                                             or                  66, AVENUE D'IENA&#13;
NASHINGTON, D.C. 20013                                                         75116 PARIS, FRANCE&#13;
IJ.S.A.&#13;
14ame:&#13;
Address:&#13;
Stock or ISBN #                            Author, Title                        Oty.       Price          Total&#13;
Sub-Total Cost:    _&#13;
Postage &amp; handling fee for more than two free items ($1.00 each):&#13;
Total copies:             Air mail surcharge ($2.00 each):&#13;
TOTAL PAYMENT ENCLOSED:&#13;
Mlake checks payable: WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
Prepayment on orders from individuals is requested. Purchase orders are accepted from booksellers, library suppliers, libraries, and institutions.&#13;
All prices include cost of postage by the, least expensive means. The prices and publication dates quoted in this Catalog are subject to change&#13;
without notice.&#13;
No refunds will be given for items that cannot be filled. Credit will be applied towards future orders.&#13;
No more than two free publications will be provided without charge. Requests for additional copies will be filled at a charge of US $1.00 per&#13;
copy to cover handling and postage costs.&#13;
Airmail delivery will require a prepayment of US $2.00 per copy.&#13;
Mail-order payment to the World Bank n,3ed not be in U.S. dollars, but the amount remitted must be at the rate of exchange on the day the&#13;
order is placed. The World Bank will also ac:ept Unesco coupons.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                         European Office               Tokyo Office                    U&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                  66, avenue d'Iena             Kokusai Building&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A        75116 Paris, France           1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234            Telephone: (1) 723-54.21      Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK           Telex: 842-620628             Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                           Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0255-8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554838">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/09/1554838/financing-state-local-government-brazil-recent-trends-issues
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/09/1554838/financing-state-local-government-brazil-recent-trends-issues</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1983/09/1554838/financing-state-local-government-brazil-recent-trends-issues</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/07/09/000178830_98101903421571/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/07/09/000178830_98101903421571/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2002-07-19T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1983-09-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Financing state and local government in
            Brazil : recent trends and issues
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Brazil's system of
            intergovernmental fiscal relations has, with some minor
            exceptions, remained unchanged for almost two decades.
            Economic, social and political conditions in the country,
            however, have undergone profound transformations during the
            same period. This paper investigates whether the mechanisms,
            established during the 1960s, for financing state and local
            governments are still adequate in the environment of the
            1980s. The main conclusion is that they are not, and that
            certain fiscal adjustments are called for in order to bring
            resource availability at the subnational level more into
            line with functional responsibilities. Given the extreme
            intra- and interregional economic disparities prevailing in
            Brazil, special attention is given to the fiscal problems of
            governments in poorer regions. The methodology used in this
            report focuses attention on the extent to which the
            intergovernmental fiscal system has achieved and maintained
            vertical balance, the balance between resource availability
            and functional responsibilities at each of the various
            levels of government, and horizontal balance, the balance
            between resources and responsibilities at given levels of
            government in different parts of the country.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Financing state and local government in
            Brazil : recent trends and issues
        </docna>
        <display_title>Financing state and local
            government in Brazil : recent trends and issues</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1983/09/1554838/financing-state-local-government-brazil-recent-trends-issues</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Banks &amp; Banking Reform,National Governance,Public Sector Management and Reform,Municipal Financial Management,Public Sector Economics</subtopic>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>Brazil</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Mahar, Dennis J.</author>
            <author>Dillinger, William R.</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South America!$!80469</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903421571</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>BY</subsc>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 612</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Public Administration, Law, and Justice</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0255-8</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Economic disparity; Expenditures; Financial
            administration; Fiscal policy; Income; Institutional
            framework; Resource availability; Local government; Levels
            of government
            accounting,ad hoc grants,administrative
            capacities,affiliates,asset
            sales,authority,autonomy,banks,Basic
            education,borrowing,bureaucratic procedures,Capital
            Expenditures,capitals,central
            government,Colonization,Constitution,Constitutional
            law,Constitutions,Current Expenditures,Debt,debt
            service,Deficit Financing,deficits,economic
            conditions,economic growth,Electricity,evasion,excise
            taxes,execution,federal government,federal
            legislation,Federal revenue sharing,Federalism,financial
            capacities,fiscal,fiscal decentralization,fiscal
            legislation,Fiscal Problems,Fiscal Reforms,fiscal
            year,government revenues,holding companies,HORIZONTAL
            BALANCE,Housing,Income,inflation,INSTITUTIONAL
            FRAMEWORK,Intergovernmental fiscal
            relations,intergovernmental fiscal system,intergovernmental
            transfers,Large Cities,legislation,levels of
            government,local government,local governments,local
            level,Local Revenue,Local Revenue Sources,local
            taxes,Ministry of Finance,Municipal Administration,municipal
            government,municipal governments,Municipal Revenue,Municipal
            Revenues,Municipal Taxes,Municipalities,national
            level,nationalism,parastatal sector,per capita
            income,politicians,provisions,public enterprises,Public
            Expenditures,public resources,Public Sector,Public
            Service,public services,public works,public works
            programs,rehabilitation,Revenue Sharing,Revenue
            Sources,roads,Rural property,Senate,social assistance,social
            security,state government,state governments,State
            Revenue,State Revenues,state taxes,street
            lighting,subsidiaries,Tax,tax administration,tax rate,tax
            rates,tax revenues,Technical
            Assistance,telecommunications,Total
            Expenditures,Transport,treasury,urban areas,Urban
            Development,VERTICAL BALANCE,water supply
        </keywd>
        <owner>LCS</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP612</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks and Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal &amp; Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Consolidation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance and Structural Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Rules</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Sustainability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macro-Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Investment Plan</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Compliance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Self Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxpayer Registry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxpayer Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Finance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipal Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Cadastre</ml:concept><ml:concept>Cadastre, Titling, Registry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks &amp; Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Revenue Sharing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Investment Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax and Revenue Policy and Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Cadastre and Land Registration</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>State Associations</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Brazil</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>