<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Exchange Rate Adjustment Under Generalized&#13;
Currency Floating: Comparative Analysis&#13;
Among Developing Countries&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 436&#13;
October 1980&#13;
..&#13;
/Vi&#13;
Prepared by: .Romeo M. Bautista (Consultant)&#13;
Economic Analysis &amp; Projections Department&#13;
Copyright © 1980&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Wash-ington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
.1'&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author&#13;
and should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated&#13;
organizations, or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
JC&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author, and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations,&#13;
or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 436&#13;
October 1980&#13;
EXCHANGE RATE ADJUSTMENT UNDER GENERALIZED CURRENCY FLOATING:&#13;
COMPARATIVE ANALYSIS AM-IONG DEVELOPING COUNTRIES&#13;
This study examines, in an admittedly limited sense, the experience&#13;
of a sample of 22 LDCs relating to exchange rate changes under generalized&#13;
currency floating with a view to drawing some implications for LDC policy-&#13;
making.   Section II develops   the framework of analysis, identifying the&#13;
basic sources of effective exchange rate (EER) changes under the post-Bretton&#13;
Woods regime which give rise to relative price effects on LDC export supply.&#13;
Major currency realignments are found to have caused a general decline in&#13;
export competitiveness in the majority of sample countries. However, both in&#13;
terms of trend and variability, the relative price effect due to foreign&#13;
exchange rate changes has generally been smaller than the observed real exchange&#13;
rate adjustments. It would appear that the price response to exchange rate&#13;
adjustments in the post-Bretton Woods period is of a very high order of practical&#13;
importance to LDC policymakers, since about 80 percent of the nominal currency&#13;
depreciation is estimated to have been added ultimately to the general price&#13;
level. The concluding part of this paper, Section VI, appraises the findings&#13;
of the study, discusses the implications for policymaking in developing countries&#13;
and indicates directions for further research.&#13;
Prepared by:.Romeo Bautista (Consultant)&#13;
Economic Analysis &amp; Projectiors Department&#13;
Copyright 0 1980&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS&#13;
Valuable comments on the preliminary papers reporting on various&#13;
parts of the study were received from many colleagues at the World Bank,&#13;
especially from James Riedel, Francis Colaco, Helen Hughes and Martin Wolf.&#13;
The preparation of this "synthesis paper" also benefited from discussions&#13;
at the seminar on "The Implications of Exchange Rate Flexibility for&#13;
Developing Countries" hosted by Economic Analysis and Projections Depart-&#13;
ment on November 16, 1979 and at the International Trade Division on&#13;
July 22, 1980. The author is indebted to Helen Hughes (who originally&#13;
suggested the study) and Nicholas Carter for logistical support, to&#13;
James Riedel for helpful discussions, to Nguyen Tho and William Shaw for&#13;
able research assistance, and Colleen Loughlin and Rebecca Sugui for&#13;
outstanding secretarial help.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CONTENTS&#13;
Page&#13;
I.  Introduction and Summary                                          1&#13;
II.  Exchange Rate Changes and Export Competitiveness                 10&#13;
Exchange Rate Policy Under Generalized Floating               10&#13;
Indices of Effective Exchange Rate and Measures of&#13;
Export Competitiveness                                     12&#13;
Derivation of EER Indices and Export Competitiveness&#13;
Measures                                                   17&#13;
III. Exchange Rate Policy, Aggregate Demand Management and&#13;
the Real Exchange Rate                                           32&#13;
IV. The Inflationary Effect of Exchange Rate Changes                  47&#13;
Introduction                                                  47&#13;
Alternative Specifications of the Price Equation              50&#13;
Empirical Results                                             58&#13;
V.  Exchange Rate Adjustments and Export Performance                 68&#13;
Introduction                                                  68&#13;
Results from Cross-Country Regressions                        69&#13;
Results from Individual Country Regressions                   74&#13;
VI.  Policy Implications and Directions for Further Research          85&#13;
Major Currency Realignments                                   85&#13;
Nominal Exchange Rate Adjustments                             88&#13;
Appendix:  Sources of Data                                             93&#13;
References                                                             96&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. INTRODUCTION AND SU114ARY&#13;
In the recent evolution of the international monetary system, an&#13;
important concern to developing countries (LDCs) has been the generalized&#13;
floating of the world's major currencies since March 1973.1/ The Jamaica&#13;
Agreement of 1976 having legitimized this basic departure from the Bretton&#13;
Woods system, it seems certain that LDCs will continue to be confronted&#13;
with the problem of adapting to the realities of floating exchange rates&#13;
in the foreseeable future.&#13;
Under the Bretton Woods system the maintenance of exchange rate&#13;
parities was a commitment of IMF member countries, and only the infrequent&#13;
official adjustment of par values occasioned exchange rate movements&#13;
vis-a-vis partner country currencies. Since the breakdown of the par&#13;
value system, developing countries have had to contend with the exogenous&#13;
changes in the exchange rates of major currencies. This would seem to&#13;
represent a potentially significant source of external economic disturbance&#13;
to developing countries with strong links in trade and payments to&#13;
developed countries. For major currency realignments can arbitrarily&#13;
alter the value of an LDC's currency vis-a-vis the currencies of its&#13;
trade partners, and hence affect thecountry's foreign trade and domestic&#13;
economy through relative price and resource allocation effects.&#13;
As previous writers (e.g., Diaz-Alejandro, 1975) have pointed&#13;
out, ikowever, currency floating by developed countries is notan "unmixed&#13;
curse" for the LDCs. While it has added to the complexity of economic&#13;
1/ See Cline (1976; pp. 12-13) for a summary of LDC attitudes to the&#13;
adoption of exchange rate flexibility by developed countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
policymaking in developing countries, it has also presented an opportunity&#13;
for LDC policymakers to undertake more active exchange rate management in&#13;
pursuing exlernal balance and other policy objectives. By wide agreement&#13;
developing countries' currencies are generally overvalued, trade controls&#13;
being used to defend unrealistic exchange rates, which contribute to the&#13;
distortion of investment incentives and inefficiency in resource allocation.&#13;
Due to domestic vested interests resistivg exchange rate adjustments,&#13;
devaluation had not been a politically attractive measure for LDC policy-&#13;
makers under the Bretton Woods system, Most devaluations in the 1950s&#13;
and 1960s had taken place "in crisis atmosphere -- usually by a government&#13;
that for years had announced its firm commitment to maintain the value&#13;
of the currency" (Krueger, 1978; p. 50), and entailed large, abrupt exchange&#13;
rate changes which frequently resulted in severe dislocations for the LDC&#13;
economy. That the decision to change the exchange rate had to be made&#13;
without the benefit of wide discussion (as it would likely induce capital&#13;
flight and speculation) also rendered difficult the formulation of rational&#13;
policies at the time.  Under present IMF rules large, once-and-for-all&#13;
devaluations are no longer necessary, since gradual (and hence less&#13;
disruptive) effective exchange rate (EER) adjustment can be undertaken that may&#13;
facilitate the correction of currency overvaluation. Moreover, the small&#13;
magnitude of exchange rate changes over time renders speculative activity&#13;
unprofitable, permitting therefore public discussion of exchange rate&#13;
policy decisions.&#13;
Such possibility of depoliticizing exchange rate adjustments has come&#13;
at a time of-giowing policy emphasis among developing countries toward export&#13;
promotion and diversification (particularly into manufactured products)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
away from the heavy import substitution drive of the 1950s and 1960s.&#13;
Related to this, "superior export performance" has been empirically&#13;
associated with rapid growth of other sources of foreign exchange earnings&#13;
(cf. Krueger, 1978), and indeed with "superior economic perfcrmance" --&#13;
1/&#13;
at least in terms of the rate of growth of real national product.-&#13;
Some interest attaches therefore to the extent to which generalized&#13;
currency floating and LDC policy reactions to it (in particular, the&#13;
type of exchange rate management adopted) have affected relative&#13;
incentives to produce for export and the export performance of developing&#13;
countries since 1973.2/&#13;
The above considerations represent the underlying motivation of&#13;
the present study. It examines, in an admittedly limited sense, the&#13;
experience of a sample of 22 LDCs relating to exchange rate changes under&#13;
generalized currency floating with a view to drawing some implications for&#13;
LDC policymaking. The developing countries in our sample are mostly in the&#13;
middle-income category,-V with relatively substantial and/or increasingly&#13;
significant exports of manufactured products in the 1970s. Significant response&#13;
to economic incentives such as that provided by a favorable exchange rate on&#13;
export profitability is deemed forthcoming only where the necessary&#13;
l/ See, for example, the recent survey of related empirical literature&#13;
by Bhagwati and Srinivasan (1978), and also Balassa (1978).&#13;
2/ There is now a large body of evidence supporting the view that the price&#13;
responsiveness of exports in developing countries is generally substantial,&#13;
and that the responses of nontraditional (mainly, manufactured) exports are&#13;
usually stronger than those of traditional exports (see, for example,&#13;
Little et al., 1970 and Krueger, 1978).&#13;
3/ Based on the World Bank classification, the exceptions are India, Pakistan&#13;
and Indonesia.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
infrastructure facilities (e.g., transport, power, commuiications) exist,&#13;
which condition may not be met in LDCs at an early stage of economic&#13;
development.&#13;
As noted elsewhere (Bautista, 1979), recent empirical studies&#13;
on the implications for developing countries of generalized currency&#13;
floating have dealt mainly with the financial aspects of the impact of&#13;
exchange rate flexibility. The "real" effects concerning trade flows,&#13;
resource allocation, output growth and income distribution, which are&#13;
important considerations for LDCs, have thus far received only scant&#13;
attention. In examining the influence of exchange rate ndjustments on&#13;
the relative incentive structure and growth of exports in developing&#13;
countries, the present study serves to provide a link through which&#13;
the further repercussions iv1 the real sphere of LDC economies could be&#13;
empirically investigated.&#13;
Section II develops the framework of analysis, identifying the&#13;
two basic sources of effective exchange rate (EER) changes under the&#13;
post-Bretton Woods regime which give rise to relative price effects on&#13;
LDC export supply. One source is the realignment of major currency&#13;
exchange rates, over which individual LDCs have no control, affecting&#13;
export profitability relative to import-competing production through its&#13;
impact on the domestic prices of exportsand imports. The country's&#13;
exchange rate policy, which determines the nominal effective exchange&#13;
rate, also gives rise to relative price effects directly influencing&#13;
export competitiveness. Other things remaining the same, an increase&#13;
in the real exchange rate -- defined as the nominal rate adjusted by the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
inflation differential (domestic versus foreign) -- raises the price of&#13;
exportables relative to home goods, which encourages the expansion of&#13;
export supply.&#13;
Following a brief discussion of the weighting procedure and data&#13;
used in calculating EER indices, the various EER measures and indices of&#13;
relative export profitability are presented and analyzed in terms of their&#13;
monthly movements and trends since March 1973 for the 22 LDCs in our sample.&#13;
Different types of "irevealed"t exchange rate policy, representing different&#13;
patterns of EER changes, are identified. As might be expected, nominal&#13;
currency depreciation, both small and large, does not lead necessarily to&#13;
a permanent improvement in the real exchange rate, in view of induced&#13;
domestic price increases that may outpace the foreign inflatiorL rate.&#13;
However, a greater proportion of sample LDCs with small, gradual EER&#13;
changes is found to have increased their export competitiveness through&#13;
currency depreciation in real terms compared to those that underwent large,&#13;
discrete devaluations and those that adopted the "crawling peg". Furthermore,&#13;
the former group of countries appears on average to have experienced the&#13;
least variability in real exchange rate. Major currency realignments are&#13;
found to have caused a general decline in export competitiveness in the&#13;
majority of the sample countries, and for most Asian and Latin American&#13;
countries the relative depreciation of the U.S. dollar vis-a-vis other major&#13;
currencies has been a dominant influence. However, both in terms of trend&#13;
and variability, the relative price effect due to foreign exchange rate&#13;
changes has generally been smaller than the observed real exchange rate&#13;
adjustments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6-&#13;
Differences in the observed changes in the real exchange rate among&#13;
sample LDCs adopting similar exchange rate policy (i.e., nominal EER&#13;
adjustment) are attributable to differences in the movement of their&#13;
domestic prices relative to foreign prices. A relevant consideration,&#13;
therefore, in any assessment of the conduct of exchange rate policy in&#13;
developing countries under generalized currency floating is the role of&#13;
macroeconomic policies in promoting balance between aggregate demand&#13;
and aggregate supply. Has macroeconomic management provided a favorable&#13;
climate for exports by holding down the differential inflation rate?&#13;
Section III of this paper examines specifically the question of whether&#13;
monetary and fiscal policies in the sample LDCs adopting different exchange&#13;
rate regimes can explain to some extent the success or failure of nominal&#13;
exchange rate adjustments in improving relative export competitiveness on&#13;
a sustained basis. The empirical analysis indicates that the effects of&#13;
macroeconomic policy are not consistently reflected in the observed movements&#13;
in the real exchange rate among the sample countries, presumably due to&#13;
the dramatic developments in the world economy in the 1970s which affected&#13;
differently'the sample LDCs and elicited different responses from them.&#13;
Moreover, the conduct of monetary and fiscal policies is not unambiguously&#13;
related to the type of exchange rate management adopted. It is therefore&#13;
not possible to infer that any of the three exchange rate regimes considered&#13;
is especially conducive to the adoption of macroeconomic policy measures&#13;
supportive of real exchange rate adjustment.&#13;
In Section IV we attempt to relate the observed movements in&#13;
the effective exchange rate to the rate of inflation in the 22 sample LDCs&#13;
during 1973-79, taking into account other possible influences on the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
domestic price level based on previous contributions to the empirical&#13;
literature. The results indicate that EER changes and excess domestic&#13;
demand can explain to a very large extent t-e observed differences in&#13;
inflation rates among the sample LDCs, and that the sensitivity of the&#13;
domestic price level to exchange rate changes does not differ significantly&#13;
among countries adopting different methods of exchange rate adjustment.&#13;
In contrast to the findings of earlier cross-country studies on the&#13;
inflationary effect of devaluations in the 1950s and 1960s, it would appear&#13;
that the price response to exchange rate adjustments in the post-Bretton&#13;
Woods period is of a very high order of practical importance to LDC&#13;
policymakers, since about 80 per cent of the nominal currency depreciation&#13;
is estimated to have been added ultimately to the general price level.&#13;
This would seem to provide justification for the caution with which&#13;
governments in developing countries tend to view currency depreciation,&#13;
at least under the conditions prevailing in the 1970s.&#13;
Section V undertakes the investigation of the influence of&#13;
exchange rate changes on export performance for the sample LDCs based&#13;
on (1) intercountry data expressed in average annual levels cr rates of&#13;
change over the observation period 1973-78, and (2) quarterly data for&#13;
individual countries for recent years. This is done for both total and&#13;
manufactured exports, utilizing two specifications of the lag structure&#13;
of export response to the movements in the two export profitability&#13;
indices derived earlier. The results emerging from the cross-country&#13;
regressions are inconclusive at best, indicating the need fdr individual&#13;
country analyses. While the relative price effect due to major&#13;
currency realignments is found to significantly affect export earnings&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
8&#13;
in fewer countries in the sample, the estimated elasticities of short-&#13;
to medium-term export response appear larger compared to those for the&#13;
real exchange rate. The negative effect on exports of the variability&#13;
of each of the two measures of export competitiveness is an additional&#13;
consideration in the empirical analysis. Again, it is the variability&#13;
of the real exchange rate that yielded statistically significant regression&#13;
coefficients for a greater number of sample LDCs. In several cases real&#13;
exchange rate uncertainty appears to be a significantly more important&#13;
influence on export earnings than the levels of the two relative export&#13;
profitability indices.&#13;
The concluding part of this paper, Section VI, appraises the&#13;
findings of the stuc.y, discusses the implications for policymaking in&#13;
developing countries and indicates directions for further research.&#13;
This study is broadly based, and it is not possible to draw strong&#13;
unambiguous conclusions from the empirical work reported here. Many&#13;
ways of improvement suggest themselves: greater disaggregation, use&#13;
of better data and more thorough in-depth analyses of individual&#13;
countries. One advantage, however, of an empirical investigation&#13;
covering many developing countries is that "it filters out some of&#13;
the unique elements that exist in each instance" (Cooper, 1971; p. 503),&#13;
at the same time that it reduces the probability of gross error arising&#13;
from sources peculiar to individual countries.&#13;
One specific generalization that can be made is the relatively&#13;
insignificant effect of major currency realignments on LDC export&#13;
competitiveness at the aggregate level. This suggests that policy&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
efforts in dealing with this new form of external economic disturbance need&#13;
to be directed to the sectoral effects, with due attention to both the&#13;
level and variability of the induced relative price effect on export supply.&#13;
Real exchange rate changes appear generally to have had a greater&#13;
impact on export profitability, although the sample LDCs also show widely&#13;
varying experiences. Correction of currency overvaluation and associated&#13;
payments imbalance under generalized floating can be facilitated by active&#13;
exchange rate management if there is proper coordination with other policy&#13;
instruments affecting the general price level. Again, more disaggregative&#13;
analysis seems warranted since there are important sectoral considerations&#13;
that typically need to be taken into account to serve the longer-term&#13;
interests of developing countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
II. EXCHANGE RATE CHANGES AND EXPORT COMPETITIVENESS&#13;
Exchange Rate Policy under Generalized Floating&#13;
There is increasing recognition that, for many developing countries&#13;
which are highly open or do not have internationally integrated capital&#13;
markets, free floating is not likely to be a viable policy option under&#13;
the present regime of generalized floating among major currencies&#13;
(cf. Crockett and Nsouli, 1977 and Branson and Katseli-Papaefstratiou,&#13;
1980). Based on McKinnon's (1963) openness criterion, if the exchange rate&#13;
were to float in a highly open LDC, contracts will be effectively denominated&#13;
in foreign exchange and there will be no basis for demand for the domestic&#13;
currency. Without asset markets which are integrated internationally,&#13;
stabilizing speculation will be absent and the floating rate will be&#13;
unstable (assuming that the Marshall-Lerner conditions concerning trade&#13;
1asticities are not met in the short run). On the other hand, fixing the&#13;
exchange rate to one or more currencies necessarily implies floating&#13;
against all other currencies under the present system of generalized&#13;
floating; hence, a genuinely fixed exchange rate is also not feasible.&#13;
Therefore, exchange rate policy in most LDCs can be represented analytically&#13;
in terms of the two policy choices: (1) what currency or basket of currencies&#13;
to peg to; and (2) how to adjust the peg. While there are diverse exchange&#13;
rate arrangements used by developing countries -- from independent floats&#13;
to joint-currency floats, crawling pegs and pegging to a basket of currencies&#13;
or to a single currency with wide or narrow bands and with frequent or&#13;
infrequent peg adjustments -- such classification "can be a misleading&#13;
guide to the actual policy being followed. Currencies that are officially&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
floating are often managed (sometimes at the cost of large changes in&#13;
reserves) to achieve a result that may be little different from formal&#13;
pegging. Conversely, with countries that maintain a formal peg, frequent&#13;
adjustments ... may be used to obviate policy changes that might otherwise&#13;
have been necessary to maintain the pegged value" (IMF Annual Report, 1976;&#13;
p. 24).&#13;
In principle, pegging to a chosen standard (whether a single&#13;
currency or basket of currencies) and adjusting the peg appropriately could&#13;
ensure attainment of a target effective exchange rate in nominal terms even&#13;
in the face of major currency realignments. Taking a simple example for&#13;
illustration, suppose that an LDC trades only with Japan (j) and the United&#13;
States (s). If base year trade shares are used as weights in measuring&#13;
the effective exchange rate (re),-L/ then the proportionate change in re&#13;
is given by:&#13;
(2.1)           re  =   (   w-w) i + ws s&#13;
where ws is the U.S. trade share, and rj and rs are the bilateral exchange&#13;
rates in units of domestic currency (say, peso) per yen and per U.S. dollar,&#13;
respectively. The yen-dollar exchange rate r* is the ratio of rs to rj;&#13;
hence&#13;
(2.2)           -i  =   is  ri*.&#13;
Substituting (2.2) into (2.1) to eliminate ij gives&#13;
(2.3)           re  =  (1 - ws) (rs - r*) +   ws is&#13;
= is - (1 - ws) i*.&#13;
1/  Variable weights due to changes in trade shares induced by exchange&#13;
rate (yen vs. dollar) movements could also be used, without affecting&#13;
the qualitative results, but would require an additional relationship&#13;
involving the substitutability between the LDC's trade flows with Japan&#13;
and the United States.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
Therefore, for any given r*, it is possible, at least in theory,&#13;
to achieve a target re by setting rs    re + (1 - ws) r*.  It is clear that,&#13;
even in the general case of n trade partners, major currency realignments&#13;
are exogenous to the LDC, while the exchange rate peg to the standard is&#13;
policy-determined. This distinction is important to recognize in LDC&#13;
policy analysis under generalized currency floating.&#13;
Indices of Effective Exchange Rate and Measures of Export Competitiveness&#13;
The geographic composition of a country's exports is usually&#13;
different from that of its imports. The effective exchange rate indices&#13;
for exports (EERx) and imports (EERm) may be expressed by weighted geometric&#13;
averages as followst&#13;
(2.4)           EER   =  H(r) wxi&#13;
x&#13;
]1   w&#13;
(2.5)           EER   =    (r.) mi&#13;
m     i&#13;
wiere wxi and wmi are the export and import weights, respectively, for the&#13;
ith partner country (~Wxi =    wmi = 1), and ri is the index of the exchange&#13;
rate, in units of the home currency per unit of i's currency, relative to a&#13;
base year level.&#13;
An export-weighted index of prices of foreign currencies in terms&#13;
of the home currency would reflect the impact of a set of exchange rate&#13;
changes on the competitiveness of exports to domestic producers. Other&#13;
things being equal, an increase in EERx raises the average profitability&#13;
of exporting, encouraging expansion of export supply. On the other hand,&#13;
an import-weighted effective exchange rate index would reflect the impact&#13;
on the cost of imported goods in terms of the home currency. Thus, EERm&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
can be directly related to the price of domestically produced goods&#13;
competing with imports. Other things remaining the same, a rise in the&#13;
import-weighted effective exchange rate improves the average profitability&#13;
of domestic import substitution, which could draw resources away from&#13;
export production.&#13;
Under the present regime of generalized floating, foreign&#13;
currency realignments affect the domestic price of exports relative to&#13;
imports, a price ratio which can be taken as an index of average export&#13;
profitability relative to import-competing production. This index&#13;
"basically seeks to capture the relative price change `t Eween exportables&#13;
-  importables on the presumption that (with the usual restrictions such&#13;
as convexity and competitiveness of markets being satisfied) this would&#13;
imply a corresponding production and hence export-level shift" (Bhagwati,&#13;
1978; p. 183). In addition to partner country currency exchange rates,&#13;
there are clearly other determinants of this index, among which are the&#13;
foreign currency prices of exports and imports, and the existence of tariffs,&#13;
surcharges, special foreign exchange taxes, import licensing and deposit&#13;
requirements on imports as well as of export taxes and subsidies. The&#13;
latter influences, associated with domestic policies which create a&#13;
wedge between local and world market prices of exports and imports, are&#13;
outside the scope of the present study.-/ While the export profitability&#13;
indices used here are admittedly of a partial nature, some interest&#13;
attaches to the separate influence of external factors such as foreign&#13;
currency realignments and changes in foreign prices.&#13;
1/ The role of domestic policies is given detailed analysis for ten LDCs in&#13;
the postwar period through the early 1970s in the recent set of NBER&#13;
studies on foreign exchange regimes and economic development (cf. Bhagwati,&#13;
1978 and Krueger, 1978).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
These external factors give rise to an export bias in the&#13;
incentive structure which may be represented by-&#13;
w i          w .&#13;
(2.6)           p        11(r.P) x/11(r P i) ml&#13;
lMiIxi             i imi&#13;
where Pxi and Pmi are the prices of exports and imports, respectively, in&#13;
country i's currency. It should be noted that, under the exchange rate&#13;
regime specified earlier, P X is invariant to the choice of currency&#13;
standard (cf. Lipschitz, 1979). Moreover, it is unaffected by peg adjust-&#13;
ments. Considering again the simple case of an LDC with Japan and the&#13;
United States as the only trade partners, suppose that the domestic&#13;
currency (peso) is pegged tothe dollar. Expressing export and import prices&#13;
in peso terms and using earlier notations,&#13;
w              1-w&#13;
(r p  ) xs (r P   /r*)   xs&#13;
(2.7)           P    ~ =     X        s xj&#13;
w              1-w&#13;
(r sP) ms (r Pmi/r*)     ms&#13;
where it is seen that rs cancels out, bearing out the above statement.&#13;
Equation (2.7) also makes clear that changes in r*, the yen-dollar exchange&#13;
rate, can affect PXM.   More generally, Pxm is affected by changes in&#13;
exchange rates among partner country currencies, but not by home currency&#13;
exchange rate adjustments with respect to the standard currency. As is&#13;
evident from (2.6), appreciation (depreciation) of export market currencies&#13;
relative to import market currencies raises (lowers) the export bias index.&#13;
1/ Since PXK is nothing but a ratio of export prices relative to import&#13;
prices, it can be interpreted as the terms of trade. See Bautista&#13;
and Riedel (1980) for ait empirical examination of quarterly terms of&#13;
trade movements among eleven developing countries and the relative&#13;
contribution of exchange rate effects in the 1960s and 1970s.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
If trade shares are fixed (cf. Branson and Papefstratiou, 1980)&#13;
or zhe underlying geographical index function is of the constant-elasticity-&#13;
of-substitution type (cf. Bautista, 1977), equation (2.6) can be transformed&#13;
into the following relationship involving proportionate changes (denoted&#13;
by a dot over the variable) in bilateral exchange rates and foreign currency&#13;
export and import prices:&#13;
(2.8)                =~w-.i+wp .                    w.P&#13;
( )     I(Wxi WmiJi    i 'xi Xi        mimi&#13;
Therefore, exchange rate realignments affect the export bias&#13;
index directly, as indicated in the first term in the right-hand side of&#13;
(2.8), and also indirectly through any induced changes in foreign currency&#13;
export and import prices. The relationship between exchange rate changes&#13;
and international price behavior of traded goods is an elusive one ar(&#13;
will be neglected here.-/ For computational purposes, the index representing&#13;
the direct effect of exchange rate changes on Pxm is defined as follows:&#13;
(2.9)          NPXM   =  exp  [  (Wxi - w  ) log r]&#13;
xi mi&#13;
The other aspect of relative export profitability considered here&#13;
relates to the substitutability in production between exports and home&#13;
goods. This index is represented by the ratio of the numerator in (2.6) to&#13;
the domestic price level,(P) termed the "purchasing-power-parity adjusted&#13;
effective exchange rate" in the NBER project, or in common usage simply&#13;
the "real exchaage rate":&#13;
w.&#13;
(2.10)         PPPEERx   = fi(ripxi) x/p&#13;
1/ See Bautista and Riedel (1980) for a further discussion which invokes&#13;
the purchasing-power-parity principle.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
It is clear that adjustment of the peg to the standard currency (or basket&#13;
of currencies) by itself, i.e., independently of foreign currency realignments,&#13;
could affect PPPEERx. This index is determined not only by exogenous foreign&#13;
price changes and the country's exchange rate policy but also by a host&#13;
of other factors influencing the general price level. Thus the&#13;
improved competitiveness accorded export industries by a depreciating&#13;
home currency could be undercut by a rise in domestic prices. This&#13;
would be related to the monetary, fiscal and trade policy measures&#13;
accompanying the exchange rate adjustment.&#13;
Not only the level but also the variability of NPXM and PPPEER&#13;
could influence an LDC's export performance. The greater instability of&#13;
major currency exchange rates after the collapse of the par value system&#13;
(cf. Artus and Young, 1979) would have contributed to the increased&#13;
uncertainty about export and import prices (in local currency terms).&#13;
There is short-term exchange risk during the period between contract and&#13;
settlement of the foreign transaction, which can be hedged by recourse to&#13;
the forward market. The availability of forward facilities in developing&#13;
countries however is limited, and even if forward cover can be obtained,&#13;
high bid-ask spreads and other transactions costs can artificially raise&#13;
the cost of exporting relative to domestic sales. Additionally, the&#13;
longer-term uncertainty about exchange rates between contracts also&#13;
entails an added cost in international trade, penalizing long-term&#13;
investment in export activities. It is clear however that the increased&#13;
exchange rate flexibility (in nominal terms) under generalized floating&#13;
could have an inhibiting effect on LDC exports only to the extent that it&#13;
is passed on to NPXM and PPPEER&#13;
x&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
Two measures of exchange rate uncertainty are used in this study.-&#13;
For the cross-country analysis of the inflationary effect of exchange rate&#13;
changes given in Section IV, it is represented by the variability of the&#13;
monthly values of EER around the trend over the observation period (March&#13;
m&#13;
1973 to December 1979). The same measure is used for the cross-country&#13;
regressions of the export coefficient in Section V, except that the monthly&#13;
values pertain to NPXM and PPPEER ; for the individual country regressions&#13;
of export earnings using time series data (also in Section V), it is repre-&#13;
sented by the variability around the mean value in the preceding 12 months.&#13;
Derivation of EER Indices and Export Competitiveness Measures&#13;
Calculation of the trade weights wxi and wmi is based on the&#13;
proportions of each LDC's exports and imports for which prices are set&#13;
in the currencies of 12 developed countries-  on the assumption that world&#13;
prices of primary agricultural products and fuels are set in U.S. dollars,&#13;
metals and minerals in British pounds, and other traded goods in the&#13;
currencies of developed country destination markets of exports or origin&#13;
of imports (cf. Bautista and Riedel, 1980). This improves on the traditional&#13;
use of bilateral trade shares in effective exchange rate calculation which&#13;
does not allow fowr pricing in third-country currencies, but is admittedly&#13;
also an imperfect weighting procedure since no account is taken of any&#13;
indirect effects on say, the U.S. dollar price of agricultural products&#13;
in the New York commodities market, of exchange rate changes involving&#13;
1/ Similar measures have been used by Abrams (1980) in his study of&#13;
bilateral trade fiows among developed countries.  It should be noted,&#13;
however, that his uncertainty measures are in terms of bilateral&#13;
exchange rates in nominal terms.&#13;
2/ Namely, the United States, Canada, Japan, United Kingdom, France,'&#13;
West Germany, Netherlands, Belgium, Italy, Switzerland, Sweden and&#13;
Australia.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
other major currencies (via the induced increases or decreases in world&#13;
demand and supply).-/&#13;
The source of data used in deriving the export and import weights&#13;
(based on the average annual trade shares during 1974-76) is the GATT&#13;
Trade System. Monthly data for bilateral exchange rates and indices&#13;
of wholesale prices (or where not available in a few countries, of consumer&#13;
prices) have been drawn from the IFS data files of the IMF.&#13;
Table 2.1 provides iniformation on the trends of the effective&#13;
exchange rate for the 22 sample countries over the period March 1973 to&#13;
2'&#13;
December 1979-' based on: (1) "price-currency total export weights" under&#13;
the assumptions given above; and (2) "manufacturing trade weights", i.e.,&#13;
using actual shares in exports and imports of manufactured products (SITC 5&#13;
to 8 minus 68).  As might be expected, countries having a high proportion&#13;
of manufactures in total exports, such as Portugal, South Korea and Spain,&#13;
show comparable values of the trend coefficient for the two EER   indices.&#13;
While this does not preclude a similar degree of comparability of values&#13;
for other countries (cf. Argentina, Brazil, Colombia and Turkey whose&#13;
manufactured exports constitute less than 25 per cent of total exports),&#13;
Table2.lindicates relatively large discrepancies between the two EER&#13;
indices for several countries (e.g., Egypt, Thailand, Indonesia and&#13;
Pakistan).&#13;
1/ It would require an elaborate world economy model to derive weights&#13;
that take into account price elasticities of world demand and supply.&#13;
For some attempts in this direction, see Rhomberg (1976) and Feltenstein&#13;
et al. (1979).&#13;
2/ Except for the following countries for which available data permitted&#13;
calculation only through the indicated month (in 1979): Greece, Mexico&#13;
(November); Spain, Turkey (October); Portugal, Indonesia (03ptember);&#13;
Egypt (July); and Morocco (May).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
Table 2.1: Trends of Monthly EER Values, March 1973-December 1979&#13;
(Estimates of b in the regression equation:  ln EER   =&#13;
a + .001 bt)&#13;
EERX weights based on:&#13;
Price-currency                  Manufactured&#13;
total export shares                export shares&#13;
Argentina                         79.92                         80.33&#13;
Brazil                            20.83                         21.99&#13;
Colombia                          7.87                           8.47&#13;
Costa Rica                        2.65                           2.88&#13;
Egypt                             4.20                           5.19&#13;
Greece                            4.32                           5.80&#13;
India                              .29                            .89&#13;
Indonesia                         3.76                           4.74&#13;
Malaysia                          -1.00                          -.52&#13;
Mexico                            10.91                         11.42&#13;
Morocco                            -.31                          1.63&#13;
Pakistan                            .34                          1.41&#13;
Philippines                        .43                           1.78&#13;
Portugal                          10.52                         f0.95&#13;
Singapore                        -1.12                           -.64&#13;
South Korea                       3.89                           4.05&#13;
Spain                             4.47                           4.93&#13;
Taiwan                            -.17                            .93&#13;
Thailand                            .25                          1.48&#13;
Tunisia                             .02*                          .66&#13;
Turkey                           11.74                          13.04&#13;
Uruguay                           31.99                         33.17&#13;
NOTE: EER = 1.00 in March 1973.&#13;
x&#13;
Asterisk (*) indicates b estimate not significantly different&#13;
from zero at the 5 per cent level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
The time profiles of the monthly values of total trade-weighted&#13;
EER given in Figure 1 indicate various types of "revealed" exchange rate&#13;
policy among the sample LDCs.  For some countries the EER   index shows&#13;
no significant departure over time from the initial values. Some&#13;
examples are Pakistan, Taiwan, Thailand, Morocco and Tunisia, for which&#13;
the monthly EER movements over the period have remained within 9 per cent&#13;
x&#13;
of the March 1973 value. In a few countries managed floating of the&#13;
domestic currency has led to an appreciation vis-a-vis the major currencies,&#13;
as exemplified by Malaysia and Singapore for which the effective exchange&#13;
rates by late 1979 were about 10 per cent lower than the initial levels.&#13;
At the other extreme the "crawling peg" countries, namely, Argentina,&#13;
Brazil, Colombia and Uruguay, have more or less continuously and&#13;
substantially depreciated their currencies during most of the period so&#13;
that by December 1979 the EER values were at least six times those&#13;
prevailing in March 1973.1/&#13;
Still another pattern of EER movements is shown by several&#13;
countries in which large currency devaluations were implemented on a&#13;
once-and-for-all basis, much like what used to happen under the Bretton&#13;
Woods system of par values.   The occurrence of discrete devaluations in&#13;
some of the sample countries is indicated below in Table 2.2, together with&#13;
the corresponding rates of EER  increase over the level prevailing in the&#13;
1/ Argentina is in a class by itself, its EERx having gone up more than&#13;
170-fold since early 1975.  The three other countries show EER   increases&#13;
within 6 to 11 times the initial level over the period from March 1973&#13;
to December 1979.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
Argentina&#13;
Brazil&#13;
Colombia&#13;
Costa Rica&#13;
Egypt    -X&#13;
Greece&#13;
India&#13;
Indonesiaa&#13;
Malaysia&#13;
Me-xico/&#13;
iar. 73   Dec.73       Dec. 4        Dec.75        Dec.76       Dec.77        Dec.78       Dec.79&#13;
Figure 1:  Time Profiles of Total Trade-weighted EER , Larch 1973 - December 1979&#13;
(in logarithmic vertical scale, March 1973 = 100)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
Morocco&#13;
Pakcistan&#13;
Philipp ineos&#13;
Singapore&#13;
South Korea&#13;
Spain&#13;
Taiwan&#13;
Tbailand&#13;
Tunisia&#13;
Turkey&#13;
Urugulay  -       f&#13;
ar.73       Dec.73        Dec. 74       Dec.75       Dec.76        Dec.77        Dec.78        Dec.79&#13;
Figure 1 (Continued)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
Tabl: 2.2: Cases of Large, Discrete Exchange Rate Changes&#13;
Percentage rise in EERX&#13;
over preceding month&#13;
Countiy          Month and Year        Total X weights    Mfd. X weights&#13;
Costa Rica      May 1974                       29.0              29.6&#13;
South Korea     December 1974                  21.7              21.8&#13;
Mexico          September 1976                 59.9               60.8&#13;
Spain           July 1977                      17.2              17.7&#13;
Turkey          March 1978                     30.5              31.7&#13;
Indonesia       November-December 1978         49.8              46.9&#13;
Egypt           January 1979                   79.2              81.2&#13;
Turkey          June-July 1979                 35.6              38.0&#13;
preceding month. Apart from these episodes, EER movements, in both&#13;
positive and negative directions, have been gradual for the rest of the&#13;
observation period. Indeed, it would appear from Figure 1 that that&#13;
relatively small movements in EER  characterize the remaining countries&#13;
in the sample, leading to moderate currency depreciation over the period.&#13;
The time profiles of the monthly values of NPXM and PPPEERx,&#13;
based on price-currency total trade and manufacturing trade weights, are&#13;
shown in Figures 2 and 3. In Table 2.3 the measures of trend and variability&#13;
of the two indices over the observation period are presented. The&#13;
derivation of these trend and variability measures is based on the&#13;
logarithmic trend regression of the monthly values of NPXM and PPPEERx;&#13;
the estimated trend coefficient (b) represents the compound monthly rate&#13;
of change, while the standard error of estimate (s.e.e.) is taken as the&#13;
measure of variability (as has been done by Aghevli (1979) among others).&#13;
Appreciable differences are observed between the results based&#13;
on total and manufactured trade weights for some countries, reflecting&#13;
the fact that the composition of major currencies in which manufactured&#13;
exports and imports of certain LDCs are priced in foreign markets can be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
1.10-                                    Argentina&#13;
1.005&#13;
1.05&#13;
1.00.                                                                                       1.00&#13;
.95                                                                                        .95&#13;
*-1&gt; =                                                               .05                                      In .. si&#13;
1.--                                                                                    1.00&#13;
1.05..&#13;
.95&#13;
1.0 &gt; v&lt;=                          +   x1.05 --Mexico&#13;
.95&#13;
1.100&#13;
1.05                                     C&#13;
1.00                                                                                         10,&#13;
1.05&#13;
.95&#13;
-95                                                                                         1.00&#13;
1.10. - -                                   Gypte&#13;
L105-                                                                                           Mm1 l#tllxilDl7llllec7ll*Morcc                           el.7      Dc78        Dc7&#13;
1.00&#13;
1.5                                                                                       Mar.73   DeI.73      ec.74      Dec.75       ec         Dec.77 DIc.78         Dec.79IIIlIIII&#13;
Mar.,73  Dec.73     Dec.74      Dec.75      Dec.76     Dec.77      Dec.78      Dec.79                     Figure 2: Time Profiles of NPXM, March 1973 - Deceabcr 1979&#13;
total trnde weightB&#13;
-manufacturing trade teighta&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
.                                               Pakistan                                            10Spain&#13;
1.05&#13;
1.00                                                                                               1.00&#13;
.95&#13;
1.05&#13;
1.00                                                                                              1.05&#13;
.95                                                                     1.00&#13;
.95&#13;
1.05&#13;
PortugaL                                            1.10&#13;
1.00                                                                                                                                               Thailand&#13;
1.05&#13;
.95&#13;
1.00&#13;
.95&#13;
1.10                                                                                                I&#13;
1.00                                                                                              1.05Tvre                                                                                          n&#13;
.95                                                                                              1.00&#13;
.95&#13;
South Korea1.00&#13;
Tunisia&#13;
1.05&#13;
1.70o                                         South Korea                                          1.00&#13;
190-                                                                                             1.10                                           Uruguay&#13;
.95&#13;
1.00 1&#13;
a  r  3   D ec         D             Dec                            7      De .Decec.79           MD.           7 3    . D e .7&#13;
Mar.3     Dc.7         De.74        Dec75         ec.6        Dc.7        De.78         Dec.79&#13;
Figure 2 (Continued)&#13;
.--- - - - -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
1.90                                 Arg.ntcin&#13;
1.80                                                                                                                      c..&#13;
1.70&#13;
1.00S ;                        Z                               .000&#13;
1.60                                 C                                                  -&#13;
1.50&#13;
1 .4S&#13;
1.30&#13;
1.20                                                                               1.00                                                             -&#13;
*1.10                                                                               .90                                Thooi&#13;
1.00                                                                                .80&#13;
.90                                                                                .70&#13;
.800-                                                                              .60&#13;
.70&#13;
1.0 -                                  Horoeco&#13;
1.00-."-t0&#13;
.90                                                        '                         3&#13;
1.30&#13;
1.00                                                                               1    7D5De&#13;
.90                                                            .ToMD&#13;
1.80                                                                                .0&#13;
|||*.IeXt0.0|§|bt"a Cee*u|i|*l||l*|l;||*l otsl tRI.&amp;                              1.40-                                 Hxt&#13;
'1.700-13&#13;
1.60                                                                                                                      Morocco&#13;
1.50-&#13;
1.80&#13;
Nar.73 Dec.73 De.7 Dec.7 Dec.76                                                                                  Dec.77      Dec.78    Dec.79De.7&#13;
- anu!acrurieg crada wieigbCe&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
1.00 -                                            Pakistan                                                          1.20                                               Spain&#13;
.90                                                                                                                1.10&#13;
.80g -                                                                                                             100&gt; &gt;9&#13;
.70                                                                                    .90&#13;
1.10                                                Taiwan&#13;
1.00                                              Phlilippines                                                      i-00&#13;
.90&#13;
.90                                                                                                                 .80&#13;
.80 - -                                                                                                             .70&#13;
.70&#13;
l                                                   Thai.80ln&#13;
1.0.0I&#13;
.90&#13;
l.-.O&#13;
.90&#13;
.80&#13;
.1 0                                             Singapore&#13;
1.00                                                                                                                 .0                                                   .ii&#13;
.90                                                                                                                10&#13;
;80t                                             ~~~1l&#13;
;80                                                                                   1.00&#13;
.90&#13;
1.20                                                Uruguay&#13;
1.100&#13;
1.00                                              South Korea                                                        ,00                                                               c&#13;
.900&#13;
,.70                                                                                                                .30-&#13;
. t:. .  . . .:i       j:   :, .     i;1   i:   i : i  t4   -        0        11 :  :   :  :  ii  I::               ... i::: i :    l!  l ll  l s-i  l  ii :  :i ::i :  : it~ ;II:   .. .           vi  1 1 19  1;  I&#13;
Mar.73     Dec.73        Dec.74         Dec.75        Dec.76         Dec.77        Dec.78        Dec.79             Mar 73     Dec.73         Dec.74        Dec.75          Dec.76       Dec.77         Dec.78        Dec.79&#13;
Figure 3 (Continued)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 2.3:  Trend and Variability of Monthly Indices of NPXM and PPPEERX, March 1973 - December 1979&#13;
(Estimates of b and s.e.e. in the regression equation: In Y = a + .001 bt)&#13;
Total Trade Weights                            Manufactured Trade Weights&#13;
NPM                  PPPEERx                      NPXM                   PPPEERX&#13;
Country           Trend    Variability    Trend     Variability      Trend    Variability    Trend     Variability&#13;
Argentina            -.586      .0329       -.777*      .2248         -1.028       .0165      -1.248*      .1996&#13;
Brazil              -.824       .0081        .845       .0461          -.582       .0121        .847       .0451&#13;
Colombia            -.764       .0222      -3.678       .0363          -.517       .0092      -3.442       .0354&#13;
Costa Rica          -.737       .0236      -1.645       .0390          -.886       .0173      -1.441       .0406&#13;
Egypt                 .170      .0096       2.741       .1540            .755      .0095       3.084       .1664&#13;
Greece              -.218       .0082        .027*      .0563            .490      .0148        .234*      .0542&#13;
India               -.888       .0082       3.860       .0477         -1.241       .0167       3.791       .0449&#13;
Indonesia          -1.548       .0366      -2.966       .0891         -1.294       .0192      -1.966       .1085&#13;
Malaysia             -.824      .0134       2.783       .0290         -1.115       .0305       2.147       .0301&#13;
Mexico               -.607      .0042       1.599       .0809          -.430       .0095       1.193       .0826&#13;
Morocco              -.608      .0088      -1.268       .0341          1.230       .0057      -2.080       .0327&#13;
Pakistan            -.240       .0052      -1.722       .0677            .124*     .0157      -1.104       .0782     ND&#13;
Philippines         -1.066      .0170       -.618       .0656         -1.464       .0322      -1.218       .0627     c&#13;
Portugal            -1.046      .0116       -.067*       .0410         -1.273      .0101       1.046       .0437&#13;
Singapore           -.759       .0174       2.588       .0427         -1.120       .0258       2.865       .0356&#13;
South Korea         -.306       .0125      -3.022       .0503         -1.698       .0410      -3.000       .0512&#13;
Spain                 .863      .0084       -.122*      .0510          -.454       .0078       -.114*      .0498&#13;
Taiwan             -1.050       .0257       1.828       .0668          -.917       .0376       2.190       .0680&#13;
Thailand           -1.150       .0280       1.302       .0362          -.983       .0273       1.670       .0460&#13;
Turkey              -.058*      .0075      -1.781       .0552            .426      .0074      -1.372       .0586&#13;
Tunisia               .731      .0135       1.438       .0481            .462      .0055       1.637       .0560&#13;
Uruguay               .032      .0028       -.186*      .1107            .300      .0197       -.028*      .1078&#13;
Asterisk (*) indicates b estimate not significantly different from zero at the 5% level&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
quite different from that for total trade. A statistically significant&#13;
negative trend in NPXM is shown for the majority of the sample developing&#13;
countries. Overall export profitability relative to import-competing&#13;
production has been enhanced by exogenous exchange rate realignments in&#13;
only four countries, each of these countries by implication a net exporter&#13;
of goods priced in relatively strong currencies. Based on manufactured&#13;
trade weights, a non-negative trend in NPXM during the period is shown&#13;
for seven sample LDCs. Both sets of NPXM trend coefficients indicate that&#13;
Indonesia, Portugal and the Philippines have been among the most severely&#13;
affected by major currency realignments. With respect to differences in&#13;
the time patterkns, it may be noted that, for most Asian and Latin American&#13;
countries, the weakening of the U.S. dollar vis-a-vis other major currencies&#13;
in 1977 appears to be behind the sustained decline in NPXM during that year;&#13;
for other countries the pattern is clearly not dominated by the relative&#13;
valuation of the U.S. dollar.&#13;
The variability measure of NPXM is characterized by a wide&#13;
spectrum of values.  Based on total trade weights, it is represented at&#13;
one extreme by Uruguay and Mexico which show the least variable NPXM among&#13;
the sample LDCs, and at the other extreme by Indonesia and Argentina,&#13;
having values of the variability measure about ten times those for the&#13;
former countries. The range of NPXM variability is relatively smaller&#13;
based on manufactured trade weights; one finds Morocco and Tunisia with&#13;
the least variability, while South Korea and Taiwan at the other extreme&#13;
are seen to have their NPXM about seven times more variable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
The number of sample LDCs showing positive trends in the PPPEER&#13;
x&#13;
index is about equal to those with negative trends. The real exchange&#13;
rate has apparently improved the most in India, Singapore, Malaysia,&#13;
Egypt and Taiwan, while at the other extreme of deteriorating PPPEERx&#13;
are such countries as Colombia, Indonesia, South Korea, Pakistan and&#13;
Turkey.&#13;
The changes in PPPEER over the period are seen to be generally&#13;
larger in magnitude compared to the NPXM index. Based on total trade&#13;
weights, the estimated trend coefficients are greater in absolute value&#13;
for the real exchange rate iidex, except for four countries (Greece,&#13;
Philippines, Portugal and Spain); in the case of the variability measure,&#13;
lower values are seen for NPXM without exception.&#13;
It is important to observe that the trend of the real exchange&#13;
rate is not unambiguously related to the conduct of exchange rate policy&#13;
in the sample LDCs as revealed by the nominal exchange rate changes over&#13;
the period. Thus, among those that showed relatively significant positive&#13;
trends in PPPEER , India and Taiwan had a rather stable EER pattern,&#13;
Malaysia and Singapore effectively appreciated their currencies slightly,&#13;
and Egypt underwent a large, once-and-for-all currency devaluation but&#13;
otherwise kept a stable exchange rate over the period.  On the othet hand,&#13;
Colombia's.crawling peg regime and the large episodic devaluations in&#13;
Indonesia and South Korea failed to provide a sustained improvement in&#13;
relative export profitability but instead resulted in a declining real&#13;
exchange rate overall.  Lastly, sample LDCs showing no trend in PPPEERx&#13;
are seen to be also a heterogenous group as far as exchange rate manage-&#13;
ment is concerned: Uruguay followed a policy of rapid and sustained&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
depreciation of its currency throughout the period, while Greece at the&#13;
other end had very gradual EERX movements leading to a modest currency&#13;
depreciation overall. It is to be noted, however, that a much larger&#13;
proportion of sample countries with relatively stable effective exchange&#13;
rates over the observation period had experienced positive trends in the&#13;
real exchange rate compared to those that adopted the crawling peg and those&#13;
that implemented large once-and-for-all devaluations.&#13;
The variability measure for PPPEER also covers a wide range&#13;
of values even among sample LDCs adopting the same exchange rate regime.&#13;
The crawling peg countries, for example, show the highest value (Argentina)&#13;
as well as one of the lowest (Colombia) in the entire sample. It is&#13;
interesting, however, that the average values indicate a higher degree&#13;
of real exchange rate variability among the crawling peggers in the&#13;
sample (.0970) than those that had small, gradual exchange rate changes&#13;
in nominal terms (.0502) and those that underwent large, discrete devaluations&#13;
(.0797). The adoption of crawling peg is sometimes viewed as a means of&#13;
reducing real exchange rate uncertainty (cf. Coes, 1979). That it is&#13;
neither a necessary nor sufficient policy measure seems clear, however,&#13;
from the above findings.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
III. EXCHANGE RATE POLICY, AGGREGATE DEMAND MANAGEMENT&#13;
AND THE REAL EXCHANGE RATE&#13;
A specific issue on which the recent experience of developing&#13;
countries in our sample might throw some light concerns the relationship,&#13;
if there is any, between the type of exchange rate adjustment adopted by&#13;
LDC governments and ability to undertake supportive fiscal and monetary&#13;
policy measures. Does a gradual depreciation of the domestic currency&#13;
allow the national authorities to conduct macroeconomic policy in line with&#13;
the requirements of real exchange rate adjustment? Large, discrete devaluations&#13;
invariably involve a difficult political decisionmaking problem, which&#13;
however may force policymakers into taking simultaneous actions on many&#13;
fronts. It has been hypothesized that small-step adjustments do not have&#13;
this advantage as the pressure would be weaker on the part of the authorities&#13;
to take strong action in the complementary areas of credit and fiscal&#13;
restraint (Bruno and Sussman, 1978).&#13;
Macroeconomic policy measures accompanying nominal exchange rate&#13;
adjustments are of course only one of many possible influences on the&#13;
behavior of the general price level. If the exchange rate change is&#13;
attended by a relaxation of trade restrictions, domestic prices need not&#13;
rise as no inflationary effect will be forthcoming where the devaluation&#13;
simply substituted for import controls. On the other hand, exogenous&#13;
developments, such as adverse terms of trade movements and bad weather,&#13;
could generate domestic inflationary pressxres independently of exchange&#13;
rate changes. Also, producers might take the opportunity to raise prices&#13;
which for any reason they have been unable to do before the devaluation;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
prime examples are public utility companies and other firms whose products&#13;
are subject to government control. The dynamics of response by wage earners&#13;
and employers to the initial increases in costs and prices will partly&#13;
determine the extent to which the effectiveness of devaluation is impaired&#13;
by increases in domestic costs. Thus, depending on their bargaining power,&#13;
workers might be able to prevent even a short-run erosion of their real&#13;
earnings, stimulating a wage-price spiral. This is reinforced by attempts&#13;
of producers to exploit monopoly power by raising product prices. The&#13;
reactions of consumers and investors to exchange rate changes would also&#13;
have an impact on aggregate demand and hence on the general level of prices.&#13;
Ultimately, however, for the general price level to increase,&#13;
there must be a permanent axpansion of money supply (or an increase in&#13;
velocity) that would validate increases in money wages and domestic prices&#13;
from any source. For cost-push types of disturbances to be a source of&#13;
continuing inflation there has to be an accompanying stimulus to aggregate&#13;
demand, as would be provided by an expansion of money supply. The role&#13;
of government policy is critical also because public expenditure represents&#13;
a major component of total "absorption" in many developing countries and&#13;
it is not uncommon that government deficit spending has led to excessive&#13;
increases in money supply. The same amount of government expenditure would&#13;
be less inflationary if financed fully by taxes or public bond issues.&#13;
Higher taxes shift demand from the general public to the government, so&#13;
that the higher spending would entail only a small one-time increase in&#13;
the price level. Likewise, bond sales to the public would shift demand&#13;
from investors to the government and cause interest rates to rise (where&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
possible), again mitigating price rises. On the other hand, financing the&#13;
increased government expenditure by money creation serves to add to, rather&#13;
than offset, the higher government demand for goods and services.&#13;
Admittedly, some part of government expenditure and subsidized&#13;
domestic credit might be directed to the expansion of productive capacity&#13;
and easing of supply bottlenecks, which are disinflationary. It will&#13;
require an intensive study of individual LDCs to provide an assessment&#13;
of the effectiveness of monetary and fiscal policies in contributing to&#13;
the expansion of aggregate supply. For purposes of the present discussion&#13;
our primary interest is in their role as instruments of aggregate demand&#13;
management.&#13;
Considering first the sample LDCs which underwent large&#13;
devaluations, we note the wide variation in the emerging patterns of real&#13;
exchange rate movements among them.   Table 3.1 below shows that after&#13;
12 months Costa Rica, Mexico and Spain had managed to retain more than&#13;
one-half of the initial increase in PPPEER . On the other hand, over&#13;
Table 3.1: Effected Devaluation on PPPEER&#13;
x&#13;
Percentage Change in PPPEERX (from month before devaluation)&#13;
1 month                6 months             12 months&#13;
Total X   Mfd. X       Total X    Mfd. X     Total X     Mfd. X&#13;
Country       weights    weights     weights    weights     weights    weights&#13;
Costa Rica        24.9      25.1        27.3        24.4       17.4       16.9&#13;
South Korea       15.3      15.3         6.3         4.7        0.7        0.0&#13;
Mexico            51.4      52.1         37.6       36.9       28.7        27.1&#13;
Spain             14.2      14.7        12.9        13.8        9.1       10.2&#13;
Turkey            25.7      26.6        12e9        13.3       -2.3       -0.6&#13;
Indonesia         25.0      15.4        13.4         8.6        1.9*      -0.6*&#13;
*Eleven months.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
the same period, the export competitiveness index in South Korea, Turkey&#13;
and Indonesia virtually reverted to the pre-devaluation level. Could&#13;
this marked difference in real exchange rate behavior in the aftermath&#13;
of devaluation be explained, at least in part, by the conduct of fiscal&#13;
and monet.Qry policies?&#13;
Table 3.2 gives a comparison of the annual growth rates of money&#13;
supply in the six countries, calculated from monthly data, during&#13;
specified periods before and after the month of devaluation. Costa Rica&#13;
and South Korea are seen to have reduced markedly the expansion of money&#13;
supply in the four quarters after devaluation (relative to the three-year&#13;
average before devaluation). Such contractionary policy would have&#13;
contributed to the observed lasting improvement in the real exchange&#13;
rate for Costa Rica; in the case of South Korea the unfavorable behavior&#13;
of PPPEER after devaluation would not be attributable to the conduct of&#13;
x&#13;
aggregative monetary policy. For the other devaluing countries, monetary&#13;
policy had not helped the cause of devaluation: Spain and Turkey appear&#13;
to have virtually maintained the pre-devaluation rate of money supply&#13;
increase, while Mexico and Indonesia even show slightly higher rates.&#13;
Due to data limitations, quarterly fiscal performance after&#13;
devaluation can be examined here only for Costa Rica, South Korea,&#13;
Mexico and Spain. Comparing levels of government deficit spending&#13;
deflated by WPI in each country before and after devaluation as done&#13;
above for money supply growth, contractionary fiscal policy appears to&#13;
have been the rule, without exception, in the first four quarters after&#13;
devaluation among these countries. The large government deficits&#13;
occurring in the pre-devaluation period were drastically reduced such&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
Table 3.2: Growth of Money Supply Before and After Devaluation:  Selected LDCs&#13;
Average annual increase in money supply (in per cent).&#13;
3-year period            Q           Q           Average&#13;
Country      before devaluation      1       2       3      Q4  Ql to Q4&#13;
Costa Rica             27.4          25.9    18.2    16.7    16.1    19.2&#13;
South Korea            38.4          21.8    27.0    21.1    26.8    24.2&#13;
Mexico                 23.7          29.1    30.4    26.2    22.0    26.9&#13;
Spain                  19.2          21.5*   18.9    18.5    19.2    19.5&#13;
Turkey                 32.9          28.1    32.3    37.0     -      32.5&#13;
Indonesia              25.0          22.5    30.9    31.9    33.2    29.6&#13;
Note: Qi    ith quarter after month of devaluation (i = 1, 2, 3, 4).&#13;
*Based on end-of-quarter data, 1976 III and 1977 III.&#13;
Dash (-) indicates data not available.&#13;
Source:  IMF , International Financial Statistics (various issues).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
that during the 12-month period after devaluation the average amounts&#13;
(in 1975 prices) were only about one-fifth (in South Korea and Mexico)&#13;
and one-tenth (in Costa Rica and Spain) of the three-year average values&#13;
before devaluation.-L/ It would appear therefore that both monetary and&#13;
fiscal policies were supportive of real exchange rate adjustment in&#13;
Costa Rica and South Korea. For Costa Rica this proved sufficient in&#13;
avoiding a reversion of the real exchange rate to the predevaluation&#13;
level.-/ For South Korea it cannot be said that the choice of inappropriate&#13;
macroeconomic policy had been responsible for the observed domestic price&#13;
increases which rapidly undercut the initial improvement in competitiveness&#13;
3/&#13;
provided by the December 1974 devaluation.-&#13;
Among countries that had small gradual changes in effective&#13;
exchange rates, monetary and fiscal policy would seem expansionary in&#13;
the majority of cases during 1973-78 relative to the five-year period&#13;
before the adoption of generalized floating among major currencies&#13;
(cf. Table 3.3). The exceptions are Singapore which reduced substantially&#13;
the rate of increase of its money supply, and Morocco and the Philippines&#13;
whose fiscal performance was contractionary. Interestingly enough, only&#13;
three (Morocco, Pakistan and the Philippines) of the ten countries&#13;
1/ As calculated from IMF International Financial Statistics data.&#13;
2/ Notice from Table 2.2 that, over the entire observation period 1973-79&#13;
Costa Rica suffered ,a negative trend in PPPEER . As shown in Figure 3,&#13;
there was a substantial fall in the real exchange rate before the May&#13;
1974 devaluation which was not fully offset by the subsequent rise.&#13;
3/  While it is beyond the scope of the present discussion to analyze the&#13;
possible causes of domestic price level movements in the sample&#13;
countries, we may note that the growth rate of real output (GDP in&#13;
1975 prices) in South Korea was much lower in 1975 (8.1 per cent)&#13;
compared to the annual average in 1973-1974 (11.8 per cent), perhaps&#13;
attributable in large part to the sharp decline in foreign demand.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
Table 3.3: -Indicators of Monetary and Fiscal Policy: Sample LDCs&#13;
With Small Changes in EER Under Generalized Floating&#13;
x&#13;
Average Annual Rate of Increase in         Average Annual Ratio of&#13;
Money Supply (end-of-year values), %   Govermment Deficit to GDP (xlO0)&#13;
Country            1967-72      1972-78               1968-72     1973-78&#13;
Greece                 11.6        20.2                  -1.99        -3.41&#13;
India                 11.3         16.6                  -3.52        -4.37*&#13;
Malaysia               12.4        18.2                  -5.80        -7.29&#13;
Morocco                11.7        19.2                  -4.04        -3.62**&#13;
Pakistan               14.2        15.8                  -6.38        -8.14&#13;
Philippines            15.6        17.5                  -2.60        - .05&#13;
Singapore              22.6        12.9                   1.98          .92&#13;
Taiwan                 18.9        28.2                    -           1.65&#13;
Thailand                9.7        13.7                  -3.56        -3.89&#13;
Tunisia                13.0        16.4                    -          -2.92&#13;
Note:   *Based on 1972-77 data.&#13;
**Based on 1972-74 data.&#13;
Dash (-) indicates data not available.&#13;
Source: IMF, International Financial Statistics (various issues).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
suffered a loss in export competitiveness due to real exchange rate&#13;
changes (cf. Table 3.3) while India and Malaysia which registered the&#13;
largest improvement in PPPEER in the entire sample appear to have&#13;
x&#13;
increased both the average rate of monetary expansion and government&#13;
deficit spending.&#13;
Finally, does active exchange rate management as exemplified by&#13;
the t"crawling peg" policy promote the adoption of supportive monetary&#13;
and fiscal policies? Table 3.4 compares average money supply growth&#13;
government deficit spending in five sample countries during specified&#13;
periods of crawling peg since 1973 and earlier years. Only Brazil seems&#13;
to have exercised both monetary and fiscal restraint during the period of&#13;
active exchange rate management, which must have contributed to the observed&#13;
improvement in the real exchange rate. Monetary policy in Colombia and&#13;
ULuguay was relatively expansionary despite an improved fiscal performance,&#13;
while both the rate of monetary expansion and government deficit spending&#13;
went up in Argentina. Thus, no clearcut conclusion emerges on the&#13;
ability of LDC authorities to accommodate, through aggregate demand&#13;
management, the expenditure-reducing mechanism of currency depreciation&#13;
under a crawling peg exchange rate regime.&#13;
The inferences from the above analysis, which simply makes a before-&#13;
and-after comparison of money supply growth and government deficit spending,&#13;
are valid to the extent that other influences on macroeconomic policy decisions&#13;
are attributable to the type of exchange rate regime adopted. A more rigorous&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
Table 3.4: Indicators of Monetary and Fiscal Policy: Sample LDCs&#13;
With Crawling Peg Exchange Rate Regime&#13;
Average Annual Rate of          Average Annual&#13;
Increase in Money Supply       Ratio of Government&#13;
Country       (end-of-year values), (%p.a.)    Deficit to GDP (%)&#13;
Argentina            1969-74:      52.0          1970-74:     - 3.56&#13;
1974-78:     194.0           1975-78:    - 6.87&#13;
Brazil               1962-67:     56.6           1963-67:     - 2.36&#13;
1972-78:      39.5           1973-78:        .14&#13;
Colombia             1961-66:     16.6.          1962-66:        .95&#13;
1972-78:      26.6           1973-78:        .04&#13;
Uruguay              1966-71:     58.7           1967-71:     - 2.63&#13;
1972-78:      65.4           1973-78:    - 2.32&#13;
Source: IMF, International Financial Statistics (various issues).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
analysis can be provided by the use of multiple regression in representing&#13;
quantitatively the conduct of monetary and fiscal policies during the period&#13;
under study.&#13;
Relative monetary performance among the sample LDCs adopting different&#13;
methods of exchange rate adjustment can be further examined by fitting a money&#13;
supply equation, based on their collective experience during 1973-79, with&#13;
dummy variables that allow the intercept to shift from one exchange rate&#13;
regime to another. It is hypothesized that the expansion of money supply is&#13;
determined (by the national authorities) on the basis of current output growth&#13;
and the accommodation of such sources of inflationary pressures as the balance&#13;
of payments, government deficit spending, money wage increases and exchange&#13;
rate adjustment. The following estimated equations are based on average values&#13;
of the variables for the sample countries over the period 1973-79:&#13;
No. of observations: 19 (excluding Egypt, Indonesia and Thailand)&#13;
(3.1)  M  = -1.512 +    1.868   Y   -  .062 CR  -  .058 GSD  +   .302 W&#13;
(-.19)    (2.37)       (-.14)       (-.07)       (1.02)&#13;
+ .151  Et   + 1.257 DS   - 7.216 DC&#13;
(3.14)         (.31)      (-1.12)&#13;
-2&#13;
R= .959            s.e.e. = 6.70&#13;
(t-statistics reported in parentheses throughout)&#13;
No. of observations: 15 (excluding Egypt, Indonesia, Thailand&#13;
and crawling peg countries)&#13;
(3.2)  M  = 11.61 + 1.321Y      +   .019 CR +   .208 GSD  +   .178 W&#13;
(1.62) (2.28)         (.07)       (.42)        (.90)&#13;
+ .058E:   -    4.066 DS&#13;
(1.42)       (-1.36)&#13;
-2 =&#13;
R=.540          s.e.e. =4.14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
No. of observations: 22&#13;
(3.3)    M  =  5.556 + 1.462 Y  +     .192 E*  -   .255 DS  -  8.12 DC&#13;
(1.10)  (2.55)       (15.29)  m    (-.08)      (-1.58)&#13;
R2 =  .959            s.e.e.  =  6.26&#13;
where&#13;
M = average annual growth rate of money supply, in per cent&#13;
Y   =  average annual growth rate of GDP (at 1975 prices), in per cent&#13;
CR  =  average annual ratio of change in reserves to GNP (at current&#13;
prices)&#13;
GSD = average annual ratio of government surplus (+) or deficit (-)&#13;
to GDP (at current prices) x 100&#13;
W = average annual rate of increase in non-agricultural (industrial,&#13;
manufaicturing) wage rate, in per cent&#13;
=  average monthly rate of increase in import-weighted effective&#13;
exchange rate, in per cent&#13;
DS  =  dummy variable:   1 for countries with small, gradual exchange&#13;
rate changes, 0 for other countries&#13;
DC  = dummy variable:    1 for crawling peg countries (Argentina,&#13;
Brazil, Colombia and Uruguay), 0 for other countries.&#13;
In regression equation (3.1) which is based on observations for&#13;
.i9 countries -- not including Egypt (no available GSD data), and Indonesia&#13;
and Thailand (no available W data) -- only the output and exchange rate&#13;
variables are seen to yield estimated coefficients significantly different&#13;
from zero at the 5 per cent level. The coefficients for DS and DC are positive&#13;
and negative, respectively, but both insignificant. Equation (3.2), in&#13;
which the crawling peg countries are also excluded, shows significance&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
of the GDP variable but not E4.    It is worth noting that the DS&#13;
coefficient has now a negative sign, although it is still insignificant&#13;
at the 5% level.  In equation (3.3), which includes  all 22 countries,&#13;
significant coefficients for GDP and Em   are observed, but again not&#13;
for the two exchange rate regime dummies.&#13;
These results tend to corroborate the earlier inference about the&#13;
lack of a clear relationship between the conduct of monetary policy and&#13;
type of exchange rate adjustment. Certainly no support is given to the&#13;
hypothesis mentioned earlier that large, discrete devaluations have an&#13;
advantage in that they apply strong pressure on the national authorities&#13;
to exercise monetary restraint. If anything, the signs of the estimated&#13;
dummy coefficients with t-values greater than unity (which add to&#13;
the explanatory power of the regression equation) point to a&#13;
relatively more restrictive monetary policy pursued in countries&#13;
adopting the crawling peg regime and small-step exchange rate adjustments&#13;
when account is taken of other influences on money supply expansion.&#13;
Turning now to the quantitative representation of the conduct of&#13;
fiscal policy among the sample LDCs during 1973-79 to test for the separate&#13;
influence of the type of exchange rate regime adopted, it seems reasonable&#13;
to hypothesize that government deficit spending would be affected by the&#13;
growth of real output, per capita income and the balance of payments.&#13;
Otllt things the same, the larger tax base associated with higher levels&#13;
or more rapid gains in real income implies a less urgent need for an LDC&#13;
government to increase deficit spending. An improvement in the balance&#13;
of payments, on the other hand, may or may not lead to contractionary&#13;
fiscal policy. As a means of offsetting the monetary repercussions of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
an increase in foreign reserves, the national authorities may decide to&#13;
restrain public spending. However, it is also possible that the improved&#13;
reserve position would provide the stimulus for increasing government&#13;
spending.&#13;
Distinguishing also the 21 sample LDCs (excluding Egypt) by type&#13;
of exchange rate adjustment, regression of these explanatory variables&#13;
on GSD, again based on average values over the period 1973-79, yielded&#13;
the following:&#13;
(3.4)  GSD  =  -8.988 + .844 Y    +  .152 PCY    -   .256 CR&#13;
(-4.48) (3.64)       (2.44)        (-2.13)&#13;
- 1.353 DS + 1.008 DC&#13;
(-1.24)        (.73)&#13;
R  = .394       s.e.e. = 2.09&#13;
where PCY is average per capita GDP, in hundred U.S. dollars at 1975&#13;
prices,and the other variables are as defined earlier.&#13;
The estimated coefficients for the three non-dummy variables are&#13;
significant at the 5 per cent level,-/ but those for the two exchange rate&#13;
regime dummies are not. The latter finding is consistent with the earlier&#13;
discussion about the ambiguous association between the method of exchange&#13;
rate adjustment and conduct of fiscal policy in the sample countries.&#13;
1/ While we make no attempt here to examine in depth the influence of these&#13;
variables on government finance, it is worth noting that the estimated&#13;
relationship given by equation 3.4 shows a negative effect of the change&#13;
in reserves variable, suggesting that fiscal policy had generally not&#13;
been used to compensate for the domestic monetary consequences of the&#13;
balance of payments among the sample LDCs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
No clearcut conclusion has thus emerged on the comparative&#13;
experience of sample LDCs classified by method of exchange rate adjustment&#13;
in relation to their ability to undertake supportive monetary and fiscal&#13;
policies. It would seem neither necessary nor sufficient that a developing&#13;
country adopt any particular type or method of nominal exchange rate&#13;
adjustment to be able to achieve real exchange rate adjustment. It&#13;
should be recognized, nevertheless, that for endemically inflationary&#13;
countries, i.e., where existing institutions and policies have a strong&#13;
built-in inflationary bias so that increases in the domestic price level&#13;
greatly exceed the foreign inflation rate, active exchange rate management&#13;
as exemplified by the crawling peg may represent the only feasible option&#13;
(short of a drastic overhaul of institutions and policies) to be able to&#13;
achieve and sustain export competitiveness. For other LDCs the above&#13;
results suggest that even without substantial currency depreciation, policy&#13;
measures directed toward domestic price stability could provide at least&#13;
as good a basis for promoting real exchange rate adjustment.&#13;
Perhaps due to the severity of the external shocks buffeting&#13;
the developing countries during the period, the conduct of macroeconomic&#13;
policy has not always appeared as a dominant factor in the observed changes&#13;
in real exchange rates,-L/ except in the case of the crawling peg countries.&#13;
This does not imply that the choice of macroeconomic policy is unimportant.&#13;
Unquestionably, exchange rate management under generalized floating can&#13;
1/ Moreover, in the context of developing economies, domestic credit and&#13;
fiscal policy measu'res would have affected not only aggregate demand but&#13;
also'aggregate supply' to the extent that they contribute to the removal&#13;
of supply bottlenecks and creation of additional production capacity,&#13;
and hence their effects on the general price level are likely to differ&#13;
in different countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
facilitate the correction of currency overvaluation and improvement of the&#13;
incentive structure for exports only if it is properly coordinated with&#13;
other policy instruments affecting the domestic price level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
IV. THE INFLATIONARY EFFECT OF EXCHANGE RATE CHANGES&#13;
Introduction&#13;
A major reason for the widespread reluctance of policymakers in less&#13;
developed countries to undertake exchange rate adjustments, despite&#13;
the recognition &amp;2 domestic currency overvaluation, is the anxiety about&#13;
induced general price increases which may "rapidly undercut the improved&#13;
competitiveness that the devaluation is designed to achieve" (Cooper, 1971;&#13;
p. 21). There is a pervasive belief that devaluation is inflationary, not&#13;
only in the sense of a once-and-for-all price increase but that some cost-&#13;
push mechanism (e.g., a wage-price spiral) will make a higher rate of inflation&#13;
inevitable. While the nature and empirical significance of such mechanisms&#13;
have been debated in the literature for some time, the evidence from cross-&#13;
country studies based on LDC experience under the Bretton Woods system&#13;
seemsto indicate that the worst fears concerning the inflationary effect of&#13;
devaluation are unfounded.&#13;
In a study of 24 devaluation episodes involving 19 (mostly developing)&#13;
countries during the period 1959-1966, Cooper (1971) finds that increases in&#13;
wholesale and consumer prices have been far less than the devaluation - on average,&#13;
by 32'and 42 per cent, respectively, of the devaluiation. Connolly and Taylor (1976)&#13;
have likewise observed that 8 devaluations in 5 LDCs during'1962-1970 resulted&#13;
in faster increases in wholesale and consumer prices in the year following&#13;
devaluation but at much lower rates than export and import prices; over.two years&#13;
"the devaluation would have added 13 and 14 1/2% to the export and import price&#13;
indices" (p.857). Finally, in a regression analysis of the inflationary impact&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
of devaluation in 10 developing countries (included in the NBER project on&#13;
foreign exchange regimes and economic development) using data through 1972,&#13;
Krueger (1978) concludes that, after taking account of monetary behavior,&#13;
the net effect of other influences on the rate of price increase in each&#13;
of the four quarters following devaluation has not been statistically signi-&#13;
ficant.&#13;
The devaluations examined in the abovementioned studies took place&#13;
under the Bretton Woods system of adjustable par values, involving large&#13;
once-and-for-all exchange rate changes. Similar cross-country studies on LDC&#13;
experience with small, gradual exchange rate adjustments under generalized currency&#13;
floating, which has been in effect since March 1973, are as yet not available.&#13;
The "crawling peg"' system, frequently involving relatively large sustained&#13;
currency depreciation in nominal terms represents still another form of&#13;
exchange rate adjustment whose inflationary effect has yet to be compared&#13;
with the other exchange rate regimes on an intercountry basis.&#13;
For several reasons the response of domestic prices to exchange rate&#13;
changes may be quantitatively different under different exchange rate regimes.&#13;
One possibility is that producers, in their pricing decisions, may react&#13;
less significantly to smaller changes (ove-: a given period) in the exchange&#13;
rate, in view of the transactions cost of changing prices in imperfectly&#13;
competitive markets. Moreover, the publicity attending policy decisions&#13;
involving large, discrete exchange rate changes may lead to greater&#13;
domestic price repercussions. Some producers may even take the opportunity&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
to raise prices of certain products which was difficult to do before the&#13;
exchange rate adjustment "for reasons of law, custom, fear of public&#13;
approbrium or simply inertia" (Cooper, 1971; p. 27);!/ the large, once-&#13;
and-for-all devaluation serves as an excuse for producers to correct prices&#13;
upwards even for unrelated reasons. On the other hand, continuous exchange&#13;
rate adjustments, whether large or small, may generate expectations of&#13;
sustained movements in the same direction, which add to the inflationary&#13;
pressure. The so-called "ratchet effect", due to a possible asymmetry in&#13;
the effects of positive versus negative cost changes (induced by fluctuating&#13;
exchange rates) on domestic prices, also needs to be considered. To the&#13;
extent that there is increased variability in an LDC's effective exchange&#13;
rate under generalized floating, downward rigidity of domestic prices could&#13;
result in a cumulative rise in the general price level. While each of the above&#13;
hypotheses is intuitively plausible, their practical significance remains an&#13;
open question.&#13;
In this section, we attempt to relate the observed movements in the&#13;
effective exchange rate to changes in the general price level based on the&#13;
collective experience of the 22 sample LDCs. Cross-country data expressed in&#13;
average annual levels or rates of change over the period 1973-1979 are utilized.&#13;
One advantage of using this type of cross-section data over time series&#13;
analysis is that dynamic considerations (e.g., adjustment lags) and short-&#13;
term disturbances can be ignored; averaging of valuesover a span of six&#13;
years serves to "smooth out" fluctuations from these sources, so that comparison&#13;
across countries provides a meaningful basis for estimating at least the&#13;
1/ Prime examples are public utility companies and other firms whose products&#13;
are subject to government price control.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
intermediate-term response of domestic prices to exchange rate changes and other&#13;
influences. It also affords an opportunity to discern any differences in the&#13;
estimated effects under different exchange rate regimes.&#13;
Alternative Specifications of the Price Equation&#13;
While there exists a wide variety of empirical models explaining&#13;
domestic price behavior, we are interested here only in those having immediate&#13;
relevance to LDCs and including the exchange rate (explicitly or implicitly)&#13;
as an explanatory variable. Moreover, data limitations require that our model&#13;
specification be kept simple; one would be ill-advised to insist on analytical&#13;
sophistication given the slenderness of the data available in developing&#13;
countries. It is necessary,however,to consider various models of inflation&#13;
in open economies as basis for the empirical tests of the effect of exchange&#13;
rate changes on the general price level. The objective is to reduce the&#13;
possibility that the test results are peculiar to only one set of assumptions&#13;
concerning the determinants of inflation in developing countries.&#13;
We start with the following variant of a fairly standard cost-push type&#13;
specification of the price equation:&#13;
(4.1)    p      =   ao+a W + a2 Pm + a3Y       a 1 a2  &gt;  0, a3&lt;    0&#13;
where&#13;
P  =  general price level&#13;
W  = money wage rate&#13;
Pm = import price, in domestic currency&#13;
Y  =  real output&#13;
and the dot (.) above each variable denoting a proportionate change.&#13;
It is hypothesized in (4.1) that the change in domestic prices bears a&#13;
linear relationship to the changes in unit labor cost and import price, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
latter embodying excharige rate changes. Because information on man-hours&#13;
worked is generally not available, output level is used instead of labor&#13;
productivity which is the usual explanatory variable in this type of inflation&#13;
model   (cf. Ball and Duffy, 1972).  The variable Y is expected to have a negative&#13;
coefficient. This would follow from a constant markup assumption, since an&#13;
increase in real output, other things the same, will lower unit costs. Alternatively,&#13;
where the markup is positively related to the level of excess demand in the product&#13;
market (or any other measure of market tightness), a rise in output supply for the&#13;
same amount of effective demand will reduce excess demand, which is disinflationary.&#13;
Imports are viewed in the above formulation "more as a factor of production&#13;
than as a finished good that competes with domestically produced finished goods"&#13;
(Goldstein, 1977; p.579), which seems a realistic assumption in the context of&#13;
developing countries.&#13;
It is possible that the money wage rate depends in part on the general&#13;
price level, in which case there will be a simultaneity problem in the&#13;
estimation of  (4.1).    Indeed the wage-price spiral is widely assumed to&#13;
provide the mechanism, or in the "structuralist" terminology (cf. Argy, 1970;&#13;
p. 80) the propagating element,that sustains a higher rate of inflation&#13;
once a price increase, from any source, has been initiated. We hypothesize&#13;
the following relationship:&#13;
(2)           W     b  + bl P + b2 Y + b3-' b1, b2, b3   &gt;  0&#13;
where L is a shift variable represai:ting the level of economic development (measured&#13;
by per capita GDP). Other things being equal, an increase in domestic prices or&#13;
real output is assumed to result in a rise in nominal wages. This might be justified&#13;
even in labor surplus LDCs on the grounds that employers will find it easier to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
comply with minimum wage requirements, or accede to union demands for pay increases,&#13;
when product prices and volumes are rising. The coefficient b3 is expected to be&#13;
positive, on the assumption that the pressure to raise wages (or the bargaining&#13;
strength of labor unions) is greater in higher income countries.&#13;
If higher income LDCs have higher levels of labor productivity (which&#13;
seems reasonable), then b3 greater than zero would be consistent with&#13;
Glytsos' (1977) hypothesis, apparently borne out by his empirical analysis&#13;
using data for nine LDCs in the 1960s, that the "rate of change of wages&#13;
depends (positively) on the level of productivity and not the rate of change&#13;
of productivity" (p. 318).&#13;
Substituting (4.2) into (4.1) yields:&#13;
(4.3)         P = a' + a' Pm + a? Y + a' L       ala'&gt;O      ,a2 &gt;0&#13;
o 0           2      3        1 3           2&#13;
where&#13;
a+a           a'      2       a-      b2 + a3       -      13&#13;
1-a      ab 1-ab                                               11&#13;
°   1 - al b1            - a b      2  1    1 1            1 - a1bl&#13;
The above discussion suggests two ways of estimating the price equation&#13;
on which to base the in-restigation of the inflationary effect of exchange&#13;
rate changes (which are embodied in P ). First, assuming exogeneity of W&#13;
m&#13;
(i.e., it is independent of P and Y), to use equation (4.1); and second,&#13;
assuming that (4 2) holds, to use the re'&gt;.ced form equation (4.3).&#13;
Another approach in the empirical analysiL of inflation in developing&#13;
countries is via the relationship between money supply and the general price&#13;
level. Justification for the use of money supply as an explanatory variable&#13;
in the price equation rests on the quantity theory of money. One advantage of&#13;
using this approach is that it avoids the structural representation of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
various influences on the general price level which, it has been argued, no simple&#13;
model can adequately provide in a cross-country study (cf. Krueger, 1978; p. 180).&#13;
Furthermore, it recognizes that for any cost-push type disturbance to&#13;
be a source of continuing inflation, there has to be an accompanying stimulus to&#13;
aggregate demand, as would be provided by an increasing money supply. While&#13;
studies of cost-push inflation tend to ignore the role of money supply&#13;
(e.g., Goldstein, 1977 and Kwack, 1977), it is clear that an accommodating&#13;
monetary policy serves to validate the higher prices and sustain wage-price&#13;
spirals. Finally, monetary theories of inflation also emphasize the tendency&#13;
for government expenditures in developing countries to be financed not by&#13;
higher taxes or bond sales to the public but by money creation. The increased&#13;
spending thus tends to stimulate faster money supply growth which results in&#13;
accelerated inflation.&#13;
Here we follow Cooper (1971) and, to some extent, Argy (1970) and&#13;
Glytsos (1977) in expressing the change in the general price level as:-/&#13;
(4.41 c             +c     +c   Y + c  P     c   c  &gt; 0,  c  &lt;   0&#13;
o    1       2      3   m'  1,c3&gt;0        2&#13;
which allows for the fact that increases in money supply are not inflationary&#13;
to the extent that they are absorbed by changes in real output.&#13;
As shown by Aghevli and Rodriguez (1979), a price equation similar to (4.4) can&#13;
be derived using a two-sector open economy model in which home goods prices&#13;
adjust in part to the excess supply of money while the price in the&#13;
1/ Instead of changes in real output ("Y) and in import prices (P ), Cooper&#13;
made use of variations in food prci:uction and devaluation rat&amp;e respectively,&#13;
as explanatory variables in equation (4.4). Argy, and Glytsos in his demand pull&#13;
submodel, did not include Pm in their regression specifications.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54 -&#13;
import-competing sector is determined directly by the world price and current&#13;
exchange rate.&#13;
As argued some    time ago by Harberger (1963) in his study of Chilean inflation,&#13;
autonomous wage increases could lead in the short run to price rises even&#13;
in the absence of money supply expansion,adding to the explanation given by&#13;
monetary movements in the rate of inflation. Of course, "if the monetary&#13;
authorities always increased the money supply by enough (or more than enough)&#13;
to assure full employment at the new wage level, there would be no strong&#13;
reason to expect that wages would add significantly to a monetary explanation&#13;
of inflation" (p. 228). It seems worthwhile in the present study to run&#13;
regressions on a specification with the wage variable included in the R.H.S.&#13;
of (4.4), i.e.,&#13;
(4.5)           c  +     A + c' Y + c' Pm + c   W.&#13;
o    1       2      3    m  4&#13;
Similar formulations have also been used by Diaz-Alejandro (1965) and&#13;
Diz (1970) for Argentina,and Colaco (1969) for Brazil and India.&#13;
A final specification of the price equation deserving some attention&#13;
concerns the use of A - Y as a measure of excess domestic demand, which&#13;
icaptures the excess liquidity created by the government fiscal deficit&#13;
as well as changes in the demand for money caused by income growth" (Blejer&#13;
and Halevi, 1980; p. 119). Equation (4.5) might then be simply modified as:&#13;
(4.6)       p     c +   c"(- Y)+      c" P  +  c"W&#13;
0  1             3    m   4&#13;
Focusing now on the import price variable, several aspects of its&#13;
influence on the domestic price level need to be recognized. First, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
55 -&#13;
effect of changes in P may vary from country to country, depending on the&#13;
extent of reliance on imported goods. We can make allowance for this by&#13;
multiplying the observed values of Pm by the factor (1 + m) where m is the&#13;
share of imports to GNP -- representing a fairly standard measure of the&#13;
"degree of openness". More highly open LDCs might be expected to exhibit&#13;
a greater response in domestic prices to a change in import price, based on&#13;
a cost-push view of inflation./&#13;
Secondly, P represents the combined changes in foreign currency&#13;
import prices, in tariff, indirect tax and other policies affecting the&#13;
domestic price of imported goods, and under generalized currency floating in&#13;
bilateral exchange rates with trade partner currencies. We do not take into&#13;
account here changes in domestic policies related to the so-called&#13;
"non-formal" component of the exchange rate which, given the complexity of&#13;
the trade and payments regime in most developing countries, would be exceedingly&#13;
difficult to make comparable across countries and over time. There is a&#13;
presumption however that "formal" exchange rate changes, being more widely&#13;
publicized and having a greater impact on expectations, have a much stronger&#13;
and faster effect on the rate of domestic inflation (Blejer and Halevi, 1980).&#13;
A third consideration, particularly warranted in the assessment of the&#13;
inflationary effect of exchange rate changes, is the possible nonlinearity of&#13;
1/ There is a competing hypothesis that views openness as a reflection of&#13;
an LDC's capacity to draw from foreign sources in times of reduced domestic&#13;
availability for whatever reason (e.g., poor crop harvest), which implies&#13;
a negative relationship between the degree of openness and inflation rate.&#13;
Additionally, more open economies are faced with a higher degree of foreign&#13;
competition, and hence are less subject to inflationary pressures arising&#13;
from monopolistic behavior of domestic producers. It would be appropriate&#13;
therefore to include m also as an intercept dummy whose coefficient is&#13;
expected to be negative.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
the domestic price response. As indicated above, large EER changes may or&#13;
may not have a more significant impact on domestic prices than small-step exchange&#13;
rate adjustments, in part depending on what expectations on future exchange&#13;
rates and costs are generated as well as on the relative cost of frequent price&#13;
adjustments. This can be dealt with by including the square of the effective&#13;
exchange rate change (EER ) as an additional explanatory variable in the&#13;
regressions. Bruno and Sussman (1978), for example, have reported a positive&#13;
coefficient for this variable, "although of not very high degree of significance"&#13;
(p. 23), in an examination of inflation and devaluation in Israel based on&#13;
quarterly data for the period 1967-75.&#13;
Fourthly, one would want to test also for the ratchet effect associated&#13;
with exchange rate fluctuations under generalized floating which, as pointed&#13;
out earlier, generate an inflationary bias due to domestic price inflexibility&#13;
in the downward direction.-/  An extension of this hypothesis would be that&#13;
upward and downward deviations of the effective exchange rate from expected or&#13;
trend values have asymmetrical effects on the domestic price level, so that&#13;
countries faced with greater EER variability around the trend would tend to be&#13;
more inflationary, other things the same. The explanatory variable used here&#13;
to capture the ratchet effect of EER variability consists of the standard error&#13;
of estimate in the logarithmic trend regression of monthly import-weighted EER&#13;
values for each sample LDC over the period March 1973 to December 1979.&#13;
A final consideration concerns the differences among sample LDCs in&#13;
the method of exchange rate Ajustment adopted during the observation period.&#13;
1/ Inconclusive results have been obtained in a recent systematic investigation&#13;
of the practical significance of ratchet effects, which however pert.ain only&#13;
to some selected major industrial countries (Goldstein, 1977).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
Some of the characteristics of exchange rate regimes would have been captured&#13;
already in the other explanatory variables mentioned earlier. For instance,&#13;
if the crisis atmosphere in which large, discrete devaluations take place&#13;
makes it easier for the national authorities to adopt contractionary monetary&#13;
policy and to rally labor groups behind a more restrained wage increase&#13;
than would be the case with small, gradual exchange rate changes, the estimated&#13;
coefficients for the money supply and wage rate variables will reflect already&#13;
the corresponding effects on the domestic price levrel. In introducing dummy&#13;
variables for particular exchange rate regimes.in the regression equation&#13;
one is representing other aspects of exchange rate adjustment and attendant&#13;
policy measures having a separate influence on the inflation rate. Thus, if&#13;
the adoption of crawling peg meant, in an ex post sense, the relaxation of&#13;
import restrictions to a greater extent than what accompanied other exchange&#13;
rate regimes, the dummy coefficients allowing the intercept of the price&#13;
equation to shift might turn out significant. It is of course hazardous&#13;
to speculate on the various relevant aspects of economic policy (which may have&#13;
offsetting influences on the domestic price level) accompanying exchange&#13;
rate adjustments and to assess their separate inflationary effects in the sample&#13;
countries. However, we can attempt to generalize from the collective&#13;
experience of the sample LDCs by examining the significance of the dummy&#13;
variables that would reflect the net effect on the domestic price&#13;
level of other policy measures attributable, at least indirectly, to the type&#13;
of exchange rate regime being adopted. Additionally, it is instructive to run&#13;
regressions excluding the crawling peg countries (Argentina, Brazil, Colombia&#13;
and Uruguay) and to compare the estimated coefficients with the corresponding&#13;
results of the regressions based on the entire sample,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 58 -&#13;
Empirical Results&#13;
The results of cross-country regressions testing for the foreign&#13;
inflation rate (Pf), wage rate changes and level of economic development&#13;
as determinants of domestic inflation are presented in Tables 4.1 and 4.2 for&#13;
sample LDCs including and excluding the crawling peg countries, respectively.-/&#13;
Other explanatory variables appearing in the various specifications are changes&#13;
in money supply, real GDP and import-weighted effective exchange rate ( m).&#13;
Given the consistently low t-values and sometimes perverse signs of&#13;
the estimated coefficients for Pf5 W and L in the relevant specifications,&#13;
it was decided not to include these variables in subsequent regressions.&#13;
The lack of significance of the foreign price variable was not entirely&#13;
surprising, in view of the observed similarity in Pf trends among the sample&#13;
LDCs (being faced with the same principal trade partners). In the case of&#13;
the wage variable, the statistical insignificance of the estimated coefficient&#13;
might have been due in part to the poor quality and low degree of comparability&#13;
of wage data among developing countries. Note however that dropping W is&#13;
consistent with equation (4.3) above, which postulates simultaneity in the&#13;
determination of P and W.  Moreover, to the extent that wage increases had&#13;
been accommodated by monetary expansion, there would be no additional&#13;
explanation of domestic inflation that is provided by W.&#13;
The regression results in Tables 4.1 and 4.2 also indicate that Y appearing&#13;
in the various specifications without M yields insignificant coefficient&#13;
estimates. Furthermore, use of M - Y is clearly superior, based on the&#13;
1/  Indonesia and Thailand, which are part of our sample of 22 countries,&#13;
do not have available wage series and hence have not been included in&#13;
these regressions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 4.1: Determinants of Domestic Inflation: Regression Results A&#13;
(Dependent variable: P: 20 observations)&#13;
--2&#13;
Equation No.      Const.     M - Y         M         Y          Em         Pf           W       L             R       s.e.e.&#13;
I           17.94        .281       -         -          .912**    -1.160     .013      -.067         .9944     3.09&#13;
(1.32)      (1.55)                         (5.05)      (-.90)     (.10)    (-.66)&#13;
II           15.90        .310       -         -          .918**    -1.091    -.033       -            .9946     3.03&#13;
(1.27)      (1.79)                         (5.19)      (-.86)    (-.28)&#13;
III            5.282**     .360*      -         -          .848**      -         -         -            .9950     2.92&#13;
(2.98)     (2.39)                          (5.83)&#13;
IV           28.15        -          .256    -7.28        .928**    -1.963     .003      -.132         .9946     3.01&#13;
(1.86)                (1.44)   (-1.90)     (5.26)     (-1.40)     (.02)   (-1.19)&#13;
Ln&#13;
V           21.91        -          .311    -.589        .931**    -1.524    -.066       -            .9945     3.06   %&#13;
(1.52)                (1.78)  (-1.59)      (5.20)     (-1.11)    (-.53)&#13;
VI            6.088*      -          .367*   -.507        .836**      -         -         -             .9947    2.98&#13;
(2.47)                (2.38)  (-1.49)      (5.56)&#13;
VII           37.30*       -          -       -.528       1.137**    -2,664      .047     -.173          .9942    3.12&#13;
(2.61)                        (-1.42)     (10.93)     (-1.96)     (.34)   (-1.56)&#13;
VIII           31.29*       -          -       -.274       1.204**    -2.259    -.037       -             .9937    3.27&#13;
(2.11)                         (-.78)     (12.14)     (-1.61)    (-.28)&#13;
IX            9.668**     -          -       -.082      1.190**       -         -         -             .9933    3.36&#13;
(4.38)                         (-.25)     (46.88)&#13;
Note:    *  Significant at 5 per cent level; ** significant at 1 per cent level.&#13;
Numbers in parentheses underneath the coefficient estimates are t-values.&#13;
L is represented by the 1976 per capita GDP, in hundred U.S. dollars.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 4.2: Determinants of Domestic Inflation: Regression Results B&#13;
(Dependent variable: P; 16 observations)&#13;
-2&#13;
Equation No.     Const.     M - Y        M          Y         Em         Pf        W         L             R      s.e.e.&#13;
I          11.80        .320      -          -         .919**     -.707      .035     -.056        .7986    3.28&#13;
(.82)     (1.24)                        (3.98)       (-.48)     (.18)    (-.48)&#13;
II          11i39        .367      -          -         .926**      -.708    -.020     -            .8126    3.16&#13;
(.82)     (1.59)                        (4.16)        (-.50)   (-.13)&#13;
III           4.529       .395*     -         -          .898**     -          -        -            .8377    2.94&#13;
(1.93)     (2.18)                        (4.67)&#13;
IV          27.10        -          .327    -.818       .859**     -1.912    -.017     -.110        .7962    3.30&#13;
(1.24)               (1.26)   (-1.38)    (3.56)       (-.98)    (-.08)    (-.840)&#13;
V          20.40        -          .398     -.695      .893**     -1.444    -.083     -            .8022    3.25    c&#13;
(1.02)               (1.65)   (-1.23)    (3.81)       (-.782)   (-.46)&#13;
VI           4.965       -          .401    -.475       .879**      -         -        -            .8251    3.05&#13;
(1.58)               (2.11)   (-1.18)    (4.04)&#13;
VII          31.78        -          -        -.474      .983**     -2.132     .112     -.164        .7843    3.39&#13;
(1.42)                         (-.88)    (4.33)      (-1.06)     (.63)   (-1.29)&#13;
VIII          22.29        -          -        -.145     1.084**     -1.433     .047     -            .7714    3.49&#13;
(1.03)                         (-.30)    (4.95)        (-.72)    (.27)&#13;
IX           9.016**     -         -          .022     1.195**      -         -        -            .7787    3.43&#13;
(3.23)                          (.06)    (6.73)&#13;
Note:   * Significant at 5 per cent level; ** significant at 1 per cent level.&#13;
Numbers in parentheses underneath the coefficient estimates are t-values.&#13;
L is represented by the 1976 per capita GDP, in hundred U.S. dollars.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 61 -&#13;
comparative values of the t-statistics,to having A and Y as separate&#13;
explanatory variables. Another striking observation from the results&#13;
is the consistently significant coefficient estimates for the exchange rate&#13;
variable in either set of regressions. Based on the specification having&#13;
only 1 - Y and Emas explanatory variables, the estimated elasticity of the&#13;
domestic price level with respect to the exchange rate is .848 for the&#13;
sample of 20 LDCs and .898 excluding the crawling peg countries which,&#13;
using the t-test, are not signiticantly different at the 5 per cent level.&#13;
Table 4.3 contains the results of regressions including the degree&#13;
of openness as an additional explanatory variable, based on the entire sample&#13;
of 22 LDCs and on a smaller sample excluding the four crawling peg countries.&#13;
The coefficient estimates for mEm, which show contrasting signs in the two&#13;
sets of regressions, are found not to be significantly different from&#13;
zero. The coefficient of the intercept dummy, while having the expected&#13;
sign, is also seen to be insignificant in every specification. The estimated&#13;
elasticity of the domestic price level with respect to the exchange rate&#13;
is .776 for the entire sample and .846 for the subsample without the crawling&#13;
peg countries. Again, the difference between these coefficient estimates&#13;
is not statistically significant.&#13;
In Table 4.4 regression results are presented testing for the&#13;
significance of exchange rate variability (v) and nonlinear price effects (E2).&#13;
Consistently low values of the t-statistic are shown for the estimated&#13;
coefficients of V in the various specifications, indicating that exchange&#13;
rate variabilitydoes not add to the explanation of intercountry differences&#13;
.2&#13;
in inflation rates. In the case of Em, insignificant coefficient estimates&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 62 -&#13;
Table 4.3: Determinants of Domestic Inflation:     Regression Results C&#13;
(Dependent variable: P)&#13;
Equation No.     Const.     M -       Y  Em        mEm         m             R       s.e.e.&#13;
22 observations&#13;
I          5.670*       .432**    .804**     -.390      -.019         .9939     3.08&#13;
(2e89)     (2.96)     (5.72)     (-.55)      (-.77)&#13;
II          4.911**      .439**    .786**     -.275       -            .9940     3.04&#13;
(2.92)     (3.14)     (5.74)     (-.40)&#13;
III           5.441**     .417**     .787**     -         -.016         .9941     3.02&#13;
(2.89)     (2.99)     (5.85)                 (-.68)&#13;
IV          4.828**      .432**    .776**      -          -            .9943     2.97&#13;
(2.96)     (3.18)     (5.89)&#13;
18 observations (excluding crawling peg countries)&#13;
V           4.541       .54*       .818*      .132      -.010         .8147     3.18&#13;
(1.71)     (2.66)     (2.76)     (1.38)      (-.38)&#13;
VI           3.941       .472**     .815*      .95        -            .8260     3.08&#13;
(1.90)      (2.98)    (2.84)      (.15)&#13;
VII           4.578       *453*      .839**     -         -.011         .8278     3.06&#13;
(1.80)     (2.77)     (4.37)                 (-.41)&#13;
VIII           3.969       .471**     .846**                -            .8373     2.98&#13;
(1.99)     (3.08)     (4.55)&#13;
Note:   * Significant at 5 per cent level; ** significant at 1 per cent level.&#13;
Numbers in parentheses underneath the coefficient estimates are t-values.&#13;
m is represented by the 1976 ratio of imports to GNP.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 63 -&#13;
Table 4.4: Determinants of Domestic Inflation: Regression Results D&#13;
(Dependent variable: P)&#13;
.2                      -2&#13;
Equation No.     Const.      M - Y       Em        .OlEm         V             R       s.e.e.&#13;
22 observations&#13;
I           5.046*       .434**    .728**     .030         .814        .9937      3.12&#13;
(2.60)      (3.05)    (4.39)      (.57)        (.05)&#13;
II           5.085**      .434**    .730**     .030        -            .9941      3.03&#13;
(2.96)      (3.14)    (4.69)      (.58)&#13;
III           -.310        .954**    -          .146*     20.33           .9874     4.42&#13;
(-.15)      (8.55)               (2.21)        (.88)&#13;
IV           4.797*       .432**    .774**      -           .651         .9940     3.06&#13;
(2.59)      (3.10)    (5.47)                   (.04)&#13;
V           .306         .993**    -          .154*        -            .9875     4.39&#13;
(.15)       (9.74)               (2.37)&#13;
18 observations (excluding crawling peg countries)&#13;
VI          4.355         .438*    1.326     -2.301     -15.66           .8217     3.12&#13;
(2.03)      (2.43)    (1.93)     (-.63)       (-.66)&#13;
VII          4.060         .431*    1.142     -1.775         -            .8288     3.05&#13;
(1.97)       (2.45)    (1.85)     (-.51)&#13;
VIII          3.288         .624**    -         4.330Q*      2.797         .7871     3.40&#13;
(1.45)       (3.76)               (3.08)        (.12)&#13;
IX          4.182         .486**    .922*       -        12.45           .8294     3.05&#13;
(2.01)       (3.06)    (3.91)                  (-.55)&#13;
X          3.320         .631**    -         4.414**       -            .8011     3.29&#13;
(1.53)       (4.22)               (3.76)&#13;
Note:    *  Significant at 5 per cent level; ** significant at 1 per cent level.&#13;
Numbers in parentheses underneath the coefficient estimates are t-valuese&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 64 -&#13;
are also observed in the regression equations having Em as another explanatory&#13;
variable; however, where Em is not included in the specification (equations III&#13;
and V for the entire sample, VIII and X for the subsample excluding the&#13;
crawling peg countries), there is apparently a significant influence of&#13;
E2                   *             .2&#13;
E~. Even so, having ES instead of Em seems superior, judged by the usual&#13;
statistical criteria (higher t-statistic and R , and lower s.e.e.). No&#13;
conclusive evidence is therefore provided with respect to the differential&#13;
effects of large versus small exchange rate changes on the domestic price level.&#13;
Overall, the most significant result of the above regression analysis&#13;
is the observed similarity in the magnitude of price response to crawling&#13;
peg changes in the exchange rate with that under the two other forms of&#13;
exchange rate adjustment. A further test is Drovided by the following&#13;
regression result, based on the entire sample of 22 countries, from a&#13;
specification having intercept and Emcoefficient dummies for the type of&#13;
exchange rate regime. (DC = 1 for crawling peg countries; DS   1 for&#13;
countries with small gradual exchange rate changes):&#13;
(4.7)   P  =  4.445 +   .459 (A - Y)  + .795 X-i .045 DCFn&#13;
(1.19)   (2.66)          (2.73)      (-.16)&#13;
+  .128 DSFm     - .086 DC -   .430 DS&#13;
(.27)          (-.02)   j (-.15)&#13;
-2&#13;
R    .9930       s.e.e. - 3.28    -&#13;
The coefficient estimates for M - Y and 4 re significant at the&#13;
5 per cent level, but not those for the exchange rate regime dummy variables.&#13;
Thus, one may accept the hypothesis that the method of exchange rate adjustment&#13;
adopted in the sample countries does not shift the price equation in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 65 -&#13;
sense indicated above.-   It is also worth noting that the estimated coefficient&#13;
for E (.795) is within the range of the corresponding estimates presented&#13;
earlier. Given the limited sample size and data imperfections, the relation-&#13;
ship between the exchange rate and domestic price level as represented in&#13;
the above regression results appears quite robust. Moreover, the high values&#13;
of the coefficient of determination are suggestive of the general validity of&#13;
the hypotheses tested.&#13;
The implication from the above results that on average the general&#13;
price level rises by about 80 per cent of the rate of currency depreciation&#13;
-- money supply and real output remaining the same -- is at variance with the&#13;
findings in earlier studies cited above. While such magnitude of the&#13;
inflationary effect does not completely nullify the improvement in&#13;
international competitiveness that a devaluation is designed to confer&#13;
on the country's products, it represents a much more severe repercussion&#13;
on domestic prices than indicated in past empirical investigations.&#13;
Part of the reason would be that longer term price effects are captured in the&#13;
present study by using average levels and rates of change over a six-year&#13;
period. The results from other empirical studies using cross-country data&#13;
pertaining to a shorter time span would reflect to some extent dynamic&#13;
adjustments and short-run disturbances which render more difficult taking&#13;
into account the cumulative effect of exchange rate changes on the domestic&#13;
price level. Hence, the long-runi inflationary effect might tend to be&#13;
1/ Ble4er and Halevi (1980) have found that the inflationary effect of&#13;
exchange rate changes in Israel during the period 1968-1976 is not sensitive&#13;
to the change in exchange rate regime, using also intercept and slope&#13;
dummy variables to distinguish the crawling peg subperiod beginning mid-1975.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 66 -&#13;
underestimated if one relied simply on estimates based on cross-country data&#13;
over one, two or three years.&#13;
Another explanation for the higher price response coefficient estimated&#13;
in this study would be that the exposure of developing countries, or at&#13;
least those included in our sample, to the international economy has presumably&#13;
become stronger over the years. The actual extent of such exposure is not&#13;
measurable simply by the weight of imports in the final expenditure basket --&#13;
our "degree of openness" variable, whose coefficient did not prove significant&#13;
in the above regressions -- but "of the relevant group of tradables, that is,&#13;
including close domestically produced import substitutes" (Bruno, 1978; p. 379).&#13;
A final consideration is that the dramatic developments in the world&#13;
economy during the 1970s might have altered the economic structure underlying&#13;
the price equation that prevailed under the Brettons Woods regime. Price&#13;
expectations, whose influence on domestic price behavior has been virtually&#13;
left out of account in the present study (as well as in most other empirical&#13;
investigations of the determinants of LDC inflation rates), would likely&#13;
have reinforced the inflationary effect of exchange rate changes in the&#13;
recent period compared to the calmer decades of the 1950s and 1960s.&#13;
The adoption of generalized currency floating among developed countries&#13;
would have contributed to the widespread breakdown of money illusion,&#13;
particularly "exchange rate illusion," in developing countries in view&#13;
of the greater attention now being given to the real international value&#13;
of an LDC's currency.&#13;
Interpreting the Em coefficient in the above regressions as a long-&#13;
run elasticity measure, the resulting estimates of around .80 would not&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 67 -&#13;
seem unreasonable. They are evidently much higher than the findings of&#13;
empirical studies pertaining to postwar LDC experience through the early&#13;
1970s, which however are not comparable in many ways. It is worth noting&#13;
that, in a recent investigation of the influence of exchange rate changes&#13;
on prices in eighteen developed countries, "the main conclusion ... is&#13;
that parity changes have a larger and a quicker effect on the rate of&#13;
inflation than they used to have" (Robinson et al., 1979; p. 48). A&#13;
related finding is obtained in an analysis of inflation rates during&#13;
1972-76 in sixteen developed countries, "pointing to a very marked direct&#13;
role of import costs in the inflationary process in these countries";&#13;
moreover, "even for a country as 'closed' as the United States empirical&#13;
studies point to a large and significant effect of import prices in recent&#13;
years" (Bruno, 1978; p. 389).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68 -&#13;
V. EXCHANGE RATE ADJUSTMENTS AND EXPORT PERFORMANCE&#13;
Introduction&#13;
two sources of effective exchange rate changes under the present&#13;
system of generalized currency floating have been identified above as having&#13;
relative price effects on export profitability (or competitiveness) in&#13;
developing countries. One is the realignment of major currency exchange&#13;
rates, over which individual LDCs have no control, affecting export&#13;
profitability relative to import-competing production through its impact&#13;
on the domestic prices of exports and imports. The country' s exchange&#13;
rate policy, which determines the nominal effective exchange rate, also gives&#13;
rise to relative price effects directly influencing export competitiveness.&#13;
Other things remaining the same, an increase in the real exchange rate --&#13;
defined as the nominal rate adjusted by the inflation differential&#13;
(domestic vs. foreign) -- raises the price of exportables relative to home&#13;
goods, which encourages the expansion of export supply.&#13;
The purpose of this section is to investigate the influence of&#13;
exchange rate changes on .the export performance of the 22 sample LDCs in&#13;
the recent period, evaluating the contributions of major currency realignments&#13;
and real exchange rate adjustments. Most empirical studies on the responsive-&#13;
ness of LDC exports to exchange rate changes have been concerned solely with&#13;
the induced relative price movements associated with changes in the real&#13;
exchange rate. While this is appropriate in the context of fixed exchange&#13;
rates among major currencies, some attention to the relative price effect&#13;
of major currency realignments is also warranted under the present system&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 69 -&#13;
of generalized currency floating among developed countries. Related to this,&#13;
one specific fear of LDCs concerning increased exchange rate flexibility&#13;
among major currencies has been that it would raise the cost of foreign&#13;
trade relative to domestic transactions, inhibiting therefore export growth.&#13;
An attempt is made in this study to empirically ascertain the negative&#13;
effect on LDC exports of the variability of exchange rates under generalized&#13;
floating.&#13;
Results from Cross-Country Regressions&#13;
The following export coeff:fcient function, expressed in terms of&#13;
proportionate changes, was estimated using data for the 22 sample countries&#13;
over the period 1973-78 to examine quantitatively the influence of NPXM and&#13;
PPPEER and their variability on total and manufactured exports:&#13;
(5.1)  x  =  f(ne, vn, pe, v , X/Y, L, DC, DS)&#13;
where&#13;
x    -   average annual rate of increase in export volume minus&#13;
average annual increase in domestic output&#13;
ne   =   average annual rate of increase in NPXM&#13;
vm   =   variability measure of NPXM&#13;
pe       average annual rate of increase in PPPEER&#13;
x&#13;
v    =   variability measure for PPPEER&#13;
p                            x&#13;
X/Y  =   ratio of total exports to gross domestic product, in per&#13;
cent&#13;
L        per capita gross domestic product, in hundred U.S. dollars&#13;
It is hypothesized in (5.1) that the share of domestic output sold&#13;
in the export market is related positively to the levels of the two export&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 70 -&#13;
profitability indices NPXM and PPPEER, and negatively to the variability&#13;
of these indices. The variable X/Y is intended to capture the "cumulative&#13;
aspect of export performance" -- LDCs which have had greater exposure to&#13;
foreign markets, benefitting from learning-by-doing and scale economies&#13;
in the production and marketing of export products -- are expected to have&#13;
greater capability in further expanding exports, other things the same.&#13;
GDP per capita is a proxy variable for the level of economic development,&#13;
assumed to be related positively to the ability of LDCs to shift supply&#13;
of tradable goods between domestic and foreign markets, e.g., in providing&#13;
the necessary complement of infrastructure facilities. Lastly, the two&#13;
dummy variables DC and DS allow the intercept to shift from one exchange&#13;
rate regime to another, distinguishing among sample countries that adopted&#13;
the crawling peg, those that had small-step exchange rate adjustments and&#13;
those that underwent large, discrete devaluations.&#13;
Table 5.1 presents a selection of regression results having the&#13;
correct signs for the coefficients of the exchange rate-related explanatory&#13;
variables. They exemplify the extremely poor statistical fit obtained for&#13;
both total and manufactured exports. Neither of the two proxy variables&#13;
for real exchange risk, vn and vp, yielded the expected negative influence&#13;
on the export coefficient, which is why they do not appear in the table.&#13;
While the range of the coefficient estimates for ne and pe seem plausible,&#13;
the very small t-values imply a low degree of reliability. On sililar&#13;
grounds no statistical significance can be given to the estimated&#13;
coefficients for X/Y and L. Lastly, the variation in the changes in&#13;
export coefficient across sample countries also cannot be attributed to&#13;
differences in the type of exchange rate adjustment adopted during the&#13;
period.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 5.1: Selected Results from Cross-Country Regressions On the Effects&#13;
of Exchange Rate Adjustment on Export Performance&#13;
(Dependent variable: x)&#13;
Equation                                                                                              2&#13;
No.          Const .       ne          pe        X/Y          L          DS           DC         R          s.e.e.&#13;
Total exports&#13;
I            6.030        .307       .238       .069        .100       -3.395      -1.712        .181       6.22&#13;
(1.66)      (.14)       (.41)     (1.01)      (.51)        (-.94)      (-.42)&#13;
II            8.564**      .427       .488                              -3.170      -2.265       .081        6.19&#13;
(2.48)      (.21)       (.91)                             (-.89)       (-.57)&#13;
III            6.999**     1.127       .292        -.037                                                      5.99&#13;
(4.25)      (.63)       (.62)&#13;
Manufactured exports&#13;
I            -.082        .649       .835      -.033        .203       -.702        5.194        .170      10.64&#13;
(-.01)      (.26)       (.81)     (-.27)      (.66)      (-.12)         (.75)&#13;
II            2.313        .943      1.047        -          -         -1.822        5.214        .146     10.14&#13;
(.54)      (.42)      (1.16)                            (-.34)         (.80)&#13;
III            2.48       1.158        .958        -          -            -            -          .076       9.97&#13;
(1.02)      (.53)      (1.18)&#13;
Notes:  **Significant at the 1 per cent level.&#13;
Numbers in parentheses underneath coefficient estimates are their t-values.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 72 -&#13;
There are several possible explanations for the insignificant results&#13;
obtained from the cross-country regressions. One is that inter-country&#13;
economic data, especially across developing countries, are generally&#13;
comparable only to a limited extent. While the comparability of say,&#13;
real output estimates (GDP, industrial and manufacturing production indices&#13;
as used above) may be questioned due to domestic price distortions of&#13;
varying extent among LDCs and other reasons, expressing the variables in&#13;
the regression equation in proportionate chavn.ges (instead of levels) as&#13;
done above serves to improve the reliability of an estimated relationship.&#13;
As may be discerned from the description of data sources given in Appendix 1,&#13;
however, other difficulties concerning data comparability are present --&#13;
for example, our having to use (due to limitations of available data)&#13;
different source materials and different measures of the same variable,&#13;
especially with respect to export volume and production data for manufactured&#13;
goods.&#13;
Another possible reason is the omission of potentially significant&#13;
explanatory variables in the export coefficient function as estimated above.&#13;
One relevant influence on export performance which has not been taken into&#13;
account due to lack of (comparable) data is that due to changes in domestic&#13;
commercial policies. The implicit assumption in the above regressions is&#13;
that the evolution of trade and payments policies in the sample countries&#13;
over the observation period 1973-78 had affected relative export incentives&#13;
in similar directions and magnitudes. This is undoubtedly more plausible&#13;
in the context of the 1970s which saw a widespread policy shift toward&#13;
export promotion (at least among the countries included in our sample)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 73 -&#13;
compared to the two previous decades. It may be noted also that, based&#13;
on a regression analysis involving the ten LDCs included in the NBE1R&#13;
project, Krueger (1978) finds that the trade and payments regime does not&#13;
exert a significant influence on export earnings "other than through an&#13;
overvalued real EER" (p. 204).&#13;
But perhaps the most important explanation for the failure of the&#13;
above cross-country regressions to estimate the export coefficient&#13;
function with any statistical significance is the lack of homogeneity&#13;
in the economic structure of the sample developing countries which the&#13;
inclusion of the shift variables X/Y and L has not adequately dealt with.&#13;
Various characteristics of LDC economies, including nonquantifiable&#13;
"cultural" and institutional factors,l/ presumably have an important bearing&#13;
on the ability of export producers to respond to the opportunities created&#13;
or eliminated by changes in the relative incentive structure.&#13;
On the basis of the above results, cross-country regression analysis&#13;
does not seem to provide a good basis for making generalizations across&#13;
developing countries about the responsiveness of export supply to the&#13;
relative price effects of exchange rate changes.    It probably requires&#13;
an elaborate country-specific model that provides for the general equilibrium&#13;
repercussions of exchange rate changes through interactions with domestic&#13;
price and output variables to be able to assess the empirical magnitude of&#13;
the long-term export response. In what follows we continue to use the partial&#13;
1/ See, for example, Keesing (1979; pp. 80-85) for a relevant discussion&#13;
of the following "problem" areas in national capabilities: management,&#13;
technology acquisition, marketing, design and capital goods.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 74 -&#13;
equilibrium framework, but applied to time series data for individual LDCs,&#13;
in seeking to evaluate the more immediate impact of the observed changes&#13;
in the two export profitability indices on export supply under generalized&#13;
currency floating.&#13;
Results from Individual Country Regressions&#13;
We follow Krueger (1978), among previous investigators, in taking&#13;
export earnings as the dependent variable in the regressions for individual&#13;
countries based on quarterly data for the period 1974-79. Our concern here&#13;
is not with the long-term or trend rate of growth of LDC export earnings,&#13;
which is assumed exogenously given,-L but with the deviations from trend.&#13;
Assuming that the trend rate of growth of exports is simply a function of&#13;
time, we attempted to estimate the following two specifications of the&#13;
export earnings function:&#13;
(5.2)  log Xt  =  g (log NEt, log Vnt, log PEt, log Vpt' t Ql' Q2, Q3)&#13;
(5.3)  log Xt  =  h (log NE', log V     log PE', log V    t,              logQX&#13;
where, for each quarter t (from 1974:I to 1979:IV),&#13;
X    =  export earnings in U.S. dollars&#13;
NE   =  average of monthly NPXM values in the current and&#13;
previous three quarters&#13;
NE' = average of monthly NPXM values in the current quarter&#13;
1/ The lack of statistical significance in the estimation results presented&#13;
earlier is consistent with the assumption that factors other than&#13;
exchange rate changes have had a predominant influence on the trend&#13;
growth rate of LDC export earnings for the period under study.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 75 -&#13;
V    =  standard deviation of monthly NPXM values in the&#13;
current and previous three quarters&#13;
PE   = average of monthly PPPEER    values in the current and&#13;
previous quarters        x&#13;
PE'  = average of monthly PPPEER values in the current&#13;
quarter                  x&#13;
V    =  standard deviation of monthly PPPEER values in the&#13;
current and previous three quarters&#13;
t    =  trend variable (t = 1 for 1974:I, etc.)&#13;
Q19 Q2, Q3  =  quarterly dummy variables.&#13;
Having the trend variable in the right-hand side of (5.2) and (5.3)&#13;
serves to isolate the trend growth rate of export earnings.-/ The other&#13;
explanatory variables are then the determinants of quarterly deviations from&#13;
the trend rate. The two specifications differ with respect to the lag&#13;
structure of export response to movements in NPXM and PPPEER . In (5.2)&#13;
current changes in the two relative profitability indices are assumed to&#13;
affect export earnings uniformly for four quarters; in (5.3) the exponential&#13;
Koyck-Nerlove lag pattern is hypothesized. There are obviously other&#13;
possible lag structures that could also have been tried; while it is common&#13;
in the estimation of behavioral equations involving distributed lags to&#13;
experiment with various lag formulations, we recognize the danger that&#13;
spurious correlations will be obtained (since each hypothesized lag&#13;
structure is not being tested by a new set of independent observations).&#13;
Two additional explanatory variables were considered in the estimation&#13;
of the export earnings function in either specification. Depending on data&#13;
l/ Inevitably, t serves as a catchall for the trend (positive or negative)&#13;
component of all influences on dollar export earnings not included in&#13;
the regression, including the foreign price of exports, level and&#13;
utilization of productive capacity in the domestic economy, and other&#13;
supply shift variables.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 76 -&#13;
availability (from the IFS computer file of the IMF), the terms of trade (TT)&#13;
variable, represented by the unit value index of exports divided by the&#13;
unit value index of imports (in U.S. dollar terms), was introduced in the&#13;
regressions to capture another aspect of relative export profitability&#13;
vis-a-vis import-competing production, i.e., the influence of external&#13;
price changes. It is recognized that unit value indices do not accurately&#13;
reflect changes in the foreign prices of a country's exports and imports&#13;
(cf. Kravis and Lipsey, 1971). More than the usual caution is therefore&#13;
warranted in the interpretation of the resulting coefficient estimates.&#13;
Additionally, for countries that underwent large, discrete devaluations or&#13;
shifted to a different exchange rate regime during the observation period,&#13;
a dummy variable (DE) was introduced to allow the intercept of the function to&#13;
take on different values. This was meant to capture any positive or negative&#13;
effects on export performance due to the adoption of other policy measures&#13;
accompanying the devaluation or shift in exchange rate regime.&#13;
The estimation of (5.2) and (5.3) was done using available (published)&#13;
quarterly data for all 22 sample LDCs in the regressions for total exports&#13;
and for 12 countries in the regressions for manufactured exports.-/ Several&#13;
regression trials were entailed for each country. Any of the four exchange&#13;
rate-related variables yielding theoretically incorrect signs, or t-values&#13;
of coefficient estimates less than one (and hence not adding to the explanation&#13;
of the variance of the dependent variable), were dropped in subsequent&#13;
regressions. The quarterly dummies were included in every regression as a&#13;
1/ Given the difficulty of compiling quarterly data on manufactured exports&#13;
by developing countries, the 12 countries had been chosen mainly on the&#13;
basis of data accessibility.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 77 -&#13;
seasonal adjustment.  The dummy variable DE was retained only where it does&#13;
not detract from the explanatory power of the exchange rate-based variables.&#13;
The same decision was made on the terms of trade variable, in recognition of&#13;
the notoriously low degree of reliability of published data on unit export&#13;
and import values.&#13;
Regression results in which the problem of autocorrelation was&#13;
evident-V from the computed values of the Durbin-Watson statistic were&#13;
re-estimated using the first-order Cochrane-Orcutt iterative technique.&#13;
As is well known, the Durbin-Watson statistic cannot be used to detect&#13;
(first-order) serial correlation in regressions with a lagged dependent&#13;
variable (as in equation (5.3) above) because it will generally tend toward 2.&#13;
We computed the h-statistic-/ in such cases and used the test of first-order&#13;
serial correlation for autoregressive models as proposed by Durbin (1970).&#13;
Multicollinearity proved to be a major problem in the estimation&#13;
of (5.3) because log Xt 1 has a strong trend for many sample countries. This&#13;
was dealt with in the relevant cases by dropping the trend variable. It&#13;
was also observed in the estimation of (5.2) that log NEt and/or log PEt are&#13;
correlated with t for some countries, the trend variable tending to&#13;
draw away from the explanatory power of the relative export profitability&#13;
variables. Since we have not done anything about this problem, the&#13;
1/ At the 5 per cent level of significance.&#13;
2/ The h-statistic is defined as&#13;
h  =  (1 - D.W./2)         N&#13;
1 - n var (a)&#13;
where N = number of observations, D.W. = Durbin-Watson statistic,&#13;
and var (a) = variance of the estimated coefficient of the lagged&#13;
dependent variable. For large sarnple size, the h-statistic follows&#13;
the standardized normal distribution if the first-order serial&#13;
correlation coefficient is zero.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 78 -&#13;
coefficient estimates for log NEt and log PEt could likely understate the&#13;
relevant export elasticities. This should be borne in mind in the inter-&#13;
pretation of the regression results, even though our primary interes.&#13;
is not in the coefficinet estimates for individual countries but rather&#13;
in the general pattern across countries.&#13;
The criterion used in choosing the "best" estimated equation for&#13;
each country from among the regression results thus screened is the&#13;
coefficient of multiple determinatiorc adjusted for degrees of freedom (R ).&#13;
Tables 5.2 and 5.3 contain these equations for total and manufactured exports,&#13;
respectively, excluding the quarterly dummy variables. The regressions for&#13;
Indonesia and Singapore did not yield any acceptable results for total&#13;
exports, which is why these two countries are not represented in Table 5.2.&#13;
Probably responsible for the poor regression results for Indonesia is the&#13;
lack of explicit consideration of the country's oil export earnings which&#13;
grew rapidly over the observation period independently of exchange rate&#13;
changes. In the case of Singapore, the strong trend component of real exchange&#13;
rate movements prevented its influence on total export earnings from being&#13;
isolated in the regressions based on (5.2) and (5.3).-/   Exactly the same&#13;
case applied to the manufactured export regressions for Malaysia,-/ for which&#13;
reason this country has not been included in Table 5.3.&#13;
At least 75 per cent of the variance of the dependent variable is&#13;
explained by the results presented in Tables 5.2 and 5.3, except for five&#13;
1/ The partial correlation coefficient is about .90 between log PE and t&#13;
and also between log PE' and log X_. It is worth noting that log PE,&#13;
together with the quarterly dummies, can explain already about 60 per&#13;
cent of the variance of log X for Singapore.&#13;
2/ Regression of log PE, Q1l Q2, Q3 on log X yielded a value of the&#13;
adjusted coefficient of determination of .52.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 5.2: 3elected Results from Individual Courntry Regressions: Total Exports&#13;
(Deperndent Variable: log X)&#13;
CouAntry                                                                                                                                -2&#13;
(Estistion techiqu;      Con.ta.-t    log NE       log Vn       l.g PE      log V           t      log X-1        log TT       DE                       s.e.e.-       D.W.&#13;
no. of observati.ns)                                                                                                                                                 (h)&#13;
Argentina                   3.012**      -          -.184*         -          -.174**     .0196**        -           -            -           .837         .062        2.13&#13;
(OLS; 22)                (52.95)                  (-2.94)                   (-4.43)     (9.33)&#13;
Brazil                    -1.928         -            -         1.798          -          .01315*        -          .764*         -           .875        .041         1.50&#13;
(OLS; 23)                 (-.63)                               (1.43)                   (9.20)                    (2.58)&#13;
Colombia                   -.163         -            -            -          -.172*        -           .727**      .476*         -           .882        .053         2.44&#13;
(OLS; 24)                 (-.63)                                            (-2.47)                   (6.95)      (2.74)                                             (-1.26)&#13;
Coata Rica                 2.032-*       -            -            -          -.052       .0150**        -           -            -           .809        .059         200&#13;
(OLS;24)                 (42.92)                                            (-1.24)     (6.11)&#13;
Egypt                    -18.81       10.73           -           -            -         -.0C12         -            -            -           .252        .074         2.56&#13;
(1OI5; 221               (-1.71)      (1.94)                                            (-.36)&#13;
Greece                     2.832**       -            -           -            .14-3*                   .191         -            -           .617        .061         2.14&#13;
C9LS; 23)                (12.44)                                            (-2.32)                   (1.68)                                                          (-.40)&#13;
India                      -.660         -            -         1.288*        -.066         -           .379         -            -           .825        .044         2.29&#13;
(OLS; 24)                (-1.30)                               (2.76)       (-1.32)                   (2.08)                                                         (-1.58)&#13;
Halayaia                  -5.850       3.069          -            -           -          .0159**        -         1.300**        -           .973        .019         1.90&#13;
{C-O; 23)                (-1.30)      (1.91)                                            (6.10)                    (7.98)&#13;
Mexico                      2.810**      -            -            -          -.071       .0234**        -           -           .862         .645        .048         2.21&#13;
(C-0; 22)                (20.74)                                            (-1.20)     (3.27)                                 (1.40)&#13;
Morocco                   -40.30**     8.56**       -¢065        2.874*        -          .0186**        -           -            -           .761         .040        1.22&#13;
(OLS; 19)                 (.6.56)     (6.46)      (-1.31)      (2.69)                   (4.61)&#13;
Pakistan                  -1.172         -            -         l.611**        -          .Ca173**       -           -            -           .823        .051         1.98&#13;
(OLS; 24)                (-1.36)                               (4.06)                   (9.37)&#13;
Philippines                -.833       2-879        -.083       1.986          -          .0209**       -            811**        -          .892         .040         2.08&#13;
(OLS; 24)                 (-.15)      (1.39)      t-1-23)      (1.98)                   (3.92)                    (4.87)&#13;
Por1.ugal                -18.18*      10.40*        -.336**       -            -          .0203**       -            -            -           .563        .068         1.27&#13;
(C2S; 23)                (-2.31)      (2.65)      (-3.36)                               (3.15)&#13;
South Korea                 .989         -            -         1.026         -.074*      .0305**       -            -          -.045         .967        .038         1.34&#13;
(OLS; 24)                  (.63)                               (1.26)       (-2.80)    (12.98)                                (-1.45)&#13;
Spain                     -8.198       5.701          -            -          -.077       .0103*        -            -            -           .920        .038         1.46&#13;
(OLS;22)                 (-1.19)      (1.65)                                (-1.96)     (2.22)&#13;
Taiwan                      .060         -            -            -          -.033         -           .987**       -            -           .950        .042         2.31&#13;
(OLS; 24)                  (.35)                                            (-1.47)                  (19.33)                                                          (-.78)&#13;
Thailand                   1.982         -            -          2.293         -          .0162**       -            -            -           .860        .041         1.88&#13;
(C-0; 23)                  (.99)                               (1.88)                   (3.45)&#13;
Turkey                    -3.586         -            -          3.222*        -          .0089*         -           -            -           .693        .071         2.26&#13;
(OLS; 23)                (-1.22)                                (2.16)                  (2.19)&#13;
Tunisia                   -4.375*        -            -          3.346**       -          .00768        -            -            -           .770        .070         2.20&#13;
(OLS- 24)                (-2.66)                               (4.07)                   (2.98)&#13;
Uruguay                     1.044        -            -           .695         -          .0167**        -           Y.           -           .762         .071        1.83&#13;
(OLS; 24)                 (1.13)                               (1.75)                   (7.32)&#13;
Notes:   Numbers in parentueses underneath the coefficient estimates are their t-values.&#13;
*Significant at the 5 per cent level.&#13;
**Significant at the I per cent l-vel.&#13;
For Mexico: DE = 0 from 1974:1     to 1976:III             For South .orea:   DE = 0 from 1974:1     to 1974:IV&#13;
=  I from 1976:IV to 1979:1II                                    = I from 1975:1    to 1979:IV&#13;
Where log X 1 (instead of t) appears in the estimated regression equation, the entries under log NE and log PE refer to log NE' and log PE', respectively.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
rable 5.3: Selected Results from Individual Country Regressions: Manufactured Exports&#13;
(Dependent Variable:  log X)&#13;
(Estimation technique;        Constant       log NE      log PE      log V            t         log X         jg TT        R2          s.e.e.       D.W.&#13;
no. of observations)                                                      P                                                                        (h)&#13;
Brazil                          .340          -             -           -.141*        -            .912**       -            .953         .027        1.15&#13;
(OLS; 20)                     (1.83)                                  (-2.47)                   (15.84)                                              (1.90)&#13;
Egypt                         -8.979           -          5.56*        -.407*       -.0064         -                         .704         .069        2.66&#13;
(OS, 15)                    (.2.21)                    (2.78)      (-2.82)        (-.76)&#13;
India                          -.624          -           1.696        -.074         .0078         -                         .833         .047        2.46&#13;
(0L5; 18)                     (-.41)                    (2.17)       (-1.47)       (1.48)&#13;
Pakistan                        .526          -            .872*         -           .0147**       -            -            .774         .037        1.39&#13;
(C-0; 23)                      (.43)                    (2.33)                     (7.76)&#13;
Philippines                   -6.140        1.274         2.531**        -           .0338**       -           .329          .979         .026        1.79&#13;
(01.S; 21)                   (-2.14)       (1.35)       (5.17)                     (9.82)                    (2.00)&#13;
Singapore                     -1.092          -            .790          -     -                   .860**       -            .946         .037        1.65&#13;
(OI.S; 24)                   (-1.23)                    (1.24)                                   (6.41)                                               (.87)&#13;
South Korea                   -2.707*       1.048*          -            -           .0255**       -          1..722**       .981         .031        1:'19    0&#13;
(OLS; 24)                    (-2.25)       (2.25)                                 (14.95)                    (6.88)&#13;
Tah,?an                         .064          -             -          -.040                       .985**       -            .939         .049        2.09&#13;
',L   24)                      (.34)                                 (-1.43)                    (17.38)                                              (-.23)&#13;
-2.832          -          2.381*         -            .0222**       -            -            .881         .066        1.19&#13;
-; 22.                    (-1.47)                    (2.46)                     (6.15)&#13;
Turkey                        -3.274           -          2.742          -           .0068*        -            -            .168         .077        1.14&#13;
(OLS; 21)                     (-.95)                    (1.56)                     (2.25)&#13;
Uruguay                       -4.474           -          2.936*         -           .0244**       -            -            .837          .105       2.05&#13;
(OS; 19)                    (-1.83)                    (2.33)                     (3.12)&#13;
Notes: . umibers in parentheses underneath the coefficient estimates are their t-values.&#13;
*Significant at the 5 per cent level.&#13;
**Significant at the I per cent level.&#13;
Where log X   (instead of t) appears in the estimated regression equation, the entries under log NE and log PE refer to log NE' and PE', respectively.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 81 -&#13;
countries in the total export regressions and two countries in those for&#13;
manufactured exports.  R values are seen to be generally higher for manu-&#13;
factured export regressions compared to those for total exports of the&#13;
respective countries.&#13;
The coefficient estimates for the exchange rate regime dummy show&#13;
contrasting signs for the tw.o countries where its influence on total exports&#13;
proved significant (marginally). For Mexico it would appear that the&#13;
devaluation of September 1976 had a favorable effect on export earnings&#13;
beyond that which can be attributed to the exchange rate change. The&#13;
opposite case seems to apply to the South Korean devaluation in December&#13;
1974. In the regressions for manufactured exports,-not one of the results&#13;
for the 12 countries indicated a significant influence of the exchange rate&#13;
dummy variable, for which reason the column for DE has been omitted in&#13;
Table 5.3.&#13;
The terms of trade variable added significantly to the explanatory&#13;
power of the estimated equations for four countries in the total export&#13;
regressions and for two countries in those for manufactured exports. The&#13;
indicated elasticities range from .33 to 1.72 for Philippine and South&#13;
Korea manufactured exports, respectively.&#13;
Considering now the exchange rate-based explanatory variables, we&#13;
find the influence of the real exchange rate -- in terms of both its&#13;
level and variabi.'Lity -- to be more pervasive among the countries under&#13;
study than that due to major currency realignments. The regression results&#13;
for total exports in Table 5.2 indicate only 5 countries with entries in the&#13;
log NE column, and 3 under log Vn. In Table 5.3 manufactured exports are&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 82 -&#13;
seen to be even less sensitive to exogenous foreign exchange rate changes:&#13;
only, 2 of the 11 countries represented have statistically acceptable&#13;
coefficient estimates for log NE, and not one for log V (which is why the&#13;
column for log V has been omitted). B-y7 contrast, significant coefficient&#13;
n                      .&#13;
estimates for log PE have been obtained for 10 countries in the total&#13;
export regressions and for 8 countries in the manufactured export&#13;
regressions; moreover, real exchange rate variability appears to be a&#13;
significant influence on total exports for 9 countries and on manufactured&#13;
exports for 4 countries.&#13;
It may be recalled that, for many of the sample LDCs, the changes&#13;
in NPXM were quite small during the observation period -- relative to the&#13;
real exchange rate (PPPEERx) movements and also in absolute terms. This&#13;
probably underlies the observed lack of significance of log NE in the&#13;
regressions for several countries. In view of the transactions costs in&#13;
shifting between domestic and export markets, the small changes in NPXM&#13;
might not have stimulated any export response for a number of sample LDCs.&#13;
However, export behavior can be expected to be significantly influenced&#13;
in cases where major currency realignments result in sufficiently large&#13;
changes in NPXM.&#13;
At least three of the coefficient estimates for log NE (which can&#13;
be interpreted as export elasticity estimates) shown in Table 5.2 appear&#13;
unrealistically very high. From a statistical viewpoint, this might&#13;
have resulted from an inappropriate association between the small changes&#13;
in NPXM and large changes in total export earnings during the observation&#13;
period which. the omission of other explanatory variables in the regressions&#13;
(due to lack of ava.ilable data) made possible. It may be noted in this&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 83 -&#13;
connection that regressions including the terms of trade variable in the&#13;
specification yielded much lower estimates to the NPXM elasticity for&#13;
either total or manufactured exports.&#13;
That the real exchange rate variable proved to have a significant&#13;
influence on exports, particuilarly manufactured exports, in the majority&#13;
of the sample LDCs is hardly surprising. It only adds to the recently&#13;
growing empirical evidence that the real exchange rate does matter.1/&#13;
By how much it matters is reflected in the sizable export response implied&#13;
by the elasticity estimates: 2/ from Tables 5.2 and 5.3,only in 4 cases are&#13;
the estimates less than 1, 6 estimates lie between 1 and 2, while the&#13;
remaining 9 estimates exceed 2.&#13;
But what is really striking about the results presented above is the&#13;
large number of cases in which real exchange rate variability appears as&#13;
a significant explanatory variable in the regressions. For several countries,&#13;
our findings suggest that real exchange rate uncertainty has been a more&#13;
important consideration in export supply than the changes in relative prices&#13;
due to nominal exchange rate adjustments and major currency realignments.&#13;
This is consistent with the results of a few previous empirical studies on&#13;
individual countries. For example, Goes' (1979) investigation of the&#13;
export coefficient function for 13 industrial and 9 primary product sectors&#13;
1/ See, for example, Donges and Riedel (1977) and Krueger (1978) wlhich&#13;
summarize the findings of individual country studies sponsored by the&#13;
Kiel Institute of World Economics and the National Bureau of Economic&#13;
Research, respectively.&#13;
2/ Note that these elasticity estimates need to be interpreted in terms of&#13;
the incremental change in export earnings in addition to whatever trend&#13;
rate of increase is being experienced.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 84 -&#13;
in Brazil for the period 1957-1974, using the Rothschild-Stiglitz "mean&#13;
preserving spread" definition of "more uncertainty", concludes that "the&#13;
reduction in real exchange rate uncertainty may have been at least as&#13;
important as changes in relative prices in explaining the greater openness&#13;
of the Brazilian economy after 1968" (p. 2). Also, according to Krueger&#13;
(1978), "Behrman [for Chile] and Diaz [for Argentina] found the variance&#13;
in the real exchange rate to be an important explanatory variable for the&#13;
behavior of exports" (p. 202). Additional work on individual LDCs seems&#13;
warranted from which to draw more definitive conclusions concerning the&#13;
influence of exchange rate uncertainty on LDC export performance than what&#13;
the present broad-based study can reasonably provide. Such in-depth studies&#13;
could examine more disaggregative export supply functions, improve on the&#13;
amount and quality of published data, test alternative measures of exchange&#13;
rate uncertainty and deal more adequately with the perennial problem of&#13;
specificatiori error and other econometric problems.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 85&#13;
VI. POLICY IMPLICATIONS AND DIRECTIONS&#13;
FOR FURTHER RESEARCH&#13;
The analyses and findings of this study provide some guidance for&#13;
LDC policymaking related to exchange rate adjustments under the present&#13;
system of generalized currency floating. It is useful to discuss the&#13;
policy implications and areas for further work under two headings corres-&#13;
ponding to the two basic sources of effective exchange rate changes as&#13;
described earlier.&#13;
Major Currency Realignments&#13;
Developing countries have been subject to a new form of external&#13;
economic disturbance since the adoption of generalized floating among major&#13;
currencies in March 1973. LDCs with strong links in trade and payments to&#13;
developed countries and a low degree of geographic and commodity diversification&#13;
seem particularly vulnerable to the exogenous realignment of major currency&#13;
exchange rates which, as shown above, gives rise to relative price effects&#13;
on export supply vis-a-vis import-competing production.&#13;
Our empirical findings indicate that such measure of relative export&#13;
profitability has generally been influenced by major currency realignments&#13;
to only a moderate extent. Moreover, while it is generally recognized that&#13;
exchange rate uncertainty in nominal terms has increased with generalized&#13;
floating among major currencies, this has apparently not been translated&#13;
into higher variability of the relative price effect on exports to a critical&#13;
extent for most LDCs. For these reasons, only for a few sample countries&#13;
was export supply found to have been significantly affected by the relative&#13;
price effect due to major currency realignments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 86 -&#13;
This does not imply of course that the real effects of exogenous&#13;
foreign exchange rate chanlges can be safely ignored by LDC policymakers.&#13;
For one thing, the export elasticity estimates as presented above appear&#13;
quite high. While we have expressed some doubt on the statistical reliability&#13;
of some such estimates, the degree of export responsiveness to changes in&#13;
relative profitability induced by foreign currency realignments remains an&#13;
open empirical question. Moreover, one cannot rule out the possibility of&#13;
greater instability in the relative incentive structure for some developing&#13;
countries in the future arising from an increased volatility of major currency&#13;
exchange rates. Finally, it should be recognized that our measure of export&#13;
bias reflects the impact of major currency realignments on the relative&#13;
profitability on average of all export activities or those in manufacturing&#13;
production vis-a-vis all import-competing activities. This tends to under-&#13;
state the extent of actual changes faced by individual export producers whose&#13;
transactions are not as diversified as those of the national economy or the&#13;
entire manufacturing sector. One would expect this to be particularly true&#13;
for LDCs with a high degree of commodity and geographic concentration in&#13;
foreign trade.&#13;
As pointed out earlier, exchange rate policy affords no protection&#13;
for small developing countries from the relative price effect of exogenous&#13;
major currency realignments. Neither the choice of currency standard nor&#13;
home currency adjustments with respect to the standard has any offsetting&#13;
influence on the export bias index. To minimize the impact of foreign&#13;
exchange rate changes, geographic diversification of trade could be&#13;
promoted. Ho*7ever, where prices of an LDC's traded goods are set in&#13;
unified commodity markets and quoted in given foreign currencies, effective&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 87 -&#13;
protection would be provided only by trade diversification beyond particular&#13;
commodity groupings, for example, shifting from fuels and minerals to&#13;
manufactured exports (cf. Bautista and Riedel, 1980).&#13;
It is of course neither necessary nor appropriate that LDCs resist&#13;
at every instance the potential effects on the domestic economy of foreign&#13;
exchange rate realignments. Shifting comparative advantage for the&#13;
developing country over time would in part be reflected by the movements&#13;
in exchange rates among the currencies of its actual and potential trade partners&#13;
which, on efficiency grounds at least, should be allowed to induce changes in&#13;
the geographic and commodity structure of trade. Intervention on the part of&#13;
the LDC government would seem warranted under certain conditions. One is&#13;
"excessive" instability in the relative price effect in the context described&#13;
above, which adds to the cost of export activity and distorts resource&#13;
allocation. Another instance would be the existence of institutional&#13;
constraints that reduce the ability of domestic producers to respond to&#13;
the opportunities created or eliminated by major currency realignments;&#13;
it has been argued, for example, that intra-firm trade (i.e., among&#13;
affiliated multinational enterprises in different countries) is rendered&#13;
insensitive to foreign exchange rate changes by existing marketing arrangements&#13;
(Helleiner, 1979).&#13;
Finally, it should be recognized that there are differential effects&#13;
of major currency realignments on the production sectors of the domestic&#13;
economy (with differing geographic and commodity composition of foreign&#13;
trade) which may very well run counter to the longer-term interests of the&#13;
developing country. If foreign exchange rate changes negate the objectives&#13;
of development policy seeking to promote expansion of certain industries&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 88 -&#13;
and contraction of others, policy measures that compensate for the sectoral&#13;
effects of major currency realignment would seem necessary. One may draw an&#13;
analogy here with the practice in many LDCs of imposing new or additional&#13;
taxes on traditional primary product exports as part of a devaluation&#13;
package, a policy measure designed to siphon off part of the windfall gains&#13;
of this sector but not those of other (favored) export industries. On&#13;
similar grounds, there are differential income distribution effects of major&#13;
currency realignments which LDC policymakers may want to offset by adopting&#13;
measures that discriminate among different income groups (Bautista, 1977).&#13;
Nominal Exchange Rate Adjustments&#13;
Many contemporary LDCs are characterized by a fundamental disequilibrium&#13;
in their foreign trade and payments, a condition inherited from the pre-1971&#13;
system of fixed exchange rates. While in the past currency devaluation was&#13;
a politically hazardous policy measure, the present regime of generalized&#13;
floating among major currencies makes it almnost necessary for the government&#13;
in a developing courntry to actively manage the exchange rate, providing also&#13;
an opportunity to revamp their trade and payments system and improve the&#13;
efficiency of resource allocation.&#13;
While exchange ratepolicy has a direct influence on the real exchange&#13;
rate, the latter is also determined in part by the rate of domestic inflation.&#13;
Given the important role of the real exchange rate, in terms of both its&#13;
level and variability, to LDC export performance as suggested by the above&#13;
findings, export promotion efforts (which represent one instrument of trade&#13;
and payments adjustment) should give some attention to the proper coordination&#13;
of exchange rate management with domestic policies (monetary, fiscal, wage,&#13;
etc.) affecting the general price level. This assumes added significance&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 89 -&#13;
in view of the apparently larger inflationary effect of nominal exchange rate&#13;
changes in the 1970s under generalized currency floating than what it used to&#13;
be. The iaplication is that, other things remaining the same, a greater&#13;
cost in terms of a higher inflation rate is now associated with a given&#13;
real" devaluation,reducing on this account the effectiveness of exchange&#13;
rate adjustment as a means of improving international competitiveness. Of&#13;
course,the "other thingst" do not always remain the same, so there is some&#13;
leeway for individual LDCs to reduce the "cost" through policy measures&#13;
affecting favorably the relationship between aggregate supply and aggregate&#13;
demand.&#13;
A relevant finding from the empirical analysis in Section IV is that&#13;
the sensitivity of the domestic price level to exchange rate changes does&#13;
not differ significantly among countries adopting different exchange rate&#13;
regimes. This is consistent with the earlier observation (Section III)&#13;
about the lack of significant correlation between the conduct of monetary&#13;
and fiscal policies and type of exchange rate management. Moreover,&#13;
austaiited improvement in export competitiveness during the recent period&#13;
of generalized floating among major currencies has been observed (in&#13;
Section II) for sample countries which actively managed their exchange&#13;
rate via the crawling peg, those which allowed only small and gradual&#13;
exchange rate movements (even including currency appreciation over the&#13;
period) and those which underwent large, discrete devaluations. On the other&#13;
hand there has also been some counter-demonstrations for each type of exchange&#13;
rate management.&#13;
It is worth noting, nevertheless, that a greater proportion of sample&#13;
LDCs with relatively stable exchange rates have shown positive trends in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 90 -&#13;
the real exchange rate over the observation period. Thus, even without&#13;
substantial currency depreciation (in nominal terms), real exchange rate&#13;
adjustment could be promoted, with a good possibility of success, if the&#13;
national authorities were to implement policy measures directed toward&#13;
domestic price stability. For developing countries that have chosen&#13;
(or have been forced) to accept a domestic inflation rate much higher than&#13;
the foreign inflation rate, large and/or frequent nominal exchange rate&#13;
adjustments represent the only means of achieving and maintaining international&#13;
competitiveness. Of course, another solution to an existing problem of&#13;
currency overvaluation and associated trade and payments imbalance for such&#13;
countries would be to eliminate the sources of inflationary bias in the&#13;
economy through appropriate reform of existing institutions and policies,&#13;
which will permit real exchange rate adjustment through a reduction in the&#13;
differential inflation rate.&#13;
In some developing countries the immediate policy concern has to do&#13;
not so much with the overall external balance but with the existing&#13;
composition of the balance of payments which cannot be sustained and/or&#13;
is incompatible with longer-term policy objectives. LDCs with a heavy&#13;
concentration of minerals (and other products based on depletable resources)&#13;
in domestic production and exports, for instance, have an understandable&#13;
interest in economic diversification long before the exhaustion of their&#13;
mineral wealth.  They would want to develop efficient import-substituting&#13;
and export industries not having the characteristics of high capital&#13;
intensity and foreign domination associated with riining industries in the&#13;
transition to a growing and diversified post-mineral economy. More&#13;
generally, LDCs with a severely underutilized labor force are likely to&#13;
find better opportunities in the expansion of their exports of labor-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 91 -&#13;
intensive products as a means of promoting employment, and they may want&#13;
to do this regardless of whether their international transactions are balanced&#13;
or not. In some of these developing countries, export earnings from resource-&#13;
and capital-intensive products, tourist expenditures and/or long-term capital&#13;
inflows are in excess of what is necessary for external (basic) balance,&#13;
resulting in an exchange rate which does not provide adequate incentives&#13;
for labor-intensive exports.-   An additional consideration is that the&#13;
effective protection structure in developing countries is typically biased&#13;
in favor of import-substituting industries,-/ so that export-oriented&#13;
manufacture is being doubly penalized.&#13;
Clearly, there are many ways of offsetting these biases in the&#13;
industrial incentive structure, consisting of alternative combinations&#13;
of export taxes and subsidies, indirect taxes, tariff rates and currency&#13;
exchange rates applied differently to different production sectors. Which&#13;
of the policy alternatives are feasible? What are the costs associated&#13;
with each feasible policy package? While these empirical questions are&#13;
best examined in individual LDC contexts, comparative analysis across&#13;
countries could provide useful generalizations about the relative cost&#13;
effectiveness of alternative exchange rate and other policies aimed at&#13;
correcting the existing biases in the incentive structure against&#13;
manufactured exports.&#13;
It is clear that active management of exchange rates is a potentially&#13;
important policy tool that could enable LDCs to protect and advance their&#13;
1/ Paauw (1978), for example, gives an analysis of the Indonesian case.&#13;
2/ See, for example, Balassa and Associates (1971) and Bhagwati (1978).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 92 -&#13;
welfare under the present regime of generalized currency floating. However,&#13;
changes in nominal exchange rates by themselves are not sufficient, but&#13;
need to be complemented by other policy measures to ensure consistency with&#13;
the multiple objectives of LDC policymaking.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 93 -&#13;
APPENDIX: SOURCES OF DATA&#13;
Sections III and IV: Regressions on N, GSD and P&#13;
Basic data for M, Y, P,- CR, GSD, PCY(=L) and m were drawn entirely&#13;
from the IFS computer file of the IMF. The ILO Yearbook of Labor Statistics&#13;
provided most of the wage (w) data, which were supplemented by published&#13;
materials from individual countries. The average annual percentage change&#13;
12&#13;
in Em for each sample LDC was calculated as [(1 + .01 E*)    - 1] x 100,&#13;
m&#13;
where Et is the coefficient estimate (b) in the logarithmic trend regression&#13;
of the monthly values of the import-weighted effective exchange rate&#13;
(cf. Section II). A similar transformation was done on the monthly rates&#13;
of change in Pf (= Hpwmi , where wmi is the "price-currency import share"&#13;
i i&#13;
of developed country i and Pi is the wholesale price index in country i).&#13;
As indicated in the text (Section IV), the measure of exchange rate&#13;
variability (V) is represented by the standard error of estimate in the&#13;
logarithmic trend regression of monthly EERm values from March 1973 to&#13;
December 1979.&#13;
Section V: Cross-country regressions on x&#13;
Calculation of ne, vn, pe and vp made use of the results of logarithmic&#13;
trend regressions of the monthly values of NPXM and PPPEERX (from March 1973&#13;
to December 1978). The estimated trend coefficients (bs) were transformed&#13;
A 12&#13;
from monthly to annual rates of change (= [l+b]    - 1) which served as the&#13;
observations for n and p. Values of the standard error of estimate (s.e.e.)&#13;
represented vn and vp.&#13;
1/ Wholesale price index or, if complete series is not available&#13;
(Malaysia, Morocco and Singapore), consumer price index.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 94 -&#13;
The IFS computer file of the IMF provided the basic data for deriving&#13;
XIY and L. Calculation of x used in the total export regressions was&#13;
based on export value (U.S. dollars) data from the IFS adjusted for the&#13;
foreign inflation rate (Pf above) and on GDP at 1975 prices also from the&#13;
IFS. In the manufactured export regressions, UNCTAD volume indices of&#13;
manufactured exports were used for the sample countries except Greece,&#13;
Indonesia, Portugal, Singapore, Spain and Taiwan; for the latter countries,&#13;
GATT data on manufactured export values (U.S. dollar) were deflated by the&#13;
UNCTAD price index for manufactured exports of developing countries.&#13;
Manufacturing (or industrial) production data were drawn from the IFS,&#13;
except for the following countries where World Bank data on manufacturing&#13;
value added at constant prices (Economic Data Sheet 1) were used:&#13;
Brazil, Colombia, Costa Rica, Egypt, Indonesia, Turkey and Uruguay.&#13;
Section V: Individual country regressions on X&#13;
Quarterly observations for NE, NE', Vn, PE, PE' and Vp were computed&#13;
from the monthly values of NPXM and PPPEERx as described in the text.&#13;
Total export earnings and terms of trade (export unit value . import unit&#13;
value) data were obtained from the IFS.&#13;
Various source materials were used in compiling quarterly data&#13;
on manufactured exports. These are indicated below by country, together&#13;
with the title of relevant tables and the last quarter for which data&#13;
were obtained. Conversion from local currency to U.S. dollars, where&#13;
applicable, made use of the average quarterly exchange rate series from&#13;
the IFS.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 95 -&#13;
Brazil        : Conjuntura Econoxnica, "Exportacao de&#13;
Productas Industrializados"; 1978: IV&#13;
Egypt         : Economic Bulletin (National Bank of Egypt),&#13;
"Main Groups of Exports"; 1977:III&#13;
India         : Monthly Statistics of the Foreign Trade of&#13;
India, "Foreign Trade by Groups, Divisions,&#13;
Sections"; 1978:II&#13;
Malaysia      : Monthly Statistical Bulletin of West Malaysia,&#13;
"Exports by SITC Sections"; 1979:III&#13;
Pakistan      : Export Receipts (State Bank of Pakistan),&#13;
"Export Receipts by Commodities"; 1979:IV&#13;
Philippines   : Philippine Financial Statistics Quarterly&#13;
Bulletin, "Exports by Commodity Group";&#13;
1979:I&#13;
Singapore     : Monthly Digest of Statistics (Department of&#13;
Statistics, Government of Singapore), "Exports&#13;
by Commodity Sections"; 1979:IV&#13;
South Korea   : Monthly Economic Statistics (Bank of Korea)&#13;
"Exports and Imports by Commodity Group";&#13;
1979:IV&#13;
Taiwan        : Monthly Statistics of Exports and Imports&#13;
(Ministry of Finance, Republic of China),&#13;
"Export Value by Commodity Classification";&#13;
1979:IV&#13;
Thailand      : Monthly Bulletin (Bank of Thailand), "Trade&#13;
by Commodity Groups". 1979:III&#13;
Turkey        : Monthly Bulletin of Statistics (State Institute&#13;
of Statistics, Government of Turkey), "Exports&#13;
by Commodity Group"; 1979:I&#13;
Uruguay       : Indicadores de la Actividad Economico-Financiera&#13;
(Banco Central del Uruguay), "Exportationes&#13;
Complidas - Por Secciones y Principales&#13;
Productos"; 1978:III&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 96 -&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
Abrams, R. K., "Actual and Potential International Trade Flows with&#13;
Flexible Exchange Rates," Research Working Paper 80-01, Federal&#13;
Reserve Bank of Kansas City (January 1980).&#13;
Aghevli, B. B., "Experience of Asian Countries with Various Exchange&#13;
Rate Policies," paper presented at the conference on "The Crawling&#13;
Peg: Past Performance and Future Prospects" in Rio de Janeiro&#13;
(October 1979).&#13;
Aghevli, B. B. and C. A. Rodriguez, "Trade, Prices and Output in Japan:&#13;
A Simple Monetary Model," IMF Staff Papers, XXVI (March 1979),&#13;
pp. 38-54.&#13;
Argy, V., "Structural Inflation in Developing Countries," Oxford&#13;
Economic Papers, XXII (March 1970), pp. 73-85.&#13;
Artus, J. R. and J. H. Young, "Fixed and Flexible Exchange Rates: A&#13;
Renewal of the Debate," IMF Staff Papers, XXVI (December 1979),&#13;
pp. 654-698.&#13;
Balassa, B. and Associates, The Structure of Protection in Developing&#13;
Countries (Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins Press, 1971).&#13;
Balassa, B., "Exports and Economic Growth: Further Evidence," Journal&#13;
of Development Economics, V (1978), pp. 181-191.&#13;
Ball, R. J. and M. Duffy, "Price Formation in European Countries," in&#13;
0. Eckstein (ed.) The Econometrics of Price Determination&#13;
(Washington, 1972), pp. 347-368.&#13;
Bautista, R. M., "Effects of Major Currency Realignment on Philippine&#13;
Merchandise Trade," Review of Economics and Statistics, LIX (1977)&#13;
pp. 152-160.&#13;
Bautista, R. M., "Exchange Rate Flexibility and the Less Developed&#13;
Countries: A Survey of Empirical Research and Policy Issues,"&#13;
Economic Analysis and Projections Department, The World Bank&#13;
(November 1979).&#13;
Bautista, R. M. and J. Riedel, "Major Curres.Icy Realignments and the&#13;
Terms of Trade in Developing Countries," Economic Analysis and&#13;
Projections Department, The World Bank (May 1980).&#13;
Bhagwati, J. N., Foreign Trade Regimes and Economic Development:&#13;
Anatomy and Consequences of Exchange Control Regimes (New York:&#13;
Columbia University Press, 1978).&#13;
Bhagwati, N., and T. N. Srinivasan, "Trade Policy and Development"&#13;
in R. Dornbusch and J. Frenkel (eds.), International Economic&#13;
Policy: Theory and Evidence (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University&#13;
Press, 1978), pp. 1-38.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 97 -&#13;
Blejer, M. I. and N. Halevi, "Effective Devaluation and Domestic Rate&#13;
of Inflation," Journal of Development Economics, VII (1980),&#13;
pp. 117-122.&#13;
Branson, W. H. and L. T. Katseli-Papaefstratiou. "Income Stability, the&#13;
Terms of Trade and Choice of Exchange Rate Regime," Journal of&#13;
Development Economics, VII (1980), pp. 49-69.&#13;
Bruno, M., "Exchange Rates, Import Costs and Wage-Price Dynamics,"&#13;
Journal of Political Economv, LXXXVI (June 1978), pp. 379-403.&#13;
Bruno, M. and Z. Sussman, "Exchange Rate Flexibility, Inflation and&#13;
Structural Change: Israel Under Alternative Regimes," paper&#13;
presented at the Ford Foundation/Central Bank of Barbados Seminar&#13;
on Developing Countries and the International Financial System,&#13;
January 12-14, 1978.&#13;
Cline, W. R., International Monetary Reform and the Developing Countries,&#13;
(Washington, D.C.: Brookings Institution, 1976).&#13;
Coes, D. V., "The Crawling Peg and Exchange Rate Uncertainty," paper&#13;
presented at the conference on "The Crawling Peg: Past Performance&#13;
and Future Prospects" in Rio de Janeiro (October 1979).&#13;
Colaco, F. X., "Harberger's Inflation Model: A Critique and Test Using&#13;
Data for Brazil and India," Indian Economic Journal, XVI (1969),&#13;
pp. 434-444.&#13;
Connolly, M. and D. Taylor, "Testing the Monetary Approach to Devaluation&#13;
in Developing Countries," Journal of Political Economy, LXXXIV&#13;
(August 1976), pp. 849-859.&#13;
Cooper, R. N., "An Assessment of Currency Devaluation in Developing&#13;
Countries," in G. Ranis (ed.), Government and Economic Development&#13;
(New Haven: Yale University Press, 1971).&#13;
Crockett, A. D. and S. M. Nsouli, "Exchange Rate Policies for Developing&#13;
Countries," Journal of Development Studies, XIII (1977), pp. 125-143.&#13;
Diaz-Alejandro, C. F., Exchange-Rate Devaluation in a Semi-Industrial&#13;
Country:  The Experience of Argentina 1955-1961 (Cambridge:    The&#13;
MIT Press, 1965).&#13;
Diaz-Alejandro, C. F., "Trade Policies and Economic Development," in&#13;
2. B. Kenen (ed.), International Trade and Finance: Frontiers&#13;
for Research (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1975).&#13;
Diz, A. C., "Money and Prices in Argentina, 1935-1962," in D. Meiselman&#13;
(ed.), Varieties of Monetary Experience (Chicago: University of&#13;
Chicago Press, 1970), pp. 111-122.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 98 -&#13;
Donges, J. B. and J. Riedel, "The Expansion of Manufactured Exports in&#13;
Developing Countries: An Empirical Assessment of Supply and&#13;
Demand Issues," Weltwirtschaftliches Archiv, Band 113, Heft 1 (1977),&#13;
pp. 58-87.&#13;
Durbin, J., "Testing for Serial Correlation in Least-Squares Regression&#13;
when Some of the Regressions are Lagged Dependent Variables,"&#13;
Econometrica, XXXVIII (May, 1970), pp. 410-421.&#13;
Feltenstein, A., M. Goldstein and L. Schadler, "A Multilateral Exchange&#13;
Rate Model for Primary Producing Countries," IMF Staff Paper, XXVI&#13;
(1979), pp. 543-582.&#13;
Glytsos, N. P., '"Determinants of Wage and Price Changes in Less Developed&#13;
Countries," Journal of Development Economics, IV (December 1977),&#13;
pp. 315-342.&#13;
Goldstein, M., "Downward Price Inflexibility, Ratchet Effects, and the&#13;
Inflationary Impact of Import Price Changes: Some Empirical Tests,"&#13;
IMF Staff Papers, XXIV (November 1977), pp. 569-612.&#13;
Harberger, A., "The Dynamics of Inflation in Chile," in C. F. Christ (ed.),&#13;
Measurement in Economics (Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1963),&#13;
pp. 219-254.&#13;
Helleiner, G. K.. "Transnational Corporations and Trade Structure:&#13;
The Role of Intra-Firm Trade", in H. Giersch (ed.), On the Economics&#13;
of Intra-Industry Trade (J.C.B. Mohr, Tubingen, 1979), pp. 159-181.&#13;
Keesing, D. B., "Trade Policy for Developing Countries," World Bank Staff&#13;
Working Paper No. 353 (August 1979).&#13;
Kravis, I. B. and R. E. Lipsey, Price Competitiveness in World Trade&#13;
(New York: NBER, Inc., 1971).&#13;
Krueger, A. O., Foreign Trade Regimes and Economic Development:&#13;
Liberalization Attempts and Consequences (New York: Columbia&#13;
University Press, 1978).&#13;
Kwack, S. Y., "The Effect of Foreign Inflation on Domestic Prices and the&#13;
Relative Price Advantage of Exchange Rate Changes," in P. B. Clark,&#13;
D. E. Logue and R. J. Sweeney, (eds.), The Effects of Exchange Rate&#13;
Adjustments (Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of the Treasury,&#13;
1977), pp. 387-398.&#13;
Lipschitz, L., "Exchange Rate Policy for a Small Developing Country, and&#13;
the Selection of an Appropriate Standard," IMF Staff Papers, XXVI&#13;
(1979) pp. 423-449.&#13;
Little, I., T. Scitovsky and M. Scott, Industry and Trade in Some&#13;
Developing Countries:  A Comparative StudZ (Oxford: Oxford University&#13;
Press, 1970).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 99 -&#13;
McKinnon, R. I., "Optimum Currency Areas," American Economic Review,&#13;
LIII (1963), pp. 717-725.&#13;
Paauw, D. S., "Exchange Rate Policy and Non-Extractive Exports,"&#13;
Economics and Finance in Indonesia, XXVI (June 1978), pp. 205-218.&#13;
Rhomberg, R. R., "Indices of Effective Exchange Rates," IMF Staff Papers,&#13;
XXIII (March 1976), pp. 88-105.&#13;
Robinson, W., T. R. Webb and M. A. Townsend, "The Influence of Exchange&#13;
Rate Changes on Prices: A Study of 18 Industrial Countries,"&#13;
Economica, XXVI (February 1979), pp. 27-50.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
RECENT PAPERS IN THIS SERIES&#13;
No.                      TITLE OF PAPER                              AUTHOR&#13;
419       Employment Patterns and Income Growth:                  J. Stern&#13;
An Application of Input-Output Analysis                 J. Lewis&#13;
420       The Evaluation of Hunan Capital in Malawi               S. Heyneman&#13;
421       A Conceptual Approach to the Analysis of External       R. Aliber&#13;
Debt of the Developing Countries&#13;
422       Estimating Total Factor Productivity Growth in          A. Krueger&#13;
a Developing Country             .                      B. Tuncer&#13;
423       Rethinking Artisanal Fisheries Develcspment:            D. Emmerson&#13;
Western Concepts, Asian Experience                      (consultant)&#13;
424       Transition toward More Rapid and Labor-Intensive        B. de Vries&#13;
Industrial Development: The Case of the Philippines&#13;
425       Britain's Pattern of Specialization in Manufactured     V. Cable&#13;
Goods with Developing Countries and Trade Protection    I. Rebelo&#13;
426       Worker Adjustment to Liberalized Trade:  Costs and      G. Glenday&#13;
Assistance Policies                                     G. Jenkins&#13;
J. Evans&#13;
427       On the Political Economy of Protection in Germany       H. Glismann&#13;
F. Weiss&#13;
428       Italian Commercial Policies in the 1970s                E. Grilli&#13;
429       Effects of Non-Tariff Barriers to Trade on Prices,      C. Hamilton&#13;
Employment, and Imports: The Case of the Swedish&#13;
Textile and Clothing Industry&#13;
430       Output and Employment Changes in a "Trade Sensitive"    J. Mutti&#13;
Sector: Adjustment in the U.S. Footwear Industry        M. Bale&#13;
431       The Political Economy of Protection in Belgium          P. Tharakan&#13;
432       European Community Protection;Aga-inst Manufactured     E. Verrydt&#13;
Imports from Developing Countries:  A Case Study        J. W4aelbroeck&#13;
in the Political Economy of Protection&#13;
433       Agrarian Reforms in Developing Rural Economies           A. Braverman&#13;
Characterized by In.terlinked Credit and Tenancy         T.N. Srinivasan&#13;
Markets                                                  (consultant)&#13;
434       How Segmented is the Bogota Labour Market?               G. Fields (consultant)&#13;
435       Pirate Subdivisions and the Market for                   A. Carroll&#13;
Residential Lots in Bogota&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554989">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1980/10/1554989/exchange-rate-adjustment-under-generalized-currency-floating-comparative-analysis-among-developing-countries
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1980/10/1554989/exchange-rate-adjustment-under-generalized-currency-floating-comparative-analysis-among-developing-countries</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1980/10/1554989/exchange-rate-adjustment-under-generalized-currency-floating-comparative-analysis-among-developing-countries</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-12T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-12T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/10/14/000178830_98101903405990/Rendered/INDEX/SWP436000Excha0developing0countries.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/10/14/000178830_98101903405990/Rendered/PDF/SWP436000Excha0developing0countries.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1980-10-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2002-03-30T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Exchange rate adjustment under generalized
            currency floating : comparative analysis among developing countries
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This study examines the experience of a
            sample of 22 LDCs relating to exchange rate changes under
            generalized currency floating with a view to drawing some
            implications for LDC policymaking. Section II develops the
            framework of analysis, identifying the basic sources of
            effective exchange rate (EER) changes under the post-Bretton
            Woods regime which give rise to relative price effects on
            LDC export supply. Major currency realignments are found to
            have caused a general decline in export competitiveness in
            the majority of sample countries. However, both in terms of
            trend and variability, the relative price effect due to
            foreign exchange rate changes has generally been smaller
            than the observed real exchange rate adjustments. It would
            appear that the price response to exchange rate adjustments
            in the post-Bretton Woods period is to a very high order of
            practical importance to LDC policymakers, since about 80
            percent of the nominal currency depreciation is estimated to
            have been added ultimately to the general price level. The
            concluding part of this paper, Section VI, appraises the
            findings of the study, discusses the implications for
            policymaking in developing countries and indicates
            directions for further research.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Exchange rate adjustment under generalized
            currency floating : comparative analysis among developing countries
        </docna>
        <display_title>Exchange rate adjustment under
            generalized currency floating : comparative analysis among
            developing countries</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1980/10/1554989/exchange-rate-adjustment-under-generalized-currency-floating-comparative-analysis-among-developing-countries</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>General Technology,Transport Security,Educational Technology and Distance Education,Information and Records Management,Information Technology</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Education,Information and Communication Technologies,Transport</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>BAUTISTA, B.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903405990</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Trade</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 436</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Education,Information and Communication Technologies,Transport</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Competitiveness; Exchange rates; Exports;
            Inflation; International monetary system; International
            trade; Policy making; Regression analysis; Allocation of resources
            HTML,HTTP,Port,server,URL
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP436</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Currencies and Exchange Rates</ml:concept><ml:concept>Educational Technology and Distance Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Radio, Television Instruction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary and Exchange Rate Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal &amp; Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Consolidation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance and Structural Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Rules</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Sustainability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macro-Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Distance Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education for the Knowledge Economy</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT and Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Export Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Export Development and Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Competitiveness and Diversification</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Exchange Rate Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Incentives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education and ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Export Competitiveness and Diversification</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>