<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Trends in International Trade&#13;
in Manufactured Goods and Structural Change&#13;
in the Industrial Countries&#13;
Bela Balassa&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WIORKING PAPERS&#13;
N.umber 611&#13;
I_____~~~~. &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 611&#13;
Trends in International Trade&#13;
in Manufactured Goods and Structural Change&#13;
in the Industrial Countries&#13;
Bela Balassa&#13;
with the assistance of Kenneth Meyers&#13;
INTERNAT1OMU MONETARY FUtD&#13;
JOINT LIBRRY&#13;
MfAR   i 1984&#13;
IN'TEUNATIONAL 8AhW  Fo0I&#13;
rxCI;.TFUC,TON HI4U' DLVELOPMIlWT&#13;
WlNVAN5L!qTUV. t'.C, 2n14,11&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright e 1984&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development / THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
First printing January 1984&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To&#13;
present the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has&#13;
not been prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal&#13;
printed texts, and the World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The&#13;
publication is supplied at a token charge to defray part of the cost of&#13;
manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to&#13;
any individual acting on their behalf. Any maps used have been prepared&#13;
solely for the convenience of the readers; the denominations used and the&#13;
boundaries shown do not imply, on the part of the World Bank and its affiliates,&#13;
any judgment on the legal status of any territory or any endorsement or&#13;
acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications is described in the Catalog of World&#13;
Bank Publications; the continuing research program of the Bank is outlined in&#13;
World Bank Research Program: Abstracts of Current Studies. Both booklets are&#13;
updated annually; the most recent edition of each is available without charge&#13;
from the Publications Sales Unit of the Bank in Washington or from the&#13;
European Office of the Bank, 66, avenue d'Iena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Bela Balassa is professor of political economy at The Johns Hopkins&#13;
University and a consultant to the World Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Balassa, Bela A.&#13;
Trends in international trade in manufactured goods&#13;
and structural change in the industrial countries.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 611)&#13;
1. Commerce. I. Meyers, Kenneth. II. Title.&#13;
III. Series.&#13;
HF1411.B2313    1984       382'.4567       83-25996&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0251-5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Abstract&#13;
This paper follows the author's "Structtural Change in Trade&#13;
in Manufactured Goods between Industrial and Developing Countries," World&#13;
Bank Staff Working Paper No. 396, June 1980. It extends the period of&#13;
observation until 1981 and also provides estimates on the importance of&#13;
trade with the developing countries for domestic production and consumption&#13;
in the industrial countries in 1973.&#13;
The results show the increasing importance of the developing&#13;
countries as markets and sources of supply for the industrial countries.&#13;
In 1973-78, the developing countries'provided 8.5 percent, and in 1978-81&#13;
11.3 percent, of the increment in manufacturing production in the industrial&#13;
countries while supplying 2.4 percent of the increment in their manufacturing&#13;
consumption in 1973-78 and 3.8 percent in 1978-81. Both groups of countries&#13;
benefited from this trade and further gains could be obtained through&#13;
multilateral trade liberalization.&#13;
Invited paper prepared for the 7th World Congress of the&#13;
International Economic Association on Structural Change,&#13;
Economic Interdependence, and World Development,&#13;
held in Madrid, Spain on September 5-9, 1983&#13;
Ce document fait suite au rapport du meme auteur intitul6 "Evolution de la&#13;
structure des 6changes de produits manufactur6s entre pays industriels et pays&#13;
en developpement" (Document de travail des services de la Banque mondiale No 396&#13;
de juin 1980). Il prolonge la periode d'observation jusqu'en 1981 et contient&#13;
des estimations sur l'importance des 6changes avec les pays en d6veloppement pour&#13;
la production et la consommation interieures des pays industriels en 1973.&#13;
L'etude montre que les pays en d6veloppement sont des marches et des&#13;
sources d'approvisionnement de plus en plus importants pour les pays industriels.&#13;
En effet, ils ont absorb6 8,5 % de la production suppl6mentaire de biens manufac-&#13;
tures des pays industriels pendant la periode 1973-78, et 11,3 % pendant la&#13;
periode 1978-81, et couvert l'accroissement de leur consommation de produits&#13;
manufactur6s a raison de 2,4 % et 3,8 % pendant les memes p6riodes respective-&#13;
ment. Les deux groupes de pays ont tire parti de ce commerce et auraient tout a&#13;
gagner d'une lib6ralisation des echanges multilat6raux.&#13;
Document pr6pare specialement pour le Septieme congres mondial&#13;
de l'Association 6conomique internationale sur les changements structurels,&#13;
l'interdependance 6conomique et le developpement mondial,&#13;
qui s'est tenu a Madrid, en Espagne, du 5 au 9 septembre 1983.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Extracto&#13;
Este informe es continuaci6n del Documento de Trabajo del Personal del&#13;
Banco Mundial No. 396 titulado "Structural Change in Trade in Manufactured Goods&#13;
between Industrial and Developing Countries" (Cambio estructural en el comercio&#13;
de bienes manufacturados entre paises industriales y en desarrollo), de junio de&#13;
1980, preparado por el mismo autor. Amplia el periodo de observaci6n hasta 1981&#13;
y tambien proporciona estimaciones de la importancia que tuvo el comercio con&#13;
los paises en desarrollo para la producci6n y el consumo internos de las nacio-&#13;
nes industriales en 1973.&#13;
Los resultados muestran la creciente importancia de los paises en desa-&#13;
rrollo como mercados y como fuentes de suministro para las naciones industria-&#13;
les. Estos paises aportaron el 8,5% en 1973-78 y el 11,3% en 1978-81 del&#13;
aumento de la producci6n manufacturera en las naciones industriales, asi como el&#13;
2,4% del incremento de su consumo de manufacturas en 1973-78 y el 3,8% en&#13;
1978-81. Los dos grupos de paises se beneficiaron con este comercio, y podrian&#13;
obtenerse otras ventajas mediante la liberalizaci6n del comercio multilateral.&#13;
Trabajo preparado por invitaci6n para el VII Congreso Mundial&#13;
de la International Economic Association on Structural Change,&#13;
Economic Interdependence, and World Development,&#13;
celebrado en Madrid, Espafia, del 5 al 9 de septiembre de 1983&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
I.  Trade in Manufactured Goods between the Industrial           2&#13;
and the Developing Countries&#13;
Change in Export and Import Flows, 1973-81                   2&#13;
Trends in the Volume of Manufactured Trade and               5&#13;
in the Gross Domestic Product&#13;
Changes in the Relative Importance of Trade in              10&#13;
Manufactured Goods between the Industrial and the&#13;
Developing Countries&#13;
Policy Implications of the Results                          13&#13;
II.  Effects of Trade on Production, Employment, and             16&#13;
Resource Allocation&#13;
Recent Trends in the Trade of Individual                    16&#13;
Commodity Groups&#13;
Employment Effects                                          21&#13;
Comparative Advantage in Trade in Manufactured Goods        24&#13;
Policy Implications of the Results                          26&#13;
Conclusions                                                 28&#13;
Notes                                                       30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TRENDS IN INTERNATIONAL TRADE IN MANUFACTURED GOODS&#13;
AND STRUCTURAL CHANGE IN THE INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES&#13;
Bela Balassa&#13;
with the assistance of Kenneth Meyers&#13;
This paper will examine recent trends in trade in manufactured goods&#13;
between the industrial and the developing countries and indicate the&#13;
implications of these trends for structural change in the industrial&#13;
countries. It will update and extend earlier papers by the author, which&#13;
dealt with the experience of the years 1973-78. 1/ The present paper will&#13;
cover the 1973-81 period, with consideration given to changes during the 1973-&#13;
78 and 1978-81 subperiods, each of which began with an oil shock, followed by&#13;
a world recession.&#13;
Part I of the paper will provide information on changes over time in&#13;
the current dollar value of trade in manufactured goods between the industrial&#13;
and the developing countries. It will further analyze trends in the volume of&#13;
trade in manufactured goods, and its relationship with economic activity, in&#13;
the two groups of countries. Finally, the relative importance of trade with&#13;
the developing countries for the manufacturing sector of the industrial&#13;
nations, and changes thereof, will be indicated.&#13;
The commodity composition of trade in manufactured goods between the&#13;
industrial and the developing countries will be the subject of Part II of the&#13;
paper. It will examine the changing importance of trade with the developing&#13;
countries for the manufacturing sector of the industrial nations in a seven&#13;
commodity-group breakdown. The discussion will also cover the employment&#13;
effects of trade in manufactured goods as well as its conformity to the&#13;
comparative advantage of the two groups of countries. The paper will conclude&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
with policy recommendations that aim at promoting international trade and&#13;
structural change.&#13;
For purposes of the statistical analysis, industrial countries have&#13;
been defined to include the United States, Canada, the European Common Market&#13;
(EC), / the European Free Trade Association (EFTA) 3/ and Japan; among&#13;
developing countries, distinction has been made between OPEC 4/ and non-OPEC&#13;
countries. The two groupings exclude Southern Europe other than Greece and&#13;
Portugal; Australia, New Zealand, and South Africa; and the centrally planned&#13;
economies.&#13;
I. Trade in Manufactured Goods between the Industrial and the Developing&#13;
Countries&#13;
Changes in Export and Import Flows, 1973-81&#13;
The period beginning with the first oil shock saw considerable&#13;
increases in the surplus of the industrial countries in their trade in&#13;
manufactured goods 5/ with the developing countries. In terms of current&#13;
dollars, the surplus grew from $36 billion in 1973 to $114 billion in 1978&#13;
and, again, to $172 billion in 1981 (Table 1).&#13;
In 1981, over one-half of the surplus in this trade was with the OPEC&#13;
countries. In that year, OPEC provided markets for two-fifths of the&#13;
manufactured exports of the industrial nations to the developing countries,&#13;
but supplied a negligible proportion of their imports of these commodities.&#13;
The export share of the OPEC countries rose from one-fourth in 1973 to two-&#13;
fifths in 1978 and stabilized afterwards.&#13;
In 1973, the industrial nations covered 43 percent of their oil&#13;
imports from OPEC by the exports of manufactured goods. This ratio rose to 62&#13;
percent in 1978, but declined to 48 percent in 1981. The increased coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table I&#13;
Trade Between the Industrial Countries and the Developing Countries in Manufactured goods&#13;
(us$ billio'n)&#13;
United States                Canada                        EC                       EFTA                      Japan              Industrial Countries&#13;
Trading Partner     Export   Import  Balance   Export  Import  Balance   Export  Import  Balance    Export  Import  Balance   Export   Import  Balance   Export  Import  Balance&#13;
Ol Exporting&#13;
Developing Countries&#13;
1973                  2.43    0.06     2.37      0.17    0.00    0.17      7.00    0.42    6.58       0.69    0.05    0.64      2.57     0.02    2.55     12.86    0.55    12.31&#13;
1974                  4.28    0.10     4.18      0.31    0.00    0.31     11.63    0.42   11.21       1.19    0.07    1.12      5.16     0.03    5.13     22.59    0.62    21.95&#13;
1975                  8.00    0.09     7.91      0.57    0.00    0.57     20.00    0.46   19.54       1.97    0.05    1.92      8.12     0.01    8.11     38.66    0.61   38.05&#13;
1976                  9.90    0.09     9.81      0.76    0.01    0.75     23.10    0.53   22.57       2.80    0.06    2.74      8.93     0.02    8.91     45.49    0.71   44.78&#13;
1977                 10.50    0.10    10.40      0.84    0.00    0.84     29.43    0.67   28.76       3.21    0.08    3.13     11.51     0.04   11.47     55.49    0.89    54.60&#13;
1978                 11.97    0.14    11.83      1.04    0.00    1.04     34.56    1.11   33.45       3.72    0.09    3.63     13.57     0.05   13.52     64.09    1.39   62.70&#13;
1979                 11.41    0.21    11.20      0.99    0.01    0.98     33.32    1.63   31.69       3.81    0.11    3.70     12.80     0.09   12.71     62.33    2.05    60.28&#13;
1980                 13.38    0.23    13.15      1.14    0.01    1.13     42.12    1.80   40.32       4.91    0.15    4.76     17.72     0.11   17.61     79.27    2.30    76.97&#13;
1981                 16.38    0.34    16.04      1.51    0.01    1.50     48.40    1.31   47.09       5.47    0.16    5.31     22.14     0.11   22.03     93.90    1.93    91.97&#13;
Oil Importing&#13;
Developing Countries&#13;
1973                 10.35    7.33     3.02      0.57    0.53    0.04     16.01    4.68   11.33       2.56    0.75    1.81      9.96     2.22    7.74     39.45   15.51   23.94&#13;
1974                 16.10    9.73     6.39      0.87    0.76    0.11     23.03    5.83   17.20       3.54    1.01    2.53     14.90     2.52   12.38     58.44   19.85    38.59&#13;
1975                 17.75    8.89    8.86       1.06    0.76    0.30     25.82    6.85   18.97       3.74    1.18    2.56     14.25     2.00   12.25     62.62   19.65   42.54    w&#13;
1976                 18.25    12.95    5.30      1.06    1.21   -0.15     25.35    8.92   16.43       3.82    1.38    2.44     16.05     2.89   13.16     64.53   27.35    37.18&#13;
1977                 18.84    15.61    3.23      1.08    1.16   -0.08     29.98   10.87   19.11       4.57    1.81    2.76     20.14     2.97   17.17     74.61   32.42    42.19&#13;
1978                 23.54   20.93     2.61      1.24    1.27   -0.03     37.28   14.10   23.18       5.89    1.93    3.96     25.64     4.27   21.37     93.59   42.50    51.09&#13;
1979                 32.22   25.75    6.47       1.67    1.72   -0.05     46.56   19.33   27.23       7.31    2.41    4.90     29.40    6.01    23.39    117.16   55.22   61.94&#13;
1980                 42.36   29.38    12.98      2.38    1.77    0.61     53.11   23.52   29.59       8.14    3.21    4.93     35.23     5.73   29.50    141.22   63.61    77.61&#13;
1981                 45.25   34.87    10.38      2.39    2.29    0.10     52.41   20.65   31.76       8.28    3.03    5.25     39.11    6.36    32.75    147.44   67.20   80.24&#13;
Developing Countries&#13;
Together&#13;
1973                 12.78    7.39     5.39      0.74    0.53    0.21     23.01    5.10   17.91       3.25    0.80    2.45     12.53     2.24   10.29     52.31   16.06   36.25&#13;
1974                 20.38    9.83    10.55      1.18    0.76    0.42     34.66    6.25   28.41       4.73    1.08    3.65     20.06     2.55   17.51     81.03   20.47   60.54&#13;
1975                 25.75    8.98    16.77      1.63    0.76    0.87     45.82    7.31   38.51       5.71    1.23    4.48     22.37     2.01   20.36    101.28   20.29   60.99&#13;
1976                 28.15    13.04   15.11      1.82    1.22    0.60     48.45    9.45   39.00       6.62    1.44    5.18     24.98     2.91   22.07    110.02   28.06   81.96&#13;
1977                 29.34   15.71    13.63      1.92    1.16    0.76     59.41   11.54   47.87       7.78    1.89    5.89     31.65    3.01    28.64    130.10   33.31   96.79&#13;
1978                 35.51   21.07    14.44      2.28    1.27    1.01     71.84'  15.21   56.63       9.61    2.02    7.59     39.21     4.32   34.89    157.68   43.89   113.79&#13;
1979                 43.63   25.96    17.67      2.66    1.73    0.93     79.88   20.96   58.92      11.12    2.52    8.60     42.20    6.10    36.10    179.49   57.27   122.22&#13;
1980                 55.74   29.61    26.13      3.52    1.78    1.74     95.23   25.32   69.91      13.05    3.36    9.69     52.95     5.84   47.11    220.49   65.91   154.58&#13;
1981                 61.63   35.21    26.42      3.90    2.30    1.60    100.81   21.96   76.85      13.75    3.19   10.56     61.25    6.47    54.78    241.34   69.13   172.21&#13;
Source:  GATT International Trade, Geneva, various issues.&#13;
Note: Exports are expressed in f.o.b. prices, imports in c.i.f. prices, except for Canada and the United States where imports are also in f.o.b. prices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
of oil imports by manufactured exports between 1973 and 1978 reflects the rise&#13;
in the spending of oil revenues by OPEC while the subsequent decline indicates&#13;
delays in using increases in these revenues following the 1979-80 oil price&#13;
rise.&#13;
The extent of coverage of oil imports by the exports of manufactured&#13;
goods, and changes in this coverage over time, vary to a considerable extent&#13;
among the industrial countries. Between 1973 and 1981, the ratio increased&#13;
from 41 to 61 percent in the European Common Market and from 19 to 33 percent&#13;
in Canada; it remained practically unchanged in the European Free Trade&#13;
Association (68 and 69 percent) and in Japan (43 and 42 percent); and it&#13;
declined from 52 to 33 percent in the United States.&#13;
The results for the European Common Market were not, however, due to&#13;
rapid increases of manufactured exports to OPEC; together with the United&#13;
States, the EC was at the lower end of the range as far as the growth of these&#13;
exports is concerned. But, while the current dollar value of oil imports from&#13;
OPEC rose more than tenfold in the United States, oil imports into the EC&#13;
increased less than five times. In turn, EFTA and Japan expanded their&#13;
manufactured exports pari passu with approximately eightfold rise in their oil&#13;
imports from OPEC, and export increases of a similar magnitude were more than&#13;
sufficient to compensate for the fivefold increase of oil imports into Canada.&#13;
In the trade of the industrial countries with the non-OPEC developing&#13;
countries, changes in the ratio of their manufactured imports to the exports&#13;
of these commodities are of interest. For the industrial countries, taken&#13;
together, this ratio rose from 39 percent in 1973 to 45 percent in 1978.&#13;
Nevertheless, given the small ratio in the initial year, the surplus of the&#13;
industrial countries in manufactured trade with the non-OPEC developing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 5 -&#13;
countries grew from $24 billion in 1973 to $51 billion in 1978. The surplus&#13;
increased further, to $80 billion in 1981, when the import/export ratio&#13;
reached 46 percent.&#13;
Import/export ratios in trade in manufactured goods with the&#13;
developing countries increased in all industrial countries and country groups,&#13;
the exception being Japan. While Japan was only slightly above the industrial&#13;
country average in terms of the growth of manufactured exports to the non-OPEC&#13;
developing countries, the increase in its imports of manufactured goods from&#13;
these countries hardly exceeded one-half of the industrial country average.&#13;
In turn, U.S. manufactured exports to the non-OPEC developing countries grew&#13;
more rapidly than those of Japan, but imports into the United States rose at&#13;
double the Japanese rate. As a result, the U.S. import-export ratio in&#13;
manufactured trade with the non-OPEC developing countries increased from 71&#13;
percent in 1973 to 77 percent in 1981; by contrast, the ratio for Japan fell&#13;
from 22 to 16 percent.&#13;
In the same period, the ratio of the imports of manufactured goods to&#13;
the exports of these commodities in trade with the non-OPEC developing&#13;
countries rose from 29 percent to 39 percent in the European Common Market and&#13;
from 29 percent to 37 percent in the European Free Trade Association,&#13;
reflecting below-average increases in their exports and roughly average&#13;
changes in their imports. Finally, Canada had an approximate balance in its&#13;
trade in manufactured goods with the non-OPEC developing countries throughout&#13;
the period under consideration.&#13;
Trends in the Volume of Manufactured Trade and in the Gross Domestic Product&#13;
In Table 1, trade in manufactured goods between the industrial and&#13;
the developing countries was reported in terms of current dollars. Table 2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
Table 2&#13;
Change in the Volume of Trade in Manufactured Goods&#13;
Between Industrial and Developing Countries and in&#13;
the Gross Domestic Product of the Industrial Countries&#13;
Exports to              All         GDP        Apparent&#13;
OPEC  non-OPEC  All LDC    fr-om-AVTLDC           Income Elasticity&#13;
average annual rate of growth        percent       percent&#13;
1963-73&#13;
Industrial Countries       -       -        8.2        16.5         4.6           3.6&#13;
1973-78&#13;
UniftfedStates           23.7     6.3      10.6         11.1        2.5           4.4&#13;
Canada                   33.7     8.8      16.5         6.8         3.4           2.0&#13;
EC                       23.3     6.2      12.5        12.1         2.1           5.8&#13;
EFTA                     23.8     5.4      10.7         8.4         1.5           5.6&#13;
Japan                    26.4     9.9      14.2         3.0         3.6           0.8&#13;
Industrial Countries     24.2     7.2      12.5        10.2         2.5           4.1&#13;
1978-81&#13;
UnTted-states            -1.3    10.6       6.9        10.5         1.6           6.6&#13;
Canada                    2.5    13.9       8.2        13.6         2.0           6.8&#13;
EC                        7.8     7.9       7.9         5.3         1.4           3.8&#13;
EFTA                      8.5     6.8       7.5         8.6         2.6           3.3&#13;
Japan                    10.3     7.9       8.8         6.6         4.1           1.6&#13;
Industrial Countries     6.9      9.5       8.3         8.4         2.0           4.2&#13;
1973-81&#13;
United States            13.7     7.9       9.2        10.8         2.2           4.9&#13;
Canada                   21.0    10.7      13.3         9.3         2.9           3.2&#13;
EEC                      17.2     6.8      10.8         9.5         1.8           5.3&#13;
EFTA                     17.8     5.9       9.5         8.5         1.9           4.5&#13;
Japan                    20.1     9.1      12.1         4.3         3.8           1.1&#13;
Industrial Countries     17.4     7.1      11.7         9.5         2.3           4.1&#13;
Sources:  1963-73 and 1973-78; Bela Balassa (1981) "Trade in Manufactured Goods:    Patterns&#13;
of Change," World Development Vol. 9, No. 3.&#13;
1978-81: Value of trade - GATT International Trade, 1980/81 and 1981/82&#13;
Unit values - Industrial countries: United Nations&#13;
Monthly Bulletin of Statistics&#13;
- Developing Countries:   Estimated from the export unit&#13;
value indices of the principal developing country exporters of manufactured&#13;
goods, accounting for 72 percent of the total.&#13;
Gross domestic product - World Bank economic and social data base.&#13;
Note:     The apparent income elasticity has been defined as the ratio of the average&#13;
annual rate of growth of imports to that of the gross domestic product.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
provides data on this trade in terms of constant prices. It further provides&#13;
information on the rate of increase of the gross domestic product in the&#13;
industrial countries and on their apparent' income elasticities of import&#13;
demand, defined as the ratio of the rate of growth of imports to that of the&#13;
gross domestic product. 7/&#13;
The apparent income elasticity of demand for manufactured imports&#13;
originating in the developing countries averaged 3.6 in the industrial&#13;
countries during the 1963-73 period; the volume of imports into these&#13;
countries rose at an average annual rate of 16.5 percent while their combined&#13;
GDP grew 4.6 percent a year. The apparent income elasticity increased to 4.1&#13;
in 1973-78 as the rate of growth of imports was 10.2 percent and that of GDP&#13;
2.5 percent; it increased further to 4.2 percent in 1978-81, when import&#13;
growth was 8.4 percent and GDP growth 2.0 percent; and it averaged 4.1 for the&#13;
entire 1973-81 period.&#13;
Considerable differences are observed, however, among the industrial&#13;
countries and country groups. While Japan leads in both periods in terms of&#13;
GDP growth, it had the lowest import growth rate in 1973-78 and the second&#13;
lowest (next to the EC) in 1978-81. Correspondingly, Japan had by far the&#13;
lowest income elasticity of import demand for manufactured goods originating&#13;
from the developing countries. In fact, between 1973 and 1981, Japan's&#13;
imports of manufactured goods from these countries increased hardly more than&#13;
its gross domestic product.&#13;
The EC and EFTA had the highest income elasticities of import demand&#13;
in 1973-78, but relatively low elasticities in 1978-81. In turn, the&#13;
elasticity rose to a considerable extent in the United States between 1973-78&#13;
and 1978-81, approaching the EC average for the entire period. Increases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
occurred also in Canada, but the average for the entire period was reduced by&#13;
the low 1973-78 income elasticity of import demand.&#13;
Apparent income elasticities have also been calculated in regard to&#13;
the developing countries imports of manufactured goods from the industrial&#13;
countries. In 1973-78, increases in GDP averaged 8.2 percent in the OPEC&#13;
countries while the volume of imports grew at an average annual rate of 24.2&#13;
percent, resulting in an income elasticity of 3.0. The corresponding figures&#13;
for the non-OPEC developing countries were 4.1 percent and 7.2 percent, with&#13;
an income elasticity of 1.8. 8/&#13;
In 1978-81, however, the gross domestic product of the OPEC countries&#13;
declined, reflecting in part the political events in Iran and in part the&#13;
unfavorable economic developments that occurred in several large oil-exporting&#13;
countries. During this period, the volume of imports of manufactured goods&#13;
increased at an average annual rate of 6.9 percent. In turn, imports grew 9.5&#13;
percent, and GDP increased 4.3 percent, a year in the non-OPEC developing&#13;
countries, resulting in an apparent income elasticity of demand of 2.2.&#13;
A longer time perspective may be taken in regard to the combined&#13;
manufactured imports of all developing countries from the industrial&#13;
nations. In the 1963-73 period, the apparent income elasticity of demand for&#13;
these imports was 1.3, with the gross domestic product and the volume of&#13;
imports growing at average annual rates of 6.2 and 8.2 percent, respectively.&#13;
9/ The elasticity rose to 2.4 in 1973-78 and increased again to 3.5 in 1978-&#13;
81; GDP increased at an average rate of 5.3 percent and the imports of&#13;
manufactured goods from the industrial countries 12.5 percent in the first&#13;
subperiod, and at average rates of 2.4 and 8.3 percent in the second.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
A comparison of export and import volume growth rates is of further&#13;
interest. In their trade in manufactured goods with the developing countries,&#13;
the volume of the industrial countries' exports and irnports rose at average&#13;
annual rates of 8.2 and 16.5 percent, respectively, between 1963 and 1973.&#13;
Average increases were 12.5 and 10.2 percent a year in 1973-78, when&#13;
manufactured exports to OPEC grew particularlY, rapidly.&#13;
The rate of increase of the industrial countries' exports of&#13;
manufactured goods to the developing cour;tries declined, however, in 1978-81&#13;
as the acceleration of the growth of exports to the non-OPEC developing&#13;
countries did not compensate for the deceleration of export expansion to&#13;
OPEC. The average volume growth rate of 8.3 percent for the manufactured&#13;
exports of the industrial nations to the developing countries approximately&#13;
equalled their import growth rate of 8.4 percent.&#13;
The conclusions are modified if value rather than volume data are&#13;
compared. Thus, the current dollar value of manufactured exports from the&#13;
industrial to th/e developing countries rose by 53 percent between 1978 and&#13;
1981 while the imports of these commodities from the developing countries&#13;
increased by 53 percent.&#13;
The results reflect an improvement in the terms of trade of the&#13;
developing countries in manufactured goods. The improvement occurred in 1981,&#13;
when European countries did not raise their export prices in terms of domestic&#13;
currency to fully offset the appreciation of the dollar whereas developing&#13;
country exporters, which generally link their currencies to the U.S. dollar,&#13;
continued to increase their prices in dollar terms.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
Changes in the Relative Importance of Trade in Manufactured Goods between the&#13;
Industrial and the Developing Countries&#13;
In the 1973-78 period, the developing countries assumed increased&#13;
importance as markets for the manufactured exports of the industrial&#13;
nations. Thus, their share in the extraregional exports of manufactured goods&#13;
of the industrial countries rose from 37 percent in 1973 to 47 percent in 1978&#13;
and to 49 percent in 1981. 2:2   And while data on average shares would seem to&#13;
indicate a deceleration over time, incremental shares remained practically&#13;
constant -- 54 percent in 1973-78 and 53 percent in 1978-81.&#13;
The developing countries also assumed increased importance as sources&#13;
of supply for manufactured goods imported by industrial countries; their&#13;
share in the industrial countries extraregional imports of these commodities&#13;
increased from 20 percent in 1973 to 24 percent in 1978 and to 25 percent in&#13;
1981. Again, incremental shares showed little change; they were 29 percent in&#13;
1973-78 and 27 percent in 1978-81.&#13;
In 1973, the developing countries accounted for the largest share of&#13;
extraregional manufactured exports in the United States (42 percent), with&#13;
EFTA (31 percent) at the lower end of the range. In turn, in 1981, these&#13;
countries had the highest share in the extraregional exports of the EC (54&#13;
percent), followed by the United States (51 percent), with Japan falling to&#13;
last place (42 percent). The results reflect differences in incremental&#13;
export shares that were especially high in the EC (63 percent) and much below&#13;
average in Japan (44 percent) during the period.&#13;
However, the United States retained first place as far as the&#13;
relative importance of developing countries in the extraregional imports of&#13;
manufactured goods is concerned. The U.S. import shares were 23 percent in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 3&#13;
The Relative Importance for the Industrial Nations of Trade in Manufac ured Goods&#13;
wiRa   the Developing Countries for the Industrial Nation        G&#13;
1973                                          1978                                              1981&#13;
XLDC/X      XLDC/p      MLDC/M     MLDC/C       XLDC/X    XLDC/p       MLDC/M     MLDC/C         XLDC/x    XLDC/p     MLDC/M      MLDC/C&#13;
United States             41.6        1.8       22.9         1.1         51.1      3.0          27.4        1.8         50.6         4.1       30.2        2.3&#13;
Canada                    35.9        1.2       12.5         0.8         50.7      2.4          17.4        1.3         47.7         3.0       20.4         1.6&#13;
EC                        37.3        3.7       18.1         0.9         49.8      6.8          23.3        1.6         54.4         8.3       24.4        2.0&#13;
EFTA                      31.0        5.2       14.4         1.2         39.7      8.9          17.8        1.9         43.7        10.0       19.2        2.3&#13;
Japan                     36.0        3.7       22.6         0.7         42.6      6.3          24.4        0.8          42.1        7.9       23.9         1.0&#13;
Industrial Countries      37.4        2.9       19.7        0.9          47.4      5.2         24.4         1.5         49.0         6.4       25.5        2.0&#13;
1973-78                                        1978-81                                         1973-81&#13;
AXLDCIAX   AXLDC6p    " MLDC,M    AMLDC/AC     A XLDC/,, X  XLDC4p    AMLDC/ M     MLDC/ C     A XLDC/4X X  XLDC/Ap  A MLDCItM   AMLDC/AC&#13;
United States             58.7        4.9       30.7         2.9         49.9        7.5        34.8        4.2          53.6        6.0       33.0        3.5&#13;
Canada                    63.1        4.5       23.9         2.0         44.0        4.7        26.6        2.6          51.6        4.6       25.2        2.3&#13;
EC                        59.1       11.5       27.2         2.6         70.8       17.2        21.7        4.3         62.9        13.1       26.8        3.1&#13;
EFTA                      46.2       13.8       23.7         2.9         57.3       13.9        19.3        3.7         50.0        13.9       21.3        3.3&#13;
JAPAN                     46.4        9.2       26.8         0.9         41.4       15.1        22.8        2.2         44.1        11.1       24.6         1.2&#13;
Industrial Countries      54.4        8.5       28.6         2.4         52.5       11.3       27.2         3.8         53.6         9.5       27.7        2.9&#13;
Sources:  GATT, International Trade; United Nations, Yearbook of Industrial Statistics; OECD, Indicators of Industrial Activity, various issues.&#13;
Notes  (a)  The definition of manufactured goods used here corresponds to that employed in trade statistics (SITC classes 5 to 8 less 68).&#13;
For 1981 production figures had to be estimated on the basis of incomplete information.&#13;
(b)  Explanation of symbols;    X = exports, M = imports, P = production, C = consumption (P+M-X), LDC = Developing Countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
1973 and 30 percent in 1981, with an incremental share of 33 percent. In&#13;
turn, EFTA remained at the last place, the relevant figures being 14, 19, and&#13;
21 percent. Finally, the share of the developing countries in Japanese&#13;
imports of manufactured goods rose between 1973 and 1978, but declined&#13;
slightly afterwards as incremental import shares in 1978-81 did not exceed the&#13;
average share at the beginning of the period (23 percent).&#13;
International trade in manufactured goods increased more rapidly than&#13;
manufacturing output in the industrial countries throughout the period under&#13;
consideration. Correspondingly, the share of exports to the developing&#13;
countries in the production of manufactured goods in the industrial countries&#13;
increased even more than their share in the extraregional exports of these&#13;
countries. The relevant proportions were 2.9 percent in 1973, 5.2 percent in&#13;
1978, and 6.4 percent in 1981. The deceleration in the rise of average shares&#13;
notwithstanding, incremental shares rose from 8.5 percent in 1973-78 and 11.3&#13;
percent in 1978-81, averaging 9.5 percent for the entire period (Table 3).&#13;
Similar trends are observed in regard to the share of imports from&#13;
the developing countries in the consumption of manufactured goods in the&#13;
industrial countries. These shares increased from 0.9 percent in 1973 to 1.5&#13;
percent in 1978 and to 2.0 percent in 1981, with incremental shares being 2.4&#13;
percent and 3.8 percent in 1973-78 and 1978-81, respectively.&#13;
Exports to the developing countries had a higher than average share&#13;
in the production, and lower than average share in the consumption, of&#13;
manufactured goods in Japan. Developing countries made little headway in&#13;
entering the Japanese market, with their share in the consumption of&#13;
manufactured goods rising only from 0.7 percent in 1973 to 1.0 percent in&#13;
1981. During this period, their incremental share in consumption was 1.2 in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
Japan, compared to a range of 3.1 to 3.5 percent in the other industrial&#13;
countries and country groups, excepting Canada.&#13;
As a result of these changes, in 1981, the developing countries had&#13;
the highest share in the consumption of manufactured goods in the United&#13;
States and EFTA (2.3 percent), followed by the EC (2.0 percent) and Canada&#13;
(1.6 percent). In the same year, the developing countries provided markets&#13;
for 10.0 percent of manufacturing output in EFTA, 8.3 percent in the EC, 7.9&#13;
percent in Japan, 4.1 percent in the United States, and 3.0 percent in Canada.&#13;
Policy Implications of the Results&#13;
Changes in the manufactured imports of the OPEC countries are largely&#13;
explained by the effects that the 1973-74 and 1979-80 oil price increases had&#13;
on their foreign exchange revenue and by the speed at which increases in these&#13;
revenues were translated into higher imports. Following the quadrupling of&#13;
oil prices, the merchandise trade surplus of the OPEC countries increased from&#13;
$21 billion in 1973 to $84 billion in 1974. It declined to $43 billion by&#13;
1978 as manufactured imports were catching up with the higher revenues. The&#13;
OPEC surplus rose again to $113 billion in 1979 and to $168 billion in 1980,&#13;
when oil prices increased two-and-a-half times; it declined only to $120&#13;
billion in 1981, indicating the time lag involved in adjusting to higher&#13;
revenues.&#13;
Nevertheless, differences are observed within OPEC as the capital-&#13;
surplus countries continued to accumulate reserves while some other OPEC&#13;
countries borrowed abroad in order to finance their ambitious development&#13;
programs. The non-OPEC developing countries also stepped up their foreign&#13;
borrowing during the period under consideration, so as to finance their rising&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
merchandise trade deficit that grew from $15 billion in 1973 to $37 billion in&#13;
1978 and to $78 billion in 1981.&#13;
Foreign borrowing represented one of several possible policy&#13;
responses of the non-OPEC developing countries to the external shocks they&#13;
experienced in the form of the oil prices increases of 1973-74 and 1979-80 and&#13;
the ensuing world recessions. Other policy responses included export&#13;
promotion, import substitution, and deflationary policies.&#13;
The observed increases in the apparent income elasticity of import&#13;
demand -- defined as negative import substitution -- more than offset the&#13;
import effects of the decline in rates of economic growth in the non-OPEC&#13;
developing countries, so that the rise of their imports accelerated. Also,&#13;
while these countries increased their export market shares in manufactured&#13;
goods, the net result was a rise in foreign borrowing as a proportion of&#13;
imports.&#13;
Foreign borrowing made it possible for the non-OPEC developing&#13;
countries to finance their growing deficit in manufactured trade with the&#13;
industrial countries, notwithstanding their higher oil bill. This increase,&#13;
in turn, benefited the industrial countries in a situation of underutilized&#13;
capacity. Assuming that the increment in net exports, over and above what&#13;
would have occurred if the 1973 ratio of net exports to production had&#13;
remained unchanged, added to manufacturing output in the industrial countries,&#13;
incremental output between 1973 and 1981 was 4.6 percent larger than it would&#13;
have been otherwise. 11/&#13;
The trade-induced rise in incremental output appears to have been the&#13;
largest in the EC (7.2 percent), followed by Japan (6.9 percent), EFTA (6.6&#13;
percent), with Canada (1.9 percent) and the United States (1.6 percent) at the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
other end of the scale. At the same time, these figures represent an&#13;
underestimate inasmuch as they do not allow for multiplier effects and an&#13;
overestimate inasmuch as they do not take account of alternative uses of the&#13;
capital outflow from the industrial countries in their own economies.&#13;
In turn, the observed rise in the industrial countries' income&#13;
elasticity of demand for the imports of manufactured goods originating in the&#13;
developing countries, and the increased developing country share in their&#13;
consumption of these commodities, do not provide an indication of increased&#13;
protectionism in the industrial countries. 13/ Japan provides an exception,&#13;
however, as it had by far the lowest income elasticity of demand for&#13;
manufactured imports from the developing countries and these countries had by&#13;
far the lowest share in its domestic consumption of manufactured goods.&#13;
These results cannot be explained on the grounds that factor&#13;
endowments are more similar between the developing countries and Japan than&#13;
between the developing countries and other industrial countries. Although&#13;
such might have been the case during the sixties, the situation changed to a&#13;
considerable extent afterwards. At the same time, with relatively high&#13;
economic growth rates, Japan's factor endowment changed rapidly, and this&#13;
should have led to rapid increases in imports from the developing countries if&#13;
these imports had not been subject to restrictions.&#13;
This is not to say that the expansion of the developing countries'&#13;
manufactured exports could be explained by demand considerations alone. In&#13;
this regard, a statement made by the author concerning the 1973-78 period&#13;
continues to apply.&#13;
"While access to industrial country markets has provided&#13;
opportunities for export expansion, the exports of manufactured&#13;
goods from the developing countries had responded to the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
policies followed by these countries. A number of developing&#13;
countries adopted an export-oriented strategy during the 1960s&#13;
and have continued with this strategy after 1973. Available&#13;
evidence suggests that countries following an export-oriented&#13;
strategy were better able to surmount the adverse effects of&#13;
the quadrupling of oil prices and the 1974-1975 world rec s7ion&#13;
than countries with an import-substitution orientation."&#13;
Developing countries following an export-oriented strategy also&#13;
relied less on foreign borrowing than import substitution-oriented countries.&#13;
14/ In turn, with lower indebtedness, they escaped the difficulties the&#13;
latter group of countries experienced as world interest rates rose. Excessive&#13;
foreign borrowing under import substitution orientation, then, helped the&#13;
expansion of manufacturing output in the industrial countries in a situation&#13;
of underutilized capacity but subsequently created difficulties for the&#13;
borrowing countries themselves.&#13;
II. Effects of Trade on Production, Employment, and Resource Allocation&#13;
Recent Trends in the Trade of Individual Commodity Groups&#13;
We have seen that the developing countries assumed increased&#13;
importance as markets for the industrial nations between 1973 and 1981. The&#13;
same picture emerges in regard to individual commodity groups, for which&#13;
comparable production and trade data are available for the entire period.&#13;
They include iron and steel, chemicals, other semimanufactures, engineering&#13;
products, textiles, clothing, and other consumer goods. For all these&#13;
commodity groups, the share of the developing countries in the extraregional&#13;
exports, and in the production, of the industrial countries rose between 1973&#13;
and 1978 and, again, between 1978 and 1981 (Table 4).&#13;
In 1973, the developing countries' share in the extraregional exports&#13;
of the industrial countries varied from 26 percent in the other consumer goods&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 4&#13;
The Relative Importance for the Industrial Nations of&#13;
Trade in Industrial Commodity Groups with the&#13;
Developing Countries&#13;
1973                                           1978                                          1981&#13;
XLDC/X     XLDC/P     MLDC/M      MLOC/C       XLDC/X     XLDC/P     MLDC/M      MLDC/C      XLDC/X     XLDC/P     MLDC/M      MLDC/C&#13;
Iron and Steel                 41.0         3.5       10.7        0.4         44.8        5.0        11.6        0.5        49.7        6.5        16.1        1.0&#13;
Chemicals                      42.2         3.4       11.2        0.4         45.5        4.6        12.1        0.6        47.5        4.9        13.7        0.7&#13;
Other Semi Manufactures        36.7         1.1       34.0        1.0         50.7        2.5        38.1        1.6        53.0         3.0       34.8        1.5&#13;
Engineering Products           36.6         3.7        9.9        0.5         48.2        7.0        15.1        1.0        48.9        8.7        16.2        1.5&#13;
Textiles                       43.0         2.8       39.8        1.3         49.3        3.6        45.8        2.7        52.6         5.0       45.2        3.0&#13;
Clothing                       28.7         0.9       63.3        6.0         40.8         1.7       69.1       10.9        46.5         2.6       73.8       14.4&#13;
Other Consumer Goods           26.2         1.2       27.7        1.4         41.2        2.3        37.0        2.4        46.2        3.3        44.4        3.3&#13;
Total Manufacturing            37.4         2.9       19.7        0.9         47.4        5.2        24.4        1.5        49.0        6.4        25.5        2.0&#13;
1973-1978                                       1978-1981                                    1973-1981&#13;
6XLDC/'X   AXLDCI P    MLDC/MM   AMLDC/t C     AXLDC/AX   t XLDC/AP  AMLDC/AM   AMLDC/AC     AXLDCkX    AXLDc/AP   AMLDC/AM   AMLDCAC&#13;
Iron and Steel                 47.6        7.3       11.5         0.7         64.8       17.5        25.4        4.8        54.3        10.0       18.9        1.8&#13;
Chemicals                      47.8         5.9      12.7         0.7         51.9         5.8       15.8        1.0        49.7         5.8       14.3         .9&#13;
Other Semi Manufactures        61.5         6.5      42.3         3.4         58.0        5.2        22.0        1.1        60.0         5.9       35.3        2.3&#13;
Engineering Products           55.7        11.2      19.0         1.6         50.4       15.9        18.0        3.8        53.4        12.8       18.5        2.3&#13;
Textiles                       59.5         5.6      49.1         6.1         61.7       17.2        45.0        6.3        60.7        8.7        48.0        6.1&#13;
Clothing                       50.0         3.2      73.3        19.6         56.3        12.2       84.5       41.5        53.1         5.2       77.8       25.5&#13;
Other Consumer Goods           53.2         3.6      43.4         3.5         54.9        7.8        63.6        7.5        54.1         4.9       51.9        4.7&#13;
Total Manufacturing            54.4        8.5       28.6         2.4         52.5       11.3        27.2        3.8        53.6        9.5        27.7        2.9&#13;
Sources: See Table 3&#13;
Notes: (a) The classification system used corresponds to that applied in GATT, International Trade.&#13;
(b) Explanation of symbols: see Table 3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
category and 29 percent in clothing to 42 percent in chemicals and 43 percent&#13;
in textiles. The differences narrowed to a considerable extent between 1973&#13;
and 1981. Other consumer goods and clothing (46 percent) remained at the&#13;
lower end of the range; semimanufactures joined textiles (53 percent) at the&#13;
upper end; and the developing countries came to account for 49 percent of the&#13;
industrial countries extraregional exports of engineering products.&#13;
The share of exports to developing country markets in production in&#13;
the industrial countries, too, increased in every commodity group. At the&#13;
lower end of the range, this share rose from 0.9 to 2.6 percent in the case of&#13;
clothing, from 1.1 to 3.0 percent for other semimanufactures, and from 1.2 to&#13;
3.3 percent for the other consumer goods category; at the upper end, the&#13;
relevant shares were 3.4 and 4.9 percent for chemicals, 3.5 and 6.5 percent&#13;
for iron and steel, and 3.7 and 8.7 percent for engineering products. In the&#13;
latter category, increases in exports to the developing countries provided&#13;
12.8 percent of incremental output in the industrial countries between 1973&#13;
and 1981. Incremental shares varied from 4.9 percent (other consumer goods)&#13;
to 10.0 percent (steel) in the other commodity groups.&#13;
The developing countries also increased their share in the&#13;
extraregional imports of the industrial countries in every commodity group&#13;
between 1973 and 1981. While this share remained relatively low in&#13;
engineering products (9.9 percent in 1973 and 16.2 percent in 1981), iron and&#13;
steel (10.7 and 16.1 percent) and chemicals (11.2 and 13.7 percent), it&#13;
increased from 39.8 to 45.2 percent in textiles, from 63.3 to 73.8 percent in&#13;
clothing, and from 27.7 to 44.4 percent in the other consumer goods category.&#13;
Imports from the developing countries, expressed as a percentage of&#13;
consumption in the industrial countries, too, rose in all commodity groups.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
Varying between 0.4 and 0.5 percent in 1973, these imports reached 1.0 percent&#13;
of consumption in the case of iron and steel, 0.7 percent for chemicals, and&#13;
1.5 percent for engineering products in 1981. At the other end of the scale,&#13;
the share of imports rose from 6.0 percent to 14.4 percent in the case of&#13;
clothing, followed by textiles (1.3 and 3.0 percent) and other consumer goods&#13;
(1.4 and 3.3 percent).&#13;
Clothing also leads in terms of incremental consumption shares (25.5&#13;
percent between 1973 and 1981), followed by textiles (6.1 percent) and other&#13;
consumer goods (4.7 percent). These results occurred, notwithstanding the&#13;
continued operation of the Multifiber Arrangement and the restrictions imposed&#13;
on some of the other consumer goods originating in the developing countries.&#13;
Moreover, incremental shares doubled between 1973-78 and 1978-81 in the case&#13;
of clothing and other consumer goods, exceeding the increases shown for total&#13;
manufacturing, while they remained constant for textiles.&#13;
The next question concerns the extent to which changes in net exports&#13;
in trade with the developing countries affected manufacturing output in the&#13;
industrial countries. Under the assumptions made earlier, the average 4.6&#13;
percent increase in output between 1973 and 1981, associated with increases in&#13;
the ratio of net exports to production, covers considerable differences among&#13;
commodity groups. The resulting rise in incremental output appears to be the&#13;
largest for engineering products (7.3 percent) and iron and steel (5.1&#13;
percent), followed by chemicals (2.9 percent), other semimanufactures (2.5&#13;
percent), and textiles (1.1 percent). In turn, no changes occurred in other&#13;
consumer goods while trade in clothing with the developing countries appears&#13;
to have reduced incremental output by 15.2 percent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
Table 5&#13;
Employment and Capital/Labor Coefficients in the Trade&#13;
of the Industrial Countries with the Developing Countries in Manufactured Goods&#13;
Stocks                            Flows&#13;
EJO        PK/E       HK/E       TK/E       PK/E       HK/E       TKM&#13;
X    M     X    M     X    M     X    M     X    M     X    M     X    M&#13;
USA&#13;
1973                  18.4 25.5  12.8  9.8  28.1 25.0  40.9 34.8   9.0  6.7   9.4  8.0  18.4 14.7&#13;
1978                  18.2 25.8  12.5  9.3  28.1 25.4  40.6 34.7   9.1  6.7   9.4  8.1  18.5 14.8&#13;
1981                  18.5 25.3  12.5  9.3  28.1 25.9  40.6 35.2   9.0  6.8   9.4  8.2  18.4 15.0&#13;
Canada&#13;
1973                  17.0 28.0  14.0  8.8  27.9 22.0  41.9 30.8   9.0  5.8   9.4  7.3  18.4 13.1&#13;
1978                  15.5 27.4  13.8  8.6  27.5 22.7  41.3 31.3   9.7  6.3   9.8  7.4  19.5 13.7&#13;
1981                  15.4 26.7  13.0  9.0  26.7 24.0  39.7 33.0   9.4  6.4   9.4  7.7  18.8 14.1&#13;
EC&#13;
1973                  18.0 25.6  13.7 11.4  27.3 21.8  41.0 33.2   9.2  6.6   9.3  7.5  18.5 14.1&#13;
1978                  18.4 25.7  12.8 10.5  27.5 22.8  40.4 33.3   8.6  6.6   9.3  7.7  17.9 14.3&#13;
1981                  18.1 25.9  12.9  9.8  27.2 23.3  40.1 33.1   8.7  6.7   9.2  7.7  17.9 14.4&#13;
EFTA&#13;
1973                  18.7 23.9  13.2 11.1  28.5 19.6  41.7 30.7   9.0  7.1   9.2  6.9  18.2 14.0&#13;
1978                  18.8 26.6  13.1  9.9  28.4 22.1  41.5 32.0   8.7  6.8   9.2  7.4  17.9 14.2&#13;
1981                  18.7 26.4  13.0  9.9  28.0 22.5  41.0 32.4   8.8  6.9   9.2  7.5  18.0 14.4&#13;
Japan&#13;
1973                  18.5 25.4  14.9 11.7  27.5 21.2  42.4 32.9   8.0  6.4   9.3  7.4  17.3 13.8&#13;
1978                  17.8 25.6  13.8 11.7  28.3 23.0  42.1 34.7   8.3  7.2   9.5  7.8  17.8 15.0&#13;
1981                  17.7 23.9  13.7 12.4  28.4 23.8  42.1 36.2   8.4  7.4   9.5  8.0  17.9 15.4&#13;
Industrial Countries&#13;
1973                  18.2 25.6  13.7 10.6  27.6 23.2  41.3 33.8   8.8  6.6   9.3  7.7  18.1 14.3&#13;
1978                  18.2 25.8  13.1  9.9  27.9 24.0  41.0 33.9   8.7  6.7   9.4  7.8  18.1 14.5&#13;
1981                  18.2 25.5  13.1  9.8  28.0 24.7  41.1 34.5   8.8  6.8   9.4  8.0  18.2 14.8&#13;
Sources:  Bela Balassa (1979) "The Changing International Division of Labor in Manufactured Goods,"&#13;
Banca Nazionale del Lavoro, Quarterly Review, No. 130, pp. 243-85 and (1979) "A 'Stages' Approach to&#13;
Comparative Advantage," Economic Growth and Resources. Volume 4:  National and International Issues&#13;
[Irma Adelman, ed.]. (London, Macmillan) pp. 121-56.&#13;
Notes:  X = exports, M = imports, E = employment, 0 = production, PK = physical capital, HK = hunlan&#13;
capital, TK = total capital. For explanation of "stocks" and "flows," see text.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
Employment Effects&#13;
Trade in manufactures also affects employment in the industrial&#13;
nations. Table 5 shows that, during the period under consideration, average&#13;
labor input coefficients were two-fifths higher in the industrial countries&#13;
imports than in their exports of manufactured goods in trade with the&#13;
developing countries. The ratios exhibited considerable stability over time&#13;
and differences among industrial countries and country groups were relatively&#13;
small. The exception is Canada where labor input coefficients were lower for&#13;
exports, and higher for imports, than the industrial country average.&#13;
The results reflect interindustry differences in labor input&#13;
coefficients, calculated from the 1975 U.S. Census of Manufacturing in a&#13;
eleven commodity group breakdown by subdividing the engineering product group&#13;
into five categories (machinery for specialized industry, office and&#13;
telecommunication equipment, road motor vehicles, other machinery and&#13;
transport equipment and household appliances). Labor input coefficients,&#13;
expressed in man years per million dollars of output, are lower than the&#13;
manufacturing average for engineering products (18.6), with a range from 6.9&#13;
for motor vehicles to 21.0 for household appliances; other semimanufactures&#13;
(18.0); iron and steel (15.9); and chemicals (13.2). By contrast, labor input&#13;
coefficients exceed the manufacturing average in the case of clothing (40.6),&#13;
other consumer goods (28.9), and textiles (26.7). 15/&#13;
The observed differences in average labor input coefficients for the&#13;
industrial countries manufactured exports and imports in trade with the&#13;
developing countries were more than offset by their surplus in this trade,&#13;
resulting in a net gain in employment. 16/ The estimated gain was 701&#13;
thousand jobs in 1973, 1439 thousand jobs in 1978, and 1474 thousand jobs in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 6&#13;
Employment Effects of Trade in Manufactured Goods with the Developing Countries&#13;
Industrial&#13;
United States           Canada               EC                 EFTA              Japan              Countries&#13;
1973  1978  1981    1973  1978  1981   1973  1978  1981    1973  1978  1981   1973  1978   1981   1973  1978  1981&#13;
Iron and Steel                                  7     3     3       1     1     1     33    57    54       2     3     3     54    75     74     97   139   135&#13;
Chemicals                                      32    56    68       1     2     2     63    92     91      8    12    12     19    28     23    123   190   196&#13;
Other Semi-Manufactures                        -8    -9     0       2     3     4      9    27    35       6    18    15     -2     13    20      7    52    74&#13;
Engineering Products                          118   239   286       8    14    15    302   622   553      48    86    79    149   351   368     625  1312  1301&#13;
of which:&#13;
Machinery for Specialized Industries         47   129   155       2     3     4    131   258    222     15    28    28     45    99    105    240   517   514&#13;
Office and Telecommunications Equipment       4    -6   -14       2     1     0     19    32     27      6     8     7     12     27    31     43    62    51&#13;
Road Motor Vehicles                          10    19    19       1     4     4     25    42    47       1     3     4     11    32     38     48   100   112    e&#13;
Other Machinery and Equipment                70   119   147       4     8     9    121   283   255      16    35    32     56    145   127    267   590   570&#13;
Household Appliances                        -13   -22   -21      -1    -2    -2      6     7     2      10    12     8     25    48     67     27    43    54&#13;
Textiles                                       -9    -3     1      -3    -2    -2      4     1     7       0     2     3     36    37     46     28    35    54&#13;
Clothing                                      -72  -134  -138      -8   -12   -12    -53   -92    -94     -9   -16   -17    -21   -25    -22   -163  -279  -283&#13;
Other Consumer Goods                          -37   -71   -78      -3    -5    -7     20    56     64      1     1     3      3     9     15    -16   -10    -3&#13;
Total Manufacturing                            31    81   143      -2    -1     1    378   763   710      56   106    98    238   488    523    701  1439  1474&#13;
Sources: Table 5 and GATT, International Trade 1980/81 and 1981/82.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
1981 (Table 6); the slowdown after 1978 is explained by the decline in export-&#13;
import ratios in trade with the developing countries.&#13;
Among the industrial countries and country groups, employment gains&#13;
decreased after 1978 in the EC and EFTA, they underwent little change in&#13;
Canada, while continued increases were shown in Japan and, in particular, in&#13;
the United States. Nevertheless, in 1981, net employment gains were by far&#13;
the largest in the European Common Market (710 thousand) and Japan (523&#13;
thousand), followed by the United States (142 thousand), and the European Free&#13;
Trade Association (98 thousand), with Canada showing an approximate balance.&#13;
The relatively low U.S. net employment gain, compared to its trade balance in&#13;
manufactures with the developing countries, is explained by its low&#13;
export/import ratio. The same considerations account for the lack of a net&#13;
employment gain in Canada.&#13;
Among individual commodity groups, iron and steel, chemicals, other&#13;
semimanufactures, all categories of engineering products, and textiles&#13;
exhibited net employment gains in the industrial countries. These gains&#13;
increased between 1973 and 1978 and showed little change afterwards, the&#13;
exception being the other semimanufactures category that experienced large&#13;
increases in net employment gains as the trade surplus of the industrial&#13;
countries increased to a considerable extent.&#13;
In 1981, net losses in employment were shown in only one commodity&#13;
group, clothing, with practically no net effect for the other consumer goods&#13;
category. In the case of clothing, net employment losses for the industrial&#13;
countries, due to their trade with the developing countries, were estimated at&#13;
163 thousand in 1973, 279 thousand in 1978, and 283 thousand in 1981.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
To put these figures into perspective, they should be compared with&#13;
actual employment statistics. The results show that, in 1981, net employment&#13;
losses due to trade with the developing countries did not reach 3 percent of&#13;
employment in the textiles, clothing, and leather products sector of the&#13;
industrial countries. -1.   The ratio was the highest for the United States,&#13;
but it did not exceed 6 percent in this case either.&#13;
Alternatively, one may compare changes in trade-induced employment&#13;
losses with changes in employment. Between 1973 and 1980, employment in the&#13;
textiles, clothing, and leather products sector of the industrial countries&#13;
declined by 1.7 million, compared to an increase of 0.1 million in net&#13;
employment losses due to trade with the developing countries. In none of the&#13;
industrial countries and country groups did the increase in the trade-induced&#13;
loss in employment reach 15 percent of the decline in employment in this&#13;
sector.&#13;
Comparative Advantage in Trade in Manufactured Goods&#13;
We have considered the effects of trade in manufactured goods between&#13;
the industrial and the developing countries on employment in the former group&#13;
of countries. Next, the factor intensity of this trade will be examined, with&#13;
separate consideration given to physical and human capital.&#13;
Physical capital/labor and human capital/labor ratios have been&#13;
derived from U.S. data with calculations made in "stock" and in "flow"&#13;
terms. The former have been defined as the value of fixed capital per worker&#13;
(physical capital) and the discounted value of the difference between the&#13;
average wage and the unskilled wage (human capital), and the latter as nonwage&#13;
value added per worker (physical capital) and the average wage (human&#13;
capital).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
Table 5 provides information on average capital/labor ratios for the&#13;
exports and imports of manufactured goods in trade between the industrial and&#13;
the developing countries. As is apparent from the table, capital/labor ratios&#13;
are substantially higher for the exports than for the imports of the&#13;
industrial countries. In 1973, the ratio for exports exceeded that for&#13;
imports by 29 percent for physical and by 19 percent for human capital,&#13;
utilizing the stock measure, and by 33 percent for physical and 21 percent for&#13;
human capital, utilizing the flow measure.&#13;
Between 1973 and 1981, the aggregate ratios (physical and human&#13;
capital combined) changed little for exports, and increased slightly for&#13;
imports. The results were practically the same under the stock and the flow&#13;
measures, with a 3 to 4 percentage points reduction in the difference in&#13;
capital/labor ratios between exports and imports.&#13;
It appears, then, that trade in manufactured goods between the&#13;
industrial and the developing countries conformed to their comparative&#13;
advantage. While textiles may appear to be an aberrant case, it should be&#13;
recognized that the industrial countries and, in particular, the United States&#13;
export high-quality textiles and import low quality textile products from the&#13;
developing countries. 18/&#13;
By-and-large similar results are obtained for the trade of individual&#13;
countries and country groups with the developing countries; exceptions are&#13;
Canada whose exports tend to be relatively more capital intensive compared to&#13;
its imports from the developing countries and EFTA where the opposite is the&#13;
case. In Canada, the high export share of the capital-intensive, natural&#13;
resource-based other intermediate products category contributed to this&#13;
result, while the EFTA countries are the most liberal among industrial&#13;
countries in admitting labor-intensive manufactures from the developing&#13;
countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
The results changed little between 1973 and 1981. An exception is&#13;
engineering products where the developing countries increased their exports to&#13;
a considerable extent. This change also conformed to the comparative&#13;
advantage of the two groups of countries, with the developing countries&#13;
gaining in the exports of labor-intensive radios and television sets as well&#13;
as in exporting labor-intensive parts, components, and accessories in the&#13;
framework of the international division of the production process.&#13;
Policy Implications of the Results&#13;
The data show that the industrial countries tend to exchange&#13;
manufactured goods intensive in physical and in human capital for products&#13;
intensive in unskilled labor. Such an exchange apparently occurs through&#13;
interindustry as well as through intraindustry specialization.&#13;
The large differences observed in capital/labor ratios among&#13;
commodity groups are indicative of the mutual gains the industrial and the&#13;
developing countries can obtain through specialization according to&#13;
comparative advantage. This result is strengthened if account is taken of&#13;
differences in capital/labor ratios within individual commodity groups. It&#13;
receives further support if consideration is given to the high research&#13;
intensity of the manufactured exports of the industrial countries.&#13;
Apart from traditional gains owing to differences in factor&#13;
proportions, the industrial countries derive benefits from trade in&#13;
manufactured goods with the developing countries through the exploitation of&#13;
economies of scale. This source of gain has assumed increased importance as&#13;
the share of the developing countries in the domestic production of&#13;
manufactured goods in the industrial countries has risen. Apart from&#13;
economies of scale in production, gains are obtained through economies of&#13;
scale in research inasmuch as a larger sales volume permits reducing unit&#13;
expenditures on research and development.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
Further gains can be obtained through intraindustry trade in the form&#13;
of horizontal or product specialization, such as the exchange of capital-&#13;
intensive for labor-intensive textiles, and vertical specialization in the&#13;
framework of the international division of the production process, involving&#13;
the importation of labor-intensive parts, components, and accessories from the&#13;
developing countries. Horizontal specialization permits reducing costs by&#13;
concentrating on fewer commodities while vertical specialization reduces costs&#13;
through the purchase of lower-priced inputs. Finally, increased competition&#13;
from developing countries provides inducements for technological improvements&#13;
as it has been the case in the textile industry.&#13;
The developing countries, too, enjoy gains from improved resource&#13;
allocation, the exploitation of economies of scale, and competition through&#13;
interindustry and intraindustry trade in manufactured goods with the&#13;
industrial countries. They enjoy the further benefit of procuring&#13;
sophisticated machinery and equipment in a world of rapidly changing&#13;
technology.&#13;
International specialization in manufactured goods also affects&#13;
employment. While at the actual level of trade the industrial countries have&#13;
a net employment gain, a balanced expansion of exports and imports would have&#13;
negative employment effects for them. This is because labor input&#13;
coefficients are, on the average, two-fifths higher for the imports than for&#13;
the exports of the industrial countries in their trade in manufactured goods&#13;
with the developing countries.&#13;
Nevertheless, projections earlier made by the author indicate that&#13;
the net employment effects of the expansion of trade in manufactured goods are&#13;
likely to be negligible. This estimate was made for the 1976-86 period on the&#13;
assumption that the exports of manufactured goods from the industrial to the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
developing countries would rise at an average annual rate of 5.7 percent, and&#13;
their imports at a rate of 12.6 percent. 19/&#13;
According to the same article, the expansion of trade in manufactured&#13;
goods would involve the upgrading of the labor force, with increases in the&#13;
number of professional, technical, and highly skilled workers and a decline in&#13;
unskilled and semiskilled workers in the industrial countries. The upgrading&#13;
of the labor force, in turn, would contribute to the increases in the&#13;
productivity and higher rates of economic growth.&#13;
Conclusions&#13;
This paper examined the increased importance of the developing&#13;
countries as markets for the manufactured goods produced in the industrial&#13;
nations. In particular, in the 1973-81 period, developing countries accounted&#13;
for one-half of the increment in the extraregional exports of manufactured&#13;
goods by the industrial countries and provided markets for one-tenth of the&#13;
increment in their manufacturing output. These shares were higher than the&#13;
average for engineering products, where economies of scale are of especial&#13;
importance.&#13;
In turn, the industrial countries increased their imports of&#13;
manufactured goods from the developing countries at rates exceeding the rate&#13;
of growth of their GDP four times. In the 1973-81 period, the developing&#13;
countries provided over one-fourth of the increment in the extraregional&#13;
imports, and three percent of the increment in manufacturing consumption, of&#13;
the industrial countries. Their share was the highest in clothing, accounting&#13;
for over three-quarters of the increase in extraregional imports and for one-&#13;
quarter of the rise in consumption.&#13;
It further appears that increases in the industrial countries net&#13;
exports of manufactured goods in trade with the developing countries had&#13;
multiplier effects on their economies in a situation of underutilized&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
capacity. In turn, the rapid rise of their manufactured exports to the&#13;
industrial countries had favorable effects on the growth process of the&#13;
developing countries.&#13;
The two groups of countries derive further benefits from improved&#13;
resource allocation, economies of scale, and increased competition through&#13;
interindustry and intraindustry trade in manufactured goods. In the&#13;
industrial countries, this trade contributes to structural change, involving&#13;
the exchange of capital for labor, the upgrading of the labor force, and the&#13;
expansion of research-intensive activities.&#13;
It follows that trade liberalization is in the mutual interests of&#13;
the industrial and the developing countries. In particular, the reduction of&#13;
trade barriers in the industrial countries becomes an agent for structural&#13;
change that is, in turn, a condition for increases in productivity and higher&#13;
rates of economic growth.&#13;
The lowering of trade barriers would also permit increased trade&#13;
among the developing countries that is presently limited by these barriers.&#13;
Interregional trade may occur between countries at the same level of&#13;
development as well as between the newly-industrializing and the less&#13;
developed countries. Also, if appropriate policies are followed, the less&#13;
developed countries can replace the newly-industrializing countries in&#13;
exporting simple, unskilled labor intensive products while the latter group of&#13;
countries can upgrade and diversify their exports.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
NOTES&#13;
1/   Bela Balassa (1979) "The Changing International Division of Labor in&#13;
Manufactured Goods," Banca Nazionale del Lavoro, Quarterly Review, no.&#13;
130, pp. 243-85; (1980) "Prospects for Trade in Manufactured Goods&#13;
between Industrial and Developing Countries, 1978-1990," Journal of&#13;
Policy Modeling, vol. 2, no. 3, pp. 437-53 and (1981) "Trade in&#13;
Manufactured Goods: Patterns of Change," World Development, vol. 9, pp.&#13;
263-75.&#13;
2/   Belgiuir-Luxembourg, Denmark, Germany, France, Greece, Ireland, Italy, the&#13;
Netherlands and the United Kingdom -- Data for 1981-83 include Greece;&#13;
this causes little distortion in the results as Greece accounts for less&#13;
than 1 percent of EC trade in manufactured goods.&#13;
3/   Austria, Finland, Iceland, Norway, Portugal, Sweden and Switzerland.&#13;
4/   Algeria, Ecuador, Gabon, Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Libyan Arab&#13;
Jamahiriya, Nigeria, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, United Arab Emirates and&#13;
Venezuela.&#13;
5/   Manufactured goods have been defined as commodity classes 5 to 8 in the&#13;
U.N. Standard International Trade Classification less nonferrous metals&#13;
(68). The same definition is used throughout in the paper.&#13;
6/   Data on oil imports are provided in GATT, International Trade, Geneva,&#13;
various issues.&#13;
7/   The expression 'apparent' income elasticity is used to refer to the fact&#13;
that this measure neglects the effects of changes in relative prices on&#13;
the volume of imports. Nor does the measure consider the interactions of&#13;
changes in demand and in supply. On the point, see p. 12 below.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
8/   Estimates based on United Nations, Monthly Bulletin of Statistics,&#13;
various issues and World Bank economic and social data base.&#13;
9/   Estimated by regression analysis from data published in United Nations,&#13;
Monthly Bulletin of Statistics and Yearbook of National Accounts&#13;
Statistics.&#13;
10/ Extraregional trade has been defined to exclude trade in manufactured&#13;
goods between the United States and Canada, one-third of which is exempt&#13;
from duty under the U.S.-Canadian Automotive Agreement while a&#13;
substantial part of the remainder represents intra-company transactions,&#13;
as well as trade within the European free trade area that encompasses the&#13;
EC and EFTA. -- All data are in current prices.&#13;
11/ The calculations have been made by relating the difference between the&#13;
incremental ratio of net exports to output in the 1973-81 period and the&#13;
average ratio in 1973 to the increment in output between 1973 and 1981.&#13;
Needless to say, the results are subject to qualifications due to the use&#13;
of current price data.&#13;
12/ For supporting evidence, see Bela Balassa (1980) "The Tokyo Round and the&#13;
Developing Countries," Journal of World Trade Law, vol. 14, no. 2, pp.&#13;
243-85.&#13;
13/ Bela Balassa, (1981) "Trade in Manufactured Goods: Patterns of Change,"&#13;
op. cit., p. 267.&#13;
14/ "Adjustment to External Shocks in Developing Economies," to be published&#13;
in the Proceedings of the Conference on the Problem of Changing Relative&#13;
Prices, organized by the International Economic Association and held in&#13;
Athens, in September 1981. World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 472, July&#13;
1981.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
15/ The calculations reflect the assumption that the same coefficients apply&#13;
to the other industrial countries and that they are invariant within a&#13;
particular category, irrespective of whether the products are exported or&#13;
replace imports. Employment gains and losses have been calculated by&#13;
adjusting the coefficients for changes in industrial prices.&#13;
16/ The calculation assumes constant labor input coefficients and disregards&#13;
the loss in employment associated with the outflow of capital.&#13;
17/ Employment data pertain to 1980 and originate in OECD, Labor Force&#13;
Statistics, 1961-1980. While data on the employment effects of trade are&#13;
not available for leather products this represents a relatively small&#13;
fraction of the total.&#13;
18/ Bela Balassa (1983) "Industrial Prospects and Policies in Developed&#13;
Countries," Fritz Machlup, Gerhard Fels, and Hubertus Muller-Groeling,&#13;
eds., Reflections on a Troubled World Economy, Essays in Honor of Herbert&#13;
Giersch. (London: Trade Policy Reserch Center) pp. 257-78.&#13;
19/ Bela Balassa, (1979) "The Changing International Division of Labor in&#13;
Manufactured Goods" op. cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
World Bank&#13;
Publications&#13;
of Related&#13;
Interest&#13;
Adjustment Polides and               Britain's Pattern of Special.        Capital Importing Oil&#13;
Problems In Developed                ization in Manufactured             Exporters: Adjustment&#13;
Countries                            Goods with Developing                Issues and Policy Choices&#13;
Martin Wolf                         Countries and Trade                  Alan 11. Gelb&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  Protection                           A background study for World&#13;
349. August 1979. 236 pages (includ-  Vincent Cable and                  Development Report 1981. Uses a&#13;
ing references).                    Ivonia Rebelo                        simple two-sector model involving&#13;
traded and nontraded goods as a&#13;
Stock No. WP-0349. $10.00.           World Bank Staff Working Paper      conceptual framework to compare the&#13;
No. 425. October 1980. 61 pages      evolution of critical macro and sec-&#13;
(including 3 appendixes).           toral variables for a number of oil&#13;
Adjustment to External               Stock No WP-0425 $3.00               economies after 1974 and discusses&#13;
Shocks in Developing                                                      govemment responses to the oil&#13;
Economies                                                                 crisis and the effects of these&#13;
Bela Balassa                                                              responses of the nonoil economies.&#13;
A background study for World                                              World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Development Report 1981. Analyzes                                         475. August 1981. 38 pages (including&#13;
adjustments to external shocks, in                                        9 tables).&#13;
the form of changes in the terms of                                      Stock No. WP-0475. $3.00.&#13;
trade and the slowdown in foreign&#13;
export demand, in twenty-eight&#13;
developing economies, classifled&#13;
according to the character of external&#13;
shocks, the level of industrial devel-&#13;
opment, and the policies applied.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
472. July 1981. 31 pages (including&#13;
appendix).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0472. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NEW                              The Export Experience of            Oxford University Press. 1982.&#13;
Developing Countries                 224 pages (including index).&#13;
The Developing Countries             Barend A. de Vries                  LC 82-6309. ISBN 0-19-520211-2,&#13;
and International Shipping           The English-language edition is     $22.50 (410.50) hardcqoer. (A specially&#13;
Harald Hansen                        out of print.                       priced edition will be auailable in India&#13;
Considers whether developing coun-   French: Resultats obtenus en matiere  from Oxford Universitxj Press branches.)&#13;
trieps can beneflt from investments in  d'exportation par les pays en voie de&#13;
international shipping and discusses  developpement. Dunod Editeur, 24-26,  Industrial Country Policy&#13;
the circumstances under which such   boulevard de l'Io6pital, 75005 Paris,  and Adjustment to Imports&#13;
investment might be favorable.       France. 1969.                        from Developing Countries&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   LC 67-28942, 10 francs.              J. M. Finger&#13;
(5ncluding 12 annexes, i38 tables,   Spanish: La experiencia de los pafses  A background study for World&#13;
bibcluiogr 12ap nxe,y),abes          en desarrollo en materia de exporta-  Development Report 1981. Reviews&#13;
bibliography).                       ciones. Editorial Tecnos, 1969.      and interprets recent analyses of the&#13;
Stock No. WP-0502. $5.00.                                                 policies established by industrial&#13;
200 pesetas.                         countries in response to Increasing&#13;
imports from developing countries.&#13;
Effects of Non-Tariff Bar-           Export Promotion Policies            World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
riers to Trade on Prices,            Barend A. de Vries                   470. July 1981. ii + 20 pages (Includ-&#13;
The Case of the Swedish              World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   ing references).&#13;
Textile and Clothing                .313. January 1979. v + 75 pages.     Stock No. WP-0470. $3.00.&#13;
Industry                             Stock No. WP-0313. $3.00.&#13;
Carl Hamilton                                                             Italian Commercial Polides&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.       NEW                              In the 1970s&#13;
429. October 1980. ii + 61 pages                                          Enzo R. Grilli&#13;
(including appendix, bibliography).  On Exports and                       World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Stock No. WP-0429. $3.00.            Economic Growth                      428. October 1980. 47 pages.&#13;
Gershon Feder                        Stock No. WP-0428. $3.00.&#13;
An analytical framework is developed&#13;
Energy, International Trade,         to analyze the sources of growth dur-&#13;
and Economic Growth                  ing the period 1964-75 for a group of  On the Political Economy of&#13;
Alan S. Manne and                    semi-industrialized developing coun-  Protection in Germany&#13;
Sehun Kim                           tries. Discusses the relationship     H. H. Glismann and&#13;
A background study for World         between exporthearnd cncludes that   F D. Weiss&#13;
Development Report 1981.             growth can be generated not only by  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Constructs a small-scale international  increases in the aggregate levels of  427. October 1980. 30 pages (includ-&#13;
trade model that focuses on issues   labor and capital but also by the    ing bibliography).&#13;
related to energy and economic       reallocation of existing resources&#13;
growth in order to determine the     from the less-efficient nonexport sec-  Stock No. WP-0427. $3.00.&#13;
extent to which increasing energy    tor to the higher-productivity export&#13;
prices impose constraints on         sector.&#13;
economic growth.                                                          Output and Employment&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper       Wo 0   erld uank Staff Worin paper Minl.d  Changes in a "Trade Sensi-&#13;
474. August 1981. 30 pages including  508 February 1982. 24 pages (nclud-  tive" Sector: Ajustment in&#13;
2 appendixes, references).           Ing appendix, references)            the U.S. Footwear Industry&#13;
Stock No. WP-04 74. $3.00.           Stock No. WP-0508. $3.00.            John H. Mutti and&#13;
Malcolm D. Bale&#13;
European Community                       NEW                              World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Euroteton Cagainst                                                        430. October 1980. 21 pages&#13;
Protection      again  s             India's Exports                      (including footnotes, references).&#13;
Manufactured Imports                 Martin Wolf                          Stock No. WP-0430. $3.00.&#13;
Ao    DevelopdyIngth Countries       Despite improved performance, the&#13;
A Case Study in the Politi-         igrowth of India's exports continues to&#13;
cal Economy of Protection            lag behind need, potential, and the&#13;
E. Verreydt and                      achievements of several of its com-&#13;
J. Waelbroeck                        petitors. This study examines India's&#13;
overall export performance in the&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   1960s and 1970s, with emphasis on&#13;
432. October 1980. 25 pages.         the central role of incentives. The&#13;
Stock No. WP-0432. $3.00.            major problems and policies are&#13;
discussed, as well as current strategic&#13;
options.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NEW                              Prospects for Partnership:            The Structure of Protection&#13;
Industrialization and Trade          In Developing Countries&#13;
Pattems of Barriers to               Policies In the 1970s                 Bela Balassa and others&#13;
Trade in Sweden: A Study in          Helen Hughes, editor                  The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
the Theory of Protection             The Johns Hopkins Unliersity Pess,   1971, 394 pages (including 5 appen-&#13;
Lars Lundberg                        1973. 310 pages.                     dlxes, Index).&#13;
This report is part of an inquiry being  LC 72-12369. ISBN 0-8018-1498-7,  LC 77-147366. ISBN 0-8018-1257-7,&#13;
undertaken by the World Bank in con-  $20.00 (fl2.00) hardcouer.          $25.00 (fl5.00) hardcouer&#13;
junction with scholars from twelve&#13;
industrial countries into the penetra-  ISBN 0-8018-1500-2, $6.95 (1.4.25)  Spanish: La estructura de la protecci6n&#13;
tion of the markets of industrial    paperback.                           en paises en desarrollo. CEMLA, Depar-&#13;
countries by exports of manufactures  tSpeantnas pesectivas de[ comercio   Mento de Publicaciones, Durango 54.&#13;
from developing countries.           Spteacinish: Las espetrivaselz6 coeri Mexico 7, D.F., MexIco. 1972.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   polfticas comerciales en la decada de&#13;
494. October1981. 35 pages (Including  los 70. Editorial Tecnos, 1974.    The Tokyo Round: Results&#13;
3 appendixes).                       ISBN 84-309-0497-2, 575 pesetas.      and Implications for&#13;
Stock No. WP-0494. $3.00.                                                  Developing Countries&#13;
Ria Kemper&#13;
The Political Economy of                 NEW                               World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Protection In Belgium                On Proetionis                         372. February 1980. li + 35 pages&#13;
lP K. M. Tharakan                    the ProectherlndsmI                   (including annex).&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper       K.A. Koekkoek J. Kol, and            Stock o. WP-0372. $3.00.&#13;
Ilo. 431. October 1980. 22 pages      L.B.M. Mennes&#13;
(including statistical appendix,     This report is part of an inquiry being  Trade Adjustment Policies&#13;
references).                          undertaken by the World Bank in con-  and Income Distribution In&#13;
Stock (Yo. WP-0431. $3.00.           junction with scholars from twelve    Three Archetype Developing&#13;
industrial countries into the penetra-  Economies&#13;
tion of the markets of industrial    Jaime de Melo and&#13;
NEW                               countries by exports of manufactures  Sherman Robinson&#13;
from developing countries.&#13;
The Political Market for              World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Protection In Industrial             493. October 1981. ii + 68 pages      442. December 1980. 91 pages&#13;
Countries: Empirical                  (including 3 annexes, references).   (including appendixes, references).&#13;
Evidence                             Stock No. WP-0493. $3.00.             Stock No. WP-0442. $3.00.&#13;
Kym Anderson and&#13;
Robert E. Baldwin                                                          Trade among Developing&#13;
This report is part of an inquiry being   NEW                              Countries: Theory,&#13;
undertaken by the World Bank In con-                                       Policy Issues, and&#13;
Junction with scholars from twelve    Shadow Prices for Trade              Principa Trends&#13;
industrial countries into the penetra-  Strategy and Investment            Oli Havrylyshyn and&#13;
tion of the markets of industrial     Planning in Egypt&#13;
countries by exports of manufactures  John Page, Jr.                       Martin Wolf&#13;
from developing countries.           This paper presents estimates of effi  A background study for World&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   ciency and social accounting prices   Deuelopment Report 1981. Presents&#13;
492. October 1981. 28 pages (including  for commodities and factors of pro-  the results of empirical work on trade&#13;
references).                          duction in Egypt that are appropriate  among developing countries. Based&#13;
for the eriod 199-1985.on data derived from a sample of&#13;
Stock No. WP-0492. $3.00.             for the period 1979-1985.            thirty-three developing countries&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   that account for about 60 percent of&#13;
521. October 1982. 212 pages.         developing countries' exports to&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0009-1. $5.00.            one another.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
479. August 1981. iv + 112 pages&#13;
Structural Change In Trade            (including 2 appendixes, references).&#13;
in Manufactured Goods                 Stock No. WP-04 79. $5.00.&#13;
between Industrial and&#13;
Developing Countries&#13;
Bela Balassa&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
396. June 1980. 46 pages.&#13;
Stock No. WP-0396. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NEW                              Trade Policy for Developing          RPMS&#13;
Countries                            Can Developing-Country Exports Keep&#13;
Trade and Employment                 Donald B. KIeesing                   Growing In the 1980?s&#13;
Helen Hughes and Jean Waelbroeck&#13;
Polides for Industrial               World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   World Bank Reprint Series: NIumber 194.&#13;
Development                         353. August 19 79. vii + 264 pages    Reprinted from The World Economy (June&#13;
Keith Marsden                        (including references).             1981):127-47.&#13;
In the last decade, the developing  Stock No. WP-0353. $10.00.            Stock t1o. RP-0194. Free of charge.&#13;
countries have proved that they can&#13;
compete internationally in exporting                                      Questlons on International Trade In&#13;
manufactured goods, as well as pri-  Trade Policy Issues for the          TextUles and Clothing&#13;
mary products and services. This     Developing Countries in              Donald B. Keesing and Martin Wolf&#13;
paper examines three sets of issues:  the 1980s                           World Bank Reprint Series: Nfumber 202.&#13;
(a) whether good export performance  Isaiah Frank                         Reprinted from The World Economy. uol. 4 (March&#13;
is attributable to special characteris-                                   1981):79-101.&#13;
tics of the most successful countries  Explores the relation between trade  Stock NfO. RP-0202. Free of charge.&#13;
or whether their success can be      policy and "industrial policy" and&#13;
readily replicated in other countries;  calls attention to points of conflict&#13;
(b) whether the penetration of the   and compatability. Reviews the       Trade Policy and Resource&#13;
markets of industrial countries has  recently completed multilateral trade  Alocatlon In the Presence of Product&#13;
reached, or will soon reach, a limit;  negotiations and assesses the policy  Differentiation&#13;
and (c) whether trade in manufactures  significance for the developing coun-  Jaime de Melo and Sherman Robinson&#13;
among the developing countries can   tries during the 1980s. Takes a new  Reprinted from The Review of Economics and&#13;
expand further. Concludes with a     look at industrial policy and struc-  Statistics, vol. 63. no. 2 (May 1981).169-177.&#13;
discussion of the contribution of    tural adjustment, fair labor stan-   Stock Nlo. RP-0214. Free of charge.&#13;
small enterprises to the creation of  dards, trade among the developing&#13;
employment and the alleviation of    countries, and trade in services.&#13;
poverty.                             World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
1982. vi + 64 pages (including annex).  478. August 1981. 52 pages.&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0017-2. $5.00.           Stock No. WP-04 78. $3.00.&#13;
Trade in Non-Factor                  Worker Adjustment to&#13;
Services: Past Trends and            Liberalized Trade: Costs&#13;
Current Issues                       and Assistance Policies&#13;
Andre Sapir and                      Graham Glenday,&#13;
Ernst Lutz                           Glenn P. Jenkins, and&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   John C. Evans&#13;
410. August 1980. iii + 137 pages    World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
(including 4 annexes).               426. October 1980. i + 86 pages&#13;
Stock No. WP-0410. $5.00.            (including 2 appendixes,&#13;
bibliography).&#13;
Trade in Services: Economic          Stock No. WP-0426. $3.00.&#13;
Determinants and Develop-&#13;
ment-Related Issues                  World Trade and Output of&#13;
Andre Sapir and                      Manufactures: Structural&#13;
Ernst Lutz                           Trends and Developing&#13;
A background study for World         Countries' Exports&#13;
Development Report 1981. Finds that  Donald B. Keesing&#13;
trade theories can help explain the  World Bank Staff Working Paper [lo.&#13;
patterns of trade in services in spite  316. January 1979. v + 69 pages&#13;
of varying and often substantial     (inldgstitcaane)&#13;
degrees of protectionism. Represents   ncluding statistical annex).&#13;
the second stage of a research       Stock No. WP-0316. $3.00.&#13;
project on trade in services.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
480. August 1981. 38 pages (including&#13;
appendix, references).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0480. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
ORDER FORM&#13;
SEND TO:&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS                                                       WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
P.Q BOX 37525                                             or                  66, AVENUE D'IENA&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013                                                         75116 PARIS, FRANCE&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Name:&#13;
Address:&#13;
Stock or ISBN #                            Author, Title                       Qty.        Price         Total&#13;
Sub-Total Cost:&#13;
Postage &amp; handling fee for more than two free items ($1.00 each):&#13;
Total copies: _     _      Air mail surcharge ($2.00 each):&#13;
TOTAL PAYMENT ENCLOSED:&#13;
Make checks payable: WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
Prepayment on orders from individuals is requested. Purchase orders are accepted from booksellers, library suppliers, libraries, and institutions.&#13;
All prices include cost of postage by the least expensive means. The prices and publication dates quoted in this Catalog are subject to change&#13;
without notice.&#13;
No refunds will be given for items that cannot be filled. Credit will be applied towards future orders.&#13;
No more than two free publications will be provided without charge. Requests for additional copies will be filled at a charge of US $1.00 per&#13;
copy to cover handling and postage costs.&#13;
Airmail delivery will require a prepayment of US $2.00 per copy.&#13;
Mail-order payment to the World Bank need not be in U.S. dollars, but the amount remitted must be at the rate of exchange on the day the&#13;
order is placed. The World Bank will also accept Unesco coupons.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG 3881.5 .W57 W67 NO.611&#13;
C.3&#13;
BALASSA, BELA A.&#13;
TRENDS IN INTERNATIONAL&#13;
TRADE IN MANUFACTURED GOODS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                         European Office               Tokyo Office&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                  66, avenue d'lena             Kokusai Building                                       z&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A        75116 Paris, France           1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234            Telephone: (1) 723-54.21      Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK           Telex: 842-620628             Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                           Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD                                                                                                  a&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
I&#13;
I.&#13;
H&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0251-5E&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554837">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/01/1554837/trends-international-trade-manufactured-goods-structural-change-industrial-countries
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/01/1554837/trends-international-trade-manufactured-goods-structural-change-industrial-countries</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1984/01/1554837/trends-international-trade-manufactured-goods-structural-change-industrial-countries</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/22/000178830_98101903421570/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/22/000178830_98101903421570/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1984-01-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-07-22T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Trends in international trade in
            manufactured goods and structural change in the industrial countries
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper examines recent trends in
            trade in manufactured goods between the industrial and the
            developing countries and indicates the implications of these
            trends for structural change in the industrial countries.
            Part I provides information on changes over time in the
            current dollar value of trade in manufactured goods between
            the industrial and the developing countries. It further
            analyzes trends in the volume of trade in manufactured goods
            and the relative importance of trade with the developing
            countries for the manufacturing sector of the industrial
            nations. The commodity composition of trade in manufactured
            goods between the industrial and the developing countries is
            the subject of Part II. It examines the changing importance
            of trade in a seven commodity-group breakdown and covers the
            employment effects and conformity to the comparative
            advantage of the two groups of countries. The paper
            concludes with policy recommendations aimed at promoting
            international trade and structural change.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Trends in international trade in
            manufactured goods and structural change in the industrial countries
        </docna>
        <display_title>Trends in international trade in
            manufactured goods and structural change in the industrial countries</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1984/01/1554837/trends-international-trade-manufactured-goods-structural-change-industrial-countries</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Free Trade,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Inequality,Poverty Assessment</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>BALASSA, B.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903421570</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Trade</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 611</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0251-5</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Comparative analysis; International trade;
            Manufactures; Structural adjustment; Trade liberalization
            adverse effects,annual rate,average
            annual,average rate,average share,borrowing
            countries,centrally planned economies,Comparative
            Advantage,constant prices,country
            markets,currency,Developing Countries,developing
            country,development programs,domestic consumption,domestic
            production,economic activity,economic
            growth,elasticities,Elasticity,elasticity of
            demand,Employment,export market,export prices,export
            ratio,export share,export shares,exporters,exports,external
            shocks,factor endowments,foreign exchange,Free
            Trade,GDP,Gross Domestic Product,growth rate,growth
            rates,imports,Income,income elasticities,Income
            Elasticity,income elasticity of demand,interest
            rates,international trade,manufacturing sector,market
            shares,multilateral trade,multilateral trade
            liberalization,multiplier effects,net exports,oil,oil
            imports,oil price,oil prices,oil revenues,oil
            shock,OPEC,Policy Implications,political economy,price
            increases,protectionism,Relative Importance,Resource
            Allocation,statistical analysis,structural change,terms of
            trade,trade data,trade deficit,trade liberalization,value of
            trade,volume of trade
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP611</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation Equipment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grade Structure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Promotion Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Student Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Capital</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing People</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Trade in Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Political Economy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Political Economy Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Free Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textiles</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport Equipment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Machinery and Equipment</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Education Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade in Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Political Economy of Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>