<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Industrial Country Policy and Adjustment&#13;
to Imports from Developing Countries&#13;
SWP470&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 470&#13;
July 1981&#13;
Prepared by: J. M. Finger&#13;
World Development Report Core Group&#13;
Development Policy Staff&#13;
81&#13;
.W.&#13;
C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
nterpretations in this document are those of the author&#13;
e attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated&#13;
to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations,&#13;
or to any other individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 470&#13;
July 1981&#13;
INDUSTRIAL COUNTRY POLICY AND ADJUSTMENT TO&#13;
IMPORTS FROM DEVELOPING COUNTRIES&#13;
A Background Study for World Development Report 1981&#13;
This essay reviews and interprets recent analyses of the policy&#13;
of industrial countries in response to increasing imports from developing&#13;
countries. Industrial country policy has been caught between the sometimes&#13;
conflicting objectives of economic security for each individual and economic&#13;
efficiency, or growth. Policies which have ignored this basic trade-off&#13;
have not been successful in achieving either objective.&#13;
International Monetary Fund&#13;
Joint Library&#13;
MAR 2 7 1992&#13;
Prepared by:  J. M. Finger&#13;
World Development Report Core Group        Internabona! 6ank Sor&#13;
Development Policy Staff                Reconstruction and Development&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20431&#13;
Copyright Q 1981&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C.   20433&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- i -&#13;
Contents&#13;
I.  INTRODUCTION AND SUMMARY ................................... 1&#13;
II. THE LITERATURE ON ADJUSTMENT: BACKGROUND&#13;
ISSUES AND POLICY FOCUS ................................... 3&#13;
Conflicting Policy Objectives ............................ 3&#13;
Policy Objectives ........................................ 4&#13;
Operational Questions .................................... 5&#13;
III.  THE DIMENSIONS AND NATURE OF THE ADJUSTMENT PROBLEM ........ 7&#13;
Disappearance of the Manufacturing Sector in&#13;
Developed Countries ..................................... 7&#13;
Employment Displacement Compared with "Revealed"&#13;
Capacity to Adjust ...................................... 8&#13;
IV.  THE EXPERIENCE OF JAPAN .................................... 11&#13;
The Political-Technocratic Order ...................       ........ 13&#13;
Planning and Economic Growth ............................. 13&#13;
International Competitiveness ............................ 15&#13;
Lessons for Adjustment Policy ............................ 16&#13;
V.  INDICATIVE PLANNING IN AN OPEN POLITICAL SYSTEM ............ 17&#13;
References             ......... 19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
List of Tables&#13;
1. Rates of Growth of Quantums of Output and&#13;
of Trade, Developed and Developing Countries,&#13;
1960-70 and 1970-78 .......................................        9&#13;
2. Increments in the Volume of Developing Country --&#13;
Developed Countries Non-fuel Trade, 1960-70&#13;
and 1970-78 ...........................                           10&#13;
3. Total Employment, 1979, and Average Annual Change&#13;
of Employment, 1975-79, in Selected Developed&#13;
Countries       .....                   ................          12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. INTRODUCTION AND SUMMARY&#13;
The literature on adjustment by industrial countries to imports&#13;
from developing countries is extensive. By way of summary -- more of the&#13;
literature than of this paper -- the following points are listed:&#13;
a Trade with the developing countries is not a threat to the&#13;
existence of a manufacturing sector in the developed countries. Such&#13;
trade, and particularly its growth in the 1960s and 1970s, has been a&#13;
significant net addition to demand for manufactured goods produced in the&#13;
developed countries.&#13;
o The shifts between industries required by adjustment to imports&#13;
from developing countries are small in relation to the magnitude of the&#13;
total structural change taking place in developed countries.&#13;
* No country has discovered a costless formula for adjustment;&#13;
that is, a way to avoid having to choose, at least at the margin, between&#13;
the economic security of individuals and the growth or efficiency of the&#13;
aggregate economy.&#13;
e Full employment and rapid economic growth have contributed more&#13;
to rapid redistribution of resources than has conscious policy to redeploy&#13;
resources.&#13;
* Comparative advantage matters. Attempts by governments of&#13;
developed countries to revitalize industries in which comparative advantage&#13;
clearly lies with labor-rich countries have not been successful. Where&#13;
revitalization programs have produced significant improvements in produc-&#13;
tivity, the new technology has been put in place in developing countries&#13;
almost as rapidly as in the innovating developed country. Japanese indus-&#13;
trial support has tended to emphasize scale of plant and quality control.&#13;
In products which are "scale and quality intensive," they have become&#13;
world leaders, but in other products they have done less well.&#13;
* The statement "Governments do not pick winners, they make winners"&#13;
is very misleading. There are more instances in which long-term government&#13;
support failed to produce a "world-class" domestic industry than instances&#13;
in which it succeeded.&#13;
* Japan's postwar growth does not illustrate that government policy&#13;
to identify and promote industries with high growth potential (at the&#13;
expense of other industries) can make a major contribution to the rate of&#13;
growth of aggregate output. Many high-growth industries (e.g., autos,&#13;
radios, televisions) were not "chosen" industries; entrepreneurship and very&#13;
high rates of saving and investment were much more important in determining&#13;
their growth.&#13;
e Mere identification of industries in which the nation has comparative&#13;
advantage and the nation's actually being a successful exporter are not the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
same thing. A high school student might have college entrance examination&#13;
scores higher than 90 percent of last year's university graduating class,&#13;
but if he presents his score report to the university registrar, expecting&#13;
to receive in exchange his diploma, he will be disappointed.&#13;
e Losers are easier to pick than winners.    Identifiable exogeneous&#13;
factors such as labor or technology intensity are significant determinants&#13;
of relative costs, but not complete determinants. Thus, one can confidently&#13;
forecast that a labor-intensive industry will not achieve world competi-&#13;
tiveness if it is located in a high-wage country. But it is much more&#13;
difficult to predict in which human-capital-rich economy a particular&#13;
human-capital or technology-intensive industry will become a world leader.&#13;
* The success of a particular policy is often closely associated&#13;
with social conditions unique to a country. There has been a marked shift&#13;
of U.S. industrial capacity into poorer regions, the South and Southwest&#13;
(or "Sun Belt"). Regional policy has been, in effect, competition among&#13;
the states to attract industry, but the overall pattern of industry&#13;
support has been consistent with the export pattern of the United States.&#13;
A major factor in this shift has been the mobility of the U.S. population,&#13;
which has made possible the transfer of significant amounts of human&#13;
capital. The European population is less willing to move, and European&#13;
regional policy has been less successful. The Japanese government's&#13;
emphasis on large scale of plant as a key feature of the structure of&#13;
export industries has been complemented by the discipline of the Japanese&#13;
work force, and this discipline has allowed a high level of quality&#13;
control to be maintained.&#13;
o Effective research of this subject will shy away from attempts&#13;
to find a better way for developed countries to adjust; instead, it will&#13;
attempt to identify the costs of protectionism or of the failure to&#13;
adjust, and the means by which such information may be brought to bear on&#13;
the relevant policy decisions.&#13;
* Some of the foregoing items may appear as truisms; nevertheless,&#13;
they define the intellectual framework from which the present analysis of&#13;
the issues emerges.&#13;
The developing countries interest in structural adjustment in&#13;
the developed countries is obvious. If the developed countries are able&#13;
to transfer resources quickly from one use to another, then their resistance&#13;
to increased imports from the developing countries will be reduced. The&#13;
developed countries' interest in their own adjustment is, of course,&#13;
equally direct. The opportunity costs of not transferring resources to&#13;
more efficient uses are large, and defensive policies put in place to&#13;
protect groups and individuals from reductions of income tend to worsen the&#13;
inflation-growth trade-off and to increase, in the long run, resistance to&#13;
adjustment.&#13;
Again, the literature on the subject is extensive; because it&#13;
has been recently reviewed by Martin Wolf (1979), this paper will not&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
attempt to repeat his exercise. The reader is referred to his excellent&#13;
survey for a listing and evaluation of the many policies and programs which&#13;
have been implemented in various countries. Likewise, the findings of the&#13;
various Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD)&#13;
committees on the subject have also been recently gathered together in one&#13;
document (OECD 1979).&#13;
This paper will take both a more superficial and a more selective&#13;
view of the subject than previous reviews have taken. At a level more&#13;
journalistic than scientific, it will examine several major hypotheses&#13;
which have an impact on public opinion, though not necessarily on informed&#13;
opinion. The following section attempts to identify the background&#13;
issues and policy questions that are concerns of the literature on adjust-&#13;
ment. Later sections discuss the following "hypotheses":&#13;
* That open trade with developing countries is a threat&#13;
to the existence of an industrial sector in developed&#13;
countries&#13;
* That the experience of Japan shows the way by which&#13;
adjustment and growth may be achieved through government&#13;
selection and nurture of particular industries with high&#13;
growth and trade potential&#13;
* That the key to successful adjustment policy is effective&#13;
technocratic planning.&#13;
II. THE LITERATURE ON ADJUSTMENT:&#13;
BACKGROUND ISSUES AND POLICY FOCUS&#13;
The size of the literature on the industrial countries' adjustment&#13;
problems and policies is impressive. The bibliography of Martin Wolf's&#13;
survey of this topic (1979) includes more than 160 items; since then at&#13;
least three sets of conference papers (Bhagwati 1980; Levenson and Wheeler&#13;
1980; McMullen 1980) and another survey paper (Krugman 1980) have appeared.&#13;
Were the number of lines written on a subject a reliable&#13;
indicator of how well the subject is understood, then the industrial&#13;
countries would know what to do to adjust to the expanding export&#13;
capacity of developing countries. There are, however, two reasons why&#13;
this is not the case.&#13;
First, this literature evaluates in terms of one objective&#13;
policies designed primarily to serve another. Most of the programs and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
policies surveyed were not established with adjustment as their primary&#13;
objective. They arose from the twentieth century liberal concern with&#13;
"economic security" [see Nelson (1981) for a discussion of the emergence&#13;
of this concern as a major element in public policy] or, more particu-&#13;
larly, from concern at a policy level with the side effects of economic&#13;
growth. The general objective of these policies was to minimize the&#13;
dislocations (geographic and sectoral) and offset the (perhaps temporary)&#13;
income losses embedded in the responses of economies to the changes of&#13;
consumer tastes and of modes of production which add up to economic growth.&#13;
But the discomfort of remaining in a declining sector and the potential&#13;
gains from-shifting to an advancing one are the incentives by which a&#13;
market economy adjusts. Thus, these policies have -- as the literature&#13;
points out -- often tended to compromise the capacity of the economies to&#13;
adjust and grow.&#13;
The second reason why this literature does not present a&#13;
clear "how-to-adjust" formula is that it reflects not so much a shift&#13;
back to growth as the sole economic objective, but an emerging plurality of&#13;
objectives. The literature emphasizes the conflict between growth&#13;
of the aggregate level of income and the economic security of individual&#13;
citizens, but it does not diagram an easy way to balance the political&#13;
forces behind each objective or to tip that balance toward adjustment and&#13;
growth. Had the literature reflected simply an exchange of one objective&#13;
for another, the task of deciding how to accomplish that objective would&#13;
have been much easier.&#13;
Policy Objectives&#13;
One or the other of two interdependent objectives underlies&#13;
most of the work on adjustment. One of these is the obvious one: to&#13;
reestablish economic growth and efficiency as a social objective coequal&#13;
with economic security and to identify the costs (in terms of capacity to&#13;
grow) of economic security policies and programs.&#13;
Perhaps the clearest example of this objective is the work&#13;
of the OECD Secretariat. An OECD ministerial communique (1979, p. 19)&#13;
recognizes that "governments are pursuing other social and political&#13;
objectives concerning the social and physical environments, the distri-&#13;
bution of income, and the fair sharing of the burden of adjustment to&#13;
structural change." The communique goes on to add that "It is essential,&#13;
however, that these goals should be sought through policies which minimize&#13;
any resulting costs in terms of reduced economic efficiency."&#13;
A second objective of "adjustment policy" is, as stated by&#13;
Martin Wolf (1979, p. 3), to "make possible the acceptance of, rather than&#13;
resistance to, market penetration by the exports of developing countries in&#13;
developed countries."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
Operational Questions&#13;
With these policy objectives always in the background, the&#13;
literature on adjustment has tended to concentrate sequentially on three&#13;
policy questions:&#13;
* How to shift resources from lower-to-higher productivity&#13;
uses&#13;
* How to choose and promote industries with high growth&#13;
potential and a strong position in international trade&#13;
* How to identify the costs of industry support programs.&#13;
Policy analysts have tended first to look for policies which&#13;
served the economic security and the growth-efficiency objective simul-&#13;
taneously; i.e., to try to find a way to avoid trading one constituency&#13;
against another. This "golden path," however, has not been found. Reviewers&#13;
have more or less unanimously agreed that public policy, to promote economic&#13;
security, has often sought to delay the transfer of resources, or at least&#13;
it has had that effect (see Ohlin 1975, p. 11). Recognizing this, OECD&#13;
documents have tended to stress the welfare gains which positive adjustment&#13;
will allow in the long run and the deterioration of the trade-off between&#13;
the short-run individual security benefits and the long-run aggregate&#13;
income-efficiency costs of defensive measures. But to those who might be&#13;
displaced by technological change or developing countries' exports, this is&#13;
a "bird-in-the-bush" argument; hence, in the relevant political context,&#13;
economic security and growth efficiency are alternatives which cannot be&#13;
achieved simultaneously.&#13;
Thus, answers to the first question did not produce a golden&#13;
path to security -- a path which had no costs in terms of growth and&#13;
efficiency. Indeed, it was generally found that "the greatest contribution&#13;
to rapid reallocation has probably been the pursuit of full employment and&#13;
a generally high level of demand" (Ohlin 1975, p. 11).&#13;
To promote adjustment through growth, one obviously has to&#13;
promote growth, and this can be approached in either a macro or a micro&#13;
context. In macro terms, growth involves the allocation of a larger share&#13;
of GNP to investment and research. It obviously reduces short-run con-&#13;
sumption possibilities. An alternative approach, which might be described&#13;
as "economic growth on the cheap," is suggested by the second policy&#13;
question listed above -- how to pick industries with high growth potential&#13;
and promote them; i.e., to transfer resources to "winners" and away from&#13;
"losers" without increasing the total amount of resources devoted to&#13;
research and investment.&#13;
Industrial policy -- policy to choose and promote industries&#13;
with high growth potential and a strong export position -- has not proven to&#13;
be the golden path either. Winners are not so easy to pick, particularly&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
for industrial countries at the frontier of technological progress and&#13;
changing patterns of consumption and possessing roughly similar factor&#13;
endowments and management skills    (OECD 1979, p. 38).  Even historically,&#13;
it is difficult to distinguish unambiguously losers from winners. Vaccara&#13;
and MacAuley (1980) measured U.S. industrial performance by several&#13;
alternative criteria (such as output growth, export performance, and&#13;
wage and price performance) and found generally insignificant correlations&#13;
between industries ranked by one criteria and those ranked by another.&#13;
Furthermore, losers have not proven easy to abandon. Economic&#13;
distress seems to be a stronger political force than economic potential.&#13;
For example, rates of assistance across industries in the Federal Republic&#13;
of Germany are negatively correlated with the export position of these&#13;
industries (Glismann and Weiss 1980, p. 14), and industrial policy in the&#13;
United States has tended to be a sequence of rescue programs for firms in&#13;
trouble.&#13;
Finally, Japan is frequently given as the prime example of&#13;
the effectiveness of picking and promoting industrial winners. The attrac-&#13;
tion of the Japanese model apparently is that it offers a costless solution&#13;
to the problem of lagging economic growth: by having government direct&#13;
or induce the available amount of savings to the "right" industries,&#13;
the growth rate of aggregate output which a given savings rate produces&#13;
will be increased. On careful examination, however, this interpretation&#13;
does not fit the Japanese case very well. Several major growth industries&#13;
(e.g., autos, radio and television receivers) were not picked by the&#13;
Japanese-government (see below, section IV).   Investment in Japan was no&#13;
more "growth efficient" than elsewhere, in the sense that a percentage point&#13;
of GNP devoted to investment did not buy more growth in Japan than it did in&#13;
other countries. There were simply more percentage points of invest-&#13;
ment in Japan.&#13;
As these attempts to find a costless way to promote adjust-&#13;
ment and economic growth have proven fruitless, attention has begun&#13;
to turn toward the less glamorous tasks of identifying the costs of&#13;
protection and of industry support programs. This involves both steps&#13;
to promote the collection and publication of information relevant to the&#13;
calculation of these costs and steps to bring this information to bear on&#13;
the relevant decisions.&#13;
These tasks might initially seem trivial, but they are not.&#13;
Anyone who has sought to identify at the product level those imports&#13;
subject to quantitative restraint will know that this is a complex and&#13;
time-consuming task. With more subtle forms of non-tariff protection or&#13;
industry support programs, the task simply of measuring their coverage&#13;
(apart from estimating their effects) is even more difficult. Examples of&#13;
government actions which make such work less difficult are the U.S. Trade&#13;
Action Monitoring System, which tabulates trade-restrictive measures put in&#13;
place by the United States; the annual record of government industrial aids&#13;
and trade protection provided by the Industries Assistance Commission in&#13;
Australia (cited in Biggs 1981, p. 19); and the German "Subsidy Report,"&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
which records by sector all federal government subsidy expenditures and&#13;
also forgone tax revenues that are a result of industry tax exemptions&#13;
(Fels and Glismann 1975).&#13;
The existence of information on the costs of industry protec-&#13;
tion or subsidization does not mean that it will influence such decisions.&#13;
The decision mechanisms through which protection and industry policy&#13;
are administered usually focus on very narrowly defined criteria, which&#13;
often do not include such costs. For example, under the General Agree-&#13;
ment on Tariffs and Trade (GATT), "injury" in a safeguard case is deter-&#13;
mined with respect to the effects of imports on domestic producers of like&#13;
or competitive products. Offsetting benefits to users of such products are&#13;
not to be taken into account. (For a more general discussion of how&#13;
countries define the focus of administered protection decisions, see&#13;
Nelson 1981.) Although the calculation and publication of the costs of&#13;
protection will surely influence the general political climate, for such&#13;
information to affect the operative decisions 'that constitute trade and&#13;
industry policy, legislative changes in these decision mechanisms will be&#13;
necessary.&#13;
In summary, studies of adjustment experience have been less&#13;
effective in finding an economically costless or politically acceptable way&#13;
to adjust than in popularizing the idea that failure to adjust has signi-&#13;
ficant costs. The OECD, for example, has popularized the term "positive&#13;
adjustment" to stress the bright side of the issue. To be effective,&#13;
further research should concentrate on the identification and quantification&#13;
of the costs of protection or failure to adjust and on finding ways to&#13;
apply these data in the decisive stages of fiscal and industrial policy.&#13;
III. THE DIMENSIONS AND NATURE OF THE ADJUSTMENT PROBLEM&#13;
At the most elementary level, the subject of adjustment&#13;
to imports from developing countries raises concerns about the state&#13;
of the manufacturing sector in the industrial countries.&#13;
Disappearance of the Manufacturing Sector in Developed Countries&#13;
As an indication of the virtual disappearance of the manufacturing&#13;
sector in industrial countries, a labor union official, testifying before&#13;
the U.S. Congress, suggested that, unless the growth of imports was controlled,&#13;
the United States would eventually become "a nation of hamburger stands."&#13;
Indeed, as Table 1 indicates, already through the 1960s the developed&#13;
countries' manufactured imports from the developing world were growing more&#13;
rapidly than was the developed countries' manufacturing production. From&#13;
1970 to 1978 manufactured exports from developing to developed countries&#13;
grew three times as rapidly as developed countries' manufacturing output.&#13;
Such figures, used in isolation, appear to give substance to the union&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
official's fears that trade with developing countries is causing the&#13;
industrial sectors of the developed countries to disappear -- i.e., to&#13;
become vast consumer depots, "nations of hamburger stands."&#13;
A more complete picture of the growth of industrial country&#13;
trade with developing countries is presented in Table 2. Figures there&#13;
indicate that in 1970 the industrial countries imported some $6 billion&#13;
($6,000 million) more of manufactured goods from developing countries than&#13;
they did in 1960. But over the same period developing country purchases of&#13;
manufactured goods from the industrial nations increased by almost three&#13;
times as much -- by over $15 billion. Thus, during the 1960s the growth of&#13;
manufactured goods trade between developed and developing countries added&#13;
in net terms almost $10 billion to demand for developed countries' manufac-&#13;
tured goods.&#13;
From 1970 to 1978 developed country sales of manufactured goods&#13;
to the developing world increased by almost $32 billion (1970 dollars),&#13;
whereas the counterflow grew by less than $12 billion.&#13;
In direct terms, growth of trade between developed and developing&#13;
countries added $10 billion to demand for developed countries' manufactured&#13;
goods over the 1960s, and $20 billion (1970 dollars) from 1970 to 1978.&#13;
From the 1960s to the 1970s, the growth rate of developed countries'&#13;
manufactured exports to other industrial countries was cut in half (11.4%&#13;
to 5.8%), whereas the growth rate of developed countries' manufactured&#13;
exports to developing countries picked up by nearly a half (6.2% to 9.2%).&#13;
These figures suggest that, far from retarding the industrial sector of the&#13;
developed countries, trade with the developing world made a significant&#13;
contribution to the vitality of the industrial'world's manufacturing&#13;
sector.&#13;
As to the fear that trade with developing countries will limit&#13;
job opportunities in the developed countries to the relatively unattractive&#13;
service sector (i.e., hamburger stands), the opposite seems to be true.&#13;
Compared with the developed countries, the developing countries are at&#13;
stages of development at which demand for manufactured goods is high&#13;
relative to demand for services. Because consumers in the industrial world&#13;
demand more "services" than do consumers in the developing world, to&#13;
isolate production in the developed countries from world commerce would&#13;
mean a larger, not a smaller, share of developed countries' production in&#13;
the service sector.&#13;
Employment Displacement Compared with "Revealed" Capacity to Adjust&#13;
Data in Table 2 make clear that the expansion of trade between&#13;
developed and developing countries has provided a net addition to demand&#13;
for developed countries' materials and manufactured goods, and therefore to&#13;
employment in both these sectors of the developed countries' economies.&#13;
Suppose now that developed countries' exports to and imports from developing&#13;
countries consist of products from different industries. We can then&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 1&#13;
Rates of Growth of Quantums of Output and of Trade,&#13;
Developed and Developing Countries, 1960-70 and 1970-78&#13;
(annual percentage rates)&#13;
Developing Countries                        Developed Countries&#13;
Sector and                              Exports                                    Exports&#13;
Period            Output      To Dev-   To Dev-   To         Output      To Dev-   To Dev-   To&#13;
eloped    eloping  World                    eloped    eloping World&#13;
(Manufacturing                              (Manufacturing&#13;
Manufacturing       Sector)     '(Manufactured Goods)          Sector)       (Manufactured Goods)&#13;
1960-70          7.5         10.5      11.1     10.5         6.2        11.4       6.2   10.0&#13;
1970-78          6.5         10.7      13.5     11.5         3.3         5.8       9.2    6.8&#13;
Aggregate          (GDP)      (All Non-Fuel Merchandise)      (GDP)    (All Non-Fuel Merchandise)&#13;
Economy&#13;
1970-70          5.6          5.1       5.8      5.0         5.1         9.6       6.0    8.2&#13;
1970-78          5.3          5.0       9.8      6.4         3.2         5.5       8.9    6.1&#13;
Sources: Growth rates of GDP and of manufactured output are from World Bank (1980, Annex&#13;
Table 1). Growth rates of exports were computed from indices given in United Nations (July&#13;
1980). "Manufactured goods" is defined operationally as SITC 5-8, and all non-fuel merchandise&#13;
as SITC 0-8, less 3. Indices for 1-digit categories were combined using 1970 trade values as&#13;
weights.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 2&#13;
Increments in the Volume of Developing Country --&#13;
Developed Countries Non-Fuel Trade, 1960-70 and 1970-78&#13;
(billions of 1970 dollars)&#13;
Raw                                                                                All&#13;
Time Period       Foods   Materials                                 Other       Non-Fuel         All         Non-Fuel&#13;
and Direction     etc.  Excl. Fuels    Chemicals    Machinery   Manufactures   Materials   Manufactures    Merchandise&#13;
(0+1)    (2+4)            (5)        (7)          (6+8)        (0+1+2+4)      (5-8)       (0-8, less 3)&#13;
1960 to 1970&#13;
Developed to&#13;
Developing        1.45     1.03           2.72         8.28         4.22          2.48         15.22          17.70&#13;
Developing to&#13;
Developed         2.56     1.90           n.a.         n.a.         n.a.          4.46          5.78          10.24&#13;
1970 to 1978&#13;
Developed to&#13;
Developing        3.86     1.88           4.36        16.57        10.90          5.74         31.83           37.57&#13;
Developing to&#13;
Developed         0.98     0.15           n.a.         n.a.         n.a.          1.13         11.48           12.61&#13;
n.a. Not available.&#13;
Source: Calculated from quantum indices and current dollar values from United Nations (July 1980).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
interpret the growth of developing countries' exports to industrial nations&#13;
as the gross amount of output displaced by the expansion of this trade, and&#13;
the trade figure multiplied by the average labor-output ratio as an approx-&#13;
imation of the number of workers it was necessary for the developed countries&#13;
to transfer from one industry to another because of the expansion of trade&#13;
with the developing world.&#13;
Figures on output per worker vary considerably from industry&#13;
to industry, but $24,000 (in 1970 dollars) is most likely a lower-end&#13;
estimate. (The actual 1978 figure for the United States over the entire&#13;
manufacturing sector was approximately $36,000 in 1970 dollars.) This&#13;
figure then implies a gross displacement, in all the developed countries&#13;
combined, of about 62,500 workers per year, (or 500,000 over the eight&#13;
years from 1970 to 1978).&#13;
Table 3 presents some rough indicators of the "revealed" capacity&#13;
to adjust in the developed countries. The figures given indicate that in&#13;
1979 total employment in the United States, the European Economic Community&#13;
(EEC), and Japan combined was approximately 250 million. The gross&#13;
displacement estimate (62,500) is 2.5 one-hundreths of one percent of this&#13;
total employment figure, or 1.4 percent of the annual change of employment&#13;
in the EEC, the United States, and Japan combined.&#13;
In conclusion, the number of job shifts made necessary in the&#13;
developed countries by growth of their trade with the developing world is&#13;
small relative to the number of changes which occur for other normal&#13;
reasons. And the total number of jobs created by the expansion of this&#13;
trade (from 1970 to 1978) is approximately three times as large as the&#13;
number displaced.&#13;
IV. THE EXPERIENCE OF JAPAN&#13;
Japan's postwar economic miracle is often cited as an example&#13;
of skillful economic planning by which the energies and skills of private&#13;
businessmen were closely controlled and coordinated by a paternalistic&#13;
and technocratic government. "The ultimate responsibility for industrial&#13;
planning, for deciding in which new directions Japan's burgeoning industrial&#13;
effort should try to go, and for fostering and protecting business as it&#13;
moves in those directions, lies with the government" (Macrae 1967; cited by&#13;
Trezise and Suzuki, in Patrick and Rosovsky 1976, p. 755). Were this&#13;
rather simple explanation for Japan's economic performance valid, then&#13;
"all" that would be required to duplicate Japan's economic performance&#13;
would be:&#13;
* To follow the Japanese blueprint in organizing a ministry for&#13;
international trade and industry&#13;
* To copy the techniques that the Japanese ministry had used to&#13;
determine which industries to promote&#13;
* To initiate the incentives which the leadership of "Japan, Inc."&#13;
had used to rally the responsive cadres of businesmen and&#13;
workers into action.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
Table 3&#13;
Total Employment, 1979, and Average&#13;
Annual Change of Employment, 19 5-79, in&#13;
Selected Developed Countries&#13;
(thousands of workers)&#13;
Total           Average Annual Change of Employment (1975-79)&#13;
Employment        Total&#13;
Area                (1979)       Employment     Industry      Services     Agriculture&#13;
EEC                103,389          +638          -442         +1,306          -225&#13;
F. R. Germany       25,017           +47           -47           +164           -70&#13;
Italy               20,287          +367          -165           +520           +12&#13;
United Kingdom      24,711           +21          -105           +135            -9&#13;
United States       96,945        +3,041        +1,459         +1,563           +19&#13;
Japan               54,790          +753          +145           +720          -112&#13;
Source: EEC (1977-80, Table II-8).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
More detailed study of the Japanese experience has, however,&#13;
produced a more balanced view of the role of government in determining&#13;
the structure of the Japanese economy. As Philip Trezise and Yukio Suzuki&#13;
sum up their evaluation: "There is no question, of course, but that, as&#13;
in all modern states, the political environment and the economic policies&#13;
that were among its products have influenced economic events pervasively&#13;
and in some respects crucially. To suppose, however, that politicians&#13;
and officials in league with businessmen were able to plan and guide&#13;
Japan's explosive economic growth in detail is neither credible in the&#13;
abstract nor (as will be seen) supported by the realities" (Trezise and&#13;
Suzuki, in Patrick and Rosovsky 1976, pp. 756-57).&#13;
The Political-Technocratic Order&#13;
Trezise and Suzuki point out (p. 785) that there was a "broad&#13;
consensus that after occupation saw economic or industrial growth as the&#13;
road to national revival and independence." As Richard Cooper (1972-73)&#13;
has pointed out, a broad consensus focused on a singular objective creates&#13;
an ideal environment for the establishment of a smoothly functioning&#13;
"technocratic track," along which problems are worked out in accordance&#13;
with established and accepted rules. The singularity of the objective&#13;
allows the smooth functioning of the technocratic track, and the smooth&#13;
functioning of the process then tends to validate the objective. But the&#13;
dynamic of such a mechanism comes from the singularity of the objective it&#13;
institutionalizes, not from its capacity to make decisions across a plur-&#13;
ality of purposes. Such synergism between a broadly accepted purpose and&#13;
technocratic mechanism has existed in instances other than postwar Japan.&#13;
Indeed, Cooper describes the Western international economic system, as it&#13;
existed in the 1950,s and 1960s, in these terms. There are, however, limits&#13;
to how much the functioning of the technocratic mechanism can prevent&#13;
eventual disillusionment with a singular purpose.&#13;
In any case, this lesson from Japan's economic history provides&#13;
no particular guidance for policy. Although singularity of purpose does&#13;
allow a complementary and smoothly working technocratic mechanism to be&#13;
created, the recent history of attempts to reform the international trading&#13;
system suggests that the construction of a technocratic mechanism does&#13;
little to generate a consensus regarding purpose. And without this consensus,&#13;
the technocratic mechanism will not be able to resolve differences over the&#13;
appropriate course of action. Such differences will jump the technocratic&#13;
track and become political issues.&#13;
Planning and Economic Growth&#13;
The idea that economic growth in Japan largely took place&#13;
through selective promotion of particular growth industries seems to&#13;
be based on one example: steel. The Japanese government provided no&#13;
particular support for other industries which have done very well in Japan&#13;
(for example, cement, paper, bicycles, radio and television receivers,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
optical goods, and motorcycles; Trezise and Suzuki, in Patrick and Rosovsky&#13;
1976, p. 794). In addition, Japanese government policy toward the automobile&#13;
industry was at best ambivalent. The auto-producing firms successfully&#13;
resisted government pressure to concentrate on a single car model, and two&#13;
of the producers which have become the most successful, Honda and Mitsubishi,&#13;
stayed out of the cartel guided and nurtured by the government (Etzioni 1980).&#13;
It is clear that the explosive growth of the Japanese economy&#13;
did not result from Japan's having developed (either by government alone&#13;
or in cooperation with business) a scientifically precise plan and then&#13;
having stuck to it. There are too many instances in which firms and&#13;
industries which were not government-picked "winners" did well. Their&#13;
doing well not only shows that the selection of industries was not precise,&#13;
it also shows that the maverick firms and industries were not cut off from&#13;
the resources needed to expand and prosper, which rigid enforcement of a&#13;
plan would have implied.&#13;
In the Brookings study of the Japanese economy (Patrick and&#13;
Rosovsky 1976), both Caves-Useuka and Trezise-Suzuki emphasize the impor-&#13;
tance of entrepreneurship. The latter authors write (p. 800) that: "If&#13;
the general environment was favorable for enterprise, it was, after all, the&#13;
enterprisers who seized the opportunities. It is not credible that these&#13;
talented men could have been closely directed by a cadre of civil servants,&#13;
however well educated, or that their vision and skills could have been&#13;
adequately exploited within a tightly managed, essentially bureaucratic&#13;
system." Industrial policy, or the choice of which industries would expand,&#13;
was apparently more an entrepreneurial decision than a governmental one.&#13;
The most striking feature of the Japanese economy is not its&#13;
government-business relationship, but its very high savings-investment&#13;
rate. (The personal savings rate in Japan runs at about 20 percent of&#13;
disposable income as compared with 6 percent in the United States. The&#13;
Japanese annually invest about 17 percent of their GNP in new plant and&#13;
equipment, versus 8 percent in the United States.) Such a savings rate has&#13;
made the determination of industrial policy in Japan relatively easy. In&#13;
cases of conflict between the views of government and business over which&#13;
of two firms or industries had the better growth prospects, the Japanese&#13;
government could allow both to expand. Thus, an amicable business-government&#13;
relationship was reinforced by the government's not having to make any hard&#13;
choices regarding the allocation of capital. The usual response by the&#13;
Japanese government to pressures generated by tax advantages or other&#13;
incentives for particular industries was to extend those advantages to yet&#13;
other industries (Trezise and Suzuki, p. 800).&#13;
In summary, growth came from the interaction of a very high&#13;
savings rate, the dynamic of private entrepreneurship, and a very supportive&#13;
business atmosphere -- not from the development or implementation of a&#13;
scientifically precise plan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
International Competitiveness&#13;
The role-of.the Japanese government in several Japanese&#13;
industries gaining leadership positions in world trade may have been&#13;
more direct. Again, the contribution of government was not in&#13;
the early identification of industries which would eventually become&#13;
export winners. Government influence was more subtle and influenced&#13;
less the industrial composition of the Japanese economy than the form&#13;
and structure of the industries which did emerge.   Through its multitude&#13;
of avenues of contact with business, and particularly through its&#13;
influence over the flow of capital, the Japanese government stressed&#13;
three characteristics:&#13;
* Large plants,. always expanding the.limits of realized&#13;
economies of scale&#13;
* Large firms, with an export orientation&#13;
* Quality control.&#13;
That some Japanese industries have not become dominant in&#13;
world trade indicates that not all industries are capital and scale&#13;
intensive; i.e., other factors or industrial characteristics contribute&#13;
significantly to comparative advantage there. But in those industries&#13;
in which these characteristics have proven to be dominant, the Japanese&#13;
record has been excellent. Capital intensity, plant size, and quality&#13;
control have acted in concert to produce a significant Japanese advantage&#13;
in labor productivity and overall costs.&#13;
What are the lessons from this experience that other countries&#13;
might apply? The stress on export orientation and quality control,&#13;
perhaps. But it is possible that the outward orientation of Japanese&#13;
businessmen and the adaptability of Japanese workers to rigorous standards&#13;
of quality control are based on cultural characteristics which would be&#13;
difficult to duplicate in other countries. Large plant size and capital&#13;
intensity might be easier-to duplicate. These are characteristics which&#13;
may be influenced by the instruments available to economic policymakers.&#13;
But two important qualifiers should be kept in mind. First of all, the&#13;
productivity increases which the Japanese gained from capital-intensity and&#13;
scale may not be possible without their rigorous standards of quality&#13;
control. The worker discipline necessary to duplicate Japanese accomplish-&#13;
ments in other countries might require changes in policy areas into which&#13;
governments would be reluctant to move.&#13;
Perhaps,the more significant qualifier is that the day in which&#13;
scale intensity and high labor productivity are winning characteristics for&#13;
industry in developed countries may have passed. Such industries may soon&#13;
become very vulnerable to competition from the newly industrialized countries&#13;
or labor-rich countries such as Indonesia and China. Wage differentials&#13;
between these countries and the developed countries are sufficiently large&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
that as they develop capacity they can become competitive even without&#13;
achieving productivity rates comparable to the Japanese. Indeed, Drucker&#13;
(1980) argues that the Japanese, aware of this, have moved away from scale&#13;
as the target industry characteristic and are now stressing automation.&#13;
Lessons for Adjustment Policy&#13;
With a very high savings-investment rate, a rate of economic&#13;
growth, and a rate of growth of the capital stock that is notably larger&#13;
than the growth rate of the labor supply, the transfer of labor between&#13;
industries presented no policy problems. Expansion simply pulled things&#13;
along. Indeed, Sekiguchi's description (1975) of adjustment in the Japanese&#13;
coal-mining industry indicates that the industry contracted despite government&#13;
programs to support it. When the 1967 production target was not met&#13;
"because labor had moved out of the coal mines to other sectors" (p. 295),&#13;
the government's response was to increase the rate of subsidization -- and&#13;
to revise the production target downward (p. 297).&#13;
The disappearance of the Japanese sulfur-mining industry illustrates&#13;
the same point. Funds were raised by the oil refiners' association to buy&#13;
up the sulfur mines and take over their labor force. The only sulfur&#13;
produced in Japan now is produced as a by-product of petroleum refining&#13;
(Sekiguchi 1975, p. 298).&#13;
The textile industry in Japan is often cited as an example&#13;
of positive adjustment policy -- policy designed to facilitate rather&#13;
than to resist the contraction of an industry which has lost its&#13;
comparative advantage. The policy mix which the Japanese government&#13;
implemented was, however, not novel and included:&#13;
* The encouragement of mergers to enlarge firm size and the&#13;
organization of a cartel to cut back production&#13;
* Subsidized loans to support innovation and capital deepening&#13;
* Restrictions on the number of spindles the industry was&#13;
allowed to operate and, eventually, purchase by the&#13;
government of facilities of firms which agreed to leave&#13;
the industry (Sekiguchi 1975, pp. 298 ff.).&#13;
All of these policies have been employed in other countries,&#13;
against a backdrop of much slower overall economic growth, where they&#13;
have not proven to be particularly effective. (See Wolf 1979, particularly&#13;
sections IV.C, IV.D.) Indeed, Trezise and Suzuki (in Patrick and Rosovsky&#13;
1976, p. 801) point out that:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
* Creation of cartels did not work because the industry was&#13;
too fragmented.&#13;
* The reduction of spindles was extended to synthetic fibers,&#13;
which were competitive in world terms and the production&#13;
of which had been promoted by the government.&#13;
* Protection against imports stayed very high, and less than&#13;
2 percent of the sales of overseas Japanese textile and&#13;
fiber plants went to the home market. (The Japanese export&#13;
base was moved offshore, but the domestic market was not&#13;
noticeably opened to imports.)&#13;
Trezise and Suzuki conclude (pp. 801 ff.) that: "If it is possible to find&#13;
in the textile experience a policy of 'progressively giving away industries&#13;
to other countries', the search must be thorough going indeed."&#13;
Thus, the lesson for adjustment policy which the Japanese exper-&#13;
ience offers is that, if things are going generally well, transfers between&#13;
industries will be relatively painless, and policy which would meet with&#13;
limited success under more trying circumstances will be satisfactory.&#13;
V. INDICATIVE PLANNING IN AN OPEN POLITICAL SYSTEM&#13;
One frequently hears that the key to successful adjustment policy&#13;
is for the government to develop a scientifically precise, long-run plan&#13;
identifying which industries will expand and which will contract and then&#13;
to implement that plan. The first objection that can be raised against&#13;
this position is that it is not easy to predict which industries will (or&#13;
should, on efficiency grounds) expand or contract. As pointed out above,&#13;
the past record of governmedts' picking winners has been spotty; even&#13;
after the fact, when measured by several alternative standards (such as&#13;
output growth, export performance, wages paid, and price stability), the&#13;
ranking of industries as good performers varies considerably, depend-&#13;
ing on which performance measure is used.&#13;
A proponent of indicative planning might in turn argue that&#13;
this is an overblown version of his proposal, and insist that policy&#13;
support be limited to a few extreme cases, the obvious winners and losers.&#13;
A look at recent trade statistics would provide preliminary lists, and&#13;
professional analytical studies of these industries would then produce the&#13;
final determinations.&#13;
The major problem with plans such as these is not that such&#13;
technical determinations are impossible: technical expertise is available&#13;
in government staffs or can be hired. The problem is that in an open&#13;
political system such determinations must be enforced and defended at a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
political level, and technical evidence is not a secure basis for a political&#13;
sorting of those industries which will receive public support and those which&#13;
must fend for themselves.&#13;
Those who lose at a technical level are free to appeal that decision&#13;
at a political level, beginning by publicizing their case so as to generate&#13;
public support. This appeal might take the form of pressing for a legislative&#13;
or administrative exception to the technical decision (as was the case&#13;
recently when the U.S. International Trade Commission determined that&#13;
imports were not a major cause of injury to the U.S. automobile industry)&#13;
or of generally supporting the political opposition to the government in&#13;
power.&#13;
In his public or political case, a potential loser (an industry&#13;
which will be excluded from public support) will attempt to do two things:&#13;
* To expand the criteria by which qualification for public&#13;
support is determined beyond the measures of economic potential&#13;
on which the technical determination is made&#13;
* To put forward evidence which challenges the negative technical&#13;
verdict; i.e., which indicates that the industry in question&#13;
is at least a potential winner.&#13;
Even if the government has a solid technical case (in the sense that&#13;
impartial, trained experts would agree that the government's decision is&#13;
correct), it may not be able to make its case stick at the political level.&#13;
At the level of public debate, where such decisions must be defended, the&#13;
relevant audience will not be technically competent to evaluate the conflicting&#13;
scientific cases.&#13;
Such a governmental decision, if it is to stick politically, must&#13;
rely for its defense on the competence of the technical staff which furnished&#13;
the data for the decision. In the United States particularly, there is a&#13;
tradition of disrespect for public officials, and in the United States&#13;
the last two presidents elected have run against the federal bureaucracy.&#13;
It would thus be impossible for a president to defend an industrial plan&#13;
by pointing out that it was developed by the same bureaucracy which he&#13;
indicted during his recent election campaign as bloated and incompetent.&#13;
In a country such as the United States, the technical part of&#13;
indicative planning would be the easy part. Confining the relevant&#13;
decisions to the technical criteria only would be the hard part.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
Bhagwati, J. N., ed. 1981. Import Competition and Adjustment: Theory&#13;
and Policy, New York, National Bureau of Economic Research. Forthcoming.&#13;
Biggs, Margaret A. 1981. The Challenge: Adjust or Protect? Ottawa:&#13;
The North-South Institute.&#13;
Caves, Richard E., and Masu Uekusa. 1976. "Industrial Organization" (in&#13;
Patrick and Rosovsky, eds., pp. 459-523).&#13;
Comptroller General of the United States. 1979. United States - Japan&#13;
Trade: Issues and Problems.: Washington, D.C.: U. S. General&#13;
Accounting Office, Sept. 21.&#13;
Cooper, Richard N. 1972-73. "Trade Policy is Foreign Policy," Foreign&#13;
Policy, no. 9 (Winter), pp. 18-36.&#13;
Drucker, Peter F. 1980. "Japan Gets Ready for Tougher Times," Fortune&#13;
(Nov. 31), pp. 108-14.&#13;
Etzioni, Amitai. 1980. "Forget about Copying Japan, Inc." Washington Post&#13;
(Dec. 7), p. Dl.&#13;
European Economic Community (EEC), Statistical Office. 1'977-80. Basic Statis-&#13;
tics of the Community. 15th-18th eds. Paris.&#13;
Fels, Gerhard, and H. H. Glismann. 1975. "Adjustment Policy in the German&#13;
Manufacturing Sector" (in OECD 1975).&#13;
Glismann, H. H., and F. D. Weiss. 1980. On the Political Economy of&#13;
Protection in Germany. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 427.&#13;
Washington, D.C.&#13;
Hirschman, Albert 0.   1980.   Exit, Voice, and Loyalty:    Response to Decline&#13;
in Firms, Organizations, and States. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard&#13;
University Press.&#13;
Krause, Lawrence B., and Sueo Sekiguchi. 1976. "Japan and the World Economy"&#13;
(in Patrick and Rosovsky, pp. 383-457).&#13;
Krugman, Paul. 1980. "Foreign Experience with Industrial Policy: A&#13;
Critical Review." Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of State, Office&#13;
of External Research    (July 15, 1980).   Processed.&#13;
Levenson, Irving, and Jimmy W. Wheeler. 1980. Western Economies in&#13;
Transition: Structural Change and Adjustment Policies in Industrial&#13;
Countries.   Boulder, Colo.:  Westview Press/London:    Croom Helm.&#13;
Macrae, Norman. 1967. "The Risen Sun," The Economist (May 27). Cited&#13;
by Trezise and Suzuki (in Patrick and Rosovsky, p. 755).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
McMullen, Neil J., ed. 1980. The United States, Western Europe and the&#13;
Newly Industrialized Countries in the 1980s. Final Conference Papers.&#13;
Washington, D.C.: Chatham House/National Planning Association.&#13;
Processed.&#13;
Morkre, Morris E., and David G. Tarr. 1980. Staff Report on Effects of&#13;
Restrictions on United States Imports: Five Case Studies. Washing-&#13;
ton, D.C.: U.S. Federal Trade Commission, Bureau of Economics.&#13;
Nelson, Douglas R. 1981. The Political Structure of the New Protectionism.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 471. Washington, D.C.&#13;
Ohlin, Goran. 1975. "Introduction" and "Adjustment Assistance in Sweden"&#13;
(in OECD 1975).&#13;
Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD). 1975. Adjust-&#13;
ment for Trade: Studies on Industrial Adjustment Problems and Policies.&#13;
Paris.&#13;
---------------. 1979. "The Case for Positive Adjustment Policies: A&#13;
Compendium of OECD Documents 1978/79." Paris.&#13;
Patrick, Hugh, and Henry Rosovsky, eds. 1976. Asia's New Giant. Washing-&#13;
ton, D.C.: Brookings Institution.&#13;
Sekiguchi, Sueo. 1975. "Industrial Adjustment Policies in Japan: A Short&#13;
Review." Paris: OECD.&#13;
Thurow, Lester C. 1980. The Zero Sum Society. New York: Basic Books.&#13;
Trezise, Philip H., and Yukio Suzuki. 1976. "Politics, Government and&#13;
Economic Growth in Japan" (in Patrick and Rosovsky, pp. 753-811).&#13;
United Nations. July 1980. Monthly Bulletin of Statistics. New York.&#13;
Vaccara, Beatrice N., and Patrick H. MacAuley. 1980. "Evaluating the&#13;
Economic Performance of U.S. Manufacturing Industries," Industrial&#13;
Economics Review (Summer), pp. 6-19.&#13;
Wallich, Henry C., and Mabel I. Wallich. 1976. "Banking and Finance"&#13;
(in Patrick and Rosovsky, pp. 249-315).&#13;
Wolf, Martin. 1979. Adjustment Policies and Problems in Developed&#13;
Countries. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 349. Washington, D.C.&#13;
World Bank. 1980. World Development Report, 1980. New York: Oxford&#13;
University Press.&#13;
Yeats, Alexander J. 1979. Trade Barriers Facing Developing Countries.&#13;
New York: St. Martin's Press.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
COMPANION PAPERS IN THIS SERIES&#13;
o.                           TITLE OF PAPER                          AUTHOR&#13;
49     Policy Experience in Twelve Less Developed Countries        B. Balassa&#13;
70     Industrial Country Policy and Adjustment to Imports         J.M. Finger&#13;
from Developing Countries&#13;
71     The Political Structure of the New Protectionism            D. Nelson (consultant)&#13;
72     Adjustment to External Shocks in Developing Countries       B. Balassa&#13;
73     Food Policy Issues in Low-Income Countries                  E. Clay (consultant)&#13;
74     Energy, International Trade, and Economic Growth            A. Manne (consultant)&#13;
75     Capital-Importing Oil Exporters:   Adjustment Issues        A.H. Gelb&#13;
and Policy Choices&#13;
76     Notes on the Analysis of Capital Flows to Developing        R.C. Bryant (consultant)&#13;
Nations and the 'Recycling' Problem&#13;
77     Adjustment Experience and Growth Prospects of the           F. Jaspersen&#13;
Semi-Industrial Countries&#13;
78     Trade Policy Issues for the Developing Countries            I. Frank (consultant)&#13;
in the 1980s&#13;
79     Trade among Developing Countries: Theory, Policy            0. Havrylyshyn&#13;
Issues, and Principal Trends                                   (consultant)&#13;
M. Wolf&#13;
80     Trade in Services:   Economic Determinants and              A. Sapir (consultant)&#13;
Development-Related Issues                                  E. Lutz&#13;
81     International Migrant Workers' Remittances:   Issues        G. Swamy&#13;
and Prospects&#13;
82     Private Bank Lending to Developing Countries                R. O'Brien (consultant)&#13;
83     Development Prospects of the Capital Surplus                R. Hablutzel&#13;
Oil-Exporting Countries&#13;
84     Private Capital Flows to Developing Countries and           A. Fleming&#13;
Their Determination&#13;
85     International Adjustment in the 1980s                       V. Joshi (consultant)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
No.                          TITLE OF PAPER                          AUTHOR&#13;
486     Adjustment in Low-Income Africa                            R. Liebenthal&#13;
487     A Comparative Analysis of Developing Country               C. Wallich&#13;
Adjustment Experiences in the 1970s: Low-Income&#13;
South Asia&#13;
488     Developments in and Prospects for the External             N. Hope&#13;
Debt of the Developing Countries: 1970-80 and&#13;
Beyond&#13;
489     Global Energy Prospects                                    B.J. Choe&#13;
A. Lambertini&#13;
P. Pollak&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554966">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1981/07/1554966/industrial-country-policy-adjustment-imports-developing-countries
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1981/07/1554966/industrial-country-policy-adjustment-imports-developing-countries</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1981/07/1554966/industrial-country-policy-adjustment-imports-developing-countries</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/23/000178830_98101903411327/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/23/000178830_98101903411327/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1981-07-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-08-23T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Industrial country policy and adjustment to
            imports from developing countries
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This essay reviews and interprets recent
            analyses of the policy of industrial countries in response
            to increasing imports from developing countries. Industrial
            country policy has been caught between the sometimes
            conflicting objectives of economic security for each
            individual and economic efficiency, or growth. Policies
            which have ignored this basic trade-off have not been
            successful in achieving either objective.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Industrial country policy and adjustment to
            imports from developing countries
        </docna>
        <display_title>Industrial country policy and
            adjustment to imports from developing countries</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1981/07/1554966/industrial-country-policy-adjustment-imports-developing-countries</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Poverty Assessment,Economic Conditions and Volatility,Achieving Shared Growth</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>FINGER, J.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903411327</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Trade</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 470</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Capital intensity; Comparative advantage;
            Industrial development; Investment policy; Productivity;
            Savings; Structural adjustment; Labor intensity
            adaptability,aggregate income,aggregate
            level,aggregate output,Annual Change,broad
            consensus,cartels,climate,coal,Comparative
            advantage,Developed Countries,developing
            countries,Developing Country,developing world,Development
            Policy,Development Report,disposable income,Economic
            Growth,economic performance,economic policies,economic
            security,economies of scale,Employment,expenditures,export
            industries,factor endowments,Fuels,GNP,growth
            potential,growth prospects,growth rate,Growth rates,high
            growth,human capital,imports,income,industrial
            capacity,Industrial policy,industrial sector,industrialized
            countries,inflation,innovation,international
            trade,investment rate,isolation,labor force,labor
            productivity,long run,Manufacturing Sector,market
            economy,mines,Monitoring System,oil,opportunity costs,output
            growth,overall costs,personal savings,Policy analysts,policy
            areas,policy decisions,POLICY FOCUS,policy level,political
            context,Political Economy,price
            stability,producers,productivity,public debate,public
            officials,public policy,quality control,radio,rich
            countries,savings,service sector,Statistical
            Office,structural adjustment,structural change,technological
            change,technological progress,Trade Policy,Wage
            differentials,wages,welfare gains,workers,World Economy
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP470</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Formulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Implementation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Productivity-Led Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry Clusters</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infant Industry Protection</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technological Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Exemption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Giveaways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Holiday</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Revenue Lost</ml:concept><ml:concept>Cartels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Horizontal Agreements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Price Fixing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textiles</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technology Transfer and Diffusion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Injury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Anticartel Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>