<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Adjustment Policies in Developing Countries, 1979-83&#13;
An Update&#13;
Bela Balassa&#13;
F. Desmond McCarthy     SWP675&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 675&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 675&#13;
Adjustment Policies in Developing Countries, 1979-83&#13;
An Update&#13;
Bela Balassa&#13;
F. Desmond McCarthy&#13;
x;=.Nm1ONAT MO1CTAR, FUtN&#13;
TO!lUT LIBRARY&#13;
.Thvil  l9S15&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright (C 1984&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing November 1984&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To present&#13;
the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been&#13;
prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed texts, and&#13;
the World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a&#13;
token charge to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The World Bank does not accept responsibility for the views expressed herein, which&#13;
are those of the authors and should not be attributed to the World Bank or to its&#13;
affiliated organizations. The findings, interpretations, and conclusions are the results&#13;
of research supported by the Bank; they do not necessarily represent official policy of&#13;
the Bank. The designations employed, the presentation of material, and any maps used&#13;
in this document are solely for the convenience of the reader and do not imply the&#13;
expression of any opinion whatsoever on the part of the World Bank or its affiliates&#13;
concerning the legal status of any country, territory, city, area, or of its authorities, or&#13;
concerning the delimitation of its boundaries, or national affiliation.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications, both free and for sale, is described in the&#13;
Catalog of Publications; the continuing research program is outlined in Abstracts of&#13;
Current Studies. Both booklets are updated annually; the most recent edition of each is&#13;
available without charge from the Publications Sales Unit, Department T, The World&#13;
Bank, 1818 H Street, N.W., Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A., or from the European&#13;
Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'lena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Bela Balassa is professor of political economy at The Johns Hopkins University and&#13;
a consultant to the World Bank. F. Desmond McCarthy is a senior economist in the&#13;
Country Policy Department of the Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Balassa, Bela A.&#13;
Adjustment policies in developing countries, 1979-1983.,&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 675)&#13;
1. Developing countries--Foreign economic relations.&#13;
2. Developing countries--Economic policy. 3. Foreign&#13;
exchange problem--Developing countries. I. McCarthy,&#13;
Desmond, 1936-         .  II. Title. , III. Series.&#13;
HF1413.B32    1984         337'.09172'4           84-22007&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0438-0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ABSTRACT&#13;
This paper updates analysis of the policies applied by developing&#13;
countries in response to the external shocks of the 1979-82 period, extending&#13;
the investigation to 1983. The external shocks in question included the two-&#13;
and-a-half fold increase in oil prices in 1979-80, the slowdown of the world&#13;
economy after 1978, the rise of interest rates starting in late 1978, as well&#13;
as the softening of commodity prices in 1981 and 1982.&#13;
Both policy variables as well as performance indicators have been&#13;
used in the analysis. Policy variables have been utilized to provide an&#13;
indication of the policy effort made by developing countries confronted by&#13;
external shocks; at the same time, the choice has been limited by the&#13;
availability of quantitative measures and, in their absence, by the&#13;
possibility of a judgmental evaluation based on available information on the&#13;
policies applied. Performance indicators have been derived in the framework&#13;
of a methodology that permits separating external shocks and policy responses&#13;
to these shocks; they have been taken to reflect the effects of the policies&#13;
applied on performance in dealing with external shocks. Thus, it should be&#13;
emphasized that the report excludes from its purview general development&#13;
policies.&#13;
The results do suggest some correspondence between policy variables&#13;
and performance indicators. In particular much of the intercountry&#13;
differences in domestic adjustment to external shocks may be explained by&#13;
exchange rate and energy price policy and to a lesser extent by monetary and&#13;
interest rate policy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CONDENSE&#13;
Ce document etend a 1'ann6e 1983 l'analyse des mesures adopt6es&#13;
par les pays en developpement face aux chocs ext6rieurs de la periode&#13;
1979-82. Par chocs exterieurs, on entend la hausse du prix du petrole,&#13;
qui a ete multiplie par deux et demi en 1979-80, le ralentissement de&#13;
l'activit6 6conomique mondiale apres 1978, la hausse des taux d'int6ret a&#13;
compter de la fin de cette meme annee et l'affaiblissement des prix des&#13;
produits primaires en 1981 et 1982.&#13;
On a utilise pour l'analyse des variables de politique&#13;
6conomique et des indicateurs de performance. Les premieres donnent des&#13;
indications sur les reactions des pays en developpement face aux chocs&#13;
ext6rieurs; mais le choix a ete limit6 par la rarete des mesures&#13;
quantitatives et, lorsque celles-ci manquaient totalement, par&#13;
l'impossibilite de proceder a une evaluation subjective d'apres les&#13;
renseignements disponibles sur la politique poursuivie. Les indicateurs&#13;
de performance ont et6 calcules d'apres une methode qui permet d'etablir&#13;
une distinction entre les chocs exterieurs et les mesures adoptees en&#13;
r6action; ils rendent compte du degr6 d'efficacit6 de ces mesures. On&#13;
doit donc souligner que ce rapport ne traite absolument pas des politiques&#13;
de developpement en g6n6ral.&#13;
On s'apercoit qu'il existe une certaine correspondance entre les&#13;
variables de politique et les indicateurs de performance. En particulier,&#13;
les differences entre les mesures d'ajustement adoptees par les pays face&#13;
aux chocs exterieurs peuvent s'expliquer en grande partie par la politique&#13;
de change et la politique des prix de 1'energie et dans une moindre mesure&#13;
par la politique mon6taire et la politique des taux d'interet.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
EXTRACTO&#13;
En el presente documento se actualiza el analisis de las&#13;
politicas aplicadas por los paises en desarrollo como reacci6n a las&#13;
perturbaciones externas del periodo 1979-82 prolongando la investigaci6n&#13;
hasta el aiio 1983. Las mencionadas perturbaciones externas fueron el&#13;
aumento de los precios del petr6leo en 2,5 veces durante 1979-80, la&#13;
desaceleraci6n de la economia mundial despues de 1978, el alza de las&#13;
tasas de interes a partir de fines de 1978 y el aflojamiento de los&#13;
precios de los productos primarios en 1981 y 1982.&#13;
En el analisis se han utilizado tanto variables de politica como&#13;
indicadores de rendimiento. Las primeras se han empleado para dar una&#13;
indicaci6n del esfuerzo hecho en materia de politicas por los paises en&#13;
desarrollo enfrentados a perturbaciones externas; al propio tiempo, la&#13;
elecci6n ha estado limitada por la disponibilidad de medidas cuantitativas&#13;
y, en su lugar, por la posibilidad de una evaluaci6n critica basada en&#13;
informaci6n aprovechable sobre las politicas aplicadas. Los indicadores&#13;
de rendimiento se han obtenido en el marco de una metodologia que permite&#13;
separar las perturbaciones externas de las reacciones a las mismas en&#13;
terminos de politicas; se ha supuesto que los indicadores reflejan los&#13;
efectos que han ejercido las politicas sobre el rendimiento al ocuparse de&#13;
las perturbaciones externas. Asi, pues, debe subrayarse que el informe&#13;
excluye de su esfera las politicas generales de desarrollo.&#13;
Los resultados indican que hay cierta correspondencia entre las&#13;
variables de politica y los indicadores de rendimiento. En especial las&#13;
politicas cambiarias y de precios de la energia, y en menor grado las&#13;
monetarias y de tasas de interes, pueden explicar gran parte de las&#13;
diferencias entre paises en cuanto al ajuste interno a las perturbaciones&#13;
externas.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS&#13;
Work on this paper was greatly helped by the contributions of&#13;
Shigeru Akiyama in estimating the performance indicators, Soonwon Kwon in&#13;
estimating the policy variables, and Kenneth Meyers in calculating real&#13;
exchange rates. Norma Campbell, Barbara Dobrovodsky and Jean Ponchamni typed&#13;
the report. The energy price index was constructed with the help of data&#13;
provided by H. Ribe and N.F. Najmabadi.&#13;
L. de Azcarate, R. Moran, and J. Edelman provided useful insights on&#13;
some of the individual countries. We further acknowledge helpful comments&#13;
received from country economists on the first draft of this report.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ADJUSTMENT POLICIES IN DEVELOPING COUNTRIES 1979-83&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Introduction ...................................................... 1&#13;
External Shocks ................................................... 6&#13;
.   . .  .   . . . . . .   . .   .   . .  . .   . .   .   . .  . .   . .   . .   . .   . .  . .   .   .   . .   .&#13;
Policy Variables .................................................. 9&#13;
Performance Indicators ........................................... 12&#13;
Policies vs. Performance ......................................... 14&#13;
Statistical Tests of the Relationship Between&#13;
Policy Variables and Performance Indicators .................... 15&#13;
Concluding Remarks ............................................... 16&#13;
.   .   . .   . . . . ..  .   .. . ..  .   ..  .   . .   . .   . .   . .   . .   .   . .   .   . .   .  &#13;
Text Tables:&#13;
Table 1:  Policy Variables for Selected&#13;
Developing Countries:   1979-82 .......                .................. 2&#13;
Table 2:  Performance Indicators in Selected&#13;
Developing Countries:   1979-82 ........................ 5&#13;
Table 3: Macroeconomic Indicators for Selected&#13;
Developing Countries:   1979-83 ........................ 7&#13;
Table 4: Evaluation of Adjustment Policies in&#13;
Selected Developing Countries:   1979-83 .............. 11&#13;
Figure 1:   External Shocks (Average 1979-82 % of GNP).             3&#13;
Annex I:   Explanation of Variables Used in&#13;
Evaluating Structural Adjustment Efforts .18&#13;
I. Policy Variables .18&#13;
II.   Balance of Payments Effects of External Shocks .19&#13;
III. Performance Indicators .20&#13;
.                   ~ ~~~~. . .   .   . .   .   . .   .   . .   .   .   . .   .   .   . . . . . .&#13;
IV. Macroeconomic Indicators .21&#13;
V.   Comparisons of Performance Indicators Estimated&#13;
in Last Year's and This Year's Report .22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex II:   Country Economic Notes and Data Sheets ................ 23&#13;
Non-Oil Exporting Countries:&#13;
Argentina ........................................     24&#13;
Bangladesh... ..'.     .'27&#13;
Banglades  n  ........................................ 27~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.   . . .. . . . . . . . .&#13;
Brazil ......................................30&#13;
Chilombi .................................................... . 33&#13;
Dominican Republic ........................................ 39&#13;
India ........................................         42&#13;
IvoryCo      ast .     ......................'45&#13;
Jamaica ........................................       48&#13;
Kenya           .............................. 51&#13;
Korea                                      ...'54&#13;
Mor occ 0....................................... 57&#13;
Pakistan           ................................... 60&#13;
Panama....                                             63&#13;
Philippines'.''.....                                   66&#13;
Philippines~~ ....          ....   . .....   ............... 6&#13;
Portugal ........                -                     69&#13;
Senegal.    .       . .72&#13;
Sri Lanka           .....                          -- 75&#13;
Sudan.                                                 78&#13;
Tanzania.                                              81&#13;
Thailand                                               84&#13;
Turkey...                                  .87&#13;
Yugoslavia...                 ..     .90&#13;
Oil Exporting Countries:&#13;
Egypt           .            .93&#13;
Indonesia''.               ..96&#13;
Malaysia               ......99&#13;
Mexico....'                        ....     ..    .. . 102&#13;
Nigeria .          .105&#13;
Peru.                                   .108&#13;
Tunisia 11.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ADJUSTMENT POLICIES IN DEVELOPING COUNTRIES, 1979-1983&#13;
Introduction&#13;
This report updates last year's analysis of the policies applied by&#13;
developing countries in response to the external shocks of the 1979-82 period,&#13;
extending the investigation to 1983. The external shocks in question included&#13;
the two-and-a-half fold increase in oil prices in 1979-80, the slowdown of the&#13;
world economy-after 1978, the rise of interest rates starting in late 1978, as&#13;
well as the softening of commodity prices in 1981 and 1982.&#13;
In carrying out the analysis, use has been made of policy variables&#13;
as well as performance indicators. Policy variables have been utilized to&#13;
provide an indication of the policy effort made by developing countries&#13;
confronted by external shocks; at the same time, the choice has been limited&#13;
by the availability of quantitative measures and, in their absence, by the&#13;
possibility of a judgmental evaluation based on available information on the&#13;
policies applied. Performance indicators have been derived in the framework&#13;
of a methodology that permits separating external shocks and policy responses&#13;
to these shocks; they have been taken to reflect the effects of the policies&#13;
applied on performance in dealing with external shocks. Thus, it should be&#13;
emphasized that the report does not deal with general development policies and&#13;
with their success or failure.&#13;
The report covers the same countries as its predecessor, except that&#13;
the Dominican Republic and Panama have been added while Algeria and Zaire have&#13;
been omitted for lack of data. It includes altogether thirty developing&#13;
countries, of which twenty-three are non-oil and seven oil-exporting&#13;
countries. The point of departure in the selection of countries has been the&#13;
forty-six country sample panel, which was utilized in analytical work for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
00  01  e-  loe-&lt;-e &lt;&gt;G ^  00*  -&#13;
0  .0   0.   I-            . .0 .1...........o...e&#13;
TI    _  7'0 00'..0 _ ' 4 0 04 0 0 0 _ 7' ...... l0 0 . _2, _&#13;
8~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.&#13;
-~~~~ ~ e -&lt;G-f /1G0_isC _Or N &#13;
OH   00 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0   00 0 0 _0,_0&gt;&gt;-f  _t_ x &#13;
;_!~ &#13;
11C_C &gt;_,_IC G_ _ 1-  .0~O 8. 0 O O 00   0. OO   C   _  f _O 00G.0G. &#13;
_ 8 &lt;.fi;1 1LN g _ 1 _ &lt;g 1&gt;C &lt; g ze _gX&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3--~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
*   *  *   *\\m \\\\\  *   9o&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~gi&#13;
t -  .  .          *'   E'        v S&#13;
:0.   :j * 'E&#13;
.00  :~~~~~~~~~~~~0&#13;
. &lt;  ,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
recent World Development Reports, but coverage had to be reduced owing to&#13;
limitations of time and data. The objective has been to ensure the&#13;
representativeness of the sample while making choices on the basis of the&#13;
importance of individual countries for Bank lending and their participation in&#13;
SAL programs. For lack of the necessary data, China, Congo P.R., and Zimbabwe&#13;
could not be included.&#13;
Table 1 summarizes information on policy variables that give an&#13;
indication of the actions taken by the individual countries with respect to&#13;
exchange rates (the real effective exchange rate), monetary policy (the money&#13;
supply ratio and the domestic credit ratio), public savings (the credit to&#13;
government ratio and the budget balance ratio), personal savings (the real&#13;
discount rate), and energy prices (the average ratio of domestic to&#13;
international prices for petroleum products). Additional policy variables&#13;
included in the analysis, for which quantitative measures were not available&#13;
but a judgmental evaluation could be made, are agricultural price policy and&#13;
trade policy.&#13;
Table 2 provides estimates of the balance-of-payments effects of&#13;
external shocks and policy responses to these shocks for the years 1979 to&#13;
1982. The results for 1979-81 derive from work recently completed by Bela&#13;
Balassa. Estimates for 1982 have been made by utilizing a simplified&#13;
methodology; the relevant data for 1983 are not available.&#13;
Table 2 shows the balance-of-payments effects of external shocks,&#13;
expressed as a proportion of GNP, as well as the composition of these shocks,&#13;
separating terms of trade effects, export volume effects, and interest rate&#13;
effects. The table further provides information on policy responses to&#13;
external shocks, including additional net external financing, export&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
. 0        I&#13;
00&#13;
g   u&#13;
o ~ ~ - N p. E. I  4 sI _ _&lt; a  N I  IN es   - _ _  I I N&#13;
I   b UluI&#13;
U  I&#13;
B 0 &#13;
t   v.  U&#13;
IC    g  g  I  cc _          ¢  _g  C  I Ca  c&#13;
V o &#13;
-  JI 0............... &#13;
~I      G .  °         G       I  C  N-    N 4r ¢-a¢r cJ^¢b &#13;
bi I  A.       -   I I    II  I  II        IC&#13;
e   C&#13;
r.   I           II   II II&#13;
0                C               C. -3.4r-a-z&#13;
00-0                               .   . .   . .&#13;
2  Vr   CNC r.   WC¢   - I .   c ¢ .4( C rt,.   r  .r. ._&#13;
N  C  C   &gt;   EiZt       I~~~~~~~~I  I&#13;
oo&#13;
@ C : Fp -&gt; ~  @  oWN  r  &lt; &lt; e e r &lt; e c X r. r _ r &lt; b m c r. &lt; N rs &lt; r. ¢&#13;
C ~ ~ ~ .0    C 'b 4U _ .4'4. 4_N4|  _ 4.-..re  .r. -4CN.  _ ~Cer.r..E &#13;
F ~ ~   ~   I .I         1.  4    I      - 1  III&#13;
, %  C    W K  0 .   C4ft . 4_ . 4Q &lt;-( __  r. rt4 l~N . C r. C ¢ -   -e  C  _  4¢ _&#13;
Q   ;                       IN"".'4-.4'xI I 5;  r  '7 --  ¢-&#13;
Z ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ I &lt;.          I  I&#13;
zz    ,1,,0  0   .4..............C.U.....4O.4. &#13;
- ~ ~ ~ ~ ~  I rI v        N  0C  II -ec  eNtX^ M&lt;¢,&lt;&gt;a e Ct^e  aI_&gt;Ir&#13;
C Ct  &#13;
_           I&#13;
c0L&#13;
C.  X   K  0 o                     .0    CC _4~ _r&#13;
0  00&#13;
0.  I ~~~~~~  ~~~  0 a  c               I&#13;
N  .   I  Ns  I   I  a  _t  I I I&#13;
rU &gt;&#13;
X  E.-  I  r.4       NN .  '.N-.4INr...4   I  -&#13;
b ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ' -D&#13;
Is  G0 1             I n N  O  C        0 0 4 -&#13;
c-C               v                   c&#13;
cn ~ ~            A:  v     o&#13;
C V       C                      I C  I_&#13;
0040.       o0 0N0.4  G00.N... ........NC.4G .4..  &#13;
}~~~~~~ N          -   /         Jg  cJ I C  9U 9&#13;
C o   0 X U o O C &gt; 0 t O x 0 0 2 O V b :I0 F  &gt;  C  gaCESZPj F&#13;
0                  0~~l  cc&#13;
0        -c                        0&#13;
@1  .-I~~~~~~~~~~ a &#13;
&lt;4. &#13;
z~~~~~~~~&#13;
C.)  00  0  0      0 1  0 ~  .4  1. &#13;
-I  le Ir  .0.  0                    Go4m&#13;
c    wo                  .00   0 40   0  40.I.  &#13;
u  oo   0  00..   .0 0 .000.0~.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
promotion, import substitution, and the effects of macroeconomic policy&#13;
measures on imports.&#13;
Table 3 provides annual averages of selected macro-economic&#13;
indicators, including the domestic savings ratio, the GNP growth rate, and the&#13;
rate of inflation. Finally, Table 4 contains a summary evaluation of the&#13;
individual policy variables and performance indicators.&#13;
Annex 1 describes the policy variables, for which quantitative&#13;
measures are available and the other indicators used in the report. It&#13;
further provides comparison of the performance indicators obtained in last&#13;
year's and this year's report for the 1979-81 period. Annex 2 contains data&#13;
sheets for the individual countries, together with a brief qualitative&#13;
assessment of the policies considered in the report.&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
The impact of external shocks varied substantially among countries;&#13;
their balance-of-payments effects, expressed as a percentage of CNP, are shown&#13;
graphically in Figure 1. These effects are seen to vary between 25.1&#13;
(unfavorable) for Sri Lanka and -5.5 (favorable) for Indonesia. Except for&#13;
Panama, oil importers were all adversely affected by external shocks,&#13;
including the effects of higher oil prices. Conversely, oil exporters gained&#13;
from increases in oil prices. Nevertheless, due to unfavorable export volume&#13;
and interest rate effects, Egypt, Peru and M4laysia suffered adverse external&#13;
shocks during the period under consideration.&#13;
Among oil importers, Senegal and Portugal experienced improvements in&#13;
their terms of trade owing to increases in export prices, but this was more&#13;
than offset by export shortfalls due to the slowdown of the world economy and&#13;
higher debt service charges associated with increased interest rates. In&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
Table 3&#13;
Macroeconomic Indicators for Selected Developing Countries 1979-83&#13;
(1976-78 and 1979-83 averages)&#13;
Domestic Savings/GNP       GNP Growth Rate           Inflation Rate&#13;
Non-Oil Countries             1976-78     1979-83      1976-78    1979-83       1976-78    1979-83&#13;
Argentina                       30.2        21.7*         0.6       -2.1         244.4       162.7&#13;
Bangladesh                       1.3         1.1          7.0        3.6           4.1       11.3&#13;
Brazil                          21.4        18.6*         6.2         1.5         41.6       96.2&#13;
Chile                           14.7        12.2          7.6       -0.4         103.4       24.7&#13;
Colombia                        20.0        17.8*         6.2        2.6          23.6       24..6&#13;
Dominican Republic              17.6        17.1          4.8        3.5           8.0        9.5&#13;
India                           21.4       21.4*          5.3        3.0           0.8       10.1&#13;
Ivory Coast                     30.3       24.0*          8.4        1.8          17.3       10.6&#13;
Jamaica                         12.3        12.5*        -4.5       -0.9*         18.1        17.1&#13;
Kenya                           22.2        17.9*         6.0        4.5          14.4       13.0&#13;
Korea                           26.0        25.0*        12.2        4.1          13.3        15.4&#13;
Morocco                         11.4         9.6*         5.8        2.3          10.3        9.9&#13;
Pakistan                         7.8        5.6           6.2        6.3           8.0        9.4&#13;
Panama                          22.2       23.1           3.9        4.2           4.3.       7.0&#13;
Philippines                     24.5       23.9           6.6        3.8           7.2       14.3&#13;
Portugal                        13.8        17.0          4.6        2.2          22.8       16.5&#13;
Senegal                          7.7        4.0           2.2        3.3           5.2       10.6&#13;
Sri Lanka                       15.8        12.1*         6.0        5.9           4.7       15.8&#13;
Sudan                           10.1        2.3          14.7       -1.1          12.5       26.0&#13;
Tanzania                        13.1        10.2*         4.6         1.8*         9.9       25.0&#13;
Thailand                        23.4       22.7           8.1        5.0           6.5       10.1&#13;
Turkey                          16.6        15.4*         4.9        2.0          29.5       50.4&#13;
Yugoslavia                      29.5       34.1*          7.4        1.1          13.2       32.4&#13;
Oil Exporting Countries&#13;
Egypt                           17.7        14.5*        14.1        7.2          11.4        14.3&#13;
Indonesia                       22.2       23.5           7.8        5.7          12.9       14.7&#13;
Malaysia                        30.9        29.6          8.1        6.7           4.1        5.9&#13;
Mexico                          22.3        26.8          5.2        2.5          20.6       43.7&#13;
Nigeria                         28.3        21.5          3.7       -1.9          20.7        12.8&#13;
Peru                            13.1        18.6          0.0       -0.3          42.8       74.4&#13;
Tunisia                         21.1        22.8          6.4         5.4          5.8        9.9&#13;
*  Indicates incomplete series -- see detailed country data.&#13;
Source: Calculation based on data from World Bank and IMF data bases. Some additional data&#13;
provided by regional economists.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
turn, as a result of the offsetting effects of these factors, external shocks&#13;
were practically zero in Panama although the interest rate effects do not&#13;
include interest charges on domestic dollar-denominated loans.&#13;
In most of the remaining countries, external shocks were dominated by&#13;
the deterioration of the terms of trade, although in higher income countries&#13;
interest rate effects also assumed importance. In the large majority of&#13;
cases, export shortfalls were rather small and Sudan actually derived a&#13;
benefit from a slight acceleration of world demand for its principal export,&#13;
cotton. Exceptions are Jamaica, that suffered from adverse world market&#13;
trends in its principal export, alumina, and Korea, whose exports consist&#13;
almost entirely of manufactured goods, for which world demand increased at a&#13;
slow rate. Also, the oil-exporting countries experienced substantial export&#13;
shortfalls as the world exports of petroleum fell in absolute terms.&#13;
All three elements of external shocks increased over time in most&#13;
countries. The terms of trade of the non-oil countries deteriorated as&#13;
primary product prices fell in 1981 and in 1982; export shortfalls grew in&#13;
magnitude as the rate of economic growth in the developed countries declined;&#13;
and increases in international interest rates raised debt service charges.&#13;
While comparable estimates are not available, the adverse effects of&#13;
external shocks appear to have declined in 1983 as primary product prices&#13;
increased again and the gross domestic product of the developed countries rose&#13;
by 2.5 percent. Also, interest rates peaked in mid-1982, and declined to a&#13;
considerable extent in 1983. Further increases in primary product prices and&#13;
the acceleration of economic growth in the developed countries have benefited&#13;
developing economies in 1984, but they have suffered the effect of higher&#13;
interest rates.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9-&#13;
Policy Variables&#13;
Countries may use a variety of measures to adjust to adverse external&#13;
shocks. Policy actions that may be undertaken for this purpose include&#13;
devaluing the exchange rate, applying restrictive monetary policies, limiting&#13;
the government's reliance on domestic financial resources, contracting public&#13;
expenditures raising real interest rates, increasing petroleum prices, and&#13;
modifying agricultural price and trade policies.&#13;
While countries with large favorable external shocks do not need to&#13;
devalue their currencies, they are well-advised to avoid the application of&#13;
expansionary measures, lest inflation accelerate and the balance-of-payments&#13;
surplus turns into a deficit. Also, higher real interest rates are called for&#13;
to encourage domestic savings while agricultural price policies and trade&#13;
policies should contribute to efficient resource allocation and to the&#13;
establishment of a well-balanced economic structure.&#13;
These considerations indicate that the evaluation of policy actions&#13;
has to depend on the character of external shocks. In assigning numerical&#13;
values to particular policies, account has further been taken of special&#13;
circumstances in the country concerned whenever the relevant information was&#13;
available.&#13;
In Brazil, for example, a 25 percent devaluation in 1979 was&#13;
accompanied by commensurate reductions in export subsidies and import&#13;
surcharges, although export subsidies were subsequently reinstated.. In turn,&#13;
in Yugoslavia the exchange rate had been to a considerable extent overvalued&#13;
in 1976-78, and the overvaluation was only partly remedied by the subsequent&#13;
devaluation. Finally, given the fixity of their exchange rate, the real&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
exchange rate variable reflects the effects of anti-inflationary efforts in&#13;
the Ivory Coast and Senegal.&#13;
Table 4 shows the numerical values assigned to particular policy&#13;
actions taken by individual countries. This has been done by reference to&#13;
changes in policies as between 1976-78 and 1979-83, with further consideration&#13;
given to trends within the latter period. In the evaluation, account has also&#13;
been taken of the absolute levels of the government budget deficit, real&#13;
interest rates, and domestic energy prices.&#13;
In interpreting the results, it should be emphasized that the&#13;
availability of quantifiable information has limited the scope of policy&#13;
actions considered in this report. In particular, an evaluation of policies&#13;
pertaining to public enterprises, the choice of investment projects, and&#13;
institutional effectiveness has not been attempted. However, available&#13;
information has been utilized to assign numerical values to agricultural price&#13;
policies and trade policies.&#13;
Among non-oil countries, the results show Turkey to have made by far&#13;
the greatest policy efforts, reflecting the effects of the January 1980&#13;
reform. It was followed by Thailand and Korea, although in the latter case&#13;
the policies applied deteriorated for a time. In turn, policy performance was&#13;
the poorest in Sudan, Tanzania, and Argentina, and the Dominican Republic.&#13;
At the same time, one finds little evidence of a correlation between&#13;
the size of external shocks and the magnitude of the policy effort. Sri Lanka&#13;
and Jamaica that suffered the largest external shocks made mediocre adjustment&#13;
efforts, notwithstanding their announced reform objectives. In the next group&#13;
in terms of the size of external shocks, Tanzania gets high negative ratings&#13;
as far as adjustment policies are concerned, Kenya apparently made little&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11| -&#13;
-H&#13;
0&#13;
0 8 ,,  +     +  +    +      +&#13;
-  0&#13;
V 0&#13;
Ai 4&#13;
C &#13;
a~~~~~~   C;  + C       CH+C;     +C&#13;
V -  -4 V.ZI   ,C+C             + o _  + &#13;
Cc&#13;
E  &gt;;           - )  C C _f C-   C  C   C D C  G  -S__CNc  C4 Cq O   .. ..&#13;
zD  gL  _,   + 0  I  I    +  +    +              X&#13;
1-4&#13;
I          -C 4   C  .JC C  CC 0 C4 0e'JC.-   C   C C  C .  .  ..&#13;
c  0                                     +   ++~~~~~++ &#13;
Z     I4 I V&#13;
C   o   C - C  C ---- -  0 - --  0  _  C - C  _ CC C  c-&#13;
I E      ++ I+           I  I I+ +      +    _&#13;
o  rr&#13;
*0  I~~~~&#13;
C~~~~~~~~~ 0C CCC--__C____-_C___       _______ 0C  --&#13;
t  1i:  I   &gt;- s1.,  +   I  I +  +  +  I+  I +  +  I+  +  + +  +  II+ +&#13;
0 ~~~~~  0~0&#13;
0             CD         C- ~- - - - _   -  - - - &#13;
CD  t  Q {L X   I  I ~~~~+  +  I + I I+  I II+  II+  + II II+&#13;
z  I  0u&#13;
PC   A&#13;
ZI U U 4&#13;
co           I   I 1 0  1 +  I  I  +   1  0  1 +  +  I I I  0&#13;
00J&#13;
1-4 ~ u1&#13;
4 t        C       - -        C             C&#13;
.&gt; &gt; S  o   *CN *6  C4 ___O-_ .__o C N * &#13;
0     g   0  1   +     +         I  +  + I&#13;
p-  u&#13;
&lt; : ~ ~ ~ C I C J N 0 C ' C'             C J ' C J&#13;
&gt;~~~~~ 4             -C -   -SC  _ O_C DS -   -   -  CD es  N   C C &#13;
0      + t   I .+  . .   +  +.  I I. .  I .+&#13;
I  0&#13;
Vc 6&#13;
I  .X OH  -ic  e-4 O-00 C00-CCD  0 0_-__-C &#13;
u  0   ++ +             + +  I I + +  + + I +&#13;
I CU&#13;
u~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
U U                           0&#13;
-H ~ ~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
I~~~~~~~ C   0 0        --Oo &#13;
I~~~~~-  4J 0  -4  -H _ N  _6 bJ _  O _ O1 'A C  O  _  O  1_tH &#13;
X a;4                         0 I +  +  I  I  I  I  &#13;
4 V        0        bl&#13;
O  .t    0w       0         0  44&#13;
Cz  0o U   C   0   C   0    -,  9.  0&#13;
PA "U   4     A0 0 Ao0  A 04  C  0  C  0  °  0-  0  0&#13;
O4  C-O  .0 uEC  u4.vle * aOu 0 C C   OJ Wv O Pu  a&#13;
I  GeUtO N HO  &lt;4  -0 &gt;44U 0  VU0 N  H , O Op.00-_40=&#13;
zo  $O0.4- $ S                H U  oa o- Oui oX0N  v -4 0 f  &gt;l&lt; &gt;  OO Z &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
adjustment effort, while Korea followed appropriate policies in the second&#13;
half of the period. Finally, in the middle group in terms of external shocks,&#13;
the favorable appraisal of the policy stance of Turkey and Thailand are&#13;
contrasted with a negative evaluation of policy efforts in Morocco and, to a&#13;
lesser extent, in Colombia.&#13;
Among oil-exporters, Peru and Tunisia appear to have made some effort&#13;
at policy improvements on the basis of the criteria utilized. In turn,&#13;
Nigeria and Mexico have overwhelmingly negative scores, with Egypt being not&#13;
far behind.&#13;
Performance Indicators&#13;
Under the methodology applied, the balance-of-payments effects of&#13;
policy responses to external shocks, used in this report as performance&#13;
indicators, add up to the balance-of-payments effects of external shocks.&#13;
Correspondingly, one cannot meaningfully relate the performance indicators to&#13;
the size of external shocks; rather, these have to be appraised on their own&#13;
merits.&#13;
In evaluating performance indicators for non-oil countries, increases&#13;
in export market shares have been assigned relatively high values. This&#13;
choice reflects the desirability of domestic adjustment to adverse external&#13;
shocks through increases in output as well as the advantages of outward-&#13;
oriented trade policies. Positive (negative) values of 2 and 1 have been&#13;
assigned in cases when increases (decreases) in export shares exceeded 20 and&#13;
10 percent, respectively, of actual exports.&#13;
In regard to import substitution in fuels and in non-fuel products,&#13;
positive (negative) values of 2 and 1 have been assigned, depending on whether&#13;
positive (negative) import substitution surpassed 40 to 20 percent of actual&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-13 -&#13;
imports, and a simple average of the two values has been taken. These values&#13;
have been adjusted upwards in cases where there is evidence that increases in&#13;
imports were due to a serious effort at trade liberalization (India, Sri&#13;
Lanka, Pakistan, Thailand, and Jamaica); they have been adjusted downwards in&#13;
cases when reductions in imports were the result of an increased bias against&#13;
imports due to higher protection (Morocco) or were due to the scarcity of&#13;
foreign exchange (Tanzania). Finally, a positive (negative) value of 1 has&#13;
been assigned in cases when macroeconomic policies led to a reduction&#13;
(increase) in imports by over 20 percent.&#13;
The described procedure has been modified in the case of oil-&#13;
exporting countries. For one thing, export and import substitution efforts&#13;
have been measured in regard to non-fuel products only; for another thing, no&#13;
value has been assigned to import savings resulting from macroeconomic&#13;
policies as the countries in question could utilize increased oil earnings to&#13;
accelerate the rate of economic growth.&#13;
Among non-oil countries, the performance criteria utilized show&#13;
Turkey to have been the most successful, followed by Brazil, Thailand, and the&#13;
Philippines, whereas negative scores predominated in the case of Sudan, India,&#13;
and the Dominican Republic. Among oil exporting countries, performance scores&#13;
were negative in Mexico and Egypt; they averaged zero elsewhere.&#13;
It will be observed that, despite their positive performance scores,&#13;
Brazil and the Philippines have encountered financial difficulties while such&#13;
difficulties have not arisen in India that has negative performance scores.&#13;
In the first two cases, the recent difficulties find their origin in the&#13;
inappropriate policies followed in the 1973-78 period of external shocks that&#13;
led to the high indebtedness of the countries concerned. There may also be a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
time lag between the policies applied after 1978 and performance, giving rise&#13;
to a conflict between the two as noted below. A time lag may also have been&#13;
operating in India, except that in this case good policies and poor&#13;
performance are shown by the indicators reported in Table 4.&#13;
Policies vs. Performance&#13;
One cannot expect to find a strong correlation between policy&#13;
variables and performance indicators. For one thing, policy changes affect&#13;
performance with a time lag, yet data for the latter are available for a&#13;
shorter period. For another thing, there are differences in coverage between&#13;
the two.&#13;
While exchange rate policies, monetary policies, policies pertaining&#13;
to public and private savings, the pricing of energy and agricultural&#13;
products, and trade policies affect exports and import substitution, these are&#13;
also importantly influenced by other policies, including those pertaining to&#13;
public enterprises and the choice of investment projects, which have not been&#13;
considered in the report. In turn, the macroeconomic policies applied receive&#13;
considerable weight in evaluating the policy actions but less so among the&#13;
performance indicators.&#13;
Nevertheless, the results for individual countries indicate the&#13;
existence of correspondence between the policy variables and the performance&#13;
indicators. Thus, Turkey is in first place in regard to policy variables as&#13;
well as performance indicators, and Korea and Thailand also have relatively&#13;
high scores in regards to both. However, the Philippines and Brazil had&#13;
positive performance scores, although they were in the middle range as far as&#13;
policies are concerned.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
In turn, Sudan ranks last in terms of both policy variables and&#13;
performance indicators. Tanzania and Argentina immediately follow Sudan in&#13;
terms of policy variables while showing a less favorable performance.&#13;
Finally, as noted above, positive scores on policy variables are associated&#13;
with low performance rating of India in terms of our indicators.&#13;
Statistical Tests of the Relationship&#13;
between Policy Variables and Performance Indicators&#13;
Statistical tests reinforce the conclusions obtained for individual&#13;
countries as to the existence of a correspondence between policy variables and&#13;
performance indicators. Thus, in the 30 country sample, the Spearman rank&#13;
correlation coefficient is 0.65, statistically significant at the 1 percent&#13;
level, between country averages of policy variables and performance&#13;
indicators. The results are not affected if the oil exporting countries are&#13;
excluded from the calculations.&#13;
For further analysis with individual policy variables, countries with&#13;
negative (favorable) external shocks have been deleted. Countries with small&#13;
unfavorable external shocks, accounting for 1 percent of GNP or less, have&#13;
also been omitted as the ratios of policy responses to external shocks are&#13;
exaggerated in this case.&#13;
We have set out to explain intercountry differences in domestic&#13;
adjustment in terms of the individual policy variables. Domestic adjustment&#13;
(DA) has been defined as the ratio of the sum of the balance-of-payments&#13;
effects of export promotion, import substitution, and macroeconomic policies&#13;
to the balance-of-payments effects of external shocks. The relevant&#13;
information is provided in Table 3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
The best equation, measured in terms of the adjusted coefficient of&#13;
determination, is shown in (1). The adjusted R2 is 0.46 and all the&#13;
regression coefficients have the expected positive sign. The energy price&#13;
variable is statistically significant at the 1 percent level, the exchange&#13;
rate policy (ERP) variable at the 5 percent level while the monetary policy&#13;
(MP) and interest rate policy (IRP) variables do not reach the 10 percent&#13;
level of significance. The result obtained in regard to the energy price&#13;
variable is of special interest since energy policy has been neglected in&#13;
macroeconomic investigations of developing countries.&#13;
(1)       DA = 53.570 + 26.553ERP + 17.601 MP + 16.965 IRP + 34.661 EPP&#13;
(4.12)   (2.40)       (1.55)      (1.54)       (3.44)&#13;
R + 0.463&#13;
Concluding Remarks&#13;
This report has examined the policies applied by thirty developing&#13;
countries during the 1979-83 period of external shocks, utilizing information&#13;
on particular policy variables and performance criteria. The results do not&#13;
show the existence of any particular relationship between the magnitude of&#13;
external shocks and the extent of the policy effort. In turn, there is&#13;
evidence of a correspondence between policy variables and performance&#13;
indicators. In particular, intercountry differences in domestic adjustment&#13;
are explained by differences in energy price policy, exchange rate policy and,&#13;
to a lesser extent, monetary policy and interest rate policy.&#13;
The limitations of the analysis should be emphasized. To begin with,&#13;
no attempt has been made to distinguish between permanent and temporary&#13;
shocks. Furthermore, the investigation has excluded variables which could not&#13;
be readily quantified, and a judgmental element has necessarily entered in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
interpretation of all the policy variables and performance indicators. Such&#13;
has been the case in particular in the evaluation of agricultural price policy&#13;
and trade policy, for which quantitative measures are not available.&#13;
Also, the performance indicators and several of the policy variables&#13;
have been defined in terms of changes compared to the base period, even though&#13;
this period may not have represented an equilibrium position. For example,&#13;
the exchange rate might have been out of line in the base period. In turn,&#13;
countries that had already deflated their economies may have found it&#13;
difficult to apply further deflationary measures whereas countries which ha-d&#13;
substantial foreign exchange reserves may have been able to avoid taking&#13;
further contractionary measures.&#13;
Finally, one should emphasize the interdependence of the policy&#13;
measures applied. It is not sufficient to provide subsidies to agricultural&#13;
exports, for example, if these are offset by an overvalued exchange rate or if&#13;
exports are constrained by the limited availability of imported inputs. Also,&#13;
the effects of a realistic exchange rate policy may be negated by an&#13;
inappropriate fiscal or monetary policy. These considerations, then, indicate&#13;
the need for devising appropriate policy packages.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
Annex I&#13;
EXPLANATION OF VARIABLES USED IN&#13;
EVALUATING STRUCTURAL ADJUSTMENT EFFORTS&#13;
I. Policy Variables&#13;
1.       Real Effective Exchange Rate -- The trade-weighted index of exchange&#13;
rates, adjusted for changes in domestic and in foreign wholesale prices.&#13;
Increases (decreases) in the index compared to the 1976-78 base peripd show a&#13;
depreciation (appreciation) of the real effective exchange rate, indicating&#13;
the extent to which use has been made of the exchange rate mechanism to remedy&#13;
balance of payments disequilibria.&#13;
2.       Money Supply Ratio -- The money supply, excluding quasi-money (money&#13;
in the International Financial Statistics), expressed as a percentage of the&#13;
gross domestic product. In the absence of rapid changes in inflation rates&#13;
that affect the desire to hold money, increases (decreases) in the ease of&#13;
monetary policy, when both domestic and foreign exchange-based changes in the&#13;
money supply are taken into account.&#13;
3.       Domestic Credit Ratio -- Outstanding domestic credit, (domestic&#13;
credit in the IFS), expressed as a percentage of GDP. Increases (decreases)&#13;
in this ratio provide an alternative indicator of changes in the ease&#13;
(restrictiveness) of monetary policy, limiting attention to domestic-based&#13;
money creation.&#13;
4.       Credit to Government Ratio -- Outstanding domestic credit to&#13;
government (claims on government in the IFS), expressed as a percentage of&#13;
GDP. This ratio shows changes in the extent of the use of available financial&#13;
resources by the government, thereby providing an indication of dissavings by&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
the government (for lack of information for one-half of the countries covered,&#13;
credit to other components of the public sector are not included, however).&#13;
5.       Budget Balance Ratio -- The government budget surplus (deficit), is&#13;
shown in the IFS and World Bank data, expressed as a percentage of GDP.&#13;
Increases (decreases) in this ratio indicate changes in the extent of savings&#13;
(dissavings) by the government, again excluding other components of the public&#13;
sector.&#13;
6.       Real Discount Rate -- The discount rate, shown in the IFS, adjusted&#13;
for changes in consumer prices. On the assumption that the entire spectrum of/&#13;
interest rates moves parallel to the discount rate, changes in the real&#13;
discount rate will provide an indication of changes in real returns to private&#13;
savers. Overly high discount rates, however, adversely affect the financial&#13;
situation of firms.&#13;
7.       Relative Energy Prices -- The ratio of domestic to international&#13;
energy prices, calculated as the weighted average of prices for four principal&#13;
petroleum products (gasoline, kerosene, diesel and fuel oil), the weights&#13;
being average consumption in 1975 in oil-importing and in oil-exporting&#13;
countries, respectively. Increases (decreases) in this ratio may be taken to&#13;
indicate increases (decreases) in the effort made to conserve energy.&#13;
II. Balance-of-Payments Effects of External Shocks&#13;
1.       External Shocks -- The balance-of-payments effects of external&#13;
shocks, expressed as a percentage of GNP. They are decomposed into terms of&#13;
trade, export volume, and interest rate effects, each of which is expressed as&#13;
a proportion of the balance-of-payments effects of external shocks.&#13;
2.       Terms of Trade Effects -- The effects of changes in the relative&#13;
prices of imports and exports on the cost of imports, compared to the 1976-78&#13;
base period.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
3.       Export Volume Effects -- The effects of changes in the growth of&#13;
world demand as between the 1963-73 and the 1978-81 periods on the country's&#13;
exports, assuming the maintenance of 1976-78 world market shares in regard to&#13;
agricultural products, non-fuel minerals, fuels, and manufactured goods.&#13;
4.       Interest Rate Effects -- The effects of increases in Euro-market&#13;
interest rates, compared to the 1976-78 base period, on the country's net&#13;
interest payments shown in balance-of-payments statistics.&#13;
III. Performance Indicators&#13;
A. Balance-of-Payments Effects of Policy Responses to External Shocks&#13;
(expressed as a proportion of the balance-of-payments effects of external&#13;
shocks)&#13;
1.       Net Additional External Financing -- The extent of net external&#13;
financing over and above that derived on the basis of import and export trends&#13;
in the years 1963-73, applied to the data of the 1976-78 base period.&#13;
Indicates the relative importance of relying on external financing in response&#13;
to external shocks.&#13;
2.       Export Promotion -- The effects on exports of increases (decreases)&#13;
in export market shares in the four product groups referred to above, compared&#13;
to the 1976-78 base period. Indicates the relative importance of export&#13;
promotion efforts in response to external shocks.&#13;
3.       Import Substitution -- The effects on imports of a decline (increase)&#13;
in the income elasticity of import demand for fuel and non-fuel products&#13;
compared to the 1963-73 period. Indicates the relative importance of import&#13;
substitution efforts in fuel and non-fuel products in response to external&#13;
shocks as well as the effects of trade liberalization on non-fuel imports.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
4.       Import Effects of Macroeconomic Policies -- The effects on imports of&#13;
decreases (increases) in GNP growth rates compared to the 1963-73 period.&#13;
Indicates the relative importance of deflationary (expansionary) policies&#13;
applied in response to external shocks.&#13;
B. Policy Response Ratios&#13;
1.       Export Promotion/Exports -- Increases in exports associated with&#13;
increases in export market shares, expressed as a proportion of actual&#13;
exports. Indicates the magnitude of the export promotion effort.&#13;
2.       Import.Substitution/Imports -- The ratio of decreases in imports due&#13;
to a fall in the income elasticity of import demand, expressed as a proportion&#13;
of actual imports. Indicates the magnitude of the import substitution effects&#13;
in fuel and non-fuel products.                       f&#13;
3.       Import Effects of Macroeconomic Policies/Imports -- The ratio of&#13;
decreases in imports due to a decline in the rate of growth of GNP, expressed&#13;
as a proportion of GNP. Indicates the magnitude of import savings associated&#13;
with the application of deflationary policies.&#13;
IV. Macroeconomic Indicators&#13;
1.       Domestic Savings Ratio -- Domestic savings expressed as a percentage&#13;
of the gross domestic product.&#13;
2.       GNP Growth Rate -- The average annual rate of growth of the gross&#13;
national product.&#13;
3.       Inflation Rate -- The average annual rate of increase of the consumer&#13;
price index.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
V. Comparisons of Performance Indicators&#13;
Estimated in Last Year's and This Year's Report&#13;
In last year's report, performance indicators were estimated using a&#13;
short-cut methodology that did not permit the product disaggregation of&#13;
exports. This has been done in the present report that also provides revised&#13;
data for prices as well as volumes.&#13;
Apart from the case of Jamaica, to be discussed below, we observe a&#13;
high correlation between the results obtained for the 1979-81 period in last&#13;
year's and this year's report.   To begin with, the Spearman rank correlation&#13;
coefficient is 0.91 between the two sets of results for the ratio of external&#13;
shocks to GNP. Note, however, that, revisions in the data have raised the&#13;
size of external shocks overall.&#13;
In turn, the rank correlation coefficient is 0.88 between the two&#13;
sets of results for the export promotion and import subs'titution ratios while&#13;
the coefficient is 0.66 for the ratio of macroeconomic policy effects to&#13;
imports. At the same time, there are few cases of sign reversals as far as&#13;
the individual policy responses to external shocks are concerned.&#13;
Jamaica, however, provides an exception as last year's calculations&#13;
showed favorable external shocks for this country compared to large&#13;
unfavorable shocks in this year's calculations. The differences find their&#13;
origin in the underestimation of increases in import prices and export volume&#13;
effects and the overestimation of increases in export prices in last year's&#13;
report. For one thing, the lack of disaggregation of exports did not permit&#13;
allowing for differential price and volume effects for Jamaica's main export&#13;
product, alumina; for another thing, the import price index was in error.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -                           ANNEX II&#13;
Country Economic Notes and Data Sheets&#13;
Non-Oil Exporting Countries&#13;
Argentina&#13;
Bangladesh&#13;
Brazil&#13;
Chile&#13;
Colombia&#13;
Dominican Republic&#13;
India&#13;
Ivory Coast&#13;
Jamaica&#13;
Kenya&#13;
Korea&#13;
Morocco&#13;
Pakistan&#13;
Panama&#13;
Philippines&#13;
Portugal&#13;
Senegal&#13;
Sri Lanka&#13;
Sudan&#13;
Tanzania&#13;
Thailand&#13;
Turkey&#13;
Yugoslavia&#13;
Oil Exporting Countries&#13;
Egypt&#13;
Indonesia&#13;
Malaysia&#13;
Mexico&#13;
Nigeria&#13;
Peru&#13;
Tunisia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Argentina&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       Adverse external shocks increased steadily from 1.6% of GNP in 1979&#13;
to 7.5% of GNP in 1982. In 1979, three fourths of the total shock was&#13;
attributed to deterioration in terms of trade, with the remainder being caused&#13;
by increases in interest rates. Interest rates assumed an increasing&#13;
importance over time and accounted for over one-half of the total shock by&#13;
1982.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       Throughout the period the government made use of the availability of&#13;
external financing. At the same time, the exchange rate was allowed to&#13;
appreciate rapidly, leading to losses in export market shares and negative&#13;
import substitution. Also, the government budget balance deteriorated with&#13;
the deficit reaching 16.5% of GDP by 1983. The financing of the budget&#13;
deficit involved rapid increases in credit to government setting the stage for&#13;
an explosion of inflation rates.&#13;
3.       Accomodating economic policy and an uncertain business climate&#13;
resulted in significant capital flight that further aggregated the external&#13;
debt situation. Correspondingly, the new civilian government faced an&#13;
extremely difficult situation, with little room to manouver. Despite the&#13;
recent agreement with the banks, it is not evident the claims of workers for&#13;
real wage increases will be resolved with a viable repayment schedule for&#13;
foreign creditors and an acceptable growth rate.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
0 m           - 25-&#13;
bO 00  %D C0O oN chO N  &#13;
&gt; CS                       -&#13;
bO0   O     ~ 0e  0-C &#13;
X,~~~~~%   .... ¢  ...&#13;
0 o:    ¢4r:  .*.&#13;
¢  ~~r_  r-  en              eno  I&#13;
z&#13;
~-&#13;
o   o    &lt; e o &lt;   N     e 4 .4  4  X~&#13;
¢0    08    hNv    Z U &#13;
Z n&#13;
~~~~~~t    C14     c        .......o CS U&#13;
fi ¢o _ ..... _ N   .              Cd&#13;
az     I.  NOC4O             4L&#13;
¢ ..                           1-&#13;
¢    C  .......           c   -a,. &#13;
&gt;               O             .... . &#13;
a ~~c        m@@o .. w&#13;
L      co               co  . &#13;
0~~ co,      CQ             ..&#13;
A4~ ~   04    4) bO0SU   0 &#13;
m  X  v  O~i C:             1 Cc&#13;
¢~~~~~d        En  P Q:   c &#13;
Z~~~~c               0 :f f &#13;
;   0 AJ  bO 04             0 c&#13;
&gt;     &gt;   :3 4iw al4 co asi  4 )   o&#13;
2  4k              &gt;o  c O  soX O &#13;
U   l -&gt;  14       to CD      - C &#13;
X-  _4. En -r-  HV Un  .0o  V4  C e&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26-&#13;
W CN'  0  cNLO  c 0CCN LOW (D  CDr-D-W&#13;
0¢0    .    ...  . ..  .  ..  ..  ..  .&#13;
C  |  8  v   ~Cl)w U)  Lot t- (D tN) tN r-  -J IL v  O  N&#13;
4           V)  o L  ) (' D  Cn N -&#13;
W V '     t-     I  _ ,  P ,&#13;
2  ('&#13;
C -  '&#13;
C  I~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
&gt;&#13;
Fo   g  U) ~LD  N 11'C)  LO 11  n tn 0c ¢)in  WC)N  -  NJ&#13;
co r)      w  m  u^)  CI) LO CY ti  co  t co&#13;
SY~~~~~~~ -n I   _,    cn  N- &#13;
CN&#13;
NN a o&#13;
w  40.~o (NWO~     C    C~ mV-'Lfl  O'OTI-&#13;
CY-'      00           0&#13;
0    -   O&#13;
C        N  u n   CO tn  Co CO t- -N-  '   -NU) -&#13;
CD        LO =   CD.  )CD  -~r,V  q'C' m N&#13;
ts       V J en  LO  ID cl ID  t- eV  M  &#13;
oL          0 &#13;
0 I      _ ..    2&#13;
N ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ V  CN  WIDN0-2     -CN&#13;
-   I'a'  Y&#13;
U-    .  n UN&#13;
*       CIY  Cl tn I  c-0  Ln CN LOm 1s   LO N t   4UN N &#13;
V)   )   cl  (t In  U)  t  Nn (D  1-- co N  C -, tN , ED  J&#13;
O   -I         _,,  ,4   , ,  L),&#13;
_I I-              I  I  I&#13;
CDOZ'   .    U - -    . . . -. .0...&#13;
,  _,   L    Q ac,  _   _z ,, &#13;
r-    Oi C   OC O  'x co I)   oC&#13;
U t- WUO    2   0   &lt;U,J&#13;
I  U,  W  WW  t'0r   0.  1-0z0.ILEn&#13;
I  ~  1-W  s-      U &#13;
U  X0WW   I-'-'  U  CZ-- aoa&#13;
..J  U.&gt;- 0D 0., I0 c O   ID CO   n f  00 00  &#13;
I  4  ZO  U,  0.1-  U.U~LL  0 0. .L0&#13;
w I- Lo  a *o w     a Z  o*&#13;
-- -aU.    00 -0.L  - I.   0) i0  C N&#13;
_    W  U  - _ _l  4   - Ol  4U&#13;
W  cc wU.U. 04W-IW.- W  X  I&#13;
0.L -            - I-7ZA&#13;
I    I      -J&#13;
I     0     0IL&#13;
I   u        r      0&#13;
U. &gt;    c   .   F   0   U) U)L M-&#13;
I  Y  Z          IS  tr a.  crU . '~&#13;
I i   0   UJ CY-00 0C  0 0 :)0 a&#13;
I -  O .   &gt;  m . U.  U  0  0 U.LZ&#13;
x   ui x V1  18 Z   O-  - ;-&#13;
I   Z   C - IL   -  UJ  C  Z  O  U7 LOFL &#13;
I   Y11 L1  0  Z     Z &#13;
I  U1  l;J  llJ leJ  C  -O:   CL  1 ~0 . X &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Bangladesh&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       In each of the years 1979 to 1982 Bangladesh faced a declining market&#13;
for its exports. In 1979 and 1980, the export shortfall was offset by&#13;
improvements in terms of trade but these also became adverse in 1981 and&#13;
1982. Interest rate increases have become an additional adverse factor after&#13;
1980.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       In response to external shocks, Bangladesh sought to rely on&#13;
additonal external financing and, after 1980, on import substitution. This&#13;
was partially negated by losses in export market shares and some increases in&#13;
imports associated with the higher growth rates of the years 1979-81.&#13;
3.       In mid July 1981, it became increasingly evident that the limited&#13;
availability of foreign aid would require lowering import levels. In order to&#13;
deal with the situation, the taka was devalued and government expenditures&#13;
were curtailed. A further devaluation in 1982 resulted in the real exchange&#13;
rate rising to 124.5 in 1983 (1976-78 = 100). At the same time, the&#13;
deflationary policies led to a decline in the GNP growth rate to 1.0%.&#13;
4.       While growth was again sluggish in 1983, exports, particularly of&#13;
jute goods, showed substantial improvement. However, domestic savings&#13;
continue to be minimal, so that the country remains heavily dependent on&#13;
foreign donors. Workers' remittances continue to be a favorable influence.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
Ca C&#13;
0  I   .&#13;
o r-0  e  o o          -4&#13;
&gt;     _&#13;
0 0% _ _ X       0 o0&#13;
0_       *&#13;
or--    C 0! c"J  -4      -'li19&#13;
X  I   *~.   .  .  .  .  .. .&#13;
Z  o   u.4j  c's en  o N en -r I&#13;
'I'~~~4 &#13;
0% c~o0%  0 C'4      e&#13;
~~~~~~.  .  .  . o  CS  .  _&#13;
0%%  0%C4&#13;
t-:  ¢-&#13;
0%~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~c&#13;
-4&#13;
0     C     * * ...&#13;
-D   0  CX J X   O-&#13;
co        _&#13;
z&#13;
I-I                     0Lt0&#13;
Xd  X   'z                *  .  * .&#13;
a  ~      0%  - ° ' I       -4&#13;
o~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~g&#13;
0 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~1&#13;
co   J&#13;
*         -4      4&#13;
'-4 l            0&#13;
4.3~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
o&#13;
1-4 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ *- &#13;
o~~~~ 0              U  n  00  o.. &#13;
I  o      c       -&#13;
0  OC I= -'      0     'cmV&#13;
ti  0  0  -..           0&#13;
0  4-JO  U1      c &#13;
CC     4      0        X&#13;
X   so b   o o ao oIn  CSb^  o-   C&#13;
o   e  I   *  .  *  .  *  .-4 &lt;   *  *  X&#13;
0   PO X   z   &gt; t_ 0&#13;
W          E-4  -. &#13;
j-%  -W00   0       0&#13;
00' -0' C   I'u4i&#13;
Cfl  %-4&gt;  " w  0  &gt;4  Z-  &gt;u   0&#13;
C  4)'4Si0   -   to   p4   co&#13;
&gt; - i()  ) U0 0 40)  Ci -4&#13;
o r. OS   0              U u4&#13;
'u             H   U0  -r..&#13;
0 x  0            V0C. 00&#13;
-,      0~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
9~~~~~~~c fi   C; 9     c44&#13;
;       ~   ~0 a* *;             C &#13;
°.   a  c  ,, &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-29-&#13;
W  * -  OCN -  0 WNtD   r-- cFN du 0 N&#13;
CZ           V  Lo  r) v   D  ) :%  - 0  1 -&#13;
Wi rv &#13;
4'       IDCN ,Oo          c&#13;
W  ~ I&#13;
4     *  0  -r LD  co ' 00 0I n u   N U),&#13;
J N * . .         ... .   ..&#13;
0     C'  C ' NU') - Wr-' )   We Ub  (   J   N '-&#13;
ZP  41  *  OJ 1 N  m N - co 0 ()  - N-  _&#13;
*t  I      cI  ,c   _  ,    o _&#13;
0)-  CZ I-I      - C'   C)CM  - L&#13;
-z                  CY0)I &#13;
C.)  I&#13;
l~~~~~~~~l &#13;
0  U  - *  U  Xw   &amp; o O Nc tnV 1N &#13;
(,  CO  .   .   . .   .   . .   .   . . ..   ...... ...&#13;
4 lx       r N 0'1 *  W  CD V- n -  | Ud  -&#13;
1 00  - ,  L  q  ur  .-  C co  I&#13;
46  0     )..  -&#13;
ia    w    r,n-      NN_&#13;
Z~~ ~~~   - el *:  .  .  .~~-&#13;
W   0  0_,)~   fl))000) ~ )0U&#13;
0). *-*~ _q     0 -e  &#13;
o       L&amp;.C lY  UCZ  C')0)0to  -, &#13;
a.   *   uU&#13;
W I    4Y-&#13;
IS  * ) CO 0Lf O   U N  O - N U  1--   r -0l N&#13;
0).  .  Z~ ~ 2. 0   ~ - &gt;&#13;
I-I   W0)r    r=)WLf 0 -U1O-N1&#13;
U .-U.U .  , _'  _  ,  U &#13;
ce  U.U. --I Ir    U  i&#13;
I   Z I   )C    I  I&#13;
I    a.&#13;
_ I    W&#13;
U  xoujw 40-       U -r 0 -&#13;
P *  .  N: )  1  U   1  i- V&#13;
I   W     VM&#13;
U   aM    a..Z  C U   0&#13;
1   t7 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ 1&#13;
*   U )1 U. &gt;  wZ t 0  N  1 U  0 -   -1&#13;
¢,~U-i   a.   Z    a.... . Z........  *...&#13;
..JWUU  U. 2-   U  X2U)..JU&#13;
1~~~~~~ w  LA  w   P.- O-  ..... W  I n  N. O-  el IZ 0........vNa &#13;
*  4La.WWU cc 42  0ea  -i  0 u)W0I-Wi- z&#13;
O~~~~  LL  cx  -c no  MOOMWtOM1 FvN  t &#13;
x      LA.L tg _  F _ _&#13;
I  0  W I4u1-   X i  -  0&#13;
I   ZL~   WI-L      I).&#13;
I    00   2w1w ZLw&#13;
I  -J L.i   aLlO &#13;
I  4  0 U   .i   aU a.X..&#13;
I   C -U~W2~Z       ~&#13;
I   _-  - o.i  0aau-U aa.a&#13;
I  X  )WX  &gt;0   4 ))    4 &#13;
I Y             -  2 t&#13;
* I              M  1 0  0  0&#13;
*   U1    .        a. WZO- -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Brazil&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       Over the 1979-82 period, Brazil suffered external shocks equivalent&#13;
to 5.7% of its GNP. Two thirds of this deterioration may be attributed to&#13;
terms of trade losses, with increased interest rate changes accounting for&#13;
much of the remainder.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       Under Delfim Netto the initial thrust of policy was largely&#13;
expansionary, requiring large increases in foreign borrowing in 1979 and&#13;
1980. By late 1980 it became increasingly evident that this policy was not&#13;
sustainable. There was a swing to contractionary monetary policy, with&#13;
attempts made to bring under control the autonomous expenditure practices of&#13;
the federal enterprises.&#13;
3.       There resulted a tightening of domestic credit, which pushed up&#13;
domestic interest rates and contributed to a decline in GNP. Wages were&#13;
indexed to about 85% of the CPI in an attempt to curb inflation, but this was&#13;
partially offset by increases in various public service charges to improve&#13;
government finances. Domestic energy prices were also increased. At the same&#13;
time, per capita income fell again in 1982 and even more in 1983 as&#13;
restrictive policies continued.&#13;
4.       On the trade side, the overall policy thrust favored the export&#13;
sector, with real effective exchange rate depreciating. Exports showed&#13;
considerable improvements in 1983 and even more so in 1984. This was coupled&#13;
with import limitations on many items, so that the merchandise trade surplus&#13;
is expected to reach $12 billion in 1984. But as exports account for less&#13;
than 10% of GNP in Brazil, even such a remarkable performance does not seem&#13;
capable of pulling up the rest of the economy. In view of the rather fluid&#13;
political situation it is not evident how the country will accept a fourth&#13;
year of recession, particularly as much of the export effort is perceived to&#13;
be negated by higher interest rates on the foreign debt.&#13;
5.       While the initial response to the oil shocks was expansionary, policy&#13;
has now become steadily more restrictive with a strong tilt towards the export&#13;
sectors. However, the overall economy is still very sluggish. Increased&#13;
political pressures may force some easing of the restrictive measures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
o 00  %(C r-Or ,_   0%  n&#13;
(V~~ ~~~  .  .   .   .** &#13;
rS   CS4  _, mo&#13;
_        0_&#13;
_'  Co  I  I     0o&#13;
00   r- 00- n0 m%    7  0L&#13;
C- 4 I  -&#13;
&gt;~~~ ONv     C &#13;
aJ es ~ ~ ~ a&#13;
C,     .....  .   .  ...&#13;
030 co  Ce-          - a  -o&#13;
&gt;~~~ L oo _ 0  , _&#13;
&gt;0%  -~~%  I  - -T Ul Or&#13;
-    C    C"  C' c'J  0n0&#13;
&lt;:~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ - &#13;
-      -  *- I  '0%u&#13;
C^ o CS C£ CS CS  Il ¢~ ,_~ o&#13;
*  . .  . .  . .  .  .  .  .&#13;
I.-.     -:    1   &lt;     Z)  _ -  I C&#13;
0%  -4      -        -~~~~~~~~~~~~-4 L&#13;
co          _ c CS   -   0c &#13;
C)&#13;
03 &#13;
Z  -   .-4~~~~C  C,  -YN -   -  I4'D&#13;
0l a'-*.4% (^) aab &lt;   ~   ~   X  \0  e&#13;
rn ~ ~ ~~~~U  q ) o:___   &gt;&lt;ntr&#13;
03~~~~~~~~             'V~~~~~~&#13;
o     0~~~~~~Lf~~~ 0 co  la.7 'J0  $&#13;
(V  I   ..       . .V&#13;
&gt;   .%    0' 0 0   '-4&#13;
cn~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~c&#13;
O O (S   CS sD e  X  &lt;  O  °° X (&#13;
¢5  cE£c        n o                m sc &#13;
03~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~~~~~~1&#13;
PZ                        D&#13;
~~ aa   &lt;  ~~~o co-o I cs e   o  sc&#13;
-0  -4         03      0&#13;
ea  ~~~~~~~~o U)v- &#13;
!  O_ O .0 0 0&#13;
0Ow --  0 -   -  W &#13;
&lt;   Q N   o - N I  IW   o  ( o W  9&#13;
4-4      0)   W&#13;
o         (V                        o 30.)(&#13;
m~~~~                        ~   ~~ &gt;  X  E i &#13;
&gt;~~~~~C  -H  (D  90 (  4&gt; &lt;&#13;
0.4           0)  4_4       4-     0&#13;
0   C-W W  C     b&#13;
CV  -J V  C     -W.'   U)   v&#13;
; ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ 0~V  -'- CC  (V &#13;
kW)  C  W03  0 u  0 W&#13;
~-  4  OV  J4J0a I  ,4  -,  "-I &#13;
&gt;      1-03'V EC0  -  (V -03&#13;
C   (  &lt;  s  : EX VX&lt; 4-&#13;
L   SU4-J 03U)X   4  Um C0 0 3&#13;
W  a  W 0   0  4-O  .O0 &#13;
aV x CZ UuPea  U  0 4 -Jo&#13;
03004- IT00D rC  OZ (V3  0 3-&#13;
e~ ~~~ C    COI-E EXW4Z.&#13;
&gt;4 - oo4o  DoX   o &#13;
-;  Ug£ac  nAn   o ac &#13;
0 ....         '  ....      3 &#13;
P.'  _ 4 '4s  4'r.  -4 CD r £ _-s -. &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
uJ N  1t   C 0 ZD- v  m 0  c 0N  to ( 0  0o Nl l&#13;
C)~ 0  1    ..   ...       ...&#13;
c        LO  C)  CY  N D  "  Nm  4 N e-0 V U&#13;
&gt;0 &#13;
C t-I&#13;
.4a&#13;
J   w  0 -   000)  0  N-  -w 0  q 0-&#13;
N    9 0    ' 00- ID~DC      tm ONr- 0... &#13;
a  ~  a      . .              7&#13;
N    co acW -                   C 0   -o0 &#13;
-9  tn 0n 1     m        04 cl    w @   * **&#13;
0~~~~~C ^   co 0) C4 Ln 0n UN1  0 tN  0 NUl) t 0 1 z1&#13;
1'-  tOt 0 ~   C| Cf  t  C-N  CNCN  - -  - -&#13;
Ow     a &#13;
_J  Z  -&gt; 0 1&#13;
W- C-&#13;
lSa Q  v  l  0  I NU) 4   /D U O  C'ON&#13;
Ci  _   0n 0      tD  N  N N  - N  N N - 0 0&#13;
4        a   . O O  _,&#13;
co _  I   e DWr-  O  OU  O    LO'&#13;
o  -,     kL UC,  u&#13;
Z    0 N F N {D N  0 U) 0 N -0  r r- t C&#13;
w    c 0 W  L.    U w   , 0 t 0 0 0 0  O r&#13;
0           U.    U&#13;
I    CJ&#13;
2a W  -  W 0 c  0   C.) N -  0-  L LON - 0 1&#13;
O~~a  UC~~ U,)  wu LO Na( C  a  a&#13;
0' 1         IU^  -  Na  N &#13;
*  uJ~~~~~~u&#13;
I      w X&#13;
a  4  I.-Z &#13;
4                 x&#13;
I    -      C)     U,&#13;
0  z  . U.U.  4  -i  --  U, CZ U&#13;
I           C,  -  U7      0  '&#13;
I           21     w &#13;
I     U     W    z   0 U0 00&#13;
*  0     U       u.   a  a.a&#13;
I   O   Q     1z   1~~~~~~~~-C  X  X  &amp;&#13;
U  uz   tt t w    Cc  : I .  w &#13;
I&lt;U    Ww Z1 O ___&#13;
a     UI    a.1  -  &gt;  a.'.  -.&#13;
U.2 4I- WW CZ 42  0  -i  U,wOI- w -i &#13;
CIf JWQO  t7M Z  z zMXZ V J_&#13;
Z C~ 2w &gt;W- W   - Zo   0"-. no  -ow&#13;
*  .  tw.L  U,2 U.U 0  C.bOuwa&#13;
C Z  I.- -w.     J  O -: 0  I.&#13;
*  U ; XLn Za Jw atD I.-  U 0  i-a-a.0Ii&#13;
a    00     2w WWZ )Z  Z s 1wU&#13;
w w w w    fcI  - o. O0  CZ 0a G . &#13;
I     C 20   a  wZU   a. c-   .u. Z U&#13;
a w x 0w w    F      _   0O F -o &#13;
ax U,wXZ &gt;0)(I    4 &gt;-'Z(I  4&#13;
I w     0j   ow     - U     Z&#13;
a    a.     -         -  .v &#13;
I  c    z             -.3 X o &#13;
a  z    o,            0 nwFFJIw I &#13;
I  tY                a. rt wZC  Y &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Chile&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       External shocks in Chile increased to a considerable extent during&#13;
the period under consideration, attaining 15.8 percent of GNP in 1982. The&#13;
principal contributing factor was the rise in interest rates on Chile's large&#13;
foreign debt, followed by the deterioration of the terms of trade and adverse&#13;
export volume effects.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       While the devaluations undertaken in the preceding period permitted&#13;
Chile to increase its export market shares to a considerable extent in 1979,&#13;
the subsequent appreciation of the real exchange rate adversely affected&#13;
exports. The overvaluation of the exchange rate also aggravated the effects&#13;
of tariff reductions on imports, leading to negative import substitution in&#13;
non-fuel products, while higher rates of economic growth up to 1981 compared&#13;
to the 1963-73 period increased Chile's import needs.&#13;
3.       Fuels provide an exception as maintaining domestic energy prices&#13;
above international levels gave rise to some import substitution. But,&#13;
increases in export market shares and savings in fuels did not suffice to&#13;
offset Chile's rising import requirements, and increased reliance was based on&#13;
foreign borrowing. At the same time, foreign borrowing was encouraged by the&#13;
government's virtual exchange rate guarantee.&#13;
4.       An important anti-inflationary factor was the generation of a budget&#13;
surplus. This surplus declined towards the end of the period, however, and it&#13;
gave place to a deficit in 1982 when the gross national product fell by nearly&#13;
18 percent.&#13;
5.       The precipitous fall of GNP reflected the adverse effects of fixing&#13;
the exchange rate in the face of a doubling of wages and salaries. Eventually&#13;
the exchange rate had to be devalued and restrictive policies applied. At the&#13;
same time, high real interest rates created considerable difficulties for&#13;
firms and banks, and it will take a long time to rebuild the financial system.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
CU       co *  0  *  0 &lt;0  -  0  r&#13;
cc ~ *.    * ¢  *       *  . &#13;
SW    -4  ' n  I  cO Z&#13;
w  r-I  --T     %C -4  -&#13;
co CN&#13;
Cu  I 0                    0 4  *&#13;
1-40'   C Liu.4    'cJ.&#13;
to 00'      -IT           -&#13;
¢0 &#13;
cc   ~*  .  *  . .¢ ..    . &#13;
a,'- On n Z aD -  C0'-0&#13;
0'  0'       -C'40Z  '.0    0-  0'&#13;
-~ ~~~~~~~ -D   I~ a:&#13;
en ~~~~~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
00&#13;
_  ~    ~~ _u&#13;
W 0 C^ cq   C9           r%  L~   rC&#13;
0\ 0 .             0       0n  0  0  C u &#13;
co |     C.      r-      -  (¢  &#13;
)-I o   n ,-,o  u^, _n zn Z  cs O- U&#13;
C&gt; 0 - _&#13;
¢-4  --&#13;
Cu      * .  .  *  *&lt; ¢     .  .     C &#13;
08   -0                            co 0  &#13;
I  &lt; -  C Ja Ln   0\q --   _ 0L  - m&#13;
0     * - c ¢ .         - ..&#13;
E-4&lt;-&#13;
V ) )0&#13;
¢d   bO r,t    0  1-  Xa,         J&#13;
u    cos I                                coNu u ) _U&#13;
E-l          *3       .-4                 '*&#13;
0 $  bO               1a Oa 0   9   -   0  1C&#13;
W  b~Cu     -. _ 3          0._&#13;
I_A                                       _{&#13;
Pe                                        O&#13;
&gt;                                         34&#13;
04                                 CL * a   0&#13;
Cu   4co  u    cc  a.   ~co&#13;
u        p3p   0  0   0&#13;
~~4  02~.~P.4  F-'  -. U    )&#13;
04       &lt;      W   '-&#13;
CZJ   J_l o ,AJ   bi  (1) 0A U  &#13;
x)  -,4 cL) 10  0 e  *Cu4&#13;
&gt;.  .i4X  -      -C  wC5¢ u)  _&#13;
O *30  O M      C..  i-i       U tw &#13;
W 'a aD   4- W 3 ) c  -4 W~    v-44 O  &#13;
&gt; 4   &gt;  A--. -  4  C  E  *-4  0Ai4  Cu&#13;
cn  -I &gt;% 4)  go 1 41 " _  z  &gt;  04  0A  ,AJ&#13;
zA  4i  AH w gA   :3 At   co  C A4&#13;
C   .u  L  0W   0  J- -a.J  &#13;
&gt;  '* 3*3033A3     0    A .4i&#13;
¢  W u * 43 w  b Q  z3 0&#13;
,   4 4- 4  J C 4    5,4&#13;
¢&gt;&gt;    (O  ! 10 4  a)  C:  Z   :&#13;
,AJ  c- e  w&gt;  w e aA   eC-)  p a.&#13;
0^                     00 o      0 iA   a)0  CO  0  =  0  w&#13;
;        1 ¶'.0r-      (4        co&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
W  N- * V N ) -  :-  Nj 0  O Cy N   :1 J}XX0&#13;
0 co  *.        . ~.. . . . .&#13;
*s *  @  r   m  N  - 07-  35 c   -  U) (&#13;
aU  I             - ,r ,C  |   ,&#13;
&gt; C)&#13;
4  Ix)  aU-f o- ~ CD ID , -  Cq  tD L flnU&#13;
u   (   .  .       .&#13;
(N&#13;
U      _&#13;
al~~~~~~~~~ w-  0 rD ID   CDOvOo 5e  : r  rO&#13;
(lS ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~I  0 &lt;tY  M lX -t  -0- t &#13;
w  tl: 01 oiw 0 N  W- co q- - n 1 - N  ,In Nr-&#13;
ac           c * -, '*CY&#13;
U-  I a  0  ZNqC' i L  M0~~N  -OW-u4 &#13;
0 ,&#13;
I  - 0  -          .  .   .  I  .   .&#13;
OM 4           ,  y&#13;
4    0    . O&#13;
o _        La. a      ID -  N  N a t _&#13;
I U   *-.  0    0 _,&#13;
zt   I   Z&#13;
LU tY     c&#13;
OQ _  ** W&#13;
Z     ,  -i      r,   0 ew  w  co X  D   n w  t--  c&#13;
co O  , ' ul X   .   .,  co........  .....' M&#13;
r-a  1-  W 1-10  0 0  0) X  O x  M   C1-   LO. OJ&#13;
=   O) .   - C,N 0  Yrr- U' O)  ftJOt1  -e4N  .N -&#13;
O  t    W     |  U.  _ _&#13;
* I U OO      I  I&#13;
U.~~~~~~~~~~~~L&#13;
0.~~~~~~&#13;
W      I A  &#13;
4     JU&#13;
*~~~~~~~~r   P.  e)  eo v  &lt; s i  ali  srn(DrO qs &#13;
oe I  X - M  4  I  I   I&#13;
2   7&#13;
C L     Wi&#13;
I   C     LUU       IC 0&#13;
0     u     L.  10. 00&#13;
a        i&#13;
_nI-InIn  w. t:    --&#13;
I ~    ~   ~  ~ ~ ~~ cc  at cc z&#13;
n    Wx     W  cc O  O M&#13;
n n L U i v wZO-   -&#13;
0.  . W  QU  Z  U  X Z A c J V7&#13;
*  z  4 U. w u  4 Z  0  - n w oi  w W-&#13;
0  Z U. L.U.  -  a.J  0- a CZlU&#13;
I .  ~Ut.. W U. 1  V) ZZ  0 z  Z i   U. uw&#13;
I LI WW W  -O   0.  D  *0.  L&#13;
U  Jy0LUW  _ -  _-: X Z&#13;
0  W41x 1-w 1 nOt-  O- a: 01--  w&#13;
t U1II      w   Z-~&#13;
IA O . i  IA)&lt; W   0 SJO  I 0  cO  W  Z.U&#13;
00    ZwIn wZ Zc flwU-&#13;
a .   U.&gt;  0  0.z w   D  w0  0 0.Z  U.M&#13;
4  20  I  0.  U-U.   '-.U.0&#13;
a Z  Z1-L   W a1- l-.W  1-Ja0.&#13;
D e  _   o A  LU z c 0 a w Z  w CZ  W Z 0&#13;
* w I- o w a: . o00 o o 00: o0 &#13;
a - 0. I-.  a00. LZ U  a0. U..ZU&#13;
a x  v w x Z  &gt;    0 x 2   c  &gt; x M&#13;
W w       0.       0. S   w&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Colombia&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       The principal adverse shock in Colombia has been through the&#13;
deterioration in terms of trade. Prices for its leading export, coffee,&#13;
showed only a modest recovery in 1982 and 1983 from the lows of 1981. At the&#13;
same time, increases in interest rates are a growing component of external&#13;
shocks.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       The leading policy response has been to increase external borrowing,&#13;
with some export promotion. In each of the years 1979-82 there has also been&#13;
substantial negative import substitution, particularly for non-fuel&#13;
products. This may be attributed to allowing the real effective exchange rate&#13;
to appreciate so that by 1981 it reached 79% of its base level (1976-78&#13;
average).&#13;
3.       On the domestic front the government sought to offset some of the&#13;
external setbacks by boosting domestic credit. This resulted in higher budget&#13;
deficit and some increase in inflation.&#13;
4.       In 1983, agriculture, in particular coffee, remained weak.   Also, the&#13;
so-called non-traditional agricultural exports began to run into difficulties&#13;
both with domestic authorities and through increased competition abroad.&#13;
5.       The situation is not a happy one but there are some indications that&#13;
prospects may brighten as the political scene shows signs of improvement and&#13;
terms of trade deterioration may have bottomed out.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
to 00%      0  c7    '.0'.&#13;
0  I   *  *  *  *   &#13;
0)    co£-     0 0 c'&#13;
wr                      e'J-x  &#13;
&gt;0%&#13;
0   C c Lnz  0   Y&#13;
¢ I &#13;
W 0, . 3       e       C &#13;
0 ~ I&lt;    *         ¢ *  *.. .  &#13;
0 --   I       -4  e.4&#13;
-4~ ~ ~~~~&#13;
bO 00I  0ES  O  -       C _'S  0   XO &#13;
&gt; a&#13;
co                   .4  C ' 4 C &#13;
Z   m  en @  @ ** &#13;
co~ ~~~~~ co          en 0-  U e e-&#13;
C.&#13;
I0%  0%   en  _  u 4_e4 c  %_ I.:&#13;
-          I         -  C'&#13;
oco                C,&#13;
-                                  0&#13;
O~ ~~~~O O   8qzs  X u   n Su &#13;
¢   av   N  _  ^  _  _ cs  x   0\ &lt; \0   v~~~~~~N cl&#13;
r.0&#13;
z                                  0&#13;
co   N     No u      -&lt;s &#13;
bo rH  a   c N o co _-T-   o   u &#13;
D~~~~c  I            sc      &gt;&#13;
O'  C0                 c; O  DX&lt;NO NON\ &#13;
t:   e  I   *  .  .  .  *  .   .. * .   .0&#13;
oj rv                  C4 O  So  SO   O 4&#13;
&gt;C,                     x      e&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~1&#13;
-4&#13;
:&gt;         0     I&#13;
~~~~~~~~~-4 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ -&#13;
:  Q- C4 )&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~1&#13;
co  cDc_   &#13;
w$4    0~~~~~~~&#13;
c  _ m      u b 9      0&#13;
&gt; )  &gt;0  ml  .e        -" e&#13;
x. U   eIi -Q     &#13;
00   -. c J  I a  ¢  a &#13;
oe   o  0i               o &gt; :   0&#13;
a)      H         ) 0 v&#13;
0    u &gt;   o c  Z  cU. C  &#13;
co  Q0. 0          A i0&#13;
A O   ww  0       0 Q  Q   W-w&#13;
rA  4  $   co .   F-  co0&#13;
&gt;J  Cu ))   0              0O&#13;
cj      &gt;   c  Zi U4 C&#13;
¢  00 0 w  )J   0  Z  0  c   4&#13;
&gt;  a)X o ~ o.              U )oS oZCQ&#13;
u: a: z a u u a0  &amp;  U 9O&#13;
I-  '-  U9  -.  -  ..-  -~  -.-  0  .-  O&#13;
_~~~~~ _      c zr i_noo &#13;
&gt;  WQJV~4OJ~    a)Pe&#13;
~~ 5Q~~4.4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
UJ Nv  r- r-WI r  ID 0  LO 00  c u) a co IT&#13;
4' 1(D ..      .    .     .... . ... ...C00&#13;
tr- 0 I          - 0  -       Ir  H  I -  LO _   w  17 N&#13;
4 -&#13;
4&#13;
C ~ ~~I -&#13;
a) '       wS co N   co 0- r- co CO -v  mr r   ro-&#13;
O   m O  O   t~V  o 0  L 0 rLr 0 0  - CO' r&#13;
o     -~             - _   I ,     I ,  ,&#13;
&gt;&#13;
I.     . &#13;
0~  [v  '  X  0O          u'v 0   7   C'-t N o W-0)t&#13;
0i    H&#13;
as-  cq C r   0       O ClV C   co  IT o   Un &#13;
.j  4        7  0               . -:  co&#13;
0.   co  I-  m CCI c( D  - rJ( ).  lw  M  LO&#13;
00  ~I      _       -              I&#13;
4       H     2 &#13;
0O           W &#13;
Z Cy      -  )   O   V Cx0       O2C- -0&#13;
4     0'            -    &#13;
I     W' C       a wI-- 0 _CNO I O&#13;
1~~~ Q                 - ~IOJC~    C 0 O O&#13;
&lt;  _   C) '   rm GD  -   r-0-&gt;~~~~~~~co c n ID   C&#13;
0 Z O  - ,  -JU.&#13;
UI.          0      0 &#13;
a,     .&#13;
Z   ,  n  s &gt; O c7  ra ~~~o 0 C)  C-)  co 0  n -&#13;
4      Z~&#13;
0 -  I  '  0  -    CY)  v - Hn I  v &#13;
W   .     UJ     U)~~W &#13;
U-&#13;
ob ~ ~ ~  a .    U&#13;
r . e7  W--o : O-el In v-  O u7 eD N O V&#13;
.~~ ~ ~~ ~~~ |   i Ucxt&#13;
&lt;   L~~~~~~~~~L&#13;
o&#13;
0&#13;
C      LU&#13;
,, LUUU         U    V Z  V) V) &#13;
Z        Z W W W           tY n U L&#13;
0  Z  L LLL~4   I.   1~  LJL/&#13;
*~   c  W           ,, U.  LA  o o 6&#13;
tn  W  Wn   n:             a.  U.zS &#13;
U,W  I   -0            I  -&#13;
*   0  U  U 0     L. w ZO  0 0 &#13;
*        W     W )U ZZ  0 W o   - U&#13;
* O~~~~ Z   IL  =      a = W &#13;
a. .W :    0 w  2Z   0 C  Zu n o LLw&#13;
*   4La.LU W 2  0 C -O   JW0 DL -W&#13;
y  L  wU  _  -    a .  0  : "I U.&#13;
0 ' Xo W    i--   0 _- -0 _W&#13;
*  0  wU42 U:  *0f   -   o    2 Z&#13;
*     010    Z O  1   0 1   0 a a  W 0&#13;
J   I-X  -  O CL . L  Z U  0C a.  U. Z U&#13;
* X  WXZ   &gt; OXX     &lt; &gt;X x   C&#13;
*   Z O  L/ w- i  U.   a. w -.La.w0:&#13;
*    s      J~a JZw0     ~   Z&#13;
U      0L       2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Dominican Republic&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       The Dominican Republic suffered external shocks which averaged 5% of&#13;
GNP over the 1979-82 period. Apart from an improvement in prices for its&#13;
dominant export, sugar, in one of the years, 1981, all three categories were&#13;
unfavorable in each year.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       The government failed to pass on higher fuel prices to the&#13;
consumer. Also, it increased credit to the public sector in the framework of&#13;
a relatively conservative monetary policy aimed at maintaining the parity&#13;
against the U.S. dollar.&#13;
3.       In fact, the exchange rate appreciated in real terms, leading to&#13;
losses in export market shares. Despite some import substitution behind high&#13;
protection, then, the Dominican Republic relied on external borrowing to&#13;
offset adverse balance of payment effects of external shocks.&#13;
4.       Because of various rigidities in the socio-political system, the&#13;
government addressed the problem of unfavorable shocks by short term&#13;
expedients -- primarily higher external borrowing. As the external situation&#13;
continued to deteriorate, little meaningful action was taken until the&#13;
situation reached crisis proportions. Even then an attempt was made to&#13;
stabilize government finances by large increases in the prices of essential&#13;
foodstuffs rather than distributing the burden more equitably. Continued&#13;
depressed markets for its exports, principally sugar, do not augur well for&#13;
its medium-term prospects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40-&#13;
bo co  o   &lt;  E  r..  U)  _4 in Un&#13;
v &gt;   es z  o  or -T Lz  co  - en IO&#13;
&gt; o           _0L&#13;
¢~~~~~ - ~ c -  Ir~19l&#13;
_d 00    ' _  I X&#13;
z    a s  os  o" "Lz  z  e o&#13;
-4 &gt;r on - S    S &#13;
1-4rEX^                Xe1&#13;
Z      co 00  % N cs -z  z&gt; In4 r &#13;
&lt;   _   ~~~~Cf%  C1 _  I&#13;
ON   O       oo   C    oo0&#13;
0%     0c X- *.- .D  % * ~   *-- %O&#13;
_ ~ ~~  0    I 0Z  0  -4  - D  &#13;
o~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~t&#13;
z                               Dw z c &#13;
C;  r0   0 o t CNE co It  CO  %  co C)  C:&#13;
c; &gt; e   __ &#13;
M0                      X~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
C;                     ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~tw&#13;
OW  0~~~~~~~&#13;
U1~~~~~~ _- 0)&#13;
OL          ow  00  Qd          0&#13;
a~~~~~~c   a  C 14  0 &#13;
¢~~      ~ ~~~ 06  C )  to    -&#13;
&gt;  -0   ci   O4C&#13;
s~~~~~~~~ 0  0 C: w  o W&#13;
U~~~~~~W Z U AiC   9    0    r-&#13;
S ~~~~~~9 40 Ai cm" 0  _- W  &#13;
;~~      ~  ~ C3  _V -4 O) C:  0 &#13;
O~~~~~~~~~ ttl  8 tS   U) X   X &#13;
X  4  0   ¢ 0 U3     C&#13;
u U  0 9  ^  C;   0- X   O&#13;
Q    X-b4Q   H C &#13;
&gt;-   &gt;                 0 &#13;
U.  _: &gt;s 9  O:,   4 C &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
w C  0     r-  r- Ln O   r- co C0  - ,-r-O&#13;
0.  t 0'     1:C NCN  .1- .- - ' c to - &#13;
CZ  &gt; 0% &#13;
-   Ic&#13;
C&#13;
2  .       m    C           I .   .  .  .  .  *  -&#13;
_    0. *~ 11 - F  e  ur oin w v ac'¢ oD&#13;
C            Cl    _Nn-c u r CY  - -&#13;
&gt; M&#13;
o    -.            -&#13;
1&#13;
0   1v -&#13;
*   cs,*  .  . ..   .  ...     . .&#13;
O) ^ .  s       * *)   v  o   rs 0   -w m   n  a ..o  o  e1&#13;
rb   tr es  C4 W  Ln  0  co :' M.  LO M' &#13;
I- F         CuN C1-,f _,   ~ &amp; -&#13;
oV-  wr-M         - L &#13;
w  4.~~~~wL&#13;
. U  .&#13;
O W    *      Y&#13;
w  9-0 UX  *   UQO  11)  v- 'On C eta  t   ss&gt;u &#13;
J       * _0.  O   -       .&#13;
m U *   X. v I &gt;ItS S   -(n-0   -Ou r,t&#13;
-I- _        4f ¢   )  s -xr  t s &#13;
C-. Z&#13;
o  _   ,   U.&#13;
z&#13;
U      U     Id)~~~~~~~  .  L CL(&#13;
Z   *  e)  F ~~Ln  n   Ln tM   0  NoIDU  0 U  )&#13;
0.~~~0 iuu       U2    U   xOJ&#13;
I     U. 1- U .0) 1  U)( NOnr'U&#13;
0) '  O      O~2U&#13;
S~~~~~~ x W                     uj&#13;
X   I   O~~~~~~~~~~I&#13;
I   W  C   J -  .&#13;
e'0Z C O- -..   O U - a o&#13;
&gt;~~~~C n &lt;r Wi &gt; ){ -  O tn  . . W.  U) n-i 11&#13;
4U   -   .     - &#13;
U W&#13;
o       d&#13;
W      W cr00D0C       0 m c&#13;
.-  Z            U a W  z Uz&#13;
U        U w.       U)  00o &#13;
U               U .X  &gt; W  Z  o -   -&#13;
W  ZU0l         U WZ    I &lt; W&#13;
Z  1-LflIfl  wZ    0- ---W  l &#13;
*   Z. zJ U  1 U 2L  U -   J   U)- D&#13;
*  2  4u.UW  42  F O - 0  fl O9-UJI&#13;
0  lu.UU  4 WJ C-  D CL 1  - L &#13;
U)  U  UW   4 .-O _ .  9 &lt;on_'  LZ ,&#13;
U ) XOWW     l-   U =9---0W&#13;
00      2wt n UZ0  _  0nWZ&#13;
J    U.&gt;  0 1.f n lX O azJo00 o U-wJ &#13;
O 20 O)  Z.1  LLU  0. D  :  .U-0&#13;
I  2  Z1- O)I1-..    )f l9i-I-..JI0. &#13;
I Z OU~0 I   ZwZ      w W1FJw2J0F1 &#13;
I  w  '-V1  g1   *o no 11Za   oon O wt:  JZO~&#13;
x   tdw(  -&gt;0i .( 6Z  4  )-)(  4S1 &#13;
U 0X-U-   U4w X ZW- :IOXz &lt; &#13;
u . O  J -        - &amp;   - :&#13;
I     _          _&#13;
O     O          0&#13;
t.       G         tL 0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: India&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       For India, exports typically account for less than 7% of GNP so that&#13;
the economy is largely insulated from external shocks. However these shocks&#13;
became increasingly adverse after 1980 as terms of trade deteriorated and&#13;
export volume effects became more important. The 1983 terms of trade showed&#13;
some improvement due to favorable developments in oil prices.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       In 1979 and 1980 and, to a lesser extent, in 1981 Indian policy&#13;
makers sought to redress the balance of payments disequilibrium by external&#13;
financing. The situation was further complicated on the domestic front by&#13;
droughts and by some difficulties in Assam which were a major setback to&#13;
domestic oil production.&#13;
3.       Domestic investment in oil began to yield significant returns from&#13;
1982. In 1984 production is expected to exceed 30 million tonnes, which would&#13;
cover about 75% of domestic needs. Besides reducing import requirements, this&#13;
will also provide a welcome boost to public finances and help moderate the&#13;
growth in credit to the government.&#13;
4.       On the external front, after an initial depreciation the real&#13;
exchange rate has been falling slowly, contributing to declines in export&#13;
market shares. At the same time, an even-keel macroeconomic policy has been&#13;
followed, with the money supply allowed to grow pari-passu with GDP. Finally,&#13;
the domestic saving effort has continued at its traditionally high level --&#13;
over 20% of GDP with about 75% of this coming from households.&#13;
5.       While the high growth rate since 1980 represents a rebound from 1979&#13;
when drought greatly reduced agricultural output, the rate of economic growth&#13;
averaged 4.4% -- exceeding the historical record between 1980 and 1983. Apart&#13;
from the bouyancy of oil production and the excellent 1983 harvest, migrants'&#13;
remittances of about $2 billion a year contributed to this result.&#13;
6.       In years when India was not buffetted by extraordinary domestic&#13;
shocks, it seems to have been able to absorb much of the adverse external&#13;
shocks. However, rising debt charges and the apparently short prospects for&#13;
the oil boom will continue to pose serious challenges for policy makers in the&#13;
medium term.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-43 -&#13;
bo 00  -4 U)      C) ~~-4&#13;
a,  _ *n _&#13;
bO 00  _0 _l '_  en -I  uri  _%&#13;
X~~~ I  .  . ....     ....... ..&#13;
C  -t O_ _I I      _ -&#13;
&gt; C  &#13;
tn oF  _7      N C1 CDO &#13;
CD  - -. o  _  _&#13;
-4       -4&#13;
v &gt;   &lt; .un Lrv es o  --  o&#13;
a,  0            C0  -; I&#13;
O _ &lt; _~~~~ I   I  cq &#13;
¢ -&#13;
0a4  -I    0.-.-~-C i  i x4  j a_ o&#13;
00&#13;
'-.4  0   CSO~CJC% _,  eN  co  _ ,&#13;
cn ~ ~ ~ ~~~~c&#13;
o~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~T&#13;
C)   oo   .  .  .  .  .  ~.  .  .  .  .0&#13;
co °-co-       I I     -           0 _&#13;
_  c;   ol   o vooo ¢sI vo l  &lt; n  en  e  &#13;
-4~~~~~~~~~~~~~-               X&#13;
w 00~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
bO rQ  C) Nc (71 r-_ 'oO   e O  C   J_)&#13;
0  Z  o I  o  rc&#13;
w r,      cn O-7        C N&#13;
0                                  3&#13;
0                                  -4x  e&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
0 ~ ~   C  Q  C  .      *    0&#13;
z~~~c                             0 sQOmcs&lt; zjXs &#13;
U,~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
.10~~~~~~~&#13;
o1  V CL U  U  O W&amp;1     4 V  e  &#13;
4  tO&#13;
Aiw fi &gt;C p 4' v O  V ;,ci  0&#13;
zC   &gt;% ux &lt;  )W c   t a cn &#13;
&gt;&gt;   &gt;  =  "  $4 c}   -14 s  C o  &#13;
ce   c C  W         5ec..&#13;
u    0 W              0oO&#13;
W  0  ui    ~ &#13;
t 0Z  4  0. ~ 4 &#13;
tcin -  r=  I-I    ci~3 Z  -4&#13;
O ...  . .  - .           c .. &#13;
oe  _   4  CD  -L.' , li  _  W  "&#13;
cc 0   4-O C)  , 04  0 W0&#13;
&gt;  - a) 40W  -4 W   0&#13;
W o  0W  0J. W0  0  0&#13;
X4  0uJ04E-     ~  U&#13;
CL,  cli  V)  rl  ci 4'  0 c&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
WuNi  0  1 -       O v o   in 0 Nw co &#13;
C  * *~ t    ? -U' n  t -   N1  0&#13;
C -&#13;
O     la C)  OOD (-1-  qD---ls &#13;
C NI                 7 .  .    7&#13;
-   XI *f      qC)  -W Fz--00  CO .. qO O0&#13;
O    0   E *   -N   N       -    ..-F........N&#13;
N&#13;
IS)   W   -- el tN  tvN  t-  ) co tv  -  1- r-  x N4 0&#13;
(l ~   .m  I  .    .  . ..    .  .&#13;
0 -  C  *    co N c  -w IS) -   in, N N O- W- U7 &#13;
as t       MS-   co  _P  C4 C -&#13;
-2&gt;0&#13;
N  Z      . 1&#13;
W C - I&#13;
.J  4   I    _ 0&#13;
W O       L     L 1r- N  r -c 4-, W N  o -v O -0uC&#13;
,   Vf        LAMl-    LLO -I *  _ ,N.&#13;
-  _0  -         I J&#13;
C-    I    Z~&#13;
U-          W&#13;
E    g *  N  W  co-  tf 0C r CD  l W  N  U  O O&#13;
a    C *      _ _:  _   NN    U:  N-&#13;
o     _,   LU.     UCN -I&#13;
0      0&#13;
L&amp;I    I    CM&#13;
W      *    W   &#13;
0.~~~~&#13;
U Co J4-&#13;
1 l-UUif0  4    ~     r- N) O 7&#13;
¢ | ' Z  '  Z~~~~~~~~Z &#13;
01     2 O  W t7 0 N  2  * v X) tN J E  rWNUO It N&#13;
~~-I  0  WC~~~N  ~~ r  r-  cx0U I&#13;
0. *   O)XN -WoO O- q N-  - *N&#13;
_  I       I  1-FN  -     I &#13;
*    W      X &#13;
*    C.     w&#13;
*    4&#13;
4 C      W&#13;
4         1-   L #Z3  ) 0&#13;
U. -    CMv    UA   Ld 0  0  0&#13;
Z   -a U. WV7t V) W       -  -&#13;
0 U7)            A.-   1-0 .  0  U&#13;
n   Yu  W    W -C  0 D      C U&#13;
g  Q   W       1~~M U2 O2O2&#13;
r un   u r  0-  w  sr  x &#13;
W 4 .CM  42  0          Z /C O-I&#13;
* C0     J-  4 U  WtJ 0 W  W -  -U&#13;
* .) Z  WW  CZ  O-  _.)   M1 u&#13;
I o 0 C21- U1 0 c-  J-  01- L U&#13;
*  _  tZ W E IL  ) ZW   Z  ^&#13;
*   W    CZ -O M  2 J  O: W   * W U,&#13;
*    00y2'c   i   wZ wo-c-:EZ&#13;
* J O   W a C .-  0  0U. O   U  0. O L L   U&#13;
* 4  20 - ) c  U -.  E  w- :U  U W  N  &gt;&#13;
* &lt; Z-fl O  wGt  w2 OL     2O&#13;
*~  /)MX _ -K 4w     ) wZ- :  Ow2  4 &#13;
*  IU  01-CM-  U CM 21   UC  2 - &#13;
I  2     J          -J&#13;
0        0          0 &#13;
O UL 0.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
45 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Ivory Coast&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       During the 1970s, Ivory Coast benefitted greatly from booming world&#13;
prices for its coffee and cocoa exports. These prices fell in the 1979-82&#13;
period, policy makers were faced with large adverse shocks. While most of the&#13;
shock could be attributed to deterioration in terms of trade, the rise in&#13;
interest rates assumed increasing importance as the government had to struggle&#13;
with the large external debt burden accummulated during the booming seventies.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       Initially the government sought to redress the adverse balance of&#13;
payments situation by higher external financing. By 1981 it became evident&#13;
that external financing could not be increased further. There followed&#13;
increasing export promotion and import substitution.&#13;
3.       On the domestic side, the growth of government expenditures&#13;
particularly investment was slowed down. Attempts were also made to moderate&#13;
the growth of the money supply, but government credit was allowed to expand to&#13;
ease domestic recessionary pressures. This, in turn, required further&#13;
external borrowing so that by 1984 the situation had reached crisis&#13;
proportions. The per capita debt became the highest in Africa and the Ivory&#13;
Coast was obliged to reschedule.&#13;
5.       The Ivory Coast embarked on an ambitious expansionary program in the&#13;
mid seventies. Much of the investment and expenditures of those years does&#13;
not seem to be generating the anticipated stream of returns. This became&#13;
apparent when the adverse external shocks of the eighties combined with&#13;
domestic setbacks.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
c  I    .         *         -&#13;
S  No %O  0 o  . Z   _o&#13;
03 1'  a% _ -  ,  I         _&#13;
&gt; &#13;
¢-&#13;
-E&#13;
03      ....      ¢..&#13;
00        a: Z    ~     C&#13;
r c    m  z _  I    _&#13;
00    00&#13;
0_    a' --:?  I 0 &#13;
or o q -1  o q    e&lt;&#13;
00  C  CS &#13;
o-T    U N   en  cl  z  C1  %  -I&#13;
-     a'O&lt; 4 a o  ' I  Z  CS4&#13;
XY  CN L,  C   ,  z  Ln'K&#13;
a'    -&#13;
-4&#13;
c.                       .  .  . CZ&#13;
E4    -            t         e'  -&#13;
to ~ ~ ~ C rv  I  I  Is   C.)Xe&lt; &#13;
10&#13;
'-4-&#13;
0&#13;
- ~  ~   a a' c~-            v       4J&#13;
03 ~  ~    b   CD *C                   0 &#13;
0o  S X  O    (n  v  0   &#13;
~~~- 4  _C ¢0C&#13;
0~~~~~~&#13;
co a*  ,cffl  ze&#13;
Cd                   ~~~~~~~~~~~0&#13;
Q C) H  O X  so Q   H  C ~~4)  'I &lt;&#13;
U) )    ( tOmCX &#13;
t)            0~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
X  S H  C          03      0&#13;
in Ai wU   o 04    bo U)c&#13;
0  "40)  0               1.4)H r-&amp;J4&#13;
&gt; --  Zv  &gt;  C  tJ   U   C -Hc&#13;
t:  .14   V 4   0 co C 3 -4  z  &gt;  o &#13;
¢     ~     -I 0               0 0 Z&#13;
J-0IPL      .0&#13;
%6  CJ 4.  a) (n U   C C&#13;
. Q."  C  in            0 i$4A&#13;
o         ) .4    0  a&#13;
bO .......      ¢   ...    &#13;
0  _ ' 0  U0  Co  1-  CA _&#13;
o  ~~  0303~4  0  mo. - 0&#13;
.-40J~~~&#13;
H  4  .UN4  2.,;   4  O  *,4 04  0n&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-47-&#13;
w cN     W  -  to N NIO C  N&#13;
C C sN  - r--  n N O0 o  v0 s Oqr-cN&#13;
2 :&gt;,  -  Wo -CN   -CN  -N  -  - -&#13;
C  '&#13;
9-  i&#13;
4&#13;
Q     0  ()0~~~~~~,  w0-7r-  CY  m  kt-0&#13;
o     -  ~~~~  ~~w  -  C14c) CNYcl&#13;
Cd&#13;
c l&#13;
O   W1 O                    CN O  i L 0 N&#13;
_   ( I ,w ,.    . . . .  .  .  .  .&#13;
o:-~  en |  o   N G0  U7 C'  co  - U OILO'  w Nr- c&#13;
r-   0      CD -   c'i   C'N&#13;
&gt; _&#13;
U  &lt;&#13;
- .   .     0**&#13;
N  CZ cc  |   _N  F u         lS  n&#13;
ui I- a.W    C14-w  -cU) -00oC   -~  n C'&#13;
4 - 'fl  O  '  - eD N-  0 Nr In  OC U1 0   r - - n&#13;
r-  CY00      D- &#13;
a          L w  2&#13;
2     *  r-  ,-w~   ocruw   w0t&#13;
U.         0     0 &#13;
N ~ ~ ~ 9  9-CN  4UOWO |   Ul&#13;
J t Ioz....       2....... ..&#13;
O 0   w  r co a)  r  N  O X   N r m 0  Ln&#13;
cx   _       t O--n  N  N   LN  - &#13;
a.&#13;
0-~~~~~~&#13;
4 O&#13;
C   I   Z~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
t- M*r    1  xC   ,w 4  9- ~ M A  VILf&#13;
w s2 ,&#13;
Z ~ ~~        W o 0:  U. D z IDO  00n&#13;
*    0               ,1 .   9V e  D &gt;-a  a.O &#13;
O ~ ~ ~  -A' _Z          0-  -- &#13;
a. l ~ woo O  2OU&#13;
O  2U.U.U.  4   U. W  0 0&#13;
U'  UULW 4- ~    I 0fl.  u.&#13;
CL ~     ~~   W9lf   I&#13;
00'  CZ~     wZ  CZ~&#13;
C ~ ~~~~ J&#13;
...J  LLQD- t  a.#O N r  &lt; Un  N   0a.N-U.  0&#13;
4  20 Z ~   a-  U a Z   .  *  t &#13;
_   -aui   z   w  w  w2.&#13;
X  fli(  &gt;0L&lt;  4 -  z&#13;
L W  LU  04        O&#13;
a.U.   I-U&#13;
I       o.&#13;
0        0         0&#13;
U   .           a. L&#13;
I ~ ~ ~  ~ Z ui cx m  wi  Z M&#13;
&gt;    w-  0  Q.      001 0.&#13;
Zo 0    m      U.U  Q. w~  U. O -&#13;
I   0           IW Q  Ln Z   wZ J&#13;
) CZ CZ W  m C WZ Z  w  o  C, F oz &#13;
Li  w:I   w w  0-  D  0 Co  cwo D  , u&#13;
x   {Y i  &lt;1  W &gt;1 x  &gt;)  X I v &#13;
LU tr   -v)          upt  t  :wzo &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Jamaica&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       Jamaica suffered from unusually severe shocks over the four year&#13;
period, equalling 7.2% of GNP in 1979 and increasing to 30.5% of GNP by&#13;
1982. Most of the adversity resulted from a decline in both volume and the&#13;
price for its export products, notably aluminium.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       The disequilibrium in the balance of payments was addressed in equal&#13;
measure by external financing and a deceleration of economic growth. These&#13;
responses were offset to some extent by failure to maintain export shares in&#13;
spite of some depreciation of the real exchange rate. In the earlier years&#13;
there was some success in non-fuel import substitution but this effort seems&#13;
to have stalled from 1981 onwards.&#13;
3.       The government has sought to stabilize the money supply/GDP ratio.&#13;
Nevertheless, domestic credit has continued to increase and credit to&#13;
government, rose even more rapidly. Much of the increase in energy prices is&#13;
now being passed on to the consumer.&#13;
4.       Overall Jamaica has suffered unusually severe external shocks which&#13;
would tax the ability of even the most resourceful policy makers. Recent&#13;
improvements of commodity prices offer some hope but it is unlikely that&#13;
Jamaica will be able to regain its per capita income levels of a decade ago&#13;
for some time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Cu  I   *  *...  .  . &#13;
&gt;0%     -4  _  vD   I  u-4_-&#13;
&gt;  cis&#13;
4of Cn %.o Z  o  U-   Z  Z&#13;
-     CO _4 X  I X-&#13;
43)  C-4-        -&#13;
b 0S&#13;
bO~ X   e 40o%C Nt- C'    ue O%e&#13;
tuo I     * o    * e         Co Co&#13;
p  43  oq It  ,) It  ,' o C4  1 &#13;
ai r-     " 4%OCn-4 1  -IT  -  -&#13;
&gt; O N-4&#13;
&lt;t&#13;
C-,&#13;
H     C'4    a%~C -4  x  _  L&#13;
r  It  *  .  4 . . ..&#13;
4-,      '~~~-4  -IU  O  4 C4-&#13;
!..,&#13;
X~~~~~~L   _n  CY  X  vN -1  X)  £ r&#13;
I      X       ..  .  .  .  .  .  4  4&#13;
0%&#13;
N  4) 00C0               I ~&#13;
bO r,     C&gt; V   C  t  x      oen Lf&#13;
0%         - 4 IT   '-4 1 L)-4 1&#13;
&gt;*4 &#13;
*s,    o                          I S  ^ &lt;^&#13;
cn              ,.       S,t&#13;
-4                Cu&#13;
u~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
0%j  ~ ~ ~ ~   N-r        41)O-&#13;
.  .  .  .  4  Q   .  . .  go&#13;
-4  ~~~~~  ...461      e,I4od      r&#13;
.0  0 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~       4 &#13;
Ou  bO       -      II b _   u _  -  _&#13;
0n           0i4r-~r-eu-&#13;
w             4)~~*  .  Cu&#13;
Cu                                     3&#13;
a~~~~~~0 L) C       W 04&#13;
G4 0 -4-.t-) C tt0&#13;
4. n  rD4 19 _4 E-  X  HX&#13;
c     -4$-  8        0 &#13;
,C      a)C -4  C:   CX  C       D&#13;
&gt;d 0   C w   0   ¢ 0  C  &#13;
wz 0 u oo w=    a  n 0 a4     O&#13;
~~~~~~~-4 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ -&#13;
0&#13;
I-       .. -4 o   X   bc  4   04  E&#13;
-~~~~ 4-t            d )  I-      1. 4&#13;
o~ ~       Cu    -   01 e0 o v &#13;
¢~~~ &gt;                          0n&lt;vXX Z t &#13;
U~   ~~~   0            1.a4 OMa o &#13;
01     M0  H             1&#13;
b;     OCu  - &#13;
o   ...... 01         ..&#13;
Cu _   JC   U     U,             C D  uS _ &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
LuJ(N   C C C r V D  I O)LflM  (D(N r) Th&#13;
-,   C I *     CY    N'v N E&#13;
.&#13;
4 - &#13;
I     fl  (D CD W  C4 -O0O ~ ~IT l)r- C-&#13;
4    0 '  O  :s zD {b -0 0( Cto D N -  0  W0No  U&#13;
o¢, j   ¢'   ) t-  r-N  U,  v &#13;
. I-.  we-&#13;
N    ~ &#13;
_z &gt; o)&#13;
W C4- &#13;
OW I-C     Y~ C(        DD     O-,&#13;
Jl  cc cx  '    , ,  r  0  Dt   z  -:&#13;
m  o.  *, 'T c, O  n N- co  -0 - 1) N &#13;
1  4                    7 0 N&#13;
00 &#13;
-a&#13;
z _ ,~~&#13;
co ,   P  U C.  IT  n  fD F n  0 v0  0 nalO &#13;
of   o        C, x  *4 ^  ........ .. .&#13;
-I  41*  -   SC      SN N{ &#13;
a          U.                   c Z'&#13;
O.   _,    UJ.  &#13;
L     0'   O      O - &#13;
U.      ~~0    0&#13;
z...      7 z '~&#13;
r-  ,    i CW 6   0:  ,  c    U&#13;
I   C   J~~~~~~I&#13;
(n   U  w - 4 InJ &lt;  0 r- 0 l  04 r DDO&#13;
UJ&#13;
C.    wi&#13;
4LI.&#13;
a&#13;
U,&#13;
0     U       L Z   -C. Z&#13;
Z U ZW U. U.  4   -  C,N  0 N  n U&#13;
. '   w - U.  WNIZ-  0 ' Z¢-0 I &#13;
I ,  W   X O.         C  U.&#13;
U  I-L 0   I.I-    4.IIZLj&#13;
I    tU W( w   --     --  u&#13;
l~~~~~~~~~&#13;
0 W411T L *0    -  0 -   U&#13;
_, u..-J  U,0   Vio cO w&#13;
00    Zwnn wZ ZQ  a n&#13;
I  .  L    W&gt;  0  .     O  O U. _&#13;
4  0 1 ,               ,U. V)  W Z  0&#13;
2   -    U W-.I-..Ur  U I.- -   aC.&#13;
) t uJW Z  &gt;DV Z   &gt;    U.&#13;
w ZI-w- uW  w- C   Uw O&#13;
I  0       0 W0 -   L FODS &#13;
I     C W_&#13;
I   x o  w 1    Q a:F  _ &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-51 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Kenya&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       Adverse external shocks from 1979 to 1981 were aggravated even&#13;
further in 1982 by a precipitous deterioration in terms of trade. The&#13;
downward spiral may have finally been broken in 1983 and 1984 as primary&#13;
product prices have risen and prospects for some of Kenya's export&#13;
commodities, particularly tea, are showing improvement.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       The policy response to external shocks had been to increase external&#13;
borrowing and to engage import substitution for non-fuel through increased&#13;
protection since 1981. Up to 1982 the real exchange appreciated slightly,&#13;
contributing to losses in export market shares.&#13;
3.       In 1982 the Kenyan shilling depreciated and there was a small&#13;
improvement in export performance after a number of years of decline. At the&#13;
same time, domestic credit was allowed to expand faster than GDP and in&#13;
particular the government share of this credit. The government budget balance&#13;
rose to 13.5% of GDP in 1982. This in turn led to higher inflation.&#13;
4.       By 1983 the government sought to moderate the expansion of domestic&#13;
credit and the government budget showed a small improvement. However, public&#13;
finances and a number of the parastatals continue to be a drag on the&#13;
economy. Also, the rural sector where over 80% of the population resides&#13;
needs a more stimulating economic environment. Nevertheless, a good harvest&#13;
in 1983 coupled with a modest producer price increase in agriculture resulted&#13;
in a 5% increase in GNP.&#13;
5.       Kenya suffered from severe external shocks in the period 1979-82.&#13;
These were further compounded by poor domestic harvests and political&#13;
instability in neighboring countries. The policy of curbing import and&#13;
increasing external borrowing may have run its course. It now appears that&#13;
public finances will need to be improved and better economic incentives&#13;
provided to stimulate the rural sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52-&#13;
wo co  en cr In o &lt;uN&#13;
0  I  *  *  *  *  .   *  .&#13;
m Io~4'~- &#13;
a -   o- _4 _I         _&#13;
&gt; &#13;
¢ -.&#13;
-4 @3MCS 1D Z Z ZCNn _&#13;
nO       -&#13;
bO 0) r-,  ON -4 rs  aI I I&#13;
&gt; &#13;
o I  *  *  -  .  *  .  ¢  .  .&#13;
OP -It 4 l    -  -s&#13;
41~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
*  **  .  .  * .   .v.  *  .&#13;
00 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ .~&#13;
cr,~ ~~~~ (I  0: 0 %  M  .4r- N'ov &#13;
a4 _-4 C I I   -4 _n&#13;
0~~~~~~~~ *            *&#13;
-~ ~~~~~~ -  Is 1- .Cl  - _'  ;&#13;
-4&#13;
cjn&#13;
0&#13;
0                     Ox&#13;
to ~ ~ ~ a ci 1o 0; r^  co ^  o cn&#13;
X  l   * . - . *  *  *  . .&#13;
v £   o a  r-.&lt;  -   I-  * *D CS   0&#13;
C,l  as -4C s   U  -4  -&#13;
&gt;~~~~~~~l %      r%      co&#13;
-               8&#13;
boo ~-T 0 o      C     00&#13;
z~            -&#13;
0  0                             r&gt;  0&#13;
5-4  U ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~-  a &#13;
*0~~~~~~~~~&#13;
A4X            &#13;
r4 0   I  -&#13;
-W  tn~~~~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
-5w       @3    0&#13;
4U        @3     4.&#13;
A4 - Q  C: (LM&#13;
H  ibo   0e      u     0&#13;
CD  IH a  0      ...~4  4 4  4&#13;
0  ~ ~ ~ &gt;0"   2-4     5.4(a&#13;
0    -.. V 3     0 . &gt;&#13;
ci 0_ C i   ¢ 4_       C&#13;
@3 0D  H         @3 OX S &#13;
g   0 m.  C   Z &gt;&#13;
04 CZ.  CJ -w  4) rn  CJ  b-  i&#13;
4  44Cn "4   EH  -- bO   wP &#13;
0   4i J 4 C CO&#13;
&gt;  40                . Z&#13;
&gt;  0 aJ3.   0    0)&#13;
X  eX&gt;0 X w  c;  ePW  ..6&#13;
s o o so  o  w  o.zr_  &#13;
&gt;: z aU c.4n a   Mo cU  0 &#13;
*.-~~~~~~e-e4J@ *s! *&#13;
_~ -4@0N3. n &lt;          0nv  st _Nnc&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-53 -&#13;
W N   -      n I  C O r - un  r- M  D - ' N -&#13;
c  *      co  r  m  C  0 uw - Mm&#13;
CZ       co      m -L  0 o|s (  Ln  r-&#13;
LU&#13;
J&gt;,&#13;
4-&#13;
|  0  t O 1 0  DU , In r  IVN  O P- IC 0&#13;
C     N  *  .  . .  .  .  .   .   .   . .&#13;
&gt;     CO (N 1? co    O Jqw la N CO tO N V 0 4&#13;
Z     0   (N   I     CO)  LU1  1  0  N f  -&#13;
LU    - I&#13;
(N&#13;
0% ^C-    0 -~~      O coN N n coJ0 -N&#13;
r-  a     -   X        - -'&gt;0r-    ,t&#13;
at I- Lui P,&#13;
-z  &gt;o 0&#13;
tu  c - &#13;
(N  a a     ,  L&#13;
w1 P-.       -    i-n   v t oo (DIJ  w 0 UN C w&#13;
J  4     _,  .  O     '   '  '&#13;
c _             v       C&gt; -r-  e-     -&#13;
I~~~        4 &#13;
c          Z&#13;
Z      a v ~ U3l(N C4 W  v -,w ( 0  in U 0 C 117&#13;
4  0        . &#13;
I     aZ C  0 w 0 r-N    0 n   -  -t O&#13;
ax   o0' -    0s    YI--u       -&#13;
o     -  I   L7.        U 7I     7N&#13;
OU    _,     IL U@        |&#13;
U. &#13;
W ~~  ,~     N   4f-O-        WOvU&#13;
0      CY  J - 00   v   M  M L&#13;
0'   . Z      Z &#13;
&gt;~~~~~~~    r|          . 7u  vn &#13;
r-  WLflU,) l  Cy r- '-~  (N 0 r-&#13;
0'     U'     L(;  , SN(N O 0' - tN  - V&#13;
6U&#13;
0~~~~~~~C &#13;
In&#13;
,~~~~~~c 0 xxx &#13;
,  en~~~~~~~~~~~I&#13;
In    w Z             I&#13;
U  LU      LA.~ ~~~ In0 0&#13;
0 C        WC &#13;
,, 0  U.L U..            0.0.&#13;
U    V)              L U  FZ  X &#13;
0  ui     z          vl o  o O -  &#13;
x  CZ D .4wxL     w a 1n G1 &gt;&#13;
*    InI-1nIn  L U.Z     0-. --&#13;
U O   I  0.   &gt;. U  0.   U.&#13;
0.  JLU. U  a  2.0 U  U  0(IC.U. Z U&#13;
x G JWx O O O Z      O &gt;X ZI J&#13;
Z 41. LU 4WCZ  0  - I wnO WF&#13;
N  LUa.L. InzzI-  0 -2Z0.Aw&#13;
In UU WWW 4C-0 C    . O &#13;
* U X OLUW W   -     U _   I-.-"_ _0O &#13;
0 O  U11 In . )0 1  -   O~  2 &#13;
In V} ILF   XOG  ..oJO uIo0wLJU&#13;
0'0[      Z W G  W Z Z ttD:W-&#13;
..J  LL&gt;I1  0  G.I V 0  00.IOG  U. E  .J&#13;
4 C 2Z0  In  G. 1  A.  0. 0  G   .0&#13;
I Z    l0 ' W  1 LFI-JW * n1/7Fw1 J0.&#13;
wU ~ -Iow  a *      o  aaooO o a&#13;
|  F-  a      GGI 000 Z   G G L.Z O&#13;
)( X VlLUXZ O0X 1 C   &gt;1&lt;   X4 &#13;
LUE 0LU    14W     1 U CW    I &#13;
I    I      _           _&#13;
0 E                  0 &#13;
U O       . o.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Korea&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       Korea suffered steadily increasing adverse external shocks over the&#13;
four-year period, reaching 22.6% of its GNP in 1982. Over two-fifths of the&#13;
deterioration may be attributed to losses in terms of trade, with a similar&#13;
amount resulting from poorer export prospects. The remainder is accounted for&#13;
by increasing interest rate charges.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       In the 1976-78 base period Korea enjoyed an average annual GNP growth&#13;
rate of 12.2%, largely through export-led growth. When the world economy&#13;
began to slow down in late 1979 and particularly from 1980 onwards, the&#13;
initial Korean policy response was to accommodate the adverse shocks by&#13;
reducing rates of economic growth. This policy induced a sharp decline in&#13;
imports. At the same time, wage controls were used and the exchange rate&#13;
depreciated in real terms after 1982, leading to higher exports.&#13;
3.       Domestic fuel prices were adjusted upwards to accommodate higher&#13;
international prices while the growth of the money supply was reduced in 1980&#13;
and 1981. This policy drove up interest rates which began to create problems&#13;
for Korean firms as historically many of the more dynamic firms had high&#13;
debt/equity ratios. By early 1982 the authorities chose to move towards a&#13;
more expansionary policy. At the same time, moderation in wage increases and&#13;
lower oil import prices help to defuse a potential acceleration in inflation.&#13;
4.       Korea's strong growth performance in the mid-seventies provided a&#13;
cushion for its policy makers. They tended to absorb most of the adverse&#13;
shock by inducing a slowdown in economic activitiy. This was followed by a&#13;
depreciation of the exchange rate to restore export competitiveness. When is&#13;
appeared in 1982 that the restrictive policies might be counterproductive, a&#13;
prudent expansionary package was applied.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
b0 00  Cn  -4 -   %D Un  CO- &#13;
0  I   *  *  *  .  *  .  .  .  .&#13;
W e    N o rs L  U  0  U   C  uf&#13;
- I&#13;
w  PI  CrA  _ -  I , - ,   _&#13;
&gt; e    &#13;
¢~~~~~ -&#13;
X     *  .  *  .  .  .  *  *  -&#13;
0)0  0%   -C  I~ &#13;
_%  -O _n  I   o&#13;
s~~~1 CCS~C"&#13;
C  I   .  .  .  .  .  I  C  *&#13;
- e%     II*  I       ( N&lt;- &#13;
¢%  -    \0 U-? ~ L&#13;
cn&#13;
-          0% X -NO II C      N&#13;
0cis0 e  m-a,  r- tLn&#13;
-C'              cr   8o C-  c  , nr&#13;
z&#13;
_  qx  &lt;7N CJ  Cr  *N  co  *  *7&#13;
- 00%-0  .  I          (NI(-&#13;
-  0  ~ W0     n     C.14(  CLf-4  &#13;
&gt;*CS&#13;
o&#13;
¢   or  CSON~u. oN X--(   J (&#13;
0  I ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ 1  0&#13;
CC-t-t-~0  (14&#13;
z                  ,0 .s&#13;
4~ ~ ~ ~~~~~~~~-&#13;
10&#13;
a4 &#13;
0&#13;
A4~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~'-&#13;
C) o N CS00 &lt; : CS........ O0)n..J&#13;
:-             0s      ......  .) ..........c  . . . 1-i&#13;
0 ZW~      Ve       0 &#13;
i  4  U O  C s:  w  o&#13;
b r   O  _ 0  - I         0. CS&#13;
0..a)41  co  a)&#13;
o  0  W  0)1..  0  0&#13;
C&lt;  Cl) ' &#13;
-40~~~i&#13;
CI  4O4  L ) 4  Z          0&#13;
Z~~                  ¢ -4  _   .¢ &#13;
_~      ~  ~ ~ JJJ C0J  C)  J-L.-  e&#13;
e Cfl  COW   Z  WO O  &#13;
&gt; o  &gt; W0)VW-4 C  0  0 0 -&#13;
C:  *. &gt;*             * o0 Z &gt;C &#13;
Om  (N  LforC.o  U  U CCd&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
IUtN  0   t Ir1   Wr-   w (O0 1f N   co  l e aUN O&#13;
CDa}      . . .  . .. ..     ...&#13;
C  I  U ItZ   U) UU n m  17 t7 coD -U: LO- I f i *r&#13;
,U4   _    V-       - -o        -&#13;
&gt; al &#13;
C  -  '-&#13;
4&#13;
w  QD  N~ ON  C  -CY, 01 r   O   -  ao w   N -J c&#13;
o&lt;          .q&#13;
oi    -,  -VI-r)                      ;&#13;
^    4D a CN   OI O -  UCYr      -1u e0t &#13;
1       I6~a  -       a a&#13;
6p-  we-ali&#13;
. i .  &#13;
C N  CZl &#13;
ui 11- *co             cv -1- N   r-  X7 co r . -a 0Dr&#13;
^;  c        }o  -  UZ Tn  - 01   a;  Ln -n N' In n&#13;
_ Z &gt;O a&#13;
LU 4a_&#13;
11^1~ ~ ~ r  tLoC,                 LO&#13;
U~~~~~~&#13;
J  4     _    .  O     '   '  '  '  '&#13;
4 -In    Qa el o    * -  -x  m r u) o O o  Lf lIn N  -*  -&#13;
4     a     Z&#13;
W~~ ~ ~~ ~~~ 0:  *z lw u OCK  )W I l&#13;
LU~~~~~  a L &#13;
a  LU~~~~~~U&#13;
Z       a ID 1 elN O   r- 1 vW O-  tC U7 NLflW&#13;
45    0  I   X   ........  _  .................  . ....&#13;
E     Wa '~   LUID J   Lf0VID St D v O  l  I N COIt'1 Il&#13;
6 ds   -    UN N N  Y @ -  a --  '  a &#13;
O    . a _  .- _ &#13;
U-      I    0      O&#13;
WU      I    L      U7&#13;
Z   &lt;D U. w ui  .5 tqu:a 0  uf tn  U -1 - UW 0&#13;
a         6  1  L Z Z .  aZ      ....&#13;
1     4 N   I&amp; x  -   - :   =  a t O  D O 1 &#13;
_ z,   Iz   .&#13;
Ix n     X -      z  wI0-&#13;
O La  U.a.  j  nx q- LUUc(Da(N  a  Na&#13;
CLO      Zw=W        ZD&#13;
0.       LU.    6    .    U  &#13;
I   C      1 n L   - P_ _  - -&#13;
a   4 0    U-a0        x &#13;
x     WX   &gt;O   z       &gt;x&#13;
I   )0&#13;
a            Z       LU       t&#13;
a    U       wU      U    InO  00o&#13;
a    0       U       U.   1-0  0.0.1&#13;
a    V)-UU   L n0UJZ      0- --&#13;
I      UI-1J -   0. C..   0.N Z   XZ  J&#13;
I     C. l.LJlU  CZO  _lU  O U  UZnJu,&#13;
a  t  Za1M IL 1  4  -  ~J  0 - &#13;
a N. sr U-U. u Z Z$  0 -Z i o  w&#13;
a  ,  LU  LU  _ 0    0.  c-0  E  Z &#13;
a U )&lt;oLuL     i-    U   WI--.- L&#13;
* 0   LU4ZI  U, *.   -    0C -&#13;
.. Z  LI   0 ..U F  )W 0  0 0 .J , LJ&#13;
a X( u L.u xZ  &gt;O( o 4 &gt; x z    c&#13;
a LU oIL-    U4L~Q  u -  Z U -~ I&#13;
E 0.                  J&#13;
a    0       o          0&#13;
a    U       tL         0.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Morocco&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       In Morocco, the balance-of-payments effects of external shocks&#13;
increased from 2.7 percent of GNP in 1979 to 10.1 percent in 1981 and hardly&#13;
changed afterwards. The deterioration of the terms of trade was the principal&#13;
adverse external shock, followed by the effects of higher interest rates on&#13;
Morocco's large foreign debt. Export volume effects were also unfavorable&#13;
throughout the period.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       The devaluation of the exchange rate was not commensurate with the&#13;
size of the external shocks Morocco suffered. Although export shares&#13;
increased somewhat, much more important was import substitution in nonfuel&#13;
products, that was induced by increases in import surcharges and the more&#13;
widespread application of quantitative import restrictions. This was offset&#13;
only in small part by negative import substitution in fuels, resulting from&#13;
the decline in-the ratio of domestic to international energy prices.&#13;
3.       The deceleration of the rate of economic growth in response to the&#13;
application of restrictive policies from late 1978 onwards led to further&#13;
import savings. The restrictive policies applied had only a limited impact on&#13;
the government budget, however. Thus, after a decline in 1979, the deficit&#13;
rose again and it remained in the range of 12-13 percent of GDP. At the same&#13;
time, credit to the government increased, both as a proportion of outstanding&#13;
domestic credit and of GDP with a slight decline occurring in 1982 as&#13;
deflationary policies were applied.&#13;
4.       The large government budget deficit, together with negative real&#13;
interest rates also contributed to a fall in domestic savings ratios in the&#13;
1979-82 period. The rate of investment also decreased as the decline in&#13;
Morocco creditworthiness made foreign borrowing increasingly difficult.&#13;
5.       Reductions in the budget deficit is a lynchpin of the program agreed&#13;
upon with the IMF while measures proposed by the World Bank aim at increasing&#13;
the exports of goods and services. In the event, reductions in the budget&#13;
deficit were below expectations while manufactured exports, tourism, as well&#13;
as workers' remittances increased to a considerable extent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 58 -&#13;
tD~~~~~~CI~      0 O         CS J0% &#13;
ea I         .. .I..&#13;
m   coi         Cs r-  %o        cs cT%&#13;
X N         _ ~~I -D&#13;
0 1~~~~&#13;
0%     Z Z Z ZO%-   -         Z OZ &#13;
0) r~  iOc'JOOc' 4 1  I&#13;
0         I       *&#13;
&gt;       I&#13;
00&#13;
0N -     -t -o u, _-It cr  cs O&#13;
-OX&lt;X    I   -:      &#13;
00  4I     C%C l 1 0%~  -&#13;
0%~ ~~~~ _I        I&#13;
0  0  o n o   o-#  0 o&#13;
'-4   O       -I -                        0 -X&#13;
C    ll 1&lt;  CS~  ,  U&#13;
w~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ,-&#13;
-~ ~~~   I-'    a0 xeoQ                 m&#13;
0%f   0VI0 crcn cn c%       -I Cn _&#13;
0     0    CS c _ - I dT       I -&#13;
co  z             -4           -4                     T&#13;
E-4 &#13;
o  bo r-      I Y   1 OcN0%-e'Ie'JCY) &#13;
o ,&#13;
S   Q   * . X . - .  *~~       * .       0 &#13;
0;  Irs  0..&lt;tfl ' ;  O C   C  -4 L  o&#13;
H  o  ^  &lt;  CS |  ,  co               X~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~c&#13;
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ -&#13;
C-                        c S0                     0D&#13;
&gt;;                                                0&#13;
X  tO r   o N Cr _ (S N  ^ coX &#13;
Pe         J e  I &#13;
4-   Cl                   -4       7&#13;
o           0~~~~~b  co&#13;
0:  0                       0 o&#13;
&gt;~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~- --          C.)&#13;
U ~~O           v     -               05&#13;
4 4 Q  C0 &#13;
CZ  4J ~  0  4   cI  0..  U)       0&#13;
&gt;  II   '-4  u-      m -i        L&#13;
eo  co D   * 0            e 0&#13;
0E'4 p0  . a)-4    &gt;. o U        co&#13;
0   -Li 0  tJPW    ) b          0&#13;
sL    0 C  C.             cz Cd a &#13;
144  -L (1 bOOC  &gt;j.j            -.4&#13;
a-4  4.4 U) -4  8 u  .- 4 'f to&#13;
Pj)  - .  4 4) 0 ,  Zo     0 z  C  0&#13;
&gt;   - D   0c '4I dt )C  04 0L  1&#13;
(   X0 0&gt; 4 0  Q 0    0   U        U&#13;
U)          U)0QJOm  Z  0 ):00&#13;
0  ~~~~~~&#13;
A4     en                              1. 4 U   :   C;  H  0  &#13;
0                          *           0 7C &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 59 -&#13;
4' N  0  n N  -   0 t  :D -r ) fC O  ON 0  0&#13;
w I-~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
U       IW coW0  N4 Q LnO 0  o O 0wm&#13;
C e *N   . ..  .....   ....&#13;
C o     0 0 v X -  -- C d  O   -  1 w m N&#13;
CZ  &gt;   lw CY CN L0  -  C. rf N&#13;
N&#13;
O 19C 1,                  a,&#13;
z&gt; &gt; -&#13;
W 4l&#13;
LU   '   -&#13;
N     N  .          . . . . &#13;
o     '&#13;
. I-.    -  Ur  O,~rW~&#13;
0         u -'   0  0  c0 N  0 0 0  00 r-N  - I CY&#13;
4   *C)0'   . .  ......'  ....... .. .....&#13;
00  -'~~&#13;
0s-  &lt; ' '  0   v O Un  O ~~~V-e  CO cn,  r  W. u l &#13;
2-    '   -J :)  CO)  - 0' 0 N  N - C&#13;
4  I  ~~z&#13;
4   0      &lt;cr.            .c&#13;
0  -'   IJ~~~~x -  U' - &#13;
NC  0:          U) m c&#13;
O  I-t-NO 1I-0 YLO LOY&#13;
Ul  tL |  _ t. UC)- 0N .. 0  --NSJOa  u &#13;
C   I  Z    IT - -      I&#13;
lz~~~~~~~L&#13;
Zi   *    Lwr sr O *o Na  r-&#13;
2 ~ ~ ~~~r 0- eV Ct'  1Z1 N  0  V) - D .0  r) -y 1   N- Cn co&#13;
z ~ ~    ~   ~~~ .   . &#13;
O          LOz4O  ON&#13;
U.~~~~U&#13;
U) )-       U    I 0 - v  11 U  N - N  - -  -  2&#13;
2      w&#13;
U     Lu     . _A  00&#13;
tLfn LA)  U,    0   -&#13;
U I-  C.- Z     o  o&#13;
Oj w   Q U   2  x  CA Uju)&#13;
Z ) 4U.LULU  UJZ  0  _  _ _U~.UI&#13;
Z  -a U.   Z w.   &gt; Z -  .  1R&#13;
a Z &lt;U. U.  &lt;  ZZO  0 W- O U.W&#13;
@- w w w  &lt;&amp; _L o: z z  o Z 2 L W&#13;
)  uw LU _w  4&lt; C      U.&#13;
U  X.0 ww      U v o--._o w&#13;
0  LU421-  U~  &#13;
I  U)  U7   Id U  )&lt; x o -J  U om UJ w  o&#13;
o 0   zw M ) wZ Za: w&#13;
J  U.E&gt;  0  C.U..  o   0n  0 . . D o o J&#13;
4  Z°  U) ,,~ uuw . J U  C. F  u '0&#13;
2  0ILU  ILgJ       -J'C.&#13;
cx 0-CC wZ wz    w wx Z 0 o&lt;&#13;
U  a 10L w  C  .00=)0c  ix00m0a&#13;
I  -  m C.-  0C.C. U. ZU  C.C0.U.Z U&#13;
x      ALxz  &gt;0&gt;(2  4  &gt;)&lt;   4&#13;
I   C. O           a.&#13;
I,_       &#13;
o     0        0&#13;
U     C.       C&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 60 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Pakistan&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       In 1982 Pakistan continued to experience adverse external shocks,&#13;
particularly due to deterioration in the prices of its main exports, cotton&#13;
and rice. The adverse terms of trade effects were excerbated by unfavorable&#13;
export volume effects and rising interest rates.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       Traditionally, the balance of payments effects of external shocks&#13;
were offset by capital inflows, supplemented by export promotion. In early&#13;
1982, Pakistan chose to break the traditional link between the rupee and the&#13;
U.S. dollar, resulting in a 10% depreciation in the real effective exchange&#13;
rate. However, largely because of poor harvests (cotton in particular),&#13;
exports did not show a significant increase until the following year, 1983.&#13;
At the same time, increases in imports moderated.&#13;
3.       A more favorable exchange rate and higher interest rates favorably&#13;
affected worker's remittances that have come to exceed $2.5 billion. These&#13;
inflows offset much of the deficit in the trade balance and contributed to&#13;
Pakistan's reserves reaching record levels.&#13;
4,       As Pakistan moves into its Sixth Plan (1983-88) it seeks to achieve&#13;
average annual growth rates of over 6%. In agriculture, which employs over&#13;
one-half the labor force, increased emphasis will be given to export crops,&#13;
such as rice, accompanied by import substitution in oilseeds. While the plan&#13;
has a large public sector investment component (mainly in energy), it is&#13;
envisaged to increase the role of the private sector through deregulation and&#13;
opening traditionally public sector activities (highways, airlines,&#13;
electricity generation) to private sector participation.&#13;
5.       As Pakistan seeks to consolidate the economic gains of the last&#13;
several years, it will need increased investment. It is recognized that these&#13;
cannot be achieved without increasing private sector participation and a much&#13;
improved domestic savings effort. The planners face a challenge to provide&#13;
the appropriate environment for this and to achieve at the same time the&#13;
announced increases in social sectors. This becomes increasingly important as&#13;
Pakistan moves towards national elections.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-61 -&#13;
to 0  0  It -t  C co  %  ' 0 en-&#13;
0  I   *  .  .  *  .  .  *  *  *&#13;
m   I  OCJ-c'J I &#13;
1-4&#13;
&gt; o&#13;
04    i L4O8C,4  -T%DPIr&#13;
!m   -4" --T 4  CI&#13;
¢)     -        -&#13;
Io o0  CS In 0 S C  o  *;t &lt;f) LM&#13;
o S&#13;
$4  a,~~~~-   -&#13;
0) oo  u00 CS4 ITr S^:&#13;
0~~ .   .  .  .  .  .  .  . &#13;
.  &gt;     -4&#13;
00               C~~~00&#13;
I                   0&#13;
00                         C&#13;
-4 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ L   0-&#13;
o  0    CI0NoLn0I4.!s  C4  -T .- c %&#13;
Ev ~ ~ ~ C  C14 -e} t  -&lt; ,r,  %n oa  a XrX.&#13;
W -~      C4e-  X en&lt; !s oO-&#13;
10&#13;
oad&#13;
-4  ~ '1-.1~I  I  0&#13;
-&#13;
0 vO        *  .  *  .  *  .*  *  .  -  0&#13;
*0    -8    O  J-t O- NIOD&#13;
04                                 0&#13;
o1                                  H C  O)&#13;
Q  1&lt;   ..... ..  *     ...      0&#13;
H ~ ~ ~ ~ .  A4  on vo Ut  lm  V S&lt; &#13;
O~   _   _  %0% I c_&#13;
0       0&#13;
4:                                4.4~3  4  L)&#13;
,~~~~~ CU         1&#13;
X   E x   o b12  w to *F &lt;  £   b1o c) &#13;
o       0~~~c  *-.-) I   0)  0. i  )~&#13;
0..  0  1  *     Po U  .    ...     0&#13;
0     04sw 0  -w ~ -  04  '0&#13;
14 luP  ci  0  -- A4       0&#13;
oo  4)  -.   0c    .  &#13;
0 4   UJ4 00  IU  0.  0  &#13;
,0  0.4 w   .4.  Ai &#13;
U 0 0 w 0  0_ _   0  CD  0&#13;
&lt; ~ ~ ~    OO U .    E-. O  US^_I s&#13;
&lt;:~~~~~~~~4                   X &#13;
OUx  1..     U  bO       0 -&#13;
-4               .          U&#13;
m~~~~~~~~~~~           4&#13;
H ~ ~ ~ z  UH.C  XV.              o &#13;
X~~~ 0.      00       U   UV&#13;
t;   X&gt; 00V.      V   0  00-&#13;
J  ~    ~~~ VO CUW&#13;
o~       ~  ~   0 _U              U &#13;
0     V     0: Q   *t *1   0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 62 -&#13;
WuCY N          4 OC 0  NOCN N   0 0 N&#13;
C~01  .   . ..  .   ...     . .&#13;
4 ' ' cN  -C 'ND  0 in  -c v -  0 o  O tD O&#13;
W(N  -c q-C')&#13;
f:C          im LoD-N   - 0  | -  0&#13;
4-         C&#13;
Lf  Cr      .    _  .   .&#13;
49 Ln  -  I&#13;
Z.&#13;
1~ w-    0   0 U N 7--m r   0 - -  0U0&#13;
MO  N     . c. ... ..  . .  . W- M .  .   L . . .  ..&#13;
I-   0          n x -   r 0  C) 0   W O N  &#13;
Y   W I 01 '              CD  M -  co&#13;
..      . &#13;
N  uI -     N 0  0  M M -  1- - W M  0  0&#13;
N~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
OW           Q  n   v v ¢ - 0 1  _ _ | _&#13;
W  1-0.  N  UWV-V-  ~D0O~O~O~Lfl  Ou U&#13;
W  U  ~~~I  ~~  ZU~~~OV-  V-NLt) LU  c  CZ CZ&#13;
W  C0  - '&#13;
--   .    _&#13;
N    0       .  .  .  .-  0&#13;
I ~~~~I  - ~~~~  0 1f~ L  DWWW  0fCL U&#13;
0    -r           UN0 '  v  U. LD U.  -  N  D 0O&#13;
W             W W WZ&#13;
ZW               -a OL - 1&#13;
s   0  1  -  ~~~~~w  1 P-  tt1-t  0  C )  zD1 &#13;
-r           q r ~   -   I  I Y  r &#13;
O ~ ~ ~  W -   )6(,N  N  N &#13;
D     W          WI O  = &#13;
WI      W4V&#13;
I    C   ~    Jf&#13;
v,  L.  -j of N       C0  0 0  N 0-  . . 0fl c f L 0&#13;
I        2 zmmwo    MM&#13;
1       &gt; 0  0 )       I) U. 00&#13;
0         U 10 -          0. 00-&#13;
I        lU  II I&#13;
I  Z    ll  W&#13;
I    C. W.JUU  2 &#13;
_   &#13;
I~ ~ ~ 2             V1iW  42  0  fWO-&#13;
I  C X  ZLL.~  4  -:       zJ tr-&#13;
I  I  W  WW  40    0.  1-f 0 0I&#13;
I   vw   c:W U.1  w   -II-Z  U&#13;
uI  0  W411  I Z0O-  -    -0- &#13;
I   Jf w&amp;1..J Q f( Q  1 Z Q  x Z 0~ JJ .&#13;
I    01 ZW W      WZ  2 c  -   oo-  J&#13;
I     IJtY  I1u  0 Z.U Z 0  00o -ZILo .&#13;
I   20  wwl  0.-o  L~C.  0. o ' .fij.&#13;
y W  1-O  _ W _       0C0- :£Z &#13;
I   X-  Q .- W  .0.u.2U  0.01 _-O&#13;
I  W  C0 2 W  U4W  I OW    I &#13;
I  J .  -j            - n DO OC  NI &#13;
I  C       -J     WQ  X   s &#13;
ZI  0  t S  0       0 wC &#13;
I    U     0.W       0._ 2   W &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 63 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Panama&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       Panama is a special case both because of its rather unique type of&#13;
economy and the manner that it presents its statistics. Thus the methodology&#13;
followed in the reports indicates that Panama suffered external shocks&#13;
amounting to 4.6 percent of its GNP in 1982. However this does not reflect&#13;
change in the fortunes of service exports which account for about two thirds&#13;
of exports. Thus the deterioration in the Latin American economies resulted-&#13;
in a collapse of the Colon Free Zone activities. Similarly the figures may&#13;
attribute too much loss to oil imports when in fact about half of these are&#13;
reexported under various service headings. In 1981, the export shortfall was&#13;
more than offset by the rise in interest rates on Panama's net foreign&#13;
balances. Panama had dollar denominated domestic borrowing that year equal to&#13;
4% of GDP. However interest rate effects were reversed in 1982, thereby&#13;
compounding the adverse export volume effect. Much of the capital account of&#13;
Panama is exogenous and to a great extent drives the current account. Thus a&#13;
macro analysis of Panama would pay greater attention to the accounts of the&#13;
consolidated public sector where adjustment takes place. However for the sake&#13;
of uniformity with the other countries, this is not given appropriate&#13;
treatment in this study.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       The policy response in 1982 was primarily to increase net external&#13;
financing and lower the GNP growth rate. There was also a substantial amount&#13;
of import substitution in fuels but this was offset by negative import&#13;
substitution in non-fuel products.&#13;
3.       The Panamanian economy is dollarized, so that the balance of payments&#13;
per se is not of paramount concern. However, the consolidated deficit of the&#13;
public sector is a critical issue. Much of the external borrowing in 1982 was&#13;
used to finance rapid increase in public sector capital expenditures, so that&#13;
the consolidated deficit of the public sector reached 11% of GDP. This was&#13;
reduced to 6% of GDP in 1983, primarily by curtailing capital and current&#13;
expenditures.&#13;
4.       Panama does not have an independent monetary policy, so that the&#13;
imbalance in its public sector accounts had to be redressed by curtailing&#13;
public sector expenditures. This was coupled with some improvements in price&#13;
policy, such as higher gasoline prices.&#13;
5.       In the short term, Panama was able to offset the effects of adverse&#13;
external shocks by first borrowing externally and then reducing the deficit of&#13;
the public sector. Reductions in investment levels were not very disruptive&#13;
in an economy which is predominantly service-oriented. However, in order to&#13;
improve economic performance in the medium to longer term, it is essential to&#13;
stimulate the productive sectors of the economy. Recent initiatives on&#13;
liberalizing trade by the Panamanian cabinet suggest that this is the future&#13;
direction of the economy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 64 -&#13;
Q ^   CO CJO o %        N0 ( &#13;
bo c o  .     .&#13;
0  I   'to%0%  Z        &lt;&#13;
~~.a0%  0  Ch(r .0  -cn  cn  T&#13;
&gt; N&#13;
¢-&#13;
0  I   *  *  *  *        &lt; *  .* &#13;
I_ _o .L Z       N I&#13;
bo co     cn _ n _ e-4 &lt;  .o&#13;
- I         *           .  .. .&#13;
a,        0 * L9  *. *1z C  .~ .  .&#13;
0%    Lf-4o Ur - %Z  0  IfcS U &#13;
-     0 O .O  I  n     N&#13;
%     co             -&#13;
-&#13;
ffi~~~~~~~0 _i * .*   9¢*&#13;
CO         O  £  I            - Cq&#13;
o     0     *   - .4         N ¢ *  .&#13;
Xcoe n a, r       D Z~ °O   Xtn en &#13;
1 -         0:   0i&#13;
N ~  ~   0'I       N       o.&#13;
00~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
ci      %_c sLA"' 0&#13;
00 lm en Ln M  z  co  m co~~~~~~*0&#13;
.0                                       co C0CPU0%  0-CO0&#13;
0 X&#13;
O   bOrsO 1  CD i0N   e _%             . _ -  e&#13;
0e  X     *  .  . 0  ..    *  .  0     0&#13;
Or-      0 Or-o I  U0     N__ &#13;
E  O                                   C C&#13;
-40 0&#13;
X :3&#13;
t;~~~~~~~~~0               ci a4 c3o&#13;
~-               In 4           0 &#13;
b4  CD              Q &#13;
s  i a toX  ;  cn cw     &lt; &#13;
e:   C: P  c H   od  C Z  _o&#13;
=w 4)0       0    0       4-&#13;
0.0L             0      0 w--  a&#13;
a b  d 0  U            4  0 4  o&#13;
&gt;-  &gt;    0          i Q  c  Q&#13;
P .  D 0 C :  C.'   0 -'   0 &#13;
m o  i   C.  0 Q4             . w  C4  Q&#13;
0.  ~ ~ ~ .3  .u 0  JJ 04C4            0&#13;
¢0.     0        Aze i.&#13;
0- 4c  "q   -H -4  0H       1.4  '&#13;
co-      0                 U  0&#13;
&gt;   0   e           0 &gt;.4    ..&#13;
co    &gt;  a-ai    a14       4.  0 &#13;
ri C4  .T =0010   o~c       09  0&#13;
CO  *v4 @ . 0 ..-  Z &lt;        0  0 &#13;
1N  _J .i N0 .   4-  0 ur     4.4 r1M_E  ez&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 65 -&#13;
W N '  cN  r-  N  O  - &gt;  tuO  N Y  -C4  -&#13;
Im       ..  ..  .... .......&#13;
&lt;  ' '  O   ~~~~ ~~~~~- t o N  IS F  D )-  m-   C l&#13;
4   as   0 o   sr  sr t  m N -0-  I ,  cIi 0 -&#13;
C .,'  -c         10 10  N! - i  0! 0I&#13;
m 0   1  14: 1  1   1   _   co_4L0 L&#13;
&lt;   _  I           c&#13;
&lt;   w   0  i fW  0 r    Cmn C O  OVOO&#13;
4            .   .   . .  . &#13;
c~~~~~l m ~   co rv rO-  N XOI  m cli u&#13;
O-  ar-    I - NC 4 - N i r m e&#13;
-2  &gt; Om&#13;
c  4I&#13;
LU      x&#13;
wi  I.- I.   W!  o CY cw  r-~-  wO6m  O(P0&#13;
m 4   C .    ... ... . ....... ....&#13;
-  &lt;   D  Z-WCN  r I  m r- -r  m  Cy CNe'J v N&#13;
0 0              7 I       7 I 7  I N&#13;
w  Z     CZ1  &#13;
2 -      -U&#13;
4          0  ,*  c 2  r  -C40L  &#13;
W &lt; _,~&#13;
4  I  0_  .  . &#13;
I  0  0  W'CNO~.   U, 01e'4,  ID  0I co  -.&#13;
t   I   0 4  U            7&#13;
W    I   w Y&#13;
tL *  4    -N I F - Om   - O&#13;
@~~~~~~~~~~~m m o m,  rD S-c  r-rm  v-szD&#13;
*   01  d-OeI  4tX0 0 * rr'm-dm-r &#13;
~~~UCW      W  I0O  -, _ , .&#13;
z  ,  Z~~~~&#13;
U   eVF O  0  rW C, v v u0 r   r 0  Cl&#13;
I- ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ I &#13;
0.  w~~~~~~~~~~~L  .0&#13;
0L0&#13;
O    .M  6 I   ¢    X  _ U..&#13;
4      S&#13;
U w u      I/ l-  u&#13;
4        -      U.&#13;
*  U, x l-    U     - &#13;
L,  2Z       w o j2 L  i- &#13;
,  w    u      O  00&#13;
§~~~~~~  ON  Mc OaNN cmr  r00 vN=NI &#13;
-  Z 0 o  o m 1^  l  U0  o  1  0  0.0.&#13;
Z  L         w   c  I  _ &#13;
0  Jc.) (L2 L(  U  0.ZLU.  Z  U,&#13;
2  4jW W  X  I   ,0~&#13;
C  ZLIJU.  &gt;O -  &gt;&#13;
0     w411i-  U  ,0I-  -  C.0  2&#13;
I   0&#13;
U 4  Z0&#13;
*  2 n 0'-  U, U  U,0 &#13;
I   Y    z wwwZ   w r w  c&#13;
I  (  U,w(  &gt;OX  4 W ~  CY 4 &#13;
I   0x   -       - n wZ   - -&#13;
I   Q  I       -5 -&gt;   L &#13;
0      0f 0W      Z0J&#13;
I    Z  WW &lt;   0.110 &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 66 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Philippines&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       Since 1980 the Philippines suffered from increasing external shocks&#13;
in all three categories, terms of trade, export market and higher interest&#13;
rates. The balance of payments effects of these external shocks equalled 6.4%&#13;
of GNP over the entire 1978-82 period.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       The initial policy response was increased external borrowing, coupled&#13;
with strong export incentives. While the export effort continued, under&#13;
increasingly unfavorable terms of trade the government had to resort to even&#13;
higher levels of external borrowing. Non-fuel imports grew as the real&#13;
exchange rate appreciated, resulting in a further deterioration of the foreign&#13;
exchange situation.&#13;
3.       Much of the increase in oil prices was not passed along to&#13;
consumers. Also, the Government budget balance began to deteriorate and was&#13;
further compounded by the need to bail out some industrial firms. At the same&#13;
time, the banking sector was pressured to provide loans on non-economic&#13;
grounds. With the deterioration of the situation, by 1982 and a fortiori in&#13;
1983, the Government was obliged to slow down economic activity. At this&#13;
stage a foreign exchange crisis ensued and the situation was further&#13;
complicated by an uncertain political climate.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 67 -&#13;
bO 00 r  ur N    0      a co e&#13;
I      ** ... .  .      .. .&#13;
W r,   m  n  I_  _ n  r _ &lt;&#13;
-     0^  -  I  -^     C.'  -&#13;
&lt;:~~~~~- -&#13;
Cs I      se    Xnec&#13;
0)  C.') ~ '         C&#13;
CO     ..  .     .      ..&#13;
a) ~ ~ ~ 0  (*NI I    '&#13;
4-4-r      o0 0cn0  -     n-T&#13;
bC' 00~         - DXOe &#13;
o  I     . .  .  .  .   .I  . &#13;
4-4  a"  ~ ~ ~ ,:Lgc4c4L&#13;
- X r-  cn  .  I  I n   c  _&#13;
En &gt; o             _&#13;
¢ -&#13;
0,4&#13;
v-44                 _&#13;
0"   -     XU C'S  I _' o- -&#13;
..         co e T Iv  cD CSN-N4 &#13;
0n-4    lfl O%4O%  -I    -  C4&#13;
o     c&#13;
4-4&#13;
Ek o ~~~~~~esn  Is _u cs n  &lt;   1-&#13;
Z;         _-4'C'''r  '0Ct-&#13;
.0 H         0' CnI           '  -&#13;
CO  O                   -&#13;
z&#13;
co&#13;
o-  0  &#13;
bO r- 00  f ON '  XLf  0  *n L %C&#13;
o      ~  ~   -~2 _    _              co&#13;
0ZC'1  II  '0 C.4&#13;
*04:~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
H           U)         0.~~~~~~~~~~~~~Q &#13;
0)       o    H     0)&#13;
bO  ~DO  -.         6   &#13;
,c X c X v  M     c      DW&#13;
xO   .JC e       0.. Cfi   C O &#13;
:     *                 . 0D X   v  bO  o&#13;
U  )  @0  0J0  0D  C.s  0 i&#13;
A  m          U V o C Q X X   v -  - C&#13;
W  rs Q W X *n Q &gt;o  Qw O0&#13;
Cn *.*~,0~~)-4  Z iCO       C&#13;
~ WQ. 0vU        t e          U co&#13;
H   C:00 -~   o  CZ  r_ &#13;
M X   W W c a W  0 U u        U&#13;
COW     Z 0COOCO    -~&#13;
¢ &gt;  oz &gt;;  ea    -H z  " &#13;
&gt;  '-4    - U  = 4  O  Q C   0 Q  _&#13;
C O O OCJO          C      U&#13;
144  C  g.  W         0:&#13;
~~  U)OOI-.0U)0  Cz~~  0ZU)0)&#13;
0  ~~~~   U~&#13;
0 .. - .    * ¢       * *     0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68 -&#13;
w  N   1  N 0  C1 N  r- OinC4 -  oO rO  N&#13;
4    C |  ZD  1 11n CD  OC~O~I U tN 0% ;  1 NC'  4 U  -&#13;
&gt; a &#13;
Z N&#13;
IL  4&#13;
2&#13;
0.           7a r~ Inn CeD 0LnrDC   s aO  InOU&#13;
-    CN  .   .  .  .   . .  .  .  .&#13;
JI  0 *NO~t o 1   X   N 1'1 -  U') -C C-0 &#13;
-    O I  -  v NCN  ts Ne* -.- r- v S -&#13;
0.. &#13;
(N&#13;
(, I  . X    .  ....  .. . . ........ . . .&#13;
a   4 w      IC tn.  ,la CD   C 0&#13;
_- Z         M0  1  4 0Ln7&#13;
N sr ~ tr~C IDl'~ 0IN&#13;
O~ W NI    Y&#13;
-z  &gt;O I&#13;
I'  C   _, . O ' &#13;
OW&#13;
CM  t0.    0  (.CC'C IIC.0 (    w rDvO   pZ  q Nvr----&#13;
C 4          Z&#13;
U      WI  0    0   - L C CD0co'  CNqr--P.&#13;
W~~~~~~~~~~~~~~L en I4     C&#13;
z Ic I   -  -   f fl  0C  N --v I   ( M (N M&#13;
tt   C       X 0 N4  Y 0 1^N- m U) -n  N. -7-&#13;
46         2 &#13;
2      I     WCN   O0rI-' tCO&#13;
4        .  U .   . -.&#13;
41    I    W w0r     C0(0    0DC4&#13;
o  - v i I  -  C  r-  Iv   I U -  N f  n&#13;
im    0&#13;
r-    w  *   Z *-,  -  cZ  * - - - - &#13;
-  I   a ~~~N Nl  P-  CI N4 &gt; t   I  7&#13;
IL  I   C&#13;
I.  I&#13;
oI    C     Ul~  2&#13;
NI  0  WI,~~~NO~~  ~CD~~NC')  -WIfl( 9A n&#13;
y.   wz       w      t&#13;
I    40    CMW        ts  s&#13;
4U      L6  In  CfIf&#13;
n    -       U wZo- Z-&#13;
I Q     CM F  tL-      00 _&#13;
z    U. w ui   -aQ   Z  w  0  J z&#13;
* ZI               w uZ W UCZO _   I &#13;
U. U. U. -61 C  _ J  0 'I _ : M&#13;
I    1fl1Ifn U. U.  w, Z  1 0  -Z  a U.&#13;
I     U1-I)  W.I W W  C-O  O:  N I U&#13;
I   4 C 4X OW W .   4 _ 0  I -_  W&#13;
I  In  CM  CMCM  4-0ui Cc .  I-2.L&#13;
I  X  I-~~~CM   ' 0ILI  41-1-1co 211.LD -&#13;
I U  aMCM  I-   U 0. -     0W&#13;
I  0   I P-. C  nO-  -  0  1-  Z&#13;
I     t C CZ  WI Z at) C  l 0  JM M IUi&#13;
I    On L1I-. O   Z  W   ..J  In W Z  2  J &#13;
I  -J  IM.I-  0  0&gt;1 a.   O U  0. . U.  U&#13;
I  C  20  A  0.'  u.  0.  NII..0E&#13;
I Z 0x        x 1C 1  WJM I&#13;
I    _.7 W  UZ IJ t WZO  Z UO0i&#13;
I W( FAM(  ,.z O W   &gt;sO :Oa  :ooZo&#13;
I  CM  0VC .  U  X Z &gt;-O  U  C X.S&#13;
I    0.    _         _&#13;
I    I     0         0&#13;
I    o0    0         o0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 69 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Portugal&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       In the 1979-82 period, the balance-of-payments effects of external&#13;
shocks averaged 1.4 percent of GNP in Portugal. This result occurred as&#13;
export shortfalls, owing to the slowdown in the world economy, and increased&#13;
debt servicing charges, owing to higher interest rates, more than offset&#13;
improvements in the terms of trade.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       Portugal's export market shares increased to a considerable extent in&#13;
1979 and in 1980 as its exchange rate depreciated in real terms. The&#13;
improvement was reversed, however, in 1981 when the real exchange rate&#13;
appreciated. In turn, trade liberalization undertaken as part of the policy&#13;
package negotiated with the IMF in the late seventies contributed to negative&#13;
import substitution, but this was more than offset by import savings&#13;
associated with the decline in GNP growth rates.&#13;
3.       On the domestic front the growth of the money supply GDP ratio&#13;
declined after 1978. However, after a temporary decline, outstanding credit&#13;
to government as a percentage of GDP rose as the government budget deficit&#13;
increased.&#13;
4.       The rise in the budget deficit was translated into foreign&#13;
borrowing increasing Portugal's external indebtedness to a considerable&#13;
extent. Also, the budget deficit remains high; its reduction will be a&#13;
priority in the program negotiated with the IMF. At the same time,&#13;
nationalized enterprises continue to represent a substantial burden for the&#13;
economy and their reform is long overdue.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 70 -&#13;
a) e4,&#13;
*C~~                   C4 cI4 &#13;
CJ~~~           -&#13;
bC    -4c'.i0O  O  I  -  -  ICS &#13;
0  I   *~~~~~~  co  en  *0 *l  PI&#13;
"I-4  (      -4&#13;
01      . .                .&#13;
&gt; o    _          _0  I  I  -9  -  ei&#13;
¢~~~~-          -&#13;
Ie-   o         e'J     O  r _&#13;
0Q CS&#13;
bC S   ON  0  Z r- cn  co  rq m &#13;
0     .  .  .  .  .  .  .   *   *  *  02&#13;
&gt;co&#13;
0! C) fc Lf0 %.-4   -  &#13;
CD        C&#13;
CS%    cn U0n on 0:      00 U  CSIDo&#13;
-c oo *   -4 .*    -&#13;
~-4        -4                 04 &#13;
Cg ~ ~~ ~ ~~~~~~~~~~~ as 08 q -N O v  N&#13;
z&#13;
-4                             0~~~0&#13;
o%    o-4       L o  ,    c &#13;
I- 00      . * r   o   *   *   *  *  *  0&#13;
-4   0%     _~ O~-4 l/4t 'C14  4I O  _  _0&#13;
eo-    _) 'T  ON   I  _     C&#13;
0  0          4        -4                0&#13;
44&#13;
O ~Or      Ou-.4r     'C O n__O   DU&#13;
0   CD                      *  . ...&#13;
a)N-   0 .4C0 N-I 0' _   - X 'J&#13;
-4     I  -_&#13;
&lt;-4                           0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
z&#13;
cn                                 I.'~~~~&#13;
A4H  e   &lt; oo O  -00 .ab  cs0&#13;
p  b  04 00&#13;
Q)  llc~~~~~~~~   .11a)J-&#13;
O4      aE r    0 00   W _4     0C&#13;
O    001    *  M  @  *-. -      0 *  *&#13;
C4   A)  4J 0D  O&#13;
-4  kW  UO "* I- -             a)&#13;
w  o  4   a$i     03U   0&#13;
¢                            ~   ~x e2JJ.E-  . U0&#13;
tg  J.J  5   rbO (L  U  OA)  0 c&#13;
&gt;              0     *d 0-&#13;
*t:  ~~a)0~CW-    Z C   C04&#13;
&gt;z2  J-J45U 0  0  i-  0  -&#13;
&lt;  44~Aa02 4i- ~&#13;
1-4  4-4UXv4 o   L9  44  oO  4 04  0&#13;
c) 0 0)       ca  O C       a)0&#13;
0 ~~~~ :U 0             UtX 0 &#13;
O  .- C  *  0  0t 0 C &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 71 -&#13;
|; N &gt;   a) -  X NCl tq- {D1) o  co 00 &#13;
(, 0 a  .  ... ..  ....... ...&#13;
&lt;~~~~~r I- -n  r-uzO C)n  to co 7s  7 0 7u c1&#13;
ct~~~~~t (D 1  C4  Ln mn r  C4 r' In0- --&#13;
4a -  ,fUO   ~ ( O&#13;
ul&#13;
wOa  U9aL ct UZ 1(D -   a 0  N (D   O&#13;
(Na   ...  .           .&#13;
0a C  OaO@ , m0  Dcn( t.OWOaf  o Clrw~&#13;
o-  aZC,L      O o o L a  Nan L  a  a  a&#13;
aN    a&#13;
0a   a     in r  -  m   o qw t- n  0q c Ol r&#13;
a   Oro      .  . ,       .   .   .&#13;
&lt; 1 1n  E  N)  C v N N   -  tN 0  0  &#13;
_~ Z a  aO  o  WUaC|  O~tD('-,  * ,&#13;
W  4-a_&#13;
(N  tY   at * (&#13;
w       a  -  ulr0    ov  m Or 0-t  0&#13;
.J  4   a  .  o&#13;
0 _0  a *   ,0    -  Safl aX-O P &#13;
2 -    a    a       a  a 1 1 l  r &#13;
&lt;    a   2&#13;
C)'.  a   w&#13;
4   O      . .  . . .... .&#13;
o     a   L6U0CC  U(NON-00 aaa&#13;
ZE   ,    w O   QOU:bs   bs&gt;@t&#13;
tY ~ ~~~~~~ 0&gt; 'm 0  t- r 1- 0  -t N  - - -  -v -&#13;
a    -       '  UZ aU) a-   7&#13;
WU    a               Ln&#13;
0.  a~~~~~~~~~~~~U&#13;
aX   t-r- XS0 4N&#13;
a  I|  O C2O w- t ! 0 u O N   (',&gt;  u  0 m&#13;
(-a  0  W'W( V   L- f l0(-N  I'--  flZ   ("&#13;
f i   WL    0 &#13;
a  Cn  a  C a  &#13;
0 O&#13;
aLA     a &#13;
a  .~- (n0 &#13;
a  Lfl _-   U;--  O.&#13;
a .  ZuiU      in     A  it&#13;
a       Fn    U.  fO  0 0&#13;
a   0  Z        W.)  U  'I,  0 .&#13;
a     -iflifl  wC       U.&#13;
Ua 0.   ..UU  U  U  (CLlJw&#13;
a   O 2u.U.U.  4t-      X&#13;
a  '-  W J  w   v 'ZZ Z 0  C XZ I- J&#13;
I    m 4 1. 11  2  0n  _   VW W , &gt; U&#13;
0 ZWM 1ol  &lt; _ JZ  Ou-=  D &#13;
a   U. &gt; wi  40 0 n  0.  0   U.aU.&#13;
a    -             4I Z  O U Z.OU.a&#13;
a  0   W  W- W  C-O . i  -  Oi   2 _ , 1&#13;
a    00 Yw           CZ W-   iC  z  &#13;
i  XO mo  m -  Q  CK F - _ O &#13;
a o 20 w n ac  U. U  0. o  _.o ZU&#13;
a    Ak-i oQ .a &gt;oX      Zw-&#13;
a  J  W     W     inJ C Xw&#13;
a  W I-0i o  w  z  o0 0t OO  O&#13;
a  (C  ini)C c &gt;0 oX7  4L Z )C  4 &#13;
a xn  w  x Z :.  U4xn  c UW-  x &#13;
a  w . o          - - Qci-   vu &#13;
a   G     _    &#13;
a   :E    J       0&#13;
a   O     O.     0O&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 72 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Senegal&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       In the years 1979-81, Senegal benefitted from improved terms of trade&#13;
which more than offset the adverse export volume and interest rate effects.&#13;
Export volume and interest rate effects continued to be adverse in 1982. With&#13;
the terms of trade showing a smaller improvement than in the previous years,&#13;
and export volume effects becoming increasingly adverse, Senegal experienced&#13;
adverse external shocks. The situation was aggravated in 1983, when terms of&#13;
trade deteriorated.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       In the 1980s, the government sought to stimulate exports by various&#13;
subsidies and to restrain imports by raising tariffs. Much of these efforts&#13;
were frustrated by droughts although there have been some improvements in&#13;
exports of phosphates and fish in recent years.&#13;
3.       On the domestic front, some attempts have been made recently to curb&#13;
government expenditures by cutting back on civil service recruitment and&#13;
investment projects with long gestation periods. Some effort has also been&#13;
made recently to reduce the drain on the Treasury caused by producer supports&#13;
for rice and groundnuts and by fertiliser subsidies.&#13;
4.       The new government in 1983 sought to come to grips with the steady&#13;
deterioration of state finances. However, yet another drought in 1983 set&#13;
back these efforts, severely reduced groundnut exports and higher food (rice)&#13;
imports caused further deterioration in the balance of payments. With&#13;
lessened access to external finance, the government will be obliged to provide&#13;
better incentives to stimulate a rather poor domestic saving effort and pursue&#13;
appropriate opportunities for import substitution in food and energy sectors&#13;
and export promotion in manufacturing and tourism.&#13;
5.       The intermittent nature of both domestic and external shocks makes&#13;
policy planning quite precarious. It would seem that some form of counter&#13;
cyclical investment programming could be incorporated in planning to help&#13;
cushion the boom-bust cycle of agriculture -- particulary for groundnuts.&#13;
This would pose certain difficulties but the experience of other countries&#13;
susceptible to intermittent shocks may be relevant.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 73 -&#13;
W e&#13;
W  I    *  *  *  .  *  .*  .  .  .&#13;
C4  1'..0O  Z&#13;
p N   _  N  &lt; I  ,        _&#13;
4)&#13;
¢z                -&#13;
&gt;~~~~~&#13;
co CI  U  *  *  *  .     *&#13;
z            *  .  .  .  .  ¢  .  .  .&#13;
0%    U  o 0  _ &lt; o  Z   ,_ _ &#13;
-4     I *  .               - &#13;
coo  _0 Cs   CJ ,~ ,_&#13;
_%    0%-~U%O% *    *  *&#13;
0%    _i    -EC-.  I &#13;
-4&#13;
U,&#13;
_   0    ~~~~~* .   *  *   *  -  *    0O&#13;
-                           0-&#13;
.0&#13;
-    0%    ~~~~~~~~~~cn4C'40co SD  CN'.4  0&#13;
P  a~~~w&#13;
_     (V co         c oN           0f&#13;
..     N~~~gs  *  .  *  .*  * .  *  -  *  0&#13;
.0  o   -     0  a,4C   I~ IT    -4 &#13;
0 Z-&#13;
0                              r-QJ' 00&#13;
C) 0  I   *  .  .  -  -  ¢   *  *  *   0&#13;
od%                                      :&#13;
:~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
U,                                        Li&#13;
A40~~~~~~~~&#13;
*41                             0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~$&#13;
bo                           O&#13;
-.4  &#13;
m~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 3&#13;
OW4~~~~~~~~4&#13;
4    C0   0 W  U&#13;
-  4)   0)        b   S &#13;
-~~~~~         0   1i&gt;z   u 0 -H I&#13;
0 ~      C     -   w           3.     0&#13;
m  -4 0 : u4 4  Q  &gt;         0z  w&#13;
0    ..-4  4) c a0 a  c&#13;
Q    4a 0 Uw   U             0 o&#13;
a f v wm:S        u0 &#13;
W cn -4 sH -4 w    C&#13;
-W      w      40 &gt;O      0&#13;
m     Q~~)  -  0 to4    -&#13;
&gt;  I    1-4       9-4 C0-    J .&#13;
Cd   0&gt;    w Q &#13;
0  4)0. 0         0     . w&#13;
, , 4  1 I )  CO PI  2  000&#13;
-&gt;  c            0  4) &gt;   -4 W.&#13;
0  .* * .           . . .O&#13;
_ cs                           U, nq  v &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 74 -&#13;
W CN'  -  0 0 0 LU  O  U' 0 m  Uc  N - UD&#13;
Co   )    0  .  .. ..   . .&#13;
I'  -  O) -0  U f(Dr 1- 0  &#13;
&lt;        0  co o 0 Nt0  - co  1-  -&#13;
Wr- *NCN -     0 08-  -'&#13;
4 -I&#13;
-, *~C~) r             (NUDa  i' o `I&#13;
W        U   tW Lf  sJN(  flO  LU7AW  ID  O U &#13;
Z   4'   0  -G) N n  O  L0O-0 co  D CO  0-&#13;
.N  .   ,&#13;
Nw   c&#13;
0    W -' .   0*vNt   U  J:)1- * &#13;
w O0*  ' .. ...... .......... .....&#13;
4  .-.L/~   O '  l0- f 0 -O ¢NO M  N N N O&#13;
00   -s W    (0vN  U) UCO f O) 't &#13;
_ z  :&gt;c            In N-&#13;
W-  C-    w        ' I&#13;
O W  0'      . &#13;
2       w  0  CO M 1-  t- to  to co q- ON O &#13;
C'S    ,      c'0C ' - C l J '&#13;
co  u  co 0 l r| co I  D  r- w a) 'D0 O   D  IT vs&#13;
&lt;  _n VZ  0X    " Ln U)mr co co) F   1 0 0   v Nv N N&#13;
_~~~~~~~~~I  Cj  * . *s0  &#13;
0 -        u.   &#13;
z     .      Ln m eq UF  m tn  0D n   O   0 co C co (D&#13;
S~~~~~~O .  w  O- CD. W. -  c- 0l CD mn  &gt;  00&#13;
tY   O  .   0~~~~~ 0 N  Y -U In r  n Nl co  (D  . . .'&#13;
1L~~~~~~~U co On I1 O n - I &#13;
=     I          Is&#13;
U.&#13;
0     _J&#13;
-  F Xq t O  C f)C O C 0   LO 1 ul LO :&#13;
-       z  -  0 t       -&#13;
-'  0  z to w  0  cO a -,0   M -,cN&#13;
*,  a.,CDw wU0co ID -CD&#13;
I        o&#13;
, ~ ~ ~~~ _-        Lt  VCL&#13;
*     C-      U  ~ V)  V) V-&#13;
x Y   z      w    C'  tY  '&#13;
I  n I. Wn tn      V1 0 00&#13;
U     Q.     I   C-.  0.0.I&#13;
I~~~= w°           C' t)C W s 2&#13;
* .  U w V U  Z  U  XZ/ O  _ L_&#13;
Z   1UW.W u Z 0  - V' WO - w -&#13;
I   Ua W L1 U-  VI ZZi- 0  - zI L UW&#13;
I  VC  W  W W  C -On  0.  C-FO D .'LJ&#13;
I n Y   u w   _  L  I. _ D  0. Z IL&#13;
I  U  X O W W  C-F _   C'I-'- C U-OW&#13;
0 W &lt; - ° 0            Z&#13;
I   'D 4  w- 2 vL)   2  w2 A  .   &gt;s.&#13;
*  n  LU .- Jc  V &lt;  . X  o J 0 V) O co W JU&#13;
o,0 Zo w Cu D w Z Z CDD Lw-&#13;
4  Z O  lA  w0C  L  c. -V)  Q. u OL  L D&#13;
UJ  -20w  C'  ~ ~   C'0O~wC_&#13;
I -Z  o  I- U w In w C..JLOU W .C IJ&#13;
ui   2 ' O w' U,  o o 5 o cx  tr ooDo C&#13;
CZ 0.i    O. tL   U. Z  a. U, ZU&#13;
x Z &gt;- C x W &#13;
c       -        _&lt;&#13;
0     00&#13;
U   .        a.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 75 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Sri Lanka&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       Since 1978 Sri Lanka suffered severe external shocks as the increased&#13;
-oil import price was accompanied by stagnant world market prices for its&#13;
principal exports. In 1983, it seems that the prices for tea and rubber are&#13;
finally staging a recovery.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       The policy response in Sri Lanka was to maintain high rates of&#13;
economic growth, primarily by external financing. Consumption levels were&#13;
sustained while the real effective rate fell to 88% in 1983 from 100% in 1979&#13;
(on a 1976-78 basis). This led to a mediocre export performance while&#13;
increased trade liberalization gave rise to some increases in imports.&#13;
3.       Sri Lanka's ready access to foreign aid, together with expansion of&#13;
domestic credit and in particular credit to the Government, helped to produce&#13;
a strong growth performance. However, government finances deteriorated and&#13;
the trade gap widened. Following his re-election in late 1982, President&#13;
Jayewardene introduced austerity measures to stabilise the economic situation,&#13;
reduced various food subsidies, and increased gasoline prices.&#13;
4.       Political disturbances caused some economic disruption, particularly&#13;
for investment and tourism. However the large Mahaveli project which seems to&#13;
be yielding its long awaited promise does not seem to have suffered. At the&#13;
same time, interest rates are still not attractive enough to stimulate higher&#13;
saving efforts so that the country still remains heavily dependent on external&#13;
aid.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 76 -&#13;
0 .3&#13;
bO     -  %c ~00 C O'c~c&#13;
to xI  boe &#13;
C I    . ... .  .        ..&#13;
0)      en  -4 _  o      -4&#13;
&gt;co  Ca_^_ &#13;
Cd -4  c  0&#13;
O .-4-,...  .   -  .&#13;
bo 00  X0 o o&gt; ,_ Un n  o)  _~  'T&#13;
0 r,  ad_C__ &#13;
&gt;0      &#13;
.¢o          |  _&#13;
oo~~~~ .           ..........  .  ..&#13;
H    o     o o '  e a  0s as -  IC_ &#13;
co   co   co~ Ci 1&lt; xIl_ 1% &#13;
a   _   cm  7 _ _I  -  &#13;
-&#13;
e ~ ~~~~~~e&#13;
01      Q% U   %O sD&lt;X   -1  .&#13;
0'~~~ I         _-4&#13;
-4~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C  -&#13;
Z                                   co&#13;
D   O' _0r       ~t .r-|I e &#13;
.0  z&#13;
X-  X        r-co          c&#13;
0  1 &#13;
4  ~-4        C 1  ON       -4 e  e _e &#13;
0    -&#13;
Cko !-C 0- ' -4  -a  C-  -4CDr&#13;
41: ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ 1&#13;
-  -4&#13;
0'    0~~~~~.          co4&#13;
N:   X  f~~~~i oj&#13;
CO  -.  C.       0&#13;
0)  a   H                 co&#13;
bO  cn~CO  -.             . c&#13;
P 4                 .0m&#13;
0    a) 0    0    cn   00&#13;
c   O  c-       -  Ua    D&#13;
x~~~bO H) e&gt;j. _ .&#13;
H   4-   ".   _ .-   Z  C -  0 -4  CO&#13;
&gt;  v  o &gt;    c7 "o W0  oHt&#13;
4   J)  i P .  J J  J1.i  0   Ci   C.)&#13;
? ~ 1.  U). &gt;  C Sctc COv &#13;
43        :3 &gt;%  W o  co c:Ci W &#13;
&gt;  - ) 0 o-c JU  0  v) CJ &#13;
Lw rW * 4  4 e   -,,  0 -H  to o+&#13;
4          00) U z  i  vUC&#13;
&gt;          00 Q Q r 2) &lt;   r c   o  a  &#13;
.  ce0 &gt;               U 4  U  eu&#13;
0    0  s   0  c) cD   W a  o  a C: &#13;
H~~~~~~&#13;
a               C) 4&#13;
0    : -*           ...     0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 77 -&#13;
W N '  -  000o  u D-Ir - u)-  -0O- Oc'&#13;
0I  C N   0  -  N _, -  -&#13;
W i           - I  _   , ,&#13;
&gt;0&#13;
C-&#13;
4&#13;
z&#13;
4  ~~~~~  ~~~O ~ C 0  mC!0'  t2'IW&#13;
H  Iq  ~C4  2 C C4 CNW CU  ~LflIWY0&#13;
-  0'  ~~~c'n  0           t &#13;
CY&#13;
Y I&#13;
w  .  In  ( r'I  c0-WifL W  0  &amp;fLn C&#13;
Z i  I&#13;
Ci 0-    aJ                  C4D -co J V0t   )  D(&#13;
J   l, N  |  . ..  . ..    . . .&#13;
a: 4  -  N~N   u e t-  N VJ v  iN v  U1 t-DCID &#13;
-.   0  el  0    0N  CN --rl-&#13;
0y   _iI     I   _     I    I  I&#13;
-z  &gt;01&#13;
I'.'  1.O.  I  10  I-Lfl r u,00U,InPfl   00C&#13;
w       x&#13;
-3  4 a   ..  0...       .............&#13;
0* ^  C*  -  n vN 000C1InN t - O V - I 1&#13;
4  .-.U z 0'  Cl@  N L 0N --&#13;
0F~~~~~~~       ~~~~ wr  cc  CZ cf b|&#13;
00 ZU                       I &#13;
..  e I &#13;
o tr        -.C.-    I I       I&#13;
oW    I   0     0&#13;
W      I    Wxt t  In   nIII &#13;
&lt;1~~~~~ ~ ~~~      ~~~~  LA uu  0 I- Cw  I-. -I&#13;
2~~~~~~~   U.U_U  , J:a &#13;
4    -3&#13;
w  0 '  tru~~0I-       C 0Chi&#13;
C  . OI X  .*    ^...&#13;
i-I1      n NO V)0t 0  OCC'  -eOU  -XOC)ON&#13;
0'   - N 0   YI J  10  N I 1   0 &#13;
1  I  O- O        II I-I-I&#13;
LA  .  W)x   -&#13;
* If &#13;
0 -     W -  'D N  I  N -&#13;
Q. ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~U&#13;
_,              U   - _   ,,,,&#13;
I         2 W&#13;
Z,fl         W OZ   11&#13;
I   V W.U. UZ      -IO  .&#13;
I  U,     W W 4 0 ~ 0&#13;
U,  _.-.j  C,~1  ...0  O1U.&#13;
I  4C0  U  0.1  UU  0.  .U0&#13;
I  Z X 0         t' 1- U,J--  I  I' UI-J I&#13;
*   YI,~   WZ WZ W    =  t&#13;
I  110   W 000     VW0O O &#13;
I   O     0W U4W  2  UW-  L &#13;
I   0. -7          - IW C:S 1&#13;
I   0     0        0 &#13;
U       0.       0. &gt; t &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 78 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Sudan&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       In 1981 and 1982 international cotton prices showed some improvement&#13;
but they were still below their historic levels. Thus, Sudan continues to be&#13;
suffering from adverse external shocks.   This is further compounded by&#13;
interest rate effects as Sudans debt obligations continued to mount.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       Due to a combination of factors, Sudan went through a very difficult&#13;
period between 1978 and 1981. Much of the investment in the 1970s seemed to&#13;
bring little benefit, while prospects for the main export crop, cotton were&#13;
bleak. The Government sought to increase external financing and restrict&#13;
imports, but its efforts were further buffeted by political instability.&#13;
3.       In 1981, the government announced increases in producer prices for&#13;
cotton. However, an overvalued exchange rate led to further erosion of&#13;
Sudan's export market share. Increased military expenditures and a steady&#13;
decline in the already meager domestic savings effort left government finances&#13;
in a precarious position. This was further complicated by a misguided attempt&#13;
to move to a fixed exchange rate in early 1982.&#13;
4.       Following the inevitable crisis, 1983 saw the Sudan under an IMF&#13;
program. This involved a devaluation of 44% and strong import restrictions.&#13;
Credit to the government-was restricted, even though there is some evidence of&#13;
continuing high levels of military expenditure. As a result of these&#13;
measures, GNP declined by 2.1%.&#13;
5.       This year Sudan should benefit from further increases in cotton&#13;
prices. There is some further attempt to rehabilitate the Gezira cotton&#13;
scheme -- which has challenged policy makers for over half a century. However&#13;
the brightest spot on an otherwise desolate horizon seems to be the prospects&#13;
for significant oil revenues.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 79 -&#13;
b 0   0  co  -T         en x-&#13;
I -&#13;
a) r  cliCnC~  I 4       CN4&#13;
0~    ¢ .       z &#13;
co)                    C%&#13;
o\  Z - co "D 0  0  Z  oC In &#13;
Cu  I  * . - . . . ¢.     .  .&#13;
cl Z&#13;
X b   o CS e  _,  _I CN&#13;
¢) C--&#13;
bo 00  *T   en .  % IT .  ¢c&#13;
- r     x -4e'JC) 0- Z    -N I&#13;
_) r-0c -  CI _,,&#13;
0&#13;
a  a    os-b--t&#13;
o  . _  0 N e _,- _N ,&#13;
co&#13;
J-I&#13;
o     co     CS X   _ _               Cu&#13;
-    0'   iD vD vC 0\ CS b   xO 'O O  0&#13;
m     t crEn  a: r  00 no   Z   °°  &#13;
C)~~~~0l             .             z&#13;
o-    X 0~                              X .&#13;
z  aI* -         .'N~   ¢I  --&#13;
u  0                          I 0  0  D   C0  .  z Z  O  &lt;  N&#13;
00&#13;
co 1 &#13;
Z                                  Cu~~~~0;C&#13;
z: &#13;
cjc&#13;
0&#13;
1-4~~~~~~~~~- &#13;
0      -H~~~~~~~&#13;
4~~~~~~~~~&#13;
Cu            44~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
4-4                               J.J~~~im ~ -&#13;
O     Q     p  a~~~~C     U      Cu&#13;
co   M      En 5.44  5-c&#13;
Cu  . P             0      Cu&#13;
bo  cDc &#13;
0&#13;
Cu  XC  -     m  v &#13;
bO  4  C  -.               Cu. &#13;
x&gt; cn  &gt;      in v   EvAi &#13;
. C  C   Q.,¢ .4&#13;
U         wC  s   o  o&#13;
X   Q C)   O. CA-) 0 w  c   C  0&#13;
¢ W    4i :Q Qf4 Q  0 t  s 9 e &#13;
4  4 C    Cu 4-   Cu -4     '-4&#13;
X '    uA 4i c  W 4  O  i     cu&#13;
&gt;.2  r-5-i.14   wC$.  14  CU 0  &#13;
&lt;  J-4&gt;a)a ux  --     U 0 04 c   z  &#13;
c5     &gt; Q  w  u  --!  4-4O O &#13;
0 0 0 o  U  o~Cu&#13;
Cu c e           0e  e.&#13;
- Q O Os.d0~ L OO   OcZ C     O&#13;
a~     ~     C   o-       U&#13;
'-4  _I-a Ub_  sr   t &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 80 -&#13;
W  N.           - -  UI D -   V  4 In r- -  I 0  IS) N UW&#13;
2  0    o   *  .  . .  .     .  .&#13;
CZ       (OI) 0      (co) W  m -N&#13;
&gt; a &#13;
C  - &#13;
c&#13;
U) F    7w   C! -O   1) U,  C) tN tM   00&#13;
C9  M0 1  a4  0 r- 00 N-  l -V  -  m 0 CD M1 ZD&#13;
o   W1   (N  U 1 '0  0 CO.-  - C  NLO N &#13;
N            0  c    c'  i  -  ONO ~  C'r)  (N&#13;
Or   u-            r-  C4P &#13;
-z &gt;a m&#13;
.   .4.&#13;
U         -&#13;
0N    C-,    ful e    r - -     u &#13;
Ow &#13;
-a.  c   ~  U O |) Ln r  m v co &gt;  0  N rO to 40 &#13;
of   a       0 1 -  - r x  N  (4 |  1 &#13;
-I  .4  1-tI         _,  ,  &#13;
_~~~ ZoO O&gt;~c              U(wf1&#13;
LU~~~~~~~-&#13;
-      C -  '&#13;
.4         2 &#13;
.4  0' ~~~ z . .  .  - &#13;
I  WI  l (N  UJO  P.  r- O N  r   -  C;  Wq'*(N&#13;
O  W    I  Y      UC   I  I  I  I  I   I&#13;
|  UC     t  0  0  0  ;1  1  S  N NO&gt;0t&#13;
w       ~~     ~~~~w in&#13;
I . C   ,   O ' &#13;
U.&#13;
c   NI{n  a) |   0F (N  W h  (N u N0-  u0 ( n 0&#13;
- Q   I      -  S  -.        I&#13;
I_   *  ~W&#13;
C   O,  .  X     _        .....~~z  .  o&#13;
1   0  |  es  w :1 U) 40  vw  L6a  ^  0  0  0-q&#13;
IU G  I  U. -  -  Y-&#13;
in &#13;
1M ~ ~ ~ i     I- O         9- 9I&#13;
WU    -       U   (fl0  00&#13;
ZGU  U  U  U   .  9 J.0.&#13;
C1-(fli  - wZ      0-- Z&#13;
u i - w   a.-:a-. s O&#13;
2  u.0           -  i  nl&amp; O   `r '&#13;
-    W4I   (/09    ;  09  2 &#13;
00   2woc   wZ 2UDW-&#13;
I  J  Lh.)&gt;I9-0  -   a. in  m  0  0.in(LU..J &#13;
I   U  0   I-.  0.9  U.0.~ZU  a.  'NIU. Z  &#13;
I  2i  09- ui  U  -4w  Q  u.IW in--J&#13;
l   IflW   WZx WZo  LU~WZ0&#13;
LU  09L- U4       W-  &#13;
I          c.  -     -  n  u &#13;
I  0     0         0 7  0&#13;
*  U     0.        0 . o- -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 81 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Tanzania&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       Tanzania continues to suffer substantial external shocks, due&#13;
primarily to deterioration of its terms of trade. Prices for its principal&#13;
exports, coffee, cotton, and sisal, failed to recover until 1982 while the&#13;
prices of pertroleum imports rose.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       Tanzania was unable to increase external financing that is largely in&#13;
the form of concessionary aid. Correspondingly, adjustment to external shocks&#13;
was through economic slowdown and strong curbs on imports. At the same time,&#13;
the Tanzanian real effective exchange rate was allowed to appreciate so that&#13;
export shares continued to be eroded.&#13;
3.       On the domestic front, heavy expenditures on the Uganda war and the&#13;
large losses of parastatals posed a severe strain on government finances.&#13;
Much of the deficit was financed by money creation so that inflation&#13;
accelerated.&#13;
4.       Agriculture, which supports 90% of the people, continues to suffer&#13;
from a wide array of problems. Drought, disillusionment with the established&#13;
forms of communal organisation, and unattractive prices contribute to a&#13;
steadily deteriorating performance. Negative interest rates are reflected in&#13;
poor domestic savings.&#13;
5.       Tanzania has achieved some success in particular areas as literacy at&#13;
85% is one of the highest in Africa, 50% of the population now have access to&#13;
potable water, and great strides have been made in the distribution of medical&#13;
and health. However, much of these gains may be lost if the policy makers&#13;
cannot correct the general economic malaise.&#13;
6.       Recent policy pronouncements suggest a tilt toward agriculture&#13;
through improved pricing and a larger share of investment funds. Export crops&#13;
muy benefit from attempts to correct the fall in the real effective exchange&#13;
rate together with some improvement in world prices for coffee and cotton.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 82 -&#13;
c _n a -              o&#13;
cv I           .... .4.... &#13;
~~a' r- W_ &lt; 0      _0.......&#13;
&gt; Z&#13;
o  - C - O vD Z  z  Z z '&#13;
C)~~~~~~~~'  %-  I         C&#13;
bO 00  CS &lt;7 c CO N r-    C  00 r-&#13;
v oE   N  o  n  e  £~~~~~U- %  Z  Zo &#13;
X~~~~~~~0 rv4 o:  T N__ &#13;
&gt; a&#13;
¢-   ¢&#13;
co    00N   N                    0o&#13;
N   oo      ¢  S        *~~~~~~~ . .&#13;
Z'    a'     o( Un  0 x   Z  ZC:  U&#13;
E¢ o  C      ONL-a             OON _&#13;
oO    _     ao CorJ -d         o:J '&#13;
b~~~~~~~~~~~~~~r ,  ^  N      ,CS4&#13;
E-4                I   -&#13;
-  -4&#13;
E r-:               *            .  ...0&#13;
¢  e     rs ~~~~~~~~~~oi   O~ r bc  O   X&#13;
Z '   ulu4r-.a'Z  z &#13;
O *                  - - &#13;
o           -      I &#13;
z&#13;
0  i0&#13;
O  a bO   O    C- -  00     -   CO 7  &#13;
c;  v qa  o o xo _ o ~~~ ~ ~~~~~~~~~~~zl~ z  ^ a&#13;
&gt; a,o_ &#13;
Pn                 0&#13;
Z                                         0&#13;
1-4           C)~~~~~~~~-&#13;
CJ0               00&#13;
C'                     C&#13;
Pw           4)  ~~~ ~ ~ ~~-Li  0)J&#13;
40c              4-4O  Q&#13;
.C-'   C  Po  .14     1-i&#13;
o                                        30  =   0)   0&#13;
P  4 ..)  '-              0&#13;
0)  ~          t  a) &#13;
&gt;  -  &gt; 0  4 -  w4U.-  c  -  .&#13;
rn  &gt;1  0~- PO 0)U.4  emc&#13;
¢i   4-C   C.         Cf c&#13;
O.    u 16  0 W              u4E  0&#13;
C X  0 ar_ Q.  E   -c CU&#13;
;~~~~~~~~~~~0  U3  A-)  m 4.    v $ &#13;
C-  CJ  C         S&#13;
Xs  u ebOJ     uo bO0        0&#13;
&lt;4  0.H0) ~ bO)  - z .&#13;
&gt;  )  CL) IV  w  W  C         -&#13;
C/ i a E  0)0&gt;  co  4  ±  4C 44&#13;
-Q   P Q J-i0ro)O      o&#13;
G) 0  0 O c    ¢ )   _       C&#13;
. e LJ-lUJ0)flU&gt;  -4  Un&#13;
a- 44~/94 v ,4~  bOn  &gt;  9-9- CXo&#13;
cJ cD H          C  J-$.r 0oQ H C &#13;
; ~  ~    U0   Z   Cn0CuO   OP  ) &#13;
&gt;D QC c4))~ )-4)   0   u) C-4&#13;
CEo      &gt;           t5 E     0 )a;.&#13;
Qs  Q C               4vOX  OZC   Q&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-83 -&#13;
WUCy N N  1r-    ( Nt-  C v v O O  N v - Lou&#13;
0   ( '  O   tNtC.N 0-  G   O ID  w D r- O C v&#13;
CZo|                r. - eD r  - v Iq q CN&#13;
&gt; 0 &#13;
c    - &#13;
_ .C&#13;
Z              v O 0   CD CO m Wun -  co mO Cr-&#13;
4t    (N   .  w   .  .        ... . ..&#13;
N     mI *    ( NL~ 1 N N 0 o m I  - N N r a&#13;
2     C    )           -w  LD   tvC!  O- } &#13;
&lt;     _,&#13;
(N&#13;
m     co-     CY m n r~ m V -o-m 0 C v m'  m&#13;
(N  -  &lt;, , m  mr N N  S) - - U) v  CN v C1&#13;
4  .U z  Os I  -   I C - I      *UO  Cr&#13;
O l.U cc      Y&#13;
4       I     o&#13;
1  ..         w    &#13;
C    0'     2 &#13;
'4-      0      0~~~n &#13;
CO         .,&#13;
U, _         4&#13;
2         ,   0    rm m0 q  LOO ur-O&#13;
Li.        2  .   2&#13;
ui~~~~~~~L&#13;
&lt; O | t x ~. ^ ..&#13;
IL     I     U*  O&#13;
P.-       Lu4 &#13;
*     U, ,!          U .-&#13;
a  -      ui c  : C  aMvCNr&#13;
u      Lu      '4   c'O  00c4c&#13;
*                    w F O N n &lt; U) m rt LO0  o M  a.i NN&#13;
0LA,  .              0 Z.&#13;
0 *  Z  0LLWW 0  '   U.l2-  0  -   L nL t)  -NN&#13;
_,   a.JL., _ /Z~    0 ,Z _.&#13;
I  L               U &#13;
*  U  X0W u  w -   a.9--ex&#13;
0 cLu4Z~-  u,   U.-   0  2&#13;
Z  a.~~~4  Wj.-ZLa. &#13;
ui    v    U  z          n  v) en&#13;
0Y 0 U-  .2    WZ  Za  Cc&#13;
.d    hL&gt;  0 v.f 0o w z   o _  _ _&#13;
a a -w Q  a- z   z     x Zv:o&#13;
Iz  ua.a.J w  &lt;0z  o   -uD -  wZ.u.&#13;
Lu  0 w -  04W-   ~~~~~~(  Uu  -'   .&#13;
x.     -&#13;
0    . 1  0        0:    Z&#13;
I -   -U  1   VI 1   C) CD  O  -Z O a  . I  W&#13;
C, v  ,z           z zwsO   a ona m w&#13;
O     w c  U,  *    o _o &#13;
- 0 m Cc w F z v: 0 w a C,-&#13;
I   O  I O   Z W tY D  W. U  Z  M. Mt:D &#13;
|~~~~    ~~~ 0 xL M&gt;  &gt; O a  &lt; :u &#13;
a:    ui C:t  WZt=    w  C  ZO&#13;
z tsow2  ooso    zooD0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 84 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Thailand&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       In 1981 and 1982, the prices of Thai exports deteriorated to a&#13;
considerable extent, particularly for items like rubber and tin. On the&#13;
average, there was little export volume effect. These adverse effects were&#13;
compounded by the impact of interest rate increases on the external debt.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       Thai policy has been traditionally export oriented.   At the same&#13;
time, part of the development effort was financed through foreign borrowing.&#13;
At the onset of the economic slowdown in 1981-82, domestic and, in particular,&#13;
government credit, have been expanded, requiring increased borrowing abroad.&#13;
3.       There followed a major rethinking of overall policy as articulated in&#13;
the Fifth Plan 1982-86. It has included major reforms in fiscal policy as&#13;
well as for industry, energy and agriculture. It has also necessitated&#13;
institutional change. Broader-based taxes and improved collection led to&#13;
increases in tax revenues to 15% of GDP in 1983. Energy prices were increased&#13;
and protection of domestic industry was lowered. On the institutional side,&#13;
some efforts were made to reduce the heavy losses of utilities.&#13;
5.       The higher domestic mobilization effort, together with some import&#13;
reductions due to a modest deceleration of economic activity, meant that&#13;
Thailand became less dependent on external financing and, incidentally, was&#13;
able to command better terms. As it moves towards the mid-eighties it is of&#13;
interest to see whether the major new thrust of policy reform can be&#13;
sustained.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 85 -&#13;
to X0  %D  &gt; r-o C1 Ln o%   _&#13;
0  1&#13;
X  ~ ~~~N   o  C' en  00  %o  _ Dc&#13;
&gt;~~~~c   tn      _&#13;
or     0%  -t-IC' &#13;
zC -~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
01 %0  N _ % eW  t_      o  (IN&#13;
_     X                  C'-  I  &#13;
0 S&#13;
WOO  X  0%0%~O~'i~  Coe  CS 4&#13;
0  I    * . - . - . *.      . .&#13;
or-    0% e -i - _I  esJ     -s&#13;
&gt;                 _&#13;
&lt;: -~~~~&#13;
z&#13;
Ics o  C_  ae~ lo  Cls  Ci  cs&#13;
X-4       *  .  *  *  *  *  *  *  * &#13;
0%    O O iD  r  u&#13;
-   0%-~~~I   -4L     e.4 &#13;
I o~~~~' CSo  oUnC   C&#13;
01*        .  .  -.  .   ...-&#13;
Iat,  'T oN - ) o 4 N cl -4 -&#13;
-4&#13;
X      *  .  -*  *  .  *  *  .  .   0&#13;
00~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.&#13;
0r    r* a  o  a.  . *      % *  *  *  0&#13;
co&#13;
4-4  0%     -.0 ('4 aseNc4  0  -zr u,0 &#13;
2:          C) - 0 - 7  I  CY)   -o  &#13;
00&#13;
E-4 z~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
00&#13;
EZo     .O-   00190c~~4f&#13;
bor-0    0 O) O 'IC 0  cD  O 4 L _U)&#13;
O  I    *  *  *  *  *  *  *   -      e&#13;
Or--   o  _  ^  I  (**&#13;
ce~~~x &#13;
10~~~&#13;
0                        -~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
o                   4-&#13;
44                  0&#13;
4i         0       4&#13;
P 0e          U       0o&#13;
I-4     0     ~~~~~~~04   J C&#13;
n a    c           &lt;    &#13;
M ~  ~~~ u    )             co&#13;
X Q  C      1&#13;
0     C c -4          0 a 0&#13;
WO  tD 0              E.  2  0&#13;
C    -.-  0                  0 &#13;
W 00     01.   0   D  O&#13;
x 02-n  . e-       -. Uo  E  0&#13;
co  4_  .Ci)          - , &lt;   C&#13;
a 4 0  w " &#156; WM  c  w  0&gt;  &#13;
04J.4O~    i      bOO        0 .. Cf &#13;
r  ~ . ( U -40  LZ  .4  1-4  04  .1&#13;
Ai    U0m &gt;:        W P..  A. i&#13;
vL~~~f     c  %  Xo  c  z  to.&gt;A:.Xe&#13;
&gt;    .  O          CCO  X  )     U&#13;
m 2 v o C  Q Q...D   U ~C4    0&#13;
&lt;£W:   J0JiL     0  4J1X &gt; ~ 4.30 &#13;
&gt;:    4 *.             4 C  iv o &#13;
S:  &gt; 0  v  Q 0  0 C &#13;
e c e ou &gt; et e X   U  e ~c..4..&#13;
-;                C.,:&#13;
o   ....           ¢             0. &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-86-&#13;
JcNi N   (N -  - O O N Q O  O  CN U7 to&#13;
Go&#13;
4    (0 ~~~~~Lm  -  L  () D  l  r- 0  C') (D&#13;
CN  .  ...&#13;
- .  - 8!-I.  00 N   CN v  - - -   - * -&#13;
4   - -       (' n  CNcN&#13;
a  M- wt-'C,&#13;
-z  &gt;o'.- &#13;
W  4&#13;
0 U &#13;
- J  N     LO .   .  .~  . ~  .~  ...  .~  .  .~C  .   . . .&#13;
m  ~    ~~ co  I 0) IC U'  U, ol Ln0 (r LO r0 0  X&#13;
c r     V) (D -  r   NN -- &#13;
I   _,~~~~~~U&#13;
- . 4  .   O       7&#13;
Q0  U J - '  ID  ZCn t  L O   l  IJ lOLl V (  U 110rQ &#13;
4  s ...Lf  ... . . .....  ~ C-  ci&#13;
co            &gt; I) ui  '' r-  N, -; u' V' O'&#13;
~~~~~-  00  - ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~n  -a&#13;
4        Z &gt;&#13;
W~~~~~~~ C- -- ,x.   -O   'c&#13;
I    C'~~~  W'~~~ C1   o wL  o  L0  0(OnO&#13;
_ ~     (0 , ~  _0l--&#13;
O W       U.   U ' c        7&#13;
J .        0    0 svO&gt; NN/DNXN .vtC&#13;
0.     (~~~~~0.u&#13;
J ~   ' C  2_,  O  '. &#13;
m~~~~~~~~t Q   a I¢  n uz:  - Qu)Oe&#13;
a' U&lt;N       WU0I ZU&#13;
w&#13;
4t  Ou '  &gt;. .  ..&#13;
2   Q,  n  W - v v  1 CZ0  ui Nr O 1  x O  tnO&#13;
(0  LPI ~   z0   i &#13;
ZO4  LL W w  Z 0/ '  Y r-&#13;
a:   ~ ~ ~ U,   I-C     -  --&#13;
o ~  LU  U. tn&lt;0, -   00 &#13;
U. U.      U.  z0  U.0.&#13;
u0 I   W         0&#13;
L)  LU  LU&gt;  0 0  IC n -   0.  0 . O)   W 0  c&#13;
Z '  W   - W IU   I  0 __&#13;
1/   |    (/')&lt;N  Q  -JO  I/)O(D W  'U U -&#13;
- .J 'J&gt; I  0! -  0-L )  C 0N  0   I '  &#13;
U -0.1  0.0. U- zU  Q. 0..z U&#13;
LU  01LU-~  U4w-X  &gt; O -&#13;
0a  W   X  -  &#13;
I   I  &#13;
0      0        0 V&#13;
I      0.     1 0.   M &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 87 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Turkey&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       The balance-of-payments effects of external shocks increased in&#13;
Turkey from 1.5 percent of GNP in 1979 to 8.2 percent in 1982, averaging 5.4&#13;
percent for the period as a whole. The deterioration of the terms of trade&#13;
was the principal influence, although increases in interest rates on Turkey's&#13;
large foreign debt, too, were of importance.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       Turkey instituted far-reaching economic reforms in January 1980,&#13;
entailing a large devaluation, the provision of export subsidies, some degree&#13;
of import liberalization, and the freeing of administered prices; the reforms&#13;
were accompanied by deflationary measures aimed at reducing inflation rates.&#13;
Interest rates were freed in July 1980, but the full effects of the reform&#13;
measures were not apparent until the military takeover of September 1980.&#13;
3.       The measures applied led to a reversal of the decline in export&#13;
market shares. At the same time, import substitution in non-fuel products&#13;
continued, albeit to a lesser extent than beforehand, as the depreciation of&#13;
the real exchange rate was accompanied by modest measures of import&#13;
liberalization. Import substitution in fuels did not occur as the ratio of&#13;
domestic to international energy prices declined only slightly. Finally,&#13;
import savings were effected as the gross national product fell in absolute&#13;
t-erms in both 1979 and 1980, followed by modest economic growth in subsequent&#13;
years.&#13;
4.       After increasing in 1979, the government budget deficit declined to a&#13;
considerable extent as measures were taken to limit the rise of public&#13;
spending. But, with the continued credit demands of the state economic&#13;
enterprises the ratio of credit to government to GDP continued to increase&#13;
while the opposite trend was observed in total domestic credit.&#13;
Correspondingly, interest rates rose and the financial position of the private&#13;
sector deteriorated&#13;
5.       Reversing the deterioration of the financial sector is one of the&#13;
policy priorities for the new Ozal government, instituted in December 1983. A&#13;
related problem is the slow growth of private investment. Also, after&#13;
declines in earlier years, the rate of inflation increased again in 1983,&#13;
necessitating the application of restrictive measures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 88-&#13;
£ x   o  a0% 0%'o x0%  '-&#13;
0 I     ...... *      .     ..&#13;
@  b   CS _  e  _  |  _ .-i  C'&#13;
.R4~~~-&#13;
,co   _       , &#13;
wc7%    csrJ             n0&#13;
s: _&#13;
W ~ ~ ~ U CS_s,ns  _E &#13;
co  I4         -&#13;
.  .  . .  - .  .  C*&#13;
.4C J-   4t- -im_   0%  LA  %O&#13;
-4       14-   C  -4-C4  &#13;
0 &#13;
0o    U' .O~-'O  uN X             C&#13;
E-     en  e   n   _       '- _n&#13;
00~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~*&#13;
al  . &gt;o  _ i _&#13;
g ~ ~ ~ ~ C  0 Os _: 0   cn X4C&#13;
-4     . .   .  .       .4&#13;
_4         _     --   C)  en _r &#13;
ad  0o      r--J)  O   _  u0 Co       C - en&#13;
CO     °l,   0-4C  IC' x        IU£&#13;
0      _     _- 4e- &#13;
oi 4~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
8)      CI                       CO4(1&#13;
Z                            w~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~o&#13;
rn oz   _   as _  -  I -  -            0&#13;
01~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
&gt; ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~144&#13;
0~~~~~~~~&#13;
1-4~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~4&#13;
cw             m~~w &#13;
bo   0  --               1.&#13;
8-4         0.~~4  0        . &#13;
¢                       C O&#13;
o  ~ ~ ~ ~ c 0 Po  .4      1.'&#13;
0.4      0    -a .  0)       0.)&#13;
z   &gt; 0s   O CS   8) I            0&#13;
U]                                 X~~~&#13;
o      0      0 0   0&#13;
rn  4 Q 090 C -  -  tot&#13;
w0  z         m 0       c&#13;
t.  QC  Ci &#13;
1-4  44vtn  0. -4 bO  Z  r    0&#13;
4i &amp;Zgz  i $ 0  LJ)4&#13;
4 o  c X &lt;  z  a  c &#13;
01   0  C 0     0  ¢ o C&#13;
O &lt;QJ0    gmCu 0 -4  U&#13;
-                      1.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~4&#13;
4c   L U 4        C4 9 QtnSQ! &#13;
0  *c °e *                   0 0eX U XO 0.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 89 -&#13;
U tN  V   0 N el  al v CY M LO N  P-t 0  It  0Xe&#13;
W   a     O   b  N   N UN  r' '  N UrO  t(&#13;
or        C-  N  ICYe 'InLf  INCr'ULC'r&#13;
&gt; I &#13;
C4-&#13;
IN  C~Ci   1 WOI ~   -O 1r- 1 IO'q&#13;
W     IN  N   J e'  o1-  0 'e CY c   X m  N P-0co&#13;
ft   0X' *-      - rX  N  '- J' ( N  '&#13;
~~  4'  ~~  W~~O~   O N IfWLO  0  w r- 0&#13;
C-  ftOl      CO  (N _ 'C 'Wf N  r  nv vNI' 'L&#13;
O~~~~1-  WC-'I   N -            n &#13;
W   I&#13;
&gt;&#13;
C..&#13;
IN            I&#13;
W 1-      0 u(f W  -C C-O   0   n 0 r- rD -  to ( n n &#13;
_J  4      .&gt;   0  .&#13;
co a-   ,         oLm  N  )       n&#13;
J~~~~ I-,    J &#13;
S  10   (JI I   VX r-  N   I r) N CIO  r v  m N  -  t&#13;
4       2~~~&#13;
-~~~~~' 10                      eV m m&#13;
4x    0'     )&lt;.- C!. ~ -U  9 ~1 &#13;
_     w' I   C~  - IO,ONI        D~O'&#13;
I ftI    v  W m v r  1 0 US W N JD ON   0 m 0 1'1 rW&#13;
t   tR *   ID  ~~~N  Y N-  r, ID -  D |n &#13;
o    _,    1,,                    co P'&#13;
I    '     0     0&#13;
ft     '    C&#13;
W        W~~~. &#13;
w Cn kna    10M -          ) &#13;
U In   Ln el  L Jn W  rJ N 0  V t-  D N &#13;
C         *Z, *- 7 ....&#13;
a.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~U&#13;
C-i - W U) Uf U_  w  0 U ° o - c -IU O&#13;
_'    ft      1 -C N  -     I&#13;
U.  U&#13;
I    U.U    zU             .&#13;
4      L.. 4CL           L&#13;
I n               CZ&#13;
_      C,      In&#13;
CZ Y    Z        W  w   -i &#13;
I   L6 W-          1^ CZ  O X  O O - &#13;
*  ,n  z4  m   w-  Z E D &#13;
*    In  0  w  Z         o-  U--&#13;
I  Z  S U W W  C    -     ft W f O  t W &#13;
CZ E      u       u. 1  C  _  I a n z 00&#13;
0W  Ca     1-  U     . 0 0 U.  . U&#13;
I Y      x W  _ IL-   C _d  x I &#13;
*    I I- W- W   Z       0- --W&#13;
I O  ..JW QU C) 2t  C.) UZ  0 1   _   O 1&#13;
I C~ ZIUU   4 V)  O. 10'..Q'ft W &#13;
*  X )  )(LUL X   1-  C)  ftIX S   C&#13;
*  0  LU41w-  I_)OC  -  -  0w-  :E&#13;
.   2   In  a.-   LL.   X  '.l&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 90 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Yugoslavia&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       Yugoslavia continues to experience increasingly unfavorable external&#13;
shocks.  In 1982 the terms of trade for its exports deteriorated further while&#13;
export volume and interest rate effects were additional negative factor.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       After a substantial borrowing in earlier years, Yugoslavia has relied&#13;
little on additional foreign financing. Most of the adjustments have been&#13;
through strong import restraints for non-fuel products and a much reduced&#13;
economic growth rate. At the same time, the continued decline of per capita&#13;
income each year from 1980 through 1983 has created increasing social&#13;
tensions.&#13;
3.       Domestic savings effort has remained strong but investment decisions&#13;
have been complicated by political considerations at the republican and&#13;
provincial level. Under IMF prodding, some effort is being made to move real&#13;
interest rates to positive levels.&#13;
4.       With less access to external financial markets and a contractionary&#13;
monetary policy, the recession is expected to continue through 1984. The real&#13;
effective exchange rate varied within a narrow range, with little success in&#13;
export promotion. Last year exports to the hard-currency area did increase,&#13;
but much of this was achieved by reductions to the Comecon group.&#13;
5.       1984 is again expected to be a difficult year, with higher&#13;
unemployment and falling real wages causing steadily rising political&#13;
pressures. Nevertheless, indications are that exports and industrial&#13;
production will show some gains during the year.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 91 -&#13;
to 00   .  Cn -4 &lt;  O ,__&#13;
X   ¢  - -¢   *      ¢  -&#13;
_  _ xD    ~   ~   ~~- IC',&#13;
bOXC- 00                en U &#13;
&gt;ON    O  X   _  _ &#13;
w  %&#13;
H¢ ~ ~ ~ ~ - ¢n cl _ - cI co -tSC&#13;
00 CCSC~ _     r'        (',&#13;
(/2a        .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .&#13;
O     o    08 CS j,.. en  o O  OC&#13;
C-  _  ON  CI    n I &#13;
&gt;4&#13;
1&#13;
00  0-     _         C'     c-JO r-°&#13;
0"j   -,c   % o c',   v-co&#13;
o  C9 r-_   C'1  c',&#13;
-~~~~&#13;
ai    oo   a   Co Oo  o_( &#13;
C;  _4 C%  XT In -Y oM C)     I N CY&#13;
Z   oul   o  es cs  vo  l_4 oo  ,¢  &#13;
-z&#13;
C.)   r_   *) .s               * OO st &#13;
~~~~~~~~~-4 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ -&#13;
w 001&#13;
14' _0 Cn  -4 r-  -1   Ln  cs&#13;
q~~~a cZ ONS'4&#13;
¢  &gt;~cs                             C&#13;
-4           2~~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
a                                     0&#13;
.3                                    :3.&#13;
co                  o &#13;
4-4~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-          Li&#13;
zD ~ ~ ~~~~~~~~~ P  C  -&#13;
J-j4.&#13;
H ~  ~   c    UL C)mS&#13;
O       $     t~WD  u- &#13;
04           44~~~04        U&#13;
1-4     4.J      Li~-             11&#13;
to uto I-            Q)~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
0.   -   1-4  0)         c&#13;
CD  a-L  c )               co&#13;
X~~~- u     z     n&#13;
o  JWt  0)L    to a)  0&#13;
X  C7)4~i. U-   '-.  U     02C&#13;
&gt;z Itz  &gt; c   4: w oco  A-)  -L&#13;
w   14  Co       0&#13;
an  u  We0Cu      0t &#13;
o 4 j R  &lt;  CJ  X   bO  (D   C u  J&#13;
(/2  &gt; X  o m cw-4  Z  &gt; a)&#13;
W      &gt; uC   .  _4 CU&#13;
0    00 ow   0i . =.&#13;
4:   .0 L  (00 &lt;   O :: &lt;O+t&#13;
&gt;                0 0  zD  zD~  d  C e  1 -4&#13;
OJzDO O  OW ED [s  O Z  C   )&#13;
0                        0~~~~~~ 0 - &#13;
o                             0a  c S&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 92 -&#13;
we'd' -  U    MqDwO oO'DO  woo1 00&#13;
a I      m    m O' 1:~ O  -  -- O&#13;
C   r- _,&#13;
&gt; &#13;
CN  C'~        ~ 01C ~   C'OW', O&#13;
tf   a N,  .  .  . . &#13;
O ~~     t: s Fa--  --l  O s O  oo  l- -&#13;
~~  W~~~~~~I  0  ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ DW  C O  U  L Le 1f(DN&#13;
-   U '  -  Cl fl- co  - c- ,r 0 I  u C&#13;
0r-  eew F          c  n&#13;
-z  &gt;O I&#13;
&gt; 4'&#13;
wi  9-..     U0d-        q    OF  O&#13;
. .     -'    0 *C&#13;
-I.  ,.,   , 4  X&#13;
-a          in al                 eqtItsIt &#13;
4s t      Z^ &#13;
U-    ' _,&#13;
O    -' I  '- Y&#13;
U-    '    0     07 |  - es  a ^ . . . . . . .&#13;
J  &lt;  *  CO a'  c"  I U, a' uN M. To 7 M 0  T 0  7o t  -co&#13;
C     '   w&#13;
|   |  40  1 rJ  U')  1- a) t n tD X   U   GO -  (- W&#13;
0.    '      .   .   . &#13;
p.      u Iw U0  v CZ YnL-   co 0   co  co U7   14 -'O&#13;
O   M  I-  L.  O   I&#13;
1L ~ ~ ~ C    I. O   4&#13;
o   I    z**   2   .&#13;
a.0. I&#13;
4  U.&#13;
4     W&#13;
*    0 .U              0. Z.0.&#13;
mL,                 M.  x xr -ntDII &#13;
_tnU,  wZ        0   - - ,&#13;
Uk--  0.-&gt;     IL C"-.&#13;
0. .IWU U  - Z3 Z  U  x Z U, J 0&#13;
Z  -aU. WW  42  0  - Uuo-'&#13;
0  Z U. U.U.  49  -  .J 0 .&#13;
a. ~W U..  U,z21-  Z -U. W&#13;
n WW W W 4-0   .I-   U.&#13;
U     xww&#13;
ca  -  L,.0   -  0 &#13;
M MI!.4  .  )2t      J1&#13;
&gt;OXZ MDW     &gt;)(   4 &#13;
-J  U.&gt; .  4 -  Uw- 00 0U D-&#13;
O         0&#13;
I  ..         J0&#13;
Y- M0.  0   L Z   U  0. r-LLz&#13;
xn owx  &gt;On   -C w ZO Xz&#13;
I ~ ~ ~ u WL  J    U (.  .) Z () X &#13;
I Z C 6 W W  Z O  _0WO Wi&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 93 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Egypt&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       Net external shocks experienced by Egypt have been adverse but rather&#13;
low on average. While it benefitted from favourable terms of trade, this was&#13;
more than offset by negative export volume effects and interest effects.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       In the late nineteen seventies Egypt became a significant oil&#13;
exporter and benefitted from increasing revenues from the Suez Canal and&#13;
migrant's remittances. From 1979 to 1983 the real effective exchange rate was&#13;
allowed to fall from 191 to 111, or a 1976-78 basis. The appreciation of the&#13;
rate exerted a strong negative impact on export performance (non-fuel) while&#13;
imports grew rapidly.&#13;
3.       On the domestic front, food subsidies continue to absorb a large&#13;
share of government expenditures while domestic fuel and energy costs are&#13;
among the lowest in the world.&#13;
4.       There have been some recent increases in domestic oil reserves but&#13;
even so it seems evident that in the medium term the Egyptian economy will&#13;
need to operate with smaller oil revenues cushion. A burgeoning population&#13;
and limited agricultural expansion possibilities make it imperative that&#13;
resources be used as productively as possible.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 94 -&#13;
bO    r- c  'C  C  0%  ITC&#13;
or-  U~~1414C~,u  i  C'J &#13;
Q rs   u~~~n  m o: n  I  s  &#13;
¢      -&#13;
w r--  D  %0 %C 4  -  1&#13;
co  O~  Cy o~  C-&#13;
* .  .  . .  ¢     . &#13;
_ n eC  0  I  -&#13;
00 ~ ~ ~ ~ C~'0%CJ4 -&#13;
a   00&#13;
bOr       -o o  I -  C-4  o C&#13;
&gt;   en 0 U c&#13;
&gt;4&#13;
0%    Ou O-C'   &#13;
-4 &#13;
0~       .... ¢             ..&#13;
r- Ln  cli 00 00 es   C&gt; C &#13;
0%   q  .Tc.-        U c-e&#13;
C 'C  - u,,         as      1&#13;
10  z      a0  r   u-  e'J  C4  -4&#13;
bs -I    c::       CN cc      IToo - &#13;
1-4  4  ~~~~~Jc,4O-  -4  I  Cr4--C'&#13;
o~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~c&#13;
.4  I~~~~~~~~~~~~~~4&#13;
H                               H&#13;
4  C.)  0%  u-ooc~~~~~~a   -4  C'\0   .&#13;
0  9 0%  00c'jr---4  r'&#13;
4  0       0%u~~~~'JI Ce &#13;
c;  o            I &lt; o o o - cs \s t  n&#13;
E-'~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~~~C C.) &#13;
n  z   o   o - o (s N  l  cs  &lt;to  e s 4) &#13;
M0~~~~~~~~- 04 X0 o)  Co-  oi 4) csr-;&#13;
S-a      00 CJW. 0DOec  O&lt; Ol &#13;
or&gt;  -  _~-J~ ' &gt; J  I             C6&#13;
7:     ¢ -      I&#13;
a~~~~~~~~~~P    O      c z         B &#13;
z ~~~~~~-4  m ~ ~ ~~ -&#13;
m  C -                 0 &#13;
4-4  0  0  4J  W  W  Q ~~~~~~~~~~~~-4  ti  0 ~ 4-&#13;
" ;1   Q   0  Ai  i      4&#13;
&gt;-I      . -4  C        u:C&#13;
o ~ ~ ~  Q  C-i  se -Q i     5- .   t&#13;
0) &gt; .                0 44&#13;
aO  OC  -. 0o ;  b &#13;
W-  &gt;  D; W  Q W  0  0  fi 0&#13;
-..-4  0 O&#13;
t1  Q  z C; 4J   O   0. 0UU:&lt;  &#13;
A4  C14 cO 4      - e          (fo&#13;
X  0X   0ifiCJ C:) UiW o *  .iC&#13;
:&gt;~~    wU      H  U X9aoC o &#13;
Q~~~~~ C                S aeX UeXW..&#13;
04  *    fr-     Z  *  'JO~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 95-&#13;
w eV *   o   0 C.o  r - 0 r , Cl rs   0 w O   C,)  0 &#13;
ix        C0'    o0 CO0     tO~'O&#13;
&gt;~~~~ ~ ~~~~~ Cl cl Cl 0c  M lr&#13;
c~~~to,  .  .       .~~~~t&#13;
C14 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~-.&#13;
&lt;&#13;
w~~~~ P.  .     r- m  N to P. m r- CY  CY q  e; &#13;
CF    n .   . .  .  .      ...&#13;
co        -    LD-o, 6 . On C LO n   c N .  co 0 -&#13;
CD    -  I    -   -  i)  '  I D   I  I:-. &#13;
lU            I         *  I&#13;
to   w'   o    .cn O     7~-Ct  U"0IC,&#13;
C   tr .  .               .&#13;
o - .     0   bOLno)  -mr-Or-ale  ('00l&#13;
s *.... .  ....&#13;
_j a        z &#13;
U&#13;
z cr          IT v   O7C n      ~  r &#13;
U)  -0.   *  o  U O)r-C. r ao b- C w  . N Cy  C .4  0 l&#13;
.J  4t  _      O 0'''&#13;
tD o            r to'  0 O Z.Imtr  r-0 fli O  U   oJ 0  )C9  o0&#13;
a _     0' LI    r-to0 0   . Cl  mflU-  I. d coN *-&#13;
_  -   I     C  &#13;
CZ                  7&#13;
U-z    I     tY&#13;
Z      I  mf  --Wu)cLt       ~  L)rCJ&#13;
4     0' I       .  -    ......... . . .&#13;
2     to  0 O w tD 11- CC0y  O   mn r e- w F   v u v &#13;
o     a~  *      o v  rNQn(ot   ezts&#13;
IL     I    U)     Li _, &#13;
0.:          ,     I      C&#13;
0I ' *   2.*    2    i&#13;
C N  U)ItoICN  C n -CU C.) ED   - r -,t N&#13;
0. .           Z..         .&#13;
W x &#13;
4U.&#13;
*    Li)&#13;
4  U)~~~~~~~V&#13;
4         ~~~~ ~~~L/  L/) .'&#13;
ii.            U     P.&#13;
U              U.  VI   0 0&#13;
0      U        L    .  0. 0.&#13;
*           c/ 0.C  U)   0.  2&#13;
MO vz                 ce Q   F F&#13;
*    LiI-Q . wZ          0- --O&#13;
LA O  M   tw  w z     0 &#13;
U ~~- ~~--  a,  O  -   _ &#13;
0.  _iwUuu   U  Z  U  oxzt'.jti&#13;
Z  Luww &lt;Z 0      -   x Z 0 -WJ&#13;
*o Z U. U.  4 -   -J 0-' 0 U&#13;
*  0. wU. U.  Z Z  0  Z    U o.w&#13;
* Y     lJ -1 -  tI  &lt;   -1 ZU &#13;
U )( W W    I-.-  U   .--0&#13;
0  W4 Q  x  o- 0F -   a   Z&#13;
am       W c1  Xvo  I -  o F Z&gt;&#13;
LI  Ll-.0   L  0t c1  (flOt:uJ.J&gt;&#13;
'~~~~~zo U7wFJa  aJo owomXw_J Q&#13;
*     00 o  zw.c ,D wZ Z 0   w D -&#13;
*  J  Ls.&gt; I  o  0 0.L.'.'  fo  o  uM.n  I&#13;
4Z 0 v O.       U   0.   LLo&#13;
Z  0*-U)   f lW- U)  J IU   fl 1- 1J I0 &#13;
r. -U).0  w2..Z z  l  u tr 0w Z o&#13;
a ::=      W oW  ro DoZ  s  o a:z&#13;
U) 1-C)0w  ix 0fl 0  0.0O:O00 0 &#13;
.-  -  a0. .  o  0.L  0L z o L a.0  ZU&#13;
X Lt)Uw XZ &gt;DX1  4 -)C X:&#13;
IUJ o0 W- U4&lt;w-    2    LU-  :E&#13;
*   0U -              -&#13;
U                    CL_  &#13;
0         0          0 &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 96 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Indonesia&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       The large favourable external shocks in 1980 were somewhat reduced in&#13;
1981, 1982 and again in 1983 as the favorable terms of trade shock was partly&#13;
eroded by adverse export volume effects.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       Indonesia has been plagued by what is often termed the Dutch&#13;
disease. From 1979 to 1982 many felt that the rupiah was over-valued. Also,&#13;
consumer energy prices were low while the government used ever increasing food&#13;
subsidies to keep down inflationary pressures. These subsidies were in large&#13;
part directed to rice producers through fertilizer subsidies.&#13;
3.       As the petroleum market softened in 1982, government finances began&#13;
to suffer. In response to the situation, fertilizer subsidies were reduced&#13;
while consumer prices were raised for petroleum products, electricity, and&#13;
transportation.&#13;
4.       In 1983, the government attempted to increase its petroleum export&#13;
volume. Also, the exchange rate was devalued so as to promote non-traditional&#13;
exports. This resulted in a substantial depreciation of the real exchange&#13;
rate (from 111% in 1982 to 142% in 1983, or a 1976-78 basis). A major new&#13;
investment initiative for agriculture was introduced, which includes&#13;
cultivating an additional 1 million hectares.&#13;
5. In the early years of the oil boom, Indonesian planners were not as&#13;
attentive as they might have been to other sectors of the economy. With a&#13;
softening of the petroleum market, they now appear to be rectifying the&#13;
imbalance and attempting to activate the non petroleum resources the country&#13;
possesses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-97 -&#13;
tD 00  1.0  CY C4     L n t_- I_&#13;
0e  I  .. . -   **      . &#13;
W r-           Ull   CN -  -&#13;
&gt; CY%@&#13;
-4&#13;
co   Pb   ocS        £X &#13;
bo 00   Un c 00  a% Z   0&#13;
w S&#13;
bo ~ O- - O 0' o    T oa 0 aboLt&#13;
d . . ...  . .a  .  ...&#13;
0) r-  q  - , ,-4  , I   C' -&#13;
&gt;     -4&#13;
Z~~~~~~' -- ,,Z        00C4O&#13;
H.&#13;
o    _u _oe&#13;
c  o     ID c i c  -  en I-   N&#13;
-4&#13;
Ut&#13;
r-CY% IT1   IT   -:  C'J  -4 0  b&#13;
0s Oc'Jc,o'e0  e'J   J-ur&#13;
0        ~.....  *...... . .  ...  .  *  *  o 2&#13;
1-4  I ~ C1             ci &#13;
H~~ -&#13;
A                     .4           0&#13;
z0&#13;
~~~~(-4'-4             -OO       -&#13;
4  p..       7  C0'U llCT            co1.-&#13;
S                                e~~~~~e&#13;
-4     I -c '4    C'&#13;
0  o~~~c&#13;
0   'a&#13;
-0&#13;
Z1             . ,      .  . * &#13;
X b~~0     -4O11        CN  '004r ........ &#13;
-4                 a~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~t-&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~&#13;
V4~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~~~'&#13;
,5 W v~~~~ow   co               e_ _ ........ sl_co&#13;
H  ~~~~~~~m    0 &#13;
M   &gt; o   ~~~o  _ &#13;
A                        fo&#13;
2~~                  ~    ~~~ ,  KL e0&#13;
C  --- c0)  c    o   &#13;
00   )  4-4              0&#13;
C   a)  H_Ai            "a&#13;
cJ   a 4  )              02 m v  oo&#13;
Ai  U O i U   Ei  _  2   0&#13;
C P   i C W  4  &lt;   0  C&#13;
A 4 W  W0a-  0    0   0O&#13;
X c4  0  W  bO Q  1-4  C  U 0 &#13;
&gt;d  Ai   A : i   &amp;j  lw A   i&#13;
OJ. a-, bO .  0  bOW &#13;
4 uO m   w   u :  4 W  H4&#13;
H    : U&lt;. b0o~  '  &lt;o  &#13;
~~  W~0  0w 0 U   0       U &#13;
H  4. C/-W f  Z  P.4.- 0iW O fiWSc&#13;
&gt;:  z X &lt; a aW-   0 o  0  1-4&#13;
&gt;  a)0¢W        rz  OZ      a )C O &#13;
0 14 c  e; oJ &gt; 4  E~ rX   0 4  U&#13;
H;  I:-C 'i         C &#13;
-,              0 &#13;
0O  - *  *  *      *n *O *v 0i_N&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
8- 9 -&#13;
WUcNv  Lfl c0G CNOW  cN cl) 7co c) c m &#13;
Wr-      c N-   -   L&#13;
cc C)      N 7 &#13;
C -  ,&#13;
&gt;&#13;
C     ,&#13;
W                   N 0 0 r - -  O O  C0  r- LO   r&#13;
Z             N .  .  .    ... .. .. ...&#13;
O    0     C  c Dr-  r- 0 O.--  wi v w O OO&#13;
O     Q~I CO' ) '             - CN qCN  N   5N `7N '&#13;
Z    -         N    ,  _, ,, &#13;
_    -              I   -   I  H   i I&#13;
(N &#13;
0   W -  -   OC(NCN  vOCO 0 -cN(N  (NC -(NtLfC1&#13;
, O¢, .     ..  . . .... ..........&#13;
C)' -  4  (0  0 sO  (NOC8 0 00 U C)0CC0 0 ~N&#13;
r-                 C,  O c O  C' I  ' N  -&#13;
adi-  wr-I   _      _&#13;
_Z &gt; C)      7&#13;
W C _&#13;
ci uI C&#13;
, -           C,   , ,  _  c:  wC  &amp;O. . (.&#13;
co  4             o-        c N  N ID CY) 0 0n&#13;
4  -'(/C  CCI  ~~LM  NI  0CCI-I     I&#13;
0 0     -N               7-&#13;
&lt;~~~~~~- I &#13;
2 -    :     J &#13;
-  _   I    4&#13;
4x         Z&#13;
Z      #    )-* r-cN  WWC)D     0 f-  - rNC&#13;
4E   0          . 0  -I  D    D0OU &#13;
2t   w&gt;   ,  w  0 '  Y -- -   '  '   -~c&#13;
CCI I  O W   II &#13;
0:     ,    L'.&#13;
01    01&#13;
W   I  W   z&#13;
wL     '          C/&#13;
CI    2     J*&#13;
C cni  wc  O m  om  C0m C  0i Lf eq.&#13;
CC'  . N ~  WO C0 0 0     (N {  O - U1&#13;
_c co    0U 0   co  N O ',0 - Ni&#13;
0- CN&#13;
tLI&#13;
a.U&#13;
4X&#13;
LM0&#13;
.4     W&#13;
2 &#13;
,   _   c:    ~~~~~~~~tn&#13;
0      U C        1 0 0 0&#13;
Ln V)   CA  LL Z &#13;
I/ Y1  Z       W CC     Cl:&#13;
(L  j     WL L) U       0  0  0jV&#13;
0. - U..JWU  ULJ   2  (  JZC/..C/&#13;
2 VL7W    2 0        0 Z   O _ _ U&#13;
or ZL6 LU  4 ,  - t      LL L- &#13;
C/ Z   U .W W 0D  0 Z   0 )W  Ca &#13;
U  xaww     1--  f.  C, d-.-.-.&#13;
0  U)W 1-  C n  01  _ 0  1-  2&#13;
I   V &gt; WC  D.  flO  0  0. Cj  &gt;&#13;
4) "I 20   C/C0.  U.Um-j  0.  N.Cj.&#13;
2 0IX O W  C/C1-_. I  C/C1-1_ _ O W&#13;
I O  L/ wZwZ         w E  0O  - O &#13;
C) 20w   z t w 0O 0 z  w0z  0   LJ&#13;
I  J-  - -   0  U&gt;  U o   0 .0 0 o .o V) L  J&#13;
I  W  F :Z o 0W-  U.W  2   ULo  U.&#13;
I    a -- 0           - O  X tL LL Z  C Z&#13;
CZ X ~  v   cc X  Z X a O i x 0 wE c x c X   C&#13;
I   0     0 '   o m (  0  &#13;
W      0. _i&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 99 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Malaysia&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       Malaysia was able to take advantage of favorable external markets in&#13;
the 1970s. In 1979 and 1980 deterioration of export markets prospects was&#13;
more that offset by favorable shifts in terms of trade. However in 1981, and&#13;
again in 1982, the terms of trade deteriorated, so that Malaysian planners&#13;
were obliged to cope with significant adverse shocks for the first time in a&#13;
number of years.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       In 1981 and again in 1982 the principal policy response was to&#13;
increase external borrowing. This was coupled with some success in export&#13;
promotion in timber and petroleum, which helped to offset the poor&#13;
performances in rubber and tin.&#13;
3.       Domestically the policy package sought to maintain economic activity&#13;
by expanding credit both to the government and the rest of the economy. This,&#13;
in turn, produced a major deterioration in government finances. Attempts to&#13;
maintain past growth rates of consumption meant that domestic savings&#13;
suffered.&#13;
4.       Agriculture seems to pose particularly difficult problems.    While the&#13;
government has announced its objective to reduce import dependence on food, it&#13;
still has not yet established a suitable set of incentives. Rice policy seems&#13;
to be torn between attempts to consolidate or redistribute land while&#13;
additional investments in the Muda River area seem to be frustrated by disease&#13;
problems. In the meantime food imports continue to rise.&#13;
5.       Malaysia benefitted from many years of favorable external shocks but&#13;
was rather tardy to adjust when these turned unfavorable from 1981. The&#13;
immediate prospects suggest some improvement for many of its exports may give&#13;
policy planners a little room to manouver.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-100 -&#13;
to co   C4 un C_ -0 r-  qxr- C&#13;
0  I     * .    .   .         0 .&#13;
0 r-    O - -.  -          C.J&#13;
&gt;              I&#13;
c-&#13;
xco O r- r z  z     b m m&#13;
0 -4 O  - N         4&#13;
0) C'4&#13;
0 I      ... &#13;
w 00    ON C 4 _-"  - -I  04 ¢&#13;
5.&gt;0'   4~-4eJ~Oe-J  C _  -r C%&#13;
0)I~~*-  O-4 -t  -4  I  n 1e&#13;
-)&#13;
cn                 c~~~~o&#13;
00~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
J     O- oo 0O r4 o' Z X   r- o-&#13;
r',  -Al  ~ ~~~0'  LA  .4  '..-&#13;
X0                C . C  * C  ¢  .  C -&#13;
_0 a~ _n  _     _E %DC4 oN&#13;
_     o-- U   I Co1--XX &#13;
0'       ~~~~~~~~~-A&#13;
-4             4O-4OO0&#13;
oD~C**          * ¢      ...&#13;
o~~~~I rv   en  en Ls CS   L 0 &#13;
_      °C 4 CI I  en     en&#13;
H             - uI st *r0 S(^  Z   JNu&#13;
-                                     0~~~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
)                        CC        *  .  ... c&#13;
0      0    a   -          -4 O o  0 o   0 &#13;
EZ O                               ~~~~~~~~~~H&#13;
&gt;.&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
0 Y  I   *  .  .  .  *  .  *  *  C -   4&#13;
O    ?u      0r.0or- O   LA n &#13;
&lt;e @ N O N ~I    I  L A &#13;
&lt;-4                                    0&#13;
$4 ~ ~ ~ -&#13;
a                                X~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.&#13;
0&#13;
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~V3                    co&#13;
H:                     H            X)      0&#13;
.C  04r_ on  0                 5&#13;
U  Pi 0        Q       0&#13;
0            0      _  0)        0Ai        c&#13;
Pi~~~~~~0         4.i                  0 &#13;
)    c  c  H           0) c&#13;
bo  cD 0  _.                   0 &#13;
c  .L  --4 0  0)            02 &#13;
c0 4J0    U     U    Ai        0&#13;
U      0 )0        0z  0       0&#13;
s  Pq c y   &lt;   02 c    &#13;
X X-A tD  rD O       0&#13;
0  a)          'ac&#13;
Ci2 *,-4~0)0&gt; 0)-4  LES 0 40&#13;
0)0   0 U       C   0          U&#13;
H   4-H 2 Ps Q         -4 H  0-~ 0&#13;
X  X H 2 C) .1 C020)  Z 020&#13;
PI  -e- J   IT CL %Q A  r-  C44  C'&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 101 -&#13;
W N *  t   F F C} tD v S N 1Dtn UN   0  0X :) &#13;
C(p0 .  .   .............&#13;
tN-        - 08 0 N   - - - W&#13;
C x           m&#13;
w t.. .II   - I    ~ &#13;
0 ~ ~~~ ~~~~~~~    m co r. Lo Corn  v (N - ,) m&#13;
*     0,  -   n {.D C  O  N 0 N  ! --C' -&#13;
C _,&#13;
O~.   C~1O.   O V  qN ITN. -&#13;
4            -4r-,CY     I4     I&#13;
z &#13;
IN    &#13;
c   WC    I   0'N     0COC,-     - n-O&#13;
(l  0  C))   .  .  ..&#13;
O^   4    0    I       0  '       CN1NN -&#13;
1- F      I.U~       0 .   tv N   N I -  N  - ' c&#13;
_- Z      Z    I      - NC '  N  I N1 &#13;
W  C-1 I      IN.     N&#13;
.a  4    ,  &#13;
IN  t   tY     I/I&#13;
z~~~o                o  o, 0, , M., M. Cl-  o) t7) Q) N mG &#13;
m O             co .    -C  r&#13;
0       - I            _ 7   ,&#13;
-J&#13;
WC  I    4&#13;
4     ,  N  2  -  U t   -  - -  U-&#13;
4     O 0    X  &lt;   -  ................  .....&#13;
01     I    OOIN  Y - - l D'v  - - - ,&#13;
o6     '     O 14@   O I -    I      I&#13;
WI           0 W    0&#13;
~cz&#13;
0U I                             P.-&#13;
01.,  . Z..   Z...&#13;
Is. 01 IvD         0 - -.-  0IN ' v N&#13;
-   I       -   I   I  I I .I- &#13;
I Z  U. 1U. U.  a  0   -&lt;  - -&#13;
o. w  U .      . W    .&#13;
4 j    LA&#13;
uL     w&#13;
I ~ ~~~           -     UI Cf&#13;
Lfl .-  -     U:0~  1--  Z-&#13;
z .9z N&#13;
o U      U- ia V  LA   90.  0.0. &#13;
04        ZWM WZzzn&#13;
w &gt;)                 0 U. v&#13;
Yl-U   wZ            0- U.&#13;
*   0.  i  0. w    )  0%.   . o &#13;
I .U a   U 2    U   1 IZ U. Z U&#13;
2 Z &lt; .Iw w cZ  0  - VU w o - w -&#13;
* o Zu.u.u.  4 -    .J O0% - . U&#13;
*. . - vIa.LA  IZZI  0  Z 1 o w&#13;
I I  IaW  WIa  4-O0D  0.  0O  0 'LI &#13;
U  C QW W    I-    U  U t1- ~ I &#13;
Z    II-IZiI       I tw &gt; X&gt;X&#13;
0.0 o,        wZ Z      uj-&#13;
*  4  Z .  Cf  0.9  IJ.  0.  *- o O  fi  L&#13;
*a c Zo a s F      IL 0X 0L &#13;
I  Z~  oIWX *   -w 0 I  4  &gt;F  4 .  e ~F**&#13;
* Ia 0_Ia    U4Ia    I  UW. w  I l &#13;
I      - ~ I&#13;
I    0       0          0&#13;
U      0) O.       g&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 102 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Mexico&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       In the years 1979-82 Mexico enjoyed an average improvement in terms&#13;
of trade due to higher petroleum prices equivalent to 4% of GNP. Much of this&#13;
improvement was however offset by increases in interest rate charges and a&#13;
deterioration in world demand for its export products. (It should be noted&#13;
that the terms of trade change is calculated on a 1978-81 basis. Using an&#13;
earlier bas-is would give rise to a smaller gain.)&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       Until 1982 Mexico followed expansionary monetary and fiscal policies&#13;
and allowed its real effective exchange rate to appreciate to a considerable&#13;
extent, with the growing balance of payments deficit financed by foreign&#13;
borrowing. Public finances deteriorated to the point where the government&#13;
budget deficit reached 18.7% of GDP in 1982 and Mexico's foreign debt&#13;
increased to a considerable extent. Public confidence was eroded and capital&#13;
flight was estimated at $10 billion, leading to the financial crisis in August&#13;
1982.&#13;
3.       The response was to move to restrictive policies by reducing the&#13;
money supply, cutting back public expenditures holding down real wages and&#13;
depreciating the real exchange rate. The depreciation of the real exchange&#13;
rate induced some recovery in non-oil exports by 1984.    At the same time, the&#13;
gradual liberalization of the economy produced a surge in the inflation rate&#13;
to over 100% in 1983 but this is abating in 1984.&#13;
4.       While the unrealistically expansionary policies produced a foreign&#13;
exchange crisis in 1982, under strong restrictive measures the balance of&#13;
payments has considerably improved. Increases in domestic oil reserves and&#13;
stronger external demand for oil give some degree of manouverability to policy&#13;
makers. It remains to be seen whether the improvement in the rest of the&#13;
domestic economy will be strong enough to preclude the surge of public&#13;
investment characteristic of the later years of previous sexenios.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 103 -&#13;
W cn&#13;
to 00&#13;
ai      ** ... .  .    .   ...&#13;
-4&#13;
.            .    .       .  . &#13;
&gt; C~~  .J :  -Ia  c'4    e'g&#13;
I            I&#13;
X  I   xD W_ O 00 Q  O  _   t_ vo0 X&#13;
o   a..         ..  .  . a** *a..&#13;
0'           r  n °-  &lt; - 0  r-  r- u-&#13;
-  -s   e  C_  _  I  cs    CJ IeC&#13;
- C&#13;
,   -I    £ - UNe4&lt;0'Qo -    CTh0&#13;
' oo      ~      t ....         .&#13;
t0 %&#13;
o      o'    oxJr'-c    0 '&#13;
t     OD.     . . *  It.  .  .   .   .  .  .&#13;
&gt; '    CO0% 'r--   r'-     cq c&#13;
-      X       I ,,       N  -SU&#13;
C)  -  a      c  ~  oC7  - C' Nr,C &#13;
~~-4       cn                  Ln~~~~~~-&#13;
00  0%      m Ce en 'j0      P- O r&#13;
En          17  3  90n  l                   vC!r&#13;
00  CN C14&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~1&#13;
~~-4   r%  C~ ~~'-4co&#13;
H~~~~~~. 0 %c ,   ....       -I ...   &#13;
C)   C) N   |  |  CS   (S i&#13;
9  C      C   U       CC!&#13;
w   "O        C,4 C4rl-r 0     4&#13;
o      .C           -.  C)&#13;
C)                       0&#13;
£    - I*  *  .  *. -  &#13;
a~~~~~~~~~ 4&#13;
X   .                            ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~o&#13;
d                            X       e~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
-    C) a1 c      0&#13;
x  9    --WC4     0 -  C&#13;
Ai W    bO      0  C   0&#13;
o  X  C  4.J4JP.   *.  U       cl)&#13;
co       ~   ~  ~~~&gt;  &gt; Z                o -  -  6&#13;
r z -   C)  C   ') C'  co'     co&#13;
&gt;i X&gt;    4 W U  a  *-4 c .     JJ&#13;
X      &lt;   C) 4.J  C   4Z &gt; CC &#13;
-J  U0J   J-J0Ci  X Q-.  CI).&#13;
w o. O C u           juC &#13;
&lt;t:                 Ai &lt;)  Ai qJ0  &gt;  0 &#13;
&gt;4  - Ci.4 c) a4 ) a     0         CC o  c&#13;
0  o en   0  w  oo aJ z  .JLa-.J&#13;
B     ° C)OO-) o~     o oZ CO&#13;
H~~~~~~~~~CU                 u &#13;
0  0  -~~~~&#13;
-4     .4                       -J&#13;
oL  _                              0 Ot   snU&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 104 -&#13;
IU ,N  I  0 c c (  ,   - LOO-fUV  O C.) ,- V&#13;
Cr0 ¢l  I  ... ...     .   ..&#13;
4'  0  cD~~~-  0-o  O-   00.0.ci ),&#13;
wir-             r-0  ~&#13;
C0  I  I   O       It -y  O O   5  o&#13;
0  8  1w  ID 1D al'  N  Iv 1t ll-   V s&#13;
x  rs'      )- ID  4 m m  08   '&#13;
4 -&#13;
0  ~ ~     e'Iinr-  0  (Nfr-U  r~ 04&#13;
O-  a           m N   ISl r-  m N   N 4 UM 1 11  -  t&#13;
U)   NI|. .    .           .   . &#13;
-     0' lrZ -        -N  1 0 inrMON  1 tt&#13;
Z  &gt;D M  *     ID   LO 1o ¢)N-N &#13;
1    - $ c      N ZN      -&#13;
0 u    1 0     r &#13;
.  ~ 0  .        .&#13;
Ni  4    0 -  O  LO N O   - m N   L fl C N&#13;
F1- *               m C; O  Na  ' -F  M w &#13;
,~9-  w ,-L    C', ,flO _u      V  lt&#13;
LU 4~~~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
U          -.&#13;
O'  J   I    Y&#13;
JU  C.  C  1fl  UO ) O  L D co - 0CD U  00-J LO P N&#13;
.J  C   _,     O ** *  * * -&#13;
M              w  r- co tg °  CI~ &gt;l O t- C- 11 O}  mA   m  N&#13;
o U  o  0 Zr-q(~~~~~~N UOFe 'uto  ~~&#13;
4s  I-.If  o)I  I  IU -0  U ' WX  t D )@OO   q' qv t &#13;
9- O 00  -      O)'( - ED - N  N,  &#13;
Ul~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~  . '  &#13;
I        4 I  &#13;
U.O         I * X @ -  . ..U&#13;
4     0.    C  - Z  - C N&#13;
1  0'  0 ~~~wr-  n0I7O 7~     f~r&#13;
1  O I   O IDt  O6  -( - I  IF&#13;
0  -I.   LL~  N   C~)tg-amO.&#13;
IA.   0.    0~~~~~~~~~.  na &#13;
LU     LU~~~~~~~~~c   L &#13;
.      I           a&#13;
N    . .i  -a F0 400tc   DO~&#13;
oI    z..    J&#13;
t-.  wdwU w -O 0.       0-&#13;
I  -   IJ -}   C1   -    N - N U&#13;
LU  o    "-: &#13;
mm- WWZ X    I  IA&#13;
VI  _,     11icc 0x0M  i0 C 0c &#13;
CIO.  LU           MZU&#13;
4        LL&#13;
C            U,&#13;
Y Y       Z      U   - _.  U&#13;
OI  U    LU     IA   In  0&#13;
0      U       U.  9 -x .CZ&#13;
In-II  LUA W,WZ    0-'- -&#13;
CI  _ .JLUUUQ  U  2  U  X Z JIn^&#13;
I Z CLLLULU CZ 0     V - ILO WI-&#13;
I  t)  2.AI, - U 4  -  -J  0u-D U&#13;
I  _n  LU  LUL  4-0   C. 9^ ZF O -Z  F &#13;
I   .-LU   I  i      --_IA.&#13;
I U X OLU W   9--.  U ^_OQlU&#13;
0 O  U19   In-0:E9-^. O  -  09- 2&#13;
In IL-.J  In&lt;0 -^  J O In00OC *U&#13;
I      I0O  ZLU  LUDWZ Z ^LU-D&#13;
J   IA.&gt;9  0 O  _ I^  DO  OC_W.InD J&#13;
I  4  Z  O n  C.9- _A-  C.  I O  &#13;
I Z  0.9-LU1  I^. WflL9--.IJ   I n9-9- FIC_&#13;
I i! -Lfl.  LUWZ =W Z Ow =zZ O&#13;
I~   U,AJ(  &gt;0&lt; _     -X ZQ __Z  4&#13;
I  lU  09-LU' -  U4CLU _   UL  I .. &#13;
I    U      J.        J&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 105 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Nigeria&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       Following the 1979-80 oil price increase, Nigeria experienced a&#13;
strong favorable shock equivalent to 10.8% of GNP. In 1981 and even more in&#13;
1982 these favourable terms of trade effects were increasingly offset by&#13;
adverse export volume effects. Both crude petroleum prices and export volume&#13;
fell in 1983.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       From 1979 to 1982 the real effective exchange rate appreciated from&#13;
94 to 79% of its base year (1976-78) level.   This led to large losses in-&#13;
export market shares while imports grew rapidly. These large losses in export&#13;
market shares apply only to non-oil exports which comprise less then 5 percent&#13;
of total exports. Food imports increased in particular as the performance of&#13;
domestic agriculture deteriorated.&#13;
3.       The money supply as well as domestic credit and government credit&#13;
expanded rapidly. Little effort was made to increase domestic resource&#13;
mobilization by the Federal and State Governments and private savings also&#13;
declined thereby increasing the vulnerability of the economy to external&#13;
shocks.&#13;
.4.       In 1981 national income fell by 4.6% as oil revenues declined.   In&#13;
response to this situation, imports were cut dramatically. The pattern&#13;
continued in 1982 and 1983 as the Government sought to adjust to lower export&#13;
revenues primarily through a slow down of economic activity. In 1984,&#13;
President Buhari introduced further contractionary measures. Current and&#13;
capital spending are to be cut back again and the wage freeze of 1983 has been&#13;
extended to 1984. Because of OPEC imposed constraints, oil revenues are&#13;
expected to be in the $10 billion range, less than one-half of what they were&#13;
in 1980, so that improvement in the current account will be sought by further&#13;
import restraints.&#13;
5.       The recession continued into 1984 but the prospects of some&#13;
improvement for oil exports may afford some relief. The government has not&#13;
yet come up with a viable solution to the Dutch disease syndrome and&#13;
considerable debate ranges over the merits of alternative exchange rates&#13;
policies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 106 -&#13;
b0) C7      0m  nU)               c&#13;
bI at   o  o~~~~o .h         .  . aa&#13;
cn  -4       ~~~~~~C..  I -&#13;
W  cra   ~0s  *  0  *.D   Z~  -  _  *&#13;
&gt;co&#13;
¢ -~~~~~~~~&#13;
z  rn -43, r0 O) z  z  CS4 Ln 0.&#13;
I        O           . *  ¢ &#13;
oo  Z x &lt; -X o Zg  Z     NU &#13;
_)       CSU C               _&#13;
bD 00   cn C: r- L D c o      ONC  r-&#13;
ea~~~~~  I ....  ¢        ..&#13;
m  1                 &lt; 4 )U) Ze-c&#13;
w  a,   oo _4 Cs _,  ,        S &#13;
&gt; O&#13;
CO  00  -t U~~ c0&#13;
z      -                           --..&#13;
¢0    co C0 -4OC          Z _¢&#13;
cn   eo   oo c^4 -  OD O  O~~00 0  1  Z  \0 -.: C&#13;
Z   _     N CS .-- _ _,N _,&#13;
-                    I4&#13;
_0     C- cN               I N |&#13;
oc&#13;
a) ~~~~-4  r..                    LI'~~I   C j-  co&#13;
O-4               Do&#13;
co z&#13;
0  to r-  C)C)  T a, CY      *n  *-       C&#13;
-  z  0" ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~c;L  Z     ,j u  -~&#13;
O      -             I  I          (N  C-4&#13;
Z                                               Dc&#13;
E-'  0                                             H&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
o      xo-    Oo--.ra    CO-.- o oC o &#13;
od                                  w~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
z&#13;
00     co&#13;
V4    1~0&#13;
|&gt;           &lt;~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0 XD   A-&#13;
--                       0) 0-  x&#13;
CoC&#13;
oo4.) co   u     c   a   CD oC&#13;
a4.1-)            0 cm  a&#13;
-4             Q~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~(  Co  U  CoD&#13;
-~~    ~         a  C o            ' aJ&#13;
Coe    -)  0             e        C&#13;
0U C   14 ( )  4-4   0i4i Q&#13;
&gt;    v &gt;   tJ4 Co      co 4-&#13;
0)    Co  -G             0 &gt;  Ca O&#13;
w   -i  C  U  z  ¢     co  In&#13;
C   v o0 c   0)                0O&#13;
Co    -   u            4 bC&#13;
&gt;- . 1   4  W *'4 p      Cov&#13;
ix  CZ3 -    M,  v - o      4 i &#13;
U      00)  0) Qv C 0 0&#13;
&gt;¢-    0 4-4 0       -   -   .       0230&#13;
4   w ut 0  e 0 w  bO  C  0          0 r_&#13;
&gt;-4                  ce ae) t  &gt;  ¢5 ae) c   a 0)  -.&#13;
&gt;^   4 -~ L,4 Z       4 oo ooo Z4 C  &#13;
C)  0)SC. 0CC.       0     4: P o  PCo  U&#13;
,   000))o           0.... g  o~&#13;
Cooo)&gt;ox _         0n&lt;*  - f &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 107 -&#13;
I4        LON Im   0   ur 1&gt;   I v   D  r  u, ua go&#13;
o0~~~t 00    co co *  .....  ...&#13;
w r 1    cN -   co  ,  ,  _&#13;
&gt;  GI1    C,&#13;
- S   0 .&#13;
-P  LU        wv I . N  cv co t: 0 ED   0  ID r- &#13;
OtS L   co  4    -0 DW -  -  -N N St&#13;
-   a. Lfl           -  N  CNl  *&#13;
(N  &#13;
0   w - *     w D &gt; -  0 N t lD  O Nr-O0&#13;
eq  ~m a  .    . . .. .. .&#13;
t~  4     Li) 'Ii *   NO  ' O)  - -  W1  *   N&#13;
- W1 r,       N -    - ,&#13;
_  Z   c o  I   C|   I-0 mr  l  r  P( &#13;
&lt;  0   C,    V  .  n 0 c  o c  - c &#13;
-z    , ~&#13;
(N            Lil: $  &#13;
.J  4        . I  O     '.&#13;
U- W;  0     '  s  IN O1  0 G -(N  C -  - IS) (DN&#13;
4  .-Uf  O)I   I /)1tU) :I  O~ ¢ 0 0-  n- -C&#13;
Z 00    ,             -X,I&#13;
-  _   I    lU&#13;
Z &#13;
0 0 0        0 W    Ow v -) N    c0o&#13;
I  ) O   ID  O X  ..... _ ...N...... . .&#13;
0         x                    C, -&#13;
m    0   '  cl S  tN (D   CD V) q () N L)- O  -  0 &#13;
O    _, ,  U. -F0   U -&#13;
U.       ~~     ~~~0  0&#13;
w           W      LA&#13;
a.I         C&#13;
4  -J~~~~~~~~~~~1 &#13;
J   r- .-  1- -0-0   CD N  G) N  .  0 1w&#13;
IJ)  .  2)    Z :0 U  ) &#13;
_,  n  1)  0  0 e&#13;
I  U      X &#13;
C LI)&#13;
C      W&#13;
S  .-         LI)~~~~~~~~~~~~~ntnL&#13;
I           C       F     SL) U  -&#13;
Y      z       u      a 1i&#13;
I U n  U .     w   tl: U.  LI&#13;
0U          U-   000&#13;
S   LM               -  _  _&#13;
_. JWU U U    z       x z -iu&#13;
Z c IL UWW  c   0   -   I w ow -&#13;
(  Z LUL.  4 c _  J  o  _ . l&#13;
tn . ~UJUU  u,Z-  0  2-&#13;
S  LI)  W  UJW  C -0   0. L  -O  I I&#13;
*  Y   W u.  - _ W -   4 c- FZU.&#13;
w x o                   U u F- Q  :F- &#13;
a (0w u    -    U c--oW&#13;
L 0  U. IJ L xom .0  -  0&#13;
o, 0   zL~ w a  *uZ Z a  0w-&#13;
S  .J  U.&gt;'.  C o .1U .  o0  o 0.C J)&#13;
4  ZO * 1I  0IL  a- I  LIU  0.  U. *&#13;
Z2   OI-W LIW 1-_j   Lfl)  iO.&#13;
*n cc t CZ  ui Z ix cx w Z o  w az tt Z o&#13;
J I-l OwW trCOMOU o o OOO &#13;
S  - ~Cl Ga.  0 0. 0. UZ U  0. 0. Z&#13;
X 0 Lw X Z &gt; a 2 x   &gt; x  4&#13;
1w 0 F 1w- 04w-   2 Ow- _   I I &#13;
tL    .   -          _&#13;
S        -J         J~&#13;
0  0         ~~~0&#13;
S  U     0~    ~    ~~. 0.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 108 -&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Peru&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       Peru suffered an adverse shock of 6.8% of GNP in 1982.   Export volume&#13;
and interest rate effects continued to exert a negative impact as they have in&#13;
each year since 1979.  But in 1982 the situation was compounded as terms of&#13;
trade effect also became adverse. This was primarily due to decreases in the&#13;
prices of Peru's leading exports, such as copper, petroleum, fishmeal and&#13;
silver. However, copper and silver prices have since shown some improvement.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       Following the policy shift effected by President Belaunde in 1980,&#13;
Peru enjoyed substantial gains in exports, stimulated by a large depreciation&#13;
of the real exchange rate. At the same time, the general policy of import&#13;
liberalization resulted in a surge of imports that was curbed to some extent&#13;
by tight monetary policy. Foreign competition posed problems for several&#13;
domestic industries, notably textiles and auto parts.&#13;
3.       Policies to reduce government expenditures included cutting food&#13;
subsidies and gradually increasing domestic fuel prices although these prices&#13;
remain still below international level. Higher food prices, together with&#13;
contractionary policies began to disrupt any feasible polito-economic&#13;
consensus.&#13;
4.       In 1983 the economic situation deteriorated rapidly, precipitated by&#13;
a succession of natural disasters. Due to the vagaries of El Nino, the&#13;
anchovies yielded a much lower harvest while much of the oil producing region&#13;
of the country was flooded and the agricultural region suffered a particularly&#13;
severe drought.&#13;
5.       The deterioration of the economy, together with increasing rebel&#13;
activity, obliged the government to take expansionary measures. The result&#13;
was a rise in inflation, seemingly unsustainable foreign debt obligations, and&#13;
a generally difficult economic situation. It seems that Peru must obtain some&#13;
form of outside assistance to address these issues either through debt&#13;
rescheduling or concessionary aid flows.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 109 -&#13;
tO X0  r- cn un X0   X0  %.O c  '&#13;
*I.                       .   .&#13;
W      0         0       - r I&#13;
&gt;&#13;
a: --&#13;
0a. *-                - '-&#13;
- e-&#13;
bO Xb , O; O~ -1 O4 N    o&#13;
a) rN  o  _  _n&#13;
u       *   .   - .  *  *  *  -&#13;
00 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~  ~  C'&#13;
0 C- -  I - - l   -  qo&#13;
00&#13;
_%    CO  %O uT  CO a %O   0 &#13;
0\ ~ ~ 0  Lns o0 aad  u   Dn  %Om&#13;
c 01&#13;
-'I   04    I -  J 1'J    U c &#13;
0) r,   CD  -0                    Cu 0_&#13;
cn                           la~~~~~~~~~&#13;
_                                        1 - Dv  *4o \  S ce   ros &#13;
1 s .               .  -   . . .   .  ..u&#13;
H  o   cr   o - oo ur o e  ~~~o:     co v  &#13;
~~  0  0'  0-~~aroOc 4                 0&#13;
D0  O    _     's _  I~  I'¶   c'4  '0&#13;
X~~~~0 Xi r&#13;
Cu~ ~ 0v     -      IDeoe &#13;
W  I*      .      .  .  . *   - °  &#13;
0&#13;
Xo      .   - I  &#13;
ok 1    C-a  bo )    0i&#13;
'-4               J'j~&gt; 0 &gt; 3 w   i  4- 0)&#13;
cn  -4 i ) 0 CU   &gt;  U c    t&#13;
Cu       0)         C&#13;
0):1(  UC   -4(       0-&#13;
bO  Co   *-)                ) c&#13;
&gt;  aa     .   0  a) o4  )&#13;
w&gt;     e 0)1-  0  U9 0w&#13;
a 0w0        U   00)&#13;
H  O      t        Cf &#13;
Cfl  H &gt;% 0 O  2a)C  -  Z  &gt;~C  Cu &#13;
-  UC .Q J:Lx%O X  4  c. 2&#13;
0)Q~ 0L  C      U            UiCt&#13;
4-  4.S~.*  2'.-44 boo   Z  .-O~   Cu)&#13;
D  - Civ-4\  UX0  Z /   J C O   C&#13;
&gt;  c e CJ &gt; '-40)2  0  e0)  -.&#13;
0)0so$o 0o JO  Cz O ZC       0)&#13;
-X               UD&#13;
o 0 _                *         0 rx &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 110 -&#13;
LW CN  W  O I- C'  IT , - co t- ur) r  -   C N eN&#13;
C*   C   L -   -  Dm  - ) ,r-0 0  C&#13;
cj:) .   z tor-  -  o  N -  N  . N N&#13;
W ~ ~ ~ ~~e  co I  -W fD  CD O-  ' ~L&#13;
CO  O -,      P-  O  nL,C'  0  'T&#13;
C4- &#13;
CNC. &#13;
uj  U)  ry LO  uz Ln co O cow  r  r4 eNC r   cou&#13;
o .           . . . .   .   .  .   .   .   .   .&#13;
9 :1   i tD   (O  c)v 1-o ID cli r 0: IV  w  1n 0 N&#13;
cx G) *   N   N? 'D J N  NS - - 1&gt;&#13;
Wu   -       I      ,  .- _&#13;
4w   C     ~    9~rO   CDDLO&#13;
O~  r.    .           -&#13;
-z &gt;a) &#13;
Lu&#13;
co   CO    Iw  v N) M LO 1- J N r- O~  l3eD a) Lo N&#13;
cn ~~~ L J r-        cli C- 0) ITO-   1&#13;
z  w rI*T       -   .~ -1 al W&#13;
Ow r _&#13;
L     , ,  _      O&#13;
4    c-W_,  .  O  ' '&#13;
cx  ai    Ln Yr IT &lt;0-  C)    7 zN&gt;- C:  D&#13;
4 : .-.U  s  u - vr-  - m  uINNtJ&#13;
O     -0 -,       -  -  -    Ia&#13;
4         U.&#13;
CZ'      &#13;
_-   ,    W&#13;
N :)  I-M   co' tS  co 1-v - )lO  M  co U'  1&#13;
O 0'  . . .....  .    .X .......  -  ...&#13;
U-   Cu ) r-  C' M W0  D r  r n C O rN&#13;
'  ~  U1l v -  f U n W- -  -  I 0  -&#13;
o  -o U.I  -  U.&#13;
LJ0  C    0&#13;
*~~~~~~ -L        Ln zo-u  a  0 os&#13;
,~ . Z.        Z      ...&#13;
o~  0C'L!  LutDn CzC&#13;
U - .- I  m-w  &gt;  a.&#13;
a. U.U  w z       - U&#13;
4   0 1 LW N.  0 E  J M  t.  t) D - N&#13;
4     Lu&#13;
x ~~-  I-    U    I-U.U-~&#13;
0 W &lt; 2    O&#13;
I       Lu  c   .  LIJ  00&#13;
&lt; z0     un U       .   0.0&#13;
Z  0 -L   Z        0   --&#13;
cx  Y    Z        W   C&gt;   0&#13;
*  JU U     W   U   ZVR O  O O&#13;
*  Z   W   42   a   -  Z  O   0 _M_&#13;
I  2Z -LL.IL  C  -  -J  O  --  D &#13;
Cc*Q.     Z C. Q. U.  U Z zo  z  Uo w&#13;
*  v,  w  w w  c-0 O .  - FOa' ,&#13;
U X Oww   I-   U _  x:--0ow&#13;
0  LU  W  - J   0 tl:  "- X  X M&#13;
-,  J  &amp;.  -  0 o .v c,e o  o : v:u  D J&#13;
4   20 o I . .  U :w~FJ .U  a.  N sJ. L-&#13;
*  =  _,n~ tr wXZ Q : wZ0 O  w CXDuwZ0O&#13;
* u w  - w  w  a:  o  o  o 00= o 0 &#13;
l  - t .-  00O cc.u-ZU o   .01.u.2U&#13;
Lu 0cluw  U4Lu-  UL&#13;
U w  o&#13;
U    a.           a._&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Adjustment Policies in 1979-83: Tunisia&#13;
External Shocks&#13;
1.       Tunisia experienced favorable external shocks in the years 1979-81,&#13;
with improvements in terms of trade being partly offset by unfavorable export&#13;
volume effects. These two influences approximately balanced in 1982 while&#13;
interest rate effects remained small.&#13;
The Policies Applied&#13;
2.       The government sought to diversify the economy through export&#13;
promotion. Gains in exports were, however, offset by negative import&#13;
substitution. Imports of investment goods increased in a fast growing&#13;
economy; efforts aimed at processing a larger share of phosphate production at&#13;
home necessitated sulphur imports; and, in earlier years, inappropriate&#13;
agricultural policies led to increases in imports of wheat and sugar.&#13;
3.       In an attempt to keep down living costs, food was subsidized and&#13;
consumer energy prices were kept low compared to international prices.&#13;
Efforts made for raising bread prices came to nought as they were greeted by&#13;
riots. Signs of popular unrest also led to excessive wage increases in&#13;
earlier years. High wages, in turn, squeezed profit margins, thereby&#13;
discouraging investment.&#13;
4.       Tunisia faces a dilemma, inasmuch as the lack of possibilities for&#13;
expanding oil exports and the limitations of its domestic market call for an&#13;
export effort in non-oil products. This, in turn, would necessitate a&#13;
comprehensive reform of the incentives system, including the liberalization of&#13;
foreign exchange, imports, and industrial prices, reductions in tariffs and&#13;
the revision of agricultural prices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 112 -&#13;
bO X0  1- 1- -   clS _   00 IT X  &lt; &#13;
o  e&#13;
w ON  ~ ; N &lt; I  I  aC      Ns&#13;
W r-  WdC-4'4U  -CsC~&#13;
&gt; e  &#13;
X    *.  .  .  .  .  .  *  *  .  -&#13;
-  -  as*M  I  -L   c',I  &#13;
C  x )  _o C'J&#13;
_     _0  N 47 ,n ,1 _0 LMu  r&#13;
ea~~~~         _&#13;
rl  CN -,: CS0Un oUN,&#13;
z  00W       t~ &#13;
0  I'D 0  ON I'D In  O4 Co4  -&#13;
- ~ ~ U -  , o   C&#13;
0I      c'J &#13;
-4&#13;
PI-4-        C-UL4 '~' -:  c&#13;
o ~ ~~  ~~~ 0  irrXJCJ o _  _   _0&#13;
W~~               ~   ~ .   .  .   *  .   )&#13;
-~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~- &#13;
rn~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
H                                   CCU&#13;
X~~~~~~~c _r  ID o CS      ID 0=e &lt;  &#13;
,   0   *  .  o  .  -  .  *   *~.  .  CU&#13;
0     e    &lt; -    I I-                 1 0&#13;
co  z-&#13;
E4  0&#13;
C.)                                    H&#13;
o   o-   C _ en 1 S 0% o) IT  CU4 :r  o&#13;
C   co  I             ....  .c .  .  .  .&#13;
-~ 4      -4 ~ o ~ 1;L&#13;
00&#13;
H &#13;
CA~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
_  Q   e   Z _ \0 rs \0 08  uN   &lt; &lt;  ~ ~ ~~~~~~~0 n4&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~1&#13;
0   b.0&#13;
CU &gt;     w _&#13;
C)    1.1 &#13;
.C  C U  H    0)&#13;
&gt; ~ ~ ~  b       C~C         C  ~   C&#13;
CU  Ai-  C)PL             f&#13;
C04  O C)  G)-  0           . &#13;
oo                 0 0&#13;
&gt;  &gt; 0 " w  0  coJ&#13;
U)  *- 0  on -C) *-4  z  &gt;  CU cocU&#13;
S  J.JS. ~ 0  z CUS.  H  cU   X&#13;
o~~-      Uns.  4J0 0.o&#13;
~3  C)  oCUuJ  C  4&#13;
0)  a.  c r_        ,D v&#13;
C4Z U 4C)c  &gt;  H 4         - 0&#13;
H-  4-4  i  4  ~-,4 v4  0H  4  cU&#13;
S .i 4    )  z  CC 0 c&#13;
&gt;  -1C)2) 0~) -4  0  ) -4&#13;
co C  &gt; co )  o      44&#13;
x 0 c  0w 0      _ = -&#13;
c4 4     rv        c4 W  P   :&#13;
0  *&gt;  0 *  *  0 *  Z         0 &#13;
:&gt; ~ QQXa&lt;  )c   o  a &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 113 -&#13;
tU Nl * ,  mL tN 11 a)  CO Z   - N  ) t- -  ID N&#13;
00   .   ..    .. . ..      .&#13;
C  * N  Nm CO ttl       LO tO-O-0 71U)FU&#13;
('4  (N0C l  IWO 0'CO)Ou~-~&#13;
I    ,          In In U)  -   -&#13;
C-&#13;
S     I     tc4  w-oc      - r--&#13;
_    o  0 v                 -( tN  ' 0 - I 1  n  '- % N 1( &#13;
21   N,I  . Ifl .N-' .   . .  . .&#13;
-'      0C'4 0  1r-0n   LO L t1  NL fl&#13;
z    e) I-          v N  (N -&#13;
(N &#13;
0  w- C' DO~r- 4 eD  0 r  a   ---r--&#13;
1~-  41  I  ('  CNvOI( 1 - 0~   IflC4C'4t N- N &#13;
W  'S-I&#13;
U     I    -.&#13;
('4  ~~~~~~  U, 4C1&#13;
C.  u4   .l    -  0 l 0  .&#13;
J ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~c S   _  O '  '' '' '' '  '&#13;
0 U '   X   I  1-00  tADt(Dr  w0Dr0&#13;
_ Of   OI  -  ub','  CN -  _  _  _  ,  ,,&#13;
Z0 _  ,     J  I    '&#13;
2- _         I W&#13;
4 &gt;&#13;
2          u  -  0        4 -  -   --&#13;
4  0'~~&#13;
Q: ~ ~~~~~~ 0)  W'  CO O' rQ N, r- N   O - __n_&#13;
I  0. ~~~~  WLflC0   ,OC U0co   ..(I&#13;
o    _,   1 .N  U  I  -  '  '  I  I  I&#13;
14    I    0    0 &#13;
tY   I      :~~~~&#13;
W     I   W     U,&#13;
C.,~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
U   -  :  W  U)~~~~  -&#13;
ce              I &#13;
0 o     4 O X en  c  m 0&amp; f N  - co  (  -,&#13;
2...Z    Z          ...&#13;
i-  -  W v N(N  2 I0  D ' tt1N  -   N 0 1.&#13;
UC' A  C' C I   &#13;
-   .- 0Y U. -' v  N I&#13;
I   W  I  X             - I  U&#13;
*         2      w&#13;
*  U    W~~~~u  L&amp;  (LO  00&#13;
I   0     U      LV  I .  O.C.&#13;
I    SU   W0W      ~ I  I&#13;
*  UI-,( l  W     0-  --&#13;
I  2  4U.WW  42   0 -) V,14J0I&#13;
I   Y ZU.L~L4.  4  - J  x Z Wn .- t &#13;
I   Q     W-  '1LJI 6  V) O  O  O&#13;
I   O )O   U. 1 .  U  1 --I0&#13;
*  0 z W   Ua  n  w Z  O -  2 -&#13;
I  U,  L i-    -J   U     0   UW_.J&#13;
I    00 J wZ        Z Z   X-ZI J.&#13;
U z   s E  w  sZ o -  wo  w &#13;
0  z us IL   VI s   u- :D&#13;
I  4n  U.  I.  C.,  0 0CUu..&#13;
0s  J  zwo w  lZZ   o u. wu&#13;
0nw wL       f cx   Z  Z D CLI &#13;
I  4  20 U, C.-  U.  UC -.u.0&#13;
I  2  0      ~Uw  I- .. J  IW U ,I-I-J0.&#13;
CZI  CZc  u WZ. XCw Z0  w atccU,0&#13;
I.   a.I-  a 0.C.. ZU  C. _-C E Z U&#13;
x U,w,x &gt;OXw     4 &gt;Xx   4&#13;
I  O  0Iw c 4J IE   Uw InoF _ &#13;
I   C.    -        - Ev   mJ s&#13;
uI  I    .J J     -JXOe  o u &#13;
0  0        0&#13;
I  s   ZCo va  X  F   E  Q  *. C.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
World Bank                                 An Analysis of Developing                     NEW&#13;
pubications .Country Adjustment&#13;
FPublications                              Experiences in the 1970s: Low-            Compounding and Discounting&#13;
of Related                                 income Asia                               Tables for Project Analysis&#13;
Christine Wallich                         (with a Guide to Their&#13;
Interest                                  Staff Working Paper No. 487. 1981 43       Applications)&#13;
pages (including references).             Second Edition, Revised and&#13;
Stock No. WP 0487. 3.                     Expanded&#13;
Adjustment Experience and                 Aspects of Development Bank               J. Price Gittinger&#13;
Growth Prospects of the Semi-             Management                                Project planners and analysts will find&#13;
Industrial Countries                      William Diamond and V. S                  this book a convenient and time-sav-&#13;
Frederick Jaspersen                       Raghavan                                  ing reference for the preparation and&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 477. 1981. 132                                              analysis of development projects. Six-&#13;
pgs(including 3 appendixes).            Deals exclusively with the manage-        decimal tables for I percent through 50&#13;
pages (including 3 appendixes).           ment of development banks. The book        percent show the compounding factor&#13;
Stock No. WP 0477. $5.                    is divided into eight sections, each      for I and for I per annum, the sinking&#13;
dealing with one aspect of manage-        fund factor, the discount factor, the&#13;
Adjustment in Low-Income                  ment of its problems, and of the var-     present worth of an annuity factor,&#13;
Africa                                    ious ways of dealing with them.            and the capital recovery factor. The&#13;
Robert Liebenthal                         EDI Series in Economic Development. The   first edition of this book underwent&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 486. 1981. 62     Johns Hopkins University Press, 1982.      seven printings in ten years and was&#13;
pages (including bibliography).           2nd printing, 1983. 311 pages.            translated into Arabic, Chinese,&#13;
Stock No. WP 0486. $3.                    LC 81-48174. ISBN 0-8018-2571-7, Stock     French, and Spanish. This new edi-&#13;
No. JH 2571, $29.95 hardcover; ISBN 0-    bon-with narrow-interval compound-&#13;
Aggregate Demand and                      8018-2572-5, Stock No. IH 2572, $12.95     ing tables added for higher interest&#13;
Macroeconomic Imbalances in               paperback.                                rates, updated project examples, a&#13;
guide to using simple electronic calcu-&#13;
Thailand: Simulations with the            Capital Accumulation in                   lators to perform the computations&#13;
SIAM    1 Model                           Eastern and Southern Africa: A            discussed, and an annotated bibliog-&#13;
Wafik Grais                               Decade of Setbacks                         raphy increases the proven usefulness&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 448. 1981. 132    Ravi Gulhati and Gautam Datta              of its predecessor, both in the class-&#13;
pages (including 3 appendixes).                                                      room and at the project site.&#13;
Analyzes the magnitude of the setback           A    l     A&#13;
Stock No. WP 0448. i5                     in capital accumulation in eastern and    May 1984. About 208 pages.&#13;
southern Africa. This phenomenon is       ISBN 0-8018-2409-5. Stock No. BK 2409.&#13;
examined in twenty-eight statistical ta-  $10.95.&#13;
NEW                                   bles. The authors sample sixteen coun-     Translations of this new edition will be&#13;
tries and rely on expert observations to  available in 1985. Still available are the&#13;
explore the proximate causes of the       following translations of the first edition:&#13;
Alternative Mechanisms for                setbacks.                                  French: Tables d'interets composes et d'ac-&#13;
Financing Social Security                 World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 562.   tualisation. Economica, 4th printing,&#13;
Parthasarathi Shome and Lyn               1983. 74 pages.                            1979.&#13;
Squire                                    ISBN 0-8213-0169-1. Stock No. WP 0562.     ISBN 2-7178-0205-3, Stock No. IB 0542,&#13;
Reviews, clarifies, and evaluates theo-   $3.                                        $6.&#13;
retical literature about the effect of so-&#13;
cial security on capital accumulation     Capital Market Imperfections               Spanish: Tablas de interes cormpuesto y de&#13;
and labor supply. Analyzes empirical      and Economic Development                   descuento para evaluaci6n de proyectos.&#13;
studies using U.S. data, the impact of    Vinayak V. Bhatt and Alan R. Roe           Editorial Tecnos, 1973; 4th printing, 1980.&#13;
pay-as-you-go financed and fully          Staff Working Paper No. 338. 1979. 87     ISBN 84-309-0716-5, Stock No. IB 0526.&#13;
funded social security schemes, and       .iages (including footnotes).              $6.&#13;
characteristics of optimal social secu-   Stock No. WP 0338. $3.&#13;
rity systems. This study provides a&#13;
starting point for everyone interested&#13;
in the relevance of existing theories for  The Changing Nature of Export             A Conceptual Approach to the&#13;
financing social security in developing    Finance and Its Implications              Analysis of External Debt of&#13;
countries.                                 for Developing Countries                  the Developing Countries&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 625. 1983. 62      Albert C. Cizauskas                       Robert Z. Aliber&#13;
pages.                                     Staff Working Paper No. 409. 1980. 43     Staff Working Paper No. 421. 1980. 25&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0292-2.Stock No. WP 0625,     pages (including 3 annexes).               pages (including appendix, references).&#13;
$3.                                        Stock No. WP 0409. $3.                    Stock No. WP 0421. $3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NEW                                  Staff Working Paper No. 632. 1984. 144   Growth and Structural&#13;
pages.                                  Adjustment in East Asia&#13;
Development Finance                      Stock No. WP 0632. $5.                  Parvez Hasan&#13;
Companies, State and Privately                                                   Staff Working Paper No. 529. 1982. 42&#13;
Owned: A Review                              NEW                                 pages.&#13;
David L. Gordon                                                                  ISBN 0-8213-0102-0. Stock No. WP 0529.&#13;
An informative guide to the function     Economic Liberalization and             $3.&#13;
and design of development finance        Stabilization Policies in               Interest Rate Management in&#13;
companies as they are set up in devel-   Argentina, Chile, and                   Developing Countries: Theory&#13;
oping countries. Case histories high-    Uruguay: Applications of the            aDeSimlatinCoun ResulTshfory&#13;
light the differences among these com-   Monetary Approach to the                and Simulation Results for&#13;
panies-their institutional structure,    Balance of Payments                     SoutdeKrevan   ij   re&#13;
management style, financial perfor-                                              Sweder van Wijnbergen&#13;
mance, and other features. Loofs at      Edited by Nicolas Ardito Barletta,      Examines the claim that higher time&#13;
the problems of resource mobilization    Mario 1. Blejer, and Luis Landau        deposit rates raise output and lower&#13;
and strategies to overcome them.         Twenty-eight leading international      inflation in the short run, and increase&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 578. 1983. 84    economists and regional specialists re-  growth through their favorable impact&#13;
pages.                                   view the salient characteristics of the  on savings rates. It concludes that this&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0226-4. Stock No. WP 0578.   monetary approach to the balance of     theory depends heavily on the as-&#13;
$3.                                      payments, examine the variations in     sumption that portfolio shifts into time&#13;
its application, and evaluate its suc-  deposits come out of unproductive as-&#13;
Development Prospects of                 cesses and failures. Emphasizes the     sets, providing less intermediation&#13;
Capital Surplus Oil-Exporting            empirical evidence and dynamic as-      than the banking system. Impact of&#13;
Countries: Iraq, Kuwait, Libya,          pects and costs. Provides an important  changes in time deposit rates on infla-&#13;
Qtanr,    : SaudIArabi huwaltya, UAEexamination of economic policies and         tion, capital, capital accumulation and&#13;
Qatar, Saudi Arabia, UAE                 their effects in a region that looms    medium term growth are discussed,&#13;
Rudolf Hablutzel                         large in current deliberations about in-  and empirical relevance is demon-&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 483. 1981. 53    ternational indebtedness and finance.   strated through simulation runs with a&#13;
pages (including statistical tables).    June 1984. About 240 pages.             macroeconomic model of South Korea.&#13;
Stock No. WP 0483. $3.                   ISBN 0-8213-0305-8. $17.50 paperback.   World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 593.&#13;
1983. 52 pages.&#13;
Developments in and Prospects            Energy Prices, Substitution,            ISBN 0-8213-0188-8. Stock No. WP 0593.&#13;
for the External Debt of the             and Optimal Borrowing in the            $3&#13;
Developing Countries: 1970-80            Short Run: An Analysis of&#13;
and Beyond                               Adjustment in Oil-Importing             International Adjustment in&#13;
Nicholas C. Hope                         Developing Countries                    the 1980s&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 488. 1981. 70    Ricardo Martin and Marcelo              Vijay Joshi&#13;
pages (including 2 annexes, references).  Selowsky                               Staff Working Paper No. 485. 1982. 57&#13;
Stock No. WP 0488. $3.                   Staff Working Paper No. 466. 1981. 77   pages.&#13;
pages (including footnotes, references).  ISBN 0-8213-0062-8. Stock No. 0485. $3.&#13;
Stock No. WP 0466. $3.&#13;
NEW&#13;
Exchange Rate Adjustment                    NEW&#13;
Domestic Resource                        under Generalized Currency&#13;
Mobilization in Pakistan:                Floating: Comparative Analysis          Links between Taxes and&#13;
Selected Issues                          among Developing Countries              Empioic    Evidence&#13;
Nizar Jetha, Shamshad Akhtar,            Romeo M. Bautista                       Empincal Evidence&#13;
and M. Govinda Rao                       Staff Working Paper No. 436. 1980. 99   Keith Marsden&#13;
Fouses on the relationship between       pages (including appendix).             Reviews the experience with growth&#13;
taxation and the three main compo-       Stock No. WP 0436. $3.                  and taxation in twenty developing and&#13;
nents of savings. Emphasizes tax re-                                             developed countries, spanning a wide&#13;
form with a view to raising additional   A General Equilibrium                   spectrum of incomes. Do countries&#13;
revenues and encouraging household       Analysis of Foreign Exchange            with lower taxes experience more&#13;
and business savings. Proposals for tax  Shortages in a Developing               rapid expansion of investment, pro-&#13;
reform take account of equity consid-    Economr                                 ductivity, employment, and govern-&#13;
erations and the need to keep tax-in-    mem      y          rdent services? This provocative paper&#13;
duced distortions in the allocation of   Kemal Dervis, Jaime de Melo, and        sheds new light on this and other key&#13;
resources to a minimum. Highlights       Sherman Robinson                        questions especially relevant to devel-&#13;
appropriate policies on current ex-      Staff Working Paper No. 443. 1981. 32   opment economists. It also examines&#13;
penditures, subsidies, user charges,     pages (including references).           the mechanisms by which fiscal poli-&#13;
public enterprise pricing, self-financing  Stock No. WP 0443. $3.                des may affect growth rates.&#13;
of investment by public enterprises.                                             Staff Working Paper No. 605. 1983. 48&#13;
Includes three annexes that examine                                              pages.&#13;
direct taxes, indirect taxes, and tax    Prices subject to change without notice  ISBN 0-8213-0215-9. Stock No. WP 0605.&#13;
changes in Pakistan's 1983/84 budget.     and may vary by country.               $3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NEW                                   The Policy Experience of                  Private Bank Lending to&#13;
Twelve Less Developed                     Developing Countries&#13;
Municipal Accounting for                  Countries, 1973-1978                      Richard O'Brien&#13;
Developing Countries                      Bela Balassa                              Staff Working Paper No. 482. 1981. 60&#13;
David C. Jones                            Staff Working Paper No. 449. 1981. 36    pages (including appendix, bibliography).&#13;
This manual is based on British prac-     pages (including appendix).               Stock No. WP 0482. $3.&#13;
tices and terminology of municipal ac-    Stock No. WP 0449. $3.                    Private Capital Flows to&#13;
counting, modified to suit the needs of&#13;
other countries, especially those lack-   The Political Structure of the            Developing Countries and&#13;
ing a core of appropriately trained ac-   New Protectionism                        Their Determinations:&#13;
countants. Provides the basic princi-     Douglas R. Nelson                        Historical Perspective, Recent&#13;
ples of municipal accounting for those          a R.                                     rieca  Persetive,&#13;
with littie or no bookkeeping experi-     Staff Working Paper No. 471. 1981. 57    Experence, and Future&#13;
ence and proceeds through successive      pages (including references).             Prospects&#13;
levels of difficulty to some of the most  Stock No. WP 0471. $3.                   Alex Flenmng&#13;
advanced concepts currently in use,                                                 Staff Working Paper No. 484. 1981. 41&#13;
including the pooling of loans. An im-                                             pages.&#13;
portant feature is the multitude of           NEW                                   Stock No. WP 0484. $3.&#13;
practical applications and examples of&#13;
forms and records.                                                                 Private Direct Foreign&#13;
A joint publication of the Chartered      Price Distortions and Growth             Investment in Developing&#13;
Institute of Public Finance and Ac-       in Developing Countries                   Countries&#13;
countancy and the World Bank.             Ramgopal Agarwala                         K. Billerbeck and Y. Yasugi&#13;
June 1984. About 900 pages.               Sixteen informative tables trace the      Staff Working Paper No. 348. 1979, 101&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0350-3. Stock No. BK 0350.    distortion in prices of foreign exchange  pages (including 2 annexes).&#13;
$30.                                      and other factors affecting the growth    Stock No. WP 0348. $5.&#13;
of developing countries. Based on sta-&#13;
The Nature of Credit Markets              tistics from thirty-one developing&#13;
in Developing Countries: A                countries.                                   NEW&#13;
FrameWork for Policy Analysis             Staff Working Paper No. 575. 1983. 78&#13;
Arvind Virmani                            pages.                                    Savings Mobilization through&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 524. 1982. 204    ISBN 0-8213-0242-6. Stock No. WP 0575.    Social Security: The Case of&#13;
pages.                                    $3.                                       Chile,, 1916-1977&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0019-9. Stock No. WP 0524.                                              Christine Wallich&#13;
$5-                                       Pricing Policy for Development            Describes the savings mobilization po-&#13;
The Newly Industrializing                 Management                                tential in Chile and in five Asian pro-&#13;
DhevNewlopIngdCuntriesafterith            Gerald M. Meier                           grams. Some sort of social security&#13;
Oievloping Countries after the            Presupposing no formal training in        program functions in almost all devel-&#13;
economics, it explains the essential      oping countries. Programs are often&#13;
Bela Balassa                              elements of a price system, the func-     costly, whether measured in relation&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 437. 1980. 57     tions of prices, the various policies     to GNP, government expenditure,&#13;
pages (including appendix).               that a govemment might pursue in          govemment revenue, or the wage bill.&#13;
Stock No. WP 0437. $3.                    cases of market failure, and the princi-  This paper compares the successful&#13;
ples of public pricing of goods and       systems.&#13;
Notes on the Analysis of                  services provided by govemment en-        Staff Working Paper No. 553. 1983. 109&#13;
Capital Flows to Developing               terprises. It also provides the would-be  pages.&#13;
Nations and the "Recycling"               practitioner with an appreciation of the  ISBN 0-82.3-0123-3. Stock No. WP 0553.&#13;
underlying logical structure of cost-     ISN081302-. tc          o.W    53&#13;
Problem                                   benefit project appraisal. To give sub-&#13;
Ralph C. Bryant                           stance to the applied and policy di-     Short-Run Macro-Economic&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 476. 1981. 67     mensions, many of the readings are       Adjustment Policies in South&#13;
pages.                                    drawn from the experience of develop-&#13;
ment practitioners and relate to such    Korea: A Quantitative Analysis&#13;
Stock No. WP 0476. $3.                    important sectors as agriculture, in-    Sweder van Wijnbergen&#13;
Notes on the Mechanics of                 dustry, power, urban services, foreign   Staff Working Paper No. 510. 1981. 182&#13;
Growth and Debt                           trade, and employment. The principles    pages (including 3 appendixes).&#13;
Benjamin B. King                          outlined are therefore relevant to a     ISBN 0-8213-0000-8. Stock No. WP 0510.&#13;
host of development problems.            $5.&#13;
A practical model to explore the way      The Johns Hopkins University Press. 1983.&#13;
in which capital inflow from abroad af-   272 pages (including bibliography and in-&#13;
fects economic growth.                    dex).&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1968.  LC 82-7716. ISBN 0-8018-2803-1, Stock&#13;
69 pages (including 4 annexes).           No. JH 2803, $35 hardcover; ISBN 0-&#13;
LC 68-8701. ISBN 0-8018-0338-1, Stock     8018-2804-X, Stock No. JH 2804, $12.95    Prices subject to change without notice&#13;
No. JH 0338. $5 paperback.                paperback.                                and may vary by country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
State Finances in India&#13;
A three-volume set of papers that ex-&#13;
plores a range of issues relating to the                                           /&#13;
nature of intergovernmental fiscal rela-        T      p          s         fo                 D&#13;
tions in India.                              "The primary source for                    World Debt Tables&#13;
Vol. I: Revenue Sharing in India              medium- and long-term                      E-         P-&#13;
Christine Wallich                                                                       _ d                      I&#13;
Vol. Il: India-Studies in State Fi-&#13;
nances                                        developing countries.99&#13;
Christine Wallich&#13;
Vol. III: The Measurement of Tax Ef-                Suhas Ketkar, Asia-Pacific&#13;
fort of State Govemments, 1973-1976                 Economist and Vice President,&#13;
Raja J. Chelliah and Narain Sinha                   Marine Midland Bank, N.A.&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 523. 1982. vol.&#13;
I, 85 pages, vol. II, 186 pages, vol. 111, 85&#13;
pages.    3SOften the only reliable&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0013-X. vol. I, Stock No...                                          &#13;
WP 1523, $3, vol. 11, Stock No. WP           source of information for&#13;
2523, $5, vol. III, Stock no. WP 3523, $3.    countries for which data&#13;
is hard to come by          ... Used quantitatively for&#13;
macroeconomic detail as well as qualitatively in&#13;
Structural Adjustment Policies               reports discussing the debt picture. I find the&#13;
in Developing Economies                       projected servicing payments a strong feature.9&#13;
Bela Balassa                                                                         Jonathan Kayes, Interational&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 464. 1981. 36                                                Economist, Republic&#13;
pages.                                                                                National Bank of New York&#13;
Stock No. WP 0464. $3.&#13;
Structural Aspects of Turkish                 World     Debt Tables, 1983-84             Edition&#13;
Inflation: 1950-1979                         The World Bank's invaluable reference Also available for the first time&#13;
M. Ataman Aksov                               guide to the external debt of develop-&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 540. 1982. 118       ing countries. Essential planning tool       Y   P&#13;
pages.                                        for economists, bankers, country risk  Debt and the Developing&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0098-9. Stock No. WP 0540.       analysts, financial consultants and all  World: Current Trends&#13;
$5.                                       .   those interested in the global system&#13;
of trade and payments. Provides data  and Prospects&#13;
on the external debt of 103 developing Includes an overview and summary ta-&#13;
Thailand: An Analysis of                     countries augmented by information,  bles from the 1983-84 edition.&#13;
Structural and Non-Structural                where available, on major economic   1984. 64 pages.&#13;
Adjustments                                  aggregates plus indicators used to ana-&#13;
Arne Drud, Wafik Grais, and                  lyze debt and creditworthiness. Shows Stock No. BK 0319, $6.50.&#13;
Dusan Vujovic                                statistical tables by country, including  Companion computerized data&#13;
Staf Woring ape No.513.1982 93figures for external public debt out-    Coma   nincmuereddt&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 513. 1982. 93        standing, commitments, disburse-     base&#13;
pages (including appendix).                  ments, service payments, and net bor- Includes all debt information given in&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0023-7. Stock No. WP 0513.       rowings. Reports on private         the unabridged volume, and, where&#13;
$3.                                          nonguaranteed debt of 19 countries.  available, offers continuous historical&#13;
Gives aggregate position of 13 major  series for 1970-82 and projected debt-&#13;
borrowers-countries with disbursed  service payments for 1983-92. Write for&#13;
Trends in Rural Savings and                  and outstanding medium- and long-    sample purchase agreement.&#13;
Private Capital Formation in                 term total debt in excess of $13.5 bil-  (9-track, phase-encoded, recording&#13;
India                                        hon at the end of 1982. Includes peri-  density 1600 bpi)&#13;
Raj Krishna and G.S.                         odic supplements as fresh data are re- Stock No. IB 0500, $5,000 (service bur-&#13;
Raychaudhurn                                 ceived.                              eaus for reselling to their clients); Stock&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 382.      1984. 328 pages.                    No. IB 0667, $2,000 (banks and commer-&#13;
1980. 43 pages (including 2 tables, 3 ap-    Stock No. BK 0315 $75 (annual subscrip- cial corporations); Stock No. IB 0666, $500&#13;
pendixes, references).                       tion)                                (universities and libraries).&#13;
Stock No. WP 0382. $3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Publications Order Form&#13;
SEND TO: YOUR LOCAL DISTRIBUTOR OR TO WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
(See the other side of this fiorm.)       P.O. BOX 37525&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013 U.S.A.&#13;
Date&#13;
Name                                                 Ship to: (Enter if different from purchaser)&#13;
Title                                                Name&#13;
Firm                                                Title&#13;
Address                                              Firm&#13;
City               State_      Postal Code           Address&#13;
Country            'Tilephone I     I                City            State_      Postal Code&#13;
Purchaser Reference No.                              Country             Telephone&#13;
Check your method of payment.&#13;
Enclosed is my El Check  l International Money Order E3 Unesco Coupons E International Postal Coupon.&#13;
Make payable to World Bank Publications for U. S. dollars unless you are ordering from your local distributor.&#13;
Charge my E VISA al MasterCard al American Express El Choice. (Credit cards accepted only for orders addressed&#13;
to World Bank Publications.)&#13;
Credit Card Account Number           Expiration Date                     Signature&#13;
E Invoice me and please reference my Purchase Order No.&#13;
Please ship me the items listed below.&#13;
Customer Internal&#13;
Stock Number  Autbor/ Title                                      Routing Code  Quantity  Unit Price  Total Amount s&#13;
All prices subject to change.  Prices may vary by country.  Allow 6-8 weeks for delivery.&#13;
Subtotal Cost  $&#13;
Tbtal copies  -      Air mail surcharge if desired ($2.00 each)  $&#13;
Postage and handling for more than two complimentary items ($2.00 each)  $S&#13;
Thtal  $   -&#13;
18RD40sXt                                                         Thank you for your order.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Distributors of World          Attn: Mr. Giancarlo Bigazzi               Attn: Mr. J.M. Hernandez&#13;
Distributors of World                     Via Lamarmora 45                         Castello 37&#13;
Bank Publications                         50121                                    Madrid&#13;
ARGENTINA                                 Florence                                 SRI LANKA AND THE MALDIVES&#13;
Carlos Hirsch, SRL,                       JAPAN                                    Lake House Bookshop&#13;
Attn: Ms. Monica Bustos                   Eastern Book Service                     Attn: Mr. Victor Walatara&#13;
Florida 165 4° piso                       Attn: Mr. Terumasa Hirano                41 Wad Ramanavake Mawatha&#13;
Galeria Guemes                            37-3, Hongo 3-Chome, Bunkyo-ku 113       Colombo 2&#13;
Buenos Aires 1307                         Tokvo                                    SWEDEN&#13;
AUSTRALIA, PAPUA NEW GUINEA,              KENYA                                    ABCE Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel&#13;
Africa Book Services (E.A.) Ltd.          Attn: Mr. Eide Se erback&#13;
VANUATU SOLOMONISLANDS,Attn: Mr. M.B. Dar                                          Re     iygatan 11. Box 16356&#13;
WESTERN SAMOA, AND                       SP.O. Boxc45245&#13;
VANUATU                                   PO   o   54&#13;
The Australian Financial Review           Nairobi                                  SWITZERLAND&#13;
Information Service (AFRIS)               KOREA, REPUBLIC OF                       Librairie Pavot&#13;
Attn: Mr. David Jamieson                  Pan Korea Book Corporation               Attn: Mr. Henri de Perrot&#13;
235-243 Jones Street                      Attn: Mr. Yoon-Sun Kim                   6, rue Grenus&#13;
Broadwav                                  P.O. Box 101, Kwanghwamun                1211 Geneva&#13;
Svdnev, NSW 20001                         Seoul                                    TANZANIA&#13;
BELGIUM                                  MALAYSIA                                  Oxford University Press&#13;
Publications des Nations Unies            University of Malaya Cooperative         Attn: Mr. Anthony Theobold&#13;
Attn: Mr. Jean de Lannov                  Bookshop Ltd.                            Maktaba Road, P.O. Box 5299&#13;
av. du Roi 202                            Attn: Mr. Mohammed Fahim Hti             Dar es Salaam&#13;
1060 Brussels                            Yacob                                     THAILAND&#13;
P.O. Box 1127, Jalan Pantai Baru          Central Department Store, Head Office&#13;
CANADA                                   Kuala Lumpur                              Attn: Mrs. Katana&#13;
Attn: M1rs. Suzanne Vermette              MEXICO                                   306 Silom Road&#13;
C.P. 85, Boucherville J4B 5E6            INFOTEC                                   Bangkok&#13;
Quebec                                    Attn: Mr. Jorge Cepeda                   Thailand Management Association&#13;
San Lorenzo 153-1 1, Col. del Valle,      Attn: Mrs. Sunan&#13;
COSTA RICA                                Deleg. Benito Juarez                     308 Silom Road&#13;
Libreria Trej os,                         3lgMxc,DF                                 ago&#13;
Attn: Mr. Hugo Chamberlain               03100 Mexico, D.F.                        Bangkok&#13;
Calle 11-13, Av. Fernandez Guell          MIDDLE EAST                              TUNISIA&#13;
San Jose                                  Middle East Marketing Research           Societe Tunisienne de Diffusion&#13;
Bureau                                    Attn: Mr. Slaheddine Ben Hamida&#13;
DENMARK                                   Attn: Mr. George Vassilou                ; Avenue de Carthage&#13;
Sanfundslitteratur                        Mitsis Bldg. 3                           Tunis&#13;
Attn: Mr. Wilfried Roloff                 Makarios fii Avenue                      TuRE&#13;
Rosenderns Alle 11                        Nicosia                                  TURKEY&#13;
DK-1970 Copenhagen V.                     Cvpros                                   Haset Kitapevi AS.&#13;
EGYPT, Arab Republic of                  (Branch offices in Bahrain, Greece,       Attn: Mr. Izzet Izerel&#13;
Al Ahram                                 Morocco, Kuwait. United Arab              469, Iseklal Caddes&#13;
Al Galaa Street                           Emirates, Jordan)                        bevoglu-lstanbul&#13;
Cairo                                     NETHERLANDS                              UNITED KINGDOM AND&#13;
MBE BV                                    NORTHERN IRELAND&#13;
FINLAND                                   Attn: Mr. Gerhard van Bussell            Microinfo Ltd.&#13;
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa                   Noorderwal 38,                           Attn: Mr. Roy Selwyn&#13;
Attn: Mr. Kari Litmanen                  7241 BL Lochem                            Newman Lane P.O. Box 3&#13;
Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100                    NORWAY                                   Alton, Hampshire GU34 2PG&#13;
Helsinki 10                              Johan Grundt Tanum A.S.                   England&#13;
FRANCE                                   Attn: Ms. Randi Mikkelborg                UNITED STATES&#13;
World Bank Publications                   P.o. Box 1177 Sentrum                    The World Bank Book Store&#13;
66, avenue d'lena                         Oslo 1                                   600 19th Street, N.W.&#13;
75116 Paris                               PANAMA                                   Washington, D.C. 20433&#13;
GERMANY, Federal Republic of              Ediciones Libreria Cultural l'anamena    (Postal address: P.O. Box 37525&#13;
UNO-Verlag                                Attn: Mr. Luis Fernandez Fraguela R.     Washington, D.C. 20013, U.S.A.)&#13;
Attn: Mr. Joachim Krause                  Av. 7, Espana 16                         Baker and Taylor Companv&#13;
Simrockstrasse 23                         Panama   one 1                           501 South Gladiola Avenue&#13;
D-5300 Bonn I                             PHILIPPINES                              Momence, Illinois, 60954&#13;
HONG KONG, MACAU                          National Book Store                      380 Edison Way&#13;
Asia 2000 Ltd.                            Attn: Mrs. Socorro C. Ramos              Reno, Nevada, 89564&#13;
Attn: Ms. Gretchen Wearing Smith         701 Rizal Avenue                          50 Kirbv Avenue&#13;
6 Fl., 146 Prince Edward Road             Mania                                    Somerville, New Jersey, 08876&#13;
Kowloon                                   PORTUGAL                                 Commerce, Georgia 30599&#13;
INDIA                                     Livraria Portugal&#13;
Attn: Mr. Antonio Alves Martins           Bernan Associates&#13;
UBS Publishers' Distributors Ltd.         Ru   oCro7-49730-E George Palmer Highwav&#13;
Attn: Mr. D.P. Veer                       Rua                                      Lanham, Maryland, 20761&#13;
5 Ansari Road, Post Box 7015              120&#13;
New Delhi 110002                         LIsbon                                    Blackwell North America, Inc.&#13;
(Branch offices in Bombay, Bangalore,     SAUDI ARABIA                            .0 B  Facwood Newl JRsea 001&#13;
Kanpur, Calcutta, and MYadras)                                                     Blackwood, New Jersea 08012&#13;
INDONESIA                                 Attn: Mr. Akram Al-Agil                  Sidney Kramer Books&#13;
Pt. Indira Limited                        P.O. Box 3196                            1722 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Attn: Mr. Bambang Wahyudi                 Riyadh                                   Washington, D.C. 20006&#13;
JI, Dr. Sam Ratulangi No. 37             SINGAPORE, TAIWAN, BURMA                  United Nations Bookshop&#13;
Jakarta Pusat                            Information Publications Private, Ltd.    United Nations Plaza&#13;
IRELAND                                  Attn: Ms. Janet David                     New York, N.Y. 10017&#13;
TDC Publishers                           02-06 Ist Floor, Pei-Fu Industrial        VENEZUELA&#13;
Attn: Mr. James Booth                       Building&#13;
12 North Frederick Street                24 New Industrial Road                    Libreria del Este&#13;
Duli Not                                 Singaporetree                             Attn. Mr. Juan Pericas&#13;
Dublin I                                 Singapore                                 Avda Francisco de Miranda, no. 52&#13;
ITALY                                    SPAIN                                     Edificio Gali an, Aptdo. 60.337&#13;
Licosa Commissionaria Sansoni SPA        Mundi-Prensa Libros, S.A.                 Caracas 106-A&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                        European Office             Tokyo Office                          U&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                66, avenue d'k6na            Kokusai Building&#13;
Washingtoni, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.     751 16 Paris, France        1-1 Marunioucihi 3-chomne&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234           Telephone: (1) 723-54.21    Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo i00, lapan&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK        TIelex: 842-620628           Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                        Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address: INT13AFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTON DC&#13;
ISSN 0253-2 115/ISBN 0-8213-0438-0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554788">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/11/1554788/adjustment-policies-developing-countries-1979-83-update
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/11/1554788/adjustment-policies-developing-countries-1979-83-update</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1984/11/1554788/adjustment-policies-developing-countries-1979-83-update</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/23/000178830_98101903424337/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/23/000178830_98101903424337/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-09-23T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1984-11-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Adjustment policies in developing
            countries, 1979-83 : an update
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Analysis of the policies applied by
            developing countries in response to the external shocks of
            the 1979-82 period is extended to 1983. The shocks in
            question include the increase in oil prices in 1979-80, the
            slowdown of the world economy after 1978, the rise of
            interest rates starting in late 1978, and the softening of
            commodity prices in 1981 and 1982. Both policy variables and
            performance indicators are used in the analysis. Policy
            variables provide an indication of the policy effort made by
            the countries confronted by external shocks; at the same
            time, the choice is limited by the availability of
            quantitative measures and, in their absence, by the
            possibility of a judgmental evaluation based on available
            information on the policies applied. Performance indicators
            are derived in the framework of a methodology that permits
            separating external shocks and policy responses to them;
            they have been taken to reflect the effects of the policies
            applied on performance in dealing with external shocks. The
            results do suggest some correspondence between policy
            variables and performance indicators. Many intercountry
            differences in domestic adjustment may be explained by
            exchange rate and energy price policy, or less so by
            monetary and interest rate policy.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Adjustment policies in developing countries,
            1979-83 : an update
        </docna>
        <display_title>Adjustment policies in developing
            countries, 1979-83 : an update</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1984/11/1554788/adjustment-policies-developing-countries-1979-83-update</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Economic Stabilization,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Inequality,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Achieving Shared Growth</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Balassa, B.</author>
            <author>McCarthy, F.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903424337</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Macro/non-trade</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 675</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0438-0</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Economic indicators; Economic policy;
            External shocks; Data analysis; Case studies
            absolute terms,Adjustment policies,adverse
            effects,agricultural exports,annual rate,average
            annual,Balance of Payments,Bank lending,CD,consumer price
            index,country data,debt,devaluation,developed
            countries,developing countries,development policies,discount
            rate,discount rates,domestic credit,domestic
            savings,economic growth,economic indicators,economic
            relations,economic
            structure,economists,elasticity,equilibrium,exchange
            rate,exchange rate policy,export promotion,export
            subsidies,exports,external shocks,financial
            resources,Foreign exchange,fuels,GDP,GNP,government
            budget,government budget deficit,gross domestic
            product,gross national product,growth rate,growth rates,high
            correlation,import substitution,imports,income,income
            elasticity,individual countries,inflation,Inflation
            Rate,inflation rates,interest rate,interest
            rates,macroeconomic policies,macroeconomic policy,monetary
            policies,monetary policy,money creation,money supply,oil,oil
            exporters,oil prices,overvaluation,overvalued
            exchange,overvalued exchange rate,personal savings,policy
            changes,policy measures,policy packages,policy stance,policy
            variables,political economy,public enterprises,public
            expenditures,public sector,rate of inflation,real exchange
            rates,real interest rates,relative importance,relative
            prices,resource allocation,savings,Structural
            Adjustment,surcharges,terms of trade,trade
            liberalization,trade policies,trade policy,wholesale prices
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP675</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Currencies and Exchange Rates</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary and Exchange Rate Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Stabilization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Exchange Rate Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Interest Rate Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Balance of Payments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>