<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>The Supply Response for Rubber in Sri Lanka&#13;
A Preliminary Analysis&#13;
Michael J. Hartley&#13;
Marc Nerlove&#13;
R. Kyle Peters, Jr.     SW    P657&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 657&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 657&#13;
The Supply Response for Rubber in Sri Lanka&#13;
A Preliminary Analysis&#13;
Michael J. Hartley&#13;
Marc Nerlove&#13;
R. Kyle Peters, Jr.&#13;
1XIERNATIONAL MONETARY FUND&#13;
JOINT LIBRARY&#13;
OCT   2 6 i1334&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANE rOH&#13;
CONSTRUCTIOIT AND DZVELOPLIENT&#13;
WASHINGTON. D.C. 20431&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright (© 1984&#13;
The Intemational Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing September 1984&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To present the&#13;
results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been prepared&#13;
in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed texts, and the&#13;
World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a&#13;
token charge to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to any&#13;
individual acting on their behalf. Any maps used have been prepared solely for the&#13;
convenience of the readers; the denominations used and the boundaries shown do&#13;
not imply, on the part of the World Bank and its affiliates, any judgment on the&#13;
legal status of any territory or any endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications, both free and for sale, is described in&#13;
the Catalog of Publications; the continuing research program is outlined in Abstracts of&#13;
Current Studies. Both booklets are updated annually; the most recent edition of each&#13;
is available without charge from the Publications Sales Unit, Department T, The&#13;
World Bank, 1818 H Street, N.W., Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A., or from the&#13;
European Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'1ena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Michael J. Hartley is an economist in the Development Research Department of&#13;
the World Bank. Marc Nerlove, a consultant to the Bank, is professor of economics&#13;
at the University of Pennsylvania. R. Kyle Peters, Jr. is an economic support systems&#13;
analyst in the World Bank's East Asia and Pacific Regional Office.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Hartley, Michael J., 1943-&#13;
The supply response for rubber in Sri Lanka.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 657)&#13;
1. Rubber industry--Sri Lanka--Mathematical models.&#13;
I. Nerlove, Marc, 1933-            .  II. Peters, R. Kyle,&#13;
1954-        .  III. World Bank.      IV. Title.     V. Series.&#13;
HD9161.S752H37      1984        338.4'76782'0724         84-17328&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0403-8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Abstract&#13;
Study of supply response for perennial crops has frequently been&#13;
limited by lack of data: in many instances data are available only on output,&#13;
producer prices, and area under cultivation. This has led many investigators&#13;
to concentrate on the estimation of a "reduced-form" equation that may fail to&#13;
capture important structural features of the determination of the supply&#13;
response of these crops. Our study is based on new extensive time series for&#13;
rubber in Sri Lanka covering total output, producer prices, new plantings,&#13;
replantings, wage rates, area under cultivation (disaggregated by region, type&#13;
of planting, size of holding, and age), as well as many other variables. In&#13;
addition, we have a survey of 49 rubber estates in which data have been&#13;
collected on yields, type and age of clone, stand densities, and many other&#13;
variables. These panel data cover a 10 year period, 1970-79. This paper&#13;
reports some preliminary analysis of the Sri Lankan data designed to test the&#13;
adequacy of Dowling's analysis of supply response for rubber in Thailand,&#13;
based on a quite sophisticated reduced form supply function developed by&#13;
Wickens and Greenfield for Brazilian coffee. Because the uprooting-replanting&#13;
decision is central to understanding rubber supply response in Sri Lanka and&#13;
because this particular structural feature is obscured in these reduced form&#13;
formulations, they prove inadequate. Our model not only focuses on the&#13;
uprooting-replanting decision but disaggregates the "reduced form" into&#13;
several structural relationships. Essential use is made of the age&#13;
distribution and age-yield profile data from the estate surveys at our&#13;
disposal. This modest extension of the Wickens-Greenfield formulation&#13;
performs significantly better in the Sri Lankan context, than a&#13;
straightforward application of the model.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Extracto&#13;
El estudio de la reacci6n de la oferta de cultivos perennes&#13;
frecuentemente se ha visto limitado por falta de datos: en muchos casos&#13;
hay datos disponibles unicamente sobre la producci6n, los precios a los&#13;
productores y la superficie cultivada. Esto ha llevado a muchos&#13;
investigadores a concentrar la atenci6n en el cAlculo de una ecuaci6n de&#13;
"forma reducida", que puede no captar caracteristicas estructurales&#13;
importantes para la determinaci6n de la reacci6n de la oferta de estos&#13;
cultivos. Nuestro estudio se basa en series cronol6gicas nuevas y amplias&#13;
relativas al caucho en Sri Lanka, que comprenden la producci6n total, los&#13;
precios a los productores, las nuevas plantaciones, las replantaciones,&#13;
los salarios, la superficie cultivada (desagregada por regi6n, tipo de&#13;
plantaci6n, tamaino de las explotaciones y edad de la plantaci6n), asi como&#13;
muchas otras variables. Ademas, se ha realizado una encuesta de 49&#13;
plantaciones de caucho, en la cual se recopilaron datos sobre&#13;
rendimientos, tipo y edad de los clonos, densidades de plantio y muchas&#13;
otras variables. El conjunto de datos abarca un periodo de 10 ainos, de&#13;
1970 a 1979. En el presente documento aparece un analisis preliminar de&#13;
los datos de Sri Lanka que tiene por finalidad poner a prueba la validez&#13;
del analisis Dowling de la reacci6n de la oferta del caucho en Tailandia,&#13;
basandose en una funci6n-oferta de forma reducida bastante avanzada,&#13;
desarrollada por Wickens y Greenfield para el cafe brasileino. Como la&#13;
decisi6n de erradicar o replantar es de importancia fundamental para&#13;
comprender la reacci6n de la oferta del caucho en Sri Lanka y debido a que&#13;
esta caracteristica estructural especifica no se define netamente en estas&#13;
formulaciones reducidas, las mismas resultan inapropiadas. Nuestro modelo&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
no s6lo se centra en la decisi6n de erradicar o replantar sino que tambi6n&#13;
desagrega la "forma reducida" en varias relaciones estructurales. Se&#13;
utilizan fundamentalmente los datos sobre distribuci6n por edad y el&#13;
perfil de los rendimientos por edad obtenidos de las encuestas disponibles&#13;
de las plantaciones. En el contexto de Sri Lanka, esta modesta ampliaci6n&#13;
de la formulaci6n de Wickens-Greenfield proporciona resultados&#13;
significativamente mejores que los de la aplicaci6n directa del modelo.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Faute de donnees, il est difficile d'etudier l'evolution de&#13;
l'offre de cultures perennes : dans bien des cas, les statistiques&#13;
disponibles ne portent que sur la production, les prix a la production, et&#13;
les superficies cultivees. De ce fait, de nombreux chercheurs doivent se&#13;
borner a formuler une equation de "forme r6duite", qui ne tient pas&#13;
toujours compte de certains elements structurels importants pour deter-&#13;
miner l'6volution de l'offre de ces cultures. La presente 6tude se fonde&#13;
sur de nouvelles series chronologiques de grande ampleur concernant le&#13;
caoutchouc a Sri Lanka; elles portent sur la production totale, les prix a&#13;
la production, les nouvelles plantations, les replantations, l'echelle des&#13;
salaires, les superficies cultivees (ventil6es par r6gion, type de plan-&#13;
tation, taille d'exploitation et age), ainsi que sur bien d'autres varia-&#13;
bles. La Banque mondiale dispose en outre d'une enquete sur 49 planta-&#13;
tions de caoutchouc, qui contient des statistiques sur les rendements, le&#13;
type et l'age des clones, la densite des peuplements, et de nombreuses&#13;
autres variables. Celles-ci couvrent une p6riode de 10 ans (1970-79). Le&#13;
present document comporte quelques analyses preliminaires des donnees&#13;
concernant Sri Lanka, analyses visant a verifier la justesse des travaux&#13;
de Dowling sur l'evolution de l'offre de caoutchouc en Thailande, a partir&#13;
d'une fonction d'offre de forme reduite, mais tres elaboree, construite&#13;
par Wickens et Greenfield pour le cafe du Bresil. Toutefois, les deci--&#13;
sions relatives a l'arrachage et a la replantation sont d'une importance&#13;
capitale pour determiner 1'6volution de l'offre de caoutchouc a Sri Lanka,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
et comme les formulations simplifi6es ne tiennent pas compte de cet e1lment&#13;
structurel particulier, elles se r6velent inadequates. Le modele present6&#13;
dans ce document n'est pas seulement fonde sur les decisions d'arrachage&#13;
et de replantation, mais il d6sagrege la "forme reduite" en diverses rela-&#13;
tions structurelles. Les donnees afferentes a la r6partition par age et&#13;
aux profils de rendement correspondant a cette r6partition, que contiennent&#13;
les 6tudes de la Banque sur les plantations de caoutchouc, jouent un role&#13;
tres important dans le modele. Dans le cas de Sri Lanka, cette modeste&#13;
extension de la formulation Wickens-Greenfield permet d'obtenir des resul-&#13;
tats sensiblement plus satisfaisants que l'application directe du modele&#13;
originel.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Acknowledgements&#13;
The research on which this paper is based was supported under World&#13;
Bank research project 672-02. We are grateful to Colin Barlow of the&#13;
Australian National University and to Ron Duncan, T. Akiyama, Alan Bowers, and&#13;
Suan Tan of the Bank, for numerous helpful comments and suggestions. We are&#13;
also grateful to Mr. Eric Swanson for his comments and suggestions, as well as&#13;
his assistance in analyzing the rubber estate data. We owe a special debt to&#13;
Graham Pyatt for his wise counsel on both substantive and procedural matters.&#13;
The usual caveats with respect to responsibility apply.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page&#13;
Introduction   .     .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   I&#13;
The Wickens-Greenfield Criticism and Foundation  . o . . . .    2&#13;
Data Related to Rubber in Sri Lanka  . . . . . . . . . . . .    6&#13;
The Model  . . . . . . . . .                           . .      8&#13;
Empirical Results  ...  . . . . . . . . . . .  * * * * * * .   12&#13;
Replanting (12)&#13;
Production (14)&#13;
New Planting (14)&#13;
Conclusion . .   ......... ......  .... .................      15&#13;
Footnotes&#13;
References&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
1. Introduction&#13;
Study of supply response for perennial crops has frequently been&#13;
limited by lack of data: in many instances, data are available only on&#13;
output, producer prices, and area under cultivation. Occasionally such data&#13;
are supplemented by information on the age distribution of the stock of trees,&#13;
the proportion of the stock uprooted over time, new plantings, replantings,&#13;
removals, labor and other inputs (principally fertilizer), and corresponding&#13;
prices. Because of the data limitations, many investigations must inevitably&#13;
rely on greatly simplified "reduced-form" equations that may fail to capture&#13;
important structural features of the determination of the supply response of&#13;
perennials. Moreover, technological progress generally takes the form of&#13;
improvement of varieties or clones. With the result that, when additions are&#13;
made to the stock of trees, significant increases in the yields of a given&#13;
age-class are obtained over time. Thus, the new planting/replanting decisions&#13;
and the age and clonal composition of the stock are crucial in understanding&#13;
the supply response.&#13;
In Sri Lanka, it turns out that the replanting decisions are in fact&#13;
of overwhelming importance in the determination of supply response. Moreover,&#13;
such decisions are qualitatively different from new planting decisions in the&#13;
case of rubber, or indeed of any perennial with a long gestation period. This&#13;
contrasts rather sharply with the neoclassical view of the investment&#13;
decision, in which investment for net additions to the capital stock and&#13;
replacement investment are regarded as equivalent in terms of the derived&#13;
demand for the stock of capital as a factor of production. The reason&#13;
replacement demand is so different than demand for net additions in this&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
context is that old and still productive capital must be removed to replace&#13;
new capital, which in turn cannot be expected to yield its flow of productive&#13;
services for a considerable future period. Response to high current prices&#13;
must, for example, take into account information affecting future prices as&#13;
well as current prices. 1/ Moreover, expected changes in future technology&#13;
affect the obsolescence of the current stock as well as the desirability of&#13;
future investment.&#13;
Recently, extensive time series have become available for rubber in&#13;
Sri Lanka covering total output, producer prices, new plantings, replantings,&#13;
wage rates, area under cultivation (disaggregated by region, type of planting,&#13;
size of holding and age), fertilizer prices and use, and monthly climatic&#13;
conditions by growing district. In addition, the World Bank has undertaken a&#13;
survey of forty-nine estates in which data have been collected on yields, type&#13;
and age of clone, fertilizer application, tapping systems and intensities,&#13;
stand densities, rainfall, elevation and soil type by field within estate, and&#13;
on labor inputs. These panel data cover a ten-year period, 1970-79.&#13;
This paper reports some preliminary analyses of the Sri Lankan data,&#13;
designed to test the adequacy of the most recent supply response study for&#13;
rubber (Dowling, 1979) based on a relatively sophisticated reduced form supply&#13;
function developed by Wickens and Greenfield (1973). Because this formulation&#13;
proves inadequate to describe the main features of rubber supply response in&#13;
Sri Lanka, we have extended the Wickens-Greenfield formulation in a way that&#13;
makes better use of the age distribution and age-yield profile data at our&#13;
disposal. Although this modest extension performs significantly better in the&#13;
Sri Lankan context, it far from exhausts the potential of our data set for the&#13;
analysis of the determinants of rubber supply response. Further analyses&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
making greater use of our data set are planned.&#13;
2. Recent Studies of Perennial Supply Response with Particular Reference to&#13;
Rubber&#13;
a. An application of the Nerlove model by Grilli et al. (1981)&#13;
The formulation developed by Nerlove (1956) for the study of supply&#13;
response for annual crops has been used with little or no modification for the&#13;
study of perennials. An example is the study of rubber by inter alios, Grilli&#13;
et al. (1979). Stripped to its essentials, the Nerlove model consists of&#13;
three equations:&#13;
(1)       A  -A      = y(A*   A&#13;
t    t-l       t    t-l&#13;
(2)       P* -P*1, =    (p~    P1'&#13;
(3)       A* = a   + a P* + a Z  + U&#13;
t    o     1 t    2 t    t'&#13;
where  At is the actual area under cultivation in period t;     Pt is the actual&#13;
(real) price of the crop per unit in t; A* is the equilibrium, or area&#13;
t&#13;
"desired" to be under cultivation in t;    P* is the "expected normal" (real)&#13;
t&#13;
price in t for all subsequent future periods;    Zt represents a vector of all&#13;
other observed and presumably exogenous factors; and     ut captures other&#13;
unobserved or "latent" factors, affecting the area under cultivation in t.&#13;
The parameters B and y are, respectively, the coefficients of expectation and&#13;
adjustment reflecting the responses of expectations to observed prices and of&#13;
observed areas under cultivation to changes in equilibrium areas.&#13;
This model leads to a reduced-form equation of the form:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
(4)     At= Yo +o1Pt-,+ ya2Zt- Y(1-6)a2zt-,+ [(1-y)+(1-B)]At-&#13;
- (1-6)(1-y)A t2 + Yu t -y(l       t-l&#13;
It is possible to recover estimates of the structural parameters when&#13;
variables such as Z are present in the equation. These variables determine&#13;
the long-run equilibrium level, but are not "expectational." In practice a&#13;
reduced form model is estimated directly from a Nerlove model--couched either&#13;
in terms of area (At ) or output (qt)--without imposing any restrictions on the&#13;
reduced-form parameters.&#13;
E.g., Grilli et al. (1981) fit the following linear model:&#13;
(5)        qt =so0     1 6 qt-0++ 6 2  t  3     t'&#13;
where qt is output (in tons of natural rubber), Pt       is the producer price&#13;
received by producers there relative to the GNP deflator, and t is a time&#13;
trend. The results for three main producing countries, Malaysia, Indonesia,&#13;
Thailand, and the Rest of the World, are shown in Table 1. For Indonesia, a&#13;
dummy variable (1 for 1963, 0 otherwise) and t2 have been included as&#13;
dependent variables. For the "rest of the world", rubber price is the price&#13;
in Singapore deflated by the U.S. wholesale price index.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE 1: Supply Elasticities for Natural Rubber&#13;
Obtained by Crilli et al. (1981)&#13;
Short-Run Supply            Coefficient of&#13;
Country                         Elasticity                Lagged Output&#13;
Malaysia                           0.19                       0.425&#13;
Indonesia                          0.10                       0.324&#13;
Thailand                           0.24                       0.379&#13;
Rest of the World                  0.15                       0.336&#13;
Comparison with the Nerlove reduced form when derived from a&#13;
structure involving qt (rather than At) reveals that either the adaptive&#13;
expectation coefficient,   a,   or the partial adjustment coefficient,    y,&#13;
must be one to eliminate qt-2 from the model if the latter is the underlying-&#13;
maintained hypothesis. The long-run supply elasticities implied by the&#13;
results are about double the short-run elasticities. The latter appear to be&#13;
quite low--less than 0.25--in all cases.&#13;
As pointed out by Wickens and Greenfield (1973), as well as Grilli et&#13;
al., this formulation fails to distinguish between the investment decision&#13;
regarding the stock of trees and the harvesting decision. Consequently, the&#13;
implications of the biological relationship between the age of the tree stock&#13;
and its yield, as well as the "vintage" effects of improvements in varieties,&#13;
are obscured. Short-run supply response, with a given stock of trees, cannot&#13;
be disentangled from long-run responses involving adjustments in the size of&#13;
the stock of trees and its age and varietal composition arising from past new&#13;
planting, uprooting and replanting decisions. Thus, the interpretation of the&#13;
results of Grilli et al. reported in Table 1, for either short- or long-run&#13;
rubber supply response, is arguable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
b. Wickens and Greenfield (1973) on Coffee&#13;
Perhaps the most sophisticated model of perennial supply, yet&#13;
published, is due to Wickens and Greenfield (hereafter WG) who develop a&#13;
vintage model and estimate the supply response for Brazilian coffee. Also,&#13;
their model has recently been applied to rubber in Thailand by Dowling&#13;
(1979). While WG regard the preferred approach to be direct specification and&#13;
estimation of the structural relationships in their model of perennial supply&#13;
--namely, an investment function, a harvesting decision function, and a&#13;
vintage production function--data limitations usually preclude this. Instead,&#13;
the procedure adopted by both WG and Dowling is to specify the structural&#13;
relationships and derive a reduced-form supply function that can be estimated&#13;
directly from available data. It is possible, however, to draw inferences&#13;
about the structural relations through the use of extraneous information on&#13;
the age composition to determine the shape of the distributed lag response of&#13;
supply to changes in relative prices. It is worth examining the model and&#13;
results of WG in some detail as it is the point of departure for our&#13;
approach. Also, Dowling bases his recent work on rubber on the WC&#13;
formulation, but appears to have carried over to rubber a relationship found&#13;
empirically valid for coffee.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
The first relationship specified by WG is a simplified vintage&#13;
production function, relating "potential" output in any year to past&#13;
investments (or plantings) of trees. This embodies the simplifying assumption&#13;
that past cultivation inputs (labor, fertilizer) and past harvesting decisions&#13;
do not significantly affect the maximum output currently obtainable from a&#13;
given stand of trees. 2/ Furthermore, other current factors, such as labor,&#13;
are not explicitly included on the assumption that they are used in fixed&#13;
proportion to the stock of trees--the proportion varying only with the age of&#13;
the tree stock--and other cooperating factors are assumed to be present in&#13;
such abundance as to guarantee full utilization of the stock. Thus, all&#13;
potential output is assumed to be harvested. 3/&#13;
Following WG, let It_i represent the number of trees planted i years&#13;
ago and surviving to year t. Potential output, Qt' is assumed to be a&#13;
linear combination of past surviving plantings with coefficients, 6(i, t),&#13;
representing the yield per tree for stock of age i in year t, which depend not&#13;
only on the biological age-yield profiles of the trees but also on any&#13;
improvements in varieties over time or changes in agronomic practices&#13;
(planting densities, tapping systems, etc.). Thus, we may write&#13;
n&#13;
(6)       Qt =i     6(i,t)  I-i I&#13;
where n is the maximum length of life of a tree, and Qt represents the maximum&#13;
output 4/ attainable at time t given past plantings less removals and losses&#13;
due to disease, pests, etc. Removals are in fact largely related to&#13;
replanting decisions. These play little role in the WG formulation--see Arak&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(1969) for a discussion of removal practices on Brazilian coffee--but, as we&#13;
shall see, are a critical element in the determination of Sri Lankan rubber&#13;
supply. In the WG specification technical change is also ruled out, so that&#13;
6(i,t) = 6i is independent of t.   Also, if   6i is zero for  i &gt; n   and  for&#13;
i &lt; n includes a factor reflecting the probability of survival, then It-i&#13;
may be taken as plantings in year t-i excluding all removals, as below. 5/&#13;
As WG point out, data on the planting of new trees, whether as&#13;
replacements for uprooted old trees or as a net expansion of area under&#13;
cultivation, are rarely available--an exception being our data on area new&#13;
planted and replanted. Thus, the usual practice, as in the Nerlove model, is&#13;
to explain the total area under cultivation by a stock demand function. WG&#13;
follow this practice but derive such a stock demand function from a formal&#13;
optimizing model under a series of assumptions. In their model, it is assumed&#13;
that expected discounted net revenue&#13;
(7) V     =   O (1+r)   -(Pe - he) Qt  Ft- f(I)], where&#13;
t=o                 t &#13;
r     = the subjective rate of discount,&#13;
pte   = the expected price of the crop in t, 6/&#13;
e&#13;
h     = the expected unit cost of harvesting in t,&#13;
t&#13;
Qt    = potential output in t as defined in (1), 7/&#13;
Ft    = fixed costs of maintaining a planting in t,&#13;
It    = new planting in t (the same as It in (6) only if removals&#13;
and losses are excluded), and&#13;
f(I ) = a nonlinear cost of planting function, such that&#13;
f' &gt; 0 and f" &gt; 0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
The first-order conditions for a maximum of V subject to (6) yield the result&#13;
(8)      f(It) =     i  (l+r)    t+i- ht+i ) 6i= Rt&#13;
That is, investment in new plantings should continue until the marginal cost&#13;
of planting an additional tree equals the expected discounted net revenue from&#13;
the future production of that tree. The importance of the nonlinearity of f&#13;
is now apparent. If investment could be carried on at constant unit costs&#13;
irrespective of the amount undertaken, the investment under those&#13;
circumstances would not take place at all if the right side of (8) were less&#13;
than the left and would increase to that associated with the available land if&#13;
it were greater than the left.&#13;
It is difficult to justify the nonlinearity of the investment cost&#13;
function as the sole basis for determining new plantings (in WG) or&#13;
replantings (more generally). Indeed, a more general approach would involve&#13;
comparison of the expected discounted net revenues of the perennial with&#13;
alternative land uses. In the case of new plantings, these are the revenues&#13;
which would be generated by alternative crops; in the case of replantings,&#13;
they are revenues from an existing stand. The decline in yields with age,&#13;
however, results in increasing marginal opportunity costs as ever younger&#13;
stands are replanted.&#13;
If, however, the function f is nonlinear with f', f" &gt;0, then via the&#13;
implicit function theorem, (8) yields the relation&#13;
(9)      It = g(Re)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
where Rte is defined as the right-hand side of (8) . For example, if f is&#13;
t&#13;
quadratic, g is linear.&#13;
If a constant density of planting is assumed, the analysis may be&#13;
A&#13;
recast in terms of newly planted area,    It = d I     If  A  is the area under&#13;
t  t         ~~~~~t&#13;
cultivation in year t and   Ut is the area uprooted or abandoned, we have the&#13;
identity&#13;
A&#13;
(10)     It   At-At- Ut&#13;
hence,&#13;
(11)     AAt = d-g(R ) + U&#13;
t &#13;
In the WG formulation, f is assumed to be quadratic so that g is linear, and&#13;
e&#13;
Ut is assumed to be a random variable independent of Rt . Thus the problem&#13;
becomes estimation of&#13;
(12)     AAt = dB   + deR e+ Ut&#13;
through a suitable representation of Rte . Before we turn to WG's solution,&#13;
note that the area uprooted or abandoned is treated as a disturbance in the&#13;
equation to be estimated; to the extent that replanting is important in the&#13;
determination of potential output, Ut will not only be large relative to&#13;
e&#13;
AAt  but will also depend on Rt . Hence, it is quite inappropriate to treat&#13;
it as a classical random error.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
As defined in (8),   Rte is a function of expected future prices and&#13;
harvesting costs (primarily labor costs), the age-yield profile, and the&#13;
discount rate. While we have data on relevant wage rates for Sri Lanka, WG&#13;
choose to model Rte by a distributed lag of current and past prices only, since&#13;
t&#13;
apparently no such wage data exist for coffee workers in Brazil. The final&#13;
form of the planting equation in the WG formulation is not, however, a general&#13;
distributed lag formulation for prices based on (12) but, rather, is based on&#13;
an empirical relationship found for Brazilian coffee during the period&#13;
1932-69. This was obtained as follows: A simple distributed lag model was&#13;
postulated of the form:&#13;
m              n&#13;
(13) A  = a  + i   ai A     +   £  8 p    + u&#13;
and estimated using ordinary least squares. However, evidence of serial&#13;
correlation was found in the calculated residuals. The model was then&#13;
reestimated assuming first-order serial correlation of ut, but none was&#13;
found.  Lags in  At greater than two and in   Pt greater than zero were found&#13;
to be insignificant and the coefficients of   At_, and  At-2 approximately sum&#13;
to one, with the coefficient of   At 1 being greater than one.   This suggests&#13;
the empirical relationship:&#13;
(14)      At =a   + al 1AtAi+ BPt + ut&#13;
for Brazilian coffee, 1932-1969. As we shall see, Dowling (1979) uses the&#13;
same relationship for rubber but provides a different motivation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
The final relationship in the WG formulation is a short-run&#13;
harvesting equation. The assumption, inconsistent with that underlying the&#13;
derivation of (11), is that a fraction of potential output is actually&#13;
harvested, with the fraction depending on a short distributed lag in past&#13;
prices. 8/ The relationship is linearized to yield&#13;
m&#13;
(15)     Qt    YO   YlQt    i-O Yi+2Pt-i    YQt-1 &#13;
where Qt = actual output in t.    The term yQt 1 is added to represent a&#13;
biennial bearing cycle, which has been found empirically for coffee (WG, 1973,&#13;
p. 437).&#13;
The final WG model thus consists of the three equations discussed&#13;
above:&#13;
*=n&#13;
(6)      Qt    i-O i t-i&#13;
(14)      At    a  + a AAt-1 + a2Pt + ut&#13;
m&#13;
(15)     Qt    YO   YI Qt + i-O Yi+2 pt-i +Y Qt-1(&#13;
By substitution of (14) into (6), using the proportionality of It to&#13;
AAt - Ut   and then into (15), WG find the final reduced-form supply function:&#13;
n&#13;
(16)     Q     c O    i-O cipt-i + (     I + al) Qt-1  1 Qt-2 + Vt&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
where vt is a complicated moving average of the past u.'s and the&#13;
coefficients   c., i=,..., n have the following definitions:&#13;
(17)     ci      = a2yfI+ Y 2 '             i=l&#13;
a2y1li + Yi+2 - alyi+l' i=1. i    m&#13;
a2yT6m+l   alym+2'       i=m+l&#13;
= a2yiSi,                  i&gt;m+l&#13;
The output-response-to-price coefficients, ci, have a simple interpretation in&#13;
the case a,= 0, which corresponds to the long-run equilibrium solution for&#13;
Brazilian coffee, 1932-1969, obtained from the empirical relation (8):&#13;
namely, for the period of immaturity when cSi = 0 , they represent the short-&#13;
run price response of harvesting decisions y2, y3,..., but after this point&#13;
(three years in the case of coffee), they are proportional to the age-yield&#13;
curve.  Even if al is not zero, if m is small relative to the period over&#13;
which trees produce, after the point at which yi becomes zero (i &gt; m) the&#13;
coefficients will reflect primarily the age-yield profile.&#13;
WC estimate a reduced-form equation (14) using an Almon lag of length&#13;
9 with a fourth-order polynomial and obtain a lag shape very similar to the&#13;
age-yield profile after 3 years, the age at which a coffee tree begins to&#13;
bear. The sum of the absolute value of the price coefficients is highly&#13;
significant, indicating substantial long-run response to price. A likelihood-&#13;
ratio test is employed to test the restrictiveness of the Almon lag polynomial&#13;
imposed and is found insignificant. On this basis the authors conclude that&#13;
the results offer ". . . striking confirmation of the predictions of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
theory. . o" and advocate use of their appproach for the general study of&#13;
supply response of tree crops.&#13;
c. Dowling (1979) on rubber&#13;
In recent work on supply response for perennial crops, variants of&#13;
the WC formulation have been widely applied: Parikh (1979) on coffee, Dowling&#13;
and Jessadachat (1979) on sugar cane, and Dowling (1979) on rubber. On&#13;
rubber, Dowling's study for Thailand and the work of Grilli et al. cited&#13;
earlier represent the current state of the art. In contrast to the latter,&#13;
Dowling's investigation is explicitly based on the WG formulation for&#13;
coffee.   However, Dowling derives his reduced form in a slightly different&#13;
way, but obtains an almost identical estimating equation (it lacks only a term&#13;
in Qt-2 )-  His derivation permits an alternative interpretation of the&#13;
coefficients of lagged prices. Dowling's reduced form is obtained as follows:&#13;
As in WG, Dowling begins with a potential output equation&#13;
(18)           co=  -  6(i,t)  _,&#13;
where after some age, say n years, 6(i,t) = 0, i.e., the oldest trees no&#13;
longer yield.&#13;
All planting is assumed to be new planting, and, in year t is&#13;
represented as a distributed lag function of past prices&#13;
(19)     It    o   i- E&#13;
i =0 W.ipt-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
It is not, as in WG, explicitly derived by equating the marginal cost of new&#13;
investment to the expected present value of future net revenue--see equation&#13;
(8) and (9). This leads to a subtle difference in the interpretation of the&#13;
distributed lag coefficients: Dowling simply assumes the standard geometric&#13;
form of the distributed lag model,&#13;
(20)     W. = a0i , 0 &lt;    &lt;1,&#13;
obtained from an adaptive expectation model for prices, and thus writes&#13;
(21)     It =    +      t&#13;
where L is the lag operator.   Assuming no replanting and replacing   It by the&#13;
change in area under cultivation, aAt , then leads to exactly the same form&#13;
that WG found empirically valid for Brazilian coffee:&#13;
(22)     AAt = ao(l¢) + 8pt +      t-1'&#13;
or, equivalently,&#13;
BPt&#13;
(23)     AAt =    +&#13;
The difference between Dowling and WG is not in the form of the relationship&#13;
for change in area under cultivation, but rather its deviation. Both neglect&#13;
uprooting and abandonment, but WG start with a general distributed lag&#13;
formulation for investment and derive an equation identical to (22) as an&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
empirical approximation for Brazilian coffee, whereas Dowling obtains it by&#13;
the ad hoc assumption of adaptive expectations. As we show in the next&#13;
section, (22) represents a very poor formulation for changes in area in rubber&#13;
under cultivation in Sri Lanka, due to the dominance of uprooting and&#13;
replanting decisions.&#13;
Finally, Dowling hypothesizes a linear relationship between current&#13;
output, Qt, potential output, Qt , and a short, nonadaptive distributed lag in&#13;
past prices:&#13;
m&#13;
(24)     Qt = Yo + rlQt + i-O Yi+2Pt-i&#13;
which is identical to WG's formulation (15) except for the term in lagged&#13;
output, Q t-l which WG include to represent a two-year bearing cycle for&#13;
coffee.&#13;
To obtain the final reduced-form supply function, Dowling&#13;
replaces Qt in (24) by (18) and hAt by    p t/(1-4L), which is equivalent to&#13;
(22), arriving at the result:&#13;
(25)     Qt =O(t) + fQ       +                2)+ )pt&#13;
+ (yls6(1,t) + r3- fr2)pt-l&#13;
+ (y166(2,t) + r4- "3)pt-2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
+ (y I  (6,t) + y8- Y7 )p7t-6&#13;
+ (y1I6 (m,t) + rm+2   fym+l) Pt-m&#13;
+ (y166 (m+l,t) -Y m+2)pt-m-1&#13;
+ (Y a6(m+2,t))pt-m-2&#13;
+ (Y86(fn,t))pt-n&#13;
where                 (t) = y  + y B(1-4L) iO 6(i,t)&#13;
Since 6(i,t)    0 for i = 0, 1,...6 or 7 in the case of rubber, the first six&#13;
or seven coefficients reflect the coefficients of price in the harvesting&#13;
equation (24). Moreover, if the lags involved in this equation are not very&#13;
long for prices, so that m is much less than n , where n is the maximum age&#13;
beyond which a rubber tree does not produce, it is apparent that, as in the&#13;
case of the WG formulation, the coefficients reflect the age-yield profile.&#13;
Dowling, as do WG, simplify the model by assuming that the age-yield profile&#13;
does not change over time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
Because of the length of the lag and because the age-yield profile&#13;
for rubber is alleged to be relatively flat after 13 years, Dowling takes&#13;
first differences of (25) to obtain&#13;
(26)     Qt    (+    ) Q t-1  Qt-2 + (y16    + y2 Pt&#13;
+ (Y8    - 60) + (1+)y2- Y3)Pt-l,*-&#13;
8 (y 6 m+- 6   )l  + (l+0)y -+1  Ym  )pt-1&#13;
('l'i  m+2  sm+l)   (     m+l  Ym+2)Pt-m-&#13;
(y16 m+3    m+2   +Ym+2 )pt-m-2&#13;
Y1MS m+4    m+3 )pt-m-3&#13;
+ . .&#13;
+ y18(6 n- 6n  )pt-&#13;
Y1( n    n-i)Pt-n-&#13;
The differences between the 6's    will be small or zero both when the    6's are&#13;
zero (up to 6 or 7 years) and when the age-yield profile is relatively flat&#13;
(from 13 to more than 30 years). Thus if m is small, the coefficients of&#13;
prices lagged less than n years will reflect the distributed lag in the&#13;
harvesting equation (24). After that point, they will be positive, reflecting&#13;
the rising age-yield profile to lag 13. Then the coefficients should be zero&#13;
until very long lags, at which point the age-yield profile declines so that&#13;
the coefficients become negative.&#13;
Dowling estimates equation (26) with a constant term, which implies a&#13;
linear trend, and without imposing the restriction that the coefficients of&#13;
Qt 1 and    Qt-2  sum to one.   He finds that the sign of the coefficient of&#13;
Qt-2 is positive in every case estimated, but that the sum of the coefficients&#13;
of Qt 1 and Qt-2 is close to one in most cases.    This suggests a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
misspecification of the distributed lag formulation in equation (22). Various&#13;
specifications of the Almon lag form are estimated (with and without end-point&#13;
constraints, 3rd-and 4th-order polynomial), and different periods chosen:&#13;
1915-39 and 1950-71 or 1950-1975, or 1950-75 alone. The sum of the lag&#13;
coefficients for prices ranges from a low of 1.117 to a high of 12.527, sug-&#13;
gesting a relatively large long-run response to price, although the estimates&#13;
are highly sensitive to the choice of period and specification of the lag&#13;
distribution. The shape of the lag distribution does approximate what was&#13;
expected, but the timing of the positive and negative portions appears strange&#13;
in the light of what is known about typical age-yield profiles. The low-order&#13;
coefficients are positive but fall off rapidly, becoming negative at lag 3.&#13;
These negative values persist until lag 9 or 10, with a trough around lag 5.&#13;
After lag 9 or 10 the coefficients become positive and increasingly signifi-&#13;
cant; they are assumed to be zero after lag 14 with an end-point constraint to&#13;
zero at lag 15 in some estimation equations.&#13;
That there should be much of any lag in the harvesting equation is&#13;
puzzling since the costs are essentially current labor costs, but if labor is&#13;
quasi-fixed, some lag effects are not implausible. The typical age-yield&#13;
profile for rubber, however, suggests that the coefficients should be positive&#13;
only after the yield profile starts to rise, reaching a peak between six or&#13;
seven years when the trees begin to yield and 13 or 14 years when yields level&#13;
off. Indeed, the age-yield profile we have estimated from the Sri Lankan&#13;
estate data shows yields rising abruptly from six years to a peak at 16 years,&#13;
then a gradual fall to age 37 and a more rapid fall after that. The highest&#13;
point in the differences, 6i+l- 6i , occurs between i = 7 and i = 8, but yield&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
is negligible before i = 6. In our own analyses, we make direct use of the&#13;
age-yield profile in estimation of the equations of the model. Possibly&#13;
significant uprooting and replanting such as that found in Sri Lanka could&#13;
account for some of Dowling's anomalous results. Indeed, the treatment of&#13;
replanting by WG and Dowling is inadequate, a gap we attempt to fill in&#13;
Section 4.&#13;
3. Replication of the Grilli et al. and Dowling Analyses with Sri Lankan&#13;
Data&#13;
The standard Nerlove model given in equations (1) - (3) leads to a&#13;
regression of area under cultivation on current or lagged price, and area&#13;
lagged one year and two years. Replacing area under cultivation by observed&#13;
output, we find for the period 1947-79:&#13;
(27)     Q  = 21904.9 + 0.6205 Qt-1 + 0.2967 Qt-2 - 10167.6 Pt-l'&#13;
(2.01)    (3.84)         (1.78)        (2.20)&#13;
R  = 0.887 ,                            D.W. = 2.053&#13;
Values in parentheses are t-ratios. Prices used were the yearly average&#13;
Columbo auction RSS #1 price deflated by the Columbo CPI. Quantity data used&#13;
were total annual production as reported in the Administrative Report of the&#13;
Rubber Controller, 1947-1979. Note that, in the standard Nerlovian model, the&#13;
coefficient of Qt-2 should be -(l-0)(l-y), that is, negative if the&#13;
coefficients of expectation and adjustment both lie between zero and one.&#13;
Nonetheless, the coefficient is positive and significant at the 10% level&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
(although not at the 5Z level). Thus the hypothesis that one of the two&#13;
dynamic parameters is less than zero is not rejected at the 10% level.&#13;
Moreover, the coefficient of price is negative and significantly different&#13;
from zero at better than the 5% level; the price elasticity of supply implied&#13;
is approximately -0.9. Thus the standard Nerlovian specification adopted in&#13;
simplified form by Grilli et al. is clearly inadequate to describe rubber&#13;
supply in Sri Lanka. 9/&#13;
We have also attempted to replicate Dowling's rubber model using our&#13;
data for Sri Lanka. In the final reduced form estimated, the model involves&#13;
only a distributed lag on deflated prices and lagged values of the dependent&#13;
variable. It differs from the original WG formulation for coffee only in that&#13;
it provides a different justification for the lagged values of the dependent&#13;
variable included and it extends the lag in price over a much longer period to&#13;
account for the differences in the age-yield profiles between rubber and&#13;
coffee. The age-yield profile for rubber based on data for 49 estates in Sri&#13;
Lanka over a 10-year period (presented in the next section) shows virtually no&#13;
yield for the first six years, then a rapid rise to a peak at 15 years and a&#13;
more rapid decline thereafter. Technological progress has not only increased&#13;
yields, but has also moved forward the period at which significant yields are&#13;
achieved. Dowling's procedure is to experiment with lags of various lengths&#13;
(Almon forms with and without end-point restrictions, using 3rd- and 4th-&#13;
order polynomials) and choose the best-fitting result. We have repeated this&#13;
procedure to obtain, for 1943-79, a 4th-degree polynomial Almon lag with no&#13;
end-point restriction, yielding the following equation:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
(28)     Qt =   39810.5           +  0.1655 Qt-l      +  0.3781 Qt-2&#13;
(0.78)             (0.81)             (1.74)&#13;
+  29090 Pt        +   2440 pt_l      -   12740 Pt-2&#13;
(2.99)             (0.70)             (2.21)&#13;
-  19330 Pt-6      -  19830 Pt-4      -   16410 Pt-5&#13;
(2.80)             (3.20)             (3.63)&#13;
-  10900 Pt-6      -   4755 Pt-7      +     901 Pt-8&#13;
(3.60)             (1.58)             (0.23)&#13;
+   5303 pt_9      +   8033 pt_-o      +   9026 Pt-il&#13;
(1.14)             (1.73)             (2.24)&#13;
+   8564 Pt-12     +   7281 Pt-13      +   6160 Pt_14&#13;
(2.72)             (2.73)              (2.24)&#13;
*   6536 Pt-15     +  10090 Pt-16&#13;
(2.32)             (2.60)&#13;
2 = 0.932                                              D.W. = 2.82&#13;
The sum of the lag coefficients on prices is 9470 with a standard error of&#13;
26876. The implied price elasticity of supply at the mean price and quantity&#13;
for 1947-79 is +0.81.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Z-                     V t ~~~~-  t &#13;
-23&#13;
The coefficient of Qt-2 is positive and significantly different from&#13;
zero at about the 10% level.   If we ignore the term in Qt-2 and interpret the&#13;
coefficient of Qt_l as one minus a coefficient of adjustment, the implied&#13;
long-run elasticity of supply is +0.97, which is much higher than any found by&#13;
Grilli et al. However, this interpretation, which is also consistent with the&#13;
high value of the Durbin-Watson statistic obtained, is not consistent with the&#13;
WG interpretation of the coefficients of lagged prices in terms of the age-&#13;
yield profile.&#13;
The coefficients of lagged prices may be compared with the&#13;
interpretation suggested by equation (26).   Ignoring the term on Q t2' the&#13;
coefficient, *, must be in the interval [0,1] to satisfy the assumptions of&#13;
the standard adaptive expectations form; however, according to&#13;
(28), * = -.8345. Also, because yield is effectively zero in the first six&#13;
years, the coefficients on price after the first represent (1+ *) Yi - Yi_l&#13;
should be positive and declining if * is small and a29...' a8 are declining;&#13;
since   = -.8345 from the coefficient of Qt 11 and a2 = 29090 from the&#13;
coefficient on Pt, a3 = 2374 and a4 = 13,133.   In general, these results are&#13;
inconsistent with a relatively short declining lag in prices in the harvest&#13;
equation. Moreover, after lag 6 or 7, the coefficients should be increasingly&#13;
positive, reflecting the sharply rising portion of the age-yield profile until&#13;
16 years. But, the coefficients on lags 6 and 7 are negative which would&#13;
indicate that the lag in the harvesting equation is unusually long; also, the&#13;
coefficients start to decline after lag 11 which is inconsistent with the&#13;
age-yield profile obtained from our sample of 49 estates (see figure 5).&#13;
Consequently, we conclude that equation (26) based on the Dowling formulation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
of WC is not a useful representation of the reduced-form supply function for&#13;
rubber in Sri Lanka.&#13;
In order to see whether the unrestricted first-difference form of the&#13;
WG equation was causing the difficulty, we also fit an equation imposing the&#13;
restriction that the coefficents of Qt 1 and Qt-2 must sum to one:&#13;
(29)     Qt   Qt-l                     41826             +0.4939   [Qt-i - Qt-2'&#13;
(2.22)               (2.51)&#13;
-  15140pt         +   4405 Pt-i        -  1962 Pt-2&#13;
(1.98)            (1.48)               (0.89)&#13;
-   5012 Pt-3      -   5667 Pt-4        -  4726 Pt-5&#13;
(1.8)            (2.06)               (2.08)&#13;
-   2861 Pt-6      -    625 Pt-7        +  1557 Pt-8&#13;
(1.60)            (0.37)               (0.82)&#13;
+   3380 Pt-9      +   4665 pt-lo       +  5356 pt-11&#13;
(1.57)             (2.04)            (2.25)&#13;
( 5521 Pt-12       +   5352 Pt-13       + 5163 Pt-14&#13;
(2.19)             (2.01)             (1.96)&#13;
*(2503) Pt-15      +   6608 Pt-16&#13;
R  = 0.526                             D.W. = 2.52&#13;
A likelihood-ratio test (x = 256.733 - 211.141 = 45.952 with 1 degree of&#13;
freedom) decisively rejects the null hypothesis that the coefficents of Qtl1&#13;
and Qt-2 in the unrestricted case, (28) sum to one. Moreover, the coeffi-&#13;
cients of lagged prices after lag 7 fail to reflect the expected shape of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
age-yield profile under the assumption that the effect of lagged prices in the&#13;
harvest equation is of relatively short duration, as discussed above.&#13;
Because we have statistics on area (recorded in the Administrative&#13;
Report of the Rubber Controller, 1947-79), we can test directly one of the key&#13;
assumptions of the Dowling adaptation of the WG formulation, namely equation&#13;
(22). Our estimate for 1947-79, in undifferenced form, is&#13;
A  = 49475.6  +   1.009  A   -  0.086  A    + 908 Pt&#13;
(30)             (0.63)    (5.48)  tl    (0.42)  t2    (0.35)&#13;
2= 0.80                       D.W. = 2.04&#13;
Dowling does not actually include At-2 in his equation, but we follow WG, who&#13;
do. The coefficient of A t-2 is insignificantly different from zero and the&#13;
coefficient of At 1 is insignificantly different from one. This means that&#13;
(22) holds with B = 0 and 0 = 0, i.e., area follows a random walk for Sri&#13;
Lanka in this straight-forward estimation of the Dowling-WG formulation.&#13;
This result is hardly surprising for Sri Lanka because the total&#13;
acreage series has been virtually constant (see Figure 1). The negligible&#13;
change in total acreage over the period 1947-79 is the result of the&#13;
predominance of replanting rather than new planting. A large replanting&#13;
subsidy was introduced in 1953, and the bulk of planting activity has involved&#13;
uprooting existing older stands and replanting with higher yielding clonal&#13;
varieties. No model that takes changes in acreage as a measure of new&#13;
investment and neglects uprooting for replanting and abandonment can possibly&#13;
serve as an adequate representation of rubber supply response in Sri Lanka.&#13;
In the next section, we formulate and estimate an extension of the WG&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
formulation that emphasizes the replanting decision as a major source of&#13;
rubber supply response in Sri Lanka.&#13;
4. Data Available and a Model of Rubber Supply in Sri Lanka&#13;
The Data&#13;
Figure 1 shows, in addition to total acreage under rubber 1940-79,&#13;
that part in smallholdings, small estates, and large estates. The stability&#13;
of the total masks a significant decline in the area under rubber in large&#13;
estates and an offsetting increase in smallholdings. 10/&#13;
Figure 2 shows total plantings of rubber broken down by new planting&#13;
and replanting. With the advent of the Rubber Replanting Subsidy Scheme in&#13;
1953, rubber plantings have been primarily replantings and, under the scheme,&#13;
all replantings were required to be high yielding clonal varieties. Thus, by&#13;
now almost all rubber stands, except for the very old trees, consist of clonal&#13;
varieties. However, these have consistently improved over time so that, as&#13;
can be seen from Figure 3, total production of rubber in Sri Lanka has&#13;
increased markedly over time--particularly since the early 1960s--despite the&#13;
stability of the total area under rubber. This reflects the higher yield&#13;
associated with replantings in the mid-50s on, which begin yielding after a&#13;
gestation period of six years. Although there was, also, a significant amount&#13;
of new planting of high-yielding varieties throughout the 1950s, most planting&#13;
consists of uprooting existing stands and replanting with clonal varieties,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
FIGURE 1&#13;
ACREAGE UNDER RUBBER, 1940-1979&#13;
50-&#13;
z&#13;
H40&#13;
CD&#13;
tc                   - _LARGE ESTATES&#13;
30-                                           \&#13;
-  -- -&#13;
20-&#13;
SMALL HOLDINGS      .--'a&#13;
, -               -  -  -  ---  -&#133;--     -  -&#13;
-- -    &#133;- - -   -  -  -  -    SMALL ESTATES&#13;
1940   1945   ls8e  1966   l9as   1ee5  1978   t975&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ACREAGE&#13;
t o                                N        N       N        N&#13;
N        Ufl              0        N        01      0J                N        (tl I&#13;
CD     0                C        CD               000 &#13;
.,                    I-         IA                               .......^ 0 * ^ l"-w-J----&#13;
:...... ..         . .............. ................ ........ ..... ,,S-&#13;
.         .  .              ...&#13;
:T     -&#13;
S        &#13;
*                                              .U&#13;
*                                                                     Ill~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
*~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
*                                                                       ~~~~~~~~~~~~z&#13;
CD~~C.&#13;
Ul                                                                                                 46-&#13;
-  De  z                                                                    -~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~c&#13;
cn~~~~~~~l&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TOTAL PRODUCTION OF RUBBER, 1940-1979&#13;
180-&#13;
188-&#13;
co&#13;
140C&#13;
10-&#13;
I 940   1 945   lose    1 955   1eo    1 985   1970   t1975&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
R-046b/WTR/5.06.84                   - 30 -&#13;
especially beginning in 1953 when substantial subsidies for such replanting&#13;
were introduced. Fluctuations over time in the amount of replanting have also&#13;
been great. Thus, no rubber supply model for in Sri Lanka that fails to&#13;
emphasize this aspect of supply behavior can begin to capture the essential&#13;
elements of the supply response. The replications of Grilli et al and Dowling&#13;
using Sri Lankan data, reported in the previous section, simply reflect the&#13;
trends in production and prices revealed in Figures 3 and 4.&#13;
Finally, Figure 5 plots the average yield of rubber latex per acre&#13;
associated with stands of different ages for 49 large rubber estates over the&#13;
10-year period 1970-79.   No allowance is made for difference in clonal&#13;
variety, type of soil, elevation, tapping practice, or other factors. In&#13;
subsequent research, we shall attempt to separate the effect of age on yield&#13;
from aspects of cultivation and harvesting practices. For present purposes,&#13;
however, we shall be content to employ the age-yield profile, which has been&#13;
described in the previous section, to characterize the underlying technology.&#13;
In addition to data on prices, production, area under cultivation&#13;
distributed by age, and replanting, new planting, etc., we have information on&#13;
wages, the general price level, some input prices, and replanting subsidies.&#13;
Our model at this stage is designed primarily to exploit the detailed&#13;
information on planting and the age distribution of the stock of trees. In&#13;
further work, we hope to utilize more fully the detailed agronomic information&#13;
from the Bank's survey of 49 estates and the regional and varietal breakdowns&#13;
of area under cultivation made possible by our sources. (A more detailed&#13;
description of the data, other than the area statistics, is given in Appendix&#13;
B.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
SL.61    0L6 1   S86 1    0861    SS6 1     S6 I    SI'61   OfrO1&#13;
I  I  I S   I I  I  I  1 ' 1  S O S I   I  I  I  I  I  I  I  I  I  I  '  I  I  I  I I I  I  6  I  0I.0I&#13;
-S'0&#13;
X L~~~~~~~~~~~01&#13;
Cl)~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
-4-Z&#13;
_c *&#13;
S0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
RUBBER YIELD PER ACRE&#13;
9 a200-&#13;
1,0000 &#13;
w 8008&#13;
0.u&#13;
H- 400-      &#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
I    5    8    1 3  1 7  2 1  25   29   33   37   4 1  45   49&#13;
AGE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
The Model&#13;
The original WG formulation consists of three equations: (1) A new&#13;
planting or investment equation, more or less based on dynamic optimization of&#13;
the discounted stream of future net revenues; (2) a "potential output"&#13;
equation, which summarizes the technological relation between the stock of&#13;
trees by age and output; and (3) a harvesting equation, which relates&#13;
potential output to realized output. Our model modifies the WG formulation to&#13;
emphasize replanting and also includes a new planting equation. Since we have&#13;
an explicit age-yield relationship, as well as the actual age distribution of&#13;
the tree stock in each year, we can calculate potential output directly rather&#13;
than introduce it as a separate equation of the model with unknown parameters&#13;
6(i,t). 11/ As do WG, we have a harvesting equation. Finally, we have a&#13;
separate equation for new planting, which corresponds to the WG investment&#13;
equation. Unlike WG, our data permit estimation of each equation separately&#13;
rather than a single reduced-form supply equation. Separate estimation and&#13;
the fact that we emphasize replanting decisions rather than treating them&#13;
residually distinguish our analysis from the WG formulation and Dowling's&#13;
application of it to rubber in Thailand.&#13;
We define the following variables:&#13;
At      =  the total area under rubber cultivation in year t;&#13;
Rt      =  the area replanted in year t (assumed to equal the area&#13;
uprooted); 12/&#13;
pe      =  "expected normal" price of rubber (deflated) in year t;&#13;
Pt&#13;
Pt      =  current rubber price (deflated) in year t;&#13;
St      =  current subsidy per acre replanted (deflated) in year t;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
wt      =  wage rates for tapping and maintenance labor (deflated) in&#13;
year t;&#13;
Xt      =  other relevant variables to be specified later;&#13;
Ft (a)  =  the current empirical cumulative age distribution of area&#13;
under cultivation in year t, i.e., the proportion of total&#13;
cultivated area in year t less than or equal to a years of&#13;
age;&#13;
*      -I&#13;
a       =  "truncation point" of the age distribution in year t, such&#13;
t&#13;
that the areas greater than age a are eligible for&#13;
replanting.&#13;
In deciding whether or not to uproot and replant a stand of rubber&#13;
trees of a given age, rubber growers must compare the current net revenue&#13;
(price times yield minus costs) and discounted future expected net revenues&#13;
per acre from the existing stand with that which may be expected from the&#13;
proposed replacement over some planning horizon (see Perrin (1972)). 13/ The&#13;
net revenues from continuing cultivation of the present stand depend on its&#13;
age and the age-yield profile for the particular variety (or mix of varieties)&#13;
of which it is composed. The revenues from the proposed replacement depend on&#13;
the expected age-yield profile for the variety to be replanted and the costs&#13;
of the uprooting-replanting operation. Both depend on current rubber prices&#13;
and a sequence of expected future prices, which extend into the distant future&#13;
because of the long period over which a rubber tree is expected to yield.&#13;
Given the decline in yield which occurs after age 15 years (although not&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
FIGURE 6&#13;
Empirical Age Distribution&#13;
Proportion ,&#13;
of Trees&#13;
F;(a)&#13;
~~~~~~~~~~~~~Fraction Uprooted for&#13;
/                           s i ~~~~~~~~~~~Replanting Year t&#13;
a-                            a. age&#13;
Word Bank-26131&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
uniformly for all varieties) and the steady improvement of the expected yields&#13;
of new clonal varieties, it will obviously pay at some point in the life-cycle&#13;
of a stand to take it out and replant with the then currently available clonal&#13;
variety. If all stands were internally uniform with respect to age and&#13;
variety and all growers faced equal price opportunities and cost constraints&#13;
and had similar expectations, only older trees would be removed. Thus we can&#13;
imagine, as in Figure 6, that only the tail of the age distribution is removed&#13;
in any year, but the point at which the truncation occurs, at , depends on a&#13;
number of other factors, as indicated above.14/&#13;
Because replanting occurs for other reasons, such as storm damage and&#13;
disease, and because expectations, opportunities, and constraints are not&#13;
exactly identical for each grower, we would not expect replanting to be&#13;
*&#13;
exactly proportional to 1 - F t(at).   Assume that the former is linearly&#13;
related to the latter with a stochastic error term:&#13;
(31)     Rt =a   + a1At [1-Ft(at)] + ut&#13;
The term a0 + Ut, for example, may be supposed to represent storm and disease&#13;
damaged replacements; a1 , not necessarily equal to one, represents any&#13;
systematic bias involved in not replacing all trees of age greater than at&#13;
Of course, all of these departures from the strict replacement model will show&#13;
up in the next period's empirical age distribution, Ft(a) , but since we have&#13;
data on this distribution we do not need to model the connection between&#13;
Ft+ (a)  and F t(a) explicitly.15/&#13;
In what follows we assume that growers expect all future prices to be&#13;
the same ("expected normal" price) but not necessarily equal to the current&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
price; that the current price is an adequate proxy not only for what growers&#13;
currently receive but also for their expectations of near-term prices up to&#13;
roughly the time at which a newly replanted stand can begin to yield signifi-&#13;
cantly; 16/ and that the current wage rate is an adequate proxy for all&#13;
current and expected future costs, and in particular, for the high labor costs&#13;
involved in the uprooting-replanting operation. It is clear that growers will&#13;
compare current prices and near-term expectations, Pt I with longer-term&#13;
expectations of prices, Pte , in order to decide whether to uproot and replant&#13;
a given stand: the higher the current prices and near-term expectations rela-&#13;
tive to expected normal price levels, the less replanting will occur; the&#13;
higher the level of expected normal prices, the more it will pay to replant&#13;
now. These expectations must be compared with what it will cost for the&#13;
operation (including the subsidies given to induce growers to switch to&#13;
higher-yielding varieties.) Thus,&#13;
(32)     a    f(p    Pt, P   wt, ste  x&#13;
where xt may have a stochastic component. Substituting (32) in (31) we obtain&#13;
a highly nonlinear replanting equation that depends not only on the parameters&#13;
of f, a., and al but also on the empirical age distribution Ft(a) at any time:&#13;
(  )   ~t   O    1  t[    t( (t   Pt   t   t, St    t  ]    t&#13;
e&#13;
It remains to specify pt . We adopt the simple adaptive expectations&#13;
model for the determination of "expected normal prices," or long-term price&#13;
expectations:&#13;
(34)     Pe - P e              e[p  e&#13;
t  t-  =    t-   - P  _&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
We could equally well use an alternative fancier formulation, e.g., quasi--&#13;
rational expectations (see Nerlove et al., 1979), but adaptive expectations&#13;
appear to work well in a variety of contexts and have the advantage of being&#13;
consistent with the optimizing model implicitly assumed.&#13;
2&#13;
Assuming ut to be NID(0, a ), specifying f parametrically and&#13;
neglecting any stochastic component in xt , given data on prices, wages,&#13;
subsidies, replantings, total area under cultivation, and the empirical age&#13;
distribution, we could, in principle, form a likelihood function that could be&#13;
maximized numerically. In fact, this is not hard to do. However, it is com-&#13;
putationally expensive. For our preliminary analysis, therefore, we adopted a&#13;
further approximation: Instead of incorporating all of the empirical age&#13;
distributions at each stage of the estimation procedure, we chose various&#13;
measures, such as the area planted to trees over 40 years of age, between 36&#13;
and 40, and between 31 and 35.&#13;
Let ACEt = a general variable reflecting such a measure or measures&#13;
of the tail of At [1-Ft)(a)] . Our preliminary replanting equation is then not&#13;
(33) but,&#13;
(35)     R  = aO+ arlp - pe] + a pe + a   w   + a s  + a AGE + a x + u&#13;
t  0   11 t   t~ ~2 t      3w       4 t    5   t   6 t    t&#13;
Equation (34) may be used to generate a series on pet given past prices and any&#13;
value of 8 in the interval [0,1). Maximum-likelihood estimates of the&#13;
parameters of (31) can be obtained by searching for B's in this interval in&#13;
order to find that value giving the highest R    for (35), provided we&#13;
assume  u - NID (0,a ).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
One problem with both the simple and the more complex estimation&#13;
procedures is that Ft or AGEt is not really exogenous and independent&#13;
Of ut or ut, but given independence of the u's over time these variables will&#13;
be predetermined.&#13;
To "close" the model we must determine production and new plantings.&#13;
Technology in this model is given simply by the age-yield profile.&#13;
We ignore weather, labor inputs, fertilizer use, and, except indirectly by&#13;
introduction of a time trend, the effects of varietal improvements over&#13;
time. Since we have an empirical age-yield profile and actual estimates of&#13;
the age distribution in each year, let y(a) = the yield per acre of rubber&#13;
trees of age a. 17/ Then the "potential" output, Qt' in year t is given by&#13;
(36)     Q    E  y(a) Ft(a) At . 18/&#13;
Actual production may differ from Qt because of weather conditions,&#13;
harvesting costs in relation to current prices, prior use of other inputs such&#13;
as fertilizer, and "slaughter" tapping in anticipation of uprooting and&#13;
replanting of older stands. In WG and Dowling, a short lag on current prices&#13;
is included in this equation; however, we have not included a lag for reasons&#13;
discussed earlier (see footnote 8 and p. 19). Thus our harvesting equation is&#13;
I *e&#13;
t = o        Qt         +    t + B4wt + B5t + vt&#13;
We expect to find 8i close to one, B2 positive, 83 small and negative,&#13;
84 negative, and 85 positive.&#13;
New planting is the most difficult to model for Sri Lanka since there&#13;
was virtually none during the period we studied. We do not expect good&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
results in this case since there is significant variation in the little new&#13;
planting that occurred only for a brief period in the 1950s. In general we&#13;
would expect new planting to depend on much the same variables as replanting&#13;
except that the entire age distribution of the stock, not just the tail&#13;
matters. Moreover since rubber output is not foregone (only the output of&#13;
other crops displaced), current prices are not likely to matter much for new&#13;
planting; longer-term expectations of prices relative to current costs of&#13;
planting and alternative crops may play some role. 19/   Let Nt = acres newly&#13;
planted to rubber in year t. We represent the effect of the existing stock&#13;
by Qt , which weights stands of different ages by their average yields. Our&#13;
equation is&#13;
(38)     Nt = y  + Y1 Q   + y pe + y3w  + Y4x    et.&#13;
5. Empirical Results&#13;
Replanting&#13;
We ran a number of regressions along the lines of equation (35) as&#13;
specified in the preceding section. In initial results, the real wage was&#13;
always found to be insignificant and was dropped from further analyses.&#13;
Indeed, on large estates, which account for the bulk of the area under rubber&#13;
as well as production, labor is a fixed factor in the short run. Since the&#13;
decision to replant involves short-run costs compared with long-run returns,&#13;
it is not surprising that the price of a fixed factor is not significant.&#13;
Our major problem in formulating an adequate replanting equation was&#13;
incorporating the effect of the age distribution. As indicated above (foot-&#13;
note 10), there is a substantial discrepancy between the official area&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
statistics, those figures available from recent censuses, and the figures&#13;
presented in various reports of the rubber controller. These discrepancies&#13;
are probably due for the most part to smallholder abandonments at higher&#13;
elevations and to removals of older vintages of low-yielding seedling&#13;
varieties. As such, the discrepancy between the official acreage series and&#13;
various alternatives based on census or other data may be expected to most&#13;
affect e stimates of the very oldest groups. Instead of working with the more&#13;
complex formulation of (33) involving the empirical age distribution in every&#13;
year, we broke the tail down into three groups:&#13;
AGE40+   = acreage planted with trees older than 40 years;&#13;
AGE36-40 = acreage planted with trees between 36 and 40 years old;&#13;
AGE31-35 = acreage planted with trees between 31 and 35 years old.&#13;
The discrepancy may be expected to affect the results of including AGE40+ more&#13;
than the other age-distribution variables. Indeed the results with this vari-&#13;
able proved to be uniformly bad, but our attempts to distribute the&#13;
discrepancy, as described in Appendix A, did not lead to results that differ&#13;
in any significant respect from those using the official data. Either the&#13;
results are not sensitive to the discrepancy or the method we adopted for&#13;
distributing it was defective.&#13;
Our initial regressions, employing the revised and offical data,&#13;
indicated that both AGE36-40 and AGE31-35 were positively and significantly&#13;
related to replanting but that AGE40+ was not significantly related. This&#13;
finding is no doubt due in part to the fact that much of the over 40 acreage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
is in smallholdings; smallholders face different constraints and opportunities&#13;
than do the managers of large and medium sized estates.&#13;
As indicated, we iterated on the coefficient of expectations, 8, in&#13;
calculating pe until we found the best-fitting regression. The reported t-&#13;
statistics are conditional on the value formed by this procedure.20/ The&#13;
expected price series was calculated recursively beginning with the last&#13;
period. We tried several specifications of equation (35) also including the&#13;
price of low grown tea (an alternative crop). The results for 1944-78 of our&#13;
best equation, using the revised area statistics are,&#13;
e              e&#13;
(39)  R = - 20469   - 13.72   (p   - p   ) + 202.1  p    + 0.831 s&#13;
t    (11.19)    (1.11)   t-1   t-1    (7.47)  t-1   (6.90   t-1&#13;
+ 0.03173 AGE31-35 + 0.0542 AGE36-40&#13;
(3.20)              (6.54)&#13;
-2&#13;
R   = 0.930                 D.W. = 1.37&#13;
8 = 0.15&#13;
The short-run price elasticity is insignificant although negative as&#13;
anticipated; the elasticity at the mean values of Rt, Pt, and P    is only&#13;
-0.005.  On the other hand, the long-run elasticity with respect to    Pt is&#13;
highly significant and positive as expected; at the mean values it is +1.74.&#13;
Presumably the value of the subsidy is responsible for short-run responses,&#13;
and this is highly significant; the elasticity of Rt with respect to St_, at&#13;
the mean is 0.52. As expected, the age distribution variables show a larger&#13;
effect on replanting for the older vintages. The coefficient of expectation&#13;
was found to be only 0.15, suggesting that expected normal prices adjust only&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
very slowly to fluctuations in current prices. The Durbin-Watson statistic&#13;
(D.W.) is rather low, but correction for first-order serial correlation did&#13;
not change the results significantly. 21/&#13;
Production&#13;
The result of running the regression suggested by equation (37),&#13;
excluding Pt , for 1944-78, yielded&#13;
*&#13;
Qt= -8617400 + 0.3295 Qt + 144925E+4 Pt   -13982200 wt + 139822E+3 t&#13;
(40)            (0.24)    (4.38)      (0.97)           (1.90)       (7.82)&#13;
- 2&#13;
R   = 0.85                                            D.W. = 1.06&#13;
*&#13;
The coefficient of  Qt is significantly different from 1, having a standard&#13;
error of 0.0752. The probable reason for this low coefficient is the use of&#13;
an age-yield profile for 1970-79. Yields in this period for all ages must be&#13;
significantly larger than for earlier periods. This is true for several&#13;
reasons: there have been technological improvements in the clones themselves;&#13;
there have been important technological changes in the quality of disembodied&#13;
inputs; and there has been a continual improvement in the skill of farmers.&#13;
The result is to weight acreage figures more heavily than should be the case&#13;
for determination of potential production (see footnote 17). The price effect&#13;
is not significantly different from zero, but the coefficient has the expected&#13;
positive sign. The wage rate is significantly negative as expected. The most&#13;
significant variable is a time trend.   If Pe were included, it is likely it&#13;
would only pick up some of this strong trend, emerging with a positive rather&#13;
than a small negative coefficient. There is also substantial first-order&#13;
residual correlation. _L/&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
While (40) is far from a satisfactory result, the regression does&#13;
illustrate the danger of trying to infer production from the age distribution&#13;
of trees and the area under cultivation without considerable further disaggre-&#13;
gation and taking into account the effects of other variables. The strong and&#13;
stable technological link betwen the age distribution and production assumed&#13;
in the WG formulation is clearly not supported by the data for Sri Lanka.&#13;
New Planting&#13;
As indicated above, we did not expect to obtain good results for this&#13;
part of our model; we were not disappointed. Equation (38) suggests&#13;
regressing Nt on Q    pe and wt.   The result for 1944-78, also including a time&#13;
trend, is&#13;
e&#13;
N  =  2618- 0.314E-5 Q    - 12727 p   + 219.8 w  - 50.71 t&#13;
t                      t           t          t&#13;
(41)           (2.12)  (1.22)         (0.09)     (0.19)      (0.47)&#13;
-2&#13;
R   = 0.05                                              D.W. = 1.20&#13;
Only the constant term is significant.    Prices and wages both have the wrong&#13;
sign.  It is clear that new planting in Sri Lanka, which is a highly insig-&#13;
nificant component of total planting in any case, is not explicable in terms&#13;
of the variables used or the model formulated. The focus on new planting in&#13;
the WG formulation is clearly inappropriate in Sri Lanka.&#13;
Conclusion&#13;
Models of perennial supply response that focus on new investment, as&#13;
does the WG formulation, are not appropriate to the study of a mature indus-&#13;
try, such as rubber in Sri Lanka, in which most response to prices and other&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
factors takes the form of uprooting and replanting existing stands. Our&#13;
replanting results show significant and positive long-run response of replant-&#13;
ing to variations in expected normal prices (elasticity = 1.7); and a small,&#13;
negative and insignificant response to current prices; and a significant,&#13;
positive response to subsidies designed to promote replacement of older stands&#13;
with higher-yielding varieties. The effects of variations in the number of&#13;
acres planted to older vintages found encourage us to believe the more&#13;
elaborate formulation, from which our regression was derived, may be worth&#13;
estimating, but the perverse effects found for the "over-40" category are&#13;
disturbing. As we suggested above, this effect may well be due to our esti-&#13;
mates of area in this category and to the concentration of this acreage in&#13;
smallholdings.&#13;
One of the most significant aspects of rubber supply in Sri Lanka is&#13;
the steady varietal improvement resulting in higher-yielding trees and a&#13;
different age-yield profile over time. 23/ This technological improvement&#13;
provides the impetus for the replanting of older trees, which in turn accounts&#13;
for most supply response to price in the long run. These changes also make it&#13;
difficult to infer production from the distribution of trees of different&#13;
ages. Our harvesting equation, while revealing a strong and significant posi-&#13;
tive association between potential output in the WG formulation and observed&#13;
output, also yields a coefficient much less than one. Since new planting is&#13;
essentially negligible, it is clear that a more complete understanding of&#13;
supply response based on the uprooting-replanting decision and on the age&#13;
distribution of the stock of trees at any point in time requires a fuller&#13;
treatment of the relation between stock and production. The WC formulation,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
while useful and appropriate to the derivation of a reduced-form supply&#13;
function, is clearly greatly oversimplified in the present context. Use of&#13;
the detailed estate data to develop a dynamic production function for rubber&#13;
should be the next step in our research on this topic.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
Appendix A&#13;
Area under Cultivation and Its Components*&#13;
This appendix is drawn, in part, from a memorandum dated October 24, 1982,&#13;
from M. J. Hartley to J. Duloy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
An initial attraction of a pilot study on rubber in Sri Lanka was the&#13;
availability of data on area under cultivation, which contained, in particu-&#13;
lar, a time-series of age-distributions--a matter of considerable importance&#13;
to the study of perennials. Subsequent examination of these data, as well as&#13;
the report of the Rubber Master Plan for Sri Lanka, conducted in 1979 by the&#13;
Commonwealth Development Corporation (CDC), revealed certain difficulties with&#13;
these data, which are described in this appendix.&#13;
As part of the International Rubber Restriction Agreement of 1934,&#13;
and in order to assess potential production for its administration reliably,&#13;
Ceylon (now Sri Lanka) was required to estimate the total area under cultiva-&#13;
tion and associated yield in a manner that would permit control of total&#13;
output. Since yields varied with age and type of producer, a massive data&#13;
collection exercise was conducted to obtain reliable estimates of total area,&#13;
broken down (marginally) by size of holding [small holders (&lt; 10 acres), small&#13;
estates (10-100 acres), and large estates (&gt; 100 acres)] and by age of exist-&#13;
ing stock (by years of planting back to 1922, with a censored "lump" in the&#13;
distribution for all ages greater than 12 years). In addition, combined two-&#13;
way breakdowns, by both district and size of holding, were estimated.&#13;
Finally, estimates of the average yield associated with each size class were&#13;
calculated, based upon the last three years of actual yield (1929, 1930, and&#13;
1931)o This provided an estimate of total "assessed standard production," as&#13;
well as a means of allocating export coupons to all existing registered&#13;
producers.&#13;
The Agreement established a national quota as a given fraction of&#13;
assessed standard production. Export coupons were then distributed to all&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
registered producers, with export entitlements determined by the area under&#13;
cultivation multiplied by the "standard-yield" of the size-class category of&#13;
the particular producer. Such coupons could be freely traded, and the average&#13;
monthly market price of coupons (per lb.) has been collected from the&#13;
inception of the coupon-rationing scheme in June 1934 until its suspension in&#13;
May 1942. The fact that export coupons required registration provided an&#13;
overriding incentive to comply with the spirit of the law. Attempts were&#13;
made, at the time, to monitor and spot-check declared registered areas and&#13;
reported yields, given the economic incentive to over report. Penalties were&#13;
severe for gross misreporting and noncompliance. In short, the "base-line"&#13;
(1934) area and age-distribution data are likely to be as reliable as can be&#13;
expected.&#13;
From 1934 on, the International Agreement also provided for a total&#13;
ban on all new planting and for replanting of existing areas only upon receipt&#13;
of an "application to replant," which was subsequently approved by the Rubber&#13;
Controller. (Indeed, the control of all new planting and replanting, through&#13;
government permits, still exists even though the restriction scheme has&#13;
expired.) Violations were prosecuted, the penalty being the uprooting of all&#13;
discovered unapproved planting. In short, the entire sequence of annual data&#13;
on areas subject to new planting and replanting since 1934 is extremely&#13;
reliable and represents the basis for the official estimates of subsequent&#13;
areas under cultivation and its associated breakdowns by age, size of holding&#13;
and revenue district. Finally, we note that no significant rubber areas were&#13;
planted with high-yielding clonal material prior to 1934, whereas all approved&#13;
new planting and replanting since 1934 has been, by law, restricted to high-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
yielding varieties. (The sequence of new planting and replanting since 1934&#13;
provides a basis to estimate the age-distribution of high-yielding varieties&#13;
and the original unselected seedling stock, separately, although we make no&#13;
use of this possibility.)&#13;
The official statistics in the sequence of Annual Reports of the&#13;
Rubber Controller (ARRC) since 1934 provide annual estimates of the so-called&#13;
"registered areas" separately for replanting and new planting, each broken&#13;
down by a joint three-way classification into revenue district, size-class,&#13;
and type of planting material (unselected seedling versus budded high-yielding&#13;
varieties). Hence, from these data, the sequence of gross additions to the&#13;
total area (new planting) can be added to the previous year's area in each&#13;
category. Replanting represents a change in area composition by age without&#13;
changing total area. The official statistics assume that the areas uprooted&#13;
for replanting always come from the seedling (older, low-yielding) varieties&#13;
and are removed in order of age priority, with the oldest stock removed&#13;
first. While this assumption may not correspond to reality, in the absence of&#13;
records indicating which specific vintages were removed, it is a plausible&#13;
approximation.24/ The major problem with the post-1934 area data, however, is&#13;
that no systematic records of gross removals from the existing stock in each&#13;
year were maintained. Such removals would be through abandonment of existing&#13;
rubber stands or diversification to alternative crops. Thus, to the extent&#13;
that any unreported removals of areas formerly under rubber cultivation&#13;
occurred, the official registered area series will be biased upward. Further,&#13;
since this effect is cumulative, the magnitude of the upward bias increases&#13;
over time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
The severity of this problem first becomes apparent in 1946, when an&#13;
independent Census of Agriculture (see column (5) of Table 1) indicated that,&#13;
exclusive of holdings of less than 1 acre in size, Ceylon had 574,522 acres of&#13;
rubber under cultivation, compared with an official registered area (column&#13;
(4)) of 659,533 acres. It may be possible that the difference of 85,031 acres&#13;
could be attributed to the missing smallholdings (&lt; 1 acre) in the 1946&#13;
Census, since the size distribution of the 146,077 acres of total small hold-&#13;
ings (&lt; 10 acres) was not known precisely, and the average small holding in&#13;
that year was officially estimated at 1.46 acres (ARRC, 1946). A second&#13;
independent estimate was obtained for 1951, with the publication of the Census&#13;
of Agriculture of 1952. It estimated a total of 337,374 acres under cultiva-&#13;
tion in Ceylon (column (6) of Table l)--a figure that excludes holdings of&#13;
less than 20 acres. The registered area in that year (column (7)) indicated a&#13;
total of 655,501 acres under cultivation, of which 343,244 were on large&#13;
estates (&gt; 100 acres) and 140,715 were on small estates (10-100 acres),&#13;
accounting for 483,959 acres. The excess in officially registered area of&#13;
146,585 acres in 1946 could represent the total area in holdings between 10&#13;
and 20 acres that were missing from the 1952 Census taxonomy, since the&#13;
average official holding in the 10-100 acre category was reportedly only 25.34&#13;
acres (ARRC, 1951). A third reference point was based upon the 1962&#13;
Agricultural Census (column (9)) as reported in the ARRC. (We have been unable&#13;
to locate the 1962 Agricultural Census.) The Rubber Master Plan (RMP) reports&#13;
a total of 566,639 acres in 1962, however, whereas the official registered&#13;
area (column (10)) is 674,274 acres. This difference of 107,635 acres is the&#13;
first estimate available that was not obscured by differences in the reported&#13;
taxonomy or missing holdings in particular size groups. A final comparison is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
Table I    S ESTIMATES OP ACREACE UNDER RU!8ER CULTIVATION (SELECTED 8E7ICHlARK YEARS);&#13;
(1)       (2)        (3)       (4)        (5)       (6)       (7)        (3)       (9)       (10)      (11)       (12)      (13)&#13;
Raven. Otstrlct:       1921      1921       1934      1946       1946      1951      1951       1951      1962       1962      1979       1979      1979&#13;
Coloebo               27.898    36,917     52,201    55,890     51,158    23,212    61,760     32,510    62,675    66,260     66,919    63.570     77.558&#13;
Lalucare              82,170    95,113    114,562   120.532    108,176    62,747    123,969    84,162   125.999    128.123   126,103    125,227   106,728&#13;
Kandy                 33,636    40,790     68,680    *8,371     35.777    18,204    69,614     35,480    17,073     65,886    *2,342     16,207     8,398&#13;
Mtacle                28,477     31,068    35.876     35,690    32,098    20,178     35.256    30,018    20,632     34,952    29,982     19,836     6,916&#13;
H o.re ElLy7             637        640       665       665        663       120        664       619        183       304       6S6        183      -&#13;
Calls                 36,603     68,126    63,933    71,539     58,962    34,237     72,158    51,265    57.868     75,636    73,193     55.527    38,779&#13;
Katars                11,493     16.773    22.347    26,822     23,743    11,673     26,937    21,072    23,.47     29,097    28,115     22,470    18,172&#13;
Mabantot.               -            60       260       260        217       125        248       175       218        242       228        224      -&#13;
Triocos1e                 80so     -                   -          -         -          -         -         -          -         -          -         -&#13;
turoosgala            13,793     16,559    17,849     18,260    17,486    12,838     12.195    16,621     15,494    18,675    17,501     14,883    16,573&#13;
Chtla                     33         51        60        60         18         7         69        32        130        77        77        128      -&#13;
8edulla               16,647     16,707    21,286    21,302     20,576    16,548     20.712    20,439     8,569     19,916    19,449     15,970      -&#13;
Recnspura             52,978     58,605    92,080    97,274     93,274    57,082     98,984    79,841    96,235    104,660   102,758     96,747    94.107&#13;
Ragalia               87,570    104,054   13,218    138,586   132.576    82,403    146,645   111.715    129.143   150,626   146,217    128,967   151,658&#13;
oefrg-la                -          -         -         -          -         -          -         -         7,972      -         -          -         -&#13;
Cayleo  Total:       390,115    661,441   606.111   659,553    576,522   337,374    655,501   483,959   s66,639    676,274   651,540    559,939   55.489&#13;
DEFINITIOHS AND 5S0URcQS&#13;
(I)   Total Arse, Cenage of Production, 1921                                        (8)   Total Area of Holdings abone 10 acres. Rubber Control Oept.&#13;
(2)   Total Area, Rubber Control Dept. tItimates In 1934 for "Prior                         1951&#13;
to 1922"                                                                    (9)   Tote1 Area of HoldInge   bo.s 20 acre., Censue of A4ric.lturs.&#13;
(3)   Total Area, Rubbor Control Dept., 1934                                                1942&#13;
(6)   Total Area. Rubber Control Dept., 1946                                        (10)   Total Ragletered Area, Rubber Control Dept, 1962&#13;
(5)   Total Area ot Holdings above I acre, Cans.    of Agrliclture,                 (LI)   Total Regiatered Area, Rubber Control De Pt    1979&#13;
1946                                                                       (12)    Total Actual Area, Rubber Control Depc., 1979&#13;
(6)   Total Area of Roldlngs abo.e 20 acree. Cans.. of Agriculture,                 (13)   Total Area, Rubber Naster Plan, 1979&#13;
1952&#13;
(7)   Total Area, Rubber Cootrol Dept., 1951&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
afforded by a detailed aerial photography survey, followed up by a stratified&#13;
random sampling of particular areas identified as being under rubber to&#13;
confirm the photographic evidence. This was conducted by the RMP in 1979&#13;
(column (13)), where a total of only 515,489 acres is estimatd as under&#13;
rubber. This compares with the official registered figure (column (11)) of&#13;
651,540 acres for 1979, or a difference of 136,051 acres.&#13;
In addition, since 1962 and as a result of the unequivocal evidence&#13;
provided by the Agricultural Census of that year, the Rubber Control&#13;
Department provides "revised" estimates of area under cultivation (broken down&#13;
by both district and size of holding since 1968), which it terms "actual areas&#13;
under rubber." The revised RCD estimate for actual total area in 1962 was&#13;
567,320 acres, 106,954 acres less than the estimate provided by registered&#13;
areas and almost identical to the Census estimate (a difference of only 681&#13;
acres). However, the official estimate for 1979 (column (12)) is 559,939&#13;
acres, which still differs from the RMP figure by 44,450 acres. The RMP&#13;
estimate for 1979 appears to be the best estimate.&#13;
In sum, between 1934 and 1979 roughly 136,000 acres disappeared from&#13;
the officially registered area rolls through unreported abandonment and/or&#13;
diversification to alternative crops. Of this difference, the Rubber Control&#13;
Department officially acknowledges 91,601 acres, or about two-thirds of the&#13;
discrepancy. If one believes the sequence of Census and RMP estimates, one&#13;
can determine the range of years over which the various removals must have&#13;
occured and then allocate these to the individual years, making use of such&#13;
knowledge as the price of rubber (e.g., rubber trees are more likely to be&#13;
removed during periods of low prices), the institutions and legislation in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54 -&#13;
effect (e.g., if a severe quota restrictions of 60% of assessed standard&#13;
production is in effect (as in 1936), removal is more likely), etc. Further,&#13;
various discussions with knowledgeable sources in Sri Lanka suggest that the&#13;
discrepancies are mostly due to small-holder abandonments in the higher&#13;
elevation regions, where yields are lower. 25/ Finally, removals are more&#13;
likely among older vintages of low-yielding seedling varieties. In short,&#13;
plausible assumptions can be advanced to allocate the discrepancy between the&#13;
registered and true areas under cultivation across years, vintages, types of&#13;
planting material, revenue districts, and size of holdings to obtain revised&#13;
estimates at the same level of disaggregation as the official registration&#13;
data.&#13;
In our statistical analyses (reported in the text), we make use of&#13;
both the official area statistics and a revised series in which the&#13;
discrepancy has been allocated across vintages only in accordance with the&#13;
rules discussed below. The sensitivity of our parameter estimates to use of&#13;
these two alternative series is slight.&#13;
Details of Age and Vintage Corrections&#13;
In constructing the revised acreage and vintage data, we have used&#13;
only two benchmarks - the Agricultural Census of 1962 and the Rubber Master&#13;
Plan Inventory Survey, 1977/78 (the 1977/78 figure was used as the total&#13;
acreage figure for 1977). The other available benchmarks were not used,&#13;
because all rubber acreage was not included; the Agricultural Censuses of 1946&#13;
and 1951 were only for holdings above 1 acre and above 20 acres, respec-&#13;
tively. As shown in Appendix Table 2, the 1962 Census of Agriculture records&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
Appendix Table 2: REVISED ACREAGE ESTIMATES (1934-78)&#13;
Official                                                  Revised&#13;
registered          Benchmark            Acreage           acreage&#13;
acreage           estimates          corrections        estimate&#13;
1934        605,132                      -                -            605,132&#13;
1935        605,893                                       - -          605,893&#13;
1936        587,889                      -                -            587,889&#13;
1937        589,382                      -                -            589,382&#13;
1938        594,724                      -                -            594,724&#13;
1939        610,225                      -                -            610,225&#13;
1940        638,274                      -                -            638,274&#13;
1941        637,632                      -                -            637,632&#13;
1942        637,560                      -                -            637,560&#13;
1943        657,289                      -                -            657,289&#13;
1944        657,532                      -                -            657,532&#13;
1945        659,803                      -                -            659,803&#13;
1946        659,553                      -          -11,960            647,593&#13;
1947        658,983                      -          -11,960            635,063&#13;
1948        658,349                      -          -11,960            622,469&#13;
1949        655,108                      -          -11,960            607,268&#13;
1950        655,225                      -                -            607,385&#13;
1951        655,501                      -                -            607,661&#13;
1952        656,879                      -          -11,960            597,071&#13;
1953        657,427                      -          -11,960            585,659&#13;
1954        659,209                      -          -11,960            575,481&#13;
1955        660,985                      -          -11,960            565,297&#13;
1956        659,247                      -          -11,960            551,599&#13;
1957        660,725                      -                -            553,077&#13;
1958        664,836                      -                -            557,188&#13;
1959        668,178                      -                -            560,530&#13;
1960        668,948                                       -            561,300&#13;
1961        670,830                      -                -            563,182&#13;
1962        674,274                566,639 /a             -            566,639&#13;
1963        675,683                      -           -1,564            566,484&#13;
1964        669,179                      -           -1,562            558,416&#13;
1965        671,487                      -           -1,564            559,160&#13;
1966        672,592                      -           -1,564            558,701&#13;
1967        673,378                      -           -1,564            557,923&#13;
1968        674,539                      -           -1,564            557,520&#13;
1969        673,515                      -           -1,564            554,932&#13;
1970        674,365                      -           -1,564            554 218&#13;
1971        673,819                      -           -1,564            552,108&#13;
1972        675,763                      -           -1,564            552,488&#13;
1973        655,920                      -           -1,564            531,081&#13;
1974        653,401                      -           -1,564            526,998&#13;
1975        652,802                      -           -1,564            524,835&#13;
1976        652,179                      -           -1,567            522,648&#13;
1977        651,157                520,059 /b             -            520,059&#13;
1978        650,849                      -                -            519,751&#13;
/a Census of Agriculture, 1962, Volume II: Land Utilization.&#13;
Th Rubber Master Plan, 1977/78 Inventory Survey.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
566,639 acres of rubber; therefore 107,635 acres of registered rubber had been&#13;
either abandoned or diversified into other crops by 1962. In discussions with&#13;
officials of the Rubber Control Department, we learned that, in the early&#13;
years of rubber planting, a large amount of seedling rubber had been planted&#13;
on higher elevations, as a substitute for coffee which was destroyed by a&#13;
blight in the late 1800s. However, rubber is a low elevation crop which does&#13;
not grow well on higher elevations. As the planters became more familiar with&#13;
it, planting on these higher elevations ceased. However, since Ceylon was the&#13;
primary rubber producer for the allies during World War II (Malaysia,&#13;
Indonesia, and Thailand were occupied by the Japanese), it was illegal to&#13;
remove rubber during this period. Also, it is unlikely that any rubber&#13;
acreage was abandoned because of the high prices resulting from its scarcity&#13;
(see Figure 3). Therefore, the majority of these acres must have been removed&#13;
in the postwar period. We decided to allocate the acreage abandoned and the&#13;
acreage diversified into other crops to the 1946-56 period. With the&#13;
exception of 1950-51, this was also a period of relatively low prices. As&#13;
shown in Table 2, we removed this acreage evenly in the years 1946-49 and&#13;
1952-56 (11,960 acres per annum). These corrections to the official rubber&#13;
statistics yielded 566,639 acres.&#13;
Our second acreage benchmark, the Rubber Master Plan's aerial and&#13;
inventory surveys, identified 520,059 acres in 1977. Since this is a period&#13;
of steadily rising prices, we did not identify any specific years in which&#13;
removals or abandonments were more likely. Therefore, we revised the acreage&#13;
series evenly throughout the period removing 1,564 acres per year. The&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
resulting acreage series, as shown in Table 2, is our revised area estimates&#13;
for the period 1934-78.&#13;
For the construction of the vintage series, we used the official&#13;
statistics published in the ARRC, (see Appendix Table 1, "Rubber Acreage in&#13;
Sri Lanka According to the Year of Planting"). However, two problems arose:&#13;
(a) allocation of the "acreage planted prior to 1922", the so-called&#13;
"lump" (see Appendix Table 1); and&#13;
(b) how to reflect our revisions of the official acreage series, as&#13;
outlined above.&#13;
For the allocation of (a) above, we used estimates of rubber acreage&#13;
provided by Snodgrass (1966) (see Appendix Table 3). Snodgrass constructs a&#13;
rubber acreage series back to the year of first planting, 1900. 26/ We have&#13;
smoothed these data during 1911-15 to reflect a steady expansion of acreage&#13;
through new planting; as outlined above, this is only an approximation and&#13;
ignores any removals or abandonment that may have occurred in this period.&#13;
This produced a "smoothed" acreage series (Appendix Table 3, column 2), and&#13;
from that series, we constructed the sequence of annual new plantings&#13;
(column 3). The annual new plantings were used to generate the percentage of&#13;
total acreage in 1921 (column 4), that was planted during 1900-21. The&#13;
allocation of the lump was achieved by multiplying the "acreage planted prior&#13;
to 1922" by these percentages; this completed the age distribution of 1934&#13;
acreage by year of planting.&#13;
The complete age distribution for 1934 was updated through 1978 by&#13;
using the official statistics on new planting, removals, and replanting.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 58 -&#13;
Appendix Table 3: RUBBER ACREAGE AND NEW PLANTING ESTIMATES (1900-21)&#13;
(1)                (2)             (3)                (4)&#13;
New planting&#13;
Snodgrass          Smoothed           New              as Z of&#13;
estimates /a        series        planting /c       1921 acreage&#13;
1900           1,729.7            1,729.7         1,729.7               0.44&#13;
1901           2,693.4            2,693.4           963.7               0.27&#13;
1902           4,200.7            4,200.7         1,507.3               0.39&#13;
1903          11,613.7           11,613.7         7,413.0               1.90&#13;
1904          13,096.3           13,096.3         1,482.6               0.38&#13;
1905          35,829.5           35,829.5        22,733.2               5.83&#13;
1906          50,408.4           50,408.4        14,579.0               3.74&#13;
1907         100,816.8          100,816.8        50,408.4              12.92&#13;
1908         131,704.3          131,704.3        30,887.5               7.92&#13;
1909         154,437.5          154,437.5        22,733.2               5.83&#13;
1910         186,560.5          186,560.5        32,123.0               8.23&#13;
1911         184,583.7          188,932.7/b       2,372.2               6.08&#13;
1912         222,637.1          191,329.57T       2,396.8               6.14&#13;
1913         232,768.3          193,751.1Th       2,421.6               6.21&#13;
1914         168,275.1          196,222.17h       2,471.0               6.33&#13;
1915         198,668.4          198,668.4Th       2,446.3               6.27&#13;
1916         221,648.7          221,648.7        22,980.3               5.89&#13;
1917         229,308.8          229,308.8         7,660.0               1.96&#13;
1918         259,455.0          259,455.0        30,146.2               7.73&#13;
1919         308,627.9          308,627.9        49,172.9              12.60&#13;
1920         347,027.0          347,207.0        38,399.1               9.84&#13;
1921         390,170.9          390,170.9        43,143.0              11.06&#13;
/a Snodgrass (1966).&#13;
7h Smoothed estimates.&#13;
Th  NPt =   At -At-li&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 59 -&#13;
Since throughout this period all plantings and removals were closely moni-&#13;
tored, these statistics are considered extremely reliable. In reconciling the&#13;
official age distributions with our revised acreage series, we adjusted&#13;
according to the rule "oldest out first," but we removed all old seedling&#13;
acreage prior to removing high-yielding acreage. In reconciling these&#13;
official age distributions with our revised acreage series, we also used the&#13;
same rule. After making these two corrections to the official data, we had a&#13;
time series of acreage and vintage data.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 60 -&#13;
Appendix B&#13;
Other Data Available for Analysis *&#13;
of Rubber Supply Response in Sri Lanka&#13;
The appendix is drawn from a memorandum dated October 24, 1982, from&#13;
M. J. Hartley to J. Duloy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 61 L&#13;
The Production Data. Reliable monthly data on total production of&#13;
all major grades of processed rubber are available back to 1934. During the&#13;
period of the International Rubber Restriction Agreement, 1934-43, the&#13;
official production data represent the quota limit assigned to Sri Lanka,&#13;
based upon a mandated, but varying proportion of the estimated potential pro-&#13;
duction for each separate year. Over this period, since the quota was not met&#13;
in some years and the shortfall carried-over to subsequent years, the data on&#13;
total exlports (available monthly) provide an extremely reliable measure of&#13;
actual production, as local consumption was negligible. From 1943 on, monthly&#13;
total production data are available, and, from 1951 on, these data are dis-&#13;
aggregated by the six major grades of processed rubber.&#13;
The major problem is that virtually no information is available on&#13;
production by size-of-holding or by type-of-planting material to enable a&#13;
reliable comparison of the production functions of smallholdings versus&#13;
estates or yields of seedling versus high-yielding varieties. The official&#13;
statistics provide a monthly breakdown of smallholder sheet production only&#13;
from 1950 to 1958, and inquiries indicated that this grade encompasses vir-&#13;
tually all of smallholder production. Since the registered area under cul-&#13;
tivation is disaggregated by size-of-holding for the entire sample period&#13;
(from 1934 on), this "gap" in the data base is regrettable. We shall, how-&#13;
ever, endeavor to make use of information contained in a cross-section survey&#13;
of smallholders in two districts (Kalutara and Ratnapura), conducted by the&#13;
(then) Ministry of Plantation Industries (in connection with a Bank Small-&#13;
holder Rubber Rehabilitation Project) in 1978. To this end we have succeeded&#13;
in relocating the original individual response forms and have recoded, punched&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
and edited these data for possible use. As is often the case, the question-&#13;
naire was designed for another purpose, and is of limited use in the present&#13;
study. Further, the absence of systematic record-keeping on the part of most&#13;
smaliholders makes even these data of dubious reliability. Another survey of&#13;
rubber smallholdings, conducted by the Ministry of Plantation Industries in&#13;
1971/72 also contains useful tabulations, but attempts to locate the original&#13;
responses failed.&#13;
Exports, Stocks of Inventories and Local Consumption. Monthly data&#13;
on total exports is available from June, 1934 to December 1979. From 1951 on,&#13;
these data are disaggregated by the six major grades. Since duties are only&#13;
levied on exports, and since the dealers and other export traders maintain&#13;
stocks of inventories prior to export (which fluctuate with currently prevail-&#13;
ing and expectations of future prices in both the Colombo and London auction&#13;
markets), there is a logical economic basis for the departure between the&#13;
timing of production and export. Indeed, presuming rational behavior on the&#13;
part of the holders of stocks of processed rubber, modelling such behavior&#13;
should reveal information as to what prices were expected in the two auction&#13;
markets.&#13;
To this end we have also collected data on the monthly stocks of&#13;
inventories held by various agents from 1935 to 1979. Total stocks are avail-&#13;
able over the entire sample period and, except for a few gaps, are disaggre-&#13;
gated by type of agent (viz., at customs; with dealers and shippers; on&#13;
estates by size-class; and at manufacturers). In addition, over the period&#13;
from 1934 to 1951, legislation restricted the maximum stock position which may&#13;
be maintained by both dealers and large estates, and these legislated maxima&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
*- 63 -&#13;
have also been collected, along with a legislative survey of such regula-&#13;
tions. To eliminate the portion of crop on which no export duties are levied,&#13;
we have collected an annual series on local consumption from 1934 to 1979.&#13;
Rubber Price Data. Monthly data on the Colombo auction price of two&#13;
of the principle grades of rubber - Ribbed Smoked Sheet No. 1 (RRS #1) and&#13;
Latex Crepe #1 - are available from 1927 to 1979. In addition, from 1913 to&#13;
1979 we have obtained annual data on the implicit export price of all grades&#13;
of rubber, combined - extracted from value and volume data of customs returns&#13;
- and, since 1955, the implicit export price of the six grade categories. The&#13;
Colombo auction price is net of all export duties, transport, freight and&#13;
insurance charges, and brokers fees, and thus represents the producer price.&#13;
We also have obtained an annual time-series of the f.o.b. price of RSS #1 from&#13;
1934 to 1979, with monthly breakdowns from 1962 on. The f.o.b. price repre-&#13;
sents the London auction price, net of freight, insurance and other such&#13;
charges. In the case of monthly f.o.b. price data, it is based on the average&#13;
of the four previous-week prices for the month. Since the f.o.b. price&#13;
reflects the effect of the exchange-rate changes, arising through devaluation&#13;
of the Sri Lankan rupee the SLR/UK and SLR/US$ official exchange rates (back&#13;
to 1933) have been compiled. Finally, we have collected the monthly prices&#13;
for export coupons over the period when the International Rubber Agreements&#13;
was operative.&#13;
Cost of Production. Unit costs of production are useful for two&#13;
related purposes within the context of a system of input demand and output&#13;
supply equations. First, the difference between the producer price and unit&#13;
cost of production define the profit margin. Second, in cases where it is not&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 64 -&#13;
possible to obtain data on the prices and/or quantities of all relevant var-&#13;
iable inputs - a situation which is typical - the specification of a pro-&#13;
duction function and/or system of input demand/output supply functions, using&#13;
only the incomplete set of observed input levels and prices will result in a&#13;
specification bias. The additional use of the cost of production data in such&#13;
a system provides an identity containing information on the total expenditure&#13;
on the unobserved inputs, or an independent check on the reliability of the&#13;
data in a "complete data" situation.&#13;
In the present case we have obtained data on the unit costs of pro-&#13;
duction for estates only. No systematic time-series data on smallholder costs&#13;
is available - though these would inevitably require the use of an implicit&#13;
market wage rate for the use of unpaid family labor. We have exploited four&#13;
separate sources to try to establish an estate total c.o.p. time-series, with&#13;
the result that the years 1910, 1913, 1918, 1920, 1921, 1925, 1929-32, 1939-&#13;
46, 1952-54 and 1957-1979 are covered. The data for 1957-79 are based upon a&#13;
regular annual survey of estates conducted by the Department of Statistics,&#13;
GOSL; whilst other data are obtained from less-formal procedures. In addi-&#13;
tion, the 1957-79 data are disaggregated by various expenditure categories&#13;
(salaries; labor wages; maternity, medical, feeding and schooling; insurance&#13;
and rent; pest control and fertilizer; and other expenditures). We are&#13;
indebted to Mr. Marshall Perrera of the RCD for making the most recent data&#13;
available to us. These breakdowns are extremely useful, as they provide an&#13;
estimate of estate employment (wages are known), and an independent check on&#13;
the fertilizer prices and quantities (see below) over that time-span.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 65 -&#13;
Inputs and Input Prices. Obtaining reliable data on the levels and&#13;
prices of variable inputs has proven to be extremely difficult. Indeed, it&#13;
should be stressed, in the context of the dynamic vintage production function&#13;
which distinguishes separate age-classes, even with complete aggregated data&#13;
there is still the remaining problem of allocating these input levels to age&#13;
clases in a manner consistent with profit maximizing behavior, given the pre-&#13;
vailing age-distribution of area under cultivation in any year. This problem&#13;
is analogous to the problem of allocating the observed levels of aggregate&#13;
area-replanted in a particular year to the particular collection of vintages&#13;
uprooted in the preceding year - required in order to endogenize the deter-&#13;
mination of the age-distribution from one year to the next.&#13;
Employment, Wages and Other Aspects of the Labor Market. There is no&#13;
time-series on the total employment in the aggregate rubber sector, or,&#13;
indeed, even in the rubber estate sector (i.e., neglecting smallholdings).&#13;
The most relevant series is total employment on estates employing Indian&#13;
labor, including not only rubber, but also tea, coconut, cardamons and cocoa -&#13;
available from 1933 to 1978. The labor force on the plantation sector in&#13;
Ceylon was (originally and currently) drawn largely from imported Indian Tamil&#13;
workers. Insofar as the British colonial government at the time maintained&#13;
records on the number of such workers, as well as its total population in&#13;
Ceylon, estimates were regularly made and published. However, the reliability&#13;
of these data is questionable. In addition, for our purposes, there is the&#13;
problem of disaggregation to the portion employed on rubber estates. The&#13;
total employment in the entire estate sector is disaggregated into Ceylonese&#13;
and Indian nationals from 1942 on.   In addition, from 1971 to 1973 we have&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 66 -&#13;
collected the total employment specific to the rubber (and tea) sectors. One&#13;
approach might be to assume a fixed relationship between area under cultiva-&#13;
tion and total employment - as a possible a priori method of disaggregation.&#13;
This approach suffers from the lack of systematic time series - except at&#13;
discrete benchmarks associated with Agricultural Census data - on area-under-&#13;
cultivation in coconuts, cardamons and cocoa. Further, such a fixed relation-&#13;
ship between area and employment defeats the purpose of analyzing changes in&#13;
the labor-per-acre utilized in response to changing wages and prices.&#13;
We have compiled a monthly time series of an index of minimum wages&#13;
payable to workers in the rubber and tea sectors from 1939 to 1964 - these&#13;
having been established by government legislation. This series may be&#13;
"spliced" with a monthly series on an agricultural wage index from 1965 to the&#13;
present. In addition, we have collected an annual time series on the average&#13;
daily wage rate for workers in rubber growing and manufacturing (disaggregated&#13;
by male and female adults, as well as children) from 1945 to 1979. Auxilliary&#13;
data on wage rates prevailing in other sectors of the economy - various forms&#13;
of manual unskilled occupations - have also been obtained, as measures of the&#13;
opportunity cost of alternative forms of employment. In addition, data on the&#13;
average number of hours worked per month has been collected (on a biannual&#13;
basis from 1964 to 1971) for male, female and child rubber-sector workers - as&#13;
an indicator of total earnings, when combined with average daily wage rates.&#13;
These can be matched with the labor wage component of the unit cost of produc-&#13;
tion.&#13;
As a further indicator of labor market conditions, we have collected&#13;
time-series for the entire plantation sector from 1934 to 1979 on the number&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 67 -&#13;
of strikes, the number of workers invoLved, man-days lost via strikes and the&#13;
number of strikes on which the data were reported. Also, as an indicator of&#13;
the availability of labor we have collected a time-series on the number of&#13;
workers registered for employment or better employment among unskilled, semi-&#13;
skilled occupations, spanning the years 1938 to 1971 (with totals available&#13;
there-after). A "highly unreliable" series on total unemployment from 1933 to&#13;
1979 (with occasional gaps) has also been obtained. Of similar alleged&#13;
quality is the unemployment rate - available, assortedly, from 1946 to 1979.&#13;
Fertilizer Use and Fertilizer Prices. The key materials input&#13;
involved in explaining secular changes in yields is fertilizer. Unfor-&#13;
tunately, these data pose similar problems. A special fertilizer study, con-&#13;
ducted by a German consultant group, to assess fertilizer use by agricultural&#13;
sector in Sri Lanka was obtained. This provided estimates of the total ton-&#13;
nage by principal source of nutrient (sulphate of ammonia, urea, rock phos-&#13;
phate and super phosphate, muriate of potash and other fertilizer) applied to&#13;
rubber (as well as separate estimates for tea, rice, coconuts and other&#13;
crops). However, the data are only available from 1962 to 1979. Discussions&#13;
in Sri Lanka with the resident German representative of the consultant group,&#13;
Dr. Udo Volz, who was in charge of the study, also indicated the difficulty of&#13;
extracting relevant data and its questionable reliability.&#13;
Since almost all of the fertilizer utilized in Sri Lanka is&#13;
imported - the exception being the recent attempts to establish urea plants as&#13;
a locally-produced source of nitrogen, we decided to conduct an intensive&#13;
investigation of the sequence of historical customs records to extract the&#13;
value and volume data of all imported sources of nitrogen (N), phosphorous (P)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68 -&#13;
and potassium (K). An exhaustive list of more than twenty-five ingredients&#13;
was compiled, and the value/volume data for every year from 1925 to 1968 was&#13;
collected. The nutrient composition (N, P, or K) by weight of every source or&#13;
ingredient was then compiled. The implicit import prices were then weighted&#13;
by nutrient-composition-weights to obtain price and quantity indices for N, P&#13;
and K, separately, for the complete time span. We have therefore have a&#13;
lengthy, highly reliable import price series for fertilizer nutrients. The&#13;
corresponding quantity series, however, applies to all agricultural sectors,&#13;
and not just rubber (or tea). The problem of how best to disaggregate the&#13;
total fertilizer nutrient measures to rubber (and tea) remains. Historical&#13;
accounts (Snodgrass (1966) and Forrest (1967)), as well as an FAO fertilizer&#13;
study (1965), indicate some useful qualitative information. Apparently, with&#13;
respect to rubber and tea, the latter sector was the principal user of&#13;
fertilizer over the span from 1933 to the early 1950s, when the rubber sector&#13;
began intensive fertilizer use (in connection with the government-subsidized&#13;
rubber replanting scheme (1953 to the present)). Thus, it would not be&#13;
correct to assume that the proportionate allocation by sector, manifest in the&#13;
data of the German fertilizer study, would be applicable to rubber (or tea)&#13;
prior to 1962. Further, smallholder use of fertilizer prior to 1958 was&#13;
alleged to be negligible, despite official recommendations to the contrary.&#13;
Resolution of this problem via statistical means therefore remains as an&#13;
issue.&#13;
Other Inputs. Cost of production breakdowns indicate that, apart&#13;
from imported capital equipment involved in the manufacturing of rubber, labor&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 69 -&#13;
and fertilizer account for the vast bulk of all expenditures. This is fortu-&#13;
nate since, apart from pesticides (which we elected not to attempt to treat&#13;
analogously to fertilizer), we were unable to locate any relevant data on&#13;
prices or quantities. Finally, we note that, if a general price deflator is&#13;
required to express prices in real terms, we have "spliced together" an annual&#13;
consumer price index from various sources from 1934 to 1979. Further, from&#13;
1938 to 1979, we have also obtained the separate components of the CPI (food;&#13;
fuel; and light; rent; clothing; and miscellaneous).&#13;
Weather Data. The varied effect of total rainfall, and its alter-&#13;
native measure, the total number of rainy days, on rubber yields is important&#13;
to the study of rubber supply. The inverse relationships between the amount&#13;
of rainfall and rubber yields - rain interferes with tapping - has been noted&#13;
by Barlow (1978) and documented with Malaysian data. In addition, temperature&#13;
and relative humidity are alleged to be correlates of the occurrence of&#13;
various types of disease and pest infestations, with an obvious indirect&#13;
effect on yield trajectories and stand densitis. Since climatic conditions&#13;
exhibit considerable regional variation within Sri Lanka, it is of some&#13;
importance to attempt to quantify the effect of weather conditions upon&#13;
current and future yields. Despite the fact that these factors are exogenous&#13;
events, they may be of importance in explaining historical changes in land-use&#13;
patterns and in guiding such choices currently and in the future. Further-&#13;
more, being able to account for the proportions of variation in yields attrib-&#13;
utable to weather is important in assessing the overall goodness of fit of the&#13;
complete model. Finally, if we are able to quantify the complete probability&#13;
distribution of weather events, it will provide an explicit quantitative means&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 70 -&#13;
by which the two principal sources of risk - the other major source being&#13;
uncertain fluctuations in world market price - may be treated.&#13;
For these reasons the discovery of extensive historical weather&#13;
records at the GOSL Department of Meteorology was considered important to the&#13;
project. From those archives we have obtained monthly time series data from&#13;
1933 to 1979 on (a) the number of inches of rainfall; and (b) the number of&#13;
days per month of recorded precipitation from a set of forty-nine weather&#13;
recording stations within the rubber (and tea) producing regions. For each&#13;
such region, our coverage contains between three and six stations per&#13;
region. In addition, we have collected monthly data on the maximum and&#13;
minimum temperature for twelve relevant locations for the same years, as well&#13;
as the monthly relative temperature for twelve relevant locations for the same&#13;
years, as well as the monthly relative humidity. These data should provide a&#13;
very reliable estimate of the probability distribution of each type of weather&#13;
index by region. Thus, for purposes of studying the effect of our weather&#13;
indices on current and future yield, we are forced to aggregate these to&#13;
national indices. We propose to utilize the area under rubber cultivation in&#13;
each region as weights to aggregate weather across regions. Here, the fact&#13;
that the official statistics on area under cultivation are flawed (see&#13;
Appendix A) created an additional statistical problem to be resolved.&#13;
Other Miscellaneous Data. The principal source of government revenue&#13;
extracted from the rubber (and tea) sectors is obtained from export duties and&#13;
cesses. Since 1934, Ceylon has imposed a variety of specific cesses per lb.&#13;
exported - each earmarked for a different purpose. We have extracted the&#13;
cess-rates (per lb.) for medical aid; research and propaganda; administration&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 71 -&#13;
of the Rubber Control Department; and the rubber replanting cess (since 1953),&#13;
separately. In addition, since 1950, a so-called sliding-scale for deter-&#13;
mining export duty rates was imposed. The rates applicable to every grade of&#13;
rubber have been collected and the "trigger-mechanisms," whereby the rate&#13;
structure changes with the prevailing Colombo auction price, have been&#13;
recorded. Further, the total amount of cess-collections (since 1934) and the&#13;
total amount of export duty collected (only given from 1962 on have been&#13;
recorded. This should permit a careful analysis of the public finance aspects&#13;
of the problem - including the possibility (via simulation of an estimated&#13;
output-supply/input-demand model) of analyzing the issue of optimal taxation&#13;
relative to a posited objective - e.g., maximize government revenues. The&#13;
fact that the estate sector (all holdings of greater than 50 acres) was&#13;
nationalized between 1972 and 1975 (and accounts for roughly 2/3 of the area&#13;
under cultivation) implies, however, that such matters may be somewhat moot&#13;
since 1975.&#13;
The major policy intervention, not yet discussed in detail is the&#13;
Rubber Replanting Subsidy Scheme, introduced in 1953. At that time, in part&#13;
due to the prior quota restrictions, in part due to the need for maximum pro-&#13;
duction to support the Allies during WWII, and in part due to the boom in&#13;
prices during the Korean War, Sri Lanka's rubber stock was both overaged and&#13;
contained a minimal proportion of high-yielding clonal varieties. In&#13;
response, Ceylon initiated a Rubber Replanting Subsidy Scheme, which provided&#13;
specified subsidy grants (per acre replanted) at yearly intervals over the six&#13;
years of gestation, with specific guidelines as to cultivation practices to be&#13;
followed to qualify for each successive payment. It was intended that the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 72 -&#13;
total of all subsidy payments would cover roughly 50% of total replanting&#13;
costs. Applications for replanting permits under the Scheme were screened as&#13;
to suitability of the land for rubber, and the subsidy rate structure was pro-&#13;
gressively revised upwards to account for inflationary trends in the cost of&#13;
replanting. Fertilizer dosages were specified for each year from planting and&#13;
government fertilizer distribution centers were established, along with&#13;
government extension service agents to advise on "proper" cultivation prac-&#13;
tices for the new varieties.&#13;
We have collected data on the progress of the subsidy rate structure&#13;
since 1953, as well as detailed information of its effect on replanting.&#13;
Breakdowns on acreage replanted each year, jointly by size-of-holding and&#13;
district, are readily available from the ARRC. Since 1958, the number of&#13;
applications to replant has been recorded and, from 1969, it is broken down by&#13;
size-of-holding. In addition, since 1953, the total income to and expenditure&#13;
from the Rubber Replanting Fund and the total of annual subsidy payments made&#13;
have been assembled, as well as the specific sources of income and the break-&#13;
down of expenditures made (subsidies, nurseries, fertilizers, extension&#13;
service agent fees, etc.). These data should permit a careful assessment&#13;
of: the financing and impact of the Scheme; estimates of the elasticity of&#13;
replanting response to subsidy levels; and, analysis of "optimal" subsidy&#13;
levels.&#13;
A major problem, as noted earier, is that of identifying the age of&#13;
areas uprooted for replanting. To this end, we have obtained a probability&#13;
distribution of the age of acres "intended for removal" from the Rubber Master&#13;
Plan survey of 1979. This is better than no data, but obviously depends upon&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 73 -&#13;
the age distribution prevailing in 1979, as well as the prevailing price&#13;
structure, etc.&#13;
As a final note, we have attempted to compile a chronological account&#13;
of all legislation applicable to the rubber sector, as well as assorted his-&#13;
torical qualitative information - such as the virtual impossibility of obtain-&#13;
ing certain fertilizer imports during WWII - to aid the eventual model con-&#13;
struction and account for the behavioral consequences of structural changes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 74 -&#13;
FOOTNOTES&#13;
1/       Since even new plantings usually replace an existing crop, current&#13;
prices of rubber must be considered not only in relation to rubber&#13;
prices in the more distant future but also in relation to the prices&#13;
of the crops now occupying the land and utilizing other resources,&#13;
now, in the interim gestation period, and finally when rubber planted&#13;
now begins to yield. The difference is that the opportunity costs of&#13;
replanting are directly related to whatever factors are affecting&#13;
current rubber prices. Since the alternatives to a newly planted&#13;
crop are generally much more diffuse, very little significant&#13;
response to prices of alternative crops has been found even in&#13;
conventional supply response studies for annual crops. Replanting&#13;
decisions are much more sharply focused. Moreover, such decisions&#13;
are likely to be quantitatively much more important in the case of a&#13;
mature industry, in which most highly suitable land is fully&#13;
exploited, than for a nascent and rapidly expanding industry.&#13;
2/       This is probably more nearly the case for coffee than for rubber. In&#13;
the case of rubber, the current rate of tapping affects the output&#13;
obtainable in later years. Indeed, when replacement of a stand of&#13;
rubber trees is contemplated, the trees are often tapped at&#13;
increasing intensities in an effort to extract the maximum latex&#13;
obtainable over the remaining life of the tree.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 75 -&#13;
3/       If all potential output is not always harvested, a discontinuity in&#13;
the derivative of output with respect to prices is introduced (see&#13;
Nerlove, 1979, p.882). Such a discontinuity implies that neither&#13;
exact nor approximate certainty equivalents for unknown future prices&#13;
exist (see Malinvaud, 1969). Supply response cannot then be derived&#13;
as the solution to a dynamic optimization problem in which uncertain&#13;
future prices or other variables are replaced by their conditional&#13;
expectations given past experience (so-called quasi-rational&#13;
expectations; see Nerlove, Grether, Carvalho, 1979, p.306).&#13;
4/       "Maximum output" is used in the figurative sense;   Qi  is not a&#13;
maximum in the prodution function sense. In fact as used in a later&#13;
section of this paper, Q. represents the average age-yield&#13;
profile. Actual output could be above or below it, therefore it&#13;
could not be a "true maximum."&#13;
5/       We have also adopted this simplification in our initial analysis,&#13;
although the longitudinal data on estates will make possible an&#13;
analysis of how technological change and other inputs affect the age-&#13;
yield profiles. Estimates of the age-yield profiles are obtained in&#13;
our case from these estate statistics.&#13;
6/       It is interesting to note that Nerlove (1956, 1979) is very explicit&#13;
about the assumption that Pt in (2) is an expectation of "normal"&#13;
price, i.e., the price expected to prevail "on the average" in all&#13;
future periods. In contrast, WG in (7) assume nothing about how the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 76 -&#13;
expectations pe are formed; implicitly they differ depending on which&#13;
period in the future the subscript refers to. When (7) is used to&#13;
derive a function representing expected discounted net future revenue&#13;
from a tree, however, static price expectations (i.e., expectations,&#13;
however formed, which are the same for all future periods) are&#13;
implicitly assumed. It can be shown (Nerlove, 1972) that static&#13;
expectations are necessary in order to make meaningful the concept of&#13;
a long-run equilibrium level towards which economic agents may be&#13;
assumed to move and thus to justify a partial adjustment model of the&#13;
type implied by equation (1).&#13;
7/       WG assume acreage will be be fully harvested.    See footnote 2.  If&#13;
this were not the case, in general the uncertain future prices which&#13;
enter the discounted net revenue function could not be replaced by&#13;
single-valued expectations.&#13;
8/       The reason for this assumption is not made clear.    One would think&#13;
that the decision depends entirely on current price in relation to&#13;
current harvesting costs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 77 -&#13;
9/       Refitting the model omitting Q t2' using current rather than lagged&#13;
price, and including a trend term yields (similar to Grilli et al&#13;
(1981))&#13;
Q  = 28,199.0   + 0.66 Q     - 88.2 Pt + 787.4t,&#13;
(2.24)       (4.86)       (0.02)     (2.35)&#13;
R   = 0.876             D.W. = 2.32&#13;
which suggests no response to price at all, but cannot then be&#13;
interpreted in terms of the standard Nerlovian formulation. The&#13;
explanation of current output is entirely determined by last year's&#13;
output and a trend, which presumably represents technical progress.&#13;
10/      There are some rather serious problems with the official area&#13;
statistics which are discussed in Appendix A to the paper.&#13;
11/      This neglects the problem of seedling vs. high-yielding varieties, as&#13;
well as major differences within each of these groups, and their&#13;
separate areas, age distributions, and age yield profiles in the&#13;
determination of the results.&#13;
12/      We ignore for the moment that areas to be replanted require a minimum&#13;
of one year to complete uprooting and clearing before replanting may&#13;
occur. This also ignores the existence of alternative crops, since&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 78 -&#13;
some uprooting may result in crop diversification and not rubber&#13;
replanting. Moreover, during the years of immaturity there are&#13;
extensive maintenance expenditures which we take into account only&#13;
through the wage rate.&#13;
13/      The revenues obtainable from nonagricultural employment and from&#13;
alternative crops, are also important, but difficult to specify, and&#13;
to estimate due to a lack of data.&#13;
14/      We can imagine the relationship to be derived by an explicit dynamic&#13;
optimization procedure in the manner of WC provided we also assume,&#13;
as they do, that all potential output from a stand will always be&#13;
harvested.&#13;
15       However, the model is not closed, since   Ft+l   is not determined.&#13;
This means that for prediction beyond the sample a rule of "oldest&#13;
out first" must be adopted.&#13;
16/      One of these varietal improvements is the lowering of the age at&#13;
which significant yield may be obtained. This could be expected to&#13;
enhance, ceteris paribus, the desirability of up-rooting and&#13;
replanting any given stand. Some of this improvement is also due to&#13;
better agronomic practice.&#13;
17/      These are taken to be the unsmoothed values from Figure 5 except that&#13;
the first six values have been set to zero. This yield curve, which&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 79 -&#13;
has been drawn from our estate sample over the period 1970-79, would&#13;
not be appropriate for all Sri Lankan producers nor for all time&#13;
periods. In fact, Colin Barlow has suggested the existence of three&#13;
distinct age-yield profiles: (i) pre-war high yielding; (ii) post-&#13;
war high yielding; and, (iii) a smallholder age-yield profile.&#13;
18/      As noted earlier, use of an average age-yield profile neglects the&#13;
effects of improvement in varieties over time (see footnote 16).&#13;
Since the age-yield profile used is for a recent period, potential&#13;
output as we have calculated it will tend to over-state true&#13;
potential output in earlier periods (and understate it in future&#13;
periods), since younger trees in earlier times yielded less than do&#13;
trees of comparable age today. Our estate data will make possible&#13;
some adjustment for this phenomenon in future analysis.&#13;
19/      Of course, to the extent that the alternative crops are also&#13;
perennials, e.g., oil palm in Malaysia, their current prices relative&#13;
to long-term expectations will matter.&#13;
20/      Since, under the assumptions, the method is maximum likelihood, we&#13;
could derive the unconditional standard errors from the information&#13;
matrix. Past experience shows this refinement typically makes little&#13;
difference.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 80&#13;
21/      We also ran this regression using the official area statistics; the&#13;
result shown below is similar to the estimates derived using the&#13;
revised data.&#13;
R   -20363   - 14.22 (P   - pe  ) + 202.1 pe   + 0.819 s&#13;
(11.20)   (1.11)   t-1   t-l    (7.54) t 1   (6.89) t-l&#13;
+ 0.0315 AGE31-35 + 0.0541 AGE 36-40&#13;
(3.20)              (6.70)&#13;
-2 = 0.930                                    D.W. = 1.39&#13;
8 = 0.149&#13;
22/      We also ran the same regression using the ratio of current rubber&#13;
prices to wages. The ratio proved insignificant, and both the&#13;
significance of the time trend and first-order residual serial&#13;
correlation were enhanced.&#13;
23/      It has been suggested that the rate of such improvement has greatly&#13;
slowed in recent years. If so, this will have significant effects on&#13;
rubber supply response in both the short- and long-run since it will&#13;
make waiting to replant at any point in time a less attractive&#13;
alternative.&#13;
24/      This same assumption is the basis for the replanting model developed&#13;
in the text. A problem arises from its applicability to&#13;
smallholders, as discussed above.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 81 -&#13;
25/      These plantings were allegedly made in former coffee-producing areas&#13;
in the higher elevations, as a result of the decline in the turn-of-&#13;
the-century coffee prices relative to rubber prices. Such plantings&#13;
were made in ignorance of subsequent experimental results indicating&#13;
the deleterious effect of higher elevations on rubber yields.&#13;
26/      The total acreage in 1921 according to Snodgrass is 390,170.9;&#13;
however, according to the ARRC, the 1934 age distribution records&#13;
461,441 acres survived until 1934. Therefore, a straightforward use&#13;
of Snodgrass's estimates was not possible.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 82 -&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
Arak, Marcelle, 1969. "Estimation of Assymetric Longrun Supply Functions:&#13;
The Case of Coffee." Canadian Journal of Agricultural Economics,&#13;
Vol. 17, No. 1:15-22.&#13;
Barlow, Colin, 1978. The Natural Rubber Industry. Kuala Lumpur: Oxford&#13;
University Press.&#13;
Dowling, J. M., 1979. "The Supply Response of Rubber in Thailand." Southern&#13;
Economic Journal, 45: 795-805.&#13;
Dowling, J. M, and P. Jessadachat, 1979. "The Supply Response of Sugar Cane&#13;
in "Thailand." Malayan Economic Review, 24:&#13;
Grilli, E., R. Helterline, and P. Pollak, 1981. "An Econometric Model of the&#13;
World Rubber Economy." World Bank Staff Commodity Paper No. 6.&#13;
Malinvaud, E., 1969. "First-Order Certainty Equivalence." Econometrica, 37:&#13;
706-718.&#13;
Nerlove, M., 1956. "Estimates of the Elasticities of Supply of Selected&#13;
Agricultural Commodities." Journal of Farm Economics, 38: 496-509.&#13;
, 1979,  "The Dynamics of Supply:   Retrospect and Prospect."&#13;
American Journal of Economics, 61: 874-888.&#13;
Nerlove, M., D.M. Grether, and J. L. Carvalho, 1979. Analysis of Economic&#13;
Time Series: A Synthesis. New York: Academic Press.&#13;
Parikh, A., 1979. "Estimation of Supply Functions for Coffee." Applied&#13;
Economics, 11:&#13;
Perrin, R.K., 1972. "Asset Replacement Principles." American Journal of&#13;
Agricultural Economics, 54: 60-67.&#13;
Snodgrass, D.R., 1966. Ceylon: An Export Economy in Transition. Homewood,&#13;
Illinois: Irwin.&#13;
Wickens, M.R., and J.N. Greenfield, 1973. "The Econometrics of Agricultural&#13;
Supply: An Application to the World Coffee Market." Review of&#13;
Economics and Statistics, 55: 433-440.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
W   orld    Bank                         Commodity Trade and Price                tices and the effects of trade policy on&#13;
Trends (1983-84 edition)                 output prices using nominal protection&#13;
.Tre__ds (1983-84edition)coefficients. Builds a simultaneous&#13;
ft   blicat1ons                          Historical information on the trade of   supply/demand model for cotton and&#13;
developing countries and eighty mar-     textiles that incorporates trade in tex-&#13;
of Related                               ket price quotations for fifty-one com-  tiles and cotton lint and the behavior&#13;
modities that figure importantly in in-  of textile mills. Used for five- and ten-&#13;
Interest                           temational trade. Actual current and     year projections given a range of pol-&#13;
constant dollar prices are shown in      icy altematives. Part of continuing&#13;
tabular and graphic form to indicate     work on the long-run prospects of In-&#13;
Analysis of the World Cocoa              commodity price movements relative       dian agriculture.&#13;
Market                                   to the international price level.        Staff Working Paper No. 618. 1983. 104&#13;
Takamasa Akiyama and Ronald C.           The Johns Hopkins University Press, jour-  pages.&#13;
Duncan                                   nals Division. 1983. Annual. 173 pages.  ISBN 0-8213-0322-8. Stock No. WP 0618.&#13;
Commodity Working Paper No. 8. 1982.     ISSN 0251-401X. Stock No. IB 0505 $20    $5.&#13;
64 pages (including 4 annexes).          paperback.&#13;
Stock No. BK 9050. $3.                   French and Spanish translations are pro-  Industrial Processing of&#13;
vided alongside the English in the same  Natural Resources&#13;
volume.                                  David Wall&#13;
Analysis of the World Coffee             Control, Accountability, and             Commodity Working Paper No. 4. 1979.&#13;
Market                                   Icnie        naScesu                      3pgs&#13;
Takamasa Akiyama and Ronald C.           Incentives in a Successful               23 pg.&#13;
Duncan                                   Development Institution: The             Stock No. BK 9046. $3.&#13;
Commodity Working Paper No. 7. 1982.     Kenya Tea Development                    International Cotton Market&#13;
59 pages (including 4 annexes).          Authority                                Prospects&#13;
Stock No. BK 9049. $3.                   Geoffrey Lamb and Linda Muller           M. Elton Thigpen,&#13;
Analyzes the institutional factors in     with Maw-Cheng Yang&#13;
the success of the Kenya Tea Develop-    Commodity Working Paper No. 2. 1978.&#13;
Case Studies on Industrial               ment Authority. Draws lessons useful     72 pages (including 3 annexes).&#13;
Processing of Primary Products           to other development institutions.       Stock No. BK 9170. $3.&#13;
Vol. 1 Bauxite,                          Staff Working Paper No. 550. 1983. 71&#13;
Rubber,Tropical Hardwood                 pages.                                   Natural Rubber&#13;
Analyzes primary products of            ISBN 0-8213-0118-7. Stock No. WP 0550.    Theodore J. Goering&#13;
interest to developing countries to                                               Examines recent developments in the&#13;
provide a basis for some general         A Dynamic Simulation Model               global rubber market that form the ba-&#13;
principles regarding industrial          of the World jute Economy                sis for establishing World Bank policies&#13;
processing in those countries. The      Jock Anderson and others                  in lending for natural rubber produc-&#13;
first of two volumes of case             Staff Working Paper No. 391. 1980. 39    tion. Builds on a comprehensive study&#13;
studies based on a joint research       pages (including references).             of the world rubber economy that was&#13;
project begun in April 1979              Stock No. WP-0391. $3.                   prepared jointly by the Bank and the&#13;
project bhegun    d  akan       h                                                 Food and Agriculture Organization of&#13;
between the World Bank and the                                                    the United Nations in 1978. It also&#13;
Commonwealth Secretariat.                An Econometric Model of the               takes note of several subsequent de-&#13;
1983. 364 pages.                         World Rubber Economy                     velopments that are likely to affect the&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0154-3. Stock No. BK         Enzo R. Grilli, Ray M. Helterline,       demand for and supply of natural rub-&#13;
0154. $20.                               and Peter K. Pollak                      ber.&#13;
Commodity Working Paper No. 3. 1979.      Sector Policy Paper. 1982. 67 pages.&#13;
Volume II. Cocoa, Coconut               44 pages.                                 ISBN 0-8213-0045-8. $5.&#13;
Oil, Tea                                Stock No. BK 9171. $3.                    The Outlook for Primary&#13;
In-depth study assesses the problems                                              Commodities&#13;
and potential benefits of processing        NEW                                   Enzo R. Grilli, editor&#13;
these primary products and gives pol-                                             Commodity Working Paper No. 9. 1982.&#13;
icy recommendations. Considers the       The Economics of Cotton                  162 pages (including 3 annexes).&#13;
most important factors in determining    Cultivation in India: Supply             Stock No. BK 0142. $5.&#13;
the partucular location of the process-  and Demand for 1980-90&#13;
ing chains, gains and losses that might  Jon A  Hitchings                         A Simultaneous Equahon&#13;
result from the initiation or expansion  o                                        Model of Price and Quantity&#13;
of local processing, and selected policy  Analyzes the contribution of irrigation  Adjustments in World Prima.&#13;
measures to relocate the processing ac-  to the cotton production growth rate.    C-mts M           k       try'&#13;
tivities so that a greater share of the  Notes the returns to cotton cultivation  Commodity Markets&#13;
value added accrues to developing        over time. Discusses the potential for   Erh-Cheng Hwa&#13;
country suppliers.                      increasing profitability through im-      Staff Working Paper No. 499. 1981. 48&#13;
1983. 290 pages.                         proved varieties and cultivation prac-   pages (including footnotes, references, ap-&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0155-1. Stock No. BK 0155.                                            pendix).&#13;
$10.                                                                              Stock No. WP-0499. S3.&#13;
Order both Volumes I and II (Stock No. IB&#13;
0506) for $20 and save $10.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Tropical Hardwood Trade in               The World Rubber Economy:                 World Rubber Market&#13;
the Asia-Pacific Region                  Structure, Changes, and                   Structure and Stabilization: An&#13;
Kenji Takeuchi                           Prospects                                 Econometric Study&#13;
The Philippines, Malaysia, and Indo-     Enzo R. Grilli, Barbara Bennett           C. Suan Tan&#13;
nesia could industrialize remote areas   Agostini, and Maria J. 't Hooft-          Examines the specification, estimation,&#13;
and more than triple foreign-exchange     Welvaars                                 and validation of an econometric&#13;
earnings through expansion of wood-      The first integrated analysis of the nat-  model of the world rubber market.&#13;
processing operations.                   ural and synthetic rubber economies,     Uses the model to forecast natural rub-&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1974.  with a unique study of the relative    ber prices and to analyze the implica-&#13;
108 pages (including 3 annexes, statistical  costs of production of the main kinds  tions of natural rubber market stabili-&#13;
appendix, references).                   of rubber.                               zation. Discusses problems of the&#13;
LC 74-4214. ISBN 0-8018-1627-0, Stock     The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1980.  world rubber market, demand for rub-&#13;
No. IH 1627, $5 paperback.                222 pages.                              ber products, supply of nrbber, natural&#13;
World Bank Commodity   ~       LC 80-554. ISBN 0-8018-2421-4, Stock     rubber export taxation, behavior of&#13;
World Bank Commodity                      No. IH 2421, $10                        rubber stocks and prices. Illustrates&#13;
Models                                                                             the impact of national government in-&#13;
Shamsher Singh, editor                    paperback.                               terventions in world commodity mar-&#13;
Commodity Working Paper No. 6. 1981.                                               kets. Includes nine appendixes and&#13;
547 pages.                                The World Sugar Economy: An              Commodity Working Paper. 1984. 424&#13;
Stock No. BK 9048. $20.                   Econometric Analysis of Long-            pages.&#13;
Term   Developments                      Stock No. BK 0264. $20.&#13;
Jos de Vries&#13;
Commodity Working Paper No. 5. 1980.&#13;
131 pages (including 2 annexes).&#13;
Stock No. BK 9047. $5.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Publications Order Form&#13;
SEND TO: YOUR LOCAL DISTRIBUTOR OR TO WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
(See the other side of thisform.)        P.O. BOX 37525&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013 U.S.A.&#13;
Date&#13;
Name                                                Ship to: (Enter if different from purchaser)&#13;
Title                                               Name&#13;
Firm                                                Title&#13;
Address                                             Firm&#13;
City              State      Postal Code            Address&#13;
Country            1Telephone (                     City            State       Postal Code&#13;
Purchaser Reference No.                             Country            'ITlephone&#13;
Check your method of payment.&#13;
Enclosed is my E Check O International Money Order O Unesco Coupons Ol International Postal Coupon.&#13;
Make payable to World Bank Publications for U. S. dollars unless you are ordering from your local distributor.&#13;
Charge my O VISA El MasterCard E American Express E Choice. (Credit cards accepted only for orders addressed&#13;
to World Bank Publications.)&#13;
Credit Card Account Number           Expiration Date                    Signature&#13;
E Invoice me and please reference my Purchase Order No.&#13;
Please ship me the items listed below.&#13;
Customer Internal&#13;
Stock Number  Autbow/ Title                                     Routing Code  Quantity  Unit Price  Total Amount S&#13;
All prices subject to change. Prices may vary by country. Allow 6-8 weeks for delivery.&#13;
Subtotal Cost  $&#13;
Thtal copies _ _  Air mail surcharge if desired ($2.00 each)  S&#13;
Postage and handling for more than two complimentary items ($2.00 each)  S&#13;
lbtal  S&#13;
ISRW053                                                          Thank you for your order.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Distributors of World                     Attn: Mr Giancarlo Bigazzi               Attn: Mr. J.M. Hernandez&#13;
Distributors ofbli  WorlVia Lamarmora 45                                           Castello 37&#13;
Bank Publications                         50121                                    Madrid&#13;
ARGENTINA                                 Florence                                SRI LANKA AND THE MALDIVES&#13;
Carlos Hirsch, SRL,                      JAPAN                                     Lake House Bookshop&#13;
Attn: Ms. Monica Bustos                  Eastern Book Service                     Attn: Mr. Victor Walatara&#13;
Flonda 165 4° piso                        Attn: Mr. Terumasa Hirano               41 Wad Ramanavake Mawatha&#13;
Galeria Guemes                            37-3, Hongo 3-Chome. Bunkyo-ku 113      Colombo 2&#13;
Buenos Aires 1307                        Tokyo                                     SWEDEN&#13;
AUSTRALIA, PAPUA NEW GUINEA,             KENYA                                     ABCE Fntzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel&#13;
FIJI, SOLOMON ISLANDS,                   Africa Book Services (E.A.) Ltd.          Attn: Mr. Eide Segerback&#13;
WESTERN SAMOA, AND                       Attn: Mr. M.B. Dar                        Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356&#13;
VANUATU                                  P.O. Box 45245                           S-1027 Stockholm&#13;
The Australian Financial Review          Nairobi                                   SWITZERLAND&#13;
Information Service (AFRIS)              KOREA, REPUBLIC OF                        Librairie Pavot&#13;
Attn: Mr David Jamieson                  Pan Korea Book Corporation                Attn: Mr. Henn de Perrot&#13;
235-243 Jones Street                     Attn. Mr. Yoon-Sun 'Km                   6, rue Grenus&#13;
Broadwa                                  P.O. Box 101, Kwanghwamun                 1211 Geneva&#13;
Sydney, NSW 20001                        Seoul                                    TANZANIA&#13;
BELGIUM                                  MALAYSIA                                 Oxford University Press&#13;
Publications des Nations Unies           University of Malaya Cooperative         Attn. Mr. Anthonv Theobold&#13;
Attn: Mr. Jean de Lannoy                 Bookshop Ltd.                            Maktaba Road, P.O. Box 5299&#13;
av. du Roi 202                           Attn: Mr. Mohammed Fahim Htj              Dar es Salaam&#13;
1060 Brussels                            Yacob                                    THAILAND&#13;
CANADA                                   P.O. Box 1127, Jalan Pantai Baru         Central Department Store, Head Office&#13;
Le Diffuseur                             Kuala Lumpur                             Attn: Mrs. Ratana&#13;
Attn Mrs. Suzanne Vermette               MEXICO                                   306 Silom Road&#13;
C.P. 85, Boucherville J4B 5E6            INFOTEC                                   Bangkok&#13;
Quebec                                   Attn: Mr. Jorge Cepeda                   Thailand Management Association&#13;
COSTA RICA                               San Lorenzo 153-11, Col. del Valle,       Attn: Mrs. Sunan&#13;
Librena Treios                           Deleg. Benito Juarez                     308 Silom Road&#13;
Attn: Mr. Hugo Chamberlain               031   Mexico, D.F.                       Bangkok&#13;
Calle 11-13, Av. Fernandez Guell         MIDDLE EAST                              TUNISIA&#13;
San Jose                                 Middle East Marketing Research           Societe Tunisienne de Diffusion&#13;
DENMARK                                  Bureau                                    Attn: Mr. Slaheddine Ben Hamida&#13;
Sanfundslitteratur            ~~Attn: Mr George Vassilou                5 Avenue de Carthage&#13;
Sanfundslitteratur                       Mitsis Bldg 3                            Tunis&#13;
Attn: Mr. Wilfned Roloff                 Makarios III Avenue                      Tuns&#13;
Rosendems Alle 11                        Nicosia                                  TURKEY&#13;
DK-1970 Copenhagen V.                    Cvprus                                   Haset Kitapevi A S.&#13;
EGYPT, Arab Republic of                  (granch offices in Bahrain, Greece,      Attn: Mr. tzzet Izerel&#13;
Al Ahram                                 Morocco, Kuwait, United Arab             469, Istiklal Caddesi&#13;
Al Galaa Street                          Emirates, Jordan)                        Bevoglu-Istanbul&#13;
Cairo                                    NETHERLANDS                               UNITED KINGDOM AND&#13;
MBE BV                                   NORTHERN IRELAND&#13;
FINLAND                                  Attn: Mr. Gerhard van Bussell            Microinfo Ltd.&#13;
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa                  Noorderwal 38,                           Attn: Mr. Roy'Selwyn&#13;
Attn: Mr. Kari Litmanen                  7241 BL Lochem                           Newman Lane, P.O. Box 3&#13;
Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100                   NORWAY                                   Alton, Hampshire GU34 2PG&#13;
Helsinki 10                              Johan Grundt Tanum A.S.                  England&#13;
FRANCE                                   Attn: Ms. Randi Mikkelborg               UNITED STATES&#13;
World Bank Publications                  P.O. Box 1177 Sentrum                    The World Bank Book Store&#13;
66, avenue d'1ena                        Oslo 1                                   600 19th Street, N.W.&#13;
75116 Paris                              PANAMA                                   Washington, D.C. 20433&#13;
GERMANY, Federal Republic of             Ediciones Libreria Cultural Panamena     (Postal address: P.O. Box 37525&#13;
UNO-Verlag                               Attn: Mr. Luis Femandez Fraguela R.      Washington, D.C. 20013, U.S.A.)&#13;
Attn: Mr Joachim Krause                  Av. 7, Espana 16                          Baker and Taylor Company&#13;
Simrockstrasse 23                        Panama Zone 1                             501 South Gladiola Avenue&#13;
D-5300 Bonn I                            PHILIPPINES                               Momence, Illinois, 60954&#13;
HONG KONG, MACAU                         National Book Store                      380 Edison Way&#13;
Asia 2000 Ltd.                           Attn: Mrs. Socorro C. Ramos              Reno, Nevada, 89564&#13;
Attn: Ms. Gretchen Weanng Smith          701 Rizal Avenue                         50 Kirby Avenue&#13;
6 Fl., 146 Prince Edward Road            Manila                                     ymve Ne&#13;
Kowloon                                  PORTUGAL&#13;
INDIA                                    Livraria Portugal                        Commerce, Georgia 30599&#13;
UBS Publishers' Distributors Ltd.        Attn: Mr. Antonio Alves Martins          Bernan Associates&#13;
UttS  Publisher s'  Distributors  L . VRua   Do  Carmo  70-74                     9730-E  George  Palmer Hi  hway&#13;
Attn: Mr. D.P. Veer                      120Lanham, Maryland, 20761&#13;
5 Ansari Road, Post Box 7015             L20o                                      Lackwe, North A   raI&#13;
New Delhi 110002                         Lisbon                                   Blackwell North America, Inc.&#13;
(Branch offices in Bombay, Bangalore,    SAUDI ARABIA                             1001 Fries Mill Road&#13;
Kanpur, Calcutta. and Madras)            Jarir Book Store                         Blackwood, New Jersey 08012&#13;
INDONESIA                                Attn: Mr. Akram AI-Agil                  Sidney Kramer Books&#13;
Pt. Indira Limited                       P.O. Box 3196                            1722   Street, N.W.&#13;
Attn: Mr. Bambang Wahyudi                Rivadh                                   Washington, D.C. 20006&#13;
JI, Dr. Sam Ratulangi No. 37             SINGAPORE, TAIWAN, BURMA                  United Nations Bookshop&#13;
Jakarta Pusat                            Information Publications Private, Ltd.   United Nations Plaza&#13;
IRELAND                                  Attn. Ms. Janet David                    New York, N.Y. 10017&#13;
TDC Publishers                           02-06 1st Floor, Pei-Fu Industrial&#13;
Attn: Mr. James Booth                      Building                               VENEZUELA&#13;
12 North Frederick Street                24 New Industrial Road                   Librena del Este&#13;
Dublin I                                 Singapore                                Attn. Mr. Juan Pericas&#13;
Dublin  1                                 Singapore                               Avda  Francisco  de  M iranda.  no. 52&#13;
ITALY                                    SPAIN                                    Edificio GalipanS Aptdo. 60.337&#13;
Licosa Commissionaria Sansoni SPA        Mundi-Prensa Libros. S.A.                Caracas 1060fiA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
| HG 3881.5 .W57 W67 NO.657&#13;
c.3&#13;
HARTLEY, MICHAEL J., 1943-&#13;
THE SUPPLY RESPONSE FOR&#13;
RUBBER IN SRI LANKA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                           European Office                  Tokyo Office&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                    66, avenue d'1ena                Kokusai Building&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.         75116 Paris, France              1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234              Telephone: (1) 723-54.21         Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK             Telex: 842-620628                Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                                Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0403-8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554793">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/09/1554793/supply-response-rubber-sri-lanka-preliminary-analysis
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/09/1554793/supply-response-rubber-sri-lanka-preliminary-analysis</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1984/09/1554793/supply-response-rubber-sri-lanka-preliminary-analysis</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/19/000178830_98101903423319/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/19/000178830_98101903423319/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-08-19T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1984-09-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The supply response for rubber in Sri Lanka
            : a preliminary analysis
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Study of supply response for perennial
            crops has frequently been limited by lack of data. This
            study is based on new extensive time series for rubber in
            Sri Lanka covering total output, producer prices, new
            plantings, replantings, wage rates, area under cultivation,
            as well as many other variables. In addition, a survey of 49
            rubber estates provides data on yields, type and age of
            clone, stand densities, and many other variables. This paper
            reports some preliminary analysis of the Sri Lankan data
            designed to test the adequacy of Dowling's analysis of
            supply response for rubber in Thailand, based on a
            sophisticated reduced form supply function developed by
            Wickens and Greenfield for Brazilian coffee. The model used
            in this study focuses on the uprooting-replanting decision,
            which is central to understanding rubber supply response in
            Sri Lanka, as well as disaggregates the reduced form into
            several structural relationships. Essential use is made of
            the age distribution and age-yield profile data from the
            estate surveys. This modest extension of the
            Wickens-Greenfield formulation performs significantly better
            in the Sri Lankan context, than a straightforward
            application of the model.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The supply response for rubber in Sri Lanka
            : a preliminary analysis
        </docna>
        <display_title>The supply response for rubber in
            Sri Lanka : a preliminary analysis</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1984/09/1554793/supply-response-rubber-sri-lanka-preliminary-analysis</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Crops and Crop Management Systems,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Access to Markets,Geographical Information Systems</subtopic>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>International Economics and Trade</teratopic>
        <count>Sri Lanka</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Hartley, Michael J.</author>
            <author>Nerlove, Marc</author>
            <author>Peters Jr., R. Kyle</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903423319</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Other agriculture</subsc>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 657</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>International Economics and Trade</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Agriculture, fishing, and forestry</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0403-8</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Time-series analysis; Supply functions;
            Mathematical models; Transplanting; Rubber crops
            adaptive expectations,agronomic
            practices,alternative crops,annual
            crops,area,aspect,CD,climatic
            conditions,coffee,CPI,crop,cultivation,debt,discount
            rate,Elasticities,Elasticity,equilibrium,expected present
            value,exploitation,fertilizer,fixed costs,GNP,GNP
            deflator,harvesting,hay,high-yielding
            varieties,identity,labor costs,labor inputs,marginal
            cost,Mathematical models,obsolescence,opportunity
            costs,perennial
            crops,perennials,plantations,planting,potential output,price
            elasticity,price elasticity of supply,produce,producer
            prices,producers,production function,random
            walk,replantation,replanting,Sales,soil
            type,substitution,sugar,sugar cane,technological
            progress,time series,total output,tree
            crops,trees,trough,wage rates,wholesale price index,yields
        </keywd>
        <owner>SAR</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP657</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technological Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Integrated Pest Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pest Control</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pesticides</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops and Crop Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Econometrics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technology Transfer and Diffusion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pest Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adaptation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Sri Lanka</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>