<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>The Effects of Population Growth, of the Pattern&#13;
of Demand, and of Technology&#13;
on the Process of Urbanization&#13;
An Application to India&#13;
Rakesh Mohan          SWP-520&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 520&#13;
#S*&#13;
147&#13;
.15&#13;
M64&#13;
1982&#13;
Co 2&#13;
! _SLC01 8352&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WYORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 520&#13;
The Effects of Population Growth, of the Pattern&#13;
of Demand, and of Technology&#13;
on the Process of Urbanization&#13;
An Application to India&#13;
Rakesh Mohan&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright © 1982&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development / THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
This is a working document published informally by The World Bank. To&#13;
present the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has&#13;
not been prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal&#13;
printed texts, and The World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The&#13;
publication is supplied at a token charge to defray part of the cost of&#13;
manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to The World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to&#13;
any individual acting on their behalf. Any maps used, have been prepared&#13;
solely for the convenience of the readers; the denominations used and the&#13;
boundaries shown do not imply, on the part of The World Bank and its&#13;
affiliates, any judgment on the legal status of any territory or any endorsement&#13;
or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of The World Bank publications is described in the Catalog of&#13;
World Bank Publications; the continuing research program of the Bank is outlined&#13;
in World Bank Research Program: Abstracts of Current Studies. Both booklets are&#13;
updated annually; the most recent edition of each is available without charge&#13;
from the Publications Distribution Unit of the Bank in Washington or from the&#13;
European Office of the Bank, 66, avenue d'Iena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Mohan, Rakesh, 1948-&#13;
The effect of population growth, the pattern of&#13;
demand and of technology on the process of urbanization.&#13;
(World Bank staff working paper ; no. 520 (Feb. 1982))&#13;
Based on author's thesis (Ph. D.)--Princeton&#13;
University, 1977.&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
1. Urbanization-India--Mathematical models.&#13;
2. India--Population--Mathematical models. 3. Consump-&#13;
tion (Economics)--India--Mathematical models.&#13;
4. Technological innovations--India-Mathematical&#13;
models. 5. Underdeveloped areas--Urbanization-Mathe-&#13;
matical models. I. Title. II. Series: World Bank&#13;
staff working paper ; no. 520.&#13;
11T147.I5M63  1982        307.7l6'0724        82-8600&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0008-3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ABSTRACT OF THE STUDY&#13;
This paper uses a computable economy wide dynamic general&#13;
equilibrium model to study the effect of population growth, the&#13;
pattern of demand and of technological change on urbanization in the&#13;
context of a low income developing county starting at a low level of&#13;
urbanization. The model is non-linear and models two regions (rural&#13;
and urban) with wages and prices adjusting endogenously. It represents&#13;
a closed economy and is therefore more suited to a large courntry such&#13;
as India. The model is validated using Indian data and the simulation&#13;
traces the development of the Indian economy well from 1950 to the&#13;
present. Agriculture, industry and services are the three sectors&#13;
modelled with the latter two being defined to be located exclusively&#13;
in urban areas and agriculture in rural areas. The three sec:tors are&#13;
linked with an input output matrix which subsumes transportat:ion costs&#13;
incurred between urban and rural areas. The model is designed to&#13;
investigate long term changes (e.g. over a thirty year period); factor&#13;
mobility is therefore assumed to be almost perfect. The model&#13;
demonstrates that rapid agricultural productivity growth, high rates&#13;
of investment, and Engel curve demand effects combine to increase&#13;
urbanization as development occurs in an economy. The rate of&#13;
urbanization is not necessarily dependent on high overall population&#13;
growth: indeed, under certain conditions, a lowering of overall&#13;
population growth might speed up the rate of urbanization. The pattern&#13;
of demand and changes in the pattern can affect the rate of urbanization&#13;
significantly: in particular, the Engel-type of demand changes&#13;
serve to make the process of urbanization logistic. The effects of&#13;
technological bias are not very strong but effective appropriate&#13;
technology policies might speed up urbanization.&#13;
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS&#13;
This paper has resulted from work originally done for my&#13;
Ph.D dissertation at Princeton University (Mohan, 1977). I wish&#13;
to thank my advisors Edwin S. Mills and Sherman Robinson for helpful&#13;
guidance, Kemal Dervis who provided useful comments. Financial&#13;
support for this research was provided from a grant to the Princeton&#13;
University Economics Department from the Sloan Foundation and from&#13;
the Income Distribution Project of the Research Program in Development&#13;
Studies at Princeton.&#13;
The author is an economist with the Development Research&#13;
Department of The World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
I.  INTRODUCTION:  URBANIZATION IN THE CONTEXT OF DEVELOPMENT            1&#13;
II.- A SUMMARY DESCRIPTION OF THE MODEL                                   10&#13;
III.  APPLICATION TO INDIA                                                 20&#13;
IV.  SENSITIVITY TESTS                                                    27&#13;
REFERENCES                                                           47&#13;
List of Tables&#13;
Table No.&#13;
1   Specification of DYNURB                                              12&#13;
2   National Product in Constant Prices                                  21&#13;
3   Growth Rates of National Product                                     22&#13;
4   Population of India                                                  23&#13;
5   Experiment No. 1                                                     29&#13;
6   Experiment No. 2                                                     32&#13;
7   Experiment No. 3                                                     37&#13;
8   Experiment No. 4                                                     40&#13;
9   Experiment No. 5                                                     44&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. INTRODUCTION: URBANIZATION IN THE CONTEXT OF DEVELOPMENT&#13;
It is now a commonplace observation that cities in poor countries&#13;
have grown at unprecedentedly high rates in the past two or three decades.&#13;
Some cities have grown from a population of less than a millioil people&#13;
in 1950 to about four million now.    The provision of essential services&#13;
like water, sewage, sanitation, roads and electricity for a city growing&#13;
by six or seven percent a year is no mean task. It is not surprising&#13;
then that many policy makers view the phenomenon of urbanization with a&#13;
great deal of trepidation. Policies and measures to contain urbanization&#13;
then result: as for example, the city of Jakarta was declared closed in&#13;
1970, and a system of residence permits introduced to keep people from&#13;
migrating into the city.   Other countries have tried less drastic measures&#13;
like encouraging investment in preferred areas and restricting it in&#13;
large cities. Such policies have been put into effect without a&#13;
clear understanding of the process of urbanization. We still do not&#13;
have a very good idea of the structural causes of urbanization:&#13;
economists have yet to develop specific ideas on what makes particular&#13;
economic activities characteristically urban. The phenomenon is usually&#13;
seen in a short term context and only partial explanations are generally&#13;
offerred. For example, rural/urban migration is explained by the existence&#13;
of a rural/urban wage gap; or by "push" from the country-side related to&#13;
the pattern of land holdings; or by "pull" from the cities related to&#13;
employment opportunities, bright lights, amenities of living, etc. A&#13;
proper understanding of urbanization should, however be attempted in a&#13;
long term context. What are the underlying structural cuases which create,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
these wage differentials? Why are fewer people required in farm employment&#13;
as development occurs through time? What happens to the structure of&#13;
demand which shifts the composition of goods produced to induce more&#13;
urban type activities?&#13;
Before proceeding further, a distinction must be drawn between&#13;
the growth of large cities and that of urbanization as a whole. Much of&#13;
the present concern is focused on the problems arising from the rapid growth&#13;
of large cities. This study, however, is not concerned with these problems&#13;
and views urbanization merely as the shift of people from rural to urban&#13;
areas in general. The level of urbanization is then the proportion of&#13;
urban population in total population. Its rate of growth is the growth&#13;
of this proportion. The growth rate of urban population then indicates&#13;
the growth of urbanization only when it is greater than overall population&#13;
growth. What is sought to be studied here therefore is the long-term&#13;
process in which there is a shift of people from rural habitation to urban&#13;
habitation and the structural causes thereof.&#13;
An adequate study of urbanization needs to look at the structure&#13;
of production, the patterns of demand for different commodities in urban&#13;
and rural areas and how these interact in the context of changing incomes&#13;
and technology. I attempt to do this by developing a dynamic general&#13;
equilibrium model for a large, poor developing country which is calibrated&#13;
on the post independence Indian experience. It is only an "attempt" since&#13;
the model is imperfect in that it places all industrial and service&#13;
activities in urban areas and only agriculture-related activities in rural&#13;
areas. This is obviously not strictly true but it does capture the essence&#13;
of urban and rural activities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
Urbanization has long been associated with industrialization:&#13;
indeed they have been considered synonymous. However, cities have&#13;
existed for a long time while industry has not. Many cities evolved&#13;
originally as market or trading centers which was necessary for&#13;
product markets to expand and consequently for economic growth. Thus&#13;
cities have traditionally been more known for their "service" sector&#13;
activities than for industry. Manufacturing activities in cities are of&#13;
a relatively recent vintage but these have been more associated with&#13;
urbanization in the last two centuries because of the prominence of the&#13;
industrial revolution and all its visible fruits. Indeed, in the&#13;
development of Western countries, rapid urbanization coincided with rapid&#13;
industrialization while in the early periods the proportion of employment&#13;
in the urban service sector usually declined. The situation is now&#13;
turning full circle: services now employ a larger proportion of people&#13;
than industry in the richest countries and this proportion is ;still tending&#13;
to increase. In less developed countries, services have tended to expand&#13;
as fast as industry so that the process of urbanization is a movement of&#13;
people to both industry and services from agricultural activities. The&#13;
essential ingredient for this to be possible--both in the early stages&#13;
of Western urbanization and current LDC urbanization--is a consistent&#13;
increase in agricultural productivity. What is somewhat different for&#13;
developing countries now is that as latecomers to the development process&#13;
the labour productivity in industry is also very high. It is only the&#13;
service sector that lags in productivity changes and therefore employs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
much of the incremental urban labour. It is essential, therefore, that&#13;
models of development and urbanization explicitly take account of the&#13;
service sector: a sector neglected in most of the dual economy development&#13;
models.&#13;
It is this neglect of the service sector and the association&#13;
of urbanization with industrialization (percent of labor force in induatry&#13;
or share of industrial product) that set off the debate started by&#13;
Hoselitz (1957). He asserted that many LDCs are currently "over-urbanized"&#13;
since they have smaller proportions of labor force in industry than was the&#13;
case in European countries in the last century when they were at similar&#13;
levels of urbanization. In so doing, Hoselitz implicitly asserted a linear&#13;
relationship between the levels of industrialization and urbanization.&#13;
The other consequence of his assertion was that current urbanization is&#13;
being caused more by rural push rather than urban pull. Sovani (1962)&#13;
and Kamerschen (1969) have both questioned this implication and have&#13;
found little correlation between levels of urbanization and indices of&#13;
rural push. In refuting his over-urbanization thesis, they separately&#13;
find that the levels of urbanization and industrialization are more closely&#13;
correlated in LDCs now and in rich countries in the last century, than in&#13;
rich countries now.&#13;
These studies have been valuable in providing some insights into&#13;
the related phenomena of economic development, industrialization and&#13;
urbanization but the basic assumptions of their methodology need to be&#13;
questioned. Urbanization is essentially a dynamic phenomenon. Thus, if&#13;
there is a connection between industrialization, development and urbanization,&#13;
it should ideally be studied in a dynamic framework within the context of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
one system. Doing a cross-country analysis -- as was done by Hoselitz&#13;
(1957) and Davis and-Golden (1954) -- involves the assumption that the&#13;
current cross-section of different levels of development replicates the&#13;
historical process of the system under investigation. An associated&#13;
problem with such cross-section analysis is that political entities, i.e.&#13;
nation-states are usually taken as the appropriate data points. Thus a&#13;
country as large as India is one data point as is a country as small as&#13;
Kuwait. The implicit assumption is then that nation states form self-&#13;
contained economic geographical systems. This may not be the case at all&#13;
except in large systems such as Brazil, the United States, Russia, China&#13;
and India. Such analysis would be improved if attempts were made to&#13;
group together certain sets of geographically contiguous countries which&#13;
can then more reasonably be regarded as self-contained systems. A third&#13;
problem with cross-section analysis is that linear relations of some kind&#13;
are usually posited -- particularly if linear regression analysis is used.&#13;
If, however, (a) the relationship between industrialization and urbanization&#13;
is non-linear.and (b) the trend of urbanization in a system is non-linear,&#13;
e.g. logistic, linear analysis clearly gives misleading results. Since&#13;
there is a logical limit (100 percent) to the level of urbanization,&#13;
its trend of growth is likely to be asymptotic and probably logistic like&#13;
many other growth series (Price, 1975). If this is the case, it is&#13;
not surprising that Kamerschen finds that the level of correlation between&#13;
industrialization and urbanization is low for rich countries now.&#13;
The fourth problem is a consequence-of the assumption that the&#13;
historical process can be captured by observing co-existing different levels&#13;
now. This implies that the process undergone in the last century was similar&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
to that now. That this may be erroneous and that the current LDC experience&#13;
is quite different, needs some elaboration. A primary factor is that the&#13;
overall population growth rate is much higher than ever before. The&#13;
growth rate of cities is high without migration. Technical change in&#13;
agriculture which raises farm productivity has to provide for the growing&#13;
rural population in addition to the burgeoning urban population. In times&#13;
when overall population growth rates were less than 0.5 percent, a 3 percent&#13;
growth in agricultural productivity was tremendous. The second major&#13;
difference from the European experience is the coexistence of high and&#13;
low technology in LDC cities. High population growth and technological&#13;
growth makes it possible to have cities with a multimillion population at&#13;
low levels of income. This was just not possible in the last century. The&#13;
sewage disposal, water supply and transport problems of a city of 8 million&#13;
are qualitatively different from those of a city of half a million, which&#13;
was the size of major Western cities at similar income levels. The third&#13;
major difference may be the decline in relative prices of transportation&#13;
and communication. There are, therefore, reasonable a priori expectations&#13;
that the current urbanization experience of LDCs may well be different&#13;
from the historical European experience.&#13;
The foregoing is   an attempt to show that cross-section cross-&#13;
country analyses of urbanization though valuable in themselves are not&#13;
likely to yield the causes of urbanization.&#13;
The contention of this study is that explanations of long-term&#13;
trends of urbanization and of its relationship with economic development&#13;
and industrialization will more likely be found if the performance of a&#13;
system is studied over time. The ideal way of doing this would be:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
i)   to catalogue the different sets of activities which take&#13;
place in urban and rural areas;&#13;
ii)   to investigate if there are underlying differences in the&#13;
conduct of these activities. One example of "underlying&#13;
differences" is the existence of different production&#13;
functions in urban and rural areas;&#13;
iii)   to indentify the above differences and model the production&#13;
structure of each area;&#13;
iv)   to model the demand side of the economy and devise methods&#13;
for achieving a static equilibrium (or rules for existence&#13;
of disequilibrium);&#13;
v)   to model the growth of the economy, i.e. find rules for invest-&#13;
ment, population growth, etc.;&#13;
vi)   simulate the system thus created and investigate the effects&#13;
of different assumptions on urbanization.&#13;
The implications of such a scheme need to be spelled out:&#13;
(a) Urbanization is being regarded as primarily an economic process;-/&#13;
(b) it is being seen as an integral part of the development process.&#13;
Thus the process of urbanization is seen as a result of the&#13;
interaction of a set of complex forces in a general equilibrium&#13;
(or general disequilibrium) framework.&#13;
The causes of urbanization being sought are therefore not regarded&#13;
as being simple. The answer is expected to be of the type: A, 13, C, D, E, etc.&#13;
interact together in certain constellations to produce an X level of&#13;
urbanization; rather than A produces X (e.g., rural pressures produces&#13;
urbanization).&#13;
(c) While the schema may be general enough to be applied to different&#13;
systems, it is not expected that specific levels of appropriate&#13;
urbanization can be prescribed for each level of industrialization&#13;
or development. There can, however, be notions of appropriate&#13;
levels within the context of specific systems.&#13;
1/ See B. J. L. Berry (1973) for non-economic reasons for existence of&#13;
cities in pre-industrial times.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
In the schema given above, (i) and (ii) are the most difficult&#13;
since they involve the interaction of spatial and production theory.&#13;
In this study, it is assumed that industrial and service activities&#13;
are exclusively based in urban areas and agricultural activities in rural&#13;
areas. Each activity has a different production function in accordance&#13;
with (iii) above, so a sharp distinction is made between the patterns of&#13;
urban and rural production activities.&#13;
The result of such an exercise can be summarized as follows:&#13;
An increase in agricultural productivity contributes to increases&#13;
in per capita income. In general, income elasticities of demand are&#13;
different for different goods, being low for agricultural goods and high&#13;
for industrial and service goods, i.e., high for urban type goods.&#13;
Surprisingly, in periods of rapid urbanization, the rate of technical&#13;
change of productivity change in agticulture is usually found to be higher&#13;
than in industry and services; that for services usually being the lowest.&#13;
Thus the process of urbanization is one that results from a number of&#13;
factors that operate simultaneously.&#13;
As an economy grows from low incomes, the proportion of income&#13;
necessary to buy food declines and thus demand is created for non-food&#13;
goods.   Technical change in agriculture permits labor to be released to&#13;
work in urban pursuits. The lack of technical change or productivity&#13;
growth in agriculture would slow down the rate of urbanization. It is a&#13;
moot question to say which comes first: income growth, technical change&#13;
or urbanization.    What is important to understand is that they happen,&#13;
simultaneously, one reinforcing the other. Rapid population growth is not&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
necessary for rapid urbanization.    It is a popular misconception that high&#13;
population growth rates induce urbanization, though high urban population&#13;
growth rates are obviously affected by high population growth. Indeed,&#13;
the rate of growth of urbanization can increase with zero population&#13;
growth if there is accompanying technical change in agriculture and&#13;
incomes are rising. Moreover, the provision of some urban services which&#13;
may be perceived as required for urban living may themselves induce a&#13;
higher rate of urbanization and a higher rate of income growth. It is&#13;
a characteristic of recent development experience that urban capital-labor&#13;
ratios are considerably higher than those in rural areas: thus high rates&#13;
of investment are necessary for rapid urbanization. The increase in urban&#13;
labor demand at later stages, as stated earlier, is more because of&#13;
service demand than industrial demand as the rate of productivity growth&#13;
is characteristically low in the service sector.&#13;
The difference in capital labor ratios between the urban and rural&#13;
sectors is much larger now, that is for "development latecomers", than it&#13;
was for the currently rich countries in their early stages of development.&#13;
Thus the labor-using technology in agriculture and capital-using technology&#13;
in urban areas has had the effect of slowing down urbanization in LDCs.&#13;
If technology policy in these countries succeeds in introducing the&#13;
adoption of "appropriate" technology, the rate of urbanizatiorn may well&#13;
increase. Furthermore, if such policies 'attract more labor into the&#13;
industrial sector, there would be a concomitant increase in demand for&#13;
labor from the service sector. However, the importance of these&#13;
technological bias effects is usually exaggerated and their impact on the&#13;
rate of urbanization is at best secondary.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
II. A SUMMARY DESCRIPTION OF THE MODEL&#13;
The model used in this paper was designed to study the long term&#13;
process of development and structural change which can occur in a large&#13;
relatively closed economy starting from very low levels of income using&#13;
India as the model economy. A study of urbanization is therefore a by-&#13;
product of this model. This section gives a brief description of the&#13;
model (hereafter called DYNURB) and its validation of Indian data.-1&#13;
DYNURB is a non-linear, three-sector, two-region, wage and&#13;
price endogenous dynamic general equilibrium model.    The three sectors&#13;
are agriculture, industry and services, with agriculture being exclusively&#13;
based in rural areas and the other two exclusively in urban areas.&#13;
Consumption of all three goods takes place in both regions and capital and&#13;
labour are mobile between sectors and regions. Transportation is an&#13;
intermediate good which is used whenever goods are transferred across&#13;
regions. The special features of the model include the specification of&#13;
transportation and that of a service sector. Particular attention is&#13;
paid to the specification of technical change which is seen as primarily&#13;
capital and labour augmenting. The model also allows for completely&#13;
exogenous (or "manna from heaven" type) technical change. The model&#13;
neglects international trade and can therefore be seen to depict a large&#13;
economy in which trade is unimportant.&#13;
The model in its present form is designed to reflect the Indian&#13;
economy in particular over a 30-year period starting in 1951, i.e.", the&#13;
1/ For a detailed description of the development, solution and validation&#13;
of the model see Mohan (1977).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
period after Indian independence. It is therefore seen as a long term&#13;
model. The model solves recursively over time -- it finds an equilibrium&#13;
for a period, then grows, and then again for the next period. Such a&#13;
process may be characterized as "lurching equilibrum" as aptly expressed&#13;
(though in a slightly different sense) by Adelman-Robinson (1978). It&#13;
is recognized that this does not reflect reality where the adjustment&#13;
process takes time and capital and labor are not perfectly mobile. The&#13;
justification for ignoring this is that in a long-term context, factors&#13;
may be regarded as more mobile. Thus the model is wr6ng in that it finds&#13;
an equilibrium for every period but is probably not too misleading in&#13;
showing trends over an extended period of time.&#13;
DYNURB bears the most resemblance to the work of Kelley, Williamson&#13;
and Cheetham (1972), Kelley and Williamson (1974) and is also related to&#13;
Yamaguchi (1973), on the one hand and in its computation and modelling&#13;
philosophy to Johansen (1974), Adelman and Robinson (1978), Dervis (1973)&#13;
and Fakhruddin Ahmed (1974). Table 1 gives the mathematical specification&#13;
of DYNURB. The key features to note are:&#13;
Production:  All three sectors--agriculture, industry, services- -/&#13;
have constant elasticity of substitution production functions.&#13;
The agriculture production function has four factors: land,&#13;
livestock, capital and labour. Capital and labour "combine&#13;
in a C.E.S. technology" to generate and index which is then&#13;
combined with land and livestock in a Cobb-Douglas technology.&#13;
Thus a C.E.S. function is nested in a Cobb-Douglas production&#13;
function for agriculture. The value added production structure&#13;
has an underlying inter-industry input-output structure for&#13;
intermediate goods.&#13;
1/  Sector 1, the agriculture sector, includes agriculture, forestry and&#13;
logging, fishing. Sector 2, the industry sector, includes mining&#13;
manufacturing, construction, utilities, transport and communication.&#13;
Sector 3, the service sector, includes wholesale and retail trade,&#13;
hotels and restaurants, banking and insurance, real estate, public&#13;
administration and defense.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 1: SPECIFICATION OF DYNURB&#13;
A. The Static Model (time subscripts omitted)                                                       4.  Interregional Wage and Rental Structure&#13;
1. Sectoral Production Functions (CES)                                                                        Wt 'W1                                 i - 2,3&#13;
Agriculture          Q, - LANDALPH LVSTKGA  QTBE                                                             -                                    (4 equatons)&#13;
Industry             q2 - QT2                                                                  5. Savings&#13;
Services             Q3 - QT3                                                                             YLAB1 ' YiWILi                         i - 1,2.3&#13;
i                    a         i                                YCAP - X1R1K1 + RENT . LAND + RLVSTK . LVSTK&#13;
QTi ' B£[Y,Ix£Kj     0, + (1-Yi)   lyiLi    at              i i - 1,2.3              YCAPi - XiRiKi                         i - 2,3&#13;
(n equations)                                         (income from labor and capital)&#13;
2. Net Price Equationsl/                                                                                      YSAVE - SLABi . YLABE  + SCAP   .YCAPi   i1,2,3&#13;
(income saved)                          (3n equations)&#13;
*~~~~~&#13;
t       tt     at jp j               (i - 1,2,3)                        6. Demand System&#13;
Jii&#13;
(n equations)                                YCONSi - (I-SLAB)    YLABt + (I-SCAPi) . YCAPi   i - 1,2,3&#13;
3. Factor Demand   (Return - Marginal Product)                                                               (disposable income)&#13;
Wages:               w                                        - 1,2,3                                        t      L                            i - 1,2,3&#13;
i  P%   - aL i                                                    i~~~~~~~~~~ 3PR-&#13;
Capital Rentals      R     pii     aK                       I - 1,2,3                           d     i,   [      j       k-l Pkj * FINk      POP    +          POP&#13;
i  ii~   aKi                                                                ij-                       k                 i &#13;
Land:                RENT - Pit    aLAND                                                       (demand for good i in sector j)    i - 1,2,31;  S - 1,2,3&#13;
LVSTK:               RLVSTK - P     aQi                                                        Price Equations&#13;
P£2    iP3                             i - 1,2,3&#13;
t2    p11 (1 + aT   ; Pl      (I + aT'    i- 1,2,3&#13;
(2n + 2 equations)                                                                        (4n + n2 equations)&#13;
1/ These equations are actually somewhat different in the model because a transport input-output coefficient, aT has also been included.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
7. Investment Demand                                                                               B. Dynamic Equations&#13;
DINV                 YSAVE             (1 equation)                                       1. Technical Change&#13;
p22    i-I        i&#13;
3. Factor Employment                                                                                    yi,t+l -   yit('   Xti); Xi,t+j - Xit(1 + xi2)      i=1,2,3&#13;
(factor augmentation)&#13;
3                    3&#13;
KTOT_     E   K i; LTOT .          Li                                                          Bi t+l =   Bit (+ GB)                        i - 1,2,3&#13;
(Exogenous neutral technical change)&#13;
(3n equations)&#13;
URBPOP= POP2 +   POP3; RURPOP1 -    POP1                                                  2. Growth of Labour&#13;
URBL  =   L2+    L3;    RURL = L1           (6 equations)                                      URBLt+L  = URBLT (I +   CURBt)&#13;
(regional population and labor)&#13;
9. Material Balances                                                                                    RURLt+l -   RURLt(l + GRURt)&#13;
Q   =  E D    +  EaQ                                                                           LTOTt+l -   URBLt+l +  RURL&#13;
1      i ij      1ijj                                                                             t+           +         t+1&#13;
(3 equations)&#13;
Q2     ED23 +   Za2 Q; +   DINV  +  DTRAN                                                 3. Growth of Capital, Land, Livestock&#13;
j    j   j&#13;
Q3 =   ED    +  Za 3JQ                                                                         KTOTt+L  = KTOTt +    DINVt -   6KTOTt&#13;
3    3j&#13;
DTRAN  =  Demand for transport as an intermediate product.                                      LANDt+I  =  LANDt (I +    GLANDt)&#13;
(n+l equations)                                      LVSTKt+l =   LVSTKt  (I + GLVSTK)&#13;
(3 equations)&#13;
10. Price Normalization                                                                            4. Savings&#13;
Qj&#13;
1S P         . 10;  Si =I         i -   1,2,3  (in the first period)                       SLABi t+1  -  SLABit (I +   GSLABi)&#13;
(n+l equations)                                      SCAP =t+l -   SCAPt   (1  +  GSCAP i&#13;
FMINt t+l = FMIN it(1 +    GFMINi )&#13;
(3n equations)&#13;
(The Static Model has 13 n + n2 + 15 equations. With n = 3,&#13;
this is 63 equations. With Walras' Law Operating, there is one&#13;
redundant equation. Thus the static model has 62 independent&#13;
equations.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
List of Exogenous Variables and Parameters                                                  List of Endogenous Variables&#13;
KTOT1, LTOTI             2    Initial total capital stock, labor force                      Qi,Ki,Li                     3n     Sectoral gross outputs, capital stocks,&#13;
labor force.&#13;
LAND1, LVSTKI            2    Land endowment and livestock                                  Pij                          n2     Price of commodity i in sector j.&#13;
Yi,' xii                 2n   Initial sectoral labor, capital quality                       P it                         n      Net prices&#13;
Bil                      n    Production function scaling parameter                         Wi,Ri                        2n     Sectoral Wages, Capital Rentals&#13;
Yi,ai                   2n   Sectoral capital intensity parameter and                      RENT, RLVSTK                 2      Land rent, return to livestock&#13;
elasticity of substitution&#13;
ALPH, GAM, BET           3    Share of land, livestock, and (capital + labor)               YCAP1, YLABi                 2n     Sectoral property, labor income&#13;
in agriculture&#13;
aij, aT               n2+1    input output, transport coefficients                          YSAVEi, YCONSi               2n     Sectoral savings, disposable income.&#13;
ei,,i                   2n   wage and rental differentials                                 POPi                         n      Sectoral population&#13;
SLABil, SCAPil           2n   Initial savings rate from sectoral labor and                  Dii                          n2     Demand for commodity in i in sector j&#13;
capital income&#13;
GSLABi, GSCAPi           2n   Growth rates in sectoral labor and capital                    DINV                         I      Investment demand&#13;
income savings rates&#13;
WPRi                     n    Sectoral (regional) workers participation ratio               Si                           n      Price weights&#13;
aij               n2    Marginal budget share of commodity i in sector j                   URBPOP, RURPOP               2      Urban and Rural population&#13;
FMINi                    n    Minimum subsistence levels                                    URBL, RURL                   2      Urban and Rural labor&#13;
Ail,lAi2                2n   Labor and capital augmenting rates                            DTRAN                        1      Transport demand&#13;
GBi                      n    Neutral technical change rates                                These are 12n and 2n2 + 8 = 62 endogeneous variables which&#13;
equal the number of independent equations in the static model.&#13;
GURB, GRUR               2    Natural growth rates of urban and rural labor&#13;
6                       1    Rate of capital depreciation&#13;
GLAND, GLVSK,            2    Rate of land, LVSTK increase&#13;
GFMIN1                   n    Rate of increase in FMINi&#13;
Thus there are 17n + 2n2 + 13 - 82 numbers required to run a simulation&#13;
of DYNURB: a relatively small data set.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
Technical change:   The C.E.S. structure allows for the most flexible&#13;
framework for modeling technical change.    Factor augmenting&#13;
technical change is allowed at different rates in different&#13;
sectors (i.e. each of Xij can be different) along with differing&#13;
rates of exogenous neutral technical change (of the "manna from&#13;
heaven" type). Thus what are really freely mobile and homogenous&#13;
between sectors are efficiency units of factors. The implication&#13;
is that when a person moves from a rural to urban area he&#13;
acquires all the characteristics of the urban area, i.e. more&#13;
efficiency units. The same holds true for capital.&#13;
Transport:   An input-output coefficient, aT, is added to the normal&#13;
input-output structure to regard transport as an intermediate&#13;
output. Thus whenever a commodity is transferred from one region&#13;
to another, it is deemed to incur intermediate transport costs.&#13;
Thus, when the agriculture sector uses 1 unit of good 2 (industrial&#13;
good) as an intermediate good, it also used aT units of transport.&#13;
Since, in DYNURB, transport is always produced by the industry&#13;
sector, this additional demand is always produced in sector 2.&#13;
The net price equations then become non-linear in aij and aT&#13;
and are highly "irregular" in structure.&#13;
Factor Demand and Inter-Region Wage Structure: The returns to factors&#13;
are equal to their marginal value products. Thus facto-rs are&#13;
demanded until their marginal products equal their wages or&#13;
rentals. An inter-region wage structure is maintained: urban&#13;
wages are higher than rural wages but efficiency units are still&#13;
regarded as homogeneous. Thus a person earns more in an urban&#13;
area than in a rural area (a) because efficiency units earn more&#13;
and (b) because he "embodies" more efficiency units in the urban&#13;
area. The justification for this inconsistency is as follows:&#13;
In such an aggregated model what we call "labour" is really an&#13;
index of labour inputs of different levels of skills and education&#13;
levels. We can suppose that, in general, only higher quality&#13;
members of the labour force move to the urban area. These members&#13;
possess higher than average efficiency units in the agriculture&#13;
sector. Thus it can be consistently maintained that efficiency&#13;
units of a factor are homogenous as well as perfectly mobile&#13;
and are augmented at different rates in different sectors.&#13;
The appropriate equalizing (within the given wage structure&#13;
outlined next) is then for the returns to the efficiency units of&#13;
the factors.  Thus, if it is sought to equalize   wages across&#13;
all sectors what is equalized is the wage per efficiency unit.&#13;
The wage per person, or augmented unit, may well be different.&#13;
This interpretation therefore conveniently maintains factor&#13;
homogeneity and mobility along with different rates of technical&#13;
change.in factor quality. However, even this difference does not&#13;
account for the total urban/rural wage differences obse-rved. There&#13;
is ample evidence that urban and rural earnings differ for the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
same skill and that there is no tendency for this gap to&#13;
be closed. Reasons for this are not entirely clear but&#13;
among them are the different costs of living, under-&#13;
utilization of skills in rural areas due to deficiency&#13;
demands and differences in skill and education mix within&#13;
the same professional or craft category. Whatever the reasons&#13;
are, an -inter-region v#age structure is imposed to approximate&#13;
reality.&#13;
Savings: DYNURB allows for different savings rates out of labour and&#13;
capital income as well as different rates in each sector.&#13;
Houthakker (1965) and Bhalla (1978) provide evidence for different&#13;
savings rates from different sources of income and Panikar&#13;
(1970) and NCAER (1965) for different sectoral savings rates.&#13;
Thus the savings function is only partially Kaldorian in that&#13;
everyone saves but at different rates. Savings rates grow&#13;
with time as in a developing economy.&#13;
Demand System: The Stone Linear Expenditure System is used but&#13;
savings are deemed to occur first, then committed expenditures&#13;
are made (for subsistence requirements) and then discretionary&#13;
expenditures. Ideally, committed expenditures should be made&#13;
before savings but this form has been used here for practical&#13;
computational convenience. In using this function, distinction&#13;
is made between the labour force and population not usually&#13;
made in such models: only people active in the labour force&#13;
work but the whole population consumes. One property of the&#13;
Stone system is that individual demand functions aggregate&#13;
perfectly if all individuals have the same utility function.&#13;
In DYNURB consumers in each of the 2 regions, urban and rural,&#13;
are identical so aggregation can be done within regions but&#13;
not across regions.   The Stone system is particularly appropriate&#13;
for modelling low income economies since we can interpret the&#13;
committed expenditures (FMINi) as subsistence requirements. It&#13;
can be shown 1/ that if only food is a subsistence requirement&#13;
(i.e. FMIN1 &gt; 0, FMIN2 = FMIN3 = 0) then the income elasticity&#13;
of demand for food is less than unity and that for other goods&#13;
is greater than unity. Thus the Stone system captures Engel&#13;
demand effects well and is particularly suited for modelling a&#13;
low income developing economy. Furthermore, the system is price&#13;
responsive, the own price elasticity being -1 if the good is not&#13;
a subsistence good and smaller in magnitude (appropriately) if&#13;
it is a subsistence good.&#13;
Population Growth:  DYNURB has exogenously different natural rates-of&#13;
population growth in urban and rural areas. Thus, because of&#13;
migration, total population growth is partially exogenous.&#13;
1/ See Mohan (1977), pp. 83-85 for the derivation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-17 -&#13;
Model Solution&#13;
DYNURB is therefore, though a relatively small mode]L, quite&#13;
complex and has a high degree of closure. Because of this, DYNURB faces&#13;
one solution problem not faced by other models in the same genre.    Both&#13;
wages and capital rentals being endogenous, both capital and labour&#13;
allocations have to be determined simultaneously. Other models usually&#13;
fix either wages exogenously or capital allocations. Here,with constant&#13;
returns to scale production functions the long run supply curve is&#13;
flat. Thus, if one sector is more profitable at one level of production,&#13;
it is so at all levels. If one attempts to find equilibrium wages and&#13;
rental simultaneously, there is a tendency for all resources to shift&#13;
to the most profitable sector. One resource therefore has to be made&#13;
"less mobile" -- in this case capital -- to be able to find the solution.&#13;
Figure 1 illustrates the solution process. A set ofE initial&#13;
prices are assumed along with a set of labour and capital allocations&#13;
by sector. Total labour and capital stocks are fixed for the period.&#13;
The labour market is then solved for market clearing wages as if capital&#13;
allocations were fixed. Given resulting factor incomes, product demands&#13;
are calculated along with intermediate demands and investment. Excess&#13;
demand equations are formed and prices changed in response. The labour&#13;
market is then solved again followed by the product market until a set&#13;
of market clearing wages and product prices are found - all the while&#13;
acting as if capital allocations were fixed. It is only then that an&#13;
excess demand capital equation is formed and capital rentals changed&#13;
accordingly resulting in a revised allocation of capital.    This allocation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-18-&#13;
-iue1:-  The Solution of DYNURB&#13;
Ki tLi t Pi&#13;
_ &gt; Net Prices&#13;
-    Outputs &#13;
| Wages               &gt;&gt;,&#13;
.L demands(4 &#13;
Laor  Make&#13;
|K Rentals     F&#13;
( L2)                        I&#13;
Demand&#13;
System&#13;
4    Prodct M, rket&gt;&#13;
-            | ~~~~Prices    l&#13;
.      ~~Solution :To Next Period&#13;
K Rentals. &#13;
3) &#13;
I I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
is then treated as fixed and the whole process repeated until a final&#13;
solution is reached in all markets: the labour market, the goods&#13;
markets and the capital market are all in equilibrium and give a set&#13;
of solution wages, rentals and prices. Associated with these are&#13;
sectoral capital and labour allocations and outputs. Thus the model&#13;
essentially solves 5 markets: the markets for labour and capital and&#13;
the markets for the 3 goods. The efficiency labour and capital are&#13;
homogeneous and have a given intersectoral wage structure. Each is&#13;
therefore regarded as an economy-wide market. The solution technique&#13;
can be regarded as simulating a market economy: capital is "less mobile"&#13;
than labour and prices adjust in response to excess demands. As mentioned&#13;
earlier, if labour and capital are made equally mobile, i.e., solved&#13;
simultaneously, the constant returns to scale nature of the production&#13;
function shifts all production to one sector. Capital is therefore&#13;
"artificially" fixed for the solution of the labour and goods markets.&#13;
As shown in Table 1, the number of equations in DYNURB is&#13;
equal to the number of endogenous variables in the static model. This&#13;
provides assurance that a solution is feasible. With neoclassical&#13;
production functions and the demand system used, it is reasonable to expect&#13;
that a unique solution exists for the model. This study does not&#13;
investigate the existence properties of the model, nor its stiability&#13;
properties any further. However, given that there is more than one&#13;
consumer, the theoretical probability of non-uniqueness exists.&#13;
Practically, it is likely that the solution is, indeed, unique since&#13;
various initial conditions were found to lead to the same solution.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
III. APPLICATION TO INDIA&#13;
DYNURB was tuned to approximate the Indian economy in 1950.&#13;
Parameter values were selected, as far as possible, from existing studies&#13;
6n India so that they were close approximations to actual estimates. Some&#13;
(e.g. the elasticity of substitution in agriculture) were mere guesses&#13;
if no estimates existed. In addition intial values had to be chosen&#13;
for variables such as total factor stocks to start off the simulation.&#13;
This section presents selected results from the base simulation (hereafter&#13;
called the BASRUN) which is regarded as tracking the Indian economy&#13;
quite well.&#13;
Table 2 shows the result of the BASRUN along with actual values&#13;
for India for the growth in total output. The two sets of series are&#13;
in remarkably close agreement considering the many unrealistic assumptions&#13;
incorporated in DYNURB. The income lags somewhat towards the end of the&#13;
period. This is probably because&#13;
i)   population growth tends to slow down in DYNURB with&#13;
increasing urbanization;&#13;
ii)   the last year for which data is shown, 1974-75, was the third&#13;
of a succession of bad years in India.&#13;
Table 3 shows the BASRUN growth rates of gross national product&#13;
along with those for per capita national product. The feature toy note&#13;
is the acceleration of growth rates. The DYNURB economy grows faster and&#13;
faster with the passage of time. Estimates for growth in GNP in different&#13;
period for India are given below:&#13;
1949 to 1955         2.92%&#13;
1954 to 1961         3.63%&#13;
1961 to 1967         3.61%&#13;
1949 to 1969         3.41%&#13;
1954 to 1969         3.62%&#13;
(Dholakia, p. 20)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
Table 2: NATIONAL PRODUCT IN CONSTANT PRICES&#13;
(Index, 1951 = 100)&#13;
BASRUN                    ACTJAL&#13;
Year                   GNP      Per Capita      GNP      Per Capita&#13;
1           2             3          4&#13;
1951                  100          100          100         100&#13;
1954                  110.7        104.5        114         107&#13;
1957                  122.7        109.4        124         110&#13;
1960                  136.4        114.8        134         112&#13;
1963                  151.7        120.7        151         118&#13;
1966                  169.1        127.1        166         121&#13;
1969                  188.5        133.9        184         129&#13;
1972                  210.5        141.2        210         137&#13;
1975                  235.5        149.2        217         136&#13;
1978                  263.5        157.6&#13;
1981                  295.0        166.7&#13;
1984                  330.5        176.5&#13;
SOURCES:  Cols. (1), (2)   BASRUN Simulation.&#13;
Cols. (3), (4)  Dholakia (1974), Government of India&#13;
(1976), M. Mukherjee (1969).&#13;
NOTES: (1) The simulation results are in constant 1951 prices.&#13;
(2)  The "Actual" data are in 1948-49 prices for the&#13;
years 1951 to 1966, while later years are in&#13;
1961 prices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
Table 3: GROWTH RATES OF NATIONAL PRODUCT&#13;
(percent per year)&#13;
Year                         Growth Rates&#13;
From 1951 to:                 GNP      Per Capita&#13;
1954                      3.45        1.49&#13;
1957                      3.48        1.52&#13;
1960                      3.51        1.55&#13;
1963                      3.54        1.58&#13;
1966                      3.56        1.61&#13;
1969                      3,59        1.63&#13;
1972                      3.61        1.66&#13;
1975                      3.63        1.68&#13;
1978                      3.65        1.70&#13;
1981                      3.67        1.72&#13;
1984                      3.69        1.74&#13;
SOURCE: BASRUN Simulations.&#13;
DYNURB's success in tracking the Indian development record over&#13;
25 years gives reason to believe that the structure of the model is plausible&#13;
and that the parameters used are well founded even though they were not&#13;
systematically estimated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
Correspondence between these estimates and the BASRUN is good. The average&#13;
for the later-years, 1969-75, however, is not as high as suggested by DYNURB.&#13;
This is partly because of unusually adverse weather conditions during&#13;
1972 to 1975.&#13;
Table 4 shows the population of India as estimated in DYNURB&#13;
as compared with the actual data.&#13;
Table 4: POPULATION OF INDIA&#13;
(in millions)&#13;
Year                BASRUN           Actual a/&#13;
1                 2&#13;
1951                 362              361&#13;
1961                 430              439&#13;
1966                 482              485&#13;
1971                 540              548&#13;
1974                 571              577&#13;
1981                 640              695 b/&#13;
1984                 678&#13;
Source: (1) BASRUN, Table A.8&#13;
(2) a/ Up to 1974, Government of&#13;
India (1979), p. 2 (taken&#13;
from the Indian Census).&#13;
b/ 1981, Bose (1973), p. 423,&#13;
estimate.&#13;
That population is estimated well by DYNURB is not very surprising because&#13;
the urban and rural natural population growth rates are exogenously specified.&#13;
The only endogeneity is caused by rural/urban movement and therefore the&#13;
model is also tracking that movement well.&#13;
The definition of urbanization places all labour that works in&#13;
industry and services in the urban region even if some of the activities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
are actually located in the rural region. Thus, while the actual level&#13;
of urbanization in India was 17.3 percent in 1951, and 19.9 percent&#13;
in 1971, in the BASRUN the levels were 26.7 percent and about 32 percent&#13;
for the two years respectively. The levels were are not comparable but&#13;
the trends are:&#13;
Growth Rate of Urban Population&#13;
BASRUN                   Actual&#13;
1951-61       2.96                      2.64&#13;
1951-71       2.84                      2.96&#13;
It is clear therefore that DYNURB models the trend of&#13;
urbanization well. A model such as this can then give a benchmark&#13;
against which we can measure the rate of a country's urbanization. If&#13;
the structure of such a model ia regarded as sound then the rate of&#13;
urbanization given by simulation can be regarded as the trend that&#13;
"ought" to exist in the modelled economy. If the rate of urbanization&#13;
is faster in the actual economy it is then, perhaps, justified in calling&#13;
it over-urbanized. Recall, however, that DYNURB assumes full employment:&#13;
thus a higher rate of urbanization in the actual economy accompanied&#13;
by rising urban unemployment would be a good index of over-urbanization&#13;
This is, in principle, better than an internationally derived norm from&#13;
cross sector data. An improvement of DYNURB which could allocate some&#13;
industry and service employment to rural areas would give better answers&#13;
to the appropriate level of urbanization as a country develops over time.&#13;
The model was further validated by examining the sectoral&#13;
distribution of output and factor stocks as they changed over time in the&#13;
30 year simulation of DYNURB. These distributions compared well with actual&#13;
data giving further confidence in the structure of DYNURB.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
In summary, therefore, the simulation shows that the transfer&#13;
of labour from rural to urban areas is as much to service sector occupations&#13;
as to industrial occupations. Thus it is essential to study structural&#13;
change in at least a 3-sector context as distinguished from the usual&#13;
2-sectors. As evidenced from the demand coefficients used in the&#13;
simulation, the demand for services is particularly significant in urban&#13;
areas and its neglect, therefore, would miss one of the most important&#13;
components of structural change in a growing economy. Other key results&#13;
from the simulation include confidence in the modelling of technical&#13;
change.  Its essential ingredients are:&#13;
(i) A labour-saving bias in urban areas along with a aapital&#13;
saving one in rural areas.&#13;
(ii) A higher rate of technical change in agriculture compared&#13;
with the other two sectors. This is essential to provide&#13;
enough food for the increasing population and for the&#13;
increasing urban, i.e., non-rural based demand.&#13;
(iii) Capital and labour augmentation account completely for&#13;
technical change in the urban based sectors but&#13;
"unexplained" change is necessary in the agricultural&#13;
sector.&#13;
The BASRUN also shows that even with a "respectable" savings&#13;
and investment rate a very low income economy like the one simulated&#13;
has difficulty achieving very high rates of growth: particularly per&#13;
capita growth when population growth rates are high. This is partly&#13;
caused by the large proportion of consumption expenditures being required&#13;
for food subsistence purposes. Thus, as population grows, much of the&#13;
investment has to be directed towards agriculture to keep food production&#13;
in line with population growth. Correspondingly, the pace of structural&#13;
change, i.e. urbanization and industrialization is slow,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
Cause and effect are characteristically difficult to separate&#13;
in a general equilibrium model. The next section provides a better&#13;
idea of some of the underlying causes of structural change through the&#13;
use of sensitivity tests of the model, now that its plausibility has&#13;
been demonstrated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
IV. SENSITIVITY TESTS&#13;
Cause and effect are characteristically difficult to disentangle&#13;
in a general equilibrium model -- even when it is a relatively small one&#13;
such as DYNURB. Moreover, as has been pointed out, though small in size,&#13;
DYNURE has a high degree of closure and hence the relationships among&#13;
its parts are complex. Analytical results are virtually impossible.&#13;
So sensitivity tests have to be used to obtain a better understanding&#13;
of the workings of the model and, by inference, of the economy it represents.&#13;
Drawing strong conclusions from the results of sensitivity tests on a&#13;
simulation model is, however, hazardous. It is not easy to distinguish&#13;
results caused by technical quirks in a model from those that are&#13;
consequences of the structure of the economy.&#13;
A large number of tests were conducted, each of which involved&#13;
a change in one of the parameters. In this paper I investigate the effects&#13;
of different rates of population growth, of changes in the pattern of demand&#13;
and of the role of different kinds of technology on the process of&#13;
urbanization. In so doing one also obtains a number of insights into the&#13;
development process, but I concentrate on urbanization here. One general&#13;
result worth reporting is that the dynamic general equilibrium system&#13;
incorporated in DYNURB behaves much like a buffalo -- as does the Indian&#13;
economy! Exogenous shocks, i.e. changes in parameter values, do not make&#13;
radical differences in the growth path of the economy -- even when these&#13;
changes are of a substantial magnitude. A shock in one component produces&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
ripples across the economy and equilibrating forces are set in motion&#13;
dampening the long run impact. This is what should be expected from a&#13;
general equilibrium system with an unchanging structure.&#13;
Population Growth&#13;
The experience of extremely high rates of urbanization in LDCs&#13;
in recent decades has partly been attributed to high population growth&#13;
rates. Thus, tests are conducted here to judge the quantitative&#13;
effects of different rates of population growth. A range of tests was&#13;
performed with small changes in the growth rates (GURB and GRUR) and&#13;
with large changes. Tables 5 and 6 report the extreme results: those&#13;
with zero population growth and with a growth rate of 2.5 percent per&#13;
year. The latter is high by Indian standards though Latin American&#13;
population growth rates are characteristically in the region of 3 percent.&#13;
The most interesting result is that with zero population growth,&#13;
(ZPG), urbanization proceeds at a more rapid rate as shown in Table 5.&#13;
In 33 years, the level of urbanization is about 42 percent as opposed&#13;
to 35 percent in the BASRUN. The reasons are not difficult to find.&#13;
With ZPG, the growth of per capita income is greater and with the income&#13;
elasticity of demand for food being less than unity, the shift in consumption&#13;
patterns toward urban goods is correspondingly faster. This shift would&#13;
be even more significant if another demand system was used in which all&#13;
income elasticities did not approach unity in the long run.-/ The&#13;
absence of the additional demand for food from increased population and&#13;
a faster shift to urban goods produces an increased demand for urban labour&#13;
1/ This distortion is not critical at low levels of income where subsistence&#13;
requirements are still substantial.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
Table 5: EXPERIMENT No. 1&#13;
Zero Population Growth    GURB = GRUR = 0.0 (NEWRN)&#13;
(See Notes Below)         GURB = 0.017, GRUR = 0.020 (BASRUN)&#13;
1951     1963     1972     1984&#13;
1.  GNP Per Capita Growth         BASRUN     -        1.58     1.66     1.74&#13;
Rate (% per year)           NEWRN      -        2.39     2.40     2.41&#13;
2.  Level (% Urban)               BASRUN    26.73    30.04    32.25    35.01&#13;
NEWRN     26.73     33.01    37.01    41.74&#13;
(% Difference)                                    9.87    14.74    19.23&#13;
3.  Growth Rate of                BASRUN              0.98     0.90     0.82&#13;
Urbanization                NEWRN               1.77     1.56     1.36&#13;
(% Difference)                                   81.25    73.73    65.61&#13;
4.  Growth Rate of                BASRUN              2.92     2.84     2.76&#13;
Urban Population            NEWRN               1.80     1.59     1.39&#13;
Notes on Tables on Sensitivity Tests&#13;
Results of experiments are reported in the same format&#13;
for each case.&#13;
1. BASRUN - The value of the variable in the BASRUN which tracked&#13;
Indian economy well.&#13;
2. NEWRN - The results of simulation with the change in parameter&#13;
as noted above the table.&#13;
3.  Percentage Difference - Percentage change in variable at time&#13;
t as compared with-value in the BASRUN.&#13;
4.  Growth Rate of Urbanization:   This is the growth rate of the&#13;
urbanization level, i.e., the growth rate of the share&#13;
or urbanization.&#13;
5. Growth Rate of Urban Population: This is the growth rate of&#13;
total population in urban areas.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
and consequently increasingly higher levels of urbanization. This result&#13;
depends on the assumed rates of technical change which permit labour to&#13;
be released from agricultural production. To the extent that agricultural&#13;
terms of trade tend to deteriorate, it would be reasonable to expect an&#13;
induced effect on the rate of innovation in agriculture. Indeed, the&#13;
rate of technical change could slow down, thus requiring more labour&#13;
in agriculture and consequently resulting in a slower urbanization rate.&#13;
To predict such changes, a more sophisticated theory of technical change&#13;
is required which, alas, DYNURB does not incorporate. Here only&#13;
different possibilities can be investigated.&#13;
Although the rate of urbanization is increased significantly&#13;
the rate of growth of urban population obviously declines. The important&#13;
point, however, is that these growth rates are significant (line 4, Table 5),&#13;
even with the extreme assumption of ZPG. With more reasonable assumptions,&#13;
i.e., natural population growth rates of between 1 to 2 percent per year,&#13;
the rate of growth of urban population is in the range of 2.0 to 2.5&#13;
percent per year as compared with about 2.8 percent in the BASRUN.      The&#13;
lesson then is that a decrease in the natural growth of population will&#13;
not remove urbanization problems in LDCs.      The six to seven percent&#13;
urban population growth rates characteristic of some Latin American&#13;
countries would only decline to 4 to 5 percent if the natural population&#13;
growth decreased to about 1.5 percent from the current 3.0 percent:a year.&#13;
These results are very important because they demonstrate that&#13;
the decline in birth rates (or population growth) is not going to solve&#13;
the urbanization problem and that we can expect cities to grow along with&#13;
the development process. This is already being observed in Latin America&#13;
where population growth rates have declined drastically in recent years&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
from about 3.0 percent to about 1.5 to 2.0 percent a year. Cities are indeed&#13;
continuing to grow at rates of 4 to 5 percent per year instead of the&#13;
earlier 6 to 7 percent.    The early Japanese development experience&#13;
in the Meiji era was somewhat similar to this characterization.&#13;
Agricultural productivity had increased but the growth rate of population&#13;
was low. Consequently, a relatively small increase in agricultural&#13;
productivity did result in significant income changes and high rates of&#13;
urbanization.&#13;
It is worth delving further into the simulation resuLts to&#13;
understand the mechanism of DYNURB which produces these results. The&#13;
most dramatic result in the ZPG simulation is the reversal in the terms&#13;
of trade making urban goods more expensive. This has a dampening effect&#13;
on the demand for urban goods including capital goods. The proportion&#13;
of net investment to GNP declines: the economy indogenously adjusts&#13;
for a slower populatin growth rate. The converse happens with an increase&#13;
in population-growth: the proportion of investment increases, thereby&#13;
mitigating somewhat the negative effect on per capita incomes. Note,&#13;
however, that the change in investment decreases in later years and&#13;
would probably equal the BASRUN in a long enough simulation in both&#13;
cases. The economy therefore has built in stabilizing influences over&#13;
the long run which can only be captured by a general equilibrium model.&#13;
To the extent that these influences tend toward a dynamic equilibrium,&#13;
the implication is that policy choices may not make a substantial&#13;
difference over a long period, but do over a period like 5-15 years.&#13;
Put another way, policy choices can determine the path taken by an economy&#13;
to reach an objective but perhaps not the objective itself.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
Table 6: EXPERIMENT No. 2&#13;
High Population Growth: GURB = GRUR = 0.025 (NEWRN)&#13;
(BASRUN  GURB = 0.017   GRUR = 0.020)&#13;
1951      1963      1972       1984&#13;
1. GNP Per Capita Growth       BASRUN                1.58      1.66      1.74&#13;
Rate (% per Year)          NEWRN                  1.34      1.43      1.52&#13;
2. Level (% Urban)            BASRUN     26.73      30.04     32.25     35.01&#13;
NEWRN     26.73       29.14     30.88     32.74&#13;
(% Difference)                         -         -3.00     -4.25     -6.50&#13;
3. Growth Rate of              BASRUN      -         0.98      0.90      0.82&#13;
Urbanization                NEWRN       -         0.72      0.69       0.62&#13;
(% Difference)                                  -26.18    -23.20    -24.98&#13;
4. Growth Rate of Urban        BASRUN      -         2.92      2.84       2.76&#13;
Population                  NEWRN       -         3.23      3.20       3.12&#13;
As should be expected with ZPG, wages increase substantially, K&#13;
rentals decline and therefore the wage rental ratio increases with a&#13;
corresponding increase in the overall capital labour ratio. Since the&#13;
elasticity of substitution between capital and labour is 1.2 in&#13;
agriculture, capital is substituted for labour to a larger extent in&#13;
that sector and the labour share consequently declines despite a&#13;
substantial rise in wages. The implication is that if the elasticity&#13;
of substitution in the two urban sectors was higher than the assumed&#13;
0.6 and 0.8, more capital would be employed, demand for labour would&#13;
decline and wages would tend to decrease. (Some of these effects are&#13;
investigated later in experiments with the elasticities of substitution).&#13;
When population growth rates are low, low elasticities of substitution&#13;
aLe better for labour!&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
The opposite result holds for high population growth. Higher&#13;
elasticities of substitution in the urban sectors would increase the&#13;
demand for labour, cause higher wages and a higher urbanization rate.&#13;
Those who call for "appropriate technologies" and a better allocation&#13;
of factors in the interest of employment generation in the context of&#13;
high populationgrowth, should be aware that higher urbanization rates&#13;
will be one of the results of such policies. This result is not&#13;
dependent on the assumption of full employment. It would be the same&#13;
even if unemployment is allowed and migration behaviour conforms with&#13;
the Harris-Todaro (1970) hypothesis or one of its variants.&#13;
The share of the service sector in total output increases more&#13;
than that of industry. Thus labour absorption in urban areas is more&#13;
due to service sector expansion. A model not including the service&#13;
sector would not have this detail and would therefore show a slower rate of&#13;
labour absorption. It is the neglect of the service sector or its&#13;
perception as a sponge that lead to fears of widespread urban unemployment&#13;
along with high urbanization growth rates. The explicit inclusion of the&#13;
service sector in DYNURB is therefore once again shown to be illuminating&#13;
a crucial aspect of development and urbanization. Recall the the relatively&#13;
faster growth in the demand for service goods is determined in DYNURB by&#13;
specification of the demand parameters.   The conclusions drawn above&#13;
therefore depend on the validity of the numerical magnitudes used.   These&#13;
have already been justified, hence these conclusions must be deemend&#13;
to be valid.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
The last result of ZPG worth noting is that the increase in&#13;
the growth of per capita income is not striking and that the difference&#13;
relative to the BASRUN declines over time. The implication is that,&#13;
ceteris paribus, over a long enough period, a high population growth&#13;
rate does not necessarily mean a smaller growth in per capita income.&#13;
This is partly because endogenous adjustments induce a higher investment&#13;
rate. What is true, though, is that per capita income is increased&#13;
with lower population growth in the short run and it is likely that&#13;
such increases cause other structural changes which make the growth&#13;
self sustaining.&#13;
This last point is worth emphasizing in the modelling context.&#13;
In any structural model like DYNURB the basic structure of the economy is&#13;
assumed to be stable over the long run. In reality, a short run&#13;
large increase in per capita income can cause a snowball effect which&#13;
then makes growth self-sustaining. The foreign sector is not modelled&#13;
at all in DYNURB. One of the usual effects of high per capita income&#13;
growth for a few years is a major improvement in a country's rating&#13;
in credit markets and the resulting large inflow of foreign investment&#13;
and credit. Such may have been the case for Korea where large U.S. aid&#13;
programs in earlier years resulted in income increases in those years and&#13;
were then followed by self sustaining accelerated growth along with&#13;
a substantial flow of foreign credit. DYNURB is clearly not equipped&#13;
to deal with such systemic responses to a changing situation. Nevertheless,&#13;
it serves to show that the rate of populatioh growth, while undoubtedly&#13;
important, as a dampening influence in a country's growth path may not&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
be as important as is sometimes made out. Moreover, those who are&#13;
concerned with the problem of rapid urbanization should realize that&#13;
a slow down in population growth will not solve their problems.&#13;
The experiments on population growth do not allow for&#13;
differential growth rates between population and labour. The participation&#13;
rate is assumed to be constant though different for urban and rural&#13;
areas. A richer demographic sub-model would allow the modelling of&#13;
changes in age structure over time -- in particular, the lag between&#13;
population growth and labour force growth.&#13;
Changes in Demand Patterns&#13;
Discussions of development and urbanization are typically&#13;
supply oriented. Thus, a large amount of attention is paid to the&#13;
possibilities of increasing efficiency in production, to inappropriate&#13;
choice of techniques, to the rate of population growth and so on.&#13;
It is usually assumed that Say's Law holds in low income countries, i.e.,&#13;
that whatever is supplied will be consumed and that the important&#13;
constraints are to do with supply. Phenomena such as the "embarrassment&#13;
of riches" associated with the recent bumper harvests in India indicate that&#13;
demand constraints may be as important. Thus the effects of changes&#13;
in demand patterns are investigated with some care in this study.&#13;
Two sets of experiments are reported. One set reports the effects&#13;
associated with changes in marginal budget shares (a ijs) and the other,&#13;
those associated with changes in perceptions of subsistence requirements.&#13;
Recalling the derivation of the Stone demand system from its&#13;
associated utility functions, it is fair to say that the set of experiments&#13;
with changing marginal budget shares is really investigating the effects&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
of changing consumer tastes. It is somewhat surprising when viewed in&#13;
this manner, that growth rates of real income can be affected by a mere change&#13;
in preferences.&#13;
Table 7 reports the effects of an increased preference for food&#13;
in urban areas. Another experiment simulated an increased preference for&#13;
urban goods in rural areas. The results of one experiment are the converse&#13;
of the other.  Thus, only the results of Experiment   3 are discussed.&#13;
As a result of the shift in urban demand in favour of food and&#13;
away from urban goods (the experiment performed makes the urban demand&#13;
pattern identical to the rural pattern), the level of urbanization decreases&#13;
in the initial year and continues to decrease relative to the BASRUN in&#13;
later years. The growth rate of urbanization decreases as well. Thus a&#13;
change in preferences produces a comparative static result which tends to persist&#13;
over time. In the BASRUN simulation it was assumed, in conformance with&#13;
the Indian consumption pattern, that people in rural areas tend to consume&#13;
more food than service goods as compared with the people in urban areas.&#13;
In this experiement therefore we are merely testing what happens if&#13;
everyone had rural preferences, i.e. the rural demand pattern prevails&#13;
everywhere.   The shift in demand towards agriculture increases the share of&#13;
agriculture in total product and resources shift to that sector accordingly.&#13;
Given that agriculture is a less productive sector (in the sense that an&#13;
equivalent amount of resources produce less value added&gt; the level of&#13;
GNP decreases in the initial year and continues to decrease relative to the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
Table 7: EXPERIMENT NO. 3&#13;
Increase in Urban Demand for Food l/&#13;
1951      1963      1972       1984&#13;
1.  GNP Per Capita Growth   BASRUN       -         1.58      1.66      1.74&#13;
Rate (% per year)     NEWRN        -         1.53      1.60      1.68&#13;
2.  Level (% Urban)         BASRUN      26.73     30.04     32.25     35.01&#13;
(% Difference)                    -11.60     -12.12    -11.92    -12.30&#13;
3.  Growth Rate of           BASRUN      -         0.98      0.90      0.82&#13;
Urbanization          NEWRN        -         0.93      0.88      0.80&#13;
(% Difference)                                -5.10     -1.68     -2.97&#13;
4.  Growth Rate of           BASRUN      -         2.92      2.84      2.76&#13;
Urban Population       NEWRN        -         2.87      2.83      2.74&#13;
Note 1:  Demand coefficients in the urban sector are made equal to those in&#13;
rural sector, i.e.,&#13;
Ag. Goods:      0 11     012  =  013  -  0.4.    (0.25)&#13;
Ind. Goods:     021  -  022  -   023  8  0.25    (0.20)&#13;
Serv. Goods:    031  -   032  -  033  -  0.35    (0.55)&#13;
(BiJ is the budget share of good i for a consumer in sector j)&#13;
Figures in parentheses are the BASRUN Urban Sector demand&#13;
coefficients.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
BASRUN levels in later years. The economy wide growth rate is lower.&#13;
Since urban based income decreases, and because urban savings rates&#13;
are higher than rural rates, the level of total investment in the&#13;
economy declines.&#13;
It is found, therefore, that a shift in urban consumer tastes&#13;
toward food has important effects on levels of income in the short as well&#13;
as over the long run. What are the effects of the converse case: when&#13;
rural preferences shift toward urban goods and larger marginal budget shares&#13;
are spent on these goods.     Such a change induces a faster growth rate&#13;
of income and higher urbanization levels. 29.2 percent of the&#13;
population in the intial period is urbanized as compared with 26.7 percent&#13;
in the BASRUN. Such a difference persists over 20 years and is therefore&#13;
a non-trivial effect.&#13;
The effects discussed above are to be distinguished from Engel&#13;
effects which are only due to different income elasticities of demand for&#13;
urban goods ( &gt;1), and for agricultural goods ( &lt;1). The increased prefer-&#13;
ence for urban goods stimulates a further structural change which could&#13;
appear with rising income causing a shift away from rural goods. A better&#13;
experiment would be to make the as variable over time so that the shift&#13;
away from agricultural goods takes place along with rising income. The&#13;
results indicate that the effects of such a structural change would be to&#13;
reinforce Engel effects and to induce a progressively higher rate of&#13;
growth of income and of urbanization.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
Subsistence Requirements&#13;
It is assumed in the simulation of DYNURB that consumers regard&#13;
only food as a subsistence good and that this is some absolute nutritional&#13;
minimum which remains the same over time. The next set of experiments&#13;
investigates the effects of changes in the perception of consumers as to&#13;
what constitutes subsistence goods. It is sometimes argued that sub-&#13;
sistence requirements rise over time along increases in income. Experi-&#13;
ment 4 investigates the consequences of such a shift in requirements, so&#13;
that FMIN (1), the amount of food required to subsist, increases at a&#13;
rate of 1.5 percent per year. Other experiments were conducted with a&#13;
once and for all increment or decrease in FMIN (1). Their results were&#13;
consistent with those reported from Experiment 5.&#13;
The effects on the level and rate of urbanization are dramatic.&#13;
The economy begins to ruralize! In 1984 the level of urbanization de--&#13;
clines to 24.2 percent of population from 26.7 percent in 1951. The&#13;
BASRUN level in 1984 is 35.0 percent. The growth rate of urban popula-&#13;
tion is still positive though only 1.60 percent per year. The increased&#13;
demand for food tends to shift resources to the agriculture sector where&#13;
there is a higher preference for food as compared with urban goods.&#13;
This serves to reinforce the effect and the economy begins to ruralize.&#13;
All these results should be expected but what is surprising is the&#13;
magnitude of the effect. The per capita income growth rate declines&#13;
from about 1.75 percent to 1.5 percent. The share of agriculture is&#13;
12.3 percent higher in 1984 than was the case in the BASRUN. The magnitude&#13;
of these effects is important if this experiment is considered in the&#13;
context of a nutrition or food subsidy program being designed in a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
Table 8: EXPERIMENT NO. 4&#13;
GROWTH IN SUBSISTENCE FOOD REQUIREMENTS&#13;
GFMINI      0.015 NEWRN&#13;
GFMIN1      0.0   BASRUN&#13;
1951     1963     1972     1984&#13;
1.   GNP per Capita              BASRUN      -        1.58     1.66     1.74&#13;
Growth Rate (% per year)    NEWRN       -        1.41     1.46     1.51&#13;
2.   Level (% Urban)             BASRUN    26.73    30.04     32.25    35.01&#13;
NEWRN     26.73    25.65    13.99     24.24&#13;
(% Difference)                        0     -14.63   -22.52   -30.77&#13;
3.   Growth Rate of Urbaniza-    BASRUN      -        0.98     0.90     0.82&#13;
tion                        NEWRN       -      -0.34     -0.32    -0.30&#13;
(% Difference)                        -      -135     -136      -136&#13;
4.   Growth Rate of Urban        BASRUN       -       2.92     2.84     2.76&#13;
Population                  NEWRN       -        1.56     1.60     1.62&#13;
1/ GFMIN1 is the growth rate in minimum food requirement FMIN      The BASRUN&#13;
had assumed that subsistence requirements remain constan .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
relatively closed economy. Where such a programme is being financed from&#13;
tax revenues, it can approximately be interpreted as increasing the food&#13;
subsistence requirement since taxes paid by consumers may be regarded as&#13;
increased allocated price-insensitive expenditures on food. Note that the&#13;
increase in food requirements is set at only 1.5 percent per year.&#13;
A converse experiment was also performed (but not reported here&#13;
in detail) where urban goods were also included in the subsistence bundle.&#13;
It is often argued that urban dwellers have minimum needs in terms of&#13;
urban infrastructure and housing such that they have a higher proportion&#13;
of allocated relatively price-insensitive expenditures. The mere provision&#13;
of necessary urban services such as roads, water supply, sewerage, etc. may&#13;
be regarded as constituting such expenditures if they are financed through&#13;
tax revenues. This is simulated in DYNURB by including both the urban goods&#13;
in the subsistence bundle (i.e., FMIN2 and FMIN3 &gt; 0).   The result is inter-&#13;
esting:  since there is now higher "forced" consumption of urban goods,&#13;
resources shift to urban areas leading to a substantial increase in the&#13;
level of urbanization, GNP and per capita income in the initial period.&#13;
Income continues to grow somewhat faster though the effect is alternated&#13;
in the long run. The growth rate of urban population declines somewhat&#13;
since it now starts from a higher base. The conclusion is therefore a&#13;
surprising one. The provision of some minimum level of urban goods and&#13;
services produces an increase in income levels as well as growth rates&#13;
along with a higher level of urbanization. Such provisions should there-&#13;
fore not be assumed to be a drain on the economy. Urban infrastructure&#13;
investments are, apart from their other justifications, therefore "product-&#13;
ive" in their own right in that they induce higher levels of incomes in the&#13;
economy through their multiplier effects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
The overall conclusion from the demand experiments is that demand&#13;
patterns matter and that changes which occur along with increases in income&#13;
and development can have reinforcing effects that accelerate the development&#13;
process. These results are consistent with the findings of Kelley, et. al.&#13;
(1972). Nutrition and food subsidy programmes can have some surprisingly&#13;
strong deleterious effects on growth while the provision of urban goods and&#13;
services as subsistence goods may have beneficial effects..&#13;
Technical Change: The Relevance of the Elasticity of Substitution and Appro-&#13;
priate Technology.&#13;
There is a widespread belief that the technology used in urban areas&#13;
in LDCs is, in some sense, inappropriate. It is argued that the factor pro-&#13;
portions used do not reflect prevailing factor prices well: in particular,&#13;
industry is 'too capital intensive.' A large amount of literature is&#13;
developed on the question of 'employment generation.' It is argued that the&#13;
use of appropriate technology would make processes more labour intensive&#13;
and therefore help in solving the problem of urban employment. The question&#13;
of appropriate technology is really a debate on the existing value of the&#13;
elasticity of substitution. If the value is unity, there is then little&#13;
justification in the argument that factor proportions do not respond to&#13;
changes in factor prices. Thus a set of experiments was done with different&#13;
elasticities of substitution. These experiments also tested the sensitivity&#13;
of DYNURB to these technology parameter assumptions since, to some extent,&#13;
the production function parameters were the least well informed -- especially&#13;
for the service sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
Various experiments were conducted but only one is reported here&#13;
where all the elasticities of substitution are set at unity and all the&#13;
production functions become Cobb Douglas functions. (In the BASRUN the&#13;
elasticity of substitution between labour and capital was set at 0.6 for&#13;
industry, 0.8 for services and 1.2 for agriculture). One general result&#13;
from the experiments is that the economy gains in efficiency the nearer&#13;
each elasticity moves toward unity.&#13;
Experiment 5 (Table 9) shows the effects of what might be char-&#13;
acterized as appropriate technology. The assumption of all Cobb-Douglas&#13;
production functions amounts to a technology which responds tc, changes in&#13;
factor prices perfectly. The technology experiments show that: any other&#13;
elasticities induce efficiency losses. The striking result is that it is&#13;
not too different from the results which had Cobb-Douglas technology in&#13;
agriculture only. The main difference is that K rentals increase, which&#13;
implies that capital is being used more efficiently. That labour share&#13;
declines significantly in the urban sector by the end of the simulation&#13;
period. This result is somewhat reminiscent of a wage equalization experi-&#13;
ment where higher efficiency and income growth were accompanied by income&#13;
losses to urban labour and a higher rate of urban labour absorption.&#13;
The conclusions from this set of experiments are:&#13;
e The choice of technique or elasticity of substitution&#13;
matters. However, the effects of choices within a&#13;
reasonable range do not appear to be significant enough&#13;
to warrant the large amount of literature devotedl to the&#13;
labour absorption issue.&#13;
* Efficiency losses do occur the further a is from unity.&#13;
"Smooth" production functions induce efficiency.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
Table 9: EXPERIMENT NO. 5&#13;
All Production Functions: Cobb-Douglas 1/&#13;
a   = 1.0   a   = 1.0    a = 1.0    NEWRN&#13;
1           2            3&#13;
o   = 1.2   a   = 0.6    a = 0.8    BASRUN&#13;
1           2            3&#13;
1951     1963     1972      1984&#13;
1.  GNP Per Capita Growth         BASRUN     -        1.58     1.66      1.74&#13;
Rate (% per year)           NEWRN      -        1.80     1.92      1.99&#13;
2.  Level (% Urban)               BASRUN    26.73    30.04    32.25     35.01&#13;
NEWRN     26.74     31.20    33.82    36.53&#13;
(% Difference)                           0.04     3.85     4.87     4.35&#13;
3.  Growth Rate of                BASRUN     -        0.98     0.90      0.82&#13;
Urbanization                NEWRN      -        1.29     1.13      0.95&#13;
(% Difference)                                   32.24    25.22    15.69&#13;
4.  Growth Rate of Urban          BASRUN     -        2.92      2.84     2.76&#13;
Population                  NEWRN      -        3.25      3.07     2.89&#13;
Note 1.  B , the production function scaling parameters are adjusted to&#13;
euate g.n.p. in the initial period between BASRUN and NEWRN.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
o The choice of appropriate technology is associated with&#13;
significant efficiency gains but not necessarily with&#13;
employment generation. Indeed, low elasticities of&#13;
substitution may be generating higher employment as well&#13;
as wages. Capital owners may gain relatively more as a&#13;
result of better utilization of capital!&#13;
o  The rate of urbanization increases with appropriate tech-&#13;
nology. This is mostly because of the labour released&#13;
from the agriculture sector where that labour using sector's&#13;
elasticity of substitution is reduced from 1.2 to 1.0.&#13;
Factor Augmentation, Bias and Technical Change.&#13;
Further sets of experiments were conducted to investigate the&#13;
effects of different types of technical change in the pace of urbanization.&#13;
The quantitative results are not reported here but may be found in Mohan&#13;
(1977)-/.  The BASRUN assumed a large neutral exogenous technical change in&#13;
agriculture since no reasonable rates of factor augmentation prcduce the&#13;
observed rate of total factor productivity change in agriculture. Such a&#13;
neutral change is also probably appropriate for a green revolution type phenom-&#13;
enon in agriculture. The key result is that a decline in this neutral technical&#13;
change produces a very large decrease E the rate of urbanization.   Essentially,&#13;
a smaller rate of increase in income mitigates the Engel type demand effects&#13;
and there is therefore a smaller demand for urban type goods and consequently&#13;
for urban labour. The best prescription for containing urbanization is&#13;
therefore stagnating agriculture' An improvement in rural cond:Ltions is&#13;
therefore not likely to result in slower rates of urbanization as supposed&#13;
by some. When the bias of technical change is reversed, that iE; the rate of&#13;
capital augmentation is made uniformly greater than that of labour, demand for&#13;
labour increases in the two urban sectors and therefore the level and rate of&#13;
1/ See pp. 261-269.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
urbanization increases. Industry and services now have a labour using bias&#13;
while agriculture has a capital using bias.&#13;
In conclusion it is clear that the rate of urbanization does depend&#13;
on the nature of technical change. Neutral technical change in agriculture&#13;
produces a greater shift to urban areas than technical change which has a&#13;
labour using bias. The reversal of bias in the technology, where the urban&#13;
sectors become labour using, also increases the rate of urbanization as&#13;
expected. The effect is small in magnitude relative to the rather significant&#13;
change in the nature of technology that uses it. In general, greater effi-&#13;
ciency and labour use generating technology changes induce a higher rate of&#13;
urbanization.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
Adelman, Irma and Robinson, Sherman. Income Distribution Policy in&#13;
Developing Countries: A Case Study of Korea, Stanford, California,&#13;
Stanford University Press (1978).&#13;
Ahmed, Fakhruddin. Migration and Employment in a Multi-Sector Model --&#13;
An Application to Bangladesh, Princeton University, unpublished Ph.D&#13;
Dissertation 1974.&#13;
Berry, Brian, J.L. The Human Consequences of Urbanization. New York:&#13;
St. Martin's Press (1973).&#13;
Bhalla, Surjit, S. "The Role of Sources of Income and Investment&#13;
Opportunities in Rural Savings",    Journal of Development Economics&#13;
Vol. 5, No. 3 (September 1978).&#13;
Bose, Ashish.  Studies in India's Urbanization - 1901-1971.   New Delhi:&#13;
McGray Hill, 1973.&#13;
Davis, Kingsley and Golden, H.H. "Urbanization and the Development of Pre-&#13;
Industrial Areas", Economic Development and Cultural Change Vol. 3,&#13;
No. 1 (October 1054), pp. 6-24.&#13;
Dervis, Kemal. Substitution, Employment and Intertemporal Equilibrium&#13;
in a Non-Linear Multi-Sector Planning Model for Turkey, Princeton&#13;
University: Unpublished Ph.D. Dissertation (1973).&#13;
Dholakia, Bakul H. The Sources of Economic Growth in India, Baroda.&#13;
Good Companions (1974).&#13;
Govt. of India (G.O.I.). Central Statistical Organization. National&#13;
Accounts Statistics: 1960-61 - 1973-74, New Delhi (1976).&#13;
Harris, J.E. and Todaro, M.P. "Migration, Unemployment and Development:&#13;
A Two-Sector Analysis", American Economic Review, Vol. 60 (March&#13;
1970), pp. 126-142.&#13;
Hoselitz, Bert F. "Urbanization and Economic Growth in Asia", Economic&#13;
Development and Cultural Change, Vol. 5 (October 1957), pp. 42-54.&#13;
Houthakker, H.S. "On Some Determinants of Saving in Developed and Under-&#13;
developed Countries", in E.A.G. Robinson (1965).&#13;
Johansen, Leif. Production Functions: An Integration of Micro and Macro&#13;
Short-Run and Long-Run Aspects, Amsterdam: North Holland (1972).&#13;
. A Multi-Sectoral Study of Economic Growth, Amsterdam:&#13;
North Holland (1974).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
Kamerschen, David R. "Further Analysis of Over-urbanization", Economic&#13;
Development and Cultural Change, Vol. 17 (January 1969), pp. 235-253.&#13;
Kelley, Allen C. and Williamson, Jeffrey, G. Lessons from Japanese&#13;
Development:. An Analytical Economic History, Chicago: University of&#13;
Chicago Press (1974).&#13;
Kelley, A.C., Williamson, J.G. and Cheetham, R.J. Dualistic Economic Devel-&#13;
opment Theory and History, Chicago: Univ. of Chicago Press (1972).&#13;
Mohan, Rakesh. Development, Structural Change and Urbanization: Explora-&#13;
tions within Dynamic Three-Sector General Equilibrium Model Applied&#13;
to India, Princeton University: Unpublished Ph.D. Dissertation (1977).&#13;
. "Contribution of Research and Extension to Productivity&#13;
Change in Indian Agriculture", Economic and Political Weekly,&#13;
Vol. 9 (September 28, 1974) A-97-104.&#13;
Mukherjee, M. National Income of India: Trends and Structure, Calcutta.&#13;
Statistical Publishing House (1969).&#13;
National Council for Applied Economic Research. Savings in India, New&#13;
Delhi, India (1965).&#13;
National Council for Applied Economic Research. All India Consumer&#13;
Expenditure Survey, Vol. II, New Delhi, India (1967).&#13;
Panikar, P.G.K. Rural Savings in India, Bombay 1970.&#13;
Price, Derek de Solla. Science Since Babylon, New Haven: Yale University&#13;
Press (1975).&#13;
Robinson, E.A.G. Problems in Economic Development, New York, St. Martin's&#13;
Press (1965).&#13;
Sovani, N.V. "The Analysis of Overurbanization", Economic Development&#13;
and Cultural Change, Vol. 12 (January 1962), pp. 216-222.&#13;
Yamaguchi, Mitoshi. Technical Change and Population Growth in the Economic&#13;
Development of Japan, University of Minnesota: Unpublished Ph.D.&#13;
Dissertation (1973).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
W    rlId Bank                      Oxford University Press, 1981. 192  ing maps, appendixes, bibliography,&#13;
World   Bank                     pages (including index, appendixes).  index).&#13;
Puiblications                      LC 81-3999. ISBN 0-19-520264-3,     LC 80-8023. ISBN 0-8018-2499-0,&#13;
$16.95 hardcover, ISBN 0-19-520265-1,  $32.50 (S20.75) hardcover;&#13;
of Related                         $7.95 paperback.                    ISBN 0-8018-2498-2, $9.50 (f6.75)&#13;
Interest                           Also available In Korean from the   paperback.&#13;
Korea Research Institute for Human&#13;
Settlements.                        Costs aind Scale of&#13;
Bus Services&#13;
The Transformation of               A. A. Wailters&#13;
Urban Shelter: Upgrading            World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
the Housing Stock in                325. April 1.979. iv + 49 pages&#13;
Cartagena, Colombia                 (including 3 annexes, references).&#13;
W. Paul Strassmann                  Stock No. WP-0325. $3.00.&#13;
In urban development It is now&#13;
often considered more practical and  Economic Forces Underly-&#13;
CiisinteDveoigefficient to upgrade the existing  Ing Urban Decentralization&#13;
Cites in the Develop ing            housing stock than to replace it with&#13;
Wowrld: Policies for Their          new construction. Housing transfor-  Trends: A Structural Model&#13;
Equiitable and Efficient            mation should not only be expected  for Density Gradients&#13;
Growth                              and tolerated, but should even be  Applied to Korea&#13;
Johannes F Linn                     fostered as a means to increase    J. R. Follain, Bertrand Renaud,&#13;
production in an important feld, to  and Gill-Chin Lim&#13;
Delineates the major policy issues  generate employment and to&#13;
that arise in the efforts to adapt to  improve equity in the distribution of  World Bank Reprint Series: Number&#13;
the growth of cities in developing  housing. This study shows how the  107. Reprinted from Environment and&#13;
couritries and discusses policies   housing stock in Cartagena was      Planning A 11 (1979):541-551.&#13;
designed to increase the efficiency  upgraded during the 1970s by&#13;
and equity of urban development.    owner-occupants and, to a lesser   Stock No. RP-0107. Free of charge.&#13;
Particular areas covered include    extent by landlords. The principal&#13;
urban employment income             conclusions are supported by exten-  Housing&#13;
redis;tribution through the fiscal  sive econometric tests and by&#13;
system, transport, housing, and    interviews with local experts and   Reviews the importance of housing&#13;
social services. The policy instru-  authorities                       dvthin the framework of urban&#13;
ments considered include public                                        development problems, and makes&#13;
inve ;tment pricing, taxation,      The Johns Hopkins University Press,  recommendations for World Bank&#13;
and regulation.                     May 1982. About 224 pages.         assistance in integrated urban&#13;
Oxfo,-d University Press, June 1982.  LC 81-48176. ISBN 0-8018-2805-8,  planning.&#13;
About 352 pages (including bibliog-  $22.50 hardcover.                  Sector Policy Paper. May 1975.&#13;
raphy. index).                                                         75 pages (including 13 annexes).&#13;
ISBN 0-19-520382-8, $27.50 hardcover;  Urban and Spatial               English, French, Spanish, and Arabic.&#13;
ISBN 0-19-520383-6, $12.50 paper-   Development in Mexico              Stock Nos. PP-7506-E, PP-7506-F,&#13;
back.                               Ian Scott                          PP-7506-S, PP-7506-A. $5.00.&#13;
Examines urbanization in a country&#13;
in which that process has been      llousing; for Low-Income&#13;
National Urbanization Policy        particularly rapid and in which such  Urban Famiies: Economics&#13;
In lieveloping Countries            issues as provision of Jobs, shelter,&#13;
Bertrand M. Renaud                  public services, and mass transit are  and Policy in the&#13;
urgent. Also considers issues that  Developing World&#13;
Natic nal urbanization policies In  arise because of the size and form of  Orville E Grimes, Jr.&#13;
deve loping countries often attempt  the system of large cities and the&#13;
withoiut a full understanding of the  linkages between them: centraliza-  Analyzes thte operation of urban&#13;
forces at work to block the growth of  tion, rural-urban Integration, and pat-  housing markets in developing coun-&#13;
thelirgst itesand to induce     trsoIteegoadvlpmnt,                 tries to determine the kinds of dwell-&#13;
the  rgest cities anomuceterns of Interregional toeopme               ings affordable by the urban poor.&#13;
deceritralization. This book takes a  The study is relevant to other coun-&#13;
critical look at such policies and their  tries in which similar problems will  The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
weak conceptual foundations and     undoubtedly become increasingly     1976. 190 pages (including statistical&#13;
desciibes problems inherent in      urgent.                             appendix, select bibliography, Index).&#13;
Implementation. The coverage Is&#13;
comlprehensive, and both global and  The Johns Hopkins University Press,  LC 76-4934. ISBN 0-8018-1853-2,&#13;
national trends are analyzed.       April 1982. About 320 pages (Includ-  $18.50 (.£950) hardcover;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Transportation&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
The Economics of Road                 Reappraisal of a Road&#13;
User Charges                          Project in Iran&#13;
A. A. Walters                         Herman G. van der Tak and&#13;
Marginal cost pricing and consumer   Jan de Weille&#13;
surplus criteria for investment       The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
decisions.                 ~~~~~1969. 142 pages (including&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press,  2 annexes).&#13;
1968; 3rd printing, 1978.             LC 68-57489. ISBN 0-8018-1030-2,&#13;
xiii + 243 pages.                     $5.00 (f.3.00) paperback.&#13;
LC 68-8702. ISBN 0-8018-0653-4,&#13;
$7.50 (&amp;4.50) paperback.              Road User Charges in&#13;
Central America&#13;
Anthony Churchill&#13;
Engineering Economics of              The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
the Maintenance of Earth              1972. 188 pages (including&#13;
The Road Maintenance                 and Gravel Roads                      bibliography).&#13;
Problem    and International         Asif Faiz and                         LC 70-187219. ISBN 0-8018-1334-4,&#13;
Assistance .                          Edgardo Staffini                     $6.00 (f3.50) paperback.&#13;
Examines the road maintenance        World Bank Reprint Series: Number     Sector and Project Planning&#13;
problem in developing countries and  120. Reprinted from Transportation    in Transportation&#13;
describes the Bank's experience in    Research Record 702 (August          Hans A. Adler&#13;
this field.                          1979):260-268.&#13;
December 1981. 71 pages.             Stock No. RP-0120. Free of charge.    The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
Stock No. PP-8102. $5.00.                                                  1967; 3rd printing, 1973. 88 pages&#13;
(including annex, bibliography).&#13;
LC 67-28574. ISBN 0-8018-0009-9,&#13;
Book Review of "Advances              Identiflcation and Appraisal         $5.00 (£3.00) paperback.&#13;
in Maritime Economics'                of Rural Roads Projects&#13;
A. A. Walters                         Henri L. Beenhakker and              Urban Transport&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Number    Abderraouf Chammari                   Attempts to analyze the long-term&#13;
110. Reprinted from Journal of Political  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   implications of alternative urban&#13;
Economy 87 (June 1979):656-659.       362. October 1979. 74 pages (includ-  in the context eogfies alnd investments&#13;
Stock No. RP-0110. Free of charge.    ing annex).                          growth in developing countries.&#13;
Stock No. WP-0362. $5.00.             Sector Policy Paper. May 1975.&#13;
The Economic Analysis of                                                   103 pages (including 7 annexes).&#13;
Rural Road Projects                                                        English, French, and Spanish.&#13;
Curt Carnemark                        Port Pricing and Investment          Stock Nos. PP-7504-E, PP-7504-F,&#13;
Jaime Biderman, and                   Policy for Developing                PP-7504-S. $5.00.&#13;
David B3ovet                          Countries&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    Esra Bennathan and&#13;
241. August 1976. 92 pages (including  A. A. Walters&#13;
annexes, tables). English and French.  Principles of cost-based prices that&#13;
Stock Nos. WP-0241-E, WP.-0241-F.     can be used to plan port tariffs and&#13;
$5.00.                                practical ways of introducing tariff&#13;
schedules to improve the alloca-&#13;
tion of resources and financial&#13;
Economics of a Unified                performance.&#13;
Transportation Trust Fund             Oxford Uniuersity Press, 1979.&#13;
Gabriel Roth                          245 pages (including glossary,&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Number     bibliography, index).&#13;
145. Reprinted from Transportation    LC 78-26143. ISBN 0-19-520092-6,&#13;
Research Record 731 (1979):49-54.     $27.50 hardcover; ISBN 0-19-520093-4,&#13;
Stock No. RP-0145. Free of charge.    $12.50 paperback.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
ISBN 0-8018-1854-0, $8.95 (£3.50)     Sites and Services Projects&#13;
paperback.                            A World Bank Paper. April 1974. 47&#13;
Spanish: Vivienda para familias urbanas  pages (including annex). English,&#13;
de bajos ingresos: aspectos econ6micos  French, and Spanish.&#13;
y de politica en el mundo en desa-    Stock Nos. PP-7401-E, PP-7401-F,&#13;
rrollo. Editorial Tecnos, 1978.       PP-7401-S. $5.00.&#13;
ISBN 84-309-0778-5, 480 pesetas.&#13;
Urban Economic and Plan-&#13;
Ownership and Efficiency              ning Models: Assessing the&#13;
in Urban Buses                        Potential for Cities in&#13;
Charles Feibel and                    Developing Countries&#13;
A. A. Walters                         Rakesh Mohan&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    Applies current urban modeling&#13;
371. February 1980. 19 pages (includ-  techniques to cities in developing&#13;
ing selected bibliography).           countries. Problems intrinsic to the&#13;
Stock No. WP-0371. $3.00.             modeling of all urban areas are&#13;
considered along with those particu-&#13;
The People of Bogota: Who             lar to cities in poor countries.&#13;
They Are, What They Earn,             The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
Where They Live                       1979. 192 pages (including bibliogra-&#13;
Rakesh Mohan                          phy, author index).&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    LC 78-8437. ISBN 0-8018-2141-X,&#13;
390. May 1980. 153 pages (including 2  $7.50 (.5.25) paperback.&#13;
appendixes, bibliography).            Urban Growth and&#13;
Stock No. WP-0390. $5.00.             Economic Development&#13;
Pirate Subdivisions and the           In the Sahel&#13;
Market for Residential Lots           Michael A. Cohen and others&#13;
in Bogota                             World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Alan Carroll                          315. January 1979. 120 pages (includ-&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    ing bibliography, 3 statistical annexes,&#13;
435. October 1980. 116 pages (includ-  map).&#13;
ing 2 appendixes, tables, references).  Stock No. WP-0315. $5.00.&#13;
Stock No. WP-0435. $5.00.&#13;
Resource Allocation to&#13;
Housing Investment: Com-&#13;
ments and Further Results&#13;
Bertrand M. Renaud&#13;
The Demand for Housing in&#13;
Developing Countries: The&#13;
Case of Korea&#13;
Bertrand M. Renaud with&#13;
James Follain and&#13;
Gill-Chin Lim&#13;
Determinants of Home&#13;
Ownership in a Developing&#13;
Economy: The Case&#13;
of Korea&#13;
Bertrand M. Renaud with&#13;
Gill-Chin Lim and&#13;
James Follain&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Plumber&#13;
183. Reprinted from Economic Develop-&#13;
ment and Cultural Change, vol. 28, no.&#13;
2 (January 1980):389-399.&#13;
C#--L- N- OD n7 O X F- -Dof rh-It&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters:&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                                                                                      U&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK&#13;
Cable address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
European Office:&#13;
66, avenue d'lena&#13;
75116 Paris, France&#13;
Telephone: 723.54.21&#13;
Telex: 842-620628&#13;
Tokyo Office:&#13;
Kokusai Building&#13;
1-1, Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telephone: 214-5001&#13;
Telex: 781-26838&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0008-3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554929">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1982/02/1554929/effects-population-growth-pattern-demand-technology-process-urbanization-application-india
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1982/02/1554929/effects-population-growth-pattern-demand-technology-process-urbanization-application-india</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1982/02/1554929/effects-population-growth-pattern-demand-technology-process-urbanization-application-india</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/07/09/000178830_98101903413282/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/07/09/000178830_98101903413282/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1982-02-28T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2002-07-19T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The effects of population growth, of the
            pattern of demand, and of technology on the process of
            urbanization : an application to India
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper uses a computable economy
            wide dynamic general equilibrium model to study the effect
            of population growth, the pattern of demand and of
            technological change on urbanization in the context of a low
            income developing country starting at a low level of
            urbanization. The model is non-linear and models two regions
            (rural and urban) with wages and prices adjusting
            endogenously. It represents a closed economy and is
            therefore more suited to a large country such as India. The
            model is validated using Indian data and the simulation
            traces the development of the Indian economy well from 1950
            to the present. Agriculture, industry and services are the
            three sectors modelled with the latter two being defined to
            be located exclusively in urban areas and agriculture in
            rural areas. The three sectors are linked with an input
            output matrix which subsumes transportation costs incurred
            between urban and rural areas. The model is designed to
            investigate long term changes (e.g. over a thirty year
            period); factor mobility is therefore assumed to be almost
            perfect. The model demonstrates that rapid agricultural
            productivity growth high rates of investment, and Engel
            curve demand effects combine to increase urbanization as
            development occurs in an economy.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The effects of population growth, of the
            pattern of demand, and of technology on the process of
            urbanization : an application to India
        </docna>
        <display_title>The effects of population growth,
            of the pattern of demand, and of technology on the process
            of urbanization : an application to India</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1982/02/1554929/effects-population-growth-pattern-demand-technology-process-urbanization-application-india</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Municipal Financial Management,Governance Indicators</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>India</count>
        <authors>
            <author>MOHAN, R.</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903413282</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>UY</subsc>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 520</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Urban Development</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Agricultural productivity; Agriculture;
            Demand; Industrialization; Industry; Models; Population
            increase; Rural-urban relations; Sector studies;
            Technological change; Urban development; Urbanization
            affiliates,Agriculture,appropriate
            technology,closed economy,constant returns to
            scale,consumers,depreciation,disequilibrium,disposable
            income,dual economy,economic development,economic
            growth,economic
            process,economists,elasticities,elasticity,elasticity of
            substitution,employment,Endogenous Variables,Engel
            curve,equations,equilibrium,Excess demand,Exogenous
            Variables,expenditures,Factor
            Demand,fishing,forestry,general equilibrium model,GNP,GNP
            Per Capita,gross national product,growth rate,Growth
            Rates,income,Income Distribution,income elasticity,income
            elasticity of demand,income growth,income
            levels,industrialization,insurance,intermediate
            goods,international trade,labor force,large cities,LDCs,less
            developed countries,logging,Marginal Product,marginal
            products,marginal value,market economy,Mathematical
            models,migration,per capita income,policy makers,population
            growth,price elasticity,product markets,production
            function,production functions,productivity,productivity
            growth,rapid industrialization,regression
            analysis,Savings,savings rates,sewage,static
            equilibrium,structural change,supply curve,technological
            change,total output,transport,urban
            services,urbanization,utility function,value added,wage
            differentials,wages,water supply
        </keywd>
        <owner>SAR</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP520</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technological Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock and Animal Husbandry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technology Transfer and Diffusion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Animal Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>India</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>