<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Infant and Child Mortality as a Determinant&#13;
of Fertility&#13;
The Policy Implications   SVV P 556&#13;
Susan H. Cochrane&#13;
K. C. Zachariah&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 556&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Her&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 556 &#13;
Infant and Child Mortality as a Determinant&#13;
of Fertility&#13;
The Policy Implications&#13;
Susan H. Cochrane&#13;
K. C. Zachariah&#13;
C '. 2 4&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright © 1983&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development / THE WVORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States ol America&#13;
First printing February 1983&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To&#13;
present the results of research with t ie least possible delay, the typescript has&#13;
not been prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal&#13;
printed texts, and the World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The&#13;
publication is supplied at a token charge to defray part of the cost of&#13;
manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to&#13;
any individual acting on their behalf. Any maps used have been prepared&#13;
solely for the convenience of the reaclers; the denominations used and the&#13;
boundanes shown do not imply, on the part of the World Bank and its affiliates,&#13;
any judgment on the legal status of a iy territory or any endorsement or&#13;
acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications is described in the Catalog of World&#13;
Bank Publications; the continuing research program of the Bank is outlined in&#13;
World Bank Research Program. Abstracts of Current Studies. Both booklets are&#13;
updated annually, the most recent edition of each is available without charge&#13;
from the Publications Distribution Urit of the Bank in Washington or from the&#13;
European Office of the Bank, 66, avenue d'Iena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Susan H. Cochrane is a senior economist and X.C Zachariah a senior&#13;
demographer in the Population, Health, and Nutrition Department of the World&#13;
Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication IData&#13;
Cochrane, Susan Hill, 1943-&#13;
Infant and child mortality as a deteminant of&#13;
fertility.&#13;
(World Bank staff workl.ng pap@z      no. 556)&#13;
Paper presented at the UK Expert Group 1Aeeting on&#13;
Fertility held in Delhi, In1dia on Jan0 5-I.Ll    1983.&#13;
Bibliographyg pO&#13;
1  Fe ertility, Human   2. laftans-l   ortality.&#13;
3. Children-Mortality.      I. Zachzrisi0 K0 C0 (Kunmi-&#13;
paramxpil Cur-iea), 1924-         TX U0  I  paerT Group&#13;
Meeting on Fertility (1983 S Delhi, Indai)       Ill  Title.&#13;
IV. Serieso&#13;
EB90iLC58   1983        312'.o          83A.a105&#13;
ISBK O.8213-0147-0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Abstract&#13;
The availability of World Fertility Survey data on 25&#13;
developing countries has allowed us to estimate the effect of infant and&#13;
child mortality on the number of births in two ways.          First, it is&#13;
possible to estimate the effect of an infant/child death on the period&#13;
between births.     For women who breastfeed their children,      an infant&#13;
death tends to shorten her period of infertility following a birth and&#13;
thus, in the absence of contraception, reduce the interval between&#13;
births. This has the effect of increasing the number of births over her&#13;
reproductive life.    While the results vary by the technique used, our&#13;
best estimates show that in this way the prevention of one infant death&#13;
averts between .016 births in Trinidad and .351 births in Lesotho with&#13;
an average of .23 for neonatal and .17 for post-neonatal deaths.        This&#13;
represents the lower limit of the effect of an infant/child death.&#13;
The total effect of infant/child mortality on number of&#13;
birthsdepends not only on biological effects through breastfeeding, but&#13;
on behavioral   adjustments through the use of contraception.        Thus a&#13;
second method of estimating the effect is to measure the number of&#13;
subsequent births a couple has depending on the survival or death of&#13;
their first few births.    This technique is likely to capture both the&#13;
biological and behavioral effects of infant/child mortality.       Our best&#13;
estimates show that couples with an infant death have between .138 more&#13;
births in Sri Lanka and .808 more births in Syria with an average of&#13;
.484 more births than those who do not experience such a death.       These&#13;
represent the upper limit on the effect of an infant/child death.&#13;
These effects are larger on average than those reported from&#13;
earlier studies but far smaller than would be necessary for mortality&#13;
declines to be fully compensated by averted births.     There may, however,&#13;
exist externalities or societal changes operating over the long run in&#13;
response to community levels of mortality which cannot be estimated with&#13;
data on individuals and their own mortality and fertility experiences.&#13;
In an illustrative analysis presented in this paper, the cost&#13;
of averting a birth through a family planning program is compared with&#13;
the cost of averting a birth indirectly by preventing an infant death.&#13;
In the 16 countries for which estimates could be made, there was one&#13;
case where mortality reduction was more "cost effective" for reducing&#13;
fertility than was family planning.      This was the case of Kenya.      If&#13;
data were available for other high mortality African countries, we may&#13;
well find the Kenya case replicated.      Thus this illustrative analysis&#13;
suggests that infant mortality may be an important component of a&#13;
fertility reduction program in countries where mortality is high and few&#13;
couples are able to have the number of surviving children they desire.&#13;
Acknowledgements&#13;
We would like to thank V. C. Chidambaram, Judith Rattenbury and John&#13;
Steele of WFS and Kalpana Mehra, Sulekha Patel, Virginia Ocampo and&#13;
Donald Brown of the Bank for their invaluable assistance in various&#13;
stages of the preparation of the paper.      We'd also like to thank Shea&#13;
Rutstein of WFS and Michel Jancloes, H.J. Park, and Timothy King of the&#13;
Bank for their helpful comments in the revision of this paper.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
INTRODUCTION                                                        1&#13;
Unanswered Policy Questions                                      2&#13;
THE CHANNELS:  THEORY AND MEASUREMENT                                4&#13;
The Biological Effects                                           5&#13;
Infant and Child Mortality Experience on Contraceptive Use     12&#13;
The Effect of Infant and Child Mortality on Parity             14&#13;
THE COST-EFFECTIVENESS OF VARIOUS PROGRAMS FOR FERTILITY&#13;
REDUCTION                                                           19&#13;
Cost-Effectiveness of Family Planning Program                  20&#13;
Cost Per Birth Averted through Mortality Reduction             23&#13;
Caveats                                                        27&#13;
SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS                                             28&#13;
BIBLIOGRAPHY                                                        30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
List; of Tables&#13;
Table No0                                                        Page No0&#13;
1     Median Birth Intervals in Months by Survival of&#13;
Previous Child                                             7&#13;
2     Median Birth Intervals in Months by Survival Status&#13;
of Previous Child                                          8&#13;
3     The Effect of Neo-Hatal and Post Neo-Matal Mortality&#13;
on Birth Intervals from Regression Equations for&#13;
1, 3, and 5                                               10&#13;
4     The Effect of Infant Deaths on Birth Intervals&#13;
Estimated by Medians and by Reduction Interval&#13;
if an Infant Death Occurs                                 11&#13;
5     The Effect of Child Death Experience on&#13;
Contraceptive Usage                                       13&#13;
6     Parity Progression Ratios by Survival Status of&#13;
the Two Previous Chilcren (Parities 2-6)                  15&#13;
7     Difference between Addlitional Children for Women&#13;
Who Had i and i-l Survive and Death of an i, itth&#13;
or Both Children                                          16&#13;
8     Effects of Infant Mortality on Fertilty:   Reduction&#13;
in Births due to a Reduction in Deaths                    18&#13;
9     Cost Per User and Per Birth Averted Using Various&#13;
Estimation Techniques                                     22&#13;
10     Cost Per Death Preven':ed                                 24&#13;
11     Cost Per Birth Averted through Preventing an Infant&#13;
Death                                                     26&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Infant and Child Mortality as a Determinant of Fertility:&#13;
The Policy Implications*&#13;
by Susan H. Cochrane and K. C. Zachariah&#13;
This paper is devoted to exploring some aspects of the effect of&#13;
infant and child mortality on fertility.     It does not exhaust all aspects&#13;
of that relationship and, of course, the effect of mortality on fertility&#13;
is only part of the total relationship between the two variables.       To de-&#13;
sign analysis and projects one must be aware of the converse direction of&#13;
causation.&#13;
The 1975 Bangkok Conference represents the existing state of the&#13;
evidence on the effect of infant and child mortality on fertility.          The&#13;
conclusion of that conference has been summarized as "on average, an addi-&#13;
tional child death in the family, ceteris paribus, leads to far less than&#13;
one additional birth". (Preston, 1978, 11).&#13;
While this effect was observed to vary depending on the level of&#13;
socio-economic development, it is less than one half in all the countries&#13;
studied (Preston, 1975, 191).    This agrees with one elasticity of .33 that&#13;
McGreevey and Birdsall found in their review of the evidence (McGreevey and&#13;
Birdsall, 1974, 65).&#13;
There is substantial new evidence available from World Fertility&#13;
Survey that will be reviewed in this paper.       That evidence shows varying&#13;
impacts of mortality on fertility depending on the methodology used.         In&#13;
this paper we wish to both review a set of new WFS tabulations on 25&#13;
countries which estimate the effect of a woman's mortality experience on&#13;
her fertility behavior and to put that evidence into a context which will&#13;
help address the policy issues.&#13;
* This paper was World Bank's contribution to the UN Expert Group&#13;
Meeting on Fertility held in Delhi, India on January 5-11, 1983.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
This approach focuses on the narrowly defined effects of an indi-&#13;
vidual couple's infant and child mo-tality experience on their fertility,&#13;
but it ignores the long term communal aggregate effects, such as changes in&#13;
perceived mortality which change insurance motivations for ch`ld bearing&#13;
and changes in the age at marriage. These latter issues are extremely rel-&#13;
evant to the long run demographic balance, but cannot be examiined in a&#13;
paper of this length.    (See Coale, 1973 for a discussion of the two demo-&#13;
graphic transitions--the first in age of marriage and the second in marital&#13;
fertility).&#13;
Unanswered Policy Questions&#13;
There are many different ways of interpreting the question: "Does&#13;
mortality decline affect fertility?'     At one extreme there are those who&#13;
claim that a mortality decline will bring about an equal decline in fertil-&#13;
ity. If this interpretation were correct, one could achieve mortality re-&#13;
ductions, which are desirable in and of themselves, without paying the&#13;
price of prolonged acceleration in population growth0 The work cited above&#13;
indicates this is not the case0      13ut other policy questions need to be&#13;
answered.   (1)   Is mortality decline necessary to initiate fertility de-&#13;
cline?  (2)   Is mortality decline a cost-effective way to initiate fertil-&#13;
ity decline? and (3)    Do mortality reduction (health) and family planning&#13;
programs have a synergistic effect?&#13;
The policy implications of these questions differ substantially.&#13;
If any one of them is answered in the affirmative, it implies that there&#13;
may be arguments for investing in nortality reducing programs beyond what&#13;
is desired on health grounds alone in order to stimulate fertility decline.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
If mortality decline is necessary to initiate fertility decline,&#13;
then health programs must be introduced prior to or in tandem with family&#13;
planning programs.    The issue of lags is critical to understanding the&#13;
proper timing of the introduction of various programs.     Even if mortality&#13;
decline is not necessary to bring about fertility decline, it maybe a cost-&#13;
effective way to do so.   The cost-effectiveness of health programs or mor-&#13;
tality reduction in bringing about fertility reduction must not be con-&#13;
sidered only vis-a-vis family planning programs, but also vis-a-vis other&#13;
programs, such a improvement in education, but to do so is beyond the scope&#13;
of this paper.&#13;
The weakest statement of the relationship would be that health&#13;
and family programs will have a synergistic effect because mortality de-&#13;
cline enhances the motivation for family planning.    Whether such synergys-&#13;
tic effects can be capitalized on depends on the increased problems, in-&#13;
creased costs and perhaps reduced efficiency that arise from combining pro-&#13;
grams.&#13;
It early on became obvious from the literature that in general,&#13;
mortality decline has not always been necessary for fertility decline.      In&#13;
both the U.S. and France, fertility decline began before or simultaneously&#13;
with mortality decline.    This probably resulted from massive economic and&#13;
social changes which shifted the demand for children downward.&#13;
In many currently developing countries there may be massive&#13;
changes which would lead parents to want fewer children than they could&#13;
have with unrestricted fertility and existing mortality rates. This would&#13;
lead to a demand to restrict fertility through contraceptives or changes in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
age of marriage. Therefore, instead of discussing necessity (wthich is dif-&#13;
ficult to prove in any case), it is more productive to discuss alternative&#13;
strategies for reducing either population growth or fertility.&#13;
Here we come to an important decision point both for policy and&#13;
for research. Should the objective of policy be simply to minimixe popula-&#13;
tion growtho   In the analysis here it was assumed that mortality reduction&#13;
is an end in and of itself.    Therefore, to achieve demographic balance one&#13;
must determine what strategies would maximize fertility reduction0 In this&#13;
paper two strategies were examined, (i) reduce infant mortality and&#13;
(ii) increase access to family planning.      I-le expected that the optimal&#13;
strategy would vary depending on tne environment and our analysis verifies&#13;
this point.&#13;
The comparision of these two strategies required that we estimate&#13;
(i) the cost of preventing an addit;ional birth through expanding the family&#13;
planning program in a country, (ii) the cost of preventing an infant death&#13;
through an expansion of a health program, and (iii) the effect of infant&#13;
mortality on fertility0    There are substantial difficulties in estimating&#13;
the costs of preventing a birth or an infant or child death which will be&#13;
discussed later, but the primary function of this paper is to estimate the&#13;
effect of infant and child mortality on fertility using WFS data from 25&#13;
countries0&#13;
THE CHANNELS:  THEORY AND MEASUREMENT&#13;
The channels through which infant and child mortality may affect&#13;
fertility are biological and behavioral.    The behavioral effects may oper-&#13;
ate at the community as well as the individual level. The ease of measur-&#13;
ing the effects varies by the channel being considered with the communal&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
being the most nebulous.   For this reason we will review first the biolog-&#13;
ical, then the individual behavioral effects but as mentioned above we will&#13;
ignore communal effects in this paper.&#13;
The Biological Effects&#13;
The biological effect of infant mortality and to a lesser extent&#13;
child mortality on fertility operates through the premature termination of&#13;
breastfeeding and the consequent shorter post-partum amenorrhea.         This&#13;
effect was very widely reviewed, modeled, and estimated (Potter, 1963)&#13;
(Perrin and Sheps, 1964) (Sheps and Perrin, 1964).      The magnitude of the&#13;
effect will depend on the normal length of breastfeeding and the relation-&#13;
ship between breastfeeding and amenorrhea.      There are substantial cross&#13;
country differences in the length of breastfeeding, and differences in the&#13;
estimated relationship between breastfeeding and amenorrhea.      The longest&#13;
observed average   amenorrhea   is  18.9  months  in  Bangladesh  (Bongaarts,&#13;
1978).    Chen reports that 45% of the length of the birth intervals could&#13;
be accounted for by lactation amenorrhea (Chen, et.al., 1974).       There is&#13;
evidence that the relationship between lactation and amenorrhea depends on&#13;
the nutritional status of the mother (Bongaarts, 1979, 15) and the pattern&#13;
of  supplemental  feeding of the child.       In an environment   similar to&#13;
Bangladesh infant and child mortality could substantially alter breastfeed-&#13;
ing, shorten birth intervals and increase the number of children ever born&#13;
if contraception is not used.&#13;
The biological effect can be measured by comparing the birth in-&#13;
tervals in which the previous child died and in which the child survived,&#13;
controlling for a number of variables to be discussed later.      These birth&#13;
intervals could be contaminated by behavioral effects as well, however, if&#13;
contraception for spacing is used and its adoption depends on the survival&#13;
status of the child.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 1 sumnmarizes HFS d;ata on the effect of a child loss on&#13;
redlan birth intervals. Table 2 sho§s the medians for those w5h$ have never&#13;
contracepted.   Table 3 summarizes regression coefficients for showing the&#13;
effect of a child death on the birth interval controlling for iother's age,&#13;
mother's education, husband's occupation,, twife's status and rural resi-&#13;
dence. The expected pattern is that the longer the child lives, the longer&#13;
the birth interval.    The difference in birth intervals reflects the in-&#13;
crease in exposure to child bearing caused by infant mortality.      The data&#13;
does not perfectly fit this expecta.tion.    In a third of the c2ses for the&#13;
first, third and fifth intervals, there is a deviation from the expected&#13;
pattern.   This is explained in part by the small number of cases In some&#13;
categories.   In addition, the data on birth intervals are not of uniformly&#13;
good quality in all countries. Averoages over the 22 countries w:ith compar-&#13;
able data show that in the first interval, a neonatal death shortens the&#13;
interval by 4.7 months and a postneonatal death by 2.4.        For third and&#13;
fifth intervals, the figures are 423, 325 and 4.1, 3.6 respectively.&#13;
The majority of the effects measured above are probably biolo-&#13;
gical, but the difference in birth intervals between those whose previ,ous&#13;
child died and those whose previous child survived also depends on whether&#13;
child loss affects how long a couple uses faiWly planning in that birth&#13;
interval0   To control for this factor, We show the median birth intervals&#13;
by child survival for those women who have never used contraceptives in&#13;
Table 20   Here, as in Table 1, slightly over a third of the cases deviate&#13;
from the expected pattern and the 'values do not differ systematically from&#13;
those found for all women0   In sunifary then medians indicate Peonatal mor&#13;
tality increases birth intervals by between 3.2 and 600 months on average&#13;
and postneonatal by 1.7 to 3080&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
TABLE 1:     Median Birth Intervals In Months by Surival of Previous Child&#13;
ALL WOMEN&#13;
INTERVAL 1                      INTERVAL 3                      INTERVAL 5&#13;
Died       Died       Survived  Died        Dled      Survived  Died        Died      Survived&#13;
COUNTRY        0 - 1      2 - 11        12+    0 - 1      2 - 11        12+    0 - 1      2 - 11       12+&#13;
Months     Months      Months   Months      Months     Months   Months      Months     Months&#13;
Bengladesh (WFS)     21.6       23.8        24.3     24.4        22.9       24.1    (16.1)       25.5       22.8&#13;
Colombia             16.1       19.3        20.8     16.0        17.3       22.4     14.5        16.3       22.5&#13;
FIJI                 18.1       21.5        22.5     22.8        22.0       24.1     23.3        17.3       22.0&#13;
Guyana              [12.71       16.7       19.2    115.51       17.3       18.2    (15.0]      (18.8)      21.3&#13;
Haiti               (24.9)      24.3        24.9    (22.5)       20.4       25.0     (23.31     (24.3)      24.8&#13;
Indonesia            20.0       22.3       31.1      24.0       21.7        30.1     19.5        19.2       29.8&#13;
Costa Rica           14.5        15.0       21.2     17.0        18.4       22.1      14.2       21.3       22.6&#13;
Korea                17.0       23.1        24.4    (17.2)       24.5       26.4     [14.51      26.5       25.2&#13;
Kenya                20.3       20.8        23.2     26.6        21.3       23.6     (25.6)      19.6       22.2&#13;
Jordan              (15.4)      18.5        19.5    (15.8)       19.3       23.3    (19.5)       18.7       23.5&#13;
Syria                14.8       16.7        18.3     17.0        18.8       21.8    (16.5)       18.8       22.0&#13;
Malaysia             17.0        18.8       22.7     17.5        18.6       24.0     (17.5)      21.4       25.1&#13;
Lesotho              23.8       22.4        25.6    (20.5)       23.6       23.9     (19.5)      21.8       24.6&#13;
Sri Lanka            19.5       21.2        25.2     21.1        19.3    -  27.7     23.7        20.9       28.4&#13;
Nepal                23.3       24.1        25.7     28.7        24.3       25.8     (31.7)      24.1       25.9&#13;
Paraguay                  19.5              25.0            18.1            25.2            18.0            25.6&#13;
Philippines          14.0        19.6       20.2     14.3        20.3       23.1      14.1       21.0       24.2&#13;
Peru                 19.6       20.0        23.9     19.9        18.8       25.4      18.7       21.1       25.9&#13;
Panama               16.5       23.0        22.5     19.2        22.0       24.5     (23.7)     (18.5)      24.1&#13;
Dominican Rep.            17.2              22.7            17.3            23.2            18.7             23.2&#13;
Jamaica             [18.0]      22.8        24.8    [20.0]      (25.0)      24.7    (26.01      [17.31      22.0&#13;
Trinidad            (20.0)      22.0        17.9    [15.1]      (16.7)      18.3     N/A        (17.7)       18.8&#13;
Venezuela                 17.5              21.1           20.5             23.3           (21.0)           22.7&#13;
Pakistan             20.6       22.2        28.8     19.5        22.9       28.6      19.0       21.8       28.7&#13;
Mexico               16.5       17.3        22.0     15.8        18.5       24.1      17.3       17.8       24.8&#13;
() Less than 25 cases&#13;
(1 Less than 10 cases&#13;
N/A No cases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
TPSLE 20    MaSUC2 Bur%h onWtaos ftl mm%s WGD &amp;Szour Ststs e7 F¢ravuczs QhU d&#13;
Never Used Contraceptive&#13;
INTERVAL 1                     INTERVAL 3                      INTERVAL 5&#13;
Died       Died     Survived   Died       Died      Survived   Died       Died     Survived&#13;
0 - 1      2 - 11     12+      0 - 1       2 - 11     12+      0 - 1      2 - 11     12+&#13;
COUNTRY       Months     Months     Months    Months     Months    Months    Months     Months    Months&#13;
Bangladesh (WFS)    22.5        24.2      24.5      24.5       23.4       23.9    (1701)      24.9       22.8&#13;
Colombla            15.5       21.0       22.6      1500       1505       23.3    (13.3)      (15.8)     23.9&#13;
Fiji                23.8       (28.0)     210     (2500)     (26.0)     (305)   [25-51     117.31      (27.0)&#13;
Guyana             [12031      (17-0)     19.7     ['7-5]     (19oO)      17.8    114.0]     [20-51      2107&#13;
Haiti              (2503)      24.6       25.1     ('7-5)      19o9       24.4    123-31     123-01      23.3&#13;
Indonesia           206       22.6      31o6      24.1       21o2        303     19o9       205       3004&#13;
Costa Rica         (1401)      (16-0)     21.2     12000]     (17.0)      22.9    [12-01      (17-5)     24.3&#13;
Korea              (2008)       27.5      27.5     [i7.51      24.9       27.6    [1203]     (24.0)      28B1&#13;
Kenya               20.9       21o2       23.6     (2508)      21.1       23.2    (22-4)      20.5       22.2&#13;
Jordan             [1600]      21.7       21o4     [15.91      19.5       23.5    116o4l      21.4       24.3&#13;
Syria               14.8        16.9      19.3     (15-0)      17.0       22.3    (16-0)      205       22o5&#13;
Malaysia            16.3        22.3      25.6      17.5       19.8       24.3    (13.5)      22.8       2553&#13;
Lesotho            (2401)      22.8       25.2     (23-4)      23.7       23.5    119.4l     (21o8)      24.0&#13;
Sri Lanka           204       21o8       26.7      21o2       23.0       28.6     23.4       19.3       28.7&#13;
Nepal               23.4        24.0      25.9      28.7       24.2       25.6    (26-4)      24.3       25.8&#13;
Paraguay                 22.0             25.2            1905            25o3           17.0            23.2&#13;
Philippines         13.7        203      208     (1401)      20.9       24.6    (13-2)      25.1       24.5&#13;
Peru                21.0        200      24.8      1904       19o7       25o8     19o1       2104        26o3&#13;
Panama               18.5      (24.0)     24.2     [19oO]     (22-2)      25.4    (23.8)      [16.8l     25.4&#13;
Dominican Rep.            19o5            23.7            19oO            2403           18.0            24.1&#13;
Jamaica            [2000]     (28-0)      27.0      N/A       [26.0]      26.0    [26.01     122.0]     (180)&#13;
Trinidad           [56011      [26-81     16.7      N/A       11507]     (206)    N/A       123.2l      118.31&#13;
Venezuela               (24-0)            23.5           (200)           24.1          (25.0]           23.9&#13;
Pakistan            205        22.3      29.2      19o8       23o4       29o1     19.5       21o2       2901&#13;
Mexico               16.9       16.9      23.7      17.5       18.4       24.8     16.8       17.8       25.5&#13;
() Less than 25 cases&#13;
- Less than 10 cases&#13;
N/A No cases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The regression results in Table 3 show negative effects of an in-&#13;
fant death on birth intervals in almost all cases and negative significant&#13;
effects are observed in 49% of the cases.     The average values of all coef-&#13;
ficients for a neonatal death for the first, third and fifth birth interval&#13;
are 7.7, 5.1 and 5.8 respectively. The effect of a post neonatal death are&#13;
4.3, 5.5 and 5.8 when all coefficients are averaged.&#13;
For women who have never used contraceptives and for whom the&#13;
effects are thus more biological than behavioral, the effect of neonatal&#13;
mortality are 7.7, 5.5 and 5.9 and the effects of post neonatal are 4.0,&#13;
6.0 and 6.2.&#13;
Table 4 summarizes the effect of infant death on birth intervals&#13;
for three parities as estimated by median differences and regression equa-&#13;
tions for all women and those who have never contracepted.      The regression&#13;
equations give higher estimates of mortality effects than do median val-&#13;
ues.1/ No clear pattern emerges across parities, nor between all women and&#13;
those never using contraceptives.     More surprisingly postneonatal effects&#13;
are not always smaller than those of neonatal.&#13;
If is difficult to put these data in the context of other re-&#13;
search since the methodology is somewhat different, but in an earlier study&#13;
of rural and semi-urban areas of those countries the effect of an infant&#13;
death reduced the birth internal by 4.3, 3.5, 6.2 and 4.6 months respec-&#13;
tively in Costa Rica, Colombia, Peru, and Mexico (Rutstein and Medica,&#13;
1978).   For those countries our average regression coefficients for neo-&#13;
1/ This may arise because the use of medians allow no control even, indi-&#13;
rectly, for maternal health.     Healthier women will have shorter inter-&#13;
vals and lower child mortality ceteris paribus.       So the intervals for&#13;
children surviving are biased downwards, as is the difference in inter-&#13;
vals. To the extent that education, rural residence and husband's occu-&#13;
pation control for health, the regression equation do not have that&#13;
short coming.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Al I  c1Sn                                         Rver Used ContraceptI@&#13;
INTERVAL 1          INTERVAL 3          INTERVAL 5          INTERVAL I       INTERVAL 3     INTERVAL 5&#13;
CCLIWTRY     0=1         2°11 101            2°11    0=1        2°11    0=1          2°11 j01          2°11  0°1&#13;
SBngIoGsh          =9.30     =4,10     =3.6      -4,30     =Go67     -2.7     =8,80      =4.j0   =2.8      -4.40   =5,1&#13;
Co I ::I I560                4&gt;1 o3    0300      °501°     ,9.30     -5,40    - 7.60     4w56     1o6       8,51  -l10.2'&#13;
F IJ I              4050     ol o7     =304      =5o1      =o12      °4,7     =2.9       o; o3   =0.3       000   A1 3,70&#13;
GuVLwSO            0903      o6 o20    o4o2      °0o8      -- o7     -Go2    oil04       °4O7    0 o2      =1o6   °10o6&#13;
Wal3H P9.=                   =3.7      =7.0      =5960)    °9,4      =9.7     =5.8       -9.6   =10o60    -o63     -7.8&#13;
9 nezn|3| Il2          ° °12,60  "10lW  "7.00&lt;   °S0.20   "0        o  o6°     3,2o)    o10.3°   -So4°    =8,40    =8,30&#13;
Cazft Roca         -3        =59 =g3,5           =5,905°   =S.7o 0    2,4 -lol           "4,0 |   8.7      -5.    ol4.80&#13;
KC?CO        -H.Sp,9     -5 -20  =1,-~ ~539cY                   '-oV     -'1?,20     -5o-01 -16,20)  -10.30   =14.3&#13;
9C'qvo        -7q5G      ,Z.950   -21        -~4,7O   -.3.0     -~        =7.70     =5,.90   =2.6     -4,80)   =1.2&#13;
Jcrda'a            og9.5 o9.=3         -9.3      .2,01    =OoS O5o80          '6 5.     -0.2    o4o1      o2.3    41 o8&#13;
SyrIa              -G6,60 o   36703 °   5,30 3    9-6O 56 3           6 D81   °7,30 3     4.5    = o6,50 o  5.40   -6.2&#13;
Malaysias          -3.0      o3,90     =800      -94°0    =10,70     =1.6     -6o6       -5.70  '12.30     -700*  =14,6&#13;
Loso.4ho           11o9  °90    4°     °7o9      =O830    -77        -20       1220      °9.00°  =3o0      °7o80   o708&#13;
SnI Lanka          -8,50     v7,10     -430      .S3°30   "3o0       o1080°   og.5°      -8.50   -2o4     -8,70    o103&#13;
Nspai             -10010     -7l01     -2.5      --G,10 I   2,7 2,590        -10.5°      -7.4'   -206      -6 1    419&#13;
ParaguaDv              -550                -7.50               -6,90                -307             =5.5             -1&#13;
Phllippinas        -9.2'     o3,6'    ,1Oo0,     -4,20     -7.80     -6.30   -1130 -5'4.1-      o12.4-     -4. 5*  11o2-&#13;
PCJ                °7 o6°    --6 o6°   °4 °0°    -7 °1 °    7202     c°9°     -7.1 °     °76 o6°2  °40 °5°  -6.3 4   3 °7o6&#13;
Pan&amp;mga            =402°     4109      =S,S      =1,6     40,3       -9A4z.   -03        4o11   =4.1     -5.2     &gt;2.0&#13;
Dc4tlfilcan Rcpo       -7,10               ,38°0               =40                  680              - 4.6          o&#13;
Janalca           -1309      =4o7    410,0       =3,3     =3.3       =395    =19.1       -2.2     °      -1209     =9.0&#13;
Trinidad           =4.2      42,0      °9°3      -8,70     o         &gt;305    +21.6       459.7  0139      -5o8&#13;
V=Ztt'-' I              =2.2                =5.8                - OZ1               °304             °7.6 o1&#13;
pc5z I s1tvi,      =7,60     =4, -°990 o7,10                         -o2'     =8.00°     -5 20W  -6 o6     =6.30   = 6,60o&#13;
MaW Ileo           -9.40-    =4.g0     =800      =3°0      -3S60     =7,20    =8,80      °-704j  -7 50     -3.1    -7, 7'&#13;
S Ignb ' Icant&#13;
1/  ControllIng fcr rtohor's aga, Pothor's education, husband's occupation, olfe's eorh, skatus, and rural resi inceo&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
Table 4&#13;
The Effect of Infant Deaths on Birth Intervals Estimated by Medians and by&#13;
Reduction Interval If an Infant Death Occurs&#13;
Regression Equations&#13;
Parity 1     Parity 3      Parity 5&#13;
All women&#13;
Median differences&#13;
neonatal                 4.6         4.4         4.2&#13;
postneonatal             2.2         3.4         3.4&#13;
Regression results&#13;
neonatal                 7.8         5.0         5.8&#13;
postneonatal             4.3         5.6         5.7&#13;
Non-contraceptors&#13;
Median differences&#13;
neonatal                 3.1         4.9         5.8&#13;
postneonatal             1.5         3.8         3.5&#13;
Regression results&#13;
neonatal                 7.7         5.4         6.2&#13;
postneonatal             3.8         6.1         6.2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
natal and postneonatal effects wiere 52 and 4.F  ,   O6D   and 3i   5.3 and 4.4&#13;
and 6.7 and 4.9 respectively.       Thus   the   stiates are trly      close&#13;
considering differences In time periods, 2tdoogies and       ampcs-&#13;
Infant and Child Mortality Experience on Contrac2eptIve Use&#13;
The above data on birth intervals for all womoen incorporates be-&#13;
havioral as well as biological effects to the extent that mortaHity experi-&#13;
ence affects contraceptive usage in the lntervalb     Analysis of the effect&#13;
of child death experience on contraceptive usage is shown in Table 5.    For&#13;
women with between four and six children, we find that without exception&#13;
those women who have experienced a C:hild death are leSs likely ~o haVe ever&#13;
used contraceptives.   For current use wte find that In 23 of 25 cases those&#13;
who have had a child death are less like)y to be using contraception than&#13;
those with no death.&#13;
Combining all parities andi controlling for the nuffiber of children&#13;
ever born, rural residences, wlfe's educction, husbnid's occupation and&#13;
wife's work status,, the experience of child mortality reduces contraceptive&#13;
use in all cases and in 20 of 25 cases this is statistically significant at&#13;
the 5% level0  The largest effect is in Jamaica atih     a child death reduces&#13;
usage by 9.4 per 1000&#13;
Other data from multiple classification Oanalysis arn useful for&#13;
comparison here.   In Colombia,, woFen with one child death weree 2.3% less&#13;
likely to use contraceptives than those with no death0        OLr regr@ession&#13;
gives 4.7o   For Costa Rica1, Peru, and M3aico our figures of 5.2, 4.7 and&#13;
2.5 compare with 3.5 1.4 and 2.3 i'See Rutstein and Medlca,, Ui78).    Again&#13;
given different time periods, data sets and iniethodology,D the flndings seei&#13;
robust.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
TABLE 5:     The Effect of Chl Id Death Experience on Contraceptive Usage&#13;
(a)  Proportions ever using and currently using                                                 (b)  Effect of Number of&#13;
contraceptive by child death experience                                                         Child Deaths on&#13;
(Parities 4 - 6)                                                                               Current Contraceptive&#13;
Usage /&#13;
% Women Ever Used Contraception     % Women Currently Using Contraception&#13;
COUNTRY       with child death without child death with child death without child death      Regresslon Coefficient&#13;
Bangladesh (WFS)        14.8               21.2                10.8               15.4                   -.024*&#13;
Colombia                56.5               67.9                50.5               61.8                   -.047*&#13;
FIJI                    74.2               80.3                55.2               65.1                   -.060*&#13;
Guyana                  54.1               63.3                37.7               44.1                   -.049*&#13;
Haiti                   35.5               46.2                24.4               31.7                   -.026*&#13;
Indonesia               40.6              48.8                43.3                50.4                   -.075*&#13;
Costa Rica              81.8               87.1               77.0                82.8                   -.052*&#13;
Korea                   60.3               72.7               50.1                56.8                   -.061*&#13;
Kenya                   27.5               41.2                 5.6                14.5                  -.021*&#13;
Jordan                  40.0               55.3               27.7                45.5                   -.043*&#13;
Syria                   31.9               44.8               27.8                41.7                   -.042*&#13;
Malavsia                39.5               55.8                38.3               48.2                   -.059*&#13;
Lesotho                 28.3               31.3                13.6               11.5                   -.017*&#13;
Sr  Lanka               45.5               57.6               44.7                55.1                   -.049*&#13;
Nepal                    5.5               10.2                 0.8                2.0                   -.013*&#13;
Paraguay                51.4               60.9                50.4               47.2                   -.002&#13;
Phillppines             56.8               69.8               44.4                56.4                   -.052*&#13;
Peru                    37.4               65.9                30.1               51.6                   -.047*&#13;
Panama                  73.3               81.3                71.4               72.0                   -.027&#13;
Dominican Rep.          53.9               59.0                48.7               53.2                   -.031*&#13;
Jamaica                 61.1               75.8               20.0                45.5                   -.094*&#13;
Trinldad                79.1               86.5               58.6                68.3                   -.020&#13;
Venezuela               63.7               75.0                56.4               65.9                   -.010&#13;
Pakistan                 9.2               17.4                6.7                12.5                   -.015*&#13;
Mexico                  37.6               56.1                34.8               49.8                   -.025&#13;
I/  Controlling for chlidren ever born, rural residence wife's education, husband's occupation, wife's work status.&#13;
Significant at 52&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
14 °&#13;
The Effect of Infant and Child Mortelity on Parity&#13;
The biological and behavioral responses to child mortaHity exper-&#13;
iences ultimately have their effect on completed family size. Table 6 sum-&#13;
marizes the effect of child mortality experience on parity progression ra-&#13;
tios. At parity 1, 2 and 3 those who have experienced child mortality have&#13;
a higher probability of having additional children than for those couples&#13;
who have not experienced mortality0    In the 189 comparisons on these three&#13;
parities there are only three exceptions to this pattern0    At higher pari-&#13;
ties 5 and 6, the pattern also prevails, but with a few more exceptions&#13;
(eight of 126 comparisons)0   In most cases we also find that the more re-&#13;
cent the death, the higher the probability of having an additional child.&#13;
That is, if the last child dies the progression ratio is higher than if the&#13;
next to last child died.    We find that among those with two or more chil&#13;
dren, if the second child dies, the probability of having an additional&#13;
child is 16% higher.    At parity 6 it is 20% higher0    Rutstein and Medica&#13;
calculated adjusted parity progression ratios based on mortality experi-&#13;
ence0   Their data show much smaller effects than those observed here.&#13;
Using 1962 data from France, Vallini and Lery found mortality had a 30% ef-&#13;
fect on parity progression rates at second parity and 19% at Ciftho     Thus,&#13;
our results are more like those of modern France than those found by&#13;
Rutstein and Medica, but this may result from the multivaricte nature of&#13;
their analyses0&#13;
It is easier to understsnd the impact of previous mortality on&#13;
fertility if one looks not at parity progression ratios but at the addi°&#13;
tional number of births0   Table 7 shows the difference in total additional&#13;
children ever born to women with different mortality experiences. For ex-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
TABLE 6:     Parity Progression Ratios by Survival Status of the Two Previous Children, (Parities 2-6)&#13;
ParIty 2                                        Parity 3&#13;
Both      1st died     1st survived             Both     2nd died      2nd survived&#13;
COUNTRY      survived 2nd survived 2nd died       Both died survived 3rd survived 3rd died        Both died&#13;
Bangladesh (WFS)     .80        .85           .90          .92      .78         .84           .91         .94&#13;
Colombia             .76        .85           .89          .94      .75         .78           .88         .96&#13;
Fiji                 .79        .90           .90          .96      .76         .84           .89         .84&#13;
Guyana               .80        .88           .91          .86      .79         .90           .85         .89&#13;
Halti               .75         .80           .85          .84      .74         .73           .88         .83&#13;
Indonesia           .75         .82           .86         .92       .74         .77          .90          .92&#13;
Costa Rica           .73        .90           .88          .94      .73         .82           .89         .96&#13;
Korea                .77        .91           .96          .97      .69         .88           .92         .94&#13;
Kenya                .83        .88           .92          .94      .82         .85           .92         .96&#13;
Jordan              .86         .94           .97          .96      .85         .94           .94         .96&#13;
Syria               .85         .90           .95          .99      .82         .88          .95          .96&#13;
Malaysia            .81         .90           .94          .94      .77         .87           .94         .96&#13;
Lesotfio            .73         .76           .86          .88      .71         .76           .79         .85&#13;
Sri Lanka           .80         .90           .89         .88       .77         .83          .87          .88&#13;
Nepal               .75         .79           .90          .93      .70         .76           .90         .92&#13;
Paraguay            .75         .86           .87          .91      .73         .82           .80         .86&#13;
Philippines          .82        .91           .92          .96      .79         .84           .91         .91&#13;
Peru                .79         .87           .93          .97      .75         .84           .90         .97&#13;
Panama               .77        .90           .94          .89      .73         .87           .86        1.0&#13;
Dominican Rep.      .79         .87           .89          .90      .78         .84           .90         .83&#13;
Jamaica             .75         .91           .83         .78       .76         .90          .89          .61&#13;
Trinidad            .71         .89           .81          .81      .74         .87          .93          .90&#13;
Veiiezuel a         .74         .71           .88          .88      .73         .83           .86         .94&#13;
Pakistan             .81        .96           .93          .93      .80         .85           .91         .94&#13;
Mexico               .83        .92           .89          .93      .90         .86           .91         .93&#13;
Par ty 4                                        Par ty 5&#13;
Bangladesh (WFS)    .75         .83           .8q          .89      .73         .74           .86         .92&#13;
Colombi3            .76         .84           .9C          .92      .74         .83           .85         .92&#13;
Fiji                .75         .80           .91          .79      .71         .71           .85         .94&#13;
Guyana              .71         .84           .80          .80      .77        .86            .86         .79j&#13;
Haiti               .74         .75           .8,          .79      .71         .73           .81         .85&#13;
Ilndonesia          .72         :77           .86         .94       .68         .75          .83          .90&#13;
Costa Rica           .75        .87           .92          .85      .76         .89           .87        1.0&#13;
Korea                .62        .71           .89          .91      .57         .76           .82         .97&#13;
Kenya               .90         .87           .9S          .92      .75         .84           .89         .96&#13;
J,oddn              .82         .88           .95         .94       .83         .90          .93         1.0&#13;
Syria               .81         .89           .93          .96      .78         .90           .92         .96&#13;
Mal5ysia            .75         .88           .88          .91      .73         .8i           .91         .96&#13;
L P$')i             .68         .60           .81          .96      .64         .72           .87         .82&#13;
Sri Lanka           .75         .76           .95          .00      .72         .7'3         .q5          .88&#13;
Nepel               .67         . ?l          .84          .90      .63         .69           .82         .97&#13;
0ardguay             .77        .83           .83          .81      .7S         .86           .94        1.0&#13;
Philippines          .77        .81           .91          .96      .76         .82           .86         .0O&#13;
Peru                .74         .83           .88          .97      .72         .83           .91         .92&#13;
Fanama              .73         .8q           .84          .94      .71         .84           .71         .6i&#13;
Dominican Rep.       .75        .88           .88          .82      .74         .93           .85         .91&#13;
Jamai:a             .75         .77           .75         .80       .74         .72          .90          .88&#13;
Trinidad            .72         .91           .93          .75      .71         .92           .77         .73&#13;
Venezuela           .71         .89           .88          .88      .71         .82          .82          .44&#13;
Pakistan             .7Y        .82           .98          .92      .74         .82           .87        .*0&#13;
Mexi:o              .80        .8            .94          .96      .80         .83           .88         .96&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
TAMLE 7:      Differercs Basthsn Additielam    Chi[dren icr Us=  tzo N-D ed I End l-i SzrVIBe -cX Death of ED 1, -it  or&#13;
BaOh ChidIrsn&#13;
COUNTRY         i = 2+   1=3+       1 = 4+    1 = 54           COUNTRY         =2+      1 = 3+     1=4+      1 =5+&#13;
Bangladesh                                                     S-l Lanka&#13;
a. i died            -0.44     -0.50     -0.39      -0.C9      a. I died            -0.43     -0.25*   -0.12*     -0.24*&#13;
b. 1-1 died          -0.40     -0.39     -0.11       0.CO      b. i-i died          -0.47     -0.23      0.02      0.02&#13;
c. i and i-I died    -1.01     -0.68     -0.65      -1.36      c. i and i-l died    -0.43     [0.021   1-0.381    -0.35&#13;
Columbia                                                       Napal&#13;
a. I died            -1.26     -1.15     -1.11      -1.(0      a. I died            -0.81     -0.32     -0.63     -0.61&#13;
b. i-1 died          -0.79     -0.81     -0.87      _0.oi      b. i-l died          -0.23     -0.21    -0.04      -0.34&#13;
c. I and i-i died   1-1.40]   1-2.45]    i-0.901   [-1.291     c. i and i-I died    -0.96     -1.21    -0.90      -0.98&#13;
Fiji                                                           Paraguay&#13;
a. I died            -0.01     -0.84     -0.72      -0.-6      a. I died            -0.55*    -0.31*   1-0.381*  1-0.401*&#13;
b. 1-1 died          -0.99     -0.75     -0.63      -0.A4      b. 1-1 died          -0.47     -0.18    -0.63     1-0.471&#13;
c. I and i-i died   [-1.821   1-0.593    1-0.331   [-0.'1]     c. i and i-1 died   1-0.371   1-2.191   [-1.081   1-0.921&#13;
Guyana                                                         Philippines&#13;
a. i died            -1.06     -0.43     -0.69      -0. 5      a. I died            -0.76     -0.79    -0.48      -0.58&#13;
b. i-1 died          -1.03     -0.74     -0.60      -0.81      b. i-l died          -0.99     -0.57     -0.51     -0.12&#13;
c. I and i-l died   [-0.811   [-1.471    1-1.081    -0.4      c. I and i-l died   1-1.601   1-1-391   1-0.781   1-0.921&#13;
Haiti                                                          Peru&#13;
a. I died            -0.14*    -0.36*    -0.38*     -0.'.1#    a. I died            -1.08     -0.92    -0.75      -0.98&#13;
b. i-i died          -0.21      0.02     -0.07      -0. 9      b. 1-1 died          -0.95     -0.67    -0.56      -0.52&#13;
c. i and i-1 died   1-0.011    10.251    1-0.21]   1-0.'51     c. I and i-l died    -2.23     -1.70     -1.46     -1.28&#13;
Indonesia                                                      Panama&#13;
a. I died            -0.67     -0.57     -0.78      -0.77      a. I died            -1.15     -1.03    -0.85     1-0.061&#13;
b. 1-1 died          -0.53     -0.68     -0.16      -0.;i0     b. i-l died          -1.33     -0.59    -0.85      -0.98&#13;
c. I and i-1 died    -1.32     -1.03     -0.98      -1.14      c. I and i-i died   1-1.681   1-1.961   [-2.771    10.181&#13;
Costa Rica                                                     Cominican Rep.&#13;
a. i died            -1.24     -1.67     -0.88      -0..19*    a. i died            -0.18*    -0.03*   -0.36*     -0.5i1&#13;
b. i-1 died          -1.68     -0.69     -1.22      -0.70      b. i-I died          -0.43     -0.09     -0.34     -0.40&#13;
c. i and i-l died   1-3.351   1-2.331    1-0.461   [-0.781     c. i and i-1 died   1-1-241   1-0.381    -1.34     -0.64&#13;
Korea                                                          Jamalca&#13;
a. I died            -1.38     -1.24     -0.79      -0.64      a. I died            -0.77     -1.15    -0.12     1-1.091&#13;
b. i-l died          -1.09     -1.04     -0.56      -0.12      b. i-I died          -1.17     -1.21     -0.60    1-0.541&#13;
c. i and i-I died   1-1.481   [-1.021    [-1.961   [-1.?91     c. I and i-1 died   [-0.701   1-1.531   1-2.811   1-0.271&#13;
Kenya                                                          Trinidad&#13;
a. i died            -0.53     -0.49     -1.03      -0.16      a. I died            -0.98     -1.30    [-1.461   [-0.411&#13;
b. i-1 died          -0.64     -0.35     -0.38      -0.35      b. i-l died          -1.55     -1.13     -0.84    1-1.071&#13;
c. 1 and i-l died    -1.40     -1.42     -1.23      -1.31      c. I and i-i died   1-2.171   [-1.211   [-0.491   1-0.221&#13;
Jordan                                                         Venezuela&#13;
a. I died            -1.76     -1.10     -1.03      -0.93      a. i died            -0.88    [-0.431   -1.02     [-0.481&#13;
b. i-l died          -1.35     -1.34     -1.19      -0.34      b. 1-1 died           0.04     -0.92    [-0.061    -0.70&#13;
c. i and i-i died    -2.28    1-2.201    [-1.171   [-1.111     c. I and i-I died   1-5.061   1-1.581   1-0.111    [0.141&#13;
Syria                                                          Pakistan&#13;
a. i died            -1.17     -1.30     -1.23      -1.31      a. I died            -0.76     -0.51     -0.48     -0.76&#13;
b. 1-1 died          -0.87     -0.77     -0.96      -1.35      b. [-1 died          -0.52     -0.33     -0.45     -0.51&#13;
c. i and i-i diad   [-2.161   1-1.961    [-1.871   [-0.901     c. I and i-i died    -1.01     -1.25     -0.82     -0.24&#13;
Malaysia                                                       Mexico&#13;
a. I died            -1.13     -1.19     -0.93      -0.53      a. i died            -0.42    [-0.651   1-0.701*  I-0.511'&#13;
b. I-i died          -1.20     -0.68     -0.72      -0.49      b. i-I died          -1.00     -0.38     -0.47     10.191&#13;
c. i and i-1 died    -1.30    1-1.671    [-0.921   1-1.121     c. I and i-1 died   [-1.881   [-1.941    10.471    -1.38&#13;
Lesotho&#13;
a. I died            -0.58     -0.13     -0.63      -0.38&#13;
b. i-l died          -0.1e     -0.3'     -0.05      -0.35&#13;
c. i and i-i died    -1.11    [-1.151    1-0.751   1-0.731&#13;
Fertility is not significantly ditferent between rrortality experience groups at the indisated parity.&#13;
[H Less than 50 cases.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
ample, the first entry for Bangladesh shows that women who have had 2 or&#13;
more children have an average of .44 fewer children if the first two sur-&#13;
vived than if the first survives and the second dies.      They have .40 fewer&#13;
than women whose first died and second survived and 1.01 fewer than those&#13;
whose first two died.     The differences are generally large, and in most&#13;
cases significant.    Only in Haiti, Sri Lanka, Paraguay and the Dominican&#13;
Republic is the pattern generally not significant.&#13;
These differences are not necessarily causally related to mortal-&#13;
ity however because both additional fertility and mortality experience may&#13;
be related to common factors such as age, education, socio-economic status&#13;
or residence.    Therefore, regression equations were used to estimate the&#13;
effect of mortality on additional births.     See Table 8)   At parity 2+, in&#13;
17 of 25 cases, both the death of the ith and ith-1 child has a significant&#13;
effect.   In an additional 5 the ith or i-lst child's death has a signifi-&#13;
cant effect.    Significance   is somewhat less at higher parities due, in&#13;
part, to smaller sample sizes.     The average effect of an infant death on&#13;
subsequent fertility in the regression is .48--larger than has been gener-&#13;
ally estimated in other studies where an effect of .20 to .33 is found and&#13;
in many cases the effect exceeds .5 larger than found in Preston, 1978.&#13;
The effect of infant mortality on additional fertility from the&#13;
regression equations can be compared with the effect of neonatal and post-&#13;
neonatal mortality on birth interval and therefore on births (Table 8).&#13;
Birth interval effects are estimated by dividing the effect of a death on a&#13;
birth interval obtained from weighted averages of regression coefficients&#13;
for parity 2 thru 6 by the average birth interval for surviving children.&#13;
This represents the lower bound of the effect for two reasons.       First the&#13;
birth interval for surviving infants is greater than the average interval&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 &#13;
TE1.E 8:     E11=9ts Df      Enf ^0 1901V Clf o Fcr:IJUUQV: Rz&lt;_z:ew UO SUrths D_s z Za   zl2ca :Q uzs'&#13;
(a) Effect of previous child death on achieved parity fr=n                    (b) t¶eighted avsr-  (c) Blrth Interval&#13;
regressions1/ Ige of effects                                                                       effects from n-an&#13;
frcm regression      Intervals2/&#13;
for 2+, 3+, 4+&#13;
and 5+&#13;
COUNTRY           Parity 2+           Parity 3+           Parity 4+&#13;
DI          Di-13/  Di           D-l-   DI          DI-l                       [Neo Natal  Post Natal&#13;
Bangladesh         0,463*    0,288*    0,389*    0.386     0,408*    0,213*         0.368            .219        .159&#13;
Colombia           0,718*    0,365*    0,802*    0,612*    0,546*    0,647*         0.558            .177        .111&#13;
FIJI               0,435     0,529*    0,460*    0,297*    0.337    0Q453*          0.436            .145        .128&#13;
Guyana             0,528*    0,396*    0.325     0,677*    0=490*    0,558*         0.504            .323        .185&#13;
Halti              0,408*    0.214     0.226     0.185     0.365     0.066          0.251            .236        .081&#13;
Indonesia          0,621*    0,511*   0,442*     0.660D   0,662*     0.2635         0.553            .261        .252&#13;
Costa Rica         0,874*    0,957*    1,003*    0.625*    0.485     0,727*1        0.739            .217        .239&#13;
Korea              0,545*    0,417*    0.836*    0.468*    0.787*    0.5890         0.589            .325        .236&#13;
lKenya             0,279*    0,428*    0,422*    0,365*    0.695:    0,298*         0.428            .220        .187&#13;
Jordan             0,968*    0,683*    0,654*    0,838*   0,694*     0.771          0.727            .249        .120&#13;
Syria              0,802*    0.690     1,004*    0,575*    1,030*    0,855*         0.808            .202        .214&#13;
Malaysia           0,554*    0,606*    0,659*    0.497*    0,621*    0,328*         0.526            .219        .146&#13;
Lesotho            0-558*    0,344*    0,289*    0,475*    0,577*    0,296*         0.422            .351        .281&#13;
Sri Lanka          0.214     0,082*    0.170     0.137    0.109      0.053          0.138            .190        .209&#13;
Nepal              0,705*    0,341*    0,458*    0,472*    0,652*    001965         0.476            .152        .182&#13;
Paraguay           0.464     0.429     0.201     0.268     0.274     0.580t         0.387                  .225&#13;
Philippines        0,495*    0,581*    0,534*    0,415*    0,467*    0,387*         0.470            .253        .175&#13;
Peru               0,552*    0,541*    0,502*    0,397*    0,412*    0,386*         0.474            .220        .223&#13;
Panama             0,604*    0,749*    0,635*    0,442*    0,704*    0,692*         0.551            .152        o135&#13;
Dominican Rep.     0.219     0.229     0.207     0.305     0.489     0.827          0.367                  .217&#13;
Jamaica           -0.079     0.536*    0.112     0.206    0.249      0.450          0.274            .204        .179&#13;
Trinidad           0.352     0.867*    0,697*    0,679*    0.733     0.382          0.610            .317        .016&#13;
Venezuela          0,840*    0.383     0.471     0,863*    1,013*    0.027          0.593                  .111&#13;
Pakistan           0,542*    0,454*    0,547*    0,405*    0,480*    0,457*         0.471            .238        .191&#13;
Mexico             0.341     0,783*    0.345     0.356     0.265     0.043          0.375&#13;
1/  Controls are age of mother, rural residences, wife°s education, husband's occupation, and wife's work status&#13;
2/  Calculated from weighted means at parities 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6&#13;
3/  DI = Death of Ith child&#13;
DI-1 = Death of i-I child&#13;
* Significant at 5%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
for all children.   Second the birth interval effect includes only the bio-&#13;
logical effect and effects of contraceptive use within the interval (spac-&#13;
ing), not the ultimate effect of infant mortality on contraceptive use to&#13;
terminate childbearing.&#13;
There is enormous variation from country to country in both esti-&#13;
mates of mortality's effect on fertility.     In all cases but two (Sri Lanka&#13;
and Jamaica) the estimates from added parity exceed those derived from&#13;
birth intervals.   Test of the relationship between the magnitude of mortal-&#13;
ity's effect on fertility showed little systematic association with country&#13;
characteristic such as GNP per capita, total fertility rates, infant mor-&#13;
tality rate, etc.    The only significant pattern found was that the effect&#13;
of post neo-natal mortality on fertility is larger the lower the level of&#13;
income, but the elasticity is small. Preston,s curvilinear pattern did not&#13;
emmerge. (Preston, 1975)&#13;
THE COST EFFECTIVENESS OF VARIOUS PROGRAMS FOR FERTILITY REDUCTION&#13;
There are some similar general issues involved in estimating the&#13;
fertility impact and cost of family planning and mortality reducing pro-&#13;
grams.  The general principle involved will first be reviewed, followed by&#13;
a separate discussion of the two estimation techniques.&#13;
The marginal cost of preventing a birth or preventing an infant&#13;
or child death is needed.    To obtain such figures it would be necessary to&#13;
separate capital from variable costs and have an estimate of how variable&#13;
costs change with level    of program activity.      Generally,  however, only&#13;
total cost and total clients or patients served are available.       Thus only&#13;
average cost per individual served can be calculated from existing statis-&#13;
tics.   This may be an inaccurate measure of marginal costs for several&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
20 &#13;
reasons0   To the extent that capital costs are included, these costs twll&#13;
not necessarily increase if numbers served increases and to tins degree,&#13;
average costs may overestimate cost per clints cr patient0 X capital and&#13;
variable costs could be separated, a prolefi, may still arise if variable&#13;
costs are rising or falling0    If clients and patients in more remote areas&#13;
or who are more difficult to treat or recruit arz the marginal group, marg-&#13;
inal cost may well be rising and *average cost would tend to Lnderastimate&#13;
cost0  A final problem that exists is that of joint costso    If several ser-&#13;
vices are offered jointly it is extremely diffIcult t0 aliocaUt joint costs&#13;
to the appropriate activity.&#13;
All these factors would have to be c&amp;rofuly weighed in making&#13;
calculations to be used for actual policy miaking0     The cost figures used&#13;
below are not made with detailed cares,    ut were drawn from a wide variety&#13;
of sources to maximize the kinds of mortality and fertility environment&#13;
considered0   The cost per birth prevented fi.gures are average costs for&#13;
existing programs with all the problems of variable, capital and joint&#13;
costs0   Thus, there may be a tendency for the birth averted cost to be&#13;
somewhat too high on average relative to those for deaths averteZd0&#13;
Cost-Effectiveness of Family Planning Program&#13;
To determine the cost of a birth prevented from a family planning&#13;
program, one needs to determine the cost of the family planning program,&#13;
the number of users of various metiods from the program, the average length&#13;
of time for which methods are usedl and the fertility that users would have&#13;
had if no method were adoptedo2/&#13;
2/  In detailed analysis the cost 'gould Ge estimated separately by method0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
The United States Agency for International Development has&#13;
assembled estimates of the resources devoted to family planning programs&#13;
and the number of married women       in the population    in 1980.    Various&#13;
estimates exist of user rates for this period and these data can be&#13;
combined to get number of users and thus cost per user. (Table 9)&#13;
The costs per user varies substantially with a low of $4.88 in&#13;
Colombia to a high of $71.61 in Kenya.     Those countries with very low cost&#13;
per user correspond well to the countries that are known to be successes in&#13;
family planning (Colombia, Sri Lanka, Thailand, Indonesia, and Korea).&#13;
In some cases very high costs per user reflect the fact that&#13;
health expenditures are difficult to separate from family planning, but for&#13;
the outliers, Kenya and Nepal, even if we delete completely all host coun-&#13;
try contributions for which this problem arises, we still find very high&#13;
cost per user ($35 for Nepal and $49 for Kenya).&#13;
To translate cost per user into cost per birth averted, we need&#13;
to make assumptions about continuation rates and the fertility foregone by&#13;
those using contraception.    Here we have arbitrarily assumed each user has&#13;
one year of coverage3/. Data from WFS on age-specific fertility rates and&#13;
age specific user rates allow us to estimate births averted.       Two estima-&#13;
tions were made.    First, we assumed that users of efficient methods had&#13;
zero fertility and would have had the age specific fertility of the average&#13;
women if she had not used contraception. Using existing age specific mari-&#13;
tal fertility, the average births averted per user was calculated.          For&#13;
countries with low user rates the approximation is probably acceptable, but&#13;
for countries with high user rates this underestimates the births averted.&#13;
Therefore, a second technique was used whereby the existing age specific&#13;
3/   If one assumed average use of 1/2 year, then clearly costs per birth&#13;
Everted would be doubled.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
TE5( 9: Onst Per User ef Per BUr-W Azzrb--ftz&#13;
UsUng Veri cus Es-UE:Szca T=lnUqaEs&#13;
$ Cost Per&#13;
Births Averted Per User      Birth Avorted&#13;
Country      $ Cost Per User/l  Low Estimate   Hlgh Estimate      Low  High&#13;
Bangladesh            20.71           o265         o282           73     78&#13;
Colombia               4o88           o233         o327            15    21&#13;
Costa Rica            15.95           o140         o310           51    114&#13;
Dominican Rep.        12.26           o249         o336           36     49&#13;
Indonesia              8.60          o187          o243           35    46&#13;
Jordan                22.47          o293          o357           63     77&#13;
Kenya                 71.61           o259         o287          250    276&#13;
Korea                  8.44           o154         o220           38     55&#13;
Malaysia              14.90           o226         o302           49     66&#13;
Mexico                15.55           c278         o368            42    56&#13;
Nepal                 57.16           o220         o242          236    260&#13;
Pakistan              10.50           o182         o190           55     58&#13;
Panama                25.60           o155         o263           97    165&#13;
Peru                   7.02           o259         o294            24    27&#13;
Philippines           13.98           o255         o308           45     55&#13;
Sri Lanka              5.60           o192         o250           22     29&#13;
/1  USAID figures for 1980 adJusted for nvi user rates for all countries&#13;
except Kenya, Jordan, Jamalca and Pakistan. Peru's figures are for&#13;
1979 so no update Is needed0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
marital fertility rate is increased by reducing the women at risk by a pro-&#13;
portion equal to the proportion using efficient methods.      The high and low&#13;
estimates of births averted are shown in Table 9 along with the correspond-&#13;
ing cost figures.&#13;
The costs per birth averted differ considerably between the two&#13;
techniques for high usage countries, Costa Rica and Panama being the clear-&#13;
est examples.    For low usage countries the values are very close.          By&#13;
either technique Nepal and Kenya are again outliers with costs considerably&#13;
in excess of any other country.&#13;
Cost per Birth Averted through Mortality Reduction&#13;
Data on cost per birth averted through family planning programs&#13;
are relatively straightforward because of the wealth of data on age-speci-&#13;
fic fertility and user rates as well as program costs. For calculating the&#13;
cost of a birth averted through a mortality reduction program, we find our-&#13;
selves with only limited data on both the cost of preventing a death and&#13;
the effect of a death averted on fertility.         In this section, we will&#13;
review the data available on the cost for averting a death and combine that&#13;
with data from the earlier section on births averted by averting an infant&#13;
death.&#13;
A number of papers have recently been prepared on the cost of&#13;
preventing a death for a number of developing countries.       These estimates&#13;
are summarized in Table 10. The costs vary widely depending on the type of&#13;
health intervention (preventive versus curative) and the estimation tech-&#13;
nique (see the range in the case of malaria).       The lowest cost estimates&#13;
come from the Narangwal program in India, and vaccination and immunization&#13;
programs in Morroco, and Kenya where for various programs the costs per&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
TcMo0 110: 0:st P          F&#13;
Cost Per Death&#13;
Author                          Matihod                       Country       Prevented&#13;
Shepard (1982)          Measles Immunization                       Ivory Coast      $490&#13;
(Includes all Joint oosts of a program&#13;
of polio, DPT, BCG and tetanus)&#13;
Barnum et al. (1980)    Total immunization progrEm                 Indonesia        $130&#13;
BCG program only                                            $445&#13;
DPTT program only                                           $135&#13;
BCG marginal                                                $101&#13;
DPTT marginal                                                $77&#13;
Barlow (1976)           Mass vaccination                          Morocco.1971&#13;
BCG                                                        $24&#13;
DPTT                                                       $38&#13;
Polio                                                   $1,100&#13;
Barnum (1980)           Immunization total                         Kenya             $85&#13;
DPT, TT, BCG only                                           $274&#13;
Measles only                                                  $50&#13;
Polio only                                                $6,357&#13;
DPT, TT, BCG                                                 $69&#13;
Measles as margiral                                          $26&#13;
Polio as marginal                                            $568&#13;
New births only                                              $70&#13;
Implementation ma;rginal all imunization                   $113&#13;
Implementation marginal DPT, BCG, polio                   $1,375&#13;
Barnum (1979)           Health program separate                    Nepal            $508&#13;
Integrated with 'amlly planning                             $271&#13;
Faruqee &amp; Johnson       Nutritton progran prenatal                 Narangwal,         $7.75&#13;
(1981)                Health care - ln4ant                       India             $2500&#13;
- Ch Id                                          $31.000&#13;
Barlow (1976)           Hospital                                   Morocco,1971&#13;
Large                                                   $2,640&#13;
Medium                                                  $2,820&#13;
Small                                                   $2,360&#13;
Horton &amp; Claquin        Hospital treatmzit for diarrhea           Bangladesh&#13;
(1982)                  Sotaki                                                    $187&#13;
Matlab                                                $1,262-1,352&#13;
Prescott (1980)         Malaria eradication                       Bangladesh    $809-25,090&#13;
Spraying and d,ugs&#13;
Walsh &amp; Warren (1979)   Mosquito oontrol - Malaria                 Cross-country    $600&#13;
(Infant and child)                      analysis&#13;
Community water supply, sanitation                      $3,600-4,300&#13;
Selective primary health care                           $200-250&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
death averted is less than $100.     Overall the figures seem consistent with&#13;
the   Walsh and Warren estimates of the cost per infant and child death&#13;
averted from selective primary care intervention of between $200 and $250.&#13;
The cost per death averted depends on the level and pattern of infant and&#13;
child deaths in a country as well as the costs of delivering health care.&#13;
The highest costs are associated with the upper range of esti-&#13;
mates for malaria erradication in Bangladesh by Prescott and the Walsh and&#13;
Warren estimates of the impact of community water supply and sanitation.&#13;
Given the limited data on costs per death averted, we will make&#13;
calculations in all cases using Warren and Walsh estimates of $250 per&#13;
death averted.   This is a conservative estimate.    Where more specific data&#13;
is available, we will make several estimates for a country.      For all esti-&#13;
mates we will use the largest and smallest estimates for the births averted&#13;
by an averted death in Table 8.&#13;
Comparing Tables 9 and 11 we find in no case is the highest cost&#13;
per birth averted from family planning above the lowest cost birth averted&#13;
through mortality reduction using $250 as the cost of an averted death.&#13;
Using country specific cost we find that in Kenya measles vaccine as a free&#13;
standing program or an add-on program is considerably less than family&#13;
planning.   If one uses the lowest estimate of the effect of mortality on&#13;
fertility, then only a measles add-on program in Kenya is superior to&#13;
family planning for reducing fertility.&#13;
The results in Table 11 are very tentative, not only because of&#13;
the wide range on effects of mortality on fertility but because of the cost&#13;
of preventing deaths.     If the Narangwal program could be replicated with&#13;
costs as low as $25 per death averted, then a wide range of countries could&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
. 26 -&#13;
(in U,,S. dollars)&#13;
Cheapest Country&#13;
Louest Cost /1       Highest Cost          Specilfic&#13;
Bangladesh            679                 1572          508 (Sotaki hospital)&#13;
Colombia              448                 2252&#13;
Guyana                496                 1351&#13;
Haiti                 966                 3086&#13;
244 (DPTT program&#13;
Indonesia             452                 992                onIy);&#13;
139 (DPTT marginal&#13;
Costa Rica            338                 1152&#13;
Korea                 424                 1059&#13;
Kenya                 584                 1337          117 (measles only);&#13;
61 maas,ies marginal&#13;
Jordan                344                 2083&#13;
Syria                 309                 1238&#13;
Malaysla              475                 1712&#13;
Lesotho               592                  890&#13;
Sri Lanka            1196                 1316&#13;
Nepal                 525                 1645          569 (integrated&#13;
family planning&#13;
MCH)&#13;
Paraguay              646                 1111&#13;
Philippines           532                 1429&#13;
Peru                  527                l136&#13;
Panama                454                 1852&#13;
Jamaica               789                 1397&#13;
Trinidad/Tobago       410                 5625&#13;
Venezuela             422                 2252&#13;
Pakistan              531                 1309&#13;
Dominican Republic    681                 1152&#13;
Naxico                667                 1316&#13;
/1  Estimated vith S250 per death averted and highest impact of mortality&#13;
on fertility.&#13;
/2  Estimated with $250 per death averted and tho smallest Impact of&#13;
mortality on fertility&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
be added, then Bangladesh, Costa Rica, Korea, Jordan, Malaysia, Nepal,&#13;
Philippines, Pakistan, Panama and marginally Indonesia could be added to&#13;
Kenya as countries where mortality reduction could be a cost-effective way&#13;
to reduce fertility. Clearly, however, cost per death averted depends on&#13;
disease patterns.   Only the poorest, high mortality countries like Nepal&#13;
and Bangladesh and countries of West Africa have real potential for very&#13;
cheap mortality reduction.4/&#13;
Caveats&#13;
The cost-effectiveness analysis above was designed to illustrate&#13;
a fairly simple way of looking at the relationship between mortality and&#13;
fertility from a policy perspective.     But the world is not so simple and&#13;
the reservations one has about the above analysis, suggests where further&#13;
reseach is needed.&#13;
The above analysis makes no explicit adjustment for a limited&#13;
demand for contraception.    In some countries like Kenya, very few people&#13;
wish to limit fertility (more may wish to space). This means there are few&#13;
acceptors of the family planning which raises the cost per user and makes&#13;
mortality reduction appear more cost effective.     In other countries, how-&#13;
ever, the low demand for family planning may result in little program&#13;
effort and cost per acceptors might well appear to be low even if it would&#13;
require substantial   expenditure to increase usage.      This might easily&#13;
distort cost-effectiveness analysis.&#13;
In using cost-effectiveness analysis one must ask the question:&#13;
are financial resources the limiting factor?      If they are not, then one&#13;
4, Evans, Hall and Warford (1981) estimate $2 per capita for coverage of a&#13;
primary health care program, but to translate this into cost per death&#13;
averted one needs death rates. With a crude birth rate of 50 and an in-&#13;
fant mortality rate of 200, there would be 10 infant deaths per 1,000&#13;
population per year.   Even if the primary health program eliminated all&#13;
infant deaths but no other deaths, the cost per death averted would be&#13;
$200.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
° 28&#13;
needs to look at the problem differently0   Xt may well be thar1  reducing in-&#13;
fant mortality is necessary to in:rease the demand for contraceptives, but&#13;
that this is not necessarily picked up by cost effectiveness analysis. To&#13;
address this issue one would need to do a more thorough analysis of contra-&#13;
ceptive use and non-use and the role played by mortality in this process.&#13;
This is a necessary further step in policy analysis of the effect of mor-&#13;
tality on fertility0&#13;
In addition, the question of ;he synergistic effect of mortality&#13;
and fertility reducing programs would have to examine the economies or dis-&#13;
economies that may arise in the supply of services as well as in the demand&#13;
for services.   This would require a separate literature review on delivery&#13;
systems.&#13;
Finally, the discussion above has been narrowly focused on the&#13;
cost effectiveness of family planning versus health prograns in reducing&#13;
fertility0   A more complete ana'ysis would require a comparison of these&#13;
with other programs such as education which affect fertility.&#13;
Summary and Conclusions&#13;
The estimates of the effect of infant mortality on fertility&#13;
reviewed in this paper show substantial variation across countries and by&#13;
the technique used0   The effect is lower for methods which depend on the&#13;
effect of mortality on birth intervals than for estimates of added births&#13;
following an infant death0   This is to be expected since birth intervals do&#13;
not take into consideration the effect of child loss on the decision to&#13;
limit rather than to space children with contraceptives0       The estimates&#13;
also differ by the technique used0 Estimation with regression gives higher&#13;
estimated effects than those de-ived from differences in means or median&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
birth intervals between those with surviving children and infant deaths.&#13;
The regression results seem more probably correct in that they control in-&#13;
directly for maternal health which would be correlated both with survival&#13;
and fecundity.&#13;
Overall, the estimates for births averted through the effects of&#13;
mortality on the birth interval are close to what is generally observed in&#13;
the literature.   The effects of a child death on subsequent fertility are&#13;
substantially higher than generally observed--about half a child on&#13;
average.   This may be due to the fact that regressions give a better&#13;
estimate of the true effect or to the better quality of WFS data than&#13;
earlier survey.'/&#13;
Even with the high estimates of the effect of an infant death on&#13;
fertility, we find only one clear case where reducing infant deaths appears&#13;
to be a more cost-effective way of reducing fertility than a family plan-&#13;
ning program. This case is Kenya. It may well be that if we had more sur-&#13;
vey data on the high mortality countries of West Africa, we might find a&#13;
number of other cases as well.     But country-specific policy making would&#13;
require more detailed cost analysis in each case and the cost analysis here&#13;
is only illustrative.&#13;
Cost-effectiveness analysis, however, implies simple tradeoffs&#13;
and either/or strategies.    In reality mortality and fertility interact in&#13;
far more complex ways which require more sophisticated analysis both of the&#13;
adoption of contraception and the delivery of health and family planning&#13;
services.&#13;
1/ Birth histories in WFS make a more complete count of births and deaths&#13;
probable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
30&#13;
Bibliography&#13;
Barlow, Robin0 "Applications of a HealthL Planning Model in Morocco."&#13;
International Journal of Health Setvices, Vol. 6, Mo0 1, 19765, p 103-121.&#13;
Barnum, Howard M. "Cost Effectiveness of Programs to Combat Co-municable&#13;
Child Diseases in Kenya." Bureau for Africa, Agency for International&#13;
Development, Washington, D.C0 AID/SOD/PDC-C-0201,   2, January .9.80.&#13;
Barnum, Ho.!, DO Tarantola and I.F. Setlady.    "Cos4 Effectivew@ss of an&#13;
Immunization Programme in Indonesiaii' Bu))etin of the World H-ealth&#13;
Organization,, Vol0 58, NoO 3, 1980:, PP   °/&#13;
Barnum., HoNo with D. Yaukey.  "Ecoiiomic Analysis of Integrated Rural&#13;
Health/Family Planning Service Projiect in Mepal.'  AID/S0D/PDC-C-0201, July&#13;
1979.&#13;
Bongaarts, John. "A Framework for &gt;'he Analysis of the Proximatz&#13;
Determinants of Fertility."   PopulEation and Development Review,,,, Vol. 2,&#13;
1970, pp. 105-132.&#13;
Bongaarts, J. "Malnutrition and Fecundity:   A Summary of Evidence." Center&#13;
for Policy Studies Working Paper Mo. 51, The Population Counc4',, December&#13;
1979.&#13;
Chen, LOCO, SO Ahmed, M0 Gesche, aid WH0H Mosley, "A Prospective Study of&#13;
Birth Interval Dynamics in Rural B5ngladesh0` Popuiation Studies, Vol0 28,&#13;
No. 2, July 1974, pp. 277297O&#13;
Coale, AoJo "The Demographic Transition,'" IUJSSP International Population&#13;
Conference Proceedings, Liege, 1973.&#13;
Evans, John, KoLo Hall, and J. Warford. ':Health Care in the Developing&#13;
World:  Problems of Scarcity and Choice tShattuck Lecture)."' The e5ew&#13;
England Journal of Medicine, Vol0 305, November 1981, PP. 1I77Tg7T7&#13;
Faruqee, R. and E. Johnson0 "Health, Nutrition and Family PlaEning in&#13;
India: A Survey of Experiments and Special Projects0" World B2nk Staff&#13;
Working Paper No. 507, February 19820&#13;
Horton, Susan and P. Claquin. "Cost-Effectiveness and User Characteristics&#13;
of Services for the Treatment of Diarrhea:   A Case Study in Bangladesh."&#13;
June 1982o M imeo.&#13;
McGreevey, William P., and M. Bircsallo "The Policy Relevance of Recent&#13;
Social Research on Fertility0" Occasional Monograph Series # 2,&#13;
Interdisciplinary Communications Frogram, Smithsonian Institute, 1974.&#13;
Perrin, E.B0 and MoCo Sheps0   "Human Reproductcion:  A Stcchas.ic Process"&#13;
Biometrics, Vol. 20, PP. 28-45.&#13;
Potter, R.G. "Birth Intervals. Structure and Change0" Popu'°ation&#13;
Studies, Vol. 17, 1973, DPP  15541660&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
Prescott, Nicholas M. "Economic Appraisal of ADP Assistance to the Malaria&#13;
Control Programme in Bangladesh." Bangladesh Public Health Program,&#13;
September 1980.&#13;
Preston, Samuel H. (ed.) The Effect of Infant and Child Mortality on&#13;
Fertility. Academic Press, 1978.&#13;
Preston, Samuel H. "Health Programs and Population Growth." Population and&#13;
Development Review, Vol 1, No. 2, 1975, pp. 189-200.&#13;
Rutstein, Shea, and V. Medica. "The Latin American Experience," in The&#13;
Effects of Infant and Child Mortality on Fertility, edited by S.H. Preston,&#13;
Academic Press, 1978.&#13;
Shepard, Donald S. "Cost-Effectiveness of the Expanded Programme of&#13;
Immunization in the Ivory Coast: A Preliminary Assessment." Center for the&#13;
Analysis of Health Practices, Harvard School of Public Health, Boston,&#13;
Massachusetts, February 1982. Draft.&#13;
Sheps, M.C. and E.B. Perrin. "The Distribution of Birth Intervals Under a&#13;
Class of Stochastic Fertility Models." Population Studies, Vol. 17, 1964,&#13;
pp. 321-331.&#13;
Vallin, Jaques and A. Lery. "Estimating the Increase in Fertility&#13;
Consecutive to the Death of a Young Child in the Effect of Infant and Child&#13;
Mortality on Fertility," edited by S.H. Preston, Academic Press, 1978.&#13;
Walsh, Julia A. and K.S. Warren. "An Interim Strategy for Disease Control in&#13;
Developing Countries." The New England Journal of Medicine, Vol. 301, No.&#13;
18, November 1979, pp. 967-974.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
World      Bank                      Confronting Urban                     these studies is presented in&#13;
Malnutrition: The Design of          Migration in West Africa:&#13;
Publicationis                        Nutrition Programs                    Demographic Aspects.&#13;
of Related                           James E. Austin                       World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Describes a framework for            415. September 1980. vi + 385 pages&#13;
Interest                             systematically carrying out urban    (including statistical annexes,&#13;
nutrition programs that examines     bibliography).&#13;
several key considerations in nutri-  Stock No. WP-0415. $15.00.&#13;
tion education, on-site feeding, take-&#13;
home feeding, nutrient-dense foods,&#13;
ration shops, food coupons, fortifica-  Economic Motivation versus&#13;
tion, direct nutrient dosage, and food  City Lights: Testing&#13;
processing and distribution.          Hypotheses about Inter-&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press,  Changwat Migration in&#13;
1980.136 pages.                       Thailand&#13;
LC 79-3705. ISBN 0-8018-2261-0,       Fred Arnold and&#13;
$6.50 (£4.50) paperback.             Susan 1H. Cochrane&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
The Costs and Benefits of             416. September 1980. 41 pages&#13;
Family Planning Programs              (including footnotes, references).&#13;
George C. Zaidan                      Stock No. WP-0416. $3.00.&#13;
A technique for measuring the&#13;
NEW                              economic returns from investing in    Economics of Supplemental&#13;
population control, with an appraisal  Eedng     of M    urised&#13;
Analyzing the Impact of              of inherent assumptions and           Feeding of Malnourished&#13;
Health Services: Project             limitations.                          Children: Leakages, Costs,&#13;
Experiences from     India,          The Johns Hopkins University Press,   and Benefits&#13;
Ghana, and Thailand                  1971. 62 pages (including             Odin K. Knudsen&#13;
Rashid Faruqee                       bibliography).                       Analyzes some of the economic&#13;
LC 7015516. ISN 0-818-137-4,issues involved in the supplemental&#13;
Reviews four categories of health    LC 70-155166. ISBN 0-801813174,       feeding of malnourished children.&#13;
indicators (environment, services    $4.00 (£2.40) paperback.              Demonstrates that supplemental&#13;
offered, services received, and                                            feeding programs are economically&#13;
changes in mortality, morbidity, and  Demographic Aspects of              justified if minimum improvements&#13;
nutritional status) in order to evaluate  emograp   c   pec     o          in mortality rates and more substan-&#13;
the impact of health projects in India,  Migration In West Africa         tial increases in productivity take&#13;
Ghana, and Thailand.                 -Volume 1                             place.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper       K. C. Zachariah                       World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
No. 546.1982. 44 pages.              and others                            451. April 1981. iv + 76 pages.&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0117-9. $3.00.           Background data on migration in       Stock No. WP-0451. $3.00.&#13;
four English-speaking countries:&#13;
Ghana, Sierra Leone, Liberia, and&#13;
The Gambia. A regional analysis       Experiments in Family&#13;
NEW                              based on these studies is presented   Planning: Lessons from&#13;
in Migration in West Africa:g&#13;
Benefits and Costs of Food           Demographic Aspects.                  the Developing World&#13;
Distribution Policies: The           World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    Roberto Cuca and&#13;
India Case                           414. September 1980. vi + 363 pages   Catherine S. Pierce&#13;
Pasquale L. Scandizzo and            (including statistical annexes,       A comprehensive review of experi-&#13;
Gurushri Swamy                       bibliography).                        mental efforts in the developing&#13;
world to determine more effective&#13;
Analyzes some of the characteristics  Stock No. WP-0414. $15.00.           ways of providing family planning&#13;
and the main consequences of the                                           services.&#13;
food distribution policies followed by&#13;
the Indian government and provides   Demographic Aspects of                The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
a quantification and a cost-benefit  Migration in West Africa              1978. 276 pages (including bibliogra-&#13;
analysis of their effects on con-    -Volume 2                             phy, index of experiments).&#13;
sumers, producers, and the govern-    K. C. Zachariah                      LC 77-16596. ISBN 0-8018-2013-8,&#13;
and others                            $19.50 (£17.50) hardcover;&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper                                            ISBN 0-8018-2014-6, $8.95 (£ 4.00)&#13;
No. 509. August 1982. 54 pages.      Background data on migration in       paperback.&#13;
four French-speaking countries: Ivory&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0011-3. $3.00.           Coast, Upper Volta, Senegal, and&#13;
Togo. A regional analysis based on&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Family Planning Programs:            Health                                  NEW&#13;
An Evaluation of Experience          Fredrick Golladay,&#13;
Roberto Cuca                         coordinating author                 Integrating Family Planning&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   Draws on experience gained from     with Health Services: Does&#13;
345. July 1979. xii + 134 pages      health components of seventy World  It Help?&#13;
(including 2 annexes, references).   Bank projects in forty-four countries  Rashid Faruqee&#13;
between 1975 and 1978.&#13;
Stock No. WP-0345. $5.00.            Emphasizes the disproportionately   Analyzes the findings of an experi-&#13;
high expenditures incurred on cura-  ment carried out in Narangwal, a&#13;
tive medicine, maintenance of expen-  village in Punjab, India, between 1968&#13;
Fertility and Education:             sive hospitals, and sophisticated   and 1974 related to health care and&#13;
What Do We Really Know?              training of medical personnel at the  family planning. The World Bank col-&#13;
Susan H. Cochrane                    cost of preventive care for the     laborated with The Johns Hopkins&#13;
A model identifying the many chan-   majority of the people. Points out  University in analyzing this data from&#13;
nels through which education might  that low-cost health care systems are  one of the best known and well-docu-&#13;
nels though determe fedtiioyanda revigt  feasible and recommends that the  mented field experiments in health&#13;
act to determine fertility and a review  Bank begin regular and direct lend-  care and family planning in the world.&#13;
between education and the interven-  ing for health, in addition to having  World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
Ing variables in the model that affect  health components as part of     No. 515. September 1982. 47 pages.&#13;
fertility.                           projects in other sectors.          ISBN 0-8213-0003-2. $3.00.&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Pr'ess,  Sector Policy Paper. February 1980.&#13;
1979.188 pages (including bibliogra-  90 pages (including 8 annexes,&#13;
phy, index).                         4 figures, map). English, French,   Kenya: Population&#13;
phy, 78-260. IB0-124-,Japanese, Spanish, andArabic. -.                   and Development&#13;
LC 78-26070. ISBN 0-8018-2140-1,     Stock Nos. PP-8001-E, PP-8001-F,    (See description under Country&#13;
$6.95 (S4.75) paperback.             PP-8001-J, PP-8001-S, PP-8001-A.    Studies listing.)&#13;
$5.00.&#13;
Fertility and Its Regulation                                             Malnourished People:&#13;
in Bangladesh                        Health Issues and Policies          A Policy View&#13;
R. Amin and                          in the Developing Countries         (See description under Development&#13;
Rashid Faruqee                       Fredrick Golladay                   listing.)&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
383. April 1980. iv + 50 pages       412. August 1980. ii + 53 pages.     Malnutrition and Poverty:&#13;
(Including references).              Stock No. WP-0412. $3.00.           Magnitude and Policy&#13;
Stock No. WP-0383. $3.00.                                                Options&#13;
Shlomo Reutlinger and&#13;
NEW                                  nEW                              Marcelo Selowsky&#13;
Health, Nutrition, and              The first large research effort in the&#13;
Food Distribution and                Family Planning in India: A         World Bank to determine the global&#13;
Nutrition Intervention: The          Survey of Experiments and           dimension of malnutrition.&#13;
Case of Chile                        Special Projects                    The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
Lloyd Harbert and                    Rashid Faruqee and                  1976; 2nd printing, 1978. 94 pages&#13;
Pasquale L. Scandizzo                Ethna Johnson                       (including 5 appendixes).&#13;
The Impact of Chile's Complementary  Surveys fourteen experiments and    LC 76-17240. ISBN 0-8018-1868-0,&#13;
Feeding Program (CFP), both on the   special projects in health, nutrition,  $4.75 (f2.85) paperback.&#13;
direct and indirect beneficiaries, Is  and family planning in India and pro-  Spanish: Desnutrici6n y pobreza:&#13;
analyzed. Describes Chile's major    poses guidelines for future Bank    magnitudes y opciones de poi7tica.&#13;
nutrition intervention programs and  projects on the basis of the survey. EdtraTens197&#13;
establishes the relative Importance of                                   E&#13;
the CFP in terms of budgetary expen-  World Bank Staff Working Paper     ISBN 84-309-0726-2, 380 pesetas.&#13;
ditures and number of beneficiaries  No. 507. February 1982. xi + 97 pages&#13;
reached. Reviews briefly the pro-   (including references).               Measuring Urban Malnutri-&#13;
grfams pasnd pottential effectiveness.  Stock No. WP-0507. $5.00.         tion and Poverty: A Case&#13;
Study of Bogota and Cali,&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.                                       Colombia&#13;
512. May 1982. v + 45 pages (including                                    Rakesh Mohan,&#13;
bibliography, annex).                                                     M. Wilhelm Wagner,&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0001-6. $3.00.                                                and Jorge Garcia&#13;
Attempts to measure the extent of&#13;
malnutrition and poverty in the cities&#13;
of Bogota and Cali, Colombia. One&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
of five papers resulting from a       Population Policy and&#13;
research program entitled "City       Family Planning Programs:&#13;
Study." a study of the workings of    bed       inPlcad&#13;
five major urban sectors in           Trends in Policy and&#13;
Colombia.                             Administration&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    Kandiah Kanagaratnam       and&#13;
447. April 1981. 80 pages (including   Catherine S. PierCe&#13;
bibliography, appendixes).             World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Stock No. WP-0447. $3.00.              411. August 1980. iii + 22 pages&#13;
(including footnotes).&#13;
Migration in West Africa:             Stock No. WP-0411. $3.00.&#13;
Demographic Aspects&#13;
K. C. Zachariah and                    Regional Aspects of Family&#13;
Julien Conde                           Planning and Fertility&#13;
The first study of the large-scale     Behavior in Indonesia&#13;
movement of people in nine West        Dov Chernichovsky and&#13;
African countries. Discusses the       Oey Astra Meesook&#13;
volume and direction of internal and&#13;
external flows and the enofintern  and  Discusses the recent decline in&#13;
external flowsractesthicsonmicrant.    Indonesia's population growth rate&#13;
social characteristics of migrants.    despite that country's relatively low&#13;
A joint World Bank-OECD study. Oxford  level of income and socioeconomic&#13;
University Press, 1981. 166 pages      development. Reviews the history&#13;
(including 22 maps, bibliography,      and organization of the family plan-&#13;
index).                                ning program and attempts to iden-&#13;
tify those factors that have been&#13;
LC 80-21352. ISBN 0-19-520186-8,       responsible for its success and&#13;
$19.95 (£10.50) hardcover,             assesses its prospects for the future.&#13;
ISBN 0-19-520187-6, $8.95 (S4.50)      World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
paperback.                             462. May 1981. 62 pages (including&#13;
appendix, references).&#13;
Nutrition and Food Needs               Stock No. WP-0462. $3.00.&#13;
in Developing Countries&#13;
Odin K. Knudsen and                    REPRINTS&#13;
Pasquale L. Scandizzo                  Health Care In the Developing World:&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.     Problems of Scarcity and Choice&#13;
(Shattuck Lecture)&#13;
328. May 1979. 73 pages (including     John R. Evans, Karen Lashman Hall, and&#13;
4 appendixes).                         Jeremy J. Warford&#13;
Stock No. WP-0328. $3.00.              World Bank Reprint Series llumber 209&#13;
Reprinted from new England Journal of Medicine,&#13;
uo/ 305 (Nlovember 1981) '1117-27.&#13;
Population and Poverty in              Stock No RP-0209. Free ofcharge&#13;
the Developing World&#13;
Nancy Birdsall                         Measurement of Deprivation and&#13;
Poverty Based on the Proportion&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.     Spent on Food: An Exploratory&#13;
404. July 1980. 96 pages (including    Exercise&#13;
2 appendixes, bibliography)            V.v Bhanoji Rao&#13;
Stock No. WP-0404. $3.00.     World Bank Reprint Series Nlumber 193&#13;
Stock No. WP-0404. $3.00.              Reprinted from World Development, vol 9, no 4&#13;
(1981):337-53&#13;
Stock No RP-0193. Free of charge&#13;
Population Policies and&#13;
Economic Development                   Nutrition, Health, and Education: The&#13;
Timothy King and others                Economic Significance of&#13;
Complementarities at Early Age&#13;
The English-language edition is        Marcelo Selowsky&#13;
out of print.                          World Bank Reprint Series. Nlumber 218&#13;
Reprinted from Journal of Development&#13;
Spanish: Polfticas de poblaci6in y     Economics, vol. 9 (19811:331-46&#13;
desarrollo econ6mico. Editorial        Stock Nlo RP-0218. free ofcharge.&#13;
Tecnos, 1975.&#13;
ISBN 84-309-0605-3, 440 pesetas.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
ORDER FORM&#13;
SEND TO:&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS                                                          WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
P.O. BOX 37525                                               or                  66, AVENUE D'IENA&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013                                                           75116 PARIS, FRANCE&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Name:&#13;
Address:&#13;
Stock or ISBN #                              Author, Title                        Qty.         Price          Total&#13;
Sub-Total Cost.&#13;
Postage &amp; handling fee for more than two free items ($1.00 each).&#13;
Total copies: _      _      Air mail surcharge ($2.00 each):&#13;
TOTAL PAYMENT ENCLOSED.&#13;
Make checks payable: WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
Prepayment on orders from individuals is requested Purchase orders are accepted from booksellers, library suppliers, libraries, and institutions&#13;
All prices include cost of postage by the least expensive means. The prices and publication dates quoted in this Catalog are subject to change&#13;
without notice&#13;
No refunds will be given for items that cannot be filled. Credit wiil be applied towards future orders&#13;
No more than two free publications will be provided without charge Requests for additional copies will be filled at a charge of US $1 00 per&#13;
copy to cover handling and postage costs.&#13;
Airmail delivery will require a prepayment of US $2.00 per copy&#13;
Mail-order payment to the World Bank need not be in U S dollars, but the amount remitted must be at the rate of exchange on the day the&#13;
order is placed. The World Bank will also accept Unesco coupons&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG 3881.5 .W57 W67 NO.556&#13;
c.3&#13;
COCHRANE, SUSAN HILL, 1943-&#13;
INFANT AND CHILD MORTALITY&#13;
AS A DETERMINANT OF&#13;
DATE   NAME AND EXTENSION  ROOM&#13;
NUMBER&#13;
, .- .o                    &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Tlhe World I3minZ&#13;
Headquarters:&#13;
1818 H Street, N W&#13;
Washington, D C 20433, U S A&#13;
Telephone (202) 477-1234&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK&#13;
Cable address INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTI'ONDC&#13;
1ErMMU* DIEL-Ci&#13;
6S, avenue d'Xena&#13;
75116 Paris, France&#13;
Telephone: 723.54.21&#13;
Telex: 842-620628&#13;
Tollyo o0ce:&#13;
Kokusai Building&#13;
1-1, Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 10, Japan&#13;
Telephone: 214-500&#13;
Telex: 781-26838&#13;
HSSi G253-22a5/MS       -     -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554890">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/02/1554890/infant-child-mortality-determinant-fertility-policy-implications
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/02/1554890/infant-child-mortality-determinant-fertility-policy-implications</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1983/02/1554890/infant-child-mortality-determinant-fertility-policy-implications</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/06/21/000178830_98101903414715/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/06/21/000178830_98101903414715/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1983-02-28T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-06-21T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Infant and child mortality as a determinant
            of fertility : the policy implications
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Two conclusions can be drawn about the
            effect of infant and child mortality on the number of
            births. First, for women who breastfeed their children an
            infant death reduces the interval between births (in the
            absence of contraception). Second, there will tend to be
            more births if infant deaths occur from the first few
            births. The estimates reported show substantial variation
            across countries and by technique used. There may be
            externalities or societal changes operating over the long
            run that require more sophisticated analysis. This paper
            presents a comparison between the cost of averting a birth
            through a family planning program and the cost of averting a
            birth indirectly by preventing an infant death. Of the 16
            countries studies, Kenya, which has a high mortality rate,
            was the one case where mortality reduction was more cost
            effective than family planning.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Infant and child mortality as a determinant
            of fertility : the policy implications
        </docna>
        <display_title>Infant and child mortality as a
            determinant of fertility : the policy implications</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1983/02/1554890/infant-child-mortality-determinant-fertility-policy-implications</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Early Child and Children's Health,Demographics,Early Childhood Development,Adolescent Health</subtopic>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Education</teratopic>
        <count>Kenya</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Cochrane, S.</author>
            <author>Zachariah, K.</author>
            <author>PHN</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Africa!$!80458</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903414715</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Primary health, including
            reproductive health, child health and health</subsc>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 556</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Education</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Health, Nutrition &amp; Population</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0147-0</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Birth rate; Cost effectiveness; Fertility;
            Fertility rate; Infant mortality; Family planning programs
            age at marriage,age of marriage,Birth
            Intervals,births,breastfeeding,child bearing,Child
            Deaths,child mortality,child survival,Contraceptive
            Usage,Contraceptive Use,contraceptives,economic
            development,family planning,family size,fertility
            behavior,Health,infant death,infant
            mortality,infertility,legal status,maternal
            health,mortality,mortality decline,mortality
            rates,motivation,neonatal death,neonatal mortality,never
            used contraceptives,Nutrition,nutritional
            status,parents,Population,population growth,reproductive
            life,use of contraception,World Fertility Survey
        </keywd>
        <owner>Office of the Regional Vice Pres (AFRVP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP556</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>IMR</ml:concept><ml:concept>Maternal and Child Mortality</ml:concept><ml:concept>U5MR</ml:concept><ml:concept>Birth Spacing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vaccines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Community Based Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Raising Awareness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Malaria</ml:concept><ml:concept>Breastfeeding</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infant and Child Mortality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Family Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contraceptives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Immunizations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Food Distribution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Kenya</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>