<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP746&#13;
School Enrollment in Indonesia&#13;
Dov Chernichovsky&#13;
Oey Astra Meesook&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 746&#13;
iL     coy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
L/C-&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 746                                      .      ?&#13;
£L)47&#13;
School Enrollment in Indonesia&#13;
INTERNAT7ONA' &amp;1iON7TM1.y FUND&#13;
Dov Chernichovsky                     10DAt7 1   RI7D&#13;
Oey Astra Meesook                   OCT (    j&#13;
IN'NATIOAL b..A&#13;
HECONSr.Mfl ND i 'N&#13;
WA!'n" D,C. 20431&#13;
The World Banik&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright (© 1985&#13;
The Intemational Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing August 1985&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To present the&#13;
results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been prepared&#13;
in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed texts, and the World&#13;
Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a token charge&#13;
to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The World Bank does not accept responsibility for the views expressed herein, which&#13;
are those of the authors and should not be attributed to the World Bank or to its&#13;
affiliated organizations. The findings, interpretations, and conclusions are the results&#13;
of research supported by the Bank; they do not necessarily represent official policy of&#13;
the Bank. The designations employed, the presentation of material, and any maps used&#13;
in this document are solely for the convenience of the reader and do not imply the&#13;
expression of any opinion whatsoever on the part of the World Bank or its affiliates&#13;
conceming the legal status of any country, territory, city, area, or of its authorities, or&#13;
concerning the delimitation of its boundaries, or national affiliation.&#13;
The most recent World Bank publications are described in the annual spring and fall&#13;
lists; the continuing research program is described in the annual Abstracts of Current&#13;
Studies. The latest edition of each is available free of charge from the Publications Sales&#13;
Unit, Department T, The World Bank, 1818 H Street, N.W., Washington, D.C. 20433,&#13;
U.S.A., or from the European Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'lina, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Dov Chemichovsky, with Ben Gurion University (Israel), is a consultant to the&#13;
World Bank. Oey Astra Meesook is an economist in the Country Policy Department&#13;
of the Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging-in-Publication Data&#13;
Chernichovsky, Dov.&#13;
School enrollment in Indonesia.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 746)&#13;
Includes bibliographical references.&#13;
1. School attendance--Indonesia. 2. Schools--&#13;
Indonesia--Location. 3. Students--Indonesia--&#13;
Socioeconomic status. I. Oey Astra Meesook.&#13;
II. Title. III. Series.&#13;
LC145.16C44     1985       371.2'19'598          85-16764&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0584-0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ABSTRACT: SCHOOL ENROLLMENT IN INDONESIA&#13;
The objective of this paper is to relate children's school&#13;
enrollment and level of educational attainment to their household&#13;
socioeconomic characteristics and the availability of schools. For&#13;
primary school enrollment, two issues are explored. The first concerns&#13;
the characteristics of those children who do not attend school, and the&#13;
reasons for this, given the relative availability of facilities. The&#13;
second concerns household expenditures on education, in particular in&#13;
relation to the availability of facilities and households' ability and&#13;
willingness to pay for education, given that many schools are privately&#13;
owned.&#13;
The data sources are the 1978 National Socioeconomic Survey&#13;
(SUSENAS) and the 1976/77 Village Social Facilities Survey (FASDES).&#13;
The SUSENAS sample of some 6,000 households provides a representative&#13;
geographical distribution of the population of Indonesia. Pertinent&#13;
information from the SUSENAS includes various household socioeconomic&#13;
characteristics. The household data are complemented by community-level&#13;
data pertaining to the availability of social services in villages from&#13;
the FASDES Survey.&#13;
The study shows that education in Indonesia, especially beyond&#13;
the primary level, is very much an income-related phenomenon. Education&#13;
is also strongly influenced by attitudes as implied by the evidence that&#13;
the relatively rich and well-educated shun vocational training, even&#13;
though it appears to yield a comparable return in the market to general&#13;
training. In addition, the fact that girls do not receive more&#13;
- iii -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
schooling may be related to parents' attitudes, although their behavior&#13;
may also be influenced by the lower market returns to girls' education.&#13;
The data clearly show that availability of facilities promotes&#13;
school attendance and educational attainment. Yet, household&#13;
considerations should not be disregarded. In the case of primary&#13;
schools, which are almost universally available, parents' decisions are&#13;
critical. Thus policies to increase enrollment may have to deal with&#13;
parents' attitudes as well as the opportunity cost to the household of&#13;
children's schooiing.&#13;
- iv -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Contents&#13;
Page&#13;
I.  Introduction                                                         1&#13;
II.  The Data and the Setting                                             4&#13;
II. l The Data                                                       4&#13;
II. 2  Rewards to Schooling in Indonesia                             6&#13;
II. 3  School Enrollment and Household Characteristics               8&#13;
II. 4  Co0t of SchooLing and Other Obstacles to School Attendance 10&#13;
III.  Determinants of School Enrollment                                   17&#13;
III. I Some Conceptual and Analytic Considerations                  17&#13;
III. 2  Determinants of School Enrollment:   Findings               20&#13;
IV. Conclusion                                                           25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
School Enrollment in Indonesia&#13;
I.       Introduction&#13;
Primary education in Indonesia is almost universal. It extends over&#13;
the first six grades and covers over 90 percent of children between 7 and 12&#13;
years of age. The coverage of secondary education is far less complete; of&#13;
children in the secondary-school age groups (13 to 15 and 16 to 18), only&#13;
about 22Z are enrolled in school. 11 However, the situation has improved&#13;
considerably since 1960 when primary school enrollment rates were around 58X&#13;
and secondary school rates were about 6 percent.&#13;
The present situation reflects a concerted effort on the part of the&#13;
government of Indonesia over a number of years to increase and equalize&#13;
educational opportunities throughout the country. The numbers of primary and&#13;
junior secondary schools increased by 62 percent between 1968 and 1979, while&#13;
the number of senior secondary schools increased by 96 percent over the same&#13;
period. Total school enrollment at all levels rose by 7.5 percent per year&#13;
between 1970/71 and 1980/81, with the rates of increase being greater at the&#13;
higher levels of schooling. Whereas only 23 percent of first-grade pupils in&#13;
1964/65 had graduated in 1970, close to 50 percent of first graders in 1969/70&#13;
graduated in 1975/76. The literacy rate improved from 47 percent in 1960 to&#13;
61 percent in 1971 and 72 percent in 1980. 2/&#13;
1/ World Bank, World Development Report 1982, Table 23.&#13;
2/ Ward Henevald, "Indonesian Education in the Seventies", Southeast Asian&#13;
Affairs, 1979, pp. 142-153.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
The allocation of resources for the construction of primary schools&#13;
has been biased in favor of the areas with fewer facilities. In Phase I of&#13;
the INPRES-SD construction program (1973-1974), allocations were made to&#13;
provinces based on the total number of primary school-age children (7-12) who&#13;
were not enrolled in school. INPRES-SD also specified that each district&#13;
(kabupaten) should receive enough units to allow for at least one building in&#13;
each subdistrict (kecamatan). The criterion used in Phase II (1975/76) was&#13;
similar but instead based on the projection of new pupils expected to be&#13;
accommodated in the district/municipality up to 1978. Similarly, the&#13;
expansion of 1,000 junior secondary schools in 1982/83 was to be allocated&#13;
first to districts where there were no junior secondary schools at all and&#13;
then to districts where there were no government junior secondary schools.&#13;
The government also made an attempt to increase the utilization of&#13;
educational services. It abolished tuition fees for the first three grades in&#13;
primary schools in 1977 and for the last three grades in 1978. Writers in the&#13;
1970's had the impression that fee levels before the abolition were already&#13;
high for many students and that raising them would limit enrollment to the&#13;
relatively well-to-do. 3/ It has also been observed that school enrollment&#13;
rates have increased dramatically, especially since school fees were&#13;
abolished. However, this statement is difficult to evaluate without a fuller&#13;
understanding of the obstacles to schooling at the household level, and&#13;
without taking into account the simultaneous rapid increase in school places&#13;
and the transfer of some students from religious schools. 4/&#13;
3/ Ruth Daroesman, "Finance of Education, Part I", Bulletin of Indonesian&#13;
Economic Studies, Vol. VII, No. 3, November 1971.&#13;
4/ Ward Henevald, "Indonesian Education in the Seventies", Southeast Asian&#13;
Affairs, 1979, p. 143.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
The objective of this paper is to study the relationship between&#13;
children's school enrollment and their household characteristics on the one&#13;
hand, and the availability of schools on the other. The study is based on&#13;
data collected from some 6,000 households in 1978 as part of the SUSENAS&#13;
survey, and community-level data concerning schooling facilities collected&#13;
from 60,000 villages in the 1976/77 Village Social Facilities Survey&#13;
(FASDES). For primary school enrollment, it is of major interest to explore&#13;
two issues. The first concerns the characteristics of those children who do&#13;
not attend school, and the reasons for this phenomenon, given the relative&#13;
availability of facilities. The second concerns some qualitative aspects of&#13;
primary education as they manifest themselves in household expenditures on&#13;
education. At the secondary level, the issues are similar, although more&#13;
attention is paid to the availability of facilities and households' ability&#13;
and willingness to pay for education, since many schools are privately owned.&#13;
These research objectives should be interpreted in conjunction with&#13;
the government's stated goals in education. These include the provision of&#13;
manpower required by the modern sector of the economy; the commitment to&#13;
provide education for all citizens; and the joint responsibility of parents,&#13;
the community and the government in the provision of education.&#13;
In the following section, the data used in the analysis are described&#13;
and some background information is provided. Specific attention is paid to&#13;
the role of education in the determination of wages in the formal labor&#13;
market. This is followed in Section III by the introduction of a conceptual&#13;
framework leading to the analysis of school enrollment and household schooling&#13;
expenditures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
II. The Data and the Setting&#13;
II. 1    The Data&#13;
The data used in this study are from the data tapes of the National&#13;
Socioeconomic Survey (SUSENAS) conducted by the Central Bureau of Statistics&#13;
in 1978. The survey was carried out in four rounds, each covering a three-&#13;
month period; these were centered around February, May, August and November.&#13;
This study is based on the May round.&#13;
The basic characteristics of the sample are presented in Table 1.&#13;
The regional and urban/rural distributions of the sample, shown in columns 1&#13;
and 2, are almost identical to those of the 1971 Population Census and the&#13;
1976 Intercensal Population Survey. Nearly two-thirds of the population are&#13;
concentrated on Java. Outside of the capital city of Jakarta, most of the&#13;
remainder of Java is classified as rural. Rural areas contain a slightly&#13;
smaller proportion of the total population in the Outer Islands. The SUSENAS&#13;
sample thus provides a representative geographical distribution of the&#13;
population of Indonesia.&#13;
Average household size, shown in column 3, is 4.6 persons overall.&#13;
Javanese families tend to be smaller than families on the Outer Islands. This&#13;
phenomenon, associated with Java's relatively low fertility rate 5/, is&#13;
consistent with the figures in column 4, which show a higher proportion of&#13;
persons age 10 and above in Java than in the Outer Islands.&#13;
5/ Dov Chernichovsky and Oey Astra Meesook, Regional Aspects of Family&#13;
Planning and Fertility Behavior in Indonesia, World Bank Staff Working&#13;
Paper No. 462, May 1981.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 5 -&#13;
Table 1:  BASIC SAMPLE CHARACTERISTICS, SUSENAS 1978 DATA, INDONESIA, 1978&#13;
Region                   Population   Rural      Average   % Age 10  Household&#13;
Population Household   &amp; above    Monthly&#13;
Size              Expenditure 1/&#13;
(%)        (%)      (persons)    (X)        (Rp)&#13;
Java                       65.76      83.67        4.6       71.8      23,574&#13;
DKI Jakarta             3.55       0.00        5.7       71.9      82,197&#13;
West Java              20.38      89.27        4.4       70.5      24,795&#13;
Central Java           17.98      90.00        4.8       70.8      17,183&#13;
DI Yogyakarta           2.09      84.72        4.7       76.6      21,840&#13;
East Java              21.76      86.84        4.5       73.3      18,585&#13;
Outer Islands              34.24      82.48        5.2       67.6      31,437&#13;
Sumatra                17.22      81.79        5.3       67.3      33,309&#13;
Bali &amp; Nusa Tenggara    5.38      92.65        5.0       68.0      22,719&#13;
Kalimantan              4.63      75.30        5.0       68.0      34,120&#13;
Sulawesi                6.72      81.63        5.3       67.9      31,582&#13;
Maluku &amp; Irian Jaya     0.29      58.12        5.7       68.4      40,799&#13;
Indonesia                 100.00      83.39        4.8       70.8      26,233&#13;
** Exchange rates applicable for the period are&#13;
$ 1 = Rp 415 before November 15, 1978&#13;
$ 1 = Rp 625 after November 15, 1978&#13;
Source: SUSENAS 1978 data tapes, Biro Pusat Statistik, Jakarta.&#13;
1/ Based on the second round of the survey conducted in May 1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
Household monthly consumption expenditure will be the basic welfare&#13;
indicator used in this study. Column 5 presents this indicator which varies&#13;
substantially from around Rp 17,000 in Central Java to over Rp 30,000 in&#13;
Sumatra, Kalimantan and Sulawesi. Jakarta shows a very high average&#13;
expenditure, being entirely urban. Likewise Maluku and Irian Jaya where the&#13;
urban population is overrepresented in the sample. Average monthly&#13;
expenditures are lower in,Java than in the Outer Islands, and they also show&#13;
more variation.&#13;
These household data are complemented by community-level data&#13;
pertaining to the availability of social services in 60,000 villages from the&#13;
Village Social Facilities Survey (FASDES) conducted in 1976/77.&#13;
II.2     Rewards to Schooling in Indonesia&#13;
The rewards to education cover a broad spectrum of market, nonmarket&#13;
and household activities. While it is beyond the scope of this paper to&#13;
discuss this issue in detail, it is of interest, nonetheless, to have a&#13;
relatively clear notion of the role of formal education in individuals'&#13;
relative well-being. For this purpose the figures in Table 2 are most&#13;
useful. These wage equations show the effect of education on the hourly wages&#13;
of formally employed males and females, while controlling for type of&#13;
community and region.&#13;
All across Indonesia we see that the higher the level of a person's&#13;
education, the higher his or her level of earnings. At the high school level,&#13;
the returns to females' vocational training in Java are higher than those to&#13;
general or teacher training. The differences in returns between primary&#13;
school and high school education, and between high school and higher education&#13;
are particularly noticeable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
Table 2: RERESSICN OEFFICIENTS ON THE NATURtL LOXiRITtM OF HOURLY&#13;
WMS   OF MALE AND FB5AIE EMWL0EES&#13;
Java                  Oater Islands&#13;
Independent Variable           Males     Femles       Mbles           Femles&#13;
Constant                       -2.5553   -2.4231      -2.5842         -2.5906&#13;
Ar-                           0.0891    0.0689      0.0954           .0.0694&#13;
(10.02)     (4.99)      (12.54)          (4.07)&#13;
Age Squared                  -0.0009    -0.0006     -0.0009          -0.0007&#13;
(-7.58)    (-3.82)      (-9.51)         (-3.03)&#13;
Education*&#13;
Incanplete Primaty            0.2742    0.1528      0.2355            0.3081&#13;
(4.38)     (2.04)      (3.84)           (2.88)&#13;
Primary                       0.5213     0.3406     0.4283            0.3266&#13;
(7.78)     (3.09)      (7.06)           (2.73)&#13;
High School: General &amp;        1.1575     1.5691     0.8584            1.3973&#13;
Teacher Training          (15.50)    (13.36)      (13.37)         (11.95)&#13;
High School: Vocational       1.0062     1.8159     0.8535            1.2931&#13;
Trainirg                  (11.64)     (9.01)      (11.69)          (9.89)&#13;
Higher Eeication              1.8797     2.6082     1.3565            1.7315&#13;
(14.77)    (10.66)      (13.83)          (8.59)&#13;
'Rsidence**&#13;
Urban                         0.1985    -0.1297     0.0501            0.0173&#13;
(4.32)    (-1.91)      (1.43)           (0.23)&#13;
Central Java &amp; Yogyakarta    -0.3498    -0.1424&#13;
(-7.21)    (-2.01)&#13;
East Java                    -0.3898    -0.2813&#13;
(-7.38)    (-3.49)&#13;
Kalirantan                                          0.4510            0.4512&#13;
(5.96)           (2.84)&#13;
Sunatra                                             0.3672           0.4570&#13;
(5.22)          (3.48)&#13;
Sulavasi                                            0.3892           0.1841&#13;
(5.22)          (1.26)&#13;
isa Tenggira                                        -0.0402         -0.3444&#13;
(-0.49)        (-2.30)&#13;
Mluku &amp; Irian Jaya                                  0.4715           0.4431&#13;
(5.53)          (2.25)&#13;
N                    1409        784          1833            545&#13;
2-&#13;
Adjlsted R                      0.4625    0.3484      0.3805           0.4677&#13;
Source: Data tapes of SUSENAS 1978, Biro Pusat Statistik, Jakarta&#13;
Note : t-statistics are given in parentheses&#13;
* DxmIy variables; those with no schooling aomtted.&#13;
* Dumry variables; rural omitted.&#13;
*** DmW variables; 'Abst Java anitted in Java equation and Bali oritted&#13;
in Outer Islands equation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8 -&#13;
Compared with females, males start out with higher earnings but,&#13;
after controlling for other factors, females are better compensated than males&#13;
at higher levels of schooling. 61 In urban areas of Java, the returns to&#13;
higher education are higher for males than for females.&#13;
II. 3       School Enrollment and Household Characteristics&#13;
Table 3 presents the proportions of children of different age-sex&#13;
groups who were enrolled in school in 1978. The age groups correspond to the&#13;
official ages for primary school (7 to 12), junior high school (13 to 15) and&#13;
senior high school (16 to 18). However, enrollment here can be at any level.&#13;
The table shows a considerable variation in school enrollment rates&#13;
by region (of which only a Java/Outer Islands breakdown is shown), urban/rural&#13;
location, level of educational attainment of the parents, occupation of the&#13;
father, and level of household per capita consumption expenditure.&#13;
There is little difference in the proportions of children attending&#13;
school in Java as compared to the Outer Islands, but what is clearly shown is&#13;
the advantage to higher educational attainment of living in urban areas which&#13;
have more and better schooling facilities.&#13;
With regard to the education of the household head, it can be seen&#13;
that children whose parents have academy/university level education are more&#13;
than proportionately represented across all levels of schooling, whereas of&#13;
those children whose parents have had no education only 20 percent of males&#13;
and 10 percent of females attend senior high school.&#13;
6/ The figures conce'rning women with higher education are unfortunately based&#13;
on small samples.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 3: PROPORTIONS OF CHILDREN IN DIFFERENT SOCIOECONOMIC GROUPS&#13;
ATTENDING SCHOOL, BY AGE GROUP AND SEX, INDONESIA, 1978&#13;
(Z)&#13;
Ages 7-12      Ages 13-15      Ages 16-18&#13;
Socioeconomic Characteristic        Male  Female    Male  Female   Male   Female&#13;
Indonesia                            84    82        60    48        35    27&#13;
Region of Residence:&#13;
Java                             82    81        59    43       31     26&#13;
Outer Islands                    86    84       62     57       40     30&#13;
Location of Residence:&#13;
Urban                            92    89       82     75       60     49&#13;
Rural                            82    81       55     41       28     21&#13;
Education of Household Head:&#13;
No schooling                     72    72       41     31       20     10&#13;
Not completed primary school     86    80       60     41       27     23&#13;
Primary school                   90    90        76    65       57     50&#13;
Junior high school               97    95       84     93       72     70&#13;
Senior high school               99    96      100     96       92     76&#13;
Academy/university               98   100      100    100      100     99&#13;
Education of Spouse:&#13;
No schooling                     80    75       48     34       23     13&#13;
Not completed primary school     86    85       67     56       37     33&#13;
Primary school                   89    92       84     67       70     64&#13;
Junior high school               97    98       95     97       92     89&#13;
Senior high school              100   100      100    100       95     83&#13;
Academy/university              100    91      100    100      100    100&#13;
Occupation of Household Head:&#13;
Professional, technical          89    89       70     64       49     32&#13;
Professional                    100    93       91     63       87     75&#13;
Administrative, executive&#13;
and managerial                100   100      100    100      100   100&#13;
Clerical                         94    97       98     77       76     73&#13;
Sales                           100    92       93     76       76    46&#13;
Services                         86    77       66     64       36    45&#13;
Agricultural                     80    81       52     38       24     19&#13;
Production workers               90    85       56     27       49     23&#13;
Production workers               90    81       69     47       36    25&#13;
Production workers &amp;&#13;
transport equipment&#13;
operators                     90     90       50     40       64     12&#13;
Monthly Per Capita Expenditure Groups&#13;
(Rupiah)&#13;
&lt; 2,000                   81     76       56    31        12     4&#13;
2,000 - 2,999                    78    74       36     34       21    11&#13;
3,000 - 4,999                    84    82       58     43       26     13&#13;
5,000 - 9,999                    88    87       71     59       44     34&#13;
10,000 or more               94     92       87    62        69    38&#13;
Source:  Data tapes of SUSENAS 1978, Biro Pusat Statistik, Jakarta.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
Even more striking is the fact that, in spite of the high average&#13;
enrollment rate for the primary-school age group, there still exists a great&#13;
deal of variation in children's schooling by level of schooling of parents.&#13;
This suggests that, rather than concentrating solely on the problems of&#13;
secondary education, we should look more closely at the reasons for failure to&#13;
attend primary school.&#13;
Significant variations in enrollment rates can also be observed by&#13;
the occupation of the household head. Only the children of members of the&#13;
administrative, executive and managerial class can report full attendance at&#13;
all schooling levels. Indeed, children of agricultural and blue-collar&#13;
workers are clearly underrepresented at both the junior high and senior high&#13;
school levels.&#13;
Income level, approximated here by household monthly consumption&#13;
expenditure, is also important in the education of children, with the&#13;
proportion of children attending school increasing steadily with the level of&#13;
household per capita expenditure.&#13;
In sum, the variations in school enrollment by location, parents'&#13;
schooling and household per capita expenditure class are more pronounced for&#13;
older age groups. Enrollment rates are consistently higher for boys than for&#13;
girls; the differentials are small or negligible for children whose parents&#13;
are highly educated, but are greater among poorer households and those&#13;
children whose parents have had little or no schooling.&#13;
II.4     Cost of Schooling and Other Obstacles to School Attendance&#13;
In this section, we assess the economic burden of sending children to&#13;
school; this affects the rate of return to schooling in any given market, and&#13;
has bearing on parents' decision to send a child to school.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Formal education entails direct costs, such as tuition and other&#13;
fees, uniforms, books, transport, etc., and indirect costs, such as the&#13;
foregone earnings and other contributions of children who attend school.&#13;
Estimates of the direct cost of schooling and its burden on the&#13;
household's budget are reported in Tables 4 and 5. The figures reported in&#13;
Table 4 provide estimates of per child expenditures by level of schooling. 7/&#13;
Since girls at higher levels of schooling on average belong to&#13;
better-off households compared with boys, it is not surprising that the&#13;
estimated expenditures for girls are higher than those for boys (although&#13;
there are some inconsistencies in the results). These estimates are meant to&#13;
be averages disregarding numerous other factors which may affect schooling&#13;
besides the grade and sex of children.&#13;
Actual expenditures are reported in Table 5. This table gives the&#13;
proportions of households reporting some expenditure on each of the three&#13;
expenditure categories related to schooling, as well as the average&#13;
expenditures for those reporting any schooling expenditure. 8/ Schooling&#13;
expenditures are much lower in rural than in urban areas. For comparable&#13;
locations, they are lower in the Outer Islands compared with Java. On the&#13;
7/ These estimates were obtained by running a regression of household&#13;
expenditures on schooling on the numbers of children enrolled in different&#13;
levels of school, with the numbers of boys and girls entering&#13;
separately. See Appendix Table 1 for detailed estimates.&#13;
8/ These numbers are all preliminary since we are not yet sure that we&#13;
properly understand the data. Many households with children in school&#13;
report no schooling expenditures whatsoever. We need to check how&#13;
frequently and when exactly tuition fees and school dues are paid. At the&#13;
moment we are using the second round of SUSENAS 1978 (the May round which&#13;
we think was collected over the period April to June). Schooling expendi-&#13;
tures are not usually made evenly throughout the year and there may not be&#13;
a "typical" month or three-month period when they are made. We may&#13;
therefore have to look at the other rounds of SUSENAS as well and attempt&#13;
to get some kind of annual estimate of schooling expenditures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
Table 4: ESTIMATED PER CHILD MONTHLY SCHOOLING EXPENDITURES BY LEVEL OF&#13;
SCHOOL, BY SEX, INDONESIA, 1978&#13;
(Rp)&#13;
Level of School          Tuition Fees   School Dues    Supplies and Books   Total&#13;
Primary School&#13;
Male                       57            27                48            132&#13;
Female                     85            35                70            190&#13;
Junior High School&#13;
Male                      521           162               179            862&#13;
Female                    668          347                 75          1,090&#13;
Senior High School&#13;
Male                      975           162               288          1,425&#13;
Female                    186           232               423            841&#13;
University                  4,555           600             1,657          6,812&#13;
Source:  Data tapes of SUSENAS 1978, Biro Pusat Statistik, Jakarta.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 5: HOUSEHOLD MONTHLY EXPENDITURES ON SCHOOLING, INDONESIA, 1978&#13;
Java              Outer Islands            Indonesia&#13;
Urban  Rural  Total     Urban  Rural  Total    Urban  Rural  Total&#13;
% of Households Reporting Expenditures on&#13;
Tuition fees                               36     15     19       32      16     19       35     16      19&#13;
School dues                                14     12     13        11     12     12       13     12      12&#13;
Supplies and books                         20     20     20        19     19     19       19     20     20&#13;
Any schooling expenditure                  52     37     39        52     39     41       52     38     40&#13;
Average Household Expenditure (Rp) 1/ on&#13;
Tuition fees                            2,237    254    679     1,056    290    457    1,821    266    602&#13;
School dues                               497    145    221      237     146    166      405    145    202&#13;
Supplies and books                        506    146    223      298     230    245      433    175    231&#13;
All schooling expenditures              3,240    545  1,123     1,592    666    868    2,659    587   1,034&#13;
% of Expenditure in Total Household Expenditure&#13;
Tuition fees                             3.23   1.09   2.05     2.06    0.80   1.16     2.89   0.96    1.70&#13;
School dues                              0.72   0.62   0.66     0.46    0.4t   0.42     0.64   0.52   0.57&#13;
Supplies and books                       0.73   0.63   0.67     0.58   0.64    0.62     0.69' 0.63    0.65&#13;
All schooling expenditures               4.68   2.34   3.39     3.10    1.85   2.20     4.23   2.11   2.93&#13;
1/ Averages refer to households reporting some schooling expenditure only.&#13;
Source:  Data tapes of SUSENAS 1978, Biro Pusat Statistik, Jakarta&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
whole, direct costs of education constitute about 3 percent of the household&#13;
budget, and is a luxury good in that it is sensitive to levels of income.&#13;
The indirect economic burden of schooling can be inferred from the&#13;
activities of children attending school compared with those who do not. This&#13;
is shown in Table 6.&#13;
The proportion of children in each age-sex group who worked during&#13;
the reference week is far greater among those who did not attend school. In&#13;
fact, astonishingly high proportions of those out of school are working, even&#13;
in the 10 to 12 age group. 9/ The proportions are higher for boys and for&#13;
older children. In order to be certain that we are not overstating the extent&#13;
to which children work, we also show the proportions who report themselves as&#13;
employed with no other activities during the reference period (i.e., they&#13;
worked and/or were absent from work only). Although a lower proportion of&#13;
girls work, very large numbers of them assist in housework. Helping around&#13;
the house is an important additional activity for both boys and girls who&#13;
attend school.&#13;
The data provide further information relating to the reasons children&#13;
do not attend school; these are reported in Tables 7 and 8. The results are&#13;
not easy to interpret, since there is no explanation of what "other" or even&#13;
"too difficult" stand for. "Other" for instance, may be related to child&#13;
labor in the household economy. Nonetheless, it is evident from the data&#13;
reported in Table 7 that economic reasons, that is, "no funds" and "school too&#13;
far away" are dominant reasons for not attending school. That is, incomes and&#13;
prices, the latter expressed partly in terms of distance, are obstacles to&#13;
9/ The question was asked for each of the seven days preceding the interview.&#13;
A person could report more than one activity on any day. The question was&#13;
only asked of those ages 10 and over; thus we are unable to determine the&#13;
extent to which children under 10 work or help around the house.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 1S -&#13;
Table 6: ACTIVITIES OF SCHOOL-AGE O41LOREN, BY AGE GUP A      SEX, IDOKESIA, 1978&#13;
(S reporting activity)&#13;
Mal*                                 Female&#13;
10-12    13-15    16-18    19-25       10-12    13-15    16-18     19-25&#13;
Attending School&#13;
Employed                            5        7        11       16          3         5        4       11&#13;
Working                          5        7        11       13          3         5        4       11&#13;
Working-or away from&#13;
work only                      3        5        8        9           2         3        3        4&#13;
Looking for work                    0        0        0        I           0        0        0        0&#13;
Taking care of house               56       55       56       41          77        78       76       71&#13;
Other nonmarket activities         31       29       30       41           14       14       16       24&#13;
Not Attending School&#13;
Employed                           48       72       78       87          43       44        46       41&#13;
Working                         46       70       75       86          39       41        43       39&#13;
Working or away from&#13;
work only                     48       64       73       79          34       29       31        21&#13;
Looking for work                    8        7        9        9           2        2        3        2&#13;
Taking care of house               17       22       11        9          62       66       65        76&#13;
Other nonmarket activities         26        9        a        6           2        4         3        2&#13;
Source: Data tapes of SUSENAS 1978, Biro Pusat Statistik, Jakarta.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
Table 7: REASONS GIVEN FOR CHILDREN BEING OUT OF SCHOOL&#13;
BY AGE GROUP, REGION AND SEX&#13;
(s)&#13;
Ages 7-12                   Ages 13-15                  Ages 16-18&#13;
Java      Outer Islands      Java       Outer Islands     Java      Outer Islands&#13;
Reason for Not               Male Female   Male  Female   Male Female   Male Female    Male Female   Male Female&#13;
Attending School&#13;
Had sufficient schooling       1.9   8.4     0.0   5.3     5.0   4.9     5.6   7.8      3.9  10.0    10.7   9.0&#13;
No funds                      48.1  49.1    49.3  43.9    51.5  47.7    56.9  55.8     55.9  49.8    53.4  55.9&#13;
Too difficult                 12.5  20.4    16.4  17.9    13.1  12.4    14.5  11.6     11.8  11.7    11.3   8.3&#13;
School too far away           9.6    2.4     0.0   0.0     7.0   8.4     4.5    1.1     5.8   5.5     2.8   1.5&#13;
Other                         27.9  19.8    34.2  33.0    23.4  26.6     18.6  23.7   22.7   23.0    21.8  25.3&#13;
Source: Data tapes of SUSENAS 1978, Biro Pusat Statistik, Jakarta.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
about half of school-age children reported as being out of school. There are&#13;
no appreciable differences between the sexes. Lack of funds appears to be&#13;
slightly more important for the older children, as might be expected.&#13;
Table 8 reports the same kind of information across provinces. The&#13;
interpretation of this table should be done in conjunction with the&#13;
availability of schools in different regions.   It can be seen that parts of&#13;
Sumatra, Nusa Tenggara, Kalimantan, and Sulawesi have relatively high&#13;
proportions of children who report that they are not in school because the&#13;
school is "too far away."&#13;
III.     Determinants of School Enrollment&#13;
III.1    Some Conceptual and Analytic Considerations&#13;
It is evident from the data presented thus far that school enrollment&#13;
is influenced by household characteristics on the one hand and availability of&#13;
schooling facilities on the other. Before assessing the relative&#13;
contributions of different factors to school enrollment, we turn to some&#13;
analytic considerations which will guide the analysis as far as the choice of&#13;
variables is concerned.&#13;
The economic analysis of children's schooling is often linked to the&#13;
analysis of the determinants of fertility behavior. The focus of these&#13;
analyses has been the parents' decision regarding the number of children they&#13;
have (quantity) and child quality, often measured by the level of educational&#13;
attainment of the children. This general notion of a quantity-quality trade-&#13;
off, formalized by Theil 101 does not permit an explicit accounting of the&#13;
costs of schooling that are clearly important in an environment where child&#13;
Lo/     H. Theil, "Quantities, Prices and Budget Inquiries," Review of&#13;
Economic Studies, No. 19, 1952, pp. 127-147.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
Table 8: REASONS GIVEN FOR CHILDREN BEING OUT OF SCHOOL, BY PROVINCE,&#13;
INDONESIA, 1978&#13;
(X)&#13;
Had                       Too        School&#13;
Province                 Sufficient    No Funds    Difficult     Too Far    Other&#13;
Schooling                                Away&#13;
D.I. Aceh                    6;1          55.8         6.6        12.2       19.3&#13;
Sumatera Utara               2.4         66.1         10.4         3.0       18.0&#13;
Sumatera Barat              0O.4         74.1         12.6         0.0       13.0&#13;
Riau                        12.0          50.0         8.0         8.7       21.3&#13;
Jambi                        7.0          50.0         3.0        10.0       30.0&#13;
Sumatera Selatan             5.9         46.8          8.1         4.3       34.9&#13;
Bengkulu                     3.7         63.0          7.4         5.6       20.4&#13;
Lampung,                    11.1          57;1        11.4         1.9       18.4&#13;
D.K.I. Jakarta               4.7         62.1         11.2         0.9       21.1&#13;
Java Barat                   3.3         71.6          7.8         2.7       14.7&#13;
Jawa Tengah                 12.9          31.3        16.3         2.0       37.4&#13;
D.I. Yogyakarta              4.3         60.1          3.2         2.1       30.3&#13;
Jawa Timur                   9.7         59.0         10.9         2.9       17.5&#13;
Bali                         6.5         41.3         13.0         0.0       39.1&#13;
Nusa Tenggara Barat          7.9          39.5        21.1          7.9      23.7&#13;
Nusa Tenggara Timur         21.4         39.3         17.9        10.7       10.7&#13;
Kalimantan Barat             7.4         41.0          7.4        13.1       31.1&#13;
Kalimantan Tengah           28.1         43.8         12.5         6.3        9.4&#13;
Kalimantan Selatan          13.0         51.4          1.4         1.9       32.4&#13;
Kalimantan Timur             7.1         57.1          7.1         7.1       21.4&#13;
Sulawesi Utara               5.3         36.0         14.7        10.0       34.0&#13;
Sulawesi Tengah              6.3         64.6          4.2         4.2       20.8&#13;
Sulawesi Selaten             0.0         31.8         26-.4       13.4       28.4&#13;
Sulawesi Tenggara           10.7         53.6         10.7         0.0       25.0&#13;
Source:  Data tapes of SUSENAS 1978, Biro Pusat Statistik, Jakarta.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
labor is common. This is due to the fact that the formulation considers the&#13;
price of a combined factor which is determined by both quality and quantity.&#13;
Analytic formulations that come closer to accounting for the cost of&#13;
education are those that deal with investments in schooling. 111 Although&#13;
they do not pertain specifically to the education of children, these models&#13;
are useful here because they emphasize foregone earnings as a major component&#13;
in the costs of education.&#13;
The basic feature in all economic formulations is that childrenis&#13;
schooling involves costs, both direct and indirect, and thus competes for the&#13;
family's scarce resources with other commodities desired by the household.&#13;
The major hypotheses derived from these formulations are as follows'. First,&#13;
schooling is positively associated with the level of the household wealth.&#13;
That is, wealthier families can afford more schooling and probably have a&#13;
higher rate of return on formal education. Second, parents may choose to&#13;
substitute the number of offspring for the average level of their children's&#13;
education. Third, household characteristics and other factors that increase&#13;
the cost of education will lower the propensity to educate children. The&#13;
discussion here is confined to these main hypotheses with emphasis on the&#13;
effect of availability of facilities as a determinant of the relative cost of&#13;
schooling.&#13;
A few measures of formal education are used. The first, whether or&#13;
not a child is enrolled in school, is intended to measure how household&#13;
W Jacob Mincer, Schooling Experience and Earning, New York, National Bureau&#13;
of Economic Research, 1974; Gary S. Becker, Human Capital and Personal&#13;
Distribution of Income: An Analytical Approach, W. S. Woytinsky Lecture&#13;
No. 1, Ann Arbor, University of Michigan, Department of Economics, 1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
characteristics affect school enrollment for all children. The second measure&#13;
is the level of education completed by those children at the time of the&#13;
survey. These measures are used as dependent variables in a regression&#13;
analysis. We attempt to explain schooling by the level of household&#13;
expenditures, household size, parents' education, age, and sex of the child,&#13;
and availability of schooling facilities, all in an attempt to test the above&#13;
hypotheses.&#13;
III.2    Determinants of School Enrollment:   Findings&#13;
The results of the regression analysis are reported in Tables 9 and&#13;
10; the former concerns school attendance, the latter levels of educational&#13;
attainment as measured by years of schooling completed. These results are&#13;
supplemented by a set of unreported regressions concerning the choice of a&#13;
particular type of high school education: general, vocational or teacher&#13;
training.&#13;
We focus on two sets of variables: those pertaining to the&#13;
household, and those pertaining to the community, namely the availability of&#13;
schools in the village to which the household belongs. Before turning to&#13;
these, however, we discuss two control variables: the age and sex of the&#13;
child.&#13;
Schooling achievements are, by definition, a function of the child's&#13;
age. Nonetheless, two aspects of the estimated coefficients are noteworthy.&#13;
First, the size and statistical significance of the coefficients decrease with&#13;
age. Second, for the cohorts above age 18, the coefficients are even&#13;
negative. Two effects of age on schooling are combined here. First,&#13;
children's propensity to enroll and attend school falls with age because both&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
Table 9: REGRESSIONS ON WHETHER OR NOT A CHILD IS ATTENDING SCHOOL&#13;
BY DIFFERENT ACE GROUPS, INDONESIA, 1978&#13;
Age Group&#13;
Independent Variable                    13-15            16-18             19-25&#13;
Constant                              -0.2620           -0.9736          -0.4396&#13;
Child's Characteristics&#13;
Child's sex (male = 1, female = 0)     0.1429            0.1307           0.0513&#13;
(6.47)            (6.41)           (6.44)&#13;
Household Characteristics&#13;
loge (household expenditure)           0.0562            0.0956           0.0352&#13;
(2.84)            (5.65)           (5.32)&#13;
Household size                         0.0065            0.0122           0.0110&#13;
(1.14)            (2.54)           (5.92)&#13;
Years of schooling of                  0.0186            0.0129           0.0083&#13;
household head                      (3.95)            (2.95)           (4.90)&#13;
Years of schooling of                  0.0163            0.0200           0.0010&#13;
spouse of household head            (3.19)           (4.06)            (0.50)&#13;
Schooling Facilities&#13;
Junior Secondary School                0.1049            0.0694&#13;
(= 1 if there is school             (4.44)           (2.64)&#13;
in village)&#13;
Senior Secondary School                                 0.1250            0.0488&#13;
(= 1 if there is school                              (3.91)            (4.61)&#13;
in village)&#13;
N                              1774              1673             2934&#13;
Note: These are ordinary least squares estimates. Hence they are&#13;
inefficient, given the dichotomous nature of the dependent variables.&#13;
This, however, does not invalidate the results. t-statistics are given&#13;
in parentheses.&#13;
Source: Data tapes of SUSENAS 1978 (May round) and Village Social Facilities&#13;
Survey, 1976/1977, Biro Pusat Statistik, Jakarta.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22. -&#13;
Table 10:  REGRESSIONS OF YEARS OF SCHOOLING COMPLETED BY&#13;
CHILDREN IN DIFFERENT. AGE GROUPS, INDONESIA, 1978&#13;
Age Group&#13;
Independent Variable                  10-12       13-15        16-18       19-25&#13;
Constant                            -7.9744      -4.5306     -1.7577      -3.5424&#13;
Child's Characteristics&#13;
Child's sex (male = 1, female = 0)   0.0182      -0.0439      0.4333       1.3945&#13;
(0.34)     (-0.54)       (3.96)     (14.19)&#13;
Child's age                          0.7337       0.4976      0.0942      -0.0732&#13;
(23.35)     (.10.23)      (1.41)     (-3.33)&#13;
Household Characteristics&#13;
loge (household expenditure)         0.2667       0.2331      0.5261       0.8225&#13;
(5.37)      (3.24)       (5.79)     (10.07)&#13;
Household size                      -0.0459      -0.0542     -0.0200       0.0778&#13;
(-3.20)     '-2.61)      (-0.76)      (3.40)&#13;
Years of schooling of                0.0463       0.0975      0.1085       0.2141&#13;
household head                    (3.86)       (5.68)      (4.63)      (10.21)&#13;
Years of schooling of                0.0287       0.0688      0.1107       0.2760&#13;
spouse of household head          (2.14)       (3.70)      (4.18)      (11.64)&#13;
Schooling Facilities&#13;
Primary School                       0.0794&#13;
(= 1 if there is schooi in        (0.58)&#13;
village)&#13;
Junior Secondary School              0.1471       0.3528      0.4683       0.3112&#13;
(= 1 if there is school in.       (2.47)       (4.10)      (3.32)       (2.57)&#13;
village)&#13;
Senior Secondary School                                       0.0988       0.3746&#13;
(= 1 if there is school in                                 (0.57)       (2.46)&#13;
village).&#13;
Adjusted  R2                         0.2840       0.1651      0.1800       0.3584&#13;
N                            1850         1774        1673         2934&#13;
Note:  t-statistics are given in parentheses.&#13;
Source: Data tapes of SUSENAS 1978 (May round) and Village Social Facilities&#13;
Survey, 1976/1977, Biro Pusat Statistik, Jakarta.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
direct and indirect costs of schooling rise with age.   Second, the younger&#13;
cohorts have better schooling opportunities than the older cohorts had.   This&#13;
is suggested by the negative coefficient of age for the oldest age group which&#13;
has by and large completed its education; the younger members have had more&#13;
schooling than the older ones.&#13;
Controlling'for other factors, boys have a higher propensity than&#13;
girls to enroll in and attend school, especially above the elementary level,&#13;
and eventually complete higher levels of schooling.   Attitudes undoubtedly&#13;
play a crucial role in parents' discrimination between sons and daughters.&#13;
Yet, we must give fuli consideration to the findings reported in Table 2 which&#13;
show that hourly earnings for females are lower than for males for the&#13;
majority of employees who have only primary education.   That is, parents'&#13;
behavior may indeed reflect the relatively low rates of return on their&#13;
daughters' schooling, unless they are prepared to educate their daughters&#13;
beyond the primary level.&#13;
The results support the hypothesis that, all other things equal,&#13;
household income, approximated by household'monthly-expenditures, has a&#13;
positive effect on the likelihood that a child attends school and on the level&#13;
of education that he or she attains.   This result holds for all levels of&#13;
education.  Not surprisingly, income matters more at higher levels of&#13;
schooling than for lower levels,"as the former are dominated by private&#13;
institutions and thus depend more on the household's ability-and willingness&#13;
to pay for schooling.  It appears (in the unreported results) that income&#13;
matters more in the Outer Islands than in JavA, apparently because facilities&#13;
are less available and less accessible in the former area.   Moreover, the&#13;
relatively well-to-do prefer general and teacher-training high school&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
education for their children, while the poor prefer vocational training.&#13;
Household size, usually also an indicator of the number of children&#13;
in the household, has the predicted effect. There is a trade-off for parents&#13;
between the number of offspring and the average level of education of each&#13;
child. The regression coefficients indicate that a child from a larger family&#13;
has a higher chance of attending school, especially at higher levels of&#13;
schooling. On the average, however, they eventually find themselves with&#13;
lower levels of',:completed education. This suggests that a well-off household&#13;
with fewer children may choose to send fewer children to school but educate&#13;
them better. This result is consistent with some role assignment on the part&#13;
of the rich; some children are assigned to acquire schooling while others may&#13;
benefit from other endowments of nonhuman capital.&#13;
Furthermore, at higher levels of schooling, a child from a relatively&#13;
large family seems to benefit from the size of his family. This result may be&#13;
typical of small agricultural settings where the marginal productivity of&#13;
labor on the farm falls, and with it the opportunity cost of schooling of&#13;
teenagers.&#13;
As expected, the education of both parents matters in the schooling&#13;
of their children. The mother's schooling matters as much as the father's in&#13;
whether or not a child attends school, especially for the younger age&#13;
groups. It is the father's education which has the greater influence on how&#13;
much schooling the child attains eventually.&#13;
As with the income effect, the relatively more educated parents are&#13;
more likely to opt for general and teacher-training high schools for their&#13;
children.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
In strict economic terms we interpret the findings concerning&#13;
parents' education as a wealth effect on the one hand, and a better perception&#13;
of the returns-to schooling on the other. It is clear, however, that&#13;
attitudes as well as social norms associated with education of parents may&#13;
play a crucial role here. Vocational training, the preferred choice of the&#13;
relatively poor and uneducated, appears to have by and large a comparable&#13;
market value, as indicated by wages, to other forms of high school training.&#13;
Finally, we look at the effect on school enrollment and years of&#13;
schooling completed of the availability of schools. We focus on schooling&#13;
beyond the primary level (ages 6-12) because schooling at the primary level is&#13;
fairly universal. Indeed, it is of interest to note the positive effect on&#13;
primary education of availability of a junior high school in the community.&#13;
This effect suggests that when the prospects to continue education are good,&#13;
they have a positive influence on the decision to stay in school. The&#13;
regression results show clearly that availability of schools in the village&#13;
improves the chances that a child attends school and completes more years of&#13;
schooling.&#13;
IV.      Conclusion&#13;
This study shows that education in Indonesia, especially beyond the&#13;
primary level, is very much an income-related phenomenon. Education is also&#13;
strongly influenced by attitudes as implied by the evidence that the&#13;
relatively rich and well-educated shun vocational training even though it&#13;
appears to yield a comparable return in the market to general training. In&#13;
addition, the fact that girls do not receive more schooling may be related to&#13;
parents' attitudes, although in this case their behavior may also be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
influenced by the lower market returns to girls' education.&#13;
The data clearly show that availability of facilities promote school&#13;
attendance and educational attainment. Yet, household considerations should&#13;
not be disregarded. In the case of primary schools, which are almost&#13;
universally available, parents' decisions are critical so that policies to&#13;
increase enrollment may have to deal with parents' attitudes as well as the&#13;
opportunity cost to the household of children's schooling.&#13;
If the government is to promote needed technical education through&#13;
vocational training, it may have to invest more than is required for other&#13;
forms of schooling. This type of education is apparently not desired by those&#13;
who appreciate and can afford schooling, the well-to-do and educated. Yet,&#13;
while this may put an added financial burden on the government, the payoff may&#13;
be substantial in terms of improved social mobility and income distribution.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Appendix Table 1:  REGRESSIONIESTIMATES FOR HOUSEHOLD EXPENDITURES ON SCHOOLING,-INDONESIA, 1978&#13;
Dependent Variable&#13;
Independent Variable              Tuition Fees         School Dues         Supplies and Books          Total&#13;
Constant                       -i4.97                -11.82                   33.47                6.68&#13;
Number of Children in School&#13;
Primary School&#13;
Male                            72.22 (1.24)          38.93 (2.09J          . 14.50 (0.63)       125.65 (1.69)&#13;
Female                          99.70 (1.68)          46.43 (2.45J            36.74.(1.56)       182.87 (2.42)&#13;
Junior High School''&#13;
Male                           536.22-(4.96)         173.62 (5.02J           145.14 (3.37)       854.98 (6.18)&#13;
Female                         682.51 (5.43)         358.87 (8.92J            41.75 (0.83)      1083.12 (6.73)&#13;
Senior High School&#13;
Male                           989.81 (6.38)         173.88 (3.51J           254.65 (4.12)       1418.35 (7.15)&#13;
Female                         200.57 (1.05).        244.08 (4.900           389.33 .(5.12)      833.97 (3.42)&#13;
University                      4570.38 (22.20)        612.22 (9.301          1623.16-(19.79)     6805.76- (25.85)&#13;
Source:  Data tapes of SUSENAS 1978 (May round), Biro Pusat Statistik, Jakarta.&#13;
Note : t-statistics are given in parentheses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
Appendix Table 2: REGRESSIONS OF WHETHER OR NOT A CHILD IS ATTENDING SCHOOL,&#13;
BY DIFFERENT AGE GROUPS, INDONESIA, 1978&#13;
Age Group&#13;
Independent Variable                    13-15             16-18             19-25&#13;
Constant                               -0.2620          -0.9736           -0.4396&#13;
Child's Characteristics&#13;
Child's sex (male = 1, female = 0)      0.1429            0.1307           0.0513&#13;
(6.47)            (6.41)           (6.44)&#13;
Household Characteristics&#13;
loge (household expenditure)            0.0562            0.0956           0.0352&#13;
(2.84)            (5.65)           (5.32)&#13;
Household size                          0.0065           0.0122            0.0110&#13;
(1.14)            (2.54)           (5.92)&#13;
Years of schooling of                   0.0186            0.0129           0.0083&#13;
household head                       (3.95)           (2.95)            (4.90)&#13;
Years of schooling of                   0.0163            0.0200           0.0010&#13;
spouse of household head             (3.19)           (4.06)            (0.50)&#13;
Schooling Facilities&#13;
Junior Secondary School                 0.1049           0.0694&#13;
(= 1 if there is school in           (4.44)           (2.64)&#13;
village)&#13;
Senior Secondary School                                  0.1250            0.0488&#13;
(= 1 if there is school in                            (3.91)            (4.61)&#13;
village)&#13;
Adjusted   R2                           0.1116            0.2050           0.1103&#13;
N                              1774              1673              2934&#13;
Note:   (i)   The coefficients in this table give the probability that a child&#13;
attends school, given his and the household's characteristics. For example,&#13;
for a child between ages 13 and 15, the probability that he is in school can&#13;
be calculated as:&#13;
-0.2620 + 0.0562 (loge (household expenditure)) + 0.0186 (number of&#13;
years of education of father) + 0.0163 (number of years of education&#13;
of mother) +0.0065 (size of household) + 0.1429 (if child is male; not&#13;
if child is female) + 0.1049 (if there is a junior secondary school in&#13;
the village; not if there is not)&#13;
(ii) t-statistics are given in parentheses. The pEoportion of the&#13;
variance of the dependent variable explained is given by     R   and the number&#13;
of observations used in the regression is given by N.&#13;
Source:  Data tapes of SUSENAS 1978 (May round) and Village Social Facilities&#13;
Survey, 1976/1977, Biro Pusat Statistik, Jakarta.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
World Bank                                                                        Education&#13;
Wadi D. Haddad, coordinating&#13;
Publkatlou                                                                        author&#13;
Emphasizes the pervasive role of edu-&#13;
of Related                                                                        cation in development and draws ex-&#13;
tensively on the Bank's experience in&#13;
education for two decades and its&#13;
close collaborative ties with other in-&#13;
ternational agencies, individuals, and&#13;
Alternative Routes to Formal                                                      institutions of developing countries.&#13;
Education:, Distance Teaching                                                     Sector Policy Paper. 1980. 143 pages (in-&#13;
for School Equivalency                                                            cluding 19 annexes, map).&#13;
Edited by Hilary Perraton                                                         Stock Nos. BK 9071 (English), BK 9072&#13;
The demand for education is outstrip-                                             (French), BK 9073 (Spanish).$5.&#13;
ping the capacity of many countries to&#13;
build schools or to recruit and pay&#13;
teachers. To meet this demand and to      Basic Education and                      Spanish: Programas de formnacion profes-&#13;
provide access to education to individ-   Agricultural Extension: Costs,           sional: su evaluacion economica. Editorial&#13;
uals who are unable to attend regular     Effects, and Alternatives                Tecnos, 1977.&#13;
schools, educators throughout the        Hilary Perraton and others               ISBN 84-309-0747-5, Stock No. IB 0536.&#13;
world are trying to develop alterna-      Hddre                                    $6.&#13;
tives to the traditional classroom. One   Addresses the effectiveness of using&#13;
of these alternativne-knw clasr   Od-     mass media for agricultural extension&#13;
of tesealteaties   nownas is-and basic education. Includes a review      The Educational Use of Mass&#13;
tance teaching-combines correspond-       of the literature on the effectiveness of  Media&#13;
ence courses with radio or television&#13;
broadcasts and occasional face-to-face   agricultural extension and-on the use     Gloria Feliciano, and others&#13;
study.                                   of mass media for rural education.        Staff Working Paper No. 491. 1981. 129&#13;
study.                        ~~~~~~~~Case studies from Malawi, Cameroon'  pages (including bibliography).&#13;
Does this alternative work? Is it        and Lesotho examine institutions us-&#13;
cheaper? This book is the first attempt  ing mass media in widely different        Stock No. WP 0491. $5.&#13;
to answer such key questions. It exam-   ways.                                     Education and Basic Human&#13;
ines the variety of ways in which dis-      Y *         Paptr No. 564i Human&#13;
tance teaching has been used, pro-       Staff Working Paper No. 564. 1983. 308    Needs&#13;
vides comparisons of specific cases,     pages.                                    Abdun Noor&#13;
analyzes their costs, and considers the  ISBN 0-8213-0176-4. Stock No. WP 0564.    Staff Working Paper No. 450. 1981. 68&#13;
effectiveness of distance teaching ver-  $15.                                      pages (including 2 annexes).&#13;
sus traditional education.&#13;
Charging User Fees for Social            Stock No. WP 0450. $3.&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press. 1982.  Services: The Case of                   Education and Income&#13;
344 pages.                               Education in Malawi                       Edited by Timothy King; prepared&#13;
LC 82-7233. ISBN 0-8018-2587-3, Stock    Mateen Thobani                            by Mary Jean Bowman and others&#13;
No. JH 2587. $35 hardcover.              An analysis of one way to reduce the      Staff Working Paper No. 402. 1980. 323&#13;
problem of recurrent expenditure in      pages (including appendix, bibliography).&#13;
social sector services. Argues that the   Stock No. WP 0402. $15.&#13;
Attacking Rural Poverty: How              deterioration or curtailment of services&#13;
Non-Formal Education Can                 resulting from low user charges affects   The Effects of Education on&#13;
Help                                     the poor disproportionately, and con-&#13;
Philip H. Coombs and                     siders conditions under which raising     Susan H. Cochrane and others&#13;
Manzoor Ahmed                 ~~~~~charges would increase efficiency     SsnH       ohaeadohr&#13;
while reducing the financing problem.     Staff Working Paper No. 405. 1980. 95&#13;
Educational efforts outside the formal   SafWrigPprN.52            93    5pgs&#13;
school system that offer potential for    Staff Working Paper No. 572. 1983. 35    pages.&#13;
rural development and productivity.      pages.                                    Stock No. WP 0405. $3.&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1974;  ISBN 0-8213-0179-9.Stock No. WP 0572.   The Evaluation of Human&#13;
3rd paperback printing, 1980. 310 pages                                            Capital in Malawi&#13;
(including 3 appendixes, references, index).  The Economic Evaluation of           Stephen P. Heyneman&#13;
ISBN 0-8018-1601-7, Stock No. JH 1601.    Vocational Training Programs             Staff Working Paper No. 420. 1980. 107&#13;
$10.95 paperback.                         Manuel Zymelman                          pages (including references, 21 tables, 6&#13;
Spanish: La lucha contra la pobreza rural:  A methodology for appraising the cost  annexes).&#13;
el aporte de la educacion no formnal. Edito-  effectiveness of alternative methods of  Stock No. WP 0420. $5.&#13;
rial Tecnos, 1975.                       industrial training in developing coun-   Farmer Education and Farm&#13;
ISBN 84-309-0559-6, Stock No. IB 0525.   tries.&#13;
$10.95.                                   The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1976.  Efficiency&#13;
134 pages (including chart, 3 appendixes,  Dean T. Jamison and Lawrence J.&#13;
bibliography).                            Lau&#13;
Prices subject to change without notice  LC 764868. ISBN 0-8018-1855-9, Stock      This book complements earlier studies&#13;
and may vary by country.                 No. JH 1855. $6 paperback.                by reviewing existing literature on the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
relation between farmer education'ind  ing and improvement of the vocational   Staff Working Paper No. 624. 1983. 116&#13;
farm efficiency. The authors then are  training system                         pages.&#13;
able ts confirm these earlier findings-  Staff Working Papers No. 554. 1983. 41  ISBN 0-8213-0291-4.Stock No. WP 0624.&#13;
cated farmers are more productive,      pages&#13;
particularly where new inputs and       ISBN 0-8213-0144-6. Stock No. WP 0554.&#13;
methods'are available-by using new      $3.                                    Mexko's Free Textbooks:&#13;
techniques to examine new data sets                                            Nationalism and the Urgency&#13;
from Korea, Malaysia, and Thailand.     The Influence of School'               to 'Educate&#13;
Price data from Thailand are used to    Resources in uence:oTceoo              Peter H. Neumann and&#13;
test the effect of education on the abil-  Resources in Chile: Their           Maureen A. Cunningham&#13;
ity of a farmer to adjust the prices and  Effect on Educational&#13;
composition of his output to the pre-   Achievement and Occupational           Staff Worktng Paper No. 541. 1982. 148&#13;
vailing prices.                        'Attainment                             pagIS.&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1982.  Ernesto Schiefelbein, Joseph P.     ISBN 0-8213-101-2. Stock No. WP 0541.&#13;
310 pages (including bibliography, appen-  Farrell, and Manuel Sepulveda-      S .&#13;
dixes, index).                          Stuardo&#13;
LC 8147612. ISBN 0-8018-2575-X, hard-   Checks out impact of investments in    Primary Schooling and&#13;
cover. Stock No. IH 2575. $27.50.       school resources as reflected by text-  Economic Development: A&#13;
Higjler Education in    'A              book use, academic achievement and     Review of the Evidence&#13;
success in the labor market. For maxi-  Christopher Colclough&#13;
Developing Countries: A Cost-           mum benefit, investments should be     Staff Working Paper No. 399. 1980. 31&#13;
Benefit Analysis                        preceded by study of teacher. attitudes  pages (including references, 5 tables).&#13;
George Psacharopoulos                   toward use of resources, be applied    Stock No. WP 0399. $3'&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 440. 1980. 129  early in the educational process and&#13;
pages (including references, tables).  take into account malnutrition and      Primary School Participation&#13;
Stock No. WP ~~~~ $5          other external problems.               andmIts Inteool Distribuption i&#13;
Stock No. WP 0440. S5.                  Staff Working Paper No. 530. 1983. 118  and lst  Intecal Distribution in&#13;
pages.                                 Eastern Africa&#13;
NEW                                 ISBN 0-8213-0145-4.Stock No. WP 0530.  Jack van L. Maas and Bert Criel&#13;
$5.                                    Staff Working Paper No. 511. 1982. 105&#13;
How Secondary School                                                           pages.&#13;
Graduates Perform in the                                                       ISBN 0-8213-0055-5. Stock No. WP 0511.&#13;
Labor Market: A Study of                   NEW$5&#13;
Indonesia&#13;
David H. Clark                          Manpower Issues in                     Publishing for Schools:&#13;
Investigates whether or not higher sec-  Educational Investment: A             Textbooks and the Less&#13;
ondary education should be expanded     Consideration of Planning              Developed Countries&#13;
in Indonesia. Compares employment       Processes and Techniques               Peter H. Neumnann&#13;
patterns and earning rates of gTadu-    George Psacharopoos D      eith        Staff Working Paper No. 398. 1980. 81&#13;
ates who enter.the labor market with    Hinoige, Pscharlopouers Dogerty,       pages (including 2 appendixes).&#13;
that of people having less education.                                          StockfffNo.hriPop0398.uger3.&#13;
Results of the National Labor Force     and Robinson Hollister                 Stock No. WP 0398. S3.&#13;
Surveys suggest that academic senior    Outlines for educators and economists&#13;
secondary schools are the best invest-  a variety of approaches to improve     The Use of First and Second&#13;
ment except in local situations where   manpower analysis. Advocates replac-   Languages in Primary&#13;
specialized secondary schools deserve   ing a dorminant technique with a well-  Education: Selected Case&#13;
a higher priority.                      structured planning methodology.       Studies&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 615. 1983. 88   Recommends a broad approach to be      Nadine Dutcher&#13;
pages.                                  used to analyze the relationship be-&#13;
ISBN 0-2134126-4.Stok No. W  0615. tween manpower and the educational  Staff Working Paper No. 504. 1982. 65&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0260-4. Stock No. WP 0615.  system'. Examines planning tech¶t      pages (including annex, references). Eng-&#13;
$3.                   .                 niques, three points of.view (country  i and Spanish.&#13;
technical assistance agency, lending   Stock No. WP 0504. $3.&#13;
Human Resources Planning in             agency), ind the role of manpower&#13;
the Republic of Korea:                  analysis planning in developing coun-  Worker-Peasant Education in&#13;
Improving Technical Education           tries. Contends that forcing all man-  the People's Republic of China&#13;
and Vocational Training                 power questions into any single ana-   Nat J. Colletta&#13;
lytical framework results in low-quality NaJ.Clea&#13;
Kye-Woo Lee                             analysis and low-quality educational   Staff Working Paper No. 527. 1982. 94&#13;
Provides a basis for human resources    investments. Cites a need for continu-  pages.&#13;
planning during a period of far-reach-  ity of manpower analysis through the   ISBN 0-821340050-4. Stock No. WP 0527.&#13;
ing structural change. Focuses. on labor  development of a planning methodol-  $3.&#13;
market problems and their solution      ogy. Suggests that such analysis&#13;
through institutional linkages between  should go beyond identifying and pre-  Prices subject to change without notice&#13;
formal education and vocational train-  paring specific education projects.    and may vary by country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
H Publications Order Form&#13;
SEND TO: YOUR LOCAL DISTRIBUTOR OR TO WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
(See the other side of thts.form.)         P.O. BOX 37525&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013 U.S.A.&#13;
Date&#13;
Name                                                 Ship to: (Enter if different from purchaser)&#13;
Title                                                Name&#13;
Firm                                                 Title&#13;
Address                                              Firrn&#13;
City               State     Postal Codt   e         Address&#13;
Country             TeIlephone I_}                   City            State-     Postal Code_&#13;
Purchaser Reference No.                              Country             Telephone I-   )&#13;
Check your method of payment.&#13;
Enclosed is my Ol Check O International Money Order O Unesco Coupons O International Postal Coupon.&#13;
Make payable to World Bank Publications for U. S. dollars unless you are ordering from your local distributor.&#13;
Charge my O VISA Ol MasterCard E American Express CO Choice. (Credit cards accepted only for orders addressed&#13;
to World Bank Publications.}&#13;
Credit Card Account Number            Expiration Date                    Signature&#13;
O Invoice me and please reference my Purchase Order No.&#13;
Please ship me the items listed below.&#13;
Cuom tntxrntl&#13;
Stock Number  Autbwo/ Tide                                       Routiln Code  Quantity  Unit Prke Total Armunt S&#13;
All prices subject to change. Prices may vary by country. Allow 6-8 weeks for deliver-y.&#13;
Subtotal Cost  $___&#13;
'Ibtal copies  .,Air mail surcharge if desired ($2.00 each)  $___&#13;
Postage and handling for more ihan two complimentary items ($2.00 each)  S.......&#13;
'Ibtal  S___&#13;
t8RD.~~~~~~~~iC63                                T~~~~~lhaink you for your order.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Distributors of World Bank Publications&#13;
ARGENTINA                          GERMANY, FEDERAL REPUBUC            KUWAIT                             SRI LANKA AND THE MALDIVES&#13;
CAlms Hrsc, SRL                      OF                                MEMR18                               ke House Bookshop&#13;
GCaea Guema                        UNO.Verlag                          P 0. Box 546                       P 0. Sox 244&#13;
Florida 163. 4th Floor4Oc. 4465    Dj300 Bn I                          Kuwait                             IX, Sir Cluttampalam A. Gudiner&#13;
1333 Buenos Aim                    Sinrockatste 23                     MALAYSIA                             Mwatha&#13;
AUSTRAUA, PAPUA NEW                GREECE                              Universitv of Malava Cooperative   Colombo 2&#13;
GUINEA, FII. SOLOMON             MEMRB                                 Bookshop. Limited                Sn LAnka&#13;
ISLANDS, AND VANUATU             24. Ippodamou Street                P 0. Box 1127. Jalia Pantai Baru   SWEDEN&#13;
Wo-Line                            Athens-11635                        Kuala Lumpur                       For srngka titls:&#13;
Overseas Do.^ment Delvey           HONG KONG, MACAU                    MEXICO                             ASCE Fntze Kunsg. Hovbokhiadel&#13;
Sox 06. GPO    0                   AsI 2000 Ltd.                       LNIFOTEC                           Regengpptis 12, Box 16356&#13;
Svdnev, NSW 2wl                    6 Fl., 146 Prince Edward Road, W,   San Loremo 153H1. CoL del Valle    5103 27 Stockholm&#13;
Austrnia                           Kowloon                               Deleg. Beruto juear              For bssptw ridersm:&#13;
BAHRAIN                            HonKong                              3100 Mexco City                   Wetrergren Willims AB&#13;
ME    oRB                          INDIA                               MOROCCO                            Box 3001&#13;
PO vBox 2213                       LBSS PubLsher' Dsustbuton Ltd.      MEMIRB                            Sc04 25 Stockholm&#13;
Manama Town 317                    Post Box 7015                       2 Rue Molie Racme                  SWffZERLND&#13;
BANGLADESH                         New Delhi l10002                    Casablan                           Lbbre Pavot&#13;
Micro Indusmes Develoment          10 First .ain Road                  THE NEnTERLANDS                    6 Rue Grenu&#13;
As atance So   '                 Gandhi Naps                         Medial Books Europe. BV (MBE)      Case   -    381&#13;
G.P.O. Box Om                      Banplore 560009                     Noorderwal 38,                     CH 1211 Geneva 11&#13;
DhaUM                              Apeeav Chanben, P 0. OX 736         7241 8L Lodtem                     TANZANIA&#13;
BELGIUM                   3~~~~ Wallace Savee                 NIGERIA                            Oxford University Pres&#13;
Pubbcatonm des Natios Lni          Bombay 400001                       Univerity Press Linited            p x. B;u 5298&#13;
Av. du Ro 202                                                          Thre Crowns Buildin Jenho          Dar as Satlm&#13;
106li Brusel                       81-8. Chownaghee Lsis.              Pevate Mail Bag 5u95&#13;
BRAZIL                             Caaut 7dA1n                                                            Centnld Deputnet Store&#13;
Pubcacoa Teaswas lnteanaorsaa      7198, I(CA), Swarup Napg             NORWAY                             306 Silotr Rad&#13;
Rdua.                             KaxopGo  2ueO02                    Tanum Kad Johah. A.S.                kngkok&#13;
Rue P9  oo Goaulde. S              Sivapnp Road                        P 0. Box 1177                       TRINIDAD &amp; T08AGO&#13;
Nunpambakkam                        Sentrum                            Sntm   tr Studia Unt&#13;
CANADA                              Madras 600034                      Oslo I                              5   sn Miurt Road&#13;
Le Ddbifurw                        INDONESIA                           PAKISTAN                           Curepe&#13;
C.P. S5.1301 Quebe Street          Pt. Indus Limited                   Miru Book Agency                    Triidad, West ndies&#13;
Boucherville. Quebec 14B 56           San RatulAgn 37                  65. Shahrah-e.Qaid-e-Azam          TUNISIA&#13;
CHILE                              lakar Pusat                         P.O Box No. 729                    Soet Tur iermue de DOLfio&#13;
Editonial Renaaieito               PO BOx 18                          Lahore 3                           3 Avenue de Cathage&#13;
Mmndlra 354                        IRELAND                             PANAMA                              Tunis&#13;
Santlitp                           TDC Publahers                       Edicortz UAber4 Cultusi             TURKEY&#13;
COSTA RICA                         12 .North Frederick Street            Pnamena, S.A.                     Haset Kitape  A.S.&#13;
Libremu Tretos                     Dubli I                             Av. 7. Espamsa 16                  16^. Isnkl Cadden&#13;
CaGle 11-13                                                            Pama    Zone I&#13;
Av. Fensadez Gued                  ITALY                               PaSll    oeIBevoglu-Istazsbul&#13;
SAv Jose f0dezUcosa Comrmaissnns Sant SPA                              PERU                                UGANDA&#13;
Via Lamarmors 45                    Editoril Desarrollo SA             Uganda Bookshop&#13;
CYPRUS                             50121 Floren                        Apartdo 3824                        Attn: .r. M%artm-Luther Galiwago&#13;
.PM;RB8                            JAPAN                               Limt                                PO  Box 7145&#13;
PNO Box 209                        Eastem Book Servce (EBS)            PHU       E                         K   Bompal&#13;
Nicosta                            37-3. Hongo 3Chome, Bunkokku        National Book Store                LUNIMD ARAB EMIRATES&#13;
DENMARK                              113                               701 Ri l Avenue                     UEU&#13;
SamhfunLittentutr                  Tokvo                               Metromanila                         P 0 BOx 6^97&#13;
Rownoemns Aile 11                  JORDAN                              POTUGAL                             Shaiuah&#13;
DK-1970 Copenhagen V                %IEMRB                             Livrmar Portuga                     UNITED KINGDOM AND&#13;
EGYPT, ARAB REPUBUC OF              P 0  ox 3143                       Rua DoCaum o7074                      NORTHERN IRELAND&#13;
Al Ahram                           Jabal                               l20 Lisbon                           ciorousfo Ld.&#13;
Gaaa Stmeet                         Amman                            . SAUDI ARABIA                        P 0. Box 3&#13;
CALM                                K    A                                  BookKENA  ii   Store           Alton. Hampshire GU 34 ZPG&#13;
FINLAND                            Arica Book Service (E.A.) Ltd.      P 0. Box 31f                        United Kingdom&#13;
Akawermnen Kuiakauppe               P 0 Box 45245                      Riyadh 11471                        VENEZELA&#13;
PO. o0x 128                         Nairbs                             SINGAPORE, TAIWAN. BURMA            Librers del Este&#13;
HelsuF 10                          KOREA. REPUBUC OF                   lnomadon Pubbc.tns Private. Ltd.    Aptdo. 6O.337&#13;
HelsInki 10                 Pan Korea Book Corporadon           02.06 1st Fl., Pei-Fu Indutrl Blg.,  Cact 10.A&#13;
FRANCE                              P 0 Box 101. Kwangwhamnun          24 New IndustrAd Road               WESTERN SAMOA&#13;
Wodd Bank Publications             Seoul                               Singapore                           Wesley Bookhop&#13;
66 Avenue d'iemsa                                                      SPAUN                               Apra&#13;
75116 Paiui                                                           lMundi-Presa Lhbros, S.A.&#13;
CasteCo 37&#13;
Hvl MAidnd&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
i&#13;
i-&#13;
M&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                          European Office               Tokyo Office                                      z&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                   66, avenue d'l6na             Kokusai Building,&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.        75116 Paris, France            1-l Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234             Telephone: (1) 723-54.21      Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK            Telex: 842-620628             Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                            Telex: 781-26838                                  0&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
0&#13;
1-&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0584-0          c&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554714">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/08/1554714/school-enrollment-indonesia
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/08/1554714/school-enrollment-indonesia</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1985/08/1554714/school-enrollment-indonesia</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/12/000178830_98101903432410/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/12/000178830_98101903432410/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-07-12T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1985-08-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            School enrollment in Indonesia
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The objective of this paper is to relate
            children's school enrollment and level of educational
            attainment to their household socioeconomic characteristics
            and the availability of schools. For primary school
            enrollment, two issues are explored. The first concerns the
            characteristics of those children who do not attend school,
            given the relative availability of facilities. The second
            concerns household expenditures on education, particularly
            in relation to the availability of facilities and
            households' ability and willingness to pay for
            education. The study, based on data, shows that education in
            Indonesia, especially beyond the primary level, is very much
            an income-related phenomenon. Education is also strongly
            influenced by attitudes as implied by the evidence that the
            relatively rich and well-educated shun vocational training,
            even though it appears to yield a comparable return in the
            market to general training. In addition, the fact that girls
            do not receive more schooling may be related to
            parents' attitudes, although their behavior may also be
            influenced by the lower market returns to girls'
            education. The data clearly show that availability of
            facilities promotes school attendance and educational
            attainment. Yet, household considerations should not be disregarded.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            School enrollment in Indonesia
        </docna>
        <display_title>School enrollment in Indonesia</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1985/08/1554714/school-enrollment-indonesia</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Youth and Governance,Gender and Education,Primary Education,Teaching and Learning</subtopic>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Gender</teratopic>
        <count>Indonesia</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Chernikovsky, Dov</author>
            <author>Meesook, Oey Astra</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southeast Asia!$!80471</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903432410</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Other education</subsc>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 746</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Gender</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Education</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0584-0</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Attitudes; Children; Educational
            achievement; Enrolment; Girls; Household consumption;
            Primary education; Schools; Secondary education;
            Socioeconomic status
            achievements,AGE GROUP,age groups,attending
            school,average level,better-off households,child labor,costs
            of education,direct costs,discrimination,educational
            opportunities,educational services,enrollment,enrollment
            rate,enrollment rates,families,Family Planning,formal
            education,girls,household income,household
            schooling,indirect costs,labor market,level of
            education,levels of education,literacy,literacy
            rate,PAPERS,parents,Primary education,primary school,primary
            school enrollment,primary schools,printing,pupils,rates of
            return,religious schools,Rural areas,School
            attendance,school education,schooling,Schools,secondary
            education,secondary level,secondary schools,Social
            Facilities,social norms,social services,teacher,teacher
            training,teenagers,tuition fees,urban areas,vocational training,wages,workers
        </keywd>
        <owner>EAC</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southeast Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP746</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>School Fees</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teacher Professional Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education and Gender Equality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Gender and Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Girls Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Girls' Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation Equipment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Basic Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Higher Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tertiary Education – Enhancing Access, Equity and Quality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Continuous Vocational Training (CVT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Lifelong Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strengthening Technical Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strengthening Vocational Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technical Vocational Education and Training Policies and Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technical and Vocational Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vocational Education and Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vocational Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education/HD Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Expenditures in Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance of Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Capital</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing People</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education for All</ml:concept><ml:concept>User Fees in Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teacher Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education and Gender</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport Equipment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Primary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Secondary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tertiary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Indonesia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>