<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Mortality Reduction, Fertility Decline, and Population Growth&#13;
Toward a More Relevant Assessment&#13;
of the Relationships among Them&#13;
Davidson Gwatkin&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 686&#13;
POPULATION AND DEVELOPMENT SERIES&#13;
Number 11&#13;
SWP686&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IAl&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 686                                 tJ&amp;:P&#13;
POPULATION AND DEVELOPMENT SERIES                     7  &amp;fi&#13;
Number 11&#13;
Mortality Reduction, Fertility Decline, and Population Growth&#13;
Toward a More Relevant Assessment&#13;
of the Relationships among Them&#13;
Davidson Gwatkin&#13;
PTEMNATIONAL MO:lETARY FUND&#13;
JOINT LIBRARY&#13;
FIB 1 '§1985&#13;
INTERNATIONiAL Bia  flon&#13;
rCO:4sTnucTI3oOI r111D IEr.LoPF.XNT&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright ° 1984&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing November 1984&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To present the&#13;
results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been prepared in&#13;
accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed texts, and the World&#13;
Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a token charge&#13;
to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The World Bank does not accept responsibility for the views expressed herein,&#13;
which are those of the authors and should not be attributed to the World Bank or to its&#13;
affiliated organizations. The findings, interpretations, and conclusions are the results&#13;
of research supported by the Bank; they do not necessarily represent official policy of&#13;
the Bank. The designations employed, the presentation of material, and any maps&#13;
used in this document are solely for the convenience of the reader and do not imply the&#13;
expression of any opinion whatsoever on the part of the World Bank or its affiliates&#13;
concerning the legal status of any country, territory, city, area, or of its authorities, or&#13;
concerning the delimitation of its boundaries, or national affiliation.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications, both free and for sale, is described in the&#13;
Catalog of Publications; the continuing research program is outlined in Abstracts of&#13;
Current Studies. Both booklets are updated annually; the most recent edition of each&#13;
is available without charge from the Publications Sales Unit, Department T, The&#13;
World Bank, 1818 H Street, N.W., Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A., or from the&#13;
European Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'Iena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Davidson Gwatkin is a visiting fellow at the Overseas Development Council in&#13;
Washington, D.C., and a consultant to the World Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Gwatkin, Davidson R.&#13;
Mortality reduction, fertility decline, and population&#13;
growth.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 686. Population&#13;
and development series ; no. 11)&#13;
1. Population policy. 2. Mortality. 3. Fertility,&#13;
Human. I. Title. II. Series: World Bank staff working&#13;
papers ; no. 686.     III. Series: World Bank staff working&#13;
papers. Population and development series ; 11.&#13;
HB883.5.G87    1984        304.6        84-25646&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0445-3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FOREWORD&#13;
This paper is one in a special series of World Bank Staff&#13;
Working Papers on population change and development. Prepared as&#13;
background papers for the World Development Report 1984, they provide&#13;
more detailed treatment and documentation of the issues dealt with in&#13;
Part II of the Report. The papers cover a range of topics, including&#13;
the effects of fertility and mortality, the links between population&#13;
growth and internal and international migration, and the management,&#13;
financing, and effectiveness of family planning programs. They include&#13;
several country and regional studies of fertility change and population&#13;
policy.&#13;
The background papers draw on a large number of published and&#13;
unpublished studies of individual researchers, on Bank policy analysis&#13;
and research, and on reports of other organizations working on popula-&#13;
tion and development programs and issues. The papers are the work of&#13;
individuals and the views and interpretations expressed in them do not&#13;
necessarily coincide with the views and interpretations of the Report&#13;
itself.&#13;
I hope these detailed studies will supplement the World&#13;
Development Report 1984 in furthering understanding of population and&#13;
development issues among students and practitioners of development.&#13;
Nancy Birdsall&#13;
Staff Director&#13;
World Development Report 1984&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Some of the Papers in the Population and Development Series&#13;
Ainsworth, Martha. Family Planning Programs: The Clients'&#13;
Perspective. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 676.&#13;
Bulatao, Rodolfo A. Expenditures on Population Programs in Major&#13;
Regions of the Developing World: Current Levels and Future&#13;
Requirements. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 679.&#13;
Bulatao, Rodolfo A. Reducing Fertility in Developing Countries: A&#13;
Review of Determinants and Policy Levers. World Bank Staff&#13;
Working Paper no. 680.&#13;
Cain, Mead. Women's Status and Fertility in Developing Countries:&#13;
Son Preference and Economic Security. World Bank Staff Working&#13;
Paper no. 682.&#13;
Gwatkin, Davidson. Mortality Reduction, Fertility Decline, and&#13;
Population Growth: Toward A More Relevant Assessment of&#13;
Relationships Among Them. World Bank Staff Working Paper no.&#13;
686.&#13;
Herz, Barbara. Official Development Assistance for Population&#13;
Activities: A Review. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 688.&#13;
McNicoll, Geoffrey. Consequences of Rapid Population Growth: An&#13;
Overview. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 691.&#13;
Sapir, Andre. Some Aspects of Population Growth, Trade, and Factor&#13;
Mobility. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 694.&#13;
Standing, Guy. Population Mobility and Productive Relations:&#13;
Demographic Links and Policy Evolution. World Bank Staff Working&#13;
Paper no. 695.&#13;
Tan, Jee-Peng, and Michael Haines. Schooling and Demand for Children:&#13;
Historical Perspectives. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 697.&#13;
Trussell, James, and Anne R. Pebley. The Potential Impact of Changes&#13;
in Fertility on Infant, Child, and Maternal Mortality. World&#13;
Bank Staff Working Paper no. 698.&#13;
Zachariah, K.C., and Sulekha Patel. Determinants of Fertility Decline&#13;
in India: An Analysis. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 699.&#13;
Zachariah, K.C. The Anomaly of the Fertility Decline in India's&#13;
Kerala State: A Field Investigation. World Bank Staff Working&#13;
Paper no. 700.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Abstract&#13;
What are the population growth consequences of public policies and&#13;
programs to reduce mortality? How large a change in growth will result from&#13;
efforts to lower fertility?&#13;
An adequate response to such questions requires an approach which begins&#13;
with the programs and policies under consideration and examines their overall&#13;
influence on fertility and mortality. There are two types of influence to be&#13;
covered: first, the influence of the policies or programs in question on mor-&#13;
tality and on fertility; and second, the influence of the resulting fertility&#13;
or mortality decline on the rate of change in the other.&#13;
Current approaches, which focus primarily on the growth consequences of a&#13;
change in mortality or fertility per se, largely overlook the former of these&#13;
two types of influence. This makes them inadequate for the assessment of&#13;
public policies and programs, especially for the assessment of the many poli-&#13;
cies and programs undertaken for the purpose of reducing mortality or fer-&#13;
tility which have a strong direct impact on the other as well.&#13;
An approach of the sort required is more difficult to apply than to&#13;
espouse. But its potential significance for policy and program analysis can&#13;
be illustrated through a few qualitative and crude quantitative examples. These&#13;
illustrations, taken in conjunction with the conceptual considerations pre-&#13;
sented, suggest two propositions to serve as interim guides to action and as&#13;
hypotheses to be confirmed or disproven through future research:&#13;
-- Most programs and polices undertaken to reduce mortality&#13;
will, in most settings and over the long run, produce even larger fertility&#13;
declines and thus slower growth.&#13;
-- Most measures designed to reduce fertility will also result&#13;
in slower growth, but by an amount that may upon occasion be significantly&#13;
less than anticipated on the basis on conventional assessment techniques.&#13;
Acknowledgements&#13;
Thanks go to Paul Altesman, Alan Berg, Nancy Birdsall, George Curlin,&#13;
David de Ferranti, Richard-Jolly, John Lewis, Robert Myers, Isabel Nieves,&#13;
Stephen Sinding, Robert Repetto, K.C. Zachariah, and others for their helpful&#13;
ideas and reviews; to the United Nations Fund for Population Activities,&#13;
UNICEF, and the Rockefeller Foundation for financial support to the work that&#13;
made possible preparation of this paper; to Ann Elwan and Jaana Myllyluoma for&#13;
their effective computational assistance; and to Nellie Rimkus and Robin E.&#13;
Ward for their typically efficient and patient help in preparing the&#13;
manuscript. None of the above, of course, can be held responsible for any&#13;
shortcomings in the material presented or in the views expressed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Condense&#13;
Quelles sont, pour la croissance demographique, les consequences&#13;
des politiques et programmes lanc6s par les gouvernements pour r6duire la&#13;
mortalite?  De quelle ampleur peut etre la variation de la croissance a&#13;
attendre des efforts en vue de r6duire la fecondite?&#13;
Pour obtenir une r6ponse satisfaisante a ces questions, il faut&#13;
une methode qui parte des programmes et politiques examines et qui etudie&#13;
leur influence generale sur la f6condite et la mortalite.   Deux types&#13;
d'influence sont a considerer : premierement, l'influence des politiques&#13;
ou programmes en question sur la mortalit6 et sur la fecondit6; et&#13;
deuxiemement, l'influence de la baisse de la fecondite ainsi suscitee sur&#13;
le taux de variation de la mortalit6, et vice versa.&#13;
Les methodes actuelles, qui se concentrent au premier chef sur&#13;
les consequences pour la croissance d'une variation de la mortalit6 ou de&#13;
la fecondite uniquement, negligent dans l'ensemble le premier des deux&#13;
types d'influence precit6s. De ce fait, elles ne sauraient convenir a&#13;
l'evaluation des politiques et programmes gouvernementaux, notamment a&#13;
l'evaluation des nombreux programmes et politiques lances pour reduire la&#13;
mortalit6 qui ont 6galement une forte incidence sur la f6condit6, et vice&#13;
versa.&#13;
Une methode du type necessaire est plus difficile a appliquer&#13;
qu'a adopter. Toutefois, on peut illustrer son importance potentielle&#13;
pour l'analyse des politiques et des programmes en donnant quelques&#13;
exemples qualitatifs et quelques chiffres.   Ces exemples, examin6s a la&#13;
lumiere des considerations de principe presentees, permettent de formuler&#13;
deux propositions destinees a servir de directives provisoires pour une&#13;
action et d'hypotheses, qui devront etre confirmees ou refutees par des&#13;
travaux de recherche futurs:&#13;
- La plupart des programmes et politiques entrepris pour reduire&#13;
la mortalite deboucheront, le plus souvent et a longue echeance, sur une&#13;
baisse encore plus forte de la f6condit6, et par cons6quent sur une crois-&#13;
sance plus lente.&#13;
- La plupart des mesures destinees a reduire la f6condit6&#13;
entraineront egalement un ralentissement de la croissance, mais d'une&#13;
ampleur qui pourrait, a l'occasion, etre sensiblement plus modeste qu'on&#13;
ne l'avait prevu en se fondant sur les techniques classiques d'evaluation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Extracto&#13;
ZCuAles son las consecuencias para el crecimiento de la poblaci6n de&#13;
las politicas y programas publicos destinados a reducir la mortalidad?&#13;
ZQu6 dimensiones tendra el cambio en el crecimiento que resultara de los&#13;
esfuerzos por disminuir la fecundidad?&#13;
Para responder adecuadamente a estos interrogantes se requiere un&#13;
enfoque que comience con los programas y politicas que se estudian y que&#13;
examine su influencia general en la fecundidad y la mortalidad. Hay que&#13;
referirse a dos tipos de influencia: primero, la de las politicas y pro-&#13;
gramas objeto del examen sobre la mortalidad y la fecundidad, y segundo,&#13;
la influencia de la disminuci6n resultante de la fecundidad o la mortali-&#13;
dad sobre la tasa de cambio en la otra.&#13;
Los enfoques actuales, que se centran primordialmente en las conse-&#13;
cuencias en el crecimiento de un cambio en la mortalidad o la fecundidad&#13;
en si, en gran parte desatienden el primero de estos dos tipos de influen-&#13;
cia. Esto los hace inapropiados para la evaluaci6n de las politicas y&#13;
programas publicos, en especial la evaluaci6n de las muchas politicas y&#13;
programas implantados con el objeto de reducir la mortalidad, o la fecun-&#13;
didad, que tambien tienen fuertes repercusiones directas en la otra.&#13;
Un enfoque del tipo que se requiere es mas dificil de aplicar que de&#13;
apoyar y defender. Pero su posible importancia para el analisis de poli-&#13;
ticas y programas puede ilustrarse mediante unos pocos ejemplos cualitati-&#13;
vos y cuantitativos basicos. Estas ilustraciones, tomadas en conjunto con&#13;
las consideraciones conceptuales que se presentan, sugieren dos proposi-&#13;
ciones que serviran de orientaciones provisionales en la adopci6n de medi-&#13;
das y como hip6tesis que se confirmaran o se refutaran mediante futuras&#13;
investigaciones:&#13;
-- La mayoria de los programas y politicas emprendidos para&#13;
reducir la mortalidad, en la mayoria de los ambientes y a largo plazo&#13;
produciran disminuciones aun mayores de la fecundidad y, por lo tanto, un&#13;
crecimiento mas lento.&#13;
-- La mayor parte de las medidas destinadas a reducir la fecun-&#13;
didad tambien daran por resultado un crecimiento mas lento, pero en un&#13;
porcentaje que en ocasiones puede ser considerablemente menor de lo pre-&#13;
visto segun tecnicas de evaluaci6n corrientes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page&#13;
Introduction Ot i o O  O O O O O O O O O O O O O O O O O O  * O a a  O O O  O* * O  D o a  o o o o a  o o   o o o o o o &#13;
10    Three Models for Assessing the Population&#13;
Growth Implications of Mortality and&#13;
Fertility Reduction Measureso0   .oo o0ooeo.0oo .   ... oooo0oooo0  2&#13;
The Models in Brief&#13;
The Models and Mortality Reduction Measures&#13;
The Models and Fertility Reduction Measures&#13;
II   The Implications of Using Model C:&#13;
Two Qualitative Illustrationso.soo0GO00.ooo. 000.00Ooooo0.0f.     9&#13;
Child Survival Programs&#13;
Equitable Development Measures&#13;
III. The Implications of Using Model C:&#13;
Three Quantitative Illustrations.000.         0.  00.0 0..oooO.Oo  18&#13;
Overall Development&#13;
Income Distribution&#13;
Child Spacing&#13;
Conclusionsoo0oo.00.0oo.ooooooooooooo.oo00.oooo..oooooooooooo. 31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Introduction&#13;
A great deal of work has gone into exploring the influence of mortality&#13;
reduction on fertility and on population growth. A comparable amount of&#13;
effort has been devoted to demonstrating the population growth implications of&#13;
faster fertility decline.&#13;
The quality of this research has often been impressive, and its findings&#13;
have frequently been illuminating. Its results, however, can be misleading.&#13;
For the population growth consequences of a mortality or fertility change per&#13;
se are not necessarily the same as - and might well, under some circum-&#13;
stances, be quite different from -- the population growth implications of the&#13;
policy or program producing that change, because of other demographic effects&#13;
produced by the policy'and program in question.&#13;
What matters from a public policy perspective is the overall impact of&#13;
measures available for consideration or under implementation rather than the&#13;
effects of only one of the changes resulting from them. An adequate appre-&#13;
ciation of the population growth implications of public efforts will thus&#13;
require movement away from the present focus on the growth impact of a mor-&#13;
tality or fertility change per se, toward a broader assessment that starts&#13;
with the programs and policies responsible for that mortality or fertility&#13;
change.&#13;
What follows represents an intial effort in this direction. It is to&#13;
proceed in the three stages. The first will feature a presentation of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
approach to be advanced, along with an explanation of how it differs from and&#13;
why it appears preferable to those currently in use. The second stage will&#13;
consist of a discussion of two prominent recent policy and program proposals&#13;
-- one for reducing fertility, the other for reducing mortality -- a&#13;
discussion designed to show how an assessment of the proposals' population&#13;
growth implications would be affected by using the approach being advanced in&#13;
place of those currently in use. Third will come an extension of the qualita-&#13;
tive presentation of part two by means of a few elementary, crude quantitative&#13;
illustrations. This will be followed by a brief summary and word of encour-&#13;
agement to anyone interested in undertaking the much more careful quantitative&#13;
work that will be required if the full demographic impacts of fertilty and&#13;
mortality measures are to be adequately appreciated.&#13;
I. Three Models for Assessing the Population Growth Implications of Mortality&#13;
and Fertility Reduction Measures&#13;
The need for change in approach and the nature of the changes needed can&#13;
be illustrated with reference to the three simple models whose principal&#13;
features are sketched in figure 1: models A, B, and C.I/ Models A and B are&#13;
those currently in use: model A with respect to mortality reduction, model B&#13;
with respect to fertility reduction. Model C is that to be advanced as more&#13;
appropriate.&#13;
The Models in Brief&#13;
Model A has the initial decline in mortality as its starting point.&#13;
According to it, mortality decline affects population growth in two ways.&#13;
First, the reduction in mortality operates directly on population growth:&#13;
ceteris paribus, the larger the mortality decline, the greater the accelera-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
Figure 1:     Approaches to the Assessment&#13;
of Demographic Change&#13;
Model A                                    Model B&#13;
The Growth Implications of                  The Growth Implications of&#13;
Changed Mortality:                          Changed Fertility:&#13;
The Current Approach                        The Current Approach&#13;
CHANGED                     -   CHANGED                           CHANGED&#13;
MORTALITY                       FERTILITY                         FERTILITY&#13;
,  .&#13;
CIIANGED                          CHANGED&#13;
CROWTH          |         |       GROWTH&#13;
Model C&#13;
The Growth Implications of&#13;
Mortality or Fertility Change Measures:&#13;
The Proposed Approach&#13;
POLICY OR PROGRAM&#13;
MEASURE\&#13;
CHANGED                         CHANGED&#13;
MORTALITY                       FERTILITY&#13;
\                       l~~~~CHNE&#13;
\       r           v           |GRWT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
tion of growth. Second, it works indirectly through fertility. Mortality&#13;
decline, especially infant mortality decline, produces a reduction in fer-&#13;
tility by extending the period of lactation and by reducing the number of&#13;
births required for a couple to produce a given number of surviving offspring.&#13;
This fertility decline, which tends to reduce population growth, represents a&#13;
countervailing pressure to that produced by the mortality decline's more&#13;
direct growth influence.&#13;
The amount of work being undertaken within the framework of this model is&#13;
voluminous. Of special concern has been a delineation and assessment of the&#13;
mechanisms through which infant mortality decline leads to a reduction of fer-&#13;
tility: the separation of the physiological from the behavioral; the division&#13;
of the behavioral into "replacement" and "insurance" or "hoarding" effects;&#13;
the measurement of the quantitative significance of each. Of equal interest&#13;
to researchers has been the overall size of the indirect relative to the&#13;
direct influences of mortality decline on population growth: whether, in par-&#13;
ticular, the influence of infant mortality reductions on fertility is large&#13;
enough to offset fully the pressure for faster population growth those reduc-&#13;
tions also generate.l/&#13;
Model B -- if the term "model" can appropriately be applied to something&#13;
so simple as two boxes connected by an arrow -- is even more straightforward&#13;
than model A. It begins with fertility decline, which is translated directly&#13;
into slower population growth. Model B is simpler than model A because it&#13;
lacks provision for an indirect effect on population growth via mortality&#13;
reduction. The implicit assumption is that faster fertility decline does not&#13;
affect the rate of mortality decline.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
This is the model behind the standard approach used in hundreds of popu-&#13;
lation projection exercises undertaken to demonstrate the influence of faster&#13;
fertility decline: exercises featuring variations in the rate of fertility&#13;
decline while leaving the rate of mortality decline unchanged in order to pro-&#13;
duce alternate projections of population size whose differences are attribu-&#13;
table to differences in the path of fertility alone.!/ This approach has also&#13;
been taken in presenting the results produced by many well-known demographic-&#13;
economic models designed to demonstrate the influence of faster fertility&#13;
decline and slower population growth on economic output.AI&#13;
As abstractions, both models A and B are quite valid. And as such, they&#13;
have proven to be of great value in pointing to features of demographic change&#13;
that would not otherwise be intuitively obvious.5/&#13;
They are not, however, adequate for policy or program analysis. They&#13;
would be satisfactory for this purpose only if mortality and fertility&#13;
declines could be made to happen exogenously -- if policy makers could simply&#13;
wish them into being. But this is not possible. Those who desire changes&#13;
must put into effect policies and programs to produce them; and these policies&#13;
and programs have demographic consequences that can be considerably wider than&#13;
those captured by models A and B. And this means results that could be&#13;
correspondingly different.&#13;
Thus model C, designed to capture these other consequences. As can be&#13;
seen, both models A and B are contained in it, but it is broader than either.&#13;
In particular, model C starts with a policy, program, or other development&#13;
leading to a change in mortality and/or fertility, rather than with the mor-&#13;
tality or fertility change itself. And it examines simultaneously the mor-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6-&#13;
tality and fertility effects of the policy, program, or development under&#13;
examination in assessing its significance for growth../&#13;
The Models and Mortality Reduction Measures&#13;
Model C provides two channels whereby activities undertaken for the pur-&#13;
pose of reducing mortality can influence fertility. The indirect channel of&#13;
model C, which operates via the mortality reduction produced, is the same as&#13;
the single channel of model A. But in addition to the indirect channel, model&#13;
C incorporates a further, largely overlooked direct channel7/ whereby mor-&#13;
tality reduction policies and programs can influence fertility by inducing&#13;
changes in attitudes and behavior in ways that are largely independent of&#13;
whatever mortality reduction might be achieved.&#13;
This second channel is incorporated in recognition of the importance of&#13;
the direct fertility reduction influence exercised by many measures frequently&#13;
discussed in terms of their mortality impact.!/ An example is women's educa-&#13;
tion, which has been closely linked with reductions in infant mortality.9/&#13;
For every point of infant mortality reduction attributable to improved mater-&#13;
nal education, there would be the indirect impact on fertility described above&#13;
with respect to both models A and C, an impact presumably equal in magnitude&#13;
to that produced by a comparably large infant mortality reduction resulting&#13;
from any other measure. But, as is well known, women's education can also&#13;
affect fertility directly: by delaying marriage to permit the completion of&#13;
schooling, for example; through increasing women's qualifications for jobs&#13;
outside the home that can compete with child-bearing as a means of gaining&#13;
satisfaction and status; by enhancing the likelihood that the lower family&#13;
size ideals cof younger women will prevail over those of older generations..LO/&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
Such effects would produce additional downward pressure on birth rates that&#13;
would be ignored were only the indirect influence to be considered.&#13;
To say that a direct influence can exist is not, of course, to claim that&#13;
it will inevitably be important. At least some mortality reduction measures&#13;
that have proven effective in the past and that are frequently mentioned as&#13;
possible models for the future seem likely to exercise little if any direct&#13;
impact on fertility. Examples include quasi-military approaches to malaria&#13;
reduction through the application of pesticides by spraying teams from outside&#13;
the villages affected, and the somewhat similar approach to vaccination and&#13;
containment that worked so well against smallpox.l/ In neither case is it&#13;
possible to see how the approach used might have contributed to any lasting&#13;
changes in couples' attitudes or reproductive behavior other than those&#13;
resulting from the mortality decline that occurred.&#13;
The strength of the direct fertility influence thus seems likely to vary&#13;
greatly from measure to measure; and because of this, the use of model C&#13;
implies that the magnitude of fertility decline associated with any given&#13;
amount of mortality reduction is not fixed.    Under model A, whose only channel&#13;
of influence on fertility flows from mortality decline to fertility, there is&#13;
little room for variability: a ten-point infant mortality decline is a ten-&#13;
point decline, regardless of how produced. But when the possibility of a&#13;
highly variable direct influence is added, the picture changes. The amount of&#13;
fertility decline per unit of mortality reduction becomes a function of the&#13;
measures or developments by which the mortality reduction in question is pro-&#13;
duced.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
The Models and Fertility Reduction Measures&#13;
Model C also provides two channels through which measures initiated in&#13;
order to reduce fertility can lower mortality as well. The first channel is&#13;
direct, analogous to that discussed earlier with respect to the effect of mor-&#13;
tality reduction measures on fertility. The second channel is indirect, per-&#13;
mitting the fertility reduction achieved to exercise an effect on mortality&#13;
decline. This effect, comparable to the much-discussed influence of mortality&#13;
reduction on fertility, has been curiously ignored in quantitative assessments&#13;
of fertility reduction's population growth implications despite the publicity&#13;
that family planning advocates give to fertility reduction's health and mor-&#13;
tality benefits.&#13;
The first of these two channels is intended to account for the propensity&#13;
of many -- although not necessarily alL2/ - fertility reduction approaches&#13;
to act directly on mortality as well.L3/ An example is income distribution,&#13;
whose relationship with fertility has been widely discussed.iL4/ Because of&#13;
the non-linearity of the income-fertility relationship, it is often argued&#13;
that a pattern of development featuring faster improvements at lower rather&#13;
than at higher income levels will produce a greater impact on fertility than a&#13;
pattern where the largest gains are enjoyed by the better-off. To think in&#13;
terms of non-linearities with respect only to fertility, though, would&#13;
obviously be a mistake. For they exist at least equally clearly if not even&#13;
more clearly with respect to mortality. It is well established that the poor&#13;
will spend a much larger proportion of any income increment on basic com-&#13;
modities reLevant for health than will the rich, thus implying that income&#13;
channeled to the poor will produce a commensurately greater impact on&#13;
mortality. 5/&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9-&#13;
The second, indirect channel is designed to account for well-known change&#13;
in mortality that can be produced by fertility reduction per se. Fertility&#13;
reduction can be expected to result in a mortality decline when the fertility&#13;
reduction occurs through particularly large declines in births with a higher-&#13;
than-average risk of early death and/or through a shift of births from a high-&#13;
risk to a low-risk category: that is, when older women with many children are&#13;
among the earliest to practice family limitation, and when birth intervals&#13;
lengthenJL6/ Where this mortality impact is found, the population growth&#13;
influence of fertility reduction will be diluted in the same manner that the&#13;
mortality decline's impact on growth is lessened by the induced change in fer-&#13;
tility.&#13;
II. The Implications of Using Model C: Two Qualitative Illustrations&#13;
So much for the theory. What does all this have to do with today's world&#13;
and the way in which population policies and programs are shaped and assessed&#13;
in it?&#13;
One way of responding to such a query is to supplement the brief allu-&#13;
sions to policy implications scattered through the preceding theoretical&#13;
discussion with a systematic look, through the lenses of the different models&#13;
presented, at the population growth implications of some measures currently&#13;
being advanced to alter mortality and fertility trends. In this manner, it is&#13;
possible to get a preliminary, qualitative sense of the difference that would&#13;
result from applying model C rather than model A or B.&#13;
Two sets of proposed measures are especially well suited for this&#13;
illustrative purpose. One, concerned primarily with mortality, features pro-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-10-&#13;
posals for increasing child survival probabilities. The other consists of&#13;
packages of development measures recommended for the reduction of fertility.&#13;
Child Survival Programs&#13;
In recent years, several international agencies have expressed interest&#13;
in developing or implementing measures that would increase the likelihood of&#13;
child survival. Among the best known are the World Health Organization's&#13;
emphasis on primary health care, UNICEF's proposal for a "child survival&#13;
revolution," and the Ford Foundation's "Child Survival/Fair Start' program..L7/&#13;
Since such interest arises primarily out of a desire to reduce mortality,&#13;
the conventional way of assessing the population growth implications of&#13;
programs emanating from it would be through the application of model A, with&#13;
its focus on the fertility reduction resulting from whatever improvements in&#13;
infant and child mortality might be produced.&#13;
The use of model C's broader outlook could be expected to produce results&#13;
differing in two ways from those of such a conventional approach. First, the&#13;
contribution of child survival programs to fertility reduction will often be&#13;
stronger. Second, the magnitude of this contribution will not be fixed but&#13;
will vary according to the mix of measures employed.&#13;
Because of its specificity, the UNICEF "child survival revolution" is&#13;
particularly well suited to an illustration of the point. The UNICEF propos-&#13;
al, first advanced in late 1982, is a package of seven measures known by the&#13;
acronym "GO1BI-FFF."18/ The seven measures are:&#13;
- Growth monitoring: the use of child growth charts along with regular&#13;
weighing and back-up advice to help parents and health workers identify&#13;
children at risk.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-11-&#13;
- Oral rehydration therapy: the oral administation of a simple solution&#13;
to counter the dehydration that is the most frequent immediate cause of death&#13;
resulting from diarrhea-producing infections.&#13;
- Breast feeding: the promotion of awareness about the benefits of breast&#13;
milk and continued reliance on it.&#13;
- Immunization: the expansion of programs to vaccinate against six major&#13;
communicable diseases of childhood: measles, tetanus, whooping cough,&#13;
diphtheria, poliomyelitis, and tuberculosis.&#13;
- Food supplements: the furnishing of extra food to poor mothers for the&#13;
purpose of reducing the incidence of low birth weights, and for high-risk&#13;
children at the time of weaning.&#13;
- Family spacing: the provision of the knowledge and the means mothers&#13;
need to lengthen the interval between births.&#13;
- Female education: the improvement in the general knowledge base and&#13;
status of the mother who represents, in UNICEF's terms, "the most important&#13;
primary health care worker.' 1L9 /&#13;
An assessment of a GOBI-FFF program implications done in terms of the&#13;
conventional (model A) framework examining only the indirect effect would in&#13;
all likelihood lead to the conclusion that the fertility influence is not&#13;
strong enough to offset fully the change in mortality decline. For there is a&#13;
general consensus among researchers that the replacement effect of mortality&#13;
decline is significantly less than one-for-one; and a strong suspicion that,&#13;
at least in the short run, the addition of the other indirect effects of anti-&#13;
mortality measures on fertility are not large enough to make up the dif-&#13;
ference. To the extent this is so, a GOBI-FFF program would be found to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-12-&#13;
produce at least some increase in population growth. The increase would not&#13;
be large, to be sure, for demographic conditions are now such that even the&#13;
fastest acceleration in infant child mortality decline realistically imagi-&#13;
nable will produce an increment that is modest relative to that which would&#13;
occur should trends continue as presently envisioned.2!0/ But however limited&#13;
the difference, it would probably be found to lie in the direction of a larger&#13;
rather than El smaller population size.&#13;
Such a conclusion would be distinctly less likely when the examination is&#13;
conducted in the context of a broader framework, like that of model C, which&#13;
can accomodate the direct as well as the indirect fertility influence of&#13;
GOBI-FFF program measures. For many of those measures clearly have strong&#13;
direct effects.&#13;
Female education's direct influence has already been described. Breast-&#13;
feeding and extended birth intervals routinely figure in lists of fertility&#13;
reduction approaches worthy of consideration.&#13;
Such other measures as immunization, oral rehydration, and growth moni-&#13;
toring would not seem necessarily to affect fertility so strongly: as&#13;
suggested earlier, for example, smallpox was eradicated through an immuniza-&#13;
tion program lacking immediately obvious direct fertility influence. Yet, as&#13;
UNICEF discussions of the GOBI-FFF programs indicate and as others have&#13;
argued, the success of such measures in the future seems likely to depend&#13;
heavily upon the personal behavior of those most affected..1-/ Mothers are not&#13;
likely to come or bring their children for immunizations, for example, unless&#13;
they are aware that disease is caused by physiological rather than by super-&#13;
natural phenomena; the success of oral rehydration or growth monitoring pro-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-13-&#13;
grams will depend heavily on the mother's awareness of how these activities&#13;
can contribute. To the extent this is so, the effective implementation of&#13;
such measures will require extensive educational as well as technology&#13;
delivery efforts; and success will depend upon women's becoming adequately&#13;
conscious and broadly "empowered" to take control of many aspects of their&#13;
lives, such as fertility, in addition to being able to act effectively in&#13;
areas of behavior most directly relevant for immunization, growth monitoring,&#13;
and oral rehydration.&#13;
This need for education may well increase the difficulty of achieving&#13;
immediate mortality gains through technologically simple programs. But it&#13;
also implies that any such programs which succeed will contain heavy doses of&#13;
health and related education that mean the programs will exercise a much&#13;
greater effect on fertility than suggested by a consideration of the programs'&#13;
technological elements by themselves, pointing toward a commensurately larger&#13;
amount of fertility decline per unit of mortality reduction achieved.&#13;
This means that conventional assessments which ignore such direct effects&#13;
clearly overstate any contribution to faster growth that GOBI-FFF programs&#13;
might make. In fact, when these direct effects are added to the indirect&#13;
influence noted earlier, it seems quite possible that some, perhaps many,&#13;
GOBI-FFF program configurations would exercise a notably larger impact on fer-&#13;
tility than on mortality, thus restraining population growth.&#13;
As noted, the addition of direct effects through a more complete (model&#13;
C) approach would also introduce the possibility of a variable mortality-&#13;
fertility relationship, rather than the fixed relationship suggested by con-&#13;
ventional (model A) thinking. As a result, the relative size of the fertility&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-14-&#13;
and mortality reductions produced by a program of the sort advocated by UNICEF&#13;
would depend on the program's structure and implementation.&#13;
When only the fertility impact of mortality decline per se is considered,&#13;
there is, as argued earlier, no basis for believing that the amount of fer-&#13;
tility reduction associated with a given mortality decline might vary from&#13;
measure to measure. Under an assessment based solely on the indirect fer-&#13;
tility effect of mortality reduction measures, it would be reasonable to&#13;
expect roughly the same population growth impact from a given amount of infant&#13;
mortality reduction, regardless of whether that reduction were produced by,&#13;
say, a GOBI, an FFF, or a total GOBI-FFF effort.&#13;
This would no longer be the case when direct effects are also considered.&#13;
For, as just described, there are grounds for suspecting that the direct fer-&#13;
tility effect of the GOBI-FFF program efforts can vary greatly, depending both&#13;
on the mix of components and upon how the selected mix of components is imple-&#13;
mented (whether, for example, immunization programs are introduced more as&#13;
technology delivery or as education efforts). If this is so, the population&#13;
growth implications of, say, a GOBI program could well differ from those of&#13;
some other mix of GOBI-FF program components - such as a "FIGO," "BIFFO," or&#13;
some other such effort. This variability provides program designers with an&#13;
opportunity to create component mixes that will vary not only with respect to&#13;
their effectiveness in reducing mortality but also respect to the ratio of&#13;
fertility to mortality reduction achieved and thus with respect to the amount&#13;
of change in population size produced.&#13;
Equitable Development Measures&#13;
A prominent feature of population discussions during the 1970s was atten-&#13;
tion to the clemographic implications of faster and more equitable development.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-15-&#13;
Particular interest was expressed in development's fertility effects, an&#13;
interest that produced material ranging in tone from the thoughtful presen-&#13;
tations of such authors as James Kocher, Robert McNamara, and William Rich to&#13;
the strident claims that 'development is the best contraceptive" expressed at&#13;
the 1974 Bucharest World Population Conference.&amp;2./ For all the important dif-&#13;
ferences in tone, however, such discussions generally led toward the common&#13;
conclusion that more rapid and more egalitarian development could produce&#13;
faster fertility decline.&#13;
The amount of reduction in population growth that could be expected to&#13;
result from this faster fertility decline was rarely if ever explicitly con-&#13;
sidered. The absence of such a consideration makes the views of those empha-&#13;
sizing development's importance for fertility reduction difficult to assess&#13;
with confidence; but they appear to have assumed that faster fertility reduc-&#13;
tion could reasonably be expected to result in a roughly commensurate23/&#13;
slowing of population growth.&#13;
This, certainly, is the conclusion that would follow from applying the&#13;
conventional (model B) approach to an assessment of the population growth&#13;
implications of faster fertility decline resulting from development measures,&#13;
for this approach does not permit consideration of the possibility that&#13;
knk1lpmont might also produem fnta.t ffi6Italfty reJuction. In allowing for&#13;
the appearance of such a countervailing change, a more complete (model C)&#13;
assessment would be likely to result in a more restrained conclusion about the&#13;
amount of growth reduction that would result from measures which reduce fer-&#13;
tility. On a priori grounds, in fact, there would be little basis for&#13;
dismissing the possibility that at least some fertility-reducing development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-16-&#13;
measures might actually lead toward faster growth by producing an even larger&#13;
decline in mortality than in fertility.&#13;
The point can best be understood with reference to a specific example.&#13;
Of those available, the most concrete and thus the most suitable for illustra-&#13;
tive purposes in the proposal of Robert McNamara contained in his well-known&#13;
1977 MIT speech.14/&#13;
McNamara's principal concern, he made quite clear at the outset of his&#13;
speech, was the threat posed by population growth. "Short of thermonuclear&#13;
war...," he said, "it (population growth) is the gravest issue the world faces&#13;
over the decade immediately ahead. Indeed, in many ways rampant population&#13;
growth is an even more dangerous and subtle threat to the world than ther-&#13;
monuclear war, for it is intrinsically less subject to rational safeguards,&#13;
and less amenable to organized control."25/&#13;
His prescription for the humane reduction in growth that he sought empha-&#13;
sized the achievement of faster fertility decline, especially through the&#13;
social and economic approaches needed to encourage couples to desire smaller&#13;
families and thus to avail themselves of the contraceptive services whose pro-&#13;
vision be aLso advocated. In particular, McNamara proposed a five-point&#13;
program. "IJovernments " he said, "should try to:&#13;
"- Reduce current infant and child mortality rates sharply.&#13;
"- Expand basic education and increase the proportion of girls in&#13;
school.&#13;
"- Increase the productivity of smallholders in the rural areas, and&#13;
expand earning opportunities in the cities for low-income groups.&#13;
"- Put greater stress on more equitable distribution of income and ser-&#13;
vices in the drive for greater economic growth.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-17-&#13;
'-- And above all else, raise the status of women socially, economically,&#13;
and politically."26/&#13;
How much of a decline in growth would result from the implementation of&#13;
such measures? The answer, which McNamara did not try to provide, will almost&#13;
certainly vary according to the way in which the measures' impact is assessed.&#13;
As has been seen, any judgment framed in terms of the (model B) approach&#13;
normally applied to a proposal presented as an approach to fertility reduction&#13;
would involve a direct translation of any fertility reduction achieved into a&#13;
slowing of population growth. For the assumption is that the measures will&#13;
not change the rate of mortality decline.27/&#13;
This, however, can hardly be considered a realistic way to deal with a&#13;
set of measures which, in different surroundings, could just as well be pre-&#13;
sented as a program for the reduction of mortality. Its first component is an&#13;
explicit call to reduce Infant and child mortality; and two others deal with&#13;
the education and status of women, whose direct influence on infant mortality&#13;
is well known. Clearly, no measures of this sort can reasonably be expected&#13;
to produce changes in birth rates unless death rates are also reduced.&#13;
A successful application of such measures would clearly make the world a&#13;
far better place than it now is, and the measures are all the more attractive&#13;
because of their ability to produce mortality as well as fertility benefits.&#13;
The fact that mortality as well as fertility will decline more rapidly,&#13;
however, also means that any population growth reduction would be at least&#13;
somewhat, perhaps significantly, smaller than suggested by an assessment&#13;
assuming no change in the rate of mortality decline.&#13;
In other words, because of the inability of the standard, model B&#13;
approach to accomodate such changes in mortality -- whether resulting directly&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-18-&#13;
from the meEtsures in question or indirectly via the fertility changes those&#13;
measures produce -- its use would project a larger reduction in population&#13;
growth than the McNamara proposal would be likely to produce. Because model C&#13;
explicitly takes mortality change into account, a demographic evaluation&#13;
undertaken within the framework suggested by it could be expected to present a&#13;
different and more restrained set of findings.&#13;
III. The Implications of Using Model C: Three Quantitative Illustrations&#13;
The two examples just presented are, of course, qualitative rather than&#13;
quantitative. Many will doubtless be reluctant to accept the value of such&#13;
qualitative arguments without assurance that they are also quantitatively&#13;
significant.&#13;
Such assurance is difficult to provide. Neither the statistical models&#13;
nor the data currently available are well suited for the task. Even if they&#13;
were, the wiLde range of program and policy options available and the large&#13;
variations In the developing country settings where they must be applied mean&#13;
that a mass:Lve volume of research would be required before any valid general&#13;
statements would be justified.&#13;
It is lpossible, however, to present crude and oversimplified quantitative&#13;
illustrations which, for all their obvious inadequacies, can contribute sig-&#13;
nificantly to a sense that the application of model C to empirical data is&#13;
likely to yield results that are not intuitively obvious -- and that are also&#13;
often likely to differ enough from those produced by the use of the concep-&#13;
tually inferior models A or B to justify efforts to apply model C despite its&#13;
greater complexity. Aside from their policy interest, such findings represent&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-19-&#13;
a justification for the more detailed work required for assessments embodying&#13;
an adequately complete, "model C" approach.&#13;
The point can be illustrated by three simple examples. Selected oppor-&#13;
tunistically on the basis of the ready availability of the prior work required&#13;
for the preparation of illustrations within the limited time available, they&#13;
do not necessarily represent the approaches of greatest policy interest. They&#13;
do, however, cover a wide range of issues. One, intended to provide a general&#13;
background, deals with the pace of overall economic and social development.&#13;
Another, somewhat more specific, concerns income distribution, one of the&#13;
McNamara fertility proposals. The third is narrower or more specific still:&#13;
child spacing, a component of the UNICEF mortality proposal.&#13;
Each example consists of a set of population projections. Each set&#13;
starts with a baseline projection, developed from some more or less reasonable&#13;
assumption about the movement of the determinant of mortality and fertility&#13;
under consideration in the absence of special efforts to change its course.&#13;
Then come projections that seek to approximate the demographic consequences of&#13;
an altered rate of change in that determinant: projections based on model A,&#13;
on model B, and on model C.&#13;
Overall Development&#13;
Overall development, clearly, is not a single policy that one puts into&#13;
effect on any particular morning. Rather, it is the cummulative result of a&#13;
myriad of actions taken over an extended period. An examination of its&#13;
demographic consequences is thus still a large step from examining the&#13;
demographic effects of an individual policy or program. Such an examination&#13;
is nonetheless an obvious place to begin, as an initial step in the right&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-20-&#13;
direction away from investigating the population growth consequences of mor-&#13;
tality or fertility change per se toward examining the consequences of the&#13;
factors that determine those changes.&#13;
Also, it is easy to produce usefully illustrative, even if far from de-&#13;
finitive, estimates of the demographic implications of faster or slower devel-&#13;
opment. These can be derived from any of several available cross-country&#13;
analyses of the relationship among demographic and other social and economic&#13;
variables at different stages of development,28! by defining as "normal" the&#13;
trajectory represented by movement through the different stages identified in&#13;
such studies and by comparing the demographic implications of alternate rates&#13;
of movement along this course.&#13;
Annex I presents a detailed description of how this can be accomplished&#13;
for one such study: the work on the correspondence among development indica-&#13;
tors by Donald McGranahan and his colleagues at the United Nations Research&#13;
Institute for Social Development..29/ As explained in the annex, the approach&#13;
employed consists of taking a population with the social, economic, and&#13;
demographic characteristics of a typical low-income country and "moving it" at&#13;
a 2% and then at a 3% annual development rate along the path described by the&#13;
relationships identified by the McGranahan group. The population size asso-&#13;
ciated with the 2% rate is defined as the baseline; and the population size&#13;
associated w:Lth the 3% rate is estimated by applying crude approximations of&#13;
models A, B, and C.&#13;
The results of the exercise are summarized in table 1. As can be seen,&#13;
the differences over the short run, defined as the initial twenty-five years&#13;
or so, are modest; but thereafter, they become progressively more significant.&#13;
In brief:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-21-&#13;
Table 1: Differences in Population&#13;
Size Associated with a 3%&#13;
rather than a 2% Annual&#13;
Rate of Development&#13;
Population Size Associated with 3% Annual&#13;
Development Scenario Relative to that&#13;
Year            Associated with 2% Scenario, in Year Indicated&#13;
As Assessed by     As Assessed by      As Assessed by&#13;
Model A            Model B             Model C&#13;
0&#13;
25               +0.5%               -0.5%              +1.0%&#13;
50               +4.7%               -7.2%              +0.5%&#13;
75               +6.7%              -24.3%             -17.6%&#13;
100               +6.2%              -43.3%             -39.9%&#13;
Source: Annex I&#13;
Notes: See table 1-3 for absolute population size figures. The&#13;
figures presented above for model A are based on those in&#13;
the "adjusted" column of that table.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-22-&#13;
-- Under the 3% scenario, mortality decline is much faster:&#13;
over the initial 50 years, the 3% scenario produces nearly three times as&#13;
large an increase in life expectancy (16.5 years vs. 5.6 years) and over twice&#13;
as rapid a decline in infant mortality (76 vs. 28 points) as the 2% scenario.&#13;
Application oF the model A approach, with its assumption that this faster mor-&#13;
tality decline is exogenously introduced in a manner producing no change in&#13;
fertility other than that induced by the faster mortality decline itself,&#13;
results in a population 6.2% larger than the baseline population after 100&#13;
years.&#13;
-- After the initial twenty-five years, during which more rapid&#13;
development has little influence on the rate of fertility change, birth rates&#13;
also fall faster under the 3% than under the 2% scenario. Between twenty-five&#13;
and seventy-five years, for instance, the crude birth rate falls by almost&#13;
twenty points under the 3 % scenario, more than double the nine points under&#13;
the 2% scenario. The use of model B, which assumes an exogenously-introduced&#13;
incease in fertility reduction that does not affect the rate of mortality&#13;
decline, yields after 100 years a total population 43.3% smaller than that of&#13;
the baseline.&#13;
-- When the population growth implications of the faster mor-&#13;
tality decline and the faster fertility reduction are assessed together, as is&#13;
done through model C, the faster fertility decline is found to be quan-&#13;
titatively more significant over the long run. After 25 years, the population&#13;
size is slightly (1%) larger. But 100 years after the starting point of the&#13;
projection, the population size under the 3% development scenario is 39.9%&#13;
smaller.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-23-&#13;
For all the reasons indicated in annex I, none of these figures can be&#13;
legitimately accepted as more than broadly indicative. Yet of the three&#13;
alternatives, that produced by the use of model C is clearly the least flawed&#13;
and thus to be preferred. For, once faster development is recognized as the&#13;
common cause of the morality and fertility change under consideration, it&#13;
makes no sense to consider either mortality or fertility change alone; if&#13;
changes are to be introduced, the two have to be taken together.&#13;
Acceptance of this view implies a recognition of the serious error which&#13;
can result from inferring that faster mortality decline necessarily means&#13;
faster population growth. When exogenously introduced, it obviously does.&#13;
But when caused by a set of factors that produce even faster declines in fer-&#13;
tility, a scenario involving more rapid reductions in mortality leads to a&#13;
smaller rather than a larger population size -- a size which, in this example,&#13;
turns out not to be much different from that estimated without regard to de-&#13;
velopment's mortality effect.&#13;
Income Distribution&#13;
Exploration of a more specific element of development policy -- namely,&#13;
income distribution -- is also possible. Like development itself, a change in&#13;
the distribution of income is the product of a mix of different programs and&#13;
policies; and as such, it too is a step removed from those programs and poli-&#13;
cies themselves which would be the preferred objects of study. But as a&#13;
determinant of fertility and mortality and as a symbol of a particular type of&#13;
development strategy, the overall demographic implications of income distribu-&#13;
tion are of interest; and because of a long tradition of empirical exploration&#13;
into it demographic effects, income distribution is much easier to examine&#13;
than most policies and programs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-24-&#13;
Especia,lly relevant is work by T.P. Dyson, C.L.G Bell, and R.H. Cassen&#13;
that examines the influence of different income distribution patterns on fer-&#13;
tility, mortality, and population growth.!2./ Annex II provides a description&#13;
of this work and of the way in which it can be used to illustrate quan-&#13;
titatively the implications of selecting model A, B, or C to assess the popu-&#13;
lation growth implications of fertility and mortality changes.&#13;
As indicated in the annex, the Dyson-Bell-Cassen exercise compares the&#13;
demographic implications of maintaining a highly unequal pattern of income&#13;
distribution as overall growth proceeds with the population growth effects of&#13;
a sharp shift toward a more egalitarian pattern of distribution when the rate&#13;
of overall iLncome growth is the same. This is done through a simulation model&#13;
projecting the population of low, medium, and high income groups on the basis&#13;
of parameters for the relationship between mortality and income and between&#13;
fertility and income established through cross-national and individual country&#13;
time series econometric analyses. These analyses produce trajectories in&#13;
which mortality and fertility generally decline at differing rates in response&#13;
to income increases.&#13;
Table 2 presents a summary of the most relevant findings resulting from a&#13;
projection exercise based on the Dyson-Bell-Cassen work. The results can be&#13;
seen to vary depending upon the time frame and method of assessment adopted.&#13;
In the short run, the differences in the population growth estimates pro-&#13;
duced by the three models are relatively small: at 50 years the difference&#13;
between the smallest and largest figures on table 2 is only about 3%. Such&#13;
differences as exist, however, suggest clearly that egalitarian development&#13;
produces faster population growth than inegalitarian development. For the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-25-&#13;
Table 2: Differences in the Population Size&#13;
Associated with More Egalitarian&#13;
rather than Less Egalitarian&#13;
Economic Development&#13;
Population Size Associated with a&#13;
"Changing Shares" Income Distribution Scenario&#13;
Relative to that Associated with a&#13;
Year             "Constant Shares" Scenario, in Year Indicated&#13;
As Assessed by     As Assessed by      As Assessed by&#13;
Model A            Model B             Model C&#13;
0&#13;
25                                   +0.5%              +1.1%&#13;
50               +0.6%               +1.8%              +3.5%&#13;
75               +3.0%               -1.7%              +4.3%&#13;
100               +6.7%              -15.5%              -4.4%&#13;
125              +10.1%              -31.5%             -17.9%&#13;
150              +11.7%              -41.6%             -28.0%&#13;
Source: Annex II&#13;
Notes: See table II-2 for absolute population size figures. The&#13;
figures presented above for model A are based on those in&#13;
the "adjusted" column of that table.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-26-&#13;
population of the "constant shares" or inequitably developing society is&#13;
smaller than the population of the "changing shares" or more equitably&#13;
developing Esociety regardless of the method used to assess the latter popula-&#13;
tion's size. This is a reflection of the greater proportion of income gain&#13;
accruing to the very poor, whose fertility response to income increases is&#13;
limited, during the initial stages of egalitarian development from a low&#13;
starting point.&#13;
Over the longer run, however, the picture changes. The magnitude of the&#13;
population size differences becomes much larger, and the way in which they are&#13;
assessed exercises a much greater influence on the policy conclusions drawn:&#13;
-- An assessment focussing only on mortality change results in a&#13;
larger population size because of the tendency of an egalitarian pattern to&#13;
produce faster mortality decline, a result of the previously noted propensity&#13;
of the poor to spend a higher proportion of an income increment on basic&#13;
needs. According to the Dyson-Bell-Cassen exercise, life expectancy is 2.3&#13;
years higher after 50 years under the "changing shares" than under the&#13;
"constant shares" scenario; after 100 years, the difference is 7.6 years. If&#13;
this increaise were to be considered an exogenous one, as in model A, the popu-&#13;
lation would be 11.7% larger than the baseline population after 150 years.&#13;
-- A judgement based only on fertility change, taken as exogen-&#13;
ously produced, obviously produces distinctly different results. Initially,&#13;
for the reason discussed earlier, a "changing shares" scenario results in&#13;
slower overall fertility decline than a "constant shares" scenario. After&#13;
about 50 years, however, fertility falls more rapidly when shares are&#13;
changing; and at 100 years the "changing shares" gross reproduction rate of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-27-&#13;
1.36 is well below the "constant shares" rate of 2.03. If only the effect of&#13;
this fertility difference is considered, as in model B, the result is a much&#13;
lower population total than that of the baseline: 41.6% smaller at 150 years.&#13;
-- When the faster mortality and fertility declines are con-&#13;
sidered together, through an approach like that suggested by model C, fer-&#13;
tility once again proves stronger than mortality in determining population&#13;
size. At 150 years, the "changing shares" population is 28.0% smaller than&#13;
the "constant shares" baseline population. This "model C" result is also&#13;
quite different from the "model A" and "model B" figures, being only about&#13;
two-thirds as large as the former and nearly one-quarter larger than the&#13;
latter.&#13;
If the model C results are taken to be as the least imperfect of the&#13;
three, the figures produced by the conventional approaches of A and B lead are&#13;
significantly misleading. Were income distribution's long-term direct effects&#13;
on fertility to be overlooked, then the conclusion could legitimately be that&#13;
a more equitable pattern of development would produce faster growth; whereas&#13;
in fact the opposite is much more likely to be true over the longer run. To&#13;
look only at distribution's fertility change implications would be to over-&#13;
state by a noticeable degree the amount of slower growth that might reasonably&#13;
be expected.&#13;
Child Spacing&#13;
While the long-term demographic benefits produced by faster and more&#13;
equitable development may be large, the profundity of the policy shifts&#13;
required to realize them is understandably unsettling to the policy maker won-&#13;
dering what specifically might be tried. What about something less all-&#13;
encompassing, more "doable?"&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-28-&#13;
Of the several candidates that come to mind, that most readily available&#13;
for study is child spacing, a point in the UNICEF GOBI-FFF program and closely&#13;
related to the increased breast-feeding that is another GOBI-FFF program ele-&#13;
ment. Like the other determinants discussed thus far, the lengthening of&#13;
birth intervals is not a program or policy in itself, but rather the outcome&#13;
of efforts to extend postpartum amenorrhea by such policies as promoting&#13;
breast feeding through educational measures, limiting in access to breast milk&#13;
substitutes, and providing creches for working mothers; and of activities that&#13;
delay conception after the reestablishment of ovulation, such as increasing&#13;
contraceptive use by younger couples..'l/ Extended birth intervals can,&#13;
though, be seen as the possible sum of the impacts of a package of such&#13;
measures and thus help serve as a basis for helping decide whether the bene-&#13;
fits of such a package are likely to be large enough to justify the time and&#13;
effort to develop it.&#13;
To embark on a study of child spacing's demographic impact is to enter&#13;
the erudite Eield of birth interval dynamics, an area of demography replete&#13;
with subtle ramifications that can be overlooked only at the investigator's&#13;
peril. For those willing to be thought simple-minded, however, interesting&#13;
suggestions about the possible demographic impact of longer birth intervals&#13;
can be gained from a set of population projections featuring a change in the&#13;
mother's age at each birth after the first.&#13;
Annex III provides a description of an exercise of this sort designed to&#13;
illustrate the long-term effects of lengthening of the average birth interval&#13;
by six month, from 24 to 30 months, within a brief period. The baseline pro-&#13;
jection of the exercise is based on parameters similar to those of the U.N.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-29-&#13;
medium variant for a typical developing country, except for the age-specific&#13;
fertility schedule which is artifically constructed in a manner that provides&#13;
for births at precise 24-month intervals. In the alternate projections, these&#13;
parameters are altered in order to illustrate the effects of shifting from 24-&#13;
to 30-month intervals. In the alternate mortality variant, infant and child&#13;
mortality rates are set 15% below those of the baseline. In the alternate&#13;
fertility variant, the age-specific schedule is changed in a way that&#13;
lengthens the inter-generational gap by six months; and the total fertility&#13;
rate is made to decline somewhat more rapidly in response to the lengthened&#13;
intervals.&#13;
The results of these changes, presented in Table 3, may be summarized&#13;
briefly:&#13;
-- An examination of only the 15% infant and child mortality&#13;
reduction, as if it were exogenously produced, would conclude that child&#13;
spacing would result in a marginally larger population size. At stabiliza-&#13;
tion, for instance, the population identified by a "model A" assessment is&#13;
0.9% larger than the baseline. The small size of the difference illustrates&#13;
the point made earlier about the limited population growth implications of&#13;
even a rapid and significant decrease in infant and child mortality, even when&#13;
the fertility effects of the measures producing that mortality reduction are&#13;
not taken fully into account. Such difference as there is, though, is in the&#13;
direction of a larger population, as dictated by the arithmetic and underlying&#13;
logic of model A.&#13;
-- A "model B" estimate, looking only at the more rapidly fer-&#13;
tility decline associated with longer birth intervals, would find a 5.2%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
--30-&#13;
Table 3: Differences in Population&#13;
Size Associated with a&#13;
30-Month rather than a&#13;
24-Month Average Interval&#13;
between Births&#13;
Population Size Associated with a "30-Month"&#13;
Fertility Scenario Relative to that Associated&#13;
Year            with a "24-Month" Scenario, in Year Indicated&#13;
As Assessed by     As Assessed by     As Assessed by&#13;
Model A            Model B            Model C&#13;
0&#13;
25               +0.4%              -2.7%              -1.9%&#13;
50               +0.6%              -4.1%              -2.9%&#13;
75               +0.8%              -5.0%              -3.5%&#13;
100               +0.9%              -5.2%              -3.7%&#13;
Source: Annex III&#13;
Notes: Se-e table III-2 for absolute population size figures. The&#13;
figures presented above for model A are based on those in&#13;
the "adjusted" column from that period; the fertility variant&#13;
used in producing the model B and model C figures incorporates&#13;
both the inter-generational and total fertility rate effects&#13;
of longer birth intervals. Year 100 figures refer to stable&#13;
populations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-31-&#13;
smaller population size attributable to spacing. As can be seen from the&#13;
tables of annex III, the longer inter-generational gap alone would produce a&#13;
population size about 1.8% smaller than that of the baseline. The remaining,&#13;
larger part of the difference is attributable to the smaller total number of&#13;
infants born to couples who space the births of their children. If birth&#13;
spacing is to have a significant effect on fertility, in other words, much of&#13;
the change will result from the change in total family size associated with&#13;
spacing rather than from the spacing per se.&#13;
-- The ultimate population size estimated by accounting for both&#13;
the mortality and fertility change, as under model C, would be 3.7% smaller&#13;
than that of the baseline. As in each of the two other examples, the faster&#13;
fertility reduction would prove to be a stronger determinant of population&#13;
size than the more rapid decline in mortality2I/&#13;
Conclusions&#13;
The three examples just presented obviously cannot be said to represent&#13;
anything like the last word on the relationship between mortality and fer-&#13;
tility reduction efforts on the one hand and population growth on the other.&#13;
As has been said before, they are methodologically crude; and by dealing with&#13;
a sample of approaches that is not necessarily representative of those&#13;
available, they may well leave an impression that the different models produce&#13;
widely divergent results more frequently than they actually do.&#13;
The examples and the other material presented earlier, however, should&#13;
when taken together at least suffice to create uneasiness about automatically&#13;
continuing to follow the present approaches that feature separate con-&#13;
sideration of only the population growth influence of mortality and of fer-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-32-&#13;
tility changes per se. With luck, the examples presented will also provoke&#13;
thought about how some of the shortcomings of the analytical techniques used&#13;
in them might be overcome in future research efforts.&#13;
Such efforts are clearly needed, for reasons that go far beyond the con-&#13;
ceptual and methodological. For, notwithstanding its inadequacies, the evi-&#13;
dence available gives rise to strong suspicions that the shortcomings of the&#13;
current approaches are producing results whose biased nature is, if not inevi-&#13;
tably, at least frequently leading to incorrect policy conclusions.&#13;
These suspicions concern the accuracy with which the demographic con-&#13;
sequences of both mortality and fertility reduction programs are assessed.&#13;
They can usefully be stated in closing, as two propositions intended to serve&#13;
both as interim guides to action and as hypotheses to be confirmed or dispro-&#13;
ven through future research.&#13;
Proposition one is that when both their direct and indirect effects on&#13;
mortality and fertility are appropriately taken into account, most policies&#13;
and programs undertaken for the purpose of reducing mortality will in most&#13;
settings and over the long run produce greater fertility than mortality&#13;
declines and thus slower population growth and a smaller population size than&#13;
would otherwise occur.&#13;
The proposition maintains, in other words, that the currently-prevailing&#13;
view that mortality reduction will normally lead to faster long-term growth is&#13;
incorrect, an artifact of inadequate model specificiation. This proposition&#13;
is based on two considerations which, if correct, mean that the normal overall&#13;
outcome of mortality reduction measures will be a reduction in long-term&#13;
growth ranging in magnitude from modest to quite large.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-33-&#13;
The first consideration is that, as has been seen, the additional growth&#13;
potential inherent in faster mortality reduction is normally rather small even&#13;
when no allowance at all is made for the fertility effects of mortality reduc-&#13;
tion efforts, very small when a reasonable (less than fully offsetting)&#13;
adjustment is entered to account for these effects. Thus, the strength of a&#13;
direct fertility reduction effect needed to "tip the balance" from faster to&#13;
slower growth would be modest in most cases. Even the immediate virtual elim-&#13;
ination of infant mortality, for example, would in a typical developing&#13;
country produce a stable population no more than 5% or so above that produced&#13;
by a normal progression; and as can be seen from the material on child-spacing&#13;
presented in annex III, even the modest fertility change represented by the&#13;
inter-generational effects of a six-month extension of birth intervals is ade-&#13;
quate to offset fully a 15% reduction in infant and child mortality.&#13;
The second consideration is that most effective mortality reduction&#13;
efforts could be expected to exercise at least some direct effect on fer-&#13;
tility. In some cases, especially those involving social and economic mea-&#13;
sures like the "general development" and "income distribution" cases discussed&#13;
above, this direct effect is likely to be very large and the resulting&#13;
restraint on future population expansion quite dramatic. In others, suich as&#13;
targetted immunization programs, it might be much smaller; and there will no&#13;
doubt be at least be some instances where it will be negligible or non-&#13;
existent, in which the modest increases in growth suggested by model A might&#13;
well result. But such instances seem likely to be infrequent. For, as noted,&#13;
there are persausive reasons for suspecting that practically all mortality&#13;
measures most currently under development will require at least some behav-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-34-&#13;
ioral change on the part of those to be served if the measures are to be&#13;
effective; and this will require a general awakening that will have&#13;
"spill-over" or direct effects on fertility that are independent of whatever&#13;
mortality results might be produced. If this assessment is correct, then the&#13;
normal overall outcome of measures that lower mortality will be a reduction in&#13;
long-term growth ranging in magnitude from modest to quite large.&#13;
This should not be taken to deny the possibility that, as seen in the&#13;
general development and income distribution examples presented, faster mor-&#13;
tality decline might produce at least slightly more rapid growth during an&#13;
initial period that might last as long as 50-75 years. The difference is&#13;
small, however, especially in relation to the much more marked tendency toward&#13;
slower growth over the longer run. Nor can the word "most" safely be&#13;
overlooked in reading the proposition. Its presence is meant to indicate that&#13;
there will almost certainly be at least some exceptions; and it is conceivable&#13;
that at least some of these exceptions33/ might prove significant.&#13;
Proposition two is that while not all programs and policies undertaken in&#13;
order to reduce fertility will produce slower growth in the near term, over&#13;
the longer run most will, when both their direct and indirect effects on fer-&#13;
tility and maortality are appropriately taken into account, be found to result&#13;
in a reduction of population growth by an amount that is at least slightly&#13;
and sometimes significantly less than suggested by current assessments which&#13;
fail to account for the mortality effects of those policies and programs.&#13;
As noted, two of the three quantitative examples given suggest that&#13;
measures often advocated Eor the reduction of fertility -- faster development&#13;
and more equitable income distribution -- produce modestly faster growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-35-&#13;
during the initial fifty years or so after their introduction. The differ-&#13;
ences are not large; but this result, a reflection of the greater response to&#13;
mortality to improvements in living standards during the initial stages of&#13;
development from a low base, must nonetheless serve as a warning to anyone&#13;
tempted to conclude from development's tendency to produce lower fertility&#13;
that development also represents an immediate solution to growth problems.&#13;
At the same time, the outcomes of the quantitative examples point to&#13;
longer-term differences that are much larger and thus correspondingly more&#13;
impressive in the direction of a smaller rather than a larger population.&#13;
Thus, the second proposition does not go as far as to claim that the conven-&#13;
tional approaches are wrong in suggesting that fertility reduction measures&#13;
will eventually produce slower rather than faster population growth. The&#13;
claim is simply that these conventional approaches overstate the amount of&#13;
slowing that will occur by failing to account for the tendency of fertility&#13;
reducing measures to produce partly offsetting mortality declines as well.&#13;
The reason for doubting that the mortality declines will often be fully&#13;
or more-than-fully offsetting over the long term is one of those mentioned&#13;
earlier with respect to the first proposition: namely, an appreciation of the&#13;
limited additonal population growth likely to result from even sharply faster&#13;
mortality reductions in most settings. This potential is so much less than&#13;
that of fertility reduction that it is difficult to imagine many circumstances&#13;
in which the mortality reduction produced in the process of limiting fertility&#13;
would overpower the fertility effect altogether and lead to faster growth.&#13;
The partial effect might still be important, however, as indicated by the&#13;
income distribution example given, where a failure to account for mortality&#13;
effects led to a misstatement of the likely population size by almost 25%.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-37-&#13;
Annex I: Overall Development&#13;
The work of Donald McGranahan and his colleagues, from which the overall&#13;
development illustration is derived, is based on a holistic view of develop-&#13;
ment. According to their approach, development is a set of interrelated&#13;
social and economic changes, among which are changes in fertility and mor-&#13;
tality. Although the processes that produce such changes may be too complex&#13;
to permit the clear establishment of causal sequences, their outcomes can fre-&#13;
quently be observed and measured; and this is what McGranahan and his&#13;
colleagues seek to do.&#13;
An example of their findings is produced in table 1-1. The findings were&#13;
developed through an analysis of cross-sectional, national-level data employ-&#13;
ing correspondence analysis, a statistical technique which features the&#13;
establishment of symmetrical relationships among the variables covered. As&#13;
can be seen, "development" means for McGranahan and his colleagues a change in&#13;
over a dozen indicators in ways such that the attainment of any specified&#13;
level of one implies the achievement of some corresponding level of another.&#13;
Thus, for example, a society with an adult literacy rate of around 60% (that&#13;
prevailing at development level 50 of table I-1) would also tend to have a per&#13;
capita income of about $300, and so forth. The corresponding crude birth rate&#13;
would be around 40; life expectancy would be on the order of 58 years.&#13;
The McGranahan group did not include the crude death and population&#13;
growth rates among the indicators they covered. But these may be added&#13;
through the use of stable population tables, as in lines 17 and 18 of table&#13;
I-1, whose figures were developed by applying the Coale-Demeny "West" family&#13;
stable population relationships to the crude birth rate and life expectancy&#13;
derived by McGranahan et al. The result is that, in addition to the other&#13;
features just noted, a society at development level 50 would be characterized&#13;
by a crude death rate slightly below 11 per 1000 population, and by a popula-&#13;
tion growth rate just under 3.0% annually.&#13;
Although individual countries will clearly follow widely differing&#13;
courses of development, a "normal" path can be defined for illustrative pur-&#13;
poses as that represented by progress from the lower toward the higher levels&#13;
outlined in table I-1 -- the trajectory identified, in other words, through a&#13;
cross-sectional examination of the current configuration of country situations&#13;
with respect to the different indicators presented in the table. While the&#13;
complexity of the relationships just described must thwart any effort to&#13;
single out progress with respect of any one variable as the pricipal cause of&#13;
or driving force behind changes in the others, any one can usefully serve as a&#13;
"reference indicator" for the purpose of measuring the rate of development&#13;
progress as defined by changes in the full set of indicators covered --&#13;
recognizing that, in measuring change in terms of the reference indicator, one&#13;
is not describing changes in that indicator alone but rather changes in it as&#13;
a shorthand way of indicating changes in all the other indicators as well.&#13;
Further, it seems safe to assume that the reason mortality and fertility indi-&#13;
cators change as one moves from left to right across table T-1 is that the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-38-&#13;
other variables are also changed -- that, in a general sense, the changes in&#13;
these other variables (and the other, unmeasured factors for which they serve&#13;
as proxies) are largely responsible for the shifts in mortality and fertility&#13;
observed -- just as these shifts in mortality and fertility are among the fac-&#13;
tors determining changes in the other variables on table I-1.&#13;
Acceptance of these propositions permits application of the figures of&#13;
table I-1 to a simple exercLse to assess the influence of faster overall&#13;
development on mortality, fertility, and population growth. The exercise con-&#13;
sists of taking a hypothetical population in a low-income country, allowing it&#13;
to move at different rates along the trajectory described by the progression&#13;
from low to high levels of development on table I-1, and examining the&#13;
demographic effects produced. By assessing these effects in terms of models&#13;
A, B, and C, it is possible to assess the quantitative significance of using&#13;
one model rather than the other.&#13;
Considerations of convenience dictate the use of the ubiquitous per&#13;
capita income as the reference indicator. Once it has been selected, the&#13;
estimates of the World Bank can be drawn upon to assist in the choice of an&#13;
appropriate starting point and a reasonable set of assumptions about the&#13;
future rate of social and economic progress.&#13;
McGranahan development level 13.5, used as a starting point, enjoys no&#13;
special sanctity; but its correspondence with a per capita income of $100&#13;
makes it a pleasantly round number, and the World Bank's figures suggest that&#13;
it is reasonably close to the income level of the typical low-income country.&#13;
According to the Bank's most recent World Development Report, the average 1981&#13;
per capita income of the thirty-four countries listed as "low-income" was&#13;
$270. A translation of this figure into the 1970 dollars used by McGranahan&#13;
and colleagues, using the World Bank's 1970-81 annual inflation rate of 11.2%,&#13;
yields an income level of around $84, not unduly below the $100 implied by the&#13;
initial point selected. (The World Bank, World Development Report 1983,&#13;
p. 148.)&#13;
As for the rate of progress, the 1983 World Development Report presents&#13;
1985-95 GDP growth scenarics for the low-income countries ranging from 3.6% to&#13;
4.6% annually (unweighted average for Africa and Asia).    Between 1980 and&#13;
2000, the Bank's projections envision a 1.7% average annual rate of population&#13;
growth in these low-income countries, producing a range of annual per capita&#13;
GDP growth scenarios of roughly 1.9% to 2.9% for the coming decade. (Ibid.,&#13;
pp. 27, 184.)&#13;
Such figures suggest 2% and 3% annual rates of per capita income growth&#13;
as reasonable possibilities. In addition to being round figures fairly close&#13;
to the World Bank estimates (heroically extrapolated to cover 100 years), use&#13;
of them permits an assessment of the demographic implications of another&#13;
appealingly round figure: a change of one percentage point in the growth rate&#13;
(of overall dlevelopment measured in terms of per capita income, albeit not in&#13;
terms of the McGranahan inclex).&#13;
Thus, the comparison rmade is between the population size increase asso-&#13;
ciated with development at a rate defined by a 2% average annual rise in per&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-39-&#13;
capita income as a baseline; and the population increase produced by the mor-&#13;
tality and fertility changes associated with a 3% annual rise. Table I-2 pre-&#13;
sents an abridged version of the two scenarios. As can be seen there, the 2%&#13;
annual per capita income increase implies a rise from the initial $100 to $724&#13;
over 100 years, an increase that is one dimension of the rise in the&#13;
McGranahan overall development index from 13.5 to 69.9. Among the other&#13;
dimensions of this rise are a decline in the crude death rate from 19.1 to&#13;
8.9, and a reduction in the crude birth rate from 46.1 to 27.4. Under the&#13;
alternate 3% scenario, the McGranahan index would rise from 13.5 to 93.0.&#13;
Among other things, this would imply an increase in per capita income from&#13;
$100 to $1922, a fall in the crude death rate from 19.1 to 9.7 (and a sub-&#13;
sequent rise to 11.6, occuring despite continuing increases in life expec-&#13;
tancy, as a result of the population's changing age structure), a crude birth&#13;
rate decline from 46.1 to 17.0 -- and also the changes in the other&#13;
demographic indicators shown in table 1-2 and in the other social indicators&#13;
of table I-1 not reproduced in table I-2 because of space limitations.&#13;
For each of these two scenarios, it is possible to construct fertility,&#13;
mortality, and population growth assumptions for use in projections. For each&#13;
five-year period, an estimate of per capita income is prepared by increasing&#13;
the preceding income figure by approximately 10.4% or approximately 15.9%, the&#13;
amounts representing five years of progress at a 2% and a 3% annual rate&#13;
respectively. Through interpolation, the corresponding development levels,&#13;
crude birth rates, and crude death rates are calculated. Subtraction of the&#13;
crude death rate from the crude birth rate yields an annual population growth&#13;
rate for the five-year period in question, which can be used to increase the&#13;
population of the preceding interval.&#13;
As indicated in the text, the two development scenarios are used in this&#13;
way as the basis for four population projections. If for convenience the fer-&#13;
tility assumptions of the 2% baseline and the 3% scenarios are designated F1&#13;
and F2, respectively, and the two mortality variants are labelled M1 and M2,&#13;
the four projections can be identified as: F1Ml (baseline), F1M2 (initial or&#13;
"crude" model A), F2M1 (model B), F2M2 (model C).&#13;
In addition, the exercise includes an "adjusted" model A projection that&#13;
reflects, as the "crude" projection does not, the widely-recognized fertility&#13;
influence of faster mortality decline. The adjustment approach used is&#13;
largely arbitrary and dramatically inelegant: it consists of reducing the&#13;
"crude" model A population figure by one-half the difference between it and&#13;
the baseline figure. The justification for this approach is essentially that&#13;
the results it produces are probably no worse than those yielded by any other&#13;
approach that might be reasonably considered. On the one hand, the widespread&#13;
recognition that faster mortality declines affect fertility makes it difficult&#13;
to avoid making at least some kind of adjustment effort. On the other, the&#13;
continuing uncertainty and debate about the strength of the effect renders&#13;
futile any effort to derive a scientifically defensible adjustment figure; and&#13;
the absence of such a figure renders quixotic any attempt to develop the&#13;
sophisticated procedure that would be theoretically preferable. Such a&#13;
situation calls for a simple approach that, while carefully avoiding any claim&#13;
of precision, indicates recognition that faster mortality decline produces an&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-40-&#13;
increase in the rate of fertility decline of a magnitude that is not hope-&#13;
lessly implaasible in lighit of current knowledge or belief.&#13;
The basis for the 50% offset figure used is hardly beyond challenge; but&#13;
at the same time, such a figure is not wildly out of line with the findings of&#13;
recent research, which tends to produce replacement effects ranging from&#13;
negligible to 80% or so. (The well-known CICRED studies, for example, pro-&#13;
duced replacment ratios of from near zero to around 0.4; and the recent World&#13;
Bank analysis of World FerLility Survey data suggested replacement ratios of&#13;
from near zero to 0.8. Samuel H. Preston, "Health Programs and Population&#13;
Growth," Population and Development Review, Vol. 1, No. 2 (December 1975),&#13;
pp. 192-93; Susan H. Cochrane and K.C. Zachariah, "Infant and Child Mortality&#13;
as Determinants of Fertility: The Policy Implications," World Bank Staff&#13;
Working Paper, No. 556 (February 1983), p. 28.) The 0.5 figure used is&#13;
somewhat higher than the mean figure from the replacement effect studies&#13;
available, a difference meant to imply informal recognition of the existence&#13;
of an additional insurance effect as well as to enhance the comprehensibility&#13;
of the numbers on table I-1.&#13;
Although logic and symmetry would seem to argue for an analogous attempt&#13;
to adjust the model B projection for the likely tendency of faster fertility&#13;
decline to induce more rapid mortality reduction, no attempt is made to do so.&#13;
This is because of the desire for model B, like model A, to reflect currently&#13;
conventional practice; and whereas the mortality-fertility relationship is&#13;
widely discussed with respect to the population growth effects of faster mor-&#13;
tality decline, the standard practice is not to adjust mortality assumptions&#13;
in response to faster fertility decline when population projections are made.&#13;
As can be seen from table I-3, which presents the projection results, all&#13;
projections start with a population of 10.0 million and extend for 100 years.&#13;
The selection of the former figure is largely arbitrary; 100 years was chosen&#13;
because it is the longest round period of time that would, at the higher rate&#13;
of income growth used, allow the highest level of development achieved to fall&#13;
within the range of values covered in table 1-1.&#13;
As table T-3 of the text also shows, the application of the approach used&#13;
produces implausibly large population totals toward the end of the projection&#13;
period. This can probably be attributed at least in part to the well-known&#13;
dangers of using cross-sectional relationships for projection purposes.&#13;
Should the result of the cross-sectional approach be a failure to account for&#13;
changes in technology leading to a structural change featuring lower fertility&#13;
and (to a lesser degree) mortality relative to other development indicators&#13;
over time, the population figures of table I-3 would overstate the amount of&#13;
growth that could reasonably be anticipated. An alternate or supplementary&#13;
possibility would be to v:Lew the large size of the population produced as a&#13;
warning against relying oni "normal" development to solve the population&#13;
problems of poor countries, especially if slow progress is all that can be&#13;
expected. For it seems cLear that the popoulation figures given are substan-&#13;
tively unrealistic, even Lf technically correct, in the sense that progress&#13;
toward them would in all Likelihood be interrupted at some point by Malthusian&#13;
checks and rising death rates that would lead to stabilization at some lower&#13;
level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-41-&#13;
Finally, it must be acknowledged that, despite the strenuous effort to&#13;
disguise the fact, the projection approach used does at least some violence to&#13;
the desire of McGranahan and his colleagues to take a "holistic approach" to&#13;
development and to avoid any implication of causality among the variables they&#13;
study. The projection approach is not so crude, certainly, as to attribute&#13;
any causal superiority to per capita income; but it does require acceptance of&#13;
the idea that different rates of overall development can be said to cause the&#13;
different rates of fertility and mortality decline observed. This is contrary&#13;
to the spirit of correspondence analysis by -vhich the relationships of table&#13;
I-l were developed, being instead in the tradition of regression analysis&#13;
which McGranahan and his colleagues chose not to apply.&#13;
The only defense to be raised against any objection raised on these&#13;
grounds is that the transgression is not so much worse than standard practice&#13;
as might at first seem to be the casa. Whether established through correspon-&#13;
dence or regression analysis, statistical relationships represent only asso-&#13;
ciations, and those who would draw causal inferences about them do so at their&#13;
peril. This being the case, it is not clear that one gains all that much more&#13;
distance from causality by using a correspondence rather than a regression&#13;
approach; or that the legitimacy of inferring casuelity from corrspondence&#13;
relationships is all that much less justifiable than the common practice of&#13;
drawing causal inferences from regression results.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-42-&#13;
Table 1--1: CorTespcdence Amrg Developqant Indicators&#13;
Index Rarge&#13;
Indicators        0     10     20     30       40       50       60       70        80       90        100&#13;
1. Crude birth rate  48.50  46.75  44.37  44.79   43.67    40.23    35.04    27.25    20.88     17.15     16.50&#13;
2. Infant mortality&#13;
rate          161.70 148.60 135.67 125.87    106.84   86.32    64.35    45.47     32.48     21.52     13.86&#13;
3. Life expectancy  41.34  44.10  47.D5  48.77    52.48    57.79    62.41    66.87    69.44     71.49     72.94&#13;
4. AninmEl prutein&#13;
corsumption&#13;
per capita&#13;
per day         9.68   11.27  11.59  12.41    14.04    18.07   24.01    35.98     45.98     53.36     63.16&#13;
5. Percert literate,&#13;
ages 15+       23.65  32.31   37.07  39.87    47.75   60.07    72.14    85.04     92.76     97.78    101.11&#13;
6. Percent aged&#13;
5-19&#13;
enrolled in&#13;
prdmy and&#13;
secxdary&#13;
school         23.50  26.80   31.08  35.67    43.76    50.69   56.49    63.27     69.33     75.15     80.68&#13;
7. Percent of&#13;
d-lirs&#13;
with&#13;
electricity    23.18  27.43   33,37  37.20    38.24    46.66   58.61     78.25    93.83     98.92     99.78&#13;
8. Neaspaper&#13;
cirailAtia&#13;
per 1,000&#13;
pcpulation      4.79   7.35   11.41  17.61    32.41    55.09    83.69   133.10   208.89    290.55    356.82&#13;
9. Telepones&#13;
per 100,000&#13;
population     136.50 205.82 348.34 607.26 1,008.23 2,011.51 3,768.04 6,768.05 12,193.11 22,482.20 41,192.50&#13;
10. Autcmbilies&#13;
per 1,000&#13;
population      1.88   3.21   4.81    7.05     8.58    13.22    23.07    46.12    92.52     166.79   299.65&#13;
11. Males in&#13;
agriculture&#13;
as percent&#13;
of total&#13;
male labor&#13;
force          91.37  81.85   71.04  64.n2    57.22    52.16    42.28    29.68    20.96     13.85      8.29&#13;
12. Steel&#13;
consumption&#13;
per capita&#13;
(kg.)           3.68   5.66   8.63   14.85    26.67   43.56    73.67    143.68   275.05    442.57    571.69&#13;
13. Energy&#13;
consuaption&#13;
per capita&#13;
(kg.)          37.15  73.22 118.58 201.02    351.72   524.39  871.88  1,600.78  2,837.27  4,389.17  6,608.19&#13;
14. Perceit GiP&#13;
fran ma-nr&#13;
facturing       9.79   10.16  10.46  11.62    14.47    17.92    19.49    22.22    27.18     30.54     32.26&#13;
15. GNP per capita&#13;
(US $)         72.00  90.29 117.95 163.10    230.46   304.09  464.77    727.58  1,081.07  1,675.49  2,500.47&#13;
16. Crude death&#13;
rate           22.24   19.85  17.57  16.33    13.77    10.82    9.42     8.85     10.18     11.63     11.52&#13;
17. Population&#13;
grath&#13;
rate           26.26  26.90   27.30  28.46    29.90    29.41    25.62    18.40    10.70      5.52      4.98&#13;
Saurces:&#13;
Lines 1-15   Prepared by D.V. McGranrhan and colleages at the United Naticns Research Institute for Social Deyelopmit,&#13;
cited in W. Parker Mauldin and Bernard Berelsan, "Conditixm of Fertility Decline in Developirg Countries,&#13;
1965-75," Studies in Family P d    Vol. 9, No. 5 (May 1978), p. 109.&#13;
Lines 16-17  Estiemted from lines 1 and 3 thrugh the application of Coael   NWest" family stable population tables&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 1-2:  Overall Developnent: 'Tw   Scenarios&#13;
YEAR                              2X SCENARIO                                                     3% SCENARIO&#13;
Per Capita McGranahan     Crude     LIfe      Infant    Crude    Per Capita McGranahan    Crude      Life       Infant    Crude&#13;
Income    Development  Birth  Expectancy   Mortality Death       Inccme    Development Birth    Expectancy Mbrtality Death&#13;
Lev_ l    Rate     at Birth     Rate     Rate                    Level      Rate    at Birth     Rate     Rate&#13;
0        $100         13.5      46.09      45.1       144      19.05      $100         13.5      46.09      45.1        144     19.05&#13;
25        $164        30.0      44.78       48.8       126      16.30      $2D9        36.8       44.03      51.3        113     14.59&#13;
50        $269        45.2      41.87       55.3        96      12.23      $438        58.3       35.90     61.6         68       9.65&#13;
75        $442        58.6      35.78       61.8        67       9.62      $918        75.4       23.82     68.3          38      9.57&#13;
10(        $724        69.9      27.36       66.8        46       8.86     $1922        93.0       16.96     71.9          19     11.60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-44-&#13;
Table T-3: Population Size (in Millions) under Different&#13;
Overall Growth Scenarios: 3 Models&#13;
Year         2% Scenario                    3% Scenario&#13;
-Moder A         model i        noaei L&#13;
____ .____  _____. ________     Crude   Adjusted&#13;
0             10.0         10.0      10.0        10.0            10.0&#13;
25             19.7         19.9      19.8        19.6            19.9&#13;
50            40.5          44.2      42.4        37.6            40.7&#13;
75            82.n          93.0      87.5        62.1            67.6&#13;
lo0           142.9         160.7     151.8        81.0            85.9&#13;
I         _ &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-45-&#13;
Annex II: Income Distribution&#13;
The study of income distribution and demographic trends by T. P. Dyson,&#13;
C. L. G. Bell, and R. H. Cassen, which serves as the basis for the income&#13;
distribution illustration, is an extension of work on redistribution and&#13;
growth initiated at the World Bank. The question posed concerns the mor-&#13;
tality, fertility, and population growth effects of movement toward a more&#13;
egalitarian pattern of income distribution.&#13;
Dyson, Bell, and Cassen explore this question through the use of a simu-&#13;
lation model. It features a division of the population under observation into&#13;
three groups by income: the top 20%, the middle 40%, the bottom 40%. The&#13;
economy as a whole is assumed to grow at 5% annually from a starting average&#13;
per capita income of $100 (in 1970 dollars), with the gain distributed among&#13;
the three income groups according to two alternate scenarios. Under the&#13;
first, termed "constant shares," the income shares of the top, middle, and&#13;
lower groups would remain fixed at their initial levels of 0.64, 0.28, and&#13;
0.08, respectively, typical of low income, high inequality countries. Under&#13;
the second, called "changing shares," the income shares of the three groups&#13;
would shift over time from the same initial distribution until, upon the&#13;
attainment of a per capita income of $300, they would approximate the pattern&#13;
of an egalitarian Eastern European country, with the top 20% of the population&#13;
receiving 33% of the national income, the middle 40% receiving 40%, and the&#13;
bottom 40% receiving the remaining 27%. That distribution would remain&#13;
constant therafter. The level and distribution of national income thus deter-&#13;
mined define the per capita income of each income group of the population for&#13;
each time period covered by the projection; and this per capita income serves&#13;
as the basis for defining the fertility and mortality levels of each group.&#13;
These fertility and mortality levels in turn determine each population group's&#13;
growth rate; and the weighted sum of the growth experienced by the three&#13;
groups represents the growth of the society as a whole. At the end of each&#13;
projection period, people are redistributed among income groups so that the&#13;
initial 20:40:40 size distribution is maintained despite differences in group-&#13;
specific growth rates.&#13;
The relationship between per capita income on the one hand and fertility&#13;
and mortality on the other is fixed by empirically derived equations of a cur-&#13;
vilinear form. The simplest of the approaches taken, which are featured in&#13;
the present example, are of two sorts. One is cross-sectional, based on&#13;
international comparisons of income and fertility or mortality levels. The&#13;
second is a time-series execise, based on data from Taiwan. At low levels of&#13;
income, the Taiwan time-series equations produce a significantly greater&#13;
change in mortality and fertility per unit of income increase that do the&#13;
international cross-sectional equations. The time series equations can thus&#13;
conveniently be referred to as the "high response" equations, those produced&#13;
by cross-sectional exercises as the "low response" equations.&#13;
The combination to be employed here for illustrative purposes combines&#13;
the low response mortality equation of the cross-sectional analysis with the&#13;
high response fertility equation of the Taiwan experience. This was selected&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-46-&#13;
because, of the combinations for which the information presented in the&#13;
published account of the Dyson-Cassen-Bell work is sufficent to support an&#13;
exercise of the sort presenled here, its results most closely approximate&#13;
those produced by the more complex exercise whose outcome was thought by&#13;
Dyson, Bell, and Cassen to offer the best reflection of reality. Over the&#13;
range of income levels covered, the mortality equation describes a progressi-&#13;
vely declining amount of life expectancy increase per dollar of incremental&#13;
income. The fertility equation features very slow fertility decline in&#13;
response to income increase at low income levels, followed by a period of high&#13;
response which slows as higher income levels are reached.&#13;
The summary mortality and fertility trajectories or variants for the&#13;
society as a whole, expressed in terms of life expectancy at birth and the&#13;
gross reproduction rate, resulting from the Dyson-Bell-Cassen exercise are&#13;
supplemented by linear interpolation to provide a figure for each 5-year&#13;
interval and are used as the bases for standard component-method population&#13;
projections. The two fertility and two mortality variants produced in this&#13;
manner (one fertility and oae mortality variant from the "constant shares"&#13;
scenario, one fertility and one mortality variant from the "changing shares"&#13;
scenario) are presented in abridged form in table II-1. They provide the&#13;
basis for four population projections, constructed in a manner analogous to&#13;
those for the overall development illustration described in annex I. That is,&#13;
the fertility and mortality trajectories of the "constant shares" scenario are&#13;
used together in a baseline projection. The fertility variant of the baseline&#13;
"constant shares" projection is combined with the mortality variant of the&#13;
"changing shares" scenario and adjusted using the same procedure and correc-&#13;
tion factor described in annex I to produce a "model A" assessment of more&#13;
equitable development's population growth implications. A combination of the&#13;
"changing shares" fertility variant and the "constant shares" mortality&#13;
variant results in a "model B" assessment. The "model C" assessment combines&#13;
the "changing shares" mortality and fertility variants.&#13;
Each of the projections starts from the same arbitrarily selected popula-&#13;
tion size of 10.0 million, as used in the overall development illustration;&#13;
each employs the same initial gross reproduction rate (3.06) and life expec-&#13;
tancy at birth (43.2 years), which is the weighted average of the initial&#13;
values for those indicators used by Dyson, Bell, and Cassen for the upper,&#13;
middle, and lower income groups; each projection starts with the same age&#13;
distribution of the population, selected from the relevant Coale-Demeny "West"&#13;
family stable! population taLble; each employs the same age-specific fertility&#13;
and mortality schedules; each projection is extended for the same 150-year&#13;
span as in the original Dyson-Bell-Cassen exercise.&#13;
The resulting population size figures, presented in table II-2, are&#13;
somewhat -- tip to about 20% -- larger than those produced by the comparable&#13;
Dyson-Bell-Cassen projections. This difference appears to result primarily&#13;
from the use of single projections based on average mortality and fertility&#13;
rates for the society as a whole, rather than the preparation and subsequent&#13;
summing of parallel projections for each income group in the manner of Dyson,&#13;
Bell, and Cassen.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-47-&#13;
Also, the population size figures, like those of the overall development&#13;
illustration, all become implausibly large toward the end of the projection&#13;
period. This suggests that they can best be regarded in the same light as&#13;
suggested in annex I for the findings of the overall development exercise: as&#13;
the inflated products of a failure to account adequately for technological&#13;
change; and/or a warning against reliance upon an altered pattern of income&#13;
distribution alone to avoid a Malthusian disaster.&#13;
Finally, it is to be remembered that the results presented in table II-2&#13;
relate directly only to the particular Dyson-Bell-Cassen exercise on which&#13;
they are based. As noted, this is but one of several that Dyson, Bell, and&#13;
Cassen undertook within the framework of their model. All of these exercises&#13;
indicate that when both fertility and the mortality affects are taken into&#13;
account (as in model C) the long-term result of more equitable income distri-&#13;
bution in the "changing shares" projection is a population smaller than that&#13;
of the baseline "constant shares" projection. In all but one of the exer-&#13;
cises, the difference, measured in proportional terms, is greater than that of&#13;
the exercise used here. Dyson, Bell, and Cassen do not produce the equivalent&#13;
of "model A" or "model B" projections; but to judge from the way in which&#13;
those projections are produced, it seems clear that a "model A" approach would&#13;
result in a population slightly larger than that of the baseline projection in&#13;
any exercise; and that a "model B" approach would inevitably yield a popula-&#13;
tion at least somewhat and possibly significantly smaller than that resulting&#13;
from the application of model C.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table II-I: Income Distribiution: Two Scenarios&#13;
Year            Constant Income Shares                    Changing Income Shares&#13;
Gross                                   Gross&#13;
Per Capita      Life      Reproduction   Per Capita      Life     Reproduction&#13;
Income     Expectancy       Rate         Tncome    Expectancy       Rate&#13;
0          100         43.2         3.06            100        43.2         3.06&#13;
25          160         46.1         2.78            158        46.6         2.84&#13;
50          302         50.3         2.69           283         52.6         2.66&#13;
75          570         55.0         2.37           521         60.3         2.00&#13;
100        1,129        60.8          2.03         1,118         68.2         1.36&#13;
125        2,393        66.3          1.57         2,766         70.7         1.32&#13;
150        5,798         70.2         1.32         7,520         70.7         1.32&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-49-&#13;
Table II-2: Population Size (in Millions) under Different&#13;
Income Distribution Scenarios: 3 Models&#13;
Year        Constant                       Changing Shares&#13;
Shares             Model A            Model B       Model C&#13;
__________________  Crude    Adjusted _  _    _    __ _&#13;
0         10.0            10.0        10.0           10.0         10.0&#13;
25         18.5           18.5         18.5           18.6         18.7&#13;
50         34.0           34.5        34.2            34.6         35.2&#13;
75         63.0           66.8        64.9            61.9         65.7&#13;
100        111.3          126.2       118.8           94.1         106.4&#13;
125        182.4          219.1       200.8           124.9        149.7&#13;
150        266.0          328.0       297.0           155.4        191.4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-51-&#13;
Annex III: Child Spacing&#13;
The child-spacing illustration is based on a component-method population&#13;
projection exercise, in which the age-specific distribution of fertility, the&#13;
infant and child mortality rates, and the total fertility rate are varied to&#13;
simulate the population growth effects of a change in the average interval be-&#13;
tween births.&#13;
The initial population size is set at the same, arbitrarily-establised&#13;
10.0 million as in the previous illustrations. The initial principal&#13;
demographic characteristics are those typical of the developing world as a&#13;
whole in the late 1970s according to the standard figures of the United&#13;
Nations: a total fertility rate just over 4.8; a life expectancy at birth of&#13;
55.0 years; and the age distribution consistent with these parameters esti-&#13;
mated by the U.N. In the baseline projection, the total fertility rate and&#13;
life expectancy are allowed to move toward an eventual low-level equilibrium&#13;
at a rate approximately equal to that presented in the medium variant of the&#13;
most recent United Nations projections. (The exact variants, like the values&#13;
of the common initial demographic variables, are those used in the projections&#13;
presented in Davidson R. Gwatkin and Sarah K. Brandel, "Life Expectancy and&#13;
Population Growth in the Third World," Scientific American, Vol 246, No. 5&#13;
(May 1982), pp. 57-65.) Once reached, a net reproduction rate of unity is&#13;
maintained in all projections for the remainder of the projection period,&#13;
which is in each case extended for 125 years, until the achievement of a&#13;
stable population.&#13;
As noted, the sources of variation between the projections arise from an&#13;
extension in the length of the average birth interval, an extension which is&#13;
posited for the purpose of this illustration as six months. All projections&#13;
start with an assumed average birth interval of 24 months. In the baseline&#13;
projection, this interval is maintained throughout the projection period. In&#13;
the alternate scenario employed, the interval is assumed to lengthen to 30&#13;
months begining with the second projection period and subsequently to remain&#13;
at this level throughout. The assumption, in other words, is that it will be&#13;
possible to lengthen the birth interval by six months within five years of the&#13;
initiation of an effort to do so, and to maintain this gain into the indefi-&#13;
nite future.&#13;
The selection of the 24- and 30-month intervals is largely arbitrary but&#13;
not totally devoid of an empirical foundation. According to a summary of&#13;
birth intervals based on World Fertility Survey data, the (unweighted) average&#13;
interval for the nine countries surveyed was 28.2 months (with a range of from&#13;
24.4 to 32.0 months) in the early 1970s, up from an average of 26.2 months a&#13;
decade earlier. (Calculated from data presented in German Rodriguez et al.,&#13;
"A Comparative Analysis of Birth Intervals," unpublished draft World Fertility&#13;
Survey Technical Paper 2199, October 1983, Table 9.) An examination of these&#13;
figures suggested that 30 months was the maximum interval length that could&#13;
safely be used if one wished to be reasonably representative; the baseline 24&#13;
months is a bit low, but necessary to provide the change of six months thought&#13;
to be the minimum required to produce interesting results, once the thirty-&#13;
month ceiling is established. To suggest that such a lengthening might be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-52-&#13;
brought about within five years, implying a six-fold increase in the natural&#13;
rate of lengthening, may be overly ambitious; but in view of the almost total&#13;
lack of information about the effectiveness of interval-extension measures,&#13;
it's not all that much worse than any alternate assumption; and handling it in&#13;
this way simplifies the presentation. The choice of extending the average&#13;
birth interval rather than reducing the number or proportion of births&#13;
occurring below some specifLed interval -- which would be preferable should&#13;
there exist some threshold level beneath which mortality rises sharply -- was&#13;
made for reasons of computational ease.&#13;
This change in the average birth interval is assumed to affect mortality&#13;
through a change in the infant and child mortality rate. It is assumed to&#13;
influence fertility through changes in the inter-generational period and in&#13;
the total fertility rate.&#13;
As for mortality, the effect of lengthening the average birth interval&#13;
from 24 to 30 months is assumed to be an immediate 15% reduction of the infant&#13;
and child mortality rate. In the 24-month variant of the mortality assump-&#13;
tions, the infant and child mortality rates used are those corresponding to&#13;
the figures for life expectancy at age five that are common to all projections&#13;
(a commonality which implies that mortality above age five is not affected by&#13;
a change in interval length), as determined by the Coale-Demeny "West" family&#13;
model life tables. In the 30-month variant, these infant mortality rates are&#13;
reduced by 15%; and the child mortality rates are set, again by applying the&#13;
Coale-Demeny "West" model life tables, at levels corresponding to the lower&#13;
infant mortality rates.&#13;
The 15% figure was selected on the basis of a literature review that&#13;
pointed toward an effect of somewhere between 10% and 20%. The review covered&#13;
studies done for the World Health Organization, the World Fertility Survey,&#13;
the World Bank, and the Population Council.&#13;
The WHO study included seventeen population groups in eight developing&#13;
countries. On average, the ratio of mortality among infants born less than 24&#13;
months after the preceding offspring to that among infants born 24-47 months&#13;
after was 1.93:1.00. If the length of the interval for those births occuring&#13;
at less than 24 months is placed at 12 months and the average length of the&#13;
24-47 month interval at 36 months, and if the relationship between mortality&#13;
and birth intervals is linear, such a ratio suggests that a six-month interval&#13;
extension would produce about a 16% reduction in infant mortality. If the&#13;
average of the 0-23 month interval is instead set at 18 months, ceteris pari-&#13;
bus, the corresponding figure would be around 19%.    (Calculated from figures&#13;
presented in A.R. Omran anel C.C. Standley, eds., Family Formation and Health:&#13;
An International Collaborative Study in India, Iran, Lebanon, Philippines, and&#13;
Turkey (Geneva: World Health Organization, 1976), pp. 216, 226, 235, 245, 255;&#13;
and in A.R. Omran and C.C. Standley, eds., Further Studies on Family Formation&#13;
Patterns and Health: An International Collaborative Study in Colombia, Egypt,&#13;
Pakistan, andi the Syrian Arab Republic (Geneva: World Health Organization,&#13;
1981), pp. 195, 206, 216.)&#13;
More recent work has suggested smaller differentials. The World&#13;
Fertility Survey, for example, has found an average ratio of 0-23:24-47-month&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-53-&#13;
interval infant mortality for the 29 developing countries covered of between&#13;
1.78:1.00 and 1.48:1.00, depending upon the estimation procedure used.&#13;
(Calculated from figures presented in Shea Oscar Rutstein, Infant and Child&#13;
Mortality: Levels, Trends, and Demographic Differentials, World Fertility&#13;
Survey Comparative Studies, no. 24 (Voorburg, Netherlands and London, England:&#13;
International Statistical Institute and World Fertility Survey, September&#13;
1983), p. 32.) The WHO differential would also seem larger than that suggested&#13;
by the conclusion of a more sophisticated analysis of WFS data by James&#13;
Trussell and Anne Pebly that "an improvement in birth spacing patterns, so&#13;
that all births subsequent to the first are spaced at least two years apart"&#13;
would reduce infant mortality by 10% and child mortality by 16% on average&#13;
among the 25 countries studied. (James Trussell and Anne R. Pebley, "The&#13;
Impact of Family Planning Programs on Infant, Child, and Materal Mortality,"&#13;
draft background paper for the 1984 World Development Report of the World&#13;
Bank, 31 October 1983, p. 20.) In addition, there are theoretical reasons for&#13;
suspecting that oversimplifications in the analysis behind differentials such&#13;
as those presented in the WHO study overstate their magnitude. (Beverly&#13;
Winikoff, "The Effects of Birth Spacing on Child and Maternal Health,"&#13;
Studies in Family Planning, Vol. 14, No. 10 (October 1983), pp. 231-45.)&#13;
(The assumption that the differential used is applicable to all births&#13;
rather than only to second and subsequent births is an obvious source of&#13;
overstatement whose magnitude would vary inversely with the level of the total&#13;
fertility rate. It would be offset to some unknown degree by the tendency for&#13;
the preceding as well as succeeding births to be affected, which is not taken&#13;
into account in the estimate presented. For evidence on this latter relation-&#13;
ship, see John Hobcraft, John W. McDonald, and Shea Rutstein, "Child-Spacing&#13;
Effects on Infant and Early Child Mortality," Population Index, Vol. 49, No. 4&#13;
(Winter 1983), pp. 585-618.)&#13;
Because of the many uncertainties surrounding the interval-mortality&#13;
relationship, only limited confidence can be placed in any figure that might&#13;
be selected. Fortunately this difficulty is not of major practical signifi-&#13;
cance for the purpose of a projection exercise of the sort undertaken here&#13;
since, as can be seen from the text, future population size is quite insen-&#13;
sitive to variations in the strength of the relationship within the wide range&#13;
of values that might reasonably be considered.&#13;
As indicated, the fertility consequences of lengthening the birth inter-&#13;
val from 24 to 30 months are estimated in two ways. First, the changes in&#13;
generational effects are estimated through the use of hypothetical age-&#13;
specific fertility schedules that are altered to reflect a lenghtening of the&#13;
birth interval. Second, the influence of longer intervals on completed family&#13;
size is estimated by adjusting the total fertility rate.&#13;
The hypothetical age-specific fertility schedules are designed in a way&#13;
that sacrifices elegance for the sake of clarity. For simplicity, the same&#13;
maternal age of first birth is adopted for all projections and held constant&#13;
within each. The figure chosen, 26.0 years, is too high to be a reasonable&#13;
approximation of reality but is adopted despite this shortcoming because of&#13;
the reasonable levels of the mean age of birth produced by its use in connec-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-54-&#13;
tion with the other elements of the procedure applied. For the 24-month&#13;
variants, the subsequent births are assumed to occur at 28.0 years, 30.0&#13;
years, and so on, with the fractional birth being allocated to the final&#13;
interval. Thus, the 24-mont:h fertility schedule for a total fertility rate of&#13;
2.50 would have one birth alt 26.0 years, one at 28.0 years, 0.50 births at&#13;
30.0 years. 'The births under the 30-month schedule are analogously placed at&#13;
26.0 years, 28.5 years, 31.0 years, etc.&#13;
For computational purposes, these schedules are translated into the con-&#13;
ventional format by allocatLng each birth between the two relevant age cate-&#13;
gories according to the birth's distance from each; and by summing the&#13;
resulting figures. The procedure can be illustrated with reference to the&#13;
just-mentioned 24-month vartant with a total fertility rate of 2.50. Age 26.0&#13;
is 20% of the distance from 25 to 30. Accordingly, 20% of the birth at age&#13;
26.0 is allocated to age 30, 80% to age 25. Similarly, 40% of a birth at age&#13;
28.0 goes into age 30; 60% to age 25. The half-birth at 30.0 years is allo-&#13;
cated totally to age 30. Adding these together produces an age-specific fer-&#13;
tility schedule with 1.2 births at age 25, 1.3 births at age 30.&#13;
In the absence of any known empirical analysis of the relationship be-&#13;
tween birth interval length and total fertility, an arbitrary procedure is&#13;
adopted. This consists of assuming that, at very high levels of fertility, an&#13;
extension of the birth interval will result in an proportionate decline in&#13;
total fertility; that, at low levels of fertility, an extension will produce&#13;
no change at all in total fertility; and that the decline in the strength of&#13;
the birth interval's influence on total fertility between these two points&#13;
will be linear.&#13;
For the illustrative purpose at hand, the highest attainable or "natural"&#13;
level of fertility is set at 10 births per woman at two-year intervals during&#13;
a 20-year reproductive period. Assuming the length of the reproductive period&#13;
to be fixed, an extension of the average birth interval from 2.0 to 2.5 years&#13;
(i.e. from 24 to 30 months) would mean a reduction of the total fertility rate&#13;
from 10 to 8 (20 years divided by 2.5 years/child), a decline of 20% from the&#13;
initial figure. (For a discussion and presentation of this procedure, see&#13;
John Bongaarts and Jane Menken, "The Supply of Children: A Critical Essay,"&#13;
The Populaticon Council Center for Policy Studies Working Paper, No. 95 (April&#13;
1983), pp. 22-24.)&#13;
The level of fertility at which an extension of birth intervals would no&#13;
longer exercise any effect at all on completed family size is assumed to be a&#13;
total fertility rate of 2.0. This is roughly the ferility level needed for&#13;
the population to replace itself when mortality is very low.&#13;
The asstumption of a linear decline in the relationship between these two&#13;
levels means that when the total fertility rate is at 6.0, the mid-point be-&#13;
tween them, a lengthening of the birth interval from 24 to 30 months would&#13;
bring a 10% reduction in the total fertility rate.   With the total fertility&#13;
rate at 4.0, a similar birth interval extension would reduce the total fer-&#13;
tility rate by 5%. And so on.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-55-&#13;
While this set of assumptions about the between the birth interval and&#13;
the total fertility rate relationship seems as sensible as any other that&#13;
might be imagined, it is strictly hypothetical in nature, as indicated&#13;
earlier. To illustrate its influence on the projection results, the results&#13;
of an alternate projection based on the extreme assumption that longer inter-&#13;
vals produce no decline at all on the total fertility rate are also presented.&#13;
Table III-1 presents the mortality and fertility scenarios that result&#13;
from the application of the assumptions described. Table III-2 contains the&#13;
population figures produced by projections based on the scenarios in table&#13;
III-1. The "model A - adjusted" figure incorporates the correction factor for&#13;
the partially-offsetting fertility reduction caused by faster mortality&#13;
decline, as described in annex I. The "model B - baseline TFR" and "model C -&#13;
baseline TFR" population size estimates are developed on the basis of the&#13;
assumption that longer birth intervals will have no effect on the total fer-&#13;
tility rate. The "model B - adjusted TFR" and "model C - adjusted TFR"&#13;
figures assume that the total fertility rate will be reduced by a lengthening&#13;
of intervals in the manner just described.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table III-1: Child Spacing: Two Scenarios&#13;
Year               24-Month Intervals                      30-Month Intervals&#13;
Infant        Life        Total          Infant       Life        Total&#13;
Mortality   Expectancy    Fertility     Mortality   Expectancy   Fertility&#13;
Rate      at Age 5*       Rate**         Rate     at Age 5*     Rate***&#13;
0          94.08        58.40        4.818         94.08       58.40         4.818&#13;
25          48.14        64.32        3.096         40.92       64.32         3.011&#13;
50          12.20        71.34        2.080         11.28       71.34         2.080&#13;
75          11.28        71.60        2.080         11.28       71.60         2.080&#13;
75           11.28       71.60         2.080         11.28       71.60         2.080&#13;
*Average of separate male and female figures (with the relationship between&#13;
them established by Coale-Demeny "West" family model life tables) used&#13;
in projections.&#13;
**With an age-specific fertility schedule assuming 1st birth at mother's age of&#13;
26.0 years; 2nd birth at 28.0 years; 3rd birth at 30.0 years; etc.&#13;
***With an age-specific fertility schedule assuming 1st birth at mother's age of&#13;
26.0 years; 2nd birth at 28.5 years; 3rd birth at 31.0 years; etc.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-57-&#13;
Table 111-2: Population Size (in Millions) under Different&#13;
Child-Spacing Scenarios: 3 Models&#13;
24-Month                        30-Month Intervals&#13;
Year    Intervals        Model A           Model B             Model C&#13;
Crude  Adjusted  Baseline   Adjusted  Baseline  Adjusted&#13;
TRF**     TRF***    TRF**      TRF***&#13;
0      10.00     10.00    10.00     10.00     10.00     10.00      10.00&#13;
25      16.03     16.15    16.09     15.88     15.60     16.00     15.72&#13;
50      21.77     22.05    21.91     21.45     20.88     21.73     21.14&#13;
75      25.85     26.26    26.06     25.39     24.55     25.80     24.94&#13;
100*     27.07     27.54   27.31      26.58     25.65     27.03     26.08&#13;
*Stable population&#13;
**Incorporating "24-Month" total fertility rate from table III-1&#13;
***Incorporating "30-Month" total fertility rate from table III-1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-59-&#13;
Footnotes&#13;
1.   For clarity of presentation, the diagrams of figure 1 cover only the&#13;
models' principal features. Hints of the many refinements and complexities&#13;
that would need to be included in any fuller presentation appear from time to&#13;
time in the text and the footnotes: the multiple channels between mortality&#13;
and fertility change in models A and C for example, as noted briefly on page 4&#13;
of the text; the network of channels between the measures of model C and fer-&#13;
tility or mortality changes, as suggested footnotes 7, 8 and 13; and the&#13;
various ways in which fertility change can influence mortality change, as&#13;
described in footnote 16.&#13;
2.   For a sense of the issues covered and of the viewpoints presented in the&#13;
extensive literature on this topic, see Samuel H. Preston, " Health Programs&#13;
and Population Growth," Population and Development Review, Vol. 1, No. 2&#13;
(December 1975), pp. 189-99; and C. E. Taylor, J. S. Newman, and Narindar U.&#13;
Kelly, "The Child Survival Hypothesis," Population Studies, Vol. 30, No. 7&#13;
(July 1976), pp. 263-78.&#13;
3.   Among the many projection exercises following the time-honored technique&#13;
of incorporating multiple fertility variants but only a single mortality&#13;
variant are such sets of well-known international projections as those of the&#13;
U.S. Census Bureau (for all the countries covered except China), the&#13;
Community and Family Study Center (CFSC) of the University of Chicago, and&#13;
Tomas Frejka. (The Census Bureau and CFSC projections are to be found in&#13;
U.S., Council on Environmental Quality and Department of State, Entering the&#13;
Twenty-First Century: The Global 2000 Report to the President, Vol. 2: The&#13;
Technical Report, pp. 7-24 and pp. 24-38. The Frejka projections are in Tomas&#13;
Frejka, The Future of Population Growth: Alternative Paths to Equilibrium (New&#13;
York: John Wiley and Sons for the Population Council, 1973).&#13;
The well-established projections of the United Nations use multiple mor-&#13;
tality as well as multiple fertility variants, but in a way that makes them&#13;
even further removed from the spirit of the argument to be developed here than&#13;
the multiple fertility/single mortality variant projections. That is, in the&#13;
U.N. projections, rapid fertility and slow mortality decline variants are&#13;
combined to produce a low population growth scenario; and the rapid mortality&#13;
and slow fertility decline variants are used together to yield a high growth&#13;
scenario. These produce estimates lying on either side of those constructed&#13;
by use of the medium fertility and medium mortality decline variants. (A&#13;
description of the method used in constructing recent U.N. projections appears&#13;
in United Nations, Department of Economic and Social Affairs, World Population&#13;
Prospects as Assessed in 1973 (ST/ESA/SER.A/60, "Population Studies No. 60";&#13;
New York: United Nations, 1977), pp. 7-13.) This is in distinct contrast to&#13;
the theme appearing following pages that the nature of the relationships be-&#13;
tween fertility, mortality, and their determinants suggest that faster mor-&#13;
tality and slower fertility decline, like slower mortality and faster&#13;
fertility decline, are likely to be mutually inconsistent.&#13;
Of course, the desire to develop a set of realistic alternate visions of&#13;
the future or to assess the population growth implications of faster fertility&#13;
decline are not the only reasons why the projection exercises cited and the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-60-&#13;
many others like them were developed as they were. In at least some cases&#13;
(notably that of Frejka), the desire was much less to approximate reality than&#13;
to make a point through the use of assumptions that were in some cases explic-&#13;
itly recognized as unrealistic. In other cases, the use of multiple fertility&#13;
variants resulted from a wish to acknowledge a lack of certainty about the&#13;
rate of fertility decline implied by the mortality trajectory employed.&#13;
To the extent that purposes such as these lie behind the selection of&#13;
variants used, the critique advanced here is not relevant. Amid a frequent&#13;
lack of clarity about the reasons for selecting the particular configuration&#13;
of variants used, however, are to be found strong hints that the desire to&#13;
account for the possibility that fertility might decline more or less rapidly&#13;
than suggested by the medium variant usually represents an important reason&#13;
for using multiple fertility trajectories. It is in the many cases where this&#13;
desire lies behind the selection of variants that the suitability of the&#13;
multiple fertility/single mortality variant approach is questionable.&#13;
4.   Examples of this tradition, also well established, are to be found in a&#13;
wide range of presentations otherwise quite different in tone and orientation.&#13;
For instance: Ansley J. Coale and Edgar M. Hoover, Population Growth and&#13;
Economic Development in Low-Income Countries (Princeton, N.J.: Princeton&#13;
TJniversity Press, 1958); presentations based on the "Rapid" model of the&#13;
Futures Group (as in The Futures Group," Central America: The Effects of&#13;
Population on Economic and Social Development," in "Appendix to the Report of&#13;
the National Bipartisan Commission on Central America" (March, 1984;&#13;
mimeographed), pp. 541-98; and Julian L. Simon, The Economics of Population&#13;
Growth (Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press, 1977). Since fertility&#13;
and mortality are both exogenously determined in models such as these, there&#13;
is nothing to prevent an alternation of mortality trends along with the&#13;
changes of fertility trends introduced in the process of developing illustra-&#13;
tion based on them. This, however, is rarely if ever done; the convention,&#13;
reflected in the publications cited, is to alter only fertility, leaving the&#13;
path of mortality unchanged.&#13;
5.   Examples include the fact that world population growth would continue for&#13;
over 100 years and that population size would increase by over 50% even should&#13;
universal replacement be immediately achieved (Frejka, The Future of Popula-&#13;
tion Growth, p. 220); and the limited likelihood that the replacement effects&#13;
of faster mortality decline would be large enough to offset fully the tendency&#13;
toward faster population growth (Preston, "Health Programs and Population&#13;
Growth;" Susan H. Cochrane and K. C. Zachariah, "Infant and Child Mortality&#13;
as a Determinant of Fertility: The Policy Implications," World Bank Staff&#13;
Working Papers, No. 556 (February 1983)).&#13;
6.   Also, unlike models A and B, model C does not distinguish in advance be-&#13;
tween programs undertaken to reduce mortality and those designed to reduce&#13;
fertility. Programs undertaken for either reason are assessed with the same&#13;
framework, in recognition of the considerable overlap that can exist between&#13;
mortality or fertility reduction measures, and of the resulting difficulty&#13;
that can arise in identifying any given measure as primarily one or the other&#13;
on a priori grounds. Such a distinction, if desired, would be made on the&#13;
basis of a measure's observed effects rather than its stated objectives: that&#13;
is, after determining the relative magnitudes of its mortality and fertility&#13;
influence.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-61-&#13;
7.   Or to be more accurate, a series or network of channels. For, as is to&#13;
appear in the text and in the footnote that follows, it seems possible for a&#13;
given mortality reduction measure to exercise more than one direct effect on&#13;
fertility; for these effects to differ in direction as well as strength; and&#13;
for the effect within each channel to differ in direction and/or strength at&#13;
different levels of mortality, fertility, or the determinant(s) under con-&#13;
sideration.&#13;
8.   As will be seen, many of the conclusions of this paper rest on the propo-&#13;
sition that the net direct fertility effect of most mortality reduction&#13;
measures is, at least within the range of values under consideration, usually&#13;
in the direction of a fertility decrease rather than a fertility increase.&#13;
While this seems a defensible generalization based on the findings of the&#13;
currently available empirical evidence, there is no obvious a priori reason&#13;
why the overall direct fertility and mortality influence of a given measure&#13;
need inevitably be in the same direction; and instances of possibly opposite&#13;
mortality and fertility effects come readily to mind.&#13;
It is intuitively plausible, for example, that at least one effect of&#13;
many health improvement measures might be an enhancement in reproductive ca-&#13;
pacity which, certeris paribus, would raise fertility; and there appear from&#13;
time to time references to instances where such is thought to be the case.&#13;
Reports of reduced birth weights and elevated levels of spontaneous abortion&#13;
associated with malaria are common, for instance (B. J. Brabin, "Analysis of&#13;
Malaria in Pregnancy in Africa," Bulletin of the World Health Organization,&#13;
Vol. 61, No. 6 (1983), pp.1011-13; David J. Wyler, "Malaria: Resurgence,&#13;
Resistance, and Research," Part I, The New England Journal of Medicine, Vol.&#13;
308, No. 15 (April 14, 1983), p. 877). Although it is not clear that the&#13;
effect is large enough to be demographically significant, its existence&#13;
suggests that malaria control measures would tend to raise fertility to at&#13;
least some degree while lowering mortality. Another example concerns improved&#13;
maternal nutrition, which some have suggested might increase fecundity and&#13;
thus fertility at the same time that mortality is reduced. (Whether this&#13;
actually happens is not clear: for a sceptical review of the literature, see&#13;
John Bongaarts, "Does Malnutrition Affect Fecundity? A Summary of the&#13;
Evidence," Science, Vol. 208, No. 4444 (May 9, 1980), pp. 564-69.) Also, the&#13;
direct impact of education, especially male education in extremely poor rural&#13;
societies, has upon occasion been found to be an increase in fertility (Susan&#13;
Hill Cochrane, Fertility and Education: What Do We Really Know? World Bank&#13;
Staff Occasional Papers, Number Twenty-Six (Baltimore: The John Hopkins&#13;
University Press, 1979)).&#13;
Model C, which does not require that the effects delineated within it&#13;
operate in the same direction, can be readily enough be used to assess the&#13;
population growth implications of measures such as these; but the nature of&#13;
the conclusion produced would obviously be quite different for a measure whose&#13;
direct fertility effect is positive rather than negative. The existence of&#13;
possibilities such as those just cited, even if infrequent or of modest quan-&#13;
titative significance in the settings under consideration, thus stands as an&#13;
important warning against assuming that mortality reduction measures will in-&#13;
evitably result in fertility as well as in mortality decline.&#13;
9.   For a review of the education-mortality evidence, see Susan H. Cochrane,&#13;
Donald J. O'Hara, and Joanne Leslie, "The Effects on Education on Health,"&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-62-&#13;
Worid Bank Staff Working Papers, No. 405 (July 1980), esp. pp. 56-92; and the&#13;
papers presented at a 1981 symposium at the University of Michigan, as&#13;
published in Health Policy and Education, Vol. 3, No. 1 (May 1982).&#13;
10. For a much fuller review of these and the other mechanisms involved, see&#13;
Cochrane, Fertility and Education.&#13;
11. A discussion of these anti-malaria approaches is to be found in Gordon W.&#13;
Harrison, Mosquitoes, Malaria, and Man: A History of the Hostilities since&#13;
1880 (New York: E. P. Dutton, 1978). For a description of the techniques used&#13;
against smallpox, see Donald A. Henderson, "The Eradication of Smallpox,"&#13;
Scientific American, Vol. 235, No. 4 (October 1976), pp. 25-33.&#13;
12. A direct impact on mortality would be difficult to envision for a family&#13;
planning service program providing only contraceptive supplies, for example.&#13;
13. As with the direct fertility impact of mortality reduction measures&#13;
described in footnote 7, what's involved is often a series of direct mortality&#13;
effects rather than a single effect. And while the net impact of these direct&#13;
effects usually seems to be a reduction rather than an increase in mortality,&#13;
there is no basis for supposing that all effects will operate in such a manner&#13;
or that the balance among them will inevitably lie in this direction, for&#13;
reasons analogous to those discussed in footnote 8 which argue against the&#13;
assumption that the direct mortality effect of fertility reduction measures&#13;
will inevitably be a decline in death rates.&#13;
The point can be illustrated with respect to the infant mortality impact&#13;
of maternal employment outside the home, an example of an often-advocated&#13;
approach to fertility reduction. This is a case where countervailing direct&#13;
mortality effects seem to exist, and the relative strengths of the competing&#13;
forces remains uncertain. On the one hand, there is the beneficial effect of&#13;
the extra income, an effect strengthened by suggestions that any incremental&#13;
income earned by mothers is more likely to be spent in ways conducive to&#13;
improved child welfare than the same incremental income earned and controlled&#13;
by men. (See, for instance, the studies cited in Daisy Hilse Dwyer, "Women&#13;
and Income in the Third World: Implications for Policy," The Population&#13;
Council International Programs Working Papers, No. 18 (June 1983), pp. 6-7.)&#13;
On the other hand, some argue that maternal nurturing and stimulation are&#13;
central child development, implying that extra-household employment, by&#13;
reducing the time and inclination of mothers to care for their children, can&#13;
contribute to increased infant mortality. (A review of the literature in this&#13;
tradition is to be found in footnotes 2-4 of Barry M. Popkin, "Rural Women,&#13;
Work, and Child Welfare in the Philippines," in Women and Poverty in the Third&#13;
World, ed. Mayra Buvinic, Margaret A. Lycette, and William Paul McGreevey&#13;
(Baltimore and London: The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1983, p. 174.) It&#13;
seems possible for both forces to exist simultaneously, with one being&#13;
stronger in some cases, the other in others. If so, the well-established&#13;
association between extra-household maternal employment and lower fertility&#13;
(ibid., footnote 1, p. 174) would suggest such employment as an instance of a&#13;
fertility reduction measure resulting at least upon occasion in higher rather&#13;
than lower infant mortality.&#13;
14. See, for example, the material presented in Robert Repetto, Economic&#13;
Equality and Fertility,in Developing Countries (Baltimore and London: The&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-63-&#13;
John Hopkins University Press for Resources for the Future, 1979). An alter-&#13;
nate view is to be found in Bryan L. Boulier, "Income Distribution and&#13;
Fertility Decline: A Sceptical View," Population and Development Review, Vol.&#13;
8, Supplement (1982), pp. 159-78.&#13;
15. Particularly well known in this respect is the relationship between&#13;
income increase and food purchase embodied in "Engel's Law," based on the&#13;
finding that the income elasticity of demand for food is normally well below&#13;
unity, so that the proportion of family income spent on food declines as&#13;
income rises.&#13;
16. Fertility declines of this nature appear to be the norm, as older, high-&#13;
parity women predominate among the early acceptors of contraception (Dorothy&#13;
Nortman, "Changing Contraceptive Patterns: A Global Perspective," Population&#13;
Bulletin, Vol. 32, No. 3 (August 1977), pp. 20-22). This suggests that family&#13;
planning programs usually result in a reduction in infant and child mortality,&#13;
at least in their early stages.&#13;
Other patterns are possible, however. A recent report from Costa Rica&#13;
suggests that fertility decline there began among younger, better-educated&#13;
women (J. Mayone Stycos, "The Decline of Fertility in-Costa Rica: Literacy,&#13;
Modernization and Family Planning," Population Studies, Vol. 36, No. 3 (March&#13;
1982), p. 24). In such a case, the effect of the fertility decline per se&#13;
(although not necessarily the overall mortality impact of the education pro-&#13;
ducing it) could well be a rise in the infant mortality rate, since the like-&#13;
lihood of death of those infants whose births were initially averted would&#13;
presumably have been lower than average in view of their prospective mothers'&#13;
age and educational status.&#13;
It is, of course, possible to question whether changes of this sort in&#13;
the infant mortality rate, whether rises or falls, are of much significance&#13;
for welfare. As suggested by the careful way in which the text is worded,&#13;
there would seem a legitimate distinction between changes in the infant mor-&#13;
tality rate that result from: a) a reduction in the number of births in a&#13;
higher- or lower-than average risk category that do not affect the death prob-&#13;
abilities of those infants whose births are not prevented; and b) a reduction&#13;
in fertility that leads to a change in the death probabilities experienced by&#13;
those born. An example of the former, under discussion here, would be the&#13;
prevention of the final birth of an older, high-parity woman. An instance of&#13;
the second would be a delay in the age of first birth or a lengthening of&#13;
birth intervals. If welfare improvements are defined as improvements in the&#13;
survival probabilities of those born, then much of the infant mortality&#13;
decline attributable to fertility reduction would be irrelevant for welfare&#13;
(although not for population growth).&#13;
Be this as it may, what has been said indicates that the indirect mor-&#13;
tality impact of fertility reduction measures cannot safely be considered&#13;
fixed. It will, rather, vary according the pattern of fertility reduction&#13;
produced by the measures under consideration. In this respect, it would&#13;
appear to differ from its counterpart -- the indirect fertility effect of mor-&#13;
tality reduction measures -- whose strength, it was claimed earlier in the&#13;
text, is likely to be the same whatever the measure producing the mortality&#13;
decline in question. (A lucid discussion of the issues involved in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-64-&#13;
assessment on family planning's impact on infant and child mortality, which&#13;
served as a starting point for many of the thoughts just expressed, appears in&#13;
James Trussell and Anne R. Pebley, "The Impact of Family Planning Programs on&#13;
Infant, Child, and Maternal Mortality," draft background paper for the 1984&#13;
World Development Report of the World Bank, 31 October 1983.)&#13;
17. The principal source document on primary health care is the "Declaration&#13;
of Alma-Ata," an outcome of a September 1978 international conference in that&#13;
city sponsored by WHO and UNICEF. The report on this conference, which in-&#13;
cludes the declaration, is available as World Health Organization, Alma-Ata&#13;
1978: Primary Health Care, WHO "Health for All" series, No. 1. The fullest&#13;
and most recent description of the UNICEF "child survival revolution" appears&#13;
in James P. Grant, The State of The World's Children 1984 (Oxford: Oxford&#13;
University Press, 1983). For the outlines of the Ford Foundation's approach,&#13;
see The Ford Foundation, Child Survival/Fair Start, Working Paper from the&#13;
Ford Foundation (New York: The Ford Foundation, August 1983).&#13;
18. When originally presented, in the 1982-83 State of the World's Children&#13;
report, the program consisted of six measures and was known as "GOBI-FF." The&#13;
third "F," representing female education, is a later addition.&#13;
19. Grant, State of the World's Children 1984, p. 57. (Pp. 25-60 of this&#13;
document contain a fuller description of the seven GOBI-FFF measures.)&#13;
20. Even the immediate virtual elimination of infant and child mortality&#13;
would produce a population less than 10% larger at stabilization in the typi-&#13;
cal developing country than the population associated with a more normal tra-&#13;
jectory -- a difference far smaller than the near-trebling that would occur&#13;
even were mortality not to decline more rapidly. Even this would overstate&#13;
the size of the true difference, since the larger population size would have&#13;
to be reduced by adjusting for the faster mortality decline's influence on&#13;
fertility which, even if not fully offsetting, could still be important.&#13;
(Davidson R. Gwatkin and Sarah K. Brandel, "Life Expectancy and Population&#13;
Growth in the Third World," Scientific American, Vol. 246, No. 5 (May 1982),&#13;
pp. 63-65.) Also, as even the most enthusiastic proponents of GOBI-FFF&#13;
programs would be quick to point out, the amount of extra mortality decline&#13;
such programs' produce will inevitably be much less than that of the extreme&#13;
case presented here.&#13;
21. Grant, State of the World's Children 1984, pp. 25-60 passim. For other'&#13;
recent work highlighting the role of personal behavior and belief, see W.&#13;
Henry Mosley, "Will Primary Health Care Reduce Infant and Child Mortality? A&#13;
Critique of Some Current Strategies, with Special Reference to Africa and&#13;
Asia," paper prepared for the IUSSP Seminar on Social policy, Health Policy&#13;
and Mortality Prospects, Paris, 28 February - 4 March 1983 (mimeographed); and&#13;
J. C. Caldwell, P. H. Reddy, and Pat Caldwell, "The Social Component of&#13;
Mortality Decline: An Investigation in South India Employing Alternative&#13;
Methodologies," Population Studies, Vol. 37, No. 2 (July 1983), pp. 185-205.&#13;
22. James E. Kocher, Rural Development, Income Distribution, and Fertility&#13;
Decline, An Occasional Paper of the Population Council (New York: The&#13;
Population Council, 1973); Robert S. McNamara, Address to the Massachusetts&#13;
Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Massachusetts, April 28, 1977 (Washington:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-65-&#13;
The World Bank, 1977); William Rich, Smaller Families through Social and&#13;
Economic Progress, Overseas Development Council Monograph No. 7 (Washingtofd&#13;
D.C.:  Overseas Development Council, January 1973).    A review,and citations of&#13;
material presenting the different positions on development's contribution to&#13;
population are to be found in Bernard Berelson, The Great Debate on PopulatLon&#13;
Policy: An Instructive Entertainment, An Occasional Paper of the Population&#13;
Council (New York: The Population Council, 1975).&#13;
23. In the sense that a reduction of, say, half a percentage point in the&#13;
crude birth rate would result in a decline of half a percentage point in the&#13;
population growth rate.&#13;
24. McNamara, Address to the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.&#13;
25. Ibid, p. 3.&#13;
26. Ibid, p. 28.&#13;
27. Whether McNamara himself assumed this is not clear. On the one hand, as&#13;
indicated in the text, McNamara did not try to provide an explicit estimate of&#13;
the amount of reduction in population growth that might result from the imple-&#13;
mentation of the measures he recommended. On the other hand, he preceded and&#13;
set the stage for his discussion of these measures with a presentation of&#13;
figures by Tomas Frejka demonstrating the growth benefits of achieving a net&#13;
reproduction rate of unity in 2000 rather than 2020 A.D. -- figures which, as&#13;
noted in footnote 3, were prepared by means of a "model B" approach that&#13;
allowed the fertility but not the mortality assumption to vary. (Ibid., pp.&#13;
10-11.)&#13;
28. Examples include Hollis Chenery and Moises Syrquin, Patterns of Develop-&#13;
ment, 1950-70, A World Bank Research Publication (London: Oxford University&#13;
Press for the World Bank, 1975); D.V. McGranahan et al., Contents and Measure-&#13;
ment of Socioeconomic Development: A Staff Study of the United Nations&#13;
Research Institute for Social Development, Praeger Special Studies in Inter-&#13;
national Economics and Development (New York, Washington, London: Praeger&#13;
Publishers, 1972); and, for Latin America and the Caribbean, Frank William&#13;
Oechsli and Dudley Kirk, "Modernization and the Demographic Transition in&#13;
Latin America and the Caribbean," Economic Development and Cultural Change,&#13;
Vol. 23, No. 5 (April 1975), pp. 391-419.&#13;
29. McGranahan et al., Contents and Measurement of Socioeconomic Development.&#13;
30. T. P. Dyson, C. L. G. Bell, and R. H. Cassen, "Fertility, Mortality, and&#13;
Income - Changes over the Long Run: Some Simulation Experiments," The&#13;
Journal of Development Studies, Vol. 14, No. 4 (July 1978), pp. 40-78.&#13;
31. Through policies and programs, in other words, operating on two of the&#13;
four segments into which birth intervals are frequently divided for analytical&#13;
purposes: i.e. on postpartum infecundability and on conception delay. The&#13;
third and fourth segments -- time added by spontaneous intrauterine mortality,&#13;
and by gestation -- are taken as notably less amenable to policy or program&#13;
intervention. (For a fuller presentation of this four-segment categorization,&#13;
see John Bongaarts and Jane Menken, "The Supply of Children: A Critical&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-66-&#13;
Es. y," Population Council Center for Policy Studies Working Paper No. 95&#13;
(I :il 1983), pp. 20-21.)&#13;
32., In interpreting this result, the importance of the assumption employed&#13;
cotIcerning the influence of longer birth intervals on total fertility is to be&#13;
kep't in mind. The result presented incorporates the assumption that a shift&#13;
from 24- to 30-month intervals would reduce the total fertility rate somewhat,&#13;
in the manner described in annex III. Were one to assume instead that the&#13;
birth interval had no influence on total fertility, the "model C" population&#13;
would be almost identical to that of the baseline. The inter-generational&#13;
effects of birth interval shift under discussion, in other words, are large&#13;
enough to offset fully the tendency toward faster growth resulting from the&#13;
reduced infant mortality produced by that shift; the magnitude of any reduc-&#13;
tion in population size relative to that on the baseline resulting from longer&#13;
intervals will depend on the strength of the mortality-total fertility rela-&#13;
tionship.&#13;
33. Such as malaria in sub-Saharan Africa. See footnote 8.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
World      BSank                        value of these findings and provides     Demographic Aspects of&#13;
World  .ank                      valuable insights mto possibilities for  Migration in West Africa-&#13;
Publications                            implementing mass programs for          K. C. Zachanah and others&#13;
needy people in villages throughout&#13;
of Related                              the world.                               Volume 1&#13;
Interest                                                                 Staff Working Paper No. 414. September&#13;
Interest  1980 369 pages (including statistical an-&#13;
Volume 1: Integrated Nutrition          nexes, bibliography).&#13;
and Health Care                         Stock No. WP 0414. $15.&#13;
Arnfried A. Kielmann and others&#13;
This volume provides detailed data      Volume 2&#13;
suggesting that synergism between       Staff Working Paper No. 415. September&#13;
malnutntion and infection is probably   1980. 391 pages (including statstical an-&#13;
the greatest cause of mortality, mor-   nexes, bibliography)&#13;
The African Trypanosomiases:            bidity, and retarded growth and devel-  Stock No. WP 0415. $15&#13;
Methods and Concepts of                 over a peniod of four years, vnlagers   (These Working Papers are background&#13;
Control and Eradication in              received nutrition care, general health  studies for Migration in West Africa:&#13;
Relation to Development                 care to control mfections, or both. Dra-  Demographic Aspects, described in this&#13;
C. W. Lee and J. M. Maurice             matic improvements, including a 40%-     section.)&#13;
Here is a practical cost-benefit ap-    50% decline m mortality, a 20% reduc-    Economic Motivation versus&#13;
proach to an age-old problem affecting  tion c in urahion oh moridity, an ai-    City Lights: Testing&#13;
humans and livestock alike, the  w      tion, detailed information on costs is   Hypotheses about Inter-&#13;
can Trypanosomiases. Describes new      presented that permits the most com-     Changwat Migration in&#13;
without destroying game animals.        plete analysis of cost-effectiveness and  Thailand&#13;
Also sumimarizes current research in    program relevant costs and benefits      Fred Arnold and Susan H.&#13;
genetic control, the use of traps and   yet available in this kind of field re-  Cochrane&#13;
screens, attractants, and pheromones.   practscal program implications and       Staff Working Paper No. 416. September&#13;
Technical Paper No 4. 1983. 107 pages.  ways in which such mtegrated services    1980. 41 pages (including footnotes, refer-&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0191-8. Stock No. BK 0191.  can be applied under field conditions.   ences).&#13;
55                                       the Johns Hopkins University Press. 1984.  Stock No. WP 0416. S3.&#13;
Analyzing the Impact of                 288 piges.                               Experiments in Family&#13;
Health Services: Project                LC 82-23915. ISBN 0-8018-3064-8.Stock    Planning: Lessons from    the&#13;
Experiences from India,                 No. JH 3064. $24.50.                     Developing World&#13;
Ghana, and Thailand                                                              Roberto Cuca and Catherine S.&#13;
Rashid Faruqee                          Volume IIn         a     Family          Pierce&#13;
Staff Working Paper No 546. 1982. 44                  negr                       A comprehensive review of experi-&#13;
0ages-                                  Planning and Health Care                mental efforts in the developing world&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0127-9. Stock No. WP 0546.   Carl E. Taylor and others              to determine more effective ways of&#13;
S3.                                      To village people, politicians, and in-  providing family planning services.&#13;
ternational health planners, health and  The Johns Hopkins University Press, 2978.&#13;
famnily planning have always seemed     276 pages (including bibliography, index of&#13;
NEW                                  to fit naturally together. But in the   expenments).&#13;
early 1960s, when international aware-  LC 77-16596. ISBN 0-8018-2013-8, Stock&#13;
Child and Maternal Health                ness of the socazl and economic conse.  No. IH 2013, $29.50 hardcover; ISBN 0-&#13;
Services in India: The        ~quences of surging population growth    8018-2014-6, Stock No. JH 2024, $8.95&#13;
Services in India: The                 moved family planning into a position    paperback.&#13;
Narangwal Experiment                     of high pnonty, some mternational&#13;
What can primary health care and         agencies began to advocate separation   Family Planning Programs: An&#13;
fanily planning do for women and         of family planning from health serv-    Evaluation of Experience&#13;
children tn the poor and depnved         ices. In international policy discussions  Roberto Cuca&#13;
areas of the world? Some of the most     the question continues to be impor-&#13;
specific evidence available today to     tant. This volume analyzes this ques-    Staff Working Paper oVo 345. 1979. 146&#13;
support the benefits of these services   tion and provides arguments and evi-    pages (including 2 annexes, references).&#13;
is contained in these two studies,       dence to support integration of health   Stock No. WP 0345. 55.&#13;
which represent the findings of re-      care and famLly planning; it outlines&#13;
search carried out during 1967-74 in     the purposes underlying the research     Fertility and Education: What&#13;
twenty-six villages in Punjab, India.    in thus area; and it proposes policy     Do We Really Know?&#13;
questions regarding the effectiveness,   Susan H. Cochrane&#13;
Members of the research staff, which     efficiency, and equity of such an inte-  Amdlietfigtemn              hn&#13;
started with 15 people and grew to       gration.                                 A model identifvtig the manv chan-&#13;
about 150 by the end of the project,                                              nels through which education' might&#13;
spent many years working with, and       The Johns Hopkins University Press. 1984&#13;
sharing the lives of, vlllagers. The     256 pages.&#13;
depth of understanding that came         LC 83-23915. ISBN 0-8028-2830-9.Stock    Prices subject to change without notice&#13;
from thLs type of sharing enhances the   No. JH 2830. S22.50.                     and may vary by country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
act to determine terfalitv and a review  Health Issues and Policies in           Kenya: Population and&#13;
of the evidence of the relation between  the Developing Countries                Development&#13;
education and the intervening varia-     Fredrick Golladay                       (See description under Country&#13;
bles in the model that affect fertility.     Workn g Pap                         Studescliting.)&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1979  Staff Working Paper No 412. 1980. 5s   Studies listing.)&#13;
188 pages (including bibliography, index).  pages&#13;
LC 78-26070. ISBN 0-8018-2140-1, Stock   Stock No. WP 0412. S3.&#13;
No. IH 2140, S6.95 paperback.            Health, Nutrition, and Family           Migration in West Africa:&#13;
Planning in India: A Survey of           Demographic Aspects&#13;
FertilityandnExperiments and Special    K. C. Zachanah and Julien Conde&#13;
Fertility and Its Regulation in          EPerojents    adSeilThe first study of the large-scale move-&#13;
Bangladesh                               Rashid Faru ee and Ethna ohnson          ment of people in nie West African&#13;
R. Amin and Rashid Faruqee                           q                            countries. Discusses the volume and&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 507 1982. 108    direction of internal and exteral flows&#13;
Staff Working PaperNo. 383. 1980. 54     pages (including references)             and the economic and social character-&#13;
pages (tncluding references).            Stock No. WP 0507 S5.                    istics of migrants.&#13;
Stock No WP 0383. 3                                                               A jotnt World Bank-OECD study. Oxford&#13;
Infant and Child Mortality as a          University Press, 1981. 166 pages (includ-&#13;
Determinant of Fertility: The            ing 22 maps, bibliography, index).&#13;
Health                                   Policy Implications                      LC 80-21352. ISBN 0-19-520186-8, Stock&#13;
Frednck Golladay, coordinating           Susan Hill Cochrane and K. C.            No OX 520186, S19.95 hardcover; ISBN&#13;
author                                   Zachariah                                0-19-520187-6, Stock No. OX 520187,&#13;
Draws on experience gained from          An illustrative analysis that suggests   $8.95 paperback.&#13;
health components of seventy World       infant mortality may be an important&#13;
Bank projects in forty-four countnes     component of a fertility reducton pro-&#13;
between 1975 and 1978. Emphasizes        gram in countries where mortality is&#13;
the disproportionately high expendi-     high and few couples are able to have    Population and Family&#13;
tures incurred on curative medicne,      the number of surviving children they    Planning in Bangladesh: A&#13;
mamtenance of expensive hospitals,       desire.                                  Study of the Research&#13;
and'sophisticated training of medical    World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 556.  Mohammad Alauddin and Rashid&#13;
personnel at the cost of preventive19344pgsFaue&#13;
care for the majoritv of the people.     1983. 44 pages.                           aruqee&#13;
Pomts out that low-cost health care      ISBN 0-8213-0147-0. Stock No. WP 0556.   Reviews major studies on family plan-&#13;
svstems are feasible and recommends      S3.                                      ning and on fertlity trends, profiles,&#13;
tsyat the Bank begm regular and direct                                            and determinants. Evaluates results of&#13;
lending for health, in addition to hav-  Integrating Family Planning              such studies and critiques their meth-&#13;
ing health components as part of pro-    with Health Services: Does It            odology and application. Underscores&#13;
jects in other sectors.                  Help?                                    need for continued study and suggests&#13;
Sector Poincy other sect . 90 pages in-  Rashel p a.;?,                           directions for future research to irn-&#13;
Sector Policy Paper 1980. 90 pages (in-  Rvashd Faruqee                           prove the Bangladesh population&#13;
cluding 8 annexes, 4 figures, map).      Staff Working Paper No. 515. 1982. 47    problem.&#13;
Stock Nos. BK 9066 (Arabic), BK 9067     pages.                                   World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 557.&#13;
(English), BK 9068 (French), BK 9069     ISBN 0-8223-0003-2. Stock No. WP 0515.   1983. 176 pages.&#13;
(Spanish). $5 -                          $3.                                      ISBN 0-8213-0150-0. Stock No. WP 0557.&#13;
$5.&#13;
Visit the World Bank&#13;
l  l  l   K Stl9t      when you are in                 Population and Poverty in the&#13;
Washington, D.C.                Nancy Birdsall&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 404. 1980. 96&#13;
I Street                                              pages (including 2 appendixes, bibliog-&#13;
raphy).&#13;
Stock No. WP 0404. $3.&#13;
H Stieet&#13;
H Steet                      Laayet Square                             Population Policy and Family&#13;
I        I-.---CP-----J                     L.J______________                      Planning Programs: Trends in&#13;
EiIfA1                   % 4 Avenue                                     Policy and Administration&#13;
Kandiah Kanagaratnam and&#13;
G Street                    The Whtt House             Catherine S. Pierce&#13;
l-        r-"--i                  Ii          i i       TStaff Working Paper No. 447. 2981. 80&#13;
L   _s    I       J         L      1 iI       _                       .            pages (including bibliogiraphy, appendixes).&#13;
World Bank Bookstore                                                          Stock No. WP 0447. $3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NEW                                  published as World Population Projec-    falling mortality, and urbanization-&#13;
tions: Short- and Long-term Projections by  factors that tend to lower fertility else-&#13;
Short-term  Population                   Age and Sex for All Countries, with Re-  where. Calls for a viable population&#13;
Projection, 1980-2020 and Long-          lated Demographic Statistics            policy and programs appropnate to&#13;
term Projection, 2000 to                 1983. 391 pages.                        the culture.&#13;
Stationary Stage by Age and              ISBN 0-8223-0355-4. 530 paperback.       Staff Working Paper No. 559. 1983. 116&#13;
Sex for All Countries of the&#13;
World                                        NEW                                  ISBN 0-8213-0152-7. Stock Nos. WP&#13;
My T. Vu, under the supervision          Rapid Population Growth in&#13;
Tf K.report gives detailed popuhat2on    Sub-Saharan Africa: Issues and           Regional Aspects of Family&#13;
projections by age and sex for each       olcies                                  Planning and Fertility Behavior&#13;
country at five-year intervals from 1980  Rashid Faruqee and Ravi Gulhati        in Indonesia&#13;
to 2020 and at twenty-five year inter-   No other country has higher fertility    Dov Chernichovsky and Oey Astra&#13;
vals from 2000 to the year in which      than Kenya and its neighbonng coun-      Meso&#13;
population becomes stationary in each   tries in Sub-Saharan Africa. This           eesook&#13;
country. The implied fertility and mor-  Working Paper examnes the reasons        Staff Working Paper No. 462. 1981. 62&#13;
tality measures are also given. Revised  for fertility rates staying high, even   pages (including appendix, references).&#13;
annually. The 1984 edition will be       rising in the face of greater education,  Stock No. WP 0462. $3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
in Publications Order Form&#13;
SEND TO: YOUR LOCAL DISTRIBUTOR OR TO WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
(See the other side of thus form)         P.O. BOX 37525&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013 U.S.A.&#13;
Date&#13;
Name                                                 Ship to: (Enter if different from purchaser)&#13;
Title                                                Name&#13;
Firm                                                 Title&#13;
Address                                              Firm&#13;
City               State_      Postal Code           Address&#13;
Country            TRlephone I_)                     City            State_      Postal Code&#13;
Purchaser Reference No.                              Country             Telephone&#13;
Check your method of payment.&#13;
Enclosed is my I Check IOI International Money Order O]Unesco Coupons O International Postal Coupon.&#13;
Make payable to World Bank Publications for U. S. dollars unless you are ordering from your local distributor.&#13;
Charge my O VISA O MasterCard O American Express O Choice. (Credit cards accepted only for orders addressed&#13;
to World Bank Publications.)&#13;
Credit Card Account Number           Expiration Date                     Signature&#13;
O Invoice me and please reference my Purchase Order No.&#13;
Please ship me the items listed below.&#13;
Customer Internal&#13;
Stock Number  Author/ Title                                      Routing Codec  Quantity  Unit Price  Total Amount S&#13;
All prices subject to change. Prices may vary by country. Allow 6-8 weeks for delivery.&#13;
Subtotal Cost  $___&#13;
Ibtal copies  .,Air mail surcharge if desired ($2.00 each)  $___&#13;
Postage and handling for more than two complimentary items ($2.00 each) $___&#13;
'Ibtal&#13;
8RD453                                                            Thank you for your order.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Distributors of World                    Attn Mr Giancarlo Bigazzi                 Attn Mr J.M  Hernandez&#13;
Distributors                              Via Lamarmora 45                         Castello 37&#13;
Bank Publications                         50121                                    Madrtd&#13;
ARGENTINA                                Florence                                 SRI LANKA AND THE MALDIVES&#13;
Carlos Hirsch, SRL.                      JAPAN                                     Lake House Bookshop&#13;
Attn Ms. Monica Bustos                   Eastern Book Service                      Attn Mr Victor Walatara&#13;
Florida 165 4° piso                      Attn. Mr Terumasa Hirano                 41 Wad Ramanavake Mawatha&#13;
Galeria Guemes                           37-3, Hongo 3-Chome, Bunkyo-ku 113        Colombo 2&#13;
Buenos Aires 1307                        Tokyo                                     SWEDEN&#13;
AUSTRALIA, PAPUA NEW GUINEA,             KENYA                                     ABCE Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel&#13;
FAJUSRSOLOMON ISLANDSE                    Africa Book Services (E A ) Ltd          Attn Mr. Eide Segerback&#13;
VANUATU                                  P     M. Box 45245 DarRe                       2ensgatan 1o2.Box 16356&#13;
The Australian Financial Review          Nairobi                                   SWITZERLAND&#13;
Information Service (AFRIS)              KOREA, REPUBLIC OF                        Libraine Pavot&#13;
Attn Mr David Jamieson                   Pan Korea Book Corpration                 Attn. Mr H-enn de Perrot&#13;
235-243 Jones Street                     Attn. Mr Yoon-Sun Kim                     6, rue Grenus&#13;
Broadway                                 P 0 Box 101, Kwanghwamun                  1211 Geneva&#13;
Sydney. NSW 20001                        Seoul                                     TANZANIA&#13;
BELGIUM                                  MALAYSIA                                 Oxford Universitv Press&#13;
Publications des Nations Unies           University of Malaya Cooperative         Attn Mr Anthonv Theobold&#13;
Attn Mr. Jean de Lannoy                  Bookshop Ltd                              Maktaba Road, P.O  Box 5299&#13;
av du Roi 202                            Attn. Mr. Mohammed Fahim Htj              Dar es Salaam&#13;
1060 Brussels                            Yacob                                    THAILAND&#13;
CANADA                                   P 0 Box 1127, Jalan Pantai Baru          Central Department Store, Head Office&#13;
Le Diffuseur                             Kuala Lumpur                              Attn Mrs. Ratana&#13;
Attn Mrs Suzanne Vermette                MEXICO                                   306 Silom Road&#13;
C P 85, Boucherville J4B 5E6             INFOTEC                                   Bangkok&#13;
Quebec                                   Attn Mr Jorge Cepeda                     Thailand Management Association&#13;
COSTA RICA                               San Lorenzo 153-11, Col del Valle,        Attn Mrs. Sunan&#13;
Librena Trejos                           Deleg Benito Juarez                      308 Silom Road&#13;
Attn Mr Hugo Chamberlain                 0310 Mexico, D.E                          Bangkok&#13;
Calle 11-13, Av Fernandez Guell          MIDDLE EAST                              TUNISIA&#13;
San Jose                                 Middle East Marketing Research           Societe Tunisienne de Diffusion&#13;
DENMARK                                  Bureau                                    Attn Mr Slaheddine Ben Hamida&#13;
Sanfundslitteratur                       Attn Mr George Vassilou                   3 Avenue de Carthage&#13;
Attn Mr Wilfned Roloff                   Makaios    Avenue                        Tus&#13;
Rosendems Alle 11                        Nicosia                                  TURKEY&#13;
DK-1970 Copenhagen V                     Cvprus                                    Haset Kita pevi A S&#13;
EGYPT, Arab Republic of                  (granch offices in Bahrain, Greece,      Attn Mr. &amp;zzet lzerel&#13;
Al Ahram                                 Morocco, Kuwait, United Arab             469, Istiklal Caddesi&#13;
Al Galaa Street                          Emirates, Jordan)                         Beyoglu-Istanbul&#13;
Cairo                                    NETHERLANDS                               UNITED KINGDOM AND&#13;
MBE BV                                   NORTHERN IRELAND&#13;
FINLAND                                  Attn Mr Gerhard van Bussell              Microinfo Ltd&#13;
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa                  Noorderwal 38,                           Attn Mr Roy Selwyn&#13;
Attn Mr Kari Litmanen                    7241 BL Lochem                           Newman Lane, P 0 Box 3&#13;
Keskuskatu 1. SF-00100                   NORWAY                                   Alton, Hampshire GU34 2PG&#13;
Helsinki 10                              Johan Grundt Tanum A S                   England&#13;
FRANCE                                   Attn Ms Randi Mikkelborg                 UNITED STATES&#13;
World Bank Publications                  P 0 Box 1177 Sentrum                     The World Bank Book Store&#13;
66, avenue d'ilna                        Oslo 1                                   600 19th Street. N W&#13;
75116 Pans                               PANAMA                                    Washington, D C 20433&#13;
GERMANY, Federal Republic of             Ediciones Libreria Cultural Panamena     (Postal address' P.0 Box 37525&#13;
UNO-Verlag                               Attn Mr Luis Fernandez Fraguela R        Washington, D C 20013, U S A&#13;
Attn Mr Joachim Krause                   Av 7, Es ana 16                           Baker and Taylor Company&#13;
SAmrockstrasse 23                        Panama   one 1                            501 South Gladiola Avenue&#13;
D-5300 Bonn I                            PHILIPPINES                               Momence, Illinois, 60954&#13;
HONG KONG, MACAU                         National Book Store                      380 Edison Way&#13;
AsHa 2000 Ltd                            Attn: Mrs Socorro C Ramos                 Reno. Nevada, 89564&#13;
Attn Ms Gretchen Weadng Smith            701 Rizal Avenue                          50 Kirbv Avenue&#13;
6 Fl, 146 Pnnce Edward Road                anla                                   Somerville, New Jersey, 08876&#13;
Kowloon      .                           PORTUGAL                                 Commerce, Georgia 30599&#13;
INDIA                                    Livraria Portugal&#13;
UBS Publishers' Distributors ILtd.       Attn Mr Antonio Alves Martins            Beman Associates&#13;
UBtn Pulihrs', Distribtr   t.Rua Do Carmo 70-74                                   9730-E George Palmer rHiifhway&#13;
5 Ansa' Road, Post Box 7015              1200                                     Lanham, Maryland. 2076i&#13;
New DelhR 110002  B    0i.bon                                                    Blackwell North America, Inc&#13;
(Branch offices in Bombay, Bangalore,    SAUDI ARABIA                             1001 Fnes MNil Road&#13;
Kanpur, Calcutta, and Madras)            Jarir Book Store                          Blackwood, New Jersey 08012&#13;
INDONESIA                                Attn. Mr Akram Al-Agil                   Sidney Kramer Books&#13;
Pt Indira Limited                        P O Box 3196                             1722 H Street, N W&#13;
Attn Mr Bambang Wahvudi                  Rivadh                                   Washington, D.C. 20006&#13;
JI, Dr Sam Ratulangi No. 37              SINGAPORE, TAIWAN, BURMA                 United Nations Bookshop&#13;
Jakarta Pusat                            Information Publications Pnvate, Ltd     United Nations Plaza&#13;
IRELAND                                  Attn- Ms Janet David                     New York, N Y 10017&#13;
TDC Publishers                           02-06 Ist Floor, Pei-Fu Industrial&#13;
Attn' Mr James Booth                       Building                               VENEZUELA&#13;
12 North Frederick Street                24 New Industrial Road                  LAbrena deM Este&#13;
Dublin I                                 Singapore                                Attn Mr Juan Perncas&#13;
Dublin  I                                 Singapore                               A vda  Francisco  de  M iranda,  no.  52&#13;
ITALY                                    SPAIN                                    Edificio GalIpan, Aptdo 60 337&#13;
Licosa Conimissionaria Sansoni SPA       Mundi.Prensa Libros, S A.                Caracas 106-A&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG 3881.5 .W57 W67 no.686&#13;
c.3&#13;
Gwatkin, Davidson R.&#13;
-Mortality reduction,&#13;
fertility decline, and&#13;
DATE    NAME AND EXTENSION    RoOM&#13;
NUMBER&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                           European Office               Tokyo Office&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                    66, avenue d'1ena             Kokusai Building&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A          75116 Paris, France           1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234              Telephone (1) 723-54 21       Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex WUI 64145 WORLDBANK              Telex: 842-620628             Telephone (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                             Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0445-3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554776">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/11/1554776/mortality-reduction-fertility-decline-population-growth-toward-more-relevant-assessment-relationships-among
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/11/1554776/mortality-reduction-fertility-decline-population-growth-toward-more-relevant-assessment-relationships-among</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1984/11/1554776/mortality-reduction-fertility-decline-population-growth-toward-more-relevant-assessment-relationships-among</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/06/14/000178830_98101903424649/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/06/14/000178830_98101903424649/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-06-14T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1984-11-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Mortality reduction, fertility decline, and
            population growth : toward a more relevant assessment of the
            relationships among them
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This discussion responds to the
            questions of programs to reduce mortality and of how large a
            change in growth will result from efforts to lower
            fertility. It considers the influence of the policies or
            programs in question on mortality and on fertility, and the
            influence of the resulting fertility or mortality decline on
            the rate of change in the other. An approach of the sort
            required to adequately assess these policies or programs is
            difficult to apply, but its potential significance for
            policy and program analysis can be illustrated through a few
            qualitative and crude quantitative examples. These
            illustrations suggest two propositions to serve as interim
            guides to action and as hypotheses to be confirmed or
            disproven through future research. First, most programs and
            policies undertaken to reduce mortality will produce even
            larger fertility declines and thus slower growth. And,
            second, most measures designed to reduce fertility will also
            result in slower growth, but by an amount that may be
            significantly less than anticipated on the basis of
            conventional assessment techniques.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Mortality reduction, fertility decline, and
            population growth : toward a more relevant assessment of the
            relationships among them
        </docna>
        <display_title>Mortality reduction, fertility
            decline, and population growth : toward a more relevant
            assessment of the relationships among them</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1984/11/1554776/mortality-reduction-fertility-decline-population-growth-toward-more-relevant-assessment-relationships-among</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Early Child and Children's Health,Demographics,Reproductive Health,Health Economics &amp; Finance</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Gwatkin, D.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903424649</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Primary health, including
            reproductive health, child health and health</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 686</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Health, Nutrition &amp; Population</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0445-3</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Mortality decline; Fertility decline;
            Population decline; Population policy; Macroeconomic models
            birth intervals,birth rates,births,child
            growth,child mortality,child mortality rates,Child
            Spacing,Child Survival,Child Survival Programs,communicable
            diseases,contraceptive services,demographic
            characteristics,demographic effects,Determinants of
            Fertility,diarrhea,diphtheria,exercises,Expenditures,families,family
            planning,family planning programs,family
            size,fertility,fertility decline,fertility
            trends,girls,health workers,Immunization,immunization
            programs,Income,Income Distribution,infant
            mortality,insurance,malaria,Maternal
            Mortality,measles,migration,Mortality,mortality
            decline,mortality rates,mothers,Oral rehydration
            therapy,parents,poliomyelitis,Population
            Activities,population change,population growth,Population
            Mobility,population policies,Population policy,Population
            Programs,population projections,population size,primary
            health care,productivity,social
            development,tetanus,vaccination,whooping cough,workers,World
            Population Conference
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP686</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutritional supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vitamins</ml:concept><ml:concept>IMR</ml:concept><ml:concept>Maternal and Child Mortality</ml:concept><ml:concept>U5MR</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographic Transition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Birth Spacing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vaccines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock and Animal Husbandry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Econometrics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Malaria</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infant and Child Mortality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographic Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Family Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contraceptives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Immunizations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Animal Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>