<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP499&#13;
A Simultaneous Equation Model&#13;
of Price and Quantity Adjustments&#13;
in World Primary Commodity Markets&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 499&#13;
October 1981&#13;
1y: Erh-Cheng Hwa&#13;
Economic Analysis &amp; Projections Department&#13;
Copyright ( 1981&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author  l I/ &#13;
and should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated&#13;
organizations, or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations,&#13;
or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 499&#13;
October 1981&#13;
A SIMULTANEOUS EQUATION MODEL OF PRICE AND QUANTITY&#13;
ADJUSTMENTS IN WORLD PRIMARY COMMODITY MARKETS&#13;
This paper presents a dynamic, simultaneous model of price&#13;
and quantity adjustments in world primary commodity markets. The model&#13;
is formulated in a disequilibrium framework, emphasizing particularly the&#13;
role of price adjustment. In addition to the price equation, commodity&#13;
consumption and production equations are also specified.&#13;
The empirical analysis of the model is carried out with the annual&#13;
data of six primary commodities: coffee, cocoa, rubber, copper, tin and&#13;
sugar. This includes the estimation of price, consumption, production&#13;
equations, the simulation tests of complete structural models for these&#13;
six commodities, and the derivation of dynamic responses (measured by&#13;
elasticities) of commodity prices to changes in world income, world inflation&#13;
and commodity outputs.    Dynamic simulations strongly confirm the commonly&#13;
observed self-generating and recurring boom-and-bust cycles of primary&#13;
commodity prices.  This finding lends credibility to the models constructed.&#13;
Prepared by:                                               Copyright  c  1981&#13;
Erh-Cheng Hwa                                              The World Bank&#13;
Economic Analysis &amp; Projections Department                 1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433.&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table of Content&#13;
Chapter                                                               Page&#13;
Introduction                                                            1&#13;
I.      Model Specification                                          2&#13;
II.      Estimation Results                                          14&#13;
III.      Simulation Results                                          24&#13;
IV.      Summary and Conclusion                                      42&#13;
Appendix                                                               46&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
A SIMULTANEOUS EQUATION MODEL OF PRICE AND QUANTITY&#13;
ADJUSTMENTS IN WORLD PRIMARY COMMODITY MARKETS*&#13;
Introduction&#13;
A typical feature of competitive primary commodity markets is that&#13;
short-run price fluctuations are generally much more pronounced than quantity&#13;
fluctuations. Quantity adjustments are stickier mainly because the production&#13;
of many primary commodities involve rather long supply lags. Prices rather&#13;
than quantities, then, assume the major burden of adjustment for restoring&#13;
market equilibrium. The purpose of this paper is to formulate a competitive&#13;
disequilibrium model of price and quantity adjustments in world primary com-&#13;
modity markets, emphasizing particularly the role of price adjustment. The&#13;
model is cast in a disequilibrium framework in the sense that it does not&#13;
assume instanteous market clearing. The dynamics of price adjustment is&#13;
explicitly modeled.&#13;
In addition to the price equation, the model consists of equations&#13;
for stocks (both demand and supply), production, and consumption. Whenever&#13;
appropriate the production and consumption equations are modeled by polynomial&#13;
distributed lag functions in lieu of the popular Nerlove lag function to allow&#13;
a more flexible specification of the lagged responses. The model is&#13;
empirically tested with the annual data of six primary commodities: coffee,&#13;
cocoa, rubber, tin, copper, and sugar. Dynamic simulations tests indicate&#13;
that the empirically estimated models, though small, have captured the&#13;
dynamics of these commodity markets fairly well.&#13;
*   The paper benefitted from useful comments by the staff of the Commodities&#13;
and Export Projections Division of the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
The plan of this paper is as follows. In the first section the&#13;
specification of the model is discussed.    This includes the derivation of a&#13;
disequilibrium price adjustment equation and the specifications of consumption&#13;
and production equations. In the second section the estimation results of the&#13;
model are presented and analyzed. In the third section the results of dynamic&#13;
simulations derived from the estimated models are presented, and this is&#13;
followed by a summary and conclusion in the last section.&#13;
I. Model Specification&#13;
Time series models of primary commodity markets are a common&#13;
phenomenon. The most common approach to commodity market modelling is to&#13;
assume instantaneous market clearing: for example, Adams and Behrman (1976),&#13;
Labys (1978), and the models developed by Tims and Singh. In a condensed&#13;
term, a typical world market modei of a storable primary commodity may be&#13;
represented by the following set of equations:&#13;
ct = f1 (p    xc   + u                                           (1)&#13;
qt = f2 (Pt   xqt) + vt                                          (2)&#13;
hd  = f3 (p    xh)    w                                           (3)&#13;
t    t-1 qt     t   t                                           (4)&#13;
hd  = h                                                           (5)&#13;
The first three equations are, respectively, consumption (c t),&#13;
production (q t) and stock-demand (hd t) equations. They all are postulated to&#13;
be a function of real prices (p t) and other relevant predetermined variables&#13;
(xct, xqt, xht) I/   The fourth is a stock supply (ht) equation, in which xt is&#13;
an exogenous variable representing the interventions by either a buffer stock&#13;
agency or national governments. The last equation is an equilibrium&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
condition, stating that the demand for stock is equal to the supply of&#13;
stock. In these equations, u t, v , wt are additive random distrubance terms.&#13;
The system may be said to be a short-run equilibrium system if&#13;
adjustments in quantities (production, consumption, stocks) with respect to&#13;
changes in prices do not complete within the time unit of observation; other-&#13;
wise, it may be said to represent a long-run equilibrium system. Irrespective&#13;
of whether it is a long-run or a short-run equilibrium system, this model does&#13;
not deal with the process of price adjustment in an explicit way. In order to&#13;
introduce an explicit hypothesis of price adjustment, it is necesary to relax&#13;
the equilibrium assumption and make due allowance for the possibility of dis-&#13;
equilibrium in both prices and quantities.&#13;
In a competitive market, the disequilibria in prices and in quanti-&#13;
ties are directly related: when quantities are in disequilibrium (the&#13;
quantity demanded is not equal to the quantity supplied at the existing price&#13;
level), prices must also be in disequilibrium, and vice versa. If functions&#13;
f1, f2, and f3 are linear, the following relation holds:&#13;
t _Pt =f1 + f2 + f3)      (hd -h ),                                  (6)&#13;
where pe is the equilibrium price level and can be derived from (5) by substi-&#13;
t&#13;
tuting into it (1), (2), (3), and (4); fi, f2, f' are, respectively, the&#13;
partial derivatives of ct, qt, hdt with respect to the price and, since these&#13;
functions are linear, they are also the marginal propensities.&#13;
It is clear from the above equation that when the market is not in&#13;
equilibrium neither the actual observed price is equal to the underly equili-&#13;
brium price nor is the stock-demand equal to the stock-supply. Therefore, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
assumption that hdt = h   literally implies Pe = p, i.e., the market is an&#13;
equilibrium market.&#13;
But what if hd is not equal to ht, or pe is not equal to pt? How is&#13;
t &#13;
the market equilibrium to be attained from a disequilibrium situation? It is&#13;
expected that it can be attained through adjustments in both prices and&#13;
quantities. But given the low short-run quantity responses exhibited for many&#13;
primary commodities, prices are much more pivotal in the adjustment process.&#13;
For modelling the dynamics in competitive primary commodity markets, it is&#13;
thus more profitable to adopt the Walrasian adjustment mechanism. Therefore,&#13;
I assume that the actual price will gradually adjust to the equilibrium price:&#13;
P  =t(L) pet                                                     (7)&#13;
where w (L) is a distributed lag function in which L is a lag operator&#13;
(Lpt =  t-    etc.).&#13;
(7) implies that the adjustment of prices will be gradual and&#13;
therefore the observed price need not be the equilibrium price. Hence eq.&#13;
(6), rather than (5), will hold in general. Inserting (7) into (6) yields the&#13;
following dynamic price equation:&#13;
Pt      ((L) - 1)      (hdt-ht),                                 (8)&#13;
where   = (fi + f2 + f3) -1   with   &gt; 0.&#13;
1    2    3&#13;
It is obvious from (8) that there can be as many dynamic price&#13;
equations as there are hypotheses concerning the specification of the&#13;
distributed lag function w(L). However, the empirical analysis conducted in&#13;
this paper and reported below indicates that it is sufficient to consider the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 5 -&#13;
following two distributed lag functions, at least with the annual data&#13;
employed here:&#13;
w(L) =         0-A-  0 &lt;A&lt;1,                                     (9-a)&#13;
and                I-. -A&#13;
1  2&#13;
@(L) =      &#133;- -------2' A1+A2&lt;1  A2A1&lt;1,  1(A2(1.               (9-b)&#13;
1-A L-A L&#13;
1   2&#13;
(9-a) is the geometric lag hypothesis, which implies a monotonic&#13;
increasing or decreasing path of price adjustment toward the equilibrium,&#13;
while (9-b) may imply a more complex adjustment pattern, with the possibility&#13;
of oscillations around the equilibrium price. Substituting (9-a) and (9-b)&#13;
into (8), respectively, yields&#13;
Dp  =(1-A) (hd                                                  (10-a)&#13;
and&#13;
A2   D        (1-A -A )&#13;
X2            (1x -2&#13;
Dpt     -+ ---   t-D +    &#133;+       (hd -h ),                    (10-b)&#13;
1    2          1     2&#13;
where Dpt =    Pt Pt-  2/&#13;
Both (10-a) and (10-b) show that price changes are a positive func-&#13;
tion of excess demand for stock, which is perfectly in agreement with the&#13;
well-known Walrasian model of competitive price adjustments. In (10-a), A&#13;
dictates both the size and speed of price adjustment; the smaller its value,&#13;
the faster and greater the adjustment of prices. When A approaches to zero,&#13;
the price adjustment will be instantaneous with respect to the time unit of&#13;
observation, and the system is then reduced to an equilibrium system.&#13;
Similarly, in (10-b) the size of A +A2 reflects the speed and magnitude of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6-&#13;
price adjustment. But in that case, price changes are also a function of past&#13;
excess demands.&#13;
In sum, the competitive disequilibrium model consistes of equations&#13;
(1)-(4), either (10-a) or (10-b). In this model, the voluntary accumulation&#13;
of stocks is not the same as the actual accumulation of stocks in each&#13;
period. This can be seen by rewriting (12) into the following relation:&#13;
ht  t-1    (ht-hdt) + (hdt-h t)&#13;
This equation shows.that the observed, ex-post accumulation of stocks during a&#13;
period consists of two components: involuntary accumulation (h t-hd t) and&#13;
voluntary accumulation (hdt - ht    ).  The observed accumulation of stocks will&#13;
equal the voluntary accumulation only if the market is in equilibrium; namely,&#13;
when h -hd = 0. Therefore, the observed changes in stocks can be consistent&#13;
with'an equilibrium market as well as a disequilibrium one.&#13;
From the viewpoint of estimation, the only unobserved variable in the&#13;
model in hd . Although the equation of the demand for stock, eq. (3), can not&#13;
be estimated directly, it can be estimated through the price equation. This&#13;
can be seen by inserting equation (3) into equations (10-a) and (10-b).&#13;
In what follows, I will discuss the specification of the price equa-&#13;
tion or, more precisely, the demand for stock equation.&#13;
The price stock demand equations&#13;
Stocks are generally held by market participants for satisfying&#13;
transaction and speculative demands. The transaction demand may be defined as&#13;
the amount of stocks held for fulfilling the requirement of present consump-&#13;
tion (sales) and future consumption (production). This demand originates from&#13;
the imperfect synchronization between present consumption and production. The&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
transaction demand can thus be expected to be a positive function consumption&#13;
(ct). The speculative demand, on the other hand, is motivated by the desire&#13;
to make profit, which is completely unrelated to the conumption and production&#13;
needs. It has been argued that speculators will hold stocks at a level at&#13;
which the expected price spread is equal !to the storage cost of holding a unit&#13;
of stock plus the interest cost and the risk premium associated with the&#13;
uncertainties involved in predicting the price: e.g., Kaldor (1939), Kohn&#13;
(1978). The speculative demand for stocks may therefore be postulated as a&#13;
positive function of the price spread and a negative function of storage and&#13;
interest costs and risk premium. The stock demand equation (in log-linear&#13;
form) can be postulated as the following:&#13;
loghd  = a +a logc +a (E logp     -logp ) + a log( t                        (13)&#13;
t   a0+a1 ogt2(           t+1     t     a3log+s)+4or        ft 5 t+&#13;
where Elogpt+l is the price level of period t+l expected at time t; it and St&#13;
are, respectively, the interest cost and storage cost; rt is the risk premium;&#13;
and t is a time trend. The trend variable is introduced to catch the long-run&#13;
effect of more efficient stock control techniques on the desired level of&#13;
stocks. The expected signs associated with the arguments in (13) are, respec-&#13;
tively, positive for ct and Ept+i-pt, but negtiave for it+st, rt, and t,&#13;
i.e., a,, a2&gt;0, a3, a4, a5&lt;0; wt is a random error.&#13;
Substituting (13) into the log-linear counterparts of (10-a) and&#13;
(10-b) yields, respectively,&#13;
Dlogpt = Ila0+PLIlogc t+pa2(Elogp t+l-logpt ) + pa3log(i t+st)&#13;
+ pa4logr + la5t-plogh +wf                                 (13-a)&#13;
and&#13;
Dlogpt =   a +   logct+a2(Elogpt+-logpt)+oa3log(t+st)&#13;
+ IaC4lo0gr + 6a t-6logh -kDlogp   + wt                    (13-b)&#13;
4  t ~5          t       t-1    t&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
where        - =  L2-2,&#13;
¢p(1-X1-X2)&#13;
12&#13;
X&#13;
k     2&#13;
1  2&#13;
LU) = pIWt&#13;
t     t&#13;
and        w" =w&#13;
t     t&#13;
These are the price adjustment equations derived for a disequilibrium&#13;
commodity market.   For an equilibrium market, hd    = h . Hence, the demand for&#13;
stock equation, eq. (13), can be directly estimated. If that equation is&#13;
normalized on the price variable, this yields&#13;
a0   a3                           a4&#13;
logpt   a2 +a2 logct + a    log(it +st) +     logr&#13;
a5     1                      1&#13;
+ _ t- -    loght + Elogp +  +     w W&#13;
a2    c2          t    t+    a2 &#13;
I now turn to the discussion of the specifications of the consumption&#13;
and production equations, i.e., eqs. (1) and (2). Since these equations are&#13;
specified and estimated on a world level while, in fact, consumption and&#13;
production decisions are made at a far less aggregate level, these discussions&#13;
are meant to be heristic.&#13;
The Consumption (Demand) function&#13;
In this study I identify the measurable counterpart of the demand for&#13;
a primary commodity as the rate of consumption.     It is well know that the&#13;
demand for a primary commodity is a "derived" demand. Because of the nature&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
of the derived demand, the derivation of the demand function for primary com-&#13;
modities requires consideration of not only the demand for primary commodities&#13;
as productive inputs but the demand for final products which employ them in&#13;
the production process as well. The following sets forth the rationale for&#13;
the specification of the world demand function of a primary commodity.&#13;
Assuming that a short-run world production function for the final&#13;
product may be expressed by the relation (time subscripts are omitted for the&#13;
time being):&#13;
y = y(d    d 2 '                                                   (14)&#13;
where y is the final product (say world GNP) and di, d2 are two primary&#13;
inputs which are close substitutes. 3/ Then the profit function is&#13;
n = Pf.y(di, d)     Pd    -P2d 2                                  (15)&#13;
where Pf, P1, and P2 are, respectively, the nominal prices of final products&#13;
(say, the world GNP deflator) and the two primary commodities. The profit-&#13;
maximizing inputs can be derived from setting the partial derivatives of (15)&#13;
equal to zero as&#13;
Pf.yI(di, d2) - p1 = 0                                          (16)&#13;
Pf.y 2(d, d 2) - P2 = 0                                          (17)&#13;
Solving equations (14), (15), (16), and (17) give optimal demands for&#13;
inputs as&#13;
d  =d    ( 1 P2     )                                            (18)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-10 -&#13;
d2 = d2 (P1i P22 Pf).                                           (19)&#13;
Thus the demand for a primary input is a function of its own price, the price&#13;
of its close substitute, and the price of the final product.     The nature of&#13;
derived demand is clearly revealed by the dependence of this demand upon the&#13;
price of the final product, since the latter is a function of final demand as&#13;
indicated below.&#13;
Assuming that the aggregate utility function of the world economy may&#13;
be represented by&#13;
u = u(y),                                                        (20)&#13;
then the aggregate demand function derived from maximizing the utility&#13;
I&#13;
function subject to the budget constraint Y-Pf.y = 0 is&#13;
y = y(Pf, Y),                                                    (21)&#13;
where Y is the world money income.&#13;
Assuming the following inverse function of (21) exists:&#13;
Pf = Pf(y, Y),                                                   (22)&#13;
then substituting (22) into (18) and (19) yields, respectively,&#13;
d  = d I(P1 P2, Pf(y, Y)),                                      (23)&#13;
and&#13;
2= d2(P1i P2, Pf(y, Y)).                                       (24)&#13;
It is thus shown that the world demand for a primary commodity depends upon&#13;
its own price, the price of its substitute, and real and nominal world&#13;
incomes. Without making explicit assumptions regarding the functional forms&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INTERNATIONAL MONETARY FUND&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
of the production and utility functions, I assume that the demand functions&#13;
are homogenous of degree zero with respect to prices (no money illusion).&#13;
Therefore, the demand function of a primary commodity in log-linear form may&#13;
be specified as eq. (25) after due allowance has been made with regard to the&#13;
lagged responses:&#13;
logct     °     w(L)logpt + a2 2(L)logps     + 6 3  (L)logy&#13;
+ 64w 4(L)Dlogy + u,                                     (25)&#13;
where w(L)'s are distributed lag functions pt and ps      are, respectively, the&#13;
real prices 4/ of the commodity in question and its close substitute; y       is&#13;
the real world income; ut is a random error; and, Dlogyt is introduced to test&#13;
the sensitivity of the demand for primary commodities with,respective towthe&#13;
cyclical changes of real income. A priori, it is expected that this variable&#13;
will be more significant for the demand for metals than for other primary&#13;
commodities.&#13;
The Production Function&#13;
I postulate the following short-run world production function for a&#13;
primary commodity (time subscript are temporarily omitted for simplicity):&#13;
q = q(ur, vi, fi, t) + v,                                          (26)&#13;
where ur stands for the utilization rate of factor inputs, vi for a variable&#13;
input, fi for capital stock, and t for technological change. 5/ Because data&#13;
for ur, vi, and fi do not exist on a global level, rather than estimating (27)&#13;
directly I estimate its reduced form. The determinants of the -respective&#13;
augments in the production function are discussed below.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
Under certain assumptions, the optimal factor inputs may be expressed&#13;
as function of relative prices and output: 6/&#13;
vi = vi (, q),                                                     (27)&#13;
fi = fi (P, q),                                                    (28)&#13;
where P stands for the nominal price of the primary product, Pv for the price&#13;
of the variable input, and Pk for the price of the fixed input.&#13;
One typical feature of the supply of many primary commodities is the&#13;
lengthy time lag between the decision to embark on new investment and the&#13;
realization of increased output. This is particularly true for certain tree&#13;
crops such as cocoa, coffee, and rubber, as well as for metals like copper,&#13;
tin. Because the scope for adjusting output through changes of capital sock&#13;
is rather limited in the short-run, the rate of utilization of existing pro-&#13;
ductive capacity assumes the main burden of output adjustments. Consequently,&#13;
I postulate that the current utilization rate is a function of real commodity&#13;
prices prevailing currently and in the recent past:&#13;
ur = ur(w (L)p),                                                   (29)&#13;
5&#13;
where w (L) represents a distributed lag function with a relatively short lag.&#13;
s&#13;
The current level of the capital stock results from past investments&#13;
which, in turn, have been brought about by decisions to bring the capital&#13;
stock to the optimal level as indicated by (28). The current capital stock&#13;
can therefore be represented as a distributed lag function of the optimal&#13;
capital stock:&#13;
fi = wL(L)[fi(E, q)],                                              (30)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
where wL (L) represents a distributed lag function with a relatively long time&#13;
lag reflecting primarily the gestation period of investment.&#13;
Substituting eqs. (27) - (30) into (26) yields a reduced form&#13;
equation of production:&#13;
q = q(w (L)p    v   w (L)p   , q, t) + v.                        (31)&#13;
s    'Pv '        P&#13;
As an approximation to (31), I estimate the following log-linear&#13;
output equations:&#13;
t     y0+Y1w (L)ogpt+Y2wL(L)logpt+y3t+y4dq+vt                (32)&#13;
where Pt stands for the real commodity price, 7/ t for a time trend, dqt a&#13;
dummy variable, for unusual climatic changes or strikes, and vt for a random&#13;
error. The expected signs are:&#13;
YI, Y2' Y3 &gt; °-&#13;
To summarize, the complete model consists of the following equations, three of&#13;
which are stochastic equations:&#13;
price:&#13;
Dlogpt =        1Il +aI iogc t+PQ2(Elogp  -logp )+Pa log(i +s )&#13;
+Pa4logr +Pa t-plogh    t&#13;
or&#13;
Dlpt =     1logct+Oa2(Elogpt+ -logpt)+O-a3log(i&#13;
+Sca4logrt O9a5t -logh t-kDlogyt+Ut&#13;
consumption:&#13;
logc  =  0 + wI (L)logpt+"2 2(L)ps t  3 w (L)logyt&#13;
+04w 4(L)Dlogy +u-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
production:&#13;
logqt = y +Yws(L)logpt+ YA (L)logpt+Y3t+Y4dqt+v&#13;
stocks:&#13;
h   = h   +q -c -x&#13;
t t-1 t t t&#13;
Definition of variables:&#13;
Pt   =     real price, nominal commodity price deflated by the final&#13;
product price (pf)&#13;
Ct        -consumption&#13;
it   -     interest rate&#13;
St        storage cost&#13;
rt   =     risk premium&#13;
t    =     time trend&#13;
Yt   =     real world income&#13;
qt         output&#13;
dqt        dummy for unusual climatic changes or strikes&#13;
ht   =     stocks&#13;
xt         stockpiling by an international buffer stock agency or national&#13;
governments.&#13;
The exogenous variables are it, st, rt, t, y, dqt, and xt.&#13;
The model also determines the nominal commodity price (Pt) with a&#13;
given final product price (or world price, Pft).&#13;
II. Estimation Results&#13;
The model has been estimated by both the ordinary least squares (OLS)&#13;
and the instrumental variables (IV) methods with annual data for six primary&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
commodities: coffee, cocoa, rubber, copper, tin and sugar. The former method&#13;
has been employee predominantly, however, owing to the lack of the degrees of&#13;
freedom. Tests of the significance of the serial correlation of the random&#13;
error terms in the stochastic equations have also been performed. Variables&#13;
with theoretically unexpected signs have been deleted from the equations. The&#13;
estimated equations reported in the ensuing tables are the best equations&#13;
according to the conventional test statistics.&#13;
In the estimation process, I have omitted variables st and rt in the&#13;
price equation, owing to the lack of their measurable counterparts. I have&#13;
also replaced Elogpt+l-logpt by a dummy variable (dst) for capturing the&#13;
effects of speculation owing to the difficulties involved in modelling price&#13;
expectations0 In addition, the real price of substitute (pst) in the con-&#13;
sumption equation is omitted due to the lack of success in the empirical&#13;
analysis0 The world price (Pft) is approximated by the U.N. export price&#13;
index of manufactures in U.S. dollars (1975=1OO)o    Real world income (yt) is&#13;
derived from the real GNPs of 14 industrial countries with 1975=100. The&#13;
interest rate used is the Euro-Dollar London rate published in the&#13;
International Financial Statistics0 All nominal commodity prices are&#13;
expressed in U.S. dollars0 Data sources and constructions are given in the&#13;
Appendix0&#13;
In the case of the estimated price equations (Table 1), the adjusted&#13;
R2S are reasonably high, considering the fact that the dependent variable of&#13;
the regression is the rate of change of prices rather than the price level.&#13;
Among the explanatory variables, the rate of consumption is the only variable&#13;
which is significant for all equations, underscoring the importance of the&#13;
transaction demand for stock0 The coefficients of the stock variable are all&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
1~~~~  N    C    N~~~~~~~ &#13;
t  s   I  .J  N  N    e-  N    N&#13;
a  0:       .     .   e   CC)E.  .  .  0&#13;
+ +      &lt;    e   K    C      = &#13;
I t o                          v 0  4  C.&#13;
I    -.                      -4- _,.00Q:&#13;
_       ~~N N  *lh  .  rM  .  Ms  .  m _ -, &#13;
_        ~~..7:  . M  .    . _   U  8 e&#13;
O4-  O                  4- O-&#13;
49~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~    - -1&#13;
o ~   ~ I                 4;             v:: M-rX-  -  4&#13;
too              | e                    =    .  8_-&#13;
O 0 eex e rS &#13;
I  4-    N  * 0O .  c.8  S  .  O 0.  *8  .  854-8 &#13;
49 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~  4 &#13;
0  a                                      4~~4  4-co&#13;
I          0.                          84 .8 c  - _ &#13;
4-~ ~ ~ 4-  (e 0.  -D  -0s- .     _  X_    cSc&#13;
'_                                            co co F &#13;
U..  U.*  U     C  .                        .8.8  .&#13;
C  C      81~~C  4  41  41     4    a      -U&#13;
e,c 4 _                                CY, en  W  a,&#13;
+ +      '8           E7 e~ *            '        :&#13;
4-  4-      N                               :~ 0'  0'8to'l&#13;
a  o   e  o   &lt;  .  w  .   :  .  .e  .  S v~~~~~~~1.  .  c&#13;
'8  '8                            *8~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~4 4-&#13;
et            49 ec O  4 O  c O  ~  O-   51 C4@&#13;
W        .~4  co  cc  'c&#13;
USE-   00                                   84-UpQX &#13;
ele       ee  cs _ ! o vo e e Cel&#13;
O ~ ~ ~~c oA           C4 C-r .L  r4 .      _&#13;
-  ,D       0   ,             0                . 0 4&#13;
R  "   e  }   ^    ,,       4'    s0; e  SQ~~~~~~4-...  0&#13;
C  8      I   I                        4ClOw_..&#13;
c 0                                           -48__4- oes_9 &#13;
I           I4  1          4    4n  4 c&#13;
I  4                   80~~~~~~~~~~~~)4-W&#13;
C  O     4-  O  t?- ¢     4 _   _ .04*8  NM  MM ^ 0 1O&#13;
4-                   -    04. 3.  _I  .  N  .  0. *   11 ) -U&#13;
0  0l        U        *.  .0 o .   .N   .1   ' - 8 .   e&#13;
- e      o     _  o-  o-  c-o     - E -&#13;
C3  -                                 C  4-.8&#13;
o           _ o  e  v                           W&#13;
e ~   ~  ~ ~~ ~ ~~~ o7  4: ID  Wc  co       _&#13;
4-       .                               4-4-88~n IZ ul  o  I&#13;
~~~~~~M      U.C' ti  ,  .0  a,  OL  _  Co  _   'v e-v&#13;
O   4    4 .8 ¢  .                    8 W&#13;
o,o      U                        8 4 - o I  c u&#13;
O  ~~       c 8 * 0 * r8G4-4- oG              4 _ - &#13;
8 ~    ~~ ll  .0.0  .N _M                  . 0  4-X&#13;
0        O       .7 0r-  0. £      .^   .N   WU-&#13;
-        _            I O8 -                     8_e_ o_ &#13;
4-       -.  4o  4e    4 &#13;
C~~~4     0   4    4   4             4  _  4-  4- I t &#13;
o           4-  U'   MU'. 0-   00 ¢8  @UM N  O8C  _   2V  I&#13;
_ ~ ~  0  O   N1  .  -  .  -4  *  -4  .  M  .  ..4  *  C  _l 4-&#13;
8        O0      . _  ._  ._7  .0  ._   ._   4O C @&#13;
8        -  e    0'-  N^   Me   0  .s  0'    4 0  4-.&#13;
.. ~      ~~~ A. o e4-&#13;
I             4   M    M/ _     0          0 0 _ 5&#13;
IC 0     - 0- V  I- '8 &#13;
CI                   C4.                      8 0/o____C &#13;
1w &gt;{  E ~1  N   N   N   rs  ,^  &lt;n  l8e.8 _ e 8&#13;
1/    -I  8-. -          - u _'_     t &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
negative, as expected. And they are very significant, except for copper and&#13;
sugar. In the case of copper, however, when the negative trend variable is&#13;
deleted from the regression, this coefficient turns out to be significant and&#13;
much larger as the following equation shows:&#13;
Dlogpt = 2.3561ogc   - 0.8751oght - 0.348Dlogp t-13.666&#13;
(4.2)**       (3.9)**       (2.3)*         (3.2)**&#13;
2&#13;
p = 0.651, R    = 0.55, DW = 1.7&#13;
This indicates the possibility of multicollinearity between the trend variable&#13;
and the stock variable in this equation. The interest rate variable is sig-&#13;
nificant for coffee and cocoa, but its impact on other commodities is either&#13;
insignificant or in the wrong direction. Other things being equal, one&#13;
percentage decrease in the interest rate will make prices accelerate by about&#13;
0.8 percent for cocoa and 0.4 percent for coffee, owing to increased demand&#13;
for stock. The time trend is significant for cocoa, sugar, copper, and tin&#13;
but not for coffee and rubber. The price change lagged by one period is&#13;
significant for cocoa and copper, suggesting that the adjustment patterns of&#13;
prices for these commodities may be more complicated than those of others.&#13;
A zero-one dummy variables, dst' has been introduced in the price&#13;
equations for cocoa, rubber, tin, and sugar to catch the speculative demand&#13;
for stock, and it was found to be significant. This variable was assigned a&#13;
value equal to one for the years during which speculative activities were&#13;
deemed to have a significant impact on the commodity market: 1977 for cocoa,&#13;
1973 for rubber, 1974 for tin and sugar. The dummy variable in the coffee&#13;
equation, dicat, represents the small but significant positive effect of the&#13;
intervention made by the International Coffee Organization during 1964-1966&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
18 -&#13;
and 1970. For these years this variable has these estimated values: 0.14,&#13;
0.20, 0.13, 0.35; for all other years, it is assigned to be zero.&#13;
In the case of the consumption equation, both prices and income are&#13;
significant variables (Tables 2 and 2. (a)); the only exception is the price&#13;
variable In the sugar equation. Except for sugar for which a geometric lag is&#13;
estiirated, other commodities have polynominal lags. The effect of income on&#13;
consumption, in general, is much greater than that of prices, however. The&#13;
long-run income elasticities range from 0.4 (coffee) to 0.9 (copper), while&#13;
the long-run price elasticities range from 0.1 (copper) to 0.5 (coffee).&#13;
Further, the income effect is mostly concentrated on the current year, whereas&#13;
the price effect is delayed and distributed over time. The mean lag of the&#13;
price effect is estimated to range f*om one to three years (Table 2.(a)). For&#13;
copper and tin, the rate of change of income, in addition to the level of&#13;
income, exerts a significant effect on consumption in the short-run; according&#13;
to single equation estimates, over a period of two years the acceleration of&#13;
income by one percent will increase copper consumption by 3.8 percent and tin&#13;
consumption by 3.5 percent. This evidence demonstrates that the short-run&#13;
demands for copper and tin are more sensitive to the business cycles than&#13;
those of dther commodities included in this study.&#13;
For the production function, the effect of prices on output is found&#13;
to be both significant and distributed over time (Tables 3 and 3.(a)). If the&#13;
short-run price elasticities are measured by the cumulative impact of prices&#13;
on output over a period of two years after the initial change in prices, they&#13;
are rather small in magnitude-not greater than 0.2. While the short-run price&#13;
effect is small owing to the limited opportunity to expand output, the long-&#13;
run price effect, which manifests itself through the decision to invest in new&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
CN e  N     0                         4 J 4J 4&#13;
0 0&#13;
x&#13;
coC&#13;
00  ~ ~-H&#13;
0  to4&#13;
4-l)&#13;
s            " +ooo W00&#13;
co        "I         4c    49      m~ 4. V&#13;
0 :      .   9     .  t   .  .  .?   . %O     w  IC&#13;
0   Ai  Ca  in   0  en  0  47  P-1  Ln   co  P-4 fl,  %D  w~~~~~~C &gt; i&#13;
_~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C U) "-4&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
"4-4 J                                                     -&#13;
~~1 Xu   u      ec    4     4t   4c     4            4J0o&#13;
r~~~ZCz ^ &#13;
.. +                          u                             s0  e^r &#13;
c                                                  a      0  0nH o  O  .. r .  er   .  Ci&#13;
0           U)   0    0   * ".  *  es  . 0%    *   %0' *  s  iH&#13;
o  ',_t.0 4                           ~       .r-  '    *   O- i&#13;
=  4                                                       0 .   .&#13;
C               aa                    Ln uC %C            P&#13;
CO                                                          000  t Z °83z&#13;
cn        O~                            .           .-C&#13;
UZ a                                    .           .T CS  kwC&#13;
C~~~~~~~~~~~4         IC   4c                          O &#13;
u-I                                                 WO.~~~~~~~~~-T%C %  nr-  n c   e ~ 0-&#13;
04  0       t-I  r%.         en        0 0Ci&#13;
0;            C14                                       w eH  -C&#13;
0'        _l4  _1-                                           hi* &lt; &#13;
9-4,?     I~~~ Cim I060!                       0e &#13;
0       3                        C;                          U C .&#13;
E0 +4                49    -K    49    49    49             Z Ai h&#13;
u Oa                 0% -   4    en    0     4     %C    4i W  u &#13;
0          &gt;O  P-   41   XS ( .    . _l . *4 tO &gt; 1      a Q a,&#13;
_0                                                 0'      0.&#13;
o  4J           e94                                        4  C.'&#13;
0 _                                                     D C  0&#13;
1-           4   .                     4     4            U ) u)4&#13;
PC cd   I                                                C&#13;
o0       o                                             SW "Oc C&#13;
o   o   erl   . un   * H   . n   . H~~~~~* '  * if .H  .Ci.  h&#13;
0 /  C&#13;
-r4 4CiC&#13;
-  Q4 W /                                           O O&#13;
4.1  4.1           4      4V         441   4     4      hi4-JU&#13;
U).             .    %  /-                        a-  - &#13;
c: co 0                                             C X&#13;
44 U        - C           .4                     u  W&#13;
.14 X      , r.  P.  o  .     -    P.  ,   -  1   0&#13;
o  o   00  u u   7 *   %OC  It *  CO      N -t *       C~ 0 &#13;
H  /   rz~I  E  Q   I  I  lw   I  w   I   ; Iv&#13;
/   O  ~~~H  w  'A  co r.  cu  cc  rQ  rN  $W f &#13;
0/- E     4 u   .     .C on  WI   . n   e -   _  -&#13;
0      E.4   0- W  0%.d D0 0a C:           0 0    I U )&#13;
hi3             4~~~~~~  0p  0p 4  4   v 4 -  -  3V4&#13;
00.-I        4 O  O    -I r3         4 O _  L1 - r   0&#13;
0.      r   -~   0%0   r     r%0   -*.   _ - r-  r__r r^&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
02 c- rs &lt;   c   4   e  o       so3,&#13;
L6  o                                &gt;. &lt; X  Q)&#13;
0 c °.                               0  aJ &#13;
1.0  CN0  'T  CDJ  CN4  C N  C 00   cNi  0 4 3CC&#13;
(ct ~  ~~~ -4                               la 1 v ; W3&lt; &#13;
IVa                                 0C &#13;
0  C                                   4  mw &#13;
~~~~~~~~~ 0 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ 1&#13;
r.                         0~~~~~~~~~~~~4 co 0&#13;
-W  4J  4i  4i  -W.  0  .&#13;
tC~~~~1  0       C1 ..  ..  ...  ...  ... la  Q  o&#13;
J-)                                  -4 - 94 t o  t  V.  to 0  0 r   s   o  OE&#13;
0  w                w  w               Q4 .o  O&#13;
C~~~~~C   jj               J  4J  4J         D _I&#13;
C~~~- O0       C O  000    OO00    C3 O     C4.J,C&#13;
a  4 -4Ij     0-40   D-4G c i4  a40,-40J  -i t Co&#13;
D~~~~~0 6q  .                              1 &lt;  O&#13;
C12  C  ~~~~~~~~-  L  4enene i  S.d  m.d  S.  S-I  Q)C&#13;
c        0                                   030)S-a&#13;
' CCD42&#13;
o c n  _ a0 .&#13;
V40 s            O .     S.                 0H &#13;
Cu fi  -        o_      o_     ~    o -%  - '-  0 = u)&#13;
6-C                    °-_ C                    S-H &#13;
0)               0. *-.-                        o  Cw&#13;
t-i co           O                              zSO *H *   v &#13;
S~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~o aa .DJ&#13;
0-     '.0        4                           Cc &#13;
X au 0&lt;C: 0  N14               _.               C  .&#13;
&gt;* -r4        C)                 ~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~04.10   -&#13;
_ IXN.r_  un                                 08-  x _u i OX_ &#13;
_I H *_I _eO * 0.     O-             *  .,.* 141 0&#13;
4                       CD                   0 ooo _&#13;
X                                            gO  1 Q 4 &#13;
0   "4     C14 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0 -i C&#13;
0  C        '-L-.~~~~enON ~ 4Lnc  %D -.   -5  -&#13;
En        0.     -_.         C            0)&#13;
0~.              0'..i  on C                 0 i OiO&#13;
M~ ~ ~           I       II               &gt; os&#13;
-W 44                     0~Iu-            ~u &#13;
v-)  en  ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~.v4) Ci&#13;
0J~~~~~~~~                              0-4  0 a   y  L  n   n r- &#13;
_6)  _      -  ^4   .      -  %D-  ^  ^&#13;
O0        u-4.s  H C 1                 .0  4   24  1 4 . cq  H  0&#13;
01  0  O'.s O       0s  O  *  C     t C&#13;
0/' ON                          .0 tT  0  C Es   Es .   +&#13;
0'M 14..  0'.- Ntn e  C   , n  0' co-'   Cu  Cu$&#13;
Cu0            _         ~~~~14.  0J DcoCu0 -  4  .&#13;
*  It%-i CD  r-4  ~ S-4   W4.l co   U&#13;
1-I  ~~~~~~~~. 0   . C  0  *  *  *.  o.'. %O   C  Cu4  6&#13;
0'..o o'o-       0-o'o-       Cu 00CI)&#13;
S-  uC-4J &#13;
-~~~~   ..-.. ~~~~~~~~0            .)   .4 .1&#13;
u-4c.~~  C"  *  r-3  ~ 4   ~ 0- o '.00 -4 -0  S-i I&#13;
0         I    I   I       I      I0  e    3 -?4 &#13;
.0                                         CO  .00~~~0  a&#13;
.If5  0 ~  .J .    0  ..      .       .C0&#13;
E-4 ~ ~ 4-~J0 C&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-21 &#13;
CLJ  CN       C'J  CC         v4.&#13;
.a 0-H&#13;
00~~~~~~~~~~t CT       c&#13;
_11~~~~~~ Lf                  i'&lt; s  a'_ 0 o e n  -I&#13;
cn~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~Ue&#13;
V.  C     O OD   *  X  *            ( o (c .  -IC&#13;
.. C - Cto S    .  r-.  0o X0  CON oEn &#13;
a %$-  v~                         co - 'o&#13;
W o v X X O     no           co          -Hoou venwv&#13;
0   en ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~~~~~~  '&#13;
0   V )              z             #  _ * _ * VW C-&#13;
c  4C         c 4C  4c&#13;
. oo   4      *    ~ ~~*  #  *  ra  -t *&#13;
en  Cf   *  r-.'.o  &lt;   a  c' O  *&#13;
c~o       Od. o&gt;,                              f &#13;
o  e~                O r-.O      ~             °c&#13;
a,  CD          CN          m~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~11  %&#13;
U  '      0  1   '-                         On p&gt; °&#13;
qQ/O~~L            en   %O         co3&#13;
44   04                    CD       ~C) 4&#13;
+a                                         -i44~-&#13;
;~~~~ 0; e'         i'              Q i' @,g, &#13;
0~  *% -  D  4% 000  *-  C-4  *  .-  * c)&#13;
'a             *U  .  5         . O  .C40 .  *rL _O°&#13;
3        °'-  -4'-  o- °'-  0'-C  0'-  0-   Ur-a&#13;
44  C'1 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ -4 . 4  P-      ;CNW      A&#13;
CD~~~~~~~)&#13;
'a -. ~ ~ ~ ~ 4  K                       :&#13;
0~-  0-  0'   .0'  0-I   0'-440&#13;
CO  'K   CO   '   K         C) *YenC) -&#13;
en 0      CC        e-        0 * I- &#13;
C))-0        '   C    -  ~     . -4   .. *  0..w-4  L&#13;
to                              0~~~~~~~~~  -&#13;
.Cc                                      LWit.  n   -4&#13;
F-                      ITi &#13;
e4~~~e &#13;
4.1en4-i  C)                    I-~~~~~~~~~~~~~C  a  i&#13;
0&#13;
0   C)0W N   C)C C      -            a* '&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
G) 1         N     &lt;     c     &lt;    c &#13;
O0 0 `                                         f&#13;
0&#13;
;  o  W       ;           W      aa  ,4~~~~~~~~~~~~~4-  C&#13;
W J 0 1                                    _CJ  C &#13;
U3  W-&#13;
0                    _4 C C&#13;
4-i ~ ~ ~  ~    ~    ~    ~    W-&#13;
Ca      0   0 ..  .. &#13;
X   4 8     9  1; s O~     C4      C Cr o  x  o c*c&#13;
0 Un                                                   co C  0&#13;
-H       -i     .                                       AiO  V&#13;
fi             oi _                                   0&#13;
C2                                                 LJ_  : &#13;
0     0  ~~~~~~m0  *                              co -i &#13;
'.4  ~  4      .0                                 0   &lt;&#13;
co             o0 _                                     Q  .&#13;
U                                                    JI   C0&#13;
3                                                   U- o 4&#13;
C'0 0  _1 .                            3 0 .&#13;
DW O-1         cn         -Tw                           w r&#13;
0               % r-      -4 xD       0N Cw XO &gt;-t&#13;
-H  CCs           .        O        .  C)               -,-I4&#13;
-               -         O          O&#13;
-H              %-                                     U &#13;
T1 v         &lt; n         ur H        r: n         _ 0   '.0&#13;
E 1   xD   O . ~~r-    o           U' _§.          3 &#13;
J-J        .-~~~~~IT  nL  - *                     '-   U)&#13;
O~d                                                       J .  C   . n  @   w  :&#13;
o 4J                                                 W,_ I C)&#13;
'... 0                                                40  0&#13;
-4 -~~~~i                                    0   0).0*  -&#13;
'4) 0           .t' Oi- .-' Wr         .                  U)E 4&#13;
0 zi           0  *        0                          a) Ai Co&#13;
0C                                                    o4 en c  W&#13;
C)             C0-)        0n          0O C &#13;
OC                                    O             3'41 v4 0&#13;
-4.                                                0-   WE &#13;
04 U                                                 0J00  H&gt;~C&#13;
3            0           C -4  *    '4I *D        UC  Q L.&#13;
O W                        CNQ'~                      3-~O  C&#13;
E  0                                                A0 v-  *  -4  *  .W3&#13;
CUO                                                J-J ~WO .  e C  O a  O . 0  ^&#13;
N 0         , *t T  C)  0 *-  0 *O     1 3W&#13;
t:     N     H  .~C1    1-   .  o   .  O * O *    C &#13;
U)       .                      *~~~~~~~~~~~~~~'JC:  .&#13;
U) 3j&#13;
m O  -400  - 4  Cu  C  %C Ur-  0I  0  3)  C&#13;
_              -4 *        I *   0  *  0o:)  .  * . 0  C)  W&#13;
co        -4    M   ~~~~~~. ent   .0  *C'J  4  3 .6;  OM&#13;
x~~0-                   0'-  0'-   0'-'  0'-  o-a 0- O &#13;
W              Cn-~'  0o'  ui  1 - \0%  !'-.-°         '-': CD  C)  3&#13;
n~~~~~~~~L                               q        co o.o.~ v &#13;
-4  -4   n  *  0- en  10  *-  0D  *4  C) *1  0 4 : &#13;
CC              .     . C)  .   l C .  C C .  . *         C l)&#13;
0'-   0'-'   O-    '-  0'-C  0'-     W     Wa&#13;
C:)  C)  0    C)            m~~~~~~~~~~~~~.  '0 ,-I (J&#13;
~~~~~~4 e 0 Q&#13;
o                o  es  n  &lt; b ~~~~~~~~~~~~~ _ 0 c _~e  t   -&#13;
cn  0&gt;  X O                          1 n  xD ~ O4-43 r-W&#13;
o  o .   o . 0- o C-. o~- . t* o .  o-.  fie&#13;
0   .   0       * 0s * 0    o 0  o 0.  J3 &#13;
0o-   0o-' 0o-'   0'-   0'-  0'-    0) l. I-&#13;
l            l      S~~~ I-a oCU&#13;
1-4  00  I-T ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~~W~).-40&#13;
Ci) CD                                    - Q 31-&#13;
'0                                            c W:&#13;
0            2 ,    -                c        o-  o&#13;
_                  - &lt;&#13;
I-    0 o 0   u               0 o   0          w _-JCI)&#13;
4.1&lt;  3     3    3     3     3     3       -4 I.W E&#13;
0-  0   W     C    W     W           l.aWU&#13;
2  ta-    0    .      .C&#13;
0   0     0    3           0 '.4          3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
capital, is usually much greater. For instance, the long-run price elastic-&#13;
ity, is estimated to be 0.87 for coffee, 0.72 for rubber, and 0.74 for tin.&#13;
However, the estimated long-run elasticities for cocoa, copper, and sugar are&#13;
rather low: 0.27, 0.16, and 0.02 repectively. The estimated mean lag of the&#13;
long-run price effect on output is 4.9 years for coffee, 12.9 years for cocoa,&#13;
11.4 years for rubber, 4.3 years for tin, and 2.2 years for sugar. These&#13;
estimates seem plausible in that they provide a realistic estimate of the&#13;
gestation lag of investment for the respective commodities. The lagged output&#13;
variable in the coffee equation represents the two-year bearing cycle of&#13;
coffee production: Wickens and Greefield (1973).&#13;
The time trend variable, which represents the gradual effect of&#13;
technological advance on output, is very significant, except for tin. The&#13;
dummy variables in the output equations stand variously for the effect of&#13;
unusual climatic variations (coffee, cocoa), strike (copper), supply manage-&#13;
ment by the buffer stock agency (tin), and 1962 Cuban crisis (sugar). For&#13;
coffee, this variable represents the detrimental effects of Brazilian frosts,&#13;
which takes the values 0.31, 0.19, and 0.28, respectively, for 1964/65,&#13;
1970/71, and 1976/77. For cocoa, it has a value 0.20 in 1964/65, 0.10 in&#13;
1971/72, and -0.16 in 1976/77. The dummy variable in the copper equation&#13;
stands for the U.S. copper industry strike in 1967, with a value being equal&#13;
to one for that year. In the case of tin, the dummy variable has values 1.0&#13;
in 1958, 0.8 in 1959, 0.3 in 1960, 0.2 in 1969, and 0.2 in 1975, representing&#13;
the effect of export quotas managed by the International Tin Council. The&#13;
Cuban crisis dummy variable in the sugar output equation is assigned values&#13;
equal to one in both 1962 and 1963.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
III. Simulations Results&#13;
Aside from the evaluation of plausibility of the estimated models on&#13;
the basis of single equation results, these models are further tested in two&#13;
ways. First, they are dynamically simulated over their respective sample&#13;
periods.   Here, the purpose is to judge the performance of the endogenous&#13;
variables of a model when the model is simulated as a dynamic, simultaneous&#13;
equation system.   Second, their dynamic response mechanisms are evaluated by&#13;
imposing upon them external shocks. The results of these excercises&#13;
frequently provide the basis for improving upon or reconsidering the&#13;
specifications of the structural equations adopted on the basis of single&#13;
equation re7sults.&#13;
After many simulation runs, it wad decided that the price equations&#13;
estimated for sugar and copper in accordance with the disequilibrium specifi-&#13;
cation needed to be changed to the equilibrium specification as eq. 13(c),&#13;
while other structural equations estimated earlier should remain intact. The&#13;
best price equation simulated for sugar is&#13;
pt  =  0.0007c   - 0.0011h   + 0.1609Pf   + 12.4658D74 - 15.188&#13;
Pt     (4.4)**t    (5.7)** t   (3.3)** t    (3.7)**      (3.0)**&#13;
-2  =  0.88, DW = 2.2.&#13;
This equation is estimated in linear functional form since the log-linear&#13;
version has given rise to significantly greater simulation error. The&#13;
inclusion of the world price index, Pft, as an additional variable reflects&#13;
the departure from the assumption that both production and consumption are&#13;
homogenous of degree zero with respect to prices. Hence, the long-run&#13;
elasticity of the nominal sugar price with respect to the world inflation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
index is greater than unity. The copper price equation that has yielded the&#13;
best simulation performance is&#13;
logp  = 1.705logc   - 0.8581ogh   + 0.169dp66   - 8.359&#13;
(4.2)**       (43.)**  t    (1.6)         (2.6)*&#13;
P1 = 0.860, p2 = -0.222, R = 0.60, DW = 1.8.&#13;
(4.3)         (1.2)&#13;
In this equation, dp66t stands for the extraordinary influence of the Vietnam&#13;
war.  Although it is not very significant, it has reduced the simulation&#13;
errors in 1965 and 1966.      1 and p2 are the estimated coefficients of .a&#13;
second-order Markov process in the disturbance term.&#13;
The simulation performance of the respective estimated models are&#13;
evaluated by the average absolute errors (AAE). The AAE in percent is defined&#13;
as:&#13;
n&#13;
AAE    i     A_- A    /n x 100,&#13;
i=1&#13;
where A stands for actual value, A for predicted value, and n for the number&#13;
of periods over which the model is dynamically simulated. The AAEs f-or the&#13;
real commodity price (p), consumption (c), production, and stock (h) of each&#13;
commodity is tabulated in Table (4). And the graphs of the actual and&#13;
simulated values of these variables for each commodity are presented in the&#13;
Charts 1-6.&#13;
Both Table (4) and the Charts indicate that prices and stocks are/&#13;
less accurately predicted by the model than consumption and production. The&#13;
errors in prices are within a 15 percent range if sugar is excluded. With the&#13;
exception of coffee and tin, the errors of the stock variable are below 10&#13;
percent. The errors of both consumption and production are usually in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
Table 4. Average Absolute Errors&#13;
(In per cent)&#13;
Variable&#13;
Real price      Consumption       Production      Stock&#13;
Commodity                   (Pt             (ct)             (qt)           (h t)&#13;
(Simulation period)&#13;
Coffee                      13.2             6.0              4.5           19.2&#13;
(1960-77)&#13;
Cocoa                       10.5             1.6              2.0            6.2&#13;
(1964-77)&#13;
Rubber                      15.8             2.3              2.7            4.2&#13;
(1963-77)&#13;
Copper                      13.7             2.2               2.0           6.3&#13;
(1961-77)&#13;
Tin                         12.3             2.7              3.0           25.3&#13;
(1961-75)&#13;
Sugar                       24.4             1.4              1.2            7.8&#13;
(1961-.77)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
Chart 1. Coffee Model Dynamic Simulations, 1960-1977&#13;
( - Actual, .... Predicted)&#13;
MI C:  (S975 GONSTWNT DOLLLFiU   nRDUCICN&#13;
o                          0&#13;
(v~o                       o&#13;
Q~~~~~~&#13;
*                         0&#13;
o~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~II I II II II&#13;
CsC:&#13;
60 63 66 69 72 75         60 63 66 6    72 75&#13;
COWSUflP7CN                  5 'ODK&#13;
o                   0~~~~~~~~~~c&#13;
O&#13;
C:)~~~~~~~~~&#13;
co~~~~~..a*~*                           .&#13;
Cs~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
C3~~~~~ &#13;
80 63 66 89 72 75  60 m  U63 Bg  7S~~N&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
Chart 2.  Cocoa Model Dynamic Simulations, 1964-1977&#13;
(-    Actual, .    Predicted)&#13;
PRIxM   tl975 CON5T   DOLLm WrMDUCt I CN&#13;
C)                                       a&#13;
CD3&#13;
0C                                       o&#13;
68-                                      8-&#13;
64    67     70     73    76             64    67     70    73    76&#13;
CCNSUKFlT I N                               SIOCI(&#13;
83C9-                                     8-&#13;
Ln                            cm~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
zn&#13;
64     87    70    73     76             6486770 73 78&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
Chart 3. Rubber Model Dynamic Simulations, 1964-1977&#13;
(-  Actual, .... Predicted)&#13;
MU C  (1S75 CON9TNC DDLLM$          RMDUCGtON&#13;
CD~~~~~&#13;
Lnr&#13;
O0O                                                  ,.&#13;
8-&#13;
C3&#13;
63   66   69  72   75         63    66   69  72   75&#13;
O                              0&#13;
C3~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~I' &#13;
u:) 0&#13;
63S          97   75      a     36       S      7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
Chart 4. Copper Model Dynamic Simulations, 1961-1977&#13;
( -  Actual, . Predicted)&#13;
MI CE  (1375 GON91f1Tf DDLLU)           MaDUG7tCN&#13;
o                                O&#13;
C4&#13;
In                             v~~&#13;
o                                o&#13;
61  64  67   70  73  76          61  64  67  70  73   76&#13;
C~4SUfl?TI ~4                SIOD&#13;
o                       0~~~~~&#13;
*                        S~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
8-                       8-~~~~~~~~~c&#13;
0                        0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~:&#13;
Lx,&#13;
61    046        07      6616                77     37&#13;
00~ ~ ~~~&#13;
1:0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~:&#13;
C3C&#13;
0~ ~~~~~&#13;
61    846    7   7      66            8    77       37&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
Chart 5. Tin Model Dynamic Simulations, 1961-1975&#13;
(- Actual, .  Predicted)&#13;
MI iE (1375 CONST DOLL=             FPRMCTIN&#13;
CD                            C&#13;
*                            c&#13;
8-                            8-&#13;
0                            0&#13;
*3                           O&#13;
u,8~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~u&#13;
C3                            C:3&#13;
_l~~~~~~~~~~~~ S&#13;
61 '64   67  70  73          61   6i  67  70   73&#13;
C04SUHTI 0N                    SIOCK&#13;
C.3~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~U&#13;
CD~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.&#13;
U~~~~~~'&#13;
6                        O~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
CD~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
St  64  67  70  73     61   61   67  70  73~~~~I.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
Chart 6. Sugar Model Dynamic Simulations, 1961-1977&#13;
(- Actual, .... Predicted)&#13;
N      t 175 COX=W DDLL                     M    tN&#13;
O                                  C&#13;
O                                  8&#13;
61   64  67   70  73   76          61  64   67   70  73  76&#13;
UNSUMION0S&#13;
co&#13;
*i                                 0&#13;
4_          1 I3 I  IIII&#13;
61   64  67   70  73 76            61  64   67  70   73  76&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
range of 2 to 3 percent. Although the errors in prices and stocks are sig-&#13;
nificant, the models are generally successful in tracing some significant&#13;
turning points. While the model can be enlarged to incorporate more struc-&#13;
tural details in a particular commodity market, the fact that the model is&#13;
small does not seem to be an important limiting factor for the model's&#13;
simulation performance for these variables. 8/ For instance, a much larger&#13;
world copper model has yielded within-sample forecasting errors for prices and&#13;
stocks, respectively, of 16 percent and 20 percent over the same simulation&#13;
period 1961-1977: Kellman (1978). These errors are greater than those&#13;
obtained by the smaller model simulated in this study.&#13;
Although each model is small, consisting merely of three stochstic&#13;
equations and one identity, its dynamic structure is nevertheless complex as&#13;
can be seen from the high order distributed lag functions in the production&#13;
and consumption equations. Further, the model is not strictly linear because&#13;
of the stock supply equation. Hence to asses the model's dynamic behavior,&#13;
the responses of the endogenous variables with respect to changes in some of&#13;
the major exogenous variables in the model are analyzed through simulation&#13;
over the sample period. Three types of dynamic responses are computed and&#13;
these relate, respectively, to a 1 percent permanent increase in the real&#13;
world income (yt), a 1 percent permanent increase in the world price level&#13;
(Pft), and a 1 percent permanent reduction in the commodity output.     For&#13;
coffee and cocoa, two additional exogenous shifts are made and these pertain,&#13;
respectively, to a 1 percent permanent increase in the interest rate and a 1&#13;
percent temporary drop in output during the initial period of simulation. The&#13;
dynamic impacts of these exogenous variables are evaluated by the correspond-&#13;
ing percentage changes in the real commodity prices over the simulation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
period. The numerical results may be called elasticities since changes in the&#13;
exogenous variables are prescribed to be one percent in all cases. The&#13;
results of these computations are reported for the six commodities in Tables&#13;
5-10.&#13;
In the case of coffee, in response to the increase in world income&#13;
the real price rises immediately as a result of both a higher demand for stock&#13;
and a simultaneous reduction in the supply of stock. The price increae&#13;
reaches its first peak during the second period when it is 1.6 percent higher&#13;
than the level reached without the increase in income. As the higher price&#13;
gradually works to dampen consumption and stimulate more output, the price&#13;
advance slows down and eventually reverse itself; the price is in fact reduced&#13;
by 2.6 percent during the 6th year. Lower prices, then, increase consumption&#13;
and hence the demand for stock, while at the same time they discourage produc-&#13;
tion and hence reduce the stock supply. Consequently, the existence of excess&#13;
demand bids up prices sharply. From there originates the next price cycle.&#13;
The price cycles tend to repeat themselves as alternate excess demands and&#13;
supplies develop, but their amplitudes are increasingly damped, indicating a&#13;
stable system. It seem that there exist two types of cycles-: one with a&#13;
periodicity of around 2-3 years and the other with a periodicity of 6-7&#13;
years. The shorter cycle may reflect the short-run output responses with&#13;
respect to price changes while the longer cycle may indicate the underlying&#13;
investment cycle of coffee production.&#13;
Both an increase in the world inflation index and a reduction in the&#13;
world coffee output yield an adjustment pattern in the real commodity price&#13;
similar to that of an increase in world income, indicating that the inherent&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
Table 5. Price Elasticities: Coffee&#13;
Exgnous&#13;
vrables&#13;
World         World                      Interest&#13;
income       inflation     Output          rate           Output&#13;
shifts in      \       (permanent    (permanent   (permanent     (permanent      (temporary&#13;
exogenous variabl       increase)     increase)    reduction)     increase)      reduction)&#13;
1                0.97         1.33          0.52         -0.26             0.53&#13;
2                1.63         2.22          1.07         -0.08             0.81&#13;
3                1.59         2.25          1.20          0.06             0.75&#13;
4                1.25         1.92          1.07          0.05             0.48&#13;
5               -1.25        -0.57         -1.29         -2.22            -1.94&#13;
6               -2.55        -1.77         -2.38         -3.31            -3.17&#13;
7                1.32         2.03          1.43          0.55             0.70&#13;
8                2.00         2.68          2.10          1.27             1.39&#13;
9                1.32         2.00          1.52          0.74             0.76&#13;
10                0.21         0.96          0.66         -0.04            -0.22&#13;
11                2.03         2.88          2.83          2.24             1.79&#13;
12                0.45         1.39          1.59          1.09             0.40&#13;
13               -0.09         0.60          0.53          0.02            -0.31&#13;
14               -0.32         0.16         -0.20         -0.75            -0.73&#13;
15               -0.29         0.13         -0.33         -0.90            -0.76&#13;
16                0.30         0.78          0.42         -0.15            -0.10&#13;
17                0.73         1.29          1.02          0.47             0.41&#13;
18                0.44         1.11          0.96          0.42             0.22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
Table 6. Price Elasticities: Cocoa&#13;
\ xgenlous&#13;
\vrables&#13;
World         World                       Interest&#13;
after the   \              income       inflation     Output          rate            Output&#13;
shifts in       \        (permanent    (permanent    (permanent    (permanent       (temporary&#13;
exogenous variable K      increase)     increase)    reduction)     increase)       reduction)&#13;
1                 2.80          2.48          2.48          -0.10             2.48&#13;
2                 1.99          2.03.         2.75          -0.13             0.35&#13;
3                 1.52          1.80          2.97          -0.05            -0.38&#13;
4                 0.79          1.09          2.12           0.02            -0.78&#13;
5                 0.86          1.03          1.73           0.03            -0.21&#13;
6                 0.80          0.92          1.48           0.05            -0.10&#13;
7                 1.12          1.19          1.71           0.01             0.18&#13;
8                 1.32          1.35          1.81          -0.09             0.22&#13;
9                 1.35          1.40          1.92          -0.11             0.12&#13;
10                 1.18          1.40          2.35           0.15            -0.08&#13;
11                 1.04          1.27          2.20           0.18            -0.12&#13;
12                 1.17          1.21          1.66          -0.14            -0.01&#13;
13                 0.81          0.92          1.45          -0.07            -0.31&#13;
14                -0.37         -0.05          0.68           0.23            -1.11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
Table 7. Price Elasticities: Rubber&#13;
Exogenous&#13;
ariables&#13;
Period                         World                World&#13;
after-the                      income              inflation             Output&#13;
shifts in                     (permanent          (permanent           (permanent&#13;
exogenous variables            increase)           increase)            reduction)&#13;
1                       2.82                3.42                 3.34&#13;
2                       3.86                5.48                 5.67&#13;
3                       2.36                4.20                 4.64&#13;
4                       0.07                1.13                 1.53&#13;
5                      -0.21                0.10                 0.24&#13;
6                       1.65                2.13                 2.13&#13;
7                       3.37                4.70                 4.84&#13;
8                      2.95                 4.82                 5.21&#13;
9                       1.09                2.56                 3.01&#13;
10                     -0.56                -0.01                 0.27&#13;
11                     -1.47                -1.70                -1.62&#13;
12                     -1.96                -2.71                -2.78&#13;
13                     -2.06                -3.08                -3.24&#13;
14                     -1.42                -2.39                -2.60&#13;
15                     -0.45                -1.09                -1.28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
Table 8. Price Elasticities: Copper&#13;
\Exogenious&#13;
\ ariables&#13;
Period   \                      World                World&#13;
after the    \                  income              inflation             Output&#13;
shifts in        \            (permanent           (permanent           (permanent&#13;
exogenous variables            increase)            increase)            reduction)&#13;
1                       3.49                 1.54                 2.80&#13;
2                       4.38                 1.60                 4.25&#13;
3                       4.57                 1.50                 4.80&#13;
4                       5.07                 1.55                 5.53&#13;
5                       4.94                 1.35                 5.68&#13;
6                       4.35                 1.09                 5.21&#13;
7                       4.49                 0.92                 5.60&#13;
8                       3.49                 0.82                 4.21&#13;
9                       2.98                 0.80                 3.46&#13;
10                       2.72                 0.86                 2.98&#13;
11                       2.58                 0.92                 2.70&#13;
12                       2.86                 0.98                 3.02&#13;
13                       3.54                 1.02                 3.95&#13;
14                       3.52                 1.04                 3.90&#13;
15.                      3.02                 1.04                 3.22&#13;
16                       3.03                 1.03                 3.26&#13;
17                       3.17                 1.02                 3.47&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
Table 9. Price Elasticities: Tin&#13;
Exogenous&#13;
variables&#13;
Period    \                      World                 World&#13;
after the                        income               inflation             Output&#13;
shifts in                      (permanent            (permanent           (permanent&#13;
exogenous variables             increase)             increase)            reduction)&#13;
1                        1.18                 0.83                   0.35&#13;
2                        2.40                  2.13                  1.30&#13;
3                        3.32                 3.70                   2.81&#13;
4                        3.36                 4.53                   3.93&#13;
5                        2.29                 4.24                   4.29&#13;
6                        0.24                 2.56                   3.41&#13;
7                       -2.36                -0.27                   1.28&#13;
8                       -4.68                -3.49                  -1.65&#13;
9                       -5.21                -5.40                  -4.00&#13;
10                       -3.57                -5.06                  -4.68&#13;
11                       -0.77                -3.15                  -3.93&#13;
12                        2.74                -0.01                  -1.93&#13;
13                        6.34                 4.05                   1.26&#13;
14                        9.19                 8.36                   5.22&#13;
15                       13.59                17.86                  14.88&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
Table 10. Price Elasticities: Sugar&#13;
x xogenous&#13;
\ariables&#13;
PDeriod   \World                                       World&#13;
after the     \                  income               inflation              Output&#13;
shifts in         \             (permanent            (permanent           (permanent&#13;
exogenous variables             increase)             increase)             reduction)&#13;
1                         8.07                 2.86                  13.48&#13;
2                         8.66                 1.87                  12.65&#13;
3                         8;85                 1.50                  12.06&#13;
4                        13.77                 1.43                  18.36&#13;
5                        17.97                 1.26                  23.50&#13;
6                        20.61                 1.12                  26.64&#13;
7                        21.58                 1.03                  27.72&#13;
8                        19.61                 0.96                  25.06&#13;
9                        16.32                 0.98                  20.76&#13;
10                        14.64                 1.03                  18.56&#13;
11                        13.98                 1.07                  17.69&#13;
12                        13.24                 1.11                  16.70&#13;
13                        11.68                 1.17                  14.68&#13;
14                         7.19                 1.17                   9.13&#13;
15                        15.46                 1.41                  19.65&#13;
16                        20.51                 1.41                  26.14&#13;
17                        23.96                 1.47                  30.64&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
dynamic response mechanism of the model is invariant with respect to the&#13;
changes in the exogenous variables.&#13;
As far as the dynamic adjustment patterns of prices in response to&#13;
exogenous stimuli are concerned, what can be said of coffee can largely be&#13;
applied to all the other commodities. One typical feature is the existence of&#13;
self-generating, endogenous price cycles, although the periodicities and&#13;
amplitudes of the price cycles vary among the commodities. Also, the magni-&#13;
tudes of the price responses are ususally many times greater than those of the&#13;
original stimuli, vividly revealing the unstable nature of the commodity price&#13;
dynamics. Judging from the price resonses, the world sugar market may be the&#13;
least stable one.&#13;
For each commodity the size of the price responses resulting from&#13;
changes in real world income and supply is not drastically different. For&#13;
cocoa, rubber, and sugar, the impact of supply variations is greater. For&#13;
copper and tin,- the effects of world income are greater during the initial few&#13;
periods, but are eventually outweighed by the supply variations. The impact&#13;
of world inflation is greater than that of the world income and of supply&#13;
variations in the case of coffee, but is much smaller copper and sugar.      For&#13;
cocoa, rubber, and tin, the impact of world inflation is comparable to that of&#13;
world income and of production variations. In the case of coffee and cocoa,&#13;
the interest rate effects are generally smaller than those of the other&#13;
exogenous stimuli. And the effects of a temporary drop in output trail those&#13;
of a permanent reduction in output.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
IV. Summary and Conclusion&#13;
This paper presents a simultaneous equation model of price and&#13;
quantity adjustments in world primary commodity markets, which depicts the&#13;
behavioral relationships between commodity's real price, consumption, produc-&#13;
tion, and stocks on a global level. Aside from certan dummy variables&#13;
representing weather variations, strikes, etc., the major exogenous variables&#13;
of the model are real world income, buffer stock interventions, the rate of&#13;
interest, and for the determination of the nominal commodity price, the world&#13;
price level. The model is formulated in a disequilibrium framework, with the&#13;
price adjustment mechanism being of the Walrasian type.&#13;
The empirical analysis of the model is carried out with the annual&#13;
data of six primary commodities: coffee, cocoa, rubber, copper, tin, and&#13;
sugar. Equations of price adjustments, stock demand, consumption, and produc-&#13;
tion are specified and estimated. The empirical models turn out to be systems&#13;
of difference equations, usually of a very high order because of the existence&#13;
of long distributed lags in the production and consumption equations. Dynamic&#13;
simulations tests over the sample period show that the respective model trace&#13;
the movements of the endogenous variables fairly well, although significant&#13;
errors occur for the price and stocks of a few commodities. When the models&#13;
are shocked by shifts in the exogenous variables, the dynamic responses of&#13;
prices confirm the commonly observed self-generating and recurring boom-and-&#13;
bust cycles. On the whole, the models fairly adequately capture the dynamics&#13;
of the world commodity markets studied and therefore can be a useful tool for&#13;
policy analysis and forecasting. Insofar as the models are used for fore-&#13;
casting commodity prices, the advantage of their being small becomes apparent&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
because besides being easier to maintain, a small model usually contains less&#13;
exogenous variables which have to be forecast in advance.&#13;
The empirical part of the models can be improved in a number of&#13;
ways. First, the determination of the observed stocks should be bettered.&#13;
The implicit working assumption that the observed stocks are always equal to&#13;
those supplied is too restictive and may well be the main cause for the large&#13;
simulation errors of this variable in the coffee and tin models. Recent&#13;
advance in the estimation and testing of a disequilibrium system may provide&#13;
useful references for the estimation of a disequilibrium commodity model:&#13;
e.g., Ito and Ueda (1979), Quandt (1978). Modeling world commodity markets by&#13;
a disequilibrium system may prove to be a more interesting and fruitful&#13;
alternative to the current practice of modeling commodity markets as an&#13;
equilibrium system, especially when quarterly or monthly time series are&#13;
employed.&#13;
Second, the dynamics of price expectation should be given more&#13;
attention than they have received in this paper. The main difficulty in this&#13;
area is that the influences of price expectations on commodity markets appear&#13;
to have been sporadic rather than systematic. Stable price expectations&#13;
functions are perhaps not easy to formulate and obtain.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
FOOTNOTES&#13;
1/ The real price of a commodity is defined as the ratio of the nominal price&#13;
to a certain deflator.&#13;
2/ It should be noted that neither (10-a) nor (10-b) has a stochastic term.&#13;
3/ I assume, without the loss of generality, that there are only two types of&#13;
primary inputs. Labor input is also ignored.&#13;
4/ It is assumed that the price of the final product (world income), Pf, is.&#13;
the deflator used for obtaining the real prices.&#13;
5/  It is assumed that in the short-run the intensity of factor utilization is&#13;
the same for all factor inputs.&#13;
6/ There assumptoions are (1) the production function is homogenous of degree&#13;
zero, (2) perfect-competition exists in both product and factor markets.&#13;
Whether relative price and output have the same effect on demand for input&#13;
depends upon the form of the production function. For instance, if the&#13;
production function is Cobb-Douglas the effect is the same. If it is CES,&#13;
the effect will be different.&#13;
7/ It is assumed that changes in the factor prices (Pv, Pk) parallel those of&#13;
the final product price Pf. Therefore, output will be a function of the&#13;
real price deflated by Pf and other relevant variables.&#13;
8/ This is not to deny the usefulness of a large structural model in that it&#13;
can provide extra information that cannot be provided by a small model for&#13;
potential users of the model.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
References&#13;
Adams, F. G., and Jere R. Behrman, Econometric Models of World Agricultural&#13;
Commodity Markets: Cocoa, Coffee, Tea, Wool, Cotton, Sugar, Wheat, Rice&#13;
(Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1976).&#13;
Ito, T. and Kazno Ueda, "Tests of the Equilibrium Hypothesis in Disequilibrium&#13;
Econometrics: An International Comparison of Credit Rationing",&#13;
Discussion Paper No. 76-119, October 1979, Center for Economic Research,&#13;
Department of Economics, University of Minnesota.&#13;
Kaldor, N., "Speculation and Economic Stability", Review of Economic Studies,&#13;
Vol. 7. Reprinted in N. Kaldor, Essays on Economic Stability and Growth&#13;
(London: Duckwath, 1961)&#13;
Kellman, M., "An Integrated Econometric Analysis of Integrated Primary&#13;
Commodity Market and Goal Attainment in Developing Countries: The World&#13;
Copper Model", for Agency for International Development, Project No.&#13;
913-11-995-057, "Integrated Primary Commodity Markets and Economic&#13;
Development", Wharton Econometric Forecasting Associates, Inc. August,&#13;
1978.&#13;
Kohn, Meir, "Competitive Speculation", Econometrica, Vol. 46 (September 1978),&#13;
pp. 1061-76.&#13;
Labys, Walter C., "Commodity Markets and Models: The Range of Experience",&#13;
in Stabilizing World Commodity Markets, F. Gerard Adams and Sonia A.&#13;
Klein, editors (Lexington, Massachusetts, 1978), pp. 3-34.&#13;
Quandt, R. E., "Tests of the Equilibrium vs. Disequilibrium Hypothesis",&#13;
International Economic Review, Vol. 19, June 1978, pp. 435-452.&#13;
Tims, Wouter and Shamsher Singh, "A System of Linked Models For Commodity&#13;
Market Analysis - Report on work done by the World Bank", 1973-1976, memo.&#13;
Wickens, M. R., and J. N. Greenfields, "The Econometrics of Agricultural&#13;
Supply:  An Application to the World Coffee Market", Review of Economics&#13;
and Statistics, November 1973, pp. 433-440.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
APPENDIX&#13;
Data Sources and Construction&#13;
The exogenous variables common to all the models are real world&#13;
income (yt), world price (Pft), interest rate (it), and time trend (t). The&#13;
real world income is an index with 1975=100, which is constructed in the&#13;
following way: First, the annual rate of change (in percent) of the real&#13;
world income is derived as a weighted average of the annual rates of change&#13;
(in percent) of real GNPs of 14 majoy industrial countries. Each individual&#13;
country weight is the share of each country's nominal GNP (in U.S. dollars) in&#13;
the total nominal GNP (in U.S. dollars) of these countries. The industrial&#13;
countries are United States, Canada, Japan, Austria, Belgium, Denmark, France,&#13;
Germany, Italy, Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, Switzerland and United Kingdom.&#13;
Then an index of the level of real world income was derived from its annual&#13;
rate of change.&#13;
The world price is also an index with 1975=100, which is derived from&#13;
the quarterly unit value index of manufactured goods exports published in the&#13;
Monthly Bulletin of Statistics by the United Nations. The interest rate used&#13;
is the Euro Dollar rate (London) in percent per annum. Data for both the Euro&#13;
Dollar rate and industrial countries' GNPs are obtained from the International&#13;
Financial Statistics. The trend variable has value 1 in 1946 and increases&#13;
linearly over time. The commodity-specific data sources are described below:&#13;
Cocoa:    The major source is Cocoa Market Report, No. 281, July 1978,&#13;
published by Gill &amp; Duffus Group Limited, London. Consumption (ct) and&#13;
production (qt), refer respectively to world grindings and net world crop of&#13;
cocoa beans. Consumption, production, and stocks (ht) are expressed in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
thousands of metric tons.   The world cocoa price is the price of cocoa beans -&#13;
fair fermented main crop Ghana, spot new year in cents per lb.     The price data&#13;
for the period 1946-47 - 1956-57 are obtained from Cocoa Statistics, Gill &amp;&#13;
Duffus Group Limited, London, England December 1975, and for the period 1957-&#13;
58 - 1976-77 from the International Monetary Fund. All the data pertain to&#13;
crop year (October/September) estimates.&#13;
Coffee:   The data are those estimated by U.S. Department of Agriculture&#13;
and International Coffee Organization. The production, consumption, and stock&#13;
data are in thousands of bags of 60-kilograms and are crop year&#13;
(October/September for most countries) estimates. Consumption is estimated as&#13;
the sum of net exports and consumption in producing countries (the difference&#13;
between production and exportable production). The world coffee price is&#13;
represented by the weighted averages of the prices, spot New York, for&#13;
unwashed arabica, robusta, other mild arabica, and Colombian mild arabica,&#13;
expressed in cents per lb and as October/September crop year estimate. The&#13;
data source for the prices is International Monetary Fund.&#13;
Rubber:   The data for natural rubber are obtained from Rubber Statistical&#13;
Bulletin, October 1978, published by International Rubber Study Group,&#13;
London. The production, consumption, and stock data are in thousands of&#13;
metric tons. The world natural rubber price is represented by the spot price&#13;
in Singapore, f.o.b., in bales, No. 1 rolled smoked sheets (RSS), expressed in&#13;
U.S. cents per lb. All data are calendar year estimates.&#13;
Copper:   The refined production and consumption data exclude those of&#13;
central planned economies and are in thousands of metric tons. The world&#13;
coffee price is represented by that of the LME Cash Settlement Wirebar, in&#13;
U.S.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
cents per lb. The data are obtained from World Metal Statistics and are&#13;
calendar yeSr estimates.i&#13;
Tin:       The data are from Tin Statistics, 1965-75, Trade in Tin 1960-74,&#13;
and various issues of Statistical Bulletin (International Tin Council,&#13;
London). The production and consumption data exclude centrally planned&#13;
economies and all quantitites are in thousands of metric tons. The tin price&#13;
is represented by that of LME cash, standard tin (99.75 percent), and is in&#13;
U.S. cent per lb.&#13;
Sugar:    The production, consumption, and stock data are obtained from&#13;
the 1977 Sugar Yearbook published by the International Sugar Organization and&#13;
are in thousands of metric tons. The price data, in U.S. cents per lb, is the&#13;
weighted average of the free market price, U.S. producer price, and E.E.C.&#13;
price as estimated by the International Monetary Fund. The data are calendar&#13;
year estimates.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG 3881.5 oW57 W67 N0OA99 Co3&#13;
HWAg ERH-CHENG.&#13;
A ... MODEL OF PRICE AND&#13;
QUANTITY ADJUSTMENT ..0&#13;
nnTMADV rnMMnDTTY MARKETSO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554932">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1981/10/1554932/simultaneous-equation-model-price-quantity-adjustments-world-primary-commodity-markets
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1981/10/1554932/simultaneous-equation-model-price-quantity-adjustments-world-primary-commodity-markets</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1981/10/1554932/simultaneous-equation-model-price-quantity-adjustments-world-primary-commodity-markets</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/23/000178830_98101903412458/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/23/000178830_98101903412458/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-09-23T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1981-10-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            A simultaneous equation model of price and
            quantity adjustments in world primary commodity markets
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper presents a dynamic
            simultaneous model of price and quantity adjustments in
            world primary commodity markets. The model is formulated in
            a disequilibrium framework emphasizing particularly the role
            of price adjustment. In addition to the price equation,
            commodity consumption and production equations are also
            specified. The empirical analysis of the model is carried
            out with the annual data of six primary commodities: coffee,
            cocoa, rubber, copper, tin and sugar. This includes the
            estimation of price, consumption, production equations, the
            simulation tests of complete structural models for these six
            commodities, and the derivation of dynamic responses
            (measured by elasticities) of commodity prices to changes in
            world income, world inflation and commodity outputs. Dynamic
            simulations strongly confirm the commonly observed
            self-generating and recurring boom-and-bust cycles of
            primary commodity prices. This finding lends credibility to
            the models constructed.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            A simultaneous equation model of price and
            quantity adjustments in world primary commodity markets
        </docna>
        <display_title>A simultaneous equation model of
            price and quantity adjustments in world primary commodity markets</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1981/10/1554932/simultaneous-equation-model-price-quantity-adjustments-world-primary-commodity-markets</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Markets and Market Access,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Access to Markets,Consumption</subtopic>
        <teratopic>International Economics and Trade</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>HWA, E.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903412458</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Other agriculture</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 499</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>International Economics and Trade</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Agriculture, fishing, and forestry</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Buffer stocks; Commodities; Commodity
            markets; Commodity prices; Consumption; Economic
            equilibrium; Income; Interest rates; Mathematical models;
            Models; Price elasticity; Production; Simulation; Supply
            &amp; demand
            aggregate demand,business
            cycles,cd,commodity markets,commodity prices,competitive
            price,demand functions,disequilibrium,Economic
            Analysis,elasticities,elasticity,empirical
            analysis,endogenous variables,equations,excess
            demand,exogenous variables,functional forms,GNP,GNP
            deflator,income,income effect,inflation,interest rate,market
            equilibrium,metals,price adjustment,price adjustments,price
            changes,price effect,price elasticities,price
            fluctuations,price index,production function,quotas,real
            income,risk
            premium,sales,spread,stocks,substitutes,technological
            change,Time series,utility function,utility functions
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP499</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technological Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>MM</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>CoC</ml:concept><ml:concept>Continuum of Care (CoC)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Econometrics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technology Transfer and Diffusion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Maternal Mortality and Morbidity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Continuum of Care</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>