<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Notes on the Analysis of Capital Flows&#13;
to Developing Nations&#13;
and the "Recycling" Problem&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 476                             SW       P476&#13;
August 1981&#13;
Prepared by: Ralph C. Bryant [Consultant]&#13;
Development Policy Staff&#13;
Copyright © 1981&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the authc  F7W AE9  .  W&#13;
and should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated  tXLE   C O Py&#13;
organizations, or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations,&#13;
or to any individual acting in their behalf, nor to the officers, trustees,&#13;
or other staff members of the Brookings Institution.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 476&#13;
August 1981&#13;
NOTES ON THE ANALYSIS OF CAPITAL FLOWS&#13;
TO DEVELOPING NATIONS AND THE "RECYCLING" PROBLEM&#13;
A Background Study for World Development Report 1981&#13;
This paper summarizes and then criticizes the conventional analysis&#13;
of the interrelations between financial markets in the industrialized countries&#13;
(the North) and capital flows to the developing nations (the South). The prox-&#13;
imate purpose of the paper is to clarify concepts and analytical perspectives.&#13;
Its ultimate purpose is to suggest how a study of capital flows to the South&#13;
should be integrated into an overall macroeconomic analysis of the effects of&#13;
the economic environment in the North and in the oil-producing countries on&#13;
the South's prospects for development.&#13;
Prepared by:  Ralph C. Bryant&#13;
(The Brookings Institution)&#13;
Consultant&#13;
Development Policy Staff&#13;
Copyright ® 1981&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C, 20433&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Contents&#13;
Page&#13;
I. Introduction   ....................................................       1&#13;
The Balance-of-Payments Identity for the South     ....    .........  6&#13;
Analytical Components of the Availability Variant     ....   ......  8&#13;
Partial Equilibrium Analysis of Capital Flows to the South ...     15&#13;
Energy Prices and the "Recycling" Problem     .......    ...........  23&#13;
The Requirements Variant of the Conventional Analysis      ... 28&#13;
II. Defects of the Conventional Analysis     ............................ 33&#13;
Balance-of-Payments Identities for the World as a Whole       ....  34&#13;
Saving-Investment Identities    ...............................    36&#13;
Consequences for the South of External Economic Events      ..... 41&#13;
An Increase in Oil Prices         ,..               .         41&#13;
Changes in Private-Sector Investment in the North       ..... 44&#13;
Other Events in External Goods Markets     ......    ..........  48&#13;
External Shocks Originating in Financial Markets      ... 50&#13;
Exogenous Shocks Originating Internally in the South       .  .. 53&#13;
Some Conclusions ........................................... 54&#13;
IV. The South and the Recycling Problem     .............................    57&#13;
Which Aspects of Recycling Deserve Priority? ............... 57&#13;
Adjustment or Compensation for the South? .................. 61&#13;
Figures&#13;
1. A Partial-Equilibrium Framework for Analyzing&#13;
the Participation of the South in World Financial Markets ...... 17&#13;
2. Consequences of an Increase in North Output Caused&#13;
by an Unexpected Spurt in Investment in the North     ....    .........  20&#13;
3. Consequences of a Tightening of Monetary Policy in the North      ....   22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. INTRODUCTION&#13;
Economic growth in a developing country is strongly influenced by&#13;
economic conditions in the rest of the world. Analysis of these&#13;
influences, by World Bank economists and others, typically assumes that&#13;
the home nation is too small to have a perceptible impact on the global&#13;
economy as a whole. Thus the analysis treats all economic events&#13;
outside the nation as exogenously determined.I&#13;
To simplify still further, the analysis is divided into separate&#13;
parts, customarily carried out by different economists. One part&#13;
examines the financial influences channeled through the capital account&#13;
in the balance of payments -- for example, the consequences for the&#13;
nation-s external borrowing of changes in the cost and availability of&#13;
credit in foreign financial markets. A second part examines the&#13;
real-sector influences channeled through trade in goods and services --&#13;
for example, the pull on the nation-s exports from economic activity in&#13;
the rest of the world.&#13;
Because all of the external influences are taken as exogenously&#13;
determined and because the financial and real-sector influences are&#13;
studied separately, analysts typically pay little attention to the&#13;
1. This approach is an application of the "small and open paradigm."&#13;
For a discussion of this and other possible paradigms for analyzing the&#13;
economic relationships of a nation or region with the rest of the&#13;
world, see Ralph C. Bryant, Money and Monetary Policy in Interdependent&#13;
Nations (Washington, D. C.: Brookings Institution, 1980), chap. 10.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2&#13;
internal consistency of the financial and real-sector assumptions made&#13;
about the rest of the world. Worrying about that consistency is left&#13;
to economists who specialize in studying macroeconomic developments in&#13;
the industrial economies. Typically, however, those economists have&#13;
little contact with the analysts specializing in the study of the&#13;
developing economies.&#13;
The simplifying assumptions and procedures used in this&#13;
conventional analysis can-lead inadvertently to misleading conclusions&#13;
even in the case of a single developing nation. But the analysis can&#13;
be especially problematic if applied to developing nations as an&#13;
aggregate.&#13;
These notes identify the main problems that can arise and indicate&#13;
in schematic form an analytical framework that would help to avoid&#13;
them. For World Bank economists or others to implement a framework of&#13;
this sort in a practical, fully operational form would be ditticult if&#13;
not impossible at the present time. Nonetheless, there is value in&#13;
providing a sketch of this framework. It may suggest guidelines for&#13;
the allocation of Bank research resources in future years. At a&#13;
minimum, understanding of deficiencies in current analytical procedures&#13;
is a precondition for remedying them.2&#13;
To keep these notes focused on the essential points overlooked in&#13;
the conventional analysis, the discussion is based on-a schematic frame&#13;
of reference that abstracts from the actual national economies that&#13;
constitute the global economic system in 1981. In particular, I&#13;
(Footnote 2 appears on the following page.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3&#13;
postulate a partitioning of the world into only three regions. The&#13;
region of primary interest, the "South," is assumed to be composed&#13;
entirely of developing countries. It imports manufactures, a&#13;
substantial proportion of its total energy requirements, and other&#13;
tradable goods; it wishes to be a net borrower from the rest of the&#13;
world to facilitate more rapid economic development; as a result of&#13;
past borrowing, it has a sizable net debtor position vis-a-vis the rest&#13;
of the world. The second region, the "North," is composed only of&#13;
industrialized countries. The bulk of financial intermediation in the&#13;
world is assumed to be carried out by banks and other intermediaries&#13;
located in the North. The North is a net importer of energy. The&#13;
remaining region, "PEX," includes only countries that are large-scale&#13;
2. The problems with which I am concerned in these notes are typical,&#13;
I believe, of most analyses of the impact of higher oil prices on&#13;
developing nations and the so-called recycling problem. Several&#13;
examples of this "conventional analysis" have recently been prepared&#13;
under the auspices of the World Bank. These papers include "Prospects&#13;
for Capital Flows to Developing Countries," paper prepared by the World&#13;
Bank staff in summer 1980 (Revised draft, July 1, 1980) and the World&#13;
Development Report for 1979 and 1980 (New York: Oxford University&#13;
Press). The background analysis for the World Development Report is&#13;
prepared with the aid of the "global modeling exercise"; for a&#13;
description of this analytical apparatus, see S. Gupta, A. Schwartz,&#13;
and R. Padula, "The World Bank Model for Global Interdependence: A&#13;
Quantitative Framework for the World Development Report," Journal of&#13;
Policy Modeling, Vol. 1, No. 2 (1979), and R. Cheetham et al., "The&#13;
Global Framework," World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 355 (September&#13;
1979). I mention these World Bank papers here not because they deserve&#13;
to be singled out for criticism (indeed, these papers are probably&#13;
better than others in the genre), but rather because they have served&#13;
as the proximate stimulus for the writing of these notes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
exporters of petroleum. Consumption of manufactures and other&#13;
non-petroleum tradable goods in PEX is largely met by imports from the&#13;
North and South. Financial assets of PEX residents are either&#13;
"domestic" claims on other PEX residents or "international" claims on&#13;
the financial intermediaries in the North. The economies of the three&#13;
regions, taken together, constitute "the world economy."&#13;
This schematization neglects the centrally planned economies. It&#13;
does not distinguish between developing nations that do and those that&#13;
do not have to import the bulk of their energy needs. In other&#13;
respects, however, the North, PEX, and the South may be considered&#13;
approximations for the dominant "North" subgroup of countries in the&#13;
Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD), the&#13;
capital surplus oil-exporting countries of the Organization of&#13;
Oil-Exporting Countries (OPEC), and the residual aggregation of all&#13;
other, primarily developing, countries.&#13;
To simplify the exposition further, I shall treat each of the&#13;
three regions as if it were a homogeneous entity internally. I shall&#13;
speak loosely of governmental economic policy in the regions (as though&#13;
each region had a single government that could coherently formulate and&#13;
implement a region-wide policy). And I shall assume that accurate&#13;
statistical data are available to enable the construction of&#13;
income-and-product and balance-of-payments accounts for each region.3&#13;
3. Obviously, the schematic simplifications used in these notes&#13;
suppress many problems that analysts cannot ignore when studying the&#13;
interactions of developing nations with the rest of the global economy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
5&#13;
Stated in terms of the schematic context just described, the&#13;
proximate concern of these notes is the net flow of capital to the&#13;
South from the North and (indirectly) from PEX. I summarize and then&#13;
criticize the conventional analysis of the interrelations between&#13;
financial markets in the North and the capital account in the South's&#13;
balance of payments.&#13;
As suggested above, answers to questions about capital flows are&#13;
not sought for their own sakes. Hence my ultimate purpose in these&#13;
notes is to indicate how a study of capital flows to the South should&#13;
be integrated into an overall macroeconomic analysis of the effects of&#13;
the economic environment in the North and PEX on the South's prospects&#13;
for development.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6&#13;
II. AN OUTLINE OF THE CONVENTIONAL ANALYSIS&#13;
The more common form of the conventional analysis of the effects&#13;
of the global economic environment on developing countries may be&#13;
labeled the "availability" variant. An alternative version is a&#13;
"requirements" variant.   In principle, the conventional analysis can be&#13;
conducted using either variant. Some examples of the analysis --&#13;
including the World Bank global modeling exercise -- seem in practice&#13;
to be a subtle, but not always self-conscious, blend of both variants.&#13;
For clarity, the discussion here at first concentrates on the&#13;
availability variant. Later on, I indicate how the requirements&#13;
variant differs from the availability variant.&#13;
The Balance-of-Payments Identity for the South&#13;
It will be helpful to refer to a simplified representation of the&#13;
balance-of-payments identity for the South.   Accordingly, let p&#13;
represent a price index for the South's exports of goods and services&#13;
and x a quantity index, so that X    p (x) is the value of South exports&#13;
(to the North and PEX); let p   and m represent price and quantity&#13;
indexes such that M    p (m) is the value of the South-s imports of&#13;
goods and services; let D represent net income payments by the South to&#13;
the rest of the world (gross debt service on outstanding external&#13;
borrowings less interest income on South assets held abroad); let ODA&#13;
represent official development assistance from the North and PEX to the&#13;
South (grants and other official transfers plus official development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
7&#13;
lending); let AR denote the net change in the South's official reserve&#13;
assets (where a positive value for AR indicates an increase in reserve&#13;
assets, a negative value a decrease); and let AK denote the net value&#13;
of all capital flows in the balance of payments other than official&#13;
development assistance and the change in the official reserve position&#13;
(hence AK includes net official borrowing from the "world" capital&#13;
market located in the North and net changes in the assets and&#13;
liabilities of private-sector residents of the South vis-a-vis the rest&#13;
of the world). All symbols represent values expressed in the currency&#13;
unit of the North ("dollars").&#13;
Given these definitions, the balance of payments of the South,&#13;
expressed in the currency unit of the North, may be written:&#13;
(1)      P (x) - p (m) - D + ODA + AK - AR - 0.&#13;
The division of the balance of payments into the current and capital&#13;
accounts -- the latter by definition equal, with opposite sign, to the&#13;
former -- is then:&#13;
(2)     CB S px(x) - pm(m) - D    -(ODA + AK - AR).&#13;
The definition of the current balance in equation (2) is the version&#13;
"excluding official transfers" (since official grants are included&#13;
together with other development assistance in ODA).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
8&#13;
The magnitude (ODA + AK - AR), the negative of the balance on&#13;
current account, is often termed the "net resource balance" or the "net&#13;
transfer of resources." It is conventionally thought to be a key&#13;
magnitude in the analysis of the South's prospects for growth.&#13;
Analytical Components of the Availability Variant&#13;
The availability variant of the conventional analysis of the&#13;
effects of the global environment on developing countries has, in&#13;
essence, three parts:&#13;
*The first is concerned with capital flows in the South's&#13;
balance of payments and with related financial phenomena.&#13;
*The second focuses on the South's trade links with the&#13;
rest of the world.&#13;
*The third takes the results of the first two parts and relates&#13;
them to analysis of the South's "domestic" economy.&#13;
In what follows I sometimes use the adjectives "financial," "trade,"&#13;
and "domestic" to refer to these three parts or the analysts&#13;
responsible for conducting them.&#13;
The goal of the first (financial) part is to prepare a&#13;
"conservative" projection of the net resource balance and the value of&#13;
net payments for debt service. In particular, the financial analyst&#13;
formulates a judgment (or accepts a judgment already made by South&#13;
policymakers) about the change in the South's net reserve position that&#13;
is tolerable or desirable.4 He makes the best possible projection of&#13;
4. The projected value for AR may be specified directly. Or it may&#13;
result more indirectly from the operation of a policy rule (for&#13;
example, a rule postulating that the ratio of reserves to imports&#13;
should follow a specified path).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
9&#13;
official grants and development lending to the South, conditional on&#13;
exogenous assumptions about government policies in the North and PEX.&#13;
And he makes the best possible projection of other net capital flows&#13;
into the South, conditional on exogenous assumptions about borrowing&#13;
rates, availability constraints, and other characteristics prevailing&#13;
in "world" financial markets. Like the projection for AR, the&#13;
projections for ODA and AK must also be informed by judgments about&#13;
what is tolerable or desirable for the South.&#13;
The projections for ODA, AR, and AK can be described as&#13;
conservative" in the sense that the analyst leans in the direction of&#13;
prudence when making the estimates. For example, he will adopt a&#13;
somewhat cautious view of the current and prospective creditworthiness&#13;
of the South in world financial markets and will, if anything, slightly&#13;
underestimate the amount of borrowing that is tolerable or desirable&#13;
for the South at the given exogenous conditions in world financial&#13;
markets. The combination of his projections for ODA, AR, and AK&#13;
enables the financial analyst to generate a projection for the South's&#13;
net resource balance (current account).&#13;
Finally, the analyst makes a projection of income payments for&#13;
debt service (and the net value of other payments and receipts of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
10&#13;
investment income). This projection of D takes into account the&#13;
outstanding stock of borrowings and the interest rates (past and&#13;
prospective) associated with that stock. The projection for D makes&#13;
use of the same exogenous assumptions about conditions in world&#13;
financial markets as those used to develop the projections for the&#13;
capital-account items proper.&#13;
The first-part analyst may have a relatively sophisticated&#13;
framework for modeling financial markets in the North, for PEX&#13;
participation in those markets, and for the interrelationships of those&#13;
markets and capital flows into the South. Alternatively, the analyst&#13;
may have to resort to loosely grounded judgments. In either case, the&#13;
conditions in Northern financial markets are analyzed from a&#13;
partial-equilibrium perspective; however detailed the analysis of&#13;
Northern financial markets, there is no explicit analysis of the&#13;
relationships between financial conditions and real economic activity&#13;
in the North and PEX.&#13;
The second (trade) part of the conventional analysis is conducted&#13;
independently of the first part. Its goal is a projection of those&#13;
flows in the current account of the South-s balance of payments that&#13;
are chiefly determined by economic developments outside the South. In&#13;
particular, the trade analyst makes the best possible projections of&#13;
the prices at which the South will be able to import goods and services&#13;
from the North and PEX (p ), the prices at which the South will be able&#13;
to sell its goods and services in the rest of the world (p ), and the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
volume of the South's exports (x) that will be associated with those&#13;
prices.  The projections for p   and p  together provide a projection of&#13;
the South's "terms of trade." The projections for p and x together&#13;
provide a projection of export receipts (in North currency units).&#13;
When making these projections, the second-part analyst may use&#13;
simple assumptions about output, price, and trade developments in the&#13;
North and PEX. Alternatively, he may use a sophisticated model that&#13;
explains the output, prices, and trade of the North and PEX in terms of&#13;
exogenous assumptions about governmental policy actions and nonpolicy&#13;
disturbances originating in the North and PEX. No matter how detailed&#13;
his model, however, the typical trade analyst concentrates only on&#13;
goods markets and the real side of economic developments. He does not&#13;
concern himself with financial-market conditions in the North.&#13;
The third (domestic) part of the conventional analysis begins with&#13;
the results of the first two parts. In effect, the domestic analyst&#13;
inserts the financial and trade projections into the South&#13;
balance-of-payments identity and thereby obtains a projection of the&#13;
"permissible" volume of imports:&#13;
(3)     m = (l/pm) p[(x) - D + (ODA + AK - R).&#13;
(The circumflexes over a variable, here and later, denote projected&#13;
values.) This magnitude of imports is permissible in the sense that the&#13;
South can prudently plan to purchase m of imports given the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
12&#13;
(conservative) projections made for its terms of trade, the volume of&#13;
its exports, its debt service obligations, and its net resource&#13;
balance.  To plan to import more than m without simultaneously changing&#13;
one or more of the projections on the right-hand side of equation (3)&#13;
would violate the ineluctable straitjacket of the balance-of-payments&#13;
identity. A plan to import less than m logically requires, for&#13;
example, a smaller capital inflow than LAK or a smaller change in&#13;
reserves than AR.&#13;
The third-part analyst is assumed to have available some sort of&#13;
model describing the South's domestic economy. As with the other&#13;
analytical steps in the procedure, this model may be detailed and&#13;
sophisticated or merely a back-of-envelope sketch. Regardless of its&#13;
nature, however, the model will indicate that output growth and price&#13;
performance in the South are dependent on -- constrained by -- the&#13;
South's imports.&#13;
The basic idea of the relationship between permissible imports and&#13;
possible output growth can be expressed as follows:5&#13;
(4)  y    f m&#13;
_ i ~~~~~~~~~/ ,,.j. &#13;
5. The function (4) is derived from -- speaking loosely, is a&#13;
distillation of -- the analyst's model of the South's domestic economy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
13&#13;
As this function emphasizes, attainable output growth in the&#13;
South, yS, is determined by many factors in addition to the aggregate&#13;
volume of imports. Changes in the relative prices of imports and goods&#13;
produced domestically in the South can lead to substitution of the&#13;
latter for the former by producers and consumers. Government policy&#13;
actions in the South -- for example, exchange-rate policy and tariffs,&#13;
subsidies, and quotas on external transactions -- can influence the&#13;
degree of this substitutability.    Many other types of government&#13;
policy actions can significantly foster (or impede) growth in the South&#13;
for any given volume of imports. Furthermore, a variety of nonpolicy&#13;
exogenous events originating in the South -- for example crop failures,&#13;
unusually favorable weather conditions, innovations in the application&#13;
of technology, changes in political conditions -- can cause South&#13;
output to be higher or lower for any given volume of imports. The&#13;
ability to import goods from the rest of the world, therefore, may not&#13;
be the most binding constraint on output growth in the South; domestic&#13;
constraints may be considerably more important.&#13;
Nevertheless, despite all the qualifications, there remains an&#13;
important causal link running from imports to output. Given all its&#13;
6. Policies that induce purchases of goods produced domestically&#13;
instead of imports -- more broadly, policies that induce both producers&#13;
and consumers to substitute nontraded goods for tradable goods -- are&#13;
often described as "switching" policies. To be successful, switching&#13;
policies usually require a change in the relative prices of tradable&#13;
and nontraded goods.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
14&#13;
other determinants, output can be higher the higher is the volume of&#13;
imports. And given all its other determinants, output must be lower if&#13;
the volume of imports declines.7&#13;
The domestic analyst, making use of the relationships schematized&#13;
by expression (4), can therefore supply policymakers in the South with&#13;
a judgment about how severely the South will be constrained by the&#13;
economic environment in the North and PEX. Then, given the level of&#13;
imports projected as permissible, the policymakers decide on the policy&#13;
actions deemed most suitable in the circumstances. To the extent&#13;
thought possible and prudent, policymakers will wish to offset a&#13;
lower-than-desired level of imports with compensating policies that&#13;
encourage high output.8&#13;
Suppose events occur in the outside world that cause the financial&#13;
analyst or the trade analyst to alter his projections in such a way&#13;
that the domestic analyst, using equation (3), calculates a lower level&#13;
of permissible imports. Then the domestic analyst and the South's&#13;
7. The causal link from imports to output is fairly straightforward&#13;
for natural resources that are not produced domestically but are&#13;
essential as an intermediate input for domestic production (for&#13;
example, petroleum) or for sophisticated manufactures that are capital&#13;
goods in domestic production but cannot yet be produced themselves&#13;
domestically (for example, machine tools). But the general point&#13;
applies even for imports that are "non-essential" consumption goods.&#13;
8. For expositional brevity, I focus on output in the South.&#13;
Analogous statements apply to the consequences of the outside&#13;
environment for other South variables that are ultimate targets of&#13;
economic policy -- for example, inflation and employment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
15&#13;
policymakers will know either that output in the South must be lower&#13;
than earlier hoped or that more strenuous policy actions in the South&#13;
must be taken sufficient to offset the downward influence on output&#13;
stemming from the lower level of permissible imports.9&#13;
Partial-Equilibrium Analysis of Capital Flows to the South&#13;
Given the preceding sketch, consider now in more detail the&#13;
financial part of the analysis dealing with capital flows.&#13;
The financial analyst's projection of official development&#13;
assistance will probably be little affected by his views about interest&#13;
rates and other credit conditions in Northern financial markets. The&#13;
more important determinants of ODA will be aid policies in the North&#13;
and perhaps also the level of economic activity in the North.&#13;
The analyst must make the projections D and \R jointly with the&#13;
projection  K so that the interrelations among the three variables are&#13;
taken into account. For example, appraisals by Northern financial&#13;
intermediaries of the South's creditworthiness will pay special&#13;
attention to the level of the South's reserves; the analyst's judgment&#13;
9. Suppose that, with the previous projection of permissible imports,&#13;
policymakers in the South had chosen settings for their policy&#13;
instruments designed to attain the best, feasible combination of all&#13;
their policy objectives. It will then be costly for the policymakers&#13;
to take additional policy actions to try to offset the effects on&#13;
output of the new projection for permissible imports; such changes in&#13;
instrument settings entail a lower probability of attaining other&#13;
policy objectives.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
16&#13;
about the change in reserves that is tolerable or desirable will&#13;
therefore have to be made simultaneously with the projection for net&#13;
new borrowing. Of course the higher the projection for outstanding&#13;
borrowing, the higher must be the analyst's projection for debt-service&#13;
payments.&#13;
For the discussion here, therefore, it is appropriate to&#13;
concentrate on the projection for net capital flows, AK.&#13;
To make projections for AK, the financial analyst relies on a&#13;
partial-equilibrium analysis of lending and borrowing in Northern&#13;
financial markets. Several elements in this analysis are portrayed&#13;
graphically in Figure 1. The right-hand panel of the figure shows the&#13;
total ("world") amounts of borrowing and lending on the horizontal axis&#13;
(measured, say, in trillions of dollars). The BB curve represents the&#13;
aggregate "demand" by borrowers of all three regions; the LL curve&#13;
indicates the amounts that the financial intermediaries are willing to&#13;
lend at different interest rates. The left-hand panel pertains only to&#13;
borrowing demand by the South (the B B curve) and the "supply" of&#13;
lending to the South by the intermediaries. Amounts of borrowing by&#13;
the South along the horizontal axis in the left-hand panel are measured&#13;
on a different scale (say, billions of dollars) from the scale used in&#13;
the right-hand panel.&#13;
Because the South is assumed to be "small" and to take conditions&#13;
in Northern financial markets as exogenously given, the South's demand&#13;
for borrowing can change (shifts in the BSBs curve in the left-hand&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
17&#13;
Figure 1&#13;
A PARTIAL-EQUILIBRIUM FRAMEWORK FOR ANALYZING&#13;
THE PARTICIPATION OF THE SOUTH IN WORLD FINANCIAL MARKETS&#13;
Rate                                              Rate&#13;
of                                                of&#13;
Interest                                          Interest&#13;
L&#13;
s&#13;
S    5  ~   ~  mutofbroigTtl                                               ol     orwn&#13;
Amouthof borrowing                                 Tortalr world  ia borrowing&#13;
(Scale: billions of dollars)                        (scale: trillions of dollars)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
18&#13;
panel) without causing a perceptible change in the world level of&#13;
interest rates paid by prime Northern borrowers.     The supply curve of&#13;
lending to the South, however, is not drawn as horizontal throughout&#13;
its range. Even with an unchanged world interest rate of ro,&#13;
variations in the quantity of South borrowing will generate changes in&#13;
the risk premium demanded by Northern intermediaries for lending to the&#13;
South; in particular, the risk premium (the difference between r and&#13;
0&#13;
r0 in the left panel) will start to widen sharply if the South&#13;
increases its borrowing beyond a certain point. (Variations in the&#13;
risk premium are synonymous with changes in the intermediaries-&#13;
appraisal of the South's creditworthiness.)&#13;
Using a more or less sophisticated framework of the sort sketched&#13;
in Figure 1, the analyst proceeds to assess the consequences of various&#13;
events occurring in Northern financial markets and their effects on&#13;
capital flows to the South. For example, suppose the analyst is told&#13;
by his real-sector colleagues who forecast international trade that&#13;
they are raising their projection for output in the North because they&#13;
have received new information about an unexpected spurt in&#13;
private-sector investment in the North. Borrowing -- more generally,&#13;
the volume of financial intermediation -- is positively related to the&#13;
10. In effect, the assumption is that the South-s borrowing is such a&#13;
small part of total borrowing that a shift of B BS in the left panel&#13;
produces only a negligible shift of BB in the right panel.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
19&#13;
real-sector activity that it finances. The financial analyst will thus&#13;
raise his projections of the demand for funds by borrowers in the&#13;
North. In terms of the figure, the increased Northern demand shifts&#13;
the BB curve to the right (from B Bo to BIBI -- see Figure 2).&#13;
When the added pressure is put on Northern financial markets,&#13;
there is an upward movement in the "world" interest rate (from r     to r&#13;
in the right panel of Figure 2) while the total volume of lending&#13;
expands (from q   to qI).  The supply of funds available to South&#13;
borrowers, however, is reduced (the relevant "supply" schedule shifts&#13;
from L L   to L1L s); given the South's demand schedule for borrowing&#13;
s S&#13;
B B , the interest rate on loans to the South (which includes the risk&#13;
premium) adjusts upward to r5 and the quantity of borrowing falls (from&#13;
1&#13;
S S&#13;
q to q1).&#13;
Hence the rise in the world interest rate, and the corresponding&#13;
interest rate paid by the South, generates a projected value for AK in&#13;
the South-s balance of payments that is smaller than the projected&#13;
value prior to the expansionary change in Northern output. Given his&#13;
new projection for capital flows, the analyst will probably also wish&#13;
to reconsider his judgments about AR. The reduction in AK, however,&#13;
will typically be larger in magnitude than an offsetting change (if&#13;
any) in AR, so that the net resource balance will fall (the&#13;
current-account deficit will be smaller). Even though the analyst will&#13;
also shade downwards his projection for debt service, the new&#13;
projection for the net sum of ODA + AK - R - D that is inserted into&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
20&#13;
Figure 2&#13;
CONSEQUENCES OF AN INCREASE IN NORTH OUTPUT&#13;
CAUSED BY AN UNEXPECTED SPURT IN INVESTMENT IN THE NORTH&#13;
Rate                                                   Rate&#13;
of                                                     of&#13;
Interest                                               Interest&#13;
Lo~~~~~~~~~~~L&#13;
SS&#13;
Amount of borrowing                                 Total world borrowing&#13;
by the South                              inl Northern financial markets&#13;
.^csIe: billions of dollars)                      (scale: trillions of dollars)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
21&#13;
equation (3) will be a smaller magnitude than before, and hence will be&#13;
assumed to imply a lower level of permissible imports. The analyst&#13;
thus will conclude that the tightening of conditions in financial&#13;
markets in the North has adverse consequences for output in the South.&#13;
Figure 3 illustrates a second type of event occurring in the North&#13;
with consequences for capital flows to the South. Suppose the analyst&#13;
receives new information that leads him to forecast tighter monetary&#13;
policy in the North (say, central bank open-market operations that&#13;
reduce the supply of bank reserves). One consequence of the tighter&#13;
monetary policy in the North is a reduction of the amount of lending&#13;
that Northern intermediaries are willing to undertake (a leftward shift&#13;
of the LL curve in Figure 3 from L L   to L2L2).   As the restrictive&#13;
monetary policy in the North begins to affect real-sector spending&#13;
decisions, the desired volume of borrowing will also begin to contract&#13;
(a leftward shift of the BB curve). The "world" level of the interest&#13;
rate may move to a new higher level (from r    to r2); the total volume&#13;
of lending and borrowing will contract (from q    to q2).&#13;
In this second example, as in the first, the supply curve of funds&#13;
to borrowers in the South shifts adversely. Thus the interest rate on&#13;
S     S&#13;
lending to the South rises from r   to r ,while the volume of lending&#13;
S S~~~ &#13;
shrinks from q to q2.&#13;
In the conventional analysis, therefore, the consequences for the&#13;
South of this second development in external financial markets are&#13;
regarded as analogous to the consequences in the first case. The&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
22&#13;
Figure 3&#13;
CONSEQUENCES OF A TIGHTENING OF MONETARY POLICY IN THE-NORTH&#13;
(OPEN-MARKET SALE OF SECURITIES BY MONETARY.AUTHORITIES IN THE NORTH)&#13;
Rate                                           Rate&#13;
of                                             of&#13;
Interest                                       Interest&#13;
I                                                     t&#13;
% dr~                                             LZ    to&#13;
Amount of borrowing                             Total world borrowing&#13;
by the South                            in Northern financial markets&#13;
(scale: billions of dollars)                   (scale: trillions of dollars)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
23&#13;
analyst reasons that net capital flows to the South will be reduced and&#13;
that the smaller value of AK means a smaller value for the net resource&#13;
balance, which in turn will mean a smaller volume of permissible&#13;
imports and hence a lower level of output in the South.&#13;
The two examples given here are representative of the method of&#13;
analysis that is implicit if not explicit in conventional projections&#13;
of capital flows to the South. The analysis is a partial-equilibrium&#13;
examination of world financial markets. In general, any events outside&#13;
the South that lead to an increase in the cost of borrowing by the&#13;
South (or a reduced availability of funds not directly reflected in&#13;
borrowing costs) are viewed as adverse for the South because they lead&#13;
to a reduction in net capital inflows. Reductions in capital inflows&#13;
are viewed as adverse because it is assumed that, by reducing the net&#13;
resource balance, they necessarily reduce the value of 'm, and hence&#13;
reduce output growth y . Any events in world financial markets that&#13;
lower the cost of borrowing to the South and increase the magnitude of&#13;
net capital inflows are interpreted as unambiguously favorable --&#13;
because they increase the level of permissible imports and thereby&#13;
permit a greater expansion of output.&#13;
Energy Prices and the "Recycling" Problem&#13;
The preceding sketch of the conventional analysis is, I believe, a&#13;
faithful account of how capital flows to the South have been&#13;
conceptualized for many years. But the large oil-price increases in&#13;
1973-74, and in 1979-80, have given a new prominence to such analysis.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
24&#13;
To highlight the role of petroleum prices and petroleum imports,&#13;
let p   and m   represent price and quantity indexes for the South's&#13;
petroleum imports. (The South is assumed here to import a major&#13;
fraction of its energy requirements.) Let p     and m   represent price&#13;
and quantity indexes for all other imports such that the values of the&#13;
two components of imports are M v p     (m ) and M  ' pm(m ) and the&#13;
p    mp   p       o    m &#13;
total value is M      M  + M . The volume of imports is the sum of m   and&#13;
p    o                                          P&#13;
m . The price index for all imports is a weighted function --&#13;
represented here as p   = f(p   , p  ) -- of the price indexes for the&#13;
two disaggregated components. Let the symbol NRB represent the net&#13;
resource balance (the current-account balance with sign reversed).&#13;
Then the expression for permissible imports in equation (3)becomes:&#13;
F&#13;
(3a)        +--------                 px(x) - D + NRB-&#13;
(p3  MO      f(mp Io       [ x&#13;
The first point emphasized in the conventional accounts of the&#13;
impacts of the energy crisis on the oil-importing developing countries&#13;
is the suddenly worsened outlook for the balance of payments and for&#13;
growth. The dilemma facing the South is evident in equation (3a).&#13;
Higher prices for petroleum dramatically reduce the purchasing power of&#13;
the South's export receipts and its net receipts of foreign exchange&#13;
from the rest of the balance of payments. In the absence of changes in&#13;
those receipts [the second set of brackets in equation (3a)], the loss&#13;
in purchasing power (the first set of brackets) sharply reduces the&#13;
total volume of permissible imports. The problem is compounded further&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
25&#13;
by the relatively low price elasticity and the relatively high income&#13;
elasticity of the demand for energy. If it should not be feasible in&#13;
the short run to curtail petroleum imports, if little can be done by&#13;
the South to increase export receipts, and if it should be judged&#13;
imprudent to allow the current-account deficit and foreign borrowing to&#13;
increase, then other imports will have to be cut drastically. If other&#13;
imports have to bear the full burden of the external shock, the level&#13;
and growth of output in the South will have to be sharply reduced,&#13;
especially in the absence of efforts to implement offsetting policy&#13;
actions within the South.&#13;
"Recycling" enters the conventional analysis at this point. All&#13;
analysts observe that PEX experiences a large current-account surplus&#13;
as a result of its upward ratcheting of the oil price and its inability&#13;
or unwillingness to expand imports of goods and services as rapidly as&#13;
the growth in its oil revenues. The capital outflow from PEX that is&#13;
the obverse of the PEX current-account surplus may be treated in the&#13;
PEX balance-of-payments accounts as an increase in international&#13;
reserves or as an investment of long-term capital. In either case, of&#13;
course, the funds remain in Northern financial markets. When all&#13;
nations in the world other than those in PEX are taken together,&#13;
therefore, there is no "financing" problem; the combined&#13;
current-account deficit of the North and South that is the arithmetic&#13;
counterpart of the PEX surplus is "automatically" financed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
26&#13;
Suppose, however, (as assumed here) that decisionmakers in PEX&#13;
believe the only attractive financial investments for them are deposits&#13;
in Northern financial intermediaries and other relatively liquid claims&#13;
on the North. For individual petroleum-importing nations and for the&#13;
single region of the South, therefore, a financing problem can exist.&#13;
Unless financial intermediaries and official institutions in the North&#13;
deliberately decide to acquire additional claims on private-sector&#13;
agents and the government in the South (that is, by "recycling" some of&#13;
the PEX investments to the South), the magnitude of NRB in equation&#13;
(3a) cannot rise to cushion the rise in oil prices and thereby permit&#13;
the volume of imports to be maintained at or near their former level.&#13;
Some amount of recycling of funds to borrowers in the South is&#13;
conventionally understood to be likely; because PEX investments are&#13;
placed in Northern financial intermediaries as the PEX surplus&#13;
accumulates, the Northern intermediaries are more flush with funds than&#13;
they otherwise would have been and are (other things being equal) more&#13;
willing to lend to the South. But it is also conventionally believed&#13;
that recycling after the second round of oil-price increases in 1979-80&#13;
will prove to be difficult and stressful. And many analysts appear to&#13;
believe that the process of recycling can become a major problem in&#13;
itself.&#13;
Some of the difficulties emphasized in the conventional&#13;
discussions of recycling are various "frictions" experienced by the&#13;
Northern financial intermediaries. For example, the capital positions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
27&#13;
of Northern banks have not grown as rapidly as their total assets and&#13;
liabilities; prudential concerns about the adequacy of their capital&#13;
may lead banks to slow down the growth of their lending. In addition,&#13;
many banks are said to be close to the internal ceilings they have set&#13;
for lending to particular nations; further lending would require&#13;
reevaluation of those country limits. The banks' own reassessments of&#13;
their attitudes toward capital adequacy and "country risk," moreover,&#13;
have been reinforced by revisions in the thinking and regulations of&#13;
the official authorities in the North who are charged with supervising&#13;
and examining the banks.&#13;
The conventional analysis also emphasizes the "creditworthiness"&#13;
difficulties of individual nations in the South -- especially those&#13;
nations with already large outstanding debts and those that have&#13;
pursued domestic policies that are imprudently expansionary or&#13;
insufficiently adapted to the higher world relative price of energy.&#13;
The prevailing view seems to be that every petroleum-importing country&#13;
must "adjust" its economic policies in some degree to the changed world&#13;
petroleum situation, and that especially strong adjustment measures&#13;
must be taken by countries whose domestic policies have been allowed to&#13;
get out of hand. "Adjustment" means acquiescing in a lower volume of&#13;
imports -- reduction of both 'm and '   in equation (3a) -- rather than&#13;
expanding the amount of borrowing (raising NRB).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
28&#13;
Finally, conventional accounts of the recycling problem mention&#13;
the possibility of banking crises or financial panics in Northern&#13;
financial markets. The triggering event for such a crisis could be,&#13;
for example, a debt default or a rescheduling by an individual borrower&#13;
that leads to a more general lack of confidence by bank depositors. A&#13;
few analysts see such dangers as probable; they urgently recommend&#13;
further lender-of-last-resort planning for the support of Northern&#13;
financial markets (in particular, some form of "safety net" for&#13;
Eurocurrency banking). A few others, holding the opposite extreme&#13;
view, dismiss such dangers as implausible. Most conventional accounts&#13;
take an intermediate view of these risks.&#13;
The Requirements Variant of the Conventional Analysis&#13;
The description to this point has concentrated on the availability&#13;
variant: the availability of aid and borrowed funds determines the&#13;
available net resource balance, which (together with export receipts)&#13;
determines permissible imports, which then constrains the level and&#13;
growth of output. The requirements variant of the conventional&#13;
analysis involves the same analytical apparatus, but reverses the flow&#13;
of the analysis through the apparatus: domestic output targets&#13;
determine a required volume of imports, which (together with export&#13;
receipts) determines a required net resource balance, which then&#13;
determines a required amount of net capital inflow.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
29&#13;
In effect, the requirements variant begins with a collaboration&#13;
between the domestic analyst and policymakers in the South. The&#13;
policymakers establish their priorities among output growth and other&#13;
domestic policy objectives and then determine (with the help of the&#13;
domestic analyst) those settings for their policy instruments deemed&#13;
most likely to bring about the chosen objectives. Taking as given the&#13;
*5&#13;
objective for output growth (y ), the other domestic objectives, and&#13;
projections of the domestic nonpolicy exogenous events that influence&#13;
the South's economy, the domestic analyst calculates the volume of&#13;
impo-rts that will be required to achieve the policy objectives. In&#13;
schematic terms analogous to those used in function (4), the&#13;
relationship between targeted output and the required volume of&#13;
petroleum and non-petroleum imports may be expressed as:&#13;
(5) m + m = g                  Y                                ,&#13;
The flow of imports required to support a given rate of output in&#13;
the South is not determined by any simple rule of proportionality. As&#13;
emphasized in the discussion of the availability variant, imports may&#13;
not be the only, or even the chief, constraint on the South's output.&#13;
Even so, the domestic analyst's model of the South's economy will&#13;
postulate an important relationship running from the South's output&#13;
objective to its required imports. Given other domestic policy&#13;
objetivs,tehgherisSthehigher&#13;
objectives, the higher is y the higher must be M.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
30&#13;
The next step in the requirements variant of the analysis is&#13;
essentially identical to the second part of the availability variant.&#13;
The trade analyst prepares projections for import prices, export&#13;
prices, and the volume of the South's exports. All the projections are&#13;
contingent on exogenous assumptions of what will happen in goods&#13;
markets in the world economy outside the South.&#13;
The final steps in the requirements variant are the responsibility&#13;
of the financial analyst. He makes a projection for the amount of&#13;
official development assistance that can be expected (ODA). Then,&#13;
accepting the projections prepared by the trade analyst, the financial&#13;
analyst uses the South's balance-of-payments identity to calculate the&#13;
South's near-term "financing requirement," designated here F.&#13;
Financing for this purpose is defined as the net sum of capital flows,&#13;
debt service, and change in the reserve position -- that is, F = (L\K -&#13;
D - AR) -- and the "required" amount is given by:&#13;
(6)     F -    p(x) - pmp(mp) - p(m ) + ODA]&#13;
For reasons given earlier, the financial analyst must relate any&#13;
calculation of debt service and any judgment about changes in the&#13;
reserve position to the outstanding stock of borrowing. Thus the major&#13;
ingredient in a plan for achieving the financing requirement F is a&#13;
calculation of the cost and risks of achieving a desired capital inflow&#13;
A that is consistent with the amount F.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
31&#13;
Suppose that the financial analyst receives new information&#13;
leading him to expect tighter conditions in world financial markets&#13;
than he had earlier expected. He will then calculate that the higher&#13;
level of world interest rates will unfavorably shift the supply curve&#13;
of funds available to South borrowers (see the earlier discussion of&#13;
Figures 2 and 3). A higher level for world interest rates will, other&#13;
things being equal, require an upward adjustment in the projected&#13;
amount of debt service for the South. The analyst will thus conclude&#13;
that the given flow of near-term financing F can only be achieved by&#13;
increasing the quantity of the South-s borrowings (despite the higher&#13;
cost and reduced availability of funds).     A higher level of required&#13;
borrowings implies a required increase in the South-s net resource&#13;
balance.&#13;
An increased flow of debt service and a larger outstanding debt&#13;
are costly and, beyond some point, potentially risky for the South. In&#13;
the long run if not in the short, the South's development prospects&#13;
could be adversely affected by an excessive accumulation of debt. For&#13;
example, future abrupt changes in the appraisals by foreign creditors&#13;
of the South-s creditworthiness could entail sudden, costly reversals&#13;
of domestic investment plans.&#13;
11.  In terms of Figures 2 and 3, the BsBs curve must be shifted to the&#13;
right. Because the LsL5 curve begins to slope upward beyond some level&#13;
of borrowing by the South, increases in borrowing may also lead to an&#13;
increase in the risk premium paid by the South.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
32&#13;
Seen from the perspective of the requirements variant of the&#13;
conventional analysis, therefore, an external economic event that&#13;
produces a tightening of world financial markets increases the costs&#13;
and risks to the South of maintaining the flow of financing F. The&#13;
requirement F is regarded as necessary in the near term for the&#13;
maintenance of the volume of imports m, which in turn is essential if&#13;
*S&#13;
targeted output in the near term y and other near-term domestic policy&#13;
objectives are to be attained.&#13;
The reasoning just summarized is also thought to be valid, given&#13;
appropriate changes in the details of the argument, for an external&#13;
economic event that has as its result a lowering of the level of&#13;
interest rates in Northern financial markets (or an easing of non-price&#13;
availability constraints). An easier world financial environment is&#13;
seen as reducing the costs and mitigating the risks of arranging the&#13;
given financing requirement F.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
33&#13;
III. DEFECTS OF THE CONVENTIONAL ANALYSIS&#13;
Each variant of the conventional analysis of the effects of the&#13;
global economic environment on developing nations accords a critical&#13;
role to capital flows and the net resource balance. Each emphasizes an&#13;
inference that purportedly connects the exogenous financial environment&#13;
in the rest of the world with current and prospective output in the&#13;
South.&#13;
In the availability variant, any external financial development&#13;
causing a prudent projection of the net resource balance to be smaller&#13;
(greater) is asserted to be unambiguously detrimental (favorable) for&#13;
output in the South. In the requirements variant, any external&#13;
financial development that increases (reduces) the projected costs and&#13;
risks of attaining a given flow of balance-of-payments financing is&#13;
asserted to be disadvantageous (favorable) for output in the South, in&#13;
the long run if not in the short.&#13;
Unfortunately, these inferences of the conventional analysis are&#13;
not necessarily correct. In many important instances, they are&#13;
invalid.&#13;
If analysis of the effects of the global economy on the South is&#13;
to avoid incorrect inferences, it must pay due attention to world&#13;
macroeconomic identities, not merely the identities that pertain to the&#13;
South alone.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
34&#13;
Balance-of-Payments Identities for the World as a Whole&#13;
The balance-of-payments identity for the South in equation (1),&#13;
rewritten here with a superscript S to differentiate the identity from&#13;
the identities for other regions, is:&#13;
(7)     xS - MS -DS + ODA + AKS -R S      O,&#13;
where XS and MS are the values of the South's exports and imports.&#13;
The balance-of-payments identity for the PEX region, expressed in&#13;
currency units of the North, may be written as:&#13;
(8)    p      XP   MP + DP +   P _ \     p   0,&#13;
where X   is the value of PEX exports (primarily petroleum revenues), M&#13;
is the value of PEX imports, D    is the value of net investment income&#13;
receipts (always positive), AK    is the value of net capital flows to&#13;
the rest of the world (always a net outflow and hence a negative&#13;
value), and \Rp is the value of changes in the PEX international&#13;
reserve position (typically an increase, where increases are recorded&#13;
with a positive sign). The PEX current-account balance is:&#13;
(9)     CB     x X-M   + D.&#13;
In the schematic framework used in this note, all assets and&#13;
liabilities of PEX residents other than domestic assets and debts are&#13;
assumed to be claims on or liabilities -to the North. All official&#13;
development assistance to the South is assumed to originate in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
35&#13;
North. (It is straightforward to amend the discussion here and in the&#13;
earlier exposition by relaxing these simplifying assumptions, and in&#13;
practice the conventional analysis does include these amendments.)&#13;
Hence the balance-of-payments identity of the North, expressed in North&#13;
currency units, is:&#13;
N    N    S     P           S     P      N&#13;
(10)     X  -_M  + D   _ D  - ODA - AK  -AK    -  R    0,&#13;
and the definition of the North current account is:&#13;
N =N      N     S    P&#13;
(11)          CB    x   _ m  + D  - D&#13;
The symbols have the same meaning as before, with the superscript N&#13;
indicating that XN, MN, and ARN are the values for the North of&#13;
exports, imports, and changes in the international reserve position.&#13;
As a further simplification, assume that the only international&#13;
reserve assets used by the thre-e regions are "outside reserves" and&#13;
that the global stock of these outside reserves is unchanged. This&#13;
assumption is of course at variance with the facts in the actual world&#13;
economy. Nevertheless, it helps to keep the exposition here&#13;
straightforward, and no conclusions in this paper are significantly&#13;
affected by its presence or absence. 12&#13;
12. Outside reserve assets are assets accepted for settlements between&#13;
national monetary authorities that are not at the same time a liability&#13;
of some governmental or private economic unit resident in a particular&#13;
nation. Gold and the International Monetary Fund's Special Drawing&#13;
Rights (SDRs ) are the main examples in practice. Securities issued by&#13;
national governments of "reserve-center" nations (or debts of private&#13;
intermediaries located in those nations) that are held by other nations&#13;
as international reserves -- which are a reserve asset for the holder&#13;
but a reserve liability for the reserve-center nation -- are "inside"&#13;
reserves. (For further discussion, see Bryant, Money and Monetary&#13;
Policy, pp. 357-60, 454-56.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
36&#13;
If the global stock of outside reserves is unchanged, then of&#13;
course the change in one region's reserve position is the negative of&#13;
the sum of the changes for the other regions:&#13;
(12)           \S + \RP + ARN - O&#13;
The preceding identities are sufficient to derive several other&#13;
identities for the world as a whole. In particular, the value of world&#13;
trade measured as exports is identical to the global total of imports;&#13;
the sum of the capital accounts in the balances of payments for all&#13;
three regions is identically zero; and the sum of current-account&#13;
balances for the world as a whole is identically zero:&#13;
(13)          CBS + CBp + CBN 50.&#13;
Saving-Investment Identities&#13;
The standard accounting identity for national output, income, and&#13;
expenditure in the North may be written as:&#13;
N    N     N    N     N    S      N     P&#13;
(14)     y    c   + I + G   + (X  + D)- (M     + D)&#13;
All magnitudes are nominal and.again expressed in North currency units;&#13;
N                                                      N   N        N&#13;
Y is the gross national product (GNP) of the North; C , I , and G are&#13;
expenditures in the North on consumption, domestic investment, and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
37&#13;
government. Because they are shown separately from the international&#13;
flows of goods and services in the balance-of-payments identity, the&#13;
North's net investment-income receipts from the South (D ) and its net&#13;
payments of interest to PEX (D ) are also included explicitly in the&#13;
national income identity.&#13;
dN&#13;
The definition of disposable income in the North, Y      , is&#13;
(15)           ydN   YN _TN&#13;
where T is the tax revenue collected by governments in the North. The&#13;
N&#13;
identity defining saving by the private sector, S , is:&#13;
(16)           SN = ydN - cN.&#13;
If the identities (14), (15), and (16) are combined with the&#13;
definition of the current-account balance for the North in identity&#13;
(11), the result is the familiar identity that links saving, domestic&#13;
investment, and "net foreign investment&#13;
N        N _N                N      -N&#13;
(17)      S   +  (T  -G) GI                            CB-.&#13;
eti     ( ;Ass.              Av45A&#13;
Each of the five macroeconomic variables in identity (17) depends&#13;
in a complex way on the evolution of output and prices within the&#13;
North. Each also depends on the evolution of output and prices&#13;
elsewhere in the world.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
38&#13;
For example, suppose that governmental units in the North sharply&#13;
raise their expenditures (one form of expansionary fiscal policy). As&#13;
a result, output and the price level in the North will rise.      Tax&#13;
revenues will increase somewhat, though less than the increment in GN&#13;
the government budget balance will thus move to a smaller surplus or a&#13;
larger deficit. Private-sector saving SN and domestic investment IN&#13;
will both rise, but the latter probably more than the former. As&#13;
imports of goods and services rise faster than exports, the&#13;
current-account balance will probably decline (that is, move toward a&#13;
smaller surplus or larger deficit).&#13;
Alternatively, suppose that governmental units in the South take&#13;
new policy actions that are successful in promoting more rapid growth&#13;
in the South. The higher level of activity in the South will be&#13;
transmitted to the North through higher North exports to the South. As&#13;
North output and prices respond to the external stimulus, North imports&#13;
will also rise. The rise in payments for imports, however, will lag&#13;
behind the increased receipts for exports, and the current-account&#13;
balance for the North will therefore increase (move toward a larger&#13;
surplus or smaller deficit). On the left-hand side of identity (17),&#13;
13. The proportion of the increase in nominal GNP that is an increase&#13;
in output rather than a rise in prices can vary, in principle, from 0&#13;
percent to 100 percent (depending on, among other things, the degree of&#13;
slack in utilization of resources). In practice, the proportion&#13;
usually falls between the two extremes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
39&#13;
tax revenues will rise in response to the increased activity in the&#13;
economy, and the budget position of the North government will therefore&#13;
show a larger surplus or a smaller deficit. Private-sector saving and&#13;
domestic investment in the North will both increase, with the former&#13;
probably rising more than the latter.&#13;
Many additional illustrations -- of other types of policy actions&#13;
or of nonpolicy shocks, originating internally in the North or&#13;
externally in the rest of the world -- could be considered. In some&#13;
cases, the directions of movement of the variables in identity (17) may&#13;
be uncertain (in the sense that different models of the domestic&#13;
economy of the North and its links to the world economy may give&#13;
different answers). No matter how complex the relationships may be,&#13;
however, it is clear that all the variables in the identity respond&#13;
"endogenously" to variations in domestic and foreign economic activity.&#13;
What is true of the saving-investment identity for the North is no&#13;
less true of the corresponding identities for the South and PEX. As&#13;
the pace of economic activity strengthens or flags in any of the&#13;
regions of the world, induced changes occur in the flows of each&#13;
region's saving and investment.&#13;
As a reminder of the manner in which the regional current-account&#13;
balances vary with economic activity, the following is a variant of&#13;
identity (13) that makes use of general functional notation:&#13;
(13a) CB N(YN YP y,...) + CBP(y- y, y,...) + CBS NyP y- .        0.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
40&#13;
N   P       S&#13;
The variables y , y , and y are the levels of output in, respectively,&#13;
the North, PEX, and the South.14 The ellipses in the functions serve&#13;
as reminders that a number of other variables would have to be included&#13;
in a complete specification. The probable signs of the partial&#13;
derivatives of a function with respect to its arguments are indicated&#13;
above the arguments.&#13;
The identity (13a) can be interpreted either as the world identity&#13;
for current-account balances or as the world saving-investment&#13;
identity; both interpretations, of course, are equally correct. To&#13;
emphasize the latter interpretation, one can write out the identities&#13;
for PEX and the South that are the counterparts of identity (17) and&#13;
combine them with identities (13) and (17). Seen from the perspective&#13;
of the South, for example, the flows of saving and investment in the&#13;
world must satisfy:&#13;
(18)        s + (T5 _ GS) _ I3]-[SN + (TN _ GN) - i&#13;
+  S  + (TP - GP) - IP&#13;
14. The extraction of natural resources is traditionally treated in&#13;
national income accounts as currently produced output. To the extent&#13;
that PEX nations lift petroleum and sell it to the rest of the world in&#13;
exchange for financial claims on Northern intermediaries (that is, run&#13;
a current-account surplus), the activity should perhaps be described as&#13;
the substitution of one type of asset for another rather than the&#13;
production of current output. This distinction, while important for&#13;
some analytical purposes, does not alter the argument made in the text;&#13;
epsentially identical copclusions follow if the volume of PEX imports,&#13;
m , is substituted for y in the functions in identity (13a)0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
41&#13;
Each one of the identities (7) through (18) is equally binding.&#13;
They are, as it were, straitjackets that inevitably hold ex post and&#13;
continuously constrain world economic activity. Analysts can ignore&#13;
the identities when making projections. Governments can ignore them&#13;
when making policy decisions. But the identities can never be&#13;
violated.&#13;
Consequences for the South of External Economic Events&#13;
With the preceding comments as background, now return to the&#13;
analysis of the consequences for the South of "exogenous" economic&#13;
events originating outside the South.&#13;
An Increase in Oil Prices. Consider first the world pattern of&#13;
current-account imbalances that is the result when the PEX nations&#13;
sharply raise the price they charge for petroleum. 5&#13;
Because PEX oil revenues rise more promptly and by a larger amount&#13;
than any induced increases in PEX imports, the PEX current account&#13;
moves strongly into surplus. In both the North and the South, the&#13;
15. The price increase assumed here is sudden and dramatic, raising&#13;
the real oil price sharply (as in 1979-80), rather than smaller&#13;
increases of the order of magnitude of the world inflation rate.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
42&#13;
increase in the oil price imparts an upward push to the general price&#13;
level; simultaneously, output tends to fall.     These price and output&#13;
N   N&#13;
effects in the North produce changes in the nominal values of S , I&#13;
and the budget balance of the North government the net value of which&#13;
is negative; saying the same thing another way, the North&#13;
current-account balance moves into deficit (because the rise in value&#13;
of oil imports is greater than offsetting increases, if any, in the&#13;
value of North current-account receipts)., Similar domestic changes and&#13;
hence a similar move into current-account deficit occur in the South&#13;
(unless -- the extreme case noted earlier -- there is no scope at all&#13;
for running down reserves, increasing ODA, or borrowing more in&#13;
Northern financial markets).&#13;
As always, the world current-account identity holds:&#13;
N       P&#13;
(13b)          ACBS + \CB   ' -CB&#13;
The combined current-account deficit of the North and South must&#13;
therefore increase as much as the increase in the PEX surplus. One&#13;
should not, however, conduct the analysis of the consequences of the&#13;
16. As has often been noted, the oil-price increase has price and&#13;
income effects on the global economy that are analogous to the price&#13;
and income effects of an increase in a (world) excise tax.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
43&#13;
oil-price increase as though the magnitude of the increase in the PEX&#13;
surplus is a given amount to be allocated between the North and the&#13;
South. As emphasized in identities (13a) and (18), each of the&#13;
regional current-account balances depends on the evolution of global&#13;
economic activity and on the distribution of the activity among the&#13;
three regions. Each region's output and prices in turn depend not only&#13;
on the price of oil but also on the entire array of government policies&#13;
in the three regions. Therefore, whatever other simplifications one&#13;
might want to make in analyzing the consequences of the oil-price&#13;
increase, one should definitely not begin the analysis with&#13;
partial-equilibrium calculation of the PEX surplus and then presume&#13;
that the North and the South must adjust to that PEX surplus.&#13;
Suppose, after the oil-price increase has occurred, that the PEX&#13;
current-account balance for the following year is estimated to be in&#13;
surplus by $100 billion; suppose the estimate is based on projections&#13;
for output, prices, and energy-conservation measures in the North and&#13;
South that were made prior to the oil-price shock. Suppose further&#13;
that the downward effects on output in the North and South due to the&#13;
oil-price increase are allowed to occur and cumulate; suppose even that&#13;
governments in the North take contractionary policy actions to restrict&#13;
aggregate demand because of their concern with the upward pressure on&#13;
the North price level from higher oil prices. As output falls in the&#13;
North and South below the levels projected before the oil shock, the&#13;
demand for energy and oil imports will correspondingly fall short of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
44&#13;
the levels implied in the $100 billion projection for the PEX&#13;
current-account surplus. The identity (13b) continues to hold&#13;
throughout the process during which global output is falling below its&#13;
previously projected level. But the three regional current-account&#13;
balances respond together in a highly endogenous manner to the&#13;
evolution of output and prices. Hence, the actual PEX surplus and the&#13;
combined North-South deficit that is its counterpart turn out to be&#13;
much smaller than the initial projection of $100 billion.&#13;
As another illustration of the same point, consider again the&#13;
South's reaction to the oil-price shock. If it is assumed that the&#13;
South-s creditworthiness is sufficiently problematic to make "recycling&#13;
finance" unavailable to the South, and if the South must therefore&#13;
reduce the volume of its imports and in turn its output, then the&#13;
reduced output in the South will likewise reduce the current-account&#13;
surplus of PEX below what it otherwise would have been. Furthermore,&#13;
the amount of funds globally available to be recycled will&#13;
correspondingly shrink. The extent of current-account payments&#13;
imbalances in the world and the volume of recycling finance are not&#13;
separate phenomena, one of them leading to the other: they are&#13;
opposite faces of the same, single coin.&#13;
Changes in Private-Sector Investment in the North. Now consider&#13;
the consequences of an unexpected spurt in private-sector investment in&#13;
the North. (The financial-market implications of this external&#13;
economic event have already been discussed -- see Figure 2 and its&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
45&#13;
discussion in the text).&#13;
The expansionary stimulus to North investment raises output and&#13;
prices in the North, which in turn increases borrowing demand and pulls&#13;
up the world interest rate. As suggested earlier, the risk-adjusted&#13;
interest rate paid by the South will correspondingly rise while the&#13;
quantity of borrowing by the South -- and hence also net capital&#13;
inflows and the net .resource balance -- will probably shrink.&#13;
The conventional analysis concludes that the tightening in world&#13;
financial markets and the resultant shrinkage in the South's net&#13;
resource balance reduces the volume of permissible South imports and&#13;
hence adversely affects the prospects for output growth in the South.&#13;
In fact, the postulated changes in the external economic environment&#13;
will on balance be favorable for the volume of permissible imports and&#13;
for output growth in the South. The crucial point that is overlooked&#13;
by the partial-equilibrium concentration on capital flows is that the&#13;
shrinkage in the South's net resource balance is likely to be more than&#13;
offset by an increase in the South's export receipts.&#13;
Consider again the world current-account identity and its&#13;
endogeneity with respect to output levels:&#13;
(13c)     NRB         (y  y P y ,...)    CB  + CB&#13;
The higher level of activity in the North (brought about by the&#13;
stimulus originating in the North) pulls the North's current-account&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
46&#13;
balance in the direction of deficit. The offsetting changes toward&#13;
surplus in the current balances of other regions occur partly in the&#13;
South, and the net resource balance of the South does fall. But the&#13;
higher levels of activity in the North are also transmitted to some&#13;
extent to the South and PEX, and hence the gross levels of saving and&#13;
investment are adjusted upwards throughout the world economy. In the&#13;
North, domestic investment rises more than the increase in the sum of&#13;
private-sector and government saving. In the South, domestic&#13;
investment rises less than the net of private and government saving;&#13;
therefore the excess of domestic investment over domestic saving (the&#13;
net resource balance) declines. But the gross levels of investment and&#13;
saving in the South both rise. Hence output in the South is higher&#13;
even though the net resource balance declines.&#13;
In the availability variant of the conventional analysis,&#13;
permissible imports are calculated as:&#13;
mM= (      (x) - D + NRB].&#13;
The financial analyst, doing his task independently of the trade&#13;
analyst, projects the decline in the sum of the net resource balance&#13;
and debt-service payments and thus jumps to the inference that&#13;
permissible imports will be lowered. In fact, the net resource balance&#13;
moves in the opposite direction from permissible imports and possible&#13;
output growth. The value of export receipts -- the first term in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
47&#13;
brackets in equation (3) -- responds to the more vigorous growth in the&#13;
rest of the world, rising by a greater amount than the fall in the net&#13;
sum of the second and third terms in the brackets.       The inference of&#13;
the financial analyst that the tightening conditions in world financial&#13;
markets are adverse for the South is thus flatly wrong. The changes in&#13;
financial conditions, reflecting a more buoyant pace of world economic&#13;
activity, are associated with improved prospects for the development of&#13;
economic activity in the South.&#13;
Note that the same conclusions hold in reverse if the external&#13;
economic event to be analyzed is an unexpected decline in&#13;
private-sector investment in the North. The resultant softening of&#13;
output in the North leads to reductions in borrowing demand in North&#13;
financial markets, a fall in the world level of interest rates, and a&#13;
larger volume of net capital inflows to the South. Yet the easing of&#13;
conditions in world financial markets and the expansion of the South's&#13;
current-account deficit are associated with a worsening, not an&#13;
improvement, in the South's prospects for growth. Lower export&#13;
receipts more than offset the increase in the net resource balance; on&#13;
balance, therefore, the permissible volume of imports is reduced, not&#13;
17. As world activity rises, prices will rise as well. Hence the&#13;
prices paid for South imports as well as those received for South&#13;
exports will probably increase. Even taking into account the rise in&#13;
p , the net change in all the variables on the right-hand side of&#13;
e'quation (3) will be positive, raising the permissible volume of&#13;
imports.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
48&#13;
augmented.&#13;
Other Events in External Goods Markets. The preceding discussion&#13;
focuses on a particular example of an "exogenous" event originating&#13;
outside the South with consequences for the South that are contrary to&#13;
those predicted in the partial-equilibrium analysis of capital flows.&#13;
The example of a change in private-sector investment in the North,&#13;
however, is not atypical. In fact, with appropriate modifications in&#13;
detail, the preceding analysis has widespread applicability.&#13;
Suppose that governmental units in the North increase their&#13;
purchases of goods and services. Or suppose that income tax rates are&#13;
reduced in the North. Or suppose that Northern households unexpectedly&#13;
lower their rate of saving to consume at a higher level. Or suppose&#13;
that the PEX nations take policy actions to step up the flow of their&#13;
imports (for example, to build new harbors and port facilities or to&#13;
improve the level and quality of consumption of PEX residents). In all&#13;
these cases, the exogenous event originates in, or has immediate&#13;
consequences for, goods markets outside the South. In each case,&#13;
output and prices outside the South are pushed upward, and this in turn&#13;
leads to a tightening of conditions in world financial markets. In&#13;
each case, despite the tightening in world financial markets and a&#13;
consequent reduction in the South's net resource balance, gross&#13;
investment and output rise in the South in response to the higher level&#13;
of economic activity outside the South.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
49&#13;
A distinguishing characteristic of all these cases is a movement&#13;
of the export receipts of the South and of South output in the opposite&#13;
direction from the movement in the South's net resource balance. The&#13;
tighter conditions in world financial markets that are a result of the&#13;
initial external stimulus do raise the costs of borrowing for the&#13;
South, reduce the availability of funds to be borrowed, or have both&#13;
effects. Taken by themselves, these "direct" effects on the South of a&#13;
more stringent world financial environment can be said to be adverse.&#13;
But one must look beyond these direct effects to the underlying&#13;
explanation for the more stringent financial environment and to the&#13;
"indirect" effects associated with the financial environment -- the&#13;
real-sector conditions in the world economy -- that are favorable for&#13;
the South.&#13;
The preceding exposition of the point overlooked in the&#13;
conventional analysis criticizes the availability variant. But&#13;
essentially the same criticism applies to the requirements variant.&#13;
The financial analyst in the requirements variant typically forgets&#13;
that the tighter conditions in Northern financial markets brought about&#13;
by a quickening in activity in the North will not only raise the costs&#13;
and risks of arranging any given flow of financing but, at least as&#13;
important, will reduce the amount of financing that is "required."18&#13;
18. The higher level of activity outside the South will pull up the&#13;
value of the South's exports,_which should lead the trade analyst to&#13;
raise the projected value p (x). As can be seen in equation (6), the&#13;
financing requirement F wilf fall. When the financial and the trade&#13;
aspects of the conventional analys's are conducted independently, the&#13;
financial analyst takes the value F as a given, thereby missing this&#13;
crucial point.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
50&#13;
External Shocks Originating in Financial Markets. Analysis of the&#13;
consequences for the South of exogenous external events would be easier&#13;
if it were true that the South's net resource balance always moves in&#13;
the opposite direction from the movement in South output.&#13;
Unfortunately for those who yearn for the simple life., a sweeping&#13;
generalization to that effect is not correct.&#13;
Consider again the example of an unexpected tightening of monetary&#13;
policy in the North (see Figure 3 and its discussion in the text). As&#13;
noted earlier, the restrictive policy action by the Northern monetary&#13;
authorities reduces the volume of intermediation in Northern financial&#13;
markets and can increase the world level of interest rates. The&#13;
tighter conditions in world financial markets will restrict the volume&#13;
of borrowing by the South and may cause the South-s current-acount&#13;
deficit to shrink.&#13;
In this instance, however, the external economic shock has&#13;
originated in financial markets rather than goods markets (the Northern&#13;
monetary authorities have conducted open-market sales of securities,&#13;
thereby reducing the supply of bank reserves). Moreover, the&#13;
tightening in financial markets leads to a reduction of aggregate&#13;
(world) borrowing and an induced weakening in North output. Because of&#13;
the reduction in economic activity outside the South, export receipts&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
51&#13;
of the South tend to fall. As the world weakness in output is&#13;
transmitted to the South, the gross flows of domestic saving and&#13;
domestic investment both weaken; at the same time, the net resource&#13;
balance (the excess of domestic investment over domestic saving) may be&#13;
shrinking.&#13;
Here is a case, therefore, where the South's net resource balance,&#13;
the South's permissible imports, and the South's output all move in the&#13;
same direction. And in this case, fortuitously, the conventional&#13;
analysis of capital flows does not lead to an incorrect conclusion. A&#13;
tightening of world financial conditions brought about by a restrictive&#13;
monetary policy in the North does have adverse effects on the level and&#13;
growth of output in the South. 9&#13;
The same conclusions hold in reverse if Northern monetary&#13;
authorities conduct expansionary open-market operations. The global&#13;
volume of financial intermediation expands hand in hand with a&#13;
19. Even this statement, of course, will need qualification if the&#13;
world economic environment or the South domestic economy are in a&#13;
highly inflationary condition before the tightening of Northern&#13;
monetary policy. For expositional brevity, I continue here to focus on&#13;
output developments rather than to bring in both output and the price&#13;
level as ultimate objectives of economic policy. I believe that most&#13;
if not all the analytical points I am stressing are readily adapted to&#13;
the international transmission of inflation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
52&#13;
quickening of Northern economic activity. The South's export receipts&#13;
will rise, and, simultaneously, the volume of net capital inflows to&#13;
the South may be enlarged.    Hence it is possible for the South's net&#13;
resource balance, its imports, and its output all to rise together.&#13;
Again fortuitously, the correlation perceived in the conventional&#13;
analysis between easier world financial conditions and better prospects&#13;
for growth in the South can turn out to yield the correct inference.&#13;
Consider another example of an external event originating in&#13;
Northern financial markets. Suppose a major bank unexpectedly fails&#13;
(as the Herstatt Bank did in 1974) and a mood of caution sweeps over&#13;
participants in the financial markets. Suppose, furthermore, that the&#13;
Northern monetary authorities, while willing to act as lender of last&#13;
resort to the market, are unwilling to conduct open-market purchases of&#13;
securities large enough to prevent a substantial upward ratcheting of&#13;
the world level of interest rates.&#13;
This example is another instance in which the tightening of&#13;
conditions in world financial markets and the probable shrinkage of net&#13;
capital inflows to the South is associated with downward pressure on&#13;
world activity and hence a weakening of the South's export receipts.&#13;
Thus here, too, the reduction in the South's net resource balance is&#13;
associated with movements in the same direction of permissible imports&#13;
and South output.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
53&#13;
More generally, a wide variety of exogenous events that originate&#13;
in financial markets outside the South are likely to generate changes&#13;
in NRB  and y  in the same direction.   For these events, it will be&#13;
correct for the analyst to infer that a tightening (easing) of&#13;
conditions in world financial markets will tend to have adverse&#13;
(favorable) implications for economic growth in the South.&#13;
Exogenous Shocks Originating Internally in the South&#13;
The focus of these notes is on the consequences for the South of&#13;
changes in economic conditions that originate outside the South.&#13;
Obviously, however, many types of events can occur internally in the&#13;
South that will require an analogous analysis of the South's balance of&#13;
payments and the relationships that link the South to the rest of the&#13;
global economy.&#13;
Consider just one example: the case where an "autonomous"&#13;
increase of investment in the South (brought about either by government&#13;
policy or by a spurt of animal spirits in the private sector) leads to&#13;
a quickening of growth (and some rise in prices) within the South. As&#13;
the higher level of internal activity develops, a larger volume of&#13;
imports will be required and there will be an incipient tendency for&#13;
the current-account deficit to increase. The capital-account&#13;
counterparts to these developments will include an augmented level of&#13;
desired foreign borrowing. If no binding availability constraints are&#13;
encountered in Northern financial markets, the net resource balance&#13;
will be enlarged (imports and the current-account deficit can actually&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
54&#13;
increase).&#13;
With this internal stimulus, therefore, the South-s output and its&#13;
net resource balance change in the same direction. Not only does the&#13;
gross level of domestic investment rise, but the excess of domestic&#13;
investment over domestic saving is further widened.&#13;
For any given set of external economic conditions, an internal&#13;
generation of more rapid growth financed in part by a widening of the&#13;
current-account deficit can only continue for as long as Northern&#13;
financial intermediaries are willing to accumulate further claims on&#13;
the South (or Northern governmental units are prepared to increase the&#13;
volume of ODA). It is self-evident that the more buoyant economic&#13;
activity is outside the South, the better the prospects for the South&#13;
to raise export receipts and thereby satisfy higher import requirements&#13;
without having to enlarge the current-account deficit. Perhaps less&#13;
obviously, but as the earlier analysis shows no less importantly, a&#13;
faster pace of economic activity outside the South will promote faster&#13;
growth within the South even as it reduces the net transfer of&#13;
resources to the South.&#13;
Some Conclusions&#13;
The preceding discussion identifies some analytical points that&#13;
tend to be overlooked in the conventional analysis of capital flows to&#13;
developing nations. Several guidelines follow from what has been said.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
55&#13;
First, analysts of capital flows should avoid the simple&#13;
correlation between conditions in world financial markets and growth&#13;
prospects for the South that is typical of the conventional analysis.&#13;
It is decidedly not true that any tightening of world financial markets&#13;
is bad for growth in the South. Nor is an easing of financial&#13;
conditions necessarily good for growth in the South. For a wide&#13;
variety of events that induce changes in financial conditions, these&#13;
inferences are flatly wrong.&#13;
Second, it is essential to look behind changes in world financial&#13;
conditions to analyze why they are occurring. Understanding the&#13;
underlying causes of the changes is crucial in determining whether the&#13;
changes have implications for the South that are, on balance, favorable&#13;
or unfavorable.&#13;
Third, it will often be helpful to differentiate external economic&#13;
events that have their initial impacts in goods markets from those&#13;
external events that have their initial impacts in financial markets.&#13;
For the former, the net resource balance of the South is likely to&#13;
change in the opposite direction from the change in South output; the&#13;
changes in financial market conditions due to the original goods-market&#13;
event are not (considered by themselves) a reliable indicator of the&#13;
likely consequences for the South. For the latter, external events&#13;
that originate in financial markets, the changes in financial-market&#13;
conditions can be more reliably interpreted as indicators of the&#13;
consequences for the South; in these instances, the net resource&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
56&#13;
balance of the South and output in the South are more likely to change&#13;
in the same direction.&#13;
Fourth, analysts will usually find it easier to project the&#13;
consequences of external economic events for South output than for the&#13;
South's net resource balance.&#13;
Fifth, regardless of whether external events originate in goods&#13;
markets or in financial markets, analysts can usually rely on the rule&#13;
of thumb that the consequences for output and prices in the South are&#13;
likely to be in the same direction as the consequences for output and&#13;
prices outside the South. Indeed, the most reliable way of assessing&#13;
the directional effects on output in the South may be to appraise&#13;
correctly the output effects in the rest of the world. Sufficient&#13;
economic interdependence exists in the world economy to ensure that&#13;
stimuli to activity in one region are transmitted, more or less&#13;
strongly, to other regions.&#13;
Finally, the analysis of the consequences of the external economic&#13;
environment for the South should not be divided into separate parts&#13;
carried out by different analysts. Only when the analysis of capital&#13;
flows and the South-s net resource balance is integrated with the&#13;
analysis of trade and real-sector conditions, and only when both parts&#13;
of the conventional analysis are conducted in the light of a model of&#13;
the world economy that appropriately incorporates the interactions of&#13;
goods markets and financial markets, can economists hope to reach&#13;
correct conclusions about the net consequences for the South of changes&#13;
in the external economic environment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
57&#13;
IV. THE SOUTH AND THE RECYCLING PROBLEM&#13;
This final section of the paper, drawing on the preceding&#13;
analytical framework, comments briefly on the current economic outlook&#13;
for the South and suggests some points that may warrant emphasis in&#13;
World Development Report 1981.&#13;
Which Aspects of Recycling Deserve Priority ?&#13;
Many discussions of the current outlook for economic growth in the&#13;
South emphasize the financial aspects of the recycling problem. The&#13;
authors of the World Development Report may feel compelled to do&#13;
likewise. The Report's analysis of the global economic environment&#13;
would then stress the capital-adequacy and lending-limit constraints&#13;
experienced by banks in the North, the greater attention to "country&#13;
risk" by supervisory and regulatory authorities overseeing the banks,&#13;
the decline (real or imagined) in the creditworthiness of South&#13;
borrowers, and the risks of major disruptions in Northern financial&#13;
markets set off by confidence crises (see the section "Energy Prices&#13;
and the Recycling Problem," above).&#13;
Given an analysis stressing these financial aspects, the policy&#13;
focus of the Report presumably would also be financial. For example,&#13;
recommendations might be offered for easing the frictions holding back&#13;
lending by private banks and for improving the existing official&#13;
channels for intermediation. Conceivably, the Report could even lend&#13;
support to the proposals for new recycling mechanisms or a new "safety&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
58&#13;
net" for Eurocurrency banking.&#13;
Mly view differs from this conventional approach to the recycling&#13;
problem. I believe that the financial aspects of the current world&#13;
outlook, though meriting discussion, are much less consequential for&#13;
the South than the growth and inflation prospects of the Northern&#13;
economies. Hence I believe that the Report's discussion of the global&#13;
environment should emphasize the macroeconomic real-sector performance&#13;
of the North.&#13;
Virtually all the Northern economies are currently experiencing&#13;
rapid rates of inflation and relatively sluggish rates of real growth.&#13;
Controversy rages both about the causes. of this "stagflation".and the&#13;
appropriate policy reactions to it. Economists' views about&#13;
macroeconomic theory and policy are in a greater state of disarray than&#13;
at any time in living memory.&#13;
Given this situation, policymakers in the North are understandably&#13;
divided in their judgments and their policy responses. Some adhere to&#13;
modified versions of the mainstream views of the 1960s. Others grasp&#13;
at new nostrums. Virtually all are uncertain and cautious.&#13;
The unsatisfactory macroeconomic outlook for the North is, of&#13;
course, the main preoccupation of economists whose task is to analyze&#13;
the North. Even analysts concerned solely with the South, however,&#13;
should appreciate the South's high stakes in the outcome of this&#13;
macroeconomic debate in the North.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
59&#13;
Imagine, for example, some improvement in macroeconomic diagnosis&#13;
and, as a result of that improvement, some new policy consensus that&#13;
permits incrementally higher real growth in the North without an&#13;
exacerbation of inflation. More specifically, suppose the path of real&#13;
output is 1 percent higher than would otherwise have been possible&#13;
while the price level in the North rises on essentially the same path&#13;
it would have followed. The favorable consequences of this development&#13;
for the South would be dramatic: the growth rate of output in the&#13;
South could be (applying a rough but conservative estimate) at least&#13;
half a percentage point higher than without the incrementally higher&#13;
Northern growth. The benefits from this faster growth in the South&#13;
would undoubtedly dominate the benefits to the South attributable to&#13;
any conceivable improvement in financial recycling mechanisms.&#13;
Alternatively, imagine a hypothetical improvement in Northern&#13;
policies for energy conservation and domestic energy production.&#13;
Suppose such new policies eased the energy constraints on macroeconomic&#13;
performance sufficiently to permit a path of output 1 percent higher&#13;
but without any raising of the paths for world oil prices and national&#13;
price levels. Again the potential benefits to the South would be&#13;
dramatic: *in the first instance through higher Southern exports and an&#13;
easing of the constraint on permissible Southern imports, but then&#13;
shortly thereafter through a faster rate of growth of Southern output&#13;
and income. Once more, the benefits to the South from any possible&#13;
improvements in financial recycling would be modest relative to the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6o&#13;
benefits from the marginally greater success of the North in combating&#13;
stagflation.&#13;
An additional point is relevant here: if ways could be found to&#13;
improve macroeconomic performance in the North, there would be less&#13;
need for, and hence less need to worry about, improvements in financial&#13;
recycling mechanisms.&#13;
I am not claiming that the financial aspects of the recycling&#13;
problem cannot become important, so to speak, in their own right. I&#13;
am, however, asserting that the financial problems in themselves&#13;
represent a less troublesome threat to the South than the real-sector&#13;
problems in the North. Furthermore, the probability of the financial&#13;
aspects becoming important in their own right is markedly greater in a&#13;
world environment where real-sector growth is very sluggish or, worse&#13;
still, negative.20&#13;
Should the World Development Report contain any diplomatically&#13;
worded policy suggestions addressed to the industrial countries of the&#13;
North? If so, from the preceding observations I conclude that the&#13;
Report should stress the crucial significance -- for the South -- of&#13;
improvements in Northern policies for dampening inflation and&#13;
maintaining growth. Any discussion of frictions in financial markets&#13;
20. If a worst-case scenario for the South should ever develop, it&#13;
will undoubtedly entail financial crises. But in all likelihood those&#13;
financial problems will derive from more deep-seated causes originating&#13;
outside financial markets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
61&#13;
or improved techniques for financial recycling should not divert&#13;
attention from the policy issue that is predominantly important.&#13;
Adjustment or Compensation for the South?&#13;
Consider now the question of what the Report might suggest about&#13;
policies to be followed in the South. Given the large, 1979-80&#13;
increases in oil prices and the resultant imbalances in world payments,&#13;
and given whatever degree of stagflation may prevail in the North, how&#13;
much scope exists for an individual nation's government in the South to&#13;
offset the adverse effects of the less favorable external economic&#13;
environment? The same question warrants asking for the South as a&#13;
whole: can the South hope to counter the adverse effects of external&#13;
events by altering internal policies?&#13;
Two extreme answers to this question can be given, and they tend&#13;
to define a spectrum along which intermediate alternatives can be&#13;
ranked. At one extreme, a strategy of full compensation would try to&#13;
offset completely the unfavorable external shocks. The other extreme&#13;
strategy would acquiesce in the shocks, with the goal being complete&#13;
adjustment.&#13;
In effect, the strategy of full compensation relies exclusively on&#13;
the requirements variant of the conventional analysis. The&#13;
policymakers in the South start with their "domestic" policy&#13;
objectives, including their goal for output growth, treating these&#13;
objectives as givens not to be adjusted. Import requirements follow&#13;
from the domestic objectives [see equation (5), above]. The value of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
"required" oil imports is sharply increased because of the higher world&#13;
oil price. Debt service on past borrowing is a predetermined quantity.&#13;
The projection for export receipts is weaker than before because of the&#13;
adverse shifts in the world environment. A revised judgment is made&#13;
about the change in reserves that is desirable or tolerable in the new&#13;
circumstances. Finally, as a residual, the policymakers determine the&#13;
amount of new borrowing from abroad that is required to cover the net&#13;
gap expected to be left by all other balance-of-payments transactions.&#13;
The basic intent of the strategy is to "compensate" fully for external&#13;
shocks, thereby maintaining the momentum of growth and development at&#13;
home.&#13;
Conversely, a strategy of complete adjustment presupposes a&#13;
mechanical reliance on the availability variant of the conventional&#13;
analysis.  The basic intent is to modify domestic objectives&#13;
sufficiently to be sure they are consistent with the altered&#13;
balance-of-payments constraint imposed by the new external environment.&#13;
In particular, the South's policymakers start their analysis with their&#13;
predetermined debt-service obligations. They err on the conservative&#13;
side in making judgments about the change in reserves that can-be&#13;
tolerated and about the amounts of new external borrowing that can be&#13;
arranged without compromising their international creditworthiness.&#13;
Given cautious projections of export receipts and the terms of trade,&#13;
the policymakers ascertain the amount of imports that can be afforded.&#13;
Domestic growth targets and other domestic objectives are then&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
63&#13;
throttled back to the point where they are consistent with the&#13;
affordable imports.&#13;
Is one or the other of these strategies likely to be appropriate&#13;
for an individual Southern government or for the South as a whole? In&#13;
my view, certainly not. Both extremes are irresponsible.&#13;
A strategy of full compensation, however desirable in the&#13;
abstract, is simply not viable. It can easily -- later if not sooner&#13;
-- place the economy in an unsustainable debt position with respect to&#13;
the rest of the world.&#13;
In a significantly open economy, adverse events occurring abroad&#13;
inescapably influence the home economy. Whatever offsetting actions&#13;
may be attempted cannot fully restore the domestic situation that&#13;
otherwise would have existed. Similarly, policy actions taken at home&#13;
inevitably spill abroad to some extent. The greater the extent of&#13;
economic openness, the more difficult are national policy decisions and&#13;
the more uncertain their consequences. Although economic&#13;
interdependence brings many benefits, it also undermines the ability of&#13;
policymakers to achieve national objectives. 21&#13;
Furthermore, suppose hypothetically that for a temporary period&#13;
the South could fully sustain domestic growth in the face of sluggish&#13;
growth or stagnation in the North. There would then occur a&#13;
21. These points are carefully explored in Bryant, Money and Monetary&#13;
Policy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
64i&#13;
continuation, indeed a probable worsening, of very large&#13;
current-account deficits. Even in the face of high domestic investment&#13;
rates and bright future prospects for development, the associated rapid&#13;
building up of external debt could eventually induce foreign lenders to&#13;
get cold feet. Sudden changes in the perceptions of creditors,&#13;
warranted or not, could then require drastic, costly reversals in&#13;
domestic policies. Drastic interruptions in development programs can&#13;
prove much more costly than smaller adjustments spaced more smoothly&#13;
over time.&#13;
Because the strategy of full compensation attempts an unattainable&#13;
insulation of domestic growth from external shocks, and because it&#13;
risks the large costs of drastic reversals in policies, it is an&#13;
imprudent, dangerous approach. "Damn the torpedoes, full speed ahead!"&#13;
sounds a brave note ex ante but, too late, induces second thoughts when&#13;
the ship takes a torpedo in the engine room.&#13;
Complete adjustment cannot be recommended in good conscience&#13;
either. Even individual developing nations that are small and quite&#13;
open have some limited scope for partially offsetting adverse external&#13;
events. In the face of stagnation in the North, for example, some&#13;
incremental amount of borrowing abroad can be prudent. Some scope will&#13;
exist for expenditure-increasing actions to mitigate the downward&#13;
pressure on aggregate demand. Various other policy actions can promote&#13;
increases in the prices of domestically produced tradable goods&#13;
relative to the prices of nontraded goods, thereby inducing domestic&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
65&#13;
residents to switch expenditures toward nontraded goods; this&#13;
expenditure switching also helps to mitigate the downward push on&#13;
Southern output. If the North turns out to have a mediocre economic&#13;
performance, it is all the more essential for the government of a&#13;
developing nation to compensate to the limited extent that is feasible.&#13;
The scope for compensatory policy actions is a function of the&#13;
structural characteristics of the national economy,-- especially, of&#13;
course, its degree of openness. For example, offsetting policies have&#13;
a better chance of (partial) success the smaller the fraction of output&#13;
represented by tradable goods, the less extensive the network of&#13;
financial claims on and liabilities to external residents, and the&#13;
smaller the elasticities of substitution between tradable and nontraded&#13;
goods and between home-currency and foreign-currency assets.&#13;
An important additional point reinforces the case against a&#13;
strategy of complete adjustment: the scope for the South as a whole to&#13;
take compensatory actions is somewhat greater than one would think by&#13;
examining the scope for each individual developing nation taken in&#13;
isolation.&#13;
In Northern governments, and possibly even in the World Bank and&#13;
the International Monetary Fund, advice to Southern governments is&#13;
frequently offered that comes too close to the "complete adjustment"&#13;
end of the policy spectrum. The tendency to give that advice may be&#13;
derived, at least in part, from a concentration of attention on&#13;
individual Southern nations one at a time without an adequate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
66&#13;
appreciation vX their economic interactions.&#13;
Suppose every nation in the South were to adopt a policy posture&#13;
close to the extreme of complete adjustment. The combined actions of&#13;
the Southern governments as they cut back on imports and domestic&#13;
growth would then impart an incremental contractionary impetus to&#13;
output in the North, over and above the contractionary effects&#13;
resulting from the increases in the world oil price. For reasons given&#13;
above (the section "Consequences for the South of External Economic&#13;
Events"), the PEX current-account surplus and the South's&#13;
current-account deficit would both be smaller than they otherwise would&#13;
have been. In the face of already sluggish growth in the North,&#13;
however, the South's adoption of complete adjustment could add&#13;
significantly to the severity of global stagflation.&#13;
To be sure, the contribution of the South to the macroeconomic&#13;
performance of the world economy -- for good or ill -- is considerably&#13;
smaller than that of the North. The oil-importing developing nations&#13;
are right to put the major share of the responsibility for global&#13;
stagflation on the North and on the PEX countries. The South nations&#13;
are much too big in the aggregate, however, to pretend that their&#13;
combined behavior is of no consequence for the world macroeconomic&#13;
outcome. Many individual nations in the South are "small and open".&#13;
But the economy of the South as a whole is certainly not small, and it&#13;
is also less open than its individual national components. Any advice&#13;
to Southern governments -- in particular any suggestions to be included&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
67&#13;
in the World Development Report -- that failed to acknowledge this fact&#13;
would in my view be open to serious criticism.&#13;
The preceding observations bring me to a final worry about the&#13;
choice of policies by Southern governments. Suppose all nations in the&#13;
South were to opt for vigorous balance-of-payments adjustment and were&#13;
to do so primarily by creating new selective incentives for exports and&#13;
new selective restraints on imports. (I include in the category of&#13;
such selective measures any further subsidies for export credit and any&#13;
additional restrictions on the availability of import financing.) A&#13;
policy of this sort can conceivably benefit a few individual nations in&#13;
the South. But it certainly does not represent a path out of the&#13;
macroeconomic swamp for all nations together, developed and developing.&#13;
And even for all nations in the South, because of the growing&#13;
importance of South-South transactions, this type of "adjustment" has&#13;
beggar-thy-Southern-neighbor consequences that may make it a costly way&#13;
for the South to react to the world environment of stagflation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
COMPANION PAPERS IN THIS SERIES&#13;
No.                          TITLE OF PAPER                         AUTHOR&#13;
449     Policy Experience in Twelve Less Developed Countries      B. Balassa&#13;
470     Industrial Country Policy and Adjustment to Imports       J.M. Finger&#13;
from Developing Countries&#13;
471     The Political Structure of the New Protectionism          D. Nelson (consultant)&#13;
472     Adjustment to External Shocks in Developing Countries     B. Balassa&#13;
473     Food Policy Issues in Low-Income Countries                E. Clay (consultant)&#13;
474     Energy, International Trade, and Economic Growth          A. Manne (consultant)&#13;
475     Capital-Importing Oil Exporters:  Adjustment Issues       A.H. Gelb&#13;
and Policy Choices&#13;
476     Notes on the Analysis of Capital Flows to Developing      R.C. Bryant (consultant)&#13;
Nations and the 'Recycling' Problem&#13;
477     Adjustment Experience and Growth Prospects of the         F. Jaspersen&#13;
Semi-Industrial Countries&#13;
478     Trade Policy Issues for the Developing Countries          I. Frank (consultant)&#13;
in the 1980s&#13;
479     Trade among Developing Countries: Theory, Policy          0. Havrylyshyn&#13;
Issues, and Principal Trends                                  (consultant)&#13;
M. Wolf&#13;
480     Trade in Services:  Economic Determinants and             A. Sapir (consultant)&#13;
Development-Related Issues                                 E. Lutz&#13;
481     International Migrant Workers' Remittances:  Issues       G. Swamy&#13;
and Prospects&#13;
482     Private Bank Lending to Developing Countries              R. O'Brien (consultant)&#13;
483     Development Prospects of the Capital Surplus              R. Hablutzel&#13;
Oil-Exporting Countries&#13;
484     Private Capital Flows to Developing Countries and         A. Fleming&#13;
Their Determination&#13;
485     International Adjustment in the 1980s                     V. Joshi (consultant)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
No.                           TITLE OF PAPER                         AUTHOR&#13;
486     Adjustment in Low-Income Africa                            R. Liebenthal&#13;
487     A Comparative Analysis of Developing Country               C. Wallich&#13;
Adjustment Experiences in the 1970s: Low-Income&#13;
South Asia&#13;
488     Developments in and Prospects for the External             N. Hope&#13;
Debt of the Developing Countries: 1970-80 and&#13;
Beyond&#13;
489     Global Energy Prospects                                    B.J. Choe&#13;
A. Lambertini&#13;
P. Pollak&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG3881.5 .W57 W67 no.476 c.3&#13;
Bryant, Ralph C.&#13;
- Notes on the analysis of&#13;
capital flows to deve.loping&#13;
I |   nations and the "recycling    I&#13;
DATE | NAME AND EXTENSION     ROOM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554957">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1981/08/1554957/notes-analysis-capital-flows-developing-nations-recycling-problem
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1981/08/1554957/notes-analysis-capital-flows-developing-nations-recycling-problem</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1981/08/1554957/notes-analysis-capital-flows-developing-nations-recycling-problem</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/19/000178830_98101903411533/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/19/000178830_98101903411533/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1981-08-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-08-19T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Notes on the analysis of capital flows to
            developing nations and the "recycling" problem
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper summarizes and then
            criticizes the conventional analysis of the interrelations
            between financial markets in the industrialized countries
            (the North) and capital flows to the developing nations (the
            South). The proximate purpose of the paper is to clarify
            concepts and analytical perspectives. Its ultimate purpose
            is to suggest how a study of capital flows to the South
            should be integrated into an overall macroeconomic analysis
            of the effects of the economic environment in the North and
            in the oil-producing countries on the South's prospects
            for development.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Notes on the analysis of capital flows to
            developing nations and the "recycling" problem
        </docna>
        <display_title>Notes on the analysis of capital
            flows to developing nations and the "recycling" problem</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1981/08/1554957/notes-analysis-capital-flows-developing-nations-recycling-problem</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Financial Intermediation,Earth Sciences &amp; GIS</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>BRYANT, R.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903411533</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Macro/non-trade</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 476</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Balance of payments; Capital markets;
            External debt; International trade; Investment policy;
            International markets
            adverse consequences,balance of
            payments,bank reserves,banking crises,borrowing,borrowing
            costs,capital adequacy,capital flows,capital goods,central
            bank,centrally planned economies,consumers,currency
            units,debt,deposits,development assistance,economic
            activity,economic conditions,economic development,Economic
            growth,economic
            policies,economists,employment,Equilibrium,exports,Financial
            assets,financial intermediaries,financial
            intermediation,financial markets,foreign
            exchange,imports,income,income elasticity,industrial
            economies,inflation,interest income,interest rate,interest
            rates,international reserves,international
            trade,macroeconomic analysis,Monetary Policy,national
            economies,natural resources,net value,oil,Oil
            Prices,OPEC,Partial Equilibrium
            Analysis,path,petroleum,point,policy instruments,price
            elasticity,price increases,price
            indexes,producers,purchasing power,quotas,recycling,reserve
            assets,risk premium,SECURITIES,statistical data,supply
            curve,terms of trade
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP476</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Formulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Implementation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Productivity-Led Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary and Exchange Rate Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>GIS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Geographical Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Land Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Intermediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Account</ml:concept><ml:concept>Current Account</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Intermediaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Balance of Payments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Geographic Information Systems</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>