<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>hORLD BANK STAFF X%O4KING PAPERS&#13;
Number 643&#13;
Prices, Terms of Trade, and the Role of&#13;
Gvoernment in Pakistan's Agriculture&#13;
Kee-Cheok Ciieone&#13;
Fmmanuel H. D'Silva&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Na' h: gton, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copynght n. 1984&#13;
Trhe International Bank for R-econstruction&#13;
arid Development I THE WNORLD BANK&#13;
1S18 H Street, N W.&#13;
Washington, DC 23033, U.S A&#13;
First printing Apnl 1984&#13;
All rights resened&#13;
Mianufactured in the United States of Armt nca&#13;
This is a work:ng document published inforrrallv by the World Bank To&#13;
pren.ent the resul:s of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has&#13;
not bevn prepartd in accordance with the proce-ures appropriate to formal&#13;
pnnted texts, and the World Bank accepts no rtsponsibility for errors The&#13;
publication is supplied at a token charge to defray part of the cost of&#13;
manufacture dnd dasuiMitiuCila&#13;
Tke vie%s and interpretations :n this document are those of the adthor(s) and&#13;
shou!d no&gt; be attributed to the World Ba nk, to its affiliated nrga/i/ations. or to&#13;
any individual a;o.ng on their   AnvL   m . Any raps uLd have been prepared&#13;
solely for the convenience of the readers, tne denominations used a id the&#13;
cundanes shown do not implv. on the part of the World Bart, and its iffiliates.&#13;
any judgment on the legal status of any tetntorry or any endorsement or&#13;
acceptance of such Nbrundanes&#13;
The full range of World Bank publication, is described in the Catalro of 1V%rld&#13;
Bantk Publicatiols, the continuing research ptogram of the Bank is outlined in&#13;
lNrId Batik Rs-earchl I'r(Nram ,1r,strarts of Current Siudres Both booklets are&#13;
updated annuaNly, the most nrcent edition of each is available without charge&#13;
from the Publication; Sales Unit of the BKank in Washington or from the&#13;
European Office of tire Bank. 66. avenue d 'I.na, 75116 Pans, France&#13;
Kte--Cheok Cheong is an economist in tht South Asia Country Programs&#13;
£p- -tmenn. and Emnmanuel 1i D'Silva a, editor in the Publications&#13;
Department, of the World Bank.&#13;
_ibrary of Congres5 Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Cheong, Kee Cheok.&#13;
I'r ces. terms of trade, and Llie role of government&#13;
in Pakistan's agriculture.&#13;
1-orld 3ank staff working ,apers: no. 643)&#13;
Bibliograptly: p.&#13;
1. Agricultur.--Ecnnorric a. pects--Pakistan.      2. Agri-&#13;
culture arnd sorte--Pakistan.      1.  )'Silva, EmrmanuelI H.,&#13;
'k951-     .   II. Title.    ill. Series.&#13;
IID2075.5.C53   1984        338.1'C9549'1       84-7273&#13;
M15E 0-8213-03f1-9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ALSTRACT&#13;
Despite the importar.ce of agriculture to the national economy&#13;
of lPakistan and the major role played oy the government in its&#13;
development, a number cf k.oy izsues have not been adequately&#13;
addressed by existing stu ic-.   This paper provides an empirical&#13;
basis for discussion of changes in the agricultural terms of trade,&#13;
growth of agricultural productivity and Incomes, priein7 of&#13;
a6rxcultsural inputs and outputs, and subsidizatimn and taxation of&#13;
agricultur,&#13;
The paper notes that the terms of trade between agriculture and&#13;
the other sectors have not eignificantly deteiiorated during che&#13;
period 1960-83.   Indeed, in absolute terms, farmers' purchasir3 power&#13;
vhether zeasured in terms of the quantity of output or per unit of&#13;
productive effort, has actually Improved, even if gradually.     Hence,&#13;
the farmers' ability to pay for agricultural inputs, d._pite gradual&#13;
increas.J in their prices, did not erode over the years.&#13;
Net returns to farmers have increased, until recently, because&#13;
of increases in crop prices and because of substantial government&#13;
subsidies for inputs. The recent sharp increaseu in fertilizer&#13;
prices have reversed this trend, but they should not affect the&#13;
continued profitability in the -,se of fertilizer even at higher&#13;
prices. Similarly, despite increases over the past fou- years, water&#13;
charges remain a small proportion of total production costs and are&#13;
in any cese, subptantially less than the estimated scarcity value of&#13;
irrigation w'ater co the farmer.&#13;
Until 1977, agricultuP zs,,ILrJbiated more in taxes to the&#13;
economy than It t-&amp;k out throtigh financial subnidies, but the&#13;
position has reversed since then.    Tiere has been a decline in nt-&#13;
aubsl6ies, particularly after I98i, mainly because of reduction in&#13;
fertilizer subsidies. With the government committed to eliminate&#13;
fertilizer subsidies by 1985, this trend is expected to continue.&#13;
Movever, the economic taxation of wheat and ba.mati rice (as a reault&#13;
of setting domestic prices belov their tnternational levels) in&#13;
cootrast to the economic subsidies provided to sugar (to offset&#13;
higher domestic prices relative to imports) should be a matter of&#13;
concern. The paper argues thit appropriate price policies that are&#13;
responsive to '-hanges in irternational ;rices are likely to hase as&#13;
salutary an effect as any at:empt to reduce financial subsidies or to&#13;
increase taxes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
EXTRACTO&#13;
Pese a la importancia de la agricultura para la economia de Pakistin&#13;
y la gran influencia del Gobierno en el desarrollo del sector agropecua-&#13;
rio, hay varios aspectos furidamentales que no han sido abordrdods debida-&#13;
mente en lrs estudios que se han realizado. LELc tr-abajo proporciona una&#13;
base empirica para examinar las variaciones en la rilaci6n de intercambio&#13;
de este sector, cl aumento de la productividad y los ingresos agricolas,&#13;
los precios de los .nsumos y prodluctos agricolas, y la subvenci6n y tribu-&#13;
taci6n de la ag:ricultura.&#13;
En el trabajo se obscrva que la relaci6n de intercambio entre la&#13;
agrIculzur4 y los demas sectores no se deterioro en medida significativa&#13;
durante el periodo de 1960-83. En realidad, en terminos absolutos, el&#13;
poder adquisitivo de los agricultores --medido en funci6n de la cantidad&#13;
de producto o del costo de :os insumos-- ha mejorado, aunqu3 gradual-&#13;
me-nte. Por consiguiente. la capacidad de los agricultcres para comprar&#13;
insumos agricolas no ha disminuido con el tiempo, pese el aumento gradual&#13;
de sus precios.&#13;
llasta hace poc:o, los ingresos netos die los agricultores aumentaron,&#13;
debido a incrementos de los precios de los cultivos y a las considerables&#13;
subvenciones gubernamentales a los insumos. Esta tendencia so ha inver-&#13;
tido a causa de los pronuncisdos aumentos recientes de los precios de los&#13;
fertilizantes, pero esto nD deberia afectar .- la rentabilidad continua del&#13;
uso de estos, aun cuando sus preclos sean mas altos.    Asimismo, peso a los&#13;
aumentos de los ultimos cuntro anos, las tarifas que se cobian por el agua&#13;
siguen representando una proporcl6n pequenia de los costos totales de pro-&#13;
ducci6n y, en todo caso, son muy inferiores al precio en ra2.on do la esca-&#13;
sez quo, ;egun se ha estimado, tendria que pagar el agricultor por el agua&#13;
para riego.&#13;
Hasta 1977 la agricultura aport6 mas a la economia en forma de impues-&#13;
tos que lo que recibi6 de esta en forma de subvenciones financiera!, pero&#13;
la sItuaci.6n ha camb:ado desde entonces. Las st'bvenciones notas han dis-&#13;
minuldo. en par.lcular a partir de 1981, principalmente debido a la reduc-&#13;
ci6n do las otorgadas a los fertilizantes.    Se preve que esta tendencia&#13;
contInuara, pues el Gobierno esta decidido a eliminar las subvenciones a&#13;
los fertilizantes hacia 1985.   Sin embargo, la tributaci6n e-con6mica del&#13;
trigo y el arroz Basmati (coMo resultado de la fijaci6n de precios inter-&#13;
nos Inferiores a los internacionales), por oposicl6n a las subvenciones&#13;
econ6micas que se otorgan al azucar (para compensar el precio interno, quo&#13;
es mns a)to que el de importaci6n), deberia ser motivo de preocupacl6n.&#13;
En el trabajo --a aduce que unas politicas de preclos adecuadas quo respon-&#13;
dan a las variaciones de los preclos internacionales tienen las mlsmas&#13;
probabilidades de surtir efectos saludables que los inte.:tos de reducir&#13;
las .-ivenciones financieras o de aumentar los Impuestos.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
M1a1gri la place que tient l'agriculture dans Vteconomie pakistaniaise&#13;
et le role que 1'Etat : , i dans son d6velop?ement, les etudes publ:cees&#13;
jusqu"a present laisses      :- l'ombre un certain nomnbre de questions cle.&#13;
Cette otude fourn't des u-..nees emplriques et examine quatre paramitres du&#13;
secteur agricole : variations des termes de lechange, croissance de la&#13;
produc.:ivite et des revenus, dtermrination des prix des intrants et ces&#13;
produi:s, et imposition et suh.entions.&#13;
11 apparait que Ies termes de l'echange enLre I'agriculture et les&#13;
autres secteurs ne so sont pas sensiblement d6grad;s au cours de la&#13;
periode 1960-83.   E,, 'iit, en cermes absolus, le pouvoir d'achat des&#13;
paysans, mesuro en foiiction de la product-on ou dui co:it des intrants,&#13;
s'est meme ameliore piM ai peu.   Bien que ies prix des facteurs de pioduc-&#13;
tion aient progressivi!rent augmente, les paysans ne sont donc pas moins a&#13;
mime de le. payer qu'-l y a quclques annees.&#13;
Jusqu'a une 6poquoe recente, les bene'fces nets des exploitants aug-&#13;
mentaient, par suite de la hauss;. des prix des r6coltes et des 'crte. sub-&#13;
ventions de I'Etat aux intrants agricoles. Cette tendance s'est renversce&#13;
a la suite de la brusque augmentation du prix des engrais, qui ne devralt&#13;
toutefois pas compromettre la rentabili:e de l'emploi des engra);. De&#13;
mime si les redevances d'eau ont ete relev6es au eou:s de. quatce der-&#13;
nieres annees, elles ne repr6sentent toujours qu'unc petite partie du cout&#13;
global de la production, et elles sont netteent. inf6rioures a In vdleur&#13;
de rarete qu'a l'eau d'irrigation pour le paysan.&#13;
Jusqu'en 1977, les imp6ts que l'Etat percevait sur l'agrlculture&#13;
etaient superieurs nux subventions qu'il lui versait. Mais la situa3Lion&#13;
s'est inversee depuis lors.    Aujourd'hui, et surtout depuls 1981, les sub-&#13;
ventions nettes sont en baisse, du fait surtout de la r6duction des sub-&#13;
ventioris aux engrais.   Les pouvoirs publics s'etant engages a 6l1mincr les&#13;
subventions aux engrais d'icl a 1985, cette tendance devrait se pour-&#13;
suivre. Cependant, la taxation economique du b1i et du riz basmati (dont&#13;
le prix sur le marche national est infe'rieur . :-ur cours sur le marche&#13;
internat:onal), compario a la subvention economique dont b6neficie Ie&#13;
sucre (du fait que son prix interieur est Iev' par rapport a celui du&#13;
sucre importe), est inquietante. Cette etude -ontre que des politiques de&#13;
prix appropriees et modulees en fonction des -ouvenents des prix interna-&#13;
tionaux peuvent avoir un effet tout aussi salutaire que toute tentative de&#13;
reduire. Ies subventions ou d'augmenter les io:s.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PRICES, TERMS (IF TRADE. AND THr ROLE OF GOVERNMENT&#13;
III PAKISTAN'S AGR[CULTURE&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
'.  INTRODUCTION    ..........................................&#13;
II.  AGRICULTURE'S TEPYS OF TRADE     ....... ..................            3&#13;
III.  OUI¶FUT GROWTH AND PRODUCTIVITY     ........................           8&#13;
IV.  INPUTVOUTPUT PRICES AVD FAR.MERS' INCOMES     ....     ..........     12&#13;
V.  TA.XES, SUBSIDIES, AND RESOURCE TRANSFERS      ....    ..........     24&#13;
VI.  CONCLUSIONS    ...........................................            37&#13;
Annex Tables&#13;
A.l - The Grovth of the AgriculLiral Sector in&#13;
Pakistan, FY70-FY81    .............................           42&#13;
A.2  -   Ratios of Wholesale Price Indices for Food,&#13;
Raw Materials and Manufactures, FY70-FY8I      .......        43&#13;
A.3   -  Real Total and Agricultural GDP Per Capita,&#13;
FY60-FY82   .......................................            44&#13;
A 4  -   Agricultura' Input Price Indices, FY70-FY82      ....   .....      45&#13;
A.5  -   Procurement and Minimum Prices for Agricultural&#13;
Co:=:odicies and Sale Prices of Fertilizers,&#13;
tY7J-FY82   .......................................            46&#13;
A.6  -   The Growth in Agriculturel Producti.;iLy, FY6O-FY81      ..        47&#13;
A.7   -  Ratios of Crop Price Indices to Agricultural Input&#13;
Price Indices, FY71-FY82     ........................          48&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. INTRODUCTTON&#13;
Agriculture remains the most important economic activity in&#13;
Pakistan, accounting for 30% of the gross domestic product (CDP). Crops&#13;
provide 69X of agricultural GDP. livestock 28%, and fishing and forestry the&#13;
.emaiuing 3%. Taxes on products of agricultural origin make up roughly 20%&#13;
of public revenue, vhile agricultural vorkers account for over 50% of the&#13;
vorkforce. Products originating in the agricultural sector figure&#13;
prominently in ?akistan's trade; :ice, cotton, yam and cloth are major&#13;
exports vhil,e edible oil and (until recently) vheat are the majinr imports.&#13;
The government plays a major role in the agricultural economy. It&#13;
sets procurerment or minimum prices for crops (wheat, rice, sugarcane, and&#13;
cotton), and fixes ;:ices for agricultural products (sugar and flour), and&#13;
for inputs (such as fertilizer and water).    Although to a dimini2hinR extent,&#13;
it participates in the processing, production, import and domestic markeLing&#13;
of agricultural crops and key inputs. Incentives to farmers have been&#13;
provided through subsidies; in fiscal year (FY) 1980, these subsidies (both&#13;
producer and consumer) awmsunted to about Rs 6,000 million, or about 28% of&#13;
che country's annual development plan. I/&#13;
Despite the importance of agriculture and the major government role,&#13;
not many studies of its impact _n incomes, and on the transfer of resources&#13;
1/ See "Potential for Irrigated Agricultu:al Development in Pakistan,"&#13;
mimeo prepared by Tariq Husain, July 1981; Pakistan: Economic&#13;
Developments and Prospects, April 1982; &amp;nd Pakistan: Special&#13;
Agriculture Sector Reviev, Vol. 1, January 1976. (These are internal&#13;
World Bank documents vith restricted circulation.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
among sectors, have emerged. jJ This appears to be partly the consequence of&#13;
paucity of data; while terms-of-trade indices between Pakistan and the rest&#13;
of the world are part of the country's official statistics, up-to-date infor-&#13;
mation on intersectoral terms of trade is less readily available. -Even so, a&#13;
number of views expressed on Pakistan's agriculture appear not to have been&#13;
based upon any analysis of existing data.    Among the'e views are that&#13;
agriculture's terms of trade have been declining cver the years, that a major&#13;
factor for the relative stagnation of agriculture is its lack of&#13;
productivity, that improvements in yields have made only marginal contribu-&#13;
tions to growth in agricultural output, and that the mobilization of resour-&#13;
ces in agriculture has been inadequate.&#13;
The purpose of this paper is to provide an empirical basis for&#13;
diocussion of four- isisues.&#13;
O Changing trezdd in the terms of trade for agriculture.&#13;
O The growth of agricultural incomes and productivity.&#13;
O The prices of agricultural inputs and outputs and their relationship.&#13;
O Subsidies for, and taxation of, agriculture.&#13;
These issues are examined in the context of the government's role in&#13;
agriculture.&#13;
1/ Among several studties on this subject are Gotsch, C. and G. Brown,&#13;
Prices, Taxeo and Subsidies in Pakistan Agriculture. 1960-1976, World&#13;
Bank Staff Working Paper Number 387, April 1980; Mahmood Hasan 'han,&#13;
Underdevelopsent and Agrarian Structure in Pakistan, Boulder, Westviev&#13;
Press, 1981.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
II. AGRICULTURE'S TERMS OF TRADE&#13;
As countries advance economically, there is a progressive decline in&#13;
the share of agriculture in SDP. In Pakistan, wvile the real value added in&#13;
agriculture increased, on the average, 2.7% per year between iY70 and FY82,&#13;
its sh.:e of the total GDP fell from 39% in FY70 to 31% in FY82.       In&#13;
contrast, the share of manufacturing (including mining) increased from 16.5%&#13;
to 17.9% during the same period.&#13;
An important measure of agriculture's position relative to other&#13;
sectors is its termis of trade (TOT), or the relationship between the prices&#13;
of goods bought and sold by farmers. There are at least two reasons why&#13;
economists are interested in agriculture's TOT.      First, it indicates whether&#13;
income is being transferred out of agriculture. Second, it signals the&#13;
strength of incentivcs to the agri-uiture sector to adopt inrnovations and to&#13;
produce more.&#13;
Fcur terms-of-trade concepts are used in this section.      The first&#13;
and most common index of TOT is the net barter teros of trsde, which is an&#13;
index of the ratio of pricPs of agricultural products to the prices of&#13;
manufactured goods. 1/ This index is estimated for FY60-FY83 in column I of&#13;
Table 1. rn the early 1950s, trade-restricting policies have turned the&#13;
terms of trade against agriculture.    From the mid-1950s to mid-19609, this&#13;
1/ See UNCTAD, "Tenrs of Trade and the Concept of Import Purchasing Power&#13;
of the Expor:s of Develop:ng Countries," Geneva, March 1966, Appendix r,&#13;
for a discussion of terms-of-trade concepts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
situation :is reversed on account of the sl-ver grovth of agriculture relative&#13;
to industry, bad veather and a dec.ine in the import of American vheat under&#13;
PL-480 fol;owed by a slight decline toward the end of the 1960s in the years&#13;
marked by the ouset of the "green revotution." LJ Hovever, despite some&#13;
variations shovn in column 1, a declining trend in agriculture's terms of&#13;
trade has not been observed over the past two decades.&#13;
1/ Levis, S.R. Jr. "Recent Movements in Agriculture's Terms of Trade in&#13;
Pakistan," The iPakistan Development Review, Autumn 1970.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
Table 1:   AGRICULTURAL TER.S ($ TRADE IN P,.JISTAN. FY60-FY83&#13;
Fiscal       Net Rarter      Output Index        Incoee           Total Factor        Single Factor'al&#13;
year     Terms of TradelD    (FY60-100)    Terms of TradeLb    Productivity Index   Terms of Trade/c&#13;
(FY60    !00)&#13;
1960           100               100              100                 100                  100&#13;
1961           106                100             106                  91                   96&#13;
1962           100               109              109                  95                  104&#13;
1963,          '95                119             113                  98                   93&#13;
1964           101                118             119                  99                  190&#13;
196'           106               128              136                 102                  108&#13;
1966           100               127              127                  99                   99&#13;
.967           108                135             !46                 103                  111&#13;
1968           104               157              163                 117                  122&#13;
1969           9)4                168             158                 325                  118&#13;
19470           q5               186              177                 140                  133&#13;
1971            94                174            '164                 129                  121&#13;
1972            94               183              172                 13!                  123&#13;
1973           1(0                188             188                 129                  129&#13;
1974           IC00              196              196                 131                  1 5.&#13;
1975            90                187             168                 125                  112&#13;
1976            E17               199             173                 130                  113&#13;
1977            87                203             i79                 130                  114&#13;
1978            93               209              194                 131                  122&#13;
1979            99               219              237                 128                  127&#13;
1980            93               239              222                 135                  126&#13;
1981           52               249              232                 136                  125&#13;
1982           100               258              258                 n.a.                 n.a.&#13;
1981/d         100               n.a.             n.n.                n.a.                 n.a.&#13;
La Calcu:ated fro= ration of GNP deflators, witb FY60-100.&#13;
Lg  tlet barter terms of trade x quantum ir.dez of' utput&#13;
Ic  Net bar:er ter-- of trade x productivity index.&#13;
'd  Estiasted.&#13;
Sources:   (1) S:atistics Division, Government of Takzstan.&#13;
(2) W'izarat. S., 'Technical Change in Pakistan'a Ay:iculture: 1953-54 Er, 1977-78,"&#13;
Researcb Report No. 120, ?ak     ran eInstitute of D-velopnent Economics,&#13;
Feb. 198!.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
T3ble 2:   RATIOS OF WHOLEZALE PRICE INDICES FOR AGRICULTURE Tn THE&#13;
WHOLESALE PRICE INDEX FOR MANUFACTURES, FY70-FY82/a&#13;
Fiscal&#13;
year      Food  Raw materi&amp;19   Wheat   Rice  Sugar   Cotton  Meat   Vegetables&#13;
1970        i00       100         100     100   100      100    100      100&#13;
1971        102        105        100      95    96      118    115      130&#13;
1972        105       103         111      97    90      125    114      102&#13;
1973        106       114         100     128   105      133    111       91&#13;
1974        112       113          96     125   114      150    120      229&#13;
1975        124       109         127     123   121      115    142      130&#13;
1976        119       113         112     122   121      125    145      132&#13;
1977        118       112          98     123   108      142    142      178&#13;
1978        123       114         108     135   104      157    147      160&#13;
1979        120       123         112     114    97      178    142      143&#13;
1980        118       113          99     101    86      142    140      140&#13;
1981        115        113         95     110   111      140    149      132&#13;
1982        129       114         110     121   126      144    n/a      n/a&#13;
/a For all wholesale price indices, FY70-100.&#13;
Source:  Ministry of Finance, Planning and Economic Affairs.&#13;
The other three terms-of-trade indices used to determine the rela-&#13;
tive status of agriculture are:&#13;
o Wholesale price rstios. Agricultural prices relative to the&#13;
price index of manufactured goods were 'zigher in FY82 than in&#13;
FY70, the base year (see Table 2).&#13;
O Income terms r, trade. This is a measure of the purchasing power&#13;
of agriculture. As a result of the rising trend of agricultural&#13;
output, there was steady inprovenent in purchasing power (over&#13;
250% between FY60 4nk -Y82) as measured by the income TOT.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
o  Sirnle factorial terms of trade. i) This index re.lects the&#13;
puichasing power of agriculture per unit f productive effort.&#13;
The gradual, if erratic, increase in this index (show-n in column&#13;
6 of Table 1) is mainly the result of improvements in the produc-&#13;
tivity of inputs used during the past two decades.&#13;
The overall trends in these terms-of-trade indices indicate that in&#13;
absolute terms, farmers    purchaFing pover, whether measured in terms oj Fhe&#13;
quantity of output, or of the unit of prod-.tive effort, has increased.&#13;
Hence, farmers' ability to pay for agriculttral inputs h.s not been eroded&#13;
over tie years, a conclusion also emphasized by other studies. 2/ liowever,&#13;
br RuFe of rhe ways they are defined, these indices are not the most direct&#13;
ceasures of farmers' welfare, nor can they be used to infer whether farmers&#13;
are better off than those in the nonagricultural sector. These major issues,&#13;
however, are the subject of the rest of this paper.&#13;
1/  This is defined as the product of the net bartpr index by an index of&#13;
factor productivity. For Pakistan's agriculture, Wizarat has constructed&#13;
a total productivity index which is the ratio of an index of agricultural&#13;
value added to an aggregate index of agricultural inputs. The in?uts&#13;
considered are land, labor, and capital. The last is approximated by&#13;
number of tubewells and the livestock population. Three alternative&#13;
definitions for land--cropped area, net area sown, and cultivated area--&#13;
were used. Clearly, the usefulness of the single factorial index depends&#13;
on the validity of the productivity index. See Wizarat, S., "Technical&#13;
Change in Pakistan's Agriculture: 1953-54 to 1977-78," Research Paper&#13;
No. 120, PIDE, Feb. 1981.&#13;
I/  See, f-or instance, Chaudhary, M.A. and M.M. Ashraf, "A Study of the&#13;
Level cud Structure of Agricultural Pricing and Taxation with Particular&#13;
Reference to Water Charges," PIDE, March 1980; nnd Ljung, P., "Water&#13;
Chargeti: P-roblems Projec:s Review" - Fall 1979, South Asia Region, (an&#13;
interr:al Wcrld Bank docu=ert with restricted circulation).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
III. OUTPUT GR01Mr AND PRODUCTIVITY&#13;
Of the factors influencing the agricultural terms of trade, output&#13;
recorded hiigher growth during FY70-FY82 than in earlier decades. This growth&#13;
has often been attributed to expansion of acreages rather than to improve-&#13;
ments in yields. O1 As Table 3 shows, however, this judgment is not always&#13;
consistent with the evidence, and is, in any case, &amp;n oversimpli.ication.&#13;
Over the period lY70-FY82, growth in yields was more important in contribut-&#13;
ing to growth in output in 5 ouc o. ' yea-; for cotton, 6 out of 8 for rice,&#13;
9 out of 11 for whea:, and 3 out of 9 for sugarcane.&#13;
At the same time, the decline in yields played a dominant role in&#13;
the fall in output in 6 ytars out of 7 for cottoil, 3 out of 4 for rice, 2 out&#13;
of 2 for wheat, and 3 out of 4 for sugarcane. Even when averages aO,- taken,&#13;
the results, vary significantly among crops and time periods. For cotton and&#13;
whest, improvemento in yielde played a major rwle in increasing output&#13;
:-aidlees of the time period selected. The reversce is true for rice and&#13;
sugarcane, but in both cases, yieleD :.-oved after FY79.       Insofar as&#13;
imp:-ovementa in productivity are associated vith an in.rease in yield, the&#13;
evidence from Table ' points LO a greater role for productivity in the his-&#13;
torical growth of agricultural output thac is often admitted.&#13;
1/  Prkiatan:   Economic Development and Prospects, op cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 3: TNE SRARE :)F !X ROVED YIELDS IN THE GROWTH OF OU1TPUT&#13;
OF MAJOR CROPS, FY70-FY82&#13;
Cotton _                Rice           _     Vheat              Sugarcane&#13;
Fiscal     Rate ')f  Share of    Rate of   Share of    Pate of  Share of    Rate of   Share of&#13;
year      Crov4h  Yield Crovtl, Crovth  Yield Grovth  Crovth  Yield Growth  Grovth  Yield Crowth&#13;
___ _ _ ~( 2)    -S)      _ _ ( - ) _ Q ) __ _ ( t)  --  Z  - __ ( Z)  _     ( i _1_  &lt; - 2 _ _&#13;
1970         1.32     56.82       18.16      76.27      10.21     89.03       20.02     27.07&#13;
1971         1.31    195.42       -8.37     12.30      -11 .22    63.90      -12.15    121.23&#13;
1972        30.63     57.82        2.8;     210.99       6.39    147.10      -13.83      4.49&#13;
1973        -0.19    324.05       3.00      59.33        8.01     58.05       -0.08  -4300.00&#13;
1974         6.16    -42.69        5.36     54.48        2.51      0.00       19.87     -4.73&#13;
1975        -3.6.9   347.42      - .58     203.53        ).59   1003.39       11.16    132.08&#13;
1976       -19.99     58.88       13.14     48.78       13.25     58.04       20.12     62.77&#13;
1977       -15.36    108.53       4.54      53.08        5.21     12.48       15.56     16.84&#13;
1978        32.19    111.84        7.78     -15.17      -8.50     91.06        1.88   -128.1)&#13;
1979       -17.b6    116.59       10.92     38.19       18.92     66.54       -9.15      7.,6&#13;
1980        53.86     75.64      -I.: 1     133.92       9.17     61.29        0.63    853.97&#13;
1981        -6.10     41.11      -2.89     -80.97        5.67     82.89       17.68     13.74&#13;
!982         9.42     28.66       S.88      74.71        1.11    151.35       12.99      6.54&#13;
Average:&#13;
FY70-FY79   -1.38     60.14        3.43      27.11       3.46     77.17        0.44   -39'.45&#13;
FY79-FY82   16.6i     72.'!       -0.40   -122.50        5.9(0    77.12        9.99     28.83&#13;
VY70-FY82    2.96     69.14        2.46     33.33        4.07     77.15        2.79    -?I q)&#13;
Note: A negative Ahare for yield impIies an increase in y eId corresponding to a eecrease In&#13;
output or vice-versa.&#13;
Source:  Planning and Development Division. Government of Pakistan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-10-&#13;
Further support for this view is provided in Table 4. VJ The data in&#13;
the Table shov that the incre!ase in the use of inputs is the major factor in&#13;
only 10 out of 17 years that the agricultural value added has increased since&#13;
FY60. Taking tho .ntire period FY60-FY81, the increase in the agricultural&#13;
input index accounted for 65% of ;he increase in output, but this share is&#13;
less than 50% if the period FY70-FY78 is excluded. (During the latter&#13;
period, output soared 1521 during the eight years.) These findings, hove?ver,&#13;
are in no way incon&gt;..A'ent with the perceptior. that the growth 'n produc-&#13;
tivity has been erratic and disappointing, that the grovth of real output per&#13;
capita has been much slover in agriculture than in other sectozs (see Annex,&#13;
Table A.3), and that considerable potential remains for improving yields.&#13;
J/ Since productivity is treated as a residual, the well-known problems&#13;
apply vhen measurement is attempted.    Under fairly restrictive&#13;
assumptions, the share of productivity change in total output grovth is&#13;
equal to ooe minus the share of increase in total inputs.     In Table 4,&#13;
no attempt haa been made to quantify productivity. The lover the share&#13;
of agricultural input in total output growth, hovever, the greater the&#13;
likelihood that productivity is important.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-11-&#13;
Table 4:  THE SHARE OF PRODUCTIVITY IN OUTPUT GROWTH IN AGRICULTURE,&#13;
FY60-FY81&#13;
(Percent)&#13;
Annual Growth of      Annual Growth of&#13;
year        Agricultural          Agricultural        Ratio of Growth Rates:&#13;
Value Added           Input Index/a       Input/Value Added/b&#13;
1960             -1.0                 1.1                     -110.0&#13;
1961             -1.4                 8.7                     -621.4&#13;
1962             3.9                  3.7                       41.3&#13;
1963              7.0                 3.9                       55.9&#13;
1964              2.8                 1.4                       52.2&#13;
1963              6.7                 4.4                       65.6&#13;
1966            -0.4                  2.0                     -500.0&#13;
1967              7.2                 2.9                       40.7&#13;
1968             16.5                 2.'                       15.3&#13;
1969              5.9                -0.7                      -11.9&#13;
1970             12.5                 0.8                        6.0&#13;
1971             -5.1                 2.6                      -51.0&#13;
1972             4.5                  3.3                       72.7&#13;
1973              1.2                 2.3                      187.9&#13;
1974              5.3                 3.7                       70.0&#13;
1975             -3.1                 1.9                      -61.3&#13;
1976              5.9                 2.1                       35.4&#13;
1977              2.0                 1.5                       77.7&#13;
1978              2.1                 1.2                       56.3&#13;
1979              2.6                 5.3                      202.7&#13;
i900              8.3                 2.4                       28.5&#13;
1981             3.8                  3.5                       92.3&#13;
Avertage:&#13;
7V60-FY70         6.4                 2.9                       45.?&#13;
F 70-FY78         1.5                 2.3                      i51.9&#13;
FY79-FY81         6.0                 2.9                       48.6&#13;
FY60-FY81         4.3                 2.8                       65.3&#13;
/   Calculated by Wizarat in her paper "Technical Change in Pakistan's&#13;
Agriculture: 1953/54 to 1977/78," Research Paper No. 120, PIDE, Feb. 1981.&#13;
/b A negative ratio indicates that agricultural value added and the&#13;
agricultural input index change in oppoa'.te directions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-12-&#13;
IV. INPUT/OUTPUT PRICES AND FARMERS' INCOKES&#13;
Wbile output and income terms of trade are important measures of&#13;
agricultural performance, farmers' net incomes are a more appropriate measure&#13;
of their velfare. The data in Table 5 shov that net returno of average&#13;
farmers in Pakistan rose for all major crops during the last decade;&#13;
increases for leading farmers in the Punjab were even higher.&#13;
The data also shov that in the Punjab, Basmati, the finer-quality&#13;
and higher-value rice, had an advantage over other varieties, vh-b: explains&#13;
vhy the leading farmers, in particular, have been switching to the bigher-&#13;
value crop in the last fev years. This conclusion, based on the data in&#13;
Table 5. hovever, needs to be regarded as tentative. IJ In general, bovever,&#13;
better returns and higher yields from the seed-fertilizer revolution have&#13;
significantl7 altered the allocation of resources among various crops. Some&#13;
cropo, sucb as wheat, have retained or extended the acreage that had cue-&#13;
t=marily been devoted to vinter cereals. Just as Basmati hbs replaced coar-&#13;
ser rice, in many areas other high-yielding rice varieties (Irri-6, for&#13;
e7ample) have replaced cotton in tradition%.l cotton-groving areas.&#13;
1/  The smaLl sample sizes used in Table 5 (aee footnote (a)) raise ques-&#13;
tions about hov representat'ive these samples are, while differences in&#13;
the cha:actatiatics of the two types of farmers measured would make&#13;
direct comparisons hazardoue.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 5: TRENDS IN NET 2ZruB2NS PER ACRE FOR MAJOR CROPS, FY70-FY81&#13;
(Rupees)&#13;
Fiscal          Wheat            Rice Paddy            Cotton&#13;
year         (Maii-Pak)     Baamati    Coarse       (American)     Sugarcane&#13;
Averase Farmer. Pakistan la&#13;
1970              54             42         8            32            187&#13;
1976             259           206        120            94            335&#13;
1978             193            60         84           J94            554&#13;
1979             167           209        196          377             102&#13;
1;a0             196            159       240          449             726&#13;
Average Leading Farmer. Puni ab /b&#13;
1975             342           7 C,'      660          496             629&#13;
1'76             372           456        565          701             812&#13;
1977             398           460        539          632             842&#13;
1978             361           429        513          960             991&#13;
1979             570            591       497        1.007             77i&#13;
1980           1,093           753        458        1,315           1,854&#13;
1901           1,198           909        588        1,173           2,236&#13;
La  "Average former' data was obtained from farmers selected by a multi-&#13;
stage sampling design with districts, villages and fornaers making&#13;
up the aamplin   =_it- from each stage.   Tne Ci76 data came from&#13;
1,209 farmers located in 152 villages and 10 districts.&#13;
lk  "Average leading faruers" are those who possess land holdings generally&#13;
betweea 12.5 acres and 25 acres. Generally such farmers produce&#13;
market:able surpluses of agriCultural commodities.&#13;
Source:  Food and Agriculture Division, Ministry of Food and Agriculture;&#13;
'lurvey Reports of Coat of Production of 'ajor Crops.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The increases in crop prices have been partly responsiole for the&#13;
rising trenod in net returns, (see Annex, Table A.5). At the same time, the&#13;
prices of agricultural inputs have also declined in relative terms as a&#13;
result of very considerzble government subsidies (more in the next sectior.).&#13;
!s Table 6 shows, the ratio of fertilizer prices to major crop prires has&#13;
remained relativsely stable over the last decade. LJ This indicates that&#13;
prices of both fertilizers and crops have moved closer together. The excep-&#13;
tions are the years FY73-FY75 for wheat and Irri-6 rice, when sharp increases&#13;
in the price of fertilizer raised the ratio substantially. The further&#13;
increase in fertii:zer prices in February 1980 is reflected in the higher&#13;
rct.o for FY80, but upward adjustments ic crop prices were able to partially&#13;
offset this increase, so that even after two upward revisions in fertilizer&#13;
prices in FY82 and FY83, ratios would be no higher than the levels reached in&#13;
FY80.&#13;
Becaus- output prices in Pakistan have generally kept pace with&#13;
input prices, it it difficult to determine the price-induced effects on input&#13;
use. Gotsch and Falcon have suggested that input demand responses are of two&#13;
types. VJ For example, if the price of fertilizer is lowered, farmers already&#13;
using fertilizer may use more of it, or farmers not previously using chemicals&#13;
XJ See also Annex, Table A.7.&#13;
J   Gotech, C.H. and W.P. Falcon; A. ic..uiural Price Policy and the&#13;
DevplZ-aent of Wost Pakistan, Vol. 1, final report (Cambridge, Mass:&#13;
Organization for Social and Technical Innovation, 1970).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 6: RATIOS OF FERTILIZER PRICES TO CROP PRICES, FY70-FY821a&#13;
Fiocal                            Rice                               Seed&#13;
year            BbPet     Rasm.ati   Irri-6/b     Sugarcane/c      Cottona/d&#13;
1970              1.26      0.61       1.02           7.77            -&#13;
1971              1.36      0.72       1.10           8.41            -&#13;
1972              1.36      0.61       1.10           9.25            -&#13;
1973              1.68      0.61       1.36           6.71            -&#13;
1974              1.79      0.65       1.49           8.93            -&#13;
1975              1.64      0.69       1.52          11.68            -&#13;
1976              1.35      0.55       1.25           8.68            -&#13;
1977              1.27      0.90       1.56           8.17           0.38&#13;
1978              1.27      0.49       1.02           8.17           0.34&#13;
1979              1.04      0.42       0.96           8.17           0.34&#13;
1980              1.49      0.63       1.43           9.98           0.51&#13;
1981              1.28      0.54       1.18           7.71           0.47&#13;
1982              1.42      0.55       1.14           8.85           0.49&#13;
1983              1.47      0.62       1.06           9.79           0.54&#13;
/a  (Sale price of urea-mininum or svtpport price of crop) x 100, in RB per lb.&#13;
Lk  Superior grade.&#13;
Ic  Millgate price, Punjab.&#13;
/d  Variety AC 1344-A.&#13;
Source: Planning and Development Division.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
may noV decide to apply them. Though both typeo of response are important,&#13;
little is known about either of these effects, particularly the latter. It&#13;
is, however, generally believed tnat the price elasticity of iemand is low&#13;
for fertilizer and that its negative price effect is more than offset by the&#13;
positive income effect. _/ Support for the latter is found in numerous&#13;
benefit-cost analyses vhich have demonstrated the continued profitability of&#13;
using fertilizer (see Section V).&#13;
Table 7: VALtVE-CvC. RATIOS OF FERTILIZER USE FOR AVERAGE LEADING&#13;
FARM!ER, PUNJAB, FY78-FY82/a&#13;
Fiscal                                 Rice&#13;
year                Wheat       Basmati     Irri-6      Cotton     Sugarcane&#13;
1978                  2.50         5.25      3.00         6.40         5.56&#13;
1979                  3.29         6.56      3.23         8.75         5.99&#13;
1980                  5.38        12.48      6.09         5.05         8.73&#13;
1981                  4.38        11.81      5.48        3.99          7.93&#13;
1982a                 3.94        11.60      5.68         3.83     -   7.15&#13;
la  The value-cost rat,o is the ratio of the value of output of a crop to&#13;
the cost of fertilizers used to produce it. Avc;age leading farmers ovn&#13;
12.5 to 25 acres of land and havL marketable surpluses of agricultural&#13;
commoditi,eo.&#13;
lb "..L.mated on the basis of fertilizer-crop price ratios in Table 6 and&#13;
grain-nutrient ratios for FY81.&#13;
Source: Planning and Development Divisiou, Government of Pakiatan, "Cort of&#13;
Production of Major Crops under Irrigated and Unirrigated (Barani)&#13;
Conditions."&#13;
i/  See Suleiman, R.M.V., "Prospectc of Fertilizer Demand and Supply in&#13;
Pakistao," National Fertilizer Development Centre, Islamabad, October&#13;
1981.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-1 7-&#13;
The charges for vater, another important input, vary widely depend-&#13;
ing on crops and areas. The charges for sugarcane are about three tines&#13;
those for vheat; those in the areas of salinity control and reclamation&#13;
projects (S'CARP) are about tvice those in areas with canal and tubevell eater&#13;
supplies (see Table 8). All water rates have increased about twofold between&#13;
FY66 a.d FY79. Crop prices however, have riaen, on the average, three to&#13;
four times over the same period, so that in FY80, water charges formed an&#13;
even smaller part of the gross returns to farmers than they did in FY70 (see&#13;
Table 9); these charges have also fallen in real terms. Table 10 shows that&#13;
in canal command areas, water rates in constart prices for wheat had, by&#13;
FY75, fallen to a third of its value in FY66; while for maize and oilseeds&#13;
th:y had fallen to one-fourth. The sharp increase (of 75%) over the !.ot&#13;
'cur years s;hould reverse this trend, but water c:larges remain only a small&#13;
prCportion of total production costs, and an even smaller proportion of the&#13;
vplue of total vater used. L/&#13;
11 See Chaudhary and Anhrez, OD cit., Chapter IV, for estimates of the value&#13;
of irrivated water supply. Taking all crops together, they estimated&#13;
vater charges to be only 2.5% of the total value of irrigated vater.&#13;
This was obtained by multiplying the marginal value product of vater&#13;
(estimated by zegression) by the average volume of water used.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-18-&#13;
Table 8:  WATER CHARGES FOR XAJo0 CROPS IN SELECTED AREAS, FY66-FY79&#13;
(Rupees per acre/feet)&#13;
SCARP Areas          Canal 6 Tubevell WEt:   SUDPY&#13;
Crop                FY66    FY70     FY79           FY66    FY70      '9&#13;
Wheat              14.40   20.80    26.00           7.20   !0.40   13.00&#13;
Cotton             24.00   32.00   40.00            2.00   16.00   20.00&#13;
Rice               22.40   33.72   42.15            1.20   16.86   21.08&#13;
Sugarcane          48.00   71.20   89.00            4.00   35.60   44.50&#13;
Maize              17.28   19.20    24.00           8.64    9.60   12.00&#13;
Oilseede           17.60   20.80   2T.00            8.80   10.40   13.00&#13;
Sourc.:  Chaudhary, H.A. and H.M. Ashcaf, "A Study of the Level and Structure&#13;
of Agricultural Pricing and Taxation vith Particular Refcrence to&#13;
Water Cbarges," PIDE, Il-rch 180.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-19-&#13;
Table 9: SuARES OF FERTILIZER AND WATER IN TOTAL COST AND&#13;
RETURNS FOR HAJOR CROPS, FY70-FY80&#13;
(Percent)&#13;
Crop/                    As Z of Total          As Z of            As Z :i&#13;
Fiscal Year              Production Costla      Gross Return       Net Return/b&#13;
Fertilizer&#13;
WheaE (Mari-Pak)&#13;
1970                          6.0                  5.1                n.a&#13;
1976                         12.8                  9.3                n.a&#13;
1978                         10.4                  9.j               67.0&#13;
1979                         12.2                  9.5               89.2&#13;
1980                         10.8                  8.5               71.3&#13;
Rice Paady (Basm.ati)&#13;
1970                          5.6                  5.0                n.a.&#13;
1976                          7.6                  6.0                n.a.&#13;
1978                          8.1                  7.8              198.0&#13;
1979                          8.6                  6.9               42.2&#13;
1980                         11.0                  9.6              103.3&#13;
Cotton (American!&#13;
1970                          5.9                   5.4               n.a.&#13;
1976                         13.5                 12.2                n.a.&#13;
1978                         10.9                  9.7              115.0&#13;
1979                         12.0                  9.2               49.3&#13;
1980                         10.0                  7.1               26.5&#13;
SuRarcane&#13;
1970                          4.6                  3.8                n.a.&#13;
1976                         11.4                  9.7                n.a.&#13;
1978                          6.6                  5.6               36.8&#13;
1979                          8.6                  8.1              220.7&#13;
1980                          5.9                  4.6               23.8&#13;
la Production cost net of value of byproducts.&#13;
lb Gross returns less total producticn cost.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 9 (cont'd)&#13;
Crop/                  As Z of Total         As % of          As % of&#13;
Fiscal Year            Production Costla     Gross Return     Net Return/b&#13;
Water&#13;
Wheat&#13;
1970                        9.4                 8.0              n.a.&#13;
1976                        7.8                 5.7              n.a.&#13;
1978                        3.5                 3.0             18.0&#13;
1979                        4.5                 3.4             10.5&#13;
1980                        5.8                 4.6              8.6&#13;
Rice Paddy (Basmati)&#13;
1970                       23.5                21.1              n.a.&#13;
1976                       21.7                16.5              n.a.&#13;
1978                        9.7                 9.3            236.0&#13;
1979                        8.5                 6.8             41.5&#13;
1980                        6.4                 5.6             60.3&#13;
Cotton (American)&#13;
1970                        6.6                 6.1              n.a.&#13;
1976                        5.1                 4.6              n.a.&#13;
1978                        4.1                 3.7             34.9&#13;
1979                        4.2                 3.3             17.4&#13;
1980                        4.4                 3.1             11.6&#13;
Sugarcane&#13;
1970                        6.5                 5.3              n.a.&#13;
1976                        4.3                 3.7              n.a.&#13;
1978                        3.6                 3.0             29.0&#13;
1979                        2.7                 2.5             68.0&#13;
1980                        3.9                 3.0             15.5&#13;
Source:  Government of Pakistan, Ministry of Agriculture and Cooperatives,&#13;
Food and Agriculture Division, "A Study on Cost of Production of&#13;
Crops."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 10: WATER CHARGES IN CANAL COMMAND AREAS, FY66-FY78&#13;
(in constant 1978 rupees)&#13;
Fiscal&#13;
year              Wheat    Cotton      Rice    Sugarcane     Maize    Oilseeds&#13;
1966               34.26     57.12     53.31     114.24       41.13     41.89&#13;
1967               '0.95     51.58     48.14     103.15       37.13     37.82&#13;
1968               30.45     50.76     47.38     101.52       36.55     37.22&#13;
1969               29.52     49.20     39.92      98.40       35.42     36.08&#13;
1970               42.80     64.61     68.08     143.75       38.76     42.00&#13;
1971               41.37     63.64     67.06     141.60       38.18     41.37&#13;
1972               40.76     62.70     66.07     139.52       36.62     40.76&#13;
1973               36.00     55.38     58.35     123.21       33.32     36.00&#13;
1974               24.76     38.06     40.11      84.69       22.84     24.74&#13;
1975               10.10     24.78     26.12      57.14       14.87     16.11&#13;
1976               14.66     22.56     23.77      50.20       13.54     14.66&#13;
1977               12.85     19.77     20.84      44.00       11.86     12.85&#13;
1978               10.40     16.00     16.86      35.60        9.60     10.40&#13;
Source:  Chaudhary, M.A. and H.M. Ashraf, "A Study of the Level and&#13;
Structure of Agricultural Pricing and Taxation uith Particular&#13;
Reference to Water Charges," PIDE, March 1980.&#13;
nTe pricing of irrigation vater continues to arouse controversy in&#13;
Pakistan. Although vater charges have been increased from time to time, they&#13;
have never risen as fant as the prices received for agricultural commodities.&#13;
Consequently, the scarcity value of the vater being supplied is still sub-&#13;
stantially above the cost charged to the farmers. One indication of this&#13;
is the sale of vater by private farmers who awn tubewells; these charges are&#13;
some three to ten times those collected by the Irrigation Department. 1]&#13;
G] Gotach, C.H. and W.P. Falcon, Agricultural Price Policy and the&#13;
Development of West ?akistan, op cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The issue of appropriate water charges has been extensively dis-&#13;
cussed in several papers. Several analytic studies in the 1960s have&#13;
estimated the "real," or scarcity value of additional irrigation water in&#13;
Pakistan. 1/ In 1970, Cotsch and Falcon, using the marginal value concept,&#13;
estimated Rs 2 per acre-inch as a "fair approximation to long-run marginal&#13;
cost" for obtaining additional water from both public and private wells. 2/&#13;
The government charged, on the average, Rs 0.4 per acre-inch, while the value&#13;
to farmers often exceeded Rs 5 per acre-inch. These studies are unanimous in&#13;
their conclusion that water charges should be raised to cover at least the&#13;
ope. - .on and maintenance costs of irrigation wells. The main supporting&#13;
arguments for this view are summarized belaw.&#13;
1. Farmers are now better able to pay for the use of water, partly&#13;
because increases in crop prices have exceeded the increases in&#13;
water rates, and partly because productivity (and hence the&#13;
efficiency of water use) has improved. This conclusion needs to&#13;
be tempered to the extent that average figures for net returns&#13;
1/ A Bank study, based on SCARP IV, estimated the value in the range of&#13;
Rs 0.6 and Rs 3 per acre-inch.   Harza Engineering's estimates, valued at&#13;
the spillway of Tarbela Dam, was Rs 15.6 per acre-inch. Tipton and&#13;
Kalmbach"s estimate (also for the SCARP IV area) was Rs 2.6 per acre-&#13;
inch. Thlese differences arise because of the use of different concepts&#13;
and methods of measurements under different soil conditions. But&#13;
whatever the differences, it is clear that what the government charged&#13;
during that period-ranging from Rs 0.31 per acre-inch for rice to Rs&#13;
0.87 for oilseeds-was way below the scarcity value.&#13;
2/ Ibid.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
to farmers mask considerable variations acng feriere qnd among&#13;
holding sizes.&#13;
2.  The distributional impact of vater charges is often highly&#13;
ske.red.  Hovever, vater charges form orly a small proportion of&#13;
the cost of production (as sho-.rn in Table 9), so that farmers'&#13;
ability co pay may nor be severely compromised by even a sizable&#13;
increase in vater rates.&#13;
3.  For the aame reason, raising water charges need not reduce&#13;
farmers' incentives cver the long run. Farmers are fully aware&#13;
of the benefits of irrigation and raising charges is unlikely to&#13;
affect aggregate production. As with fertilizers, estimates of&#13;
the price elasticity of demand for water have been less than&#13;
one in value. j/&#13;
SJ ee Naqvi, S.N.H., et al., "Econometric Model of Pakistan's Economy&#13;
(1959-61) to 19,78-79)," PIDE, December 1981; and Hicks, N., "A Long-term&#13;
Projection Model for Pakistan," September 1977.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
V. TAXES. SUBSIDIES. AND RESOURCE TRANSFERS&#13;
In Pakistan, the role of government in creating infrastructure for&#13;
agriculture has been extremely important because the proper allocation of&#13;
vater is of paramount importance to agricultural production. Vhile both&#13;
agricultural output and input prices have been major instruments of govern-&#13;
ment policy, the government also intervenes in agriculture through taxes and&#13;
financial subsidies.&#13;
The government's financial transfers affecting agriculture conslst&#13;
of taxes on, and subsidies to, the sector. Prior to the devaluation of the&#13;
rupee in 1972, agricultural taxation was light, and no duty vas levied on&#13;
exports. Discrimination against agricultural exports, hovever, took the form&#13;
of unfavorable exchange rates in the country's multiple exchange rate "bonus"&#13;
systez. Export duties on rice and cotton were introduced after devaluation&#13;
and they made up the bulk of all taxes on agriculture in the first half of&#13;
the 1970s. Profits from the rice and cotton export corporations (RECP and&#13;
CECP, respectively), established in 1973, also became, with rising prices,&#13;
major sources of revenue to the government (see Table 11). The decline in&#13;
international prices for Pakistan'o major exports and the need to protect&#13;
Pakistan's agricultural producers led to the removal of export taxes in FY78.&#13;
Profits of the export corporations became the predominant sources of export&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 11: TAXES AND SUBSIDIES IN THE AGRICULTURAL SECTOR, FY75-FY83&#13;
(R:: mill.uao)"&#13;
FY75      FY76     FY77      FY78     FY79      FY80     FY81      FY82/b     FY831c&#13;
Taxes                        1.865     1,432      896       814    1,080     1,710    1,606     1,751      1.029&#13;
Export Duties:&#13;
Rice                      333       241        58       -         -        -         -        -           -&#13;
Raw Cotton                 535      340         1       -         -        -        500      150         462&#13;
Profits of Export&#13;
Corporations:&#13;
Rice (RECP)                769      591        39      504       789      538       530      377         348&#13;
Cotton (CECP)               -        -        662      185        -        -        350        -          -&#13;
Land Revenue                 228      260       136      125       291       172      226       230        219&#13;
Subsidies                      515     1.043      728     1.147    2,222    3,084     3,119     2.601      2,359&#13;
Fertilizer                   326      607        87      617     1,692    2,454     2,457    1,819       1,600&#13;
Plant Protection             112      241       421      347       267      218        62        -          -&#13;
Tubevells                     16       43        48       37        24       22        20        24         24&#13;
Wheat Seeds                   -         6         6       25         8        29        2         8          8&#13;
Net Irrigation Costs/[        61      146       166      121       231      361       578       750        727&#13;
Net Taxes /d                 1,350      389       168     -333    -1,142   -1,374    -1,513      -844     -1,330&#13;
la  Operations and mainttnance costs less water charges.&#13;
/b  Revised estimates.&#13;
/c Budget estimates.&#13;
Id Taxes less subsidies.&#13;
Source: Planning and Development Division.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
taxation. There was virtually no direct tax on agricultural incomes. A land&#13;
tax was levied, but despite restructuring to increase progressivity in 1975,&#13;
revenues stagnated throughout the decade. I! Water charges were alsc levied,&#13;
but revenues from these represented only a fraction of the total operations&#13;
and maintenance cont of the country's irrigation system.&#13;
Subsidies for the import of fertilizers and for the use of pes-&#13;
ticides and herbicides are the major subsidies given to agriculture. The&#13;
rationale for subsidizing inputs is to provide "incentives" to agriculture.&#13;
Unlike higher commodity prices, it is argued, subsidies do not raise directly&#13;
food and rav material prices paid by urban consumers and the growing&#13;
industrial sector; they also ensure that the benefits of government expendi-&#13;
tures accrue only to cultivators using inputs to expand production. jI On the&#13;
1/ Farmers o:n irrigated land were exempt from land taxation if their&#13;
holdings were less than 11 acres. Famsers vith holdings between 25 and&#13;
50 acres had rates of assessment increased 50%. Those with more than 50&#13;
acres had rates increased 100%. Since the winter of 1982, the government&#13;
has introduced a new levy called ushr based on the gross value of&#13;
agricultural production. To make an allowance for production costs, the&#13;
levy is restricted to 75S of the vnlue of production and is collected&#13;
froar landowners and leaseholders (but not tenants) aL a rate of 5% of&#13;
their shatre of the produce. Farmers who produce 948 kg of wheat (or its&#13;
equivalent in value) are exempt. It is too early to make any judgmeat on&#13;
tbe impact of ushr on the transfer of resources from agriculture to other&#13;
sectors, or on the resources it has raised for the government. See&#13;
Jeths, N., S. Akhtar, and M.G. Rao, Domeatic Resource Mobilization in&#13;
Pakistan: elec.ted Issues, World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 632,&#13;
Wasbington, 1984.&#13;
Ij Gotsch, C.H. and W.P. Falcon, ARricultural Price Policy and the&#13;
Development of West Pakistan, Op cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
other hand, subsidies are a burden on scarce public resources. L/&#13;
In thte case of fertilizers, the rate of growth in its use has been&#13;
phenomenal and, along with the use of nev seeds, has been primarily respon-&#13;
sible for spectacular increases in grain production between 1964 and 1969.&#13;
Througbout the 1950s and 1960s, Pakistan maintained a "cheap" fertilizer&#13;
policy vith subsidies, during much of this time, a=ounting to as much as 50%.&#13;
The subsidy decreased in FY70 to about 30%, but rose thereafter, particularly&#13;
between FY73 and FY75; this rapid growth can be attributed to at least three&#13;
factors:&#13;
o F&amp;rmers' purchase price of fertilizer vas kept low after devalua-&#13;
tion to minimize the effect of devaluation on domestic prices of&#13;
basiic foods.&#13;
O  Thc increase in oil prices after 1973 made fertilizer imports&#13;
more expensive.&#13;
O  Fertilizer imports increased rapidly after FY75 as domestic&#13;
production vas unable to aeet demand.&#13;
Government subsidies for irrigation also increased, particularly after FY76,&#13;
reflecting the increasging need for maintenance of Pakist&amp;n's aging irrigation&#13;
mystem.&#13;
T/ Tis is pariticularly true fer fertilizers.     Evidence from India sug-&#13;
gests that 15 years of subsidy ought to be long enough for most farmers&#13;
to have a good acquaintance vith that input. See Shetty, N.S., "Agricul-&#13;
tural Innovations: Leaders and Laggards," Development Digest, April&#13;
1969.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Despite the increases in input prices, taxes collected from agricul-&#13;
ture were substantially larger than financial subsidies prcvided to the&#13;
sector up to FY77, resulting in a net transfer of public resources out of&#13;
agriculture. This situation was reversed after FY78, vhen total financial&#13;
subaidies exceeled tota! tax revenue fron agriculture. The decline in net&#13;
subaidies after FY80 has been due mainly to reduced fertilizer subsidies,&#13;
although reductions in subsidies for pesticides and irrigation vere also&#13;
contributory factors. With government plans to phase out the fertilizer&#13;
subsidy by 1985, under the Three Year Public Sector Development Program, and&#13;
major increases in the price of irrigation water (an increase of 75% in the&#13;
past four years), the level of subsidies is expected to decline in tbe next&#13;
five ycars.&#13;
In addition to financial subsidies, farmers receive an econoxic&#13;
subsidy if the prices for their products are higher than those that obtain in&#13;
the interr.ational market.  The size of this subsidy to producere is given by&#13;
the difference between the output value at domestic (procurement) prices and&#13;
that at vorld prices.   The higher the nominal rate of protection (that is,&#13;
the ratio between doesatic and border prices), the larger is the economic&#13;
subsidy. 1/ The total subsidy given to producers is the sum of financial and&#13;
economic subsidies.&#13;
J  For coqisumers, the subsidy is measured by the difference between the&#13;
value of consumption it world prices and that tt domestic (market)&#13;
prices..&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-29-&#13;
The ratios of domestic prices to international prices for the ma,jr&#13;
crops shown in Table 12 indicate that price discrimination hao historically&#13;
been most severe for wheat and for rice, particularly Basmati. LJ But with&#13;
the procurement prices raised significantly since FY81, domestic prices for&#13;
these crops have moved somewhat closer to international prices. The extent&#13;
of nominal protection for cotton vrs influenced cons:derably by wide fluctua-&#13;
tions in the international price; the recent experience has been a very close&#13;
alignment between the two prices. The only major crop which was protected&#13;
was sugar; domnestic priceo since FY81, whether in export or import parity&#13;
terms, have been substantially above international prices. Since the extent&#13;
of nominal protection is as much e function of exogenous price trends as one&#13;
of domestic piice policies, a strategy of aligning domestic prices to inter-&#13;
national prices will not only minimize the degree but also the variance of&#13;
price discrimination against protection of major crops. 2/&#13;
|j For the export crops o. rice and cotton, incidentals and other unit&#13;
costs have been added to procurement -prices to yield export parity&#13;
prices. For wheat and sugar, import perity prices have been used.&#13;
TJ This does not mean that domestic prices should be allowed to respond to&#13;
shcrt-term fluctuations in international prices, but rather that they&#13;
should be aligned to trends in international prices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-30-&#13;
Table 12:   RATIOS OF DOMESTIC TO INTERNATIONAL PRICES, FY74-FY82/a&#13;
(percent)&#13;
Rice/c&#13;
Fiscal&#13;
year                Cotton/b      Basnati     Irri-6      Wheat/c       Sugarld&#13;
1974                    62             46        35          34            -&#13;
i975                     90            41        46          58            -&#13;
1976                    102           61         77          56            -&#13;
1977                     82            99        97          72            -&#13;
1978                   117             93        75          85            -&#13;
1979                    130            52        75          73            -&#13;
1980                    97             56        74          61            -&#13;
1981                     87           65         70          64            -&#13;
1982                    113           66         94          75(102)      163&#13;
1983/e                   95           68         97          74(98)       206&#13;
/a  For rice and cotton, domestic prices are compared with equivalent export&#13;
parity prices. For wheat and sugar, comparisons are WiLh import parity&#13;
prices; export parity comparisons for FY82 and FY83 are shown in&#13;
parentheses. International prices for rice, cotton and sugar are the&#13;
averages of third and fourth quarter prices in the fiscal year. Those&#13;
for wheat are the averages of the fourth quarter price in the fiscal&#13;
year nnd the first quarter price in the following fiscal year.&#13;
/b  Based on wholesale price of lint, Karachi market.&#13;
/c  Based on procurement prices.&#13;
L/. Based on rationshop sales price.&#13;
Le   International prices based on World Bank commodities price projections.&#13;
Source: World Bank data.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-31-&#13;
Tables 13-15 show calculatinns of total subsidy equivalents for&#13;
vheat and rice betveen the years 1972 and 1981. LJ In revieving these&#13;
calculations, the folloving observations should be noted:&#13;
o In the case of wheat, a part of the marketed produce is procured&#13;
by government for sa'e in ration shops at issue prices (assumed&#13;
to be equal to procurement prices) and the remainder is sold in&#13;
the open market at vholesale or retail prices. Z/ In the case of&#13;
rice, procurement for export is undertaken by RECP and the&#13;
balance is sold in the open market.&#13;
o  The calculatione take into account producers who are also con-&#13;
sumers by considering only marketed output, but do nct explicitly&#13;
recognize middlemen as a group.    The latter buy markftce  output&#13;
at around procurement prices and sell at wholesale or retail&#13;
prices; they are grouped together with consumers.&#13;
O No account is taken of the effects of price distorticns on demand&#13;
or supply.&#13;
Table 13 shovs that if price discrimination is takeu into account,&#13;
producer oubsidies for wheat are all negative, although the price appears to&#13;
J  Corresponding estimates for FY72-FY76 vere calculated by Gotach and&#13;
Brown, OD Cit.   However, these vere based upon sotmewhat different&#13;
assumptions.&#13;
ZI If the issue price is belov procurement price, the assumption under-&#13;
states the cost to the government of intervening in the market. Past&#13;
experience shows that the error resulting from this assumption las been&#13;
insignificaint.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-32-&#13;
have improved from FY74.   This is because of the narroving gap between domes-&#13;
tic prices and import parity prices. Despite this, the adverse effects of&#13;
price discrimination considerably outweighed the favorable impact of finan-&#13;
cial subsidies to the sector. As recently as FY82, the proportional subsidy&#13;
equivalent-the value of the subsidy equivalent as a proportion of the value&#13;
of marketecd production in domestic prices--was as high as -43%.&#13;
H!uch the same picture is presented in Table 14, which shovs cor-&#13;
reaponding calculations for Basmati rice. Up to FY76, both government taxa-&#13;
tion and a very large gap between domestic and international prices. con-&#13;
tributed to a transfer of resources out of agriculture valued at almost, or&#13;
more than, the value of production in domeotic prices. As with wheat, price&#13;
discrimination has been reduced by a closer alignment between international&#13;
prices and export unit cost. For Irri-6 rice, these prices have become&#13;
almort identical by FY82, so that a positive subsidy equivalent--about 9X of&#13;
the value of marketed production at domestic prices--vas recorded. Ho-'ever,&#13;
this close alignment between domestic and international prices has resulted&#13;
mainly from a sharp fall in the latter rather than from an adjustmaent in tbe&#13;
domestic price.   Whether future pricing decisions vill be more responsive to&#13;
international price trends remain to be seen.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
T.ble 12:   PRODUCIB SUBSIDY tQUIVALENTS ro9 UULAT ryl'-rY$21A&#13;
rsii      r Is       rYve v6rr            rIi8      r7 9       n80       ns8l       nT82&#13;
lotel Producti&gt;a76 29                      7674      8491       9144      8367      995%:     10805      11473     11420&#13;
Iatketed  roduct oma            3357       3376      3824       4023      3681      *375       4754       5048      5025&#13;
of vbtcb:&#13;
Coveroment Procurement      1342       1253      1236       2376      1842      1)86       2376      2955       3989&#13;
Ovem .auksi gal*e           2015       2i23      2586      1i4        1839      3392       2378      2093       1036&#13;
Imports                         1288       1164      116t        499      1035      22'6       b02        304&#13;
Ptocvrem,ot prtce              22.50      S7t0      37.00      37.00     37.00     45 ;12     4. '5     54.12      54.12&#13;
A.*  e WSolcaale Fir i C.      24i27      AL47   ?   !.67     !59.73     S9.OS     5047              2 :.2&#13;
jaort Dr..Z reost&#13;
Local M&amp;rF.tL.               77.02      63.08     62.69      53.18     59 .35    71.66      78 .64    80.138      9.58&#13;
,Vlu* of marketed Produc-&#13;
tion. Doetic tricesLi         2227       3601      3906        108      4245       5787      6228      7251       t512&#13;
of vbtchb&#13;
Gove:nneat Procurement       809       !242      1225       2355      1826      1309       29)0      4285       5784&#13;
Open Market Sales           1418       2359      2681       1753      2419      4478       3258       2966      1728&#13;
Valu, of tarrket-d Produc-&#13;
tioo. lZport PriceaLt         6927       S706      6421       5516      5853      8405      10016     10844      12060&#13;
Price Protection/&#13;
tocooic Subsidya             -4700      -2105     -2517     -1408      -1608     -2618      -3788     -3593      -4548&#13;
Direct Producer&#13;
SubsidieaLg                     64        200       398        114       387       1023      1494       1582      1300&#13;
Total Equivalent Subsidy       -4636      -1q05     -2119      -1294     -1221      -1595     -2294      -2011     -3248&#13;
Proportional Subs!dy:&#13;
nioancfel                      2.          .5      10.2        2.8       9.1       11.7      24.0      :1.8       17.3&#13;
Econo.ic                    -211.0      -SX.5     -64.4      -34.3      37.9     -45.2      -60.8     -49.6      -60.5&#13;
Euivalent                   -208.2      -)2.9 s    54.2     -31.5      -28.8     -27.6      -36.8     -21.7      -43.2&#13;
LA  Production in tKusand metric tons, prices in ripees per saund.     wtlus. in *illion rupees, proportions in percent.&#13;
L Assumed equal to 4.A of total produiction. See Ministry of Frood and Agriculture, Government of Pakistan, 'A&#13;
Study of Utilization Patterne of Agricultural. C'modieirs 1977- 8 " March 1980.&#13;
i Based on price of U.S. Red WLnter, f.oJ. G ulf ports to vhich v-e added       rtiiated freight and other costs to&#13;
local markets in Pakititan.  Import price is fc,r last twc quarterd of fiscal year.&#13;
jj  Value of government procurwent is quantity ptccur4d a procurrJent price.      Value of op°n narket eales is&#13;
quantity of open market sal.es x averg*e vwolesole price.&#13;
Li  -uantity marketed a import unit cost, local oa:ket&#13;
LL  Va!ue of marketed production, domestic prit.. - value of marketed production, import price.&#13;
LL  Assieud equAl to    t of !ertilizer subsidy and 40* of net irrigeston cost.    The forner share is based on&#13;
tertiliser usage and tho latter on irrigated acreage.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Tlae _4:    PRODIICZR SUBSIGT NNUIVAL411S FOR MSXh.il RICE rY74-rY82li&#13;
nY74      FY75       rY6       Y?7        FY7R      rY79       Fyn80     FY8I     fn&#13;
Total ProJuction               -86       602       643        660)       550       878        887       9PD      10&#13;
Marketed Producrionn/          316       391        418       4'9        364        571       577       637       6&#13;
of which:&#13;
Cow IO.sen( Procure.gnt    216       287       319        201        193       394        38i       309       3&#13;
rl.f. s.arktc Sales        1OO       104         99       228        17:       177        190       326       3&#13;
Exports                        235       184        311       0;O        298       181        315       410       2&#13;
Procurement Price            6'.00     90.0Dn    90.00      95.00      95.00    110.00     110.00    127.82    139.&#13;
Averave Vholesals Price      86.21     95.09      99.31    119.23     145.53     173.64    132.17    172.16    185..&#13;
ZEport Onit Cost,&#13;
f.o.b. Karichi/j           80.53    115.47    117.08     124.98     126.29    144.36     146.60    169.64    186&#13;
Export Price,&#13;
f.o.b. Karachi            173.00    281.00    I 0.00     126.U0     136.00    276.00     264.00    261.68    318.(&#13;
Value of Marketed Pro-&#13;
duction, Domestic            747      122/.      1236      1584       1463      2273       2379      213S      375&#13;
Price ld&#13;
of which:&#13;
Government Procurement     466       888       1001       673        653      1524       1520      1404      190&#13;
Open Market Salem          281       '36        335       911        810       749        859       734      188&#13;
Value of Marketed Pro-&#13;
duction. Export             1465      2943       2128      1448       13-d      4222       4081      3064       584&#13;
PriceeLe&#13;
Price Protection/&#13;
Economic SubsidyLf          -718     -1719      -892        136        137     -1949      -1702      -91i.    -205.&#13;
Pet Direct SubsidiesA         -233      -178       -100       -22         51        136       201       218       18:&#13;
of which: Subsidies            6        23         54        18         53        136       201       218       18i&#13;
: Taes             -239       -208      -154       -40           -         -         -          _&#13;
Tutal Equivalent Subsidy      -951     -1847      -992        114        190     -1813     -1501       -708     -1867&#13;
Proportional Subsidy:&#13;
Frnaui1'al                  -31.2     -14.5      - 8.1     -1.4        3.6         6.0      8.4      10.2       4.9&#13;
Ec')no:iic                  -96.1    -140.4     -72.2       8.6        9.4      -85.7    -71.5      -43.3     -54.2&#13;
Equivalent                 -127.3    -150.9     -80.3       7.2       12.9      -79.8    -63.1      -33.1     -49.2&#13;
Is  Production in thousand metric tons, prices in rupees per mAund, values in million rupees, proportions in perce&#13;
Lk  Assuned equal to 662 of total production.    See Ministry of Food and Agriculture, Government of Pakistan, "A&#13;
Study of Utilization Patterns of Agricultural Cortmoditiea, 1977-78," March 1980.&#13;
lc  Procurement price plus in:identals and trrnsportation to Karachi.&#13;
Ld Value of government procurement is quantity procured x procurezent price. Value of open market sales is&#13;
quantity sold on the open market x average wholesale price.    Both prices are converted to export unit costs.&#13;
/i Quantity marketed x export price. f.o.b. Xarichi.&#13;
L( Difference between value of marketed production in domestic prices and in export prices.&#13;
IA  Subsidies are taken to be 71 of total fertilizer subsidy and 8? of net irrigation cost.     The former La baed&#13;
on fertilizer conaumption, the latter share on irrigated acreage. Taxis con3ist Of expo . duties on rice, with&#13;
Basati's share being 54t .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Icble lS:   PRODUCER SU6SIDY EQUIVALEITS FOR 1IR1 RICE VFY74-FY82IA&#13;
FY74       FY75      FY76        FY77     FY78        YY79       7Y8O     FY81        FY8:&#13;
Total Productioo               1299      1107       1290        1315     1671        1949       1958     1796        1906&#13;
W.:b::    'zoductioaL&amp;          585       498        580         592      52         877        881      808         85t&#13;
oi which:&#13;
RECP Procurement          288        301        320        430       714         806       742       696        706&#13;
Open Karket Sales          297       197        260        162        38          71       139       112         152&#13;
Exports                         362       294        471         435      582         834       772       834         689&#13;
Procure=ent Price             27.00     40.00      40.00       46.00    46.00       49.00     49.00     62.18       77.19&#13;
Export Unit Cost.&#13;
f.o.b.  aracbia            317.28     53.95      54.92      62.89     63.68       67.92     69.28     85.85     104.21&#13;
Export Price.&#13;
f.o.b. RarachiLj          163.93     107.75      69.99      71.61    107.18       86.42    115.60    139.60     103.41&#13;
Value of Marketed Pro-&#13;
duction, Dowestic&#13;
PricesL                       584       720        85I         998     1283        1596       1635     1858        2395&#13;
Value of Marketed Pro-&#13;
duction. Export&#13;
PriceaLi                     2569      1438       1088        1136     2159        2031      2729      3022        2377&#13;
Price Protect icD/&#13;
Economic Subsidy!X         -1985       -718       -235       -138       876        -435     -1094     -1164          18&#13;
Net Direct Subsidiealk         -219      -109        -33           0       53         136        201      218         187&#13;
of vbicb: Subsidies             6        23         54          18       53         136        201      218         187&#13;
Taxes             -225       -112       -87         -18                    -          -         -          -&#13;
Total Equivalent Subsidy      -2204      -827       -268        -138     -823        -299       -893      946         205&#13;
Proportional Subsidy:&#13;
Financial                   -37.5     -15.1       -3.9        0.0       4.1         8.5       12.3     11.7         7.8&#13;
Economic                  -339.9      -59.7      -27.5      -13.8     -68.3       -27.2     -66.9     -62.6        0.8&#13;
Equivalent                -377.4     -114.9      -31.4      -13.8     -64.1      -18.7      -54.6     -50.9         8.6&#13;
La  Production i_ thousaud metric tons. prices in rupees per maund. valued it million rupees, proportions in percen'&#13;
/b  Assuzed equal to 451 of total production.     See Kinictry of Food and Agriculture, Covernnent of Pakistan. 'A&#13;
Study oi 'trilixation Patterns of Agricultural Cocnodities. 1977-78, March 1980.&#13;
Lc Procurement price plus incidentals and transportation charges to karachi.&#13;
/d  Quantity marketed x export unit coat. f.o.b. Karachi.&#13;
/e  Quantity marketed x export price, f.o.b. Kara,ht.&#13;
Li Aasumed equal to 752 of price of Thai rice, A broken, f.o.b. Bangkok.&#13;
LL  Value of marketed production. domeatic priceo mi7.ss value of marketed production, export prices.&#13;
bh Subsidies are taken to be 72 of fertilizer subsidy and 82 of net irrigation cost. The former is based on&#13;
estimated usage and the latter on irrigated acreage. Taxes consist of export duties, with Irris share assumed&#13;
to be 50S.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Simnilar calculations have not been made for cotton and sugarcane.&#13;
Data required for quantifying total subsidies for cotton are not available;&#13;
hovever, thic ratios between domestic and internaticnal prices for cotton&#13;
(shown in Table 12) suggest that of the four major crops, cotton may be least&#13;
subject to t:he distortionary effects of price policy. Since the domestic&#13;
price referred to ginned cotton, however, it is by no means obvious that this&#13;
has benefited cotton grovers vho sell their produce to ginners. These&#13;
remarks apply also to sugarcane, vhich appears to receive the heaviest&#13;
protection from government prici7g.&#13;
Tvo final points need to be noted. First, for all four major crops,&#13;
incidental unit costs represent sizable components of total domestic prices&#13;
ranging from 23% to 382.   Clearly, greater adainistrative efficiency vill cut&#13;
these costs and may lead to higber prices for producers. Second, although&#13;
discussion of -axes anx subsidies does not give a clear picture of resource&#13;
transfers for the entire agricultural sector, large groups of farmers were&#13;
subject to price discrimination .n excess of direct financial subsidies the&#13;
government provides to themn.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
VI. CONCLUSIONS&#13;
In the preceding sections, secondary data on agricultural prices and&#13;
uctivity, government taxes, and subsidies were analyzed. The analysis&#13;
its us to highlight several interesting implications. These are sum-&#13;
zed below.&#13;
The terma of trade between the agriculture sector and nonagriculture&#13;
Drs have not significantly deteriorated over the last decade. Indeed, if&#13;
it is taken into account, the purchasing power of agriculture has&#13;
ally improved in absolute terms, even if gradually. Similar improvemenL&#13;
iown when productivity increases are incorporated into the terms-of-trade&#13;
c. However, the linitations of the terms-of-trade index should be clear;&#13;
,urchasLng power of agriculture has vorsened if compared with other&#13;
)rs, partly on account of the more rapid grovth of nonagricultural&#13;
)rs.&#13;
The slov grovtb in productivity remains a major concern, par-&#13;
arly since the experiences of the "green revolution" period in Pakistan&#13;
-FY71), and those of other countries, have demonstrated that a much&#13;
r rate of improvement in productivity can be sustained. This has fre-&#13;
ly been discussed in the context of yields making a major contributioi&#13;
e grovth in output among the major crops.    Empirical evidence, hovev:r,&#13;
no support for this conclusion. In the 1970a, improvement in yields&#13;
t least as important as expansion of acreages in promoting the grovth in&#13;
t. Similarly, in the light of available data, it cannot be convincingly&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
argued that grovth in output in recent years has almost exclusively been&#13;
accounted for by higher levels of inputs. Nevertheless, the need for&#13;
measures to raise productivity-such as improving the timeliness and quality&#13;
of inputs, better management techniques, efficient use of resources, and&#13;
minimizing distortionary effects of policy measures-is not diminished by&#13;
these findings.&#13;
3.    Covernment's policies on prices for crops and inputs have, in&#13;
general, been based on the principle of a fair return to farmers. Changes in&#13;
input prices have, therefore, alvays been accompanied (or folloved) by&#13;
adjustment:s in output prices in the same direction. This has contributed to&#13;
a gradual increase in farmers' incomes, although empirical evidence in sup-&#13;
port of this conclusion is, at best, partial and tentative. The observation&#13;
that farmers are more able to pay for inputs because of improvements in their&#13;
net returns finds some support in the data on "average leading" farmers in&#13;
Table 5. Hovever, an important qualification should be noted. Wide varis-&#13;
tions in farm sizes, in output per farm, and in agricultural incomes make&#13;
generalizations from the findings for "average leading farmers" hazardous.&#13;
4.    The argument that sharp increases in fertilizer prices will prove a&#13;
disincentive to farmers has some validity, especially if farmers perceive&#13;
that increases in the prices of inputs vill exceed any corresponding&#13;
increases in the prices chey get for their crops; this, at best, vill be a&#13;
short-term view. The gradual improvemente in agricultural incomes and&#13;
(still) highly favorable benefit-cost ratios in the use of fertilizer should,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
bovever, point to the continued increase in the use of inputs in the medium&#13;
or long term.&#13;
5.    A similar conclusion applies to water charges, and for the same&#13;
reasons. lIaving said this, the principle of relating cost recovery to&#13;
operation-and-maintenance expenditures appears to be no more than an empiri-&#13;
cally convenieut rule of thumb. An economically optimal change can well lead&#13;
to one which recovers both fixed and variable costs. Major determinants of&#13;
this optimum are the demand for vater and the existence of a budget&#13;
constraint. V&#13;
6.    rhe picture of government financial subsidies to agriculture has&#13;
changed dramatically over the decade. In the early 1970s, the sector vas&#13;
taxed much more than it vas subsidized, but the position was reversed after&#13;
FY76. The future level of net financial subsidies to producers vill be&#13;
affected by two major developments. The first is the movement of domestic&#13;
prices closer to border prices which vill affect the profits of the state&#13;
1/  See George, K.D. and J. Shorey, The Allocation of Resources, Loodon,&#13;
Allen and Uovin, 1978. Where there are constraints on the budget, where&#13;
user charges are lov and the demand for the service is in excess of&#13;
supply, there ia a need to raise the user charges to at least the mar-&#13;
ginal cost of providing the service. The additional revenue thus&#13;
garnered can be used to expand the service. It has also been shovo that&#13;
"raising user charges in line vith the efficiency rule suggested vill&#13;
result in more of the poor benefiting as compared to the rich." See&#13;
Thobani, H., Charfinf User Fees for Social Services: The Case of&#13;
Education in Malavi, World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 572, Washington,&#13;
1983.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
trading corporations. The second is the success of the stated policy of&#13;
reducing the fertilizer subsidy and its eventual elimination after 1985.&#13;
7.    Increases in the net financial subsidies to agriculture has been&#13;
used to support arguments that the sector ia lightly taxed. As the calcula-&#13;
tions of economic subb dies have shown, such arguments are extremely&#13;
misleading. The extent of economic subsidization or taxation depends on the&#13;
ratio of domestic to international prices. For wheat and rice, domestic&#13;
prices historically have been substantially below their international levels.&#13;
For sugarcane, producers have been heavily protected. In the absence of&#13;
similar calculations for other crops and activities, the picture for the&#13;
sector as a whole is unclear. However, what can be emphasized is that while&#13;
massive increases in the fertilizer subsidy have raised the financial burden&#13;
of the government in the last three years, appropriate price policies that&#13;
are responsive to changes in international prices are likely to have as&#13;
salutary an effecl: as any attempt to reduce financial subsidies or increase&#13;
taxes.&#13;
8.    The calculations of subsidy equivalent values are based on a number&#13;
of simplifying assumptions and should therefore be regarded as indicative.&#13;
They do nevertheless provide a rudimentary framework for analyzing the&#13;
effecto of government policies on prices and taxes/subsidies on resource&#13;
transfers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
9.    The data presented here do not permit any conclusions to be drawn on&#13;
cbe impact of policy interventions on income distribution. Hcwever, to the&#13;
extent that all producers benefit from higher prices, while benefits from&#13;
subsidized inputs tend to accrue to larger producers, an even stronger case&#13;
can be made for according price policies the highest priority.&#13;
10.    Finally, the calculations in the tables and annexes highlight the&#13;
pitfalls of relying upon findings of other studies. Despite the scarcity of&#13;
data, the existing data base should be able to support much more quantitative&#13;
and qualitative analysis of major sources than exist at present.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX&#13;
Table A.1: THE GROWTH OF THE AGRICULTURAL SECTOR IN PAKISTAN, FY70-FY81&#13;
Agriculture in GDP            Agriculture         Total GDP&#13;
Fiscal            Constant Factor Prices           as Z share     Constant Factor&#13;
year          Million 1960 Rupees   % Change    of Total GDP      Prices x Change&#13;
1970                 12,574              -          38.9&#13;
1971                 12,188           -3.1          37.6                0.1&#13;
1972                 12,611            3.5          38.4                0.9&#13;
1973                 12,821             1.7         36.4                7.2&#13;
1974                 13.357            4.2          35.2                7.7&#13;
1975                 13,074           -2.1          33.2                3.9&#13;
1976                 13,659            4.5          33.6                3.3&#13;
1977                 13,998             2.5         33.5                2.5&#13;
1978                 14,364             2.5         32.0                7.4&#13;
1979                 14,789            2.9          31.5                4.6&#13;
1980                 15,814            6.9          31.5                7.0&#13;
1981                 16,412            4.4          31.1                5.7&#13;
1982                 17,363             5.1         30.8                6.2&#13;
Source: Plannting and Development Division.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
AN?1EX&#13;
Table A..?  RATIOS OF WHOLESALE PRICE IN'DICES FOR FOOD,&#13;
RAW PU1TERIALS AND MANUFACTURES, FY70-FY81&#13;
(FY70   100)&#13;
Fiscal                        Food                  Raw MHterials&#13;
year                    Manufactures               Manufactures&#13;
1970                         100.0,                     100.00&#13;
1971                         102.43                     104.66&#13;
1972                         105.05                     103.26&#13;
1973                         106.32                     114.04&#13;
1974                        il2.42                      113.42&#13;
1975                         ;24.48                     109.22&#13;
1976                         119.84                     113.24&#13;
1977                         118.34                     112.13&#13;
1978                         123.21                     114.46&#13;
1979                         120.08                     123.24&#13;
1980                         118.41                     112.76&#13;
1981                         114.98                     113.14&#13;
Source: Pakistan Economic Survey.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A.3: REAL TOTAL AND AGRICULTURAL GDP PER CAPITA, FY60-FY82&#13;
(1960 Rupees)&#13;
Ratio of Per&#13;
Fiscal           Value (Rs)           Index (FY60-l00)       Capita Agricultural&#13;
year        Total  Agriculture     Total   Agriculture         to Total GDP&#13;
1960          373        171          100       100                  100&#13;
1961          381        166          102        97                   95&#13;
1962          393        172          105       101                   96&#13;
1963          409        176          110       103                   94&#13;
1964          424        175          114       102                   89&#13;
1965          450        179          121       105                   87&#13;
1966          471        175          126       102                   81&#13;
1967          472        179          126       105                   83&#13;
1968          490        195         131        114                   87&#13;
1969          507        198         136        116                   85&#13;
1970          542        211          145       123                   85&#13;
1971          527        198         141        116                   82&#13;
1972          518        199         139        116                   83&#13;
!973          539        196          144       115                   80&#13;
1974          564        199          151       116                   77&#13;
1975          569        189          152       110                   72&#13;
1976          571        192         1i3        112                   73&#13;
1977          568        191         152        112                   74&#13;
1978          592       190          158        111                   70&#13;
1979          603       191          162        112                   69&#13;
1980          628       198          168        116                   69&#13;
1981          648        200          174       117                   67&#13;
1982          671       202          180        118                   66&#13;
Source:   National Accounta of Pakistan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A.4:   LGRICULTURAL INPUT PRICE INDICES, FY70-YY82&#13;
(F760-100)&#13;
Fiscal                                   Transportation                 All&#13;
year      Fertilizer    Seed   Water/a      Charges      Pesticides   InputsLb&#13;
1970           255        125     200          128            46         195&#13;
1971           272        128    200           133            46         205&#13;
1972           257        136    201           143            46         204&#13;
1973           195        179    219           168            79         221&#13;
1974           216        219     2Z6          201           129         231&#13;
1975           278        296    270           258           196         277&#13;
1976           260        291    265           276           291         279&#13;
1977           26 2       322    268           301           326         285&#13;
1978           252        355    300           337           336         312&#13;
1979           237        373    293           364           453         305&#13;
1980           255        386    320           383           500         326&#13;
1981           332        432    371           418           630         382&#13;
1982           428        477    454           477          600          466&#13;
[a  Based on data on irrigation revenues in the Punjab.     These revenueo&#13;
account for some twro-thirds of total irrigation revenues collected by&#13;
the provincial goveranents. Data on the value of irrigation vater in&#13;
the national accounits included land revenue, and could not be -s.ed.&#13;
All other input prices are based oa value of inputs data in the national&#13;
accounts.&#13;
Lb Adjusted for /a.&#13;
Source: National Accocnts of Pakistan; Gover&amp;nent of Pun;ab.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4 -&#13;
ANNEX&#13;
Table A.5:  PROCUREMENT AND MINTMUM PRICES FOR AGRICULTURAL COMMODITIES&#13;
AND SALE PRICES OF FERTILIZERS, FY70-FY82/a&#13;
Fiacal                       Rice               Cotton                        Fertilizer&#13;
year         Wheat    Basaati    Trri-6    (Seed Cotton)/b    Sugarcane/c     (Urea)/d&#13;
1970          17.00      35.00     21.00          -               2.75           582.00&#13;
1971          17.00      32.00     21.00          -               2.75           630.00&#13;
1972          17.00      38.00     21.00          -               2.50           630.00&#13;
1973          17.00      46.00     21.00          -               4.25           777.00&#13;
1974          22.50      62.00     27.00          -               4.52         1,100.00&#13;
1975          37.00      90.00    40.00           -               5.25         1,660.00&#13;
1976          37.00      90.00    40.00           -               5.75         1,360.00&#13;
1977          37.00      52.00    30.00        120.00             5.75         1,280.00&#13;
1978          37.00      95.00    46.00        132.00             5.75         1,280.00&#13;
1979          45.00     110.00    49.00        134.00             5.75         1,280.00&#13;
1980          46.65     110.00    49.00        134.00             7.00         1,904.00&#13;
1981          54.12     127.82    58.78        145.56             9.00         1,890.00&#13;
1982          54.12     139.90    67.64        154.80             9.00         2,094.00&#13;
1983          59.72     142.76    83.05       163.29              9.00         2,399.00&#13;
La  Crop prices in rupees per maund, fertilizer price in rupees per long ton.&#13;
/b  Local varieties.&#13;
Lc  Factory gate, Punjab.&#13;
Ld  Domestic.  Prices for domestic and imported fertilizers are the samc from&#13;
rY76.&#13;
Source:  Ministry of Finmsrce, Planning and Economic Affairs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX&#13;
Table A.6: THE CROWTH IN AGMCULTURALI PRODUCTIVITY, FY60-FY81&#13;
Fiscal                Yield Index (FY60-100)                 Total Factor&#13;
year          Wheat    Cotton      Rice    Sugarcane      Productivity Index/a&#13;
1960           100.0     100.0     100.0      100.0              100.0&#13;
1961           102.2     109.C     !05.5      111.5               90.7&#13;
1962           101.2     109.0     112.3      120.:               95.3&#13;
1963           103.5     125.9     111.1      129.0               98.2&#13;
1964           103.5     134.9     111.1      125.6               99.4&#13;
1965           103.5     121.7     120.0      137.9              101.6&#13;
1966            94.3     125.9     113.4      139.t'              99.2&#13;
1967           101.2     134.9     116.6      125.6              103.3&#13;
1968           133.4     134.9     126.6      137.5              117.4&#13;
1969           133.4     143.4     157.8      150.9              125.0&#13;
1970           146.0     143.4     178.9      158.0              139.8&#13;
1971           134.5     148.1     176.6      135.3              129.2&#13;
1972           148.4     169.8     186.6      134.6              130.8&#13;
1973           155.2     165.1     190.0      139.0              129.4&#13;
1974           155.2     169.8     195.5      137.5              131.4&#13;
1975           164.6     148.1     173.3      117.5              12%.9&#13;
1976           177.2     130.7     184.4      135.3              129.5&#13;
197;           178.4     109.9     188.6      139.4              130.1&#13;
1978           164.1     147.2     187.1      136.0              131.3&#13;
1979           185.5     117.9     194.6      134.9              128.0&#13;
1980           194.9     165.1     190.5      142.4              135.3&#13;
1981           204.1     165.1     193.8      145.4              135.7&#13;
L_ The ratio of the index of agricultural value added to the aggregate&#13;
input index.  The latter is a veighted average cf    and. 1.tsor ind&#13;
capital indices. See Wizarat, S., "Technical Change in Pakis 'anas&#13;
ACriculturs: 1953-54 to 1977/78." Researcb Report go. 120, Vakistan&#13;
:astitute of Dcvelopuent Uonomic:, P-b. 1981.&#13;
Soirce:  Ministry of food, Ag:iculture and Cooperatiies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A.7: RATIOS OF CROP PRICE IhDICES TO AGItICULTURAL INPUT&#13;
PRICE INDICES, FY71-FY82&#13;
( F-'60 - 100)&#13;
Rice    Wheat   Cotton    Sugrrcane   Major Crops    All Crops&#13;
Seed&#13;
1971       1.23    1.02     1.48       0.47         1.68          i.50&#13;
1972       1.09    1.01     1.39       0.62         1.04          1.07&#13;
197'       1.07    0.86     1.29       0.58         0.90          0.97&#13;
1974       1.13    0.88     1.21       0.52         C.93          0.99&#13;
1975      0.95     1.04     0.82       0.43         0.89          0.93&#13;
1976       1.G4    1.01     1.06       0.57         0.9,          1.01&#13;
1977       1.11    0.93     1.30       0.56         0.94          1.00&#13;
1978      0.93     1.0P     1.18       0.50        0.97           1.01&#13;
1979      0.94     i.00     1.54       0.48         0.99          1.02&#13;
1980      0.95     0.98     1.32       0.53         1.00          1.02&#13;
1981      0.97     0.91     1.30       0.60         0.9/          1.01&#13;
1982       1.01    0.98     1.26       0.62         1.00          1.04&#13;
Ferti i ize:&#13;
1971      0.61     0.51     C.74       0.24        0.84           0.75&#13;
1972      0.62     0.57     0.79       0.35        0.59           0.61&#13;
1373       1.)2    0.82     1.23       0.55        0.86           0.93&#13;
1q74       1. 3    0.88     1.21       0.52        0.94           0.97&#13;
1975      0.96     1.06     0.83       0.44         0.91          0.94&#13;
1976       1.21    1.13     1.!8       0.64         1.08          1.13&#13;
1977       1.36    1.14     1.(t       0.69         1.16          1.23&#13;
1973      1.32     1.52     1.67       0.70         1.37          1.42&#13;
1979       1.49    1.58     2.45       0.76         1.58          1.62&#13;
1960       1.45    1.51     2.02       0.81         1.52          1.56&#13;
1981       1.25    1.17     1.67       0.77         1.25          1.30&#13;
1982       1.13    1.09     1.40       0.69         1.11          1.16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX&#13;
Table A.7 (page 2)&#13;
Rice     Wheat    Cotten     Sugarcane     Major Crops     All Crops&#13;
Water&#13;
1971        0.68     0.56      0.8,         0.26          0.93            0.82&#13;
1972        0.64     0.59      0.81         0.36          0.62            0.63&#13;
1973        0.,70    0.57      0.85         0.38          0.59            0.64&#13;
1974        0.86     0.67      0.93         0.40          0.72            0.74&#13;
1975        0.96     1.05      0.83         0.44          0.90            0.94&#13;
1976        0.97     0.90      0.94         0.51         0.86             0.90&#13;
1977        1.17     0.98      1.38         0.60          1.00            1.06&#13;
1978        0.82     0.95      1.04         0.44         0.85             0.88&#13;
1979        0.92     0.98      1.51         0.47          0.97            1.00&#13;
1980        0.82     0.85      1.14        0.46          0.86            0.88&#13;
1951        0.88     0.82      1.18         0.55          0.89            0.92&#13;
1982        0.83     0.S0      1.01        0.50          0.82            0.85&#13;
All Inputs&#13;
1971        0.79     0.66      0.94         0.33          1.08            0.;6&#13;
1972       0.72      0.67      0.92        0.41          0.69            0.71&#13;
i73        0.86     0.70      1.04         0.47         0.72             0.78&#13;
1974        1.05     0.82      1.13        0.49          0.87            0.90&#13;
1975        0.95     1.05      0.83        0.44          0.90            0.93&#13;
1976        1.07     0.99      1.04        0.56          0.95            0.99&#13;
1977        1.13     0.95      1.34        0.57          0.97             1.02&#13;
1978        1.02     1.17      1.28        0.54          1.05             1.08&#13;
1979        1.08     1.14      1.78        0.55          1.14             1.17&#13;
1980        1.12     1.16      1.55        0.62          1.1;            1.20&#13;
1981        1.07     1.00      1.43        0.66          1.07            1.11&#13;
1982        :.05     1.02      1.31        0.64          1.04             i.08&#13;
Notes:  1.   Price deflators for crops are for g7oss output.&#13;
2.  Input deflators for seed, fertilizer acid water are for major&#13;
crops only. Deflators for individual crops are not available.&#13;
3.  Includes both major and minor crops.     Inputs are seed, fertilizer,&#13;
pestlcides, water, transporz charges, wastage.&#13;
Sources: Statistics Division, Covernment of Pakistan, National Accounts,&#13;
1978/79-1981/82; 1977/78-1980/81; 1975/76-1978/79;&#13;
1973/74-1976/77; 1971/72-1974/75, 1969/7'-1972/73.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Wpoces rn developing rpounknes ar d  World Bank Staff Working Paper (1o.&#13;
InterestBadu                                  theor       lons            388 April 1980. x+ 164 pages (nclud-&#13;
ing annex. bibi)ography).&#13;
A World Bank Paper. Mlay 1975. 85   Stock No. WP4388. SS.OO.&#13;
pages (including 14 annier abcs5'.  Stk    .WP08.5..&#13;
Adoption of Agzcicitrai               rngltsh. Trnch, and Spanuh.         A&#13;
Innovations in '                      Stock nfos PP-7502-f- P7-7502-r.    and the Developing&#13;
Countries. A    kurvey                JIP 752- Sn0tpperack&#13;
Gershon Feder, Richarcd Just                                              Countries&#13;
and David Silberman                                                       George Tolley, Vlnod Thomas.&#13;
Kevkw3 variou stidies Tha h    PM-    I'he Aicultural Economy of          and Chung Ming Wong&#13;
vided a desripdori of and picsbk      ilortheast B                        This book flrst considers price&#13;
explanation for patterns of Irunoat   Gary P Kutcher and                  policies In KNorea. Bangladesh. Thal-&#13;
adopton In the agricultural sctoe     Pasquale L. Scandizzo               Land, and Venezuela. brtnging out th&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper   .    This study. based on an agricultural  and revenucf   fart n irgoverment coat&#13;
nO. 542.1982. 65 page.                survey of a ooo f     a       the   ducer and consumer wJfac Other&#13;
ISBtl o.-en-oias9-. SJ0.              extent and root causes of pervasive  -ffects Including thosc on agri-&#13;
rural poverty  northeast Brazil. The  cultural dIersification. Inflation.&#13;
Agran iReform a-                      authors review a numnber of podicy  economic growth and the balance of&#13;
UJnfinisbed Bulea                     and project options thery conclude  payments are aLso dLscusseci. TI.C&#13;
the Selected Papers o                 that courageus land reform is the   s        part of the book proAdes a&#13;
Wolf Ladejlnslty            ~~only efl'ectNve means of dealing with  methoiogy~ for estimating these&#13;
Wolfs J.dWalnskiy.eio                 the prob4eIT                        effects in any country. Operatoioal&#13;
Louis J. Wallnslh;-y, editor          The Johns Hopkins University Pfers.  tools for measuring thce effects on&#13;
StudIes In agrarian policy and Land   1982. 268 pago.                     producem conume.3 and govern-&#13;
reform spanning fcour decads.  t      LC 81-47615. IS8tl 0-8018-2581-4.   rnenl are developed and applIed.&#13;
Lroed e ch _nol  a yasn Wa shrinxUt   £25 00 (fl 7_4) hardcoucr.          The Johns Hopkins Uruerslby, Pess.&#13;
Ladjlnlsyeas I Wahinto.1                                            1982. 256 pages.&#13;
Tokyo. and Vketnam arnd while at the&#13;
rord rounctation and the World Bank.  Agrcultural Extension: The          LC 81U1585. ISBN1 0-8018-2704.3,&#13;
Oxford Universiy fPess. 1977.614      TrainIng and Visit System           S25.00 (SI 750) hardcorer.&#13;
pagea (Including appendires. tndcx.   Daniel B    Qenor&#13;
LC 772425. ISn CLJ.9209$S.and Jarnes Q. Harrison                 Agzlcultural Project&#13;
£32.50 f114.95) hardcoer,             Describes the Traiiiing anl VA           Lysil CsId             and ext&#13;
15SM 0-19-92rXj98-L- $14.95 W.25)     System of txtenskon devesoped by     E.xertIses&#13;
Daniel Benor and introduced in a    Case studIes and exercises on&#13;
paperback.                            number of projects asssted by the   agricultural project preparation and&#13;
Aararian Redorams In                  Wortd Bank in dexeloping countries,  analysis developed for. and used In.&#13;
Developing Rural                      May 1977. 55 pages (Includizg annex).  WDIs rural developmcnt and rur3l&#13;
Economies Characterized by            eng/lsh. french. and Spanush.       ctdit courses.&#13;
Intertinked Criedit and               'ock tas. Pn-7701-C P[1-7701*r.     World Bank (CII. 1979. u.1-uil'&#13;
Tenancy Markets                       PN- 7701-S. S3.00 paperbacx.         712 pagets. u2-lu * 113 pages. uJ&#13;
Avishay Bravermian                                                        -la + 157 pages. (Auailate ferom ILS,&#13;
and T. Ni. Srlnlvasan                 Agricultural Lz2d                    1715 Connecticut Avenue. n W_&#13;
Settlement                          Washington. D.C. 20009. U.5SA.J&#13;
Wortd Bank 5(4 Working Paptr rio.     Todore J. Goera, coor-              $9.00 oaperback.&#13;
W3, ctober 1980. 32 pages (includIng  dlnadng author&#13;
references).                            iitn      uhrAgiutm                                 ecm&#13;
Stock ro. .WP-0433. 1.00              C.-mines selected lssues rejated     AgictUai&#13;
to the World Banks lending for Land  Points out (hat deveJoping countries&#13;
settieme'i and gives estimates of   must Invest more In agricultural&#13;
the globa! rate o( settlement and   research !f they awe to mect Uth&#13;
the workvs ultirate potentially     needs of Uteir growing populations.&#13;
arable land.                        States that studlcs In BrazIL India&#13;
JaparL Mexic. and tne United Sta!-s&#13;
A World Bank issues gaPi. Janu lry  show that agrkcultiral reseath yiels&#13;
1978. 73 pages WUcluding 4 a1.ncexJ.  a rate of return that Is more Ian twO&#13;
EngIlsh. Prench. and Spanish.       to thre tIcrs greater than rUimns&#13;
Stock ffos. F PP'8O1-C ?P-7801-P.    rom  mort alterrntIve ;nuve7iems&#13;
7. 7801-. $S5.00 DaperbaL,          and cites sone of the succces  M '&#13;
xth hIah-Yked.na variets of rice and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
agrictural resarcrie and eAtensikw                                       .~~~~~~ ~~~~ -r--*  s  ^ -,    -&#13;
parlcuiary foer the arodurtion of    Maxwell L. Brown                     ture: Instltutonal Re'orm&#13;
food and ocher commoxlities that art  Clarifies the relation between simple  and the Smiai Fanner&#13;
cd importance to lo-Inrome con-     farm income anakfsLs and the broader  Daniel W. Bromley&#13;
surmer  unall fanners and resourc-   Ried of aajkultuLra project analysis  A model of farmer Intcependence bs&#13;
poor aras.                           and emphasLzcs the more practcal     develped to providc 3ugqesdons for&#13;
Sector Pky f'aper. June 1981. LO   agspecs of project paraton and       Improving existing t rraigaon systems.&#13;
pages (including annexesJ. EnguLs&amp;  for   guidance arcto  !rc.  ible      as Weil as for designing new ones.&#13;
fmc. n Spais.                     o plannlng In agriculture.WolBakSffokn&#13;
tock *no. PP-5101-t. PP-13101-P.     CDI Series in Economic Un flo,Pe    World Bank Stf Woring Paper&#13;
Stock a PP-101-t PP-801-l.T,, Johns Hlopk!ru Univesity Press.   No .531. 1982 96 pages.&#13;
pp-8101-S. 55.00 papertbick.         1980. 154 pages.                    ISBII 0-8213-0064-4. SS 00&#13;
A Derdlopmcant Model for             LC 79-3704. ISB15 0-018.2386-2.&#13;
Ah De    culo uren  Soeltor         $1-0 (1 10350) harcour.:NE&#13;
the   gulcJtouSal Sector              Bls 8-8018-2387-0. 60 $6W&#13;
of Portugal                          (14.50) paperback.&#13;
Alvn C. Egbert                       Span Lil: Presupuecstos de fincas.   Inreascingitytra&#13;
arHd tvur-g M. ICim                 Editorial Tecnaxs, 1982.              Producthty&#13;
a~d IlyuT'g M. Kim  Cdltorial Tecnas. 1982.(Proceedings of the Third Annual&#13;
59adal matheatiUcal progmmnmanig d   ISBt 84-309-0886-2. 723 pesetas.    Agricultural Sector Symposium)&#13;
used to develop comprthensIve and&#13;
quantltatvc methods to suggest                                           Ted J. Davis, editor&#13;
development strategies In Portug's   Fishery                             These proceedings are the third In a&#13;
agriculture xtor.                   Highlights the importance of ftherles  series of records of Agricultural 5Xc-&#13;
The Johns Hopkins UnIlmnity Pn=s&amp;   to the economics of developing coun-  tor Symposia presented at the World&#13;
L97S. L10 pages (includirig         tries and recmmenda that the World    Bank each January since L980. Con-&#13;
bicegraphy).                        Bank provide asssarnce to those      tans the papcrs prexsnted by thc&#13;
countries that have the fishery      speaKecs. chai1rpe ron.'Vsaerfwn1&#13;
I-C 75-26662. 158(1 0-8018-1793-5.  resources and are willing to develop  and summaries of the discussions&#13;
56.50 (IL4001 paperback.            them hLrthr.                         prepared by the rapporieun.&#13;
Economic ABpicts! and               Sector Policy Paper December 1982.   1982. 307 pages lIncluding Index)&#13;
Poicy Lssues In Ground-             15BN 0-8213-0138-1. S5 00 paperback.  ISBN 0-8213-0099- 7 S15 00.&#13;
water Development_&#13;
Ian Carruthers and Roy Storner      Food Security In Food                     NEW&#13;
eAamlnes a wide range of economk     Defiit Countries&#13;
and podky  1ue riatccl to deveklop   Shlomo Reutlinger                    Indta: Demand and Supply&#13;
ment of groundwater for IrrigatiorL  and Keith Knapp                      Proapects for Agrculture&#13;
World Bank SW7 Working Paper         World Bank StaWf Working Paper tto.  James Q. Harrison.&#13;
Ila 496. October 1981. l0 pages      393. June 1980. 39 pages (including  Jon A. Hltchings.&#13;
OIncluding anntex. bibllography).    appendLr. references).               and John W. Wall&#13;
Stock 1No. WP-0496 S5 00.           Stock No. WP-093. SJ 00.              Contains four papers that report on&#13;
the World Banks economic work in&#13;
the agricultural sector in India and&#13;
.EW                              Forestry                             the Implicatlons of thLs development&#13;
Craham   Donaldson. coordi-           both for foodgalns and for other&#13;
Economic Return to Invest-          nating author                         maJor agricultural commoditics.&#13;
Focuses on the demand for&#13;
ment In Irrigation In India          .lAines the sIgnificancC of forests  agricultural commoditks through the&#13;
Lesile A. Abble.                    In econormk developrnenl and con-     year 2000. the foodgraln economy&#13;
James Q. iarrisonr                   cludes that the Wof1d Bank should    the vegetable oil economy. and the&#13;
and John W. Wall                     greatuy Increase Its rode In forestry  sugar economy.&#13;
deve3oprmenL both as a lender and&#13;
Peports on an Lrrvestigatlon Into the  advv3e to gov amkn       a         World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
efFicency of Irmestnent In surface                                       1No. SOO. October 1981. 133 pages&#13;
and groundw= a  lrrigatlon In indlc.  Sector Policy Paper. !c.tbnLay 1978. 63  (includIng 5 appendixe. tterences.&#13;
pages (including 7 anex.aJ. Eng lsh.  annex).&#13;
Wold Sank SW    IffrkWirng t per    frenchL and 5pansh.&#13;
nX 56 1982. 52 p4gr. enct n                   PP- 7804C PP-781)4-         Stock No. WP-OS00. £3.00.&#13;
15&amp;0( 0-823-00-0. £.C00.             PP. 7804-S. S5.00 paperback.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-,      '-F-..&#13;
ana roav KLsiev                      PrgrazmXlg Studies for               Thme case studies prepared In con-&#13;
C=r.wnf   the roke of sdctlkc        Mexkan AaIrultural Policy           Jurction with the eDI Agricultural&#13;
CJ arnd tchnodogki dcange In        Edited by Roge D. Norton and        Pn&gt;Jcb Courses In 5panish and&#13;
LrKrc=&amp;G agrWturW prod-Uvtr)L  Leopodo Solis M.Intended primarty for teachers of&#13;
Ir*n     agriuntu producI:i1         Leopoido Solls M.                     roec an°ris&#13;
Yale Unixnlay Pf's 502 Tenmple 5cCs   The pirncJpal tod of analysis is the&#13;
Meao Mavn. Connecricut 06520. U.SA.  sctOx mwdel C1AC. Wnsed aft the       World Bank (0I). March 1974: revised&#13;
1975. xi + 204 pages (Inctudimg 10   t1fan rin god. This modd can te      January 1975. 480 pages (AuatWiL&#13;
appenLzeL references. Index).        uelrouaiout the sector to coter      f,tm ILS. 1715 ConnectHcut Aenue.u&#13;
Vap ct-cyce crop. their Input&amp; and   11 W., W;shiungton, D C. 20009. U-SA&#13;
LC 7415210. ISBN 0-300-01LS-0.         ,r rnark    I can also btc broken&#13;
Sl5.00 hardcover 158 0-300-71877-0.  down Into submodeii for parcuarap                c&#13;
Sim paperback.                       bUtkt   If mor detailed analysis is&#13;
Spars. Irrestgaci6m agcoa y          requred. The ffodel helpo planners   The Design of Organiza-&#13;
Spazlb   weigh the ccs among polky goals,&#13;
d   ¢KtivId. Udira/ Tecn.os 1976.    wtich can vary froam region to r     dons for Raral Developaaent&#13;
kW   84-309-0641-X 420 peet.         Th voer     r         e.xpcicnce of   Projcits-9 a PrOves&#13;
uslng the CNAC model and also pr-    Rcport&#13;
x      puny  ntdoc         artal-    Wlillam E. Smith.&#13;
AsroI    duStIIAJ ProJec.            Trhe Johns Hopkins UnIvrsnity hes.   rmncis J. Lethem. and&#13;
Analys&amp;.                             196J. 632 pages.                     Ben A. Thoolen&#13;
James E. ALLstln                     LC 80-29366 IS8fl 0-8018-2585- 7.    World Bank SWa Worklng Paper Nlo.&#13;
1         and Illustrates a tran-eorU  £33.00 (124.50) hardcouer.        .575. March 1980. 48 pages. tngilsh&#13;
for arying  and designing agro-&#13;
ndtrw p*c.                                                             and rnwnch.&#13;
Stock No. WP-0375-CL WP-0375-P.&#13;
MN Series In tconomic De1iopnvent                   SJ00.&#13;
rhe Johm Mopkits UnIctr34bj Fiess.&#13;
L98L 224 paga (Including appen-      Baiding latioUai Capscity&#13;
dtes biblibgraphy&amp; and Index).       to Develop TAWater Uer'              The Design of Rural&#13;
LC 80-M0 15M 0-018-2412-5.           Aa.odatio         Experkece          Developmeant LesIow&#13;
S16S0 (110.00) hardcover IS811      ftom the Fh.bUpples                   ftoetm Africa&#13;
0-01S-2413-3. $7.50 (1425)           Frances r Korten                     Urna Lele&#13;
paperback                            Over a fve-yter perod the Natornal   Analyzes new ways of designing rural&#13;
renc)h: LMaluys des projeLS agro-    Irr1gfton Admninstat1on (M LA) of the  develoment ProJects to mrach lare&#13;
industlcls. Cconornka. 1982.         Phlipplnc3 has been building Its     numbr of low-incorrwe subastenc&#13;
Isu 2- 178-0480-3. 49 fras.         r      pacty to develop wstr uers     populations. The paperbact reprint-&#13;
association4 on srn.I-ncale Irrigation  Ing In 1979 contains a new chapter by&#13;
Spanibh. AnriLss de prtos ;o          s   s. Ths paper deta is thc        the authior updatng her findingr.&#13;
i.dustriales. tdittoria Tecnos. 1981.  changes thut have been made withdn  The Johns Hopkins Univrtl&#13;
S11 84-309-882-L 600 pectas.       the agency as a result of the devtop  1975T Jod pttntJng 1979.260 pages&#13;
r    d tJ' U1                              rp     n associatin.s preor to&#13;
Du consowdon of th physkal           (Including glossary. appendLx. maps.&#13;
Argentia: Coamty Ca"e                ssn ard the Irrw*Ave:nt of           bilbiography. Index).&#13;
Sty of A(    kCLltural Prn:es,        rsociation m tbe  in the planning   IStf 0-8018-1769-2. $9.95&#13;
Taxes, and 5ubs6diles                                  of conctim 3taguc   It aiao  paperack.&#13;
LucIo QC  Reca                       1umc       hais the has le  to e chwng  French: Le dwloppement&#13;
Wold Sank Sa Working Paper ,fa       and dbsO.Aas the Lmpikatons for      rural: I'cxrerKnce AMcaine.&#13;
58 April1980. 72 pages inciuiding    donor support oot&amp;er II        talC conomica. 1977.&#13;
1 a    ).                            tnon pro           and rom           158tf 2- 7178-0006-9. 39 rnncs.&#13;
geWally lor progmu   IrrvoMng&#13;
Stack lo. WP-W6. J3.00.                           1 w&#13;
1Word Bank Sa Working Paper&#13;
Plo. 528. July 12. v * 69 pages&#13;
(including references).&#13;
5U1 0-8l-0051-2. £3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
reforg. its lrnpikatnul  for ale    Catuu      Cem ounfng ltImpmTnenta.  Concepts, Asian E&#13;
don has been accepted In principle  Cocpt.Asa&#13;
eco;XX.s -!-of developing counties.  __ o        55cms ,a   ,t           Donald K. Emmerson&#13;
V    m   Bank In tPhisY 0 6open to $hrtolore ben fonmulated The con-     World Bank Stall Working Maper flo&#13;
c i    monitoring and cvaltion      423. October 1980. x - 97 pagcs&#13;
A Wod Bank Paper. May 1975. 73       am dflr    ad and       Sthat       lincluding refemences).&#13;
page lincluding 2 annemls.           need to be conskioded In deskJinng&#13;
ngtlb  Imncl. and Spa  h.            sysemu to mni tor and evaluete      Stock Nfo. WP-0423. $5.00.&#13;
speuiflc prevects are outlned.&#13;
S? -7C    $5F.0 P 5aIr-P                        the tIfl1elifl phs ingthd Uti  DCVr     p oftt&#13;
numiltortng functions for effective  Rua     Cvopmnt&#13;
nftagenertL Claborates on such      Discusses strate' designed to extend&#13;
technical isucs as seJection of indka-  the bcenels of development to thC&#13;
Land Tcnume Systeas and             ton. selecton of survey rnethodoogy  rural poor and ouUlnes the World&#13;
Social ImplCaLons of                d     analysis, and presentation. It LS  5nk's plans for Ireasing its assIb-&#13;
Forltry Development                 dected prirnaly to thoce wx  ing     tarfc In this sector.&#13;
rrogpzams                           wtth specic prvJects and wUIl be use-  Sector Policy Paper. february 1975. g&#13;
Mkhadf M. CerTea                    Rd to pcect appratial teamn. to           (Including 14 annezal. Engil&#13;
designrxs of monitoring an evla     pages incuig1     nee)     nls&#13;
World Ban* Staff Worg Paper nO.     dn systern. and to project tff wo    French, Spanlsh. and Arabk.&#13;
452 April L9B1. 33 pages (Lrcludlng  work with these systems.            Stock Nas. PF-7501-C. PP 7501-f.&#13;
iefzvtwm "lography).                The Johns Hopkins Uniuersity tres    PP. 7501 -. tfPP- 7501 -A. $5 00&#13;
Stck (.1 WP-0452. £3.00.            1982. 145 pages french and Spanish   paperback.&#13;
Axt±ing.&#13;
awnq Ifo           aftion for       LC 82-712&amp; ISBN 0-8018-2910-0. S850   url Pe     ry Unprceltyed:&#13;
~~~                        I i~~~~~~6i0) paperbiack.            Problems and Remedies&#13;
RV3,al Dedelopment:: 1,4naoos                                            Robert Chambers&#13;
hto Ea           AMtca&#13;
Cuido Deboeck and Bill Kinxey       Moiltortng Rural Develop-            World Bank Staff Working Paper (to.&#13;
d Bak  oiEapA.                      400. July 1980. 51 pages (including&#13;
111tb ri Bn SW War*nlr _'ap         Quiro Deboec     and Ronald 1ig     references).&#13;
3 79. Mrch L9. vil +70page  GuidoDeboeckand Roald Ng   Stock Noa WP-0400. $5 00.&#13;
(includitg 5 annees inder).         Ubrtd Bank St  Worklng Paper fto.&#13;
Sock (lo. WP-(3 79. $5.00.          439. October 1980.91 pages (including  Ru,- Projects Thro-&#13;
!utngPr: Slc No. Wf'0439 SJ 00.      Urban Eyes: An Interpreta-&#13;
Pieasmtng Project limpectz.            okT.WP09                          tJon of the Wo,id Bank's&#13;
Moniortng and Evaluation                                                 Mew-Style Rural Develop-&#13;
In the PIDER Rural Develop.          lMutrttioual Consequences           ment Projects&#13;
me4t    Profect..  exjlo            of Atlk     tural Projects:          Judith Tendler&#13;
MIC1ade M. Cernea                   Conceptual Relationships             This paper describes thx Banks nw-&#13;
orld hank SWt Working aper          and Asessment                        styk rural development projects,&#13;
3322 Jw2 1979. vi + L1 pago         AplproacbeS                          Including some of the things that hap-&#13;
includrIng 3 annexes. appendLc. map)  Per P¶nstrp-Andersen               psn In the pd4itkal snronm ent ot a&#13;
Shxk (To. WP-0M2. M.00.              Wort d 8ank Sa Working Paper lie.   by the BanK redirect their public-sec.&#13;
M April 19d1. 93 pages (including    tor services and subsidIes to the Lnul&#13;
bbliography. appendlx).              Poor.&#13;
fEW                              Stock s  nX WP-0456. S3.00.         World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
Molftortsig and Evaluation                                               to 532. 1982.100 page.&#13;
of   A CUItwm and Iura I              rrkes, Taxes, and Susldies         ISBtr 0.213-0028-8. $5.00.&#13;
Develop      tent Proects            im Pakistn AgrPc   ulture,&#13;
Dennis 1 Casley                      1960-1976                           Sociocultural Aspects of&#13;
and Denis A. Lury                    Carl Gotsch and Gilbert Brown       Developing Sail -Scale&#13;
Tht book provdes a how-to tool for   Woo    n  Stak Working Paper no.     sbeil*est DltverinP&#13;
d0gn pad hmp6enienrlon of           387. April 1980.108 pags.            SerYCCS to the Poor&#13;
nmoUxt3     d cvahutIonsysterroL in  S                                       a W 387. 5.00Rd B. Pollnac&#13;
nnU devlpmnt pre&amp;c                                                        World Bank S    Working Paper To.&#13;
nm devkpnr proeC3 aMcOM                                                  490. October U81. III + 61 pag=&#13;
pCL    qy seekl to bereit  rge nutrr                                     lOncluding refoetncels.&#13;
pxpN oo. WP04 90. £3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
J%aj lsu-olilwa af(a U. ,.                    .^eW ifacirnnl dna ai.n. irnnivasan&#13;
RaychaudhtJri                                  Wo,id Sanir Reprint Scrie lumber 216.&#13;
Aepnnir.d horm Journal of Developmcnt&#13;
Wor!J Bank Steaf Workirng Paper r.o.           .conarnics uoi 9 (December 1981) 289.12&#13;
381. April 1980. 62 pages (including           Stock .-o RP-0216 fec -I cha rgc&#13;
2 appendixes. 6 tab:es. bibliograpny).&#13;
SlaCk ri'o. WP.OJa1. 5.oo                      ratm suze and the Diffusion of Gre&#13;
R.evotion Technolog on Donoonation&#13;
and lnovaLion Diffusion: A Bycslan&#13;
Approah&#13;
A System    cof Monitoring and                 Gernon reder and Gerald T O'Mara&#13;
Evaluating AgricUlturad                         0r dank Reprint Series .umix, 207&#13;
Exteuslon Projects                             ?eonnk-d 1mm Economic D"eflopmentinJ&#13;
Michael M. Cemea and                                 Change uO) .0 no I (Octobet&#13;
-,1. 59 76 and kmerican Journal ol Agricaitural&#13;
Benjamin J. Tepping n-oornir-S tiol -54 no I tlcDruaryl982 145-47&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper (fo.            5irci . o RP-0207 rree ol charge&#13;
272. December 1977. vi - UIS pages&#13;
(including 9 annexes. brbliographty)           SOc:O&amp;oSkaJ Dimensions of Extension&#13;
Stock rio. WP-02 72. S5.00                      OrsanfxaUoa: The Introduction of the&#13;
T&amp;V System in India&#13;
,!ikhacJ 9 Cemra&#13;
rhailand-Cas       Study of                     onld 8ank Reprint Serioes 'umber 196&#13;
R.eprnnted (mm t-tension COucatioi, and Pwn.i&#13;
Agricuiturai Inpult and                         C-CopmenL -ot 2 11981) 221-35 281&#13;
Output P1-icing                                Strci.'lc RP-0196 free o(charge&#13;
Trent Bertrand&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper rIo&#13;
385. April 1980 ix - 1.34 pages                    !IEW&#13;
(includlng 2 ippendlxesl.&#13;
Stock No. wP-0J83 SS 00.                       Economlc AnaLysis of Agricultural Projects&#13;
Second edition, completely revised and&#13;
cxpanded&#13;
RZPRItIrS                                      J. Price Gittinger&#13;
This entirely new edition of the World Banks best-selling&#13;
Adpop Of 0ntenr'eated A1kn   iur                boOik sets out a careful and practcal rmthodology for&#13;
lnatlOns Cd en5PIc   ti,ty and the             analyzing agricultural development projects and for using&#13;
ImVcnon rec     ce                              these analysts to compare proposed inves3tents. It&#13;
*ond Sins Aepnni  4 uirwe,                     covers what constitutes a projectV what must be con-&#13;
AcPnAd,m kep  ncan ;ciumloArXKe               5sidered to identify possible agricultural projects. the life&#13;
PeonnSOM  am 64 nto I Jourruary A1 9C .r101     cycie of a project the strengths and pitfalls of project&#13;
SDcor,lo RP40206. rnof fcrai1y                  anadytys. and the calculations required to obtain fIRnancial&#13;
S4och'lb R-0206 freera'c'a,~e.and economic project accounts.&#13;
In the ten years since its pubilcatlon. the first edJtion has&#13;
A Sc  icuat me adntSd Dei3ELinnowt:            been accepted widely as a standard reference and text The&#13;
to kd            lsa           ed               methodology renlects the best of contemporary practice in&#13;
iartha n. deMelO                                government agencies and international development&#13;
load Saici Rrnnt Sena N.~mber 19.               institutions concemed with investing in agriculur  and Is&#13;
tonsS Anx Atprint Xrr3 JulleDcr 191.  accessible Lo a broad readership of agriculturaJ plarners.&#13;
mLo 1. no. 2 (Ma*y 19 791.2l7.4                 engineers. and analysts.&#13;
Stock No, RP-0191. lr,'  CAv                      This revision adds a wealth of recent project data;&#13;
expanded treatment of famm budgets and the efikcncy&#13;
prics used to calculate the effects of an investmrent on&#13;
CWoce of Techique to Sabeta fkie                natlonal Incone: a glossary of technical tenrms expanded&#13;
P1odactio                                       appendLxes on preparing an agricultural projeat repot and&#13;
Qwsa   J Mlumphrry and !k   Rp Peanon           using discounting tables: and an expanded completely&#13;
wIk  &amp;nk Rdnnt eninc 'umber 199.                annotated bibliography.&#13;
ReprlnkdS Porn 00 Prtc,d SieiL1.DvlopmenJt.&#13;
nO 3 f1979-80):215 77                            cDI Series In konomic Development.&#13;
5ik ho. RP-0199. t'ee cof chsre.                 The Johns Mopkins Unlverslty Pfse July 1982. 528 pages&#13;
(Lrtcluding appendlres and glassanj/lndex).&#13;
LC 82-15262. ISBN -8018-2912-7. 37.50 ff2250) hardcover:&#13;
IS&amp;1 0-8018-2913-5. $L350 4f8.75) paperback.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
SEND TO:&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBILICATIONS                           WORLD BANK PUBUCATIONS&#13;
PO. BOX 37525                         or           66, AVENUE D'IENA&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013                             75116 PARIS, FRANCE&#13;
U.S.AI&#13;
Name:&#13;
Address:&#13;
Stock o ISBN#  |            Authornie T              rt.ePnce        Total&#13;
_  _ _ _ _ ___  '_     _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _S _   _  - I   Tota  Co t&#13;
.~~~~~~~~ j_                                                      I _&#13;
.~ ~ ~ ~~~~~~~~~~________                  --    ,&#13;
i      i  _ _     I      !_ _&#13;
Sub-Tota] Cast: ____&#13;
Poszge &amp; handling fee for more than two free iterns (S1.00 each):&#13;
Total copies: _ _ Air mail surcharge (S2.00 each):&#13;
TOTAL PAYMENT ENCLOSED:&#13;
Make checks payable: \hORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
PI'AWw on oten frnm rza:a zS rs gsw P  0Mcr n oeri a.u fo trorn wowAs. vCr1q S tem wanes. arI tSutons&#13;
A os wxe cm posdage vy to" aw wo means The vce arc &gt;ubcawn w" o  in Us Ca4 g are ubyc to0 Cane&#13;
w*lx rWa.&#13;
P;   a rsts be  ,wn bwens at  v be Mac C'd wo oe wo': tovr 1u  o&#13;
?N re eo tan Or V Ptf  3 0a be &gt;o wWOu chWgS. P   be 30*0Onm  wd e fde as a dune of US Si 00 pe'&#13;
at lo c  hq Iad C c osza g =&#13;
Airr." dewrj wt recuwe a  ptymflW of US S200 pw coy&#13;
Ma-crler paymw to tus d Brak r*d ro be in U-S doarl. w the arrourv run:a rtsl De a To rma of excawrg on me aay me&#13;
ovd.' 'is d. The Wrd Bar.- w 8wa  lk.No couo&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554809">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/04/1554809/prices-terms-trade-role-government-pakistans-agriculture
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/04/1554809/prices-terms-trade-role-government-pakistans-agriculture</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1984/04/1554809/prices-terms-trade-role-government-pakistans-agriculture</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/05/17/000178830_9810190342274/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/05/17/000178830_9810190342274/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-08-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1984-04-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Prices, terms of trade, and the role of
            government in Pakistan's agriculture
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Despite the importance of agriculture to
            the national economy of Pakistan and the major role played
            by the government in its development, a number of key issues
            have not been adequately addressed by existing studies. This
            paper provides an empirical basis for discussion of changes
            in the agricultural terms of trade, growth of agricultural
            productivity and incomes, pricing of agricultural inputs and
            outputs, and subsidization and taxation of agriculture. It
            notes that the terms of trade between agriculture and the
            other sectors have not significantly deteriorated during the
            period 1960-83, and farmers' purchasing power has
            actually improved. Net returns to farmers increased until
            the recent sharp increases in fertilizer prices reversed
            this trend. Economic taxation of wheat and basmati rice in
            contrast to the economic subsidies provided to sugar should
            be a matter of concern. This paper argues that appropriate
            price policies which are responsive to changes in
            international prices are likely to have as salutary an
            effect as any attempt to reduce financial subsidies or to
            increase taxes.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Prices, terms of trade, and the role of
            government in Pakistan's agriculture
        </docna>
        <display_title>Prices, terms of trade, and the
            role of government in Pakistan's agriculture</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1984/04/1554809/prices-terms-trade-role-government-pakistans-agriculture</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Crops and Crop Management Systems,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Agricultural Knowledge and Information Systems,Agricultural Research</subtopic>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Agriculture</teratopic>
        <count>Pakistan</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Cheong, Kee-Cheok</author>
            <author>D'Silva, Emmanuel</author>
            <author>ASA</author>
            <author>PUB</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_9810190342274</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Other agriculture</subsc>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 643</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Agriculture</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Agriculture, fishing, and forestry</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0361-9</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Agricultural prices; Agricultural
            productivity; Agricultural subsidies; Price policy;
            Taxation; Terms of trade
            agriCultural commodities,agricultural
            crops,agricultural incomes,agricultural inputs,agricultural
            output,Agricultural prices,agricultural
            productivity,agricultural products,agriculture,base
            year,cereals,Cooperatives,cotton,crop,crop
            prices,Crops,Dam,deflators,economic activity,Economic
            Development,Economics,economists,empirical
            basis,exports,FARM,farmer,farmers,fertilizer,fertilizer
            subsidies,FERTILIZER USE,Fertilizers,financial
            subsidies,fishing,flour,forestry,GDP,GDP Per
            Capita,GNP,government subsidies,grain,gross domestic
            product,GROWTH IN AGRICULTURE,hay,imports,income,income
            effect,Innovation,input prices,input
            use,Irri,irrigation,livestock,maize,marginal cost,marginal
            value,Meat,oil,oilseeds,output per capita,Paddy,price
            elasticity,produce,production costs,productivity,Purchasing
            Power,reclamation,rice,rice varieties,scarcity
            value,seed,sugar,sugarcane,taxation,terms of trade,TOT,total
            output,UNCTAD,value added,value of output,Vegetables,water
            supply,wheat,WHOLESALE PRICE INDEX,yields
        </keywd>
        <owner>SAR</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP643</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock and Animal Husbandry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Integrated Pest Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pest Control</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pesticides</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forest and Forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Management &amp; Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops and Crop Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Use</ml:concept><ml:concept>Econometrics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Animal Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pest Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Procurement</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Pakistan</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>