<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP488&#13;
Developments in and Prospects for&#13;
the External Debt of the Developing Countries:&#13;
1970-80 and Beyond&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 488&#13;
August 1981&#13;
REMOVE&#13;
Prepared by Nicholas L Hope&#13;
External Debt Division&#13;
Economic Analysis and Projections Department&#13;
Development Policy Staff&#13;
Copyright (® 1981                                    044-01                       0222&#13;
The World Bank                                       Feathery James K.&#13;
1818 H Street, N W                                         N 234&#13;
ington, D.C 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
PUB&#13;
HG Iiews and interpretations in this document are those of the author&#13;
3881.5   hould not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated&#13;
.W57     izations, or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
167&#13;
.0 .488&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations,&#13;
or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 488&#13;
August 1981&#13;
DEVELOPMENTS IN AND PROSPECTS FOR THE EXTERNAL DEBT&#13;
OF THE DEVELOPING COUNTRIES: 1970-1980 AND BEYOND&#13;
A Background Study for World Development Report 1981&#13;
Much has been made of the perils to the developing countries - and to&#13;
the international banking system - from the rapid expansion of their&#13;
debt during the 1970s. This paper examines the borrowing patterns&#13;
of developing countries, as they have evolved over the past decade,&#13;
by drawing on data contained in the Debtor Reporting System (DRS) of&#13;
the World Bank. Changes in the debt situation of these countries -&#13;
in aggregate, for important sub-groups, and individually - are&#13;
assessed by a consideration of how debt and associated service payments&#13;
have changed relative to major macro-economic variables that are often&#13;
used to assess a borrowing country's creditworthiness. The paper then&#13;
examines the prospects for borrowing during the 1980s.&#13;
Prepared by: Nicholas C. Hope&#13;
External Debt Division&#13;
Economic Analysis and Projections Department&#13;
Development Policy Staff&#13;
Copyright    )  1981&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ii&#13;
This paper draws heavily on the work of the staff of the External Debt&#13;
Division. Particular contributions have been made by Austin Hu,&#13;
Thomas Klein and David McMurray. Ms. V. Beharry provided valuable&#13;
assistance in preparing and analyzing data. Helpful comments on an&#13;
earlier version of the paper were provided by John Holsen, Helen Hughes,&#13;
Paul Isenman, Thomas Reichman, Frances Stewart, and Mildred Weiss.&#13;
Excellent typing support was provided by Sally Heycox, Dianne Lust, and&#13;
the secretaries of the World Development Report Core Team.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
iii&#13;
Contents&#13;
Page&#13;
I.     Introduction   ................................................        1&#13;
II.   The Evolution of the Developing Countries'&#13;
External Indebtedness:    1970-80   ............................      6&#13;
Developments in the Stock of Debt     ......................      6&#13;
Developments in Debt Flows    .............................      14&#13;
The Evolution of Debt Indicators     .......................     21&#13;
III. The Debt of Individual Developing Countries&#13;
and Country Groups .........................................         29&#13;
The Debt of Principal Borrowers     ........................     29&#13;
Experience within Country Groups     .......................     32&#13;
Developments in the Debt of Oil-Exporting&#13;
Countries   ........       .................................  33&#13;
Developments in the Debt of Low-Income&#13;
Oil-Importing Countries    ...........................     36&#13;
Developments in the Debt of Middle-Income&#13;
Oil Importers that Are Major Exporters of&#13;
Manufactures    ......................................      38&#13;
Developments in the Debt of Other Middle-&#13;
Income Countries    ..................................     40&#13;
IV.   The Outlook forBorrowing in the 1980s      .......................     43&#13;
Determinants of Borrowing in the 1980s     ....      .............  45&#13;
The Importance of Export Growth     .....      ...............  47&#13;
Official Sources of Capital     ........................    48&#13;
V.     Summary and Conclusions            .....................................  53&#13;
Annex I         Debt and Debt-Service Indicators for Major&#13;
Groups of Developing Countries     .......   .............  55&#13;
Annex II        Major Groups Reporting to DRS     ........   ..............  65&#13;
Annex III       Developing Economies' Shares in Outstanding Public&#13;
Debt - 1970-79    .............                            67&#13;
References ........ 70&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
iv&#13;
Text Tables&#13;
Page&#13;
la.     Medium- and Long-Term External Debt Outstanding&#13;
and Disbursed: Public Debt by Creditor Source&#13;
and Private Non-Guaranteed Debt, 1970-80&#13;
(US$ billions) .    ...................................        8&#13;
lb.     Medium- and Long-Term External Debt Outstanding&#13;
and Disbursed: Public Debt by Creditor Source&#13;
and Private Non-Guaranteed Debt, 1970-80&#13;
(annual growth rates, percent)    ............  ............  l0&#13;
Ic.     Medium- and Long-Term External Debt Outstanding&#13;
and Disbursed: Public Debt by Creditor Source&#13;
and Private Non-Guaranteed Debt, 1970-80&#13;
(shares of total debt, percent)    ..     .....................  11&#13;
2a.     Commitments, Disbursements,Service Payments, and&#13;
Net Capital Movements: Medium- and Long-Term&#13;
Debt, 1970-79 (US$ billions) .       ......... __ .............  15&#13;
2b.      Commitments, Disbursements, Service Payments, and&#13;
Net Capital Movements: Medium- and Long-Term&#13;
Debt, 1970-79 (annual growth rates, percent) .16&#13;
3.      Average Terms of Borrowing:    Commitments of Public and&#13;
Publicly Guaranteed Debt, 1970-80 .19&#13;
4a.      Evolution of Debt and Debt-Service Indicators:&#13;
All Developing Countries, Aggregates 1970-79,&#13;
Total Debt ........ 23&#13;
4b.     Evolution of Debt and Debt-Service Indicators:&#13;
All Developing Countries, Debt-Weighted Aggregates&#13;
1970-79, Total Debt ....................................     26&#13;
4c.     Evolution of Debt and Debt-Service Indicators:&#13;
All Developing Countries, Aggregates and Debt-&#13;
Weighted Aggregates 1970-79, Public Debt Only     ....  .....  27&#13;
5.      Principal Borrowers, 1979:    Debt and Debt-&#13;
Service, 1970 and 1979 ...............       .................. 30-&#13;
6.      Shares of Thirteen Major Borrowers in Debt and&#13;
Debt-Service Payments, 1974, 1977, 1979 ....        ............ 32&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
v&#13;
Acronyms and Abbreviations&#13;
CPE                            Centrally planned economy&#13;
DAC                            Development Assistance Committee&#13;
DOD                            Debt outstanding and disbursed&#13;
DRS                            Debtor Reporting System of the World Bank&#13;
IDA                            International Development Association&#13;
IMF                            International Monetary Fund&#13;
ODA                            Official development assistance&#13;
OECD                           Organisation for Economic Co-operation&#13;
and Development&#13;
OPEC                           Organization of Oil-Exporting Countries&#13;
WDR                            World Development Report&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-1-&#13;
I. Introduction&#13;
In the 1970s, the external indebtedness of developing countries&#13;
caused increasing concern. It has been a particular preoccupation since&#13;
the oil price rises of 1973-74, in the aftermath of which the debt and&#13;
debt-servicing obligations of developing countries rose rapidly as they&#13;
borrowed heavily in the international capital markets (and especially from&#13;
commercial banks) to finance enlarged balance-of-payments deficits.&#13;
Several factors are important contributors to unease over the developing&#13;
countries' current debt situation.&#13;
First, compared with the 1950s and 1960s, the 1970s witnessed&#13;
significant changes in the composition of borrowed and of other capital&#13;
inflows to developing countries. In the mid-1960s, grants and grant-like&#13;
flows plus foreign direct investment accounted for well over half (58 per-&#13;
cent in 1964-66) of the net flow of financial resources to developing&#13;
countries. (1) By 1979, the share of these flows in total net capital&#13;
inflow had fallen to one-third. Within debt-creating flows, there has been&#13;
a large decline in the share of net capital inflow from bilateral official&#13;
sources, a marginal decrease in the share from multilateral institutions,&#13;
and a large increase in the proportion of loans from private creditors --&#13;
especially from financial institutions.&#13;
1.   Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD)&#13;
data (balance-of-payments basis). See Development Co-operation,&#13;
various issues.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
Second, as well as augmenting investment and easing structural&#13;
bottlenecks to growth, an important role for external capital in the 1970s&#13;
has been to ease for oil-importing countries the burden of adjustment to&#13;
much higher oil prices and a general deterioration of the international&#13;
economic environment. Emphasis in debt management during the 1960s&#13;
centered mainly on payments imbalances and foreign exchange shortages&#13;
resulting from inappropriate domestic policies. Exogenous external shocks&#13;
(e.g., to exports) tended to be viewed as reversible, thus creating a&#13;
need for "compensatory finance" -- as in the International Monetary Fund's&#13;
(IMF) facility of the same name -- that would be drawn on during a cyclical&#13;
downturn in foreign exchange availability and repaid during a cyclical&#13;
peak. The process would take place with no change in a country's&#13;
longer-term indebtedness.&#13;
But the oil price increase is apparently irreversible: energy&#13;
prices have risen permanently by large discrete amounts. The two-fold&#13;
adjustment process involving the reduction of current account deficits to&#13;
levels that can be financed from normal capital inflows and the adaptation&#13;
of domestic production and consumption patterns will be eased by foreign&#13;
borrowing. After adjustment is complete, however, the external indebted-&#13;
ness of oil-importing countries probably will be higher than it would have&#13;
been without the oil price increase -- and certainly it will be higher&#13;
relative to GNP. This could have lasting effects on debt and debt manage-&#13;
ment policy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
The third difference, related to the above, is that the oil shock&#13;
is a shared experience for a large number of developing countries, which&#13;
have experienced a simultaneous increase in their financing needs. Rather&#13;
than focussing on the debt situation of individual countries and their&#13;
creditworthiness, concern has been directed to the debt situation of&#13;
developing countries as a group. (2)&#13;
Finally, concern over the ability of developing'countries, as a&#13;
group, to manage their debt has led observers to question the stability of&#13;
the financial intermediaries -- especially the commercial banks -- if&#13;
developing countries collectively, or even a major borrower singly,&#13;
should fail. This has deflected attention from the growth of individual&#13;
countries to the success of the "recycling" process. While recycling&#13;
would not be judged a complete success if accompanied by a sharp fall in&#13;
the growth of developing countries, the "success" in recycling has come to&#13;
be viewed as maintaining the stability of the system of financial inter-&#13;
mediation, and this stability therefore has become viewed as an end in&#13;
itself rather than the means by which global economic activity can be&#13;
maintained at high levels.&#13;
The new round of oil price increases in 1979-80 and the uncertain&#13;
outlook for oil supply from the Middle East have awakened fresh concern in&#13;
the international community over the feasibility of recycling oil&#13;
surpluses efficiently and the prospects for continued large borrowings by&#13;
2.   This point is made by Holsen in "Notes on the 'LDC Debt Problem',"&#13;
World Development, Vol.7 (1979), pp. 145-49.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
developing countries. A common perception is that their earlier heavy&#13;
borrowing makes these countries -- as a group -- significantly less well-&#13;
placed in the early 1980s to finance adjustment with growth than they&#13;
were in the mid-1970s.&#13;
This paper assesses the extent to which this perception is valid.&#13;
It does so by comparing the debt situation in which developing countries&#13;
now find themselves with that which prevailed earlier in the decade and&#13;
by evaluating the prospects for borrowing to finance adjustment, with&#13;
strong growth, in the 1980s. In Section II, the evolution during the&#13;
1970s of the debt of developing countries that report to the Debtor Reporting&#13;
System (DRS) of the World Bank is considered. Section III then takes up&#13;
a more detailed evaluation of the significant changes in the debt situation&#13;
of important country groupings and individual countries. It includes a&#13;
consideration of the effects of borrowing on debt and debt-service&#13;
indicators. The outlook for the 1980s is discussed in Section IV. The&#13;
summary and conclusions are presented in the final section.&#13;
In brief, the main conclusions of the paper are that there is no&#13;
evidence of a systematic deterioration in the external position of the&#13;
developing countries during the past decade -- notwithstanding the fact&#13;
that some countries have experienced debt-management difficulties. Easy&#13;
market conditions have contributed to the rapid build-up of debt on&#13;
commercial terms; but so too have good adjustment and debt-management&#13;
policies in many of the more creditworthy developingcountries. If not&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
arguably the best of times, the 1970s do not appear to have been the worst&#13;
of times for developing countries' foreign debt.&#13;
This does not mean that one should be optimistic about borrowing&#13;
prospects in the 1980s. Developing countries still require substantial&#13;
flows of foreign capital, in addition to sound domestic policies, if&#13;
they are to attain high growth during the adjustment period of the next&#13;
few years. Although as a group they may not be constrained severely by&#13;
past borrowings (indeed, the renewed capital market activity of the last&#13;
quarter of 1980 and so far in 1981 supports the opposite view), depressed&#13;
export prospects combined with a comparative dearth of official capital&#13;
for development could cause severe, future debt-management difficulties&#13;
for countries that adopt an ambitious growth strategy founded on large&#13;
inflows of foreign capital.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6-&#13;
II. The Evolution of Developing Countries'&#13;
External Indebtedness: 1970-80&#13;
Three main questions are asked when changes in the debt&#13;
situation of developing countries are analyzed:&#13;
*     What has happened to the (nominal) stock of debt&#13;
by creditor source? (3)&#13;
*     How have flows of debt capital and the associated&#13;
terms of borrowing changed?&#13;
o     How have debt and debt-servicing obligations changed&#13;
relative to the major macro-economic aggregates that&#13;
affect assessments of creditworthiness?&#13;
Developments in the Stock of Debt&#13;
The changing patterns of the disbursed and outstanding debt of&#13;
developing countries during the 1970s are shown in Tables la,&#13;
3.   The "real" level of indebtedness associated with a given nominal value&#13;
will vary, of course, depending on inflation. In its recent work on debt,&#13;
the IMF (see references) has investigated the impact of inflation by using&#13;
different price indices. No index is perfectly satisfactory, but the IMF&#13;
concludes that debt in the 1970s, for example, grew at only 6-9 percent&#13;
(in real terms) compared with 12 percent in the 1960s. These figures are&#13;
suggestive, but not easy to interpret. However, they do support similar&#13;
conclusions from earlier internal studies in the World Bank. Rather than&#13;
attempting to correct for inflation with imperfect price indices, this&#13;
paper assesses the "real situation" by reference to the evolution of debt&#13;
indicators (ratios) (see the sub-section of that title). Note that&#13;
attention centers on the external liabilities of developing countries,&#13;
and no account is taken of their external assets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
lb, and Ic (4). The first table provides the volume of public and publicly&#13;
guaranteed debt at end year by creditor source plus non-guaranteed&#13;
debt for 1970-80; the second gives the end year to end year growth rates of&#13;
debt for 1970-80, as well as trend growth (by least squares) in each&#13;
category, for 1970-79; and the third gives the shares of each category&#13;
in total debt disbursed and outstanding. (5)&#13;
The total medium- and long-term debt of the developing countries&#13;
reached US$379 billion in 1979, of which $306 billion (81 percent) was public&#13;
or publicly guaranteed. In 1970, total debt was only $64 billion (83 percent&#13;
of which was public), so there was a six-fold increase in nine years.&#13;
Preliminary data indicate a further increase of some $44 billion to&#13;
$423 billion in 1980.&#13;
4.   Tables include data for all developing countries that are included in&#13;
the World Development Report 1981 andthat report to the DRS except Iran&#13;
and Iraq, for which no reliable data later than 1978 are available. Figures&#13;
for public and publicly guaranteed debt are as reported to the DRS by&#13;
World Bank members; figures for private non-guaranteed debt are based on&#13;
actual and estimated data for forty-two countries considered significant&#13;
in such flows, of which seventeen report to the DRS. Debt is medium- and&#13;
long-term (i.e., having an original maturity of more than a year).    Spe&#13;
Annex III for details of included countries.&#13;
5.   All 1980 data are estimates based on preliminary and incomplete&#13;
information. The numeraire for all volume figures is the U.S. dollar.&#13;
Because of exchange rate volatility and the currency mix of outstanding debt,&#13;
valuation adjustments can distort year-on-year changes in external indebt-&#13;
edness. Considered over the whole period, these effects are less important.&#13;
Flows of borrowed capital are discussed in the next sub-section; generally,&#13;
exchange rate movements mean that stock and flow figures cannot be recon-&#13;
ciled fully.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table la&#13;
MEDIUM- AND LONG-TERM EXTERNAL DEBT OUTSTANDING AND DISBURSED:&#13;
PUBLIC DEBT BY CREDITOR SOURCE AND PRIVATE NON-GUARANTEED DEBT,  1970-80&#13;
(US$ billions)&#13;
1970     1971     i972      1973      1974      1975      1976       1977       1978    1979      1980 /&#13;
Public Debt&#13;
Total Concess. Bilateral           22.6      27.0     30.1     34.8      40.2       45.5      51.6       59.5      67.5     71.4       78.3&#13;
DAC Governments                  18.0      21.7     24.4     28.0       31.7      34.0      38.0       43.4      49.8     52.0       55.6&#13;
OPEC Governments                  0.4       0.5      0.5      0.8        1.8       4-6       6.3        7.6       8.6      9.8       11.6&#13;
CPE Governments                   3.8       4.5      4.8      5.7       6.1        6.2       6.6        7.6       8.0      8.6        9.9&#13;
Other Bilateral                   0.3       0.3      0.4      0.4       0.6        0.7       0.8        0.9       1.0      1.1        1.3&#13;
Total Offic. Export Credits          4.3       4.6      5.3      6.2       8.0        9.4      11.5       13.8      18,3     21.2       23.4&#13;
DAC Governments                   3.9       4.3      4.9      5.7       6.9        7.8       9.2       10.6      14.0     16.6       17.9&#13;
OPEC Governments                  0.0       0.0      0.0      0.1       0.2        0.6       1.6        1.6       2.3      2.6        2.9&#13;
CPE Governments                   0.3       0.1      0.2      0.2        0.3       0.4       0.5        0.5       0.8      0.8        1.1&#13;
Other Bilateral                   0.1       0.1      0.2      0.3       0.5        0.7       0.8        1.0       1.2      1.3        1.5&#13;
Total Multilateral Loans             8.0       9.2     10.8     12.9      15.7       19.3      23.4       29.5      36.4     43.5       51.8&#13;
IBRD                              4.9       5.6      6.4      7.2       8.3        9.9      11.6       13.4      15.6    18.5        21.9&#13;
IDA                               1.8       2.1      2.8      3.6       4.5        5.6       6.9        8.0       9.1    10.4        12.1&#13;
Regional Banks Concessional       0.5       0.5      0.6      0.7       0.9        1.0       1.3        1.7       2.3      3.0        3.9&#13;
Regional Banks Non-Concessional   0.5       0.7      0.9      1.2        1.6       2.1       2.7        3.4       4.4      5.3        6.4&#13;
Other Multi-Concessional          0.0       0.1      0.1      0.1        0.2       0.3       0.4        1.9       3.6      4.5        5.8&#13;
other Multi-Non-Concessional      0.2       0.2      0.1      0.1        0.2       0.3       0.6        1.1       1.5      1.7        11.7&#13;
Total Private Source Loans          17.7      21.2     26.6     35.1      47.2       60.8      80.5      104.9     138.9    169.3      187.3&#13;
Suppliers Credits                 7.0       7.8      9.1     10.1      12.0       13.1      14.6       17.4      21.6     21.5       19.4&#13;
Financial Markets                 9.5      12.3     16.5     23.4      33.5       46.3      64.0       86.0     115.9    146.7      167.2&#13;
Financial Institutions          6.3       8.7     12.5     18.7       28.4      40.8      57.2       75.4     101.4    131.2      147.9&#13;
Bonds                            3.2      3.5      4.0      4.7        5.1       5.5       6.8       10.6       14.5    15.5       19.3&#13;
Other                              1.1      1.1      1.0      1.2        1.7       1.4       2.0        1.6       1.3      1.1        0.7&#13;
Total Public Debt                   52.6     62.1      72.8     89.0     111.0      135.0     167.1      207.1     261.1   305.5      340.7&#13;
Total Private Non-Guar. Debt        11.0     14.2      19 3     25.7      32.2      38.8       45.7       53.4      64.4     73.4      82.5&#13;
Total Public and Private Debt       63.S     76.2      92.0    114.8     143.3      173.9     212.9      261.0     325.5    378.8      423.3&#13;
of which:&#13;
Total Bilateral                  26.9      31.7     35.3     41.0      48.1       54.9      63.2       73.3      85.7     92.7      101.7&#13;
Total Official                   34.9      40.9     46.2     54.0      63.8       74.2      86.6      102.8     122.2    136.2      153.5&#13;
Total Private Source             28.6      35.3     45.9     60.8      79.4       99.6     126.3      158.2     203.3    242.6      269.8&#13;
Total Concessional               24.9      29.8     33.6     39.3       45.8      52.4      60.2       71.1      82.5     89.4      100,1&#13;
Total Non-Concessional           38.6      46.5     58.5     75.5       97.5     121.4     152.6      189.9     243.0    289.4      323.2&#13;
Note: Figures include all developing countries in the World Development Report (WDR) data base that report to the DRS except Iran and Iraq.&#13;
DAC, Development Advisory Committee (of the OECD); OPEC, Organization of Oil-Exporting Countries; CPE. centrally planned economy;&#13;
IBRD, Ilteraatioual Bank for Reconstruction and Levelopment (World Bank); IDA, International Development Association (of the World Bank).&#13;
/a    All 1980 data are estimates.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9-&#13;
Debt from official sources increased from $35 billion to&#13;
$154 billion between 1970 and 1980 -- an impressive expansion that was&#13;
dwarfed, however, by the explosion of debt to private creditors, which rose&#13;
from $29 billion to $270 billion. During the same period, debt on non-&#13;
concessional terms increased much more than concessional debt: from three-&#13;
fifths of the total in 1970 it rose to more than three-quarters in 1979.&#13;
(6)   Within public debt from private creditors, financial institutions&#13;
accounted for an astonishing increase -- from $6 billion in 1970 to&#13;
$148 billion in 1980. Suppliers' credits had exceeded financial credits&#13;
in 1970, but were less than one-seventh the volume of total financial&#13;
credits in public debt in 1980. (7)&#13;
Inflation obscures the inferences that can be drawn from nominal&#13;
debt figures. But Tables lb and lc offer a somewhat better appreciation of&#13;
the rapidly changing composition of external debt as well as the&#13;
fluctuations (including valuation adjustments) in the end year to end&#13;
year growth of debt. Trend rates (by least squares) of growth for 1970-79&#13;
6. These figures probably overstate the decline in debt on concessional&#13;
terms because they neglect the effects of inflation. Concessional debt is&#13;
defined as having a grant element of 25 percent or more, discounting&#13;
service obligations at the traditional 10 percent. The increase in&#13;
inflation over the decade and the resulting increases in nominal interest&#13;
rates suggest that the share of concessional assistance is biased downwards&#13;
by using the same discount rate at the beginning and end of the decade.&#13;
But concessional debt tends to have a high grant element -- around 85 percent&#13;
for International Development Association (IDA) terms -- so the classifica-&#13;
tion may not be very sensitive to changes in the discount rate.&#13;
7. Estimates of private non-guaranteed debt are available only at the&#13;
aggregate level. Therefore, discussion of specific sub-categories of&#13;
debt refers to public and publicly guranteed debt only.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table lb&#13;
MEDIUM- AND LONG TERM EXTERNAL DEBT OUTSTANDING AND DISBURSED:&#13;
PUBLIC DEBT BY CREDITOR SOURCE AND PRIVATE NON-GUARANTEED DEBT, 1970-80&#13;
(annual gtowth rates, percent)&#13;
1970      1971      1972     1973      1974      1975       1976      1977       1978      1979       1980-L    Trend/&gt;&#13;
Growth&#13;
1970-79&#13;
Public Debt&#13;
Total Concessional Bilateral       14.5       19.7     11.2      15.7      15.4      13.3      13.5       15.3      13.4       5.9        9.7       13.9&#13;
DAC Governments                    15.7       20.5     12.3       15.0     13.0        7.4     11.6       14.3      14.7       4.3        6.9       12.3&#13;
OPEC Governments                    3.1       12.0      5.9      57.0     144.2      150.4     36.2       22.1      13.0      13.4      18.4        53.3&#13;
CPE Governments                    10.7       18.1      6.5       17.0      7.1        1.7      6.9       15.0       6.1       7.0       15.1        8.8&#13;
Other Bilateral                     8.7        1.9      9.1      -5.4      60.8      22.5      14.2       14.2      13.8       7.0      18.2        16.7&#13;
Total Official Export Credits        15.4       7.5      13.6      18.8      27.5      18.7      22.2       19.3      32.7      16.4      10.4        20.5&#13;
DAG Governments                    17.1       12.1     12.4       17.6     20.2       13.3     18.7       15.2      31.2      18.5        7.8       17.6&#13;
OPEC Governments                  -18.0     -16.2       2.2      122.9    249.4     141.5      80.3       58.9      41.6      12.1       11.5       81.2&#13;
CFE Governments                   - 3.5      -56.4     28.2       18.2     79.8       29.1      8.4       16.3      49.9       3.1       37.5       21.6&#13;
Other Bilateral                    26.9       13.0     38.3       33.2     91.2      27.7      22.7       17.1      24.3       8.2       15.4       32.5&#13;
Total Multilateral Loans             12.4      15.2      17.5      19.5      21.5      22.8      21.4       25.9      23.5      19.3      19.1        21.3&#13;
IBRD                               11.2       12.7     13.9      12.7      16.4      i9.1      16.7       15.7      16.2      19.1       18.4       16.0&#13;
IDA                                10.4       15.1     33.6      28.5      24.7      23.5      23.3       15.8      12.8      15.1      16.3        22.2&#13;
Regional Banks Concessional        23.1       19.5     12.5       23.8     15.5      19.9      24.7       34.3      34.4      28.5       30.0       23.2&#13;
Regional Banks Non-Concessional    18.8       30.2     24.6      36.0      34.4      32.1      26.7       27.7      29.5      21.0       20.8       29.8&#13;
Other Multi-Concessional           62.3       24.3     19.1       13.8    136.4      54.2      33.0      361.4      92.0      25.9       28.9       73.0&#13;
Other Multi-Non-Concessional       14.2       26.1    -58.7       35.9     61.2      68.2      74.9       87.8      39.2      12.3        0.0       36.9&#13;
Total Private Source Loans           27.4      19.9      25.8      31.7      34.6      28.9      32.5       30.2      32.4      21.9      10.6        29.9&#13;
Suppliers Credits                  14.4       11.3     15.9      15.3      15.0       9.4      10.9       19.1      24.5     - 0.7      -9.8        13.9&#13;
Financial Markets                  36.2       29.1     34.7      41.6      43.0      38.2      38.2       34.3      34.8      26.5       14.0       37.0&#13;
Financial Institutions           31.8       38.2     43.1      49.6      51.6      43.9      39.9       31.9      34.5      29.4       12.7       41.4&#13;
Bonds                            45.6       11.0     13.9       16.7      8.5        6.9     24.9       55.0      37.4       6.3       24.5       20.0&#13;
Other                              51.8      - 4.7    - 4.9       16.0     41.1     -18.7      46.6      -21.5     -14.1     -14.3     -36.4         3.2&#13;
Total Public Debt                    18.2       18.1     17.3      22.4      24.7      21.6      23.8       24.2      25.7      17.0       11.5       22.3&#13;
Total Private Non-Guaranteed&#13;
Debt                                 -         29.2     36.0      33.5      25.3      20.4      17.8       16.7      20.7      13.9       12.4       23.4&#13;
Total Public and Private Debt         -         20.0     20.7      24.7      24.8      21.4      22.4       22.6      24.7      16.4       11.7       22.5&#13;
of which:&#13;
Total Bilateral                    14.6       17.7     11.5      16.2      17.2      14.2      lS.O       16.0      17.0       8.1        9.7       15.1&#13;
Total Official                     14.1       17.1     12.9       17.0     18.3      16.3      16.6       18.7      18.9      11.4       12.7       16.7&#13;
Total Private Source              106.5       23.4     29.9       32.5     30.6      25.5      26.7       25.3      28.5      19.4       11.2       27.5&#13;
Total Concessional                 14.4       19.3     12.8       16.9     16.5      14.6      14.9       18.1      15.9       8.4       12.0       15.5&#13;
Total Non-Concessional             70.4      20.4      25.8      29.2      29.1      24.6      25.7       24.4      28.0      19.1       11.7       25.9&#13;
Note:    Figures include all developing ceuntries in the WOR data base that report to the DRS except Iran and Iraq.&#13;
/a      All 1980 data are estimates.&#13;
/b      Growth rates estimated by least-squares regression analysis.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 1c&#13;
MEDIUM- AND LONG-TERM EXTERNAL DEBT OUTSTASING AND DISBURSED;&#13;
PUBLIC DEBT BY CREDITOR SOURCE AND PRIVATE NON-GUARANTEED DEBT. 1970-80&#13;
- (shares of total debt, percent)&#13;
1970       1971        1972       1973       1974        1975       1976       1977       1978        1979       1980&#13;
Public Debt&#13;
Total Concessional Bilateral            35.6       35.5        32.7       30.3       28.0        26.2      24.2        22.8        20.7       18.9       18.5&#13;
DAC Governments                       28.4       28.5        26.5       24.4       22.1        19.6      17.8        16.6        15.3       13.7       13.1&#13;
OPEC Governments                       0.6        0.6         0.5        0.7         1.3        2.6       2.9         2.9         2.7        2.6        2.7&#13;
CPE Governments                        6.0        5.9         5.2        4.9        4.2        3.5        3.1         2.9        2.5         2.3        2.3&#13;
Other Bilateral                        0.5        0.5         0.4        0.3        0.4         0.4       0.4         0.4         0.3        0.3        0.3&#13;
Total Official Export Credits             6.8        6.1         5.7        5.4        5.6         5.4       5.4         5.3        5.6         5.6        5.5&#13;
DAC Governments                        6.1        5.7         5.3        5.0        4.8         4.5       4.3         4.1         4.3        4.4        4.2&#13;
OPEC Governments                       0.1        0.0         0.0        0.1        0.2         0.3       0.5         0.6         0.7        0.7        0.7&#13;
CPE Governments                        0.4        0.2        0.2         0.2        0.2        0.2        0.2         0.2        0.2         0.2        0.3&#13;
Other Bilateral                        0.2        0.2         0.2        0.2        0.4         0.4       0.4         0.4         0.4        0.3        0.4&#13;
Total Mulilateral Loans                  12.6        12.1       11.8       11.3        11.0       11.1      11.0         11.3       11.2       11.5       12.2&#13;
I8RD                                   7.8        7.3         6.9        6.2        5.8         5.7       5.4         5.1         4.8        4.9        5.2&#13;
IDA                                    2,9        2.8         3.1        3.2        3.2         3.2       3.3         3.1         2.8        2.8        2.9&#13;
Regional Banks Concessional            0.7        0.7         0.7        0.7        0.6         0.6       0.6         0.7         0.7        0.8        0.9&#13;
Regional Banks Non-Concessional        0.8        0.9         0.9        1.0         1.1        1.2       1.3          1.3        1.4        1.4        1.5&#13;
Other Multi-Concessional               0.1        0.1         0.1        0.1        0.1         0.2       0.2         0.7         1.1        1.2        1.4&#13;
Other Multi-Non-Concessional           0.3        0.3         0.1        0.1        0.1         0.2       0.3         0.4         0.5        0.4        0.4&#13;
Total Private Source Loans               27.8       27.8        28.9       30.5       32.9        35.0      37.8        40.2        42.7       44.7       44.2&#13;
Suppliers Credits                     11.0       10.3         9.8        9.1        8.4         7.6       6.8         6.7         6.6        5.7        4.6&#13;
Financial Markets                     15.0       16.1        18.0       20.4       23.4        26.6      30.1        32.9        35.6       38.7       39.5&#13;
Financial Institutions              10.0       11.5        13.6       16.3       19.8        23.5      26.8        28.9        31.1       34.6       34.9&#13;
Bonds                                5.0        4.7         4.4        4.1        3.6         3.1       3.2         4.1         4.5        4.1        4.6&#13;
Other                                  1.8         1.4        1.1        1.0         1.2        0.8       0.9         0.6         0.4        0.3        0.2&#13;
Total Public Debt                        82.7       81.4        79.1       77.6       77.5        77.2      78.5        79.6        80.2       80.6       80.5&#13;
Total Private Non-Guaranteed Debt        17.3        18.6       20.9       22.4        22.5       22.3      21.5         20.4       19.8       19.4       19.5&#13;
Total Public and Private Debt           100.0      100.0       100.0      100.0       100.0      100.0     100.0        100.0      100.0      100.0      100.0&#13;
of which:&#13;
Total Bilateral                       42.3       41.6        38.4       35.8       33.6        31.6      29.7        28.1        26.3       24.5       24.0&#13;
Total Official                        54.9       53.6        50.1       47.0       44.6        42.7      40.7        39.4        37.5       35.9       36.3&#13;
Total Private Source                  45.1       46.4        49.9       53.0       55.4        57.3      59.3        50.6        62.5       64.1       63.7&#13;
Total Concessional                    39.3        39.1       36.5       34.2       32.0        30.2      28.3        27.3        25.3       23.6       23.6&#13;
Total Non-Concessional                60.7       60.9        63.5       65.8       68.0        69.8      71.7        72.7        74.7       76.4       76.4&#13;
Note:    Figures include all developing countries in the WDR data base that report to the DRS e.-cept Iran and Iraq.&#13;
/a       All 1980 data are estimates.&#13;
Source: DRS.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-12-&#13;
(Table lb) show that total debt increased at 23 percent annually for the&#13;
period, with little difference in the rates for guaranteed and non-&#13;
guaranteed debt. But growth was sharply below trend (16 percent) in&#13;
1979, and estimates suggest a further significant decline (to 13 percent)&#13;
in 1980. Debt to official creditors grew at a trend rate of 17 percent;&#13;
to private creditors, at the much higher rate of 28 percent. Disbursed&#13;
and outstanding (publicly guaranteed)liabilities to private financial&#13;
institutions grew at the extraordinary trend rate of 41 percent a year.&#13;
Within public debt from official sources, multilateral credit&#13;
grew faster than bilateral -- at an average annual trend rate of 21 per-&#13;
cent. A notable feature was that outstanding multilateral debt on concessional&#13;
terms increased more rapidly than multilateral debt on hard terms. The&#13;
opposite- was true for bilateral   flows:  concessional lending grew at&#13;
only 14 percent (partly as a result of the rising share of grants in&#13;
development assistance) compared with 21 percent for official export&#13;
credits. In both bilateral categories, growth was boosted by the emergence&#13;
of Organization of Oil-Exporting Countries'(OPEC) governments as major&#13;
sources of finance.&#13;
From 10 percent of total debt in 1970, public debt held by&#13;
private financial institutions accounted for 35 percent in 1980. By&#13;
contrast, the share of suppliers' credits fell from 11 percent to 5 per-&#13;
cent. Despite the increased flows of capital to developing countries and&#13;
their strong growth (compared with industrial countries), the share of&#13;
bonds in total debt has not increased from 5 percent. This is an&#13;
undesirable development, given the developing countries' need for long-term&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-13-&#13;
capital. It might result from the unattractiveness of fixed-rate instruments&#13;
in a period of high and very uncertain interest rates, in which case&#13;
increasing recourse to floating-rate bonds could boost long-term capital&#13;
flows substantially. The share of all private source debt rose to&#13;
64 percent of total debt in 1979 from 45 percent in 1970; estimates indicate&#13;
that the share fell marginally in 1980.&#13;
The declining share of official debt was most marked for&#13;
bilateral credits on concessional terms. From 1971 the share of development&#13;
assistance lending from the Development Assistance Committee of the OECD&#13;
(DAC) governments in total debt of the developing countries has fallen&#13;
steadily and spectacularly -- from 29 percent in 1971 to only 14 percent&#13;
at end of 1979. (8) Another noteworthy change, especially given the&#13;
comparatively small overall decline in the share of multilateral lending,&#13;
was the steady fall in the share of developing countries' debt held by the&#13;
World Bank. Bank lending on harder terms fell from 8 percent of total&#13;
debt in 1970 to only 5 percent in 1979 and 1980. The share of lending on&#13;
concessionary terms (by IDA) fell only marginally during the full period,&#13;
but the decline between 1976 and 1980 was from 3.3 to 2.9 percent.&#13;
Some increase in the share of debt from private creditors is a&#13;
natural result of the substitution of debt for equity in investment flows&#13;
during the 1970s. Even so, the falling share of official source capital&#13;
8.   Only a small amount of this change can be explained by the increased&#13;
share df grants in bilateral official development assistance (ODA) and the&#13;
rising share of multilateral aid in total ODA.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-14-&#13;
in total debt prompts concern, since in the past it has complemented rather&#13;
than substituted for private flows. The rising share of grants in ODA&#13;
is a desirable trend, and the expansion of private capital inflows is an&#13;
encouraging development because it reflects the enhanced creditworthiness&#13;
and real economic progress of the leading developing countries. But,&#13;
for many, official capital on appropriate terms is needed to fund long-&#13;
lived, socially oriented projects; in the absence of a sustained increase in&#13;
finance from official sources, its distribution will be crucial to the&#13;
prospects of the poorest, less creditworthy economies.&#13;
Developments in Debt Flows&#13;
Changes in stocks of debt are suggestive, but flows of capital&#13;
are better indicators of the provision of resources to developing countries.&#13;
Information (in a condensed form) on the evolution of the important annual&#13;
flows of borrowed capital is provided in Tables 2a (volume) and 2b (annual&#13;
growth and trend growth for 1970-79). (9) Total commitments to developing&#13;
countries expanded rapidly from $17 billion in 1970 to $112 billion in&#13;
1979. New credits from official sources increased comparatively slowly;&#13;
the share of official credits in commitments fell from 44 percent in 1970&#13;
to 26 percent in 1979. Of the three-quarters of total commitments from&#13;
private creditors in 1979, the bulk was public credits from the financial&#13;
markets. These increased at a trend rate of 37 percent in 1970-79 to reach&#13;
49 percent of total commitments in 1979 (20 percent in 1970).&#13;
9.   Comparable data on flows in 1980 are not available.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 2a&#13;
COMMlITMENTS, DISBURSEMENTS, SERVICE PAYMENTS,AND NET CAPITAL MOVEMENTS:&#13;
MEDIUM- AND LONG-TERM DEBT 1970-79&#13;
(US$ billions)&#13;
1970      1971       1972      1973       1974      1975     1976        1977      1978       1979&#13;
COMMITMENTS&#13;
Total Public and Private              17.1      20.5       27.8      36.4       54.7      62.1      74.2       81.3      103.6     111.8&#13;
Official Sources                    7.5        8.4      10.6       12.9      20.2      21.7      24.7       26.0       29.6      29.3&#13;
Private Sources                     9.7       12.1      17.1       23.5      34.5      40.4      49.6       55.3       73.9      82.5&#13;
of which.&#13;
Public Credits from Financial&#13;
Markets                           3.4       4.7        7.0      11.8       17.1      20.4     28.5        32.2      46.9       55.1&#13;
DISBURSEMENTS&#13;
Total Public and Private              13.9      16.9       23.4      29.8       39.9      50.5      57.7       68.5       91.2      98.5&#13;
Official Sources                    5.4        6.0       6.8        8.8      11.3      15.4      15.1       17.3       19.5      21.5&#13;
Private Sources                     8.5       10.9      16.6       21.0      28.7      35.1      42.6       51.2       71.7      77.0&#13;
of which:&#13;
Public Credits from Financial&#13;
Markets                           2.6       4.2        6.3       9.5       13.2      17.1      22.9       28.7      42.8       50.3&#13;
AMORTIZATIONS&#13;
Total Public and Private               5.6       6.4        8.2       11.7      14.4      16.5      19.4       25.8       37.3      44.4&#13;
Official Sources                    1.6        1.7       2.1        2.5       2.8       3.2       3.4        4.1        4.8       6.3&#13;
Private Sources                     4.0        4.6       6.1       9.2       11.6      13.4      16.0       21.7       32.5      38.1&#13;
of which:&#13;
Public Credits from Financial&#13;
Markets                           1.2        1.6       2.1       3.0        3.7       3.8       4.8        8.2       16.4      19.8&#13;
NET FLOW&#13;
Total Public and Private               8.4       10.5      15.2      18.1       25.5      33.9      38.3       42.7       53.9      54.1&#13;
Official Sources                    3.9        4.3       4.7        6.3       8.4      12.2      11.7       13.2       14.7      15.2&#13;
Private Sources                     4.5        6.2      10.5       11.8      17.1      21.7      26.6       29.5       39.2      38.9&#13;
of which-&#13;
Public Credits from Financial&#13;
Markets                           1.4        2.6       4.3       6.5        9.6   1   13.3     18.1       20.5       26.4      30.5&#13;
INTEREST&#13;
Total Public and Private               2.5        3 0       3.8       5.1        6.9       8.9      10.1       12.8       17.6      25.8&#13;
Offical Sources                     0.9        1.1       1.3        1.6       1.8       2.3       2.7        3.5        4.4       5.2&#13;
Private Sources                     1.5        1.9       2.4        3.5       5.1       6.6       7.4        9.3       13.2      20.6&#13;
of which.&#13;
Public Credits from Financial&#13;
Markets                           0.5        0.6       0.8        1.2       2.1       3.0       3.7        5.2        7.7      12.4&#13;
NET TRANSFER&#13;
Total Public and Private               5.9        7.5      11.4      12.9       18.6      25.0      28.2       29.8      36.3       28.3&#13;
Official Sources                    2.9        3.2       3.4       4.7        6.6       9.9       8.9        9.7       10.4      10.0&#13;
Private Sources                     3.0        4.3       8.0       8.2       12.0      15.1      19.3       20.1       26.0      18.3&#13;
of which:&#13;
Public Credits from Financial&#13;
Markets                           0.9        1.9       3.5        5.2       7.4      10.3      14.4       15.3       18.7      18.1&#13;
Note:     Figures include public and publicly guaranteed debt plus private non-guaranteed debt. Coverage as in Tables 1.&#13;
Data for 1980 are not available.&#13;
Source:  DRS.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-16-&#13;
Table 2b&#13;
COM9ITMENTS, DISBURSEMENST, SERVICE PAYMENTS, 48D NET CAPITAL MOVEMENTS&#13;
MEDIUM- AND LONG-TERM DEBT,     1970- 79&#13;
(annuaI growtb rates, percent)&#13;
1970      1971      1972      1973      1974      1975        1976       1977      1978       1979               Treed&#13;
1970-79 I&#13;
COMMSITMENTS&#13;
Total Public and Private                          -Lb  19 8     35 S      31 0      30 S      13 4        19 5        9 5      27 4        7 9                 24 3&#13;
Offlual Source                           31.9      13 4      26.0     20 7      37.4       7 5         13 5       3 2      14 1       -1 1                 19 2&#13;
Private Sources                               lb   24.8      43.1     37.2      46 6      16 9        228 9       I  7     33 6       II 5                 27 6&#13;
of which&#13;
Public Credits from Pieancial1..97112                                                                                   4           753.&#13;
Markets                              46 5      38 4      47 7      69.2      43 2      190         37          32       45         17566&#13;
DISBUSEOMENTS&#13;
Total Public and Pricate                         /b   21 1      38 6      27 4      34 0      26 4        14 3       18 7      33 2        9 5                23.1&#13;
Official Sources                         20 V      15 4      12 7      30 4      27 4     36 7       -1 9         14 3     13 0        10 0                17.9&#13;
Private   ore                                 /5   27 9      52 9      26 2     36 7      22 3        21 4        20 2     40 0         7 5                28 2&#13;
of which&#13;
Public Credits fr.. Finan.cial&#13;
Market.                               20 2      61 6      52 0      50 0      39 7     29 3         33 6       25 7     48 9        17 6                38 4&#13;
AMORTIZATIONS&#13;
Total Public and Private                         A'   14 7      28 4      43 2      23 5      14 6        17 2       33 1      44 7       19 1                 26 2&#13;
Official Sources                         20 7       9 4      19.4      22 5      12 6      11 8         7 9       18 4     18.6       31 6                 IS 7&#13;
Priv-tniou.rcn                                _'   1698      3198     50 3      25 9      15 3         194       36 2      49 6       172                  291&#13;
of which&#13;
Public Credits free Pluanriel&#13;
Markats                               33 1      34.0      29 3      47.0      21 2       4.8        24 4       72 2      99 8       21 1                 35 3&#13;
MET FLOW&#13;
Total Public and Private                              25 3      44 7      18.9      41 1      33 0        12 9       11 5      262 7         4                 24 3&#13;
Official Sources                         20.9      IS 9      IS I      34 I     33 4      45 I          4 4       13 3      11 3       3 0                 18.8&#13;
Private Sources                              /b    37.6      69 5      12 1     45 2      27 1        22 6        10 6     33 0      -    6                27 5&#13;
of which&#13;
Public Credits free FinancIal&#13;
Marbeta                               II 5      83 1      66 5      SI 4      48 4      38 7        36.2       13 4      28 6       15 3                 39 9&#13;
INTEREST&#13;
Total Public and Private                         /6   20.2      25.8      36 6      34 8      28.9        13 1       27.1      37 2       46 3                 28 9&#13;
Official Sourcee                         16 3      12 2      24.4     22 8       13.0     26 1         18.6      27.4      24 9        18 2                21 3&#13;
Private.Sources                              lb    25.1      26 5     44 5      44 8      29 9         11 I      26 9      41 7       3556                 32i1&#13;
ofwhich&#13;
Public Credits from Financial&#13;
Macbeta                                63.5      19 4      21.9     58.7      74 8      41 2        22 0       41 5      47 2       61 I                 43 0&#13;
NET TRANSFER&#13;
Total Public and Private                        /b    27 5      52 3      13 1      43 5      34 6        12 5        5.9      21 8      -22 2                 21 8&#13;
Official Sources                         22 5      10.4       5 3      38 5       0       50 4       -9 8          9 0      6 4      - 3 6                  1.&#13;
Private Sources                              /b    44 1      87 4       2.5      45.3     25 9         27 6        4 4     29 2      -29.6                 24 6&#13;
of which:&#13;
Public Credita free Financial&#13;
Marka te                               -7 7     125 6      80.5      49.8     42 3      37 9        40 3         6 3     22 3      - 3 2                 38 &#13;
Met~e:       Figucee include public and publicly guacenteed debt plus prIvate -ne         u-5caateed debt    Cevarage as in Tables DILOc       fa r 1980 not avilable&#13;
La           Trend growth rates estSnated by least- s-ee        cerea-slon analyais.&#13;
Lb           Estimates of private -n-g-jar-t-d debt ace net avilable for 1969.&#13;
Source       DRS5.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-17-&#13;
The annual growth in commitments slowed sharply in 1979 to 8 per-&#13;
cent (compared with a trend rate for the period of 24 percent) and&#13;
commitments of official credits actually fell. New loans from private&#13;
sources also slowed. By contrast, 1978 had seen a strong increase in&#13;
commitments -- part of which was for refinancing on better terms. The pause&#13;
in 1979, which seems to have continued in 1980, may represent only a&#13;
stabilizing of borrowing at the higher level reached in 1978.&#13;
Disbursements also grew slowly (by 8 percent) in 1979 after&#13;
increasing by one-third in 1978.   The share of private credits in disburse-&#13;
ments was 78 percent in 1979 compared with 61 percent in 1970. Disburse-&#13;
ments on public credits from the financial markets were 51 percent of total&#13;
disbursements in 1979, compared with 19 percent in 1970. The higher shares&#13;
for private credits in disbursements compared with commitments reflect the&#13;
short time lags in disbursing debt from private creditors.&#13;
Despite the rapid growth of disbursements from 1976 to 1979, the&#13;
even more rapid growth in debt-service payments has resulted in a decline&#13;
in the ratio of net transfers (net flows less interest payments) to&#13;
disbursements. In 1970, after amortization and interest payments, 42 percent&#13;
of disbursements was available for purchasing goods and services from abroad&#13;
and for reserve accumulation. The ratio of net transfers to disbursements&#13;
rose to nearly 50 percent in 1975-76, but -- partly as a result of the&#13;
refinancing of debt noted above -- it had fallen to 40 percent by 1978.&#13;
In 1979 the slowing of disbursements, combined with the surge in interest&#13;
payments as interest rates have caught and passed inflation rates, caused a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-18-&#13;
decline to only 28 percent. The move back to positive real interest&#13;
rates effectively has eliminated the inflation-induced transfer from&#13;
lender to borrower.&#13;
But both net flows and net transfers have increased substantially&#13;
in real terms from 1970 to 1979. Net flows of $8 billion in 1970 rose to&#13;
$54 billion in both 1978 and 1979; although interest payments more than&#13;
doubled between 1977 and 1979, net transfers at $28 billion in 1979 were&#13;
four times their size in 1970. But the effects of higher interest rates&#13;
were marked; net transfers fell by more than one -uarter from the peak&#13;
of $36 billion in 1978. Continued high interest rates probably prevented&#13;
a rise in net transfers in 1980, but some growth should be evident during&#13;
1981 if monetary conditions ease and the interest-service payments on new&#13;
and on floating-rate debt decline.&#13;
The average terms on which developing countries have borrowed&#13;
public and publicly guaranteed debt in 1970-79 -- interest rate, maturity,&#13;
and grace period -- are shown in Table 3. Terms are shown for total&#13;
debt as well as debt from official and private sources.     Grant elements&#13;
shown are calculated at the standard discount rate of 10 percent (10).&#13;
10.   As noted in footnote 6, this convention tends to bias the grant&#13;
element downward over time as nominal interest rates have risen.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 3&#13;
AVERAGE TERMS OF BORROWING: COMMITMENTS OF PUBLIC AND&#13;
PUBLICLY GUARANTEED DEBT,1970-80&#13;
(percent,  years)&#13;
1970      1971       1972      1973       1974      1975       1976      1977      1978       1979      1980 /a&#13;
Total Public Debt&#13;
Interest Rate        (%)                5.3       5.6       5.7        6.7       7.1        6.9       6.8        6.9       7.9       9.6        n.a.&#13;
Maturity         (years)               20.0      18.8       18.0      28.6       17.2      15.5      14.6       14.2      14.6       14.0&#13;
Grace Period     (years)                5.4       5.2       5.0        5.7       5.3        4.8       4.4        4.5       4.7        4.7&#13;
Grant Element        (%)               31.8      28.2      27.5       23.4      20.4       19.8      18.6       18.2      14.1        6.3&#13;
Total Official Debt&#13;
Interest Rate       (M)                 3.7       4.3       4.4        4.1       4.4        4.9       5.5        5.2       4.9       5.0          5.2&#13;
Maturity         (years)               27.8      26.3      25.3       26.9      24.1       24.3      22.5       22.9      24.5       24.1        23.7&#13;
Grace Period     (years)                7.6       5.8       6.7        7.5       7.2        7.2       6.3        6.3       6.5        6.3         6.1&#13;
Grant Element        {X)               47.3      41.5      40.8       44.0      40.6       36.8      31.8       34.2      37.6      36.5        35.5&#13;
Bilateral&#13;
Interest Rate       (M)                 2.8       3.6       3.8        3.8       4.0        4.2       5.0        4.6       4.6       4.6          5.0&#13;
Maturity         (years)               28.1      25.5       24.0      24.2      21.7       22.2      21.3       23.0      23.5       23.0        21.3&#13;
Grace Period     (years)                8.5       7.3       7.0        7.7       7.5        7.6       6.7        7.0       6.8        6.5         5.9&#13;
Grant Element        (Z)               54.8      46.1      44.0       44.8      42.3       40.3      34.6       38.7      39.0       38.5        36.1&#13;
Multilateral&#13;
Interest Rate        (Z)                5.4       5.6       5.5        4.7       5.3        6.0       6.4        5.9       5.1       5.3          5.3&#13;
Maturity         (years)               27.2      27.7      27.7       31.6      29.0       27.8      24.7       22.8      25.8       25.1        25.7&#13;
Grace Period     (years)                5.9       6.0       6.2        7.1       6.6        6.3       5.7        5.6       6.1        6.2         6.2&#13;
Grant Element        (%)               33.8      33.6      34.6       42.7      37.2       31.1      26.8       29.2      35.9      34.4         35.0&#13;
Total Private Source Debt&#13;
Interest Rate        (M)                7.5       7.4       7.5        9.0       9.8        8.7       7.8        8.1       9.7      11.8         13.2&#13;
Maturity         (years)                9.3       8.9        9.1      11.0      10.4        7.8       8.5        8.0       8.9        9.1         8.8&#13;
Grace Period     (years)                2.5       3.0       2.9        4.1       3.4        2.7       2.9        3.2       3.7        3.9         3.6&#13;
Grant Element        (M)               10.6      10.7      11.1        4.5       0.7        4.9       8.2        6.8       0.5      -8.4        -15.1&#13;
Note:       Figures are based on public debt for which information tn terms is available.&#13;
/a         Estimates based on incomplete reports of new commitments in 1980.&#13;
Source:    DRS.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-20-&#13;
As expected, the table reveals the hardening of the average terms&#13;
under which developing countries now borrow. Average maturities have&#13;
fallen from 20 years in 1970 to 14 years in 1979, and grace periods have&#13;
fallen from 5.4 to 4.7 years during the same period. The average interest&#13;
rate on new commitments was over four percentage points higher in 1979&#13;
than in 1970, but the significance of this change is hard to assess given&#13;
inflation rate changes and the increasing proportion of commitments that have&#13;
floating interest rates. Even allowing for some downward bias, the fall&#13;
in the grant element is evidence of harder terms in the later years of&#13;
the decade.&#13;
Harder average terms are explained, however, more by the shift in&#13;
borrowing to private sources than by a general hardening of terms from&#13;
individual creditor groups. Overall terms for borrowing from multilateral&#13;
sources clearly have improved during the decade. Average interest rates in&#13;
1979 were unchanged from 1970 despite inflation, and the 2-year reduction&#13;
in average maturity was compensated by a small increase in the average&#13;
grace period. The grant element of multilateral credit was higher in 1979&#13;
than in 1970; the actual increase in concessionality probably is under-&#13;
stated (see footnote 6).&#13;
The average terms on bilateral official loans have deteriorated&#13;
even with the modest rise (1.8 percentage points) in the nominal interest&#13;
rate, but the rising share of multilateral debt has moderated the hardening&#13;
of terms of total official debt. And despite the fall in the grant element,&#13;
the terms of private source debt do not appear to have hardened appreciably.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-21-&#13;
Average maturity was 9.1 years in 1979, down marginally from 9.3 years in&#13;
1970, but this was more than compensated by a rise in the average grace&#13;
period from 2.5 to 3.9 years. Both of these changes may be explained&#13;
partly by the shift away from suppliers' credits and towards financial&#13;
credits in private source debt. (11) In real terms, the average terms of&#13;
private debt seem little harder in 1979 than they were in 1970, but they&#13;
remain harder than those on official credits.&#13;
In 1980, real interest rates rose sharply and the positive gap&#13;
between nominal rates in the capital markets and the rate of inflation has&#13;
widened further in 1981. Based on partial information for 1980, this trend&#13;
is reflected in harder average terms for both official and private debt.&#13;
On private and bilateral official debt, interest rates, maturities, and&#13;
grace periods all have moved adversely. By contrast, maturities for multi-&#13;
lateral lending were lengthening slightly from 1979, and the grant element&#13;
improved marginally.&#13;
The Evolution of Debt Indicators&#13;
Although their external debt has increased rapidly from 1970 to&#13;
1980 and, on average, it has become more expensive, this does not mean that&#13;
developing countries cannot or should not borrow large sums to meet their&#13;
11.   As reported to DRS, financial credits include buyers' credits for&#13;
which terms may be similar to -- though presumably no harder than -- those&#13;
for suppliers' credits. DRS data cannot determine the extent to which&#13;
buyers' credits have substituted for suppliers' credits.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-22-&#13;
renewed need for adjustment finance in the early 1980s. Some indication of&#13;
their capacity for further borrowing can be obtained by comparing their&#13;
situation at the end of the decade with that at the beginning, as measured&#13;
by the changes in the ratios of debt and debt-service payments to the&#13;
several key macro-economic aggregates that strongly influence a country's&#13;
ability to make service payments abroad.&#13;
Table 4a provides aggregate data (12) for the debt-service and&#13;
interest-service ratios, the capital-service ratio (defined as the ratio of&#13;
debt-service payments plus other investment income paid abroad to exports&#13;
of goods and all services), and the ratios of debt outstanding and disbursed&#13;
(DOD) to GNP, exports of goods and all services,and reserves. (13) The&#13;
ratio of interest service to GNP -- a measure of the current cost of borrowed&#13;
capital in terms of output -- also is provided. (14)&#13;
The aggregate data suggest that developing countries as a group&#13;
are not much worse positioned to borrow and service debt at the end of the&#13;
decade than they were at the beginning. The growth of exports and reserves&#13;
12.   Time-series data for some countries reporting to the DRS are&#13;
incomplete. These countries are excluded from the aggregates; see note&#13;
to Table 4a and Annex II.&#13;
13.   Other investment income is obtained from IMF balance-of-payments data;&#13;
for some items and for some countries the figures are net rather than gross.&#13;
14.   Because GNP already excludes net interest payments, for some purposes&#13;
GDP would be a preferable denominator.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 4a&#13;
EVOLUTION OF DEBT AND DEBT-SERVICE INDICATORS:&#13;
ALL DEVELOPING COUNTRIES,&#13;
AGGREGATES 1970-79,&#13;
TOTAL DEBT&#13;
(percent)&#13;
1970     1971      1972     1973      1974     1975      1976     1977      1978     1979&#13;
Indicators&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio              12.4     13.0      13.6     13.4      11.5     13.5      13.2     14.4      17.9     17.8&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio           3.8      4.2      4.3       4.1      3.8       4.8      4.6       4.8       5.7      6.5&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio           18.0     18.3      18.0     18.0      15.5     17.1      16.4     17.8     20.8      20.2&#13;
DOD/GNP                         15.1     16.3      17.4     16.9      16.3     18.0      19.8     21.4      22.9     22.1&#13;
DOD/Exports                     97.5    105.6     104.6     90.5      77.3     93.2     96.6     100.1     108.0     97.2  N&#13;
DOD/Reserves                   321.1    297.1     234.2    199.1     185.9    250.5    261.4     269.9    270.8     219.9&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP             0.6      0.6      0.7       0.7      0.8       0.9      0.9       1.0     1.2        1.5&#13;
Total Debt&#13;
(US$ billions)                    61.4      73.4     88.5     109.7    136.7     165.9    203.2     250.1    313.7     365.6&#13;
Note:     Figures include all developing countries in the WDR data base that report to the DRS except those for&#13;
which complete and reliable time-series data are not available (Afghanistan, Bahrain, Botswana,&#13;
Burundi, Comoros, Guinea, Iran, Iraq, Lebanon, Lesotho, Liberia, Maldives, Nepal, Papua New Guinea,&#13;
and South Africa).&#13;
Source: DRS.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-24-&#13;
have kept pace with the growth of debt. The debt-service ratio has risen&#13;
sharply -- by 4 to 5 percentage points -- but almost all of this increase has&#13;
occurred in 1978 and 1979. As discussed above, refinancing explains much of&#13;
the increase in 1978, and some major borrowers (for example, Mexico) made&#13;
substantial prepayments also in 1979; and the rapid rise in the interest-&#13;
service ratio indicates that high interest rates helped raise the debt-&#13;
service ratio in 1978 and, especially, in 1979.&#13;
The high debt-service payments of the past two years have contributed&#13;
to raising the capital-service ratio. But, even with this increase, the&#13;
capital-service ratio is very little higher at the end of the decade (around&#13;
two percentage points) than at the beginning. The growth of debt relative&#13;
to equity capital has resulted in a (proportional) substitution of interest&#13;
and amortization payments for dividends. The ratio of debt to GNP has&#13;
increased, but this is not unusual for countries growing rapidly and importing&#13;
capital from abroad. As a share of GNP, interest-service payments have&#13;
risen strongly, but the proportional decline in service payments on equity&#13;
and the neglect (in this analysis) of external assets earning high interest&#13;
rates probably overstates the real increase in carrying costs of borrowed capital.&#13;
Aggregate data can be misleading, however, in that they do not&#13;
allow fully for changes in the situations of countries that are major current&#13;
borrowers. For instance, the exports and reserve holdings of countries&#13;
that are not creditworthy or that choose not to borrow will not improve&#13;
the market prospects of those countries that do. One way to allow for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-25-&#13;
this is to weight the debt and debt-service indicators for individual&#13;
countries by their shares in outstanding debt. (15)&#13;
Unfortunately, information by country on private non-guaranteed&#13;
debt is available only since 1974. Table 4b shows debt and debt-service&#13;
indicators for all developing countries for 1974-79, weighted by their&#13;
shares in total debt. Even allowing for the heavy influence of Brazil,&#13;
Mexico (which by common agreement has not had a deterioration in its&#13;
borrowing prospects), and Spain, the indicators in Table 4b suggest that&#13;
the current borrowers have experienced a deterioration in their external&#13;
situation between 1974 and 1979. The interest-service ratio increased&#13;
by more than 60 percent, the debt-service ratio by 53 percent, and the&#13;
capital-service ratio by 38 percent. Unfortunately, even these large&#13;
changes permit no firm conclusions because 1974 was a particularly favorable&#13;
year, being the peak of an export boom.&#13;
Table 4c presents a comparison of the unweighted and weighted&#13;
indicators over the decade for public debt only. (16) The patterns are&#13;
15.   The aggregate indicator I =y =Ii-         I.D    where D   is the&#13;
value of the indicator for country i, D. the level of its debt, and D&#13;
the total debt for all included countries. Clearly, this indicator is far&#13;
from perfect -- it downplays the borrowing potential of countries that&#13;
have underutilized debt-servicing capacity; it is sensitive to shocks&#13;
(for example, a sharp downturn of exports) in important borrowers; and for&#13;
some purposes (the capital-service ratio is an example) the weights are&#13;
inappropriate -- but it does provide some feeling for the aggregate impact&#13;
on key indicators of changes in the economies of major current borrowers.&#13;
16.   Countries' shares in public debt (the weights for Table 4c) are&#13;
provided in Annex III.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 4b&#13;
EVOLUTION OF DEBT AND DEBT-SERVICE INDICATORS:&#13;
ALL DEVELOPING COUNTRIES,&#13;
DEBT-WEIGHTED AGGREGATES 1974-79,&#13;
TOTkL DEBT&#13;
(percent)&#13;
1974     1975     1976      1977     1978     1979&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio           18.6     21.9     21.2     23.3     28.0     28.4&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio       6.5       8.4      7.8      7.9      9.3     10.5&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio        22.8     26.1     25.2     27.5     32.3     31.5&#13;
DOD/GNP                     25.5     25.2      27.0     29.1     31.3     29.8&#13;
DOD/Exports                138.7    158.5     162.5    164.9    172.7    153.0&#13;
DOD/Reserves                490.2    698.5    707.2    696.3    630.9    532.6&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP         1.0      1.2       1.2      1.3      1.6      1.9&#13;
Note:      Figures include all developing countries in the WDR data base that report to the&#13;
DRS except those for which complete and reliable time-series data are not available&#13;
(Afghanistan, Bahrain, Botswana, Burundi, Comoros, Guinea, Iran, Iraq, Lebanon,&#13;
Lesotho, Liberia, Maldives, Nepal, Papua New Guinea, and South Africa).&#13;
Weighted aggregate indicators are obtained from indicators for individual&#13;
countries weighted by their shares in total debt. (See Annex III for the&#13;
debt shares 1970-79).&#13;
Source:     DRS.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 4c&#13;
EVOLUTION OF DEBT AND DEBT-SERVICE INDICATORS:&#13;
ALL DEVELOPING COUNTRIES,&#13;
AGGREGATES AND DEBT-WEIGHTED AGGREGATES 1970-79,&#13;
PUBLIC DEBT ONLY&#13;
(percent)&#13;
1970     1971      1972     1973      1974     1975     1976      1977     1978      1979&#13;
Indicators&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio           8.9       9.2      9.0       8.8      7.1      8.4       8.4      9.5     12.4      12.6&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio       2.8       2.9      2.8      2.7       2.4      3.2       3.3      3.5      4.2       4.8&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio /a    14.5      14.5     13.4      13.4     11.1     11.9      11.5     12.9     15.5      15.0&#13;
DOD/GNP                     12.3      13.1     13.5      13.1     12.6     13.9      15.5     17.0     18.3      17.8&#13;
DOD/Exports                 80.1      85.2     81.8      70.0     59.6     72.1      75.6     79.6     86.6      78.3&#13;
DOD/Reserves               263.7     239.9    183.2     153.9    143.5    193.9     204.6    214.5    217.3     176.4&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP         0.4       0.4      0.5      0.5       0.5      0.6       0.7      0.7      0.9       1.1&#13;
'eighted Indicators /b&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio          14.9      14.0     14.1      13.4     11.5     13.7      13.7     15.9     19.7      20.8&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio       4.9       4.9      4.6      4.3       4.1      5.4       5.6      5.9      6.8       7.7&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio       20.6      20.2     18.5      18.2     15.6     17.9      17.7     20.0     23.9      23.8&#13;
DOD/GNP                     18.0      19.9     20.7      21.7     20.1     22.7      24.3     26.7     28.7      27.6&#13;
DOD/Exports                175.9     187.9    166.0    135.6     119.2    134.0     135.8    139.5    144.4     130.5&#13;
DOD/Reserves               725.3     708.4    503.2    392.9     448.7    632.5     628.8    663.2    611.8     494.7&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP         0.5       0.5      0.6      0.7       0.7      0.9       1.0      1.1      1.3       1.6&#13;
Memo Item&#13;
Total Public DOD of Included&#13;
Countries (US$ billion)   50.4      59.3     69.3     84.8     105.5    128.4     159.1    198.9    251.7     294.4&#13;
Note:      Figures include all developing countries in the WDR data base that report to the DRS except those tor&#13;
which complete and reliable time-series data are not available (Afghanistan, Bahrain, Botswana, Comoros,&#13;
Guinea, Iran, Iraq, Lebanon, Lesotho, Liberia, Maldives, Nepal, Papua New Guinea, and South Africa).&#13;
/a         Excluding debt-service on non-guaranteed debt.&#13;
/b         Weights are the shares of individual countries in public debt of the group.&#13;
Source:   DRS.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-28-&#13;
similar to those in Tables 4a and 4b, but some of the unweighted indicators&#13;
-- the ratios of public debt to exports and to reserves -- are better at&#13;
the end of the decade than at the beginning. The stability of the capital-&#13;
service ratio (excluding service payments on private non-guaranteed&#13;
debt) is even more evident.&#13;
Compared with early years of the decade, 1974 is revealed as a&#13;
banner year. Virtually all of the deterioration in debt-service indicators&#13;
-- both weighted and unweighted -- occurred in 1978 and 1979, when debt-&#13;
service payments were raised above trend by persistent refinancing and&#13;
high interest rates. However, there is a widening gap between the weighted&#13;
and unweighted indicators during the period, which is an indicator of some&#13;
deterioration in the external situation of major current borrowers during&#13;
the 1970s. For example, in 1970 the weighted debt-service ratio&#13;
exceeded the unweighted by 6 percentage points; by 1979 the gap had widened&#13;
to about 8 percentage points. For the capital-service ratio, the gap also&#13;
widened by about 2 points over the period. Similar widening occurred for&#13;
the weighted and unweighted ratios of debt to GNP; but for the debt-to-&#13;
exports ratio the opposite occurred because major borrowers tended to raise&#13;
exports feaster than public debt.&#13;
From aggregate analysis, therefore, the conclusion follows that,&#13;
despite some evidence of a deterioration in the position of major borrowers,&#13;
borrowing by the developing countries during the decade has not resulted&#13;
in a pronounced fall in their current debt-servicing capability. (17)&#13;
17.   The IMF study (see references) reached similar conclusions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-29-&#13;
III. The Debt of Individual Developing Countries and Country Groups&#13;
Clearly, an examination of debt-weighted aggregate indicators&#13;
cannot substitute for careful analysis of individual developing countries&#13;
in assessing their external debt situation and their likely access to funds&#13;
in the 1980s.   Such individual analyses are beyond the scope of this paper;&#13;
but, in this section, an examination is made of changes in the debt of the&#13;
principal borrowing countries during 1970-79. As well, the situations of&#13;
four groups of developing countries -- oil exporters; low-income oil&#13;
importers; middle-income oil importers that are significant exporters of&#13;
manufactures; and other middle-income oil importers -- are assessed through&#13;
an examination of the changes in debt indicators.(18)    The discussion is&#13;
illustrated by reference to the situation of individual countries, which&#13;
are classified -- on the basis of superficial examination of their debt&#13;
indicators -- as better- or worse-placed to borrow in 1980 than in 1970.&#13;
The Debt of Principal Borrowers&#13;
Concerns over portfolio constraints on further private&#13;
lending to developing economies as well as over the stability of the&#13;
process of financial intermediation raise the questions of how much of the&#13;
debt is held by how few and of what changes have taken place during the&#13;
decade.   Table 5 shows that 31 economies accounted for 88 percent of&#13;
total debt in 1979 -- 92 percent of private debt and 80 percent of&#13;
official debt -- and 94 percent of debt-service payments.&#13;
18. To reduce the numbers appearing in the text, tables corresponding&#13;
to Tables 4a-c for these sub-groups of countries are in Annex 1.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-30-&#13;
Table 5&#13;
PRINCIPAL BORROWERS, 1979:&#13;
DEBT AND DEBT SERVICE, 1970 and 1979&#13;
(US$ billions)&#13;
Outstanding Public and Publicly Guaranteed Debt&#13;
Official                 Private&#13;
Sources                 Sources                  Total                Debt Service&#13;
1970      1979           1970     1979           1970      1979          1970      1979&#13;
OIL EXPORTERS&#13;
Algeria                              0.5        2.2            0.5     13.2           0.9      15.3           0.0        2.7&#13;
Egypt                                 1.2       9.5            0.4      1.9           1.6      11.4           0.3        1.0&#13;
Indonesia                            2.2        8.5            0.3      4.8           2.4      13.3           0.1       2.1&#13;
Malaysia                             0.2        1.2            0.2      1.8           0.4       3.0           0.1        0.6&#13;
Mexico                                1.2       3.6            2.0     25.2           3.2      28.8           0.7       10.4&#13;
Nigeria                              0.4        1.0            0.1      2.7           0.5       3.7           0.1        0.3&#13;
Peru                                 0.4        2.7            0.5      3.2           0.9       5.9           0.1        0.9&#13;
Syria                                0.2        2.1            0.0      0.2           0.2       2.3           0.0       0.4&#13;
Tunisia                              0.4        1.9            0.2      1.2           0.5       3.1           0.1        0.3&#13;
Venezuela                            0,4        0.5            0.4      9.3           0.7       9.8           0.1        1.5&#13;
TOTAL                            7.1      33.2            4.6     63.5          11.3       96.6           1.6      20.2&#13;
ADVANCED MEDITERRANEAN ECONOMIES&#13;
Greece                               0.4        0.8            0.6      2.6           0.9       3.5           0.1        0.7&#13;
Israel                               1.0        6.5            1.3      3.5           2.3      10.0           0.0        0.9&#13;
Portugal                             0.2        1.6            0.3      2.1           0.5       3.7           0.1        0.4&#13;
Spain                                0.7        2.0            0.6      6.7           1.2       8.7           0.2        1.7&#13;
Turkey                                1.8       7.2            0.1      3.8           1.9      11.0           0.2        0.6&#13;
Yugoslavia                           0.9        3.3            0.3      0.4           1.2       3.7           0.2        0.6&#13;
TOTAL                            5.0      21.4            3.2      19.1           8.0      40.6           0.8       4.9&#13;
OTHER DEVELOPING ECONOMIES&#13;
0.6       1.9            1.2       6.8           1.9       8.7           0.5       1.5&#13;
Argentina                             -         2.7             -       0.2            -        2.8            -         0.1&#13;
Bangladesh  '                         1.9       5.8            1.4     29.3           3.2      35.1           0.4        6.3&#13;
Brazil                                1.2       1.7            0.9      3.1           2.1       4.8           0.2        1.3&#13;
Chile                                 1.1       2.2            0.2      1.3           1.2       3.4           0.1        0.7&#13;
Colombia                              7.6      15.4            0.3      0.2           7.9      15.6           0.5        1.0&#13;
IndiaCas                             0.1        1.1            0.1      2.5           0.3       3.5           0.0        0.5&#13;
ory a                                0.6        5.8            1.2      8.9           1.8      14.7           0.3        2.6&#13;
Korea                                0.6        2.9            0.1      3.3           0.7       6.2           0.1        0.8&#13;
Morocco                               2.8       7.6            0.3      0.4           3.1       8.0           0.2        0.5&#13;
Pakilitpne                           0.3        2.3            0.3      2.9           0.6       5.2           0.1        0.8&#13;
Philippinesa                         0.0        o.d            1.1      7.4           1.1       7.4           0.2        2.2&#13;
out     rca                          0.3        1.4            0.3      1.6           0.6       3.1           0.1        0.7&#13;
Thailand                             0.3        1.6            0.0      1.1           0.3       2.7           0.0        0.3&#13;
hailn                                0.1        1.6            0.2      2.2           0.3       3.8           0.0        0.2&#13;
airTOTAL                             17.5      54.0            7.6     71.2          25.1     125.0           2.7       19.5&#13;
TOTAL ABOVE (31)                        29.6      108.6           15.4    153.8          44.4     262.2           5.1      44.6&#13;
(As % of all developing economies'     (84.8)     (79.7)        (87.0)    (90.8)        (84.4)    (85.8)        (87.9)    (89.4)&#13;
public and publicly guaranteed debt)&#13;
TOTAL ALL DEVELOPING ECONOMIES          34.9      136.2           17.7    169.3          52.6     305.5           5.8      49.9&#13;
Memo Item&#13;
Above 31 as % ot all developing&#13;
ecouomies' total debt /b-              (84.8)     (79.7)          n.a.    (92.0)          n.a.    (87.6)          n.a.     (93.9)&#13;
/a  Included in Pakistan in 1970.&#13;
79   riicludea prilvte non-guafanteed debt, of fpnhich a small portion may bef7rom official sources.&#13;
Data for private non-guaranteed debt by economy not available for 1970.&#13;
Source: DRS and World Bank staff estimates.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-31-&#13;
Because disaggregated data for private non-guaranteed debt are&#13;
not available for 1970, comparisons of data for 1970 and 1979 do not give&#13;
much information about the increasing concentration of total debt.&#13;
Figures for public and publicly guaranteed debt, however, show a small&#13;
increase in the shares of the principal borrowers between 1970 and 1979.&#13;
Their share in public debt from private sources has risen (from 87 to&#13;
91 percent), but this rise was partly offset by a declining share in public&#13;
debt from official sources (85 to 80 percent). This fall is more than&#13;
fully explained by the decline in India's share of loans from official&#13;
sources, and it reflects an emphasis (particularly by the multilateral&#13;
institutions) on the poorest and least developed economies.&#13;
Of more significance to the stability of the financial markets&#13;
are the figures in Table 6 showing shares in total debt of the 13 major&#13;
borrowers from 1974 to 1979.(19) They show that private debt has become&#13;
more concentrated on major borrowers. As a result of the increasing&#13;
share of private in total debt, this is true also of total debt despite&#13;
the fall in the share of debt from official sources to this group of&#13;
countries from 57 percent in 1974 to 53 percent in 1979.&#13;
19. These are countries with disbursed and outstanding total medium- and&#13;
long-term debt estimated at more than $10 billion in 1979: Algeria,&#13;
Argentina, Brazil, Egypt, India, Indonesia, Israel, Republic of Korea,&#13;
Mexico, Spain, Turkey, Venezuela, and Yugoslavia.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-32-&#13;
Table 6:&#13;
SHARES OF THIRTEEN MAJOR BORROWERS IN DEBT&#13;
AND DEBT-SERVICE PAYMENTS, 1974, 1977, 1979&#13;
(percent)&#13;
1974    1977    1979&#13;
Shares in Total Debt                      60.8    62.7    62.8&#13;
Shares in Debt from Official Sources   56.6    54.1    53.0&#13;
Shares in Debt from Private Sources    64.2    68.o    68.1&#13;
Shares in Total Debt-Service              63.1    63.5    66.5&#13;
Source: DRS and World Bank staff estimates.&#13;
This marginal increase in the concentration of private debt on&#13;
a small number of borrowing countries (with little change since 1977)&#13;
should not cause significant problems for private creditors. Because of&#13;
the overall growth of the developing countries' share in the assets of&#13;
the commercial banks,(20) however, the major borrowers among developing&#13;
countries comprise an increasing share of the banks' portfolios; default&#13;
by a majo2 borrower could therefore have a greater destabilizing influence&#13;
on the system of financial intermediation in 1980 than would have been&#13;
the case in 1970.&#13;
Experience within the Country Groups&#13;
There are two major types of debt indicators:&#13;
*     Those that increase a country's capacity for making&#13;
payments in foreign exchange (the "liquidity" indicators)&#13;
20. Bank for International Settlements (BIS) data indicate that this share&#13;
may have doubled in the 1970s, but to a figure somewhat under 5 percent of&#13;
commercial bank assets at the end of the decade.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-33-&#13;
*     Those that measure a country's capacity for producing&#13;
real resources with which to service debt (the "solvency"t&#13;
indicators).(21)&#13;
Examples of the former are the debt-service, interest-service, and capital-&#13;
service ratios; the ratio of interest payments to GNP is an example of&#13;
the latter. Movements in debt indicators alone, however, will not&#13;
necessarily point to firm conclusions. In some cases, a "deterioration"&#13;
in debt indicators during the 1970s results from a country's discovering&#13;
(or being discovered by) the market and proving itself creditworthy for&#13;
borrowing from private sources. In these cases, experience in the market&#13;
and the establishment of a good track record could mean better access to&#13;
the market in the future despite higher debt and debt-service ratios.&#13;
Conclusions presented here based on an examination of indicators alone&#13;
must be viewed as suspect unless supported by careful analysis of a&#13;
country's overall economic situation. In particular, no account is taken&#13;
of policy initiatives (for example, export promotion and diversification)&#13;
that already have been undertaken but which have not yet been reflected&#13;
in the indicators.&#13;
Developments in the Debt of Oil-Exporting Countries&#13;
The rise in oil prices in 1979-80 has improved the balance-of-&#13;
payments situation and thereby tended to raise the creditworthiness of the&#13;
oil-exporting developing countries,(22) though not all are necessarily&#13;
better positioned to borrow than they were in 1974-75. Debt-management&#13;
difficulties for the oil exporters (as a group) are much more likely to&#13;
21. For a discussion of the distinction between the liquidity and solvency&#13;
problems in servicing debt, see Robert Z. Aliber, A Conceptual Approach to&#13;
the Analysis of External Debt of the Developing Countries, World Bank Staff&#13;
Working Paper No.421 (October 1980).&#13;
22.  Country coverage    shown in Annex II. Note that Bolivia will not be a&#13;
net oil exporter in 19 .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-34-&#13;
arise from undisciplined borrowing, leading to inefficient investment and&#13;
excessive increases in consumption, than from an inability to service&#13;
the modest increases in debt that would be required to attain growth&#13;
levels that are feasible without strain on absorptive capacity.&#13;
At the group level, the issue is clouded by the changes in status&#13;
of the countries between 1973-74 and 1978-79. Not all countries benefited&#13;
as much from the oil price rises of 1973-74 as from those of 1979-80.&#13;
(The obvious example is Mexico, which despite a rapid buildup of debt&#13;
through the 1970s still appears an attractive prospect to most lenders&#13;
because of its vastly enhanced potential earnings from energy exports&#13;
compared with 1975.) But, with the exception of Egypt and Syria, the&#13;
oil exporters have shared with most other developing countries the dramatic&#13;
change in the distribution of their borrowing by source; in contrast to&#13;
the earlier period, they may have exhausted the benefits from being newly&#13;
creditworthy in an easy market. Bankers may no longer look to the oil&#13;
exporters to add diversity to their portfolios.&#13;
Tables A.la and A.lb of Annex I give for oil-exporting developing&#13;
countries data comparable to those provided in Tables 4a-c for all developing&#13;
countries. The build-up of total debt and debt-service payments for the&#13;
oil-exporting developing countries has been rapid. A notable feature of&#13;
their borrowing experience is the doubling of the aggregate debt-service&#13;
ratio between 1974 and 1979; but all of the increase in debt-service has&#13;
been at the expense of dividend and other capital-service payments. This&#13;
indicates heavy substitution of debt for equity capital in the external&#13;
financing of these countries; only in 1978-79 did capital-service ratios&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-35-&#13;
for the group approach the levels of the early 1970s. Weighted indicators&#13;
(including the capital-service ratios) show sharper deterioration in recent&#13;
years; this mainly reflects the heavy weight of Mexico in the group.&#13;
The longer time series for public debt indicators in Table A.lb&#13;
evidence similar behavior and confirm that 1974 was an atypically good&#13;
year. Rising oil prices in 1979 helped to improve the indicators (most&#13;
notably the debt-to-exports ratio) compared with 1978, and the impact&#13;
should be greater in 1980. But the high debt-service (22 percent) and interest-&#13;
--rvice (7 percent) ratios for total debt (Table A.la) show that the potential&#13;
exists for serious debt-management difficulties for oil-exporting countries.&#13;
Declining oil revenues (a possibility in the near term at least) and a commitment&#13;
to rapid growth could lead them to borrow beyond their servicing capacity&#13;
unless they can attain strong growth of their non-oil exports.&#13;
Conclusions about individual countries are handicapped by the&#13;
comparative lack of detailed information -- most importantly, for Iran and&#13;
Iraq. (23) Almost all of the countries are better placed to borrow early in&#13;
1981 than they were early in 1979; more difficult to judge is their current&#13;
situation compared with 1974. On the basis of debt indicators alone,&#13;
countries that now are in a stronger position to borrow are Egypt (where&#13;
the rapid increase in official lending has helped to improve debt indicators&#13;
substantially since 1973), Malaysia, Nigeria, and Trinidad and Tobago.&#13;
Indonesia probably falls into this group as well. Debt-service ratios&#13;
there have risen compared with the early 1970s, mainly as a result of the&#13;
23. Political factors, which clearly uill affect access to capital,&#13;
are neglected here.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-36-&#13;
rising share of private-source debt, but exports have more than kept pace,&#13;
and Indonesia is one of the few creditworthy countries for which the ratio&#13;
of debt to GNP has declined since the early 1970s.    Based&#13;
on the limited data available, Iran and Iraq also are members of this&#13;
group.&#13;
Algeria, Ecuador, and Peru are the only oil exporters for which&#13;
borrowing prospects may have deteriorated since the early 1970s. In&#13;
Algeria's case this serves only to underline its attractiveness to&#13;
creditors in 1973-74, and the worst of Peru's troubles already may be&#13;
behind it. Bolivia has experienced recent liquidity problems but has&#13;
reduced its ratio of debt to GNP and its overall position seems little&#13;
changed. Mexico has had a deterioration in all indicators except the&#13;
debt-to-exports ratio; of particular note, in 1979 interest payments&#13;
reached an estimated 10 percent of GNP.   Despite this, Mexico's access&#13;
to the market seems unimpaired. Venezuela is similarly placed, and the&#13;
borrowing prospects of the other oil exporters appear unchanged.&#13;
Developments in the Debt of Low-Income Oil-Importing Countries&#13;
The low-income oil-importing countries(24) need large capital&#13;
inflows to achieve high growth rates during the adjustment period of the&#13;
early 1980s. Since few qualify to borrow from private sources on commercial&#13;
terms, their access to foreign resources will depend primarily on the&#13;
availability of official capital. Superficially, this is obscured by the&#13;
changes in debt-service indicators shown in Annex Tables A.2a and A.2b.&#13;
Debt-service ratios for the low-income countries declined significantly&#13;
24. Country coverage is shown in Annex II.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-37-&#13;
and consistently over the decade; the decline in the capital-service ratio&#13;
is even more marked -- it fell by 8 percentage points between 1970 and&#13;
1979. For the low-income countries, 1974 was not the favorable year that&#13;
it was for other developing countries. In particular, the debt-to-exports&#13;
ratio continued to improve over the decade and, although debt increased&#13;
marginally relative to GNP over the whole period, the debt-to-GNP ratio&#13;
declined significantly from peak levels in 1976-78.&#13;
But, as the figures in Table A.2c (as in Table A.2a, but with&#13;
India excluded) show, most of the improvement for the group is attributable&#13;
to India -- the one low-income country in 1981 that seems creditworthy for&#13;
substantially more borrowing on commercial terms. Indian exports of goods&#13;
and services grew at more than twice the trend rate of GNP during the&#13;
1970s; as a result, debt-service ratios were cut in half during the decade.&#13;
The ratio of debt to exports declined similarly, and debt fell by one-sixth&#13;
relative to GNP.&#13;
For all other low-income countries, the debt-service ratio was&#13;
unchanged over the decade. This means borrowing terms improved during the&#13;
1970s because the debt of these countries has risen faster than their&#13;
exports. In fact, debt has increased by one-third relative to exports and by&#13;
one-half relative to GNP over the period. The fact that the weighted&#13;
debt-to-exports ratio has not increased suggests that current borrowers'&#13;
exports have grown faster than the average for the group.&#13;
Although the conclusion may be too sweeping, all low-income&#13;
countries (excluding India and perhaps Pakistan, which has achieved some&#13;
gains that might make it more attractive to commercial lenders) can be&#13;
classified as being no better placed to borrow from the capital markets in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-38-&#13;
1980 than in 1974. Those that were able to borrow private capital in the&#13;
earlier adjustment period no longer have even the novelty factor working&#13;
for them, and over the past year or two many have had problems in making&#13;
debt-service payments, which would not have enhanced lenders' perceptions&#13;
of their creditworthiness.&#13;
Developments in the Debt of Middle-Income Oil Importers&#13;
that Are Major Exporters of Manufactures&#13;
The diversity of the experiences and current situations of this&#13;
group of 11 economies(25) is demonstrated amply by the familiar indicators&#13;
in Annex Tables A.3a and A.3b; similar conclusions can be drawn from&#13;
indicators based on either total or only public debt.    The aggregate&#13;
indicators in Table A.3a, for example, generally show a steady deterioration&#13;
over the 1970s -- a trend that is, however, entirely consistent in this&#13;
case with the group's prudent borrowing to finance adjustment and with&#13;
their expanding economies and international trade. Since 1975, aggregate&#13;
exports have kept pace with aggregage debt, which in turn has not increased&#13;
much faster than aggregate GNP. Debt-service ratios rose in 1978-79,&#13;
mainly due to refinancing and an increase in interest payments. The latter&#13;
reflects the importance of variable-rate debt in the external liabilities&#13;
of these countries. The debt-weighted indicators display similar trends,&#13;
but the much larger increase between 1976 and 1979 in the weighted debt-&#13;
service ratio (9 percentage points compared with 3 for unweighted) shows&#13;
the importance of Brazil, with its high debt-service obligations relative&#13;
to exports and large share (36 percent) of the debt of the groun.&#13;
25. Country coverage is shown in Annex II.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-39-&#13;
All political considerations aside, the four rapidly growing&#13;
Asian economies -- Hong Kong, Korea, Singapore, and Taiwan, China -- are ir a&#13;
much stronger position to borrow now than in the mid-1970s. Although all&#13;
have enjoyed high GNP growth, the exports of each have grown even faster,&#13;
and their debt-servicing capacity has been raised considerably over the&#13;
decade.&#13;
Three countries could encounter difficulties if they attempt to&#13;
expand their borrowing as rapidly as in the past: Brazil, Portugal, and&#13;
Yugoslavia. For each of these, the ability to grow during the adjustment&#13;
period of the early 1980s will be constrained by the need to raise exports&#13;
rapidly so that creditworthiness can be maintained.&#13;
The remaining countries -- Argentina, Israel, Greece,and Spain --&#13;
seem more or less unchanged. The position of the first two seems somewhat&#13;
better in 1980 than in 1974, and that of the second pair seems somewhat&#13;
worse. For a country of its size and economic strength, Spain's debt-&#13;
service indicators were very favorable in 1979, but in 1973 they were&#13;
even more so because the country had borrowed abroad very little. During&#13;
the 1970s, debt grew twice as fast as GNP; debt from private creditors&#13;
(nearly 90 percent of the total in 1979) grew at 40 percent a year during&#13;
the decade.&#13;
Since the debt of these 11 economies comprises nearly 40 percent&#13;
of total disbursed and outstanding debt of the developing countries, their&#13;
borrowing policies and general economic management will be important&#13;
determinants of the overall growth of lending by private creditors to&#13;
developing countries. If, for example, the East Asian members of the group&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-40-&#13;
continue to minimize their reliance on external capital and if Brazil,&#13;
Yugoslavia, and (possibly) Spain are all forced to slow their borrowing,&#13;
the overall flow of funds to developing countries from the capital markets&#13;
would be likely to slow, thus imparting a deflationary impulse to the&#13;
adjustment period of the early 1980s.&#13;
Developments in the Debt of Other Middle-Income Countries&#13;
The total debt of the 40 remaining middle-income oil-importers(26)&#13;
is less than half that of the 11 exporters of manufactures, and the included&#13;
countries differ widely both in income per head and in creditworthiness&#13;
for commercial borrowing.   Notwithstanding this diversity, which virtually&#13;
guarantees the emergence of some major new borrowers in the 1980s, the&#13;
temptation is to conclude that their immediate prospects for borrowing&#13;
are diminished in 1980 compared with 1974 because of the depressed real&#13;
prices for commodity exports. This may be too sweeping a generalization,&#13;
but countries with buoyant borrowing prospects are hard to identify.&#13;
Developments in the debt indicators for the group are shown in&#13;
Annex Tables A.4a and A.4b. The (unweighted) aggregate debt-service ratios&#13;
for both total and public debt are currently higher than they are for the&#13;
middle-income exporters of manufactures. The reverse is true for the&#13;
weighted ratios, and this indicates that debts (and debt-service ratios)&#13;
are distributed more evenly in this group of countries. Not surprisingly,&#13;
the aggregate ratio of debt to exports has increased steadily since 1974,&#13;
and for the weighted aggregate the same is true except for 1976. The&#13;
unweighted debt-service ratio jumped sharply in 1978-79; debt grew&#13;
substantially faster than both exports and GNP, and debt-service payments&#13;
were boosted by prepayments and rising interest rates.&#13;
26. Country coverage is shown in Annex II.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-41-&#13;
Of the seven countries in this group that are listed as major borrowers&#13;
in Table 5 (page 30), only Colombia appears likely to find more favor with&#13;
private lenders in this adjustment period than it did in the last. Debt&#13;
indicators suggest that Morocco, the Philippines, Thailand,. Turkey, Ivory Coast,&#13;
and Chile will all encounter more difficulty this time around. For Chile there&#13;
are offsetting factors that may ease its borrowing problems, and the deterior-&#13;
ation in the Ivory Coast's debt indicators results from better policies&#13;
leading to enhanced creditworthiness in the private financial markets, so the&#13;
overall situation does not seem much altered. Another substantial borrower&#13;
of the mid-1970s, Sudan, should be included with countries that will&#13;
experience much greater difficulty in the markets in the 1980s.&#13;
Most of the other countries are not creditworthy for much capital&#13;
from private sources, though some at the margin of acceptability to the&#13;
markets might benefit (as some countries did in the mid-1970s) from the&#13;
declining popularity of current borrowers.&#13;
This examination of debt indicators for individual countries and&#13;
important sub-groupings generally supports the view that there has been no&#13;
systematic deterioration in the external situation of developing countries&#13;
-- but with some qualifications. The concentration of lending has not&#13;
increased greatly during the 1970s; the process of international financial&#13;
intermediation should be no more at risk at the end of the decade than at&#13;
the beginning. However, individual banks that have increased their&#13;
exposure in particular developing countries much faster than they have&#13;
increased their capital may be more vulnerable to default now than was&#13;
the case in 1970. Among generally creditworthy borrowers, some seem less&#13;
well-placed to finance adjustment to the second oil shock than they were&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-42-&#13;
to the first; others are in the opposite situation. Low-income countries,&#13;
other than India,and the commodity-exporting middle-income countries&#13;
generally do not seem as well-placed to borrow in 1980 as they were&#13;
coming off the commodities' boom in 1973-74.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-43-&#13;
IV. The Outlook for Borrowing in the 1980s&#13;
Although the preceding sections have uncovered scant evidence of&#13;
systematic deterioration in the external debt situation of the developing&#13;
countries, they have shown the need for caution in future borrowing on the&#13;
part of some of them. An important difference for oil-importing countries&#13;
facing the need to adjust in 1980-81 is that there was no commodities'&#13;
export boom in 1979-80 equal to that in 1973-74. And the prospect of&#13;
depressed growth of world trade threatens to constrain the ability and&#13;
willingness of most developing countries to borrow from abroad to sustain&#13;
high growth during t.e adjustment phase. Even if capital markets are as&#13;
liquid in the early 1980s as in the mid-1970s, developing countries must&#13;
decide if their export prospects justify heavy borrowing to defer, and&#13;
thereby ease, adjustment.&#13;
On the surface, the circumstances of the financing needs of&#13;
developing countries in the early 1980s are sufficiently similar to those&#13;
of the mid-1970s that these countries might expect to confront the same&#13;
problems and to reap the same benefits as in the earlier period. Among&#13;
the latter were the declining real price of oil in 1974-78; the rapid&#13;
erosion of the OPEC surplus; the easy conditions in international capital&#13;
markets; and, especially in 1974-76, the positive response of the inter-&#13;
national community to their financing needs. Many observers argue that&#13;
none of these factors is likely to be as favorable to developing countries&#13;
in the 1980s. Add to this the alleged difficulties that commerical banks&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
face in lending to developing countries (capital inadequacy, portfolio&#13;
constraints, and regulation) and their financing prospects appear&#13;
bleak. (27)&#13;
There are countervailing factors to soften this view. First,&#13;
the notion that lending to developing countries as a group poses a threat&#13;
to the viability of the financial intermediaries no longer commands much&#13;
attention (if it ever did) among bankers. Given the profitability of&#13;
lending to developing countries, with few exceptions their exemplary records&#13;
in meeting their obligations, and their continuing need for foreign&#13;
finance, there appears to be no prospect that financial intermediaries&#13;
will discriminate systematically against developing countries in their&#13;
lending policies. The concern for the debt of all developing countries&#13;
that occupied regulators, financial commentators, and some bankers in&#13;
the 1970s is likely to be replaced by a return to greater emphasis on the&#13;
creditworthiness of individual countries, (28) this despite the common&#13;
financing needs of oil-importing countries facing immediate adjustment&#13;
problems.&#13;
27.   See Chapter 3 of World Development Report 1980 for a typical&#13;
discussion.&#13;
28.   The resurgence of borrowing by developing countries in the last&#13;
quarter of 1980 and in the first half of 1981, after the "stand-off" in&#13;
1980 between borrowers seeking fine terms and lenders seeking higher&#13;
spreads, indicates that the markets continue to regard many developing&#13;
countries as creditworthy. High real interest rates provide a contrast&#13;
with the earlier adjustment period and should temper the desire to borrow.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-- 45-&#13;
There is evidence that commercial lenders have tended to treat&#13;
individual developing countries on their respective merits, with the&#13;
possible exception of 1977-78, when bank regulators (especially in the&#13;
United States) expressed vocal concern over (U.S.) bank exposure in developing&#13;
countries collectively. In the past five years, the banks generally have&#13;
been responsive to the needs of developing countries experiencing debt-&#13;
management difficulties; in some cases, countries have preferred to&#13;
negotiate flexible (and less political) refinancing arrangements with the&#13;
commercial lenders rather than to reschedule debt from official sources. An&#13;
example is the success of Nicaragua in quickly negotiating a satisfactory&#13;
rescheduling with commercial lenders, compared with its prolonged negotiations&#13;
to reach agreement with its official creditors.    In fact, bankers have&#13;
negotiated a series of well-publicized debt reschedulings -- among them for&#13;
Peru, Zaire, Turkey, Jamaica, Bolivia, and Liberia -- often in an unstable&#13;
political environment, with little fuss, minimal losses, and no discernible&#13;
impact on the stability of the financial intermediaries or their ability to&#13;
recycle oil surpluses.&#13;
Second, the constraints on commercial banks imposed by capital&#13;
adequacy and portfolio considerations, to the extent that they do exist,&#13;
are essentially short-term. Although some banks may be so highly leveraged&#13;
that prudence dictates slower growth in their international lending, others&#13;
that are not "lent up" will profit by boosting their loan activity in&#13;
international markets. Profitable lending opportunities eventually will&#13;
attract new capital, and possible new institutions, into foreign lending.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-46-&#13;
Similarly, when a bank (or even a group of banks) is holding all the assets&#13;
it deems prudent in a particular (creditworthy) country, other lenders will&#13;
take up the slack as long as profitable opportunities for lending remain.&#13;
Viewed over the decade, therefore,neither capital availability nor&#13;
portfolio considerations are likely to reduce lending to developing&#13;
countries significantly.&#13;
There is, however, an important qualification. If existing&#13;
institutions do face short-term constraints in responding to the developing&#13;
countries' financial needs, countries may opt for slower growth (as a&#13;
result of immediate borrowing problems) than their creditworthiness and&#13;
longer-term access to capital would permit.     Once such a decision&#13;
has been made it could be difficult to reverse. Countries that want to&#13;
finance high growth while adjusting must convince lenders of their sound&#13;
debt-management policies and continued creditworthiness and diversify&#13;
their borrowing (at least in the short term) as much as possible. A&#13;
similar situation could arise without a portfolio constraint if there&#13;
is a general, but erroneous, perception in the capital markets that a&#13;
country's creditworthiness has declined. (Brazil's experience during&#13;
1980 might be an example.)&#13;
Determinants of Borrowing in the 1980s&#13;
Within the general description of sound economic (and external&#13;
debt) management, two specific factors, in the near term, appear most&#13;
likely to affect a country's creditworthiness for commercial borrowing:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47-&#13;
*      Its actual and prospective export performance measured&#13;
against its import requirements&#13;
s      The distribution (by creditors)of its existing and&#13;
prospective external liabilities.&#13;
Commercial banks as a group are unlikely to seek a rapid expansion of their&#13;
lending to countries with poor export prospects. In addition, they may be&#13;
wary of countries (and already are of some) that have borrowed heavily from&#13;
them and, therefore, are burdened with a disproportionate volume of&#13;
private debt on market terms or of countries that are not receiving support&#13;
from official creditors. (29)&#13;
Although some developing countries now appear close to prudent&#13;
limits to their debt-servicing capabilities, there are others that, due to&#13;
rising and diversified exports and moderate borrowing in the 1970s, are&#13;
well positioned to enter the capital market in the 1980s. Unfortunately,&#13;
the unused debt-servicing capacity of developing countries that have not&#13;
resorted to foreign borrowing in the 1970s is not available to support&#13;
further borrowing by those that did so. (30) (In some instances, of course,&#13;
29.   Again, the discussion rules out consideration of political risk.&#13;
30.   But indirectly it could be made available.   One potential avenue for&#13;
financing that could develop rapidly in the 1980s is financial intermediation&#13;
-- between money-center banks and ultimate borrowers -- by the banks of&#13;
developing countries. For example, if portfolio considerations limit the&#13;
rate at which the banks of OECD countries can lend to Brazil, banks in&#13;
Singapore can ease this constraint by lending to Brazil and funding them-&#13;
selves by borrowing (with or without government guarantee) from banks in&#13;
the traditional money centers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48-&#13;
countries have low debt-servicing ratios because they are not creditworthy&#13;
for commercial borrowing,not because they have eschewed it.)&#13;
The Importance of Export Growth&#13;
The strong export performance of developing countries in 1973-74&#13;
meant that the aggregate debt-service ratio and other aggregate indicators&#13;
of the debt-servicing capacity of developing countries (Tables 4) generally&#13;
were at their most favorable levels for the decade in 1974. Countries that&#13;
were experienced borrowers and many that were new entrants to the finnancial&#13;
markets were poised to take advantage of the liquid markets that developed&#13;
in subsequent years. Despite some improvements in the debt indicators in&#13;
1979 (compared with 1978) and allowing for the circumstances in 1978 and&#13;
1979 (prepayments and refinancing, and high, variable interest rates) that&#13;
have raised (probably only temporarily) debt-service ratios, developing&#13;
countries as a group are not in quite as strong a position from which to&#13;
finance their adjustment in the early 1980s. Moreover, as the earlier&#13;
discussion of weighted indicators has underlined, countries that have&#13;
borrowed heavily in the past must be careful in further borrowing.&#13;
If these countries -- especially the middle-income oil importers --&#13;
are to achieve high growth while adjusting, they will require continuing&#13;
access to large amounts of capital from the commercial banks; hence, their&#13;
immediate need is to raise debt-servicing capacity -- that is, exports --&#13;
rapidly. Borrowing in advance of export growth (as in 1974-78) could create&#13;
severe debt-management problems for many countries by the mid-1980s.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-49-&#13;
But, as in 1974-75, developing countries can expect comparatively&#13;
slow export growth in the early 1980s due to recession in the OECD.     Moreover,&#13;
many observers project that the recovery, when it comes, will be at least&#13;
as sluggish as the feeble and faltering upturn that began in 1976 and&#13;
lingered until the oil price increases in the middle of 1979. If growth of&#13;
world markets is slow, developing countries will need to adopt aggressive,&#13;
outward-looking policies if exports are to expand rapidly enough to maintain&#13;
their debt-servicing capacity. And they will need to create new markets&#13;
by trading much more with each other. There will be a corresponding&#13;
obligation on the industrial and oil-surplus economies to avoid&#13;
protectionism and to extend generous access to their markets to&#13;
developing countries.&#13;
Official Sources of Capital&#13;
The slowdown in growth of the medium- and long-term debt of&#13;
developing countries thatwas evident in 1979 appears to have persisted in&#13;
1980, when much of the financing needs of developing countries seems to&#13;
have been provided by use of reserves and a rapid build-up of short-term&#13;
(less than 12-month maturity) debt. Such a financing strategy is&#13;
short-run.   In 1981, many countries will need to consolidate short-term&#13;
debt into longer maturities, some may need to reconstitute reserves, and&#13;
most may hesitate to deplete their reserves much further. This means that&#13;
a substantial amount of gross borrowing in 1981 may be to restructure assets&#13;
and liabilities rather than to add to net resource availability.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50-&#13;
The tables of Section II showed that net transfers from official&#13;
creditors, after more than doubling from 1973 to 1975 ($4.7 to $9.9 billion&#13;
-- see Table 2a)(31), have not increased since, and that the declining&#13;
share of official debt in total debt of developing countries has been the&#13;
principal reason for the hardening of terms of the developing countries'&#13;
disbursed and outstanding debt. Immediate prospects do not presage a&#13;
reversal of this trend (IMF lending may be an exception -- see&#13;
below), and both the need to consolidate short-term debt and the emphasis&#13;
placed on the role of private capital by the new U.S. administration suggest&#13;
that it may accelerate. The results would be an increased debt-service&#13;
burden for developing countries as private debt levels rise, and a&#13;
continuing decline in the net transfer that foreign borrowing affords&#13;
them. The situation could be eased by a significant increase of official&#13;
lending (both on concessional and non-concessional terms, providing&#13;
the credits have long maturities).&#13;
Unfortunately, this does not seem likely. (32) The comparative&#13;
scarcity of official financing means that developing countries will be all the&#13;
more dependent on private sources of funds. Moreover, the fact that&#13;
official capital is growing slowly compared with the financing needs of&#13;
31.   Figures exclude use of IMF resources, except for disbursements&#13;
by the Trust Fund.&#13;
32.   An exception could be official capital from oil-surplus countries,&#13;
but their lending would have to expand enormously to have a major impact&#13;
on the overall debt situation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-51-&#13;
developing countries may inhibit flows of private capital to some countries.&#13;
Private lenders are likely to feel more exposed when official lenders&#13;
are hesitant in their support of developing economies. In particular,&#13;
faced with (for example) a U.S. administration that proposes to restrict&#13;
aid and other official assistance to a reduced range of countries and&#13;
purposes, banks may think twice before committing themselves to&#13;
countries that are out of official favor.&#13;
In the past, official and private capital have tended to be&#13;
complements rather than substitutes. While private capital is largely&#13;
untied, of comparatively short maturity, and (increasingly) at floating&#13;
interest rates, official capital is more often tied (by country of&#13;
expenditure and by project), of longer maturity, and mainly at fixed&#13;
(often concessional) interest rates. Besides this, the involvement of&#13;
official capital in infrastructure and other long-lived projects, where&#13;
social returns are high but difficult to appropriate, has had the effect&#13;
both of leaving more "bankable" projects (i.e., those that provide faster&#13;
and more easily assimilable returns) for private investors and of raising&#13;
the returns on these projects. As private foreign capital increasingly&#13;
substitutes for official capital in infrastructure and social services,&#13;
problems associated with debt management could become more severe.&#13;
One source of official capital that offers considerable financing&#13;
potential during the adjustment period is the IMF. Recently the Fund's&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-52-&#13;
Board of Executive Directors has expanded the access to the resources provided&#13;
under the various IMF facilities. With the expanded quotas approved under the&#13;
Seventh General Review in place, and with members in severe payments&#13;
difficulty being able to receive up to 150 percent of quota annually or&#13;
450 percent of quota over a three-year period, up to a cumulative limit of&#13;
600 percent of quota, the Fund has the potential to make a significant&#13;
contribution to financing needs during the adjustment period. This depends on&#13;
the Fund itself obtaining access to adequate financing beyong the resources&#13;
provided by members' quotas.&#13;
In addition to its own contribution to financing adjustment with&#13;
growth, the involvement of the Fund is likely to enhance developing&#13;
countries' access to the capital markets. Bankers' confidence is likely&#13;
to be raised by the knowledge that the IMF has approved an adjustment program;&#13;
they also may derive comfort from an increased involvement by other lenders.&#13;
Fund involvement, however, will not meet all the objections raised by the&#13;
declining importance of other official lenders. The Fund offers balance-&#13;
of-payments finance that can provide valuable assistance during the&#13;
adjustment period, but the comparatively short maturities make it&#13;
inappropriate funding for long-lived development projects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-53-&#13;
V. Summary and Conclusions&#13;
The 1970s witnessed a very rapid build-up of the external debt of&#13;
developing countries, accompanied by a pronounced shift away from official&#13;
(especially bilateral) and towards private capital, mainly from the commercial&#13;
banks. As a result, developing countries were aided in maintaining&#13;
(comparatively) high growth during the adjustment phase in the middle of&#13;
the decade. A concomitant of the shift in the source of foreign borrowing&#13;
has been a hardening of the average terms for foreign debt (but the&#13;
terms for private debt financing did not harden appreciably through 1979).&#13;
At the same time, debt has been a substitute for other forms of capital, so&#13;
that increased debt-service payments have been offset partially by a&#13;
(proportional) fall in other capital-service payments.&#13;
There is no evidence of a systematic deterioration in the external&#13;
position of developing countries during the decade, especially when&#13;
allowance is made for the changes in external indicators that necessarily&#13;
accompany expanded access to the international capital markets. Nor has&#13;
the concentration of debt changed markedly. Some diversification of&#13;
official credit to poorer (less creditworthy) countries is indicated, but&#13;
its significanceis hard to assess given the political factors that have&#13;
influenced the rapid reduction in India's share of official debt.&#13;
Some countries have encountered debt-management difficulties;&#13;
others are poised to do so. These countries will have to exercise caution&#13;
in future foreign borrowings. Other countries are in a strong position to&#13;
borrow -- if they decide to do so. The tentative conclusion is that&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54-&#13;
developing countries jointly are more constrained in their ability to&#13;
finance adjustment through external borrowing in the early 1980s than they&#13;
were in the mid-1970s. The main reason for this conclusion is the absence in&#13;
1979-80 of an export boom comparable to that in 1973-74; developing&#13;
countries thus do not appear to have the same under-utilized debt-servicing&#13;
capability this time around.&#13;
The borrowing problems of developing countries would be eased by&#13;
the adoption of accommodating policies in the OECD and capital-surplus&#13;
oil-exporting nations. The creditworthiness of developing countries would&#13;
be enhanced by a rapid growth in exports and by an expansion of official&#13;
funding on appropriate terms. Neither of these outcomes appears likely in&#13;
an environment of global recession. As a result, private capital inflow&#13;
is unlikely to boost the growth of developing countries in the early 1980s&#13;
to the extent that it did during the earlier adjustment period.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX I&#13;
Debt and Debt Service Indicators for Major Groups of Developing Countries&#13;
Taole A.la:       Oil-Exporting Countries:&#13;
Aggregates 1970-79 and Debt-Weighted Aggregates 1974-79, Total Debt&#13;
Table A.lb:       Oil-Exporting Countries:&#13;
Aggregates and Debt-Weighted Aggregates 1970-79, Public Debt Only&#13;
Table A.2a:       Low-Income Oil-Importing Countries:&#13;
Aggregates 1970-79 and Debt-Weighted Aggregates 1974-79, Total Debt&#13;
Table A.Zb:       Low-Income Oil-Importing Countries:&#13;
Aggregates and Debt-Weighted Aggregates 1970-79, Public Debt Only&#13;
Tible A.2c:       Low-Income Oil-Importing Countries   Excluding India:&#13;
U,&#13;
Aggregates 1970-79 and Debt-Weighted Aggregates 1974-79, Total Debt&#13;
Tabie A.ja:       Middle-Income Oil Importers that Are Major Exporters of Manufactures:&#13;
Aggregates 1970-79 and Debt-Weighted Aggregates 1974-79, Total Debt&#13;
Table A.3b:       Middle-Income Oil Importers that Are Major Exporters of Manufactures;&#13;
Aggregates and Debt-Weighted Aggregates 1970-79, Public Debt Only&#13;
Table A.4a:       Middle-Income Oil Importers Excluding Major Exporters:&#13;
Aggregates 1970-79 and Debt-Weighted Aggregates 1974-79, Total Debt&#13;
Table A.4t:       Middle-Income Oil Importers Excluding Major Exporters:&#13;
Aggregates and Debt-Weighted Aggregates 1970-79, Public Debt Only&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A.la:&#13;
EVOLUTION OF DEBT AND DEBT-SERVICE INDICATORS:&#13;
OIL-EXPORTING COUNTRIES ,/a&#13;
AGGREGATES 1970-79 AND DEBT-WEIGHTED AGGREGATES,1974-79,/b&#13;
TOTAL DEBT&#13;
(percent)&#13;
1970     1971      1972     1973     1974     1975      1976     1977     1978      1979&#13;
I.  INDICATORS&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio          15.5     15.3     16.3      15.6     10.4     12.3      13.7     16.5     21.3     21.9&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio       4.5      4.6      4.8       4.2      3.2      4.3      4.9       5.5      6.8      7.3&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio       28.6     28.5     28.4      28.5     19.6     20.2     20.4      23.6     28.1     26.9&#13;
DOD/GNP                     17.1     15.3     15.8      16.3     17.8     19.7      23.7     26.8     29.3     27.7&#13;
DOD/Exports                101.4    111.3    112.2     101.1     63.5     86.3     95.4     106.1    124.0    100.0&#13;
DOD/Reserves               379.1    327.8    293.7     248.7    141.2    185.3    226.1     266.9    346.7    247.3&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP         0.8      0.8      0.8       0.8      0.9      1.0       1.2      1.4      1.6      2.0&#13;
II. WEIGHTED INDICATORS /b&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio          -        -        -         -        19.7     23.7      26.4     31.3     33.8     34.9&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio      -        -        -        -          6.6      9.1     10.2      10.8     10.6     11.1&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio       -        -        -        -         29.5     33.2     33.8      38.0     40.2     39.6&#13;
DOD/GNP                     -        -        -         -        22.4     25.7     30.8      35.5     38.7     36.1&#13;
DOD/Exports                 -        -        -         -       119.7    164.0    179.1     190.1    181.1    145.1&#13;
DOD/Reserves                -        -        -         -       399.7    796.1    904.3     968.1    877.8    617.0&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP        -        -        -        -          1.0      1.2      1.5       1.8      2.1      2.5&#13;
Memo Item&#13;
Total DOD (US$ billions)&#13;
of included countries     15.5     18.9     22.1     29.4      36.4     47.6     60.9      78.5     99.0    114.2&#13;
/a     See Annex II for country coverage.&#13;
/b     Weights are the shares of individual countries in total debt of the group.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A.lb:&#13;
EVOLUTION OF DEBT AND DEBT-SERVICE INDICATORS:&#13;
OIL-EXPORTING COUNTRIES, /a&#13;
AGGREGATES AND DEBT-WEIGHTED AGGREGATES 1970-79, /b&#13;
PUBLIC DEBT ONLY&#13;
(percent)&#13;
1970     1971      1972     1973     1974     1975      1976     1977     1978      1979&#13;
I. INDICATORS&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio          10.7     10.7     11.7      11.8      7.6      9.1      10.3     13.2     17.9      19.1&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio       3.0      2.9      3.2       3.0      2.4      3.4      3.9       4.6      5.9      6.4&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio       23.7     23.8     23.8      24.7     16.8     17.0      17.0     20.3     24.7     24.2&#13;
DOD/GNP                     13.8     15.3      15.8     16.4     14.7     16.6      20.4     23.7     26.4     25.1&#13;
DOD/Exports                 81.6     88.8     90.7      81.7     52.5     72.6      82.1     93.7    111.7      90.7&#13;
DOD/Reserves               305.0    261.5    237.4     201.0    116.9    155.9     194.7    235.7    312.2    224.3&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP         0.5      0.5      0.6       0.6      0.7      0.8       1.0      1.2      1.4       1.8&#13;
II. WEIGHTED INDICATORS   4b&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio          14.4     14.0      14.5     15.7     12.3     15.5      17.8     23.6     27.6      19.8&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio       3.7      3.4      3.7       3.8      4.1      6.4       7.5      8.4      8.8      9.5&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio       24.7     23.8     25.2      27.0     21.9     24.8      25.1     30.3     34.0     34.3&#13;
DOD/GNP                     19.0     22.3     22.9      22.5     20.0     23.5      27.3     32.3     35.9     33.8&#13;
DOD/Exports                126.5    143.0    173.6     115.3     89.3    130.1     145.0    161.1    160.8     130.3&#13;
DOD/Reserves               706.9    761.5    467.7     372.4    312.8    677.1     742.8    871.8    788.1    549.9&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP         0.5      0.5      0.6       0.6      0.8      0.9       1.2      1.5      1.8       2.2&#13;
Memo Item&#13;
Total Public DOD (US$ billions)&#13;
of included countries     12.5     15.1     17.9      23.8     30.2     40.1     52.5      69.3     89.1    103.6&#13;
/a See Annex II for country coverage.&#13;
/b Weights are the shares of individual countries in public debt of the group.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A.2a:&#13;
EVOLUTION OF DEBT AND DEBT-SERVICE INDICATORS:&#13;
LOW-INCOME OIL-IMPORTING COUNTRIES, /a&#13;
AGGREGATES 1970-79 AND DEBT-WEIGHTED AGGREGATES 1974-79, /b&#13;
TOTAL DEBT&#13;
(percent)&#13;
1970     1971      1972     1973     1974     1975     1976      1977     1978     1979&#13;
I.  INDICATORS&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio          14.3     14.4     15.1     13.3      12.5     12.5     10.8      9.5       9.1      9.2&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio       5.1      5.4      5.5      4.9       4.3      4.2      3.9      3.5       3.6      3.8&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio       17.4     17.6     16.3     14.3      13.6     14.0     12.1     10.7      10.0      9.5&#13;
DOD/GNP                     16.3     17.5     18.6     18.2      17.4     18.9     20.6     20.3      19.4     18.8&#13;
DOD/Exports                200.8    225.5    220.5    196.9     188.1    188.1    184.4    171.1     158.6    150.8&#13;
DOD/Reserves               648.2    672.9    562.4    505.7     494.2    639.8    471.0    358.0     329.6    248.6&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP         0.4      0.4      0.5      0.5       0.4      0.4      0.4      0.4      0.4       0.5&#13;
II. WEIGHTED INDICATORS   lb                                                                                              a&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio          -        -        -        -         14.0     13.2     11.2      9.9      9.4       9.6&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio      -        -        -        -          4.8      4.5      4.3      3.9     3.9        4.0&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio       -        -        -        -         14.5     13.9     11.9     10.6     10.1      10.1&#13;
DOD/GNP                     -        -        -        -         25.7     28.2     29.1     30.2     28.3      27.8&#13;
DOD/Exports                 -        -        -        -        231.2    220.1    214.0    202.9    184.6     171.9&#13;
DOD/Reserves                -        -        -        -        648.9    914.7    792.1    677.4   709.9      585.6&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP        -        -        -        -          0.6      0.7      0.6      0.6     0.6        0.7&#13;
Memo Item&#13;
Total DOD (US$ billions)&#13;
of included countries     13.7     15.6     17.3     19.8      23.2     26.0     29.6     33.8    38.2       40.5&#13;
/a  See Annex II for country coverage.&#13;
/b Weights are the shares of individual countries in total    debt of the group.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A.2b:&#13;
EVOLUTION OF DEBT AND DEBT-SERVICE INDICATORS:&#13;
LOW-INCOME OIL-IMPORTING COUNTRIES, /a&#13;
AGGREGATES AND DEBT-WEIGHTED AGGREGATES 1970-79, lb&#13;
PUBLIC DEBT ONLY&#13;
(percent)&#13;
1970     1971      1972     1973     1974     1975      1976     1977     1978     1979&#13;
I. INDICATORS&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio          13.5     13.5      13.9     12.2     11.5     11.5      9.8       8.8      8.4      8.5&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio       4.9      5.1      5.2       4.6      4.1      4.0      3.7       3.4      3.5      3.6&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio       16.6     16.7     15.1      13.2     12.7     12.9      11.1     10.0      9.4      9.1&#13;
DOD/GNP                     16.1     17.3      18.3     17.7     16.9     18.4     20.1      19.8     18.9     18.4&#13;
DOD/Exports                198.0    222.3    216.6     191.9    183.1    183.2     180.0    167.3    154.9    147.2&#13;
DOD/Reserves               639.4    663.1    552.6     492.7    481.0    623.0    459.6     350.1    321.9    242.8&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP         0.4      0.4      0.4       0.4      0.4      0.4      0.4       0.4      0.4      0.4&#13;
II. WEIGHTED INDICATORS lb&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio          22.2     20.2      18.3     15.1     13.1     12.6      10.6      9.6      9.0      9.0&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio       8.6      7.9      7.2       5.9      4.7      4.3      4.2       3.8      3.8      3.8&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio       25.6     23.5      18.8     15.5     13.6     13.1     11.2      10.2      9.5      9.4&#13;
DOD/GNP                     20.0     21.4      22.9     27.8     24.9     26.8     28.0      29.0     27.5     26.8&#13;
DOD/Exports                358.9    379.8    312.5     258.2    230.8    218.8    213.2     200.8    182.1    168.8&#13;
DOD/Reserves              1343.5   1132.8    834.6     672.1    636.9    884.3    752.3     655.5    683.6    568.8&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP         0.5      0.4      0.5       0.6      0.5      0.6      0.6       0.6      0.6      0.6&#13;
Memo Item&#13;
Total public DOD (US$ billions)&#13;
of included countries     13.5     15.4     17.0      19.3     22.6     25.3     28.8      33.0    37.3      39.6&#13;
/a See Annex II for country coverage.&#13;
/b Weights are the shares of individual countries in public debt of the group.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A.2c:&#13;
EVOLUTION OF DEBT AND DEBT-SERVICE INDICATORS:&#13;
LOW-INCOME OIL-IMPORTING COUNTRIES EXCLUDING INDIA, /a&#13;
AGGREGATES 1970-79 AND DEBT-WEIGHTED AGGREGATES 1974-79, /b&#13;
TOTAL DEBT&#13;
(percent)&#13;
1970     1971     1972      1973     1974     1975     1976      1977     1978     1979&#13;
I. INDICATORS&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio          10.7     10.1     11.5      10.4      9.7     12.2     10.7      9.3      9.9      10.3&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio       3.6      3.4      3.8      3.7       3.4      4.2      4.1      3.7      4.3       4.4&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio       15.5     15.0     13.3      11.9     11.5     14.7     13.2     11.5     11.8      11.5&#13;
DOD/GNP                     18.9     21.7     24.4     27.8      25.0     26.1     30.0     30.4     28.4      28.1&#13;
DOD/Exports                129.3    150.7    151.3    141.1     148.2    176.6    185.7    174.6    185.9     172.4&#13;
DOD/Reserves               520.2    624.8    440.5    404.7     489.8    683.2    635.3    572.0    695.0     553.1&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP         0.5      0.4      0.5      0.6       0.6      0.6      0.7      0.6      0.7       0.7&#13;
II. WEIGHTED INDICATORS /b&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio          -        -        -        -         10.5     13.3     10.7     10.1     10.6      10.6&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio      -        -        -        -          3.8      4.7      4.5      4.3      4.9       4.6&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio       -        -        -        -         11.5     14.5     12.0     11.3     11.7      11.3&#13;
DOD/GNP                     -        -        -        -         37.7     40.2     38.1     42.1     38.4      37.3&#13;
DOD/Exports                 -        -        -        -        203.5    233.4    224.2    228.7    220.7     199.2&#13;
DOD/Reserves                -        -        -        -        792.6   1189.1   1071.9   1003.8   10 3.8     865.7&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP        -        -        -        -          0.8      1.0      0.9      0.8      0.8       0.9&#13;
Memo Item&#13;
Total DOD (US$ billions)&#13;
of included countries      5.8      6.7      7.5      9.2      11.6     13.7     16.2     19.1    22.7       24.7&#13;
/a See Annex II for country coverage.&#13;
Lb Weights are the shares of individual countries in total debt of the group&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A.3a:&#13;
EVOLUTION OF DEBT AND DEBT-SERVICE INDICATORS:&#13;
LOW-INCOME OIL IMPORTERS THAT ARE MAJOR EXPORTERS OF MANUFACTURES, /a&#13;
AGGREGATES 1970-79 AND DEBT-WEIGHTED AGGREGATES 1974-79, /b&#13;
TOTAL DEBT&#13;
(percent)&#13;
1970     1971      1972     1973     1974     1975     1976      1977     1978     1979&#13;
I. INDICATORS&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio          10.8     11.6     12.5      12.8     12.4     14.9     13.4     14.2     16.9      16.7&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio       3.3      3.7      4.1       4.1      4.3      5.5      4.6      4.6      5.5       6.5&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio       12.9     13.4     13.8      14.2     13.5     16.0     14.6     15.8     18.5      17.9&#13;
DOD/GNP                     11.6     12.8     14.9      14.0     14.1     16.0     17.0      18.6    20.0      18.6&#13;
DOD/Exports                 69.1     74.9     78.8      67.8     69.4     82.3     84.2     84.9     89.5      82.4&#13;
DOD/Reserves               225.4    204.3    161.8     135.0    168.2    247.6    250.9    251.2    223.7     190.5&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP         0.4      0.4      0.4      0.5       0.9      1.1      0.9      1.0      1.2       1.5&#13;
II. WEIGHTED INDICATORS /b&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio          -        -        -         -        22.4     26.2     23.1     24.1     31.6      32.4&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio      -        -        -        -          8.4     10.7      8.3      8.1     11.1      13.2&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio       -        -        -        -         25.0     28.6     25.9     28.2     36.0      35.8&#13;
DOD/GNP                     -        -        -         -        19.6     21.4     22.3     23.2     25.5      23.7&#13;
DOD/Exports                 -        -        -        -        127.9    145.6    150.6    148.7    176.1     137.6&#13;
DOD/Reserves                -        -        -        -        413.7    469.9    349.3    348.6    308.1     362.9&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP        -        -        -        -          1.1      1.3      1.1      1.1      1.4       1.8&#13;
Memo Item&#13;
Total DOD (US$ billions)&#13;
of included countries     18.8     23.7     32.0     40.1      52.2     63.4     78.5     95.6    123.0     142.5&#13;
/a See Annex II for country coverage.&#13;
/b Weights are the shares of individual countries in total debt of the group.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A.3b:&#13;
EVOLUTION OF DEBT AND DEBT-SERVICE INDICATORS:&#13;
MIDDLE-INCOME OIL IMPORTERS THAT ARE MAJOR EXPORTERS OF MANUFACTURES, /a&#13;
AGGREGATES AND DEBT-WEIGHTED AGGREGATES i970-79, /b&#13;
PUBLIC DEBT ONLY&#13;
(percent)&#13;
1970     1971      1972     1973      1974     1975      1976     1977     1978      1979&#13;
I.  INDICATORS&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio           6.9       7.4      6.9       6.7      6.0       7.2      6.7      7.2      9.8       9.0&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio       2.1       2.2      2.2       2.3      2.3      3.0       2.8      2.8      3.4       3.9&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio        9.0       9.2      8.2       8.1      7.1      8.3       7.8      8.8     11.4      10.3&#13;
DOD/GNP                      8.4       9.0      9.6       8.9      8.8      10.0     10.8     11.9     13.0      12.1&#13;
DOD/Exports                 50.5      52.4     50.6      43.1     43.5      51.4     53.4     54.3     57.8      53.7&#13;
DOD/Reserves               164.7     143.0    104.0      85.8    105.4     154.7    158.9    160.7    144.7     124.2&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP         0.4      0.4       0.4      0.5       0.5      0.6       0.6      0.6     0.8        0.9&#13;
II. WEIGHTED INDICATORS /L&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio          10.7      12.7     13.0      12.1     11.0      13.3     12.2     12.7     18.0      19.1&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio       3.2       3.9      4.2       4.4      4.3      5.6       5.1      5.0      6.9       8.4&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio       14.8      16.6     15.7      15.0     13.6     15.6      15.1     16.7     22.5      22.7&#13;
DOD/GNP                     14.8      16.9     18.1      17.7     15.8      17.8     18.4     18.8     20.8      19.4&#13;
DOD/Exports                 91.5     100.1    100.8      86.2     85.8      99.4    102.1     99.5    120.9     114.1&#13;
DOD/Reseryes               330.5     363.7    241.0     173.9    374.9    347.6     257.4    247.5    230.2     265.5&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP         0.4       0.6      0.7       0.9      0.7      0.9       0.8      0.8      1.0       1.2&#13;
Memo Item&#13;
Total Public DOD (US$ billions)&#13;
of included countries     13.7      16.6     20.6     25.5      32.7     39.5      49.7     61.1     79.5      92.9&#13;
/a See Annex II for country coverage.&#13;
/b Weights are the shares of individual countries in public debt of the group.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A.4a:&#13;
EVOLUTION OF DEBT AND DEBT-SERVICE INDICATORS:&#13;
MIDDLE-INCOME OIL IMPORTERS EXCLUDING MAJOR EXPORTERS OF MANUFACTURES, /a&#13;
AGGREGATES 1970-79 AND DEBT-WEIGHTED AGGREGATES 1974-79, /b&#13;
TOTAL DEBT&#13;
.(percent)&#13;
1970     1971     1972     1973     1974     1975     1976     1977      1978     1979&#13;
I.  INDICATORS&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio          11.0    12.5      12.3     12.3     10.8     12.5     12.8     13.8    18.6      17.1&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio      3.4      4.1      3.7      3.6       3.3      4.2      4.4      4.5     5.4       6.3&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio      16.5     17.2      16.5     16.0     13.6     15.6     15.8     16.4    21.0      18.4&#13;
DOD/GNP                    19.2      19.7     19.6     19.3     18.9     19.8     20.6     21.0    23.3      25.8&#13;
DOD/Exports                97.8    108.9     104.0    89.3      77.8     90.2     91.7     97.3   109.0     110.2&#13;
DOD/Reserves              292.5    303.3     230.6    211.8    207.2    265.8    258.7    267.8   258.3     230.8&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP        0.6      0.6      0.6      0.7       0.8      0.9      1.0      1.0     1.1       1.5&#13;
II. WEIGHTED INDICATORS /b&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio         -        -        -        -         13.4     17.4     16.7     17.5    22.2      20.5&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio     -        -        -        -         4.1       5.7      5.6      5.6     6.5       7.5&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio      -        -        -        -         15.9     20.2     19.8     20.3    24.6      21.6&#13;
DOD/GNP                    -        -        -        -         25.6     29.8     29.4     29.7    33.3      33.6&#13;
DOD/Exports                -        -        -        -        103.4    122.5    116.0    124.0   140.5     145.0&#13;
DOD/Reserves               -        -        -        -        636.4    843.7   1106.4    992.8   860.5     716.0&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP       -        -        -        -          1.1      1.5      1.5      1.4     1.7       2.0&#13;
Memo Item&#13;
Total DOD (US$ billions)&#13;
of included countries    13.4     15.1     17.2     20.4     24.9      28.9     34.3     42.3    53.6      68.3&#13;
/a See Annex II for country coverage.&#13;
/S Weights are the shares of individual countries in total debt of the group.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A.4b:&#13;
EVOLUTION OF DEBT AND DEBT-SERVICE INDICATORS:&#13;
MIDDLE-INCOME OIL IMPORTERS EXCLUDING MAJOR EXPORTERS OF iIANUFACTURES, /a&#13;
AGGREGATES AND DEBT-WEIGHTED AGGREGATES 1970-79, /b&#13;
PUBLIC DEBT ONLY&#13;
(percent)&#13;
1970     1971      1972     1973      1974     1975      1976     1977      1978     1979&#13;
I. INDICATORS&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio           8.4       9.5      8.7       9.0      7.0       8.5      8.7      9.4     12.9      12.5&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio       2.7       3.2      2.7       2.6      2.4      3.1       3.3      3.5      4.2       4.9&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio       13.9      14.2     13.0      12.7      9.8      11.5     11.7     12.0     15.3      13.8&#13;
DOD/GNP                     14.6      15.9     16.0      15.5     15.1      16.0     16.8     17.6     19.9      22.1&#13;
DOD/Exports                 78.2      87.3     83.9      71.2     62.9      73.2     75.0     81.3     93.1      94.1&#13;
DOD/Reserves               233.7     243.3    186.2     169.1    167.4    215.7     211.7    223.9    220.6     197.2&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP         0.5       0.6      0.5       0.6      0.6      0.7       0.7      0.8      0.9       1.1&#13;
II. WEIGHTED INDICATORS /b&#13;
Debt-Service Ratio          11.5      12.2     10.1      10.1      9.3     12.8      12.1     12.3     16.0      15.4&#13;
Interest-Service Ratio       3.6       4.1      3.1       3.0      3.0      4.5       4.3      4.5      5.2       6.0&#13;
Capital-Service Ratio       16.9      16.5     13.7      13.3     11.8     15.5      15.1     15.0     18.5      16.5&#13;
DOD/GNP                     18.3      18.7     18.6      19.2     21.2     25.2      25.2     26.8     30.1      30.6&#13;
DOD/Exports                110.7     121.7    124.1      98.5     92.6    108.0      99.1    109.2    123.1     131.2&#13;
DOD/Reserves               472.5     580.6    528.7     438.3    561.4    767.6     948.7    979.6    876.5     714.1&#13;
Interest-Service/GNP         0.6       0.7      0.6       0.7      0.8      1.1       1.1      1.2      1.4       1.7&#13;
Memo Item&#13;
Total Public DOD (US$ billions)&#13;
of included countries     10.7      12.1     13.9      16.3     20.1     23.4      28.0     35.4     45.7      58.4&#13;
/a See Annex II for country coverage.&#13;
/b Weights are the shares of individual countries in public debt of the group.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-65-&#13;
ANNEX II&#13;
Major Groups Reporting to DRS&#13;
Low-Income Oil Importers                Middle-Income Oil Importers:&#13;
Non-Major Exporters of Manufactures&#13;
*    Afghanistan                                      Barbados&#13;
Bangladesh                                    * Botswana&#13;
Benin                                            Cameroon&#13;
Burma                                            Chile&#13;
*    Burundi                                          Colombia&#13;
Central African Republic                         Costa Rica&#13;
Chad                                             Cyprus&#13;
*    Comoros                                          Dominican Republic&#13;
Ethiopia                                         El Salvador&#13;
Gambia, The                                      Fiji&#13;
*    Guinea                                           Ghana&#13;
India                                            Guatemala&#13;
Kenya                                            Guyana&#13;
*    Lesotho                                          Haiti&#13;
Madagascar                                       Honduras&#13;
Malawi                                           Ivory Coast&#13;
*    Maldives                                         Jamaica&#13;
Mali                                             Jordan&#13;
*    Nepal                                         * Lebanon&#13;
Niger                                         * Liberia&#13;
Pakistan                                         Malta&#13;
Rwanda                                           Mauritania&#13;
Sierra Leone                                     Mauritius&#13;
Somalia                                          Morocco&#13;
Sri Lanka                                        Nicaragua&#13;
Tanzania                                         Panama&#13;
Uganda                                        *  Papua New Guinea&#13;
Upper Volta                                      Paraguay&#13;
Zaire                                            Philippines&#13;
Senegal&#13;
* South Africa&#13;
Sudan&#13;
Swaziland&#13;
Thailand&#13;
Togo&#13;
Turkey&#13;
Uruguay&#13;
Yemen, Arab Rep. of&#13;
Yemen, P.D.R.&#13;
Zambia&#13;
(List continues on following page.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-66-&#13;
ANNEX II (cont.)&#13;
-                ~~~~~Oil Exporters&#13;
Middle-Income Oil Importers:    **&#13;
Major Exporters of Manufactures               Algeria&#13;
* Bahrain&#13;
Bolivia&#13;
Argentina                                Congo, P.R. of the&#13;
Brazil                                   Ecuador&#13;
Greece                                   Egypt, Arab Rep. of&#13;
Hong Kong                                Gabon&#13;
Israel                                   Indonesia&#13;
Korea, Rep. of                        *  Iran&#13;
Portugal                              *  Iraq&#13;
Singapore                                Malaysia&#13;
Spain                                    Mexico&#13;
Yugoslavia                               Nigeria&#13;
Oman&#13;
Peru&#13;
Syrian Arab Rep.&#13;
Trinidad and Tobago&#13;
Tunisia&#13;
Venezuela&#13;
* Indicates economies for which complete time series are not&#13;
available; they are excluded from tablesshowing weighted&#13;
aggregate debt indicators.&#13;
** Tables include data for Taiwan, China.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX III&#13;
DEVELOPING ECONOMIES' SHARES IN&#13;
OUTSTANDING PUBLIC DEBT, 1970-79 *&#13;
(percentages x 100)&#13;
1970     1971     1972     1973     1974     1975     1976     1977     1978     1979&#13;
Afghanistan                  86.2     82.9     81.4     70.5     60.5     52.7     49.1     46.2     42.3     37.4&#13;
Algeria                     178.1    198.5    204.4    329.4    297.7    331.6    349.9    400.4    486.4    501.8&#13;
Argentina                   357.1    346.3    326.2    312.7    292.4    230.9    264.8    242.2    260.3    285.3&#13;
Bahrain                       0.7      2.3      3.0      3.1      4.0      3.8      3.7      3.1      2.9      3.0&#13;
Bangladesh                    -        -        7.4     41.3     91.1    119.3    116.0    110.4    105.9     93.0&#13;
Barbados                      2.4      2.3      1.1      2.9      2.4      1.9      1.8      2.2      2.3      2.2&#13;
Benin                         7.7      8.1      6.2      6.5      7.3      6.6      6.7      6.6      6.3      6.1&#13;
Bolivia                      90.7     84.6     84.7     70.9     62.5     59.0     61.2     66.1     63.1     60.1&#13;
Botswana                      2.8      5.3     10.3     12.9     12.1     10.9      9.9      8.7      4.6      4.4&#13;
Brazil                      613.4    645.9    784.6    839.0    971.5   1008.0   1030.0   1032.0   1155.0   1148.7&#13;
Burma                        19.2     20.7     21.8     26.0     25.0     20.8     18.4     24.3     33.0     37.3&#13;
Burundi                       1.4      1.3      0.9      0.9      0.8      1.3      1.3      1.9      2.5      3.4&#13;
Cameroon                     24.9     26.1     26.8     26.6     24.7     27.6     30.8     40.3     44.3     53.5&#13;
Central African Rep.          3.7      4.1      4.7      6.0      5.7      5.5      5.3      5.4      5.2      4.9&#13;
Chad                          6.1      5.9      3.6      4.3      4.8      5.0      5.7      5.6      6.0      5.6&#13;
Chile                       392.7    351.0    355.6    316.0    341.4    276.4    214.8    176.3    166.7    156.0&#13;
Colombia                    237.4    222.9    224.1    215.0    188.6    173.9    146.8    128.6    107.4    112.2&#13;
Comoros                       0.2      0.2      0.2      0.2      0.4      0.3      1.1      1.1      1.1      1.2&#13;
Congo, P.R. of the           27.1     25.5     24.5     22.7     25.7     26.9     24.7     24.0     28.8     26.1&#13;
Costa Rica                   25.5     26.9     28.5     28.0     27.3     31.2     32.1     35.4     36.6     41.8&#13;
Cyprus                       10.7      6.6      5.5      6.4      6.9      5.7      5.6      7.8      9.2      9.8&#13;
Dominican Republic           40.4     39.0     39.5     34.2     32.2     30.4     29.4     28.9     27.8     27.1&#13;
Ecuador                      40.6     37.2     42.0     37.2     29.5     33.8     37.0     54.8     60.8     72.2&#13;
Egypt, Arab Republic of     312.5    291.8    272.3    249.8    254.9    357.7    345.1    389.6    380.0    373.4&#13;
El Salvador                  16.7     14.9     15.0     12.0     15.8     14.5     15.7     12.8     12.8     13.0&#13;
Ethiopia                     32.1     32.8     31.1     29.0     26.3     26.2     24.7     22.0     19.6     20.3&#13;
Fiji                          1.9      2.0      1.9      3.8      3.8      3.7      3.4      3.9      3.1      3.5&#13;
Gabon                        17.3     20.5     27.6     38.9     44.3     53.9     63.6     60.3     48.4     39.7&#13;
Gambia, The                   1.0      0.9      1.0      1.0      1.1      0.9      0.8      1.2      1.0      1.5&#13;
Ghana                        93.0     85.6     76.5     79.1     63.1     49.8     40.4     37.8     32.3     32.0&#13;
Greece                      172.1    166.0    183.9    173.1    183.5    189.0    142.5    125.7    119.6    115.6&#13;
(Annex continues on following pages.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX III (cont.)&#13;
1970     1971     1972      1973     1974     1975      1976     1977     1978     1979&#13;
Guatemala                     20.2     17.6      14.4     12.6     10.3      12.2     12.6     13.2     14.1      15.8&#13;
Guinea                        59.7     68.0      67.3     68.0     65.1      56.4     48.0     39.8     34.7      32.4&#13;
Guyana                        15.0     23.8      20.6     18.5     18.4     21.6      21.7     19.1     16.4      15.3&#13;
Haiti                          7.7      6.2       6.0      4.6      4.1       4.2      4.7      6.2      6.6       6.8&#13;
Honduras                      17.1     16.5      16.4     15.0     15.4      19.6     20.6     22.0     22.8      24.4&#13;
Hong Kong                      0.5      0.3       0.2      0.1      1.6       1.6      3.7      7.9      8.6      13.3&#13;
India                       1508.7   1432.9   1341.6    1168.5   1033.0    906.3     794.4    700.0    588.0    512.0&#13;
Indonesia                    464.5    555.9    577.5     589.7    572.7    593.7     599.5    561.9    502.8    436.2&#13;
Israel                       432.4    482.4    492.5     508.6    469.2    438.2     429.9    389.3    352.7    325.8&#13;
Ivory Coast                   48.7     56.6      54.8     65.0     61.8     67.9      69.3     93.0    107.7     116.1&#13;
Jamaica                       29.3     29.3      29.2     38.4     46.5      50.7     52.7     45.3     40.4      38.7&#13;
Jordan                        22.5     23.5      23.5     23.5     24.3      25.2     24.6     30.0     32.2      34.3&#13;
Kenya                         77.2     69.2      65.4     63.2     58.9      53.3     50.8     51.3     47.3      51.6&#13;
Korea, Republic of           341.9    375.8     396.7    409.5    403.8    419.5     415.3    420.1    462.4     481.0&#13;
Lebanon                       12.2     11.0       8.5      6.3      4.4       3.4      2.3      1.9      1.8       3.0&#13;
Lesotho                        1.5      1.4       1.3      0.9      0.9       1.0      1.0      1.2      1.3       1.7&#13;
Liberia                       30.0     25.5      21.6     17.6     14.4      13.0     12.5     12.8     12.8      14.9&#13;
Madagascar                    17.7     17.4      12.4     13.1     12.4      12.5     10.8     10.2     10.6      11.4&#13;
Malawi                        23.0     22.5      22.5     22.6     20.5      18.0     15.4     14.5      15.3     13.9&#13;
Malaysia                      74.1     85.8      93.6     80.9     78.1      99.1     97.7     98.7    103.1      98.3&#13;
Maldives                       -        -         -        -        -        -         0.0      0.1      0.1       0.2&#13;
Mali                          45.2     42.2      35.2     32.0     30.0      25.9     22.3     21.6     20.6      17.9&#13;
Malta                          4.7      2.9       2.9      2.6      2.4       2.4      2.9      2.5       2.4      2.2   90&#13;
Mauritania                     5.2      6.4       7.8     11.9     15.2      13.9     23.5     22.1     22.0      19.3&#13;
Mauritius                      6.0      5.4       4.5      3.9      3.7       3.4      3.0      3.4       5.8      7.4&#13;
Mexico                       609.6    562.6     538.1    627.5    748.9     854.3    952.9   1000.7    981.9     942.9&#13;
Morocco                      135.3    140.4     126.2    112.1    109.8     129.8    140.1    196.3    196.8     203.8&#13;
Nepal                          0.5      1.3       1.6      2.2      2.4       2.5      2.6      3.5      3.3       4.1&#13;
Nicaragua                     29.5     30.4      32.3     37.6     41.4     44.3      39.2     41.6     36.8      36.0&#13;
Niger                          6.0      6.7       7.4      7.2      8.3       8.3      7.8      5.7      7.4       7.7&#13;
Nigeria                       90.9     92.5      93.3    129.9    109.8     80.4      50.1     42.9     83.5     122.6&#13;
Oman                           -        -         -        4.7     14.9      20.0     25.3     26.6     21.5      14.9&#13;
Pakistan                     581.6    580.5     521.3    475.5    417.4    377.5     359.1    326.9    289.6     261.8&#13;
Panama                        36.9     39.4      47.5     51.4     50.9     57.3      66.0     65.2     73.0      68.9&#13;
Papua New Guinea               6.9     14.4      17.9     24.7     22.0     20.4      17.1     16.1     14.2      12.9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX III (cont.)&#13;
1970     1971      1972     1973      1974     1975     1976      1977     1978      1979&#13;
Paraguay                       21.2     19.7     18.1      16.3     14.7      13.9     14.1      16.2     16.7     16.1&#13;
Peru                          162.7    145.4     144.9    162.0    200.1     223.8    219.4     226.8    206.9    194.2&#13;
Philippines                   120.4    113.6    121.6      98.5     98.9     102.0    127.9     141.8    162.5    169.6&#13;
Portugal                       89.5     75.8      67.8     68.1     64.3      61.2     59.6      67.2    107.5    121.4&#13;
Rwanda                          0.4      0.3       0.5      0.9      1.1       1.8      2.9       3.5      3.7      4.1&#13;
Senegal                        18.6     19.6      18.7     19.8     22.1      21.9     20.9      20.2     23.3     25.7&#13;
Sierra Leone                   11.3     11.0      10.0     10.1     12.2      10.8      9.4       9.3      9.3      9.5&#13;
Singapore                      28.9     33.4     41.1      47.5     46.2      40.7     42.2      48.1     43.4     43.3&#13;
Somalia                        14.7     13.6     13.8      14.2     15.7      16.9     17.1      18.5     19.2     17.9&#13;
South Africa                 207.0     237.2    265.7     266.0    306.5     323.8    334.3    286.6     237.4    242.2&#13;
Spain                         229.8    219.3    199.5     191.5    226.5     252.5    285.7    335.6     291.2    283.3&#13;
Sri Lanka                      60.2     63.5     58.0      54.5     52.9      44.3     41.6      37.5     38.8     35.5&#13;
Sudan                          58.7     53.7     51.0      52.2     81.4      87.5     96.1      86.6     79.9     69.2&#13;
Swaziland                      7.0       5.6      4.5       4.1      3.3       2.5      2.4      2.5       3.9      4.8&#13;
Syrian Arab Rep.               44.2     47.3     46.2      46.4     45.4      50.2     60.0      74.1     75.4     74.7    1&#13;
Tanzania, United Rep. of       61.3     62.5      62.0     62.6     65.6      67.9     61.4      57.7     46.4     41.7&#13;
Thailand                       61.2     57.9      53.4     49.7     46.2      45.6     49.2      51.4     68.6     88.4&#13;
Togo                            7.6      7.6       6.3      6.4      7.9       8.7     10.1      14.6     22.3     2-.9&#13;
Trinidad and Tobago            19.1     16.3      16.8     16.9     15.0      11.8      6.4      12.4     16.0     13.8&#13;
Tunisia                       103.6    100.7     96.1      93.0     84.8      77.2     70.2      85.6     90.4    100.1&#13;
Turkey                        352.5    359.5    336.6     322.3    281.1     234.0    214.4     205.7    240.7    359.1&#13;
Uganda                         27.8     25.4     25.1      21.4     19.1      16.1     14.6      12,0     10.8      9.0&#13;
Upper Volta                     3.9      3.8       2.7      3.5       4.2      4.7      5.2       6.6      7.2      8.4&#13;
Uruguay                        50.8     46.8      44.6     38.7     46.5      45.7     41.4      35.4     30.4     29.9&#13;
Venezuela                     138.5    165.3    194.9     173.1    134.5      93.4    177.2     213.1    26'.0    320.7&#13;
Yemen, Arab Rep. of             -        -         0.0     19.4     20.7      18.1     16.1      16.6     17.8     15.3&#13;
Yemen, P.D.R.                   0.1      0.5       2.7      5.6      7.0       7.4      9.3      12.3     13.3     14.4&#13;
Yugoslavia                    227.8    215.7    221.8     210.9    188.5     172.4    167.9     149.4    133.2    121.1&#13;
Zaire                          59.1     58.5     78.7     101.2    120.8     127.2    135.6     138.2    136.9    123.7&#13;
Zambia                        113.3     95.7     87.8      73.6     68.7      81.4     74.9      67.0     53.5     51.0&#13;
Memo Item&#13;
Public Debt (US$ billions)     52.6     62.1      72.8     89.0    110.0     135.0    167.1     207.7    261.1    305.5&#13;
Calculations include data for Taiwan,China.    Its shares in public debt (percentages x 100) are as follows:&#13;
114.2    112.9    107.6     104.9    100.3     121.1    133.6     126.6    112.4     100.9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-70-&#13;
References&#13;
Aliber, Robert Z. A Conceptual Approach to the Analysis of External Debt&#13;
of the Developing Countries, World Bank Staff Working Paper No.421&#13;
(October 1980).&#13;
Avramovic, Dragoslav. Debt-Servicing Capacity and Postwar Growth in&#13;
International Indebtedness. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
1958.&#13;
Bank for International Settlements. Fifty-First Annual Report,&#13;
1st April 1980 - 31st March 1981. Basle, June 1981.&#13;
OECD. Development Co-operation, Efforts and Policies of the Members of&#13;
the Development Assistance Committee, 1980 Review. Paris, 1980.&#13;
Holsen, J. "Notes on the 'LDC Debt Problem'," World Development, Vol.7&#13;
(1979), pp.145-49.&#13;
Hughes, H. "The External Debt of Developing Countries," Finance and&#13;
Development, Vol.14 No.4. (December 1977), p.22.&#13;
IMF. External Indebtedness of Developing Countries, IMF Occasional Paper&#13;
No.3, Washington DC, 1981.&#13;
World Bank. World Development Report 1980, New York: Oxford University&#13;
Press, 1980.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
COMPANION PAPERS IN THIS SERIES&#13;
No.                           TITLE OF PAPER                          AUTHOR&#13;
449     Policy Experience in Twelve Less Developed Countries        B. Balassa&#13;
470     Industrial Country Policy and Adjustment to Imports         J.M. Finger&#13;
from Developing Countries&#13;
471     The Political Structure of the New Protectionism            D. Nelson (consultant)&#13;
472     Adjustment to External Shocks in Developing Countries       B. Balassa&#13;
473     Food Policy Issues in Low-Income Countries                  E. Clay (consultant)&#13;
474     Energy, International Trade, and Economic Growth            A. Manne (consultant)&#13;
475     Capital-Importing Oil Exporters:   Adjustment Issues        A.H. Gelb&#13;
and Policy Choices&#13;
476     Notes on the Analysis of Capital Flows to Developing        R.C. Bryant (consultant)&#13;
Nations and the 'Recycling' Problem&#13;
477     Adjustment Experience and Growth Prospects of the           F. Jaspersen&#13;
Semi-Industrial Countries&#13;
478     Trade Policy Issues for the Developing Countries            I. Frank (consultant)&#13;
in the 1980s&#13;
479     Trade among Developing Countries: Theory, Policy            0. Havrylyshyn&#13;
Issues, and Principal Trends                                   (consultant)&#13;
M. Wolf&#13;
480     Trade in Services:   Economic Determinants and              A. Sapir (consultant)&#13;
Development-Related Issues                                  E. Lutz&#13;
481     International Migrant Workers' Remittances:   Issues        G. Swamy&#13;
and Prospects&#13;
482     Private Bank Lending to Developing Countries                R. O'Brien (consultant)&#13;
483     Development Prospects of the Capital Surplus                R. Hablutzel&#13;
Oil-Exporting Countries&#13;
484     Private Capital Flows to Developing Countries and           A. Fleming&#13;
Their Determination&#13;
485     International Adjustment in the 1980s                       V. Joshi (consultant)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
No.                          TITLE OF PAPER                          AUTHOR&#13;
486     Adjustment in Low-Income Africa                            R. Liebenthal&#13;
487     A Comparative Analysis of Developing Country               C. Wallich&#13;
Adjustment Experiences in the 1970s: Low-Income&#13;
South Asia&#13;
488     Developments in and Prospects for the External            N. Hope&#13;
Debt of the Developing Countries: 1970-80 and&#13;
Beyond&#13;
489     Global Energy Prospects                                   B.J. Choe&#13;
A. Lambertini&#13;
P. Pollak&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PUB HG3881.5 .W57 W67 no.488&#13;
Hope, Nicholas C.&#13;
Developments in and prospects&#13;
for the external debt of the&#13;
developing countries :&#13;
PUB HG3881.5.W57 W67 no.488&#13;
Hope, Nicholas C.&#13;
Developments in and prospects&#13;
for the external debt of the&#13;
d&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554943">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1981/08/1554943/developments-prospects-external-debt-developing-countries-1970-80-beyond
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1981/08/1554943/developments-prospects-external-debt-developing-countries-1970-80-beyond</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1981/08/1554943/developments-prospects-external-debt-developing-countries-1970-80-beyond</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/01/08/000178830_98101903411846/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/01/08/000178830_98101903411846/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-01-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1981-08-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Developments in and prospects for the
            external debt of the developing countries : 1970-80 and beyond
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Much has been made of the perils to the
            developing countries - and to the international banking
            system - from the rapid expansion of their debt during the
            1970s. This paper examines the borrowing patterns of
            developing countries, as they have evolved over the past
            decade, by drawing on data contained in the Debtor Reporting
            System (DRS) of the World Bank. Changes in the debt
            situation of these countries - in aggregate, for important
            sub-groups, and individually - are assessed by a
            consideration of how debt and associated service payments
            have changed relative to major macro-economic variables that
            are often used to assess a borrowing country's
            creditworthiness. The paper then examines the prospects for
            borrowing during the 1980s.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Developments in and prospects for the
            external debt of the developing countries : 1970-80 and beyond
        </docna>
        <display_title>Developments in and prospects for
            the external debt of the developing countries : 1970-80 and beyond</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1981/08/1554943/developments-prospects-external-debt-developing-countries-1970-80-beyond</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Public Sector Economics,Strategic Debt Management</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>HOPE, N.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903411846</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Macro/non-trade</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 488</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Borrowing; Capital movements; Debt
            management; Debts; External debt; Indebtedness; Structural adjustment
            Bank lending,banking
            system,Bonds,borrowing,capital flows,capital
            markets,Centrally planned economy,commercial
            banks,consumption
            patterns,Creditor,creditors,creditworthiness,debt,debt
            disbursed,Debt Flows,debt management,Debt Outstanding,Debtor
            Reporting,deficits,Development Assistance,discount
            rate,economic activity,Economic Analysis,economic
            progress,exchange rate,Export Growth,exports,external
            debt,financial institutions,financial
            intermediaries,Financial Markets,financial resources,foreign
            borrowing,foreign debt,foreign
            exchange,GNP,Income,inflation,interest rates,international
            banking,multilateral debt,nominal interest rates,Oil,oil
            prices,OPEC,outstanding debt,payments imbalances,price
            increases,Private Debt,Public Debt,recycling,Regional
            Banks,regression analysis,Suppliers Credits,valuation
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP488</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Trade in Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Intermediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Volatility</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Intermediaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade in Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>