<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Trade in Services: Economic Determinants&#13;
and Development-Related Issues&#13;
SWP480&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 480&#13;
August 1981&#13;
Prepared by: Andre Sapir [Consultant]&#13;
Emst Lutz&#13;
Intemational Trade and Capital Flows Division&#13;
Economic Analysis and Projections Department&#13;
Development Policy Staff&#13;
Copyright ®) 1981&#13;
The MMl Bank                             tL               COPY&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.r&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the authors&#13;
and should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated&#13;
organizations, or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the aubthors and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations,&#13;
or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 480&#13;
August 1981&#13;
TRADE IN SERVICES: ECONOMIC DETERMINANTS AND DEVELOPMENT-RELATED ISSUES&#13;
A Background Study for World Development Report 1981&#13;
This paper represents the second stage oE a research project on&#13;
trade in services. The results are preliminary; further work may be done to&#13;
improve or expand the analysis.&#13;
One of the main conclusions is that trade theories can indeed, to a&#13;
large extent, explain the patterns of trade in services in spite of varying&#13;
and often substantial degrees of protectionism. Comparative advantage in&#13;
freight services appears to be related to capital intensity, scale,&#13;
composition of trade, and distance from trading partners. Performance in&#13;
passenger services depends in part on capital abundance and the flow of&#13;
passengers. In trade in insurance services the availability of human capital&#13;
and economies of scale seem to be important determinants.&#13;
In addition to their role as exports or imports, some traded&#13;
services such as consultant and engineering services, licensing, and technical&#13;
assistance are means of transfer of technology and are thereby important in&#13;
the development process.&#13;
Prepared by: Andre Sapir [Consultant] and Ernst Lutz&#13;
International Trade and Capital Flows Division&#13;
Economic Analysis and Projections Department&#13;
Development Policy Staff&#13;
Copyright   D    1981&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
We are indebted to several of our colleagues for valuable comments&#13;
and discussions. Among others, we particularly would like to thank Francis X.&#13;
Colafo, Harald Hansen, Oli Havrylyshyn, James Riedel, Jo Saxe, Gurushri Swamy,&#13;
Martin Wolf, John Zerby, and the participants of a World Bank workshop in&#13;
international trade and finance.    We would also like to express our gratitude&#13;
to Millie Kim for providing excellent research assistance and to May-O Kuo for&#13;
the efficient typing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Contents&#13;
Page&#13;
I.  INTRODUCTION.............................................. &#13;
II. THE DETERMINANTS OF COMPARATIVE ADVANTAGE IN SERVICES .....              5&#13;
A.   Theory ...............................................             5&#13;
B.   Empirical Results ....................................            10&#13;
1.  Freight Services ................................ .           10&#13;
2.   Passenger Services .     . .....            .   .......      14&#13;
3.   Insurance Services .     .     .............................  17&#13;
C.   Conclusions ..................................... .....           21&#13;
III. THE ROLE OF SERVICES IN THE DEVELOPMENT PROCESS           .    .       23&#13;
A.   Services, Infrastructure, and Technology Transfer....             23&#13;
B.  Trade in Capital Goods        .      ..            .  ......       27&#13;
IV.   SUMMARY OF FINDINGS .     .     .    ...................................  31&#13;
APPENDIX: INPUT DATA FOR THE EMPIRICAL ANALYSIS AND FOR THE&#13;
DEFINITION OF CAPITAL GOODS .....................     ...       32&#13;
REFERENCES ..................................................      ..       36&#13;
Tables&#13;
2.1    Regression Equations for Freight Services ...............            12&#13;
2.2    Regression Equations for Passenger Services .............            16&#13;
2.3    Regression Equations for Insurance Services .............            20&#13;
3.1    Trade in Capital Goods, 1975 ............................            29&#13;
A.1    First Set of Input Data Used&#13;
for Econometric Analysis, 1977 .......................            33&#13;
A.2    Second Set of Input Data Used&#13;
for Econometric Analysis, 1977 .......................            34&#13;
A.3    Definition of Capital Goods .............................            35&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. INTRODUCTION&#13;
Not a week in recent months seems to have gone by without the&#13;
meeting of a national or international study group composed of business or&#13;
government representatives who seek to shape the future of international&#13;
transactions in services.L/ There are several reasons for this sudden&#13;
interest in services. First is the recognition - mostly in the United States -&#13;
that services constitute a large and important component of international&#13;
transactions. Second is the fact that services have been left relatively&#13;
untouched by international negotiations and, at the same time, that the&#13;
achievements of the Tokyo Round in goods trade allow the international&#13;
community to attack a new problem. Third is the slowdown in the&#13;
industrialized economies and the repercussions of this slowdown on the&#13;
international scene. Indeed, the lack of effective demand at home has forced&#13;
the producers of services in the industrialized economies to reinforce their&#13;
efforts in outside markets in order to sustain their activity level.&#13;
Simultaneously, the developing economies are seeking to diversify their&#13;
exports away from labor-intensive goods, in which they enjoy a strong&#13;
comparative advantage but face a new protectionist attitude in the markets of&#13;
the industrialized world.&#13;
So far, the meetings have attempted to provide a framework for&#13;
further research in this new area of interest. The research agenda agreed&#13;
upon by the participants at the Conference on Research Possibilities in&#13;
/ An excellent way to follow the activity is to consult the International&#13;
Services Newsletter published quarterly by the Office of the U.S. Trade&#13;
Representative.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2&#13;
Services held at Wye, Maryland, on March 29, 1980, offers a good summary of&#13;
the directions that.are being proposed in the various meetings. This agenda&#13;
includes the following:&#13;
a.   Compilation of data on international flows of services and the&#13;
analysis of such data&#13;
b.   Development of economic models that would help explain&#13;
international flows of services&#13;
C.   Research on individual service sectors to provide more detailed&#13;
information about each sector's worldwide activity&#13;
d.   Analysis of alternative negotiating solutions&#13;
e.   Research on the applicability of domestic trade legislation to&#13;
international flows of services.&#13;
A previous study has already compiled and analyzed much of the&#13;
existing data.I/ At this stage more conceptual research is required,&#13;
including research on economic models of the international flows of services.&#13;
The purpose of this paper is to analyze the pattern of trade in services by&#13;
means of the tools provided by trade theories. Moreover, an attempt is made&#13;
to use this analysis to place services in a light appropriate for further&#13;
work, both theoretical and policy-oriented.&#13;
The remainder of the introduction will be devoted to clarifying some&#13;
of the concepts used in this paper. Chapter II presents an analysis of the&#13;
determinants of comparative advantage in trade in services. Chapter III&#13;
examines the role of services in the development process. A fourth chapter&#13;
summarizes the main findings, and an appendix presents the input data used in&#13;
the analysis.&#13;
2! See-Sapir and Lutz (1980).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3&#13;
The object of this paper is the study of services within the context&#13;
of the international economy. Services constitute activities producing an&#13;
intangible output. In terms of the International Standard Industrial&#13;
Classification (ISIC), services correspond to the heterogeneous set of&#13;
activities classified under the following major divisions:&#13;
6 Wholesale and retail trade, restaurants and hotels&#13;
7 Transport, storage, and communication&#13;
8 Financing, insurance, real estate, and business services&#13;
9 Community, social, and personal services.&#13;
Within the framework of the international economy, one must&#13;
distinguish between international service transactions and international&#13;
service activities. The former refers exclusively to exports and imports and&#13;
corresponds therefore to international trade. The latter, on the other hand,&#13;
includes foreign sales and purchases by affiliates or branches established&#13;
abroad and therefore implies international investment. Although this&#13;
distinction concerns not only services but also goods,-/ it is undoubtedly&#13;
more important for services. This is because, by their very nature, services&#13;
often are non-tradeables. In the present study, we will devote most of our&#13;
attention to international service trade, making only brief references to&#13;
international investment.&#13;
Among the services that give rise to international transactions,&#13;
some are actually traded and some are not. Those not traded are services&#13;
being sold within the domestic economy to foreign individuals or firms&#13;
residing abroad. They consist mostly of tourism and port services and will be&#13;
t  See Baldwin (1979), which analyzes the determinants of trade and foreign&#13;
investment for goods.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4&#13;
ignored in this work.i' Therefore, international service transactions are&#13;
defined as comprising the following categories.2/&#13;
a.   Transport (of goods, services, persons by air, sea, road, etc.)&#13;
b.   Communications (transport of information)&#13;
c.   Financial services (banking, insurance, brokerage)&#13;
d.   Professional and technical services (accounting, advertising,&#13;
construction and engineering, consulting and management, data&#13;
processing, legal services, etc.).&#13;
/  Besides, tourism constitutes what can be called a "Ricardo service"; that&#13;
is, a service whose comparative advantage is largely determined by natural&#13;
endowments.&#13;
2/ The concept used here is therefore narrower than that utilized by Sapir&#13;
and Lutz (1980), where services were defined as "non-factor services."&#13;
Compared with the previous concept, the present one excludes the following&#13;
items: port services, travel, the labor income and property income&#13;
components of other private services, and other government services.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
5&#13;
II. THE DETERMINANTS OF COMPARATIVE ADVANTAGE&#13;
IN TRADE IN SERVICES&#13;
This chapter analyzes the pattern of comparative advantage in trade&#13;
in services. It deals with net exports, which are thought to be a better&#13;
index of trade performance than either exports or imports alone. The chapter&#13;
is divided into three sections. Section A describes various trade theories&#13;
and the variables selected to represent them. Section B reports and analyzes&#13;
the empirical findings. Comparisons with other studies and policy&#13;
implications are discussed in section C.&#13;
A. Theory&#13;
In the introduction to his recent survey of empirical research on&#13;
trade theories, Stern (1975) writes: "International trade theory is mainly&#13;
concerned with determining what goods and services countries will buy and sell&#13;
in foreign trade" (p. 3). Despite this opening statement, no mention of&#13;
services is made in the remainder of Stern's excellent paper. Yet, no one&#13;
could argue that the absence of references to services reflects the author's&#13;
bias in favor of goods. There simply has been no empirical work on the&#13;
determinants of comparative advantage in services.&#13;
The reasons for this state of affairs are threefold. First,&#13;
economists have long failed to appreciate the role played by services in the&#13;
balance of trade. Second, the lack of adequate data has proved to be a&#13;
formidable hinderance to our understanding of services trade. Finally, there&#13;
seems to be widespread a priori opinion among researchers that the&#13;
determinants of trade in services either are not economic in nature or are&#13;
essentially the same as the factors that determine trade in goods. Thus no&#13;
special study of services seemed warranted. This study will examine the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6&#13;
extent to which trade theories, which have been tested with respect to goods,&#13;
can explain the pattern of trade in services.&#13;
As formulated by Ricardo, the theory of comparative advantage&#13;
suggests that trade patterns are determined by variations in comparative costs&#13;
among economies. However, it was not until the days of Heckscher and Ohlin&#13;
that it was hypothesized that variations in comparative costs among economies&#13;
derive from variations in factor endowments. Following Leontief's (1953)&#13;
work, attempts have been made to go beyond the simple two-factor (capital and&#13;
labor) Heckscher-Ohlin-Samuelson (H-O-S) model of compatative advantage.&#13;
Essentially, these attempts can be grouped under four theories:&#13;
a.   The extended H-O-S theory, which accounts for variation in&#13;
national resources and human capital among economiesl/&#13;
b.   The neo-technology theory2&#13;
c.   The scale economy theory3/&#13;
d.   The market-imperfection theory, which accounts particularly for&#13;
tariff and non-tariff barriers.&#13;
The five trade theories listed above (including the simple H-O-S&#13;
model) have recently been subjected to empirical test. Most authors seek to&#13;
4/&#13;
explain the inter-industry trade composition of a particular economy .&#13;
However, following the work of other economists,-5/ Leamer (1974) has argued&#13;
/  The original contributors are Diab (1956), Vanek (1963), Kravis (1956),&#13;
Kenen (1965), and Keesing (1965).&#13;
2/ See Hufbauer (1965) and Vernon (1966).&#13;
See Dreze (1960).&#13;
See Baldwin (1971, 1979), Branson and Monoyios (1977), Harkness and Kyle&#13;
(1975), Hufbauer (1970), and Stern (1976).&#13;
See Chenery (1960) and Keesing (1968).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
7&#13;
that trade theories have to be tested against the trade variations among&#13;
economies of a particular commodity.1i The latter approach will be used to&#13;
investigate the determinants of comparative advantage in services.&#13;
Ideally, one might want to test all the various competing theories&#13;
simultaneously. In practice, however, this is not feasible-because of the&#13;
difficulty in quantifying some of these theories. Also, problems of sample&#13;
size and multicollinearity typically restrict the simultaneous inclusion of&#13;
many explanatory variables in the regression,equations 2/ The solution&#13;
adopted here is a two-step approach to the problem. The first step consists&#13;
of regressing trade patterns on a limited number of explanatory variables.&#13;
The second step analyzes the residuals from the previous stage and uses&#13;
qualitative information to draw inferences about the unobservables.&#13;
The dependent variable that was selected to reflect the pattern of&#13;
comparative advantage across economies is the ratio of exports to imports of a&#13;
particular service, a variant of the usual net trade balance variable. The&#13;
independent variables serve as proxies for the trade theories we intend to&#13;
test. They can be classified into five categories corresponding to the five&#13;
theories discussed earlier.&#13;
First, the simple H-0-S model is represented by the capital-labor&#13;
ratio. Following the procedure employed by Hufbauer (1970) and Balassa&#13;
(1979), we have approximated the capital stock by the sum of gross fixed&#13;
investment over the period 1960-75, measured at constant prices and converted&#13;
into U.S. dollars using a weighted average of 1968 and 1973 exchange&#13;
/, For an interesting combination of the two approaches, see Balassa (1979).&#13;
21 Leamer (1974) partially solved these problems by using the Bayesian&#13;
approach.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
8&#13;
rates     The data have been divided by the corresponding labor force&#13;
figures2./ to obtain an estimate of the capital-labor ratio (KL).&#13;
Second, we have experimented with various proxies for human capital&#13;
endowment:&#13;
a.   A modification of Hufbauer's (1970) measure, consisting of the&#13;
ratio of professional, technical, and related workers3/ to the&#13;
labor force (PTR)&#13;
b.   The percentage of the labor force with secondary-school&#13;
education, approximated by the ratio of secondary-school&#13;
enrollment to the entire population (EDS)&#13;
c.   The percentage of the labor force with third-level education,&#13;
approximated by the ratio of third-level enrollment to the&#13;
entire population (EDT).4/&#13;
The proxies EDS and EDT are adapted from Baldwin (1971), who used variables&#13;
indicating the percentage of the labor force with various years of education.&#13;
Third, technological factors are proxied, as in Leamer (1974), by&#13;
S5/&#13;
national research and development expenditures5 relative to GDP (RD).&#13;
Fourth, economies of scale are reflected by the gross domestic product&#13;
(GDP). Finally, market imperfections are considered as unobservables and are,&#13;
therefore, absent from the regression equations. Nevertheless, they will be&#13;
I' Investment data are from the World Bank's national accounts file.&#13;
2/ Labor-force figures are from the International Labor Office, ILO Yearbook&#13;
of Labor Statistics 1979 (Geneva: ILO, 1979).&#13;
3/ Also from the ILO Yearbook.&#13;
4/ Secondary-school and third-level enrollment figures are from the United&#13;
Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization, UNESCO&#13;
Statistical Yearbook 1978/79. (Paris: UNESCO, 1980)&#13;
Also from the UNESCO Yearbook.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
9&#13;
the object of qualitative comments in connection with the regression&#13;
residuals.&#13;
The data base for the dependent variable consists of 1977 figures&#13;
reported by the International Monetary Fund (IMF) for the following service&#13;
categories:&#13;
a. Freight (FR)&#13;
b. Passenger services (PS)&#13;
c. Insurance&#13;
1. Total (INT)&#13;
2. Non-merchandise (INN)&#13;
3. Merchandise (INM)&#13;
d. Other services, including non-merchandise insurance (OS).!'&#13;
The data collection was undertaken for a sample of 52 economies including 35&#13;
developing and 17 industrialized ones (the data are shown in Tables A.1 and&#13;
A.2 of the appendix). There was no category for which the data were available&#13;
and reliable for all 52 economies,!/ so that the actual sample that was used&#13;
varied from one category to another. The sample size ranged from 35 for&#13;
freight to 13 for total insurance. However, because it was not possible to&#13;
obtain estimates for each explanatory variable for all the 52 economies, the&#13;
actual sample size had to be further reduced, ranging finally from 32 for&#13;
freight to 13 for total insurance.&#13;
I/ Other services include communications, financial services, and&#13;
professional and technical services.&#13;
2/ Special care was taken to leave aside unreliable figures. This task was&#13;
accomplished by scrutinizing the data together with the IMF's balance-of-&#13;
payments specialists, the World Bank's country economists, as well as&#13;
other economists.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
10&#13;
The model can now be written in general form:&#13;
"(x/M)       ~+~ aS +      S   E                             (2.1)&#13;
ik    ok     lk ik  j  jk  ijk&#13;
where    i = economy index&#13;
j = relative endowment index&#13;
k = service category index&#13;
X = exports&#13;
M = imports&#13;
E = relative endowment (KL, PTR, EDS, EDT, RD)&#13;
S = scale (GDP).&#13;
The model was estimated over a cross-section of economies both in linear and&#13;
log-linear forms.&#13;
B. Empirical Results&#13;
1. Freight Services&#13;
In dealing with freight services, one is first confronted with a&#13;
data problem because a substantial proportion of the world's maritime fleet is&#13;
registered under open-registry flags, the so-called flags of convenience. As&#13;
a result, the available figures on freight service trade are unreliable,&#13;
particularly as far as credits are concerned. The problem is thought to be&#13;
rather less severe for debits. Presumably, there is a better chance of&#13;
knowing whether an economy is importing shipping services than of knowing&#13;
which economy actually earns the counterpart payment. Therefore the solution&#13;
adopted here consists of using debit figures exclusively and redefining the&#13;
dependent variable as the ratio of freight debit to total merchandise import.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
11&#13;
Shipping is generally thought to be a capital-intensive activity.&#13;
Therefore, we hypothesize that comparative advantage in freight services is&#13;
related to an economy's capital-labor ratio.'/ It seems possible that there&#13;
are economies of scale with respect to operating a maritime fleet. Indeed,&#13;
there might be a threshold in merchandise imports below which it is&#13;
uneconomical to own carriers and produce freight services. In this case, all&#13;
freight services would have to be imported. Therefore, we postulate a&#13;
relationship between merchandise imports (M) and our dependent variable.&#13;
Another possibility would be to include GDP as a scale variable.&#13;
In addition, two other hypotheses are formulated. First, we&#13;
recognize that freight costs per unit of imported merchandise vary according&#13;
to the type of merchandise. And, indeed, different types of cargo move in&#13;
different carriers. Therefore, we hypothesize a relationship between the&#13;
share of manufactures in total imports (MM) and the dependent variable.&#13;
Second, we account for the fact that, other things being equal, location is&#13;
likely to have an effect on freight costs: a dummy variable (DIS), which&#13;
takes the value of 1 if the location is exceptionally far from major suppliers&#13;
and 0 otherwise, is introduced to that effect.&#13;
We expect to find a negative impact of KL and M and a positive&#13;
impact of MM and DIS on the dependent variable (FR). The regression equation&#13;
was estimated for a total sample of 32 economies as well as for two sub-&#13;
samples of 20 developing and 12 industrialized economies, respectively.&#13;
Estimates of the regression coefficients are reported in Table 2.1.&#13;
1/  Freight refers to air, overland, and maritime operations.    Generally,&#13;
available data do not provide a breakdown. However, it would appear that&#13;
maritime freight is the dominant item which we, therefore, use to&#13;
formulate our hypotheses. It is assumed that they also apply broadly to&#13;
the other two items.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
12&#13;
Table 2.1:&#13;
REGRESSION EQUATIONS FOR FREIGHT SERVICES&#13;
Equation  Dependent            Independent Variables a/          2    Sample&#13;
Number    Variable         KL       M        MM        DIS      R      Size&#13;
1        FR         -3471       -0.05     1.01    32.15      0.62    32&#13;
4.91**    0.15      2.42*    2.40*   11.23**&#13;
2        FR         -3222       -5.66     1.02     12.05     0.69    20&#13;
3.38**    3.20**    2.07*    0.74     8.40**&#13;
3        FR         -3746        0.07     0.97     45.36     0.61    12&#13;
2.09*     0.20      1.58     2.63*    2.78&#13;
4        log(FR)      -0.31     -0.04     0.26      0.31     0.58    32&#13;
3.61**    0.39     0.86      1.32     9.23**&#13;
5        log(FR)      -0.35     -0.22     0.96     -0.04     0.78    20&#13;
4.66**    2.40*     3.14**   0.18    13.59**&#13;
6        log(FR)      -1.31      0.11     0.79      0.93     0.48    12&#13;
1.95*     0.40      1.13     1.77     1.60&#13;
Note:  The equations were estimated with a constant which is not reported.    A&#13;
* and a ** indicate 95 and 99 percent significance levels,&#13;
respectively, for the t-values (shown below the corresponding&#13;
regression coefficients) and for the F-ratio (shown below the squared&#13;
multiple correlation coefficient).&#13;
a! The logarithm of the independent variables (except DIS) is used for the&#13;
equations in the lower panel.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
13&#13;
Rather remarkably, the results strongly indicate that economies&#13;
relatively well-endowed with physical capital have a comparative advantage in&#13;
freight services. While this result holds for both sub-samples, no similar&#13;
finding was made for the scale effect. This would suggest that there are&#13;
economies of scale in the freight industry, but also that industrialized&#13;
economies operate in a range free of this effect. This might be due either to&#13;
the size of their imports or to the fact that they engage extensively in&#13;
cross-trades.&#13;
We also observe that the distance only affects the sub-sample of&#13;
industrialized economies. This result can be attributed to the fact, on the&#13;
one hand, that developing economies import mostly from industrialized&#13;
economies and are all located far away from them. On the other hand, among&#13;
industrialized economies, there is a strong dichotomy of trade partners'&#13;
location between the European economies compared with Japan, Australia, and&#13;
New Zealand.L/    Finally, the effect of trade composition on freight costs&#13;
appears somewhat more pronounced for the developing economies than for the&#13;
rich ones.  This is probably the consequence of more varied industrialization&#13;
levels and trade strategies among the former group.&#13;
To conclude our analysis of the freight equations, we examine the&#13;
residuals of equations 2 and 3. They indicate that the predicted value of the&#13;
dependent variable is substantially above its actual value for Brazil, Greece,&#13;
Korea, Norway, and Taiwan. The opposite holds for Spain. These results&#13;
invite several observations. First, there are historical factors at play&#13;
which make shipping a major activity in Greece and Norway. Second, shipping&#13;
is an area of heavy protectionism affecting many economies. There is evidence&#13;
1/ The United States and Canada occupy an intermediate position.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
14&#13;
that both Brazil and Korea severely discriminate in favor of their fleets./&#13;
Third, a number of developing economies prefer to time-charter or lease&#13;
vessiels rather than to import shipping services. This has the effect of&#13;
artificially reducing freight figures, because chartering operations are&#13;
recorded under the item "other transportation" by the IMF. It is known that&#13;
Brazil and Korea have widely adopted this practice.2/ Finally, the mode of&#13;
transportation (by air, land, or sea) affects freight costs. Everything else&#13;
being the same, use of modes other than sea transportation incurs higher&#13;
costs. In our sub-sample of developing economies, Spain is the most likely to&#13;
do so since it is rather close to its main suppliers and is connected to them&#13;
by land. Despite these various unobservables, our regressions perform&#13;
surprisingly well. There is little doubt that the pattern of trade in freight&#13;
services is to a considerable extent shaped by the economic factors identified&#13;
by trade theories.&#13;
2. Passenger Services&#13;
Like the transportation of goods, the transportation of passengers&#13;
is likely to be a capital-intensive activity. Thus, we postulate that&#13;
comparative advantage in passenger services is related to an economy's&#13;
capital-labor ratio. International transportation of passengers can be either&#13;
by air, by ship, or by ground transportation. However, the airline industry&#13;
dominates the business. A given economy exports passenger services only to&#13;
the extent that foreign nationals travel on its carriers and purchase their&#13;
1/ See Sapir and Lutz (1980).&#13;
2/ Recent data show that about 40 percent of Brazil's foreign trade is&#13;
carried by chartered vessels.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
15&#13;
transportation titles abroad.L/ Similarly, it imports passenger services when&#13;
its nationals travel on foreign carriers. Because international arrangements&#13;
generally grant landing privileges on a reciprocal basis, airlines are&#13;
severely limited in the volume of cross-trades they can pick up2/&#13;
Consequently, domestic carriers will tend to transport passengers to and from&#13;
their home. Therefore, an economy where many foreigners come will be more&#13;
likely to export passenger services, and an economy where many nationals go&#13;
abroad will be more likely to import passenger services. For simplicity, we&#13;
proxy flows of passengers with flows of travel credits and debits and&#13;
hypothesize the existence of a relationship between the ratio of travel&#13;
credits to travel debits (TR) and comparative advantage in passenger services.&#13;
We expect to find a positive impact of KL and TR on the dependent&#13;
variable (PS) defined as the ratio of passenger services credit to passenger&#13;
services debit. The regression equation was estimated for a total sample of&#13;
31 economies and two sub-samples of 22 developing and 9 industrialized&#13;
economies, respectively. Estimates of the coefficients are reported in Table 2.2.&#13;
For the entire sample, the relative endowment in physical capital&#13;
and the travel balance appear to be two of the determinants of comparative&#13;
advantage in passenger services. For the developing economy sub-sample, the&#13;
same basic result prevails.1/    However, for the sub-sample of 9&#13;
Titles purchased in the country are classified by the IMF under the&#13;
"travel" item.&#13;
2/ Thus, even though a route between countries A and B might be attractive,&#13;
only rarely will carriers from C be allowed to fly it.&#13;
3/ The coefficient of the TR variable in equation 2 is significant at the&#13;
94.5 percent level (one-tail test).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
16&#13;
Table 2.2&#13;
REGRESSION EQUATIONS FOR PASSENGER SERVICES&#13;
quation     Department        Independent Variable a/         2       Sample&#13;
Number       Variable            KL             TR           R         Size&#13;
1           PS               44.90         0.20          0.25        31&#13;
1.92*        2.82**        4.72*&#13;
2           PS               82.24         0.13          0.30        22&#13;
2.29*        1.66          4.17*&#13;
3           PS               23.05         0.58          0.78        9&#13;
0.39         3.54**       10.76*&#13;
4            log(PS)          0.22         0.35          0.21        31&#13;
1.57         2.49**        3.67*&#13;
5            log(PS)          0.17         0.32          0.16        22&#13;
0.70          1.69         1.86&#13;
6           log(PS)          -0.10         0.52          0.51        9&#13;
0.10          1.70         3.09&#13;
Note: The equations were estimated with a constant which is not reported. A&#13;
* and a ** indicate 95 and 99 percent significance levels,&#13;
respectively, for the t-values (shown below the corresponding&#13;
regression coefficients) and for the F ratio (shown below the squared&#13;
multiple correlation coefficient).&#13;
a! The logarithm of the independent variables is used for the equations in&#13;
the lower panel.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
17&#13;
industrialized economies, the coefficient of KL is not significant and that of&#13;
TR is highly so. This might indicate that the impact of (restrictive)&#13;
international airlines arrangements affects the industrialized economies more&#13;
than the developing ones.&#13;
Turning now to the residuals of equations 2 and 3, we attempt to add&#13;
some insight to our results. The main observation concerns the fact that TR&#13;
is an imperfect proxy for the phenomenon it is intended to capture --&#13;
essentially because it ignores a location factor. Indeed, a problem arises:&#13;
there is not a one-to-one correspondence between tourists' expenditures in an&#13;
economy and their transportation costs to that economy. Thus, Australia,&#13;
Japan, and the United States have predicted values of the dependent variable&#13;
substantially above the actual values because their nationals usually spend&#13;
more on transportation when going abroad than do Europeans (who form the rest&#13;
of the sub-sample). Economies that attract tourists from relatively far away&#13;
have predicted values below the actual values. This is the case of Korea,&#13;
Malaysia, Portugal, and Turkey. In addition, protectionism constitutes a&#13;
distorting element that might account for some of the important gaps between&#13;
predicted and actual values of PS. Again, despite several factors that are&#13;
left unaccounted for, it is surprising (and reassuring) to find that our&#13;
theories perform so well.&#13;
3. Insurance Services&#13;
Insurance companies usually engage in two types of activity:&#13;
insurance and reinsurance. The first type is a retail activity that often&#13;
requires the company to maintain a service branch near its customers.1/&#13;
Therefore, except in the case of large and special types of risks, there is&#13;
/  See Carter and Dickinson (1979) for other reasons branches are required to&#13;
do insurance business.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
18&#13;
relatively little direct insurance placed internationally; that is, there are&#13;
few actual imports and exports of insurance services. On the contrary,&#13;
reinsurance is essentially a wholesale activity that enables insurance&#13;
companies to spread their risks and share them with other insurance firms.&#13;
Efficient operation of the reinsurance market involves substantial&#13;
international transactions.&#13;
What determines comparative advantage in (re)insurance services?&#13;
The essential element seems to be "a well-educated labor force, including a&#13;
whole range of professional expertise in financial, legal, and technical&#13;
subjects.'' 1/ Large amounts of financial capital constitute a necessary&#13;
condition for entry into the (re)insurance business, but very little physical&#13;
capital is needed. Comparative advantage is therefore linked to the&#13;
availability of human capital and the existence of a well-functioning&#13;
financial market. In addition, the volume of business constitutes an&#13;
important element of comparative advantage. Indeed, if the level of premium&#13;
receipts within a economy is small, there will be a relative lack of&#13;
opportunities to spread the risk, and insurers will be forced to reinsure&#13;
abroad most of the business they write. This phenomenon is frequent in&#13;
developing economies where the volume of business is typically low. We use&#13;
GDP to capture this size factor.&#13;
We expect both the human capital (PTR, EDS, or EDT) and the size&#13;
(GDP) variables to be positively related to the dependent variable defined as&#13;
the ratio of insurance services credit to insurance services debit. Separate&#13;
regression equations were estimated for merchandise insurance (INM),&#13;
non-merchandise insurance (INN), and total insurance (INT). All equations&#13;
I/ See Carter and Dickinson (1979), pp. 44-45.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
19&#13;
were fitted over a total sample including both developing and industrialized&#13;
economies. The size was too small to regress over sub-samples. Estimates of&#13;
the coefficients are reported in Table 2.3.&#13;
Equations 6, 11, and 18 indicate that human capital and scale i/ are&#13;
indeed among the factors that determine comparative advantage in insurance&#13;
services. Total and non-merchandise insurance seem to be relatively intensive&#13;
in the use of third-level graduates, while merchandise insurance appears to&#13;
require relatively more second-level graduates. Unexpectedly, these two&#13;
indexes of human capital performed much better than the measure of&#13;
professional, technical, and related workers in the labor force.&#13;
Protectionist measures will boost the export-import ratios, either&#13;
by reducing imports or increasing exports. Foreign firms might be allowed to&#13;
do business in an economy if they agree to "reciprocate good conduct" and to&#13;
reinsure some of their foreign business in that economy. Alternatively, an&#13;
economy might operate a state-owned reinsurance company, which takes enough&#13;
business on the international reinsurance market to command "reciprocal&#13;
favors." And, indeed, most economies listed by Carter and Dickinson (1979,&#13;
Table 4, pp. 72-73) as having state-owned insurance companies exhibit&#13;
predicted values of the dependent variable greater than actual ones in&#13;
equations 6, 11, and 18. This is the case for Algeria, India, Italy, Morocco,&#13;
New Zealand, Peru, and the Philippines.&#13;
/  The coefficient of log (GDP) in equation 6 is significant at the 91&#13;
percent level (one-tail test).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
20&#13;
Table 2.3&#13;
REGRESSION EQUATIONS FOR INSURANCE SERVICES&#13;
Equation   Dependent           Independent Variables at                    Sample&#13;
Number     Variable         CDP     PTR      EDS       EDT       R         Size&#13;
1         INT            0.75     8.38      -        -        0.28         13&#13;
1.90*   0.69       -        -        1.99&#13;
2          INT           0.37      -        -       22.96     0.46         13&#13;
0.95     -         -       1.97*     4.25*&#13;
3          INT           0.58      -       3.25       -       0.33         10&#13;
1.55     -        1.06      -        1.74&#13;
4          JUT           0.54      -       3.19      3.26     0.33         10&#13;
0.98     -        0.96     0.13      1.00&#13;
5          log(INT)      0.28     0.21      -         -       0.59         13&#13;
3.36**  1.17       -        -        7.16*&#13;
6          log(INT)      0.13      -        -        0.42     0.72         13&#13;
1.46     -         -       2.55*    12.66**&#13;
7          log(INT)      0.25      -       0.17       -       0.42         10&#13;
2.22*    -        0.75      -        2.56&#13;
8          log(INT)      0.34      -       0.23    -0.38      0.45         10&#13;
1.59     -        0.86     0.50      1.61&#13;
9          INM           0.90    15.98      -         -       0.24         23&#13;
2.10*   1.17       -        -        3.21&#13;
10        INM            0.36      -        -      27.63      0.37         24&#13;
0.80     -         -       2.51**    6.23**&#13;
11        INM            0.74      -       5.54      -        0.38         20&#13;
1.73*    -        2.18*     -        5.23*&#13;
12        INN            0.66      -       4.81      5.20     0.38         20&#13;
1.17     -        1.21     0.24      3.31*&#13;
13        log(INM)       0.92    -2.57      -         -       0.12.        23&#13;
1.19    1.52       -        -         -&#13;
14        log(INM)       0.82      -        -      -0.81      0.04         24&#13;
0.90     -         -       0.66      0.41&#13;
15        log(INM)       0.67      -      -0.92      -        0.04         20&#13;
0.73     -        0.50      -        0.31&#13;
16        log(INM)       1.37      -       1.23    -2.07      0.07         20&#13;
1.03     -        0.35     0.73       -&#13;
17        INN            0.68     6.94      -        -        0.24         23&#13;
2.36*   0.80       -        -        3.23&#13;
18        INN            0.48      -        -       13.11     0.40        23&#13;
1.76*    -         -       2.44**    6.63**&#13;
19        INN            0.60      -       2.30      -        0.31        20&#13;
2.12*    -        1.35,     -        3.91*&#13;
20         INN           0.50      -       1.40      7.99     0.36         20&#13;
1.72*    -        0.74     1.09      3.03&#13;
21        log(INN)       0.10     0.14      -         -       0.25         23&#13;
2.02*   1.08       -        -        3.27&#13;
22         log(INN)      0.07      -        -       0.17      0.29        23&#13;
1.35     -         -       1.58     4.11*&#13;
23         log(INN)      0.13      -       0.05      -        0.28        20&#13;
2.40*    -        0.32      -        3.37&#13;
24        log(INN)       0.11     -        0.01     0.12      0.30        20&#13;
1.91*    -        0.09     0.67     2.33&#13;
Note:  The equations were estimated with a constant which is not reported.     A&#13;
* and a ** indicate 95 and 99 percent significance levels, respectively, for&#13;
the t-values (shown below the corresponding regression coefficients) and for&#13;
the F ratio (shown below the squared multiple correlation coefficient).&#13;
The logarithm of the independent variables is used for the equations in the&#13;
lower panel.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
21&#13;
C. Conclusions&#13;
The results from the regressions clearly indicate that conventional&#13;
trade theories can go a long way in explaining trade patterns in services.&#13;
Despite the protectionism from which trade in services suffers, a number of&#13;
economic factors do, indeed, emerge as determinants of comparative&#13;
advantage. On the one hand, performance in transportation services (freight&#13;
and passenger services) appears to be related to capital abundance. For&#13;
insurance services, performance seems, on the other hand, to hinge upon the&#13;
availability of human capital.i/ Location and economies of scale are also&#13;
important in certain instances. These findings indicate that economies that&#13;
are abundant in physical and human capital have a comparative advantage in&#13;
services.&#13;
The fact that differences in trade patterns among economies reflect&#13;
differences in factor endowments lends support to the "stages approach" to&#13;
comparative advantage recently put forward by Balassa (1979) for manufactured&#13;
goods. Indeed, it would suggest that, as developing economies accumulate&#13;
human and physical capital, they will gain comparative advantage in certain&#13;
types of services. However, one suspects that industrialized economies will&#13;
generally retain their prominence in services trade thanks to their&#13;
technological lead and their abundance of physical and human capital.&#13;
I/ Human capital also seems to be the main determinant for trade in total&#13;
private services (including non-merchandise insurance services). However,&#13;
since they represent such a heterogeneous collection of services, the&#13;
empirical results are not presented here. The lack of detailed data&#13;
prevents an estimation of determinants for the various sub-categories of&#13;
total private services such as consultant/engineering services,&#13;
construction services, banking services, management services, etc.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
22&#13;
Comparative advantage need not be the same in multilateral and&#13;
bilateral trades.-/ Thus, developing economies at the upper end of the&#13;
spectrum -- that is, the newly industrializing economies (NICs) -- can at the&#13;
same time be net importers of services overall and net exporters of services&#13;
to other developing economies. Indeed, this group seems to have a dualistic&#13;
export structure: exporting (physical) capital and skill intensively to less&#13;
developed economies (LDCs) and products that have been produced by unskilled&#13;
labor intensively to more developed economies.2/&#13;
See Yoo (1978).&#13;
2/ This structure is readily observable for manufactured goods.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
23&#13;
III. THE ROLE OF SERVICES IN THE DEVELOPMENT PROCESS&#13;
In the previous chapter, we found that abundance in physical and&#13;
human capital determines comparative advantage in services trade. This result&#13;
may in part explain why the United States has taken the lead in recent efforts&#13;
to liberalize trade (as well as foreign investment) in services, a lead that&#13;
the other members of the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and&#13;
Development (OECD) are following with great care. 'Among the developing&#13;
economies, only a few, those relatively well-endowed with capital, have shown&#13;
signs of interest in the service issue.&#13;
The purpose of this chapter is to show that, quite apart from the&#13;
comparative advantage question, services play a vital role in the growth&#13;
process and should, therefore, be of concern for the developing economies. In&#13;
section A, we will argue that a strong relationship exists between services&#13;
and the concepts of infrastructure and technology transfer, which give to&#13;
services their major importance. In section B, we analyze the pattern of&#13;
trade in capital goods and hypothesize a complementarity between trade in&#13;
technology-related services and trade in capital goods.&#13;
A. Services, Infrastructure, and Technology Transfer&#13;
The services that give rise to international transactions are, for&#13;
the most part, producer rather than consumer services. Indeed, with some&#13;
limited exceptions, services are traded in response to an intermediate rather&#13;
than to a final demand. Viewed in this fashion, services can be seen as&#13;
providing an essential link among economic agents, both domestically and&#13;
internationally, that enables the interdependent functioning of domestic and&#13;
world markets. In other words, many services (banking, communications,&#13;
transportation, etc.) are in fact services of infrastructure industries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
24&#13;
Nearly four decades ago, Rosenstein-Rodan (1943) stated that&#13;
infrastructure industries must be given priority during the early phase of&#13;
industrialization. His strategy thus called for a "big push" toward "balanced&#13;
growth" among various sectors of an economy .1 Although the discussion of&#13;
infrastructure by Rosenstein-Rodan was essentially limited to the closed-&#13;
economy case, the same theme was recently put forward in contributions to the&#13;
open-economy development literature. Thus, Little et al. (1970) and Baldwin&#13;
(1978) emphasize that the level and quality of the services of infrastructure&#13;
industries are among the main factors that determine the degree of success of&#13;
trade and development policies. They insist that, in some economies, the&#13;
development of various sectors has been handicapped by underprovision of&#13;
services.&#13;
Among the infrastructure industries, an important distinction can be&#13;
made according to the nature of investment they require. At one end of the&#13;
spectrum, the investment is essentially in physical capital (communications&#13;
and transportation). At the other end, the investment is mostly in human&#13;
capital (financial, professional, and technical services).Z! Although both&#13;
types of service industries require capital in their operation, only the first&#13;
one calls for social overhead capital.-' Except for the services of overhead&#13;
capital industries, which are characterized by externalities, economies of&#13;
scale, and immobility, the provision of serviees can be obtained either from&#13;
/  For a discussion, see Datta-Chaudhuri (1980).&#13;
2/ Although it would be convenient to deal only with the two polar cases,&#13;
there are, obviously, cases of infrastructure industries located in the&#13;
middle of the spectrum (e.g., education and health).&#13;
3/ Transportation requires not only trucks and ships but also roads or ports.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
25&#13;
domestic or foreign firms. In the case of services requiring human capital,&#13;
acquisition from abroad often represents a form of technology transfer.&#13;
According to Stewart (1979), "technology is knowledge - knowledge of&#13;
how to do and make useful things" (p. 1). Technology is transferred in&#13;
various forms, which can be classified as either direct or indirect&#13;
mechanisms. The former type (also sometimes referred to as "united" or&#13;
"unpackaged") includes:&#13;
a.   Services of consultants&#13;
b.   Services of construction and engineering firms&#13;
c.   Training of manpower abroad&#13;
d.   Capital goods.&#13;
The later type of transfer (also called "tied" or "packaged") consists of:&#13;
a.   Foreign direct investments&#13;
b.   License and patent agreements.&#13;
Thus, a number of services represent direct mechanisms of technology&#13;
transfer. Therefore, although the type of transfer mechanism itself depends&#13;
upon the industry and economy involved,i/ international transactions in these&#13;
services can probably be explained by the theories of foreign direct&#13;
investment recently put forward.2/&#13;
A number of economic and non-economic arguments can be made in favor&#13;
of indigenous production of infrastructure and technology services:&#13;
externalities, the need for suitable products and services and for appropriate&#13;
technology, and independence. It is easy to share these arguments, but harder&#13;
1/ See Stewart (1979), pp. 11-19.&#13;
2/ A recent survey of these theories is Dunning (1979).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
26&#13;
to agree on a strategy to achieve the goal of local production. The solution&#13;
recommended here consists of two elements:&#13;
a.   An economy-wide effort aimed at raising the level and quality of&#13;
infrastructure and technical skill&#13;
b.   A selective policy toward import of services.&#13;
These two elements should be put into action simultaneously to reinforce each&#13;
other.&#13;
The above prescription follows the successful Japanese example,&#13;
which has also been adopted by Korea. Recently, Pursell and Rhee (1978) have&#13;
used a firm-level survey in order to analyze the role played by technology in&#13;
the export-oriented Korean development strategy.L/ Some of their findings are&#13;
worth summarizing here:&#13;
a.   The economy has made a large effort to train its labor force,&#13;
both by setting up institutes at home and by sending nationals&#13;
to study or work abroad.&#13;
b.   For the most part, the acquisition of foreign technology has&#13;
taken place through direct transfer mechanisms. Moreover,&#13;
Korea has concentrated its research and development effort in&#13;
industries for which it has a comparative advantage.&#13;
c.   The previous two characteristics have allowed for rapid rates&#13;
of technological learning. In the field of services, the major&#13;
example of technological learning consists of construction and&#13;
engineering services which Korea has been exporting on a large&#13;
scale to the Middle East since 1973.!' Part of this learning&#13;
1/ See also Westphal, Rhee, and Pursell (1980).&#13;
2/ Asian Finance of July 15, 1980, reports that Korea has won 9.3% of Middle&#13;
East construction/engineering contracts in 1979-80.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
27&#13;
process was acquired through involvement in United States&#13;
military construction projects.&#13;
It is not surprising that developing economies are generally running&#13;
a deficit on services trade. Nor is this deficit necessarily a cause for&#13;
alarm. Rather it might be an encouraging sign that other sectors are being&#13;
expanded, requiring infrastructure and technology services. For instance, the&#13;
role of services in developing infrastructure and transferring technology is&#13;
seen in the large imports of services by economies in their early stage of&#13;
natural resource exploitation. Indeed, it is very much the same phenomenon&#13;
that caused the companies of the early British and Dutch colonial period to&#13;
engage in activities such as banking, trade, and transport, and which has&#13;
induced Norway to increase sharply its imports of various consultant services&#13;
associated with oil and gas activities.&#13;
However, developing economies should be able to compete effectively&#13;
in world markets as providers of services for which the progressive import-&#13;
substituting development strategy outlined above has been followed. In view&#13;
of the remarks made above, this possibility should essentially apply to&#13;
exports from the NICs to other developing economies. In this respect, Stewart&#13;
(1979) indicates that the process of technology transfer among developing&#13;
economies (often via services trade) is well engaged for a handful of them&#13;
(for example, Argentina, India, Korea, and Taiwan).&#13;
B. Trade in Capital Goods&#13;
As we have noted earlier, the category "other services" used in&#13;
chapter II constitutes a heterogeneous collection of items. Some of these&#13;
items are technology-related services, which the available data do not permit&#13;
us to isolate from unrelated services.&#13;
However, international transactions in technology-related services&#13;
are likely to be related to trade in capital goods, since both constitute&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
28&#13;
However, international transactions in technology-related services&#13;
are likely to be related to trade in capital goods, since both constitute&#13;
direct mechanisms of technology transfer. Thus, one can hope to learn&#13;
something about trade in these services by examining readily available data on&#13;
capital-goods trade. Using the definition of capital goods shown in Table A.3&#13;
of the appendix, United Nations data for 1975 were assembled to form the trade&#13;
matrix in Table 3.1 11 Some interesting findings that emerge from the table&#13;
are:&#13;
a.   Trade among developed economies accounts for 45.7 percent of&#13;
world trade; trade among developing economies accounts for 2.4&#13;
percent; and trade between the two groups for 31.0.&#13;
b.   Although developing economies as a whole acquire 6.7 percent of&#13;
their imports of capital goods from other developing economies,&#13;
this proportion is 3.6 percent for the NICs and 8.1 percent for&#13;
the other developing economies.&#13;
c.   Although the NICs have an overall deficit in capital goods,&#13;
they have a surplus with their partners in the developing&#13;
world.&#13;
d.   The developing-economy markets account for about 50 percent of&#13;
the NICs' exports of capital goods to the world.&#13;
In summary, the industrialized economies dominate the world exports&#13;
of capital goods, with the developing economies providing a large import&#13;
market. Also, developing economies acquire their capital-goods imports mostly&#13;
from the industrialized world, but low-income developing economies import a&#13;
sizable share of capital goods from their partners in the developing world --&#13;
essentially the NICs.&#13;
j/ Generous help was provided by Oli Havrylyshyn in this process.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
29&#13;
Table 3.1&#13;
TRADE IN CAPITAL GOODS, 1975&#13;
(in billions of US$)&#13;
Value of Imports from Source to:&#13;
Source of                      Other      All    All      LDCs &amp;    Other&#13;
Exports             NICs a/     LDCs      LDCs   DCs       DCs     Economies      World&#13;
NICs                 0.5         2.1      2.6     1.9      4.5          0.8        5.3&#13;
Other LDCs           0.2         1.1      1.3    0.9       2.2         0.2         2.4&#13;
All LDCs             0.7         3.2      3.9    2.8       6.7          1.0        7.7&#13;
All Developed&#13;
Economies (DCs)   17.8        33.3     51.1   75.4     126.5        23.8       150.3&#13;
LDCs and DCs        18.5        36.5     55.0   78.2     133.2         24.8      158.0&#13;
Other Economies      0.8         3.2      4.0    1.2       5.2          1.8        7.0&#13;
World               19.3        39.7     59.0   79.4     138.4        26.6       165.0&#13;
a   The NICs include Argentina, Brazil, Greece, Hong Kong, Israel, Korea, Mexico,&#13;
Portugal, Singapore, Spain, and Yugoslavia. Taiwan is not included in the table.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
30&#13;
Moreover, additional data indicate that capital goods have become an&#13;
important export item for the NICs. Indeed, in 1975, capital goods&#13;
represented about 40 percent of their manufactured exports to developing-&#13;
economy partners and 13 percent of equivalent exports to industrialized&#13;
partners.-/&#13;
Clearly both high- and low-income developing economies acquire most&#13;
of their capital goods from the industrialized world. In exchange for these&#13;
(physical and human) capital-intensive goods, developing economies export&#13;
mostly labor-intensive manufactures to the rich economies. However, the NICs&#13;
also export large amounts of capital goods to low-income developing&#13;
economies. This indicates again that, besides the transfer of technology that&#13;
takes place from the North to the South, there is some degree of transfer from&#13;
the rich South to the poor South, presumably resulting, in part, from the&#13;
adoption of technology previously acquired from the North.&#13;
/  Obviously, the type of capital goods may differ in each case.    For further and&#13;
insightful remarks on capital goods trade, see Havrylyshyn and Wolf (1981).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
31&#13;
IV. SUMMARY OF FINDINGS&#13;
1. Conventional trade theory applies not only to goods but also to services.&#13;
Despite protectionism, from which trade in services suffers, a number of&#13;
economic factors do, indeed, emerge as determinants of comparative&#13;
advantage.&#13;
2.  The main factors shaping comparative advantage in services trade are the&#13;
availability of physical and human capital.&#13;
3. Although the industrialized economies, with their abundance of physical&#13;
and human capital, usually enjoy a strong competitive edge in services&#13;
trades, developing economies that are successful in accumulating capital&#13;
have good prospects for exporting services. Nevertheless, for most&#13;
developing economies, emphasizing the export of services does not appear&#13;
to be a realistic prospect.&#13;
4. Because many services depend on the development of infrastructure or&#13;
technological capacities, the acquisition of such services will often be a&#13;
precondition for economic growth. This acquisition will have a dynamic&#13;
impact on trade by changing capital availability. Acquisition of services&#13;
can be done either through imports or local production. Presumably,&#13;
imports will generally be necessary, but several arguments favor&#13;
progressive import substitution.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
32&#13;
APPENDIX: INPUT DATA FOR THE EMPIRICAL ANALYSIS&#13;
AND FOR THE DEFINITION OF CAPITAL GOODS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
33&#13;
Table A.1:&#13;
FIRST SET OF INPUT DATA USED FOR ECONOMETRIC ANALYSIS, 1977&#13;
ECONOMY               DIS    EDS      EDT      FR      GDP      INM      INN      INT&#13;
Algeria              0     38.2      3.2   104.5     19554    0.19     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Ivory Coast          0     17.6      1.3     n.a.    6265     n.a.     n.a.    n.a.&#13;
Kenya                0     44.6      1.7   144.9     4590     0.63     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Morocco              0     30.8      2.6   133.4    10397     0.09     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Nigeria              0      7.6      0.4   121.6    40104     0.04     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Senegal              0      n.a.     1.6     n.a.    1944     n.a.     n.a.    n.a.&#13;
Sudan                0     20.4      1.3   135.3     6005     0.20     n.a.    n.a.&#13;
Tunisia              0     41.2      4.1     n.a.    5007     n.a.     0.50     n.a.&#13;
Israel               0      n.a.    22.1    27.3    14703     0.91     0.74     0.75&#13;
Egypt                0     58.4     12.6   102.5    13245     n.a.     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Sri Lanka            0      n.a.     1.1   116.7     2691     0.08     0.47    0.14&#13;
Taiwan               0      n.a.     n.a.   48.3    21497     0.45     n.a.     0.33&#13;
India                1      n.a.     5.3   109.0   104110     0.55     0.34     0.47&#13;
Indonesia            0     29.8      2.2   138.3    45175     n.a.     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Korea                0    102.3      9.4    37.7    35377     0.81     0.93     0.91&#13;
Malaysia             1      n.a.     3.2     n.a.   13108     n.a.     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Pakistan             1     28.9      1.6   107.9     15096    0.17     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Philippines          0     55.6     18.1   102.7    20985     n.a.     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Singapore            0     84.4     10.2    68.3     6542     0.35     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Thailand             1     30.4      3.2   131.4    19265     0.15     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Argentina            0     52.2     24.4     n.a.   52121     n.a.     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Bolivia              0     26.2     10.6   122.8     3442     n.a.     0.62     n.a.&#13;
Brazil               0      15.3    12.0    37.9   164163     0.62     0.73     0.71&#13;
Chile                0     47.7     12.9     n.a.    n.a.     n.a.     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Colombia             0     68.5      7.9     n.a.   19459     n.a.     0.67     n.a.&#13;
Ecuador              0     62.5     24.7     n.a.    6456     n.a.     0.77     n.a.&#13;
Mexico               0     54.7      9.1     n.a.   74191     n.a.     0.86     n.a.&#13;
Peru                 0     62.6     15.0     n.a.    12554    n.a.     0.39     n.a.&#13;
Uruguay              0      n.a.    11.6     n.a.     4194    n.a.     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Venezuela            0     49.9     19.6     n.a.   35596     n.a.     0.87     n.a.&#13;
United States        0     95.3     52.4     n.a. 1878880     n.a.     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
United Kingdom       0     89.2     12.6     n.a.  244500     n.a.     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Austria              0    102.5     14.0    35.9    47952     1.00     0.84     0.85&#13;
Belgium              0     86.8     16.3    40.6    79205     0.51     0.92     0.87&#13;
Denmark              0     57.9     21.7     n.a.   46016     n.a.     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
France               0     93.7     19.7    42.4   380653     1.74     0.95     1.15&#13;
Germany              0     63.3     13.5    35.2   516194     0.48     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Italy                0     90.6     17.5    63.1   194045     0.74     0.68     0.70&#13;
Netherlands          0     97.5     21.1    61.3   102585     n.a.     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Norway               0     82.4     16.7     9.9     35592    n.a.     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Sweden               0     64.9     19.9    45.7     78266    0.41     0.49     0.46&#13;
Switzerland          0     69.3     10.1    21.5    60591     n.a.     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Canada               0     113.1    35.8     n.a.   200244    n.a.      1.16    n.a.&#13;
Japan                1      82.9    21.1    45.9    691140    0.65      0.98    0.91&#13;
Finland              0      91.6    16.4    59.8     30167    n.a.     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Greece               0     75.0     12.3    47.5     26239    n.a.      0.29    n.a.&#13;
Portugal             0     80.0      8.4    72.6     16255    0.15      0.46    0.25&#13;
Spain                0     89.6     15.2    39.0    116249    0.51     0.91     0.73&#13;
Turkey               0      n.a.     8.1   127.3     47789    0.28      n.a.    n.a.&#13;
Yugoslavia           0    108.3     18.5     n.a.   45524     n.a.     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Australia            1     82.5     20.4   115.5    100063    n.a.     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
New Zealand          1    116.9    .24.4   101.8     14212    n.a.     0.63     n.a.&#13;
n.a. Not available.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
34&#13;
Table A.2&#13;
SECOND SET OF INPUT DATA USED FOR ECONOMETRIC ANALYSIS, 1977&#13;
ECONOMY               KL      M        MM      OS      PS      PTR       RD      TR&#13;
Algeria            49.1     5.31   77.3      n.a.    0.22    3.4       0.81    0.18&#13;
Ivory Coast        24.9     1.30   72.2     0.14     n.a.    n.a.     0.81     n.a.&#13;
Kenya              16.9     0.96   67.6     n.a      1.23    n.a.      3.14    6.44&#13;
Morocco             8.9     2.40   63.8      n.a.    1.09    4.0       n.a.    3.49&#13;
Nigeria             6.7     8.28   83.4      n.a.    0.16    n.a.      0.84    0.15&#13;
Senegal             8.4     0.60    n.a.    n.a.     n.a.    n.a.     n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Sudan              10.4     0.55    n.a.    n.a.     n.a.    2.5       1.73    n.a.&#13;
Tunisia            20.0     1.37   68.3      n.a.    1.29    4.4       n.a.    5.31&#13;
Israel            282.8     4.74   65.2     0.83     3.12   19.1      10.11    2.49&#13;
Egypt              10.5     3.52   64.8      n.a.    n.a.    4.4       5.70    n.a.&#13;
Sri Lanka           4.8     0.55   33.0     n.a.     1.15    4.0      2.37     9.33&#13;
Taiwan             19.3     7.11   57.4      0.87    n.a.   *5.5       n.a.    n.a.&#13;
India               4.0     5.30   43.3      1.48    n.a.    2.7      4.31     n.a.&#13;
Indonesia           8.4     6.40   66.9     n.a.     n.a.    2.1      n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Korea              32.3     9.01   52.4      n.a.    3.29    3.1       6.32    3.60&#13;
Malaysia           18.7     3.82   63.7      n.a.    1.44    4.5      n.a.     0.59&#13;
Pakistan            4.5     2.13   59.6      n.a.    n.a.    3.0      0.99     n.a.&#13;
Philippines        16.2     3.35   59.2      0.74    0.11    5.3       1.54    4.13&#13;
Singapore          54.1     8.29   53.5     n.a.     n.a.    9.5      0.32     n.a.&#13;
Thailand           10.8     3.63   63.4      1.14    0.55    2.6       n.a.    1.44&#13;
Argentina           5.9     3.25   68.8      n.a.    0.88    7.5       2.97    1.21&#13;
Bolivia             8.4     0.55    n.a.     0.48    0.69    5.9      n.a.     0.78&#13;
Brazil             27.9    10.30   52.2      0.57    0.22    4.8       1.06    0.24&#13;
Chile               0.4     1.68    n.a.     n.a.    n.a.    7.1      n.a.     n.a.&#13;
Colombia           14.6     1.69   73.6      n.a.    1.57    4.5       0.54    1.25&#13;
Ecuador            11.4     1.65   87.1      n.a.    0.64    5.2       1.60    0.70&#13;
Mexico             35.4     4.49   79.6      n.a.    0.84    6.2       n.a.    1.79&#13;
Peru               10.7     1.85   64.4      n.a.    0.44    7.4       2.03    3.10&#13;
Uruguay             0.5     0.58   50.7      n.a.    n.a.    7.2       0.85    n.a.&#13;
Venezuela          64.8     8.86   83.6      n.a.    n.a.    8.6       0.64    n.a.&#13;
United States     193.9   129.90   52.3      n.a.    0.50   14.7       n.a.    0.83&#13;
United Kingdom     96.0    50.64   56.5      n.a.    1.97   11.1       3.92    1.98&#13;
Austria           134.3    11.7    73.3      n.a.    n.a.    9.5       2.13    n.a.&#13;
Belgium           142.1    29.41   62.7      1.81    0.91   11.1       8.11    0.62&#13;
Denmark           173.5    10.90   64.0      n.a.    n.a.   12.2       5.94    n.a.&#13;
France            168.8    54.73   55.0      1.61    n.a.   11.4      16.06    n.a.&#13;
Germany           171.6    80.94   56.2      0.83    0.90    9.8      18.08    0.35&#13;
Italy              78.4    37.70   42.4      1.24    3.43    7.3      8.29     5.33&#13;
Netherlands       137.7    34.15   58.1      1.35    n.a.   13.4      18.30    n.a.&#13;
Norway            206.7    11.36   76.1      0.58    n.a.   15.8      12.14    n.a.&#13;
Sweden            217.0    15.98   67.6     0.89     1.61   22.9     15.80     0.35&#13;
Switzerland       233.2    15.15   72.1     n.a.     n.a.   12.1     22.20     n.a.&#13;
Canada            184.2    34.46   76.9     n.a.     n.a.   14.0      8.50     n.a.&#13;
Japan             124.7    53.12   18.8     0.66     0.41    7.1      16.20    0.20&#13;
Finland           147.8     6.07   60.4      1.08    1.70   16.9      10.69    0.99&#13;
Greece             62.2     4.87   68.2     n.a.     0.11    5.7       1.81    5.99&#13;
Portugal           23.5     3.88   54.0      1.03    2.21    3.6      2.61     2.97&#13;
Spain              60.4    14.18   43.0     0.70     4.07    5.5      2.32     7.78&#13;
Turkey             15.6     4.42   67.1     n.a.     1.58    4.0      7.52     0.77&#13;
Yugoslavia         57.0     7.03   66.1      n.a.    n.a.    7.6      7.47     n.a.&#13;
Australia         165.8    10.44   78.7     n.a.     0.41   10.1      9.34     0.61&#13;
New Zealand         n.a.    2.42   71.5     n.a.     n.a.   14.4      8.55     n.a.&#13;
n.a. Not available.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
35&#13;
Table A.3: DEFINITION OF CAPITAL GOODS&#13;
Standard International Trade Classification&#13;
(SITC) Rev. 1 Codes&#13;
692&#13;
695                 minus 695.24&#13;
698.2&#13;
71                  minus 717.3, 719.4&#13;
722&#13;
723&#13;
724.91&#13;
724.92&#13;
726&#13;
731&#13;
732                 minus 732.1, 723.8, 732.9&#13;
733                 minus 733.1, 733.4&#13;
812.1&#13;
821.02&#13;
861.3               minus 861.31&#13;
861.7&#13;
861.8&#13;
861.9&#13;
864.2&#13;
894.5&#13;
895.11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
36&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
Asian Finance, July 15, 1980.&#13;
Balassa, B. 1979. "A Stages Approach to Comparative Advantage," in Economic&#13;
Growth and Resources, vol.4, ed. I. Adelman. London: Macmillan.&#13;
Baldwin, R. B. 1971. "Determinants of the Commodity Structure of U.S. Trade."&#13;
American Economic Review (March).&#13;
. 1978, "International Resource Flows and Patterns of Trade and&#13;
Development." Indian Economic Review (April).&#13;
. 1979. "Determinants of Trade and Foreign Investment: Further&#13;
Evidence." Review of Economics and Statistics (February).&#13;
Branson, W. H., and N. Monoyios. 1977. "Factor Inputs in U.S. Trade." Journal&#13;
of International Economics (May).&#13;
Carter, R. L., and G. M. Dickinson. 1979. Barriers to Trade in Insurance.&#13;
Thames Essay, no.19. London: Trade Policy Research Center.&#13;
Chenery, H. B. 1960. "Patterns of Industrial Growth." American Economic Review&#13;
(September).&#13;
Datta-Chaudhuri, M. 1980. "Infrastructure and Location," in Policies for&#13;
Industrial Progress in Developing Countries, ed. J. Cody et al. Oxford:&#13;
Oxford University Press.&#13;
Diab, M. A. 1956. The United States Capital Position and the Structure of Its&#13;
Foreign Trade. Amsterdam.&#13;
Dreze, J. 1960. "Quelques Reflexions Sereines sur l'Adaptation de l'Industrie&#13;
Belge au Marche Commun," Comptes Rendus des Travaux de la Societe Royale&#13;
d'Economie Politique de Belgigue (December).&#13;
Dunning, J. H. 1979. "Explaining Changing Patterns of International&#13;
Production: In Defence of the Eclectic Theory." Oxford Bulletin of&#13;
Economics and Statistics (November).&#13;
Harkness, J., and J. Kyle. 1975, "Factors Influencing United States&#13;
Comparative Advantage." Journal of International Economics (May).&#13;
Havrylyshyn, O., and M. Wolf. 1981. "Trade among Developing Countries: Theory,&#13;
Policy Issues, and Principal Trends." World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
no.479. Washington, D.C.: World Bank (August).&#13;
Hufbauer, G. C. 1966. Synthetic Materials and the Theory of International&#13;
Trade. London: Duckworth.&#13;
. 1970. "The Impact of National Characteristics and Technology&#13;
on the Commodity Composition of Trade in Manufactured Goods," in The&#13;
Technology Factor in Foreign Trade, ed. R. Vernon. New York: National&#13;
Bureau of Economic Research, distributed by Columbia University Press.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
37&#13;
International Labour Office. 1979. ILO Yearbook of Labor Statistics, 1979.&#13;
Geneva.&#13;
Keesing, D. B. 1965. "Labor Skills and International Trade: Evaluating Many&#13;
Trade Flows with a Single Measuring Device." Review of Economics and&#13;
Statistics (August).&#13;
. 1968. "Population and Industrial Development:   Some Evidence&#13;
from Trade Patterns." American Economic Review (June).&#13;
Kenen, P. B. 1965. "Nature, Capital, and Trade." Journal of Political Economy&#13;
(October).&#13;
Kravis, I. 1956. "Wages and Foreign Trade." Review of Economics and Statistics&#13;
(February).&#13;
Leamer, E. E. 1974. "The Commodity Composition of International Trade in&#13;
Manufactures: An Empirical Analysis." Oxford Economic Papers (November).&#13;
Leontief, W. 1953. "Domestic Production and Foreign Trade: The American&#13;
Capital Position Re-examined." Proceedings of the American Philosophical&#13;
Society (September).&#13;
Little, I., et al. 1970. Industry and Trade in Some Developing Countries: A&#13;
Comparative Study. Oxford: Oxford University Press.&#13;
Pursell, G. and Y. W. Rhee. 1978. "A Firm-Level Study of Korean Export&#13;
Technology." Washington, D.C.: World Bank (December). Internal&#13;
circulation only.&#13;
Rosenstein-Rodan, P. N. 1943. "Problems of Industrialization of Eastern and&#13;
South-Eastern Europe." Economic Journal (June-September).&#13;
Sapir, A., and E. Lutz. 1980. Trade in Non-Factor Services: Past Trends and&#13;
Current Issues. World Bank Staff Working Paper, no. 410. Washington,&#13;
D.C.: World Bank (August).&#13;
Stern, R. M. 1975. "Testing Trade Theories," in International Trade and&#13;
Finance, ed. P. B. Kenen. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.&#13;
. 1976. "Some Evidence on the Factor Content of West Germany's&#13;
Foreign Trade." Journal of Political Economy (February).&#13;
Stewart, F. 1979. International Technology Transfer: Issues and Policy&#13;
Options. World Bank Staff Working Paper, no.344. Washington, D.C.: World&#13;
Bank.&#13;
UNESCO. 1980. UNESCO Statistical Yearbook, 1978/79. Paris.&#13;
Vanek, J. 1963. The Natural Resource Content of United States Foreign Trade,&#13;
1870-1955.  Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press.&#13;
Vernon, R. 1966. "International Investment and International Trade in the&#13;
Product Cycle." Quarterly Journal of Economics (May).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
38&#13;
Westphal, L., Y. W. Rhee, and G. Pursell. 1980, "Korean Industrial&#13;
Competence: Where It Came From." Washington, D.C.: World Bank&#13;
(December). Internal circulation only.&#13;
Yoo, J. 1978. "The Heckscher-Ohlin Theorem and U.S. Trade in Manufactured&#13;
Commodities." Ph.D. thesis. University of Wisconsin, Madison.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
COMPANION PAPERS IN THIS SERIES&#13;
No.                           TITLE OF PAPER                          AUTHOR&#13;
449     Policy Experience in Twelve Less Developed Countries        B. Balassa&#13;
470     Industrial Country Policy and Adjustment to Imports         J.M. Finger&#13;
from Developing Countries&#13;
471     The Political Structure of the New Protectionism            D. Nelson (consultant)&#13;
472     Adjustment to External Shocks in Developing Countries       B. Balassa&#13;
473     Food Policy Issues in Low-Income Countries                  E. Clay (consultant)&#13;
474     Energy, International Trade, and Economic Growth            A. Manne (consultant)&#13;
475     Capital-Importing Oil Exporters: Adjustment Issues          A.H. Gelb&#13;
and Policy Choices&#13;
476     Notes on the Analysis of Capital Flows to Developing        R.C. Bryant (consultant)&#13;
Nations and the 'Recycling' Problem&#13;
477     Adjustment Experience and Growth Prospects of the           F. Jaspersen&#13;
Semi-Industrial Countries&#13;
478     Trade Policy Issues for the Developing Countries            I. Frank (consultant)&#13;
in the 1980s&#13;
479     Trade among Developing Countries: Theory, Policy            0. Havrylyshyn&#13;
Issues, and Principal Trends                                   (consultant)&#13;
M. Wolf&#13;
480     Trade in Services:  Economic Determinants and               A. Sapir (consultant)&#13;
Development-Related Issues                                  E. Lutz&#13;
481     International Migrant Workers' Remittances:   Issues        G. Swamy&#13;
and Prospects&#13;
482     Private Bank Lending to Developing Countries                R. O'Brien (consultant)&#13;
483     Development Prospects of the Capital Surplus                R. Hablutzel&#13;
Oil-Exporting Countries&#13;
484     Private Capital Flows to Developing Countries and           A. Fleming&#13;
Their Determination&#13;
485     International Adjustment in the 1980s                       V. Joshi (consultant)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2-&#13;
No.                          TITLE OF PAPER                          AUTHOR&#13;
486     Adjustment in Low-Income Africa                            R. Liebenthal&#13;
487     A Comparative Analysis of Developing Country               C. Wallich&#13;
Adjustment Experiences in the 1970s: Low-Income&#13;
South Asia&#13;
488     Developments in and Prospects for the External             N. Hope&#13;
Debt of the Developing Countries: 1970-80 and&#13;
Beyond&#13;
489     Global Energy Prospects                                    B.J. Choe&#13;
A. Lambertini&#13;
P. Pollak&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I   1&#13;
r 7  HG3881.5 .W57 W67 no.480 c.3&#13;
I Sapir, Andrel'.&#13;
I Trade in services : economic&#13;
determinants and              j&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554962">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1981/08/1554962/trade-services-economic-determinants-development-related-issues
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1981/08/1554962/trade-services-economic-determinants-development-related-issues</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1981/08/1554962/trade-services-economic-determinants-development-related-issues</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/19/000178830_98101903411638/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/19/000178830_98101903411638/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1981-08-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-08-19T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Trade in services : economic determinants
            and development related issues
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            One of the main conclusions of this
            paper is that trade theories can indeed, to a large extent,
            explain the patterns of trade in services in spite of
            varying and often substantial degrees of protectionism.
            Comparative advantage in freight services appears to be
            related to capital intensity, scale, composition of trade,
            and distance from trading partners. Performance in passenger
            services depends in part on capital abundance and the flow
            of passengers. In trade in insurance services the
            availability of human capital and economies of scale seem to
            be important determinants. In addition to their role as
            exports or imports, some traded services such as consultant
            and engineering services, licensing, and technical
            assistance are means of transfer of technology and are
            thereby important in the development process.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Trade in services : economic determinants
            and development related issues
        </docna>
        <display_title>Trade in services : economic
            determinants and development related issues</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1981/08/1554962/trade-services-economic-determinants-development-related-issues</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Health Economics &amp; Finance,Knowledge Economy</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Sapir, Andre</author>
            <author>Lutz, Ernst</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903411638</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Trade</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 480</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Capital goods; Capital intensity;
            Comparative advantage; Freight; Human capital; Insurance;
            International trade; Passenger transport; Protectionism;
            Spatial analysis; Trade; Trade policy
            accounting,affiliates,agents,appropriate
            technology,banking services,Capital Flows,Capital
            Goods,Comparative advantage,Copyright,development
            policies,development strategy,Econometric Analysis,Economic
            Analysis,economic factors,economic models,economies of
            scale,economists,effective demand,EMPIRICAL
            ANALYSIS,empirical
            research,Equations,expenditures,exports,externalities,Financial
            services,GDP,gross domestic product,human
            capital,imports,income,industrialization,insurance,Insurance
            companies,insurance firms,insurers,International
            Trade,knowing,labor force,LDCs,legislation,licensing,local
            production,natural endowments,natural resource
            exploitation,net
            exports,oil,producers,protectionism,research agenda,scale
            effect,tariff barriers,technical assistance,technological
            factors,Technology Transfer,trade balance,Transport
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP480</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Port Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport Terminals</ml:concept><ml:concept>MM</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research and Development Commercialization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research and Innovation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Capital</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing People</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Trade in Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freight Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Econometrics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport Logistics Providers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Maternal Mortality and Morbidity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research, Development and Innovation (RDI)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade in Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freight Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>