<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP704&#13;
Fuelwood Consumption and Deforestation&#13;
in African Countries&#13;
Dennis Anderson&#13;
Robert Fishwick&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 704&#13;
.~~~~~~~~~&#13;
~ ~~flL~~~~~~~~~  ! &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 704&#13;
C \ &#13;
Fuelwood Consumption and Deforestation&#13;
in African Countries&#13;
Dennis Anderson           INTEREUiTiONAL ,T6l:-lY FUND&#13;
Robert Fishwick&#13;
FA': -'. -&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright (© 1984&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing December 1984&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To present&#13;
the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been&#13;
prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed texts, and&#13;
the World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a&#13;
token charge to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The World Bank does not accept responsibility for the views expressed herein, which&#13;
are those of the authors and should not be attributed to the World Bank or to its&#13;
affiliated organizations. The findings, interpretations, and conclusions are the results&#13;
of research supported by the Bank; they do not necessarily represent official policy of&#13;
the Bank. The designations employed, the presentation of material, and any maps used&#13;
in this document are solely for the convenience of the reader and do not imply the&#13;
expression of any opinion whatsoever on the part of the World Bank or its affiliates&#13;
concerning the legal status of any country, territory, city, area, or of its authorities, or&#13;
concerning the delimitation of its boundaries, or national affiliation.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications, both free and for sale, is described in the&#13;
Catalog of Publications; the continuing research program is outlined in Abstracts of&#13;
Current Studies. Both booklets are updated annually; the most recent edition of each is&#13;
available without charge from the Publications Sales Unit, Department T, The World&#13;
Bank, 1818 H Street, N.W., Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A., or from the European&#13;
Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'lena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Dennis Anderson is a senior economist, and Robert Fishwick, now retired, was senior&#13;
forester, both in the Projects Department of the World Bank's Western Africa Regional&#13;
Office.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Anderson, Dennis, 1937-&#13;
Fuelwood consumption and deforestation in African&#13;
countries.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 704)&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
Includes index.&#13;
1. Fuelwood industry--Africa. 2. Fuelwood industry--&#13;
Environmental aspects--Africa. 3. Deforestation--Africa.&#13;
I. Fishwick, Robert. II. Title. III. Series.&#13;
HD9769.F843A354      1984       333.75         84-26975&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0464-X&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ABSTRACT&#13;
The paper reviews recent reports on the level and growth of&#13;
fuelwood consumption in Africa, and on the ecological, economic and&#13;
possible micro-climatic effects of deforestation. It then reviews the&#13;
economic and operational aspects of policies open to governments (i) to&#13;
encourage fuelwood conservation, (ii) to facilitate the substitution of&#13;
commercial energy for fuelwood, where desirable on grounds of relative&#13;
costs, (iii) in developing the 'traditional' functions of the forestry&#13;
services in maintaining the forest reserves and undertaking plantings in&#13;
watersheds and shelterbelts, and (iv) in promoting the practice of&#13;
agro-forestry, i.e. the planting and maintenance of trees in copses and&#13;
around farms by the farm families themselves. All four are important,&#13;
but it is argued that (iv) offers considerable promise in terms of&#13;
increased planting rates, low budgetary requirements, ecological&#13;
benefits and good economic and financial rates of return. The&#13;
importance of the 'policy environment' for the success of each is also&#13;
discussed, as are the various research, education, training and other&#13;
requirements of (iv).&#13;
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS&#13;
Special thanks are due to Hans Fuchs, Jean Gorse, Tariq&#13;
Husain, Henrik Hvidberg-Hanser., Ken Newcombe, D.C. Rao and John Spears&#13;
for many helpful comments and suggestions, and to numerous others cited&#13;
in the References for providing further source material and perspectives&#13;
on the problems discussed. The paper was prepared following Hans Fuchs'&#13;
request for an assessment of the fuelwood situation in Africa., and a&#13;
review of policy options.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CONDENSE&#13;
Ce document fait le point sur un certain nombre de rapports&#13;
publies recemment au sujet du niveau et de la croissance de la&#13;
consommation de bois de feu en Afrique et des consequences ecologiques et&#13;
6conomiques ainsi que des effets microclimatiques possibles du&#13;
deboisement. Puis il examine les aspects economiques et op6rationnels des&#13;
diff6rentes politiques qui s'offrent aux gouvernements : (i) favoriser la&#13;
conservation de bois de feu, (ii) faciliter la substitution de 1'energie&#13;
commerciale au bois de feu, lorsque les coats relatifs le justifient,&#13;
(iii) d6velopper les fonctions traditionnelles des services forestiers&#13;
- entretien des reserves forestieres et travaux de plantation dans les&#13;
bassins versants et les rideaux-abris, et (iv) promouvoir la pratique de&#13;
l'agroforesterie, c'est-a-dire des activites de plantation et d'entretien&#13;
d'arbres dans les bosquets et autour des exploitations agricoles par les&#13;
familles d'agriculteurs elles-m&amp;mes. Ces quatre politiques sont toutes&#13;
importantes, mais ce document fait valoir que la quatrieme offre la&#13;
promesse de taux de plantation plus elev6s, de besoins budg6taires&#13;
reduits, d'avantages ecologiques et de taux de rentabilite economique et&#13;
financiere eleves. Il analyse egalement l'importance de "l'environnement&#13;
politique" pour le succes de chacune de ces politiques ainsi que les&#13;
divers besoins en matiere de recherche, d'6ducation et de formation et&#13;
autres exigences de la quatrieme politique.&#13;
EXTRACTO&#13;
En este documento se examinan informes recientes sobre el nivel&#13;
del consumo de lenia en Africa y su aumento, y sobre los efectos ecol6gicos&#13;
y econ6micos de la deforestaci6n asi como sus posibles consecuencias para&#13;
el microclima. Se consideran luego los aspectos econ6micos y operativos&#13;
de las politicas que pueden seguir los gobiernos para i) fomentar la con-&#13;
servaci6n de este recurso, ii) facilitar la sustituci6n de la leiia por&#13;
energia comercial, ii) expandir las funciones 'tradicionales' de los ser-&#13;
vicios forestales en lo relativo al mantenimiento de las reservas y las&#13;
plantaciones en cuencas y como protecci6n contra los vientos, y iv) promo-&#13;
ver la agro-silvicultura, es decir, la plantaci6n y el mantenimiento de&#13;
arboles en pequenios bosques y alrededor de las explotaciones por los mis-&#13;
mos agricultores. Estos cuatro puntos son importantes pero se alega que&#13;
el iv) promete mucho en lo que se refiere al aumento de las plantaciones,&#13;
requerimientos presupuestarios reducidos, beneficios ecol6gicos y buenas&#13;
tasas de rentabilidad econ6mica y financiera. Tambien se analiza la&#13;
importancia del 'ambiente politico' para el exito de cada una de estas&#13;
medidas y los diversos requisitos de investigaci6n, educaci6n, capacita-&#13;
ci6n y demas que son necesarios para este uiltimo punto.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
OVERVIEW&#13;
Introduction: Fuelwood Consumption and Deforestation&#13;
in Africa&#13;
Policy Options&#13;
-   (i)   Substitution by Commercial Fuels&#13;
-   (ii)  Fuelwood Conservation&#13;
-   (iii) Increasing Supplies by Replenishing Tree Stocks&#13;
Summary&#13;
FUELWOOD DEMAND AND SUPPLY:   TRENDS AND IMPLICATIONS           11&#13;
Household Energy Consumption Rates&#13;
Trends and Regional Variations in Consumption Rates&#13;
Tree Stocks and Depletion Rates&#13;
Supply and Demar.d Dynamics: Simulation Studies&#13;
Supply and Demand: An Analytical Aside&#13;
Ecological Consequences&#13;
Effects on and of Climates&#13;
A REVIEW OF POLICIES                                            26&#13;
Some Limitations of 'Autonomous' Demand and Supply&#13;
Responses&#13;
The Substitution of Commerical Energy for Fuelwood&#13;
The Conservation of Fuelwood&#13;
Forestry and Agro-Forestry:&#13;
(i)       Yield Measurements and Rainfalls&#13;
(ii)      Relative Yields of Forestry and Agro-Forestry:&#13;
A Project Study in the Soudanian Zone&#13;
(iii)     Planting and Production Rates&#13;
(iv)      Financial Returns to Forestry and Agro-Forestry&#13;
(v)       Economic Returns to Agro-Forestry&#13;
Forestry, Agro-Forestry and Public Policy:&#13;
(i)       Investment in Information&#13;
(ii)      Research, Training and Education&#13;
(iii)     Extension Services and Agro-Forestry&#13;
(iv)      Nurseries, Seedling Distribution and Planting&#13;
Techniques&#13;
REFERENCES                                                      49&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I OVERVIEW&#13;
1.1      This report first reviews recent studies   1/ on the growth of&#13;
consumption of fuelwood in Africa, and on the economic, ecological and&#13;
social consequences of deforestation. It then assesses the economic and&#13;
operational merits of various policy options. Chapters II and III&#13;
present the evidence and analysis in detail, while the present chapter&#13;
provides a self-contained overview. It is found that there has been a&#13;
convergence of views amongst foresters and economists in recent years on&#13;
several practical steps that governments could take to begin to address&#13;
the problem, given the commitment, and which by encouraging private as&#13;
well as public plantings, conservation, and, depending on relative costs,&#13;
a shift to 'commercial' fuels, would place modest demands on the&#13;
governments' administrative and budgetary resources while offering&#13;
prospects of very good economic returns to investment.&#13;
Introduction: Fuelwood Consumption and Deforestation in Africa&#13;
1.2       In Africa around 90% of the population use fuelwood for&#13;
cooking, in the equivalent amount of roughly 1.5 tons of oil per family&#13;
per year. The consumption of fuelwood energy by households is typically&#13;
ten times the total consumption of commercial energy for all purposes&#13;
(including transport and electricity generation) in the low income&#13;
countries, and in Nigeria twice the total. The annual rate of&#13;
consumption has now reached the point where it is estimated to exceed&#13;
the annual rate of additions to supply through the growth of trees by&#13;
the following margins (estimates rounded):&#13;
-    in Senegal, by -35% (a slight surplus),&#13;
-    in the Sahelian countries, by 30%,&#13;
-    in Niger, by 200%,&#13;
-    in Northern Nigeria by 75%,&#13;
-    in Ethiopia, by 150%,&#13;
-    in Sudan, by 70%.&#13;
1.3       Forestry plantations and fuelwood plantings currently account&#13;
for very small percentages (less than 5%) of supplies; fuelwood demands&#13;
1/   In particular the recent Energy Assessment and Forestry Sector&#13;
Reports prepared by Bank staff and various publications listed in&#13;
the bibliography. The following paper by Jean Gorse and James&#13;
Thompson goes into the agro-silvo-pastoral aspects of policy in the&#13;
arid and semi-arid zones into more detail, "Towards Better&#13;
Management of the Renewable Resource Base of the Desertification -&#13;
Threatened, Drought-Prone Sahelian and Soudanian Zones in West&#13;
Africa," while Gunter Schramm's report, "Sub-Saharan Africa&#13;
Background Paper" provides another perspective. (Both are in&#13;
draft.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
are thus being met increasingly by the consumption of tree stocks.&#13;
Furthermore the tree stocks are declining at an accelerating rate&#13;
because consumption is increasing exponentially with population growth&#13;
while the annual additions to supply through new tree growth (the mean&#13;
annual increment) are declining in proportion to the volume of stocks.&#13;
For this reason the excess of consumption over the mean annual increment&#13;
is expected to rise to 620% in Niger by the end of the century, in the&#13;
Sahelian countries together, to 130%, and in Northern Nigeria by around&#13;
250%. These estimates do not allow for the effects of land clearance&#13;
for agricultural purposes, which in some regions contributes more to&#13;
deforestation than fuelwood consumption, or for depletions in stocks&#13;
arising from industrial consumption. The half-life of the tree stocks&#13;
(the time which it would take for stocks to decline to half their&#13;
current level) averages about 25 years in West African countries at&#13;
present but, on account of the accelerating trends, is likely to average&#13;
10 years or less (on further depleted stocks) by the end of the century;&#13;
very large areas have either experienced or soon face the prospects of&#13;
very large losses of tree cover.&#13;
1.4       The rapid depletion of tree stocks is causing unprecedented-&#13;
and, without remedial policies, irreversible - changes in the ecology of&#13;
rural areas, principally in the carrying capacity or fertility of the&#13;
soil. The depletion of tree stocks itself introduces a breach in the&#13;
nutrient cycles in the affected areas, though this is perhaps less&#13;
serious than the loss of protection they once provided against the&#13;
erosion of the soil during rains and winds. But so long as demands for&#13;
fuelwood continue to rise the nutrient cycles are breached in two&#13;
further respects: in the removal of animal dung and of crop residues for&#13;
fuel. Overgrazing and poor cropping practices further deplete the&#13;
fertility of the soil. Originally, the ecological changes were confined&#13;
to the Sahelian and Sahelo-Saharan belts, where low rainfalls and&#13;
recurrent droughts make the land fragile, and exceedingly vulnerable to&#13;
the economic activities of small populations. This is apparently why&#13;
desertification advanced in the region over the centuries under the&#13;
influence of, by today's measures, comparatively small perturbations&#13;
associated with trans-Saharan trade, the establishment of small&#13;
settlements, and the gum-arabic trade with Europe over the fifteenth to&#13;
nineteenth centuries. 2/ However, the process of desertification&#13;
associated with human economic activity is no longer confined to these&#13;
areas. Professor Sharon Nicholson, in a report for the Club du Sahel,&#13;
also concluded that "the possibility that human activities in the Sahel&#13;
can affect its climate cannot be ruled out. On the contrary there is&#13;
much evidence that landscape changes can act to reinforce the&#13;
drought..."&#13;
2/   "Environmental Change in the West African Sahel", a study published&#13;
in 1983 by the U.S. National Resarch Council.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
1.5       The reports documenting these developments are reviewed more&#13;
fully in Chapter II. It will be seen that their authors are careful to&#13;
point to the uncertainties and ambiguities in the data, and in fact&#13;
several make proposals for improving the data base on tree stocks and&#13;
fuelwood consumption rates. The demand and supply situation also varies&#13;
between one area and another within countries. There is, however,&#13;
gereral agreement on the underlying trends and on the likely economic&#13;
and ecological consequences.&#13;
Policy Options&#13;
1.6       Policy options fall into three categories:&#13;
(i) substitution - principally of commercial fuels (kerosene, LPG,&#13;
electricity) for fuelwood and charcoal in urban areas;&#13;
(ii) conservation - through the encouragement of changes in&#13;
people's methods and habits of cooking in ways that save&#13;
fuelwood; and through increased efficiency in harvesting&#13;
(reduction of wastes) and in charcoal conversion methods;&#13;
(iii)increasing supplies - through investment in forestry and&#13;
agro-forestry.&#13;
1.7       In regions of rising scarcity of fuelwood, all three changes&#13;
are taking place autonomously under the influence of rising real costs&#13;
cf fuelwood. Autonomous demand and supply adjustments, however, are&#13;
appreciably less than what is required to address the problem in hand.&#13;
Several reasons for this are discussed in Chapter III, but the most&#13;
important one perhaps arises from people's open exploitation of forest&#13;
reserves and wooded areas as a 'public' or 'free' good, without regard&#13;
to the external environmental ard ecological costs noted above. This&#13;
means that fuelwood demands are appreciably higher - i.e. economy in the&#13;
use of fuelwood and the rate of substitution to 'commercial' fuels are&#13;
both lower - and the supplies from new plantings are appreciably lower&#13;
than is economically desirable. The theoretical answer to this problem&#13;
is to apply a stumpage tax as an incentive for conservation, for&#13;
substitution, and for private tree plantings, but the administrative and&#13;
political difficulties of applying such a tax over large areas, and of&#13;
protecting the forest reserves, are formidable, and in practice stumpage&#13;
taxes amount to very small percentages of social. costs. Land tenure&#13;
issues and the 'commons' problem are also thought to undermine the rate&#13;
of investment in agro-forestry and fuelwood plantations. Nevertheless,&#13;
the observed adjustments in demand and supply, working through the price&#13;
mechanism, reveal an underlying responsiveness of the urbarn and rural&#13;
populations to the changes now toking plece, and this provides a natural.&#13;
starting point for the formulation of policies.&#13;
(i) Substitution by Commercial Fuels&#13;
1.8       In a large number of African towns and cities, the real costs&#13;
of cooking with fuelwood have risen above the real costs of cooking with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
commercial fuels such as kerosene, LPG or, in some places, electricity.&#13;
Hence in urban areas there is an economic gain from substitution, even&#13;
ignoring the ecological benefits of reduced fuelwood consumption, and&#13;
the price differences have in fact induced some substitution. However,&#13;
only about 10% of Africa's population use commercial fuels for cooking,&#13;
almost all in the urban areas, though this percentage may double or&#13;
triple in the next 15 years with urbanization and growing fuelwood&#13;
scarcity.- It is frequently repoted, also, that substitution does not&#13;
take place extensively in urban areas until the surrounding tree stocks&#13;
are badly depleted, often over a radius of a 50-100 miles or more. In&#13;
rural-areas, the costs of distributing commercial fuels are very high,&#13;
given the distances involved and the poor infrastructure. Hence the&#13;
(private) cost differences between fuelwood and its commercial&#13;
alternatives continue to favor the consumption of fuelwood or, once this&#13;
runs out, crop residues and animal dung.&#13;
1.9       Hence the recommended policy is to encourage substitution and&#13;
energy conservation in urban areas, including the regional towns and&#13;
cities, while attempting to increase tree stocks and also encourage&#13;
conservation in rural areas. Since policies with respect to the supply&#13;
of commercial energy have been the subject of much analysis elsewhere -&#13;
covering the pricing, investment and institutional aspects - no further&#13;
comment is provided in this report. 3/&#13;
1.10      The rate of substitution - and thus reductions in the rate of&#13;
deforestation - will also depend on the oil importing countries'&#13;
capacities to finance imports. The financing of energy imports in these&#13;
countries absorbed small shares (around 10-15%) of export earnings in&#13;
the 1960s, but now account for large and still growing shares, e.g. for&#13;
44% in Ethiopia in 1981, 63% in Kenya, 77% in Senegal, 44% in Sudan, 24%&#13;
in Liberia and 23% in Niger. Hence the rate of substitution will depend&#13;
crucially on the success with which the countries manage their trade and&#13;
exchange rate policies. Indeed, the issue is wider than this, since the&#13;
frequent overevaluation of currencies in African countries, and the&#13;
preference for channeling resources away from agriculture (both exports&#13;
and food crops) toward industry has greatly undermined the private&#13;
returns to investment in rural areas, including, it must be concluded,&#13;
investments in agro-forestry and erosion control. Hence for two reasons&#13;
- the disincentives for the substitution of commercial fuels, and for&#13;
investment in rural areas - the less successful the countries are in&#13;
managing their trade and exchange rate policies, the greater will be the&#13;
rate of deforestation.&#13;
3/   See e.g. the World Bank's recent report, The Energy Transition in&#13;
Developing Countries (1983).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
(ii) Fuelwood Conservation&#13;
1.11      Under this heading, the idea that has attracted most attention&#13;
has been the introduction of wood-burning stoves, and changes in&#13;
people's habits and methods of cooking in ways that would save on&#13;
fuelwood. So far, however, programs to put the idea into practice have&#13;
met with mixed success. As discussed in Chapter III, experiments&#13;
suggested that two or three fold increases in the fuel efficiency of&#13;
cooking would be possible over tradtional "three-stone" methods.    In&#13;
addition, the use of aluminum pots, whether on open fires or on stoves,&#13;
has been found to add significantly to efficiency, with further gains&#13;
being thought possible through improvements in cooking habits and&#13;
utensils. Overall it was once thought that a four-fold reduction in the&#13;
specific consumption rates of fuelwood could be achieved by these&#13;
various devices, from around 0.8 cubic meters per capita per year, to&#13;
0.2 cubic meters. It is not difficult to show that such gains would&#13;
greatly reduce the rate of deforestation. Furthermore, the costs are&#13;
low; the stoves for instance can be made by artisans, with payback&#13;
periods of 20-60 days assuming the efficiency gains are realized.&#13;
1.12      Undoubtedly one reason for the low response so far has been&#13;
that the programs to effect such changes are still in their pilot&#13;
phases, and were not intended to have a wide distribution; in this&#13;
respect, it is still too early to arrive at definitive conclusions as to&#13;
their success. It is thought however that the inefficiencies of&#13;
traditional methods of cooking were over-estimated in tests, while, on&#13;
the other hand, there is still much experimentation to be done to find&#13;
stoves that meet with people's requirements. There have also been some&#13;
difficulties with the ways the programs were organized. E.g. several&#13;
attempts were made to implement the pregrams through the forestry&#13;
services, which were not well placed to undertake the research or to&#13;
disseminate the idea. It is now thought that it would be better to rely&#13;
more on the private voluntary organizations, the rural extension&#13;
services and the manufacturers themselves (most of whom are likely to be&#13;
artisans and small scale establishments).&#13;
1.13      It shou].d be noted also that the costs of the programs are&#13;
generally very small, being, e.g., only small fractions of one percent&#13;
of, say, net public investments in energy. Hence financial support for&#13;
the programs entails no significant financial risk for either donors or&#13;
governments while offering prospects of large benefits if consumers and&#13;
manufacturers respond to the idea. Hence the programs seem worth&#13;
persisting with.&#13;
(iii) Increasing Supplies by Replenishing Tree Stocks&#13;
1.14      There are broadly two complementary approaches:&#13;
(a)  Ihe "forestry approach", involving plantations, the better&#13;
management of forest reserves, the recovery of forest&#13;
residues, and the establishment of fuelwood and erosion&#13;
control plantations in water-sheds and shelterbelts. This&#13;
approach works through the forestry services;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6-&#13;
(b) The "agro-forestry approach", involving the planting and&#13;
maintenance of trees near dwellings, on the boundaries of&#13;
arable land and in small lots (sometimes intercropped) by the&#13;
farm families themselves.&#13;
1.15      The forestry approach has so far accounted for the larger&#13;
share of government (and donor) allocations to fuelwood, ecology control&#13;
and related investments in Africa. Rising scarcity prices frecuently&#13;
show fuelwood plantations to have prospects of good financial and&#13;
economic rates of returns, e.g. as with peri-urban plantations for towns&#13;
and cities where local reserves are badly depleted, and multi-purpose&#13;
plantations providing fuelwood, poles and erosion control in rural&#13;
areas. The ecological benefits are also important, e.g. in watersheds&#13;
and regions subject to loss of soil through winds, and may justify&#13;
investments even where, on account of the public's open exploitation of&#13;
existing reserves keeping prices down, the financial returns are low.&#13;
1.16      In terms of defining future policies, however, there is one&#13;
over-riding issue associated with the forestry approach. This is that,&#13;
institutionally and financially, what it can accomplish falls far short&#13;
of what is needed to meet rural and urban demands for fuelwood and to&#13;
protect the soil from erosion and losses in fertility in rural areas.&#13;
For example, the World Bank's energy policy paper 4/ contained the&#13;
results of some simulation studies by John Spears, from which it was&#13;
concluded that, even if the demand for wood were to be reduced by 20 to&#13;
30 percent through conservation, and through subsititution for other&#13;
fuels, a fifteenfold increase in current planting rates would be&#13;
required in African countries to bring demand and supply into better&#13;
balance by year 2000. These results were averages for quite large&#13;
regions; in regions where fuelwood is most scarce, much larger increases&#13;
in plarting rates were thought to be needed. Another way of looking at&#13;
planting requirements is to note that plantations currently account for&#13;
significantly less than 5% of fuelwood supplies, the balance of over 95%&#13;
coming from the felling and lopping of natural woodland and farm fallow.&#13;
1.17      The budgetary institutional development problems to be&#13;
surmounted to accomplish such an increase are formidable, and come at a&#13;
time when forestry services in the region have received appreciable&#13;
budget cuts rather than increases. While it is desirable for&#13;
governments to increase budgetary allocations to the forestry services,&#13;
increases of the order required to achieve a 15 fold increase or more in&#13;
the planting rates and, equally important, to maintain the plantations&#13;
and existing forest reserves, do not seem a realistic proposition. In&#13;
addition there would be the difficulties of recruiting, training and&#13;
managing very large increases in the forestry labor force.&#13;
4/   "The Energy Transition in Developing Countries", 1983.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
1.18      Now consider the potential yields and output of agro-forestr.&#13;
Agro-forestry practices 5/ are sometimes described as 'old traditions&#13;
in the Soudano-Sahelian zones of West Africa, though it is now believed&#13;
that they are breaking down under the influences of the growth of human&#13;
and animal populations, the demand for fuelwood, and changes in cropping&#13;
practices in the region. So far, however, there has been little&#13;
government support for the development of the practices, and it. is&#13;
reported that much of the land clearing taking place for agricultural&#13;
development proiects has further discouraged their development., Yet of&#13;
the policies so far put forward, those for rekindling and developing the&#13;
traditions further offer the most grounds for encouragement:&#13;
(i)  Planting Rates.  Farmers outnumber foresters by 1,000 to&#13;
10,000 to 1. If their families spend, say, only 10 days per&#13;
year on the planting and care of trees, as an "off-farm"&#13;
activity, their combined labor inputs would outweigh that of&#13;
the foresters by 40 to 400 to 1. If then the farmers arc&#13;
given adequate incentives to adopt the practice, with suitable&#13;
encouragement and advice from the rural extension services,&#13;
and are supplied with seedlings, an appreciable increase in&#13;
planting rates would be achievable;&#13;
(ii) Costs and Returns. The financial costs of wage labor, which&#13;
are the main expenditure item in the forestry services'&#13;
budgets, would be eliminated (though further investments in&#13;
extension would be needed). The economic costs of farm&#13;
families' labor would also be reduced, over the long-term,&#13;
because of the time that would otherwise have to be spent in&#13;
gathering and transporting fuelwood, and the possibility&#13;
arises that the social costs of the programs would be&#13;
negative, i.e. there would be a social gain. These factors&#13;
make the practice of agro-forestry financially and&#13;
economically attractive. The economic and financial&#13;
attractiveness is further increased by:&#13;
(iii)Ecological Benefits. These are revealed most directly in the&#13;
crop yields. Agro-forestry practices require dispersed&#13;
plantings of large numbers of trees over large areas, as&#13;
compared to the concentrated plantings over relatively small&#13;
areas of the forestry appraoch. This means that the&#13;
ecological benefits of improved nutrient cycles, improved&#13;
moisture retention in the soil and reduced soil erosion are&#13;
both larger and better distributed over the farm lands. It&#13;
also means that there would be positive financial returns to&#13;
the farmers;&#13;
5/   For further details on the practices, see Agro-forestry in the West&#13;
African Sahel, National Academy Press, Washington, D.C., 1983.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
(iv) Planting Areas and Yields. Only small areas of farmlands are&#13;
taken up by the practice. For Northern Nigeria it is&#13;
estimated that 40-50 trees planted on farm boundaries and near&#13;
dwellings, occupying less than 5% of arable land on, say, a 2&#13;
hectare farm is sufficient to meet the fuelwood needs of a&#13;
farm family. One reason for this is that the yields of&#13;
free-standing trees are typically 3 or more times those in&#13;
plantations and forests. In more arid northern Soudanian and&#13;
Sahelian regions yields are significantly lower, so&#13;
correspondingly more plantings over a greater proportion of&#13;
arable area would be needed if self-sufficiency in fuelwood&#13;
were sought; nevertheless, and even where self-sufficiency is&#13;
not sought, the practice would make a significant contribution&#13;
to fuelwood supplies, providing by-products such as fruit,&#13;
fodder and shade, reducing erosion, and improving the carrying&#13;
capacity of the soil.&#13;
(v)  Farmer Response.  The low costs, the ecological benefits, and&#13;
the prospects of good economic and financial returns, provide&#13;
reasons for expecting a good response to the agro-forestry&#13;
approach, as has been the experience with social forestry&#13;
projects in India (see Part III).&#13;
1.19      In practice, the main factor working against the development&#13;
of agro-forestry is the externality problem noted earlier, which is&#13;
that, so long as local tree stocks are not in short supply and can be&#13;
cut as a 'free good,' there is little incentive for private plantings.&#13;
Further, the ecological costs of overcutting are indirect and delayed,&#13;
and not immediately apparent. In these circumstances, there is a good&#13;
case for programs to encourage the practice, e.g. through the extension&#13;
services, supporting research into suitable species of trees, and&#13;
through the establishment of networks of nurseries (see para 1.21 below&#13;
and Part III).&#13;
1.20      The unit costs of such programs to support agro-forestry are&#13;
also very low - of the order of 10% to 20% of the costs of plantation&#13;
projects, possibly less. This of course further enhances the case for&#13;
the programs since the budgetary commitments, and thus the financial&#13;
risks, are comparatively low while the prospective economic returns to&#13;
public investments are likely to be large. A recent study in Nigeria 6/&#13;
estimated the discounted average financial cost to be 7% of those of&#13;
fuelwood plantations. This included the costs of seedlings and seedling&#13;
distribution, but excluded the costs of complimentary investments in the&#13;
education and training (or re-orientation) of the rural extensionists in&#13;
the agro-forestry approach, and of providing suporting&#13;
6/   World Bank Energy Assessment Report.    (See Part III, below, Para&#13;
3.35).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
research. The components of agro-forestry projects are discussed in&#13;
Chapter III; but such calculations, which are consistent with project&#13;
experience in South Asia and Latin America, show that the benefits noted&#13;
under (ii) also lead to major reductions in the financial costs of&#13;
projects.&#13;
1.21      The various components of an agro-forestry development program&#13;
are also discussed in Chapter III, with special reference to the arid&#13;
and semi-arid zones of West Africa. Most of the components, however,&#13;
apply to other regions. In brief, they are as follows:&#13;
(i) Investment in Information - to improve the data on fuelwood&#13;
consumption, tree stocks, yields, depletion rates and&#13;
ecological conditions; also studies of sociological, economic&#13;
and tenurial factors likely to influence both people's&#13;
response to the programs and their choice of trees.&#13;
(ii) Research, Training and Education. The changing emphasis in&#13;
the arid and semi-arid zones of West Africa to tree planting&#13;
more closely associated with, and carried out by private&#13;
house-owners and farmers, would require fundamental changes in&#13;
the priorities of fcrestry research, university curricula and&#13;
technician training. Research and extension linkages in&#13;
forestry scarcely exist today in the majority of the West&#13;
African countries. It is noteworthy also that forestry is&#13;
never included in T and V agricultural extension programs. In&#13;
the forthcoming era of integrated tree-planting with farming&#13;
it will be vital to invest further in the education of&#13;
extension workers as to the practices of agro-forestrv and to&#13;
provide supporting research.&#13;
The forestry research centers,which have suffered from much&#13;
neglect in African countries, thus merit far more budgetary&#13;
and developmental support than they have received in the past.&#13;
There are also good reasons for establishing a regional center&#13;
in West Africa on agro-sylvo-pastoral research, or at least to&#13;
coordinate it. As to technolgies and methods, although tree&#13;
planting, usually with exotics, has been successfully carried&#13;
out in the region since the early 1900s, success was due&#13;
largely to the plantations being on superior sites and better&#13;
rainfalls than experienced in the last 16 years. The drought&#13;
and the dearth of good soils have urderscored the need for&#13;
Improved technological packages and breeding programs from&#13;
survivor trees.&#13;
(iii)Nurseries, Seedling Distribution and Planting Techniques. A&#13;
key to fostering 'spontaneous' tree planting efforts is the&#13;
establishment of a highly decentralized nursery and seedling&#13;
distribution system. In addition to providing a source of&#13;
seedlings themselves, public and community nurseries could&#13;
serve a valuable demonstration effect for private investments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
Summary&#13;
1.22      Several studies in recent years have converged towards&#13;
operationally workable policies for addressing the problems stemming&#13;
from the consumption of fuelwood in Africa. It is desirable to persist,&#13;
in the first place, with programs to encourage savings on fuelwood&#13;
consumption and, in the second, with addressing the various issues&#13;
affecting the supply of commercial energy and thus (especially in urban&#13;
areas) its substitution for the burning of fuelwood and charcoal.&#13;
Third, it is economically desirable to increase budgetary and&#13;
developmental support for the traditional work of the forestry services,&#13;
particularly in the management of the forest reserves and the&#13;
establishment of erosion control plantations in water-sheds and&#13;
shelterbelts; plantations for fuelwood and its by-products, if&#13;
appropriately located, also can show good rates of return. Each have&#13;
their contribution to make and the appropriate circumstances for&#13;
investment, at least for commercial fuels and forestry projects, should&#13;
be revealed by economic and financial analysis. It would be desirable,&#13;
however, to take further the current (and somewhat small and isolated&#13;
initiatives) to develop agro-forestry practices in Africa. In terms of&#13;
its prospective economic and ecological benefits, financially low risks,&#13;
and breadth of scope, the development of agro-forestry would merit&#13;
substantially increased support from Governments and development&#13;
agencies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
II FUELWOOD DEMAND AND SUPPLY:&#13;
TRENDS AND IMPLICATIONS&#13;
Hlousehold Energy Consumption Rates&#13;
2.1       Fuelwood, together with the burning of animal dung and crop&#13;
residues, meets practically the whole of rural households' energy&#13;
demands in West and East Africa, and appreciably more than half of the&#13;
demands of urban households. This means that, in round numbers, about&#13;
90% or more of the population are dependent on fuelwood, animal dung or&#13;
crop residues for heating and cooking. Statistics are scarce on the&#13;
extent to which animal dung and crop residues are consumed, but some&#13;
estimates have been made for fuelwood. AveSage annual fuelwood&#13;
consumption is estimated to be around 0.6 m   per capit   among households&#13;
burning fuelwood or charcoal in urban areas, and 0.8 m or more in rural&#13;
areas. 1/ The energy of one cubic meter of wood is equivalent to&#13;
approximately 0.3 tons of oil (t.o.e.), so that, for a household of six&#13;
these consumption rates are roughly equivalent to one ton of oil in&#13;
urban areas and one and a half tons or more in rural areas. The&#13;
following table shows how such consumption rates add up over all&#13;
households in selected countries in the region; also included are&#13;
estimates, where available, of the consumption of animal dung; for&#13;
comparison, some data on the consumption of commercial fuels are also&#13;
provided:&#13;
1/        These figures are in the middle of the ranges cited in the&#13;
Energy Assessment RepoSts. The ranges tend to be quite broad&#13;
(e.g. for 0.5 to 1.0 m per meter in Nigeria) for several&#13;
reasons: (i) cooking habits and methods vary, as does the&#13;
quality of wood; (ii)) animal dung and crop residues are often&#13;
used as substitutes, though to an unknown extent; and (iii)&#13;
measurement errors. The slightly lower rate of consumption in&#13;
urban areas might possibly be due to the more extensive use of&#13;
stoves and metal pots than in rural areas, which improves the&#13;
fuel efficiency of cooking (see Part III); on the other hand,&#13;
charcoal is more widely used which tends to raise fuelwood&#13;
consumption since, as Mr. Schramm remarks "the conversion&#13;
losses in making charcoal from wood using traditional kilns or&#13;
not fully compensated for by improvements in cooking&#13;
efficiency," (p 20).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
Table 2.1 Household Energy Consumption for Selected Countries (1980)&#13;
Sudan  Ethiopia   Niger   Senegal   Nigeria&#13;
Household Energy Consumption:&#13;
% Distribution by Source:&#13;
-Fuelwood, including charcoal   94       46         99     95        88&#13;
-Animal dung and crop residues   5       54        n.a.    n.a.      n.a.&#13;
99      100         99     95        88&#13;
-Electricity                     0.2      0.05       0.6    3         7&#13;
-LPG, Kerosene                   0.5      0.15       0.6    2         5&#13;
0.7      0.2        1.2    5        12&#13;
Total (rounded)                100%     100%       100%   100%      100%&#13;
Actual Househgld Energy Con-&#13;
sumption, 10  t.o.e.           10.2      8.1       0.7    1.5       16.6&#13;
Mtemo Items, in 10  t.o.e.:&#13;
-Total Commercial Energy&#13;
Consumption in Countrv         1.3      0.5        0.2   1.4        9.8&#13;
-Household Consumption of&#13;
Fuelwood                       9.6      3.7        0.7   1.4       14.6&#13;
Source: Energy Assessment Studies for household energy consumption;&#13;
Bank (1983) paper on "The Energy Transition in Developing&#13;
Countries" for total commercial energy consumption.&#13;
2.2       The top rows show that. household uses of commercial energy&#13;
account for low percentages of household energy demand. The rate of&#13;
fuelwood consumption (measured in energy units) is also appreciably in&#13;
excess of the total consumption of commercial energy, including that&#13;
used for power generation, industry and transport, as can be seen from&#13;
the last two rows of the table.&#13;
Trends and Regional Variations in Consumption Rates&#13;
2.3       When examining trends in consumption rates it is first&#13;
necessary to distinguish between urban and rural areas, since the&#13;
possibilities for the substitution of commercial fuels for fuelwood (and&#13;
charcoal) are much greater in urban areas. In West Africa, the urban&#13;
populations now range from 11% of total population in Upper Volta to 41%&#13;
in Ivory Coast; for Sub-Saharan Africa the average is 24%, having&#13;
increased from 14% in 1960. On account of the rapid rates of&#13;
urbanization, the urban population in Africa is likely to be around 40%&#13;
of the total by the end of the century; the following table shows some&#13;
projections for selected countries, based on current trends.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
Table 2.2: Urban and Rural Population Growth: Past&#13;
Trends and Projections, Selected Countries&#13;
Country/       Population Growth, % p.a.      Urban Population, % Total&#13;
Region         Total/     Urb  1/   Rural2/       3/    Year 2000&#13;
Tota___U_  r anrr-              MRE=-    Year__2000&#13;
Sudan            2.6       6.8       0.0        25          54&#13;
Ethiopia         2.0       6.5       0.1        14          33&#13;
Niger             3.1      6.9       2.2        13          27&#13;
Senegal          1.6       3.1       0.1        34          46&#13;
Nigeria           2.5      4.7       1.8        20          31&#13;
S-S. Africa      2.7       5.6       1.3        24          42&#13;
1/  Historical trends, 1960-1980, from IBRD World Tables.&#13;
2/  Estimated as residual for 1980-2000, assuming continuation of&#13;
historical rates of urbanization.&#13;
3/ Most recent estimate.&#13;
Economic policies .and several other factors may change the rates of&#13;
urbanization eventually experienced, but the point remains that the&#13;
urban populations are likely to be large, totalling around 250 million&#13;
in year 2000. 2/&#13;
2.4       The rapid rates of growth of urban areas are inducing&#13;
appreciable demands for fuelwood and charcoal, and account for much of&#13;
the observed declines in tree stocks in the surrounding countryside -&#13;
often up to a radius of 50-100 miles or more. The reason is that, so&#13;
long as local wooded areas and forests are not depleted, the costs of&#13;
cooking with fuelwood or charcoal continue to be lower than those of the&#13;
commercial alternatives. In a study by Mr. Fuller (quoted in the Energy&#13;
Assessment Report for Zimbabwe and in Mr. Schramm's review) it was found&#13;
that the total costs of collecting fuelwood from indigenous woodlands,&#13;
transporting it to urban areas, and retailing were competetive with the&#13;
costs of commercial fuels up to a radius of about 100 km; from fuelwood&#13;
plantations (including plantation costs) the costs were competetive up&#13;
to a radius of 65-85 km. Such comparisons naturally depend on location&#13;
and the quality of local roads and transport; conversion to charcoal&#13;
further reduces transport costs and, perhaps, widens the radius. But&#13;
the main point is that, so long as fuelwood is available locally, urban&#13;
2/        World Development Report, 1984, Chapter 4 and statistical&#13;
annexes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
areas burn it and, in doing so, greatly deplete the local tree cover.&#13;
In Ethiopia, Mr. Newcombe also found that, once the local fuelwood&#13;
resources were depleted, an active urban market developed for animal&#13;
dung. 3/ Thus the demand for fuelwood in urban areas remains strong and&#13;
accounts for much of the deforestation taking place in Africa. 4/&#13;
2.5       In rural areas practically the whole of the population use&#13;
fuelwood for cooking ana account for 70-90% of the demand. There are&#13;
only very limited substitution possibilities for commercial fuels.    This&#13;
is because first, the gathering of fuelwood is a subsistence-level,&#13;
non-monetized activity, whereas the sale of commercial fuels requires a&#13;
degree of monetization. Second, as discussed below (para 3.7), the&#13;
costs of distributing commercial fuels in rural areas remain exceedingly&#13;
high, except perhaps in the larger villages and rural towns.&#13;
Historically, the consumption of fuelwood has grown directly with the&#13;
growth of the rural populetior. and, as in urban areas, the demand&#13;
continues to be "strong"; it is difficult to see a decline occuring&#13;
until rising scarcity prices compel. people to reduce consumption, to&#13;
bccome involved in tree planting programs, or to turn substitutes.&#13;
2.6       On account of regional variations in population density, and&#13;
also in the rates of urbanization, the demand for (and supply of)&#13;
fuelwood shows great regional variation. While, for example, there is&#13;
growing scarcity of fuelwood in the Northern States and urban centers of&#13;
Nigeria, "over much of Central Nigeria there are enormous areas of&#13;
woodland, but transport costs preclude them from being used to alleviate&#13;
fuel scarcity problems of the north and many urban centers". 5/&#13;
Similarly, in the Sahelian countries, the supply-demand balances vary&#13;
greatly, with slight surpluses existing in semi-arid zones, accounting&#13;
for 20% of the land and 12m of the 31m inhabitants of these countries,&#13;
but very large deficits, of the order of 300% or more, in the low&#13;
rainfall areas in the north. 6/&#13;
3/        Energy Assessment Report.&#13;
4/        Reliable estimates of the extent of and trends in urban&#13;
fuelwood consumption are not readily available for African&#13;
countries. In Seengal urban areas account for roughly 30% and&#13;
a rising share of consumption; in Nigeria about 40% of the&#13;
urban population use fuelwood, but yet lower income countries&#13;
the percentage is much greater.&#13;
5/        Memo for Bob Fishwick, January 19, 1984.&#13;
6/        Report by Mr. Keita, FAO, 1982.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
Tree Stocks and Depletion Rates&#13;
2.7       The following table compares recent estimates of annual&#13;
fuelwood consumption. with annual additions to supply (or 'mean annual&#13;
increment') from new tree growth. Also included are the demand&#13;
forecasts contained in the various energy assessment studies for year&#13;
2000.&#13;
Table 2.3 Fuelwood Consumption Compared with the Mean Annual&#13;
Increment of Tree Stocks in Selected Countries&#13;
Accessible Supply    Fuelwood       Excess of Consumption&#13;
From3Tree Growth,    Conslmption 1/ Over3New Supply&#13;
OOOm /year 2/        OOOm /year      OOOm /year    %&#13;
Mauritania           97                  963              866      893&#13;
Senegal - 1981   7,200                 4,600          - 2,600      -36 3/&#13;
- 2001   6,300                 7,200             900        14&#13;
Niger - 1980      1,400                4,100            2,700      193&#13;
- 2000     1,000                 7,200           6,200&#13;
Sahel - 1980     17,000               22,000            5,000       30&#13;
- 2000    15,000                34,000           19,000      127&#13;
N. Nigeria       13,500 4/            23,300            9,800       73&#13;
Ethiopia -1982   13,600               34,000           20,400      150&#13;
Sudan - 1980    44,400                75,800           31,400       71&#13;
Source:  Energy Assessment Studies in the respective countries, and the&#13;
seminar notes of Jean Gorse on the Sahel, attached to a&#13;
memorandum dates May 16, 1983.&#13;
1/ Including wood used for charcoal (except Nigeria). The figures for&#13;
Sudan also include use for poles.&#13;
2/ The trend projections are based on current trends, unmodified&#13;
according to the policy responses outlined in the respective&#13;
studies.&#13;
3/ A surplus.&#13;
4/ The average of the range of estimates provided in the Assess Ient&#13;
Studies. The estimate assumes a me n annual increment oi Im /ha in&#13;
7.5m ha of forests and 0.2 to 0.6 m /ha (average of 0.4m ) in 15.2m&#13;
ha of savannah woodlands.&#13;
2.7        Since the figures in the right hand column are averages for&#13;
countries listed, they conceal the above mentioned regional variations&#13;
in demand and supply. The Energy Assessment report for Nigeria, in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
addition to drawing attention to the uncertainties in the data, cautions&#13;
that "global figures can be very misleading (and) it is important to&#13;
evaluate each state on a sub-regional basis. So far, the only northern&#13;
state evaluated in this way is Kano, Nigeria's most populous State,&#13;
which has nearly nine million inhabitants ....   .... Results from this&#13;
study show (i) diminishing forest reserve areas due to land clearing for&#13;
agricultural development, (ii) depletion of farm tree densities and&#13;
extreme variations within the State .... and (iii) annual fuelwood&#13;
demand outstripping supply at a ratio of 5:1, which could lead to a&#13;
depletion of the state's wood capital in less than a decade". 7/&#13;
2.8       The quality of the data on which the above estimates are based&#13;
leaves much to be desired, as the various sources cited make clear.&#13;
Data on tree stocks, on the annual additions to supply from the growth&#13;
of trees (mean annual increment) and, as noted above, on consumption&#13;
rates, are subject to quite large margins of uncertainty. Inventories&#13;
and annual increments are compiled from the reports on field trips by&#13;
local foresters and consultants, supplemented where possible by aerial&#13;
photography, though the latter source of information is still quite&#13;
limited in Africa; surveys are often described as "patchy", and it is&#13;
not clear whether they comprise statistically representative samples.&#13;
As will be seen in Part III, the rainfall gradients are also steep as&#13;
one moves south and south west from the Sahelo-Saharar zones; this too&#13;
affects the mean annual increment.&#13;
2.9       In addition, the supply figures are based on what is termed&#13;
"accessible supply", and exclude forest and tree-savannah areas too&#13;
remote from the more populated areas, or simply too difficult or costly&#13;
to exploit. According to an FAO survey in 1980, for example, only 18%&#13;
of the tree stocks in Mauritania were "accessible", 42% in Senegal, 40%&#13;
in Niger, and 34% for the Sahelian countries together. 8/ Accessibility&#13;
is reportedly higher in other countries, but again uncertain. Obviously&#13;
a change in assumptions here would affect the estimates.&#13;
2.10      As the studies cited have concluded, therefore, it will be&#13;
important to invest in improving the information base on tree stocks,&#13;
yields and consumption rates as a necessary element in the preparation&#13;
and implementation of re-afforestation and energy supply programs. The&#13;
establishment of systems through which environmental., climatic and&#13;
ecological changes can be better monitored and researched in the region&#13;
has also been proposed. Such proposals are discussed further in Part&#13;
III.&#13;
2.11      Notwithstanding the uncertainties in the data, however, it is&#13;
now widely reported that supply deficits are both widespread and&#13;
7/        Op.cit. p 123.&#13;
8/        Keita, op.cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
increasing: the underlying trends are not in dispute; it is the precise&#13;
extent and locations of the changes taking place that are uncertain.&#13;
Also, the estimates in Table 2.3 neglect the depletion of tree stocks&#13;
arising from industrial forestry, 9/ the demands for building and&#13;
fencing materials, and the clearance of land for agriculture, which in&#13;
some countries outweighs the losses due to fuelwood consumption. E.g.&#13;
in Liberia, which is more heavily forested than most African countries,&#13;
the mean annial increment of the current growing stock is about 21&#13;
million in m per year, while the rati of loss through forest clearing&#13;
is estimated to be about 24 millio   m- per year, and through fuelwocd&#13;
and charcoal demands 4.2 million m per year. 10/ There are thus&#13;
reasons for thinking that the above estimates understate the rate of&#13;
depletion of stocks.&#13;
Supply and Demand Dynamics: Simulation Studies&#13;
2.12      In regions where iuelwocd consumption exceeds the mean annual&#13;
increment there is a decline in tree stocks. Further, since consumption&#13;
grows directly with population growth, while the mean annual increment&#13;
from existing stocks declines in direct proportion to the decline in the&#13;
stocks, both the annual increment and the stocks decline at accelerating&#13;
rates. (The next section presents a simple differential equation which&#13;
represents these changes.)&#13;
2.13      Consider the Sahelian countries, for example, where the&#13;
consumption rate is currently 1.3 times the mean annual increment.&#13;
Additions to supply on account of the natural growth of existing stocks&#13;
would be roughly 10% over a five year period, while the consumption rate&#13;
would increase by 13%, a net decline in stocks of 3% over the period.&#13;
However, on account of population growth the consumption rate increases&#13;
and, by year 2000, it is estimated that the consumption rate will be&#13;
2.27 times that of the natural rate of addition to stocks. Hence an&#13;
addition of 10% to already depleted stocks in the following five years&#13;
would be offset by an extraction of 22.7%, a net decline of stocks of&#13;
12.7%, over four times the rate of experienced earlier. The level of&#13;
tree stocks declines therefore at more than an exponential rate, since&#13;
the rate of decline is itself increasing exponentially, and it is this&#13;
that makes the whole process so precipitous.&#13;
2.14      The point is worth illustrating again by reference to the&#13;
simulation studies in the energy assessment report for Sudan. The&#13;
following table summarizes the key figures:&#13;
9/        See Mr. Guppy's article in Foreign Affairs, in Spring 1984.&#13;
10/       Energy Assessment Report (Draft), June 1984.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
Table 2.4 Tree Stocks and Fuelwood Consumption in Sudan&#13;
1980      1985       1990      1995      2000&#13;
Growing Stockg:3&#13;
-volume, 10 m      1,994     1,810     1,539      1,145      607&#13;
-% 1980 stock        100        91        77         57       30&#13;
Mean Annual    6 3&#13;
Increment 10 m        44        40        34         25       14&#13;
Consumption 1/, 10 6m3  76        88       102        121.     141&#13;
Excess of Consumption&#13;
Over Mean Annual&#13;
Increment: 6 3&#13;
-volume, 10 m         32        48        68         96      127&#13;
-%                    73       120       200        380      907&#13;
1/  Includes losses and use of wood for poles and timber, which together&#13;
account for about 4-5% of consumption.&#13;
2.15    3 In the above case, the ilitial stock is approximately&#13;
2000 m m , and increases ~y 44 m m per year due to natural growth, or&#13;
roughly 5 x 44 = 220 m m    over tle period 1980-85; but consumption&#13;
extracts roughly 5 x 76 3= 380 m m  over the same period, a net decline&#13;
of 380 - 220 = 160 m m , or 8% of the stock. The yield on existing&#13;
stocks, which is priportional to the size of the stock, thus falls by 8%&#13;
(from 44 to 40 m m   per year) for the following five years while       3&#13;
consumption increases by 16% (from an already large base) of 76 to 88m3.&#13;
As can be seen, the process accelerates rapidly and the scarcity of&#13;
fuelwood, as measured by the excess of the rate of consumption over the&#13;
mean annual increment, increases twelvefold, from 73% to 907%, over the&#13;
20 year period, with the stock of trees being depleted to 30% of its&#13;
1980 level and being virtually eliminated 5 years later.&#13;
2.16      An accelerating rate of decline of tree stocks occurs in any&#13;
region once the rate of consumption exceeds the additions to stocks from&#13;
the growth of trees. It is now occuring in numerous African countries&#13;
including all the Sahelian countries (with the possible exception of&#13;
Senegal), the populous northern regions of Nigeria, and Kenya, Ethiopia,&#13;
Malawi, Sudan and others.&#13;
2.17      The above simulation studies neglect the effects on demand&#13;
(including substitution to other fuels) of increases in real costs and&#13;
prices as fuelwood becomes more scarce. John Spears made some&#13;
allowances for this in his study for the Bank's recent energy policy&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
paper. 11/ As in the present analysis, however, no allowance was made&#13;
for the loss of stocks due to land clearance for agriculture. The&#13;
following are the estimates for Niger: 12/&#13;
Fuelwood Consumption,   1980, m m3                       3&#13;
Expected Consumption,   2000, m m                        4&#13;
- less,3savings, of&#13;
1 m m  from wood-&#13;
burning stoves and            3&#13;
use of commercial fuels    m m                         3&#13;
Mean annual increment,          3&#13;
year, 2000                  m m                         0.3    3&#13;
Difference                                               2.7 m m&#13;
Planted area required to meet deficits,       300,000 hectares&#13;
or:      15,000 ha/year over 20 yrs.&#13;
Current programs of forestry service          1,500 ha/year&#13;
Ratio of required to current planting rates      10:1&#13;
Supply and Demand Dynamics: An Analytical Aside&#13;
2.18      In regions where consumption begins to exceed the mean annual&#13;
increment,the rate of change in the volume of tree stocks can be&#13;
represented by the equation:&#13;
dS/dt = (a-f)S - C&#13;
where S denotes stocks at time t, C the rate of consumption, a the mean&#13;
annual increment per unit of stocks, and f the net rate of felling&#13;
arising from agricultural, industrial and other activities less&#13;
plantings by the forestry services and farmers (f is not necessarily&#13;
constant but is here put as a parameter associated with S on the grounds&#13;
that current planting rates are small and that the rate of land clearing&#13;
declines with S).&#13;
2.19      The rate of consumption is thought to be increasing&#13;
exponentially with population growth. But as fuelwood becomes scarce,&#13;
real costs and prices rise, and people turn to substitutes or otherwise&#13;
reduce consumption. Hence we might write consumption as C=(A/P) exp(pt),&#13;
where A is a constant, P price and p the population growth rate. In&#13;
turn, the price increases might be expected to vary inversely with&#13;
(among other things) the available stocks, from which&#13;
11/       "Energy Transition...". 1983.&#13;
12/       Spear's consumption estimates are lower than those shown in&#13;
table 2.3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
20&#13;
Figure 1&#13;
Decline of Tree Stocks When Rate of&#13;
Consumption Exceeds the Mean Annual Increment&#13;
B              A&#13;
500            1.0           A                         I&#13;
0.9 &#13;
400            0.8           B              \ &#13;
0.7                                 II&#13;
8    300 -          0.6&#13;
C 01 5\&#13;
0 &#13;
2000                    10        20 0040504&#13;
u.u                           I'             I    &#13;
Cas A       0          4110                 2071                 26             ne     Yers Dfct-&#13;
Case B   0         80        264        720       2013       7370&#13;
('ndex of Deficit =(Consumption -Mean Annual Increment)-.Mean Annual Increment, %)&#13;
A = Example with No Felling for Land Clearance&#13;
B = Example Where Rate of Felling for Land Clearance = Mean Annual Increment&#13;
World Bank-26587&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
C=(Co/So) S exp(pt)&#13;
where Co/So is the ratio of the consumption rate to stocks at t=o. This&#13;
gives:&#13;
(ds/dt) = S(a-f-(Co/So) exp(pt))&#13;
the solution to which, taking the case where f is constant, is&#13;
(S/So) = exp ((a-f) t - (Co/pSo) (exp(pt) -1))&#13;
2.20      The term inside the exponent includes an exponential term,&#13;
showing that the rate of decline of tree stocks, under the circumstances&#13;
considered, itself has an exponential element. E.g. taking the case&#13;
where there is no felling and lopping other than for fuelwood(f=o), an&#13;
initial consumption rate just equal to the mean annual increment&#13;
(Co/So=a), a mean annual increment equal to 2.5% of stocks (a=0.025),&#13;
and a population growth rate of 3% per year, the annual rates of decline&#13;
of stocks at 0,10,20,30,40, and 50 years are 0.0%, 1.0%, 2.1%, 3.6%,&#13;
5.8% and 8.7% respectively. For a perhaps more realistic case where the&#13;
rate of open felling other than for fuelwood equals the mean annual&#13;
increment (a=f) the corresponding rates of decline are 2.5%, 3.4%, 4.6%,&#13;
6.1%, 8.3% and 11.2% respectively. Since in many regions the rate of&#13;
consumption from felling (for fuelwood and other purposes) began to&#13;
exceed the mean annual increment 20 or more years ago, one can see from&#13;
these figures why they are now facing prospects of losing the forest&#13;
cover within half a working lifetime. Initially, stocks are abundant,&#13;
and decline at around 2% or less per year; but these rates then triple&#13;
or quadruple to 8% or more within short periods, the felling of tree&#13;
stocks becoming more visible each year.&#13;
2.21      Figure 1 shows plots of the two cases just described.     Also&#13;
shown is an index of prices (or of costs facing fuelwood gatherers)&#13;
based on the reciprocal of stocks; under this assumption, real prices&#13;
and costs may double or triple in a decade once stocks are significantly&#13;
depleted, as Ken Newcombe has reported has happened recently in&#13;
Ethiopia. 13/&#13;
Ecological Consequences&#13;
2.22      The depletion of the tree cover, followed by the burning of&#13;
animal dung and crop residues, breach all three of the natural cycles&#13;
through which nutrients are returned to an initially rich topsoil,&#13;
namely (1) the tree cycle, (2) the grass and crop residue cycle, and (3)&#13;
the dung conversion cycle. The process is analyzed in a way that is&#13;
analytically useful by Ken Newcombe in the energy assessment report for&#13;
13/       Energy Assessment Report.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-22 -&#13;
Ethiopia. It is difficult to do better than to summarize his report.&#13;
The process is divided into five phases:&#13;
I - Deterioration in the ecology begins once the rate of&#13;
timber harvested for all purposes exceeds the average annual&#13;
rate of production. This may occur because of major&#13;
land-clearing projects or with the growth of demand for&#13;
fuelwood and charcoal from local urban and rural households.&#13;
Nutrient cycle 1, the "tree cycle", begins to decline, though&#13;
with an imperceptible impact on food production;&#13;
II - With further growth in the demand for and rising scarcity&#13;
of fuelwood, peasants begin to use cereal straw and dung for&#13;
fuel. Nutrient cycles (2) and (3), the crop residue and dung&#13;
cycles, are breached for the first time and the recycling of&#13;
nutrients diminishes. Use of crop residues and dung for&#13;
cooking leads to lower inputs of soil organic matter, poor&#13;
soil structure, lower retention of nutrients in the crop root&#13;
zone, and reduced protection from the erosive effects of heavy&#13;
rainfalls and winds. Hence the nutrient reserves of the&#13;
topsoil begins to decline;&#13;
III - Virtually all tree cover is removed and the "tree cycle"&#13;
ceases completely. Now, a high proportion of dung produced is&#13;
collected; the woodier cereal stalks are systematically&#13;
stored; and both are sold for cash to urban markets. The&#13;
yields of cereal crops and, in consequence, animal carrying&#13;
capacity begins to decline and the land becomes overgrazed.&#13;
Soil erosion becomes serious;&#13;
IV - Dung is the only source of fuel and has become the major&#13;
cash crop. All crop residues are used for animal feed, though&#13;
they are not sufficient for the purpose. Nutrient cycle 2 is&#13;
negligible and number 3 is greatly reduced. Soil erosion is&#13;
dramatic and the top soil is much depleted. In such a&#13;
situation, extended dry periods can be devastating because the&#13;
ecosystem loses its capacity to recover quickly;&#13;
V - There is a total collapse in organic matter production,&#13;
usually catalyzed by dry periods, which were previously&#13;
tolerable. Peasants abandon their land, which has now become&#13;
desert.&#13;
The report adds that "this transition from the first to the final stage&#13;
is in process right accross Ethiopia and has reached the terminal phase&#13;
in parts of Tigrai and Eritrea".&#13;
2.23      This analysis is consistent with that of others in attributing&#13;
the process of desertification to human activity rather than to&#13;
climatological or other natural factors. E.g. the UN report on the&#13;
subject concluded that&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
"Deserts themselves are not the sources from which&#13;
desertification springs. Except for hot winds, the deserts&#13;
themselves supply none of the essential impetus for the&#13;
processes described. Desertification breaks out, usually at&#13;
times of drought stress, in areas of naturally vulnerable land&#13;
subject to pressures of population .... It is generally&#13;
incorrect to envision the process as an advance of the desert&#13;
frontier engulfing usable land on its perimeter:&#13;
Desertification, as a patchy destruction that may be far&#13;
removed from any nebulous front line, is a more subtle and&#13;
insiduous process."&#13;
For the Sahelian regions, it has been variously noted, also, that the&#13;
recovery of the vegetation after years of drought is becoming&#13;
progressively slower after each drought, and less in quantity, on&#13;
account of progressive reductions in root residues from which recovery&#13;
used to come in the past. 14/&#13;
2.24      In addition to the contribution of deforestation to&#13;
desertification, through the consumption of fuelwood and through the&#13;
clearance of lands for agriculture, numerous studies have placed equal&#13;
weight on the growth of livestock in the region, overgrazing, and&#13;
changes in cropping practices. 15/&#13;
Effects on and of Climates&#13;
2.25      The process of desertification and the drought of 1968-73 led&#13;
to extensive research into historical variations in rainfall in the&#13;
Sahel, drawing on fossil and fluvial records as well as more recent&#13;
records of rainfalls and river flows. The questions were asked, is the&#13;
climate changing for the worse? and is desertification in any way&#13;
affecting the climate? The conclusion was that the drought fell well&#13;
within the range of variability of rainfalls experienced over the last&#13;
few centuries: 16/&#13;
(i) the 1968-73 drought was not unique; drought occurred in&#13;
earlier centuries, in the 1910s, 1940s and in 1976-80;&#13;
14/       Bob Fishwick's comments on January 17, and April 23, 1984.&#13;
15/       See e.g. the review by Mr. Grainger (1983) for the&#13;
International Institute for Environment and Development,&#13;
entitled "Desertification".&#13;
16/       Taken from the papers by Prof. Sharen Nicholson of the Club du&#13;
Sahel (1982) and in the publication by the National Academy&#13;
Press, "Environmental Change in the West African Sahel", 1983.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
(ii) an unusual feature of rainfalls in the Sahel is the extreme&#13;
persistence of rainfalls above or below average over one or&#13;
two decades; persistent periods with rainfalls 30-50% above or&#13;
below the mean are common;&#13;
(iii)rainfalls are also extremely variable over space, as well as&#13;
time; "in normal years 40 or even 50% of the individual&#13;
stations experience below-normal rainfall"; and&#13;
(iv) "the possibility that human activities in the Sahel can affect&#13;
its climate cannot be ruled out. On the contrary, there is&#13;
much evidence that landscape changes ... can act to reinforce&#13;
the drought. These changes include the vegetative cover, the&#13;
reflectivity of the ground surface (due to removal of&#13;
vegetation and deterioration of the soil), and the storage of&#13;
moisture in the ground" (due to the diminished soaking up of&#13;
the rains and increased run-off).&#13;
2.26      The World Meteorological Organization have recently published&#13;
a paper supporting the fourth point. 17/ It is argued that, while there&#13;
is still some uncertainty about the macro-climatic effects of&#13;
deforestation and desertification, the micro-climatic effects appear to&#13;
be less ambiguous. Turning to policy implications, the paper concludes:&#13;
"Controlled land use, so as to ameliorate the surface micro-climates,&#13;
offers the most certain return. The maintenance of an adequate plant&#13;
cover is the key to such control. The capacity of a region to survive a&#13;
drought, and then recover its productivity, depends on its soil's&#13;
capacity to retain nutrients, organic substances, and a high&#13;
infiltration capacity. A favorable micro-climate also requires these&#13;
qualities."&#13;
2.27      Although there is a consistency of views on the likely&#13;
micro-climatic and ecological consequences of deforestation, insofar as&#13;
the likely directiors of change can be indicated, the studies cited also&#13;
point to serious inadequacies in the data base, and which preclude a&#13;
satisfactory quantitative analysis. Inadequacies in the information on&#13;
tree stocks, yields and consumption rates have already been referred to;&#13;
they also extend to the conditions and fertility of the soils in the&#13;
deforested regions. Professor Nicholson also draws attention to the&#13;
shortcomings in the systems for monitoring and understanding the climate&#13;
in the region, noting a decline of the observing networks for surface&#13;
and upper air measurements, and in data transmission systems, at a time&#13;
when the information systems need to be upgraded and expanded. 18/&#13;
Again, therefore, though the general direction of the changes in the&#13;
environment and ecology of the region, as a result of deforestation, are&#13;
17/       Paper by Kenneth Hare (Jan., 1983)&#13;
18/       Prof. Nicholson's paper, op. cit., p. (ii) and pp. 25 et.seq.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
agreed upon, the information base requires substantial improvement; this&#13;
issue is also taken up further in Part III.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
III A REVIEW OF POLICIES&#13;
3.1       There are broadly two demand-side and two supply-side adjust-&#13;
ments which might be expected to take place in areas where tree stocks&#13;
are becoming depleted; they are through:&#13;
(1) Substitution - mainly in urban areas, of commercial energy&#13;
(such as kerosene, electricity, coal, lignite or LPG) for&#13;
fuelwood and charcoal;&#13;
(2) Conservation - following changes in people's methods and&#13;
habits of cooking in ways that reduce the consumption of&#13;
fuelwood; also reducing fuelwood consumption are improvements&#13;
of the efficiency of kilns used to produce charcoal;&#13;
(3) Public and private investment in forestry;&#13;
(4) Investments in agro-forestry - that is, private plantings by&#13;
farmers and rural communities in copses, around farm bound-&#13;
aries and dwellings, or on farm lots for rotation periodically&#13;
with cropping and pastoral activities. (These practices are&#13;
known under several names, e.g. as social forestry, rural&#13;
forestry, agro-sylvo-pastoral associations, or agro-forestry,&#13;
the last of these terms being preferred in this paper.)&#13;
An overview of the policy options associated with each was provided in&#13;
Chapter I. The present Chapter presents the same arguments, but in more&#13;
detail, drawing on several reports by Bank staff and others.&#13;
Some Limitations of 'Autonomous' Demand and Supply Responses&#13;
3.2       Under the influence of rising real costs of fuelwood, both&#13;
absolutely and relative to the costs of substitutes, all four of the&#13;
above adjustments are reported to be taking place, notwithstanding&#13;
negligibly low levels of government intervention. This has led some&#13;
economists to wonder if reforestation and agro-forestry investments are&#13;
not best 'left to the market' so to speak, given a proper management of&#13;
a country's price mechanism.&#13;
3.3       There are, however, reasons for thinking that such&#13;
'autonomous' demand and supply responses are less than what is&#13;
economically desirable. Commonly cited are the low levels of&#13;
monetization of rural economic activities and an associated&#13;
under-development of capital and insurance markets to support&#13;
term-investments in trees (as in agriculture); the (large) fixed or&#13;
indivisible costs of establishing infrastructural and marketing services&#13;
in rural areas; uncertainities in the yields (or mean annual increment)&#13;
arising from changing soil conditions and the great variability of&#13;
rainfalls between locations in any year, between years, and even between&#13;
decades (see paras 3.23 to 3.27 below); and the point that the&#13;
ecological costs of overcutting are delayed and indirect, such that the&#13;
'autonomous' response itself is delayed too long (and is often too&#13;
late). In addition, there are the not-well understood issues of land&#13;
tenure, in particular, the 'commons' problem, which as Mr. Spears and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
others pointed out to us have afflicted agricultural development in the&#13;
region for a long time. Although traditional land tenure systems are&#13;
apparently changing under the influence of population growth, they&#13;
frequently remain ill-adapted to the development of forestry-related (as&#13;
of agricultural) activities and provide too little an economic incentive&#13;
for private tree planting activities. 1/ Each of these arguments poses&#13;
difficult empirical problems, and could form the subject of a separate&#13;
inquiry. For purposes of the present paper, however, it is sufficient&#13;
to concentrate on one other problem while emphasizing that the others&#13;
just listed may be important also; it concerns the external costs&#13;
arising from the felling of tree stocks.&#13;
3.4        Existing forest reserves and wooded areas in Africa are&#13;
widely exploited as a 'public' or 'free' good. This occurs both on&#13;
common land and on government land, in the latter case even where&#13;
felling is illegal, on account of the administrative difficulties of&#13;
protecting the reserves. The private costs of this consist of the costs&#13;
of people's own labor and tools. But depending on the region, the&#13;
social costs may include, in addition, one or more of the following:&#13;
(i)       The silting of existing reservoirs for water supplies and&#13;
power generation;&#13;
(ii)      the loss of prospective water supply and hydro schemes,&#13;
again because siltation problems would be too acute;&#13;
(iii)     increased seasonal irregularities in river flows, both&#13;
adversely affecting the economics of hydro schemes and&#13;
increasing the likelihood of flash floods;&#13;
(iv)      eventual reductions in the fertility of the soils in&#13;
agricultural regions, and ultimately a loss of the soil&#13;
itself, on account of increased erosion through winds and&#13;
rains; also a decreased capacity of an area to recover&#13;
from droughts;&#13;
(v)       not discussed in the present report, the loss of national&#13;
forest and game reserves; and&#13;
(vi)      the possibility of adverse micro-climatic effects.&#13;
Examples of the first five items abound in reports on the region while&#13;
(vi), as noted, is still the subject of much research, and has not been&#13;
dismissed by climatologists. Items (ii) and (iv) also remind us that,&#13;
though arable land, tree stocks and the potential energy of rivers are&#13;
1/   See e.g. Noronha and Lethem (1983), "Traditional Land Tenures and&#13;
Land Use Systems in the Design of Agricultural Projects" World Bank&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 561, and Noronha's note "Sociological&#13;
Aspects of Forestry Project Design" (Nov. 1980). AGR Technical&#13;
Note No. 3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
all properly regarded as 'renewable' resources, losses of soils and&#13;
siltation are virtually irreversible processes, and so in reality are&#13;
being treated as 'depletable' resources. 2/&#13;
3.6       There are therefore several reasons why public intervention is&#13;
necessary. Some of these are of an economic nature (external costs,&#13;
failure in the capital and insurance markets, and indivisilities in&#13;
infrastructure investments), others are partly, though not wholly,&#13;
technical (uncertainties in vields) while others are institutional (land&#13;
tenure questions in particular). The following are the most commonly&#13;
discussed forms of intervention:&#13;
raising stumpage taxes to act as an incentive both to reduce&#13;
felling and to encourage private plantings. Ideally, the&#13;
taxes should reflect the costs of avoiding the losses, i.e.&#13;
the costs of the erosion control and various planting programs&#13;
of the forestry services, and of maintaining the forest&#13;
reserves. In practice, however, direct budgetary support for&#13;
the forestry services is needed also on account of the&#13;
political and administrative difficulties of applying the.&#13;
taxes to large populations over large areas;&#13;
2/   In turn, this has led to some attempts to estimate the discounted&#13;
value of the ultimate losses in agricultural output, and in the&#13;
output of prospective hydro and water supply schemes, and include&#13;
these in the benefit streams of forestry and erosion control&#13;
projects (the benefits of losses avoided). However, such estimates&#13;
are exceedingly uncertain. In addition, there are some tricky&#13;
assumptions which merit further analysis: - (i) the resources are&#13;
being depleted for subsistence purposes only, and their use does&#13;
not contribute in any readily apparent way to the growth of output;&#13;
in fact, there may be a decline in economic output on account of&#13;
disinvestment in land, or at least a lack of maintenance of land,&#13;
in which case future generations would be worse-placed to deal with&#13;
the losses. While the use of an imputed cost to such&#13;
disinvestments might make a theoretically correct allowance for&#13;
this problem, the risks of errors in the analysis, including errors&#13;
in the estimates of effects on output,and of the 'right' discount&#13;
rate, remain very large. Further, if eventually future generations&#13;
would be worse off what social discount rate should be used in the&#13;
worst case scenarios? (ii) Obvious substitutes for the loss of&#13;
resources (including food imports for the loss of arable land) may&#13;
not be financiable or available, which would go against the&#13;
assumptions of much of the economic theory of the treatment of&#13;
depletable resources in investment analysis. For further&#13;
discussions on discount rates and external costs see Ferejohn and&#13;
Page (1977), and for papers on depletable resources, see the&#13;
readings under editorships of Vernon L. Smith (1977) and D.W.&#13;
Pearce and J. Rose (1975).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
clarification - and, where needed, reforms -   of rights of&#13;
ownership of land and of trees, again as an incentive for&#13;
private plantings. 3/&#13;
various forms of public support for agro-forestry practices,&#13;
as discussed further below (in paras 3.48 et.seq.).&#13;
These practices may not only reduce future losses, but&#13;
actually increase future output on agricultural lands on&#13;
account of favorable effects on nutrient cycles and moisture&#13;
retention in the soil; and&#13;
direct investment in forestry and erosion control plantations,&#13;
The following paper, however, is concerned only with the last two forms&#13;
of intervention, plus the 'demand side' adjustments noted above on the&#13;
substitution of commercial energy for fuelwood, and fuelwood&#13;
conservation.&#13;
The Substitution of Commercial Energy for Fuelwood 4/&#13;
3.7       Relative Costs.   In some urban areas fuelwood prices have&#13;
risen such that the private costs of cooking with fuelwood and charcoal&#13;
are now comparable to or greater than those of cooking with commercial&#13;
fuels. This must mean also that in recent times the real prices of&#13;
fuelwood have risen at rates comparable to or greater than those of oil&#13;
(in Addis Abbaba, e.g., the energy assessment mission found real price&#13;
increases averaging 9% per year between 1970 and 1983). The following&#13;
table provides some estimates of the costs of cooking with various&#13;
commercial energy sources relative to those of cooking with fuelwood.&#13;
Reading from left to right, the countries have been ranked in increasing&#13;
order of scarcity of fuelwood, with Cameroon having the greatest&#13;
abundance and Ethiopia the greatest scarcity:&#13;
3/   Again see Mr. Naronha's paper, cited above.&#13;
4/   Since fuelwood and charcoal are often marketed "commercially", the&#13;
term "modern fuels" for kerosene, electricity, coal, lignite and&#13;
LPG is sometimes preferred. However, such sources of energy are&#13;
themselves now quite old, and use of the term "commercial energy"&#13;
is adopted below.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
Table 3.1&#13;
Relative Costs of Fuelwood and Commercial&#13;
Energy for Cooking in Selected Countries (in 1982-83)&#13;
Cameroon  Senegal    N.Nigeria   Niger   Ethiopia&#13;
Relative Costs 1/&#13;
Fuelwood             1.0       1.0       1.0        1.0       1.0&#13;
Charcoal             3.4       0.9       2.4        1.4       1.6&#13;
Kerosene            10.0       1.7       0.6        1.7       0.7&#13;
LPG                  n.a.    1.3-1.9     2.0        2.0       1.1&#13;
Electricity         11.1       3.3       1.1        2.8       2.0&#13;
Fuelwood costs,&#13;
cents per KWh&#13;
of "useful"&#13;
heat 2/               4         9        11          9        26&#13;
Source: Energy Assessment Reports for Senegal, N. Nigeria, Niger and&#13;
Ethiopia, and Working Paper 6.6 (by Fishwick) for the SAR on&#13;
the Cameroon rural development project, 1980.&#13;
1/   Assuming thermal efficiencies of 13% and 22% respectively for&#13;
cooking by fuelwood and charcoal using metal pots. The fuelwood&#13;
prices used in the calculations correspond to those found in urban&#13;
centers, and include the costs of appliances.&#13;
2/   i.e. per KWh of heat output by the stove and absorbed by the pot.&#13;
The nature of the trial on which the data are based is not&#13;
described in some sources, so it is not possible to provide a&#13;
confidence interval for the estimates.&#13;
3.8       The above relative costs correspond to those obtaining in&#13;
urban areas. They vary greatly between one urban center and another&#13;
within each country depending on the degree of local scarcity and&#13;
transport costs. The figures are very rough, but do serve to make the&#13;
general point that, on account of growing scarcity, the costs of cooking&#13;
with fuelwood or charcoal are often comparable to or greater than those&#13;
of cooking with commercial fuels in urban areas. Given that the urban&#13;
population in Africa are likely to expand from around one quarter to&#13;
two-fifths or one half of the total population in the next 15 years,&#13;
this is obviously likely to increase the demand for commercial fuels&#13;
greatly.&#13;
3.9       In rural areas the costs of gathering and retailing fuelwood&#13;
are appreciably lower than the estimates used to construct the above&#13;
table, while the costs of commercial fuels are appreciably higher on&#13;
account of the high costs of distribution.   E.g. the Energy Ass ssment&#13;
Report for Nigeria notes ex woodlot price! starting at $4 per m in the&#13;
northern region, as compared to $40 per m in urban areas; on the other&#13;
hand, it found that LPG "is sold ex-refinery at $76/tonne, but the&#13;
handling costs and margins are so high (even in urban areas) that it&#13;
retails for about $462/tonne" and would retail at yet higher prices in&#13;
rural areas.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
3.10      Hence the logical policy is to concentrate investments in&#13;
commercial fuels in the urban areas, and to seek other alternatives in&#13;
rural areas (the main ones being, it will be seen, in forestry and&#13;
agro-forestry until the infrastructure is better developed). Several&#13;
people have independently come to this conclusion, including the Nigeria&#13;
energy assessment mission which concluded:&#13;
"The thrust of any fuel substitution effort will have to be in&#13;
urban areas where fuel use is most influenced by price, rather&#13;
than in rural areas where most people live outside the&#13;
monetized economy and wood is considered a 'free fuel"'.&#13;
Since urban areas include rural towns and regional cities, programs to&#13;
improve the distribution of commercial fuels could have a very broad&#13;
spread geographically, and would facilitate some substitution in nearby&#13;
rural areas. Private traders may also extend distribution to larger&#13;
villages.&#13;
3.11      Such a policy, of course, does not preclude complementary&#13;
policies to improve supplies of fuelwood and charcoal to urban areas&#13;
through the establishment of, for example, peri-urban plantations. 5/&#13;
Appreciably more than half of Africa's urban populations depend on&#13;
fuelwood or charcoal for cooking; consumption in the majority of urban&#13;
areas is still rising, and it is unrealistic to think in terms of this&#13;
demand vanishing totally even over quite long periods of 10-20 years.&#13;
While high fuelwood prices are making commercial energy more attractive,&#13;
they also increase the financial and economic returns to fuelwood&#13;
plantations.&#13;
3.12      A major issue to be faced with respect to commercial energy&#13;
supplies is the finance of the import bills in the oil importing&#13;
developing countries. The following table indicates of the size and&#13;
growth of this bill; the figures exclude the foreign exchange costs of&#13;
financing capital projects, such as hydro schemes:&#13;
Table 3.2   Energy Imports as a Percentage of&#13;
Merchandise Exports. Selected African&#13;
Oil Importing Countries, 1960 and 1981&#13;
Upper Volta                               38              71&#13;
Tanzania                                  n.a.            50&#13;
Niger                                      6              23&#13;
Kenya                                     18              63&#13;
Sudan                                      8              44&#13;
Senegal                                    8              77&#13;
Ethiopia                                  11              44&#13;
Ivory Coast                                5              21&#13;
Source: World Development Report, 1984.&#13;
5/   ...and also, of supply other fuels not discussed in this report,&#13;
such as residue and lignite briquettes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
3.13      Hence the extent to which commercial fuel substitution takes&#13;
place will be greatly influenced, in the first place, on the countries'&#13;
trade and exchange rate policies, and in the second on the efficiency&#13;
ofthe incentives' structures and the supporting infrastructural and&#13;
financial services provided to agriculture and industry. These issues of&#13;
economic management have been discussed at length in numerous other&#13;
reports. 6/ What might be added from the perspective of the present&#13;
report is that the less sucessful are the policies followed by the&#13;
countries, the greater will be the scarcity prices of commercial energy&#13;
in oil importing countries; in turn this must reduce the rate of substi-&#13;
tution of commercial energy for fuelwood and charcoal in urban areas,&#13;
and accelerate further the rate of deforestation in the region. As for&#13;
the energy policies themselves, there is no good alternative to pricing&#13;
policies based on social. marginal costs, to which a tax element might be&#13;
added to encourage conservation and to raise revenues; the latter could&#13;
advantageously be applied to the forestry programs (among other things).&#13;
The Conservation of Fuelwood&#13;
3.14      The following notes draw on the reports of World Bank staff on&#13;
experience with the so-called 'wood-stove' components of Bank-financed&#13;
projects. The Energy Policy Paper of 1980 committed the Bank to include&#13;
"more efficient stoves and improved charcoaling techniques in as many&#13;
projects as possible." The policy arose from the rather persuasive&#13;
evidence that simple designs of stoves were capable of raising the&#13;
efficiency of cooking by wood from around 5-10% to 10-20%,&#13;
6/   See e.g. the Bank's report on Accelerated Development in&#13;
Sub-Saharan Africa (1980), and the World Development Report Series,&#13;
IBRD 1977-84.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
say from 7 to 15%. 7/ In addition, the use of aluminum pots, whether on&#13;
open fires, or on mud or metal stoves, has been found to add 5-8% to&#13;
efficiency, 8/ with further gains being thought possible through general&#13;
improvements in cooking habits and utensils. 9/ Overall, it is currently&#13;
thought that the efficiency of cooking could be increased frcm around 7%&#13;
for cooking on open fires with clay pots to around 25-30% (say 28%) for&#13;
cooking on metal stoves using better utensils. These are very impressive&#13;
gains which if they were to be realized would reduce wood consumption in&#13;
rural areas from around 0.8 cubic meters per person per year to around&#13;
0.2 cubic meters; this would greatly help to reduce both fuelwood&#13;
scarcity and the rates of deforestation reported above.&#13;
3.15      Furthermore, the costs of introducing new or improved&#13;
woodburning stoves and pots are also quite low. The stoves can be made&#13;
by artisans with estimated payback periods of 20-60 days, 10/ while the&#13;
payback period for aluminum pots alone (on open fires or on stoves) has&#13;
recently been estimated to be less than 20 days. 11/&#13;
3.16      Progress So Far.   Currently there are 15 Bank projects with&#13;
components to encourage the development and use of woodburning stoves,&#13;
of which three are in West Africa (as components of forestry projects in&#13;
Niger, Mali and Upper Volta) and five in East Africa. The components&#13;
are quite small, typically between 20 and 300 thousand dollars, or 1% or&#13;
less of project costs. In addition, several Private Voluntary&#13;
Organizations have been active in promoting the idea, as have AID, who&#13;
are planning to increase their operations in the area. The Intermediate&#13;
Technology Development Group (ITDC) of London reported having "records&#13;
of over 100 stove programs ..... being implemented worldwide.&#13;
(though) only 12 have been running for more than 2 1/2 years." As with&#13;
the Bank's program, the projects are all quite new, and properly&#13;
described in the ITDG report as pilot projects.&#13;
3.17      So far, however, the response to the stoves has been limited -&#13;
though information is scarce as to the extent of the response. A recent&#13;
paper concluded that "while there has been some good progress in&#13;
developing, testing and demonstrating improved woodstoves, there is not&#13;
yet, insofar as we know, any country in which woodstoves promotion has&#13;
7/   E.g. David Hughart's Staff Working Paper 346.   Efficiency is&#13;
measured in terms of heat output (heat actually used for cooking)&#13;
as a percentage of heat input (calorific value of the fuel). A&#13;
reciprocal definition, "specific fuel consumption", is often used,&#13;
but most available statistics are based on the former measurements.&#13;
8/   Newcombe's report for the Energy Assessment Mission for Ethiopia.&#13;
9/   Comments by Manibog, in a memorandum dated Feb. 29, 1984.&#13;
10/  Hughart's paper and the Energy Assessment Report on Ethiopia.&#13;
11/  Energy Assessment Report on Ethiopia.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
been sucessful on a large scale, except perhaps in Senegal where over&#13;
4,000 improved stoves have reportedly been distributed, most of which&#13;
are in use. 12/ This conclusion is applied to both Bank and non-Bank&#13;
initiatives. As to the Bank's own project experience, it was reported&#13;
in August 1982 that of the 13 projects including fuelwood components, 7&#13;
are to be implemented at a later date and 5 others have had serious&#13;
delays.&#13;
3.18      It is still too early to provide a satisfactory evaluation of&#13;
the programs, since the majority are new and, as noted, in their pilot&#13;
phases. 13/ The underlying idea, that significant reductions in the rate&#13;
of fuelwood construction are possible, remains robust, and has been&#13;
supported by numerous laboratory and field experiments.&#13;
3.19      Part of the poor response to woodstoves is said to stem from&#13;
defects in the stove designs, improper use, and the point that "stoves&#13;
designed to be smokeless were not suitable to users who prefer a certain&#13;
level of smokiness to reduce insect pests and maintain thatched roofs."&#13;
The stove designs and materials vary from one country to another, and it&#13;
seems that there is still some experimentation and testing to be done&#13;
before satisfactory models are found. In an FAO stove conference it was&#13;
reported that the "stove groups consider most unfortunate the tendency&#13;
to expect large numbers disseminated by now since all the early programs&#13;
were of a pilot nature ...... and never aimed at widespread diffusion." 14/&#13;
3.20      The relative efficiency of stoves over open fires may also&#13;
have been over-estimated. John Spears reported that, at a stove seminar&#13;
organized by non-government organizations in Nairobi, 15/&#13;
"Several African women delegates stressed the fact that when&#13;
using the traditional 3-stone cooking method, housewives&#13;
living in rural areas have already adopted effective cooking&#13;
techniques for cutting down wood consumption, e.g. by&#13;
dampening one end of the log and feeding the fire with just&#13;
12/ Paper by Manibog of August 1982; there was also a conference&#13;
organized by FAO in October 1983, involving several agencies,&#13;
including the Bank, which is reported in a memorandum by Mr.&#13;
Manibog (Nov. 9, 1983).&#13;
13/ As Mr. Manibog argued in his review paper for Bank staff in&#13;
November 1983.&#13;
14/ Manibog's Back to Office Report of November 9, 1983.&#13;
15/ Memo of May 25, 1982.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
enough fuel to keep the pot boiling; and seondly, by making&#13;
use of maize cobs or similar crop residues ..... Since the 3&#13;
stone hearth and crop residues cost nothing, and because many&#13;
women do not perceive, as a particular 'hardship', the time&#13;
spent in collecting such residues as fuelwood or twigs, there&#13;
is little incentive to change cooking habits and to invest in&#13;
$10 stove of unproven performance which might use more wood&#13;
than they currently do at present."&#13;
3.21      Nevertheless, laboratory and field tests quoted earlier&#13;
continue to suggest that gains in efficiency are possible using stoves&#13;
and better utensils; the programs are also very low cost, typically say&#13;
0.1 to 1.0 of the costs of an energy or forestry project, and entail no&#13;
serious risks for the institutions financing them. Hence it seems worth&#13;
persisting with the idea, drawing experience so far. Two lessons worth&#13;
noting are (i) ir. the past there was frequently "little or no&#13;
effort.... to survey the market.... (and) no satisfactory arguments were&#13;
offered in response to hard evidence of low fuel. savings, and low&#13;
quality control of these improved stoves." 16/ Preparatory surveys and a&#13;
monitoring of progress are obviously desirable. (ii) Forestry services&#13;
have not been successful (or even shown much interest) in disseminating&#13;
the idea, and it has been variously noted that private voluntary&#13;
organizations and the rural extension services are much better in this&#13;
task, and in working with local manufacturers and artisans.&#13;
Forestry and Agro-Forestry&#13;
3.22      As discussed earlier, forestry and agro-forestry are not&#13;
mutually exclusive but mutually complementary approaches. With&#13;
population growth, however, the demand for arable land is increasing&#13;
rapidly, which means that the need for agro-forestry practices to be&#13;
introduced in the region is also growing rapidly in importance - both to&#13;
meet the needs of rural families for fuelwood and building poles, and to&#13;
improve yields in agricultural and pastoral activities by improving the&#13;
fertility of the soils. In establishing the economic case for the&#13;
circumstances in which each approach is best pursued, the following&#13;
notes discuss: (i) yields (or mean annual increments) and how they vary&#13;
with rainfall; (ii) the relative yields of forestry and agro-forestry;&#13;
(iii) planting rates; (iv) financial returns; and (v) economic returns.&#13;
(i) Yield Measurements and Rainfalls&#13;
3.23      The yields of forests and agro-forestry associations vary&#13;
greatly from one region to another in W. Africa largely, though not&#13;
exclusively, on account of variations in the amount and duration of the&#13;
rainfalls. Professor Nicholson notes that "the further south one goes&#13;
from the Saharan margin, the greater the rainfall and the longer the&#13;
season. Rainfall gradients are steep.... in West Africa annual rainfall&#13;
increases by 100 mm with each 100 km of increasing distance south of the&#13;
16/ op. cit. p 2.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
FIGURE t AVERAGE RAINFALLS IN WEST AFRICA IN&#13;
MILIMETERS PER YEAR&#13;
200 mm&#13;
,_ - J ~~~~~~400 mm&#13;
&lt; ~~~750 mm&#13;
1000 mm&#13;
1400 mm&#13;
1800 mm&#13;
1800 mm &#13;
(Figure taken from "Agro-forestry in the West African Sahel",&#13;
National Academy Press, Washington D.C., 1983. Original&#13;
Source: Weber 1977.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
desert margin." Various attemps have been made to correlate measured&#13;
yields with rainfall; the following table provides a very rough summary;&#13;
population figures are also provided for information:&#13;
Table 3.3      Rainfall and Mean Annual Increments&#13;
of Forests and Woodland Savannas in W. Africa&#13;
Climatic              Rainfall                    Avg. Yield   Approximate&#13;
Zones          Average   Duration,  Variability, 3             Population,&#13;
mm      months       %         m /ha/year        m&#13;
Sahelo-Sahara   50-100     1-2         50        0.09               0.8&#13;
Sahelian        100-400    2-3      30-50        0.2                5.0&#13;
Soudanian      400-1200    3-5      20-30        0.4-1.6 1/        24.2 2/&#13;
Soudano-&#13;
Guinean      1200-1600    5-8      15-20        1.6-2.7 1/ not estimated&#13;
Sources: Nicholson, op. cit., for zonal classifications and rainfall&#13;
data. Keita, op.cit., for yields in the Sahelo-Saharan and&#13;
Sahelian regions; Clement (1982) for the Soudanian and&#13;
Soudano-Guinean Zones.&#13;
1/   The lower figures correspond to averages at the lower end of the&#13;
range of rainfalls quoted, and the higher figures to averages at&#13;
the higher end.&#13;
2/   Population of the Sahelian countries only; Northern Nigeria also&#13;
comes into this climatic zone.&#13;
3.24      The attached map (figure 2) shows how average rainfalls vary&#13;
with location. The Sahelo-Saharan zone, where the yields average only&#13;
0.09m /ha/year, or one twentieth of those in the higher rainfall zones,&#13;
includes the northern half of Mauritania and the northernmost regions of&#13;
Mali, Niger and Chad. The populations are small and nomadic.&#13;
3.25      In the Sahelian climatic zone proper, the yields average about&#13;
0.2 m/3/ha/year, or one tenth of those in the higher rainfall zones; it&#13;
includes the southern half of-Mauritania, the central regions of Mali,&#13;
Niger and Chad, and the northern half of Senegal. About 5 million&#13;
people or one sixth of the Sahelian countries' population live in this&#13;
zone.&#13;
3.26      The Soudanian climatic zones, include much of Upper Volta,&#13;
Gambia, the southern regions of Senegal, Mali and Niger, and the&#13;
norihern states of Nigeria; yields are significantly higher, averaging&#13;
1.0 m/ha/year. About 25 million, or five-sixths of the Sahelian&#13;
countries' populations live in these zones.&#13;
3.27      Actual yield measurements vary even more than the above&#13;
figures suggest, on account of differences in tree densities, the&#13;
quality of soils, and the degree to which local forests have been&#13;
cultivated and protected from animals and fires. The definitions of&#13;
'forests' and 'woodlands' are also unavoidably imprecise; the above&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
averages conceal measurement variations of plus or minus 50% in regions&#13;
with comparable rainfall, and a statistical confidence interval of&#13;
around +70%.&#13;
(ii) Relative Yields of Forestry and Agro-Forestry: A Project Study in&#13;
the Soudanian Zone.&#13;
3.28      The following table compares the estimated actual and&#13;
potential yields of forestry and agro-forestry projects in the&#13;
conditions prevailing in northern Nigeria; it is based on the working&#13;
paper for a Bank-financed agricultural development project in Kano.&#13;
Table 3.3  Actual and Potential Yields of Fuelwood ( in m ) from Farmland,&#13;
Fallowland and Forest Reserve in Kano&#13;
woodLana&#13;
Farmland      Fallowland      Forest 1/     Total&#13;
Area,000 ha                 3145            646            118        3909&#13;
Existing Stocks Trees/ha       3           n.a.            24           -&#13;
m3/ha                          5.4            9.0           12.0        -&#13;
Total, m m3                   17.0            5.8            1.4       24.2&#13;
Total, %                      70%            24%            6%        100%&#13;
Present Yield and Production&#13;
m3/ha/year                     0.2            0.2           0.4        -&#13;
Total, 000 m3/year           629            129            47         805&#13;
Total, %                      78%            16%             6%      100%&#13;
Potential Yield and Production&#13;
Case I:&#13;
m3/ha/year 3                   1.0            1.0            1.0        -&#13;
Total, 00 m /year           3145            646            118        3909&#13;
Total, %                      80%            17%             3%        100%&#13;
Increase, 000 m3/year 2/    2516            517            71         3104&#13;
Share in Increase, % -        81%            17%             2%        100%&#13;
Potential Yield and Production&#13;
Case II:&#13;
m3/ha/year                     0.4            0.4            2.0        -&#13;
Total, 000 m3/year          1258            258            236        1752&#13;
Total, %                      72%            15%            13%        100%&#13;
Increase, 000 m3/year 2/     629            129           189          947&#13;
Share in increase, % -        67%            14%           20%         100%&#13;
Source:  Working Paper C7 by Bob Fishwick for the Kano ADP, 1981.&#13;
1/ Excludes about 92 thousand ha used for game reserves.&#13;
7/ Hectarage multiplied by difference between present and potential yields.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
3.29      Kano is a state where population is high in relation to&#13;
woodland available.   Farms and fallowland account for 98% of useable    3&#13;
land, the remainder being forests. Consequently, a small yield of 0.2m&#13;
per hectare per year over a large area of farmable land presently&#13;
accounts for 94% of the current supply from the State's 3tree stocks.&#13;
The yields of woodlands and forests are higher at 0.4 m per hectare per&#13;
year, but the forest areas are small and declining and so account for&#13;
only a small percentage (around 6%) of current output.&#13;
3.30      Turning to potential yields and production, the contribution&#13;
of forests and plantations remains low (though not insignificant) on&#13;
account of the relatively small area that could be planted given the&#13;
population's demand for available land. The budgetary problems and&#13;
wage-labor requirements of the forestry service also set limits on the&#13;
amount of planting that could be done and the extent to which reserves&#13;
and new plantations could be protected and maintained. The forest&#13;
reserves are described as being "seriously degraded through&#13;
indiscriminate lopping and felling and annual fires...(Also), a number&#13;
of reserves have been invaded by farmers, and the security of the&#13;
forestry estate is very fragile." 17/ The yields could be increased (as&#13;
assumed in the above table) by improved management of the reserves, and&#13;
it is thought that the conversion of some areas to plantations using&#13;
fist growing species might also raise the yields appreciably, up to 5&#13;
m /ha or more, over 10 times present levels; 18/ this would, of course,&#13;
raise the share of forests and plantations in total production, from&#13;
around 3-13% in the above examples, to 15-25%; but it would require a&#13;
very large planting and conservation effort on the part of the forestry&#13;
services.&#13;
3.31      The potential contribution of agro-forestry to output is large&#13;
on account of the much larger areas that could be planted. Currently,&#13;
it is estimated that th5 density of trees on farmland is around 3 per&#13;
ha, yielding only 0.2 m /ha/year; by increasing densities to 15 trees&#13;
per hectIre it is estimated that yields could be increased to&#13;
0.4-1.Om /ha/year, providing around 90% of the total increase in supply,&#13;
depending on what the plantation programs themselves yielded (compare&#13;
Cases I and II in the above table).&#13;
(iii) Planting and Production Rates&#13;
3.32      Such calculations show that agro-forestry practices hold good&#13;
prospects of increasing tree stocks and the availability of fuelwood in&#13;
rural areas. The long-run increase in wood supplies is the product of&#13;
-the area planted, and&#13;
-the yield (per unit area).&#13;
17/ Working Paper by Fishwick.&#13;
18/  Mr. Keito's study presents estiamtes of 8m /ha for managed&#13;
plantations in this climatic zone.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
Agro-forestry has smaller yields than plantation or forestry projects,&#13;
but covers areas which are very much larger. Agro-forestry also&#13;
benefits from the higher yields of "free-standing" trees, which may be 3&#13;
or 4 times those of trees in wooded areas or forests.&#13;
3.33      The area planted and maintained also depends on labor inputs.&#13;
Since farmers may outnumber foresters in the ratio of 1,000 to 10,000 to&#13;
1, it follows that, if their families spend, say, 10 days per year on&#13;
the planting and maintenance of trees, or 1/25th of the time of a&#13;
full-time forester, their total labor input would be 40 to 400 times&#13;
that which could be provided by forestry services. Hence there is a&#13;
very important institutional difference between agro-forestry and&#13;
forestry, and the encouragement of the former holds prospects of a&#13;
significant increase in planting rates, by one or two orders of&#13;
magnitude or more. It also holds prospects of being financially low&#13;
cost and, aside from research, education and training aspects (discussed&#13;
in paras 3.48 et.seq. below), financially self-sufficient.&#13;
(iv) Financial Returns to Forestry and Agro-Forestry&#13;
3.34      Plantation-type fuelwood projects have had difficulties in&#13;
showing good financial returns, notwithstanding the rising scarcity&#13;
prices of fuelwood and the low consts of labor in rural areas. The&#13;
reason is that they require significant financial expenditures on labor&#13;
and materials for the preparation of land, on fertilizers, fencing,&#13;
planting seedlings, the maintenance and protection of the property, and&#13;
on the felling and transport of the fuelwood, whereas the exploitation&#13;
of existing forest reserves involves only the costs of felling and&#13;
transportation. In plantation projects, the discounted costs of felling&#13;
are typically only 5% of the discounted financial costs of supply, less&#13;
if land values are included in the cost stream. Since the price cf&#13;
fuelwood is related to the costs of exploiting natural reserves, it&#13;
follows that plantation projects are competing against a price&#13;
considerably below their financial costs; exceptions are rural and urban&#13;
areas remote from forest reserves, where transport costs and high and&#13;
rising scarcity prices make plantations financially more attractive.&#13;
3.35      The following calculations taken from the Nigeria Energy&#13;
Assessment Report serve to illustrate these points; they relate to a 2&#13;
hectare woodlot with plantings of Eucalyptus:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
Table 3.4 Costs of Hypothetical Plantation Fuelwood Project&#13;
in Northern Nigeria&#13;
Year                  Item                 Cost, $     %    Felling Vol. m&#13;
Investment&#13;
1        Labor                               114       4&#13;
- Land Preparation                 114       4&#13;
- Planting and Fertilizing         277      11&#13;
Materials&#13;
- 1670 seedlings at $0.24          400      15&#13;
- Fertilizers, etc.                112       4&#13;
- Fencing                          966      38&#13;
- Tools                             53       2&#13;
Sub-total               1,922      74          -&#13;
Maintenance and Felling&#13;
2-7      Labor -Maintenance                  240       9           -&#13;
8        Labor - Felling                     143        6         43&#13;
9-11     Labor - Maintenance                  83       3           -&#13;
12       Labor - Thinning                     43       2          10&#13;
13-15    Labor - Maintenance                  10       0+          -&#13;
16       Labor - Felling                     143       6          43&#13;
Sub-total                 662      26&#13;
Total                 2,584     100         96&#13;
Source:  Nigeria Energy Assessment Study.&#13;
The high proportion of fencing costs in plantation establishements is&#13;
significant. Apart from the expense, its ineffectiveness on any large&#13;
scale has frequently been demonstrated, indicating that the prospective&#13;
financial returns do not motivate people strongly to invest in and&#13;
maintain plantations.&#13;
3.36      Th5 average discounted costs (at a 10% discount rate) works&#13;
out at $71/m , excluding transport and 3marketing, as compared with3&#13;
current ex-woodlot prices of only $6/m   and retail prices of $50/m   in&#13;
urban areas. Hence the mission did "not recommend starting a massive&#13;
fuelwocd plantation program for the fuelwood-short northern States.&#13;
Instead, it recommends ..... making available to farmers fast growing&#13;
seedlings for home lot planting, and ..... dissemination programs for more&#13;
efficient wood stoves."&#13;
3.37      The report estimated the costs of producing and distributing&#13;
seedlings to small farmers to be 45 US cents.   HenSe "assuming a 30%&#13;
survival rate and a mean annual increment of 3.9 m to meet a family's&#13;
fuelwood requirements, the investment costs per family would be $64."&#13;
Tlis investment would establish about 43 surviving trees, producing 3.9&#13;
m  per year, at a discounted average cost of $5 per year, or 7% of the&#13;
financial cost of fuelwood from plantations. The financial rate of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
return would be around 20% assuming a price of $10/m3 of fuelwood in&#13;
rural areas.&#13;
3.38      Similar   results have been found in other regions.   Mr. Spears&#13;
comments that 19/ "experience can be cited from the South Asia and&#13;
Latin America regions, for example, where average farm forestry costs&#13;
(including the inputed cost of family labor) are in the order of $250&#13;
per ha equivalent compared with more than $1,000 for government financed&#13;
plantations. Economic rates of return for farm forestry in the South&#13;
Asia Region typically range from 25 to 30 percent, compared to 12&#13;
percent for government financed plantations."&#13;
3.39      Hence the financial analysis returns us again to the&#13;
agro-forestry concept.   It does so because of the considerable savings&#13;
in labor costs that would arise from the involvement of farm families in&#13;
the planting and maintenance of the tree stocks, the same factors which&#13;
make an appreciable increase in tree planting rates in the region a&#13;
practical possibility. There would also be some savings in investment&#13;
costs, e.g. in fencing materials, which for farm trees could be replaced&#13;
by local thorns; and in transport costs, on account of the closer&#13;
proximity of the trees to rural families. The use of multi-purpose&#13;
trees, e.g. for fruit, fodder and poles, as well as fuelwood, further&#13;
increases financial returns.&#13;
3.40      Notwithstanding the financial advantages of agro-forestry in&#13;
rural areas, there remain instances in which plantation projects show&#13;
satisfactory financial rates of return. (As noted above, the Nigerian&#13;
energy assessment report rightly recommended only against "massive"&#13;
fuelwood plantation investment programs, not against plantation&#13;
investments in general.) The main instances, perhaps, are peri-urban&#13;
plantations for towns and cities remote from the forest reserves, in&#13;
which three factors enhance financial returns: high transport costs and&#13;
rising scarcity prices of alternative sources of fuelwood; low levels of&#13;
land use; and low transport costs between the plantations and urban&#13;
areas. In rural areas also it is sometimes "necessary to have fuelwood&#13;
produced as a by-product of the much more valuable pole production.&#13;
These are produced more readily from formal plantations, and should&#13;
perhaps be the main justification for supporting these types of&#13;
plantations." 20/&#13;
(v) Economic Returns to Agro-Forestry&#13;
3.41      The economic returns for agro-forestry can be expected to be&#13;
greater than the financial returns for two reasons: savings in labor&#13;
costs, and ecological and environmental benefits. (Ecological benefits&#13;
also arise from plantation projects, most obviously in watershed and&#13;
19/ Comments of John Spears, January 20.&#13;
20/ Comments of Bob Fishwick, January 17.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
erosion control areas, but also, as Mr. Newcombe's study for the&#13;
Ethiopia Energy Assessment Report found, through reductions in the&#13;
burning of animal dung and its value instead as a fertilizer.)&#13;
3.42      Savings in labor costs can be estimated directly from surveys&#13;
of the time spent by rural families in gathering fuelvood. Several&#13;
surveys undertaken in the 1960s were already finding that the time so&#13;
spent was appreciable, 21/ higher than what is likely to be required for&#13;
the planting and maintenance of trees on farms.&#13;
3.43      It is of some practical importance to find that rural families&#13;
are themselves reportedly aware of the ecological benefits. In a survey&#13;
in the Yemen Arab Republic, for example, it was found that "although the&#13;
majority of households realized the severity of current and future&#13;
shortages of fuelwood they also thought that protection of the&#13;
environment should be a major aim of tree planting projects. 30 percent&#13;
and 46 percent of the households in Ibb and Taizz respectively wanted to&#13;
plant trees for environmental purposes, e.g. halting soil loss,&#13;
beautifiying villages and towns, providing shade, etc." A survey in&#13;
Malawi came to similar conclusions. 22/ The awareness of farmers of the&#13;
benefits of agro-forestry also helps to explain the success of several&#13;
'social' forestry projects in India, where it was found that tree&#13;
planting exceeded the projects targets by appreciable amounts. 23/&#13;
Lastly, in reporting on a farm survey undertaken recently in Thailand,&#13;
Mr. Spears noted "the density of trees in the rice fields is low and the&#13;
species have not been selected for rapid growth. Nevertheless, these&#13;
trees are an important marginal source of fuel for the household and are&#13;
carefully husbanded. Indeed, all wood sources in this area are treated&#13;
carefully". 24/&#13;
Forestry, Agro-Forestry and Public Policy 25/&#13;
3.44      The evidence on the prospective financial and economic returns&#13;
to agro-forestry, on the low costs per tree planted and maintained, and&#13;
21/ John Cleave's study, (1974).&#13;
22/ John Spear's memorandum and attachments of January 20, 1984.&#13;
23/ Staff papers on Social Forestry in India. Also in the Staff&#13;
Appraisal Report (Restricted) on the Karnartaka Social Forestry&#13;
Project. The States reported on included Gujarat, Uttar Pradesh&#13;
and West Bengal.&#13;
24/ Discussion paper (draft), March 1984, for the Energy Assessment&#13;
Mission.&#13;
25/ See also the Bank's policy paper on Forestry, February 1978, and&#13;
the publication of the National Academy Press, Agro-forestry in the&#13;
West Africa Sahel, (1983).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
on the awareness of farmers as to the value of the practice, gives&#13;
grounds for encouragement that there would likely be a good response to&#13;
public programs to support practice. Moreover, the financing required&#13;
is likely to place minimal demands on the public revenue while the&#13;
programs are being developed.&#13;
3.45      Notwithstanding these benefits of agro-forestry, however, it&#13;
is clear that the 'traditional' functions of the forestry departments&#13;
merit far more support than they have received in the past, for&#13;
plantings in watersheds and shelterbelts, peri-urban plantations (where&#13;
the economic analysis shows this to be desirable) and more generally in&#13;
the maintenance of the forest reserves. Numerous reports have drawn&#13;
attention to the low, declining and unpredictable budgetary support for&#13;
the forestry services in African countries (forestry budgets are&#13;
typically less than 2% of the allocations to energy and agriculture),&#13;
and it must be hoped that the importance of developing the forestry&#13;
services will soon be recognized - and reflected in budgetary&#13;
allocations.&#13;
3.46      It is not only the budgetary support for planting programs&#13;
that is lacking, however, but for investment in information, in forestry&#13;
research, educetion and training; and in nurseries and seedling&#13;
distribution programs. The following comments on these topics.&#13;
(i) Investment in Information&#13;
3.47      Although the broad trends in demand and supply are clear, data&#13;
on fuelwood consumption, tree stocks, yields and depletion rates are&#13;
exceedingly poor; the regional variations in these quantities within and&#13;
across countries are appreciable. Hence a priority for the forestry and&#13;
energy departments much be the establishment of a proper information&#13;
base for planning purposes, and a svstem for monitoring the changes&#13;
taking place. A related need for project design is for sociological&#13;
surveys into questions of ownership rights, of land and of trees, since&#13;
traditional tenure systems "may prevail and, at times, run counter to&#13;
formal legislation." 26/ Surveys are also necessary for a proper&#13;
understanding of demand.   Available surveys have found that farmers&#13;
plant trees for several purposes, besides fuelwood and erosion control,&#13;
such as for fruit, fodder, building poles and shade, and are more likely&#13;
to be responsive to programs if the nurseries, public or private, can&#13;
ensure a ready supply of trees suited to their purposes.&#13;
3.48      The information base for research into, and the monitoring of,&#13;
climate and the changing ecology of Africa leaves much to be desired,&#13;
and has been a source of concern among scientists. Analyses of climate&#13;
and ecology go together becaue of feedback between the two: the effects&#13;
of climate on soil fertility and, less understood, the micro-climatic&#13;
effects of changes in the vegetative cover the moisture content of the&#13;
26/ AGR Technical Note No. 3, "Sociological Aspects of Forestry Project&#13;
Design" by Noronha, 1980.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
soil, surface evaporation, and the reflectivity of the ground surface.&#13;
As noted earlier, Professor Nicholson has drawn attention to a serious&#13;
deterioration of observation and data transmission networks for surface&#13;
and upper air measurementsin the Sahelian region, while the ecological&#13;
changes taking place are poorly monitored - when they are monitored at&#13;
all.&#13;
3.49      Research, Training and Education&#13;
The changing emphasis in the arid and semi-arid zones of West&#13;
Africa to tree planting vore closely associated with, and carried out by&#13;
private house-owners and farmers, requires fundamental changes in the&#13;
priorities of forestry research, university curricula and technician&#13;
training. Research and extension linkages in forestry scarcely exist&#13;
today in the majority of the West African countries. It is noteworthy&#13;
also that forestry is never included in T and V agricultural extension&#13;
programs. A successful blending will be necessary to resolve the&#13;
increasingly severe fuelwood supply problems facing many communities i&#13;
Africa.&#13;
3.50      Research.  A recent Bank paper on desertification in West&#13;
Africa has made the following points: 27/&#13;
(a)  existing national research centres should be utilized and&#13;
strengthened. This coud be helped by "twinning" institutions&#13;
in developed countries with national research centres in the&#13;
developing countries.&#13;
(b) there are good reasons for establishing a regional center in&#13;
West Africa to specialize in agro-sylvo-pastotal resarch, or&#13;
at least to coordinate it. A start to this proposal would be&#13;
to collect all the information available on past research&#13;
efforts in this region.&#13;
(c) Technologies. Although tree-planting, usually with exotics,&#13;
has been sucessfully carried out in West Africa since the&#13;
beginning of the 20th century, success has been due largely to&#13;
the fact that the plantations were sited on superior sites&#13;
during a period when the rainfall in general was above average&#13;
and adequate for good tree growth. The current drought, and&#13;
dearth of good soils now available for tree-planting, have&#13;
created a situation in which it is unlikely that large blocks&#13;
of plantations now have any place in resolving the fuelwood&#13;
crisis. Nevertheless, improved technical packages are&#13;
required, and the individual survivors of the drought - both&#13;
exotic and indigenous multi-purpose species - should be&#13;
utilized for bio-technology advances. The most important&#13;
advances are likely to come from the following:&#13;
27/ By Mr. Gorse.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
breeding programs from surviving superior trees.   Rooted&#13;
cuttings and tissue culture are the techniques that need&#13;
to be utilized;&#13;
inoculation of the trees with symbiotic micro-organisms&#13;
which enable the tree roots to fix atmospheric nitrogen,&#13;
improve the supply of phosphorous to the plant, enhance&#13;
the uptake of trace elements and increase the absorption&#13;
of soil moisture;&#13;
intercropping food production with suitable trees and&#13;
shrubs, utilizing the technique involving symbiotic&#13;
micro-organisms to maintain soil fertility; and&#13;
evaluation and improvement of tree and shrub fodder&#13;
species for the important dry season protein feed to&#13;
livestock.&#13;
(d)  Donor coordination.  A missing link in forestry (as in&#13;
agricultural) research is the schism between basic research at&#13;
the university level, field trials by research centers and&#13;
adoption by the farmers. Part of the trouble arises from the&#13;
universities and research centers competing for funds&#13;
available from different sources. There is obviously much&#13;
that donors might do to help by coordinating their assistance&#13;
for the development of national centers, and also for the&#13;
developmert of the agro-sylvo-pastoral center proposed above.&#13;
3.50      Training and education.   West African university forestry&#13;
education has been dominated by curricula derived from developed&#13;
forestry cultures. It should be possible by now however for local&#13;
institutes to develop curricula more suited to the local environment and&#13;
problems.&#13;
(iii)     Extension services and Agro-forestry&#13;
3.51      The T and V extension programs need to include forestry for&#13;
the farmers. This need not be at a sophisticated level. The majority&#13;
of the tree and shrub species likely to be useful are robust and not&#13;
difficult to raise from seed and plant out. The intrinsic value of the&#13;
trees and shrubs to the well-being of the farmers, and the importance of&#13;
early protection until well established are perhaps the most important&#13;
elements in such an extension program. Training of the extension&#13;
workers therefore needs to concentrate on these aspects.&#13;
3.52      The involvement of the rural extension services, as opposed to&#13;
extension services provided by the forestry departments, would be&#13;
something of a departure from previous practices.   But it offers&#13;
considerable scope both for cost reducticns and for better relating&#13;
farm-tree planting activities to agricultural and pastoral activities in&#13;
a way that will enhance farm output. On the cost side Mr.&#13;
Hvidberg-Hansen has expressed the idea succinctly as follows, in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
connection with the preparatory work on a project in Nigeria: 28/ "A&#13;
major effort should be initiated to involve the farmers in the program,&#13;
primarily through the extension services. Rather than duplicating at&#13;
considerable cost the existing agricultural extension services in the&#13;
five participating states, the program should develop training&#13;
materials, data and practical information for use by existing&#13;
agricultural extension workers in a continued agriculture and tree&#13;
planting conservation/extension effort. More specifically, this would&#13;
involve close working agreements with current statewide ADPs&#13;
(Agricultural development projects) and forthcoming new State ADPs, to&#13;
establish a fcrum for joint training design and the training of trainers&#13;
and extension workers."&#13;
3.53      Experience from other regions supports this conclusion of&#13;
working with or through existing agricultural extension services, rather&#13;
than requiring forestry departments to undertake the work entirely&#13;
themselves. The social forestry projects in India have taken this&#13;
approach, with considerable success both in terms of lowering costs and&#13;
achieving a widespread response from rural families. 29/&#13;
3.54      Obviously, it is necessary for the extension services to be&#13;
supported by, and to be kept abreast of, developments in agro-forestry&#13;
research. Past experience has clearly shown that farmers will not adopt&#13;
new technologies that put their precarious food production systems at&#13;
risk, or that do not offer immediate economic advantages. The same&#13;
attitudes will face the introduction of new forestry technologies.&#13;
(iv) Nurseries, Seedling Distribution and Planting Techniques 30/&#13;
3.55      A key to fostering 'spontaneous' tree planting efforts, and to&#13;
accelerating the planting rates, is the establishment of effective&#13;
distribution systems for tree nurseries. Again, this requires changes&#13;
in the policies of forestry departments. Historically, the departments&#13;
have favored centralized large scale nurseries producing trees in&#13;
polythene pots. By contrast, for rural tree planting to be effective, a&#13;
decentralized tree nursery network is essential. In one Indian State&#13;
where social forestry is being promoted, the density of nurseries has&#13;
been increased from 1 per 83 villages in 1980 to 1 to every 10 villages&#13;
in 1983. The availability of a ready local supply of seedlings has been&#13;
a decisive factor in securing people's response. Ideally, there should&#13;
28/ Report of Mr. Hvidberg-Hansen, dated August 20, 1983. See also the&#13;
Nigeria forestry sector paper which had a special section on&#13;
agro-forestry.&#13;
29/ Staff reports on Social Forestry Projects in India.&#13;
30/ Taken from notes provided by Mr. Spears.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
be a small tree nursery at every market center in Africa, selling both&#13;
seedlings and packets of tree seed.&#13;
3.56      Improvements are also possible in techniques for tree&#13;
planting. Traditionally polythene potted stock costs something ir the&#13;
order of $50 or mere per 1000 trees. Each tree has a ball of soil&#13;
around the roots and the tree plus polythene pot weighs about a kilo.&#13;
It is difficult for a farmer to carrry more than 10 such trees at a time&#13;
from a nursery back to the farm homestead, and the distance to be walked&#13;
from the nursery to the homestead becomes critical.. In order to&#13;
overcome this, new low cost techniques have been devised and are being&#13;
successfully applied in many countries. Notable is the "basket" system&#13;
in which several hundred small seedlings are raised in a shallow straw&#13;
basket and grown to about 1 inch in height. Such a basket of trees can&#13;
be carried as a head load or on a bicycle back to the village and&#13;
distributed to a farmer's neighbors.&#13;
3.57      Another highly effective system is direct seeding.    Under a&#13;
'10 cent Tree Seed Packet Scheme' introduced in Kenya in the 1950s,&#13;
large numbers of farmers in the Kericho and Nyanza region planted&#13;
Eucalyptus and Black Wattle seed on their holdings for a very low cost.&#13;
Direct seeding of hedge species is practiced in some African countries,&#13;
and merits expansion. Few forest services have an organized tree seed&#13;
distribution system for the rural areas. Several thousand kilometers of&#13;
strip plantations have been seeded in India in recent years, and direct&#13;
seeding is commonly practiced in China. The costs are extremely low&#13;
(less than $5/1000 trees, less than one tenth of planting 'potted&#13;
stock', ignoring savings in distribution costs).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
References&#13;
In addition to the various publications cited below, the above&#13;
report has drawn on numerous field reports and memoranda written by&#13;
our colleagues in the World Bank. Most of these have not been&#13;
published and are not therefore generally available. They have,&#13;
however, been cited below to acknowledge their contributions. The&#13;
comments received on the first draft exceeded the length of the draft&#13;
by 50% and cortained much additional information and views bared on&#13;
field experience. The usual disclaimers apply. Unpublished sources&#13;
are marked thus, *.&#13;
* Berg, Klaus, Memo on Woodburning Stoves, September 1, 1982.&#13;
Cleave (1974). African Farmers: Labor Use in the Development of&#13;
Smallholder Agriculture. Praeger Press.&#13;
Clement, Jean (1982) "Estimation des Volumes et de la Productivite&#13;
des Formations Mistes Forestiers et Gramineenes Tropical,"&#13;
Centre Technique Foresties Tropical.&#13;
* Falloux, Francois (1983) Sierra Leone: Analysis of Land Issues,&#13;
January 1983 (Draft).&#13;
* Fishwick, Robert. Working Paper C6 for SAR on Cameroon Rural&#13;
Development Project.&#13;
* Ibid. Working Paper C7 for Kano State ADP (1981).&#13;
* Ibid. Memo on Woodburning Stoves (August 30, 1982).&#13;
* Ibid. Memo January 19, 1984 on Fuelwood Problems in West Africa.&#13;
Fishwick, R. and F. Weber (1983). "Shelterbelt Establishment in the&#13;
Drylands of West Africa." In Environmental Change in the West&#13;
African Sahel, National Academy Press.&#13;
* Flood, Willem, Back-to-Office Report on Woodburning Stoves&#13;
Conference, November 1983.&#13;
Fuller B.F. (1981) "Woodfuel: Planning for Solutions", Zimbabwe&#13;
Science News, Vol 15, No.1, January.&#13;
* Gorse, Jean. Briefing Paper for the Club du Sahel Conference of&#13;
October 28-19, 1983, dated October 19, 1983.&#13;
*  Ibid.  Memo of January 10, 1984, on Fuelwood Problems in West Africa.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
* Ibid. With others. Draft note on Desertification Control in the&#13;
Soudanian and Sahelian Zones in West Africa.&#13;
Grainger Alan. (1983) Desertication, International Institute for&#13;
Environment and Development.&#13;
* Grut, Michael. Memo of 30 September 1983, on Fuelwood Project in East&#13;
Africa.&#13;
*  Ibid.  Memo February 24, 1984 on the same subject.&#13;
*  Ibid.  Background on Forestry Project in Niger, 1977.&#13;
Guppy, Nicholas. "Tropical Deforestation" Foreign Affairs, Spring&#13;
1984.&#13;
Hare, Kenneth (1983) "Climate and Desertification" WMO, Environment&#13;
Program. (Mimeo)&#13;
Hughert, D. (1979) "Prospects for Traditional and Non-Conventional&#13;
Energy Sources in Developing Countries," IBRD Staff Working&#13;
Paper 346.&#13;
* Hvidberg-Hansen, H. August 20, 1983. Nigeria - PreAppraisal Report&#13;
for the Second Forestry Project.&#13;
IBRD. The Energy Transition in Developing Countries (1983).&#13;
IBRD. Energy in Developing Countries (1980).&#13;
* IBRD/UNIDO. Energy Assessment Series: Sudan (1983), Ethiopia (1983),&#13;
Niger (1983), Senegal (1983), Nigeria (1983), Mauritania&#13;
(1984), Malawi (1982), Kenya (1982), Ivory Coast (1984),&#13;
Liberia (1984).&#13;
*  IBRD.  Nigeria Forestry Sector Paper, 1982.&#13;
*  IBRD:  Karnataka Social Forestry Project Staff Appraisal Report,&#13;
1983.&#13;
*  IBRD:  India-Forestry Education, Training, Research and Extension&#13;
Sub-Sector Review (October 1983).&#13;
*  IBRD:  Malawi: Phase II of National Rural Development Program (Wood&#13;
Energy Project).&#13;
IBRD.  Forestry:. Sector Policy Paper (1978).&#13;
IBRD/FAO. "Forestry Research Needs in Developing Countries - Time&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
for a Reappraisal? Paper for the 17th Congress of the&#13;
International Union Forestry Research Organization, Kyoto,&#13;
Japan, 6-17 Sept. 1981. (Mimeo)&#13;
IBRD. World Development Report Series, 1978-84.&#13;
IBRD. Accelerated Development in Sub-Saharan Africa (1980).&#13;
* J. Spears. Note on Fuelwood Operations of the Bank, 15 September&#13;
1982&#13;
*      Ibid.  Memo - Memorandum on Fuelwood Based Energy Lending&#13;
Potential in West Africa, June 16, 1983.&#13;
*  Ibid.  Memo of May 25, 982, on woodburning stoves.&#13;
*  Ibid.  Memo of January 20, 1984, on Fuelwood Problems in West Africa.&#13;
*  Ibid.  FY83 Review of Forestry Projects.&#13;
Ibid.  Draft, 1983.   Sectoral Paper on Forests, Executive Summary,&#13;
World Resources Institute.&#13;
Keita, M.N. "Les Disponibilites de Bois de Feu en Region Sahelienne&#13;
de L' Afrique Occidental - Situation et Perspectives" FAO,&#13;
Rome.&#13;
* Manibog, Fernando. August, 1982. Progress Report on Woodburning&#13;
Stoves&#13;
*  Ibid.  November 9, 1983.   Back-to-Office Report on FAO Conference on&#13;
Woodburning Stoves.&#13;
*  Ibid.  Memorandum of February 29, 1984, on The Fuelwood Situation in&#13;
West African Countries.&#13;
* Newcommber, Ken (1983). "An Economic Justification for Rural&#13;
Afforestation: The Case of Ethiopia" Energy Department Paper&#13;
(Draft).&#13;
* Ibid. Memo of January 6, 1984, on Fuelwood Problems in West Africa.&#13;
Nicholson, Sharon (1982) "The Sahel: A Climatic Perspective" Report&#13;
for the Club du Sahel.&#13;
* Noronha, Raymond.    "Sociological Aspects of Forestry Project Design"&#13;
IBRD Technical Note No. 3 for the Agricultural and Forestry&#13;
Projects Staff, November 1980.&#13;
Noronha, Raymond and Lethem, Francis J., "Traditional Land Tenures&#13;
and Land Use Systems in teh Design of Agricultural Projects"&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Papers, No. 561 (1981).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
Page, Talbot and Ferejohn, John (1977) "On the Foundations of&#13;
Intertemporal Choice" American Economics Association&#13;
Proceedings of December Meetings.&#13;
Pearce, D.W. with the assistance of J. Rose, The Economics of&#13;
Natural Resource Depletion, MacMillan Press Ltd, London, 1975.&#13;
* Schramm, Gunter. "Background Notes on Household Energy Use in&#13;
Africa, Memo, April 1984.&#13;
Smith, Vernon L. (Ed.), Economics of Natural and Environmental&#13;
Resources, Gordon and Breach, New York, 1977.&#13;
United Nations (1977). Conference on Desertification: Report on&#13;
Round-up, Plan of Action and Resolution.&#13;
U.S. National Research Council, National Academy Press.&#13;
Environmental Change in the West African Sahel (1983).&#13;
U.S. National Research Council, National Academy Press.&#13;
Agro-Forestry in the Sahel.&#13;
* Wilton, Max. Memo of March 2, 1984, on the Fuelwood Problems in West&#13;
Africa.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
W   orld    Bank                          The Agricultural Development             their productivity. Valuable to policy-&#13;
Wo .td   Bank                     Experience of Algeria,                   makers, project designers, rural sociol-&#13;
Pl   Nka        tiE Morocco, and Tunisia: A                                        ogists, extension workers, and other&#13;
FUbIlcatIotm                    M~~~~omprocco, and  Stunteisia   A o    agricultural researchers.&#13;
of Related                                Comtparson of Strategies for             1984. 176 pages.&#13;
Interest                                  Kevin M. Cleaver                         ISBN 0-8213-0301-5.Stock No. BK 0301.&#13;
Compares agricultural experience of      $13.50.&#13;
Algeria, Morocco, and Tunisia. Pro-&#13;
vides insights into the importance of&#13;
food and agriculture for development,        NEW&#13;
and determinants of agricultural&#13;
Adoption of Agricultural                  growth.                                  Agricultural Extension: The&#13;
Innovations in Developing                 Staff Working Paper No. 552. 1983. 55    Training and Visit System&#13;
Countries: A Survey                       pages.                                   Daniel Benor, James Q. Harrison,&#13;
Gershon Feder, Richard Just,and           ISBN 0-8213-0120-9. Stock No. WP 0552.   and Michael Baxter&#13;
David Silberman                           $3Contains guidelines for reform of agri-&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 542. 1982. 65                                              cultural extension services along the&#13;
pages.                                                                             lines of the training and visit system.&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0103-9. Stock No. WP 0542.                                             The central objective-making the&#13;
$3.                                       The Agricultural Economy of              most efficient use of resources avail-&#13;
Northeast Brazil                         able to govemments and farmers-is&#13;
Agraria  Refor  asUGary P. Kutcher and Pasquale L.      achieved through encouraging and fa-&#13;
Agrarian Reformn as Unfinished            Scandizzo                                cilitating feedback from farmers to re-&#13;
Business--the Selected Papers             This study, based on an agricultural     search workers through extension per-&#13;
of Wolf Ladejinsky                                           ~~~~~~~~~~~~~sonnel who visit and advise farmers&#13;
of Wolf Ladejinsky                        survey of 8,000 farms, assesses the ex-  on a r    lar,  and s dule thus&#13;
L.ouis J. Walinsky, editor                tent and root causes of pervasive rural  on a regular, fixed schedule, thus&#13;
Studies in agrarian policy and land re-   poverty in northeast Brazil. The au-     helping research to solve actual pro-&#13;
form spanning four decades, grouped       thors review a number of policy and      duction constraints faced by the&#13;
chronologically according to Ladejin-     project options; they conclude that&#13;
sky's years in Washington, Tokyo, and     courageous land reform is the only ef-   Explains the complex relationships in&#13;
Vietnam and while at the Ford Foun-       fective means of dealing with the        training and visit extension and draws&#13;
dation and the World Bank.Oxford          problem.                                 attention to the range of considera-&#13;
University Press, 1977. 614 pages (in-    The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1982.  tions that are important to implement-&#13;
cluding appendixes, index).               288 pages.                               ing the system.&#13;
LC 77-24254. ISBN 0-19-920095-5, Stock    LC 81-47615. ISBN 0-8018-2581-4, Stock   1984. 95 pages.&#13;
No. OX 920095. $32.50 hardcover; ISBN     No. IH 2581. $25.00 hardcover.           ISBN 0-8213-0140-3. Stock No. BK 0140.&#13;
0-19-920098-X, Stock No. OX 920098,                                                $5.&#13;
$14.95 paperback.&#13;
Agrarian Reforms in                                                                Agricultural Land Settlement&#13;
Developing Rural Economies                    NEW                                  Theodore J. Goering, coordinating&#13;
Characterized by Interlinked                                                       author&#13;
Credit and Tenancy Markets                Agricultural Extension by                Examines selected issues related to the&#13;
Avishay Braverman and T.N.                Training and Visit: The Asian            World Bank's lending for land settle-&#13;
Srinivasan                                Experience                               ment and gives estimates of the global&#13;
Srinivasan           Edited by Michael M. Cemea,             ~~~~rate of settlement andthe world's ulti-&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 433. 1980. 32     Edited by Michael M. Cernea,maeptnhley                     nge     rdsutj&#13;
(includoringPaeNo43.18       2         John K. Coulter, and John F.A.            mate potentially arable land.&#13;
pages (including references).             Russell                                  A World Bank Issues Paper. 1978. 73&#13;
Stock No. WP-0433. $3.                    Captures nearly ten years of experi-     pages (including 4 annexes). English,&#13;
ence with the Training and Visit Ex-     French, and Spanish.&#13;
Agricultural Credit                       tension System. Addresses five issues:   Stock Nos. BK 9054 (English), BK 9055&#13;
Outlines agricultural credit prachices    farmer participation, the research-ex-   (French), BK 9056 (Spanish). $5 paper-&#13;
and problems, programs, and policies      tension linkage, training, system man-   back.&#13;
in developing countgres and discusses     agement, and monitoring and evalua-&#13;
their implications for World Bank op-     hon. Within this framework, extension&#13;
erations.                                 system managers and evaluators from      Agricultural Price Management&#13;
eratWorld BanksPaper..1975. 85pages(in-   six Asian countries and six discussants  in Egypt&#13;
Cluding 14 annex tabpes).                 present their experience and analyses.   William Cuddihy&#13;
cluding 14 anex tables).Notes the World Bank's strong com-               SafWrigPprN.38               90   7&#13;
Stock No. BK 9039 (English), BK 9052      mitment to agricultural development      Staff Working Paper No. 388. 1980. 174&#13;
(French), BK 9053 (Spanish). $5 paper-    in its member countries and to helping   pages (including annex, bibliography).&#13;
back.                                     least advantaged farmers to improve       Stock No. WP-0388. $5.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Agricultural Price Policies and          Stock Nos. BK 9074 (English),BK 0160        NEW&#13;
the Developing Countries                 (French), BK 0161 (Spanish). $5 paper-&#13;
George Tolley, Vinod Thomas, and         back.&#13;
Chung Ming Wong                          Agroindustrial Project Analysis&#13;
This book first considers price policies  James E. Austin                             AM.n frnP..haw 10-t&#13;
in Korea, Bangladesh, Thailand, and      Provides and illustrates a framework&#13;
Venezuela, bringing out the conse-      for analyzing and designing agro-in-                    ,    (&#13;
quences for govemment cost and reve-     dustrial projects.&#13;
nue, farm income, and producer and       E  S      i E&#13;
consumer welfare. Other effects, in-     EDI Series in Economic Development.&#13;
cluding those on agricultural diversifi-  The Johns Hopkins University Press,         l              'f 1a  1&#13;
cation, inflation, economic growth,      1981.2nd printing, 1983. 224 pages (in-  \ -.               2..,&#13;
and the balance of payments are also     cluding appendixes, bibliography, and&#13;
discussed. The second part of the book   index).                                              ,.   I&gt;. f N. ' .'&#13;
provides a methodology for estimating    LC 80-550. ISBN 0-8018-2412-5,Stock                         I    r   1&#13;
these effects in any country. Opera-     No. IH 2412, $16.50 hardcover; ISBN 0-&#13;
tional tools for measuring the effects   8018-2413-3, Stock No. IH 2413, $7.50             '               I&#13;
on producers, consumers, and govern-     paperback.                                     N L&#13;
ment are developed and applied.          French: L'Analyse des projets agroindus-    I&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press. 1982.  triels. Economica, 1982. ISBN 1-7178-&#13;
256 pages.                               0480-3, Stock No. IB 0537. S7.50 paper-  Appraising Poultry Enterprises&#13;
LC 81-15585. ISBN 0-8018-2704-3, Stock   back.                                   for Profitability: A Manual for&#13;
No. IH 2704, $25 hardcover; NEW: ISBN    Spanish: Analisis de proyectos agroindus-  Potential Investors&#13;
0-8018-3124-5, Stock No. JH 3124, $9.95  triales. Editorial Tecnos, 1981. ISBN 84-  International Finance Corp.&#13;
paperback.                               309-0882-X, Stock No. IB 0520, $7.50 pa-  Decisionmaking tool for entrepreneurs&#13;
perback.                                and project managers considering in-&#13;
NEW                                                                          vestments in integrated poultry pro-&#13;
NEW                                 jects. Use this guide to conduct on-site&#13;
Agricultural Prices in China                                                     investigation of proposed project. Fig-&#13;
Nicholas R. Lardy                        Alternative Agricultural Pricing        ure production costs and determine&#13;
Analyzes recent adjustments to           Policies in the Republic of             fixed asset and working capital for&#13;
China's agricultural pricing systems     Korea: Their Implications for           broiler operations. Analyze market and&#13;
and its effects on urban consumers       Government Deficits, Income             accurately forecast market prices. This&#13;
and overall production pattems. De-      Distribution, and Balance of            comprehensive guide tells how to&#13;
fines price ratios from key inputs and   Payme    nt                              manage integrated broiler operations,&#13;
outputs and examines price/cost rela-    Payments                                gives specifications for broiler and&#13;
tions in view of the institutional set-  Avishay Braverman, Choong Yong          breeder houses and summarizes pro-&#13;
ting for price policy.                   Ahn, Jeffrey S. Hammer                  duction costs.&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 606.1983. 84     Develops a two-sector multimarket       Technical Paper No. 10. 1983. 110 pages.&#13;
pages.                                   model to evaluate agricultural pricing  ISBN 0-8213-0165-9.Stock No. BK 0165.&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0216-7. Stock No. WP 0606.   policies, replacing insufficient standard  S5.&#13;
$3.                                      operational methods. Measures the&#13;
impact of alternative pricing policies   The Book of CHAC:&#13;
Agricultural Research                    on production and consumption of rice   Programming Studies for&#13;
Points out that developing countries     and barley, real income distribution,   Mexican Agricultural Policy&#13;
must invest more in agricultural re-     import levels of rice, self-sufficiency in&#13;
search if they are to meet the needs of  rice, and public budget. Provides a     adLed          Solis M.&#13;
their growing populations. Notes that    valuable synthesis of the work that has  andLeopoldo Solis M.&#13;
studies in Brazil, India,Japan, Mexico,  been done to date on agricultural       The principal tool of analysis is the&#13;
and the United States show that agn-     household models. Helps economists      sector model CHAC, named after the&#13;
cultural research yields a rate of return  evaluate the impact of alternative pric-  Mayan rain god. This model can be&#13;
that is more than two to three times    ing policies aimed at reducing deficits.  used throughout the sector to cover&#13;
greater than returns from most alter-    Based on the experience of the Grain    short-cycle crops, their inputs, and&#13;
native investments and cites some of     Management Fund and the Fertilizer      their markets. It can also be broken&#13;
the successes of the high-yielding vari-  Fund in Korea.                         down into submodels for particular lo-&#13;
eties of rice and wheat that were de-    Staff Working Paper No. 621. 1983. 174  calities if more detailed analysis is re-&#13;
veloped in the mid-1960s. Discusses      pages.                                  quired. The model helps planners&#13;
the World Bank's plans to expand its    ISBN 0-8213-0275-2. Stock No. WP 0621.   weigh the costs among policy goals,&#13;
lending for agricultural research and    $5.                                     which can vary from region to region.&#13;
extension, particularly for the produc-                                          This volume reports the experience of&#13;
tion of food and other commodities       Argentina: Country Case Study           using the CHAC model and also pre-&#13;
that are of importance to low-income     of Agricultural Prices, Taxes,          sents purely methodological material.&#13;
consumers, small farmers, and re-        and Subsidies                           The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1983.&#13;
source poor areas.                       Lucio G. Reca                           624 pages (including maps, bibliographies,&#13;
Sector Policy Paper. 1981. 110 pages (in-  Staff Working Paper No.386. 1980. 72  index).&#13;
cluding annexes). English, French, and   pages (including 3 annexes).            LC 80-29366. ISBN 0-8018-2585-7, Stock&#13;
Spanish.                                 Stock No. WP-0386. $3.                  No. IH 2585. $35 hardcover.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Building National Capacity to            The Design of Rural                     Economic Aspects and Policy&#13;
Develop Water Users'                     Development: Lessons from               Issues in Groundwater&#13;
Associations: Experience from            Africa                                  Development&#13;
the Philippines                          Uma Lele                               Ian Carruthers and Roy Stoner&#13;
Frances F. Korten                       Analyzes new ways of designing rural     Staff Working Paper No. 496. 1981. 110&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 528. 1982. v +  development projects to reach large      pages (including annex, bibliography).&#13;
69 pages (including references)          numbers of low-income subsistence       Stock No. WP-0496. $5.&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0051-2. Stock No. WP 0528.  populations. The third paperback         Economic Retum to Investment&#13;
$3.                                      printing contains a new chapter by the  EcnmcRtrtoIvs                  et&#13;
author updating her findings.           in Irrigation in India&#13;
Bureaucratic Politics and               The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1975;  Leslie A. Abbie, James Q.&#13;
Incentives in the Management            3rd printing, 1979. 260 pages (including  Harrison, and John W. Wall&#13;
of Rural Development                    glossary, appendix, maps,bibliography, in-  Staff Working Paper No. 536. 1982. 52&#13;
Richard Heaver                          dex).                                    pages.&#13;
ISBN 0-8018-1769-2, Stock No. IH 1769,  ISBN 0-8213-0083-0. Stock No. WP 0536.&#13;
Analyzes management problems in         $9.95 paperback.                         $3.&#13;
implementing rural development from     French: Le developpement rural: 1'experi-&#13;
a bureaucratic political standpoint.     ence    develoment 1977l ISBNer-        Farm Budgets: From Farm&#13;
Emphasizes the need to take account     ence Afr0catneEconokNca, 1977. ISBN 2-   Income Analysis to&#13;
of informal interests in managing pro-  7178     -, Stoc  o.  0545, $9.95        Agricultural Project Analysis&#13;
grams. Suggests possible methods for    paMaxwell L. Brown&#13;
assessing incentives.                   Economic Analysis of                     Clarifies the relation between simple&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 537. 1983. 74   Agricultural Projects                    farm income analysis and the broader&#13;
pages.                                  Second edition, completely revised      field of agricultural project analysis&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0084-9. Stock No. WP 0537.  and expanded                             and emphasizes the more practical as-&#13;
$3.                                     J. Price Gittinger                       pects of project preparation. Gives&#13;
Sets out a careful and practical meth-  guidance to those responsible for plan-&#13;
NEW                                  odology for analyzing agricultural de-  ning in agriculture.&#13;
velopment projects and for using these  EDI Series in Economic Development.&#13;
The Common Agricultural                 analyses to compare proposed invest-     The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
Policy of the European                  ments. It covers what constitutes a      1980. 154 pages.&#13;
Community: A Blessing or a              "project," what must be considered to    LC 79-3704. ISBN 0-8018-2386-2,Stock&#13;
Cours  for Dvelo     ing I              identify possible agricultural projects,  No. IH 2386. $15 hardcover; ISBN 0-&#13;
Curse for Developing                    the life cycle of a project, the strengths  8018-2387-0, Stock No. IH 2387, $6.50&#13;
Countries?                              and pitfalls of project analysis, and the  paperback.&#13;
Ulrich Koester and Malcolm D.           calculations required to obtain financial  Spanish: Presupuestos de fincas. Editorial&#13;
Bale                                    and economic project accounts.           Tecnos, 1982. ISBN 84-309-0886-2. Stock&#13;
Examines the importance of the Euro-    The methodology reflects the best of     No. IB 0522, $6.50 paperback.&#13;
pean Community (EC) in global agri-     contemporary practice in government&#13;
cultural trade. Points out that the EC  agencies and international develop-      Fishery&#13;
is the leading importer of agricultural  ment institutions concerned with in-    Highlights the importance of fisheries&#13;
goods and is the dominant exporter of   vesting in agriculture and is accessible  to the economies of developing coun-&#13;
a number of agricultural products. Em-  to a broad readership of agricultural   tries and recommends that the World&#13;
phasizes that policymakers in develop-  planners, engineers, and analysts.       Bank provide assistance to those coun-&#13;
ing countries must understand the im-   This revision adds a wealth of recent   tries that have the fishery resources&#13;
plications of the EC's common           project data; expanded treatment of      and are willing to develop them fur-&#13;
Agricultural Policy. Spells out how this  farm budgets and the efficiency prices  ther.&#13;
policy operates and categorizes impor-  to be used to calculate the effects of an  Sector Policy Paper.1982.&#13;
tant commodities.                       investment on national income; a glos-   ISBN 0-8213-0138-1. Stock No. BK 0138,&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 630. 1984. 64   sary of technical terms; expanded ap-    $5 paperback.&#13;
pages.                                  pendixes on preparing an agricultural&#13;
Stock No. WP 0630. $3.                  project report and using discounting     Forestry&#13;
tables; and an expanded, completely      Graham Donaldson, coordinating&#13;
The Design of Organizations             annotated bibliography.                  author&#13;
for Rural Development                   EDI Series in Economic Development.      Examines the significance of forests in&#13;
Projects: A Progress Report             The Johns Hopkins University press. July  economic development and concludes&#13;
William E. Smith, Francis J.            1982. 2nd printing, March 1984. 528      that the World Bank should greatly in-&#13;
Lethem, and Ben A. Thoolen              pages (including appendixes and glossaryl  crease its role in forestry development,&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 375. 1980. 48   index).                                  both as a lender and adviser to gov-&#13;
pages. English and French.              LC 82-15262. ISBN 0-8018-2912-7, Stock   ernments.&#13;
Stock Nos. WP 0375 (English), BK 9241   No. IH 2912, $37.50 hardcover; ISBN 0-   Sector Policy Paper. 1978. 63 pages (in-&#13;
(French). $3.                ~~~~~8018-2913-5, Stock No. JH 2913, $13.50  cluding 7 annexes). English, French, and&#13;
paperback.                               Spanish.&#13;
Spanish: Analisis economico de proyectos  Stock Nos. BK 9063 (English), BK 9064&#13;
Prices subject to change without notice  agricolas. Editorial Tecnos, S.A. ISBN 84-  (French), BKL 9065 (Spanish). $5 paper-&#13;
and may vary by county.                  309-0991-5. $13.50.                     back.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
major policy options open to the         pages (including 3 annexes, appendix,&#13;
NEW                                  World Bank in this field.                map).&#13;
Forestry Ternis-Terminologie             A World Bank Paper. 1975. 73 pages (in-  Stock No. WP-0332. $5.&#13;
forestiere                               cluding 2 annexes).Monitoring and Evaluation of&#13;
English-French; Francais-                Stock No. BK 9042. $5 paperback.         Agriculture and Rural&#13;
Anglais.                                 Land Tenure Systems and                  Development Projects&#13;
Presents terminology related to for-     Social Implications of Forestry          Dennis J. Casley and Denis A.&#13;
esty development and erosion control      Development Programs                    Lury&#13;
in arid and semiarid lands. Since fuel-  Michael M. Cernea                        This book provides a how-to tool for&#13;
wood problems and desertificationthdeianimletfonf&#13;
have become serious, particularly in      Staff Working Paper No. 452. 1981. 35   the design and implementation of&#13;
Westem Africa, the World Bank has        pages (including references, bibliography).  rural development projects. Because&#13;
become increasingly involved in wood-    Stock No. WP-0452. $3.                   rural development projects are com-&#13;
based energy and erosion-control andprje                                          plex, they seek to benefit large num-&#13;
in forest-management projects. Assists        NEW                                 bers of people in remote rural areas,&#13;
translators and researchers who work                                              and they involve a variety of invest-&#13;
in this field.                                   . ___                            ments. The need for monitoring and&#13;
A World Bank Glossary-Glossa ire de                _   &gt;    _ D i                 evaluating them during implementa-&#13;
la Banque mondiale                                            P .*                tion has been accepted in principle,&#13;
1984. 48 pages.                                    _                              but effective systems have not hereto-&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0175-6. Stock No. BK 0175.                -                           fore been formulated. The concepts of&#13;
$.                                                  _             _monitoring and evaluation are differ-&#13;
35.                                              ;F;-v        *i1Ft               entiated and issues that need to be&#13;
Improving Iffigated  ~ ~  ~     ~     ~     'considered in designing systems to&#13;
Agriculture: Institutional                                                        monitor and evaluate specific projects&#13;
Reform   and the Small Farmer                                                     are outlined, emphasizing the timeli-&#13;
Danieform and Bromley Small Farmer              t=         4ness of the monitoring functions for&#13;
Daniel W. Bromley                                                                 effective management. Elaborates on&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 531. 1982. 96                                             such technical issues as selection of in-&#13;
pages.                                                                            dicators, selection of survey methodol-&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0064-4. Stock No. WP 0531.    Managing Elephant                       ogy data analysis, and presentation. It&#13;
$3.  ~ ~ ~   ~    ~    ~   ~    MnaigElpatis directed primarily to those working&#13;
$3.                                       Depredation in Agricultural             with specific projects and will be use-&#13;
India: Demand and Supply                  and Forestry Projects                   ful to project appraisal teams, to de-&#13;
Prospects for Agriculture                John Seidensticker                       signers of monitoring and evaluation&#13;
James Q. Harrison, Jon A.                 Outlines procedures for managing ele-   systems, and to project staff who work&#13;
Hitchings, and John W. Wall               phants in and around project areas as&#13;
Staff  orkingPaperNo. .50. 198. 133part of the project design. Helps proj-  The Johns Hopkins University Press. 1982.&#13;
pages (including 5 appendixes, references,  ect designers plan activities that will l45 page.&#13;
annex).                       ~~~~~~~~protect wildlife and prevent financial  LC 82-7126. ISBN 0-8018-2910-0, Stock&#13;
annex).                                   loss from damage by animals. Illus-     No. JH 2910. $8.50 paperback.&#13;
Stock No. WP-0500. $5.                   trates methods used to investigate ele-  Monitoring Rural Development&#13;
phant behavior and ecology. Notes&#13;
Irrigation Management in                ithat careful scheduling of project activ-  in East Asia&#13;
Irrigation M nagement inities is required to ensure that ele-   v-     Guido Deboeck and Ronald Ng&#13;
China: A Review of the                   phants are not isolated in production   Staff Working Paper No. 439. 1980. 91&#13;
Literature                               areas.                                  pages (including annexes).&#13;
James E. Nickum                          Technical Paper No. 16. 1984.50 pages.  Stock No. WP-0439. $3.&#13;
Analyzes irrigation management in the    ISBN 0-8213-0297-3.&#13;
People's Republic of China. Major top-   Stock N  BK 0297 $3                         NEW&#13;
ics covered are the institutional envi-         °&#13;
ronment, the organizational structure,   Managing Information for                 Monitoring Systems and&#13;
water fees and funding, and water al-    Rural Development: Lessons               Irrigation Management: An&#13;
location. The report is based on&#13;
Chinese-language materials published     from Eastern Africa                      Experience from the&#13;
in China and now available in the        Guido Deboeck and Bill Kinsey            Philippines&#13;
United States.                           Staff Working Paper No. 379. 1980. vii +  Agricultural economists, planners, and&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 545. 1983. 106   70 pages (including 5 annexes, index).  field workers will find this 1983 case&#13;
pages.                                   Stock No. WP-0379. $3.                   study report a practical guide for de-&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0110-1. Stock No. WP 0545.                                            signing efficient monitoring and evalu-&#13;
$5.                                      Measuring Project Impact:                ation systems for irriation and similar&#13;
Monitoring and Evaluation in             projects. It illustrates the practical ap-&#13;
Land Reform                              the PIDER Rural Development              plication of the principles covered in&#13;
th  92 publication Monitoring and&#13;
Examines the characteristics of land re-  Project-Mexico                          the 198uation     Monitoring anD&#13;
form, its implications for the econom-   Michael M. Cernea                        velopment Projects. Highlights the prob-&#13;
ies of developing counties, and the      Staff Working Paper No. 332. 1979. 137  lems as well as the successes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
1983. 162 pages.                         World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 387.  permitting a full social cost-benefit&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0059-8. Stock No. BK         1980. 108 pages.                        analysis of the project.&#13;
0059.$5.                                 Stock No. WP-0387. $5.                  The Johns Hopkins University Press. 1982.&#13;
Project_Evaluation_in_Regional          336 pages (including maps and index).&#13;
NEW                                  Project Evaluation in Regional          LC 81-48173. ISBN 0-8018-2802-3, Stock&#13;
Perspective: A Study of an              No. IH 2802, $30 hardcover.&#13;
Opportunities for Biological             Irrigation Project in Northwest&#13;
Control of Agricultural Pests in         Malaysia                                Rethinking Artisanal Fisheries&#13;
Developing Countries                    Clive Bell, Peter Hazell, and Roger      Development: Western&#13;
D. J. Greathead and J. K. Waage          Slade                                   Concepts, Asian Experiences&#13;
Describes how to use living organisms    This innovative study develops quanti-  Staff Working Paper No. 423. 1980.107&#13;
as pest control agents, either alone or  tative methods for measuring the di-    pages (ncluding references).&#13;
as one component of pest manage-         rect and indirect effects of agricultural  Stock No. WP-0423. $5.&#13;
ment. Biological control offers hope of  projects on their surrounding regional&#13;
long-term-permanent-results, causes      and national economies. These meth-     Rural Development&#13;
no pollution, poses no risk to human     ods are then applied to a study of the  Discusses strategy designed to extend&#13;
health and is often cheaper than         Muda irrigation project in northwest   the benefits of development to the ru-&#13;
chemical controls. Gives methods and     Malaysia. A linear programming          ral poor and outlines the World Bank's&#13;
costs. Specifies controls for specific   model is used to analyze how a project  plans for increasing its assistance in&#13;
crops found in developing countries.     changes the farm economy, and a so-     this sector.&#13;
Technical Paper No. 11. 1983. 55 pages.  cial accounting matrix of the regional  Sector Policy Paper, 1975, 89 pages (in-&#13;
economy is then estimated. This pro-    cuig1     nee)&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0164-0. Stock No. BK 0164.   vides the basis for a semi-input-output  cluding 14 annexes).&#13;
$3.                                      model, which is used to estimate the    Stock No. BK 9036. $5 paperback.&#13;
indirect effects of the project on its re-&#13;
Prices, Taxes, and Subsidies in          gion. Thereafter, a similar methodol-&#13;
Pakistan Agriculture,1960-1976           ogy is used to estimate the project's       NEW&#13;
Carl Gotsch and Gilbert Brown            effects on key national variables, thus&#13;
Rural Financial Markets in&#13;
Developing Countries&#13;
NEW  -.        J. D. Von Pischke, Dale W.&#13;
NEW                                                                       Adams, and Gordon Donald&#13;
Rural Development in China                              Selected readings highlight facets of&#13;
Rural Development an     China                                                rural financial markets often neglected&#13;
Dwight H. Perkins and Shahid Yusuf                                            in discussions of agricultural credit in&#13;
developing countries. Considers the&#13;
Looks at China's rural development  China's rural development policy.         performance of rural financial markets&#13;
experience as a whole since 1949. Ana- Helps clarify both the strengths and   and ways to improve the quality and&#13;
lyzes China's agricultural performance  weaknesses of a self-reliant strategy  range of financial services for low-in-&#13;
and traces it back to the technology  of rural development.                   come farmers. Also reflects new think-&#13;
and other sources that made that per-                                         ing on the design, administration,&#13;
formance possible. Goes beyond the                .                           evaluation, and policy framework of&#13;
conventional sources of growth analy-        r. ural finance and credit programs in&#13;
sis to examine the political and organi-              .                       developing countries.&#13;
zational means that enabled the                      .                        The Johns Hopkins University Press. 2983.&#13;
Chinese to mobilize so much labor for             '                           430 pages.&#13;
development purposes.                   s         , .                         ISBN 0-8018-3074-5.Stock No. IH 3074.&#13;
Describes the successes and failures of            i$ 32.50 hardcover.&#13;
.g~iImbm.i~'.l.            -   ~     JRural Poverty Unperceived:&#13;
-    -               Problems and Remedies&#13;
-t    ."~            --       &gt;      _Robert Chambers&#13;
.   . '~ ., :-  .E ;..  _  -  ^Staff Working Paper No. 400. 1980. 51&#13;
s ; ' ;\-Mw oR ~~ 4 -:e.t'tS,s1   f t.2i     pages (including references).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0400. $3.&#13;
Rural Projects through Urban&#13;
&lt; v;r _,t .-g ^ Eyes: An Interpretation of the&#13;
World Bank's New-Style Rural&#13;
Development Projects&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press. 1984.  .-        M        -               Judith Tendler&#13;
232 pages.                                                             -      World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 532.&#13;
LC 83-049366. ISBN 0-8018-3261-6. Stock  ' ,                                  1982. 100 pages.&#13;
No. JH 3261. $25 hardcover.                   , 2                             ISBN 0-8213-0028-8.Stock No. WP 0532.&#13;
?'" ~~~~~~~~~~~$.''¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NEW                                 most important determinant of overall  ISBN 0-8213-0168-3. Stock No. WP 0561&#13;
economic growth, has been sluggish in  (English) $3.&#13;
Sheep and Goats in                      Sub-Saharan African countries during   ISBN 0-8213-0269-8. Stock No. BK 0269&#13;
Sheep an   oatsInthe past two decades. This overview                        (French) $3.&#13;
Developing Countries: Their             takes a three-pronged approach to un-&#13;
Present and Potential Role              derstanding the problems of agricul-&#13;
Winrock International Livestock        tural production in the 47 countries&#13;
Research and Training Center            that make up the region. It outlines       NEW&#13;
Sheep and goats are viewed as an in-    domestic and global constraints; sum-&#13;
tegral component of complex agricul-    marizes price, trade, and consumption  Training and Visit Extension&#13;
tural systems. This comprehensive       forecasts for major agricultural exports;  Daniel Benor and Michael Baxter&#13;
analysis leads to recommendations on    and project trends.                    Contains a comprehensive explanation&#13;
the need for a balanced production      Staff Working Paper No. 608. 1983. 172  of the organization and operation of&#13;
system approach for research, training,  pages (including more than 75 tables and  the training and visit system of agri-&#13;
and development programs. Assesses      charts).                               cultural extension. Emphasizes sim-&#13;
the role of sheep and goats in food     ISBN 0-8213-0221-3. Stock No. WP 0608.  plicity and decisiveness. Defines or-&#13;
production systems by examining ad-     $5.                                    ganization and mode of operation and&#13;
vantages and disadvantages, aid/donor                                          allows continuous feedback from farm-&#13;
support, constraints on contributions,                                         ers to extension and research workers.&#13;
and overcoming constraints. Empha-      A System of Monitoring and             This method has been adopted in&#13;
sizes the need for a combination of     Evaluating Agricultural                some 40 countries in Asia, Africa, Eu-&#13;
support activities and marketing and    Extension Projects                     rope, and Central and South America.&#13;
and thgeir producotsfr sRmall ruminants  Michael M. Cernea and Benjamin        Useful to extension staff at all levels,&#13;
andjethei prdcs    eiw    non           J. Tepping                             agricultural research personnel, train-&#13;
projects.                               J. eppmg                               ers, and staff of agricultural organiza-&#13;
Technical Paper No. 15.1983. 109 pages.  Staff Working Paper No. 272. 1977. 121  tions, as well as universities and train-&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0272-8.                     pages (including 9 annexes, bibliography).  ing institutions involved in agricultural&#13;
Stock No. BK 0272. $5.                  Stock No. WP-0272. $5.                 and rural development and public ad-&#13;
ministration.&#13;
Sociocultural Aspects                                                          1984. 214 pages.&#13;
ofDeveloping Small-Scale                Thailand: Case Study of                ISBN 0-8213-0121-7.Stock no. BK 0121.&#13;
Fisheries: Delivering Services          Agricultural Input and Output          $15.&#13;
to the Poor                             Pricing&#13;
Richard B. Pollnac                      Trent Bertrand&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 490. 1981. 64   Staff Working Paper No. 385. 1980. 143  Women and the Subsistence&#13;
pages (including references).           pages (including 2 appendixes).         Sector Economic Participation&#13;
Stock No. WP-0490. 53.                  Stock No. WP-0385. $5.NEW              and Household&#13;
Decisionmaking In Nepal&#13;
Some Aspects of Wheat and               Traditional Land Tenure and             Meena Acharya and Lynn Bennett&#13;
Rice Price Policy in India-             Land Use Systems in the                 Fascinating analysis of the complex so-&#13;
cial, demographic,and economric fac-&#13;
Raj Krishna and G.S.                    Design of Agricultural Projects        tors that affect women's decisionmak-&#13;
Raychaudhuri                            Raymond Noronha and Francis J.          ing role in the subsistence sector. Data&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 381. 1980. 62   Lethem                                  collected from seven villages show&#13;
pages (including 2 appendixes, 6 tables,  The feasibility of agricultural projects  women play a major role in agricul-&#13;
bibliography).                          and their intended impact are often     tural production, both as laborers and&#13;
Stock No. WP 0381. $3.                  determined by traditional patterns of   managers. Bringing women into the&#13;
tenure and land use. This paper pro-   market economy would make better&#13;
vides agricultural project designers    use of local resources and improve&#13;
NEW                                 with an analytical basis and rationale  their status and economic security in&#13;
Sub-Saharan Agriculture:                for examining systems and suggests     Nepal.&#13;
Sub-Saharan Agriculture:               how to use such information in de-     Staff Working Paper No. 526.1983. 160&#13;
Synthesis and Trade Prospects           signing projects.                      pages.&#13;
Shamsher Singh                          Staff Working Paper No. 561. 1983. 54  ISBN 0-8213-0024-5. Stock No. WP 0526.&#13;
Agricultural production, the single     pages.                                  $5.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
E! The World Bank&#13;
Publications Order Form&#13;
SEND TO: YOUR LOCAL DISTRIBUTOR OR TO WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
(See the other side of this frbm.)        P.O. BOX 37525&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013 U.S.A.&#13;
Date&#13;
Name                                                Ship to: (Enter if different from purchaser)&#13;
Title                                               Namne&#13;
Firm                                                Title&#13;
Address                                             Firm&#13;
City              State_       Postal Code          Address&#13;
Country             Teiephone (     )               City             State_      Postal Code_&#13;
Purchaser Reference No.                             Country             Tilephone&#13;
Check your method of payment.&#13;
Enclosed is my rl Check O International Money Order O Unesco Coupons (O International Postal Coupon.&#13;
Make payable to World Bank Publications for U. S. dollars unless you are ordering from your local distributor.&#13;
Charge my EOVISA [ MasterCard [ American Express L Choice. (Credit cards accepted only for orders addressed&#13;
to World Bank Publications.)&#13;
Credit Card Account Number           Expiration Date                     Signature&#13;
EO Invoice me and please reference my Purchase Order No.&#13;
Please ship me the items listed below.&#13;
Customer Internal&#13;
Stock Number  Author/ Title                                     Routing Code  Quantity  Unit Price  Total Amount t&#13;
All prices subject to change.  Prices may vary by country.  Allow 6-8 weeks for delivery.&#13;
Subtotal Cost  $&#13;
'Ibtal copies     Air mail surcharge if desired ($2.00 each)  $&#13;
Postage and handling for more than two complimentary items (S2.00 each)  S_&#13;
'Ibtal  S_&#13;
tBRDOOst                                                         Thank you for your order.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Distributors of World                    Attn: Mr. Giancarlo Bigazzi             Attn: Mr. J.M. Henandez&#13;
Distributors of World         ~~Via Lamarmora 45                       Casteilo 37&#13;
Bank Publications                        50121                                   Madrid&#13;
ARGENTINA                                Florence                                SRI LANKA AND THE MALDIVES&#13;
Carlos Hirsch, SRL,                      JAPAN                                   Lake House Bookshop&#13;
Attn: Ms. Monica Bustos                  Eastern Book Service                    Attn: Mr. Victor Walatara&#13;
Florida 165 4° piso                      Attn: Mr. Terumasa Hirano               41 Wad Ramanavake Mawatha&#13;
Galeria Guemes                           37-3, Hongo 3-Chome. Bunkyo-ku 113   . Colombo 2&#13;
Buenos Aires 1307                        Tokyo                                   SWEDEN&#13;
AUSTRALIA. PAPUA NEW GUINEA,             KENYA                                   ABCE Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel&#13;
Fiji, SOLOMON ISLANDS,                   Africa Book Services (E.A.) Ltd.        Attn: Mr. Eide Segerback&#13;
WESTERN SAMOA, AND                       Attn: Mr. M.B. Dar                      Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356&#13;
VANEiATU                                P.O. Box 45245                           S-103 27 Stockholm&#13;
The Australian Financial Review          Nairobi                                 SWITZERLAND&#13;
Information Service (AFRIS)             KOREA, REPUBLIC OF                       Librairie Pavot&#13;
Attn: Mr. David Jamieson                Pan Korea Book Corporation               Attn: Mr. Henri de Perrot&#13;
235-243 Jones Street                    Attn: Mr. Yoon-Sun Kim                   6, rue Grenus&#13;
Broadway                                P.O. Box 101, Kwanghwamun                1211 Geneva&#13;
Sydney, NSW 20001                       Seoul                                    TANZANIA&#13;
BELGIUM                                 MALAYSIA                                 Oxford Universitv Press&#13;
Publications des Nations Unies          University of Malava Cooperative         Attn: Mr. Anthony Theobold&#13;
Attn: Mr. Jean de Lannov                Bookshop Ltd.                            Maktaba Road, P.O. Box 5299&#13;
av. du Roi 202                          Attn: Mr. Mohammed Fahim Htj             Dar es Salaam&#13;
1060 Brussels                           Yacob                                    THAILAND&#13;
CANADA                                  P.O. Box 1127, Jalan Pantai Baru         Central Department Store, Head Office&#13;
Le Diffuseur                            Kuala Lumpur                             Attn: Mrs. Ratana&#13;
Attn: Mrs. Suzanne Vermette             MEXICO                                   306 Silom Road&#13;
C.P. 85, Boucherville J4B 5E6           INFOTEC                                  Bangkok&#13;
Quebec                                  Attn: Mr. Jorge Cepeda                   Thailand Management Association&#13;
COSTA RICA                              San Lorenzo 153-1 , Col. del Valle,      Attn: Mrs. Sunan&#13;
Librera Treios                          Deleg. Benito Juarez                     308 Silom Road&#13;
Attn: Mr. Hugo Chamberlain              03100 Mexico, D.F.                       Bangkok&#13;
Calle 11-13, Av. Fernandez Guell         MIDDLE EAST                             TUNISIA&#13;
San Jose                                Middle East Marketing Research           Societe Tunisienne de Diffusion&#13;
DENMARK                                 Bureau                                   Attn: Mr. Slaheddine Ben Hamida&#13;
Sanfundslitteratur                      Attn: Mr. George Vassilou                5 Avenue de Carthage&#13;
Attn: Mr. Wilfried Roloff               Makaris     3                            Tunis&#13;
Rosenderns Alle 11                      Makanios [ia   Avenue                    TURKEY&#13;
DK-1970 Copenhagen V.                   Cvprus                                   Haset Kitapevi AS.&#13;
EGYPT, Arab Republic of                 (Branch offices in Bahrain, Greece,      Attn: Mr. Izzet Izerel&#13;
Al Ahram                                Morocco, Kuwait, United Arab             469. Istiklal Caddesi&#13;
Al Galaa Street                          Emirates, Jordan)                       Bevoglu-lstanbul&#13;
Cairo                                    NETHERLANDS                             UNITED KINGDOM AND&#13;
MBE BV                                   NORTHERN IRELAND&#13;
FINLAND                                  Attn: Mr. Gerhard van Bussell           Microinfo Ltd.&#13;
Akateeminen Kiriakauppa                 Noorderwal 38,                           Attn: Mr. Rov Selwyn&#13;
Attn: Mr. Kari Litmanen                 7241 BL Lochem                           Newman Lane, P.O. Box 3&#13;
Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100                  NORWAY                                   Alton, Hampshire GU34 2PG&#13;
Helsinki 10                             Johan Grundt Tanum A.S.                  England&#13;
FRANCE                                  Attn: Ms. Randi Mikkelborg               UNITED STATES&#13;
World Bank Publications                 P.O. Box 1177 Sentrum                    The World Bank Book Store&#13;
66, avenue d'lena                       Oslo 1                                   600 19th Street, N.W.&#13;
75116 Paris                              PANAMA                                  Washington, D.C. 20433&#13;
GERMANY, Federal Republic of             Ediciones Libreria Cultural Panamena    (Postal address: P.O. Box 37525&#13;
UNO-Verlag                              Attn: Mr. Luis Fernandez Fraguela R.     Washington, D.C. 20013, U.S.A.)&#13;
Attn: Mr, Joachim Krause                Av. 7, Espana 16                         Baker and Taylor Company&#13;
Simrockstrasse 23                        Panama  one 1                           501 South Gladiola Avenue&#13;
D-5300 Bonn 1                           PHILIPPINES                              Momence, Illinois, 60954&#13;
HONG KONG, MACAU                        National Book Store                      380 Edison Way&#13;
Asia 2000 Ltd.                          Attn: Mrs. Socorro C. Ramos              Reno, Nevada, 89564&#13;
Attn: Ms. Gretchen Wearing Smith        701 Rizal Avenue                         50 Kirbv Avenue&#13;
6 Fl., 146 Prince Edward Road           Manila                                   Somerville, New Jersey, 08876&#13;
Kowloon                                 PORTUGAL                                 Commerce, Georgia 30599&#13;
INDIA                                   Livraria Portugal&#13;
Attn: Mr. Antonio Alves Martins          Bernan Associates&#13;
UBS Publishers' Distributors Ltd.       Ru    oCro7-49730-E George Palmer Hi'hwa&#13;
Attn: Mr. D.P. Veer                     Rua Do Carmo 70-74                       Lanham, Maryland. 2076ifway&#13;
New Delhi 110002                        Lisbon                                   Blackwell North America, Inc.&#13;
(Branch offices in Bombav, Bangalore,   SAUDI ARABIA                             1001 Fries Mill Road&#13;
Kanpur, Calcutta. and MNadras)          larir Book Store                         Blackwood, New Jersey 08012&#13;
INDONESIA                               Attn: Mr. Akram Al-Agil                  Sidney Kramer Books&#13;
Pt. Indira Limited                  .   P.O. Box 3196                            1722 f Street, N.W.&#13;
Attn: Mr. Bambang Wahyudi               Riyadh                                   Washington, D.C. 20006&#13;
JI, Dr. Sam Ratulangi No. 37            SINGAPORE, TAIWAN, BURMA                 United Nations Bookshop&#13;
Jakarta Pusat                           Information Publications Private, Ltd.   United Nations Plaza&#13;
IRELAND                                 Attn: Ms. Janet David                    New York, N.Y. 10017&#13;
TDC Publishers                          02-06 1st Floor, Pei-Fu Industrial       VE&#13;
Attn: Mr. James Booth                     Building                               LEN    ZUELA&#13;
12 North Frederick Street               24 New Industrial Road                   Librenra del Este&#13;
Dublin I                                Singapore                                Attn. Mr. Juan Pericas&#13;
Dublin I  Singapore                   Avda Francisco de Miranda, no. 52&#13;
ITALY                                   SPAIN                                    Edificio Galipan, Aptdo. 60.337&#13;
Licosa Conmmissioinaria Sansoni SPA     Mundi-Prensa Libros, S.A.                Caracas 1060-A&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
'HG 3881.5 .W57 W67 no.704 c.3&#13;
Anderson, Dennis, 1937-&#13;
Fuelwood consumption and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                        European Office              Tokyo Office&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                 66, avenue d'Ina            Kokusai Building&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.      75116 Paris, France           1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234           Telephone: (1) 723-54.21     Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK          Telex: 842-620628            Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                         Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0464-X&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554748">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/12/1554748/fuelwood-consumption-deforestation-african-countries
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/12/1554748/fuelwood-consumption-deforestation-african-countries</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1984/12/1554748/fuelwood-consumption-deforestation-african-countries</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/08/000178830_98101903425368/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/08/000178830_98101903425368/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-07-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1984-12-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Fuelwood consumption and deforestation in
            African countries
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The paper reviews recent reports on the
            level and growth of fuelwood consumption in Africa, and on
            the ecological, economic and possible micro-climatic effects
            of deforestation. It then reviews the economic and
            operational aspects of policies open to governments: (i) to
            encourage fuelwood conservation; (ii) to facilitate the
            substitution of commercial energy for fuelwood, where
            desirable on grounds of relative costs; (iii) in developing
            the "traditional" functions of the forestry
            services in maintaining the forest reserves and undertaking
            plantings in watersheds and shelterbelts; and (iv) in
            promoting the practice of agro-forestry, i.e. the planting
            and maintenance of trees in copses and around farms by the
            farm families themselves. All four are important, but it is
            argued that (iv) offers considerable promise in terms of
            increased planting rates, low budgetary requirements,
            ecological benefits and good economic and financial rates of
            return. The importance of the "policy environment"
            for the success of each is also discussed, as are the
            various research, education, training and other requirements
            of (iv).
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Fuelwood consumption and deforestation in
            African countries
        </docna>
        <display_title>Fuelwood consumption and
            deforestation in African countries</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1984/12/1554748/fuelwood-consumption-deforestation-african-countries</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Crops and Crop Management Systems,Urban Environment,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Wood Manufacturing and Industry,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</subtopic>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Urban Development</teratopic>
        <count>Africa</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Anderson, D.</author>
            <author>Fishwick, R.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903425368</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Forestry</subsc>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 704</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Urban Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Agriculture, fishing, and forestry</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0464</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Fuelwood; Deforestation; Agroforestry;
            Forestry; Forest conservation; Forest policy; Energy
            consumption; Climatic change
            afforestation,agricultural
            extension,agriculture,arable land,by-products,carrying
            capacity,charcoal,cities,consumers,Consumption
            Rates,cooking,cost differences,crop,crop residues,crop
            yields,cropping,dates,deforestation,development
            agencies,dung,ecological conditions,Ecological
            Consequences,ecological costs,ecology,economic
            activity,Economic policies,economists,electricity
            generation,energy conservation,Energy Consumption,energy
            demand,energy imports,exchange
            rate,exploitation,exports,externality,FAO,farm,Farmer,Farmers,farming,farms,felling,food
            crops,forecasts,forest reserves,foresters,forestry,forestry
            development,forestry projects,forestry research,forestry
            research centers,Forestry
            Sector,forests,Fuels,Fuelwood,harvesting,heating,imports,income,Inventories,labor
            force,labor inputs,land clearance,Land tenure,low rainfall
            areas,Nurseries,oil,Overgrazing,packages,plantations,planting,poles,policy
            environment,population growth,potential yields,price
            differences,Production Rates,savings,seedlings,social
            costs,social forestry,soil erosion,soils,total costs,tree
            planting,trees,urban areas,urban centers,urban households,Yields
        </keywd>
        <owner>Office of the Regional Vice Pres (AFRVP)</owner>
        <repnb>SWP704</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Demand</ml:concept><ml:concept>Currencies and Exchange Rates</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Extension</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research and Extension</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>agro forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>agroforestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forest and Forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Degraded Lands</ml:concept><ml:concept>Desertification</ml:concept><ml:concept>Dry Lands</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drylands &amp; Desertification</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops and Crop Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Exchange Rate Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forests</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT and Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agro-forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Erosion Control</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drylands</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>