<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Mexico's Free Textbooks&#13;
Nationalism and the Urgency to Educate&#13;
Peter H. Neumann        SWP54I&#13;
Maureen A. Cunningham&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 541&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Mexico's Free Textbooks&#13;
Nationalism and the Urgency to Educate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
rt.    flt, CN&#13;
-~~~~~~~~~~  .:&#13;
'1;~~~~~~~~~~~~.'&#13;
A Mdexican Child Practicing the Alpha'bet&#13;
(Oourtesy, ONLTG)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 541&#13;
Mexico's Free Textbooks&#13;
Nationalism and the Urgency to Educate&#13;
Peter H. Neumann&#13;
Maureen A. Cunningham&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright © 1982&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development ¡ THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
This is a working document published informally by The World Bank. To&#13;
present the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has&#13;
not been prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal&#13;
printed texts, and The World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The&#13;
publication is supplied at a token charge to defray part of the cost of&#13;
manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to The World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to&#13;
any individual acting on their behalf. Any maps used have been prepared&#13;
solely for the convenience of the readers; the denominations used and the&#13;
boundaries shown do not imply, on the part of The World Bank and its&#13;
affiliates, any judgment on the legal status of any territory or any endorsement&#13;
or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of The World Bank publications is described in the Catalog of&#13;
World Bank Publications; the continuing research program of the Bank is outlined&#13;
in World Bank Research Program: Abstracts of Current Studies. Both booklets are&#13;
updated annually; the most recent edition of each is available without charge&#13;
from the Publications Distribution Unit of the Bank in Washington or from the&#13;
European Office of the Bank, 66, avenue d'Iéna, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Neumann, Peter H.&#13;
Mexico's free textbooks.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 541)&#13;
1. Text-books--Publication and distribution--Mexico.&#13;
'I. Cunningham, Maureen A., 1936-          II. Title.&#13;
III. Series.&#13;
LB3048.M6N48   1982      379.1'56      82-15949&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0101-2&#13;
Peter H. Neumann and Maureen A. Cunningham are consultants to the&#13;
Education Department of The World Bank&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Abstract&#13;
Mexico has set an example other nations may well wish to&#13;
emulate. It supplies free textbooks to all its children in the&#13;
six grades of public and private primary schools. How Government&#13;
arrived at this decision twenty years ago&amp;and how the country&#13;
mustered the political will and the resources to accomplish its&#13;
ambitious goal, is described in this Study, written by experts in&#13;
the field and based largely on Mexican sources.&#13;
Textbooks often are the most cost effective means to upgrade&#13;
academio achievement and inarease the effectiveness of a school&#13;
system. Good textbooks continue to be in short supply in most&#13;
IDCs. The Study suggests ways to remedy this situation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ACXNOWLEDGMENTS&#13;
We are greatly indebted to the Mexican authorities for their&#13;
patience, their explanations, their always present hospitality and&#13;
courtesy, and in particular, for their willingness to discues in&#13;
critical terma their decisions and their achievements.&#13;
Our warmest and heartfelt thanks to go Dr. Emilio Rosenblueth,&#13;
Under Secretary for Educational Planning, Dr. Roger Diaz de Cossio,&#13;
Under Secretary for Culture, Lic. Enrique González Pedrero, Managing&#13;
Director of the National Comnission for Free Textbooks and his&#13;
Director of Production, Prof. Roberto Salcedo Aquino, Lic. José&#13;
Angel Pescador Osuna, President of the National Technical Council&#13;
for Education, Lic. Javier Barros, General Director of Publications&#13;
and Libraries and the Assistant Director, Lic. Mauricio de la Paz,&#13;
Lic. Sergio de la Vega Aguirre, Director of the Sub-Directorate for&#13;
Educational Content and Methods, and Lic. Oscar René Cruz Oliva,&#13;
Technical Secretary of CODIECLI. They, along with other officials,&#13;
opened many doors for us and provided the background as well as&#13;
much of the information and insights on which this Study is based.&#13;
Our friends and colleagues in the Mexican publishing industry&#13;
added to and deepened our understanding. Our sincere gratitude goes&#13;
to Don Abelardo Fábrega, Carlos Noriega Milera, Jorge Flores del&#13;
Prado, Luis Fernández González, Francisco Trillas Mercader, Ing.&#13;
Enrique Reyes t4orfin, Rafael Giménez Navarro, Juan José&#13;
Fernández-Gaos, Jorge J. Giannetto, and Jonathan Rose.&#13;
This Study has been a learning experience for us. It has been&#13;
challenging to analyze a wealth of information, much of it from&#13;
reports, articles, and interviews in Spanish, and to present facts&#13;
and conclusions in what we trust is a coherent, useful, and&#13;
acceptable manner.&#13;
We are grateful to the Education Department of the World Bank&#13;
for sponsoring the Study. We hope that it will be of value to Bank&#13;
staff as well as to educators and publishers, particularly in the&#13;
developing countries, many of whom we count among our friends.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PREFACE&#13;
This is a study of the Mexican çxperience with free primary&#13;
school textbooks:  their development, publication and distribution,&#13;
written for World Bank Staff concerned with education and educational&#13;
materlals. It l8 recommended reading for those in other national&#13;
and international.agencies who asslst the less developed countries,&#13;
and for educators, government officials, and publíshers who face a&#13;
similar challenge: that of providing attractive, low-cost educa-&#13;
tional materials for the children of their own countries.&#13;
The Study describes ehow Mexico met and essentially overcame&#13;
the political, economical, and technical obstacles aseociated with&#13;
large-scale national free textbook programs.   These are the same&#13;
obstacles responsible today for the critical shortage of appropriate&#13;
textbooks in most developing countries--a shortage that delays the&#13;
improvement of primary and secondary education, while.it places&#13;
additional burdens on generally underpaid, overworked, and under-&#13;
educated teachers.&#13;
By its actions Mexico has recognized that the use of textbooks&#13;
raises academic standarde and increases the efficiency of a school&#13;
system. It accords the production and distribution of textbooks the&#13;
same priority as teacheral salaries and achool buildings in its&#13;
budget allocations.&#13;
Mexico has managed to establish a large and varied free textbook&#13;
program over the last twenty years that creates a sense of national&#13;
unity ín the minds of Mexícan chíldren, and reaffírms the socio-&#13;
economic principles and goale of the Mexican Revolution. At the same&#13;
time, wíth government backing and support, the country has developed&#13;
the most dynamic private sector publishing índustry in Latin Ameríca.&#13;
This Study la based primarily on Mexican sources. It quotes&#13;
aseseamenta by government officiala and others of these book programs.&#13;
Researched and written by educational publishere familiar wlth Mexico&#13;
aud with the publishíng problema of the Third World, the Study draws&#13;
useful lessons other countries may wish to follow. In the first&#13;
chapter it summrizes important lessons learned about the development&#13;
and publication of schoolbooks intended to support the teacher and&#13;
instruct the chíld.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-iv-&#13;
Major conclusions of the Mexican experience are:&#13;
a.  Textbook development and supply require and deserve the&#13;
same priority as teacher development and school construction;&#13;
b. Textbooks must be a long-range commítment of government&#13;
supported by regular and adequate annual expenditures. Adequate&#13;
fundizg can be provided by setting aside a small percentage, i.e.,&#13;
2%-4%, of the national budget for education;&#13;
o. Policy decisions on whether textbooks should be published&#13;
by government or by private sector publishera deserve careful con-&#13;
sideration. In the Mexican experience government restraint and&#13;
support saved the Mexican publishing industry and helped to make&#13;
it into a national asset;&#13;
d.  Whether undertaken by Government or private sector, textbook&#13;
publishing requires permanent, professional organizations and a&#13;
considerable range of technical skills;&#13;
e.  Prínting ie not publishing.   The two should not be confused,&#13;
as publishing can be carried out independently of where the books&#13;
are to be printed;&#13;
f.  There are strong arguments and great benefits in favor of&#13;
providing every child in the school system with free books;&#13;
g.  Choice ís i¡iportant for teachere who prefer books they&#13;
consider appropriate, and for- children whose differing backgrounds&#13;
and abilities require a range of suitable materíals, in addition to&#13;
the guidance and interpretations of dedicated teachers, for an&#13;
education to be effective. Every effort must be made, and there&#13;
are several options available, to build choice and teacher parti-&#13;
cipation lnto a national free textbook program.&#13;
Peter H. Neumann Associates, Inc.               Peter H. Neumann&#13;
Marblehead, Massachusetts   01945               Maureen A. Cunningham&#13;
USA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
LISTING OF INSTITUTIONS AND ACRONYMS CITED&#13;
ALALC&#13;
Asociación Latino Americano de Libre Comercio - Latin American&#13;
Free Trade Association&#13;
Cámara Nacional de la Industria Editorial Mexicana - Mexican&#13;
National Publishers Association&#13;
CEMPAE&#13;
Centro para el Estudio de Medios y Procedimientos Avanzados de la&#13;
Educacd n - Center for the Study of Advanced Educational Media and&#13;
Techniques&#13;
CNLTG&#13;
Comisión Nacional de los Libros de Texto Gratuitos - National&#13;
Commission for Free Textbooks&#13;
CNTE&#13;
Consejo Nacional Técnico de la Educación - National Technical&#13;
Council for Education&#13;
CODIE9LI&#13;
Comite Consultivo para el Desarrollo de la Industria Editorial&#13;
y Comercio del Libro - Committee for the Development of the&#13;
Publishing and Bookselling Industries&#13;
CONAFE&#13;
Consejo Nacional para el Fomento de la Educacion - National Council&#13;
for the Promotion of Education&#13;
Consejo Coordinador de Sistemas Abiertos - Coordinating Council for&#13;
Open (Adult) Education Programs&#13;
Consejo de Contenidos y Métodos Educativos - Council for Educational&#13;
Content and Methods&#13;
Consejo de Programas Culturales y Recreativos - Council for Cultural&#13;
and Recreational Programs&#13;
Dirección General Adjunta de Contenidos y Métodos Educativos -&#13;
Sub-Directorate for Educational Content and Methods&#13;
Direcciín General de Materiales Didácticos y Culturales - General&#13;
Directorate for Teaching and Cultural Materials&#13;
Dirección General de Publicaciones y Bibliotecas - General Directorate&#13;
for Publications and Libraries&#13;
I,DCs&#13;
Leas Developed Countries&#13;
PRI&#13;
Partido Revolucionario Institucional - Institutional Revolutionary&#13;
Party&#13;
PRIAD&#13;
Primaria intensiva para adultos - Primary level Intensive Course&#13;
for Adulta&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-viii-&#13;
RTAC&#13;
Regional Technical Aids Center&#13;
SEP&#13;
Secretaria de Educación P'ublica - Secretariat of Public Education&#13;
SMSG&#13;
Science of Mathematics Study Group&#13;
USAID&#13;
United States Agency for International Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABILE OF CONTENTS&#13;
I.  Summary and Conclusions                                    1&#13;
II.  Introduetion                                              13&#13;
III. lsues and Priorities leading to a National Policy&#13;
for Providing Free Primary Sçhool Textbooka&#13;
A.  The Mexican Constitution, Politics, and               17&#13;
Educational Milestones in Mexican History&#13;
B.  The Nationalization of Primary School Textbooks       22&#13;
IV.  The Secretariat of Public Education (SEP)&#13;
A.  Organization and Objectives, with Emphasis on         25&#13;
Educational Programa and Materials&#13;
B.  Advisory Councils                                     29&#13;
1.  The National Technical Council for                29&#13;
Education (CNTE)&#13;
2.  The Council for Educational Content and           32&#13;
Methods and The Sub-Directorate for&#13;
Educational Content and Methods&#13;
Y. Development of the Free Textbook Program, 1959 to&#13;
the Present&#13;
A.  The National Commission for Free Textbooks            37&#13;
1.  Mandate and Charter                               37&#13;
2.  Present Organization and Duties                   41&#13;
a.  Production Department                         42&#13;
b.  Distribution Department                       44&#13;
B.  The National Pree Textbook Program                    48&#13;
1. Phase 1: 1959-1970,.the First Generation           48&#13;
of Free Textbooks&#13;
2.  Phase IIM  1970-1978, the Second Generation       51&#13;
of Free Textbooks&#13;
3.  Phase III:  1978-Present (1981), ohe New          60&#13;
Integrated Textbooks for Grades 1 and 2&#13;
4. A Sumnary of the Pree Textbook Program             68&#13;
a.  Books Produced:  Titles and Quantities        68&#13;
b.  Costa                                         69&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-X-&#13;
VI. Related Educational Publishing Activities&#13;
Supported by Government&#13;
A.  The General Directorate for Publications              73&#13;
and Libraríes&#13;
B.  The General Directorate for Teaching and              79&#13;
Cultural Materiali&#13;
VII. Private Sector Publishing&#13;
A.  The Mexican Publishing Industry:   An Overview        81&#13;
B.  Government Support of the Private Publishing          86&#13;
Industry&#13;
1.  Fiscal Incentives                                 87&#13;
2.  Copublishing Projeots                             88&#13;
3.  Protection for the Publishing Industry            89&#13;
Appendices&#13;
A.  Organizatíon Chart:   The Secretariat of              95&#13;
Public Education (SEP)&#13;
B.  Organization Chart:  The National Technical           96&#13;
Council for Education (CNTE)&#13;
C.  Organization Chart:  The Sub-Directorate for          97&#13;
Educational Content and Methods&#13;
D.  Organization Chart:  The National Commission          98&#13;
for Free Textbooks (CNLTG)&#13;
E. The National Commission for Free Textbooks (CNLTG)&#13;
1.  Table 001:  Total Nuiber of Books Produced        99&#13;
by CNITG, 1960-1982, in Millions&#13;
of Copies&#13;
2.  Table 002:  Listing pf All Titles Produced       100&#13;
by CNLTG, 1960-1981&#13;
3.  Table 003                                        111&#13;
a.  CILTG's Annual Subsidies from Government,&#13;
1960-1981&#13;
b.  CNLTG's Capital Investment in Printing&#13;
Plant: 1960, 1975, 1980&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-xi-&#13;
4.  Table 004:   Average Manufacturing Costs         112&#13;
Per Signature, 1960-1980&#13;
5.  Table 005:  Average Estimated Cost Per           113&#13;
Textbook (Produced between&#13;
1965 and 1980)&#13;
F. Mexican Book Industry Statistics&#13;
1.  Table 001:  Annual Mexican Book Trade            114&#13;
Balances, 1970-1980 (In millions&#13;
of pesos)&#13;
2.  Table 002:  Mexican Book Trade Balance,          115&#13;
1979-1980 (By geographic area)&#13;
3.  Table 003:   Estimated Paper Consumption         116&#13;
by Category&#13;
4.  Table 004:   Paper Production by Category        118&#13;
5.  Table 005:   Importation of Paper by Category    120&#13;
Bibliography                                                  123&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. Summary and Conclusions&#13;
Mexicols free textbooks for primary schools and the range of&#13;
other educational materials produced and subsidized by Government&#13;
would be an impressive achievement under any set of circumstances.&#13;
It ¡a a unique accomplishment in our experience for a developing&#13;
country.with limited resources. Nationalism and the urgency to&#13;
educate, major forces of the Mexican Revolution, combiJned to produce&#13;
the political will that has provided the organization, the talent,&#13;
and the money for these programa. As a result, by 1981 every Mexican&#13;
child ready to enroll found a place in primary school and was given&#13;
free textbooks.&#13;
Mexico views education as an investment not an expense. More&#13;
than twenty years ago Government acknowledged that free schools and&#13;
free teachers were not enough to aseure an acceptable level of educa-&#13;
tion, that free textbooks and other teaching materiala were equally&#13;
essential. In 1959 the Mexican government nationalized textbook&#13;
publishing at primary school level by establishing the National&#13;
Commission for Free Textbooks (CNLTG). Succeeding governnents&#13;
have continued their strong support for CNLTG. Mexico has been&#13;
liberal with its investment in education. The Secretariat of&#13;
Public Education (SEP), with ite hundreds of thousands of teachere,&#13;
is said to account for nearly half of all government employees in&#13;
the country. In 1959 almost 16% of Governnent's budget was allocated&#13;
to education. In 1980 the total budget for education was approxi-&#13;
mately Mp 160 billion (US$6.7 billionl). Textbooks fór primary&#13;
schools accounted for about Mp 700 million (US$29.2 million1), or&#13;
leas than 0.5% of the total. Including all the other books and&#13;
periodicals published or subsidized by SEP, Government spends perhaps&#13;
1% of ita education budget on these materiala. This ¡a an insignifi-&#13;
cant expenditure, we were repeatedly told, in relation to the total&#13;
investment in education, and yet one of the most eseential. This&#13;
1 Note: All currency exchanges are based on the rate of&#13;
exchange prevailing at the time this Study was conducted and written,&#13;
i.e., US$1.00 - Mp 24.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
uncommon insight into the relationship of academic achievement to&#13;
the availability of textbooks1 alone makes the Mexican experience&#13;
worthwhile to study for anyone concerned with the development of&#13;
education, for anyone concerned with development, and for anyone&#13;
responsible for education in less developed countries.&#13;
The struggle to provide a reasonable level of education for&#13;
all Mexicans and to eradicate illiteracy has engaged the energy of&#13;
all administrations. The present Secretary of Education stresses&#13;
the improvement of the quality of education as the main goal of hiá&#13;
administration.&#13;
In July, 1977 the National Institute of Educational Investiga-&#13;
tion issued a report on problema in education based on a survey&#13;
conducted by the Institute of the opinions of primary school&#13;
teachers.2 The information reflects the opinions of teachers in&#13;
600 primary schools, a sample selected statistically out of approx-&#13;
imately 42,000 primary schools 1n order to produce results in a&#13;
relatively short time. Opiniona of the teachers polled through&#13;
prepared questionnaires were grouped into 113 categories of problems,&#13;
classified into three main areas:&#13;
* Problems that affect learning (28 categories)&#13;
* Problema that affect teaching (74 categories)&#13;
* Problems that affect the social objectives of the school&#13;
(6 categories)&#13;
* Miscellaneous (5 categories)&#13;
Only seven problems were mentioned more than 50% of the time.&#13;
The two most frequently mentioned:&#13;
1. Economic problema of the family (72%)&#13;
2. Low teachers' salaries (55.7%)&#13;
1 Refer to Stephen P. Heyneman, Joseph P. Farrell, Manual A.&#13;
Sepulveda-Stuardo, Textbooks and Achievement: What We Know (World&#13;
Bank Staff Working Paper No. 298, Washington, D.C.:   The World&#13;
Bank, 1978).&#13;
2 "Sondeo de opinión al magisterio nacional de educación&#13;
primaria del sector federal sobre la pro,lematica educativa" (Mexico,&#13;
D.F.: Instituto Nacional de Investigacion Educativa, SEP, July, 1977).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
Of the five other problems, only one affects teaching directly:&#13;
Lack of teaching materials (53.6%)&#13;
The rest are socio-economic problems:&#13;
1. Bad health habits (53.6%)&#13;
2. Malnutrition (52.3%)&#13;
3, Poor student performance (51.7%)&#13;
It is worthwhile noting the importance of teaching materials to&#13;
teachers in this sampling.&#13;
Textbooks, obviously, are not the sole answer to the problems&#13;
teachers face in the developing countries. Nor are all textbooks&#13;
equally effective. Nationalization of textbook püblishing in a&#13;
democratic country such as Mexico goes not without challenge. It&#13;
creates a suspicion that succeeding Governments may use their&#13;
monopoly to shape the views and attitudes of young citizens in&#13;
their own image rather than in that of the nation. Moreover, if&#13;
nationalization is carried out without some measure of restraint,&#13;
it may do irredeemable harm to a countryts indigenous publishing&#13;
industry. At times, govern.ments lack the expertise to fulf1ll their&#13;
promises when nationalizing industries. This applies equally well&#13;
to the publishing industry, especially to educational publishing&#13;
with its added responsibílities.&#13;
All of these factors are present in the atory of Mexico's&#13;
efforts to provide quality educational materials. On the whole,&#13;
the experience has been positive. Among Mexican governnent officials&#13;
and private publishera we interviewed, in reports and articles re-&#13;
flecting views of parents and of teachera we read, we found strong&#13;
consensus that free textbooks have been good for education and&#13;
represent a proud accomplishment in spite of remaíning reservations.&#13;
The following pages detail the problems and the progress&#13;
that are part of the Mexican experience. We would hope that these&#13;
pages reflect as well the excitement and dedication we have wit-&#13;
nessed in Mexico, and that they provide examples and guidelines&#13;
that may serve others as useful modelo.&#13;
Criticism of textbooks ia a fact of life in any society where&#13;
freedom to criticize exists. The perfect textbook has yet to be&#13;
invented. National book programa are especially vulnerable to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
criticism as they leave the teacher and parent no choice. National&#13;
textbooks at times alienate teachers who feel that their voice and&#13;
experience have not been considered. Such teachers are likely to&#13;
retaliate by refusing to use a textbook they do not like or have&#13;
difficulty in understanding.1   If a single set of national textbooks&#13;
is to serve a country of great cultural and socio-economic diversity,&#13;
textboók materials are apt to be flawed in several ways. They are&#13;
likely to stress the urban middle class values and attitudes of their&#13;
authors, which makes it likely that rural teachers and children will&#13;
find it difficult to identify with such books. National textbooks&#13;
often expect too much from teacher and child, especially if they are&#13;
prepared by subject matter specialists at the main (urban) centers&#13;
of higher education.&#13;
There are no easy answers to such inherent problems of textbook&#13;
development and production. However, we would like to offer the&#13;
following general observations, based on long experience, not because&#13;
they have been generally disregarded in Mexico, our Study proves&#13;
otherwise, but because these are essential points that have to be&#13;
taken constantly into consideration.&#13;
The development, production, manufacture, and distribution of&#13;
textbook materials should not be carried out in isolation and without&#13;
professional competence. Institution building, teacher training,&#13;
long-range government comnitment, a comprehensive look at the book&#13;
industry of a developing country, are prerequisites for success.2&#13;
Good, existing textbooks, whether from within the country or from&#13;
elsewhere, should be studied and considered as models. They are&#13;
examples of what seemingly works in specific circumstances. Exper-&#13;
tise in educational publishing from within the country if available,&#13;
1 In fact, this has been a major problem with the Mexican&#13;
textbook programi, as it is so often the case under similar circum-&#13;
stances in other countries. It has been estimated that at times&#13;
as many as 25% of Mexican teachers have not used some of the&#13;
official textbooks.&#13;
2 Refer to Peter H. Neumann, Publishing for Schools. Textbooks&#13;
and the Less DeveloPed Countries (World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
No. 398, Washington, D.C.: The World Bank, 1980).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
or from outside, should be employed in the planning and execution of&#13;
major programs. Problems in educating children through textbooks&#13;
are more similar throughout the world than local authorities would&#13;
have us at times believe. If at all possible, choice and variety&#13;
should be introduced in the number of titles and series made available&#13;
to schools. Choice should be a local matter, made by teachers, super-&#13;
visors, or committees at school district level. This presupposes the&#13;
existence of informed selectors of textbooks, in addition to a variety&#13;
of materials prepared for differing school audiences. The latter is&#13;
being accomplished in Mexico in several ways. The free textbooks&#13;
are increasingly concentrating on providing basic education, a unify-&#13;
ing national force, and SEP is encouraging schools to acquire&#13;
supplementary texts, either from private sector publishers or through&#13;
its own offerings.&#13;
In countries where textbooks are published by the private sector,&#13;
even though they may be purchased with public money, careful choice&#13;
is a necessity, We feel that insufficient attention has been given&#13;
by developing countries to the development of acceptable methods for&#13;
selecting or adopting textbooks at local level. Lack of discrimina-&#13;
tion by teachere is frequently cited as the reason for avoiding their&#13;
involvement altogether. In certain instances, offering differing&#13;
sets of textbooks to different groups within a school system has&#13;
been regarded as a form of discrimination, or it is argued that it&#13;
adds greatly to the costs of providing free books. We do not&#13;
necessarily agree with such views. It is generally accepted that&#13;
different children need differing levels of presentation, different&#13;
amounts of material, and different motivation. The prevailing&#13;
method of allowing for such differences where only one kind of&#13;
textbook is used nationally is generally unsatisfactory. It places&#13;
the burden on the primary school teacher who is asked to provide&#13;
additional activities, exercises, and problems, as well as special&#13;
attention to both slow learners and to the brighter students, while&#13;
still taking care of the average. Sometimes teachers' manuals will&#13;
simply exhort teachers to do this giving few helpful examples,&#13;
while at other times teachers' manuals go to great length listing&#13;
nunerous activities and providing other concrete suggestions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6-&#13;
However, all of this is directed at primary school teachers who are&#13;
underpaid, undereducated, "underappreciated" by their superiors, and&#13;
perennially overworked. They already have to cope with long hours of&#13;
teaching, large classes of children, and absenteeism caused by economic,&#13;
social or health conditions. When things do not work out in the&#13;
classroom, and the low efficiency and cost effectiveness of most school&#13;
systems in the Less Developed Countries (LDCs) is ample proof of this,&#13;
the same poor, overburdened teachers generally receive most of the&#13;
blame, including the severe strictures of the textbook authors.&#13;
Nowhere in the world are good textbooks more needed than in the&#13;
LDC8. Nowhere else are textbooks required to carry such a heavy&#13;
burden of motivating, communicating, educating, Yet nowhere are&#13;
textbooks produced with a finer disregard for accumulated wiadom&#13;
and experience in educational publishing. This disregard of avail-&#13;
able models and expertise is often blamed on nationalism; it ¡a more&#13;
often due, in our experience, to a lack of familiarity with the&#13;
process by which textbooks should be developed. Patience and care&#13;
are necessary in the development of textbook materials, and a pro-&#13;
fessional editorial and publishing staff, which acta as facilitator,&#13;
líaison, and moderator between high-powered authors and primary&#13;
school teachera. Textbooks can be produced that are largely inde-&#13;
pendent of the use of elaborate teachers' editions, Teachers'&#13;
editiona can combine text pages with simple, straightforward&#13;
instructions on how to teach the given material. Teacher training&#13;
Bpecific to the use of textbooks, at teacher training institutions&#13;
and as inservice training, should be considered as absolutely&#13;
essential. Any national effort to provide free textbooks should&#13;
attempt to include an element of choice for the teacher; it should&#13;
strive to provide a variety of materials, either as basic series or&#13;
as supplements.&#13;
The essential elements for success in any national effort to&#13;
provide free textbooks for school children, as we have detailed in&#13;
this Study of the Mexican program, could be suammed up as follows:&#13;
1.  Strong and continued government commitment, including&#13;
appropriate annual allocations of money, to a national school&#13;
textbook program;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
2.  Carefully planned institution building, whether public or&#13;
private, with proper concern for the needs and welfare of the&#13;
indigenous publishing industry;&#13;
3.  Development of a realistic curriculum for the primary&#13;
grades, one which serves well as a basis for textbook develop-&#13;
ment;&#13;
4. Competent, adequately paid, and properly motivated staff.&#13;
Extensive use of expert educational publishing technicians,&#13;
either homegrown or to be trained with the help of technical&#13;
assistance from abroad and fellowships;&#13;
5.  Regard for, and study of, existing models of succeasful&#13;
textbooks and series, whether from within the country or&#13;
without;&#13;
6.  Participation of working teachers in the development and&#13;
writing of the kind of textbooks that will effectively teach,&#13;
requiring minimum study and support by the teacher, and of&#13;
well-conceived, straightforward teacherse editions;&#13;
7. Research and testing of all the materials before they are&#13;
introduced in the school system on a grand scale;&#13;
8. Training of teachers in the use of newly-introduced&#13;
textbooks;&#13;
9.  A program for the continuous improvement and revision of&#13;
textbook materials;&#13;
10. An element of choice in the national textbook program, to&#13;
be exercised locally by teachers and school boards.&#13;
There are other areas of controversy with regard to textbooka&#13;
that we should briefly mention:&#13;
*  Should textbooks be free or should they be subsidized and&#13;
sold at low prices, perhapa with the school district&#13;
profiting from their sale and investing the money in&#13;
purchases for the local library?&#13;
* Should books be given to children or should they be loaned&#13;
to them?&#13;
*  Should the books be consumable, i.e., write-in, or should&#13;
they be non-consumable?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Before we attempt to suggest answers, we need to make certain&#13;
assumptions and to narrow the focus of the inquiry, so to speak.&#13;
Let us assume we are dealing with primary school textbooks for&#13;
grades 1-6; assume the conditions prevailing in most developing&#13;
countries, and think in terms of paper-covered books rather than&#13;
hardbound books.&#13;
Let us narrow the focus even further and begin by investigating&#13;
the merits or otherwise of consumable versus non-consumable books&#13;
for grades 1 and 2, without deciding for the moment whether such&#13;
books should be supplied free or at low prices.&#13;
In the early two grades we deal with small children, six or&#13;
seven years old. With these children the lifespan of a paper-covered&#13;
book is very limited, even if as often happens, the teacher collects&#13;
the books at the end of class, locks them up, and in addition, insists&#13;
that pupils cover the paper covers of the book with brown kraft paper.&#13;
There seems to be every incentive for supplying consumable textbooks&#13;
for the early grades, letting the children color, write in, and&#13;
solve problems, having them own books and even take them home. This&#13;
relieves the teacher of the responsibility to account for his supply&#13;
of books, makes the books better teaching instruments, and saves&#13;
exercise books.&#13;
If we accept these arguments, how much more expensive is it&#13;
going to be to supply consumable books? We needLfurther assumptions&#13;
to attempt an answer, We will assume a consumable bóok printed on&#13;
inexpensive paper, that costs a total of US$0.50, of which 60% or&#13;
US$0.30 is the cost of paper and other materials, and 10% or US$0,05&#13;
1&#13;
is the cost of distribution.   We will then assume a non-consumable&#13;
book with essentially the same characteristices, number of pages,&#13;
paper covers, printing and binding, but using slightly better quality&#13;
text paper and cover stock for longer lasting wear. The slightly&#13;
better quality text paper and cover stock are 33% more expensive, we&#13;
assume, than the lower quality papers used in the consumable book.&#13;
Thus our non-consumable book costs around US$0.60 per copy. We&#13;
1 The balance consists of the cost of printing and general and&#13;
administrative expenses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9.-&#13;
know that the consumable book will last a maximum of one year.   How&#13;
much more usage can we expect in grades 1 and 2 from non-consumable&#13;
books?  We ran some experiments in the Philippines and elsewhere on&#13;
this question, i.e., collected books that had been used for a year&#13;
or more from schools, and attempted to determine how long on the&#13;
average books might last. The books collected after one year were&#13;
by and large in poor shape. Not that they could not have been used&#13;
some more, but covers were torn, pages bent, torn and spotted, there&#13;
were writings in the books; all of the things one expects made&#13;
somewhat worse by a tropical climate, humidity, and inadequate&#13;
storage facilities. That many books survived at all for one year&#13;
and more was heavily influenced by a provision in Philippine law&#13;
that treats books as equipment as well as government property.&#13;
Teachers are personally responsible for their book supplies;&#13;
accountability is reinforced by a provision that teachers upon&#13;
retirement from their jobs have to account for all government&#13;
property in their care, including books, and may be required to&#13;
pay for losses out of their own pockets¿ Thus teachers in the&#13;
Philippines tend to limit the exposure of textbooks in their care&#13;
to children and guard their property jealously. Nevertheless, we&#13;
determined that books for grades 1 and 2 would not last more than&#13;
2, or at most 3, years, and that on the average one third of the&#13;
non-consumable textbooks would have to be replaced each year.&#13;
We should also mention that it was decided to replace all books&#13;
every four or five years with new revisions. Over four years,&#13;
assuiníng a school population of 100,000 pupíls per grade level,&#13;
we might thus expect to use 400,000 consumable books versus about&#13;
200,000 non-consumables. There will be non-consumables left at&#13;
the end of the period, but they may be made obsolete by a new&#13;
edition or revision. If we now include an amount of $100,000 for&#13;
the development and production of the books, including payment to&#13;
authors, illustrations, color separation, etc., our equation will&#13;
be as shown on the following page:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-10-&#13;
Textbooks needed over four years for grade 1&#13;
on the basis of 100.000 pupils per grade&#13;
Consumable   Non-consumable&#13;
Cost of Development &amp; Production      $100,000       $100,000&#13;
Cost of Books&#13;
400,000 x $0.50                   200,000&#13;
200,000 x $0.60                                  120,000&#13;
Cost of Additional Exercise Books&#13;
400,000 x $0.15                                   60,000&#13;
Total Costs                           $300,000       $280,000&#13;
There are, of course, a number of different scenarios that may&#13;
affect these figures. But, we believe that on the basis of our&#13;
assumptions, the difference in real costs is slight, especially&#13;
when one compares it to the advantage of providing every child with&#13;
a brand new book. The problem ¡e that many authorities will not&#13;
consider development as part of the costs as it comes from a differ-&#13;
ent budget, nor the cost of exercise books that may have to be&#13;
bought by parents.&#13;
We have used the example of the first two grades, given paper-&#13;
covered books, tropical conditiona and small children; the results&#13;
are not all that different at the higher grade levele. Unless the&#13;
savings in absolute terma are critical, one should consider the&#13;
expense of textbooks in relative terma as Mexico does.&#13;
Should books be given free to pupila or sold at low prices?&#13;
This is not solely an economic question. Many people feel that&#13;
books are valued more if purchased, even at highly subsidized prices.&#13;
It ¡e tempting to devise a scheme by which schools may sell textbooks&#13;
to pupils and pocket the money in order to invest it in their school&#13;
library.  In real life, and in the situation of the LDCs, the&#13;
necessary logistics we feel would make any such scheme awkward, if&#13;
not impossible to adminieter, and might even open a national textbook&#13;
program to abuse and profiteering,&#13;
We generally agree with the argument that what is free is not&#13;
always appreciated, but not in the case of basic schoolbook materials&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
for school children. If educatíon is free and compulsory, then as&#13;
President López Mateos asserted, the necessary schoolbooks and&#13;
other materialas should be supplied free also.&#13;
Mexico does well by its children and by its older citizens&#13;
who are in need of basic education. The Mexican textbook program&#13;
is well on its way toward producing better prepared textbooks and&#13;
introducing more choice and variety into the system. They have&#13;
opted for attractive, colorful books that are consumable where&#13;
this is appropriate, and that are supplied new and fresh to each&#13;
Mexican school child each year. Mexico's example and achievement&#13;
offer  hope, encouragement, and a helpful model to other countries&#13;
facing a similar challenge.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
II. Introduction&#13;
"Providing free textbooks for every child in primary school ¡s&#13;
a problem of political will, organization and talent, and not of&#13;
money." This remarkable statement, from our interview with Dr.&#13;
Roger Diaz de Cosslo, Under Secretary for Culture in the Secretariat&#13;
of Public Education, in Mexico City uniquely demonstrates the spirit,&#13;
the approach, and the determination of Mexico in the fields of edu-&#13;
cation and of textbook production.&#13;
The National Commission for Free Textbooks (CNLTG)1 was created&#13;
in 1959 during the administration of President López Mateos. It was&#13;
given a broad mandate to devise guidelines and to prepare, produce,&#13;
and distribute free textbooks and workbooks to all children in the&#13;
six grades of public and private primary schools. With the firm&#13;
support of every succeeding administration, this task is being&#13;
achieved in spite of an ever-expanding school system. In 1981&#13;
primary education planners accomplished a long sought goal: they&#13;
were able to provide a place in school and a complement of textbooks&#13;
for every child ready to enroil. In 1980 15,000,000 children were&#13;
enrolled in the primary schools of Mexico, a country with a total&#13;
population of close to 70,000,000.&#13;
Not every nation in the industrialized world, and few aamong the&#13;
developing countries, can match these achievements.  They have not&#13;
come easily. The free textbook project was born to controversy. In&#13;
1962 more than one million people from the important industrial city&#13;
of Monterrey demonstrated against Government-1s plane to nationalize&#13;
primary schoolbooks. They expressed the fear that such Government&#13;
dominance of early education, including the content of textbooke in&#13;
social studies, would politicize the educational system to an extent&#13;
not palatable to large segments of the population. Some of these&#13;
criticismo continue today and are reflected with some regularity in&#13;
newspaper articles, writings, and reporte.&#13;
Another source of strong opposition, especially in the early&#13;
days of the free textbook project, has been the Mexican publishing&#13;
1 Comisión Nacional de los Libros de Texto Gratuitos.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-14-&#13;
industry. Prior to nationalization, primary school textbook sales&#13;
formed a major part of the lifeblood of that industry. With nation-&#13;
alization perhaps as much as 60% of its educational market was lost,&#13;
A number of publishíng firms did not survive the change. Major&#13;
Mexican publishers, however, did survive. They adapted, diversified,&#13;
and have created over the last 20 years what today ls arguably the&#13;
most important publishing industry in Latin Ameríca.   Their efforts&#13;
were helped by the gradualness of the change. It took CNLTG eight&#13;
years to complete the first generation of free textbooks. Of even&#13;
greater importance to the publishing industry was Government's decí-&#13;
sion to limit CNLTG to producing basic textbooks for prímary schools,&#13;
leaving to the private publishing sector the rapidly expanding míddle&#13;
schools, and secondary and tertiary education.   Government and private&#13;
sector publishing organizations over the last decade have developed&#13;
a dynamic relationship of mutual support and cooperation.&#13;
Thus we found among Mexican officials and private publishers&#13;
we interviewed, in reporte and articles reflectíng views of parente&#13;
and of teachers that we read, a strong consensus in spite of remain-&#13;
ing reservatíons that free textbooks have been good for education and&#13;
represent a proud achievement for Mexico. In no other way, it le&#13;
argued, given the economic and political circumstances twenty years&#13;
ago, could Mexico have provided each chíld in its primary school&#13;
system with free textbooks in language arte, mathematics, the natural&#13;
solences, and social studies. These books, it lB pointed out, which&#13;
every child receíves annually to keep and to take home, ímpart a&#13;
sense of national unity, as well as the minimum curriculum materiale&#13;
in each subject area.  They help the child learn, they support the&#13;
teacher, and they may even contribute to a belated education for some&#13;
parents. Introducing children to books at an early age promotes book&#13;
learning, the reading habit, and perhaps a desire to continue educa-&#13;
tion beyond primary echool. The free textbook project ie given&#13;
credit for making educatíon more accessible to children in the re-&#13;
moter areas of Mexico, for encouraging them to stay in school longer,&#13;
and for making education more meaningful to the child and to ite&#13;
parento.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-15-'&#13;
The preceding describes the pragmatic underpinnings of Mexico'a&#13;
educational publishing efforts.  Indeed, pragmatism, a practical&#13;
approach to the problema of education, is much in evidence and is&#13;
identified by a willingness to experíment, to use common sense, to&#13;
act first and evaluate later.&#13;
Mexico over the laBt 10 years has had an explosive growth in&#13;
education at all levelsa from primary through secondary school educa-&#13;
tion, and at university level as well. There la little doubt that&#13;
the free textbook project has contributed to this growth. It pro-&#13;
vides free primary school textbooks, it establishes the book as a.&#13;
major teaching tool, it frees parents from the need of payíng for&#13;
books, and thereby makes it possible for many achoola to adopt and&#13;
to purchase supplementary enríchment materiale from the book trade.&#13;
Success with the free textbooks has led Government into addi-&#13;
tional educational publishing programs, a number of which are carried&#13;
out jointly with the private publishing industry.&#13;
Critica may argue that the early generation of free textbooks&#13;
was of poor pedagogical and physical quality; publishers argue that&#13;
if they had been given the money that Government has invested to&#13;
produce the textbooks, they would have produced books of much better&#13;
quality given their expertise. It is poasible to concede these&#13;
pointa in argument and yet be convinced that the Mexican government&#13;
did what was polítically and economically practical and feasíble at&#13;
the time in a major effort to improve primary education.&#13;
In 1959 when Mexíco, possibly unique among developing nations,&#13;
decided to provide free textbooks for all primary school children&#13;
it acted on these aseumptions:&#13;
1.  Government's responsibiíity to provide free primary&#13;
education for all children of school age meana providing&#13;
clasarooms, teachera, and educational materialas includine&#13;
textbooks;&#13;
1 "El Maestro" (Peribdico Mural, 4iio I, Número 2, México D.F.:&#13;
Consejo Nacional Tecnico de la Educacion de SEP, April, 1981).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-16-&#13;
2. A uniform set of free textbooks covering a core curriculum&#13;
in each of the four major diaciplines should be provided for&#13;
every child in primary school, whether publio or private;&#13;
3. A major organization with considerable autonomy, the&#13;
National Comnission for Free Textbooks, should be established,&#13;
liberally financed, and professionally staffed to carry out&#13;
the task of providing free textbooks;&#13;
4.  Textbooks/workbooks should be written by educators and&#13;
professional writers; they should be attractively illustrated.&#13;
They .should also be accompanied by teachers' manuals.&#13;
Mexico was going to use the book as a major teachinR tool.&#13;
Mexico accorded textbooks the same importance as school buildingas&#13;
and teachers. Government realized that expenditures for textbooks,&#13;
however significant, constitute only a minor if essential part of&#13;
the total budget for education. The Mexican government, in assuming&#13;
the task of providing textbooks, knew that in order to achieve its&#13;
goals a long-term, evolutionary effort requiring a permanent profes-&#13;
sional organization and sustained support by Government would be&#13;
essential.&#13;
In succeeding years the Secretaríat of Public Education and&#13;
the National Commission for Free Textbooks have not hesitated to&#13;
change textbook materials, to experiment with different approaches,&#13;
and to improve the quality from one generation of books to the next.&#13;
The following pages describe and analyze in more detall the&#13;
development of public and of private educational publishing in&#13;
Mexíco, with special emphasis on the free textbook program.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
III.  Issues and Priorities Leading to a National Policv&#13;
for Providinr Free Primarv School Textbooks&#13;
A. The Mexican Constitution. 2olitics. and Educational&#13;
Milestones in Mexican Historv&#13;
It may be argued that the development of education in Mexico&#13;
with ita concomitant free textbook project l8 unique to that country,&#13;
cannot be duplicated, and la not germane to situationa of other&#13;
nations. Obviously, we do not subscribe to this view, but rather&#13;
see parallels to situations elsewhere and useful lessona that may&#13;
be applied by other nations.&#13;
It is important, however, to view Mexicols dedication to free,&#13;
compulsory education within the context of the Mexican Revolution,&#13;
a revolution that began on November 20, 1910 with a massive uprising&#13;
against President Porfirlo Diaz. Significantly, the cry of the&#13;
revolutionaries for "Land and Schools"'1 15 immortalized on the walls&#13;
of the Secretariat of Public Education by the magnificent frescoes of&#13;
Diego Rivera. Mexico's Revolution continues to this day. It demanda&#13;
accelerated social change, but ita current emphasia ía on peaceful&#13;
evolution rather than the violent overthrow of government.&#13;
The Mexican Constitution of 1917 gave legal expression to&#13;
revolutionary goals. Article 32 concerne education; ita implica-&#13;
tiona continue to be debated and are variously interpreted, partio-&#13;
ularly, as Article 3 provides the basis for the central role in&#13;
education that Government has assumed. Major provisions of Article&#13;
3 are:&#13;
1.  Instruction imparted by the State shall be free;&#13;
2. All instruction in public institutions ahall be secular;&#13;
3. No religious corporation or minister ehall establish or&#13;
direct achools of primary instruction;&#13;
1 Clark C. Gill, Education in a Chanainz Mexico (Washington, D.C.:&#13;
U,S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1969), p. 37.&#13;
2 Constitution of the United Mexican States. 1917 (As Amended)&#13;
(Washington, D.C.:  Pan American Union, 1964), Pp. 1-2.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-18-&#13;
4.  Private primary schools may only be established subject&#13;
to official supervision.&#13;
Other articles of the Constitution provide for compulsory school&#13;
attendance in as far as possible to age 15.&#13;
The anti-clerical flavor of Mexico's provisions for education&#13;
must be underetood against the backdrop of bitter struggle between&#13;
Church and State beginning in the eighteenth century and extending&#13;
into the twentieth. This followed an earlier period beginning in&#13;
the mid-sixteenth century when education in Mexico owed much to the&#13;
Roman Catholic Church, especially to the Jesuita, who exerted a&#13;
profound influence on ite structure.   The Jesuita were expelled from&#13;
Mexico in 1767.&#13;
Two revisione of the Constitution followed in 1921.   Among other&#13;
things they established that:&#13;
1. The central government was authorized to establish, organize,&#13;
and support primary and rural schools throughout the Republio;&#13;
2. The central government was authorized to establish the&#13;
Federal Secretariat of Public Education, with full cabinet&#13;
status, to promote the organizing and funetioning of education&#13;
throughout the nation.&#13;
Second only to the influence of the Mexican Revolution on&#13;
Mexico'a attitudes and achievements in education, ranks the structure&#13;
and remarkable stability of its strong central government. This has&#13;
enabled the country to provide the political leadership, will, and&#13;
talent for the uninterrupted development of basic education. It is&#13;
useful, therefore, to outline briefly the political setting.&#13;
The Federal Republic of Mexico consists of 31 states and one&#13;
Federal District, which includes Mexico City, These administrative&#13;
unita encompass a Spanish-apeaking country of great diversity&#13;
containing more than 50 distinet indigenous languages, dialects,&#13;
and cultures.&#13;
The national government ¡a comprised of three branches: the&#13;
executive, the legislative, and the judiciary. The executive clearly&#13;
dominates. It ia headed by a president, elected for six years, who&#13;
cannot succeed himself. Unique among democratic governments,&#13;
Mexican politics have long been dominated by one party, the PRI&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-19-&#13;
(Partido Revolucionario Institucional),1 founded in 1929, which has&#13;
never lost a national election.&#13;
Political dialogue in Mexico ia not only represented by the&#13;
rather weak opposition parties, but significantly ¡a carried on&#13;
among the right, left, and centrist factions of the PRI. The leader-&#13;
ship of the PRI nominates the presidential candidate every six years,&#13;
thereby virtually assuring his election. Strong presidents impose&#13;
their political views on the administration and on the nation, in-&#13;
cluding the direction of education. It ¡a important to underatand&#13;
the system to appreciate the sometimes profound shifts in educational&#13;
priorities and philosophy that occur every aix years, as well as the&#13;
determination and ability of every administratíon to achieve major&#13;
goals.&#13;
Federal expenditure is one measure of the influence of the&#13;
national governnent on education. In 1981 approximately 70% of&#13;
total educational expenditures was contributed by the Federal&#13;
Government, 22% was derived from State budgets, and 8% from private&#13;
investment,2&#13;
In the following paragraphs we list "milestones"3 that demarcate&#13;
the road to today'e educational establishment:&#13;
1921: The beginning of the federal educational movement.&#13;
President Obregón establishes the Federal Secretariat of&#13;
Public Education (SEP)4 and appoints José Vasconcelos its&#13;
first Secretary.&#13;
1 Institutional Revolutionary Party.&#13;
2 A type of private support for elementary achools i8 provided&#13;
by Article 123 of the Constitution, which requires industrial and&#13;
agricultural companies to establish achools for children of workers.&#13;
_3D. cit. (Numero 1, México D.F.: Consejo Nacional Técnico de&#13;
la Educaci6n de SEP, March, 1981).&#13;
4 Secretaría de Educación Públíca.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-20-&#13;
1921-1928:  Emphasis is on rural, indigenous, farming, and&#13;
teacher education, the creation among other things of Cultural&#13;
Missions1 and teacher training schools. By 1924 1000 rural&#13;
schools have been established, their number tripling by 1928.&#13;
1929-1934: Introductionr of syllabi at the national level;&#13;
expansion of primary and secondary educational services, both&#13;
urban and rural.&#13;
1935-1940: A Six-Year Plan to align educational objectives&#13;
more closely with socialistio lay education, i.e., with the&#13;
social and economic goals of the country.   !his is a time of&#13;
intensified Church-State conflict, rapidiy increasing land&#13;
distribution, expropriation of foreign oil holdings, and&#13;
nationalization of railways.&#13;
Important institutions of learning are established during&#13;
this period: the National Polytechnic Institute; the National&#13;
School for Physical Education; the Institute of Anthropology&#13;
and History; the National Institute of Pedagogy.&#13;
1941-1958: Article 3 of the Constitution is reinterpreted as&#13;
demanding that education more closely serve the goal of national&#13;
unity, and promote collaboration among social clasaes. A&#13;
national campaign against illiteracy is waged to extend the&#13;
benefits of education to the masees. Teacher training is&#13;
strengthened by the establishment of the "Escuela Normal&#13;
Superior" and the Instituto Federal de Capacitación del&#13;
Magisterio (Federal Teacher Training Institute), the latter&#13;
providing non-certified, inservice teachers with the opportunity&#13;
for certification.&#13;
1 Cultural Missions are teans of specialists who originally&#13;
provided inservice education for Federal rural teachers, and brought&#13;
the rudiments of culture and hygiene to communities in which the&#13;
missione worked. Their activities today focus on five aspects of&#13;
integral community development:  health, home, the economy,&#13;
recreation, and general cultural knowledge.&#13;
2 The Mexican Constitution sanctions private ownership of land&#13;
but reserves rights to all resources which líe below the surface,&#13;
such as oil, coal, and minerale, for the State (Article 27).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-21-&#13;
1959-1970: Promulgation of the Eleven-Year Plan, officially&#13;
called the "National Plan to Improve and Expand Prímary School&#13;
Education in Mexicoi"1  During this period efforts are made to&#13;
ascertain the extent of the actual demand for primary education,&#13;
and to learn the reasons for the low levels of enrollmente&#13;
and attendance. The long-term goal of the plan i to extend&#13;
free primary education to all Mexican children, as required&#13;
by the Constitution.&#13;
Accomplishmenta of this period include the innovative&#13;
design and construction of model, semi-prefabricated rural&#13;
classroomá and of schools providing housing for teachers, the&#13;
"aula-casa," a concept that has won international aoclaim and&#13;
awards.&#13;
It took more than the eleven years to meet the goals set&#13;
for echool construction in 1959.  Nevertheless, between 1958-1964&#13;
alone almost 22,000 classrooms, rural and urban versions of the&#13;
"aula-casa," are put lnto service.&#13;
In 1959 the National Commission for Free Textbooks (CNITG)&#13;
ia created to devise guidelines and to prepare, produce, and&#13;
distribute free textbooks and workbooks to all children in the&#13;
Bix grades of publio and private primary achools.&#13;
Impetus is provided secondary education and the extension&#13;
of Becondary educational opportunities to young adulta in&#13;
remote areas of Mexico through educational television, the&#13;
Otelesecundaria."&#13;
Increasingly the national media, newapapera, magazines,&#13;
and television, are put to use in the service of education.&#13;
1971-1976: 'Educational reform becomes a priority and is&#13;
reflected in the changed syllabi and teaching methods for&#13;
primary and secondary Bohools, and for teacher training (normal&#13;
education). Adult education le Btrengthened; support i given&#13;
to technical/vocational education in such areas as farming and&#13;
fishing, and to industrial training as well. More systematic&#13;
1 yl Plan Nacional para el Mejoramiento y la Expanslón de la&#13;
Educacibn Primaria en México.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-22-&#13;
planning and evaluation of the educational syatem are being&#13;
streased in order to improve the delivery of educational&#13;
services.&#13;
1977-Presept: The promise of the Constitution, the long-term&#13;
goal of providing every child with the opportunity to attend&#13;
aix grades of primary achool, i.e., to have a place in a&#13;
school with a teacher and textbooks, is achieved in 1981.&#13;
A principal objective of the present Secretary of Education,&#13;
Fernando Solana, ls to improve the quality of education. As he&#13;
wrote recently: "The quality of life la not achieved in the&#13;
abstract. In order for everyone to attain a better life, we all&#13;
need to exert a maximum personal and collective effort. The work&#13;
of teachera occupies a central place as the quality of life depende&#13;
primarily on the quality of education."1&#13;
B.  The Nationalization of Primarv School Textbooks&#13;
When President L6pez Mateos (1958-1964) established the National&#13;
Commission for Free Textbooks (CNLTG) in 1959 by presidential decree,&#13;
he put Government into the business of preparing, publishing, and&#13;
distributing milliona of textbooks to public and private primary&#13;
schools. The decree nationalized a maJor sector of educational&#13;
publishing heretofor reserved to private enterprise. It put Govern-&#13;
ment in complete control of the content of achoolbooks that became&#13;
mandatory for all primary schoola to use. Government not only&#13;
asaumed a major task, but also the financial burden of providing&#13;
free textbooks.&#13;
In the face of considerable opposition fromparents and intel-&#13;
lectualh, especially from the industrialized and urban areas of the&#13;
country, and from the disenfranchised Mexican publishing industry,&#13;
President L8pez Mateos and his administration advanced strong&#13;
arguments in favor of the free textbook program.&#13;
1 Fernando Solana, El maestro y la calidad de la educación&#13;
(México, D.F.: Secretaria de Educacíbn Pblica, 1980).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-23-&#13;
The Mexican Constitution, the president declared, extends to&#13;
every Mexican child the promise of free, as well as compulsory,&#13;
primary education. If education í8 to be free it must not only&#13;
include school buildings and teachers, but something else essential&#13;
to the quality of education, namely, free textbooks and other sehool&#13;
materíals.  His admlnistration estimated that only one child in four&#13;
in the sehool system possessed a schoolbook of any kind.   Large&#13;
numbers of parents were simply unable to provide the money necessary&#13;
to pur¢hase books for their children. On the basis of such estimates&#13;
the president aseerted that private publishers were unable to produce&#13;
suffícient books, and simultaneously attacked them for publishing&#13;
textbooks that were too expensive. He declared that current text-&#13;
books in social studies were at odda with the aims of the Mexícan&#13;
Constitution, and that these books reflected the profit-oriented&#13;
philosophy of their authors and publishers. Indeed, Presldent López&#13;
Mateos drew support from Mexican textbook authors who had long com-&#13;
plained about the use of textbooks by foreign authors, and in some&#13;
instances, of books translated from foreign languages.&#13;
With the creation of the National Commission for Free Textbooks&#13;
(CNLTG), Presldent López Mateos held out the promíse of provlding&#13;
every school child in Mexico with identical, unique, free textbooks.&#13;
It was his hope and expectation that his act would further enhance&#13;
the feelíng of national unity.&#13;
It could be argued that Government, by espousing such an&#13;
uncompromising adversary position in relation to the private pub-&#13;
lishing industry, deprived itself of know-how and experience that&#13;
could have made the transition to a free textbook program more&#13;
efficient and leas costly.  As it was, and as will be described in&#13;
this Study, Government entered textbook development, production, and&#13;
distribution with little if any expertise.   It took some time and&#13;
possibly more money than necessary until the free textbooks approached,&#13;
in content and quality, the better products of private publishers.&#13;
Yet in spite of such arguments, it may well be true that President&#13;
Lopez Mateos acted in the only manner that was politically and&#13;
economically feasible at the time. By his action he commítted the&#13;
Mexican government to a long-term effort. He provided CNLTG with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-24-&#13;
a measure of autonomy, a liberal budget, and in the person of Don&#13;
Martín Luis Guzmán, with someone of national status as ite first&#13;
director. Don Martin served CNLTG for 18 years. He had been one&#13;
of the principal authors and proponents of plans for a national free&#13;
textbook program. His status and tenure did much to assure continuing&#13;
and generous support of the program by succeeding Mexican presidents,&#13;
including the present administration,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IV. The Secretariat of Public Education (SEP)&#13;
A. Organization and ObJectives. with Emohasis on Educational&#13;
Programs and Materiala&#13;
The Mexican Constitution of 1917 gave legal expression to&#13;
revolutionary goals and provided the basis for the central role ln&#13;
education that Government has assumed, as mentioned in an earlier&#13;
section. Revisions to the Constitution in 1921 authorized Government&#13;
to establish the Federal Secretariat of Public Education with full&#13;
cabinet status, emphasizing the importance accorded education.&#13;
The President of Mexico has extensive executive and political&#13;
powers; changes can be wrought swiftly, indeed by fiat. Cabinet&#13;
members are, by definition, political appointees, and usually change&#13;
their position at least every six years. Mexican presidents have&#13;
regularly appointed well-known índlviduals to the post of Secretary&#13;
of Education, in. some cases literary personages, in other cases&#13;
businesamen or former cabinet membere.  All Secretaries seem to have&#13;
been concerned with the same overwhelming problems of education:&#13;
eradicating illíteracy and institutionalizing mass education.&#13;
SEP has overall responsibility for all levels of the educational&#13;
establishment in Mexico.  The Secretariat administere a vast network&#13;
of federal schools and supervises those schools supported by states&#13;
and municipalitles, as well as echoole supported by private agencies.&#13;
In addition, SEP supervises educational activities directed towards&#13;
farmers and workere, as epecified in Article 3 of the Constitution.&#13;
The present Secretary of Education, Fernando Solana, was&#13;
appointed by President López Portillo in. 1977.  In the four years&#13;
since his appointment, Secretary Solana has effected major changes&#13;
in the organizational structure of the Secretariat.   An up-to-date1&#13;
organization chart ¡e reproduced in Appendix A.&#13;
We were told that SEP employB nearly 50% of all government&#13;
employees ín the country, including hundreds of thousanda of&#13;
schoolteachers, The Secretariat is organized around seven Under&#13;
1 As of January, 1981.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-26-&#13;
Secretaries of Education, an increase of two since 1980.  In January&#13;
of 1981 Secretary Solana created the poste of Under Secretary for&#13;
Secondary Education and Under Secretary for Sports. He transferred&#13;
some of the responsibilities from the Department for Basic Education&#13;
(renamed Elementary Education) to create the new position of Under&#13;
Secretary for Secondary Education in order to strengthen, broaden,&#13;
and improve educational service at that level.&#13;
There are presently nine advisory councils that report directly&#13;
to the Secretary of Education and over which he presides, as de-&#13;
lineated on the organization chart. These councils serve the Secre-&#13;
tary primarily as advisory boarda in establishing policies for the&#13;
various general directorates. Councils have no authority to admin-&#13;
ister policy; they serve as channels of communications, for example,&#13;
between the Secretariat and teachers, the Secretariat and state&#13;
governments, the Secretariat and etudente.  Membere of the advisory&#13;
councils include the IJnder Secretaries of Education, the heads of&#13;
other councils, the directors of the various general directorates,&#13;
teachers, technical advisore, and administrators.&#13;
Secretary Solana created the General Directorate for Publica-&#13;
tions and Libraries2 in 1977; the Council for Educational Content&#13;
and Methods3 and ite working division, the Sub-Directorate for&#13;
Educational Content and Metbods,4 in 1978; in 1980 he recommended&#13;
for appointment (by President López Portillo) a new president for&#13;
the National Technical Council for Education.5 He established two&#13;
other advisory councils during these years--the Council for Cultural&#13;
and Recreational Programa6 and the Coordinating Council for Open&#13;
1El Maestro (Aií I, Número 1, México, D.F.:   Consejo Nacional&#13;
Tacnico de la Educacion de SEP, March, 1981), p. 2.&#13;
2 Dirección General de Publicaciones y Bibliotecas.&#13;
Consejo de Contenidos y Métodos Educativos.&#13;
4 Dirección General Adjunta de Contenidos y Métodos Educativos.&#13;
5Consejo Nacional Técnico de la Educación.&#13;
6 Consejo de Programas Culturales y Recreativos.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-27-&#13;
(Adult) Education Prograns1--and at least two other General&#13;
Directorates.&#13;
The Council for Educational Content and Methods defines the&#13;
policies of the two organizationa that most concern Us in this Study&#13;
since they are principally responsible for the development, produc-&#13;
tion, manufacture, and distribution of the free textbooks for primary&#13;
schools, i.e., the Sub-Directorate for Educational Content and Methods&#13;
and the National Commission for Free Textbooks.   These organizations&#13;
will be discussed in subsequent sections.&#13;
Secretary Solana's organizational changes are designed to&#13;
further the five principal objectives2 of his administration:&#13;
1. To assure everyone a basic education of 10 grades;&#13;
2. To link education with Mexico's socio-economic systems;&#13;
3.  To improve the quality of education;&#13;
4. To improve the cultural atmosphere of the country;&#13;
5. To inerease the efficiency of the educational system.&#13;
SEP, in a country of close to 70,000,000 people, an increase in&#13;
population of over 425% since 1921, continues to be preoccupied with&#13;
eradicating the last vestiges of illiteracy (some 6,300,000 people).3&#13;
There has been impressive progress. In 1921 the rate of illiteracy&#13;
was more than 70% of the population,4 in 1950 it was 43.3%,5 by 1960&#13;
illiteracy was down to 34.7%,5 by 1968 it was. 27.2%,5 and by 1980 it&#13;
had been reduced to 15.1%.5&#13;
There is similar progress in other areas of education. Accord-&#13;
ing to Dr. Emilio Rosenblueth, Under Secretary for Educational&#13;
Planning, the Secretariat expects at leaet 75% of the primary school&#13;
population to complete six years of schooling in six years' time by&#13;
1 Consejo Coordinador de Sistemas Abiertos,&#13;
2 El Maestro IPeri5dico Mural) Año I, Numero 1, México D.F.:&#13;
Consejo Nacional Tecnico de la Educaci6n de SEP, March, 1981).&#13;
3 Excelsior (Mexico City), May 30, 1981, p. 7-A.&#13;
4 Over 15 years of age.&#13;
5 General Directorates of Planning and Programnming of SEP.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-28-&#13;
1985; by contrast, only 53% of the primary school population accomp-&#13;
lished this feat in 1980.&#13;
Other concerns of the Secretariat include:&#13;
1.  Education for some 15,000,000 primary and 3,000,000&#13;
secondary school children;&#13;
2. Basic education for 300,000 indigenous children for whom&#13;
Spanish is not a first language;&#13;
3.  Mass education for adults, i.e., the means for upgrading&#13;
the education of 13,000,000 adulta who have not completed aix&#13;
years of primary education;&#13;
4.  Intensive self-study primary education programs for those&#13;
adulta not fortunate enough to have ever participated in the&#13;
educational procesa.&#13;
In support of these concerns SEP aponsora not only the free&#13;
textbook program for public and private primary schools (grades 1-6),&#13;
but also a wide range of other educatíonal materials produced mainly&#13;
under the aegis of the Under Secretary for Culture, and discusaed in&#13;
Chapter VI.&#13;
With the discovery of large oil reserves and rapid industrial-&#13;
ization, Mexico now faces the need for better trained technicians&#13;
and industrial workers, both of which are in short supply in the&#13;
workforce. The Secretariat ís focusing considerable attention on&#13;
vocational education by building schools, encouraging industry to&#13;
provide trainee programa, and by developing appropriate curricula&#13;
to follow the first nine years of general schooling.&#13;
The Mexícan government regards education as an investment and&#13;
not as an expense,1 and therefore has funded the Secretariat gener-&#13;
ously over ita sixty year history. In 1980 the total education&#13;
budget was Mp 160 billion,2 of which perhaps Mp 1 billion went for&#13;
1 Excél1ior (Mexico City), May 29, 1981, p. 19-A ("EJ. exceso&#13;
de petrodblares ha indigestado a muchos pueblos, advierte Fernando&#13;
Solana").&#13;
2 Equivalent to US$6.7 billion.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-29-&#13;
the production, publication, and distribution of textbooks and other&#13;
teaching materials. In 1921, when SEP was established, the educa-&#13;
tion budget was lees than 5% of the national budget;1 in 1959,&#13;
almost 16%;1 in 1967, more than 26%;1 and in 1981 it was around 12%.&#13;
B.  Adviíory Councila&#13;
Of the nine advisory councils that report directly to the&#13;
Secretary of Education, we ahall describe the two that are largely&#13;
concerned with educational materials.&#13;
1. The National Technical Council for Education (CNTE)&#13;
CNTE was formally established as a Council by executive order&#13;
of President Ruiz Cortines in 1957. For three years prior to that&#13;
date it had existed as a commission with the primary purpose of&#13;
approving textbooks for secondary schools. CNTE continues to approve&#13;
textbooks based on the following criteria:&#13;
a, Article 3 of the Mexican Constitution;&#13;
b. Article 5 of the Federal Law on Education;&#13;
c. The existing curriculum;&#13;
d. Physical appearance of the books.&#13;
The National Technical Council for Education acto as a consult-&#13;
ing body to SEP similar in role to a National Academy of Science.&#13;
Its major funetiona are educational research, promoting the partí-&#13;
cipation of teachera in the analysis of educational policy, and&#13;
providing liaison in areas of education with atate goverTlmenta.&#13;
Organized in a General Assembly, or Plenary group, of 117 members,&#13;
the Council is responsible to a Board of Directors chaired by the&#13;
Secretary of. Education. CNTE2 is headed by a president appointed&#13;
by the President of Mexico usually upon the recommendation of the&#13;
Secretary of Education. A General Secretary, reporting to the&#13;
Councilla president, oversees the work of its seven separate com-&#13;
miasiona. The General Assembly meets once a year at the behest of&#13;
1 OD. cit., p. 27.&#13;
2 See Organization Chart, Appendix B.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-30-&#13;
the Secretary of Education. The Board of Directora convenes at&#13;
least bimonthly to review and plan the work of the Council.&#13;
In its role as researcher and consultant to SEP, CNTE has&#13;
undertaken numerous important educational studies over ita 24 year&#13;
history.  In July, 1959 SEP directed CNTE to study and revise the&#13;
primary school curriculum so that it would contribute more to the&#13;
growth of civic responsibility and of practical skills. The&#13;
curriculum developed from this study became effective in 1960 and&#13;
remains basically unchanged.&#13;
In November, 1964 CNTE undertook an evaluation of the accom-&#13;
plishments of SEP over the previous six-year period. Among CNTE's&#13;
recommendations for improving primary education in Mexico were the&#13;
following:&#13;
a. New laws should be passed so that the costs of education&#13;
are ahared more equitably among the federal government, state&#13;
governments, and municipalities;&#13;
b. The orientation (inservice training) of teachera in new&#13;
educational programs should be continued;&#13;
c. The federal distribution of free textbooks and workbooks&#13;
should be continued and the states should be encouraged to&#13;
prepare and distribute free supplementary books on state folk-&#13;
lore, geography, and history;&#13;
d. State commissiona on education should be established;&#13;
e. Continued attention should be given to monolingual Indian&#13;
communities;&#13;
f. More consolidated and primary boarding schools in rural&#13;
areas should be established.&#13;
In 1966, charged with reevaluating the entire educational&#13;
system, CNTE issued a report pinpointing areas needing urgent&#13;
attention. Of the eleven areas stressed in the report, two are&#13;
of special concern to us:&#13;
a. The need to provide elementary education for all achool&#13;
age children as envisioned by the "Eleven Year Plan," and as&#13;
demanded by the Constitution;&#13;
b. Equalization of educational opportunities throughout the&#13;
country, with additional emphasis on the remoter regions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-31-&#13;
CNTEIs original charter was first amended in 1959, when the&#13;
newly established National Commission for Free Textbooks was given&#13;
special responsibilities for the schoolbooks for grades 1-6. In&#13;
April of 1979 President López Portillo abolished CNTE's previous&#13;
charter and replaced it with a new one. Nonetheless, most of CNTE's&#13;
eseential funetions remain intact under the new charter, i.e.:&#13;
a. To act as a consultative body of experta to the Federal&#13;
and State Secretariate of Education;&#13;
b.  To encourage and facilitate the participation of teachera&#13;
in the analysis of educational policy;&#13;
c.  To conduct studies and research into all areas of education.&#13;
CNTE continues to approve textbooks for secondary education,&#13;
which remains an important function even though it ¡a possible to&#13;
publish schoolbooks in Mexico without such approval. (Whether such&#13;
books will sell is another matter.) The current president of ONTE&#13;
would like to see the textbook approval process liberalized. It&#13;
has been dominated by a very formal, academic approach to textbooks&#13;
that frowns upon such currently popular devices as the use of cartoons,&#13;
for example, and of humor.&#13;
In 1977 the Council negotiated an important agreement with the&#13;
Mexlcan Publishers Association that established a mutually accept-&#13;
able formula for pricing secondary school textbooks. The formula&#13;
makes it possible to adjust prices annually on the basis of the&#13;
current rate of inflation.&#13;
CNTE remaina the official clearing house for the approval of&#13;
all educational materiala produced by Government; however, with&#13;
the free primary school textbooks its approval has become perfuno-&#13;
tory. The Council is active in the evaluation of current efforts&#13;
in basíc adult education, it is attempting to measure the impact of&#13;
the free textbooks on academic achievement, and it participated in&#13;
1979 in polling 370,000 primary school teachera about their reactions&#13;
to the new integrated textbooks for grades 1 and 2,1 receíving re-&#13;
aponses from 162,000 teachere.&#13;
1 The new integrated textbooks are described on pages 60-68.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-32-&#13;
Perhaps one of CNTE's most important funetione remaina its&#13;
special relationship with Mexico's teachers. Ita president, for&#13;
one, travele extensively throughout the country explaining to&#13;
teachers Governmentls plans for education and the new methode&#13;
currently being introduced in the curriculum.&#13;
2. The Councíl for Eduoational Content and Methods and the&#13;
Sub-Directorate for Educational Content and Methods&#13;
Secretary of Eduoation Solana established the Council for&#13;
Educational Content and Methods, over which he presides, in 1978 to&#13;
help him to improve the quality of education. The creation of this&#13;
Council diminished the roles and responsibilities of two older&#13;
organizations: the National Technical Council for Education, as&#13;
previously mentioned no longer the principal group responsible for&#13;
approving the content of the free primary textbooks, and the National&#13;
Commission for Free Textbooks, now no longer responsible for develop-&#13;
ing the content of the free prímary texte.&#13;
The Council for Educational Content and Methods Includes among&#13;
ita 17 membera ex officio the Under Secretaries of Education, the&#13;
President of the National Technícal Council for Education, the&#13;
Managing Director of the National Commission for Free Textbooks,&#13;
Directora of the General Directorates for Publicationa and Libraries&#13;
and for Teaching and Cultural Materials, as well as a number of&#13;
teachers and other individuale. The Council defines the polícies&#13;
of the two organizations presently responsible for the duvelopment&#13;
of currículum and the supply of free textbooks to primary schools,&#13;
namely:&#13;
a.  The Sub-Directorate for Eduoational Content and Methods,&#13;
a department of SEP reporting to the Under Secretary for&#13;
Educational Planning, that is responsible for the content&#13;
and design of the books;&#13;
b. The Natíonal Commissíon for Pree Textbooks, formerly in&#13;
complete charge of the free textbook program but now restrieted&#13;
to their manufácture and distribution, whilh reporte direotly&#13;
to the Secretary of Education.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-33-&#13;
This new arrangement provides SEP with better control over the&#13;
content of the free textbooks, including the relationship of content&#13;
to the established curriculum.&#13;
The Sub-Directorate for Educational Content and Methods&#13;
This Sub-Directorate,  under the management of a young and&#13;
dynamic director, is evidence of Mexico's ability to offer attractive&#13;
careers and reasonable compensation to ite clvil servants. With&#13;
adequate funds and a large professional staff, the Sub-Directorate&#13;
has been assigned the following tasks:&#13;
a, Curriculum development;&#13;
b. Planning the content of the free textbooks;&#13;
c. Manuscript development;&#13;
d. Testing and evaluation of materíals;&#13;
e. Design and illustration of textbooks, including the production&#13;
of camera-ready materials for delivery to the printer, i.e., the&#13;
National Commission for Free Textbooks.&#13;
Ita duties are not restrieted to primary school education, it was&#13;
emphasized, but instead include three levela of education: pre-&#13;
school, primary, and secondary.   Of immediate concern, however, is&#13;
primary education.&#13;
The Sub-Directorate ís organized into five departments with&#13;
the following responsibilities:&#13;
a.  Academie Department&#13;
This.group selects and proposes major teaching objectives and&#13;
provides content suggestions for each of the four basic disciplines&#13;
or subject areas for grades 1-6 (mathematics, language arta, the&#13;
natural sciences and social studies), and in addition, for health&#13;
education, physical education, technical education, and the arta.&#13;
The department consists of 50 apecialista who are part of the&#13;
permanent staff, and at the time of this writing, some 25 parttime&#13;
consultants.&#13;
1 See Organization Chart, Appendix C.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-34-&#13;
b. Curriculum Department&#13;
A group of 25 educational psychologists and pedagogues develope&#13;
curriculum for each grade level in close cooperation with the&#13;
Academic Department. At times this department undertakes to survey&#13;
the attitudes and reactions of teachere to certain textbooks by&#13;
soliciting reviews and evaluations.&#13;
co. Manuscript Department&#13;
This department í8 in charge of the writing and preparation&#13;
of manuscripta conforming to the outlines prepared by the Curriculum&#13;
Department and approved by the Academic Department. It also handles&#13;
the entire editorial development and production of the books, with&#13;
much of the material written inhouse. It is responsible for manu-&#13;
acript design and the selection and preparation of illustrations;&#13;
it orders typesetting, and produces and delivers camera-ready text-&#13;
book pages to CNLTG. There are 40-60 people in this department,&#13;
including those who work on a freelance or parttime basis.&#13;
d. Testing Department&#13;
The Sub-Directorate engages in extensive field testing of the&#13;
materíale it produces, sometímes on a very large scale, as will be&#13;
described in a later section. Field testing of textbooks in&#13;
preliminary editione and of teacherel manuals is carried out in&#13;
close cooperation with the appropriate departments of SEP, with&#13;
observers provided by the school systems. It i supervised by the&#13;
ataff of the Testing Department, whích devises questionnaires and&#13;
other means of piloting materials in schools.&#13;
e. Administrative Services&#13;
Among other things this group prepares contracts (with authors&#13;
and outside suppllers), purchases services and materials and dis-&#13;
penses salaries.  The Administrative Services Department and the&#13;
Testing Department combined comprise some 35 staff members.&#13;
As ls clear from the above description, the Sub-Directorate&#13;
la a large and complex organization. Ita fírst task, begun in&#13;
September of 1978, has been a revision of the curriculum of grades&#13;
1-6. This revision has resulted in a radical break with the past&#13;
as represented by the Second Generation of textbooks published in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-35-&#13;
the 1970s by CNLTG. After considerable study in consultation with&#13;
currlculum specialíste, educatore, and teachers, it was decided&#13;
to develop an integrated curriculum for grades 1 and 2, and to&#13;
produce one integrated textbook (and one workbook) for each of&#13;
these grades that would cover the traditíonally separate subjects&#13;
of language arte, mathematics, the natural eciences, and sooial&#13;
etudies.&#13;
The concept of combined or integrated texto (depending on&#13;
the way subjects are handled) ¡e not new, of course, and has&#13;
certain advantages. Two books for a emall child to handle and to&#13;
carry back and forth to school ís obviously easier than the cus-&#13;
tomary four books. Considerable money may be saved by printing&#13;
and binding fewer books annually for grades 1 and 2, thus makíng&#13;
it more economical to offer consumable, write-in texto and work-&#13;
books, attractively illustrated and printed in four colore.&#13;
However, certain disadvantages of integrated texts have&#13;
generally persuaded educators and teachers to prefer separate&#13;
textbooks for each subject, even though they may agree that the&#13;
number of subjecte, as well as the amount of material taught in the&#13;
early grades, should be limited. For example, many educators feel&#13;
it is difficult fortmost teachers, and requires more individual&#13;
effort, to teach subjects wíth differing teaching objectives as an&#13;
integrated course. Consequently, it becomes necessary to provide&#13;
more elaborate teachers' guldes than wlth the usual textbook.&#13;
Indeed, the teacheral guides that have been developed for the new&#13;
integrated texto are quite elaborate. Whether Mexican teachers&#13;
can be persuaded to use these guides as extensively as is planned&#13;
may well decide the succese of the program.&#13;
We shall describe the lntegrated textbooks in more detall in&#13;
Chapter V under "Fhase III, The New Integrated Textbooks. n We&#13;
should add here that the Sub-Directorate has plano to produce a&#13;
book for parente that will explain the philosophy of the new&#13;
program. Purthermore, the group le aesisting with the publication&#13;
of regional supplements (monographs) for each state that are&#13;
intended to provide children with more of thelr local culture,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-36-&#13;
history, and geography. There are aleo plano to introduce greater&#13;
diversification in the textbook program. Finally, the Sub-Directorate&#13;
hopes to institute a program of regular revisione of the textbooks,&#13;
lees dependent on the changes in administratione.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
'V. DeveloPment of the Pree Textbook Program.&#13;
1959 to the Present&#13;
A.  The National Commission for Free Textbooks&#13;
1.  Mandate and Charter&#13;
Anyone who visíts the offices and printing plant of the&#13;
National Commission for Free Textbooks (CNLTG) at Dr. Rio de la&#13;
Loza 116, in Mexico City, cannot fail to be' impressed. The massive&#13;
buildinge cover an entire city block. Close to 1,100 people work&#13;
there:  742 workera are employed in the printing plant, and 346&#13;
work in administration, distribution, and management.   In 1981&#13;
plano called for the manufacture and distribution of 82,316,000&#13;
books to some 57,000 publio and private primary schools by September&#13;
2, the beginning of the school year. The responsibility for seeing&#13;
that this was accomplished rested on the shoulders of Lio. Enrique&#13;
González Pedrero, the Managing Director of CNLTG, and his capable&#13;
Director of Production, Prof. Roberto Salcedo Aquino.&#13;
Plano for establishing CNLTG were formulated during 1958. On&#13;
February 12, 1959, President Adolfo Lopez Mateos signed into law&#13;
the presidential decree that created what has since become a&#13;
national institution, even though ite funetions have been recently&#13;
curtailed..&#13;
It is instructive to read the original decree, its preamble and&#13;
various articles. The eloquent preamble asserts, with reference to&#13;
the Constitution ,that makes primary education "obligatory and free,"&#13;
that free education will only be achieved when pupila receive free&#13;
textbooks, since textbóoks are indispensable to their studies. It&#13;
mentions the high. cost of books then available in the marketplace,&#13;
the state of the world economy that ís reflected in escalating&#13;
prices, and the lack of purchasing power among certain social&#13;
classes in Mexico. There follows the statement that textbooks of&#13;
a commercial nature are bound to present diverse views, and to&#13;
reflect in their prices and in their general characteristics the&#13;
economic intereste of those who produce them. Government produc-&#13;
tion of textbooks will lower costa to the point where it will be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-38-&#13;
possible for government to assume the burden of providing free books&#13;
to all pupila. Pupils, who will receive these books, as an act of&#13;
law and not of charity, will be instilled with a sense of duty to&#13;
their country, the very country of which some day they will become&#13;
citizens.&#13;
The decree itself may be briefly summarized as follows:&#13;
Article 1. Establishes CNLTG, which reports to the Secretariat of&#13;
Publio Education.&#13;
Article 2. Functions, duties, etc., of CNLTG&#13;
I. To define the general characteristica of textbooks&#13;
intended for primary school, in line with accepted&#13;
methodology and the respective ourriculum.&#13;
II.  To proceed, by means of competitions,1 or in&#13;
other ways if competitions prove ineffective, to the&#13;
selection of manuscrípts and to the production, i.e.,&#13;
editing, illustrating, typesetting, etc., of the&#13;
textbooks.&#13;
III. To appoint, subject to prior approval by the&#13;
Secretariat, the personnel to carry out CNLTG's miesion&#13;
effectively, and to formulate with the approval of the&#13;
Secretariat, standards and procedures that will govern&#13;
their activities.&#13;
IV. To consider, when it is judged prudent, opportune,&#13;
and useful, the aseistance that private industry has to&#13;
offer, provided that these offerings are judged by&#13;
whether they are expressions of a generous and día-&#13;
interested wish to participate in a patriotic venture.&#13;
V. To seek, with competent authorities, adequate&#13;
measures to prevent anyone from profiteering from&#13;
the books, except for the legitimate benefita ensuing&#13;
to writers, illustrators, printera, etc.; to prevent&#13;
a* black market in these books, prevent export to other&#13;
1 Authors were asked to compete by submitting manuscripta for&#13;
publication in the different subject areas. This was soon abandoned&#13;
in favor of the planned development of textbook series by author&#13;
teams selected by CNLTG.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-39-&#13;
countries, and to prevent that in any other way someone&#13;
obtains a benefit from these books that ¡a contrary to&#13;
their original purpose.)&#13;
Article 3.  CNLTG will consist of:&#13;
I. A president, a general secretary, and aix directora&#13;
capable of assuring that the textbooks are designed to&#13;
develop adequately and properly all of the faculties of&#13;
the pupils and prepare them for a useful life, that they&#13;
promote a feeling of kinahip among atudenta, that they&#13;
are oriented towarda civil affairs, and above all, that&#13;
they instill a love of country, fortified by a knowledge&#13;
of ita historic achievementa that provide the foundation&#13;
for ite democratic evolution.&#13;
II.  A panel of 12 consultants on mattera of education.&#13;
III. Five (5)2 outside representatives.&#13;
IV.  A professional accountant and a professional&#13;
auditor.&#13;
Article 4.  The President, secretary, directora and outside repre-&#13;
sentatives are to be appointed by the Chief Executive&#13;
(the President of Mexico). Other personnel of CNLTG&#13;
will be appointed by the Secretary of Education.&#13;
Artiole 5.  CNaTG will have at ita disposal the following economil&#13;
resources:&#13;
I. The suma that the Federal Government, the States,&#13;
and the Municipalities assign to it.&#13;
II. Contributiona by private industry.&#13;
As the first preBident of CNLTG, President López Mateos&#13;
appointed Don Martin Luis Guzman, who served the organization and&#13;
the cause of free textbooks for an unprecedented term of 18 yeara&#13;
until his death on December 22, 1976. He was followed as president&#13;
by Don Agustin Yanez, a former Secretary of Education and an&#13;
1 To this day every free textbook carries a cautionary notice&#13;
to this effect, prohibiting comnercial use, exportation of the books,&#13;
etc., under penalty of law.&#13;
2 Enlarged to 10 by presidential decree in 1977.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-40-&#13;
outatanding literary figure, who served from January 8, 1977 to&#13;
November 15, 1979. In addition to the determination of President&#13;
López Mateos, it was perhaps the appointment of Don Martín Luis&#13;
Guzmán as much as anything else that gave the fledgling organization&#13;
authority, and gained for it the support of each succesaive president&#13;
of Mexico and of his administration. Don Martin Luií Guzman, a man&#13;
of the Revolution, had been Pancho Villa's private secretary. Exiled&#13;
in Spain, he served Spain's last president, Manuel Azaña, as private&#13;
secretary, in addition to managing a newspaper. When he returned to&#13;
Mexico in 1938, Don Martin Luis.Guzman founded the magazine TiemDo,&#13;
was elected senator from his state,'and wrote a biography of Pancho&#13;
Villa. He was a principal proponent of a national free textbook&#13;
program and was appointed president of CNLTG upon ita creation in 1959.&#13;
Not until 1978 did the status, mandate, and organization of&#13;
CNLTG change to any considerable degree from ita original purpose.&#13;
Major changes, however, did occur about that time and were confirmed&#13;
and enacted into law by presidential decree1 signed-by President&#13;
José López Portillo on February 20, 1980. This decree followed a&#13;
major reorganization within the Secretariat (SEP) described in more&#13;
detail in Chapter IV.   Among other changes, as already mentioned,&#13;
that reorganization created the Council for Educational Content and&#13;
Methods, and under ite auspices a department2 within SEP to develop&#13;
and design the free primary school textbooks.   CNLTG was transformed&#13;
into an autonomous public corporation, its activities focused on the&#13;
manufacture and distribution of textbooks, rather than on their&#13;
editorial development andAdesign. CNLTG does retain, however, an&#13;
advisory functíon with regard to development and design. In the&#13;
person of its director, CMLTG participates in the meetinga of the&#13;
Council for Educational Content and Methods. Moreover, it has&#13;
retained ita advisory panel of 12 educational consultants.&#13;
1 "Decreto por el cual se crea la Comisión Naciopal de los Libros&#13;
de Texto Gratuitos como organismo descentralizado" (Mexico, D.F.:&#13;
Diario Oficial, February 28, 1980)..&#13;
2 The Sub-Directorate for Educational Content and Methode.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-41-&#13;
2.  Present OrRanization and Duties&#13;
As described earlier, CNLTG continues to be a large and vital&#13;
organization,1 even though it l8 now dependent on the Sub-Directorate&#13;
for Educational Content and Methods for development and delivery of&#13;
new textbook materials in final camera-ready form for printing.&#13;
CNTLG's chief task has become the manufacture, i.e., printing and&#13;
binding, and the distribution to schools of the free textbooks for&#13;
grades 1-6. The Managing Director of CNLTG retains final respon-&#13;
sibility for supplying adequate quantities of free textbooks to the&#13;
Mexican primary school system each year prior to the opening of&#13;
schools in September. He may discharge that responsibility by&#13;
reprinting previous editions if new textbook materials are not&#13;
received in time to allow for their printing and distribution before&#13;
school opening.&#13;
CNLTG's budget for 1981 was set at Mp 1.056 billion, the equiv-&#13;
alent of US$44 million at the then current rate of exchange. Thirty-&#13;
six thousand (36,000) tons of paper, specially produced for the free&#13;
textbook proJect, and manufactured from nbagasse" (the straw of&#13;
sugar cane), were to be used to print some 82,000,000 books.   The&#13;
paper ia similar to newsprint paper, with good opacity but grayish-&#13;
blue in color; at 60 gms per aquare meter, it ia heavier than&#13;
newsprint. Paper, other materíals, and labor account for 80% of&#13;
the cost of the textbooks while the remaining 20% pays for general&#13;
and administrative expenses, and for distribution. The Mexican&#13;
governnent over the years has made large investments in buildings&#13;
and a printing plant for CNLTG, whilh are not reflected in these&#13;
figures.&#13;
Under the leadership of ite Managing Director, CNLTG la&#13;
organized into two major departments, the Production Department&#13;
and the Administrative and Finance Department that includes the&#13;
Distribution Department, plus a amaller support group under a&#13;
General Secretary.&#13;
1 See Organization Chart, Appendix D.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-42-&#13;
a.  Production Department&#13;
The Production Department 18 responsible for the complicated&#13;
logisties of planning and scheduling a large manufacturing program,&#13;
and for the supervision and quality control of the modern printing&#13;
plant. Its responsibility begins when originals or mechanicala of&#13;
text pages are received by the department, and extends to the delivery&#13;
of books to CNLTG's central warehouse. At present approximately 80%&#13;
of the printing and binding is done inhouse by CNLTG's modern printing&#13;
plant, while 20% is purchased from outside sources. Upon arrival at&#13;
the plant, the mechanicals, i.e., textbook pages containing type and&#13;
artwork, are photographed while four-color illustrations are separated&#13;
by means of a modern scanner. Color proofs are then submitted to&#13;
the Sub-Directorate for Educational Content and Methods for approval&#13;
before final imposition of the film for plate-making.   Converting&#13;
mechanicals into film may take 30-40 days because of the numerous and&#13;
complicated full color illustrations. Most of the printing is by&#13;
four-color offset on three large webfed presses, capable of producing&#13;
an average of 17,000 signatures per hour per printing press. Three&#13;
Roland sheetfed offset presses (two are two-color preases) are used&#13;
for covers and smaller print runs. The bindery has 17 folding&#13;
machines and three multi-stage Sheridan flexible binding production&#13;
lines. Since all of the equipment ís imported, breakdowns and the&#13;
supply of spare parts pose major problema, sometimes tying up equip-&#13;
ment for weeks or months. Training of maintenance people and of&#13;
other technical staff, lack of experienced technicians in some of&#13;
the departments, at times complicate production achedules.-. Workers&#13;
are unionized and well paid. Their pay acale l8 comparable to&#13;
private industry, they are eligible for federal social security&#13;
benefits, and enjoy a number of fringe benefita. For example, they&#13;
receive 70 days of pay as a bonus annually,1 and enjoy subsidized&#13;
meals in the plant's cafetería.&#13;
With the introduction of a major new web press in 1980, print-&#13;
ing quallty has been greatly improved in apite of the low quality&#13;
1 By law private companies in Mexico are required to pay a&#13;
minimum of 15 days in annual bonuses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-43-&#13;
of paper that le being used in the books. ONLTG purchases paper from&#13;
two government-owned mills, Mexpapel and Tuxtepec, but does not re-&#13;
ceive preferentíal prices. At times CNLTG imports paper, such as&#13;
coated groundwood, for special projecte.&#13;
The standard trim size of the textbooks and teachera' manuals&#13;
CNMTG produces ¡s 6 7/8" x 10" (17.5 x 25.5 cm). Covere are of a&#13;
slightly heavier paper stock and are printed in four colore. Flexible&#13;
(hot-melt), or so-called perfect, binding la used throughout. The&#13;
average textbook le about 224 pages, but actual page counte vary by&#13;
subject and grade level, with earlier grade levels having as few as&#13;
144 pages, except for the new integrated texto for grades 1 and 2.&#13;
These have 240 pages per volume,1 plus additional workbooks. Books&#13;
are richly illustrated with photographs, four-color artwork, and&#13;
line drawíngs.&#13;
Teacherel manuale are of the same size and general appearance&#13;
as the pupil textbooks, but are simpler in design and illustration.&#13;
Nevertheless, many of the teachersl manuals contain some illustra-&#13;
tione printed in full color. Teachers' manuals may aleo vary in&#13;
page count. They often contain fewer pages than the textbook they&#13;
accompany, although there are exceptiona. The largest teachers'&#13;
manual so far produced accompanies the new integrated pupil book&#13;
for grade 1. It contains approxímately 448 pages and le prlnted&#13;
in two colore.&#13;
The printing plant works around the clock to meet its production&#13;
targete.  Some departnents, such as the webfed preoses, work 24 hours,&#13;
others 16 hours, or even 8 hours, depending on the flow of work. If&#13;
the prínting plant cannot handle all of the work, whi¢h le regularly&#13;
the case as pointed out earlier, and ls sometimes aggravated by&#13;
equlpment breakdowns, outside printere from the private sector are&#13;
employed. In such cases CNLTG provides all of the materíals, 'in-&#13;
cluding paper, to the outeide printer. Outside printing le done&#13;
under contract; any orders in exceso of Mp 50,000 (approximately&#13;
1 Refer to Sectlon B, 3 of this chapter entitled "Phase III."&#13;
The integrated textbook for grade 1 was published in two volumes&#13;
of 240 pages each, accompanied by a workbook aleo published in two&#13;
volumes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-44-&#13;
US$2,000 at the then prevailing rate of exchange) are placed by open&#13;
bídding.  Penalties for late delivery can be severe, as much as a&#13;
5% penalty per day.&#13;
b. Distribution DeDartment&#13;
The free textbook program distributes new books to every child&#13;
in the school system each year. These books are not loaned; they&#13;
become the property of the individual child. Obviously, the die-&#13;
tribution of more than 82,000,000 textbooks to some 57,000 schools,&#13;
the task for 1981, requires careful planning and efficient distri-&#13;
bution. To accomplish its mission CNLTG has evolved a highly complex&#13;
system.&#13;
As mentioned earlier, the Production Department le responsible&#13;
for the manufacture of books and for their delívery to CNLTG's&#13;
central warehouse in the Federal Distríct. The books are delivered&#13;
in corrugated cartons, each containing an average of 50 copies,&#13;
ready for shipment. Distribution to schools i8 accomplished in&#13;
three major stages:&#13;
1) CNLTG's Department of Distribution la responsible for&#13;
delivery of the books from the central warehouse to 153&#13;
regional warehouses provided by the various atate governments;&#13;
2) Local authorities, generally the representatives of SEP&#13;
in each state, are responsible for delivering the books from&#13;
the regional warehouse to local inspectora in the school&#13;
distriete covered by their warehouse;&#13;
3) Local school inspectora normally have about 10 schools&#13;
under their supervision, and are responsible for distributing&#13;
the books they receive from regional warehouses to these&#13;
schools. There are over 3,000 school inspectora in the system.&#13;
In the Firat StaRe, school enrollments are computerized by&#13;
school distriet at CNLTG and are then compared with SEPts projec-&#13;
tions. On this basis book requiremente are calculated for each&#13;
district. Computerized printouts of the yearls printing schedule,&#13;
listing titles and quantities of books to be printed for each&#13;
distriet, are then sent to all distriet inspectora, generally in&#13;
February of each year.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-45-&#13;
At the time books are shipped, sometime between February and&#13;
August, a copy of the shipping documents is sent to each inspector&#13;
along with a copy of the printing schedule mailed earlier in&#13;
February. A second set of these documento is sent to the inspectorts&#13;
local warehouse, which may in fact be a couple of rooms in one of&#13;
his local schoole. The purpose of informing the inspector is to&#13;
alert him well in advance of the quantity of books he will receive&#13;
and of their shipping date.  If the books do not arrive when expected,&#13;
the inspector will send a telegram to CNLTG's department of distri-&#13;
bution.&#13;
At CNLTG'e central warehouse book shipments are presorted and&#13;
addreesed to each school district; they are color-coded and consoli-&#13;
dated into large shipments to the regional warehouses.&#13;
CNLTG arranges its book distribution to the regions with the&#13;
support of the Secretariat of Communications and Transportation and&#13;
in close coordination with the central post office in Pantaco&#13;
(Mexico City) and the management of the National Railroads.&#13;
The vast majority of CNLTG's book shipments (95% in 1980) are&#13;
shipped by raill under a unique arrangement with the National&#13;
Raílroads. Under this arrangement, CNLTG may use the raílroad&#13;
system by reserving in advance a full carload, the equivalent of&#13;
approximately 1,000 cartone, to be delivered to a specific designa-&#13;
tion. This takes careful planning of print rune, and coordlnation&#13;
with the time tables and scheduled runs of the railroad system.&#13;
Books move in presorted, consolidated lots from CNLTG's central&#13;
warehouse to the central post office in Pantaco, which is located&#13;
next to a railroad facility. From the central post office, railroad&#13;
care are loaded for their respective destinations. These cars carry&#13;
only CNLTG books. It normally takes three days or less for the&#13;
railroad cars to reach their destination near a regional warehouse&#13;
where the books are unloaded at the railroad station. The cost of&#13;
this unique service, not available to anyone else, is Mp 0.50 per&#13;
kilogram, or about US$0.02 at the then prevailing rate of exchange.&#13;
1 The rest goes by mail or truck.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-46-&#13;
Shipments to the various regíons are staggered. Normally&#13;
deliveries of new books to the more remote parta of the country are&#13;
made between February 15 and July 30, while the Federal District,&#13;
including Mexico City, which contains 20% of all the schools in the&#13;
country, le served in August.&#13;
Most of the textbooks are reprinted annually, generally between&#13;
August and February. They are to be delivered in advance of school&#13;
opening in September. CNLTG does not carry over large book inven-&#13;
tories from one year to the next. Nor would such a practice result&#13;
in any economies of scale since printing quantities run into the&#13;
millíons of copies per title in any case. Some allowance is made&#13;
for contingencies, e.g., wrong quantities being delivered, loes of&#13;
books in transit, water damage, or other causes. State warehouses&#13;
normally carry reserve stocks to cover such contingencies; where&#13;
local inventories are insufficient, the school dlstrict (inspector)&#13;
has to contact CNLTG directly and request replacements from CNITG's&#13;
central reserve stocks.&#13;
The first Btage of book distribution, for which CNLTG alone is&#13;
responsible, depends on well-developed logistics, planzing, and&#13;
coordination. By and large it seems to be working well, although&#13;
mishaps occur when railroad cars have to be shuttled from a main&#13;
line to a trunk line, or books have to be transhipped by truck, as&#13;
sometimes happens.&#13;
In the Second Staae, raliroad cara are unloaded at local&#13;
stations, and cartons are left to be picked up by local officials&#13;
and transported to the regional warehouse. At this stage of dis-&#13;
tribution additional problema are likely to be encountered. Books&#13;
are especially sensitive to humid conditions, or water damage&#13;
through rain. For reasons of economy CNLTG's cartone are not water-&#13;
proofed, nor ía their contents wrapped in waterproof paper or plastic.&#13;
Books need to be picked up promptly from the ralíroad station if&#13;
there ¡a likelihood of rain, and they need to be stored in well-&#13;
constructed, dry warehouses. Some of the regions do not have proper&#13;
warehouses. Sometimes the pick-up from the railroad station, which&#13;
may depend on the availability of local transport, such as municipal&#13;
trucks, le not well organized.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-47-&#13;
In the Third Stage, assuming that the first two etages of&#13;
distribution have worked, books are now available at the regional&#13;
warehouse. Distriet inspectora arrange tó have them picked up and&#13;
brought to a distriet storeroom. At this point members of the&#13;
community, local mayors, parente, the local militia, and farmere&#13;
with their donkeya pitch in to complete the chain of deliveries&#13;
to the schools ín each distríet.&#13;
Obviously Stages 2 and 3 of the system of distribution depend&#13;
on the goodwill and on the resources of atates and localities.&#13;
Wherever in rural areas school authorities and parente are anxious&#13;
and eager to get the textbooks into the hands of their children,&#13;
and where resources for efficient distribution exist in cities and&#13;
urban areas, books eventually will reach individual schools.&#13;
However, problema of distribution at Stages 2 and 3 are&#13;
numerous enough to concern CNL?G. The Department of Distribution&#13;
has launched a study and ls developing plano for improving the&#13;
system. Questionnaires have been sent to regional inspectors, to&#13;
warehouse managers, and to schools asking for information on the&#13;
condition of the books when they arrive, whether the correct&#13;
quantities of books are received, whether communications among&#13;
the people involved in the various etages of distribution work&#13;
well, and so forth.&#13;
One proposal for improving the dietribution system calla for&#13;
CNITG and the Federal Government to asaume direct responsibility&#13;
for the delivery of books to local inspectora or even to achools.&#13;
A proposal the Managing Director of CNLTG will present to SEP&#13;
would have the Federal Government construct appropriate regional&#13;
warehouses, especially in those states that have not been able to&#13;
accomplish this by themselves, The Department of Distribution&#13;
would like to eliminate intermediate pointe of delivery, such as&#13;
local warehouses or stockrooms run by local inspectora. They would&#13;
like regional warehouses to have the vehicles and other means&#13;
necessary to pick up books promptly from the local railroad station&#13;
and to deliver them equally expeditiously directly to their echool&#13;
destination.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-48-&#13;
B. The National Free Textbook Proaram&#13;
The free textbook program may be conveniently divided into&#13;
three overlapping phases, of which the last phase covera the efforts&#13;
of the present administration. These phases coincide with the pub-&#13;
lication of three generationa of textbooks. Por practical purposes&#13;
we are mostly concerned with the latest edition of textbooks, to&#13;
which we intend to devote much of this section.&#13;
1. Phase I: 1959-1970. the First Generation of Free Textbooks&#13;
This period encompasaes the establishment of CNLTG, described&#13;
earlier, its initial organization, staffing, definition of policies,&#13;
the beginninge of textbook development and production, the estab-&#13;
lishment of the printing plant, and the completion of the First&#13;
Generation of textbooks.&#13;
Major criteria evolved during the early years that remain valid&#13;
today:&#13;
a. Free textbooks will be provided for all children in both&#13;
public and private primary schools at grade levels 1-6;&#13;
b. Only one kind of textbook will be provided for each subJect&#13;
at each grade level.  It will be mandatory for every public and&#13;
private school to use the official textbooks in their classes,&#13;
thereby assuring that every Mexican child ¡a educated on the&#13;
basis of the same set of books,1 a policy designed to provide&#13;
a sense of unity among children;&#13;
c. Books will be of the textbook/workbook type, i.e., to be&#13;
written in, especially for the early grades. Thus each year&#13;
a new supply of textbooks will be printed and distributed to&#13;
all schools. Children will use these books in clase and in&#13;
the home, where in addition to helping them with their homework&#13;
1 Schools are permitted and even encouraged to prescribe&#13;
additional books, published by the private sector, as supplementary&#13;
materials where parents can afford such purchases. Moreover, in an&#13;
effort to strengthen a child's identification with the environment&#13;
and culture peculiar to the region in which he lives, the Secretariat&#13;
of Public Education has prepared supplementary texts (regional&#13;
monographs) apecific to each major region of the country (31 atates&#13;
plus the Federal Distriot).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-49-&#13;
they will constitute a mini-library, a feature that may be&#13;
particularly important in rural areas.   In this way it is&#13;
hoped that the books may even contribute to the education of&#13;
parents;&#13;
d. Books wíll be accompanied by instructions for the teacher,&#13;
teacherst manuals or guides (in addition, since 1975 regular&#13;
workshope for teachera have been initiated devoted to the&#13;
proper use of textbooks in the classroom);&#13;
e.  Since a new supply of textbooks is to be reprinted annually&#13;
for the entire primary school population, books must be produced&#13;
inexpensively, i.e., printed on newsprint or similar low-quality&#13;
paper, and inexpensively bound with paper covers. Despite these&#13;
limitatione, every effort should be made to produce attractive&#13;
books, including the extensive use of illustrations and of color&#13;
whenever affordable.&#13;
During Phase I CNLTG began the proceso of acquiring textbook&#13;
materiala by sponsoring conteste for teachers to submit suitable&#13;
manuscripte for publication. This approach did not produce quality&#13;
materiala and was eoon abandoned. Next CNLTG began an activo search&#13;
for competent teacher/authors. Still there was little attempt, or&#13;
perhaps appreciation of the need, to prepare textbooks that each&#13;
covered a major subject, such as mathematics or social studies, or&#13;
to plan textbook series that logically progrese from one grade to&#13;
the next.1 Little editorial guidance or help was offered the authors&#13;
aside from comments and critiques of manuscripts provided by the&#13;
"asesores pedagógicos permanentes," a group of technical reviewers&#13;
soon to be set up within CNLTG to review the submitted materials.&#13;
Nor was it thought necessary to test or pilot the textbooks in the&#13;
classroom in preliminary form prior to publication.&#13;
As a result, textbooks published during the first phase, for&#13;
better or worse, tended to reflect the writing ability, experience,&#13;
and competence of individual authors. A major subject such as&#13;
1 Refer to Peter H. Neumann, Publishing for Schools. Textbooks&#13;
and the Lees Developed Countries (World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
398, Washington, D.C.: The World Bank, 1980).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-50-&#13;
mathematics would be separated into individual volumes on arithmetic,&#13;
algebra, geometry, etc., and the resulting profusion of small books&#13;
made classroom mnanagement more difficult for teachera.&#13;
In 1962 CNLTG acquired the buildings and printíng plant of the&#13;
defunet newspaper El Tabloide, which had gone into bankruptcy. With&#13;
the plant CNLTG acquired a webfed rotary letterpress and some binding&#13;
equipment.  A second and third rotary press were added in 1964 and&#13;
1968, together with sheetfed offset presaes and more binding equip-&#13;
ment.1 At no time has the printíng plant been capable of meeting&#13;
all of the needs of CNLTG, nor has this been the intention of&#13;
management. During the early period over 50% of the printing was&#13;
given out to commercial printing establishmenta.  In the early 1970s&#13;
roughly 50% of all work was done wíthin the plant and 50% on the&#13;
outside. Only recently, in the 1980s, has this percentage shífted&#13;
with about 80% of the work being performed by the CNLTG printing&#13;
plant.&#13;
Duríng the early years of CNLTG the Mexican post office under-&#13;
took to mail the government textbooks free of charge. The military&#13;
was pressed into service to reach the outlying areas. It soon&#13;
became apparent that the mails could not be relied upon for the&#13;
timely distribution of large quantities of books. Distribution&#13;
methods then changed wíth increasing use being made of the national&#13;
railways, as described earlier.&#13;
CNLTGts First Generation of textbooks was printed in one color&#13;
with multicolor covers. By most standards these books were not as&#13;
good as many of those available in the Spanish-speaking world&#13;
produced by commercial publishers.  Nor should it be assumed that&#13;
these books were effectívely used in the classroom by teachers who&#13;
had little experience with textbooks, and had not received any&#13;
special training. Constraints of time and money, a lack of exper-&#13;
ience with the complexities and problems assocíated with the&#13;
development and mass production of prímary achool textbooks, a&#13;
reluctance to use the publishíng know-how and techniques avaílable&#13;
1 More equipment was added in 1980.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-51-&#13;
from knowledgeable sources, all took their toll. Nevertheless, a&#13;
grand total of 57 textbooks and teachers' manuals, totaling some&#13;
517 million copies, were produced and distributed by CNLTG during&#13;
the effective life of the First Generation of textbooks from 1960&#13;
to 1972. Without a doubt, many of these books reached the hands&#13;
of children who had never before seen or owned a book of any kind.&#13;
2. Phase II: 1970-1978. the Second Generation of Free&#13;
Textbooks&#13;
Before proceeding further with our brief descriptions of the&#13;
free textbooks, we may as well mention the obvious: this Study&#13;
cannot, and does not, offer a detailed analysis of the quality of&#13;
Mexican textbooks as educational tools. We are aware that no one&#13;
has as yet produced the perfect textbook, and Mexico is no exception.&#13;
However, more than most other countries with similar problema,&#13;
Mexico has struggled to provide educational materíals for its&#13;
schools on a very broad scale. What we are attempting to describe&#13;
in this Study ¡s the process and progress of the Mexican model.&#13;
Wherever poesible we are drawing on Mexican sources for descrip-&#13;
tione, for points of view, and for criticisms to illustrate that&#13;
process and progresa.&#13;
The Second Generation of free textbooks was conceived and&#13;
produced during the administration of President Luis Echeverrla&#13;
(1970-1976) and bears the imprint of his political-philosophical&#13;
views.&#13;
New textbooks began to appear during the early 1970s. These&#13;
books are still being reprinted and used today, though with some&#13;
revisions and modifications. The only exceptions are grades 1&#13;
and 2, where a radical departure from these earlier models is&#13;
taking place, which we describe under Phase III, or the Third&#13;
Generation.&#13;
To date the Second Generation of free textbooks in quality of&#13;
content, in design, illustration, and printing, and in sheer&#13;
numbers as well, has been the most important achievement of the&#13;
National Commission for Free Textbooks.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-52-&#13;
During the first 13 years of its existence CNLTG produced&#13;
approximately 57 mainline titles (First Generation)1 of which&#13;
517 million copies2 were printed and distributed.   During the next&#13;
9 years, 1972-1981, 55 titles of the new, larger (Second Generation)&#13;
books1 were published, and a total of 652.7 million copies2 were&#13;
printed, this time in four colors, and distributed. The total&#13;
number of copies in both instances include supplementary and special&#13;
editions published by CNLTG. However, the largest number of copies&#13;
by far was printed of the basic texts for grades 1 through 6.&#13;
Teaching materialas alone are not the sole cure for an ailing&#13;
educational system. Nevertheless, the lack of teaching materials&#13;
ranked third among problems directly affecting teaching that are&#13;
facing the Mexican educational system, according to a survey of&#13;
teachers conducted in 1976-1977.3 The Second Generation of free&#13;
textbooks is a major contribution of CNLTG towards alleviating&#13;
this lack of teaching materíals in schools.&#13;
"The focus of educational reform of this administration&#13;
(Echeverría, 1970-1976)," Dr. Pablo Latapl, Director of Prospectiva&#13;
Universitaria, said in an interview with Educación,4 Ois on primary&#13;
school teaching and the free textbooks. The new textbooks embody&#13;
the concept of education as a personal proceso of discovery and of&#13;
exploration, as an assimilation of methods and languages rather&#13;
than an accumulation of information." Hé adds that less attention&#13;
was given the updating of teachers and cites this as limiting the&#13;
effectiveness of the reform.&#13;
1 See Appendix E, Table 002, "Listing of All Titles Produced&#13;
by CNLTG, 1960-1981."1&#13;
2 See Appendix E, Table 001, "Total Number of Books Produced&#13;
by CNLTG, 1960-1982, in Millions of Copies," The figure cited&#13;
includes books printed for grades 1 and 2 of the Third Generation&#13;
of textbooks, first published in August, 1980.&#13;
3"11Sondeo de oplinión al magisterio nacignal de educaoión&#13;
primaria del sector federal sobre la problematica educativa"&#13;
(Survey of Opiníon of Federal Teachere of Primary Education),&#13;
Instituto Nacional de Investigaci6n Educativa (SEP), July 1977.&#13;
4~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
A quarterly magazine, the official organ of the National&#13;
Technical Council for Education.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-53-&#13;
The Second Generation of. free textbooks replaced the numerous&#13;
topics covered'by,the small books of the First Generation with four&#13;
major textbook series in language arts, mathematics, the natural&#13;
eciences, and social studies. Proceeding from grade 1 to grade 6,&#13;
four attractive series of books were produced, all of which are&#13;
richly illustrated and printed in four colora. As a rule, one book&#13;
per subject and grade is provided. Spanish, with two books each&#13;
for grades. 5 and 6, and the natural and social scíences combined&#13;
into one textbook for each of the first three grades, are the&#13;
exceptiona.&#13;
An important innovation of this generation ls that each subject&#13;
area now has an editorial coordinator .who -is responsible for the&#13;
entire six grades, and coordinates:the efforts of a team of authors,&#13;
consultanta, collaborators, designers and illustrators.  This is&#13;
meant to aseure continuity of development of the series, as well as&#13;
of style and presentation. Individual textbooks appear to be&#13;
developed and written by rather large teams or committees. A&#13;
cursory inspection of author teams, listed on the frórit pages of&#13;
the teachers' manuals, reveals a strong reliance on academics or&#13;
specialists from varlous prestigious institutions. This is common&#13;
practice wíth textbooks of the Third World, where primary scho'ol&#13;
teachera generally are not considered sufficiently educated to&#13;
participate in the writing of textbooks. However, excessive re-&#13;
liance on university people, who may be far removed from primary&#13;
school teaching experience, often creates problems. The textbooks&#13;
they produce tend to be too difficult for the ordinary teacher and&#13;
child, too ambitious in their number of concepts as well as in the&#13;
level of reading comprehension, and contain too much'material for&#13;
teachers to complete during the school term.  Indeed, such short-&#13;
cominga are evident in the Mexican téxtbooks and are pointed out&#13;
in the articles of Educación and of other publications.&#13;
Matemáticas (Mathematics): This serles of aix books and six&#13;
teachers' manuáls began to appear in 1972. The books are well-&#13;
designed and colorfully illustrated. To anyone familiar with the&#13;
development of modern mathematics teaching in the United States&#13;
during the 1950s and 1960s, the influence of programs such as&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-54-&#13;
SMSG (Science of Mathematics Study Group), and of textbooks derived&#13;
from such innovative programs, is evident.   "Matemáticas" begina&#13;
with sorting and grouping, with the language of sets and with other&#13;
basic mathematical concepts that tended to characterize the text-&#13;
books of that era. The books are consumable, write-in textbooks/&#13;
workbooks, and include numerous problems and exercises for pupils&#13;
to solve. Each lesson in the textbook concludes with workbook&#13;
pages for the pupil to complete. These are designed as exercises&#13;
and as evaluations of the pupíl's understanding of the previously&#13;
taught ideas or concepts. The teachers' manual explains that the&#13;
nucleus of each unit is a series of lessons or activities, and that&#13;
there are suggestions for the teacher on specific ways to develop&#13;
the teaching objectives. The manual stresses (quoted from the&#13;
teachers' manual of Grade 2) that throughout the textbook the main&#13;
emphasis i on the discovery of ideas. The lessons are to aid the&#13;
teacher in structuring the discussions and presenting the materials.&#13;
The manual concludes that it is advisable not to rely on memoriza-&#13;
tion, but to insist that the children obtain an adequate understand-&#13;
ing of the ideas involved in the subjects being studied. The&#13;
authors of the mathematícs series, as listed on the credit page,&#13;
are from prestigious national institutions, e.g., Centro de&#13;
Investigación y de Estudios Avanzados, Instituto Politécnico&#13;
Nacional; Colegio de Ciencias y Humanidades, Universidad Nacional&#13;
Autónoma de México.&#13;
"Matemáticas," grades 1-6, are attractive yet formidable&#13;
textbooks when one considers the likely background of most of the&#13;
primary teachers in Mexico,in modern mathematics. They poínt up&#13;
the difficulties of producing one textbook to be used by all&#13;
children in a system, whether they come from sophisticated urban&#13;
or simpler rural backgrounds.&#13;
Ciencias Naturales (Natural Scíences): The richly illustrated&#13;
secience series has similar roots in the modern science movements of&#13;
the 1950s and 1960s. Again, six textbooks and six teachers' manuals&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-55-&#13;
constitute the series.1 Observation and experiment are stressed as&#13;
a means of developing an understanding of the scientific method.&#13;
Topics range from the traditional "parts of a plant" to such con-&#13;
temporary and controversial features as sex education and the&#13;
environiment. The illustrations are beautiful and imaginative.&#13;
They range from reproductions of major Mexican and European paint-&#13;
ings used for chapter openings, to well-conceived photographs of&#13;
children performing simple experiments. Line drawings, photographs&#13;
and a wealth of other illustrative materials are in these books,&#13;
often reproduced in full color.&#13;
The authors of the scíence series are again drawn from the&#13;
Instituto Politécnico Nacional, the Universidad Nacional Autónoma&#13;
de México, the Secretarlia de Agricultura, the Secretaria de&#13;
Educación Pública, and similar institutions.&#13;
Ciencias Sociales (Social Studies): While some themes had to&#13;
be changed in most of the subject series to meet criticism or simply&#13;
to improve presentation, the most furor, the most determined opposi-&#13;
tion to the free textbooks has been engendered by the social studies&#13;
programs. This is not surprising as it is in social studies that&#13;
succeeding Mexican governments have been able to use the mandatory&#13;
textbook program to promote their respective political-social&#13;
philosophies.&#13;
As described earlier, President López Mateos saw the textbook&#13;
program as a powerful tool for unifying the country, for instilling&#13;
a sense of pride and of citizenship in its children. Education in&#13;
Mexico, writes El Maestro,2 is characterized by being:&#13;
a. Nationalistic: furnishing the elemente for understanding&#13;
our problems, taking advantage of our resources, defending our&#13;
1 Por grades 1-3 scíence and social studies are produced as&#13;
two parts of one textbook. They are not integrated, but instead&#13;
in grade 3, for example, the first 114 pages of the text deal with&#13;
science and next 108 pages with social studies, with separate tables&#13;
of contents for each section.&#13;
2A bulletin addressed to teachers published by the National&#13;
Technical Council for Education.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-56-&#13;
political independence, assuring our economic independence,&#13;
and preserving our ,culture;&#13;
b.  Free:  the State is comnitted to offering free education&#13;
as a public service;&#13;
c. Individual: sustaining the ideals of brotherhood, of&#13;
equality of rights, and developing'an attitude of collabora-&#13;
tion and respect among people;&#13;
d.  Democratic:  extending education to all peopíe within a&#13;
representative political system, and the continuous economic,&#13;
social, and cultural improvement of the life of the nation;&#13;
e* Scientific: separating education from religious belief,&#13;
being opposed to ignorance, unreasoning passion, fanaticism,&#13;
and prejudice against scientific progresa;&#13;
f. Compulsory: all Mexicans between the ages of 6 and 15&#13;
should obtain a primary education.&#13;
However, each Mexican president, within a broad spectrum of agree-&#13;
ment, has had his own views on how such characteristics should be&#13;
reflected in what is taught in the school system.&#13;
President Echeverria, for one, aligned his country with the&#13;
social revolutionary forces of the Third World, a political point&#13;
of view that was to permeate the social studies texts prepared&#13;
during his administration. He strongly supported the new. wave of&#13;
mathematics and science teaching coming out of prestigious academic&#13;
institutiona,&#13;
Amador Jiménez Alarcón, writing in Educación in 1977 on&#13;
"Social Studies in Primary Education," has this to say:   "Between&#13;
1972 and 1974 Mexican education made great strides.in the modifi-&#13;
cation of the curriculum of primary schools and the publication of&#13;
new textbooks. In spite of the obstacles--lack of preparation of&#13;
teachers; small groups of teachers who did not conform to the&#13;
political views put forth; open opposition; the burning of books&#13;
in various cities--the 'new books were generally accepted." He&#13;
adds that at least until 1976 subsequent printinge of these books&#13;
were effected without changing the general structure of the books,&#13;
albeit with a number of modifications following the suggestions by&#13;
teachers and by some of the public opposition.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-57-&#13;
Jiménez Alarcón lista the following comments by teachers and&#13;
epecialists regarding the free textbooks in general, not just the&#13;
social studies texts, which appear relevant judged by similar-&#13;
comments from other sources:&#13;
a,  Books in the different subject areas suffer from being&#13;
produced separately, making correlation in the teaching-&#13;
learning process more difficult;1&#13;
b.  Some of the books contain an excessive amount of material&#13;
for coverage during the school year, others may not contain&#13;
enough;2&#13;
c.  There is not always agreement between the textbook and&#13;
syllabus;'&#13;
d. The integration of subjects is not fully accomplished in&#13;
all books;&#13;
e.  Specialists predominate among the author teams, .who have&#13;
no teaching experience at the elementary level, which causes&#13;
teaching problems;&#13;
f. A total of five books for pupils in grades 1 and 2 creates&#13;
difficulties for such small children in carrying and handling&#13;
1 For example, the vocabulary taught in language arts and that&#13;
used to teach other subjects at:the same grade level need careful&#13;
correlation.&#13;
2 It ¡o often argued that books can safely contain more&#13;
material than the teacher can cover during a school term, that this&#13;
added material is a further resource for brighter students, etc. At&#13;
primary school level it is important for the teacher and the average&#13;
child to be able to cover adequatelv (including questions and dis-&#13;
cussions) the complete textbook materials. Such an achievement&#13;
provides motivation and does not leave unexplained gaps in knowledge&#13;
when, as so often happens, the class does not .finish its asíigned&#13;
text for grade 2, for example, and yet begins with a new textbook&#13;
in grade 3 that assumes the grade 2 content has been mastered.&#13;
3 Another common complaint yet almost inevitable in situations&#13;
where new textbooks are introduced. In some situations the teáchers'&#13;
manual may be used to offer suggestions for covering those items&#13;
from the syllabus that are missing in the text, in others the new&#13;
government-approved textbook may become the de facto syllabus.&#13;
However, if the teacher is confronted with such a dilemma and not&#13;
given explanation or aid, he or she may well decide not to use the&#13;
new textbook and instead cover the syllabus in the traditional manner.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-58-&#13;
so many books, as well as their being able to assimilate and&#13;
integrate the contents;1&#13;
g.  Many teachers doubt the scientific validity of some of&#13;
the concepts presented in the books.&#13;
In spite of these comments, adds Jiménez Alarcón, the new&#13;
books and syllabi are much superior to the first versions (genera-&#13;
tion) of textbooks. They can be said to achieve their objective of&#13;
teaching the child to investigate, to know and to learn, applying&#13;
scientific methods. Furthermore, in social studies an important&#13;
problem that has been solved with considerable success in the new&#13;
syllabi is the integration of all the social seciences (sociology, eco-&#13;
nomics, anthropology, law, social psychology, political secience,&#13;
geography, history, and civics) in explaining concrete problems.&#13;
EsPafiol (Language Arts):  In the Second Generation of language&#13;
arts textbooks the principal objective in grade 1, as stated in the&#13;
Introduction to the Teachers' Manuals, is "to teach children to read&#13;
via a rapid and easy 'ideo-visual' discrimination. An adequate visual&#13;
vocabulary is developed by using the global method of structural&#13;
analysis...children learn to recognize words as a result of a constant&#13;
visualization of words....'"&#13;
The language arts texts for all six grade levels of this&#13;
generation were authored by ene group of specialists (from the&#13;
Instituto Mexicano de la Audición y el Lenguaje, the Escuela Manuel&#13;
Bartolomé Cossío, the Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México, El&#13;
Colegio de México, and the Secretariat of Education), and were&#13;
published between 1972 and 1976. They are remarkable for a number&#13;
of reasons:&#13;
a. The first five textbooks and teachers' manuals were&#13;
published within two years of the decision to revise radically&#13;
the First Generation of textbooks, i.e., in 1972. Pupil book&#13;
6 was published in 1974 and its teachers' manual in 1976;&#13;
b. The books are lavishly illustrated and printed in full&#13;
color, including the teachers' manuals;&#13;
1 The problem has been addressed with the Third Generation&#13;
(Integrated) texto.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-59-&#13;
c. Textbooks and teachers' manuals include introductions with&#13;
words of advice to pupils and teachers, e.g.:&#13;
Pupils are urged to learn to read and to develop the&#13;
reading habit, reading being their passport to a better life;&#13;
teachers are advised that Mexican Spanish ls of necessity&#13;
different from the language of the Mother Country (Spain).&#13;
This ls as it should be, it is explained, for what is spoken&#13;
in schools is the authentic language, i.e., the spoken language.&#13;
To quote from the introduction: "We are going to teach Spanish&#13;
but with other criteria (than were used in the past). A new&#13;
grammar exists that is part of "linguistics"....Linguistics lS&#13;
one of the great sclences of our time.....like other sciences,&#13;
it is dedicated to observing. It observes language, sees it&#13;
as it is, and does not worry about what it "should be"...it&#13;
acknowledges the prímacy of the spoken language....A linguist&#13;
stresses use (of language) before grammatical correctness:&#13;
what people say (i.e., common usage) ls generally acceptable.&#13;
Nobody is going to tell us what our Spanish (language) should&#13;
be, because we are the ones who are going to discover it...."1&#13;
The pupil texts of grades 1-4 are divided into two sections:&#13;
brief examples of different literary styles for structural analysis&#13;
including exercises (2/3 of the book), and longer excerpts from&#13;
literature for readíng profíciency. Examples and excerpts vary&#13;
greatly in style and authorship (a few were written or adapted by&#13;
the specíalists-authors, but most are from original materials, in-&#13;
cluding translationa, taken from world literature). Each book also&#13;
contains a selection from Mexican history; most of the books end&#13;
with a stanza of the Mexican national anthem.&#13;
Two volumes are published for each grade 5 and 6, separating&#13;
the teaching of grammar and vocabulary with exercises from the&#13;
reading selectiona. A brief listing of some of the authors whose&#13;
1 Español 2. Libro del Maestro Para el Segundo Grado (México,&#13;
D.F.: Secretaria de Educación Pública, 1972), pp. 16-17.&#13;
Underlíned words appear in italics in the Introduction, and those&#13;
enclosed in quotation marks are similarly enclosed in quotation&#13;
marks in same; the words in parentheses are ours.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-60-&#13;
works are contained in the reader for grade 6 demonstrates the&#13;
diversity of the offerings: Ray Bradbury, Julio Cortázar, Art&#13;
Buchwald, Gabriela Mistral, Azorin, Oscar Wilde, Gabriel Garcia&#13;
Márquez, Herman Melville, Rafael Alberti, Luis de Góngora, Lewis&#13;
Carroll.&#13;
Organization of the material at these higher levels remains&#13;
basically the same as for the earlier grades. Grammar is formally&#13;
presented in grade 6, where an appendix is devoted to the conjuga-&#13;
tion of verbs, rules of punctuation, etc.&#13;
The teachers' manuals describe each lesson in some detail,&#13;
stating objectives and giving hints on how best to utilize the&#13;
activities. Only the teachers' manual for book 3 presents some&#13;
pages of the pupilst edition as reduced faesimiles. Unfortunately,&#13;
these pages are reduced to such an extent that they are barely&#13;
legible. All teachers' manuals contain a section devoted to the&#13;
"Elements of Linguistics.11 Teachers' guides are moderate in size&#13;
(120-208 pages) and are well printed; whether they are extensively&#13;
read and used by teachers has been called into question.&#13;
We have tried with the foregoing to present a small measure&#13;
of feelíng and of appreciation for these textbooks. Their strength&#13;
and attractiveness are remarkable, yet they share the shortcomings&#13;
common to school books produced in many lands.&#13;
3. Phase III: 1978 - Present (1981). The New Integrated&#13;
Textbooks for Grades 1 and 2&#13;
In an earlier section on the establishment of the Sub-Directorate&#13;
for Educational Content and Methods within SEP, we have briefly&#13;
discussed the concepts and organization behind the new integrated&#13;
textbooks for grades 1 and 2 of the free textbook program for&#13;
primary schools. These books, with their workbooks (cut-out books)&#13;
and teachers' guides, are the first products of the separation from&#13;
CNLTG of editorial and editorial production,1 which occured in 1978&#13;
1 Editorial production embraces book desígn, illustration,&#13;
typesetting, and page make-up, all of the steps preparatory to&#13;
camera work.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-61-&#13;
when the Sub-Directorate was established.   They are the beginnings&#13;
of a Third Generation of free textbooks.&#13;
We have alluded in various places in this Study to Mexican&#13;
criticisms of the free textbooks, which at times have come from the&#13;
general public, other times from academzics,and are documented in&#13;
speeches, newspaper columns, and articles in periodicais. :There&#13;
have been criticisms of teaching philosophy and of method., The&#13;
content of sorne of the textbooks has been. attacked as too radical,&#13;
or variously as too traditional, urban, or .middle class.. Critics&#13;
have complained that some books contain too much information, others&#13;
too little.  The global method of teaching reading, instituted in&#13;
1972 with the Second Generation of textbooks, was rejected by many&#13;
teachers; modern mathematics renewed the familiar complaint for a&#13;
need for more skill development.&#13;
The Sub-Directorate, as a new force combining responsibility&#13;
for curriculum development and the preparation of new textbook&#13;
materials, launched a major effort to produce new teaching materials.&#13;
Starting in 1978 it began the revision of syllabi and of the text-&#13;
books used in primary school. Teachers, other educators, and&#13;
specialists were asked their opinion of necessary changes. The&#13;
result led the Sub-Directorate to propose a new approach: integrated&#13;
textbooks for grades 1 and 2.1   It was reasoned that three or four&#13;
books in four different subjects were too cumbersome for children&#13;
and teachers at the early levels; that children of six or seven years&#13;
of age,view the world around them as a whole; that previously children&#13;
had to-integrate by themselves the different subjects that the books&#13;
will now do for them. Another result of the survey was the decision&#13;
to stress language arts ánd mathematics in grades 1 and 2. The&#13;
presentation of these subjects was to be integrated and taught within&#13;
a setting of the natural and social sciénces, including physical and&#13;
health education and the arts.   Primary skills to be developed are&#13;
observation and communication; theksocialization of the child is a&#13;
primary teaching objective.&#13;
1 Textbooks for grades 3-6 will be published in subject-&#13;
oriented series as before.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-62-&#13;
Once these criteria were established, several proposals were&#13;
written for the first grade program. The aid of the National Tech-&#13;
nical Council for Education was enlisted, as described earlier, in&#13;
polling 370,000 primary school teachers through questionnaires on&#13;
their reactions to these proposal. We were told that 162,000&#13;
teachers responded and that these responses were considered in&#13;
modifying the original plans. We do not know how such a massive&#13;
response was tabulated, how much time teachers actually had to com-&#13;
plete the questionnaire, or how meaningful responses were in relation&#13;
to the effort that was expended in the polling. However, the decision&#13;
was made to publish integrated texts, and to test both new textbook&#13;
materials and teachers' guides in the form of preliminary editions.&#13;
These are the first textbooks and teachers' materíals since the&#13;
inception of the free textbook program to undergo extensive field&#13;
teBting.&#13;
The testing of textbook materials started in the summer of 1979,&#13;
with groups organized during school vacations.1 It continued during&#13;
the school year 1979-1980. The materials were tested in experimental&#13;
editions of single units, essentially 48-page sections, prepared with&#13;
illustrations and with covers, and printed in full color to simulate&#13;
the final form of the books.   Five thousand (5000) copies were nor-&#13;
mally printed of these preliminary versions. A cross section of 22&#13;
and of 432 schools representing the 31 states, urban and rural,&#13;
public and private schools, was selected for field testing. Observers&#13;
attended class each day to monitor the reactions of teachers and&#13;
pupils to the integrated materials. They were required to send&#13;
monthly reports to the Testing Department of the Sub-Directorate,&#13;
which supervised the testing. As a result of the testing, content&#13;
and graphic design of the units were revised or modified, at times&#13;
a second version of a particular unit would be prepared as an&#13;
1 The timing of this part of the testing probably left little&#13;
time for teachers actually to read and to comment on the books.&#13;
2 Twenty-two (22) schools for grade 1 and 43 schools for&#13;
grade 2.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-63-&#13;
experimental revised edition and tested again. Some of the questions&#13;
addressed by the observers were the following:&#13;
* Relationship between child and book: Does the child finish&#13;
the material?&#13;
* Is the material clearly presented?&#13;
* Are the activities in the books adequate?&#13;
*  Is the sequence of materials adequately developed?&#13;
* How do teachers help pupils understand the books?&#13;
* How are the books used in different areas of the country?&#13;
* How do the books assist the total integration of the child?&#13;
* How do pupils respond to the book?&#13;
Similarly, consultations and conferences took place with regard&#13;
to the preparation of the teachere' guide that culminated in the&#13;
introduction of a preliminary edition of the guide for grade 1 to a&#13;
session of the National Technical Council for Education held in&#13;
Cocoyoc, near Mexico City, on April 25 and 26, 1980. At this meeting&#13;
it was decided to distribute 450,000 copies of this preliminary&#13;
teachers' guide to every primary school teacher in the country.&#13;
This occured during June, 1980. Each copy of the guide was accom-&#13;
panied by a questionnaire for the teacher to complete. Results of&#13;
this extensive sampling probably produced only minor changes in the&#13;
final version of the teachers' guide that came off the press shortly&#13;
thereafter in August of 1980. However, responses continue to be&#13;
received and will influence changes to be made in subsequent print-&#13;
ings. Additionally, we were told the mailing of these guides helped&#13;
to familiarize all teachers with the new approach and the new&#13;
materials that they were to use in school later that year. It gave&#13;
them a feeling of participation in the upcoming effort to improve&#13;
the quality of education.&#13;
What are the new integrated textbooks like? We have seen final&#13;
versions of the grade 1 materials, a few preliminary units of grade&#13;
2, and the preliminary teachers' guide for grade 2. Their physical&#13;
appearance is as follows:&#13;
Grade 1:  Mi Libro de Primero, Tomo 1&#13;
6 7/8 x 10 1/4"; 240 pages printed in full, four-&#13;
color offset; paper covers in four colors; perfect&#13;
binding;60 2 textpaper;125gm2&#13;
binding; 60 gsm2 text paper; 125 gsmn cover stock,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-64-&#13;
Mi Libro de Primero, Tomo 2&#13;
6 7/8 x 9 7/8"; 240 pages printed in full, four-&#13;
color offset; paper covers printed in four colors;&#13;
perfect binding; 60 gsm2 text paper; 125 gsm2 cover&#13;
stock.-&#13;
Mi Libro de Primero. Tomo 1. Recortable (Cut-outs)&#13;
6 7/8 x 9 5/8"; 16+112 pages printed on one side&#13;
only in full-four-color offset; perfect bound;&#13;
2                                2&#13;
105.gsm. text paper (cut-outs); 125 gsm   cover stock.&#13;
Mi Libro de Primero. Tomo 2. Recortable (Cut-outs)&#13;
6 7/8 x 10 1/8"; 112 pages printed on one side only&#13;
in full, four-color offset; perfect binding; 105&#13;
gsm2 text paper (cut-outs); 125 gsm2 cover stock.&#13;
Libro para el Maestro. Primer Grado (Tomo 1 and 2) -&#13;
(Teachers' Guide, First Grade)&#13;
6 7/8 x 10 1/8"; 412+68 pages.printed in two colors;&#13;
perfect binding;.60 gsm2 text paper; 125 gsm2 cover&#13;
stock.&#13;
It is evident that the two-volume integrated textbooks,1 accom-&#13;
panied by two volumes of cut-outs, a total of 480+240 pages, equal&#13;
in number of pages the three or four books of the Second Generation&#13;
first-grade texto previously offered in the natural and social&#13;
sciences, mathematics, and Spanish. The amount of material in the&#13;
integrated texto we would judge also to be equivalent roughly to&#13;
what was contained in the earlier Second Generation texts.&#13;
Each volume of the integrated textbook is organized into four&#13;
units of approximately 45 pages per unit, followed by a section of&#13;
about 54 pages entitled "lecturas," or reading selections. The&#13;
symbol of a pair of scissors appears at the bottom of those text&#13;
pages that have related activities in the two cut-out books that&#13;
accompany the textbook material. Cut-out books serve as coloring&#13;
pages and for cutting-out and pasting into related sections pictures,&#13;
1 These texts may be combined into one volume in future printings;&#13;
a book of almost 500 pages would be difficult for small children to&#13;
handle.-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-65-&#13;
numbers, or words to complete an activity. Great care has been&#13;
taken, and in this instance in particular, feedback from field&#13;
testing has been helpful, to select appropriate, unambiguous and&#13;
attractive illustrations, mostly color photographs and some full&#13;
color drawings.&#13;
The eight units making up volumes 1 and 2 for grade 1 are&#13;
divided into four sub-units. Their headings give some indication&#13;
of content:&#13;
Mi Libro de Primero. Tomo 1 (Mv First Grade Book. Volume 1)&#13;
Unit 1, module 1: Me.&#13;
Unit 1, module 2: Things that I see.&#13;
Unit 1, module 3: How things are.&#13;
Unit 1, module 4: How it sounds and where it is.&#13;
Unit 2, module 1: What I like to do.&#13;
Unit 2, module 2:   The family.&#13;
Unit 2, module 3: The house.&#13;
Unit 2, module 4: The services of the house.&#13;
Unit 3, module 1: Seeds.&#13;
Unit 3, module 2: We are born.&#13;
Unit 3, module 3: We grow.&#13;
Unit 3, module 4: We collaborate.&#13;
Unit 4, module 1: The place where I live.&#13;
Unit 4, module 2: People work.&#13;
Unit 4, module 3: We use water and wind.&#13;
Unit 4, module 4:   People make useful things.&#13;
Readings&#13;
Mi Libro de Primero, Tomo 2 (Mv First Grade Book. Volume 2)&#13;
Unit 5, module 1: The countryside and the city.&#13;
Unit 5, module 2: Work in the city and in the countryside.&#13;
Unit 5, module 3: We transform nature.&#13;
Unit 5, module 4: Collaboration between countryside and city.&#13;
Unit 6, module 1: Our house protecto us.&#13;
Unit 6, module 2: Neighbors.&#13;
Unit 6, module 3: Everywhere the sun rises.&#13;
Unit 6, module 4: We learn everywhere.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-66-&#13;
Unit 7, module 1:  Places in Mexico.&#13;
Unit 7, module 2:  Communication.&#13;
Unit 7, module 3:  We are Mexicans.&#13;
Unit 7, module 4:  Mexico and other countries.&#13;
Unit 8, module 1: Before, now, later.&#13;
Unit 8, module 2:  W/hat goes on in my family.&#13;
Unit 8, module 3:  The place where I live...then and now.&#13;
Unit 8, module 4:  Mexico and her past.&#13;
Readings&#13;
The Recortables or "Cut-out" books follow the organization of&#13;
the textbooks and provide activities for coded (seissors) textbook&#13;
pages as explained earlier.&#13;
The teachers' guide is a large book. It will have to be used&#13;
by the teacher in conjunetion with the textbooks, since textbook&#13;
pages are not reproduced in the guide.1   The teachers' guide retains&#13;
much of the appearance of a preliminary edition; neither paper&#13;
quality nor the perfect binding make it likely that the book will&#13;
last long if extensively used by the teacher. This may be intentional,&#13;
as there are plans for revising the guide.&#13;
The guide begins with a two-page preface explaining the role of&#13;
the Secretariat of Education to the teacher, the creation and the&#13;
role of the Council for Educational Content and Methods established&#13;
in 1978, and of the Sub-Directorate in the development of curriculum&#13;
teaching materials, and especially, the new integrated texts. By&#13;
pointing out in some detail, as we have done earlier, the process of&#13;
consultations, of experimentation, and of testing that produced the&#13;
new books, the preface intends to assure the teacher that these&#13;
materials have been created with his or her participation and will&#13;
function in the classroom. It asks, in addition, for feedback and&#13;
comments from teachers based on classroom experience, and for sugges-&#13;
tions for improving the textbooks and guides in future revisions.&#13;
1 When textbook pages are reproduced, publishers call the results&#13;
a "teachers' edition" or "TE" rather than a guide or manual.   With&#13;
careful design, producing a TE has the advantage for the teacher of&#13;
combining textbook pages and teaching instructions into one book for&#13;
easy reference.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-67-&#13;
A section on primary education in Mexico follows coverino in&#13;
approximately 36 pages the subject matter of the basic curriculum,&#13;
i.e., language arts, mathematics, the natural seiences, social&#13;
studies, technical education, physical education, health education,&#13;
and the arts. Teaching objectives are listed and briefly explained&#13;
for each of these subjects.&#13;
The section that follows, "The Integrated Program for the&#13;
Primary Grades," elaborates in some 40 pages the psychology,&#13;
pedagogical aspects, and especially the structure of the integrated&#13;
program, which makes it different from the textbooks of the Second&#13;
Generation used previously by teachers. Several schematic drawings&#13;
illustrate structural relationships between the abstract and the&#13;
concrete; basic concepts expressed in real situations--verified by&#13;
observation and expressed.  Reading, writing, and mathematics are&#13;
covered in more detail in this section; class management and evalua-&#13;
tion of pupils are among the topics.&#13;
The bulk of the teachers' guide, some 300 pages, contains detailed&#13;
comments and suggestions for activities related to content and the&#13;
objectives of the eight units of the two textbooks for the first grade.&#13;
The teacher is expected to personalize his or her copy of the&#13;
guide, which provides space for the teacher to write in comments and&#13;
observations relating to the proposed activities. Preprinted forms&#13;
are included in the guide to encourage the teacher to list activities&#13;
of his own developed in connection with the presentation of the&#13;
materials, and for explaining his methods and means for evaluation;&#13;
the forms are to be sent to the editors.&#13;
The appendix contains a bibliography for the teachers' reference&#13;
in addition to a table of suggested activities.&#13;
The overall impression one gains from looking at these books,&#13;
confirmed by some of our interviews,is that textbook content as well&#13;
as the methods for teaching Spanish and mathematics, have not changed&#13;
that much from the previous books of the Second Generation for the&#13;
early grades. Reading continues to be taught by the global method,&#13;
mathematics remains in the modern vein. What has changed is the&#13;
structure and organization of the materials, emphasis, and selection,&#13;
and noticeably the quality of the illustrative materials. There&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-68-&#13;
appears to be strong reliance on making teachers use the teachers'&#13;
guide. Furthermore, the introduction of the new textbooks will be&#13;
supported by workshops to be organized by SEP.&#13;
The Third Generation of free textbooks continues to be the&#13;
work mainly of groups of specialists and of reviews by committees&#13;
and other peer groups at the higher levels of the educational&#13;
establishment, as was the case with the Second Generation. However,&#13;
the emergence within the Sub-Directorate of a dedicated, professional&#13;
group that provides inhouse capability for textbook development, has&#13;
the backing of SEP, and works for gradual changes of textbooks over&#13;
a number of years and for regular revisions, promises further&#13;
improvements in the teaching materials and in the revision of the&#13;
curriculum.&#13;
4.  A Summary of the Free Textbook Program&#13;
a. Books Produced: Titles and Quantities&#13;
Table 0011 summarizes the total number of books produced&#13;
annually by CNLTG from 1960 to 1982: 1,262.7 million copies in&#13;
all. The bulk of these quantities is accounted for by the textbooks&#13;
and teachers' guides produced for grades 1-6 of the national free&#13;
textbook program, though as was previously stated, they include&#13;
some special editions and titles not part of the mainline textbook&#13;
program.&#13;
Table 002 lists by grade all of the titles produced by CNLTG&#13;
between 1960-1981, giving the date they were first published and&#13;
the length of time they remained in production. Fifty-seven (57)&#13;
titles are listed for the First Generation of textbooks, 55 titles&#13;
for the Second Generation, 5 titles for the Third Generation, plus&#13;
some 96 miscellaneous titles.   The latter include supplementary&#13;
texts produced occasionally and used generally for a few years&#13;
only, Braille editions now discontinued of the books for all six&#13;
grades, a few titles in various Indian languages, books for adult&#13;
education, and so forth.&#13;
1 All tables listed in this section appear in Appendix E.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-69-&#13;
b. Coste&#13;
It i difficult to provide all-inclusive costa by title or&#13;
series in book publishíng. In private sector publishing indirect&#13;
costs are often -tated as percentages of net sales and absorbed&#13;
as such. It le necessary for the'private sector to establish&#13;
costs that are related as'closely as possible to individual titles&#13;
or series.  Such costs divided by estimated "lífetime" sales in&#13;
copies enable the publisher to price his books within the range&#13;
permitted by competition or government.   His calculations enable&#13;
him to determine whether a publishing project le likely to result&#13;
in a profit, will break even or threatens a loes.   Some'costs/&#13;
expenses are easy to identífy and to assign, they are "direct"&#13;
costs and include production coste, manufacturíng coste (paper,&#13;
printing, and binding), and some aspects of promotion.   Other&#13;
expenses are more difficult to allocate to specific publishíng&#13;
projects: general and admínistrative expenses; management; ware-&#13;
housing; editorial research; even marketing and sales. These&#13;
expenses are incurred by the various departments of a publishing&#13;
house that handle the entire list of publications at any one time.&#13;
They become "indirect" costs and are generally accumulated by&#13;
category over a period of one year and expressed as percentages&#13;
of net sales, e.g., expenses forthe salesfórce were 10% of&#13;
annual sales in the average year, ergo, it le assumed that it&#13;
costs 10% of net príce of each title to sell it.   There are&#13;
refinements of this-formula, but for our purpose the general¡-&#13;
zation holds true. The overriding incentive for a private publisher&#13;
to keep track of his coste, and to hold costs down to reasonable&#13;
proportions by running an efficient operation, is the profit&#13;
motive.&#13;
Government, quite properly, does not operate in this manner.&#13;
It does not normally develop or sell a product nor does it expect&#13;
to make a profit, at least not in societies that are based on the&#13;
private ownership of the means of production, as le generally the&#13;
case in Mexico.  Governments operate on the basis of annual budget&#13;
allocations, they do not normally use cost accounting procedures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-70-&#13;
Therefore, it is much more difficult to establish the true costs&#13;
of government-produced books. As the publisher of national text-&#13;
books government has certain advantages over private industry:&#13;
it establishes a monopoly for its products; assigns itself the&#13;
largest captive audience in the nation, the school population;&#13;
makes the use of ita books mandatory; self-finances; keeps no&#13;
permanent inventory; extends no discount or credit; and accepts&#13;
no returns. As a school publisher government publishes bestsellers,&#13;
editions that run into the millions of copies (it is not likely to&#13;
produce a book that it cannot somehow distribute in the expected&#13;
numbers). Por all of these reasons, a fair comparison of costa&#13;
incurred by government to produce books and of prices the private&#13;
sector must normally charge to meet its altogether different set&#13;
of expenses on a great number of titles produced in small editions,&#13;
as well as to make a profit, is not only difficult but often&#13;
impossible.&#13;
We explain this in some detail, not because we necessarily&#13;
believe that governments should not publish textbooks. We do&#13;
recommend, however, that a government that contemplates taking&#13;
over textbook production assess carefully all of the costs, in-&#13;
cluding the impact of its actions on ite private publishing industry.&#13;
A cooperative effort between government and private publishers can&#13;
produce quality books at low cost, an acceptable profit for the&#13;
private investors, and help the development of a national pub-&#13;
lishing industry. Creating a nationalized textbook program&#13;
rather than purchasing textbooks from the publishing industry&#13;
with public funds,may be a political decision made necessary by&#13;
circumstances, as in the case of Mexico. It can only rarely be&#13;
justified on purely economic grounds. Later sections of this Study&#13;
will show how the present Mexican government is actively increasing&#13;
its number of cooperative publishing ventures.&#13;
After this preamble our statement that we find it difficult to&#13;
assess the full costs of the Mexican free textbook program may come as&#13;
no surprise to the Reader. It would be even more difficult to compare&#13;
these costs on an equitable basis with the prices of textbooks in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-71-&#13;
Mexican bookstores. We have been able, nevertheless, to compile&#13;
some admittedly incomplete cost figures for the free textbook&#13;
project.&#13;
Table 003 (Appendix E) lists annual subsidies received by&#13;
CNLTG from the Mexican government in current not constant Mexican&#13;
pesos, beginning with 1960 and ending with 1981. It Surthermore&#13;
lists major capital investments made in the printing plant in 1960,&#13;
1975, and 1980, again in current pesos.&#13;
Table 004 provides costs over the same number of years using&#13;
as units 32-page signatures (7 x 10"1 page size) and breaking down&#13;
costs by 1) paper, printing, and binding, 2) distribution, and&#13;
3) general expenses.&#13;
Table 005 uses the above figures to extrapolate some admit-&#13;
tedly rough cost estimates for an average book printed in four&#13;
colors of seven signatures or 224 pages, approximately 7 x 10",&#13;
produced between 1965-1980.&#13;
It is difficult to compare annual cost figures given in&#13;
Table 005. CNLTG produced many more books in some years than in&#13;
others. Besides, first editions printed in one color began to be&#13;
phased out in the early 1970s and to be replaced by four-color&#13;
versions.  Paper costs may well have varied considerably from&#13;
year to year, and inflation has been especially high over the&#13;
last few years.&#13;
We would estimate the average book of 224 pages probably cost&#13;
the Mexican government around US$.751 in 1980 and close to US$1.00&#13;
in 1981. The new integrated texts of the Third Generation, with&#13;
240 pages per book and heavy editorial production expenses, may&#13;
be closer to US$1.251 each.&#13;
1 At the then prevailing rate of exchange of US$1.00 = Mp 24.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
VI. Related Educational Publishing Activities&#13;
Supported by Government&#13;
A.  The General Directorate for Publications and Libraries&#13;
The Secretariat of Public Education is primarily concerned with&#13;
institutionalizing mass education and eradicating illiteracy, as we&#13;
have noted previously. With a population of almost 70,000,000, Mexico&#13;
has a primary and secondary school population of 18,000,000 students.&#13;
One of the five objectives of the present administration and of the&#13;
Secretariat of Education is to guarantee all Mexicans an education&#13;
of 10 years.&#13;
The Secretariat, having achieved its long-term goal of providing&#13;
a place in school and a book in each subject area for each pupil in&#13;
grades 1-6, is now focusing much of its attention on pre-school&#13;
education, on supporting the development of kindergartena and of&#13;
pre-school materials, and.with the establishment in January, 1981&#13;
of an Under Secretary for Secondary Education, on secondary and&#13;
technical education. In addition, illiteracy continues to be a&#13;
serious problem for the country and hampers its continued development.&#13;
In sum, SEP has to provide education for its 15,000,000 primary&#13;
school children, for 300,000 indigenous children for whom Spanish il&#13;
not a first language, for 3,000,000 secondary level atudents, and&#13;
for adults as well.  It has to upgrade the education of 13,000,000&#13;
adults who have completed less than six years of schooling, and&#13;
moreover, provide intensive self-study primary school programa for&#13;
adults who have never participated in the educational process at&#13;
all. In líne with these responsibilities, SEP has undertaken to&#13;
support the publication of a wealth of educational materiala in&#13;
addition to the free textbook program for grades 1-6.&#13;
Under the aegis of the Under Secretary for Culture, the General&#13;
Directorate for Publications and Libraries was established in&#13;
December of 1977 with the present Under Secretary for Culture as&#13;
1 Llrecci~n General de Publicaciones y Bibliotecas.&#13;
1Dirección General de Publícacíones y Bibliotecas,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-74-&#13;
its first director.   It was given the mandate to promote the&#13;
reading habit throughout the country. Once established the General&#13;
Directorate undertook to research the state of the book in Mexico:&#13;
its cost, its use, its accessability. The research showed that:&#13;
1. Books were expensive, chiefly because of the high cost&#13;
of paper (much of the paper manufactured in Mexico is not&#13;
intended for books);&#13;
2.  Families, on the whole, had little money to spend on&#13;
books;&#13;
3. Book distribution to outlying regions was poor.&#13;
Consequently, the General Directorate mapped the following strategy&#13;
in order to promote the reading habit:&#13;
1. Produce inexpensive subsidized books;&#13;
2. Publish quality (in both content and physical aspect)&#13;
comic books aimed at the adult illiterate population, as its&#13;
first thrust at promoting the reading habit;&#13;
3. Produce and publish such books in areas not well covered&#13;
by the private publishing sector, e.g., children's literature;&#13;
4. Make a serious commitment to upgrading and expanding the&#13;
nation's public library system.&#13;
The General Directorate began its publishing activities in&#13;
1979; by 1981 it produced and published, at times in conjunetion&#13;
with other governmental agencies or with private publishers, some&#13;
30,000,000 copies of adult education materials and some 30,000,000&#13;
copies of cultural materials. All of these materials are subsidized&#13;
by the government. They are distributed free of charge or sold at&#13;
very low prices.&#13;
The General Directorate has a large staff: some 200 inhouse&#13;
and freelance writers, editors, and production personnel; 100&#13;
administrative staff; about 700 employees in libraries throughout&#13;
the country. Its annual budget for 1981 was Mp 1'196,000,000 or&#13;
approximately US$45,000,000 at the then prevailing rate of exchange.&#13;
1 The General Directorate existed previous to 1977 as a group&#13;
charged with coordinating publications with libraries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-75-&#13;
The General Directorate for Publications and Libraries may act&#13;
as its own publisher or may produce material for others to publish&#13;
under contract. Its own publications include "El Correo del Libro,"&#13;
a bulletin for teachers published 10 times a year in full color,&#13;
with synopses of recent titles published orsponsored by SEP, and a&#13;
listing of all of SEP's recent publications and copublications.&#13;
All titles are offered to teachers at reduced prices and may be&#13;
purchased by mail. Titles copublished by SEP with the private&#13;
publishing sector are offered to teachers at a 20966-30% discount&#13;
from publisher's list price, the General Directorate having pur-&#13;
chased a certain quantity (3000-4000 copies) from the publisher at&#13;
50%-55% discount.&#13;
Two hundred thousand (200,000) copies of "El Correo del Libro"&#13;
are printed monthly. The books listed in the bulletin can be&#13;
purchased at 200 points of sales throughout the country.&#13;
The General Directorate develops, produces, and has printed&#13;
a wide variety of high quality books, booklets, magazines, etc.,&#13;
which are then published under the imprint of another government&#13;
agency, such as the Consejo Nacional para el Fomento de la Educación&#13;
(CONAFE);1 CONASUPO, the government-supported food chain running&#13;
some 8,000 stores throughout the country, distributes many of SEP's&#13;
publications. In conjunetion with such organizations, the General&#13;
Directorate produces:&#13;
1. Indian Language textbooks: An Indian language text for&#13;
beginners (consisting of 76 pages) was produced by the&#13;
General Directorate and published by SEP in 1980; it is&#13;
distributed free of charge to children. The text is being&#13;
regionalized for various areas of Mexico. To date four&#13;
versions have been produced (for the regions of Veracruz,&#13;
Guerrero, Puebla and San Luis Potosi); the Introduction of&#13;
the book mentions that 22 Indian language editions are&#13;
planned;&#13;
1 The National Council for the Promotion of Education.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-76-&#13;
2. Gulas de Estudio: Study Guides to accompany the national&#13;
secondary school television program, the "Telesecundaria,"&#13;
and sold to secondary students for 30 pesos;&#13;
3. Manuales de Audio Primaria: Manuals to accompany tape&#13;
recordings used by secondary school students in communities&#13;
that do not have a teacher, or that have a teacher who only&#13;
visits the community one or two days a week, produced in&#13;
conjunction with CONAFE;&#13;
4.  Cómo Hacer Mejor:  A series of lavishly illustrated, full&#13;
color, "How-To-Do-Better" booklets of an average 32 pages&#13;
each. The Cómo Hacer Mejor booklets are targeted for chíldren&#13;
and the young adult audience.   They sell at the low subsidized&#13;
price of 10 pesos (US$0.411) at any kiosk, newspaper stand or&#13;
at CONASUPO stores. Each issue is devoted to one topic that&#13;
is presented in detail by excellent illustrations with brief&#13;
captions. Topics are interesting and practical, such as:&#13;
"Cheese" (How to make it in your own home); "Bread" (The&#13;
secreta of making rolle); "Furniture" (How to make it easily&#13;
and quickly); "The Breeding of Bees"; "Sewing"; "Toys"; "The&#13;
Cultivation of Avocados"; etc. To date, 50 different Cómo&#13;
Hacer Mejor booklets have been published out of 200 that are&#13;
being planned. One hundred thousand (100,000) copies of these&#13;
booklets are printed and sold every week;&#13;
5. Novelas Mexicanas:2   A series of pocket-sized comices&#13;
printed in one color and dealing mainly with various historical&#13;
topics;&#13;
6. Cuadernos Mexicanos:3 A series of short novels (48 pages)&#13;
illustrated in one color (but not in comic book style).&#13;
A larger number of publications produced by the General&#13;
Directorate are published under contract by the privatei sectór, e.g.:&#13;
.&#13;
1 At the then prevailing rate of exchange.&#13;
2 "Mexican Novele"&#13;
3 'Mexican Notebooks"&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
077-&#13;
1.  Enciclopedia Infantil Colibri:  A beautifully produced,&#13;
sophisticated, full color children's encyclopedia published&#13;
by Salvat Mexicana de Ediciones, in installments of 24 pages&#13;
each, on high gloss paper with self covers. Each issue is&#13;
illustrated by one of Mexico's outatanding artists, who&#13;
generally donates his time and work to the project.   Each&#13;
installment is priced at 25 pesos (US$1.001); 50,000 copies&#13;
are printed of each weekly issué;.&#13;
2. Mixico. Historia de un Pueblo: A series of high quality,&#13;
full color, comic books of-88 pages each on-Mexican history&#13;
geared specifically to illiterate adults, published by CONAFE&#13;
in conjunction with Editorial Nueva Imágen, a,private publisher.&#13;
This highly visual and attractive series of serious comics&#13;
is representative of the General Directorate's attempts to&#13;
introduce books to-largely illiterate adults via the most&#13;
popular medium in the country.  According to our information,&#13;
the General Directorate aponsora some 70,000,000 copies of&#13;
such comics monthly, including México. Historia de un Pueblo;&#13;
3. Condensations of novels published by CONAFE in.conjunotion&#13;
with private publishers, such as Promexa (Promociones Editoriales&#13;
Mexicanas).&#13;
Another facet of the work of the General Directorate for Publí-&#13;
cationa and Libraries is its commitment to upgrade and expand the&#13;
country's library system, a commitment considered crucial to ita&#13;
educational efforts. Pifty years ago few libraries were being built&#13;
or were properly operated, there were few up-to-date reference books,&#13;
and even fewer trained librarians.&#13;
As recently as 1979 the public library system in Mexico was&#13;
modernized by SEP and plano were made to expand it under the direc-&#13;
tion of the General Directorate. Eighteen (18) new libraries were&#13;
built in 1980, and 20-25 were to be built in 1981. Open ahelves&#13;
were introduced in public libraries and books may now be borrowed&#13;
for home use. As the General Directorate has decided to focus&#13;
attention on children, hoping they will develop the reading habit&#13;
1 At the then prevailing rate of exchange.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-78-&#13;
at an early age, all publio libraries now contain a collection of&#13;
books for children.&#13;
In 1980 alone the General Directorate distributed to public&#13;
libraries 1,000,000 copies of new publications that were purchased&#13;
from both public and private publishers. There are presently 2270&#13;
libraries in all of Mexico, 140 under the direct control of SEP,&#13;
554 school libraries, 670 public libraries, and 906 libraries that&#13;
are part of institutions of higher learning.&#13;
An extension of public libraries, which are defined as stocking&#13;
a minimum of 500 volumes, is the "reading room" system.   In commu-&#13;
nities of 800-2500 inhabitants, the establishment of reading rooms&#13;
under a manager appointed by the local community is encouraged by&#13;
the General Directorate. These rooms are seen as cultural resource&#13;
centers and may purchase books via the General Directorate at very&#13;
low cost.  There are presently 2800 reading rooms, with their number&#13;
projected to grow to 4100 by 1982.&#13;
The Center for the Study of Advanced Educational Media and&#13;
Techniques (CEMPAE),1 is an autonomous agency of SEP for which the&#13;
General Directorate produces materials for adult education. An&#13;
outstanding example is the series entitled Primaria intensiva para&#13;
adultos (PRIAD),2 a sixth to ninth grade level course of intensive&#13;
self-study for adults. The series covers the four basic disciplines&#13;
(language arts, mathematics, the natural sciences, and social&#13;
studies). It is being published in cooperation with various private&#13;
publishers.3&#13;
1 Centro para el Estudio de Medios y Procedimientos Avanzados&#13;
de la Educaci6n.&#13;
2 "Primary Level Intensive Course for Adults."&#13;
3 In all cases of cooperation with the private sector, contracts&#13;
are negotiated by the General Directorate. Publishers receive the&#13;
materials in the form of camera-ready mechanicals, including&#13;
illustrations, and they assume responsibility for the manufacture&#13;
and commercial distribution, and pay a royalty of 12% on list price&#13;
to the government. List prices are established by mutual agreement.&#13;
Government purchases copies for its own distribution at 50%-55%&#13;
discount.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-79-&#13;
In 1980 the General Directorate purchased approximately 11,000&#13;
tons of paper (5,000 tons short of its request, owing to a paper&#13;
shortage); in 1981 it received approximately 16,000 tons. The&#13;
General Directorate and CNLTG together make SEP one of the largest&#13;
consumers, if not the single largest consumer, of paper for books&#13;
and magazines in the country.&#13;
Apparently SEP has not found it difficult to have funds appro-&#13;
priated for its budget, especially over the last two years. In&#13;
addition to federal funding, several of the directorates and agencies&#13;
receive revenue from other sources. The General Directorate derives&#13;
income from royalties paid it by private publishers as compensation,&#13;
for their copublishing ventures. Such royalties acerue in a revolv-&#13;
ing account, to be reinvested in its publishing programs. In 1980&#13;
the General Directorate collected some 3,000,000 pesos (US$125,000&#13;
at the then prevailing rate of exchange) in royalties.&#13;
B. The General Directorate for Teaching and Cultural Materials&#13;
This General Directorate reports also to the Under Secretary for&#13;
Culture, and one of its creative initiatives is the development and&#13;
production of ancillary educational materials to accompany the free&#13;
textbook program. Its best-known effort is a 16-page (6 x 9 3/4"&#13;
type page), full color workbook-type segment that is published six&#13;
days a week as a supplement in one of Mexico City's leading news-&#13;
papers, El Nacional. These 16-page supplements are activity-oriented&#13;
and deal with history, math, the arts, and science.&#13;
Por these supplements the General Directorate for Teaching and&#13;
Cultural laterials prepares camera-ready mechanicals which, after&#13;
appropriate approval from the Sub-Directorate for Educational Content&#13;
and Methods and the National Technical Council for Education, are&#13;
delivered to the newspaper for printing. The average daily presa&#13;
run of El Nacional is 80,000; however, the workbook supplement is&#13;
included only in those issues of the newspaper distributed in the&#13;
Federal District.&#13;
The General Directorate also prepares a weekly Sunday supplement&#13;
for teachers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
VII. Private Sector Publishing&#13;
A. The Mexican Publishing Industry: An Overview&#13;
"Nationalism and a Passion for Education Govern Mexico's&#13;
Attitude Toward Publishing," the U.S. book trade periodical&#13;
Publishers Weekly headlined an article about Mexico in 1975. The&#13;
headline suns up well our own experience in studying the Mexican&#13;
publishing scene, whether public or private.&#13;
Publishing in the Spanish language has always been dominated&#13;
by Spain, called the Mother Country in Latin America. Spain pub-&#13;
lishes approximately 24,000 titles a year and ranks seventh in&#13;
worldwide book production. By contrast, Mexico, with approximately&#13;
5,500 titles annually, ranks twenty-third.1   In Latin America,&#13;
however, Mexicots dynamic publishing industry ranks number one, with&#13;
Argentina, formerly the leading Latin American publisher, in the&#13;
number two position, followed at some distance by Colombia.&#13;
Facts and figures of publishing industries, with very few&#13;
exceptions, are based largely on informed estimates, and Mexico is&#13;
no exception. Most Mexican publishing companies are privately&#13;
rather than publicly owned, and consequently, do not publish sales&#13;
and financial information. Publishing industries may be compared&#13;
in different ways, e.g., paper consumption, numbers of titles pub-&#13;
lished, numbers of copies printed, trade (general) versus educational&#13;
publishing. Therefore, the figures we are quoting may be open to&#13;
question, though they have been reviewed by representatives of the&#13;
Mexican publishing industry.&#13;
Historically, Mexicots publishing industry is young. As&#13;
recently as forty years ago most of Mexicols book needs were met&#13;
by Spain. The Spanish Civil War drove many Spanish intellectuals&#13;
into exile; a considerable number settled in Mexico and have con-&#13;
tributed to the intellectual growth of the nation. The publishing&#13;
1 Patricia Holt, "Publishing in Mexico: Its Time has Come,"&#13;
Publishers Weekly, Vol. 217, No. 16 (New York: R.R, Bowker Co.,&#13;
April 25, 1980), p. 33.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-82-&#13;
industry profited from this influx, as it profited from the influx&#13;
of Cuban refugees and of Argentinians at a later date. Mexico's&#13;
publishing industry is so young that some of its founders and major&#13;
contributors are still alive. Among those we met, and who assisted&#13;
us greatly during our inquiry, are Don Abelardo Fábrega, Carlos&#13;
Noriega Milera, Jorge Flores del Prado, and Luis Fernández González.&#13;
Mexico's publishing industry ¡a well-organized and is chiefly&#13;
represented by its trade organization, the Cámara Nacional de la&#13;
Industria Editorial Mexicana,1 founded in 1964.   The Cámara has more&#13;
that 1,000 members,2 however, the number of reasonably active pub-&#13;
lishers in Mexico is possibly closer to 100, with 30 to 40 major&#13;
firms dominating the market, many of which are related to each other&#13;
through common partners. We are speaking here of book publishers&#13;
rather than publishers of newspapers (17 in Mexico City alone) or&#13;
of magazines. With few exceptions, Mexico's publishers are located&#13;
in Mexico City, one of the largest urban concentrations in the world&#13;
with approximately 15 million people.&#13;
Mexico's publishing industry faced difficult problems in the&#13;
beginning phases of ita development in the 1940s. Even today some&#13;
of these problems continue to perplex and challenge the industry,&#13;
although the general outlook is optimistic.&#13;
Chief among its problems is a limited home market for Mexican&#13;
publishers, especially for general trade books. Estimates we have&#13;
seen of the book-buying public range from a low 2% to 6% of the&#13;
population (currently at 70 million). Moreover, in the home market&#13;
foreign competition from Spain was, and to an extent remains, perva-&#13;
sive. Consequently, even today most general books in Mexico, fiction&#13;
and non-fiction, are published in small editions of 2,000-3,000&#13;
copies. This is not enough to sustain the growth of a publishing&#13;
industry, and therefore, like publishera the world over, Mexicana&#13;
began publishing for schools when the industry was founded.&#13;
1 The Mexican National Publishers Association.&#13;
2 Its current membership numbers 1091, and the association&#13;
is divided into four groups: book publishers; magazine and periodical&#13;
publishers; distributors; suppliers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-83-&#13;
Nationalism and a passion for education helped the publishing indus-&#13;
try in those early years to face foreign competition and to grow.&#13;
However, as early as the 1950s the Mexican government instituted not&#13;
only stiff but unrealistic price controls on schoolbooks that hurt&#13;
the growth of the industry, and resulted in poorer and poorer text-&#13;
books being actually published.  "In those days," one of the publishers&#13;
told us, "our government had little understanding or appreciation of&#13;
our publishing industry." By 1959, as we have seen earlier in this&#13;
Study, Government, through the establishment of CNLTG, nationalized&#13;
primary school textbook publishing and gradually took this market&#13;
-away from the private sector, A number of private publishers did&#13;
not survive the change.  Othera diversified and eventually started&#13;
to profit from a growing demand for textbooks in secondary education,&#13;
on which the private educational publishing industry most heavily&#13;
relies, from an increasing demand for university textbooks, from&#13;
book exports, and last but by no means least, from a change in govern-&#13;
mental attitude towards the publishing industry. "Today," as our&#13;
publishing friend continued, "Government understands publishing much&#13;
better." Prices of schoolbooks are still controlled but on a more&#13;
realistic basis. Many cooperative publishing ventures between&#13;
Government and the private sector have come into being as described&#13;
in earlier sections, and Government provides other important support&#13;
and incentives, Much of the credit for the improved relationship&#13;
with Government is due to major publishers who have maintained a&#13;
dialogue with important government officials, and effectively organ-&#13;
ized themselves with the establishment of the Cámara Nacional de la&#13;
Industria Editorial Mexicana. Other factors helped, such as the&#13;
establishment in Mexico of major branches of Spanish publishers,&#13;
which began in the 1940s and boosted publishing know-how. During&#13;
the 1960s USAID, under the direction of RTAC (Regional Technical&#13;
Aids Center), provided Mexican publishers with subsidies for pub-&#13;
lishing low-level technical institute and first-year university&#13;
textbooks in the aciences and technology. This helped many Mexican&#13;
publishers to expand their publishing activities and to enter a&#13;
field of publishing that had been hitherto dominated by Spanish&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-84-&#13;
publishers, who were among the first to translate university texts&#13;
in the sciences and technology into Spanish on a large seale, texts&#13;
that had been published originally in the U.S.A., Britain, Germany&#13;
or France.  RTAC support came at a time when university enrollments&#13;
began to explode and modern textbooks in the Spanish language were&#13;
much in demand. RTAC would normally purchase a predetermined number&#13;
of copies, 2000-3000 on average, of a title selected by a Mexican&#13;
publisher for translation. This purchase enabled the publisher to&#13;
cover the costs of translation and production (typesetting, illustra-&#13;
tiona, etc.), and also to acquire the foreign rights. RTAC undertook&#13;
to distribute the purchased copies outside of Mexico in other Latin&#13;
American countries, and thereby, helped to create export opportunities&#13;
for the Mexican publisher.&#13;
Increasing cooperation between Mexican and U.S. publishers in&#13;
the publication of tertiary level science and technology texts and&#13;
reference books, led to the establishmient of several joint-venture&#13;
publishing houses in Mexico, a development that further strengthened&#13;
the industry and has been welcomed by most responsible Mexican&#13;
publishers.&#13;
It is difficult to estimate the present size of the Mexican&#13;
book publishing industry, either in titles published annually,1 in&#13;
paper consumption2 or in total sales. Total book sales for 1981&#13;
may be in the range of Mp 8 billion (US$334 million3). If we&#13;
accept this figure, at least'50%, if not 60-65%, of these sales are&#13;
of textbooks and other educational materials. Textbooks for secondary&#13;
and tertiary education account for the bulk of these sales. However,&#13;
it is interesting to note that Mexican publishers, with the tacit&#13;
support of Governnent, are again publishing books for primary schools.&#13;
One reason for this recent development is the diversity of Mexican&#13;
1 Five thousand five hundred (5,500) appears to be an accepted&#13;
figure, but we do not know whether this figure includes revisions&#13;
and new editions, in addition to new publications.&#13;
2,Seé Appendix F, Table 003, tIEstimated Paper Consumption by&#13;
Category."&#13;
3 At the then prevailing rate of exchange.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
schools; another i9 a new, if modest, affluence based on oil income&#13;
that gives schools and parents more of an opportunity.to supplement&#13;
the free textbooks with other materials of their choice. There ¡e&#13;
yet another reason for this recent growth in, private sector primary&#13;
school publishing that has to do with book exports. The greatest&#13;
challenge for Mexican publishers ia to increase the export of their&#13;
books. Inroads have been made into other Latin American countries&#13;
where Mexican textbooks, especially at tertiary level, are beginning&#13;
to sell well. In 1980, for example, book exporto amounted to approx-&#13;
imately Mp 1.100 billion1  mostly to South America, i.e., Ar~gentina,&#13;
Colombia, Venezuela and Chile, to Central America, and to Spain.&#13;
These markets, neverthelesa, are limited and in some instances,&#13;
politically unstable. Mexican books, due to recent inflation, are&#13;
not particularly inexpensive, at least by the standards of the poorer&#13;
Latin American countries. The largest potential export market has&#13;
mostly eluded Mexican publishers so far; it is the United States&#13;
with a Hispanio population estimated at a little over 20 million,&#13;
a majority of whom are of Mexican-American descent. Spanish pub-&#13;
lishers are selling books in this market, Mexicans by and large are&#13;
not. One reason i that Mexican publishera, unlike Spanish publishers,&#13;
have had little that is suitable to offer the United States'a Hispanic&#13;
population, which needs readera and similar elementary school mater-&#13;
¡ala. CNLTG'a free textbooks, for example, may not be exported and&#13;
probably would not be acceptable in the U.S.A. for other reasona.&#13;
However, the Mexican goverrment for political reasons is interested&#13;
in encouraging the export of Mexican publlcations to the U.S. Hispanie&#13;
population, and the private-publishing industry la responding by&#13;
publishíng once again for primary schools.&#13;
1 See Appendix F, Tables 001 and 002, "Annual Mexican Book&#13;
Trade Balances, 1970-1980,".and "Mexican Book Trade Balances by&#13;
Geographic Area, 1979-1980.";&#13;
By contrast, about Mp 2.218 billion in books were imported in 1980.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-86-&#13;
B. Government Suprort of the Private PublishinR Industrv&#13;
"In significant ways the economic growth and health of a publish-&#13;
ing industry is dependent on the continuous and consistent expenditure&#13;
of public funde for schoolbooks, and on library development for the&#13;
public, for schools, and research institutes.... A mature and&#13;
economically strong publishing industry, supported by a vast reading&#13;
public, can survive moderate fluctuations in government support by&#13;
concentrating on the more consistent sales to the general public.&#13;
But it must be obvious that a newly-established publishing industry,&#13;
in a young country without widespread literacy or ingrained book-&#13;
buying habits, must be carefully nurtured and must depend upon the&#13;
regular expenditure of public funda."1 Our paper, published in 1980,&#13;
outlines the case for government intervention and support of a young&#13;
or limited2 publishing industry. It insists that governments have&#13;
to create a market for books in education through expenditure of&#13;
public funda. The point is made that even in highly industrialized&#13;
nationa with large book-buying populationa, for example the USA or&#13;
UK, as much as 50% or more of publishing industry sales depend on&#13;
government expenditures for education. Without such sales to the&#13;
educational establishment, e.g., the school system and libraries,&#13;
publishing industries even in the developed countries would wither&#13;
away. Access to the educational market and to libraries is crucial&#13;
to publishing industries because of the nature of the industry, what&#13;
might be called its strength and bane: the richness and diversity&#13;
of the titles that are being published for every conceivable taste&#13;
and purpose, a majority of which do not make monev for the vublisher.&#13;
but at best onlv break even.  Bestsellers, and steady sellers   such&#13;
as textbooks and reference works, provide the very stuff of survival&#13;
and of growth for a publishing industry.&#13;
1 Peter H. Neumann, Publishing for Schools. Textbooks and the&#13;
Leas Developed Countries (World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 398,&#13;
Washington, D.C.: The World Bank, 1980), PP. 53-54.&#13;
2 Government subsidies are not necessarily restricted to IDCs.&#13;
See the above-cited paper for examples from industrialized nationa.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-87-&#13;
In México Editor1 Francisco Trillas Mercader of Editorial&#13;
Trillas, S.A., a leading Mexican publisher, is quoted as saying:&#13;
"We need more official aid, even though we have had official assis-&#13;
tance for some years now.  The last two governments wanted the&#13;
Mexican publishing industry to grow. We represent information,&#13;
communication, and culture. Yes, we publish works that generate&#13;
foreign exchange."&#13;
Indeed over the last decade the Mexican government has taken&#13;
major steps to assist the publishing industry, even though some of&#13;
the tensions, and perhaps misunderstandings, that are almost tradi-&#13;
tional between those representing the civil service and those&#13;
representing private entrepreneurship, remain. While the Mexlcan&#13;
government continues to engage in the large scale production and&#13;
publication of educational materials, as we have seen in previous&#13;
chapters, at the same time it has decisively moved towards bolstering&#13;
the publishing industry in several ways: fiscal incentives; copub-&#13;
lishing activities; and a measure of protection from foreign 2&#13;
competition. A major move in this direction came with the decree&#13;
establishing CODIECLI (Comnimttee for the Development of the Publish-&#13;
ing and Bookselling Industries), signed by President Luis Echeverr&lt;a&#13;
Alvarez in April of 1975. Established to protect the publishing and&#13;
bookselling industries from being swamped by foreign publications,&#13;
the decree spells out most of the tax incentives, subsidies, and&#13;
preferences afforded said industries. Those affecting publishers&#13;
are briefly described in the following.&#13;
1. Fiscal Incentives&#13;
Publishers pay no income tax on profits as long as these profits&#13;
are reinvested in the growth of the business. Royalties paid to&#13;
authors are also exempt from taxes. Books have been exempted from&#13;
1 A newsletter published by the Cámara Nacional de la Industria&#13;
Editorial Mexicana, June 1981, on the occasion of the opening of the&#13;
Tenth Metropolitan Book Fair in Mexico City.&#13;
2 "Decreto por el que se crea un Comité Consultivo para el&#13;
Desarrollo de la Industria Editorial y Comercio del Libro," published&#13;
in the Diario Oficial, April 9, 1975.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-88-&#13;
IVA, a value-added type of sales tax. amounting to 10%. Publishera&#13;
may apply for low interest loans, especially for financing export&#13;
sales. Under certain circumstances paper may be imported free of&#13;
duty,1 e.g., if the majority-of the resulting books are exported,&#13;
if there ia a paper ahortage in the country, if suitable paper is&#13;
not available locally. Applications for paper importation are&#13;
processed via the Publishera Aseociation.&#13;
2. Cobublishing Projecta&#13;
Examples of copublishing projecta have been described in&#13;
previous sections. These and similar arrangemente may become&#13;
inereasingly important to the publishing industry as long as Govern-&#13;
ment continues ita present level of involvement in the production of&#13;
educational materials. Under current arrangementa, development and&#13;
production of the materiala, i.e., the writing, editing, designing,&#13;
and illustrating, are carried out by an agency of Government, such&#13;
as the General Directorate for Publications and Libraries. The&#13;
publisher receives mechanicals ready for reproduction, and controls&#13;
manufacturing, marketing, sales and distribution vía commercial&#13;
channels. At times Government will supply the paper. At other times&#13;
the publisher may not even handle manufacturing, for he is supplied&#13;
instead with ready-made books. In all cases the publisher pays a&#13;
.royalty on his sales to Government. He will usually sell quantities&#13;
of the copublications to a government agency for ita distribution at&#13;
special prices to teachers and to government-supported institutions&#13;
(libraries), or to apecial groups of consumers, e.g., via CONASUPOs2&#13;
to the newly literate. This relationship and business ¡e important&#13;
to publishers. It allows them to be associated with government&#13;
publishing, it increases their list of available titles, and it also&#13;
helps the book trade.- However, it does not strengthen the essential&#13;
1 See Appendix F, Tables 003, 004,i and 005: "Estimated Paper&#13;
Consumption by Category"; "Paper Production by Category"; "Importa-&#13;
tion of Paper by Category."&#13;
2 Refer to Chapter VI, p. 75.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-89-&#13;
role of publishers as facilitators or co-creators in the editorial&#13;
development of materials.. Nor is this type of business particularly&#13;
profitable for the publisher.&#13;
3. Protection for the Publishing Industry&#13;
By law foreign interests cannot control a Mexican publishing&#13;
company; they may, however, be minority partners with as much as&#13;
49% interest in the business. Publishing ís very much defined as&#13;
printing in Mexico. Unlese one exporta the entire edition, one&#13;
cannot print (i.e., reprint an existing book) in Mexico and sell&#13;
it there without being a Mexican publisher. If one publishes for&#13;
the school market and wishes government approval, the printing of&#13;
the book must be done in Mexico. Nevertheless, it is possible to&#13;
sell books to echools in Mexico without obtaining government approval,&#13;
as has been pointed out earlier. Consequently, some books sold to&#13;
schools are in fact imported.&#13;
Restrictions have been placed at times on the importation of&#13;
books. About six years ago the government imposed a 10% import duty&#13;
on invoice value and a requirement for an import permit for all book&#13;
imports in all languages. The reaction from the book trade, however,&#13;
including publishers who often import books themselves as agents,&#13;
was so unfavorable1 that these rules were never enforced in this&#13;
manner to the best of our knowledge. Instead the rules were modified&#13;
several times, and at present the following restrictions are in&#13;
force, as explained to us:&#13;
a. All books in languages other than Spanish.may be imported&#13;
without any permits and without any special book import duty;&#13;
b. All books in Spanish printed in and shipped from-countries&#13;
that are members of the Latin American Free Trade Association&#13;
(ALALC), may be imported without permits or special book import&#13;
duties;&#13;
c, All books in Spanish printed in or shipped from countries&#13;
that are not members of the ALALC (USA, Spain, Panama, etc.),&#13;
1 Among the argumente for modification of the rules was the&#13;
fear that other countries might retaliate against Mexican book&#13;
exports.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-90-&#13;
require an import permit in order to be imported into Mexico&#13;
and pay an import duty that was 2% at last count.&#13;
In order to obtain an import permit one must apply to the&#13;
Bureau of Poreign Trade in the Secretariat of Commerce, and after&#13;
a period of 10 to 20 days a permit is either issued or denied.&#13;
A permit ¡a usually issued when the application i made&#13;
for one importation only of a specific shipment. A global&#13;
permit for a large amount of books to be imported over 12&#13;
months time will be denied unless prior acceptance has been&#13;
obtained from the Committee for the Development of the Publish-&#13;
ing and Bookselling Industries (CODIECLI) that reviews book&#13;
imports into Mexico, and makes certain that those importers&#13;
who request permits do so only for their own use and not as&#13;
intermediaries for third parties....&#13;
Although the system la not perfect, it has been funetional&#13;
and not overly bureaucratic. For a one-time importer it may&#13;
seem complicated, but for those who import on a regular basis,&#13;
it is a formality one lives with and does not even complain&#13;
about too much.&#13;
What more could be done by Government to aid the book trade?&#13;
One area we feel deserves attention le distribution. A better scheme&#13;
might be devised that would enable publishers to reach other available&#13;
outlets for books more readily, especially in rural areas. Improving&#13;
the efficiency of the book post would be of considerable help. A&#13;
favorable rate existe for books, but publishere are reluctant to&#13;
use the mails because they are not reliable. CNLTG has managed a&#13;
special arrangement with the railroads for the distribution of the&#13;
free textbooks. Perhaps they could act as distributor for other&#13;
publications, an arrangement that would enable the book trade to&#13;
tie into CNITG's system.&#13;
Out of its nationalism and dedication to education Mexico has&#13;
managed to create a balanced approach towards its need for public&#13;
as well as private sector publishing. Few would argue that the&#13;
balance at times goes out of kilter, or that it may be weíghted&#13;
somewhat in favor of public publishing for a country with the socio-&#13;
economic structure of Mexico. Nevertheless, Mexico has accomplished&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-91-&#13;
both a fairly plentiful supply of free, or subsidized, educational&#13;
materials, and a growing, dynamic publishing industry practically&#13;
free of censorship, and indeed enjoying strong government support.&#13;
In terms of paper consumption and of copies printed, it must be&#13;
assumed that government sector publishing is considerably larger&#13;
than the private sector. The millions of copies printed for the&#13;
free textbook project, as well as the very large printings of comics&#13;
and of other adult education materials, account for that. A national&#13;
newspaper, in its issue of February 20, 1981, quoted the Secretary of&#13;
Education as saying that SEP produces 12 times more books than&#13;
private publishers, somewhere in the order of 150 million copies&#13;
versus 12-13 million copies. Perhaps this í9 so, but SEP's quan-&#13;
titíes result from a limited number of book titles, and from&#13;
magazines and comies, perhaps lese than 500 book titles annually.&#13;
This would be less than 10% of the number of titles published by&#13;
the private sector. In the equation SEP publishes only educational&#13;
bestsellers, an accomplishment no single private publisher can&#13;
possibly hope to match.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDICES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
SECRETARIAT OF PUBLIC EDUCATION (SEP)                                                                                                                                          APPENDIX A&#13;
&lt;january, 1981&#13;
F1A-'L TECH. COUBCILL&#13;
FOR E.DUCATION (CNTE) I  .NAT'L CONSULTING&#13;
r COOR. COUN1L FOR COUXNCIL FDR NORMAL&#13;
OPEN ED. PROGRAMS      NTRACOISN&#13;
COUNCIL OF CULTUGAL   FOR ADH. AND PLANNINC&#13;
AND RECREATIONAL &#13;
PROGRAMS           GEEHRR1 COMMISSION&#13;
| COUHCIL OF ED. LFOR SCHOLARSHIPS&#13;
NTENT AND METHODSI&#13;
CODNCIL OF NATIONALL&#13;
SYSTEM FOR TECH. RD. .&#13;
POR~~ ~         UNDER RRCERM FOR R.  PO SENDNDNEPR SRE-CROLETA . TD RDEN. SECRETARY FOR. ||UHERSECFORHIT H. |   NDERTRECALO TOEN.HE. P| L OM LECRARETM   OF POO UH RO. S ARFR OP.  HINACHEAL CLESRRCSHI&#13;
GCENERAL. DIRECTORATE  G CENERAL DIRECTDRATE I   GENEL DRECTORATE  CON.RDIRECTORATE R  G CENERAS. DIRECTORATE  GEN. OIR. POR MARHIN  GEN. OSE. PORTAEN .  CEN. DIREGTORATR POR  GES. DIRECTORATE  |&#13;
OI CRO.AR DELETIONSI E P OR NAE AING        PR PRIMAR! DR.A    SUON P I SOR CEC. ES.  P I RCPEDCION  ICH. AT.                   A       I  AULT EDUCATIORA  PSICLMEDTIOP S   SOPLHESAN RRSOVCES&#13;
GENERAL DIRECTORATE  SNERAL DIRECTORATE POR  GEN. DIRECTORATE FOR  GTERLEECTNDATE    GENE DFRSCTORATE OI GEN. DRC   POR        GEERN.DIT                                 GR      E   A DIRECTORATE FOREI&#13;
PO. FDR INF. RELAND.R.  [IFORESCHED.LANO IEAL.  PEO! OCR. IRR-DOL. ID1P TEC. GR SECONDMY ED.   ROEMSER EDCATIORN  TO  TECH. ED. | 1  PO  CA I         PHYSICAL EDUCATGITN  FPROHAAL RESOURCES|&#13;
I CNERL DRETORTE  I ENRATA PECNIRO CTOTE.  G ENERAL DRECTRE T  ICCTORATE  GOAEFO  ENERAL. IDIECTORATE   GRO EN. OPR TDRAMMNEIR  GENERA DIR ORECTORATO.                G E.DRGORT  O EN. DIRECTORATE PORI &#13;
CENERAL DIRECTONRSTE  CENA   ODIELTOR P RANN.GOBEEONAL 0OIECWRAT                                      IRERCERRTE          POR    POPUEARA ECUTURAE                      CEEAM DINRMTORA&#13;
j GEN. OIRECTORATE ROR |                      .               I                    J GEN. DIRECTORATE F F   O       R         | GENERAL DIRECTORATE&#13;
IN IDIGENUN ERCATION                     ¡                     ¡                        CULTURAL PROMOTIN                           P I  FOR PAYRERTO&#13;
GENERAL DIRECTORATE &#13;
P OR SCROOL HYGIlENEII&#13;
DRCENTRALIZED OREARN[ZATICOS                                                        ¡                                           I&#13;
RL  RATIONA RPEDAGOGRCAS.HL |  1S ED  IL  POLYTECHNIC |  AONTHROPOOC AND  |&#13;
OR INF. .1  -1  SUPERITORITT-7¿  NlTEL NINT. OS!E             I&#13;
GEEA DERE EL CAL RDIIS  |&#13;
oourpce NR?.                                                             TORSONS                        EEEGTIN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The National Technical Council                                                                                                                         APPENDIX B&#13;
for Education (CNTE)&#13;
GENERAL&#13;
GNovember, 1980                                                            ASSEBLY&#13;
BOARD OF&#13;
DIRECTORS&#13;
GENERAL&#13;
SECRETARY&#13;
|  COORD. OF     COORD. OF&#13;
INVESTIGATION        STATE&#13;
AND  PROJECTS       COUNCILS&#13;
CON. FOR     ~COM. FOR                            XTOKC                                     FRON            R&#13;
PLANNING,     CUR.RICUJLA,     COM. FIOR ED.                                                         EDUK~  O.FR N. CO.FRCON.TO&#13;
COORD., &amp; IP.  SYLLABI,EVALUATION           REFERENCE        F.VLIIl            TEACHING        EDCTONAL&#13;
OF ECTIMPN        SYIIABIC                          B00K COM.        OFSUDE              ATERIALS       LEGISLATION&#13;
DEPT. OF&#13;
ADMIN.&#13;
SERVICES&#13;
Source: CNTE.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The Sub-Directorate for Educational                                                                                                                              APPENDIX C&#13;
Content and Methods&#13;
GENERAL DIRECTORATE&#13;
1978                                                                                FOR PLANNING&#13;
|SUB-DIR. FO R ED.&#13;
CONTENT AND METHODS&#13;
ACADEMIC                                        CURRICULUM                            MANUSCRIPT                               TESTINb                              \&#13;
|   DEPARTMENT              .DEPARTMENT                                                 DEPARTMENT                            DEPARTMENT    &#13;
Source: Sub-Directorate for Educatíonal Contents and Methods.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The National Commission for Free Textbooks                                                                                                                   APPENDIX D&#13;
(CNLTG)&#13;
BOARD OF DIRECTORS &#13;
GMarch, 1980                                                    BOA- &#13;
GEN. DIR.         |&#13;
INTERNAL COM. OF ADMIN.&#13;
AND SCHEDULING&#13;
|  GENERAL ,ECRETARY  |                          l    ~~~~~SUB-DIRECTORATE                                      SUB-DIREC TORATE FOR&#13;
PEDA|OGIG                                                      O      EDU    GO                     C  iCAL SUPERV.                                        ACCOUNTING&#13;
CONSULTANTS                                                                                                        ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~DEPARTMENT&#13;
|  CONTRACTS A7ND     l                                           MANAGER OF                MGrR. OF PRITIN                MAINTENANCE           .      |    DISTRIBUTION&#13;
REGULATIONS                                                   CAMERA DEPT.                                                MANAGER                           MANAGER&#13;
ASST. MGR. OF &#13;
FILE OOF800K:S                                     DEPT. OF PASTE-UP               WEB PRESS DEPT.              MAINTENANCE                      FINANCE MANAGER&#13;
|NS HIPPING DEPT.                                           INT     DE| SHEETFED PRSS  AN BA PT. OF  PERSONNEL MANAGER&#13;
LIBRARY  SCHEDULING DEPT.          SHIPPING DEPT.                  ~DEPARTMENT                BACKU'P EQUIP.&#13;
SUPERVIS|                       LLUSTRATION DEPT              OLDING DEPARTMENT |I|                D EPT . OF               WAREHOUSE MANAGER&#13;
CORRESPONDENE                 ANO CONTROLDETILUTTIN                         ET.ODNG                EATET              PRODUCTION EQUIP .&#13;
MAINT. DEPT. OF                   GENERAL SERVICES&#13;
BINDING DEPT.            SPECIALIZED EQUIP.                       MANA&#13;
RECEIVING AND                 LETTERPRESS                       SECURITY AND&#13;
DISPATCHING DEPT.               DEPARTMENT                     FIRE DEPARTMENTS&#13;
Source: CNLTG.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
THE NATIONAL COMMISSION FOR FREE TEXTBOOKS (CNLTG)                                             APPENDIX E: Table 001&#13;
Total Number of Books Produced by CNLTG, 1960-1982, in Millions of Copies&#13;
(Source: CNLTG)&#13;
100 -&#13;
95 -                                                                                                                 93&#13;
90 -&#13;
85 -&#13;
80 -                                                              79.7                                    ,&#13;
75 -&#13;
705 &#13;
.70 -                                                                       68.7&#13;
65 -&#13;
60 -                                                    57.7&#13;
55 -&#13;
50 -                                               48.7&#13;
45 -&#13;
40 -                                          3.&#13;
35 -&#13;
30 -            27.5            _&#13;
25 -       23.1 '     '3   '6   '    '    '    '&#13;
20 - 17.6 &#13;
15 -   *         8   l         l &#13;
lo - &#13;
'60  '61 -'62  '63  '64  '65  '66  '67  '68  '69  '70   '71  '72 '73  '74  '75 '76    '77  '78  '79  '80  '81  '82&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX E, Table 002&#13;
The Natíonal Commiosion,-,for Free Textbooks (CNLTG)&#13;
listinR of All TitleosProduced bv CNLTG. 1960-19811&#13;
Fírst Grade&#13;
Yirst Generation of Pree Textbooke:&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE TRABAJO               Produced and kept in print: 1960-9971. Not printed: 1970.&#13;
MI LIBRO DE PRIMER AIO                                           1960-1972.&#13;
INSTRUCTIVO PARA EL MAESTRO                                      1960-1972. Not printed: 1962.&#13;
MANUAL APRENDER HACIENDO                                         1970.&#13;
Seoond Generation of Free Textbooks:&#13;
LIBRO CIENCIAS NATURALES                                         1972-1979.&#13;
.LIBRO CIENCIAS NATURALES MAESTRO                                 1972-1979.  Not printed: 1976 and&#13;
1978.&#13;
LIBRO CIENCIAS SOCIALES                                          1972-1979.&#13;
LIBRO CIENCIAS SOCIALES MAESTROn                                 1972-1979. Not printed: 1978.    o&#13;
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
LIBRO ESPANOL                                                    1972-1979.                       0&#13;
LIBRO ESPANOL MAESTRO                                            1972-1979.  Not printed: 1978.&#13;
LIBRO MATEMATICAS                                                1972-1979.&#13;
LIBRO MATEMATICAS MAESTRO.                                       1972-1979.  Not printed: 1978.&#13;
LIBRO RECORTABLE ESPAÑ'OL                                        1972-1979.&#13;
Third Generation of Free Textbooks:&#13;
MI LIBRO DE PRIMERO 1                Produced and Printed:.       1980-&#13;
MI LIBRO DE PRIMERO 1 - RECORTABLE              n                1980-&#13;
MI LIBRO DE PRIMERO 2                           n                1980-&#13;
MI LIBRO-DE PRIMERO 2 - RECORTABLE              a                 1980-&#13;
LIBRO PARA EL MAESTRO, PRIMER GRADO             n                1980-&#13;
Source:  CNjTG&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
llsting of All Titles Produoed bv CNTG. 1960-1981&#13;
Second Grade&#13;
Píret Generation of Free Textbooks:&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE SEGUNDO ANO           Produoed.and.kept'in prints:1960-1971-. Not printed: 1963.&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE SEGUNDO AIO DE&#13;
ARITMETICA Y GEOMETRIA                                           1960-1971.                1963.&#13;
MI LIBRO DE SEGUNDO AO                                          1960-1972.&#13;
INSTRUCTIVO'PARA EL MAESTRO                                      1960-1971.&#13;
Second Generation of Free Textbooks:&#13;
LIBRO CIENCIAS NATURAIES MAESTRO                                 1972-'1979. *Not printed: 1978'.&#13;
GIBRO CIENCIAS SOCIALES',                                        1972-1979.             -&#13;
LIBRO CIENCIAS SOCIALES MAESTRO                                  1972-1979.  Not printed: 1978.&#13;
LIBRO ESPA90OL                                                   1972-1979.                1977.&#13;
LIBRO ESPANOL MAESTRO                                            1972-1979.                1978.&#13;
LIBRO MATEMATICAS                                                1972-1978.     -                  b&#13;
IIBRO MATEMATICAS MAESTRO                                        1972-1979. Not printed: 1978.&#13;
LIBRO RECORTAL   ESPdAOLn                                        1972.&#13;
LIBRO CIENCIAS NATURALES                                         1973-1979. Not printed: 1977.&#13;
LIBRO IETURAn                                                    1973-1979.                1977.&#13;
Third Generation o£ Pree Tertbooks:&#13;
MI LIBRO DE SEGUNDO                  Produced--and printed:      1981-&#13;
LIBRO PARA EL MAESTRO, SEGUNDO GRADO          -"                 1981-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Listing of All Titles Produced by CNLTG, 1960-1981&#13;
Third Grade&#13;
First Generation of Free Textbooks:&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE L.N.H.C.               Produced and kept in print: 1960-1972.  Not printed: 1961-1963.&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE GEOGRAFIA                           o              1960-1972.&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE ARITMETICA Y GEOMETRIA                             1960-1972.  Not printed: 1961-1963.&#13;
MI LIBRO DE HISTORIA Y CIVISMO                                    1960-1972.&#13;
MI LIBRO DE LENGUA NACIONAL                                       1960-1971.  Not printed: 1962.&#13;
MI LIBRO DE GEOGRAFIA                                             1960-1972.&#13;
MI LIBRO DE ARITMETICA Y GEOMETRIA                                1960-1972,  Not printed: 1961-1962.&#13;
MI LIBRO DE TERCER ANO 2a.&#13;
PARTE (A.G.)                                                      1961-1962.&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE TRABAJO la. ,&#13;
PARTE (L.N.)                                                      1961-1963.&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE TRABAJO 2a.&#13;
PARTE (A.G.)                                                      1961-1963.&#13;
INSTRUCTIVO DE TERCER GRADO                                       1962-1972.&#13;
MI LIBRO DE TERCER ANO (L.N.H.C.)                  n              1962.&#13;
Second Generation of Free Textbooks:&#13;
LIBRO DE CIENCIAS NATURALES                        n              1973-&#13;
LIBRO DE CIENCIAS SOCIALES                         n              1973v&#13;
LIBRO ESPA&lt;OL                                      n              1973"       Not printed: 1977 and&#13;
LIBRO LECTURA                                                     1973             u       19771978.&#13;
LIBRO MATEMATICAS       -                                         1973-&#13;
LIBRO CIENCIAS NATURALES MAESTRO                   n              1973-       Not printed: 1976 and&#13;
1978.&#13;
LIBRO CIENCIAS SOCIALES MAESTRO                    n              1973-                    1976 and&#13;
1978.&#13;
LIBRO ESPAÑOL MAESTRO                              n              1973-            n       1978.&#13;
LIBRO MATEMATICAS MAESTRO                                         1973-            n       1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Listing of All Titles Produoed by CNLTG, 1960-1981&#13;
Fourth Grade&#13;
Pirst Generation of Pree Textbooks:&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE ARITMETICA Y          Produced and kept in print:   1960.&#13;
GEOMETRIA&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE LENGUA NACIONAL                     n               1960.&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE GEOGRAPIA                           n               1960-1973.&#13;
MI LIBRO DE LENGUA NACIONAL                        a               1960-1973.&#13;
MI4 LIBRO DE GEOGRAPIA                             0               1960-1973.&#13;
MI4 LIBRO DE HISTORIA Y CIVISMO                    n               1960-1972.&#13;
MI LIBRO DE ARITMETICA Y GEOMETRIA                 0               1960-1968. Not printed: 1961-1962.&#13;
INSTRUCTIVO PARA EL MAESTRO                        o               1960-1972.      o       1961-1962.&#13;
MI LIBRO CUARTO AYO 2a. PARTE (A.G.)                               1961-1973.              1963-1967.&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE TRABAJO 2a. PARTE (L.N.)                            1961-1964.&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE TRABAJO 2a. PARTE (A.G.)                            1961-1973. Not printed: 1968.&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE LENGUA NACIONAL,                                    1     9A9&#13;
HISTORIA Y CIVISMO                                                 1965-1973.              1972.&#13;
Second Generation of Free Textbooks:&#13;
LIBRO DE CIENCIAS NATURALES                                        1974-&#13;
LIBRO DE CIENCIAS SOCIAIES                                         1974-      Not printed: 1978.&#13;
LIBRO DE ESPANOL                                                   1974-&#13;
LIBRO DE LECTURAS                                                  1974-      Not printed: 1976.&#13;
LIBRO DE MATEMATICAS                                               1974-&#13;
LIBRO DE CIENCIAS NATURALES MAESTRO                                1974-      Not printed: 1978.&#13;
LIBRO DE CIENCIAS SOCIALES MAESTRO                                 1974-                   1978.&#13;
LIBRO DE ESPAMOL MAESTRO                                           1974-                   1978.&#13;
LIBRO DE MATEMATICAS MAESTRO                                       1974-                   1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
listing of All Titles Produced by CNLTG, 1960-1981&#13;
Pifth Grade&#13;
Firat Generation of Pree Textbooks:&#13;
MI LIBRO DE QUINTO-AffO-2a.&#13;
PARTE (A.G.) ,, .  -                 Produced and kept in print: 1961-1963.&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE QUINTO ANO 2a.&#13;
PARTE (A.G.)                                                    .1961-1963.&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE TRABAJO LENGUA NACIONAL            '              1964-1972.&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE ARITMETICA Y GEOM.&#13;
Y E.N.                                                           1964-1972.&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE GEOGRAJIA                                         1964-1972.&#13;
MI CUADERNO'DE HISTORIA Y CIVISMO                                1964-1972..&#13;
MI LIBRO'DE LENGUA NACIONAL                                      1964-1972.. Not printea: 1971.&#13;
MI lIBRO DE GEOGRAFIA                                            1964-1972.                       u&#13;
MI LIBRO DE HISTORIA Y CIVISMO                                   1964-1972.&#13;
MI LIBRO DE ARITMETICA Y GEOM. Y.E.N.                            1964-1972.&#13;
INSTRUCTIVO PARA EL MAESTRO                                      1965-1971.  Not prínted: 1967.&#13;
LIBRO DE ESTUDIO DE LA NATURALEZA                                1966.&#13;
Second Generation of Free Textbooks:&#13;
LIBRO DE CIENCIAS NATURALES                                      1973-&#13;
LIBRO DE CIENCIAS SOCIALES                        '              1973-&#13;
LIBRO DE ESPA OLB,          , ,1973-                                         Not printed: 1976.&#13;
LIBRO LECTURAS                                                   1973-&#13;
LIBRO MATEMATICAS                                                1973-&#13;
LIBRO CIENCIAS NATURALES MAESTRO                                 1973-       Not''printed: 1976 and&#13;
1978.&#13;
LIiRO CIENCIAS SOCIALES'MAESTRO                                 '1973-            n      . 1976-1978.&#13;
LIBRO MATEMATICAS MAESTRO                                       .1973-                    1978.&#13;
LIBRO ESPAWOL MAESTRO                                            1974-                    1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Listing of All Titles Produced by CNLTG, 1960-1981&#13;
Sixth Grade&#13;
FirBt-Generation of Free Textbooks:&#13;
MI LIBRO DE SEXTO ANWO 2a. PARTE (A.G.) Produced and kept in print: 1962-1963.&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE SEXTO AiO 2a.&#13;
PARTE (-A.G.)                                                        1962-1963.&#13;
MI LIBRO ARITMETICA Y GEOM. Y E.N.                                   1964-1973. Not printed: 1971.&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE ARITMETICA Y GEOMETRIA                                1964-1973.              197-1.&#13;
MI CUADERNO,ESTUDIO DE LA NATURALEZAn                                1964-1973.  ,           1971.&#13;
INSTRUCTIVO                                                         1964-1971.               1967 and&#13;
1969.&#13;
MI-LIBRO DE ESTUDIO DE LA NATURALEZA,                n                965-1973.              1970.&#13;
-MI LIBRO DE HISTORIA Y CIVISMO                                      1966-1973.-,&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE HISTORIA Y CIVISMO-                                   1966-1973.-Not printed: 1971.&#13;
MI LIBRO DE LENGUA NACIONAL     '                                    1968-1973.                      °&#13;
MI LIBRO DE GEOGRAFIA                                                1968-1973.&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE LENGUA NACIONALn                                      1968-1973. Not printed: 1971.&#13;
MI CUADERNO DE GEOGRAFIA                                             1968-1973.              1971.&#13;
Second Generation of Free Textbooks:&#13;
LIBRO DE MATEMATICAS                                                 1974-&#13;
LIBRO DE ESPAOLn                                                     1974-&#13;
LIBRO DE LECTURAS                                                    1974-&#13;
LIBRO DE CIENCIAS SCIAILES                                           1974-&#13;
LIBRO DE CIENCIAS NATURALES                                          1974-&#13;
LIBRO-DE MATEMATICAS MAESTRO                                         1974-      Not printed: 1978.&#13;
LIBRO DE ESPANOL.MAESTRO                                             1974-                   1976 'and -&#13;
'1978.,&#13;
LIBRO DE CIENCIAS SOCIALES MAESTRO                                   1974-                   1978. -&#13;
LIBRO DE CIENCIAS NATURALES MAESTRO                                  1974-                   1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
listíng of All Titles Produced by CNLTG, 1960-1981&#13;
Supplementarv Editions&#13;
First Grade&#13;
L LIBRO BRAILLE                          Produced and printed: 1966, 1971, 1976 and 1977.&#13;
Second Grade&#13;
LIBRO BRAILIE                                                1966 and 1972.&#13;
Third Grade&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE LENGUA NACIONAL                 n           19669 1968 and 1976.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE GEOGRAFIA                        n          1966, 1968 and 1976.&#13;
LIBRO BRAIhLE DE HISTORIA Y CIVISMO              n           1968, 1976 and 1977.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE ARITMETICA Y GEOMETRIA          o           1968 and 1976.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE ESTUDIO DE LA&#13;
NATURALEZA                                                   1968, 1972 and 1976.&#13;
Fourth Grade&#13;
LIBRO BRA.ILLE DE HISTORIA Y CIVISMO 1           n           1968, 1971 and 1977.&#13;
LIBRO BRAIILE DE HISTORIA Y CIVISMO II           n           1968 and 1976.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE ARITMETICA Y&#13;
GEOMETRIA II                                     n           1968.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE ESTUDIO DE LA&#13;
NATURALEZA                                       u           1968 anid 1977.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE ARITMETICA Y&#13;
GEOMETRIA                                        n           1971 and 1977.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE GEOGRAFIA                       n           1971 and 1977.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE LENGUA NACIONAL                  n          1972 and 1977.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
listIng of All Titles Produced by CNLTG, 1960-1981&#13;
Plfth Grade&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE GEOGRAFIA I                  Produced and printed: 1968 and 1976.&#13;
LIBRO BRLTTLE DE GEOGRAFIA II                                        1968 and 1977.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE LENGUA NACIONAL II                                  1970 and 1977.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE HISTORIA Y CIVISMO                                  1970 and 1977*&#13;
LIBRO TRAITL  DE ARITMETICA Y GEOMETRIA                u            1970 and 1977.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE ESTUDIO DE LA NATUAZA I                u            1970 and 1977.&#13;
rIBRO BRALE DE ESTUDIO DE LA NATURAIEZA II              a            1970 and 1977.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE HISTORIA Y CIVISMO II                  n            1971.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE LENGUA NACIONAL I                      y            1972 and 1977.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE HISTORIA Y CIVISMO I                   a            1977.&#13;
Sixtb -rade&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE IENGUA NACIONAL II                     n1970, 1971 and 1977.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE HISTORIA Y CIVISMO I                   n            1970-1971&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE ESTUDIO DE LA NATURAIEZA I             n            1970, 1971 and 1977.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE ESTUDIO DE LA NATURALEZA II            n            1970 and 1977.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE GEOGRAFIA I                            a            1970 and 1977.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE GEOGRAFIA II                           n            1970 and 1971.&#13;
LIBRO BRAIILE DE GEOGRAFIA III                                       1970 and 1971.&#13;
IIBRO BRuILLE DE IENGUA NACIONAL I                                   1971 and 1977.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE HISTORIA Y CIVISMO II                               1972.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE ILENGUA NACIONAL III                   n            1977.&#13;
LIBRO BRAITTL  DE LENGUA NACIONAL IV                    n            1977.&#13;
LIBRO BRTIILE DE ARITMETICA Y GEOMETRIA I               n            1977.&#13;
LIBRO BRAILLE DE ARITMETICA Y GEOMETRIA II                          -1977.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
listing of All Tltles Produced by CNLTG, 1960-1981&#13;
LECTURAS CLASICAS I                              Produced and prínted: 1971.&#13;
LECTURAS CLASICAS II                                                    1971.&#13;
CAMPANA NACIONAL CONTRA El ARALFABETISMO                               1965.&#13;
CARTA                                                                  1974.&#13;
DOCUMENTO                                                              1974.&#13;
GUIA                                                                   1974.&#13;
First Grade&#13;
MANUAIL APRENDER HACIENDO                                           1970.&#13;
Second Grade&#13;
MANUAL APRENDER RACIENDO                                            1970.&#13;
*Third Grade&#13;
MANUAL APRENDER HACIENDO                                            1970.&#13;
Fourth Grade                                                                                          O&#13;
MANUAL APRENDER HACIENDO                                            1970.&#13;
Fifth Grade&#13;
MANUAL APRENDER HACIENDO                                            1970.&#13;
Sixth Grade&#13;
MANUALi APRENDER HACIENO                                            1970.&#13;
First and Second Grades&#13;
CUADERNO DE ALFABETIZACION OAXACA                                  1973.&#13;
LIBRO DE ALFABETIZACION OAXACA                                      1973.&#13;
Third and Fourth Grades&#13;
CUADERNO DE ALPABETIZACION OAXACA                                  1973.&#13;
LIBRO DE ALFABETIZACION OAXACA                                      1973.&#13;
Fifth and Sixth Grades&#13;
CUADERNO DE ALFABETIZACION OAXACA                                  1973.&#13;
LIBRO DE AIFABETIZACION OAXACA                                      1973.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
listing of All Titles Produced by CNLTG, 1960-1981&#13;
First Grade&#13;
PLAN Y PROGRAMA DE EDUCACION PRIMARIA        Produced and printed: 1973.&#13;
Seoond Grade&#13;
PLAN Y PROGRAMA DE EDUCACION PRIMARIA                              1973.&#13;
Third Grade&#13;
PLAN Y PROGRAMA DE EDUCACION PRIMARIA                              1973.&#13;
Fifth Grade&#13;
*-PLAN Y PROGRAMA DE EDUCACION PRIMARIA                              1973.&#13;
AIYO INTERNACIONAL DE LA MUJER                                         1975.&#13;
CIENCIAS NATURALES INTRODUC. PRIMARIA&#13;
ADULTOS la. PARTE                                                      1975.&#13;
.CIENCIAS .SOCIALES INTRODUC. PRIMARIA&#13;
ADULTOS la. PARTE                                                      1975.                          ¡&#13;
INTRODUCCION A LAS MATEMATICAS"                                        1975.                         °&#13;
ESPANOL INTRODUC. PRIMARIA ADULTOS la. PARTE                           1975.&#13;
INTRODUC. PRIM. ADULTOS AUX. DIDACTICO                                 1975 and 1977.&#13;
INTRODUC. PRIM. ADULTOS CUADERNO DE TRABAJO                            1975 and 1977.&#13;
LIBRO DE CONSULTA                                                      1975.&#13;
MATEMATICAS PRIM. INTRODUC. ADULTOS, la. PARTE                         1975.&#13;
TESORO DEL PUEBLO                                                      1975.&#13;
-AUXILIAR DIDACTICO CIRCULO DE ESTUDIOS                                 1976 ajid 1977.&#13;
COMO IDENTIFICAR LAS DROGAS                                            1976.&#13;
DESARROLLO DE LA COMUNIDAD                                             1976.&#13;
DIARIO GESTION TOMO I                                                  1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Listing of All Titles Produced by CNLTG, 1960-1981&#13;
DIARIO GESTION TOMO II                           Produced and printed: 1976.&#13;
DOCUMENTOS S/1EY NACIONAL"                                             1976.&#13;
EDUCACION TECNOLOGICA Y DIDACTICA                                      1976.&#13;
HISTORIA DE LA EDUCACION EN MEXICO 5°y6n                               1976.&#13;
LIBRO CONSULTA CIENCIAS SOCIALES 30y 40                                1976.&#13;
MEXICO EN LA MUSICA JULIO 76                                           1976.&#13;
MEXICO EN LA MUSICA AGOSTO 76                                          1976.&#13;
MEXICO EN LA MUSICA SEPTIEMBRE 76                                      1976.&#13;
MEXICO EN LA MUSICA OCTUBRE 76                                         1976.&#13;
MEXICO EN LA MUSICA NOVIEMBRE 76                                       1976.&#13;
la. JORNADAS INTERNACIONALES CAZALS (FOLLETO)                          1976.&#13;
la. JORNADAS INTERNACIONALES CAZALS (PROGRAMA)                         1976. &#13;
la. JORNADAS INTERNACIONALES CAZALS (POSTERS)                          1976.&#13;
PROBLEMAS ECONOMICOS Y SOCIALES DE MEXICO                              1976.&#13;
PSICOLOGIA 3°y 40                                                      1976.&#13;
SECRETARIA DE EDUCACION (DIV, LIBROS)                                  1976.&#13;
SISTEMA NACIONAL PARA PROMOTORES Y ASESORES                            1976.&#13;
SISTEMA NACIONAL SECUNDARIA ABIERTA                                    1976.&#13;
LIBRO DE CONSULTA CIENCIAS SOCIALES 5°y 60                             1977.&#13;
PLAN Y PROGRAMA DE EDUCACION PRIM. 10                                  1977.&#13;
PLAN Y PROGRAMA DE EDUCACION PRIM. 20                                  1977.&#13;
PLAN Y PROGRAMA DE EDUCACION PRIM. 30                                  1977.&#13;
PLAN Y PROGRAMA DE EDUCACION PRIM. 40                                  1977.&#13;
PLAN Y PROGRAMA DE EDUCACION PRIM. 50                                  1977.&#13;
PLAN Y PROGRAMA DE EDUCACION PRIM. 60                                  1977.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-111-&#13;
APPENDIX E, Table 003&#13;
The National Commíssion for Free Textbooks (CNITG)&#13;
a. CNLTG's Annual Subsidies from Government. 1960-19811&#13;
1960     Mp $  40'675,346.00        1971     Mp $ 118'532,157.00&#13;
1961           28'572,214.00        1972          143'447,810.00&#13;
1962          105'189,585.00        1973          133t333,000.00&#13;
1963           43'022,702.00        1974          1321938,000.00&#13;
1964           61'754,345.00        1975          329'389,000.00&#13;
1965           671000,000.00        1976          452'495,000.00&#13;
1966           73#000,000.00        1977          6791347,000.00&#13;
1967          1069999,999.00        1978          451'153,996.00&#13;
1968          103'999,999.00        1979          678'027,000.00&#13;
1969          1061068,672.00        1980          741'199,999.00&#13;
1970          114'537,849.00        1981          990!000,0000C&#13;
b. CNLTG's Capital Investment in Printing Plant1&#13;
Initial Investment:   1960       Mp $      387,300.00&#13;
Added:  1975                           105'996,955.00&#13;
Added:  1980                           158'241,565.00&#13;
1Source: CNLTG.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX E, Table 004&#13;
The National Commission for Free Textbooks (CNLTG)&#13;
AveraRe Manufacturing Costa1 Per Sianatture. 1960-1980&#13;
Adj .Av.&#13;
Total                    2        Av. Cost/                   Av. Cost/  General         Av. Cost/                   Av. Cost/   Cost3&#13;
Ye_arSlntrs_P SSinature                             Distribution - Si~nature- Exipenses         Sigmature Total Cost        Signature  Si_.__&#13;
1960   80'070,482.00   *30'776,141.71   0.384363             0.00        000       43,819423    0.000547   30'819,960.94   0.384910    1.834&#13;
le61  104'372,187.00    42'282,122.27   0.405109             0.00        000     1'309,087.49   0.012542   43'591,209.76   0.417651    1.926&#13;
1962  115'178,613.00    42'611,026.66   0.369956             0.00        000    1'536,303.46    0.013338   44'147,330.12   0.383294    1.722&#13;
1963  215'497,656.00    79'252,353.56   0.367764             0.00        000    2'003,731.29    0.009298   81'256,084.85   0.377062    1.640&#13;
1964  153'919,644.00    61'456,870.28   0.399278             0.00        000    2'406,839.13    0.015636   63'863,709.41   0.414915    1.642&#13;
1965  199'712,545.00    65'323,458.44   0.327087       569,609.15   0.002852    5'901,312.74    0.029549   71'794,380.33   0.359488    1.431&#13;
1966  206'704,995.00    60'444,967.39   0.292421     1'396,638.77   0.006756    6'191,510.45    0.029953   68'033,116.61   0.329131    1.246&#13;
1967  298'991,436.00    83'922,643.11   0.280685     1'506,652.50   0.005039    8'040,753.42    0.026892   93'470,049.03   0.312617    1.173&#13;
1968  304'617,831.00    90'607,659.88   0.297446     2'005,131.35   0.006582    9'449,730.85    0.031021  102'062,522.08   0.335051    1.230&#13;
1969  305'079,665.00    90'540,076.34   0.296775     1'993,008.64   0.006532    8'535,191.81    0.027976  101'068,276.79   0.331284    1.180&#13;
1970  334'421,376.00    97'414,326.29   0.291292     2'191,064.06   0.006551    9'198,925.96    0.027506 108'804,316.26    0.325350    1.099&#13;
1971  361'376,749.00   110'344,831.29   0.305345     2'372,051.18   0.006563    9'875,816.86    0.027328 122'592,699.33    0.339237    1.098 -&#13;
1972  361'357,150.00   128'514,283.69   0.355643     2'718,050.41   0.007521   13'214,800.31    9.036569  144'447,134.41   0.399735    1.224&#13;
1973  330'842,664.00   132'565,628.17   0.400690     2'620,424.77   0.007920   12'403,168.73    0.037489 147'589,221.67    0.446100    1.217&#13;
1974  371'457,094.00   243'162,714.15   0.654618     3'486,317.04   0.009385   18'148,484.85    0.048857 264'797,516.04    0.712861   1.567&#13;
1975  492'104,326.00   396'770,709.75   0.806273     3'312,242.46   0.006730   22'668,239.99    0.046063 422'751,192.20    0.859068   1.620&#13;
1976  501'531,810.00   347'264,322.16   0.692407     5'497,483.15   0.010961   27'495,585.30    0.054823 380'257,390.61    0.7581.91  1.175&#13;
1977  457'182,620.00   463'636,314.67   1.014116     7'485,190.34   0.016372   33'071,263.99    0.072337 594'192,769.00    1.102825   1.293&#13;
1978. 445'482,097.00   403'399,213.51   0.905534     7'324,325.80   0.016441  .41'742,768.54    0.093702 452'466,307.85    1.015677   1.015&#13;
1979  502'223,771.00   5051442,841.61   1.006409    17'026,596.25   0.033902   39'767,575.53    0.079182 562'237,013.39    1.119495&#13;
1980  350'242,483.00   561'360,047.57   1.602775    48'248,629.76   0.137758   68'307,602.62    0.195029 677'916,279.95    1.935563&#13;
1 In Mexican pesos&#13;
2 Paper, Printing, Binding&#13;
3 Adjusted average cost per signature according to index of prices.&#13;
Source: CNLTG.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX E, Table 005          -113-&#13;
Average Estimated Cost per Textbook1&#13;
Specifications:  224 pages (7 signatures of 32 pages), approximately&#13;
7 x 10" printed in full four-color web offset;&#13;
paper covers in four coloss; perfect (hot melt)&#13;
binding; textpaper 60 gsm produced in Mexico from&#13;
bagasse, similar in quality to newsprint but&#13;
heavier; coverstock 125 gsm2 of same quality.&#13;
Year   Current  Adjusted according     Year    Current   Adjusted2&#13;
Pesos    to Index of Prices2            Pesos&#13;
1965:   2.51           10.00           1973:    3.12        8.52&#13;
1966:   2.30           8.72.           1974:    4.99        10.97&#13;
1967:   2.19           8.21            1975:    6.01       11.34&#13;
1968:   2.34           8.61            1976:    5.30        8.22&#13;
1969:   2.32           8.26            1977:    7.70        9.05&#13;
1970:   2.24            7.69           1978:    7.07        7.10&#13;
1971:   2.37            7.69           1979:    7.84&#13;
1972:   2.80            8.57           1980:   13.58&#13;
Note:  The figures indicate a dramatic increase in costs from 1979&#13;
to 1980 for which we do not have an explanation.   According to&#13;
Table 004 of Appendix E, paper increased 60% in cost from 1979 to&#13;
1980, distribution costs increased 4 times, from 0.034 to 0.137,&#13;
and general expenses increased by over 100%.&#13;
1 Costa are based on Table 004 and are in current Mexican pesos.&#13;
Costs include: color separation; film and plate-making; paper,&#13;
printing, and binding; distribution; and general overhead of CNLTG.&#13;
Costs do not include: Depreciation of printing plant; and for Third&#13;
Generation textbooks, at least, there are considerable additional&#13;
expenses incurred by the Sub-Directorate for Educational Content and&#13;
Methods in editorial development, production, testing, etc. Nor do&#13;
costs include teacher training, which has never been a responsibility&#13;
of CNLTG.&#13;
2 Costo promedio adjustado con indices de precios = Adjusted&#13;
average cost according to the índex of prices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX F, Table 001&#13;
Annual Mexican Book Trade Balances&#13;
1970 - 1980&#13;
(Millions of pesos)&#13;
Years        Exportations          Importations     Surplus/Deficit&#13;
1970             212                    188                24&#13;
1971             143                    299              (156)&#13;
1972             157                    523              (366)&#13;
1973             223                    543              (320)&#13;
1974             295                    575              (280)&#13;
1975             289                    450              (161)&#13;
1976             391                    545              (154)&#13;
1977             711                    766              ( 55)&#13;
1978             824                    939              (115)&#13;
1979           1,016                  1,711              (695)&#13;
1980           1,101                  2,218           (1,117)&#13;
Source:  Compiled by CODIECLI with figures from the annual&#13;
statistics of the Foreign Trade Bureau of the Secretariat of&#13;
Commerce for the period 1970-1977. The figures for the years&#13;
1978-1981 are from the General Directorate of Customs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX P, Table 002&#13;
Mexican Book Trade Balance&#13;
1979 - 1980&#13;
(Volume in metric tons and value in thousands of pesos)&#13;
Exportations        Importations       Surplus/Deficit&#13;
Country or Area                                                 1979&#13;
Volume    Value    Volume     Value    Volume    Value&#13;
North America                          413      62,381   3,169    312,457  -2,756      -250,076&#13;
Central America                      1,322     161,544     287     13,473    1,035      148,071&#13;
South America                        2,929     556,532     967    190,154    1,962      366,378&#13;
Caribbean                              687      97,038      90     10,519      597       86,519&#13;
Spain                                  664     121,799   9,786  1,089,589  -9,122    -'-.d967,790&#13;
European Common Market                 110      12,373     428     79,105  -   318     - 66,732&#13;
Eastern Europe                          11       1,205     149      3,427  -   138     -  2,222&#13;
Rest of Europe                          17       1,080      66      4,161  -    49     -  3,081&#13;
Asia &amp; Africa                           15       2,111     114      8,109  -    49     -  5,998&#13;
Oceania                                  3         327      _          14        3          313&#13;
Unknown                                  -          -       13        272  -    13     -    272&#13;
TOTAL                                6,171   1,016,390  15,069  1,711,280  -8,898      -694,890&#13;
1980&#13;
North America                          677      86,394   3,694    379,160 - 3,017    - &lt;-292,766&#13;
Central America                      1,452     192,689     191     16,514    1,261      176,175&#13;
South America                        3,076     555,156   1,156    208,450    1,920      346,706&#13;
Caribbean                              853     129,060      84     10,109    . 769      118,951&#13;
Spain                                  597     125,587  12,207  1,440,703 -11,610    -1,315,116&#13;
Suropean Common Market                  23       5,329     741    122,562 -    718   -  117,233&#13;
Eastern Europe                           3         955     363     10,877 -    360   -    9,922&#13;
Rest of Europe                           7         455      59      5,875 -     52   -    5,420&#13;
Asia &amp; Africa                           15       2,731     176     23,140 '    161   -   20,409&#13;
Oceanía                                 15       2,262       1        401       14        1,861&#13;
Unknown                                  1         123       3         125-      2   -        2&#13;
TOTAL                                6,719   1,100,741  18,675  2,217,916 "11,956    -1,117,175&#13;
Source:  General Directorate of Customs. (Courtesy of CODIECII)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX F, Table 003&#13;
Estimated Paper Consumption by Category&#13;
Newspapers  Other Papers   Subtotal:  Packing    Sanitary  Special&#13;
Year               &amp; Free       &amp; Cover       Writing &amp;  Papers     &amp; Facial   Papers     Total&#13;
Textbooks   Stocks         Printing              Papers&#13;
Papers&#13;
Production    51,008        167,974     218,982      587,739   58,392     42,708    907,821&#13;
1971  Importations 168,430         11,777     180,207          900         5    13,812    194,924&#13;
Total        219,438        179,751     399,189      588,639   58,397     56,520  1,102,745&#13;
Production    51,000        193,413     244,413      622,410   70,985     43,319    981,127&#13;
1972  Importations 168,880         15,350     184,230       15,879       75     21,138    221,322&#13;
Total        219,880        208,763     428,643      638,289   71,060     64,457  1,202,449&#13;
Production    43,341        214,637     257,978      729,610   88,015     37,055  1,112,658&#13;
1973  Importations 153,215         14,135     167,350       23,513       589    22,573    214,025&#13;
Total        196,556        228,772     425,328      753,123   88,604     59,628  1,326,683&#13;
Production    57,000        239,828     296,828      805,395   99,752     51,713  1,253,688   ;&#13;
1974  Importations 216,417         17,962     234,379       35,413      746     21,938    292,476&#13;
Total        273,417        257,790     531,207      840,808  100,498     73,651  1,546,164&#13;
Production    46,723        239,135     285,858      759,018  105,176     34,551  1,184,603&#13;
1975  Importations 249,374         13,636     263,010       27,696     -        11,500    302,206&#13;
Total        296,097        252,771     548,868      786,714  105,176     46,051  1,486,809&#13;
Production    74,019        275,068     349,087      824,893  112,491     44,451  1,330,922&#13;
1976  Importations 241,584          7,514     249,098       30,693               5,064    284,855&#13;
Total        315,603        282,582     598,185      855,586  112,491     49,515  1,615,777&#13;
Production   104,218        289,704     393,922      888,987  126,324     44,423  1,453,656&#13;
1977  Importations 250,557          7,396     257,953       34,893     -         4,353    297,199&#13;
Total        354,775        297,100     651,875      923,880  126,324     48,776  1,750,855&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX F, Table 003&#13;
Estimated Paper Consumption by Category (contd.)&#13;
Newspapers  Other Papers  Subtotal:- Packing     Sanitary  Special&#13;
Year               &amp; Free       &amp; Cover       Writing &amp;  Papers     &amp; Facial  Papers      Total&#13;
Textbooks   Stocks        Printing               Papers&#13;
Papera&#13;
Production   108,737        325,491     434,228      956,005  145,483    47,368   1,583,084&#13;
1978  Importations  97,424         10,203     107,627       40,664     -        12,689    160,980&#13;
Total        206,161        335,694     541,855      996,669  145,483    60,057   1,744,064&#13;
Production   131,540        369,813     501,353    1,013,687  162,363    54,022   1,731,425&#13;
1979  Importations 110,036         23,571     133,607       85,386     -       21,670     240,663&#13;
Total        241,576        393,384     634,960    1,099,073  162,363    75,692   1,972,088&#13;
Production   143,252        416,423     559,675    1,108,479  183,834    44,415   1,896,403&#13;
1980  Importations*200,358         65,280     265,638      250,284     -       66,258     582,180&#13;
Total        343,610        481,703     825,313    1,358,763  183,834   110,673   2,478,583&#13;
Estimated Difference by Inventories                                                 171,000&#13;
Adjusted Estimated Consumption.                                                   2,308,000&#13;
Unit: Metric ton.&#13;
*Annual figures based on actual importations during the period January-October.&#13;
Source:  Industry statistics, the Secretariat of Commerce, and the Secretariat&#13;
of Planning and the Budget. (Courtesy of CODIECLI.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX F, Table 004               -118-&#13;
Paper Production by Category&#13;
Year                       1971    1972       1973      1974      1975&#13;
1. Writing &amp; Printing Papers&#13;
1.1 Paper                       196.104 220.616    228.746   270.279   251.968&#13;
1.1.1 Airmail &amp; Tissue Sheets     7,534   8,294      7,900     7,584    10,702&#13;
1.1.2 Bond                       95,745 109,461    127,191   154,743   143,385&#13;
1.1.3 Book                        8,814  11,940      9,640    10,725    16,048&#13;
1.1.4 Coated                     33,003  39,921     40,674    40,227    35,110&#13;
1.1.5 Newspaper                  37,943  39,664     39,180    40,000    29,380&#13;
1.1.6 Textbooks                  13.065  11.336      4.161    17.000    17.343&#13;
1.2 Paper Cover Stock            22.878  23,797     29,232    26,549    33,890&#13;
1.2.1 Not coated                 18,959  18,868    1bq,7b5    21,715    251,115&#13;
1.2.2 Coated                      3.919   4.929     10.469     4.836     8.775&#13;
Subtotal                  218.982 244.413    257.978   296.828   285.858&#13;
2. Packing&#13;
2.1 Paper                       479,415 503.205    590.015   653.933    619.063&#13;
2.1.1 Sacks                      80,832  80,149     93,630   101,520    117,276&#13;
2.1.2 Bags                       38,043  36,910     37,805    33,971     38,482&#13;
2.1.3 Envelopes                  60,761   57,226    65,393    69,355     70,350&#13;
2.1.4 Cartons                   203,482 228,940    269,236   332,484    281,287&#13;
2.1.5 Corrugated Cartons         96.297  99.980    123.951   116.603    111.668&#13;
2.2 Fine Cardboard              108.324 119.205    139.595   151.462    139.955&#13;
2.2.1 Uncoated Maiila Board      36,794  28,240     22,763    26,392     20,215&#13;
2.2.2 Coated Manila Board        44,141   63,300    85,461    95,219    89,970&#13;
2.2.3 GraU Board                 27.389   27.665    31.371    29.851     29.770&#13;
Subtotal                  587.739 822.410    729.610   8058395   759.018&#13;
3. Sanitary &amp; Facial             58,392   70,985    88,015    99,752    105,176&#13;
4. Special&#13;
4.1 Glassine                      2,690    3,616     4,733     3,800      4,000&#13;
4.2 Chinese                       3,652    2,556     1,791     2,504      3,420&#13;
4.3 Others                       36.366   37.147    30.531    45.409     27.131&#13;
Subtotal                     42.708  43.319     37.055    51.713    34.551&#13;
Total:                      907,821 981,127 1,112,658 1,253,688 1,184,603&#13;
Unit: Metric ton.&#13;
Source:  Industry etatistices.  (Courtesy CODIECLI.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX F, Table 004               -119-&#13;
Paper Production bv Category (conttd.)&#13;
Year                    1976      1977       1978      1979      1980&#13;
1. Writing &amp; Printing Papers&#13;
1.i Paper                      316.617   360.934   397.817    454.641   500.830&#13;
1.1.1 Airmail &amp; TissueSheets    7;592     6,219      7,776     8,460   11,766&#13;
1.1.2 Bond                    173,115   183,131    207,898   236,232   270,119&#13;
1.1.3 Book                     19,747    15,744     20,008    22,834    27,000&#13;
1.1.4 Coated                   42,144    51,622     53,398    55,575    48,693&#13;
1.1.5 Newspaper                56,204    89,664     84,430    94,925   115,734&#13;
1.1.6 Textbooks                17.815    14.554     24.307    36.615    27.518&#13;
1.2 Pa-er Cover Stock          32 470    32.988     24        46 612    588&#13;
1.2.1 Not Coated               26,550    28,511     30,175    33,881    40,923&#13;
1.2.2 Coated                    5.920     4.477      6.236    12.831    17.922&#13;
Subtotal                349.087   393.922   434,228    501.353   559.675&#13;
2. Packing&#13;
2.1 Paper                     665.140   722.318    780.095   822.537   882.260&#13;
2.1.1 Sacks                   117,632   123,296    133,758   124,690    120,633&#13;
2.1.2 Bags                     36,186    36,567     35,623    35,540    37,313&#13;
2.1.3 Envelopes                59,207   64,548      69,555    67,655    65,999&#13;
2.1.4 Cartons                 319,072   347,615    376,405   400,960   442,184&#13;
2.1.5 Corrugated Cartons      133.043   150.292    164.754   193.692   216.131&#13;
2,2 Pine Cardboard            159.7$3   166.669    175.910   191.150   226.219&#13;
2.2.1 Uncoated Manila Board    21,195    10,893     16,593    20,177    21,615&#13;
2.2.2 Coated Manila Board     104,628   117,891    122,916   136,375   180,247&#13;
2.2.3 Gray Board               33.930    37.885     36.401    34.598    24.357&#13;
Subtotal                824 893   888.987   956,005   1¡013.6871.1088479&#13;
3. Sanitary &amp; Facial          112,491   126,324    145,483   162,363   183,834&#13;
4. Special&#13;
4.1 Glassine                    4,600      5,386     3,302     3,201      2,564&#13;
.4.2 Chinese                    2,378      2,026     1,096     2,204      1,486&#13;
4.3 Others                     37.473    37.011     42.970    48.617    40.365&#13;
Subtotal                   44.451    44.423     47.368    54,022    44.415&#13;
Total:                  1,330,922 1,453,656 1,503,084 1,731,425 1,896,403&#13;
Unit: Metric ton.&#13;
Source: Industry statistics. (Courtesy CODIECLI.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX F, Table 005            -120-&#13;
Importation of Paper by Categor_&#13;
Year                   1971       1972     1973     1974     1975&#13;
Paners&#13;
Newspaper                   N.D.      N.D.    120,717  194,291  220,592&#13;
Textbook                    N.D. 1    N.D.     32,498   22,126   28,782&#13;
Subtotal: Newspaper       168,430    168,880  153,215  216,417  249,374&#13;
&amp; T,xtbook&#13;
Couche                      59422     9,841     7,923    99291    9,007&#13;
Key Punch Cards             5,753      5,049    5,479    7,820    2,494&#13;
Bank Checks                   588        416      660      762      458&#13;
Other Writing &amp; Printing       14        44        73       89    1,677&#13;
Papers&#13;
Subtotal:  Writing &amp;       11,777     15,350   14,135   17,962   13,636&#13;
- Printing Papers&#13;
Fine CaErdboard              -          -       1,460      925      265&#13;
Sanitary Cardboard            700     11,714   18,377   24,451   21,000&#13;
Kraft, more than 160 gr.    N.D.       N.D.     N.D.     N.D.     N.D.&#13;
Kraft, less than 160 gr.    N.D.       N.D.     N.D.     N.D.     N.D.&#13;
Other Packing Papers          200     4,165     3,676   10,037    6,431&#13;
Subtotal: Packing Papers      900     15.879   23.513   35.413   27.696&#13;
Other Papers for Special   13,817    21,213    23,162   22;,684  11,500&#13;
Use&#13;
Total                194,924   221,322   214,025  292,476  302,206&#13;
Unit: Metric ton&#13;
1 Possibility of breaking out the total figure after 1973.&#13;
N.D. Impossible to break out the individual figures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX P, Table 005            -121-&#13;
Importation of Paper by Category (conttdj)&#13;
Year                    1976      1977     1978     1979     1980*&#13;
Papers&#13;
Newspaper                  207,745   233,217   87,033    N.D.     N.D.&#13;
Textbook                    33,839    17,340   10,391    N.D.     N.D.&#13;
Subtotal:  Newspaper       241,584   250,557   97,424  110,036  200,358&#13;
&amp; T$xtbook&#13;
Couche                       4,578     4,293    5,158   179430'  38,76-0'&#13;
Key Punch Cards              2,124     2,639    3,332    4,566    3,934&#13;
Bank Checks                    425       464      831      741    1,920&#13;
Other Writing &amp; Printing       387      -         882      834   20,666&#13;
Papers&#13;
Subtotal:  Writing &amp;         7,514     7,396   10,203   23,571   65,280&#13;
Printing Papers&#13;
Fine Cardboard                -         -        -       7,5159   7,2007&#13;
Sanitary Cardboard          30,693    34,045   38,452   42,172   56,160&#13;
Kraft, more than 160 gr.     N.D.      N.D.     N.D.     9,327   54,360&#13;
Kraft, less than 160 gr.     N.D.      N.D.     N.D.    23,952  129,480&#13;
Other Packing Papers        N.D.         848    2,212    2,420    3,084&#13;
Subtotal:'Packing Papers    30.693    34.893   40.664   85.386  250.284&#13;
Other Papers for Special     5,064     4,353  :12,689   21,670   66,258&#13;
Use&#13;
Total                284,855    297,199  160,980  240,663  582,180&#13;
Unit: Metrie ton&#13;
1 Includes papers, cover stock paper, and cardboard.&#13;
2 Includes Manila Board and Multiplex Board.&#13;
*Annual figures based on actual importations during the period&#13;
January-October.&#13;
N.D. Impossible to break out the individual figures.&#13;
Source:  Statistics from the paper industry, the Secretariat of&#13;
Commerce, and the Secretariat of Planning and the Budget. (Courtesy&#13;
of CODIECLI.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
BIBLIOGRAPHY&#13;
Background Reading&#13;
Constitution of the United Mexican States. 1917 (As Amended) (Text&#13;
tranalated from Constitución Política de los Estados Unidos&#13;
Mexicanos, Déeima Edición, 1959, Editorial Porrúa, S.A.,&#13;
México, D.F.  Subsequent amendments to June 22, 1963, from&#13;
Diario Oficial.) (Washington, D.C.: Pan American Union, 1964).&#13;
Drake, Diana Mack. "Bilingual Education Prograns for Indian Children&#13;
in Mexico," The-Modern Language Journal, LXII (September-October,&#13;
1978, pp. 239-248.&#13;
Gill, Clark C. Education in a Changing Mexico. (U.S. Department of&#13;
Health, Education, and Welfare, Office of Education and Institute&#13;
of International Studies, Superintendent of Documents Catalog&#13;
No. FS5.214:14139.) Washington, D.C.: Government Printing&#13;
Office, 1969.&#13;
Heyneman, Stephen P., Joseph P. Farrell, Manuel A. Sepulveda-Stuardo.&#13;
Textbooks and Achievement: What We Know (The World Bank Staff&#13;
Working Paper No. 298) Washington, D.C.: The World Bank, 1978.&#13;
Holt, Patricia. "Publishing in Mexico: Its Time has Come,." Publishers&#13;
Weekly, Vol. 217, No. 16 (New York: R.R. Bowker Co., April 25,&#13;
1980)9 PP. 33-46.&#13;
Mabry, Donald J. Mexico's Acción Nacional (A Catholic Alternative&#13;
to Revolution) Syracuse University Presa, Syracuse, N.Y. 1973.&#13;
Made in Mexico (Denver, Co.), IV, Number 1 (1981).&#13;
"Mexico:  Molding More Practical K-6 Programs," Nationts Schools&#13;
(New York), 84:2 (August, 1969), p. 32.&#13;
Neumann, Peter H.  Publishing for Schools. Textbooks and the Less&#13;
DeveloPed Countries (The World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 398)&#13;
Washington, D.C.: The World Bank, 1980.&#13;
Niemeyer, Jr., E.V. Revolution at Queretaro (-The Mexican Constitu-&#13;
tional Convention of 1916-1917) Institute of LA Studies,&#13;
University of Texas Presa, Austin, 1974.&#13;
Solana, Fernando. El maestro Y la calidad de la educación Mexico,&#13;
D.F.: Secretaria de Educacibn P&amp;blica, 1980.&#13;
Wagner, Susan.   "Nationalism and a Passion for Education Govern&#13;
Mexico's Attitude Toward Publishing," Publishers Weekly,&#13;
Part I (New York: R.R. Bowker Co., August 18, 1975), p. 34.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-124-&#13;
Regulations, Decrees, Statistics, etc., Issued by the Various&#13;
De,artments of the Secretariat of Public Education (SEP)&#13;
Análisis critico de los libros de texto gratuitos para la educaci6n.&#13;
Primaria de 30 a 6U-- grados, México, D.F.: Consejo Nacional&#13;
Técnico de la Educación de la SEP, n.d.&#13;
Bases instructivas, México, D.F.: Comisión de Libros de Texto y de&#13;
Consulta, Consejo Nacional Técnico de la Educación de la SEP, n.d.&#13;
40 Informe de Gobierno. Anexo I (José López Portillo) (1970-1980),&#13;
México, D.F., 1980.&#13;
Decreto Por el que se crea la Comision Nacional de los Libros de&#13;
Texto Gratuitos como organismo público descentralizado, M6xico,&#13;
D.F.: 20 de febrero de 1980.&#13;
Decreto que crea la Comisi6n Nacional de los Libros de Texto Gratuitos&#13;
dependiente de la SE?, 12 de febrero de 1959.&#13;
Decreto que modifica la fracci6n III del ArtIculo 30 que cred la&#13;
Comisión Nacional de los Libros de Texto Gratuitos, 22 de&#13;
marzo de 1977.&#13;
Estadlstica básica del sistema educativo nacional (fin cursos 1976-&#13;
19.77) México, D.F.: Dirección General de Programacid2n y&#13;
Dirección de Estadística Educativa de la SEP, agosto de 1978.&#13;
Evaluaci6n del currlculo Para la educación básica, Mexico, D.F.:&#13;
Dirección General Adjunta de Contenidos y Métodos Educativos&#13;
de la SEP, n,d.&#13;
Instructivo general, México. D.F.: Comisión Coordinadora de la&#13;
Distribución de los Libros de Texto Gratuitos, n.d.&#13;
Instructivo general sobre la distribución de los libros de texto&#13;
rratuitos, Méxieo, D.F.: Comisión Nacional de los Libros de&#13;
Texto Gratuitos, 1977.&#13;
Manual de oraanización, Comision Nacional de los Libros de Texto&#13;
Gratuitos, México, D.F., marzo de 1980.&#13;
Manual de Procedimientos para el trabajo contratado con una empresa&#13;
maauiladora, México, D.F.: Comisión Nacional de los Libros de&#13;
Texto Gratuitos, n.d,&#13;
Normas fundamentales.   Nuevos reglamento interior y diagrama de&#13;
or anizacin   3a Edii6n4 de febrero de 1980, M6xico, D.F.:&#13;
Dirección Genera   de Pu   caciones y Bibíiotecas de la SEP,&#13;
marzo de 1980.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-125-&#13;
Programa de producci6n, calendario 1981-1982, M6xico, D.F.: Comisión&#13;
Nacional de los Libros de Texto Gratuitos, n.d.&#13;
Programas: educaci6n normal Ireescolar, Mexico, D.F.: Consejo&#13;
Nacional Técnico de la Educación de la SEP, 1978.&#13;
Programas: educaci¿n normal primaria, México, D.F.: Consejo Nacional&#13;
Técnico de la Educación, 1978.&#13;
Reglamento (del Consejo Nacional Técnico de la Educación), México,&#13;
D.F.: Consejo Nacional Técnico de la Educación de la SEP,&#13;
abril de 1979.&#13;
Reglamento interior    diagrama de organizaci6n/6, 20 de enero de 1981.&#13;
("Cuadernos/SEP") México, D.F.: Dirección General de Publica-&#13;
ciones y Bibliotecas de la SEP, febrero de 1981.&#13;
Sondeo de opini6n al magisterio nacional de educácion primar4a del&#13;
sector federal sobre la Problemtlica educativa, México, D.F.:&#13;
Subsecretarla de Educacibn Básica y el Instituto Nacional de&#13;
Investigaci6n Educativa, julio de 1977..&#13;
Free Textbooks, Testing Booklets, and Questionnaires Published by&#13;
the Secretariat of Public Education (SEP)&#13;
Mi libro de Primero. Tomo 1.   México, D.F.: Secretaría de Educación&#13;
Pública, 1980.&#13;
Mi libro de primero. Tomo 2. México, D.F.: Secretar&lt;a de Educaci6n&#13;
P«blica, 1980.&#13;
Mi libro de primero   1 Material recortable, México, D.F.: Secretar&lt;a&#13;
de Educación P&amp;blica, 1980.&#13;
Mi libro de primero. 2 Material recortable, M4xico, D.F.: Secretar£a&#13;
de Educación Pdblica, 1980.&#13;
Libro Para el maestro. Primer grado.   México, D.F.: Dirección&#13;
General Adjunta de Contenidos y Métodos Educativos de la&#13;
SEP, 1980.&#13;
Mi libro de seguido, Unidad 1, Edición experimental, México, D.F.:&#13;
Dirección General Adjunta de Contenidos y Métodos Educativos&#13;
de la SEP, agosto de 1980.&#13;
Mi libro de segundo, Unidad 4, Edición experimental, M4xico, D.F.:&#13;
Direcci6n General Adjunta de Contenidos y Métodos Educativos&#13;
de la SEP, diciembre de 1980.&#13;
Libro para el maestro, Programa integrado de segundo grado (Versión&#13;
jara consulta nacional), México, D.F.: Direcci6n GeneralTAdjunta&#13;
de Contenidos y Métodos Educativos de la SEP, marzo de 1981.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-126-&#13;
Espanol, segundo grado, ejerciciosV lecturas, 1972.&#13;
Ibid., libro del maestro, 1972.&#13;
Español, tercer grado, ejercicios y lecturas, 1972.&#13;
Ibid., libro del maestro, 1972.&#13;
Espalol, cuarto grado, ejercicios y lecturas, 1972.&#13;
Ibid., libro del maestro, 1974.&#13;
Es,pañool, guinto grado, lecturas, 1972.&#13;
I_id, ejercicios, 1972.&#13;
Ibid., libro del maestro, 1972.&#13;
Españlol, sexto grado, lecturas, 1974.&#13;
Ibid., ejercicios, 1974.&#13;
Ibid., libro del maestro, 1976,&#13;
Matemáticas, primer grado, 1972.&#13;
Matemáticas, segundo grado, 1972.&#13;
Ibid., libro del maestro, 1972.&#13;
MatemAticas, tercer grado, 1972.&#13;
Ibid., libro del maestro, 1972.&#13;
Matemáticas, cuarto grado, 1974.&#13;
Ibíd., libro del maestro, 1974.&#13;
Matemáticas, quinto grado, 1972.&#13;
Ibid., libro del maestro, 1972.&#13;
Matematicas, sexto grado, 1974.&#13;
Ibid., libro del maestro, 1974.&#13;
Ciencias naturales y ciencias sociales, segundo grado, 1972.&#13;
Ciencias naturales, segundo, grado, libro del maestro, 1976.&#13;
Ciencias sociales, segundo grado, libro del maestro, 1979.&#13;
Ciencias naturales y ciencias sociales, tercer grado, 1973.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-127-&#13;
Ciencias naturales, tercer grado, libro del maestro, 1976.&#13;
Ciencias sociales, tercer grado, libro del maestro, 1979.&#13;
Ciencias naturales, cuarto arado, libro del maestro, 1975.&#13;
Ciencias sociales, cuarto grado, n.d.&#13;
Ibid., libro del maestro, 1972.&#13;
Ciencias naturales, quinto grado, 1977.&#13;
Ibíd., libro del maestro, n.d.&#13;
Ciencias sociales, quinto arado, 1978.&#13;
Ibid., libro del maestro, 1972.&#13;
Ciencias naturales, sexto grado, 1976.&#13;
Ibid., libro del maestro, n.d.&#13;
Ciencias sociales, sexto grado, 1974.&#13;
Ibid., libro del maestro, 1974.&#13;
Ciencias naturales, Primaria intensiva para adultos, Primera Darte,&#13;
México, D.F.: Centro para el Estudio de Medios y Procedimientos&#13;
Avanzados de la Educaci6n de la SEP, 1975.&#13;
____________________&#13;
Noamoch tlen se xiuitl tlamachtilistli, Mi libro de nahuatl. (Tlapa,&#13;
Guerrero), 1980.&#13;
Noamoch tlen se xiuitl tlamachtilistli, Mi libro de nahuatl&#13;
(Huauchinango, Puebla), 1980.&#13;
Noamoch tlen se xiuitl tlamachtilistli, Mi libro de nahuatl&#13;
(Chicontepec, Veracruz), 1980.&#13;
____________________&#13;
Cuaderno de evaluacion del alumno,   rimer Rrado, México, D.F.:&#13;
Secretaria de Educacion Piblica, 1980.&#13;
Cuestionario a almacenes, México, D.F.: Comisión Nacional de los&#13;
Libros de Texto Gratuitos, n.d,&#13;
Cuestionario a escuelas, México, D.F,: Comisi6n Nacional de los&#13;
Libros de Texto Gratuitos, n.d.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-128-&#13;
Cuestionario a inspectores de zona, México, D.F.: Comision Nacional&#13;
de los libros de Texto Gratuitos, n.d.&#13;
Encuesta de opinion sobre el libro para el maestro de primer grado,&#13;
México, D.F.: Secretaría de Educación Pública, marzo de 1980.&#13;
Encuesta de opinión sobre e   libro Para el maestro de segundo grado,&#13;
México, D.F.: Secretaria de Educaci6n Pública, marzo de 1981.&#13;
Mi hilo en Primer grado de primaria (recomendaciones para los padres&#13;
de familia), México, D.F.: Secretaria de Educación Pública, n.d.&#13;
Registro de asistencia y evaluación para escuelas primarias, Mexico,&#13;
D.F.: Dirección General de Programací6n de la SEP, 1980.&#13;
Educational Materials Other than Textbooks Published by Various&#13;
Departments of the Secretariat of Public Education (SEP) Alone or&#13;
in Conjunetion with Others&#13;
Newspaper Supplements (Workbook Pages)&#13;
El Nacional, Aio I. Num. 34. Martes, Direccion General de Materiales&#13;
Didacticos y Culturales de la SEP, junio de 1981.&#13;
Ibid., Num. 34, Mie'rcoles.&#13;
Ibid., Niúm. 35, Lunes.&#13;
Ibid., Martes.&#13;
Ibid., Miércoles.&#13;
Ibid., Viernes.&#13;
ColeccFón Ctmo hacer meJor, M4xico, D.F.: ConsejoNacional para el&#13;
omento de la Educacíón de la SEP, 1980.    (Numeros 1, 2, 4-27,&#13;
29-32, 34, 36-46, 48-52, 54, 55, 57-61.)&#13;
D&lt;az Covarrubias, Juan. Gil GÓ'mez, el insurgente ("Biblioteca de&#13;
Clasicos Mexicanos Condensados.WTiMéxico, D.F.: Consejo&#13;
Nacional para el Fomento de la Educacidón de la SEP y Promociones&#13;
Editoriales Mexicanas, S.A. de C.V. (Promexa), 1981.&#13;
El sol vencido: la batalla por M64xico-Tenochtitlan (IMéxico,&#13;
historia de un pueblo," tomo 2). México, D.F.: Consejo Nacional&#13;
para el Fomento de la Educación de la SEP y Editorial Nueva&#13;
Imagen, 1980.&#13;
Enciclopedia infantil colibr&#143;, N&amp;meros 40, 42, 45 y 49. M,éxico,&#13;
D.F.: Consejo nacional para el Fomento de la Educacion de la&#13;
SEP y Salvat Mexicana de Ediciones, S.A., 1979.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-129-&#13;
Garza,"Roque G. La batalla de Torreón. (Cyadernos mexicano,, Ano I,&#13;
Numero 21.") Mexico, D.F.: Secretaría de Educacion Publica y&#13;
Conasupo, n.d.&#13;
Payno, Manuel. los bandidos de Río Fro ("Biblioteca de Clásicos&#13;
Mexicanos Condensados.")   Mexico, D.F.:  Consejo Nacional para&#13;
el Fomento de la Educación y Promociones Editoriales Mexicanas,&#13;
S.A. de C.V. (Promexa), 1981.&#13;
Urquiz9, Frangisco I. Tropa vieja ("Novelas M,xicanas Ilustradas,"&#13;
Ano I, Numero 1.) Mexico, D.F.: Direccion General de Pu»lica-&#13;
ciones y Bibliotecas de la SEP y el Grupo Sayrols, Companla&#13;
General de Ediciones, S.A., n.d.&#13;
Articles from Educational and Publishing Magazines&#13;
"Acuerdo núm. 17 que establece las yormas a que deberán sujetarse&#13;
los procedimientos de evaluacion .el aprendizaje en los distintos&#13;
tipos y,modalidades de la educacion, bajo el control de la SEP,"&#13;
Educacion, CNTE, (julio de 1978), pp. 92-94.&#13;
"Algunos obstáculos a la reforma educativa," Educación, CNTE, pp. 3-4.&#13;
"Alvarez Constantino, Higilio. "Educación rural: viejas necesidades,&#13;
nuevas soluciones," Educacion, CNTE, pp. 34-43.&#13;
Caball9ro  C., Arqulm9des.   "El problema del acceso a la educación&#13;
basica," Educacion, CNTE, PP. 5-11.&#13;
Cardenas Vázquez, Sebastián. "Log planes de estudio p,ra la preparación&#13;
de los profesores de educacion primaria," Educacion, CNTE,&#13;
PP. 55-67.&#13;
"Consejo Nacional Técnico de la EdIcación:   instructivo para elaborar&#13;
los libros de texto," Educacion, CNTE, pp. 23-24.&#13;
"Consejo Na4lonal Técnico de la Educación:   los nuevos programas de&#13;
educacion primaria," Educacion, CNTE, PP. 33-44.&#13;
"Consejo Nacional Técnico de la Educación: los nuevos programas de&#13;
educacion primaria: objetivos generaleg e instructivos para el&#13;
uso de cada una de las areas de formacion," Educacion, CNTE,&#13;
pp. 27-43.&#13;
El maesro, Organo del Consejo Nacional Técnico de la Educación&#13;
(México, D.F.) Año I, Numero 1 (marzo de 1981).&#13;
El maestro Organo del Consejo Nacional Técnico de la Educación&#13;
(México, D.F.) Año I, Numero 2 (abril de 1981).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-130-&#13;
El maestro, Organo del Consejo Nacional Te'cnico de la Educaci6n&#13;
(México, D.F.) Sexta Epoca, Ano I, Número 3 (mayo de 1981).&#13;
Jimenez Alarcón, Amador,   "Las ciencias sociales-en la educacion&#13;
primaria," Educacio'n, CNTE, PP. 45-50.&#13;
0J.L.P. Inaugura la Décima Feria Metropolitana del Libro, junio 29,&#13;
1981" México Editor, Portavoz de la Cámara Nacional de la&#13;
Industria Editorial Mexicana, Extraordinary Issue, June 29, 1981.&#13;
López Arenas, Jorge. "Dos puntos de vista sobre la reforma educativa:&#13;
I. Entrevista al Dr. Pablo Latapl," Educacidh, CNTE, PP. 42-45.&#13;
Lourie, Sylvain. "Para una formación permanente del docente de&#13;
educacion básica," Educación, CNTE, pp. 19-39.&#13;
"Mejoramiento, de la calidad de la vida:  urgente accion educativa,"&#13;
Educacion, CNTE, pp. 3-4.&#13;
Noguez Ram&#143;rez, Antonio.   "Una experiencia mexicana:   la telesecundaria,"&#13;
Educaci&amp;n, CNTE, pp. 57-63.&#13;
Núnez Urquiza, Carlos.   "Direcciócn general de educacidn para adultos,"&#13;
Educaci6n, Vol. VII, 4a. época, CNTE. (January-March 1981),&#13;
PP. 9-19.&#13;
Pierre Vielle, Jean. "Educación no formal, capacitación para el&#13;
trabajo e innovación tecnol6gica en el medio rural," Educaci6n,&#13;
CNTE, pp. 56-71.&#13;
Saenz, Molses,   "La escuela rural de México," Educacicn, ONTE,&#13;
pp. 19-26.&#13;
Salas, Ismael S.   "El gasto educativo de las familias en México,"&#13;
Educación, CNTE, pp. 65-74.&#13;
Salas, Ismael S.   "El sistema educativo mexicano (primera de dos&#13;
partes)," Educacidn, CNTE, pp. 67-78.&#13;
Salas, Ismael S. "El sistema educativa mexicano (segunda y Última&#13;
parte)," Educacioón, CNTE, pp. 57-68.&#13;
Salas, Ismael S.   "Estadlsticas educativas:  las desigualdades&#13;
educativas en México," Educación, CNTE, pp. 69-84.&#13;
"Secretaria de Educacion Pu'blica, acuerdo 3810 sobre evaluacion,&#13;
instructivo y ejemplos," Educación, CNTE, pp. 5-26.&#13;
Todd Pérez, Luis Eu enio.   "Reflexiones actuales sobre el futuro&#13;
de la educaci n,"Educacion, ONTE, pp. 36-44.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-131-&#13;
Newspaper Articles&#13;
Aranda, Rosario.   "Formará el IPN en 10 aros 90 mii ingenieros  ara&#13;
el mejor desarrollo tecnol6gico del pa s," El Nacional (Méx'ico,&#13;
D.F.) (9 de junio de 1981), p. 10.&#13;
"Aumento 4.5 veces la producción bruta anual de papel en tan sollo&#13;
ocho aníos," El Nacional (México, D.F.) (9 de junio de 1981),&#13;
P. 11.&#13;
Camargo B., Angelina. "La SEP edita doce veces mís ejemplares que&#13;
la iniciativa privada," (20 de febrero de 1981).&#13;
Cervantes, Lluis de.   "El exceso de petrodólares he, indigestadlo a&#13;
muchos pueblos, advierte Fernando Solana," Excélsior (Md'xico,&#13;
D.F.) (29 de mayo de 1981), pp. 19-A, 29.&#13;
Chavez de Pizano, Ramona.   "A pesar del esfuerzo del gobierno, hace&#13;
falta más dinero para educación," El Nacional (Mexico, D.F.) (2&#13;
de junio de 1981), p. 18.&#13;
"Datos reveladores obtiene la PF9 en una investigació'n sobre colegios&#13;
particulares," Metrópoli (Mexico, D.F.) (10 de junio de 1981), p.5.&#13;
"Debe legislarse para impedir abusos en la educación: Ortiz A,"&#13;
i,etrdpoli (Mlxico, D.F.) (10 de junio de 1981), p. 5.&#13;
"Educar es invertir,," Excélsior (México, D.F.) (29 de mayo de 1981),&#13;
p. 6-A.&#13;
"Eficaz método de la SEP que enseiWa a leer y escribir a adultos en&#13;
80 horas," El Nacional (M6xico, D.F.) (9 de junio de 1981),&#13;
P. 10.&#13;
"Fungirán como promotores de saLud en todo el pa&lt;s más de 400 mil&#13;
maestros," El Nacional (Mé'xico, D.F.) (8 de junio de 1981),&#13;
P. 14.&#13;
Gutierrez, Cuauhtemoc Anda. "45 millones de analfabetos," Excélsior&#13;
(México, D.F.) (30 de mayo de 1981), pp. 7-A, 8.&#13;
Ortega, Antonio. "Enseianza de baja calidad imparte el estado e&#13;
impone héroes: UNPF," Excélsior (México, D.F.) (31 de mayo de&#13;
1981), PP. 4-A, 7.&#13;
Ramos M., Aurelio.   "SEP y SPP estudian establecer sueldos diferenciales&#13;
para maestros del interior," Excélsior (México, D.F.) (29 de&#13;
mayo de 1981), p. 28-A.&#13;
Serrat, Oscar J. "En América latina hay más de 43 millones de&#13;
analfabetos," El Día Internacional (México, D.F,) (10 de junio&#13;
de 1981), p.,17.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-132-&#13;
Reference Library&#13;
The library of the National Technical Council for Education&#13;
(CNTE) contains numerous publications and articles written&#13;
about the free primary schoolbook program in Mexico.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG3881.5 .W57 W67 no.541 c.3     1&#13;
Neumann, Peter H.&#13;
Mexico's free textbooks :&#13;
nationalism and the urgency&#13;
to educate /&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters:&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK&#13;
Cable address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
European Office:&#13;
66, avenue d'léna&#13;
75116 Paris, France&#13;
Telephone: 723.54.21&#13;
Telex: 842-620628&#13;
Tokyo Office:&#13;
Kokusai Building&#13;
1-1, Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telephone: 214-5001&#13;
Telex: 781-26838&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0101-2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554898">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1982/01/1554898/mexicos-free-textbooks-nationalism-urgency-educate
        </url>
        <availablein>Spanish</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1982/01/1554898/mexicos-free-textbooks-nationalism-urgency-educate</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1982/01/1554898/mexicos-free-textbooks-nationalism-urgency-educate</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/26/000178830_9810190341402/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/26/000178830_9810190341402/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-07-26T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1982-01-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Mexico's free textbooks : nationalism
            and the urgency to educate
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This is a study of the Mexican
            experience with free primary school textbooks: their
            development, publication and distribution. It supplies free
            textbooks to all its children in the six grades of public
            and private primary schools. How the Government arrived at
            this decision twenty years ago and how the country mustered
            the political will and the resources to accomplish its
            ambitious goal, is described in this Study, written by
            experts in the field and based largely on Mexican sources.
            Textbooks often are the most cost effective means to upgrade
            academic achievement and increase the effectiveness of a
            school system. Good textbooks continue to be in short supply
            in most LDCs. The Study suggests ways to remedy this
            situation. It describes how Mexico met and essentially
            overcame the political, economical, and technical obstacles
            associated with large-scale national free textbook programs.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Mexico's free textbooks : nationalism
            and the urgency to educate
        </docna>
        <display_title>Libros de texto gratuitos en
            México: El nacionalismo y la urgencia por educar</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1982/01/1554898/mexicos-free-textbooks-nationalism-urgency-educate</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Curriculum &amp; Instruction,Gender and Education,Primary Education,Teaching and Learning</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Gender</teratopic>
        <count>Mexico</count>
        <authors>
            <author>NEUMANN, P.</author>
            <author>CUNNINGHAM, M.</author>
            <author>EDC</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>North America!$!80465</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_9810190341402</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Primary education</subsc>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 541</colti>
        <lang>Spanish</lang>
        <historic_topic>Gender</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Education</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Cost of education; Education; Educational
            policy; Primary education; Primary schools; Teaching aids; Textbooks
            absenteeism,academic
            achievement,achievement,achievements,addition,basic
            education,binding,climate,compulsory education,core
            curriculum,cost effectiveness,curriculum,developing
            countries,dialects,discrimination,Education,education
            budget,Education Programs,educational materials,Educational
            Media,Educational Planning,educators,effective
            means,exercises,free primary,free textbook,free
            textbooks,Health,illiteracy,indigenous languages,inservice
            training,Instruction,investment in
            education,isolation,leadership,learning,Let,level of
            education,Libraries,local authorities,local
            level,Malnutrition,manuals,Mathematics,motivation,PAPERS,parents,primary
            education,primary school,primary school teachers,primary
            school textbooks,primary schools,Printing,private primary
            schools,private sector,professional organizations,public
            institutions,pupils,quality of
            education,reading,retirement,rural schools,rural
            teachers,school attendance,school construction,secondary
            education,social studies,student performance,teacher,teacher
            development,teacher training,teachers,Teaching,teaching
            materials,tertiary education,textbook
            production,textbooks,Total Costs,Training of teachers,workbooks
        </keywd>
        <owner>LCS</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>North America</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP541</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutritional supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vitamins</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teacher Professional Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textbooks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Basic Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education Quality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Quality and Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Owned Enterprise Restructuring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teacher Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning Materials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplementary</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Price Controls</ml:concept><ml:concept>Price Controls </ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Primary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Secondary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Quality of Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprises</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Incentives</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Mexico</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>