<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Growth and Structural Change&#13;
in Large Low-Income Countries&#13;
Adrian Wood              SWP763&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 763&#13;
A Background Study&#13;
for&#13;
China: Long- Term Development Issues and Options&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Long-Term Development Issues and Options&#13;
Tbis report is suipplemented by six annex volumes publisbed by tbe World Bank:&#13;
I China: Issues and Prospects in Education&#13;
2 China: Agriculture to the Year 2000&#13;
3 China The Energy Sector&#13;
4 China Economic Model and Projections&#13;
5 China: Economic Structure in International Perspective&#13;
6 China: The Transport Sector&#13;
In addition, nine background papers, numbered bere as they are referred to in the&#13;
text, have been prepared in connection witb the report. They are available as&#13;
World Bank staff working papers.&#13;
I The Asian Experience in Rural Nonagricultural Developillent and Its&#13;
Relevance for China (Staff Vorking Paper 757)&#13;
2 International Experience in Urbanization and Its Relevance for China (Staff&#13;
Working Paper 758)&#13;
3 Alternative International Economic Strategies and Their Relevance for China&#13;
(Staff Working Paper 759)&#13;
4 Internarional Experience in Budgetary Trends during Econoinic&#13;
Development and Their Relevance for China (Staff WVorking Paper 760)&#13;
5 Productivity Growth and Technological Change In Chinese Industry (Staff&#13;
Working Paper 761)&#13;
6 Issues in the Technological Development of China's Electronics Sector (Staff&#13;
WVorking Paper 762)&#13;
7 The Environment for Technological Change in Centrally Planined Economies&#13;
(Staff WVorking Paper 7 18)&#13;
8 Managing Technological Development. Lessons from the Nev lv&#13;
Industrializing Countries (Staff NVorking Paper 717)&#13;
9 Growth and Structural Change in Large Lox-Income Countries (Staff&#13;
Working Paper 763)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 763                                  @O57&#13;
A Background Study                                 7&#13;
for&#13;
China: Long-Term Development Issues and Options         ,&#13;
Growth and Structural Change&#13;
in Large Low-Income Countries&#13;
Adrian Wood&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright (© 1986&#13;
The Intemational Bank for Reconsthuction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
AU rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing February 1986&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To present the&#13;
results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been prepared&#13;
in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formnal printed texts, and the World&#13;
Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a token charge&#13;
to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The World Bank does not accept responsibility for the views expressed herein, which&#13;
are those of the authors and should not be attributed to the World Bank or to its&#13;
affiliated organizations. The findings, interpretations, and conclusions are the results&#13;
of research supported by the Bank; they do not necessarily represent official policy of&#13;
the Bank. The designations employed, the presentation of material, and any maps used&#13;
in this document are solely for the convenience of the reader and do not imply the&#13;
expression of any opinion whatsoever on the part of the World Bank or its affiliates&#13;
conceming the legal status of any country, territory, city, area, or of its authorities, or&#13;
conceming the delimitation of its boundaries, or national affiliation.&#13;
The most recent World Bank publications are described in the annual spring and fall&#13;
lists; the continuing research program is described in the annual Abstracts of Current&#13;
Studies. The latest edition of each is available free of charge from the Publications Sales&#13;
Unit, Department T, The World Bank, 1818 H Street, N.W., Washington, D.C. 20433,&#13;
U.S.A., or from the European Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'1ena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Adrian Wood is a senior economist in the China Division of the World Bank's East&#13;
Asia and Pacific Regional Office.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging-in-Publication Data&#13;
Wood, Adrian,&#13;
Growth and structural change in large low-income&#13;
countries.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 763)&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
1. Developing countries--EcoDomic conditions--&#13;
Econometric models. I. China, long-term development&#13;
issues and options. II. Title. III. Series.&#13;
HC59.7.W645     1986     338.9'009172'4            86-1530&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0713-4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Abstract&#13;
This paper summarizes the results of empirical research on changes&#13;
in the structure of expenditure, production, employment and investment in the&#13;
course of economic development, with special reference to large countries at&#13;
low-to-middle income levels. It was written as background material for a&#13;
World Bank report on China (China: Long-Term Development Issues and Options,&#13;
1985). All the studies surveyed, however, relate to other developing&#13;
countries. The objective was to identify regularities in the pattern of&#13;
structural change elsewhere that might be relevant to China's future&#13;
development. The paper is intended to be intelligible to readers previously&#13;
unacquainted with the studies surveyed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Sectoral Definitions&#13;
The term primary sectors covers agriculture and mining. Light&#13;
manufacturing includes food processing, textiles and clothing, wood, paper and&#13;
printing and miscellaneous manufacturing. Heavy manufacturing includes&#13;
metallurgy, chemicals, building materials (nonmetallic minerals), metal&#13;
products and machinery. Infrastructure is construction, transport and&#13;
electricity, gas and water. Services includes commerce, education and health,&#13;
public administration and defense, finance and other business services,&#13;
community and personal services, and housing. The term goods refers to&#13;
agricultural, mining and manufactured products, the term nontradeables to&#13;
infrastructure plus services.&#13;
Acknowledgements&#13;
The author is extremely grateful to Moshe Syrquin for providing&#13;
unpublished data, answering many questions of fact and interpretation, and&#13;
commenting on earlier drafts of this paper and related material. Valuable&#13;
comments and suggestions were also received from Irma Adelman, Hollis Chenery,&#13;
Sherman Robinson, Gene Tidrick, and participants in a seminar organized by the&#13;
Chinese Academy of Social Sciences and chaired by Sun Shangqing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
The Chenery-Syrquin Model ...............    .        1&#13;
Investment and Consumption ...      ...      .        6&#13;
Foreign Trade ....................................................  12&#13;
Input-Output Relationships  .......         .        15&#13;
Production Structure          ..       .     .       17&#13;
Labor Productivity and Employment  .    .    .       25&#13;
Capital S to ck .................................................. .  32&#13;
Sources of Growth  .. ................ ............. .  39&#13;
Trends at Hig her I ncome Levels          ..         45&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
GROWTH AND STRUCTURAL CHANGE IN LARGE LOW-INCOME COUNTRIES&#13;
This paper summarizes the results of empirical research on changes&#13;
in the structure of expenditure, production, employment, and investment in the&#13;
course of economic development. These results have been obtained by analyzing&#13;
two quite different sorts of data: time series, which record the changes that&#13;
have occurred as income has risen in particular countries or groups of&#13;
countries; and cross-sections, which compare the structures of economies at&#13;
different levels of development at a particular moment in time. The data and&#13;
the studies based on them also relate to a wide range of countries (including&#13;
some socialist countries) and historical periods, many of which exhibit&#13;
important and interesting special features. But despite the variety of the&#13;
material analyzed, certain common patterns of change (including systematic&#13;
variation with country size and level of development) quite consistently&#13;
emerge. In what follows, particular attention will be given to the typical&#13;
pattern for large countries at low-to-middle income levels.&#13;
The Chenery-Syrquin Model&#13;
Although other studies will be referred to, the results of much&#13;
research are conveniently encapsulated in a single source, the general model&#13;
of industrialization developed by Professors Hollis Chenery and Moshe Syrquin&#13;
[Chenery 1979; Chenery and Syrquin 1980; Chenery, Robinson and Syrquin (CRS),&#13;
1986]. The model describes and quantifies the process of growth and&#13;
structural change for a typical country in the following way.&#13;
(a) Drawing on various statistical studies, the composition of final&#13;
demand is related to (per capita national) income; this determines&#13;
both the allocation of demand among broad categories such as&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
consumption, investment and exports, and the allocation within these&#13;
categories among sectors such as agriculture, textiles, and&#13;
machinery.&#13;
(b) The resulting pattern of final demand at any given income level is&#13;
then combined with a typical input-output table (whose structure&#13;
varies with the level of income) to generate demand for intermediate&#13;
inputs and the sectoral composition of gross and net output.&#13;
(c) Coefficients reflecting typical capital and labor input requirements&#13;
(which also vary with the level of income) are then applied to&#13;
sectoral output levels to determine the size and sectoral&#13;
composition of the capital stock and of employment.&#13;
(d) The amount of investment--determined in step (a)--and exogenous&#13;
population and labor force growth, together with typical changes in&#13;
capital and labor productivity, then cause an increase in income to&#13;
a new level, at which the whole process is repeated.&#13;
In this fashion, starting from the lowest income level for which the&#13;
underlying data are thought to be reasonably reliable (about $300 at 1981&#13;
prices), the model traces a path of rising income and changing structure, up&#13;
to the income level of a developed country. We shall focus here only on the&#13;
range of immediate relevance to China, namely from $300 to $1,200. Tables 1-3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 1. CHENERY-SYROUIN LARGE COUNTRY MODEL RESULTS&#13;
Per Capita GNP = US$300 (1981 dollars)&#13;
Private    Govt.&#13;
consump-  consump-   Invest-                         Final      Int.      Gross      Net&#13;
tion      tion      ment     Exports    Imports    demand    demand    output     output&#13;
1.   Agriculture                 56.0       0.3        0.0      20.7       4.5       72.5      38.2       110.7      93.2&#13;
2.   Mining                       0.2        0.3       0.0       1.3        0.8       0.9       7.4         8.3       6.2&#13;
3.   Food processing             34.1        1.6       0.0       0.7        3.4      33.0      22.5        55.5      17.0&#13;
4a.  Textile, clothing, etc.     20.1        0.5       0.0       3.1        3.3      20.4      10.4        30.8      14.4&#13;
4b.  Wood, paper, other mfg.      4.4        0.8       0.0       0.5        1.3       4.3       11.6       15.8       7.0&#13;
5a.  Chemicals, etc.              4.3        0.4       0.0       0.2        6.3      -1.4       9.5         8.1       4.2   W&#13;
5b.  Nonmetallic minerals         0.8        0.0       0.0       0.2        0.6       0.4       4.0         4.4       3.1&#13;
5c.  Metals                       1.3        0.2       0.0       0.6        2.5      -0.5       10.5       10.0       3.8&#13;
6.   Machinery                    0.5        0.3      17.0       0.0       11.8       6.0       4.1        10.2       5.3&#13;
7a.  Construction                 0.0        0.6      27.7       0.0        0.0      28.3        5.3       33.6      15.5&#13;
7b.  Electricity, etc.            5.0        0.3       0.0       0.0        0.0       5.3        2.7        8.0       5.3&#13;
7c.  Transport                   10.5        1.3       0.2       2.1        2.0      12.1        9.4       21.5      15.3&#13;
8a.  Commerce                    45.5        0.3       2.5       5.4        5.0      48.7       12.2       60.9      50.4&#13;
8b.  Housing                     12.4        0.3       0.0       0.0        0.0      12.7        2.5       15.2      13.2&#13;
8c.  Other services              32.7       24.5       0.0       0.0        0.0      57.3       15.4       72.6      46.3&#13;
Total                 227.7      31.8       47.3      34.7      41.5      300.0     165.6      465.5      300.0&#13;
Source:  Special tabulation of unpublished data, adjusted to 1981 prices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 2. CHENERY-SYRQUIN LARGE COUNTRY MODEL RESULTS&#13;
Per Capita GNP = US$600 (1981 dollars)&#13;
Private    Govt.&#13;
consump-  consump-   Invest-                         Final      Int.     Gross       Net&#13;
tion      tion      ment     Exports    Imports   demand     demand    output    output&#13;
1.   Agriculture                 74.9       0.7       0.0       27.5      10.8      92.3      72.7       165.0     126.2&#13;
2.   Mining                       0.6       0.7        0.0       2.4       2.7       1.1       20.0       21.0      15.6&#13;
3.   Food processing             67.5       3.5        0.0       2.3       6,2      67.1       48.8      115.9      35.5&#13;
4a.  Textile, clothing, etc.     40.8       1l1        0.0       8.8       3,9      46.9       28,1       75.0      35.2&#13;
4b,  Wood; paper, other mfg.     10.7        1.7       0,0       2.9       2.2      13.0       32,2       45.2      19.9&#13;
5a.  Chemicals, etc.              9,8       0.8        0.0       1.7      12,1       0.2       2801       28,2      13.7&#13;
5b.  Nonmetallic minerals         1,5       0,0        0,0       008       1,0        1.3      11,4       12.6       8.8&#13;
5c.  Metals                       4,2       0,3        0.0       3.1       5.4       2.2       33.4       35,5      13.7&#13;
6.   Machinery                    1.5       0,7       43,2       0.5      21,3      24,6       12,2       3608      19.2&#13;
7a,  Construction                 0.0       1,4       70.4       0.0       0.0      71,7       13.2       84,9      39.2&#13;
7b. Electricity, etc.            10,5       0.7        0,0       0.0       0,0      11.3        6,6       17,9      11,9&#13;
7c,  Transport                   22,5       2,8        0.6       4.8       3.8      26,9       21,9       48,8      34.7&#13;
8a.  Commerce                    84,4       0.7        6,3      12,4       9,6      94.1       27,1      121,3     100,3&#13;
8b.  Housing                     24,2       0,7        0.0       0.0       0.0      24,9        5,0       29.9      25,8&#13;
8c. Other services               68.8      53,9        0,0       0.0       0,0     122,7       34,6      157,3     100.2&#13;
Total                 421,9      69.7     120,5       67.0      79.1     600.0      395.2      995,2     600,0&#13;
Source:  Special tabulation of unpublished data, adjusted to 1981 prices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 3. CHENERY-SYRQUIN LARGE COUNTRY MODEL RESULTS&#13;
Per Capita GNP = US$1,200 (1981 dollars)&#13;
Private    Govt.&#13;
consump-   consump-  Invest-                          Final      Int.      Gross       Net&#13;
tion      tion       ment     Exports   Imports    demand     demand    output     output&#13;
1.   Agriculture                  96.1       1.6       0.0       32.4       25.4     104.7       131.5      236.2     161.1&#13;
2.   Mining                        2.7       1.6        0.0       4.2       10.0      -1.5        49.2      47.7       35.6&#13;
3.   Food processing             129.2       7.7        0.0       6.7       11.1     132.5       100.6      233.2      71.3&#13;
4a.  Textile, clothing, etc.      80.9       2.5        0.0      17.6        4.8      96.3        63.9      160.1      75.4&#13;
4b.  Wood, paper, other mfg.      26.7       3.6        0.0      12.3        4.1      38.6        82.4      121.1      53.2&#13;
5a.  Chemicals, etc.              22.7       1.7        0.0       6.2       22.8       7.9        71.5      79.4       38.0    '&#13;
5b.  Nonmetallic minerals          2.6       0.0        0.0       2.9        1.6       3.8        27.5      31.3       21.8&#13;
5c.  Metals                       13.0       0.7        0.0       9.1       11.3      11.4        94.2      105.7      40.7&#13;
6.   Machinery                     4.3       1.6       98.1       7.9       39.8      72.0        33.2      105.2      55.0&#13;
7a.  Construction                  0.0       3.1      159.9       0.0        0.0     i62.9        28.6      191.5      88.3&#13;
7b.  Electricity, etc.            21.7       1.6        0.0       0.0        0.0      23.3        14.8      38.0       25.2&#13;
7c.  Transport                    46.6       6.2        1.3      10.9        7.5      57.4        47.8      105.2      74.8&#13;
8a.  Commerce                    158.2       1.6       14.4      28.0       19.1     183.0        56.2      239.3     197.9&#13;
8b.  Housing                      45.8       1.6        0.0       0.0        0.0      47.4         9.5      56.9       49.1&#13;
8c.  Other services              140.4     119.7        0.0       0.0        0.0     260.1        73.4      333.5     212.6&#13;
Total                 790.9      154.9     273.6      138.0     157.4    1,200.0      884.2     2,084.2   1,200&#13;
Source:   Special tabulation of unpublished data, adjusted to 1981 prices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
present the pattern of expenditure and output generated by the model at each&#13;
of these three income levels.l/&#13;
Before examining these tables, some general qualifications and&#13;
limitations should be mentioned. The large-country version of the model, from&#13;
which all the results in this paper are drawn, relates to a country of only 40&#13;
million people, and does not take explicit account of geographical aspects of&#13;
size. The model emphasizes the development of manufacturing industry, with&#13;
less attention to energy, agriculture, infrastructure and services. No&#13;
account is taken in the model of changes in prices in the course of develop-&#13;
ment. The data on which the model is based were drawn mainly from nonsocialist&#13;
countries in the 1950s and 1960s. For these and other reasons to be discussed&#13;
later, the numbers generated by the model should be interpreted as indicating&#13;
no more than the approximate magnitude of the structural changes experienced&#13;
in the course of development.&#13;
Investment and Consumption&#13;
As income rises, the share of it that is used for saving and invest-&#13;
ment tends to increase. From Tables 1-3 (in which all items are expressed in&#13;
1981 dollars per capita), it can be calculated that domestic savings as a&#13;
share of GDP rise from 14 percent at an income level of $300 to 21 percent at&#13;
/1   The Chenery-Syrquin model was originally calibrated in 1964 US dollars,&#13;
which for the purposes of this paper have been roughly converted into&#13;
1981 US dollars by multiplying by a factor of 3 based on the US GDP&#13;
deflator (Chenery and Syrquin 1975, footnote on p. 22). At higher income&#13;
levels than those considered in this paper, it would be necessary to&#13;
apply larger conversion factors, since between 1964 and 1981 the exchange&#13;
rates of rich couxtries have, on average, appreciated substantially&#13;
relative to those of poor countries. In other words, the proportional&#13;
income gap between rich and poor countries (in any given year) appears&#13;
much larger--approximately twice as large--when measured in 1981 dollars&#13;
than when measured in 1964 dollars.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
$1,200. Since the net inflow of foreign capital remains at about 2 percent of&#13;
GDP, this causes (fixed plus inventory) investment to rise from 16 percent to&#13;
23 percent of GDP. Government consumption of goods and services (excluding&#13;
transfer payments such as unemployment benefits) also rises, from 11 percent&#13;
to 13 percent of GDP. The share of household consumption correspondingly&#13;
declines--from 76 percent to 66 percent of GDP--although in absolute per&#13;
capita terms it increases three-and-a-half times.&#13;
The updating and extension of the earlier statistical studies that&#13;
underlie the Chenery-Syrquin model, incorporating data for the 1970s and early&#13;
1980s (Syrquin 1985), closely confirms this pattern of change in domestic&#13;
saving, government consumption and household consumption.2- But the pattern&#13;
of foreign capital inflows, and hence the relationship between saving and&#13;
investment, has changed. Capital inflows have become much larger, especially&#13;
at low income levels (6 percent of GDP at an income level of $300, declining&#13;
to 3 percent at $2,500). Hence investment rates are also higher, and the&#13;
difference in investment rates between low-income and middle-income countries&#13;
has diminished.&#13;
The sectoral composition of investment (the mix of construction,&#13;
equipment and so on) and of government consumption is assumed in the Chenery-&#13;
Syrquin model, on the basis of available evidence, not to change systemati-&#13;
cally in the course of development. The composition of household consumption,&#13;
however, does change significantly. Considering only goods (sectors 1-6) to&#13;
begin with, the share of food (sectors 1 plus 3) declines from 74 percent at&#13;
2/   This updating is being undertaken in World Bank Research Project&#13;
RPO 673-51. Preliminary results for large countries are tabulated in&#13;
Annex E of China: Long-Term Issues and Options (World Bank 1985), as&#13;
well as in Syrquin 1985.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
an income level of $300 to 60 percent at $1,200, while the share of processed&#13;
food--sector 3--in total food consumption rises by 20 percentage points.&#13;
Among the nonfood items, substantial increases are observed for textiles and&#13;
clothing (from 16 percent to 21 percent), wood, paper and miscellaneous&#13;
manufactures (from 4 percent to 7 percent of all goods consumed), machinery&#13;
(from 2 percent to 5 percent), and chemicals (from 4 percent to 6 percent).&#13;
Changes in the consumption of nontradeables (sectors 7-8), and in&#13;
the allocation of consumption between goods and services, are obscured in&#13;
Tables 1-3 (as in most input-output tables) by the use of producer prices&#13;
rather than retail prices, which means that "consumption" of transport and&#13;
commerce consists mainly of the transport and commercial margins on other&#13;
items consumed. Nonetheless, we can see from these tables that there are&#13;
small increases (about half a percentage point each) in the shares of elec-&#13;
tricity and housing in total consumption, and a considerable increase&#13;
(from 14 percent to 18 percent of total consumption) in the share of other&#13;
services.&#13;
This impression of a rising share of nontradeables in household con-&#13;
sumption is confirmed--at current retail prices--by the work of Kravis&#13;
(1983). In 1975, the share of nontradeables in consumption in his Group I&#13;
countries (whose per capita GNP at 1981 prices averaged $390) was 24 percent,&#13;
compared with 32 percent in his Group II countries (with an average income of&#13;
$1,230). However, Kravis is also able to calculate that much of the differ-&#13;
ence is due to higher prices of nontradeables, relative to goods, in the Group&#13;
II countries: at constant prices, the difference in shares is only 4 percent-&#13;
age points. This phenomenon--a marked rise in the relative price of many&#13;
nontradeables as income increases--is observed in time series as well as&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
cross-section data, and at all levels of development.31 (Its causes are&#13;
discussed below).&#13;
The work of Kravis (1982) on the composition and determinants of&#13;
expenditures in countries at different levels of development also includes a&#13;
more detailed breakdown of consumption of goods and services. The first two&#13;
columns of Table 4 compare the shares of about 25 categories of consumption in&#13;
total consumption, measured at current prices, in Kravis's Groups I and II&#13;
countries. In examining these shares, it should be borne in mind that Kravis&#13;
defines total consumption to include public expenditures on education, health&#13;
care and recreational services; that many of the categories cannot be directly&#13;
compared with those in Tables 1-3 (for example, both transport and recreation&#13;
are mixtures of equipment purchases and service purchases); and that each&#13;
group contains only a small sample of countries.&#13;
The marked decline in the share of food is similar to that predicted&#13;
by the Chenery-Syrquin model over a comparable income range: Table 4 shows&#13;
that it is mainly due to a decline in the share of bread and grain, although&#13;
the shares of all other foodstuffs except meat also decline. The share of&#13;
clothing and footwear increases much less than the Chenery-Syrquin model&#13;
predicts (and Table 4 shows that almost all of the increase is attributable to&#13;
footwear); but the modest increases in the housing and fuel shares, and the&#13;
substantial increase in the share of other services, conform with the model&#13;
results. The increases in Table 4 in the shares of furniture and consumer&#13;
/3   At constant prices, Kravis concludes that the share of nontradeables in&#13;
total final demand does not change much in the course of development.&#13;
The share in household consumption rises somewhat, but is offset by a&#13;
declining share of nontradeables in investment and government&#13;
expenditures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
Table 4. COMPOSITION OF CONSUMPTION AT DIFFERENT PER CAPITA INCOME LEVELS&#13;
Percentage shares of         Difference in       Estimated "income elasticity of&#13;
total consumption /a         relative  rice       quantity demanded;" based on&#13;
Group I /b   Group II 7c       Groups I-II  d       data for all Groups (I-V) /e&#13;
($390)         ($1,230)&#13;
Food&#13;
=read, grain                   19.5          10.5               1.12               0.06&#13;
Meat                          4.6           6.8              0.99                1.24&#13;
Fish                          3.6           1.8              0.88                0.47&#13;
Milk, eggs &amp; cheese           4.7           3.8              0.73                0.74&#13;
Oil, fat                      2.7           1.8              0.68                0.74&#13;
Fruits &amp;-vegetables          10.0          8.5               1.08                0.46&#13;
Coffee, tea &amp; cocoa           0.8          0.8               0.82                0.97&#13;
Spices, sweets &amp; sugar        5.0          3.7               0.70                0.87&#13;
Subtotal                50.9         37.7               0.96               0.69      0.65*    0.66**&#13;
Beverages                       3.1          3.0               1.01                1.08&#13;
Tobacco                         2.7           3.1              0.66                1.00&#13;
Clothing. Footwear&#13;
Clothing                      6.7          6.8               0.84                1.02              0.97**&#13;
Footwear                      0.8           1.6              1.01                1.22&#13;
Subtotal                 7.5          8.3               0.86                1.04     1.07*&#13;
RentA Fuel&#13;
Rent                          5.1           6.5              1.06                1.40&#13;
Fuel &amp; electricity            2.9           3.2              0.77                1.15&#13;
Subtotal                 8.0          9.7               0.95                1.28     1.35*    1.n1**&#13;
Household Goods &amp; Services&#13;
Furniture &amp; appliances        1.7           2.8              1.06                1.45&#13;
Other goods &amp; services        3.6          3.1               1.07                0.95&#13;
Subtotal                 5.4          5.9               1.16                1.28&#13;
Transport &amp; Communications&#13;
Equipment                     0.9           1.6              0.70                1.91               1.98**&#13;
Operating cost                1.7          2.7               0.68                1.24&#13;
Purchased transport           2.7           4.5              1.24                0.84&#13;
Communications                0.3          0.4               0.42                1.65&#13;
Subtotal                 5.6          9.2               0.93                1.36              2.46**&#13;
Recreation. Education /a&#13;
Recreation                    2.8           3.7              0.93                1.40              1.81**&#13;
Education                     5.2          5.6               1.46                0.54&#13;
Subtotal                 8.0          9.3               1.36               0.94&#13;
Other Services&#13;
Personal care                 1.5           2.7              1.09                1.31               1.53**&#13;
Miscellaneous /f              3.7           7.3              0.84                1.42               1.79**&#13;
Subtotal                 5.2          9.9               0.89                1.37&#13;
Total                  100.0        100.0               0.98                -&#13;
/a  Includes public expenditures on education, health care and recreational services.     All valued at current&#13;
purchasers' prices.&#13;
/b Unweighted average of Malawi, Kenya, India, Pakistan, Sri Lanka, Zambia, Thailand, Philippines, all in&#13;
1975.&#13;
/c Unweighted average of the Republic of Korea, Malaysia, Colombia, Jamaica, Syria, Brazil, all in 1975.&#13;
7T  Ratio of relative price in Group II to relative price in Group I.     Prices in each case measured relative&#13;
to GDP, not to total consumption.&#13;
/e Proportional increase in quantity of item consumed divided by proportional increase in total real&#13;
consumption, corrected for the effect of changes in the relative prices of different items. The numbers&#13;
marked * are for Asian countries alone; those marked ** are from a different source (Lluch, Powell, and&#13;
Williams 1977) and are averages for four middle-income developing economies.&#13;
/f Includes restaurants and hotels.&#13;
Source:   Kravis (1982), Tables 6-6, 6-9, 9-3 and 9-5.    Failure of individual items to add to subtotals and&#13;
totals is due to rounding errors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
appliances, and of transport equipment, are likewise consistent with the&#13;
increases in Tables 1-3 in the shares of other light manufacturing and&#13;
machinery. There is also (in Table 4) a sharp increase in the share of&#13;
purchased transport services.&#13;
Some of these differences in expenditure shares between Groups I and&#13;
II are probably attributable to the differences in relative prices shown in&#13;
column 3 of Table 4, some of which (like higher prices for many nontrade-&#13;
ables)4/ may be a normal consequence of higher per capita income, but others&#13;
of which reflect circumstances--including natural resource endowments and tax&#13;
and subsidy policies--peculiar to the samples of countries in these groups.&#13;
Moreover, such differences in relative prices have two opposing effects on the&#13;
expenditure shares: a higher price for a given item will, on the one hand,&#13;
tend to raise the expenditure share associated with a particular quantity of&#13;
purchases; but will on the other hand, tend to cause consumers to purchase a&#13;
smaller quantity. Considerable interest is thus attached to the "income&#13;
elasticity" numbers in the last column of Table 4, which are estimates of the&#13;
effect of higher real income on the quantity of purchases in each of these&#13;
categories at given (unchanging) relative prices: a value of 1.5, for&#13;
example, means that a 10 percent increase in real income would tend to cause a&#13;
15 percent increase in the quantity of the item in question purchased. These&#13;
estimates are derived from data on countries at all income levels (ranging&#13;
from Malawi to the United States), and may thus be thought of as pertaining to&#13;
middle-income countries. It is possible that income elasticities are&#13;
4/ "Other services" in Table 4 are an exception to this generalization.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
significantly different at lower income levels, although Kravis (1982,&#13;
Chapter 9) found only modest differences between country groupings.&#13;
In any event, what the estimated elasticities in Table 4 indicate is&#13;
that demand for food on average grows more slowly than income: demand for&#13;
bread and grain in particular scarcely increases, and meat is the only food&#13;
item for which demand grows faster than income. Demand for clothing, another&#13;
large category, grows only slightly faster than income. By contrast, consumer&#13;
demand for housing, furniture and consumer appliances, transport (especially&#13;
personal transport equipment), recreation (including equipment), and other&#13;
services increases 30-40 percent faster than income. So does demand for&#13;
medical goods and services (although these estimates include public expendi-&#13;
tures, as do the estimates for education, which has a surprisingly low income&#13;
elasticity).&#13;
Foreign Trade&#13;
The data in Tables 1-3 suggest that in large countries the relative&#13;
importance of foreign trade does not change significantly as per capita income&#13;
rises: the ratios of exports and imports to CDP (11-12 percent and 13-14 per-&#13;
cent, respectively) are much the same at $1,200 as at $300. This conclusion,&#13;
which contrasts with the increasing importance of trade in the course of&#13;
development in smaller (and typically more open) economies, is supported by&#13;
Table 5, which presents data for the nine most populous countries in the world&#13;
(other than the USSR, for which comparable statistics are not available).&#13;
Both in 1981 and in 1960, there is considerable variation, independent of&#13;
income; if China is excluded, a slight tendency for the export share to rise&#13;
with income level can be detected in 1981 (for the four poorest countries it&#13;
averages 13.5 percent, for the four richest 14.8 percent), but not in 1960.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
Table 5. EXPORT SHARE OF LARGE COUNTRIES, RANKED BY INCOME LEVEL&#13;
Exports/a as&#13;
GNP per capita       Population      percentage of GDP&#13;
1981 ($)       1981 (millions)      1960     1981&#13;
Bangladesh                140                 91              10         7&#13;
India                     260                690               5        7&#13;
China                     300                991               4        9&#13;
Pakistan                  350                 85               8       12&#13;
Indonesia                 530                150              13       28&#13;
Nigeria                   870                 88              15       25&#13;
Brazil                  2,220                121               5        9&#13;
Japan                  10,080                118              11       15&#13;
US                     12,820                230               5       10&#13;
/a  Of goods and nonfactor services (which are things such as earnings from&#13;
transportation and tourism, as distinct from factor services and transfers&#13;
such as receipts of interest and remittances).&#13;
Source: World Development Report, 1983, Indicators Table 5.&#13;
The table also shows, however, that export shares have tended to&#13;
rise significantly over time in large countries (as in smaller countries) at&#13;
all income levels: again excluding China, the average for these large&#13;
countries in 1960 was 9 percent, and in 1981 14 percent. This marked upward&#13;
shift in trade ratios emerges also from the updating work of Syrquin (1985)&#13;
mentioned earlier: over the income range $300-$1,500, the predicted ratio of&#13;
exports to GDP for a country of 60 million people around 1980/81 was&#13;
16-17 percent, rising to nearly 18 percent at an income level of $2,500.&#13;
Although increases in income level do not much affect the overall&#13;
weight of foreign trade in large countries, it can be seen from Tables 1-3&#13;
that they do bring about significant changes in its composition. In exports,&#13;
the share of primary (especially agricultural) products in the total drops&#13;
sharply, from 63 percent at an income level of $300 to 27 percent at $1,200.&#13;
This is matched by a sharp rise in the share of manufactured exports, from&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
15 percent to 45 percent.51 (Higher oil prices have subsequently somewhat&#13;
altered these magnitudes: but the marked shift from primary to manufactured&#13;
exports in the course of development is a pattern that persists--Syrquin&#13;
1985). Within manufactured exports, the relative importance of processed food&#13;
and textile products declines (although their share of total exports&#13;
increases, from 11 percent to 18 percent), with a corresponding rise in the&#13;
relative importance of other light manufactures (1 percent to 9 percent) and&#13;
heavy manufactures (3 percent to 19 percent), including machinery (zero to&#13;
6 percent).&#13;
The composition of imports appears to change less. The Chenery-&#13;
Syrquin large-country model predicts an increase in the share of primary&#13;
imports--both mining and agricultural--from 13 percent at an income level of&#13;
$300 to 22 percent at $1,200. (Although the corresponding numbers have become&#13;
much larger since the early 1970s, because of higher oil prices, the share of&#13;
primary products in total imports still does not appear to change much as&#13;
income levels rise--Syrquin 1985.) But the level and pattern of primary&#13;
imports in any particular country clearly depends on natural resource endow-&#13;
ments, especially of primary energy and agricultural land, as well as on&#13;
policies for developing these resources. Among manufactured imports, the only&#13;
significant compositional changes in Table 1-3 are the declines in textile&#13;
products (from 8 percent to 3 percent of total imports) and in machinery (from&#13;
28 percent to 25 percent), although the latter is still the single largest&#13;
import category. There is little change in the other main categories of manu-&#13;
/5 Primary and manufactured exports do not sum to total exports because of&#13;
''service exports" which (because these data are at producer prices)&#13;
consist partly of transport and trade margins on other exports.&#13;
Similarly for imports.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
factured imports--processed food (7-8 percent of total imports), chemicals&#13;
(14-15 percent) and metals (6-7 percent).&#13;
Looking at the trade balances sector-by-sector, Tables 1-3 suggest&#13;
that the income transition from $300 to $1,200 involves a sharply reduced&#13;
export surplus in primary products (from nearly 6 percent of GDP to virtually&#13;
zero). The deficit in manufactured trade widens in absolute terms (from $24&#13;
per capita to $33), but diminishes sharply as a share of GDP (from 8 percent&#13;
to 3 percent). A small surplus on trade in services emerges (from zero to&#13;
1 percent of GDP).&#13;
In interpreting these particular Chenery-Syrquin model results, it&#13;
should be borne in mind that foreign trade has been found to be the least&#13;
uniform feature of structure and structural change. Depending on natural&#13;
resources and development strategy (openness to trade and borrowing), as well&#13;
as on size, the level and composition of exports and imports varies quite&#13;
widely among countries at similar income levels.&#13;
Input-Output Relationships&#13;
The evolution of production structure depends not only on the&#13;
changing patterns of domestic final demand (consumption and investment) and&#13;
foreign trade, but also, and to an increasing degree, on the need for inter-&#13;
mediate inputs--goods and services which are used up in the production&#13;
process. One important aspect of intermediate usage is the relationship&#13;
between gross output and net output (gross output less intermediate purchases)&#13;
in individual production sectors. The Chenery-Syrquin model assumes, in&#13;
accordance with most of the limited available evidence, that net-to-gross&#13;
output ratios in all sectors but one remain constant as per capita income&#13;
rises. The exception is agriculture, where the net-to-gross output ratio&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
declines substantially in the course of modernization: in the income range&#13;
($300-$1,200) covered by Tables 1-3, it falls from 84 percent to 68 percent.&#13;
It should be added that the ratios in the other sectors, though they do not&#13;
individually change, are by no means uniform (31 percent in food processing,&#13;
52 percent in machinery, 74 percent in mining, and 83 percent in commerce, to&#13;
take four specific examples), as a result of which the average net-to-gross&#13;
output ratio changes in the course of development also because of changes in&#13;
the relative sizes of different sectors.&#13;
Another important aspect of input-output relationships concerns the&#13;
level of intermediate demand by other sectors for the output of particular&#13;
sectors. This also varies from one sector to another (for example, being&#13;
higher relative to total demand in basic metals than in agriculture). In&#13;
addition, the Chenery-Syrquin model embodies the spirit of earlier empirical&#13;
research on input-output tables by making intermediate use of the output of&#13;
particular sectors (row coefficients), rise in sectors with above-average&#13;
output growth and decline in sectors with below-average output growth. Thus,&#13;
for example, the share of basic metals in intermediate usage in each sector&#13;
rises in the course of development, but the share of agricultural products&#13;
declines.&#13;
Although the importance of intermediate production increases&#13;
substantially as income rises, because of changes in the composition of output&#13;
and alterations in particular input-output coefficients, the average "density"&#13;
of the input-output coefficient matrix (as measured by, for example, the&#13;
average size or sum of all the coefficients) in the Chenery-Syrquin model&#13;
remains constant, with the exception--mentioned above--of the increasing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
coefficients in the agriculture column.61 This is consistent with the&#13;
findings of Kubo (1981, Table 1), who observed constancy or slight increases&#13;
over periods of 10-25 years in the average density of coefficient matrices in&#13;
a sample of eight middle-income developing economies, plus Norway. It also&#13;
conforms with the findings of Stern and Lewis (1980), based on the income-&#13;
level-specific input-output tables developed by Leontief for the UN world&#13;
model, which imply that the increase in average coefficient density over a&#13;
wide per capita income range is relatively small.&#13;
However, only a limited amount of empirical research has been done&#13;
on changes in input-output relationships in the course of economic develop-&#13;
ment, especially at low-income levels (where there may be more significant&#13;
increases in average coefficient density). The input-output matrix of the&#13;
Chenery-Syrquin model is thus a comparatively weak link, whose shortcomings&#13;
probably contribute to some of the deviations (discussed below) between the&#13;
model's predictions and direct observation at the bottom of its income range.&#13;
Production Structure&#13;
These various changes in the pattern of domestic, foreign and inter-&#13;
mediate demand tend to generate changes in the pattern of production. It is&#13;
clear that all of them will contribute to a marked rise in the share of manu-&#13;
facturing output and a corresponding decline in agriculture: this is partic-&#13;
ularly true of the rising share of investment, the declining share of food in&#13;
household consumption, the increasing share of manufactures in total exports,&#13;
/6   Increased average density increases the total amount of intermediate&#13;
demand generated by any given pattern of final demand. Constant density,&#13;
by contrast, means that changes in the total amount of intermediate&#13;
demand are due solely to changes in the level and pattern of final&#13;
demand.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
and changes in the pattern of input-output coefficients. What will happen to&#13;
the nontradeable sectors' output is less immediately obvious, but there is&#13;
some presumption that the output shares of both infrastructure and services&#13;
will increase in response to changed consumer and intermediate demand.&#13;
Looking first at the behavior of gross output in the Chenery-Syrquin&#13;
model, it can be calculated from Tables 1-3 that the share of the primary&#13;
sectors in the total declines by 12 percentage points over the income range&#13;
$300-$1,200, entirely because of a drop in the share of agriculture (mining&#13;
increases slightly), and even though agricultural output per capita more than&#13;
doubles in absolute terms. The share of manufacturing increases almost&#13;
equally sharply, by 11 percentage points, with a particularly marked rise in&#13;
the share of heavy manufactures (8 percentage points), especially basic metals&#13;
and machinery (in each case, a 3-percentage-point increase). The share of&#13;
nontradeables (infrastructure plus services) rises very slightly, with small&#13;
declines in commerce and housing offset by small increases in other sectors.&#13;
Since net-to-gross output ratios in all sectors but agriculture&#13;
remain constant, the pattern of changes in net output shares in the Chenery-&#13;
Syrquin model is fairly similar--although changing sectoral composition&#13;
contributes to a decline in the aggregate net-to-gross output ratio from&#13;
64 percent at an income level of $300 to 58 percent at $1,200. The share of&#13;
agriculture declines somewhat more steeply (17 percentage points), while that&#13;
of industry again increases by 11 percentage points, with heavy manufactures,&#13;
which are more intermediate-intensive, accounting for rather less (but still&#13;
two thirds) of the increase. The share of nontradeables, which have a&#13;
comparatively high net-to-gross output ratio, increases by considerably more&#13;
(5 percentage points), two thirds of which is accounted for by infrastructure.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
Total net output growth can also be decomposed in such a way as to&#13;
show the relative importance for each sector (and in aggregate) of the&#13;
different sources of demand discussed earlier. Table 6 presents the relevant&#13;
data for the Chenery-Syrquin large-country model in the income range $300-&#13;
$1,200. In each sector (especially nontradeables), and in aggregate, growth&#13;
of domestic final demand is by far the largest component, but export expansion&#13;
accounts for a significant part of primary output growth, with changes in&#13;
input-output coefficients pulling in the opposite direction. Export growth&#13;
and changes in input-output coefficients are significant sources of demand&#13;
expansion in both light and heavy manufacturing, with import substitution as a&#13;
significant additional source for heavy manufacturing. The importance of&#13;
foreign trade and input-output coefficient changes appears greater when the&#13;
contribution of different sources of demand to deviations from equipropor-&#13;
tional output growth in all sectors (that is, to structural change) is calcu-&#13;
lated. In this income range, domestic final demand accounts for only 59 per-&#13;
cent of the downward deviation of primary sector growth from overall growth,&#13;
and for only 10 percent and 27 percent respectively of the upward deviations&#13;
of light and heavy manufacturing growth from the average (Chenery 1979,&#13;
pp. 124-125, averaging the first two periods).&#13;
Comparison of the Chenery-Syrquin model results with other data on&#13;
changes in production structure confirms their general accuracy, but reveals&#13;
some shortcomings. Considering broadly defined sectoral shares first, Chenery&#13;
and Syrquin themselves report that, compared with regression equations&#13;
estimated from actual 1950-70 data, the model in low income ranges substan-&#13;
tially underestimates the share of primary production in GDP (at an income&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
Table 6. SOURCES OF GROWTH IN SECTORAL DEMAND&#13;
IN CHENERY-SYRQUIN LARGE-COUNTRY MODEL&#13;
(Percentage of total GDP increase over income range $300-$1,200)&#13;
Domestic demand                                 Changes in&#13;
(consumption, govt.,                Import       input-output&#13;
and investment)     Exports    substitution    coefficients&#13;
Primary                    9.9            2.0          -0.3              -0.8&#13;
Light manufacturing       20.1            3.0           0.9               1.6&#13;
Heavy manufacturing       11.1            2.2           2.5               1.5&#13;
Nontradeables             42.9            2.8           0.4               0.6&#13;
Total                  83.9            9.9           3.4               2.9&#13;
Source: CRS (1986), Chapter 6, Table 6.3. Simple averages of percentages in&#13;
first two income ranges.&#13;
level of $300, this share is 46 percent in the regressions, but only 33&#13;
percent in the model),7/ and correspondingly overestimates the shares of&#13;
manufacturing, infrastructure and services.8/    Syrquin's (1985) updated&#13;
regressions predict a primary share at an income level of $300 that is&#13;
somewhat smaller (41 percent) than in the regressions based on the earlier&#13;
data, but still substantially greater than in the model.&#13;
More important for the present purpose is the conformity of the&#13;
pattern of change predicted by the model with that directly estimated from&#13;
/7   The discussion in this paragraph is based on Chenery (1979), pp. 86-89,&#13;
and Chenery and Syrquin (1975), p. 204. Per capita income is adjusted to&#13;
1981 prices. Output shares at $1,200, when not reported, are taken to be&#13;
the averages of the shares at $900 and $1,500. In this earlier work,&#13;
construction is added to manufacturing and excluded from infrastructure.&#13;
/8   As Chenery (1979, p. 86) points out, the share of manufacturing in low-&#13;
income countries may be understated because of omission or underreporting&#13;
of handicraft activities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
actual data. The correspondence with Chenery and Syrquin's 1950-70 regres-&#13;
sions is not close: in these regressions, the primary production share&#13;
declines over the income range $300-$1,200 by 24 percentage points, as against&#13;
17 in the model, with correspondingly larger increases in the shares of other&#13;
sectors. But the correspondence between the model and Syrquin's (1985)&#13;
updated regressions is much closer. Over a similar income interval ($300-&#13;
$1,400) for large countries other than China, the predicted decline in the&#13;
primary share in these regressions is 17 percentage points, exactly as in the&#13;
model. The predicted increases -in the shares of other sectors are also fairly&#13;
similar to those in the model, although the share of manufacturing increases&#13;
somewhat less (9 points, as against 11 in the model), and that of nontrade-&#13;
ables somewhat more (8 points, as against 5 in the model)--almost entirely&#13;
because of a larger increase in services.&#13;
The model also conforms more closely with the regression results of&#13;
Prakash and Robinson (1979, Annex Table 7), which differ significantly from&#13;
the Chenery-Syrquin 1950-70 regression results, despite being based on a&#13;
heavily overlapping body of data. The differences between these two sets of&#13;
regression results arise because the scarcity of large low-income countries&#13;
with long and reasonably reliable statistical series in the period 1950-70&#13;
made it hard to derive precise and robust estimates of "normal" structural&#13;
changes in such countries. As Chenery and Syrquin (1975, p. 171) demonstrate,&#13;
the estimated pattern of structural change at low-income levels in this period&#13;
is significantly affected by changes in the composition of the sample.&#13;
For changes in the composition of manufacturing output, the model&#13;
results may be compared with the regression analyses of Chenery and Taylor&#13;
(1968.) and Prakash and Robinson (1979), although the sectoral classifications&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
and income ranges are not completely consistent. The summary in Table 7&#13;
reveals broad consistency in the direction and magnitude of changes, though&#13;
with some significant variations.9- The share of food processing in total&#13;
manufacturing drops sharply, as (to a lesser extent) does that of textiles,&#13;
narrowly defined. The shares of clothing and footwear and of other light&#13;
industry (including wood, paper and printing) rise significantly, as do the&#13;
shares of basic intermediate products (especially chemicals and basic metals).&#13;
The steepest increase is in the share of metal products, including machinery.&#13;
In relation to GDP rather than to total manufacturing, incidentally, the&#13;
shares even of food processing and textiles in most cases increase, implying&#13;
substantial rises in absolute output.&#13;
Information on changes in the composition of output within broad&#13;
sectors other than manufacturing has not been analyzed so systematically.&#13;
This is particularly true of agriculture, which is invariably treated as a&#13;
single sector in studies of structural change. But it applies also to the&#13;
nontradeable sectors, despite the fact that they account for 40-50 percent of&#13;
GDP and in absolute terms contribute more than either agriculture or&#13;
manufacturing to raising GDP. (For example, in the Chenery-Syrquin large-&#13;
country model, nontradeable net output rises by 70 percent more than&#13;
manufacturing output over the income range $300-$1,200).&#13;
9/   Chenery (1979, pp. 88-89) compares the sectoral growth elasticities (pro-&#13;
portional increases in sectoral output divided by proportional increase&#13;
in aggregate output) of the Chenery-Syrquin model with elasticities&#13;
calculated by Prakash. At the level of aggregation in Tables 1-3 and 7,&#13;
the correspondence is quite close; the ratios of sectoral elasticities&#13;
in the model to those of Prakash range from 0.92 to 1.02 (with the excep-&#13;
tion of chemicals, where the Prakash data are suspect--see note in&#13;
Table 7). At a more detailed level, the correspondence becomes less close.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
Table 7. CHANGES IN THE COMPOSITION OF MANUFACTURING OUTPUT&#13;
IN LARGE COUNTRIES&#13;
(Absolute change over specified per capita&#13;
income range in percentage share of&#13;
total manufacturing net output)&#13;
Chenery-Syrquin      Chenery-Taylor      Prakash-Robinson&#13;
model            regressions          regressions&#13;
$300-$1,200         $285-$1,140          $425-$1,660&#13;
Food products                 -11                 -23                   -8&#13;
Textiles                    )                  )   -3                   -6&#13;
Clothing, footwear         )   -5              )&#13;
and leather              )                   )   +3                   +1&#13;
Other light industry            +2                 +4/a                 +2/a&#13;
Chemicals and rubber           +3                  +4                   -17i&#13;
Nonmetallic minerals           +1                  +2                    0&#13;
Basic metals                   +4                  +6                   +2&#13;
Metal products                 +6                  +9                  +11/c&#13;
/a  Wood, paper, and printing.&#13;
/b This figure is suspect because it is contradicted by other data in the&#13;
same paper (for instance, Figure 4, Annex Figure 1) which imply, in&#13;
accordance with expectations, that the share of chemicals in total&#13;
manufacturing output rises.&#13;
/c Includes other manufacturing.&#13;
Sources: Column 1: Tables 1-3. Columns 2 and 3: Prakash and Robinson&#13;
(1979); the numbers in column 2 were roughly derived from the&#13;
diagrams in Annex Figure 2, those in column 3 from Annex Table 7.&#13;
All per capita income data are converted to 1981 prices.&#13;
Table 8 presents some data on the composition of nontradeable output&#13;
in a few large developing countries, and compares it with the predictions of&#13;
the Chenery-Syrquin model. That the share of total nontradeable output in GDP&#13;
rises substantially with income is confirmed both by the cross-section data in&#13;
the top half of the table and by the data on changes over time (at current&#13;
prices) in the bottom half, though there is clearly considerable intercountry&#13;
variation. Within the nontradeabLe sector, the relative importance of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
Table 8. CONPOSITION OF NONTRADEABLE NET OUTPUT IN LARGE COUNTRIES&#13;
Chenery-&#13;
Syrquin&#13;
India   Pakistan    Indonesia   Thailand   Turkey     Brazil    Model&#13;
(a)  Level in 1970s ( percent of total nontradeable output)&#13;
(per cap. inco)         ($260)    ($350)     ($530)       ($770)   ($1,540)   ($2,220)  ($1,200)&#13;
Construction              13.7       9.5        11.2         9.2      10.8        9.7      1307&#13;
Electricity/gasi/ater      3.0       3.0         1.5         2.4       3.1        3.6       3e9&#13;
Transport                 13.5      13.9        10.4        12.0      17.7        8.9      11.5&#13;
Co merce/finance          37.1      34.7       45.3         47.0      28.1       39.8      30.6 /b&#13;
Public admin./defense     11.7      14.9        16.8         8.2      22.4       13.5)&#13;
Other /a                  21.1      23.8        14.8        21.2      17.9       24.6)     40.3&#13;
Total                  100.0     100.0      100.0        100l 0    100.0      100.0     100l 0&#13;
(Total as&#13;
percent GDP)         (34.9)    (49.5)     (39.3)       (50A0)    (51.9)     (58.6)    (54.0)&#13;
(b)  Change 1950o-70a at current prices (changes in sectoral shares&#13;
of total nontradeable output, in percentage points)&#13;
($300-&#13;
($1,200)&#13;
Construction              .1,4      +3,2       .5.3         -0.7      -1.9       -1.4      #3,0&#13;
Electricity/gao/water     41.6      41,8       +0.6         o1.5      +1.5       +1.4      +0,2&#13;
Transport                 -0.5       O. 1      -4.8         -3.9      +2,1       -1.9      o1.0&#13;
Commzrce/finance          +9.0      .1.8       +0,3        410.4      +5,6       +8o4      -3.9 /b&#13;
Public damino/defenoe     -1.2      +1,6     * +3.6         -1,7      +3.9       +0.9)&#13;
Other /a                 -10.1      -8.8       -9.3         -5.5     -11.3       -7.5)     -0.3&#13;
(Total ao&#13;
percent GDP)         (*4.5)    (.8.1)     (*5.3)       (+3.6)    (+7.0)     (*2.8)    (+5.3)&#13;
/a Includes houcing, real estate and other business services, education and health, other&#13;
community and persooual services, and statistical discrepancy.&#13;
/b Commerce only.&#13;
Source: World Tables, the Second Edition (1980); and Tables 1-3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
infrastructure displays less of a tendency to increase with income (both in&#13;
crosssection and over time) than would be expected from the model. This is&#13;
particularly true of the two biggest infrastructure sectors, construction and&#13;
transport. Electricity, gas and water output appears to increase over time&#13;
(but not in cross-section) rather faster than the model would predict.&#13;
Correspondingly, the relative importance of the service sectors&#13;
(narrowly defined) within the nontradeable sector does not in aggregate appear&#13;
to decline with income in the manner predicted by the model, but to remain&#13;
approximately constant. The difference is particularly striking for commerce,&#13;
which declines significantly in the model, but remains roughly constant in&#13;
cross-section and increases considerably over time in the countries shown in&#13;
the table.!21 The relative share of public administration and defense remains&#13;
roughly constant as income rises in cross-section, but shows a weak tendency&#13;
to increase over time. The relative share of other services (including&#13;
housing, education and health, and business and personal services) also&#13;
remains roughly constant in cross-section, but shows a strong tendency to&#13;
decline over time. (More disaggregated information regarding this somewhat&#13;
surprising last finding is not readily available, but it may reflect improve-&#13;
ments in national accounting--reductions in the extent of "unallocated"&#13;
activities, which are included with other services in the statistical source&#13;
used).&#13;
Labor Productivity and Employment&#13;
Per capita income growth depends above all else on increasing average&#13;
net output per worker, partly by shifting workers from low-productivity to&#13;
/10 Part of the discrepancy, however, is due to the inclusion of banking and&#13;
insurance with commerce in the country data.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
high-productivity sectors, partly by raising productivity within individual&#13;
sectors. Table 9, derived from the Chenery-Syrquin model, presents measures&#13;
of labor productivity in terms of both gross and net output over the L2levant&#13;
income range.  It is immediately apparent, first, that labor productivity&#13;
rises a lot in every sector, and second, that there are large and persistent&#13;
differences among sectors in output per worker (partly explained, as will&#13;
emerge later, by differences in the amount of capital per worker).&#13;
Table 9. LABOR PRODUCTIVITY AT DIFFERENT INCOME LEVELS&#13;
Workers required             Net output per worker ($)&#13;
per thousand dollars                                    $1,200&#13;
of gross output                                       divided&#13;
$300    $600   $1,200      $300      $600     $1,200    by $300&#13;
Agriculture        3.44     2.05     1.22     244.7     373.1      559.1      2.3&#13;
Mining             2.00     0.87     0.38     373.5     853.9    1,964.0      5.3&#13;
Food processing    0.27    0.16      0.09   1,134.5   1,914.4    3,397.2      3.0&#13;
Other light&#13;
manufacturing    1.10    0.51      0.24     417.5     898.8    1,905.5      4.6&#13;
Other heavy&#13;
manufacturing    0.73    0.30      0.13     675.8   1,590.2    3,572.4      5.3&#13;
Machinery          0.93     0.39     0.17     558.7   1,337.8    3,075.4      5.5&#13;
Infrastructure     0.80    0.41      0.25     715.1   1,380.4   2,250.4       3.1&#13;
Services           0.85    0.56      0.37     869.5   1,309.9    1,972.6      2.3&#13;
Source:  Unpublished data from Chenery-Syrquin model (maximum available degree&#13;
of disaggregation: more detailed data regarding gross output are&#13;
available in Stern and Lewis 1980). Dollar figures converted to 1981&#13;
prices.&#13;
Closer examination reveals that there are also important differences&#13;
among sectors in the rate of productivity growth.   In terms of net output,&#13;
labor productivity increases twice as fast in manufacturing as in agriculture,&#13;
and especially fast in machinery and other heavy manufacturing (also in&#13;
mining). Labor productivity in the infrastructure sectors grows at an inter-&#13;
mediate pace, while in the service sectors it grows no faster than in&#13;
agriculture.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
Slower-than-average growth of labor productivity in the service&#13;
sectors, a tendency which would appear more pronounced if allowances were made&#13;
for the rise in the relative price of services mentioned earlier, is due&#13;
partly to the way in which the output of some service sectors is measured.!!,&#13;
In particular, in public administration and defense and in education and&#13;
health, output is--for want of any better alternative--measured by the amount&#13;
of inputs, mainly labor, which means that productivity does not grow at all&#13;
(and that the relative price of the service increases in line with real wage&#13;
rates).  In most other services--commerce, finance, laundry, entertainment,&#13;
for example--there is a marketed output that can be measured independently of&#13;
inputs; but the labor-intensive nature of some of these services limits the&#13;
scope for productivity increases, which in turn causes the cost (and hence the&#13;
relative price) of these services to rise as the general level of real wage&#13;
rates increases. In some service sectors in some developing countries, this&#13;
tendency apparently has been offset by a decline in relative wage rates in&#13;
these sectors, which in turn has been caused by pressure of surplus labor&#13;
unable to find productive employment in agriculture or industry.121     (But on&#13;
average across all service sectors in developing countries, real net output&#13;
11/ Problems with nontradeable output measurement in developing countries are&#13;
discussed in Blades (1974).&#13;
12/ This couLd perhaps explain why, in Table 4, the relative price of "other&#13;
services" is lower in Group II than in Group I countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
per worker--as conventionally measured--has not been driven down by disguised&#13;
unemployment.13/&#13;
As a result of different rates of labor productivity growth, the&#13;
differences among sectors in productivity levels also change. Most notably,&#13;
the gap between agriculture and manufacturing widens substantially in the&#13;
income range $300-$1,200 (from a ratio of 1:2.4 to 1:4.7). So, to a smaller&#13;
degree, does the initially larger gap between agriculture and infrastructure&#13;
(1:2.9 to 1:4.0), while the fourfold gap between agriculture and services&#13;
remains roughly constant. Output per worker in manufacturing, which on&#13;
average at an income level of $300 is below that in the nontradeable sectors,&#13;
has by $1,200 overtaken both infrastructure and services, though not by very&#13;
much. Within manufacturing, the relative productivity levels of different&#13;
sectors, as well as their respective weights, change: food processing,&#13;
initially well above the others in terms of labor productivity, is overtaken&#13;
by other heavy industry, with machinery not far behind. Other light manufac-&#13;
turing remains in fourth place. (Some of these changes in relative sectoral&#13;
net output per worker are caused by changes in capital per worker, to be&#13;
discussed below. It is also possible that the apparently widening produc-&#13;
tivity gap between agriculture and industry in this income range in part&#13;
reflects increasing distortion of prices against agriculture and in favor of&#13;
industry.)&#13;
13/ From World Development Report 1983, Indicators Tables 2 and 21, it can be&#13;
calculated that net output per worker in the service sectors (plus&#13;
transport) grew during the period 1960-81 at the following annual average&#13;
percentage rates: India, 2.1; low-income countries other than India and&#13;
China, 0.4; lower-middle-income countries, 1.1; upper-middle-income&#13;
countries, 3.0. Net output growth is supposed to be measured at constant&#13;
prices in this source, although the underlying data are probably, in many&#13;
cases, not very reliable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
Associated with these changes in labor productivity, as well as with&#13;
changes in the composition of output, are substantial changes in the&#13;
distribution of employment among the various sectors, as shown in Table 10.&#13;
In agriculture, with below-average productivity growth, the share of employ-&#13;
ment drops less (the share at $1,200 is 0.67 of that at $300) than the share&#13;
of net output (for which the corresponding ratio is 0.43). In the nontrade-&#13;
able sectors, the effect of below-average productivity growth is to cause the&#13;
share of employment to rise faster (the share at $1,200 is 1.57 of that at&#13;
$300) than net output (for which the corresponding ratio is 1.11). This is&#13;
especially true of services, where a 5 percent increase in the share of net&#13;
output is associated with a 60 percent increase in the share of employment.&#13;
Table 10. SECTORAL EMPLOYMENT SHARES AT DIFFERENT INCOME LEVELS&#13;
(Percentage of total employment)&#13;
$300              $600          $1,200&#13;
Agriculture                                57.1             47.7             38.0&#13;
Mining                                      2.5              2.6              2.4&#13;
Food processing                             2.3              2.6              2.8&#13;
Other light manufacturing                   7.7               8.6             8.9&#13;
Other heavy manufacturing                   2.5              3.2              3.7&#13;
Machinery                                   1.4              2.0              2.4&#13;
Infrastructure                              7.6              8.8             11.0&#13;
Services                                   19.0             24.4             30.8&#13;
Total                                100.0            100.0            100.0&#13;
Source: Chenery-Syrquin large country model (derived from data in Tables 1-3&#13;
and 9).&#13;
In manufacturing, the effect of rapid labor productivity growth&#13;
largely offsets that of rapid output growth: the share of manufacturing in&#13;
total employment rises by only 4 percentage points; and the shares of the four&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
manufacturing sectors in total manufacturing employment also change relatively&#13;
little (light manufacturing declines from 72 percent to 66 percent, with a&#13;
corresponding increase in heavy manufacturing). The predominant shift in the&#13;
pattern of employment in the Chenery-Syrquin model, then, is from primary&#13;
sectors, particularly agriculture, to nontradeable sectors, particularLy&#13;
services, with manufacturing as a less important source of additional&#13;
employment.&#13;
As discussed earlier, the model appears over this income range to&#13;
understate the level of primary output and to overstate that of other sectors,&#13;
even though the changes in output shares seem approximately correct.&#13;
Comparison of the data on sectoral employment shares in Table 10 with Chenery&#13;
and Syrquin's (1975, p. 49) earlier regressions, and with Syrquin's (1985)&#13;
updated regressions, suggests that the level of primary employment is also&#13;
understated. At an income level of $300 in Syrquin's updated regressions, for&#13;
example, the predicted employment share of agriculture for a large country&#13;
around 1980/81 is 67 percent, as compared with 57 percent in the model. The&#13;
decline in primary employment in Table 10 is proportionately similar to that&#13;
in the regression equations over a comparable income range, but smaller in&#13;
terms of percentage points (19, compared with 22-23 in the regression&#13;
equations).&#13;
The initial share of manufacturing employment in Table 10 is about&#13;
5 percentage points above what Syrquin's updated regression equation would&#13;
predict (precise comparison is impeded by different sectoral definitions), but&#13;
the increase in the share of manufacturing employment predicted by this&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
regression equation (about 8 percentage points)-41 is larger than in Table 10&#13;
(4 percentage points), which would imply that the model overstates the growth&#13;
of labor productivity in manufacturing. The initial share of nontradeable&#13;
employment in Table 10 is also higher (by about 3 percentage points) than that&#13;
predicted by Syrquin's updated regression; but the increase in the share&#13;
predicted by this regression equation (about 15 percentage points) is close to&#13;
that in Table 10. (The increase predicted by the Chenery-Syrquin 1950-70&#13;
regressions is much smaller.)&#13;
The discrepancies between the model and the regressions, and between&#13;
the two sets of regressions, may be attributable--as mentioned above--to the&#13;
limited availability of data for low-income countries, a problem which is more&#13;
acute for employment than for output statistics. But the model's qualitative&#13;
prediction that the shift from primary employment is more into nontradeables&#13;
than into manufacturing is supported both by Syrquin's updated regressions and&#13;
by simple inspection of the trends in developing countries over the past two&#13;
decades: in India, the increase in the employment share of services (broadly&#13;
defined) was 3 percentage points, as against 2 for industry (broadly defined);&#13;
in low-income countries excluding India and China, the corresponding figures&#13;
are 5 and 4; in lower-middle-income countries, 10 and 6; and in upper-middle-&#13;
income countries, 11 and 8.151 This prediction also conforms with what&#13;
14/ The increase is 10.4 percentage points when mining, construction, and&#13;
electricity are included. The increase is larger in the Chenery-Syrquin&#13;
1950-70 regressions. All references to Syrquin's updated regressions&#13;
refer to a country of 60 million people around 1980/81, with China and&#13;
small countries excluded from the underlying data.&#13;
15/ World Development Report 1983, Indicators Table 21. Mining, electricity&#13;
and construction are included in industry in this source; and "services"&#13;
includes transport.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
happened in earlier decades in most of the developed market economies (Kuznets&#13;
1966, pp. 105-111).&#13;
A similar pattern, with more growth of nontradeable than of manufac-&#13;
turing employment, occurred in the USSR, even though the employment share of&#13;
agriculture has consistently been unusually large and that of services.&#13;
(especially commerce, finance, and personal services other than education,&#13;
health, and restaurants) unusually small. Thus from 1926 to 1964, a period in&#13;
which per capita GNP in 1981 prices is estimated to have risen from $570 to&#13;
$3,700, agriculture's share of the labor force fell from 71 percent to 33 per-&#13;
cent, while that of manufacturing and mining rose from 13 percent to 28 per-&#13;
cent, and that of nontradeables rose from 16 percent to 39 percent (of which&#13;
infrastructure went from 5 percent to 15 percent, and services from 11 percent&#13;
to 24 percent).i6/ These changes appear quite close, with due allowance for&#13;
the persistent difference in levels, to what would be predicted on the basis&#13;
of cross-section data for other countries (Ofer 1973, pp. 145-146). Within&#13;
the service sector, however, commerce appears to have increased unusually&#13;
slowly, and other services (especially education and health) unusually fast.&#13;
Capital Stock&#13;
To increase labor productivity, both within sectors and by realloca-&#13;
tion among sectors, accumulation of capital is required. Table 11, which&#13;
16/ These numbers are from Ofer (1973), p. 2, with the division of industry&#13;
between infrastructure (excluding electricity) and manufacturing (assumed&#13;
to include mining) based on Table E-2. The income data are from p. 137,&#13;
adjusted to 1981 prices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
Table 11. CAPITAL PRODUCTIVITY AT DIFFERENT INCOME LEVELS&#13;
Fixed capital required&#13;
per dollar of gross        Net output per dollar&#13;
output ($)             of fixed capital ($)&#13;
$300   $600    $1,200     $300    $600     $1,200&#13;
Agriculture                  1.00    1.20     1.44     0.84    0.64       0.47&#13;
Mining                       0.70   0.86      1.06     1.07     0.86      0.70&#13;
Food processing              0.45   0.45      0.45     0.68    0.68       0.68&#13;
Other light manufacturing    0.70   0.70      0.70     0.66    0.65       0.65 /b&#13;
Other heavy manufacturing    1.00    1.00     1.00     0.49    0.48       0.46 Tr&#13;
Machinery                    0.65   0.65      0.65     0.80    0.80       0.80&#13;
Infrastructure               4.30   3.88      3.50     0.13    0.15       0.16&#13;
Services /a                  1.30   1.27      1.24     0.57    0.58       0.59&#13;
/a Excludes housing.&#13;
/b Declines in net output per dollar of capital are due to changes in&#13;
subsectoral composition, which alter average net-gross output ratios.&#13;
Source: Unpublished data from Chenery-Syrquin model (first three columns:&#13;
last three columns derived also from Tables 1-3).&#13;
covers only fixed capital (and excludes housing),17/ summarizes sectoral&#13;
capital requirements and productivity in the Chenery-Syrquin model. Since the&#13;
underlying data on capital stocks are neither abundant nor reliable, these&#13;
figures should be treated as no more than rough approximations. Focusing&#13;
first on changes in the amount of capital required per unit of gross output as&#13;
income rises, the individual sectors fall into three groups: in both primary&#13;
sectors (agriculture and mining), capital-output ratios increase as develop-&#13;
ment proceeds, reflecting increased mechanization and land improvement; in&#13;
17/ Some idea of the significance of these omissions may be obtained by&#13;
looking at figures for the United Kingdom in 1974. Dwellings comprised&#13;
31 percent of the total fixed capital stock (at replacement cost, net of&#13;
depreciation). Inventories (circulating capital) were equal to 12 per-&#13;
cent of the total fixed capital stock.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
individual manufacturing sectors, capital-output ratios remain approximately&#13;
constant (though of course there is a shift in the composition of output&#13;
towards more capital-intensive manufacturing sectors); and in the nontradeable&#13;
sectors, capital-output ratios decline somewhat. Looking at capital&#13;
productivity (net output per dollar of capital), a broadly similar pattern of&#13;
change is observed, although the falling net-gross output ratio causes the&#13;
productivity of capital in agriculture to decline somewhat faster.&#13;
Infrastructure consistently, and by a very wide margin, has the&#13;
highest capital requirements per unit of output and the lowest capital&#13;
productivity. The differences in capital productivity among the other sectors&#13;
are less pronounced and tend to diminish as income increases, with initially&#13;
high levels in agriculture and mining declining to or below the constant&#13;
levels in manufacturing. The productivity of capital in services is only&#13;
slightly below the manufacturing average (though the gap would probably be&#13;
significantly larger if housing and working capital were included). Within&#13;
manufacturing, the productivity of capital is highest in machinery, lowest in&#13;
other heavy manufacturing (basic metals, chemicals, etc.), with food pro-&#13;
cessing and other light manufacturing in between.&#13;
Changes in capital requirements, together with changes in the&#13;
composition of output, alter sectoral shares in the economy's stock of fixed&#13;
capital (summarized in Table 12). Yet the predominant impression is of&#13;
constancy rather than change. At income levels of both $300 and $1,200, two&#13;
fifths of the capital is in infrastructure, and more than a quarter in&#13;
services (excluding housing). Agriculture's share of the capital stock&#13;
declines significantly, but, because of increasing capital-intensity in&#13;
agriculture, by much less than its share of CDP. The share of manufacturing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
increases by 50 percent, but is only one fifth of the total capital stock even&#13;
at an income level of $1,200. Within manufacturing, the relative share of&#13;
machinery and other heavy manufacturing increases substantially (from 34 per-&#13;
cent to 49 percent), with a corresponding decline for light industry,&#13;
especially food processing.&#13;
Table 12. SECTORAL SHARES OF FIXED CAPITAL STOCK AT&#13;
DIFFERENT INCOME LEVELS&#13;
(Percentage of total)&#13;
Implied allocation&#13;
of fixed investment&#13;
$300    $600     $1,200       $300-$1,200 /b&#13;
Agriculture                      16.6     13.8      11.6            10.4&#13;
Mining                            0.9      1.3       1.7             1.9&#13;
Food processing                   3.7      3.6       3.6             3.6&#13;
Other light manufacturing         4.9      5.9       6.7             7.2&#13;
Other heavy manufacturing         3.4      5.3       7.4             8.4&#13;
Machinery                         1.0      1.7       2.3             2.6&#13;
Infrastructure                   40.6    41.1       40.0            39.9&#13;
Services /a                      28.9     27.3      26.7            26.2&#13;
Total                  100.0   100.0      100.0          100.0&#13;
/a Excludes housing.&#13;
/b Assuming that total capital stock quintuples and that depreciation affects&#13;
all sectors equally.&#13;
Source: Chenery-Syrquin large-country model (derived from data in Tables 1-3&#13;
and 11).&#13;
From the capital stock shares in Table 12, one can roughly infer the&#13;
allocation of annual fixed investment among sectors. In the income range&#13;
$300-$1,200 (see last column), the Chenery-Syrquin model implies that approxi-&#13;
mately 10 percent of total investment goes into agriculture and 2 percent into&#13;
mining. Manufacturing industry receives 22 percent, divided approximately&#13;
equally between light and heavy sectors, but with other heavy manufacturing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
(basic metals, chemicals, etc.) getting about two fifths of all manufacturing&#13;
investment. Infrastructure absorbs 40 percent of the total, and services&#13;
about a quarter. The share of services would be substantially higher and that&#13;
of all other sectors lower if housing investment were included.&#13;
Other studies broadly corroborate the capital-related results of the&#13;
Chenery-Syrquin model, though there are some differences. Table 13 presents&#13;
an alternative set of data on sectoral capital requirements per unit of gross&#13;
output at different income levels, derived from the UN world model. The&#13;
"direct requirements" are similar in terms of both level and change to those&#13;
in Table 11 (although comparable figures for agriculture and mining are not&#13;
available). "Total requirements," however, which include the investment&#13;
needed in sectors supplying intermediate inputs and supporting services, can&#13;
be seen from Table 13 to be much higher than direct requirements. The&#13;
difference is particularly striking in manufacturing, where total capital&#13;
requirements are typically two to three times direct capital requirements.&#13;
This is partly because each manufacturing sector requires inputs from other&#13;
manufacturing sectors, but also because all manufacturing sectors need power,&#13;
transportation, commerce and other inputs from nonmanufacturing sectors&#13;
(which, in turn, helps explain why direct investment in manufacturing is&#13;
typically a fairly modest proportion of total investment).&#13;
Table 14 shows sectoral shares in the fixed capital stocks of four&#13;
economies, each at two points in time. Although the income levels are&#13;
generally higher than those in Table 12, the two tables are not very&#13;
different. The share of the primary sectors, though apparently somewhat&#13;
higher in Table 14 than the Chenery-Syrquin model implies, tends to decline&#13;
moderately in both tables (but with an exceptionally sharp drop in Japan).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
The share of the nontradeable sectors is likewise very large in both tables,&#13;
although it varies considerably among the economies in question, and shows a&#13;
modest but irregular tendency to decline. The share of manufacturing in the&#13;
totals in Table 14 is in three cases similar (10-20 percent) to that in&#13;
Table 13. ALTERNATIVE ESTIMATES OF FIXED CAPITAL&#13;
REQUIREMENTS AT DIFFERENT INCOME LEVELS&#13;
(Dollars of fixed capital per dollar of gross output)&#13;
$430 /a               $1,600 /a&#13;
Agriculture                                    -                      -&#13;
Mining                                         -                      -&#13;
Food processing                               0.63  (1.72)           0.63  (1.65)&#13;
Other light manufacturing /b                  0.59  (1.46)           0.57  (1.30)&#13;
Textiles and clothing                       0.38  (1.15)           0.38  (1.07)&#13;
Wood, paper, printing /c                    0.55  (1.32)           0.55  (1.30)&#13;
Other heavy manufacturing /d                  0.78  (2.01)           0.77  (1.79)&#13;
Chemicals /e                                0.77  (2.03)           0.77  (1.79)&#13;
Basic metals                                0.83  (1.94)           0.83  (1.87)&#13;
Metal products                              0.68  (1.60)           0.59  (1.40)&#13;
Machinery /f                                  0.60  (1.27)           0.55  (0.91)&#13;
Infrastructure 8                              3.29  (4.62)           2.68  (4.47)&#13;
Construction                                0.58  (1.45)           0.43  (1.33)&#13;
Electricity, gas, water                     3.83  (4.50)           3.92  (4.50)&#13;
Transport /h                                5.79  (6.26)           5.38  (6.03)&#13;
Services /i                                   1.16  (1.66)           1.39  (1.82)&#13;
Commerce                                    1.47  (1.88)           1.39  (1.82)&#13;
Other services                              0.84  (1.44)           0.80  (1.39)&#13;
/a At 1981 prices.&#13;
7T Unweighted average of furniture, textiles, printing, wood, paper, other.&#13;
7E Unweighted average: includes furniture.&#13;
7   Unweighted average of other chemicals, rubber, fertilizer, metal products,&#13;
basic metals, cement, glass, industrial chemicals, petroleum refining.&#13;
/e Unweighted average: includes rubber and petroleum refining.&#13;
7T Unweighted average of professional instruments, electrical machinery,&#13;
shipbuilding, machinery, and motor vehicles.&#13;
/g  Unweighted average of electricity, construction, transport, and&#13;
communications.&#13;
/h Includes communications.&#13;
7T  Unweighted average of commerce and other services.&#13;
Source:  Stern and Lewis (1980), Table B3.    The data for agriculture and&#13;
mining in this source are not comparable with Table 9 above, since&#13;
they exclude most of the main agricultural and mining sectors.&#13;
Numbers in parentheses are "total" fixed capital requirements, which&#13;
include both the investment needed directly in the sector in question&#13;
(the number not in parentheses) and the investment required in&#13;
sectors supplying intermediate inputs and supporting services&#13;
(calculated with an input-output table).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
Table 14. SECTORAL SHARES IN FIXED CAPITAL STOCKS OF FOUR ECONOMIES&#13;
(Percentage of total capital stock)&#13;
Korea           Japan         Israel          Mexico&#13;
1963   1973     1955   1970    1958    1972    1950   1975&#13;
Primary                  9.8   10.2     21.5   13.3    25.9    18.8    19.3  15.1&#13;
Light manufacturing      5.0    8.4     11.0   11.0    12.7    11.8     9.9   8.7&#13;
Heavy manufacturing      2.9    9.2     12.7   25.5    14.1    12.8     7.4   11.1&#13;
Nontradeables           82.3   72.2     54.8   50.2    47.3    56.6    63.4  65.1&#13;
Total           100.0  100.0   100.0   100.0   100.0  100.0    100.0 100.0&#13;
Source:  Data base for the Comparative Study of the Sources of Industrial&#13;
Growth and Structural Change (World Bank Research Project 671-32).&#13;
Table 12, but is higher in Israel and in Japan (24 percent, rising to 37 per-&#13;
cent).  Except in Israel, and to a lesser degree in Mexico, the manufacturing&#13;
share shows the same marked tendency to increase, especially in heavy&#13;
manufacturing.&#13;
Other sources of information on the share of manufacturing in total&#13;
annual fixed investment are also broadly consistent with the figure of 22 per-&#13;
cent in Table 12. Data assembled by Stern and Lewis (1980, Table 4) reveal&#13;
that the corresponding number for India (1960-72) was 26 percent, for Thailand&#13;
(1970-74) 18 percent, for Korea (1965-74) 23 percent, and for Malaysia&#13;
(1969-70) 17 percent.181 In Japan, in the period 1951-65, the share of&#13;
manufacturing and mining in annual fixed investment--excluding dwellings--&#13;
averaged 32 percent (30 percent for manufacturing alone); in the period&#13;
18/ The figures in Table 12 exclude housing from the denominator, whereas&#13;
those of Stern and Lewis include it. With housing excluded, the figure&#13;
for Korea, for example, would be 27 percent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
1916-30, excluding dwellings and military investment, it averaged 11 percent&#13;
(Ohkawa and Rosovsky 1973).&#13;
Sources of Growth&#13;
The preceding discussion has emphasized the effects of growth in per&#13;
capita income on the patterns of demand, production, employment and invest-&#13;
ment. But these changes in economic structure themselves contribute to&#13;
economic growth, partly by increasing the rate of accumulation of capital,&#13;
partly by shifting resources towards sectors in which productivity is higher&#13;
or increasing faster. Methods for disentangling these contributions have been&#13;
developed and applied to various sorts of data, including that generated by&#13;
the Chenery-Syrquin model. In what follows, particular attention will be paid&#13;
to the sources of growth in per capita, rather than total, income--neglecting,&#13;
that is to say, the role of population expansion.&#13;
It is convenient to begin by looking at an aspect of growth that is&#13;
largely independent of structural change, namely productivity increases in&#13;
individual sectors. It will be recalled from Table 9 that net output per&#13;
worker increases substantially in every sector, though at widely varying rates&#13;
(faster in mining and manufacturing, slower in agriculture and services).&#13;
Part of this increase, however, is due to a rise in capital per worker, which,&#13;
in turn, is partly a reflection of the shift in the structure of demand&#13;
towards investment. The remainder of the increase is known as "total factor&#13;
productivity (TFP) growth." Its measurement is dependent upon rather strong&#13;
assumptions about the reliability of input and output data and about the&#13;
nature of production technology (especially regarding the relative&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
contributions of increases in labor and capital to increases in&#13;
production).19/&#13;
Table 15 summarizes some relevant results of the Chenery-Syrquin&#13;
model in the per capita income range $300-$1,200. On average across sectors,&#13;
about 60 percent of the rise in net output per worker is attributed to&#13;
increased capital per worker, and about 40 percent to TFP growth (which&#13;
averages about 1 percent per year in nonagricultural sectors, and 0.4 percent&#13;
in agriculture). The range of variation in these shares among sectors is&#13;
substantial: increased capital per worker accounts at one extreme for 71 per-&#13;
cent of labor productivity growth in agriculture,20/ at the other for 41 per-&#13;
cent in services. In consequence, the ranking of sectors by TFP growth is&#13;
significantly different from their ranking by labor productivity growth.&#13;
Agriculture is at the bottom in both cases, but by a wider margin with respect&#13;
to all other sectors in terms of TFP growth (for example, labor productivity&#13;
grows at the same rate in agriculture and services, but TFP in services grows&#13;
twice as fast as in agriculture, partly because of increasing capital&#13;
intensity in agriculture, but also--in a sense spuriously--because the&#13;
relative price of services is rising). Heavy manufacturing's higher labor-&#13;
productivity growth, compared with light manufacturing, is shown to be&#13;
19/ It is also in principle possible, and in important respects more&#13;
illuminating, to make a similar analysis of the sources of growth in&#13;
gross output per worker, allowing for the contribution of material&#13;
inputs. The necessary data, however, are less commonly available. For a&#13;
critical view of TFP calculations, which nonetheless emphasizes the&#13;
contribution of resource reallocation to economic growth, see Nelson&#13;
(1981), esp. pp. 1053-1056.&#13;
20/ The remaining 29 percent, moreover, could be due partly to increased land&#13;
availability rather than to TFP growth: see note b of Table 15.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
entirely due to faster growth of capital per worker; in terms of--more&#13;
economically relevant--TFP growth, the two sectors are equally attractive&#13;
(surpassing both mining and infrastructure).&#13;
Table 15. SOURCES OF SECTORAL NET OUTPUT GROWTH&#13;
IN THE INCOME RANGE $300-$1,200&#13;
Contributions to&#13;
growth of output&#13;
Annual growth rates            per worker           Level of total&#13;
(percent)               (percent shares)     factor productivity&#13;
Output             Increased                 Income level&#13;
per                capital                    of $600&#13;
Output   worker    TFP /a   per worker    TFP /a   (Agriculture = 100)&#13;
Agriculture           3.90     1.47      0.42 /b     71        29 /b           100&#13;
Mining                5.84     2.90      1.09        62        38              179&#13;
Food processing   )                                                            232&#13;
Other light mfg. )    5.75     2.36      1.18        50        50              164&#13;
Other heavy mfg. )                                                             204&#13;
Machinery         )   6.67     2.86      1.17        59        41              217&#13;
Infrastructure        5.64     2.14     1.07         50        50              134&#13;
Services              5.26     1.46     0.86         41        59              205&#13;
/a  Total factor productivity:   for definition see text.&#13;
7b Latest draft of CRS (1986) subdivides this between TFP growth and increases in land&#13;
availability, implying that TFP growth in agriculture is less than these numbers&#13;
suggest.&#13;
Sources:  Tables 9 and 11, and CRS (1986), Chapter 8, Table 8.4 (subdivision of&#13;
manufacturing unpublished). Growth rates in periods II and III were averaged&#13;
on the basis that the former lasts 35 years, the latter 22 years. Growth of&#13;
output per worker was derived from the other data given. Column 6 was derived&#13;
from the labor and fixed capital (net output) productivity figures in Tables 9&#13;
and 11, which were averaged using as weights the Period II sectoral&#13;
elasticities of output with respect to capital and labor (net output per&#13;
worker in Table 9 was divided by 1,000 to put it into commensurate units).&#13;
TFP growth at the sectoral level has many specific causes, but is&#13;
essentially a matter of improved technology and knowledge, embodied partly in&#13;
better (and in some cases larger-scale) equipment and other material inputs,&#13;
partly in better trained and more experienced workers, partly in more effi-&#13;
cient institutions.   It is neither costless (the increase of physical capital&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
measures only part of the accumulation of resources required for economic&#13;
growth), nor independent of economic policies and circumstances. Indeed, the&#13;
most striking finding of the few studies that have attempted statistical&#13;
explanations of sectoral TFP growth is that differences among sectors,&#13;
especially within manufacturing, are less systematic and pronounced than&#13;
differences among countries. In other words, although agriculture (at low-&#13;
and middle-income levels) and services tend to have relatively low TFP growth,&#13;
and although there may be a weak tendency for the ranking of manufacturing&#13;
subsectors to be similar across countries (with machinery near the top), what&#13;
stands out much more strongly is that in any particular country TFP growth in&#13;
all sectors tends to be higher or lower than in other countries. Within&#13;
manufacturing, there is some evidence to suggest that export orientation&#13;
contributes to faster TFP growth (see CRS 1986, Chapters 8-10).&#13;
The impact of intersectoral resource shifts on economic growth&#13;
depends not only on intersectoral differences in TFP growth, but also on&#13;
intersectoral differences in TFP levels. Differences among sectors in net&#13;
output per worker are very large (Table 9), but are offset to a considerable&#13;
degree by differences in capital requirements (Table 11), as is shown in&#13;
Table 15, which in the last column presents estimates--which should be treated&#13;
with considerable caution--of sectoral TFP levels at a per capita income of&#13;
$600. TFP in the most productive sector is only 2.3 times that of&#13;
agriculture, compared with 5.1 times for labor productivity alone; and the&#13;
high capital requirements of infrastructure make its TFP only 34 percent&#13;
higher than that of agriculture, despite labor productivity 3.7 times as&#13;
great. Nonetheless, the intersectoral differences remain substantial--TFP&#13;
levels in mining, manufacturing and services are on average double that of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
agriculture. As a result, even without intersectoral differences in TFP&#13;
growth rates, intersectoral shifts of labor and capital can significantly&#13;
increase aggregate TFP--although, as already mentioned, it is not usually&#13;
possible to realize the potential gains from such shifts without substantial&#13;
expenditure on education, training and research, or without the evolution of&#13;
policies and institutions congruent with an enhanced division of labor.&#13;
As at the sectoral level, the growth of aggregate output per worker&#13;
(which, with changes in the ratio of workers to population, is the key deter-&#13;
minant of per capita income growth) is attributable partly to increased&#13;
capital per worker, and partly to TFP growth. But aggregate TFP growth can&#13;
itself be divided into two parts: that caused by TFP growth in individual&#13;
sectors and that caused by intersectoral shifts of resources. In the Chenery-&#13;
Syrquin model over the income range $300-$1,200, aggregate output per worker&#13;
grows at an annual average rate of 2.1 percent, of which about half is&#13;
attributable to increased capital per worker and half to TFP growth, of which&#13;
in turn about four fifths is due to TFP growth in individual sectors and one&#13;
fifth to intersectoral resource shifts.21/&#13;
Within this income range, growth of net output per worker acceler-&#13;
ates; from 1.7 percent per year in the subrange $300-$600, to 2.8 percent in&#13;
the subrange $600-$1,200 (in each subrange, per capita income doubles; but the&#13;
acceleration of growth means that the second doubling occurs more quickly--22&#13;
years in the model--than the first doubling, which is 35 years). The&#13;
acceleration of labor productivity growth is due partly to faster growth of&#13;
capital per worker (labor force growth slows and the share of investment in&#13;
21/ CRS (1986), Chapter 8, Tables 8.1, 8.4 and 8.6.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
output rises), but slightly more to faster aggregate TFP growth. The relative&#13;
contribution of intersectoral resource shifts to aggregate TFP growth also&#13;
increases slightly.&#13;
These conclusions of the Chenery-Syrquin model conform quite closely&#13;
to the results of other studies, although there is substantial variation among&#13;
countries and income levels. Averaging the results of about 30 studies of&#13;
(mainly middle- and upper-middle-income) developing countries, increased&#13;
capital per worker appears to have contributed about one third, and TFP growth&#13;
about two thirds, of the growth in aggregate net output per worker (3 percent&#13;
per year).221 This is similar to the predictions of the model in a comparable&#13;
income range, although in the model, output per worker grows faster (4 percent&#13;
per year) and TFP growth contributes a somewhat smaller share (57 percent).&#13;
The acceleration of growth in middle-income countries predicted by the model&#13;
accords well with cross-section data (annual growth of GNP per capita in&#13;
1960-81 average 0.8 percent in low-income countries other than India and&#13;
China, 1.4 percent in India, 3.4 percent in lower-middle-income countries, and&#13;
4.2 percent in upper-middle-income countries). 231 It also accords with the&#13;
average time-series experience to developing countries from 1950 to 1970 (GNP&#13;
per capita growth of 2.7 percent in 1950-60, 3.1 percent in 1960-65, and&#13;
3.8 percent in 1965-70), although there was deceleration for low-income&#13;
countries in 1960-65 and for most developing countries after 1970.24/&#13;
22/  CRS (1986), Chapter 2, Table 2.2.    This calculation assumes that growth&#13;
of employment (number of workers) and growth of "labor input" are the&#13;
same thing, although in some TFP studies the latter is adjusted for&#13;
changes in labor quality.&#13;
23/ World Development Report 1983, Indicators Table 1.&#13;
24/ World Tables, 1980, p. 372.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
Cross-country regression studies (CRS 1986, Chapter 2, Table 2.4)&#13;
confirm that there is an association between structural change, particularly&#13;
away from agriculture and into industry, and growth.    In seven middle-income&#13;
developing countries in various periods between 1950 and 1975, intersectoral&#13;
resource shifts are calculated to have contributed on average 10-15 percent of&#13;
labor productivity growth, close to what the model predicts (CRS 1986,&#13;
Chapter 8, Table 8.7). This does not mean that agriculture is unimportant:&#13;
without doubling net output per agricultural worker, it would be virtually&#13;
impossible for a low-income country to become a middle-income country; inter-&#13;
country variation in agricultural growth explains a significant part of the&#13;
variation in overall growth (Hwa 1983). The rapid development of infrastruc-&#13;
ture and services is likewise essential to output and efficiency gains in both&#13;
industry and agriculture.&#13;
Trends at Higher Income Levels&#13;
The preceding account of growth and structural change in other&#13;
countries has focused mainly on the income range $300-$1,200.     In the middle&#13;
to upper-middle-income range, many of the same trends continue. The share of&#13;
food consumption declines further and the share of investment in GDP increases&#13;
further. Together with a continuing increase in the share of manufactures in&#13;
total exports and in intermediate use, these changes in demand reduce the&#13;
primary sector's share of GDP from over 20 percent eventually to under 10 per-&#13;
cent, while further raising those of manufacturing and nontradeables.&#13;
The labor productivity gap between agriculture and other sectors&#13;
reaches a maximum and then begins to shrink, with an accelerated decline in&#13;
agriculture's share of the labor force.    Manufacturing's share of employment&#13;
rises further, while continuing slower growth of labor productivity in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
nontradeable sectors contributes to them eventually employing a majority of&#13;
the labor force. Changes in sectoral capital stock shares continue to be&#13;
smaller than changes in output and employment shares: the nontradeable&#13;
sectors (excluding housing) continue to account for more than 60 percent of&#13;
the total; increased agricultural mechanization moderates the decline in the&#13;
primary sector's share (to 10-15 percent) but the capital stock share of&#13;
manufacturing rises significantly.&#13;
Faster growth of capital per worker (due to slower labor force&#13;
growth and a higher investment rate), faster TFP growth in all sectors, and a&#13;
larger contribution of intersectoral resource shifts to aggregate TFP growth&#13;
combine to cause continued acceleration of labor productivity and per capita&#13;
income growth. At even higher income levels, the pace of growth, and that of&#13;
structural change, gradually slows down.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
Blades, D.W., and others (1974).   Service Activities in Developing Countries,&#13;
OECD.&#13;
Chenery, H.B., and L. Taylor (1968).   "Development Patterns:    Among Countries&#13;
and Over Time," Review of Economics and Statistics. November, pp. 391-&#13;
416.&#13;
Chenery, H.B. and M. Syrquin (1975).    Patterns of Development 1950-1970.&#13;
Oxford University Press.&#13;
Chenery, H.B. (1979). Structural Change and Development Policy. Oxford&#13;
University Press.&#13;
Chenery, H.B. and M. Syrquin (1980). "A Comparative Analysis of Industrial&#13;
Growth," in R.C.O. Matthews (ed.), Economic Growth and Resources, Volume&#13;
2:  Trends and Factors.   St. Martin's Press.&#13;
CRS (1986).  Chenery, H.B., S. Robinson and M. Syrquin.     Industrialization and&#13;
Growth: A Comparative Study. Forthcoming.&#13;
Hwa, E.C. (1983).   "The Contribution of Agriculture to Economic Growth:     Some&#13;
Empirical Evidence," World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 619.&#13;
Kravis, I.B., A. Heston and R. Summers (1982). World Product and Income.&#13;
Johns Hopkins University Press.&#13;
Kravis, I.B., A. Heston and R. Summers (1983).    "The Share of Services in&#13;
Economic Growth," in F.G. Adams and B.G. Hickman (eds.), Global&#13;
Econometrics. MIT Press.&#13;
Kubo, Y. (1981). "Interindustry Linkages and Industrial Development."&#13;
University of Tsukuba Discussion Paper No. 133.&#13;
Kuznets, S. (1966). Modern Economic Growth. Yale University Press.&#13;
Lluch, C., A. Powell and R. Williams (1977). Patterns in Household Demand and&#13;
Saving. Oxford University Press.&#13;
Nelson, R. (1981). "Research on Productivity Growth and Productivity&#13;
Differences: Dead Ends and New Departures," Journal of Economic&#13;
Literature. September.&#13;
Ofer, G. (1973). The Service Sector in Soviet Economic Growth. Harvard&#13;
University Press.&#13;
Ohkawa, K. and H. Rosovsky (1973). Japanese Economic Growth. Stanford&#13;
University Press.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
Prakash, V. and S. Robinson (1979). "A Cross-Country Analysis of Patterns of&#13;
Industrial Growth." Unpublished.&#13;
Stern, J.J. and J.D. Lewis (1980). "Employment Patterns and Income Growth."&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 419.&#13;
Syrquin, M. (1985).   "Patterns of Development Since 1960:    A Comparison for&#13;
China." Unpublished.&#13;
World Bank (985).   China:  Long-Term Issues and Options, Annex E:    China's&#13;
Economic Structure in International Perspective. Baltimore: Johns&#13;
Hopkins University Press; Annexes published separately (Washington, DC:&#13;
World Bank).&#13;
World Bank (1984). Comparative Study of the Sources of Industrial Growth and&#13;
Structural Change. World Bank Research Project 671-32.&#13;
World Development Report 1983. World Bank, Oxford University Press.&#13;
World Tables: The Second Edition (1980). World Bank, Johns Hopkins&#13;
University Press.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG 3881.5 .W57 W67 NO.763     (&#13;
C .3 &#13;
WOOD, ADRIAN.&#13;
GROWTH AND STRUCTURAL CHANGE&#13;
- IN LARGE LOW-INCOME&#13;
I   ,_ .~  .               . .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                         European Office              Tokyo Office&#13;
1818 H Street; N.W.                  66, avenue d'Ina            Kokusai Building&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.       75116 Paris, France          1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234            Telephone: (1) 47.23.54.21   Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK           Telex: 842-620628            Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                          Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTON DC&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0713-4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554699">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1986/02/1554699/growth-structural-change-large-low-income-countries
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1986/02/1554699/growth-structural-change-large-low-income-countries</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1986/02/1554699/growth-structural-change-large-low-income-countries</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/16/000178830_98101903433126/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/16/000178830_98101903433126/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-09-23T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1986-02-28T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Growth and structural change in large
            low-income countries
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper summarizes the results of
            empirical research on changes in the structure of
            expenditure, production, employment and investment in the
            course of economic development, with special reference to
            large countries at low to middle income levels. All the
            studies surveyed, however, relate to developing countries
            other than China. The objective is to identify regularities
            in the pattern of structural change elsewhere that might be
            relevant to China's future development.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Growth and structural change in large
            low-income countries
        </docna>
        <display_title>Growth and structural change in
            large low-income countries</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1986/02/1554699/growth-structural-change-large-low-income-countries</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Governance Indicators,Inequality,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Health Economics &amp; Finance</subtopic>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <count>China</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Wood, Adrian</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Asia!$!80460</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903433126</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Macro/non-trade</subsc>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 763</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0713-4</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Cross section analysis; Employment;
            Expenditures; Investment; Production; Structural adjustment;
            Time-series analysis
            aggregate,agricultural
            output,Agriculture,average income,basic metals,constant
            prices,construction,consumers,country size,cross-section
            data,Developing countries,development strategy,Domestic
            demand,Econometric models,economic development,Economic
            Strategies,Economic
            Structure,elasticities,elasticity,empirical
            research,equipment,exchange rates,Export
            growth,exports,Fish,Foreign Trade,GDP,GDP deflator,GNP,GNP
            per capita,government expenditures,growth,health
            care,Imports,income,income elasticity,income level,income
            levels,increasing share,industrialization,intermediate
            inputs,investment rates,labor force,Labor Productivity,low
            income,low- income countries,low-income
            countries,Metals,natural resources,net output,Oil,oil
            prices,output per capita,PER CAPITA INCOME,PER CAPITA INCOME
            LEVELS,poor countries,production
            increases,Productivity,Productivity Growth,Proportional
            increase,public expenditures,real income,regression
            results,relative importance,relative prices,resource
            endowments,savings,sectoral composition,structural
            change,Technological Change,time series,transfer payments,underestimates,unemployment,Urbanization
        </keywd>
        <owner>EAC</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP763</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technological Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation Equipment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative and Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Management and Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textiles</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technology Transfer and Diffusion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education and Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport Equipment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>China</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>