<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP591&#13;
A Relat:ionship between t]he Rate of Economic&#13;
Growth and the Rate, Allocation, and&#13;
Efficiency of Investment&#13;
Dennis Anderson&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 5'01&#13;
L.5&#13;
7&#13;
591&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 591&#13;
A Relationship between thte Rate of Economic&#13;
Growth and the Rate, Allocation, and&#13;
Efficiency of Investment&#13;
Dennis Anderson&#13;
* The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright © 1983&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development / THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
First printing May 1983&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To&#13;
present the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has&#13;
not been prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal&#13;
printed texts, and the World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The&#13;
publication is supplied at a token charge to defray part of the cost of&#13;
manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to&#13;
any individual acting on their behalf. Any maps used have been prepared&#13;
solely for the convenience of the readers; the denominations used and the&#13;
boundaries shown do not imply, on the part of the World Bank and its affiliates,&#13;
any judgment on the legal status of any territory or any endorsement or&#13;
acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications is described in the Catalog of World&#13;
Bank Publications; the continuing research program of the Bank is outlined in&#13;
World Bank Research Program: Abstracts of Current Studies. Both booklets are&#13;
updated annually; the most recent edition of each is available without charge&#13;
from the Publications Distribution Unit of the Bank in Washington or from the&#13;
European Office of the Bank, 66, avenue d'Iena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Dennis Anderson is a senior economist in the West Africa Projects&#13;
Department of the World Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Anderson, Dennis, 1937-&#13;
A relationship between the rate of economic growth&#13;
and the rate, allocation, and efficiency of investment.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 591)&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
Includes index.&#13;
1. Economic development--Mathematical moldels.&#13;
2. Capital investments--Mathematical models.&#13;
I. Title. II. Series.&#13;
HD75.5.A6   1983       339.5         83-6890&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0186-1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS&#13;
The preparatory work for this paper was begun while I was on&#13;
sabbatical leave at Queen Elizabeth House, Oxford. I am most grateful to&#13;
Arthur Hazlewood for his help and encouragement during my stay there, and&#13;
for arranging a seminar on the subject. Special words of thanks are extended&#13;
to Maurice Scott, for his comments on various notes and drafts, and for&#13;
generously guiding me through the manuscripts of his forthcoming book on the&#13;
subject; and to Ralph Turvey, both foX his encouragement and for his exceed-&#13;
ingly searching comments on the previous draft.&#13;
ABSTRACT&#13;
The paper derives the relationship described in the title and&#13;
then discusses how the methods and results of micro-economics might be&#13;
brought to bear on the analysis of growth. The approach is compared with&#13;
those of several long-standing studies on the subject. It is shown that&#13;
the "residual", i.e. the technical progress parameter in these studies turns out&#13;
not to be a parameter but a function of the rate of investment, the allocation of&#13;
:investment among economic activities, the rates of return to investment in&#13;
these activities, and variables representing the influence of investment on&#13;
:Labor's share in economic output. The weighted average returns to investment&#13;
implied by the approach are estimated for several countries and, it is suggested,&#13;
are' not inconsistent with project experience and with their observed growth&#13;
rates. As the argument is developed, an attempt is made to discuss the&#13;
relevance of the approach for the analysis of economic policy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS&#13;
ABSTRACT&#13;
I   INTRODUCTION   ....   .     .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .  1&#13;
Purpose of Paper . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .       1&#13;
Relation to Other Methods of Studying Growth .       . . . . . . . .   2&#13;
Organization of Paper ....    .     .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .  5&#13;
II  AN AGGREGATE FORM OF THE RELATIONSHIP BASED ON SOLOW'S VINTAGE&#13;
MODEL OF GROW,TH    ....  .     .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .  7&#13;
III DERIVATION OF THE RELATIONSHIP .12&#13;
The Relationship Based on Some Simplifying Assumptions. . . . .       12&#13;
Structural Change in the Relationship . . . . . . . . . . . . .       17&#13;
A More Generial Form.. .................                              20&#13;
IV  MICRO-ECONOMIC ANALYSIS AND THE ANALYSIS OF GROWTH      . . . . . .   22&#13;
Marginal Analysis.. ................                                  22&#13;
Non-Marginal Investments and Structural Change     . . . . . . . .    25&#13;
Conclusion..                 . ...............                        26&#13;
V   A COMPARISON WITH OTHER METHODS OF ACCOUNTING FOR GROWTH      . . .   28&#13;
Kuznets (1966) and Later Growth Accounting Studies     . . . . . .    28&#13;
Methods Using Incremental Capital-Output Ratios      . . . . . . .    31&#13;
Rates of Return and Growth: Estimates for Some Countries. . . .       31&#13;
VI  DOES THE ABSENSE OF A RESIDUAL IMPLY NC TECHNICAL PROGRESS? . .       37&#13;
VII CONCLUSIONS    .........................                          .   41&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. INTROI)UCTION&#13;
Purpose of Paper&#13;
In the analysis of economic growth, in the developing as in the&#13;
industrialized countries, the methods of micro-economic analysis for&#13;
appraising the efficiency of investments are rarely (if ever) used. One&#13;
reason for this, perhaps, is that a large number of studies have estimated&#13;
investment's contribution to growth to be comparatively minor. Typically only&#13;
about one quarter of economic growth in t:he industrialized countries is&#13;
attributed to material investment, perhaps another quarter or third to&#13;
investment in the education, or the "qua:Lity" of the labor force, and a large&#13;
measure of the remainder to exogenous technical progress, brought about by&#13;
comparatively small investments in research and development.l/ In the earlier&#13;
studies, before allowances were made for improvements in the quality of labor&#13;
force, over 80% of the measured increases in growth were attributed to&#13;
technical progress. 2/&#13;
The purpose of this paper is to derive and discuss a relationship&#13;
between the raLte of economic growth and variables representing the rate,&#13;
allocation and efficiency of investment. Following Maurice Scott's lead, 3/&#13;
there is no "residual" or trend term in i:he relationship to account for&#13;
technical progress. 4/ It is not that technical progress is held not to&#13;
occur, or that it is held to be possible without investment in research and&#13;
development, but rather that it is reflected in people's abilities, including&#13;
the abilities of those working in R and D, to find new forms of investment&#13;
offering positive rates of return once the previous investments have become&#13;
economically obsolete - for example, because of a rise in the costs of&#13;
labor.  Drawing on standard methods of investment analysis, the rate of&#13;
economic growth is related directly to economists' measures of the rate and&#13;
allocative efficiency of investment decisions. Further, it is shown that the&#13;
technical progress "parameter" that appears in both the economists' models of&#13;
growth, and their procedures for accounting for it, turns out not to be a&#13;
parameter but a simple function of the variables noted in the title. The&#13;
1/k The literature of the subject is huge, and one necessarily must start&#13;
with the pape]rs of those who have reviewed it: e.g., Nelson (1981), Binswanger&#13;
and Ruttan (1978), Kennedy and Thirlwall (1972), the long-standing survey of&#13;
Hahn and Matthews (1967), and the readings in Sen (1970) and Stiglitz and&#13;
Uzawa (1969). For historical and cross-country comparisons see Kuznets&#13;
(1966); for a review of material and a study on Japan see Nishimizu and Hulten&#13;
(1978), also Nishimizu and Jorgenson (1978) and Denison and Chung (1978); on&#13;
US estimates, Denison (1962 and 1974); on US and Europe, Denison (1967); and&#13;
on education, see Griliches (1970). A review is also provided in Maurice&#13;
Scott's forthcoming book on growth. The preceding list is unavoidably&#13;
selective, since the present paper is not a review; but the references cited&#13;
in the papers of these authors together provide a comprehensive bibliography.&#13;
2/   E.g., Solow (1957).&#13;
3t/  Scott (1981), and in his forthcoming book.&#13;
4/   As in any analysis, there may be a residual due to "errors and omissions"&#13;
or random factors. But in the above analysis, the errors and omissions appear&#13;
in the estimates of the rates of return, the rate of investment, or both.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
economic rate of return to investment is taken to be a measure of economic&#13;
efficiency, and can be estimated by the familiar methods of micro-economic&#13;
analysis; it is not difficult to reformulate the relationship in terms of the&#13;
more general measure, the net present value of investment, and the choice of&#13;
the former in this paper is a matter of convenience.&#13;
The analysis below departs in several respects from the types of&#13;
analysis followed in a number of influential studies on the subject. But I am&#13;
encouraged in the endeavor by the recent work of Maurice Scott, and by the&#13;
proposals of others for an approach towards the analysis of growth according&#13;
to the principles followed below. A further stimulus was provided by the&#13;
recent critique of research on productivity growth by Nelson (1981), who&#13;
called attention to the surprising fact that the role of efficient resource&#13;
allocation, and of the numerous economic, social, institutional and poLitical&#13;
influences that bear on it, has been given little weight by economists in&#13;
their theoretical and empirical work on growth over the past 25 years. He&#13;
proposed that "the reallocation of resources ought to be seen as a key process&#13;
in productivity growth which governs the pace at which potentialities opened&#13;
up by new technology can be exploited" (op. cit., p. 1054). At the risk of&#13;
lengthening the introduction, it is worth considering what other economists&#13;
have proposed in a similar vein.&#13;
Relation to Other Methods of Studying Growth&#13;
Nearly twenty years ago, Johnson suggested that the influence of&#13;
efficient resource allocation on growth would best be studied through "a&#13;
generalized capital accumulation approach towards economic development,"&#13;
observing that:l/&#13;
The growth of income that defines economic development&#13;
is necessarily the result of the accumulation of capital, or&#13;
of "investment"; but "investment" in this context must be&#13;
defined to include such diverse activities as adding to&#13;
material capital, increasing the health, discipline, skill&#13;
and education of the human population, moving labor into&#13;
more productive occupations and locations, and applying&#13;
existing knowledge or discovering and applying processes.&#13;
All such activities involve incurring costs, in the form&#13;
of use of current resources, and investment in them is&#13;
worth while if the rate of return over cost exceeds the&#13;
general rate of interest, or the capital value of the&#13;
additional income they yield exceeds the cost of obtaining&#13;
Lt. From the different perspective of planning, efficient&#13;
development involves allocation of investment resources&#13;
according to priorities set by the relative rates of&#13;
return on alternative investments.&#13;
Similarly, Schultz (1970, pp. 301-2), who refers to Johnson and&#13;
seemed to hope "that we have disposed of the residual", remarked that "the&#13;
growth problem, thinking in terms of economic decisions, requires an&#13;
investment approach to determine the allocation of investment resources in&#13;
/   Johnson (1964, p. 221).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
accordance with the priorities set by the relative rates of return on&#13;
alternative investment opportunities. It is applicable not only to private&#13;
decisions but, also, to public decisions ... for example, the investment in&#13;
research where the fruits of it do not accrue to the individual researcher or&#13;
his financial sponsor but are captured by many producers and consumers ... For&#13;
particular investments, and there are many areas in the domain of human&#13;
capital, the value of the resources added (services rendered) is exceedingly&#13;
hard to come by. It is all too convenient to leave the hard ones out, yet&#13;
each and every omission falsifies the true picture of the full range of&#13;
investment opportunities."&#13;
In these remarks Johnson and Schultz are explicit about the crucial&#13;
importance of a proper classification and ertumeraton of investment and&#13;
consumption activities, a task taken up by Scott in the references cited. A&#13;
large number (if not all?) of previous studies and the accounts data they use&#13;
are shown to be faulty in this respect. Mary expenditures commonly classified&#13;
as consumption, including (but not only) so-called capital consumption or&#13;
depreciation expenditures, turn out, on a closer inspection, to be a sacrifice&#13;
of consumption intended to raise economic output; that is, they would be&#13;
better classified as investments. As Scott remarks (op. cit., 1981, pp. 212-&#13;
213):&#13;
"In a static economic all output would be consumed and&#13;
investment would be zero. There would, of course, be expen-&#13;
diture on maintenance, but that should be regarded as part&#13;
of the current costs of production. If output is to grow, the&#13;
static economy must be changed.   It seems to me that this will&#13;
involve incurring expenditures which need not be incurred in a&#13;
static economy, for the building of new buildings, roads, vehicles,&#13;
machines, etc., and the improvement of existing ones, for moving&#13;
labor from places where its marginal product is low to where&#13;
it is high, for improving labor quality through better health,&#13;
education and skills, for developing new products, processes,&#13;
markets and sources of supply, and so on. All these changes&#13;
are costly, and so involve a present sacrifice of consumption&#13;
in the hope of subsequent gain."&#13;
While some of these expenditures, such as those on new buildings and machines,&#13;
might be thought to be counted as investment in most studies, in practice they&#13;
are often unwittingly netted out of the analysis by imprecise distinctions&#13;
between maintenance and depreciation; and the frequent use of the latter as an&#13;
estimate of the former again leads to underestimations of the proportion of&#13;
gross investment that is, on closer inspection, devoted to introducing&#13;
economic change and growth. It is true that some studies are more careful in&#13;
this respect, but Scott's review shows that the issues remain important&#13;
nevertheless.&#13;
Aside from the misclassification and underenumeration of investment&#13;
activities, further errors arise from the neglect of changes in the&#13;
occupations of the labor force brought about by material investment. Most&#13;
studies attempt to allow for such changes, but only for broadly defined&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
occupations--e.g., for the movement of workers from agriculture to industry,&#13;
defined at the one-digit level. The practice is broadly as follows.l/ The&#13;
labor force is grouped according to the occupations, educations and ages of&#13;
its male and female members. The contribution of labor to the growth of&#13;
income is then taken to be a weighted average of the rates of change of the&#13;
proportions of the labor force in each group, the weights being the average&#13;
incomes of labor in each group divided by national income per worker. Then&#13;
(i) if there is a net movement of workers from, say, agriculture to industry,&#13;
with wages being higher in industry, there is a rise in income attributable to&#13;
the redeployment of labor; (ii) if there is an increase in the proportion of&#13;
workers in the higher paid, higher educated groups, there is a rise in income&#13;
attributable to investment in education; (iii) if there is an increase in the&#13;
average age, such that a greater proportion is in the higher paid age groups,&#13;
there is a further rise attributable to the increased experience of the labor&#13;
force; and (iv) if there is an increase in the proportion of women in the&#13;
labor force, the average contribution of labor to the growth of income may be&#13;
estimated to fall, since women, within any particular education-age-occupation&#13;
group, are paid less than men. 2/&#13;
It is apparent that a greater disaggregation of occupational or&#13;
industrial groupings would show the rate of redeployment of the labor force,&#13;
and the increases in income derived from redeployment, to be significantly&#13;
greater than the analyses following the above approach have so far&#13;
concluded. Take manufacturing activities for example, which are treated as a&#13;
homogenous group in most studies. In the course of economic growth both the&#13;
size distribution and the composition of activities change appreciably over&#13;
time --e.g., from a concentration of employment in small scale cottage&#13;
industries and workshops in food processing, textiles, wearing apparel and&#13;
light engineering, towards a greater concentration on heavy engineering.3/&#13;
The earnings differentials between these activities for workers of a given age&#13;
and education are often large, e.g., over a 2 or 3 to one range as between&#13;
large and small firms in a given industry, 4/ and it follows that an&#13;
application of the above method of analysis would attribute some, if not a&#13;
large share of the observed increases of incomes of labor in manufacturing to&#13;
redeployment within manufacturing. Similar remarks can be made about changes&#13;
in the scale and composition of activities within agriculture (arising, e.g.,&#13;
from changes in produce over time), commerce (arising from changes in the&#13;
types and scales of retailing, wholesaling and banking activities for&#13;
example), transport and construction. Furthermore, each generation of the&#13;
labor force is continually redeploying itself through introducing new "high&#13;
technology" industries and products in the industrialized countries, or&#13;
1/   For a recent study see Nishimizu and Hulten (1978), and for an earlier&#13;
one, see Denison (1967).&#13;
2/   Schultz has questioned this last view of women's contribution to the&#13;
growth of economic output drawing attention to the "troublesome omission" of&#13;
investment in females and by them in the upbringing of children (op. cit. pp.&#13;
297-306).&#13;
3/   On the structural changes see e.g., Chenery (1979), Staley and Morse&#13;
(1965), Hoselitz (1959), Banerji (1978) and Anderson (1982).&#13;
4/   See e.g., Shinohara (1966) on wage differentials between large and small&#13;
firms in Japan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
diversifying the industrial base in the developing countries. Insofar as the&#13;
new industries are associated with higher earnings levels for workers in a&#13;
given age and education group, a redeployment of the labor force towards them&#13;
will again account for some of the observed increases of both labor's income&#13;
and value added.&#13;
It is unlikely, however, that a greater disaggregation of industries&#13;
or occupations, say to the 4 or 5 digit level, would provide a satisfactory&#13;
estimate of the rate of redeployment that takes place in a growing economy,&#13;
even assuming the formidable difficulties of data compilation could be&#13;
solved. The reason is that workers of a given age and education may be&#13;
redeployed by material investment without changing their industry or&#13;
occupation--or evien their place of employment. In agriculture, for example,&#13;
changes from rainfed to irrigation crops, from traditional to high yield seed-&#13;
Fertilizer varieties, from the use of bullocks to tractors, all bring about a&#13;
redeployment of agricultural labor, often without changing the crop variety.&#13;
It is not difficuLt to think of examples in other inddstries, each being&#13;
associated with a change in the nature of work, economic output and ultimately&#13;
labor's income.&#13;
If further disaggregation will not provide the necessary information&#13;
it is evidently desirable to consider another approach. As discussed later,&#13;
the increases in labor's income brought about by redeployment of the labor&#13;
force within the principal economic sectors may be comparable to those brought&#13;
about by redeployment between the sectors, and possibly greater. This is a&#13;
conclusion of some practical importance, and has been recognized in the&#13;
literature on development policy for some time(e.g., in the arguments for&#13;
rural-led industriLal growth). But it has yet to be reflected in growth theory&#13;
as the subject has developed over the past 25 years, or in the methods used in&#13;
growth accounting ,&#13;
The approach proposed in this paper is based on the net present&#13;
value of labor's share in the value added by investments. This quantity&#13;
provides a measure of the changes in labor's income brought about by the&#13;
redeployment of labor on the investments. Iit can be estimated from the series&#13;
on value added ancl wages and salaries for each sector of interest; evidence&#13;
from "samples" of investments in each sector would provide another source if&#13;
project studies are available. As will be sesen, it also fits quite simply&#13;
into the resource allocation framework for the study of growth and development&#13;
policies.&#13;
Organization of the Paper&#13;
To begin, Part II derives an aggregate form of the relationship&#13;
drawing on Solow's; vintage model of growth, as expounded in his book on growth&#13;
theory in 1970. T'his book contains a discussion of redeployment and wage&#13;
cletermination in the presence of technical clhange, and which it will be&#13;
helpful to lean orn in Part III.  The question is raised, what is the rate of&#13;
return to investment implied by the vintage model? In striving to answer it,&#13;
I arrive at an aggregate form of the relationship derived in Part III.&#13;
Part III shows that the rate of economic growth can be related to&#13;
the following prodluct: the rate of investment times a weighted average of the&#13;
economic rates of return to investment taken over all economic sectors. The&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
weights are each sector's share in total investment times a factor&#13;
representing the present value of labor's share in the output of the&#13;
investment. The rates of return and the weights indicate the allocative&#13;
efficiency with which capital and labor resources are deployed. Part IV,&#13;
which dicusses the applicability of the methods of micro economics to the&#13;
analysis of growth, argues that the relevant rate of return is the social&#13;
rather than the private return where the two differ.&#13;
Part V first compares the analysis with those of a number of&#13;
influential and long-standing growth accounting studies, such as those of&#13;
Kuznets and Denison. It then considers data on investment and growth for some&#13;
industrialized and developing countries, and asks if the economic rates of&#13;
return implied by the relationship are implausibly high, as Denison and others&#13;
have suggested they would be. In this I am again following Maurice Scott's&#13;
lead, and reach the same conclusion.1/ Part VI considers the question, does&#13;
the absence of a residual (since there is none in the accounting definitions&#13;
used in this paper) imply no technical progress? and, by refe-ence to Solow's&#13;
vintage and non-vintage models, concludes that it does not. Part VII presents&#13;
the conclusions.&#13;
Op. cit., 1981.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
II - AN AGGREGATE FORM OF THE RELATIONSHIP&#13;
BASED ON SOLOW'S VINTAGE MODEL OF GROWTH I/&#13;
In this model, technical progress is assumed to be labor augmenting,&#13;
increasing output per worker at a given rate denoted by 100 b percent per&#13;
year. The output per worker for an investment introduced in year v would then&#13;
be bo(l + b)v,, where bo is the output in the base year. (I have changed&#13;
Solow's notation slightly, and am working with discrete, one year time&#13;
intervals instead of continuous time.) The output per worker in the oldest&#13;
vintage of investments (age n) in the economy would then be bo(l + b)v-n while&#13;
that of some intermediate vintage would be somewhere in between this and bo(1&#13;
+ b)v. This is illustrated in figure 1, which shows the output per worker for&#13;
different vintages from (v-n) to v, arranged in ascending order of their&#13;
outputs per worker.   The labor force in v, denoted by L , is deployed on these&#13;
various vintages of plant as indicated oni the horizontaL axis; the total&#13;
output in the economy is represented by the area under the (stepped) curve,&#13;
and the quasi-rent on any given vintage of plant is, by definition, the&#13;
difference between the total output on that vintage and the wage bill, again&#13;
as indicated.&#13;
To continue the analysis, if a new vintage of investments is&#13;
introduced in the following year with oul:puts of b o(l + b)v , they would, on&#13;
these assumptions, have higher quasi-rent:s. If the labor force were either&#13;
fully employecd, or alternatively if the 'Labor requirements of the new vintages&#13;
exceeded unemployment levels plus the number of new entrants to the labor&#13;
force, then labor would have to be redep:Loyed from existing investments. As&#13;
Solow explains, in any competitive econotay, or in any planned economy&#13;
maximizing output per worker, they would become redeployed from the oldest&#13;
investments, which would be duly retired.   Further, in a competitive economy,&#13;
wages would be bid up to the point where the quasi-rents of the oldest&#13;
(marginal) investments remaining in operation were zero (or close to zero).&#13;
That is, the output per worker on the oldest investments determines the wage&#13;
rate, which rises whenever those investments are displaced by, and labor is&#13;
redeployed on, new investments. In explaining this, Solow considers the case&#13;
history of a single factory as follows:2/&#13;
"when it is new it earns profits equal to the difference&#13;
between its productive capacity and its wage bill.    As it&#13;
ages, its productive capacity iis unimpaired and its ouput&#13;
per man is unchanged. But if, as is normal, the real wage&#13;
rises through time because of t:echnological progress and&#13;
the competition of newer and more efficient factories, its&#13;
bill will rise and its profits will diminish. Eventually the&#13;
wage! rises as high as the outpuxt per man in this factory and&#13;
it bLas become the marginal no-rent factory. Let the wage go&#13;
a tcouch higher, and this factory goes out of business; it has&#13;
become obsolete, not because oi' any reduction in its efficiency,&#13;
but because the rising real wage has rendered it incapable&#13;
of covering its own variable costs of production."&#13;
1/   As presented in Chapter III of his book :Ln 1970. A note on his earlier&#13;
non-vintage model is provided in Part VI of this paper.&#13;
2/   op. cit., p. 47.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
Figure 1:&#13;
Solow's Vlntage Model: Ernployment,&#13;
ProductMdy, Wages and Quasi-Rents for&#13;
SuccessNe Vintages of Investrents&#13;
Value ardded&#13;
(net od&#13;
maintenance)&#13;
- bo(i + b)V+'&#13;
b.(1 +b) - --  _______________ - &#13;
b4i + b)v-n___                                         ,&#13;
-RAE t&#13;
Lv (no vakefs enaIolod In v)  (ra deie on new v*nte)&#13;
"iue 2:&#13;
As above, but with low rates of&#13;
r8dePloWIment of te labor force on new&#13;
lrwesrnts (Large shams of labor force&#13;
an "old" vIntoges)&#13;
Vaue aodded&#13;
(neo d&#13;
-------- T---------------------           1-&#13;
oddoct Pe        I&#13;
wltoreIncl                 n   ae         nv &#13;
maboditennarc&#13;
aclttitles&#13;
L v (no WOeIn ernoflted In v)      no (nae -ennwv1ntoge)&#13;
Word8at*-24711&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
The only point one might add to this is that "old" factories may continue to operate&#13;
in these circumstances by introducing the new methods of production, i.e., new&#13;
vintages, themselves--that is, by redeploying their own workers. As noted in the&#13;
introduction, It is these changes that growth accounting studies commonly neglect.&#13;
It is of course possible that the technological characteristics of new&#13;
investments may be such that they redeploy very little labor (the new "blocks" in&#13;
figure 1 becoming increasingly narrow and taLl). In this case the wage rate would&#13;
barely increase. If in addition the labor force is expanding quickly, the majority&#13;
of its members may be working with exceedingLy old methods of production with low&#13;
levels of labor productivity, as illustrated in figure 2. This is indeed the&#13;
situation of many developing countries today, as one might gather from the extensive&#13;
literature concerning the choice of "appropriate" technologies and the case for more&#13;
labor demanding investment incentives in industry and agriculture. For the moment,&#13;
however, let us proceed with the conditions where real wages are rising and labor is&#13;
being redeployed from the older, lower productivity investments, which are being&#13;
displaced.&#13;
We now consider the question, what is the rate of return to investment&#13;
implied by Solow's vintage model? To answer this it is necessary to compare the&#13;
present worth of the quasi-rents with the investment costs. To simplify algebra,&#13;
the lead time of investment is ignored.l/ For investments introduced in year v, the&#13;
present worth of quasi-rents per worker employed on them at a discount rate of r per&#13;
year, is given by:&#13;
n             n&#13;
-bo (l+b)v  E  (l+r) -t_  E wv+t (l+r) t&#13;
t=1           t=1&#13;
From the above explanation of wage determination in the vintage model, the&#13;
wage level in any period is causally related to the rate of investment.     In the&#13;
present case:&#13;
wt+v - b (lqb)v+t-n&#13;
t   0&#13;
that is wt+V is determined by the output per worker of investments about to be&#13;
retired as a result of the new investments.    On substituting for w     in the&#13;
previous expression, it becomes apparent that the ratio of the secotn term to the&#13;
first term, that is to say, the PW of labor's share in the value added by the&#13;
investment taken over the lifetime of the investment, depends only on b, and under&#13;
conditions of steady growth is constant. Let us denote this ratio by X 2/.&#13;
1/   Inclusion of lead times in the analysis is discussed in Part III.&#13;
2/   It is apparent that there is a close relation between X and the more&#13;
commonly used quantity, labor's share in current output which is denoted in&#13;
this paper by X,'. After substituting for wt+v and simplifying (the E's are&#13;
over 1 to n):&#13;
[E(1+b)t/('1r) t]/[E(l+r) t] l+b]&#13;
For relatively slow rates of growth of the labor force, labor's share in&#13;
current output turns out to be (theE's are again over 1 to n) :&#13;
X' = nb (1+b), n/b (1+b)v t = n/[E (l+b) t][l+b]n&#13;
For given r and b, the ratio ofA toV'is constant. A more precise expression&#13;
is given in the following footnote.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
(Note that even if growth is not steady, there is still a causal relationship&#13;
between the two terms on account of investment's influence on wages and thus on&#13;
labor's share in value added; in Parts III and V further use is made of this&#13;
relationship.) Hence the expression becomes:&#13;
n&#13;
(1-X) bo (1+b)v   E  (1+r)ft                         (1)&#13;
1&#13;
To obtain the total investment per worker in v, it is first necessary to&#13;
determine the total output per worker and multiply this by the rate of investment,&#13;
denoted here by i. In turn, this requires some assumptions about how the labor&#13;
force employed in v, denoted here by Lv, is deployed on the various vintages of&#13;
investments. Let c be the rate of growth of the employed labor force and Ev the&#13;
number employed on the vintages introduced in v. Then&#13;
n&#13;
Lv =       E v-t&#13;
t=l&#13;
If we take the case where the rate of redeployment EV/Lv is constant, we can write&#13;
Ev_t in the form EV(1 + c) t . 1/ Substituting into the above expression and&#13;
summating the series gives:&#13;
Ev =cL /(1     (1 + c)  )&#13;
(1/n)Lv, if c is small.2/&#13;
The total output in v is equal to the total output per worker on each vintage of&#13;
plant in use in v, namely bo(l+b)v t, multiplied by the number of workers on each&#13;
vintage, namely Ev_t, added up over all vintages t = 1....n.    The total investment&#13;
in v is then the resulting expression multiplied by i, namely:&#13;
n&#13;
iE b (1+b)v-t   Ev(1+c) t                          (2)&#13;
t=l&#13;
1/   This expression is consistent with one of the "stylized facts" of growth&#13;
with which Solow is concerned, namely the approximate constancy of labors'&#13;
share over time. At time v, the wage bill is given by:&#13;
n&#13;
b0(1+b)v-nEv E (+c     t&#13;
while total output is given by:&#13;
n&#13;
E EV(l+c) tbo(l+b)v-t&#13;
Taking the ratio and simplifying leads to the following expression for labor's&#13;
share:&#13;
= (1+b) n(1-(1+c) n)(b+c)/c(1-(1+b+c) n)&#13;
which reduces to the expression in the previous footnote for small c.&#13;
2/   As discussed in Part I, the rate of redeployment Ev/L    2 (1/n) may&#13;
significantly exceed the rate of growth of the labor Torce, c, in regions of&#13;
economic growth. E.g. in high growth economies, the average lifetime of&#13;
investments may be in the range 10 to 15 years, from which the rate of&#13;
redeployment of the labor force (under the conditions assumed) would be around&#13;
7 to 10% per year.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
The present worth of total output from the investment, on the other hand, is (1)&#13;
multiplied by the number of workers engaged on it, E .    If we now choose the&#13;
discount rate such that it is the same as the rate oY return on the investments,&#13;
then by definition of this quantity we can set (2) equal to (1) times Ev; that is,&#13;
we choose r such ithat the present worth of the quasi-rents from the investments&#13;
equals the costs of the investments. Doing this, using the approximation (l+b)t&#13;
(1+r) t   (1+b+r) t, and rearranging leads to&#13;
(b+c) = g = air/(l- X)                (3)&#13;
where a    (1-(l+g) n)/(1-(1+r) n)&#13;
and g is the rate of economic growth. (The term in the numerator of a represents&#13;
the loss of outpult from the retirement of old investments, and the denominator the&#13;
"iend correction", familiar from project analysis, which allows for the discounting&#13;
of the output of investments over a finite lifetime. To a good approximation a is&#13;
likely to be a constant even when r and g change    slowly  1/, and we will refer to&#13;
it, perhaps imprecisely, as a parameter.)&#13;
Hence we have an accounting identity in which the rate of economic growth&#13;
is related to the rate of investment, the present worth of labor's share in the&#13;
value added by investment, and the economist's commonly used measure of economic&#13;
efficiency, the rate of return to investment. In earlier growth accounting studies,&#13;
the "contribution" of investment was taken to be given by the product ir, but as&#13;
will be discussed in Part V, this significantly understates investment's&#13;
contribution to growth because a cross-derivative, namely the change in labor's&#13;
income brought about by investment, is neglected. In other words, the product ir is&#13;
based on the partial derivative of the inrease in output with respect to investment,&#13;
holding labor's income constant, while (3) is based on the total derivative, in&#13;
which the change in labor's income induced by investment is included. This is the&#13;
reason why the term (1-X) appears in the denominator above.&#13;
The preceding relationship is obviously too aggregative to apply to&#13;
examine the influence of resource allocation on growth. The lead times of&#13;
investments have also been neglected. Consider now how these limitations might be&#13;
addressed.&#13;
/   r and g also move in the same directions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
III DERIVATION OF THE RELATIONSHIP&#13;
The Relationship Based on Some Simplifying Assumptions&#13;
In the following analysis, the level and change in economic output (value&#13;
added) is considered to be the aggregate of the levels and changes in the output of&#13;
all investments in use in an economy. Throughout, the analysis allows for changes&#13;
in relative prices but ignores inflation or deflation; that is, it is couched in&#13;
terms of "real" prices. To begin, it is also convenient to introduce the following&#13;
simplifying assumptions:&#13;
-the case where the cost and revenue streams of an invest-&#13;
ment provide a satisfactory basis for estimating its contri-&#13;
bution to economic output. That is, consumers' surplus,&#13;
externalities, and distortions in the pricing system are at&#13;
first ignored and discussed later (in Part IV);&#13;
-the revenue and cost streams have a fairly simple form;&#13;
-departures between ex post and ex ante returns are&#13;
ignored, and the analysis at first concentrates on&#13;
ex post returns only.&#13;
Let X   denote the gross output of an investment in year v, and atv the&#13;
sum of materialitnputs and maintenance costs per unit of output.    Alternatively, Xtv&#13;
can denote a group of comparable investments within a narrowly defined sector, with&#13;
v again being the year in which they are brought into service. Later we shall&#13;
identify such a sector by introducing an additional subscript, j ; but to economize&#13;
on notation, the subscript is not introduced until needed. Then the contribution of&#13;
the investment to value added in year t, denoted by Ytv, is given by:&#13;
Ytv   (1 - atv) Xtv&#13;
Similarly, let E be the number of people employed to produce output from&#13;
the investment. They may include one or more of the following:&#13;
-new entrants to the labor force and employed for the first&#13;
time as a consequence of the investment;&#13;
-people who have been redeployed within their present places&#13;
of work to use the investment; e.g., those previously making&#13;
products, providing services or using technologies and&#13;
methods of organizing their work that have been changed by&#13;
the investment;&#13;
-people redeployed from other occupations or places of&#13;
employment and who may or may not have been unemployed&#13;
during the transition.&#13;
In any economy in which the productivity of a large proportion of its labor force is&#13;
rising it is likely that the rate of redeployment would be far greater than the rate&#13;
of increase in the labor force, since even quite minor investments may introduce&#13;
changes in the nature of the work and in the productivity of people already&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
employed, as noted in the introduction.&#13;
If' then wiV represents the average annual earnings per person employed on&#13;
the investment, the net revenues (quasi-rents) in each year are given by:&#13;
(Ytv - Ev wtv)&#13;
For fixed assets, the investment expenditures are often incurred over&#13;
several years, or over what is sometimes called the lead time or gestation period of&#13;
the investments. Let the total investment over this period be denoted by Iv. Most&#13;
series on investment expenditures do not include what in physical investment is&#13;
often termed "interest during construction", or perhaps more simply as the costs of&#13;
financing the investment expenditures during this period. These costs are simple to&#13;
estimate however from a knowledge of the profile of investment expenditures over&#13;
time. Expressing them in per unit terms by dividing by Iv, and denoting the&#13;
resulting ratio by f, then by definition the discounted value of the investment&#13;
expenditures, referred to the time when the investment is brought into service, is&#13;
given by (1 + f)Iv&#13;
Denoting the rate of return to the investment by r, then by definition of&#13;
this quantity:&#13;
v+n                    v+n&#13;
(1+f)IV =z Yt     (1+r)-(t-v)     E Ev w   (1+r)-(t-v)&#13;
tv+l                  t=v+l    t&#13;
where n is the economic life of the investment, and is determined by the time at&#13;
which the quasi-rents have declined to zero. Note that since Ytv is net of&#13;
maintenance costs the relevant measure of Iv to be used in the above relation is&#13;
vross investment.   1/&#13;
To put the equation into a form where it can be manipulated for use in the&#13;
analysis of growth it is helpful to introduce some approximations with respect to&#13;
the variations over time of revenues and costs.     There are obviously a large number&#13;
of possibilities, but the profiles shown in figure 3 capture the main elements of&#13;
most, which are the lead time (or construction or gestation period), the rise and&#13;
then the decline of value added and quasi-rents, and finally the retirement of the&#13;
investments. If the data were available for samples of actual investments from each&#13;
economic sector, it would be possible to work with the actual profiles in equations&#13;
of the above form, and use the methods of numerical analysis to estimate the&#13;
contribution of the! investments to the growth of output. But in the absence of&#13;
this, it is easier to work with the stylized version shown in the lower of the two&#13;
diagrams.   In this version, Ytv is constant over the period v+1 to v+n and is now&#13;
denoted by Yv; it is the value added by the investments after they have been fully&#13;
brought into service.&#13;
In figure! 3, the wage bill is also taken to be rising over time such that,&#13;
eventually, the quasi rent declines to zero and the investment is retired. The&#13;
quasi rents may of course decline for other reasons - changes in the relative prices&#13;
of material inputs, for example, or due to changes in demand. But for the moment,&#13;
let us concentrate on wages. The basic assumption is that, as in Part II, new&#13;
investments are being introduced in times t&gt;v, labor is being redeployed on them&#13;
/   In this I am following Maurice Scott (1981, and in his forthcoming book).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
Fgure 3:&#13;
Valations Over nme of Costs, Gross Output, Intermediate&#13;
Inputs, Value Added, Wage Bill and Quasl-Rents&#13;
of an Investmrent&#13;
ACTUALVARIATIONS:&#13;
Cash&#13;
Rows--&#13;
-Gross Output&#13;
Value Added&#13;
Wage Blil (times minus one)&#13;
Rents                                     +n&#13;
---o_ Time&#13;
Expenditures on&#13;
IMaintenance and&#13;
Intermediote Inputs&#13;
t = v-I ~~ExpendHwes&#13;
1,ead irne  D                    Economic Ufetitne&#13;
Cash&#13;
Flows/5                                 SrYLISED FORM OF ABOVE:&#13;
Gro output&#13;
r--- ------&lt;&#13;
Value Added&#13;
'N aeBill (times minus one)&#13;
Time&#13;
Expenditures on Maintenance&#13;
Investment Expenditures                        and Intermediate Inputs&#13;
World Bonk-24712&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
from old investments, whose quasi rents have declined to zero, and the wage levels&#13;
are related to the output per worker on these old investments.&#13;
As noted in the introduction, this process of redeployment has two&#13;
components. The first is redeployment withirn sectors, as labor moves from the use&#13;
of old to new vintages of investments; the second is redeployment across sectors as&#13;
a consequence, for example, of the emergence and growth of new kinds of economic&#13;
activities and products and the displacement of old ones. Both may be associated&#13;
with changing shares of the labor force in th,e various sectors of an economy. Thus&#13;
the number of workers deployed on a new investment in a particular sector, denoted&#13;
above by Ev, will generally differ, except by chance, from the number of workers&#13;
deployed on investments in the same sector n years earlier, Ev_n, and which are&#13;
about to be retired. A lot will depend, of course, on the nature and extent of&#13;
structural changes taking place in an economy.    Thus (Ev.n - E ) would be redeployed&#13;
elsewhere if E     exceeds E , as happens for example in agricuYture as&#13;
industrialization procedes in developing countries; while (Ev - E     ) would be&#13;
redeployed from elsewhere if the sector is expanding relative to Vtoers. But for&#13;
our present purposes, the important point is that, as a consequence of this process&#13;
of redeployment, the wage bill is taken to rise over time on any particular vintage&#13;
of investment (in regions of economic growth) and the quasi rent to decline as&#13;
indicated.&#13;
As in Part II, let X denote the present value of labor's share in the&#13;
value added by the investment, using r as the discount rate. It is the second term&#13;
divided by the first on the RHS of the above equation. The above expression then&#13;
becomes (after substituting for Yv and simplifying):-&#13;
(1+f) Iv = (1-X) Yv (l-(l+r)-n)/r                (4)&#13;
As the quantity has been defined above, Yv is strictly the gross increase&#13;
in value added, net of maintenance costs, in year v. To arrive at the net increase&#13;
in value added (net of maintenance costs) it is necessary to deduct from this the&#13;
value added by the investments that are to be taken out of service in v as a&#13;
consequence of new investment. For such investments, the quasi-rents would have&#13;
declined to zero, and their total value added (net of maintenance) would just be&#13;
sufficient to cover labor costs, as indicated in the lower diagram of figure 3. In&#13;
practice few investments are retired so abruptly but rather are "run down" towards&#13;
the end of their economic lifetime, with the labor working on them being gradually&#13;
redeloyed to other, generally newer investments. Hence just before retirement they&#13;
may be generating little or no output and providing little or no employment at all,&#13;
as indicated in the upper diagram. However, in the years preceding retirement both&#13;
the value added and net revenues would be declining, and it is necessary to make&#13;
some allowance for this. The required allowance depends on the nature of the&#13;
economic changes taking place in the sector over the period of interest.&#13;
If for instance there has been a period of steady growth in the industry&#13;
or sector in question, at a rate of lOOg % per year, then the output of investments&#13;
introduced n years earlier, and which are about to be retired, would have been&#13;
(l+g) -n times that of current investments. Hence the net increase in value&#13;
added in year v, denoted by YV* would be:&#13;
Yv = (1 - (l+,,)-n) yv&#13;
This is the same term that appeared in the elementary manipulation in Part II of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
Solow's vintage model of growth; for convenience it is used in the analysis of this&#13;
paper, but with the following qualification.&#13;
This is that, if the growth rate and the economic lifetimes of investments&#13;
are changing in a particular sector - as of course they do in conditions of rapid&#13;
structural change - the above term is at best an approximation. Moreover, and&#13;
particularly in developing regions, net increases in value added may be&#13;
discontinuous and not simple to formulate algebraically: e.g. the transition from&#13;
traditional seed varieties and methods of cultivation in rural areas, in which g may&#13;
have been zero and n large over a long period, to high yield seed-fertilizer&#13;
varieties, irrigation and more mechanized methods of cultivation, in which g is&#13;
positive and n relatively short. If we are concerned with the analysis of growth&#13;
over relatively short periods, say of about 20 years, then it may be possible to&#13;
take g and n to be approximately constant over those periods.   If not, however, or&#13;
if changes have been more abrupt, then there would seem no alternative than to&#13;
examine the rate of retirement of investments directly, along with the influence of&#13;
this on the net increase economic output.&#13;
Substituting for Yv* and rearranging (4) we then have:&#13;
Yv*   Iv.r.a/(1-X)              (5)&#13;
where a = (1+f) (I _ (1+g)-n)/(1-(1+r)-n), and is similar to the term defined in&#13;
Part II, differing only because it now allows for the financing costs associated&#13;
with the gestation period of the investment.&#13;
To procede from (5) to the relationship we are seeking, it is necessary to&#13;
consider how the total expenditures, Iv, on investments brought into service in v,&#13;
are related to the annual rate of investment. The reason is essentially an&#13;
operational one in that series are usually published on the latter but not on the&#13;
former quantity; otherwise, we could procede with the analysis using Iv as defined&#13;
above. Using the annual rate of investment unavoidably introduces some&#13;
aproximations into the analysis. Where it might be felt that the approximations&#13;
discussed are unreliable, the right approach would be to reclassify annual&#13;
investment expenditures for the industry or sector in question according to the&#13;
vintages of the investments with which they are associated. Since this evidently&#13;
would be an arduous task, it seems appropriate to search for some procedure that&#13;
would permit the use of existing series while making clear the nature of the&#13;
approximations involved.&#13;
The difficulty arises from the point that in any year t, and for any&#13;
particular sector, investments will be in progress whose first year of output will&#13;
be t+1 for those nearing completion, t+Q years later for those just being started,&#13;
and t+2 to t+Q-1 years later for those at some intermediate stage.    Suppose the&#13;
investment expenditures, Iv, are distributed over the gestation period according to&#13;
the shares al, a2 ... a9, with (a, + a2 .... + aQ)= 1, so that a, Iv are the&#13;
expenditures (excluding financing costs) in the firstyear, a ?I are the&#13;
expenditures in the second year, and so forth. (In the stylize3 form of figure 3,&#13;
all the a's are equal; but this approximation is not used below.) If the a's are&#13;
similar for investments brought i?ito service over the years v-Q +1,....v,....v+Q -1,&#13;
then the following are the annual investment expenditures, denoted by Iv*, over the&#13;
period (v-Q +1) to v:-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
I*    a1   +a    a I&#13;
v     2 tv +-i -v+1a --------------   a I&#13;
I*_   =  a I        +a   I             alI&#13;
v-Q+1     2t v- Q+1 +aQ Z v-2.++l      1 v&#13;
The RHS of each of these expressions is of the order of Iv, since the a's&#13;
add up to unity, the first being somewhat greater than Iv if investment in the&#13;
sector or industry is expanding, the last being correspondingly less; and conversely&#13;
if it is contracting. This suggests the approximation, after adding the expressions&#13;
together and dividing by Q :-&#13;
I  =1 (Iv* + Iv,                v-* +1)&#13;
That is, Iv corresponds approximately to the average annual level of investment in&#13;
the sector over the period spanned by the leacL time of the investment. We denote&#13;
this quantity by Iv *.&#13;
Substituting for Iv in (5) we now hetve&#13;
Yv = Iv* r a/(1-X )&#13;
The sum of Yv* over all sectors of etconomic activity represents the net&#13;
increase in economic output in the economy in year v, while the sum of Iv* over all&#13;
sectors represents total investment . Introducing the subscript j to denote sector&#13;
j, noting that r, c,X and Iv* all may differ between sectors, and adding over j:&#13;
E Y.*  =(     *)    {!.*/Z 1.*Ir joj/(l-X;&#13;
J          ivJV    j JV   JV  JJ      J&#13;
The first term within the summation is evidently the share of the sector&#13;
in total investment over the period (v-Q +1) to v, which we denote by s..     Dividing&#13;
through by the total value added in the econony in v gives:-&#13;
g   i E r siao/( -X.)                         (6)&#13;
where g is the rate of economic growth and i is a measure of the average rate of&#13;
gross investment.&#13;
This is the relationship noted in the introduction. Before relaxing the&#13;
simplifying assumptions stated earlier, to arrive at a more general form of (6), it&#13;
might be helpful to comment on the behaviour of the relationship when the variables&#13;
on RHS are changing over time. In growing economies the variables that perhaps&#13;
change most noticeably are the sectoral shares and the relative rates of return to&#13;
investment, so we confine our attention to these.&#13;
Structural Change in the Relationship&#13;
The term structural change is commonly associated with changes in the&#13;
shares of output, employment and investment in the various sectors of economic&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
activity 1/, for example the rise in industry's shares with growth and the fall in&#13;
agriculture's shares.  It may also occur within sectors such as with the growth of&#13;
'heavy ' relataive to 'light' industry as industrialization procedes, and with the&#13;
emergence of new industries and products that had not existed previously.2/ With&#13;
sufficient disaggregation, many of these changes within sectors would be re-&#13;
classified as cross-sector changes and would become apparent, in the above&#13;
relationship, in the relative values of the sj's.&#13;
Two types of structural change are illustrated respectively in figures 4&#13;
and 5. The first is one in which one kind of economic activity or method of&#13;
production is contracting and being displaced by another, which is expanding.&#13;
Examples might be the replacement of steam by electric power in factories, of draft-&#13;
animals by tractors in agriculture, and of sea-passenger by air-passenger&#13;
transport. In the second, one industry is maturing and is either constant in size&#13;
or expanding only slowly relative to a newly emerging high growth industry.&#13;
In the first example, the variations in gross output over time in the two&#13;
industries are shown in figure 4a, and the schedules of new investments in years v&#13;
and v+1 are shown below it in 4b. These schedules represent the rates of return to&#13;
investments introduced in years v and v+1, ranked in descending order of their rates&#13;
of return. Since figure 4b is for a contracting industry, the schedule for year v+1&#13;
is shown below that for year v; the opposite applies to the schedules shown in&#13;
figure 4c for the expanding industry. Note that in the former case, new investment&#13;
possibilities are taken to exist for a period even though the industry is&#13;
contracting; that is, the investment schedule is assumed to decline steadily rather&#13;
than to vanish or fall abruptly below the opportunity cost of capital.3/&#13;
What happens to the rates of return to investment in the two industries?&#13;
If capital markets are functioning efficiently and investors make decisions&#13;
according to the expected rates of return to investment, the ex ante returns on the&#13;
marginal projects in the two industries would be the same and equal to the&#13;
opportunity cost of capital (shown as r in the figures). Ex post returns will&#13;
generally differ from these, however, for the obvious reason that perfect forecasts&#13;
are impossible; but if the forecasts on which the investment&#13;
decisions were based are unbiased, then over a period one might expect the ex post&#13;
returns on the marginal projects in the two industries to be equal on average.&#13;
The above relationship, however, is concerned with the returns to all&#13;
investments in each industry in the years in question rather than with the marginal&#13;
returns.  In other words it is better to think of the r 's as being average&#13;
values. This variable may of course differ appreciably between sectors even when&#13;
marginal values are comparable, but in a way that is difficult to determine&#13;
theoretically. Intuitively, in a rapidly expanding industry one would generally&#13;
expect the average returns to be higher, that is, for the investment schedules shown&#13;
in figure 4c to be steeper. If in addition there are uncertainties and difficulties&#13;
in transferring finance to the new industries, there may be a rental element, which&#13;
would tend to raise further the average rates of return in the expanding industry&#13;
relative to those in the contracting industry.&#13;
1/   See e.g. Chenery (1979) and Kuznets, op.cit. 1966.&#13;
2/   See especially Kuznets (1971), table 47 pp. 316-318, and the accompanying&#13;
discussions.&#13;
3/   This again seems to be a matter of experience. Ibid.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-19-&#13;
Figure 4                                  Rgure 5&#13;
Gross                                                           (a)&#13;
Output                (a)                                        (a)&#13;
New "High Growth" Industry&#13;
Industry;&#13;
"Maturing" Industry&#13;
Time (v)                                  Time (v)&#13;
Rate of           (b) Investment Schedules                (b) Investment Schedules&#13;
Return to           of Contracting Industry                 of "Maturlng" Industiy&#13;
Investment&#13;
Opportunity Cost of Capitol&#13;
,  Year v&#13;
Yer +Year v + I&#13;
Yearv +1                                 Year v&#13;
Rate of            (c) Investment Schedules                 (c) Investment Schedules&#13;
Return to             of Expanding Indust,y                       of New Industry&#13;
Investment\\&#13;
--   \     Opportunity Cost of Capital           -v&#13;
\ Year v                       \W&#13;
World Bank-24713&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
Turning to the second case, in which one industry is "maturing", the&#13;
difference is that innovation continues in this industry and, with it, the&#13;
possibilities remain for new investment with rates of return greater than the&#13;
opportunity costs of capital. That is, the investment schedule may not contract&#13;
significantly; it may even move outwards, as in figure 5b. The associated changes&#13;
in the investment shares are obviously less than in the first case. The points to&#13;
be made about relative rates of return are similar.&#13;
A More General Form&#13;
So far the cost and revenue streams of investments have been taken to have&#13;
a simple form, with the yearly value added by each investment being constant over&#13;
its economic lifetime once it has been brought into service. Furthermore, the only&#13;
changes in relative prices that were considered were those between labor and all&#13;
other inputs and outputs. These obviously restrictive assumptions need to be&#13;
removed:&#13;
-the value added each year by any investment may change&#13;
appreciably over economic cycles, and also exhibit some&#13;
randomness (e.g. on account of the weather's influence on&#13;
crop and energy prices); it may also change over time with&#13;
"learning by doing" and with the experience of the labor force&#13;
working on the new vintages of investments;&#13;
-changes in the terms of trade affect the relative prices&#13;
of inputs and outputs for many commodities and services;&#13;
-scarcities may develop in the supply of certain factors;&#13;
and&#13;
-innovation may change the relative prices of several inputs&#13;
and outputs.&#13;
In addition, the analysis was concerned with the rate of growth of output at a&#13;
particular time. Studies of growth however are usually concerned with the&#13;
underlying rate of growth of economies over long periods, in which r.,s ,    and i&#13;
might vary appreciably. Hence it is necessary to reformulate the re4iationship in&#13;
more general terms.&#13;
To begin, the accounting identity given in (4) can be rewritten in the&#13;
form:-&#13;
v+n               t      v&#13;
( +   v   v IV (1 O  'v ) E Ytv (1 + rv)t    v)          (7)&#13;
t=v+1&#13;
where, to be general, subscripts v have been attached to those quantities that may&#13;
vary between vintages of investments. The possibility of variations over time in&#13;
the output of an investment of vintage v are acknowledged by reintroducing the&#13;
subscript t in the variable Ytv. As before, the subscript j is omitted until&#13;
needed.&#13;
To simplify the term on the RHS, we can define a weighted average value of&#13;
Ytv,denoted by Y , as follows, in which the discount factors are the weishts:&#13;
y       (1+  )-(t-v)  =      Y    (+r )-(t-v)&#13;
vt=v+l     V           t=v+l  tv     v&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
Note that Yv is approximately equal to the average output of the investments over&#13;
their lifetime, which is denoted here by yv . 1/    Using this approximation in (7)&#13;
and simplifying gives:&#13;
rv(l + fv)Iv -i -     v)Yv (1 - (1+rv)n)&#13;
Previously it was also shown that Iv might be approximated by the average&#13;
rate of investment over the years v-Z+1 to v, denoted by Iv*. An adjustment was&#13;
also made in the relationship to allow for the output no longer provided by those&#13;
investments displaced by the new vintages.   The adjusted value of Yv was denoted by&#13;
an asterisk. Making the same adjustment to Yv gives:&#13;
Yv   ! Iv *v cv/('-v&#13;
Re-introducing the subscript j, and adding over all sectors:&#13;
Jv yv           Jv    J     jvvjv   jv&#13;
Dividing through by current output in year v, the LHS gives the proportionate&#13;
increase in average value added associated with investments introduced in year v.&#13;
It follows that if we summate over a long interval, say v = 1 ....T years, this is&#13;
the same as the average annual rate of growth over the interval times T; denoting&#13;
this by g gives:-&#13;
T&#13;
V=l v    ajv jv     jv     jv&#13;
where iv is the rate of investment in v.&#13;
In this relataionship, changes in relative prices (e.g. those arising from&#13;
changes in the terms of trade, factor scarcities or innovation) should become&#13;
apparent in changes in the rates of return to investment. Depending on their&#13;
incidence, changes in sector shares in total investment and in labor's share in&#13;
output may also occur. Changes induced by economic cycles and, particularly in&#13;
LDCs, by yearly variations in agricultural output, would probably be associated with&#13;
changes in both the rate of investment and the rates of return to investment.&#13;
To show this,write&#13;
Ytv   YV + AYtv&#13;
where A Ytv is the deviation of Ytv from its average value. By definition:&#13;
EAYtv =&#13;
which suggests the approximation:&#13;
(t-v)&#13;
EAYtv (1+rv)       = °&#13;
from which it follows Y - Y&#13;
v   v&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
IV MICRO-ECONOMIC ANALYSIS AND&#13;
THE ANALYSIS OF GROWTH&#13;
The following discussion first considers the methods of marginal&#13;
analysis, and then the procedures for dealing with non-marginal changes.&#13;
Marginal Analysis&#13;
As a starting point for discussion, we might note Nelson's 1/ recent&#13;
objections to the application of marginal analysis to the analysis of growth:&#13;
"When the changes in question are large, marginal analysis may be&#13;
misleading. Thus, factor prices measure the contribution of a factor&#13;
at the margin. However, growth accounting usually has been concerned&#13;
with changes over a considerable interval of time. The fact that the&#13;
yearly percentage increases in labor, capital and gross national&#13;
product are typically quite small should not obscure the fact that,&#13;
even over a period as short as a decade, the percentage changes are&#13;
substantial.....&#13;
"If factors are complements, growth is super-additive in the sense&#13;
that the increase in output from growth of inputs is greater than the&#13;
sum of increases in output attributable to input growth, calculated&#13;
one by one, holding other inputs constant at their base level in each&#13;
sub-calculation. The growth of one input augments the marginal&#13;
contribution of others. Where complementary is important, it makes&#13;
little sense to try to divide up the credit for growth, treating the&#13;
factors as if they were not complements."&#13;
Scott makes a similar observation with respect to the complementarities&#13;
between physical investment and R &amp; D: 2/ "If R &amp; D is just an element in a&#13;
total package, all of which is essential, then it is the total package and not&#13;
just R &amp; D to which growth must be attributed."&#13;
There seem to be three problems here. First, many investments are&#13;
in fact large when accumulated over a long period; this question is discussed&#13;
in the next section. Second, marginal analysis does not seem to deal&#13;
satisfactorily with complementarities. Third, and partly on account of this,&#13;
estimating the changes in output associated with the change in each input in&#13;
an economy, and summating over inputs may not give a correct estimate of the&#13;
total change in economic output. Nelson refers to this third problem as "the&#13;
adding-up problem" and, since the summation procedures in Part III appear to&#13;
be at variance with Nelson's argument, this problem ought to be addressed.&#13;
One answer to Nelson's difficulties with marginal analysis is that&#13;
marginal analysis does not necessarily have to rest on the assumptions of&#13;
partial analysis. That is, it is possible to take the total rather than the&#13;
1/   Op. cit. pp. 1053-4.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
partial derivative when estimating the effects of investment on output. This&#13;
was essentially the procedure followed in Part III, in which the accounting&#13;
identities used included two terms, one being the present worth of quasi-rents&#13;
generated by the investments, and which are the returns that would be&#13;
estimated by an analysis of partial effects, the second being the change in&#13;
labor's income brought about by the redeplo;yment of labor to new vintages of&#13;
investments in the same or other sectors. As will be seen in Part V, a&#13;
similar result emerges when we take the total derivative of output with&#13;
respect to change in capital stock, assuming that the labor's income is not&#13;
independent of the change in capital stock.&#13;
Marginal analysis is similarly adaptable to the study of the effects&#13;
of investments in complementary activities on the output of the activity in&#13;
question. Further, it turns out that it is sometimes more difficult to&#13;
analyse investments holding other inputs constant since the analyst may be&#13;
faced with the tasks of estimating the scarcity prices arising from any&#13;
bottlenecks that might have developed.   Consider -for example the analysis of&#13;
the returns to investment in agriculture. If for some reason there had been&#13;
significant underinvestment in crop processing services, or alternatively in&#13;
the provision of fertilizers and farm equipnLent, then there would be a&#13;
rationing element. in the prices of such services and inputs, and the returns&#13;
to investments in agriculture would be loweir than otherwise. If on the other&#13;
hand the complementary investments were made!, it would be sufficient to allow&#13;
for them by valuing inputs at marginal cost, including their long-run&#13;
elements, the marginal cost of the investments.&#13;
It follows that, except for large investments, it is not incorrect&#13;
first to consider each investment's contribution to output on its own account,&#13;
and then to summate over all investments to obtain their total contribution,&#13;
as was done in Part III. So long as we are concerned with their total and not&#13;
their partial effects, this aspect of the "adding up" problem, as Nelson sub-&#13;
titled the passages from which the above remarks were taken, seems to be&#13;
answered. For the case where prices reflect marginal costs among the&#13;
investments under analysis, including prices of the outputs of any upstream or&#13;
downstream investments, the answer is to be found in the cost-benefit&#13;
literature regarding the treatment of secondary effects. Prest and Turvey 1/&#13;
consider an example in which several investments are indubitably&#13;
complementary, being those of farmers, millers and bakers to produce bread.&#13;
In this example they were also concerned with the treatment of one non-&#13;
marketed input (irrigation water). But here it is sufficient to concentrate&#13;
on the other aspect of their analysis, which is whether, in examining the&#13;
returns to the farmers' investments it is necessary to include the returns to&#13;
those of the millers and bakers on the grounis that these "stem" from the&#13;
farmers' investments. Do estimates of the private returns to the farmers'&#13;
investments (assuming prices everywhere = marginal cost), understate their&#13;
overall contributiLon to output and, if so, should we compare the value of the&#13;
final product (bread) with the combined costs of all three activities? Or can&#13;
we first estimate the returns to each separately, and add up later to&#13;
determine their total contribution to output'?&#13;
1/   In their survey in 1966, p. 161-162.   See also Turvey (1974).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
The answer is that, with a properly functioning price mechanism, the&#13;
result would be the same. In this circumstance, the mechanism is performing&#13;
the job of imputing values to the final and various intermediate inputs, and&#13;
regulating the final demand and the derived demands at each stage of&#13;
production such that prices = marginal values = marginal costs. If we were&#13;
estimating the contribution of investment to output at each stage of&#13;
production, and adding up later, we would be using these prices, while if we&#13;
were working with the consolidated account, we would be using marginal&#13;
costs. It is then a tautological excercise to show that the result is the&#13;
same in both cases.&#13;
The question arises, what if prices do not equal marginal costs,for&#13;
example because of monopolistic practices in certain industries, the structure&#13;
of taxes and a tariffs in an economy, or because the currency is overvalued?&#13;
Further, what if there are external costs to an investment? Or, to turn to a&#13;
different example, what if its output is not marketable, such as happens with&#13;
public goods and certain types of R&amp;D? It would be beyond the scope of this&#13;
paper to present a satisfactory discussion of these questions, on which&#13;
guidance should be sought in the literature on cost-benefit analysis.1/&#13;
Although this literature is for the most part concerned with ex ante analysis,&#13;
there seems no objection in principle to applying the methods recommended to&#13;
ex post analysis. For the present purposes of this paper it is sufficient to&#13;
make two points. First, and perhaps most obviously, these commonly discussed&#13;
shortcomings of pricing systems do not invalidate the principle of applying&#13;
marginal analysis to estimate investment's contribution to output; in fact,&#13;
cost-benefit procedures are essentially an extension of marginal analysis to&#13;
deal with the kinds of questions just raised.&#13;
Second, in most cases, the actual contribution of investments to&#13;
output are better measured through estimates of their social rather than their&#13;
private returns since the former are intended to include net contributions to&#13;
output not included in the latter. Thus if investments in a particular sector&#13;
are subsidized or otherwise benefit through various devices at the expense of&#13;
others, then estimates of their private returns would be misleading as to&#13;
their net contribution to output whereas those of their social returns would&#13;
not. Exceptions might arise, if one attempts to apply the recommended&#13;
procedures religiously, with investments having elements in their social costs&#13;
and returns that may not appear in the national accounts - the value of public&#13;
goods and environmental costs are two common examples and another related to&#13;
consumers' surplus will be discussed below. The recommended procedures in&#13;
such instances are helpful for assessing the desirablility of an investment,&#13;
but take us beyond the more limited task of assessing investment's&#13;
contribution to economic output, as it appears in national accounts. The&#13;
postulates of applied welfare economics on which cost benefit analysis is&#13;
based, as Professor Harberger (1971) remarked, "incorporate a greater degree&#13;
of subtlety of economic analysis than does national income methodology".&#13;
Provided one is aware of this, however, and concentrates on those elements of&#13;
the social rates of return that do appear in the accounts, the social rates of&#13;
return provide a better guide as to the contribution of investment to output&#13;
1/   E.g. Mishan (1971), Little and Mirrless (1974) and Prest and Turvey&#13;
op. cit., 1966.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
than do private rates of return; at the same time, if used in conjunction with&#13;
relationships of the form derived in Part III, they would also serve to&#13;
indicate the costs of various distortions in an economy, as measured in terms&#13;
of growth sacrificed.&#13;
Non-Marginal Investments and Structural Change&#13;
The micro-economic analysis of non-marginal investments in an&#13;
economy is most frequently associated with indivisibilities, or more generally&#13;
with large changes at a given point in time. But in the analysis of growth&#13;
the more common case is one in which large changes take place over a long&#13;
period. As Nelson remarks, while the changes in any year might be small in&#13;
relative or absolute terms, when accumulated over a decade or more they are&#13;
often substantial. An example is one in which electric power and motors are&#13;
introduced to replace steam power and engines on railways or in factories.&#13;
Over periods of time that are not long, the returns to investments in the user&#13;
industries may have risen appreciably either because of reductions in costs, a&#13;
greater volume of output from their investments, or both; a new group of&#13;
supplier industries may have emerged (electric power and motors) and which did&#13;
not exist before; while the old ones may have declined (steam engines) or had&#13;
found new outlel;s (coal). Numerous other examples could be cited. Hence it&#13;
is necessary to consider how to address this problem; again, guidance is to be&#13;
found in the literature on cost benefit analysis, in the present case in that&#13;
part of it concerning the concept and measurement of consumers' surplus.&#13;
The distinguishing feature of the present case, when contrasted with&#13;
those discussed under marginal analysis, is that a change in prices is&#13;
involved. The examples discussed in the section on marginal analysis were&#13;
essentially simple expansions of the activities with prices = marginal&#13;
costs. In the present case, however, there may be significant reductions in&#13;
prices (of power and energy), and also an outward shift of the derived demand&#13;
curve for the irnput if the new inputs lead to a productivity shift in the user&#13;
industry. The prices paid by the users wi:Ll thus not reflect the total&#13;
contribution of the investments in the supplier industry to economic output.&#13;
There are then two procedures that might be followed.&#13;
The first is to estimate the consumers' surplus (in the user&#13;
industries, to continue the example) associated with the changes described,&#13;
and attribute these to the investments in t;he new supplier industries. If&#13;
this were done then to avoid double counting it would be necessary to deduct&#13;
the consumers' surplus from the net revenue streams of the user industry.&#13;
This procedure, however, aside from the empirical difficulties involved, runs&#13;
into the problem mentioned above regarding the differences between what cost-&#13;
benefit analysis counts as the net returns and the net returns that are&#13;
included in the national accounts. In this context Harberger 1/ has shown&#13;
that the change in national welfare, as the! concept is often used in cost-&#13;
benefit analysis, associated with changes in economic inputs, is equal to the&#13;
change in national income plus the change in consumers' surplus. Actually,&#13;
Harberger's approach may have overstated the difference between the two&#13;
measures of welfare since the point that some consumers' surplus benefits may&#13;
1/   Op.cit. 1971.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
enter the national accounts is not allowed for in his analysis; the cost&#13;
savings to industries previously using the old inputs provide one example.&#13;
Nevertheless, the point remains that if the consumers' surplus benefits are&#13;
counted as part of the returns to investments,inconsistencies may arise when&#13;
comparing the aggregate results with national income data.&#13;
Hence it might be simpler to acknowledge that those consumers'&#13;
surplus benefits eventually appearing in the national accounts do so in the&#13;
accounts of the beneficiaries and not (by definition) in the accounts of those&#13;
industries whose investments have generated them. In this case, the pitfall&#13;
to avoid would be to attribute too much of the causation of the changes in the&#13;
.users' contribution to output to their own investments. Given the extent of&#13;
the interdependence of investments in present day economies, however, this is&#13;
an obvious pitfall to be aware of.&#13;
Conclusion&#13;
To sum up, the methods of micro-economics seem readily applicable to&#13;
the analysis of growth, over long or short periods. The practical relevance&#13;
of this conclusion arises from the point that an exceedingly large number of&#13;
micro-economic studies are now available, in both the developing and the&#13;
industrialized countries, regarding the effects of policies, and often of&#13;
political and institutional reforms, on the rate and yield of investment.&#13;
Further, for the developing countries, various studies have identified&#13;
policies that would raise the demand for labor and, by implication, labor's&#13;
share in output, while not reducing - and possibly increasing - the rate and&#13;
yield of investment. 1/ Even where the empirical results are not available,&#13;
there are now well-developed and robust methods within the discipline that&#13;
would enable the economist to examine the effects of economic decisions on the&#13;
micro-economic variables we have been examining in this paper.&#13;
Suppose then that a country has been observed to raise the PW of&#13;
labor's share in output and the rate and weighted average yield of investment&#13;
in the amounts AX, Ai and Ai respectively. These quantities may of course&#13;
change over time.for reasons unconnected with internal policies - such as with&#13;
changes in the terms of trade or, to take a different example, through chance&#13;
discoveries of high yielding resources. But let us concentrate on those&#13;
increases that can be attributed to changes in policies. They may have been&#13;
achieved in one or more of several ways:-&#13;
-    through raising the incentives to save and invest in general,&#13;
-    through encouraging more investment in high yielding (and possibly&#13;
1/   Three sections of the development literature arive at this&#13;
conclusion: the industry and trade literature, e.g. Little, Scitovsky&#13;
and Scott (1970), Myint (1971) and Ranis (1973); the technology&#13;
litetature, e.g. Stewart (1977), Sen (1974) and Bhalla (1975); and the,&#13;
rural development literature, e.g. Johnston and Kilby (1975) and Mellor&#13;
(1976). For more comprehensive reviews incorporating a large volume of&#13;
new evidence and country studies, see the IBRD's World Development&#13;
Reports, I to V, 1978 to 1982.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
also more labor demanding) and less in low yielding activities,&#13;
through the choice and management of its public investment programs,&#13;
through its ability to address sources of market failure (e.g. with&#13;
respect; to the distribution of educational opportunities),&#13;
-    through raising the returns to investment in general (e.g. through&#13;
appropriate macro and exchange rate policies),&#13;
and so forth. IThen from the aggregate form of the relationship derived in&#13;
Part III, the proportional change in the rate of growth would be given by:&#13;
Ag/g = Ar/r + Ai/i + dX/(L-X) + ----------&#13;
plus higher order terms if the changes are large and if there are significant&#13;
inter-relationships between    r, i and X 1/.  In other words it is possible to&#13;
appeal to the micro-economic explanation of the observed changes in r, i&#13;
and X to explain changes in g.&#13;
1/   As e.g. the financial intermediation literature argues there is&#13;
between r and i.  See Shaw (1973) and McKinnon (1973 and 1976).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
V A COMPARISON WITH OTHER&#13;
METHODS OF ACCOUNTING FOR GROWTH&#13;
Kuznets (1966) and Later Growth Accounting Studies&#13;
Kuznets estimated the relative contributions of capital, labor&#13;
(measured in man-hours) and technical progress to the growth of output in the&#13;
industrialized countries in the following way:I/&#13;
"By relating property income from assets to the total capital that&#13;
yields it, we can ascertain the relevant rate of input. Income from&#13;
assets, excluding the part implicitly contained in the incomes of&#13;
individual entrepreneurs (i.e. return on capital excluding&#13;
entrepreneurial equity) averages about 20 percent of total income...&#13;
Returns on entrepreneurial equity differ widely.. (But] since&#13;
entrepreneurial capital in developed countries is at most 25% of&#13;
total income - the contribution of capital input to total product -&#13;
is about a quarter of the latter..."&#13;
"The combined inputs of man-hours and capital would account for an&#13;
even smaller fraction of the growth in product per capita. Since&#13;
man-hours per capita are found to decline 2 to 3 per cent per decade&#13;
and their weight in total product is 0.75 (since income from assets&#13;
is assumed to account for 0.25), the direct contribution would be a&#13;
reduction in the rate of growth of per capita product of 1.5 to 2.25&#13;
percentage points. If the rate of growth of per capita product is,&#13;
say, 15 percent per decade, the reduction amounts to a tenth of the&#13;
rate or more... the inescapable conclusion is that the direct&#13;
contribution of manhours and capital accumulation would hardly&#13;
account for more than a tenth of the rate of growth in per capita&#13;
product - and probably less. The large remainder must be assigned to&#13;
an increase in efficiency of productive resources - a rise in output&#13;
per unit of input, due either to the improved quality of the&#13;
resources, or to the effects of changing arrangements, or to the&#13;
impact of technological change, or to all three."&#13;
Kuznets subsequently qualifies this conclusion by emphasizing that "the low&#13;
proportions of growth in per capita product allocated to increased input of&#13;
man-hours and capital do not mean that the absence of such an input would have&#13;
resulted in only a small proportionate loss... The lines of the relationship&#13;
between absolute increases in population, labor force and capital on the one&#13;
hand, and growth in the per capita product on the other are numerous and far&#13;
reaching ... in ways that make it difficult, if not impossible, to establish&#13;
the correct partial effects of increases in inputs of man hours and capital on&#13;
growth of per capita product."2/ Furthermore, the link between structural&#13;
changes and investment is clearly established in his subsequent analysis.&#13;
These passages raise an issue that continues to afflict, though to a&#13;
1/   Op. cit., pp. 79-81.&#13;
2/   Ibid., p. 85.  The emphasis on partial effects is mine.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
lesser degree, thie more recent growth accounting studies cited in the&#13;
introduction. This is that only the partial effects of investments on output&#13;
are considered whien the intention of the large majority of investments is to&#13;
raise the productivity of other inputs--principally, though of course not&#13;
exclusively, by redeplying labor. Consequently it is more useful to consider&#13;
the total effects together. 1/&#13;
To make the point formally, consider the commonly used national&#13;
accounting identi-ty:&#13;
Y = rK + wI,&#13;
where Y is net national income, K is the net capital stock, L the labor force,&#13;
w wages and r the returns to capital.2/ Now consider a change in K. Taking&#13;
the total derivative gives:&#13;
1 dY   dK  =  rK  dK  + 1    a(wL)  dK&#13;
Y dK           Y   K     Y    a K&#13;
It is apparent from this expression that what is omitted in the&#13;
above estimates of Kuznets is the second terim on the right hand side, which&#13;
measures the change in labor's income, in relation to national income, with&#13;
respect to a change in capital stock. If for instance we assume this term is&#13;
zero and take rK/Y = 0.25, then the increase in output attributed to the&#13;
increase in capital stock is only 0.25 dK/K, as he estimated. As discussed in&#13;
Part I, later studlies continue to make the same omission with respect to&#13;
material investment, though not with respect to investment in education. It&#13;
is true that the effects of material investment on labor's income -&#13;
accomplished by redeploying labor towards occupations or industries in which&#13;
wages are higher - are partly recognized, but only for redeployment across&#13;
broadly defined occupations or industries, e.g., from agriculture to&#13;
industry. Changes in labor's income brought about by redeployment within&#13;
industry or agriculture for example, and alsD within given places of&#13;
employment, for example on farms or in firms, are necessarily overlooked by so&#13;
aggregative an analysis.   Thus the effects of material investment on labor's&#13;
income through the redeployment of labor are significantly underestimated.&#13;
It was also noted in the introduction that even a highly&#13;
disaggregated ana:Lysis of occupations could not be relied upon (assuming it&#13;
1/   This also seems to be one of Nelson's points when discussing the&#13;
"adding up" problem in growth accounting, in which he observes" two&#13;
evident kin(ds of interaction among the three sources of economic growth&#13;
- technological advance, capital growth and rising educational&#13;
attainment. First, they appear to be complementary in the sense that an&#13;
increase of any one raises the marginal contributions of the others.&#13;
Second, because of this, forces that lead to the augmentation of any one&#13;
are likely to stimulate an increase in the others", op.cit., 1981, p.&#13;
1050.&#13;
2/   In this identity, r is not of course the same as the internal rate&#13;
of return to investment, used in Parts II and III.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
were practical) to address the issue. What is needed in practice is a means&#13;
of estimating a(wK)/3K reliably for each sector at whatever level of&#13;
aggregation is thought appropriate for analysis. The simplest procedure is to&#13;
appeal to the relationships discussed variously above, between the change in&#13;
labor's income and investment. First apply the above accounting relationship&#13;
to each sector such that&#13;
Yj = rj K. + (wL).&#13;
and then consider a change in total net capital stock, given by dK = d(E&#13;
K.). Then the total change in Y is given by: j&#13;
dYj = rj aKj dK +  a(wL). dK                       (9)&#13;
(Note that the wage bill in sector j is more influenced by the total change in&#13;
net capital stock than by the change in the net capital stock in sector j, on&#13;
account of the greater influence of the former on the demand for labor.) As&#13;
in Parts II and III, now define a variable relating the change in labors'&#13;
income in sector j to the change in value added in sector j 1/ as follows&#13;
X = a (wL .dK&#13;
aK )dY.&#13;
X " would equal labor's share in current output, denoted in Part III by X&#13;
ii the latter quantity were constant over time. However, there is no need to&#13;
make this assumption&#13;
The first term on the RHS of (9) can be written as rjsj, where as before s&#13;
is sector j's share in investment.  Adding (9) over all j, substituting for X'"&#13;
and rearranging we obtain:&#13;
g = i x sjrj/(1-XI.)                            (lo)&#13;
j 33 &#13;
This expression differs from the one derived in Part III because lead times&#13;
have been ignored and it is based on a different accounting identity, the&#13;
identity in Part III, it will be recalled, being based on the internal rate of&#13;
return to investment. The two expressions are similar however.&#13;
Taking an average growth rate over the period v=O....T, we can also&#13;
obtain an expression similar to the more general relationship, (8), derived in&#13;
Part III:&#13;
-      ~~T&#13;
g = (1/T)fO{i E s r /(l-X'!)}dv           (11)&#13;
where i,sj,r, and Xi" may vary with v, as before.&#13;
1/   Given the definitions of K, Y and r, we are currently talking in&#13;
terms of labor's share in net valued added.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
Methods Using Incremental Capital-Output Ratios&#13;
Rewriting (10)in the form:&#13;
dY = {E s r./(1-X'.)}dK&#13;
dt    j J J       J  dt&#13;
the incremental output-capital ratio, denoted here by a, can be seen to be&#13;
given by:&#13;
E s.r./(1-XI)                                   (12)&#13;
j  J J     J&#13;
There are therefore some similarities between the commonly used INCOR methods&#13;
of analyzing growth, the early Harrod-Domar accelerator models, and the&#13;
generalized capital accumulation approach followed in this paper. All of&#13;
these approaches place the rate and the yield of investment in a central&#13;
position in the explanation of economic growth.&#13;
There would seem to be two advantages to decomposing the capital-&#13;
output ratio in the manner implied by equation (12). First, the RHS of (12)&#13;
uses a standard measure of comparing the efficiency of investments between&#13;
sectors. Thus if the rate of return to investment in one sector is, say 15%,&#13;
and in another 5%, while the opportunity cost of capital is 10%, the economist&#13;
is led to inquire as to the circumstances that are leading to what is, at&#13;
first sight, a misallocation of resources. In contrast, capital-output ratios&#13;
may vary appreciably between sectors and over time whether or not resources&#13;
are being allocated efficiently, making it difficult to interpret them&#13;
unambigously. Second, the returns to labor resulting from investment are&#13;
distinguished from the returns to capital and, as discussed variously above,&#13;
attention is then focussed on the importance of a proper and efficient&#13;
deployment of labor (as well as of capital) in the process of growth.&#13;
Rates of Return and Growth: Estimates for Some Countries&#13;
Since there is no "residual" in the approach suggested above (apart&#13;
from errors and omissions in estimating i and r) does this imply that the&#13;
rates of return to investment   would have to be implausibly high, as Denison&#13;
argued, for the approach to be reconciled with observed growth rates?1/    Scott&#13;
reconsidered this question based on a more careful analysis of the definitions&#13;
and measurement of investment, and finds that they would not, averaging around&#13;
13.2% for 10 OECD countries.2/&#13;
If anything, Scott's estimates may be on the high side, since with&#13;
minor adjustments he takes Denison's figures for the quality adjusted labor&#13;
force, and (rightly) adds to these Denison"s estimates of the increases in&#13;
labor's income aLrising from the contraction of self-employment and employment&#13;
in agriculture, that is to say, from the redeployment of labor towards higher&#13;
income wage and salary work in industry and commerce. The sum is deducted&#13;
from the overall increases in income to arrive at that part of growth&#13;
1/   Op. cit., 1967, p. 144.&#13;
2/   Op. cit., 1981, pp. 222-224.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
unaccounted for by labor. The difference is then divided by the share of&#13;
investment in output to arrive at the figure of 13.2% just noted.&#13;
As discussed variously above, however, the proportionate increases&#13;
in labor's income arising from redeployment are underestimated by this&#13;
procedure. Consider, for example, a generation of workers entering industry&#13;
in a particular period and whose formal educations have by then been&#13;
completed. There are three ways in which their incomes may increase the&#13;
average income level of the labor force over time as a consequence of&#13;
investment:&#13;
(1) with structural changes in the economy, they may increase the&#13;
proportion of the labor force in higher paid industrial jobs instead&#13;
of lower paid agricultural jobs than would otherwise be the case;&#13;
(ii) They may belong to higher paid, higher educated groups than the&#13;
generation preceding them; and&#13;
(iii) with structural changes and growth within industry, many of&#13;
these workers will be redeployed at various times in their&#13;
working lives to work on or with new methods of production&#13;
involving higher outputs and ultimately higher earnings per&#13;
worker. Some retraining may be needed for this, though often&#13;
with little change in their formal educational status.&#13;
The procedures followed by Denison and later writers allow for the effects of&#13;
(i) and (ii) on labor's income but neglect (iii), which appears in the&#13;
"residual" or technical progress term.   Similar remarks apply to the labor&#13;
force becoming redeployed by within agriculture by agricultural investments,&#13;
e.g. in irrigation, new seed-fertilizer varieties, tractors, and so forth. If&#13;
the "residual" is included in the capital account, the implied rates of return&#13;
to capital do seem high.l/ But if it is seen as the returns to labor arising&#13;
from investment in methods of production with higher outputs per worker, this&#13;
is no longer the case. The actual rates of return to capital turn out to be&#13;
lower than Scott's estimates, and strengthen his argument.&#13;
Two estimates of the returns to investment in various developing and&#13;
industrialized countries are presented in the table (columns 9 and 10). The&#13;
first is based on an aggregate form of equation (10)2/:-&#13;
rl = g(1-X')/(i-d)&#13;
1/   Though not as high as Denison suggested, if Scott's accounting&#13;
procedures are followed--in particular, if gross rather than net&#13;
investment is used.&#13;
2/   Recall that e = (1/T)!0{r(i-d)/(1-X")}dt. X"2_' and, since X'&#13;
varies slowly over time, we can to a good approximation.&#13;
factor it out of the integral and write j(1-X')_ (1/T)fjOr(i-d)dt, from&#13;
which it follows that the average value of r is given by&#13;
g(1-V')/(1/T)roT (i-d)dt = g(-'/lT(-)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
where g, which iE; shown in the first column,, is the average rate of growth of&#13;
GDP (taken to be close to that of net national income), X' labor's share in&#13;
net output (taken to be approximately equal to labor's share in the change in&#13;
net output, denoted above by A"), and i and d the average rates of investment&#13;
and depreciation respectively. It is apparent from the identities on which&#13;
this relation is based that r4 corresponds more closely to what is sometimes&#13;
called the accourLting rate of return (or the rate of profit) based on revalued&#13;
assets.&#13;
The second is the economic rate of- return, and is based on an&#13;
aggregate form of the general relationship (8) derived in Part III 1/:-&#13;
r2= g(l-X)J'ci&#13;
where X is the present worth of labor's share in the output of investments,&#13;
and a is a parameter (or near-parameter) to allow for the financing costs of&#13;
investments during their gestation periods and for the eventual retirement of&#13;
investments. It can be seen from a comparison of columns (6) and (7) that X&#13;
is somewhat less than labor's share in net cutput, the reason being that&#13;
discounting leads to relatively low weights being placed on labor's share in&#13;
the later years of an investment, when the shares are at their highest (and&#13;
quasi-rents at their lowest), and relatively high weights in the early years,&#13;
when the shares are at their lowest. The estimates of a , which are shown in&#13;
column (8) rise directly with the financing costs of investment, and thus with&#13;
the lead times and the cost of capital, but tend to decrease with the&#13;
allowance for retirement, to an extent depending on g and the cost of capital&#13;
(see formula for a ).&#13;
From an economic point of view, it. is more appropriate to&#13;
concentrate on the estimates of the economic. rate of return to investment&#13;
shown in the last column. As Fisher and McGowan (1983) have shown, it is only&#13;
by co-incidence that the two measures of the return to investment will be&#13;
equal, even assuming (as is done implicitly in the above analysis since we are&#13;
working with a measure of investment in terms of its share in real income)&#13;
that the accounting rate of return is based on revalued assets. The estimates&#13;
of the two quantities are often in the same vicinity, but sometimes depart&#13;
significantly.&#13;
Some comments on the range of uncertainty in the estimates might be&#13;
useful. First, it was necessary to make some allowance for the opportunity&#13;
cost of the owner's and family labor in what is termed in the accounts&#13;
"entrepreneurial income from unincorporated enterprises". This is, perhaps,&#13;
too fanciful a description for many of the activities coming under this&#13;
heading in developing countries, since they mostly comprise peasant farmers&#13;
and small scale manufacturing and tertiary activities in households and&#13;
workshops. Nevertheless, the total income from this source is often&#13;
comparable to and sometimes greater than that from wage and salaried&#13;
employment (c.f. columns 4 and 5). For the industrialized countries it is a&#13;
comparatively small, though not a negligible source. Since entrepreneurial&#13;
1/   Using an averaging procedure for the rate of investment similar to&#13;
that used in the preceding footnote.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
income is made up of the returns to investment plus the returns to the owner's&#13;
and family labor, it is necessary to make some assumptions as to the relative&#13;
magnitudes of the two. In the absense of direct evidence on this point from&#13;
family or firm-level surveys, I have followed Harberger's example 1/ and&#13;
considered a range of values, the lower one being that the returns to&#13;
investment contribute one third, and the higher one, one half, to reported&#13;
entrepreneurial income from unincorporated enterprises. For the developing&#13;
countries, where labor is surely the principal input, both are probably over-&#13;
estimates, and, inconsequence, imply an over-estimate of the returns to&#13;
investment in columns 9 and 10 (and thus under-state my argument).&#13;
To estimate the present worth of labor's share in output (column 7),&#13;
and also the parameter a , it was necessary to make some assumptions about the&#13;
economic lifetime of investments. For infrastructure and construction&#13;
projects, lifetimes are typically 20-30 years, sometimes longer, while for&#13;
agricultural and industrial projects, where economic obsolescence may be more&#13;
rapid, depending on the returns to new investments and the rate of growth,&#13;
lifetimes of 10-15 years may be typical. The estimates in the table are based&#13;
on 15 years. It turns out that the results are not overly sensitive to this&#13;
assumption; e.g. an increase from 15 to 20 years raises the estimated economic&#13;
rate return by a factor in the range 1.05 to 1.15.&#13;
The estimate of a also requires some assumptions as to the lead time&#13;
of investments. The figure in the table is based on an average of 5 years -&#13;
though it is possibly longer than this for many investments in the developing&#13;
countries; e.g. it may be 5-10 years or more between the initial investment in&#13;
agricultural projects and the achievement of a sustainable increase in&#13;
yields. Lead times for infrastructure projects are typically 4-7 years,&#13;
though those for manufacturing may be less than this. An increase from 5 to 6&#13;
years would reduce the estimated rates of return in column (10) by a factor of&#13;
1.05 to 1.1, depending on the rate of interest assumed, and from 5 to 7 years&#13;
by a factor of 1.1 to 1.2.&#13;
The estimates shown also exclude investment in vocational training,&#13;
education, and health. For the developing countries some of the costs of&#13;
agricultural extension should also be counted as investment (as they are in&#13;
project analysis). Investment in education, for example, is around 4% of GDP&#13;
for the countries listed; if this were included in i, the estimated returns in&#13;
the last column would be reduced by a factor of about 1.15 to 1.2.&#13;
With these qualifications in mind, it does not seem that omitting&#13;
the "residual" leads to implausibly high estimates of the returns to&#13;
investment 2/, inconsistent with project experience. The accounting rates of&#13;
1/   In his article "Capital and Technology in Less Developed&#13;
Countries". Harberger (1979).&#13;
2/   The estimates for several of the countries listed are remarkably&#13;
similar to those made by Harberger, op. cit., 1979, who estimated the&#13;
reproducible capital stock of 18 countries using the perpetual inventory&#13;
method, and divided this into his estimates of annual income from the&#13;
stock.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3 5-&#13;
THE RATES OF ECONOMIC GROWTH AND TIlE RATES OF AND&#13;
RETURNS TO INVESTMEINT FOR SOME DEVELOPING COUNTRIES (1970-80)&#13;
AND SOME INDSTRIALIZED COUNTRIES (1960-80)&#13;
Average Rare of    Shares in Output of:-&#13;
Rate of       Invearment 1/                                    Labor-'s         PW of Labor's                       Returns to Invetmet (1&#13;
Growth of                      Wages &amp;     Entrepreneurial.    Shari, in Net    Share in                            Using Relationship    n-&#13;
Country                    GOP        Gross     Net       Salaries   Income 2/          Outpu~t 3/       Ou!tpu4            Pa.rameter 5./    Par,t V 6/ T  Pa rt IIW 7/&#13;
(1)          (2)      (3)       (4)          (5)                 (6W8                                                (9)             (io)&#13;
Kenya                     6.5           22      (17)      0.39        n.a.              (0.62-0.71)       (0.57-0.65)          1.08           11410-12&#13;
Ivory Coast               6 .7         24        19      0.39         n.a.              (0.62 -0.71)      (0.58-0.67)          1.08           :0-13             9-11&#13;
India                     3.6          20        14       ...0.78 ....(0.62-0.71)                         (0.57-0.65)          0 .7 3          7-jQ             9-Il1&#13;
Sri Lanka                 4.1           16       11       0.45        0.44               0.71-0.80        0.64-0.72           0.80             7-11             9 -1I2&#13;
Thailand                  7 .2          25       18       0.27        0.49               0.55--0.66        0.48-0.57           1.14           14-18            1 1-il&#13;
Philippines               6.3           27       18       ...0.84 ....(0.69--0.78)                        (0.61-0.69)          1.07            8-1179&#13;
Colombia                  5.9           20       12       0.40        0.45               0.70-0.78        (0.61-0.68)          1.01           11                9-Il&#13;
S. Korea                  9.5           2 7      20       0.37        0.32               0.57-.0.61       (0.50-0.53)          1.34           1 7-20           12-13&#13;
Japan&#13;
-1960/70                 10.9           36       24       0.47        0.21               0.65--0.70        0.65-0.68           1.38           14-16             7-8&#13;
-1970/No                  5.0           34       21       0.62        0.15               0.80--0.83        0.70-0.76           1.37            4                  '3&#13;
-1960/80                  7.9           35       22       0.57        0.17               0.76-.0.79        0.65-0.68           1.35            895-6&#13;
UK&#13;
-1960/70                  2.9           19       11       0.65        0.09              0.76-0.78          0.73-0.75           0 .7 2          '6                '46&#13;
-1970/80                  1.9           20        9       0.69        0.11               0.83-0.86         0.74-0.75           0.6334 &#13;
-1960/80                  2.4           19       10       0.67        0.10               0.79-0.81         0.70-0.71           0.79            .5                 vS&#13;
USA&#13;
-1960/70                  4.3           19        8       0.68        0.09               0.81-0.83         0.71-0.73           0.88            9-10               '7&#13;
-1970/80                  3.0           18        6       0.70        0.06              0.83-0.84          0.73-0.74           0.79      ~      9                  64&#13;
-1960/80                  3.6           18        7       0.69        0.07               0.82-0.83         0.72-0.73           0.79            -9                 1&#13;
Sources:   Data on g from IBED World Develpet       eot. 1982, Table 2.      The aver.sgR rates of gross investment are taken from IBRD World&#13;
Tables * Se cond Editionr, 190   Table 3.   Th   stimtes of depreciation, d, and of the shares in output of wages cod _sal_a_ries and&#13;
inco-rporated entrepreneurial income, were taken from the U.N. Yearbook of National Accounts Statistics, Vol. 1, Iodividual Country&#13;
Data, 1979, tables, 1, 10 and 16; since all three quantities change from year to year, averages were takes over the relevant&#13;
periods where data perm,itted or, when this was not possible, the estimites relate to the middle of the period.&#13;
Footnotes and Basis of Estimates&#13;
l/  Averages over the periods 1970-77 for the developing countries and 1960-70 and 1970-77 for the industrialized coutries.           The bracketed&#13;
figure of the rate of net investmant for Kenya assumes a - 5% (actual estimat:es are not available).&#13;
2/  Entrepreneurial income of unincorporated enterprises.      For the industrialized countries, the income from ownership of dwellings was&#13;
excluded (it amounts to around 5 to 10% of entrepreneurial income); it was not possible to exclude it for the developing countries&#13;
because it is not shown separately.&#13;
3/  Sin,e I, andA    (cola. 4 and 5) relate to shares in gross output, they are divided by (1-d) to give shares in net output.        The two cots-&#13;
- mares o   A' reYcte to AY  + 0.5 1   and A  + 0.7 A   respectively (see text for further discussion).     For Kenya, Ivory Coast, India and tIe&#13;
Philippines, for which wseparate estriamtwes of A  and A   wore not available, wu have assumed I se , by reference to th.edata for the othar&#13;
developing countries listed.                     w      ew0&#13;
4/  The p.w. of labor's share in oUtPUt is estimated from the formulae footnoted in Part III, which give the relation between A ai.d A          (see&#13;
pages 9   and 10 ).  A simple way of writing the relation is X/X' - (1-d)A(n.,r-g+c)A(n,g)/A(n.r)A(n.c), where A(n.s) is tie present&#13;
value of "one" over n at a discount rate of a; i.e. A(n,x) - (1._(ln,) n)/r. We have also multiplied by (1-a) to re-express labor's&#13;
share in terms of gross output (see f.n. 3). Here c is the rate of growth of the labor force, sod appears in the espression because it&#13;
influences how the labor fortsa is deployed on the various vintages of investnients (see Part II); the estimates of this quantity for the&#13;
developing countries are unreliable, since the annual surveys often exclude certain categories of self and family employmeet. Hence we&#13;
took c - population growth rate for the developing countries, as listed in the IBRD World Development Report. 1982, Table 17. For the&#13;
industrialized countries, the estimates of c were taken from the ILO Yearbooks of Labor Statistics, 1973 and 1982, table 3. For the&#13;
developing countries, beginninig with Kenya and reading down the list, the values of c used were 3.4, SO0, 2.1, 1.6, 2.5, 2.7, 2.3 and&#13;
1.7. the high value for Ivory Coast being due to immigration; for Japan. 1.4, 1.0 and 1.2 for 1960-70, 1970-80 and 1960-80; for the&#13;
UK ~o in all three periods; and for the US. 2.1, 2.4 and 2.3.&#13;
Note also, that to estimate A, it is necessary to begin with an estimate of r and iterate; the estimate taken was that glues in&#13;
column (9). The value of n was taken to be 15 years (see test).&#13;
5/  a - f (I(-nn/I(IrT) and f - (1/i)f (1+r)t~. (f represents the financing costs of the Investments.) The estimates are&#13;
based on n-IS years, an iterated value of r.       and a lead time, 1, equal to i years.     See test for further discussion.&#13;
6/  r1 -~(-)UI.            see test for further discussion.    The two estimates of r1 correspond to the two values ofA'&#13;
7/  r2 .    (I-A )/j o, aee text for further discussion.     The two estimates of r 2 ilsocrepntohewovlsofX&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
return for Japan, the UK and the USA are estimated to be around 8-9%, 5% and&#13;
9% respectively over the period 1960-80. For the lower growth developing&#13;
countries, they are in the range 7-11%, but nearly twice this level for the&#13;
high growth E. Asian countries (except for the Philippines). The economic&#13;
rates of return are generally lower all round - particularly if one allows for&#13;
investment in educaton - but are again consistent with project experience. It&#13;
should be noted also that the estimates shown are averages, and will be higher&#13;
than the marginal rates of return.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
VI DOES THE ABSENSE OF A RESIDUAL&#13;
IMPLY NO TECHNICAL PROGRESS?&#13;
The answer to this question follows from the analysis provided in&#13;
Part II, in which it was shown that the technical progress parameter was in&#13;
fact equal to an aggregate form of the accounting relationship derived in Part&#13;
III, less an adjustment for the growth of output associated with the growth of&#13;
labor inputs (measured in natural units). The answer can also be derived&#13;
using Solow'a non-vintage model of growth, as presented in his 1957 paper on&#13;
the subject; this will be done below in order to make an elementary point&#13;
about how technical progress is in practice reflected in the returns to&#13;
investment.&#13;
Solow's non-vintage model of growth with technical progress was of&#13;
the form (Y/L) = f(t, K/L), where L is the size of the labor force measured in&#13;
natural units (say, man years per year), K is the net capital stock, Y value&#13;
added and t, time. Taking a Cobb-Douglas form, assuming constant returns to&#13;
scale and letting X' denote labor's share in value added, then:&#13;
(Y/L)t =&#13;
where B(t) is a trend representing the contribution of technical progress to&#13;
output as distinct from the contribution of capital per worker. From this it&#13;
follows that:&#13;
Yt = bt + (1-X')kt                              (13)&#13;
where yt is the rate of growth of output per worker, kt of capital per worker,&#13;
and bt the contribution of technical progress to yt.&#13;
For the industrialized countries the rates of growth of output and&#13;
of net capital stock have tended to be about the same over long periods (one&#13;
of the "stylized facts" of growth theory). Solow (1970, Ch.1) remarks that&#13;
this has always been a rather controversial reading of the facts because of&#13;
the difficulties of measuring capital stock and, second, because however the&#13;
measurement prob:Lems are resolved, the evidence is inconclusive. However,&#13;
over long periods, the capital-output ratio for the industrialized countries&#13;
has appeared to remain roughly constant.   Putting kt - Yt. the percentage&#13;
contribution of technical progress to the growth of output is then 100 b&#13;
100 X'. If X' is around 0.75 to 0.8, then roughly three-quarters to four-&#13;
fifths of the growth of output per worker is attributed to technical&#13;
progress. This finding was common in the earlier studies up to the mid'&#13;
1960s. Later studies modified this conclusion by allowing for changes in the&#13;
"quality" of the labor force following the *procedures summarized in Part I.&#13;
When this was done, the contribution of tec1hnical progress to growth was&#13;
reduced to about half of the earlier estimates, and to about a third if, in&#13;
addition, changes in the (broadly defined) occupational structure were allowed&#13;
for.1/ Rather than working with "quality-adjusted" estimates of the size of&#13;
the fabor force, however, some points of principle emerge if we retain Solow's&#13;
original model and work with natural units.&#13;
1/   See e.g., Denison (1967, Chapter 21).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
It is possible that there is a specification problem with (13),&#13;
since if we used it to obtain an independent estimate of A' by regressing kt&#13;
on Yt, we would find X'; o    and   bt    0 given the close relation between&#13;
the two variables. (If we took the stylized fact literally, A' and bt would&#13;
both exactly equal zero.) Hence it is instructive to look at the assumptions&#13;
again.&#13;
It might be questioned, for example, whether the technical progress&#13;
term, B(t), is independent of the rate of investment. If instead it is&#13;
assumed to change with changes in K, then multiplying the expression preceding&#13;
(13) by L, so that we are considering changes in total output again,&#13;
differentiating and dividing through by Y we obtain:&#13;
1  dY   =   K  dB ldK     +  (1-V') 1  dK  +  )' dL&#13;
Y     dt    Bf IT K dt              K      T   L  dt&#13;
or&#13;
g  =gb     +    (1-')gK    +   X1 L                         (14)&#13;
where g is the rate of growth of total output, as before, gK and gL are the&#13;
rates of growth of capital stock and of the labor force respectively, and gb&#13;
is the rate of growth due technical progress, related in this expression to gK&#13;
and the elasticity term (K/B)dB/dK.&#13;
The question arises, what is the function for gb? If the analysis&#13;
in Parts III and V is correct, the answer might be provided in an aggregate&#13;
form of equation (8), namely,&#13;
g = ria&#13;
where r is now a weighted average return on investment, a is the parameter&#13;
defined previously, and X is the P.W. of labor's share in the value added by&#13;
the investments. Comparing this expression with (14) gives:&#13;
gb = ria/(KX) (l   X)gK - 'gL = ria/(1- A) - go, say,&#13;
where g0 is the growth rate that is possible without technical progress--that&#13;
is , the growth due to gand g     with the methods of production remaining&#13;
unchanged. Hence the production function would become, with Bo being a&#13;
constant:                r(&#13;
Y  = B .e    rio/O   -   0g  t K(t)  L(t)             (15)&#13;
0    0&#13;
The exponent of the technical progress term in this expression&#13;
resembles that proposed by Eltis (1973, Chapter 6), in which the exponent was&#13;
written in the form (a+bi)t, where a and b are constants. There is, however,&#13;
an important difference, since in (15) 'b' would not necessarily be&#13;
constant. It is equal to ria/(1-X), and thus varies both with the returns to&#13;
investment, including those to investments in R&amp;D, and with the manner in&#13;
which investments deploy the labor force. Thus suppose for instance the&#13;
political and economic policies of a country were such that investments were&#13;
consistently ill-conceived and generated poor returns. Then b would fall to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
low levels; it would fall to zero if the re;urns barely covered operating&#13;
costs; and it would become negative, implying negative per capita growth, if&#13;
the returns on a sufficient number of investments could not cover operating&#13;
costs but continued to function on account of internal or external&#13;
subsidies. It is, unfortunately, not difficult to find examples. Another&#13;
instance might be where applied R&amp;D for one reason or another did not succeed&#13;
in generating investments with good returns..&#13;
For these reasons it seems to me desirable to represent the&#13;
influence of technical progress on growth not by a parameter, but by variables&#13;
that reflect both the rate of investment (asi in Eltis's model) and the&#13;
efficiency of investment. Since the rate and, in particular, the efficiency&#13;
of investment are in turn influenced by numerous other variables - e.g. the&#13;
choice of investments (including investmentsa in R&amp;D), pricing policies,&#13;
incentive structures, and factors determining what have come to be called&#13;
management or "X"' efficiencies - it would seem unrealistic to strive to&#13;
represent them endogenously. But the important point is that technical&#13;
progress is and must be treated by a variab:Le function. Where it is&#13;
represented by a parameter there is, as Scott remarks, the underlying&#13;
assumption that it is "manna from heaven", with the implication:1/&#13;
"that later vintages of capital goods are better than earlier ones&#13;
just because they are later, so that their efficiency is purely a&#13;
matter cf time and nothing to do with investment or the yield of&#13;
investmefnt itself. In vintage theory this is precisely what is&#13;
assumed to happen, but it is wildly implausible. It implies, for&#13;
example, that if no investment at all had taken place anywhere in the&#13;
world between 1881 and 1981, and if the world economy had been static&#13;
over this period, then miraculously, in 1981 we would have been able&#13;
to build jet airplanes and electric computers despite this century of&#13;
stagnation."&#13;
Including the rate of investment in the teclnical progress term helps to&#13;
remove some of these difficulties; but most economists would agree, I would&#13;
think, that the yield of investment is equally important, as Scott himself has&#13;
shown, including, if we may use the term more broadly, labors' share in the&#13;
yield.&#13;
The above equation helps to explain how technical is reflected in&#13;
the relationships derived in Parts III and Vr. The absence of the "residual"&#13;
in the latter does not imply that the influence of technical progress on the&#13;
growth is ignored. Rather, it is revealed in the following manner. In a&#13;
growing economyr wages are generally rising, unless labor's share is falling&#13;
inversely or faster with growth. Under these conditions, the quasi-rents on&#13;
existing types of' investment would eventually fall to zero, and further rises&#13;
in real wages could not be sustained unless investors were able to draw on&#13;
advances in knowledge and methods of production to find new types of&#13;
investment with positive rates of return at the higher wage levels. The&#13;
technical progress term in (15) increases over time so long as investors are&#13;
able to do this.&#13;
1/   Op. cit., 1981, p. 219.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
If advances in knowledge ceased or were not reflected in new&#13;
investments and methods of production, wages could not rise in real terms, the&#13;
rate of investment would decline to levels sufficient only to employ new&#13;
entrants to the labor force at the prevailing static wage rate, and the growth&#13;
rate would be given by g .  To show that the model satisfies this condition,&#13;
recall that:&#13;
n              n&#13;
XA= {E£ w /(l+r)t }/{Y n/(l+r)}&#13;
1          ~~~~~~1&#13;
Recalling that Y is net of maintenance costs, then with no technical progress&#13;
and constant wages ( = w, say) the lifetime of the investment is very long.&#13;
Furthermore, there is no redeployment of labor from old to new investments.&#13;
Hence E -* L whereas with technical progress and redeployment it was much less&#13;
than L . Hence the above expression for A becomes wL/Y. If labor's share,&#13;
X'= wL/Y is constant, then X'=X and the rate of growth is given by:&#13;
g = ria/(l-X')&#13;
Recall that the parameter, a , is unity if n is large and if we ignore&#13;
financing costs during the gestation period of the investment. Using this&#13;
approximation and rearranging:&#13;
g = ri+X'g&#13;
The first term on the RHS can be re-written as r(l/Y)(dK/dt), or&#13;
(rK/Y)(1/K)(dK/dt), that is to say, as the share of the returns to capital in&#13;
output times the rate of growth of capital stock. Similarly, the second term&#13;
can be re-written as ( w dL/dY)(l/Y)(dY/dt), which rearranges to&#13;
( w L/Y)(1/L)(dL/dt), that is to say, labor's share in output times in the&#13;
rate of growth of the labor force. Hence:&#13;
g = (l-X')Yk + X'YL      go&#13;
That is, output increases only with increases in K and L. (Q.E.D.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
VII    CONCLUS3IONS&#13;
This paper has sought to show how the rate of economic growth can be&#13;
accounted for by the economist's measures of the rate, allocation and&#13;
efficiency of investment. The purpose of the excercise, and also its&#13;
implications, were I think amply summed up in the quotations given in the&#13;
introduction from Johnson, Schultz and Scott. In the relationship derived,&#13;
there is no "residual" (as the term is commonly used in the analysis of&#13;
growth) to represent technical progress. There may of course be a residual&#13;
arising from errors and omissions, but that is a different question. Instead,&#13;
it was argued that technical progress is accounted for in the returns to&#13;
investment plus the changes in labor's income induced by investment.    A large&#13;
number of growth accounting have under-estimated the latter because they have&#13;
underestimated the rate of redeployment of ]abor, both within and between&#13;
different sectors of economic activity, or even within given enterprises,&#13;
brought about by material investment.&#13;
In the analysis of growth, the investment approach followed above&#13;
draws attention to four variables:&#13;
-    the rate of investment (and thus a country's capacity to raise&#13;
savings),&#13;
-    the yields of investment in the various sectors of economic activity,&#13;
-    the allocation of investment among these various sectors (and thus&#13;
the weighted average yield of investment), and&#13;
-    the deployment of labor.&#13;
It is perhaps the principal advantage of the approach that through it the&#13;
methods of micro-economic analysis, and the empirical findings of a large&#13;
number of micro-economic studies concerning the choice and efficiency of&#13;
investments, can be brought to bear on the analysis of growth. On savings and&#13;
investment, for instance, attention is focussed on the incentives to save and&#13;
invest, on the measurable costs of any distortions or administrative&#13;
constraints that might be acting on such incentives and, especially in&#13;
developing countries, on institutional shortcomings in the capital markets&#13;
that may diminish the financial intermediaries'capacitites to identify and&#13;
finance "good" projects. On the yield of investment it is focussed on the&#13;
choice of investments, pricing policies, managerial or "X" inefficiencies and,&#13;
again, on incentives structures. And on labor it is focussed on educational&#13;
and institutional factors that facilitate or' prevent the redeployment of labor&#13;
to those investments with higher yields and, ultimately, higher earnings per&#13;
worker. Other examples could be added. The main point, however, is that many&#13;
policy implications might emerge from an application of the investment&#13;
approach to growth which so far have not, I believe, emerged sufficiently&#13;
clearly from other approaches.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
Anderson, Dennis (1982) "Small-Scale Industry in Developing Countries: A&#13;
Discussion of Issues". World Development Vol. 10, No. 11, pp. 913-948.&#13;
Banerji, Ranader (1978) "Small-Scale Production Units in Manufacturing: An&#13;
International Cross-Section Overview". Weltwietschafliches Archiv,&#13;
pp. 62-82.&#13;
Bhalla, A.S., Editor (1975) Technology and Employment in Industry, I.L.O.&#13;
Binswanger, Hans and Ruttan, Vernon (1978) Induced Innovation: Technology,&#13;
Institutions, and Development. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University&#13;
Press.&#13;
Chenery, Hollis D. (1979) Structural Change and Development Policy. Oxford&#13;
University Press.&#13;
and Syrquin, Moses (1975) Patterns of Development: 1950-&#13;
1970. Oxford University Press.&#13;
Denison, Edward F. (1962) "The Sources of Economic Growth in the United&#13;
States and the Alternatives Before Us" Committee for Economic&#13;
Development, New York.&#13;
(1967) Why Growth Rates Differ: Postwar Experience in Nine&#13;
Western Countries Washington, D.C. The Brookings Institution.&#13;
(1974) Accounting for United States Economic Growth&#13;
Washington, D.C. The Brookings Institution.&#13;
and Chung, William K. (1976) How Japan's Economy Grew So&#13;
Fast: The Sources of Postwar Expansion. Washingtoxl, D.C.: The&#13;
Brookings Institution.&#13;
Eltis, W.A. (1973) Growth and Distribution, London: McMillan.&#13;
Fisher, Franklin M. and McGowan, John J. (1983) "On the Misuse of Accounting&#13;
Rates of Return to Infer Monopoly Profits, American Economic Review,&#13;
Vol. 73, No. 1, March, pp. 82-97.&#13;
Griliches, Zvi (1970) "Notes on the Role of Education in Production&#13;
Functions and Growth Accounting" in W. Lee Hansen, Editor,&#13;
Education Income, and Human Capital. N.B.E.R. Studies in Income&#13;
and Wealth, Vol. 35, Colombia University Press.&#13;
Hahn F.H. and Matthews, R.C.O. (1967) "The theory of Economic Growth", in&#13;
Surveys of Economic Theory, Vol. II: Growth and Development. Edited&#13;
by the AEA and the RES, New York: St. Martin's Press, pp. 1-124.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
Harberger, Arnold (1971) "Three Basic Postulates for Applied Welfare&#13;
Economics". Journal of Economic Literature, Vol. IX, No. 3,&#13;
pp. 785-797.&#13;
__________________ (1979) "Perspectives on Capital and Technology in&#13;
Less-Devieloped Countries" in Kenneth P. Jameson and Charles K.&#13;
Wilbe7; Directions in Economic Development, Univ. of Notre Dame Press.&#13;
Hoselitz, Bert F. (1959) "Small Industry in Underdeveloped Countries" Journal&#13;
of Economic History, Vol. 19.&#13;
J'ohnson, Harry G. (1964) "Towards a Generalized Capital Accumulation Approach&#13;
to Economic Development" in a note entitled "Comments on Mr. John&#13;
Vaizey's Paper" in an O.E.C.D. publication entitled: The Residual&#13;
Factor and Economic Growth.&#13;
Johnston, Bruce F. and Kilby, Peter (1975) Agriculture and Structural&#13;
Transformation: Economic Strategies in Late Developing Countries.&#13;
London, Oxford University Press.&#13;
Kennedy, C and Thirlwall, A.P. (1972) "Technical Progress: A Survey,"&#13;
Economic Journal, March.&#13;
Kuznets, Simon (1966) Modern Economic Growth: Rate, Structure, and Spread.&#13;
Yale University Press.&#13;
Little, I.M.D., Scitovsky, T., and Scott, M. Fg. (1970). Industry and Trade&#13;
in Some Developing Countries, O.E.C.D.&#13;
McKinnon, Ronald I. (1973) Money and Capital Ln Economic Development The&#13;
Brookings Institution, Washington, D.C.&#13;
McKinnon, Ronald I., Editor (1976) Money and Finance in Economic Growth and&#13;
Development.   Essays in Honor of Edward S. Shaw. Marcel Dekker Inc.,&#13;
New York and Basel.&#13;
Mellor, John W. (1976) The New Economic of Growth: A Strategy for India and&#13;
the Developing World, Cornell University Press.&#13;
Mishan, E.J. (1971) Cost-Benefit Analysis: An Introduction, Praeger&#13;
Publishers.&#13;
Myint, H. (1971) Economic Theory and the Underdeveloped Countries. Oxford&#13;
UniversfE37 Press.&#13;
Nelson, Richard R. (1981) "Research on Productivity Growth and Productivity&#13;
Differences: Dead Ends and New Departures". Journal of Economic&#13;
Literature, Vol. XIX (September), pp. 1029-1064.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
Nishimizu, Mieko and Hulten, Charles R. (1978) "The Sources of Japanese&#13;
Economic Growth: 1955-71." The Review of Economics and Statistics,&#13;
Vol. LX No. 3 August.&#13;
Nishimizu, Mieko and Jorgenson, Dale W. (1978) "U.S. and Japanese Economic&#13;
Growth, 1952-74: An International Comparison" The Economic Journal,&#13;
88 (Dpcember 1978), pp. 707-726.&#13;
Prest A.R. and Turvey, R. (1966) "Cost-Benefit Analysis: A Survey" in Surveys&#13;
of Econimic Theory, Vol. 3, Resource Allocation, Prepared for the&#13;
A.E.A. arn the R.E.S. St. Martin's Press, pp. 155-207.&#13;
Ranis, G. (1973) "Industrial Sector Labor Absorption," Economic Development&#13;
and Cultural Change, Vol. 21, April.&#13;
Schultz, Theodore W. (1970) "The Reckoning of Education as Human Capital" in&#13;
W. Lee Hansen, Editor, Education, Income and Human Capital, Studies&#13;
in Income and Wealth, No. 35, NBER, Colombia University Press.&#13;
Scott, Maurice Fg. (1981) "The Contribution of Investment to Growth" Scottish&#13;
Journal of Political Economy, Vol. 28, No. 3, November.&#13;
Sen, Amartya, Editor (1970) Growth Economics, Penguin Modern Economic&#13;
Readings.&#13;
Sen, Amartya K (1974) Employment, Technology and Development, Clarendon&#13;
Press, Oxford.&#13;
Shaw, Edward S. (1973) Financial Deepening in Economic Development. Oxford&#13;
University Press.&#13;
Shinohara, M. (1968) "A Survey of the Japanese Literature on Small Industry"&#13;
in Bert F. Hoselitz, Editor, The Role of Small Industry in the&#13;
Process of Economic Growth, Mouton Press.&#13;
Solow, Robert M. (1957) "Technical Change and the Aggregate Production&#13;
Function" Review of Economic Statistics, August, 39, pp. 79-115.&#13;
(1970) Growth Theory: An Exposition Oxford University Press.&#13;
Staley, Eugene and Morse, Richard (1965) Modern Small-Scale Industry for&#13;
Developing Countries, Mc Graw-Hill.&#13;
Stewart, Frances (1977) Technology and Underdevelopment, Westview Press,&#13;
Boulder, Colorado.&#13;
Stiglitz, Joseph E. and Uzawa, Hirofumi, Editors (1969) Readings in the&#13;
Modern Theory of Economic Growth. The M.I.T. Press.&#13;
Turvey, R (1974) "How to Judge W.hen Prices Will Improve Resource Allocation"&#13;
The Economic Journal, December, Vol. 84, No. 336 pp. 825-832.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
World Bank                          Aggregate Demand and                  Capital Market Imperfec-&#13;
Macroeconomic Imbalances              tions and Economic&#13;
nilblications                       In Thailand: Simulations              Development&#13;
olf Related                         with the SIAM 1 Model                 Vinayak V. Bhatt and&#13;
Wafik Grais                           Alan R. Roe -&#13;
Initerest                           Focuses on the demand-side adjust-    World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
ments of the Thai economy to lower    No. 338. July 1979. 87 pages&#13;
agricultural growth and to higher     (including footnotes).&#13;
energy prices. Discusses p,Dlicy&#13;
measures and structural changes that  Stock No. WP-0338. $3.00.&#13;
might enable the economy to over-&#13;
come these problems and continue to&#13;
maintain high GDP rates of growth.    The Changing Mature of&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paiper No.   Export Finance and Its&#13;
448. April 1981. 70 pages (inicluding  Counictriens   frDvlpn&#13;
2 appendixes).Conre&#13;
Stock No. WP-0448. $3.00.             Albert C. Cizauskas&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
409. July 1980. 43 pages (including&#13;
An Analysis of                        3 annexes).&#13;
Developing Country                    Stock No. WP-0409. $3.00.&#13;
Adjustment Experience and            Adjustment Experiences In&#13;
Growth Prospects of tlhe             the 1970s: Low-Income Asia&#13;
Semi-Industrial Countries            Christine Wallich                     Compounding and Dis-&#13;
f'rederick Jaspersen                 This background study for World       counting Tables for&#13;
This background study for World      Development Report 1981 examines      Project Evaluation&#13;
Development Report 1981 examines      low-income South Asia's adjustment   J. Price Gittinger, editor&#13;
the successful process of adjustment  to the external shocks of the 1970s,  Easily comprehensible, convenient&#13;
to extemal "shocks" of the 1970s      especially those factors that helped  tables for project preparation and&#13;
(rising prices of oil imports, reduced  make the effects of these external  analysis.&#13;
demand for exports, slower economic  developments less severe in the&#13;
growth in the OECD countries) in the  region than In other parts af the    The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
semi-industrial developing countries.  developing world.                   1973; 7th printing, 1982. 143 pages.&#13;
Presents an analytical framework for  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   LC 75-186503. ISBN 0-8018-1604-1,&#13;
quantifying the effects of demand    487. August 1981. Iv + 39 pages       $6.00 paperback.&#13;
management and structural a4iust-    (including references).&#13;
ment in forty-two countries, with par-                                     Arabic: World Bank, 1973. (Available&#13;
ticular reference to Uruguay, Brazil,  Stock No. WP-0487. $3.00.           from ILS, 1715 Connecticut Avenue,&#13;
Republic of Korea, and Turkey' N.W., Washington, D.C. 20009. U.S.A.)&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   Aspects of Development                $4.00 paperback.&#13;
477. August 1981. 132 pages (Including  Bank Management                    French: Tables d'int&amp;ets composes et&#13;
3 appendixes).                        William Diamond and                  d'actualisation. Economica, 4th print-&#13;
Stock No. WP-04 77. $5.00.            V. S. Raghavan                       ing, 1979.&#13;
Deals exclusively with the manage-   ISBN 2-7178-0205-3, 36 francs.&#13;
Adjustment In                         ment of development banks. The       Spanish: Tabias de interes compuesto y&#13;
Low-income Aftica                     book Is divided Into eight sections,  es pdescuto paba devaiuaci6n de proyec&#13;
Robert Liebenthal                     each dealing with one aspect of      dos Edisuetorial a Tenos. 1975 4th printc-&#13;
Thiseueckrouend studyt for1 Wnad      management of its problems, and      ing, 1980.&#13;
This bckgrond stuy forWorldof the various ways of dealing         ig  90&#13;
Develaopment Report 1981 analyzes     with them.                           ISBN 84-309-0716-5, 380 pesetas.&#13;
the adjustment to external shocks&#13;
during the 1970s made by a group      EDI Series in Economic Development.&#13;
of middle-income and low-income       The Johns Hopkins Universily Press,  A Conceptual Approach to&#13;
African countries, with particular    1982. 311 pages.                     the Analysis of External Debt&#13;
reference to Kenya, Tanzania,&#13;
Sefeneal, and Sudan.                  LC 81-48174. ISBN 0-8018-2571-7,     of the Developing Countries&#13;
$29.95 hardcover, ISBN 0-8018-2572-5,  Robert Z. Aliber&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   $12.95 paperback.                     World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
(incl8uding bibtiography).                                                 421. October 1980. 25 pages (including&#13;
(inclkding bibliography),                                                  appendix, references).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0486. $5.00.                                                  Stock No. WP-0421. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Development Banks                   Developments in and                  Food Policy Issues in&#13;
William Diamond                     Prospects for the External           Low-income Countries&#13;
Operating experiences that serve as a  Debt of the Developing            Edward Clay and others&#13;
practical guide for developing coun-  Countries: 1970-80                 A background study for World&#13;
tries, with a selected list and     and Beyond                           Development Report 1981. Discusses&#13;
summary description of some          Nicholas C. Hope                    food distribution-especially its&#13;
development banks.                                  d     f Wold         insecurity in the face of external&#13;
The Johns llopkins University Press,  Development Report 1981 analyzes   economic pressurend potential&#13;
1957; 5th printing, 1969. 141 pages  the debt situation and its implica-  concerns-in general and with&#13;
(including 2 appendixes, index).    tions for future borrowing.          reference to Bangladesh Zambia&#13;
LC 57-13429. ISBN 0-8018-0708-5,     World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  and India.&#13;
$5.00 (i5.50) paperback.            488. August 1981. 70 pages (including  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
2 annexes, references).              473. August 1981. vii + 115 pages.&#13;
Development Finance Com-            Stock No. WP-0488. $3.00.            Stock No. WP-04 73. $5.00.&#13;
panies: Aspects of Policy&#13;
and Operation                       Energy Prices, Substitution,         A General Equilibrium&#13;
William Diamond, editor;            and Optimal Borrowing in             Analysis of Foreign&#13;
essays by E T    nuiper,            the Short Run: An Analysis           Exchange Shortages in a&#13;
Douglas Gustafson, and              of Adjustment In OUi.                Developing Economy&#13;
P. Mi. Mathew                       Importing Developing                 Kemal Dervis, Jaime de Melo,&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press,  Countries                           and Sherman Robinson&#13;
1968.130 pages (including appendix,  Ricardo Martin and                  Examines the consequences of alter-&#13;
index).                             Marcelo Selowsly                     native adjustment mechanisms to&#13;
LC-68-27738. ISBN 0-8018-0166-4,     Develops a short-term model for     foreign exchange shortages in semi-&#13;
$5.00 (f3.25) paperback.             evaluating the adjustment (par-     industrial economies. Compares&#13;
French: Les societes flnancieres de  ticularly, extemal borrowing) of oil-  devaluation to two forms of import&#13;
developpement: quelques aspects de  importing developing countries to the  rationing and finds that adjusting by&#13;
leur politique et de leurs actlvites.  increases in oil prices during the  rationing is much more costly in&#13;
(Avalabe ft frm th Wold Bnk, 1970s. Discusses the borrowing     terms of lost gross domestic product.&#13;
Washvingtn, D. C)                    strategies that can be expected in the  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Wpansh:iLgt  on pa, D.Cnacir)       future and the demands that will be  445. January 1981. 52 pages (includ-&#13;
Spanish: Las compan~ias financieras  made on multilateral institutions.  in3. rearncesy198.32pgs(nld&#13;
de desarrollo: algunos aspectos de su                                    ing references).&#13;
politica y de sus actividades. Editorial  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  Stock No. WP-0443. $3.00.&#13;
Tecnos, 1969.                        466. July 1981. 77 pages (including&#13;
300 pesetas.                        footnotes, references).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0466. $3.00.               NlEW&#13;
Development Prospects&#13;
of Capital Sarplus OilU              Exchange Rate AdJustment            Growth and Structural&#13;
Exporting Countries: Iraq,           under Generalized Currency          Adjustment in East Asia&#13;
Kuwait, Libya. Qatar,                Floating: Comparative               Parvez Hasan&#13;
Saudi Arabia, UAE                    Analysis among Developing           Analyzes the economic performance&#13;
Rudolf HPlablutzel                  Countries                            of the five large market economies of&#13;
This background study for World      Romeo M. Bautista                   Philippinesi Malaysia and&#13;
Development Report 1981              Examines the experiences of twenty-  Indonesia-during the last two&#13;
discusses the production strategies  two developing countries in adapting  decades; focuses on the key factors&#13;
and the development policies of the  to the generalized floating of the  explaining their remarkable economic&#13;
capital-surplus oil-exporting        world's major currencies since 1973  and social progress; and identifies the&#13;
countries.                           and discusses the implications that  main economic issues for the 1980s.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  currency floating has on policymaking  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
483. August 1981. 53 pages (including  Ions for further research.        529. 1982. 42 pages.&#13;
statistical tables).                 World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  ISBN 0-8213-0102-0. $3.00.&#13;
Stock N1o. WP-0483. $5.00.           436. October 1980. 99 pages (including&#13;
appendix).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0436. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
International A4justtment In        Motes on the Mechanics of          ect appraisal. To give substance to&#13;
the 980s                            Growth and Debt                    the applied and policy dimensions,&#13;
Vea Josh                           Growthamnd BDebti                   many of the readings are drawn from&#13;
Vijay Joshi                         BenJamin B. King                   the experience of development prac-&#13;
A backgound study for Worli        A practical model to explore the way  titloners and relate to such important&#13;
Development Report 1981. Analyzes   in which capital inflow frcm abroad  sectors as agriculture, industry&#13;
the macroeconomics of intemational  affects economic growth.           power, urban services, foreign trade,&#13;
adjustment. Highlights potential                                       and employment. The principles&#13;
market failures and areas for       The Johns Hapkins University Prss  outlined are therefore relevant to a&#13;
intervention.                      1968. 69 pages (including 4 annexes).  host of development problems.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  LC 68-8701. ISBII 0-8018-0338-1, $5.00  The Johns llopkins University Press.&#13;
485. August 1982. 5 7 pages.       (03.00) paperback.                  February 1983. About 304 pages.&#13;
ISBN1 0-8213-0062-8. $3.00.                                            LC 82-7716. ISBN 0-8018-2803-1,&#13;
The Policy Experience of            $35.00 hardcover; ISBIY 0-8018-2804-X.&#13;
Twelve Less Developed               $12.95 paperback.&#13;
NEW                             Countries, 1973-1978&#13;
Bela Balassa                        Private Bank Lending to&#13;
The Nature of Credit               Uses the methodology applied in the  Developing Countries&#13;
Markets In Developing              author's 'The Newly Industrializing  Richard O'Brien&#13;
Countries: A Framework             Developing Countries after the Oil&#13;
foir Policy Analysis               Crisis" (World Bank Staff Working   A background study for World&#13;
Arvind Virmani                      Paper Nlo. 473, October 1980) to   Development Report 1981.&#13;
examine the policy experience of    Describes the evolution of relation-&#13;
The: central purpose of the paper is to  twelve less developed countries in  ships between private banks and&#13;
analyze various forms of government  the period following the quadrupling  developing countries.&#13;
intervention in the loan mariket in  of oil prices in 1973-74 and the  World Bank Staff Working Paper IYo&#13;
terms of their effect on efficiency,  world recession of 1974-75.      482. August 1981. li + 54 pages&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper 11o.  World Bank Staff Working P aper No.  (including appendix, bibliography).&#13;
524. 1982. 204 pages.              449. April 1981. 36 pages (including  Stock No. WP-0482. $3.00.&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0019-9. $5.00.         appendix).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0449. $3.00.&#13;
Private Capital Flows to&#13;
The Newly Industrializing                                               Developing Countries and&#13;
Developing Countries after         The Political Structure of          Their Determinations:&#13;
the Oi Crisis                      the New Protectionilsm              Historical Perspective,&#13;
Bela Balassa                        Douglas R. Nelson                  Recent Experience, and&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  This background study for World    Future Prospects&#13;
43 7Ocoe190      7pae(icuig        Development Report 1981             Alex Fleming&#13;
37. October1980 57 pages (Including  presents a political-econoirnic   A    Fleming&#13;
appendix).                         analysis of what has been called the  A backgound study for World&#13;
Stock No. WP-0437. $3.00.           "new protectionism."               Development Report 1981.&#13;
Discusses the nature and deterrnina-&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  tion of recent private capital flows to&#13;
Notes on the Analysis of           471. July 1981. 57 pages (including  developing countries. Focuses on&#13;
Capital Flows to Developing         references).                       those flows passing through the&#13;
Maltlons anmd the                  Stock No. WP-04 71. $3.00.          international banks and examines the&#13;
Nations and the   Stock Mo. WP-04 71. $3.00.          prospects for and constraints on&#13;
"Recycling"' Problem                                                   developing countries' continuing&#13;
Ralph C. Bryant                                                        access to the international capital&#13;
A backgound study for World            NEW                              markets.&#13;
Development Report 1981.                                                World Bank Staff Working Paper N1o.&#13;
Summarizes and criticizes the con-  Pricing Policy for Develop-        484. August 1981. 41 pages.&#13;
ventional analysis of the interrela-  ment Management&#13;
tions between financial markets In  Gerald M. Meier                    Stock No. WP-0484. $3.00.&#13;
the industrialized countries and capi-&#13;
tal flows to the developing nations.  Presupposing no formal training in&#13;
economics, it explains the essential  Private Direct Foreign&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  elements of a price system, the     Investment in Developing&#13;
476. August 1981. 67 pages.         functions of prices, the vai-ious   Countries&#13;
Stock No. WP-0476. $3.00.           policies that a government, might&#13;
pursue In cases of market failure,  K. Billerbeck and Y. Yasugi&#13;
and the principles of pubili: pricing of  World Bank Staff Working Paper 11o.&#13;
goods and services provided by      348. July 1979. iv + 97 pages (includ-&#13;
government enterprises. It also pro-  ing 2 annexes)&#13;
vides the would-be practitioner with  i&#13;
an appreciation of the underlying   Stock tto. WP-0348. $5.00.&#13;
logical structure of cost-beneflt proj-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NEW                             Structural Adjustment               implications in terms of income&#13;
Policies in Developing              generation, extemal deflcit, and&#13;
Short-Run Macro-Economic            Economies                           inflation.&#13;
Adjustment Policies in              3ela Balassa                        World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
South Korea: A Quantitative         Examines structural adjustment      513. June 1982. 93 pages (including&#13;
Analysis                            policies (policy responses to extemal  appendix).&#13;
Sweder van Wjnbergen                shocks, such as the quadrupling of  ISBN 0-8213-0023- 7. $3.00.&#13;
oil prices and the world recession of&#13;
An analysis of the startling reversal of  the 1970s) of developing countries.&#13;
performance of the South Korean     Considers reforms in production     World Debt Tables&#13;
economy in 1979 and 1980 compared  incentives, incentives to save and to&#13;
with the preceding flfteen years, and  invest, public investments, sectoral  A compilation of data on the extemal&#13;
an exploration of the short-run     policies, and monetary policies, and  public and publicly-guaranteed debt&#13;
macro-economic policy options       comments on the interdependence of  of 101 developing countries plus&#13;
available to Korea in 1981. Highlights  the various policy measures and on  eighteen additional tables of private&#13;
the role of commercial banks, foreign  the international environment in  and nonguaranteed debt from the&#13;
capital inflows, and money markets  which they o  rate.                 World Bank Debtor Reporting&#13;
and the use of credit obtained from            pe                       System. Describes the nature, con-&#13;
these sources to flnance fixed and  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  tent and coverage of the data;&#13;
working capital.                    464. July 1981. 36 pages.           reviews the external debt of 101&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  Stock No. WP-0464. $5.00.           countries through 198L contains&#13;
tables on external public debt out-&#13;
510. November 1981. iv + 178 pages                                      standing, commitments, disburse-&#13;
(including 3 appendixes).                                               ments, service payments, and net&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0000-8. $5.00.              NEW                             borrowings of 101 developing coun-&#13;
tries, by country, 1972-1981.&#13;
Structural Aspects of               (EC-167/81). December 1982. Annual.&#13;
NEW                             Turkish Inflation:                  About 300 pages.&#13;
1950-1979                           ISSN 0253-2859. $75.00.&#13;
State Finances in India             M. Ataman Aksoy                     Computer tapes containing the data&#13;
A three-volume set of papers that   Inflation has been one of the major  bases for the World Debt Tables are&#13;
explores a range of issues relating to  problems of the Turkish economy  available from the Publications&#13;
the nature of intergovemmental flscal  during the postwar period. This paper  Distribution Unit, World Bank. The&#13;
relations in India.                 develops altemative inflation models  tapes are available to international&#13;
and analyzes their performance in   agencies and offlcial nonproflt agen-&#13;
light of the Turkish experience In  des of member govemments at a&#13;
Vol I., Revenue Sharing             order to provide a framework on     nominal fee. For information concem-&#13;
In India                            which a more realistic macro model  ing fees for other organizations,&#13;
Christine Wallich                   can be developed.                   please write to the addressee listed&#13;
Deals speciflcally with the principles  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  above.&#13;
of revenue sharing in India.        540. 1982. 118 pages.                Supplements to World Debt Tables are&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0098-9. $5.00.          issued periodically as information&#13;
Vol II: India-Studies In                                                becomes available; the current&#13;
State Finances                                                           updates are included with orders for&#13;
Christine Wallich                       NEW                              World Debt Tables.&#13;
Examines in detail the implications of&#13;
revenue sharing for project finance.  ThaiFland: An Analysis of&#13;
Structural and Non-                 The Impact of Contractual Savings on&#13;
Resource Mobilization and Allocation:&#13;
VoL III: The Measurement of         Structural A4justments              The Experience of Malaysia&#13;
Tax Effort of State Govern-         Arne Drud, Wafik Grais, and         Social Security Funds In Singapore&#13;
ments, 1973-1976                     Dusan Vujovic                      and the Philippines: Ramlcatlons of&#13;
Raja J. Chelliah and                This study was prepared as a        Investment Poicies&#13;
Narain Sinha                        background paper for the preparation  Investments of Social Security Funds&#13;
Attempts to evaluate the tax perfor-  of a structural-a4Justment loan to  and Experience&#13;
mance of particular states in terms of  Thailand and Is a follow-up to a pre-  Parthasarathi Shame and&#13;
the average tax effort of all states.  vious paper entitled 'Aggregate  Katrine Anderson Saito&#13;
Demand and Macroeconomic            World Bank Reprint Series: Number 144.&#13;
World Bank Working Paper No. 523.   Imbalances in Thailand: Comparative  Reprinted Banm The Malayan Economic Review, uol.&#13;
September 1982. vol. I, 85 pages. vol. II  statistics are used, within the frame-  23, no. I (April 1978):54-72; Labour and Society,&#13;
186 pages, vol. III, 85 pages.      work of a four-sector macroeconomic  vol. 5. no. I (January 1980):19-30; and The Indian&#13;
model, to assess altemative ways of  Joumal of Economics. vol. 60. part 3. no. 238&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0013-X- vol. I, $3-00, vol. 11  macroeconomic adjustment in the  (January 1980):349-60.&#13;
$5.00, vol. IIl, $3.00.             Thai economy. Discusses specifically  Stock no. RP-0144. Free of charge.&#13;
fiscal policy interventions, manipula-&#13;
tions of the exchange rate, and pro-&#13;
ductivity improvements and their&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Polcy Responses to Cxteirnal Shocks In&#13;
Selected Latin American Countries&#13;
Bela Balassa&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Nlumber 221.&#13;
Reprinted from Quarterly Review of Economics and&#13;
Business. vol. 21, no. 2 (Summer 1981):131-64.&#13;
Stock No. RP-0221. Free of charge.&#13;
Restructurtng the World Econory:&#13;
Round 11&#13;
Hlollis Chenery&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Nlumber 204.&#13;
Reprinted from Foreign Affairs&#13;
(Summer 1981I:1102-U20.&#13;
Stock t10. RP-0204. free of charSfe.&#13;
Risk Assessn,ents and Ribk Premiums&#13;
In the Eurodollar Market&#13;
Gershon Feder and Knud Ross&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Nlumber 220.&#13;
Reprinted from The Journal of Firiance, uol. 37.&#13;
no. 3 (June 1982):679-91.&#13;
Stock Nio. RP-0220. Free of charge.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBIICATIONS&#13;
ORDER FORM&#13;
SEND TO:&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS                                                         WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
P.O. BOX 37525                                             or                   66, AVENUE D'IENA&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013                                                          75116 PARIS, FRANCE&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Name:&#13;
Address:&#13;
Stock or ISBN #                             Author, Title                        Oty.        Price         Total&#13;
Sub-Total Cost:&#13;
Postage &amp; handling fee for more than two free items ($1.00 each):&#13;
Total copies:     __    - Air mail surcharge ($2.00 each):&#13;
TOTAL PAYMENT ENCLOSED:&#13;
Make checks payable: WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
Prepayment on orders from indiviJuals is requested. Purchase orders are accepted from booksellers, library suppliers, libraries, and institutions.&#13;
All prices include cost of postage by the least expensive means. The prices and publication dates quoted in this Catalog are subject to change&#13;
without notice.&#13;
No refunds will be given for items that cannot be filled. Credit will be appliedJ towards future orders.&#13;
No more than two free publications will be provided without charge. Requests for additional copies will be filled at a charge of US $1.00 per&#13;
copy to cover handling and postage costs.&#13;
Airmail delivery will require al prepayment of US $2.00 per copy.&#13;
Mail-order payment to the World Bank need not be in U.S. dollars, but the arnount remitted must be at the rate of exchange on the day the&#13;
order is placed. The World Bank will also accept Unesco coupons,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PUB HG3881.5 .W57 W67 no.591&#13;
Anderson, Dennis, 193;'-&#13;
A relationship between the&#13;
rate of economic growth and&#13;
the rate, allocation, and&#13;
PUB HG3881.5.W57 W67 no.591&#13;
Anderson, Dennis, 1937-&#13;
A relationship between the&#13;
rate of econanic growth and&#13;
the r&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters:&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK&#13;
Cable address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
European Office:&#13;
66, avenue d'lena&#13;
75116 Paris, France&#13;
Telephone: (1) 723-54.21&#13;
Telex: 842-620628&#13;
Tokyo Office:&#13;
Kokusai Building&#13;
1-1, Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
Telex: 781-26838&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0186-1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554862">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/05/1554862/relationship-between-rate-economic-growth-rate-allocation-efficiency-investment
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/05/1554862/relationship-between-rate-economic-growth-rate-allocation-efficiency-investment</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1983/05/1554862/relationship-between-rate-economic-growth-rate-allocation-efficiency-investment</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/01/08/000178830_98101903420350/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/01/08/000178830_98101903420350/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-01-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1983-05-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            A relationship between the rate of economic
            growth and the rate, allocation, and efficiency of investment
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The purpose of this paper is to derive
            and discuss a relationship between the rate of economic
            growth and variables representing the rate, allocation, and
            efficiency of investment. It discusses how the methods and
            results of microeconomics might be brought to bear on the
            analysis of growth. The approach is compared with those of
            several long-standing studies on the subject. It is shown
            that the technical progress parameter in these studies turns
            out not to be a parameter but a function of the rate of
            investment, the allocation of investment among economic
            activities, the rates of return to investment in these
            activities, and variables representing the influence of
            investment on these activities, and variables representing
            the influence of investment on labor's share in
            economic output. The weighted average returns to investment
            implied by the approach are estimated for several countries
            and do not seem to be inconsistent with project experience
            and with their observed growth rates. An attempt is made to
            discuss the relevance of the approach for the analysis of
            economic policy.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            A relationship between the rate of economic
            growth and the rate, allocation, and efficiency of investment
        </docna>
        <display_title>A relationship between the rate
            of economic growth and the rate, allocation, and efficiency
            of investment</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1983/05/1554862/relationship-between-rate-economic-growth-rate-allocation-efficiency-investment</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Trade and Regional Integration,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Economic Theory &amp; Research,International Terrorism &amp; Counterterrorism,Economic Growth</subtopic>
        <teratopic>International Economics and Trade</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>ANDERSON, D.</author>
            <author>WAP</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903420350</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Macro/non-trade</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 591</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>International Economics and Trade</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0186-1</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Investment; Mathematical models; Rate of
            return; Allocation of resources; Economic growth
            affiliated
            organizations,agriculture,allocative efficiency,alternative
            investments,average incomes,base year,bid,capital
            accumulation,consumers,deflation,development
            policies,discount rate,discounted value,ECONOMIC
            ANALYSIS,economic change,Economic development,economic
            efficiency,economic growth,economic life,economic rate of
            return,economic
            sectors,economists,employment,expenditures,externalities,first
            year,fixed assets,gross investment,gross output,Growth
            Accounting,growth problem,growth rate,growth rates,growth
            theory,human
            capital,income,industrialization,inflation,Intermediate
            Inputs,investment expenditures,investment incentives,labor
            costs,labor force,labor productivity,legal status,Marginal
            Analysis,marginal product,Mathematical models,model of
            growth,national income,planned economy,present
            value,producers,productive
            capacity,productivity,productivity growth,real wage,real
            wages,relative prices,resource allocation,streams,Structural
            Change,structural changes,technical progress,total
            output,unemployment,value added,variable costs,wage differentials,wages
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP591</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Formulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Implementation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Productivity-Led Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Bill</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Compression</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research and Development Commercialization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research and Innovation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Electric Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis of Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Employment and Wage Data</ml:concept><ml:concept>Terrorism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research, Development and Innovation (RDI)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>