<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP682&#13;
Women's Status and Fertility in Developing Countries&#13;
Son Preference and Economic Security&#13;
Mead Cain&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 682&#13;
POPULATION AND DEVELOPMENT SERIES&#13;
Number 7&#13;
H(&#13;
C&#13;
w&#13;
t iLE ui*Y&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 682                                4)67&#13;
POPULATION AND DEVELOPMENT SERIES&#13;
Number 7                                .&amp;&#13;
Women's Status and Fertility in Developing Countries&#13;
Son Preference and Economic Security&#13;
Mead Cain&#13;
INhTENATIlOSAL W1OUIETARY FUND&#13;
JOINT LIBRARY&#13;
FL2    1 185&#13;
nrC'U0N3Tn.VCilO1CI-DN EE.tP:&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright C 1984&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 hI Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
ManuFactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing November 1984&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To present&#13;
the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been&#13;
prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed texts, and&#13;
the World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a&#13;
token charge to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The World Bank does not accept responsibility for the views expressed herein, which&#13;
are those of the authors and should not be attributed to the World Bank or to its&#13;
affiliated organizations The findings, interpretations, and conclusions are the results&#13;
of research supported by the Bank; they do not necessarily represent official policy of&#13;
the Bank. The designations employed, the presentation of material, and any maps used&#13;
in this document are solely for the convenience of the reader and do not imply the&#13;
expression of any opinion whatsoever on the part of the World Bank or its affiliates&#13;
concerning the legal status of any country, territory, city, area, or of its authorities, or&#13;
concerning the delimitation of its boundaries, or national affiliation&#13;
The Full range of World Bank publications, both free and for sale, is described in the&#13;
CataloXg of Publications; the continuing research program is outlined in Abstracts of&#13;
Current Studies. Both booklets are updated annually; the most recent edition of each is&#13;
available without charge from the Publications Sales Unit, Department T, The World&#13;
Bank, L818 H Street, N.W., Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A., or from the European&#13;
Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'Iena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
An associate of the Center for Population Studies of The Population Council, New&#13;
York, Mead Cain is a consultant to The World Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Cain, Mead.&#13;
Women's status and fertility in developing countries.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 682)&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
1. Family size--Developing countries. 2. Sex of&#13;
chilcLren, Parental preferences for--Developing countries.&#13;
3. Women--Developing countries--Economic conditions.&#13;
4. Fertility, Human--Developing countries. I. Title.&#13;
II. Series.&#13;
HQ762.D44C35     1984       304.6'32'091724          84-22109&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0446-1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FOREWORD&#13;
This paper is one in a special series of World Bank Staff&#13;
Working Papers on population change and development. Prepared as&#13;
background papers for the World Development Report 1984, they provide&#13;
more detailed treatment and documentation of the issues dealt with in&#13;
Part II of the Report. The papers cover a range of topics, including&#13;
the effects of fertility and mortality, the links between population&#13;
growth and internal and international migration, and the management,&#13;
financing, and effectiveness of family planning programs. They include&#13;
several country and regional studies of fertility change and population&#13;
policy.&#13;
The background papers draw on a large number of published and&#13;
unpublished studies of individual researchers, on Bank policy analysis&#13;
and research, and on reports of other organizations working on popula-&#13;
tion and development programs and issues. The papers are the work of&#13;
individuals and the views and interpretations expressed in them do not&#13;
necessarily coincide with the views and interpretations of the Report&#13;
itself.&#13;
I hope these detailed studies will supplement the World&#13;
Development Report 1984 in furthering understanding of population and&#13;
development issues among students and practitioners of development.&#13;
Nancy Birdsall&#13;
Staff Director&#13;
World Development Report 1984&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Some of the Papers in the Population and Development Series&#13;
Ainsworth, Martha. Family Planning Programs: The Clients'&#13;
Perspective. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 676.&#13;
Bulatao, Rodolfo A. Expenditures on Population Programs in Major&#13;
Regions of the Developing World: Current Levels and Future&#13;
Requirements. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 679.&#13;
Bulatao, Rodolfo A. Reducing Fertility in Developing Countries: A&#13;
Review of Determinants and Policy Levers. World Bank Staff&#13;
Working Paper no. 680.&#13;
Cain, Mead. Women's Status and Fertility in Developing Countries:&#13;
Son Preference and Economic Security. World Bank Staff Working&#13;
Paper no. 682.&#13;
Gwatkin, Davidson. Mortality Reduction, Fertility Decline, and&#13;
Population Growth: Toward A More Relevant Assessment of&#13;
Relationships Among Them. World Bank Staff Working Paper no.&#13;
686.&#13;
Herz, Barbara. Official Development Assistance for Population&#13;
Activities: A Review. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 688.&#13;
McNicoll, Geoffrey. Consequences of Rapid Population Growth: An&#13;
Overv:Lew. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 691.&#13;
Sapir, Andre. Some Aspects of Population Growth, Trade, and Factor&#13;
Mobility. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 694.&#13;
Standing, Guy. Population Mobility and Productive Relations:&#13;
Demographic Links and Policy Evolution. World Bank Staff Working&#13;
Paper no. 695.&#13;
Tan, Jee-Peng, and Michael Haines. Schooling and Demand for Children:&#13;
Historical Perspectives. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 697.&#13;
Trussell, James, and Anne R. Pebley. The Potential Impact of Changes&#13;
in Fertility on Infant, Child, and Maternal Mortality. World&#13;
Bank Staff Working Paper no. 698.&#13;
Zachariah, K.C., and Sulekha Patel. Determinants of Fertility Decline&#13;
in India: An Analysis. World Bank Staff Working Paper no. 699.&#13;
Zachariah, K.C. The Anomaly of the Fertility Decline in India's&#13;
Kerala State: A Field Investigation. World Bank Staff Working&#13;
Paper no. 700.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Abstract&#13;
This paper examines the relationship between women's status--defined&#13;
in terms of the degree to which they are economically dependent on men--&#13;
and fertility in developing countries.  The paper adopts a particular&#13;
theoretical perspective regarding fertility determinants in developing coun-&#13;
tries and explores the implications of women's status within that context.&#13;
This perspective gives special attention to the value of children as security&#13;
assets in settings where public welfare assistance is minimal or non existent&#13;
and financial and insurance markets are poorly developed. In this context,&#13;
women's economic status, and the institutional factors that create a&#13;
particular degree of dependence, determine the relevance of sex of children&#13;
in defining security goals. In societies where women are highly dependent on&#13;
men, security goals will, of necessity, be defined in terms of surviving sons;&#13;
where women are relatively independent economically, it is more likely that&#13;
children of either sex can serve security goals. Given similar security needs,&#13;
and other things being equal, fertility will be considerably higher in settings&#13;
where there is a strong preference for sons than in settings where son&#13;
preference is weak. A cross-national empirical analysis is presented that&#13;
lends support to this argument.&#13;
Acknowledgements&#13;
Comments on an earlier draft of this paper by Judith Bruce, Ethel Churchill,&#13;
Odile Frank, Judith Heyer, and Geoffrey McNicoll are gratefully acknowl-&#13;
edged. The figures were prepared by Adrienne Lindgren.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Condense&#13;
Cette 6tude examine le rapport qui existe entre la situation de&#13;
la femme - d6finie selon son degre de dependance a 1'egard de l'homme - et&#13;
la f6condite dans les pays en d6veloppement. Partant d'un certain point&#13;
de vue theorique en ce qui concerne les e16ments dont d6pend la f6condite&#13;
dans les pays en developpement, elle analyse les implications qu'il&#13;
comporte pour la situation de la femme. Selon ce point de vue, dans un&#13;
contexte oii l'aide sociale est minime ou inexistante et oui les march6s&#13;
financiers et l'assurance sont peu developpes, l'enfant revet une impor-&#13;
tance particuliere en tant que source de s6curit6. A cet 6gard, l'impor-&#13;
tance du seKe des enfants pour la definition des objectifs en matiere de&#13;
s6curite est fonction de la situation 6conomique de la femme et des fac-&#13;
teurs institutionnels qui creent pour elle un certain degr6 de depen-&#13;
dance. Dans les soci6tes oui les femmes sont fortement tributaires des&#13;
hommes, l'objectif de securite se traduit necessairement par le nombre de&#13;
fils vivants; en revanche, lorsque les femmes jouissent d'une certaine&#13;
ind6pendance economique, le sexe des enfants a moins de chances d'inter-&#13;
venir dans la definition des objectifs de securite. Toutes choses etant&#13;
6gales par ailleurs, si l'on suppose des besoins de s6curit6 similaires,&#13;
la f6conditi5 sera beaucoup plus elevee dans une soci6te qui accorde une&#13;
nette pr6ference aux fils que dans une autre oui cette pref6rence est moins&#13;
marqu6e. Une analyse empirique effectu6e dans plusieurs pays corrobore ce&#13;
point de vue.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Extracto&#13;
En este documento se examina la relaci6n entre la situaci6n de la&#13;
mujer --definida en funci6n del grado en que dependen del hombre en el&#13;
aspecto  econ6mico-- y   la fecundidad   en los paises en desarrollo.      Se&#13;
adopta una determinada perspectiva te6rica con respecto a los determinan-&#13;
tes de la fecundidad en estos paises y se exploran las repercusiones de la&#13;
situaci6n de la mujer en ese contexto.      Con esta perspectiva se presta&#13;
especial atenci6n al valor de los hijos como elemento de seguridad en&#13;
situaciones en las que la asistencia publica en asuntos de bienestar es&#13;
minima o inexistente y los mercados financieros y de seguros estan poco&#13;
adelantados.   En este contexto, la situaci6n econ6mica de la mujer y los&#13;
factores institucionales que crean un determinado grado de dependencia&#13;
determinan la importancia del sexo de los hijos para definir metas de&#13;
seguridad.   En las sociedades en que las mujeres dependen mucho de los&#13;
hombres, las metas de seguridad se definirAn, necesariamente, en t6rminos&#13;
del nuimero de hijos varones que sobrevive; cuando las mujeres tienen una&#13;
relativa independencia econ6mica, es mas probable que los hijos de ambos&#13;
sexos sirvan a estos fines.     Con necesidades similares de seguridad y a&#13;
igualdad de los demas factores, puede considerarse que la fecundidad es&#13;
mas elevada en ambientes en que hay una marcada preferencia por los hijos&#13;
varones que cuando esta preferencia es debil.      Se presenta un analisis&#13;
empirico en varios paises que apoya este argumento.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Contents&#13;
Page&#13;
I.   Introduction                                              1&#13;
II.   A Partial Theory of Fertility                             2&#13;
1.  Children as security assets                           2&#13;
2.  A safety-first model of fertility                     4&#13;
3.  Economic development and fertility decline            6&#13;
III.   Women's Status and Fertility                              9&#13;
1. Economic dependence: Son preference&#13;
and patriarchal risk                                9&#13;
2.  Example:  Bangladesh and South India                 11&#13;
3.  Family structure:  Boundaries of the&#13;
corporate group                                   17&#13;
4. A structural perspective on women's&#13;
economic status                                   25&#13;
IV.   Framework for Empirical Analysis                         30&#13;
1.  Direct effects of patriarchal structure              30&#13;
2.  Indirect effects of patriarchal structure            34&#13;
3. Empirical application: Age difference&#13;
between spouses                                   38&#13;
4.  Preference for sons                                  47&#13;
V.   Conclusion                                               55&#13;
Notes                                                           60&#13;
Appendix                                                        67&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. Introduction&#13;
The task of assessing the significance of the "status of women" as a&#13;
determinant of fertility in developing countries encounters certain diffi-&#13;
culties that are common to all reviews of the relationship between a&#13;
particular explanatory variable and fertility. In all cases one is&#13;
confronted by a large body of literature, with no common theoretical&#13;
foundation, which includes work at different levels of analysis, from&#13;
different parts of the world, of widely varying quality. The majority of&#13;
empirical work is oriented toward generating measures of statistical&#13;
association between variables; however, interpretation of statistical&#13;
relationships is impeded by the lack of theory and a generally poor&#13;
understanding of local cultural and institutional contexts. Additional&#13;
complications arise in a review of work in which "the status of women" is the&#13;
variable of primary interest. In part these derive from the elusiveness of&#13;
the concept itself -- there seems to be no common or ready understanding of&#13;
what is meant by "the status of women" -- and in part because work in this&#13;
area often produces an uneasy mixture of positive analysis and normative&#13;
prescription.&#13;
This paper adopts a particular theoretical point of view regarding&#13;
fertility determinants and examines the implications of women's status for&#13;
fertility within that context. The theory, which is briefly outlined in the&#13;
first section of the paper, gives special attention to the value of children&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
as security assets in developing country settings. This perspective can be&#13;
ccntrasted with conceptual frameworks that put great emphasis on the&#13;
near-term costs of children to parents, often to the exclusion of later&#13;
security concerns. The paper also focuses rather narrowly on one dimension&#13;
of women's status -- women's economic dependence on men -- that is&#13;
particularly relevant to reproductive behavior in the context of the&#13;
"safety-first" model of fertility. Women's economic dependence is viewed as&#13;
a consequence of patriarchal structure: elements of the institutional&#13;
setting that serve to restrict the economic independence of women. The&#13;
relationship Cbetween women's economic dependence and fertility, and the&#13;
relevance of family structure to this relationship, are discussed in the&#13;
second major section of the paper. Women's economic dependence is thought to&#13;
influence fertility primarily through associated parental preferences for the&#13;
sex of children. The final section presents a cross-national analysis of&#13;
women's status, its social structural antecedents, and fertility with the use&#13;
of World Fertility Survey data.&#13;
This paper does not attempt to systematically survey the literature on&#13;
women's status and fertility. For such a survey the reader is referred to an&#13;
excellent recent critical review by Mason.&#13;
II. A Partia:L Theory of Fertility2&#13;
1. Children as security assets. In those parts of South Asia that I&#13;
have studied, all indications -- from individual responses to such questions&#13;
as why sterilization is delayed until a particular parity and child-sex&#13;
composition hcave been achieved; from instances of misfortune befalling aging&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
parents who do not have a surviving son to depend on; or from evidence of&#13;
the insecurity of property rights, widespread failure of financial and&#13;
insurance markets, and absence of important extrafamilial welfare&#13;
institutions -- point to the salience of parental security concerns for&#13;
reproductive strategies.3&#13;
In rural South Asia (and, indeed, most other parts of the developing&#13;
world), where financial and insurance markets are poorly developed and there&#13;
is no tradition of extrafamilial welfare institutions, children have a number&#13;
of desirable properties as security assets. Most importantly, with respect&#13;
to security for elderly parents, they fulfill the need for an annuity.&#13;
Uncertainty about length of life and the period and severity of debility that&#13;
may precede death requires an investment that yields an assured income for an&#13;
indefinite period. A strategy of asset accumulation followed by dissaving is&#13;
not responsive to this requirement. Although the accumulation of wealth will&#13;
clearly contribute to security in old age, one can rarely be certain that&#13;
contingencies, such as unusual longevity, will not arise for which the sale&#13;
of a fixed quantity of assets will prove to be inadequate.&#13;
Many amenities and necessary services illustrate the desirability of&#13;
receiving "annuity payments" in the form of labor, and argue for the&#13;
superiority of children as a security investment. A partial list might&#13;
include health care, food preparation, and companionship. (The labor in&#13;
these instances is more likely to be provided by a son's wife than by a son.)&#13;
Although one could conceivably obtain some of these services in the market,&#13;
they would be highly imperfect substitutes for those provided by kin.&#13;
Children, of course, are neither costless nor risk-free investments.&#13;
They may die or become disabled; and they may refuse to honor their&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
obligations to parents. Despite the risks entailed in investing in children&#13;
as security assets, however, they embody qualities that set them apart.&#13;
First among these is the quality of support they provide to parents, which is&#13;
another way o:E acknowledging the central position of the family in developing&#13;
societies.  Life without family is barely worth living. Although the&#13;
maintenance of an adequate level of subsistence in old age represents an&#13;
important goal, individuals aspire to a good deal more. They may aspire as&#13;
much or more to their due as elders: deference from others, comfort, peace,&#13;
and companionship. For such "ccmmodities" there are clearly no substitutes&#13;
for their chi:Ldren and their children's families. Second is the versatility&#13;
of children as security assets in settings where insecurity is rife and&#13;
derives from imany different sources, of which the process of aging is only&#13;
one. Third, in many settings the security of land, a potential alternative&#13;
to children as a "second best" annuity, and of income derived from land is in&#13;
doubt. In such circumstances, children may, in fact, serve as an important&#13;
means of insuring against property loss.&#13;
2.  A safety-first model of fertility.  Accepting the proposition that&#13;
parents in most developing countries place a high value on children as&#13;
security assets, how does one best incorporate this into models of&#13;
reproductive decision-making? One class of decision models, which draws&#13;
partially on bounded rationality theory, seems particularly promising in&#13;
application to old-age security concerns and reproductive decisions:&#13;
lexicographic decision rules based on the criterion of "safety-first" (ISF).4&#13;
Develcped to study innovation adoption behavior of farmers, LSF models assume&#13;
that farmers, in making production decisions, are motivated not only by a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
desire to maximize net returns, but also by the condition that net returns&#13;
not fall beneath some specified "disaster level."&#13;
In the case of reproductive decisions, assume that parents wish to&#13;
maximize "utility" subject to the chance constraint that the probability of&#13;
inadequate support and quality of life in old age is less than or equal to&#13;
some target probability. Here, the first priority is to make adequate&#13;
provision for the future with reasonable certainty. Only after this&#13;
constraint is satisfied do parents concern themselves with the fertility&#13;
implications of the more familiar time and commodity costs and benefits of&#13;
children.&#13;
The LSF model as applied to reproductive decisions suggests that parents&#13;
define minimum requirements for old-age security in terms of a certain number&#13;
of surviving children. Suppose, for example, that this minimum is one&#13;
healthy and loyal surviving son. The fertility level that is consistent with&#13;
this goal will depend primarily on the probability of child survival and the&#13;
probability of child default. The higher the level of child mortality, the&#13;
greater the fertility necessary to achieve the goal. Similarly, concern over&#13;
child default should induce higher fertility than if there were no such&#13;
concern.5 Mortality and default risks may cause the operational "rule of&#13;
thumb" to be revised upward, such that tWo sons surviving through infancy&#13;
becomes the goal. In particular developing societies, the way in which&#13;
targets are defined, and thus their implications for fertility strategies,&#13;
will depend on several factors. For example, societies vary in the extent to&#13;
which sex of offspring is relevant to framing targets. For some societies,&#13;
only sons will do, while in others it may only be necessary to have x&#13;
surviving children, irrespective of sex.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6-&#13;
The target may be adjusted upward in response to the need for additional&#13;
insurance against other contingencies.6 For example, if the security of&#13;
property rights is dependent upon strength in numbers, the target may be&#13;
raised from two sons to three. Culturally determined restrictions on the&#13;
economic activities of women may create dependency that places them at&#13;
extraordinary risk in the event of widowhood or divorce, and thus have a&#13;
similar effect. The presence of additional sources of risk would not&#13;
necessarily require an adjustment in the target, however. It could well be&#13;
that the target set for old-age security is sufficiently high to satisfy&#13;
additional needs. Nevertheless, multiple sources of risk would serve to&#13;
reinforce rejproductive goals and increase the significance of attaining them.&#13;
3.  Ecnomic development and fertility decline.  How would one's&#13;
expectations about change in fertility in response to economic development&#13;
differ with the 1SF model as compared to coupeting theories?&#13;
According to the relative child cost framework developed by Peter&#13;
Lindert7, an improvement in infant and child mortality should have an&#13;
unambiguous negative effect on the relative cost of children because time&#13;
costs in particular are heaviest in the first few years of a child's life,&#13;
while the returns from child labor do not begin to accrue until after the&#13;
period of highest mortality risk. On the other hand, in the LSF model an&#13;
improvement in infant and child mortality would, other things being equal,&#13;
reduce the ninber of births needed to achieve the security target. Unless&#13;
this number exceeded the level of natural fertility, one would expect an&#13;
improvement in mortality to have a nlegative effect on fertility.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
According to the LSF model, change in the time and commodity costs of&#13;
child rearing or in the value of child labor can be expected to exert a&#13;
negative influence an fertility only if fertility exceeds the level&#13;
associated with the security target. If fertility is less than or equal to&#13;
the target level, such change should have no impact on demand for children or&#13;
fertility. Suppose, for example, that the absolute value of children&#13;
(considering anly costs and returns up to age 15 or 20) is negative. One can&#13;
imagine several sources of change that would make children even more costly:&#13;
for example, an increase in female wages or labor force participation that&#13;
raises the time costs of children, or technological change that erodes the&#13;
market for child labor, thus reducing the potential contributions of&#13;
children. These changes, however, could quite plausibly leave the target&#13;
unaffected, and thus have no effect on fertility: the cost of insurance will&#13;
have risen; yet the need for insurance will remain. According to the Chicago&#13;
School microeconomic theory of fertility, on the other hand, an increase in&#13;
the absolute or relative cost of children should, ceteris paribus, decrease&#13;
the demand for children and result in an appropriate adjustment in fertility.&#13;
The operation of a security constraint, such as described by the LSF model,&#13;
may help to explain the disappointing results of empirical tests of&#13;
microeconomic models in developing countries, and the failure to discover,&#13;
for example, a consistent and significant relationship between women's work&#13;
activity and fertility.8&#13;
Reductions in the target itself could be produced by elimination or&#13;
moderation of sources of risk, or the replacement of children by other&#13;
sources of insurance, or some combination of these. Administrative and&#13;
political development, for example, may eliminate the need for the political&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
self-insurance that a large family provides. Growth in income and savings&#13;
cpportunities may reduce dependence on children for security. However, even&#13;
with income growth, as long as insurance and financial markets remain badly&#13;
incomplete, children will not be easily displaced as primary sources of&#13;
security.&#13;
In settings characterized by multiple sources of serious risk for which&#13;
children represent the best or only means of insurance, the target for&#13;
surviving children may be particularly resistant to change. If little&#13;
separates thea targets implied by different sources of risk, then all sources&#13;
must be moderated in order to induce a fertility response.&#13;
The LSF model suggests a different pattern of fertility transition from&#13;
that experien-ced in the West and depicted by conventional demographic&#13;
transition theory. The latter describes a smooth and irreversible transition&#13;
from high to low fertility. By contrast, the LSF model suggests a two-stage&#13;
transition. In the first stage, fertility adjusts to a new mortality regime.&#13;
The very sharp and nearly global improvements in mortality that followed&#13;
World War II in many cases decreased the level of fertility necessary for&#13;
achieving security goals. (The targets themselves need not have been&#13;
altered.) The extent of fertility decline in the first stage will vary from&#13;
society to society depending on the extent of mortality decline and the level&#13;
of the security target.   The second stage of fertility transition is&#13;
triggered by change that reduces the target itself: that is, improvement in&#13;
the environmnt of risk and/or development of alternative sources of&#13;
insurance. In exceptional cases, postwar economic development will have been&#13;
so rapid that the two stages merge together and produce an unbroken&#13;
transition from high to low fertility (as in Singapore, for example). More&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9-&#13;
typically, however, fertility will remain at an intermediate level between&#13;
the first and second stages, possibly for a considerable period.&#13;
There is evidence, partial and incomplete because of data shortages and&#13;
the recency of declines, that after an initial period of quite rapid decline,&#13;
fertility has, indeed, leveled off considerably above replacement rates in&#13;
many developing countries. Among those countries with relatively good data,&#13;
Sri Lanka (total fertility rate of 3.8), Tanisia (5.3), Costa Rica (3.8),&#13;
Fiji (3.4), and Malaysia (4.0) are examples.9 Moreover, the fertility levels&#13;
at which these plateaus occur vary from country to country. I suggest that&#13;
an explanation for these developments -- both the plateau phenomenon and&#13;
variation in level of plateau - may lie in the safety-first model sketched&#13;
above.&#13;
III. Women's Status and Fertility&#13;
1. Economic dependence: Son preference and patriarchal risk. Women's&#13;
status is relevant to the safety-first model in two important ways. The&#13;
first relates to the definition of security targets: whether or not the sex&#13;
of offspring is relevant to framing such targets. In societies in which&#13;
women are relatively independent economically, in which they share relative&#13;
equality with men with respect to economic opportunity and control of&#13;
property, parents will be more indifferent about the sex of offspring vis a&#13;
vis insurance and security. In societies in which women are more dependent&#13;
on men, where they are excluded from mainstream economic activities, parents&#13;
will place a greater premium on sons. Other things equal, the fertility&#13;
level implied by a necessity for sons will be considerably higher than the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
level implied by a security target that can be satisfied by children of&#13;
either sex. 'The second way in which women's status enters the model is as a&#13;
distinct source of risk for which additional insurance may be needed.&#13;
Economic dependence on men can entail special risks for women -- risks that&#13;
are independent of other sources, such as natural disasters or the process of&#13;
aging to whic,h both men and women are exposed. Widowhood, divorce,&#13;
separation, or incapacitating illness of the husband represent threatening&#13;
events in situations in which Women are excluded from mainstream sources of&#13;
income and aria thus prevented from providing for themselves through their own&#13;
labor and entierprise. An important source of insurance against the risk of&#13;
losing the economic support of a husband is sons.  The greater the economic&#13;
dependence of women on men, the greater the salience of this source of risk.&#13;
Both son preference and "patriarchal risk" stem from the same cause: the&#13;
relative econoDmic dependence of Women. They do not, however, have the same&#13;
consequences Eor fertility. Of the two, son preference may be viewed as the&#13;
more significant, because it affects target-setting irrespective of source of&#13;
risk. If there is a necessity to have sons in order to achieve security&#13;
goals, rather than children of either sex, this requirement will hold for old&#13;
age security and other contingencies, as much as for insurance against&#13;
patriarchal risk. With respect to the risks which dependent Women face, as&#13;
noted in the previous section, it could well be that the fertility level&#13;
consistent with the target set for old-age security is sufficiently high to&#13;
satisfy the demand for insurance created by such risks. Rather than implying&#13;
a higher leveL of fertility, therefore, the presence of patriarchal risk may&#13;
only serve to reinforce reproductive goals and make them more resistant to&#13;
change.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-11-&#13;
If one takes a broad view, and considers in retrospect the whole of the&#13;
developing world at the conclusion of World War II, the status of women --&#13;
understood to mean the degree of economic dependence of women on men -- was&#13;
probably the single most important predictor (other than mortality decline)&#13;
of subsequent experience in fertility trends. This is because it quite&#13;
likely was (and is) the single most important determinant of level of&#13;
security target. As we shall see below, those societies whose fertility has&#13;
declined the most are, in general, societies in which women had the greatest&#13;
economic independence and where, therefore, the "intrinsic" security target&#13;
was the lowest at the onset of mortality decline. Post-war mortality decline&#13;
served, I would argue, to "reveal" these targets, and permit fertility to&#13;
adjust accordingly. The extent of mortality decline has not, of course, been&#13;
uniform throughout developing regions.  Most notably, mortality decline has&#13;
been least extensive in sub-Saharan Africa. Relatively high mortality,&#13;
extraordinary levels of infertility ° (which, in the LSF model would have the&#13;
same effect as mortality), and aspects of African family structure take&#13;
precedence in this region, and exempt it from the generalization regarding&#13;
the status of women.&#13;
2. Example: Bangladesh and South India. A comparative analysis of a&#13;
village in Bangladesh and several villages in Maharashtra and Andhra Pradesh&#13;
States of India will serve to illustrate the significance of women's&#13;
dependence on men.11  Both regions are agricultural and comparably poor.&#13;
There is no difference in the dependence of the elderly on their children for&#13;
support in the two areas. The opportunities for the productive employment of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-12-&#13;
children do seem to be greater in the Bangladeshi village, but even there the&#13;
productivity of children does not appear sufficient to warrant unlimited&#13;
fertility. Yet, while there is practically no birth control in the&#13;
Bangladesh setting, many couples in the Indian villages have acted to limit&#13;
their fertility. There is, moreover, evidence of the beginnings of a&#13;
fertility decline in both Maharashtra and Andhra Pradesh.&#13;
A major difference in the environment of risk in the two settings&#13;
centers on women. The economic freedom and opportunities of women in rural&#13;
Bangladesh are much more severely restricted than those of women in the three&#13;
Indian villages. There is a pronounced division of labor by sex in both&#13;
areas; however, the division that has evolved in rural Bangladesh&#13;
effectively excludes women from all the most important sources of wage&#13;
employment and from activities that would permit them to cultivate or&#13;
supervise the cultivation of their own land. Women are not permitted to seek&#13;
employment in any of the field cperations for the main crops of paddy and&#13;
jute, which provide the bulk of wage employment opportunities in rural&#13;
Bangladesh.&#13;
The situation of women in the three Indian villages is quite different.&#13;
In contrast to rural Bangladesh, women in the Indian villages are not&#13;
excluded from participating in field operations and there is a high demand&#13;
and active wage labor market for tasks that women specialize in. Women on&#13;
their own in the Indian villages can provide for themselves, either by&#13;
selling their labor or cultivating their own land. It may not be easy, and&#13;
the resulting standard of living may be lower than if the woman had a man as&#13;
her partner, but it is possible.&#13;
What is the fate of women in these two settings who have lost their&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-13-&#13;
husbands and have no other mature males on whom they can depend? In a sample&#13;
of 114 households from the Bangladesh village, of 14 women widowed in&#13;
unfavorable circumstances, ten were left with some land at the time of their&#13;
husbands' death and four were landless. Of the ten who had land at one time,&#13;
all subsequently sold or otherwise lost at least some of their land, and four&#13;
lost all of it. Of the four who were initially landless, one became a beggar&#13;
and all are destitute. In a sample of 119 households in the three Indian&#13;
villages, of 12 women widowed under similar circumstances, three were&#13;
landless at the time of their husbands' death and nine were left with some&#13;
land. In contrast to the widows in Bangladesh, of these nine, only one&#13;
subsequently lost or sold land, and the three landless widows manage to&#13;
subsist on their own, one through agricultural wages and two through&#13;
small-scale trading.&#13;
The ability of women in the Indian villages to provide for their own&#13;
subsistence is not the only reason why these widows were able to hold on to&#13;
their land and maintain a relatively stable life after their husbands died,&#13;
but it is undoubtedly an important factor. While the presence of mature sons&#13;
would have made life more comfortable, their absence did not precipitate the&#13;
sharp declines in welfare experienced by widows in the Bangladesh village.&#13;
In the Bangladesh setting, there is a greater incentive for women to produce&#13;
sons, because they have much more to lose if they do not. Similarly, with&#13;
respect to other security needs, including those in old age, one can&#13;
conjecture that conditions in Bangladesh lead to a greater premium for sons&#13;
than is the case in south India.&#13;
A recent paper by Dyson and Mbore permits an extension of this analysis&#13;
to provide a more comprehensive view of regional patterns of women's status&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-14-&#13;
in relation to fertility in South Asia12. They identify and contrast "north"&#13;
and "south" Indian patterns of kinship and female status. In their scheme,&#13;
the situation of women in Bangladesh corresponds roughly to the north Indian&#13;
pattern, and that of women in Maharashtra and Andhra Pradesh to the south.&#13;
The three major principles of north Indian kinship are village and kin&#13;
exogamy, relatively close ties between patrilineally related males, and&#13;
ccntrol of property by males. By contrast, in the south, endogamy is more&#13;
ccmmon, males' ties with affines (those related through marriage) are&#13;
strcnger, and1 women may inherit and transfer property rights. In the north&#13;
there is greater control of female sexuality both through the kinship rules&#13;
mentioned above and through the seclusion of women and various other&#13;
restrictions on their freedom of movement and interactions with others.&#13;
There are associated north-south differences in the economic activity of&#13;
women, femalie age at marriage, family planning prevalance, and fertility, as&#13;
shown in Table 1.&#13;
Dyson aind Moore identify "female autonomy" as the key variable&#13;
distinguishiing the north from the south. Female autonomy is defined as "the&#13;
capacity [of women] to manipulate [their] environment. Autonomy indicates&#13;
the ability - technical, social, and psychological -- to obtain information&#13;
and to use it as the basis for making decisions...(p. 45)". In linking&#13;
female autonomy to fertility behavior Dyson and Moore emphasize the scope&#13;
that autonouq offers for innovative action and independent decisions. This&#13;
emphasis, which the authors share with a number of other interpretations of&#13;
the relationship between women's status and fertility, is, I believe,&#13;
misplaced. The suggestion is that fertility is higher in the north than the&#13;
south because northern women do not have the freedom and independence to act&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-   e acv  to-,  wqr %C  ce  - hr . m   r4   C4&#13;
W 4-      W           - &#13;
B~~~~~~~~- 0, rV     at    C-       1&#13;
-a*.r~a' fllCr  -F&#13;
II                         U~~~~ &#13;
co&#13;
#   % S  onoF&gt;t  FoF22:    b~~~~~~~~~~4 tF r&#13;
IL                   f-0.r.   f44C-&#13;
U,     *~ I.                      f.'J C!'N c'!-&#13;
~ .s  | ]  .i. e t. t X N  ° wb 1 -  0 2 - !-4&#13;
t~     U-                             - *tF  u  N&#13;
| i  E t E  N = pe N =  ° -; = c ~ c  &gt; ,&gt; t &gt;  o&#13;
@ ~     ~~~          -Ov   0- eN'4 - ;&lt;ggX3i  ;a56&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-16-&#13;
on their owrL behalf. This presumes that fertility levels in the north&#13;
reflect male fertility preferences and that male and female preferences&#13;
diverge. Th,e difficulty with this construction is that it ignores one&#13;
important aspect of family structure: despite gender inequality, the conjugal&#13;
unit is also a corporate unit in this region and, therefore, men and women in&#13;
the same family share many common interests and concerns. Given a corporate&#13;
structure, the kind of divergence in reproductive goals implied by Dyson and&#13;
Moore is unlikely to occur. A more plausible link between gender inequality&#13;
or female autonomy and fertility operates through security needs and the&#13;
premium on sons that derives from women's position of economic dependence.&#13;
Female age at marriage, differences in which clearly underly much of the&#13;
difference in total fertility between the north and the south, must be&#13;
treated separately in my view. Decisions about age at marriage and choice of&#13;
partner remain the province of the elder generation in both the north and the&#13;
south.   Con,trol over marriage decisions is thus not a part of the autoncmy&#13;
of women in the south. Early female age at marriage, evident in north India,&#13;
is a principal means by which the control of women is effected, and as such&#13;
should be thought of as one part of an integral system of patriarchal control&#13;
(see the case of Bangladesh described below). In the south, where there has&#13;
historically been less concern over control of women's sexuality, and where&#13;
kinship structure and social organization are such as to permit women greater&#13;
economic independence and freedom, there is greater inherent flexibility in&#13;
age at marriage. Because the control of women is not at stake (to the same&#13;
degree as irL the north), female age at marriage is relatively free to respond&#13;
to new educational and economic opportunities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-17-&#13;
3. Family Structure: Boundaries of the corporate group. As suggested in&#13;
the previous section, an appreciation of the corporate nature of the family&#13;
is essential in interpreting the relationship between women's status and&#13;
fertility. Too often analyses that focus on women's status abstract from the&#13;
corporate context of the family, and therefore overlook the fact that&#13;
regardless of tangible indications of inequality between men and women,&#13;
women's welfare and interests are closely aligned with the corporate&#13;
interests of the family as a whole.13 This perspective underlies my&#13;
difference with Dyson and Moore's interpretation of the relationship between&#13;
women's autonomy and fertility in India and also reservations that I have&#13;
concerning Caldwell's analysis of the "situational advantage" of patriarchs&#13;
and its significance for fertility in developing countries.14&#13;
It is equally important, however, to note that the boundary of the&#13;
corporate family group is not the same in all developing societies. In Asia&#13;
this boundary typically encompasses the nuclear family unit -- husband, wife&#13;
and children. Although the system of family formation that characterizes&#13;
this region is aptly labeled "joint", 15 and while most nuclear family units&#13;
experience periods of extension in their developmental cycles, the majority&#13;
of households at any given time will nevertheless be nuclear in structure.&#13;
The relatively high degree of corporateness that is typical of the conjugal&#13;
unit in Asia is, however, characteristic of neither sub-Saharan Africa nor of&#13;
Caribbean (and some Latin American) societies.&#13;
In the "Caribbean" family system the conjugal bond is relatively weak:&#13;
formal marriage is the exception rather than the norm, a substantial part of&#13;
reproduction occurs outside of marriage or stable unions, women often&#13;
experience a series of unions with different men over the course of their&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-18-&#13;
reproductive lives, and the biological father often bears little or no&#13;
financial responsibility for his children.16 In much of sub-Saharan Africa,&#13;
the conjugal bond also tends to be weak. There, however, the locus of&#13;
reproductive decisions, and the appropriate referent when considering the&#13;
costs and benefits of children, is the larger kin group rather than one or&#13;
another parent, as in the case of the Caribbean family system, or the&#13;
conjugal unit, as in Asian family systems.17&#13;
In both sub-Saharan Africa and the Caribbean, women have a relatively&#13;
high degree of economic autonomy. Indeed, the kind of economic dependence&#13;
that is characteristic of women in Bangladesh is, from a functional&#13;
standpoint, inconsistent with a system in which a weak conjugal bond is the&#13;
norm. However, while these regions would tend to be at the lower end of an&#13;
international scale of female dependence and therefore relatively free of the&#13;
fertility incentives associated with a high degree of dependence, aspects of&#13;
family structure in the two regions introduce other pronatalist forces. In&#13;
the case of the Caribbean, the fact that a father may share in the benefits&#13;
of reproduction while avoiding the costs creates the possibility of a "free&#13;
rider" situation.18 In sub-Saharan Africa, although there are some&#13;
similarities to the Caribbean with respect to conjugal relations, it is the&#13;
greater size of the corporate group that is of most significance as a&#13;
pronatalist force. The cases of Jamaica and Ghana illustrate bow family&#13;
structure in the two regions may operate to induce high fertility.&#13;
* Jamaica. Female labor force participation, female literacy, and&#13;
female educational attainment in Jamaica are among the highest in the&#13;
developing world. Fertility has been relatively slow to decline, however,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-19-&#13;
and current estimates indicate a TFR of approximately 4 births per woman. In&#13;
international perspective, Jamaica's sluggish fertility transition is a&#13;
puzzle because it seems out of line not only with the indicators of "female&#13;
status" mentioned above, but also with levels of per capita income,&#13;
urbanization (50% of the population lives in urban areas), health and&#13;
mortality. Some understanding of the relatively high fertility of Jamaican&#13;
women can be obtained by considering the problem from the perspective&#13;
outlined above. Jamaica conforms to the "Caribbean" family system: most&#13;
Jamaican women spend a majority of their reproductive lives in visiting and&#13;
consensual unions with men.19 In a visiting union a man will typically not&#13;
bear responsibility for the costs of rearing children that he has fathered;&#13;
these costs are borne by the woinan. A man may participate in more than one&#13;
visiting union simultaneously; and a woman will often experience a series of&#13;
visiting unions during her reproductive life. Typically there will be a&#13;
shift toward a more stable union in the later phase of the reproductive span:&#13;
a visiting union is transformed into a consensual union or marriage.&#13;
The Caribbean system of reproductive organization generates "free rider"&#13;
problems and externalities that are far in excess of the more typical pattern&#13;
of domestic organization associated with universal and early marriage and&#13;
corporate households built around nuclear families. Men are motivated to&#13;
father children in visiting unions in order to demonstrate virility;&#13;
something on which a high social value is placed. Their behavior is,&#13;
however, uninhibited by child cost constraints. Women wish to avoid the&#13;
stigma of infertility and are thus likewise motivated to reproduce at an&#13;
early stage. Bearing a man's children is, moreover, an important step toward&#13;
establishing a more stable union. Marriage is something that women have&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-20-&#13;
vested interest in, because, despite high rates of labor force participation&#13;
by internatiornal standards, women face a segmented labor market and are&#13;
shunted into lower paying, less secure forms of employment in the Jamaican&#13;
economy. Marriage, therefore, represents the prospect of greater financial&#13;
security for a woman and her children through access to a man's superior&#13;
employment opportunities and earnings. In this setting women are very likely&#13;
motivated to reproduce at levels in excess of those dictated by child costs&#13;
alcne. These incentives are a product of women's subordinate position in the&#13;
society and economy, the uncertainty that they face with respect to the&#13;
stability of unions and their economic security, and the male-biased ideology&#13;
that sustains this family system and the attendant inequitable distribution&#13;
of child costs within unions.&#13;
* The Kwiahu of Southern Ghana.20 The Kwahu are an Akan sub-group who&#13;
live in southern Ghana. Ghana as a whole is notable both for its high&#13;
fertility and the high rates of female economic participation. Kwahu is a&#13;
matrilineal society whose people are engaged primarily in farming and&#13;
tradirg. Marriage among the Kwahu is not a highly valued institution.&#13;
Conjugal rights and duties are amibiguous:&#13;
"There are no clear rules as to where the husband, the wife and the&#13;
children should stay, how much husband and wife should contribute toward&#13;
the upkeep of the family, where exactly the father's authority over the&#13;
children lies and where that of the mother and mother's brother, with&#13;
whom the children are to stay after divorce or after the death of one of&#13;
the parents, etc." (pp. 22-23)&#13;
There are also few positive or negative sanctions that enforce adherence&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-21-&#13;
to marriage norms:&#13;
"Sexual satisfaction can be obtained outside marriage virtually without&#13;
public disapproval. There is no such thing as illegitimacy. Children&#13;
belong by definition to their mother's lineage...&#13;
"Summarising, one could say that the institution of marriage is fragile&#13;
and viewed with lukewarm feelings.  Primordial attachment and dependence&#13;
lies in most cases with the matrilineage and not with the conjugal&#13;
partner. A norm which is not ambiguous is that in conflicts people must&#13;
side with their matrilineage, if need be against their partner in&#13;
marriage."(p. 23)&#13;
The high degree of marital instability and the marginality of husbands&#13;
in the Kwahu system produce a free rider problem similar to that found in the&#13;
Caribbean:&#13;
"After divorce men often do not support their children at all, or stop&#13;
doing so after some time has passed. Meanwhile a man who marries a&#13;
divorcee will not expect to contribute to the maintenance ... of any of&#13;
his wife's children by a previous marriage. Thus men, since they can&#13;
more easily shed past parental responsibilities, may be less constrained&#13;
to limit the number of births they beget..."(p. 26).&#13;
However, what distinguishes the Kwahu, and sub-Saharan Africa more&#13;
generally, is the dominance of the lineage in matters of reproduction:&#13;
"For a man to decide to have children is somewhat unreal. Strictly&#13;
speaking, the child which he may decide to have will not be 'his' child&#13;
but the child of his wife's lineage...&#13;
"The influence of the matrilineage ... makes individual or conjugal decision&#13;
making difficult and to some extent superfluous. The ties of marriage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-22-&#13;
are less important than those of descent. Lineage membership overrides&#13;
all other social ties and permeates every aspect of daily life. More&#13;
than anything else, reproduction is a matter of concerm for the lineage.&#13;
According to the matrilineal rule, women bear children to their own&#13;
lineage and not to their husbands'. As men cannot themselves continue&#13;
the descent of the lineage, they have to wait and see what the female&#13;
members of their lineage bring forth. A woman who does not become&#13;
pregnant will be pressed by her lineage to leave her husband and try her&#13;
luck with another man" (pp. 27-28).&#13;
The lineage is not only the locus of reproductive decisions but also of&#13;
reckoning the costs of reproduction. Thus in the event of divorce, a woman&#13;
may receive dlirect financial assistance from her lineage. The practice of&#13;
child fostering is also an important means of spreading the cost of&#13;
reproduction within the lineage:&#13;
"The rearing of children by non-parental kin and others is a widespread&#13;
practice in West Africa in general and Ghana in particular ... It is a&#13;
practice which has a pervasive impact on the distribution of the costs&#13;
and benefits of children, which are often spread between kin group&#13;
members, with different individuals providing economic assistance,&#13;
childcare or training at different points in the growing child's career,&#13;
and with a variety of people benefiting from the child's help in&#13;
domestic tasks, childcare, agriculture and trade" (p. 29)&#13;
The Kwalhu, and the Akan more generally, are unusual in their matrilineal&#13;
kinship organization. The majority of societies in sub-Saharan Africa are&#13;
characterizei by patrilineal kinship systems. Despite the differences that&#13;
distinguish patrilineal from matrilineal systems (the importance of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-23-&#13;
brideprice, for example), there are key similarities. Notably, in both&#13;
systems conjugal ties tend to be subservient to lineage allegiance and, as&#13;
evidenced by the ubiquitous practice of child fostering, the locus of&#13;
reproductive decisions and benefit/cost considerations is the larger kin&#13;
group rather than the nuclear family. A number of studies in Ghana and&#13;
elsewhere in sub-Saharan Africa suggest that in some communities --&#13;
particularly among urban educated elites -- the strength of corporate lineage&#13;
organization has diminished in the course of recent social and economic&#13;
change. Nevertheless for the bulk of African populations corporate lineage&#13;
groups would appear to remain a potent fact of social life.&#13;
Th summarize, one can broadly distinguish three basic family types among&#13;
developing countries according to the boundary of the corporate group:&#13;
"Caribbean", where the boundary would normally encompass a mother and her&#13;
children, but exclude the father(s); "Asian", where the boundary is&#13;
coterminous with the nuclear family; and "African", where the boundary&#13;
encompasses a larger kin group. The Caribbean and African versions share&#13;
weak conjugal ties, while the conjugal bond is relatively strong in the Asian&#13;
family. In both Caribbean and African systems, women are very active&#13;
economically, in ways that permit considerable independence from men, while&#13;
the Asian system accomodates a broad range of female economic activity levels&#13;
and degrees of female dependence on men.&#13;
The relationship between family structure and women's economic&#13;
dependence is shown schematically in Figure 1. The shaded cone in the lower&#13;
left of the figure (OCD) represents the zone of highest patriarchal risk.&#13;
Representative societies here, all of the "Asian" family type, would include&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-24-&#13;
j&#13;
I~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~I-&#13;
a-I&#13;
U.&#13;
_                       a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-25-&#13;
Bangladesh, north India, Pakistan, and the Mislim countries of north Africa&#13;
and west Asia. Fertility tends to be high in this zone because of the&#13;
economic dependence of women on men and the associated patriarchal risks and&#13;
focus on sons for security. The shaded cone in the upper right of Figure 1&#13;
(EAF) is the zone of weak conjugal ties, occupied by Caribbean and African&#13;
societies. Fertility may be resistant to change in this zone, despite the&#13;
relative economic independence of women, due to free riders in the Caribbean&#13;
and the predominance of lineage ties in Africa. The area closest to point B&#13;
in Figure 1 is, ceteris paribus, most favorable for fertility decline. Most&#13;
of south India and southeast Asia would be located in the non-shaded area,&#13;
with countries such as Thailand and Sri Lanka located closest to point B.&#13;
4. A structural perspective on women's economic status. It is important to&#13;
locate the analysis of women's status and fertility at the appropriate level&#13;
of aggregation. It makes little sense to conduct household- or&#13;
individual-level analyses of a variable that is properly measured at a higher&#13;
level of aggregation. One can think of many individual-level measures of&#13;
women's economic dependence on men; however, the factors that condition an&#13;
individual's experience -- the sexual division of labor, labor market&#13;
segmentation, inheritance rules, religious norms of behavior, rules of&#13;
marriage and family formation -- are clearly located in a society's&#13;
institutional structure. While one may observe substantial variation in the&#13;
individual experience of women in a particular society, the distribution of&#13;
such experience will be constrained by institutionally determined bounds. In&#13;
important respects, therefore, women's status -- the extent to which they are&#13;
economically dependent on men -- should be viewed as a structural phenomencn.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-26-&#13;
It is also important to keep in mind that in situations where women are&#13;
highly dependent on men one is dealing with structured inequality: systems&#13;
of stratification that give advantage to men over women. Corporate&#13;
households notwithstanding, men benefit from their dominant positions in such&#13;
systems and, just as with elites more generally, they have a vested interest&#13;
in protecting their rank and the system that elevates them to positions of&#13;
power and control. These interests represent a potentially powerful source&#13;
of resistance to change, over and above the "dead hand of tradition."&#13;
Patriarchal structure, by which I mean the sum of institutional&#13;
mechanisms that serve to limit women's economic autonomy relative to men's,&#13;
may thus possess considerable inertia. When considering the prospects for&#13;
change in any one element of patriarchal structure -- female age at marriage,&#13;
for example -- one must reckon with the weight of the entire structure. The&#13;
case of Bangladesh, sketched below, serves as an illustration.21&#13;
In rural Bangladesh male dominance is grounded in control of material&#13;
resources and supported by interlocking and reinforcing elements of the&#13;
kinship, political, religious, and economic systems. Powerful norms of&#13;
seclusion extend to labor markets, severely limiting women's opportunities&#13;
for independent income generation. Potential agents of change and sources of&#13;
resistance to the current system are undermined by the interaction of age,&#13;
sex and class hierarchies.&#13;
* Kinship. The custom of patrilocal marriage removes a newly married&#13;
woman from her family of birth and places her in her husband's locality.&#13;
Preference for lineage and village exogamy attenuates a woman's ties with her&#13;
family of birth and reduces the possibility that her family will intervene on&#13;
her behalf after marriage. Exogamy and physical separation also make it less&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-27-&#13;
likely that a woman will claim her share of inheritance and more likely that&#13;
her brothers will seize control of her share of inherited land regardless of&#13;
her wishes. Arranged marriage and differences in age at marriage by sex of&#13;
almost ten years place a woman in a subordinate position relative to her&#13;
husband at the outset of marriage. Furthermore, evidence suggests that a&#13;
woman does not receive a substantial dowry upon marriage: at the time of&#13;
marriage, a woman is endowed with neither money nor property that is hers&#13;
alone and that represents independent security.&#13;
* Political System. Men monopolize political power. Elected&#13;
officials, administrators, and police are all men. Village councils&#13;
(salish), which adjudicate most local disputes, are composed exclusively of&#13;
men. Power brokers - villagers who have ties and influence with officialdom&#13;
outside - are men. Solidarity groups (mallot), which gather on the occasion&#13;
of members' marriages and deaths and at various religious festivals, are&#13;
ccntrolled and led by men. In part because of the male domination of&#13;
political institutions and in part because formal judicial institutions and&#13;
administration are weak, particularly in rural areas, legal protection of&#13;
women (under either civil or Islamic laws) is nominal. If a female litigant&#13;
in a land dispute, for example, is not closely identified with and supported&#13;
by a man, she is likely to lose regardless of the merits of her case.&#13;
* Religion. Both as an ideology and as the normative force that&#13;
channels behavior and expectations, Islam represents a strong apology for&#13;
patriarchy. Islam is explicit about the sexual division of labor and&#13;
responsibility and, in effect, sanctifies male dominance. According to&#13;
Islam, man is the earner and woman is the server of man. Islam "clearly&#13;
states that men and women have their own spheres of activity - a scheme of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-28-&#13;
functional division in accord with their respective natural dispositions and&#13;
inherent physical and physiological qualities and characteristics."22 Two&#13;
further aspects of Islam as interpreted in Bangladesh have direct effects as&#13;
instruments of patriarchal control: the laws of inheritance and the&#13;
manifestations of purdah - the seclusion of women.&#13;
Muslim inheritance laws allow a daughter one-half the share received by&#13;
a son. In practice, women frequently receive less than their rightful share&#13;
under the law. Moreover, if a woman inherits land, her husband cultivates it&#13;
(when accessible) as if it were his own. A number of observers have also&#13;
noted a tenderncy for women to relinquish their share of inheritance to their&#13;
brother(s) as a way of gaining favor and generating good will.23&#13;
Purdah is a "system of secluding women and enforcing high standards of&#13;
female modesty."24 Its manifestations in Bangladesh include severe&#13;
restrictions on women's movements outside their immediate homestead (bari -&#13;
which usually consists of an open compound surrounded and shielded by huts,&#13;
foliage, and fencing) and standards of dress that hide their face and form.&#13;
Women who move out of the homestead into the public "male space" are&#13;
considered both provocative and offensive.&#13;
* The DiLvision of Labor.  The predicament of women who do not have men&#13;
on whom they can depend and who must generate income on their own is that the&#13;
same elements of patriarchal structure that force them into relative&#13;
seclusion in the household compound also deny them access to most forms of&#13;
market work. In Bangladesh, a division of labor among household members has&#13;
evolved whereby women specialize in work inside or near the homestead (food&#13;
processing ansi preparation, household maintenance, cultivation of vines and&#13;
other crops located in or near the homestead, and animal husbandry) and men&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-29-&#13;
specialize in work outside the home (rice and jute cultivation, trading, and&#13;
other forms of market work). This division itself engenders a powerful&#13;
element of partriarchal control over women, enforcing women's dependence on&#13;
men by denying them direct access to income-earning opportunities. The&#13;
sexual division of labor applies in large part to all women, regardless of&#13;
economic status or household structure. As a consequence, women are totally&#13;
excluded from most agricultural wage employment, and the costs, in terms of&#13;
abuse and loss of status, of engaging in other types of work that require&#13;
movement outside the homestead (e.g. petty trading) are very high indeed.&#13;
*  Interlocking Hierarchies.  The final element of patriarchal control&#13;
in the Bangladesh setting derives from the interaction of age, sex, and class&#13;
hierarchies. Among women, solidarity and potential resistence are&#13;
undermined by an age hierarchy that allies older women with patriarchal&#13;
interests and by class differences between women. The young bride enters her&#13;
husband's household to find herself under the control and supervision of her&#13;
mother-in-law. In general, older women dominate younger women --&#13;
mothers-in-law dominate daughters-in-law, elder brothers' wives dominate&#13;
younger brothers' wives, and so on. This age stratification among women&#13;
allies older women with partriarchal interests (because both share domination&#13;
and exploitation of younger women) and also gives younger women something to&#13;
look forward to with advancing age. Similarly among poor men, for whom the&#13;
material benefits of patriarchy are less than for the relatively rich, and&#13;
whose well-being might improve if their wives could find more and better&#13;
employment, potential resistance is blunted by their position of dependence&#13;
in the class hierarchy.&#13;
Bangladesh unquestionably occupies an extreme position among developing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-30-&#13;
countries with respect to strength of patriarchal structure. (This is not to&#13;
say that Bangladesh is an isolated case: in broad outline Pakistan, much of&#13;
North India, West Asia, and North Africa are similar in patriarchal&#13;
structure). Even a casual survey of other societies reveals a range of&#13;
institutiona:L arrangements that are less restrictive of women and that permit&#13;
a greater degree of economic freedom and independence than is the case for&#13;
Bangladesh. For our purposes, the question of why different institutional&#13;
arrangements have evolved in different regions of the developing world is not&#13;
so important. What is important is to note that particular patriarchal&#13;
structures have deep historical roots, and that the pattern of variation in&#13;
patriarchal structure which can be observed today in the developing world is&#13;
essentially the same as the pattern that existed three and four decades ago,&#13;
when mortality began its precipitous decline.&#13;
IV. Framework for Empirical Analysis&#13;
1. Direct effects of patriarchal structure. The direct causal&#13;
relationships linking patriarchal structure, women's status and fertility are&#13;
summarized i,n Figure 2. Elements of patriarchal control combine to produce a&#13;
particular degree of female economic dependence on men. The economic&#13;
dependence of women, then, affects security target setting in two ways.&#13;
First, and mDst important, for a given level of risk (and availability of&#13;
alternative sources of insurance) the dependence of women determines the&#13;
relevance of sex of children in figuring security needs. The more dependent&#13;
women are, the greater the need for sons rather than children of either sex.&#13;
Secondly, economic dependence may increase the demand for children as&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
\1 0;10&#13;
I~i i&#13;
I    ~- -&#13;
I~~~ &#13;
N  .! &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-32-&#13;
security assets over and above what it would otherwise be, because it&#13;
introduces an additional source of risk. The security target -- expressed in&#13;
terms of desired number of surviving sons or children -- in turn, has&#13;
implications for the level of fertility. The level of fertility consistent&#13;
with a particular security target depends on levels of mortality and natural&#13;
fertility. Other things equal, the greater the chances of child survival,&#13;
the lower the fertility necessary for achieving security goals. However, as&#13;
noted in section II, if the security target is high, the situation may be one&#13;
of excess demand, such that improvements in mortality simply facilitate the&#13;
achievement of security goals which before were out of reach.25&#13;
As suggested in the case of Jamaica, where there are weak conjugal ties&#13;
and the nuclear family unit lacks cohesiveness, complications may arise. In&#13;
this situation, the free rider problem may serve to "short-circuit" the&#13;
connection drawn between the security target and fertility in Figure 2. In&#13;
international perspective, and judging from the incidence of "non-legal"&#13;
unions shown in Table 2, the free rider problem appears to be a factor in&#13;
many Latin American societies, or for a considerable proportion of their&#13;
populations. As indicated by the substantial fertility declines registered&#13;
in a number of these countries, however, the free rider problem is not the&#13;
same order of constraint as is represented by the oombined effects of extreme&#13;
economic dependence.26&#13;
Among the "other complications" referred to in Figure 2 are infertility,&#13;
child fostering, and the probability of child default. The implications of&#13;
child default for fertility were discussed in the context of the&#13;
Lexicographic Safety First Model in Section II. Little more can be added&#13;
here except to raise the question of whether systematic differences in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-33-&#13;
Thb  2 Pam       of w  'm   reroioucde yon  x    t  be&#13;
sped In v     mutitd ts' by mu.ky&#13;
Totalt   Sngle                  Married                  Divoced   Wuiowed&#13;
of&#13;
Total      First LAter  Legal Nonlegal  seprat&#13;
Cary                       (   tan      union union  unioM  union&#13;
d maried&#13;
Africa&#13;
Kenya         100     14        77        71    7      ...    ...         4         4&#13;
Lesotho       100     1S        72        70    2      ...    ...         4         8&#13;
ahngldeh      100      5        82        72    10     ...    ...         3        11&#13;
HJ1           100     20        74        64    10     ...    ...         3         3&#13;
Indokesia     100     16        72        48   24      ...    ...         6         6&#13;
Iordan        100     20        75        72    3      ...    ...         1         4&#13;
Repubic af&#13;
KOMa         100     24         69       66     3      ...   ...         2         5&#13;
Malaysda      100     24        69        60    9      ...    ...         3         4&#13;
Nepal         100      8        84         ...  ...    ...    ...         1         7&#13;
pakistan      100     14        80        75     4     ...    ...         2         4&#13;
Philippines   100     30        66        63    3      ...    ...         1         2&#13;
&amp;i lsIAka     100     30        63        60    3      ...    ...         2         5&#13;
Ibailkad      100     24        69        61     8     ...    ...         4         3&#13;
Latn America&#13;
Colnmbia      100     28        61        53     8     46     15          8         3&#13;
Costa Rica    100     29        62        57c   Se     51     11          7         2&#13;
Dinim&#13;
REqxblic     100      17        66       45    21      28     38        15         2&#13;
Guyana        100     17        73        52   21      54     19           -10-&#13;
amaisca       100     13        71        34    37     32     39           -15-&#13;
bMexico       100     22        69        64    6      60      9          6         3&#13;
Panmmas       100     21        67        50    16'    31     33         11         1&#13;
Ptru          100     26        66        58    7      52     14          6         2&#13;
'9buhedc aim eatma, based an ap suiefic mnital *mu dsibi ma da dm o th swvey.&#13;
"bepa     fa cmegmin may n add m 100 bm  ec roxiq.&#13;
'Aaun sha modW w    imapn w eap grV  to 19 ae a in fim Da:ia&#13;
Source: United Nations, Marital Status and Fertility: A Ccmarative&#13;
Analysis of World Fertility Survey Data for 21 Countries. New York,&#13;
Department of International, Economic and Social Affairs. ST/ESA/SER.&#13;
52, 1983.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-34-&#13;
probability of child default can be observed across developing societies (or&#13;
within particular societies), and how such probabilities have shifted in the&#13;
course of post-war modernization and social change in particular cultural&#13;
contexts. Unkfortunately there are few data to bring to bear in answer.&#13;
Both extraordinary levels of infertility and the institution of child&#13;
fostering are characteristic of sub-Saharan Africa. High levels of&#13;
infertility introduce additional uncertainty ccncerning the achievement of&#13;
reproductive goals to an environment where uncertainty surrounding child&#13;
survival is, in general, already great. The tenuous control over&#13;
reproduction implied by the combination of a high incidence of infertility&#13;
and high levels of mortality is antithetical to the notion of deliberate&#13;
fertility limitation.27 While the incidence of infertility is by no means&#13;
uniform throughout sub-Saharan Africa, it is high on average, and, at the&#13;
upper end of the range, produces rates of childlessness among older women in&#13;
excess of 30 percent.28 Child fostering, as practiced in much of sub-Saharan&#13;
Africa, provides a means of diffusing and redistributing the costs of&#13;
reproduction and also of acquiring child services when reproduction fails.29&#13;
The significance of this institution in relation to reproductive behavior,&#13;
however, lies less with narrow cost and benefit considerations than as a&#13;
reflection of a social organization in which the conjugal bond is weak, the&#13;
primary ccporate group is the lineage rather than the conjugal unit, and&#13;
where costs and benefits of reproduction must be evaluated from the&#13;
perspective cf this larger corporate group rather than that of parents.&#13;
2. Indirect effects of patriarchal structure. Patriarchal structure has&#13;
important indirect implications for fertility because it ccnditions the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-35-&#13;
potential for change in Women's educational attainment and work patterns, and&#13;
the flexibility of age at marriage in response to educational and work&#13;
opportunities. Patriarchal structure has further implications for fertility&#13;
through its effects on infant and child mortality.  The potentially powerful&#13;
effects of education on both fertility and child mortality have been&#13;
persuasively argued by Caldwell and others.30 The point that I wish to&#13;
emphasize is that patriarchal structure constrains the scope for rapid&#13;
improvement in female educational attainment. In societies characterized by&#13;
a highly restrictive and oppressive structure, such as that described for&#13;
Bangladesh, the scope for improvement is limited. Where patriarchal&#13;
structure is weak, and the control of women is less at issue, the scope for&#13;
improvement is much greater. Similarly, where patriarchal structure is weak,&#13;
there is greater inherent flexibility in female age at marriage and potential&#13;
for transformation of women's labor force participation and patterns of work.&#13;
The indirect links between patriarchal structure and fertility are&#13;
depicted in Figure 3. The principal indirect effect operates through female&#13;
age at marriage, which is viewed as responding to both educational and&#13;
employment opportunities, given a permissive patriarchal structure.31 In a&#13;
similar way, and under similar conditions, infant and child mortality may&#13;
respond to improvements in female education, and, in turn, induce a response&#13;
in fertility. Patriarchal structure thus operates as a covariate: the&#13;
structure itself is assumed to remain relatively unchanged, but different&#13;
structures either enable or inhibit other types of change. According to this&#13;
interpretation, evidence of marked improvements in female secondary school&#13;
enrollment, for example, is less an indication of transformation in&#13;
patriarchal structure, than a reflection of the existence of a "favorable"&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-36-&#13;
*4J~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~4&#13;
/r&#13;
'000.O,/,&#13;
is              /&#13;
04.-3W&#13;
0)&#13;
4-4  ~   h-L&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-37-&#13;
structure.32&#13;
The arrow ccnnecting educational and employment opportunities with&#13;
fertility in Figure 3 is broken in order to indicate ambiguity of effect and&#13;
subservience to the causal mechanism described in Figure 2. There is reason&#13;
to think that female employment and education may initially have a positive&#13;
impact on fertility, by curtailing breastfeeding and thus the period of&#13;
post-partum amenorrhea.33 On the other hand female employment and education&#13;
may introduce a conflict between child rearing and other activities,&#13;
including work, and by increasing the opportunity costs of children, exert a&#13;
negative influence on fertility. Education arguably has a number of other&#13;
effects that combine to produce a negative influence on fertility. Notably,&#13;
the acquisition of education may serve to reduce the psychic and real "costs&#13;
of fertility regulation."34 However, as argued in Section II, security&#13;
considerations are expected to take precedence, and the potential negative&#13;
effects of female employment and education should be evaluated in this&#13;
context. Thus, reduction in the costs of fertility regulation may well&#13;
facilitate the achievement of fertility levels that are consistent with&#13;
security targets, but it will not override the determinant influence of these&#13;
targets. Similarly, an increase in opportunity costs will make children a&#13;
more expensive form of insurance, but in the absence of change that affects&#13;
the need for insurance or the availability of alternative forms of insurance,&#13;
is unlikely to induce a fertility response.&#13;
These remarks are intended to apply in broad international perspective,&#13;
over what is a rather short period of time (the last few decades). The image&#13;
of monolithic and immutable structures is admittedly a crude abstraction.&#13;
However, the distortion of reality that it entails is much less grievous, in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-38-&#13;
my view, than the implicit denial that structure exists at all.&#13;
3. EmpiricaL application:   Age difference between spouses.  One encounters&#13;
formidable difficulties in trying to operationalize the concepts of&#13;
patriarchal structure and women's economic status and move toward empirical&#13;
tests of the relationships suggested in Figures 2 and 3. For example,&#13;
regarding the specific dimensions of women's economic dependence identified&#13;
in Figure 2, one is hard pressed to find any adequate indicators in&#13;
international statistical compendia. Of these dimensions, labor force data&#13;
are the most readily available; however, they are virtually&#13;
uninterpretable.35 Specifying the boundaries of particular patriarchal&#13;
structures, and thus the appropriate level of analysis, is also problematic.&#13;
The example of Bangladesh is misleading because that country displays&#13;
extraordinary homogeneity in culture and social structure within its&#13;
boundaries. Even there, however, one finds a substantial Hindu minority,&#13;
various tribal groups, and elements of a Westernized urban elite who deserve&#13;
separate treatment. More typically, developing countries exhibit much&#13;
greater internal heterogeneity than is the case for Bangladesh, that may&#13;
result in quite different patriarchal structures for different regions,&#13;
distinctive ethnic or religious communities, or, indeed, classes. Dyson and&#13;
Moore's analysis shows this clearly for the case of India. Moreover, as a&#13;
further ccmplication, conditions of risk and insurance more generally may&#13;
vary importantly between regions and population subgroups, and also may not&#13;
be contiguous with the boundaries of patriarchal structure. It is,&#13;
therefore, with some trepidation that I introduce a cross-cultural analysis&#13;
of patriarchal structure and fertility, with countries as the unit of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-39-&#13;
analysis, and age differences between spouses as an indicator of patriarchal&#13;
structure.&#13;
Aside from the problems just mentioned in identifying suitable empirical&#13;
indicators of the dimensions of women's economic status, there are good&#13;
reasons to look first at patriarchal structure, rather than women's status,&#13;
as the critical variable in cross-national fertility comparisons. First,&#13;
women's status is a function of patriarchal structure: as depicted in figure&#13;
2 it is an intermediate link in a causal chain connecting patriarchal&#13;
structure and fertility. Second, patriarchal structure is a more stable set&#13;
of social institutions than might be inferred from certain plausible, but&#13;
partial, indicators of women's status (labor market participation, for&#13;
example). Given the variability in such indicators that certain structures&#13;
allow, it is more appropriate to infer women's status from patriarchal&#13;
structure than structure from status. Thirdly, because patriarchal structure&#13;
is relatively stable through time, it should yield more reliable measures&#13;
than the dimensions of women's status.&#13;
The question remains, however, whether it is possible to measure&#13;
patriarchal structure in a parsimonious way. The example of Bangladesh is&#13;
not encouraging. It seems certain that any single indicator would fail to&#13;
capture all the elements of patriarchal structure and their variation across&#13;
societies. Nevertheless, as a first approximation the age difference between&#13;
spouses (or partners in unions) has several attractive features as an&#13;
indicator of patriarchal structure.&#13;
In general, a large difference in age of spouses (male greater than&#13;
female) is associated with patrilineal kinship structure and patrilocal&#13;
residence, while a small difference is consistent with bilateral kinship and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-40-&#13;
greater flexibility in the residence pattern of newly married couples. A&#13;
large age difference itself connotes a potentially powerful means of male&#13;
control over women, and is further indicative of the kind of control that&#13;
derives from the interaction of sex and age hierarchies, as described for the&#13;
case of Barg]Ladesh. Moreover, the larger the age difference between spouses,&#13;
the greater the probability of widowhood that women face. Widowhood is a&#13;
critical juncture in a woman's life, and, in societies where women's economic&#13;
independence is curtailed, is the focal point of patriarchal risk.&#13;
A recent compilation and analysis of data on age difference between&#13;
union partners from World Fertility Survey sources offers further insight&#13;
into the properties of this indicator.36 Table 3 reproduces the median age&#13;
difference between partners (male minus female ages) by duration since union&#13;
for 21 countries grouped by continent.37 From the first column (duration&#13;
less than ten years), note that median age difference ranges from a low of&#13;
2.5 years in the Philippines to a high of 9.1 in Bangladesh. The next three&#13;
columns show the median age difference for successively smaller durations&#13;
since first umion, and thus give an indication of the degree of change in age&#13;
difference in the 15 years preceding the date of the survey (in most cases&#13;
about 1975). While some change is indicated, usually toward a narrowing of&#13;
the age differences, what is most striking to me is the overall stability of&#13;
median age differences through time. For the most part, countries maintain&#13;
their rank order in columns 2 through 4 of Table 3, and inter-country&#13;
variance in median age difference dominates intertemporal variance.&#13;
Median age difference between spouses also displays remarkable&#13;
invariance across socioeconomic groups within countries.38 For example,&#13;
contrary to what one might expect, median age difference within the great&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-41-&#13;
Table 3: Median Age Difference Between Partners, by Duration Since&#13;
Union (Years): Once in Union Wtmen&#13;
COUNTRY                          MEDIAN AGE DIFFERENCE&#13;
DURATION SINCE UNICN (YEARS)&#13;
&gt;, 10     10-14     5-9     0-4&#13;
AFRICA&#13;
Ghana                        7.6       9.5      8.2     7.2&#13;
Kenya*                       7.1       8.0      6.9     7.3&#13;
Lesotho*                     5.6       6.5      5.7     5.5&#13;
Sudan*                      8.4        9.4      8.6     8.2&#13;
ASIA&#13;
Syria*                      6.1        6.8      6.2     6.0&#13;
Bangladesh*                  9.1      10.1      9.3     9.0&#13;
Nepal*                       3.8       4.6      4.1     3.6&#13;
Pakistan*                    6.5       5.9      6.4     6.6&#13;
Sri Lanka*                  4.8        6.1      5.3     4.3&#13;
Indonesia                   4.9        5.3      5.2     4.7&#13;
Korea, S                     4.0       3.7      4.0     3.9&#13;
Malaysia:  Malay             4.8       5.1      5.0     4.6&#13;
Chinese           3.9        3.6     3.9     3.9&#13;
Philippines*                 2.5       2.7      2.5     2.5&#13;
Thailand*                    3.3       3.5      3.4     3.2&#13;
AMERICAS&#13;
Colombia                     4.6       5.1      5.6     4.6&#13;
Paraguay                     4.0       4.4      4.1     4.0&#13;
Peru                         3.8       4.3      3.9     3.8&#13;
Costa Rica                   3.0       3.7      3.6     2.4&#13;
Mexico*                      3.0       3.5      3.2     2.9&#13;
Haiti                        4.1       4.9      4.0     4.2&#13;
Jamaica                      4.1       3.3      3.8     4.9&#13;
*Data nertain to women currently in union onlv&#13;
Source : Casterline and McDona1d7, cited in note 36, Tables 4 and 5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-42-&#13;
majority of countries of Table 3 does not vary systematically with wife's&#13;
years of schooling. Nor does it vary according to husband's occupation, or&#13;
wife's childhood place of residence (city, town, or village). With respect&#13;
to its merits as an indicator of patriarchal structure, this evidence of&#13;
robustness is reassuring.&#13;
Figure 4 plots the Total Fertility Rate (TFR) against median age&#13;
difference between spouses for the 21 countries listed in Table 3. Two TFRs&#13;
are used. The first, designated by (X), is that yielded by the World&#13;
Fertility Survey (this will be referred to as TFR(l)), and the second,&#13;
designated by (0), is the most recent reliable estimate available (TFR(2)).39&#13;
In the case of Nepal, Pakistan, and Bangladesh, the more recent estimate of&#13;
TFR is greater than the WFS estimate. This reflects the likelihood that the&#13;
WFS underestimated current fertility in those countries, rather than a real&#13;
increase in fertility between the date of the survey and the present. In&#13;
none of these three oountries is there reason for supposing that there has&#13;
been any recent change in national fertility rates. The more recent TFR&#13;
estimates shoRwn elsewhere in Figure 4 should be interpreted as indicating&#13;
real declines in fertility.&#13;
Visual inspection of Figure 4 suggests a positive relationship between&#13;
median age difference and fertility. Indeed, the simple correlation between&#13;
the two variables (using TFR(l)) is .65 - higher than the correlation&#13;
between fertility and infant mortality (.50), the logarithm of GNP per capita&#13;
(-.35), median age at first marriage for women (-.58), or female secondary&#13;
school enrollment ratios (-.59). The regression line drawn in Figure 4 has a&#13;
slope of .45. The regression line for TFR (2), reflecting recent declines in&#13;
fertility, has a slightly steeper slope (.57) and a better fit (R2 = .49; F =&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-43-&#13;
6u.4&#13;
of&#13;
i&#13;
I-&#13;
is&#13;
w                                §*-? a-&#13;
Ei                 aN                     g                     -&#13;
ow&#13;
m~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
a.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
i  \                   o&#13;
I     I      t     I     I     I   . AL I  _I   *_ I  .Xlo&#13;
d     ad     1'    d      VI   I;     i      i     4     id&#13;
31VM AJtitim3a 1V.OJ&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
44-&#13;
18.5). The estimated effect of median age difference on fertility is not&#13;
substantially diminished when statistical controls for infant mortality, GNP&#13;
per capita, age at marriage, or female secondary school school enrollment are&#13;
introduced.&#13;
It is also clear from Figure 4, however, that the strong positive&#13;
correlation between median age difference and fertility derives from the&#13;
position of two clusters of countries in the plot: the cluster in the lower&#13;
left, comprised primarily of Southeast Asian and Latin American countries,&#13;
with both relatively low age differences and low fertility; and the cluster&#13;
in the upper right, comprised of African, South Asian (M&amp;uslim) and West Asian&#13;
countries, with large age differences and high fertility. (If median age&#13;
difference is collapsed, distinguishing only two categories -- below five&#13;
years and five years and greater -- the correlation between this dichotomous&#13;
variable and TrFR increases to .78). If one looks within each cluster,&#13;
however, no clear relationship between median age difference and fertility&#13;
can be discenaed. Therefore, our indicator of patriarchal structure appears&#13;
to be able to distinguish at best two distinct regimes, one "weak" and one&#13;
"strong" .   Within the weak cluster, one can observe that many countries&#13;
have experienced further recent fertility declines. The change involved in&#13;
moving from TFR(1) to TFR(2) (excluding the outliers Nepal and Korea) has had&#13;
the effect of compressing the range of fertility within this group&#13;
considerably. No such movement in fertility is evident in the strong&#13;
cluster.&#13;
One measure of the effect of patriarchal structure on fertility can be&#13;
obtained by regressing TFR on median age difference between spouses,&#13;
controlling for possible confounding variables. The first four columns of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-45-&#13;
Table 4 presents the results of these regressions. To facilitate&#13;
interpretation, median age difference is transformed into a dichotomous&#13;
variable, set equal to zero if median age difference is less than five years&#13;
and equal to one if median age difference is five years or more. These&#13;
regression models incorporate successively as controls: infant mortality&#13;
rate, logarithm of GNP per capita, median age at first marriage (females) and&#13;
female secondary school enrollment ratios. The coefficients for median age&#13;
difference (the first row in Table 4) imply that a strong patriarchal regime&#13;
is responsible for adding something in excess of two live births to the Total&#13;
Fertility Rate. (Table 4 uses the more recent TFR(2) as the dependent&#13;
variable; the results using TFR(1) are equally consistent, although the&#13;
estimated coefficients for age difference average about 1.9 instead of 2.2).&#13;
The effects of patriarchal structure on fertility can be examined&#13;
further by testing for statistical interaction between median age difference&#13;
and the "control" variables (infant mortality, etc.). Recall that&#13;
patriarchal structure was posited to act as a covariate. Where patriarchal&#13;
structure is strong, it was argued, mortality decline would simply facilitate&#13;
the achievement of security targets that were out of reach before, and,&#13;
therefore, one would not necessarily expect fertility to decline in response.&#13;
For weak patriarchal regimes, however, where intrinsic security targets were&#13;
already low, one would expect fertility to decline (presumably with some lag)&#13;
in response to a decline in mortality. Similarly, weak patriarchal regimes&#13;
possess greater inherent flexibility in female age at marriage, education and&#13;
employment. These should prove more responsive to change in the course of&#13;
economic development, and, through the channels described in the previous&#13;
section, could potentially have an impact on fertility.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-46-&#13;
m  ko~~~~ &#13;
LA ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~~nc&#13;
r-              00r- &#13;
*                       00   u-4  s-V&#13;
-W               Ln  r-  00~~~~ L&#13;
CN  LA&#13;
*.          CD*  S  -LA      * &#13;
*  -* 1&#13;
rz4~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~$&#13;
(Nw           0              0  - (&#13;
(N&#13;
11-I~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~4&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~ppQ              3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-47-&#13;
In order to test for the presence of interaction, a variable consisting&#13;
of the product of the dichotomous age difference variable and the appropriate&#13;
control variable was added to the simple models of columns (1) through (4) of&#13;
Table 4. The results are shown in columns (5) through (8) of that table, and&#13;
plotted in Figure 5. Because the age difference variable is dichotomous, the&#13;
results are easily interpreted. For example, in the case of infant mortality&#13;
(column 5), when the age difference variable is zero, the estimated&#13;
relationship between infant mortality and fertility can be written:&#13;
TFR = 2.6 + .02 IMR&#13;
When age difference is equal to 1, however, the relationship is:&#13;
TFR = (2.6 + 6.1) + (.02 - .04) IMR, or&#13;
TFR = 8.7 - .02 IMR&#13;
The results are quite striking.  Among strong patriarchal regimes (AD&#13;
5+), variation in GNP per capita, infant mortality, median age at first&#13;
marriage, and female secondary school enrollment bears either no relation to&#13;
fertility levels or a relationship that is contrary to what one would&#13;
ordinarily expect.41 Among weak patriarchal regimes (AD &lt; 5), on the other&#13;
hand, the four predictor variables behave very much as expected: fertility is&#13;
positively related to the infant mortality rate, and negatively related to&#13;
GNP, age at marriage, and school enrollment. The size and statistical&#13;
significance of the estimated effect of these variables is in each case&#13;
enhanced by introducing an interaction term.42&#13;
4. Preference for sons. Societies in which women have little economic&#13;
independence should generate a strong preference for sons. According to our&#13;
interpretation, the material basis for son preference in such societies is&#13;
the need for security -- first and foremost, security in old age. Quite&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-48-&#13;
FIGURE 5i INTERACTION EFFECTS OF AGE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN&#13;
SPOUSES CAD) WITH GNP PER CAPITA, INFANT&#13;
MORTALITY. AGE AT FIRST MARRIAGE. AND FEMALE&#13;
SECONDARY SCHOOL ENROLLMENT&#13;
TFR                             TFR&#13;
7       * TFR a 7.5      AD     7          TFR IL 7 -.1&#13;
ADUI 5+&#13;
4-                              4-&#13;
2     TrFR* 7.,5- .      AD S   95  _      ,     . z ,2SR&#13;
_4~                      I       _&#13;
4j   5   a    7 L     S        5         110 15&#13;
PER CAPITA                           MTALITY&#13;
RATE&#13;
TFR                             TFR&#13;
'MR - 4.2 + .12UA&#13;
7                     ADS.      7         TFR -&amp;75      AD 5&#13;
5-&#13;
4\                              4                       AD-J'S&#13;
TPR - 5.1 - .UFENROLL&#13;
2               AD -45     2-4&#13;
1              -TPR 1LI.44DA    1&#13;
1       25     25                1D    28   B3    43   53&#13;
MEDIAN AGE                        FEMALE&#13;
AT FIRST                          SECONDARY&#13;
MARRIAGE                          SCHOOl&#13;
ENROLLMENT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-49-&#13;
apart from any other potential channel of influence, women's status should&#13;
have fundamental implications for fertility because it determines the extent&#13;
to which the sex of children is relevent to planning for future security&#13;
needs.&#13;
The World Fertility Survey has recently issued a report in their&#13;
comparative studies series that analyzes preferences for the sex of children&#13;
for 27 countries.43 The analysis focuses on responses to the question "Would&#13;
you prefer your next (first) child to be a boy or a girl?"; which was asked&#13;
of all pregnant women and all currently married non-pregnant women who wanted&#13;
at least one more child and considered themselves capable of having another&#13;
child. As a summary indicator of preferences the countries were ranked&#13;
according to the ratio of "boy" responses to "girl" responses, after&#13;
apportioning the occasionally large group of undecided women equally between&#13;
the numerator (boys) and the denominator (girls).44 Four groups of countries&#13;
were identified on this basis, ranging from "strong son preference" to&#13;
"daughter preference":&#13;
Strong son        Mbderate son        Equal               Daughter&#13;
preference (1)    preference (2)      preference (3)      preference (4)&#13;
Pakistan   4.9    Lesotho    1.5      Kenya        1.1    Venezuela  0.8&#13;
Nepal      4.0    Sri Lanka  1.5      Indonesia    1.1    Jamaica    0.7&#13;
Bangladesh 3.3    Sudan      1.5      Peru         1.1&#13;
Korea      3.3    Thailand   1.4      Guyana       1.1&#13;
Syria      2.3    Fiji       1.3      Trinidad and&#13;
Jordan     1.9    Malaysia   1.2        Tobago     1.1&#13;
Dbminican           Columbia     1.0&#13;
Republic 1.2      Paraguay     1.0&#13;
Mexico     1.2      Costa Rica   1.0&#13;
Panama       1.0&#13;
Philippines  0.9&#13;
Haiti        0.9&#13;
Source:  Cleland, Verrall, and Vaessen, cited in note 43, p.10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-50-&#13;
Middle-eastern and South Asian countries dominate the strong son&#13;
preference group; Southeast Asian and sub-Saharan African countries are&#13;
distributed between the moderate son preference and equal preference group;&#13;
while Latin Azerican and Caribbean countries generally display equal&#13;
preference. A more detailed analysis of preferences by parity (limited to&#13;
parities two through four) and existing sex composition of children suggests&#13;
that within the strong son group, a net preference for girls occurs only&#13;
among women whio have no daughters. In the three other groups, preferences&#13;
reveal a desire for a balanced sex composition. The desire to correct an&#13;
imbalance is evident both in groups (2) and (3); however, when a balance&#13;
already exists, the moderate son group expresses a net preference for sons,&#13;
while the equil preference group exhibits no marked preference for either&#13;
sex.&#13;
In Figure 6, the sex preference ratios are plotted against median age&#13;
difference between spouses for the sample of countries for which both types&#13;
of data are available. With several notable (and interpretable) exceptions&#13;
one can distinguish a rough correspondence between our measure of patriarchal&#13;
structure and degree of son preference. Latin American, Caribbean, and&#13;
Southeast Asian countries are clustered in the quadrant to the lower left,&#13;
with equal, or weak son, preference and a relatively small age difference&#13;
between spouses, and Muslim South Asian and Middle eastern countries are&#13;
located in the upper right-hand quadrant. (The tattered appearance of this&#13;
plot is due in no small part to the meager sample of countries from the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I                              ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~n)&#13;
b                                    - d #bX~~a- &#13;
Q~~~~~~~~~&#13;
I!   Ux &#13;
Ui.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~U&#13;
sW x x x SxSXMx E 1 x&#13;
N  i  d  d  s ..  d  v               of d s &#13;
va~~~TCluv4i MonS 'wc    i dm&#13;
U.        S39f1xw| N33AIM MaO"ICa aWV NVICB&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-52-&#13;
latter region. Although median age difference data is not readily available&#13;
for Jordan or Egypt, judging from the difference in mean age at marriage for&#13;
these countries and data that is available on son preference, they would form&#13;
a tight cluster with Syria in Figure 6.)45 The misfits in the figure are&#13;
Korea and Nepael (low age difference between spouses, strong son preference)&#13;
and the African countries (large age differences between spouses, weak son&#13;
preference or indifference).&#13;
The position of the African countries is not unexpected given the&#13;
particular interpretation of a large age difference between spouses that is&#13;
appropriate in that setting (see Note 40). The continuing importance of&#13;
corporate kin groups and the institutions of brideprice and polygyny suggest&#13;
that large age differences between spouses are more a reflection of lineage&#13;
(and generational) control than the economic subordination of women by men.&#13;
Weak son preference, or a preference for balanced sex composition, is&#13;
consistent with this interpretation.&#13;
In Korea, it is likely that the material basis for son preference has&#13;
been substantially eroded through the process of rapid economic development&#13;
and the consequent amelioration of risks, development of financial and&#13;
insurance markets, and growth of social security and employee benefits.46&#13;
This is not to say that the link between material security (particularly in&#13;
old age) and reproduction has been completely eliminated. The very strong&#13;
son preference that persists in Korea is, however, placed in a better&#13;
perspective by noting that of women (currently married, fecund, and&#13;
non-pregnant) with one son and one daughter, 72 percent indicated that they&#13;
did not want any more children, and of women with two sons and one daughter,&#13;
97 percent said they wanted no more children.47&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-53-&#13;
Although Nepal has a very heterogeneous population, two major cultural&#13;
groups can be identified: Hindu Indo-Arayan and Tibeto-Burman (primarily&#13;
Buddhist).48 In kinship and women's economic status, the former, which is&#13;
the numerically dcminant cultural group (approximately 80 percent of the&#13;
total population), is akin to the "north Indian" pattern.49 I have no ready&#13;
explanation as to why the median age difference between spouses is low in&#13;
Nepal; however, given women's relatively low economic status in the majority&#13;
group, it would seem that, in the aggregate, the country belongs with other&#13;
"strong" patriarchal societies, as is suggested by the marked preference for&#13;
sons.&#13;
In Figure 7, the total fertility rate is plotted against another measure&#13;
of child sex preference. The horizontal axis of Figure 7 is the difference&#13;
between the percentage of women who want a son and the percentage of women&#13;
who want a daughter among currently married fecund women who already have two&#13;
living sons and one daughter and who want more children.50 For countries in&#13;
the negative range there is a net preference for daughters, and for those in&#13;
the positive range, a net preference for sons. Because these women already&#13;
have two living sons and because the current sex composition of their&#13;
children is unbalanced, this index represents a "strong" test of son&#13;
preference. The sample of countries in Figure 7 includes all those for which&#13;
data on preference for the sex of children are available. With the exception&#13;
of Korea, countries with a marked preference for sons also have high and&#13;
relatively unyielding fertility. Similarly, countries that tend toward a&#13;
preference for balanced child sex composition (with the exception of&#13;
sub-Saharan Africa) have all experienced some degree of fertility decline.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-54-&#13;
aw                   I%c U._       ^&#13;
I.-~~~~~~~~I&#13;
Ex  I _I.&#13;
LiL ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~  ~  ~  L&#13;
(' UU.&#13;
w~~~~~~~~&#13;
I fi                  Ex  xi      U&#13;
U.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.&#13;
CL&#13;
~~~xd&#13;
w &#13;
U.d                               i&#13;
31v2 AlIlllH3A 1Y±O1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-55-&#13;
As in the case of median age difference between spouses, the sex&#13;
preference index of Figure 7 is capable of distinguishing two distinct&#13;
regimes: the cluster to the lower left, in which a strong preference for a&#13;
balanced sex composition is evident, and the cluster to the upper right where&#13;
a net preference for sons persists. Kenya, Lesotho, and Sudan form a loose&#13;
grouping of their own, although Lesotho is more closely aligned with the&#13;
"balanced" cluster, while Sudan is shaded toward the strong son preference&#13;
group. Sri Lanka and Korea are off by themselves, with each sharing a slight&#13;
net preference for daughters. (It should be noted for these two countries&#13;
that the number of observations on which the percentages are based is small,&#13;
particularly in the case of Korea.)&#13;
The regression line drawn in Figure 7 is based on the entire sample of&#13;
countries. If Korea and the sub-Saharan countries of Kenya and Lesotho are&#13;
excluded, the estimated slope is unchanged (.028) but one achieves a much&#13;
better fit (R2= .54, F= 24.9). Introducing a statistical control for infant&#13;
mortality rate does not substantially alter this result.51&#13;
V. Conclusion&#13;
Given the caveats offered concerning this mode of analysis, and the&#13;
empirically uncertain status of some components of the argument, it would be&#13;
unwise to claim too much on the basis of these results. Nevertheless, they&#13;
clearly do provide support for the proposition that patriarchal structure and&#13;
women's economic dependence are important mediators of fertility transition&#13;
in the developing world. I will conclude by commenting on several&#13;
implications of this proposition for research and policy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-56-&#13;
The scq?e for cross-national quantitative analysis of fertility is&#13;
sharply constrained by the meager data that are available. The important&#13;
conceptual distinction between women's economic status, on the one hand, and&#13;
its structural determinants, on the other, and the need for independent&#13;
indicators of both, greatly increases the demands on data. As argued in the&#13;
previous section, patriarchal structure cperates as a covariate: it&#13;
interacts with social and economic development in such a way as to both limit&#13;
the variability of coQponents of women's economic status and affect the&#13;
relationship between such components (and other development variables) and&#13;
fertility. Indicators of women's economic status (labor force participation&#13;
rates or school enrollment ratios, for example) even if they are meaningfully&#13;
measured, cannot, therefore, be used as indicators of underlying patriarchal&#13;
structure. Judging from the results in Table 4, omission of this variable in&#13;
cross-national analyses of fertility would seriously bias the results. The&#13;
functional form of statistical models is an equally important potential&#13;
source of specification error and bias. A recent review of 33 cross-national&#13;
studies of fertility in developing countries conducted between 1962 and 1981&#13;
revealed that all used additive statistical models.52 What is called for&#13;
instead (assuming that one has a measure of patriarchal structure) is an&#13;
interaction model. The likelihood of errors in model specification (both&#13;
omitted variables and functional form) lead me to question the results of&#13;
these studies, while problems of data availability make me pessimistic about&#13;
the prospect of pushing the analysis much beyond that which is presented in&#13;
this paper. The complications introduced by distinctive family structures in&#13;
different regions serve to further dim these prospects.&#13;
What is needed more immediately, in my view, is research that can&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-57-&#13;
elaborate the elements of patriarchal structure in different settings,&#13;
focusing on the circumstances of women's economic vulnerability, and the role&#13;
and importance of sons and daughters as sources of security. I would give&#13;
high priority to field-based work such as that of Cppong and Bleek among the&#13;
Kwahu which can comment simultaneously on the economic relations between&#13;
parents and children and between men and women, on family and kinship&#13;
dynamics, and the locus and criteria of reproductive decisions.&#13;
With respect to policy, the analysis in this paper suggests that the&#13;
task of fertility reduction in societies with strong patriarchal regimes is&#13;
enormously more difficult than in those with weak regimes. Consider the case&#13;
of educational expansion and the promotion of literacy, a favorite anti-natal&#13;
policy prescription. In the weak patriarchal regime, beginning with a low&#13;
level of literacy, the government can set about expanding the educational&#13;
sector and creating educational opportunities (preferably in conjunction with&#13;
increasing demand for an educated work force) with a reasonable expectation&#13;
that such a policy will induce a fertility response, as age at marriage rises&#13;
and various other channels of influence are activated. In the strong&#13;
patriarchal regime, beginning with the same level of literacy and policy&#13;
course, the government can expect (a) resistance to female school enrollment,&#13;
because it conflicts with the logic and inertia of patriarchal structure, and&#13;
(b) to the extent that female education is promoted, a weaker fertility&#13;
response.&#13;
Recognition that the problem lies at the structural level, while a&#13;
necessary step toward informed policy, does not make the problem less&#13;
formidable or more amenable to policy intervention. Among societies with&#13;
strong patriarchal regimes there are, as yet, no demographic success stories&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-58-&#13;
from which policy lessons might be drawn; nor are there many examples among&#13;
these societies of concerted policy attacks on the institutional bases of&#13;
women's econoxmic dependence. One country in which there has been such an&#13;
effort is Tun:Lsia, where President Bourguiba has long championed the cause of&#13;
women, and, in the interests of improving their status, instituted a broad&#13;
range of legal reforms, and vigorously promoted female education and female&#13;
political part:icipation. While these efforts have unquestionably had some&#13;
effect, particularly as evidenced by a rise in female age at marriage and&#13;
substantial increase in female primary school enrollment, the total fertility&#13;
rate in Tunisia remains above five. As described by Larson, an&#13;
anthropologist: who worked in a rural area of Tunisia and monitored the impact&#13;
of these policies, the institutional framework of patriarchy has proven quite&#13;
resilient.53 The villagers in this locality were selective in their&#13;
acceptance of the various laws and policies: adcpting those which did not&#13;
seriously threaten the social order and rejecting those that did. For&#13;
example, delaying marriage until age 19 or 20 was agreeable because it would&#13;
permit a girl "time to develop her housekeeping and wifely skills"54 and,&#13;
similarly, primary education for girls was seen as "a good opportunity for a&#13;
woman to acquire the basic skills she will need to be a good wife and&#13;
mother".55  Ibwever, the villagers, particularly men, resisted the idea of&#13;
secondary education for females: "Older and middle aged men did not see the&#13;
value of secordary education and feared sending their daughters to a school&#13;
outside the village where they would have opportunities to flirt with&#13;
men... Such education [young men argued] not only would compromise their wives'&#13;
reputations but would raise their expectations in ways that would make them&#13;
unsuited to village life. They would disdain hard work, make too many&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-59-&#13;
material demands, and challenge village customs..."56 Despite the policies of&#13;
the state, women in this locality remain excluded from the economic&#13;
mainstream and highly dependent on men.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-60-&#13;
Notes&#13;
1.   Karen 0. Mason, "The status of women, fertility and mortality: A review&#13;
of interrelationships," (Paper prepared for the The Population Sciences&#13;
Division, The Rockefeller Foundation, New York, July 1983). See also:&#13;
Ruth Dixon, "The roles of rural women: Female seclusion, economic&#13;
production and reproductive choice," in Population and Development, ed.&#13;
R. Ridker (Baltimore:  The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1976);&#13;
Christinle Cppong, "Women's roles, opportunity costs, and fertility," in&#13;
Determinzants of Fertility in Developing Countries, eds. R. Bulatao and&#13;
R.D. Lee et al. (New York: Academic Press, 1983), pp. 439-473;&#13;
Constantina Safilios- Rothschild, "Female Power, autonomy and demographic&#13;
change in the Third World," in Women's Roles and Population Trends in the&#13;
Third World, eds. R. Anker, M. Buvinic and N.H. Youssef (London:&#13;
Croom Helm, 1982); and Helen Ware, Women, Demography and Development&#13;
(Canberra: The Australian National University, 1981).&#13;
2.   For an ealaboration of this argument see:  Mead Cain, "Fertility as an&#13;
adjustment to risk," Population and Development Review 9, no.4 (December&#13;
1983), pp. 688-702.&#13;
3.   For some supporting evidence see Mead Cain, "The household life cycle and&#13;
economic mobility in rural Bangladesh," Population and Development&#13;
Review 4, no. 3 (September 1978): 421-438; Mead Cain, "Risk and&#13;
insurance: Perspectives on fertility and agrarian change in India and&#13;
Bangladesh," Population and Develcpment Review 7, no. 3 (September 1981):&#13;
435-474; and Mead Cain, "Perspectives on family and fertility in&#13;
developing countries," Population Studies 36, no. 2 (July 1982): 159-175.&#13;
4.   LSF and other approaches to modeling uncertain decisions are described in&#13;
J. A. Roumasset, J. Boussard, and I. Singh (eds.), Risk, Uncertainty and&#13;
Agricultural Development (New York: Agricultural Development Council,&#13;
1979). Lexicographic decision rules based on other criteria are&#13;
discussed in Harvey Leibenstein, "Economic decision theory and human&#13;
fertility behavior: A speculative essay," Population and Develcpment&#13;
Review 7, no. 3, (September 1981): 381-400.&#13;
5.   If the frequency of default were high enough, parents might conceivably&#13;
give up on children. However, if there were no alternative to children,&#13;
the frequency would have to be very high before this would happen.&#13;
6.   For a fuller discussion see Cain, 1981, cited in note 1.&#13;
7.   Peter H. Lindert, "Child costs and economic development," in Population&#13;
and Economic Change in Develcping Countries, ed. Richard A. Easterlin&#13;
(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1980), pp. 5-79.&#13;
8.   For a review of this literature, see Guy Standing, "Women's work activity&#13;
and fertility," Chapter 16 in Bulatao et al. Determinants of Fertility&#13;
in Developing Countries, 2 vols. (New York: Academic Press, 1983), pp.&#13;
416-438.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-61-&#13;
9.   United Nations, World Population Trends and Policies 1982 Monitoring&#13;
Report, Volume 1: Population Trends (New York: United Nations,&#13;
forthcoming).  It is tempting to extend this list to other countries&#13;
where data are less complete. For example, the most recent contraceptive&#13;
prevalence survey in Thailand (1981) gives the first indications that the&#13;
rapid fertility decline experienced by that country may be "bottoming&#13;
out" at a TFR of about 3.5.    (John Knodel, et al., Fertility in&#13;
Thailand: Trends, Differentials, and Proximate Determinants, Committee on&#13;
Population and Demography Report No. 13, Washington D.C.: National&#13;
Academy Press (1982): 18-19.) However, as the authors note, it is only&#13;
one survey, and one that is methodologically suspect at that.&#13;
10. See Cdile Frank, "Infertility in sub-Saharan Africa: Estimates and&#13;
implications,"  Population and Development Review 9, no. 1 (March 1983):&#13;
137-144.&#13;
11. Fram Cain, 1981, cited in note 3.&#13;
12. T. Dyson and M. Moore, "On kinship structure, female autonomy, and&#13;
demographic behavior in India," Population and Develcpment Review 9, no.&#13;
1 (March 1983): 35-60.&#13;
13. This point is discussed in Cain, 1982, cited in note 3.&#13;
14. John C. Caldwell, "A theory of fertility: From high plateau to&#13;
destabilization," Population and Development Review, 4, no. 4 (December&#13;
1978): 553-577.&#13;
15. John Hajnal, "TIWo kinds of preindustrial household formation systems,"&#13;
Population and Development Review 8, no. 3 (September 1982), pp. 449-494.&#13;
16. George W. Roberts, "Family unions in the West Indies and some of their&#13;
implications," in Nuptiality and Fertility, ed. Lado T. Ruzicka (Liege:&#13;
Ordina Editions, 1982).&#13;
17. For example, see the selections in Christine Oppong (ed.), Female&#13;
and Male in West Africa (London: Allen and Unwin, 1983) ard Ca-ldwell's&#13;
analysis of the Yoruba: John C. Caldwell, "Toward a restatement of&#13;
demographic transition theory," Population and Development Review 2, no.&#13;
3-4 (1976), pp. 321-366. An overview is provided in the chapter on&#13;
sub-Saharan Africa in William J. Goode, World Revolution and Family&#13;
Patterns (New York: The Free Press, 1963), pp. 164-202.&#13;
18. H. Leibenstein, "The economic theory of fertility: Survey, issues and&#13;
considerations," in International Population Conference, Mexico, 1977,&#13;
Volume II (Liege: IUSSP, 1977), pp. 49-64.&#13;
19. See Roberts, cited in note 16, and E. Clark, My Mother Who&#13;
Fathered Me (London:  Allen and Unwin, 1975).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-62-&#13;
20. This section is based on: Christine Cppong and Wolf Bleek, "Econmric&#13;
models aLnd having children: Some evidence from Kwahu, Ghana," Africa 52,&#13;
no. 4 (1982), pp. 15-32. The quotations below are froom this article.&#13;
21.  This antlysis draws on M. Cain, S. R. Khanam, ard S. Nahar, "Class,&#13;
patriarchy, and women's work in Bangladesh," Population and Develcment&#13;
Review 5, no. 3 (September 1979): 405-438.&#13;
22.  A. A. M1-ududi, Birth Control:  Its Social, Political, Economic, Moral&#13;
and Religious Aspects (Lahore: Islamic Publications, 1968); and quoted&#13;
in H. Pipanek, "Purdah:  Separate worlds and symbolic shelter,"&#13;
Comparative Studies in Society and History 15, no. 3 (1973), p. 308.&#13;
23. See Peter J. Bertocci, "Elusive villages: Social structure and community&#13;
organization in rural East Pakistan," Ph.D. dissertation, Michigan State&#13;
Univers:ity, 1970; and T. Abdullah and S. Zeidenstein, Village Women of&#13;
Bangladesh: Prospects for Change (Elmsford, N.Y.: Pergamon Press,&#13;
1981).&#13;
24. Papanek, cited in note 22, p. 289.&#13;
25. Once a security target has been determined for a particular society,&#13;
Easterlin's framework should be useful in sorting out its implications&#13;
for fertility and fertility transition.  Easterlin's framework focuses on&#13;
"desired family size" -- the number of surviving children a couple would&#13;
want in a society in which the aosts of fertility regulation were&#13;
negligible. This framework is concerned less with the determinants of&#13;
desired family size, than the implications for fertility once desires,&#13;
the costs of fertility regulation, and potential family size have been&#13;
determined. Cne important modification to this framework that is&#13;
suggested by the safety-first model of fertility would be the&#13;
specification of the sex composition of surviving children. See R.A.&#13;
Easterlin, "An economic framework for fertility analysis," Studies in&#13;
Family Planning 6, no. 3 (March 1975): 54-63. For recent empirical&#13;
applications in India see E.M. Crimmins, R.A. Easterlin, S.J. Jejeebhoy,&#13;
and K. Srinivasan, "New perspectives on the demographic transition: A&#13;
theoretical and empirical analysis of an Indian state, 1951-1975,"&#13;
Economic Development and Cultural Change 32, no. 2 (January 1984):&#13;
227-253, and K. Srinivasan, S.J. Jejeebhoy, R.A. Easterlin, and E.M.&#13;
Crimmins, "Factors affecting fertility control in India: A cross-&#13;
sectional study," Population and Develcpment Review (forthcoming 1984).&#13;
26. See Figure 4.&#13;
27. See Frank, cited in note 10.&#13;
28. Frank, cited in note 10.&#13;
29. 0. Frark, "Child fostering in sub-Saharan Africa" (Paper presented at the&#13;
Population Association of America Annual Meeting, Minneapolis, May&#13;
1984).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-63-&#13;
30.  J.C. Caldwell, "Mass education as a determinant of the timing of&#13;
fertility decline," Population and Development Review 6, no. 2 (June&#13;
1980): 225-255; J.C. Caldwell, "Education as a factor in mortality&#13;
decline: An examination of Nigerian data," Population Studies 33, no. 3&#13;
(November 1979): 395-413; S.H. Cochrane, Fertility and Education: What&#13;
do we really know? (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1979).&#13;
31. One may observe an increase in female age at marriage for reasons&#13;
unrelated to these stimuli. Changes in age structure and an attendant&#13;
marriage squeeze may place upward pressure on female age at first&#13;
marriage. For example, see J.C. Caldwell, P.H. Reddy, and P. Caldwell,&#13;
"The causes of marriage change in South India," Population Studies 37,&#13;
no. 3 (November 1983): 343-361.&#13;
32. Cf. Dyson and Mcore, cited in note 12.&#13;
33. M. Nag, "The impact of sociocultural factors on breastfeeding and sexual&#13;
behavior," Chapter 6 in Bulatao et al. (eds.) Determinants of Fertility&#13;
in Develcping Countries, 2 vols. (New York: Academic Press, 1983), pp.&#13;
134-162.&#13;
34. This refers to the couple's attitudes toward fertility regulation and&#13;
access to family planning services and supplies, including both the&#13;
subjective disadvantages and economic costs. See Easterlin, cited in&#13;
note 40.&#13;
35. See: R.B. Dixon, "Women in agriculture: Counting the labor force in&#13;
developing countries," Population and Development Review 8, no. 3&#13;
(September 1982): 539-566; and Cain et al., cited in note 21.&#13;
36. J.B. Casterline and P.F. McDonald, "The age difference between union&#13;
partners," World Fertility Survey, WFS/TECH. 2070, 28 March 1983 (also&#13;
presented at the Population Association of America Annual Meeting,&#13;
Pittsburgh, May 1983).&#13;
37. For a detailed description of the data see Casterline and McDonald, cited&#13;
in note 36. The data for Sudan pertain to the northern part of that&#13;
country only. Age difference data is missing for less than twelve&#13;
percent of the women surveyed in every country except Indonesia, Haiti&#13;
and Jamaica. The loss is most severe for Haiti and Jamaica, where the&#13;
estimated median age difference pertains to less than half of the women&#13;
first entering a union in the ten years preceeding the survey.&#13;
38. See Casterline and McDonald cited in note 36.&#13;
39. The sources of these and other data that will be used in the analysis are&#13;
given in Appendix Table 1.&#13;
40. I would prefer to treat the sub-Saharan African countries (Ghana, Kenya,&#13;
and Lesotho) separately in the following analysis. I include them only&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-64-&#13;
because of the limited number of observations available. While these&#13;
countries behave in a fashion that is consistent with the other members&#13;
of the "strong" patriarchal cluster, they do so, I believe, in part for&#13;
the wrong reasons.  In sub-Saharan   Africa, control of women (and men)&#13;
by the larger kin group is, perhaps, more at issue than control of women&#13;
by men. The large age differences between spouses in Ghana, Kenya, and&#13;
Lesotho bear a distinct interpretation. The age differe3nce may be large&#13;
in part because of the persistent demands of brideprice. (Men must delay&#13;
marriage until sufficient wealth is accumulated to meet these substantial&#13;
demands.) The age difference also reflects the practice of polygyny. For&#13;
example, in Kenya (the only country for which data are available frcm WFS&#13;
sources) the median age difference according to union type and rank of wife&#13;
is as follows:&#13;
Median Difference          Number of Women&#13;
Monogamous                             6.1                        1727&#13;
First wife                             7.4                          91&#13;
Second wife                           15.0                         318&#13;
Third or higher                       22.9                         104&#13;
(from Casterline and McDonald, cited in note 36, Table 17)&#13;
With the exception of the Akan people of Ghana, these societies are, I&#13;
should add, characterized by patrilineal kinship, patrilocal residence, and&#13;
male (or patrilineal) control of property and female labor. Their presence&#13;
in the "strong" cluster is, therefore, not totally ancmalous. However, the&#13;
system is not geared toward the control of female sexuality through&#13;
restrictions that severely constrain women's econcmic activity (although&#13;
women typically operate in separate "spheres") as is the case in Bangladesh&#13;
and North India. Indeed, women in sub-Saharan Africa are very active&#13;
economically, usually in ways that give them ccnsiderable independence frcm&#13;
their husbands. Rather, as is suggested by the importance of brideprice,&#13;
the object of control is women's labor per se (and their reproductive&#13;
potential), and the major actors in the game are corporate kin groups.   In&#13;
this setting, the age difference between spouses is more a reflection of&#13;
lineage control than of patriarchal control, as we have conceived it.&#13;
41. The range of the predictor variables is substantial in both groups:&#13;
Age Difference &lt;5          Age Difference 5+&#13;
High          Low          High          LDW&#13;
CNP          2250          150          1570          140&#13;
IMR           142           42           139           65&#13;
MWAM            22.0         16.6           18.4         13.9&#13;
FEN1DL           62            4            32             7&#13;
42. The interaction is weakest for female secondary school enrollment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-65-&#13;
43. John Cleland, Jane Verrall, and Martin Vaessen, "Preferences for the sex&#13;
of children and their influence on reproductive behaviour", WFS Comparative&#13;
Studies No. 27. (Voorburg, Netherlands: International Statistical&#13;
Institute, November 1983).&#13;
44. The residual category actually lumps together expressions of indifference&#13;
concerning the sex of the next child, with indecision and non-response. Among&#13;
the countries considered in this analysis, the size of this category varied&#13;
frcm a low of 14 percent for the Dominican Republic to a high of 54 percent for&#13;
Kenya. Although no systematic cross-national pattern of variation in residual&#13;
response is evident, the fact that the size of residual category varies so&#13;
much, ccmbined with its unknown, but quite likely varying, composition suggests&#13;
the need for caution in interpreting indices of sex preference based on this&#13;
question. Further consideration of cross-cultural variations in the&#13;
appropriateness of verbalizing such preferences and differences in interview&#13;
setting (for example, the extent to which interviewers insist on a positive&#13;
choice by respondents) underscores the need for caution in interpretation.&#13;
45. Jordan Fertility Survey, 1976, Vols 1 and 2 (Amman: Department&#13;
of Statistics, 1979) and The Egyptian Fertility Survey 1980, Vols 1&#13;
through 4 (Cairo: Central Agency for Public Mbbilization and Statistics,&#13;
1983).&#13;
46. Robert Repetto, et al., Economic Development, Population Policy, and&#13;
Demographic Transition in the Republic of Korea. (Cambridge, Mass.:&#13;
Harvard University Press, 1981).&#13;
47. Cleland et al. cited in note 43, Table A2, p. 37.&#13;
48. George L. Harris, et al., Area Handbook for Nepal, Bhutan, and Sikkim.&#13;
(Washington, D.C.: U.S. Government Printing Office, 1973).&#13;
49. A clear difference in the pattern of women's work exists between Hindu&#13;
Indo-Aryan and Tibeto-Burman communities, with the extent of market&#13;
participation and short term labor migration by women much greater in the&#13;
latter than in the former. See Meena Acharya and Lynn Bennett, "Women and the&#13;
subsistence sector: Economic participation and household decision making in&#13;
Nepal", World Bank Staff Working Papers No. 526. (Washington, D.C.: The&#13;
World Bank, 1982).&#13;
50.  Fran Cleland et al., cited in note 43, Table Al, pp. 31-35.&#13;
51. For the reduced sample, the estimated equation with infant mortality&#13;
included is:&#13;
TFR = 4.9 + .024 BG + .008 IMR R2 = .57&#13;
(.007)    (.008)     F  = 13.0&#13;
52. Phillips Cutright, "Statistical models of interrelations between&#13;
socio-economic development and fertility in less developed areas". Paper&#13;
prepared for the Fertility Determinants Project, Indiana University,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-66-&#13;
Bloomirngtori, Indiana (1983). Fbr a recent analysis which has the same problems&#13;
see: Phillips Cutright, "The ingredients of recent fertility decline in&#13;
develcping countries". International Family Planning Perspectives 9,&#13;
no. 4 (DecEmber 1983): 101-109.&#13;
53. Barbara K. Larson, "The status of women in a Tunisian village: Limits to&#13;
autonomy, influence, and power", Signs 9: no. 3 (Sprirng 1984): 417-433.&#13;
54. Larson, cited in note 53, p. 424.&#13;
55. Larson, cited in note 53, p. 425.&#13;
56. Larson, cited in note 53, p. 425.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-67-&#13;
m             .r-  r-  C  0   0  a  a  O  O   q M&#13;
%.bJ&#13;
-4~~~~~~~~~~4~&#13;
(4  4           0~~~ *  +  +  +*  *+  +* *0  o &#13;
m  -4 e          . N  C  0  0  ' o  'o  f  0 t o&#13;
-4W  |             -4          U,  N  Cl S  b  N  ' Y0s@ b - &#13;
M  d     vv*+++*v++vvvv**n M v &#13;
X   ^'S~~~  I  |   Iz f.  I z  U; e;  U; t  wb@^ H &#13;
-- 4                                           3 i   t   f&#13;
2~~~~                 IV    Ln  M  _  N   v   v  W  &gt;4. &#13;
.!   !                         i  ' t j&#13;
I 3  a  1  3 X fl  :;1 T&#13;
.! l ia  x ~W W^  X n X0 . -e  -  X . ^  E''j' 't &#13;
i t 2k  &gt;0X-o^ t*** N  ^t^^I' J. aI §|i I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-68-&#13;
Appendix&#13;
Table A2: Means and Standard Deviations of Variables Used in&#13;
Regression Analysis&#13;
Standard&#13;
Mean                 Deviation&#13;
TFR(2)                           5.09                  1.50&#13;
Age Difference (01.)              .33                    .48&#13;
IMR                             84.2                   34.3&#13;
Log GNP Per Capita               6.53                   0.83&#13;
Me-dian Age at Marriage         18.9                    1.86&#13;
Female Secondary School&#13;
Enrollirent                    28.1                   18.3&#13;
AD * IM5'                       35.8                   54.4&#13;
AD * ILCXNP                      2.02                   2.95&#13;
AD * MUSM                        5.76                   8.40&#13;
AD * FE2DaDL                     5.19                   9.29&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
World      Bank                         value of these findings and provides     Demographic Aspects of&#13;
valuable msights mto possibiities for   Migration in West Africa-&#13;
Publications                            implementing mass programs for           K. C. Zachanah and others&#13;
needy people in villages throughout&#13;
of Related                               the world.                              Volume 1&#13;
Interest              Staff Working Paper No. 414. September&#13;
Interest                                                                1980 369 pages (including statistical an-&#13;
Volume 1: Integrated Nutrition          nexes, bibliography)&#13;
and Health Care                         Stock No WP 0414. 515&#13;
Amfried A. Kielmann and others&#13;
This volume provides detailed data       Volume 2&#13;
suggesting that synergism between       Staff Working Paper NVo 415. September&#13;
malnutntion and infection is probably   1980 391 pages (zncluding statistical an-&#13;
the greatest cause of mortality, mor-   nexes, bibliography).&#13;
bidity, and retarded growth and devel-  Stock No. WP 0415. 515.&#13;
The African Trypanosomiases:            opment in children. In an expenrient     (These Working Papers are background&#13;
Methods and Concepts of                 over a penod of four years, villagers    sThes forkig        We    acao&#13;
Control and Eradication in              received nutntion care, general health  studies for higrahton in West Afnica:&#13;
Relation to Development                  care to control infections, or both. Dra-  Demographic Aspects, described In this&#13;
C. W. Lee and J. M. Maurice             matic improvements, including a 40%-     secion.)&#13;
Here is a practical cost-benefit ap-    50% decline in mortality, a 20% reduc-   Economic Motivation versus&#13;
proach to an age-old problem affectng   creases in heightonmorlihY, and in-      City Lights: Testing&#13;
humans and livestock alike, the Afri-   tion, detailed information on costs is   Hypotheses about Inter-&#13;
can Trypanosomiases. Describes new      presented that permits the most com-     Changwat Migration in&#13;
techniques that offer tsetse control    plete analysis of cost-effectiveness and  Thailand&#13;
without destroying game animals.        program relevant costs and benefits      Fred Arnold and Susan H.&#13;
Also summanzes current research ir      yet avaLlable in this kind of field re-  Cohrause&#13;
genetic control, the use of traps and   search. The study focuses directly on&#13;
screens, attractants, and pheromones.   practical program implications and       Staff Working Paper No. 416. September&#13;
Technical Paper No. 4. 1983 107 pages.  ways in which such integrated services   1980. 41 pages (tncluding footnotes, refer-&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0191-8. Stock No. BK 0191.  can be applied under field conditions.  ences).&#13;
55                                       The Johns Hopkins University Press. 1984.  Stock No. WP 0416. 53&#13;
Analyzing the Impact of                 288 pages.                               Experiments in Family&#13;
Health Services: Pgoject                LC 82-23915. ISBN 0-8018-3064-8 Stock    Planning: Lessons from the&#13;
Experiences from India,                                                          Developing World&#13;
Ghana, and Thailand                                                              Roberto Cuca and Cathenne S.&#13;
Rashid Faruqee                           Volume IL Integrated Family             Pierce&#13;
Staff Worng Paper No 546. 1982. 44       Volume I. Integrated Family             A comprehensive review of experi-&#13;
Staffs Wokig apr o    46 182       ~     Planning and Health Care                mental efforts in the developing world&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0117-9. Stock No. WP 0546.   Carl E. Taylor and others               to determine more effective ways of&#13;
SB3                                      To vlllage people, politicians, and in-  providing fanmly planning services.&#13;
ternational health planners, health and  The Johns Hopkzns University Press, 1978.&#13;
familly planning have always seemed     276 pages (including bibliography, index of&#13;
NEW                                  to fit naturally together. But m the    experiments).&#13;
early 1960s, when international aware-  LC 77-16596. ISBN 0-8018-2013-8, Stock&#13;
Child and Matemal Health                 ness of the social and econonmc conse-  No. IH 2013, $19.50 hardcover; ISBN 0-&#13;
Services in India: The                   rquences of surging population growth   8018-2014-6, Stock No. IH 2014, $8.95&#13;
Services in India: The         moved family planning into a position   paerback.&#13;
Narangwal Experiment                     of high priority, some intemational&#13;
What can primary health care and         agencies began to advocate separation   Family Planning Programs: An&#13;
family planning do for women and         of family planmng from health serv-     Evaluation of Experience&#13;
children in the poor and deprived        ices. In mtemational policy discussions  Roberto Cuca&#13;
areas of the world? Some of the most     the question continues to be impor-&#13;
specific evidence available today to     tant. This volume analyzes this ques-   Staff Working Paper No 345. 1979. 146&#13;
support the benefits of these services   tion and provides arguments and evi-    pages (including 2 annexes, references).&#13;
is contained in these two studies,       dence to support integration of health  Stock No. WP 0345. S5.&#13;
which represent the findings of re-      care and family planning; it outlines&#13;
search carried out durng 1967-74 m       the purposes underlying the research    Fertility and Education: What&#13;
twenty-sLx villages in Punjab, India.    in this area; and it proposes policy    Do We Really Know?&#13;
Members of the research staff, which     questions regarding the effectiveness,  Susan H. Cochrane&#13;
started with 15 people and grew to       efficiency, and equity of such an inte-  A model identifying the many chan-&#13;
about 150 by the end of the project,     gration.                                 nels through which education might&#13;
spent many years working with, and       The Johns Hopkins University Press. 1984.&#13;
sharing the lives of, villagers. The     256 pages.&#13;
depth of understanding that came         LC 83-23915. ISBN 0-8018-2830-9 Stock    Prices subject to change without notice&#13;
from this type of sharng enhances the    No. [H 2830. 522.50.                     and may vary by country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
act to determine tertlitv and a review   Health Issues and Policies in           Kenya: Population and&#13;
of the evidence ot the relation between  the Developing Countries                Development&#13;
education and the intervening vana-      Fredrick Golladav                       (See descnpton under Countrv&#13;
bles in the model that affect fertlitv.iy        o   aa&#13;
The Johns Hopkins Lnzversity Press, 1979  Statf Workgng Paper No 422. 1980 55    Studies listng.)&#13;
238 pages (including bibliographi, index)  pages&#13;
LC 78-26070 ISBN 0-8018-2140-1, Stock    Stock No WP 0412 3&#13;
No JH 2140, 56.95 paverbcick             Health, Nutrition, and Family            Migration in West Africa:&#13;
Planning in India: A Survey of           Demographic Aspects&#13;
.. .. Experiments and Special     .       . K. C. Zachanah and Julien Conde&#13;
Fertility and Its Regulation in          Projects                                 The tirst study of the large-scale move-&#13;
Bangladesh                               Rashid Faruqee and Ethna Johnson         ment of people in nine West Afncan&#13;
R Anmun and Rashid Faruqee                        auean          njnsn            countries Discusses the volume and&#13;
Staff Working Paper No 507 1982 108      directon of internal and extemal flows&#13;
Staff Working Paper No 383 1980 54       pages (including references)             and the economic and socal character-&#13;
pages (including references)              Stock No WP 0507 55                     istics of migrants.&#13;
Stock No WP 0383 53                                                               A joint World Bank-OECD study. Oxford&#13;
Infant and Child Mortality as a          University Press, 1981 166 pages (includ-&#13;
Determinant of Fertility: The            ing 22 maps, bibliography, index).&#13;
Health                                   Policy Implications                      LC 80-21352 ISBN 0-19-520186-8, Stock&#13;
Fredrick Golladay, coordinating          Susan Hill Cochrane and K. C.            No OX 520186, SZ9 95 hardcover, ISBN&#13;
author                                   Zachanah                                 0-19-520187-6. Stock No OX 520187,&#13;
Draws on expenence gaimed from           An illustratve analvsis that suggests    58 95 paperback&#13;
health components of seventv World       mfant mortality mav be an important&#13;
Bank projects in forty-four countries    component of a fertility reducton pro-&#13;
between 1975 and 1978 Emphasizes         gram in countries where mortality isl                  and Fml&#13;
the disproportionately high expendi-     high and few couples are able to have    Populanion and Famdly&#13;
tures incurred on curative medicne,      the number of surviving children they    Planning in Bangladesh: A&#13;
maintenance of expensive hospitals,      desire.                                  Study of the Research&#13;
and sophisicated tramng of medical       World Bank Staff Working Paper No 556    Mohammad Alauddin and Rashid&#13;
personnel at the cost of preventive      19° 44     es                            Faruqee&#13;
care for the majontv of the people.      1.      pag                              F&#13;
Points out that low-cost health care     ISBN 0-8213-0147-0. Stock No WP 0556     Reviews major studies on familv plan-&#13;
svstems are feasible and recommends      53                                       ning and on fertility trends, profiles,&#13;
that the Bank begn reguwar and direct&#13;
lending for health, in addciton to hav-  Integrating Family Planning              such studies and cntques their meth-&#13;
ing health components as part of pro-    with Health Services: Does It            odology and apphcation. Underscores&#13;
)ects in other sectors  Help?                               ~~~~~~~~need for continued study and suggests&#13;
jects in other sectors                   Help?                                    directions for future research to im-&#13;
Secto7 Policy Paper 1980 90 pages (in-   Rashid Faruqee                           prove the Bangladesh population&#13;
chiding 8 annexes, 4 figures, map)       Staff Working Paper No 515. 1982 47      problem.&#13;
Stock Nos BK 9066 (Arabic), BK 9067     pages                                     World Bank Staff Working Paper No 557&#13;
(English), BK 9068 (French), BK 9069     ISBN 0-8213-0003-2. Stock No WP 0515      1983 176 pages&#13;
(Spanish) 55                             5                                        I3 ISBN 0-8223-0150-0 Stock No WP 0557&#13;
55&#13;
rG I IIVisit the World Bank&#13;
st \e          whn yBookstore                Population and Poverty in the&#13;
K Street               when you are in                 Developing World&#13;
Washington, D.C.                Nancy Birdsall&#13;
D        I                 L     J I-II    Li                                      Staff Workzng Paper No 404 1980 96&#13;
I Street   7                                          pages (including 2 appendixes, bibliog-&#13;
tn            Y f tn {         { en {  \   7         graphy)&#13;
=  .2   \  \Stock No WP 0404. 53&#13;
H Street&#13;
H Street                                     Lafayette Square           Population Policy and Family&#13;
I                         |                  &lt;"Q&gt; Planning Programs: Trends in&#13;
Avenue                                          Policy and Administration&#13;
Kandiah Kanagaratnam and&#13;
I I                  White House           ~~~~~~~~~Staff Working Paper No. 447. 1981. 80&#13;
[   ~     Ipages (including bibliography, appendixes)&#13;
World Bank Bookstore                                                          Stock No. WP 0447. 53.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
N VEW                                     published as World Population Pro;ec-     falling mortalitv, and urbanization-&#13;
tions Short- and Long-term Projections bv  factors that tend to lower fernlitv else-&#13;
Short-term   Population                   Age and Sex tor AUl Countries, with Re-   where Calls for a viable population&#13;
Projection, 1980-2020 and Long-           lated Demographic Statistics              policy and programs appropriate to&#13;
term  Projection, 2000 to                 1983 391 pages                            the culture&#13;
Stationary Stage by Age and               ISBN 0-8213-0355-4 530 paperback          Statf Working Paper .\No 559 1983 'l6&#13;
Sex for All Countries of the                                                        pa ges&#13;
World                                          VEW                                  ISBN 0-8213-0152-7 Stock Nos WP&#13;
NIv T Vu, under the supervision           Rapid Population Growth in&#13;
of K. C. Zachanah                         Sub-Saharan Africa: Issues and&#13;
This report gives detailed population          cRegional Aspects of Family&#13;
prolections bv age and sex for each        olicies                                  Planning and Fertility Behavior&#13;
countrv at yve-vear intervals from 1980   Rashid Faruqee and Ravi Gulhati           in Indonesia&#13;
to 2020 and at twentv-five vear inter-    No other country has higher fertilitv     Do   Che     s       a    e&#13;
vals trom 2000 to the vear in which       than Kenya and its neighboring coun-      'vIeesook&#13;
population becomes stationarv in each     tnes in Sub-Saharan Atnca This&#13;
country The implied fertllty and mor-    Working Paper examines the reasons        Statf Working Paper No 462. 1981 62&#13;
talltv measures are also given Revised    for fertilitv rates staying high, even    pages (including appendix, rererences)&#13;
annuallv. The 1984 edition will be        nsing in the face of greater education,   Stock No WP 0462 53&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Publications Order Form&#13;
SEND TO: YOUR LOCAL DISTRIBUTOR OR TO WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
(See the other side otl /his tlortn       P.O. BOX 37525&#13;
WASHINGTON, D C. 20013 U S.A&#13;
Date&#13;
Name                                                 Ship to: (Enter if different from purchaser)&#13;
Title                                                Name _&#13;
Firm                                                 Title&#13;
Address                                              Firm&#13;
City               State_      Postal Code           Address_&#13;
Country            e'Iephone (      I                City _     _       State_    Postal Code_&#13;
Purchaser Reference No.                  .           Country              Telephone&#13;
Check your method of payment&#13;
Enclosed is my a Check a International Money Order a Unesco Coupons O International Postal Coupon.&#13;
Make payable to World Bank Publications for U S. dollars unless you are ordering from your local distributor&#13;
Charge my D VISA g MasterCard W Amencan Express Z Choice. (Credit cards accepted only for orders addressed&#13;
to World Bank Publications )&#13;
Credit Card Account Number            Expiration Date                     Signature&#13;
LInvoice me and please reference my Purchase Order No.&#13;
Please ship me the items listed below.&#13;
Customer internal&#13;
Stock Number  Author/ Title                                       Routing Code  Quantity  Unit Price  Total Amount S&#13;
All prices subject to change  Prices may vary by country.  Allow 6-8 weeks for delivery&#13;
Subtotal Cost  $_&#13;
Total copies       Air mail surcharge if desired ($2 00 each)  $_&#13;
Postage and handling for more than two complimentary items ($2 00 each)  S  -_&#13;
Total   $&#13;
IBRD0053                                                           Thank you for your order.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Distributor-s oil World                  \ttn Mlr G,iar,arlo Bi4azzi             Attn Mr J %I Hernandez&#13;
I a amarmo- i45                        Castello 37&#13;
Bank Publicatitons                       ;0 121                                  Madrid&#13;
ARGENTINA                                1-l,rencu                               SRI LANKA AND THE MALDIVES&#13;
L,iHOo, Hir-k h SRL                      JAPAN                                   Lake House Bookshop&#13;
*\ttn \b MIonica Bu11t,i                 Eastern Book S,ervice                   Attn Mr \ icor '.5atatara&#13;
Florida lb; 4 ps                         Attn Mr Teru-nasa Hirano                41 tAad Ramanaxake MIassatha&#13;
Galeria Guerne-,                         37-3, Hcngo 3 Chome Bunks Lu-ku 113     Colombo 2&#13;
Buenos Amris 13k 7                       Tokxo                                   SWEDEN&#13;
AUSTRALIA, PAPL A NELvS GLINEA,          KENYA                                   ABCE Forizs Kungl Hcosbokhandel&#13;
FIJI, SOLOMON ISLANDS,Attrica Book St-\ ice, I E A     L -td           Attn, Sr Eide SegerbaLk&#13;
Fii.SOLONSMOA,ISANDS                     A tn\P  51 B Dar                        Regering,gatan 12 Box 1t6356&#13;
WESNUTER  SAO,P 0 Bos 4524;                                                      S-IO,3  ~ LStOLkholmu&#13;
Fhe Australian Fmioi, al .5t \ eNairobi                                          SWITZERLAND&#13;
Inturmatior' SUr\1kL Al\FI'              KOREA, REPUBLIC OF                      Librairie Paxot&#13;
Attn Mxr DJa idi farnie,o                Pan Korea Book Corporation              Attn Mr Henri de P'errot&#13;
23;-243 lones ~'treut                    Attn Sir N oon-Sun K(imn                h rue Grenus&#13;
Broad\sas                                P 0  Box\ 11I K%sangh%\amun             1211 Gene%a&#13;
Ssdnes \SliN 20031                       Leoul                                   TANZANIA&#13;
BELGIUMI                                 MALAY SIA                               Oxtord Lnixersit% Press&#13;
Publications des \at.ons Lnies,          Lnisersits ot 'slalaxa Cooperatise      Attn Mxr Anthons Theoboid&#13;
A,tn Mxr lean de: Linno\                Sookshop Ltd                             \Iaktaba Road, P 0 Box 5299&#13;
ax Lio Rci 202                           Attn Mr Mohammed Fahim litj             Oar e, Salaam&#13;
I3bt) Brus-els                          Yacob                                    THAILAND&#13;
CANADA                        ~~~~~~~~~~P 0 Box 1127 Jalan Pantai Baru  Central Department Store, Head Oftice&#13;
CANADituAu                               Kuala Lumpur                            Attn Mrs Ratana&#13;
Attn MIr, n,u,ann, \ ermoette           MEXICO                                   306 Silom Road&#13;
C P 85 6ou~herxiL~e 1413 SF6             l`\F0-Tl:C                               Bangkok&#13;
Quebec                                   Attn MIr forgo C-epeda                  Thailard Management Association&#13;
COSTA RICA                    S~~~~~~~~Lan Lorenco) 153-Il Coi dielValle,  Attn Mrs Sunan&#13;
CrOriA tRICoA                           DeLeJV  Ben;to jluarez                  308 Silomn Road&#13;
AttneiL SIr Hu0o Chmelan3100 Mcxico D F                                          Bangxo&#13;
Calle 11-13 A.\s Fe nandeL Guell         MIIDDLE EAST                            TUNISIA&#13;
San Jose'                                Siddlc Fast \IarketinL~ Research        So0iOtj Tunisienne die Ditfusion&#13;
Buireau                                  Attn Sir SlaheLddine Ben Hamida&#13;
DENMIARK                                 A'ttn SxIr CCe ree S asiou              ; As enue de Carthage&#13;
§~antundshitteratur                      \Iitsis Bldg 1                           Tunis&#13;
-Stn Mr 55 ltrned Rctoit                 Silakario, tii \s enue&#13;
Rosenderns Alle 1 1                      \Nw-1a                                  TURKEY&#13;
DK-1970 Copenhage-n                      C\ pro-                                 Haset Kita pe  A S&#13;
EGYPT, Arab Repilblic of                 Ban     t~i      ari,Ge,                 Attn Mr Izze  zee&#13;
Al Ahram                                \loroo.o Kuisait L nited Arab            4(6'S Itiklal Caddesi&#13;
Al Galaa Street                          Lmnirates Jorlani                       Bexoglu-Istanbul&#13;
Cairo                                    NETHERLANDS                             UNITED KINGDOM AND&#13;
SIBE B'.                                 NORTHERN IRELAND&#13;
FINLAND                                  Attn Mr Gerhard van Bussell             Mucrointo Ltd&#13;
AkateeminenKinalkauppa\0order-Nsal IS                                  Attn Mr Rov- Selwvn&#13;
Akteeminenar LKrakauper                 '241 BI Lochem                           Ness man Lane, P 0 Box 3&#13;
Ke,kuskatu I SF-0i1J30                   NORWAY                                  Alton, Hampshire GU34 2PG&#13;
H-elsinki 1LI                           Johan Grundt TanuIm A S                  England&#13;
FRANCE                                   Attn Sis Randi Nslikketborg             UNITED STATES&#13;
\S,ortdl Bank PUbIlsaton1,               P 0 Box 1177 Sentrum                    The SNorld Bank Book Store&#13;
b6, axsenue d lena                       Oslo 1                                  600 19th Street, N W&#13;
:;IlIt Pan:s                            PANAMA                                   Psashington, D C 20433&#13;
GERMANY, Federal Republic of             Ediciones Libreria Cultural I'anamena   (Postal address P 0 Box 37525&#13;
L\CI-Serlag                              Attn \ir Luis Fernandez Fraguela R      SSashington D C 20013, U S A &#13;
Attn Mr joachium Kraust                 As    Esyanna 16                         Baker and TaN (or Company&#13;
Simroekstrase 23              ~~~~~~Panama Loe I                       501 South Gladiola Avenue&#13;
D-;300 Bonn I                            PHILIPPINES                             Momence, Illinois, 60954&#13;
HONG KONG, MvACAU                        National Boo(k Store                    380 Edison iAav&#13;
Asia 2000 Ltd                           Attn MIrs Socorro C Ramos                Reno, \esada, 89564&#13;
Attn Ms Gretchern '.5earing Smith       701 Rizal As enue           ~0 Kirbv As enue&#13;
, Fl 146, Prince ELIssard: Roadi         Manil.a                                 Somers ille, New Jersey, 08876&#13;
Koss loon                                PORTUIGAL                               Commerce Georgia 30599&#13;
INDIA                                    Li\ raria Portugal&#13;
L BS Publishers Distributors Ltd         Attn MIr Antonio Alkes Martins          Bernan Associates&#13;
RLia DL) Carmo 70-74          9730-F George Palmer Highwav&#13;
Attn Sir D P S,ter                      Ru    oCro7-4Lanham, Maryland, 20761&#13;
\S"Ansari Rod,I'xtBo 71                  I isho,n                                Blackwell North America, Inc&#13;
Brness Delhi,e 113m032an,0r                                                      1001 Fries NMill Road&#13;
Branch oltks in Bomba  Bangalore SAUDI ARABIA                          Blackxsoodi New fersev 08012&#13;
Kanpur C,alcutta and Mvadrast           larir Book Store&#13;
INDONESIA                     ~~~~~Attn Mr AKramA-gi                   Sidnes Kramer Books&#13;
Pt Indira LirnuteLl                      P 0 Box 31%4                             72RSre        &#13;
Attn SIr Bamnbang SS,ahs udi             Rixadn                                  liashington. D C 20006&#13;
]I Dr ~arn Ratulan4i \,, 37              SINGAPORE, TAIWAN, BURMA                Lnited Nations Bookshop&#13;
Jakarta Pusat                            Informnation Publications Private Ltd   Lnited Nations Plaza&#13;
IRELAND                                 Attn Ms Janet David                      Nesw York, N Y 10017&#13;
TDC Publishers                          02-116 1st Floor, Pet-Eu Industrial      VENEZUELA&#13;
Attn Mxr James 3ooth                      Building&#13;
12 North Fredericx Str,et               24 Ness Incastrial Road                  Libreria diel Este&#13;
Dublin I                                Singapore                                Attn Mr Juan Pericas&#13;
Asda Francisco de MAiranda, no 52&#13;
ITALY                                   SPAIN                                    Editict) Gait pan, Aptdo 60 337&#13;
I to-aorn nii-i naria 's.nunson SPA     Mtundi-Prensa Libros. 5 A                Caracas 1060-A&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG 3881.5 .W57 W67 no.682&#13;
c.3&#13;
Cain, Mead.&#13;
Women's status and fertility&#13;
in cl,An-n1 ni na coulntries&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                        European Office              Tokyo Office                          U&#13;
1818 H Street, N W                  66, avenue d'1ena            Kokusai Building&#13;
Washington, D C 20433, USA          75116 Paris, France           1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone (202) 477-1234            Telephone (1) 723-54 21      Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Felex WUI 64145 WORLD)BANK          Telex 842-620628             Telephone (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                         Telex 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHING TONDC&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0446-1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554772">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/11/1554772/womens-status-fertility-developing-countries-son-preference-economic-security
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/11/1554772/womens-status-fertility-developing-countries-son-preference-economic-security</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1984/11/1554772/womens-status-fertility-developing-countries-son-preference-economic-security</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/06/14/000178830_98101903424545/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/06/14/000178830_98101903424545/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-06-14T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1984-11-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Women's status and fertility in
            developing countries : son preference and economic security
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The relationship between women's
            status, which is defined in terms of the degree to which
            they are economically dependent on men, and fertility in
            developing countries is examined. The paper adopts a
            particular theoretical perspective regarding fertility
            determinants and explores the implications of women's
            status within that context. This perspectives gives special
            attention to the value of children as security assets in
            settings where public welfare assistance is minimal or
            non-existent and financial and insurance markets are poorly
            developed. In this context, women's economic status,
            and the institutional factors that create a degree of
            dependence, determine the relevance of sex of children in
            defining security goals. High dependence results is defining
            security goals in terms of surviving sons. Given similar
            security needs, and other things being equal, fertility will
            be considerably higher in settings where there is a strong
            preference for sons than in settings where son preference is
            weak. A cross-national empirical analysis is presented that
            supports this argument.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Women's status and fertility in
            developing countries : son preference and economic security
        </docna>
        <display_title>Women's status and fertility
            in developing countries : son preference and economic security</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1984/11/1554772/womens-status-fertility-developing-countries-son-preference-economic-security</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Population &amp; Development,Gender and Social Development,Primary Education,Anthropology</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Gender</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Cain, M.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903424545</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Primary health, including
            reproductive health, child health and health</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 682</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Gender</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Health, Nutrition &amp; Population</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0446-1</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Women; Economic status; Fertility;
            Dependency burden; Cross country analysis; Fertility rate;
            Boys; Economic security
            aging,autonomy,birth control,child
            rearing,child survival,choice of partner,daily life,decision
            making,dependence,disasters,divorce,elderly,employment,endogamy,exogamy,families,family
            planning,Family size,feelings,female sexuality,femme,food
            preparation,gender,health
            care,households,infertility,innovation,kinship,literacy,males,migration,mortality,norms,nuclear
            families,old age,parents,parity,Population Studies,property
            rights,quality of life,reproduction,safety,Sex,sexuality,societies,society,spouses,sterilization,villages,widows
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP682</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technological Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>IMR</ml:concept><ml:concept>Maternal and Child Mortality</ml:concept><ml:concept>U5MR</ml:concept><ml:concept>Birth Spacing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Employment and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Improving Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Market Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets, Job Creation and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technology Transfer and Diffusion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infant and Child Mortality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Family Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Elderly</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Child Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>