<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP737&#13;
Sustaining World Economic Recovery&#13;
laE C O pyThe Challenges Ahead&#13;
FILE  COPY  Jean Baneth&#13;
Enzo Grilli&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 737&#13;
4FILE COPY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS                      ,W7&#13;
Number 737&#13;
Sustaining World Economic Recovery&#13;
The Challenges Ahead&#13;
Jean Baneth&#13;
Enzo Grilli&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright (C 1985&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing May 1985&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To present the&#13;
results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been prepared&#13;
in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed texts, and the World&#13;
Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a token charge&#13;
to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The World Bank does not accept responsibility for the views expressed herein, which&#13;
are those of the authors and should not be attributed to the World Bank or to its&#13;
affiliated organizations. The findings, interpretations, and conclusions are the results&#13;
of research supported by the Bank; they do not necessarily represent official policy of&#13;
the Bank. The designations employed, the presentation of material, and any maps used&#13;
in this document are solely for the convenience of the reader and do not imply the&#13;
expression of any opinion whatsoever on the part of the World Bank or its affiliates&#13;
concerning the legal status of any country. territory, city, area, or of its authorities, or&#13;
concerning the delimitation of its boundaries, or national affiliation.&#13;
The most recent World Bank publications are described in the annual spring and fall&#13;
lists; the continuing research program is described in the annual Abstracts of Current&#13;
Studies. The latest edition of each is available free of charge from the Publications Sales&#13;
Unit, Department T, The World Bank, 1818 H Street, N.W., Washington, D.C. 20433,&#13;
U.S.A., or from the European Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'lena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Jean Baneth is director of the Economic Analysis and Projections Department of the&#13;
World Bank; Enzo Grilli is an assistant director.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Baneth, Jean, 1936-&#13;
Sustaining world economic recovery.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 737)&#13;
1. Developing countries--Economic conditions.&#13;
2. International economic relations. 3. Economic&#13;
history--1971-         .   I. Grilli, Enzo R.      II. Title.&#13;
III. Series.&#13;
HC59.7.B327     1985        338.9'009172'4          85-9529&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0546-8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ABSTRACT&#13;
The paper analyzes the characteristics of the 1983-84 world economic&#13;
recovery and its effects on developing countries adjustment. It looks at the&#13;
conditions for medium-term non-inflationary growth in the world economy and at&#13;
the changes in policies necessary to cope with and redress over, time the real&#13;
and financial   imbalances that threaten the sustainability of the current&#13;
recovery.   It presents a scenario for medium-term growth,      resulting from&#13;
moderate policy changes in industrial countr-ies, within which-the room for&#13;
growth and continued policy adjustment in developing countries is' examined in&#13;
some detail.    The risks of failure inherent in a continuation -of present&#13;
policy trends are also examined.&#13;
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS&#13;
This paper draws extensively on work done in the Global Analysis &amp;&#13;
Projections Division of EPD.     In addition, Messrs. Peter Miovic, Christian&#13;
Moran, Paul Armington, Denis Richard and Charles Larkum contributed in various&#13;
ways to the preparation of this paper. Their help is gratefully acknowledged.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
RESUME&#13;
Cette note analyse les characteristiques de la reprise&#13;
economique mondiale en 1983-84, et ses effets sur l'ajustement des&#13;
pays en developpement. Elle examine les conditions d'une croissance&#13;
a moyen terme dans la stabilite des prix, et les modifications qu'il&#13;
faut apporter aux politiques economiques afin de corriger les&#13;
desequilibres, financiers et reels, qui risquent de compromettre la&#13;
poursuite de la reprise actuelle. Elle presente un scenario de&#13;
croissance a moyen terme qui serait le resultat d'adaptations modestes&#13;
des politiques economiques des pays industriels, et elle examine&#13;
l'impact de ce scenario sur la croissance economique des pays en&#13;
developpement, et sur leur capacite a mener a bien des politiques&#13;
d'ajustement. Finalement, la note examine aussi les risques que&#13;
presenterait une continuation des politiques actuelles.&#13;
REMERCIEMENTS&#13;
Cette note est en grande partie basee sur le travail de la&#13;
Division d'Analyse et Projections Globales du Departement d'Analyses&#13;
et de Projections Economiques. De plus, Messieurs Peter Miovic,&#13;
Christian Moran, Paul Armington, Denis Richard et Charles Larkum ont&#13;
beaucoup contribue a sa preparation. Les remercient vivement de leur&#13;
aide.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
RESUMEN&#13;
El trabajo analiza las caracterfsticas de la recuperacio'n&#13;
economica mundial de los anios 1983-84 y sus efectos en el ajuste de los&#13;
pafses  en  vias  de  desarrollo.     Describe  las  condiciones  para  un&#13;
crecimiento no-inflacionario a mediano plazo en la economfa mundial, y&#13;
los cambios en las polfticas necesarios para enfrentar y revertir los&#13;
desequilibrios reales y financieros que amenazan el sostenimiento de la&#13;
recuperaci6n actual.   Presenta un escenario a mediano plazo que supone&#13;
un   ajuste  moderado   en  las   polfticas  econo'micas  de   los  palses&#13;
industrializados, y que sirve para examinar en detalle las posibilidades&#13;
de crecimiento y ajuste en las poifticas de los pafses en desarollo.&#13;
Los riesgos inherentes a una continuacion de las polfticas econo'micas&#13;
actuales son tambien examinados.&#13;
AGREDECIMIENTOS&#13;
Este estudio descansa en gran parte en el trabajo efectuado en&#13;
la Division de Analisis Global y Proyeciones del Banco Mundial.        Los&#13;
seniores Peter Miovic, Cristian Moran, Paul Armington, Denis Richard y&#13;
Charles Larkum contribuyeron en variadas formar a la preparacio'n de este&#13;
trabajo. Agradezco enormemente la colaboracion que ellos prestaron.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Page No.&#13;
SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS     ............................................        ix&#13;
I.  INTRODUCTION    .................................................          1&#13;
II. THE ENVIRONMENT FOR THE DEVELOPING COUNTRIES: ECONOMIC&#13;
RECOVERY IN THE INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES, 1983-84       ..............       3&#13;
III.   FINANCIAL ADJUSTMENT IN DEVELOPING COUNTRIES: 1982-84       ...   .....  11&#13;
IV. THE CHALLENGES AHEAD: TRANSITION TOWARDS SUSTAINABLE LONG-&#13;
TERM GROWTH    ................................................         28&#13;
V. MEDIUM TERM ALTERNATIVES FOR INDUSTRIAL AND DEVELOPING&#13;
COUNTRIES ........                                                      34&#13;
A. A Medium-Term Scenario with Moderate Policy&#13;
Adjustments:    1985-90   ............................       36&#13;
A.1.   The Industrial Countries     ....    ..........  36&#13;
A.2.   The Developing Countries     ....    ..........  43&#13;
B. The Risks of Non-Adjustment and the Effects on&#13;
Developing Countries    .............................        55&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS&#13;
i.       The world economy is now in a revival phase.    In 1981-82 it suffered&#13;
its deepest and most widespread recession in half a century, and in 1982-83&#13;
the debt servicing problems of many developing countries imposed strains on&#13;
the international financial system that at times threatened it with breakdown.&#13;
ii.      Real output increased by 2.6 percent in 1983 and by an estimated 4.2&#13;
percent in 1984. World trade has also recovered strongly. After declining in&#13;
both volume and value terms in 1982 and showing only a modest volume increase&#13;
in 1983, world exports are estimated to have grown by between 8 and 9 percent&#13;
in 1984.   Despite the pace of this recovery, inflation in the industrialized&#13;
countries has continued to moderate.    In 1984, expressed in terms of the GDP&#13;
deflator, it fell to its lowest level since the late 1960s, and a further&#13;
modest improvement is anticipated for 1985.&#13;
iii.     This  performance   shows  important  gains  from  the policy changes&#13;
adopted by industrialized countries in response to the 1979-80 oil price&#13;
shock, when aggregate demand was adjusted downwards (in contrast to the demand&#13;
supporting policies widely pursued after the 1973-74 oil shock) and monetary&#13;
policies were tightened.     It has also provided a vital respite for debtor&#13;
countries facing the need both to allocate a higher proportion of foreign&#13;
exchange earnings to debt service and to shift resources within their&#13;
economies to more productive sectors.    The recovery in world trade, strongly&#13;
fuelled by US import demand, has encouraged exports, enabling adjustment--&#13;
- ix -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
especially for the major Latin American debtor countries--to be undertaken in&#13;
an environment of positive economic growth. Internal policies, however, were&#13;
critical to the progress made by developing countries in financial adjustment&#13;
during the 1982-84 period.&#13;
iv.      Progress in recovering from the economic and financial difficulties&#13;
of the years immediately following the second oil shock has thus been&#13;
tangible.  Important imbalances and disequilibrium persist, however.    This is&#13;
true of the progress in adjustment made by different groups of debtor&#13;
countries and of the economic stances of the developed countries. It is also&#13;
true of real interest rates, exchange rates, and, very importantly, of&#13;
attitudes towards trade and the reviving tendency of protectionism. Given the&#13;
scale of the problems that developed in the 1970s--quantitatively reflected in&#13;
such variables as the size of developing countries' debts and their debt&#13;
ratios, and the current account imbalances of key industrial countries--these&#13;
disequilibria will need to be addressed and progressively corrected over a&#13;
period of years for real stability to return as an inherent property of the&#13;
world economy.&#13;
v.       For both developed and developing economies the necessary changes&#13;
will be more easily effected against a background of steady, reliable and&#13;
strong  overall  output  growth.    Indeed, without   such a background it is&#13;
questionable whether rigidities in the developed economies could be&#13;
successfully removed, and whether--in circumstances of continuing high real&#13;
interest rates and uncertain access to export markets--developing countries&#13;
could maintain the momentum of adjustment needed to sustain creditor&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
confidence and, avoid a recurrence of widespread financial disruption.      For&#13;
both groups of countries a failure of growth would involve high, social and&#13;
political, as well.-as economic, costs.&#13;
vi.      This paper examines the issues involved in moving from the present&#13;
recovery phase in the economic cycle to a sustainable level of world output&#13;
growth adequate to permit a workable resolution of the problem of present debt&#13;
levels carried by the developing countries.&#13;
vii.     Three factors precipitated the debt and-payments   crisis-of the early&#13;
1980s:   the deterioration in the debtors   terms of trade, the sharp rise in&#13;
interest rates, and the weakness in export demand that resulted from recession&#13;
in the- industrialized countries.    These undermined the basis on "which the&#13;
rapid growth of lending had previously been undertaken--namely, the relative&#13;
stability of debtor countries    debt servicing ratios through the 1970s--and&#13;
precipitated a sudden loss of confidence by creditors.&#13;
viii.    Underlying   these  visible   causes  were  other,   more  fundamental&#13;
factors.   Borrowing had been used by many countries to sustain policies that&#13;
delayed necessary adjustment and allocated investment inefficiently. Exchange&#13;
rates were -left to go out of balance reducing price competitiveness in export&#13;
markets that had become less assured because of growing -trade protectionism.,&#13;
ix.      Both  for  internal  and  external   reasons,  therefore,  all  debtor&#13;
countries faced the need to reduce domestic consumption relative to output and&#13;
to achieve a new balance of resource allocation in their economies through&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
appropriate policy change.    As the paper shows, the need for adjustment, in&#13;
nature and scale, was different in different groups of countries, and&#13;
structural flexibilities and policy capabilities were also different across&#13;
countries.    Some countries,   by timely action and as a result of long-&#13;
established patterns in the orientation of their economies, avoided the need&#13;
to reschedule their debts, thereby retaining some flexibility in their access&#13;
to external finance. Others responded early and vigorously and have achieved&#13;
substantial progress in adjusting their external payments position.       Others&#13;
have scarcely begun the process. While still others, mainly among sub-Saharan&#13;
African countries, appear to have little prospect of restoring growth through&#13;
adjustment without considerable further financial assistance on concessional&#13;
terms.&#13;
x.       Even among those major debtors, however, whose progress in improving&#13;
their payments position has been of vital importance in reducing financial&#13;
tensions, the balance and durability of adjustment so far achieved leave room&#13;
for  uncertainties.    Investment  has  borne   the brunt   of  domestic  demand&#13;
compression, falling by 40 percent between 1981 and 1983 in the four major&#13;
Latin American oil importing debtor countries.     While the tempo of domestic&#13;
policy reform needs to be maintained and, for many debtor countries,&#13;
quickened, the emphasis must shift towards patterns sustainable in the longer-&#13;
term.&#13;
xi.      The external environment in which this shift is undertaken is likely&#13;
to be crucial to its outcome. In this regard the role of economic policies in&#13;
the developed and developing economies is both critical and clear. Industrial&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
countries policies will largely determine the level of real interest rates,&#13;
the freedom of world    trade movements and,    through the aggregate current&#13;
account position maintained by the developed countries, the levels of&#13;
financing  available  to  the developing   countries.    Developing   countries&#13;
policies  will  determine   to  a  significant  extent  where  better   external&#13;
conditions are translated into domestic growth.&#13;
xii.     The paper focuses on the changes in policies that industrialized&#13;
countries will need to implement over the period 1985-90 in order to establish&#13;
the basis for sustainable growth in the world economy after 1990 and on the&#13;
scope that this will leave to developing countries trade, finance and&#13;
growth.    The necessary adjustments to policy are moderate and should be&#13;
implemented gradually, but they cannot be long delayed.    A key component is a&#13;
change in the current fiscal stance of the United States and a corresponding&#13;
realignment of US monetary policy, together with a sympathetic untightening of&#13;
monetary conditions in Europe and a reduction of the degree of restrictiveness&#13;
of fiscal policies in those countries where room for manouver exists from the&#13;
standpoint of inflation. Japan also falls in this category of countries.&#13;
xiii.    The remainder of this decade could be either a period of transition&#13;
to renewed worldwide economic growth in a reasonably stable price environment,&#13;
or one of disorder and decline.      This sombre scenario is easy to imagine.&#13;
Continued budget deficits in the United States at the level now assumed by the&#13;
Congressional Budget Office in case no policy is initiated to contain them,&#13;
would feed a continued and growing current account deficit. This would become&#13;
increasingly difficult to finance, putting upward pressure on interest&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
rates.   In such an environment, a growing trade deficit in the U.S. and&#13;
continued slow growth in Europe would feed pressures which would easily lead&#13;
to increased trade protectionism.    Growth in the industrial countries would&#13;
falter and reach an average of only 2.5 percent for the rest of the decade.&#13;
Exports of the developing countries would suffer both from a slow growth of&#13;
overall demand and protectionism, and would grow only at a rate of perhaps 3&#13;
percent.   Overall GNP growth in developing countries would amount to only&#13;
about 4 percent; only about 3 percent excluding India and China whose relative&#13;
inward orientation and low debt would, for a time, somewhat protect them from&#13;
the implications of this scenario.    Taking into account the decline in their&#13;
terms of trade, most developing countries would face stagnating or declining&#13;
per capita incomes.&#13;
xiv.     But this picture might be overoptimistic.      The financing crisis of&#13;
U.S. deficits might emerge suddenly and precipitate a sharp recession with&#13;
growth much below the average for a year or two.        This would have obvious&#13;
implications for the developing countries' debt servicing ability. Even under&#13;
the scenario depicted above, the developing countries would have to generate&#13;
continuous large trade surpluses to service their debt, under conditions of&#13;
slow  growth.    Industrial  countries would have    to be willing    to accept&#13;
corresponding trade deficits despite their unemployment.      Commercial banks,&#13;
through involuntary lending or rescheduling would have to continue slowly&#13;
increasing their exposure in developing countries, despite the latters&#13;
impaired prospects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
xv.      However, this scenario is not unavoidable.       Timely, moderate, but&#13;
credible reduction in U.S. fiscal deficits could still bring about a much&#13;
better outcome.    The US dollar could decline gradually, and allow gradual&#13;
decline  in real dollar interest     rates.    If this is accompanied by some&#13;
relaxation of financial policies in other industrial countries (mostly&#13;
monetary in Europe, largely fiscal in Japan), and by adequate wage and other&#13;
factor cost restraints, industrial countries could grow at a rate of 3 percent&#13;
for the remainder of the decade and somewhat faster thereafter. Protectionism&#13;
could then be more easily contained and developing countries exports grow at a&#13;
rate of about 5 percent.    Middle-income developing countries would then have&#13;
an environment which could allow them to rebuild their debt service capacity&#13;
and commercial banks gradually return towards modest, voluntary lending to&#13;
them. Under this scenario, overall developing countries GNP could grow at 5&#13;
percent allowing room for growth in per capita incomes.      Only in Sub-Saharan&#13;
Africa would income growth not resume till the end of the period; but at least&#13;
declines would halt.&#13;
xvi.     Of   course,   the   international  environment,   determined   by   the&#13;
industrial  countries    policies,  is  only   a  necessary,  not  a  sufficient&#13;
condition, for such an outcome.    Developing country policies would also have&#13;
to continue to improve, both in moving towards reduction of internal and&#13;
external imbalances and in terms of greater factor movement flexibility and&#13;
improved pricing.&#13;
xvii.    The acceptable outcome outlined above is not the best possible.      One&#13;
can imagine better ones.    They would require firmer correction of financial&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
imbalances in the industrial countries, roll back rather than containment of&#13;
protectionism,  and more official capital flows.      They would also require&#13;
bolder movement toward improved policies in the majority of developing&#13;
countries. While one cannot realistically count on this happening within the&#13;
transition period under consideration, it is perhaps not too much to fix such&#13;
improved policies and the faster growth they entail as a realistic and&#13;
attainable goal for the 1990s.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. INTRODUCTION&#13;
1.       In 1981 and 1982 the world economy suffered its deepest and most&#13;
widespread recession in half a century. By 1983, recovery was under way, and&#13;
it strengthened and spread further in 1984.        It helped to relax payments&#13;
tensions, to ease the path of domestic adjustment policies in developing&#13;
countries and to contain the "debt crisis".      Beyond these positive results,&#13;
however, causes for concerns remain.     Not the least of which is that a major&#13;
driving force behind    the recovery so far has been the emergence of new&#13;
disequilibria in domestic finances, external payments and factor employment&#13;
within industrial countries, which are themselves not sustainable in the&#13;
medium term.&#13;
2.       The world economy has not yet returned to an even growth path.    Aside&#13;
from the real and financial imbalances that still need to be corrected, trade&#13;
protectionism is still a major threat and the danger of financial insolvency&#13;
is still present for several countries.       Furthermore, many industrial and&#13;
developing countries will continue to face serious structural adjustment&#13;
problems for several years, as adaptation to past price, demand and supply&#13;
changes necessary to ensure fuller employment of existing factor supplies,&#13;
especially labor, is still far from complete in many of them.&#13;
3.       The   present  economic   recovery  presents   both  opportunities  and&#13;
challenges to policy makers in industrial and developing countries.           Its&#13;
continuation in the medium term, which is in their strong common interest,&#13;
requires that economic policies be consistent with this objective.       Current&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
policies must therefore be continuously reassessed, to identify the changes&#13;
needed to achieve and maintain such consistency.         Sustaining the current&#13;
recovery, moreover, both depends upon and is a precondition for a return to&#13;
durable  trade and financial equilibria and for making steady progress in&#13;
redressing the structural imbalances that stand in the way towards sustainable&#13;
long-term non-inflationary growth.&#13;
4.       Transition from the present cyclical recovery to steady long-term&#13;
growth will have to be managed during the remainder of this decade, and this&#13;
is the focus of this paper.     The first part deals briefly with the overall&#13;
impact on developing countries of the 1983-84 economic recovery in industrial&#13;
countries.   The second part examines in some detail the external adjustment&#13;
paths followed by developing countries.      The third part sums up the policy&#13;
challenges  that lie ahead.     The last section deals specifically with the&#13;
medium term prospects for the world economy and for developing countries in&#13;
particular, in the event of moderate policy adjustments in industrial&#13;
countries, and also assuming continuation of present policy trends.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
II. THE ENVIRONMENT OF THE DEVELOPING COUNTRIES: GLOBAL ECONOMIC&#13;
RECOVERY IN THE INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES, 1983-84&#13;
5.       The world economy now appears to be on the mend.         In 1983-84 the&#13;
major industrial countries succeeded in setting their economies on a recovery&#13;
path, while also reducing inflation.     In developing countries the growth of&#13;
output was less fast and domestic inflation rates were still on the rise, but&#13;
despite rising interest rates and associated debt service burdens, many of&#13;
them made substantial progress in dealing with the payment difficulties. they&#13;
faced. On the whole, financial tensions were eased and world output and trade&#13;
once again grew.&#13;
6.       World  real   output  increased  by 2.4 percent    in 1983 and    by an&#13;
estimated 4.2 percent in 1984. World trade, which had declined in both volume&#13;
and value in 1982 and had returned to a positive, if modest, volume growth in&#13;
1983 registered a strong increase in 1984, pulled by the expansion in economic&#13;
activity in both industrial and developing countries.       The growth of world&#13;
exports is estimated at about 9 percent in 1984 (Table 1).&#13;
7.       Industrial countries- real output grew by 2.6 percent in 1983 and,&#13;
according to preliminary estimates, by 4.8 percent in 1984.          Recovery in&#13;
industrial countries was still regionally unbalanced.    Real growth was fastest&#13;
in the United States, whose economic expansion fueled the world recovery.&#13;
Japan followed, with the second highest rate of growth of real domestic&#13;
product for the whole year, and resumed its traditional place as the fastest&#13;
growing industrial economy in the second half of 1984. Europe's recovery was&#13;
at best tentative and slow, and unemployment there continued to increase.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
Table 1: WORLD OUTPUT, TRADE AND PRICES&#13;
Actual           Estimated   Projected&#13;
1981   1982    1983       1984        1985&#13;
(------------------% change&#133;-----------------&#13;
REAL OUTPUT&#13;
Industrial Countries           1.9   -0.5     2.6        4.8         3.1&#13;
Developing Countries           3.3    1.9     2.0        4.1         4.5&#13;
High-Income Oil Exporting&#13;
Countries                    0.1   -1.7    -7.0        0.4         3.6&#13;
East European Countries        1.8    2.1     3.0        2.6         2.7&#13;
World                       2.0    0.0     2.4        4.2         3.3&#13;
TRADE (EXPORT VOLUMES)&#13;
Industrial Countries           2.2   -1.6     2.0        9.0         6.0&#13;
Developing Countries          -1.3    3.1     5.8        8.9         6.8&#13;
World /a                    1.5   -2.0     2.1        8.6          5.7&#13;
TRADE ($ PRICES)&#13;
Export Unit Values of&#13;
Industrial Countries        -3.8   -4.0    -3.5       -3.2         4.0&#13;
Export Unit Values of&#13;
Developing Countries        -5.0   -6.7    -3.4       -2.5        -2.2&#13;
Manufactures' Export&#13;
Prices (MUV)                -5.0   -1.9    -4.2       -2.8         5.0&#13;
Non-Fuel Primary Commodity&#13;
Prices                     -18.5 -16.8      3.7       -2.1         1.1&#13;
Oil Prices                    12.4   -3.2   -12.3       -2.4         0.0&#13;
DOMESTIC PRICES (LOCAL CURRENCIES) /b&#13;
Industrial Countries          10.5    7.8     5.3        5.0         4.5&#13;
Developing Countries          30.0   30.5    41.5       47.5        44.0&#13;
/a  Including estimates for high-income oil exporting countries and the East&#13;
European economies.&#13;
/b  Consumer prices (weighted averages).&#13;
Sources: OECD, IMF, World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 5 -&#13;
8.       Despite the pace of the recovery, inflation generally continued to&#13;
moderate in the industrial countries.     Overall, the rate of increase of the&#13;
GDP deflator expressed in national currencies fell to its lowest level since&#13;
the late 1960s.    Continued restraint in monetary policy, moderation in the&#13;
growth of wages and other industrial input costs were the key to this positive&#13;
performance.   In the United States and in Japan price stability was bolstered&#13;
by rising exchange rates (Table 2).     But the progress made against inflation&#13;
was equally solid in Europe, and given the cost-push impact of depreciating&#13;
exchange rates, this is perhaps even more remarkable.&#13;
9.       The recovery of world demand did not exert any significant upward&#13;
pressure on traded good     prices.   The prices of manufactures exported by&#13;
industrial countries rose even less than their GDP deflators.      Reductions in&#13;
domestic   inflation   rates,   coupled  with   improvements   in  manufacturing&#13;
productivity, and strong competition in export markets helped contain the&#13;
increase in manufactured goods prices in terms of domestic currencies.         In&#13;
dollar terms, their prices continued to fall in 1984 as the dollar continued&#13;
to appreciate. The prices of primary commodities also fell in 1984, under the&#13;
impact of dollar appreciation and of interest rate increases (Table 2).&#13;
10.      That the cause of the continued appreciation of the US dollar are not&#13;
well understood is illustrated by most observers' having forecast that it&#13;
would decline in 1984. What is clear, however, is that the high value of the&#13;
dollar, coupled with the early and vigorous resumption of growth in the United&#13;
States  contributed   to a surge   of imports.     The  Federal  budget  deficit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 2: SELECTED MONETARY INDICATORS FOR INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES&#13;
1981    1982    1983              1983                        1984&#13;
iQ     2Q     3Q     4Q     iQ     2Q     3Q     4Q&#13;
(-                                  %)&#13;
A.  Short-Term Domestic Interest Rates /a&#13;
United States                            14.1   10.7      8.6     8.1    8.4    9.2    8.8    9.1    9.8   10.3    9.1&#13;
Japan                                     7.7     7.1     6.7     6.9    6.7    6.8    6.5    6.3    6.3    6.3    6.3&#13;
Germany                                  12.1     8.9     5.8     5.7    5.4    5.7    6.3    6.0    6.0    6.0    5.9&#13;
France                                   15.3    14.7    12.6    12.9   12.6   12.6   12.5   12.7   12.5   11.6   10.8&#13;
United Kingdom                          13.0     11.5     9.6    10.5    9.7    9.3    8.9    8.7    8.7   10.4    9.4&#13;
B.  Short-Term International Interest Rates&#13;
Eurodollar Rate /b                       16.5    13.1     9.6     9.2    9.3   10.1    9.9   10.1   11.4   11.9    9.9&#13;
London Interbank Rate /b                 16.8    13.2     9.6     9.3    9.3   10.0    9.8   10.2   11.4   11.8   10.0&#13;
London Interbank Rate 7T                 16.6    13.5     9.8     9.5    9.5   10.4   10.0   10.4   11.8   12.2   10.4&#13;
C.  Effective Exchange Rates /d              (--yearly % change--)    (----------  change from previous quarter----------)&#13;
United States                            12.7    11.7     5.8    -2.8    2.9    3.6    0.3    0.7    0.9    6.0    2.7&#13;
Japan                                    13.1    -5.7    10.1     9.2    1.1    0.4    4.4    2.1    1.0   -2.4    1.0&#13;
Germany                                  -9.5     4.1     2.4     1.7    0.1   -2.4    0.3    0.0   -0.1   -2.1   -1.6&#13;
France                                 -10.6     -9.1    -8.7     0.5   -5.5   -2.6   -1.6   -1.0    0.1   -2.0   -1.5&#13;
Italy                                  -13.3    -7.5     -5.1     0.2   -2.0   -2.3   -2.4   -1.5   -0.4   -1.7   -1.9&#13;
United Kingdom                           -1.1    -4.8    -8.0    -9.5    4.6    0.6   -2.0   -1.7   -2.5   -2.2   -3.8&#13;
Australia                                10.4    -5.0    -7.3    -2.2   -5.6    3.3    3.9    2.8   -2.4   -3.9    2.8&#13;
Canada                                    2.9     1.9     3.2    -0.6    1.1    1.4   -0.3   -1.2   -2.7    0.9    0.8&#13;
/a  Three months treasury bill rates or private bill rates, except for France and Germany, for which interbank money&#13;
rates are quoted.&#13;
/b  Three months, on US dollar deposits.&#13;
7T  Six month, on US dollar deposits.&#13;
7- MERM weights.&#13;
Source: IMF, International Financial Statistics (various issues).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
constituted a parallel influence, also clearly related to the appreciating&#13;
dollar.   As a result, US import expenditure rose by 6 percent in 1983 and by&#13;
26 percent in 1984, while export revenue grew much less. The trade deficit of&#13;
the US rose from $43 billion in 1982 to $108 billion in 1984, and the current&#13;
account deficit increased by more than $90 billion over the same period (Table&#13;
3).&#13;
11.      The corresponding increase in the net surplus outside the United&#13;
States exercised a powerful expansionary influence on the rest of the world,&#13;
equivalent to about 1 percent of world GDP. However, the distribution of this&#13;
impulse  was  uneven.    Although   emphasis  on  absolute  values  is  rendered&#13;
difficult by the errors and omissions in the world current account balance, 1/&#13;
the broad trends are clear.     Among industrial areas, the improvement in the&#13;
current accounts of Japan and Europe over the 1982-84 period was of about&#13;
equal magnitude: $28 billion.    However, while improvement in the position of&#13;
Japan came as an addition to existing surpluses, Europe reached equilibrium in&#13;
its overall current account only in 1983, and improved slightly upon it in&#13;
1984. Some European countries are still running sizable deficits, offset by&#13;
surpluses in others.    One consequence of this is that concerns about balance&#13;
of payments, and about the effects of deficits on exchange rates and on&#13;
domestic inflation still constrain some European governments' willingness to&#13;
relax financial policies in order to stimulate output and employment growth.&#13;
1/ "Errors and omissions" have increased rapidly since 1980. See Table 8.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 3: ECONOMIC PERFORMANCE OF INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES: 1981-85&#13;
Actual           Estimated  Projected&#13;
1981    1982    1983       1984      1985&#13;
(-------------------% change----------------)&#13;
RETA GNr&#13;
United States                   2.5   -2.1      3.7        6.8       3.0&#13;
Japan                          4.0      3.2     3.0        5.7       5.0&#13;
Europe                        -0.1      0.6     1.3        2.3       2.5&#13;
Total OECD                          1.9   -0.5      2.6        4.8       3.1&#13;
REAL TOTAL DOMESTIC DEMAND&#13;
United States                  3.1    -1.2      5.0        8.7       3.7&#13;
Japan                          2.1      3.1     1.6        4.2       4.5&#13;
Europe                        -1.8      0.8     1.0        2.0       2.0&#13;
Total OECD                          1.1     0.0     2.7        5.2       3.0&#13;
PRIVATE CONSUMPTION DEFLATORS&#13;
United States                  8.6      5.9     3.7        3.2       3.5&#13;
Japan                           4.5     2.7     1.6        2.2       2.7&#13;
Europe                         11.6    10.7     8.4        8.0       7.0&#13;
Total OECD                          9.4     8.0     5.4        5.0       4.7&#13;
(&#133;--------$ billion---------------)&#13;
CURRENT ACCOUNT BALANCES&#13;
United States                   6.3    -9.2   -41.6     -100.0    -130.0&#13;
Japan                           4.8     6.9    20.8       35.0      40.0&#13;
Europe                       -21.5    -17.8     0.9       10.0      14.0&#13;
Total OECD                       -25.0    -27.5   -25.2      -61.5     -86.0&#13;
(--------------% of labor force------------)&#13;
UNEMPLOYMENT&#13;
United States                   7.6     9.7     9.6        7.5       7.0&#13;
Japan                          2.2      2.4     2.6        2.7       2.5&#13;
Europe                         8.2      9.5    10.5       11.0      11.5&#13;
Total OECD                          6.9     8.4     9.0        8.5       8.5&#13;
Source: OECD: Economic Outlook (various issues).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
12.      Table 3 shows the relationship between the movements in GNP, domestic&#13;
demand and the balance of payments in the three major industrial areas.        In&#13;
the United States, real domestic demand grew much faster than real GNP. This&#13;
was largely due to the impact of the rapidly growing fiscal deficit in a&#13;
country where private savings, traditionally quite low, have barely exceeded&#13;
private investments. Demand expansion fueled the growth of GNP, but also gave&#13;
rise to the current payments gap, as in the past two years the growth of real&#13;
domestic demand exceeded that of domestic product by more than 3 percentage&#13;
points. In Europe, in part because of concern with the balance of payments,&#13;
the growth of real domestic demand remained below that of GNP, thereby acting&#13;
as a break on the growth of real domestic output.       As for Japan, where the&#13;
balance of payments constraint was never operative and domestic price rises&#13;
were also contained more successfully than even in the United States and in&#13;
most European countries, the growth in domestic demand accelerated only&#13;
recently and remained on average lower than that of GNP, thus contributing to&#13;
rising payments surpluses.&#13;
13.      On the whole, the current account deficit of industrial countries&#13;
increased from $25.2 billion in 1982 to $61.5 billion in 1984.      This growing&#13;
overall payments deficit and the rising imports of the industrial countries&#13;
have contributed to easing the developing countries' financial adjustment to&#13;
the particular problems of the early 1980s.       Their own mounting debt, the&#13;
changes intervened in the attitudes of commercial lenders and of aid&#13;
suppliers, as well as the rise in interest rates, required the developing&#13;
countries to move towards a trade surplus position.      This was facilitated by&#13;
the developments in the overall trade and payments position of industrial&#13;
countries just described.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
14.      Developing countries' export revenues increased by 8 percent in 1984,&#13;
while import expenditure grew by 2.4 percent.     Their trade balance went from&#13;
an overall deficit of $49 billion in 1982 to a surplus of about $3 billion in&#13;
1984. 1/ Their current account imbalance was reduced by two-thirds during the&#13;
same period. The upsurge of exports to the United States, and, to a smaller&#13;
extent, to Europe and Japan also helped the recovery of domestic output in&#13;
most developing countries.    On the whole, their real GDP growth rate nearly&#13;
doubled between 1983 and 1984.       The impact of improved world demand and&#13;
relative  price  conditions   2/    for  developing  countries  exports  varied,&#13;
depending   on   individual   country's  export   structure   (by   product   and&#13;
destination), capacity to respond to outside stimuli, external financial&#13;
position and the nature and extend of the imbalances affecting it.       It also&#13;
depended critically on the domestic policies that were followed by the various&#13;
countries, not only during the 1983-84 recovery period, but also earlier.&#13;
1/ See further Table 4.&#13;
2/ Developing countries' terms of trade improved in 1984 on account of the&#13;
decline in the price of both manufactured products exported by industrial&#13;
countries and oil (Table 10).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
III. FINANCIAL ADJUSTMENT IN DEVELOPING COUNTRIES: 1982-84&#13;
15.      In mid-1982, when Mexico's inability to meet its contractual debt&#13;
service  obligations  suddenly transformed   the "debt   problem"  into a "debt&#13;
crisis", the world economic recession was at its worst.       Economic activity,&#13;
export prices and volumes were declining.      The sharp reduction of voluntary&#13;
private lending to developing countries (for many, a virtual cessation) left&#13;
to those countries faced with a pressing need to reduce their balance of&#13;
payments deficits no alternative     to cutting back their imports.      In some&#13;
countries, which had either tried to anticipate the- emergence of financial&#13;
difficulties or had already been affected by them (e.g. Turkey, Brazil), the&#13;
adjustment   process  began  earlier.     On  the   whole,  however,  developing&#13;
countries' imports began to be cut severely in 1982. 1/     In that year overall&#13;
import expenditure by developing countries fell by almost 8 percent.         Low-&#13;
income Sub-Saharan African countries, hit by a dramatic decline in commodity&#13;
export revenues, and middle-income Latin American countries, facing the most&#13;
acute debt problems, reduced their import outlays most sharply; but. import&#13;
cutbacks were general across geographical regions and income groups (Table&#13;
4).   Except for China and some of the agricultural Asian countries, most&#13;
developing countries also suffered declines in GDP growth rates.          In the&#13;
1/ Unless otherwise specified, the developing countries' data quoted in this&#13;
paper refer to a panel of 90 countries, which account for 97 percent- of&#13;
total developing countries' population, 92 percent of total GNP and 86&#13;
percent of total-exports. The list is provided in Annex Table 1, together&#13;
with the components of the various regional and analytical subgroups used&#13;
in this paper.    The IMF grouping. of developing countries that is most&#13;
comparable with the 90 country panel totals is "non-oil developing&#13;
countries".&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 4: IMPORTS, EXPORTS AND TRADE BALANCES OF DEVELOPING COUNTRIES&#13;
Export Values                      Import Values                    Trade Balances&#13;
1981    1982    1983    1984       1981    1982    1983    1984      1981    1982     1983    1984&#13;
(--&#133;--------------------  %  change--------------------               --) ( ----Billions US$------)&#13;
LJOR. am GROUPS&#13;
1.   Sub-Saharan Africa /a      -22.2   -11.2    -9.6     8.0        5.9  -11.8    -16.7   -14.8      -7.1    -6.1    -2.7      4.3&#13;
2.   East Asia                    8.5    -0.6     4.3     9.8      10.1    -3.0      5.6     4.5      -9.8    -5.8    -8.0    -3.3&#13;
3.   South Asia                   3.8    -3.1     5.9     4.3      -2.0    -4.3    -0.7      0.9     -10.3    -9.7    -8.8    -8.5&#13;
4.   EMENA                        3.4    -6.1    -2.0     5.5       8.0    -3.9     -4.0    -2.3     -36.0   -35.9   -33.4   -29.6&#13;
5.   Latin American 6&#13;
Caribbean                   3.1    -4.8     3.8     7.0       7.1   -20.7   -26.9     10.9     -10.9     6.2    31.9     35.4&#13;
ANALTTICAL C2DUPS&#13;
1.   Low-Income Countries         3.0    -1.2     2.1    13.9      -3.9     -8.6     2.0     3.5     -15.2   -10.8   -11.0    -11.5&#13;
Africa                   -23.0    -6.8    -3.0     8.6     -13.2   -10.0     -6.4     1.0      -4.9    -4.2    -3.7    -3.3&#13;
Asia                      10.2    -0.2     3.0    14.8      -1.2     -8.2     4.1     3.8     -10.3    -6.6    -7.3     -8.2&#13;
2.   Middle-Income Countries      0.4    -3.3     1.8     7.1        9.9    -7.8    -7.2     1.7     -57.7   -38.2    -6.1     14.4&#13;
2.1  Oil Importers                4.9    -2.5     6.4     7.4        6.1   -7.0     -3.8     2.2     -61.2   -47.4   -24.8    -11.9&#13;
Major Exporters of&#13;
Manufactures               7.1    -2.6     6.7     7.5        5.8   -6.2     -3.4     2.8     -35.8   -27.4    -9.3     -1.4&#13;
Other Non-Oil               -5.1    -1.6     4.8     6.6       7.3   -10.1    -5.3     -0.4     -25.4   -20.0   -15.5   -13.3&#13;
2.3  Oil Exporters               -6.3    -4.6    -5.9     6.5      19.3    -9.5    -15.0     0.6       3.5     9.2    18.7     26.3&#13;
ALL DEVKLOPING COUNTRIES /b           0.7    -3.1     1.9     7.9        7.9    -7.9    -6.1     1.9     -72.9   -49.0   -17.0      2.9&#13;
/a  Excluding South Africa.   The IMF definition excludes both South Africa and Nigeria.&#13;
71 Figures refer to a sample of 90 developing countries.&#13;
Source: World Bank, Economic Analysis and Projections Department.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
regions where import reductions were sharpest, the absolute level of output&#13;
actually fell, by about 1 percent in Latin America and by 1.2 percent in Sub-&#13;
Saharan Africa (Table 5).&#13;
16.      In 1983, middle-income Latin American countries, whose debt servicing&#13;
difficulties had reached a peak, again reduced their imports expenditure by&#13;
compressing   real   domestic  absorption,   including   investments.      Import&#13;
expenditure fell by 27 percent and the decline in their real output also&#13;
accelerated (to -2.9 percent). The combined effect of such a strong reduction&#13;
of imports and of increased exports to the United States and other industrial&#13;
countries was a first strong improvement in current accounts during the year.&#13;
17.      In  the   course  of  the  adjustment   process,  private  incomes  and&#13;
consumption expenditures were reduced throughout Latin America.     However, the&#13;
brunt of the compression of domestic demand fell on investment.       In Brazil,&#13;
for instance, the value of investment in constant prices was reduced by well&#13;
over one-third in three years; in the four major oil-importing debtor&#13;
countries (Argentina, Brazil, Chile, and Colombia) total real investments in&#13;
1983 were 40 percent below their 1981 level.&#13;
18.      East Asian middle-income countries provided the sharpest contrast to&#13;
Latin America.     These countries,  and particularly the major exporters of&#13;
manufactures, had weathered the 1982 fall in their trade with only a moderate&#13;
slowdown in their traditionally fast growth of real output.          Recovery of&#13;
demand for their exports, particularly in the United States, allowed them to&#13;
restore normal import growth rates in 1983, and to raise the growth rate of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
Table 5: REAL GDP GROWTH IN DEVELOPING COUNTRIES&#13;
Actual       Estimated      Projected&#13;
1982      1983      1984     1985&#13;
(---------% change--------)&#13;
MAJOR BANK GROUPS&#13;
1.  Sub-Saharan Africa /a             -1.2      -2.4      -0.8      2.0&#13;
East Africa                        0.1        1.0      1.3      2.6&#13;
West Africa                       -1.8       -3.9     -1.7      1.7&#13;
2.  East Asia                          5.4        7.3      7.2      6.3&#13;
China                              7.4        9.0      9.0      7.0&#13;
Other East Asia                    3.8        5.9      5.5      5.8&#13;
3.  South Asia                         2.8        6.2      4.4      5.3&#13;
India                              2.6        6.5      4.2      3-7&#13;
Other South Asia                   3.5        5.2      4.9      6.4&#13;
4.  EMENA                              3.5        2.5      2.6      3.6&#13;
5.  Latin America and Caribbean       -0.9      -2.9       2.8      3.6&#13;
WDR ANALYTICAL GROUPS&#13;
1.  Low-Income Countries               5.0        7.2      6.6      6.0&#13;
Africa                             0.7        07       19         -&#13;
Asia                               5.4        7.8      7.1      6.3&#13;
2.  Middle-Income Countries            0.8        0.0      3.1      3.8&#13;
2.1  Oil Importers                 0.8        0.7      3.3      3.8&#13;
Major Exporters of            1.3        0.7      3.5      4.0&#13;
Manufactures&#13;
Other Non-Oil                -0.7       0.4       2.7      3.2&#13;
2.2  Oil Exporters                 0.9      -1.0       2.7      3.9&#13;
ALL DEVELOPING COUNTRIES /b                 1.9       2.0      4.1       4.5&#13;
Memorandum Items:&#13;
Low-Income Countries (excluding&#13;
China and India)                 2.3       3.0       3.2      4.3&#13;
All Developing Countries&#13;
(excluding China and India)      0.9       0.2       3.1      3.9&#13;
/a Excluding South Africa.&#13;
lb Including South Africa. Total refers to a panel of 90 developing countries.&#13;
Source: World Bank, Economic Analysis and Projections Department.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
domestic output while also reducing their external deficits.        This pattern&#13;
continued and was consolidated in, among others, Korea, Thailand, Hong Kong&#13;
and Singapore, whose joint current account balance improved by $4 billion and&#13;
whose output growth was in excess of 5 percent during 1983.      Better domestic&#13;
policies, reflected in lower domestic inflation rates, lower budget deficits&#13;
and more adroit exchange rate managements than in other middle-income&#13;
developing countries, coupled with greater capacity to respond to changes in&#13;
external conditions (built up through years of export-oriented fast&#13;
development) helped this fast and relatively painless adjustment.&#13;
19.      In the middle-income countries of the Middle East, North Africa and&#13;
Southern Europe, 1/    the pattern of events followed a course mid-way between&#13;
Latin America and the Far East.     Turkey, for instance, became unable to meet&#13;
its debt service obligations well before the onset of the world recession.&#13;
Its adjustment thus begun at a time when external circumstances were more&#13;
favorable.    In the early 1980s,    its exports and real GDP never stopped&#13;
growing, and by 1983 private per capita consumption, and by 1984 investments&#13;
could also start to recover.&#13;
20.      As for Asian low-income countries, limited dependence on external&#13;
trade partly insulated India and China from external shock.        More broadly,&#13;
these countries continued to improve their domestic policies, maintaining and&#13;
even accelerating their output growth rates. They had contained their balance&#13;
of payments deficits in the 1970s, and generally reduced them in the early&#13;
1/ These are the countries included in the Bank's EMENA region.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
1980s.   China moved into substantial surplus.   Only in the case of India and&#13;
China, however, was the size of the payments deficit policy determined, in the&#13;
sense that few, if any, of the other countries in this group had the ability&#13;
to borrow much on commercial terms.     India and China pursued very cautious&#13;
foreign borrowing policies, with the deliberate aim of avoiding excessive&#13;
dependence on external capital.&#13;
21.      Sub-Saharan Africa continued to face the most severe difficulties in&#13;
the early   1980s.    The value of its exports,     almost exclusively primary&#13;
commodities, fell by more than 40 percent in 1981-83.    Import expenditure had&#13;
to be drastically reduced over the same period.     The improved trade balance,&#13;
however, was not enough to allow the region's debtor countries to meet their&#13;
debt service obligations. GDP continued to fall, and per capita incomes, now&#13;
frequently below their pre-independence levels, fell even more sharply.&#13;
Undoubtedly, domestic policy improvements in the region remained limited and&#13;
the policy thrust often unstable; but for these raw material exporters, with&#13;
often very trade-dependent economies, the negative evolution of raw material&#13;
prices, the lack of recovery in their traditional European markets and the&#13;
decline of aid left very little room for sustained adjustment measures which&#13;
did not require politically unenforceable sacrifices.&#13;
22.      The consolidation of economic recovery in industrial countries during&#13;
1984, together with the significant shift in policy response that occurred in&#13;
many developing countries, determined a major turnaround in adjustment&#13;
results.    Increased demand for their exports and greater ability to take&#13;
advantage of improved export market conditions created by a combination of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
expenditure reduction and expenditure switching policies, put developing&#13;
countries in a position to resume output growth, while at the same time&#13;
reducing further their payment deficits (Table 6).&#13;
23.      The changes in terms of trade that occurred in 1984 and the relative&#13;
import-export volume performances determined final outcomes in terms of trade&#13;
balances.  Middle-income countries accounted for most of the improvement that&#13;
occurred from 1983 to 1984 ($14.5 billion).    Among them the largest movements&#13;
towards surplus were made by the major exporters of manufactures, in both East&#13;
Asia and Latin America.      Quantity factors played the major role, as the&#13;
improvement in middle-income countries terms of trade was minimal in 1984.&#13;
Low-income developing countries only marginally reduced their overall trade&#13;
deficit.   Sub-Saharan African countries and, to a smaller extent, India and&#13;
China showed the largest improvement in trade balances.        The former were&#13;
helped by a strong improvement in terms of trade, largely determined by a fall&#13;
in the prices of imported food and manufactures and a sharp increase in the&#13;
prices of exported tropical beverages (Table 4).&#13;
24.      Middle-income  countries   registered  the  strongest  improvements  in&#13;
current account balances during 1984, despite sharply rising interest&#13;
payments.   Middle-income oil importing countries registered a $15 billion&#13;
reduction in deficit, while oil exporters managed to reduce their current&#13;
account imbalance by almost $7 billion.    Net private lending to middle-income&#13;
countries continued to fall in 1984, although by less than in 1983. Despite a&#13;
small increase in official lending, this group of countries registered a net&#13;
outflow of about $14 billion in 1984, as interest payments on existing and new&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
Table 6:  DEVELOPING COUNTRIES   CURRENT ACCOUNT BALANCE AND ITS FINANCING, 1970-84&#13;
(Billions of Current US$)&#13;
1970     1980      1981     1982     1983     1984&#13;
A. OWW-INCOME COUNTRIES&#13;
Asia&#13;
Net Exports (GNFS)               -1.358  -15.755   -11.498   -6.831   -7.246   -8.687&#13;
Net Factor Income                -0.390    0.078   -0.212    -0.983   -0.523   -0.605&#13;
Interest on KLT Debt             -0.286   -1.363   -1.560    -1.515   -1.598   -1.833&#13;
Official                      -0.241   -0.689   -0.657    -0.762   -0.962   -1.079&#13;
Private                       -0.045   -0,674   -0.904    -0.752   -0.636   -0.754&#13;
Current Account Balance          -1.551   -9.685   -6.164    -1.364   -1.001   -3.083&#13;
(Excl. Official Transfers)&#13;
Net Official Transfers            0.370    1.952     2.084    1.884    2.011     1.952&#13;
MLT Loans                         0.987    4.878     3.227    3.957    4.199     6.541&#13;
Official                       0.971    3.410     3.452    3.883    3.542    4.222&#13;
Private                        0.016    1.468   -0.225     0.074    0.657    2.319&#13;
Net Direct Investment             0.029    0.159     0.422    0.488    0.546    0.643&#13;
Change in Reserves               -0.187    0.449     2.406    2.135   -4.224   -3.184&#13;
Debt Outstandtng and Disbursed   11.524   38.412    39.545   42.941   46.290    52.831&#13;
As Percent of GNP              6.958    7.798     8.175    8.850    9.058    9.741&#13;
*As Percent of Exp. GS       183.636    96.704   89.501   95.064   98.880   100.032&#13;
Debt Service Ratio               12.423    7.996     9.295   10.929    8.311     8.443&#13;
Africa&#13;
Net Exports (GNFS)               -0.381   -5.385   -5.391    -4.135   -4.339   -3.784&#13;
Net Factqr Income                -0.161   -0.901    -1.098   -1.004   -1.049   -1.294&#13;
Interest on MLT Debt             -0.080   -0.698   -0.643    -0.567   -0.662   -1.000&#13;
Official                      -0.042   -0.312   -0.259    -0.267   -0.315   -0.435&#13;
Private                       -0.038   -0.386   -0.384    -0.300   -0.348   -0.565&#13;
Current Account Balance          -0.679   -5.837   -5.882    -4.978   -4.900   -4.594&#13;
(Excl. Official Transfers)&#13;
Net Official Transfers            0.297    2.109     1.813    1.515    2.008     1.925&#13;
MLT Loans                         0.276    3.349     2.862    2.198    1.910     2.025&#13;
Official                       0.247    2.366     2.249    1.858    1.922     2.231&#13;
Private                        0.030    0.983     0.614    0.340   -0.012   -0.206&#13;
Net Direct Investment             0.173    0.236     0.221    0.223    0.211     0.086&#13;
Change in Reserves               -0-111    0.555     0.377    0.500    0.171     0.607&#13;
Debt Outstanding and Disbursed    2.874   20.787    22.905   24.487   25.399    26.583&#13;
As Percent of GNP             17.931   39.936    43.753   47.765   52.223    54.550&#13;
As Percent of Exp. GS         75.232  175.807   216.466  260.561  279.452   278.067&#13;
Debt Service Ratio                6.065   12.541    13.801   15.654   16.507    19.893&#13;
B. MIDDLE-INCOME COUNTRIES&#13;
Major Exporters of Manufactures&#13;
Net Exports (GNFS)               -5.719  -28.892   -26.983  -17.988    0.487    19.590&#13;
Net Factor Income                -1.768  -17.058   -25.505  -30.822  -32.135  -38.481&#13;
Interest on MLT Debt             -1.120  -14.880  -19.504   -22.510  -20.139  -25.839&#13;
Official                      -0.217   -2.158   -2.381    -2.948   -3.320   -3.818&#13;
Private                       -0.903  -12.722  -17.123   -19.562  -16.819  -22.021&#13;
Current Account Balance          -5.500  -35.260   -41.696  -38.294  -21.969   -9.345&#13;
(Excl. Official Transfers)&#13;
Net Official Transfers            0.502    2.483     2.550    2.608    3.180     3.735&#13;
MLT Loans                         3.590   21.401    29.160   25.043   16.617    17.474&#13;
Official                       0.868    5.065     5.139    4.827    6.525     7.626&#13;
Private                        2.722   16.336   24.021    20.216   10.092    9.848&#13;
Net Direct Investment             1.076    4.356     6.106    5.888    4.478     4.605&#13;
Change in Reserves               -0.503    1.606     0.127    4.098    4.369  -10.554&#13;
Debt Outstanding and Disbursed   24.357  166.602   191.029  215.801  242.016  266.818&#13;
As Percent of GNP             15.871   22.848    24.839   28.017   34.746    37.638&#13;
As Percent of Exp. GS         91.507   77.315    81.728   97.079  105.221  109.099&#13;
Debt Service Ratio               15.100   16.060    17.067   19.350   16.189    15.997&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
Table 6: DEVELOPING COUNTRIES' CURRENT ACCOUNT BALANCE AND-ITS FINANCING,&#13;
1970-84 (CONTINUED)&#13;
(Billions 'of Current US$)&#13;
1970     1980      1981     1982      1983     1984&#13;
Other Non-Oil&#13;
Net Exports (GNFS)               -1.345   -18.179  -23.517  -17.146   -12.721   -9.617&#13;
Net Factor Income                -0.960    -5.188   -6.005   -7.761    -9.900  -10.567&#13;
Interest on MLT Debt             -0.445    -4.457   -5.551   -6.762    -6.733   -8.002&#13;
Official                      -0.194    -.136   -1.353   -1.604    -1.927   -2.418&#13;
Private                       -0.251   -3.321    -4.198   -5.157    -4.805   -5.584&#13;
Current Acdount Balance          -1.923   -18.564  -24.056  -19.804   -17.743  -15.022&#13;
(Excl. Official Transfers)&#13;
Net Official Transfers            0.583     3.084    3.'278    3.228    2.653    2.539&#13;
MLT Loans -                        1.747   11.789   12.866'   11.873'   7.918   10.798&#13;
Official                       0.800     5.931    6.119    5.905     5.160    5.333&#13;
Private                        0.947     5.857    6.748    5.968     2.758    5.466&#13;
Net Direct Investment             0.149     1.653    1.875     1.355    1.390    1.126&#13;
Change ih Reserves               -0.635    -3.420    0.397     3.619    3.003    1.461&#13;
Debt Outstanding and Disbursed   11.916    68.327   78.850    88.932   97.751  108.035-&#13;
As Percent of GNP             21.986    30.187   33.831   40.713    48.658   52.966&#13;
As Percent of Exp. GS        110.987   120.672  136.398  155.433   175.472  183.860&#13;
Debt Service Ratio               13.577    17.184   20.765    22.697   23.094   24.929&#13;
Oil Exporters&#13;
Net Exports (GNFS)               -0.915    14.628  -10.713  -13.701     7.854  .16.666&#13;
Net Factor Income                -2.207   -16.186  -19.006  -23.981   -22.631  -24.692&#13;
Interest on MLT Debt             -0.693  -11.454   -13.903  -16.660   -17.463  -21.252&#13;
Official                      -0.209    -1.656   -2.045   -2.132    -2.508   -2.830&#13;
Private                       -0.485   -9.798   -11.859  -14.529   -14.956  -18.421&#13;
Current Account Balance          -2.930     1.509  -27.297  -35.680   -11.052   -3.543&#13;
(Excl. Official Transfers)&#13;
Net Official Transfers            0.595     2.007    2.485     1.918    1.918    1.809&#13;
MLT Loans                         1.643    16.998   23.559   20.503    18.133   13.323&#13;
Official                       0.i61     4.'800  - 4.706   5.314     3.660 '  6.194&#13;
Private                        0.881    12.198   18.853   15.190    14.473    7.129&#13;
Net Direct Investment             0.8i0     4.192    6.369     5.283    3.717'   2.922&#13;
Change in Reserves               -0.499   -17.077    2.217   15.767     3.549   -7.339&#13;
Debt Outstanding and Disbursed   17.631   135.564  155.326  173.586   208.176  232.153&#13;
As Percent of GNP             18.519    24.863   25.058   32.386    39.893   43.849&#13;
As Percent of Exp. GS        115.298    87.431   98.507- 123.694   157.769  164.274&#13;
Debt Service Ratio               18.073    17.848   19.776    24.977   26.132   28.090&#13;
C. ALL DEVELOPING COUNTRIES&#13;
Net Exports (GNFS)               -9.717   -53.582  -78.102  -59.802   -15.966   14.168&#13;
Net Factor Income                -5.486   -39.255  -51.827  -64.551   -66.238  -75.640&#13;
Interest on MLT Debt             -2.624   -32.851  -41.161  -48.014   -46.596  -57.925&#13;
Official                      -0.902    -5.951   -6.694   -7.714    -9.032  -10.580&#13;
Pri'vate                      -1.721' -26.899   -34.'467  -40.301  -37.564  -47.345&#13;
Current Account Balance         -12.583   -67.837 -105.095.-100.121   -56.665  -35.588&#13;
(Excl. Official Transfers)&#13;
Net Official Transfers            2.347    11.635   12.209   11.153    11.768   11.960&#13;
MLT Loans                         8.243    58.414   71.675    63.575   48.778   50.162&#13;
Official                       3.646  -21.572    21.665   21.786    20.810   25.606&#13;
Private                        4.596   36.842    50.010   41.788    27.969   24.556&#13;
Net Direct Investment             2.317    10.595   14.992   13.237    10.342    9.383&#13;
Change in Reserves               -1.935   -17.887    5.524   26.119     6.868  -19.008&#13;
Debt Outstanding and Disbursed   68.303   429.692  487.655   545.748  619.631  686.420&#13;
As Percent of GNP             14.096    21.008   22.596   26.477    31.311   33.758&#13;
As Percent of Exp. GS        108.863    89.761   96.759  115.'037  130.843  135.383&#13;
Debt Service Ratio               14.746    16.016   17.589   20.543    18.999   19.690&#13;
Notes: GNFS. - Goods and Non-Factor Services; MLT - Medium-and Long Term; Debt Service&#13;
Ratio - Ratio of interest and amortization payments to exports.&#13;
Source:  World Bank, Economic Analysis and Projections Department.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
debt increased sharply during the year, and exceeded new loan receipts by that&#13;
amount. The current account deficit of Asian low-income countries widened by&#13;
about $2 billion in 1984, while that of African low-income countries remained&#13;
virtually unchanged. Rising interest payments offset the small improvement in&#13;
trade balances experienced by low-income African countries during 1984 (Table&#13;
6).&#13;
25.      Growth in demand for developing countries      exports was stimulated&#13;
mostly by the US recovery and the strong dollar, and, to a more limited&#13;
extent, by similar quantity and relative price impulses in Japan. Regionally,&#13;
it affected most positively those developing countries which are traditional&#13;
trading partners of the United States and of Japan.      In terms of commodity&#13;
composition, it most strongly affected exports of manufactures.      The demand&#13;
for non-fuel primary commodities and for petroleum remained surprisingly weak&#13;
by historical standards. These demand factors largely explain the differences&#13;
in observed trade patterns.     Obviously, policy performance differences also&#13;
intervened, but the weakness of primary commodity markets, particularly in&#13;
1984, left little room for export expansion to those countries which had not&#13;
already developed a manufactures export potential in earlier years.&#13;
26.      Generally speaking, the Latin American and East Asian countries, more&#13;
deeply tied to booming demand in North America and to Japan, and also&#13;
generally possessing relatively advanced manufacturing sectors were able to&#13;
expand their exports most easily.      African countries, more tied to Europe&#13;
(where import demand grew much less than in North America and Japan) and, at&#13;
the same time, more dependent on exports of primary commodities, found&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
themselves in a less favorable position.      The same applies to South Asian&#13;
countries (with India being a partial exception), for which exports of primary&#13;
products are of great importance.&#13;
27.      The differences in external pull faced by various developing regions&#13;
are evident from their exports to the United States, Japan and the three major&#13;
European countries (Germany, France and the United Kingdom) over the 1982-84&#13;
period.   Africa's exports to these countries grew more slowly in 1984 than&#13;
those of East Asia and Latin America, and recouped barely three-fifths of the&#13;
loss experienced in 1983.      Exports of East Asia to the major industrial&#13;
countries increased in dollar value by about 6 percent in 1983, and by almost&#13;
25 percent in 1984.    Latin American exports expanded by 13 percent in 1984&#13;
(about one-third faster than in the previous year), and South Asia's by about&#13;
12 percent (Table 7).&#13;
28.      Within   these  total  increases,  developing   countries'  exports   of&#13;
manufactured goods to the major industrial countries increased in dollar value&#13;
by 15.5 percent in 1983 and by almost 29 percent in 1984, pulled by a 31&#13;
percent increase in exports to the United States in 1983, followed by a 44&#13;
percent increase in 1984.     Exports to Japan rose much less, and to Europe&#13;
least, although even exports to Europe rose at least twice as fast as overall&#13;
demand for manufactures in that region.        Still incomplete data appear to&#13;
indicate that primary commodity exports to industrial countries, including&#13;
petroleum, also began to recover in 1984, even though they remained the&#13;
weakest component of the developing countries' overall export picture.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
Table 7: MAJOR INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES' IMPORTS FROM DEVELOPING COUNTRIES&#13;
BY GEOGRAPHICAL ORIGIN&#13;
(% change)&#13;
1983      1984 (Jan.-Sept.)&#13;
UNITED STATES&#13;
from:  Africa                               -24.3       4.0&#13;
East Asia                             16.3      38.5&#13;
South Asia                            47.8      17.8&#13;
Latin America                         10.9      16.0&#13;
Total /a                             6.0      22.0&#13;
JAPAN&#13;
from:  Africa                               -11.8      11.1&#13;
East Asia                             -4.0      21.6&#13;
South Asia                             3.0      -1.8&#13;
Latin America                          6.4      15.3&#13;
Total /a                            -2.0      17.7&#13;
EC3 /b&#13;
from:  Africa                                -1.4      11.4&#13;
East Asia                              5.2       3.1&#13;
South Asia                           -18.5      14.8&#13;
Latin America                          6.5       0.0&#13;
Total /a                            -0.5       4.7&#13;
MAJOR INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES /c&#13;
from:  Africa                               -13.7       8.1&#13;
East Asia                              6.4      24.5&#13;
South Asia                             8.1      12.2&#13;
Latin America                          9.5      12.6&#13;
Total /a                             2.3      15.4&#13;
/a Including imports from EMENA countries.&#13;
lb United Kingdom, France and Federal Republic of Germany.&#13;
7E United States + Japan + EC3.&#13;
Source: IMF, Direction of Trade (various issues) and DRI, Trade System.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
29.      Expanding   exports   directly  contributed   to  GDP   growth  in  all&#13;
regions.    In many countries,   improved balance of payments positions also&#13;
allowed the relaxation of direct import control measures and, somewhat less&#13;
broadly, of financial stringency.      Real GDP growth in 1984 was enough to&#13;
ensure some increase in real per capita GNP in most developing regions, with&#13;
the exception of Sub-Saharan Africa.     1/    Particularly remarkable was the&#13;
turnaround in real output growth that occurred in Latin America:       from -2.6&#13;
percent in 1983 to 2.6 percent in 1984.&#13;
30.      Domestic adjustment policies played a key role in determining these&#13;
outcomes. In the impact phase (1982 and the first part of 1983) a combination&#13;
of direct restraint of imports (through quantitative controls and devaluation)&#13;
and reduction in domestic absorption was predominant.      This is particularly&#13;
evident in the case of middle-income Latin American countries (Chart 1).&#13;
Sometimes, direct import controls led to the reduction of production and&#13;
income-generation through the scarcity of raw materials, and of machinery and&#13;
other inputs into investment projects; sometimes, financial and other&#13;
restraints on income (including depreciation of effective exchange rates)&#13;
brought about the desired reduction of imports, also at the cost of lower&#13;
production; most often, these two effects were combined.&#13;
31.      Expenditure  switching measures,    among which currency devaluations&#13;
were paramount, together with the onset of the recovery in industrial&#13;
countries, set the stage for a recovery of exports that began in late 1983 and&#13;
streugthened in 1984 (Chart 2).     However, reduced domestic absorption still&#13;
1/ Per capita GDP growth is shown in Table 12.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
Chart 1: REAL DOMESTIC ABSORPTION AND REAL INVESTMENT, 1980-84&#13;
(1980-100)&#13;
Developing Countries /a                                Middle-Income Latin America /b&#13;
O3  06=m. -bmrption  4'  riI t rrm.t                O                       __A_IIry-strn-r.t&#13;
Chart 2: REAL EXPORTS AND REAL EFFECTIVE EXCHANGE RATES, 1980-84&#13;
(1980-100)&#13;
Developing Countries /a                                Middle-Income Latin America /b&#13;
,f1a            -&#13;
Oao                                                 so&#13;
lo        *lt*we             Iga        19         19ao      *"t        lo        lt        1064&#13;
O   .es F.nl E:-. r--t=4     Rft=l E co,eRmte       O3  M.er,-j,zr.:ie EF__=rt2; 4  R.ewnl Ex-hN=r9s- R=.nt_&#13;
/a  Based on a sample of 26 developing countries.&#13;
A7 Argentina, Brazil, Chile, Colombia and Mexico.&#13;
Source: World Bank, Economic Analysis and Projections Department.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
played a considerable role during 1984. In most of Latin America, and in many&#13;
Mediterranean and several Asian developing countries, as well as in Sub-&#13;
Saharan Africa, per capita consumption continued to decline in 1984.&#13;
Investment was also generally lower than in earlier years, and mostly&#13;
concentrated on- the completion of old projects.&#13;
32.      Developing countries as a group succeeded in reducing their external&#13;
imbalance by two-thirds in a relatively short time (between 1981 and 1984),&#13;
despite interest rates which remained exceptionally high both in nominal and&#13;
real terms throughout the period, and despite further growth in their stock of&#13;
debt.   The remarkable success attained in adjusting external imbalances is&#13;
most evident in Latin America, whose trade balance went from -1.5 percent of&#13;
GDP in 1981 to about 5 percent in 1984 (in absolute amounts, from a deficit of&#13;
$11 billion to a surplus of about $35 billion).&#13;
33.      Developing  countries  as a group have made      dramatic progress in&#13;
fitting the growth of their economies to that of available resources, not only&#13;
by cutting overall demand through financial policies, but also by switching&#13;
production   from   the   domestic   market   to   exports   through   effective&#13;
devaluations.  - The only major exception was Sub-Saharan Africa.        African&#13;
governments were either laggard in appreciating fully the need for policy&#13;
change or were unable to implement them.    However, the resources available in&#13;
many African countries made it extremely difficult to implement policy changes&#13;
that involved further reduction in domestic demand in the short term.       More&#13;
importantly still, the economic structures of these countries, with embryonic&#13;
manufacturing sectors, greatly limit the scope that they have in the short run&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
for switching production to import substitution and, pending the revival of&#13;
commodity markets, to exports.&#13;
34.      While financial adjustment has made considerable progress in 1982-84,&#13;
adjustment in the deeper sense of modified economic structures has barely&#13;
begun in many developing countries. As shown by falling investment, resources&#13;
continue to be scarce.      In addition, high present and projected interest&#13;
rates, and the uncertainties of financial markets, render even those&#13;
developing countries that could borrow hesitant to do so and impel present&#13;
borrowers (like those in East Asia) to reduce their current account&#13;
deficits. Paradoxically, with Europe barely emerging from its current account&#13;
deficit and Latin American countries still barely able either to service or to&#13;
refinance  their  debt   service  obligations  despite  their   current  account&#13;
surpluses, only the country with the largest payments deficit, the United&#13;
States, is pursuing its expansion totally unconstrained by balance of payments&#13;
considerations (while Japan's huge surplus has not provided it an incentive to&#13;
accelerate growth).    This unusual situation raises concerns as to what will&#13;
happen to world economic growth when the US current account deficit is&#13;
reduced, either by deliberate policy choice or by the emergence of a financing&#13;
constraint.&#13;
35.      Another  concern relates to trade.      One can no longer deny that&#13;
protectionism is renascent and active.     This is even better illustrated by&#13;
Bangladesh shirts than by Japanese automobiles and Brazilian and Korean&#13;
steel. When one of the world's poorest countries took a miniscule fraction of&#13;
the world market in a product whose strategic importance for industrial&#13;
countries is minor, it soon ran into quotas. Protectionism, and the threat of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
it, most strongly affect the poorer developing countries by slowing down the&#13;
process of specialization in labor-intensive expotts.&#13;
36.      Finally,  capital flows to developing countries have not yet been&#13;
restored to normal levels.    Financial market conditions - high real interest&#13;
rates, high debt stocks, -reduced present willingness to lend (as compared to&#13;
pre-1980 conditions)   and the increased    risk of sudden future changes      in&#13;
lending conditions continue to impose on developing countries strong pressures&#13;
to reduce the growth of real domestic demand.    Official flows have also fallen&#13;
dramatically.. With few exceptions, middle-income countries have to do wi.thout&#13;
significant development assistance at earlier stages of development than did&#13;
their predecessors ten or twenty years ago.     Poor countries, including those&#13;
in Sub-Saharan Africa, whose needs are most acute, have to do with- lower&#13;
concessional   flows  than was   generally  expected-. before  the, worsening  of&#13;
external payments conditions in the early 1980s.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
IV. THE CHALLENGES AHEAD: TRANSITION TOWARDS SUSTAINABLE&#13;
LONG-TERM GROWTH&#13;
37.      The   current  recovery  presents   opportunities  and  challenges   to&#13;
policymakers in industrial and developing countries both. Sustaining it is a&#13;
matter  of  strong,  common interest.     Unemployment is still very high in&#13;
industrial countries, particularly in Europe.       Productive capital is also&#13;
generally  underutilized.    Shifts  in the composition of demand,      and  the&#13;
reallocation of factor uses (in response to these shifts and to past and&#13;
ongoing changes in factor prices) continue to require considerable structural&#13;
adjustments in many industrial countries. Steady, reliable and strong overall&#13;
output growth would facilitate the management of these changes.      Conversely,&#13;
the rigidities which have often contributed to past problems tend to be&#13;
reinforced by an environment of slow growth in which unemployment is rife. On&#13;
the financial side, debt, particularly public debt is very high in all&#13;
industrial countries and still growing.     The resulting large interest rate&#13;
payments will have to be shouldered for many years.        If inflation is kept&#13;
under control, only accelerated income growth will ease management of&#13;
corporate and public finances.&#13;
38.      Developing   countries  are  completing   their  financial   adjustment&#13;
phase.   They need a continuation of the world recovery to complete it, to&#13;
fully restore their creditworthiness, to regain access to the world capital&#13;
market and to concentrate on the structural adjustments of their economies&#13;
that are necessary to achieve long-term growth.        The domestic costs, and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
social  and   political  pressures   associated  with   the  current   financial&#13;
adjustment phase, are already quite high, and would become even more difficult&#13;
to bear without continued growth in export markets, a reduction in real&#13;
interest rates and resumption of capital inflows.     Without them the momentum&#13;
of policy reform in developing countries would also falter and the attainment&#13;
of structural adjustment goals would again be postponed.&#13;
39.      To cope with the sharp reduction in the net inflows of medium and&#13;
long term capital that occurred in 1982-84 as a consequence of the cutbacks in&#13;
international private lending, developing countries had no alternative but to&#13;
reduce their current account deficits.       To do so, in the face of rising&#13;
interest payments on existing and new debt, they had to move rapidly towards a&#13;
trade surplus. This was facilitated in 1983-84 by the widening of the trade&#13;
deficit  in  the  United States.     In fact, developing countries reached a&#13;
substantial positive balance in goods and non-factor services in 1984, as&#13;
their payments on interest and amortization on medium and long term debt&#13;
exceeded the value of the new loans they were able to obtain from official and&#13;
private sources.&#13;
40.      While  most  industrial   and  developing  countries were   drastically&#13;
reducing their current account deficits (or increasing their surpluses), the&#13;
payments deficit of the-United States was rapidly growing, as the mirror image&#13;
of the expanding US budget imbalance (Table 8).     The channelling of the rest&#13;
of the world's (ex-ante) excess savings into the United States in 1983-84&#13;
helped generate a level of world economic activity higher than would have&#13;
otherwise been possible. However, this pattern cannot last if output growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
Table 8: WORLD TRADE AND CURRENT ACCOUNT BALANCE&#13;
1970-72   1976-78    1981    1982    1983     1984&#13;
(Est.)&#13;
(-------------------Billions US$----------------)&#13;
TRADE BALANCE&#13;
Industrial Countries        10.5      -7.0     -28.0   -20.0   -16.0   -42.0&#13;
of which:&#13;
United States           -2.0     -26.0     -28.0   -36.5   -61.0  -108.0&#13;
Japan                     7.0      17.0     20.0    18.1    31.5    44.0&#13;
Europe                   1.7      -4.0     -24.0   -14.2    -1.0     5.0&#13;
High Income Oil Exporters     4.0      39.0    132.0    62.0    37.0    56.0&#13;
Developing Countries        -7.5     -23.0     -73.0   -48.0   -15.0     2.0&#13;
Other Countries             -2.5        5.0     -2.0    15.0    17.0    18.0&#13;
Total /a                 4.5       14.0     29.0     9.0    23.0    34.0&#13;
CURRENT ACCOUNT BALANCE /b&#13;
Industrial Countries        14.5       12.0     -4.0    -5.0    -3.0   -38.0&#13;
of which:&#13;
United States            1.0       -4.5     10.7    -3.8   -35.5  -100.0&#13;
Japan                     5.0      10.5      6.2     8.1    22.3    35.0&#13;
Europe                   8.5       12.0     -6.3    -2.1    14.3    23.4&#13;
High Income Oil Exporters /c 3.5       24.0     60.0    10.0   -11.5    -4.5&#13;
Developing Countries       -16.0     -38.0    -105.0  -100.0   -56.5   -35.5&#13;
Other Countries              1.0     -16.0      -8.0     8.0    10.0    12.0&#13;
Total /a                -0.5      -18.0    -57.0   -87.0   -61.0   -66.0&#13;
/a Reflects statistical errors and asymmetrics.&#13;
lb Excluding official transfers.&#13;
7-c Partially estimated in 1983 and 1984.&#13;
Source: IBRD, OECD and IMF.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
31 -&#13;
in Europe and Japan rise towards their potentials and developing countries&#13;
restore a measure of creditworthiness. It is unlikely that the United States&#13;
can continue to draw on external savings at the same rate as in 1984.     It is&#13;
also undesirable that it should do sp.      In the medium-term, a return to a&#13;
pattern of savings allocation more in line with the capital endowments of the&#13;
world's major regions would seem to be necessary on efficiency grounds.&#13;
Without renewed access to world capital markets and to the rest of the world's&#13;
excess savings, not only would the growth prospects of developing countries be&#13;
considerably reduced, but also those of the whole world economy. This implies&#13;
a return of industrial countries to a position of overall surplus on current&#13;
account and to a net flow of savings to developing countries.&#13;
41.      A period of sufficiently high and steady non-inflationary economic&#13;
growth is needed to allow the progressive reabsorption of idle resources&#13;
(particularly of unemployed labor), the correction of existing disequilibria&#13;
in financial stocks and flows, and the completion of structural adjustments&#13;
underway in industrial and developing countries and their fruition, in terms&#13;
of greater efficiency in resource use and in capital accumulation.           The&#13;
challenge lies in that a partial solution to these problems is a precondition&#13;
for sustained, non-inflationary growth, but it can hardly be achieved without&#13;
adequate growth already taking place.     Credible, sustained non-inflationary&#13;
growth constitutes both a means and an end, which could become even more&#13;
elusive unless it -is pursued without delay.&#13;
42.      The developing countries are seeking to regain a reasonable medium-&#13;
term balance in domestic and external finance.        They need a more stable&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
external environment in terms of market access and finance to complete their&#13;
financial adjustment processes.    Once this phase is over, they will have to&#13;
concentrate their efforts on the achievement conditions favorable to long term&#13;
growth, that is on the shifts in prices, in expenditures and in factor uses&#13;
most conducive to the sustained expansion of domestic output.&#13;
43.      The tempo of domestic policy reform in developing countries needs to&#13;
be maintained and whenever possible quickened for the second phase of their&#13;
adjustment process to bear maximum results.       Reform needs, though country&#13;
specific, have some common threads. Better utilization of existing productive&#13;
resources  is clearly paramount.      Greater efficiency is in large part a&#13;
function of internal price relationships and of correct balance between&#13;
domestic and world prices. Subsidies which distort prices and encourage waste&#13;
must be reduced, along with those which directly sustain undesirable&#13;
activities or inefficient enterprises. Reduction in subsidies is often a key&#13;
precondition for reducing fiscal deficits, themselves an indirect cause of&#13;
inflationary pressure.   Reduced budget deficits, complemented by appropriate&#13;
monetary policies, are a precondition for the build-up of efficient financial&#13;
markets, which can attract renewed inflows of foreign capital and serve to&#13;
channel efficiently domestic savings into domestic investments. Allocation of&#13;
available capital resources, whether market or state determined, needs to be&#13;
inspired by stringent performance objectives.    The more flexible the domestic&#13;
price system and the lower trade and exchange rate distortions, the greater&#13;
the chances that private and public investment decisions will be economically&#13;
and socially productive.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
44.      In shaping the future, the role of economic policies is central and&#13;
clear. In the short-term, a key objective of policies in both industrial and&#13;
developing countries must be to ensure the continuation of the present&#13;
economic recovery. In the medium-term, the objective of policies is to ensure&#13;
sustained non-inflationary growth. The industrial countries bear a particular&#13;
responsibility for ensuring, through appropriate domestic policies, that&#13;
freedom of trade is maintained, that capital flows from the richer towards the&#13;
poorer countries are renewed, and that national economic objectives are&#13;
compatible with each other and with international efficiency in the use of&#13;
resources.    International  cooperation for these objectives,     so effective&#13;
during the past three decades, is both a necessary condition for resumed&#13;
growth and dependent upon it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
V. MEDIUM TERM ALTERNATIVES FOR INDUSTRIAL AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES&#13;
45.      The next 10 years, viewed schematically for the purpose of analyzing&#13;
macroeconomic policy and setting priorities, can be divided into two phases: a&#13;
period of unwinding the existing financial tensions, restoring more&#13;
sustainable global payment balances, normalizing interest and exchange rates,&#13;
decisively reducing inflationary expectations, and achieving a better&#13;
equilibrium in net flows of funds; followed by a period of faster output&#13;
growth in industrial countries and of overall development in developing&#13;
countries, funded by sustainable patterns of domestic capital accumulation and&#13;
of net foreign borrowing.    These two phases roughly coincide with the medium&#13;
and the long term perspectives normally taken in World Bank World Development&#13;
Reports. Attention is focused here on the first phase.&#13;
46.      Reasonably favorable central assumptions for the medium-term policy&#13;
scenarios are that industrial countries will attempt to bring about a&#13;
convergence of real interest rates with the trend growth rates of their&#13;
outputs, and to reduce the deficit in their current accounts without&#13;
disrupting the present phase of recovery in world economic activity.       It is&#13;
further assumed, in part as a result of a correct growth perspective being&#13;
maintained by policymakers, and in part as the result of the postulated fiscal&#13;
and monetary adjustments, that trade protection will not increase during this&#13;
period.  This assumption would be a break from recent trends.    The effects of&#13;
an increase in trade protectionism will be examined as part of the downside&#13;
risks to the main scenario.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
47.      Given the short-term dynamics-of the.4984-85 situation, characterized&#13;
by strong financial tensions and considerable imbalances in trade and&#13;
payments flows .within and across regions, progress towards these objectives&#13;
will not be easy.    Dealing in a positive and anticipatory fashion with the&#13;
risks inherent in the current situation will require moving away from policies&#13;
which have been successful in the short run.      Good timing, and a degree.of&#13;
compatibility (whether planned or coincidental) --of financial policies within&#13;
and across countries are also prerequisites.       An added difficulty is that&#13;
correcting existing internal and external imbalances may, at least in the&#13;
short term, tend to restrain output growth in both industrial and developing&#13;
countries.   However, at least in industrial countries, actual inflation and&#13;
inflationary expectations seem to be under better control than at any time in&#13;
the past 15 years, and this should leave some leeway to the policy adjustments&#13;
necessary  to sustain growth in the short-term.        Moderate demand growth,&#13;
continued restraint in the setting of wage rates and expectations of very slow&#13;
increases in the prices of internationally traded primary commodities&#13;
(including oil) -should facilitate the task of, financial authorities in&#13;
regaining and maintaining control of both internal and external balances,&#13;
without unduly great risks.&#13;
48.      Considerable uncertainties    thus surround the attainability of the&#13;
policy objectives assumed to be pursued in the medium term, and not only&#13;
because the efficacy of available policy instruments may itself be in doubt.&#13;
However, there seems to be enough agreement on the desirability of the&#13;
objectives to be pursued, appreciation of the scale of the adjustment problem&#13;
at hand (particularly as it relates to the United States and to developing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
countries), and signs of a will for action to make it reasonable to assume&#13;
that the opportunity to start a viable transition to sustainable and balanced&#13;
growth in the 1990s will be seized.        However,  if the assumption of the&#13;
adoption of gradual adjustment policies seems reasonable, it nevertheless&#13;
remains an assumption.    We have not forecast that national authorities will&#13;
indeed act in this way; we have merely explored some of the consequences that&#13;
will ensue if they do--and also if they do not.&#13;
49.      A continuation of existing policy trends would likely lead to medium&#13;
term results appreciably worse in terms of growth, and no better in terms of&#13;
inflation, than would a moderate but steady adjustment scenario. Moreover, a&#13;
"do nothing" scenario presents considerable risks of crisis, given that the&#13;
continued financing of some of the persisting fiscal and external payments&#13;
disequilibria is in no way automatically ensured.        Even without a sudden&#13;
financing crisis, pressures towards greater trade protections could become&#13;
irresistible in many countries. Avoiding these risks should be an additional&#13;
reason for looking at feasible adjustment alternatives.&#13;
A. A Xediumr-Term Scenario with Moderate Policy Adjustments: 1985-90&#13;
A.l: The Industrial Countries&#13;
50.      The assumptions underlying the medium-term scenario illustrated here&#13;
reflect appreciable adjustment in the existing financial imbalances, starting&#13;
with the industrial countries. While moderate and gradual, such adjustments&#13;
are assumed to start quite soon, probably within 1985 in terms of policy&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
decisions, and in 1986-87 in terms of initial effects. They are also expected&#13;
to be broadly credible in the various markets and to generate some positive&#13;
anticipatory effects. A key component of the overall adjustment process here&#13;
envisaged is a change in the current fiscal position of the United States and&#13;
a realignment of the US monetary stance to this new situation.        The other&#13;
major industrial countries are expected to assess correctly the trend, scale&#13;
and likely effects of the US fiscal adjustment and to take action to ensure&#13;
broad compatibility of financial policies- across the major industrial areas,&#13;
in particular by ensuring that fiscal adjustment in the United States does not&#13;
lead to overall tightening of global demand.      While broad compatibility of&#13;
policies is presumed, active coordination is not envisaged.&#13;
51.      The reduction of    the US budget    deficit,  beginning  in 1986 and&#13;
continuing in the medium term is postulated to be such as to reduce the&#13;
Federal budget deficit to about 3 percent of 1990 GNP, from about 5 percent of&#13;
GNP in 1984.    Monetary policy is assumed partly to offset the short-term&#13;
negative impact on domestic output of this tightening in fiscal policy.&#13;
Continued wage restraint, consistent with current and projected levels of&#13;
unemployment, should make a limited monetary accommodation possible and still&#13;
ensure a non-inflationary environment.     The credibility of the change in US&#13;
fiscal position should also be of help in reducing expectations of future&#13;
inflation.&#13;
52.      Fiscal and monetary stances are assumed to change in other industrial&#13;
countries. A parallel relaxation of monetary conditions is expected to take&#13;
place in those European countries where domestic inflation rates and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
inflationary expectations have already been brought under satisfactory&#13;
control.   In some cases it is expected that the restrictiveness of fiscal&#13;
policy, as measured by the changes in structural budget balances, will be&#13;
loosened, and taxes changed to stimulate investments.       This should also be&#13;
possible in Japan.&#13;
53.      The main financial consequences of these gradual policy changes in&#13;
industrial countries during the 1985-90 period are expected to be:         (a) a&#13;
progressive decline in real interest rates on US dollar assets; (b) a gradual&#13;
depreciation of the US currency; (c) substantial stability of inflation&#13;
(measured in local currencies); and (d) a very modest increase in the real&#13;
price of non-fuel primary commodities, accompanied by a small decline in real&#13;
fuel prices. Economic growth in industrial countries is expected to continue&#13;
at a positive, if relatively modest, rate and to show greater stability than&#13;
in the past ten years.    These results would ensure that an unwinding of the&#13;
existing financial tensions takes place in a context of reasonable, non-&#13;
inflationary growth, that would leave developing countries room for continued&#13;
internal and external adjustment (Table 9).&#13;
54.      The  postulated  fiscal-monetary corrections    are expected   to bring&#13;
about a considerable reduction in real dollar interest rates:           six-month&#13;
dollar LIBOR rates should gradually decline from the current 7 percent to&#13;
about 4 percent in real terms by the end of the 1980s, and real long term&#13;
dollar interest rates should gradually fall to a 3 - 4 percent range.        This&#13;
would bring them down close to the trend growth of real output by the end of&#13;
the transition period, a significant break from the trends of the past five&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- -39 -&#13;
Table 9: AVERAGE PERFORMANCE OF INDUSTRIAL AND DEVELOPING&#13;
COUNTRIES, 1960-90&#13;
1960-73    1973-79    1980-85     1985-90&#13;
INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES&#13;
(Average Annual Percent Change)&#13;
GDP Growth                           4.9        2.8        2.1         3.0&#13;
Inflation Rate-/a                    5.9        8.0        5.8         5.2&#13;
(Average Annual Rate)&#13;
Real Interest Rate /b /c             2.5        0.7        6.8         4.1&#13;
Nominal Interest Rate 7a;            5.8        8.4       12.6         9.5&#13;
DEVELOPING COUNTRIES /d&#13;
(Average Annual Percent Change)&#13;
GDP Growth                           6.3        5.2        3.0         5.0&#13;
Low-Income Asia                   5.9        5.2        6.4         5.6&#13;
Low-Income Africa                 3.5        2.1        1.5         3.1&#13;
Middle-Income Oil Importers&#13;
Major Exporters of Manuf.       6.7        5.8        2.0         5.5&#13;
Other                           5.3        4.3        1.5         3.8&#13;
Middle-Income Oil Exporters       6.9        4.9        1.8         4.4&#13;
Export Volumes /e                    5.2        4.1        4.7         5.3&#13;
Manufactures /e                  13.8       11.0         7.7        8.5&#13;
Primary /e                        3.6        1.3        2.6         2.5&#13;
Import Volumes /e                    5.9        5.9        2.0         6.5&#13;
Trade Prices (in current US$)&#13;
Manufactures                      3.8       12.7       -1.8         7.9&#13;
Oil                               4.6       37.9       -1.4         7.1&#13;
Non-Oil                           4.8        7.8       -7.0         9.5&#13;
/a  GDP deflator in-local currencies.&#13;
7W   6-month dollar LIBOR.  Owing to the lack of historical data, the 1960-73&#13;
and 1973-79 period averages use a 3-month Eurocurrency rate.&#13;
/c  Deflated by the U.S. GDP deflator.&#13;
7W_ Estimates/projections for 1980-85 and 1985-90 are based on a sample of 90&#13;
developing countries.&#13;
/e  Historical growth rates are for the periods 1965-73 and 1973-80.&#13;
Source: World Bank, Economic Analysis and Projections Department.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
years, when the divergence from trend output growth has increased.       Nominal&#13;
rates would follow a similar path from 1986 onwards.&#13;
55.      Under  this  scenario,   by  1990  the  dollar  would  have  gradually&#13;
depreciated by about 15 percent in terms of the SDR, relative to its average&#13;
1984 level.    This trend could start as the combined result of reduced US&#13;
borrowing of foreign funds (as the growth of the US economy returns to a more&#13;
normal and sustainable rate), and of the relaxation of monetary restraints.&#13;
The reduction in expectations of future inflation generated by a credible&#13;
program of budget deficit reduction, continued wage restraint and the slow&#13;
growth of domestic unit costs should help allow the movement to remain&#13;
gradual. A sympathetic relaxation of monetary conditions in major European&#13;
countries would support the US policy adjustments.       It would also help to&#13;
ensure, via a broadly parallel decline in short term interest rates, that the&#13;
depreciation of the dollar be gradual and orderly.&#13;
56.      Inflation in industrial countries would remain stable at 4 to 5&#13;
percent throughout the period.    The rate of increase of domestic prices would&#13;
tend to accelerate somewhat in the US, but decelerate in Europe, as exchange&#13;
rate adjustment unfolds.       This process should be helped not only by a&#13;
normalization of consumer expectations, but also by overall stability in&#13;
international  commodity  prices.      Prices  of  non-fuel   commodities  would&#13;
increase in real terms at only 1.5 percent per annum between 1985 and 1990,&#13;
while fuel prices would on average decrease in real terms by about 1 percent&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
per annum. 1/ Manufactured goods' export prices are also expected to increase&#13;
only moderately in local currency terms, reflecting the slow growth of unit&#13;
labor costs and competitive market conditions. In dollar terms, their prices&#13;
would grow faster (at about 8 percent per annum in 1985-90), reflecting the US&#13;
dollar depreciation.   This would reverse the cumulative 14 percent decline in&#13;
their dollar prices which occurred between 1981 and 1984.&#13;
57.      Under this scenario of gradual adjustment, industrial countries' real&#13;
growth would average 3 percent per annum over the' 1985-90 period..        This&#13;
represents only a moderate acceleration of trend growth with respect to the&#13;
previous five years    (2.1 percent per annum).     As trade protectionism is&#13;
assumed to stay at its present level, these growth' results must be seen as a&#13;
positive, if limited, outcome of a moderate fiscal-monetary adjustment&#13;
package.   If there also occurred substantial realignments in factor prices,&#13;
and a reduction of rigidities in product and factor markets (particularly&#13;
labor markets), growth would accelerate further, as a result of higher&#13;
investment and of greater efficiency in the use of factors of production. In&#13;
any case, this moderate adjustment package would also lead to a further&#13;
acceleration of growth and slowdown in- inflation in industrial countries&#13;
further in the 1990s.   Simple continuation of these macro policy trends would&#13;
improve the average growth of real output by half a percentage point in 1990-&#13;
95, and reduce average inflation by about the same amount. Real interest rate&#13;
normalization would also be completed in this period, by a convergence of real&#13;
interest rates and real growth rates of output in the early 1990s.&#13;
1/ The export prices of manufactured goods are used as deflators (Table 9).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
58.      The  projected   behavior  of  current  account  balances  is causally&#13;
related  to the projected path of interest rates.         Globally,  the current&#13;
account deficit of the industrial countries would decline. This would involve&#13;
some reallocation of surpluses from Japan to Europe, and a decline in the&#13;
current account deficit of the United States. The overall savings deficit of&#13;
the industrial countries would thus diminish.    Taking into account errors and&#13;
omissions (which prevent a precise balancing of the global payments account),&#13;
the reduction in the overall current account deficit of industrial countries&#13;
would allow increased financing of the capital needs of the developing&#13;
countries, and some untightening of global capital markets. Nevertheless, at&#13;
the end of the period under consideration (1990), global balance will not yet&#13;
have been re-established.     In particular, the United States would still be&#13;
running a substantial deficit on current account, and also a fairly large&#13;
structural (full employment) budget deficit. The persistence of these is not&#13;
desirable; nor is it likely that their financing could continue to be ensured&#13;
without risk.     It is therefore assumed that an effort towards a further&#13;
reduction and ultimate elimination of these twin deficits will be made before&#13;
1990.   Indeed, the gradual nature of the adjustment (in particular, of the&#13;
decline of the dollar) partly rest on the assumption that policies will&#13;
rapidly be put in place, and in such a way as to lend credibility to the&#13;
expectation that the U.S. payments deficit will in fact be eliminated before&#13;
an excessive foreign debt is accumulated.     Given the importance of the first&#13;
steps towards the achievement of this goal, which are assumed to take place&#13;
during the 1985-90 period, success in the transition phase should make the&#13;
rest comparatively easy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
A.2: The Developing Countries&#13;
59.      Moderate but timely policy changes in the industrial countries would&#13;
make it easier-for developing countries to complete their internal adjustment&#13;
process and to return, through trade and renewed access to private capital&#13;
markets,  to a relatively    fast sustainable rate of economic growth.        The&#13;
interdependences are -numerous.    Growth in the industrial countries    imports&#13;
(itself  dependent   on  income   growth  there   and  on   the  containment  of&#13;
protectionism) is a necessary condition for the restoration of the developing&#13;
countries' creditworthiness.    To allow developing countries first to resume&#13;
fully their contractual debt service, and then to reduce the share of exports&#13;
absorbed by it, the export recovery of 1983-84 needs to be sustained.       Trade&#13;
growth is needed not only to service debt and to finance indispensable&#13;
imports; it is vital to promoting specialization and efficiency in domestic&#13;
production.&#13;
60.      In the medium term scenario just described, developing countries'&#13;
export volumes could grow by about 5 percent per annum between 1985 and 1990:&#13;
8.5 percent for manufactures products and about 2.5, percent for primary&#13;
commodities   (Table  9).   Relative   to GDP  trends   in both  industrial   and&#13;
developing   countries,  such   export  growth  would   constitute  a   favorable&#13;
performance and would entail further success of policies to promote exports&#13;
and  to penetrate markets    in industrial   countries.   Developing countries&#13;
overall terms of trade would remain virtually unchanged over the period, as&#13;
the projected modest changes in the real prices of non-fuel commodities and of&#13;
oil have virtually offsetting effects.     However, there are some differences&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
across country groups:     oil importing middle-income countries should enjoy&#13;
some improvement, mirrored by the worsening in the terms of trade of oil&#13;
exporting countries.    Low-income countries, which rely on commodity exports&#13;
with the weakest price prospects, are likely to face a worsening of their&#13;
terms of trade during the 1985-90 period (Table 10).&#13;
61.      The  projected   evolution  of   financial  markets  would  also   help&#13;
developing countries.   Lower interest rates would reduce their debt service&#13;
burden and, together with export growth, help restore the creditworthiness of&#13;
many countries, particularly the heavily indebted middle-income countries of&#13;
Latin America.    As their debt-service ratios fall from the extremely high&#13;
levels of 1982-83 and as international private banks become more confident in&#13;
the ability of a number of developing countries to sustain export growth,&#13;
voluntary  lending  could  gradually   resume  (Table  11).    This  would  help&#13;
accelerate the return to adequate investment growth, together with a gradual&#13;
relaxation of the restraints on private consumption.&#13;
62.      Lower interest rates and adequate export growth would also ease the&#13;
adjustment path of those middle-income countries--particularly in Asia--which&#13;
are still creditworthy and continue to rely on significant private capital&#13;
inflows. They would be able to reduce their balance of payments deficit more&#13;
gradually than some of the large borrowers in Latin America had to do in&#13;
recent years, and thus continue to cope with external imbalances at lesser&#13;
costs in terms of reduced investments and foregone consumption.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 10: CHANGE IN TERMS OF TRADE, 1965-90&#13;
(Percent change per annum)&#13;
1965-73   1973-80   1981   1982   1983   1984 /b   1985 /c  1985-90 /c&#13;
TERIIS OF TE&#13;
Developing Countries /a         0.5        2.0     0.3   -0.5   -0.6    0.8     -1.1        0.0&#13;
Low-Income                 0.4      -1.5    -0.3   -1.5     0.9    3.4     -2.1       -0.1&#13;
Asia                     0.8      -1.6      1.1   -2.1    0.5    3.1     -1.8       -0.1&#13;
Africa                  -0.7      -1.0    -5.6     0.3    2.8    5.2     -3.8       -0.3&#13;
Oil Importers             -0.2      -2.3    -4.2    -0.7    2.5    0.1      0.0        0.1&#13;
Oil Exporters             -0.4       9.0      9.8    1.0   -7.0    1.0     -2.8       -0.3&#13;
High-Income Oil Exporters       2i9       12.3    14.6    2.3   -8.6   -1.0      n.a.       n.a.&#13;
Industrial Countries           -0.5      -3.5    -2.1     2.0    2.1   -0.2      n.a.       n.a.&#13;
/a  Estimates for developing countries are based on a sample of 90 developing economies.&#13;
7W Preliminary estimates.&#13;
7T Projected.&#13;
Source: World Bank, Economic Analysis and Projections Department.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
63.      Private capital inflows would in any case be less important than in&#13;
the 1970s as a vehicle for increasing developing countries' investment&#13;
resources; private net lending to developing countries is expected to grow&#13;
only slowly in the next five years.    The share of developing countries in the&#13;
total claims of private banks is also anticipated to decline during the&#13;
remainder of the 1980s.    However, the role of international private capital&#13;
would still be quite important for some groups of developing countries,&#13;
particularly the middle-income countries that are major exporters of&#13;
manufactures and for the large low-income Asian countries.&#13;
64.      Finally, official flows to middle-income countries could grow more&#13;
evenly and be used more effectively.    In a steadier trade growth environment,&#13;
where current account imbalances in major industrial countries were also being&#13;
reduced and protectionist practices kept in check, export credits could again&#13;
expand faster than world trade.      Given the expected lower growth rate of&#13;
private capital flows and the uncertainties surrounding them, growth in&#13;
official aid flows would be particularly important not only for low-income&#13;
countries,  but   also  for  many  middle-income   developing  countries.     By&#13;
facilitating the implementation of necessary policy reforms and by becoming&#13;
the catalyst for other capital flows, the overall impact of higher aid flows&#13;
could be a multiple of the yield of the investments that they directly&#13;
finance.&#13;
65.      Improvement in the economic outlook of the developing countries does&#13;
not depend only on the external conditions they face.          Sustained export&#13;
growth, the essential precondition for creditworthiness, depends both on&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table I1: Q'UERMTAC'WCO   SBALA8  AM ITS 1I1hCING IM OEVLRPI1DG COUNTRIES, 1980, 1983 and 1990 /a&#13;
(Billions of current US$)&#13;
ALL DEVELOPING&#13;
COUNTRiRs                   LCM-INCoIR COUNTRiEs                                  NIDOI.B-INcoNR CoUNTRIES&#13;
Major Exporters                               Oil Eaporting&#13;
Asia                 Africa             of Manufactures       Other Non-OIl            countries&#13;
1980    1983   1990   1980    1983   1990   1980    1983   1990    1980   1983   1990    190   1983    1990   1980    1983   1990&#13;
Imi WKNTl (GM)                                -53.6  -16.0  -36.8   -15.8   -7.2   -26.6   -5.4   -4.3    -5.5  -28.9     0.5    0.7  -18.2   -12.7   -7.7    14.6    7.9     2.2&#13;
1011ISr ON MtU M        IAC   T  D13          -32.9  -46.6  -84.2    -1.4   -1.6   -6.0    -0.7   -0.7    -1.9  -14.9   -20.1  -36.9   -4.5    -6.7  -11.4   -11.5  -17.5   -27.9&#13;
Official                              -5.9    -9.0  -20.9   -. 7    -1.0   -2.2    -0.3   -0.3   -1.7    -2.2   -3.3    -6.8   -1.1    -1.9   -4.8   -1.7    -2.5   -5.3   1&#13;
Private                              -26.9   -37.6  -63.3   -0.7    -0.6   -3.7   -0.4    -0.3   -0.2   -12.7  -16.8  -30.0    -3.3   -4.8    -6.6   -9.8   -15.0  -22.6   4,'&#13;
C91mmAOOf      EALAmf lb                      -67.8  -56.7  -83.5    -9.6   -1.0   -20.5   -5.9   -4.9    -6.7  -35.4   -22.0  -27.2   -18.6  -17.7   -13.8    1.5  -11.1   -15.2&#13;
M   omCI      UNUSIU                       11.6    11.7   22.9    2.0    2.0     2.8    2.1     1.9    3.5     2.5    3.2    9.1     3.1    2.7     4.5    2.0     1.9    3.0&#13;
MI=A      I.D T     uoamii                 58.4   48.8    72.6    4.9    4.2    19.8    3.3     1.9    2.9    21.4   16.6   28.7    11.8    7.9     6.4   17.0    18.1    14.9&#13;
Official                              21.6    20.8   27.4     3.4    3.5    8:3     2.4    1.9     3.5    5.1    6.5     3.2    5.9 .   5.2    6.0     4.8    3.7     7.1&#13;
Private                               36.8    28.0   45.2    1.5     0.7   11.5     1.0    0.0   -0.6    16.3   10.1    25.5    5.9     2.8    0.4    12.2   14.5     7.9&#13;
liOtao     [to:&#13;
Debt Outatanding end Disbursed            429.7   619.6 1030.3   38.4    46.3  129.4   20.8    25.4   41.9   166.6  242.0   395.2   68.3   97.8   151.0   135.6  208.2   312.8&#13;
Aa a percent of GNP                   21.0    31.3   23.3    7.8     9.-i  10.6    39.9   52.2    44.8   22.8   34.7    25.0   30.2    48.7   36.2    24.9   39.9    28.0&#13;
As a percent of Exports               89.8   130.8   94.9  - 96.7   98.9  118.3   175.8  279.5  252.1    77.3   105.2   67.8  120.71  175.5  125.3    87.4  157.8   121.9&#13;
Debt Service as a Percent of Exports       16.0   19.0    17.4    8.0    8.3-   10.9   12.5.   16.5   26.8    16.1   16.2    14.5   17.2   23.1    22.3   17.8    26.1   24.0&#13;
/a ligures are based on a sasple of 90 developing countrite.&#13;
Tb Excludes official transfers.&#13;
Source: Vorld Bank. Econogic AsnlysL antd Projections Departmnt.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
demand growth in the industrial countries and on developing countries price&#13;
competitiveness.   The role of competitiveness is especially important for the&#13;
exporters of manufactures, and also for exporters of those foods and&#13;
industrial raw materials for which alternative supply sources exist in&#13;
industrial  countries.    Export  price  competitiveness   depends  on relative&#13;
productivity, and on exchange rates.     Domestic policies have effects on the&#13;
former, and fully determine the latter.      Openness of domestic markets, and&#13;
thus the degree of competition and the structure of incentives afforded to&#13;
domestic   producers,    is   an   important   determinant   of    productivity.&#13;
Rationalization and movement towards greater liberalization of existing trade&#13;
and exchange regimes are important requirements for improved performance of&#13;
many developing countries in the 1980s.&#13;
66.      Similarly,  capital   inflows  contribute  to  determining   investment&#13;
levels, but domestic savings are the key source of investment financing.&#13;
Encouragement of savings must remain a principal objective of development&#13;
policy.  Efficiency in the use of available savings and, more broadly, of all&#13;
resources is not less important.      Price distortions foster waste in many&#13;
countries.    They frequently involve waste of capital.       In some countries&#13;
misaligned incentives and inefficient firms (public or private) may actually&#13;
destroy national wealth. Through foreign borrowing, they may be absorbing and&#13;
misusing not only savings of the past, but also those of the future. Improved&#13;
processes of capital accumulation must, therefore, be accompanied by greater&#13;
efficiency in the use of domestic capital.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
67.      For low-income developing countries, external and internal conditions&#13;
for growth are -even more diverse than for middle-income countries.         More&#13;
dependent on exports of primary commodities and generally less dependent on&#13;
international private capital inflows than their middle-income counterparts,&#13;
they face very mixed prospects.     India and China, whose overall performance&#13;
dominates the low-income Asian countries, appear in general well placed to&#13;
continue  to make   steady progress   in agricultural   production.    Continued&#13;
internal policy reform should help boost domestic production and improve their&#13;
export prospects. The relative weight of manufactures in their total exports&#13;
is greater than the average at their income levels.         The ratio of their&#13;
overall exports to GDP and of their manufactures exports to industrial&#13;
production is still low, but these conditions magnify the potential benefits&#13;
of a continued trend towards greater external openness.&#13;
68.      Under this scenario one can foresee a modest increase in the current&#13;
account deficit of these countries, in absolute amount and as a percentage of&#13;
GDP. Within a global scenario of steady growth and declining interest rates,&#13;
both India and China should be able to take on and use effectively increased&#13;
amounts of private capital.      Under the conditions assumed in industrial&#13;
countries, and their implications for world capital markets, these large&#13;
countries should be able to expand their borrowing on commercial terms without&#13;
assuming undue risks, particularly if they can also rely on the projected&#13;
steady support by official capital flows. The expected increase in their debt&#13;
service and debt-to-GNP ratios is thus a reflection of these two economies&#13;
improved performance and increased flexibility, and of improved global&#13;
conditions. Both should maintain a strong growth performance in the remainder&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
of  the  1980s.   Most other low-income Asian countries could,       under  this&#13;
scenario, replicate this performance, although at generally lower levels, and&#13;
with greater reliance on aid rather than commercial capital.&#13;
69.      By contrast, low-income African countries face a more uncertain and&#13;
difficult economic future.     They suffer from slow demand growth for their&#13;
exports, declining terms of trade and low productivity in their agriculture.&#13;
The region, moreover, has suffered enormously from natural disasters. It has&#13;
experienced an almost constant decline in per capita income over the past&#13;
decade.  Current high debt service and debt to GNP ratios are not expected to&#13;
return to historical levels within the next decade.          Low-income African&#13;
countries have virtually no capacity to borrow in private capital markets.&#13;
Their external debt is small in absolute amount, but very large in relation to&#13;
their servicing capacity.&#13;
70.      Naturally,  external conditions are not alone responsible for the&#13;
African countries   plight.   Many domestic policy causes of their inadequate&#13;
earlier performance have been identified elsewhere.        Some improvement in&#13;
performance has already taken place in many countries, particularly in overall&#13;
demand management.&#13;
71.      Preventing a further sharp decline in per capita income in low-income&#13;
African countries would require steady improvement of domestic policies and&#13;
better  external  support.    Even  under  our  relatively   optimistic  central&#13;
scenario, net capital flows to these countries are expected to drop&#13;
considerably in the medium term, because of the relatively slow growth of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
gross flows in nominal terms and the concomitant substantial growth of debt&#13;
service.  Nowhere is aid a sufficient condition for economic improvement; but&#13;
nowhere is it more evidently one of the necessary conditions than in Sub-&#13;
Saharan Africa.   Without a significant increase in the net resource inflows&#13;
provided by official development assistance (bilateral and multilateral),&#13;
adequate support for ongoing policy reforms and restructuring of development&#13;
and  investment  programs   will  not be   forthcoming.    This will   require  a&#13;
combination of growing    gross  inflows  and,  in  some cases,   of additional&#13;
rollovers of amortization charges on earlier loans. As emphasized by,a recent&#13;
World Bank report on Sub-Saharan Africa, it is necessary at a minimum that net&#13;
capital inflows be maintained in real terms at their 1980-82 ievels; otherwise&#13;
these countries will not have a chance to stop the economic and social decline&#13;
of the past 15 years. 1/&#13;
72.      With an improved external environment and a measure of success in&#13;
domestic policies, developing countries as a group should be able to return to&#13;
a fairly rapid overall rate of output growth in the second part of the&#13;
1980s.   A global export growth of about -5 percent per annum in 1985-90,&#13;
combined with expansion of official development assistance in line- with GNP&#13;
growth in industrial countries and growth in net private lending of about 10&#13;
percent per annum (from the very low levels-of 1985) should allow developing&#13;
countries to sustain import growth slightly above that of exports.          Under&#13;
these conditions their current account deficit in 1990 would be almost twice&#13;
1/  World   Bank,   Towards  Sustained   Development   in   Sub-Saharan  Africa,&#13;
Washington, D.C., 1984.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
as large as in 1983 in current dollars, but would decline from 29 to 22&#13;
percent of GNP.   The debt/export ratio for all developing countries would also&#13;
decline and tend to return to levels roughly comparable to those of 1980,&#13;
while the debt service ratio would return to the same level as in 1983 (Table&#13;
11).&#13;
73.      On average, developing countries would considerably improve their&#13;
growth prospects with respect to the first half of the 1980s.         They would&#13;
experience an annual growth rate of real GDP of about 5 percent (Table 9).&#13;
Low-income countries are expected to grow slightly faster rate than middle-&#13;
income countries; but this result is totally attributable to the projected&#13;
fast growth of China and, to a lesser extent, India. In per capita terms, all&#13;
regions would advance, with the exception of low-income Africa, where even&#13;
stemming recent declines would require considerable effort (Table 12).&#13;
74.      In  summary,   under  this  scenario,   the  salient  features  of   the&#13;
transition period would be:      (a) a modest but steady growth in economic&#13;
activity in industrial countries, and a reasonably favorable growth of markets&#13;
for manufactured goods of developing countries; (b) a reduction of the global&#13;
current account deficit of industrial countries; (c) gradually declining&#13;
interest rates;   (d) a return to substantive creditworthiness of developing&#13;
countries and renewal of voluntary lending to them by international commercial&#13;
banks; and (e) a fairly substantial increase in real per capita output growth&#13;
in all regions (except for Africa South of the Sahara, where a return towards&#13;
as yet modest growth would also be in sharp contrast to the earlier decline).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 12: GROWTH RATES OF GDP PER CAPITA FOR DEVELOPING COUNTRIES, 1965-90&#13;
(Percent change per annum)&#13;
1965-73   1973-80   1981  '1982   1983   1984 /b  1985 /c  1985-90 /c&#13;
DEVELOPING COUNTRIES /a             4.1       3.3     1.2   -0.2   -0.1    2.1      2.4        3.0&#13;
Low-Income                      3.0       3.1     2.0    3.0    5.2    4.7      4.1        3.6&#13;
Asia                       3.2       3.5     2.5    3.4    6.0    5.3      4.4        3.9&#13;
Africa                     1.3       0.0    -1.4   -2.4   -2.4   -1.5     -0.3       -0.2&#13;
Oil Importers                   4.6       3.1    -0.2   -1.4   -1.6    1.1      1.6        2.9&#13;
Major Exporters of&#13;
Manufactures             5.1       3.5    -0.4   -0.7   -1.3    1.5      2.0        3.5&#13;
)ther Non-Oil              2.8       2.1     0.8   -3.2   -2.1    0.2      0.7        1.3&#13;
Oil Exporters                   4.5       3.1     2.0   -1.7   -3.6    0.1      1.3        1.8&#13;
/a All data are based on a sample of 90 developing countries.&#13;
7-b Preliminary estimates.&#13;
7-c Projected.&#13;
Source: World Bank, Economic Analysis and Projections Department.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54 -&#13;
75.      The   reduction  in  the   current  account   deficits  of   industrial&#13;
countries, while representing a move in the right direction, will still be a&#13;
long way off the desirable objective of a surplus.       In a period when very&#13;
large surpluses are not expected to reappear soon in high income oil exporting&#13;
countries, the restoration of a substantial surplus position in the global&#13;
current account of industrial countries is a precondition for the cessation of&#13;
net resource flows from the developing to the industrial countries.&#13;
76.      Managing   the  transition  period  is   going  to  require   sense  of&#13;
direction.   The practical steps are numerous and gradual.     To keep a steady&#13;
course will require perseverance in the face of less than dramatic results.&#13;
Not doing so, would imply not only the loss of recent hard-won gains, but&#13;
possibly incurring further and much more serious failures.&#13;
77.      The type of policy adjustment here envisaged only includes what is&#13;
deemed essential to the continuation of the current world economic recovery&#13;
and to the achievement of moderate, steady growth during the transition&#13;
period.    At the higher end of the adjustment spectrum one could easily&#13;
envisage a range of policy changes that would have even more beneficial&#13;
effects on the world economy. If, for example, in addition to the changes in&#13;
fiscal and monetary mixes assumed in the moderate policy adjustment scenario,&#13;
one envisaged an actual decrease in trade protectionism and a growth of real&#13;
wages at a rate below that of overall production (so as to allow a buildup of&#13;
profits and of savings), incomes and employment could grow much faster still&#13;
in both industrial and developing countries. Further improvements could come&#13;
from improvements in labor mobility, from greater flexibility in labor and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
capital utilizati6oi and, particularly- in the United States, from increased&#13;
private savings propensities.&#13;
B. The Risks of Non-Adjustment and the Effects on Developing Countries&#13;
78.      Continuation of present policies and lack of fiscal adjustment in&#13;
industrial countries, especially in the United States, would pose a serious&#13;
threat to the durability of the present economic recovery. If existing fiscal&#13;
and payment imbalances were to widen, this could well put an end to the&#13;
recovery and cause a return to wide cyclical swings in the world economy.&#13;
Continued high interest rates would tend to slow down the growth of private&#13;
investments, consumption and real output in the United States and in the rest&#13;
of the industrialized world.     Budget imbalances would in turn tend to widen&#13;
further, because of ensuing cyclical reduction in the growth of fiscal&#13;
revenues and increases in interest payments.     The interest service burden on&#13;
public debt, on average already close to 5 percent of GNP in the seven major&#13;
industrial countries (up from 2 percent in the 1970s)- would increase further,&#13;
thus reducing by itself the already limited flexibility of fiscal policy.&#13;
79.      The deterioration of world economic conditions could even be more&#13;
severe if the large fiscal and external payment imbalance of the United States&#13;
were to meet serious financing constraints deriving from changes in portfolio&#13;
preferences of wealth holders.    Unless credible measures are taken to reduce&#13;
the fiscal deficit of the United States, external savers would, at some point&#13;
soon, raise the interest premium they demand for accepting the exchange risk&#13;
inherent in financing the US deficit.     A sharp rise in dollar interest rates&#13;
or a sudden, sharp devaluation of the dollar could ensue. As the latter would&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
renew inflationary pressures and inflationary expectations whose control would&#13;
require considerable monetary tightening in the United States.      The rise in&#13;
interest rates that might ensue could be even more pronounced and the&#13;
deterioration of growth conditions in industrial countries sharper and&#13;
deeper.    Other  industrial  countries might   then be unable    to prevent   a&#13;
recession even if they relax their own financial policies.&#13;
80.      Employment,   under   these  circumstances,   would   suffer.     Trade&#13;
protectionist pressure could then become irresistible.    Reduced international&#13;
competition would in turn contribute to a reversal of recent trends towards&#13;
greater flexibility in the use of productive resources in many industrial&#13;
countries. This would lead to rising real costs, first in the more protected&#13;
sectors and then economy wide.&#13;
81.      The causality chain could vary across countries, depending on local&#13;
as  well  as global circumstances.      The  economic  impact of higher    trade&#13;
protection could also vary depending on its size, typology and regional&#13;
spread. What is clear, however, is that under a "do nothing" scenario, in&#13;
terms of economic policies and fiscal imbalances in particular, it would be&#13;
very difficult to avoid increased trade protectionism and reduced wage and&#13;
cost discipline in the tradable goods sectors.&#13;
82.      Under these conditions, real output in industrial countries could&#13;
grow at best at only 2.5 percent between 1985 and 1990, a rate roughly the&#13;
same as that of 1973-84, and unemployment would continue to increase.&#13;
Developing countries would suffer even more in terms of reduced output&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
growth.     Export   volume  and   terms  of   trade  prospects   would   worsen&#13;
substantially, due to increased trade protection, slower overall demand growth&#13;
for developing countries' goods and a fall -in the relative prices of primary&#13;
commodities.   Developing countries'   export volume growth could slow down to&#13;
about 3 percent per annum in 1985-90. 1/ Terms of trade could decline by as&#13;
much as 6 percentage points and purchasing power of exports would thus&#13;
increase at only 2 percent per annum.     Roughly one-quarter of export revenue&#13;
would have to go to service existing debt.     Considering the likely growth of&#13;
other net factor income, transfers and official long-term lending, simply to&#13;
maintain debt service ratios at 1985 levels developing countries would have to&#13;
constrain their import growth to about 2.5 percent per annum in real terms.&#13;
83.      Reduced capacity to import, slower investment rates and deterioration&#13;
in the relative prices of tradable goods would substantially constrain the&#13;
rate of growth of developing countries    real output:   to less than 4 percent&#13;
per annum between 1985 and 1990, as compared to the 5.2 percent achieved in&#13;
the 1970s.   This rate of growth of real output could even be slower if, as&#13;
seems in fact likely under these circumstances, a number of developing&#13;
countries found it impossible to maintain the momentum of policy reform&#13;
assumed in the calculations.   This could happen as a result of a breakdown of&#13;
the social consensus necessary to keep meeting external obligations, and more&#13;
broadly to continue exerting present efforts with a view to future results.&#13;
1/ Export volume growth could be even lower, approaching the growth of real&#13;
GNP in industrial countries, if trade protection were to limit severely&#13;
the expansion of exports of manufactured products from developing to&#13;
industrial countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 58 -&#13;
84.      Excluding from the total India and China, whose creditworthiness may&#13;
continue to ensure access to international private lending, reveals the extent&#13;
of  the  possible  deterioration  of  growth  prospects   for  other  developing&#13;
countries under these circumstances.     For the remainder of the developing&#13;
countries, average annual real output growth would be slightly higher than 3&#13;
percent.  Taking into account the decline in their terms of trade, this would&#13;
mean that per capita income would either stagnate or decline in many of these&#13;
countries.&#13;
85.      The medium term sustainability of such a scenario is open to serious&#13;
questions.    New  lending would   fall short of interest payments     for many&#13;
developing countries, which for the entire period would need to run a&#13;
considerable annual external surplus to meet their debt service obligations.&#13;
Higher net resource inflows could materialize only through increased official&#13;
flows, which is unlikely, or through continued involuntary lending by&#13;
international private banks to many developing countries having no concrete&#13;
prospects of-a restoration of their debt servicing capacity.&#13;
86.      The two large Asian countries would also suffer substantially from&#13;
this situation, in terms of foregone growth, delayed modernization of their&#13;
agricultural sectors, retarded expansion of manufacturing capacity and loss of&#13;
policy reform momentum.    Middle-income developing countries of Latin America&#13;
and Asia could perhaps increase intra-regional trade (already larger for them&#13;
than for other developing countries) to sustain export growth, but much would&#13;
depend on their external payments situation, which increased protection on&#13;
manufactured goods exports could render precarious.        Other oil importing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 59 -&#13;
middle-income- countries would   find  themselves  in an -even more difficult&#13;
situation, faced by a. massive deterioration of. export growth and terms of&#13;
trade.   Middle-income oil exporting devel-oping countries might. be able to&#13;
sustain their export growth to industrial ,countries -and domestic investments&#13;
somewhat better, although under these circumstances price prospects, for oil&#13;
would not be bright.&#13;
87.      Even without a disruptive and prolonged financial crisis, the world&#13;
economy would suffer considerably in terms, of foregone growth and increased,&#13;
instability from lack' of policy adjustment.    While the case for adjustment&#13;
cannot rest entirely on the anticipation o'f possible future losses and on&#13;
their avoidance, the risks involved inma "do nothing" scenario appear to be so&#13;
considerably high that their careful consideration should add both urgency arid&#13;
purpose  to  the  efforts  that  are  needed  to. afford  both  industrial  and&#13;
developing countries the possibility of a- sustained, non-inflationary period&#13;
of growth.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
World      Bank                             NEW                                indicate the effects of these systems on&#13;
the aUlocation of resources, intema,&#13;
Pub      cations                        Sub-Saharan Africa: Progress           tional trade, and economic growth.&#13;
Of Related                         Report on Development                   The Johns Hopkins Univmrsity Press, 1982;&#13;
of Related                              Prospects and Programs                 paperback 1984. 416 pages (including ap-&#13;
Interest                               A review of the foregoing book two      pendixe, index).&#13;
years later.                            LC-81-15558. ISBN 0-8018-2569-5, hard-&#13;
Highlights some of the major problems  cover; ISBN 0-8018-2570-9, paperback.&#13;
that African governments have faced    Stock Nos. JH 2569, $39.95 hardcover; IH&#13;
in designing and implementing pro-     2570, $18.50 paperback.&#13;
gramns of reform. Examines changes&#13;
that have been introduced in the level,  Eastern and Southern Africa:&#13;
pattem, and design of World Bank       Past Trends and Future&#13;
economic work and operations in sup-   Prospects&#13;
port of such reforms. Reviews the ex-      * ulhati&#13;
tent of donor government responses to  Ravi G&#13;
the increased and changed needs of     Staff Working Paper No. 413. 1980. 24&#13;
African countries for external assis-  pages.&#13;
tance.                                 Stock No. WP 0413. $3.&#13;
1983. 37 pages.&#13;
Stock No. BK 9169. Free.               Economic Growth and Human&#13;
Resources&#13;
Accelerated Development in                                                     Norman Hicks, assisted by&#13;
Sub-Saharan Africa: An                     NEW                                 jahangir Boroumand&#13;
Agend   forAction                                                           Staff Working Paper No. 408. 1980. 40&#13;
Agenda for Action                      Decentralization in Developing          pages (including 3 appendixes, bibliog-&#13;
In the faU of 1979, the African Gover-  Countries: A Review of Recent          raphy, and references).&#13;
nors of the World Bank addressed a&#13;
memorandum to the Bank's president     Experence                               Stock No. WP 0408. $3.&#13;
expressing their alarm at the dim eco-  Dennis A Rondinelli, John R.&#13;
nomic prospects for the nations of sub-  NeUis, and G. Shabbir Cheema             NEW&#13;
Saharan Africa and asking that the      Reports on the objectives of decentrali-&#13;
Bank prepare a "special paper on the   zation. Notes that many developing      Economic Reform in Socialist&#13;
economic development problems of       countries began decentralization dur-   Countries: The Experiences of&#13;
these countries" and an appropriate    ing the last 10 years to find ways of   China, Hungry, Romania, and&#13;
program for helping them. This report,  using limited resources more effec-    Yugoslavia&#13;
building on the Lagos Plan of Action,   tively. Evaluates types of decentraliza-  Peter T. Knight&#13;
is the response to that request.       tion and conditions and factors affect-&#13;
The report discusses the factors that   ing the implementation of policies     Descrbes the Soviet-style system of&#13;
explain slow economic growth in Af-    supporting decentralization. Provides   centralized planning as a prelude to an&#13;
rica in the recent past, analyzes policy  information on political commitment,  in-depth discussion of reform design&#13;
changes and program orientations        administrative support, effective de-  as expenienced in China, Hungary, Ro-&#13;
needed to promote faster growth, and    sign and organization of programs,     mania, and Yugoslavia. Some lessons&#13;
concludes with a set of recommenda-     and the need for adequate resources.   from the reform of these countries are&#13;
tions to donors, including the recom-   Annexes look at Indonesia's provincial  noted as possibly ylevant to future at-&#13;
mendation that aid to Africa should     development program, China's "pro-     tempts at improving the efficiency&#13;
double in real terms to bring about re-  duction responsibility" system, and   both of socialst economies and state&#13;
newed African development and          Tunisia's deconcentration program.      sectors of mixed economies.&#13;
growth in the 1980s. The report's       Staff Working Paper No. 581. 1983. 112  Staff Working Paper No. 579. 1983. 131&#13;
agenda for action is general; it indi-  pages.                                 pages.&#13;
cates broad policy and program direc-   Stock No WP 0581 S5                    ISBN 0-8213-0229-0. Stock No. WP 0579.&#13;
tions, overall priorities for action, and                                      $5.&#13;
key areas for donor attention. Like the  Development Strategies in&#13;
Lagos Plan, the report recognizes that  Semi-Industrial Economies              The Extent of Poverty in Latin&#13;
Africa has enormous economic poten-    Bela Balassa and Associates             America&#13;
tial, which awaits fuUer development.   Provides an analysis of development    Oscar Aimdr&#13;
1981; 3rd printing 1983. 198 pages (in-  strategies in semi-industrial economies  Staff Working Paper No. 522. 1982. 117&#13;
cluding statistical annex, bibliography).  that have established an industrial  pages.&#13;
French: L.e developpemnent accelere en af-  base. Endeavors to quantify the sys-  ISBN 0-8213-0012-1. Stock No. WP 0522.&#13;
rique au sud du Sahara: programme indi-  tems of incentives that are applied in&#13;
catif d'action.                        six semi-industrial developing econom-  S5.&#13;
Stock Nos. BK 9114 (English) and BK     ies-Argentina, Colombia, Israel, Ko-   Prices subject to change without notice&#13;
9116 (French). Free.                    rea, Singapore, and Taiwan-and to      and may vary by country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NEW                                  Implementing Programs of                 Managing Project-Related&#13;
Human Development                        Technical Assistance: The&#13;
The Effects of Corruption on             Edited by Peter T. Knight;               Lessons of Success&#13;
Administrative Performance:              prepared by Nat J. Colleta, Jacob        Francis Lethem and Lauren&#13;
Illustrations from Developing            Meernan, and others.                     Cooper&#13;
Countries                                Staff Working Paper No. 403. 1980. 376   Practical guidance for technical assis-&#13;
David J. Gould and Jose A.               pages (including references).           tance designers and appraisers based&#13;
Amaro-Reyes                              Stock No. WP 0403. $15.                  on feedback from aid agencies and&#13;
technical assistance recipients in Af-&#13;
Analyzes the effects of corruption on    International Technology                 rica, Asia, and the Middle East who&#13;
thE- administrative performance of de-   Tase.Ise             n    oiypriiae                 nscesu       rjcs&#13;
veloping countries. Examitines the po-                                            Part       an success   wiful  benefit&#13;
ical, economic, and social factors that  Optionts                                 Plnnrsm and provnadvctitinerhs will rt&#13;
contribute to its incidence. Data from   Frances Stewart                          Covers idpentfaidvicei  i this report.&#13;
Asia, Africa, and Latin America form     Staff Working Paper No. 344. 1979. 178   of services and administration, imple-&#13;
the basis for discussion.                pages (including references).            mentation and management of techni-&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 580. 1983. 60    Stock No. WP 0344. $5.                   cal assistance.&#13;
pages.                                                                            Staff Working Paper No. 586. 1984. 104&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0259-0. Stock No. WP 0580.                                            pages. English and French.&#13;
$3.                                          NEW                                  ISBN 0-8213-0239-6. Stock No. WP 0586.&#13;
First Things First: Meeting                                                       $5.&#13;
Basic Human Needs in the&#13;
Developing Countries                                   n                              NEW&#13;
Paul Streeten, with Shahid Javed                                                              the P&#13;
Burki,Mahbub ul Haq, Norman                                                       Managing the Public Service s&#13;
Hicks, and Frances Stewart                                                        Developig Countries: Issues&#13;
The basic needs approach to economic                                             eanu Prospects&#13;
development is one way of helping the                            -  .                            ways Ozgediz&#13;
poor emerge from their poverty. It en-                                            Identifies better ways to manage hu-&#13;
ables them to earn or obtain the ne-                                              man resources to meet escalating de-&#13;
cessities for life-nutrition, housing,                                            mand for improved public services in&#13;
water and sanitation, education, and                                              developing countries, where public&#13;
health-and thus to increase their pro-                                            service employment is growing four&#13;
ductivity.                                                                        times faster than in developed coun-&#13;
This book answers the critics of the                                              tries. Resultant problems in personnel&#13;
basic needs approach, views this ap-                                              management, pubbic service training&#13;
proach as a logical step in the evolu-                                            programs, and the applicability of&#13;
tion of economic analysis and develop-    -                                       western management practices in de-&#13;
ment policy, and presents a               -                                       veloping country settings are consid-&#13;
ment policy, and presents a                                 ~~~~~~~~~~ered.&#13;
clearsighted interpretation of the is-   The Japanese and Korean                  Staff Working Paper No. 583. 1983. 100&#13;
sues. Based on the actual experience of  Experienes       an     an               pages.&#13;
various countries-their successes and    Experences in Managing                   pages.&#13;
failures-the book is a distillation of   Development                              ISBN 0-8213-0243-4. Stock No. WP 0583.&#13;
World Bank studies of the operational    Miyohei Shinohara, Toru                  $3.&#13;
implications of meeting basic needs. It  Yanagihara, and Kwang Suk Kim&#13;
also discusses the presumed conflict     The special style of economic manage-     dist     on for     and&#13;
between economic growth and basic        ment that has produced the "econonmicc Distribution, for Brazil&#13;
needs, the relation between the New      miracles" of these two countries is      Lance Taylor, EdmariL. Bacha,&#13;
Intemational Economic-Order and          analyzed. Of particular interest are in-  Eliana Cardoso, and Frank J. Lysy&#13;
basic needs, and the relation between    ferences about the power of prices and   Explores the Brazilian experience from&#13;
human rights and basic needs.            role of compefition, both intemal and    the point of view of political economy&#13;
Oxford University Press, 1981; 3rd paper-  extemal. Korean and Japanese eco-      and computable general equilibrium&#13;
back printing, 1984. 224 pages (including  nomic management are characterized    income distribution models.&#13;
appendix, bibliography, index).          as pragmatic and flexible.               Oxford Univsity Press, 1980. 368 pages&#13;
LC 81-16836, ISBN 0-19-520-368-2, hard-  Stqff Working Paper No. 574. 1984. 98   (including references, appendixes, index).&#13;
cover; ISBN 0-19-520-369-0, paperback.   pages.                                   LC 80-13786. ISBN 0-19-520206-6, hard-&#13;
Stock Nos. OX 520368, $18.95 hardcover;  ISBN 0-8213-0233-7. Stock No. WP 0574.  cover; ISBN 0-19-520207-4, paperback.&#13;
OX 520369, $8.95 paperback.              $3.                                      Stock Nos. OX 520206, $27.50 hardcover;&#13;
The Hungarian Economic                   Levels of Poverty: Policy and            ox 520207, $14.95 paperbac.&#13;
Reform, 1968-81                          Change                                   Patterns of Development, 1950-&#13;
Bela Balassa                             Amartya Sen                              1970&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 506. 1982. 31    Staff Working Paper No. 401. 1980. 91    Hollis Chenery and Moises&#13;
pages (including references).            pages (including references).            Syrquin&#13;
Stock No. WP 0506. $3.                   Stock No. WP 0401. $3.                   A comprehensive interpretation of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
structural changes that accompany the    in developing countries during the      Meeting Basic Needs: An&#13;
growth of developing countries, using    post-World War 1 period. Analyzes       Overview&#13;
cross-section and time-series analysis   problems, successes and failures,       Mahbub ul Haq and Shahid Javed&#13;
to study the stability of observed pat-  e,nerging trends, and lessons learned.  Buki&#13;
terns and the nature of time trends.     Staff Working Paper No. 576. 1983. 71   Pureo&#13;
Oxford Unitersity Press, 1975; 4th paper-  pag.                                  Presents a sumary of the main find-&#13;
back prnnting, 1984. 250 pages (including  ISBN 0-8213-0303-1. Stock No. WP 0576.  World n ank as part of a program for&#13;
technical appendix, statistical appendix,                                        Wa2&#13;
bibliography, index).                                                            reducing absolute poverty and meeting&#13;
LC 74-29172. ISBN 0-19-920075-0, hard-       NEWb1                                    2 pees(&#13;
cover; ISBN 0-19-920076-9, paperback.                                            1980. 28 paga (including 2 annexes).&#13;
Stock Nos. OX 920075, S19.95 hardcover;  Policies for Strengthening              Stock Nos. BK 9015 (Arabic), BK 9016&#13;
OX 920076, $8.95 paperback.              Local Government in                     (English), BK 9027 (French), BK 9018&#13;
Spanish: LA estructural del crecimiento  Dev(popin    Countnes                   (ppanae), BK 9019 (Spanish). $3 paper-&#13;
economico: un analisis para el periodo   Glyev  Cochpine                         Sheltec&#13;
1950-1970. Editorial Tecnos, 1978.                                               Shelter&#13;
ISBN 84-309-0741-6, Stock No. IB 0523,   Looks at the ways by which highly       Anthony A. Churchill&#13;
$8.95,                       ~~~~~~~~centralized govemnments effectively&#13;
S8.95.                                   utilize and improve resources within    Defines the elements that constitute&#13;
local governments. The need for         shelter; discusses the difficulties en-&#13;
NEW                                  strengthening personnel performance     countered in developing shelter pro-&#13;
at the local level is discussed, includ-  grams for the poor; estimates orders of&#13;
Pioneers in Development                  ing an analysis of useful methodology,  magnitude of shelter needs for the&#13;
Edited by Gerald M. Meier and            Discussion of local revenue sources     next twenty years; and proposes a&#13;
Dudley Seers                             and patterns of revenue generation      strategy for meeting those needs.&#13;
Some of the pioneers in development      provides a framework from which to      1980. 39 pages.&#13;
economics-Lord Bauer, Cohn Clark,        examine factors affecting government    Stock Nos. BK 9020 (Arabic), BK 9021&#13;
Albert 0. Hirschman, Sir Arthur          performance at higher levels.           (English), BK 9022 (French), BK 9023&#13;
Lewis, Gunnar Myrdal, Raul Prebisch,     Staff Working Paper No. 582. 1983. 76   (Spanish). $3 paperback.&#13;
Paul N. Rosenstein-Rodan, W.W. Ros-      pages.&#13;
tow, H. W. Singer, and Jan Tinber-       ISBN 0-8213-0240-X. Stock No. WP        Water Supply and Waste&#13;
Ren-offer a retrospective view of the    0582. $3.                               Disposal&#13;
formative decade after World War 11                                              Discusses the size of the problem of&#13;
when they made their seminal contri-     Policy Interventions for                meeting basic needs in water supply&#13;
butions to the subject. In individual    Technological Innovation in             and waste disposal and its significance&#13;
papers, the pioneers recapture the in-   Developing Countries                    to development in the context of the&#13;
tellectual excitement, expectations, and  Charles Cooper                         International Drinking Water Supply&#13;
activism of that period and provide                                              and Sanitation Decade. Examines the&#13;
rare autobiographical detail and insight  Staff Working Paper No. 441. 1980. 59  Bank's past role in improving water&#13;
into why they said what they did and     pages (including references).           supply and waste disposal facilities in&#13;
what they now think about the state of   Stock No. WP 0441. $3.                  developing countries and draws con-&#13;
development thought and policy.                                                  clusions for the future.&#13;
Commentary is provided by econo-         Poverty and Basic Needs Series          1980. 46 pages.&#13;
mists of the succeeding generation,&#13;
who reappraise their ideas with the      A series of booklets prepared by the    Stock Nos. BK 9024 (Arabic), BK 9025&#13;
benefit of hindsight. General over-      staff of the World Bank on the subject  (English), BK 9026 (French), BK 9027&#13;
views of the subject have been written   of basic needs. The series includes     (Spanish). $3 paperback.&#13;
by Gerald Meier and Paul Streeten.       cept of basuc needs, counhtrre the csn-P&#13;
Oxford University Press. May 1984.       ies, and sectoral studies.              Poverty and the Development&#13;
About 400 pages. Hardcover only.                                                 of Human Resources: Regional&#13;
ISBN 0-19-520452-2. Stock No. OX         Brazil                                  Perspective&#13;
520452, $29.95.                          Peter T. Knight and Ricardo J.          Willem Bussink, David Davies,&#13;
Moran                                   Roger Grawe, Basil Kavalsky, and&#13;
NEW                                  An edited and updated edition of the    Guy P. Pfeffermann&#13;
more detailed publication, Brazil: Hu-  Staff Working Paper No. 406. 1980. 199&#13;
Planning in Developing                   man Resources Special Report (see de-   paga (including 7 tables, 2 appendixes,&#13;
Countries: Lessowts -of                  scription under Country Studies list-   refprences, footnotaes).&#13;
Experience                                                                       Stock No. WP 0406. $5&#13;
Ramgopal Agarwala                        Z981. 98 pages (including statistical ap-&#13;
Reports that, in most developing         pendix, map). English.                  Poverty and Human&#13;
countries, planning failed to live up to  Stock No. BK 9028. S5.                 Development&#13;
expectations. Outlines steps to remedy   Malnourished People: A Policy           Paul Isenman and others&#13;
this situation. Recommends a general     View                                    Since economic giwth alone has not&#13;
reorientation and emphasis on the                                                reduced absolute poverty, it has been&#13;
most effective areas in the initial for-  Alan Berg                              necessary to consider other strategies.&#13;
mulation of plans.Provides an in-depth   Please refer to Food and Nutrition for  The strategy examined in this study-&#13;
review of the experience of planning    information.                             human development-epitomizes the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
idea that poor people should be          LC 79-18026. ISBN 0-19-520094-2, hard-  in public administration and manage-&#13;
helped to help themselves. Four chap-   cover, ISBN 0-19-520095-0, paperback.    ment training (PAMT) in developing&#13;
ters provide an overview of alternative  Stock Nos. OX 520094, $34.50 hardcover;  countries. Highlights various aspects&#13;
strategies; a detailed look at health,   OX 520095, $12.95 paperback.            of traWng and career development&#13;
educadon, nutrition, and fertility; les-  French: Changement des structres c poli-  programs including the impact of&#13;
sons from exising programs; and an       tque de devloppement. Econo ica, 1981.  PAMT programs in developing coun-&#13;
examinaion of broader issues in plan-    ISBN 2-7178-0404-8, Stock No. IB 0540,  tries during the past 30 years, the rea-&#13;
ning.                                    $12.95.                                 son for successful programs, and some&#13;
Oxford University Press. 1982. 96 pages  Spanish: Cambio estructural y politica de  innovative training designs and meth-&#13;
(including statistical appendix).  .     desarrollo. Editorial Tecnos, 1980. ISBN  st&#13;
LC 82-2153. ISBN 0-19-520389-5. Stock    84-309-0845-5, Stock No. iB 0612,       Staff Woring No. 584. 1984. 127 paga.&#13;
No. OX 520389. $7.95.                    $12.95.                                ISBN 0-8213-0234-5.Stock No. WP 0584.&#13;
_ _ _ _ _ _ _                 $~~~~~~~~~5.&#13;
Reforming the New Economic                   Ne                                                   n&#13;
Mechanism in Hungary                         NEW&#13;
bela Balassa                             Successes and Failures in               Development. Human Ecologic&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 534. 1982. 56    Meeting the Management                  Considerations&#13;
pagIS.                                   Challenge: Strategies and Their         Robert Goodland&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0048-2. Stock No. WP 0534.   Implementation     .                    At the current time, approximately 200&#13;
$3.                                      Milan Kubr and John Wallace             milion tribal people live in all regions&#13;
-       ~~of the world and number among the&#13;
Social Infrastructure and                Exankines the original nature of key    poorest of the poor. This paper de-&#13;
Services in Zimbabwe           -         management problems faced by devel-     scribes the problems associated with&#13;
Rashid Faruqee                           oping countries and outlines proven     the development process as it affects&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 495. 1981. 111   strategies for improving management     tribal peoples; outlines the requisites&#13;
pages (including bibliography, map).     competence and performance. Presents    for meeting the human ecologic needs&#13;
SokN.WP 0495. $5.                    approaches to management develop-       of tribal peoples; and presents general&#13;
Stock No. WP 0495. S5.                   ment recently introduced by enter-      principles that are designed to assist&#13;
prises and institutions such as busi-   the Banks staff and project.designers&#13;
ness clinics and self-development       in incorporating appropriate proce-&#13;
NEW                                  programs for management as well as      dures to ensure the survival of tribal&#13;
tailored and action-oriented programs.  peoples and to assist with their devel-&#13;
Some Temporal Aspects of                 Staff Working Paper No. 585. 1984. 120  opment.&#13;
Development: A Survey                    pages.                                  1982, 118 pages (including 7 annexes, bib-&#13;
R. S. Eckaus                             ISBN 0-8213-0254-X.Stock No. WP 0585.   liography).&#13;
Identifies, quantifies, and explains fac-  S5.                                   ISBN 0-8213-0010-5. Stock No. BK 0010.&#13;
tors that lengthen project design and    Tourism-Passport to                     $5.&#13;
completion. Analyzes changes that        Development? Perspectives on&#13;
take place over time in principal areas  th  S       and Cultr     Eff           The Tropics and Economic&#13;
that affect economic development-la-       e   ocl an        tura     es         Development: A Provocative&#13;
bor supply, social structures and their  of Tourism in Developing                Inquiry into the Poverty of&#13;
behavior, govemrnment support func-      Countries&#13;
tions, market organization and effi-     Emanuel de Kadt, editor                 Nations&#13;
ciency, and capital productivity. Notes  The first serious effort at dealing with  AnrwM.aac&#13;
that development has proved to be a      the effects of tourism development in   Examines major characteristics of the&#13;
relatively slow process.                 a broad sense, concentrating on social  tropical climates that are significant to&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 626. 1983. 51    and cultural questions.                 economic development.&#13;
pages.                                   A joint World Bank-Unesco study. Oxford  The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1976;&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0300-7.Stock No. WP 0626.    University Press, 1979. 378 pages (includ-  2nd printing, 1979. 128 pages (including&#13;
$3.                                      ing maps, index).                        naps, bibliography, index).&#13;
Structural Change and                    LC 79-18116. ISBN 0-19-520149-3, hard-  LC 76-1 7242. ISBN 0-8018-1891-5, hard-&#13;
Development Policy                       cover; ISBN 0-19-520150-7, paperback.   cover; ISBN 0-8018-1903-2, paperback.&#13;
Development Policy            ~~~~Stock Nos. OX 520149, $24.95 hardcover;  Stock Nos. JH 1891, $12.50 hardcover, IH&#13;
Hollis Chenery                           OX 520150, $9.95 paperback.             1903, $5 paperback.&#13;
A retrospective look at Chenery's                                                Spanish: Los tropicos y desarrollo econom-&#13;
thought and' writing over the past two                                           ico: reflexiones sobre la pobreza de las na-&#13;
decades and an extension of his work         NEW                                 ciones. Editorial Tecnos, 1978. ISBN 84-&#13;
in Redistribution with Growth and Pat-                                           309-0740-8, Stock No. IB 0529. $5.&#13;
terns of Development. Develops a set of  Training for Public&#13;
techniques for analyzing structural      Administration and                      Twenty-five Years of Economic&#13;
changes and applies them to some ma-                                             Development, 1950 to 1975&#13;
jor problems of developing countries     Management in Developing                David Morawetz&#13;
today.                                   Countries: A Review                     A broad assessment of development&#13;
Oxford University Press, 1979; 2nd paper-  Samuel Paul                           efforts shows that, although the devel-&#13;
back printing, 1982. 544 pages (including  Analyzes the results of a survey of the  oping countries have been remarkably&#13;
references, index).                      trends, developments, and problems      successful in achieving growth, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
distribution of its benefits among and   LC 77-17243. ISBN 0-8018-2134-7, hard-   ica, 1978. ISBN 2-7178-0038-7, Stock No.&#13;
within countries has been less satisfac-  cover; ISBN 0-8018-2092-8, paperback.   IB 0546, $7.95.&#13;
tory.                                    Stock Nos. IH 2134, $16.50 hardcover; IH  Spnish: Venticinco anos dc daarroJlo&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1977;  2092, $7.95 papback.                   economico: 1950 a n975. Editorial Tesnos,&#13;
3rd printing, 1981. 136 pages (including  French: Vingt-cinq annees de deveop*-   1978. ISBN 84-309-0792-0, Stock No. IB&#13;
statistical appendix, rerences).         ment economnique: 1950 a 1975. Econom-   0529, $7.95.&#13;
World Development Report&#13;
issue brings not only an overview of   M   anagement and&#13;
/                ~~~~~~the state of development, but also a&#13;
detailed analysis of such topics as    Development Senes&#13;
i ' /                 structural change, the varying experi-&#13;
/fi  | !  ,            ences of low- and middle-income         Decentralization in Developing&#13;
countries, the relation of poverty and  Countries: A Review of Recent&#13;
- t -                        human resource development, global     Experience. WP 0581. $5. (Development)&#13;
-  I -  -            and national adjustment, and agricul-  Development Finance Companies, State&#13;
K  _     _ /                ture and food stability. Each contains a  and Pdvately Owned: A Review. WP&#13;
statistical annex, World Development   0578. S3. (Finance and Debt)&#13;
A large-format series of annual studies Indicators, that provides profiles of  Economic Reform in Socialbt Countries:&#13;
of 200 or more pages, the World Devel- more than 120 countries in twenty-five  The Experiences of China, Hungary,&#13;
opment Report, since its inception, has  multipage tables. The data cover such  Romania, and Yugoslavia. WP 0579. $5.&#13;
been what The Guardian has called "a  subjects as demography, industry,    (Development)&#13;
most remarkable publication. It is the  trade, energy, finance, and develop-  The Effect of Corruption on&#13;
nearest thing to having an annual re-  ment assistance and such measures of  Administrative Performance: lllustrations&#13;
port on the present state of the planet social conditions as education, health,  from Developing Countries. WP 0580. 53.&#13;
and the people who live on it." Each  and nutrition.                       (Development)&#13;
The Japanese and Korean Experiences in&#13;
Managing Development. WP 0574. 53.&#13;
World Development Report 1983       World Development Report 1978          (Development)&#13;
Profiles the economies of 125 nations.  (Discusses the development experi-  Managing Project-Related Technical&#13;
Explores the role of management in  ence, 1950-75, development priorities   Assistance: The Lessons of Success. WP&#13;
successful development enterprises,  in the middle-income developing        0586. $5. (Development)&#13;
Provides reliable up-to-date statistics.  countries, and prospects for alleviating  Managing the Public Service in&#13;
Oxford University Press, 224 pages (in-  poverty.)                          Developing Countries: Isues and&#13;
cluding maps, annex, World Development Ordering information for World Devel-  Prospects. WP 0583. 53. (Development)&#13;
Indicators). ISBN 0-19-520432-8; $20  opment Report. All editions are $8, pa-  Managing State-Owned Enterprises. WP&#13;
hardcover; $8 paperback.            perback.                                0577. S5. (Industry)&#13;
World Development Report 1982       World Development Report 1983:          Planning in Developing Countries:&#13;
(Tackles the principal issues and obsta- Stock Nos. OX 520431 (English) hard-  Lessons of Experience. WP 0576. $3.&#13;
des in the efforts to improve the per-  cover; OX 520432 (English) paperback.  (Development)&#13;
formance of world agriculture.)     World Development Report 1982:         Polides for Strengthening Local&#13;
World Development Report 1981       Stock Nos. BK 0086 (Arabic), OX 503225  Goverfinent in Developing Countries.&#13;
(Discusses adjustment-global and na- (English), BK 0087 (Spanish), lB 0607  WP 0582. $3. (Development)&#13;
tional-to promote sustainable growth (French), IB 0606 (Japanese).         Price Distortions and Growth in&#13;
in the changing world economy.)     World Development Report 1981:         (Finance and Debt)res     . S3.&#13;
Stock Nos. lB 0594 (Arabic), OX 502998  (Finaces and Dauebt)   etig h&#13;
World Development Report 1980       (English), IB 0598 (German), IB 0593   Succes and Failu in Meing the&#13;
(Discusses adjustment and growth in                                        Management Challenge: Strategies and&#13;
the 1980s and poverty and human de- (Spanish).                             Their Implementation. WP 0585. $5.&#13;
velopment,)                         World Development Report 1980:         (Development)&#13;
Stock Nos. OX 139419 (English), IB 0599  Training for Public Administration and&#13;
World Development Report 1979       (Spanish).                             Management in Developing Countries: A&#13;
(Discusses development prospects and World Development Report 1979:        Review. WP 0584. $5. (Development)&#13;
intemnational policy issues, structural  Stock No. OX 502638 (English).    Please see category indicated after&#13;
change, and country development ex-&#13;
perience and issues.)               World Development Report 1978:         each title for description and&#13;
Stock No. OX 139414 (English).         bibliographic information.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The Wfrld Bank&#13;
Publications Order Fonn&#13;
SEND TO: YOUR LOCAL DISTRIBUTOR OR TO WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
(See the other side of this form.)        P.O. BOX 37525&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013 U.S.A.&#13;
Date _&#13;
Name                                                 Ship to: (Enter if different from purchaser)&#13;
Title                                                Name&#13;
Firm                                                Title&#13;
Address                                              Firm&#13;
City              State      Postal Code             Address&#13;
Country             Telephone (     )                City            State  -   Postal Code&#13;
Purchaser Reference No.                              Country             Tilephone&#13;
Check your method of payment.&#13;
Enclosed is my S Check L] Internmtional Money Order O Unesco Coupons OL International Postal Coupon.&#13;
Make payable to World Bank Publications for U. S. dollars unless you are ordering from your local distributor.&#13;
Charge my O VISA a MasterCard O American Express O Choice. (Credit cards accepted only for orders addressed&#13;
to World Bank Publications.)&#13;
Credit Card Account Number           Expiration Date                     Signature&#13;
a Invoice me and please reference my Purchase Order No.&#13;
Please ship me the items listed below.&#13;
customer nlaeral&#13;
Slock Number  Author/ Title                                      Routing Code  Quantity  Unit Prie Total Amount S&#13;
All prices subject to change. Prices may vary by country. Allow 6-8 weeks for delivery.&#13;
Subtotal Cost  $&#13;
Total copies .      Air mail surcharge if desired ($2.00 each)  $&#13;
Postage and handling for more than two complimentary items ($2.00 each)  S&#13;
rlbtal  $&#13;
Thank you for your order.&#13;
IsRD00s3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Distributors of World Bank Publications&#13;
ARGENTINA                          GERMANY, FEDERAL REUBUC             KUWAIT                            SRI LANKA AND THE MALDIVES&#13;
Carlos Hirsch, SRL                   OF                                MEMRB                              LAka Hous Bookshop&#13;
Galena Guemes                      UNONVerla                           P.O. BD 5463                       P.O. Box 244&#13;
Florida 165, 4th FloorOfc. 4531465  D5300 Bonn I                       Kuwat                              100, Sir Chittmpalam A. Gadiner&#13;
1333 Buen  Aim                     SArocst4sst 23                     MALAYSI                              MawCthb&#13;
AUSTRAUA, PAPUA NEW                G    aEECE                          Univmity of Mal Coopendve         Colomo 2&#13;
GUINEA, FilI, SOLOMON            MEMRB                                 Bookshop, Linuted&#13;
ISLANDS, AND VANUATU             24, Ippodamou Steet                 P.O  Box 1127. hun Pantal Ban      SWEDEN&#13;
Info-Line                          Athens-1635                         Kual Lumpw                         For single titus:&#13;
Ovemas Docunent Delivery           HONG KONG, MACAU                    KE)uzCO                            ABCE Frtzes Kung. Hovbokhendl&#13;
Box S06, GPO                                                                                              Rep     g tn 12 Box 16356&#13;
Sydney, NSW 2001                   As15 200 Ltd.                       LNFOTEC                             eeipaanI         o  65&#13;
AustaNWa                           6 Fl., 146 Prince Edward Road, W,   San LorefrD 153311 Col. del Valle  503 27 Stockholm&#13;
Kowloon                               Deleg, Benito luae               For bscription odm:&#13;
BAkRAIN                            Hong Kong                           03100 Mexio City                   We     Me   W        AB&#13;
P.O. Box 22103                      NDIA                               MOROCCO                            Box 300D4&#13;
Pa    a O TBown 3217               UBS Pubishers Distnbutors Ltd.      MEMRB                              S104 25 Stockholm&#13;
Manama Town 317                    Post Box 7015                       2 Rue Moiere Rac neSWTZAND&#13;
BANGLADESH                         New Delhi 110002                    Casablanca                         Libinte Pavot&#13;
Micr Industnes Development         10 Fist Main Road                   THE NETHERLANDS                    6 Rue Gmwus&#13;
Assiutance Socie                 Gandhi Napr                         Medical Books Europe. BV 1MBE)     Cae posL 381&#13;
G.P O BOX aoo                     3Bngalore 5609                       Noorderwal 38,                     CH 1211 Genea 11&#13;
BELGIUM                            Apee0ay Chamber, P.O. Box 736       724  L Lochem                      TANZANIA&#13;
PuMficadons dn Nations Unies       5 Walace Stet                       NIGERIA                            Oxfotd Universi Prms&#13;
Publica6ons des Nations Unins      Bombv 4000DI                        Univerity Pms Limited              P. O. Box 3299&#13;
Av. du Rol 202                                                         Three Coo      aIdng Jesiho        Dr es Salum&#13;
1060 BmsseLs                       811-B. Chownnghee LAne              PM d   on Cii Bwn 509  cho&#13;
BRAZIL                   ~~~~~~~~Calcutta 70016               Pibadae MA aStoreTAfAN&#13;
PubEcacoes Tecrticas internacionasis  7188, II(CA). Swaup Nagar        NORWAY                             306 Siom PRad&#13;
Ltdae                            Kampeua                             Tanum Kad Johan, AS.               Bgkok&#13;
0R409S eo PGulod SP                Sivapan   Road                      P 0. Box 1177                       TR    AS     OAiGO&#13;
01409 Sao Paulo,  ~       Nuigamakka                          Senhum                             Svo    tc StlfftUi&#13;
CANADA                             Madrs 600034                        Oslo 1                             55 Ent    Min Road&#13;
C.P 85 131 Ape   _             INDO U NESIA                       PAIaSTAN                           Cuper&#13;
CBPR 6S 1501 Ampue J4ree           Pt. Indim Limuted                   MAX Book AgeN   y                  Trinzda  West Indies&#13;
30uchetvilb Quebec J4B            11A Sam Rtulangl 37                  65 Shahrh-Quaide-Azam              TUNSIA&#13;
CHILE                              Jakart Pusat                        P.O. BOx No. ;29                   Societe Tunisiesu  de Dfumsn&#13;
EditorilRea cirm iento             PO BOx ISI                          Lahote 3                           ; Avenue de Carta&#13;
Snflcm 35n                         IRELAND                             PANAMA                             TurCl&#13;
Santt5                          TDC Publisher                       EdiciomnLibrenxCultuni             TURKEY&#13;
COSTA RICA                         12 North Frederick Steet              Panmena. SA.                     Haet Kiaprv AS.&#13;
Ubria Tejos                        Dublin I                            Av. 7. Espan 16                    469 lstikWalCddeas&#13;
CaUe 11.13                          TALY                               Panama Zone i                      Beyogu Lubul&#13;
Av. Fernandez GuellITL&#13;
Avn losemz     GueU                Ucosa Commisliinaha Saoni SPA       PERU                               UGANDA&#13;
Via Lamarmor 45                     Elitonal Desamollo SA              Uganda Bookshop&#13;
CYPRUS                             50121 Florence                      AparUdo 3824                       Attn: Mr. Marn-Luther GalAwango&#13;
PE.URB                             JAPAN                                                                  P.O. Box 7145&#13;
p O Box 23                         Eastern Book Service (EES)          PHIULIPINES                        Kampala&#13;
37.3. HonD 3{home, Bunkloku         Nationl Book Store                 UNED ARAB EMIRATES&#13;
DENMARK                              113                               701 Rizal Avenue                    MEMR&#13;
Samfunlditittel'tur                Tokvo                               Metro Manla                        P 0 Box 6097&#13;
RosenoeD1 s ACne 11                JORDAN                              PORTUGAL                           Shar ah&#13;
DK 197D Copnhagen V                  EILMRB                            Uvmana Portugal                    UNITED KINGDOM AND&#13;
EG   T, ARAB REPUIUC OF           PFO Box 313                          Rua Do Carmo 7D074                   NORTHERNIIRELND&#13;
Al Ahram                           Jabal                               1200 Lisbon                          NORfTHRo Ltd&#13;
GalarSoeet                         Amman                               SAUDI ARABIA                       P 0. Box 3&#13;
KENYA                              law  Book Store                     Alton, Hampshire GU 34 2PG&#13;
FINLAND                            Atnca Book Service (E A.) Ltd.      P.O. Box 3196                      United Kingdom&#13;
Akateemmnen KiLakauppa             P O Box 45245                       Riyadh 11471                       VE?lEZUELA&#13;
PSO    BoxS12                      Naiob                                INGAPORE, TAIWAN, BURMA           Librea del Este&#13;
SF4.0010                           KOREA, REP'BLIC OF                  Information Pubiations Private, Ltd.  Aptdo. 60.337&#13;
Helsinki 10                        Pan Korea Book Corporation          0206 Ist Fl., Pes.Fu Indwuatrl Bldg..  Cara 1060-A&#13;
FRANCE                             P 0 Box 101. Kwangwhamun            24 New Industn  Roa  d             WESTERN SAMOA&#13;
World Bank Publations              Seoul                               Sinppore                           Wesley Bookshop&#13;
66 Avenue d'iena                                                                                          Api&#13;
75116 Pans                                                             Mundi-Prensa Libros, SA.&#13;
Castello 37&#13;
28001 Madind&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
~HG 3881.5 .W57 W67 NO.737&#13;
c..3&#13;
C BANETH, JEAN, 1936-&#13;
SUSTAINING WORLD ECONOMIC&#13;
IRECOVERY&#13;
DATE    NAME AND EXTENSION   ROOM&#13;
NUMBER!&#13;
i~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~________________ l&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                          European Office               Tokyo Office&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                   66, avenue d'1ena             Kokusai Building&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.        75116 Paris, France           1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234             Telephone: (1) 723-54.21      Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK            Telex: 842-620628             Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                            Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
ISSN 0)2,3-2115/iSBN 0-8213-05'16-8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554716">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/05/1554716/sustaining-world-economic-recovery-challenges-ahead
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/05/1554716/sustaining-world-economic-recovery-challenges-ahead</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1985/05/1554716/sustaining-world-economic-recovery-challenges-ahead</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/10/03/000178830_9810190343211/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/10/03/000178830_9810190343211/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1985-05-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-10-03T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Sustaining world economic recovery : the
            challenges ahead
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The paper analyzes the characteristics
            of the 1983-84 world economic recovery and its effects on
            developing countries' adjustment. It looks at the
            conditions for medium-term non-inflationary growth in the
            world economy and at the changes in policies necessary to
            cope with and redress over time the real and financial
            imbalances that threaten the sustainability of the current
            recovery. It presents a scenario for medium-term growth,
            resulting from moderate policy changes in industrial
            countries, within which the room for growth and continued
            policy adjustment in developing countries is examined in
            some detail. The risks of failure inherent in a continuation
            of present policy trends are also examined.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Sustaining world economic recovery : the
            challenges ahead
        </docna>
        <display_title>Sustaining world economic
            recovery : the challenges ahead</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1985/05/1554716/sustaining-world-economic-recovery-challenges-ahead</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Macroeconomic Management,Poverty Assessment,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Achieving Shared Growth</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Baneth, Jean</author>
            <author>Grilli, Enzo</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_9810190343211</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Macro/non-trade</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 737</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0546-8</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Economic growth; Economic policy; Economic
            recovery; External debt; Finance; Interest rates;
            International trade; Production increase; Protectionism;
            Structural adjustment
            adjustment policies,adjustment
            process,aggregate demand,balance of payments,budget
            deficits,capital flows,Commercial
            banks,competitiveness,concessional terms,consumption
            expenditures,current account,current account
            deficit,debt,debt ratios,deflators,developed
            countries,Developing countries,Developing country,developing
            economies,disequilibrium,domestic currencies,domestic
            demand,domestic inflation,Domestic Interest Rates,domestic
            policies,economic activity,Economic Analysis,Economic
            conditions,economic expansion,economic growth,Economic
            history,Economic Outlook,ECONOMIC PERFORMANCE,economic
            policies,economic recession,economic relations,exchange
            rate,exchange rates,exports,external conditions,external
            environment,external imbalances,external trade,financial
            policies,financial system,fiscal policies,foreign
            borrowing,foreign exchange,GDP,GDP deflator,GNP,growth
            rate,growth rates,imports,income,income developing
            countries,income groups,income growth,Increased
            demand,increased exports,INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES,industrialized
            countries,inflation,inflation rates,interest rate,interest
            rates,labor force,LONG- TERM GROWTH,long-term
            growth,Low-Income Countries,MEDIUM TERM,Middle-Income
            Countries,monetary policies,monetary policy,oil,Oil
            Exporters,Oil Prices,output growth,payments crisis,per
            capita incomes,policy change,policy changes,policy
            improvements,policy makers,policy reform,policy
            response,price stability,primary commodities,PRIVATE
            CONSUMPTION,productive
            sectors,productivity,protectionism,rapid growth,real
            GDP,real GNP,real interest,real interest rates,Real
            output,reducing inflation,resource allocation,savings,sharp
            reduction,slow growth,structural adjustment,sustainable
            growth,terms of trade,trade balance,trade deficit,unemployment,wages
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP737</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Formulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Implementation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Productivity-Led Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary and Exchange Rate Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal &amp; Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Consolidation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance and Structural Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Rules</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Sustainability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macro-Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Current Account</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Balance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Balance of Payments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>