<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Tools for Manpower Planning&#13;
The World Bank Models&#13;
Volume I&#13;
Technical Presentation of the Models&#13;
Ismail Serageilin&#13;
Bob Li              SWP587&#13;
WORLD BANK ST'AFF WOIRKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 587&#13;
PUB&#13;
HG&#13;
3881.5&#13;
.W57&#13;
W67&#13;
no.587-59&#13;
v.1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF W9RKING PAPERS&#13;
l'ools for Manpow(er Planning&#13;
The World Bank Models&#13;
Volume I&#13;
Technical Presentation of the Models&#13;
Number 58;'&#13;
Volume II&#13;
User's Guide for the Country (Compound) Model&#13;
Number 588&#13;
Volume III]&#13;
User's Guide for the Regiional (Expanded) Model&#13;
Number 589&#13;
Volume IV&#13;
User's Guide for the M[igration Model&#13;
Number 590&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORK.ING PAPERS&#13;
Number 587&#13;
Tools for Manpower Planning&#13;
The World Bank Models&#13;
Volume I&#13;
Technical Presentation of the Models&#13;
Ismail Serageldin&#13;
Bob Li&#13;
The World Banik&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright ( 1983&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development / THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
First printing May 1983&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To&#13;
present the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not&#13;
been prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed&#13;
texts, and the World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is&#13;
supplied at a token charge to defray part of the cost of manufacture and&#13;
distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to&#13;
any individual acting on their behalf. Any maps used have been prepared solely&#13;
for the convenience of the readers; the denominations used and the boundaries&#13;
shown do not imply, on the part of the World Bank and its affiliates, any&#13;
judgment on the legal status of any territory or any endorsement or acceptance of&#13;
such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications is described in the Catalog of World&#13;
Bank Publications; the continuing research program of the Bank is outlined in&#13;
World Bank Research Program: Abstracts of Current Studies. Both booklets are updated&#13;
annually; the most recent edition of each is available without charge from the&#13;
Publications Distribution Unit of the Bank in Washington or from the European&#13;
Office of the Bank, 66, avenue d'Iena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Ismail Serageldin is chief of the Urban Projects Division and Bob Li is senior&#13;
operations officer and leader of the Organization and Management Unit,&#13;
Technical Assistance and Special Studies Division, both in the Europe, Middle&#13;
East, and North Africa Regional Office of the World Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Serageldin, Ismail, 1944-&#13;
Tools for manpower planning.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 587-590)&#13;
Contents: v. 1. Technical presentations of the models&#13;
-- v. 2. User's guide for the country (compound) model&#13;
-- [etc.]- -- v. 4. User's guide for the migration model.&#13;
1. Manpower policy--Mathematical models. 2. World&#13;
Bank.   I. Li, Bob.   II. Title.   III. Series.&#13;
HD5713.S47   1983        331.11'0724         83-6962&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0183-7 (v. 3)&#13;
ISIBN 0-8213-0181-0 (v. 1)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Foreword&#13;
The explosion of international migration in the Middle East and&#13;
North Africa Region in the 1970s was a major development on the international&#13;
economic scene with profound implications for both the labor-importing and the&#13;
labor-exporting countries. The World Bank urndertook a research study on the&#13;
subject in 1978 under the leadership of Ismail Serageldin and his group of&#13;
committed colleagues in the Technical Assistance and Special Studies Division&#13;
of the EMENA Projects Department. The study was completed in 1981 and the&#13;
Report has been widely disseminated. It has been published in book form this&#13;
year. 1/&#13;
The set of simulation models developed by the Technical Assistance&#13;
and Special Studies Division and elaborated during the research project has&#13;
been applied to study manpower problems and planning issues in several&#13;
countries and proven to be a useful tool for manpower planning. The wide&#13;
availability and a full description of these models is important and to be&#13;
welcomed.&#13;
Vinod Dubey&#13;
Chief Economist&#13;
Europe, Middle East and North Africa Region&#13;
May 1983&#13;
1/ Ismail Serageldin, James A. Socknat, Stace Birks, Bob Li,&#13;
and Clive Sinclair, Manpower and International Labor Migration&#13;
in the Middle East and North Africa (Oxford University Press for&#13;
the World Bank, 1983).&#13;
v&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Preface&#13;
This document, published in four vo]Lumes as part of the World Bank's&#13;
staff working papers, is intended to set fort:h the mathematical formulation of&#13;
the Bank's various Manpower Planning Models, most of which have now been used&#13;
in a number of countries and studies, but whose technical documentation was&#13;
not hitherto available to the public.&#13;
Applied Models are living entities, constantly changing and (we hope)&#13;
improving to meet the new requirements introduced by their users. The present&#13;
publication must therefore be seen as a snapshot in time, but one which&#13;
presents the interested user with the opporttnity of reviewing the technical&#13;
documentation as well as the user's guides as they stand at the beginning of&#13;
1983. They are not likely to change significantly until a new round of&#13;
intensive applications produces a new generation.&#13;
The technical presentation provides, for completeness, a detailed&#13;
discussion (pp. 98-132) of a simultaneous procedure method for the migration&#13;
model.  This has not been implemented to date, partly because time and&#13;
resources constraints prevented its complete development and elaboration, but&#13;
it nevertheless sketches out the likely direction of our next round of&#13;
research and development efforts, planned for 1983/84.&#13;
It is important to emphasize, however, that while we were the main&#13;
protagonists in the development of these models, the work would not have been&#13;
possible without the support, guidance and incisive comments of many&#13;
colleagues in and outside the Bank. To all of them we owe a great debt of&#13;
intellectual and moral gratitude. We emphasize, however, that any errors or&#13;
shortcomings in the present manuscript are purely our own.&#13;
vii&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Among those in the Bank who provided constant support and&#13;
encouragement during the six year life of these manpower planning efforts, of&#13;
which this document is just a small part, we must thank in particular&#13;
Mr. Vinod Dubey, Chief Economist of the EMENA region, whose constant personal&#13;
and technical support from the earliest days to the present have made this task&#13;
possible. The long-term study efforts have also benefitted from the strong&#13;
support of Messrs. R. Chaufournier, Vice-President of EMENA; and M.P. Benjenk,&#13;
currently Vice-President, External Relations and formerly Vice-President of&#13;
EMENA; and Messrs. A. David Knox, currently Vice-President for West Africa&#13;
(formerly Projects Director, EMENA); A. Karaosmanoglu, currently Vice-President&#13;
for East Asia and Pacific (formerly Director of ProRrams, EMENA), and M.P. Bart,&#13;
Director of Programs, EMENA; and A.S. El Darwish, Director of Projects, West&#13;
Africa (formerly Assistant Director of Projects, EMENA); and especially&#13;
Messrs. R. Picciotto, Director of Projects, EMENA; and J.J. Stewart, Assistant&#13;
Director of Projects, EMENA. A special mention is also needed of the support&#13;
given by Mr. D. Avramovic when he was Director of the Bank's Development&#13;
Economics Department, and Mr. S. Acharya when he was Research Advisor.&#13;
Many colleagues from the Bank have contributed valuable comments and&#13;
insights to the general studies of which these Models were the central part,&#13;
among these we must name S. Birks, C. Blitzer, F. Colaco, Z. Ecevit, I. Hume,&#13;
J.P. Jallade, T. King, G. Pennisi, R. Prosser, N. Sherbiny, C. Sinclair,&#13;
J. Socknat, and M. Wilson. The computer related work was ably done by Peter&#13;
and Tom Wolfe (Consultants). Earlier versions were programmed by A. McClinton&#13;
of the Phoenix Corporation. Applications on various countries were undertaken&#13;
with the support of G. Cima, B. Krishna, B. Smith, M. Pemmarazu, M. Youssef,&#13;
and M. Allak.&#13;
viii&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Among the colleagues from the academic world, special thanks are due&#13;
to the contributions of Professors I. SirageLdin (Johns Hopkins University),&#13;
C.S. Kelly (Ohio S;tate University), R. Davis and W. Alonso (both of Harvard&#13;
University), and the late Arthur Smithies (Harvard University).&#13;
Finally, Professor John Kantner (Jolins Hopkins University) and&#13;
Mr. Mervin E. MulLer (Senior Advisor to the 'Vice-President and Controller)&#13;
reviewed this manuscript, and Mr. R. Wolfe (Consultant) provided editorial&#13;
support. To each and everyone our thanks andi appreciation.&#13;
Ismail Serageldin and Bob C. Li&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C.&#13;
May 1983&#13;
ig&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NOTE&#13;
The purpose of this series of World Bank Staff Working Papers is&#13;
to describe the structure, input, output, use and operation of the World Bank&#13;
manpower forecasting Models, implemented for IBM 370 systems.&#13;
Staff of the Technical Assistance and Special Studies (TASS)&#13;
Division of the World Bank are available, under appropriate arrangements, to&#13;
discuss with potential users the collection and preparation of required input&#13;
data for running the models. In some cases, the TASS Division can also&#13;
conduct short orientation and training sessions on the capabilities and&#13;
operation of the models.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Page&#13;
Volume I: Technical Presentation of the Models&#13;
Foreworde ....................................... ,....O.......... v&#13;
Preface-l ......................... ,           ................     vii&#13;
PART I:   INTRODUCTION&#13;
0.1    Introduction .................      .     .........., ................... 1&#13;
0.2    The Country-Specific Model ............... ...............    2&#13;
0.3    Submodels of the Country-Specific Modelt...                   3&#13;
0.4    The Expanded Model..................... .. ........ .         6&#13;
0.5    The Migration Model    ......... I .. .....................   7&#13;
0.6   Applications ... ...........O.*., ......... ,o*- ...................  12&#13;
PART II: METHODOLOGY OF THE MODELS&#13;
CHAPTER 1:   The Country Model.........................       .........   15&#13;
1.1 Inl:roductione.e.e....,.*...too..e...*...... ....., 15&#13;
1.2   Overview:   Goals and Applications...................        16&#13;
1.3   Det:ailed Structure of the Model......e...............       19&#13;
1.4   The Sector/Occupation Matrix........................         21&#13;
1.5   General Characteristics of the Four Submodels........        27&#13;
1.6   General Programming Approach of the Country Model....        29&#13;
1.7   The Labor Force Model (LFH) ........................ , 32&#13;
1.8   The Manpower Requirements Model (MRM)................        36&#13;
1.9   The Education Simulation ModeL (ESM)M.................       40&#13;
1.10  The Manpower Policy Model (PMP).................. O".        53&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CHAPTER 2: THE EXPANDED MODEL&#13;
2.1    Introduction ................, ...........                   61&#13;
2.2   Local Analysesn....                .............       .      61&#13;
2.3   Global Analyses.       a     lse.... ...s........................  63&#13;
2.4    Overall System Design Specifications..*..*.**.....           65&#13;
2.5    Phaeh........................s                               66&#13;
2.6 Assumptions... .O .. 0 .                              ..0       68&#13;
2.7    Outputs/Reports........... . ...        ....  . ..... .      68&#13;
2.8    Phase I Internal Specifications: Local Analysis.....         69&#13;
2.9   Phase I Internal Specifications: Global Analysis....          77&#13;
2.10  Phase II Internal Specifications: Local Analyses....          83&#13;
2.11   Phase II Internal Specifications: Global Analysis...         85&#13;
CHAPTER 3:   THE MIGRATION MODEL&#13;
3.1   Background ........         ..................................  87&#13;
3.2    Sequential Solutions Procedure ......................        88&#13;
3.3    Conditions of Excess Supply or Demand .        ................  93&#13;
3.4    Simultaneous Solution Procedure .....................        98&#13;
Models:   Glossary of Notation .......................       129&#13;
PART III: USER'S GUIDES&#13;
Volume II: User's Guide for the Country (Compound) Model&#13;
Volume III: User's Guide for the Regional (Expanded) Model&#13;
Volume IV: User's Guide for the Migration Model&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PART I&#13;
INTRODUCTION&#13;
0.1 This paper describes the manpower model which has been developed by&#13;
the Technical Assistance and Special Studies Division of the Europe, Middle&#13;
East, and North Africa Projects Department of the World Bank, with the&#13;
problems of both labor importing and exporting countries in mind. The&#13;
principal applications for planners are: (1) to forecast manpower&#13;
requirements (national and expatriate) required to meet specific sectoral&#13;
output targets; and (2) to identify and isolate specific problems in the&#13;
supply of manpower through simulation of flows of students a9d trainees&#13;
through the education and training system in the light of such modifiable&#13;
parameters as participation, repetition and dropout rates, and&#13;
qualifications required to enter programs. The system also permits the&#13;
planner to set specific manpower targets through an allocation submodel,&#13;
such as maximizing the number of nationals in certain occupational&#13;
categories in a given sectorar optimizing the allocation of qualified labor&#13;
to occupations in those sectors of the economy which are considered as&#13;
having a high priority. Since the model incorporates sectoral production&#13;
targets, together with certain assumptions about productivity growth for&#13;
the sectors concerned, the model can also be used to estimate what&#13;
production levels might be achieved in given sectors, working with existing&#13;
and likely indigenous manpower stocks but with certain limits, if so&#13;
desired, placed on the growth or overall numbers of expatriate manpower.&#13;
The model consists of three interrelated simulation models (with&#13;
optimization capabilities) that relate economic growth, education and&#13;
training, labor force, unemployment, and the importation/exportation of&#13;
labor. The three models are a country-specific model, an expanded country&#13;
model that analyses by region within a specific country, and an&#13;
1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
international labor migration model that quantifies labor flows between&#13;
countries.&#13;
The Country&#13;
!/model, which the World Bank has used to analyze manpower problems&#13;
in more than 10 countries, has been adopted and used by five governments&#13;
(Saudi Arabia, Kuwait, Tunisia, Algeria, and Portugal) and is presently&#13;
being considered by a number of other governments in the Middle Eastrand&#13;
North Africa for adoption as a planning tool in their own agencies.&#13;
O.2  The Country-Specific Model&#13;
The country model relates growth, education, labor supply and&#13;
requirements, and the need for nonnational members of the labor force on a&#13;
national basis. The model provides for a basic flow in input data in a&#13;
simultaneous process to three submodels: The labor force model (LFM); the&#13;
manpower requirements model (MRM); and the education simulation model&#13;
(ESM). The LFM is linked to the MRM; and both are linked along with the&#13;
ESM to the fourth submodel, the manpower policy model (MPM), which, in&#13;
turn, generates both output and feedback to earlier stages.&#13;
A basic tool for articulating the coherent human resources development&#13;
strategy represented by the country model is the sector/occupation matrix&#13;
(SOM). This joins with the four submodels to provide the fifth basic&#13;
component of the country model. The matrix is defined by economic activity&#13;
by sector (rows) and by varying occupations (columns).&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
A simplified schema of the.model is shown below in figure 0-1.&#13;
Figure 0-1&#13;
Country-Specific Model&#13;
Labor Force&#13;
Model (LFM)&#13;
Manpower&#13;
|Input Data k         Requirements    -               |&#13;
L       l        Model (MRM)&#13;
Manpower&#13;
Policy                 Output&#13;
Education     e.       Model (MPM)&#13;
Simulation&#13;
Model (ESM) _&#13;
0.3 Submodels of the Country-Specific Model&#13;
The basic characteristics of the four submodels mentioned above are as&#13;
follows:&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Manpower Requirements Model. (MRM)&#13;
The MRM requires specification of sector production targets (usually&#13;
on the basis of a development plan). Its principal function is to&#13;
calculate occupational requirements in the light of assumptions about&#13;
initial productivity in the base year and productivity growth.&#13;
Requirements are then expressed in terms of educational qualifications.&#13;
For example, senior technical occupations may be regarded as requiring a&#13;
science or math-based degree or, a more specific example, an agricultural&#13;
project manager would require a higher agricultural qualification.&#13;
Labor Force Model (LFM)&#13;
The LFM identifies available national labor force at the beginning&#13;
of each simulation year by occupation within sector and applies an&#13;
attrition rate. (Eventually, a promotion filter, or lateral transfer may&#13;
be incorporated in later versions of the model to take account of movement&#13;
upwards in the occupational structure); next, the LFM takes account of&#13;
available new labor force entrants from the ESM, after applying a&#13;
participation filter (for example, not all outputs from lower secondary&#13;
girls' programs will enter tOe labor force--some will marry). The output&#13;
of the LFM is the net supply of manpower for the simulation year.&#13;
Education Simulation Model (ESM)&#13;
The ESM simulates flows of students and trainees through the system&#13;
on the basis of initial enrollments and assumptions about participation&#13;
rates (e.g., percentage of girls and *boys in a program, of an age group, or&#13;
of graduates entering a course from a previous one, such as percentage of&#13;
primary graduates going to either lower secondary general or into the labor&#13;
force), repetition rates, and dropout rates. These parameters can be&#13;
changed to reflect educational policy decisions such as: higher&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
participation of girls in a given program; increased flows from secondary&#13;
to vocational/technical programs, or specif1ication of particular&#13;
proportions of upper secondary school entraints to literary and&#13;
science-oriented courses; introduction of 'automatic promotion," or&#13;
limiting of repetition to a minimum number of times. For the purpose of&#13;
flows to the labor force, the model considers any year of program as an&#13;
exit point (each program year is called a "course") classifying leavers in&#13;
two ways (boy/girl; completer/dropout).&#13;
Manpower Policy Model (MPM) and Sector Occupation Matrix (SOM)&#13;
The MPM allocates supply from the labor force and from the ESM to&#13;
the overall SOM according to specific priorities.    For example, in&#13;
allocating manpcwer with professional qualifications and senior technical&#13;
qualifications--e.g., engineers--a priority might be assigned to those&#13;
occupational categories within the oil industry and within other sectors&#13;
considered as strategically important, such as public utilities or&#13;
communications, depending on the country.    The MPM can also be set to&#13;
maximize the number of nationals employed in a specific occupation within a&#13;
sector.  In a case where supply is greater thin deman'd, the participation&#13;
and repetition coefficients in the ESM will have to be adjusted.&#13;
Alternatively, the planner may adjust entry requirements elsewhere,&#13;
introducing alternative follow-on courses.   In cases where supply is less&#13;
than demand, the most critical priorities wlill'be satisfied first.   Where-&#13;
priorities are equal and supply insufficient, allocation between&#13;
occupation/sector cells is made on the basis of each cell's net&#13;
requirements weighted by the degree of nationalization already obtained.&#13;
5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The allocation of expatriates to the SQM cells is made by a linear&#13;
programming model (LPM) which can respect these constraints. Because the&#13;
model as a whole accommodates up to ten nationalities or national groups&#13;
and there are 234 cells in the SOM, the total variables are 2,340. To make&#13;
allocation less complex, the SOM has been partitioned into critical skill&#13;
areas. For example, a "partition" might be managerial and senior technical&#13;
posts in three key sectors. The LPM allocates available expatriate labor&#13;
to the most critical partition, then operating within the previously&#13;
mentioned constraints, then proceeds to the next partition, working with a&#13;
supply which has been reduced in the previous allocation steps. The&#13;
process continues until all the residual requirements in the SOM have been&#13;
satisfied.&#13;
0.4 The Expanded Model&#13;
The expanded model extends the methodology used in the country model&#13;
to produce analyses of interregional (within country) labor flows. In the&#13;
expanded model, there are two major stages of analysis: local analyses, or&#13;
within           regional analyses; and global analyses3 which are national&#13;
analyses within a specific country, in which various local analyses are&#13;
taken into account in the overall allocation of manpower surplus and&#13;
deficit in the country.&#13;
After all localities or regions in a global unit have gone through&#13;
their individual local analyses, the global analysis will reallocate pooled&#13;
leakages from each locality to various ozner localities, in accordance with&#13;
a transition mnatrix or matrices, and will also estimate corresponding&#13;
6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
changes in population and enrollments due to labor force migration.    The&#13;
global analysis will then estimate expatriate requirements, taking into&#13;
account existing available local nationals and expatriates residing in the&#13;
global unit.&#13;
0.5 The Migration Model&#13;
In order to-deal with the problems of local flows between countries in&#13;
a supranational region, it is not sufficient to juxtapose country-specific&#13;
models. The interaction effects also need to be identified and modeled.&#13;
The migration model simulation is designed to consider a region of&#13;
countries, and to determine the pattern of migration of laborers resulting&#13;
from imbalance in labor supplies and requireaments among the countries.&#13;
Each country has; labor requirements (divided into sectors and occupations)&#13;
determined from user-specified data covering target outputs,&#13;
productivities, growth, and other national economic goals. Labor&#13;
availability is determined for each country from user-supplied information&#13;
about the educational system, existing labor stocks, attrition and&#13;
sector/occupation distribution, in conjunction with carryover information&#13;
from the previous simulation year.&#13;
The simulation combines information about labor supplies and demands&#13;
in the regional countries with user-specified data ranking attractiveness&#13;
of countries to laborers, restrictions imposed by countries on nonnational&#13;
participation in their labor forces, and other constraints. From these&#13;
input data and constraints, a pattern of latbor allocation is determined&#13;
which includes local allocation of each national labor force, as well as&#13;
migration of nationals to other countries. Remaining deficiencies in labor&#13;
supplies are assumed to be filled by expatriates from an undivided source&#13;
called "rest of the world."&#13;
7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
In essence, the migration model links together the individual&#13;
country-specific manpower projections produced by the country-specific&#13;
model, through the regional simulation of labor migration flows.&#13;
Therefore, many of the computations can be performed independently for each&#13;
country. After the completion of the "internal" country-specific&#13;
calculations, the migration model simulates regional interaction, labor&#13;
importation, and the return home of nonnational workers (less attrition).&#13;
As in the country model, each year is simulated by a sequence of&#13;
computations reflecting, for example, attrition of workers, educational&#13;
advancement and entry into the workforce, labor importation, and other&#13;
labor force movements. The order in which each annual simulation is&#13;
carried out is as follows.&#13;
For each country, the attrition of workers from the labor force is&#13;
computed, based upon attrition rates entered as input data. Attrition of&#13;
local nationals results in their permanent withdrawal from the labor&#13;
force. Attrition of nonnational workers (expatriates) results in their&#13;
return to their home countries, where they must remain for at least one.&#13;
year, before being available again as potential migrant workers.&#13;
For each country, the leakage (as distinct from attrition) of&#13;
nationals from the local labor force is computed based upon leakage rates&#13;
entered as input data. Nationals who leak out of the labor force are pooled&#13;
by occupational level according to the sector occupation combinatlons-from&#13;
which they leak. The pooled workers are subjected to a zero-to-three-year&#13;
wait, and are then subpooled either for reallocaion into the local labor&#13;
force (subpool type 1), or for exportation to other countries which import&#13;
labor (subpool type 2).&#13;
8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
In each locality the educational system is simulated using the&#13;
education simulation model, which produces several categories of school&#13;
leavers. Underage school leavers are pooled according to skill levels, and&#13;
are then placed in type 1 subpools for immediate allocation into the local&#13;
labor force. The stocks of graduates and dropouts are multiplied by&#13;
course-specific participation rates, and those who Survive this "filter"&#13;
are pooled according to skill levels as potential entrants to the labor&#13;
force. These pooled graduates and dropouts are divided into two subpools:&#13;
1) available for immediate allocation in the local labor force only; or 2)&#13;
available for exportation to other countries, in a type 2 subpool (if the&#13;
locality is an exporter of labor at this skill level).&#13;
The cell-specific sector/occupation labor requirements for each&#13;
country are compared with the existing labor force remaining in that&#13;
country after losses from attrition and leakage, to determine additional&#13;
labor requirements in each cell.&#13;
In each country, pools of any unallocated nationals are formed.    Each&#13;
occupation pool is-divided into two subpools.    Sub-pool type 1 contains--&#13;
nationals who are available -for immediate allocation into the local labor&#13;
force and nowhere else. 'As described above, this includes che underage-&#13;
school leavers and unleaked graduates and. diropouts from the local&#13;
educational system, as well as returning nationals who have dropped out of&#13;
another country's labor force (through attrition).- Sub-pool 2 contains all&#13;
the other nonallocated nationals available for immediate work. This&#13;
includes, as described above, nationals who have leaked from the local&#13;
labor force and gone through the zero- to thiree-year timefilter, leaked&#13;
graduates and dropouts from the local schooll system, and any surplus type 1&#13;
or type 2 subpool members who were not allocated in the prior simulation&#13;
year.&#13;
9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Type I subpool members are never subjected to exportation from the&#13;
home counry. Type 2 subpool members are subject to exportation only if the&#13;
occupational level is one for which the subpool's locality is designated to&#13;
be a labor-exporting country. There are several rounds of labor exchange&#13;
and countries exporting labor at one stage might subsequently become&#13;
importers of labor.&#13;
For each country, the simulation immediately allocates type 1 subpools&#13;
into the local labor force. Before type 2 subpools can be allocated, the&#13;
total exportation requirement must be calculated.&#13;
The labor migration sim4btion examines each occupation subpool looking&#13;
at all countries together. For each allocation level at a given&#13;
occupational level, the importing countries (designated in input data) are&#13;
determined, and allocation of their type 2 subpools is computed. (Note&#13;
that, by this point, these subpools are no longer subject to additional&#13;
exportation.) After the allocation is completed, the remaining need for&#13;
imports of labor in these importing countries is computed by examining each&#13;
sector occupation cell corresponding to the specific occupational level.&#13;
Within each "competing"-cell, anhinitial. estimate of the numbers of&#13;
the various expatriates to be imported is determined such that after&#13;
importation the expatriate percentages best correspond to the target&#13;
fractions entered for the cell. Importation is allowed only from countries&#13;
designated as suppliers (exporters) at the appropriate occupational and&#13;
allocation level combination, as stipulated on the data card(s). These&#13;
initial import input estimates are summed by nationality across all&#13;
competing cells and each sum is compared to the size of the pool of workers&#13;
available for export in the corresponding supplier locality. If any of&#13;
these export pools is inadequate to meet the combined import demand, the&#13;
10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
import estimates for corresponding suppliers are reduced on a pro rata&#13;
basis in all competing cells as necessary to assure no overdraft of&#13;
supplies.&#13;
Since supply limitations may prevent adequate importation to fulfill&#13;
the labor requirements of all the competing cells, a mechanism for&#13;
computing additional worker migration is provided. For those competing&#13;
cells which still have unfulfilled requirements after initial importation,&#13;
an attempt is made to import additional workers from regional supplier&#13;
localities with excess supply. All competing cells have equal priority in&#13;
drawing upon these excess supplies; and wit;hin each cell additional&#13;
supplier expatriates will be imported subject to the overage limits entered&#13;
by the user. These secondary import figures will be prorated across&#13;
competing cells to prevent overdraft of suplplies, and will be prorated&#13;
within cells to best maintain the relative expatriate representation&#13;
designated by the user.&#13;
After all excess regional supplies have been allocated to the maximum&#13;
extent possible within the limitations of the overage figures for specific&#13;
nationalities, workers from designated nonregional supplier localities will&#13;
be imported to fulfill remaining worker requirements in the competing&#13;
cells. These workers will be imported subject to their corresponding&#13;
overage limits, if stipulated. No prorating across competing cells is&#13;
necessary, however, since nonregional supplhies are presumed to-be&#13;
unlimited.&#13;
Finally, any remaining unfulfilled requirements within competing cells&#13;
will be filled by importation of workers from the last nonregional&#13;
nationality (generally, the true "rest-of-thie-world"), without reference to&#13;
any user entered limitations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Once the import pattern is determined for.a given allocation level,&#13;
migration is effected   to accomplish the desired importation.   This means&#13;
that the importing cells are allocated their determined worker imports, and&#13;
the type 2 subpools of exporting localities are reduced by the amount of&#13;
exportation. The computational technique assures that the type 2 subpools&#13;
have sufficient workers to satisfy the exportation.&#13;
Population aging is simulated for each country in addition to the&#13;
labor force computations, and population figures are adjusted to reflect&#13;
the movement of laborers and their dependents from country to country. The&#13;
numbers of migrating laborers are based upon user-entered dependency rates.&#13;
As an aid in analysis, shortages or surpluses of national laborers&#13;
(based on full nationalization of the labor force) are computed for each&#13;
occupational level in each country.&#13;
A schematic of the Migration Model appears in Figure 0-2.&#13;
0.6 Applications&#13;
The main virture of this complex methodology is that it allows the&#13;
simulation of labor flows by nationality in a disaggregated,&#13;
sector/occupation-specific fashion--this being where the critical&#13;
bottlenecks and problems arise, even in the presence of aggregate&#13;
equilibrium situations.&#13;
The primary utility of the model for country-level planning lies in&#13;
its ability to focus attention on the feasibility of reaching given&#13;
development targets in those countries where labor, rather than capital, is&#13;
a major constraint. Through use of real data from the national&#13;
education/training system, the model can show what additional imports of&#13;
expatriate labor will be required to reach specific output plan targets,&#13;
and what output targets by sector can be achieved with existing labor.&#13;
12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 0-2&#13;
MIGRATION MODEL&#13;
Worker Fow Diagram for-Typical Locality&#13;
dilrect - &#13;
entry             Type 1    -    -attrition return &#13;
-  -Subpool   J Leak~age|&#13;
_coEntroLr--j                              attrito0n&#13;
--allotation&#13;
underage                                         1RImportati0n-&#13;
leavers                                                                    _&#13;
ne          EDUCATION                                                        44&#13;
entrants      System                                             LABOR FORCE&#13;
Locals Expats            I mportato            t er Local&#13;
grad ates&#13;
dropouts                                                                -   attritio&#13;
Participation       Leakage&#13;
F11ter       ,Control                              'attr tion of&#13;
of              nationals&#13;
leaka e of &#13;
MV    ~nationals                  I&#13;
Waiting tTme             (                          0|blivionj&#13;
Workers          Filter                                                              expor ation&#13;
allo ation&#13;
2&#13;
Type 2&#13;
Subpool&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The model can also help answer questions of concern to planners and&#13;
policymakers such as the following: How soon can manpower and output goals&#13;
be achieved, if at all? What modifications, in terms of programs, training&#13;
infrastructure, instructors and redirected student flows, will be needed if&#13;
goals are to be achieved within a reasonable time horizon?&#13;
There are, however, three major prerequisites for such applications of&#13;
the model: (1) the availability of trained personnel (usually national&#13;
planners of the planning, education, and other sectoral ministries&#13;
concerned with training); (2) the maintenance of an up-to-date data base;&#13;
and (3) good coordination and common understanding between the agencies and&#13;
ministries involved. This last factor is perhaps the most important. The&#13;
recommendations flowing from the simulation of plans and policy measures&#13;
should lead, above all, to appropriate action to modify programs, redirect&#13;
flows, and charege administrative regulations.  The model is only a tool--a&#13;
means to those ends.&#13;
This paper comprises three parts, of which this introduction is Part&#13;
I. Part II describes the methodology of the country-specific model, the&#13;
expanded model, and the migration model, and discusses applications of the&#13;
model in detail. Part III Is a detailed user's guide.&#13;
14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PART II: METHODOLOGY OF THE MODEL&#13;
CHAPTER 1. THE COUNITRY MODEL&#13;
1.1 Introduction&#13;
This chapter presents and analyzes a compound computer-based simulation&#13;
model (the "country" model) that integrates aspects of a crucial process:&#13;
the balance between the supplies of and requirements for national and&#13;
nonnational (expatriate) labor in an expanding economy.1/   The chapter is&#13;
divided into several sections. First, an overview of the model is&#13;
presented, with a description of its goals and application, its basic&#13;
structure, and its forecasting capabilities. The sector/occupation matrix&#13;
(SOM)--a basic tool for articulating a coheirent manpower development&#13;
strategy--is also introduced.&#13;
The following sections present more detailed analysis of the four submodels&#13;
of the country model: the labor force modell (LFM); the manpower require-&#13;
ments model (MRM); the education simulation model (ESM); and the manpower&#13;
policy model (MPM). The discussion of each submodel is structured around&#13;
four elements: function, data requirements,, principal output reports, and&#13;
technical description.&#13;
The terms "requirements" and "supplies" are used instead of "demand"&#13;
and "supply" since the latter have a specific cost-asssociated meaning&#13;
in economic literature. What we mean by requirements and supplies are&#13;
absolute values that are assumed to be inelastic to price/cost&#13;
variations. They represent concepts that are more technological than&#13;
economic in nature.&#13;
15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
1.2  Overview:  Goals and Applications&#13;
The main purpose of the country model is to assist primarily labor-impor-&#13;
ting countries to develop coherent and workable human resource development&#13;
strategies. By grouping together a suitable series of analytic submodels&#13;
in an integrated fashion, the country model provides a tangible, systematic&#13;
framework within which various policy options can be explored and simu-&#13;
lated.&#13;
The great value of the country model is its ability to provide simulated&#13;
solutions derived on an iterative basis involving the sequential and inte-&#13;
grated solution of its component blocks or submodels. Such an approach&#13;
makes it possible to simulate an array of solutions based on rather varied&#13;
assumptions and constraints. This is preferable to a solution that is&#13;
based on optimization or constrained maximization, because the pattern&#13;
requires explicitly quantified tradeoffs. In the countries that would&#13;
profit from use of this model, such quantified tradeoffs are not yet&#13;
possible. At the present time, it is necessary to build upon variables&#13;
whose exact correlations are unknown, and upon the targetting of possibly&#13;
conflicting or contradictory objectives, such as maximum economic growth&#13;
versus nationalization of the labor force. Quite apart from difficulties&#13;
with the data base, the quantification of such tradeoffs is impossible to&#13;
determine without introducing largely arbitrary value judgments and perhaps&#13;
even the personal biases of the analyst.&#13;
The country model avoids such pitfalls by allowing decision makers to simu-&#13;
late the likely developments associated with any set of policies. It also&#13;
allows them to undertake a sensitivity analysis on any single policy vari-&#13;
able. The model imposes a framework of consistency for analysis of&#13;
economic growth and structural change, the performance of the education and&#13;
training system (ETS), and the importation and exportation of labor.&#13;
16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
In addressing the requirements for and supplies of labor in an expanding&#13;
economy in this way, the country model facilitates the resolution of&#13;
cballenges that arise on a geographical, temporal, and functional basis.&#13;
From the geographical perspective, although the country model was designed&#13;
primarily for labor-importing countries, with minor adjustments it can be&#13;
and has been applied to labor-exporting countries on a subnational, inter-&#13;
country basis, where the countries of concern can be conceptually defined&#13;
as comprising the region as a whole. (See Chapters 2 and 3 for a&#13;
discussion of the Expanded and Migration Models.) However, because the&#13;
initial design of the model was geared to the urgent needs of the&#13;
capital-rich (but labor-poor) Arab oil countries, use of the model by&#13;
labor-importing countries has predominated and, hence, will be emphasized&#13;
in the subsequent discussion.&#13;
From the temporal perspective, the country model also addresses major&#13;
short- and long-term considerations.   Its immediate value has been as an&#13;
instrument for the identification of potential structural inconsistencies&#13;
and discontinuities in the initial stage of accelerated industrialization&#13;
and for setting out alternative strategies t;o deal with them. For example,&#13;
it can evaluate the feasibility of any given set of growth targets and&#13;
explore alternative strategies for rapid growth in the face of short-term&#13;
constraints imposed by manpower scarcities. Further, however, there are&#13;
obvious structural discontinuties between thie initial stage of industriali-&#13;
zation, with great emphasis on infrastructure development, and the long-&#13;
term patterns of economic growth. When these stages are compressed in&#13;
time, as is the case with the oil-rich Arab countries, it is essential to&#13;
develop a transitional strategy that will avoid severe dislocation and high&#13;
social costs. A transitional strategy is particularly relevant since the&#13;
17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ETS invariably responds with very long lead/lag times. Such a transitional&#13;
strategy would seek to avoid locking the ETS into a pattern geared to&#13;
produce huge numbers of personnel within specific categories of manpower&#13;
for which the short- to medium-term need is acute, but for which the long-&#13;
term need is only moderate--especially when the time lag for producing such&#13;
personnel is long, as in the case of, say, port engineers. The country&#13;
model assists planners as they confront this challenge, although it is&#13;
recognized that long-term predictions are increasingly speculative.&#13;
From the functional perspective, the model can also address such distinc-&#13;
tions as that between aggregate analysis and a concentration on critical&#13;
skills, that is, on a subset of occupations where employment is numerically&#13;
small but qualitatively significant. The model concentrates on aggregate-&#13;
lemel consistency because of its systematic approach, but retains the&#13;
flexibility for further elaboration in such critial skill areas by&#13;
partitioning the sector/occupation matrix (SOM) described later.&#13;
Within the framework of these general goals, four specific applications of&#13;
the manpower model may be identified. Others will become evident during&#13;
subsequent discussions on the constituent submodels and their. outputs. -The&#13;
four applications of the country model are:&#13;
(1) To help planners in developing countries to forecast national and&#13;
nonnational manpower requirements necessary to meet specific sectoral&#13;
output targets;&#13;
(2) To identify and isolate specific problems in the supply of manpower&#13;
through simulation of flows of students and trainees through the ETS&#13;
in the light of such parameters as participation, repetition, dropout&#13;
rates, and qualifications required to enter programs;&#13;
18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(3)  To use an allocation submodel to set specific manpower targets, such&#13;
as maximinizing the number of nationals in certain occupational cate-&#13;
gories in a given sector, or improving the allocation of qualified&#13;
labor to occupations in those sectors of the economy that are consi-&#13;
dered to have a high priority; and&#13;
(4) To estimate! what production levels might be achieved in certain sec-&#13;
tors, atsuniing the use of existing, and probably indigenous, manpower&#13;
stocks, but with limits placed on the growth or overall numbers of&#13;
nonnational expatriate manpower.&#13;
1.3 Detailed Structure of the Model&#13;
The basic elements of the country model were described in the preview&#13;
section. More detailed flows and linkages, as well as sequential&#13;
operations within each of the submodels, are show in Figure 1-1. In this&#13;
figure, the main emphasis is on the systematic nature of the country model&#13;
as a whole, with flows and linkages represenited by solid lines; the various&#13;
submodels, characterized as "blocks," are shown as rectangles. The&#13;
detailed components shown in Figures 1.1 will be discussed in subsequent&#13;
sections of this chapter.&#13;
19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Figure 1.1&#13;
THE COUNTRY (COMPOUND) MODEL&#13;
r-LA OR F O7R C E BLO7C K ( L  FM-)  t--------- -- --&#13;
l~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~1 _m -  bo _.. w_  - rt      ww.y _2 ._ &#13;
_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ + bb._ ".-   .d  d$&#13;
I&#13;
_  _  _  |  MANPOWER  REQUIREMENT  BLOCE  (MRM)  MANPO WER ( P OLIC&#13;
--L~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ by        by  j8L&#13;
EUCATION TANN  LCC(S).         _ _ _ _ _ &lt;S   { &#13;
L _ _ _ _ - - - - - - - - - - -~~~~~b,b y-  by pad  oth_ _ _&#13;
I~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~d.R&#13;
I~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ .dw &#13;
I ~ L - - - - - - - - - - - -   - - - - - - - - - -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
1.4 The Sector/Occupation Matrix&#13;
A basic took for articulating the coherent human resources development&#13;
strategy represented by the country model is the sector/occupation matrix&#13;
(SOM) illustrated in Figures 1-2, 1-3, 1-4, 1-5. The SOM joins the four&#13;
submodels already outlined to provide the fifth basic component of the&#13;
country model. As Figures 1-2 to 1-5 indicate, the matrix is formed by&#13;
simultaneously analyzing economic activity by sector and by varying levels&#13;
of occupation. The sectors are divided into two main subdivisions, public&#13;
and private.   These are further divided into categories such as petroleum&#13;
products or education.   Occupations are ranked into a number of subdivi-&#13;
sions. An occupation in a given sector is represented by a single cell in&#13;
the matrix. The SOM thus offers a disaggreagated view of the labor force&#13;
employed. The country model allows for as many as 400 cells in the SOM.&#13;
The SOM is a very useful tool for articulating policy choices. This can&#13;
best be demonstrated by example. Consider a country whose rapid economic&#13;
growth is generating a demand for labor that will continue to outstrip its&#13;
best efforts at nationalization and training. Foreign labor will be needed&#13;
for the foreseeable future. The question is whether government should con-&#13;
centrate its nationalization and training efforts on nationalizing ali&#13;
parts of the labor force, or whether it should give priority to specific&#13;
areas.&#13;
The SOM can help answer this question, but three caveats must be empha-&#13;
sized: (1) nationalization of a sector/occujpation does not mean excluding&#13;
all expatriates; rather it- means employing only-a large majority of&#13;
nationals in the sector/occupation; (2) assigning priority to training and&#13;
21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Figure 1-2&#13;
THE SECTOR/OCCUPATION MATRIX (SOM) AND&#13;
ALTERNATIVE POLICY OPTIONS - I "ADMINISTRATIVE CONTROL"&#13;
Occupational groups&#13;
Economic activity          *  *&#13;
a     C  5 &#13;
sPrivateetors             -   0            O - .5  a&#13;
1.  Agriculture, etc.&#13;
2. Petroleum productior              _  _  _  _ &#13;
3. Other  ining and quarrying &#13;
4. Ilanuf cturifng (petroleu)_       _  _  _  _  _ &#13;
S.Manuf u e  ring (other)         _       _&#13;
6. Utilities~~~~~~~~~~rirtycel&#13;
7. Construction                         Non-pr_ority cells&#13;
S1. Trade  nd come4Xrce &#13;
9. Transport and counteztlions          V   c_ _ _s&#13;
10. Frannes; etc.                    _  _  _  _  _ 2&#13;
It. annity services__                       _ &#13;
12.~ Nod                       El,       NW   g&#13;
Govrnmnt seetorEs  &#13;
13 Publi aminitrattion snd defens e  __    ___ &#13;
15. Health                           - &#13;
Priority calls&#13;
0 Non-ptliorLty cello&#13;
Vold calls&#13;
22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Figure 1-3&#13;
THE SECTOR/OCCUPATION IMATRIX (SOM) AND&#13;
ALTERNATIVE POLICY OPTIONS-II "KEY SECTORS"&#13;
Occupational aroup&#13;
ESconomie activity&#13;
sector'                                   * e   :&#13;
I       uw   I     I       .   &#13;
*0    5        0          U   -          5&#13;
Private sectors:&#13;
1. Agriculture. etc.&#13;
2. Petrolem production&#13;
3. Other mining md quarrying&#13;
4. Manufacturing (petroleum)&#13;
5   Manufecturing (other)&#13;
7. Construction&#13;
8. Trade and comerc_&#13;
9. Transport *nd cmnications&#13;
10. Finance, etc.&#13;
11. Cozniqty services&#13;
12. Nomads&#13;
Covernment sectors:&#13;
13. Public administration  nd defense      La&#13;
14. Education&#13;
15. Uslth                               _   _ &#13;
Priority celil&#13;
R Non-priority cells&#13;
Void cells&#13;
23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Figure 1-4&#13;
THE SECTOR/OCCUPATION MATRIX (SOM) AND&#13;
ALTERNATIVE POLICY OPTIONS III "ACROSS THE BOARD"&#13;
Occupational groups&#13;
Eeonei                     tvt 2 -la~t &#13;
'Pr tva te sec tors:   W   g  s   g  ^  ^ Pri   c&#13;
2. Petroleum production               N       cell.&#13;
3.  other mining  nd quarrying &#13;
5.  Manufacturing (other)   _ 0N      |  g   0 &#13;
S. Utilities                     @    g  g   2 &#13;
7. COnutrUction       1X     E|       gEE &#13;
B. Trade and cemrtee  &#13;
1. Transport and convounicationQ       V   cell s&#13;
IO. Finance,e,tc.   - _'  1 24&#13;
1L.Cum nity   ervices ~1E &#13;
12. NomdsJ               f                          __&#13;
13. Publi   administration and defense  0   @5 &#13;
15  Health                              3  &#13;
M Priority cells&#13;
0 Non-priority calls&#13;
iEVoid calls&#13;
24&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Flgure 1-5&#13;
THE SECTOR/OCCUPATION MATRIX (SOM) AND&#13;
ALTERNATIVE POLICY OPTIONS -IV                                "SELECTED EMPHASIS"&#13;
Occupational groupe&#13;
Economic activity&#13;
cectors                                   oo e  e * a  1.  g        X     S1&#13;
;      u-o  1          U u              --e &#13;
.      a uc    .       .    _&#13;
03 0&#13;
ZO  0.  S..es:    A   , e       0       0 C,  . &#13;
Private sectors&#13;
1.  Agriculture, etc.&#13;
2.  Petroletm production&#13;
3.  Other mining and quarrying&#13;
4. Mtanufacturing (petroleum)&#13;
5.  mlanufacturing (other)&#13;
6. Utiliti*s ;_ &#13;
7. Construction&#13;
S.  Trade and commerce&#13;
9. Transport and com     ,nicetions&#13;
10. Finance, *tc.&#13;
11. Comunity ervices&#13;
Government sector-a:&#13;
13. Public administration and defene                         00&#13;
14. Education&#13;
IS.Helth                                    g    S     S   _ &#13;
* Priority ce*la&#13;
N Hon-priority cells&#13;
3 Void Cella&#13;
25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
employment of nationals in one sector/occupation does not mean that other&#13;
sectors/occupations will be ignored; and (3) selection of priority&#13;
sectors/ocupations does not guarantee that their nationalization will be&#13;
achieved in the timeframe under discussion.&#13;
Four alternatives sketches--purposefully exaggerated for emphasis--indicate&#13;
the implications of responding to the question posed above. They demon-&#13;
strate how useful the SOM can be in bringing clarity to the articulation of&#13;
alternative policy options. The four alternatives are illustrated in&#13;
Figures 1-2, 1-3, 1-4, and 1-5.&#13;
(a) Alternative I: "Administrative Control"&#13;
In this sketch, illustrated in Figure 1-2, the government would concentrate&#13;
on controlling the upper skill levels (professional, managerial, and higher&#13;
technical) across all sectors and would tolerate as many expatriate workers&#13;
as necessary to run the economy in the lower skill categories. This would&#13;
ensure that all decisions in all sectors are made by nationals. However,&#13;
this alternative has three main drawbacks: (1) it does not recognize the&#13;
great heterogeneity of the existing national population by assuming that&#13;
they should (or could) all be channeled into the upper skill levels? (2) it&#13;
does not afford options for those who drop out of tne tls on tneir way to&#13;
becoming managers, professionals, or technicians, or for those-currently&#13;
too old to enter the ETS in the appropriate streaming; and (3) it does not&#13;
recognize that operatives and skilled workers are equally necessary to keep&#13;
the economy going and that these occupations would be largely staffed by&#13;
expatriates.&#13;
(b) Alternative II: "Key Sectors"&#13;
This alternative is based on the assumption that some sectors are the&#13;
critical keys that control the economy. In Figure 1-3, four sectors--oil&#13;
26&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
production, construction, finance, and government administration and&#13;
defense--have been chosen as key sectors. Government efforts would be&#13;
geared to achieving nationalization in these' sectors at the possible&#13;
expense of other sectors. Again, there are drawbacks in that other sectors&#13;
are also significant. Education, for example, controls coming generations;&#13;
transport and communications could paralyze the country; and so on.    This&#13;
alternative does not sufficiently recognize! interlinkages between sectors.&#13;
(c) Alternative III: "Across the Board"&#13;
This alternative, as Figure 1-4 indicates, depicts the government efforts&#13;
as aimed at universal nationalization. Although nationalization is a legi-&#13;
timate long-terml goal, this alternative would spread national labor&#13;
resources too thinly, leaving the present labor-deficient situation rela-&#13;
tively unaffected for a number of years.    The national graduates at all&#13;
levels would be too few in each sector/occupation to make an immediate&#13;
impact on the labor shortage.&#13;
(d) Alternative IV:- "Selected Emphasis"&#13;
As Figure 1-5 indicates, this alternative is a stage in the achievement of&#13;
Alternative III,, and:combines the goals of Alternatives -I and II. It is&#13;
the most reasonable approach to the.problem.    Key sectors/occupations,&#13;
designated as cells wittin the SOM, would:be given priority. After the&#13;
most important cell is nationalized, the next most important set of cells&#13;
is given priority, until over the long term, Alternative III is reached.&#13;
Having outlined the used of the SOM in articulating poicy choices, we will&#13;
now discuss the general characteristics of the four submodels.&#13;
1.5  General Characteristics of the Four Submodels&#13;
The LFM accounts for the available labor force at the beginning of each&#13;
year by sector/occupation categories, including nationals and nonna-&#13;
27&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
tionals resident in the country.   Although some of the labor force is lost&#13;
through attrition, and will therefore. not be available in subsequent years,&#13;
additional resources will become available through output from education&#13;
systems and importing of nonnational manpower. The stock of available&#13;
manpower must be updated accordingly. Also, some members of the labor&#13;
force will be promoted within or across sectors; and it is necessary,&#13;
therefore, to introduce transition matrices to simulate internal movements&#13;
within the labor force itself.&#13;
The MRM first compiles the total manpower requirements for each sector/&#13;
occupation category to achieve given target products by dividing the speci-&#13;
fied target product by sector productivity, defined as value added per&#13;
worker per year.2/ Alternatively--as Figure 1-1 indicates--total manpower&#13;
requirements can be entered directly. This would be appropriate where good&#13;
data exist (for example, petroleum production in oil countries), or in&#13;
cases where employment is not necessarily a function of output (for&#13;
example, government employment).   Next, the net manpower requirements are&#13;
calculated by sector/occupation categories after subtracting the available&#13;
manpower stock from the total manpower requirements.&#13;
The ESM itself has-been designed on-the basis of an-earlier model of -the-&#13;
same name originally developed by UNESCO;' Basically, it estimates-those&#13;
leaving the school system by age and by level or type. It should be noted&#13;
that not all those leaving school will Join the labor force. Some will be&#13;
below the legal minimum age to work and will not join the labor force until&#13;
some years later. Some will not work for social, cultural, or other&#13;
2/ In this discussion, productivity is defined as value added per employed&#13;
worker in one year, without adjustments for time.&#13;
28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
reasons. Thus there is a need to introduce, the concept of a filter matrix&#13;
as a function of time. For those who enter given sector/occupation catego-&#13;
ries of the labor force, entrance qualifications may change over time,&#13;
depending on the evolving technological need, and there is, therefore, a&#13;
need to introduce the concept of entrance qualification matrices as a&#13;
function of time.&#13;
The MPM compares new manpower requirements with manpower supplies from the&#13;
education system, and attempts to allocate mnanpower in accordance with a&#13;
priority matrix. The priority and proportion of nationalization in each&#13;
sector/occupation is specified by policymakers. The ESM may be called upon&#13;
to readjust its intakes into given disciplines in order to meet manpower&#13;
requirements in accordance with the priority matrix for nationalization.&#13;
After this has been done, policies for the importation or exportation of&#13;
nonnationals would be articulated. In this exercise, a feasibility linear&#13;
programming model (LPM) (as opposed to an olptimization model) is intro-&#13;
duced, taking into account various policy constraints.&#13;
1.6 General Programming Approach of the Country Model&#13;
The model is basically a Markovian one. Simulation proceeds on an annual&#13;
basis, and the historical. data needed for the simulation of events or acti-&#13;
vities in a given year will include only those-of-the preceding year. At&#13;
the outset of any simulation run, an input editing program is activated to&#13;
ensure that all needed data are properly prepared. This program edits all&#13;
required inputs in one pass.3/! The editing to be done will mainly include&#13;
3/  This steD is made oossible because each card format has been designed&#13;
to contain an identification field which includes ID on submodel, card&#13;
types, and sequence numbers. This 'information is sufficient for an&#13;
edit program! to check all data types submitted for a given run.&#13;
29&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
programming editing and minor logical editing, such as a unit sum of&#13;
repetitions, dropouts, and promotion rates. As with any computer model, it&#13;
is the responsibility of users of the model to ensure that the data entered&#13;
are valid, because the model cannot protect itself from inaccurate or&#13;
fallacious inputs.&#13;
Once the data have passed the edit stage, the simulation starts with a run&#13;
to bring all base year data up to date. During this stage, input data are&#13;
sorted in the following order: by year; by block or submodel ID (labor&#13;
force block, manpower requirement block, education simulation block- and&#13;
manpower policy block); by card type; and by card sequence numbet. After&#13;
sorting is complete, the base year data are read into the allocated areas,&#13;
and the simulation for t = 1 begins.&#13;
The main control program then sequentially calls each submode-l-to simulate&#13;
events or activities in the year t = 1. The first call is made to the LFM,&#13;
which passes back to the main control program a flag indicating where the&#13;
base year data are stored. The second call is to the MRM, which calculates&#13;
the first year manpower requirements by sector and by occupation, and also&#13;
reads manpower requirements data for, the sectors where such data are deter-&#13;
mined exogenously, for example, government and petroleum sectors. The&#13;
third call is made to the ESM to obtain manpower requirement estimates for&#13;
teachers and to calculate net manpower supplies.   The fourth call is to an&#13;
entry point in the MRM to estimate net manpower requirements by sector and&#13;
occupation. The fifth call is made to the MPM to read a priority matrix&#13;
into the allocated areas,-comparing net manpower requirements with supplies&#13;
from the ESM. There may be feedback calls to a entry point in the ESM to&#13;
derive an acceptable education program to produce students in accordance&#13;
with the priority matrix. After these feedback calls, the MPM then&#13;
30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
proceeds to estimate available sector outputs based on the existing&#13;
available manpower including nationals and nonnationals in the country, and&#13;
to allocate nonnational manpower requirements in accordance with a linear&#13;
programing process. This necessarily oversimplified description outlines&#13;
the first year simulation.&#13;
At the beginning of the second year simulation, the cycle just described is&#13;
repeated, with some minor changes to each submodel. For example, the LFM&#13;
updates the existing labor force by incorporating additional manpower&#13;
supplies from the ESM and additional nonnationals permitted to work in the&#13;
country; estimates attritions; estimates internal labor force movements, if&#13;
any, and derives the net manpower stock available accordingly. In spite of&#13;
the minor changes in each submodel, the calling sequences from the main&#13;
control program to each submodel remain the same as for tne year t =1.&#13;
To summarize, there are four major advantages to this design. First, all&#13;
necessary input editing is done in one job submission. Second, any number&#13;
of simulation years can be accommodated by the system, subject to the&#13;
long-term uncertainties already mentioned. Third, the Markovian approach&#13;
allows users to simulate for one year, examine-the results, proceed for&#13;
another year, and so on. Fourth, .incorporation of.the LFM allows the&#13;
system to take inventories of the-existing labor force over-time to include-&#13;
nationals and nonnationals. Based on the existing labor force, achievable&#13;
sectoral outputs, and their nonnational manpower requirements correlates,&#13;
if any, can be estimated.&#13;
Having outlined the main features of tne country model, its goals and&#13;
applications, and its structure and general program approach, it is now&#13;
appropriate to examine each of the submodels in detail. In the followng&#13;
discussions, a standard format is used for this analysis, comprising four&#13;
31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
elements:  The function of the submodel; its principal data requirements;&#13;
the associated output reports; and a technical description. The submodels&#13;
are discussed in the followng order: the labor force model (LFM); the man-&#13;
power requirements model (MRM) the education simulation model, and the&#13;
manpower policy model (MPM). Reference should be made to Figure 1-2&#13;
throughout the discussion.   It should also be noted that the country model&#13;
and its submodels do not form a fixed system, but rather are designed as a&#13;
flexible methodological and empirical tool. Thus some aspects of the&#13;
submodels as described will continue to be refined and supplemented as the&#13;
model is applied for longer periods, in more countries, under different&#13;
circumstances.&#13;
1.7 The Labor Force Model (LFM)&#13;
Function&#13;
The LFM identifies the available national labor force at the beginning of&#13;
each simulation year by occupation within sector, and applies an attrition&#13;
rate. As a further refinement, a promotion filter may be used to account&#13;
for upward movement in the occupational structure or lateral transfers.4/&#13;
The LFM accounts for available new labor force entrants. from the ESM, after&#13;
applying a participation filter. For example, not all outputs from lower&#13;
secondary girls' programs will enter the labor force; some will probably&#13;
marry and remain outside the labor force permanently. The LFM also&#13;
computes the net supplies of manpower for the simulation year.&#13;
4/  Although She system's -logic allows this refinement, the statistical&#13;
data base needed to estimate transitional matrices is so huge that this&#13;
step will probably not be used in the near future.&#13;
32&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Principal Data Requirements&#13;
The principal data requirements for the LFM are: (1) the labor force for&#13;
the base year, by occupation within sector, disaggregated by nationals and&#13;
nonnonationals (by separate nationalities or groupings of nationalities);&#13;
aAd (2) attrition rates by occupation within sector, and by nationality.&#13;
(Alternatively, an average length of stay, as estimated from immigration&#13;
records, can be used for expatriates).&#13;
Principal Reports&#13;
The principal reports of the LFM describe the national labor force-by&#13;
occupation within sector. The reports include: the labor force at the&#13;
beginning of the simulation year; the numbers affected by attrition; the&#13;
labor force subsequent to attrition; the current labor force allocations&#13;
from the ESM; the total labor force availability at the end of-the simula-&#13;
tion year; the national labor force disaggiregated by occupations (summed&#13;
across sectors); the national labor force by sectors (occupations summed);&#13;
and various analyses of the expatriate labor force by nationality, by sec-&#13;
tor, and by occupation for the simulation year. The last category will&#13;
include:  the expatriate labor force; attrition (numbers affected by&#13;
average length of stay and retirement); the expatriate laDor fo'ce after&#13;
attrition; the expatriate requirements needed to fill deficits (after&#13;
al4ocation of nationals to the sector/occupation matrix according to&#13;
established priorities); and the net imporltation of expatriates.&#13;
Technical Description&#13;
Two basic categories are involved here: national labor, and the nonna-&#13;
tional (expatriate) labor force.&#13;
Taking the national labor force first, the following basic inputs are&#13;
required:&#13;
33&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
[NLF(O,i,j)]      =Base year national labor force stock by sector by&#13;
occupational category mix (i desiginates sector, j&#13;
occupational category).&#13;
NA(t,j)     =Attrition rates vector by occupation for national&#13;
labor. It is assumed that NA(t,j) = NA(t-1,j)&#13;
unless this is specifically changed by entering&#13;
attrition rates vectors for t.&#13;
The following functional relationships emerge:&#13;
NLF(t,i,j)      =National labor force at the beginning of year t, by&#13;
sector/occupation category.&#13;
(1.1)NLF(t,i,j)        =NLF(O,i,j), for t =1.&#13;
(1.2)NLF(t,i,j)        =NLF(t-1,i,j).(1-NA(t-1,i,j))+MSE(t-1,i,j) for t&gt;2&#13;
where MSE(t-1,i,j) is the labor force supplied Ey&#13;
the educational system in year t-1, by sector, by&#13;
occupation.&#13;
Outputs will then be existing labor force at the beginning of-year t by&#13;
sector, by occupational category and by year.&#13;
It should be noted at this point that.the model also allows for the&#13;
possible introduction of an intersectoral, interoccupational mobility&#13;
analysis. This analysis would be built uDon a "promotibn matrix"&#13;
[PRO(t,l,j) for national manpower to indicate the fraction-of sector/&#13;
occupation category (i,j) in t-+ 1. This.indicates internal transition&#13;
within the existing labor force as time advances from t to t + 1. If this&#13;
matrix is not entered, it is assumed that no such transition takes place&#13;
during the simulation period, but the design allows for its presence as a&#13;
dummy routine.&#13;
If this matrix were to be entered at a future date, equation (1.2) would&#13;
read:&#13;
34&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(1.3) NLF(t,i,j)    =NLF(t-1,i,j).(1-NA(t,-1,j)) + Net LPM(t-1,i,j)&#13;
+MSE(t-1,i,j) for t;&gt;2&#13;
Where [Net LPM(t-1,i,j)] indicates the nel; change in national labor force&#13;
due to promotions.&#13;
Turning now to the nonnational labor force, the following inputs are&#13;
required (for a given nationality n);&#13;
[XLF(O,i,j)]     =Base year nonnational (expatriate) labor force stock&#13;
by sector by occupational category matrix.&#13;
[XA(t,j)]     =Attrition rates vector by occupation.   It is assumed&#13;
that XA(t,j) = XA(t;-1,j) unless this is specifically&#13;
changed by entering attrition rates vectors for t.&#13;
The following functional relationships emerge:&#13;
[XLF(t,i,j)]      =Nonnational labor lForce at the beginning of year t,&#13;
by sector, by occupational catebory.&#13;
(1.4) XLF(t,i,J)     =XLF(O,i,j) for t = 1.&#13;
(1.5) XLF(t,i,j)     =XLF(t-1,1,j).(1-XAI:t-1,i,j)) + Net X(t-1,i,j) for&#13;
t&gt;2 where [Net X(t-.1,i,j)] is the net importation or&#13;
net exportation of nonnational manpower by sector,&#13;
by occupational category in year t-1, as calculated&#13;
by the MPM.&#13;
Inputs Needed&#13;
Let [XLF(O,n,i,j)]     =Expatrlate (fonnatlonal l-abor force in the country&#13;
by nationality (n) by sector (i) hy occupation (j)&#13;
in the base -year, then&#13;
(1.6) XLF(,O,n)   =-ZZXLF(O,n,i,j)&#13;
I              3&#13;
35&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(1.7) XLF(O,i,j)    =XLF,Z (O,n,i,j)&#13;
n&#13;
(1.8) XLF(t,n)    =XLF(t-1,n) + Net X (t-1,n) for t&gt;2)&#13;
Where [Net X(t-1,n)]  = is the net importation or exportation of expatriate&#13;
(nonnational) manpower by nationality in year t-1 as&#13;
calculated by the MPM (details of the procedure for&#13;
the estimation of this element will be found in the&#13;
description of the MPM itself).&#13;
1.8 The Manpower Requirements Model (MRM)&#13;
Function&#13;
The MRM requires specification of sector production targets, usually, on the&#13;
basis of a national development plan.   Its principal function is to calcu-&#13;
late occupational requirements for nationals in the light of asssumptions&#13;
about initial productivity in the base year and productivity growth.&#13;
Requirements are then expressed in terms of educational qualifications.&#13;
For example, senior technical occupations may be regarded as those requir-&#13;
ing a science or math-based degree, or, to be more specific, an agricul-&#13;
tural project manager would require a higher agricultural qualification.&#13;
Principal Data Requirements&#13;
The principal data requirements of the MRM are: gross domestic product&#13;
(GDP) for the base year by sector, annual sector targets for projected&#13;
years, sector productiviby for the base year, and sector productivity&#13;
growth rates.  If it is desired, labor-output elasticities can also be used&#13;
to estimate employment needs.&#13;
Principal Reports&#13;
The principal output reports associated with the MRM include:    (1) expected&#13;
production by sector and related manpower requirements by occupation within&#13;
36&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
sector, by year (indicating available nationals, existing expatriates, and&#13;
net additional requirements) and (2) aggregated manpower requirements by&#13;
sector.&#13;
Technical Description&#13;
For target sectoral products, several options are available:&#13;
Option 1: Input streaming vectori&#13;
Q(t,i)     The target product foir sector i, during period t,&#13;
measured in monetary terms.&#13;
Option 2: Given a constant production growth rate K and the base&#13;
year sectoral products Q(O,1)&#13;
(1.9) (Q(t,i)   = Q(t-l,i).(l + K)&#13;
Option 3:  Given variable growth rate K (t), a function of t,&#13;
and the base year sectoral products Q(O,i)&#13;
(1.10) Q(t,i)   - Q(t-1,i).(1 + K (t))&#13;
2Ltion 4:   Linear interpolation&#13;
Q(O,i): Base year sector product vector&#13;
Q(T,i) : Last simulat:ion year, T, sector product&#13;
vector.&#13;
For target sectoral productivities, again several options are available:&#13;
Option 1:   lnput streaming vector&#13;
P(t,i)     [nput productivity diata for each period t and for each&#13;
;ector i.&#13;
Option 2:   Given a constant growth rate K and the base year&#13;
productivity vector P(O,i)&#13;
(1.11) P(t,i)     P(t-1,l).(1 + K)&#13;
37&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Option 3: Given variable growth rate K (t), as a function of t,&#13;
and the base year productivity vector P(O,i)&#13;
(1-12)  P(t,i) =P(t-l,i).(l+K(t))&#13;
Option 4:  Linear interpolation&#13;
P(O,i) : Base year productivity vector&#13;
P(T,i) : Last simulation year, T, productivity vector&#13;
(1.13)  P(t,i) =P(t-l,i)+(T,i)-P(O,i))/T&#13;
If both Q(t,i) and P(t,i) are given, then employment estimates are derived&#13;
by:&#13;
(1.14) E(t,i) = Q(t,i)/P(t,i), P(t,i)&gt;O&#13;
where E(t,i) is the target employment level for sector&#13;
i in year t.&#13;
If data for Q or P are unavailable, E(t,i) must be input and may have one&#13;
of the following options:&#13;
Option 1:  Input Stream Vector&#13;
E(t,i)   - target employment vector for each period t and for&#13;
each sector i.&#13;
Option 2:  Given a constant employment growth rate Z and the base&#13;
year employment vector E(O,i)&#13;
(1.15)  E(t,i)   E(t-l,i).(l + Z)&#13;
Option 3:  Given variable employment growth rate Z(t) as a&#13;
function of t and the base-year,vector E(O,i)&#13;
(1.16)  E(t,i) = E(t-l,t).(l + Z(t))&#13;
Option 4:  Linear interpolation&#13;
E(O,i): Base year employment vector&#13;
E(T,i): Last simulation year T, employment vector.&#13;
To convert the employment estimates into the sector/occupation matrix&#13;
(SOM), the following inputs are required:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
[H(t,i,j)]     = the matrix defining the distribution of occupation&#13;
j for each sector i at time t. The elements&#13;
h(t,i,j) of the matrix have the following&#13;
properties:&#13;
(1.17)   h(t,i,j) = 1.0, where h(t,i,j) is the share of the Jth&#13;
occupational input in the total labor input in&#13;
sector i in year t.,&#13;
(1.18) 1.0&gt;h(t,t,j)&gt;0.0&#13;
As was previous'ly noted, total employinent by year for some key sectors (for&#13;
example the petroleum and the government sectors) may be exogenous and&#13;
should be entered directly, while total requirements for teachers will be&#13;
obtained from the ESM.   These estimates would then be converted by"&#13;
EH(t,i,j)] into sector/occupation breakdowns, unless entered as such.&#13;
The following functional relationships emerge:&#13;
Let [TLF(t1,,j)] = the manpower requirement matrix&#13;
l(t,i,j) = the elements of [TL,F(t,i,j)]&#13;
e(t,i) = the elements of [E(t,i)], the employment estimates&#13;
for sector i, in year t&#13;
h(t,jt) = the elements of [H(t,i,j)]&#13;
(1.19) l(t,,ij) - e(t,1).h(t,i,j); that is, labor requirements in&#13;
(i,j) are derived as the product of target&#13;
employment in sector i and the jth occupation share&#13;
The following properties hold:&#13;
(1.20) i l(to X =) e e(t,i ).h(t,i J) = e(t,i ).Ih(t,i J) = e(t,l)&#13;
where&#13;
YE l(t,ij) = Total manpower requirements for sector i at time t.&#13;
l(ti,j) = Total manpower requirements for occupational&#13;
category j at time t.&#13;
and&#13;
(1.21) E zl(t.i,j) =     e(t,i)&#13;
ij                              3&#13;
39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
It is now possible to derive net manpower requirements.    Let Net MR(t,,J)&#13;
be the net manpower requirement for the current-year school leavers&#13;
(dropouts) and nonnationals: and recall that.TLF(t,i,j) is the manpower&#13;
requirement in period t for sector i and occupational category j, and&#13;
NLF(t,i,j) is the existing national labor force at the beginning of t for&#13;
sector i and occupational category j, then&#13;
(1.22)   Net MR(t,i,j) = TLF(t,i,j) - NLF(t,i,j)&#13;
The associate outputs are: (1) estimated employment by sector by year; (2)&#13;
estimated output by sector by year; (3) estimated manpower requirements by&#13;
sector by occupational category by year; and (4) net manpower requirements&#13;
for the current-year school leavers and for nonnationals.&#13;
1.9 The Education Simulation Model (ESM)&#13;
Function&#13;
The ESM or the Educational Training System (ETS), simulates flows of stu-&#13;
dents and trainees through the system on the basis of initial enrollments&#13;
in the base year and assumptions about participation rates, repetition&#13;
rates, promotion rates, and dropout rates. Participation rates are defined&#13;
as those of girls and boys in a program or of a percentage of an age group,&#13;
or of a percentage of graduates entering a course from a previous one, for&#13;
example, the percentage of primary graduates going to either lower secon-&#13;
dary general establishments or out into the labor force.    Repetition, drop-&#13;
out, and promotion rate, by definition, add up to unity. However, dropouts&#13;
are split into two groups: those leaving at the end of the year having&#13;
successfully completed the year (i.e., noncontinuing completers) and those&#13;
who have not successfully completed the year (dropouts).    This differentia-&#13;
tion is important since employers make this distinction.    This schema lends&#13;
itself to a Markovian type of analysis as can be seen from Figure 1-6.&#13;
40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Figure 1-6&#13;
THE MARKOVIAN BASIS OF THE ESM(ETS)&#13;
(Possible nev entrants are allowed)&#13;
Repeater&#13;
Entrant                  Continuing completer                                                      T&#13;
Dropout               Non-continuing&#13;
comtpleter&#13;
Exit points t'rom ETS&#13;
Note., Eacb audezw in any given course IAs one of four posible succesr ates: (i) epeca in sWe. coune; (ii)&#13;
compkter continuing to wsceemr coue; (iii) nron-coinwuing completer. (iv) nonornpleting da apos. The&#13;
lht two consdttu exit point from the ETS.&#13;
41&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
These parameters can be changed to reflect such educational policy deci-&#13;
sions as: a greater participation of girls in a given program; increased&#13;
flows from secondary to vocational/technical programs, or specification of&#13;
particular proportions of upper secondary school entrants to literary and&#13;
science-oriented courses; or the introduction of "automatic promotion" or&#13;
limiting of repetition to a preestablished maximum number of times.&#13;
The policy changes are reflected in the pattern of flows of students&#13;
through and out of the ETS. This can be understood more clearly by looking&#13;
at a graphic representation of a typical ETS structure as it would be simu-&#13;
lated by the ESM (Figure 1-7). For the purpose of flows to the labur&#13;
force, the model considers any year of any program as a "course." Each&#13;
course has two exit points since the model classifies ETS leavers in two&#13;
ways: completer and dropout.&#13;
The treatment of ETS leavers is graphically illustrated in Figure 1-8,&#13;
which indicates that exit points from courses feed through a participation&#13;
matrix into pools from which a number of given occupations in specified&#13;
sectors can draw. This procedure overcomes one of the most common objec-&#13;
tions to most manpower modeling, namely the education-occupation correspon-&#13;
dence. The approach allows each output point from the ETS to lead to more&#13;
than one occupation in a given sector. It also allows each occupation in a&#13;
given sector to draw on more than one exit point of the ETS. If adequate&#13;
statistical data were available, probability distribution functions could&#13;
be employed. The design of the model allows for this possibility.&#13;
However, even without the probabllltytunctlons, tne pooling method&#13;
provides a great deal of realism to the modeling work. It also ensures a&#13;
certain flexibility. For example, it might be assumed that skilled&#13;
clerical occupations draw upon completers (but not dropouts) from years two&#13;
42&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Figure 1-7&#13;
A TYPICAL ETS STRUCTURE [N TERMS OF&#13;
COURSES FOR SIMULATION IBY THE ESM&#13;
Polytechnic&#13;
1    2&#13;
Vocational        Vocational        Teacher training&#13;
training          training&#13;
Arts and Sciences&#13;
General&#13;
Kindergarten    I            Primary                Preparatory        Secondary        Engineering&#13;
I &#13;
I       .                         I                                     Medicine&#13;
i                                 I                    Technical&#13;
Secondary&#13;
Primary Teacher Training&#13;
I                               JI                                    I&#13;
I                                 I &#13;
.E- Preschool                 Primary -1                        Secondary               I -          Higher&#13;
43&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Figure 1-8&#13;
THE POOLING CONCEPT&#13;
Another set of                A third set of&#13;
k set of ETS exit points            ETS exit points               ETS exit points&#13;
Participation&#13;
matrix&#13;
POOL                              POOL 2                         POOL 3&#13;
A set of SOM cells            A second set of SOM cells      A third set of SOX cells&#13;
44&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
and three of the preparatory program.   Planners can insert their own infor.&#13;
mation about the changing recruitment practices of employers. This flexi-&#13;
bility is important since manpower surpluses or shortages may raise or&#13;
lower recruitment levels as expressed in educational attainment. One&#13;
inviolable rule of the system is that no cell (occupation in a given sec-&#13;
tor) in the sector/occupation matrix (SOM) may draw upon more than one&#13;
pool. A pool, however, can be made as large or as small as conditions&#13;
warrant. The total number of pools (or exit points) is theoretically&#13;
bounded by the size of the SOM, which can have as many as 400 pools,&#13;
although such extreme disaggregation would greatly diminish the flexibility&#13;
and usefulness of the pooling approach.&#13;
Principal Data Requirements&#13;
The principaX base line data requirements fDr the ESM are: base year&#13;
enrollments of nationals in each course (as defined above--this means for&#13;
every year of the program, in every level and branch of the system),&#13;
together with age/grade distribution, if possible; participation, dropout,&#13;
and repetition rates; stock of teachers by type; and desirable student/&#13;
teacher ratios for each program.&#13;
Principal Reports&#13;
The principal reports of the ESM are divided into two main categories:&#13;
status of underage school leavers by age and level (that is, those who are&#13;
too young to enter the labor force) if the age/grade distribution is given;&#13;
and current dropouts and potential participants (filtered for participa-&#13;
tion) by grade and by program.&#13;
Technical Description&#13;
The UNESCO ESM model has been significantly modified for use as part of the&#13;
country model. The two most important modifications involve streaming con-&#13;
trol and age ancl labor force participation.&#13;
45&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
In regard to streaming control, it was important that the educational&#13;
system should not produce more students in any discipline than the number&#13;
needed to meet the manpower requirements. A-feedback mechanism was there-&#13;
fore required so that the ESM, while taking into account repetition,&#13;
dropout, and promotion rates in various grades, was able to readjust its&#13;
intake at postprimary levels in order to meet the manpower requirements in&#13;
accordance with national priorities (as defined by the priority matirx).&#13;
This feedback originally applied only to requirements for teachers, but was&#13;
expanded to include other disciplines. Adjustments were made to promotion&#13;
distribution functions so that intakes for a given discipline would not&#13;
produce more students than target graduates, who, after being filtered by a&#13;
participation matrix and mapped by an entrance qualification matrix, would&#13;
merge into the existing labor force.&#13;
The modifications regarding age and labor force participation are more&#13;
complex to describe. Among those leaving school, there are underage&#13;
students who will not be able to participate in the labor force because of&#13;
the minimum legal age requirements. As a result, the ESM was modified to&#13;
be able to calculate underage dropouts by age and by educational level.&#13;
Finally, it should be noted that the ESM should also try to account for&#13;
those who never attend any form of schooling but who ultimately enter the&#13;
labor force. The programming effort needed to do this is insignificant if&#13;
the data are available.&#13;
In general, the Markovian structure of the model can be summarized as&#13;
follows:&#13;
Each student (s) in any given course (c) at time (t) has one of several&#13;
possible successor states in t + 1: s (rep), s (pro), s(cont), s(non cont),&#13;
and s(d).&#13;
46&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Where:  1.  s(rep)       =  repeater in same course;&#13;
2.  s(pro)      =  completer (promoted), whether continuing or not&#13;
continuing to successor course c;&#13;
3.  s(cont)     =  completer (promoted) continuing to sucessor&#13;
course;&#13;
4.  s(non cont) =  completer (promoted) not continuing in ETS; and&#13;
5.  s(d)        = dropout (non cormpleter)&#13;
Let total enrollment in course c at time t = TS(t,c)&#13;
epro(t,c) = promotion rate in course c at time t&#13;
rep(t,c) = repetition rate in course c: at time t&#13;
d(t,c) = dropout rate in course c at; time t&#13;
then:&#13;
(1.23) epro(t,c) + rep(t,c) + d(t,c). = 1.0&#13;
(1.24) s(rep, t + 1) = TS(t,c) . rep(t,c)&#13;
(1.25) s(d,t + 1) = TS(t,c) . d(t,c)&#13;
(1.261 s(ioro,t + 1) = TS(t,c) . epro't,c)&#13;
Where s (pro, t + 1) is the total number ol' students/trainees to be&#13;
promoted into higher courses or become gracluates in time t.&#13;
The treatment of outDut of the ESM is as follows:&#13;
47&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Assuming the existence of the following input:&#13;
[UAD(O,c,a)]    = the existing cumulative underage dropouts by course c&#13;
and by age a in base year. It is asumed that c and a&#13;
are well defined. Also let:&#13;
AA = the minimum legal age to work minus one, and&#13;
BB = the minimum age allowed to attend any school&#13;
Where BB &lt; AA.&#13;
[FIL(t,c)]    = rates of graduates from course c, in year t, to&#13;
participate in the labor force. Unless FIL(t,c) is&#13;
modified, it is assumed to be the same as the preceding&#13;
year.&#13;
[EQk(t,c.i j)]    = entrance qualification matrix for graduates from course&#13;
c into sector i and occupational category j in year t.&#13;
Unless modified, it is assumed to be the same as the&#13;
preceding year. EQM(t,c,i,j) should be applied to&#13;
graduates filtered by FIL(t,c).&#13;
Two functional relationships emerge: the calculation of underage dropouts,&#13;
and manpower supplies by.the ESM.&#13;
Approaching first the calculation of current underage dropouts&#13;
[CUD(t,c,a)], it is necessary to note that:&#13;
EUAD(t,c,a)]   = cumulative underage dropouts by course c and by age a&#13;
at the end of year t;&#13;
[UAD(t-l,c,a-1]   = the cumulative underage dropouts by course c and by age&#13;
a-i at the end or year t-1;&#13;
[CUD(t,c,a)]   = the current year flow of underage dropouts by course c&#13;
and by age a in year t.&#13;
48&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(1.27) UAD(t,c,a) = UAD(t-1,c,a-1) + CUD{t,c,a)&#13;
for all c and a which satisfies the constraint&#13;
BB + 1&lt;a&lt;AA,t&gt;1&#13;
(1.28) UAD(t,c,BB) = CUD(t,c,BB) for all of c.&#13;
It should also be noted that [UAD (t-1,c,AA)] will be allowed to go into&#13;
the labor market in year t, because in year t those students of age AA in&#13;
year t-1 will reach the legal minimum age to work.&#13;
Turning now to imanpower supplies by the ESM:&#13;
Let [LG(t,c)]       = the number of graduates from course c who will be&#13;
eligible to participate in the labor force after&#13;
filtered by FIL(t,c) in year t.&#13;
(1.29)     [LG(t,c) = FIL(t,c)] . G(t,c)&#13;
Where: [G(t,c)] is the number of graduates from course c in year t.&#13;
To provide realism, the filtering matrix [FIL(t,c)] can be made&#13;
age-specific, allowing a number of underage dropouts to participate in the&#13;
labor force, even though they are below the legal entry age. This concept&#13;
is graphically illustrated in Figure. 1-.9.&#13;
MSE(t,i,J)]  = Manpower supplies by ESM to go into labor force by&#13;
sector i, occupational category j, in year t.&#13;
(1.30) MSE(t,i,j)   = EQM(t,c,i,j) LG(t,c) where [LG(t,c)] is summed for&#13;
all c having the same i and j in EQM(t,c,i,j). This,&#13;
in effect, says that graduates from different courses&#13;
may be qualified into the same setor/occupation&#13;
Associated reports acategory.&#13;
re: (1) underage dropouts by age and by course and&#13;
year (cumulative data); and (2) manpower supplies by ESM into the existing&#13;
labor force by sector by occupational category by year.&#13;
49&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Figure 1-9&#13;
THE TREATMENT OF UNDERAGE SCHOOL LEAVERS:&#13;
THE FILTER MATRIX&#13;
l     giniam b&#13;
C -   Underage           &gt;   of entry  |     e ao   age&#13;
into labor      lgl"&#13;
force&#13;
(x-4)   (x-3)   (x-2)    (z-I)     (x      .1)    (x4.2)  (.43)&#13;
Output of ITS&#13;
by &amp;a&#13;
0&#13;
2&#13;
_3&#13;
La years&#13;
Output of ITS eligible to participete in labor Lorce&#13;
Pa ticlpatian&#13;
labojr corce -rools"&#13;
50&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Incorporation of' Additional Capability&#13;
An additional czipability has. also been incorporated into UNESCO's ESM&#13;
system. Its purpose is to ensure that the teacher training facilities in&#13;
an educational system. will not produce more teachers than what is required.&#13;
The expanded capability includes an algorithm for backward calculations to&#13;
determine desired intakes for a given level of teachers' training (or&#13;
targeting); and a search scheme for needed data, such as dropout/repeating&#13;
rates at a given point in time.   The details are given below:&#13;
Inputs&#13;
The following additional data are'required, some for the purpose of clarity&#13;
and some for computational requirements;&#13;
a.  Teacher Group Descriptions&#13;
b.  Base Year Teacher Stock by Group&#13;
c.  Attrition Rates by Teacher Group&#13;
This includes both voluntary and involuntary withdrawals from the&#13;
teaching forces.&#13;
d.  Course Number&#13;
Definition of Variables and Algorithm&#13;
ST(O,g) = Base year teacher stock for group g; it is a vector input, in&#13;
which the dimension is equal to the total number of teacher&#13;
groupings.&#13;
AT(g)    = Constant annual attrition rates for group g; it is a vector&#13;
input. AT(g)&lt;i.O&#13;
ST(t,g)  5 Teachers available in year t&gt;1 for group g;&#13;
= ST(t-1,g) . (1-AT(g)) for each group g;&#13;
TTR(t,g) = Total teacher requirements in t&gt;1 for group g as projected by&#13;
ESM&#13;
51&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Net TR(t,g) = Net teacher requirement in t&gt; 1 for group g&#13;
- TTR(t,g)-ST(t,g)&#13;
= Total requi-red, less those available)&#13;
Note: This is also called the target graduates, from which the desired&#13;
intakes will be calculated, taking into accounts both the&#13;
dropout/repeating rates and the years in stream.&#13;
[DIT(t,g)] = Desired intakes in year t to produce target graduates&#13;
[NetTr(t+b,g)] from which will be calculated DIT(t,g),&#13;
where b is years in stream.&#13;
[PIT(t,g)] = Projected intakes in year t for teacher group g as&#13;
calculated by the ESM. This is a straightforward&#13;
application of distribution patterns (PPDD values) to a&#13;
given graduating class.&#13;
Algorithm&#13;
(1) If PIT(t,g) = DIT(t,g), no adjustment is required for group g, i.e.,&#13;
the projected intakes are less than or equal to the desired intakes.&#13;
Therefore, no over-production of teachers in group g is anticipated.&#13;
(2) If PIT(t,g)&gt;DIT(t,g), the following adjustments should be made, but&#13;
note that any adjustments could be done only for t&gt;1, because actual&#13;
intakes (i.e., intakes that took place in or before the base year)&#13;
cannot be readjusted. Namely, intake adjustments could be done only&#13;
for target graduates in t + b and beyond.&#13;
To adjust, the difference (i.e., PIT(t,g)-DIT(t,g) should be redistributed&#13;
in accordance with the conditional (or revised) PPDD distribution excluding&#13;
the proportion allocated for the intake into teacher group g in t for a&#13;
given graduating class.   To illustrate, let the original PRDD distribution&#13;
for a given graduating class, say, of 1,000 students be:&#13;
52&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
20% or 200 students for teacher training&#13;
50% or 500 students for general studies&#13;
30% or 300 students available fo the labor market&#13;
and let the desired intake as calculated by the ESM for teacher training be&#13;
120 students. Since the desired intake of 120 DIT(t,g) is less than the&#13;
projected intake of 200 PIT(t,g), the difference of 80 (200-120) should be&#13;
redistributed in accordance with the conditional distribution of 50/80 and&#13;
30/80 to general studies and available for 1the labor market, respectively.&#13;
If we compare against the original projection, the adjusted intake will be&#13;
as follows:&#13;
Original Pirojection     Revised Projection&#13;
Teacher Training                          200                     120&#13;
General Studies                           500                     550&#13;
Available for the Labor&#13;
Market                                  300                     330&#13;
F, OUF                  TUUU&#13;
1.10 THE MANPOWER POLICY MODEL (MPM)&#13;
Function&#13;
The basic function of the MPM is to allocate supplies from the existing&#13;
surviving labor iforce, from the ESM, and from foreign sources of labor to&#13;
the overall SOM according to specific priorities and constraints. For&#13;
example, in allocating manpower with professional qualifications and senior&#13;
technical qualiflications--i.e., engineers--a priority might be assigned to&#13;
those occupational categories within sectors considered to be strategically&#13;
important (for example, in the oil industry).&#13;
The MPM can also maximize the number of nationals employed in a specific&#13;
occupation withirn a sector. In a case where supplies exceed requirements,&#13;
53&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
adjustments in participation and repetition coefficients in the ESM will&#13;
have to be made. Alternatively, the planner may adjust entry requirements&#13;
elsewhere, introducing alternative labor force entry points and/or ESM&#13;
follow on courses. In cases where supplies are smaller than requirements,&#13;
the most critical priorities will be satisfied first. Where priorities&#13;
are equal and supplies are insufficient, allocation between sector/occupa-.&#13;
tion cells is made on the basis of each cell's net requirements weighted by&#13;
the degree of nationalization already obtained.&#13;
Special note must be taken of the allocatioin of expatriate personnel.&#13;
Once the available national labor force has been allocated to the SOM (that&#13;
is, the existing labor force less attrition, plus the new entrants from the&#13;
ESM) the residual requirements--in the form of expatriate personnel--can be&#13;
estimated.&#13;
To simulate reality, four sets of constraints are introduced into the model&#13;
to govern to allocation of expatriate labor and the solution of the related&#13;
forecasts:&#13;
Quantitative constraints, by nationality groups, limiting the maximum&#13;
numbers of each group that the model may draw from. This set provides some&#13;
realistic ceilings within which the forecast must remain.&#13;
Qualitative constraints, to reflect- either-the entry requirements. of spe-&#13;
cific positions (for example, that nonnationals cannot be considered for&#13;
teaching requirements) or the nature of the supplying labor force (for&#13;
example, that Americans will not be used for unskilled labor).&#13;
Policy constraints, limiting the allowable proportion of expatriates in any&#13;
single sector, occupation, or cell in the SOM. Such constraints could also&#13;
be reflected as a limit of the allowable proportion of any single national-&#13;
ity group among expatriates in any single sector, occupation, or cell in&#13;
the SOM.&#13;
54&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Boundary constraints, limiting the extent to which the magnitude of the&#13;
forecast components can vary from year to year.   This can be viewed as a&#13;
smoothing function, providing a maximum feasible band within which the&#13;
forecast must remain.&#13;
The allocation of expatriates to the SOM cellls is made by a linear program-&#13;
ming model (LPM) that can respect these constraints.    Since the model a a&#13;
whole accommodates up to 10 nationalities or national groups, and there can&#13;
be as many as 400 SOM cells, the total variables (or possibilities of&#13;
assignment to a nationality pool) are 4,000. To make allocation less com-&#13;
plex, the SOM can be partitioned into critical skill areas--for example,&#13;
into the category of managerial and senior technical posts in key sectors.&#13;
The LPM allocates available expatriate labor-, in the light of the previ-&#13;
ously mentioned constraints, to the most critical partition. It then pro-&#13;
ceeds to the next partition, while taking into account those from a given&#13;
nationality and/or skill mix who have already been used in the preceding&#13;
allocation. The process continues until residual SOM requirements are&#13;
satisfied.&#13;
Principal Data Requirements&#13;
The MPM has two basic categories of data requirements.    The first consists&#13;
of SOM priorities, which may be either judgmental or based on labor market&#13;
surveys designed to inventory critical -skill needs on the part -of both pub-&#13;
lic and private enterprises.   The second consists of the appropriate tar-&#13;
gets and constraints for the percentage of nationalization and expatriate&#13;
mix. This is a policy decision that is made by national decisionmakers.&#13;
Principal Reports&#13;
The MPM produces a variety of reports, including allocation reports (such&#13;
as the allocation of "pooled" leavers by occupation within sector), and a&#13;
55&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
nationalization program analyses report (comprising (a) sector/occupation&#13;
requirements, (b) existing natioal labor force, (c) nationalization, (d)&#13;
number of nationals needed, (e) the difference between (a) and (b), (f)&#13;
current ESM supplies, and (g).net additional requirements). It also&#13;
provides nationality for every occupation withn a given sector), total&#13;
sector employment distribution by naitonality, total employment by occupa-&#13;
tion distributed by nationality group, comoarison of target sectoral&#13;
outputs with achievable outputs given the existing (national and&#13;
nonnational) labor force, and manpower availability by pool.&#13;
Technical Description&#13;
As indicated, the MPM articulates manpower policies, taking into account&#13;
national priorities in the process of nationalization and policy cons-&#13;
traints on the expatriate labor force. Manpower supplies from the&#13;
educational system are allocated in accordance with a priority matrix in&#13;
which the priority of each sector/occupation and the fraction of nation-&#13;
aliztion are specified. The priority matrix is defined as PM(i,j,m,f)&#13;
where f indicates the fraction, and p, the priority of nationalization for&#13;
sector i, occupation j. The manpower supplies from the-ETS are pooled and&#13;
allocated to each sector/occupation in accordance with the priority matrix&#13;
PM(i,j,m,f). The prioritY f. as stipplied by policymakers, will determine&#13;
the sequence of allocation among the set of sector/occupation cells compe-&#13;
ting for the same pool of manpower supplies. If manpower supplies exceed&#13;
requirements the question of priority allocation will not arise. However,&#13;
when requirements exceed supplies, one of several allocation mechanisms can&#13;
be used to allocate the pooled manpower supplies among competing sector/&#13;
occupations having the same priority rating. The model allows a choice of&#13;
four possible methods.&#13;
56&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Method 1--The allocation is done in proportion to the net additional&#13;
requirements needed to achieve nationalization targets. Namely, each&#13;
shortage required to achieve the nationalization program will have equal&#13;
weight to command the allocation of manpower supplies from a given pool.&#13;
With this method, no consideration is given to the percentage of nationali-&#13;
zation already achieved, nor does the method aim at necessarily completing&#13;
nationalization of any given sector/occupation.&#13;
Method 2--Here the sector/occupation having the lowest achieved percentage&#13;
of nationalization will get its allocation First among the competing&#13;
sector/occupations having the same priority for the same pool.&#13;
Method 3--This method maximizes the total number of sector/occupations that&#13;
would have achieved the nationalization proclram after allocation of the&#13;
current year's manpower supplies. The rules are:&#13;
(a) the competing sector/occupation requiring the fewest number of the&#13;
pooled manpower supplies to achieve thie nationalization program will&#13;
get its allocaion first;&#13;
(b) If there are still unallocated supplles, then the sector/occuDation&#13;
requiring the next fewest number of the pooled manpower To acnieve&#13;
its nationailization program will get the next allocation; and&#13;
(c) So on until all available pooled manpower supplies are exhausted.&#13;
Method 4--This method is a variant of method i, weighted by the percent&#13;
that is still required to achieved the natioi,alization program of a given&#13;
sector/occupation.&#13;
Let f(i,j) be the target share of workers in sector i and occupation J,&#13;
that is national labor force&#13;
[TLF(t,i,j)] is the estimated total manpower requirements for sector i and&#13;
occupation j&#13;
57&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
1.31)Then, NG(t,i,j) = TLF(t,i,j). f(i,j) is the target level of national&#13;
labor which meets the nationalization goal&#13;
(1.32)Recall that NLF(t,i,j) is the extsting national labor force in sector&#13;
i and occupation j&#13;
Then, the net additional manpower requirements NAR(t,i,j) to achieve the&#13;
nationalization program for sector i and occupation j are given by&#13;
[NAR(t,i,j)] = NG(t,i,j)-NLF(t,i,j).   It is to be noted that if and when&#13;
NAR(t,i,j)&lt; 0, then NAR(t,i,j) = 0. Namely, the required fraction of the&#13;
nationalization program has already been achieved.&#13;
Let PER(t,i,j) be the percent of the target of national workers still&#13;
needed to nationalize in a given sector/occupation (i,j) in t, that is:&#13;
PER(t,i,j) = NAR (t,i,j)/NG(t,i,j) x 100&#13;
Using the above parameters, the allocation formula for Method 4 for a given&#13;
set of i and j having the same priority and sharing a common pooled&#13;
manpower supply, will be as follows:&#13;
(1.33)Alloc (t,i,j) =     NAR(t,i,j).PER(t,1,j) . pool&#13;
X_T KAR(t,1 j).PER(t,l ,}&#13;
ij&#13;
for i and j sharing the pooled manpower supply.&#13;
It should be noted that if Alloc (t,i,j)&gt;NAR(t,i,j), then the actual_&#13;
allocation should be less than or equal to NAR(t.i,j), and whatever remains&#13;
in the pool will be allocated to the next priority i and j sharing the&#13;
pooled manpower supply.&#13;
There are certainly other methods that can be devised to reflect&#13;
policymakers' choices, and further refinements to the model are possible in&#13;
this area. Further work in this area is being carried out at present.&#13;
Turning now to the linear programming package, one of many that can be&#13;
introduced into the single country exercise, the following application is&#13;
for labor-importing countries. There the task is to minimize the total&#13;
na&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
imputed cost (social and economic) of having expatriates work in the&#13;
country, assuming that it is possible to impute unit costs of having one&#13;
expatriate-man-year of a given nationality work in a given sector/occupa-&#13;
tional category. The LP package has linear constraints in sector/occupa-&#13;
tional restrictions, as well as in the number of persons of a given nation-&#13;
ality allowed to work in the country.&#13;
The linear programming will be solved for each period to minimize an&#13;
objective function representing the total imputed cost of having the&#13;
expatriate labor force work in the country to supplement the manpower&#13;
shortage for the desired output targets.&#13;
1.34 Z = IJnCOST (t,i,j,n).XLF (t,i,j,n)&#13;
Where: COST (t,i,j,n) designates the imputed unit cost of having one&#13;
expatriate man-year of nationality n work in sector i and&#13;
occupational category j; and&#13;
XLF(t,i,j,n) designates the number of expatriate labor force&#13;
personnel of nationality n working in sector i and occupational&#13;
category J. If imputed costs are not easily available, the linear&#13;
programminng package can be used excilusively-to test for feasibil-&#13;
ity within the given constraints. The constraints are that:&#13;
(i)  the expatriate labor force allowed to work in a particular sector&#13;
must equal or exceed the sectoral manpower shortage;&#13;
(ii)  the expatriate labor force allowed to work in a particular&#13;
occupation must equal or exceed the occupational manpower shortage;&#13;
and&#13;
(iii) the share oT expatriate iaDor Trom a particular country be within&#13;
certain bounds.&#13;
59&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Symbolically, the linear programming&#13;
Z = nij COST(n,i,j) XLF(n,i,j)&#13;
subject to (t,i,j,n) . XLF(t,i,j,n)&#13;
(i) nrNji XLF(t,i,j,n)&gt;NMR(t,l); where Nji is a given nationality set&#13;
for sector i;&#13;
(ii)  nEN21i XLF(t,i,j,n)&gt;NMR (t,j); where N2j is a given nationality set&#13;
for occupation J;&#13;
(iii) Bl(n)&lt; iJXLF(t,i,j,n)&#13;
_~~~ &lt; 82(n)&#13;
nijNMR(t,i ,n,n)&#13;
where:  B1(n) = lower bound&#13;
B2(n) = upper bound&#13;
The implications of this process are that the LP package, as indicated,&#13;
will be solved for each period t, and the solution will be in terms of the&#13;
number of nonnational labor force personnel with nationality n working in a&#13;
given sector/occupation (i,j); that is, XLF(t,i,j,n). Since *XLF(t,i,j,n)&#13;
indicates the level of nonnational labor force personnel required in year t&#13;
needed to meet the manpower shortage, the difference between XLF(t,i,j,n)&#13;
and XLF(t-l,i,j,n) yields the required movement of nonnational labor force&#13;
personnel from year t-1 to year t. Therefore, if XLF(t,i,j,n)&gt;&#13;
XLF(t-l,i,j,n), then the difference indicates the net importation of&#13;
nonnational labor force personnel of nationality n to work in sector i and&#13;
occupation j. On the other hand, if XLF(t,i,j,n) &lt; XLF(t-1,i,j,n), the&#13;
difference will imply net exportation.&#13;
It is to be noted that:L&#13;
; XLF(t,i,j,n) = total nonnatlonal labor force of nationality n&#13;
working in occupation j in year t;&#13;
j XLF(t,i,j,n) = total nonnational labor force of nationality n&#13;
working in sector i in year t; and&#13;
ij XLF(t,i,j,n)    = total nonnational labor force of nationality n in the&#13;
country in' year t.&#13;
60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Chapter 2. THE EXPA1NDED MODEL&#13;
2.1  Introduction&#13;
The expanded model produces regional and national manpower analyses&#13;
including interregional labor force migration and the associated movement&#13;
of nonmembers of the labor force. The expanded model comprises two major&#13;
stages of analysist  local analysis, which refers to regional analyses&#13;
within the country, and global analysis, whiich refers to national&#13;
analyses. This labeling was adopted to avoid confusion with the&#13;
supranational region that could refer to a group of nations.&#13;
2.2 Local Analyses&#13;
In a local analysis, each locality is treated as a sep irate entity&#13;
with a unique information: estimated manpower stocks by sector/occupation,&#13;
estimated manpower requirements to meet its economic development targets,&#13;
an education/training system (ETS), and manpower allocation priorities with&#13;
respect to the a'llocation of manpower from ETS. However, expatriates are&#13;
not allocated at the local level but rather at the global level, due to the&#13;
international context of Immigration.&#13;
There are leakages of manpower from one locality to others.   The&#13;
attrition of labor force in one localitv could be an addition to another's;&#13;
or losses from tnie labor force in one locality could be an addition to&#13;
another's, or could be permanent losses. Therefore, attrition must be&#13;
interpreted with caution since the current-year graduates may not accept&#13;
jobs within their region, thereby affecting the traditional entrance rates&#13;
into the labor force in each locality.  The situation may have to be&#13;
interpreted in a broader context to allow participation with other&#13;
localities. Alsci, leakages of dropouts from one locality to another may&#13;
take place. These leakages are similar in concept, although opposite to&#13;
61&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
the much-discussed case of 'brain-drain", where the outflow of skilled&#13;
manpower continues due to better social, political, economic, and financial&#13;
conditions prevailing somewhere else, despite the existence of a real local&#13;
need for skilled manpower and the government's best efforts to retain it.&#13;
The migration of labor from one locality to another could cause other&#13;
population movements as well, due to the movement o'f dependents, including&#13;
students currently enrolled in the local FTS. These associated movements&#13;
will change the demographic picture, enrollment figures, and,, consequently,&#13;
the local requirements of infrastructure.&#13;
These leakages and associated movements are not explicitly dealt with&#13;
in the country model, but if they are viewed in the context of a locality,&#13;
thee could be positive or negative flows of manpower, which the expanded&#13;
model is equipped to handle.&#13;
It may be useful to relate the country model to local analyses, and to&#13;
describe in general terms how the country model has been modified or&#13;
expanded for local analyses. Recall that the country model contains four&#13;
major submodels:&#13;
- Labor Force Model (LFM)&#13;
- Manpower Requirements Model-(MRM)&#13;
- Education Simulation Model (ESM).&#13;
- Manpower Policy Model (MPM)&#13;
As mentioned earlier,-the country model computes separately each&#13;
locality's available labor force by sector/occupation category and its&#13;
estimated manpower requirements and supplies. The expanded model's local&#13;
analyses add to this process an accounting of leakages in both labor-force&#13;
and non-labor-force populations in each locality.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Another major difference between the country model and the expanded&#13;
model for local analyses is in the manpower policy submodel. The MPM in&#13;
the country model allocates expatriates along with the national labor force&#13;
at the country level.  Expatriates are not allocated at the local level in&#13;
the country model, and the MPM, likewise, does not attempt this in the&#13;
local analyses. The local analyses do, however, allocate available local&#13;
manpower supplies, minus leakages, in accorcdance with the local priority&#13;
matrix. Further, the local analyses calculaite achievable outputs in each&#13;
locality, taking into account available labor force nationals and&#13;
expatriates, using the method applied at the country level in the country&#13;
model.&#13;
2.3 Global Analyses&#13;
In a global analysis, leakages into and out of localities are&#13;
reallocated. A mechanism has also been incorporated which updates&#13;
population and enrollment figures in each locality resulting from the&#13;
movements of labor force, and, in some cases, unemployment is calculated&#13;
for those "leakage labor force" members in a transient-state. Furthermore,&#13;
a manpower allocaition mechanism-for expatriates has been added. From this&#13;
general description of a global7analysis,--it may be appropriate to consider&#13;
the global analysis as a consolidation analysis, in which the emphasis is&#13;
placed on the reallocation of surpluses, deficits, leakages, updating of&#13;
the associated movements of non-labor force population, the allocation of&#13;
expatriates, and estimates of the labor force in.a transient state.&#13;
The Pool Concept&#13;
The pool concept was introduced in the country model. Those with&#13;
similar qualifications, or those considered t;o have similar qualifications,&#13;
are pooled together. For example, the educat;ion/training system supplies&#13;
63&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
graduates and dropouts, and they are pooled (called Category I) according&#13;
to their qualifications. From these pools various sector/occupations draw&#13;
their manpower needs in accordance with a priority matrix. The concept of&#13;
pooling is also used in the expanded model to pool leakages from local&#13;
labor forces, graduates, and dropouts. The pooled labor force, by&#13;
locality, is then reallocated to the corresponding pool identification of&#13;
other localities (called Category II) in accordance with i transition&#13;
matrix or matrices as a function of time. These two categories of pools&#13;
differ in that Category I is for graduates and dropouts, who will be&#13;
allocated in the current year to local manpower requirements during the&#13;
local analysis, while Category II is for leakages, who will be reallocated&#13;
with a time lag, during the global analysis, to various localities.&#13;
Time Lags&#13;
In the allocation or reallocation of both categories of pools, time&#13;
lags could exist. However, it is more reasonable to assume greater time&#13;
lag in the global analysis than in the local analysis. Graduates are more&#13;
likely to go into the labor force in the-year they graduate, if they do go&#13;
into the labor force in the locality; while leakages, who go into labor&#13;
forces in other localities, tend7to have a time lag. Therefore, it is&#13;
assumed that the allocation of pools (Category I) of current-year graduates&#13;
and dropouts in the-local analysis will have no time lag, and that the&#13;
reallocation of leakages will have a constant time-lag, whatever-they may&#13;
be, in the global analysis, throughout the simulation time horizon in the&#13;
expanded model. As a matter of system design approach, the time lag is&#13;
treated as a controllable parameter. Users could change its value to see&#13;
what impact the time lag has on manpower supplies and demands in the global&#13;
analysis. It is anticipated that providing employment information&#13;
nationwide could reduce time lags in labor force movements.&#13;
64&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Initial and Terminal Conditions&#13;
Initial and terminal conditions must be considered, particularly when&#13;
the time lag is long and the simulation horizon is short. Initial data&#13;
sets have been provided to satisfy the requirements of initial conditions,&#13;
and users' opticins are incorporated into the system to allow users'&#13;
selection of how terminal data (i.e., leakages yet not reallocated) should&#13;
be treated at the end of the simulation horizon.&#13;
Transition Matrices&#13;
In the reallocation of leakage labor force, some localities may be&#13;
preferred to others by those who are looking for jobs. This preference is&#13;
taken into account-in the transition matrix or matrices.&#13;
Misalllocations&#13;
If, after the reallocation of leakage llabor force, a condition results&#13;
in which surpluses continue to exist in some localities and deficits exist&#13;
in other localities, this will indicate the misallocation of national human&#13;
resources. The expanded model will provide this type of analysis if and&#13;
when such a condition exists.,&#13;
After the reallocation of leakage labor force, the corresponding&#13;
non-labor-force movements are updated by-locality; including local-&#13;
population and enrollment figures.&#13;
2.4 Overall System Design Specifications&#13;
As mentionecl earlier, each locality-will go through its own analysis&#13;
every year (or every period). The computational algorithms in local&#13;
analysis are very similar-to the country model, with additional&#13;
computations required to account for leakages, surpluses, or deficits, and&#13;
to update the associated changes in local population and student&#13;
enrollments.&#13;
65&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
After all localities in a gloal unit have gone through their&#13;
individual local analysis in a given year (or period), the global analysis&#13;
will then start to re-allocate pooled leakages from each locality to&#13;
various localities in accordance with a transition matrix or transition&#13;
matrices, and will also estimate corresponding changes in population and&#13;
enrollments due to labor force migration. All these calculations will take&#13;
time lags into account. After the reallocation processes for leakages and&#13;
surpluses are completed, the global analysis will then start to estimate&#13;
expatriate requirements, taking into account existing available local&#13;
nationals and expatriates residing in the global unit. See Table 2-1 for&#13;
a comparative description, by labor force category, of attrition and&#13;
leakage between local nationals and expatriates.&#13;
Leakage labor force available to each locality from other localities&#13;
is reallocated by the global analysis via transition matrices in accordance&#13;
with the local priority matrix. The system design also allows for the&#13;
introduction of different allocation rules for such labor-force leakages as&#13;
may be required in the future.&#13;
2.5 Phases&#13;
The following phases, to be executed in each time-period,-willVgive a&#13;
general idea of how the expanded model will perform each simulation run:&#13;
Phase I&#13;
Local Analyses for All Localities-&#13;
- Estimate labor force inventories&#13;
- Estimate labor force requirements&#13;
- Estimate education/training and supplies&#13;
- Estimate manpower leakages and pooling&#13;
66&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 2-1&#13;
GLOBAL ANALYSIS: ExPatriates and Local Nationals&#13;
Attrition and Leakage&#13;
Labor Force Category                      Expatriates                                  Local Nationals&#13;
(a). Attrition - Dropout from the          (a)  Attrition - Dropout from&#13;
labor force                               the local&#13;
labor force&#13;
(1)  Existing Labor F'orce        `(b)  Leakages -  No leakage realloca-     (b)  Leakage  -  Assumed avail-&#13;
tion will be calcu-                        able for&#13;
lated                                     reallocation&#13;
within the&#13;
country&#13;
(2)  Current Graduates           ',Assumed not applicable                    (a)  Leakage  -  Assumed avail-&#13;
able for&#13;
reallocation&#13;
within the&#13;
country&#13;
(3)  Dropouts                     Assumed not applicable                     (a)  Leakage  -  Assumed avail-&#13;
able for&#13;
reallocation&#13;
within the&#13;
country&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- Perform manpower allocations of graduates minus leakage&#13;
Global Analysis&#13;
- Reallocate leakages to localities, with time lags taken into&#13;
account&#13;
- Estimate non-labor-force movements and adjustments, with time lags&#13;
taken into account&#13;
Phase II&#13;
Local Analyses&#13;
- Allocate manpower reallocated by the global analysis&#13;
- Calculate achievable local outputs&#13;
Global Analysis&#13;
- Calculate global achievable outputs&#13;
- Calculate labor force in a transient state&#13;
- Estimate net requirements for expatriates&#13;
- Apply linear programming submodel&#13;
2.6 Assumptions&#13;
As mentioned, it might be appropriate to consider-the global analysis&#13;
as a cosolidation analysis of various local analyses; therefore, some&#13;
commonalities must exist among localities:&#13;
- Similar education/training structure at. uici iuLai level&#13;
- Similar definition of pools&#13;
- Similar sector/occupation matrix&#13;
- Free movement of surplus or leaked manpower and associated&#13;
population changes.&#13;
2.7 Outputs/Reports&#13;
In addition to most of the outputs/report capability of the country&#13;
model, the following flow analysis reports are available with the expanded&#13;
model:&#13;
68&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- Leaked labor force by sector/occupation, by year, by locality&#13;
- Leaked graduates by pools, by year, by locality&#13;
- Leaked dropouts by age, by year, by locality&#13;
- Associaited changes in population and enrollment, by year, by&#13;
locality&#13;
- Achievable outputs by sector, by year, by locality&#13;
- Achievable global outputs by sector, by year&#13;
- Labor force in a transient state, by year&#13;
2.8  Internal Specifications:   Local Analysis&#13;
In the country model, a nation is considered to be a single unit,&#13;
within which internal leakage flows are not explicitly dealt with.&#13;
However, in the expanded model, two additilonal dimensions are introduced&#13;
into-the system design: one relates to the dimension of space, i.e.,&#13;
locality, and the other relates to time lag in flow analyses.    It should be&#13;
noted that a time period is different from a time lag--they should not be&#13;
confused or used interchangeably.&#13;
To make this description as-self-contaiined as possible, some&#13;
specifications described in the glossary will be repeated here. In the&#13;
remainder of this-chapter,-the.following symbols will be used throughout,&#13;
and will have the meaning defined below unless otherwise noted:&#13;
r = localit ies&#13;
lag = time lag&#13;
t = time period&#13;
i = sector ID&#13;
j = occupation IC&#13;
n = nationalities other than local nationals&#13;
p = pool ID&#13;
69&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Labor Force Model:  National Labor Force&#13;
Inputs:  The following base year data are required:&#13;
NLF(O,i,j,r)   =    Base year national labor force stock by sector i,&#13;
occupation j and locality r.&#13;
NA(t,j,r)      =   Attrition rates vector by occupation j and&#13;
r for national labor. It is assumed that&#13;
NA(t,j,r) = NA(t-l,j,r) unless specifically&#13;
changed by entering attrition rates vector for a&#13;
given t.&#13;
LEAK(O,r,p,t-lag =    Initial stocks of leaked labor force from&#13;
locality r in pool number p and available for&#13;
reallocation by the-global analysis, in time&#13;
period t, taking into account time lag.&#13;
When t-lag =    0, the initial data should be input.   The time&#13;
lag variable "lagu specifies the number of&#13;
periods the analysis will go beyond the base year&#13;
for the initial data set. When t-lag = 1, the&#13;
data will be computed by the-system,--taking into&#13;
account leakage-rates-in the existing labor&#13;
force, graduates, and dropouts.&#13;
Functional Relationships&#13;
NLF(t,i,j,r)       National labor force at the beginning of year t,&#13;
by sector i, occupation j and locality r;&#13;
NLF(t,i,j,r)   =   NLF(O,i,j,r) for t =1&#13;
NLF(t,i,j,r)   =    NLF(t-1,i,j,r) . (1-NA(t-1,j,r))&#13;
+   MSE(t-l,i,j,r)&#13;
-   LKLF(t-1,i,j,r).NLF(t-1,i,j,r)&#13;
+   REALLOCATED (t-,1,j,r,t-lag)&#13;
(For t&gt;2)&#13;
70&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Where MSE(t-1,i,j,r) is the labor supply from ESM:&#13;
LKLF(t-l,i,j,r) is the rate of leakage, and LKLF.NLF are leakages;&#13;
REALLOCATED(t_1,i,j,r,t-lag) is the reallocated leakages, with lags&#13;
by the cllobal analysis.&#13;
What this functional relationship says is that the existing&#13;
available labor force in sector i, occupaticin j, locality r, and year t, is&#13;
the sum of workers remaining after attrition, plus those supplied from ESM,&#13;
and leakages rea'llocated by the global analyses, minus the leakages in year&#13;
t-1.&#13;
Outputs&#13;
The output' from this functional relationship is the existing&#13;
national labor Force at the beginning of year t by sector, by occupation,&#13;
and by locality.&#13;
Labor Force Model: Expatriate Labor Force&#13;
Inputs&#13;
The following base year data for the expatriate labor force are&#13;
required:&#13;
- XLF(O,i,j,,r,n) =   Base year expatriate labor.of nationality n,&#13;
working in locality r, in sector i, and&#13;
occupation j.&#13;
XA(t,j,r,n)     = _ Attrition rates vector by occupation J, locality&#13;
r, and nationality--n. -It is assumed XA(t,j,r,n)&#13;
X XA(t-l,j,r,n) uniless specifically changed by&#13;
entering attrition rates vector for t. It is&#13;
further assumed, when no detailed attrition rate&#13;
data are available for various nationalities,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
that all nationalities will have the same&#13;
attrition rates by occupation and locality. When&#13;
no detailed attrition rate data are available by&#13;
iocality, it will then be assumed that attrition&#13;
rate will be by occupation only.&#13;
When the expanded model is to be applied at the international level&#13;
and when time lags exist in the movement of expatriates across national&#13;
boundaries, the similar initial conditions, i.e., initial date of labor&#13;
force in a transient state, should also be provided by sector, by&#13;
occupation, by locality, and by nationality.&#13;
Functional Relationships&#13;
XLF(t,i,j,r,n) =    Expatriate labor force at the beginning of year t&#13;
in sector i, occupation j, locality r, and&#13;
nationality n.&#13;
XLF(t,i,j,r,n) =    XLF(O,i,j,r,n) for t = 1&#13;
XLF(t,i,j,r,n) =    XLF(t-l,i,j,r,n).(l-XA(t-l,j,r,n)) + Net&#13;
- X(t-l,i,j,r,n) (For t&gt;2)&#13;
The net expatriate:labor force at-the.beginning of year-t, Net-X&#13;
(t-1,i,j,r,n) is the sum of what remains after attrition, and what is&#13;
allocated by the manpower policy submodel of the global analysis. It is&#13;
assumed that the leakages of expatriates are included in the attrition-&#13;
computation.&#13;
Outputs&#13;
The following outputs/reports are available, as in the country&#13;
model:&#13;
- Expatriate labor force by sector, by occupation, by year&#13;
- Expatriate labor force by sector, by occupation, by locality, by&#13;
year&#13;
72&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- Expatriate labor force by nationality, by year&#13;
- Expatriate labor force by nationality, by locality, by year&#13;
Manpower Requirements Model&#13;
The methods for estimating manpower reqluirements differ between the&#13;
country model and the expanded model in only one respect, the additional&#13;
dimensions of locality in the expanded model. Since each locality is&#13;
treated as an entity by itself having its own development targets, it has&#13;
its own manpower requirements estimates. The expanded model accordingly&#13;
requires input data broken down by locality, and produces output/reports&#13;
with breakdowns by locality.&#13;
The country model provides a choice of three major methods for&#13;
inputing manpower requirements:   the elasticity method, the productivity&#13;
growth method, and the direct input method. These are also available in&#13;
the expanded model.&#13;
Education Simulation Model&#13;
The ESM Submiodel used in the country model is also used in the&#13;
expanded model, with one additional dimension (locality) for local analyses&#13;
in the expanded model. No changes have been made in calculation-of-&#13;
graduates and dropouts,ithe -accounting of dropouts under-the minimum-legal&#13;
working age, and the concept of pooling via -filtering by participation&#13;
rates.&#13;
Input data required by the ESM are broken down by locality. The ESM&#13;
is run for each locality to estimate manpower supplies. Outputs/reports&#13;
available for ESM have breakdowns by locality. The expanded model also&#13;
provides aggregated reports similar to those available from the ESM in the&#13;
country model.&#13;
73&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Estimation of Leakages&#13;
As mentioned, the major differences between the country model and the&#13;
expanded model in local analyses lie in the accounting of leakages in the&#13;
local labor-force and non-labor-force populations. There are three&#13;
possible major labor force categories that could have leakages:&#13;
- The existing labor force&#13;
- The graduates&#13;
- The dropouts&#13;
There are also two possible major categories of non-labor-force&#13;
leakages due to labor force migrations:&#13;
- Local population&#13;
- Local enrollments&#13;
In this section, only the leakages from the labor force, will be&#13;
discussed. The non-labor-force leakages will be discussed in a later&#13;
section on global analyses because, by definition, associated movements for&#13;
the non-labor-force depend on labor force distribution.. Therefore, it is&#13;
only after the reallocation of leakage labor force-is completed, with-&#13;
consideration for time lags, that the adjustments of non-labor-force&#13;
population can be calculated.&#13;
Labor Force Leakages&#13;
Inputs&#13;
The following input data -are required to estimate pooled- leakage&#13;
labor force:&#13;
LKLF(t,i,j,r) = The leakage rate for the existing labor force in&#13;
sector i, occupation j in locality r, in time&#13;
period t.&#13;
74&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
i,j Ep         =    The data about how sector i and occupation j are&#13;
defined in the pool p.&#13;
LKSC(t,r,p)    =    The leakage rate for the graduates in the pool p&#13;
in locality r and in time period t.&#13;
LKUG(t,r,p)    =   The leakage rate for the dropouts in the pool p&#13;
in locality r and the time period t. This&#13;
leakage rate should be distinguished from the&#13;
leakage of underage entrants and potential&#13;
entrants analysis as currently calculated in the&#13;
country model. It is assumed that the leakages&#13;
to global units come from the underage leakage&#13;
pools.&#13;
Functional Relationships&#13;
LKPOOL(t,r,p,t-lag =    The pooled leakages, in time period t, in pool p,&#13;
(For t &gt; lag + 1)       in locality r to be reallocated with time lag of&#13;
"lag" periods.&#13;
LKPOOL(t,r,p,t-lag) =       NLF(t-1,i,j,r).LKLF(t-1,i,j,r)&#13;
+ -SCPOOL(t-l,r,p).LKSC(t-l,r,p)&#13;
-+- UGPOOL(t-1,r,p).LKUG(t-1,r,p)&#13;
What this functional.relationship says is that the total pooled&#13;
leakages from a given locality's pool and available for later (time lag)&#13;
reallocations is the sum of the leakages from the existing labor force&#13;
NLF(t,i,j,r), graduates SCPOOL(t-1,r,p), and the underage UGPOOL(t-1,r,p),&#13;
provided they al'l have th'e same pool number p, and locality r.&#13;
Outputs&#13;
The outputs/reports available from the calculations include:&#13;
- Leakage report, by sector, by occupation&#13;
75&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- Leakage report, by pool, by:year&#13;
Manpower Policy Model&#13;
The manpower Policy Model in the country model serves to articulate&#13;
*manpower policies for both nationals and expatriates. In the expanded&#13;
model, however, only the allocation of nationals is dealt with in the local&#13;
analysis. The distribution of expatriates is done at the global level, due&#13;
to national and international immigration policies.&#13;
Recall that there are two major categories of manpower supplies from&#13;
ESM--the graduates and the dropouts. Although by law the dropouts are not&#13;
allowed to go into the labor force until they reach the minimum legal age,&#13;
they do, in some cases, participate illegally in the labor force. In the&#13;
country model provisions are made availabie for the leakage of dropouts&#13;
into the labor force. (Note the difference between the leakages as&#13;
described here, which are available for local analysis with time lag, and&#13;
the leakages to global unit, which are available for global reallocation&#13;
with a time lag). Leaked dropouts are first pooled by their educational&#13;
level as specified by users, and from these pools, the-leakages to both the&#13;
local unit and the global unit are calculated. -Next, the underage leakage&#13;
pools are separated into two types: one available -to-local analysis-&#13;
without a time lag, and the other available to global analysis with a time&#13;
lag for later reallocation. Those available for local analysis in the year&#13;
(or period) the leakage occur, will be allocated:in conjunction with the&#13;
allocation of pooled graduates,-in accordance with the manpower allocation&#13;
priority matrix to meet local nationalization programs.&#13;
Before the allocation of available local manpower takes place, the&#13;
following adjustments must be made to avoid double counting:&#13;
SCPOOL(t,r,p).(1-LKSC(t,r,p))&#13;
76&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
This states that the leakage of gradualtes to global analyses are&#13;
subtracted from the graduate pool.&#13;
UGPOOL(t,r,p).(l-LKUG(t,r,p))&#13;
This states that the leakage of dropouts to global analyses are&#13;
subtracted from the dropout pool.&#13;
Note that the adjustments of the leakages from the existing labor&#13;
force have already been taken into account iin the recursive functions of&#13;
existing available labor force.&#13;
After the above adjustments have been completed, the manpower&#13;
allocation rules as detailed in the country model can be applied, taking&#13;
into account the priority matrix of each locality as specified by users of&#13;
the model.&#13;
2.9  Phase I Internal Specifications:   Global Analysis&#13;
After local analyses have been performed for each locality, the&#13;
leakage labor from various localities becomes known. This leakage labor is&#13;
then reallocated to other localities in accordance with transition matrices&#13;
as a function of time.   This is the first step in the global analysis.&#13;
Once reallocation to various localities is completed, the global analysis&#13;
estimates movements--of:non-labor-force population, deriving both population-&#13;
and enrollment figures.. The following discussion addresses the-&#13;
reallocation process and the adjustments for non-labor-force population&#13;
movements.&#13;
Transition Matrix and Reallocation Process&#13;
Transition matrices by pool and by year are introduced to estimate&#13;
transition of leaked labor force. Each row and column of the matrices will&#13;
designate a locality number.&#13;
77&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Each matrix is a square matrix, whose rows designate "from" or&#13;
Usources3 and whose columns designate "to" or "recipient" in the transition&#13;
of leaked labor force. Each element in a matrix is the rate of transfer&#13;
for a given pool of leakage labor force, and the sum of all row elements in&#13;
a given row must be equal to 100%. The diagonal elements in a matrix&#13;
represent those choosing to stay in their own localities after they are&#13;
considered as leaked labor force. If this situation is considered unlikely&#13;
to occur, then all the diagonal elements have zero values. The number of&#13;
rows (or the number of columns) is equal to the number of localities to be&#13;
included in the global unit. The mathematical operations required to&#13;
:obtain reallocation of a set of pools with the same pool ID from each&#13;
locality are described below.&#13;
Let the transition matrix [TRAN(p)] for pool ID-p be defined as&#13;
follows:&#13;
a(21), A(22), A(23), . .&amp;. .. . . . . . a(2R)&#13;
TRAN(P)   =&#13;
a(Rl), A(R2), a(R3), .......... a(RR)&#13;
R          R&#13;
WhereZa(lr) = 7a(2r) = . . . = 1.0; R = total number of localities.&#13;
r=1       r=1&#13;
Also let PL(r,p) be the pooled leakages in locality r for pool ID&#13;
p. By definition, there is one and only one PL (r, p) for each locality r&#13;
for a given p. Therefore, there is a total of R pools, one from each&#13;
78&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
locality. For locality 1, the PL(1,p) will be distributed according to&#13;
a(21), a(22), ...a(2R); and so on.   Let TRAlMp be the matrix of the&#13;
redistributed leakage labor force:&#13;
b 11, b 12 , b 13         ....             b(1R)&#13;
RLLF(p)   =      b 21), b(22), b 23)    , . . . . . . . . . b(2R)&#13;
b(R1), b(R2), b(R3), , . . .   . . . . . b(RR)&#13;
The summation by "recipient" localitlies is the reallocated leakage&#13;
labor force, which is allocated by the recipient localities in accordance&#13;
with the local priority matrices.&#13;
Adjustments of Non-Labor-Force Movements&#13;
Recall that the migration of labor force leakages takes place with a&#13;
time lag. Theref;ore, by definition, the movements of the associated&#13;
non-labor force migration will also take place with a time lag.    To&#13;
simplify the programming tasks without loss of validity, the movements of&#13;
the associated non-labor-force will be assumed to take place with the same&#13;
time lag as that of the labor force leakage migrations. The calculations&#13;
of non-labor-force population movements are done by the global analyses&#13;
after the calculations of reallocations for leakage labor force.&#13;
It is further assumed that the associated populition movements are&#13;
functions of the leakages of the existing labor force only. Recall that&#13;
three general categories of leakages could take place--from the existing&#13;
labor force, froin graduates, and from the underage dropouts. Nevertheless,-&#13;
the leakages from the last two cause almost no associated movement of&#13;
non-labor-force igeneral population. 'This is due primarily to their youth,&#13;
unmarried status, and general lack of financial means to support a family&#13;
at that point in their lives. This assumption does not cause any&#13;
noticeable distortions in the simulation results.&#13;
79&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Although no associated movements due to the migration of the leaked&#13;
graduates and the uderage dropouts are assumed, these two categories of&#13;
leakages are part of the population figures in the locality where they are&#13;
or will be staying. As leakages occur, they will move into other&#13;
localities, and should, therefore, be included in the population figures of&#13;
the locality they are moving into, and excluded from the population figures&#13;
of the locality they are moving out of. These move-in and move-out&#13;
calculations also apply to the leakages of the existing labor force, which&#13;
will cause associated movements of non-labor force population.&#13;
Adjustments of Population Figures&#13;
In the expanded model, the following inputs are assumed for each&#13;
locality:&#13;
- Base-year population figures by age, by sex (this includes&#13;
those in schools and those not attending any schools).&#13;
- New births by year, by locality, by sex&#13;
- Survival rates by age, by year, by sex&#13;
In addition to these general demographic data, the following data are&#13;
needed:&#13;
RATE(t,a,r) = Rate of associated movements in ponulation out of&#13;
locality r, for age group a, per 100 existinq labor&#13;
force migrations.&#13;
Although it might be claimed that there could be some relationships&#13;
between family size and the level of 'lncome/education/occupation/pools, the&#13;
same rate is applied acr6ss all pooled leakages of the existing labor force&#13;
in a given locality. Namely, regardless of what pool the leaked existing&#13;
labor force belongs to, as long as they are all from the same locality,&#13;
they will have the same RATE(t,a,r) of associated non-labor-force movementS&#13;
out of their locality.&#13;
80&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Functional Relationships&#13;
- Move-outs (t,r,t-lag) of existing labor force;&#13;
- Move-ins; (t,r,t-lag) of existing labor force;&#13;
- Move-outs (t,a,r,t-lag, graduates);&#13;
- Move-ins (t,a,r,t-lag, graduates);&#13;
- Move-outs (t,a,r,t-lag, dropouts);&#13;
- Move-ins (t,a,r,t-lag, dropouts).&#13;
Although in quantitative terms move-outs and move-ins have some&#13;
canellation effects, they should be kept separated for the purposes of flow&#13;
analyses, as well as stock computations of existing populations in various&#13;
localities that take into account cancellation effects.    For a given&#13;
locality r', the calculations of population at the beginning of each&#13;
period will then be:&#13;
POP(t,a,r')  =   POP(t-1,a,r').SURVIVERATE(t-1,a)&#13;
-   RATE(t-1,a,r').MOVEOUTS(t-1,r',t-lag)/100&#13;
+    .i  RATE(t-1,a,r) MOVEINS(t-1,r,t-lag)/100&#13;
r#r -&#13;
MOVEOUTS(t-1,a,r't-lag, graduates)&#13;
-   MOVEOUTS(t-1,a,r't-lag,- dropouts)&#13;
+   E    MOVEINS(t-1,a,r,t-lag, graduates)-&#13;
r#r'&#13;
+       -- MOVEINS(t-1,r,t-lag, dropouts)-&#13;
r#r'&#13;
In a very simplified-explanation, this function says that the&#13;
population figures for a given age group in a given locality is the sum of&#13;
what is surviving, plus all move-ins, less all move-outs.    During the&#13;
course of the simulation run, the new births by year by locality should&#13;
also be calculated by using the input provicled by users of the model.&#13;
81&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Outputs&#13;
The outputs/reports to be made available include both stock and flow&#13;
analyses of population migrations due to labor force movements.&#13;
Adjustments of Enrollments&#13;
In the current ESM system, detailed information about enrollment&#13;
statistics is kept within the country model. The movements of students are&#13;
only a function of labor force movements, by virture of the definitional&#13;
relationship between associated movements in population and labor-force&#13;
movements. Therefore, there are also two-way movements (move-ins and&#13;
move-outs) into and out of the local education/training system. The&#13;
computational step for the adjustments of enrollments (with time lags) is&#13;
very much the same as that in the adjustments of population figures,&#13;
provided the dimensionality is in terms of course number c and locality&#13;
r. 1/&#13;
Input&#13;
The following input is required:&#13;
RATES (t,c,r)  =   Rate of assoiated movements in course number c,&#13;
out of localityir to go into the same course&#13;
number c in other localities.due to per 100&#13;
existing labor force migrations. (Sum of&#13;
RATES(t,c,r) for all c equal to 1.0)&#13;
1/   Another possibility also being explored as present, is to link the&#13;
rate RATES(t,c,r) t6 the associated non-labor-force population figures&#13;
rather than the labor force figures. While this has more conceptual&#13;
clarity and would not necessarily require locality adjustments, it may&#13;
lead to cumulation of error by applying an estimated coefficient to a&#13;
figure derived from the application of another estimated coefficient&#13;
to a product of still another coefficient estimate.&#13;
82&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Functional Relationships&#13;
For a given locality r'&#13;
MSE(t,c,r')  = MSE(t-l,c,r')&#13;
- RATES (t-l,c,r').MOVEOUTS(t-l,r',t-lag)/100&#13;
+   E7   (t-1,c,r).MOVEINS(t-l,r,t-lag)/lOO&#13;
rfr&#13;
This functional relationship states t:hat the enrollment figure for a&#13;
given course c at the beginning of a period t in locality r is what is&#13;
remaining from the previous period (t-I). less the associated move-outs&#13;
from the course, plus all the associated move-ins from other localities.&#13;
Outputs&#13;
The outputs/reports include both stock and flow analyses of student&#13;
enrollments.&#13;
2.10 Phase II Internal Specifications:   Local Analyses&#13;
Allocation of Reillocated Workers&#13;
Subsequent to the global analyses on the reallocation of the leakage&#13;
labor force, and the adjustments of nonlabor migrations, Phase II of each&#13;
local analysis starts to allocate the reallocated manpower supplies from&#13;
various localities.  The rules on the allocation of the local ESM manpower&#13;
supplies in accordance with a priority matrix continue to apply to the.&#13;
local allocation of workers reallocated by the global analyses.&#13;
Calculations of Net Local Manpower Requirements&#13;
The calculations of the net manpower requirements start, by taking&#13;
into account what is available in the local labor force, both local&#13;
nationals and expatriates.   The mathematical descriptions of these&#13;
calculations are Identical to those in the manpower policy model of the&#13;
country model, ani therefore, will not be repeated here.&#13;
83&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Calculations of Achievable Local Outputs&#13;
As in the manpower policy of the country model, local achievable&#13;
outputs can be estimated by taking into account the existing available&#13;
labor force, both local nationals and expatriates, and sectoral&#13;
productivities in the locality.&#13;
The backward calculations and the mathematical specifications for&#13;
these calculations are also identical to those in the manpower policy model&#13;
of the country model.&#13;
Surplus Manpower Supplies&#13;
Some pools may have surplus manpower supplies after the allocation of&#13;
the reallocated labor force is completed by the local analyses. In this&#13;
case, two possible treatments of surplus manpower supplies can be&#13;
considered:&#13;
- This surplus manpower could be considered to stay where they are and&#13;
be available for allocation in the following years, either in their&#13;
locality or through leakages to other localites.: In this case, they&#13;
could be considered to be unemployed in their locality in the year&#13;
when the surplus situation occurs.-&#13;
- The surplus manpower, supplies could be considered to be available-.&#13;
for reallocation, with a time lag, to-other localities by the global&#13;
analyses in the year the situation occurs.&#13;
The difference between these two approaches is that the latter will&#13;
automatically treat the surplus-as leakages, while the former will not. In-&#13;
the current system designr for the expanded model, the first approach is&#13;
utilized for its simplicity. A Bayesian approach could be considered in&#13;
the future to take Into account what is happening in the trend on the&#13;
requirements for, and supplies of, leakage manpower.&#13;
84&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2.11 Phase II Internal Specifications:   Global Analysis&#13;
Global Achievable Outputs&#13;
Once the estimates of achievable local outputs are complete for each&#13;
locality, the computation of global achievable outputs starts. It is&#13;
correctly assumed that sectoral productivities are different from locality&#13;
to locality; therefore, the calculations of global achievable outputs&#13;
should be done by summing all local achievalble outputs in the global unit.&#13;
Labor Force in a Transient State&#13;
The consideration of time lags in laboi- force migration implies that&#13;
there are some segments of the labor force, who are willing and able to&#13;
hold a job, and who are in a transient state and unemployed, due to&#13;
circumstances beyond their control. In a manpower-short nation, this is&#13;
deterimental to national development efforts. The information/reports&#13;
about transient national labor (i.e., moving or waiting to find jobs) will&#13;
be of value to decision makers in manpower planning.    The expanded model is&#13;
designed to keep track of this information, and to produce reports on the&#13;
status of national workers still waiting for reallocation in various&#13;
localities.&#13;
The expandedi model also calculates the value of output lost-due to. a&#13;
segment of the labor force being in a-transient state, taking into account-&#13;
local productivilties.&#13;
Furthermore,, the exponded model produces an overview-report on global&#13;
conditions of manpower supplies and requirements.    Following the Phase II&#13;
local analyses, complete -information will be available regarding manpower&#13;
supplies and requirements for each locality. If manpower surplus exists in&#13;
one locality, while deficits exists in other localities, then a manpower&#13;
misallocation exists. The expanded model produces a report on manpower&#13;
allocation or misallocation by summarizing manpower surpluses and deficits&#13;
in various localities.&#13;
85&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Net Expatriate Manpower Requirements&#13;
Upon the completion of Phase II local analysis calculations, the net&#13;
manpower shortage/surplus at each locality is known. From this, net&#13;
additional requirements of expatriates are estimated. In this calculation,&#13;
those in a transient state, and surplus manpower not yet allocated, should&#13;
be taken into account in deriving the net additional requirements of&#13;
expatriates. This is based on the reasoning that any expatriate who is&#13;
allowed to work in a nation should not deprive local nationals of existing&#13;
job opportunities, even though the misallocations exist.&#13;
Linear Programming Applications&#13;
The linear programming submodel in the country model is intended to be&#13;
-applied at the national level. Once the total national manpower shortages&#13;
are known, the linear programming submodel is applied and the manpower&#13;
shortage is met by filling these openings with expatriates, who are assumed&#13;
to be residual and available.&#13;
86&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Chapter 3 THE MIGRATION MODEL&#13;
3.1 Background&#13;
The basic purpose of the 'migration", or international model, is to&#13;
simulate labor flows between labor-exportinr and labor-importing countries&#13;
in a supra-national region, such as the Arab countries in the Middle East&#13;
and North Africa.&#13;
The structure of the migration model allows for a choice between two&#13;
mechanisms for aLlocating labor among the ccountries within the region, once&#13;
individual country requirements have been determined by application of the&#13;
country model.&#13;
The two alternative methods of solving the problem are a sequential one&#13;
and a simultaneous one. Within the sequential solution, the penultimate&#13;
step may be solved either by a series of small sequential steps or as a&#13;
linear programming optimizing simultaneous solution.&#13;
On the whole, the simultaneous solution method is. certainly more&#13;
elegant and conceptually more satisfactory. Nevertheless, the sequential&#13;
solution probably has merit, at least insofar as one can probably relate&#13;
more directly with the ordinal rankings it requires than with the&#13;
simultaneous solutions parameters, although che latter have more&#13;
interpretive policy meaning. In the final analysis, both methods should be&#13;
developed, letting actual usage be the testing ground for the empirical&#13;
superiority of one method over the other.&#13;
87&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3.2 Sequential Solution Procedure&#13;
Framework&#13;
The simulation is designed to consider a region of countries and&#13;
determine the pattern of migration of lacborers resulting from imbalance in&#13;
labor supplies and demands among the countries. Each country has labor&#13;
requirements (divided into sectors and occupations) determined from&#13;
user-specified data covering target outputs, productivities, growth, etc.&#13;
Labor availability is determined for each country from user-supplied&#13;
information about the educational system, existing labor stocks, attrition,&#13;
sector/occupation distribution, etc., in conjuction with carryover&#13;
information from the previous simulation year.&#13;
The simulation combines information about labor supplies and demands in&#13;
the regional countries with user-specified data ranking attractiveness of&#13;
countries to laborers, restrictions imposed by countries on nonnational&#13;
participation in their labor forces, etc. From these, a pattern of labor&#13;
allocation is determined. It includes both local allocation of each&#13;
national labor force and migration of.-nationals to other countries.&#13;
Remaining deficiencies in labor supplies are assumed to be-filled by&#13;
expatriates from an undivided source called "the rest of the world."&#13;
Steps&#13;
The following sequence of event' occur in the annual cycling of the&#13;
international migration simulation:&#13;
88&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Initial Local Phase I (For each country)&#13;
- Compute attrition (attrition of local nationals assumes that they&#13;
are lost to the labor force forever; attrition of nonnationals&#13;
assumes that they return to their cotntry of origin).&#13;
- Simulate the education system for nat:ionals (ESM). Nonnationals1are&#13;
not included in the education computations. There is no movement of&#13;
children into or out of the educational system associated with&#13;
migration (not numerically significant in terms of their entry into&#13;
the labor force).&#13;
- Compute labor requirements based on ithe information input about&#13;
sector outputs, productivities, growth rates, etc.&#13;
Global Interaction Phase I&#13;
Increase the net labor available in each country to account for the&#13;
returning nationals who left other countries by attrition. (Note: There&#13;
may be some merit to introducing a time lag before these returnees-are&#13;
available for work again.)&#13;
Local Phase II (For each country)&#13;
- Compute the net labor availability by pool, including the attrition&#13;
return of nationals previously working in other countries.&#13;
- Allocate available nationals. to fill local needs as much as&#13;
possible.&#13;
89&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- Determine surplus nationals available for export.&#13;
- Determine allocated nationals not subject to export according to&#13;
user-supplied tolerance levels.&#13;
- Determine remaining allocated nationals available for export, if&#13;
surplus laborers are insufficient to meet the needs of importing&#13;
countries.&#13;
(Note: There could also be a time lag here.)&#13;
Global Interaction Phase II&#13;
Compute the labor migration pattern: In order to provide for&#13;
flexibility in determin'ing migration patterns, movements are determined for&#13;
single pool levels or groups of pool levels. Groups are processed&#13;
independently and in an order specified by the user.&#13;
For each pool group processed, the allocation mechanism will permit one&#13;
to specify a priority of importing countries. Migration will be determined&#13;
to satisfy the requirements of a higher priority country before a lower&#13;
priority country's-needs are considered.   Countries not specified are-&#13;
considered to be labor-exporting countries for the pool.&#13;
Migration into any country will be subject to user-specified&#13;
restrictious on expatriate representation in that country. These&#13;
restrictions, which may vary from country to country, may be general (e.g.,&#13;
no more than 40% nonnational laborers in the work force) or very specific&#13;
(e.g., no more than 15X of laborers in technical occupations in the oil&#13;
sector are to be from a given country).&#13;
90&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
When attempting to import laborers to fill the requirements of an&#13;
importing country, the first source of workers will be those who are surplus&#13;
nationals in exporting countries (with a time lag considered). If these are&#13;
insufficient to fill the needs of an importiLng country, there will be an&#13;
attempt to seek workers from the nonsurplus labor forces of labor-exporting&#13;
countries. Thip stealing of workers will be limited to the user-specified&#13;
tolerance levels for each labor-exporting country.&#13;
There are various possibilities for undertaking the next step in the&#13;
sequence: the determination to fulfill a pool group need in an importing&#13;
country. Two possibilities are advanced: a sequential method and a linear&#13;
programming method.&#13;
The sequential method would require the user to specify a ranking of&#13;
exporting countries that may supply a designated importing country. The&#13;
surplus nationals in those exporting countries would be chosen for&#13;
importation according to the ranking designated, subject to the expatriate&#13;
constraints imposed by the importing country. The method would require a&#13;
sector/occupation cell-by-cell determination of needs,. restrictions, and&#13;
.availabilities of-imported laborers.  The sequential:nature-of this-method&#13;
would not ensure an optimal allocation of imported workers. That is,--a -&#13;
choice of importation to one cell may, becaiuse of expatriate restrictions,-&#13;
unnecessarily restrict importation possibilities for later cells.&#13;
91&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The alternative, but more costly approach in terms of computer time is&#13;
to use a linear programming allocation mechanism. With this method, the&#13;
needs of an importing country, the supplies available from exporting&#13;
countries, and the expatriate participation constraints are considered&#13;
simultaneously.&#13;
Final Local Phase III (For each country)&#13;
- Revise the available labor figures to reflect migration in and/or&#13;
out according to the pattern computed in the global interaction&#13;
phase.&#13;
-  Compute labor surplus or shortages.&#13;
- Compute achievable output.&#13;
- Compute residual requirements to be filled with expatriates from&#13;
outside the countries simulated.&#13;
- Import these expatriates to fill the labor requirements of the&#13;
country.&#13;
- Compute the final labor force breakdown.&#13;
Note that, in addition-to these:steps, the system will compute the&#13;
general population figures-in each country,--by nationality and by age-group&#13;
(where possible), adjusting these figures for passage of time (aging,&#13;
births, and deaths), as well as for migration (attrition and&#13;
importation/exportation).&#13;
92&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3.3 Conditions of Excess Supply or Demand&#13;
This sectic,n describes two methods of expatriate manpower allocations&#13;
under two different manpower supply conditions (defined as available for&#13;
exportation) within the Region under study:&#13;
(A) When the demand of a group of labor importing countries for a&#13;
given exporting country is less than or equal to the supply of&#13;
the exporting country for a given lpool; or&#13;
(B) When the demand of a group of labor importing countries exceeds the&#13;
supply of a given labor exporting country for a given pool.&#13;
Condition A-Excess Supply&#13;
In the case of excess supply.(or supply equals demand), the labor&#13;
importing countries could use special program cards, which prescribe the&#13;
desired expatrialte distribution at the end of a given year, to allocate the&#13;
labor supply of a given exporting country fcr a given pool. Any remaining&#13;
unallocated labor supply will be assumed as 'not exported".&#13;
To further facilitate the use of these special cards for target&#13;
control, the International Migration Model wrill provide a linear-&#13;
interpolation capability-between-the base year and the target year. The use&#13;
of this capability will prescribe a linear step course of actions from.the&#13;
base year throughi the target year in order to achieve the desired target&#13;
distribution.&#13;
93&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
interpolation capability between the base year and the target year. The use&#13;
of this capability will prescribe a linear step course of actions from the&#13;
base year through the target year in order to achieve the desired target&#13;
distribution.&#13;
Condition B - Deficit Supply&#13;
If the combined importing countries' demands for a given exporting&#13;
country in a given pool exceed what this exporting country can supply, then&#13;
the deficit supply Condition (B) exists for this particular exporting&#13;
country and, in order to make up the shortages, the supplies from other&#13;
exporting countries for the similar pool will have to be increased, if an&#13;
excess supply condition exists in the other exporting countries. What&#13;
follows is a proposed allocation mechanism to handle the deficit supply&#13;
condition.&#13;
Step 1&#13;
For a given labor exporting country n in a given occupation pool J,&#13;
because the supply V is less than the total demand W, the actual allocation&#13;
Net X to a given labor importing country i for this pool will be reduced to:&#13;
Net X (i,j,n) = W (i,j,n) . V (j,n)&#13;
FEW-(i,j,n)&#13;
i&#13;
While the Shortage K (i,j,n) will be&#13;
94&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
KR(i,j,n) - W (i,j,n) - Net X (i,j,n)&#13;
Step 2&#13;
For the sake of discussion, let S (j,n) designate excess supply or&#13;
surplus of exporting country n and pool J, then the actual allocation&#13;
Net X (i,j,n) fcor the desired demand W (i,j,n) will be met from the supply&#13;
V (J,n), and the excess supply S (,n) will be&#13;
S (J,n) - V (j,n) - 7W (i,j,n)&#13;
i&#13;
The above two steps will be applied to all i,n, and V while the&#13;
shortage K (i,j,n) will be made up from Excess gupply S (j,n,) in accordance&#13;
with the following steps.&#13;
Step 3&#13;
For a given labor importing country i, rank the expatriate target&#13;
distributions for exporting countries that are in the pet of S (J,n) (i,e.,&#13;
countries with excess supply of pool J) in an increasing order.--&#13;
Let U (n)&#13;
be the rank set of expatriate target distributions of exporting countries&#13;
which has the following relationship:&#13;
95&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
To fill up the shortage in the given importing country i, the expatriate S&#13;
(1) will be allocated first, then S (2), then S (3), etc. However, the&#13;
number of additional expatriates to be reallocated depends on U (n) in&#13;
accordance with the following ranges:&#13;
for 0 &lt; U (n) &lt; d (1), use x (1)%&#13;
for d (1) &lt; U(n) &lt; d(2), use x (2)%&#13;
for d(n) &lt; U(n) &lt; 1, use x (m)%&#13;
Where d(m) &lt; 1.0 and x(m) are input data supplied by users of the&#13;
Migration Model; and&#13;
Where x(m) could be considered as overage allowed over and above target&#13;
distribution.&#13;
Step 4&#13;
The application of Step 3 could result-In two cgnsequences:&#13;
Consequence 1&#13;
There exists enough supply of S(n) to meet the combined additional&#13;
allocation in accordance with Step 3 calculations;&#13;
96&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Consequence! 2&#13;
There does not exist enough supply of S (n) to meet the combined&#13;
additional allocation in accordance with Step 3 calculations. In this case,&#13;
whatever available supply from S (n) will be proportionally allocated to&#13;
importing countries using the following weight&#13;
Excess Supply S (J,n)&#13;
total additional demand   K (i,j,n)&#13;
i&#13;
Although shortages will continue to eaist, the reallocation, process&#13;
will be terminated and the rest of the shortages will be made up with the&#13;
labor force fro.m the rest of the world.&#13;
97&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3.4 Simultaneous Solution Procedure J/&#13;
The general procedure discussed in this section draws on a more general&#13;
theory of movements or transitions.A/ This procedure has four main&#13;
advantages. First, it is based on a very general approach and, therefore,&#13;
in spite of its apparent complexity, makes a minimum of arbitrary&#13;
assumptions. Second, it makes full use of the information now being&#13;
gathered by the World Bank on current distribution of the labor force and&#13;
future plans or forecasts of the demand and supply of labor. Third, it&#13;
yields certain values that can be interpreted and may assist in the&#13;
diagnosis of the situation. Fourth, it permits judgmental modification of&#13;
certain parameters to incorporate knowiedge of expectations not included in&#13;
the data on which the model is calibrated, or to reflect policy,&#13;
preferences.&#13;
1I This method was developed by Prof. William Alonso of Harvard University&#13;
and refined/adapted in discussions with Bob Li and I. Serageldin of the&#13;
TASS Division.&#13;
2/ Ref. W. Alonso, A Theory of Movements, Working Paper No. ZZb, Institute&#13;
of Urban and Regional Development, University of California at Berkeley,&#13;
June 1976.&#13;
98&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The procedure suggested here could be called 'systemic" because it&#13;
simultaneously considers both the composition and the interrelation of the&#13;
national demands and supplies of labor. Therefore, it is more stable than&#13;
the sequential allocation approach that has been discussed earlier. By&#13;
comparison to the optimizing (e.g. linear programming) approach, the&#13;
systemic approach is more behavioral; it does not include the dubious task&#13;
of choosing an appropriate objective function. However, the systemic&#13;
approach may conceivably be combined with en optimizing procedure for&#13;
certain purposes.&#13;
Data Needed to Run the Model&#13;
The World Bank is currently engaged in generating Aata that will&#13;
provide an inventory of (the region's) labor by country, by nationality, by&#13;
industry, and by occupation (or pool). This amounts to a vast matrix of&#13;
nationality and. pool by nation, industry, and pool. Although data&#13;
difficulties will result in some aggregation of some of these categories,&#13;
this presents no intrinsic difficult for the systemic approach.&#13;
Whereas the model is calibrated on the- matrix of the present&#13;
distribution of labor, its principal use is to generate a distribution-of&#13;
labor at some future date that is consistent with the supply of pools of&#13;
labor of various nationalities and with the demand for various types of&#13;
labor by varicus sectors in the various countries.&#13;
99&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
General Structure Behind the Model&#13;
Since it is assumed that there is no significant occupational mobility&#13;
among pools, each pool of labor may be treated independently. If categories&#13;
in the large matrix are appropriately grouped, each pool of labor will&#13;
constitute a submatrix along the major diagonal of the large matrix, the&#13;
rest of which consists of zeros. Therefore, it is convenient to deal with&#13;
the submatrices independently.&#13;
The majority of the pools--with the possible exception of that of the&#13;
least skilled labor--are expected to be in a condition of regional labor&#13;
shortage, meaning that the region will have to import labor from the rest of&#13;
the world. Therefore, the discussions that follow will be concerned with&#13;
the approach for pools in which there is a regional labor shortage. The&#13;
approach for pools in which there's a regional labor surplus is slightly&#13;
different and will be presented later in this section.&#13;
For a given pool, then, let:&#13;
V(n) - the supply (number of nationals from country. n in the region,&#13;
regardless of what-country they are in). For the current&#13;
period for which data are being gathered it is the marginal&#13;
sum of a row in the Matrix. For planning or forecasting,-it&#13;
is generated by other elements of the compound model, exogenous&#13;
to the allocation model presented here.&#13;
V(F=1) - a dummy slack variable for workers from the rest of the world&#13;
100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
W(i) the demand (number) for workers in sect:or i or in country i, regardless&#13;
of nationality. For the present period, it is the column sum for that&#13;
sector or country, including workers from the rest of the world. For&#13;
planning or projection, the figure is produced by the World Bank staff&#13;
exogenously to this allocation model. For ease of exposition, i stands&#13;
both for sector and nation. Note that for a given occupation pool (j),&#13;
W(i) - TLF (t,i,j) in the country model.&#13;
M(n,i) = the number of workers of nationality n in country i (sector i).&#13;
M(f,i) - number of workers from the rest of the world in country i (sector&#13;
i).&#13;
The following functional relationships are utilized:&#13;
(3.1)    V(n) -    M(n,i)&#13;
i&#13;
where: nfF&#13;
(3.2)    W(i) wE M(n,i) = (NLF(i) + XLF(i))&#13;
n&#13;
(3.3)   XM(F,i) aEW(i) -ZV(n)&#13;
1           i        n&#13;
where  n    F&#13;
Thus, for the relevant pool:   (a) -Equation. (6.1) says that labor from&#13;
country n is the sum of its workers regardless of wlhere they are working;&#13;
101&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(b) equation (6.2) says that the effective demand at country i (sector i) is-&#13;
defined as the total number of national and nonnational workers present,&#13;
regardless of origin; and (c) equation (6.3) says that, for a pool in labor&#13;
deficit in the region (i.e., EV &lt;YW), the rest of the world will make up&#13;
the deficit.&#13;
This is based on several assumptions, of course, principally that, for&#13;
dates in the future, (a) the national supply pools can be forecast (or&#13;
planned), (b) the various national demands can be forecast or planned and&#13;
will be met, (c) the supply and demand of the regional labor pool are&#13;
sufficiently integrated that it has first crack at clearing the market, and&#13;
(d) the rest of the world stands ready to meet any regional deficits, no&#13;
less and no more. These appear to be workable assumptions, but at some&#13;
future time one may want to modify them to make the model more useful or&#13;
relevant.&#13;
z(n,l)       a numerical statement of the accessibility of i (country,&#13;
sector) by nationals of a given country (p). Note that this is&#13;
within a given labor pool. It may be thought of in many ways:&#13;
as the ease of movement, as the attractiveness of wage&#13;
differences, or as cultural compatibility.- Although this&#13;
variable is conceptually crucial to the model, it will not be&#13;
present as such in the operational model and will only be&#13;
estimated inferentially to a proportion. Therefore, the&#13;
important thing at this time is to grasp that z(n, i) is a&#13;
measure of transitivity. It may be helpful to think of z(n, i)&#13;
- xpref(n, i) . ipref(n, i), where xpref(n, i) is the&#13;
102&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
preference of workers of origin n for nation i (sector i), and&#13;
ipref is the preference of the host nation i (sector i) for&#13;
nationals from n. Obviously, Lf either forbids the other&#13;
xpref(n, i) or ipref(n, i) = O), then z(n, i) = 0, and as will&#13;
be seen below, no interaction itakes place. While banning is a&#13;
simple extreme form, it id likely that much of the policy&#13;
interest will lie in less drastic increases or decreases of&#13;
the estimated z's (z's), which will be discussed below.&#13;
z(F, i): The accessibility from the rest ofE the world to country-sector i&#13;
is defined as unity.&#13;
The basic interaction equation is a flow of M workers from n to i&#13;
proportionate to the product of supply at n and demand at i, with&#13;
the floDw screened by accessibility z(n, i):&#13;
(3.4)     M(n, i) - V(n)   . W(i) . z(n,i)&#13;
n 0 F&#13;
where D(i) and C(i) are defined as follows:&#13;
(3.5)    D(n)  liO W(i) . z(n, i).&#13;
i C(i)&#13;
(3.6)    C(i) -T V(n) . z(n, i) + 1&#13;
U D(n)&#13;
103&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
For workers from the rest of the world (n - F), the equivalent&#13;
equations are:&#13;
(3.4a) M(F, i) - W(i) . z(F, i) - W(i)&#13;
C(i)              C(i)&#13;
(3-5a) D(F)    - E WMl     . z(, i) =YW(i)&#13;
i C(i)             i C(i)&#13;
Interpretation of the Equations&#13;
Equation (3.4) corresponds, in the general model, to the case X(n)&#13;
Y(i) - 0. That is to say that we regard equations (3.1) and (3.2) as&#13;
constraints. Or that all of the workers available in a pool must be placed&#13;
in jobs within the region (remember that we are limiting this to pools in&#13;
regional labor deficit), and all of the jobs within the regioh must be&#13;
filled. These two constraints ensure that the labor deficit will be met&#13;
exactly by workers from the rest of the world, which amounts to equation&#13;
(3.3). Accordingly, equations (3.4a) and (3.5a) are predicated on X(F) = 1,&#13;
V(F) - 1, z(F, i) - 1, which ensures that the number of workers from the&#13;
rest of the world will respond exactly to the regional deficit.&#13;
A brief interpretation of the equations follows:&#13;
Accept intuitively that C(i) is the potential supply of workers per job&#13;
opening at i.&#13;
104&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Then D(i) may be interpreted as: a measure of the job opportunities per&#13;
worker at i, and the right hand side of equation (3.5) may be read as&#13;
the sum total of job openings in the region, weighted inversely by the&#13;
respective potential workers (i.e., by the chance of getting that job)&#13;
and weightetd positively by their accessibility to workers from n.&#13;
Conversely, C(i) may now be interprete,i, in the right hand side of&#13;
equation (3.6), as the sum total of wolrkers in the region, each&#13;
weighted inversely by the alternative opportunites available to that&#13;
worker (i.e., the chance of getting him) and positively by his&#13;
accessibility to the job at i.&#13;
Note that this is followed by the addiition of unity: this represents&#13;
the potential contribution of the rest of the world to the supply of&#13;
workers per job at i.   This follows mal:hematically from the parameters&#13;
we are using for F, but it can be easily grasped intuitively that, if&#13;
we are saying that any unfilled job wiLl be filled by workers from the&#13;
rest of the world, their potential conl:ribution to any job is one.&#13;
According to equation (3.4) then, the lumber of workers from n at i&#13;
will be proportional to the number of workers in the pool from n,&#13;
weighted inversely by the per-worker sum total of opportunities in the&#13;
region (i.e., the chance of getting each worker), times the number of&#13;
openings in i, weighted inversely by the potential number of workers&#13;
per opening (i.e., the chance of getting that job), and this product&#13;
weighted by the mutual attraction of n and i, or the accessibility of i&#13;
from n.&#13;
105&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Equations (3.4), (3.5) and (3.6) make evident another interpretation of&#13;
z(n, i): it is the spatially discounted value of a unit.&#13;
In spite of its complicated appearance, the M(n, i) of equation (3.4)&#13;
and (3.4a), if summed over n, will indeed reduce to W(i) and will&#13;
reduce to V(n) if summed over i, as required in equations (3.1) and&#13;
(3.2).&#13;
Calibration of the Model&#13;
The inventory of labor force being carried out by the World Bank will&#13;
be a matrix of M(n, i) and, by definition, the row marginals will be V(n)&#13;
and the column marginals W(i).&#13;
The one primary variable that cannot be observed directly is the z(n,i)&#13;
matrix. (D(n) and C(n) are variables derived from the others). Therefore&#13;
it is necessary to estimate it. If we have an estimated z(n,i) matrix for&#13;
any projected set of V's and W's, we can forecast the M matrix, with the&#13;
usual assumption that the relations z are unchanged from one period to the&#13;
next.&#13;
From our estimates of-z, and the projections of V and W, we-will then&#13;
A                                              1&#13;
compute C and D. We will then be in a position to estimate M. -&#13;
At this point the notation will be modified slightly by leaving out (n)-&#13;
and (i) except in cases of ambiguity. A (0) or (T) will denote the date of&#13;
the variable, where (0) refers to the calibration date and (T) to the-&#13;
projection date to be used.&#13;
106&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Thus:&#13;
V(O), W(O), M(O), etc:   actual supply of workers from n V(n), demand for&#13;
workers at i W(i), workers from n at i M(n, i),&#13;
etc., at the calibration date (0).&#13;
AA                A&#13;
z(O), D(O), C(O), M(0): estimated transitiv:Ltyfz(n, i), regional demand&#13;
D(n), regional supply C(i), and workers from n at&#13;
i M(n, i).&#13;
D(T), C(T), V(T), W(T),&#13;
M(T), z(T):             the equivalent variables at date of projection (T).&#13;
k:             an arbitrary constanl: that can conveniently be&#13;
set at W. We now esl:imate z(O) from observed&#13;
variables:&#13;
(3.7)  z(0) -  M(0) k&#13;
V(0) W(O)&#13;
This is equivalent to estimating z(0) as tho ratio of the observed M(0) to&#13;
that which might be expected by double proportionality to the row and column&#13;
marginals. It is closely related to the logic of the contingency table (and&#13;
related also to maximum likelihood estimateis). If the constant k is set-at--&#13;
1EM(O)    (=5W(0), the relation.to these st:andard approaches becomes&#13;
obvious.&#13;
It also becomes clear why it is conveniLent to set k - E    ():&#13;
because it centers the resulting values of z(0) on unity.     But it does&#13;
not matter what value is used for k:. the mathematics of this systemic&#13;
107&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
approach guarantee that z, D, C, will adjust proportionately to give&#13;
the same result.&#13;
In addition, readers with a background in applied economics will&#13;
recognize the parallels of the approach suggested here to the RAS&#13;
method of updating input-output tables on the basis of incomplete&#13;
information as developed by Leontief, Stone, Bacharach, and most&#13;
recently by Fisch and Gordon. Similarly, readers with a backgound in&#13;
traffic modeling will recognize the similarities to the entropy&#13;
approach of A. Wilson and his associates. Those with a background in&#13;
sociology will find distinct echoes from the current lively investigation of&#13;
intergenerational .occupational mobility.&#13;
In brief, then, the approach presented here is closely related&#13;
operationally to these various approaches to the estimation of a&#13;
transitivity operator. The essence of the differences lies in the pattern&#13;
of available data and unknowns in the various problems at hand and in the&#13;
implicit assumptions in the various literature as to theoretical values of&#13;
the transitivity coefficients X(n) and Y (i).&#13;
Aspects of the Estimating Process-&#13;
It is necessary to make one point strongly: z(O) is not strictly an&#13;
estimate of z. By joining equations (3.4) and (3.7), we have.&#13;
108&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3.8)  z(0)  -      kz&#13;
n#f       0(O) D(0)&#13;
Thus, z(O) is not strictly an estimate of %,. but rather of k. The&#13;
distinction makes no operational difference for estimation, but is important&#13;
for interpretation.&#13;
We would next compute C(o), and D(0) using U1(0), V(0), z(0):&#13;
(3.9) D(0)  - W(0) z(O)&#13;
n+F       ITO-&#13;
AA&#13;
(3.10) C(0) - V(0) z(O) + 1&#13;
n#F&#13;
We can do this by setting C(0)'s at an arbit:rary value, estimating D(0)'s&#13;
using this value, reestimating e(0)'s and continuing to iterate until they&#13;
converge. From some numerical experiments, they should converge at about&#13;
the rate of one significant digit per dozen iterations; that is to say, they&#13;
should converge quickly. The solution is unique.&#13;
Without attempting a full proof-here, ithe following will be true:&#13;
109&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
all D(O)'s will be equal to k (except for D(F), which will be equal&#13;
to   W - E V), and all C(O)'s will be equal to 1.&#13;
i     n&#13;
niF&#13;
C O)D(O) = k.   (This derives, by substituting equation (3.8) into&#13;
equation (3.9) or (3.10).&#13;
- M = M, within the limits of round-off error; in otner words, the&#13;
estimation is exact for the calibration period. This can be seen by&#13;
joining equations (3.4) and (3.8) and C(O) D(O) = k.&#13;
- although z(0) is an estimate of (z/C(0)D(O)) rather than of z, it&#13;
will be highly correlated with z except under perverse conditions;&#13;
therefore, for practical purposes, in policy or alternative scenario&#13;
uses of the model, proportional changes in z(O) can be considered as&#13;
proportional changes in z.&#13;
C(O) and D(O) have no interpretive or diagnostic use.    They appear&#13;
to be balancing accounting factors in the model. However, as will&#13;
be seen below, C(T) and D(T)-do have interpretive meaning.     For the-&#13;
rest of the world, the relevant equations are (retaining V(O,F) =&#13;
1):&#13;
(3.11) z(O,F,i) = kM(F,i!&#13;
110&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(3.13) D(O,F) = EW(j) z (O,F,i); = M(O,F,i) =E W(i) -i V(n).&#13;
I       I        ~~~~~~n&#13;
n#f F&#13;
Projection of the Model&#13;
We will now consider the use of this systemic allocation model for&#13;
projection without policy intervention.    This amounts to accepting a set of&#13;
projected V(T), W(T), and an unchanging matrix of z for which the matrix of&#13;
z(O) is substitluted.&#13;
We then generate M(T) for countries within the region (n / F), by&#13;
analogy to equations (3.4), .(.5),and (3.6).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(3.14)  M(T)    V(T) W(T) z(O)&#13;
V(T) '(T)&#13;
n f F&#13;
where (3.15) D(T) - W(T) z (O)&#13;
n + F   ;CZTz&#13;
(3.16)  C(T) - V(T)   z(O) + z(T,F,i)&#13;
CTT1&#13;
n f F&#13;
There is no known analytic solution for finding t(T) and D(T)&#13;
simultaneously. Therefore, the solution procedure is to assume an arbitrary&#13;
A                            ~~~~~~~A&#13;
set of values for C(T), derived from these estimates of D(T), use these to&#13;
recalculate C(T), and continue iteratively until convergence to the derived&#13;
number of significant digits.&#13;
The relation of equations (3.14), (3.15), and (3.16) apply to the&#13;
situation of labor for nationals within the region. For the rest of the&#13;
world, we still assume X (F) - 1, V(F) - 1; therefore, by anology to&#13;
equations (3.4a), (3.5a):&#13;
)A                A&#13;
(3.17) M(T,F,i) - W(T) z (F,i)&#13;
A&#13;
(3.18) D(F,T) -EM(T,F,i) -iW(T,i)        z(F,i)&#13;
i             i C(T,i)&#13;
112&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
C(F) is undefined within the.model, since by assumption there is no&#13;
rest-of-the-world destination.    (Note:  This has not always been the case&#13;
since World War II; witness the brain-drain of many technical specialists&#13;
out of developing and into developed countries. But, by assumption, this&#13;
does not occur here.)&#13;
Summary of the Projection Procedure&#13;
Having obtained the M(o) matrix, which the World Bank is doing,&#13;
0&#13;
Calculate z.(O) =     k M(O)     where 'k =&#142;W(O), and z (O,F,i) =&#13;
i M() M(O)&#13;
n       i&#13;
kM(O,F,l)&#13;
E M(O,n,i)&#13;
n&#13;
Having obtained a set of V(T), W(T) from naitional plan and projection,&#13;
determine that this is a pool in labor deficit by (ZW(T) - YV(T)) &lt; 0;&#13;
estimate by interaction until they converge!&#13;
D(T) =  W(T)  z(0); D(T,F) =-YgW T     ? (0,F); and&#13;
C(T)~~~~~~ (r)&#13;
C(T)&#13;
C(T) -2V(T) z(0) + z(O,f,1)&#13;
D1T)&#13;
113&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
using z(O), D(T), C(T), V(T), W(T) estimate&#13;
M(T) - V(T) W(T) z (0), and M(T,F,i) - W(T) z (O,F,i).&#13;
AxT) 'D(T)              'C()A&#13;
The Relation of M(T) to M(T), z(O) to Z, D(T) to D(T), C(T) to C(T)&#13;
M(T) will be the eyact estimate of M(T) if the structural&#13;
relations of of labor exchange within the region are unchanged from date 0&#13;
to date T. The reason is as follows:&#13;
If we knew true z's, then we could calculate equation (3.19) rather&#13;
than equation (3.14).&#13;
.(3.19) M(T) V V(T) W(T) z&#13;
C(T) D(T)&#13;
n 4 F&#13;
Substituting the relation noted on equation (3.8), z     -      kz     , into&#13;
equation (3.14).                                      n 'tF  C(0) D(0)&#13;
114&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(3.20) M(T) = V(T) W(T) zk&#13;
n*F     V(TMT)G(O)DPT&#13;
Clearly, then, from this equation, the approximation of M(T) by M(T) will be&#13;
A &#13;
exact if (1/k) C(T)D(T)C(O)D(0) = C(T)D(T).&#13;
Although there is no strong proof that; this is the case, it is&#13;
consistent with numerical experiments and with the mathematical structure of&#13;
the model.&#13;
What happens is that the individual C(T) and D(T) are differentiated by&#13;
the structure of the model to make this approximation of M(T) by MIT) exact,&#13;
or nearly so.&#13;
Since k is an arbitrary constant, set it for the moment at 1.     Then&#13;
(C(T)D(0)) (D(T)D(0)) = C(T)D(T), and, a strong conjecture can be made that&#13;
A&#13;
(3.21) C(T) C(0) =C(T)&#13;
(3.22)  D(T) D(0) = D(T)&#13;
A &#13;
That is to say, the estimation procedure produces a set of C and D such that&#13;
they translate the corresponding C(0) and D(O) into the correct C(T) and&#13;
D(T).&#13;
115&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
From equations (3.21) and (3.22) it follows that, although we cannot&#13;
know directly the true values of C and D at either date, we can know how&#13;
they are changing. Rewrite the last two equations as:&#13;
(3.21a) C(T) = C(T)/C(O)&#13;
A&#13;
(3.22a) D(T) 5 D(T)/D(O)&#13;
Similarly, if we define Y* as the ratio of an earlier to a later value&#13;
for that variable (i.e., Y* = Y(O)/Y(T)) then the prior combinations of&#13;
equations yield.&#13;
(3.23) M(T) =kV*W*M(O)&#13;
'V(T) '[(T)&#13;
(3.24) M*   =     V*W*&#13;
'QT) 'UT)&#13;
A ~A&#13;
That is to say, C(T) and D(T), in accordance with equations (3.21a) and&#13;
(3.22a), modify the relevant marginal changes in V and W (i.e., V* and W*),&#13;
A&#13;
to update the M(O) observed earlier to the current M(T).&#13;
116&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Therefore, knowing C(T), we can tell by how much the supply of labor&#13;
(true C) has changed from date 0 to date T for a given destination.&#13;
Similarly, knowing D(T) we would know how the demand (true D) has changed&#13;
for a pool of workers of a given nationalilty.&#13;
Sdnce Industry prefers to have as plentiful a supply as possible, and&#13;
A     A&#13;
workers as many opportunities as possible, C and D are useful indicators of&#13;
whether the situation is improving or deteriorating for particular&#13;
industries or groups of workers. They provide a means of evaluating&#13;
alternative projections.or policy scenarios. They also suggest a very&#13;
interesting optimizing approach that will be discussed in the last part of&#13;
this section.&#13;
There is, as yet, no analytic proof of the relations of equations&#13;
(3.1ta) and (3.22a). But extensive numerilcal analysis yields this result,&#13;
and algebraic analysis shows, through various paths, its consistency with&#13;
the structure of the model. While a strict proof is still wanting, we can&#13;
proceed with confidence, on both the. basis.of the analysis-and numerical&#13;
experimentation done for-this project,: and-the related techniques mentioned&#13;
earlier in this paper.&#13;
Procedure for Pools In Regional Labor Surplus&#13;
IfIV &gt;5TW, this pool is in regional labor surplus.    The suggested&#13;
procedure is parallel to that for the workers from the rest of the world.&#13;
117&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
We assume that countries for which a national labor surplus is&#13;
projected (i.e., V(T,i) &gt; W(T,i) will retain those workers who cannot find&#13;
work at home or abroad. In other words, we assume that countries do not&#13;
export their unemployment.&#13;
For this purpose we add to the set of W(T)'s a set of W(T,u,i), one for&#13;
each country i with surplus labor. Apd we assign the following values:&#13;
W(u,i) - 1;&#13;
Y(u,i) - 1;&#13;
z(n,u,i) - kM(O,n,u,i)    for countries in labor surplus in this pool;&#13;
V( 0,n)&#13;
z(n,u,i) - 0              for countries in labor deficit in this pool;&#13;
z(i,u,n) - 0, i 0 n       that is, unemployment is not exported;&#13;
M(O,n,u,i) -              observed unemployed (in that pool) in country&#13;
i in period 0.&#13;
This procedure will ensure that M(T,n,u,i) will be the total unemployed in&#13;
that pool in that country in period T, and that:&#13;
(a)    1M(T,n,i) - W(T,n)   , that is, that all members of that country's&#13;
j                       pool are accounted for; and&#13;
118&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(b)  I  M(T,n,i) - V(T,n)   , that is' that the demand for the labor in that&#13;
1 i                     country is met.  Note that it is possible that,&#13;
if some 'z (i,n) (ifn)are nonzero, there will be&#13;
some workers from other countries in the region&#13;
working in country i in spite of its&#13;
unemployment. This may be quite realistic.&#13;
But if one wants to prevent this, one only has&#13;
set all z (n,i) at zero for i7in.&#13;
The equations to be used to operate thie labor surplus case are:&#13;
(3.25) z(n,i)        -       M(O,n,i)&#13;
V(O,n) W(O,i)&#13;
A                                   1&#13;
(3.26) M(T,n,i)      -      V(T,n) W(T,i)  2(n,i), i # (u,n)&#13;
tZT,i) 'U(T,n)&#13;
A                                       A&#13;
(3.27) D(T,i)            E  W(T,i) . z(n,il + z(i,u,n)&#13;
(3.28) C(T,i)       -    E   V(T,n) . z(n,i)&#13;
n  T1T,n)&#13;
119&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(3.29) M(T,n,u,i)     -    V(T,n)  . z(n,u,i)&#13;
IXT,n)&#13;
A &#13;
(3.30) C(T,u,i)       -    V(T,n)   . z(n,u,i)&#13;
T(T,n)&#13;
The procedure, then, is exactly as in the case of labor deficit.&#13;
First, determine thatY.V   &gt;W.    Then calculate Z's from the M(0) matrix.&#13;
A           A             AA &amp;&#13;
Then, by iteration, estimate C(T)'s and D(T)'s. Use z, C(T), D(T), V(T),&#13;
and W(T) to estimate the M(T)'s.&#13;
Note the further symmetry with the labor deficit case: instead of&#13;
having a slack-variable rest-of-the-world origin, we have a slack-variable&#13;
A&#13;
national destination for each country; instead of a - + z(F,i)" at the tail&#13;
end of the definition of C, we have ' + t n,u,i)" accordingly at the tall&#13;
A&#13;
end of D; and whereas in the case of labor deficit we could specify D but&#13;
A                                                      ~~~~~~~~~~~A&#13;
not C for the slack variable, in the case of labor surplus we can specify C&#13;
A&#13;
but not D.&#13;
Remember, of course, that there is no 'rest of the world' in the case&#13;
of regional labor surplus. It is assumed that nationals of the region will&#13;
have first call on the labor deficits that may exist in some of the&#13;
regions's countries, even though the region as a whole is in surplus. It&#13;
may be possible to construct a procedure that includes both slack variables&#13;
120&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
for supply of labor by the rest of the world, and for the absorption of&#13;
unemployment in labor-surplus countries. However, this possibility is still&#13;
to be explored. The resulting system would be very complex, and&#13;
considerable analytic and numerical explorat:ion would probably be needed&#13;
before its properties could be fully undersltood.&#13;
Regions that Change between Surplus and Deficit&#13;
Whether in the case of regional labor surplus or deficit, the&#13;
procedures outlines above presume that an observed inflow/outflow in the&#13;
base period provides the basis for the estimation of transitoriness in the&#13;
later period. As long as there has been a migrant flow in the direction of&#13;
interest, z can be estimated.&#13;
But consider a case where, for a given pool, a country goes from&#13;
deficit to surplus, or vice versa, from the base to the projection period.&#13;
Then there is no base-period migration flow in or out of the country on the&#13;
basis of which that particular z may be estimated. Yet, if the situation&#13;
changes in the nation from deficit to surplus, or vice versa, some new flow&#13;
A&#13;
will arise for whicu there is no prior experience on which to calibrate z.&#13;
Such cases will probably be rare. Where they occur, best results can&#13;
A&#13;
probably be obtained if the relevant z is made equal to the average of the&#13;
obsevedA                       A&#13;
observed z's (i.e., z(F,i)'s, or z(n,u,i).&#13;
121&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Aggregation, Collapsing Categories, and Data Efficiencies&#13;
The proposed procedure is perfectly tolerant of aggregation or&#13;
disaggregation of classes of origin, or destination. For-instance, if&#13;
several industries in a country are aggregated into W(y) = W(i,l) +&#13;
W(i,2)..., then z(n,y) =           for all i,l; i,2; etc., instead of&#13;
V(-n) W(y)&#13;
A                                      A&#13;
z(n,i,l) = M(n,l)        etc. Clearly, z(n,y) will be an average value of the&#13;
V(n) W(i,l)&#13;
A&#13;
(n,i,l)'s: z(n,y) = M(n,i,l) + M(n,i,2) +&#13;
V(n) W(y,l) + (i,2) +&#13;
A similar process involves aggregations of origins, as might occur if&#13;
several small countries of origin are grouped as suppliers of a certain: type&#13;
of labor.&#13;
The advantage of this is that, where the data are sketchy or&#13;
aggregated, they can still be used in the general framework. If later or&#13;
more detailed data become available, or one wishes to disaggregate into more&#13;
detail (by whatever combination of data, assumptions, or policy), it can be&#13;
done locally, without reestimating the whole model.&#13;
The same applies in the other direction, of course if, for any reason,&#13;
some of the distinctions among categories of destination or origin are&#13;
uninteresting, the model may be collapsed accordingly.&#13;
122&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Policy Uses&#13;
Thus far, procedures described amount to using the model for&#13;
projection, perhaps under alternative assumptions as to V(T) and W(T). But&#13;
clearly an important use of the model is for policy simulation. Three&#13;
principal approaches come to mind: modifying z's, limiting M's or&#13;
optimization.&#13;
A&#13;
Modifying zs&#13;
A&#13;
In the first case, imagine that a certain M(n,i) is regarded as too low&#13;
by the host country i, which would like to fill more of its labor needs with&#13;
nationals from n. Country i tries to increase labor from n by a variety of&#13;
devices: propaganda, direct recruitment, iFacilitation of visas and work&#13;
permits, speciaLl facilities such as housing, wage supplements, family&#13;
permits and family allowances, etc. In so doing, it would be trying to&#13;
A&#13;
raise the value of z(n,i). There is no clear procedure by which one could&#13;
assign a given increase (or decrease) to ztn,i).associated with a-particular&#13;
package of inducements (or restraints) to labor migr4nts from n to i.&#13;
A&#13;
Therefore, the increase (or decrease) attributed to z(n,i) must be a matter&#13;
of judgment: one might say that the policies have made it 60X easier (or&#13;
50X harder) to go from n to i, and therefore multiply the original z(n,i) by&#13;
1.6 (or by .5).&#13;
Conversely, a labor supplying cquntry n may alter its preferences, for&#13;
whatever reasons, as to the destination oJ. its nationals, and attempt to&#13;
change the &#143;' n,i)'s by one or another mea1is:  visas, propaganda, placement&#13;
123&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
programs, etc. Again, it would be a matter of judgment as to the proportion&#13;
by which the z(n,i)'s would be changed.&#13;
A&#13;
Recall the early section of this description in which z(n,i) was&#13;
imagined to be the product of xpref(i,n) and ipref(i,n) where xpref(i,n) was&#13;
the preference or affinity of origin n for destination i, and ipref(i,n) was&#13;
the preference or affinity of destination i for origin n.&#13;
Clearly, we cannot measure xpref(i,n) or ipref(i,n) directly; in fact,&#13;
A                         A&#13;
we cannot measure z(n,i), but only estimate z(n,i). But, conceptually, a&#13;
policy-induced increase of 50% in ipref(i,n) would increase its value by a&#13;
factor of 1.5, and would increase z(n,i) by the same amount. Similarly, a&#13;
30% increase (decrease) in xpref(i,n) would result in an increase by a&#13;
factor of 1.3 (a decrease by a factor of .7) in z(n,i). Simultaneously,&#13;
changes in xpref(i,n) and ipref(i,n) would result in changes in z(n,i)&#13;
proportional to the factor changes in xpref(i,n) and ipref(i,n).&#13;
In the extreme case, where i bans workers from n, or where n forbids&#13;
its workers to go to i, we have that xpref(i,n) - 0 or ipref(i,n) - 0, and&#13;
in either case z(n,i) ! 0. This case, although extreme, it not unknown in&#13;
the Middle East.&#13;
But, of course,_z(n,i) cinnot be measured directly.- One can only&#13;
AA&#13;
estimate z . Mk/VW - zk/CD. But z is highly correlated to z, and, so,&#13;
proportional changes in z will result in approximate proportional changes in&#13;
z.&#13;
124&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Therefore, if judgmental proportional changes are apportioned to&#13;
xpref(i,n) or ipref(i,n), z(n,i) should be changed by the product of these&#13;
changes.&#13;
These changes may originate in origin or destination country policies,&#13;
or in events thsLt are not the result of conscious policy, such as social&#13;
conflict, health factors, 'beaten track' effects of friends and relatives,&#13;
etc. Whatever their source, relative changes in the putative xpref(i,n) and&#13;
ipref(n,i) would be echoed in z(n,i) and strongly reflected in the&#13;
operational estimated z(n,i).&#13;
A&#13;
It is important to recall here that the z's are estimated nearly&#13;
independently from each other: z - Mk/VW. Therefore, for practical&#13;
A~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
purposes individual Z's may be changed one ab a time to reflect changes in&#13;
policies or circumstances, without having l:o be concerned with modifying the&#13;
other z's.&#13;
Increasing the value of a particular Iz will have, in general, the&#13;
effect of increasing the value of the corresponding N by about the same&#13;
proportion. The values of the other M's for that row and column will be&#13;
accordingly deiressed, sifice,--under the constraints of this model, if more&#13;
go from n to i,, fewer will go from i elsewhere and fewer will arrive at i&#13;
from elsewhere; therefore, as the row n arid column i values decline (except&#13;
A                                                        A&#13;
for M(n,i) itself), the values of the&amp;other elements in the M matrix will&#13;
tend to rise slightly.&#13;
A&#13;
The directions of these ripples'resulting from a change in X(n,i) will&#13;
be reversed, of course, if it Is decreased rather than increased,&#13;
125&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
At any rate, having this general understanding of the direction of&#13;
effects, policies, or scenarios may be tried out on the model by modifying&#13;
L's.&#13;
A&#13;
Limiting M's&#13;
There will be cases when a host country i will 4ecide that it wants no&#13;
more than a given ratio F(n,i) of workers from origin n for a given pool.&#13;
A&#13;
In such cases, if the model run without constraints yields M(n,i)/W(N,i)&lt;&#13;
F(n,i), there is no problem. But, if M(n,i)/W(n,i) &gt; F(n,i), then one would&#13;
proceed as follows:&#13;
(a)  set M(n,i)  =  W(n,i) . F(n,i);&#13;
(b)  set Q(n,i)     0 0 to ensure that no more workers from n come to i;&#13;
(c) rerun the model;&#13;
(d) check again for exceeded limits;&#13;
(e) run again if necessary.&#13;
Optimization and Evaluation&#13;
It might be useful to have.a sense of the efficiency of current or&#13;
projected patterns of labor movement within the region. Two approaches can&#13;
be suggested:&#13;
126&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(1)  A simpile measure of the efficiency of population movements, by now&#13;
traditional in the migration literature, is the ratio of net changes in&#13;
stock to the actual flows. Allowing that the model proposed here generates&#13;
estimates of stocks at a given date rather than actual behavioral flows, we&#13;
can adopt the concept to measure the ratio of the minimum expatriation of&#13;
labor within the region to the actual expatriation. For a given labor pool&#13;
in regional deficit, the maximum expatriation within the region for nations&#13;
with labor deficit is zero, and for nations with labor surplus, it is the&#13;
surplus. Thus, the minimum number of moves in the region is J {t(i) where,&#13;
Y(i) - 0 if W(i) &gt; V(i); Y(i) X (V(i) - W(i)) if W(i) &lt; V(i).     For a labor&#13;
pool in regional surplus, Y(i)     (W(i) - V(i) if W(i) &gt; V(i) and Y(i) - 0 if&#13;
W(i) &lt; V(i).   The actual number of moves within the region arei5jM.&#13;
n+i,F&#13;
This measure of efficiency of migration is then the ratio of the minimum&#13;
necessary moves within the region to the tc,tal number of actual moves within&#13;
the- region: J/EEM&#13;
nfi,F&#13;
It may be interesting for-policy to keep track of this evaluator of 0&#13;
A&#13;
migration efficiency under various assumptions as to V(T), W(T), and z.&#13;
(2) It would be--useful, both for evaLuation and for policy design, to&#13;
have an optimized solution for reference or as a benchmark. The main&#13;
problem is that there is no clearly acceptable or interpretable objective&#13;
function: what is to be optimized?&#13;
A possible objective function comes to mind. If z(n,i) is the ease of&#13;
movement or trELnsitivity from a to 1, then v. 4(n,i) is a measure of the&#13;
difficulty or work done in going once from n to i.&#13;
127&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Therefore, 2      z-l is an estimated measure of the migratory effort or&#13;
nfi, ij(u,n)&#13;
cost within the region and a potential objective function to be minimized,&#13;
subject to the contraints provided by V and W.&#13;
Note that Mz-l = VW/CD, so that minimizing migratory effort (Mz-l) is&#13;
akin to maximizing the product of demand and supply of labor (CD .    This&#13;
appears to be a very reasonable dual: maximizing the opportunites&#13;
available to workers (D) and the pool of workers available per job (C).    It&#13;
is particularly attractive because it echoes perfectly the logic of such&#13;
optimizing models as those that economize in the use of resources.    The&#13;
clearest parallel is that to models that minimize transport costs and that&#13;
have as their dual the maximization of the value of resources (rents and&#13;
quasi-rents).&#13;
At this writing, the nature of such an optimization, has not been&#13;
properly explored. The first question that comes to mind is whether the&#13;
iterative equilibrating procedure suggested here results in itself in that&#13;
optimum, in the style of neoclassical economics and the invisible hand.&#13;
That is to say, that the sum total of bilateral transactions would be&#13;
optimal for the whole. On the other hand, it may be that such an optimum&#13;
lies elsewhere. In either-case, there might-be much to be learned from a&#13;
contrast and comparison of optimization of simulation within this system.&#13;
128&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Manpower Model:  Glossary of Notation&#13;
Symbol                          meaning&#13;
AA                    Minimum legal age to work minus one&#13;
a(l,l)                 Element4of transition matrix TRANI (p)&#13;
At(g)                  Constant annual teacher attritioni rate for group g&#13;
B                     Bounds of optimizing function&#13;
BB                    Minimum age allowed to attend any school&#13;
c                     Course in ESM&#13;
C(i)                   Potential supply of workers per job opening at i&#13;
COST(i.J,n)            Imputed cost of one expatriate man-year working in&#13;
sector i.&#13;
D(i)                  Job opportunities per worker at sector/country i&#13;
D(noncont)            Completer (promoted) not continuing in ETS&#13;
d(t,c)                Dropout--rate in course c at time t&#13;
E(t,i)                Target employment level&#13;
e(i,t)                 Elements of the employment estimates for sector i-at&#13;
year t&#13;
epro(t,c)             Promotion rate in course c at time t&#13;
EQM(t,c,i,j)          Entrance qualification matrix&#13;
f                     Target national share of workers&#13;
f(i,;)                Target share of workers that is national labor force&#13;
FIL(t,c)              Rates of graduates from course c in t&#13;
129&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
9                     Teacher group&#13;
G(t,c)                Number of graduates from course c in year t&#13;
H(t,lj)               Occupation distribution matrix&#13;
h(i,j)                Element for share of jth occupational input in total&#13;
labor input in sector i&#13;
i pr1f (I,n)          Preference of host nation i and sector i for nationals&#13;
from n (migration model)&#13;
I                     sector/county&#13;
i                      Occupation&#13;
k                     Arbitrary constant (migration model)&#13;
K                     Constant growth rate of output&#13;
lag                   Time lag&#13;
LEAK (o,r,p,t-lag)    Initial stock of leaked labor force&#13;
l(t.j,t)               Elements of the manpower requirement matrix&#13;
LG(t,c)               Number of graduates from course c participation in&#13;
labor participation in labor force after filtered&#13;
130&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
LKLF (t,i,j,r)         The leakage rate for the existing labor force&#13;
LKPRO (t,i,j,i,j)      Promotion matrix&#13;
LKPOOL (t,r,p,t-lag) Pooled leakages&#13;
LKSC (t,r,p)           Leakage rate for current school leavers&#13;
M(F,i)                 Number of workers from rest of world in country i&#13;
M(n,i)                 Number of workers of nationality n in the region in&#13;
country i, sector i&#13;
moveins, moveoLits     moveins, moveouts&#13;
MSE                    Labor force supplied by ETS&#13;
MSE(t,i,j)             Manpower supplies by ESM to go into labor force&#13;
n                      Nationality or worker; Origin of worker (in&#13;
migration model)&#13;
Origin of worker (in migration model)&#13;
NA(t,j)                Attrition rate vector for national labor&#13;
NAR (t,i,j)            Net additional manpower requirement&#13;
Net MR(i,j)            Net manpower requirement for current schooleavers&#13;
Net NLPM               Net change in national labor force due to promotions&#13;
Net TR(g)              Net teacher requirement in group g&#13;
Net X (t-l,i,j,r,n)    Global allocation of expatriates by MPM&#13;
Net X                  Net importation or exportation of nonnational manpower&#13;
131&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NG (t,i,j)             Target level national labor in sector i occupation j&#13;
which meets goal&#13;
NLF(t,i,j)             National labor force&#13;
NLF (O,i,j)            Base year national labor force&#13;
0                      Base Period (migration model)&#13;
p                      Pool ID (in migration model)&#13;
PER (t,i,j)            Percent of target still needed to meet nationalization&#13;
goal for a given sectorJoccupation&#13;
PIT (t,g)              Target intake of teachers of group g as calculated by&#13;
ESM in year t&#13;
P(t,i)                 Input productivity data&#13;
PL (r,p)               Pooled leakages in locality r for pool p&#13;
PM                     Priority matrix&#13;
POP (t,a,r)            Population of age a In locality r&#13;
132&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Q (t,i)                Target product for sector i in year t&#13;
Q (O,i)                Base year sectoral product&#13;
R                      Total number of localities&#13;
Locality; Student (in ESM); Years in stream (in PS of&#13;
ESM)&#13;
RATES (t,c,r)          Rate of non-labor movement&#13;
Reallocated&#13;
(t- ,i,j,r,t-lag)    Reallocated leakages&#13;
rep (t,c)              Repetition rate in ccourse c at time t&#13;
RLLF                   Matrix of redistributed leakage labor force&#13;
S (cont)               Completer (promoted) continuing to course Cl&#13;
S (d)                  Dropout (non-completer)&#13;
S (noncont)            Completer-(promoted) not continuing in ETS&#13;
S(pro)                 Completed (promoted) whether or not continuing&#13;
S(rep)                 Repeater in same course&#13;
SAL (t,c,a)            Current year underage school leavers&#13;
SCPOOL (t-l,r,p)       Current year school lleavers&#13;
SoM                    Sector/occupation matrix&#13;
ST(t,g)                Teachers available in year t&gt;l for group g&#13;
ST(O,g)                Base year teacher stock for group g&#13;
133&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Survivor Rate         Rate of survival of population&#13;
T                     The value at the calibration date; last simulation&#13;
year&#13;
t                     Year (of analysis)&#13;
TLP(t,ij)             The manpower requirement matrix&#13;
TRAN(p)               Transition matrix for pool ID&#13;
TS(t,c)                Total students in course c at time t&#13;
TTR (t,g)             Total teacher requirement for group i&#13;
UAS(t,c,a)            Existing cumulative underage school leavers by course&#13;
c and age a in year t&#13;
UGPOOL (T-l,r,p)       Underage school leavers&#13;
V                      Unemployed&#13;
V(F-1)                 Dummy slack variable for workers from rest of world&#13;
V(n)                   The supply of nationals from country n in the region&#13;
V(O,n)                 The supply of workers from country n at the&#13;
calibration date&#13;
W(M)                   Demand for workers in sector in country i regardless&#13;
of nationality&#13;
134&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
XA(t,j)               Attrition rate vector for foreign labor&#13;
xpref (i,n)           Preference of workers of origin n for nation I&#13;
(migration model)&#13;
XLF                   Non-national labor force stock&#13;
XLF (O,i,j)           Base year non-national labor force&#13;
Y                     Number of moves V-Wl (migration model)&#13;
Z                     Constant employment; growth rate; objective function&#13;
minimizing cost of employing expatriate labor&#13;
z(F,i)                Accessibility from rest of world to country i&#13;
z(n,l)                Accessibility of country i from country n&#13;
135&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Part III USER'S GUIDE&#13;
The User's Guide is presented in three parts, each corresponding&#13;
to one of the three interrelated models: country specific (compound),&#13;
regional (expanded), and migration. The purpose of the guide is to provide&#13;
users with information on the features of each model, available reports and&#13;
outputs, and instructions on how to use the models. The user has a choice of&#13;
which of the models to use, and the information contained in the preceding&#13;
discussion should be of assistance in making a selection.&#13;
Each part of the guide is being published as a separate volume in&#13;
the World Bank Staff Working Papers series. Volume II (Number 588) is the&#13;
User's Guide for the Country (Compound) Model; Volume III (Number 589) is the&#13;
User's Guide for the Regional (Expanded) Model; and Volume IV (Number 590) is&#13;
the User's Guide for the Migration Model.&#13;
136&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
World Bank&#13;
PubUications&#13;
of Related&#13;
Interest&#13;
NEW&#13;
The Deterninants of Labour           income countries in terms of a num-  Economic Growth and&#13;
Earnings In Developing               ber of socioeconomic indicators, it is  Employment in China&#13;
Metropolses: Estimates               noted that there are iairge regional  Thomas G. Rawski&#13;
disparities between the northeast and&#13;
from Bogota and Call,                the southeast with the northeast far-  Examines how China's agricultural&#13;
Colombia                             Ing about the same as most low-      sector has made significant strides&#13;
Rakesh Mohan                         Income countries.                   toward full employment for a labor&#13;
force of neariy hailf a biiilon prsons.&#13;
Examines the patterns of behavior    World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   f&#13;
implicit In the variation of labor earn-  505. February 1982. 91 pages (includ-  Oxford University Press, 1979.&#13;
Ings In Bogota and Call. Colombia.   Ing references, map).                208 pages (including maps, bibliogra-&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   Stock No. WP-0505. $3.00.            phy, index).&#13;
498. October 1981.135 pages (includ-                                      LC 79-19550. ISBN 0-19-520151-5,&#13;
Ing 2 appendixes, bibliography).                                          $18.95 hardcover. ISBN 0-19-520152-3,&#13;
Stock No. WP-0498. $5.00.            The Distrlbutioni of                 $7.95 paperback.&#13;
Income In Brazil                     French: Croissance et emploi en Chine.&#13;
}Guy e Pfeffermann and               Economica, 1980.&#13;
rMEW                             Richard C. Webb                     ISBN 2-7178-0282-7, 39 francs.&#13;
Differences In Income.               World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   Spanfsh: Crecimiento econ6mico y&#13;
Nlutrition, and Poverty356. September(1979. U6 pages                      empleo en China. Editorial Tecnos,&#13;
wutithion Baznd Pvry(including 2 appendIx,es).                           1980.&#13;
Vinod Thomas                         Stock No. WP-0356. $                 ISBN 84-309-0871-4, 600 pesetas.&#13;
Regional disparities In lilving stan-&#13;
dards In Brazil are examined and                                          Employment Patterns&#13;
estimates for real Income and nutrl-                                      and Income Growth&#13;
tional levels and poverty for maJor                                       Jn Stem           and&#13;
urban and rural areas are provided.                                       Joseph J. Stem and&#13;
Although the growth rate of the coun-                                     Jeffrey D. Lewis&#13;
try surpasses the averaite for most                                       World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
developing countries arid the country41.Spebr98.7pas&#13;
performs as well as maniy middle-                                         419. September 1980. 70 pages&#13;
(including bibliography, 2 appen-&#13;
dixes).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0419. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Employment Policy In                 Household Income or                 Income Distribution Policy&#13;
Developing Countries:                Household Income                    in the Developing Coun-&#13;
A Survey of Issues                   per Capita in Welfare               tries: A Case Study of Korea&#13;
and Evidence                         Comparisons                         Irma Adelman and&#13;
Lyn Squire                          Gautam Datta and                     Sherman Robinson&#13;
Low rates of growth in industrial   Jacob Meerman                        Seeks to answer the question of how&#13;
employment high rates of unemploy-   World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  much can actually be done to&#13;
ment among new entrants to the      37g                        i         improve Income distrlbuon by&#13;
urban labor market, and low levels of  38. March 1980. 32 pages (includ)ng  means of a dynamic general&#13;
labor productivity and remuneration   appendixes. references).           equilibrium model for investIgating&#13;
are the three issues addressed in this  Stock No. WP-03 78. $3.00.       the potential impact of standard&#13;
study. The author identifles the impor-                                  policy instruments and programs&#13;
tant determinants of labor demand                                        Intended to improve the relative and&#13;
and supply and the extent to which   How Segmented is the                absolute incomes of the poor.&#13;
the growth of labor demand has been  Bogota Labor Market?                Stanford University Press, Stanford,&#13;
constrained-and labor supply                                             S   f     U      PmSnr&#13;
advanced-by inappropriate policies.  Gary S. Fields                      California 94305, U.S.A. (except the&#13;
On the demand side, industrial trade  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  United Kingdom and the Common-&#13;
policy, agricultural growth, and the  434. October 1980. 99 pages (includ-  wealth Market). 1978. Oxford Uniuersity&#13;
operation of capital markets are    Ing bibliography).                   Press (except Mexico, United States,&#13;
discussed; on the supply side, atten-  Stock No WP-0434 $300             and Canada). 1978. 364 pages (includ-&#13;
tion is focused on population and                                        ing 6 appendixes, index).&#13;
education policy.                                                        LC 76-14269. ISBN 0-8047-0925-4&#13;
Oxford University Press, 1981. 242   Incidence of Poverty and            (Stanford), $12.50 hardcouer.&#13;
pages (including bibliography, index).  the Characteristics of           ISBN 0-19-920084-X (Oxford), 7.50&#13;
LC 81-2844. ISBN 0-19-520266-X,      the Poor In Peninsular              hardcover.&#13;
$16.95 (f11.50) hardcover; ISBN      Malaysia, 1973&#13;
0-19-520267-8, $7.95 (5.00)         Pravin Visaria                       Income Inequality and&#13;
paperback.                           Examines the results of the          Poverty: Methods of Estima-&#13;
Household Expenditure and Income     tion and Policy Applications&#13;
Growth and Equity in Semi.           Survey conducted In peninsular       Nanak C. Kakwani&#13;
Malaysia during 1973 In order toNnaC.Ikwn&#13;
Industralized Countries              understand better the correlates     Deals with income distribution&#13;
Joel Bergsman                        of poverty.                          methods and their economic&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  applications.&#13;
351. August 1979. II + 113 pages     460. May 1981. vil + 213 pages      Oxford University Press, 1980. 432&#13;
(including references).              (including statistical appendix).   pages (including bibliography,&#13;
Stock No. WP-0351. $5.00.            Stock No. WP-0460. $10.00.          Indexes).&#13;
LC 80-14229. ISBN 0-19-520227-9,&#13;
Growth with Equity:                  Income Distribution                  $12.95 paperback.&#13;
The Taiwan Case                      and Poverty in Mexico&#13;
John C. H. Fei, Gustav Ranis,        Joel Bergsman                            NEW&#13;
and Shirley W. Y. Kuo                World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Introduces a method for tracing      395. July 1980. 46 pages (including  Inequality and Poverty&#13;
the Inequality of family Income to  references).                         in Malaysia:&#13;
the Inequality of various kinds of   Stock No. WP-0395. $3.00.            Measurement and&#13;
factor income and the shares                                              Decomposition&#13;
of factor Income In family income.                                        Sudhir Anand&#13;
Oxford University Press, 1980.                                           An account of Income Inequallties&#13;
444 pages (including Index).                                              and poverty In Malaysia. The research&#13;
LC 79-23354. ISBN 0-19-520115-9,                                          Is policy oriented and the flndings, to&#13;
$27.50 (10.25) hardcouer;                                                which the authors statistical tech-&#13;
ISBN 0-19-520116-7, $12.95                                                nique is appled, are thoroughly&#13;
(f4.25) paperback.                                                        discussed. A range of issues Is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
covered, from data problems to con-  regarding links between human       Studies the evolution of the structure&#13;
ceptual questions arising with respect  development and labor productivity  of consumer preferences as a func-&#13;
to measurement.                     and focuses on policy measures       tion of economic development.&#13;
Oxford University Prs. 1982. 3S4     aimed at raising the productivity of  Oxford University Pres, 1977. 312&#13;
the poor and promoting economic      Ofr    nvriyPes 97       1&#13;
pages (including bibliography, index).  development                      pages (including bibliography,&#13;
LC 81-14178. ISBN 0-19-520153-1,     Wopment.                            Indexes).&#13;
$27.0 hardcoer.                      World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  LC 77-3442. ISBN 0-19-920097-1,&#13;
o497. October1981. it + 70 pages     $22.50 hardcover;&#13;
(including bibliography).            ISBN 0-19-920100-5, $12.95&#13;
International Migrant                Stock No. WP-0497. $3.00.           paperback.&#13;
Workers' Remittances:&#13;
Issues and ProspectsNE&#13;
Gurushri Swamy                            EW                              Policy Interventions for&#13;
Auackgrousnr swamy for World                                             Technological Innovation in&#13;
DeAeaopgrent Report 1981. Puts       Manpower and intemrational           Developing Countries&#13;
together available data on intema-   Labor Migration in the Mid-          Charles Cooper&#13;
tional migrant workers' remittances to  die East and North Africa         World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
developing countries and analyzes    Ismail Serageldin, James A.          441. December 1980. 59 pages&#13;
the regional structure of andgrowth  Socknat Stace Birks, N3ob Li,       (including references).&#13;
in thiese flows. Relates the flow of anClvA.Scai&#13;
remittances to the level of and fluc-  n   Ive  . inclair                 Stock No. WP-0441. $3.00.&#13;
tuations in economic activity and to  This study of labor market trends in&#13;
inflation in the host countries and  the region from 1975 to 1985&#13;
attempts to forecast future demand   analyzes the demand for and supply   Poverty and Growth&#13;
for migrant labor and the likely     of manpower by country sector,      in Kenya&#13;
growth in remittances.               occupatIon sex, educational level,   Paul Collier and Deepak Lal&#13;
and ethnic composition. It indicates&#13;
Wor/d Bank Staff Working Paper No.   the sources and destinations of      World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
481. August 1981. 64 pages (Including  workers and examines the social and  389. May 1980. 76 pages (including&#13;
2 appendixes, bibliography).         economic effects of migration for    2 appendixes, bibliography).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0481. $3.00.            both Importers and exporters, par-   Stock No. WP-0389. $5.00.&#13;
ticularly the Implications for        tcNoWP08.300&#13;
government policy and planning.&#13;
Labor Migration                      Oxford University Pres. 1983. About  Poverty and Unemployment&#13;
from Bangladesh to                   224 pages.                          In India: An Analysis of&#13;
the Middle East                      ISBN 0-19-520406-9. $27.50 hardcover.  Recent Evidence&#13;
Syed Ashraf All,                                                          Pravin Visaria&#13;
Abu Ahmed Arif,&#13;
A. K. Md Habibullah,                 A Model for Income                   World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
A.R.M. Anwar lHossain,               Distribution, Employment.            417. October 1980. iii + 39 pages&#13;
Rizwanul Islam, Wahiduddin           and Growth: A Case Study             (including statistical annex).&#13;
Mahmud. S. R. Osmani,                of Indonesia                         Stock No. WP-041 7. $5.00.&#13;
Q.M. Rahman, and                     Syamaprasad Gupta&#13;
A.M.A.Hi. Siddiqui                   Presents a quantitative framework to  Pubilc Expenditure In&#13;
Discusses the economic and social    explore the Implications c f alternative  Malaysia: Who Beneflts&#13;
Implications of labor migration from  policies for Investment, eirnploy'menL  and Why&#13;
Banigladesh to the Middle East. Part of  Income distribution, and flscal&#13;
a research project that also Includes a  activity for medium-term and     Jacob Meerman&#13;
study on Pakistan.                   long-term growth.                    A methodologically novel study of&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Pres,   the household distribution of public&#13;
World ank Stff Woring Paer No. 1977,18 page (Incldliqlservices in relation to incomes. The&#13;
Wo4 ArldBnStfWoknPaeN. 1977. 158 pages (including pedLe,bblorpi)          study examines public spending for&#13;
454. April 1981. 596 pages (Including    . peies bibo   gr )education, medical care, agriculture,&#13;
Stock No. WP-0454. $15.00.           LC 76-53909. ISBN 0-8018-1950-4,     public utilities, and welfare transfers&#13;
$5.50 (0.25) paperback.              and the use of these services by&#13;
households.&#13;
NEW                              Patterns in Household                Oxford University Press, 1979. 404&#13;
Demand and Saving                    pages (including map, bibliography,&#13;
Labor Productivity: IJn Tour         Constantino Lluch, Alan A.           Index).&#13;
d"lorizon                            Pwl,adRsA            Atlam           LC 79-1122. ISBN 0-19-520096-9,&#13;
Suisan Horton and                    Pwell, aondtribtoss A.t Williams,    $27.50 4.7.25) hardcover;&#13;
Timothyzon                           with contributions bKn  Roger R      ISBN 0-19-520097-7, $12.50 (3.25)&#13;
Betancourt, Howard*Howe,             paperback.&#13;
This study surveys the state of      and Philip Musgrove&#13;
knowledge and the research available&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Rural Enterprise and                Trends in Rural Savings and         LC 79-16384. ISBNl 0-19-520098-5,&#13;
Nionfarm Employment                 Private Capital Formation           $20.00 (i6.25) hardcouer;&#13;
Dennis Anderson and                 In India                            ISBNl 0-19-520099-3, $9.95 (2.25)&#13;
Mark Leiserson                      Raj Krishna and                     paperback.&#13;
Examines the importance of rural    G.S. Raychaudhuri&#13;
nonfarm activities as a source of   World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  Women in the Urban Labor&#13;
employment and Income for the       382. April 1980. 43 pages (including  Markets of Africa: The&#13;
poorest groups of the world's       2 tables, 3 appendixes, references).  Case of Tanzania&#13;
A World pank Paper. January 1978. 87  Stock Plo. WP-0382. $3.00.         Nwanganga Shields&#13;
pages (including 25 annexes). English,                                   World Bank Staff Working Paper Nlo.&#13;
French, and Spanish.                Unskilied Labor for                 380. April 1980. 136 pages (including&#13;
Stock NYos. PP-7802-E, PP-7802-F,   Development:                        5 appendixes).&#13;
PP-7802-S. $5.00.                   Its Economic Cost                   Stock Plo. WP-0380. $5.00.&#13;
Orville John McDiarrnid&#13;
Size of Land Holding, Living        Estimates the economic cost of      REPRINS&#13;
Standards and Employment            unskilled labor by examining market  Income Distribution Effects of Techni-&#13;
in Rural Western India,             conditions that cause a significant  cal Changes Some Analytical Issues&#13;
spread between economic and         Hans R Blnswanger&#13;
1L972-73                            market wages.                       World Bank Reprint Series: fumber 212.&#13;
Pravin Visaria            ~~~~The Johns Hlopkins Universityj Press.  Reprinted from South East Asian Economic&#13;
Analyzes the relationship between the  1977. 218 pages (including 5 appenS-  Scew, w. R1, no. 3 (fcemharg980.179-218.&#13;
size of land holding possessed by a  dixes, biblIography).              Stck No. RP-0212. Free of charge.&#13;
household and the household's level&#13;
of per capita expenditure in rural  LC 76-47398. ISBN1 0-8018-1938-5,   Intra Urban Location of Manufacturing&#13;
areas of Gujarat and Maharashtra    $14.00 (S8.50) hardcover,            Employment In Colombia&#13;
states of India from October 1972 to  ISBN6 0-8018-1949-0, $5.50 (f325)  Kyu Sik Lee&#13;
September 1973, on the basis of the  paperback.                          World Bank Reprint Series: Nlumber 195.&#13;
27th Round of the Indian Natlonal                                       Reprinted from Joumal of Urban Economics. ool.&#13;
Sample Survey.                                                          9 (1981):222-41.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper Nlo.  The Urban Labor Market             Stock No. RP-0195. Free of charge.&#13;
459. May 1981.1 7 pages (including  aid Income Distrlbution:&#13;
statistical appendix).              A Study of Malaysia                  Technological Change, Distributive&#13;
statistical appendix).  ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~' of  3'S ~Blas, and Labor Transfer In a Two-&#13;
Stock Plo. WP-0459. $5.00.          Dipak Mazumdar                       Sector Economy&#13;
An Integrated analysis of differences  Ume Lele and John W. Mellor&#13;
In Income among urban households,   World Bank Reprint Series: Number 205.&#13;
NEW                              the determinants of employment      Reprinted from Oxford Economic Papers, uol. 33.&#13;
rates of household members, and     no. 3 (November 1981):426-41.&#13;
Some Aspects of Relative            the major factors affecting personal  Stock No. RP-0205. Pree of charge.&#13;
Poverty in Sri Lanka,                    Unisi&#13;
1969-70                             Oxford Uniuersiy Press, 19U.&#13;
Pravin Visaria                      392 pages (Including Index).&#13;
The major flndings of an Intensive  LC 80-24413. ISBNY 0-19-520213-9,&#13;
analysis of the data collected In the  $26.00 hardcouer; ISBNI 0-19-520214-7,&#13;
Socioeconomic Survey of Sri Lanka   $9.95 paperback.&#13;
from November 1969 to October 1970&#13;
are presented. Highlights the Impor-&#13;
tance of the criteria used to rank  Ulho Beneflts from Gover-&#13;
households (per capita vs. total    ment Expenditure? A Case&#13;
household expenditure or income) for  Study of Colombia&#13;
the estimates of the level of Inequal-  Marcelo Selowsky&#13;
Ity as well as for the measures of&#13;
elasticity of demand and for different  Clearly identifles which Income&#13;
categories of consumption Items.    groups beneflt from public expendi-&#13;
tures and attempts to separate the&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  factors behind the supply of and&#13;
461. May 1981. xil + 242 pages (Includ-  demand for a public service as a&#13;
Ing 5 annexes).                     means of understanding the present&#13;
Stock No. WP-0461. $10.00.          pattern of consumption.&#13;
Oxford University Press, 1979. 202&#13;
pages (Including statistical appendix,&#13;
bibliography, Index).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBIICATIONS&#13;
ORDER FORM&#13;
SEND TO:&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS                                                          WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
P.O. BOX 37525                                              or                   66, AVENUE D'IENA&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013                                                           75116 PARIS, FRANCE&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Narne:&#13;
Address:&#13;
Stock or ISBN #                             Author, Title                         Qty.        Price          Total&#13;
Sub-Total Cost: ____&#13;
Postage &amp; handling fee for m-ore than two free items ($1.00 each):&#13;
Total copies: ______        Air mail surcharge ($2.00 each):&#13;
TOTAL PAYMENT ENCLOSED:_____&#13;
M/ake checks payable: WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
Prepayment on orders from indJividuals is requested. Purchase orders are accepted from booksellers, library suppliers, libraries, and institutions.&#13;
All prices include cost of postaige by the least expensive means. The prices and publication dates quoted in this Catalog are subject to change&#13;
without notice.&#13;
No refunds will be given for items that cannot be filled. Credit will be aipplied towards future orders.&#13;
No more than two free publications will be provided without charge. Requests for additional copies will be filled at a charge of US $1 00 per&#13;
copy to cover handling and postage costs.&#13;
Airmail delivery will require a prepayment of US $2.00 per copy.&#13;
Mail-order payment to the World Bank need not be in U.S. dollars, but the amount remitted must be at the rate of exchange on the day the&#13;
order is placed. The World Bank will also accept Unesco coupons.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
ORDER FORM&#13;
SEND TO:&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS                                                          WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
RO. BOX 37525                                               or                   66, AVENUE D'IENA&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013                                                           75116 PARIS, FRANCE&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Name:&#13;
Address:&#13;
Stock or ISBN #                             Author, Title                         Oty         Price          Total&#13;
Sub-Total Cost &#13;
Postage &amp; handling fee for' more than two free items ($1.00 each):&#13;
Total copies:   _   ___     Air mail surcharge ($2.00 each):&#13;
TOTAL PAYMENT ENCLOSED:_____&#13;
Make checks payable: WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
Prepayment on orders from individuals is requested. Purchase orders are accepted from booksellers, library suppliers, libraries, and institutions.&#13;
All prices include cost of postage by the least expensive means. The prices and publication dates quoted in this Catalog are subject to change&#13;
without notice.&#13;
No refunds will be giveni for items that cannot be filled. Credit will bEi applied towards future orders.&#13;
No more than two free publications will be provided without charge. Flequests for additional copies will be filled at a charge of US $1.00 per&#13;
copy to cover handling and postage costs.&#13;
Airmail delivery will require a prepayment of US $2.00 per copy.&#13;
Mail-order payment to the World Bank need not be in U.S. dollars, blut the amount remitted must be at the rate of exchange on the day the&#13;
order is placed. The World Bank will also accept Unesco coupons.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PUB HG3881.5 .W57 W67&#13;
no.587-590 v.1&#13;
Serageldin, Isniail, 1944-&#13;
Tools for manpower planning&#13;
the World Bank models /&#13;
PUB HG3881.5.W57 W67 no.587-590&#13;
v.1&#13;
Serageldin, Ismail, 1944-&#13;
Tools for manpower planning&#13;
the World Bank models /&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters:                                                                                     U&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORI_DBANK&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK&#13;
Cable address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
European Office:&#13;
66, avenue d'lena&#13;
75116 Paris, France&#13;
Telephone: (1) 723-54.21&#13;
Telex: 842-620628&#13;
Tokyo Office:&#13;
Kokusai Building&#13;
1-1, Marunouchi 3-chorne&#13;
Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telephone: (03) 214-500:1&#13;
Telex: 781-26838&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0181-0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554857">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/05/1554857/tools-manpower-planning-world-bank-models-technical-presentation-models-volume
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/05/1554857/tools-manpower-planning-world-bank-models-technical-presentation-models-volume</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1983/05/1554857/tools-manpower-planning-world-bank-models-technical-presentation-models-volume</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/01/08/000178830_98101903420045/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/01/08/000178830_98101903420045/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-01-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1983-05-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Tools for manpower planning : the World
            Bank models - technical presentation of the models - volume I
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper describes the manpower model
            which has been developed with the problems of both
            labor-importing and labor-exporting countries in mind. The
            principal applications for planners are to forecast manpower
            requirements for specific sectoral output targets, and to
            identify and isolate specific problems in the supply of
            manpower through simulation of flows of students and
            trainees through the education and training system in the
            light of such modifiable parameters as participation,
            repetition and dropout rates, and qualifications required to
            enter programs. It also allows setting specific targets
            through an allocation submodel, and it can be used to
            estimate possible production levels. The model consists of
            three interrelated simulation models that relate economic
            growth, education and training, labor force, unemployment,
            and the importation/exportation of labor. They are a
            country-specific model, an expanded country model, and an
            international labor migration model. User's guides to
            each model are available.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Tools for manpower planning : the World Bank
            models - technical presentation of the models - volume I
        </docna>
        <display_title>Tools for manpower planning : the
            World Bank models - technical presentation of the models -
            volume I</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1983/05/1554857/tools-manpower-planning-world-bank-models-technical-presentation-models-volume</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Geographical Information Systems,Labor Markets,Educational Technology and Distance Education,Health Economics &amp; Finance</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Education</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>SERAGELDIN, I.</author>
            <author>LI, B.</author>
            <author>EMP</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903420045</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Labor markets and employment</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 587</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Education</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Social Protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Manpower planning; Mathematical models;
            Simulation; Employment
            aggregate
            analysis,attractiveness,attrition,debt,dependency,economic
            activity,economic growth,Economics,equilibrium,Foreign
            labor,guides,imports,Labor Force,Labor Migration,labor
            supply,laborers,manpower,manpower planning,Manpower
            policy,Manpower Requirements,occupations,oil,policy
            decisions,productivity,productivity growth,simulation,social costs,suppliers,tradeoffs,unemployment
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP587</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teacher Professional Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Educational Technology and Distance Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Radio, Television Instruction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grade Structure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Promotion Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Student Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Distance Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education for the Knowledge Economy</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT and Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research and Development Commercialization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research and Innovation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Owned Enterprise Restructuring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative and Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Management and Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Employment and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Improving Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Market Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets, Job Creation and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teacher Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Education Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education and ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Research, Development and Innovation (RDI)</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprises</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>