<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP-573&#13;
Paraprofessionals in Rural Developmenlt&#13;
Issues in Field-level Staffing&#13;
for Agricultural Projects&#13;
Milton J. Esman&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 573&#13;
HD&#13;
141'   l&#13;
E8s9 &#13;
198' *** HD1417 .E84 1983 c2&#13;
c.2   Paraprofessionals in rural development issues in field-lev&#13;
XI _______SLC026922&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WIORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 573&#13;
Paraprofessionals in Rural Developmient&#13;
Issues in Field-level Staffing&#13;
for Agricultural Projects&#13;
Milton J. Esman&#13;
Property of&#13;
oljeots Policy Department Library&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright © 1983&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development / THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
First printing April 1983&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To&#13;
present the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has&#13;
not been prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal&#13;
printed texts, and the World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The&#13;
publication is supplied at a token charge to defray part of the cost of&#13;
manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to&#13;
any individual acting on their behalf. Any maps used have been prepared&#13;
solely for the convenience of the readers; the denominations used and the&#13;
boundaries shown do not imply, on the part of the World Bank and its affiliates,&#13;
any judgment on the legal status of any territory or any endorsement or&#13;
acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications is described in the Catalog of World&#13;
Bank Publications; the continuing research program of the Bank is outlined in&#13;
World Bank Research Program: Abstracts of Current Studies. Both booklets are&#13;
updated annually; the most recent edition of each is available without charge&#13;
from the Publications Distribution Unit of the Bank in Washington or from the&#13;
European Office of the Bank, 66, avenue d'Iena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Milton J. Esman, director of the Center for International Studies at Comell&#13;
University, is a consultant to the lbrid Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging In Publication Data&#13;
Esman, Milton J. (Milton Jacob), 1918-&#13;
Paraprofessionals in rural development.&#13;
(World Bank staff working paper ; no. 573)&#13;
Includes bibliographical references.&#13;
1. Underdeveloped areas--Agricultural development&#13;
projects--Mangaement. 2. Rural development projects--&#13;
Management.   3. Paraprofessionals in social service.&#13;
I. Title. II. Series.&#13;
H,D1417.E84  1983    338.118'0683           83-6706&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0180-2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ABSTRACT&#13;
The World Bank; and other international aid agencies have expeaded&#13;
their commitments in recent years to small-scale agriculture. The&#13;
sociological and instit:utional problems of implementing such projects have&#13;
tended to receive insufficient attention from donors or host governments.&#13;
This has been especially true of implementation at the field level. Tnere&#13;
are many opportunities to strengthen local institutions and improve the&#13;
quality and relevance of services by drawing on private enterprise,&#13;
voluntary organization; and associations of local farmers, as well as&#13;
improving the performance of government agencies. Many combinations are&#13;
available to strengthen local action capabilities.&#13;
The cost-effectiveness of agricultural projects can tbe increased&#13;
by innovations in the .ield level staffing of government agencies that&#13;
provide services to rural publics. It is at the point of contact between&#13;
field representatives of government agencies and local publics that&#13;
agricultural projects often break down. Instead of relying primarily on&#13;
inadequate numbers of relatively costly subprofessional civil servants,&#13;
governments should experiment with less formally trained and m,uch less&#13;
costly, local persons to extend the outreach of agricultural services to&#13;
groups that could otherwise not be served.&#13;
The World Bank has already begun to support projects that employ&#13;
"paraprofessional" staEf in such diverse fields as agricultural extension,&#13;
irrigation, livestock, and forestry development.    Drawing from such&#13;
projects and from much more extensive experience in health administration,&#13;
a number of institutional and sociological lessons emerge for improving&#13;
the cost-effectiveness- of paraprofessional staffing.&#13;
Such lessons include: 1) consultation with project beneficiaries&#13;
in the choice of paraprofessionals, 2) the employment of female&#13;
paraprofessionals to assist in the performance of farming roles normally&#13;
played by women, 3) preservice and frequent refresher training in&#13;
practical, job-related information and skills, and 4) reliable referral,&#13;
logistical, and supervisory support for paraprofessional staff.&#13;
Rural service centers can provide useful and convenient&#13;
facilities for the location of related experimentation, training and&#13;
support services. Certain changes in administrative procedures may be&#13;
required, including the redefinition of subprofessional roles and&#13;
appropriate retraining to emphasize supervisory functions and skills,&#13;
rather than the front-line provision of services which become increasingly&#13;
the responsibility of paraprofessionals.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Paraprofessionals selected by, compensated by, and accountable to&#13;
local organizations and associations of farmers (e.g., water users'&#13;
associations) can increase the relevance and cost-effectiveness of&#13;
services while enhancing local self-reliance.&#13;
In paying more attention to the sociological dimensions of&#13;
development, the Bank has begun to incorporate local organizations into&#13;
its project designs, but has not matched this interest with complementary&#13;
attention to field-level management and staffing problems. Donor agencies&#13;
can strengthen the field staffing of agricultural projects by sponsoring&#13;
training facilities and assisting with training materials and&#13;
methodologies and by building process monitoring into projects. The&#13;
latter should focus on local implementation, including the performance of&#13;
the specific combinations of field-staffing methods designed for the&#13;
project in question. Process monitoring facilitates organizational&#13;
learning and the incremental improvement of field operations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS&#13;
The author acknowledges with gratitude the kind and patient&#13;
assistance of the many members of the World Bank staff who shared with me&#13;
their detailed experience with agricultural projects and commented on&#13;
earlier versions of this paper.   These include Michael Cernea, who&#13;
organized the Bank sociological workshop for which this paper was written,&#13;
Pierre Landell-Mills, Peter Nottidge, Donald C. Pickering, James Hendry,&#13;
David Steeds, John Cleave, John Russel, John Malone and Bernard Woods.&#13;
At the Cornell Center for International Studies, Norman Uphoff&#13;
and Virginia Haufler provided valuable assistance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Page&#13;
Abstract&#13;
I.     STAFFING AND PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION .....        ..................  1&#13;
II,     THE NEGLECT OF FIELD-LEVEL STAFFING .....         ..................  7&#13;
III.      PATTERNS OF F'IELD-LEVEL STAFFING ......      .................... L3&#13;
IV.     WORLD BANK EXPERIENCE WITH FIELD-LEVEL STAFFING&#13;
IN AGRICULT'URAL PROJECTS.                                    18&#13;
1. Service Delivery .19&#13;
2. Education.                                              20&#13;
3.   Denmonstrating and Testing Innovations.               21&#13;
4. Group Organization .21&#13;
5. Regulation .23&#13;
6. Ancillary Tasks .24&#13;
V.      PROBLEMS IN THE EMPLOYMENT AND MANAGEMENT OF&#13;
FIELD PERSONNEL .    ......................................... 29&#13;
A.   Status and Compensation .......       ....................... 29&#13;
B.   Selection Criteria and Methods .....        .................. 31&#13;
C.   Traininp ......g....................................... 33&#13;
D.   Supervision and Organizational Support ....       ........... 36&#13;
E.   Designing and Redesigning Jobs .....        .................. 38&#13;
F.   Community Relations .........      ......................... 40&#13;
G.   Financing and Comparative Costs .....        ................. 41&#13;
VI.      CONCLUSIONS AND RECOMMENDATIONS ......       ...................... 44&#13;
NOTES      .       .................................................... 53&#13;
APPENDIX A - World Batik Assisted Projects Reviewed in this Study ... 55&#13;
Chart 1.   Field Tasks and Field Agents ...................... I ....... 28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I.       STAFFING AND PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION&#13;
The purpose of this inquiry is to examine feasible and&#13;
cost-effective ways to handle field staffing in agricultural development&#13;
projects. Field staff effectiveness is paramount for accomplishing the&#13;
social changes envisaged by rural development projects. Most agricultural&#13;
projects assisted by the World Bank in recent years are designed to&#13;
enhance the productivity, employment opportunities, and incomes of&#13;
small-scale cultivators; and pastoralists. Achieving these goals requires&#13;
improvements in the quality, relevance, reliability, and access of farmers&#13;
to such services and resources as extension information, credit,&#13;
production inputs, processing, and marketing. Some of these agricultural&#13;
support services and resources can be provided through private sector&#13;
channels and some by the initiatives of organized farmers, but much of the&#13;
responsibility must be assumed by governments and their bureaucratic&#13;
agencies.&#13;
The principal task of contacting rural people and delivering&#13;
these services falls on the field staffs of government agencies. These&#13;
field staffs are often insufficient in number to maintain effective&#13;
contact with all the families they are expected to serve. All too often&#13;
these technicians are indifferently trained, inadequately equipped, poorly&#13;
paid, and undermotivated.   Condemned to dead-end jobs in rural areas, they&#13;
are far removed from the sophisticated planners and high-level civil&#13;
servants in capital cities who negotiate foreign assistance projects on&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
behalf of their governments. Yet the success of agricultural projects in&#13;
which governments and foreign donors invest scarce financial and&#13;
administrative resources depends, in large measure, on tne performance of&#13;
these field staffs.&#13;
Agricultural projects, especially those oriented to small and&#13;
marginal farmers, are especially sensitive to the quality of implementation.&#13;
In addition to making services accessible to their intended beneficiaries,&#13;
project managers must ensure that such services are, in fact, accepted and&#13;
used by the farmers. Most of the services provided in agricultural projects&#13;
require some changes in their behavior. Farmers cannot be compelled, but must&#13;
be induced and convinced that new or allegedly improved services, resources or&#13;
techniques will actually benefit them and that the changes required in such&#13;
areas as cultivation methods, water management, or marketing procedures are&#13;
worth the costs and the risks to them of accepting the changes. It is the&#13;
field staffs of the agricultural service agencies on whom governments and&#13;
donors must rely not only to deliver new or improved services, but also to&#13;
persuade farmers to accept them and to work with farmers to adapt them to&#13;
specific local conditions.&#13;
The World Bank's commitment to agricultural and rural development&#13;
projects has escalated more than tenfold in current dollar terms during the&#13;
past two decades, from an annual lending level of less than $400 million in&#13;
the early 1960s to more than $3 billion in FY82. Government financial&#13;
commitments for agricultural services have also increased considerably in many&#13;
countries. This has imposed enormous burdens on the hard-pressed budgets of&#13;
developing countries, especially for the recurrent costs of field personnel&#13;
whose numbers have increased in order to staff new and expanded agricultural&#13;
activities. As numbers expand, governments in many cases have been unable to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
maintain the quality of agricultural field staff, whose training, technical&#13;
capacities and communication skills were in any case quite modest. The high&#13;
costs and indifferent performance of field personnel have induced some&#13;
governments to consider several measures to relieve the financial burden,&#13;
while continuing to expand needed services at acceptable levels of perfonnance&#13;
to less advantaged rural producers.&#13;
Three such measures are: 1) to entrust the provision of some&#13;
services, especially the supply of inputs and marketing of products, to&#13;
networks of private commercial dealers; 2) to engage locally resident, low&#13;
cost, non-civil service persons, an innovation we designate as&#13;
"paraprofessional," to perform a variety of service delivery and associated&#13;
functions; and 3) to induce local groups of farmers or village communities to&#13;
assume greater responsibility for the acquisition, provision and management of&#13;
agricultural and rural development services.&#13;
These methods dc, not imply that governments can or should eliminate&#13;
services, but, rather that more cost-effective ways can be found to implement&#13;
the goals of increasing productivity and generating employment for the small&#13;
cultivators, who will continue to constitute rural majorities in most low&#13;
income countries.&#13;
The purpose of this paper is to explore management methods that can&#13;
increase the cost-effectiveness of government and donor investments and&#13;
expenditures in small-scale agriculture through innovative staffing patterns.&#13;
It is part of the conventional wisdom that development projects tend&#13;
to be well designed, but unfortunately, are often poorly implemented. This is&#13;
a convenient myth to explain away the neglect of sociological, administrative&#13;
and institutional feasibility analysis during the preparation and appraisal of&#13;
projects. That projects which directly affect the interests and require&#13;
changes in behavior among farmers can be competently designed in the absence&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
of any consultation with the farmers concerned or with their representatives -&#13;
for most agricultural development projects are in fact designed top down&#13;
without such consultation or involvement - is an interesting question which&#13;
need not detail us here; but that many such projects are, in fact, poorly&#13;
implemented is supported by massive testimony of knowledgeable observers.&#13;
The details of implementation that are so frequently overlooked in&#13;
project design include many that involve action on the ground -- logistics,&#13;
financial procedures, schedules, and especially staffing. Often project&#13;
designers, having dealt with the major issues of finance, technology,&#13;
organizational placement, and estimated benefits, assume that such operational&#13;
details as field-level staffing do not require the time and attention of&#13;
senior officials of donor agencies or governments and can be worked out by&#13;
subordinate managers at a later date. Unfortunately, the neglect of&#13;
implementation planning at the design stage often contributes to project&#13;
failure because the administrative assumptions in the design are not spelled&#13;
out and the envisaged social change proves to be operationally unfeasible; and&#13;
when they are feasible in principle, they are often botched by casual or&#13;
indifferent attention to field-level management.&#13;
Non-performance and poor performance of field personnel are often&#13;
cited as deficiencies in project implementation. Yet this is not an&#13;
irremediable problem. The performance of field staffs can be upgraded and&#13;
their outreach can be extended by good personnel management practices&#13;
supplemented by staffing innovations that have already been developed and&#13;
tested in several projects, including some sponsored by the World Bank. These&#13;
staffing innovations using local, non-civil service personnel or&#13;
paraprofessionals do involve additional operating or recurrent costs for aid&#13;
donor and financially hard-pressed governments. But these costs are modest&#13;
compared with the costs of normal civil service staffing. Moreover, in many&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 5 -&#13;
cases the provision of services can be shared with private sector networks and&#13;
with project beneficiaries at considerable saving to government and at no cost&#13;
in effectiveness or efficiency. Field-level staffing and related metnods of&#13;
service delivery are an important dimension of institutional development and&#13;
social change at the grass roots. It is one of those "software" components of&#13;
project implementation that has been neglected in many foreign-assistance&#13;
activities by governments and donors alike.&#13;
Prior to the preparation of this paper, a monograph was produced by&#13;
the writer and several associates at Cornell on Paraprofessionals in Rural&#13;
Development. 1/ This monograph reviewed the state-of-the-art in the use of&#13;
indigenous, non-civil service personnel to expand the outreach of government&#13;
agencies in rural areas and to improve the quality of their interactions and&#13;
exchanges with local publics. Though most of the published data dealt with&#13;
community health workers, experiments were identified which app'Ly this&#13;
innovation in other sectors, including agriculture and forestry. *&#13;
Because of the possibility that the paraprofessional method could be&#13;
useful for World Bank sponsored agricultural projects, the writer was invited&#13;
to examine Bank projects which included this innovation.    More rhan twenty&#13;
such projects were identified and reviewed; the term "paraprofessional" was&#13;
not used in Bank documents, but the roles were there. These projects are&#13;
listed in Appendix A.&#13;
*   Those interested in more factual field information than can be&#13;
incorporated in the present paper, may find it in four volumes of country&#13;
case studies on patterns and experiences of paraprofessionaL's work (Sri&#13;
Lanka, the Philippines, Senegal and Upper Volta) published in the Cornell&#13;
University "Special Series on Paraprofessionals."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6-&#13;
In the course of interviews with World Bank personnel, it became&#13;
evident that paraprofessionals could most adequately be treated as part of the&#13;
broader problem of field staffing in tne implementation of agricultural&#13;
projects. Though specific data from the Bank's experience are drawn from&#13;
projects that employ paraprofessionals, the projects reviewed by this author&#13;
represent only a small fraction of Bank-supported agricultural projects. My&#13;
more general observations came from interviews with Bank officials, my&#13;
previous study of parc-rofessional activities, and many years as a participant&#13;
observer of rural development and development administration in various&#13;
countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
II.      THE NEGLECT OF FIELD-LEVEL STAFFING&#13;
One of the leasr: satisfactory elements in development projects are&#13;
the field-level bureaucr;ats directly in touch with members of the public for&#13;
whose benefit services are designed and provided. This neglect is&#13;
particularly evident in the literature on the agricultural and rural sectors&#13;
in developing countries. 2/ It reflects lack of interest and low priority by&#13;
governments and development assistance agencies.&#13;
The consequence is that members of the field staffs of government&#13;
bureaucracies working in agriculturally-related activities tend to be&#13;
undertrained, burdened with more tasks than they can handle, poorly&#13;
supervised, under-supplied with the information and the supplies they need to&#13;
assist their clients, poorly compensated and consequently ill-motivated.&#13;
Because they, as well as their publics, know that they cannot perform&#13;
satisfactorily they often protect themselves by avoiding contact, by setting&#13;
up or enforcing complex paper routines, and by confining themselves in their&#13;
offices. Often their numbers are insufficient to serve more than a smaLl&#13;
percentage of the farmers and farm families in their nominal area of&#13;
responsibility. Consequently, their services cannot be effective; they&#13;
resolve this dilemma by confining their efforts to a small number of the&#13;
better endowed, more "progressive" fanaers or to those near the larger&#13;
settlements who are easiest to reach. 3/&#13;
Yet the effecti'veness of most agricultural projects, especially those&#13;
oriented to the majority of rural people who are smallholders, depends on&#13;
their ability to reach i:hese large and often dispersed publics with&#13;
information and other services which can help them increase their productivity&#13;
and raises their incomes. Project goals can seldom be achievecl by occasional&#13;
and superficial contact because they require the innovation or adoption of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
unfamiliar farming practices, which entail risks to resource constrained&#13;
farmers, the consequences of which cannot be predicted in advance. The need&#13;
is for continuing service and for two-way communication so that needs,&#13;
innovations, and responses can flow steadily from farmers to government&#13;
agencies and vice versa.&#13;
Most developing country governments are not yet equipped to provide&#13;
services to their rural publics in this mode. Agency headquarters tend to be&#13;
well equipped and staffed with capable and qualified personnel. At provincial&#13;
headquarters the quality of staff and equipment is quite respectable. But the&#13;
closer one approached tne field where services must actually be delivered, the&#13;
less qualifird and the more poorly equipped and motivated are the staff who&#13;
bear the ultimate burden of interacting with farmers, the point at whicn&#13;
projects pay off or fail. The rapid expansion of agricultural services, often&#13;
prompted by the resources made available through aid agencies, has multiplied&#13;
the presence in the field of poorly equipped and ineffective staff.&#13;
In general policy statements and analyses of development problems,&#13;
World Bank documents and staff recognize the importance of field-level&#13;
staffing. 4/ The Rural Development Sector Policy Paper of February 1975&#13;
devoted a page and a half to this topic, and dealt at similar length with tne&#13;
closely related subject of local participation. 5/ The 1980 World Development&#13;
Report emphasizes the same themes:&#13;
"Improving administration at the periphery is far more complex and&#13;
difficult than administrative reform at the center, a task that has&#13;
itself often proved intractable. Many of the poor are hard to reach&#13;
through conventional public programs, and the end-of-the-line workers&#13;
may not be motivated to break the social, linguistic and physical&#13;
barriers that separate them from the poor. Supply lines for&#13;
textbooks or medicine may be continually breaking down, and the&#13;
necessary technical support may be lacking. But these and similar&#13;
difficulties must be overcome to reach the poor; that usually means&#13;
improving organization at the grass roots." 6/&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
In a sociological analysis of Bank assisted projects, (ernea has&#13;
called attention to the need for systematically building farmers,'&#13;
organizations at the grass-roots level and for:&#13;
"practical methodologies for carrying it out; of a social&#13;
technology for building farmers groups.. .National&#13;
governments and international technical agencies are not&#13;
geared toward such an orientation and individual&#13;
'development experts' from an outside international agency&#13;
cannot change that situation by themselves; moreover, in&#13;
many cases those experts are not equipped with systemat:ic&#13;
expertise about this side of the development effort.. .This&#13;
lack of personnel exists primarily at the project level.." 7/&#13;
Despite growing recognition of these issues in Bank policy&#13;
statements and studies, a review of on-going projects indicates a lag in&#13;
the application of these concepts to concrete country projects.&#13;
Institutional analyses in project appraisal reports tend to be ifragmentary&#13;
and to focus on the senior staffs of ministries, departments or project&#13;
organizations, often passing over lightly the networks of operat:ing&#13;
personnel at the grass roots level. The implicit assumption, springing&#13;
from conventional organization theory, is that if senior personnel are&#13;
technically and managerially well qualified and highly motivated, they&#13;
will ensure that staffing and the details of staff performance lhroughout&#13;
the organization are adequate to their tasks. Senior staff are expected&#13;
to install logistical supervisory and information systems that provide the&#13;
intended outputs and ensure quality control. Field-level staffing is&#13;
often treated as a residual concern that will somehow be taken care of at&#13;
a subsequent time by medium-level managers.&#13;
Given what is known about pluralism among and within bureaucratic&#13;
agencies and the political dimensions of administrative behavior,&#13;
especially in rural areas, this command model is simply not a valid basis&#13;
for project design. The legitimate concern of Bank staff and of member&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
governments to limit the recurrent costs of projects, especially of&#13;
projects that are necessarily labor-intensive, is sometimes cited as&#13;
another reason for evading the problems of field-staffing.&#13;
The effectiveness of agricultural development projects largely&#13;
depends on the interaction at the boundary between the government's&#13;
bureaucratic agencies and the publics they are intended to serve. This is&#13;
partly a question of numbers, but more than numbers is involved. Project&#13;
effectiveness also depends on the training, equipment, attitudes, morale&#13;
and supervision of field staffs, the system of incentives and rewards&#13;
under which they operate, and their behavior toward the publics they&#13;
encounter. Since farmers can seldom be compelled but must usually be&#13;
induced to accept advice or services from government agents, the latter&#13;
need negotiating and political, as well as technical skills. Such&#13;
concerns are little evident in the Bank's project documentation,&#13;
especially in appraisal reports, despite their importance to project&#13;
success.&#13;
The principal exceptions to these observations are the Bank&#13;
sponsored T and V Extension projects which are explicitly concerned with&#13;
organization, staffing and supervision at the field level. Whatever else&#13;
may be said about this still evolving system, these seem to be among the&#13;
first of the Bank's agricultural projects that specifically and&#13;
systematically address field-staffing and the nexus between government&#13;
personnel and their publics. 8/&#13;
Institutional changes and specific improvements at the grass&#13;
roots are often difficult because they depend in some measure on&#13;
government-wide processes - on national level personnel systems, on&#13;
general financial procedures, on ministry level procurements systems, and&#13;
on methods of supervision that are determined in capital cities. A common&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
prescription, therefore, is to begin by reforming government-wide&#13;
administrative systems on the premise that the center determines what can&#13;
happen at the periphery.&#13;
Three decades of experience with efforts at government-wide&#13;
administrative reforms have demonstrated, however, that such efforts&#13;
encounter stubborn vesited interests and that even when government-wide&#13;
reforms are formally adopted they are very slow to be carried out and are&#13;
often blocked in the interstices of bureaucracy before they ever reach the&#13;
field.  While field-level reforms may be inhibited by government-wide&#13;
administrative and managerial procedures and by associated bureaucratic&#13;
interest groups, experi'ence had demonstrated that there are usually&#13;
degrees of freedom for specific improvements in project operations in the&#13;
field, especially if these improvements are initially promoted and&#13;
encouraged by donor agerncies. Administrative entrepreneurship can often&#13;
be evoked at project and program levels, even in spite of government-wiae&#13;
procedures. Indeed thet pressure of project needs and demonstrated success&#13;
of innovations at the field level can provide further leverage for more&#13;
comprehensive ministry-wide and government-wide reforms.&#13;
While the Bank is now contemplating more attention to&#13;
government-wide reforms and there may be circumstances when this indeed is&#13;
the most effective strategic point of entry, many more improvements in&#13;
methods of implementation and in institutional development have been&#13;
induced in specific project and program contexts than in efforts at&#13;
system-wide reform. There is no reason to believe that improvements in&#13;
field-level staffing and in related institutional developments should not&#13;
be attempted in conjunction with specific agricultural projects. If they&#13;
can be combined with macro-level reforms, so much the better, but the main&#13;
focus should continue to be on those specific, incremental changes that&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
are needed and appear to be feasible to make particular projects and&#13;
programs function more effectively and at acceptable costs. The&#13;
field-level capabilities that must be tapped and encouraged should not,&#13;
however, be confined to bureaucratic personnel. They should also allow&#13;
greater scope for activity and responsibility by non-governmental groups&#13;
including the beneficiary publics themselves.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
III.     PATTERNS OF FIELD-LEVEL STAFFING&#13;
There are three main methods for the staffing of field services and&#13;
all of them are evident in agricultural activities. Within each method there&#13;
are distinctive variations, some of which will be identified and discussed in&#13;
this paper.&#13;
Method one involves the use of subprofessional staff in direct&#13;
contact with members of the public. Method two employs agency&#13;
paraprofessionals responsible to a government department as links between the&#13;
subprofessional and the public. Method three draws on members of local&#13;
organizations, community paraprofessionals, to perform locally required&#13;
services and link the local organizations of farmers with the subprofessional&#13;
representative of the government agency. We shall outline each of these&#13;
methods.&#13;
Before discussing the common methods of field staffing, reference&#13;
should be made to the role of agricultural professionals in providing services&#13;
to rural households. It is unlikely that fully qualified profe3sionals -&#13;
agronomists, veterinarians, plant scientists and others with university&#13;
degrees or their equivalent and the status that these confer - will be widely&#13;
present on the ground in direct contact with local farmers and their&#13;
families. They are seldom in evidence, except as members of training or&#13;
supervisory cadres. They are usually too expensive and too few in number to&#13;
be used for direct service, especially to small farmers; the social and&#13;
cognitive distance between them and uneducated, low-status farmers is often so&#13;
great as to inhibit effective communication and cooperation; and most of them&#13;
refuse to live and work in rural communities. Except in training, supervisory&#13;
and occasionally group organizational roles, full fledged professionals do not&#13;
constitute a significant component of field-level staffing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
Subprofessionals&#13;
Service delivery and public contact are usually the functions of&#13;
subprofessionals. These are men (occasionally women) who are graduates of&#13;
secondary schools and of two- or three-year technical institutes or colleges.&#13;
Normally they are full-time and pensionable public functionaries, members of a&#13;
state bureaucracy with the status and perquisites of civil servants. They&#13;
receive technical and usually managerial guidance from, and are accountable&#13;
to, professional members of the same department or agency.&#13;
The conventional and most common pattern of service delivery (method&#13;
1) involves the subprofessional, e.g., the agricultural assistant, veterinary&#13;
assistant, or cooperative officer, in direct contact with members of the&#13;
public. These contacts can be on a one-to-one basis, though usually the&#13;
staff-client ratios in smallholder areas makes this impossible or infrequent&#13;
and necessarily superficial.   Otherwise, contact occurs with and through&#13;
organized groups of farmers and their families, a topic that will be explored&#13;
later in this paper.&#13;
Paraprofessionals&#13;
As defined by the Cornell research team, paraprofessionals are&#13;
persons indigenous to the service area with limited formal schooling and&#13;
limited pre-service training; while they may be part of an organized public or&#13;
voluntary agency, they do not enjoy the status or the perquisites of civil&#13;
servants; they are in direct contact with the public, they often work&#13;
part-time, and their compensation, if any, is usually quite modest. 9/&#13;
The paraprofessional method relies on indigenous people to be&#13;
intermediaries between the subprofessional civil servant and members of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
the public. Though they- have been in evidence for many years,&#13;
paraprofessionals represent an underutilized resource in many agricultural and&#13;
other rural development projects. As the last link in the state's&#13;
bureaucratic structure, the agency paraprofessional (method 2) extends the&#13;
outreach of the government agency so that through him or her it can maintain&#13;
direct and more intensive contact with a much larger number of farmers and&#13;
their families than would be possible for the much more costly&#13;
subprofessional. The paraprofessional works under the guidance and&#13;
supervision of the subprofessional. His access to the information and&#13;
resources of the government agency is usually through this channel. The&#13;
objective of the paraprofessional system is to extend the range of public&#13;
services in a cost-effective way. The main risk is that the quality of&#13;
service may be attenuated by the limited skills and knowledge of the&#13;
paraprofessional. For this reason, as we shall see, the paraprofessional role&#13;
can usually be effective only if it is supported by reliable training,&#13;
supervisory, and logistical arrangements.&#13;
Agency paraprofessionals can develop the relations with their publics&#13;
in two ways:  they can transact directly with individual farmers and members&#13;
of their families in the areas to which they are assigned; or they can work&#13;
with and through formal or informal organizations of their publics, such as&#13;
farmers' organizations, water users' associations, cooperatives., or credit&#13;
unions.&#13;
In the latter case, the paraprofessional may have to help activate or&#13;
even form these organizations and be responsive to their group interests, if&#13;
he or she is to benefit from their ability to "retail" information and&#13;
services to their members or to mobilize local resources on behalf of the&#13;
project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
Where groups of farmers are reasonably well organized, they are able&#13;
to provide a number of services for themselves through their collective&#13;
resources or by mutual assistance. Usually, however, these organizations of&#13;
small farmers cannot be entirely self-reliant; they lack some of the skills or&#13;
information required to manage their affairs or to transact with government&#13;
agencies or private firms on which they depend for needed resources. Instead&#13;
of depending on paraprofessionals responsible to a government agency, the&#13;
community paraprofessional (method 3) is selected by and accountable directly&#13;
to the local organization to which he or she belongs and to its members. The&#13;
government agency must usually help to train and enhance the skills of the&#13;
local organization's paraprofessionals and provide them with other&#13;
back-stopping services. Private voluntary organizations are often useful&#13;
intermediaries in support of community paraprofessionals. The important&#13;
distinction is that the community paraprofessionals are responsible and&#13;
accountable to their neighbors, not to a bureaucratic agency.&#13;
To sum up, these are the three basic patterns of local-level&#13;
staffing: (1) the subprofessional civil service technician in direct contact&#13;
with the public; (2) the combination subprofessional-agency paraprofessional;&#13;
and (3) the community paraprofessional linking with the subprofessional.&#13;
There are, of course, numerous variations to these main patterns. One set of&#13;
examples are the T and V extension projects. There the village extension&#13;
worker (VEW) is clearly a subprofessional (technical training, civil service&#13;
status), a "professional extension worker" as defined by the Indian Ministry&#13;
of Agriculture and Cooperatives. 10/ The contact farmer is a pale but still&#13;
palpable embodiment of the agency paraprofessional. In the Bank-assisted&#13;
Indonesian 16th Irrigation Project, the project design provides for two levels&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
of paraprofessionals working under the guidance of subprofessionals: the "key&#13;
farmers" who are agency paraprofessionals, and the "water user association&#13;
representatives" who appear to be community paraprofessionals selected by WUA&#13;
members. A Bank-sponsored study of village drinking water systems identified&#13;
the need for "field assistants," a type of agency paraprofessional to&#13;
supervise local self-help construction activities, and for "local artisans,"&#13;
which would be a kind of community paraprofessionals in charge of handling&#13;
minor repair and maintenance tasks. 11/&#13;
Other combinations are certain to emerge and one useful. task for&#13;
future research is to identify more precisely the combinations cf field-level&#13;
staffing that are appropriate for different local service requirements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
IV.      WORLD BANK EXPERIENCE WITH FIELD-LEVEL STAFFING IN AGRICULTURAL&#13;
PROJECTS&#13;
The information available to me indicates that the World Bank&#13;
assisted projects have not usually attached high priority to this subject in&#13;
project design or implementation. This view was confirmed in a number of&#13;
interviews with Bank officials. It was reinforced by my review and analysis&#13;
of 20 or so project appraisal reports which were brought to my attention&#13;
because they included paraprofessionals.&#13;
The appraisal reports included in this rather small group of projects&#13;
were very thin in their discussion of field-level staffing, though one might&#13;
have expected projects that incorporate paraprofessionals to be especially&#13;
sensitive to this subject. The staff appraisal reports that were reviewed&#13;
seldom contained more than a few sentences on field-level staffing and the&#13;
same can be said for the project performance audit reports.&#13;
The written information was so fragmentary and incomplete that it is&#13;
often difficult to answer some of the more common and obvious questions about&#13;
staffing, practical questions which governments and donor agencies must&#13;
perforce deal with in the design and management of projects. Perhaps more&#13;
written documentation about field staffing is available than I was able to&#13;
locate, but my impression is that this subject has not been of great interest&#13;
to appraisal missions.&#13;
There appear to be four kinds of Bank-sponsored agricultural projects&#13;
in which field staffing has included paraprofessionals: livestock projects&#13;
employing paraveterinarians; social forestry activities using "motivators;"&#13;
irrigation projects involving ditch tenders and other local skills associated&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
with small water management units; and extension,the great majority of which&#13;
incorporate some version of the T and V system, and in which paraprofessional&#13;
roles are variously designated as contact farmers, farmer-foremen, promotors,&#13;
model farmers or demonstration farmers.&#13;
In its previous study on paraprofessionals, the CornelL report&#13;
identified a set of eight functions or activities in which paraprofessionals&#13;
participate. With minor modifications, these are common functions of&#13;
field-level staff in agricultural projects.   To what extent do field personnel&#13;
in Bank assisted projects become involved in these activities? The incomplete&#13;
data derived primarily from design documents indicate the main activities&#13;
which field staff are expected to perform, but seldom the proportion or&#13;
relative weight of such activities:&#13;
1.   Service delivery - This covers the provision of physical resources,&#13;
technical information, or managerial skills that were not previously&#13;
present and might not otherwise be available to local farmers. All&#13;
the projects examined in this survey provided some incremental&#13;
services to their publics. The most common was information on&#13;
improved cropping practices (T and V system), but they range from&#13;
drugs for the treatment of animal diseases to feed supplements,&#13;
credit, fertilizers, pesticides, storage and marketing facilities,&#13;
and the provision of seedlings. In small irrigation projects, the&#13;
community paraprofessionals are in such service roles as&#13;
ditchtenders, water masters and bookkeepers. Some services are&#13;
provided to particular groups; for example, the Benin Atacora P'roject&#13;
had a special component oriented to the needs of village women.,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
2.   Education - Paraprofessionals and other field-level personnel are&#13;
frequently involved in spreading information about improved practices&#13;
and new technologies. An authoritative review of 39 low-cost&#13;
AID-financed health projects indicated that 79X were involved in&#13;
community education 12/. Non-formal transfer of information is the&#13;
main activity of the village extension worker-contact farmer&#13;
combination in the T and V system. All T and V projects emphasize&#13;
practical information, including, in the several T and V projects in&#13;
India and the Nepal Hill Food Production Project, farm management&#13;
training. In all the projects in this sample, non-formal education&#13;
in the form of transfer of knowledge was a major component of the&#13;
subprofessional and the paraprofessional roles.&#13;
Information transfer is, of course, the most vulnerable role for&#13;
paraprofessionals because of their limited technical expertise. Yet&#13;
recent experiments, such as ICTA in Guatamala and the PNIA project in&#13;
Honduras reported by Whyte, indicate that ordinary small farmers have&#13;
much useful local information to contribute to the improvement of&#13;
farming practices in their distinctive micro environments and that&#13;
their representatives (community paraprofessionals) can be useful&#13;
bridges between their fellow farmers and agricultural scientists.&#13;
13/ The experience of the Comilla project yielded similar results.&#13;
The paraprofessionals need scientific support and some training in&#13;
communication skills; with these resources they can be effective as&#13;
two-way commnunicators of useful, practical information.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
3.   Demonstrating and :esting innovations - This activity is closely&#13;
associated with non-formal education. It can be considered one&#13;
method of informat-ion transfer, the main activity of model. farmers,&#13;
contact farmers and their counterparts in livestock management.    The&#13;
implicit premise i3 that useful innovations are exogenous to the&#13;
local society and rhe objective is to secure new "adoptiorLs" of&#13;
improvements developed by scientists at their experiment stations.&#13;
If, however, innovations are to be syntheses of exogenous science and&#13;
local, often site-specific, knowledge based on the experience of&#13;
local farmers, the latter would have to be accorded a more positive&#13;
role in the research and development function than is permitted now.&#13;
Even the feedback of results from a system of prescribing and&#13;
communicating information to be demonstrated and tested by local&#13;
field staff and taken up by local farmers, when and if it actually&#13;
occurs through bureaucratic channels, cannot substitute for the&#13;
participation of local farmers in suggesting improvements rather than&#13;
merely responding to those proposed and demonstrated by others.&#13;
4.   Group organization - The data available suggest that in about&#13;
two-thirds of the cases, including all the T and V projects, an&#13;
important activity of field agents is to work with and through&#13;
existing communities or functional groups or to help to organize&#13;
members of the public into new associations to stimulate mutual&#13;
assistance and to facilitate relations with government agencies.&#13;
This involves bringing rural people together, either an entire&#13;
village or a particular segment, so that they may better take&#13;
advantage of avai).able services, participate in their management,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
and mobilize labor, information and local skills that constitute&#13;
their contribution to the project 14/.&#13;
Many ongoing Bank-assisted agricultural projects suggest that&#13;
community or group organization is probably the most difficult,&#13;
sophisticated, and proactive of all the roles assigned to project&#13;
field staff, including paraprofessionals. This role often involves&#13;
the choice between tapping existing informal networks and sponsoring&#13;
the establishment of new organizations. In the Bank-assisted Ulla&#13;
Ulla Development Project in Bolivia, the paraprofessionals were&#13;
expected to work primarily with already organized campesino groups.&#13;
Conversely, in other Bank-assisted projects, like the Benin Atacora,&#13;
Mali-sud, and Niger-Dosso projects, the paraprofessional personnel&#13;
financed under the project are required also to form new associations&#13;
among the beneficiaries. In the recently Bank-approved Communal&#13;
Irrigation Project in the Philippines, the organization of local&#13;
water users' associations is assigned to what the project calls&#13;
"community organizers," working under the guidance of professional&#13;
social scientists, because of what were considered the sophisticated&#13;
skills required for that task. The community organizers are required&#13;
to live and work full-time in the village; the physical construction&#13;
or rehabilitation of irrigation works is not to begin until the&#13;
community organizations are formed and functioning.&#13;
A few Bank-financed projects follow the Comilla model of the&#13;
early 1960s, sponsoring local organizations which then select members&#13;
to be trained and assisted by government field agencies to perform&#13;
part-time roles as community paraprofessionals under&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
the control of, and accountable to, the local organization 15/.&#13;
Among such projects are the Ethiopian Minimum Package Program 2, and&#13;
the Indonesian Sixteenth Irrigation Project.&#13;
A study carried out by Michael Cernea found that, during the&#13;
reviewed fiscal year, about 40% of Bank-sponsored agricultural&#13;
projects included some form of local organization and farmier&#13;
participation 16/. It appears that this orientation is due more to&#13;
the practical judgment of Bank staff than to explicit conceptual or&#13;
policy support for this approach.&#13;
There seems, however, to have been far less concern asnd support&#13;
for project staffing in support of local organizations.    This is a&#13;
serious oversight because local organizations cannot entirely&#13;
substitute for fieLd-level staffing, though they may reduce the need&#13;
for large numbers of government technicians. It is the right&#13;
combinations of government staff and local organizations that&#13;
facilitate more productive small-scale farming and it is futile to&#13;
attempt to rely on local initiative and responsibility without&#13;
explicit concern for the proper numbers and quality of government&#13;
support staff.&#13;
Because our sample of reviewed projects emphasized&#13;
paraprofessionals, it is likely that community organization&#13;
activities found in these projects reflect a higher proportion of&#13;
responsibility given to field personnel than in the total universe of&#13;
Bank-sponsored agricultural projects.&#13;
Regulation - There are a few examples of regulatory activities among&#13;
our cases, includirng forest protection and controlling access to&#13;
water in irrigation projects. The literature on field staff in&#13;
agricultural projects emphasizes the burden of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
regulatory tasks and the time and energy they drain away from service&#13;
activities. These regulatory duties range from gun licensing to the&#13;
collection of overdue loans and the enforcement of animal disease&#13;
controls. Many of them are necessary functions which have to be&#13;
performed by someone, though paraprofessionals are seldom used for&#13;
such purposes. One of the objectives of the Bank-assisted T and V&#13;
extension projects is to relieve extension agents of the panoply of&#13;
ancillary tasks, including regulatory activities, that have so often&#13;
been inflicted on them simply because they happen to be in the field&#13;
and are available. The inevitable effect, however, is to shift these&#13;
regulatory tasks to other government functionaries.&#13;
The borderline between service and regulatory activities is not&#13;
always clear, for example, in the control of plant diseases. Though&#13;
regulatory activities are not prominent in our sample of projects, no&#13;
summary of the activities of field personnel would be complete&#13;
without mentioning their role in regulation and enforcement.&#13;
6.   Ancillary tasks - Previous analysis of the activities of&#13;
paraprofessionals disclosed a number of tasks which they and other&#13;
field-level workers perform. Since they did not emerge prominently&#13;
in the limited number of Bank projects reviewed for this paper, they&#13;
will be collapsed into a single category and mentioned only briefly.&#13;
They include:&#13;
a)   The acquisition of goods and services for local publics from&#13;
sources outside the community or outside the government agency&#13;
itself. In this respect the field agent becomes an&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
advocate or expediter, helping farmers to tap resources that&#13;
would otherwise be unavailable. Since programs frequently lack&#13;
effective and reliable supply lines, field agents must often&#13;
exert pres3sure on their own organization (or on others) to&#13;
provide resources, such as credit, vaccines, fertilizers or&#13;
storage facilities when and where they are needed.&#13;
b)   When problems arise, for example, an unfamiliar plant disease&#13;
which the field staff cannot deal with, he refers the problem to&#13;
specialists who provide answers or visit the locality in order&#13;
to examine and apply their more specialized skills and&#13;
experience to a problem which is beyond the capacity of local&#13;
personnel. The referral process is built into the T and V&#13;
system, linking field level staff with subject matter&#13;
specialists and research centers. Because of their limited&#13;
technical skills, paraprofessionals must have readily available&#13;
referral resources in order to maintain their effectiveness and&#13;
their local credibility. This applies as well to agency as to&#13;
community paraprofessionals.&#13;
c)   Field agents are often responsible for the distribution of&#13;
supplies and the maintenance of equipment. These functions&#13;
usually involve the closely related functions of detailed record&#13;
keeping ani reporting. While record keeping and reporting are&#13;
essential l.o the maintenance of accountability, their volume,&#13;
detail, and frequency generate one of the most conmon complaints&#13;
of field personnel, who argue that these routines often displace&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
their service and educational functions and keep them tied to&#13;
office routines. Yet failure to maintain meticulous control of&#13;
supplies and equipment and to submit reports on time may be more&#13;
costly to the employee's reputation and career than the neglect&#13;
of his service, educational and community organization tasks.&#13;
To overcome this perverse bias will require changes in job&#13;
definitions and in the incentive and reward systems governing&#13;
field staff -- a topic to which we shall return.&#13;
d)   Because they are conveniently located in rural settlements in&#13;
direct contact with rural publics, paraprofessionals and other&#13;
field agents are often used to collect and transmit field-level&#13;
data, including data of little relevance to their operating&#13;
responsibilities. One of the explicit objectives of the T and V&#13;
system was to relieve extension personnel of these distracting&#13;
tasks. Agricultural staff may be required to observe, measure,&#13;
and report on a variety of subjects ranging from routine crop&#13;
reporting to early warnings of plant or animal diseases, the&#13;
results of innovations in cultivation practices, or water levels&#13;
in irrigation channels. The collection, preliminary analysis,&#13;
and transmission of such data may be vital to the ability of&#13;
government agencies to insure timely interventions.&#13;
Paraprofessionals are well situated to collect field data at&#13;
relatively low cost. Project designers and managers must,&#13;
however, ensure that these duties do not compromise their basic&#13;
operational responsibilities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
As a rough guide to project designers from governments and&#13;
donor agencies and to appraisal missions, the mai:rix that&#13;
follows summarizes available experience concerning the kinds of&#13;
tasks that can most suitably be committed to different&#13;
categories of field personnel in agricultural projects oriented&#13;
to the needs of small farmers. It assumes that project&#13;
designers are free to select the most appropriate category of&#13;
field staff for the task at hand, that a major concern is with&#13;
cost-effectiveness, and that the political climate tolerates the&#13;
activities of local farmer organizations.&#13;
While a single chart such as this oversimplifies the&#13;
realities of specific projects in specific environments, it is&#13;
suggestive of the range and combinations of choices available to&#13;
project designers. Except at the level of the ir,dividual&#13;
project, t:here is no one best way to staff field activities.&#13;
This matriix includes both the private sector and private&#13;
voluntary agencies as possible resources available to project&#13;
designers,, along with the aforementioned government and&#13;
quasi-government personnel.&#13;
We have circled those activities in which it appears that a&#13;
particular method may have a marked advantage over others. A&#13;
task for future research is to identify more precisely which&#13;
method is likely to be most useful (cost effective) for which&#13;
kinds of specific project tasks under alternative political and&#13;
social environments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CHART 1. FIELD TASKS AND FIELD AGENTS&#13;
Agents                                                      Commun-&#13;
Sub-          Aaency            ity                          Private&#13;
Profes-           Profes-       Paraprofes-     Paraprofes-       Private       Voluntary&#13;
Activities          sionals           sionals         sionals         sionals          Sector      Organizations&#13;
Service&#13;
Provision                               x               x               x               x               x&#13;
Information                              x               x               x                               x&#13;
3roup&#13;
Organization         G                  x               x               x                               D&#13;
Regulation                               @&#13;
Demonstrating&#13;
Innovations                             x               x&#13;
kcquisition of&#13;
goods and&#13;
services                                                x               x               x               x&#13;
Distribution&#13;
of supplies                             x                               x               x               x&#13;
Referrals                                x               x               x&#13;
Recordkeeping                            x                               x&#13;
Collection of&#13;
field data                              x               x&#13;
Supervision,&#13;
training, and&#13;
guidance of&#13;
field staff                             x                                                               x&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
V. PROBLEMS IN THE EMPLOYMENT AND MANAGEMENT OF FIELD PERSONNEL&#13;
Though the Bank staff appraisal and project performance audit reports&#13;
contain little detailed information about field-level staff, certain specific&#13;
bits of information, combined with what is known from previous research about&#13;
employment practices at this level, permit a number of general observations.&#13;
A.   Status an,d Compensation&#13;
Subprofessional workers are normally part of the state bureaucracy,&#13;
full-time, salaried and pensionable civil servants. Their salaries tend to be&#13;
much lower than professionals, but much higher than the annual incomes of most&#13;
of the farmers they serve. They have job and income security, medical&#13;
benefits and retirement rights. Because they represent a major recurrent&#13;
burden on hard-pressed government budgets, it is important that their numbers&#13;
be limited and that they be assigned to tasks which cannot be equally well&#13;
performed by much less costly paraprofessionals, local organizations, or the&#13;
private sector.&#13;
The structure of subprofessional employment often provides few&#13;
prospects for promotion or career development, since professional posts are&#13;
restricted to persons with the requisite professional (formal.) education. The&#13;
deleterious effects of dead-end positions on morale and on performance can De&#13;
relieved by establishing subprofessional career lines that reward good&#13;
performance but do not require professional education. When this expedient is&#13;
limited, the subprofessional salary range should be elongated. in order to&#13;
allow satisfactory performance to be rewarded by periodic salary increases&#13;
throughout a full career. Non-material incentives, including opportunities&#13;
for refresher training and job enrichment (training in new skills and&#13;
procedures), can help to sustain employee interest and morale.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
The working conditions and status of paraprofessionals are quite&#13;
variable. They may be part-time (contact farmers) or full-time&#13;
(para-veterinarians in the Eastern Senegal Livestock Development Project);&#13;
unsalaried, except for inputs used in demonstrations (T and V contact farmers)&#13;
or compensated by stipends or honorariums (West Bengal Social Forestry&#13;
"motivators") or by sales of inputs (drugs in the Niger Livestock Project).&#13;
Paraprofessionals do not enjoy the status, security, perquisites,&#13;
regular salaries or retirement prospects of civil servants. Though extensions&#13;
of bureaucratic agencies, agency paraprofessionals are not themselves&#13;
bureaucrats; the resultant flexibility, much lower costs, and wider outreach&#13;
are an important part of the case for using paraprofessionals and for limiting&#13;
the growth of less cost-effective subprofessional cadres. Some agency&#13;
paraprofessionals, however, begin to aspire to civil service status as a&#13;
reward for faithful service so that they can participate in the job security,&#13;
pension rights, and career advancement available to civil servants. But since&#13;
they are locally based and part-time, a stipend or hororarium plus local&#13;
prestige usually constitutes sufficient material reward for their service.&#13;
The source of salary or honorariums is usually the government,&#13;
invariably for subprofessionals and normally for agency paraprofessionals.&#13;
The local group or community may be asked to make contributions in kind or in&#13;
profits from the sale of goods and services to provide some compensation for&#13;
paraprofessionals. Where subprofessional staff are employed by local&#13;
organizations (e.g., Farmer's Associations in Taiwan) tney are paid by the&#13;
local organization. Similarly, honoraria for persons serving as community&#13;
paraprofessional in such projects as the water users' associations in the&#13;
Philippines are expected to be contributed by the local organization. In the&#13;
Bank-sponsored Mali-sud cotton marketing project, field staff are selected by,&#13;
responsible to, and compensated by the associations of local growers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
B.   Selection Criteria and Methods&#13;
Subprofessionals are usually selected on the basis of educational&#13;
attainment, depending on the general educational levels of the country.&#13;
Though a large number of farming activities are carried out by women,&#13;
agricultural subprofessionals are usually men. Political patronage, ethnic&#13;
affinity, and kinship connections often influence access to such positions,&#13;
including entrance to the schools that provide the required credientials. They&#13;
are chosen by competitive examination, enrolled for two or three years in a&#13;
technical training institute and then employed by the Ministry ot Agriculture&#13;
or a parastatal agency and assigned to the field. Usually, they are&#13;
indigenous to the area in that they speak the local language or dialect and&#13;
understand local conditions, but this is not invariably the case. Members of&#13;
the local public have no voice in the selection of subprofessional civil&#13;
servants. They are considered agents of the state, not of the local community.&#13;
Since paraprofessionals must be able to work compatibly with local&#13;
publics and are always indigenous people, local communities are sometimes&#13;
consulted in their selection. Those consulted may be local officials or&#13;
traditional chiefs, less often the entire community. Most observers agree&#13;
that the effectiveness oE agency paraprofessionals depends on an active role&#13;
by the local community in their selection. Project beneficiaries must have&#13;
confidence in the persons who serve them. Since local communities are often&#13;
socially stratified, government agencies should attempt to insure that the&#13;
consultations includes a broad spectrum of the publics with whom the&#13;
paraprofessional will work 17/. In fragmented communities it may be necessary&#13;
to engage a separate paraprofessional for each segment of a seriously divided&#13;
local population.&#13;
Where the community pays, or the paraprofessionals are accountable to&#13;
a local organization, as in the case of the Peasant Associations in Ethiopia,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
the latter select the paraprofessionals from their own ranks. The choice of&#13;
most agency paraprofessionals, including the T and V contact farmers, is made&#13;
by government staff, usually the subprofessional under whose direction they&#13;
will work.&#13;
Age and literacy are seldom critical limiting criteria in the&#13;
selection of paraprofessionals, but permanent local residence is greatly to be&#13;
preferred. The important factors are motivation for service and the respect&#13;
of neighbors. In some circumstances and for some tasks illiteracy is no bar&#13;
to a person who is otherwise well equipped. A middle-age person or couple who&#13;
are permanently identified with a community may command local confidence more&#13;
than a better educated but less compatible young man or woman, though the&#13;
required training period may be longer.&#13;
The factor of gender deserves more attention that it usually&#13;
receives. Since a large proportion of farm work is done by women and the&#13;
customs of some societies preclude or seriously inhibit extra familial contact&#13;
between men and women, there is a strong case for preferring women in many&#13;
paraprofessional roles, especially when they are aiding or assisting in&#13;
farming activities usually performed by women. When the subprofessional civil&#13;
servants are men, as is usually the case, there is a specially strong need for&#13;
inducting women into paraprofessional roles 18/.&#13;
In the T and V system an effort is made to find a "representative"&#13;
farmer, not the most progressive and certainly not an inefficient cultivator,&#13;
but one who is respected and can be imitated. The T and V approach seems to&#13;
suggest sometimes a rotation of contact farmers; length of tenure is not dealt&#13;
with in other Bank project documents. The question of tenure and rotation of&#13;
paraprofessionals is one on which there is little agreement even in the&#13;
community health field where there has been considerable experience in the&#13;
employment of paraprofessionals. Paraprofessionals gain useful experience by&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
long tenure on the job, but periodic rotation spreads both responsibility and&#13;
access to useful skills. In some projects the agency paraprofessional may&#13;
remain on the job for -many years, while the community paraprofessionals who&#13;
also represent local leadership may rotate more frequently.&#13;
C.   Training&#13;
Subprofessionals are formally trained before being post:ed. Often&#13;
their training is purely technical; they are deficient in communications and&#13;
political skills, in understanding the dynamics of peasant society and how to&#13;
interact with resource-constrained small farmers, their organizations, and&#13;
especially rural women. These deficiencies in training help to account for&#13;
frequently observed awkwardness and mistakes in relating to rural publics and&#13;
for insisting on the enforcement of rigid rules rather than responding to the&#13;
changing needs of small farmers. Once they graduate from their technical&#13;
institute their knowledge may not be reinforced or kept up-to-date, so that&#13;
they are increasingly lunable to respond to the problems of their publics. One&#13;
of the main objectives of the T and V and similar arrangements is to insure&#13;
that the technical information and communication skills of the&#13;
subprofessionals are continuously reinforced and developed by training&#13;
sessions every two weelcs. Outside the T and V projects, Bank documentation is&#13;
silent on the problem of maintaining and upgrading the skills of-&#13;
subprofessional staff.&#13;
Training avai'Lable to paraprofessionals varies widely. The Cornell&#13;
survey indicated that paraprofessionals tend to be undertrained and that&#13;
in-service training is the greatest deficiency. The contact farmers receive&#13;
no formal training but their information comes from regular visits by&#13;
subprofessionals and o:casional visits by subject matter specialists. In the&#13;
Eastern Senegal Livestock Project, the first group of trained&#13;
paraprofessionals are expected, in turn, to train others. The Bank's&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
contribution to the Philippine community irrigation project is, inter alia, to&#13;
support training facilities for community paraprofessionals. This is also a&#13;
critical factor in the Community Forestry Development Project in Korea.&#13;
The Cornell report on paraprofessionals emphasizes the importance of&#13;
providing not only pre-entry training to inculcate basic technical and&#13;
communications skills, but also periodic reinforcement. The emphasis, of&#13;
course, should be on practical job-related information and problem-solving&#13;
skills. The paraprofessional job should be broken down into specific&#13;
technical and communications tasks and the curriculum should focus on these&#13;
tasks and skills, especially those directly pertinent to the local area.&#13;
Standard syllabi should, if available, be specifically adapted to the local&#13;
situation. It is also important that trainers understand, preferaDly by&#13;
first-hand experience, the actual setting in which the paraprofessional will&#13;
be working in order to provide a more relevant learning experience. As the&#13;
Cornell report indicates:&#13;
The intent of such curriculum development is to break down the&#13;
paraprofessional role into its most basic components and to&#13;
train accordingly. This also insures that the paraprofessional&#13;
role is clearly defined; appropriate training cannot be&#13;
developed without clarifying what the paraprofessional is to do,&#13;
how and what resources are necessary to accomplish these&#13;
tasks...Simplifying the training curriculum in this manner means&#13;
that paraprofessionals with limited formal education can more&#13;
easily assimilate the needed knowledge and skills. Tasks are&#13;
portrayed by a series of steps which can be accomplished by&#13;
relatively inexperienced workers. Furthermore, the&#13;
paraprofessional is trained in a fashion which is directly&#13;
transferable to the work setting, combining pedagogic techniques&#13;
with technical training. By using simple words and basic&#13;
concepts in training programs the paraprofessionals will find it&#13;
easier to teach others in a like fashion as there is a minimal&#13;
discrepancy between what is learned in the training sessions and&#13;
what is to be performed in the work setting. For example, local&#13;
food stuffs not urban purchased foods should be used in teaching&#13;
nutrition education; paraprofessionals should be taught with the&#13;
same visual aids they will in turn employ on the job;&#13;
agricultural techniques should be relearned using actual tools&#13;
and supplies in the field setting; the local language, not a&#13;
cosmopolitan language should be used in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
training sessions. Experience shows that the most successful training is&#13;
that which trains the paraprofessionals in the same methods and language&#13;
which the paraprofessional will subsequently use on the job. The Lardin&#13;
Gabas project in Nigeria trains its health workers through parables, drama&#13;
and songs, which th-e workers in turn use in conveying health messages in&#13;
their villages. 19/&#13;
Because their publics are aware of their limited education, the&#13;
self-confidence, credibility and effectiveness of paraprofessionals depend&#13;
entirely on demonstrated access to specialized information (and often&#13;
resources) and on skills not available to their neighbors. There are many&#13;
ways to provide practical training of this kind, but the experience of&#13;
many programs is that paraprofessionals, after limited initial training,&#13;
are put out into the field where in the absence of follow-up training,&#13;
their information, skills and eventually their effectiveness gradually&#13;
dissipate. Projects which employ paraprofessionals must be prepared to&#13;
invest in their continuing education and in the upgrading and renewal of&#13;
their information and their skills either on the job or in classroom&#13;
situatiouis. Put differently, it is far better to put fewer staff in the&#13;
field and to invest adequately in their continuing training than to&#13;
over-expand field staff without providing for adequate renewal of their&#13;
skills.&#13;
One method for the continuing renewal of paraprofessional&#13;
information and skills is through regional agricultural training centers,&#13;
similar to those provide,l in the Nepal Hill Food Production Project.&#13;
Paraprofessionals can repair to such centers on a scheduled basis to&#13;
refresh their information. The center can serve as a primary referral&#13;
point for unresolved fieLd problems and as the focus for visiting&#13;
specialists and researchers to impart information and to learn about&#13;
problems encountered in the field. Following the Comilla experience, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
regional agricultural service center can become the point of continuing&#13;
exchanges of information and of ongoing training for field personnel,&#13;
including community leaders. Donor agencies can contribute to the&#13;
establishment of facilities and the development of improved training&#13;
methodologies, following the example in the 16th Indonesian Irrigation&#13;
Project. The regional center thus becomes the core of the agricultural&#13;
development infrastructre in the field. Local communities can be expected to&#13;
take responsibility for the maintenance of these basic facilities of which&#13;
they are the beneficiaries, while government provides the professional and&#13;
subprofessional staff.&#13;
D.   Supervision and Organizational Support&#13;
Field staff, whether subprofessional or paraprofessional, are at the&#13;
periphery of state bureaucratic organizations which are directed by&#13;
hierarchical lines of command from urban centers. Frequently, the operational&#13;
needs of field staff are not among the priorities of departmental&#13;
headquarters, whose information systems do not bring such problems and needs&#13;
to the center's attention in time. Research stations often fail to work on&#13;
problems of priority concern to the field; credit and production inputs are&#13;
not received when they are needed, - thus demoralizing field staff and&#13;
undermining their credibility with farmers. The classical report is of field&#13;
personnel with nothing useful to extend, immobilized in their offices because&#13;
of the failure of headquarters to provide the gasoline or spare parts they&#13;
need to travel out to visit their clients. Rigid expenditure controls and&#13;
procurement systems contribute to the inadequate logistical support which&#13;
compromises the effectiveness of field staff.&#13;
The World Bank many years ago adopted the practice of setting up&#13;
special project units to manage Bank-supported activities, one objective&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
of which was to circumvent some of these common deficiencies of public&#13;
administration in host countries, only to find that the disease spreads&#13;
rapidly to special project units as well. It is now recognized that creating&#13;
project management units as "enclaves," strong at top and weak at bottom,&#13;
without an overall institution building effort, has been an error, which the&#13;
Bank is now attempting to avoid.&#13;
One of the main virtues of the T and V extension projects is that&#13;
they build in systematic and regular supervisory, informational and research&#13;
support for field-level extension in sharp contrast with the heLplessness and&#13;
sense of abandonment that so often confront and undermine field staff&#13;
providing agricultural services 20/.&#13;
To make local staff more effective, field administration will have to&#13;
be toned up, service-by-service. This is a problem that should be explicitly&#13;
provided for at the stages of project design and project appraisal. If the&#13;
necessary administrative infrastructure and backstopping cannot be provided,&#13;
the project is ipso facto defective; it fails the test of managerial&#13;
feasibility and should be abandoned or redesigned. The burden on public&#13;
administration can often be shared for some tasks with the private sector; for&#13;
others, with private voluntary organizations; for others, with ]ocal&#13;
membership organizations. But a basic structure must be provided for the&#13;
reliable flow and controL of supplies and equipment and the provision of&#13;
useful information. And supervisors must be available to field personnel to&#13;
ensure the intended and responsible use of government resources and, more&#13;
importantly, to provide i.or technical and managerial reenforcement for&#13;
modestly trained persons who cannot be expected to function entirely on their&#13;
own.&#13;
How to build and strengthen this institutional infrastructure will&#13;
depend on a prior assessment of the administrative resources available to each&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
program of activity. This assessment will have to be sustained during&#13;
implementation by process monitoring which should be a standard element in all&#13;
agricultural projects, for it permits organizational learning and timely&#13;
responses to unanticipated problems. These concerns with institutional&#13;
development should address not only the attitudes, skills, incentives, rewards&#13;
and performance of field personnel, but also the capacity and willingness of&#13;
senior staff to take field operations seriously and to provide the logistical&#13;
and supervisory support that local staff urgently require 21/. One dimension&#13;
of institutional development may involve such structural and procedural&#13;
reforms as the substantial delegation of decision-making authority and power&#13;
to act to field staffs to enable them to meet local needs in a timely way and&#13;
adjust general rules to local requirement.&#13;
E.   Designing and Redesigning Jobs&#13;
When paraprofessionals are employed their tasks must be specially&#13;
designed to take account of their limited formal training and skills and to&#13;
take advantage of their continuous presence in local communities and their&#13;
ability to empathize with the problems of their neighbors. They cannot be&#13;
expected to replicate the skills, knowledge, and tasks of full-time and&#13;
trained subprofessionals. They can keep records of the progress of field&#13;
trials, identify and prescribe for common pathologies, but they cannot be&#13;
expected to recommend new pesticides on their own. They can be trained to&#13;
perform routine vaccinations of cattle, but not to diagnose diseases -- though&#13;
they can facilitate referral. This calls for the specific design of tasks for&#13;
which paraprofessionals can be specially trained, in effect for job&#13;
simplification. Experience with health programs indicates that&#13;
paraprofessionals trained in simple skills can handle 85-90% of local health&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
problems without the need for external referral.    Training experiences must&#13;
emphasize the specific skills required for their tasks so that they can be&#13;
performed convincingly, but opportunities should also be available for&#13;
paraprofessionals to enlarge the scope of their services as they demonstrate&#13;
greater capacity.&#13;
The tasks of subprofessional civil servants must be redesigned to&#13;
emphasize less the direct provision of services - for which most: of thetn are&#13;
originally trained - and more the supervision and support of agency and&#13;
community paraprofessionals as the latter assume greater responsibility for&#13;
direct contact and front-line services to farmers and their families. As&#13;
suggested in paragraph D above, subprofessionals must acquire the basic&#13;
managerial skills needed to backstop field services as paraprofessionals&#13;
penetrate more deeply into rural areas. Thus the introduction and use of&#13;
paraprofessionals have implications for the design of all field-level jobs and&#13;
for management structures and procedures. These must be taken into account in&#13;
the formulation of agricultural projects.&#13;
In T and V projects, contact farmers are limited to the closely&#13;
related tasks of education and demonstration. The Mali-sud project, in&#13;
contrast, imposes a variety of tasks on its polyvalent paraprofessionals,&#13;
including extension, credit, inputs, marketing, and group organization. There&#13;
are considerable degrees of freedom in designing paraprofessional roles, but&#13;
since paraprofessional recruits have limited education and formal training, it&#13;
is dangerous to impose too many responsibilities on them. The Cornell study&#13;
indicated that paraprofessionals should begin with one or very few basic&#13;
tasks; these can be expanded as the original tasks are mastered. Training&#13;
activities must be directly synchronized with the expansion of job content.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
F.   Community Relations&#13;
In conventional administrative theory the administrative agent&#13;
normally relates to individual members of the public. Circumstances in rural&#13;
areas of most countries in which the Bank operates make this an unlikely&#13;
prospect, given the limited budgetary resources of governments and the large&#13;
number of households to be served, especially among small and marginal&#13;
farmers. Moreover, local communities and functional groups represent a vast&#13;
resource for the self-provision of services and for multiplying the&#13;
effectiveness of those provided by government. Therefore, one of the most&#13;
interesting and potentially productive areas of sociological research and&#13;
experimentation are local associations of rural people, formal and informal,&#13;
and the means by which they can relate with government agencies, while&#13;
providing many elements of service to their members through mutual assistance&#13;
and collective effort. The small sample of cases available for this review&#13;
and analysis substantiates the data cited by Cernea (see footnote 7) that Bank&#13;
staff have begun to recognize and experiment with this potential resource.&#13;
These efforts range from the rather amorphous groups with which the T and V&#13;
contact farmers work, to the pastoralist associations in the Eastern Livestock&#13;
Development Project and the more formal Water Users' Associations in&#13;
Indonesia, Peasant Associations in Ethiopia, and Village Associations in&#13;
Mali-sud.&#13;
In several projects, including the Philippine Communal Irrigation&#13;
Project and the Benin Atacora Province Rural Development Project the field&#13;
staff is expected to organize farmer groups. Frequently, this task requires a&#13;
degree of sophistication that is beyond the capacity of most field staff&#13;
unless they are specially trained for that task. In the Philippine Communal&#13;
Irrigation Project and the Gal Oya project (not Bank supported) in Sri Lanka,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
specially trained professional-level personnel were engaged to help farmers&#13;
form local associations and to initiate the processes of mutual assistance and&#13;
of interaction with government agencies. Private voluntary organizations,&#13;
where they are available, have proved to be effective at community&#13;
organization because of the patient commitment of their members to the welfare&#13;
of disadvantaged people and the flexibility available to them in their&#13;
operations.&#13;
Bank-supported agricultural projects might attempt, in cooperation&#13;
with governments, to identify PVOs, domestic or international, that might be&#13;
willing to become involved in working with local publics to help build and&#13;
strengthen their organizations for self help and for interacting more&#13;
effectively with government agencies.&#13;
As the 3ank and other international donors begin to tap the latent&#13;
resources of community and group organization, they should bear in mind that&#13;
even when such groups are available they cannot operate with complete autonomy&#13;
from sources of information, production inputs and market channels. They need&#13;
the support and assistance of government agencies; similarly government&#13;
agencies operate more efficiently if they are supported by active&#13;
organizations of the users of their services. Thus, in projects that foster&#13;
local organizations, it is important to include adminstrative procedures and&#13;
personnel skills, incentives, and rewards that enhance the compatibility and&#13;
the mutual dependence of government field staff and local organizations of&#13;
rural people.&#13;
G.   Financing and Comparative Costs&#13;
There are no hard data on the comparative costs of paraprofessional&#13;
versus subprofessional methods of field staffing. My rough estimate is that&#13;
five to seven agency patraprofessionals can usually be fielded at the same&#13;
overall cost as one subprofessional civil servant. The substantial savings in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
salary and fringe benefits costs are, however,significantly offset by the&#13;
higher training, supervisory and monitoring costs required for effective field&#13;
operations that rely heavily on paraprofessionals. In last instance, the main&#13;
benefits of paraprofessional staffing are:&#13;
1.   The much more intensive outreach, and coverage of rural&#13;
publics than would otherwise be possible;&#13;
2.   The employment of persons with greater ability to&#13;
appreciate and respond to the needs of the groups they&#13;
serve; and&#13;
3.   Especially in the case of community paraprofessionals, the&#13;
activation of local responsibility and self help.&#13;
The financial case for paraprofessional staffing can probably not&#13;
be made in absolute cost terms, but rather in terms of&#13;
cost-effectiveness. The latter can be realized only through greater&#13;
attention to local institutional development and the details of better&#13;
project management. The question of comparative costs of alternative&#13;
methods of field staffing is a prime candidate for future research.&#13;
The desperate budget crises encountered by so many developing&#13;
countries during the current period of international economic stagnation&#13;
confront governments and donors with a specially difficult problem.&#13;
Unfortunately, the shift in donor priorities to agricultural projects that&#13;
emphasize productivity and employment among small holders has occurred at&#13;
the same time that the budgets of host countries are under very great&#13;
stress. To maintain even the present inadequate scale of rural public&#13;
services may be difficult, for often the first items to be reduced are the&#13;
material and transportation resources which enable field personnel to&#13;
reach and serve their publics. While the employment of agency and&#13;
especially of community paraprofessionals in support of small-scale&#13;
farming is likely to be a cost-effective measure, it does entail some&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
incremental costs to government budgets. Donors, including the World Bank,&#13;
should be prepared to finance for extended periods these incremental local&#13;
currency expenditures, if they believe that the benefits of the project in&#13;
productivity, incomes, or employment justify the increased locaL costs in tne&#13;
first place. Otherwise these projects may falter or never be irnplemented&#13;
because of budgetary shortfalls and the inability of governments to shift&#13;
their financial priorities rapidly enough to agriculture and rural development.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
VI. CONCLUSIONS AND RECOMMENDATIONS&#13;
This survey of field-level staffing in agricultural projects, drawing&#13;
on World Bank experience, has touched on some, but by no means all the&#13;
problems of field administration. Omitted, for example, have been the need to&#13;
decentralize to the field greater authority to act and the related problem of&#13;
field-level coordination among specialized bureaucratic agencies, subjects&#13;
that require a separate paper 22/.&#13;
Our point of departure was paraprofessionals -- an innovation in&#13;
field administration that seeks to extend at relatively low cost the effective&#13;
coverage of public services to rural people who could not otherwise be&#13;
reached. We found that the functional equivalent of the agency&#13;
paraprofessional as the last link in the bureaucratic chain is the community&#13;
paraprofessional - a member of a local community selected by and accountable&#13;
to his neighbors. This suggests the many alternatives and options that are&#13;
available for field-level staffing of agricultural projects - beyond the&#13;
conventional subprofessional technicians - and opens up some of the larger&#13;
issues of how to provide effective and responsive agricultural services at&#13;
reasonable cost to rural publics.&#13;
That service to farmers at the field level, especially to the large&#13;
and important constituency of small and marginal farmers, is a weak link in&#13;
many agricultural development projects (even when physical infrastructure and&#13;
appropriate technologies are available) is recognized by knowledgeable&#13;
observers of rural development. It is at the nexus between the government&#13;
agency and its rural publics that agriculturally oriented delivery systems&#13;
frequently break down. Having been neglected by scholars, by governments and&#13;
by donor agencies, including the World Bank, this is a subject whose time may&#13;
finally have come. In the new emphasis on institution-building or&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
institutional development, both at the Bank and at USAID, attention is&#13;
focusing on strengthening field-level institutions, both the state's&#13;
bureaucratic structures and local organizations of small farmers and their&#13;
families. Included in this broad topic is the division and sharing of&#13;
responsibilities and taskcs between local farmer organizations, government&#13;
agencies, and private coimmercial networks in an effort to achieve more&#13;
effective "local action capabilities" 23/. Government-wide administrative&#13;
policies, practices and regulations that impinge on field operations will have&#13;
to be taken into account and modified where possible, but the main emphasis&#13;
should be on strengthening field-level capacities and on program-specific&#13;
incremental improvements that draw on all available organizatiorLal resources.&#13;
In this framework, field-level staffing is a primary ccomponent - the&#13;
selection, posting, training, support and management of personnel equipped and&#13;
motivated to provide responsive and timely services, often with and through&#13;
formal and informal organizations of local farmers. The term "bureaucratic&#13;
reorientation" has recently been coined to express the need for greatly&#13;
improved performance in field operations and the attention that must be&#13;
devoted to the details of staff performance by those in direct contact with&#13;
small farmers and their organizations 24/. As with most complex problems,&#13;
especially those that require changes in human behavior and in social&#13;
institutions, there can be no quick fixes in this area. Governtents will have&#13;
to be persuaded to attach higher priority to field operations than they have&#13;
been willing to in the past, if they expect to see progress in the&#13;
smallholders' sector. They may have to consider changes in operating&#13;
procedures that they have resisted, including the delegation to better trained&#13;
and better motivated field staff of greater authority to act so that more&#13;
timely accommodation can be made to specific local demands and needs of&#13;
farmers and their families.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
The Bank's experience with field-level staffing of agricultural&#13;
projects indicates that governments and international donors should devote&#13;
more attention to the details of project implementation. Without neglecting&#13;
implementation at the headquarters and intermediate levels of government, much&#13;
greater emphasis needs to be directed to the field, at the interface between&#13;
government agencies and the local users of services, both men and women, whom&#13;
projects are designed to help. The requirements of implementation should be&#13;
envisaged at the design stage of projects and assessed during the process of&#13;
project appraisal. That they can be left out at design stage, and somehow be&#13;
adequately taken care of during subsequent implementation is a myth, refuted&#13;
by three decades of experience.&#13;
The working assumption should be just the opposite: that without a&#13;
specific and detailed implementation plan the project will probably run into&#13;
trouble. This is especially true of the software elements of projects that&#13;
involve contact with, and social and behavioral change among, large numbers of&#13;
people. Do means exist for reaching these farmers with the services the&#13;
project will provide? Are there sufficient incentives to induce farmers to&#13;
use the services? Are the staff providing these services adequately equipped&#13;
and supported and attuned to the circumstances and capabilities of the&#13;
particular farmers whom they address?&#13;
The development of a detailed operational plan and the establishment&#13;
of a monitoring system to check on the processes of implementation as well as&#13;
on project outputs should be a required component of every Bank-sponsored&#13;
project design - a test of administrative and socio-cultural feasibility.&#13;
Process monitoring can provide the information that permits organizational&#13;
learning - timely adjustments to events that were unanticipated in operational&#13;
planning. This discipline can serve as an element of technical assistance to&#13;
governments, strengthening their institutional capacities to plan and carry&#13;
out future projects, whether or not they are supported by the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
Implementation plans must deal with questions of organization and&#13;
procedures, many of which are beyond the scope of this paper. On the vital&#13;
question of field-level staffing, much can be done by the national agencies.&#13;
as well as by international aid and technical assistance agencies, to promote&#13;
the cost-effectiveness in the management of agricultural projects. The&#13;
following propositions should be taken into account in assessing provisions&#13;
for the field-level staffing of agricultural projects:&#13;
1.   Governments are unlikely to be able to afford to provide agricultural&#13;
services to the mass of small and marginal farmers and pastoralists&#13;
through full-time, fully trained, civil servants. In addition,&#13;
governments as well as the Bank or other aid agencies are&#13;
understandably concerned with limiting the recurrent costs of&#13;
projects.&#13;
2.   To control recurrent budget costs while expanding services that&#13;
enhance productivity and employment, project designers should draw on&#13;
all available local action capabilities, including private sector&#13;
commercial networks and local organizations of farmers. It is&#13;
especially important, as agricultural services expand, to limit the&#13;
employment and control the costs of conventional civil service&#13;
personnel, particularly subprofessional staff.&#13;
3.   Local paraprofessionals provide a means by which many services can be&#13;
extended at relatively low cost to rural publics. Such indigenous,&#13;
usually part-time people, may enjoy better rapport with local&#13;
cultivators, be better informed of local needs and capabilities, and&#13;
be more effective for many roles (as indicated in Chart: 1) than&#13;
full-time, relatively expensive civil service staff, even if the&#13;
latter were available.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
a)   Whenever agricultural projects must reach large numbers&#13;
of small farmers, consideration should be given to including&#13;
paraprofessionals in the project.&#13;
b)   Paraprofessionals may be either unifunctional or polyvalent.&#13;
They should in any case start with a limited range of functions&#13;
which can be expanded after the initial tasks have been mastered.&#13;
c)   Jobs should be redesigned and simplified so that they can be&#13;
handled by relatively uneducated local paraprofessionals with&#13;
limited practical training.&#13;
d)   Normally, local communities and members of the affected publics&#13;
should be consulted and directly involved in the selection of&#13;
paraprofessional personnel.&#13;
e)   Since they are an important component of the agricultural work&#13;
force, women should be chosen for paraprofessional roles when&#13;
the principal publics are likely to be women.&#13;
f)   To be effective, paraprofessionals require practical,&#13;
job-related training, both in technical and communications&#13;
skills. This training must be periodically or continuously&#13;
reinforced. Facilities for preentry and in-service training&#13;
should be specifically incorporated into project design.&#13;
g)   Paraprofessionals also require supervision, support, and&#13;
dependable sources of information and material inputs, all of&#13;
which should be built into project design. Subprofessional&#13;
roles and skills should be modified to take account of the&#13;
increasing presence of paraprofessionals as the front line&#13;
providers of many services. Thus, subprofessionals should be&#13;
retrained and motivated to provide the back-up supervision,&#13;
reinforcement and managerial support for paraprofessional staff.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
h)   While volunl:ary service may be an important motivation,&#13;
paraprofessLonals usually require some modest material&#13;
compensatioIl or perquisites, even when they serve on a part-time&#13;
basis. Agency paraprofessionals should receive small payments&#13;
from government; community paraprofessionals can be compensated,&#13;
at least in part, by local farmers organizations.&#13;
4.   Wherever possible, responsibility for project management should be&#13;
shared with project beneficiaries through their local associations:&#13;
a)   Local organizations can mobilize and contribute labor and&#13;
material resources, provide government agencies with reliable&#13;
information and feedback on local needs and capabilities, and&#13;
retail services and resources at low cost to their members.&#13;
They can and should participate in the design and ongoing&#13;
management and modification of local project activities, thus&#13;
accepting greater responsibility for their own development.&#13;
b)   Members of the local organization selected by, responsible to,&#13;
and compensated by their peers, can serve as community&#13;
paraprofessionals. They can provide services which complement&#13;
those made available by government staff, thus reducing burdens&#13;
on the government's budget and on its administrative resources&#13;
and enhancing community or group self-reliance.&#13;
c)   One function of p. oject personnel is to develop and work with&#13;
and through local organizations of project beneficiaries. In&#13;
many cases, they must help to activate these organizations,&#13;
though this is not their greatest strength. Private voluntary&#13;
organizations and fully qualified professionals specially&#13;
prepared fcr this task are usually more effective in activating&#13;
local groups.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
5.   The Bank and other international aid agencies could certainly help&#13;
government agencies to improve the ability of locally-based staff&#13;
members to work compatibly and responsively with organized publics.&#13;
a)   The development of appropriate skills will, in many cases,&#13;
represent a substantial reorientation of bureaucratic attitudes,&#13;
procedures and behavior and require changes in prevailing job&#13;
requirements, expectations and rewards. Such assistance in&#13;
management improvement and institutional development should be&#13;
specifically incorporated into project design when estimates of&#13;
administrative feasibility disclose the need for such measures.&#13;
b)   Because of the acute pressure on government budgets during the&#13;
current period of international economic stagnation, the Bank&#13;
should be prepapred to finance the incremental costs of&#13;
training, supervising, supporting, and compensating agricultural&#13;
professionals.&#13;
6.   A vital contribution of the Bank to the success of agricultural&#13;
projects is to support improved training facilities and programs for&#13;
all categories of field staff, including agency paraprofessionals,&#13;
community paraprofessionals, and subprofessional personnel.&#13;
a)   Such training should be practical, job related and provide for&#13;
periodic reinforcement; it should include technical,&#13;
communications, and social skills.&#13;
b)   The retraining of subprofessionals in supervisory and management&#13;
skills is an important training priority to which the Bank's&#13;
assistance should be directed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
c)   Regional agricultural centers provide an effective way to&#13;
combine referral facilities, sources of project inputs, and&#13;
field experimentation with the supervision and training of field&#13;
staff.&#13;
It is important that training and support activities be specifically&#13;
incorporated into project: design and monitored continuously during project&#13;
implementation.&#13;
International donors, including the World Bank, could contribute to&#13;
the effectiveness of agricultural projects by paying much more attention to&#13;
the details of project implementation, to institutional developmient at the&#13;
local level, and especia'Lly to field staffing. The cases analyzed in this&#13;
review indicate that such a change may already be underway, but the Bank is&#13;
far more advanced in its appreciation of the potential utility of local farmer&#13;
organizations than in met:hods to improve the structure and procedures of&#13;
bureaucratic agencies and of field-level personnel. As the Worl.d Bank has&#13;
helped to reorient the development priorities of its member countries in the&#13;
direction of agricultura:L and rural development and towards the needs and&#13;
potentials of small-scale producers, it can similarly help to reorient them to&#13;
the importance of field-level institutional development in support of&#13;
broadly-based rural deve:Lopment.&#13;
To do so will require explicit consideration of these issues in the&#13;
preparation and appraisa:L of projects and consequent pressure on implementing&#13;
agencies. Far more atteution will have to be devoted to the det:ails of&#13;
administrative and institutional feasibility and to field-level staffing at&#13;
the point where projects engage their intended beneficiaries. This will&#13;
entail greater capacity and higher priority along these lines among the Bank's&#13;
own staff, particularly among those who participate in the design and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
supervise the implementation of agricultural projects. Some of this enhanced&#13;
capacity on issues of field-level implementation may be available from outside&#13;
contractors and consultants, but these can not substitute fully for greater&#13;
capacity, priority and sensitivity on the Bank's core staff.&#13;
After substantial investments and various experiences with&#13;
agricultural projects, the Bank has arrived to a recognition of the complexity&#13;
of the problems of field-level management, the need for detailed institutional&#13;
and sociological analysis at the stages of project design and implementation,&#13;
and the many options and combinations of staffing methods that may be&#13;
available in specific project environments. Much more precise information is&#13;
needed to guide decisions, especially on the various options for field-level&#13;
staffing. An intensive experimental and learning focus on this range of&#13;
problems by the unique array of resources available to the Bank could have a&#13;
beneficial effect on the state-of-the-art, on the effectiveness of project&#13;
performance, and on the eventual productivity and welfare of millions of small&#13;
farm families.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
NOTES&#13;
1. Esman, Milton J., Royal Colle, Norman Uphoff and Ellen Taylor,&#13;
Paraprofessionals in Rural Development, Cornell University, Center for&#13;
International Studies, Rural Development Committee, 1980.&#13;
2. The underdeveloped state-of-the-art and the literature on this subject is&#13;
reflected by Coralie Bryant and Louise G. White in Chapter 9, "Lower Level&#13;
Administrators and Field Agents" of their recent volume, Managing&#13;
Deve'opment in the Third World, .estview Press, 1982, p. 179-204.&#13;
3. David Leonard, Reaching the Peasant Farmers: Organization Theory and&#13;
Practice in Kenya, Chicago, University of Chicago Press, 1977.&#13;
4. In her 1975 study, The Design of Rural Development, Lessons from Africa,&#13;
published for the World Bank by the Johns Hopkins University Press, Uma&#13;
Lele identified field administration as a pervasive weakness and&#13;
recommended greatly improved training of field staff (p. 182-184). A Bank&#13;
Staff Working Paper 375 (1980), The Design of Organizations for Rural&#13;
Development Projects - A Progress Report (by Smith, W., F. Lethem, and B.&#13;
Thoolen) concentrates on inter-organizational coordination, rather than&#13;
the interface with client groups or special problems of field staffing.&#13;
5. World Bank, Rural Development Sector Policy Paper, Washington, February,&#13;
1975.&#13;
6. Reproduced by the Oxford University Press as Poverty and Human&#13;
Development. The quotation is from p. 44 of the Oxford University Press&#13;
edition.&#13;
7. Cernea, Michael M., "Modernization and Development Potential of&#13;
Traditional Grass Roots Peasant Organizations," in Mustafa 0. Attir,&#13;
Burkard Holzner, and Zdenek Suda (eds.), Directions of Change:&#13;
Modernization Theory, Research, and Realities, Westview Press, 1981.&#13;
8. See Cernea, Michael, "Sociological Dimensions of Extension Organization:&#13;
The Introduction of the T and V System in India," World Bank Reprint&#13;
Series, Number 196, January, 1979; the paper makes a sociological and&#13;
organizational analysis of the T and V extension system.&#13;
9. Esman et al., work cited in footnote I above.&#13;
10. "Agricultural Extension: The Training and Visit System," Ope-rational Note&#13;
4, distributed by the Directorate of Agricultural Extension, Ministry of&#13;
Agriculture and Cooperation, Government of India, mimeo, no date.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54 -&#13;
,. ;jumslag, Nanmi, et al, AID Intpgrated Low Cost Health Projects, Vol. II,&#13;
9%nalysis. -  i .- f£JL USA-D by the Office of Iinternational Health, U.S.&#13;
Department of Health, Education and Welfare, Rockville, Maryland, 1978.&#13;
13. Whyte, William F., Participatory Appron'ches to Agricultural Research and&#13;
Development: A State-of-the-Art Paper, Cornell University, Rural&#13;
Development Committee, Center for International Studies, 1981.&#13;
14. The role of local organizations in agricultural and rural development is&#13;
analyzed by Milton J. Esman and Norman Uphoff in their monograph, Local&#13;
Organization and Rural Development. The State-of-the-Art, Rural&#13;
Development Committee, Cornell University, Center for International&#13;
Studies, 1982.&#13;
15. For an analysis of the Comilla project, see Harry Blair, The Elusiveness&#13;
of Equity: Institutional Approaches to Rural Development in Bangladesh,&#13;
Ithaca, Cornell University, Rural Development Committee, Center for&#13;
International Stulies, 1974.&#13;
16. Cernea, M., see work cited in footnote 7.&#13;
17. This point is emphasized by Lin Compton in his recent review of the T and&#13;
V system in Thailand, Evaluating the Training and Visit System, Cornell&#13;
University, March 13, 1982, mimeo.&#13;
18. Robert Orr Whyte and Pauline Whyte, The Women of Rural Asia, Westview&#13;
Press, 1982.&#13;
19. Cornell report cited in footnote 1, page 36.&#13;
20. Benor, Daniel and J. Harrison, Agricultural Extension, The Training and&#13;
Visit System, World Bank, Washington, DC 1977.&#13;
21. Korten, David and Norman Uphoff have discussed this need in their paper on&#13;
"Bureaucratic Reorientation for Participatory Development," NAASPA Working&#13;
Paper 1, Washington, National Association of Schools of Public Affairs&#13;
and Administration, December, 1981.&#13;
22. World Bank Staff Paper No. 375 (cited in footnote 4) refers to this&#13;
problem. See also Milton J. Esman, "Field-Level Organization for Rural&#13;
Development," in G. Shabbir Cheema (ed.) Institutional Dimensions of Rural&#13;
Development, Nagoya, Japan, Maruzen Asia, 1981 (for the UN Center for&#13;
Regional Development).&#13;
23. This useful term was first employed by Jerome T. French in his 1971 paper,&#13;
"AID Review of the Role of LDC Institutions and Joint Organizations as&#13;
Program Interdiaries for Increasing Local Action Capabilities," Office of&#13;
Development Administration, AID, July 15, 1971.&#13;
24. See footnote 21.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
APPENDIX A&#13;
lWorld Bank Assisted Projects*&#13;
Reviewed for the Preparation of this Report&#13;
1. Turkey: Seyhan Irrigation Project (June 1969)&#13;
2. Kenya: First Population Project (March 1974)&#13;
3. Thailand Northeast Thailand Rural Development Project (January 1976)&#13;
4. Senegal: Eastern Senegal Livestock Development Project (June 1976)&#13;
5. Colombia Integrated Rural Development Project (Dec. 1976)&#13;
6. Mali: Mali-Sud Cotton Marketing Project (December 1976)&#13;
7. India: West Benegal Agricultural Extension and Research (March 1977)&#13;
8. Mexico: Tropical Agricultural Development Project (April 1978)&#13;
9. Bolivia: Ulla Ulla Development Project (January 1978)&#13;
10. Sri Lanka: Kurunegal.a Rural Development Project (March 1979)&#13;
11. Niger: Livestock Development Project (March 1979)&#13;
12. Brazil: Sergipe Rural Development Project (May 1979)&#13;
13. Niger: Dosso Agricultural Development Project December 1979)&#13;
14. Nepal: Agricultural Extension and Research Project (February 1981)&#13;
15. Mexico: Rainfed Agricultural Development Project (January 1.981)&#13;
16. Nepal: Hill Food Production Project (February 1981)&#13;
17. Ethiopia: Second Ag-ricultural Minimum Package Project (May 1981)&#13;
18. India: West Bengal Social Forestry Project (May 1982)&#13;
19. Philippines: Small Scale Communal Irrigation (June 1982)&#13;
20. Indonesia: Sixteenth Irrigation Project (July 1982)&#13;
21. Benin: Atacora Rural Development Project (September 1982)&#13;
22. Korea: Rural Infrastructure Project (March 1976)&#13;
*   In parentheses, the date when each project became effective,.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
World      Bank                       The Agricultural Economy of          Agricultural Price Policies&#13;
Pu     b        Nan                   Northeast Brazil                     and the Developing&#13;
Gary P Kutcher and                   Countries&#13;
of Related                            Pasquale L. Scandizzo                George Tolley, Vinod Thomas,&#13;
Inlaerest                            This study, based on an agricultural  and Chung Ming Wong&#13;
survey of 8,000 farms, assesses the  This book first considers price&#13;
extent and root causes of pervasive   policies in Korea, Bangladesh, Thai-&#13;
rural poverty in northeast Brazil. The  land, and Venezuela, bringing out the&#13;
Adoption of Agricultural              authors review a number of policy    consequences for govemment cost&#13;
Innovations In Developing             and project options; they conclude   and revenue, farm income, and pro-&#13;
Countries: A Survey                   that courageous land reform is the   ducer and consumer welfare. Other&#13;
Gershon Feder, Richard Just           only effective means of dealing with  effects, including those on agri-&#13;
ancl David Silberrman                the problem.                          cultural diversification, inflation,&#13;
The Johns Hopkins Universitj Press,  economic growth, and the balance of&#13;
Reviews various studies that have pro-  1982. 288 pages.                   payments are also discussed. The&#13;
vided a description of and possible                                        second part of the book provides a&#13;
explanation for patterns of innovation  LC 81-47615. ISBN 0-8018-2581-4,   methodology for estimating these&#13;
adoption in the agricultural sector.  $25.00 (f17.50) hardcover.           effects in any country. Operational&#13;
Woric Bank Staff Working Paper  .                                          tools for measuring the effects on&#13;
No. 5B2.k1982. 65 pages.              Agricultural Extension: The          producers, consumers, and govern-&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0103-9. $3.00.            Training and Visit System            ment are developed and applied.&#13;
Daniel Benor                         The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
Agrarian Reform as         -          and James Q. Harrison                1982. 256 pages.&#13;
Unfinished Business-                  Describes the Training and Visit     LC 81-15585. ISBN 0-8018-2704-3,&#13;
the Selected Papers of                System of extension developed by     $25.00 (.1;i.50) hardcover.&#13;
WolF Ladejinsky                       Daniel Benor and introduced in a&#13;
Louis J. Walinsky, editor             number of projects assisted by the   Agricultural Project&#13;
World Bank in developing countries.  Analysis: Case Studies and&#13;
Studies in agrarian policy and land &#13;
refon n spanning four decades,        May 1977. 55 pages (including annex).  Exercises&#13;
grouped chronologically according to  English, French, and Spanish.        Case studies and exercises on&#13;
Ladejinsky's years in Washington,     Stock Nos. PM-7701-E, PM-7701-F,     agricultural project preparation and&#13;
Tokyo, and Vietnam and while at the   PM-7701-S. $3.00 paperback.          analysis, developed foi; and used in,&#13;
Ford Foundation and the World Bank.                                        EDI's rural development and rural&#13;
Oxford University Press, 1977. 614  -  Agricultural Land                   credit courses.&#13;
page,,: (including appendixes, index).  Settlement                         World Bank (EDI), 1979, v.l-viii +&#13;
LC 7;-24254. ISBN 0-19-920095-5,      Theodore J. Goering, coor-           711 pages. u.2-iv + 113 pages. u.3&#13;
$32.50 (£14.95) hardcover,            dinating author                      -iv + 157 pages. (Available from ILS,&#13;
ISBN 0-19-920098-X, $14.95 (f5.25)    Examines selected issues related     1715 ConnecticutAvenue, N.W.,&#13;
paperback.                           to the World Bank's lending for land  Washington, D.C. 20009. U.S.A.)&#13;
settlement, and gives estimates of   $9.00 paperback.&#13;
Agrnrian Reforms In                   the global rate of settlement and&#13;
Developing Rural                      the world's ultimate potentially     Agricultural Research&#13;
Economies Characterized by            arable land.                         Points out that developing countries&#13;
Interlinked Credit and               A World Bank Issues Paper. January    must invest more in agricultural&#13;
Tenancy Markets                      1978. 73 pages (including 4 annexes).  research il they are to meet the&#13;
Avisliay Braverrnan                   English, French, and Spanish.        needs of their growing populations.&#13;
Avisl,ay Braverman  English.                            ~~~~~~~~~~~States thalt studies in Brazil, India.&#13;
and T N. Srinivasan                   Stock Nos. PP-7801-E, PP-7801-F,     Japan, Mexico, and the United States&#13;
Worl' Bank Staff Working Paper No.   PP- 7801-S. $5.00 paperback.          show that agricultural research yields&#13;
433. O)ctober 1980. 32 pages (including -                                  a rate of return that is more than two&#13;
references).                         Agricultural Price                    to three times greater than returns&#13;
Management in Egypt                  from mosl. alternative investments&#13;
Stock No. .WP-0433. $3.00.            William Cuddihy                      and cites some of the successes of&#13;
the high-yielding varieties of rice and&#13;
A8riicultural Credit                  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   wheat that were developed in the&#13;
Outlirnes agricultural credit practices  388. April 1980. x + 164 pages (includ-  mid-1960s. Discusses the World&#13;
and problems, programs, and           Ing annex, bibliography).            Bank's plans to expand Its lending for&#13;
and problems, programs, and                            ~~~~~~~~agriculturali research and extension,&#13;
policies in developing countries and  Stock No. WP-0388. $5.00.            particularla for the production of&#13;
discusses their implications for World&#13;
Bank operations.                                                           food and other commodities that are&#13;
of Importance to low-income con-&#13;
A Wo,ild Bank Paper. May 1975. 85                                          sumers, srnall farmers, and resource-&#13;
page-,: (including 14 annex tables).                                       poor areas.&#13;
Engli;h, French, and Spanish.                                              Sector Polic:y Paper. June 1981. 110&#13;
Stock Nos. PP-7502-E, PP-7502-F,                                           pages (including annexes). English,&#13;
PP- 7! 02-S. $5.00 paperback.                                              French, an(d Spanish.&#13;
Stock No. P P-8101-E, PP-8101-F,&#13;
PP-8101-S. $5.00 paperijack.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Agricultural Research and               NEW                             Casos y    jerciclos Sobre&#13;
Productivity                                                            Proyectos Agricolas&#13;
Robert E. Evenson                   The Book of CllAC:                  Edited by Orlando T. Espadas&#13;
and Yoav Kislev                     Programming Studies for             Three case studles prepared in con-&#13;
Examines the role of scientific     Mexican Agricultural Policy        junction with the EDI's Agricultural&#13;
research and technological change in  Edited by Roger D. Norton and     Projects Courses in Spanish and&#13;
increasing agricultural productivity.  Leopoldo Solis M.                intended primarly for teachers of&#13;
project analysis.&#13;
Yale University Press, 302 Temple Street,  The principal tool of analysis is the&#13;
New Haven, Connecticut 06520, U.SA.  sector model CHAC, named after the  World Bank (EDI), March 1974; reuvsed&#13;
1975. xl + 204 pages (Including 10  Mayan rain god. This model can be   January 1975. 480 pages (Auailable&#13;
appendixes, references, index).     used throughout the sector to cover  from ILS, 1715 Connecticut Avenue,&#13;
short-cycle crops, their Inputs, and  N.W., Washington, D.C. 20009, U.S.A.)&#13;
LC 74-15210. ISBN 0-300-01815-0,    their markets. It can also be broken  $.00 pack.&#13;
$15.00 hardcover; ISBN 0-300-01877-0,  down into submodels for particular  S5.00 paperback.&#13;
$3.95 paperback.                    localities If more detailed analysis is&#13;
required. The model helps planners&#13;
Spanish: Investigaci6n agricola y pro-  weigh the costs among policy goals,  The Design of Organiza&#13;
ductividad. Editorial Tecnos, 1976.  which can vary from region to region.  tions for Rural Development&#13;
ISBN 84-309-0641-X, 420 pesetas.    This volume reports the experience of  Projects-a Progress&#13;
using the CHlAC model and also pre-  Report&#13;
sents purely methodological material.  William E. Smith,&#13;
Agroindustrala    Project           The Johns Hopkins UniversIty Press,  Francis J. Lethem, and&#13;
alysis                              1983. 632 pages.                    Ben A. Thoolen&#13;
James E. Austin                     LC 80-29366. iSBN 0-8018-2585-7,    World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Pfrovides and Illustrates a framework  $35.00 (924.50) hardcover.       375. March 1980. 48 pages. English&#13;
for analyzing and designing agro-                                       and French.&#13;
industrial projects.&#13;
Stock Mo. WP-03 75-E, WP-03 75-f.&#13;
EDI Series In Economic Development.     NEW                             $3.00.&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University jPess,&#13;
1981. 224 pages (including appen-   Building national Capacity&#13;
dLxes, bibliography, and Index).    to Develop Water Users'             The Design of Rural&#13;
LC 80-550. ISBN 0-8018-2412-5,      Associations: Experience            Development: Lessons&#13;
$16.50 (l10.00) hardcover; ISBN     from the PhFlippines                from Africa&#13;
0-8018-2413-3, $7.50 (S4.25)        Frances E Korten                    Uma Lele&#13;
paperback.                          Over a flve-year period, the Natonal  Analyzes new ways of designing rural&#13;
French: LAnalyse des projets agro-  Irrigation Administration (NIA) of the  development projects to reach large&#13;
industriels. Economica, 1982.       ihilippines has been building Its    numbers of low-income subsistence&#13;
ISBN 2-7178-0480-3, 49 francs.      capacity to develop water users     populations. The paperback reprint-&#13;
associations on small-scale irrigation  ing in 1979 contains a new chapter by&#13;
Spanish: Analisis de proyectos agro-  systems. This paper details the   the author updating her findings.&#13;
industriales. Edlcorlal Tecnos, 1981.  changes that have been made within&#13;
ISBN 84-309-0882-X, 600 pesetas.    the agency as a result of the develop-  The Johns propkins Unigersit. Press,&#13;
ment of these associations prior to  1975; 3rd printing,1979. 260 pages&#13;
the construction of the physical    (including glossary, appendix, maps,&#13;
Argentina: Country Case             system and the involvement of       bibliography, index).&#13;
Study of Agricultural Prices,       association members in the planning  ISBN 0-8018-1769-2, $9.95&#13;
Taxes, and Subsidies                and construction stages. It also    paperback&#13;
examines the nature of the leaming  paerck.&#13;
Lucio 0. Reca                       process that has led to these changes  French: i.e developpement&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  and discusses the Implications for  rural: I'experience Africaine.&#13;
386. April 1980. 72 pages (including  donor support of other small-scale  Economica, 1977.&#13;
3 annues).                          Irrigation programs and more        ISBN 2- 7178-0006-9, 39 francs.&#13;
annexes). WP-386 S300.generally for programs Involving&#13;
Stock No. WP-0.386. $5.00.          village-level work.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
No. 528. July 1982. v + 69 pages&#13;
(Including references).&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0051-2. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
A Dlevelopment Model for            Farm Budgets: From Farm                  NEW&#13;
thin Agricultural Sector            Income Analysis to&#13;
of Portugal                         Agricultural Project Analysis        Improving Irrigated Agricul-&#13;
Alvin C. Egbert                     Maxwell L. Brown                     ture: lnstiltutlonal Reform&#13;
andi Hyung M. Kim                   Clarifies the relation between simple  and the Simall Farmer&#13;
Spatial mathematical programming is  farrn income analysis and the broader  Daniel W. ESromley&#13;
usei to develop comprehensive and   fleld of agricultural project analysis  A model of farmer interdependence is&#13;
quantitative methods to suggest     and emphasizes the more practical      del      o providepens       Is&#13;
dev*lopment strategies in Portugal's  aspects of project preparation and  developed to provide suggestions for&#13;
agriculture sector.                 gives guidance to those responsible  improving existing irrigation systems.&#13;
for planning in agriculture,        as well as for designing new ones.&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press,                                      World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
197 i. HO pages (including          EDI Series in Economic Development.  No. 531. 1982. 96 pages.&#13;
bibl!ography).                      The Johns tfopkins University Press,&#13;
LC ;5-26662. ISBN 0-8018-1793-5,    1980. 154 pages.                    ISBN 0-8213-0064-4. $3.00.&#13;
$6.50 (.f4.00) paperback.           LC 79-3704. ISBN 0-8018-2386-2.&#13;
$15.00 (S10.50) hardcover,&#13;
ISBN 8-8018-2387-0, $6.50               nEW&#13;
NEW                              (f4.50) paperback.&#13;
Spanish: Presupuestos de fincas.     Productasint&#13;
Eco)nomic Analysis of               Editorial Tecnos, 1982.             (Prodcdin    t&#13;
(Proceedings of the Third Annual&#13;
Agiricultural Projects              ISBN 84-309-0886-2, 725 pesetas.     Agricultural Sector Symposium)&#13;
Se:ond edition, completely                                               Ted J. Davis, editor&#13;
reil lsed and expanded              ____&#13;
rev Lsed and expeWed        These proceedings are the third in a&#13;
(Sec Publications of Particular         NEW                             series of recc'rds of Agricultural Sec-&#13;
Interest, page 1.)                                                      tor Symposia presented at the World&#13;
Fishery                             Bank each January since 1980. Con-&#13;
Highlights the importance of fisheries  tains the papers presented by the&#13;
NEW                              to the economies of developing coun-  speakers, chairpersons' statements,&#13;
tries and recommends that the World  and summaries of the discussions&#13;
EcAnomic Aspects and                Bank provide assistance to those     prepared by the rapporteurs.&#13;
Policy Issues In Ground-            countries that have the fishery&#13;
was:er Development                  resources and are willing to develop  1982. 307 pages (including index).&#13;
Ian Crruthrs an   Roy  toner them further.                     1ISBN 0-8213-0099-7. $15.00.&#13;
lan Carruthers and Roy Stoner&#13;
Exainines a wide range of economic  Sector Policy Paper. December 1982.&#13;
and policy issues related to develop-  ISBN 0-8213-0138-1. $5.00 paperback.  NEW&#13;
merit of groundwater for irrigation.&#13;
Worid Bank Staff Working Paper      Food Security In Food                India: Demand aind Supply&#13;
No. 496. October 1981.1L0 pages     Deficit Countries                    Prospects for Agriculture&#13;
(inc uding annex, bibliography).    Shlomo Reutlinger                    James Q. 11arrison,&#13;
Stock lo. WP-0496. $5.00.           and Keith Knapp                      Jon A. Ilitchings,&#13;
and John WV. Wall&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  Contains four papers that report on&#13;
NEW                             393. June 1980. 39 pages (including  the World Bank's economic work in&#13;
appendix. references).               the agricultural sector in India and&#13;
Economic Return to Invest-          Stock No. WP-0393. $3.00.           the implications of this development&#13;
ment in Irrigation in India                                              both for food.grains and for other&#13;
Les lie A. Abbie,                                                        major agricultural commodities.&#13;
Forestiry                            Focuses on the demand for&#13;
Jaries Q. Harrison,                 Graham Donaldson, coordi-            agricultural commodities through the&#13;
and John W. Wall                    nating author                        year 2000. the foodgrain economy,&#13;
Rep:)rts on an investigation Into the                                    the vegetable- oil economy, and the&#13;
efficiency of investment in surface  Examines the signifcance of forests  sugar economyY.&#13;
and groundwater irrigation in India.  In economic development and con-   WrdBn        tf  okn     ae&#13;
cludes that the World Bank should    World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
Worid Bank Staff Working Paper      greatly Increase its rcle In forestry  No. 500. October 1981.133 pages&#13;
No. 536.1982. 52 pages.             development both as a lender and     (including 5 appendIxes, references,&#13;
15Bf 0-8213-0083-0. $3.00.          adviser to governments.              annex).&#13;
Sector Policy Paper. February 1978. 63  Stock No. WP-0500. $5.00.&#13;
pages (including 7 annexes). English,&#13;
French, and Spanish.&#13;
Stock Nos. PP-7804-E, PP-7804-F,&#13;
PP-7804-S. $5.00 paperback.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Land Reform                           and they involve a variety of invest-  Rethinking Artisanal Fish-&#13;
Examines the characteristics of land  ments. The need for monitoring and    eries Development: Western&#13;
reform, its implications for the      evaluating them during implementa-    Concepts, Asian Experiences&#13;
economies of developing countries,    tion has been accepted in principle,  Donald K. Emmerson&#13;
and the major policy options open to  but effective systems have not&#13;
the World Bank in this fleld.         heretofore been formulated. The con-  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
cepts of monitoring and evaluation    423. October 1980. x + 97 pages&#13;
A World Bank Paper. May 1975. 73      are differentiated and issues that    (including references).&#13;
pages (including 2 annexes).          need to be considered in designing&#13;
English, French, and Spanish.         systems to monitor and evaluate       Stock No. WP-0423. $5.00.&#13;
specific projects are outlined,&#13;
Stock Nos. PP-7503-E, PP-7503-F,      emphasizing the timeliness of the&#13;
PP-7503-S. $5.00 paperback.           monitoring functions for effective    Rural Development&#13;
management. Elaborates on such        Discusses strategy designed to extend&#13;
technical issues as selection of indica-  the benefits of development to the&#13;
Land Tenure Systems and               tors, selection of survey methodology  rural poor and outlines the World&#13;
Social Implications of                data analysis, and presentation. It is  Bank's plans for increasing its assis-&#13;
Forestry Development                  directed primarily to those working  tance in this sector.&#13;
Programs                              with specific projects and will be use-  Sector Policy Paper. February 1975, 89&#13;
Michael M. Cernea                    ful to profect appraisal teams, to    pages (including 14 annexes). English,&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   tion systems, and to project staff who  French. Spanish. and Arabic.&#13;
452. April 1981. 35 pages (including  work with these systems.             Stock Nos. PP-7501-E, PP-7501-F,&#13;
references, bibliography).            The Johns Hopkins University Press.   PP-7501-S, PP-7501-A. $5.00&#13;
Stock No. WP-0452. $3.00.             1982. 145 pages. French and Spanish  paperback.&#13;
forthcoming.&#13;
LC 82- 7126. ISBN 0-8018-2910-0, $8.50  Rural Poverty Unperceived:&#13;
Managing Information for              (£6.50) paperback.                   Problems and Remedies&#13;
Rural Development: Lessons                                                 Robert Chambers&#13;
firom Eastern Africa&#13;
Guido Deboeck and Bill Kinsey         Monitoring Rural Develop-             World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
ment In East Asia           ~~400. July 1980. 51 pages (including&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    men in eas        a                  references)&#13;
379. March 1980. vii + 70 pages       Guido Deboeck and Ronald        g      tock No. WP-0400. $3.00.&#13;
(including 5 annexes, index).         World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Stock No. WP-03 79. $3.00.            439. October 1980. 91 pages (including&#13;
annexes).                                 NEW&#13;
Measuring Project Impact:             Stock No. WP-0439. $3.00.             Rural Projects Through&#13;
Monitoring and Evaluation                                                   Urban Eyes: An Interpreta-&#13;
in the PIDER Rural Develop-           Nutritional Consequences              tion of the World Bank's&#13;
ment Project-Mexico                   of Agricultural Projects:             New-Style Rural Develop-&#13;
Michael M. Cernea                     Conceptual Relationships              ment Projects&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    and Assessment                       Judith Tendler&#13;
332. June 1979. vi + 131 pages        Approaches                            This paper describes the Bank's new-&#13;
(including 3 annexes, appendix, map).  Per Pinstrup-Andersen                style rural development projects,&#13;
Stock No. WP-0332. $5.00.             World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    including some of the things that hap-&#13;
456. April 1981. 93 pages (including  pen in the political environment of a&#13;
project when governments, assisted&#13;
___________  bibiography. appendix).  by the Bank, redirect their public-sec-&#13;
NEW                               Stock No. WP-0456. $3.00.             tor services and subsidies to the rural&#13;
poor.&#13;
Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
of Agriculture and Rural              Prices, Taxes, and Subsidies          World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
Development Projects                  In Pakistan Agriculture,              No. 532.1982.100 pages.&#13;
Dennis J. Casley                      1960-1976                             lSBN 0-8213-0028-8. $3.00.&#13;
and Denis A. Lury                     Carl Gotsch and Gilbert Brown&#13;
This book provides a how-to tool for  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    Sociocultural Aspects of&#13;
the design and implementation of      387. April 1980. 108 pages.           Developing Small-Scale&#13;
monitoring and evaluation systems in  Stock No. WP-0387. $5.00.             Fisheries: Delivering&#13;
rural development projects. Because                                         Services to the Poor&#13;
rural development projects are com-                                         Richard B. Pollnac&#13;
plex, they seek to benefit large num-&#13;
bers of people in remote rural areas,                                       World Bank Staff Working Paper llo.&#13;
490. October 1981. iii + 61 pages&#13;
(including references).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0490. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
siome Aspects of Wheat and                        Credit and Sharecropping In Agraian&#13;
1.Uce Price Policy In India                       Societies&#13;
lRaj Krishna and G. S.                            Avishay Braverman and T.N. Srinivasan&#13;
lRaychaudhuri                                     World Bank Reprint Series: Number 216.&#13;
Reprinted from Journal of Development&#13;
IYorld Bank Staff Working Paper Nio.              Economics, uol. 9 (December 1981): 289-312.&#13;
.581. April 1980. 62 pages (including             Stock No. RP-0216. Free of charge.&#13;
2 appendixes, 6 tables, bibliography).&#13;
;.tock No. WP-0381. $5.00.                        FaRevolution Technology On information&#13;
and innovation Diffusion: A Bayesian&#13;
Approach&#13;
it System   of Monitoring and                     Gershon reder and Gerald T. O'Mara&#13;
JBvaluating Agricultural                          World Bank Reprint Series: Number 207.&#13;
IExtenslon Projects                               Reprinted from Economic Development and&#13;
'l&#156;ichael M. Cernea and                           Cultural Ctiange, vol. 30. no. I (October&#13;
19811:59- 76: and American Journal of Agricultural&#13;
13enjamin J. Tepping                              Economics, vol. 64. no. I (February 1982):145-47.&#13;
IVorld Bank Staff Working Paper to.               Stock No. RP-0207. free of charge.&#13;
;!72. December 1977. vi + 115 pages&#13;
(including 9 annexes, bibliography).              Sociological Dimensions of Extension&#13;
itock No. WP-02 72. $5.00.                        Organization: The Introduction of the&#13;
T&amp;V System In India&#13;
Michael M. Cernea&#13;
'rhallad-CaseStu(tyof                      World Bank Reprint Series: Number 196.&#13;
.Thailand-Case Study of                           Reprinted from Extension Education and Rural&#13;
kgricultural Input and                             Development. vol. 2. (1981:221-35, 281.&#13;
Output Pcing                                      Stocir No. RP-0196. free of charge.&#13;
'rent Bertrand&#13;
IVorld Bank Staff Working Paper No.                   NEW&#13;
,85. April 1980. ix + 134 pages                           ____&#13;
(including 2 appendixes).                         Economic Analysis of Agricultural Projects&#13;
.~;tock lo. WP-0385. $5.00.                Second edition, completely revtsed and&#13;
expanded&#13;
I:EPRINTS                                         J. Price Gittinger&#13;
This entirely new edition of the World Bank's best-selling&#13;
A doption of interrelated Agzlcsdtural            book sets out a careful and practicai methodology for&#13;
ImnovaUons: Complementarity and the:              analyzing agricultural development projets and for using&#13;
Impacts of Risk, Scale, and Creditaayinagiutrldvopetrjesadfruig&#13;
Ciershon Feder                                    these analyses to compare proposed investments. It&#13;
C,eorshoBank ReprintdSerIes: Number 206.          covers what constitutes a "project," what must be con-&#13;
MorldBank ReprintSeriesn Joumber 206.             sidered to identify possible agricultural projects, the life&#13;
heprinted from American Joumal of Agricultural    cycle of a project, the strengths and pitfalls of project&#13;
Economics. vol. 64, no. I (Februany 1982):94-101.  analysis, and the calculations required to obtain financial&#13;
Stock No. RP-0206. Free of charge.                and economic project accounts.&#13;
In the ten years since its publication, the first edition has&#13;
A gicultural Policies and Development:             been accepted widely as a standard reference and text. The&#13;
A Socioeconomc investigMion Appied                 methodology reflects the best of contemporary practice in&#13;
Martha H. de Meio                                 government agencies and internationail development&#13;
W'Orld Bank Reprint Series: Number 191.  Institutions concerned with investing in agriculture and is&#13;
lporld Bank Reprint Serles: Noumber 191.           accessible to a broad readership of agricuiltural planners,&#13;
Rprinted from The Journal of Policy Modeling.      engineers, and analysts.&#13;
Scl. 1. no. 2 (May 1979):217-34.                     This revision adds a wealth of recent project data;&#13;
Stock Mo. RP-0191. free of charge.                 expanded treatment of farm budgets and the efflciency&#13;
prices used to calculate the effects of an investment on&#13;
Choice of Technique In Sahellan Rice               national Income; a glossary of technical terms; expanded&#13;
F'roduction                                        appendixes on preparing an agricultural project report and&#13;
C harles P Humphreys and Scott R. Pearsoll         using discounting tables; and an expanded, completely&#13;
Uorld Bank Reprint Series: Number 199.             annotated bibliography.&#13;
Reprinted from Food Research Studies, vol. 17.     eD Series In Economic Development.&#13;
no. 3 (1979-80):235577.EDSeisIEcnmcevlp                                             nt&#13;
S!ock No. RP-0199. free ofcharge.                  The Johns Hopkins Uniuersity Press. July 1982. 528 pages&#13;
(Including appendixes and glossary/lIndex).&#13;
LC 82.15262. ISBNt 0-8018-2912-7, $3 7.50 (J22.50) hardcover;&#13;
ISBN 0-8018-2913-5, $13.50 (48.75) paperback.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
ORDER FORM&#13;
SOEND TO:&#13;
'NORLD BANK PUBLICATIONIS                                                        WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
lO. BOX 37525                                                or                  66, AVENUE D'IENA&#13;
'NASHINGTON, D.C. 20013                                                          75116 PARIS, FRANCE&#13;
IJ.S.A.&#13;
Name:&#13;
Address:&#13;
Stock or ISBN #                              Author, Title                        Qty.         Price          Total&#13;
Sub-Total Cost: ______&#13;
Postaige &amp; handling fee for more than two free items ($1.00 eaich):&#13;
Total copies: -_____ Air mail surcharge ($2.00 eatch):&#13;
TOTAL PAYMENT ENCLOISED:_____&#13;
Make checks payable: WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
Pre payment on orders from individuals is requested. Purchase orders are accepted from booksellers, library suppliers, libraries, and institutions.&#13;
All prices include cost of postage by the least excpensive means. The prices and publication dates quoted in this Catalog are subject to change&#13;
wit lout notice.&#13;
No refunds will be given for items that canniot be filled. Credit will be applied towards future orders.&#13;
No more than two free publications will be provided without charge. Requests for additional copies will be tilled at Et charge of US $1.00 per&#13;
cop.y to cover handling and postage costs.&#13;
Airmail delivery will require a prepayment cf US $2.00 per copy.&#13;
Mail-order payment to the World Bank neecd not be in U.S. dollars, but the amount remitted must be at the rate of oxchange on the day the&#13;
order is placed. The World Bank will also accept Unesco coupons.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
*** HD1417 .E84 1983 c.2&#13;
Eaman, Milton J. (Milton&#13;
Jacob), 1918-&#13;
Paraprofessionals in&#13;
rural development:&#13;
4 malligCa  i n  $F i onQ  A ^- I  VC 10 &#13;
_ &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters:                                                                                                 U&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK&#13;
Cable address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
European Office:&#13;
66, avenue d'lena&#13;
75116 Paris, France&#13;
Telephone: (1) 723-54.21&#13;
Telex: 842-620628&#13;
Tokyo Office:&#13;
Kokusai Building&#13;
1-1, Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Chivoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
Telex: 781-26838&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0180-2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554867">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/04/1554867/paraprofessionals-rural-development-issues-field-level-staffing-agricultural-projects
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/04/1554867/paraprofessionals-rural-development-issues-field-level-staffing-agricultural-projects</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1983/04/1554867/paraprofessionals-rural-development-issues-field-level-staffing-agricultural-projects</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/07/09/000178830_98101903415533/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/07/09/000178830_98101903415533/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2002-07-19T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1983-04-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Paraprofessionals in rural development :
            issues in field-level staffing for agricultural projects
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Sociological and institutional problems
            of implementing small-scale agriculture projects have been
            neglected, particularly in connection with implementation at
            the field level. Cost-effectiveness of agricultural projects
            can be increased by innovations in field level staffing. The
            Bank has already begun to support projects that employ
            paraprofessional staff in agricultural extension,
            irrigation, livestock, and forestry development. Lessons
            learned from this include: (i) consultation with project
            beneficiaries in the choice of paraprofessionals; (ii)
            employment of female paraprofessionals to assist in the
            performance of farming roles normally played by women; (iii)
            preservice and frequent refresher training in practical,
            job-related information and skills; and (iv) reliable
            referral, logistical, and supervisory support for
            paraprofessional staff. Paraprofessionals selected by,
            compensated by, and accountable to local organizations and
            associations of farmers can increase the relevance and
            cost-effectiveness of services while enhancing local self-reliance.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Paraprofessionals in rural development :
            issues in field-level staffing for agricultural projects
        </docna>
        <display_title>Paraprofessionals in rural
            development : issues in field-level staffing for
            agricultural projects</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1983/04/1554867/paraprofessionals-rural-development-issues-field-level-staffing-agricultural-projects</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Agricultural Knowledge and Information Systems,Health Economics &amp; Finance,ICT Policy and Strategies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Esman, M.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903415533</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>KN</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 573</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Agricultural technicians; Agriculture; Cost
            effectiveness; Field work; Projects; Rural development;
            Women in agriculture
            affiliates,Agricultural
            development,agricultural extension,agriculture,animal
            diseases,bureaucracies,capital cities,civil
            service,communication skills,community health,credit
            unions,development projects,donor
            investments,employment,entrepreneurship,equipment,expenditures,experiment
            stations,families,farmers,feed,fertilizers,fiscal year,Food
            Production,health workers,incomes,information
            systems,Information
            transfer,innovation,innovations,institutional
            development,intermediaries,learning,livestock,low
            income,management methods,managers,marketing,medicine,new
            technologies,pastoralists,plant diseases,private
            sector,productivity,programs,public services,quality
            control,regulatory tasks,rural
            development,scientists,secondary schools,Service
            Delivery,technicians,training materials,voluntary organizations,workers
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP573</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock and Animal Husbandry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Extension</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research and Extension</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forest and Forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>HRH</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Workers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indigenous Communities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ethnic Minorities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indigenous Peoples</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nationalities &amp; Ethnic Groups</ml:concept><ml:concept>Religious Minorities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Support Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Animal Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT and Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textbooks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources for Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ethnic, Religious and other Minorities</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>