<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Commodity Price Stabilization&#13;
The Theory and Its Application&#13;
Andrew Schmitz&#13;
SWP668&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 668&#13;
V1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 668&#13;
Commodity Price Stabilization&#13;
The Theory and Its Application&#13;
Andrew Schmitz&#13;
1I'TERNATIONAL MONETARY FUND&#13;
JOINT LIBRARY&#13;
Yi- 1 5 1984&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR&#13;
RECONSTRUCT1,Oil AND DEVELOPtMENT&#13;
WASPINGTCN. D.C. 20431&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright (© 1984&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing September 1984&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To present the&#13;
results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been prepared&#13;
in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed texts, and the&#13;
World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a&#13;
token charge to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to any&#13;
individual acting on their behalf. Any maps used have been prepared solely for the&#13;
convenience of the readers; the denominations used and the boundaries shown do&#13;
not imply, on the part of the World Bank and its affiliates, any judgment on the&#13;
legal status of any territory or any endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications, both free and for sale, is described in&#13;
the Catalog of Publications; the continuing research program is outlined in Abstracts of&#13;
Current Studies. Both booklets are updated annually; the most recent edition of each&#13;
is available without charge from the Publications Sales Unit, Department T, The&#13;
World Bank, 1818 H Street, N.W., Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A., or from the&#13;
European Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'1ena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Andrew Schmitz is professor of agricultural economics at the University of&#13;
California, Berkeley, and a consultant to the Country Policy Department of the&#13;
World Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Schmitz, Andrew.&#13;
Commodity price stabilization.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 668)&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
1. Commodity control. 2. Price regulation.&#13;
I. Title. II. Series.&#13;
PF1428.S28     1984      332.64'4            84-17431&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0415-1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ABSTRACT&#13;
The literature on commodity price stabilization is extensive in its&#13;
coverage, diverse in its objectives, complex in its theoretical constructs,&#13;
and confusing in its results. The purpose of this essay is to clarify and&#13;
simplify the results of this broad body of literature in order to provide the&#13;
operational economist with a better sense of the conditions under which com-&#13;
modity stabilization schemes will be successful and the welfare effects of&#13;
such schemes.&#13;
The essay begins by introducing the early framework under which price&#13;
stabilization was analyzed and then continues by relaxing the assumptions of&#13;
the early model in order to demonstrate the variance of results under alterna-&#13;
tive (more realistic) situations. Topics such as storage and food security,&#13;
inflation and economic development, public storage and futures markets, and&#13;
non-storable goods are treated.&#13;
The more important conclusions that arise from this work are: that&#13;
some countries may lose from price stabilization even though there is a net&#13;
global gain; that liberalized trade reduces the need for buffer stocks; that&#13;
futures markets reduce instability at a lower cost than buffer stocks; that&#13;
many national price stabilization schemes are actually price support systems&#13;
used to improve farmers' incomes; that good price forecasting is a prerequi-&#13;
site to well-managed buffer stocks; that price stability in poorer countries&#13;
is not sufficient to avoid occasional food shortages; and that food is costly&#13;
to store in developing countries and may not alleviate famine if an adequate&#13;
transportation and distribution system is not already in place.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Abreg6&#13;
La stabilisation des prix des produits de base a fait l'objet&#13;
d'une litterature tous azimuts caracterisee par des objectifs divers, des&#13;
raisonnements complexes et des conclusions peu claires. Le present expose&#13;
vise a mieux expliquer, en les simplifiant, les enseignements que l'on&#13;
peut tirer de cette somme de publications, afin de donner aux economistes&#13;
praticiens une meilleure idee des conditions a remplir pour que les sys-&#13;
temes de stabilisation des prix des produits de base soient efficaces et&#13;
des effets qu'ils ont sur le bien-etre social.&#13;
II decrit tout d'abord les bases th6oriques sur lesquelles s'est&#13;
fondee, a l'origine, l'analyse de la stabilisation des prix. II demontre&#13;
ensuite comment, avec des hypotheses moins restrictives (plus realistes),&#13;
on obtient des resultats differents. II traite notamment du stockage et&#13;
de la securit6 alimentaire, de l'inflation et du developpement 6conomique,&#13;
des stocks publics et des march6s internes ainsi que des denrees non&#13;
stockables.&#13;
Les principales conclusions du pr6sent article sont les sui-&#13;
vantes : la stabilisation des prix peut se faire au detriment de certains&#13;
pays mime si, au niveau international, le bilan est positif; la liberali-&#13;
sation des echanges rend moins necessaire l'entretien de stocks regula-&#13;
teurs; les caisses nationales de stabilisation des prix sont souvent, en&#13;
r6alite, des systemes de soutien des prix qui servent a ameliorer les&#13;
revenus agricoles; pour gerer au mieux les stocks regulateurs, il est&#13;
indispensable de pouvoir disposer d'un bon systeme de prevision des prix;&#13;
la stabilite des prix ne suffit pas a garantir les pays pauvres de toute&#13;
p6nurie alimentaire; enfin, le stockage des denrees alimentaires est coci-&#13;
teux pour les pays en developpement et risque de n'etre guere utile en cas&#13;
de famine sans un reseau suffisamment d6veloppe de transport et de dis-&#13;
tribution des produits.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
EXTRACTO&#13;
La literatura sobre estabilizaci6n de precios de los productos&#13;
basicos es muy amplia, tiene objetivos diversos y una construcci6n te6rica&#13;
compleja y sus resultados son desconcertantes. Este ensayo tiene por&#13;
objeto aclarar y simplificar los resultados de esta amplia literatura, a&#13;
fin de dar al economista operacional una idea mas precisa de las condicio-&#13;
nes en que los m6todos de estabilizaci6n de precios de los productos bAsi-&#13;
cos resultaran satisfactorios y de los efectos de dichos metodos desde el&#13;
punto de vista del bienestar.&#13;
En el ensayo se comienza por introducir el primer marco dentro&#13;
del cual se analiz6 la estabilizaci6n de precios y luego se liberalizan&#13;
los supuestos de ese primer modelo para demostrar la varianza de los&#13;
resultados en distintas situaciones (mas realistas). Se tratan temas como&#13;
el almacenamiento y la seguridad de los alimentos, la inflaci6n y el desa-&#13;
rrollo econ6mico, el almacenamiento publico y los mercados de futuros, y&#13;
los bienes no almacenables.&#13;
Las conclusiones mas importantes que se derivan de este trabajo&#13;
son las siguientes: que la estabilizaci6n de precios puede perjudicar a&#13;
algunos paises aun cuando el total de paises se beneficie globalmente; que&#13;
el comercio liberalizado reduce la necesidad de mantener existencias regu-&#13;
ladoras; que los mercados de futuros reducen la inestabilidad a un costo&#13;
menor que las existencias reguladoras; que muchos sistemas nacionales de&#13;
estabilizaci6n de precios son en realidad sistemas de precios de sustenta-&#13;
ci6n que se usan para incrementar los ingresos de los agricultores; que el&#13;
pron6stico acertado de los precios es indispensable para administrar efi-&#13;
cientemente las existencias reguladoras; que en los paises mas pobres la&#13;
estabilidad de los precios no basta para evitar la escasez ocasional de&#13;
alimentos, y que en los paises en desarrollo el almacenamiento de los&#13;
alimentos es caro y quizAs no permita aliviar la hambruna si no existe un&#13;
sistema adecuado de transporte y distribuci6n.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE C? CONTENr&#13;
Page&#13;
1. Squniary' ............ ........ ..***...... ...... . .. ..*...........  1&#13;
2.  Introduction ................................ ..... .....  ....  8&#13;
3.  The Early Framework .............*............                  8&#13;
4.  Partial Price Stabilization ................   ...............  17&#13;
5.  Price vs. Income Stabilization . ............... ...  .........  18&#13;
6.  Instability in Imperfect Markets            .........          20&#13;
7.  International Trade Cases . ................................   23&#13;
8.  Nonlinearity and Multiplicative Disturbances ............. .   27&#13;
9.  A Utility-Maximizing Approach .............................    34&#13;
10. Formation of Expectations . ................................   36&#13;
11. Price Instability, Storage and Food Security       ..............  39&#13;
12. Instability, Inflation and Economic Development      ...........  49&#13;
13. Public Storage, Private Storage and Futures Markets     .......  50&#13;
14. Supply Response and Risk Preferences        ......................  56&#13;
15. Multiple Policy Instruments and Goals       .....................  58&#13;
16. Nonstorable Goods ...........    ..............................  62&#13;
17. Instability, Storage and the Pure Theory of Trade     .........  64&#13;
18. Emnpirical Results ............   .............................  68&#13;
19q 1 D  D D C  __________________. Re e en e   _  ......................................................................  77&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
1&#13;
COMMODITY PRICE STABILIZATION: THEORY AND APPLICATIONS&#13;
Summary&#13;
Research on price stabilization is diverse in objectives, methods&#13;
and assumptions; it ranges from highly sophisticated theoretical and&#13;
empirical models to somewhat rather simplistic approaches. Because of&#13;
this, it is extremely difficult to grasp the essence of this vast and&#13;
somewhat confusing literature. As a result, this paper highlights the&#13;
results from research on commodity price stabilization. Among the&#13;
major conclusions are:&#13;
1. Many of the early theoretical developments focussed on the effects&#13;
of price stabilization both in aggregate and from a distributional&#13;
viewpoint. Generally price stabilization leads to a net welfare&#13;
improvement especially in those cases where it is accompanied by&#13;
income stabilization. A net welfare improvement implies that if&#13;
there are losers from price stabilization, the gainers could&#13;
easily compensate this sector such that everyone could be made&#13;
better off.&#13;
2. In terms of distributional effects, the results are very sensitive&#13;
to model specification. Producers can lose or gain from stabili-&#13;
zation depending on such factors as the source of the instability&#13;
and the degree of non-linearity in demand and supply curves.&#13;
Producers generally prefer price instability to stability in those&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2&#13;
cases where:   (a) they are good at price forecasting, (b) the&#13;
government provides price supports which prevents substantial&#13;
price falls in a down market and/or (c) producers are risk takers.&#13;
3.  From a trading standpoint, certain countries may actually lose&#13;
from price stabilization even though the net gain to all countries&#13;
taken together is positive. Thus with compensation all can be&#13;
made better off with price stabilization. In terms of countries&#13;
generally major exporters lose fron price stabilization especially&#13;
export producers.&#13;
4.  The distribution issue does point to a major problem with inter-&#13;
national reserves.    Some countries and hence groups within&#13;
countries may actually lose from stabilization even though all&#13;
countries taken together gain. f Thus, why should all countries&#13;
want to contribute to an international buffer stock? Theory and&#13;
empirical evidence suggest that the importers of food should hold&#13;
larger reserves than has traditionally been the case.&#13;
5.  The gains from stabilization are generally small if risk is not an&#13;
important factor.   However, in cases where price stabilization&#13;
schemes reduce risk and where producers are risk averse, the gains&#13;
resulting because of added supply response far outweigh the gains&#13;
from riskless price stabilization schemes (i.e., schemes which&#13;
reduce risk but do not trigger a producer supply response).&#13;
6. Liberalized trade greatly reduces the need for buffer stocks since&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3&#13;
trade itself has a price stabilizing effect. Hence the gains from&#13;
price stabilization while positive are smaller with free trade&#13;
than when trade distortions exist. The need for buffer stocks&#13;
also is diminished when risk sharing can be facilitated through&#13;
such means as international futures markets, efficient credit&#13;
markets and international investments in securities.&#13;
7. In many cases, price stabilization schemes are introduced where&#13;
price and income policies are already in effect.    Some of the&#13;
literature considers price stabilization jointly with such&#13;
policies as price supports.    Generally, the effectiveness of&#13;
stabilization is reduced when other policies exist.&#13;
8. Fbr many commodities, futures markets exist.     Their existence&#13;
generally reduces price irstability. WMere futures markets are&#13;
feasible, they may be a less costly way to reduce instability then&#13;
are buffer stocks. Also, where stabilization schemes are used to&#13;
reduce producer risk in the presence of already functioning&#13;
futures, the gain may be negligible since one of the reasons why&#13;
futures markets exist is to provide a price hedge for those who&#13;
want to minimize risk exposure.&#13;
9. Stocks are held by both the private and public sectors. Private&#13;
holdings include storage by farmers. Generally, as government&#13;
increase their size of stocks, the private sector reduces its&#13;
holdings. Thus, how large an optimal government stockpile should&#13;
be depends in part on how the private sector responds. If there&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4&#13;
is a one to one substitution, government stockholding is generally&#13;
not needed unless it is used, for example, to support farm&#13;
incomes. At the extreme, where either stocks are entirely held&#13;
privately or publically the variability in farmers' incomes will&#13;
generally be greater under publically held stocks than if storage&#13;
is done by the private sector.&#13;
10. Gcvernment owned reserves do not always exist as merely an&#13;
instrument to bring about price stability. They generally are a&#13;
result of price support policies to improve farmers' incomes.&#13;
When government puts in place a price support system which&#13;
prevents producer prices from falling in an abundant supply&#13;
periods, the government generally ends up buying the quantity&#13;
which the market can't clear at the support price (certain&#13;
countries will subsidize the producers to hold part of this&#13;
stock).   These stocks are released in tight market situations.&#13;
However, the size of the stockpiling activity is generally greater&#13;
than what would be needed if the sole aim were price stabilization&#13;
rather than farm income enhancement.     Seldom is the role of&#13;
government stockpiling solely one of price stabilization.&#13;
11. In many countries, price stabilization schemes are tied to farm&#13;
income programs. Stocks are not used merely to facilitate the&#13;
efficient functioning of markets. In this regard, farmer held&#13;
reserves might even be larger than if government and/or private&#13;
stocks were used only for price stabilizing means.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
5&#13;
12. Certain commodities cannot be stored. In such cases governments&#13;
often introduce a price stabilization scheme which is supposed to&#13;
be self-financing (i.e., a deficiency payment is used in low&#13;
market periods along with a producer tax during good market&#13;
periods). However, generally such schemes turn out to be income&#13;
enhancing for producers since the government outlay exceeds the&#13;
tax.&#13;
13. From a private firm standpoint, if it has sufficient market power&#13;
it will use storage in order to manufacture price instability and&#13;
gain as a result.    This phenomenon also applied to a food&#13;
importer with market power. Also multiproduct firms may prefer&#13;
price stability for the major crop produced but prefer instability&#13;
in minor crops.  This result is important since marketing boards&#13;
are often used as marketing institutions.    In cases where they&#13;
aren't used to tax producers, they are often supported to market&#13;
major crops but minor crops can be left to the open market.&#13;
14. Theory shows that the optimal amount of storage should allow&#13;
prices to fluctuate within some band (i.e., with positive storage&#13;
costs complete price stabilization is not optimal).  The empirical&#13;
studies are generally consistent with the theoretical develop-&#13;
ments.   They show that often government stockpiling is nuch&#13;
greater than that needed to bring about an optimal allocation of&#13;
resources. It thus appears that for countries such as the U.S.,&#13;
storage activities have resulted in a misallocation of resources.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6&#13;
15. Empirical studies show that good price forecasts are needed to&#13;
optimally manage buffer stocks.    Also, because of the large&#13;
fluctuations in prices of agricultural commodities, a storage&#13;
policy should provide flexibility in both the build up and release&#13;
of stocks. Generally, this flexibility has been lacking in past&#13;
stock policies.&#13;
16. There is now a vast literature on food security and the role of&#13;
buffer stocks to meet emergency food needs. It does not follow&#13;
that price stability brought about in commercial markets through&#13;
buffer stocks guarantees on adequate supply of food during extreme&#13;
droughts in poor countries.   Some of the early studies on this&#13;
subject suggest that a buffer stock be set up specially targeted&#13;
to meet the emergency needs of poor countries. These stocks would&#13;
be separate from working stocks which are needed in comnercial&#13;
markets.&#13;
17. Recent studies on the food security issue conclude that even with&#13;
price stability poor countries still experience famine when&#13;
production shortfalls occur.    They contend that the problem is a&#13;
shortage of foreign exchange in order to purchase food.     They&#13;
propose the setting up of a foreign exchange reserve to be made&#13;
available to poor countries so that the stocks can actually be&#13;
purchased during periods of famine.   The idea is to store money&#13;
not food because it is not the lack of food on a worldwide basis&#13;
that is the problem.   The problem lies in the lack of purchasing&#13;
power to buy it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
7&#13;
18. Food is costly to store in less developed countries. In addition,&#13;
it has to be stored in places where it can be easily accessible&#13;
for famine relief. Thus good transportation becomes vital to&#13;
avoid famines. A good transportation system along with financial&#13;
reserves would greatly reduce starvation during severe production&#13;
shortfalls in less developed countries. In the past, there have&#13;
been famines in poor countries even though large amounts of grain&#13;
were in storage in developed countries.     Thus, even though&#13;
stability in commercial markets adds to food price stability to&#13;
poor countries, there is no guarantee that the poor countries will&#13;
receive any of the benefits from such a scheme.&#13;
19. Future research has to tie the food security issue and the price&#13;
stabilization schemes for cammercial markets together. The theory&#13;
does not pay adequate attention to the effects of instability on&#13;
poor people.  The sophisticated programming models also generally&#13;
lump poor and rich importing countries together.       Further&#13;
modelling should treat the less developed countries as a separate&#13;
region.&#13;
20. Because the private sector can perform at least part of the&#13;
storage function to stabilize conrercial markets coupled with the&#13;
fact the advanced countries over stock because of public stock-&#13;
holding due to income support policies, agencies such as the World&#13;
Bank might well focus only on the food security issue and develop&#13;
means to implement, for example, a financial reserve mechanism.&#13;
Often there are excess stocks, for example, in the U.S., and&#13;
insufficient stocks in poor countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
8&#13;
Introduction&#13;
The dramatic increase in commodity price instability in the 1970's&#13;
brought with it a voluminous literature on its effects. Some of these&#13;
studies were of a highly theoretical nature while others were quanti-&#13;
tative and applied. However, even though most of the studies were&#13;
initiated after the decade of the sixties, formal treatment of the&#13;
effects of price instability was presented in 1944 by Waugh. It was&#13;
this paper which laid the groundwork for the early theoretical work on&#13;
price instability. However, the theoretical developments in this area&#13;
since Waugh's seminal paper, have gone in many different directions as&#13;
have the empirical analysis.&#13;
Because the literature on the welfare effects of price instability&#13;
is so vast and in a sense does not contain any unifying theme, it is&#13;
difficult for someone not dealing in this area to quickly grasp the&#13;
implications of this research for economic policy analyses and imple-&#13;
mentation.  Consequently, the purpose of this paper is to review the&#13;
literature on price stabilization and highlight the key conclusions&#13;
reached.&#13;
The Early Framework&#13;
Much of the discussion on the effects of price instability has&#13;
focused on agricultural commodities where stochastic fluctuations in&#13;
demand and supply can be particularly important.     In 1944 Waugh&#13;
analyzed the effects of price instability on consumers.      'This&#13;
methodology was later extended by others to other sectors in the&#13;
economy.   The Waugh conclusion was that consumers preferred price&#13;
instability to stability--a conclusion which to many is counter-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
9&#13;
intuitive. How then, did Waugh arrive at this result?&#13;
His results are developed in Figure 1 where D represents demand&#13;
and consumers face prices P1 and P2, each of which occurs half the&#13;
time, i.e., with probability 0.5.     These price variations may be&#13;
caused by random fluctuations in supply between S1 and S2. When price&#13;
is P1, consumers buy q1 so that consumer real income (surplus) is&#13;
represented by area a + b + c. (The areas are bounded only by solid&#13;
lines).   when price is P2, consumers buy q2 so that consumer real&#13;
income is represented by area a. On the other hand, if prices are&#13;
stabilized by a Government policy at the average price level, wp = (p1&#13;
+ P2)/2, then consumption takes place at qo with consumer real income&#13;
represented by area a + b.&#13;
FIGURE 1&#13;
price&#13;
p2~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
"p&#13;
p1&#13;
I        i         I                       .&#13;
q2        qo       q,       quantity/U.t.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
10&#13;
'Ib investigate why Waugh arrived at his result, note that half the&#13;
time consumers gain area b as price is lowered from P2 to pp, but the&#13;
other half of the time consumers lose area c as price is raised from&#13;
P1 to pp.   Since P2 - 1'P = pP - Pl, the loss obviously outweighs the&#13;
gain; the average loss is 1/2 (area c - area b). Thus consumers&#13;
prefer price instability if they can take advantage of it by buying&#13;
more at &#142;-i prices and less at high prices.&#13;
'The concept underlying the above analysis is that of "econanic&#13;
surplus." Waugh used the concept of consumers' surplus while later&#13;
the notion of economic rent or producers' surplus will also be&#13;
entertained. There is a vast literature on whether or not this&#13;
concept has a legitimate use in economics (Currie, Murphy and Schmitz,&#13;
Just, Hueth and Schmitz).    It forms the basis for applied welfare&#13;
economics. In the case of consumers' surplus it is the area below the&#13;
demand curve bounded by the equilibrium price line. This area is a&#13;
money measure of willingness to pay. Ebr example, in Figure 1 the&#13;
area c represent how much a consumer is willing to pay to have the&#13;
price drop from pp to p1.&#13;
Fbllowing Waugh another somewhat counterinituitive result was&#13;
presented in 1961 by Oi on producers' preferences for instability. Oi&#13;
showed that they also preferred instability to stability.       To&#13;
understand his results, consider Figure 2 where supply is represented&#13;
by S and producers are confronted with two prices, P1, and P2, each of&#13;
which occurs with probability 0.5. These price variations may be&#13;
caused by random variation in demand between D1 and D2. When price is&#13;
P1, producers will ql so that producer real income (surplus) is repre-&#13;
sented by area a.   When price is P2, producers sell q2 so that real&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
'I&#13;
FIGURE 2&#13;
price&#13;
p2&#13;
P &#13;
C  ~ ~ ~  ~  ~~~D            I&#13;
p2                                       21&#13;
1          q         q2    quantityIut.&#13;
income is represented by area a + b + c.    On the other hand, if prices&#13;
are stabilized by some means such as Government policy at the average&#13;
price level lip = (P1 - P2)/2, then production is qO and producer&#13;
welfare is represented by area a + b. Where price would otherwise be&#13;
p1, producers gain area b and where price would otherwise be P2,&#13;
producers lose area c with stabilization. Since P2 - uP = PP - Pl,&#13;
the latter loss is larger than the former gain; and since each occurs&#13;
half the time, producers lose on average fron price stabilization&#13;
(unless supply is completely inelastic).&#13;
The key to the above analysis is that producers can adjust&#13;
instantaneously to price changes. This inplies that in Figure 2 the&#13;
high price corresponds with the high quantity. One can arrive at the&#13;
same result by assuming, for example, that producer's expected price&#13;
and expected output at the time of planting are actually realized. In&#13;
Figure 2, P2 and q2 can be expected price and expected quantity both&#13;
of which are realized.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
12&#13;
If the above results are correct, why do policy makers introduce&#13;
policies which are aimed at price stabilization? As we shall see,&#13;
this policy aim is correct since stabilization is preferred when both&#13;
consumers and producers are considered jointly. Samuelson argued that&#13;
in fact, an economy cannot "pull itself up by the bootstraps" by&#13;
sinply-generating instability. The consumers gain fran instability in&#13;
the Waugh case because there is in essence a Santa Claus in the&#13;
background who is losing.   The same is true in the Oi analysis. Thie&#13;
economic surplus to make both consumers and producers better off fran&#13;
instability has to come from scmewhere and as Massell (1969) showed&#13;
this needed surplus is nowhere to be found when consumers and&#13;
producers are considered jointly.&#13;
The Massell approach is presented in Figure 3A. Consumer demand&#13;
is represented by D and that stochastic supply is represented by S1&#13;
and S2, each of which occurs in alternating periods.    Thus, equili-&#13;
brium prices are P1 and P2, respectively.    Assume that prices are&#13;
stabilized at p, say, by means of a buffer stock authority which buys&#13;
excess supply, q1' - qO, when S, occurs and sells qO - q2 when S2&#13;
occurs. In the event of S1, consumers lose area c + d while producers&#13;
gain area c + d + e for a net gain of area e. With S2, producers lose&#13;
area a but consumers gain a + b for a net gain of area b.  The average&#13;
overall effect of price stabilization with such a reserve policy is a&#13;
gain of 1/2 (area b + area e).  This result implies that the loss fran&#13;
stabilization for consumers offsets some of the gain for producers who&#13;
are benefited by stability. Furthermore, the gain for producers more&#13;
than offsets the consumer loss.&#13;
The results in Figure 3B are for fluctuations in demand. With&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
X X  X              --           - - - &#13;
X  - - - ---- - - - --W&#13;
N-  ~   ~    ~   ~ ~ ~    X\          C&#13;
I2  -  -  -  -1 -  -0-  -  -  -  -  -  -   -  - ---  -  -  -  -  -  -  -  -  -  - -&#13;
.7  \  '&#13;
C43 \4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
14&#13;
price varying between D1 and p1 and D2 and P2, respectively, price&#13;
stabilization at vp via a buffer stock leads to a gain of area e if D&#13;
occurs or of area c if D12 occurs. On average, the producer loss of&#13;
1/2 [area (a +b) - area (d + e)] is more than offset by a consumer&#13;
gain of 1/2 [area (a + b + c) - area d].l&#13;
The results suggest that society benefits by stabilizing prices of&#13;
storable cormmodities through a reset-.re policy if storage costh are not&#13;
excessive.  Hbwever, what is equally as interesting is that even&#13;
though society gains there are both gainers and losers fran stabiliza-&#13;
tion policies. In Figure 3A consumers lose from stability while in&#13;
Figure 3B producers lose from stability. However, one group gains&#13;
more from stability than what the other loses. As a result, through&#13;
some form of a conpensation, everyone can gain from a price&#13;
stabilization policy.&#13;
At this point one 'doesn't find it hard to believe that society&#13;
benefits from price stabilization. What's difficult to understand is&#13;
why with demand shifts producers prefer price instability to stability&#13;
-the result also obtained by Oi. As Figure 4 shows using the Massell&#13;
framework this result need not hold. -As the results show, producers&#13;
are indifferent to instability vs stability and consumers gain from&#13;
stability; stability is Pareto superior. In Figure 4 the right hand&#13;
side of the diagram shows the mrodel in Figure 3B-the Oi-Massell&#13;
results.   The new results are derived in the larger of the two&#13;
diagrams.   The notion of planning curves are introduced-S is the&#13;
1 Additional results for the vertical market case are given in Just&#13;
and Salk in. Also a somewhat different approach to stabilization&#13;
analysis is given in Knapp.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
15&#13;
FIGLTE 4&#13;
p&#13;
p&#13;
S(planning)&#13;
P2                                                  Pp&#13;
p1~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
D (ssell-Oi f1,bdel                Q&#13;
(planning)~&#13;
Q                               Q&#13;
planning supply curve (ex ante) and D is the planning demand curve (ex&#13;
ante).   If no random terms are introduced P and Q are both expected&#13;
and realized prices and quantities.    In the model a random term is&#13;
introduced in the demand curve hence D is no longer an exact&#13;
relationship between P and Q.    Consistent with Massell's model we&#13;
assur,e that there is a probability of .5 of demand being either above&#13;
or below D.    (We have sketched in demand curves D1I and       to2 t&#13;
correspond with D1 and D2 in the right hand side of the diagram.) It&#13;
is clear that even though demand is stochastic the expected price and&#13;
output at planting is PQ. Now since supply is nonrandom realized&#13;
output is Q. However realized price is not P. If demand is D2 price&#13;
is P2 and if demand is D1 price is P1*    Prices can be stabilized by&#13;
storing ae when demand is D1 and releasing it when demand is D * Note&#13;
now how different the results are from the Massell-Oi model.&#13;
Producers there preferred price instability-now they are indifferent:&#13;
2(PQ)   P2Q + P1Q.   Consumers clearly prefer stability   thus a buffer&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
16&#13;
stock scheme is Pareto Superior to no buffer stocks-the opposite to&#13;
the Massell-Oi result.    Also what is interesting is: (1) price&#13;
variability is greater in our model, (2) storage needed to bring about&#13;
stability is greater and (3) the benefits fron stabilization are&#13;
greater.   On the last point the shaded areas are the gains in&#13;
Massell-Oi's framework.    This underestimates the gains by the&#13;
cross-hatched area ace.&#13;
Why the different results?     The difference is due to how&#13;
instability is generated in the model and how much information is&#13;
assumed. In the Oi-Massell model the high price corresponds to the&#13;
high output and vice versa. That is, ex ante expectations and actual&#13;
outcomes coincide (i.e. demand D1 and D2 are known with certainty at&#13;
the time of planting). This assumption however is unrealistic and&#13;
inconsistent with the Massell-Oi mathematical model where demand is&#13;
random and where different outcomes are assigned a .5 probability. In&#13;
this case, as we show, there is no output adjustment to demand&#13;
fluctuations; only prices adjust if there is no storage.       With&#13;
coiplete storage however, expected price equals actual price.&#13;
Hbwever, in the Massell-Oi graphical model this is not the case.&#13;
As a caveat, it is clear in the Oi-Massell framework why producers&#13;
prefer price instability to stability.    This is because at the high&#13;
price, output is large but at the low price output is low. Generally,&#13;
in reality high prices correspond to low output-not the other way&#13;
around. It is easy to make money in the Oi situation because of&#13;
perfect foresight just like it is to "buy low and sell high".     The&#13;
problem in reality however, is running the risk of "buying high and&#13;
selling low".   This is why in the left hand side of the diagram&#13;
expected or planning price equals the realized price with storage (in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
17&#13;
the Oi-Massell result the storage price or stabilized price is between&#13;
these two expected prices).2&#13;
Partial Price Stablization&#13;
In the above discussion storage is assumed to be costless.   When&#13;
positive storage costs are introduced, it is no longer optimal to&#13;
pursue complete price stabilization.3 Massell (1970) early introduced&#13;
a partial stabilization scheme notion and it was still later&#13;
elaborated on by Just and Schmitz and Turnovsky (1979). TIhis buffer&#13;
stock policy has the effect of miodifying the demand curve by&#13;
purchasing and selling quantities to make up the difference in actual&#13;
and modified demand (Figure 5). The market demand in the absence of&#13;
storage is D.  Producer expected price is P and expected output is Q.&#13;
Let the disturbance be due to supply fluctuations such that in one&#13;
period output is    and in the second period output is Q1. A modified&#13;
demand curve of D in essence yields a price band pOP* since Q2Q* is&#13;
m2&#13;
stored in one period giving price P* in that period; stocks are&#13;
released in the high price period giving price Po.&#13;
The above imodel in essence uses a linear adjustment rule which&#13;
ensures that a fixed proportion of the excess of any given crop over a&#13;
2 The Oi-Massell model of instability generated because of demand&#13;
fluctuations has been applied by Tisdell to price stabilization&#13;
schemes in the Australian wool industry.      He concluded that&#13;
stabilization of wool prices by the Wool Ccumission may reduce the&#13;
average annual net income of growers and also of manufacturers of&#13;
wool.&#13;
3 As Newbery and Stiglitz (1981) show, if output fluctuations are&#13;
uncorrelated through time, there will come a point where with total&#13;
price stabilization the stock pile will become exhausted making&#13;
ccmplete price stabilization infeasible.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
18&#13;
Figure 5&#13;
p&#13;
p&#13;
1&#13;
po&#13;
p2&#13;
Q1      Q0   QQ*         Q2           Q&#13;
normal crop is saved for times of shortage. However, not all partial&#13;
stabilization schemes follow a linear adjustment rule. A non-linear&#13;
adjustment rule is needed when buffer stocks alter the probability&#13;
distribution of the market price in a nonsymmetric way.   In practice,&#13;
the most common scheme of partial price stabilization is that of a&#13;
price band (i.e., the authority allows prices to fluctuate between PC)&#13;
and P* (Figure 5). However, as will be discussed later, adjusting&#13;
stocks so as to operate within a specified price band may be non-&#13;
optimal.&#13;
Price vs. Income Stabilization&#13;
An important point raised by Newbery and Stiglitz (1981) and&#13;
Bigman is that in some cases stabilization of prices enhances income&#13;
variability. Their proof is mathematical.4 However one can show this&#13;
4 They show that the result holds when demand elasticity &gt; 1/2.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
19&#13;
result using the Massell framework in which it is also possible to&#13;
discuss the role of private vs. public stockholding.     In Figure 6,&#13;
price fluctuations are caused by supply fluctuations.       Without&#13;
storage, producer incomes over the two periods are PlQl and P2Q2.&#13;
Income is less than if U is sold both periods since 2(P OQ   &gt; (P1Q  +&#13;
P2Q2). Storage, however, which stabilizes price need not yield stable&#13;
incomes. Suppose the government, for supply S1, stores 5D* and pays&#13;
producers Pu in the same period Si occurs. Then in that period income&#13;
is PuQ*. In the next period, supply is S and the governments release&#13;
the stocks.   Producer income is now only PuUo.      The scheme is&#13;
self-financing since government outlays for stocks equals the money&#13;
Figure 6&#13;
p&#13;
Pp&#13;
P21&#13;
I                Iw &#13;
QO  01 Q       Q2 Q* &#13;
received by government when stocks are released. However, now producer&#13;
income has a larger variance with government storage than if no&#13;
storage occurred. since PUQo &lt; P1 Q1 and PUQ* &gt; P2Q2. There are two&#13;
additional results worth noting: (1) producers still prefer price&#13;
stabilization even with government storage to price instability since:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
20&#13;
(PuQo + PuQ*) &gt; (PlQl + P2Q2)-    (2) In the absence of government&#13;
storage producers privately would store in view of the price&#13;
stabilization result above.   Also they may have the objective of&#13;
income stabilization which means they would store iQ* for sale in the&#13;
following period. But now note the important result: with private&#13;
storage, both income and price are stabilized since to achieve price&#13;
Pu prnducers have to store iQ* (for which they get no payment) and&#13;
sell it the following period. Thus, in the case presented, the degree&#13;
of income variability generated by price stabilization depends&#13;
critically on whether the public or the private does the storing.&#13;
Instability in Imperfect Markets&#13;
The above analysis is based on perfectly corpetitive markets.&#13;
Here we show some of the results in a closed economy model where&#13;
imperfectly competitive markets exist.   Several cases were considered&#13;
by Bieri and Schmitz (1974).    Their sinplist case of a producer&#13;
marketing board with monopoly power is presented in Figure 7.&#13;
FIGURE 7&#13;
p&#13;
ES&#13;
5&#13;
l    I                              Q&#13;
01  *  Q)                         Q&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
21&#13;
Consider a market were AR is the average revenue curve and MR is&#13;
the corresponding marginal revenue schedule.      Fbr a two-period&#13;
analysis, AR is also the sum of marginal revenue schedules.       A&#13;
ronopolist marketing board will equate AR with the sum of the supply&#13;
schedules S and S1 which is denoted by r S. Consumer prices are&#13;
stabilized at P* as are producer prices at Ps. This is brought about&#13;
by storage by the board (Q*Q2 in the surplus year to be released in&#13;
the deficit year).&#13;
A nore complicated case was developed by Bieri and Schmitz where a&#13;
marketing firm has both monopoly and monopsony power. The analysis&#13;
shows how such a firm will use storage to stabilize consumer prices&#13;
but destabilize producer prices. The firm in essence buys the large&#13;
quantity at a low price and buys a small quantity at a higher price.&#13;
In this case the producer supply curve is downward sloping. These&#13;
type of models clearly demonstrate that storage by private firms&#13;
improve their economic position but at the expense of other groups.&#13;
The losses are born by consumers and/or producers. Also, as these&#13;
models show, price instability can be "manufactured".      'Ibis is&#13;
opposite to the type of price instability in the Waugh, Oi and Massell&#13;
models where instability is due to natural phenomena such as weather.&#13;
Even though the manufactured price instability model was developed&#13;
for a no trade environment, Schmitz et al. (Dec., 1981) in a recent&#13;
book on Grain Export Cartels argue that this phenomenon might also&#13;
apply to trade in wheat and feedgrains. They contend, for example,&#13;
that the Soviet Union gives false price signals in the market which&#13;
encourage production which is later sold at prices below the cost of&#13;
production.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
22&#13;
Recent papers have also examined storage in imperfect markets but&#13;
from a different perspective. Young and Schmitz consider the case&#13;
where production is controlled by a cartel which behaves as a&#13;
monopolist. They allow for fluctuations in both demand and supply and&#13;
consider cases where the high demand occurs during the high cost, low&#13;
production period (eg. milk). In the case of milk, it can be stored&#13;
as powder and reconstituted such that the end product is indistin-&#13;
guishable from fresh milk. Ihe authors, through a somewhat compli-&#13;
cated supply and demand nodel, try to answer why producers have&#13;
opposed the introduction of reconstituted milk into the market since&#13;
at first glance it would appear that storage should increase producer&#13;
profits. They show that profits can be lower with storage and uniform&#13;
pricing. Also, given the magnitude of the dairy price supports,&#13;
storage can be nonprofitable for a producer cartel.&#13;
Newbery rigorously derives results for the optimal stock rule for&#13;
a monopolist. The optimum storage rule is nonlinear. Also he shows&#13;
that: (1) a monopoly stocking rule leads to larger storage than under&#13;
competition, (2) a monopolist facing a stable linear 'demand schedule&#13;
will undertake more price stabilization through storage activities&#13;
than a competitive market producing the same average supply (this&#13;
result does not hold for all demand schedules) and (3) if an inter-&#13;
national buffer agency is set up and instructed to maintain prices&#13;
within a bandwidth then a monopolist will be able to speculate against&#13;
the agency. However under a ccmpetitive rule this would not happen.&#13;
Also there would be cases when the monopolist would perform no&#13;
storage.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
23&#13;
Nichols and Zeckhauser develop a model which might be called&#13;
international countervailing price stabilization. They consider large&#13;
competitive consuming nations facing an export cartel.   They show that&#13;
it would generally pay the consuming nations to build up a strategic&#13;
stockpile, whose presence would suppress price in future periods even&#13;
when the supply conditions of the producing cartel were nonrandom and&#13;
stationary.   In the Schmitz et al. Grain Export Cartel book they&#13;
contend that importers exert monopsony power through such devices as&#13;
optimal tariffs and they propose pricing and storage strategies to&#13;
deal with these distortions.&#13;
International Trade Cases&#13;
The earlier competitive models were first applied to international&#13;
trade by Hueth and Schmitz.     It was shown that even with trade&#13;
countries taken together prefer price stability. Hueth and Schmitz&#13;
clearly show this by the use of excess supply and demand curves. In&#13;
Figure 8 the excess supply curve for a given good is ES (i.e. the&#13;
amount exported at different prices) while the excess demand curves&#13;
for both periods are ED and ED'. It follows from Figure 3 and 4 that&#13;
the net gain for both the importer and exporter aggregated together is&#13;
a + b.   In this case the exporter loses from stability while the&#13;
importer gains. However, if the instability was due to a stochastic&#13;
supply system the exporter would gain from stability while the&#13;
inporter would lose.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
24&#13;
FIGUR;E 8&#13;
p&#13;
ES&#13;
P2 -\&lt;/&#13;
ph&#13;
p1   0ED&#13;
Q&#13;
This model raises the interesting issue about who should hold&#13;
reserves to bring about stability. In the first case, the imrporter&#13;
should hold the largest percentage of reserves. On the basis of this&#13;
model international cooperation in setting up an international reserve&#13;
pool is difficult since the countries do not share the gains equally.5&#13;
The above framework has been used by Bieri and Schmitz (1973) to&#13;
incorporate tariff policies. It was shown that in the cptimal tariff&#13;
case an importer no longer prefers instability even when the source of&#13;
the instability is external (i.e. caused by shifts in the excess&#13;
supply curve in Figure 8).    In this nodel, the importer will impose&#13;
tariffs along with positive storage.&#13;
Also Hueth and Schmitz show that an importer    (both producers and&#13;
consumers) may prefer instability to stability when the source of the&#13;
disturbances are external to the country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
25&#13;
In summary, in an international trade context the welfare of all&#13;
countries taken together is increased by the use of storage (i.e. what&#13;
the gainers gain is more than what the losers lose). However, even&#13;
though this is true some countries may actually lose fran stability&#13;
due to storage. In these type of models the distributional effects&#13;
critically depend on such factors as the source of the instability&#13;
(i.e. whether it is generated from without or within a country) and&#13;
the height of the tariffs.&#13;
The Hueth-Schmitz model was empirically tested for the wheat and&#13;
feedgrain sectors of the United States. Konandreas and Schmitz found&#13;
that U.S. producers and consumers taken together benefit from policies&#13;
which would stabilize feed grain prices but instability was preferred&#13;
in the wheat sector.    The model upon which this conclusion rests&#13;
specifies a U.S. domestic demand relationship for food and feed use,&#13;
stock relationship and.a foreign demand sector.&#13;
A version of the Bieri-Schmitz optimal tariff model was tested by&#13;
Carter and Schmitz for U.S. and Canada wheat exports to the EEC and&#13;
6&#13;
Japan. It was found that those importing nations do in fact pursue a&#13;
tariff policy that is welfare- iproving for importers.    The optimal&#13;
tariff model was also tested by Sampson and Snape but for feedgrains&#13;
was well as wheat. Also instability created by tariffs and storage&#13;
was explicitly introduced.    Their results show that a substantial&#13;
income transfer from the major grain exporters to the EE occurs as a&#13;
6See Bale and Lutz and Lutz and Bale for welfare consequences with&#13;
price distortions.    Also see papers by Shei and Thompson and&#13;
'Tbshihisa.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
26&#13;
result of the combined tariffs and instability.   These studies are&#13;
reviewed in detail in Schmitz et al. (1981).&#13;
What is often overlooked in the literature is that the degree of&#13;
trade liberalization can affect the magnitude of price instability and&#13;
hence the need for buffer stocks. As Newbery and Stiglitz (1981)&#13;
show, international trade by reducing price instability has similar&#13;
effects to a buffer stock scheme and may be a cheaper substitute;&#13;
although, as shown earlier, storage can yield added gains to the free&#13;
trade no storage rrmdel. 'The proposition that freer trade results in&#13;
greater price stability was also shown by Sarris and Taylor (1978) and&#13;
Bigman. One of Bigman's results is given in Figure 9. Ebr example,&#13;
free trade has associated with it much less price instability than has&#13;
no trade.&#13;
ETIGU 9&#13;
Cv&#13;
(11.)&#13;
20-                        * 'Small' Country&#13;
a 'Large' Country&#13;
16-                        o 'Very Large' Country&#13;
Q-&#13;
8&#13;
0&#13;
No     Restricted  Free  'Partial' 'Solid'  'Complete'&#13;
Trade    Trade   Trade      Stabilizing Trade&#13;
Source: Bigman, p. 325.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
27&#13;
The effects of buffer stocks also critically depend on the degree&#13;
and type of market distortions present.    As Newbery and Stiglitz&#13;
(1981) show, if non-linear trade policies are used such as quotas,&#13;
price stabilization will generally yield larger benefits than if such&#13;
trade distortions are absent.&#13;
Nonlinearity and Multiplicative Disturbances&#13;
The above framework is based on linear supply and demand relation-&#13;
ships and additive disturbances (i.e., parallel shifts in supply and&#13;
demand schedules).  We relax first the linearity assumption.   Tb see&#13;
the implications of nonlinearity, consider Figure 10 where the demand&#13;
curve D is nonlinear and supply alternates between S1 and S2' Now&#13;
suppose price is stablized by purchases when supply is high and sales&#13;
from buffer stocks when supply is low. For such a buffer stock to&#13;
operate for a long period of time, the increase in stocks when supply&#13;
is high must be the sare as the decrease in stocks when supply is low.&#13;
Otherwise, the buffer stock would either tend to accumulate until some&#13;
of the stock would require disposal or stocks would tend to run out so&#13;
that the stable price could not be realized.   (This was also assumed&#13;
in the linear case). With this requirement, excess supply, q1 - qo,&#13;
at S1 is equal to excess demand q0 - q2, at S2 so the buffer stock's&#13;
sales in a short supply period are the same as their purchases in a&#13;
long supply period; thus, the net welfare effect is zero on average&#13;
with complete price stabilization (excluding storage and transactions&#13;
costs).&#13;
The stable price p in Figure 10 must be chosen so that the&#13;
horizontal distance between Sl and D is the same as between S2 and D.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
28&#13;
FIGURE 10&#13;
P2                                                 5&#13;
q2         qO         q        quantity/u.t.&#13;
2      a~~~~~&#13;
Hence, if demand is upward bending (convex) as in Figure 10, then the&#13;
stabilized price is lower than the average destabilized price; if&#13;
demand is downward bending (concave), then stabilized price is above&#13;
the average destabilized price.   TIhe welfare gains and losses for&#13;
producers and consumers in terms of areas a, b, c, d, and e in Figure&#13;
10 are exactly the same as in Figure 3A,except that areas a and b are&#13;
now relatively large and areas c, d, and e are relatively small. As a&#13;
result, an average net gain of 1/2 (area b + area e) is still&#13;
possible, but now the average consumer effect of 1/2 [area (a+b) -&#13;
area (c-d)] may be positive rather than negative (with sufficient&#13;
nonlinearity) because the stabilized price is lower than the average&#13;
destabilized price. Also, the average producer effect of 1/2 [area&#13;
(c4d+e) - area a] can possibly become negative, thus obtaining exactly&#13;
the opposite qualitative impacts on producers and consumers then was&#13;
suggested by Figure 3A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
29&#13;
A similar generalization of the analysis for the case of upward-&#13;
bending (convex) supply also shows that sufficient non-linearity in&#13;
supply can reverse the qualitative effects of price stabilization when&#13;
instability is due to fluctuations in demand. Hbwever, as before, the&#13;
net effect of price stabilization considering both sectors is&#13;
posi ve.&#13;
eabcte conclusions were suggested in a paper by Hillman,&#13;
Johnson and Gray prepared for the Food and Agricultural Organization&#13;
They state "A demand curve grown steeper at higher prices and&#13;
shallower at lower prices enhances the consumer stake while diminish-&#13;
ing the producer stake in reserves.     This calls for a dramatic&#13;
reversal from policies which accumulate reserves ostensibly in the&#13;
producer's interests, away from the notion that stocks acquisitions&#13;
benefit producers, toward explicit recognition of the overriding&#13;
consumer interest." (p. 8)&#13;
Another important issue in the stabilization literature is the&#13;
form of the disturbance as to whether it is additive or multiplica-&#13;
tive. Up to now, additive disturbances have been assumed. Additive&#13;
means that if supply or demand is written with quantity q as a&#13;
function of price p, say f(p), then the actual demand or supply curves&#13;
correspond to q = f (p) + E where E is a random disturbance with the&#13;
same variance regardless of price level, E(E) = 0. One alternative&#13;
form of disturbance defended, for example, by Turnovsky (1976) is the&#13;
multiplicative specification q = f(P)E, E(E) = 1.&#13;
To demonstrate the implications of multiplicative disturbances&#13;
graphically in Figure 11, suppose demand is stable at D but supply is&#13;
unstable with multiplicative variation represented by fluctuations&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
30&#13;
FIWCJI 11&#13;
price                                           s2&#13;
P2&#13;
up  ~ ~   aSi&#13;
p1&#13;
L;1                      &#13;
I    D&#13;
I &#13;
q 1            q O          q2            quantity/u.t.&#13;
between S1 and S2 in alternating periods.    Fbr buffer stocks to be&#13;
self-liquidating, prices must be stabilized at p where q2 - qO = qo&#13;
q1 rather than at the average destabilized price, i'p = (Pl + P2)/2&#13;
Again, the welfare effects in Figure 11 are the same as in Figure 3A in&#13;
terms of areas a, b, c, d, and e; but, again, as with nonlinearity,&#13;
areas c, d, and e are smaller than areas a and b. As supplies S1 and&#13;
S2 diverge (as the slope of Si falls), these results are accentuated&#13;
until area c + d + e = 0. Hence, with sufficiently strong multipli-&#13;
cative disturbances, net overall gains of 1/2 (area b + e) are still&#13;
possible; but, again, even the qualitative implications for indivi-&#13;
duals or groups may switch. Producers may lose (if area (c4d+e) -&#13;
area a &lt; 0] and consumers may gain [if area (a+b) - area (c4d) &gt; 01.&#13;
Results similar to those in Figure 11 can also be developed for&#13;
the case of multiplicative disturbances in demand in which case the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
31&#13;
qualitative implications can possibly be just opposite of those in&#13;
Figure 3Bwheredemand disturbances are additive.&#13;
As a caveat, a recent study by Dunn and Heien quantitatively&#13;
determined both whether consumers prefered price instability and the&#13;
magnitude of the gains. They used Monte Carlo techniques to generate&#13;
randan prices and then used a translog expenditure function to measure&#13;
the ienefits.  They conducted a large number of experiments and found&#13;
for/te realistic case that the gains frcm price instability were quiet&#13;
smajL. The average benefit was $1.14 out of $20,000 expenditure, or&#13;
.0057 percent.&#13;
The analysis incorporating both non-linear demand relationships&#13;
and multiplicative disturbances was carried out in a free trade&#13;
context by Just et al. (1978) and in a trade distorted world by Just&#13;
et al. (1977).    Unlike in the early trade results by Hueth and&#13;
Schmitz, the source of the price instability in terms of whether it is&#13;
generated within a country or externally no longer plays a key role.&#13;
This is clear from Figure 12. Suppose ED is the excess demand by an&#13;
importer and ES1 and ES2 are fluctuating excess supply curves. If ED&#13;
were linear the importer would gain from instability. However,- this&#13;
is no longer true. Using the analysis developed to this point, it is&#13;
clear that a stabilization policy which results in p is preferable&#13;
for the importer over fluctuating prices P1 and P2.&#13;
The interesting result in both of the papers by Just et al. is&#13;
that producers in exporting countries prefer instability but consumers&#13;
in inporting countries gain from stabilization. It was found that&#13;
exporting countries generally are worse off and inporting countries&#13;
better off with stabilization. However, as with all of the studies&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
32&#13;
FIGUE 12&#13;
ES&#13;
1     ~ES2&#13;
P1.&#13;
p&#13;
1&#13;
ED&#13;
surveyed to this point, with appropriate compensation the world as a&#13;
whole can actually gain from stabilization. As already pointed out,&#13;
these results were found to be the case for wheat in the study by&#13;
Konondreaus and Schmitz using the Hueth-Schmitz linear framework.&#13;
Interestingly, the degree of curvature of the excess demand curve in a&#13;
sense substitutes for the source of the instability as a major&#13;
determinant of the distributional effects of price stabilization.&#13;
Table 1 presents some of the results from the effects of price&#13;
instability in a trading context when non-linearity and multiplicative&#13;
disturbances are considered. Nbte that the strong conclusion is&#13;
supported which is that inporters prefer price stability and exporters&#13;
generally do not. Also, although some of the results are incon-&#13;
clusive, an interesting distributional effect is apparent. Producers&#13;
in both inporting and exporting countries prefer instability while&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
33&#13;
Table 1: International Price Stabilization: Who Gains and Who Loses in Polar&#13;
Cases of Nonlinearity&#13;
Demand Fluctuations in             Demand Fluctuations in&#13;
Country 1 (exporter)               Country 2 (importer)&#13;
Iffpacb       Extreme                           Extreme&#13;
Group         Nonlinearitya      Linearitya     Nonlinearitya      Linearitya&#13;
Country 1&#13;
Producers        -?&#13;
Consumers        +                 ?                +&#13;
Country          -                 +&#13;
Country 2&#13;
Producers        -                 +                                 0&#13;
Consumers        +                                  +                +&#13;
Country          +                                  +                +&#13;
World              +                 +                +                +&#13;
Supply Fluctuations in             Supply Fluctuations in&#13;
Country 1                         Country 2&#13;
Extreme                            Extreme&#13;
Nonlinearity       Linearity       Nonlinearity       Linearity&#13;
Country 1&#13;
Producers        -?&#13;
Consumers        +                 ?               +&#13;
Country          -?&#13;
Country 2&#13;
Producers                 -                                          +&#13;
Consumers        +                 +                +                 0&#13;
Country          +                 +                +                 +&#13;
World              +                 +                +                 +&#13;
a + indicates a gain; - indicates a loss; 0 indicates no inpact; and&#13;
? indicates uncertain.&#13;
b Country 1 is the exporter and and Country 2 is the imhporter.&#13;
Source: Richard E. Just, E. Lutz, A. Schmitz and S. Turnovsky,   "'The&#13;
Distribution of Welfare Gains fran International Price Stabilization&#13;
Under Distortions", American Journal of Aqricultural Economics,&#13;
Vol. 59, November, 1977, p. 658. &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
34&#13;
consumers in both prefer stability.    In this regard, the preference&#13;
for stability by consumers in importing countries is stronger than foi&#13;
consumers in exporting countries.&#13;
A Utility-Maximizing Approach&#13;
The Waugh and Oi analysis outlined earlier have been generalized&#13;
by Hanoch to a multicommodity situation.    In generalizing the Waugh&#13;
approach, the benefits are included in terms of a concave (or convex)&#13;
utility function, rather than in terms of consumers' surplus.&#13;
Turnovsky, Shalit and Schmitz, also using the indirect utility&#13;
approach, show under what conditions the Waugh proposition holds.&#13;
They derive the following expression:&#13;
sgn / a2v   = sgn [s1(n-r)-                        (1)&#13;
where P1 = random selling price of good 1&#13;
V = indirect utility function&#13;
r = a2VA M2.M = coefficient of relative risk aversion&#13;
s= P1C14M = share of consumer's budget allocated to good 1&#13;
e = own unoompensated price elasticity of demand for good 1&#13;
n = income elasticity of demand for good 1.&#13;
It follows that the desirability of price instability depends on&#13;
the share of the consumer's budget allocated to the commodity. Also&#13;
the desirability of price stability decreases with the magnitude of&#13;
the price and income elasticities but increases with the coefficient&#13;
of relative risk aversion. While it is possible for a2V/aP2 &lt; O (in&#13;
which case Waugh's proposition does not hold), Turnovsky et al. use&#13;
empirical evidence to suggest thata2V/aP2 &gt; 0 in which case the Waugh&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
35&#13;
proposition holds true.   (Note that Dunn and Heien also found this to&#13;
be true in the translog approach).&#13;
Schmitz, Shalit and T'urnovsky also applied the above framework to&#13;
a rulti product firm case in which they express producer's utility in&#13;
terms of the prevailing input and output prices. They develcp the&#13;
following criterion.&#13;
sgn ( 2V/aP2) = sgn  [(r)        -rJ                         (2)&#13;
where ej = a       -j, price elasticity of supply&#13;
a ) yi&#13;
y = -irU", Arrow-Pratt measure of relative risk aversion&#13;
-U'&#13;
1V = profit margin as measured by profit to cost ratio&#13;
aj = total revenue contributed by good j.&#13;
In the single product case (not shown in (2), aj not present), if&#13;
firms are risk-neutral a2VkP2 depends solely on the slope of the&#13;
supply curve. As long as it is positive, Oi's result holds. This&#13;
result that producers prefer price instability will, of course,&#13;
continue to hold if firms are risk takers (r &lt; 0). However, if r &gt; 0&#13;
the result may cease to apply.     As the degree of relative risk&#13;
aversion increases, so does the firm's preferences for stability-over&#13;
instability.&#13;
Fbr the multiproduct firm (2) applies since unlike for the single&#13;
produce case the term a    is added.   Whether or not a firm prefers&#13;
price instability with respect to a single good of the many it&#13;
produces depends in addition to the determinants in the single good&#13;
case the total revenue contributed by this good. A risk-averse firm&#13;
may prefer instability in some of the markets for its products and not&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
36&#13;
in others. However, as (2) shows the firm is likely to prefer price&#13;
instability in those goods that contribute relatively little to its&#13;
total revenue.&#13;
In a different framework Newbery and Stiglitz (1981) also discuss&#13;
the implications of price stabilization when more than one product is&#13;
considered.   They argue that price stabilization for one of the&#13;
products may increase income risk. "If the farmer is widely diver-&#13;
sified and the income variability fran the crop were uncorrelated with&#13;
his other sources of income, then the variability in this source of&#13;
income has a negligible effect on the welfare of the individual...&#13;
Fbr crcps whose return is negatively correlated with income from all&#13;
sources in the aggregate, the reduction in income variability would&#13;
actually increase total income risk and hence have a deleterious&#13;
effect on welfare." p. 27&#13;
Fbrmation of Expectations&#13;
The above mncdels generally assume that producers ex ante price and&#13;
quantity expectations are actually realized. 'This essentially assumes&#13;
that they have perfect foresight.    Tufrnovsky (1974) relaxed this&#13;
assumption and analyzed this effects of price stabilization for two&#13;
different price expectation forrulations: Adaption Expectations and&#13;
Rational Expections.7&#13;
7 Consumers are still assumed to make their decisions on the basis of&#13;
actual prices.   These nmcdels are spelled out in more detail in&#13;
Turnovsky (1978), pp. 119-48.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
37&#13;
(a) Adaptive Expectations&#13;
In the adaptive expectations framework supply decisions are based&#13;
on anticipated prices as follows:&#13;
S(Pt) = B + bPt + Vt                b &gt; O                   (3)&#13;
where Pt denotes the selling price producers expect at time t.   With&#13;
adaptive expectations the equation becomes:&#13;
*    *               *&#13;
Pt   Pt-i   y(Pti + Pt0l) O&lt; y &lt; 1                          (4)&#13;
The change in expectations equals some fraction of the previous&#13;
periods forecast error, where y describes the rate of adaptation.&#13;
The expected gains for producers from stabilization (G ) are given&#13;
p&#13;
by the expression:&#13;
E(G) + E{(P3 - Pt)[S(ps) - S(Pt)]} - E[(Pt - P5)S(Pt)]      (5)&#13;
Turnovsky has shown that as with the previous models overall welfare&#13;
is increased with stabilization even though one group may be hurt.&#13;
However, the Oi conclusions that producers prefer price instability&#13;
due to demand fluctuations no longer holds. Whether they prefer price&#13;
stability depends on the relative slopes of the demand and supply&#13;
schedules, on the auto-regressive properties of the randon&#13;
disturbance, and on the length of lag in the formation of&#13;
expectations. However the Waugh proposition that consumers are hurt&#13;
by having prices stabilized in the face of supply fluctuations still&#13;
applies.&#13;
(b) Rational Expectations&#13;
The hypothesis of rational price expectations can be stated as:&#13;
Pt  -E (t)                                                 (6)&#13;
t-l&#13;
where E denotes conditional expectations at time (t-l)&#13;
t-l&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
38&#13;
Equation (6) asserts that the forecaster's predicted price for period&#13;
t should equal the price predicted conditional on all the information&#13;
at time (t-l) when the forecast is made.     From the formulation&#13;
Turnovsky derived qualitative conclusions similar to the Massell's&#13;
perfect flexibility model.&#13;
1. The total gains from price stability are always positive.&#13;
2. Consumers lose from price stabilization if the source of the&#13;
instability is due to supply shifts.&#13;
3. Producers lose fran price stabilization if the source of the&#13;
instability is random shifts in demand provided that these random&#13;
disturbances are autocorrelated.&#13;
From the above, it is clear that whether or not the Oi prqposition&#13;
extends to firms that base their supply decisions on expected prices&#13;
depends critically on how their forecasts are generated. Also the&#13;
total gains from stabilization which is based on a model that assumes&#13;
rational expectations are at least is great as those obtained when the&#13;
firm has perfect flexibility. However, one cannot deduce anything&#13;
definite about the comparative gains under rational versus adaptation&#13;
expectation schemes.&#13;
Also using a rational expectations framework Subotnik and Houck&#13;
compared the benefits from mean price stabilization to those of&#13;
-alternative schemes that stabilize production and consumption at their&#13;
respective means. Depending on certain parameters, the expected total&#13;
gains fram supply stabilization may be greater or less than those from&#13;
price stabilization.   In either case, the gains exceed those from&#13;
demand stabilization. Also they consider the variance of changes in&#13;
government stocks associated with each of three different schemes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
39&#13;
The larger the variance in stocks the more the government nust hold in&#13;
order to operate the buffer stock. Fbr each scheme the variance of&#13;
the change in government stocks is proportional to expected social&#13;
gains. Subotnik and Houck show that the storage costs involved can be&#13;
ranked in the same order as the expected gains from the various&#13;
stabilization schemes. Thus the more beneficial the scheme the higher&#13;
is the cost.&#13;
Price Instability, Storage and Food Security&#13;
The studies surveyed to this point do not explicitly deal with&#13;
food security or the impacts of instability and storage on vulnerable&#13;
groups in the world's population. The following studies focus on&#13;
grain reserves as a means to assure global or food security by less&#13;
developed countries.8&#13;
A set of papers on this issue were conducted by economists at&#13;
M.I.T. Sarris and Taylor (1976) argue that conceptually the emergency&#13;
8 The Waugh theorem is highly questionable for people who are poor and&#13;
spend a large share of their income on food. If at the low price in&#13;
the moDdel people could only buy sufficient food to meet nutritional&#13;
needs what happens at the high price? In terms of purchasing power at&#13;
this price malnutrition has to result. Waugh was clear that his model&#13;
doesn't necessarily apply to the-poverty and malnutrition cases since&#13;
his theorem is true only if the consumer can adjust his expenditure&#13;
among the n periods. Also using consumer surplus is a measure of&#13;
rising price on demand and hence malnutrition can create problems if&#13;
not done carefully. As Bigman notes: "In a more relatistic world&#13;
there is no way for us to measure the total welfare losses caused in&#13;
times of supply shortfalls and high prices, because there is no way&#13;
for us to measure the damage caused by malnutrition or the loss of&#13;
human life caused by starvation", p. 78. Willingness to pay measures&#13;
of which consumer surplus is an approximation may be difficult to&#13;
obtain when there is a wide discrepancy between willingness to pay and&#13;
what a consumer can actually pay.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
40&#13;
and food aid problems must be separated from price stabilization.9&#13;
Based on net cereal imports, an annual food aid commitment of 5&#13;
million tons would help maintain nutritional standards but an annual&#13;
flow of 10 million tons of critical aid would be more realistic. This&#13;
commitment should be made in physical and not value terms. They argue&#13;
that quantities allocated for emergencies or food aid are net drains&#13;
on the resources of a reserve while buffer stocks for price&#13;
stabilization are released in shortfall periods but replenished in&#13;
surplus times.&#13;
Taylor, Sarris and Abbott evaluate price-stabilizing buffer stocks&#13;
through foreign exchange gains and losses from stabilization. 'They&#13;
show that the U.S.S.R. could save $1 to $2 billion in foreign exchange&#13;
from stabilized prices while the major exporters would lose. Mbst&#13;
wheat importing countries, especially less developed ones, would also&#13;
gain.  They also show how a grain buffer stocks could provide order&#13;
and effectiveness to international efforts for famine relief. The&#13;
actual magnitude of required relief efforts is small and this would&#13;
only have a minimal impact on the grain buffer stocks or the world&#13;
market in general.   They suggest a guaranteed flow of funds to a&#13;
relief agercy which would use the would market, shipping facilities&#13;
and the storage from a price-stabilizing grain reserve.      Grain&#13;
reserves must be viewed as supporting food aid, but aid of a special&#13;
kind: its destinations will vary from region to region and from time&#13;
to time.&#13;
The work by Sarris, Abbot and Taylor draws partly on the above two&#13;
9Additional material on this subject is contained in Huddleston et&#13;
al. Intrnational Finances for Food Security.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
41&#13;
studies. They distinguish between "food aid", "emergency relief" and&#13;
"stabilization". They conduct a simulation analysis for wheat and for&#13;
feed grains.10 As an example, one of their figures shows how foreign&#13;
exchange earnings are a function of the width of the price band. They&#13;
also calculate the effect of a buffer stock on consumer and producer&#13;
surpluses. An example for feedgrains is given in Table 2.&#13;
Table 2: Effects of Feedgrains Buffer Stock on Consumer and Producer&#13;
Surpluses&#13;
Change in                      Change in&#13;
Consumer       Standard        Producer       Standard&#13;
Surplus        Deviation       Surplus        Deviation&#13;
($ billions)                   ($ billions)&#13;
USA      -0.480           0.516          0.531          0.702&#13;
CAN      -0.022           0.022          0.034          0.032&#13;
AUS      -0.006           0.011          0.012          0.025&#13;
ARG       0.016           0.308         -0.072          1.60&#13;
EEC      -0.103           0.093         -0.042          0.074&#13;
JAP      -0.023           0.022          0.0            0.0&#13;
BRA       0.017           0.106         -0.007          0.100&#13;
MEX       0.0             0.0            0.0            0.0&#13;
EGY      -0.019           0.019         -0.013          0.023&#13;
IND       0.0             0.0            0.0            0.0&#13;
PAK      -0.000           0.002          0.001          0.003&#13;
Note: Estimates of surpluses and standard deviations are calculated&#13;
across 200 Monte Carlo simulation runs.   The buffer stock&#13;
capacity is 10 mmt, and the price band is (93.1, 130.0).&#13;
Source: Sarris, Abbott and Taylor.&#13;
10 Various stock rules have been worked out by Newbery and Stiglitz&#13;
(1981) including one for famile relief (p. 416).      They specify a&#13;
famine utility function and postulate optimal storage strategies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
42&#13;
They go on to incorporate emergency relief and argue that it&#13;
should be viewed as a flow not a stock. They suggest a famine relief&#13;
fund and its purchasing power would increase with the existence of a&#13;
stabilization reserve. In addition, part of the stabilization reserve&#13;
itself could be purchased at low prices by the famine relief authori-&#13;
ties. An international price-stabilizing reserve could make famine&#13;
relief a much mDre orderly and effective cperation. Erergency stocks&#13;
have to be viewed as a special kind of fosd aid. They show that the&#13;
yearly magnitude of a reserve for emergencies is extremely small&#13;
relative to world production and trade. They also provide an excel-&#13;
lent discussion of the interrelationships of food aid, emergency&#13;
relief, and a price-stabilization buffer stock. Also they examine in&#13;
detail the food security proposals which followed the 1972-74 grain&#13;
crisis.  They discuss the economic and political obstacles to agree-&#13;
ment on food aid emergency relief and price stabilization.      The&#13;
gainers and losers from price stabilization have been shown in the&#13;
previous section. They conclude by showing the needed reserves for&#13;
price stabilization, emergency relief and food aid. The wheat reserve&#13;
could be less than 15 million- metric tons while the emergency relief&#13;
would be much smaller-one million metric tons per year. In general,&#13;
they argue that food aid should be phased out and replaced by general&#13;
economic assistance.11&#13;
In a World Bank study, Reutlinger (1976) used a simulation model&#13;
for evaluating worldwide buffer stocks of wheat where food aid&#13;
requirements were explicitly considered. Reutlinger contends that a&#13;
11 TIhe interest reader should also refer to works by Taylor (1978) and&#13;
Sarris (1980, 1981).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
43&#13;
policy which aims at assuring food aid at a given level when needed&#13;
and at the least possible cost would not separate food aid stocks from&#13;
other stocks. With such a food aid objective the holding of large&#13;
stocks is desirable and the value of these stocks would be higher. He&#13;
shows the additional gains and losses fran storage attributable to the&#13;
change in the demand function resultIng fran food aid.  The additional&#13;
economic benefits are sufficient to turn a net loss from storage&#13;
(without food aid) at almost any level to a net gain for as much as 30&#13;
million tons of storage capacity. Also there is a large effect of&#13;
storage on consumer gains and producer losses. Without storage the&#13;
added demand generated by food aid during shortages causes steep price&#13;
rises; consumers (in the commercial market) register large losses&#13;
while producers make large gains from the added demand for food aid.&#13;
In essence storage reduces the cost of food aid.12&#13;
Studies by the International Food Policy Research Institute have&#13;
also addressed the issue of food security for LDC's.  A food insurance&#13;
scheme was analyzed using an economic simulation model by Konandreas,&#13;
Huddleston, and Ramangjura.   The scheme was designed to stabilize&#13;
consumption and grain import costs for LDC's.     The scheme could&#13;
operate as an international financing program or as a combined financ-&#13;
ing and grain reserve program. Large reserves increase the proba-&#13;
bility that LDC's can obtain grain when needed to keep supplies from&#13;
12 The book edited by A.H. Chisholm and R. Tyers, Food Security:&#13;
Tfheory Policy, and Perspectives fran Asia and the Pacific Rim contains&#13;
many interesting chapters on food security, some of which are not&#13;
reviewed here. Those who are especially interested in food security&#13;
issues for specific regions should read this volume. Tb give the&#13;
readers some scope of the regions covered, Bderisinghe deals with Sri&#13;
Lanka, Dixon and Tyers with India's food security and Yamada focuses&#13;
on food security in Japan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
44&#13;
falling below 95 percent of their trend production. A 20 million ton&#13;
reserve is recomnended to be combined with a comrensatory financinq&#13;
program.&#13;
Recently, Valdes strengthens the argument put forward by&#13;
Reutlinger (1977) that the problem of instability for LDC's is the&#13;
resulting fluctuation in real income within the country. Clearly food&#13;
prices abroad could be stabilized even though internally domestic&#13;
incomes could be depressed by droughts or whatever which reduces their&#13;
purchasing power even though world prices mav not have risen. TIhe&#13;
standard solution is to hold assets in the form of food stocks&#13;
themselves. Vald6s argues as did Reutlinger that an alternative and&#13;
generally less costly strategy is to hold foreign exchange reserves to&#13;
import more food in the lean periods. The foreign exchange available&#13;
to import food appears to be the most critical factor to stabilize&#13;
food consumption.   Valdes presents data (Table 3 below) on food&#13;
imports and balance of payments (i.e. the average ratio of the food&#13;
import bill to total export revenues from goods and services).    The&#13;
higher the food import bill relative to the supply of foreign exchange&#13;
the more severe the food import problem is. Table 2 shows that for 10&#13;
of the 18 countries the mean ratio is high suggesting a "severe&#13;
constraint."&#13;
Valdes presents data (Table 4 below) also on the foreign exchange&#13;
cost of the "excess food import bill" relative to the supply of&#13;
foreign exchange. Note that the extra cost represents 10 percent and&#13;
sometimes as high as 20-30 percent of the supply of foreign exchange.&#13;
This is over and above the trend value of cereal imports in those&#13;
years and represents a short-run unexpected excess demand for foreign&#13;
exchange. Valdes uses these and other data to show that world price&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
45&#13;
Table 3:  Patio of Gross Food Imports to Total Export Revenues&#13;
Country                  1965/67   1970/72   1975/77    Maximum for the&#13;
Period&#13;
(Percent)&#13;
ASIA&#13;
Bangladesh            n.a.      n.a.      67.0        104.9  (1975)&#13;
Sri Lanka             36.9      40.4      39.4         57.4  (1975)&#13;
India                 40.2      12.7      19.4        43.4   (1967)&#13;
Ip"donesia             7.6      14.9       7.6        18.5   (1970)&#13;
P1illippines          10.4       8.6       6.)         12.9  (196,)&#13;
NORTH AFRICA/MIDDLE EAST&#13;
Spornalia             n.a.      24.4      52.1         67.0  (1977)&#13;
Egypt                 n.a.      19.3      34.1         46.0  (1975)&#13;
Jordan                n.a.      43.7      19.2         47.5  (1972)&#13;
Syria                 n.a.      25.4      16.7         34.3  (1971)&#13;
SUB-SAHARAN AFRICA&#13;
Mali\                 n.a.      21.0      27.9        112.7  (1974)&#13;
Senegal               n.a.      21.2      17.1         33.5  (1973)&#13;
Upper Volta           n.a.      11.1      13.8         23.5  (1974)&#13;
Tanzania              n.a.       7.1      13.5         29.3  (1974)&#13;
TATIN AMERICA&#13;
Haiti                 16.9      15.1      29.8         33.9  (1979)&#13;
Bolivia               15.4      13.9      11.6         17.2  (1965)&#13;
Peru                  n.a.       8.4      14.5         18.3  (1975)&#13;
Chile                  8.4      11.8      11.7         24.1  (1974)&#13;
Brazil                11.6       6.2       5.7         13.5  (1967)&#13;
Note:  Gross food defined to include cereals, meats, dairy products,&#13;
fruits and vegetables,-,sugar, pulses, root crops, oilseeds and&#13;
vegetable oils, cocoa beans and derivatives. Total exports&#13;
defined to include total merchandise and service exports plus&#13;
net private unrequited transfers.&#13;
Source: Valdes (1982).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
46&#13;
Table 4: The Foreign Exchange Cost of the Excess Food Import Bill&#13;
(expressed as a percentage of the supply of foreign exchange*)&#13;
Maximum Value&#13;
Country         1967    1969     1971   1973   1975    1977   (1967-77)&#13;
(percent)&#13;
ASIA&#13;
Bangladesh     n.a.   n.a.     n.a.   14.0   86.2    55.4   114.1   (1976)&#13;
Sri Lanka       0.9     2.2     3.4   11.2   23.7    6.1     23.7   (1975)&#13;
India          1.6     -7.5     2.4   -5.9   17.0    -1.3    17.0   (1975)&#13;
Indonesia     28.7      8.7    11.3    8.0   13.7   11.8     28.7   (1967)&#13;
Philippines     1.0     1.3     1.8    3.0    1.7     0.9     3.4   (1974)&#13;
NOR=H AFRICA/MIDDLE EAST&#13;
Scmalia         6.5     0.7    -5.1   -3.3   -1.5    -5.6     6.5   (1967)&#13;
Egypt          -3.8     2.4     1.7    4.2  -12.0    -5.3     4.2   (1973)&#13;
Jordan          6.7    14.5    10.7   15.2   10.7     5.7    17.0   (1974)&#13;
Syria           0.7     2.4     7.7   10.7    5.3     5.1    12.7   (1968)&#13;
SUB-SAHARAN AFRICA&#13;
Mali            7.5  -407.2     5.7   -9.9  -19.4    13.6    24.9   (1968)&#13;
Senegal       n.a.     -2.2     1.9    0.0    1.6     0.7     3.2   (1968)&#13;
Upper Volta   n.a.      7.5     7.4    5.1    7.0    13.5    14.5   (1976)&#13;
Tanzania        9.6    10.9     6.1   10-.2  20.8    22.8    22.8   (1977)&#13;
LATIN AMERICA&#13;
Haiti           1.3     4.3     3.6    7.8   17.5    11.7    17.5   (1975)&#13;
Bolivia         1.7     3.9     2.8    4.5    4.2     3.7     4.9   (1974)&#13;
Peru           -0.1     0.5     2.0    2.3     2.3    0.6     2.3   (1975)&#13;
Chile         -1.9     -0.2    -2.5    0.0   -1.9    -1.4     0.7   (1972)&#13;
Brazil         -0.8     6.8     7.0   10.4    12.2    5.0    12.4    (1974)&#13;
* The supply of foreign exchange is defined to include total export&#13;
receipts plus private unrequited transfers and plus net capital inflow.&#13;
Food defined to include cereals, meats, dairy products, fruits and&#13;
vegetables, sugar, pulses, root crops, oilseeds and vegetable oils, cocoa&#13;
beans and derivatives.&#13;
Source: Vald6s (1982).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
47&#13;
stabilization schemes can help mitigate food insecurity but alone it&#13;
is insufficient.&#13;
On the issue of food aid it is often unresponsive to widespread&#13;
production shortfalls. The volume is often reduced in years of higher&#13;
world prices when aid is most needed. Valdes contends that what is&#13;
needed is a financial facility which provides foreign exchange on&#13;
years when food imports exceed their trend level.13&#13;
Reutlinger's (1982) argument runs along lines similar to those put&#13;
forward by Vald6s.14 Fbod-grain consumption in developing countries&#13;
was unstable in the 1950's and 1960's in spite of relatively stable&#13;
world-market prices.   Hence a stable world price provided little&#13;
insurance against food insecurity.    In this context Reutlinger&#13;
contends that: "The major cause of consumption instability was&#13;
instability of production in the developing countries and not unstable&#13;
external supplies or prices. Imports were not used more aggressively&#13;
to compensate for the inherent instability in production of individual&#13;
countries   probably  for   the   following  good   reasons:&#13;
balance-of-payments problems, instability -in demand caused by&#13;
instability in consumers' incomes, inadequately flexible distribution&#13;
13 In a study, McIntire compares the cost and benefits for seven&#13;
countries in the Sahel from three policy systems: variable levies on&#13;
grain imports, security stocks of grain, and foreign exchange assis-&#13;
tance. The study shows that the three policy instruments are comple-&#13;
mentary thus the cost of providing food security to the Sahel can be&#13;
greatly reduced through a ccmbination of policies. Also an important&#13;
finding is that the foreign exchange costs of relying solely on grain&#13;
reserves are far higher than the costs of financial assistance&#13;
schemes.&#13;
14 There are several other papers on this subject. See; Feutlinger&#13;
(1978), RIijko, Sanderson 91975, 1977).   Reutlinger et al. (1976,&#13;
1981), Bigman et al. (1978, 1979) and Pinstrup. Anderson et al.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
48&#13;
channels and transportation and port handling facilities." p. 23 He&#13;
concludes through the use of a simulation model, that the removal of&#13;
trade and market-demand constraints are likely to be more effective&#13;
and less costly than buffer stocks for eliminating temporary and&#13;
periodic shortfalls in consumption. In addition financial insurance&#13;
schemes would greatly reduce the effect of unstable food import bill,&#13;
by less dependent countries.&#13;
The impact of trade policy itself on food insecurity has been&#13;
determined by Bigman (Figure 13). This work first started with Bigman&#13;
and Reutlinger (_AE, 1979, AER, 1979).      It is clear that more&#13;
liberalized trade leads to greater food security than does protec-&#13;
tionism. Thus trade liberalization itself can reduce the need for&#13;
holding strategic reserves.&#13;
FIGUR 13&#13;
30-&#13;
Food Insecurity (5 */)&#13;
P:"20&#13;
.0&#13;
L.&#13;
a.&#13;
10&#13;
Food&#13;
Insecurity&#13;
(10 II.)&#13;
o            1.      1     I&#13;
No    Restricted  Free  Partiol'  'Soid'  Complete&#13;
Trade  Trade     Trade       Stabilizing Trade&#13;
Souroe: Bigman (1982).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
49&#13;
Instability, Inflation and Economic Develo'ment&#13;
A shortcoming of the standard price stabilization models is that&#13;
they do not analyze the irpact price inceases may have on inflation.&#13;
As Adams and Behrman state:    "A boom may add to aggregate-demand&#13;
inflationary pressure, add to cost-push wage pressures by permitting&#13;
more easy pace setting wage increases in the primary production&#13;
sector, and reduce cost-push or structural devaluation inflation by&#13;
increasing the availability of foreign exchange." p. 28 Clearly, a&#13;
bust would tend to work in the cpposite direction.     In terms of&#13;
examrples, clearly the oil and grain price boom in the early 1970's&#13;
added to the existing inflation which generated many interesting&#13;
changes. As an example raising grain prices and the rising inflation&#13;
triggered off a phenomenal rise in the real price of farmland in the&#13;
North American region the effects of which have not been fully&#13;
analyzed.&#13;
The recent book by Adams and Behrman adds an additional important&#13;
aspect to the price stabilization literature.15 They explore in depth&#13;
the relation between primary comnodity markets and economic goal&#13;
-attainment in developing countries. The emrpirical part of the bock&#13;
assesses the impact of fluctuating coffee and ccpper prices on nine&#13;
quite different developing countries.    This is due for both price&#13;
fluctuations and secular price movements.    'The attainment goals&#13;
specified are: (1) increases in per capita income, (2) distribution&#13;
of income wealth and economic power, (3) utilization of production&#13;
capacity and cyclical stabiity in real output, (4) price or nominal&#13;
15 The reader interested in the impact of price stabilization on&#13;
export earnings should read the papers by Nguyen (1979 and 1980).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
50&#13;
stability and (5) international economic position.&#13;
The authors develop an integrated econometric approach to the&#13;
commodity problem and economic development.    They develop first a&#13;
macro econometric model for nine countries and embed in each of these&#13;
a primary comnmdity sector micro model for coffee and copper.   These&#13;
combined models are then integrated with econometric models of&#13;
internationally traded goods specifically copper and coffee. An&#13;
analysis is then made of the inpact of fluctuating ccpper and coffee&#13;
prices on the five goals outlined earlier.     They show how the&#13;
instability effects are spread over several years and demonstrate&#13;
intracyclical dynamics. Whether instability is good or bad depends on&#13;
the weights attached to various economic goals in the appropriate&#13;
welfare function. The authors also show the dynamic effects resulting&#13;
from a sustained price increase or decrease in ccpper and coffee&#13;
prices.  The impacts are found to be more ccmplex than for mere price&#13;
fluctuations. Various impacts cannot be considered independently of&#13;
the producer country's policy responses.    These include tax rate&#13;
changes, buffer stocks programs and export tax schemes.&#13;
Public Storage, Private Storage and Futures Markets&#13;
In the previous models, who actually holds the stocks to bring&#13;
about price stabilization is not spelled out explicitly.although it is&#13;
generally irmplicit that governments do theactual storing. However,&#13;
Gustafson, Sarris, Gardner (1979), Newbery and Stiglitz (1981) and&#13;
Lutz point to a finding that has significant implications for public&#13;
policy.   This finding is that a private storage industry with many&#13;
traders could carry socially optimal stocks and that in the presence&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
51&#13;
of such private storage public stocking intervention will be&#13;
coapletely ineffective.    Only in the presence of a less than&#13;
one-to-one trade off in private for public stocks can the case for&#13;
public intervention be made. A related issue as to how the private&#13;
trade reacts to government stockpiling appears to be unresolved (Stein&#13;
et al.). But if the private trade reduces carry-over stocks by as&#13;
much as the public authorities' stockpile, then there is no extra&#13;
price stability induced by government intervention.16&#13;
Recently Peck uses the "supply-of-storage" theory developed by&#13;
Working (1948, 1949) and later by Brennan to test the trade-off&#13;
between public and private stockholding.   This theory postulates a&#13;
positive relationship between the price of storage (a discounted,&#13;
expected future price minus the current price) and the quantity&#13;
stored.   Peck shows that the substitutability between private and&#13;
public stocks is much less than one to one.17 In a different but&#13;
related study. Sharples and Holland used the supply-of-storage theory&#13;
to determine the impact of the U.S. farmer owned reserve on privately&#13;
owned wheat stocks. hi ey hypothesized that wheat held in the farm&#13;
held reserve substituted for wheat which would have been otherwise&#13;
held privately by farmers. They separate pipeline stocks (stocks held&#13;
16 It was shown earlier that which of the agents hold stocks can have&#13;
a markedly different effect on inccme variability even though their&#13;
effect on price stabilization may be the same, an inportant point&#13;
which seems to have been neglected in the literature.      Private&#13;
stockholding by producers will tend to bring about both price and&#13;
producer income stability while government stockholding by itself will&#13;
bring about price stability but income instabiity can result which can&#13;
be greater than if no storage was undertaken by the public and/or&#13;
private.&#13;
17 Peck found a negative coefficient of only -.12 between U.S. privatel&#13;
owned wheat stocks and government owned year-end stocks.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
52&#13;
by processors and traders that are normally hedged on the futures&#13;
market) and speculative stocks.    Most of the latter appear to be&#13;
unhedged stocks owned by wheat producers. Sharples and Holland found&#13;
the interesting result that the farmer held reserve did not substitute&#13;
for otherwise private stockholding. They found that the two can be&#13;
conplementary in that an increase in the demand for private&#13;
stockholding can be positively related to the increase in the demand&#13;
by the farmer held reserve.&#13;
Sarris attempts to answer why there is not a one-to-one tradeoff&#13;
between public and private stockholding and why private stockholding&#13;
only can yield non optimal results. Some of the factors are different&#13;
private discount rates, different marginal variable storage costs,&#13;
risk aversion and different information sets.    Sarris derives the&#13;
following inportant propositions:&#13;
(1) If private storage firms are large in number and have information&#13;
equivalent to that available to society then aggregate private&#13;
carry-over is equal to the socially optimal one.&#13;
(2) In the presence of a risk-averse private storage industry the&#13;
trade-off between public and pr-ivate storage is less than one.. It&#13;
follows that if the storage industry consists of many traders&#13;
public stockpiling with a known role will have no effect upon&#13;
total carry-over.l8&#13;
(3) When the public storage is less than socially optimum then the&#13;
aggregate stocks are less than the socially optimum. Unless the&#13;
public sector takes over all of the storage the mixed performance&#13;
18 Sarris shows that if public stocks are larger then the socially&#13;
optimal land, the private trade carries no stocks.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
53&#13;
of private and public sectors together is less than optimal.&#13;
(4) In the presence of a public policy rule that is uncertain rather&#13;
than certain, to achieve the same level of total stocks requires a&#13;
larger public carry-over (i.e. if government policy is unpredic-&#13;
table at most denote more resources to achieve the same level of&#13;
optimality).&#13;
Helmberger and Weaver also develop a model where private storage&#13;
activities are incorporated. In their nmdel production and storage&#13;
decisions respond to rational expectations of uncertain prices. They&#13;
assume a competitive storage industry and show how benefits and costs&#13;
to various groups are affected by alternative programs. Tb find the&#13;
competitive level of storage they derive a supply and demand function&#13;
for storage (Competition pushes storage to the level where expected&#13;
profit is driven to zero). They find that: (1) a competitive storage&#13;
industry does not prevent large swings in grain prices, (2) differ-&#13;
ences between expected and actual prices are much greater in the&#13;
absence of competitive storage, (3) producers can gain from the&#13;
existence of a competitive storage industry though not necessarily so,&#13;
(4) buyers may or may not gain from competitive storage.19&#13;
Helmberger and Weaver show the effects of three different govern-&#13;
ment stabilization programs:   (1) complete price stabilization, (2)&#13;
partial price stabilization, and (3) stabilization of quantity pur-&#13;
chased. In comparing complete price stabilization by government&#13;
versus competitive storage they show that the transfer to producers&#13;
from buyers under the former can be quite significant. For partial&#13;
19 Points (3) and (4) are within reference to zero storage levels.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
54&#13;
stabilization producers gain, consumers lose and economic efficiency&#13;
is decreased. They also show that quantity stabilization schemes may&#13;
not be feasible in a free market economy.      They conclude that&#13;
conpetitive storage leads to the maximization of net benefits. But&#13;
conpetitive storage is consistent with wide price fluctuations and&#13;
significant differences between expected and realized prices.    They&#13;
contend that market failure might provide a rationale for government&#13;
intervention to stabilize prices. However, they point out that this&#13;
argument had not been used by others to justify a price stabilization&#13;
policy.   Fbr example, Cochrane and Danin appear to accept price&#13;
stabilization as an ultimate policy goal requiring no further analysis&#13;
of the linkages between the degree of price stability and the welfare&#13;
consequences.&#13;
Fbr many commoldities futures markets exists.   Therefore, their&#13;
role in stabilizing prices has to be taken into account. A deficiency&#13;
of the stabilization literature is that it focuses on spot prices and&#13;
ignores the role of futures markets.   Turnovsky (IPE 1978) addresses&#13;
this issue and assumes that the futures price equals the statistical&#13;
expectation of the spot price which will prevail at the maturity of&#13;
the contract. If futures market do indeed stabilize spot prices&#13;
significantly (a highly debatable subject), then the introduction of&#13;
futures markets may be an effective and certainly cheaper alternative&#13;
to buffer stocks stabilization. Turnovsky demonstrates the following:&#13;
(1) the introduction of futures trading tends to stabilize spot prices&#13;
where no private storage takes place.&#13;
(2) the choice will generally be true even in the presence of private&#13;
storage.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
55&#13;
(3) producers gain from futures, consumers lose and there are overall&#13;
society benefits.20&#13;
(4) A conventional buffer stock stabilization scheme will generally&#13;
yield a larger increase in surplus gains than will a futures&#13;
market which provides only partial price stabilization. However,&#13;
given the relative costs of the two, futures markets may be&#13;
preferred.&#13;
(5) the introduction of private storage in the presence of an already&#13;
existing futures market inproves the overall welfare of society&#13;
although the benefits to the various groups is indeterminate.&#13;
(6) information is an important stabilizing device and thus efficient&#13;
futures are stabilizing. Thus, for futures versus government&#13;
stabilization by some intervention rule, if the authorities have&#13;
to operate on the basis of past information, their intervention&#13;
will never improve upon the performance of an efficient futures&#13;
market.&#13;
Sarris (1982) extended the Turnovsky analysis and concluded that:&#13;
(1) futures trading coordinates and facilitates the carrying of&#13;
speculative stocks across different production periods, (2) with&#13;
rational expectations futures matket tend to stabilize cash prices&#13;
and (3) the use of futures prices by producers for planning production&#13;
is always stabilizing.21&#13;
20 This is the Massell result when instability is due to supply fluc-&#13;
tuations.&#13;
21 FDr additional excellent studies on the inplications of futures&#13;
markets in the presence of buffer stocks, see Peck, McKinnon and&#13;
Newbery and Stiglitz (1981).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
56&#13;
Supply Response and Risk Preferences&#13;
In the standard surplus models reviewed the assumption of risk&#13;
neutrality is made. However, what if producers are risk averse and&#13;
they face uncertainty? It is argued that if price stability can be&#13;
attained generally risk can be greatly reduced. As risk is reduced,&#13;
risk-responsive producers may increase supply; as a result, both&#13;
producer and consumer welfare may increase by more than the standard&#13;
Massell risk-neutrality assumptions would indicate.    Once risk is&#13;
taken into account, estimates of gains from stabilization may be&#13;
seriously biased and any efforts to determine an optimal stabilization&#13;
policy-for example, a normal price about which to stabilize--may be&#13;
in vain when risk preferences and responses are not considered.&#13;
The topic of welfare measurement for producers operating with risk&#13;
has been addressed in the context of stabilization policy by Just&#13;
(1975) and by Just and Hallam. Changes in welfare are adequately&#13;
reflected by changes in the area above the supply curve and below&#13;
price if a producer's economic welfare depends linearly on expected&#13;
profits and the variance of profits. With risk, however, the relevant&#13;
supply curve depends on expected price (possibly a function of lagged&#13;
prices) and the subjective variance of price (also possibly determined&#13;
22&#13;
by previous experience).     Specifically, consider the risk-neutral&#13;
supply curve or certainty supply curve S in Figure 14. Now suppose&#13;
22 Or, alternatively in the case of grain supply, acreage can be&#13;
specified as depending on the subjective mean and variance of returns&#13;
per acre. Such a specification automatically corrects for any corre-&#13;
lation between prices and yields which may otherwise have differing&#13;
implications for income stability when price is stablized. That is,&#13;
due to negative correlation between price and average yield, price&#13;
stability may actually destablize income; if so, this would be appro-&#13;
priately reflected by returns per acre.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
57&#13;
FIGURE 14&#13;
prioe&#13;
pg&#13;
p                         4&#13;
q         q                 Quantity/u.t.&#13;
that the introduction of a given amount of price risk causes the&#13;
producer to contract production so that supply shifts to S*.     The&#13;
results by Just and Hallam show that the appropriate curve to use in&#13;
measuring economic welfare effects for the producer is the curve S*&#13;
which holds the amount of risk constant. Thus, the surplus area which&#13;
reflects economic welfare under- risk is area a + c at expected-price&#13;
p'. Under risk neutrality or certainty at p', the supply curve S&#13;
would imply real income of area a + b + c + d + e so the real income&#13;
loss associated with price uncertainty is area b + d + e. Of course,&#13;
if the risk response from q to q' associated with price stabilization&#13;
is ignored, then the associated real income benefits of area b + d + e&#13;
would be ignored. Thus, Just and Hallam argue that the identification&#13;
of significant risk preferences as evidenced by risk- responsive&#13;
decision may be crucial in justifying a price-stabilizaton policy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
58&#13;
The issue of price stablization under uncertainty has also been&#13;
dealt with by Berck and Schmitz. They show explicitly that, if pro-&#13;
ducers are risk averse and they cperate under conditions of uncer-&#13;
tainty, the standard Massell-Thrnovsky result, does not hold.  Ihe&#13;
reduction of uncertainty triggers a net positive supply response which&#13;
has to be taken into account in managing a buffer stock.23&#13;
An excellent book on the subject    The Theory of Ccmmodity Price&#13;
Stabilization: A Study in the Economics of Risk has been recently&#13;
published by Newbery and Stiglitz.24 Some of their results have&#13;
already been referred to.    They find generally that if price&#13;
stabilization is to have a significant impact, it has to be on its&#13;
effects through risk reduction. That is, the efficiency gains from&#13;
stabilization because of supply rsponse far more than outweighs the&#13;
distriutional and net effects modelled by Massell.     This is also&#13;
supported by Bigman. In the cases where price stabilization does not&#13;
reduce risk or producers are risk takers, its net welfare effect can&#13;
be relatively small and even negative.&#13;
Multiple Policy Instruments and Goals&#13;
Often price stabilization through storage is not undertaken merely&#13;
23 The issue of instability with uncertainty has also been dealt with&#13;
by Just, Hueth and Schmitz in the case where attitudes toward risk are&#13;
not explicitly considered. Producers determine quantity before price&#13;
is known. They show that expected quasi-rent under instability is&#13;
exactly the same as if prices were stablized at their mean. However,&#13;
expected welfare quantities are generally not the ones actually&#13;
realized.&#13;
24 Newbery and Stiglitz (1979) also present an excellent discussion on&#13;
commodity price stabilization rules.   Also see Hazell and Scandizzo&#13;
for optimal price policies under risky production.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
59&#13;
for the purpose of stabilizing prices or producer's income.     As&#13;
Gardner (1979) points out: "The inherent difficulty of operating a&#13;
buffer-stock regime can be anplified by a tendency to tailor price&#13;
bands to goals other than stabilization, such as farm-income support&#13;
(leading to upper limits on stocks which are too large coupled with&#13;
acquisition prices which are too high) or minimizing budget costs&#13;
(which leads to a preference for production controls over the costs of&#13;
carrying large stocks over a period of years)." p. 158 Gardner's.&#13;
simulations show that: "even when production deviations and random&#13;
demand shifts are serially independent, it is not uncommon to find&#13;
runs of several years during which carryover stocks are continually&#13;
above the mean stock level." p. 158&#13;
A model which incorporated at least two policy instruments&#13;
together was developed by Bieri and Schmitz (1973) in the context of&#13;
trade where an importer pursued optimal tariff policies in conjunction&#13;
with storage. Storage added gains on to those already achieved&#13;
through tariffs. Also Bigman in a recent book has examined the role&#13;
of buffer stocks when internal price policies 'are already in place.&#13;
"The presence of internal price policies dramatically changes the role&#13;
and effects of buffer stocks. When, for instance, a procurement&#13;
program is in operation, most of the storage activities are auto-&#13;
matically carried out through it. A storage facility is then only an&#13;
instrument of the procurement policy, and the stock policy is&#13;
meaningful only to the extent that it changes rules of intervention&#13;
defined by the price band." pp 246-247. In addition Bigman shows that&#13;
"the larger the independent stabilizing effect of the support program&#13;
the smaller will be the added stability achieved through buffer stocks&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
60&#13;
and the more rapid will be the decline in the marginal productivity&#13;
(expressed in terms of the stabilizing effects) of additional storage&#13;
units." p. 216&#13;
The welfare inplications of a combined stocks and price support&#13;
system have been shown by Berck and Schmitz. Several models are&#13;
developed along the lines of the one which follows. In Figure 15&#13;
price fluctuations, in the absence of storage and government price&#13;
supports, are P1 and P2. With storage, a stable price P could be&#13;
obtained. It is easy to see why fron the nmodel producers can prefer&#13;
price instability to stability through storage if in fact the&#13;
government uses price supports to prevent producer prices fran falling&#13;
to P1 in the abundant supply period. Clearly if government for&#13;
example setsthe support price at Ps for producers and allowed the&#13;
market to clear by charging price P1 to consumers, producers would&#13;
prefer price instability to stability. This is opposite to the result&#13;
one would derive using the Massell model.    However, in the Massell&#13;
model the only policy instrument is storage. In Figure 15 to this&#13;
point the comparison is between storage versus no storage and price&#13;
supports.                         FIGUIE 15&#13;
s(planning)&#13;
p2&#13;
P~&#13;
5&#13;
ps&#13;
Q2 %      i  Qs Q1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
61&#13;
One can combine price supports and storage in this type of model.&#13;
These two generally go hand in hand. That is, to deal only with&#13;
storage excluding price supports, and/or loan rates is unrealistic in&#13;
some cases. Fbr example the U.S. Food and Agriculture Act of 1977 has&#13;
as its cornerstone a "loan rate" coupled with a "farmer-owned&#13;
reserve'. The latter is basically a subsidy program for on-farm&#13;
stor3ge. To illustrate the combined effects of price supports and&#13;
farmer held reserves, a government storage subsidy for producers of&#13;
the cross-hatched area   (QlQs) is introduced.  This storage will be&#13;
-released by producers in period 2 and will cause prices to be P21&#13;
instead of P2 in that period. Because of the inelastic demand total&#13;
revenue will decrease when the stocks are released. However, if the&#13;
price support Ps is maintained even though it is on a smaller ouptut Q&#13;
it is aparent why producers prefer price .instabiltiy alorng with price&#13;
supports, and farmer held reserves to stability brought about only&#13;
with reserves. -In the model this result holds since:&#13;
2(V) &lt; [(P2Q21 + PSQS] + T(QsQl)]&#13;
Apart from many other inplications which can be drawn from the&#13;
above model -it is apparent why -farm groups generally prefer price&#13;
instability to stability--cpposite to the Massell result.    This is&#13;
because price supports or some such device are used along with storage&#13;
to enhance farmers income-not merely stabilize it. As Figure 15&#13;
shows, price supports, in essence chop off the part of the price&#13;
distribution containing the low prices.&#13;
25 Clearly producers are worse off with farmer held reserves and a&#13;
support price P  on output Qs than if Ps applied to Q1 where farmer&#13;
held reserves aAe absent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
62&#13;
Nonstorable Goods&#13;
The major emphasis in the stabilization literature is on storable&#13;
commTdities.   Hbwever, stabilization schemes also exist in various&#13;
parts of the world for nonstorable goods. Price stabilization schemes&#13;
exist, for example, in the production of beef, pork and mutton.&#13;
Unfortunately detailed studies are not available which have analyzed&#13;
the purpose of these schemes, how they are managed and their effect on&#13;
producer response through the reduction of risk.     Figure 16 is&#13;
presented to highlight what such a scheme might do and how it can run&#13;
into difficulty.   The nodel also supports the contention by Newbery&#13;
and Stiglitz that if efficient risk sharing apparatus are available&#13;
along with properly functioning credit markets, the need for&#13;
stabilization programs is greatly reduced.&#13;
The example used in Figure 16 applies to a now storable good such&#13;
as beef cattle. Suppose actual market prices move above and below&#13;
some price p and because of this instability producers pressure&#13;
government into enacting a "beef stabilization scheme". Suppose the&#13;
-board in charge determines that such a program can be made actuarily&#13;
sound by using a cost of production formulae.     In the model the&#13;
program is actually sound if price P which is received by the&#13;
-producers covers the cost of production; at price P the net pay out by&#13;
the government for running the program is zero since over time the&#13;
government payout a + c is equal to the tax on producers b &amp; d.&#13;
However, what happens if cattle prices fail to rise but production&#13;
costs rise.   Suppose the rise in costs has the board set Pl to&#13;
producers. Clearly in this case the beef producers are never taxed&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
63&#13;
FIGURE 16&#13;
p&#13;
Pe                                                    ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~Producer&#13;
b                                         ~~~~~~~~~~~~~Price&#13;
Recei Ved&#13;
Market&#13;
Prices&#13;
t          Time&#13;
and the government runs a deficit in supporting the beef stabilization&#13;
program (i.e. the program is no longer actually sound).&#13;
The mrodel in Figure 16 raises some interesting points.   If the&#13;
program is actuarily sound in that the net government outlay for the&#13;
program is zero why would producers want it? In a different context&#13;
as Newbery and Stiglitz point out, if active futures and credit&#13;
markets exist the need for such a scheme is greatly reduced if the-&#13;
intent of stabilization is to reduce income variability of producers&#13;
and hence consumption variability.    In the example, without the&#13;
stabilization scheme producers could borrow in a and repay in b and so&#13;
on. However, even if means are available to spread risk producers are&#13;
still likely to opt for a stabilization scheme if by various means the&#13;
board in charge can use it as a means to enhance farmers income-not&#13;
merely reduce variability in incomes.    In Figure 16 price Pl is a&#13;
price support but unlike in the previous model it is not acconpanied&#13;
by storage.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
64&#13;
In particular cases if the stabilization program is not actuarily&#13;
sound how long the government is willing to subsidize it through&#13;
covering producer costs depends on many factors including the lobbying&#13;
power of the group involved. Of course, one way that the government&#13;
could make the programs self financing at price Pl is to use supply&#13;
management techniques so that market prices rise to cover costs of&#13;
production. In many countries such as Canada supply management is&#13;
commDn. It would be interesting to know how many supply management&#13;
schemes were a result of price stabilization schemes which at their&#13;
inception were deemed to be self-financing without supply management.&#13;
It is clear why if producers received price Pl through a&#13;
stabilization scheme they would prefer this to a free market&#13;
situation.  This is because price stabilization is accompanied by an&#13;
income support.&#13;
Instability, Storage and the Pure Theory of Trade26&#13;
An important and growing literature has devoted attention to the&#13;
more general incorporation of uncertainty into gains from trade&#13;
-theorizing and how to optimally deal with the uncertainty. Rffin has&#13;
investigated the case of a small trading country experiencing large&#13;
fluctuations in the terms of trade as a result of uncertain&#13;
transaction costs and/or of erratic movements in spot exchange rates.&#13;
The following nonautarky theorem was derived: Given trade uncertainty&#13;
(and excluding "pathological" distortions), autoarky will not be&#13;
26 A more detailed summary is contained in John M. Letiche, R.G.&#13;
Chambers and A. Schmitz "The Development of Gains from Trade Theory:&#13;
Classical to Modern Literature".&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
65&#13;
optimal regardless of variations in the terms of trade. Similarly, by&#13;
introducing forward markets into the analysis, it was shown that in&#13;
the long run autarky cannot be optimal regardless of the variations in&#13;
terms of trade and whatever the level of forward prices.&#13;
Batra and RIssell considered the effects of increasing uncertainty&#13;
of world prices on the social welfare of a trading nation and&#13;
demonstrated that it would bring about a reduction of expected&#13;
utility. Under conditions of uncertainty, therefore, free trade may&#13;
not be an cptimal policy.   Tb reduce the effects of uncertainty, and&#13;
to increase the potential gains from trade, the authors considered&#13;
various governmental policies designed to minimize the cost to&#13;
consumers resulting from variations in actual as compared with&#13;
expected terms of trade. Among the policies considered was the use of&#13;
buffer stocks.&#13;
Batra further examined the effects of uncertainty by introducing a&#13;
random variable in the production function and by assuming that the&#13;
expected utility of the producers is to be maximized. Although the&#13;
theorems derived are narrow in scope, they provide insights for the&#13;
application of gains from trade theory, especially in regard to the&#13;
"commodity problem" and the stabilization of terms of trade.&#13;
In effect, the introduction of uncertainty is shown to have&#13;
important consequences for standard trade theory. Contrary to the&#13;
standard Heckscher-Ohlin conclusion, given constant commodity prices&#13;
and the customary assumptions regarding homcgeneity-with uncertainty,&#13;
changes in factor endowments do affect relative factor prices. Still,&#13;
the following related theorems remain in tact:     (1) the Stopler-&#13;
Samuelson theorem, which demonstrates that a tariff increases the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
66&#13;
return to factors used intensively in the import-competing industry,&#13;
(2) the Samuelson theorem on the bne-to-one corresiondence between&#13;
international commodity-price ratios and factor-price ratios; and (3)&#13;
the celebrated Rybczynski theorem: At constant commodity prices,&#13;
accumulation of a factor increases the output of the coTmodity that&#13;
uses that factor intensively and reduces the output of the other&#13;
commndity.   Even the Heckscher-Ohlin theorem, it is shown, can be&#13;
valid for conditions of uncertainty if we define factor abundance in&#13;
physical terms. However, under certain specifications of risk&#13;
aversion, complete factor-price equalization is ruled out. But the&#13;
weak factor-equalization theorem, i.e., the existence of a tendency&#13;
toward factor-price equalization, remains. However, the volume of&#13;
trade and the gains from trade, it is conclusively demonstrated, are&#13;
smaller under uncertainty than under certainty.&#13;
The Ricardian model also has been reworked to include uncertainty&#13;
and this conclusion reached: Expected gains from trade for a&#13;
risk-averse country which, under certainty, would wish to trade may,&#13;
under postulated assumptions with price uncertainty, become negative,&#13;
causing it to cease trading.     Several authors have formulated a&#13;
trading mz-del in which both price uncertainty and storage activities&#13;
were included. Feder, Just and Schmitz, for example, showed that with&#13;
nonincreasing risk aversion but increased price uncertainty, both&#13;
importers and exporters of the stored commodity tend to reduce the&#13;
volume of their trade and, at the limit, would be better off not&#13;
trading. Also, an uncertainty increases, importers store relatively&#13;
more of the uncertain good. A framework has been developed for the&#13;
analysis of trade under conditions of substantial fluctuations in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
67&#13;
prices, given alternative specifications of risk by the governments of&#13;
respective trading partners.&#13;
Theoretically, the presence of uncertainty in the foreign trade of&#13;
goods and assets can, to a degree, be treated as an additional or&#13;
joint "commodity", denoted as "risk." In the absence of satisfactory,&#13;
or feasible, risk-sharing arrangements-reflected by the fact that&#13;
this "commodity" is not internationally traded-the prices of these&#13;
risk elements in production and distribution are manifestly different&#13;
in different countries.    As a consequence, some of the basic&#13;
properties of international trade theory may not hold. Without such&#13;
minimal risk-sharing arrangements, analysis of the effects of&#13;
substantial uncertainty on the basic properties of trade theory (e.g.,&#13;
comparative advantage) has little predictive value for international&#13;
specialization in the pattern of trade. Nevertheless, studies which&#13;
have considered a planning model in which a social welfare function&#13;
(expected utility) is maximized subject to the country's technological&#13;
constraint, can be interpreted as models which include domestic stock&#13;
markets and/or domestic Arrow-Debreu contingent comnodity markets.27&#13;
For effective gains-from-trade analysis under uncertainty, the&#13;
incorporation into these models of international trade in firms'&#13;
equities and/or other national and international risk-sharing&#13;
arrangements appears to be a primary requisite.&#13;
The role of trade in affecting uncertainty in price instability&#13;
has been also emphasized by writers such as Newbery and Stiglitz and&#13;
Bigman.   They contend that liberalized trade smooths out price&#13;
27 See for example E. Helpman and A. Razin&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
68&#13;
fluctuations and in a sense free trade has similar effects to a buffer&#13;
stock scheme and may be a cheaper substitute. 28 Also the work by&#13;
Newbery and Stiglitz support the findings by economists such as&#13;
Helpnan and Razin that the need for price stabilization schemes is&#13;
greatly reduced if adequate credit markets exist and there are means&#13;
available to share risks. International futures markets, and trade in&#13;
a firm's equities are certainly such means.29&#13;
Empirical Results30&#13;
As a concluding section to this paper, some additional empirical&#13;
studies are presented. The following studies largely focus on optimal&#13;
stockpiling from the U.S. point of view. According to Gardner (1979)&#13;
"optimal stockpiling is holding quantities back from current&#13;
consumption such that expected welfare, as measured by an objective&#13;
function, is maximized given the current state of the world. An&#13;
optimal stockpiling policy is a set of rules which specifies optimal&#13;
stocks for every possible state of the world, p. 3". To arrive at&#13;
optimal stockpiling rules, Gustafson more than 20 years ago treated&#13;
28 Although, as shown by Hueth and Schmitz, a buffer stock scheme can&#13;
yield welfare improvements over a situation of free trade and no&#13;
stocks.&#13;
29 To highlight risk sharing activities the Japanese experience&#13;
provides a good example. In the purchase of grain from abroad they&#13;
actively use the Chicago futures markets as a hedging means. Also&#13;
they have invested in the U.S. in local elevators and terminal in&#13;
order to be near the source of supply; thus they do not have to rely&#13;
solely on purchases from export marketing boards and non-Japanese&#13;
multinational grain firms.&#13;
30 Some of the studies reviewed here are also discussed in Houck and&#13;
Ryan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
69&#13;
grain stockpiling as an optimal inventory problem.31      Gustafson&#13;
considered production per acre as a random variable with fixed mean&#13;
and shows given a value (welfare) function for grain, storage costs,&#13;
and a discount rate how an optimal carryover policy would be&#13;
specified. He derived an optimal storage rule which determines each&#13;
year's carryover as a function of the year's beginning supply.   Among&#13;
the important applications, extensions and improvements on this work&#13;
are reported in Johnson and Summner (1976, 1978), Cochrane and Danin,&#13;
Arzac, Talpaz and Taylor, Taylor and Talpaz, and Burt, Koo and Dudley.&#13;
Among the most sophiscated storage models is that developed by&#13;
Burt, Koo and Dudley of the U.S. wheat economy. They first develop an&#13;
econometric mnodel of the U.S. wheat sector which incorporates the&#13;
dynamics of supply response then they use these results to develop a&#13;
stochastic dynamic programming nmodel to estimate optimal stockpiling&#13;
strategies for the U.S.   They used two separate criterion fucntions:&#13;
domestic and world welfare. They used as the domestic criterion the&#13;
sum of domestic consumers' and producrs' surpluses minus storages&#13;
costs (consistent with the Massell framework).    The world welfare&#13;
criterion also contained consumers' surplus associated with the export&#13;
demand equation. 32&#13;
In their stochastic storage miodel, the decision variable is&#13;
quantity of wheat exported that indirectly controls year to year&#13;
31 The study by Gislason C. is also of interest as an early mrodel of&#13;
grain storage.&#13;
32 In computing the annual expected net benefit function they replaced&#13;
the random variables by their mean values in the demand and supply&#13;
equations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
70&#13;
carryover. The disturbance term in their econometrically estimated&#13;
export price equation is unknown at the time a storage policy decision&#13;
is made. Thus, a specific level of exports does not determine price&#13;
but only the probability distribution. In their mrodel the probability&#13;
distributions for price and the disturbances in supply and demand in&#13;
conjunction with the sate variables determine the distribution of&#13;
domestic consunption, production and ending carryover for the ensuring&#13;
crop year.&#13;
They state the general recursive equation of dynamic programming&#13;
as:&#13;
Vn(Y) = Max(gn(x,y) + aE{VVn-1 I[T,(x,y)]}),                (7)&#13;
where y and x are vectors of state and decision variables, respec-&#13;
tively, and E[.] is the expectation operator. In the wheat storage&#13;
problem Vn (y) is the present value of expected net benefits over an&#13;
n-year planning period when following an optimal storage policy and&#13;
given that the initial state vector is y; ais the discount factor with&#13;
0 &lt; a &lt; 1. The function g n(x,y) is expected annual net benefits from&#13;
the first year of n future years, while T n(x,y) is the transformed&#13;
vector of state variables at-the-beginning of a planning horizon of&#13;
n-i years. Actually Tn(x,y) is a random variable and the function&#13;
notation is used to show that x and y enter as parameters in the&#13;
multivariate distribution functon of the vector of state variables.&#13;
The subscript n on Tn(x,y) inplies that the probabiity distribution is&#13;
permitted to change fran stage to stage in the decision process.&#13;
Since in their wheat model they have a total of fifteen state&#13;
variables they use an approximation method for arriving at a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
71&#13;
solution.33 In their approximation they suppress all state variables&#13;
except two: stocks of wheat and wheat price lagged one year.&#13;
The empirical results obtained by Burt et al. provide evidence&#13;
both on the distributional effects from storage and the optimal&#13;
storage capacity needed.   In their model domestic producers gained&#13;
from a storage program while domestic and foreign consumers lose.&#13;
They also conclude that the U.S. storage capacity for wheat is&#13;
substantially above what can be justified economically.    They show&#13;
that the marginal value of capacity beyond 2.5 billion bushels is near&#13;
zero even when fixed costs are ignored. They also show the gain in&#13;
going from 1,000 million to 2,000 million bushels capacity (the latter&#13;
is near optimum).   Under the domestic criterion the gain is $300&#13;
million annually; the conparable figure for the world criterion is&#13;
$190 million.&#13;
Prior to the above work, Taylor and Talpaz formulated a stochastic&#13;
simulation nmodel to determine optimal carryover levels for wheat in&#13;
the United States. Unlike in the Gustafson framework they allow for&#13;
supply response and demand uncertainty.      Also, they simulate&#13;
stochastically the use of a first period, first-order certainity&#13;
equivalence decision rule.    Other studies prior to this sirmply&#13;
computed the expected optimal stocks level. Their decision criterion&#13;
33 They use a variance of the method suggested by Arrow. The approxi-&#13;
mation discussed by Arrow is to replace V    (.) in (11) by an estimate&#13;
of some kind.  The usual computational TA4 od of dynamic programming&#13;
calculates. the function V (.) recursively starting with V (.) as a&#13;
given function. But now w are considering some a priori 8stimate of&#13;
V -1(.) in order to estimate the optimal decision rule for stage n&#13;
oRly. It is seen from (11) that if Vn_l(.) were a known function, the&#13;
optimal decision for stage n could be oBtained from a static optimiza-&#13;
tion algorithm.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
72&#13;
is the maximization of the expected present value of a perpetual steam&#13;
of consumers' and producers' surpluses less storage costs. Their&#13;
basic framework is the first order certainty equivalence principle.&#13;
the classical certainty equivalence theorem states that the optimal&#13;
decision in a risky situation is the same as in some associated&#13;
riskless situation.34&#13;
They denote the objective function in general form as:&#13;
T&#13;
W*       Wt(Pt,Pt-l, St, St-l)rt                             (8)&#13;
T&#13;
t-l r [ft(Pt) - gt(Pt_l) - cStI,&#13;
t=l&#13;
where Pt is price (dollars per bushel); St, total stocks (million&#13;
bushels); ft(Pt), area under the demand curve as a function of Pt;&#13;
t (Pt-,) area under the supply functions at time t as related to Pt-,&#13;
and t; c, annual storage cost (dollars per bushel); r, discount rate;&#13;
and T, length of planning horizon (years). From this expression they&#13;
derive an equation for determining optimal level of stocks though&#13;
simulation trials.&#13;
Their results show that U.S. stock levels beginning in 1976/77&#13;
have been too high. Also the use of a certainty equivalence rule to&#13;
manage stocks increased welfare by $199 million per year in the U.S.&#13;
compared to the current system. However, price variabitility doubled.&#13;
In terms of distributional affects domestic producers become worse off&#13;
34 Their model is less complicated than that used by Burt et al. since&#13;
exports are estimated as a function of world price with the random&#13;
disturbance reflecting variations in exports for a given price. Thus&#13;
in the Taylor-Talpaz mcodel price or at least a target price is the&#13;
decision variable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
73&#13;
by $236 million annually, while domestic consumers gain about $414&#13;
million. Also, under the certainty equivalent rule foreign consumers'&#13;
surplus increases by about $70 million.&#13;
Gardner (1979) also calculated the optimal U.S. wheat storage&#13;
policy using simulation techniques. His results are consistent with&#13;
other studies on this subject with respect to the amounts of grain the&#13;
U.S. actually stores.  He concludes that generally U.S. stock levels&#13;
are too high - nean socially optimal U.S. wheat stocks should be put&#13;
at 550 to 600 million bushels. Gardner also calculates optimal stock&#13;
levels for different interest- rates and varying levels of private&#13;
stockholding combined with public stockholding.&#13;
The Cochrane and Danin study specifies a world nmodel of wheat,&#13;
coarse grains, rice and all grains and a U.S. nmodel for wheat to&#13;
evaluate several stock decision rules. The focus is on stock size&#13;
relative to price stabilization associated with a specific probability&#13;
of success.   The optimal rule generates stock changes to minimize&#13;
price instability. They conclude that a world stock reserve of 38 to&#13;
57 million metric tons of all grains would keep prices within 10&#13;
percent of the target price level four years out of five. Also,&#13;
reducing variation by more than that provided by a 10 percent price&#13;
band governing stock activity requires very large stocks.&#13;
Analysis by Johnson and Sumner (1976, 1978) show that grain&#13;
reserves are desirable chiefly because there is no free trade in&#13;
grains. Trade clearly reduces optimal stock sizes. As an example, in&#13;
the Far East region for a given year, stocks would be 7.5 million&#13;
metric tons under free trade. This ccrpares to 22.5 million tons with&#13;
no intraregional trade and each nation doing its own stockpiling.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
74&#13;
The models by Zwart and Meilke estimated an econometric model of&#13;
the Canadian and rest of the world wheat economies. They tested&#13;
several variations of three grain reserve storage rules by simulation&#13;
experiments. The storage rules tested differed more in their impact&#13;
on price stability and consumer welfare than on producer welfare. Fbr&#13;
the model as a whole producer reserves are stabilized more by a price-&#13;
stabilizing storage scheme than by a quantity stabilizing scheme.&#13;
Hower, the most stability for consumers comes from storage rules that&#13;
combine price and quantity triggers.   They conclude that mixed rules&#13;
seem to yield the best overall results.&#13;
The above papers give some of the typical findings concerning&#13;
stockpiling. There are many other studies also on this general topic&#13;
but the general conclusions are similar.  These are listed below.  The&#13;
two exceptions are studies by Gardner and Just for the U.S. General&#13;
Accounting Office on farmer held reserves. They generally conclude&#13;
that these reserves have been ineffective in meeting their stated&#13;
objectives.   Some of the other studies on the general topic of&#13;
stabilization are:   (1)  Adams et al. (1977) "A Welfare Analysis of&#13;
Long-Term Bbrest Products Price Stabilization",      (2)   Alaouze&#13;
"Australian Wheat Storage:   A Dynamic Programming Approach",    (3)&#13;
Bailey et al. Grain Stock Issues and Alternatives,     (4)   Brandow&#13;
!'Grain Reserves and the U.S. Economy:   A Policy Perspective",   (5)&#13;
Brzozowski "Grain Sales and Production Cycles - A Computer Simulation&#13;
Study", (6) Casley et al. "Instability of Production and Its Impact&#13;
on Stock Requirements",   (7)  Chaipravat "International Rice Buffer&#13;
Stock Cperations, A Simulation Study",   (8) Eaton et al. "The Joseph&#13;
Problem:  How Large a Grain Reserve?",   (9)  Ericksen "Farm Programs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
75&#13;
and Grain Reserves - Simulated Results", (10) F.A.O. "Report of the&#13;
Expert Cbnsultation on Cereal Stock Policies Relating to World Food&#13;
Security",   (11)  Greenes et al. "Insulating Trade Policy, Inter-&#13;
vention and Wheat Price Stability," (12) Hathaway "Grain Stocks and&#13;
Economic Stability:   A Policy Perspective",    (13)  Jones "Grain&#13;
Reserves in Agricultural and Food Policy" and "A Grain Reserve&#13;
Program",   (14) Josling An International Grain Reserve Policy,   (15)&#13;
Just and Hallam "New Developments in Econometric Evaluation of Price&#13;
Stabilizing and Destabilizing Policies",   (16)  Keeler "A Model for&#13;
Evaluating Grain Reserve Policies", (17) Lewis et al "AGRIMOD. A&#13;
Simulation Model for Analysis of U.S. Food Policies", (18) Morrow et&#13;
al. "Toward a World Food Reserve System", (19) National Commission&#13;
Government and the Nation's Resources,   (20)  O'Carroll et al.   "An&#13;
Economic Analysis of a Reserve Stock Program for Rice in the United&#13;
States",  (21)   Ray "Managing Instability with Commodity Reserves: A&#13;
Preliminary Assessment", (22) Ray et al. "A Simulation Analysis of a&#13;
Reserve Stock Management Policy for Feed Grains and Wheat",     (23)&#13;
Sharples and Walker (1975) "Reserve Stocks of Grain: Analysis of&#13;
Wheat Loan Rates and-Target Prices Using a Wheat Reserve Stocks&#13;
Simulation Model",    (24)  Sharples et al. (1976) Managing Buffer&#13;
Stocks to Stabilize Wheat Prices,   (25)  Sharples and Walker (1977)&#13;
"Grain Reserves: Price Instability and the Food Supply",      (26)&#13;
Sharples et al. "Alternative Agricultural and Food Policy Directions".&#13;
(27)  Steele "The Grain Reserve Issue",   (28)   Steele "Alternative&#13;
Approaches to Stabilizing International Markets",     (29)  Trezise&#13;
Rebuilding Grain Reserves,   (30)  Tweeten et al. An Economic Analysis&#13;
of Carryover Policies,   (31)  U.S. Congress (various studies),  (32)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
76&#13;
U.S.D.A. "vzrld Food Security and Grain Stocks",       (33)  U.S.D.A.&#13;
"International Food Policy Issues - A Proceedings", (34) Walker and&#13;
Slaughter Managing Buffer Stocks to Stabilize Wheat Prices, and (35)&#13;
Walker and Sharples (various studies).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
77&#13;
REEENCES&#13;
Adams, Darius M.; Richard W. Haynes; and David R. Darr.    "A Welfare&#13;
Analysis of Long-Term Fbrest Products Price Stabilization",&#13;
American Journal of Agricultural Economics, Vol. 59, November,&#13;
19/7, pp. 6b2-673.&#13;
Adams, F.G. and S. Klein (eds.). Stabilizing Wbrld Commodity Markets.&#13;
Lexington Books, 1978.&#13;
Adams, F.G. and J.R. Behrman. Commodity Eports and Economic Develop-&#13;
ment. Lexington Books, 1982.&#13;
Alao|ze, C.; H. Sturgess; and A. Watson. "Australian Wheat Storage: A&#13;
Dynamic Programming Approach" Australian Journal of Agricul-&#13;
tural Economics, Vol. 22, Nov. 1978, pp. 158-74.&#13;
Arrow, K.J. "Statistics and Economic Policy". Ezonometrica, Vol. 25,&#13;
1957, pp. 523-31.&#13;
Arzac, E.R. "An Econometric Evaluation of Stabilization Policies for&#13;
the U.S. Grain Market." Research Paper No. 174. Columbia&#13;
University, Graduate School of Business, New York, February,&#13;
1977.&#13;
Bailey, W.R.; F.A. Kutish; and A.S. Rojko. Grain Stock Issues and&#13;
Alternatives - A Progress Report. Economic Research Service/&#13;
U.S. Department of Agriculture Agricultural Economic Report,&#13;
February, 1974.&#13;
Bale, Malcolm D. and Ernst tAltz. "Price Distortions in Agriculture&#13;
and Their Effects: An International Cbmparison", American&#13;
Journal of Agricultural Economics, Vol. 63, FebruaryfI981, pp.&#13;
8-22.&#13;
Batra, R.N. and W.R. Russell. "Gains From Trade Under Uncertainty,"&#13;
American Economic Review. Vol. 64, Dec. 1974, pp. 1040-48.&#13;
Berck, P. and Andrew Schmitz. "The Simple Analytics of Price Supports&#13;
in the Context of Trade" in A. Sarris et al., Westview Press,&#13;
forthcoming.&#13;
Bieri, Jurg and Andrew Schmitz.    "Market Intermediaries and Price&#13;
Instability: Some Welfare Implications", American Journal of&#13;
Agricultural Economics, Vol. 56, May, 1974, pp. 280-85.&#13;
Bieri, Jurg and Andrew Schmitz.   "Export Instability, Moncpoly Power&#13;
and Welfare", Journal of International Economics, Vol. 3,&#13;
November 1973, pp. 389-96.&#13;
Bigman, David and S. Reutlinger. "Fcod Price and Supply Stabiliza-&#13;
tion: National Buffer Stocks and Trade Policies", American&#13;
Journal of Agricultural Economics, Vol. 61, November, 1979, pp.&#13;
657-667.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
78&#13;
Bigman, David and S. Reutlinger. "Food Price and Supply Stabiliza-&#13;
tion: National Buffer Stocks and Trade Policies." Wbrld Bank&#13;
and International Monetary Fund, May, 1978 (mimeographed).&#13;
Bigman, David and S. Reutlinger. "National and International Policies&#13;
toward Food Security and Price Stabilization." World Bank and&#13;
International Monetary Fund, August, 1978 (mimeographed).&#13;
Published in American Economic Review, May, 1979.&#13;
Bigman, David. Coping With Ringer: Toward a System of Food Security&#13;
and Price Stabilization, Ballinger Publishing Co., Cambridge,&#13;
Mass. 1982.&#13;
Brandow, G.E. "Grain Reserves and the U.S. Economy: A Policy Perspec-&#13;
tive." Analyses of Grain Reserves - A Proceedings, Economnic&#13;
Research Service, U.S. Department of Agriculture in cooperation&#13;
with the National Science Foundation. ERS Report No. 634&#13;
(August, 1976):92-97).&#13;
Brennan. M.J. "The Supply of Storage". American Economic Review,&#13;
Vol. 48 (1958), pp. 51-69.&#13;
Brzozowski, Leonard J.    "Grain Sales and Production Cycles - A&#13;
Computer Simulation Study." In Analyses of Grain Reserves - A&#13;
Proceedings, Economic Research Service, U.S. Department of&#13;
Agriculture, in cooperation with the National Science&#13;
Foundation, ERS Report No. 634 (August, 1976):174-196.&#13;
Burt, Oscar R.; Won W. Koo; and Norman J. Dudley. "Cptimal Stochastic&#13;
Control of U.S. Wheat Stocks and Exports", American Journal of&#13;
Agricultural Economics, Vol. 62, May, 1980, pp. 172-187.&#13;
Carter, Colin and A. Schmitz. "Import Tariffs and Price Formation in&#13;
the World Wheat Market." American Journal of Agricultural&#13;
Econanics. Vol. 61 (Aug. 1979), pp. 517-522.&#13;
Casley, D.J.; J.B. Simaika; and R.P. Sinha. "Instability of Produc-&#13;
tion and Its Inpact on Stock Requirements", Monthly Bulletin of&#13;
Agricultural Economics and Statistics 23 (May, 1974):1-8.&#13;
Chaipravat, Olarn. "International Rice Buffer Stock Cperations, A&#13;
Simulation Study." In Stabilizing World Cammodity Markets,&#13;
edited by F. Gerard Adams and Sonia Klein. Lexington, Mass.:&#13;
D.C. Heath and Co., 1978, Chapter 3, pp.63-81.&#13;
Chisholm, A.H. and R. Tyers.    Food Security: Theory, Policy, and&#13;
Perspectives from Asia and the Pacific Rim, Lexington, Mass.&#13;
1982.&#13;
Cochrane, Willard W. and Yigal Danin. Reserve Stock Grain Models, the&#13;
World and United States, 1975-1985, Minnesota Agricultural&#13;
EXperiment Station Technical Bulletin Nb. 305, 1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
79&#13;
Currie, J.M.; J.A. Murphy; and A. Schmitz. "The Concept of Economic&#13;
Surplus and Its Use in Economic Analysis", The Economic&#13;
Journal, Vol. 81, Dec. 1971, pp. 741-799.&#13;
Dunn, James and D.M. Heien. "The Gains from Price Stabilization: A&#13;
Quantitative Assessment", American Journal of Agricultural&#13;
Economics, Vol. 64, August, 1982, pp. 578-580.&#13;
Eaton, David; W. Scott Steele; Jared L. Cohon; and Charles S. ReVelle.&#13;
"The Joseph Problem: How Large a Grain Reserve?" The John&#13;
Hopkins University, Department of Geography and Environmental&#13;
Engineering, March 5, 1976. (mimeographed.)    Also appears in&#13;
Analyases of Grain Reserves - A Proceedings. Economic Research&#13;
' Service, U.S. Department of Agriculture, in cooperation with&#13;
the National Science Foundation, ERS Report No. 634 (August,&#13;
1976):39-55.&#13;
Ericksen, Milton H.; Daryll E. Ray; and James W. Richardson. "Farm&#13;
Programs and Grain Reserves - Simulated Results."   In Analyses&#13;
of Grain Reserves, A Proceedings, Economic Research Service,&#13;
U.S. Department of Agriculture, in cooperation with the&#13;
National Science Foundation, ERS Report No. 634 (August,&#13;
1976):136-156.&#13;
Feder, G.; R.E. Just; and A. Schmitz. "Storage With Price Uncertainty&#13;
in International Trade." International Economic Review, Vol.&#13;
18, Cct. 1977, pp. 553-68.&#13;
Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, Cormittee on&#13;
CanTodity Problems.   "Report of the Expert Consultation on&#13;
Cereal Stock Policies Relating to World Food Security." FAO&#13;
Publication CCP:75/15, Romxe, March, 1975.&#13;
Gardner, Bruce L. Cptimal Stockpiling of Grain. Lexington MA:DC.&#13;
Heath Co., 1979.&#13;
Gardner, Bruce- L. --Farmer-Owned Grain Reserve Program Needs Modifica-&#13;
tion to Improve Effectiveness:-Consequences of USDA's Farmer-&#13;
Owned Reserve Program for Grain Stocks and Prices. Report to&#13;
the Congress, Vol. 2, June 26, 1981.&#13;
Gislason, Conrad.    A Quantitative Analysis of Grain Storage.&#13;
Technical Bulletin 37. Washington State University, Washington&#13;
Agricultural Experiment Station, August, 1961.&#13;
Greenes, T.; P.B. Johnson; and M. Thursby.   "Insulating Trade Policy,&#13;
Interventions and Wheat Price Stability", American Journal of&#13;
Agricultural Economics 60 (February, 1978):132-134.&#13;
Gustafson, Robert L. Carryover Levels for Grains, U.S. Department of&#13;
Agriculture Technical Bulletin 1178.      Washington, D.C.&#13;
Government Printing Office, October, 1958.&#13;
Hanoch, G. "Desirability of Price Stabilization or Destabilization",&#13;
Harvard Institute of Economic Research, 1974.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
80&#13;
Hathaway, Dale E.   "Grain Stocks and Econanic Stability: A Policy&#13;
Perspective." Analyses of Grain Reserves - A Proceedngs,&#13;
Economic Research Service, U.S. Department of Agriculture, in&#13;
cooperation with the National Science Foundation. ERS Report&#13;
Nb. 634 (August, 1976):1-11.&#13;
Hazell, P.B.R. and P.L. Scandizzo.     "Cptimal Price Intervention&#13;
Policies When Production is Risky", presented at the&#13;
Agricultural Development Council Conference on Risk and&#13;
Uncertainty in Agricultural Development, CDMMYT, Mexico, 1976.&#13;
Helmberger, Peter and Rob Weaver. "Welfare Implications of Commodity&#13;
Storage Under Uncertainty", American Journal of Agricultural&#13;
Economics, Vol. 59 (1977), pp. 639-651.&#13;
Helpman, E. and A. Razin. "Uncertainty and International Trade in the&#13;
Presence of Stock Markets."    Review of Economic Studies,&#13;
forthcoming.&#13;
Helpman, E. and A. Razin. "Welfare Aspects of International Trade in&#13;
Goods and Securities," Quarterly Journal of Economics, XCII&#13;
(Aug. 1978), pp. 489-508.&#13;
Hillman, J.; D.G. Johnson; and R. Gray. "Food Reserve Policies for&#13;
World Food Security: A Consultant Study on Alternative&#13;
Approaches." Background document for the Expert Consultation&#13;
on Cereal Stock Policies Relating to World Food Security, Food&#13;
and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, FAO&#13;
Publication, ESC/CSP:75/2, rome, February 24-28, 1975&#13;
(mimeographed).&#13;
Houck, James P. and Mary E. Ryan. Economic Research on International&#13;
Grain Reserves: the State of Knowledge, Agricultural&#13;
Experimnental Station Bill 532, 1979, University of Minnesota.&#13;
Huddleston, B.; D.G. Johnson; S. Reutlinger; and A. Valdes. Inter-&#13;
-- - national Finances for Food Security. (Baltimore, Maryland: John&#13;
Hopkins Univ. Press, forthcoming).&#13;
Hueth, Darrell and Andrew Schmitz.    "International Trade in Inter-&#13;
mediate and Final Goods:     Some Welfare Implications of&#13;
Destabilized Prices", Quarterly Journal of Economics, Vol. 86&#13;
(1972), pp. 351-365.&#13;
Johnson, D. Gale and Daniel Sumner.    "An Cptimization Approach to&#13;
Grain Reserves for Developing Countries." Analysis of Grain&#13;
Reserves - A Proceedings, Economic Research Service, U.S.&#13;
Department of Agriculture, in oooperation with the National&#13;
Science Foundation, ERS Report No. 634 (August, 1976):56-76.&#13;
Johnson, D. Gale and Daniel Sumner. "Estimating Appropriate Levels of&#13;
Grain Reserves for the United States". Research Report, Paper&#13;
Nb. 77(February 10, 1978):26.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
81&#13;
Jones, B.F. "Grain Reserves in Agricultural and Food Policy." Purdue&#13;
University, Agricultural ExperiTmnt Station, West Lafayette,&#13;
Indiana, Bulletin No. 124, May, 1976.&#13;
Jones, B.F. "A Grain Reserve Program." Purdue University, Department&#13;
of Agricultural Econcmcs, Agricultural Experiment Station, West&#13;
Lafayette, Indiana, Bulletin No. 137, August, 1976.&#13;
Josling, Timothy. An International Grain Reserve Policy. British-&#13;
North American Ccmmittee, 1973.&#13;
Just, Richard E.   "Risk Response Models and Their Use in Agricultural&#13;
Policy Evaluation", American Journal of Agricultural Economics,&#13;
Vol. 57 (1975), pp. 836-843.&#13;
Just, Richard E.; Darrell L. Hueth; and Andrew Schmitz.     Applied&#13;
Welfare Economics and Public Policy, Prentice Hall Inc.,&#13;
Englewood Cliffs, N.J., January, 1982.&#13;
Just, Richard E.; Darrell L. Hueth; and Andrew Schmitz. Farmer-Cwned&#13;
Grain Reserve Program Needs Modification to Inprove Effective-&#13;
ness: Theoretical and Empirical Conditions in Agricultural&#13;
Buffer Stocks Policy Under the Food and Agricultural Act of&#13;
1977. Report to the Congress, Vol. 3, June 26, 1981.&#13;
Just, Richard E.; Ernst Lutz; Andrew Schmitz; and Stephen Turnovsky.&#13;
"The Distribution of Welfare Gains from Price Stabilization: An&#13;
International Perspective", Journal of International Economics,&#13;
Vol. 8, No. 4 (Nov. 1978), pp. 551-563.&#13;
Just, Richard E.; Ernst Lutz; Andrew Schmitz; and Stephen Turnovsky.&#13;
"The Distribution of Welfare Gains fron International Price&#13;
Stabilization Under Distortions,' American Journal of&#13;
Agricultural Economics, Vol. 59 (1977), pp. 652-661.&#13;
Just, Richard E. and J. Arne Hallam.     "Functional Flexibility in&#13;
Analysis of Commodity Price Stabilization Policy", Proceedings,&#13;
Journal of the American Statistical Association, 1978, pp.&#13;
177-186.&#13;
Just, Richard E. and J.A. Hallam. "New Developments in Econometric&#13;
Evaluation of Price Stabilizing and Destabilizing Policies", in&#13;
New Directions in Econometric Modelling and Forecasting in U.S.&#13;
Agriculture, ed. Gordon C. Rausser (Amsterdam: North-Holland),&#13;
1981.&#13;
Just, Richard E. and M.S. Salkin. "Welfare Effects of Stabilization&#13;
in a Vertical Market Chain", Southern Economic Journal, Vol. 42&#13;
(1976), pp. 633-643.&#13;
Just, Richard E. and Andrew Schmitz. "The Instability-Storage-Cbst-&#13;
Trade-Off and Nonoptimality of Price Bands in Stabilization&#13;
Policy",   Giannini Fbundation Wbrking Paper, Department of&#13;
Agricultural and Resource Economics, University of California,&#13;
Berkeley, 1979.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
82&#13;
Keeler, Emmett B. "A Model for Evaluating Grain Reserve Policies.n&#13;
The Rand Corporation, Santa Monica, California, March, 1976&#13;
(mimeographed).&#13;
Knapp, Keith C.    "Cptimal Grain Carryover in Cpen Economics: A&#13;
Graphical Analysis", Journal of Agricultural Economics, Vol.&#13;
64, May, 1982, pp. 197-204.&#13;
Konandreas, Panos A. and A. Schmitz. "Welfare Inplications of Grain&#13;
Price Stabilization: Some Empirical Evidence for the United&#13;
States", American Journal of Agricultural Economics, Vol. 60,&#13;
February, 1978, pp. 74-84.&#13;
Konandreas, Panos A.; Barbara Huldleston; and Virabongsa Ramangjura.&#13;
Food Security; an Insurance Approach.      Research Report 4,&#13;
International Food Policy Research Institute, Washington, D.C.,&#13;
September, 1978. Also see Konandreas, Panos. "Cost Analysis&#13;
of a Food Insurance Scheme for Developing Countries", August,&#13;
1978 (mimeographed).&#13;
Letiche, J.M.; R.G. Chambers; and A. Schmitz. "The Development of&#13;
Grains from Trade Theory: Classical to Modern Literature in&#13;
M.B. Ballabon Economic Perspectives: An Annual Survey of&#13;
Economics, Vol. 1 1979, pp. 119-149. Harwood Academic&#13;
Publishing, New York.&#13;
Levis, A.H. and E.R. Ducot. "AGRIMOD; A Simulation Model for Analysis&#13;
of U.S. Food Policies.' Paper No. 5152-02. Systems Control,&#13;
Inc., 1976 (mimeographed).&#13;
Lutz, Ernst. Grain Reserves and International Price Stabilization,&#13;
unpublished Ph.D. thesis, Department of Agricultural and&#13;
Resource Economics, University of California, Berkeley, 1977.&#13;
Lutz, Ernst and Malcolm D. Bale.      "Agricultural Protectionism in&#13;
Industrialized Countries and Its Global Effects: A Survey of&#13;
Issues", The Swiss Review.-of International Econanic Relations,&#13;
Vol. 35, December 1980, pp. 311-54.&#13;
McIntire, John.   Food Security in the Sahel: Variable Import Levy&#13;
Grain Reserves and Foreign Exchange Assistance #26, Inter-&#13;
national Food Policy Research Institute, Washington, D.C. 1981.&#13;
McKinnon, R.I. "Futures Markets, Buffer Stocks and Income Stability&#13;
for Primary Producers", Journal of Political Economy, Vol. 75,&#13;
1967, pp. 844-861.&#13;
Massell, B.F. "Price Stabilization and Welfare", Quarterly Journal of&#13;
Economics, Vol. 83 (1969), pp. 285-297.&#13;
Massell, B.F.    "Some Welfare Implications of International Price&#13;
Stabilization, Journal of Political Economy, Vol. 78 (March/&#13;
April 1970) pp.-404-17.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
83&#13;
Mbrrow, Daniel T. and W. Scott Steele.    "Toward a World Food Reserve&#13;
System." Paper presented at International Studies Association&#13;
Meeting, Washington, D.C., February 24, 1978 (mimeographed).&#13;
National Ommission on Supplies and Shortages.     Government and the&#13;
Nation's  Resources.    U.S. Government Printing Office,&#13;
Washington, D.C., December, 1976, pgs. 150-154.      Also see&#13;
Studies on Economic Stockpiling.     U.S. Government Printing&#13;
Office, Washington, D.C., September, 1976.&#13;
Newbery, D.N.G. and J.E. Stiglitz.    The Theory of Commodity Price&#13;
Stabilization: A Study in the Economics of Risk, Oxford:&#13;
Clarendon Press, 1981.&#13;
Newbery, D.N.G. and J.E. Stiglitz. "Comnmdity Price Stabilization&#13;
Rules", The Economic Journal, Vol. 89, Dec. 1979, pp. 799-817.&#13;
Newbery, D.N.G.    "Commodity Price Stabilization in Inperfectly&#13;
-   Competitive Markets", World Bank Discussion Paper No. 32,&#13;
December, 1981&#13;
Nguyen, D.T. "The Implications of Price Stabilization for the Short-&#13;
Time Instability and Long-Term Level of LDC's Export Earnings",&#13;
Quarterly Journal of Economics, Vol. 93, February 1979, pp.&#13;
149-154.&#13;
Nguyen, D.T.    "Partial Price Stabilization and Export Earning&#13;
Instability". Cxford Economic Papers, Vol. 30. July 1980, pp.&#13;
340-52.&#13;
Nichols, A.L. and R.J. Zeckhauser. "Stockpiling Strategies and Cartel&#13;
Prices", Bell Journal of Econanics, Vol. 8, pp. 66-96, 1977.&#13;
O'Carroll, Francis X. and Harlon D. Traylor. "An Econanic Analysis of&#13;
a Reserve Stock Program for Rice in the United States." D.A.E.&#13;
Research Report No. 517.     Louisiana State University and&#13;
-Agricultural and Mechanical College, April, 1977.&#13;
Oi , W.Y.   "The Desirability of Price Instability Under Perfect&#13;
Competition", Econometrica, Vol. 27 (1961), pp. 58-64.&#13;
Peck, Anne E. "Hedging and Income Stability - Concepts, Implications&#13;
and An -Example", American Journal of Agricultural Economics,&#13;
Vol. 58, February 1976, pp. 410-419.&#13;
Peck, Anne E. "Futures Markets, Supply Response and Price Stability",&#13;
Quarterly Journal of Economics, Vol. 90, 1976, pp. 407-423.&#13;
Pinstrup-Anderson, Per, M.R. de Londons and Edward Hoover.       "The&#13;
Impact of Increasing Food Supply on Human Nutrition: Implica-&#13;
tions for Commodity Priorities in Agricultural Research and&#13;
Policy", American Journal of Agricultural Economics, Vol. 58,&#13;
May, 1976, pp. 131-142.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
84&#13;
Ray, Darryll E.   "Managing Instability with Commodity Reserves: A&#13;
Preliminary Assessment."   Stability: The Continuing Quest.&#13;
Proceedings of the Great Plains Agricultural Policy Seminar,&#13;
Denver, Colorado, May 19-20, 1975. Great Plains Agricultural&#13;
Council, Publication No. 74, pgs. 89-97.&#13;
Ray, Darryll E.; James W. Richardson; and Glenn S. Collins.      "A&#13;
Simulation Analysis of a Reserve Stock Management Policy for&#13;
Feed Grains and Wheat.n    Southern Journal of Agricultural&#13;
Economics 7 (July, 1975):81-87.&#13;
Reutlinger, Shlomo.   "A Simulation Model for Evaluating Worldwide&#13;
Buffer Stocks of Wheat", American Journal of Agricultural&#13;
Economics, Vol. 58 (Feb. 1976), pp. 1-12.&#13;
Reutlinger, Shlomo and David Bigman. "Feasibility, Effectiveness and&#13;
costs of Food Security Alternatives in Developing Countries" in&#13;
Food Security for Developing Countries, ed. Alberto Valdes&#13;
(Boulder, Colorado: West View Press, 1981).&#13;
Reutlinger, Shlomo; David Eaton; David Bigman; and David Blum.&#13;
"Should Developing Nations Carry Grain Reserves?" World Bank&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 244, September, 1976. Also in Analyses&#13;
of Grain Reserves, A Proccedings, Economic Research Service,&#13;
U.S. Department of Agriculture, in cooperation with the&#13;
National Science Foundation.    E1S Report No. 634 (August,&#13;
1976):12-18.&#13;
Reutlinger, Shlomo. "Food Insecurity: Magnitude and Remedies." World&#13;
Bank Staff Working Paper No. 267, July, 1977, and in World&#13;
Development, Vol. 16(1978):794-811.&#13;
Reutlinger, Shlomo.   "The Level and Stablity of India's Food Grain&#13;
Consumption." In "India Occasional Papers," World Bank, Staff&#13;
Working Paper No. 279, January, 1978 (mimeographed).&#13;
Reutlinger, Shlomo.   "Policies for Food Security in Food Irrporting&#13;
Countries" in A.H. Chisholm and R. Tyers Food Security: 'Theory,&#13;
Policy and Perspectives fran Asia and the Pacific Rim, 1982.&#13;
Rojko, Anthony S. "The Economics of Food Reserve Systems." American&#13;
Journal of Agricultural Econonics 57 (December, 1975):866-872.&#13;
Ruffin, R.F.   "International Trade Under Uncertainty,"   Journal of&#13;
International Economics, Vol. 4(Aug. 1974), pp. 243-59.&#13;
Sampson, G.P. and R.H. Snape.    "Effects of EEC's Variable Import&#13;
Levies", Journal-of Political Economy, Vol. 88, October 1980,&#13;
pp. 1026-1040.&#13;
Samuelson, Paul A.   "The Consumer Does Benefit from Feasible Price&#13;
Stability", Quarterly Journal of Econanics, Vol. 86, No. 3&#13;
(1972), pp. 476-493.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
85&#13;
Sanderson, Fred H. "The World Food Problem: Posibilities of Inter-&#13;
national Action." Cirrent History 68 (June, 1975):265-270,&#13;
276-277.&#13;
Sanderson, Fred H. "Economic Stockpiling: Grains." Paper presented&#13;
at the panel on Economic Stockpiling, sponsored by the Society&#13;
of Government Economists, New York, N.Y., December 29, 1977&#13;
(mimeographed).&#13;
Sarris, Aleco; A. Schmitz and G. Storey. International Agricultural&#13;
Trade: Advanced Readings in Price Formation, Market Structure&#13;
and Price Instability, Westview Press (forthcoming).&#13;
Sarris, Aleco.  "Export Taxes Versus Buffer Sto.ks as Cptimal Export&#13;
Policies  Under Uncertainty".     Giannini Foundation of&#13;
Agricultural Economics, University of California, Berkeley&#13;
Working Paper No. 174.&#13;
Sarris, Aleco.    "Speculative Storage, Futures Market, and the&#13;
Stability of Commodity Prices", Calif. Ag. Expt. Station&#13;
Giannini Foundation Working Paper No. 160, March, 1982.&#13;
Sarris, Aleco.   "Grain Inports and Food Security in an Unstable&#13;
International Market". Journal of Development Economics, vol.&#13;
7, 1980, pp. 489-504.&#13;
Sarris, Aleco.   "Methods for Cptimal Grain Stockpiling for Inter-&#13;
national Price Stabilization", Buropean Review of Agricultural&#13;
Economics, Vol. 5, 1981, pp. 71-84.&#13;
Sarris, Aleco and Lance Taylor.   "Buffer Stocks Analysis for Agri-&#13;
cultural Products: Theoretical Murk or Empirical Resolution" in&#13;
F.G. Adams and S. Klein (ed's) Stabilizing World Comnodity&#13;
Markets, Lexington Books 1978.&#13;
Sarris, Aleco and Lance Taylor. "Cereal Stocks, Food Aid and Security&#13;
for the Poor", World Development, 1976, vol. 4, pp. 967-976.&#13;
Sarris, Aleco; P.C. Abbott; and Lance Taylor.      "Grain Reserves,&#13;
Emergency Relief, and Food Aid" in W.R. Cline (ed.) Policy&#13;
Alternative for a New International Economic Order, Praeger,&#13;
Schmitz, Andrew; Alex F. McCalla; Donald 0. Mitchell; and Colin A.&#13;
Carter. Grain Export Cartels, Ballinger Publ. Co., Cambridge,&#13;
Mass. December, 1981.&#13;
Schmitz, Andrew; H. Shalit; and S.J. Turnovsky. "Producer Welfare on&#13;
-the Preference for Price Stability", American Journal of&#13;
Agricultural Economics, Vol. 63, February 1981, pp. 157-160.&#13;
Sharples, J.A. and Forrest D. Holland.    "Impact of the Farmer-Owned&#13;
Reserve on Privately Owned Wheat Stocks", American Journal of&#13;
Agricultural Economics, Vol. 63, August 1981, pp. 538-543.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
86&#13;
Sharples, J.A. and Rodney L. Walker.     "Reserve Stocks of Grain:&#13;
Analysis of Wheat Loan Rates and Target Prices Using a Wheat&#13;
Reserve  Stocks Simulation Model."   Research Status Report No.&#13;
2. Commodity Economics Division/Economic Research Service/U.S.&#13;
Department of Agriculture and Department of Agricultural&#13;
Economics, Purdue University, May, 1975.&#13;
Sharples, J.A.; Rodney L. Walker; and Rudie W. Slaughter, Jr.&#13;
Managing Buffer Stocks to Stabilize Wheat Prices. Economic&#13;
Research Service/U.S. Department of Agriculture Agricultural&#13;
Economic Report No. 341, July, 1976.&#13;
Sharples, J.A. and Rodney L. Walker.      "Grain Reserves: Price&#13;
Instability and tiAe Food Supply."   Agricultural-Food Policy&#13;
Review.    Economic Research Service/7.S. Department of&#13;
AgiIculture AFPR-l(January, 1977):85-92.&#13;
Sharples, Jerry A. and Rudie W. Slaughter, Jr.    "Alternative Agri-&#13;
cultural and Food Policy Directions for the U.S. with Emphasis&#13;
on Stability of Prices and Producer Income." Agricultural and&#13;
Food Price and Income Policy, Alternative Directions for the&#13;
United States,   edited by Robert G.F. Spitze, Report of a&#13;
Policy Research Wbrkshop, Washington, D.C., January 15-16,&#13;
1976. University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Agricultural&#13;
Experiment Station, Special Publication No. 43, August, 1976,&#13;
pp. 74-92.&#13;
Shei, Shun-Yi and Robert L. Thompson.   "The Impact of Trade Restric-&#13;
tions on Price Stability in the World Wheat Market". American&#13;
Journal of Agricultural Economics, Vol. 59, Nov. 1977, pp.&#13;
628-638.&#13;
Steele, W. Scott.   "The Grain Reserve Issue."    Economic Research&#13;
Service/U.S. Department of Agriculture/Foreign Demand and&#13;
Ccmpetition Division working paper, July, 1974.&#13;
Steele, W. Scott.- "Alternative Approaches to Stabilizing Inter--&#13;
national Markets." Southern Journal of Agricultural Economics&#13;
8(July, 1976):57-62.&#13;
Stein, John P.; Emett Keeler; and Rodney T. Smith. U.S. Grain&#13;
Reserves Policy: Cbjectives, Costs and Distribution of&#13;
Benefits. R-2028/-RC.  The Rand Corporation, February, 1977.&#13;
Stein, John P. and Rodney Tbpper Smith. The Economics of United&#13;
States Grain Stockpiling.   R-1861-CIEP.  The Rand Corporation,&#13;
March, 1977.&#13;
Subotnik, A. and J.P. Houck.    "Welfare Implications of Stabilizing&#13;
Consumption and Production," American Journal of Agricultural&#13;
Economics, Vol. 58 (1976), pp. 13-20.&#13;
Talpaz, Hovav and Robert C. Taylor. "Cptimal Wheat Reserves in the&#13;
United States." Paper presented at the European Econometric&#13;
Society Annual Meeting, Vienna, Austria, September, 1977.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
87&#13;
Taylor, C.R. and H. Talpaz. "Approximately Cptimal Carryover Levels&#13;
for Wheat in the United States", American Journal of Agri-&#13;
cultural Economics, Vol. 61, February, 1979, pp. 32-40.&#13;
Taylor, Lance.   "Rich Country Policy and Food Security for the Less&#13;
Developed World.n    Paper prepared for the Agricultural&#13;
Development Council Seminar on "LDC Food Security: The&#13;
International Response, I  Reston, Virginia, August, 1978.&#13;
Massachusetts Institute of Technology, International Nutrition&#13;
Program, July, 1978 (mimeographed).&#13;
Taylor, Lance; Alexander H. Sarris; and Philip C. Abbott. "Grain&#13;
Reserves, Energency Relief, and Food Aid." Overseas Develop-&#13;
ment Council, Wcashington, D.C., 1977.&#13;
Tisdell, C. "Some Circumstances in Which Price Stabilization by the&#13;
Wool Commission Reduces Income", Australian Journal of&#13;
Agricultural Economics, August 1972, Vol. 16, pp. 94-101&#13;
Toshihisa, Tbyoda. "Import Instability and Tariffs: Some Implications&#13;
of Price Stabilization". Journal of Political Economy, Vol. 84,&#13;
April 1974, pp. 395-400.&#13;
Trezise, P.H.   Rebuilding Grain Reserves: Toward an International&#13;
System. Brookings Institute, Washington, D.C., 1976.&#13;
Turnovsky, Stephen.   "The Distribution of Welfare Gains from Price&#13;
Stabilization: The Case of Multiplicative Disturbances",&#13;
International Economic Review, Vol. 17 (1976), pp. 133-148.&#13;
Turnovsky, Stephen.   "Price Expectations and the Welfare Gain from&#13;
Price Stabilization", American Journal of Agricultural&#13;
Economics, Vol. 56, 1974, pp. 706-716.&#13;
Turnovsky, Stephen.   "The Distribution of Welfare Gains from Price&#13;
Stabilization: A Survey of Some Thieoretical Issues" in&#13;
-Stabilizing World ComTcdity Markets, ed. F.G. Adams and S.A.&#13;
Klein (Lexington, Mass: Heath - Lexington Books, 1978), pp.&#13;
119-48.&#13;
Turnovsky, Stephen.   "Futures Markets, Private Storage, and Price&#13;
Stabilization", Journal of Public Economics, Australian&#13;
National University, June, 1978.&#13;
Turnovsky, Stephen; H. Shalit; and A. Schmitz.   "Consumer's Surplus,&#13;
Price Instability and Consumer Welfare", Ezonometrica, Vol.&#13;
48, January 1980, pp. 135-52.&#13;
T[weeten, Luther; Dale Kalbfleisch;- and Y.C. Lu. An Economic Analysis&#13;
of Carryover Policies for the United States Wheat IndustrY.&#13;
Technical Bulletin T-132, Oklahoma State University, Agri-&#13;
cultural Experiment Station, October, 1971.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
88&#13;
U.S. Congress, House Cbmmittee on Foreign Affairs.  International Food&#13;
Reserves:Background and Qirrent Proposals.   Prepared for the&#13;
Foreign Affairs and Envirornmental Policy Division, Subcammittee&#13;
on International Organizations and Movements, Library of&#13;
Congress, Congressional Research Service, October, 1974, 93rd&#13;
Congress, 2nd Session.&#13;
U.S. Congress, House Committee on International Relations. The U.S.&#13;
Proposal for an International Grain Reserves System. Report of&#13;
a staff study mission to the Septembr 29-30, 1975, meeting of&#13;
the International Wheat Council Preparatory Group, November,&#13;
1975, Ccmmittee Print, 94th Congress, 1st Session.&#13;
U.S. Congress. The U.S. Proposal for an International Grain Reserves&#13;
System II. Report of a staff study mission to the September&#13;
28-COtober 3, 1977, meeting of the International Wheat Council&#13;
Preparatory Group, Cofmmittee Print, 95th Congress, 1st Session.&#13;
U.S. Congress. Senate Select Cbmmittee on Nutrition and Human Needs,&#13;
Caoptroller General of the United States. "Grain Reserves: A&#13;
Potential U.S. Food Policy Tool," March 26, 1976. OSP-76-16.&#13;
U.S. Department of Agriculture, Economic Research Service.    "WDrld&#13;
Food Security and Grain Stocks." The World Food Situation and&#13;
Prospects to 1985, Foreign Agricultural Economic Report No. 98,&#13;
December, 1974, pgs. 40-47.&#13;
U.S. Department of Agriculture, Economic Research Service. "Inter-&#13;
national Food Policy Issues - A Proceedings." Papers presented&#13;
at the Conference on International Food Policies Issues, held&#13;
in Washington, D.C., April 28-29, 1977. Foreign Agricultural&#13;
Economic Report No. 143, January, 1978.&#13;
Valdes, Alberto,   "Food Imports and Food Security: A Stabilization&#13;
Problem for Developing Countries", Paper presented at Global&#13;
Interdependence Center Conference, Minneapolis, Minnesota,&#13;
September 12-14, 1982.&#13;
Valdes, Alberta (ed.)    Food Security for Developing Countries.&#13;
Westview Press, Boulder, Colorado, 1981.&#13;
Walker, Rodney L; Jerry A. Sharples; and Forrest Holland.     "Grain&#13;
Reserves for Feed Grains and Wheat in the World Grain Market."&#13;
In Analyses of Grain Reserves - A Proceedings, Economic&#13;
Research Service/tU.S. Department of Agriculture, in cooperation&#13;
with the National Science Foundation.    ERS Report No. 634&#13;
(August, 1976):114-135.&#13;
Walker, Rodney L. and Jerry A. Sharples. "Stabilizating the Inter-&#13;
national Wheat Market with a U.S. Buffer Stock." Contributed&#13;
Papers of the 16th Governmental Conference of Agricultural&#13;
Economists, Cxford, 1977, pp. 55-68.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
89&#13;
Walker, Rodney L. and Jerry A. Sharples. Reserve Stocks of Grain: A&#13;
Review of Research.   U.S. Department of Agriculture, Economic&#13;
Research Service, Agricultural Economic Reoort No. 304, August,&#13;
1975.&#13;
Walker, Rodney L. and R.W. Slaughter.    Managing Buffer Stocks to&#13;
Stabilize TAheat Prices, Washington D.C., U.S.D.A. GRS&#13;
Agricultural Economics Report #341,1976.&#13;
Waugh, Frederick V.     "Does the Consumer Benefit from Price&#13;
Instability?", Quarterly Journal of Economics, Vol. 58 (1944),&#13;
pp. 602-614.&#13;
Working, H.   "Theory of the Inverse Carrying Charge in Futures&#13;
Markets." Journal of Farm Economics, Vol. 30 (1948) pp. 1-28.&#13;
Working, H.   "The Theory of the Price of Storage". American Economic&#13;
Review, Vol. 39, 1949, pp. 1254-62.&#13;
Young, Leslie and A. Schmitz. "Storage Under a Cartel" in A. Sarris&#13;
et al. Westview Press (forthcoming).&#13;
Zwart. A.C. and K.D. Meilke.    "The Influence of Domestic Pricing&#13;
Policies and Buffer Stocks on Price Stability in the World&#13;
Wheat Market", American Journal of Agricultural Economics, Vol.&#13;
61, August 1979, pp. 434-445.&#13;
Zwart. A.C. and K.D. Meilke.   "Economic Implications of International&#13;
Wheat Reserves."'   Discussion Paper No. 1.   University of&#13;
Guelph, School of Agricultural Economics and Extension&#13;
Education,    Guelph,   Ontario,    June,   1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
W   orld    Bank                         Commodity Trade and Price               tices and the effects of trade policy on&#13;
kTrends (1983-84 edition)                                        output prices using nominal protection&#13;
.   b    caTr                                      18  84 c                      coefficients. Builds a simultaneous&#13;
*ublic_tions                         Historical information on the trade of   supplv/demand model for cotton and&#13;
of Related                              developing countnes and eighty mar-      textiles that incorporates trade in tex-&#13;
ket price quotations for fifty-one com-  tiles and cotton lint and the behavior&#13;
Interest                                modities that figure importantly in in-  of textile mills Used for five- and ten-&#13;
ternational trade. Actual current and    year projections given a range of pol-&#13;
constant dollar prices are shown in     icy alternatives. Part of continuing&#13;
tabular and graphic form to indicate     work on the long-run prospects of In-&#13;
Analysis of the World Cocoa              commodity pnce movements relative        dian agriculture&#13;
Market                                   to the international price level.        Staff Working Paper No. 618. 7983 104&#13;
Takamasa Akiyama and Ronald C.           The Johns Hopkins University Press, Jour-  pages.&#13;
Duncan                                   nals Division. 1983. Annual 173 pages.  ISBN 0-8213-0322-8. Stock No WP 0618&#13;
Commodity Working Paper No 8 1982.      ISSN 0251-401X Stock No IB 0505 S20      55&#13;
64 pages (including 4 annexes)           paperback.&#13;
Stock No. BK 9050. 53.                   French and Spanish translations are pro-  Industrial Processing of&#13;
vided alongside the English in the same  Natural Resources&#13;
volume.                                  David Wall&#13;
Analysis of the World Coffee            Control, Accountability, and              Commodity Working Paper No 4 1979&#13;
Takamasa Akiyama and Ronald C.           Incentives in a Successful               23 pages.&#13;
Duncan                                   Development Institution: The             Stock No BK 9046 53&#13;
Commodity Working Paper No. 7. 1982.    Kenya Tea Development                     International Cotton Market&#13;
59 pages (including 4 annexes).          Authority                                Prospects&#13;
Stock No. BK 9049. $3.                  Geoffrey Lamb and Linda Muller            M. Elton Thigpen,&#13;
Analyzes the institutional factors in    with Maw-Cheng Yang&#13;
the success of the Kenya Tea Develop-    Commodity Working Paper No 2. 1978.&#13;
Case Studies on Industrial              ment Authority Draws lessons useful       72 pages (including 3 annexes)&#13;
Processing of Primary Products          to other development institutions.        So     No. BK 910  237&#13;
Stock No. BK 9170. S3.&#13;
Vol. 1 Bauxite,                         Staff Working Paper No. 550 1983. 72&#13;
Rubber,Tropical Hardwood                pages.                                    Natural Rubber&#13;
Analyzes primary products of            ISBN 0-8213-0118-7. Stock No. WP 0550     Theodore J. Goering&#13;
interest to developing countries to                ,                              Examines recent developments in the&#13;
provide a basis for some general        A Dynamic Simulation Model                global rubber market that form the ba-&#13;
principles regarding industrial         of the World Jute Economy                 sis for establishing World Bank policies&#13;
processing in those countries. The      Jock Anderson and others                 in lending for natural rubber produc-&#13;
first of two volumes of case            Staff Working Paper No 391. l980 39      tion. Builds on a comprehensive study&#13;
studies based on a joint research       pages (including references).             of the world rubber economy that was&#13;
project begun in April 1979             Stock No WP-0391. $3.                     prepared jointly bv the Bank and the&#13;
between the World Bank and the                                                    Food and Agriculture Organization ot&#13;
the United Nations in 1978 It also&#13;
Commonwealth Secretariat.               An Econometric Model of the               takes note of several subsequent de-&#13;
1983. 364 pages.                        World Rubber Economy                      velopments that are likely to affect the&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0154-3. Stock No. BK        Enzo R. Grilli, Ray M  Helterline,        demand for and supply of natural rub-&#13;
0154. $20.                               and Peter K. Pollak                      ber.&#13;
Commodity Working Paper No. 3. 1979      Sector Policy Paper. 2982 67 pages&#13;
Volume II. Cocoa, Coconut               44 pages.                                ISBN 0-8213-0045-8. j5&#13;
Oil, Tea                                Stock No. BK 9171. $3                    The Outlook for Primary&#13;
In-depth study assesses the problems                                             Commodities&#13;
and potential benefits of processing        NEW                                   Enzo R. Grilli, editor&#13;
these pnmary products and gives pol-                                             Commodity Working Paper No 9. 1982&#13;
icy recommendations. Considers the      The Economics of Cotton                   162 pages (including 3 annexes)&#13;
most important factors in determining   Cultivation in India: Supply             Stock No. BK 0142 S5.&#13;
the partucular location of the process-  and Demand for 1980-90&#13;
ing chains, gains and losses that might  Jon A. HitchingsSmultaneous Equaton&#13;
result from the initiation or expansion  An  A.     c           oigo             Model of Price and Quantity&#13;
of local processing, and selected policy  Analyzes the contrbution of irrigation  Adjustments in World Primary&#13;
measures to relocate the processing ac-  to the cotton production growth rate&#13;
tivities so that a greater share of the  Notes the returns to cotton cultivation  Commodity Markets&#13;
value added accrues to developing       over time. Discusses the potential for   Erh-Cheng Hvva&#13;
country suppliers.                      increasing profitability through im-     Staff Working Paper No 499. 1982 48&#13;
1983. 290 pages                         proved varieties and cultivation prac-   pages (incluIudin tootnotes, reterences, np-&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0155-1. Stock No BK 0155                                             pendix).&#13;
$10                                                                              Stock No. WP-0499 83&#13;
Order both Volumes I and 11 (Stock No. IB&#13;
0506) for $20 and save 510.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Tropical Hardwood Trade in               The World Rubber Economy:                World Rubber Market&#13;
the Asia-Pacific Region                  Structure, Changes, and                  Structure and Stabilization: An&#13;
Kenji Takeuchi                           Prospects                                Econometric Study&#13;
The Philippines, Malavsia, and Indo-     Enzo R. Grilli, Barbara Bennett          C. Suan Tan&#13;
nesia could industralize remote areas    Agostini, and Maria J. 't Hooft-         Examines the specification, estimation,&#13;
and more than triple foreign-exchange    Welvaars                                 and validation of an econometric&#13;
earnings through expansion of wood-      The first integrated analysis of the nat-  model of the world rubber market.&#13;
processing operations                    ural and synthetic rubber economies,     Uses the model to forecast natural rub-&#13;
The Jolins Hopkins University Press. 1974  with a unique study of the relative    ber prices and to analvze the implica-&#13;
108 pages (iciliding 3 annexes, statistical  costs of production of the main kinds  tions of natural rubber market stabili-&#13;
appendix, references),                   of rubber.                               zation. Discusses problems of the&#13;
LC 74-4214 ISBN 0-8018-1627-0. Stock     The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1980.  world rubber market, demand for rub-&#13;
No. IH 1627, 55 paperback.               222 pages                                ber products, supply of rubber, natural&#13;
World Ban   Commodit  LC 80-54. ISBN 08018-24214, Stockrubber export taxation, behavior of&#13;
World Bank Commodity                     LC 80-554.No. IH I421B 0 8 -             rubber stocks and pnces. Illustrates&#13;
Models                                                                           the impact of national government in-&#13;
Shamsher Singh, editor                   paperback.                               terventions in world commodity mar-&#13;
Commoditi,' Working Paper No. 6 2981.                                             kets. Includes nine appendixes and&#13;
Commodity Working Paper .Vo. 6 Z98Z.                                      bibliography.&#13;
547 pages.                               The World Sugar Economy: An              Commodity Working Paper 1984 424&#13;
Stock No. BK 9048 $20.                   Econometric Analysis of Long-            pages.&#13;
Term   Developments                      Stock No. BK 0264. S20.&#13;
Jos de Vries&#13;
Commodity Working Paper No. 5. 1980.&#13;
131 pages (including 2 annexes).&#13;
Stock No. BK 9047. S5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
*       The World Bank&#13;
Publications Order Form&#13;
SEND TO: YOUR LOCAL DISTRIBUTOR OR TO WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
(See the other side of this form)         P.O. BOX 37525&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013 U.S.A.&#13;
Date&#13;
Name                                                 Ship to: (Enter if different from purchaser)&#13;
Title                    '                           Name&#13;
Firm                                                 Title&#13;
Address                                              Firm&#13;
City              State_       Postal Code           Address&#13;
Country             TeIlephone (    )                City            State_      Postal Code   _&#13;
Purchaser Reference No.                              Country             Telephone&#13;
Check your method of payment.&#13;
Enclosed is my 0 Check gI International Money Order W Unesco Coupons W International Postal Coupon.&#13;
Make payable to World Bank Publications for U. S. dollars unless you are ordering from your local distributor.&#13;
Charge my O VISA f] MasterCard I American Express K] Choice. (Credit cards accepted only for orders addressed&#13;
to World Bank Publications.)&#13;
Credit Card Account Number           Expiration Date                     Signature&#13;
L Invoice me and please reference my Purchase Order No.&#13;
Please ship me the items listed below.&#13;
Customer Internal&#13;
Stock Number  Author/ Title                                      Routing Code  Quantity  Unit Price  Total Amount 5&#13;
All prices subject to change.  Prices may vary by country.  Allow 6-8 weeks for delivery.&#13;
Subtotal Cost  $&#13;
Thtal copies      Air mail surcharge if desired ($2.00 each)  $&#13;
Postage and handling for more than two complimentary items ($2.00 each)  S -&#13;
Total  $&#13;
IBRD-0053                                                         Thank you for your order.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Distributors of World                    Attn Mr. Giancarlo Bigazzi               Attn. Mr J7M. Hernandez&#13;
Via Lamarmora 45                         Castello 37&#13;
Bank Publications                        50121                                    Madrid&#13;
ARGENTINA                                Florence                                 SRI LANKA AND THE MALDIVES&#13;
Carlos Hirsch, SRL,                      JAPAN                                    Lake House Bookshop&#13;
Attn: Ms. Monica Bustos                  Eastern Book Service                     Attn: Mr. Victor Walatara&#13;
Florida 165 4° plSO                      Attn: Mr Terumasa Hirano                 41 Wad Ramanavake Mawatha&#13;
Galeria Guemes                           37-3, Hongo 3-Chome, Bunkyo-ku 113       Colombo 2&#13;
Buenos Aires 1307                        Tokyo                                    SWEDEN&#13;
AUSTRALIA, PAPUA NEW GUINEA,             KENYA                                    ABCE Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel&#13;
Fiji, SOLOMON ISLANDS,                   Africa Book Services (E.A ) Ltd          Attn. Mr. Eide Segerback&#13;
WESTERN SAMOA, AND                       Attn Mr MB. Dar                          Regeingsgatan 12, Box 16356&#13;
VANUATU                                  P.0 Box 45245                            S-103 27 Stockholm&#13;
The Australian Financial Review          Nairobi                                  SWITZERLAND&#13;
Information Service (AFRIS)              KOREA, REPUBLIC OF                       Libraine Pavot&#13;
Attn Mr. David Jamieson                  Pan Korea Book Cororation                Attn: Mr. Henri de Perrot&#13;
235-243 Jones Street                     Attn Mr. Yoon-Sun Kim                    6, rue Grenus&#13;
Broadwav                                 P 0. Box 101, Kwanghwamun                1211 Geneva&#13;
Sydney, NSW 20001                        Seoul                                    TANZANIA&#13;
BELGIUM                                  MALAYSIA                                 Oxford Universitv Press&#13;
Publications des Nations Unies           University of Malaya Cooperative         Attn. Mr. Anthony Theobold&#13;
Attn: Mr. Jean de Lannov                 Bookshop Ltd.                            Maktaba Road, P 0. Box 5299&#13;
av. du Roi 202                           Attn Mr. Mohammed Fahim Htj              Dar es Salaam&#13;
1060 Brussels                            Yacob                                    THAILAND&#13;
CANADA                                   P.O  Box 1127. Jalan Pantai Baru         Central Department Store, Head Office&#13;
Le Diffuseur                             Kuala Lumpur                             Attn: Mrs. Ratana&#13;
Attn Mrs Suzanne Vermette                MEXICO                                   306 Silom Road&#13;
C.P. 85, Boucherville J4B 5E6            INFOTEC                                  Bangkok&#13;
Quebec                                   Attn Mr Jorge Ce eda                     Thalland- Management Association&#13;
San Lorenzo 153-1 e Col del Valle,       Attn Mrs. Sunan&#13;
Librera Treios                           Deleg. Benito Juarez                     308 Silom Road&#13;
Attn: Mr Hugo Chamberlain                0310 Mexico, D.F.                        Bangkok&#13;
Calle 11-13, Av. Fernandez Guell         MIDDLE EAST                              TUNISIA&#13;
San Jose                                 Middle East Marketing Research           Societ6 Tunisienne de Diffusion&#13;
DENMARK                                  Bureau                                   Attn Mr. Slaheddine Ben Hamida&#13;
Sanfundslitteratur                       Attn. Mr George Vassilou                 5 Avenue de Carthage&#13;
Attn: Mr. Wilfried Roloff                 lakais l 3Avenue                        Tus&#13;
Rosenderns Alle 11                       Nicosla                                  TURKEY&#13;
DK-1970 Copenhagen V.                    Cvprus                                   Haset Kita pei A S&#13;
EGYPT, Arab Republic of                  (Branch offices in Bahrain, Greece.      Attn. Mr Izzet lzerel&#13;
Al Ahram                                 Morocco, Kuwait, United Arab             469, Istiklal Caddesi&#13;
Al Galaa Street                          Emirates, Jordan)                        Bevoglu-lstanbul&#13;
Cairo                                    NETHERLANDS                              UNITED KINGDOM AND&#13;
MBE BV                                   NORTHERN IRELAND&#13;
FINLAND                                  Attn. Mr. Gerhard van Bussell            Microinfo Ltd.&#13;
Akateeminen Kirlakauppa                  Noorderwal 38,                           Attn: Mr Rov Selwyn&#13;
Attn: Mr Kan Litmanen                    7241 BL Lochem                           Newman Lanre, P.O. Box 3&#13;
Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100                   NORWAY                                   Alton, Hampshire GU34 2PG&#13;
Helsinki 10                              Johan Grundt Tanum A S.                  England&#13;
FRANCE                                   Attn Ms. Randi Mikkelborg                UNITED STATES&#13;
World Bank Publications                  P 0. Box 1177 Sentrum                    UNThEWrD BTAnkBokStr&#13;
66, avenue d'lena                        Os1 lo 1                                 600 19th Street, N.W&#13;
75116 Paris                              PANAMA                                   Washington, D C. 20433&#13;
GERMANY, Federal Republic of             Ediciones Libreria Cultural Panamena     (Postal address: P.O. Box 37525&#13;
UNO-Verlag                               Attn: Mr Luis Fernandez Fraguela R.      Washington, D.C 20013, U S A.)&#13;
Attn: Mr. Joachim Krause                 Av. 7, Espana 16                         Baker and Taylor Companv&#13;
Simrockstrasse 23                        Panama oone 1                            501 South Gladiola Avenue&#13;
D-5300 Bonn I                            PHILIPPINES                              Momence, Illinois, 60954&#13;
HONG KONG, MACAU                         National Book Store                      380 Edison Way&#13;
Asia 2000 Ltd                            Attn: Mrs. Socorro C. Ramos              Reno, Nevada, 89564&#13;
Attn Ms Gretchen Wearing Smith           701 Rizal Avenue                         50 Kirby Avenue&#13;
6 Fl.. 146 Prince Edward Road            Manila                                   Somerville, New Jersey, 08876&#13;
Kowloon                                  PORTUGAL                                 Commerce Georgia 30599&#13;
INDIA                                    Livraria Portugal                        Cerce, Georga     309&#13;
UBS Publishers' Distributors Ltd         Attn: Mr Antonio Alves Martins           Bernan Associates&#13;
Attn- Mr. D P Veer  Rtia Do Carmv 70-74                      ~9730-E George Palmer Highway&#13;
Attn- Mr. D P Veer                       RaD     am     07                        Lanham, Maryland. 20761&#13;
1200                                                          "&#13;
5 Ansari Road, Post Box 7015             l2bo                                      Lankam, North Aec.n&#13;
New Delhi 110002                         isbon                                    Blackwell North Amenca, Inc&#13;
(Branch offices in Bombay, Bangalore.    SAUDI ARABIA                             1001 Fries Mill Road&#13;
Kanpur, Calcutta, and Madras)            Jarir Book Store                         Blackwood, New Jersey 08012&#13;
INDONESIA                                Attn Mr Akram Al-Agil                    Sidnev Kramer Books&#13;
Pt. Indira Limited                       P 0. Box 3196                            1722 R Street, N.W&#13;
Attn Mr Bambang Wahyudi                  Rivadh                                   Washington, D C. 20006&#13;
JI, Dr. Sam Ratulangi No. 37             SINGAPORE, TAIWAN, BURMA                 United Nations Bookshop&#13;
Jakarta Pusat                            Information Publications Pnvate, Ltd.    United Nations Plaza&#13;
IRELAND                                  Attn: Ms Janet David                     New York, N.Y 10017&#13;
TDC Publishers                           02-06 Ist Floor, Pei-Fu Industrial&#13;
Attn: Mr. James Booth                      Building                               VENEZUELA&#13;
12 North Frederick Street                24 New Industrial Road                  LAbrerna    del Este&#13;
Dublin I                                 Singapore                                Avda Francisco de Miranda, no 52&#13;
ITALY                                    SPAIN                                    Edificio Galipan, Aptdo. 60.337&#13;
Licosa Commissionaria Sansoni SPA        Mundi-Prensa Libros, S.A.                Caracas 1060-A&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IHG 3881.5 .W57 W67 NO.668&#13;
c.3&#13;
/-SCHMITZ, ANDREW.&#13;
COMMODITY PRICE&#13;
STABILIZATION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                                 European Office            Tokyo Office&#13;
1818 H Street, N W                           '66, avenue d'lena         Kokusai Building&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.               75116 Paris, France         1-1 Marunouchl 3-chome&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234                    Telephone: (i) 723-54.21    Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK                   Telex: 842-620628           Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                                Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
ISSN 0253-21 15/ISBN 0-8213-0415-1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554781">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/09/1554781/commodity-price-stabilization-theory-application
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1984/09/1554781/commodity-price-stabilization-theory-application</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1984/09/1554781/commodity-price-stabilization-theory-application</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/23/000178830_98101903423830/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/23/000178830_98101903423830/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-08-23T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1984-09-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Commodity price stabilization : the theory
            and its application
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This essay attempts to clarify and
            simplify the results of the literature on price
            stabilization in order to provide a better sense of the
            conditions under which commodity stabilization schemes will
            be successful and the welfare effects of such schemes. After
            introducing the early framework under which price
            stabilization was analyzed, the paper demonstrates the
            variance of results under alternative and more realistic
            situations. It treats topics such as storage and food
            security, inflation and economic development, public storage
            and futures markets, and non-storable goods. The conclusions
            are: (i) some countries may lose from price stabilization
            even though there is a net global gain; (ii) liberalized
            trade reduces the need for buffer stocks; (iii) futures
            markets reduce instability at a lower cost than buffer
            stocks; (iv) many national price stabilization schemes are
            actually price support systems used to improve farmers'
            incomes; (v) good price forecasting is a prerequisite to
            well-managed buffer stocks; (vi) price stability in poorer
            countries is not sufficient to avoid occasional food
            shortages; and (vii) food is costly to store and may not
            alleviate famine if transportation and distribution systems
            are inadequate.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Commodity price stabilization : the theory
            and its application
        </docna>
        <display_title>Commodity price stabilization :
            the theory and its application</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1984/09/1554781/commodity-price-stabilization-theory-application</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Markets and Market Access,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Access to Markets,Geographical Information Systems</subtopic>
        <teratopic>International Economics and Trade</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Schmitz, Andrew</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903423830</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Other agriculture</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 668</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>International Economics and Trade</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Agriculture, fishing, and forestry</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0415-1</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Price stabilization; Food storage; Food
            security; Inflation; Futures markets; Supply &amp; demand;
            Stochastic models
            area,bandwidth,buffer,cartel,Cartels,closed
            economy,commercial markets,competitive markets,competitive
            models,Consumer prices,consumers,demand curve,demand
            curves,demand elasticity,developed countries,economic
            development,economic rent,empirical analysis,empirical
            evidence,empirical studies,equilibrium,excess demand,excess
            supply,exports,free trade,Future
            research,Income,inflation,International Trade,less developed countries,
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP668</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Formulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Implementation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Productivity-Led Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Cartels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Horizontal Agreements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Price Fixing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Food Security and Nutrition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Free Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Econometrics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Anticartel Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adaptation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>