<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP785&#13;
The impact of Changing Affluence on Diet&#13;
and Demand Patterns&#13;
for Agricultural Commodities&#13;
Rajiv Chaudhri&#13;
C. Peter Timmer&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 785&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
For insertion in SWP 785&#13;
ERRATUM&#13;
The Impact of Changing Affluence on Diet and Demand Patterns&#13;
for Agricultural Commodities&#13;
by Rajiv Chaudhri and C. Peter Timmer&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 785&#13;
Page 10, last equation:&#13;
It says:&#13;
D(log Cj) = b.D(log Ej)&#13;
It should say:&#13;
D(log Cj) = b.D(log EP)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 785&#13;
The Impact of Changing Affluence on Diet&#13;
and Demand Pattems&#13;
for Agricultural Commodities&#13;
Rajiv Chaudhri&#13;
C. Peter Timmer&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright ©) 1986&#13;
The Intemational Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing January 1986&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To present the&#13;
results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been prepared&#13;
in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed texts, and the World&#13;
Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a token charge&#13;
to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The World Bank does not accept responsibility for the views expressed herein, which&#13;
are those of the authors and should not be attributed to the World Bank or to its&#13;
affiliated organizations. The findings, interpretations, and conclusions are the results&#13;
of research supported by the Bank; they do not necessarily represent official policy of&#13;
the Bank. The designations employed, the presentation of material, and any maps used&#13;
in this document are solely for the convenience of the reader and do not imply the&#13;
expression of any opinion whatsoever on the part of the World Bank or its affiliates&#13;
conceming the legal status of any country, territory, city, area, or of its authorities, or&#13;
concerning the delimitation of its boundaries, or national affiliation.&#13;
The most recent World Bank publications are described in the annual spring and fall&#13;
lists; the continuing research program is described in the annual Abstracts of Current&#13;
Studies. The latest edition of each is available free of charge from the Publications Sales&#13;
Unit, Department T, The World Bank, 1818 H Street, N.W, Washington, D.C. 20433,&#13;
U.S.A., or from the European Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'1ena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Rajiv Chaudhri is a securities analyst wih Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company in New York;&#13;
C. Peter Timmer is John D. Black professor of agriculture and business at the Harvard&#13;
University Graduate School of Business Administration. Both are consultants to the&#13;
World Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging-in-Publication Data&#13;
Chaudhri, Rajiv, 1957-&#13;
The impact of changing affiuence on diets and&#13;
demand patterns for agriculture.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 785)&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
1. Food consumption. 2. Food preferences. 3. Diet--&#13;
Economic aspects. 4. Diet--Social aspects. 5. Poor--&#13;
Nutrition. 6. Produce trade. I. Timmer, C. Peter,&#13;
1941-       .   II. Title.    III. Series.&#13;
HD9000.5.C49     1986              338.1'9            85-29424&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0683-9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Abstract&#13;
Demand for agricultural commodities, particularly for basic food-&#13;
stuffs, depends on a household's income, the prices it faces, and a set of&#13;
unique household characteristics which include tastes, location, education,&#13;
family composition, and farm status. This monograph reviews disaggregated&#13;
evidence at the national level on the relative contribution of each of&#13;
these factors and performs statistical analysis of national aggregate data&#13;
in a search for reliable patterns in this contribution. The paper examines&#13;
patterns of food consumption of the poor and amply confirms that the poor&#13;
are significantly more responsive to economic signals than better-off&#13;
households. The food consumption parameters of low-income groups can thus&#13;
serve as the basis for designing targeted food interventions that improve&#13;
their nutritional status without distorting the rest of the economy--an&#13;
important objective for food policy decisions and implementation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
As a lad, he had grown up in a poor family of Italian&#13;
origin. He was raised on blood sausage, pizza, spaghetti,&#13;
and red wine. After completing high school, he went to&#13;
Minnesota and began working in logging camps where --&#13;
anxious to be accepted -- he soon learned to prefer beef,&#13;
beer and beans, and he shunned all Italian food. Later he&#13;
went to a Detroit industrial plant, and eventually became a&#13;
promising young executive. This was in the days when it was&#13;
still fairly easy for a noncollege man to rise in industry.&#13;
In his executive role he found himself cultivating the&#13;
favorite foods and beverages of other young executives:&#13;
steak, whiskey and seafood. Ultimately he gained acceptance&#13;
in the city's upper classes. Now he began winning admira-&#13;
tion from people in his elite social set by going back to&#13;
his knowledge of Italian food and serving them, with the aid&#13;
of a man servant, authentic Italian treats such as blood&#13;
sausage, pizza, spaghetti and red wine.&#13;
-- Vance Packard, The Status Seekers, p. 146&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
THE IMPACT OF CHANGING AFFLUENCE ON DIETS AND DEMAND PATTERNS FOR&#13;
AGRICULTURAL COMMODITIES&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
Summary and Conclusion ............................................. vii&#13;
PART I&#13;
I  Introduction ..................................................     I&#13;
II  International Food Consumption Comparisons .        ...................  3&#13;
III An International Comparison of&#13;
Nutritional Patterns .......................                        9&#13;
PART 2&#13;
IV An Examination of Household Income&#13;
and Expenditure Data ........................................... 23&#13;
V  The Price Factor .    ............................................. 32&#13;
VI  The Influence of Demographic Variables ......       .................. 39&#13;
VII The Impact of Urbanization&#13;
on Diet Patterns .............................................. 44&#13;
VIII  The Social Factors .     ........................................... 47&#13;
PART 3&#13;
IX Consumption Patterns in the United States&#13;
1909-1980 .................................................... 50&#13;
X Implications of Affluent Food&#13;
Consumption Patterns .     ......................................... 59&#13;
References ......................... 63&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Page No.&#13;
Tables&#13;
1     Expenditure and Price Elasticities for Pooled Countries        .......  5&#13;
2      Per Capita Daily Food Supplies .........        .......................  9&#13;
3      Elasticity Coefficient from Caloric Intake Regression            -&#13;
Analysis Using Double Logarithmic Functions              ..          14&#13;
4      Elasticity Coefficients for Various Aspects of Diet&#13;
Quality Using Double Logarithmic Regression Functions                17&#13;
5     Relationship Between Income and Percent of Protein&#13;
in Caloric Intake        .      ......... . *.    ......             18&#13;
6      Distribution of Expenditure on Food and Drink by Income or&#13;
Expenditure Classes by Geographic Area (Mexico and Brazil)           26&#13;
7      Distribution of Expenditure on Food and Drink by Income or&#13;
Expenditure Classes by Geographic Area (Ghana and Kenya)             27&#13;
8      Distribution of Expenditure on Food and Drink by Income or&#13;
Expenditure Classes by Geographic Area (Japan and Korea) .           29&#13;
9     Distribution of Expenditure on Food and Drink by Income or&#13;
Expenditure Classes by Geographic Area (India)         ............... 30&#13;
10    Elasticity Estimates, United States, 1922-41 ........      ..   ........ 32&#13;
11    Compensated Price Responses by Income Class,&#13;
Indonesia, 1976 ............................................... 34&#13;
12    Hierarchy of Calorie Costs for Seven Countries, 1975 ..........       35&#13;
13    Price of 1000 Calories in National Currencies for&#13;
Seven Countries with Calories/Capita/Day from Each&#13;
Source    ....................................................... 37&#13;
14    Sao Paulo: Income and Age Distribution .........          ............... 41&#13;
15     Sao Paulo: Mean Family Size ................        ................... 42&#13;
16    Share of Major Food Groups in Nutrient Intake .........         ........ 53&#13;
17    Per Capita Consumption of Beef, Pork, and Poultry,&#13;
1970-80 ..    ............................................... 53&#13;
18    Relative Importance of Major Food Groups in Food Budget ....... 54&#13;
19     Trends in Processed Food ...............   .   ...................... 56&#13;
20    Retail Demand Elasticities for Selected Farm Products ........      . 58&#13;
21     Demand Elasticities for Meat          ..................... 61&#13;
22    Annual Per Capita Grain Consumption in Selected Countries .....        62&#13;
Figures&#13;
1     The Income Expansion Path for Caloric Intake .................. 20&#13;
2     A Hypothetical Adult Equivalent Scale for Consumption&#13;
of a Typical Food in the United States.                   .     ..   40&#13;
3      Trends in Four Measures of Per Capita Food Consumption&#13;
in the United States...... 51&#13;
4      Trends in Per Capita Consumption of Selected Food Products&#13;
i   n th  e  United States Potato.Consumptio  Per.Capia52&#13;
5      Fresh and Processed Potato Consumption Per Capita&#13;
in    the   United   States  .................       ....- ....  o..   &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- vii -&#13;
SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS&#13;
The ultimate goal of food consumption analysis is to improve the&#13;
potential for and efficiency of government interventions in increasing&#13;
staple food intake among the very poor. Food consumption interventions can&#13;
be targeted in a variety of ways, but they all require significant&#13;
knowledge about food consumption patterns of the poor, both descriptively&#13;
(including who the poor are and where they are located) and analytically&#13;
(how they change their food consumption patterns when their incomes or&#13;
prices change).&#13;
The analytic knowledge required includes answers to such&#13;
questions as, when average GNP per capita rises, how much is market demand&#13;
for rice likely to increase? Market demand for wheat? For cassava, corn,&#13;
and meat? How much meat is grain-fed, and what will growing meat demand do&#13;
to grain demand? How sensitive is market demand to absolute and relative&#13;
food prices? If all foodgrain prices rise relative to nonfood prices, how&#13;
much does demand drop? When prices rise, does wheat consumption rise while&#13;
rice consumption falls, and by how much?&#13;
In other words, knowing what the poor eat and why and how those&#13;
patterns will change when the external environment changes is essential to&#13;
designing targeted food interventions. Since most food interventions take&#13;
the form of an implicit or explicit subsidy, altering either the price&#13;
facing the consumer or transferring real income, the necessity to have&#13;
disaggregated price and income elasticities for important food staples is&#13;
obvious.&#13;
To the extent that it was possible, this is what this paper has&#13;
attempted. Despite the many gaps that currently exist in our knowledge,&#13;
one fact emerges quite clearly--the poor are significantly more responsive&#13;
to economic signals. Both income and price elasticities are higher for the&#13;
low-income classes as compared to the richer classes whether behavior is&#13;
measured in expenditures, quantities or amount of nutrient intake.&#13;
This has two implications. Firstly it suggests that perceived&#13;
undernutrition is not felt in the middle- and upper-income classes even in&#13;
the poor countries--otherwise their expenditure elasticities would be&#13;
higher. This apparently trivial point leads to the important policy&#13;
conclusion that generalized food subsidies which enable the entire&#13;
population to access cheap food are a wasteful use of public funds in as&#13;
much as this food is consumed by those who are going to use this 'income&#13;
transfer' to finance nonfood or better quality food consumption.&#13;
Secondly, it suggests that small increases in income can make&#13;
substantial differences to the caloric intake, and hence nutritional&#13;
status, of the extremely poor. The number of under-nourished people in the&#13;
world has been variously placed between 300 and 1,300 million. Whatever&#13;
the actual figure, it is clear that if their calorie-income elasticities&#13;
are as high as 0.6, then small increases in their income would lead to&#13;
significant increases in the market demand for foodgrains and exert an&#13;
upward pressure on grain prices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The fact that this does not happen and the world is periodically&#13;
deluged by grain surpluses is testimony to the extreme softness of demand&#13;
for the undernourished. Thus grain surpluses exist not because world&#13;
production is too much but because many of those who need the grain do not&#13;
have the resources to buy them. Also, it is clear to us that the only way&#13;
the poor will obtain these resources (in the long-run) is through increases&#13;
in their income from agriculture--on which the bulk of them currently&#13;
depend for their livelihood.&#13;
It is therefore tragically ironic to see such grain surpluses&#13;
cited as evidence and rationale for following a development strategy that&#13;
deliberately neglects agriculture. It is quite true that government&#13;
investment decisions should be guided by prospects of long-term payoff.&#13;
But one important aspect of a planner's intuition is the ability to foresee&#13;
that even if certain sectors are going to decline in future, some&#13;
investments in those sectors are needed to generate the economic growth&#13;
that ultimately powers that decline. In other words, it is important to&#13;
get the causation right. It is not a declining agricultural sector that&#13;
leads to economic development, hence justifying a neglect of government&#13;
investment in agriculture, but the other way round. It is economic&#13;
development that results in a declining agricultural sector, and, more&#13;
often than not this economic development has itself been powered by a&#13;
dynamic agricultural sector.&#13;
This brings us to the heart of the food policy dilemma. For the&#13;
farmer food prices are the major factor determining his income. The output&#13;
price signals the incentives to the farmer to use purchased inputs, new&#13;
technology, and household labor and managerial skills. Food prices&#13;
communicate the need to maintain adequate food supplies. Thus the need to&#13;
include dynamism in the agricultural sector translates into a need to&#13;
maintain attractive output prices for the producers.&#13;
On the other hand, for consumers, higher food prices restrict the&#13;
range of purchase available of both foods and other goods and services,&#13;
while lower food prices offer scope for greater food intake, a wider&#13;
variety of foodstuffs and higher quality diet, as well as an occasional new&#13;
shirt or a radio. For the very poor, survival itself may hinge on low food&#13;
prices.&#13;
Most governments use a variety of policy instruments to influence&#13;
the rural-urban terms of trade in general, and food prices in particular.&#13;
Frequently these prices are set to protect urban interests, to keep wages&#13;
low, or even to increase staple food intake among the poor. While the&#13;
short-run effects of these price policies might be viable and satisfactory&#13;
to government officials, their long-run and dynamic consequences are&#13;
frequently negative and worse, poorly understood.&#13;
Although food price policy in particular is seldom considered as&#13;
part of macroeconomic policy, in many poor countries with large rural&#13;
sectors, or simply a large fraction of personal income spent on basic food&#13;
commodities, the macroeconomic consequences of food price changes are quite&#13;
significant. The obvious impact is through the size of the government&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
budget devoted to price subsidies, but the foreign exchange impact may also&#13;
be quite important when food price changes alter the volume of imports or&#13;
exports. Countries with significant industrial sectors producing behind&#13;
tariff barriers for domestic consumption can also experience Keynesian&#13;
fluctuations in employment when food prices change. Higher food prices,&#13;
for example, force consumers to increase the budget share devoted to food&#13;
and reduce purchase of other goods and services supplied by domestic&#13;
industry and workers. If the reduced domestic demand cannot be compensated&#13;
by increasing exports, significant unemployment and reduced national income&#13;
can result.&#13;
At the same time, the impact of the macro-economy on the food&#13;
system is so powerful that it frequently dooms all efforts of policy makers&#13;
within the agricultural sector to make any headway in 'getting agriculture&#13;
moving' when the macro sector is sending contrary signals. A distorted set&#13;
of macro policies--which typically includes rapid inflation, an overvalued&#13;
exchange rate, subsidized interest rates for preferred creditors, minimum&#13;
wages for an urban working class elite, and depressed rural incentives--&#13;
makes rapid agricultural growth extremely difficult while it serves&#13;
simultaneously to skew the distribution of income.&#13;
Since much of the environment for rural decision-making is&#13;
dictated by macro policy and macro prices, rapid rural growth over long&#13;
periods of time can occur only when this macro environment encourages the&#13;
efficient allocation of resources. Short bursts of growth are possible&#13;
from any of the other elements in the decision-making environment--a new&#13;
seed technology, subsidized fertilizer, or a more effective extension&#13;
service. But for the long haul rural growth will falter in the absence of&#13;
an overall economic environment that encourages, and ultimately forces the&#13;
allocation of land, labor and capital into their most productive uses.&#13;
Macro policy reform require that the distortions usually&#13;
found--overvalued exchange rates, subsidized interest rates, depressed&#13;
agricultural incentives, and low food prices--be corrected. The&#13;
devaluation that brings foreign exchange rates into equilibrium usually&#13;
will pump new purchasing power into rural areas, with positive effects on&#13;
rural employment and improved income distribution. Price increases will&#13;
help reduce budget subsidies and cut inflationary pressures. Eventually,&#13;
scarcity values for labor and capital will induce a new efficiency in&#13;
resource use.&#13;
At the same time, the incentives needed to generate much of this&#13;
rural dynamism can seriously affect the food consumption of poor people.&#13;
By designing short-run targetted food consumption subsidies to help poor&#13;
people across the bridge to long-run dynamic economic growth, it can be&#13;
made easier for macro policy makers to implement the needed reforms in the&#13;
first place. To design much policy interventions, disaggregated&#13;
consumption parameters need to be used in order to identify how different&#13;
income classes adjust their consumption. The major concern, of course, is&#13;
to measure the extent to which consumer groups with marginal or inadequate&#13;
caloric intake may be pushed significantly below the margin if food prices&#13;
rise.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
In conclusion, we wish to emphasize the paramount importance of&#13;
getting prices right" in sending the right signals to the&#13;
decision-makers--consumers and producers--to ensure long term growth. The&#13;
overwhelming lesson of development experience over the past few decades is&#13;
that the efficiency with which resources are allocated determines how&#13;
dynamic and rapid the growth path will be. This notion is contrary to&#13;
early expectations of many economists and planners, who noted that static&#13;
economic losses due to allocative inefficiencies tend to be very small,&#13;
typically less than 2 percent of national income even of severe&#13;
distortions, and hence could easily be dominated by more rapid growth.&#13;
Just the opposite has happened.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-1-&#13;
Part 1&#13;
I. INTRODUCTION&#13;
It might seem quite apparent, on the basis of casual empiricism&#13;
alone, that human behavior diverges widely across nations because of&#13;
'social-cultural' reasons.   In fact this may be more true for food&#13;
consumption patterns than for other items of expenditure. What then, is&#13;
the justification for cross country studies of food habits?&#13;
Ernst Engel established well over a century ago that expenditures&#13;
for such basic human needs as food, clothing and housing followed patterns&#13;
that were closely related to income. The most famous of these patterns,&#13;
that the share of food expenditures in the total household budget falls as&#13;
income rises, is now well established as Engel's Law.    The remarkable&#13;
aspect of Engel's Law is its seeming universality. Although Engel himself&#13;
based the first formulation of the food expenditure on his observation of&#13;
several dozen Saxony families who shared a common geographical and cultural&#13;
setting, subsequent research has confirmed the pattern for households in&#13;
every other country in which it has been studied. Even more remarkably,&#13;
comparisons of households across countries with different per capita income&#13;
levels show the same tendency.&#13;
This alone is sufficient to establish a prima facie case for&#13;
further investigation along cross country lines.     But there is more.&#13;
The real issue is not whether behavior, 'interculturally', is&#13;
similar or not, but whether similar determinants of behavior patterns help&#13;
explain the diversity. More specifically, the pertinent questions are&#13;
whether these determinants have similar functional relationships, with&#13;
behavior patterns across nations, and what the limits of these similarities&#13;
are. Three questions can be satisfactorily answered only after conducting&#13;
the international empirical analysis, not before.&#13;
It is also clear to us that we need to get a more precise handle&#13;
on what is meant by 'tastes' or 'preferences'. These terms have been used&#13;
rather loosely in the literature as catch-all expressions subsuming all the&#13;
eccentricities that economics finds difficult to explain. Quite obviously,&#13;
it would be useful to define, measure and isolate the impact of tastes on&#13;
behavior patterns. Chapter I, entitled "International Food Consumption&#13;
Comparisons", which examines expenditure patterns is an effort in that&#13;
direction.&#13;
While Chapter I looks at the relationship between income and&#13;
broad expenditure categories, Chapter II bears on the implications of this&#13;
relationship for nutritional status. The focus is on intakes of calories&#13;
and proteins rather than food expenditures and on how these are determined&#13;
by incomes and prices. Again cross-country data are analyzed, so what we&#13;
see emerging are the long-run relationships.&#13;
The first two chapters constitute Part 1 of this essay. Their&#13;
distinctiveness lies in the fact that a highly aggregative methodology is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
adopted. Aggregation is implied both in the use of national average&#13;
indices and in the extremely broad definition of consumption categories. A&#13;
balance is obviously required, and this is provided in Part 2 which&#13;
examines the disaggregated picture.&#13;
Instead of international comparisons, domestic data are&#13;
analyzed. Instead of gross categories like expenditure on food or total&#13;
caloric intake, the dependent variables now are the different categories of&#13;
food expenditure, like cereals, vegetables, meat, milk products, etc. The&#13;
primary focus is on the less-developed countries.&#13;
Five major independent variables are identified for this&#13;
purpose--household incomes, prices, household size and composition,&#13;
urbanization, and 'social factors'. The impact of each of these is&#13;
discussed in successive chapters. Not only is it sought to establish&#13;
relationships between these factors and specific food categories, but an&#13;
attempt is also made to isolate the consequent impact on nutritional status&#13;
and the issues that arise for policy makers.&#13;
The last chapter in Part 2 deals with social factors and points&#13;
out that there is an international dimension to food consumption patterns.&#13;
The diets in the low- and middle-income countries have increasingly&#13;
followed the trends established in the developed nations. A study of&#13;
consumption trends in the United States would therefore provide important&#13;
insights into where the rest of the world is headed. This is the subject&#13;
of Part 3.&#13;
Part 3 looks at two other related issues. The first is the&#13;
implications for nutritional status of affluent food consumption patterns.&#13;
The second is the implications for the world food system of the derived&#13;
demand for grain arising from increased meat consumption in the rapidly&#13;
growing middle-income countries.&#13;
In Part 4 we present our substantive conclusions. The focus is&#13;
entirely on domestic policy in the less developed countries. The&#13;
conclusion emphasizes the need for an approach to food policy that, on the&#13;
one hand, balances both the consumption and production aspects of the food&#13;
sector, and, on the other, integrates the various policy instruments&#13;
available in an internally consistent fashion to achieve that balance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
II. INTERNATIONAL FOOD CONSUMPTION COMPARISONS&#13;
This chapter is devoted to the study of food consumption as&#13;
measured in terms of expenditures on that category. Schematically, the&#13;
first part reviews the results of the three major studies of international&#13;
food consumption patterns that have been conducted in the last twenty-five&#13;
years. The reference is to the works of Houthakker (1957), Weisskoff&#13;
(1971), and Kravis, et al. (1982). The second section bears on the&#13;
legitimacy of international comparisons. In the process the issue of&#13;
'tastes' and preferences' is discussed, with emphasis on how such&#13;
influences can be empirically isolated.&#13;
At the outset it must be pointed out that the three studies are&#13;
not similar either in the data sets used, or the methodology adopted, or&#13;
even in the objectives that guided the research. However, several lessons&#13;
can be drawn from them and these have implications for the discussion in&#13;
the second section.&#13;
Houthakker's primary concern was to estimate expenditure&#13;
elasticities for 30 countries for the broad consumption categories of food,&#13;
housing, clothing, and miscellaneous items, using household budget survey&#13;
data- 1/ Secondarily he was interested in seeing if enough similarity&#13;
could 'Fe found in the elasticity values as to make them 'transferable' for&#13;
use in countries where own budget data were not available. The latter&#13;
would be accomplished by using the rough principle that if the individual&#13;
country elasticity values had a narrow range, and the standard errors were&#13;
small, then an average of all elasticities could be calculated. This could&#13;
then be treated as an estimate of the 'true' elasticity for people round&#13;
the world. Using the double-log functional form and specifying a household&#13;
size variable (to control for the strong correlation between income and&#13;
family size in household surveys), Houthakker came upon the following&#13;
results.&#13;
In all cases, food expenditure elasticities were less than unity,&#13;
strongly confirming Engel's Law. The range of values was 0.34 to 0.73.&#13;
Not much support was found for the hypothesis that elasticity for food&#13;
would decrease with an increase in the general level of income. This could&#13;
conceivably be because relative prices are not considered. Higher prices&#13;
of food (relative to nonfood) in a high-income country could lead to higher&#13;
food expenditure elasticities compared to a low-income country which had&#13;
much lower relative prices of food.&#13;
The elasticities for clothing with respect to expenditure were&#13;
found to be greater than 1.0 and generally less than 1.5. Clothing may&#13;
therefore be termed a moderate luxury. No particular pattern was apparent&#13;
1/ Strictly speaking, expenditure elasticities are higher than income&#13;
elasticities by roughly the share of savings in total income. We have,&#13;
however, used the two terms interchangeably throughout.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
across countries with different per capita income levels, and here again&#13;
prices may have been an important additional determinant. Housing&#13;
elasticities were found to be mostly less than 1.0. In sum, Houthakker&#13;
could conclude that:&#13;
What has been shown is mainly that the elasticities of the&#13;
our main items of expenditure with respect to total&#13;
expenditure are similar but not equal -... if no data on the&#13;
expenditure patterns of a country are available at all, one&#13;
would not be very far astray by putting the partial&#13;
elasticity with respect to total expenditure at 0.6 for&#13;
food, 1.2 for clothing, 0.8 for housing, and 1.6 for all&#13;
other items...&#13;
Weisskoff's objectives were to estimate long-run and short-run&#13;
expenditure elasticities as well as to investigate the structuralists'&#13;
contention that in the developing country context, price elasticities are&#13;
insignificant. Houthakker's sample had included both developed and&#13;
underdeveloped countries; Weisskoff restricted himself to LDCs.&#13;
According to Weisskoff, long-run elasticities are those derived&#13;
from cross sectional studies (whether domestic or cross-country), while&#13;
short-run elasticities are estimated from time series data. The underlying&#13;
reasoning is that a cross-sectional study works with data that has a wider&#13;
dispersion of income than a time series study which only considers averages&#13;
over periods of time. The former is therefore able to capture the changes&#13;
in consumption associated with substantial changes in income. It is also&#13;
true that cross-sectional differences in income have been around for a much&#13;
longer time than differences in average income which occur from year to&#13;
year because of economic growth. An elasticity measure which captures the&#13;
impact of substantial income differences that have existed for a&#13;
considerable period for time may be justifiably called a long-run&#13;
elasticity.&#13;
Back to Weisskoff. Since cross-country data were used for the&#13;
long-run model, all expenditure and price data were converted into 'rates&#13;
of change' form to overcome currency conversion problems. This also&#13;
necessitated using the double-log functional form.&#13;
In Table 1, 'within countries' models estimate short-run&#13;
elasticities, while the 'between countries' models estimate long-run&#13;
elasticities. Models 1 and 2 represent Weisskoff's estimates, while 3 and&#13;
4 represent Houthakker's estimates (made in a later study in 1965) for 13&#13;
OECD countries using essentially the same methodology.&#13;
It is interesting to observe that in LDCs short-run expenditure&#13;
elasticities are higher than in the long-run, while for developed countries&#13;
the reverse is true. An explanation for this is not easily forthcoming.&#13;
What is very clear, however, and in line with intuitive expectations, is&#13;
that the LDCs' expenditure elasticities are higher than those for developed&#13;
countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
Table 1: EXPENDITURE AND PRICE ELASTICITIES FOR POOLED COUNTIRES&#13;
Model                                           Food Expenditures&#13;
Expenditure         Price&#13;
1)  Within Countries (W)                    1.1095            -0.8743&#13;
2)  Between Countries (W)                   0.8258            -0.4612&#13;
3)  Within Countries (H)                     0.351            -0.161&#13;
4)  Between Countries (H)                    0.744            -0.234&#13;
Note: W = Weisskoff's Estimates&#13;
H = Houthakker's estimates&#13;
Source: Weisskoff (1971), p. 330&#13;
The price elasticities are also higher for the less-developed&#13;
countries compared with the developed countries, as would be expected at&#13;
low income levels. On the other hand, the short-run (within countries)&#13;
price elasticities would be expected to be smaller than long-run (between&#13;
countries) elasticities, but this expectation is belied for LDCs. Perhaps&#13;
this is due to the difficulty of making international price comparisons&#13;
with Weisskoff's data set. Differences in levels between countries are not&#13;
captured in his methodology, only differential rates of change, and this&#13;
limitation may account for the relatively smaller long-run elasticities in&#13;
his analysis. Houthakker's analysis would have significantly fewer&#13;
problems in this regard because the OECD countries are much more similar in&#13;
income levels.&#13;
Weisskoff next stratified his sample between LDCs where European&#13;
influence has been higher, and those that were 'typical' developing&#13;
nations. The former included such countries as South Africa, Greece, and&#13;
Israel. The latter included countries such as Nigeria, Peru, and Jamaica.&#13;
It was found, after regressing the data for each group separately, that the&#13;
'European-type' LDCs exhibited elasticity patterns similar to Houthakker's&#13;
results for Europe in Table 1, that is, the short-run elasticities were&#13;
found to be lower.&#13;
How can this be explained? Is this difference in elasticities&#13;
for the two sets of LDCs a difference attributable to 'lifestyles' or&#13;
tastes? Or is it a reflection of different income levels in the two sets?&#13;
This issue is taken up later.&#13;
It is well known that official exchange rates do not adequately&#13;
reflect the purchasing power of currencies in their domestic setting. More&#13;
specifically, the exchange rates of most LDCs are grossly 'undervalued'.&#13;
The reason why a laborer in India can survive on 70 cents a day is because&#13;
that can buy as much as 3 or 4 dollars worth of key consumption goods.&#13;
The upshot of this 'undervaluation' has been that until recently&#13;
any international comparison (which necessarily requires conversion of all&#13;
monetary aggregates to a single currency) had to be done using first&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6-&#13;
differences rather than the absolute figures. Otherwise econometric&#13;
analyses would yield spurious results. Fortunately, the publication of&#13;
successive reports of the "International Comparison Project" (the third&#13;
report is titled "World Product and Income: International Comparisons of&#13;
real Gross Product", by Kravis, Heston, and Summers, 1982) has changed all&#13;
that.&#13;
Data is now available for 151 final expenditure categories for 34&#13;
countries all expressed in one base currency with real income and price&#13;
data (for all consumption categories) also expressed in the same currency.&#13;
Kravis, et al., regressed category-wise expenditure data against&#13;
incomes and prices across the 34 countries. This demand analysis was&#13;
carried out at the summary-category and the detailed-category levels of&#13;
aggregation. The former considered 25 summary categories of consumption.&#13;
The latter covered 103 detailed consumption categories. The summary-&#13;
category specification had identified nine categories of food consumption.&#13;
Thus, bread and cereals constituted one category. Meat was another, and&#13;
fish still another. And so on.&#13;
Relative prices and income were found to explain the variations&#13;
in quantities consumed among the 34 countries very well. For 17 of the 25&#13;
categories the R2 (i.e., the coefficient of determination) exceeded 0.75,&#13;
and only in three cases was the R2 less than 0.50.&#13;
When the detailed-category specification (which identified 36&#13;
categories of food consumption) was used, the proportion of variance in&#13;
quantities explained tended to be smaller than for the summary categories.&#13;
Although over 70 percent of the R2S were 0.50 or higher, only about one-&#13;
third exceeded 0.75.&#13;
Having laid out the evidence, it is now possible to discuss the&#13;
question of international differences in 'tastes'. One way of tackling the&#13;
issue is to start with the assumption of no differences. The question then&#13;
is what kind of empirical evidence is required to validate or refute that&#13;
hypothesis. This in turn depends on the meaning given to the word&#13;
'similarity'.&#13;
Similarity of tastes can be defined in several ways. For&#13;
example, it could be interpreted to mean the same magnitude of expenditure&#13;
on any particular consumption category, or the same budget share, or the&#13;
same marginal propensity to consume, or the same income elasticity, or the&#13;
same price elasticity, or finally, the same functional relationship between&#13;
quantity consumed, income and prices.&#13;
No one would argue that similarity of tastes should be reflected&#13;
in similar quantities consumed or similar budget shares of the various&#13;
consumption categories regardless of other factors like incomes and&#13;
prices. Consequently, the focus here will be on whether similar income and&#13;
price elasticities should be expected from people with similar tastes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
Income elasticities are considered first. Mathematically, the&#13;
sum of expenditure elasticities for all consumption categories (including&#13;
savings), weighted by their budget shares, has to be equal to 1.0 . If the&#13;
expenditure elasticity of a category is greater than 1.0, its budget share&#13;
will increase and that of other categories will decline. To maintain the&#13;
identity, all elasticities have to change sympathetically. This logic can&#13;
be carried further to assert that over a wide range of income, any&#13;
elasticity that starts much higher than 1.0 has to decline. Thus similar&#13;
income elasticities should not be expected from countries with similar&#13;
tastes if their incomes differ. In fact the elasticities will differ.&#13;
Pure substitution elasticities associated with price changes can&#13;
also be expected to be different for different income levels. The reason&#13;
for this is as follows. At low levels of income, most of it is consumed&#13;
and very little saved. Thus, when the price of a commodity goes up, the&#13;
only way of approximating to previous living standards is to substitute&#13;
away from that commodity.&#13;
At higher levels of income, a significant portion is saved.&#13;
These savings act as a 'buffer' that helps absorb price shocks thereby&#13;
enabling the effort to maintain consumption standards. In such situations&#13;
maintaining consumption levels would be an end in itself. Of course, this&#13;
would tend to be more true for necessities than for luxuries. Thus the&#13;
tendency to substitute away from commodities whose prices are rising will&#13;
be less.&#13;
Given the above, it does seem that operational significance may be&#13;
given to the concept of 'same tastes' only by asserting that this requires&#13;
that the same functional relationship should exist between quantity&#13;
consumed, incomes and prices, across all countries; Kravis, et al, express&#13;
the idea in the following way.&#13;
If in two situations a market choice is made on the basis of&#13;
the same tastes about what to consume and in what&#13;
quantities, the actual choices will be determined by the&#13;
available consumption opportunities defined by prevailing&#13;
prices and the consuming unit's income. The degree to which&#13;
it is useful to speak of tastes being the same in different&#13;
countries turns on the extent to which prices and incomes&#13;
explain differences in consumption patterns in the&#13;
countries.&#13;
Thus the focus shifts from elasticity estimates themselves to the&#13;
amount of variation that is explained by the regression equation, that is,&#13;
to the coefficient of determination, R2. If the R2 value is 'high', then&#13;
it is possible to be confident about an international similarity of tastes&#13;
(always assuming that the the estimates are significant). Harking back to&#13;
Kravis' own calculations, it may be recalled that for his 'summary-&#13;
category' specification, the R2 exceeded 0.75 for 17 out of 25 categories.&#13;
This result is not insignificant.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
The natural next question is whether these high values of R2&#13;
hold up when consumption categories are defined at a more disaggregated&#13;
level. In Kravis' 'detailed-category' specification; 103 consumption&#13;
categories were identified. It was then found that only about one-third of&#13;
the R2s exceeded 0.75. This result is not surprising. In fact it squares&#13;
with casual empiricism. For example, it is common observation that while&#13;
there may not be many people who prefer say, French fries of a particular&#13;
brand, there will be more who like French fries in general, still more who&#13;
relish potato products, and nearly everyone consumes a starchy staple of&#13;
some sort.&#13;
Thus, the value of R2, and hence the similarity of taste patterns&#13;
is a function of the degree of aggregation at which consumption categories&#13;
are defined. The more specifically a product is defined, the more&#13;
restricted the preferences for it will be, and this will be reflected in&#13;
lower values of R2.&#13;
In a later chapter the influence of 'social class' as a&#13;
determinant of consumption patterns will be discussed. It will be shown&#13;
then how some factors that seem to be non-economic at first glance are&#13;
really rooted in economics, and that an analysis in sociological terms is,&#13;
in many instances, only the slip side of a study in economic terms. This&#13;
of course underscores our earlier point that conceptual clarity in defining&#13;
and giving operational content to the variables used is imperative.&#13;
For now it is sufficient to state that while non-economic factors&#13;
are important, sufficient grounds exist to pursue an analysis in largely&#13;
economic terms. While diversity of behavior exists, it is not so random as&#13;
to overwhelm the analyst. Regularities exist and can be discovered. This&#13;
makes knowledge obtained in one setting transferable, with appropriate&#13;
modifications, to other settings. The part is a window to the whole.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9-&#13;
III. AN INTERNATIONAL COMPARISON OF NUTRITIONAL PATTERNS&#13;
The relationship between expenditures on food and income per&#13;
capita gives only broad hints about the impact on nutritional status.&#13;
Expenditure elasticities include the effects of changes in the quantity of&#13;
food consumed as well as changes in its price. An increase in either one&#13;
of these does not necessarily imply an improving nutritional status with&#13;
increasing incomes.&#13;
The 'quantity' of food consumed (whether measured by weight or by&#13;
volume) may increase, but if there is a simultaneous shift between food&#13;
categories from low bulk-high nutrition foods to high bulk-low nutrition&#13;
foods, then total caloric intake may not increase.   Similarly, increases in&#13;
the average price paid for food commodities (with higher incomes) may or&#13;
may not reflect better nutritive quality. Higher prices may be paid for&#13;
greater values added through processing and other services built into the&#13;
food. Such processing may actually detract from the nutritional quality.&#13;
It is clear, therefore, that in looking at the relationship&#13;
between nutritional status and incomes, a more direct measure than food&#13;
expenditures is required. The direct measures of greatest interest from a&#13;
nutritional standpoint are caloric intake and protein intake. Adequate&#13;
protein-calorie intake is required for growth, activity, and general&#13;
health.&#13;
A relationship between incomes and nutritional indicators is&#13;
obvious from Table 2, which is based on food balance sheet data for 1977.&#13;
But more than just income levels separate the developed and developing&#13;
countries, and a more complete specification of the relationship is&#13;
necessary. Apart from providing greater insight, an improved empirical&#13;
understanding of nutrient-income elasticities is needed because they are&#13;
central to quantifying the magnitude of the calorie deficit in the&#13;
developing countries.&#13;
Table 2: PER CAPITA DAILY FOOD SUPPLIES, 1977&#13;
Animal Protein-&#13;
Total     Proteins   Starchy Staple  Total Protein&#13;
Calories     (grams)       Ratio           Ratio&#13;
World                    2571        69           56%              35%&#13;
All Developed            3395        99           35               56&#13;
Countries&#13;
All Developing           2260        57           68               21&#13;
Countries&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-10-&#13;
Recent attempts to estimate these elasticities include Thomson's&#13;
(1974), which was based on a time series of food balance sheet data for 35&#13;
countries, and Reutlinger and Selowsky (1976) and Knudsen and Scandizzo&#13;
(1982), who used within country household budget data. This paper uses an&#13;
approach similar to the one used by Thomson, and it would be appropriate at&#13;
this stage to outline the differences and improvements that distinguish the&#13;
present approach.&#13;
Thomson's basic model was:&#13;
Cjt = aEb    where&#13;
C = caloric intake, and&#13;
E = total per capita consumption expenditure while 'j'&#13;
refers to country and 't' to time period.&#13;
First differences (D) were taken over time series for individual&#13;
countries after converting to double-log form, giving:&#13;
D(log Cjt) = b'D(log Ejt)&#13;
The mean value for each country over the total time period was&#13;
calculated, and these values then served as the basis of regression&#13;
analysis.&#13;
D(log Cj) = b-D(log Ej)&#13;
There were several problems with this approach. The relative&#13;
price of food items is likely to be an important determinant of nutrient&#13;
intake, but lack of data prevented their inclusion in Thomson's analysis.&#13;
Another problem was the comparability of data on income per capita which&#13;
were denominated in national currencies. Converting income to dollars at&#13;
the official exchange rates is a poor procedure since such exchange rates&#13;
do not adequately reflect the internal purchasing power of these&#13;
currencies. Thomson used the rates of change of income rather than income&#13;
itself, which required the use of the double-log functional form for&#13;
regression. Even so, only relative rates of change could be examined, not&#13;
absolute differences in starting levels of income.&#13;
The "International Comparison Project" referred to earlier has&#13;
made a major contribution to overcoming the above two problems. The task&#13;
of calculating the real GDP of countries on a comparable basis--that is,&#13;
correcting for systematic differences in domestic prices between&#13;
countries--requires the calculation of purchasing power parities for&#13;
commodities at a fine level of disaggregation.     The purchasing power&#13;
parity is the number of domestic currency units required to buy goods&#13;
equivalent to those that can be bought with one unit of the currency of the&#13;
base country (in this case, the United States). It is the price in&#13;
national currency of an amount of a commodity that can be bought for a&#13;
dollar in the United States.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-11-&#13;
With exchange rates based on purchasing power parity, the two&#13;
problems faced by Thomson can be overcome becausa the prices of different&#13;
commodities across nations are available, while the real quantities of&#13;
goods and services produced by each country are valued at 'international&#13;
prices' to produce comparable GDP figures for each country. Note, however,&#13;
that systematic differences in food prices, for example, will be reflected&#13;
in the purchasing power exchange tastes and in 'real' GDP purchasing power&#13;
rather than by the raw prices themselves. Consequently, the food price&#13;
variable used in this analysis will tend to reflect a pure substitution&#13;
effect only, rather than the combined income and substitution effect&#13;
normally estimated in demand analysis.&#13;
The treatment of caloric requirements also needs explanation.&#13;
Even for a given income and price environment, caloric intake should be&#13;
related to caloric requirements. Peoples of colder climates and of larger&#13;
body size need more calories for a given level of activity. Similarly, if&#13;
the composition of the population is biased toward adults and males, the&#13;
average population requirement will be higher. To take this into account,&#13;
the analysis here uses the population average calorie requirements for&#13;
individual countries published by the FAO in its Fourth World Food Survey&#13;
(1977). These requirements are introduced directly into the regression&#13;
analysis to serve as a 'shifter' of the overall estimated structural&#13;
regression or, alternatively, are used to convert calorie intake into a&#13;
'proportion of requirements' variable.&#13;
Apart from estimating calorie-income and protein-income&#13;
elasticities it is also useful to estimate income elasticities for the&#13;
starchy staple ratio and the animal protein-total protein (AP-TPR). These&#13;
two ratios may be considered measures of the quality of the diet. Since&#13;
the quality of diet improves with incomes, the income elasticity of the&#13;
starchy staple ratio should be negative and that for AP-TPR should be&#13;
positive. These elasticities are also estimated here.&#13;
The Model&#13;
With comparable data available for direct comparison of different&#13;
countries' levels as well as rates of growth, the choice of functional&#13;
forms was relatively open. Two were tested--the double-log and the&#13;
semi-log. The former offers the advantage that the regression coefficients&#13;
are themselves the elasticities, whereas the latter provides the advantage&#13;
that it gives an income elasticity that declines as incomes rise, a likely&#13;
outcome in view of earlier empirical work. In fact, the semi-log form&#13;
added nothing to the explanatory power after slope and intercept modifiers&#13;
were introduced into the double-log specification, and no semi-log results&#13;
are presented here.&#13;
Other notable points about the model are:&#13;
(i) several combinations of the independent variables were&#13;
tested;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-12-&#13;
(ii)  relative food prices were used only in the caloric intake&#13;
specifications; for others the general food price variable&#13;
was not the appropriate specification for inclusion.&#13;
(iii)  differences in the elasticities between developed (DC) and&#13;
less developed countries (LDC) were examined with two&#13;
techniques. One used variables to modify slopes and/or&#13;
intercepts where appropriate. The other was simply to split&#13;
the sample into data for DCs and LDCs, and do the regression&#13;
analysis separately. The dummy variable method was used by&#13;
creating a variable with value equal to one if the per&#13;
capita incomes of the particular observation was less than&#13;
the mean for the entire sample, a value of 28.5 percent of&#13;
the United States per capita income. The DC-LDC approach&#13;
simply segregated the sample countries into 17 DCs and 17&#13;
LDCs on the basis of the World Bank's classification. It is&#13;
important to realize that the two divisions will produce&#13;
similar but not identical samples. The zero-one low income&#13;
dummy variable was sometires used by itself to serve as an&#13;
intercept shifter and sometimes was multiplied by the log of&#13;
income or price to provide an elasticity shifter.&#13;
(iv)  The food price variable measures movement in food prices&#13;
relative to nonfood prices after correcting differences in&#13;
observed prices across countries for the real purchasing&#13;
power of foreign exchange. Consequently, most of the income&#13;
effect of different food prices has been captured directly&#13;
in the income coefficient, and the price coefficient will&#13;
reflect primarily 'pure' substitution elasticities. The&#13;
prices of 'caloric commodities' (i.e., food) relative to&#13;
'noncaloric commodities' (i.e., nonfood), are measured from&#13;
a base where this price ratio was set at 1.00 for the United&#13;
States for 1975. The ratio varies over time if the prices&#13;
of food grow faster or slower than nonfood within a&#13;
country. And it varies across countries depending on how&#13;
food and nonfood prices behave in those countries. Any&#13;
country and year could have been chosen as a base without&#13;
affecting the results.&#13;
An example illustrates the calculations. Suppose a&#13;
country's purchasing power parity for food for 1975 is 3&#13;
units of national currency and for nonfood it is 4. Then&#13;
the relative price of food to nonfood in this country is&#13;
0.75 compared to 1.00 for the United States. If the price&#13;
of food now goes up 10 percent in 1976, while the price of&#13;
nonfood goes up only 5 percent, then the relative price in&#13;
1976 would be 0.79 for the country in question. The United&#13;
States could also have differential price movements, and so&#13;
the price ratios are linked only for the year 1975, the base&#13;
year for Kravis' comparative work.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-13-&#13;
At this stage a compromise had to be made with data availa-&#13;
bility. While food price indices are published by most countries, nonfood&#13;
price indices are rare. The ratios actually used related to food prices&#13;
and general prices, that is, all nonfood and food categories. This has&#13;
important implications for the price ratios, especially for those of the&#13;
developing countries since it has led to significant understatement of the&#13;
true change in relative prices. The understatement is directly&#13;
proportional to the magnitude of food expenditure in the total consumption&#13;
expenditure.   This is higher than 50 percent for many LDCs.    The corollary&#13;
is that it is likely that the elasticities estimated here will understate&#13;
their true values.&#13;
One last note on the price data is important. It is well&#13;
recognized that food prices in poor countries, and especially basic food&#13;
prices (e.g., for the starchy staples), are significantly lower than in&#13;
rich countries when prices are converted as market exchange rates. Both&#13;
because of exchange rate biases and official government policies,&#13;
developing countries tend to have their staple grain prices below&#13;
international market levels, and rich countries tend in the opposite&#13;
direction. These tendencies are actually reversed by the Kravis purchasing&#13;
power parity adjustment; the relative food nonfood price index used here&#13;
shows a noticeable downward trend as per capita income levels rise. 2/&#13;
That is, nonfood items ('luxuries') are relatively cheap in poor countries&#13;
and become more dear in the process of development. This is probably a&#13;
reflection of the limited trading opportunities available to LDC for their&#13;
nonfood products.&#13;
The sources of data as well as the list of countries included in&#13;
the sample are given in an appendix to this chapter.&#13;
The Results&#13;
The results, estimated by ordinary least squares regression are&#13;
presented in Tables 3 and 4. The first nine equations have log of caloric&#13;
intake as the dependent variable. For the total sample per capita income&#13;
has a very high explanatory power with the income elasticity equal to 0.20&#13;
when income is entered alone in Equation Cl, and it remains as high as 0.15&#13;
in Equation C5 when variables for calorie requirements and for low-income&#13;
price responsiveness are included.&#13;
When the price variable is added (Equation C2), the income&#13;
elasticity drops only slightly, while the price elasticity is -0.1 and&#13;
significant only at the 10% level. It has been pointed out that prices and&#13;
income are significantly (and negatively ) correlated, and so the income&#13;
variable has already captured some for the price effect. With just a price&#13;
2/ For the 34 countries in the sample analyzed here, a double log&#13;
regression with the relative food to nonfood price index as the&#13;
dependent variable and per capita GDP as the independent variable&#13;
showed the following negative relationship:&#13;
Log Relative Food Price = 0.38 - 0.08 Log Per Capita GDP         R2 = 0.21&#13;
(5.64)                   N  = 117&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
0 &#13;
It     C14 coN  £-4-&#13;
1-4             0!          9  C~~CI v-&#13;
cn          o              n   o- &#13;
3                              -4 00  0 -     _&#13;
H        V4    ~            coL*1-0&#13;
Z           0 wI&#13;
On                             0 _  o O x&#13;
1-4 W  i           oo U) -&#13;
V)      ~o                   . O  . C&#13;
OO&#13;
i -   &gt;     o jo&#13;
cn  0     &#13;
;T4~~~~~~~=&#13;
$4 ,- ,                      CD&#13;
0      C1   .   4--IC  .  n cC   ~&#13;
Z14     8   . 0  .          . &#13;
Q g 0  o aS                         E~cj~  9~&#13;
8~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C    C: 4  C, 3~  C| ; ,&#13;
-   1~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~~~~~~~  ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~   tf~~~~~~~~~~~~r-. ~~~~~~~~~~~ r-I ~ a&#13;
o-    co-   c  o                     c-.&#13;
..                                          O~~~~~~~~~~H&#13;
n~~~~~~~~~~~~~L       rP0 0-rc&#13;
C)~~~&#13;
H~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 4.&#13;
'-4 Q                                     Q&#13;
a 4 _ q  en &lt;-T Lr I'D r-  0   0'&#13;
0      03 tD tD 0D tD tD tD 0Dt &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-15-&#13;
coefficient alone in the equation, the estimated elasticity rises in&#13;
absolute value from -0.10 to -0.66. Due to the manner in which the price&#13;
ratio is defined, it is entirely possible that higher price coefficients&#13;
than those reported in Table 3 would be observed if nonfood rather than&#13;
general price indices were to be used. Again, it must also be recalled&#13;
that these price coefficients include little of the income effect that&#13;
makes up a normal response to changes in food prices.&#13;
A priori the elasticity figures for LDCs are expected to be&#13;
higher than those for DCs. The income elasticity should be higher because&#13;
caloric intake has limits, and the price elasticity (the pure substitution&#13;
effect) should be higher for reasons outlined in Chapter I. Further, if&#13;
the "Timmer effect" holds, then the pure substitution elasticity would&#13;
decline in absolute size as incomes increase at about half the rate of&#13;
decline in income elasticities. (Timmer, 1982).&#13;
These hypotheses are tested in Equations C6 and C8, which report&#13;
separate equations for sub-samples of the developed and less-developed&#13;
nations. The income and price elasticities for developed countries are&#13;
much lower than those for LDCs and were not significant at the 5% level.&#13;
Interestingly enough, the "Timmer effect" was confirmed. The decline in&#13;
income elasticity from 0.15 for low-income countries to 0.06 for the high-&#13;
income countries represents a 0.9 percent decline. One would therefore&#13;
expect the decline in substitution elasticity to be of the order of 0.045&#13;
percent. The actual decline is 0.05 percent.&#13;
Confirmation of the significance of the price effect is seen in&#13;
Equation C3 where it takes the robust value of -0.20 and is very highly&#13;
significant. In this equation a dummy variable was used to set prices at&#13;
zero for countries with greater than average GDP per capita. Thus the&#13;
estimated coefficient represents the price elasticity for countries with&#13;
less than average GDP per capita, while the (implicit) price elasticity for&#13;
upper-income countries is zero.&#13;
The inclusion of the calorie requirement variable considerably&#13;
alters the picture (Equations C4 and C5). Looking at Equation C4, it is&#13;
obvious that the income variable was picking up some of the effect of&#13;
variation in calorie requirements. Historicallv, higher incomes and higher&#13;
caloric requirements have been found to go together (due to colder climates&#13;
and larger body size in the DCs). Allowing for this collinearity causes&#13;
the estimated income-calorie elasticity to drop by one-sixth, from 0.18 to&#13;
0.15.   Calorie requirements are also correlated with food prices, even&#13;
after allowance is made for the food price-income correlation. In Equation&#13;
C5, the low-income sample price elasticity drops to -0.12, with lowered&#13;
significance.&#13;
The 'calorie requirement elasticity' estimates have little&#13;
operational meaning other than the obvious: a 1 percent increase in&#13;
'requirements' does not automatically lead to a 1 percent increase in&#13;
caloric intake. Per capita incomes and food prices obviously play a&#13;
critical role in determining whether requirements can actually be&#13;
satisfied. Equation C10 reports a regression with calorie intake as a&#13;
proportion of requirements as the dependent variable. The income&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-16-&#13;
elasticity of 'satisfying requirements" is 0.14, more or less in line with&#13;
calorie elasticities estimated directly. However, this approach&#13;
unnecessarily constrains the value of the calorie requirements elasticity&#13;
to be exactly one, which empirically it is not.&#13;
Table 4 presents results for various measures of dietary quality.&#13;
the regressions with the starchy staple ratio as the dependent variable are&#13;
shown in Equations Ql to Q6. Equation Ql shows the starchy staple ratio&#13;
regressed against income. The elasticity of -0.39 is highly significant&#13;
and has substantial predictive power, as the simple equation has an R2 of&#13;
0.74. Even the introduction of low-income slope and constant shifters,&#13;
along with a price term, raises the R2 only to 0.80. Per capita incomes are&#13;
clearly the dominant factor explaining this measure of dietary quality. To&#13;
the extent a difference is likely to exist in income elasticities for the&#13;
starchy staple ratio, the DC elasticity should be larger in absolute&#13;
terms. This would happen partly because the peoples of poor countries would&#13;
exhibit a certain stickiness in behavior, having been accustomed to a&#13;
starchy diet for so long (for example, many wealthy individuals in Asia do&#13;
not feel they have 'eaten a full meal' unless they also eat rice).     In&#13;
addition, significant scope exists for upgrading the diets of low-income&#13;
people within the context of starchy staples. Thus wheat can substitute&#13;
for sorghum, or maize for cassava, and rice for maize. Only when diets&#13;
begin to diversify dramatically in significant quantities to meat, sugar,&#13;
fish, milk, and other 'high quality' (and expensive) calories does the&#13;
starchy staple ratio decline rapidly.&#13;
This hypothesis is borne out in Equations Q5 and Q6. Separate&#13;
equations for DCs and LDCs show that the starchy staple ratio elasticity is&#13;
-0.64 in DCs and only -0.23 for LDCs. Both coefficients are highly&#13;
significant. A different formulation in Equation Q3 using dummy variables&#13;
for low incomes found virtually identical results.&#13;
Equation Q4 introduces the relative food price variable used in&#13;
the calorie regressions into the starchy staple ratio analysis with low&#13;
income coefficients separate from the overall coefficients. The price&#13;
coefficient reveals a fairly high price elasticity of 0.25, and it is&#13;
significant at around 7 percent. The positive sign of the elasticity&#13;
indicates that the starchy staple ratio increases when relative food prices&#13;
increase.   Since the earlier calorie analysis showed caloric intake&#13;
responsive to this same food price variable, the explanation for its impact&#13;
on the starchy staple ratio is probably through caloric intake (the&#13;
denominator of the ratio) rather than by changing starchy staple intake for&#13;
a given level of calories. In other words, an increase in relative food&#13;
prices leads to a substitution from nonstarchy staple foods to nonfood&#13;
categories. Thus the positive sign is logical and expected. What would be&#13;
interesting, of course, would be to test the impact of starchy staple&#13;
prices relative to other calorie prices.    No comparable data are available&#13;
to do this, unfortunately.&#13;
Equations Q7 to Q9 report the relationship between protein intake&#13;
and incomes. The protein-income elasticity is 0.25 for all countries, 0.15&#13;
for LDCs and 0.04 for DCs. This is to be expected. Once a diet has&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
0-Ln 4L&#13;
.-4  IALf W&#13;
U '-  O4  O  ?C    ~ 0 c~  0   c&#13;
-t~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~    -&#13;
0  0;  0  0 0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-18-&#13;
reached saturation levels as far as calorie levels are concerned, very&#13;
little addition to the total protein intake will take place. Why would&#13;
this happen?&#13;
It seems that a diet that is 'balanced' from the perspective of&#13;
the human palate can only take a certain percentage of nourishment as&#13;
proteins. Table 5 presents the evidence. As can be seen, protein intake&#13;
as a proportion of total calories is very close to being the same in all&#13;
the countries, rich or poor. Thus, increments in protein intake closely&#13;
follow increments in calories. This would provide an additional&#13;
justification for the thesis that protein deficiencies can best be&#13;
alleviated by increasing overall caloric consumption.&#13;
Back to Table 4. The three protein equations show particularly&#13;
clearly a characteristic of this particular sample and a behavioral&#13;
relationship of some significance. Equation Q7 shows a protein-income&#13;
Table 5: RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN INCOME AND PERCENT OF PROTEINS IN CALORIC&#13;
INTAKE&#13;
Country                            GDP/capita in                 Calories&#13;
International            from proteins as %&#13;
dollars, 1973            of total calories&#13;
Kenya                                     379                    12.86&#13;
India                                     394                    11.13&#13;
Philippines                               755                    10.74&#13;
South Korea                               904                    11.79&#13;
Iran                                     1809                    11.97&#13;
Hungary                                  2793                    11.44&#13;
Italy                                    2913                    12.64&#13;
United Kingdom                           3750                    12.20&#13;
Netherlands                              4234                    11.65&#13;
Belgium                                  4663                    12.22&#13;
West Germany                             4761                    11.36&#13;
United States of America                 6192                    13.43&#13;
Sources:  Kravis, Heston and Summers, International Comparisons of Real&#13;
Product and Purchasing Power&#13;
FAO, Food Balance Sheets, 1975-1977.&#13;
elasticity of 0.25 when the total sample is considered. When the sample is&#13;
split, the DC elasticity is 0.04, and the LDC elasticity is 0.15. Neither&#13;
elasticity from the split sample is as high as from the combined sample.&#13;
Normally, the elasticity for the total sample should be a weighted average&#13;
of the two sub-samples. That is not happening here for two reasons.&#13;
First, the DC sample represents a different population than the LDC sample&#13;
due to different calorie requirements as well as to a host of other&#13;
'modernt traits that do not come immediately with higher income. Second,&#13;
patterns of behavior take considerable time to adjust to changed income&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-19-&#13;
levels. The elasticities for each sample separately can be thought of as&#13;
representing short-run adjustments to income change, while the elasticity&#13;
for the combined sample represents a long-run adjustment.&#13;
Equations QIO to Q12 examine the relationship between animal&#13;
protein and incomes. The animal protein-income elasticity is 0.77 for all&#13;
countries, 0.65 for LDCs and 0.47 for DCs. The animal protein-protein&#13;
ratio-income elasticity can be read off by subtracting the protein&#13;
elasticity from the animal protein elasticity. The elasticity figures in&#13;
this case are 0.52 for all countries, 0.43 for DCs and 0.50 for LDCs. The&#13;
animal protein-protein ratio-income elasticity for DCs is lower than for&#13;
LDCs, a pattern laterally inverse to that for the starchy staple ratio.&#13;
The conclusions that seem to be emerging from the above analysis&#13;
are rather disturbing. On the one hand, calorie-income elasticities even&#13;
for LDCs are very low. On the other, protein intake is directly related to&#13;
caloric intake. Further, the low calorie-income elasticity of around 0.15&#13;
is to be contrasted with the income elasticity of food expenditure of over&#13;
0.6. This suggests that a 10 percent increase in income will increase food&#13;
expenditures by 6 percent but caloric intake by only 1.5 percent. If the&#13;
average calorie deficit is around 15 percent, a doubling of per capita&#13;
income will be required before the deficit can be closed. Given the low&#13;
historical rates of growth in many LDCs, this possibility can be safely&#13;
ruled out for the rest of this century.&#13;
At the same time, one should be cautious about such&#13;
prognostigations. This is because estimates of the total calorie deficit,&#13;
the number malnourished and the effort required to reduce the deficit are&#13;
highly sensitive to estimates of calorie-income elasticities. In the above&#13;
scenario, for example, if this elasticity was 0.30 instead of 0.15, then&#13;
'only' a 50 percent increase in per capita income would be required--a much&#13;
more manageable problem.&#13;
In fact, in a recent paper, Knudsen and Scandizzo (1982) estimate&#13;
the calorie income elasticity to cluster around 0.6 for poor consumers in&#13;
the 6 low income countries they studied. This of course makes the problem&#13;
of calorie deficits even' more manageable. Can both estimates be 'correct'?&#13;
A reconciliation of these conflicting points of view is attempted&#13;
in Figure 1 which shows the income expansion path for the 'consumption' of&#13;
two attributes of food--quality and quantity. The income expansion path PP&#13;
is the locus of all points where the budget lines are in equilibrium with&#13;
the individual's indifference map. As income increases, the consumer on&#13;
the basis of his preferences, selects bundles of quality and quantity as&#13;
outlined by PP.&#13;
It is quite likely that this study, which has national averages&#13;
as its unit of measurement, is estimating elasticities in the region to the&#13;
right of point B. Knudsen and Scandizzo had used intra-country household&#13;
expenditure surveys as their data set and their estimates probably refer to&#13;
the region around point A. This would be true because the average income in&#13;
any country would obviously be higher than the incomes of its lowest&#13;
strata.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-20-&#13;
Figure 1: The Income Expansion Path for Calorc Intake&#13;
Quality&#13;
(cost/caloric)&#13;
p&#13;
0       A                   B&#13;
Quantity&#13;
(no. of calories)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-21-&#13;
Thus the two estimates are potentially consistent and their&#13;
usefulness depends on the income levels of the population under considera-&#13;
tion.&#13;
From the viewpoint of nutritional policy the important point is&#13;
that several points of inflexion exist on the expansion curve PP. A&#13;
population at point B might be subsisting on an inadequate diet in the&#13;
sense that they would consume more calories if their budget allowed them.&#13;
However an intervention policy that seeks to transfer income to them will&#13;
have only a marginal impact on their caloric intake. At the same time the&#13;
quality of their diet will be substantially improved. Most price subsidy&#13;
programs that are targeted at the urban middle class and even the organized&#13;
labor class probably fall in this category.&#13;
The greater payoff from nutrition interventions is to be found in&#13;
the region of point A. It is here that significant increases in caloric&#13;
intake can be achieved. Also, given the low intake level, additional&#13;
calories probably have a greater impact on the physical and mental well-&#13;
being of the individual.&#13;
Appendix to Chapter II. The Sources of Data and Country List&#13;
The Sources of Data&#13;
The sources of data are:&#13;
i) World Product and Income (1982) for real gross domestic&#13;
income per capita for 34 countries for the years 1965,&#13;
1970,1975, and 1977 as well as for purchasing power parities&#13;
for 1975.&#13;
ii) FAO, Food Balance Sheets, 1972-1974 and 1975-1977 for data on&#13;
nutrient availability.&#13;
iii) FAO, Fourth World Food Survey, 1977, for data on calorie&#13;
requirements.&#13;
iv) U.N., Yearbook of National Accounts Statistics, Volume II,&#13;
1979, for real GDP per capita growth rates.&#13;
v) ILO, Yearbook of Labor Statistics, 1979, for general and food&#13;
price indices.&#13;
vi) The 34 countries in the sample, with the number of observa-&#13;
tions for each, are as follows:&#13;
Developed Countries&#13;
Austria (3)        Belgium (4)            Denmark (4)           France (4)&#13;
Hungary (2)        Ireland (4)            Italy (4)             Japan (4)&#13;
Luxembourg (4)     Netherlands (4)        Poland (1)            Romania (1)&#13;
Spain (4)          United Kingdom (4)     United States (4)     Yugoslavia (1)&#13;
Germany (4)&#13;
17 countries; 56 cases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-22-&#13;
Less-Developed Countries&#13;
Brazil (3)         Colombia (4)           India (3)            Iran (4)&#13;
Jamaica (3)        Kenya (4)              Korea (4)            Malawi (3)&#13;
Malaysia (4)       Mexico (4)             Pakistan (4)         Philippines (3)&#13;
Sri Lanka (4)      Syria (3)              Thailand (4)         Uruguay (4)&#13;
Zambia (3)&#13;
17 countries; 61 cases&#13;
Total Sample:   34 countries: 117 cases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-23-&#13;
Part 2&#13;
IV.   AN EXAMINATION OF HlOUSEHOLD INCOME AND EXPENDITURE DATA&#13;
Household budget surveys show food consumption for different&#13;
income groups at particular points in time.    Cross section analyses based&#13;
on such surveys have the advantage of showing the influence of incomes on&#13;
food consumption without major disturbing effects from changes in prices.&#13;
However, even in cross-section surveys, different consumers face different&#13;
prices for the same commodity depending on where they live and what their&#13;
quality preferences are.&#13;
With appropriate concern for such differential price effects,&#13;
household surveys give a clear sense of the eventual directions that&#13;
consumption patterns are likely to take as incomes grow because the&#13;
population under study is narrowly defined both in terms of space (within a&#13;
country or a region) and time (inter-generational taste consistency not&#13;
required). Thus the population may be expected to behave consistently&#13;
within its context. Thus, if it is sought to determine, for example, the&#13;
rate at which meat consumption is likely to increase in India, household&#13;
survey data would be a good point to start.&#13;
Before the evidence is presented, it would be appropriate to&#13;
discuss what kind of patterns should be expected.&#13;
It would seem axiomatic to assert that more 'preferred foods'&#13;
would be consumed as incomes rise since, by definition, preferred foods&#13;
cost more. 3/ After all, if a preferred food were cheap enough for&#13;
satiety to be reached at the lowest income levels, it would not remain&#13;
preferred. Thus it should be expected that the budget share of preferred&#13;
(i.e., costlier) foods would rise with increasing incomes.&#13;
This also means that a 'heirarchy' of food categories can be&#13;
drawn up on the basis of costs per calorie. As incomes increase, people&#13;
would move down the heirarchy, their food budget increasingly composed of&#13;
more expensive calories. Bennett (1954) expresses the idea this way:&#13;
There are strong reasons to believe that there has for long&#13;
existed a scale or heirarchy in the prices of different&#13;
foods paid by consumers such that the prices of first-&#13;
processed grain products (fLour and meals of various sorts)&#13;
and of starchy roots and tubers (such as white and sweet&#13;
potatoes, yams, manioc, taro and plantains) tend to be the&#13;
lowest per 1000 calories of all food prices. If this is so,&#13;
then the poorest people of the world may be expected to lean&#13;
much more heavily on these foods to satisfy hunger or energy&#13;
requirements than would the wealthier; economic pressure&#13;
would create such an outcome. One would expect, on compar-&#13;
ing the food intake of national populations, or of any large&#13;
3/ Cost here is being measured in terms of cost per calorie.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-24-&#13;
population groups, to find the poorest deriving a relatively&#13;
large fraction of their caloric intake from these starchy&#13;
staples.&#13;
Bennett further asserts that the calorie-price heirarchy would&#13;
take the following general form internationally, since relative costs of&#13;
production would not differ much from country to country.&#13;
i) milled grain products and starchy roots;&#13;
ii)  vegetable fats and oils;&#13;
iii)  dried pulses (beans, peas, lentils);&#13;
iv)  sugar;&#13;
v)  milk and its products; possibly fish;&#13;
vi)  pork;&#13;
vii)  beef, mutton, lamb, buffalo meat, poultry and eggs; and&#13;
viii)  vegetables and fruits.&#13;
On this basis, if household expenditure data for different&#13;
countries were examined, with increasing income the following patterns&#13;
would emerge:&#13;
i)  the share (in the food budget) of starchy staples would&#13;
decline;&#13;
ii)  the share of fats and oils would increase initially, then&#13;
decline;&#13;
iii)  the share of dried pulses would increase until middle-income&#13;
levels and then decline;&#13;
iv)  the shares of sugar, milk and milk products would increase;&#13;
v)  the shares of meats of all kinds, poultry, eggs and fish&#13;
would increase; and&#13;
vi)  the shares of vegetables and fruits would increase, very&#13;
slowly at first and rapidly later.&#13;
To test this out, a 'representative' sample of seven countries&#13;
was selected--Mexico and Brazil in Latin America; Ghana and Kenya in&#13;
Africa; and Japan, South Korea, and India in Asia (Tables 6-9).&#13;
As can be seen, unfortunately, the food categories are not&#13;
exactly the ones that were discussed earlier. "Bread and cereals" replace&#13;
starchy staples with roots and tubers being subsumed under "fruit and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-25-&#13;
vegetables". Pulses presumably have been included with "bread and&#13;
cereals". The category "meals outside the home" has not been split up into&#13;
the food groups. Instead it is presented as a category of food itself. On&#13;
the positive side, for some countries data are available separately for&#13;
rural and urban households.&#13;
This means that some of the expectations need to be modified.&#13;
Specifically,&#13;
i) the category "bread and cereals" would decline slowly at&#13;
first rather than sharply. This is because some substitution&#13;
will take place between inferior and high quality cereals on&#13;
the one hand, between cereals and pulses on the other.&#13;
ii) the category "fruits and vegetables" would have a sizable&#13;
share at low-income levels also (because of the inclusion of&#13;
roots and tubers) and hence increases in consumption of&#13;
fruits and vegetables proper would not show up so&#13;
dramatically.&#13;
iii) it would be expected that the category "meals outside the&#13;
home" would show increases in share with higher incomes.&#13;
Because of their convenience and higher cost they have the&#13;
character of a preferred good or even a luxury.&#13;
iv) in comparing urban and rural patterns, there might be&#13;
systematic differences (keeping incomes constant) because of&#13;
factors such as different prices and different age, sex, and&#13;
size structures of the households.&#13;
Table 6 shows the budget data for Mexico and Brazil. In Mexico&#13;
the shares of "bread and cereals" and "meat and fish" follow expected&#13;
patterns. So do shares for every other category except sugar which&#13;
declined in both rural and urban areas. That rural and urban shares follow&#13;
the same pattern is a striking aspect of these data although there is a&#13;
difference of a few percentage points.&#13;
An important feature of the Brazilian data is the very high share&#13;
of meat in the food budget--32 percent. This should be compared with&#13;
meat's budget share in Mexico where it is 9 percent less even while the&#13;
latter's per capita GDP is 25 percent higher. Fats and oils show an&#13;
increase, which is contrary to expectations unless it is due to the nature&#13;
of Brazilian cooking. Other anomalous trends are the inconsistency of the&#13;
share of "milk, etc." and the decline in the shares of sugar, fruits and&#13;
vegetables. It seems that other foods are being "sacrificed" so that more&#13;
meat and fat can be consumed.&#13;
In Africa (Table 7), the familiar declining trend is found for&#13;
bread and cereals. While the share of meat increases in both urban Ghana&#13;
and Kenya, the increase is quite marginal--4 percent in Ghana and 2 percent&#13;
in Kenya from the poorest to the richest households. The rural pattern in&#13;
Ghana for meat shows stagnation if not decline. It is noteworthy that in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-26-&#13;
Table 6: DISM1T1  ON OP MXPENDITURE ON POOD AND DRINK BY eiNOE OR ECPENDIURE CLASSES BY CEGAICAL AREA&#13;
Average total&#13;
exgpenditure                                Percentage of food and drink expenditure on&#13;
on food and drink&#13;
Currency           Bread   Ieat  Fats   Milk, Milk   Fruits   Sugar, Jam.   teals     Non-&#13;
Coontry        and      Period    and    and   and   Products,     and      Confection- Outside  Alcoholic  Alcoholic    Food&#13;
AImunt           Cereals  Fish   Oils    Eggs     Vegetables    aries    the Ho    Beverages  Beverages  n.e.c.&#13;
I             2        3        4      5     6       7           8           9         10        11         12         13&#13;
Mico 1968           Peso&#13;
hxhouseholds.&#13;
nno-agricul tural&#13;
and agricultural&#13;
sectors, whole&#13;
commrry)&#13;
Household inam&#13;
per soth (Pesos)&#13;
Wdhole coumtry:&#13;
Over-all          778.34   Mouth    19.6    22.7   5.6     17.6       15.1         2.7       6.5      6.2        2.0        2.0&#13;
less tbh  301     196.12     .       37.3    7.7   7.7      9.2       2.3.9        4.1        1.8      4.4       2.6        1.3&#13;
301-   600      317.73     .       32.5   11.5   7.9     13.1       20.1         3.9        2.4      5.4       8.0        1.2&#13;
601 - 1,000     510.16     .       25.8   17.8   7.0     16.0       16.8         3.4        3.9      6.2        1.7        1.4&#13;
1,001 - 3,000     834.81     .      19.6   22.9    5.7     18.1       14.9        2.7        6.1      6.6        1.5        1.9&#13;
3,001 - 6,000    1 936.01    .      15.3   26.2    4.9     19.2       13.7         2.3       7.4      6.3        2.4        2.3&#13;
6,001 -10.000    1 394.41            13.3   29.5   4.0     17.7       12.3         2.1       10.1      5.5        2.9       2.6&#13;
10,001 sd +      2 572.87     .      10.8   27.7    3.9     18.2       13.0        2.1       13.5      4.7        3.3        2.8&#13;
Noo-Agri. Sector&#13;
Over-all          938.08     .       17.6   24.4   5.2,    18.3       14.6         2.5        7.1      6.2        1.9        2.2&#13;
Less thr  301      221.12     -      34.9     7.8   8.3     10.3       2.3.3        4.2        1.8      5.0        3.0        1.4&#13;
301-   600       315.82     .      29.3    12.7   7.3     14.9       19.5         3.5        4.4      5.6        1.5        1.3&#13;
601 - 1 000      500.90     .       24.1   18.8   6.9     17.2       17.2         3.1        3.3      6.5        1.3        1.6&#13;
1 001 - 3 000      865.68     .      19.0    23.4   5.5     18.5       14.8         2.5       6.2       6.6        1.4       2.1&#13;
3 001 - 6 000     1 403.50            15.2   26.7   4.7     19.0       14.0         2.2        7.3      6.2        2.2       2.5&#13;
6 001 -10 000     1 912.36            12.9   28.9   3.9     18.0       12.2         2.2       11.0      5.5        2.7        2.7&#13;
10 001 an d       2 597.75            10.9   28.8    3.7     18.6       13.0         2.1       12.4      4.8       3.4        2.3&#13;
Agric. Sector&#13;
Over-all          548.58   MInth    24.6    18.6   6.8     15.7       16.3        3.3        5.2       6.1        2.0        1.4&#13;
Ias than 301      189.38             36.1    7.7   7.5      8.9       24.0        4.1        1.7       4.2        2.4        1.4&#13;
301-   600      318.41     .       33.6   11.1   8.1     12.4       20.3        4.0        1.7       5.3        2.2        1.3&#13;
601 - 1,000      518.77    .       27.4   16.9   7.1     14.9       16.5        3.7        4.4       5.9        2.0        1.2&#13;
1,001 - 3.000     760.24            21.3    21.4   6.4     17.0       15.4        3.0        5.8       6.8        1.6        1.3&#13;
3.001 - 6.000    1 325.08    _       16.4   22.4   6.4     21.2       10.8        2.4        7.9       7.2        3.8        1.5&#13;
6,001 -10,000    2 103.44            15.4   33.5   4.5     15.8       12.8        1.7        4.7       5.5        4.4        1.7&#13;
10,000 and +     2 446.49     .      10.0    21.5   4.5     16.1       13.3        2.1       19.7       4.4        2.6        5.8&#13;
Brazil, 1962      Cruiro&#13;
(Al  rya of&#13;
househol4a, rural&#13;
Federal States of&#13;
R.G. do Sul ad&#13;
Perumb co)&#13;
Household lnc&#13;
per year (Cruzeiro)&#13;
Rio Crukde do Sul:&#13;
Over-all          254.5     Year     20.0   31.7   7.5     11.1       13.8        3.9        2.1       0.7        2.4        6.8&#13;
Up to 99           103.3             28.9    25.6   5.8      8.9       14.1        6.6        0.4       1.0        0.4        8.3&#13;
100-   249       165.3             22.5    25.2   9.1     12.9       13.8        4.7        1.4       0.9        1.6        7.9&#13;
250-   499       231.7      _      20.1    31.0   7.0     10.8       15.8        3.9 129    1.1       0.7 130    2.5        6.3 131&#13;
500-   799       305.9              18.2   31.2   6.3     13.2       13.4        3.9        3.2       0.5        3.8        6.4&#13;
800- 1,199       458.0      .       16.8   37.3   5.2      9.3       14.2        3.1        3.4       0.6        0.9        9.2&#13;
1,200 a   4        501.2             20.2    37.0   8.7      9.0       10.6        3.6        2.7       0.9        2.9       4.4&#13;
129 - Sugar only       130 - Excluding tea ad cooo     131-  clsudig jam snd confectionsires, tea nd cocos&#13;
Source: fD, Household Income ud Expenditure Statiatica. No. 2, 1974.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-27-&#13;
9b                                   10~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~a 'a  1 '0 'a a'.0 1&#13;
W  .0 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~~~~aN  aN' a.~N&#13;
0  bO                                    co~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~'  ~ N   '3 'a c, '0 &#13;
-   -   -   -   -   -   -  -   -   -   -   -   -   -  l~~~~~~~~~~ a  l3  a In  l3a  'a la  In&#13;
.9 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~n1 ~nn                99C iC&#13;
.0  ~~~~4)                                      -0-  3t3 a'- N-- -  --  --  -- &#13;
co  I&#13;
o  La  .0 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ .....  &#13;
4)  t~~~~~~.  40    ,Al  ,  &#13;
4)~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~4W&#13;
4)  M~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 34i4~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-28-&#13;
Ghana fruits and vegetables make up a high and stable share--more than&#13;
one-third--of the total food budget.     In Kenya the share of fruits and&#13;
vegetables is the more usual 10 to 15 percent; it increases marginally then&#13;
declines. Sugar shows a declining share, while milk and milk products&#13;
retain a constant share.&#13;
Japanese consumption patterns (Table 8) are quite remarkable in&#13;
that the shares are about the same for all income classes for fats, milk&#13;
products, eggs, fruits, vegetables, and alcoholic beverages. There is a 9&#13;
percentage point decline in the share of bread and cereals between the&#13;
lowest and the highest income households, and this is absorbed by a 4 point&#13;
increase in meat share and a 6 point increase in meals eaten outside the&#13;
home.&#13;
In the Republic of Korea (Table 8), the meat share doubles from&#13;
11 to 22 percent between the poorest and richest households. The share of&#13;
bread and cereals remains very high--the highest for any country (except&#13;
rural India) in this survey--almost 30 percent for the highest income&#13;
class. Milk products, sugar products, and meals away from home show&#13;
significant increases, doubling or even tripling their budget shares.&#13;
Fruits and vegetables also show an increase, though a more modest one.&#13;
In India (Table 9), the income classes are stated in terms of&#13;
fractiles rather than monetary income. The highest fractile in the rural&#13;
areas spent 48 percent of its food budget on cereals, while the lowest&#13;
spent 74 percent, the highest in this sample. While this is partly due to&#13;
India's having the lowest per capita income among these countries, it does&#13;
not fully explain this large share. Kenya has nearly the same per capita&#13;
income, and the cereals share of the highest income class in that country&#13;
was 16 percent. The equivalent income class in urban India spent around 15&#13;
percent of its budget for cereals. A more probable explanation lies in the&#13;
fact that the survey was conducted in the drought year of 1965-1966. Rural&#13;
areas might have been harder hit than urban areas where government&#13;
distribution efforts were better organized. If so, cereals would be&#13;
significantly cheaper in the cities, permitting the budget share to be&#13;
lower for a given quantity consumed. Also fractile for fractile rural&#13;
incomes must have been much lower than urban incomes.&#13;
Meat consumption in India starts from a very low base of 2 to 3&#13;
percent of poor household' budgets, the lowest among countries in the&#13;
sample, and does not increase to very significant levels--6.7 percent in&#13;
the richest urban households and 3.3 percent in the richest rural&#13;
households. These numbers suggest that if urban per household food&#13;
expenditures trebled, from Rs. 22 to Rs. 66, the share of the budget&#13;
allocated to meat would increase from the current average of 5 percent to&#13;
only 6.7 percent. This suggests the severe limits to growth in per capita&#13;
meat consumption in India. In contrast, milk and milk products show very&#13;
dramatic increases. From a low 2-3 percent, expenditures rise to 13&#13;
percent in rural areas and 18 percent in the urban centers. Sugar's share&#13;
declines in richer households in the urban areas, while it rises in the&#13;
rural areas.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-29-&#13;
Table 8. - Distribution of Expenditure on Food and Drink by Income&#13;
or Expenditure Classes by Geographical Area&#13;
Average total&#13;
expenditure                                   Percentage of food and drink expenditure on&#13;
on food and drink&#13;
Country                  _&#13;
milk,&#13;
Currency            BreAd   Meat   Pats    Milk        Fruits      Sugar,     Meals      Non                  Food&#13;
and     Period     and    and    and   products,     and         je,       outside  alcoholic  Alcoholic   n.e.c.&#13;
amount            Cereals  Fish   Oils    eggs     vegetables   confection-   the    beverages  beverages&#13;
aries      hown&#13;
1            2        3         4      5      6       7           8           9          10        11         12         13&#13;
J      1969          Yen&#13;
(Japanese house-&#13;
holds of two or&#13;
more persons&#13;
except farmers&#13;
and fishermen,&#13;
whole country)&#13;
Household moey&#13;
income per month&#13;
(Yen)&#13;
Overall            28 531   Month     19.2   22.1  0.8       7.6       19.2         1.6        9.8        2.2        5.7        11.8&#13;
Less than 20 000   13 797             24.4   21.1  0.8       6.8       21.2         1.7         5.7       1.8        5.1        11.4&#13;
20 000 - 29 999    16 743            22.6    22.2  0.9       7.3       21.2         1.7        6.3        1.8        5.4        10.6&#13;
30 000 - 39 "9     18 277            21.6    21.3  0.8       7.8       20.4         1.7        6.7        1.9        6.1        11.7&#13;
40 000 - 49 999    20 567     .       20.6   21.4  0.8       8.3       19.9         1.8        7.7        1.9        5.8        11.8&#13;
50 000 - 59 999    22 694             20.0   21.3  0.8       8.2       19.7         1.8        8.3        2.0        6.0        11.9&#13;
60 000 - 69 999    24 913     .      20.0    21.2  0.8       8.3       19.3         1.8        9.0        2.0        6.1        11.5&#13;
70 000 - 79 999    27 059             19.9   21.2  0.8       8.0       19.1         1.9        9.3        2.0        5.9        11.9&#13;
80 000 - 89 999    28 990             19.3   21.9  0.8       7.7       19.2         1.8        9.8        2.2        5.7        11.6&#13;
90 000 - 99 999    30 334             19.1   21.8  0.8       7.7       18.8         1.8       10.3        2.2        5.8        11.7&#13;
100 000 -119 999    32 313            19.2    22.3  0.8       7.3       18.8         1.7       10.4        2.2        5.6        11.7&#13;
120 000 -139 f99    34 711            18.8    22.8  0.8       7.1       18.8         1.8       10.2       2.4         5.3        12.0&#13;
140 ODO -159 999    36 460            18.1    22.8  0.8       7.3       18.8         1.6       10.8       2.4         5.7        11.7&#13;
160 000 -179 999    39 054            17.7    23.3  0.8       6.8       18.9         1.4       11.2        2.6        5.0        12.3&#13;
180 000 -199 999    38 351            17.5    25.5  0.9       7.2       18.7         1.5       11.0       3.1         4.8        11.8&#13;
200 000 -249 999   41 867              17.4   23.6  0.8       6.6       19.1         1.6       11.3        2.7        5.3        11.6&#13;
250 000 and +       45 154             15.8   24.8  0.8       6.3       18.7         1.4       12.3       2.7         4.9        12.3&#13;
Kores (Rep of),      won&#13;
1971&#13;
(Korean houe-&#13;
holds of two or&#13;
more persons&#13;
urban, whole&#13;
country)&#13;
Household income&#13;
per month (Ions)&#13;
Salary and wage&#13;
earners:&#13;
Overall            13 460   Month    43.4   16.9            3.5        16.4         4.1         2.2                 1.7        11.8&#13;
Less than 20 000    8 380            56.2   11.1            2.4        14.2         3.2         1.3                 2.0        9.1&#13;
20 000 - 27 999    11 180            49.2   14.0            3.0        15.7         3.6         1.5                 1.3       11.7&#13;
28 000 - 35 999    13 760     "      44.4   16.7     99     3.2 99     16.2         3.7 100    2.0         101      1.5       12.3 IOZ&#13;
36 000 - 45 999    15 760            40.7   18.6            3.7        17.2         3.8        2.2                  1.7       12.1&#13;
44 000 - 51 999    17 400             36.3  20.2            3.8        17.1         4.6         3.2                 1.6        12.2&#13;
52 DO - 59 999     18 380             37.9  21.3            3.4        17.3         4.2         2.3                 2.1        11.5&#13;
60 000 and +       24 020             29.9  22.3  I   _     5.0  _     17.8         6.1  _      4.1                 2.2        12.6&#13;
99 - Included with 'Food n.e.c.' Butter included with -milk, milk products, egp.'&#13;
100 - Including soft drinks.&#13;
101 - Soft Drinks included with 'sugar, jam and confectionaries'.&#13;
102 - Including fats and oils.&#13;
Food n.e.c. - Food item not elsewhere elasified.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-30-&#13;
Table 9. - Distribution of Expenditure on Food and Drink by Income&#13;
or Expenditure Classes by Geographical Area&#13;
Average total&#13;
expenditure                                 Percentage of food and drink expenditure on&#13;
on food and drink&#13;
Country-                         -      -&#13;
Milk,&#13;
Currency           Bread   Meat  Fats    Milk       Fruits      Sugar,    Meals      Non                 Food&#13;
and     Period    and    and   and   products,     and         j ai,   outside  alcoholic  Alcoholic   n.e.c.&#13;
amount           Cereals  Fish  Oils    eggs     vegetables  confection-  the    beverages  beverages&#13;
aries      home&#13;
1           2        3        4      5      6       7          8           9         10       11         12         13&#13;
India, 1565-66     Rupee&#13;
lU -huseholds,&#13;
urban end rural,&#13;
whole teuntry)&#13;
Fractile groups&#13;
of households104&#13;
Urban areas:&#13;
Over-all        22.63     30 days   44.0   5.0   6.6    13.3        11.3        4.4        6.0      6.5         ...      3.9&#13;
0-   5          8.30               64.2   3.4   4.8     3.5        11.7        4.6        0.7      2.6         ...      4.5&#13;
5- 10          11.63               57.6   3.4   6.1     6.4        13.2        5.0        0.4      3.0         ...      4.9&#13;
10- 20          13.92       _       56.9   3.7   5.7     6.5        13.2        5.0        1.0      3.4        ...       4.6&#13;
20- 30          16.35               52.1   4.3   6.5     9.4        14.2        4.8        0.8      3.5         ...      4.4&#13;
30- 40          18.60               50.3   4.1   6.4    10.0        14.7        4.7        1.2      4.1         ...      4.5&#13;
40- 50          20.89 1             46.3   4.4   7.2    11.4        15.8        5.0        1.2      4.6         ...      4.1&#13;
50- 60          23.98        _      41.7   5.0   7.7    13.6        16.6        4.7        1.1      5.2         ...      4.4&#13;
60- 70          27.44               36.6   6.2   7.5    14.9        17.0        4.7        2.5      6.5         ...      4.1&#13;
70- 80          32.51               32.0   5.1   6.7    17.5        16.0        4.1        7.4      7.7         ...      3.5&#13;
80- 90          39.71               24.8   5.5   6.1    16.8        15.9        3.5       15.3      9.1         ...       3.0&#13;
90- 95          45.35               21.6   5.5   5.8    19.0        17.8        3.7       12.9     10.8         ...       2.9&#13;
95 - 100        66.74        _      15.7   6.7   6.7    19.0        18.3         2.8      13.3     15.0         ...       3.1&#13;
Cities combined*1&#13;
Over-all        30.83     30 days   20.2   8.3   7.6    15.7        19.4         4.0       9.5     11.8         ...       3.5&#13;
0-    5        10.93               49.3   5.4   6.9     5.7        16.6         6.3        -       4.0         ...       5.8&#13;
5- 10          14.79               37.1   8.3   9.1     8.0        19.2         6.5       0.4      6.1         ...       5.3&#13;
10- 20          18.24        .      35.0   8.6   7.8    10.6        19.5        5.3        1.3      7.1         ...      4.8&#13;
20- 30          21.45 1             28.1   8.2  10.1    13.6        20.6         5.9       0.8      8.1         ...      4.6&#13;
30- 40          25.55               25.7  10.8  10.0    12.3        19.8         5.3       2.9      9.0         ...      4.2&#13;
40- 50          33.09               20.1   8.7   6.3    18.3        17.5        4.5        8.2     10.4         ...      6.0&#13;
50- 60           34.64              16.8   8.0   8.5     14.6        18.7        3.6       13.5    13.3         ...        3.0&#13;
60- 70           42.18              15.2   7.4   7.5     17.1        19.9        3.5       13.6    12.4         ...        3.4&#13;
70- 80           43.91  1           12.2   6.9   6.3     20.2        16.9        2.9       18.6    13.3         ...        2.7&#13;
80- 90           51.92              13.5   6.3   6.5     17.6        20.3        3.2       14.0    16.2         ...        2.4&#13;
90- 95           61.04              13.0   6.9   5.2     22.9        22.4        2.5       8.8     14.8         ...        3.5&#13;
95 - 100         79.02               7.9  12.9   7.1     14.1        18.6        1.5       18.6    17.3         ...        2.0&#13;
Urban areas:&#13;
Over-all         19.34    30 days   63.6   2.8   4.3      8.5        11.2        3.4       0.8      1.9         ...        3.5&#13;
0-    5          7.06              73.9   2.1   3.5      2.0         9.1        1.8        1.3      1.7        ...        4.6&#13;
5- 10            9.93              74.9   2.2   3.6      2.0         8.7        2.3        1.0     1.5         ...        3.8&#13;
10- 20           12.01       _      71.9   2.1   3.9      3.5         9.5       2.5        1.2      1.5         ...        3.9&#13;
20- 30           13.96       _      70.3   2.6   4.2      4.2        10.2        2.7       0.4      1.5         ...        3.9&#13;
30- 40           15.80              69.4   2.7   4.2      4.8        10.6        2.5       0.5      1.5         ...        3.8&#13;
40- 50           17.51 1            67.7   2.5   4.4      6.4        10.5        3.0       0.4      1.6         ...        3.5&#13;
50- 60           19.60              65.9   2.7   4.4      7.1        11.1        3.0       0.7      1.7         ...        3.4&#13;
60- 70           21.79              64.1   3.2   4.3      8.4        11.2        3.2       0.5      1.7         ...        3.4&#13;
70- 80           24.83              61.6   2.9   4.3     10.4        11.5        3.6       0.5      1.8         ...        3.4&#13;
80- 90           28.86       _      58.3   3.2   4.5     11.7        12.1        4.0       0.9      2.1         ...        3.2&#13;
90-95            34.66       _      54.3   3.1   4.6     13.7        13.2        4.3        1.2     2.3         ...        3.3&#13;
95-100           46.07              48.3   3.3   5.0     17.0        12.7        5.7       2.2      2.3         ...        3.5&#13;
*Cltins oombined includes only Bomaby, Calcutta, Delbi, and Madras.&#13;
I - per capita.     63 - including laundry soap.&#13;
104 - estlmted percentage of households based on the results of ranking the households by ascending order of consumption per person.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-31-&#13;
This survey makes obvious the importance of income as the driving&#13;
force causing basic changes in food consumption patterns--witness the&#13;
substantial difference in budget shares of food categories between the&#13;
highest and lowest income categories within countries. At the same time it&#13;
also reveals significant differences in behavior patterns across&#13;
countries--only three of the a priori expectations were confirmed with any&#13;
degree of universality. These related to budget shares of bread and&#13;
cereals, meat and fish, and meals away from home.&#13;
In other areas major differences were observed both in terms of&#13;
trends and levels of consumption. Tthese findings suggest that either the&#13;
general cost heirarchy is not as universal as Bennett thought it was or&#13;
that there might be a universal heirarchy, but for a variety of social or&#13;
cultural reasons, people in specific countries do not behave according to&#13;
it. As the next chapter shows, there are elements of truth in both these&#13;
views.&#13;
The final point to note is that at very low income levels,&#13;
changes in prices of staples automatically imply significant changes in&#13;
real incomes. Therefore, income growth may be a laudable long-run&#13;
objective; but in the short-run, it is prices that determine the&#13;
nutritional status of the poor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-32-&#13;
V.   TltE PRICE FACTOR&#13;
In 1957, an article in the FAO publication, The State of Food and&#13;
Agriculture could claim that&#13;
In the United States the general trend of opinion among&#13;
economists at the present time seems to be that the&#13;
influence of price levels on food consumption is relatively&#13;
minor and that more attention should be paid to the effect&#13;
of changes in income...(FAO, 1957, p.95)&#13;
This view has roots in the structural model of the development&#13;
process. According to the structuralists, food prices are irrelevant to&#13;
the development process since both producers and consumers are insensitive&#13;
to changes in prices. Such a 'trend of opinion' was surprising even in&#13;
1957 when estimates of price and income elasticities clearly showed that&#13;
the former were as high as, and sometimes higher than the latter, as shown&#13;
in Table 10.&#13;
Table 10: ELASTICITY ESTIMATES, UNITED STATES, 1922-1941&#13;
Price              Income&#13;
Category          Elasticity         Elasticity&#13;
All Food            -0.34               0.27&#13;
All Meat            -0.64               0.56&#13;
Beef                -0.79               0.73&#13;
Source:  FAO, 1957 (p.95).&#13;
It is now generally accepted that prices play a very important&#13;
role in the production sector.    Their role in the consumption sector is&#13;
less well documented although Geissler and Miller (1982) have argued in a&#13;
recent article that the principal reason for differential occurrence of&#13;
malnutrition in Thailand and the Philippines--two countries that are very&#13;
similar in GNP per capita, population size, industrialization, and adequacy&#13;
of food supply--is lower food prices in Thailand. The Philippines has&#13;
three times as many doctors per head, twice as many people enjoying safe&#13;
drinking water, and literacy rates 23 percent higher. Yet according to one&#13;
estimate (Reutlinger and Aldereman, 1980), 71 percent of the Philippine&#13;
population suffered from some calorie deficit while the corresponding&#13;
figure for Thailand was 53 percent.&#13;
Price changes have two distinct and separable impacts--the&#13;
substitution and income effects. The substitution effect causes consumers&#13;
to substitute away from the costlier product and is always negative in&#13;
direction. The income effect generally causes consumption of all goods to&#13;
fall (if prices increase) although exceptions are made for 'inferior'&#13;
goods. This is expressed algebraically in the "Slutsky equation",&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-33-&#13;
eij = Eij - eia;,&#13;
where    eij = total price elasticity of good i when good j's price&#13;
changes,&#13;
Eij = the Slutsky 'pure' substitution elasticity for the same&#13;
price change,&#13;
Ei = the income elasticity for good i,&#13;
aj   = the budget share for good j.&#13;
The income effect, represented by Ei aj, is itself quite&#13;
substantial for poor households. If the income elasticity for food for the&#13;
poor is 0.8 and the budget proportion is about the same, the observed&#13;
Cournot elasticity (eii) would be -0.64 even if the substitution effect&#13;
were zero. Moreover, work by Timmer (1981) suggests that not only is the&#13;
substitution effect considerable, but it is also higher for the poor than&#13;
for the richer households. In other words, were a third dimension&#13;
reflecting household incomes to be added to the Slutsky matrix, the terms&#13;
of the matrix for a given commodity would 'curve' smoothly from poor to&#13;
rich households.&#13;
A sample of results for substitution between rice and cassava in&#13;
Indonesia is shown in Table 11. The data base was the 1976 Socio-economic&#13;
Survey (SUSENAS V) which collected detailed commodity expenditure and&#13;
quantity data for the entire cross-section of households, making it&#13;
possible to calculate implicit prices.&#13;
As Table 11 shows, all the substitution terms are significant for&#13;
all income classes except the rice-cassava cross-substitution terms, which&#13;
are not significantly different from zero at normal confidence levels.&#13;
This has important policy implications insofar as consumers,&#13;
especially poor consumers are concerned. Not only are prices the&#13;
substantial determinant of nutritional status in the short run (simply&#13;
because income growth takes time) but they can be much more easily&#13;
manipulated by government policies.&#13;
Therefore, food policy design should incorporate the matrix of&#13;
consumption parameters disaggregated by income class. While estimating&#13;
these parameters is a daunting and expensive process, the results in terms&#13;
of better policy make it worthwhile.&#13;
The gains to public policy accrue in two forms. Firstly, a full&#13;
consumption parameters matrix enables a systemic approach to food policy&#13;
since it accounts for all the linkages between food prices and their&#13;
overall impact on nutritional status. Questions like, e.g., the impact on&#13;
rice consumption of changing cassava prices and the net impact of this on&#13;
the caloric intake of the lowest income class, can be answered. Secondly,&#13;
it becomes possible to target subsidy type interventions better and to&#13;
minimize leakages, thus reducing the burden on the exchequer.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-34-&#13;
Table 11:   COMPENSATED PRICE RESPONSES BY INCOME CLASS, INDONESIA, 1976&#13;
Slutskly Elasticities (E&#156;j)a&#13;
Income Class                                    Rice            Cassava&#13;
Low                                  Rice       -1.318          -0.043ns&#13;
Cassava      1.364         -1.251&#13;
Low-Middle                                      Rice            Cassava&#13;
Rice        -1.002          -0.007nS&#13;
Cassava      0.950         -0.807&#13;
High-Middle                                     Rice            Cassava&#13;
Rice        -0.856         -0.078ns&#13;
Cassava      0.897         -0.939&#13;
High                                            Rice            Cassava&#13;
Rice        -0.669         -0.006ns&#13;
Cassava      0.648         -0.801&#13;
Note: ns = not signficant&#13;
aRows refer to the commodity whose quantity changes and columns refer to&#13;
the commodity whose price changes. Also, cassava refers to fresh&#13;
cassava.&#13;
Source: Timmer (1981, p. 400)&#13;
Many useful insights about nutritional behavior of the poor can&#13;
also be gained by examining the cost per calorie of the various food&#13;
categories.&#13;
In the last chapter the point was made that either the&#13;
cost-hierarchy is not universal or that consumers exercise preferences base&#13;
on non-cost considerations. It is now time to test these ideas.&#13;
Table 12 shows the hierachy of calorie costs for 13 food&#13;
categories for 7 countries for 1975. The prices are expressed in index&#13;
form with the cheapest commodity in each country being the base (=100).&#13;
The prices were calculated using data from Kravis, et al., (1982)&#13;
and the FAO's Food Balance Sheets, 1975-1977. The former provides&#13;
expenditure data in national currencies for each food category, while the&#13;
latter gives the calories derived from them. For some categories where a&#13;
country's consumption is very low (e.g., meat in India or pork in Kenya),&#13;
expenditure and calorie data had a high margin of error. In such&#13;
instances, the calorie costs were calculated using purchasing power&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-35-&#13;
Table 12: THE HIERARCHY OF CALORIES COSTS FOR SEVEN COUNTRIES, 1975&#13;
Food Category               USA   India  Kenya  Korea  Brazil   Mexico  Japan&#13;
1)  Roots and Tubers        100    163    100    208     114      400     163&#13;
2)  Sugars and Honey        114    170    286    213    100       100     100&#13;
3)  Rice                    136    147    790    148    253       200     191&#13;
4)  Other Cereals           186    100    !90    100     210      200     303&#13;
and Pulses&#13;
5)  Pork                    186    151    438    298     834     1200    1122&#13;
6)  Milk and                236    626   1029    556     639      700    1084&#13;
Milk Products&#13;
7)  Egg and Egg             255    653   1019    494    1858     3300     388&#13;
Products&#13;
8)  Lamb and Mutton         273    312    648    287    1566     5500     413&#13;
9)  Beef                    314    163    605   1735    1502     3200    3209&#13;
10) Poultry                 464   1328   3000    640   2902      4500    1428&#13;
11) Fruits                  545   595    2905   1015    380       900    1434&#13;
12) Vegetables             1632   895    2471    377   8468      6000    2216&#13;
13) Fish                   1705    100   4794    525   2249      2600    1741&#13;
Note:  The cheapest commodity in each country is set as base      100&#13;
Sources: Kravis et al. (1982)&#13;
FAO, Food Balance Sheets, 1975-77.&#13;
parities, also given by Kravis, et al. The actual prices in national&#13;
currencies are shown in Table 13 along with the amounts of calories&#13;
provided by each source. As can be seen, an unfortunate weakness is that&#13;
the category 'other cereals and pulses' (which accounts for a large share&#13;
of calories) could not be disaggregated further because of data&#13;
unavailability.&#13;
Despite Bennett's assertion about the cost-hierarchy for food&#13;
categories, the cost per calorie is not likely to be the same for all&#13;
commodities in all countries. Casual observation of Table 12 shows that&#13;
the relative prices across countries tend to differ both in terms of&#13;
'spacing' (between contiguous commodities in the hierarchy) and in the&#13;
ordering of the hierarchy itself. Of course there are broad similarities;&#13;
for example, sugar and cereals are generally cheaper and fruits and&#13;
vegetables are generally more expensive. But it is difficult to be&#13;
confident about a common international hierarchy of prices. Clearly,&#13;
there are limits to price equalization from international trade.&#13;
How can 'taste effects' be isolated from all the other supply and&#13;
demand factors that are acting simultaneously to determine prices?&#13;
Conceptually, a positive taste effect implies a propensity toward a&#13;
commodity so that for a given price and income setting, demand is greater&#13;
than in other societies. A negative taste effect works in the opposite&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-36-&#13;
direction. These simple categorizations can be illustrated in a&#13;
surprisingly clear fashion with the comparative calorie cost data in&#13;
Table 13. In the cases of India and Kenya, the Indians seem to exercise a&#13;
'negative preference' for tubers, pork, beef, and fish. On the other hand,&#13;
they have a positive preference for milk. The Kenyans seem to have a&#13;
negative preference for tuber, pork, and eggs.&#13;
It must be emphasized here that the term 'negative preferences'&#13;
is not being used as a synonym for 'taboos'. In fact to label all negative&#13;
preferences as taboos is to miss an important analytical point and make&#13;
policy options seem narrower than they actually are.&#13;
To return to the India example, the reasons why people consume&#13;
less beef are quite different from the reasons why they consume fewer&#13;
tubers. The origins of the negative preferences are different in the two&#13;
instances.&#13;
The negative preference for beef has historical and religious&#13;
associations, and taboo is an appropriate term. However, there is no taboo&#13;
against potatoes or sweet potatoes. The potato is a fairly recent entry in&#13;
the food habits of the Sub-continent, and has been slow to spread because&#13;
it has never been actively propagated. If people have traditionally eaten&#13;
rice, wheat or maize and have not discovered (or needed to discover) that&#13;
potatoes are also a cheap source of calories, then it is not taboos but&#13;
habit, inertia, and ignorance that prevent more flexible dietary patterns.&#13;
Household decision-making is made on the basis of incomes and prices to be&#13;
sure. But the manner in which the consumption possibility set is defined&#13;
is largely a function of the 'received experience' from the family and the&#13;
larger society.&#13;
This perspective on food preferences makes it possible to&#13;
distinguish among different categories of 'cheap' calories and the policy&#13;
options that are best suited to each.&#13;
The first category includes those foods already consumed to a&#13;
fair degree by most people, especially the poor. Since in most countries&#13;
these grains, roots, or tubers tend to be 'inferior goods for at least the&#13;
middle- and upper-income households, they are an ideal vehicle for income&#13;
redistribution and overcoming malnutrition through price subsidies.&#13;
Examples of such foods are cassava and maize in Indonesia, and coarse wheat&#13;
in India.&#13;
The second category is comprised of foods that may be even less&#13;
expensive than the first. They are likely to have a short history as&#13;
edible or available food in the region, for example, tubers, or pulses, or&#13;
soybeans. Although such foods are highly nutritious sources of calories&#13;
and proteins, their consumption is restricted because of people's habits&#13;
and lack of knowledge. Since their prices are already quite low, what is&#13;
needed is not a subsidy policy but a dissemination of their palate-pleasing&#13;
and nutritive properties. In fact, further lowering of their prices runs&#13;
the risk that such foods might be perceived as useless since apparently&#13;
nobody wants to eat them. Naturally, this type of nutrition education has&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-37-&#13;
-ts~~                                         ~        ~ _  ..  ,&#13;
i  }  }  S   R  @   S    S   R  a    A ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C4  M C4  LI Co&#13;
|  _  ;S  n  g  s  e  @   S n    ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~n  C  gN &#13;
R ~ ~   ~  ' _N                                   I -' W% 0-&#13;
8 8  |&#13;
X  X  ;    X     g  ^    g   S    e  e   e    @   g  g  r     e&#13;
-    n    N  n                                   .4&#13;
F". ~~~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
8~~~~ :             4P N       B M A       0'  N &#13;
g~ ~   ~~    -_ BA            N                       AP .  .    ,&#13;
P.-  - -^^O d&#13;
1~~~~~~N~~                     NN         -   '. '0 irB &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-38-&#13;
to be done in the context of how they are to be cooked and eaten with other&#13;
traditional foods. The message has to mesh with the food ways of society.&#13;
In some countries another category of foods, generally meats, has&#13;
the lowest caloric price of all, mainly because the foods are taboo. These&#13;
foods have strong negative associations either because of religion, as beef&#13;
among Hindus or pork among Muslims, or cultural attitudes. Policies&#13;
designed to increase consumption of such foods face ridicule and loss of&#13;
credibility for the policy makers. There is little point in investing&#13;
policy efforts in such directions.&#13;
It bears repetition, however, that some foods are available in&#13;
every society whose prices are already low and which are not regarded as&#13;
taboo or culturally inferior. They are not consumed in substantial&#13;
quantities because of the inertia of eating habits. Active propagation of&#13;
their palatability is what is required, not a further subsidy on their&#13;
costs.&#13;
The list of economic forces shaping consumption patterns&#13;
encompasses not only incomes and prices but also demographic factor. There&#13;
are two reasons for this. On the one hand, intra-household behavior is&#13;
determined by aspects of the structure of households--their size,&#13;
male/female-child/adult composition, number of working members, and so on.&#13;
On the other, certain demographic trends like urbanization imply changing&#13;
lifestyles and their impact on food habits cannot be fully captured by&#13;
income and price elasticities. Accordingly, they are the subjects of the&#13;
next two chapters.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-39-&#13;
VI. THE INFLUENCE OF DEMOGRAPHIC VARIABLES&#13;
The object of this chapter is to investigate the effects of&#13;
household size and composition on consumption patterns. By 'household&#13;
composition' is here meant the age and sex of members of the household.&#13;
In analyzing the detrimental effect of adding a person of a&#13;
particular type to the household, it is necessary to distinguish two stages&#13;
in the calculation. There is, first, the question of how an increase&#13;
merely in the number of persons in the household would affect consumption,&#13;
all persons being of the same standard type. Once this has been&#13;
determined, it is possible to go to the second stage and ask how the&#13;
additon of the person of the particular type would compare with that of a&#13;
person of the standard type.&#13;
One simple hypothesis that may be used to start with is the&#13;
'homogeneity hypothesis'. According to this, a proportionate increase in&#13;
household size leads to a percentage decline in income per capita of the&#13;
same magnitude, hence the change in consumption will be given by the&#13;
incomne elasticity applicable to that expenditure category. This is&#13;
equivalent to asserting that, holding income per capita constant, the&#13;
'elasticity of per capita demand with respect to household size' is zero.&#13;
This hypothesis is not very realistic. Indeed, it would not have&#13;
been mentioned here but for its widespread usage, mostly implicitly.&#13;
Economies of scale accrue to large households in both purchase and&#13;
production of food. Savings in value of consumption per person may be made&#13;
in large households for certain foods simply by buying in large quantities&#13;
at lower unit prices. Also leftover wastage as a proportion of food cooked&#13;
is lower. Thus it should be expected that the household size elasticity,&#13;
which is defined as the rate of change in consumption per capita relative&#13;
to the rate of change in the size of households, should have a non-zero&#13;
value. Estimates for the United States show that the elasticity varies&#13;
from -0.2 to -0.4. For example, consider a family whose size goes up from&#13;
4 to 5 members. To remove any 'income effect', their income is adjusted so&#13;
that the per capita income remains the same as before. For this 25 percent&#13;
increase in household size, per capita food expenditures will decline to 95&#13;
percent of their former level, assuming a household size elasticity of&#13;
-0.2. Stated differently, a 25 percent increase in household size leads to&#13;
a 19 percent increase in total food expenditures.&#13;
The influence of age and sex on food requirements may now be&#13;
considered. For comparison, the standard is defined as the consumption of&#13;
an adult male of 'average' body size who engages in the 'average' amount of&#13;
physical activity for that population. The consumption of people of other&#13;
ages and sex can then be expressed as a percentage of the standard. Such&#13;
scales are called 'adult equivalent scales', and have been constructed in&#13;
the United States. Figure 2 shows what a typical scale might look like.&#13;
As can be seen, for any given age group, women would consume less&#13;
than men. Also consumption levels are likely to be higher in youth (16-22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-40-&#13;
0~~~~~~~~0&#13;
I  I~~~~~~~V &#13;
0~~~I'&#13;
'a      a)     I &#13;
E                       c~I &#13;
0&#13;
0-     I~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
I~~~~~~&#13;
C%J120~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
a)  I~~~~ &#13;
I          Qo~~~~~~~ &#13;
co&#13;
'I         (~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~'&#13;
.a)~~~~~~~~~~~a&#13;
0) ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-41-&#13;
years) than in later years, and they drop substantially after the age of&#13;
55.&#13;
It is now possible, having isolated the separate effects of&#13;
household size, age and sex composition, to see how they interact with each&#13;
other and with income per capita. It should be expected that for given&#13;
levels of income per capita, consumption effects will be different for&#13;
large households vs. small households, younger households vs. older&#13;
households, and so on. Our primary interest here is in the characteristics&#13;
of household structures that are associated with low per capita incomes.&#13;
Below we present our hypotheses and the evidence.&#13;
It should be expected that households with low per capita incomes&#13;
would tend to be younger on average as compared to higher income&#13;
households.&#13;
This would happen partly for normal life-cycle reasons--in most&#13;
occupations a person's earnings grow with age. It would also happen&#13;
because households with low per capita incomes are less able to afford the&#13;
cost of adequate nutrition and health facilities, and are therefore liable&#13;
to greater mortality risk. In other words they have a greater chance of&#13;
dying young. Table 14 shows how the age distribution differs among income&#13;
groups in a study done in Sao Paulo.&#13;
Table 14:   SAO PAULO:  INCOME AND AGE DISTRIBUTION&#13;
Income                          Percentage of Family in Age Group&#13;
Less than 5 years    Less than 15 Years    15-35 Years&#13;
0 - 0.5*                  29.3%                 63.1%              30.3%&#13;
0.5 - 1.0                   30.8                  50.0               39.5&#13;
1.0 - 1.5                   32.4                  46.3               46.0&#13;
*Income measured in units of minimum income per month with&#13;
one minimum unit = US$80 - $100&#13;
Source: Escola Pualista, p. 15, cited in J. Austin. et al.&#13;
In Sao Paulo the lowest per capita income households have 63&#13;
percent of their members younger than 15 years, while those households with&#13;
incomes in the highest category have only 46 percent of their members that&#13;
young.&#13;
The other relationship of interest is that between incomes and&#13;
household size. The a priori expectation would be that low per capita&#13;
income households would tend to be larger.    They would have more children&#13;
because even a child has a marginal product in sundry occupations. Also,&#13;
given the high mortality risk, having more children is simply insurance for&#13;
old age. Table 15 shows how the mean family tends to decline from 6-7&#13;
members to about 4-5 as income grows.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-42-&#13;
Table 15: SAO PAULO: MEAN FAMILY SIZE&#13;
Nutritional                                    Income*&#13;
Status&#13;
0 - 0.5       0.5 - 1.0       1.5 - 2.5      2.5 plus&#13;
Malnourished**           7.1             5.9              4.2          4.6&#13;
Well Nourished           6.2             5.3              4.6          4.5&#13;
*In minimum income units&#13;
**Malnourished defined as 2nd and 3rd degree malnutrition according to the&#13;
Gomez, weight for age.&#13;
(Sample size approximatley 1,300)&#13;
Source: Escola Paulista, p. 42, cited in J. Austin, et. al.&#13;
No data could be availed on the relationship between household&#13;
income and sex composition. It is very possible, however, that low-income&#13;
families have a greater percentage of males than the high-income families.&#13;
This is based on the common observation that in poor countries infant&#13;
mortality among females is higher than that for males. This has been&#13;
attributed to a poverty that necessitates tough choices between&#13;
alternative ways of spending the family health budget. It is also attri-&#13;
butable to a deliberate neglect of female infants arising from the attitude&#13;
that female children are less desirable or productive than males.&#13;
To summarize, if our hypotheses are correct and the Sao Paulo&#13;
data have any claim to universality, low income households would tend to be&#13;
characterized by lower than average age, larger family size and higher male&#13;
proportion than the upper-income households.&#13;
The combination of low per capita income and large family size&#13;
means that poorer households are in a better position to exploit economies&#13;
of scale in the purchase and production of food. This does not mean very&#13;
much since the net output of this--nutritional status--is already captured&#13;
in data that relates to their caloric intake. To the extent nutritional&#13;
deficiencies exist, they are after accounting for the beneficial influence&#13;
of economies of scale.&#13;
What it does suggest is that the emergence of nuclear families&#13;
without significant changes in income places additional pressure on these&#13;
families. This is specially pertinent in the context of rapid urbanisation&#13;
in many low- and middle-income countries.&#13;
The net impact of more male members in low income households&#13;
(which leads to demand for more calories) and lower average age (which may&#13;
reduce demand for calories or increase it depending on proportions of&#13;
children and youths) is likely to be higher need for calories than in&#13;
richer households. This is without taking into account the manual nature&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-43-&#13;
of low income occupations. Also, demand for the various food groups would&#13;
be effected. Among younger populations the demand (or at least the need)&#13;
for milk would be higher as would demand for other low-bulk, higher protein&#13;
foods.&#13;
It is difficult to arrive at more specific conclusions regarding the&#13;
impact of household structures on consumption patterns since data in this&#13;
area are woefully lacking. In fact an important aspect which was totally&#13;
ignored here relates to the decision-making process that allocates&#13;
resources within the household. What should be clear, however, is that the&#13;
factors considered here have an impact that is captured by aggregate&#13;
econometric estimates of parameters like elasticities, and secondly, that&#13;
the extent to which these factors change (trends towards nuclear and&#13;
single-parent families, longer life-spans, etc.) introduces elements of&#13;
instability in the underlying consumption parameters themselves.&#13;
This completes our study of the 'economic factors'--incomes,&#13;
prices, and household size and composition. The next two chapters will&#13;
examine the impact of the 'non-economic factors'--urbanization and social&#13;
class.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-44-&#13;
VII. THE IMPACT OF URBANIZATION ON URBAN DIETS&#13;
The world has been undergoing a rapid change in its settlement&#13;
patterns. Urban centers have grown through internal population growth and&#13;
because of substantial migration from the rural areas. This trend is&#13;
likely to continue. In 1980, 77 percent of the population of the&#13;
industrial market economies were living in urban settlements. In contrast,&#13;
only 27 percent of the low-income countries were similarly settled.&#13;
Obviously, the scope of further urbanization in LDCs is considerable--with&#13;
or without economic growth.&#13;
In evaluating the impact of urbanization on dietary patterns, it&#13;
is important to distinguish between the 'total effect', and its 'separate&#13;
effect'. The total effect would merely compare differences in consum,-ion&#13;
between urban and rural areas. Thus it would ignore urban-rural&#13;
differences in income and prices. The 'separate effect' analysis would&#13;
eliminate the 'noise' emanating from different incomes and prices. It would&#13;
isolate the impact that is uniquely attributable to urbanization. In the&#13;
context of this paper, this would refer to all factors associated with&#13;
urbanization other than incomes and prices--new life-styles, social&#13;
relationships, marriage patterns, family structures, availability of new&#13;
packaged and processed foods, and advertising and the media.&#13;
DeGarine (cited in J. Austin, p. 70), looking for the total&#13;
effect, found certain common patterns in the differences between the diets&#13;
of urban and rural peoples. He based the following observations on studies&#13;
conducted in Brazil, the Philippines, Cuba, and Chile.&#13;
a) The food of city dwellers is more varied; many different&#13;
kinds of foods are available, albeit for a price;&#13;
b) city dwellers generally consume more animal proteins, fats&#13;
milk;&#13;
c) urban consumers are more responsive to innovations in the&#13;
field of food, especially those foods easy to prepare quickly&#13;
and cheaply;&#13;
d) the diets of city dwellers are less subject to seasonal&#13;
variations, but mDre subject to fluctuations in wages, etc.;&#13;
e) the caloric value of the urban consumer's diet may be less&#13;
than that of rural consumers;&#13;
f) more fresh vegetables and fruit are eaten on a yearly basis&#13;
by urban dwellers; and&#13;
g) finally, given that a mDre diverse diet is likely to supply&#13;
the essential nutrients better than one that is less diverse,&#13;
he concluded that the urban consumer is, on the whole, better&#13;
off than his rural counterpart.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-45-&#13;
Thus, according to DeGarine, the total effect of urbanization is&#13;
a positive one. Does an examination of the separate effect reveal a&#13;
similar picture? The little evidence that exists is not very assuring.&#13;
Most of the food eaten by the urban poor is prepared in their&#13;
homes. Even so, snack foods have become increasingly popular, and some of&#13;
them are cheap enough to be purchased by low-income peoples--sweets, ice-&#13;
creams, fried foods, fruit preparations, and, of course, soft drinks.&#13;
The magnitude of snack food consumption has not been adequately&#13;
documented in the literature. Even if snack foods constitute only 5&#13;
percent of the total food budget, this is a fairly sizable amount given the&#13;
size of the protein or calorie deficit which has been found in their diets.&#13;
These snacks are, compared to home-cooked food, very expensive sources of&#13;
calories, and their protein content is often negligible.&#13;
Meals consumed away from home can be a significant component of&#13;
an urban dweller's diet, particularly those wage earners whose jobs are far&#13;
from their homes. During the 'lunch hour' the sidewalks of the big cities&#13;
come alive with a plethora of eating places offering both traditional and&#13;
non-traditional meals. It is difficult to comment on the nutritional value&#13;
of such meals except to say that the fat content is frequently very high.&#13;
As far as consumption of starchy staples, the 'backbone' of the&#13;
diet, are concerned, two kinds of shifts have been noticed. First, in the&#13;
cities there is a trend away from the consumption of 'inferior grains' such&#13;
as maize and sorghum. Second, there is a tendency toward the consumption&#13;
of highly milled and polished rice and wheat as compared with home-pounded&#13;
grain eaten in the countryside.&#13;
These trends have two implications. The shift toward superior&#13;
grains results in a higher percentage of the food budget being spent on&#13;
staples (since these are costlier) leaving less money for other foods. The&#13;
shift toward polished, attractive looking grain often contributes to&#13;
reduced vitamin intake.&#13;
Surveys carried out among the Bantu in the Union of South Africa&#13;
showed that their normal rural diet of whole grain cereals and milk is&#13;
often replaced by one based on refined maize meal, white bread and&#13;
mineral water and that efforts to spread nutrition education among the&#13;
urbanized Bantu are necessary to counteract that tendency. Another&#13;
example is the increasing incidence of beri-beri, a serious deficiency&#13;
disease, in some countries in South and East Asia as a result of the&#13;
spread of small rice mills producing highly milled and polished but&#13;
vitamin-deficient white rice. (FAO, 1957)&#13;
Much more than the rural populace, the urban poor encounter a&#13;
wide variety of advertised, processed, and packaged products. In a sense,&#13;
the emergence of product differentiation based on brand identification and&#13;
the decline of commodity-based selling are natural concomitants of the&#13;
process of industrialization. (After all, a country can consider itself&#13;
developed if the tomatoes in its grocery markets carry brand names. Import&#13;
of bottled water from France could well be a symptom of the post-industrial&#13;
society.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-46-&#13;
But, the assurance of quality that brand names carry, and the&#13;
marketing efforts required to build brand loyalty, carry a price tag that&#13;
is ultimately borne by consumers. To the extent that these products are&#13;
consumed by the poor--instant coffee, Western-style white bread, milk&#13;
powder, snack foods, etc.,--they crowd out more essential items of&#13;
consumption.&#13;
Nutritional status is a function not only of the volume and&#13;
composition of food intake but also of the physical characteristics of&#13;
urban life, which for the poor frequently means overcrowding, poor&#13;
sanitation, disease, ignorance, insalubrity, lack of drinking water, etc.&#13;
The undernourished individual is always living in an inadequate&#13;
environment, and the damage produced by undernutrition is aggravated by an&#13;
urban slum environment. Thus, it has been observed that children with an&#13;
acceptable food intake but living in an inadequate socioeconomic&#13;
environment show low efficiency in psychomotor development tests.&#13;
One particularly vulnerable urban group is that of the recently&#13;
arrived migrants. Rural people just arriving in the cities are quite&#13;
unfamiliar with the norms and modes of urban life. Their education and&#13;
skill levels are generally low, and their ignorance about the job market&#13;
makes them easy prey for exploitation. Those migrants who stubbornly stick&#13;
to their traditional rural diets, perhaps as a form of psychological&#13;
security, would not be at greater nutritional risk. But if they cannot&#13;
afford to buy all of what they used to eat in the countryside and if all&#13;
those foods are not available in the city, an imbalance in the diets of&#13;
these people would occur.&#13;
The family structure is also disrupted when men migrate to the&#13;
city alone. Without female partners such men may be deprived of emotional&#13;
as well as logistical support. This may lead to less complex food habits,&#13;
'quick-fix' meals, a greater propensity to eat out, and, perhaps even&#13;
alcoholism.&#13;
The thesis that emerges is that nutritional status of the urban&#13;
poor is not likely to be comparable to that of their rural brethren, and&#13;
that there are good reasons to expect it to be inferior for any given&#13;
income level. Where the city offers significantly greater income-earning&#13;
potential, of course, average nutritional status may well be better than in&#13;
the countryside.&#13;
Two public policy issues arise from this discussion. First is&#13;
the need to make available cheap, nutritious, packaged food with built-in&#13;
maid service to the urban poor. At present such foods simply do not exist.&#13;
The packaged foods currently available are either nutritionally negligible&#13;
or too expensive or both. The second point is that urban centers act as&#13;
channels by which the habits, customs, fads, and fashions of the developed&#13;
world get communicated to the semi-urban and rural areas. Policy that aims&#13;
at popularizing new food habits in the countryside where the bulk of the&#13;
population still lives--the use of soybeans for example--must necessarily&#13;
aim at achieving success in the urban areas first.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-47-&#13;
VIII. THE SOCIAL FACTORS&#13;
Consider the following observation which relates to the eating&#13;
habits of the poor:&#13;
Long experience with poverty results inevitably in adjustment to&#13;
the realities of inadequate income. Attitudes about&#13;
food as well as food choice become adapted to the&#13;
existing situation in ways that seem suitable. One&#13;
adjustment that must invariably be made concerns the&#13;
relative importance of food--how does food rank in&#13;
priority when compared to other needs. Hunger, of&#13;
course, gives food an overriding importance but the&#13;
kind of food with which one assuages the accompanying&#13;
discomforts matters relatively little. Except to&#13;
prevent hunger, food is pushed downward in the scale of&#13;
priorities by other wants that are considered more&#13;
pressing; in fact a deliberate choice is occasionally&#13;
made to undergo periodic and temporary mild hunger in&#13;
order to acquire some object deemed eminently&#13;
desirable. Middle-class persons are prone to criticize&#13;
such a practice as being foolish and short-sighted, not&#13;
recognizing that a vitally needed lift to the spirit&#13;
can result from a new possession, for example, a pair&#13;
of stylish shoes or some article of personal&#13;
adornment. The poor are just like everyone else in&#13;
deriving great personal satisfaction from the&#13;
acquisition of some longed-for object which is not&#13;
exactly utilitarian; for them as for everyone else, an&#13;
occasional luxury is an emotional necessity. (Gifft,&#13;
et al, 1972 p.103)&#13;
From the viewpoint of this paper, such seemingly perverse&#13;
behavior raises two questions of interest. Firstly, what implications do&#13;
such behavior patterns have for policy analysis. And secondly, what are&#13;
the implications for economic theory in general and parameters like income&#13;
elasticity in particular.&#13;
With respect to policy analysis, the most important implication&#13;
that suggests itself is that there might be limits to the kind of useful&#13;
impact that education can have on the nutritional status of the poor.&#13;
An appeal to 'rationality' based on nutritional science may not&#13;
result in a higher expenditure on food simply because, as long as hunger is&#13;
assuaged, food is pushed down in the order of priorities. However this&#13;
still leaves considerable scope for improving the mix of food eaten so that&#13;
the 'bang for the buck' is maximized. This may therefore be a more&#13;
productive plank for launching nutritional interventions.&#13;
In discussing the implications for economic theory, the view&#13;
adopted here is essentially that expressed by Prais and Houthakker (1971)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-48-&#13;
in "The Analysis of Family Budgets". According to them, apart from current&#13;
income, past and expected income, and the amount of capital possessed have&#13;
to be brought in as independent variables to explain expenditure patterns.&#13;
Consider...the typical working-class household, the economic&#13;
characteristics of which are that it has a negligible&#13;
amount of capital at its disposal and the prospect of&#13;
an uncertain and irregular income stream...The problem&#13;
which such a household has to solve is that of&#13;
establishing habits of expenditure which will allow it&#13;
to survive in the future as far as it can foresee it.&#13;
Habits, however, are difficult to establish and even&#13;
more difficult to change; in particular, it is easier&#13;
to become accustomed to an increase than to a decrease&#13;
in the consumption of a particular commodity...In these&#13;
circumstances a working-class household will be acting&#13;
in a perfectly rational manner if it discounts very&#13;
heavily its expected future income stream and&#13;
establishes habits of expenditure, at any rate as far&#13;
as the staple items are concerned, which are&#13;
appropriate to a lower income level than it may in fact&#13;
be [currently] enjoying; that is, habits which on the&#13;
whole are similar to those of a household expecting a&#13;
lower but regular income stream. The excess income is&#13;
then spent as quickly as possible in some&#13;
nonhabit-forming direction...(Prais and Houthakker,&#13;
1971, p.155)&#13;
The implication of this is that the concept of income elasticity&#13;
has to be elaborated so that a distinction may be drawn between the effects&#13;
of long-term and short-term changes in income.&#13;
Thus a short-term increase in the income of a worker may merely&#13;
lead to an increase in his expenditure on entertainment; but a long-term&#13;
increase may lead to a change of social class, an increase in education,&#13;
and even a change of occupation.&#13;
It should be noted that there is a difference between the impact&#13;
of short term changes in income and the short run impact of a long term&#13;
change in income. The former would result merely in an increase in&#13;
non-essential expenditure. The latter would initiate a process of change&#13;
in behavior more in line with the social class to which the household&#13;
aspires. Non-essential expenditure may actually be cut down as the&#13;
household tries to build up its capital stock quickly.&#13;
At the same time changes in expected long-term income will effect&#13;
food habits--as is succinctly and only half-humorously described in the&#13;
quote at the beginning of this essay.&#13;
The perspective that has been developed so far suggests that&#13;
consumption patterns associated with different social classes may, in&#13;
economic terms, be described as behavior attributable to expected long-term&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-49-&#13;
income. Thus, the different approaches--sociological and economic--should&#13;
be regarded as potentially consistent.&#13;
The dynamics of economic and social change does not end here.&#13;
There is an international dimension to it and this will be explored next.&#13;
The origins of the international connection are quite clear. The&#13;
twentieth century revolution in transportation and communications has&#13;
brought the world together like never before. This has allowed--through&#13;
commerce, tourism, and television--an interaction, unprecedented in scale,&#13;
of peoples, cultures, and consumption patterns.&#13;
Previously 'status-seeking' behavior had only a national (or even&#13;
sub-national) character as the lower social classes imitated the&#13;
consumption patterns of the upper classes to bootstrap themselves&#13;
socially. The dimension that has now been added is that the elite of the&#13;
poor countries is imitating the consumption patterns of their middle- and&#13;
upper-class counterparts in the richer countries. This phenomenon has been&#13;
termed 'international demonstration effect'.&#13;
Instances are available from India where it used to be that low&#13;
castes gave up eating beef and other meats after they had gained the&#13;
economic clout to be accepted in the middle-castes. With the&#13;
'internationalization' of social classes, food habits are increasingly&#13;
following the Western pattern. This is especially noticeable in the big&#13;
cities. Not only are meats like chicken, lamb and pork being consumed by a&#13;
wider number of sub-castes (and by implication, a larger number of people),&#13;
but Western preparations like burgers, pizzas and pies are very popular in&#13;
the metros. Of course acceptability of beef is still a long while away.&#13;
What all this means is that in attempting to foresee the&#13;
long-term changes in consumption in the low- and middle-income countries&#13;
one necessarily has to look at the patterns that are currently prevailing&#13;
(and evolving) in the richer nations. This is the subject of Part 3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-50-&#13;
Part 3&#13;
IX.   CONSUMPTION PATTERNS IN THE UNITED STATES, 1909-1980&#13;
The United States seems to set the pattern for the rest of the&#13;
world in food consumption behavior. A study of its dietary patterns is not&#13;
only necessary to predict short-run trends within the country, but is also&#13;
very revealing of the directions in which consumption patterns are headed&#13;
in other parts of the globe. In examining the trends it should be borne in&#13;
mind that by today's standards the United States was already a&#13;
'middle-income' nation in 1909. To that extent the following analysis is&#13;
more relevant to the rapidly growing middle-income countries in East Asia&#13;
and Latin America than the low income countries of Africa and the Indian&#13;
sub-continent.&#13;
Figure 3 shows the trends in total per capita caloric intake.&#13;
There was a long-term decline between 1909 and 1966 from around 3400&#13;
calories per capita per day to 3175, a reduction which reflects a tendency&#13;
toward sedentary lifestyles. This has also been found in other&#13;
industrialized nations. After 1966, caloric intake started rising. The&#13;
rise may be attributable partly to government food assistance programs for&#13;
the poor, partly to greater consciousness of physical fitness and exercise,&#13;
and partly to some increase in food waste at the household and&#13;
institutional level. It may be noted in passing that caloric 'intake'&#13;
actually refers to the total disappearance of foods at the retail level.&#13;
The share of this total that is ingested by the American people depends on&#13;
a number of factors, including economic and social pressures to avoid waste&#13;
as well as the technology of food preservation and marketing. Thus the gap&#13;
between caloric disappearance at the retail level and actual calories&#13;
ingested is likely to be much higher (and fluctuating) in the U.S. and&#13;
other DCs than in LDCs. The important point to be noted here is the almost&#13;
complete absence of incomes as a factor in explaining caloric intakes.&#13;
Currently the intake is around 3500 calories.&#13;
Figure 4 summarizes the trends for the major food categories.&#13;
Table 16 quantifies the changes that have taken place in calorie-sour ing.&#13;
As can be seen, starchy staples declined from 42.5 percent of total&#13;
calories in 1909-1913 to only 22.6 percent in 1980. Most of this decline&#13;
had occurred by 1947-1949. Consumption of meat, fish and poultry increased&#13;
by 26 percent to bring their calorie share to 21 percent. Fats, oils,&#13;
dairy products and eggs increased their share by 7 points to provide almost&#13;
30 percent of all calories in 1980. The consumption of sugar and other&#13;
sweeteners increased by 130 percent so that they now provide fully&#13;
one-sixth of all calories.&#13;
Because of these trends, the source of proteins in the diet has&#13;
shifted towards animal products (Table 16 and Figure 5). While in 1909 the&#13;
shares of vegetable and animal proteins were almost equal, by 1980&#13;
vegetable sources provided less than one-third of protein intake.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
C-- -    t'Ji~~~D M&#13;
'0C  -~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0&#13;
0-c  F~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
C'                   -co&#13;
__  __     C~~~~~~~  0C&#13;
CO &#13;
C              co  R~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
0 ~ ~ ~  ~   ~~     0&#13;
U  -  -  ~ ~~~~~~~, -t &#13;
~~~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
zo:              2,  'C- ,nE&#13;
Eoc EE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-52-&#13;
Figure 4:&#13;
Trends in Per Capita Consumption of&#13;
Selected Food Products in the United States&#13;
Percent of 1909&#13;
IU Food&#13;
Potatoes &amp; 11                        Dairy Products&#13;
100                         1&#13;
30             __ r__ _ _ _ ___ol&#13;
20C~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ _                                     ___ _ _ _&#13;
Melons ;t~&#13;
o   l   I   I   i  I   I   I  I    I   I    I  I    I &#13;
300&#13;
Sugar&amp;l                       Y&#13;
Other Sweeteners         Coffee&#13;
2001          '%,lt&#13;
, 5v_4AJJ _\{^_j_                 ~~~~Eggs-,i&#13;
12 sV ~~Cereal &amp;                   _WI&#13;
100 b   y       s &amp;              Products ft&amp;i&#13;
Potatoes      Se7ce.                        DaUS D  Products0-(&#13;
Sweet Potate&#13;
400                                                     Vegetrble oll N       o&#13;
300                          oultry1977&#13;
200                             cc                        /      . )&#13;
100      et&amp;V                                                          &amp;OI&#13;
Beef &amp;                      ~~~~Animal Fats z&#13;
1910        1930        1950           1910        1930        1950         1970&#13;
Year&#13;
Trends mnper capita fooDdconsumption items are combmnedin termsotfconstant retallprices Butteris included&#13;
with both dairy products &amp; fats &amp; oils&#13;
Source. Economic Research Service, U S Department of Agriculture, Neg EFS 4017-59 ( 10). In Dahl, D C&#13;
and Hammond, J W Market and Price Analysis The Agriculture Industries, McGraw Hlill New York,&#13;
1 977&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-53-&#13;
The meat, fish and poultry category has seen substantial growth&#13;
in its calorie share as well as major changes in its composition (Table&#13;
17). Pork consumption has increased only marginally over the last 70&#13;
years, while beef consumption has increased 2.6 times. Interestingly, beef&#13;
consumption has declined by 18 pounds (almost 20 percent) between 1976 and&#13;
1980. It may be too early to call this a trend but it clearly reflects a&#13;
consciousness of the harmful consequences of fatty meat.&#13;
Despite the increase in meat consumption, the share of animal&#13;
products has actually declined in the total food budget (Table 18). The&#13;
share of the budget spent on meat, fish and poultry has remained around 34&#13;
percent, while the shares of eggs and animal fats have declined. Even as&#13;
the share of crop products increased, starchy staples declined 4.2&#13;
percentage points. The slack was taken up by sugar and other sweeteners&#13;
whose share of the budget increased dramatically from 4.3 to 7.6 percent.&#13;
This was largely because of increasing consumption of soft drinks. Between&#13;
1960 and 1980, the consumption of these drinks increased threefold from&#13;
13.6 gallons per capita per annum to 37.8 gallons. With the emergence of&#13;
'diet' soft drinks, there might be a significant change in this trend.&#13;
Table 16: SHARE OF MAJOR FOOD GROUPS IN NUTRIENT INTAKE&#13;
1909-13   1947-49       1970     1980&#13;
Food Group&#13;
1)  Meat, Fish and Poultry                15.8       17.3        20.9     21.0&#13;
2) Fats, Oils, Butter, Dairy&#13;
Products &amp; Eggs                      23.1       30.3        31.0     29.9&#13;
3)  Fruits &amp; Vegetables                    4.4        6.0         5.8      6.0&#13;
4)  Starchy Staples                       42.5       27.0        22.0     22.6&#13;
5)  Sugars &amp; Other Sweeteners             11.7       15.7        16.8     17.0&#13;
Proteins&#13;
1909-13     1947-49      1970     1980&#13;
1)  Animal Products                       51.8       63.7        69.8     68.9&#13;
2)  Crop Products                         48.2       36.3        30.2     31.1&#13;
Source:   ESCS, U.S. Department of Agriculture, Statistical Bulletin 364,&#13;
U.S. Food Consumption, Sources of Data and Trends, and various&#13;
supplements.&#13;
Table 17: PER CAPITA CONSUMPTION OF BEEF, PORK AND POULTRY, 1970-80&#13;
(Pounds)&#13;
1910-19 1970-74 1975   1976    1977    1978  1979   1980&#13;
Commodity&#13;
1)  Beef               50.5   83.8    87.9   94.4   91.8    87.2   78.1   76.5&#13;
2)  Pork               60.4   62.3    50.6   53.7   55.8    55.9   63.8   68.3&#13;
3)  Poultry            16.8   49.6    49.0   52.2   53.6    56.2   60.9   60.9&#13;
4)  Total (1+2+3)     127.7  195.7   187.5  200.3  201.2   199.3  202.8  205.7&#13;
Source: See Table 16.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-54-&#13;
Table 18: RELATIVE IMPORTANCE OF MAJOR FOOD GROUPS IN FOOD BUDGET&#13;
Commodity                                1909-13        1947-49            1976&#13;
1)  Animal Products                        59.4          58.0             53.8&#13;
2)  Crop Products                          40.6           42.0            46.2&#13;
3)  Meat, Fish &amp; Poultry                   34.3           31.5            34.2&#13;
4)  Fruits &amp; Vegetables                    16.1           17.2             18.1&#13;
5)  Starchy Staples                        14.7            9.6             10.5&#13;
6)  Sugars &amp; Other Sweeteners               4.3            6.3             7.6&#13;
Source: See Table 16.&#13;
Advances in technology have produced new and improved methods of&#13;
preserving and processing, freezing, and drying. These techniques have had&#13;
their greatest impact on fruits and vegetables (Table 19). More than half&#13;
of all fruits and vegetables bought in the supermarket are processed, and&#13;
the trend is rising. Innovations on the supply side have been matched by&#13;
the popularity of processed foods on the demand side. Not only are they&#13;
well suited to current life-styles, they are also in line with the emerging&#13;
demographic trends--more women taking up careers, single parent households,&#13;
and indeed single person households.&#13;
Another aspect of processing is the extent to which it has&#13;
influenced the consumption of a starchy staple--the potato. By 1960,&#13;
potato consumption had declined to about 55 percent of the 1909 level.&#13;
Then came potato chips and frozen French fries and other potato snacks.&#13;
Not only was the decline arrested, but overall potato consumption has&#13;
actually been increasing in the '70s (though this is not reflected in&#13;
Fig.5).&#13;
Over time there has been an increasing tendency to eat away from&#13;
home. In 1980, 27 percent of all food expenditures were made outside the&#13;
home as compared with 20 percent in 1960-61. And there is scope for&#13;
further increases--the top income-quintile spent as much 37 percent of the&#13;
food budget on 'away meals' in 1972-73. Apart from rising incomes, other&#13;
factors that explain this trend are greater the greater the proportion of&#13;
working mothers and single person households.&#13;
Disaggregating the separate influence of changing incomes and&#13;
prices, changing household size, composition and age of the population on&#13;
these consumption patterns is a major task and will not be attempted here.&#13;
The interested reader is referred to Burk (1951 and 1961), George and King&#13;
(1971), Houthakker and Taylor (1970), and Nino-Gajardo (1977), for&#13;
authoritative reviews of the subject.&#13;
However, another important issue will be probed here: Is it&#13;
reasonable to expect that price and income changes will have very little&#13;
effect on food consumption patterns in the U.S. After all, the budget&#13;
share of food has reached such low levels--16 percent of disposable income&#13;
on food, and 1.7 percent on starchy staples--that income and price&#13;
elasticities should be expected to be very low.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-55-&#13;
a)&#13;
CN~~~~~&#13;
U)                                                              0      -~~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
OU)&#13;
0- ~ ~  ~   ~   i   0&#13;
0                                                           -o~~~~~~~~ &#13;
&gt;-                 0&#13;
CO.                                                             0                 0      f&#13;
cl                                                        c~~~~~~~~~~~~~~c&#13;
(L                    .......- a   0.......                                     0&#13;
*0-&#13;
0)                                                               C~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
(N          CO~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-56-&#13;
The underlying logic of this argument would liken food to a&#13;
commodity like common salt. Salt can be consumed only up to a limit, and&#13;
since it is cheap, saturation levels are reached at fairly low levels of&#13;
income. Thus neither income nor price changes significantly affect the&#13;
quantity of salt consumed. Similarly, food consumption has reached its&#13;
limits, whether measured in volume, weight or calories. In a rich society,&#13;
by definition the food price is low compared with income.     Since saturation&#13;
levels have already been reached at much lower levels of income, changes in&#13;
price and income will not affect the quantity of food consumed. Therefore,&#13;
the argument would conclude, calorie levels should be independent of price&#13;
and income changes.&#13;
The evidence certainly seems to back this up--caloric levels in&#13;
the U.S. seem to be impervious to changes in income or prices.&#13;
Table 19: TRENDS IN PROCESSED FOODS&#13;
1910-19   1930-39   1950-59  1970-74&#13;
Commodity                              -----------------% ----------------&#13;
1) Processed Fruits share&#13;
in total fruits                    17        24        48         61&#13;
2) Processed Vegetables share&#13;
in total vegetables                33*       34         50        56&#13;
* Refers to 1920-29. Figure for 1910-19 was not available.&#13;
Source: See Table 16.&#13;
The next question to ask is whether this 'income and price&#13;
rigidity' extends to food categories.    In other words, is it possible that&#13;
own-price, cross-price, and income elasticities for food categories are&#13;
also negligible or close to zero? The qualitative evidence available&#13;
suggests that is is so. The following examples are drawn from the sharp&#13;
economic dislocations of 1972-74.&#13;
i) when prices of cereals rose, consumers did not reduce the&#13;
quantities that they consumed, they merely switched to buying&#13;
items that had a good deal less value-added.&#13;
ii) and, the restaurant industry's performance was a classic&#13;
illustration of&#13;
...the extent to which consumers were willing to trade down but&#13;
not give up the conveniences they had come to expect in&#13;
food consumption. Fast food restaurant chains&#13;
continued to achieve record sales levels in 1973-74,&#13;
when meat prices were going up rapidly, and also in&#13;
1974-75, when incomes were declining. A medium-priced,&#13;
high-quality restaurant chain experienced the same&#13;
thing. Its sales increased rapidly in 1974-75, as&#13;
consumers traded down from the higher-priced French&#13;
restaurants. (Paarlberg, ed., 1977, p.143)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-57-&#13;
This suggests that prices and incomes do have an impact, but that&#13;
impact is primarily on the quality (or price paid) of the food purchased,&#13;
not on the quantity. In other words, the 'substitution effect' on quantity&#13;
is negligible, and the 'income effect' operates primarily through changes&#13;
in the quality of food. Thus there is little change in the quantity&#13;
consumed of each food category.&#13;
It must be pointed out that the validity of this hypothesis&#13;
depends pivotally on how broadly or narrowly food categories are defined.&#13;
If categories are defined as broadly as, e.g., meat, dairy products and&#13;
foodgrains, then own- and cross-price elasticities would both be very&#13;
low--that is, quantities would be rigid.&#13;
On the other hand, if the meat category is broken up into beef,&#13;
pork, and poultry, and dairy products into eggs, butter, cheese, etc., then&#13;
own-price elasticities can be quite substantial. This can be seen in Table&#13;
20 which presents George and King's (1971) estimates. At the same time,&#13;
cross-elasticities among categories as well as income elasticities are&#13;
quite small. This suggests that the 'rigidity hypothesis' tends to lose&#13;
validity as the level of disaggregation becomes finer, and it seems to have&#13;
greater validity for income-elasticities than for own price elasticities.&#13;
Thus the general assertion can be made that as incomes rise, own&#13;
price and income elasticities will tend to decline with the latter&#13;
declining faster than the former. This is, of course, another way of&#13;
stating that with increasing incomes, the level of category disaggregation&#13;
at which high elasticities will be observed will go up. To take a specific&#13;
example, as incomes rise, (assuming tastes remain the same), the price and&#13;
income elasticity for beef will tend to decrease, and significant&#13;
elasticities will be observable only at the level of steaks and&#13;
hamburgers. At still higher levels of income, the substitutions will take&#13;
place between prime grade steak and choice grade steak. And so on.&#13;
As a matter of fact, the most important changes taking place in&#13;
the American diet today have little to do with incomes or prices. They are&#13;
the result of a combination of fads and fashions, as well as growing&#13;
awareness of the link between foods and diseases. The 'rediscovery' of the&#13;
potato, the proliferation of 'all natural' foods, the recent reduction in&#13;
the consumption of beef, and the movement away from excessive salt and&#13;
sugar, are some examples of this.&#13;
This raises an interesting, and important, question: Will the&#13;
middle- and low-income countries follow the American experience in toto or&#13;
will they learn from it and reject outright some of the medically harmful&#13;
aspects of the American diet. As the next chapter shows, the evidence&#13;
seems to be stacked in favor of the former.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-58-&#13;
E  Oh - u n -   0 0  InO 0   N&#13;
o 1  On  OD   CD  c o-Ooeo o  Ine&#13;
e  NLA.-LAtE- 0O VLON NONO- N&#13;
O- N  n 00 0 0a 0000g0&#13;
LA      Ili   . Li9 -  4&#13;
*. uo -c -        00 gE-&#13;
_  O  OO  -  8  o,  8 8 oD o  o.°&#13;
0  ci C ~ ~ ~ 0  V&#13;
0&#13;
A  I PA n m eo  NN  O   0 0IA&#13;
to  o  ol r. ol p  r- 0   W% % o  oou  u &#13;
_      i 9 O  O   -1NOr-LAe 0CLAN  C 0.&#13;
:..  0000000000000 0 C_&#13;
o R     e  - %D W%  -   g e  o&#13;
0     00-  0- - N O   WI O   C!&#13;
L~ ~~ O C OOO  O O O C   i &#13;
L.  9  i9 .I.- &#13;
m oCo oo oo 000000  CL&#13;
co 08&#13;
Ci,      0  OC. N ~ L 0 ~ O O  Oe  _oN  KO  L  C&#13;
1-       C  0  00000000     0&#13;
V)       0  O     a O O O O&gt; O   0 0 0  'AO&#13;
C L&#13;
o          &gt; o o S sD - e o X &gt; et  N O O  _ X0a&#13;
wi       L  gO-f1~~ (Cs 0'IAN0 0  -12&#13;
J.-      L  O U-  N  -  0  NCIA  -  -e N C -  4-&#13;
a  o  O  O  O  O  O O e00 80 o&#13;
OCCCCCCC CD C O  0  OV&#13;
OD  N  N  = 1UO UN  W I I o&#13;
z        60  8     3 _&#13;
In       cC ... ......   ..&#13;
F     O ~~~~co oaoo o o o o o o o oo  o '&#13;
8        c  00000000 n 0 0 0  N O  0 0 0 0   0  0 0&#13;
o       0                IC NIuo Icm  0  e  o  C&gt; O  -&#13;
0 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ -&#13;
IL      0-  0O- o8OA Q ~ 0 o  C oooON N  _&#13;
L  00 OcOO    0 0O&#13;
U..                   C~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
O      -3C   0C,0  0 0  C0  4-&#13;
i           .  . ...  .  9  . ..  I  a&#13;
o ~  ~~ o OC O O O O O   C oooooo  l to&#13;
2    e   N - e ~~~0 -N N % D N  WN -a W%  - D &#13;
t O O-OOONO t-  O iOOn  OnO-  &#13;
I~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~I.&#13;
e     W c  o o  o on on in  (7o e o o  oOO &#13;
v7        I r- &#13;
U Q   C.  ff10 %9-N0iOmL  0 P0  10&#13;
U- C. ~~  8888S8~~9  000008  4-+1&#13;
0                        OOrOCO CONO  0  V0&#13;
_ ~ ~~~         ~  ~~~~~~~~ 9 9  lc 9  fo &#13;
_ c e so O f N 1~-n U  e N  W% 0 O-&#13;
_   C        10-0L e N  0 on 1-  VN U, 0 0&#13;
GOOOO -  OA  -  -N  10O  -  O - - &#13;
0000C;ololo 0 a 0   C&#13;
O_      ON1  0 0 0  0    0 0  °  &#13;
OQC            ..          . .0.....s................... D@2&#13;
U    C OOOCO O 0 01 0 0 0 0  0  0  0   0  0  0&#13;
c       ~~C0L&#13;
0        A U    c     04--)&#13;
0  C          InC '&#13;
w-  _    0 I 00'e° h A 0)  _ N_ NW  L 0 $  O &#13;
tWE .0   4-  LA10NIt AO  OOO -  N  -NE 0--&#13;
..     ~O O ON OO OO OO OO O OO  C 03 &#13;
_0      1.  N00  0'  N C 0 -  Q  -  VNL   C &#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~O1  0F1 0  - O000 0 0000  _2&#13;
000...............  X&#13;
~~~~~~~~~ o0)- ooooooo ,o &#13;
I  c           0-IA&#13;
|         * N  S~~C&#13;
f   Y      X~~~~~~ L&#13;
O + C F   Y  O a c0 uLv0' _)0 V &#13;
0  .0 A 00- 8 -      2: V  1 &#13;
S cc 000000000000000L  n ^  _c   o &#13;
n~~              IIo m  1wm &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-59-&#13;
X.     IMPLICATIONS OF AFFLUENT CONSUMPTION PATTERNS&#13;
The spread of affluence and the accompanying shifts in dietary&#13;
patterns, most acutely represented in the United States but now well&#13;
established in most of the developing world, have two important&#13;
implications. First, considerable alarm has been expressed over the&#13;
long-run health consequences of the American diet, with its high&#13;
concentration of refined sugar, saturated fats, and cholesterol, and&#13;
relative lack of dietary fiber, fresh fruits and vegetables. The alarm has&#13;
sometimes spilled over to hysteria, and innocent visitors from the&#13;
developing world are often shocked to find that many of the foods to which&#13;
their people aspire are treated as poisons by friends and the press in the&#13;
United States.&#13;
It cannot be denied that the relationship between diet and&#13;
disease is complicated and insufficiently understood scientifically for&#13;
government policy to play an active role in the promotion or discouragement&#13;
of different foods or dietary patterns. At the same time, many&#13;
well-informed and health-conscious citizens are making private judgements&#13;
about the evidence and are altering their entire life-styles with the&#13;
expectation of significant benefits to health and well-being. As evidence&#13;
accumulates that validates such decisions, and that is certainly the trend&#13;
of scientific results over the past thirty years, an important dilemma will&#13;
be faced by policy makers in developed countries.&#13;
...society's interest in this decision extends beyond&#13;
humanitarian concern. Even if sufficient information&#13;
were available to indicate the probable benefits of the&#13;
'good' life-style, many in society will continue to&#13;
choose the 'poor' life-style for a variety of personal&#13;
reasons. Although the individual who chooses the 'poor'&#13;
lifestyle pays part of the costs through more chronic&#13;
disease and higher medical costs, not all of such costs&#13;
are private. Society pays an important share of such&#13;
costs through losses in productivity of workers and&#13;
through partial public financing of medical costs.&#13;
That is, there is a strong investment in the&#13;
individual's 'lifestyle' decision, and some mechanism&#13;
is needed to reconcile the difference between private&#13;
and public costs and benefits to alternative dietary&#13;
lifestyle decisions. (Timmer and Nesheim, p.168)&#13;
Such concerns seem a far cry from the hunger and calorie deficits&#13;
so prevalent in the developing countries. But many countries, especially&#13;
those which have emerged recently into middle-income status, seem intent on&#13;
achieving American-style diets as soon as possible. Thus, the second&#13;
implementation of affluent diets is their possible international economic&#13;
repercussions if extended widely to the rapidly emerging middle-class&#13;
households of the third world. Apart from any potential health concerns,&#13;
the grain resources needed to provide such diets are an issue of&#13;
considerable importance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-60-&#13;
The earlier econometric estimates of animal protein income&#13;
elasticities (chapter II) showed how vigorous the desire is for meat&#13;
products in developing countries. For particular meats, especially beef,&#13;
that desire remains strong even in the richer countries, as is shown in&#13;
Table 21. The income elasticity for beef is more than 0.6 in the European&#13;
community, is 0.7 in Mexico and Central America, and is 1.2 in Japan, where&#13;
extremely high prices make beef a luxury good even at present levels of per&#13;
capita incomes.&#13;
The implication of these large income elasticities for meat can&#13;
be seen in table 22, which reports both direct grain consumption per capita&#13;
and indirect grain consumed by feeding livestock, for a variety of&#13;
countries from the United States to India. Despite direct grain intake in&#13;
the United States of about half the Indian level, total grain consumed is&#13;
4.5 times as large as India's total grain consumption per capita--646 kg&#13;
per year versus 143.&#13;
The ramifications on world grain markets of 'follower' countries&#13;
adopting American-style diets and the indirect grain demand implicit in&#13;
them are staggering. If all the countries from Japan and below in Table 22&#13;
were to reach the average level of grain consumed in the United Kingdom and&#13;
Germany (340 kg per capita per year, a figure only slightly more than half&#13;
the United States level), more than 300 million metric tons of additional&#13;
grain would be needed, a figure equal to one-fifth of global grain&#13;
production. Even excluding both India and the People's Republic of China&#13;
from the calculation leaves an added grain demand of more than 60 million&#13;
metric tons, more than one-quarter of world grain trade in recent years.&#13;
If income growth proceeds rapidly in these countries, and they&#13;
are fast growers in historical terms, the derived demand for grain through&#13;
increased meat consumption will be the major force determining the balance&#13;
of supply and demand in world grain markets. Failure of income to grow&#13;
rapidly will depress demand and could lead to significant grain surpluses&#13;
in years of good harvests. But a combination of vigorous economic growth&#13;
around the world with a poor harvest in the United States would see the&#13;
supply-demand balance tighten and prices rise to allocate supplies to those&#13;
most willing to pay.&#13;
Here then is the dilema of affluent diets for the direct grain&#13;
consumers of the poorest countries. The demand for meat in the middle- and&#13;
upper-income countries determines the international market price not only&#13;
for feedgrains (which many poor people consume directly as well) but also&#13;
for wheat and rice. Through the feedgrain-livestock-meat connection, the&#13;
diets of the poor and the rich are linked.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-61-&#13;
Table 21: DEMAND ELASTICITIES FOR MEAT&#13;
Elasticity with respect to price of&#13;
Income&#13;
Item                      Beef          Pork       Poultry        Elasticity&#13;
United States:&#13;
Beef                     -.7           .1            .1              .4&#13;
Pork                      .4          -.8            .1              .1&#13;
Poultry                   .3           .2          -1.0              .8&#13;
Canada:&#13;
Beef                     -.6           .3            .15             .7&#13;
Pork                      .4          -.7            .15             .15&#13;
Poultry                   .3           .2           -.8              .9&#13;
EC-6:&#13;
Beef                     -.7           .3            .1              .6&#13;
Pork                      .5          -.8            .12             .5&#13;
Poultry                   .38          .5          -1.07            1.0&#13;
EC-3:&#13;
Beef                     -.6           .2            .08              .7&#13;
Pork                      .18         -.8            .2               .45&#13;
Poultry                   .3           .3           -.6             1.0&#13;
Other Western&#13;
Europe:&#13;
Beef                     -.6           .2            .1              .7&#13;
Pork                      .2          -.7            .2              .6&#13;
Poultry                   .1           .2           -.8              .9&#13;
Japan:&#13;
Beef                    -1.2           .26           .35            1.2&#13;
Pork                      .20         -.90           .11             .9&#13;
Poultry                   .50          .17         -1.10             .6&#13;
Mexico and&#13;
Central America:&#13;
Beef                     -.4           .1                            .7&#13;
Pork                      .1          -.3                            .6&#13;
Brazil:&#13;
Beef                     -.6           .3                             .4&#13;
Pork                      .2          -.6                            .4&#13;
Source: ESCS, USDA, FAER No. 146, Washington, D.C., April 1978, p. 88.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-62-&#13;
Table 22:  ANNUAL PER CAPITA GRAIN CONSUMPTION IN SELECTED COUNTRIES&#13;
1975-1977 Average&#13;
Total Grain&#13;
Consumed&#13;
Grain         Grain                        as multiple&#13;
Consumed      Consumed       Total Grain    of India's&#13;
Directly      Indirectly        consumed    Consumption&#13;
(kgs)         (kgs)            (kgs)&#13;
USA                       63             583             646            4.5&#13;
USSR                     141             444             585            4.1&#13;
Argentina                100             275             375             2.6&#13;
Germany                   67             288             355            2.5&#13;
U.K.                      71             254             325             2.3&#13;
Japan                    132             144             276             1.9&#13;
Korea                    199              54             253             1.8&#13;
Brazil                    91             124             215             1.5&#13;
China                    156              52             208             1.5&#13;
Philippines              131              35             166             1.2&#13;
Indonesdia               142              10             152             1.1&#13;
India                    128              15             143             1.0&#13;
Note:  Grain Consumed Indirectly is not corrected for imports and exports&#13;
of meat and poultry.&#13;
Source: FAO, Food Balance Sheets, 1975-1977.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-63-&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
1) Austin, J. E. et al. 1976. "Urban Malnutrition - Problem Assessment&#13;
and Intervention Guidelines". Washington, D.C.:The World Bank.&#13;
2) Bennett, M. K. 1954. "The World's Food". New York: Harper &amp;&#13;
Brothers. p. 114.&#13;
3) Burk, M. C. 1951. "Changes in the Demand for Food from 1941 to&#13;
1950". Journal of Farm Economics.&#13;
4) Burk, M. C. 1961. "Trends and Patterns in U.S. Food Consumption".&#13;
Economic and Statistical Analysis Division, AH-214, USDA.&#13;
Washington, D.C.: U.S. Government Printing Office.&#13;
5) Food and Agricultural Organization. 1957. "Factors influencing the&#13;
Trend of Food Consumption". The State of Food and Agriculture.&#13;
Rome. pp.95 and 104.&#13;
6) Food and Agricultural Organization. 1977. "The Fourth Food Survey".&#13;
FAO Statistics Series No. 11. Rome.&#13;
7) Food and Agricultural Organization. 1980. "Food Balance Sheets,&#13;
1975-77". Rome.&#13;
8) Geissler, C. and Miller, D. August 1982. "Nutrition and GNP - A&#13;
Comparison of Problems in Thailand and the Philippines". Food&#13;
Policy, pp. 191-206.&#13;
9) George, P.S., and King, G.A. 1971. "Consumer Demand for Food&#13;
Commodities in the United States with Projections for 1980".&#13;
Monograph No. 26. Berkeley: Giannini Foundation of Agricultural&#13;
Economics.&#13;
10) Gifft, H.H., Washborn, M.B., and Harrison, G.G. 1972. "Nutrition&#13;
Behavior and Change". New Jersey: Prentice-Hall, Inc.&#13;
11)  Houthakker, H.S. July 1957.    "An International Comparison of Household&#13;
Expenditure Patterens, commemorating the Centenary of Engel's Law".&#13;
Econometrica, 25:532-551.&#13;
12) Houthakker, H.S. and Taylor, L.D. 1970. "Consumer Demand in the&#13;
United States: Analysis and Projections". Cambridge: Harvard&#13;
University Press.&#13;
13) Houthakker, H.S. and Prais, S.J. 1971. "The Analysis of Family&#13;
Budgets". Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.&#13;
14) International Labor Office. 1977. "Household Income and Expenditure&#13;
Statistics, No. 2, 1960-1972, Africa, Asia, Latin America". Geneva.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-64-&#13;
15)  International Labor Office.    1979.  "Yearbook of Labor Statistics".&#13;
Geneva.&#13;
16) Knudsen, O.K. and Scandizzo, P.L. 1982. "The Demand for Calories in&#13;
Developing Countries". American Journal of Agricultural Economics.&#13;
Vol. 64, No. 1.&#13;
17) Kravis, I.B. Heston, A. and Summers, R. 1982. "World Product and&#13;
Income - International Comparisons of Real Gross Product".&#13;
Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins University Press.&#13;
18) Nino-Gajardo, J. 1977. "Food Consumption Patterns in U.S.A. - An&#13;
Application of the Houthakker and Taylor Dynamic Demand Model".&#13;
Stanford University, Food Research Institute: Dissertation.&#13;
19) Paarlberg, D. (ed.) 1977. "Food and Agricultural Policy". Remarks by&#13;
K.J. Fedor. Washington, D.C.: American Enterprise Institute for&#13;
Public Policy Research, p.143.&#13;
20) Reutlinger, S. and Selowsky, M. 1976. "Malnutrition and Poverty".&#13;
Washington, D.C.: The World Bank, Occ. paper no. 23.&#13;
21) Reutlinger, S. and Alderman, H. 1980. "The Prevalence of&#13;
Calorie-Deficient Diets in Developing Countries". Washington, D.C.:&#13;
World Development, 8:399-411.&#13;
22) Thomson, A.M. 1974. "A Cross-Country Analysis of Changing Nutrition&#13;
Patterns". Stanford: Food Research Institute Studies, Vol. XIII,&#13;
3:275-284.&#13;
23) Timmer, C.P. and Nesheim, M.C. 1978. "National Farm Summit Task Force&#13;
Report on Nutrition Product Quality, and Safety", p.168.&#13;
24) Timmer, C.P. 1979. "Food Prices and Food Policy Analysis in LDCs".&#13;
Presented at the World Food Policy Seminar. Boston: Harvard&#13;
Business School.&#13;
25) Timmer, C.P. 1981. "Is there "Curvature" in the Slutsky Matrix?" The&#13;
Review of Economics and Statistics. Vol. LXIII, 3:395-402.&#13;
26) Timmer, C.P., Falcon, W.P., and Pearson, S.R. 1983. Food Policy&#13;
Analysis. Johns Hopkins University Press for The World Bank.&#13;
27) Weisskoff, R. 1971. "Demand Elasticities for a Developing Economy:&#13;
An International Comparison of Consumption Patterns", in Chenery,&#13;
H.B. (ed.) 1971. "Studies in Development Planning". Cambridge:&#13;
Harvard University Press, p.330.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG3881.5 .W57 W67 no.785 c.3&#13;
Chaudhri, Rajiv, 1957-&#13;
The impact of changing&#13;
affluence on diet and demand&#13;
patterns for agricultural&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                          European Office               Tokyo Office&#13;
1818 H Street, N W                    66, avenue d'lena             Kokusai Building&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S A         75116 Paris, France           1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone (202) 477-1234              Telephone. (1) 47.23.54 21    Chyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japane&#13;
Telex WUI 64145 WORLDBANK             Telex. 842-620628             Telephone (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                            Telex 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
a_&#13;
C&#13;
c&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0683-9&#13;
C&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554681">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1986/01/1554681/impacts-changing-affluence-diets-demand-patterns-agricultural-commodities
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1986/01/1554681/impacts-changing-affluence-diets-demand-patterns-agricultural-commodities</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1986/01/1554681/impacts-changing-affluence-diets-demand-patterns-agricultural-commodities</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/02/000178830_98101903434247/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/02/000178830_98101903434247/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1986-01-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-08-02T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The impacts of changing affluence on diets
            and demand patterns for agricultural commodities
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Part I of this report uses cross country
            data to examine the relationship between income and broad
            expenditure categories and the implications of this
            relationship for nutritional status. The focus is on intake
            of calories and proteins rather than food expenditures, and
            on how these are determined by incomes and prices. Part II
            examines domestic data for different categories of food
            expenditures such as cereals, vegetables, meat, milk
            products, etc. Five major independent variables are
            identified - household incomes, prices, household size and
            composition, urbanization, and social factors. Part III
            looks at two other related issues: (i) the implications for
            nutritional status of affluent food consumption patterns;
            and (ii) the implications for the world food system of the
            derived demand for grain arising from increased meat
            consumption in the rapidly growing middle-income countries.
            Part IV presents the conclusions, which emphasize the need
            for an approach to food policy that balance both the
            consumption and production aspects of the food sector and
            integrates the various policy instruments available in an
            internally consistent fashion to achieve that balance.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The impacts of changing affluence on diets
            and demand patterns for agricultural commodities
        </docna>
        <display_title>The impacts of changing affluence
            on diets and demand patterns for agricultural commodities</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1986/01/1554681/impacts-changing-affluence-diets-demand-patterns-agricultural-commodities</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Poverty Lines,Inequality,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Consumption</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Chaudhri, R.</author>
            <author>Timmer, C.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903434247</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Other agriculture</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 785</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Agriculture, fishing, and forestry</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0683-9</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Agricultural products; Data analysis; Diet;
            Food consumption; Food policy; Food preferences; Nutrition
            status; Commodities
            agriculture,average income,Caloric
            Intake,caloric requirements,calorie intake,consumer
            groups,consumers,consumption expenditure,consumption
            levels,Consumption Patterns,Consumption Per
            Capita,cross-country data,data set,data sets,demand
            analysis,devaluation,developed countries,developing
            countries,developing country context,development
            strategy,differences in income,domestic consumption,domestic
            demand,economic development,economic factors,economic
            growth,economists,Elasticity,empirical analysis,empirical
            evidence,empirical work,employment,equilibrium,exchange
            rate,Expenditure Data,expenditures,explanatory
            power,exports,fish,Food consumption,Food Consumption
            Patterns,food expenditure,food expenditures,food intake,food
            items,food prices,foreign exchange,functional
            form,functional forms,Geographic Area,GNP,GNP per
            capita,Grain Consumption,household characteristics,Household
            Income,household incomes,household size,household
            surveys,imports,income,income differences,income
            distribution,income elasticity,income groups,income
            levels,income rises,income transfer,individual
            countries,inflation,interest rates,international
            comparisons,LDCs,less developed countries,living
            standards,logging,low income,macro policy,macroeconomic
            policy,marginal propensity to consume,mean value,minimum
            wages,national income,nutritional status,overvalued exchange
            rate,overvalued exchange rates,Per Capita Consumption,per
            capita income,per capita income levels,per capita
            incomes,personal income,policy decisions,policy
            instruments,policy interventions,policy makers,policy
            reform,poor countries,poor people,positive effects,power
            parity,price changes,Price Elasticities,price
            elasticity,Price increases,price subsidies,prices
            change,producers,purchasing,purchasing power,rapid
            growth,real GDP,real income,regression analysis,Relative
            Importance,relative price,relative prices,resource use,rural
            areas,Sales,savings,securities,series data,standard
            errors,statistical analysis,substitution effect,substitution
            elasticities,tariff barriers,terms of trade,time series,undervaluation,unemployment,wages
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP785</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Community Based Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Raising Awareness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Econometrics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Price Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Food Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>