<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Alternative Mechanisms tor&#13;
Financing Social Security&#13;
Parthasarathi Shome     SWP625&#13;
Lyn Squire            W   P625&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 625&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 625&#13;
Alternative Mechanisms foir&#13;
Financing Social Security&#13;
Parthasarathi Shome&#13;
Lyn Squire&#13;
INTERNATIONAL MONETARY FUND&#13;
JOINT LIBRARY&#13;
[AR 2', 1984&#13;
iTiOTRMTIONAL BANK FOR&#13;
r:E :;STEm'jCTI0 Ari D D.IJELOPREMIT&#13;
N*AR1!1!!'GTC1N, D.,C. 29t91&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright © 1983&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development / THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
First printing November 1983&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To&#13;
present the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has&#13;
not been prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal&#13;
printed texts, and the World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The&#13;
publication is supplied at a token charge to defray part of the cost of&#13;
manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to&#13;
any individual acting on their behalf. Any maps used have been prepared&#13;
solely for the convenience of the readers; the denominations used and the&#13;
boundaries shown do not imply, on the part of the World Bank and its affiliates,&#13;
any judgment on the legal status of any territory or any endorsement or&#13;
acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of World Bank publications is described in the Catalog of World&#13;
Bank Publications; the continuing research program of the Bank is outlined in&#13;
World Bank Research Program: Abstracts of Current Studies. Both booklets are&#13;
updated annually; the most recent edition of each is available without charge&#13;
from the Publications Sales Unit of the Bank in Washington or from the&#13;
European Office of the Bank, 66, avenue d'Iena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Parthasarathi Shome is an economist in the Fiscal Affairs Department of the&#13;
International Monetary Fund; Lyn Squire is chief of the Resource Mobilization&#13;
and Public Management Division in the Country Policy Department of the&#13;
World Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data&#13;
Shome, Parthasarathi, 1950-&#13;
Alternative mechanisms for financing social security.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 625)&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
1. Social security--Finance--Mathematical models.&#13;
2. Capital--Mathematical models. 3. Labor supply--&#13;
Mathematical models.     I. Squire, Lyn, 1946-&#13;
II. Title. III. Series.&#13;
HD7091.S398    1983        35182 '56           83-23510&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0292-2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ABSTRACT&#13;
This paper provides a review, clarification, and extension of the&#13;
theoretical literature concerning the effect of social security on capital&#13;
accumulation and labor supply. Within a framework of overlapping generations,&#13;
the paper reviews the theoretical results regarding the impact of bcth pay-as-&#13;
you-go financed and fully-funded schemes. Relevant empirical studies using&#13;
U.S. data are also reviewed. The paper also analyzes the characteristics of&#13;
optimal social security systems.&#13;
A major part of the paper is concerned with the oeutrality or non-&#13;
neutrality of social security's impact on capital accumulat:ion and labor&#13;
supply. While it is generally agreed that a fully-funded system is neutral,&#13;
views differ significantly on the issue of neutrality under a pay-as-you-go&#13;
system. The analysis presented in the paper demonstrates that these differences&#13;
arise from two assumptions. The first requires that, in providing bequests,&#13;
those in the older generation must focus on net (i.e., net of all other inter-&#13;
generational flows including those arising from the social security system)&#13;
bequests rather than gross bequests. The second requires that the representative&#13;
individual be aware of the government's budget constraint. If these two assump-&#13;
tions are met, a pay-as-you-go social security system is neutral. If either&#13;
assumption is unfulfilled, the system will affect behavior. In particular, if&#13;
the second assumption is not met, social security will affect capital accumula-&#13;
tion (a dynamic effect) and will also introduce a distortion into the labor&#13;
market (a static effect).&#13;
The second major part of the paper is concerned with normative&#13;
issues. It contrasts the standard procedure of equating optimality to the&#13;
maximization of a representative individual's utility function with an approach&#13;
which rationalizes the need for social security by reference to a paternalistic&#13;
concern for the welfare of the retired population. It is shown that with a&#13;
paternalistic motivation, a fully-funded system can be used to move the economy&#13;
towards its social optimum whereas a pay-as-you-go system moves the economy&#13;
away from its optimal path. These results reverse the conclusions in the&#13;
literature where the focus has been exclusively on private utility maximization.&#13;
The paper provides a starting point for anyone interested in assess-&#13;
ing the relevance of the existing theoretical literature for social security&#13;
issues in developing countries. These issues are already important in Latin&#13;
America and are also becoming important in some Asian countries. At present,&#13;
most of the theoretical literature captures characterist:Lcs more akin to those&#13;
of developed countries. Nevertheless, the existing approaches have the&#13;
advantage of capturing both static and dynamic effects, a very important&#13;
consideration in the analysis of an instrument that can be expected to influence&#13;
static resource allocation through the labor market and the dynamics of growth&#13;
through capital accumulation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- iv -&#13;
ABSTRAIT&#13;
Le document ci-apres vise a analyser, preciser et developper les tra-&#13;
vaux theoriques ant6rieurs concernant l'effet de l'assurance vieillesse sur&#13;
l'accumulation de capital et l'offre de main-d'oeuvre. Au moyen d'un modele a&#13;
g6nerations multiples, on etudie les effets theoriques des systemes fonctionnant&#13;
selon le principe de la repartition d'une part, et des systemes a capitalisation&#13;
integrale, d'autre part. On examine egalement des etudes empiriques pertinentes&#13;
utilisant des donnees des Etats-Unis. On analyse aussi les caracteristiques des&#13;
regimes d'assurance vieillesse optimaux.&#13;
Une grande partie du document est consacree a la neutralit6 ou a la&#13;
non-neutralite des effets de l'assurance vieillesse sur l'accumulation de capi-&#13;
tal et l'offre de main-d'oeuvre. On s'accorde generalement a penser qu'un&#13;
regime a capitalisation integrale est neutre, mais les avis sont tres partages&#13;
pour ce qui est du systeme de la repartition. L'analyse presentee demontre que&#13;
ces differences decoulent de deux hypotheses de travail. Selon la premiere, en&#13;
accordant des legs, la g6neration la plus ancienne doit considerer les legs nets&#13;
(c'est-&amp;-dire nets de tous autres flux intergenerations, y compris les flux pro-&#13;
venant du regime d'assurance vieillesse) plutot que sur les legs bruts. Selon&#13;
la deuxieme hypothese, l'individu representatif doit avoir conscience des con-&#13;
traintes du budget de l'Etat. Si ces deux hypotheses sont verifiees, les&#13;
regimes a repartition sont neutres. Si l'une ou l'autre des deux hypoth6ses ne&#13;
l'est pas, le regime influe sur le comportement. En.particulier, si la deuxieme&#13;
hypothese n'est pas verifiee, l'assurance vieillesse influe sur l'accumulation&#13;
de capital (effet dynamique) et introduit une distorsion sur le marche du&#13;
travail (effet statique).&#13;
La deuxieme grande partie du document est consacree a des questions&#13;
normatives. Elle oppose la methode habituelle consistant a definir l'optimalit6&#13;
comme etant la maximisation de la fonction d'utilit6 d'un individu representatif&#13;
a une approche qui fonde la necessite de la securite sociale sur le souci pater-&#13;
naliste du bien-&amp;tre de la population retraitee. Il est demontre que dans une&#13;
perspective paternaliste, la capitalisation integrale peut contribuer a rap-&#13;
procher l'6conomie de son optimum collectif, tandis que la repartition l'en&#13;
eloigne. Ces resultats vont a l'encontre des conclusions auxquelles parviennent&#13;
les chercheurs qui se concentrent exclusivement sur la maximisation de l'utilit6&#13;
individuelle.&#13;
Le document ci-apres peut fournir idn point de d6part a ceux qui cher-&#13;
chent a evaluer dans quelle mesure les travaux de recherche th6oriques qui ont&#13;
ete faits sur les questions d'assurance vieillesse sont applicables dans les&#13;
pays en developpement. Cas questions sont deja importantes en Amerique latine&#13;
at commencent a se poser dans certains pays d'Asie. A l'heure actuelle, la&#13;
plupart des travaux traitent plut6t de caract6ristiques apparentees a celles&#13;
qu'on observe dans les pays developpes. Neanmoins, les methodes actuelles pr6-&#13;
sentent l'avantage de saisir a la fois les effets statiques et dynamiques, ce&#13;
qui n'est pas a dedaigner lorsqu'on analyse un instrument qui a des chances&#13;
d'influer sur l'affectation statique des ressources par l'intermediaire du mar-&#13;
chi du travail, et sur la dynamique de la croissance, par le biais de l'accumu-&#13;
lation de capital.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
EXTRACTO&#13;
En este documento se examina, clarifica y amplia la literatura te6rica&#13;
relativa a los efectos de los planes de seguridad social en la acumulaci6n de&#13;
capital y la disponibilidad de mano de obra. Dentro de un marco de generaciones&#13;
superpuestas, se examinan en 6l los resultados te6ricos relativos al efecto de&#13;
los sistemas de transferencia inmediata (pay-as-you-g_) y de financiamiento&#13;
pleno (fully-funded). Tambien se examinan estudios empiricos pertinentes que&#13;
utilizan datos relativos a los Estados Unidos. Ademn&amp;s se analizan las&#13;
caracteristicas de los sistemas 6ptimos de seguridad social.&#13;
Una parte importante del documento se refiere a la neutralidad o falta&#13;
de neutralidad de los efectos del seguro social en la acumulaci6n de capital y&#13;
la disponibilidad de mano de obra. Si bien en general hay acuerdo en que un&#13;
sistema de financiamiento pleno es neutro, las opiniones diEieren ampliamente&#13;
con respecto a la neutralidad en el de transferencia inmediata. El an&amp;lisis que&#13;
aqui se presenta demuestra que estas diferencias surgen de dos supuestos. El&#13;
primero requiere que al proporcionar donaciones las personas mayores se&#13;
concentren en las donaciones netas (es decir, deducidas todas las demas&#13;
corrientes intergeneracionales que incluyen las que: surgen del sistema de&#13;
seguridad social) mas bien que en donaciones brutas. El segundo supuesto&#13;
requiere que el individuo representativo este consciente de las limitaciones&#13;
presupuestarias del gobierno.   Si los dos supuestos se cumplen, el sistema de&#13;
seguridad social de transferencia inxmediata es neutro. Si no se cumple uno de&#13;
ellos, el sistema afectara al comportamiento. En especial, si no se cumple el&#13;
segundo supuesto, el seguro social afectara a la acumulaci6n de capital (efecto&#13;
dinamico) y tambien introducira distorsiones en el mercado laboral (efecto&#13;
estatico).&#13;
La segunda parte principal del documento se refiere a cuestiones&#13;
normativas. Se contrasta el procedimiento est&amp;ndarc de igualar lo 6ptimo con la&#13;
maximizaci6n de la funci6n de utilidad de un individuo representativo empleando&#13;
un enfoque en el que se racionaliza la necesidad de la seguridad social con&#13;
referencia a una preocupaci6n paternalista por el bienestar de la poblaci6n&#13;
jubilada. Se demuestra que, con una motivaci6n paternalista, un sistema de&#13;
financiamiento pleno puede utilizarse para llevar la economia hacia su grado&#13;
social 6ptimo, en tanto que el sistema de transferencia inmediata aleja a la&#13;
economia de su curso 6ptimo. Estos resultados invierten lias conclusiones de la&#13;
literatura en que el punto central ha sido exclusivamente el acrecentamiento&#13;
maximo del provecho privado.&#13;
El documento sirve de punto de partida para toda persona interesada en&#13;
evaluar la pertinencia de la literatura te6rica existente sobre los problemas de&#13;
la seguridad social en los paises en desarrollo, que ya son importantes en&#13;
America Latina y empiezan a adquirir importancia e.n algunos paises de Asia. En&#13;
la actualidad la mayor parte de la literatura te6rica capta caracteristicas mas&#13;
parecidas a las de los paises desarrollados. Sin embargo, los enfoques&#13;
existentes tienen la ventaja de presentar los efectos tanto estAticos como&#13;
dinamicos, consideraci6n muy importante en el anilisis de un instrumento que se&#13;
puede prever influira en la asignaci6n estatica de recursos a traves del mercado&#13;
laboral y en la dinamica del crecimiento mediante la acumulaci6n de capital.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- vii -&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Introduction   .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  ..  .  1&#13;
Enunciation of Model and Central Issues                      2 .  .  2&#13;
1. Overlapping Generation's Models  . . . . . . ... .        2&#13;
2.  The  Golden  Rule  .  .  .  .  .  .   .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  4&#13;
3. Central Issues   .     . . .      . . . . . . . . .      6&#13;
Positive Issues     . .......       .. .. .  .  .  . .       7&#13;
1. Social Security Systems   . . . . . . . . . . . . .       7&#13;
2. Capital Accumulation    . . . . . . . . . . . . . .     11&#13;
3. Endogenous Labor Supply         .   .     . . . . . .   18&#13;
4. Empirical Evidence on the U.S.  . . . , . . . . .        23&#13;
Normative Issues  . . . . . . . . .  . I . . . . . . .      27&#13;
1. Retirement Exogenous, No Bequests  . . . . . . . . .     29&#13;
2. Long-run Welfare Implications of Endcgenous.&#13;
Retirement and Bequests         . . . . . . . . . .     36&#13;
Conclusion       .  .  .  .  . . . . . .  .  . .           40&#13;
Appendix to Section III.2  .      . .   . . . . . . . .  .  44&#13;
References     .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .   .   .   .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  48&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Introduction&#13;
The objective of this paper is two-fold. First, it clarifies the&#13;
role of different assumptions made by previous authors in the determination of&#13;
results regarding the neutrality or non-neutrality of social security's impact&#13;
on capital accumulation and labor supply. To this end, it analyses the&#13;
differential effects of alternative financing mechanisms - fully-funded and&#13;
pay-as-you-go schemes - within the framework of a multiperiod model with&#13;
overlapping generations. Second, the paper addresses the question of the&#13;
optimal size of social security. It contrasts the standard procedure of&#13;
equating optimality to the maximization of a representative individual's&#13;
utility function with an approach which rationalizes the need for social&#13;
security by reference to a paternalistic concern for the welfare of the&#13;
retired population.&#13;
Section I describes the central model and the main issues that are&#13;
addressed in the following sections. Section II investigates "positive"&#13;
concerns. Clarifying the alternative financing mechanisms within our&#13;
framework, it traces their differential effects on. capital accumulation and&#13;
labor supply, and provides pertinent empirical evidence from the U.S. in&#13;
support of our findings. Section III is concerned with normative issues of&#13;
optimality in both an individualistic and a paternalistic framework. It&#13;
examines the ability of alternative social security mechanisms to achieve the&#13;
rate of capital accumulation associated with the Golden Rule and explores the&#13;
effect of social security on the optimality of the Golden Path. A concluding&#13;
section summarizes the main results and an appendix elaborates a more&#13;
complicated version of the simple normative model developed in Section III.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
I. ENUNCIATION OF MODEL AND CENTRAL ISSUES&#13;
1.1       Overlapping Generations Models&#13;
Overlapping generations models are so called because at any point in&#13;
time they include at least two distinct generations. Most models, and all of&#13;
those reviewed here, identify only two generations - a working generation and&#13;
a retired generation, or, more accurately, a young generation for whom&#13;
retirement is not a feasible choice and an old generation for whom retirement&#13;
is a possibility. To clarify the generational structure of these models and&#13;
to introduce our notation, the distribution of consumption between groups in&#13;
each of two periods is described by:&#13;
Period t           Period t + 1&#13;
Young Generation             c                 ct +1&#13;
Old Generation               c2t               c2&#13;
The table shows the complete, lifetime consumption of only one generation -&#13;
Ct  and   c +1    are the levels of consumption of the same generation when&#13;
young in period t and when old in period t + 1.&#13;
Consumer Maximization&#13;
In the simplest models (Diamond (1965) and Samuelson (1975)), the&#13;
only choice to be made by the consumer is that of determining his&#13;
intertemporal pattern of consumption. In particular, the individual must&#13;
choose how much to save while working in order to finance his consumption when&#13;
retired. Accordingly, the consumer is assumed to:&#13;
max       U = U (c, c      )    ui &gt; 0, uii &lt; o                    (1)&#13;
t   t + 1 +     r w&#13;
s.t.      c~   c + c   (1 + r)1     w                              (2)&#13;
t     I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
where r is the rate of interest and w is the wage rate for one period of&#13;
work. Consumer equilibrium requires that:&#13;
r = Lu   /  u_1                                                  (3)&#13;
6c1   6c2&#13;
which signifies the standard relationship between the marginal rate of&#13;
substitution between consumption in periods 1 and 2 and the interest rate.&#13;
Equations 2 and 3 can be solved for cl and    c2   as functions of the two&#13;
prices, r and w.&#13;
Producer Maximization&#13;
Technology is characterized by a constan,t returns to scale&#13;
production function which may be written as:&#13;
f = f (Q)                                                        (4)&#13;
where f is output per unit of capital and Q is labor input per unit of&#13;
capital. Profit maximisation implies that&#13;
w= f                                                               (5)&#13;
and        r= f - Qf                                                        (6)&#13;
or         r =(w)      p   -Q &lt; O        -l/f   &gt; O                         (7)&#13;
which is the factor-price frontier. Equations 5 and 6 can, be used to express&#13;
the factor prices as a function of the labor: capital ratio.&#13;
Factor Supply&#13;
Total population (P) is assumed to grow at a rate of g percent a&#13;
year. Accordingly, labor supply (L) in period t is:&#13;
Lt =P    (1 - 0)                                                  (8)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
where e = 1/(2 + g) is the proportion of the population in the second period&#13;
of their life and who, in this simple model, are fully retired.&#13;
Since the capital stock (K) in period t is determined by the savings&#13;
decisions of those who are in the young age group in period t - 1, we have&#13;
K  = P0Ok                                                       (9)&#13;
t    t kt-l(9&#13;
where  kt 1 is the per capita supply of capital provided by the older&#13;
generation's savings from the previous period. Or,&#13;
K  = S       (w       1 ) L (9l)&#13;
And since, as noted above, ct    is a function of w 1 and r    1   the supply of&#13;
capital is determined exogenously as far as decisions in period t are&#13;
concerned. This completes the system of equations and implies that&#13;
consumption per capita in period t is   wt - st   (consumed by the young&#13;
generation) plus   (1 + r) stl1  (consumed by the old generation) and that&#13;
total investment is   St - St 1-   In the following, we will be exploring more&#13;
complicated models but the basic structure remains the same.&#13;
I.2      The Golden Rule&#13;
An important part of the literature has investigated, not just the&#13;
positive issue of how a perfectly competitive economy functions, but the&#13;
normative question of what is the highest level of steady-state consumption&#13;
per capita that can be achieved when steady-state is characterized primarily&#13;
by a constant value for the labor: capital ratio. In particular, authors have&#13;
explored the choice among alternative steady-states in the context of a&#13;
centrally planned economy. This has involved the maximisation of equation 1&#13;
subject to the production technology (equation 4) and subject to the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5 -&#13;
exogenously given growth in the labor supply (equat:ion 8). Unlike the&#13;
preceeding analysis, however, in this version the capital stock (and hence the&#13;
labor: capital ratio) is chosen by the planner to maximise the steady-state&#13;
consumption path, whereas previously it was determined by individual&#13;
preferences between consumption and saving.&#13;
The constraint faced by the planner may be formulated as:&#13;
1    1  2     2&#13;
Ct Lt + c   Lt = Kt ft   I&#13;
that is, total consumption must equal total output less investment. Since in&#13;
steady-state the labor: capital ratio is constant, the capital stock must grow&#13;
at the same rate (g) as the labor force. It follows that:&#13;
I  = g&#13;
t   gKt&#13;
so that dividing through by   Lt,   the constraint may be expressed as&#13;
1    2&#13;
ct + ct/(1+g) = (f   - g)/X                                     (10)&#13;
where Q is the constant labor: capital ratio. The planner maximizes equation&#13;
1   2&#13;
1 by choosing the values of cl, c , and Q subject t:o equation 10. This&#13;
yields:&#13;
du  /Su                                                    (3')&#13;
g = -s.- / -F- - 1                                              3 &#13;
and&#13;
g   f - Q f                                                    (6)&#13;
Equations   3 , 6   and 10 define the maxiLmum level of steady-state&#13;
consumption in a planned economy. From equations 2, 3, 5 and 6, it is clear&#13;
that the first-order conditions defining equilibrium in a perfectly&#13;
competitive economy are identical to those in the planned economy with the&#13;
sole exception that in the latter "the rate of inte.rest" is exactly equal to&#13;
the rate of population growth. This extra condition arises from the planner's&#13;
ability to treat the labor: capital ratio as a poli'cy variable whereas in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
perfectly competitive economy it is the result of private decision-making.&#13;
Except by chance, there is no reason to suppose that in a competitive economy&#13;
the equilibrium rate of interest will equal the population growth rate, and&#13;
hence there is no reason to suppose that a competitive economy will achieve&#13;
the steady-state level of consumption associated with the Golden Rule.&#13;
I.3      Central Issues&#13;
These simple models are useful in indicating the major issues that&#13;
have arisen in the analysis of social security systems. In general, we can&#13;
identify three questions that have been central to the social security&#13;
literature:&#13;
i) Can the rate of capital accumulation be influenced by the&#13;
introduction of a social security system? Within our simple model,&#13;
this would involve investigating whether or not savings (S t) are a&#13;
function of tax payments and pension benefits. The question becomes&#13;
somewhat broader if other motives - beside the life-cycle motive -&#13;
for saving are introduced. The bequest motive is one that has&#13;
received considerable attention (Barro, 1974).&#13;
ii) If labor supply is endogenous, does the presence of a social&#13;
security system influence labor supply decisions? This turns&#13;
attention away from the dynamic behavior of the economy and towards&#13;
issues of static resource allocation. In terms of our model, one&#13;
would want to investigate whether the payment of taxes and the&#13;
receipt of pensions drives a wedge between labor's supply price and&#13;
its marginal revenue product (Hu, 1979).&#13;
iii) The questions so far have been positive in character. If,&#13;
indeed, private behavior can be influenced by social security, then&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
important normative questions arise. In particular, one would want&#13;
to know if social security can enable a competitive economy to obtain&#13;
the steady-state associated with the Golden Rule of Samuelson. More&#13;
fundamentally, one can question whether or not t'he presence of social&#13;
security causes the social optimum to depart from the Golden Rule.&#13;
These questions form the point of departure for the remaiinder of the paper.&#13;
Before exploring them, however, we comment briefly on the main financing&#13;
mechanisms of social security and their relative importance in a selection of&#13;
countries.&#13;
II.      POSITIVE ISSUES&#13;
II.1     Social Security Systems&#13;
The theoretical literature has focussed on two different types of&#13;
funding that are usually known as the fully-funded system (FF) and the pay-as-&#13;
you-go system (PAYG). The former involves an intertemporal transfer in which&#13;
workers are taxed in period t and then receive in period 1: + 1 their tax&#13;
payments (t) plus interest in the form of pension benefits; (z). For this&#13;
system, therefore, we have:&#13;
L 2  Z = LI t(l + r)                                           (11)&#13;
t+1      t&#13;
In most systems in the world, t is a payroll tax and hence raises the&#13;
possibility of a distortion in the labor market. In several models in the&#13;
literature, however, labor supply is exogenously determined and the tax is&#13;
assumed to be of the lump-sum variety.   This is an important point at which&#13;
the models are at variance with reality and we return to it in Section 11.3.&#13;
Note that in this system, although the government"s account is obviously&#13;
balanced through time, it will not generally be balanced at any point in time&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
(i.e., in a cash-flow sense).   Thus, in period t, total receipts are tLt and&#13;
2             2&#13;
total expenses are zL   = t(l + r) L . If the tax remains constant through&#13;
t              t&#13;
time, and if the population growth rate is g, then total receipts exceed total&#13;
expenses if g &gt; r and vice versa if r &gt; g.&#13;
By way of contrast, it is a characteristic of the PAYG system that&#13;
the government's account is balanced at each point in time:&#13;
zL2 = tLt                                                      (12)&#13;
t     t&#13;
that is, the benefits paid to the retired population exactly equal the tax&#13;
receipts from the working population. The PAYG system, therefore, involves an&#13;
intergenerational transfer rather than an intertemporal one.&#13;
Table 1 groups selected developed and developing countries, which&#13;
have sizeable social security institutions, according to broad financing&#13;
mechanisms of the old age pension component of their social security&#13;
systems. The first group of countries, Australia, New Zealand and the U.K.,&#13;
finance their benefit payments from general revenues; hence there is no&#13;
surplus or deficit in their pension schemes by definition. Nor is there any&#13;
earmarking; social security payments are not linked in any way to a specific&#13;
tax such as a payroll tax. Most of the analysis presented here does not,&#13;
therefore, apply to these countries.&#13;
The second group of countries, which run their old age pension&#13;
schemes primarily on a funded basis, usually run sizeable surpluses in their&#13;
pension accounts, ranging between 50 percent (Japan) and 80 percent (Malaysia,&#13;
Sri Lanka) of total receipts. As explained, this is because in a funded&#13;
system, the social security budget need not be balanced at any point in&#13;
time. Instead, it is balanced across time for every contributor because the&#13;
discounted value of the returns he receives from the system should match his&#13;
contributions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
The third group of countries are those which rely primarily on a&#13;
PAYG system of social security. Here we expect, asi in our theoretical&#13;
analysis, the social security budget to balance every year. Indeed, while we&#13;
see that the surplus (or deficit) in this system is relatively small when&#13;
compared to that of a FF system, in reality, however, the budget cannot be&#13;
expected to balance exactly. Even in a PAYG system, depending on the&#13;
prevalent social security tax laws, a national old age pensions scheme can be&#13;
expected to yield small surpluses or deficits. Thuts, in 1977 and&#13;
subsequently, both the U.S. and West Germany yielded deficits, necessitating a&#13;
revision upwards in social security taxes.&#13;
The vintage of a-PAYG system affects the social security budget.&#13;
Relatively young PAYG systems, for example most of the post-War European and&#13;
the U.S. systems, yielded annual surpluses since every old age pensioner was&#13;
supported by a bigger pool of workers, compared to later years. As these&#13;
schemes matured and the demographic compositions of these societies changed, a&#13;
lower pool of workers had to support every old age pensioner. As a result,&#13;
with the progress of time, the surpluses vanished, the systems then arrived at&#13;
a balanced position, and finally ran into deficits unless compensated by&#13;
higher taxes. This was evinced by Sweden which, with a heavy reliance on high&#13;
tax rates, is still generating a considerable surplus in its PAYG system of&#13;
old age pension. Thus while it is theoretically correct to expect a PAYG&#13;
system to be balanced every year, in practice, one may perceive deviations&#13;
from this balance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
Table 1: FINANCING OF OLD AGE PENSIONS&#13;
In Selected Countries 1977 1/&#13;
Receipts x 100             Total Receipts (=100)            Surplus x 100&#13;
Country            GDP             Employee  Employer   Government  Other     Total Receipts&#13;
Australia          3.9                  0          0         100       0              0&#13;
New Zealand        5.5                   0         0         100        0             0&#13;
United Kingdom     4.0                  0          0         100       0              0&#13;
India              1.2                 40         40           1      19             72&#13;
Japan              3.4                 32         28          19      21             53&#13;
Malaysia           2.8                 29         29           0      42             79&#13;
Singapore          8.7                 38         42           0      20             63&#13;
Sri Lanka          1.3                 27         40           0      33             80&#13;
Turkey             2.3                 35         40           0      25             62&#13;
Argentina          4.0                 40         50           0      10             26&#13;
Belgium            5.4                 33         43          17       7              6&#13;
Canada             3.7                 14         14          58      14             28&#13;
Chile              3.6                 27         48          10       15            26&#13;
Germany           11.2                 34         33          19      14             -7&#13;
Sweden            12.9                  3         63          13      21             32&#13;
Uruguay            5.6                 31         44           8      17             12&#13;
United States      3.8                  50        46           1        3            -2&#13;
1/  These figures exclude old age pension schemes for public sector employees.&#13;
Source: Basic Tables, The Cost of Social Security, Tenth International Inquiry, 1975-77,&#13;
ILO Geneva, 1981.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
II.2     Capital Accumulation&#13;
Fully-Funded System&#13;
Much of the analysis of this and the next section can be conducted&#13;
by means of a careful investigation of the effect of social security on the&#13;
individual's budget constraint. For example, consider the introduction of a&#13;
FF system into an economy characterized by equations 1, 2, S and 8. The only&#13;
equation affected by the SS system is the lifetime budget constraint. In&#13;
particular, we can write:&#13;
1    2 &#13;
Ct + ct+/(1+r) = w - t + z (1+r)                              (2)&#13;
in place of equatiai 2. Recall, however, that in a FF system benefits equal&#13;
tax payments plus accrued interest - that is, from equation 11, z = t(l+r) and&#13;
hence equation 2 collapses to equatim 2 and the economy is totally&#13;
unaffected by the presence of the FF system.&#13;
This result is well-known and is generally accepted in the&#13;
literature (Samuelson, 1975). For future reference, however, it is worth&#13;
noting that it depends on the individual's awareness of the relation between&#13;
taxes and benefits and on the equivalence of the rate of return on public&#13;
savings and the interest rate facing the private sector. Provided these&#13;
conditions are fulfilled, total capital accumulation remains the same but its&#13;
distribution between the public and private sectors dependis on the rate of&#13;
taxation. If, however, these conditions are not fulfilled, the rate of&#13;
capital accumulation will be affected. For example, assumte that the rate of&#13;
return on public saving is less than that on private savings. In this event,&#13;
the individual suffers a real income loss and, since consumption in both&#13;
periods is assumed to be normal, the reduction in private savings will be more&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
than social security payments and the overall level of capital accumulation&#13;
will suffer.&#13;
The significance of different rates of return to private and public&#13;
savings emerges clearly from the Sheshinski and Weiss (1981) model. In their&#13;
model, the length of life and hence the length of retirement is uncertain.&#13;
Accordingly, their FF social security system offers an annuity. The return on&#13;
private savings is (1 + r). Assuming that the social security system is&#13;
actuarially fair, the return on an annuity is   0(l+r)/t, where   t is the&#13;
fraction of the individual's potential retirement that is actually realized,&#13;
and * is the expected duration of retirement in the population. Clearly, in&#13;
this case the presence of a social security system can be expected to&#13;
influence private behavior. Equally clearly, however, had the individual had&#13;
access to a private annuities market that offered a return of 0(l+r)/O , the&#13;
introduction of a social security sytem would only imply a reallocation of the&#13;
individual's annuities from the private market to the public sector without&#13;
any consequence for real prices or capital accumulation.&#13;
Pay-as-you--o System&#13;
The effect of a PAYG system on capital accumulation is considerably&#13;
more controversial. Just as private saving offers a means of offsetting the&#13;
intertemporal transfers associated with a FF system, so, according to Barro,&#13;
private bequests offer a means of offsetting the intergenerational transfers&#13;
associated with a PAYG system. Views on this matter, however, diverge&#13;
sharply. Consider these quotes from two recent contributions:&#13;
"If social security is financed on a pay-as-you-to basis, i.e.,&#13;
if taxes on the currently working population are used to finance&#13;
benefits to the retired population, it is a perfect substitute for&#13;
private bequests. Hence, a forced increase in social security will&#13;
reduce bequests by an equal amount. Consumption, private savings,&#13;
and aggregate savings will be unaffected. In such models the optimal&#13;
level of social security is clearly undetermined." (Sheshinaki and&#13;
Weiss, 1981, pp. 189-190.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
"Without further complications and great loss of generality, let&#13;
us assume that the only role played by the go-vernment is to provide&#13;
Social Security. Moreover, it finances Social Securilty by a "pay-as-&#13;
you-g o" system under which the government does not accumulate capital&#13;
and it merely transfers payments by workers to retirees....It is&#13;
further shown that an appropriate Social Security sysltem can increase&#13;
the long-run well being of the economy by causing the rate of return&#13;
on capital to converge to the Golden Rule level." (Hiu, 1979, p. 274&#13;
and p. 278.)&#13;
The authors quoted above arrive at fundamentally different&#13;
conclusions regarding the effect of a social security sysltem financed on a&#13;
PAYG basis. Sheshinski and Weiss reproduce Barro's original result whereby&#13;
changes in private decisions with respect to bequests completely offset social&#13;
security tax payments leaving all real variables unchanged. Hu, on the other&#13;
hand, demonstrates that a PAYG system can influence the economy's steady-state&#13;
rate of capital accumulation. The purpose of this section is to pinpoint the&#13;
causes of these different conclusions.&#13;
To explore this issue we need to introduace a bequest motive into the&#13;
model captured by equations 1, 2, 4 and 8. In particular:, we adopt the&#13;
procedure followed by Hu and write:&#13;
U - U(C1) + V(c2, ,                                          (1 )&#13;
which implies that the marginal rate of substitution between second-period&#13;
consumption and bequests (0) is independent of first-period consumption.&#13;
Several authors have used a more general version of the ut:ility function. For&#13;
example, Barro (1974) writes:&#13;
U = u(c, c , U )                                              (1)&#13;
where U* is the maximum level of utility attainabLe by the individual's&#13;
heir.  However, since U  is itself a function of any bequest, the first-order&#13;
conditions derived from equations (1/) and (1") both involve   au/ a.   From&#13;
equation (1')  au/B - av/a&#156;, whereas from equation (1V) it is expressed as&#13;
au1au* Du /Da.    That is, apart from the additive characteristics of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
equation 1-, the two formulations are the same.&#13;
An advantage of equation 1", however is that the effect of a bequest&#13;
on utility can be divided into its two component parts. The first - au/au -&#13;
represents the individual's evaluation of his own utility relative to that of&#13;
his heir. Presumably, the former receives more weight than the latter so that&#13;
au/Dau may be interpreted as the rate at which an individual discounts the&#13;
utility of his heir. For a general utility function, Drazen (1978)&#13;
demonstrates that bequests will be positive only if this rate of discount is&#13;
less than the market rate of interest. This condition ensures that the loss&#13;
of consumption to the donor entailed by a bequest is, despite the discount&#13;
factor, more than offset by the value to him of the consumption - (1+r) times&#13;
the bequest - enjoyed by his heir.   The second component -  au /as - is simply&#13;
the effect of a bequest on the heir's maximum attainable level of utility.&#13;
This advantage notwithstanding, we work with equation 1 throughout most of&#13;
the paper because of its notational convenience.&#13;
In the context of a model with a growing population, some authors&#13;
(Drazen (1978), Carmichael (1982), Burbidge (1983)) have explored whether&#13;
S should represent the bequest per heir or total bequests. If one focusses&#13;
on the bequest per heir and the population growth rate is g, then, in addition&#13;
to the discount factor discussed above, the value of a bequest to the donor&#13;
will depend on the number of heirs. The population growth rate will operate,&#13;
therefore, as a second discount factor. We, however, will follow prevalent&#13;
opinion (see Drazen (1978) and Burbidge (1983)) as well as personal&#13;
preference, and focus exclusively on total bequest rather than bequest per&#13;
heir. Accordingly, a should be interpreted as the total amount bequeathed so&#13;
that each heir receives S/(l+g) where g is the population growth rate.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
With these clarifications of equation (1) examine, first, the&#13;
consequences of a PAYG system for a person in the second period of his life.&#13;
Unlike the earlier models in which second-period consumption was determined by&#13;
first-period savings, in this model, given the level of first-period savings,&#13;
the individual still has a choice between consumption and leaving a bequest.&#13;
Accordingly, the individual is assumed to:&#13;
max  v = v(c ,                                                  (13)&#13;
s.t.  c + B = (l+r) (St-l + ht-l) + z                           (14)&#13;
where 8 is the individual's measure of the value of his bequest, and B is the&#13;
monetary cost of that bequest (see below) . The individual"s income comprises&#13;
savings (st-1) from the last period plus any inheritance (hzt_1) from the last&#13;
period and his pension (z).&#13;
If the individual focusses on the net transfer of resources from him&#13;
to his children, then:&#13;
8 = B - t (l+g)                                                (15)&#13;
rjthere t is the tax on the beneficiary generation, and, assuming that each&#13;
individual has the same number of children, (1+g) Ls the number of heirs. In&#13;
addition, if the individual knows that the govenment's budget for social&#13;
security must be balanced in every period, then, from equation 12:&#13;
z = t(l+g)                                                     (16)&#13;
On substituting equations 15 and 16 into the second-period budget constraint,&#13;
the social security variables disappear, indicating that the individual's&#13;
behavior is not influenced by the introduction of a PAYG system. Moreover,&#13;
provided members of the younger generation recognize that t:heir inheritance,&#13;
received at the end of the first period, will be the same regardless of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
social security system, then, even though they pay taxes, their behavior will&#13;
also be unaffected.&#13;
Assumptions 15 and 16 guarantee the Barro result obtained by&#13;
Sheshinski and Weiss. If, however, either or both of the conditions&#13;
represented by equations 15 and 16 are not fulfilled, the Barro result no&#13;
longer holds. For example, Hu assumes that:&#13;
B   B                                                         (15)&#13;
implying that the individual derives utility from the gross level of the&#13;
bequest rather than from the net intergenerational transfer of resources. For&#13;
an individual in period two of his life, the budget constraint would be:&#13;
2 &#13;
c + B     (l+r) (st-1 + ht-)     t(+)                         (14)&#13;
In this case, the receipt of a pension [t(l+g)] would be perceived as a net&#13;
increase in wealth, utility being unaffected by the fact that the generation&#13;
receiving the bequest () will now be poorer because of their tax payments.&#13;
Since both c and B are assumed to be normal, the introduction of a PAYG&#13;
system will increase the level of bequests.&#13;
Turning our attention to the young generation, their budget&#13;
constraint is now:&#13;
Ct + c2  /(l+r) + 8t+1/(l+r) - w    - t + a /(l+g) + t(l+g)/(l+r)      (2")&#13;
t    t+l            + &#13;
We have already seen that the bequest (ht - 8t/(l+g)) to be received by this&#13;
generation will be larger as a result of PAYG system. It follows that if&#13;
g &gt; r, lifetime income is unambiguously increased and, again assuming that&#13;
c2 and 8 are normal, saving will be increased. Since in this model, total&#13;
capital accumulation is:&#13;
K    - a L 2 + s&#13;
Kt+1    t L   +  t Lt&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
it is clear that the introduction of a PAYG system will affect capital&#13;
accumulation (at least in a partial equilibrium sense) and, if the population&#13;
growth rate exceeds the interest rate, that effect will be unambiguously&#13;
positive.  Equation 15 , an exclusive focus on gross bequests, is sufficient,&#13;
therefore, to generate conclusions similar to those of Hu.&#13;
This analysis bears on the debate between Barro and Feldstein&#13;
regarding the effect of social security in a growing economy. Barro had&#13;
established his original result in the context of a zero-growth economy.&#13;
Feldstein (1976) contended that the result was unlikely to hold in a growing&#13;
economy. Our formulation of the problem demonstrates clearly that, regardless&#13;
of the growth rate of the economy, the Barro focus on net transfers is&#13;
sufficient to ensure the neutrality of a PAYG system, prov:ided the individual&#13;
is aware of the government's budget constraint (equation 16), a result also&#13;
shown by Carmichael (1982).&#13;
Sheshinski and Weiss (1981) introduce uncertainty into the Barro&#13;
model. The length of life, and hence the duration of retirement, is assumed&#13;
to be uncertain. If f is the fraction of the potential retirement period&#13;
that is actually realized, the second-period budget constraint may be written&#13;
as:&#13;
4c2 + B = (l+r)(s+h) + z                                      (14')&#13;
Sheshinski and Weiss assume that the social securilty system offers annuities&#13;
so that the budget is balanced when:&#13;
(l+g) t                                                  (16)&#13;
where     is the expected length of retirement in the population.   This implies&#13;
that even if the individual is aware of the governoment's butdget constraint and&#13;
focusses on net bequests (equatim 15) , second-period income is still changed&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
by an amount equal to   t(1+)(+-O)/f.    The PAYG system, therefore, modifies&#13;
private sector behavior. Sheshinski and Weiss, however, do not allow for a&#13;
private annuities market. Assuming the existence of such a market, an&#13;
individual in the second (uncertain) period of his life could buy an annuity&#13;
instead of providing a lump-sum bequest. The individual would then be able to&#13;
bequeath B+/I and, accepting equation 16' together with a focus on net&#13;
bequests, the social security variables disappear from the budget constraint&#13;
once again.&#13;
II.3     Endogenous Labor Supply&#13;
Labor supply can be made endogenous without affecting any of the&#13;
earlier results provided the payment of taxes and the receipt of benefits is&#13;
not linked to the retirement decision, that is, provided the tax and the&#13;
benefit retain their lump-sum characteristic. This can be verified by&#13;
including in the utility function, the proportion (co of the second period&#13;
that is allocated to retirement, and by adding (1 - d)w to the second period&#13;
budget constraint. This will now yield a new first-order condition:&#13;
dv dv                                                          (17)&#13;
da dc2&#13;
which equates the marginal rate of substitution between leisure and second-&#13;
period consumption to the wage rate. Apart from these changes everything else&#13;
remains the same.  That is, if equations 11 and   15   hold for a FF system and&#13;
if equatim 15 and 16 hold for a PAYG system, then social security has no&#13;
effect on capital accumulation or labor supply. And, in the event that these&#13;
conditions are not fulfilled, social security will influence total lifetime&#13;
income and hence will affect both capital accummulation and labor supply.&#13;
Now let us explore what happens if it is assumed that, instead of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
lump-sum taxes and pensions, the individual is taxed and receives benefits at&#13;
a fixed rate per unit of time. For a FF system, the government's budget will&#13;
be balanced if:&#13;
L   za = L   t(l+r) + L    t(l-a)                              (11 )&#13;
t+1      t            t+l&#13;
that is, if total benefits paid for the duration of retire:ment in period two&#13;
equal the tax paid in period one plus accrued interest plus the tax paid while&#13;
working in period two. If the individual is aware of equation 11 , then, as&#13;
before, capital accumulation and labor supply are unaffected. If, however,&#13;
the individual is unaware of equation 11 and acts as though&#13;
za * t(l+r) + t(l-a), then behavior is altered, not only by an income effect,&#13;
but also by a price effect. To verify this, note that the lifetime budget&#13;
constraint in this case would be:&#13;
c + [c2 +B]/(l+r) = w - t + h +   (w-t)(l--d) + cz]/(l+r)&#13;
or          1     2&#13;
c + [c + B + a(w-t-z)]/(l+r) - w - t + h + (w-t:)/(l+r)         (2..)&#13;
From this constraint, it is clear that differentiat:ion of the utility function&#13;
with respect to a will lead to a first-order condition of the form:&#13;
dv/ dv   w - t - z                                             (17)&#13;
da dc2&#13;
relating the marginal rate of substitution between second-period consumption&#13;
and retirement to the net wage. Thus, in this version, if the individual is&#13;
unaware of the link between tax payments and pension benefits, behavior is&#13;
affected not only by a change in lifetime income but also by a change in the&#13;
effective wage rate facing the individual. Moreover, since there is no reason&#13;
to suppose that the (gross) wage is not equal to labor's marginal revenue&#13;
product, this result implies a distortion in the labor market in that the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
marginal rate of substitution between consumption and leisure is no longer&#13;
equal to labor's marginal revenue product. Thus, while in general it is&#13;
impossible to predict the overall effect on savings, bequests, and retirement,&#13;
it is clear that in this case the introduction of social security distorts the&#13;
labor market.&#13;
A similar point arises with a PAYG system. For example, let us&#13;
accept the Barro focus on net bequests (i.e., 8 - B - t(l+g)) but now assume&#13;
that, as far as the individual is concerned, taxes and pensions are perceived&#13;
to be independent: the individual responds to a change in taxes without&#13;
anticipating any associated change in pensions. This is the assumption&#13;
adopted by Hu. In exploring the general equilibrium consequences of social&#13;
security, Hu does, of course, introduce the government's budget constraint.&#13;
The point remains, however, that in the Hu model the individual behaves as&#13;
though taxes and pensions can be varied independently. Accordingly, for an&#13;
individual in the second-period of life the budget constraint becomes:&#13;
2                         W&#13;
c + 8 + a(w-t-z) = (1+r) (sh) + (w-t) - t(l+g)               (14-)&#13;
indicating both a price effect (w is now w-t-z) and an income effect (second&#13;
period income is decreased by t + t(l+g)). Again this will imply a labor&#13;
market distortion and, of course, capital accumulation will be affected. If,&#13;
however, the individual is aware of the government's budget constraint, that&#13;
is, if he knows that:&#13;
2   tL            2&#13;
z aLt= tLt + t(1-a)Lt                                          (12-)&#13;
then, insertion into equation   14    reveals clearly that the relative price of&#13;
consumption to retirement is once again given by the gross wage (w) thereby&#13;
eliminating the source of the distortion in the labor market.&#13;
It appears, therefore, that the individual's awareness of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
overall government budget constraint is of some importance. Even if payroll&#13;
taxes and social security benefits infringe directly on the retirement&#13;
decision, provided the individual is aware of the government's budget&#13;
constraint, individual labor supply decisions will not be affected and there&#13;
is no reason to suppose that this method - payroll taxation - of raising&#13;
revenue will distort the labor market.   More generally, this point arises in&#13;
the context of any earmarked tax where the link between a particular payment&#13;
and the receipt of a particular transfer or servi,ze can be easily identified&#13;
in a separate budget account. Because then, even if the l:ax payment is&#13;
related to a particular activity - such as consumption of a given commodity or&#13;
supply of labor - provided the individual believes that he will ultimately&#13;
receive a benefit of equivalent value, the imposit:ion of a tax need not be&#13;
distortionary.  Moreover, if this could be verified for any given tax - say,&#13;
payroll taxation - it would be a strong argument f or recommending a more&#13;
general use of earmarking as a means of raising revenue irL a nondistortionary&#13;
manner.&#13;
The behavior implied by the use of equation 11 for a FF system and&#13;
equation  12    for a PAYG system is, of course, unusual in that it requires an&#13;
assumption by each individual that all other individuals wrill behave as he&#13;
does. For example, consider what happens if a taa: at the rate of t is levied&#13;
on earnings in the second period. If the individual does not change his&#13;
behavior - that is, if, as far as this individual is concerned, the tax does&#13;
not distort labor market behavior - then a certaini amount of revenue will be&#13;
generated. If the individual could guarantee that an equivalent amount of&#13;
money would be returned to him then, indeed, he would have no motive to change&#13;
his behavior. This would be true if the government balanced its social&#13;
security budget by balancing each individual's contributions and receipts. Of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
course, the government does not do this: it is interested solely in the&#13;
overall balance. Accordingly, if everybody else reduces their labor supply,&#13;
some of the revenue contributed by the individual who maintains his pre-tax&#13;
labor supply will be transferred to the other members of society to ensure&#13;
that the rate at which pensions are paid is the same for everybody and to&#13;
finance the additional time that everybody else is retired. In short, it only&#13;
makes sense for the individual to maintain his labor supply in the face of an&#13;
increase in tax rates if he believes that everyone else will behave in the&#13;
same way. If, on the other hand, he sees a population of free riders, then it&#13;
would be prudent to reduce labor supply implying the usual distortion for the&#13;
labor market.&#13;
This analysis of the two assumptions - that relating to bequests and&#13;
that relating to knowledge of the government's budget constraint - yields the&#13;
following conclusions. First, if the individual is unaware of the&#13;
government's overall budget constraint, then a social security system that&#13;
links payment of taxes and receipt of benefits to the length of working life&#13;
will distort the labor market. It will also reduce lifetime income. This&#13;
holds for both FF and PAYG although for PAYG the magnitude of the reduction&#13;
depends on one's assumptions regarding bequests. Second, if the individual is&#13;
aware of the government's budget constraint, then a FF system has no effect on&#13;
behavior. In this case, the issue of net or gross benefits is irrelevant,&#13;
since there are no intergenerational tax payments. Third, if the individual&#13;
is aware of the government's budget constraint, then a PAYG system will not&#13;
distort the labor market but it may affect lifetime income. Fourth, if the&#13;
individual focusses on the net intergenerational transfer, the income effect&#13;
is zero and PAYG has no effect on behavior. And fifth, regardless of the&#13;
assumption regarding the individual's awareness of the government's budget&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
constraint, a focus on gross rather than net intergeneratiLonal transfers&#13;
implies a change in lifetime income that is positive or negative depending on&#13;
whether the population growth rate exceeds the int:erest rate or not.&#13;
II.4     Empirical Evidence on the U.S.&#13;
Evidence is accumulating to suggest thal: the primary rationale of&#13;
private saving is the provision of bequests to one's progeny rather than the&#13;
reallocation of consumption within one's lifetime.    Mirer (1979, p. 435), for&#13;
example, finds that the "aged tend to increase their wealt.h over time" and&#13;
Kotlikoff and Summers (1981, p. 729) conclude that:, "Intergenerational&#13;
transfers appear to be the major element determining wealt.h accumulation in&#13;
the United States". Assuming that bequests are an important component of&#13;
total saving behavior, it remains to discover whet:her individuals focus on the&#13;
gross or the net intergenerational transfer of resources and whether they are&#13;
aware of the government's budget constraint.&#13;
If those in the old age group are concerned about the net transfer&#13;
(equation 15) and are aware that the government must balance (approximately)&#13;
its budget (equation 16), then any transfer of resources from the young to the&#13;
old through the social security system would be returned via an increase in&#13;
bequests. It follows that if the accumulated savings of the aged are&#13;
regressed on the transfer from the young to the ol.d induced by social&#13;
security, the coefficient on the independent variable should approximate&#13;
one. In a regression to explain the accumulated wealth of those at retirement&#13;
age, Kotlikoff (1979) includes among his independent variables the lifetime&#13;
wealth increment (LWI) associated with participation in the social security&#13;
system. Kotlikoff (1979, p. 397) notes that "the vast majority of Social&#13;
Security beneficiaries up to the present have enjoyed positive lifetime wealth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
increments from the system due on the one hand to high real benefit levels&#13;
and, on the other hand, to their escape from taxation when young". It follows&#13;
that LWI approximates the transfer of resources from the currently young to&#13;
the currently old. Kotlikoff, however, finds that the coefficient on LWI is&#13;
0.237 and is not significantly different from zero. In a similar exercise,&#13;
David and Menchik (1981) regress accumulated wealth at death on LWI. In&#13;
several different formulations the coefficient on LWI is either insignificant&#13;
or significant and negative. This evidence, therefore, is clearly&#13;
inconsistent with the Barro hypothesis and suggests that either individuals&#13;
are primarily concerned with the gross measure of bequests (equation 15') or&#13;
they are unaware of the method of financing the transfers arising from the&#13;
social security system.&#13;
Empirical evidence concerning labor supply response can also be used&#13;
to shed light on the choice of assumptions. Recall that the price of second-&#13;
period consumption relative to leisure changes from w to w-t-z if individuals&#13;
are unaware of the overall budget constraint for the social security system or&#13;
if they perceive a population of free-riders who will reduce their labor&#13;
supply in response to a tax increase. Recent experiments have indicated that,&#13;
while free-riding behavior is observed, it is not as extensive as one might&#13;
imagine. For example, Scheneider and Pommerehne (1981, p. 702) conclude "that&#13;
there is only modest evidence for free-riding as compared with the importance&#13;
attributed to it in the literature. The individuals [in their experimental&#13;
study] did systematically behave as free riders in line with the different&#13;
incentives offered by the experiment's three stages, but the extent to which&#13;
free riding occurred was not great." The behavior implied by equations 11'&#13;
and 12' may not, therefore, be so improbable.&#13;
Nevertheless, direct estimates of labor supply functions suggest&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
that labor supply behavior is influenced significantly by t:he introduction&#13;
PAYG social security. From equation 17', it is clear that the retirement&#13;
decision will be a function of z. In particular, assuming that the&#13;
substitution effect dominated, the duration of retLrement should be positively&#13;
related to z. On the other hand, if individuals aire aware of the social&#13;
security budget constraint and believe that others will behave as they behave,&#13;
then the price faced by the individual will once again be w and, assuming&#13;
individuals focus on net bequests, the retirement decision should be&#13;
independent of z. Alternatively, even if the price faced by the individual is&#13;
w, a focus on gross, rather than net, bequests wou:ld result: in a positive&#13;
income effect (see equation 14').   If either of the basic assumptions for&#13;
neutrality is violated, we should, therefore, be able to identify a positive&#13;
relationship between the length of retirement and z. Both Boskin (1977) and&#13;
Boskin and Hurd (1978) demonstrate that the probab:Llity of retirement is&#13;
related positively and significantly to the potentlal beneiits (z) to be&#13;
derived from social security. Boskin (1977, p. 13' remarksi that "An increase&#13;
in social security benefits from $3,000 to $4,000 per year per couple raises&#13;
the annual probability of retirement from 7.5 percent to 16 percent."&#13;
Similarly, Boskin and Hurd (1978, p. 373) conclude that "a thousand dollar&#13;
increase in benefits leads to an increase in the probabilit:y of retirement of&#13;
about eight percentage points over the two years of the sample.    This is a&#13;
large increase, almost equal to our estimated probability of 0.115". It&#13;
appears, therefore, that either individuals attach considerable weight to the&#13;
importance of free-riding behavior in this particular instance or they focus&#13;
on the gross intergenerational transfer. It also t3uggests the possibility&#13;
that a PAYG social security system will distort the labor market.&#13;
On the basis of admittedly inadequate empirical evidence, therefore,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
it appears that at least, one, and possibly both of Hu's assumptions may be&#13;
more appropriate. 1/ That is, individuals focus on the gross&#13;
intergenerational transfers and perceive no link between the payment of taxes&#13;
and the receipt of pensions. Accepting these propositions, PAYG social&#13;
security will affect the economy-wide rate of capital accumulation and will&#13;
distort the labor market. Recent results by Feldstein (1982) and Leimer and&#13;
Lesnoy (1982) can be interpreted in this light. The former finds that,&#13;
between 1929 and 1971, social security reduced personal saving by 44 percent&#13;
in the U.S., while the latter find no significant relationship between the&#13;
two. The basic difference in their results can be related to the divergent&#13;
ways in which they calculate SSW, or the social security wealth variable.&#13;
Feldstein attached little importance to the "changing perceptions"&#13;
of contributors to the system regarding potential benefits that they will&#13;
receive, assuming, instead, that they expect the ratio of benefits per&#13;
beneficiary to per capita disposable income to remain primarily the same.&#13;
This implies, in terms of our analysis, that participants in the U.S. social&#13;
security system are not necessarily aware of the government's budget&#13;
constraint, even as the demographic composition changes.&#13;
In their calculation of SSW, Leimer and Lesnoy, on the other hand,&#13;
focus on, and correct for, the changing expectations regarding the benefit:&#13;
income ratio with decreasing mortality rates, increasing ratios of retirees to&#13;
dependent beneficiaries among women, and so on. Inasmuch as these&#13;
expectations reflect the actual benefit structure and revenue potential of the&#13;
1/ Blinder, Gordon and Wise (1980), for example, have indentified another&#13;
aspect of social security provisions - the automatic benefit recomputation -&#13;
which, if fully recognized by participants in the system, casts some doubt on&#13;
existing econometric results.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
system at any point in time, one may interpret their individual as being aware&#13;
of the government's social security budget constra:Lnt. Also since Leimer and&#13;
Lesnoy's results carry over to the Barro model of net bequests (see their&#13;
Footnote 16), one can say that their individual's interest lies in leaving a&#13;
constant net bequest.&#13;
It is then quite apparent why Feldstein'n; result is so different&#13;
from that of Leimer and Lesnoy. Feldstein's indiviidual is not aware of the&#13;
government's budget constraint: his social security system, therefore, affects&#13;
capital accumulation. Leimer and Lesnoy's individual focuEses on net bequests&#13;
and recognizes the government's budget constraint: their pEay-as-you-go system,&#13;
therefore, is neutral in its effects on personal saving.    If, as we argued&#13;
above, Hu's assumptions are right, i.e. individuals focus on gross bequests&#13;
and perceive no link between social security taxes and benefits, then&#13;
Feldstein's calculation of SSW and, therefore, his results, are more&#13;
convincing than those of Leimer and Lesnoy.   If, on the other hand,&#13;
individuals do become increasingly aware of a tax-benefit link, then Leimer&#13;
and Lesnoy's assumption of "changing perceptions" becomes realistic&#13;
III.     NORMATIVE ISSUES&#13;
So far we have addressed positive issues within the context of&#13;
intertemporal models of overlapping generations. We have shown that, in&#13;
certain circumstances, private sector behavior is riodified by the social&#13;
security system. In those models where the social security' system is shown to&#13;
influence private behavior, most authors have usually externded their analysis&#13;
to address normative issues. That is, they have investigated whether or not a&#13;
competitive economy can be moved towards the path associated with the Golden&#13;
Rule of capital accumulation. In one of the most comprehensive models, for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
example, Hu (1979) demonstrates that, when allowance is made for general&#13;
equilibrium effects on the wage rate and the rate of interest, a PAYG system&#13;
creates a distortion in the labor market - the marginal rate of substitution&#13;
between consumption and retirement does not equal labor's marginal product -&#13;
but can ensure a steady-state, long-run equilibrium of the economy that is&#13;
closer to the path defined by the Golden Rule of capital accumulation. In the&#13;
model, the individual is assumed to focus on gross bequests and to be unaware&#13;
of the overall government budget constraint. For a FF system, however,&#13;
provided the individual expects his pension to exactly equal his tax payments&#13;
plus accrued interest, all real prices and quantities will remain unchanged,&#13;
although the distribution of capital between the public and private sectors&#13;
will be altered. This, of course, parallels Samuelson's result (1975).&#13;
The models referred to above define "optimality" by reference to the&#13;
maximum steady-state value of a representative individual's utility. Social&#13;
security, however, is usually rationalized on paternalistic rather than&#13;
individualistic grounds. For example, Musgrave and Musgrave (1980, p. 729)&#13;
remark that "the compulsory approach [to social security] may be viewed as a&#13;
paternalistic decision by society to protect the imprudent against starvation&#13;
in old age." Similarly, Samuelson (1975, p. 543), although basing his own&#13;
analysis on individual utility maximization, notes:&#13;
Many social security systems, like the New Deal U.S.&#13;
System, may be deemed most valuable precisely because the&#13;
myopia ignored by the present models does in fact&#13;
prevail. People live miserably in old age because they&#13;
do not realize when young what are the consequences of&#13;
their private saving habits. So by democratic fiat, they&#13;
paternalistically impose on themselves a within-life&#13;
pattern of consumption that favors old age at the expense&#13;
of the young. Precisely because of the myopia that makes&#13;
paternalism optimal, once citizens are subject to social&#13;
security taxation and benefits they do not see clearly&#13;
how they can undo by private-saving offsets what the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
mandatory system is doing to them. So, both because of&#13;
themselves and yet despite themselves, they contrive&#13;
social security that makes them better off.&#13;
Accordingly, in this paper, the relative merits of a FF system and a&#13;
PAYG system are re-examined in a paternalistic version of the individualistic&#13;
model presented above. It is shown that, whereas Hu's conclusions with&#13;
respect to the PAYG system remain unchanged, a FF system can now also be used&#13;
to influence the long-run, steady-state of the economy even if the individual&#13;
is assumed to be fully aware of the overall government budget constraint.&#13;
III.1.   Retirement Exogenous, No Bequests:&#13;
In this Section, we derive the relationship between the equilibrium&#13;
rate of interest and the level of taxation in both PAYG and FF systems, using&#13;
the simple overlapping generations model introduced in Section 11.1. Labor&#13;
market equilibrium is secured if the demand for labor emerging from equation 5&#13;
matches the supply implied by equation 8. Using equations 8 and 9,&#13;
equilibrium in the labor market requires that:&#13;
w(t) 'f (     1k(-8)                                            (18)&#13;
W(t)Okt-)&#13;
Equations 7 and 18 can now be solved to obtain the equilibrium values of w and&#13;
r given the supply of capital from the previous period.&#13;
Pay-as-you-go System:&#13;
In PAYG, the government never accumulates investible funds through&#13;
the social security system as explained in Section II.2. The supply of&#13;
capital is, therefore, determined solely by private savings. In a two period&#13;
model, savings will equal the difference between disposable income and&#13;
consumption in the first period. That is:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
ks     ~w 1t        1                                          ()&#13;
kt= St-l   Wtl   C_ C     (r, y)&#13;
t  - 1tI             &#13;
where lifetime income is:&#13;
y = Wt_1-t t_1 + z/(l+r),&#13;
t is the payroll tax and c is first period consumption written as a function&#13;
of the rate of interest, r, and lifetime income, y. The latter is defined as&#13;
disposable income in the first period plus the discounted value of the&#13;
pension, z, received in the second period. Eliminating subscripts, if s is&#13;
written as:&#13;
ss(w-t, r,z)                                                    .t19)&#13;
then 1&gt;s &gt;O,s &gt;0 and S3&lt;0. That is, assuming that consumption in each&#13;
period is a normal good, an increase in the net wage will increase savings&#13;
less than proportionately. The effect of an increase in the rate of interest,&#13;
however, is indeterminate. It definitely increases savings by reducing the&#13;
present value of lifetime income and hence consumption in period one. But it&#13;
also reduces the relative price (1/(l+r)) of second-period consumption.&#13;
Assuming that the substitution effect dominates, then s2 is unambiguously&#13;
positive. And finally, an increase in the pension level has a positive income&#13;
effect on period-one consumption and thus reduces savings.&#13;
For a long-run, steady state equilibrium, in which k remains&#13;
constant, equations 7 (the factor-price frontier), 12 (the government budget&#13;
constraint), 18 and 19 can be solved for the four endogenous variables, w, r,&#13;
k and z, as functions of t. Totally differentiating this system of equations&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
and expressing in elasticity notation, yields&#13;
xI    - c3w)                                        (0&#13;
dlnr  (nr - E r + Lp2w)    dlnt&#13;
where      C    s = 81W/S &gt; 0&#13;
E2 = s2r/s 8 0&#13;
c3   s3Z/S &lt; 0&#13;
and        n = -wkO/f"(l-0) &gt; 0 and is the elasticity of labor demand.&#13;
Equation 20 depicts the change in r as t is changed and the economy shifts to&#13;
a new long-run, steady-state equilibrium. (It says nothing about the process&#13;
of transition between states). The numerator of equation 20 is unambigously&#13;
positive.  Although the denominator appears indeterminate, Hu (1979, p. 280)&#13;
argues that it must be assumed positive in consideration of the stability of&#13;
the long-run equilibrium, in which case changes in r and t are positively&#13;
related.&#13;
Hu argues that PAYG can move the steady-state equLlibrium of the&#13;
economy closer to the Golden Path where the return to capital equals the&#13;
population growth rate. If payroll taxation and the rate of interest are&#13;
related positively, however, this can only occur along a curve such as AA in&#13;
Figure 1 which requires that in the absence of social securitty the economy's&#13;
rate of capital accumulation must exceed that associated wil:h the Golden Path&#13;
and the rate of return to capital must lie below the populat:ion growth rate.&#13;
If, on the other hand, the rate of return exceeds the population growth rate&#13;
in the absence of social security, then PAYG will tend to move the economy&#13;
further away from the Golden Path on a curve such as AA in Figure 1.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
Interest Rate&#13;
Figure 1A&#13;
.        ?VXI&#13;
A~~~~~BA&#13;
A   FF (s &gt;lo)\          &#13;
Population&#13;
Growth Rate                       %)&#13;
At&#13;
FF (s 7 o) &#13;
- t Payroll Tax&#13;
0&#13;
Fully-Funded System&#13;
In FF, the pension received by a participant equals exactly the&#13;
future value of his tax payments compounded at the market rate of interest,&#13;
the relationship between the social security tax and pension being given by&#13;
equation 11. Moreover, the total supply of capital by the older generation is&#13;
now equal to the sum of their savings (private investment) and their tax&#13;
payments (public investment), i.e.     kt = st 1 + t t1    Substituting equation 11&#13;
into the definition of lifetime income, and ignoring subscripts, k, the supply&#13;
of capital per member of the older generation, may be expressed as:&#13;
k - w - c (r,w)                                                  (9''')&#13;
If, as before, we solve for k, r, and w in a steady-state&#13;
equilibrium, it is clear from an examination of equations 7, 18 and 9... that&#13;
the resulting solutions are independent of the level of payroll taxation. As&#13;
Samuelson (1975, p. 541) notes, "Any increase in 'fully-funded' social&#13;
security merely displaces as much private capital as the public capital it&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
brings into being", the representative individual being indifferent between&#13;
the two forms of ownership as long as each yields exactly the same return. It&#13;
follows that the relationship between the steady-state, equilibrium rate of&#13;
interest and the level of payroll taxation can be represented by horizontal&#13;
lines such as AB and A-B' in Figure 1.  It may be concluded that a fully-&#13;
funded social security system has no capability whatsoever of moving the&#13;
economy towards the steady-state associated with the Golden Rule.&#13;
This result holds as long as the level of taxation is constrained to&#13;
be less than, or equal to, the individual's preferred level, of savings had&#13;
there been no social security.  If the optimal social security system is&#13;
defined by means of individual utility maximization, then, clearly, the&#13;
optimal payroll tax will never be large enough to force private savings to&#13;
zero because this would imply a (private) distortion between the interest rate&#13;
and the marginal rate of substitution between consumption in period one and&#13;
consumption in period two. Maximization of a paternalistic welfare function,&#13;
however, is perfectly consistent with zero private savings. In particular,&#13;
assume that society considers the privately chosen level of' consumption in the&#13;
second period to be inadequate. In this case, maximization of a paternalistic&#13;
welfare function would yield a level of taxation in excess of the&#13;
individualistically determined rate of capital accumulation. Private savings&#13;
would, therefore, be zero and k would equal t. This informiation is sufficient&#13;
to allow the solution of equations 7 and 18 for the equilibrium interest rate&#13;
and wage rate as functions of t, the level of payroll taxation. Moreover,&#13;
totally differentiating the resulting solution yields:&#13;
dinr = -   dlnt &lt; 0                                           (21)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
where n is the ratio of labor income to capital income.&#13;
Unlike equation 2. , which depicted the relationship between changes&#13;
in r and changes in t for PAYG, equation 21, which depicts the same&#13;
relationship for FF, is unambigously negative. It follows that if private&#13;
savings are insufficient to guarantee a socially acceptable level of&#13;
consumption during old age, a paternalistically motivated, fully-funded system&#13;
can move the economy towards its preferred steady-state equilibrium.&#13;
Moreover, if society selects the consumption path associated with the Golden&#13;
Rule, it can be obtained by setting payroll taxation at the appropriate&#13;
level. Returning to Figure 1, if capital accumulation is below the rate&#13;
associated with the Golden Rule, and if B is the point at which private&#13;
savings become zero, then increasing t beyond B will move the steady-state&#13;
economy along a path such as BC towards the Golden Rule equilibrium.&#13;
Alternatively, if the economy is accumulating too much capital, then a FF&#13;
system would move the economy even further away from the Golden Rule&#13;
equilibrium along a path such as BC'.&#13;
This analysis is open to the same type of criticism leveled against&#13;
the Sheshinski and Weiss model (see section II.2). Optimality in their model&#13;
rests on two basic assumptions - an uncertain lifetime and the absence of a&#13;
private annuities market. In Barro, where there is no uncertainty, any&#13;
increase in the social security tax is simply offset by decreasing private&#13;
bequests. In such a model, "the optimal level of social security is clearly&#13;
undetermined" (Sheshinski and Weiss, p. 190). In addition to making lifetime&#13;
uncertain, however, Sheshinski and Weiss also assume that "all annuities are&#13;
supplied by the public sector through a social security system" (p. 192).&#13;
Obviously, if a private market for annuities was incorporated in their model,&#13;
individuals would be able to offset an increase in social security taxes by&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
reducing their participation in the private annuities market and exactly the&#13;
same results, as in Barro, would follow without any implication for the&#13;
optimal size of social security. The discussion of an "optimal" social&#13;
security system by Sheshinski and Weiss, therefore, rests heavily on the&#13;
assumption of exclusive government provision of annuities. Inasmuch as a&#13;
private annuities market does exist, their "optimality" results must be&#13;
qualified. In our model of a paternalistically motivated FF system, each&#13;
individual is taxed by the social security institution to the point where his&#13;
private saving is driven to zero. Then, were a private annuities market&#13;
available to him, it could be argued that he would turn to it for loanable&#13;
funds, and borrow against his future social security benefits and/or his&#13;
future labor income. In this event, the concept of optimality would once&#13;
again be undefined.&#13;
There is considerable doubt, however, whether individuals can&#13;
actually borrow against such future income. As Evans (1982) points out,&#13;
"capital markets are such that it is not possible, or only minimally possible,&#13;
to borrow against future labor income to finance current consumption."&#13;
Similarly, it is equally questionable when "we simply do not know how (even)&#13;
individuals perceive their social wealth" (Leimer and Lesnoy, p. 619), to&#13;
expect the private capital market to lend against future social security&#13;
benefits. Thus, in our treatment of the paternalistic case of FF, it is not&#13;
unrealistic to assume away the possibility of individuals turning to the&#13;
private annuities market for loanable funds when their private savings has&#13;
been driven to zero by the social security institution. Similarly, it would&#13;
be possible to construct a paternalistic version of the Sheshinski and Weiss&#13;
PAYG system in which the individual is obliged by the social security&#13;
authorities to hold more annuities than he would have purchased in the private&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
market. In this case, the existence of a private annuities market is not&#13;
sufficient to ensure that individuals can offset the effects of social&#13;
security. It is also necessary to assume (unrealistically) that individuals&#13;
can borrow against anticipated social security benefits.&#13;
III.2    Long-Run Welfare Implications of Endogenous Retirement and Bequests&#13;
The paternalistic approach developed above can be extended to&#13;
incorporate retirement and a bequest motive. In this section, we explore the&#13;
optimal steady-state solutions for these more general models within a&#13;
paternalistic framework. We start, therefore, with a social welfare function&#13;
of the form:&#13;
W a w (c ) + v(c 2  ct  )                                       (32)&#13;
where, within the relevant range,    aw/lac1&lt;  au/ac1 implying that, compared&#13;
with individual preferences, society attaches more importance to future&#13;
consumption relative to present consumption.&#13;
Fully-Funded System&#13;
Totally differentiating equation 27 with respect to a change in&#13;
payroll taxation and assuming that the individual is aware of the government's&#13;
budget constraint yields:&#13;
dW 'w    dc +    1    dc  + wdd + d%                            (23)&#13;
dtl(dt            -c dt           dt&#13;
ac       (1r)     dt    t&#13;
-  aw  ~1&#13;
where   (l+r) ,   /ac   and reflects society's preference for current relative&#13;
av/ ac&#13;
to future consumption. Assuming that first-period savings have been driven to&#13;
zero by social security, the second period income constraint is:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
c2 + S + aw = w + (l+r)(hIt)                                   (24)&#13;
where h=O/(l+g) is his bequest from the previous period. Since savings are&#13;
zero, we know that k - h+t and that cl aw-t. Finally, noting that from&#13;
equation 7 we have:&#13;
dr      1 1-g + 1- c dw&#13;
dt          k       dt&#13;
we can derive the welfare maximizing level of t by setting dW/dt = 0:&#13;
(r-g) + (r-r) = - d     (l+r)                               (25)&#13;
-it                   dt (l+r)(l+g)&#13;
Hence, it is clear that a paternalistic FF system will yield its maximum&#13;
benefit by moving the economy to the steady-state path defirLed by the Golden&#13;
Rule, only in the absence of a bequest motive. On this path, both society's&#13;
marginal rate of substitution between present and future consumption and the&#13;
marginal return to capital will equal the population growth rate.&#13;
In this more complicated model, it is no longer pc,ssible to derive a&#13;
simple, unambiguous relationship between the rate of interest and the rate of&#13;
taxation (See Appendix). In general, however, if the private individual's&#13;
labor supply and bequests are relatively unresponsive to changes in the wage,&#13;
the interest rate, and taxation, then the likelihood of a negative&#13;
relationship between the rate of interest and taxation is in!creased. In the&#13;
extreme, when these response coefficients are zero, the relationship is that&#13;
given by equatim 21.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
It is unlikely that a social security system would be implemented in&#13;
such a way that all private savings are driven to zero. Nevertheless, it is&#13;
highly likely that, if the objective is to prevent the consumption of a&#13;
particular group in society from falling below socially preferred levels&#13;
during retirement, a social security system would be implemented such that the&#13;
savings of the target group were driven to zero. Provided the system is&#13;
financed on a fully-funded basis, total savings - the sum of private savings&#13;
and payroll taxation - by the non-target group would, of course, remain&#13;
unchanged. This approach would thus achieve the objective of ensuring minimum&#13;
consumption standards for everyone during old age, without affecting the&#13;
savings behavior of the non-target group.&#13;
Pay-as-you-go System&#13;
Lastly, we demonstrate the consequences of our paternalistic&#13;
assumption for Hu's model of a PAYG system. Corresponding to equatkn 23 we&#13;
have:&#13;
dt   -   ldt +   I  (dt    + (w-t-z) d+   d                       126)&#13;
ac1        l+rdt                     t&#13;
where the price of retirement - w - in FF is replaced by the corresponding&#13;
price - w-t-z - for PAYG. Recall that this arises because in the Hu model,&#13;
the individual is unaware of the government's budget constraint (see section&#13;
II. . Making use of the budget constraints for lifetime income and for&#13;
second period income (see equation 2 ') and using the relationship between&#13;
the equilibrium interest rate and wage rate (equation 7) , we can derive the&#13;
optimal value of t by setting equation 26 equal to zero. This yields:&#13;
dw  -         dk           zd (l+r) +         + (l    -   dz     (27&#13;
d-t gr      +  t (r-r)      do-   r)+(l-;) +1-a                  (27&#13;
-(r-                ~~~~dt (1+g)                 -d&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
Unlike equaticn 25, equatim 27 only indicates the optimality of the Golden&#13;
Rule if both the bequest motive and the retirement decision are absent. The&#13;
former, of course, implies da/dt = 0. The latter may be seen by examining&#13;
dz/dt. In PAYG with retirement endogenous, the governnment"s budget is&#13;
balanced when:&#13;
zOa = (1-0a) t&#13;
Although in the model the individual behaves as though he Ls unaware of this&#13;
constraint, the model's equilibrium does, of course, impose this constraint.&#13;
It follows that:&#13;
dz    1-Ox      t + z  da&#13;
dz   (lOa) - (t     Z)c&#13;
dt   (Oa          0    dt&#13;
If labor supply is fixed,   da/dt = 0 . Recalling that     0 = 1/(2+g), with no&#13;
bequest motive and retirement exogenous, equatim 27 collapses to:&#13;
dw (r-g) + dk (r-r)&#13;
Thus, in the absence of a bequest motive, PAYG would indicate the optimality&#13;
of the Golden Rule only if labor supply is fixed. This resault for the&#13;
paternalistic model parallels that obtained by Hu (1979) in his&#13;
individualistic model. It differs from the result for the FF system because&#13;
of the difference in assumption regarding the individual's awareness of the&#13;
government's budget constraint.&#13;
As with the FF case, the relationship between the rate of interest&#13;
and the rate of payroll taxation is ambiguous [ see equations 33, Y' and 35 of&#13;
Hu (1979)]. Nevertheless, the basic point remains clear: in choosing between&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
a (paternalistic) FF system and a PAYG system, one needs to know where the&#13;
economy is in relation to the Golden Path and whether or not the introduction&#13;
of a social security system modifies the Golden Path. Consider the following&#13;
possibility. Omitting the bequest motive, assume that, in the absence of any&#13;
form of social security, the rate of interest is observed to lie above the&#13;
rate of population growth. That is, the rate of accumulation in the economy&#13;
is less than that associated with the Golden Path. Assume further that the&#13;
government investigates the relationship between the rate of interest and the&#13;
rate of payroll taxation in a PAYG system and finds that it is negative. Is&#13;
this sufficient information on which to base a recommendation to institute a&#13;
PAYG system? The answer is no, because the introduction of a PAYG system may&#13;
itself modify the Golden Path. If the behavior of individuals is such that&#13;
the PAYG system causes a distortion in the labor market, the optimum long-run&#13;
equilibrium for the economy is no longer characterized by the equality of the&#13;
rates of interest and population growth (see equation 27) . In fact, the PAYG&#13;
system may move the economy towards the (now irrelevant) Golden Path and away&#13;
from the modified Golden Path. Thus, where social security is presumed to&#13;
influence total capital accumulation, we conclude that an investigation of&#13;
optimality requires information on the relationship between the rate of&#13;
interest and the rate of population growth and on the relationship between the&#13;
modified Golden Path and original Golden Path.&#13;
Conclusion&#13;
This paper has analyzed the major results in the social security&#13;
literature of recent years, clarifying the underlying assumptions responsible&#13;
for their diversity. It has extended the analysis of both 'positive' issues -&#13;
the effects of social security on capital accumulation and labor supply - and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
normative  issues-whether social security can move the economy to its optimal&#13;
steady-state growth path. In the process, the paper introduced and analyzed a&#13;
paternalistic motivation for social security. In the analysiis of both&#13;
positive and normative issues, the results are shown to depend on whether the&#13;
system is fully funded (FF) or financed on a pay-as-you-go (PAYG) basis.&#13;
With respect to the positive issues, the effect of' social security&#13;
on capital accumulation is neutral if one common condition is fulfilled for&#13;
both FF and PAYG systems and if one other system-specific condition is met.&#13;
The common condition is that the representative individual recognize the&#13;
budget constraint faced by the social security system. For a FF system, the&#13;
second condition is that the rates of return in the private and public sectors&#13;
be the same, and for a PAYG system, it is that the representative individual&#13;
focus on the net, rather than the gross, value of bequests. Provided these&#13;
conditions hold, neutrality is assured whether or not labor supply is&#13;
endogenous. For each system, if either or both of the conditions are not&#13;
fulfilled, capital accumulation will be affected.&#13;
When labor supply is made endogenous, the importance of the common&#13;
condition - that the individual recognize the social securit:ys budget&#13;
constraint - is increased. If this condition is not fulfilled when labor&#13;
supply is endogenous then, not only is capital accumulation affected, but also&#13;
the presence of a social security system introduces a distortion into the&#13;
labor market. Moreover, with labor supply endogenous, the likelihood that the&#13;
common condition be fulfilled is reduced since the fulfilment of that&#13;
condition now requires an expectation on the part of the representative&#13;
individual that the labor supply behavior of all other individuals matches his&#13;
own.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
Our focus on both capital accumulation and the labor market allows&#13;
us to draw on empirical evidence for savings behavior and labor supply&#13;
behavior in the U.S. to shed light on the two assumptions required for&#13;
neutrality of a PAYG system. Although scant, both sources of empirical&#13;
evidence are consistent in rejecting the joint fulfilment of the two critical&#13;
assumptions. The results do not therefore, support the neutrality hypothesis&#13;
of Barro but suggest as in the Hu model the possibility of both a non-neutral&#13;
effect on capital accumulation and the creation of a labor market distortion.&#13;
With respect to normative issues, the paper contrasted the accepted&#13;
approach of defining optimality by reference to individual utility&#13;
maximization with a paternalistic definition of optimality. In particular,&#13;
the paper explored Samuelson's observation that society may adopt a social&#13;
security system that forces individuals to "save more than they otherwise&#13;
would thereby ensuring that the myopic vision of the individual does not lead&#13;
to socially unacceptable levels of consumption when old. It is shown that a&#13;
paternalistically-motivated FF system that drives private savings to zero can&#13;
influence capital accumulation even if the two critical conditions for&#13;
neutrality are fulfilled. Paternalism of this kind, however, does not affect&#13;
a PAYG social security. Since all social security transfers are&#13;
intergenerational rather than intertemporal in this case, it follows that a&#13;
PAYG system cannot be used to offset individual myopia. For a PAYG system,&#13;
paternalism would have to involve some attempt to limit the amount individuals&#13;
bequeath, a withinrperiod decision that is not affected by myopia. Since this&#13;
may prove administratively difficult within the context of a social security&#13;
system, we conclude that, unlike a FF system, a PAYG system will only&#13;
influence capital accumulation if one or both of the basic neutrality&#13;
conditions are violated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
We also show that the effect on capital accumulation is system-&#13;
specific. For example, in a simple model that excludes bequests and labor&#13;
supply decisions, a paternalistic FF system will move an economy closer to the&#13;
steady-state path associated with the Golden Rule only if the rate of capital&#13;
accumulation is below that characterizing the Golden Path. A PAYG system, on&#13;
the other hand, will move the economy towards the Golden Path only when the&#13;
rate of capital accumulation on the existing path is above that associated&#13;
with the Golden Rule. Thus, in choosing between systems, it is important to&#13;
take account of their effects on capital accumulation and of the economy's&#13;
present location relative to the Golden Path.&#13;
Finally, in more complicated models in which both bequests and labor&#13;
supply are endogenous, the introduction of a social security system implies&#13;
that the optimal steady-state path is no longer that described by the Golden&#13;
Rule. The optimum will depart from the Golden Path both because bequests&#13;
provide a return - an increase in the utility of the donor in excess of the&#13;
rate of interest - and because of the possibility of static welfare losses in&#13;
the labor market. Unlike the former cause - the bequest motive - of a&#13;
departure from the Golden Rule, the latter cause - a labor market distortion -&#13;
is a direct consequence of the social security system. As a result, the&#13;
introduction or modification of a social security system may move the economy&#13;
towards the now-irrelevant Golden Path (appropriately modified to allow for&#13;
bequests) and away from the new steady-state optimum (which must also&#13;
accommodate the static welfare loss in the labor market) . lhis raises at&#13;
least a theoretical possibility that, even though a social security system may&#13;
influence capital accumulation, the optimal steady-state path with positive&#13;
taxes and benefits may be less preferable than the existing path on which&#13;
taxes and benefits are zero.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
Appendix to Section 111.2&#13;
Fully-Funded System&#13;
Since the individual's savings in period one are zero, c1 = w-t. In&#13;
addition, since the individual is fully employed during the first period of&#13;
his life, his period-one labor supply is also uniquely determined. The&#13;
individual retains choice, however, over the distribution of his income among&#13;
second-period consumption, retirement, and his bequest. Thus, the individual&#13;
in period 2 is assumed to:&#13;
2&#13;
max v(c , a, @&#13;
subject to  c + S + wa= w + (1+r) (h+t)&#13;
where we have used the government's budget constraint - za = t(l+r) +t(W-c -&#13;
to eliminate the pension (za) and second-period taxes (t(1- ).&#13;
The first order conditions can be solved for    c , a and 3.   In&#13;
particular, since h + t is the available capital stock (k), we have:&#13;
a = a(w, r, k)&#13;
a, &lt;Q a2 &gt;Ql a3 &gt; 0&#13;
and        a = O(w, r, k)&#13;
1 &gt;a   a2 &gt;Q   83 &gt; 0&#13;
Provided the negative effect of a higher price for retirement dominates the&#13;
positive effect of a larger income, an increase in the wage will reduce the&#13;
length of retirement. Both an increase in r and k, however, will increase&#13;
retirement as a result of positive income effects. Similarly, bequests can be&#13;
assumed to increase as a result of increases in w, r, and k because of&#13;
positive income effects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
Total labor supply is now given by the sum of (1-E) from period-&#13;
one individuals and 0(1-a) from period-two individuals. To ensure&#13;
equilibrium in the labor market, therefore, we require:&#13;
w = f (     -) = f (LiO)&#13;
K        Ok&#13;
We can now derive the relationship between t and r. Using the&#13;
condition for labor market equilibrium, the factor price frontier (equation 7&#13;
in the text), the fact that k = t + a, and the behavioral functions for&#13;
a and 1, we have five equations to solve for the five unknowns - w, r, k,&#13;
a and a. Taking the total differential of this system and expressing in&#13;
elasticity notation, we obtain:&#13;
-f(l- ak) (l-m)&#13;
dlnr = m(l- a )(    -   T) - (1 - Ikm)(r *C- a 7     - dlnt&#13;
k   w    r            i    w     r&#13;
where     n1 = wL/rK&#13;
m = a/k &lt; 1 - private ownership of capital&#13;
a = -Oalw/(1-Oa)         &gt; 0           - partial elasticities of labor&#13;
ar = -Oa2r/(1-0cQ        &lt; 0             supply&#13;
ak = -Oa3k/(1-Ga)        &lt; 0&#13;
= a w/O               &gt; 0           -  partial elaLsticities&#13;
of                                                   supply of bequests&#13;
%r =2r/a                 &gt;0&#13;
(k '63k/1                &gt;0&#13;
and n   -wkO/f'(1-0O) &gt; 0 - partial elasticity of labor demand.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
The relationship between r and t is indeterminate. Relatively simple&#13;
conditions will, however, ensure a negative relationship. For example, if&#13;
im &lt; 1 and G -     r 11 &lt; 0, r and t are negatively related.  If labor supply is&#13;
fixed and there are no bequests, the relationship collapses to that reported&#13;
as equaticn 21 in the text.&#13;
Pay-as-you-e-o System&#13;
For a PAYG system in which the individual focusses on gross bequests&#13;
and is unaware of the government's budget constraint, the relationship between&#13;
r and t can be derived immediately from Hu s results since the&#13;
individualistic and paternalistic models coincide. The three critical&#13;
behavioral functions in this model are those for bequests, savings and labor&#13;
supply. Recall also that because the individual is unaware of the&#13;
government's budget constraint, the social security variables affect private&#13;
behavior. Accordingly, we introduce the following definitions. In addition&#13;
to the partial elasticities of labor supply defined above, we also have:&#13;
at = Otat /(1-0a         &lt; 0&#13;
and        a = -0 a4/(l-0a)         &lt; 0&#13;
where     a4 = aa/az (see Hu (1979) p. 277). The partial elasticities for the&#13;
supply of capital (i.e., savings and bequests) are given by:&#13;
(s     +  1) w/k&#13;
(s2+ 82) r/k&#13;
'k 83(s3 + 1)&#13;
Ct =-(s1 + a1) t/k&#13;
and         z =(s4 + 84) z/k&#13;
where 84 and   84 are  as/az and   a8/az respectively (see Hu (1979) p. 280).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
With these definitions, and using equations 34 and 35 in Hu (1979) p. 280, and&#13;
the equilibrium relationship between w and r, we obtain:&#13;
dlnr                *[ q   + a    -a (a+ °t) + a(atCZ    -   Zt&#13;
dlnt   [a1 (Cw- ]I~  -a2          r    +          ar- aT a( -.TI              I'ar&#13;
I   w    r)   a(w- "lr+     +a3fn(ctz- af i         (    r+(w        0r'&#13;
where   a1 = t(l-ak), a2    t(l-k), and a3 = (t+z)&#13;
Although complicated, this expression can be analyzed by exploring the&#13;
consequences of making labor supply and bequests exogenous. If labor supply&#13;
is fixed, then   q + 0 for all i.   And if bequests are zero, the&#13;
C elasticities collapse to the e elasticities of the text, and the&#13;
relationship between r and t is captured by equation 20 of the text. Thus, as&#13;
the responsiveness of labor supply and bequests becomes less, the likelihood&#13;
that r and t are positively related increases.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
References&#13;
Barro, R.J., "Are Government Bonds Net Wealth?", Journal of Political&#13;
Economy, Vol. 82, No. 6, November-December 1974, pp. 1095-117.&#13;
Blinder, A.S., R.M. Gordon, and D.E. Wise, "Reconsidering the Work&#13;
Disincentive Effects of Social Security," National Tax Journal, Vol.&#13;
33, No. 4, Decem1-r 1980, pp. 431-442.&#13;
Boskin, M.J., "Social Security and Retirement Decisions," Economic Inquiry,&#13;
Volume 15, January 1977, pp. 1-25.&#13;
Boskin, M.J., and M.D. Hurd, "The Effect of Social Security on Early&#13;
Retirement," Journal of Public Economics, Vol. 10, No. 3, December&#13;
1978, pp. 361-378.&#13;
Burbidge, J.B., "Government Debt in an Overlapping-Generations Model with&#13;
Bequests and Gifts", American Economic Review, Vol. 73, No. 1, March&#13;
1983, pp. 222-7.&#13;
Carmichael, J., "On Barro's Theorem of Debt Neutrality: The Irrelevance of&#13;
Net Wealth," American Economic Review, Vol. 72, No. 1, March 1982,&#13;
pp. 202-213.&#13;
David, M. and P.L. Menchik, "The Effects of Social Security on Wealth&#13;
Accumulation and Bequests", paper presented at Workshop in Public&#13;
Economics, Queens University, September 1981.&#13;
Diamond, P.A., "National Debt in a Neoclassical Growth Model", American&#13;
Economic Review, Vol. 55, No. 5, December, 1965 pp. 1126-50.&#13;
Drazen, A., "Government Debt, Human Capital, and Bequests in a Lifecycle&#13;
Model", Journal of Political Economy, Vol. 86, No.3, June 1978, pp.&#13;
505-16.&#13;
Evans, O., "Social Security and Household Saving in the United States: A Re-&#13;
Examination," Departmental Memo DM/82/75, International Monetary&#13;
Fund, November 1982.&#13;
Feldstein, M., "Perceived Wealth in Bonds and Social Security: A Comment,"&#13;
Journal of Political Economy Vol. 84, No. 2, April 1976, pp. 331-336.&#13;
, "Social Security and Private Saving: Reply," Journal of&#13;
Political Economy, Vol. 90, No. 3, 1982, pp. 630-642.&#13;
Hu, S.C., "Social Security, The Supply of Labor, and Capital Accumulation,"&#13;
American Economic Review, Vol. 69, No. 3, June 1979, pp. 274-283.&#13;
Kotlikoff, L.J., "Testing the Theory of Social Security and Life Cycle&#13;
Accumulation", American Economic Review, Vol. 69, No. 3, June 1979,&#13;
pp. 396-410.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
Kotlikoff, L.J., and L.H. Summers, "The Role of Intergerational Transfers in&#13;
Aggregate Capital Accumulation", Journal of Political Economy, Vol.&#13;
89, No. 4, August 1981, pp. 706-732.&#13;
Leimer, D.R., and S.D. Lesnoy, "Social Security and Private Savings: New Time-&#13;
Series Evidence," Journal of Political Economy, Vol. 90, No. 3, 1982,&#13;
pp. 606-629.&#13;
Mirer, T.W., "The Wealth-Age Relation Among the Aged," American Economic&#13;
Review, Vol. 69, No. 3, June 1979, pp. 435-443.&#13;
Samuelson, P.A., "Optimal Social Security in a Life-Cycle Growth Model,"&#13;
International Economic Review, Vol. 16, October 1975, pp. 539-544.&#13;
Schneider, F., and W.W. Pommerehne, "Free Riding and Collective Action: An&#13;
Experiment in Public Microeconomics", Quarterly Journal of Economics,&#13;
November l'981, 4, pp. 689-704.&#13;
Sheshinski, E., and Y. Weiss, "Uncertainty and Optimal Social Security&#13;
Systems", Quarterly Journal of Economics, Vol. 96, No. 2, May 1981,&#13;
pp. 189-206.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
World Bank                           Aggregate Demand and                  Capital Market Imperfec-&#13;
Macroeconomic Imbalances              tions and Economic&#13;
Publications                         In Thailand: Simulations              Development&#13;
with the SIAM 1 Model                 Vinayak V. Bhatt and&#13;
of Related                           Wafik Grais                           Alan R. Roe&#13;
Interest                             Focuses on the demand-side adjust-    World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
ments of the Thai economy to lower    No. 338. July 1979. 87 pages&#13;
agricultural growth and to higher     (including footnotes).&#13;
energy prices. Discusses policy&#13;
measures and structural changes that  Stock No. WP-0338. $3.00.&#13;
might enable the economy to over-&#13;
come these problems and continue to&#13;
maintain high GDP rates of growth.    The Changing ac    ature of&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper Nlo.   Empliain ort iac   adev    oI ng&#13;
448. April 1981. 70 pages (including  Cmpou  tines    for        I   ng&#13;
2 appendixes).                        Countries&#13;
Stock No. WP-0448. $3.00.             Albert C. Cizauskas&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
409. July 1980. 43 pages (including&#13;
An Analysis of                        3 annexes).&#13;
Developing Country                    Stock No. WP-0409. $3.00.&#13;
Adjustment Experience and             Adjustment Experiences in&#13;
Growth Prospects of the               the 1970s: Low-income Asia&#13;
Semi-Industrial Countries             Christine Wallich                     Compounding and Dis-&#13;
Frederick Jaspersen                   This background study for World       counting Tables for&#13;
This background study for WordDevelopment Report 1981 examines              Project Evaluation&#13;
ThisevelopmntReporto98   l examines   low-income South Asia's adjustment    J. Price Gittinger, editor&#13;
the successfuv process of adjustment  to the external shocks of the 1970s,  Easily comprehensible, convenient&#13;
to external "shocks" of the 1970s     especially those factors that helped  tables for project preparation and&#13;
(rising prices of oil imports, reduced  make the effects of these external  analysis.&#13;
demand for exports, slower economic   developments less severe in the&#13;
growth in the OECD countries) in the  region than in other parts of the     The Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
semi-industrial developing countries.  developing world.                    1973; 7th printing, 1982. 143 pages.&#13;
Presents an analytical framework for  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    LC 75-186503. ISBN 0-8018-1604-1,&#13;
quantifying the effects of demand     487. August 1981. iu + 39 pages       $6.00 paperback.&#13;
management and structural adjust-     (including references).               Arabic: WorldBank,1973. (Available&#13;
ment In forty-two countries, with par-                                      Aai:WrdBn,17.(vial&#13;
ticular reference to Uruguay, Brazil,  Stock No. WP-0487. $3.00.            from ILS, 1715 ConnecticutAvenue,&#13;
Republic of Korea, and Turkey.                                              N.W., Washington, D.C. 20009, U.S.A.)&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    Aspects of Development                $4.00 paperback.&#13;
477. August 1981. 132 pages (Including  Bank Management                     French: Tables d'interets composes et&#13;
3 appendixes).                        William Diamond and                   d'actualisation. Economica, 4th print-&#13;
Stock /Yo. WP-04 77. $5.00.           V. S. Raghavan                        ing, 1979.&#13;
Deals exclusively with the manage-    ISBN 2- 7178-0205-3, 36 francs.&#13;
Adjustment In                         ment of development banks. The        Spanish: Tablas de interes compuesto y&#13;
Low-Income Africa                     book is divided into eight sections,  de descuento para evaluaci6n de proyec-&#13;
Robert Liebenthal                     each dealing with one aspect of       tos. Editorial Tecnos, 1973: 4th print-&#13;
This background study for World       of the various ways of dealing        ing, 1980.&#13;
Deuelopment Report 1981 analyzes      with them.                            ISBN 84-309-0716-5, 380 pesetas.&#13;
the adjustment to external shocks&#13;
during the 1970s made by a group      EDI Series in Economic Deuelopment.&#13;
of middle-income and low-Income       The Johns Hopkins Uniuersity Press,   A Conceptual Approach to&#13;
African countries, with particular    1982. 311 pages.                      the Analysis of External Debt&#13;
reference to Kenya, Tanzania,                                               of the Developing Countries&#13;
Senegal, and Sudan.                   LC 81-48174. ISBN 0-8018-2571-7,&#13;
$29.95 hardcover; ISBN 0-8018-2572-5,  Robert Z. Aliber&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.    $12.95 paperback.                     World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
486. August 1981. il  + 56 pages                                            421. October 1980. 25 pages (Including&#13;
(including bibi0ography).                                                   appendix, references).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0486. $3.00.                                                   Stock No. WP-0421. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Development Banks                    Developments in and                  Food Policy Issues In&#13;
William Diamond                      Prospects for the External           Low-income Countries&#13;
Operating experiences that serve as a  Debt of the Developing             Edweird Clay and others&#13;
practical guide for developing coun-  Countries: 197080                  A background study for World&#13;
tries, with a selected list and      and Beyond                           Development Report 1981. Discusses&#13;
summary description of some          Nicholas C. Hope                     food dlistribution-especially its&#13;
development banks.                                       f Wl Insecurity in the face of external&#13;
This ackgoundstudytar  orldeconomic pressures and potential&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press,  Development Report 1981 analyzes     conflicts with internal production&#13;
1957; 5th printing, 1969.141 pages  the debt situation and its implica-   concerns-in general and with&#13;
(including 2 appendixes, index).    tions for future borrowing.           reference to Bangladesh, Zambia.&#13;
LC 57-13429. ISBN 0-8018-0708-5,     World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   and Imdia.&#13;
$5.00 (f3.50) paperback.             488. August 1981. 70 pages (including  World Bank Staff Working Paper llo.&#13;
2 annexes, references).              473. August 1981. Wii + 115 pages.&#13;
Development Finance Com-             Stock No. WP-0488. $3.00.            Stock lYo. WP-04 73. $5.00.&#13;
panies: Aspects cf Policy&#13;
and Operation                        Energy Prices, Substitution,         A General Equilibrium&#13;
William Diamond. editor;             and Optimal Borrowing In             Analt sis of Foreign&#13;
essays by E. T. Kuiper,              the Short Run: An Analysis           Exchange Shortages In a&#13;
Douglas Gustafson, and               of Adjustment in Oil-                Developing Economy&#13;
P. M. Mathew                         Importing Developing                 Kiemal Dervis, Jaime de Melo,&#13;
The Johns Hlopkins University Press,  Countries                           and 'iherman Robinson&#13;
1968.130 pages (Including appendix,  Ricardo Martin and                   Examines the consequences of alter-&#13;
index).                              Marcelo Selowsky                     native adjustment mechanisms to&#13;
LC-68-27738. ISBN 0-8018-0166-4,     Develops a short-term model for      foreign exchange shortages in semi-&#13;
$5.00 (3.025) paperback.             evaluating the adjustment (par-     industrial economies. Compares&#13;
French: Les socites financieres de  ticularly, external borrowing) of oil-  devaluation to two forms of import&#13;
developpement: quelques aspects de   importing developing countries to the  rationing and finds that adjusting by&#13;
leur politique et de leurs activites.  Increases in oil prices during the  rationing is much more costly in&#13;
(Available fr-ee from the World Bank  1970s. Discusses the borrowing      terms of lost gross domestic product.&#13;
Washvai  fn, D. C)                   strategies that can be expected in the  World 1Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Washington, D.C.)          ~~future and the demands that will be  45 aur     91   2pgs(nld&#13;
Spanish: Las compahias flnancieras   made on multilateral institutions.   443. January 1981. 32 pages (includ-&#13;
de desarrollo: aigunos aspectos de su                                     ing references).&#13;
polftica y de sus actividades. Editorial  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  Stock No. WP-0443. $3.00.&#13;
Tecnos, 1969.                        466. July 1981. 77 pages (including&#13;
300 pesetas.                         footnotes, references).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0466. $3.00.                NEW&#13;
Development Prospects&#13;
of Capital Surplus Oil-              Exchange Rate Adjustment             Growth and Structural&#13;
Exporting Countriles: Iraq,          under Generalized Currency           A4dUustment In East Asia&#13;
Kuwait, Libya, Qatar,                Floating: Comparative                Farvez Hasan&#13;
Saudi Arabia, UAE                    Analysis among Developing            Analyzes the economic performance&#13;
Ru   1if HablNitzel                  Countries                            of the live large market economies of&#13;
Romeo M. Bautista          ~~East Asia-K~orea, Thailand. the&#13;
This background study for World      Romeo M. Bautista                    Philippines, Malaysia. and&#13;
Development Report 1981              Examines the experiences of twenty-  Indonesia-during the last two&#13;
discusses the production strategies  two developing countries in adapting  decades; focuses on the key factors&#13;
and the development policies of the  to the generalized floating of the   explaiming their remarkable economic&#13;
capital-surplus oil-exporting        world's major currencies since 1973  and social progress; and identifies the&#13;
countries.                           and discusses the Implications that  main economic issues for the 1980s.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   currency floating has on policymaking  World Blank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
483. August 1981. 53 pages (including  tions for further research.        529.1982. 42 pages.&#13;
sttistical tables).                  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.   ISBN 0-8213-0102-0. $3.00.&#13;
Stock No. WP-0483. $3.00.            436. October 1980. 99 pages (including&#13;
appendix).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0436. $3.00.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Intemational Ajdjstment in          Notes on the Mechanics of           ect appraisal. To give substance to&#13;
the 1980s                           Growth and Debt                     the applied and policy dimensions,&#13;
Vija JoshiBenjaminB. Kingmany of the readings are drawn from&#13;
Vijay Joshi                          venjamin B. King                   the experience of development prac-&#13;
A backgound study for World         A practical model to explore the way  titioners and relate to such important&#13;
Development Report 1981. Analyzes   In which capital inflow from abroad  sectors as agriculture, industry,&#13;
the macroeconomics of international  affects economic growth.           power, urban services, foreign trade,&#13;
a4justment. Highlights potential                                        and employment. The principles&#13;
market failures and areas for       The Johns Hopkins University Press,  outlined are therefore relevant to a&#13;
intervention.                       1968. 69 pages (including 4 annexes).  host of development problems.&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  LC 68-8701. ISBN 0-8018-0338-1, $5.00  The Johns Hopkins Uniuersity Pess.&#13;
485. August 1982. 57 pages.         (0     per     .                    February 1983. About 304 pages.&#13;
ISBN1 0-8213-0062-8. $3.00.                                             LC 82-7716. ISBN 0-8018-2803-1,&#13;
The Policy Experience of            $35.00 hardcover; ISBN 0-8018-2804-X,&#13;
Twelve Less Developed               $12.95 paperback.&#13;
NEW                             Countries, 1973-1978&#13;
Bela Balassa                        Private Bank Lending to&#13;
The Nature of Credit                Uses the methodology applied in the  Developing Countries&#13;
Markets In Developing               author's The Newly Industrializing  Richard O'Brien&#13;
Countries: A Framework              Developing Countries after the Oil&#13;
for Policy Analysis                 Crisis" (World Bank Staff Working   A background study for World&#13;
Arvind Virmani                      Paper No. 473, October 1980) to     Development Report 1981.&#13;
examine the policy experience of    Describes the evolution of relation-&#13;
The central purpose of the paper Is to  twelve less developed countries in  ships between private banks and&#13;
analyze various forrns of govemment  the period following the quadrupling  developing countries.&#13;
intervention in the loan market in  of oil prices in 1973-74 and the    World Bank Staff Working Paper No&#13;
terms of their effect on efficiency.  world recession of 1974-75.       482. August 1981. ui + 54 pages&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  (Including appendix, bibliography).&#13;
524.1982. 204 pages.                449. April 1981. 36 pages (including  Stock No. WP-0482. $3.00.&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0019-9. $5.00.          appendix).&#13;
Stock No. WP-0449. $3.00.&#13;
Private Capital Flows to&#13;
The Nzewly- Industrializing .Developing Countries and&#13;
Developing Countries after          The Political Structure of          Their Determinations:&#13;
the OiH Crisis                      the N4ew Protectionism              Historical Perspective,&#13;
Bela Balassa                        Douglas R. Nelson                   Recent Experience, and&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  This background study for World     Future Prospects&#13;
437. October 1980. 5 7 pages (Including  Development Report 1981        Alex Fleming&#13;
appendix).                          presents a political-economic&#13;
analysis of what has been called the  A backgound study for World&#13;
Stock No. WP-0437. $3.00.           "new protectionism."                Development Report 1981.&#13;
Discusses the nature and determina-&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper ('o.  tion of recent private capital flows to&#13;
Mlo-tes4on the Analysis of          4-71. July 1981. 57 pages (including  developing countries. Focuses on&#13;
Capital Flows to Developing         references).                        those flows passing through the&#13;
Nations and the                     Stock No. WP-04 71. $3.00.          prospects for and constraints on&#13;
"Recycling" Problem                                                     developing countries' continuing&#13;
Ralph C. Bryant                                                         access to the intemational capital&#13;
A backgound study for World             NEW                             markets.&#13;
Development Report 1981.                                                World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
Summarizes and criticizes the con-  Pricing Policy for Develop-         484. August 1981. 41 pages.&#13;
ventional analysis of the Interrela-  ment Management&#13;
tions between financial markets in  Gerald M. Meier                     Stock No. WP-0484. $3.00.&#13;
the Industrialized countries and capi-&#13;
tal flows to the developing nations.  Presupposing no formal training in&#13;
economics, it explains the essential  Private Direct Foreign&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  elements of a price system, the     Investment in Developing&#13;
476. August 1981. 67 pages.         functions of prices, the various    Countries&#13;
Stock No. WP-04 76. $3.00.          policies that a govemrment might     K Billerbeck and Y. Yasugi&#13;
pursue In cases of market failure,  K.ilebcanY.aug&#13;
and the principles of public pricing of  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
goods and services provided by       48. July 1979. iu + 97 pages (Includo-&#13;
governrment enterprises. It also pro-  ing 2 annexes).&#13;
vides the would-be practitioner with  3&#13;
an appreciation of the underlying   Stock No. WP-0348. $5.00.&#13;
logical structure of cost-benefit proj.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Structural Adjustment              impilcations in terms of income&#13;
Policies in Developing             generation, external deflcit, and&#13;
Short-Run Macro-Economic           Economies                           inflation.&#13;
Adjustment Policies in              Bela Balassa                       World /3ank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
South Korea: A Quantitative        Examines structural adjustment      513. June 1982. 93 pages (including&#13;
Analysis                           policies (policy responses to extemal  appenCtlx).&#13;
Sweder van Wijnbergen              shocks, such as the quadrupling of  ISBN 0-8213-0023-7. $3.00.&#13;
oil prices and the world recession of&#13;
An analysis of the startling reversal of  the 1970s) of developing countries.&#13;
performance of the South Korean    Considers reforms in production     WorlFd Debt Tables&#13;
economy in 1979 and 1980 compared  incentives, incentives to save and to Acopltoofdaonhexerl&#13;
with the preceding flfteen years, and  invest, public investments, sectoral  A compilation of data on the exteal&#13;
an exploration of the short-run    policies, and monetary policies, and  public and publIcly-guaranteed debt&#13;
macro-economic policy options      comments on the Interdependence of  of 101 developing countries plus&#13;
available to Korea in 1981. Highlights  the various policy measures and on  eighteen additional tables of private&#13;
the role of commercial banks, foreign  the intemational environment in  and nonguaranteed debt from the&#13;
capital inflows, and money markets  which they operate.                World Bank Debtor Reporting&#13;
and the use of credit obtained from                                    Systeni. Describes the nature, con-&#13;
these sources to flnance fixed and  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  tent, and coverage of the data,&#13;
working capital.                   464. July 1981. 36 pages.           reviews the external debt of 101&#13;
$3.00.        ~~countiles through 198L contains&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  Stock No. WP-0464. $3.00.          tables on external public debt out-&#13;
510. Nouember 1981. iu + 178 pages                                     standing, commitments, disburse-&#13;
(including 3 appendixes).                                              ments, service payments, and net&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0000-8. $5.00Q              NEW                            borrowings of 101 developing coun-&#13;
tries, by country, 1972-1981.&#13;
Structural Aspects of              (EC-167/81). December 1982. Annual.&#13;
NEW                             Turkish Inflation:                 About .300 pages.&#13;
1950-1979                          ISSN 0253-2859. $75.00.&#13;
State Finances in India             M. Ataman Aisoy                    Compiater tapes containing the data&#13;
A three-volume set of papers that  Inflation has been one of the major  bases for the World Debt Tables are&#13;
explores a range of issues relating to  problems of the Turkish economy  available from the Publications&#13;
the nature of intergovemmental fiscal  during the postwar period. This paper  Distritiution Unit, World Bank. The&#13;
relations In India.                 develops alternative inflation models  tapes are avaliable to intemational&#13;
and analyzes their performance in  agencles and official nonprofit agen-&#13;
light of the Turkish experience In  cies ol member goverments at a&#13;
Vol. I.: Revenue Sharing           order to provide a framework on     nominal fee: For Information concem-&#13;
In India                            which a more realistic macro model  ing fees for other organizations,&#13;
Christine Wallich                   can be developed.                  please! write to the addressee listed&#13;
Deals specifically with the principles  World Bank Staff Working Paper No.  above.,&#13;
of revenue sharing in India.        540. 1982. 118 pages.              Supplements to World Debt Tables are&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0098-9. $5.00.          issuecl periodically as information&#13;
VoL II: India-Studies In                                               becomes available; the current&#13;
State Finances                                                          updates are Included with orders for&#13;
Christine Wallich                       NEW                            WorldDebt Tables.&#13;
Examines in detail the implications of&#13;
revenue sharing for project finance.  Thailand: An Analysis of         Tepa&#13;
Structural and Nuon-                The Inipact of Contratual Saving, on&#13;
Structural and Mon-  ~     Reource M0obilizcation and Ailocatlon:&#13;
VoL 11l: The Measurement of         Structural Adjustments             The cxpeience of Malaysia&#13;
Tax Effort of State Govern-         Arne Drud, Waflk Grais, and         Soca Security funds in Singapore&#13;
nients, 1973-1976                   Dusan Vujovic                       and thie Philippines: Ramcations of&#13;
Investment Policies&#13;
Raja J. Chelliah and                This study was prepared as a&#13;
Niarain Sinha                       background paper for the preparation  Invenstenta of SociLa  SecuLity s ua d&#13;
Attempts to evaluate the tax perfor-  of a structural-adjustmIent loan to  and ltperience&#13;
mance of particular states in terms of  Thaland and Is a follow-up to a pre-  Partharathl Shome and&#13;
the average tax effort of all states.  vious paper entitled "Aggregate  Katrine Anderson Salto&#13;
Demand and Macroeconomic            World fLink Reprint Series: Nlumber 144.&#13;
World Bank Working Paper No. 523.   Imbalances In Thailand Comparative  Reprinted from The Malayan economic Rew, uoV .&#13;
September 1982. vol. 1, 85 pages, vol. II,  statistics are used, within the frame-  23. no. 2 (April 1978).54-72: Labour and Soiety,&#13;
186 pages, vol. iII, 85 pages.      work of a four-sector macroeconomic  wol. 5. no. 1 (January 1980).19-30: and The Indian&#13;
model, to assess alternative ways of  Joumal of Economics, wol. 60, part 3, no. 238&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0013-X. ol. 1, $3.00, ol I/  macroeconomic adUustment in the  (January 1980).349-60.&#13;
$5.00, vol. III, $3.00.             Thal economy. Discusses specifically  Stock n,,. RP-0144. ree of charge.&#13;
fiscal pollcy Interventions, manipula-&#13;
tions of the exchange rate, and pro-&#13;
ductivity Improvements and their&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Policy Responses to External Shocks in&#13;
Selected Latin American Countries&#13;
Bela Balassa&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Nlumber 221.&#13;
Reprinted from Quarterly Review of Economics and&#13;
Business. vol. 21. no. 2 (Summer 1981):131-64.&#13;
Stock Nob. RP-0221. free of charge.&#13;
Restructuring the Worid Economy:&#13;
Round 11&#13;
Hollis Chenery&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Number 204.&#13;
Reprinted from Foreign Affairs&#13;
(Summer 1981):U102-120.&#13;
Stock no. RP-0204. free of charge.&#13;
Risk Assessments and Risk Premiums&#13;
In the Eurodollar Market&#13;
Gershon Feder and Knud Ross&#13;
World Bank Reprint Series: Nlumber 220.&#13;
Reprinted from The Journal of Finance, vol. 37.&#13;
no. 3 (June 1982):679-91.&#13;
Stock No. RP-0220. Free of charge.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
ORDER FORM&#13;
SEND TO:&#13;
WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS                                                       WORLD 13ANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
P.O. BOX 37525                                            or                  66, AVENUE D'IENA&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013                                                        75116 PARIS, FRANCE&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Name:&#13;
Address:&#13;
Stock or ISBN #                            Author, Title                       Qty.       Price          Total&#13;
Sub-Total Cost: _&#13;
Postage &amp; handling fee for more than two free items ($1.00 each):&#13;
Total copies:,   . .___   Air mail surcharge ($2.00 each):&#13;
TOTAL PAYMENT ENCLOSED:_____&#13;
Make checks payable: WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
Prepayment on orders from individuals is requested. Purchase orders are accepted from booksellers, library suppliers, libraries, and instiutons.&#13;
All prices include cost of postage by the least expensive means. The prices and publication dates quoted in this Catalog are subject to change&#13;
without noties.&#13;
No refunds will be given for items that cannot be filled. Credit will be applied towards future orders.&#13;
No more than two tree publications will be provided without charge. Requests for additional copies will tbe tilled at a charge of US Si .00 per&#13;
copy to cover handling and postage costs.&#13;
Airmail delivery will require a prepayment of US $2.00 par copy.&#13;
Mall-order payment to the World Bank need not be in U.S. dollars, but the amount remitted must be at theo rate of exchAinge on the day the&#13;
order is placed. The World Bank will also accept Unesco coupons.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG 3881.5 .W57 W67 NO.625&#13;
c.3&#13;
SHOME, PARTHASARATHI, 1950-&#13;
ALTERNATIVE MECHANISMS FOR&#13;
FINANCING SOCIAL SECURITY. -&#13;
DATE   NAME AND EXTENSION  NUMBER&#13;
5//44~~ -is u9 ^ 5  JiN 23 '8,fwq 834.8z, &#13;
SEP 15 'U&#13;
ggg t  /t(4  A wk rS   -e-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                         European Office              Tokyo Office&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                 66, avenue d'lena             Kokusai Building&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A       75116 Paris, France           1-1 Marunouchi 3-chorne&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234           Telephone: (1) 723-54.21      Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
* Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK          Telex: 842-620628             Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                          Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0292-2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554825">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/11/1554825/alternative-mechanisms-financing-social-security
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/11/1554825/alternative-mechanisms-financing-social-security</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1983/11/1554825/alternative-mechanisms-financing-social-security</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/08/000178830_98101903422185/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/08/000178830_98101903422185/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-08-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1983-11-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Alternative mechanisms for financing social security
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The objective of this paper is two-fold.
            First, it clarifies the role of different assumptions made
            by previous authors in the determination of results
            regarding the neutrality or non-neutrality of social
            security's impact on capital accumulation and labor
            supply. To this end, it analyzes the differential effects of
            alternative financing mechanisms - fully-funded and
            pay-as-you-go schemes - within the framework of a
            multiperiod model with overlapping generations. Second, the
            paper addresses the question of the optimal size of social
            security. It contrasts the standard procedure of equating
            optimality to the maximization of a representative
            individual's utility function with an approach which
            rationalizes the need for social security by reference to a
            paternalistic concern for the welfare of the retired
            population. Section I describes the central model and the
            main issues that are addressed in the following sections.
            Section II investigates "positive" concerns.
            Section III is concerned with normative issues of optimality
            in both an individualistic and a paternalistic framework. A
            concluding section summarizes the main results and an
            appendix elaborates a more complicated version of the simple
            normative model developed in Section III.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Alternative mechanisms for financing social security
        </docna>
        <display_title>Alternative mechanisms for
            financing social security</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1983/11/1554825/alternative-mechanisms-financing-social-security</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Economic Stabilization,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Economic Growth,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Shome, P.</author>
            <author>Squire, Lyn</author>
            <author>CPD</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903422185</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Labor markets and employment</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 625</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Social Protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0292-2</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Capital; Mathematical models; Savings;
            Social security; Labor supply
            affiliates,budget constraint,capital
            accumulation,capital stock,centrally planned
            economy,deficits,developed countries,discounted
            value,Empirical Evidence,empirical
            studies,Equations,equilibrium,GDP,government budget,growth
            rate,income effect,inheritance,interest rate,INTERNATIONAL
            MONETARY FUND,labor force,labor input,Labor
            supply,leisure,level of capital,marginal
            revenue,Mathematical models,payroll
            taxes,pensions,population growth,production
            function,production technology,public savings,public
            sector,rate of return,real income,real prices,real
            variables,relative price,resource allocation,Resource
            Mobilization,Retirement,returns to scale,savings,social
            security,tax laws,tax rates,taxation,total consumption,total
            output,unit of capital,utility function,utility maximization,wealth
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP625</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Political Economy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Political Economy Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Employment and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Improving Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Market Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets, Job Creation and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Stabilization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Econometrics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Old Age Pension</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Political Economy of Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>