<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>SWP747&#13;
Government Policy and the Development&#13;
of Financial Markets&#13;
The Case of Korea&#13;
Arvind Virmnani&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 747&#13;
-~ ~         =&#13;
FIL C OP&#13;
.E COPY  t                ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~------&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 747&#13;
Government Policy and the Development&#13;
of Financial Markets&#13;
The Case of Korea&#13;
Arvind Virmani&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright (© 1985&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development/THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W,&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
First printing August 1985&#13;
This is a working document published informally by the World Bank. To present the&#13;
results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has not been prepared&#13;
in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal printed texts, and the World&#13;
Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The publication is supplied at a token charge&#13;
to defray part of the cost of manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The World Bank does not accept responsibility for the views expressed herein, which&#13;
are those of the authors and should not be attributed to the World Bank or to its&#13;
affiliated organizations. The findings, interpretations, and conclusions are the results&#13;
of research supported by the Bank; they do not necessarily represent official policy of&#13;
the Bank. The designations employed, the presentation of material, and any maps used&#13;
in this document are solely for the convenience of the reader and do not imply the&#13;
expression of any opinion whatsoever on the part of the World Bank or its affiliates&#13;
concerning the legal status of any country, territory, city, area, or of its authorities, or&#13;
conceming the delimitation of its boundaries, or national affiliation.&#13;
The most recent World Bank publications are described in the annual spring and fall&#13;
lists; the continuing research program is described in the annual Abstracts of Current&#13;
Studies. The latest edition of each is available free of charge from the Publications Sales&#13;
Unit, Department T, The World Bank, 1818 H Street, N.W, Washington, D.C. 20433,&#13;
U.S.A., or from the European Office of the Bank, 66 avenue d'l6na, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Arvind Virmani is an economist in the Development Research Department of the&#13;
World Bank.&#13;
Library of Congress Cataloging-in-Publication Data&#13;
Virmani, Arvind, 1949-&#13;
Government policy and the developmerit of financial&#13;
markets.&#13;
(World Bank staff working psLpers ; no. 747)&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
1. Monetary policy--Korea (South) 2. Banks and&#13;
bankcing--Korea (South) 3. Interest rates--Korea&#13;
(South) 4. Financial institutions--Korea (South)&#13;
5. Securiteis--Korea (South)         I. Title.     II. Series.&#13;
HF1280.5.V57     1985    332.4'95195           85-15779&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0587-5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PREFACE&#13;
The ground work for this study was done while the author was a member&#13;
of a World Bank mission which visited Korea at the end of 1983. The study was&#13;
perceived as another application of the analytical work presented in "The&#13;
Nature of Credit Markets in Developing Countries: A Framework for Policy&#13;
Analysis," (Staff Working Paper No. 524). The first application of the work&#13;
was presented in, "Evaluation of Financial Policy: Credit Allocation in&#13;
Bangladesh." The current study therefore tried to put greater emphasis on&#13;
issues not present in Bangladesh or ones which were relatively neglected in&#13;
that study. The most important of the latter were securities markets and the&#13;
micro impacts on the financial system of monetary policy. As a result some of&#13;
the issues which were extensively covered in the earlier study, such as the&#13;
detailed effect of a large number of specific allocation instruments including&#13;
specialized banks, have not been covered in depth.&#13;
ABSTRACT&#13;
Direction and control of the financial system has had a significant&#13;
role in the Korean government's development strategy. The paper shows how&#13;
this influenced the evolution of the Korean financial system, and how the&#13;
latter responded to shocks during the 1980s. Review of the Korean experience&#13;
also suggests two important hypotheses: that subsidy policies (not interest&#13;
ceilings) directed solely at promoting market and economic efficiency are more&#13;
likely to be successful, and that forced lending policies (often combined with&#13;
interest ceilings) directed at social, political and other non-economic goals&#13;
are likely to weaken the financial system and be much less likely to&#13;
succeed. Given the nature of this study, however, its conclusions, like that&#13;
of other similar studies, should be considered only tentative in the absence&#13;
of rigorous empirical testing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Page No.&#13;
Section 1 Introduction                                                   1&#13;
Section 2  Interest Rate Policy                                          3&#13;
2.1  The Loan Rates:  Appropriate Level and Flexibility           3&#13;
2.2  Level of Interest Rates                                      8&#13;
2.3  The Structure of Loan Interest Rate                          9&#13;
2.4  Deposit Rates                                               15&#13;
2.5  Interest Rate Levels and Bank Profitability                 18&#13;
Section 3 The Financial System:    Intermediaries and Instruments      20&#13;
3.1  Specialized Banks and Development Institutions              20&#13;
3.2  Commercial Banks                                            22&#13;
3.3  Trade Credit                                                27&#13;
3.4  Diversified Corporations as Allocators of Capital           28&#13;
Section 4  Securities Markets:   Debentures and Equities               32&#13;
4.1  Bond Market                                                 34-&#13;
4.2  Secondary Market in Bonds                                   39&#13;
4.3  The Stock Market                                            41&#13;
4.4  Accelerated Depreciation and Debt-Equity Ratios             46&#13;
Section 5  Banking System as Resource Allocator                        48&#13;
Section 6  Monetary Policy in a Constrained Financial System            52&#13;
6.1  Consequences of the Oil-Shock                               52&#13;
6.2  Policy Response and Consequences:   A Financial Perspective 53&#13;
6.3  Monetary Policy Reversal                                     56&#13;
6.4  Screening by Expected Returns                               57&#13;
6.5  The Curb Market                                              59&#13;
Section 7  Conclusions                                                  61&#13;
Appendix                                                                66&#13;
Appendix Tables                                                   69 - 97&#13;
Footnotes                                                               98&#13;
References                                                              99&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
LIST OF FIGURES&#13;
Page No.&#13;
Figure 1:  Average Quarterly Interest Rates                        4&#13;
Figure 2:  Ratio of Loan &amp; Deposit Rates to UFM                    7&#13;
Figure 3: Proportion of Institution's Asset To&#13;
Total Assets of Financial Institutions                 21&#13;
Figure 4:  Proportion of Loans and Credits                        28&#13;
Figure 5:  Proportion of Finance Provided                         33&#13;
Figure 6:  Loan Repayment Profile                                 68&#13;
Figure 7:  Firms Net Return Profile                               68&#13;
LIST OF TABLES&#13;
Page No.&#13;
Table 1:  Correlation Between Interest Rates                       6&#13;
Table 2:  Curb Market Interest Rates in 1983                      11&#13;
Table 3:  Money and Savings Deposit                               16&#13;
Table 4:  Simple Average Interest Rate Ratios                     24&#13;
Table 5:  Book Value of Capital to Real Capital Stock             47&#13;
Table 6:  Government Coverage of NIF Deficit                      51&#13;
Table 7:  Ratio of TD to Unofficial Market Rates - Quarterly      54&#13;
Table 8:  Rates of Growth of Land Prices                          60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLES IN APPENDIX&#13;
Al:   Average Quarterly Interest Rates (x)&#13;
A2 (I):   Major Interest Rates on Discounts of Deposit Money Banks&#13;
(II): Major Interest Rates on Loans and Discounts of Deposit Money Banks&#13;
A3:   Interest Rates of Deposit Money Banks by Maturity&#13;
A4:   Commercial Bank Credits by maturity&#13;
A5:   Rediscount Ratio of Bank of Korea&#13;
A6:   Private Corporations:   Structure of Assets &amp; Liabilities&#13;
A7:   Individual Portfolio Composition&#13;
A8:   Proportion of Institution's Assets to Total Assets of Financial&#13;
Institutions&#13;
A9:   Financial System:   Sources of Finance&#13;
A10: Financial Intermediation: Asset Proportions&#13;
All:  Financial Assets and Liabilities Outstanding at End of Year 1982&#13;
A12: Commercial Banks: Guarantee on Bonds&#13;
A13: Size of Industrial paper Market&#13;
A14: Investment and Finance companies&#13;
A15: Amounts and Ratios of Different Types of Bonds Outstanding&#13;
A16: Annualized Yields on Different Type of Bonds&#13;
A17: Composition of the Secondary and Tertiary Market&#13;
A18: Bond Trading Under Repurchase or Reverse Repurchase Agreements&#13;
A19: Bond Trading Under Repurchase Agreements (Repo Transactions)&#13;
A20   Net Purchase and Sale of Repo by Investor&#13;
A21: Secondary market Activity: Stocks&#13;
A22: Rates of Return in the Equity market&#13;
A23: Distribution of Shareholdings&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
A24: Ownership of Listed Stocks by Type of Holders&#13;
A25:  Ratio of Book Value of Capital Stock to Real Capital in Steady State&#13;
A26: Ratio of Book Value of Capital Stock to Actual Capital&#13;
A27: Deposit Money Bank's Banking Fund Loans&#13;
A28: Directed Loans of DMBs&#13;
A29: National Investment Fund NIF Ratio Cumulated Repayment on Cumulated New&#13;
Loans&#13;
A30:  Loans and Discounts of Deposit Money Banks by Industry&#13;
A31: Land price Index (Rate of Growth)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
1. Introduction&#13;
Direction and Control of the financial system has had a significant&#13;
role in the Korean Government's development strategy. In the 1960s credit and&#13;
interest rate policy was merely one among a host of tax, tariff and import&#13;
concessions to exporting industries. With the reduction and elimination of&#13;
some of these concessions in the 1970s, and the perceived need to change the&#13;
structure of the economy, the financial system began by the mid-1970s, to have&#13;
a much more central role in development strategy. Broadly speaking the&#13;
structure of financial regulation had three elements: The creation of new&#13;
public and private financial institutions with specified limitations on the&#13;
type of activities, control of the level and structure of interest rates, and&#13;
direct and indirect credit allocation policies. The primary focus of this&#13;
paper is to study the evolution of Korean financial markets under this&#13;
regulatory regime, and to analyse how they responded to external shocks and&#13;
internal policy changes in the 1980s. This experience suggests lessons which&#13;
may be of use to other countries with similarly regulated financial systems.&#13;
The analysis shows that both the identification/choice of sectors and&#13;
uses for increased allocation of capital, and the instruments used for this&#13;
purpose can have profound effects on the evolution of the financial system.&#13;
In both these areas, mistakes which seem to predominate in many other&#13;
countries with strong regulatory structures, were relatively rare in Korea,&#13;
but not entirely absent. For example, one possible reason for relatively&#13;
greater success, in the choice of favored uses for funds, is a much greater&#13;
emphasis on economic returns, rather than on equity/distributional&#13;
considerations (or even worse, political pressure). Mistakes can,_and did&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
arise even in judging the uses for which long-term economic benefits were&#13;
greater than those perceived by lenders (i.e. in identifying market failure).&#13;
Incentive Mechanisms and Forced Lending policies, the two broadly&#13;
defined categories of intervention instruments, were both used in Korea. As&#13;
in the case of many other countries, Korea demonstrates the grave risks in&#13;
using forced lending policies. The most important risk is the potential&#13;
undermining of the profitability and viability of the financial system,&#13;
particularly the banking system. This is not to say, as many have that no&#13;
good can come out of a regulated system; by changing private profits from&#13;
different types of lending, it can encourage socially profitable innovation in&#13;
new instruments and markets. Direct incentives can, however, usually achieve&#13;
the same results at lower cost and risk. Similarly incentives mechanisms like&#13;
subsidized rediscounting and credit guarantee mechanisms have quite different&#13;
consequences from forced lending policies.&#13;
Loan interest rate ceilings are almost always an essential element of&#13;
the forced lending policies. They also have a pervasive influence on the&#13;
development of the financial structure. The paper therefore starts with an&#13;
examination of recent interest policies, and demonstrates a simple methodology&#13;
for determining an appropriate interest rate structure. In the succeeding&#13;
sections it is shown how failings in this structure affected the evolution of&#13;
the financial system. At least in Korea, management of the level of loan&#13;
interest in the face of changing conditions in money markets has been quite&#13;
successful. Other countries can learn from this experience.&#13;
In the final section we consider the reactions of this financial&#13;
system to external shocks and the governments macroeconomic (mainly monetary)&#13;
policy response to this shock. The constraints imposed by the financial&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
system, and the role of the informal or curb market (which is itself largely a&#13;
consequence of the regulated structure) in modifying the effects of financial&#13;
policy is analysed.&#13;
Section 2. Interest-Rate Policy&#13;
Interest rate policy enters into consideration of, and effects&#13;
virtually all financial sector issues. It is therefore useful to first&#13;
consider it separately. The issue in my view is not one of government control&#13;
versus (idealized) competitive rate setting, but one of the appropriate level&#13;
and structure of rates. For this purpose it is instructive to look at the&#13;
recent experience in Korea.&#13;
2.1 Loan Rates: Appropriate Level and Flexibility&#13;
Columns B to E of Appendix Table Al give a sampling of the loan rates&#13;
of the deposit money banks, which were subject to varying degrees of&#13;
government control and advise. The ones given are the interest rate on&#13;
overdue loans, the rate on overdrafts, call market rate and the rate on bills&#13;
and discounts for A class enterprises. Figure 1 shows the general time&#13;
pattern of variation in these rates. The table reveals a striking difference&#13;
in the behavior of these rates in the 10 quarter period ending in the fourth'&#13;
quarter of 1979 and that beginning in 1980 (lst quarter). All these rates&#13;
were much less volatile (flexible) in the first period than in the second.&#13;
For example, the coefficient of variation for the discount rates on bills was&#13;
10.4X in the first and 17.5% in the second period. Similarly the variation in&#13;
the call rate was 5.5X in the first and 15.4X in the second period.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 1:  AVERAGE QUARTERLY INTEREST RATES&#13;
55-&#13;
50 -&#13;
45&#13;
40-&#13;
35-&#13;
30-&#13;
25-2 &#13;
20-&#13;
15-&#13;
10- &#13;
0       4       8       12      16     20      24      28&#13;
QUARTERS (1977 TO 1983)&#13;
+  OVER      O   DRAFT      ^   CALL      x   GENERAL       v   C&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
This behavior seems to contrast with that of the two rates, which are&#13;
generally thought to be reasonably free. The interest rate in the curb (UFM)&#13;
markets and the yield on corporate bonds. There is no superficially visible&#13;
difference in their behavior before and after the first quarter of 1980&#13;
(Columns A and I). Comparison of the coefficient of variation for the curb&#13;
market rates reveals, however, that there was an equal if not greater change&#13;
in the variability of this rate. The coefficient of variations went from 9.8%&#13;
in the first to 17.7% in the second period. This suggests that the government&#13;
behavior changed from making larger discrete changes to smaller quicker&#13;
changes after the oil shocks. There is clearly a trade off between stability&#13;
and responsiveness to market conditions and government policy correctly&#13;
changed towards the quicker responsiveness required to reflect market&#13;
conditions.&#13;
The secondary bond market, because of its limited nature (discussed&#13;
below) and the curb market, because of its quasi-illegal status, suffer from&#13;
limitations, as reflections of the supply-demand conditions in financial&#13;
markets. An examination of Row 6 of Table 1 shows however, that during the&#13;
first shock period (1980-1 to 1982-2) the correlation between the bond yield&#13;
and the lagged curb rate at 0.88 was significantly higher than the same period&#13;
correlation or the correlation between the curb rate and the lagged bond&#13;
yield. This leads to the conclusion that curb rates had an influence in&#13;
determining bond yields and that the reverse effect was minimal. It also&#13;
suggests that the curb market reflects market conditions better.&#13;
The first column of Table 1 shows the same period correlation between&#13;
the curb interest rate and the bills discount rate, the 1 year time deposit&#13;
rate for DMBs and the bond yield rate. As we might expect the curb markets&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
Table 1: Correlation Between Interest Rates (1980-lst to 1982-2nd quarter)L/&#13;
1. UFM Rate 2. UFM Rate 3. UFM Rate2V 4. Corporate 5. Lagged 6. Bond2/&#13;
Lagged                        Bond         Bond       Yield&#13;
Yield        Yield&#13;
1.  Overdue loans   0.83         0.52           0.29&#13;
2.  Overdrafts      0.53         0.89           0.14&#13;
3.  Call Market     0.93         0.91           0.51&#13;
(-0.10)&#13;
4.  Gen. Bills      0.89         0.89           0.47            0.94     0.74             0.73&#13;
&amp; Loans        (0.86)       (0.75)&#13;
5.  1 Yr.TD         0.84         0.85           0.46&#13;
6.  Corporate       0.58         0.82           0.58&#13;
Bond&#13;
7.  SIFC Deposit    0.80         0.92&#13;
Rates&#13;
1/   Figures in brackets are for period 1977-3rd to 1979-4th quarter.&#13;
2/   The numbers in this column represent correlation coefficient with the lagged&#13;
values of the rates referred to in the extreme left hand column.&#13;
Source: Calculated from Table Al.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FG 2 R ATI O (DF LC)AN &amp;4 DEPOF)CSIT RA-TE S                  10 LJF M&#13;
0.6 --l&#13;
0.5-&#13;
0.4-&#13;
0.3&#13;
0.2-&#13;
01&#13;
0  -  ;-   § ZIl Tl^-- &#13;
0       4S       8       12      16      20       24      28&#13;
QUJARTERS (1977 TO I 983)&#13;
-   GENE:RAL/UFM         +   TD RATE;S /' UFM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
response to external factors such as inflation, was similar to that of the&#13;
government response in terms of the movement of controlled rates; while this&#13;
was much less true of bond markets. Columns 2 and 3 show that for the DMB's,&#13;
deposit and general loan rates were much more closely correlated with lagged&#13;
curb rates than curb rates were with lagged loan and deposit rates. This&#13;
suggests that the government used curb market rates, or other indicators&#13;
correlated with them, as measures of market excess demand. This information&#13;
was used in adjusting controlled rates. It is worth noting that if government&#13;
controlled rate changes were totally independent of economic changes which&#13;
effect supply-demand conditions in financial markets, we would expect a&#13;
negative correlation between the curb and bank rates. If the government&#13;
responded weakly or only part of the time, the correlation would be close to&#13;
zero.&#13;
2.2. Level of Interest Rates&#13;
Columns K and M of Table Al and Figure 2, show the ratio of general&#13;
bill discount to curb rate, and the 1 Yr time deposit rate to the curb rate.&#13;
The changes in the latter ratio and its effect on the portfolio shifts between&#13;
the curb market and deposit money banks will be analysed subsequently. The&#13;
table shows that adjustment of loan interest ceilings in early 1980 led to a&#13;
rise in the ratio from .43 to .55 by the 3rd quarter of 1980. The average&#13;
ratio rose from .42 during the period 1977-2 to 1979-4 to .517 during the&#13;
period 1980-1 to 1982-4. With the sharp downward adjustment in the loan rates&#13;
in June 1982 the ratio fell sharply from .43 in 1982-1 to .36 (.34) in the&#13;
next quarter (1982-2). But in early 1983 it had already recovered to between&#13;
.4 and .50 (the 1983 curb data is in different format from earlier data).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
Curb interest rates continued to decline in the 3rd quarter with a temporary&#13;
increase in the 4th quarter. There was no sharp permanent increase (even&#13;
relative to the other rates). Any conclusions that the curb market is a&#13;
manifestation of a condition of chronic excess demand in the formal financial&#13;
system is highly exaggerated. l/ What the curb market does represent is a&#13;
segmentation arising from an inappropriate structure of interest rate&#13;
controls. The spread between average interest rate on bank loans to the&#13;
average interest rate on bank deposit is, however, of critical importance to&#13;
the banking system. We consider this below.&#13;
2.3 The Structure of Loan Interest Rates&#13;
Korea, like many other developing countries, has perceived interest&#13;
rate ceilings on specific types of loans and borrower groups as an instrument&#13;
of development policy. Appendix Table A2 gives a flavor of the types of loans&#13;
and discounts for which such ceilings have been used. Favored categories have&#13;
included loans for export industries, machine industry promotion, agriculture&#13;
and medium industries. The ostensible objective of such policies is to reduce&#13;
the effective cost of capital for favored uses. Their actual effect is to&#13;
increase collateral requirements and to reduce loan amounts to borrower&#13;
categories to which they really act as ceilings 2/. As this defeats the&#13;
entire purpose of the policy it is often coupled with implicit or explicit&#13;
forced lending policies. Such allocation policies will be considered&#13;
separately.&#13;
In the middle of 1982, the government of Korea unified the interest&#13;
ceilings on loans and deposits of Deposit Money Banks (DMBs), for the&#13;
ostensible purpose of eliminating such "subsidies": Loan and discount&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
ceilings were set at 10%, and deposit of ceilings at 8%. This of course had&#13;
the effect of eliminating desirable differentials by loan and deposit terms.&#13;
Paradoxically this represented a shift away from a policy of lower ceilings on&#13;
socially desirable activities and towards what might superficially be thought&#13;
of as socially unproductive sub-sectors. These were firms which from the&#13;
banks' perspective had suffered the greatest decline in the expected earnings&#13;
stream. The market rate of interest for such firms, in cases where banks&#13;
would want to continue lending, would be significantly higher than for general&#13;
loans.3/ Consequently the 10% rate would act as a more severe constraint.&#13;
The important issue in this context is not, however, one of socially&#13;
productive or unproductive sectors, but one of differentiation of interest&#13;
rates by borrower risk class. This is of course part of the general problem&#13;
of differentiating the structure of interest rate by the Return/Risk&#13;
characteristics of borrowers, and by loan size and maturity.&#13;
Return/Risk Characteristics&#13;
It can be shown 4/ that the profitability or expected returns of the&#13;
borrower will be negatively related to the interest rate on loans. The best&#13;
borrowers will not need any collateral, and pay an interest equal to the cost&#13;
to intermediaries of obtaining and transferring funds. In Korea the interest&#13;
rate on general bills and discounts of A class borrowers can be taken as this&#13;
base or prime rate. The ceilings on borrowers with worse return-risk&#13;
characteristics must rise progressively. Till mid-1970 the interest ceiling&#13;
on B class borrowers was 1.1(%) point above that of A class, and was reduced&#13;
to 0.5(X) point at that time. Even the 1 point difference was not adequate at&#13;
that time, representing less than a 7X spread over the prevailing A-class rate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
of 15%. Table 2 shows that the average curb-rate for B-class borrowers was&#13;
21% higher than that of A-class borrowers in the third quarter of 1983. A&#13;
spread of 15 to 25% for B-class borrowers over the prime rate would not&#13;
therefore be inappropriate. Such spreads should in principle be applied to&#13;
all intermediaries and instruments .5/&#13;
Table 2: Curb Market Interest Rates in 1983&#13;
(in percent per annum)&#13;
March              June             September&#13;
A Class               19.6-21.0       21.0-22.4&#13;
(20.3)           (21.7)&#13;
B Class               23.9-25.3       23.9-25.3            26.8-28.3&#13;
(24.6)           (24.6)               (27.5)&#13;
Figures in brackets represent simple averages.&#13;
Source: Investment &amp; Finance Association of Korea&#13;
Loan Term and Size&#13;
Since 1976 the interest on loans of less than 1 year and those of .1&#13;
to 3 years has been virtually identical, with interest rate on loans of 3 to 8&#13;
years generally one percentage point above these rates. The differential for&#13;
the longer category has therefore been between 6.7% and 4.2% higher than the&#13;
shorter term category which ranged from 16% to 25.5% (Table A3). This would&#13;
appear to be a totally inadequate differentiation which was itself eliminated&#13;
in June 1982. If we look at the coefficient of variation for the relatively&#13;
more stable period 1977, 3rd quarter, to 1980, 1st quarter, it was&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
approximately 10% for both the general bills rate and for the curb market&#13;
rate. This suggests that range allowed was inadequate even in the earlier&#13;
period. An examination of the loan maturity structure of commercial banks&#13;
(Table A4) suggests a word of caution, however. A regression of the ratio of&#13;
the loan rates for 3-8 year loans to that of less than 3 year loans on the&#13;
proportion of loans of over 3 years maturity yields a weak negative&#13;
relationship. This would suggest that no differentiation is necessary.&#13;
Nevertheless, in my judgment, a difference in ceiling of 5% for the 1-3 years&#13;
over that for 1 year loans and a further 5% for 3-8 years loans seems to be&#13;
the minimum useful amount. An alternative would be to set bands of 0-10% for&#13;
each of these categories.&#13;
An often overlooked subcategory in most discussions of&#13;
differentiation by maturity is the problem of very short duration&#13;
loans/discounts. One of the important features of these loans is that they&#13;
must be processed and disbursed quickly. This usually requires greater&#13;
flexibility and decentralization of authority than most banks have and these&#13;
loans are usually given directly to clients, by other intermediaries. In&#13;
fact, this may be an important category of loans for the curb market, even&#13;
after an appropriate structure is created. Quickness of processing means that&#13;
either greater administrative/transaction costs must be incurred by the&#13;
institution, or greater risks must be taken. In either case, these type of&#13;
loans also require higher loan ceilings than those applicable to loans of&#13;
6-month - 1 year duration.&#13;
Table A4 gives the proportion of commercial bank loans of less than&#13;
1 year, 1 to 3 years, and over three year maturity. We make the arbitrary&#13;
assumption, that within these categories, the average maturity is 6 months,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
2 years and 5 years respectively. Using this, the average maturity of the&#13;
commercial bank loan portfolio for 1982 is approximately 1.4 years and must&#13;
therefore lie between 1 and 2 years. Lending costs were approximately 2.1% of&#13;
loan amounts. Transaction costs for a 3-month or smaller duration loans could&#13;
easily by 50 to 150% greater than this. The premium for short duration loans&#13;
could therefore be between 1 and 3(X) points. A minimum differential of 1,&#13;
2 and 3 points for loans of 3, 2 and 1 month respectively would seem to be&#13;
quite reasonable. These illustrative calculations assume that the marginal&#13;
cost of funds is independent of the marginal allocation of loans, the usual&#13;
assumption in market analysis.&#13;
An overdraft facility is an instrument used by banks to lower the&#13;
transaction costs of emergency quick dispersing short term loans. It has the&#13;
limitation, however, that it is restricted to regular clients. This rate has&#13;
generally been set 2(%) points above the base/prime rate. This falls squarely&#13;
within the range given in the above section. In proportional terms 2 points&#13;
represented a spread of 13% above the base/prime rate of 15% in 1977-78&#13;
(Al). A ceiling which is higher by 15 to 20% on very short duration loans&#13;
seems quite reasonable.&#13;
Another differentiation which is ignored is by size of loan. There&#13;
are generally two parts to the administrative or transaction cost of making&#13;
loans. There is a cost which varies with loan amount. This includes the cost&#13;
of servicing deposits (2.11% in 1982) and part of the cost of processing&#13;
loans. There is also a proportion of loan cost which depends only on whether&#13;
a loan is made or not, i.e. some basic amount of paper work and loan appraisal&#13;
is necessary no matter how small the loan. If we assume that 1/10th of the&#13;
average cost of processing the loan (2.1%) is a fixed cost, then the average&#13;
cost of a loan (C) can be written&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
C = .04 - .00211 x Lav.&#13;
L&#13;
For a loan which is 1/5th to 1/10th the size of the average loan,&#13;
(Lavg.), transaction costs would be 1 to 2(X) points above those for the&#13;
average loan. For 1982, this is 8% to 16% above the average loan rate for the&#13;
year. These calculations are purely suggestive, and much more accurate&#13;
calculations could easily be made by banks and the government.&#13;
The Call Market&#13;
As Table 1 shows, the Call money market interest rates were most&#13;
highly correlated with the Curb market during the 1980, 1st quarter, to 1982,&#13;
2nd quarter, period. This would suggest, that perhaps this is a market, where&#13;
on the margin, both formal and informal markets were interacting. We find,&#13;
however, the same period correlation coefficient and the correlation between&#13;
the call rate and the lagged curb rate are both high at over .9. As in the&#13;
case of the general bill rate, the correlation between the curb rate and the&#13;
lagged call rate is significantly lower at .5. Thus, the call market rate was&#13;
more likely to be adjusting to the curb rate than vice versa.&#13;
Call market rate behavior during 1977, 3rd quarter, to 1979, 4th&#13;
quarter, was remarkably different however. There was virtually zero or&#13;
perhaps negative (-0.1) correlation with the curb rate. As noted earlier&#13;
this could be a sign that interest controls in the call market were pushing&#13;
borrowers into the curb market. The curb market has a potential role as a&#13;
bridge between different intermediaries. All such institutions should be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
allowed to participate in it. It can also serve as a link to the informal&#13;
market, and provide a more accurate indicator of supply-demand condition. It&#13;
is therefore a prime candidate for complete liberalization. Any potential&#13;
harmful effects can be mitigated by having a Bank of Korea discount window for&#13;
general rediscounts which can put an effective ceiling on rates by supplying&#13;
all borrowers at that rate.&#13;
2.4 Deposit Rates&#13;
The average level of loan and deposit rates for the deposit money&#13;
banks will be a result of both the level and structure of rates. The spread&#13;
between the two rates plays a critical role in the issue of bank&#13;
profitability. The question of deposit rate levels is conventionally very&#13;
closely linked to the question of interest elasticity of savings. Information&#13;
constraints and lack of markets usually result in a large degree of&#13;
segmentation in the range of savings instruments available to different&#13;
groups. Free private intermediaries are likely to tacitly collude in using&#13;
this segmentation and setting rates so as to obtain deposits at minimum&#13;
costs. This has implications for equity between different groups which the&#13;
government may wish to change by setting deposit rates. Other longer term&#13;
objectives may also influence the social policy.&#13;
It is useful to distinguish at least three groups of private&#13;
depositors: Corporations, Household firms, and Household wage &amp; salary&#13;
earners. Household firms may be divided into general business and moneylender&#13;
or curb dealers. Table 3 gives the money and deposit holdings of corporations&#13;
and households between 1975 and 1982, as a proportion of their total asset&#13;
portfolio. The money holdings to total asset ratio has been declining for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
Table 3: Money and Savings Deposit Holdings to Total Assets&#13;
in Portfolio of Corporations and Individuals&#13;
1982      1981       1980      1978      1975&#13;
Private Corporation&#13;
Money                 8.2       6.7        7.5       9.1       9.4&#13;
Deposits             11.2      11.5       18.5      22.1      22.1&#13;
Time &amp; Savings      7.5      12.1      15.6       19.0      20.7&#13;
with ISCs           3.7       2.9       2.9        3.1       1.4&#13;
Individuals&#13;
Money                 9.5       9.2       12.7      16.9      19.9&#13;
Deposits             43.4      42.0      41.7       40.9      39.3&#13;
Time &amp; Savings     41.7      39.8      38.9       37.3      35.9&#13;
with ISCs           1.7       2.2       2.8        3.6       3.4&#13;
ISCO: Investment and Savings Companies&#13;
Source: Appendix Tables A6 and A7.&#13;
both entities, but shows a dramatic drop from 19.9% in 1975 to 9.5% in 1982&#13;
for households. In the case of corporations, the ratio declined steadily from&#13;
1975 to 1981 but rose in 1982.&#13;
Household checking deposits have had special higher rates of 6%&#13;
between 4-22-77 and 9-7-79, as against 1.8% for passbook and 1% for temporary&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
accounts. Similarly, from 7-1-1981 to 2-29-1982, the interest rate on&#13;
checking accounts was 14.4% (1.8% for others), and was subsequently reduced to&#13;
12% and then to 8% (6-28-82). This suggests that the changing portfolio&#13;
composition reflects a long term decline in relative money holdings of&#13;
households. If household firm behavior is anything like that of corporations&#13;
Free market demand deposit rates for this category would therefore&#13;
probably fall to zero. The government argument for giving higher rates&#13;
appears to be based on long term considerations of promoting the checking&#13;
habit. Though this can be a legitimate argument, household checking deposit&#13;
rates appear to be far out of line. Thus, the required minimum rate should be&#13;
dramatically reduced or eliminated. Alternatively, a rate differential could&#13;
be maintained through a government subsidy.&#13;
Table 3 shows a contrasting behavior of corporations and individuals&#13;
for the holding of deposits in their portfolio. Corporate holdings of&#13;
deposits have halved from 22.1% of total assets in 1975 to 11.2% in 1980.&#13;
Interestingly, this has been accompanied by a shift towards holding these&#13;
deposits with Investment &amp; Savings institution. The overall decline probably&#13;
represents a shift to other new savings instruments, which have become&#13;
available. The shift to Investment and Savings institutions is related to&#13;
this but is also associated with the increase in loan and intermediation&#13;
business that they performed for the corporations. The fluctuation in the&#13;
ratio also represents a degree of responsiveness of the portfolio to interest&#13;
rate changes.&#13;
Individual portfolio holdings of deposits show a slow and steady&#13;
uptrend, with a shift within deposits away from investment institutions. If&#13;
household firms' behavior is intermediate between that of corporations and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
salary earners, then the trends must be even more dramatic for these&#13;
individuals. Though concrete evidence is lacking, I would hypothesize that&#13;
this category of individuals has much less information about alternative&#13;
instruments and economic conditions, and is therefore less responsive to&#13;
interest rate changes. Individual businesses probably fall in between them&#13;
and corporations. Money lenders are probably most responsive in their&#13;
portfolio composition to interest changes.&#13;
Free market deposit setting would therefore probably result in fairly&#13;
low rates where concentration of salaried depositors (value) is high and&#13;
higher rates where those of corporations are high. Equity consideration&#13;
therefore have a role in deposit rate setting. Efficiency considerations&#13;
suggest that deposit rates should be positively related to maturity and&#13;
size. Some compromise between private rate setting and equity and efficiency&#13;
may be necessary.&#13;
2.5 Interest Rate Levels and Bank Profitability&#13;
One of the hazards of controlling bank interest rates is the effect&#13;
that mistakes in rate setting can have on the profitability and health of the&#13;
banking system. This is well illustrated by the changes in interest rate&#13;
policy during 1982 and 1983. As previously noted the unification and&#13;
reduction in loan rates to 10% was accompanied by a reduction of deposit rates&#13;
to 8%. The simultaneous reduction in deposit rates was of course designed to&#13;
maintain the nominal spreads between borrowing and lending rates. The&#13;
reduction in Bank of Korea discount rates on loans and discounts to 5.0% was&#13;
also designed to maintain the profitability position of intermediaries. For&#13;
commercial banks this was supplemented by widening the permitted range of bank&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
business to include profitable activities like sale of commercial bills and of&#13;
public bonds under repurchase. These measures were not however sufficient in&#13;
reversing the decline in effective spread resulting from the overhang of&#13;
longer term deposits at higher rates. Rough estimates suggest that the profit&#13;
margin between deposits and loans may have fallen from about 1.2% in 1981 to&#13;
0.8% in 1982. This was followed, however, in 1983 by a reduction of Bank of&#13;
Korea rediscount ratio's on most loan categories. As shown in Table A5 the&#13;
automatic discount proportion for defense and fishery loans was reduced by 10&#13;
percentage points and Energy Loans by 20 percentage points in February.&#13;
Rediscount proportions on export loans were subsequently (June) adjusted by 10&#13;
percentage points. One purpose of this action was to reduce subsidies to&#13;
these categories of borrowers 6/.   This, however, put renewed pressure on bank&#13;
profitability, despite the subsequent increase in the interest rates paid on&#13;
required reserves (effective retroactively) and the various fees banks are&#13;
permitted to charge (e.g. on Bond guarantees). By rough estimate the&#13;
effective spread between deposits and loans is likely to have declined to 0.2%&#13;
in 1983 (from 0.8%). There is no doubt that either a downward adjustment in&#13;
deposit rates or an upward adjustment in loan discount rates was absolutely&#13;
essential.&#13;
Within the principles outlined earlier, both deposit and loan rates&#13;
should be set through genuine consultation between intermediaries and the&#13;
government. To summarize, the level of the base rates must be set keeping in&#13;
account the supply-demand conditions and bank profitability, and should be&#13;
responsive to changing conditions. The rate structure must be differentiated&#13;
across categories and types, but must be the same across institutions if the&#13;
category/type is identical, to avoid destabilizing capital movements across&#13;
institutions (considered more fully below).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
Section 3. The Financial System: Intermediaries and Instruments&#13;
In the development of the financial system, the role of different&#13;
intermediaries is often interlinked with the role of different financial&#13;
instruments. It is useful, however, to look first at the former. Figure 3&#13;
gives the time pattern of change in the proportion of assets of different&#13;
financial intermediaries. The overall picture is one of the decline in the&#13;
role of the deposit money banks relative to other institution since 1975.&#13;
3.1. The Specialized Banks and Development Institutions&#13;
If one compares the period before 1975 to that after it, there appears&#13;
to have been a fairly sharp decline in the role of special banks. Their&#13;
assets declined from a ratio of 34% in 1972-74 to about 27% since then (Table&#13;
A8). A slightly different perspective suggests a relative decline during the&#13;
period 1972 to 1976, from 35% to 25% and a stabilization at around 27% since&#13;
then. Analysis suggests that such institutions can play a useful,-role in&#13;
developing new markets, where information and other constraints keep existing&#13;
intermediaries from making loans.   This is because they ae implicitly or&#13;
explicitly subsidized by governments to encourage development of new markets,&#13;
where they dobnot exist before.   That is historicafly they have tended to be&#13;
incentive based rather than forced lending instruments in most countries&#13;
including Korea.&#13;
The stabilization of their assets suggests that at last for the older&#13;
institution, such a push has been virtually exhausted. To the extent that an&#13;
inappropriate structure of interest rates has held back their development,&#13;
suggested reforms will have a positive effect. An additional possibility for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGUE 3:    PROPOORTION OF INSTITUTION'S ASSETS To&#13;
TOTAL ASSETS OF FINANCIAL INSTITUTIONS&#13;
50-&#13;
40 -&#13;
30&#13;
-.                          ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
20 -&#13;
1 0 -&#13;
10&#13;
1972   1973   1974   1975   1976   1977   1978   1979. 1980    1981   1982&#13;
E            +                                      A                  X&#13;
COMMERCIAL BANKS SPECIALIZED BANKS DEVELOPMENT INSTITUTIONS SAVING INSTITUTIONS LIFE INSURANCE CO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
these established institutions, would be to allow diversification of their&#13;
activities. A gradual lifting of restrictions to allow activities formerly&#13;
reserved for other institutions would allow them to use their special&#13;
information in new areas. Incentive systems for directing loans in desired&#13;
directions would then be applicable across institutions. 71&#13;
Though the share of development institutions in total financial assets&#13;
shows a weak rising trend, the above analysis applies with equal force to&#13;
these institutions. This is particularly true for the Korea Development Bank&#13;
and the Korean Long Term Credit bank. Necessary reform of the maturity&#13;
structure will have a positive effect on these institutions. Serious&#13;
consideration should be given to lifting restrictions on their lending and&#13;
deposit activities.&#13;
3.2 Commercial Banks&#13;
The share of assets of the commercial banks have declined&#13;
progressively from 49% in 1975 to 37% in 1982. This is a period marked by&#13;
considerable ferment in financial markets. The primary reason for the decline&#13;
is much more mundane. That is, a relative decline in their primary activity --&#13;
loans Figure 4, and Table A9 (2nd row), show that the proportion of loans&#13;
supplied by deposit money banks declined from 55.6% in 1975 to 43.8% in&#13;
1982. This, of course, contains the loans by special banks. As the&#13;
specialized bank's assets have hovered around 26-27% during this period, it is&#13;
reasonable to assume that most of this decline is for the commercial banks.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FUM 4:       PROPORTION OF LOANS AND CREDITS&#13;
PROVIDED BY DIFFERENT INSTITUTIONS&#13;
60&#13;
50&#13;
40&#13;
30&#13;
20&#13;
10&#13;
1975      1976     1977      1978      1979     1980      1981      1982&#13;
+   INSUR             I&amp; F          A    OTH       x   GOV        v   TRADE CR&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
Table 4: Simple Average Interest Rate Ratios&#13;
1               2               3             4&#13;
Prime Loan      Prime Loan      1 Year TD     1 Year TD&#13;
Curb Rate      SIFC Discount    Curb Rate     SIFC Deposit&#13;
(60-90 day)&#13;
1977           .42             .76 1/          .415           .81&#13;
1978           .40             .81             .42            .86&#13;
1979           .435            .82             .44            .85&#13;
1980           .52             .87             .51            .86&#13;
1981           .55             .87             .55            .88&#13;
1982           .40             .83             .35            .80&#13;
1983           .48             .83             .38            .75&#13;
1/  Average over 3rd and 4th quarter only.&#13;
Source: Table A2&#13;
A prime (conventional) culprit in bringing about this result would be&#13;
interest rate controls. Table 4 gives a summary of interest rate ratios which&#13;
may be used as a proxy for the degree of interest constraint or the supply-&#13;
demand imbalance in the bank loan market: High ratios denote little&#13;
constraint and vice versa. At least, for the period 1977-1982, these do not&#13;
provide an explanation for the decline. The fairly high ratio's in 1980 and&#13;
1981 do not seem to have had any effect on the declining trend between 1979&#13;
and 1982. The explanation lies in the distinction drawn earlier between the&#13;
level and structure of interest rates. Table 4 measures only the former while&#13;
the real problem stems from the latter.&#13;
To obtain the full picture we have to look at another aspect of bank&#13;
business, that of bond guarantees. These guarantees represent a commitment to&#13;
repay to bond holders 100% of the value of the bond in case of default. From&#13;
the banks' perspective, these bonds are almost identical to a loan backed by a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
fixed deposit of equal amount and term. A minor difference is that it does&#13;
not have to incur the cost of servicing the deposit and collects the spread&#13;
directly from the issuing company as a guarantee fee. In principle, a bond is&#13;
also tradeable in a secondary market though this activity has not been&#13;
significant so far (analyzed later). But by the same token loans can be taken&#13;
on the surety of a fixed deposit at a small premium.. In the Korean context,&#13;
these bonds have been virtually identical to loans, though their profitability&#13;
to banks may have differed.&#13;
Table 12 shows the ratio of bond guarantees given by commercial banks&#13;
to their loans from banking funds. Bond guarantees as a share of these two&#13;
activities grew rapidly from 1.2% in 1975 to 14.6% in 1980. In the next two&#13;
years this ratio stabilized at approximately 14%, and then grew again in&#13;
1983. Columns 1 and 3 of Table 4 show that relative interest constraints on&#13;
loans (and TDs) were reduced sharply in 1980 and maintained at those levels in&#13;
1981. This position was reversed again in 1983. This suggests that loan&#13;
ceilings may have had a greater (somewhat lagged) effect on this aspect of&#13;
bank business. The bond guarantee business seems to be negatively affected by&#13;
the relative level of interest rate in the bank loan market. Table All shows&#13;
that of total debentures outstanding in 1982, 75% were the liabilities of&#13;
private corporations and 25% that of government corporations. Most of the&#13;
guaranteed bond issues are by the largest and strongest private&#13;
corporations. Earlier analysis (authors 1982/1984) has already suggested that&#13;
given an inappropriate structure of interest rates, tight ceilings affect the&#13;
weakest (low returns and/or high risk) borrowers first and the strong ones&#13;
last. If there were no other lending constraints, banks would shift their&#13;
portfolio towards the large corporations when these constraints are more&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
binding and away from them when less binding. Therefore, we expect guaranteed&#13;
bond activity to be positively affected in the later case, as has been&#13;
observed in the recent period.&#13;
The overall decline in bank loan business is, in this environment,&#13;
much more strongly affected by the structure of interest rates. The incorrect&#13;
structure has led at least at this broad level (though detailed data is not&#13;
available for confirmation) to a steady decline in the proportion of loans&#13;
that banks make to the relatively weaker firms. Despite the increase in this&#13;
indirect form of lending through loan guarantees, the loan proportion of banks&#13;
adjusted for bond guaranteesrshows a smaller but definite declining trend.&#13;
The decline is from 55.8% in 1975 to 46.1% in 1982 instead of from 55.6% to&#13;
43.8% for loans alone (based on data frp, A9 and A12).&#13;
Liberalization&#13;
Pressures arising directly or indirectly from the balance of payments&#13;
position had led in 1981 to a resurrection of the policy of denationalization,&#13;
with Hanil Bank returning to private hands. Two more banks were&#13;
denationalized in 1982 and another in early 1983. These were supplemented by&#13;
liberalized entry rules, with two new banks being allowed to open business&#13;
over the same period. The entry of new banks raised the aggregate capital&#13;
assets of the banking system, and can, over the long run, provide beneficial&#13;
competition. In the prevailing situation it was probably another factor in&#13;
worsening bank profitability. Similarly, though denationalization could in&#13;
principle encourage a shift towards the use of profitability criteria in&#13;
lending decisions, it takes time to professionalize management and reorient&#13;
internal and external monitoring and control mechanism. It is not sufficient&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
just to declare formal managerial autonomy in budgeting, personnel management&#13;
and organizational decisions (Dec. 1982). Given the declining profitability&#13;
and the growing volume of "non-performing" (non-repayed) loans&#13;
denationalization also reduces the perceived stability of the banking system,&#13;
by eliminating the government's formal backing.&#13;
3.3 Trade Credit&#13;
An important counterpart of the decline in the relative proportion of&#13;
bank loans is the increase in the relative importance of trade credit. As&#13;
shown in Table A9, trade credits as a proportion of total loans (&amp; credit)&#13;
increased from about 15% in 1975 (14% in 1974) to about 21% in 1982. Though&#13;
it fluctuates strongly in some years, the general trend has been upward.    Even&#13;
more important has been the structure of trade credit itself. The proportion&#13;
of total trade credit given by private corporations increased from 82% in 1975&#13;
to over 90% by 1982. This has been accompanied by an even sharper fall in the&#13;
proportion of trade credit going to these corporations. This fell from 72% of&#13;
total trade credit in 1975 to 42% in 1982 (see All for recent data). Thus,&#13;
there has been a substantial. growth1 in the net trade credit given by private&#13;
corporations.&#13;
An examination of the corporate sectors' asset portfolio confirms this&#13;
conclusion (Table A6). Though trade credit taken as a proportion of total&#13;
liabilities fluctuated considerably, it shows no clear trends. Trade credit&#13;
outstanding as a proportion of total assets virtually doubled from 21% in 1975&#13;
to 40% in 1982. As a counterpart to this, the asset portfolio of households&#13;
(including firms) shows a clear inverse trend. Trade credits as a proportion&#13;
of total liabilities increased from 2% in 1975 to 17% in 1982.    This issue is&#13;
. _ _~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
related somewhat to the issue of bank loan portfolio shifts and guaranteed&#13;
bonds analyzed earlier. It is also an example of the broader issues of the&#13;
existence and efficiency of capital markets.&#13;
3.4 Diversified Corporations as Allocators of Capital&#13;
The previous analysis suggests that large private corporations in&#13;
Korea have increasing-l-y-t-aken on the role of financial intermediation for&#13;
smaller less diversified household firms. As suggested earlier, this is&#13;
partly due to the incorrect structure of interest controls. It also&#13;
illustrates, however, the capital market inefficiencies resulting from&#13;
information constraints.   As most of these smaller firms have no direct access&#13;
to security and bond markets, the only capital market relevant to them are the&#13;
various loan and credit markets.   The important role of different information&#13;
between potential lenders in loan markets, has been anlaysed elsewhere 8/.&#13;
Corporations, of course, have unique and extensive knowledge about the&#13;
behavior and characteristics of their suppliers, and to a lesser extent, their&#13;
buyers. More importantly, the large corporations because of the extent of&#13;
their diversification can pool returns and reduce risk, a function which&#13;
equity markets, perform in developed countries. They can, therefore, provide&#13;
a partial substitute for these markets, by directing their own and input&#13;
suppliers capital, as well as borrowed funds, to their most efficient use.&#13;
Though the short term effects appear to be quite clearly positive, there are&#13;
some pitfalls. The major one is that suppliers would tend to get locked into&#13;
individual corporations. Paradoxically, this phenomena seems analogous to the&#13;
problem of interlinkage between loan and output markets or share-tenancy in&#13;
some LDC agricultural markets. Lack of alternative loan sources can therefore&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
reduce the flexibility and responsiveness of the suppliers and reduce&#13;
~~~~~~~~ ~~~~~-          --- -  --- - -- - -- &#13;
competitiveness in these markets. The case for providing either positive or&#13;
negative incentives to intermediaries to encourage or discourage such behavior&#13;
by corporations is not however, strong.&#13;
Short Term Investment and Finance Companies (SIFCs)&#13;
Both insurance companies and savings institutions have slowly but&#13;
gradually increased their intermediation role as_shown_by-th-ierrelative&#13;
assets (Table A8). The most dramatic increase has however been in the role&#13;
played by SIFCs. The share of their assets in the assets of financial&#13;
intermediaries increased from 4.3% in 1975 to 10.7% in 1982. A popular&#13;
explanation of the relative growth of the SIFCs is that in the absence of&#13;
formal ceilings on their loan and deposit rates they have been able to offer&#13;
higher deposit rates and to do more aggressive marketing of loans.&#13;
Columns 2 and 4 of Table 4 (p.23) give the ratio of the bank bill rate&#13;
to the SIFC discount rate and the one year deposit rate to the SIFC deposit&#13;
rate. These confirm that over the period 1977 to 1983 the SIFC loan and&#13;
deposit rates have been significantly higher than that of deposit money&#13;
banks. Table A9 shows however that the ratio of SIFC loans to total loans and&#13;
credits was almost the same in 1982 as it was in 1975 (3.2 to 3.3%).     Though&#13;
it grew marginally to 4.2% in 1978, it has declined since then. Though the&#13;
loan interest gap narrowed in 1980 and 1981 (Table 4) there is no noticeable&#13;
impact of this on loan shares from 1980 to 1982 (Table A9).&#13;
The SIFCs were set up after the curb loan freeze of 1972 to provide an&#13;
alternative channel to the underground curb market. For the long term it was&#13;
hoped that SIFCs would compete with short term informal markets for depositors&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
and business borrowers. An important part of their business is the issuance&#13;
of their own paper which are effectively like deposits. As previously&#13;
suggested if any interest ceilings are to be applied they must be based on&#13;
deposit characteristics and not on institutions. There is a minor&#13;
qualification arising from the fact that banks may be much more safe from&#13;
depositors' perspective than the SIFCs. There are two ways of dealing with&#13;
this problem. One is to have a National Deposit insurance scheme which&#13;
insures deposits, but charges a higher insurance fee from SIFCs. An&#13;
alternative is to allow SIFCs to give marginally higher deposit interest rates&#13;
on deposits of comparable maturity and size.&#13;
The other important segment of their business and the major reason for&#13;
their fast growth, is dealing in paper issued by business firms. This has two&#13;
components: The placing of Industrial (and commercial) paper issued by firms,&#13;
and the rediscounting of promissory notes and bills. Most of this business&#13;
relates to bills issued by large companies. Table A13 shows the rapid rise in&#13;
the growth of Industrial papers between 1975 and 1982. The ratio of&#13;
Industrial Papers outstanding to loans and credits has grown from 1.4% in 1975&#13;
to 4.7% in 1981 and stabilised thereafter. An indication that the SIFCs have&#13;
reaped a major part of the benefit of the growth of this new instrument is&#13;
given in Table A14. The growth of bills resold by SIFCs kept pace with the&#13;
growth in industrial papers. Between 1975 and 1982, the compound yearly&#13;
growth rate for the former was 63.7%, and for the latter 63.8%.&#13;
The importance of Resold Bills in the business of SIFCs is also shown&#13;
in Table A14 by the ratio of Resold Bills to Assets and Liabilities. This&#13;
grew from .33 in 1975 to 1.23 in 1981 and has since declined to 1.05 at the&#13;
end of the third quarter of 1983. This is partly due to the leveling off in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
the relative growth of industrial papers. A change in regulations has also&#13;
permitted the sale of commercial bills by banks since September 1982. Another&#13;
reason is the change in government regulations which permitted entry of 10 new&#13;
SIFCs between July 1982 and March 1983. The assets of the SIFCs have&#13;
therefore increased due to new capitalization. The result of all this will be&#13;
intense competitive pressure even on the established SIFCs.&#13;
Banks Entry into the Commercial Paper Market&#13;
The freedom for banks to expand into the short term paper market is a&#13;
positive development for two reasons. Firstly, as suggested earlier, direct&#13;
short term loans may have very high transaction costs, so that discounting of&#13;
industrial and commercial paper may be a more efficient way of making short&#13;
term loans. Secondly, the banks will have the opportunity of using their base&#13;
of information and knowledge about their current clients in new directions.&#13;
They are thus likely to take over on increasing share of the corporate&#13;
business. The changing nature of the distribution of industrial paper&#13;
suggests that this may be a substantial portion of base steady state issue of&#13;
such paper. As shown in Table A13 almost 100% of the paper was issued by&#13;
private corporations in 1982 and 1981. In 1981, however, 60% of this paper&#13;
was held by individuals and 36% by corporations. This shifted significantly&#13;
in 1982 to 49% by individuals and 45% by corporations.&#13;
The SIFCs will be forced by this competition into moving into new&#13;
directions or folding. Some of them are likely to get even more closely&#13;
linked to individual business groups and serve as a conduit for short term&#13;
funds to them and their associated non-corporate suppliers and customers. The&#13;
alternative is to compete much more directly with the curb market by&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
increasing their flexibility and responsiveness. Their ability to do this&#13;
will depend critically on the interest rate differentials that are allowed on&#13;
this type of higher risk, quick disbursing, high transaction cost lending&#13;
activity.&#13;
Section 4. Securities Markets: Debentures and Equities&#13;
The relative importance of the loan, securities and industrial paper&#13;
markets can be seen from Figure 5. Taking a simple average for 1981 and 1982&#13;
(from Table A9), we find that they constitute approximately 70%, 26% and 4% of&#13;
the financial assets and liabilities respectively. Comparison of the&#13;
distribution for 1975 and 1982 shows that the relative importance of the&#13;
securities markets has increased only marginally by about .5%. One might&#13;
suspect that this is due to a shift away from government bonds to private&#13;
bonds and stocks. On the contrary the latter as a proportion of total&#13;
securities actually declined from 80% in 1975 to 61% in 1982.&#13;
Table All gives the distribution of holdings of total securities, and&#13;
of specific securities by type of holder. For total securities, the holder&#13;
category Other Financial Institutions (OFIs) have increased their proportion&#13;
of both the holdings and issue of securities. The holdings going from 14% of&#13;
total in 1975 to 23% in 1982 and issues going from 7% in 1975 to 19% of total&#13;
in 1982. The distribution of holdings of (private) debentures suggests, that&#13;
much of this increase was in holding of debenture.- Between 1975 and 1982 OFIs&#13;
almost doubled their holdings from 29% to 57% of total outstandings. Much of&#13;
these holdings are concentrated in the investment institutions including the&#13;
SIFCs. Thus these financial intermediaries have progressively increased their&#13;
intermediary role in the securities markets. As the previous analysis of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 5:     PROPORTION OF FINANCE PROVIDED&#13;
THROUGH DIFFERENT INSTITUTIONS&#13;
80&#13;
70                                                                   3&#13;
60&#13;
50&#13;
40&#13;
30&#13;
20&#13;
10&#13;
-1976      1977       1978       1979       1980      1981       1982&#13;
n LOANS &amp; CREDITS                 +   SECURITIES            o   INDUSTRIAL PAPERS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
relative asset growth showed (Table A8) the OFIs grew relatively faster than&#13;
other intermediaries and their role in the securities market is an important&#13;
reason for it.&#13;
The proportion of securities held by Individuals has declined from 52%&#13;
in 1975 to 45% in 1982 (Table All). A look at individual portfolio holdings&#13;
(Table A7) shows that securities as a proportion of their portfolio have shown&#13;
a marginal increase from 29% to 30% during the same period. More significant&#13;
has been the shift away from stocks to debentures and beneficiary&#13;
certificates. Between 1975 and 1982 stock holdings declined from 25% to 18%&#13;
of the portfolio while debentures and beneficiary certificates increased from&#13;
1% to 3% and nil to 8% respectively. The previous analysis of OFI&#13;
intermediation suggests that much of the beneficiary certificates represent&#13;
holdings of debentures and to a lesser extent government bonds or financial&#13;
debentures. The holdings of stocks versus the direct and indirect holding of&#13;
other securities is almost equal in 1982.&#13;
Two conclusions follow from this: Firstly, that financial&#13;
institutions will continue to play an increasing role in making various type&#13;
of bonds available to small individual holders. Secondly, that there is a&#13;
need for an institution providing a mutual fund of securities, through which&#13;
individuals of small or medium wealth can pool the risk of holding such&#13;
securities.&#13;
4.1 Bond Markets&#13;
The most significant development in the Bond market over the past&#13;
decade has been the growth of primary corporate bond_market. Compared to a&#13;
rate of growth of 42% in total bonds outstanding , corporate bonds outstanding&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
grew at a compound annual rate of 77% from 1975 to 1982 (Table A15). They&#13;
therefore increased their share of the bond market from 50% in 1975 to 85% in&#13;
1982. Of even greater significance is the fact that most of this growth was&#13;
in guaranteed bonds. These grew at a compound annual rate of 89% increasing&#13;
their share from 62% in 1975 to 97% in 1982 (Table A15). The primary&#13;
corporate bond market is therefore virtually identical to the market for&#13;
guaranteed bonds. It operates primarily through the stock exchange, with&#13;
almost 98% of outstanding bonds listed on the stock exchange in 1982.&#13;
Financial Innovation&#13;
The growth of guaranteed bonds therefore represents a major innovation&#13;
in the Korean financial market. It was shown earlier that these bonds are&#13;
virtually like loans as far as banks are concerned. In fact because banks do&#13;
not take any collateral for making such an "implicit loan" they are much more&#13;
risky for the banks. Thus they tend to transfer risk from equity to bond&#13;
holders, but in this case to the bank which guarantees them 9/. The only case&#13;
in which the banks will be willing to take such risk is if they have&#13;
information about, and some influence on the issuing firms, through the&#13;
mechanism of their regular loans to these firms. Much of these guarantees&#13;
have been by deposit money banks; their share between 77% and 92%, with a&#13;
simple average of 83% over the 1975 to 1980 period.&#13;
It is therefore instructive to analyse the reasons for this&#13;
innovation. It has been shown how lack of information and incorrect judgement&#13;
can result in non-lending to certain categories of borrowers or of certain&#13;
types of loans 10/. It was also shown how private returns to individual&#13;
institutions might be lower than the social returns because as soon as the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
activity was demonstrated to be profitable, such profits would tend to get&#13;
competed away 11/. Restrictions imposed in certain markets as they were in&#13;
the bank loan market in Korea, can change the private incentives and&#13;
perceptions about other markets. This is, I believe, what happened in the&#13;
guaranteed bond market.. A relative lack of incentives/opportunities of direct&#13;
lending made it profitable for banks to adopt this more risky form of lending.&#13;
As guaranteed bonds are equivalent to deposit-loan combinations of&#13;
equal maturity and issuer/borrower type, applicable interest rates must be&#13;
similar. If we assume that depositers are indifferent on margin between bank&#13;
deposits and guaranteed bonds, we can equate the risk adjusted returns (as a&#13;
crude approximation). These bonds are somewhat riskier for banks but involve&#13;
somewhat lower administrative costs (r-i-t). They may also be perceived as&#13;
somewhat riskier than deposits by bond holders. If we assume that depositors&#13;
are indifferent on margin between making a bank deposit or buying a guaranteed&#13;
bond, we can equate the risk adjusted returns (as a crude approximation).&#13;
Then the real unit cost of funds to the firm R is then given by the sum of&#13;
payments to final holders and intermediates, i.e.,&#13;
R = (l+a) i + d + (r-i-t) + p&#13;
where the decrease in bank's administrative cost is t , the broker takes a&#13;
commission d , i is the deposit interest rate, a the proportional premium&#13;
required by bond holders, r is the interest rate on loans and p the or&#13;
risk premium required by the bank.&#13;
It is useful to start with a look at the bond holder's yields. In the&#13;
above equation this is given by (l+a)i. Table A16 shows that the yield on&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
corporate bonds was 16.8% in 1982 while the average deposit interest rate on&#13;
1-3 year deposits was 11% (Table Al). From this, it is easily seen that&#13;
a = 0.527. Government also set ceilings on rates payable on 3 year bonds at&#13;
11% + 1.5% (=.1364xll) for the first year, and 1.3 times the time deposit (TD)&#13;
rate for the next two years. We can make an alternative calculation by a&#13;
using these rates to&#13;
obtain  a  =   0.1364 +   .3     +            =  0.525  .   This suggests that&#13;
1.168    (1.168)2    (1.168)3&#13;
bond holders correctly calculated the effective yield on bonds. It is&#13;
impossible to believe, however, that a risk premium of 53% is required to&#13;
induce depositors to hold corporate bonds guaranteed by banks when perfectly&#13;
riskless government. Even more paradoxically, public bonds have even higher&#13;
yields (as high as 17.7 in 1982; Table A16). It confirms therefore the&#13;
previously mentioned hypothesis of segmented deposit markets.&#13;
Using the formula given above, we can calculate the cost of funds to&#13;
the issuer of bonds for 1982. We assume that the maximum discounting allowed&#13;
by the government (4%) was the actual discount, and covered both brokerage&#13;
fees and bank transaction costs. If we also assume that the risk premium of&#13;
the bank is equal to the guarantee fee (1%) we find that the cost of funds&#13;
R  was 21.8%.   If, alternatively, the entire discount was passed on to bond&#13;
holders the cost of funds would be 17.8% (16.8 + 1%). Even taking this lower&#13;
estimate suggests that these firms paid a premium of 5% points for bond&#13;
financing. According to conventional treatment, this would represent the&#13;
element of effective interest ceiling and rationing in the market. The firms&#13;
do not, however, give any collateral to obtain this finance. It can be shown&#13;
that if collateral is constrained below its effective value, the interest rate&#13;
will be much higher than it would have been without the constraints. It was&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
also shown earlier that firms effectively transfer all risk to the banks. For&#13;
both these reasons firms may be willing to pay a 37% premium on the&#13;
collateralized loan rate.&#13;
Implicit in the lower bound calculation is a zero return to bank&#13;
capital from making loans. We have already shown that the average return on&#13;
loans in 1982 was negative. Bank's had at least a 1% return on guarantees&#13;
through the guarantee fee. If all the returns from discounting bonds was not&#13;
passed on to the bond holders intermediates would receive an extra return of&#13;
between 0 and 4%. This would provide an incentive to shift good borrowers&#13;
from loans to bond guarantees. Incentives may have been even stronger in the&#13;
preceeding years. Within the limitations of available data, this provides&#13;
indirect evidence for the innovation hypothesis presented above. It also&#13;
supports the bank portfolio shifts analysed earlier in Sections 3.2. Now that&#13;
much of the innovation has taken place in this particular area, banks should&#13;
be allowed to charge much higher guarantee fees than the current 1.5%.&#13;
Policy Measures&#13;
There is a more fundamental incentive problem with 100% guaranteed&#13;
bonds, which needs to be addressed directly. They provide an incentive for&#13;
engaging in "excessively" risky activities. Their zero collateral nature&#13;
coupled with the 100% guarantee effectively makes banks into nonvoting equity&#13;
holders. They cannot directly dissuade firms from undertaking risky&#13;
activities which may result in nonrepayment of bonds and a consequent loss to&#13;
banks. For the development of a genuine primary corporate bond market,&#13;
greater encouragement needs to be given to urguaranteed4boiis.    Issue of such&#13;
bonds by ligsted-compahies should therefore be freed from all control&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
regulations including any form of interest ceilings. The need to protect&#13;
bondholders suggests, however, that firms must be required to publicize their&#13;
true debt and financial position whenever they issue such bonds. This will&#13;
allow potential bondholders to assess the value of holding such bonds.&#13;
Another possible measure to develop the market would be to introduce&#13;
guaranteed bonds which carry a lower than 100% guarantee.     For example&#13;
government might encourage the development of bonds carrying a guarantee of&#13;
say 90%, by setting significantly higher interest ceilings. This may be&#13;
accompanied by tax incentives for holders.&#13;
4.2 Secondary Market in Bonds&#13;
A superficial look at the bond market gives a misleading picture of&#13;
the secondary markets. For example, Table A17 suggests that 6,247 billion Won&#13;
of bonds were traded on this market in 1982 which is almost three times the&#13;
amount of corporate bonds issued in that year. A more accurate picture&#13;
requires an understanding of the markets as presented in tables A18 and A19.&#13;
The entire secondary market consists of sales and purchase of bonds under&#13;
repurchase agreements, and not of outright sale as is typical in developed&#13;
country markets. The nature of this transaction is therefore basically like a&#13;
loan against the collateral of bonds. A simplistic analysis of Tables A18 and&#13;
A19 suggests that the period of "loan", or the period between the initial or&#13;
reverse repurchase transaction and its inverse was approximately one month in&#13;
the 1977 to 1980 period and varying between 1 and 3 months in later periods.&#13;
Similarly, the period of the "loan" repo transactions was about 4 months in&#13;
1982 and 1983, and varying between 2 and 6 months. In other words, these were&#13;
fairly short term "loans".&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
The statistics in Table Al8 are gathered largely from brokerage houses&#13;
and other security related companies. As these constituted most of the&#13;
institutional trades in the early stages this table gives a fairly accurate&#13;
picture. For 1982 and 1983 a complete picture is available from Tables A19&#13;
and A20. The other data problem relates to the fact that the sale of bonds&#13;
under repurchase agreements for one side of the market should be equivalent to&#13;
the purchase of a bond under reverse-repurchase. The data in these two tables&#13;
suggests that only one side of the market is being caught even though some of&#13;
the transactions may have been caught from both sides. We will ignore the&#13;
latter possibility.&#13;
After initial growth between 1977 and 1978 the market seems to have&#13;
fluctuated till 1980. Thus the ratio of Repos Outstanding to listed Bonds&#13;
outstanding was 0.7% in 1977, 6.0% in 1978 and about 2% in 1979 and 1980&#13;
(Table A18 column 11). The market grew rapidly thereafter; the rate of growth&#13;
of total outstandings was 175% between November 1981 and December 1982, and&#13;
lower, but still fairly high, at 64% between September 1982 and September&#13;
1983. (Bottom of Table A19). Thus Repos Outstanding as a proportion of total&#13;
bonds outstanding grew from 7.5% at the end of 1981 to 15.4% at the end of&#13;
1982 and to 19.9% at the end of the third quarter of 1983.&#13;
Table A20 gives an idea of the operators in this market, or the net&#13;
borrowers and lenders in this short term loan market. Individuals appear to&#13;
be the most important borrowers in the market, followed by corporations. If&#13;
we assume that the amount of loan is proportional to the value of the bonds&#13;
which acts as collateral we can calculate the proportion. Their borrowing&#13;
constituted about 70% of the total at 1982 and, 66% at end of October 1983.&#13;
Corporate borrowers have increased sharply, however from 21% to 31% over the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
same period. This is probably a reflection of the loan market constraints&#13;
analysed earlier. Listed companies were the major lenders in 1982, but&#13;
withdrew from the market in 1983 reflecting the same credit conditions.&#13;
The fact that there is discrepancy of 500 billion Won between&#13;
borrowing and lending at 1982 end 1975 billion Won by October 1983, suggests&#13;
that most of the lenders were not identified. I would hypothesize that most&#13;
of this discrepancy represented informal or curb market loans. The sharp&#13;
increase in this discrepancy would then represent a shift of curb lenders out&#13;
of this traditional channels (e.g., against promissory notes and bills) to new&#13;
methods.&#13;
The growth of this market does represent a widening and diversifying&#13;
of the loan market and is therefore a positive development. The permission&#13;
given to commercial banks in August 1982 to handle sales of government and&#13;
public bonds under repurchase agreements is therefore also a positive&#13;
development. It does not however represent, at this stage, a secondary market&#13;
in the traditional sense. Any view which sees, this as a widening of the&#13;
broader capital market (securities market), must therefore be viewed with&#13;
caution.&#13;
4.3 The Stock Market&#13;
As graphed in Figure 5 and shown in Table A9 all securities as a&#13;
proportion of total assets increased only marginally from 26.1% in 1975 to&#13;
26.8% in 1982. Stocks as a proportion of total securities fell drastically&#13;
from 76.5% to 38.9%. As the composite stock price index in 1982 was 127.3&#13;
compared 89.7 in 1975 this fall in proportion reflects a relative decline in&#13;
the importance of the stock market. This also reflected in the portfolio&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
composition of private corporations. Stocks as a proportion of total&#13;
liabilities declined from 34% in 1975 to 24% in 1982 and 16% in 1982 (Table&#13;
A6).&#13;
The proportion of stocks issued and held by corporations both show a&#13;
U shaped pattern between 1975 and 1982. The former was 75% and 77% at the&#13;
two end points while the latter was 17% at both points. The proportion of&#13;
stocks held by individuals also shows similar patterns, but increased from 58%&#13;
in 1975 to 63% in 1982. The importance of stocks in the individual portfolio&#13;
declined however from 25% of total assets in 1975 to 16% in 1982.&#13;
There is a question about the nature of equity markets in developing&#13;
countries which is worth investigating in the Korean context. It is my&#13;
hypothesis that in the early stages of development of the stock market, these&#13;
markets are qualitatively different from those in developed countries. The&#13;
smallness and its thinness for particular equities or subgroups of equities&#13;
makes the quantity to be bought or sold as important as the price (cannot be&#13;
treated parametrically). The time period or quickness with which a sale is&#13;
made may also significantly affect the price. Equity holding cannot therefore&#13;
be used as a reserve asset to supplement missing consumption loan markets, in&#13;
evening out the flow of consumption. Control over the financial decisions of&#13;
firms therefore becomes a critical factor. This appears in the large number&#13;
of firms in which an individual' family or group of friends hold majority&#13;
shares to ensure financial control. This in turn can make equities less&#13;
attractive to minority or noncontrolling shareholders.&#13;
In the Korean context the previously mentioned existence of large&#13;
diversified conglomerates can complicate this simple picture. Such firms have&#13;
an alternative channel for smoothing consumption. Relative to almost all&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
other potential borrowers, they have virtually unlimited access to loan&#13;
markets. Thus they can easily shift funds between use of loan for business&#13;
purposes and use for consumption (or dividend payments). We would therefore&#13;
expect a genuine equity market to emerge first for these type of firms.&#13;
Table A21 gives two different estimates of the secondary market&#13;
activity in the Korean stock exchange. Column I shows the number of existing&#13;
stocks traded as a proportion of the average number of listed stock. This has&#13;
fluctuated between .03% and .07% with the latter proportion prevailing-'in both&#13;
1969 and 1981. Though this is consistent with the hypothesis presented above,&#13;
the facts are more complicated. Column E shows the value of trade in existing&#13;
shares as a proportion of the average market value (beginning to end of&#13;
period) of outstanding stocks. This shows a completely different picture,&#13;
with the ratio fluctuating between 29% and 81% over the same period.&#13;
The explanation lies in the proviso given in the previous&#13;
paragraph. For 1982 we find that the shares of 40 large companies were&#13;
responsible for about 71% of the total value of sales. These companies&#13;
represent 12% of all the companies listed on the stock exchange in 1982. The&#13;
large discrepancy between the two measures provided earlier probably arises&#13;
because most of the secondary activity is in a small number of very highly&#13;
priced stock. This would make the value measure much higher than the volume&#13;
measure. It also suggests that a genuine equity market may be emerging for a&#13;
small number of large diversified firms.&#13;
Rates of Return&#13;
An examination of Table A22 shows that the average rate of return on&#13;
equity for the period 1976 to 1982 was 22.8% while that of corporate bonds was&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
20.9%. On the other hand, the variance in stock yields was 67.4% as against&#13;
21.7% for bonds. A rate of return premium of 1l.9% seems totally inadequate to&#13;
compensate for the much higher variance. This again seems to confirm the&#13;
hypothesis presented earlier. A word of caution is, however in order. The&#13;
difference in returns between the two types of securities was significantly&#13;
positive during the 1976-78 period, but became significantly negative over&#13;
1979 to 1982 period. This may be partly due to the major shock to the system&#13;
following from the oil shock (analysed later). This should not, however&#13;
affect the relative returns for more than one or at most two years. The fact&#13;
that stock market return continued to be lower than bond yields in 1981 and&#13;
1982 reduces the effect of this cautionary note.&#13;
Tables A23 and A24 give the pattern of share holding over 1981 and&#13;
1982. Three related facts emerge for this period: (1) a decline in the total&#13;
number of shareholders; (2) a decline in proportion of shares held by&#13;
individuals; and (3) an increasing concentration of the proportion of shares&#13;
held by those over 100,000 shares. These facts suggest that small individual&#13;
shareholder, the ones most likely to constitute "minority" shareholdings are&#13;
leaving the market. This is consistent with the lower returns mentioned&#13;
earlier.&#13;
In Korea the bogus name system combined with minority share holding&#13;
requirements for listing, have probably resulted in a large number of&#13;
apparently minority shareholders who are really part of the majority group.&#13;
Thus the possible introduction of the real name system may push these out of&#13;
the market. The introduction of this system may therefore require some&#13;
loosening of the minority holdings requirements if a fall in the number of&#13;
listed companies is to be prevented. The increase in the proportion of shares&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
held by security companies and insurance companies and other corporations may&#13;
represent a converse of this phenomenon (Table A24). Majority groups may have&#13;
worked out mutual arrangements through the aegis of the securities companies&#13;
or directly, to become minority holders. This is possible because many of the&#13;
companies listed in the stock market also have holdings in security, insurance&#13;
investment and savings institutions.&#13;
The development of equity markets can be seen from two related but&#13;
slightly different perspectives, the width and depth of the market. The&#13;
former is usually viewed in terms of the number of listed companies, or the&#13;
proportion of total investment capital raised in the equity market. This&#13;
results in policies to encourage (incentives) or force (outside discentives)&#13;
to firms to list their stock on the capital market. Examples of such policies&#13;
would be a reduction in minority holding requirements and higher tax rates for&#13;
nonpublic firms.&#13;
More important, in my view, is the deepening of the market in terms of&#13;
secondary trading. According to the hypothesis presented previously, the&#13;
investor's perspective and his ability to sell and buy any given amount in a&#13;
reasonable time, is critical to his holding of equities. In the light of&#13;
evidence presented earlier the opportunities for secondary trading in shares&#13;
of large companies is very important, and will play a major role in the future&#13;
development of the market. It is therefore important to encourage expansion&#13;
of this market.&#13;
Public and semipublic institutions (e.g. a Social Security Fund) are&#13;
most likely to be "expected profit" rather than "expected-utility"&#13;
maximizers. Encouragement should therefore be provided for such institutions&#13;
to participate in the holding and trading of equities. A gradual easing of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
restrictions on financial intermediaries to allow holding of and trading in&#13;
equities could be considered, though this must be traded off with the&#13;
possibility of greater industrial concentration. Wealthy individuals should&#13;
be encouraged to hold equities in firms which they do not control by providing&#13;
differential tax treatment. Restrictions on loans for equity buying should&#13;
also be eased.&#13;
4.4 Accelerated Depreciation and Debt-Equity Ratios&#13;
Many observers have noted the apparently high debt-equity (net-worth)&#13;
ratios in Korea and some have attributed-it to availability of "subsidized"&#13;
credit.  It is, of course, well known that inflation can change the real value&#13;
of both these terms.   In the Korean context the accelerated depreciation&#13;
provided, is I believe a more important factor, as observers have typically&#13;
used the book value of capital in their net-worth measures. An examination of&#13;
the income tax law shows special depreciation provisions giving an&#13;
acceleration in depreciation of. between 40% and 80%. Using a simple algebraic&#13;
model we can derive the following relationship between the steady state values&#13;
of the book value of capital (KB) to the real capital stock (K): 13/&#13;
KB    (1-6 a)g&#13;
K    g+68- 6&#13;
where  g   is the rate of gross investment to real capital,     6  is the real&#13;
depreciation rate,   6B  is the allowable depreciation rate, and    B  is the&#13;
proportion of investment which is allowed to be depreciated within the year of&#13;
investment itself.&#13;
The above formula shows that the ratio of book value to real capital&#13;
is positively related to the gross investment ratio and negatively related to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
the allowed depreciation. Accelerated depreciation therefore leads to an&#13;
understatement of capital and consequently an overstatement of the rate of&#13;
return to capital. Tables A25 and A26 give an idea of the orders of magnitude&#13;
involved. The case in which the real depreciation rate is 8% and allowable&#13;
depreciation rate is 12%, or 50% accelerated depreciation, is shown below:&#13;
Table 5: Book Value of Capital to Real Capital Stock (Z)&#13;
Investment to&#13;
Real Capital (g)              10     15       20     30&#13;
Investment to&#13;
Book Capital (gB)             16     22       27     36&#13;
Book to Real&#13;
Capital                       62     69       73     83&#13;
Even with a fairly high investment ratio of 30% real or 36% book value, book&#13;
value of capital is only 83% of real value. Thus even in a period of high and&#13;
steady growth with only 50% accelerated depreciation, the debt/equity ratio&#13;
could be overstated by 20%. With 100% accelerated depreciation the&#13;
overstatement would be as much as 50%. In the manufacturing sector the&#13;
investment to book value ratio was approximately 26%, 17% and 21% in 1981,&#13;
1982 and 1983 respectively. Over such a period the steady state ratio of book&#13;
value to real capital would change from 0.73 to 0.69 to.0.62 for the case&#13;
depicted above. This fluctuation is much less than the fluctuation in the&#13;
investment ratio. For a given level of acceleration in depreciation (say 40%)&#13;
the fluctuation increases however with the level of real depreciation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
Section 5. Forced Lending Policy and the Banking System&#13;
There are two fundamental issues which arise when the banking system&#13;
is used by the government to allocate capital. One is the desirability of&#13;
increasing (decreasing) the flow of resources to the particular sub-sectors or&#13;
uses. The case for such intervention must be based either on grounds of market&#13;
failure or of a discrepancy between social and private returns. As I have&#13;
shown elsewhere, the discrepancy between the expected marginal returns to&#13;
loans and the cost of funds to the banking system can be used as an indicator&#13;
of market failure. The other is the instruments to be used to affect&#13;
reallocation. These can be classified broadly into incentive mechanisms and&#13;
forced lending. The former includes subsidized rediscounting by the central&#13;
bank and subsidized credit (collateral) guarantee funds. The latter is often&#13;
combined with interest rate ceilings, as it has been in Korea. I have&#13;
shown elsewhere that incentive mechanisms are, with few exceptions, much more&#13;
efficient instruments for influencing resource allocation. 14/&#13;
If the choice of preferred borrower categories is made purely on&#13;
social (or worse political) grounds, the choice of an incentive versus a&#13;
forced system is also a choice between budgetary subsidies and subsidization&#13;
through implicit taxation of the banking system. If the choice is made on&#13;
efficiency/market failure grounds, the choice between the two methods&#13;
similarly represents a choice between the government assuming the&#13;
risks inherent in identifying market failure, or transferring these risks to&#13;
the banking system. The experience of Korea shows the hazards of forcing&#13;
banks to subsidize society and to take on the risks that the government should&#13;
bear.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-49 -&#13;
As noted in the introduction, credit policy has been one of the&#13;
instruments used by the government in its export oriented development&#13;
strategy, which started in the 1960s. Ai_ort-term loans were automatically&#13;
available to any exporter with a valid letter of credit. These covered the&#13;
entire gamut of production, inventories and bills receivable from foreign&#13;
importers. Long-term loans included foreign currency loans, Exim Bank loans&#13;
for import on credit and equipment loans for export industries. A major&#13;
element of the incentive structure was 100 rediscounting by the central bank&#13;
(BOK) of loans for export support and over 70% for export bills (Table A5).&#13;
This below market rate discounting represented a true interest subsidy or&#13;
incentive policy. Elements of forced lending included loan interest ceilings,&#13;
and explicit or implicit pressure on managers. As elements of both were used&#13;
to implement this scheme rigorous separation of the two is difficult.&#13;
Evidence of the success of the reoriented development strategy, and the&#13;
economic success of the export drive came fairly quickly. Under these&#13;
circumstances, the coercive elements of the policy would tend to become&#13;
redundant rapidly (i.e. interest ceilings become nonbinding). This would be&#13;
reinforced by the fact that large conglomerates, which usually obtain the best&#13;
terms, played a major role in the export drive. I would judge, therefore,&#13;
that with the possible exception of new and small exporters, interest ceilings&#13;
on these loans were not effective, and therefore the element of coercion was&#13;
minimal, during the 60s and early 70s.&#13;
The practice of automatic rollover of the short term debt of corporate&#13;
borrowers who were able to repay 20% of loan amount is consistent with this&#13;
conclusion. Given the absence of strong cyclical fluctuation, and the high&#13;
growth rates, this represented a rational conclusion that current liquidity&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
did not necessarily reflect future income and repayment possibilities. A&#13;
lower bound to the extent of automatic rollover is obtained by comparing&#13;
the equipment loans and term loans of the deposit money banks. As shown in&#13;
Table A27, in 1972 and 1973 equipment loans were 10% and 14%, while term loans&#13;
were only 3% and 2% of total banking fund loans.    The difference of 7-12%&#13;
probably represents virtually unconditional rollover. To this must be added&#13;
various levels of conditional rollover implicit in the 20% repayment criteria.&#13;
Starting from the mid-1970s, there is evidence of the increasing role&#13;
of forced lending in the governments allocation policy. This change is&#13;
associated with the governments strategy of bringing about a structural change&#13;
in industry by developing heavy and chemical industries (hereafter HC). Though&#13;
the electronics industry was included in this strategy, it does not really fit&#13;
under the HC label, and any conclusions drawn with respect to HC industries do&#13;
not necessarily apply to it. Table A28 shows that between 1978 and 1981&#13;
approximately 50% of the total loans of the deposit money banks were "directed&#13;
loans". Yang (1982) has estimated that 92% of directed/preferential loans&#13;
allocated to the manufacturing sector were earmarked for the HC industries&#13;
during the 1978-1980 period.&#13;
An important, though not the only, instrument of the forced lending&#13;
policy was the National Investment Fund (NIF). Some idea of the economic&#13;
problems arising from the lending policy towards the HC industries can&#13;
therefore be obtained from available NIF statistics. Table 6 (below) shows&#13;
that the governments subsidy to the NIF increased from 2.2 billion Won in 1974&#13;
to 43 billion Won in 1979. Appendix Table A29 shows the repayment&#13;
performance of the HC industries in terms of cumulated repayments&#13;
and cumulated new loans. This measure is used so as to minimize the effect of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
differences in loan terms, data for which is not available. If we ignore&#13;
defense industries in which both quantities and prices are determined by&#13;
government defense policy, the highest repayment rate in 1982 was 26%. The&#13;
shipbuilding industry had the lowest repayment rate of 13% (1982). Available&#13;
data on capacity utilization rates in manufacturing sub-sectors confirms that&#13;
the problem is not restricted to NIF loans. Park's (1983) data shows that&#13;
during the entire 1975-1980 period, the Transport equipment and Machinery sub-&#13;
sectors had the lowest capacity utilization rates. In 1980 the rates were 44%&#13;
and 42% respectively.&#13;
Table 6: Government Coverage of NIF Deficits: Unit Bi. Won&#13;
1974     1975      1976     1977     1978      1979     1980     1981&#13;
2.2      5.3      10.5     15.6     18.2      43.0     40.0     40.0&#13;
The result of the forced lending policy of the government was that the&#13;
banks entered the eighties with a substantial proportion of what were&#13;
euphuistically referred to as "Non-Performing" loans. With their asset&#13;
structure undermined, commercial banks could have become a prey to a crises of&#13;
confidence in the banking system, but for the fact that they were largely&#13;
government owned. As it was, the oil shock of 1979-80 magnified the problem&#13;
to an extent that it became a serious problem even for the government, and&#13;
constrained its freedom to undertake monetary policy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
Section 6.   Monetary Policy in a Constrained Financial System&#13;
6.1 Consequences of the Oil-Shock&#13;
The oil shock of 1979-80 resulted in an inflation rate (GNP deflator)&#13;
of 19.3% in 1979 and 23.8% in 1980. It also led to the first serious reces-&#13;
sion in the Korean economy, with a growth rate of -6.2% in 1980. Even though&#13;
the growth rate of GNP rebounded sharply in 1981 to reach 6.4% recessionary&#13;
conditions in world markets continued to affect export markets and producing&#13;
sectors connected with them. Though the recession in developed country&#13;
markets may be predominantly a cyclical phenomenon the slowing of the growth,&#13;
in the middle eastern markets, probably had a more permanent effect on&#13;
previously fast growing export sectors such as construction.&#13;
The preceding decade had been characterized by sustained high economic&#13;
growth and fairly high inflation, an environment to which banking practices&#13;
had adapted. In such an environment the nominal market value of assets held&#13;
by borrowers was quite rationally expected to increase steadily over time.&#13;
This was reflected in Banking practices which treated 100% of the current&#13;
market value of assets as collateral. Banks were also not unduly perturbed by&#13;
the apparently high Debt to Net-Worth (Book Value) ratios which have so&#13;
worried outside observers. Given the rate of inflation, and the provision of&#13;
accelerated depreciation book value of equity overstates the true Debt to Net&#13;
Worth ratios.&#13;
The unexpected and prolonged decline in the rate of growth of many&#13;
export sub-sectors and in the absolute demand in some has severely affected&#13;
many firms in these sectors. A financial system attuned to steady growth had&#13;
not developed expertise and experience in differentiating between short term&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
and long term effects. Faced with the consequences of this shock the&#13;
difficult judgement of cyclical versus long term consequences was probably&#13;
weighted too heavily towards the former. Though income and growth prospects&#13;
had declined in several sub-sectors, as had the market value of collateralized&#13;
industrial assets, borrowing and lending activities adjusted much more&#13;
slowly. Loans continued to be rolled over as before, and in some cases even&#13;
increased to meet what were wrongly perceived as short-term liquidity&#13;
problems. This resulted in a reduction in firm bankruptcies below what they&#13;
would otherwise have been, but increased the probability of future loan&#13;
defaults.&#13;
6.2 Policy Response and Consequences: A Financial Perspective&#13;
On the financial side interest rate ceiling were raised sharply in&#13;
early 1980 to cope with inflationary pressures arising from the oil price rise&#13;
(from about 18.6$/bbl to in 1979 to 30.5$/bbl in 1980). Time deposit rate&#13;
ceiling for deposit money banks were raised from 18.6% to 24.0%. Similarly&#13;
the basic loan rate - the discount rate for commercial bills and the interest&#13;
rate for general fund loans was raised from 18.5 to 24.5 for prime&#13;
enterprises.&#13;
A gradual change in the official attitude toward inflation, starting&#13;
in 1980, was given effective operational content by a sharp reduction in Ml&#13;
growth in the latter half of 1981. Ml growth was 25.4%, - 5.8% and 4.6% in&#13;
the second, third and fourth quarters of 1981 respectively, over that of a&#13;
year earlier. The rate of inflation declined to 18.1% in 1981 at least partly&#13;
as a consequence of this policy.&#13;
The fact that M2 continued to grow at 24% to 25% over the last three&#13;
quarters of 1981 seems to belie this reasoning, however. To the extent the&#13;
unofficial financial market rates can be taken seriously the expLanation seems&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54 -&#13;
to lie in relative interest rate changes. Table 7 (derived from Table Al)&#13;
gives the 1 year time deposit rates of deposit money banks. It shows, that&#13;
the ratio of Bank TD rates to the informal market rate rose from 0.43 in the&#13;
fourth quarter of 1979, to 0.56 in the 4th Quarter of 1980. This ratio&#13;
remained at a historically high average of 0.55 over 1981. This change in&#13;
relative interest rates would tend to shift funds from the informal into the&#13;
formal markets. An approximate estimate of this shift can be obtained by&#13;
using a portfolio equation estimated earlier for data from 1964-1 to&#13;
1979-4 15/. Taking account of the direct as was well as lagged effects of&#13;
relative interest (TD&amp;UFM) rate changes from the 1st quarter of 1980 to the&#13;
3rd quarter of 1981 these would have the effect of increasing real time&#13;
deposits (TD/CPI) by 35%.&#13;
Table 7: Ratio of TD to Unofficial Market Rates - Quarterly&#13;
1979                 1980                      1981                       1982&#13;
4th      1st     2nd     3rd     4th       1st     2nd     3rd    4th      1st&#13;
0.43     0.46    0.49     0.54    0.56      0.53    0.55    0.56   0.56     0.46&#13;
The formal banking system was it appears, largely spared the effects&#13;
of the tight money policy during 1981. It therefore had sufficient funds to&#13;
continue supporting its traditional clients during this period. By early&#13;
1982, there was a growing realization of the extent of the real problem of&#13;
potential firm failure. This was reflected during the 1st half of 1982, in a&#13;
sharp change in the loan portfolio away from construction, one of the worst&#13;
affected sectors. As Table A30 shows, the proportion of industry loans of&#13;
deposit money banks going to construction fell from 12.8% at end 1981 to 9.9%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
at end June 1982. During this period therefore the firms closest to the verge&#13;
of bankruptcy were increasingly pushed to the curb market.&#13;
This factor combined with the diversion of funds away from the curb to&#13;
the formal markets resulted in a progressive crunch in the curb market. A&#13;
major manifestation of this was probably the drying up of traditional channels&#13;
both formal and informal, for the high risk firms. I have shown how adverse&#13;
selection problems can lead to elimination of markets for sets of&#13;
borrowers. 161 Risk taking lenders and desperate borrowers opened new&#13;
channels and used unconventional methods, which first came to light in the&#13;
curb market scandal of May 1982, and were probably a major causative factor.&#13;
The banks did not escape the consequences entirely. Partly because of the&#13;
delayed effect of the recessionary conditions, and partly as a consequence of&#13;
the curb manipulation, the earlier overhang of non-performing loans was&#13;
starting to worsen.&#13;
In June 1982 the government undertook a major realignment of the&#13;
interest rate structure. Interest rate ceilings applicable to the deposits&#13;
and loans of the deposit money banks were lowered. Similar adjustments were&#13;
also made in the ceilings applicable to other institutions. To an extent this&#13;
was merely an adjustment of nominal rates in line with inflation. Ceilings&#13;
which had been raised in 1980 to reflect higher inflation were periodically&#13;
lowered from mid-1980 to mid-1982 to reflect the declining rate in 1981 and&#13;
1982. An unstated but important objective of lowering loan rates was to&#13;
reduce the interest costs of potentially bankrupt firms and thus to provide&#13;
more time for recovery. As discussed earlier the reduction of DMB loan rates&#13;
to lOX and deposit rates to 8% had an adverse effect on bank profitability.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
6.3 Monetary Policy Reversal&#13;
The decline in bank loan and deposit rates was not matched by an&#13;
equivalent fall in rates in unofficial markets during the second half of&#13;
1982. Table A2 shows that the ratio of Time Deposit rates to informal loan&#13;
rates fell from about .41 in the 1st half to about .28 in the second half of&#13;
1982. Thus the forced lending policy (previous section) required a loosening&#13;
of monetary policy to ease the tightening liquidity position of banks. This&#13;
combined-with the general desire to supply liquidity to firms through the&#13;
financial system led to a sharp increase in money supply. The growth rate,&#13;
which was 3.1% in 1982-1 and 13.5% in 1982-2 was stepped up sharply to 69% in&#13;
1982-3 and maintained at about 45% in the next two quarters. To the extent&#13;
that an anti-inflationary posture by the government was a relatively new&#13;
development, the earlier reduction in Ml growth was clearly overdone. It had&#13;
therefore played a role in accentuating the crises. Some easing of the&#13;
monetary growth policy was therefore called for. By the same token however,&#13;
the abrupt and sharp reversal had the potential of re-igniting inflationary&#13;
expectations. The public was likely to view this as proof of governments'&#13;
intentions regarding inflation and monetary control. Though inflation&#13;
continued to fall, to 18.1% in 1981, 8.0% in 1982 and 2.8% (est.) in 1983, the&#13;
decline in import prices probably played a major role in this decline.&#13;
The Money growth rate which had been increased in the second half of&#13;
1982 was maintained at a fairly high rate in early 1982. This was coupled&#13;
with selective public expenditure policies directed to the most affected&#13;
sector-construction. The result was to raise the share of Deposit Money Bank&#13;
loans going to the construction sector to 10.6 percent by end 1982 and 11.7 by&#13;
October 1983 (Table A30). Partly because of the revival in export and GNP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
growth and partly because of a perception that inflationary expectations were&#13;
reviving (wage rate growth) monetary policy was tightened again. The,growth&#13;
rate of Ml fell from 35Z in 1983-2nd quarter 13% in 1983-3rd quarter (both&#13;
over a year earlier). This was accomplished partly by reduction of Bank of&#13;
Korea rediscount ratio's on most loan categories.&#13;
There is an important lesson for monetary policy in the analysis&#13;
carried out so far. In this type of situation sharp reversals in monetary&#13;
policy are likely to have an adverse effect on both the firm bankruptcy and&#13;
the financial stability problem and on inflationary expectations. Too sharp a&#13;
tightening can itself induce an expectation of a subsequent reversal. A firm&#13;
but gradual policy of monetary tightening is therefor to be preferred.&#13;
6.4 Screening by Expected Returns&#13;
As analysed more fully in the appendix, when collateral value falls&#13;
virtually to zero as the result of a particularly severe and unanticipated&#13;
shock, borrowers became risk lovers, to the detriment of the lenders&#13;
(expected) repayment possibilities. To the extent that banks find it in their&#13;
interest to reduce sectoral exposure during a recession they also have the&#13;
problem of distinguishing between borrowers with relatively good and bad&#13;
future prospects (over a wide grey area). I have shown how this results in a&#13;
reduction in loans and an increase in interest rates to the entire set of&#13;
borrowers.-71 Government intervention may be necessary if it has better&#13;
information or a greater ability to obtain such information. The best&#13;
information is of course likely to be with firms within the sector.&#13;
Government can therefore provide incentives to eliminate bad firms within the&#13;
sector through take-over by the stronger firms. One way of accomplishing this&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 58 -&#13;
is for the government to subsidize the take over of repayment obligations. To&#13;
the extent that banks are also responsible, the costs may be shared by them&#13;
through partial write-off of bad loans. If, however, the forced lending&#13;
policy of the government is largely responsible for pressuring banks to lend&#13;
to unprofitable sectors against their judgement, it must take on a major part&#13;
of the costs. This seems to have been the case for certain heavy industries,&#13;
but not necessarily in the construction export sector. Though the Korean&#13;
authorities seem to have been slow in recognizing the magnitude of the problem&#13;
(not till September 1983) they seemed to have realized that this is good way&#13;
of solving the problem.&#13;
The moral hazard problem also becomes very acute for firms close to&#13;
bankruptcy. When firms are virtually bankrupt there is little additional cost&#13;
to them from failure to fulfill new obligations. They therefore become&#13;
willing to take loans at any interest rate. If lenders perceive the correct&#13;
situation they would quite correctly not be willing to give them new loans.&#13;
If the government has the correct information it should intervene before&#13;
individual banks lacking such information get overcommitted.&#13;
Because of mistakes of this type, or purely due to chance, particular&#13;
banks may be saddled with a much larger proportion of bad loans. This seems&#13;
to have been the case in Korea. The free market solution is to let banking&#13;
firms or other financial intermediaries suffer the consequences of their&#13;
actions or luck. Failure of one institution can have much more serious&#13;
consequences, however, for the public faith in and the future development of&#13;
the entire system. Thus in developed countries each intermediaries' action&#13;
can have strong external diseconomies on all others. This argues strongly for&#13;
all intermediaries sharing at least in the effect of adverse changes beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 59 -&#13;
their control. Government action is therefore necessary to spread the costs&#13;
of firm bankruptcy and nonrepayment. The Korean government did this by&#13;
providing liquidity to affected banks through the nonaffected ones so that the&#13;
latter will in effect share some of the risk faced by the former. In effect&#13;
the risk is pooled among the banks and the government. A better long term&#13;
solution would be to improve the loan guarantee system and to use subsidized&#13;
rediscounting instead of forced lending-interest ceilings policies to&#13;
influence the flow of credit.&#13;
6.5 The Curb Market&#13;
The sharp spurt in the rate of growth of real estate prices in 1983&#13;
was seen in Korea both as a cause and a symptom of rising inflationary&#13;
expectations. It was thought that land speculation could somehow thwart the&#13;
government's policy of controlling inflation through tight money policy.&#13;
Table A31 shows that the rate of growth of land prices declined progressively&#13;
from 1978 to 1982. In. particular the growth rate declined from 11.7% in 1980&#13;
to 5.4% in 1980, largely in line with the decline in inflation (Table 8).&#13;
There was however a sharp upturn in 1983 to 20%. A look at real land prices&#13;
suggests that the reversal may have started in 1982 (Table 8). As loans by&#13;
formal intermediaries for "speculative activities" are forbidden there exists&#13;
a suspicion that the phenomenon is connected with the Curb Market.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 60 -&#13;
Table 8: Rates of Growth (X) of Land Prices&#13;
1980     1981      1982     1983&#13;
test.)&#13;
Land Price Index                    11.7      8.5      5.4        20&#13;
GNP deflator                        23.8     18.1      8.0       2.8&#13;
Real land prices                   -10.1   -10.6      -2.6     +17.2&#13;
An examination of recent curb market rates in Table 8 and comparison&#13;
with rates in 1982 (Column A, Table Al) shows that they rose slightly in     the&#13;
fourth quarter of 1982, then fell sharply in the first quarter of 1983, and&#13;
have been rising gradually since then. Comparison with commercial bank loan&#13;
rates (Column K, Table Al) shows that after the cut in loan ceiling in mid-&#13;
year the ratio of loan rates to the curb rates was at about .35 for the rest&#13;
of the year. This was the lowest ratio in more than three years. It suggests&#13;
that risk premia in informal markets increased sharply because of talk about&#13;
controlling these markets through various measures such as the introduction of&#13;
the real name system. By the first half of 1983 the ratio seems to have risen&#13;
to more normal levels (.43 to .49), suggesting a reduction in the risk&#13;
premium. As potential firm bankruptcy was still a serious problem, while the&#13;
recognition of this fact in financial markets was growing, it seems unlikely&#13;
that curb lending risk declined. An alternative hypothesis is that&#13;
potentially bankrupt firms were, at this stage, being almost totally excluded&#13;
from the traditional curb markets. The measured interest rate therefore&#13;
reflects only the reduced level of relatively lower risk transactions which&#13;
were being undertaken. The curb scandals of mid-1983 suggest that the only&#13;
way in which excluded borrowers could obtain loans was by opening new and&#13;
virtually illegal channels. The only condition under which lenders were&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 61 -&#13;
prepared to make loans was with virtually complete repayment guarantees&#13;
through illegal collusion with bank personnel. In my view this was a&#13;
manifestation of the very difficult prevailing conditions. It is not, as many&#13;
people have come to believe, the standard and overwhelming method of operation&#13;
of the curb market during the 1980's.&#13;
If this hypothesis is correct, then it is very likely that traditional&#13;
curb market lenders shifted their portfolio composition towards real estate.&#13;
This could have been either by increasing loans to this sector, or more&#13;
likely, through direct investment. Both the rising curb market interest rates&#13;
and rising real estate prices during 1983 are a reflection of this&#13;
phenomenon. The introduction of the real name system for transactions and&#13;
increased capital gains taxes on real estate may be useful as a damper on&#13;
speculation. In my view, however, there was no cause for excessive alarm&#13;
about the effect of real estate speculation on anti-inflationary policy.&#13;
Section 7. Conclusions&#13;
Over the period analysed in the present paper, Korea appears to have&#13;
done a reasonably good job in setting the base level of controlled loan&#13;
interest rates. The most important factor in this success was the&#13;
governments' flexibility in adjusting rates to credit conditions. For this&#13;
purpose the Informal or Curb loan market served a useful function in providing&#13;
information on supply-demand conditions in financial markets. In effect the&#13;
government reached a good compromise between unstable and flexible rates.&#13;
Their experience suggests that the existence of an unregulated credit market&#13;
segment and access to information about it greatly facilitated this job. To&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 62 -&#13;
reduce dependence on this source the government should completely free the&#13;
inter-bank call money market.&#13;
There seems to have been much less success in setting the structure&#13;
of loan interest rates. It was shown how an incorrect structure influenced the&#13;
evolution of the financial system; Both the relative growth of different&#13;
financial instruments, and the relative growth of different institutions.&#13;
Conventional analysis with its exclusive focus on "real rates" tends&#13;
to discount the great importance of an appropriate structure of loan interest&#13;
rates. An inappropriate structure of loan rates means that some segments of&#13;
the credit market face effective interest ceilings. I have shown elsewhere&#13;
that this tends to reduce loan amounts to these segments and to increase&#13;
collateral requirements. In Korea, this effected both the relative growth of&#13;
institutions more heavily involved in these segments and the development of&#13;
new instrument.&#13;
At least in recent years the spread between the average loan rates and&#13;
the average deposit rates of the banking system, has also been&#13;
inappropriate. This had a strong negative effect on the profitability of the&#13;
banking system, and reduced its flexibility in responding to external shocks.&#13;
Low profits for the banking system, particularly a nationalized one, often&#13;
have little immediate visible impact. These profits are therefore often&#13;
undermined by governments facing a tight budgetary situation. This can&#13;
gradually eat away at the vitality and professionalism of the banks. This can&#13;
effect the health and viability of a critical element of the financial system.&#13;
The interest ceilings inherent in the structure of loan interest&#13;
rates, and the type and range of business that particular institutions are&#13;
permitted to carry out,, interactively influenced the evolution of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 63 -&#13;
financial system. Incentive policies such as subsidized rediscounting by the&#13;
central bank (BOK) were also a factor. These combined with implicit ceilings&#13;
on longer term and more risky loans effect the profitability and growth of&#13;
the specialized banks and development institutions. The former had a more&#13;
important (positive) effect on these institutions' development in the early&#13;
stages. As the information collection and market development potentialities&#13;
were exhausted, the latter effects began to predominate and slow down the&#13;
growth.&#13;
The banking system was the most important channel for implementing the&#13;
allocation policies of the government. It is the part of the financial system&#13;
most affected by interest ceilings and forced lending policies. In Korea this&#13;
was reflected in a declining share of total loans originating from them.&#13;
The permission granted by the government to them to offer repayment guarantees&#13;
on bonds issued by corporations opened an alternative channel which they&#13;
eagerly exploited. The phenomenal growth of this instrument has been one of&#13;
the important innovations in Korea's financial structure over the last&#13;
decade. As our analysis showed this was, for the banks, merely a means to&#13;
expand lending in a relatively unconstrained segment of the market. To&#13;
preserve the incentive structure in the long term, a reduction in the current&#13;
100% guarantee proportion is, however necessary. Serious moral hazard problems&#13;
can arise otherwise.&#13;
Another important development was the growth of the industrial and&#13;
commercial paper market. As in the case of guaranteed bonds interest ceilings&#13;
were relatively less binding. As only the short term investment and finance&#13;
companies were allowed to operate in this market, they grew rapidly. In both&#13;
cases the degree to which interest ceilings act as a constraint depend on the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 64 -&#13;
type of borrower. In contrast to the large corporate borrowers, the ceilings&#13;
were binding on the smaller more risky (from the lenders information&#13;
perspective) firms.&#13;
This in turn led to another important development; the growth of Trade&#13;
Credit given by the corporate sector. Analysis suggests that the corporate&#13;
sector increasingly acted as a financial intermediary channeling funds to its&#13;
non-corporate suppliers. The information advantage that it has in this&#13;
situation is clearly an important reason for this development, along with the&#13;
constraints imposed on the banks.&#13;
The nature of information problems in the equity market work in the&#13;
same direction. Large diversified conglomerates are correctly perceived by&#13;
the financial system as low average risk. In the constrained Korean system&#13;
they tended to act as internal capital markets, pooling risk across their&#13;
diverse activities. They could therefore allocate capital, with_some&#13;
limitation, to the most productive activities, even though the formal&#13;
allocation was for specific activities. In the initial stages of&#13;
development of equity and secondary security markets, these companies&#13;
still tend to act as closely held family concerns; using the flexibility to&#13;
optimize their intertemporal saving-consumption problem. Our analysis shows&#13;
that the largest corporations are beginning to emerge from this phase and act&#13;
more as conventional profit maximizers in developed markets. Evidence for&#13;
this is provided by the increasing activity in the secondary market for&#13;
their equities. This trend needs to be encouraged. A mutual fund containing&#13;
a mix of bonds and equities, which takes over the monitoring role for the&#13;
large number potential small investors is one step that can be taken in this&#13;
direction.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 65 -&#13;
Though methods exist for identifying market failure and the need for&#13;
government intervention in credit markets, these are often difficult to apply,&#13;
and perhaps for that reason are seldom applied. In addition they are not&#13;
completely adequate for dealing with completely new economic activities&#13;
such as some of the specific industries within the broadly defined Heavy and&#13;
Chemical industries, which were picked out by Korea. The results of such&#13;
intervention can be (and often are) quite bad.&#13;
Even if the methods are applied without social or political bias, for&#13;
both the above reasons, intervention can be risky, and the successes and&#13;
failures of Korea's experience illustrate this fact. Thus the correct choice&#13;
of (export) growth sectors in the 1960s was somewhat tarnished by mistakes in&#13;
the selection of certain heavy and chemical industries in the mid-1970s.&#13;
__               -   -  _-, &#13;
The relative emphasis on incentive based versus forced lending&#13;
instruments applied to the banking system, have a major effect on who bears&#13;
this risk of intervention. Use of forced lending instruments transfers this&#13;
risk from the government budget to the banking system. The selection mistakes&#13;
coupled with increasing resort to forced lending policies resulted in an&#13;
increasing overhang of nonrepayment of loans. This considerably weakened the&#13;
banking systems ability to respond to adverse shocks. The 1980 oil shock&#13;
which affected internal, and particularly, export markets for Korean firms&#13;
created the threat of large scale firm bankruptcy. This in turn put an&#13;
unbearable strain on the weakened banking system.&#13;
In this situation, the exercise of monetary policy was severely&#13;
constrained. A sharp reduction in monetary growth heightened the bankruptcy&#13;
problem. The consequent reversal of policy led to inflationary expectations&#13;
which were then more difficult to control with subsequent tightening. The&#13;
lesson which emerged from this experience, is that a gradual and firm&#13;
tightening of monetary growth is preferable to radical departures which&#13;
may not be economically or politically sustainable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 66 -&#13;
APPENDIX&#13;
Firm Bankruptcy and Bank Failure: The Role of Collateral&#13;
In an idealized capital market, perhaps approximated by the US one,&#13;
society benefits from firms going bankrupt. In fact, banks would force firms&#13;
into bankruptcy to collect at least the collateral value of their initial&#13;
loans and to write-off uncollectible debts. This view neglects several&#13;
informational problem which can arise, and seem to have arisen in Korea:&#13;
these are the Cyclical Variation in Collateral Value, Moral Hazard problems&#13;
which become particularly acute when bankruptcy is possible, Adverse Selection&#13;
arising from the difficulty of distinguishing between those with relatively&#13;
good and those with worse prospects, and negative externalities arising from&#13;
the failure (sometimes even suspected failure) of even one financial&#13;
institution.&#13;
Resale Value of Collateralized Assets&#13;
Markets for used capital goods are known to be very fragmentary even&#13;
in developed countries. Cyclical fluctuations in returns to different sectors&#13;
(or the economy) are, however, reflected fairly well in fluctuations in&#13;
expected future returns (stock prices) and the resale/collateral value of&#13;
capital assets. Stock prices are known to-be a leading indicator, and&#13;
collateralized equipment prices are probably a lagging one. In the presence&#13;
of rudimentary stock and used capital asset markets, banks or other lenders&#13;
are more likely to suffer a locking-in effect. That is, loans given when&#13;
current returns and asset value of equipment was high cannot be severely&#13;
reduced at or near the bottom of recessions, even if the expected future&#13;
income prospects appear to have worsened. This is because the collateral&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 67 -&#13;
value has worsened even more, and it would not be worth declaring default.&#13;
This is particularly true when the severity or timing of the cyclical downturn&#13;
was unanticipated, or as seemed to have happened in Korea it was virtually&#13;
unanticipated shock.&#13;
When the cyclical recession in a particular sector or a group of&#13;
sectors is anticipated, banks or lenders will start trying to reduce their&#13;
loan portfolio exposure before the conditions materialize. Further each bank&#13;
or lender would prefer to be out first to get either the full repayment, or if&#13;
that is not possible the maximum resale value of the collateral. The&#13;
selection of firms for reducing loans is likely to be based most heavily on&#13;
current returns.  This is likely to worsen their liquidity position.    This may&#13;
result in failure of some firms which are basically sound, and acts as an&#13;
additional factor in speeding up the recession. Some form of government&#13;
intervention may then become necessary. To an extent, this happened with&#13;
international lending to Korea and in the absence of international government&#13;
the multilateral agencies (World Bank, IMF) had to intervene. This probably&#13;
staved of a preemptive reduction in private loans which would have accentuated&#13;
the shorter term crises.&#13;
When the downturn is due to a particularly severe and unanticipated&#13;
shock as seems to have been the case for some sectors such as construction, so&#13;
that collateral value falls virtually to zero, another problem arises. As&#13;
shown in the following Figures 6 and 7 18/, the repayment function changes&#13;
from being of form DCBA to DCBA' and the firm net return function from HGFE to&#13;
HGFE'. Technically this means that banks will now act as strictly risk averse&#13;
lenders and firms as risk loving borrowers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68 -&#13;
FIGURE 6                                    FIGURE 7&#13;
Firm Return&#13;
Repayment                                 after Repayment&#13;
to Bank&#13;
C           D&#13;
H&#13;
El         F&#13;
GLFirm's Gross&#13;
R nReturn&#13;
A          B&#13;
--Collateral: CI&#13;
-L  C-L                  Firm's&#13;
Gross&#13;
Return&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TARLR Al:   AVF.RAGR QUARTRRLY INTERVST RATF.S (S)&#13;
A             B         C         )        8              F         C            H            I        .1                    L          H    N&#13;
UFI/      overdue     Over-     Call    General       Resold     Discount       TD        Corporate  Stock&#13;
(Curb)                   drafts    Loans   Bills &amp;      w/ Non       Third        Rates        Bond     Market     1            F          H&#13;
Loans       Recourse     Party/       (Non       Yields     Returns    A           G           A     F&#13;
(60-90)      Bank      Household,              (Yearly)&#13;
(Deposits) Guarantee     (I Year)&#13;
1977  1       42.1                                          17.0      19.0                                               .40               .38   .85&#13;
2       40.5                                          17.0      19.6                                               .42         .3    .40   .83&#13;
3       35.5         25        17.0      20.0         15.0      19.6         19.71       16.2     20.2    15.84    .42         .76   .46   .83&#13;
4       34.0         25        17        20          15         19.6         19.71        14.3    20.0             .44         .76   .42   .73&#13;
1978  1       38.4        25         17        20          15         19.6         19.71       14.4     20.7             .39         .76   .38   .73&#13;
2       38.4         25        17        21.7         15        19.8         20.0         18.0    20.6    11.5     .39         .75   .47   .91&#13;
3       43.2        25         20.0      22.0        18.0       20.6         21.0         18.6    20.6             .42        .86    .43   .90&#13;
4       46.8         25        20.5      20.3         18.5      20.6         21.0         18.6    22.2             .40         .88   .40   .90&#13;
1979  1       44.0        25         20.5      19.0         18.5      20.7         21.0         18.6    26.0             .42         .88   .42   .90&#13;
2       42.1         25        20.5      19           18.5      20.9         21.0         18.6    26.8    16.5     .44         .88   .44   .89&#13;
3       40.7        25         20.5      19.          18.5      21.8         24.3         18.6    26.9             .45         .76   .46   .85&#13;
4       42.7         25        20.5      19.          18.5      24.5         25.0         18.6    27.1             .43         .74   .44   .76&#13;
1980  1       50.8         29.4      2S.7      24.3         23.7      25.1         28.9         23.3    30.5             .47         .82   .46   .93&#13;
2       48.8         29.7      26.5      24.7         24.5      29.2         28.2         24.0    31.9    17.92    .50         .87   .49   .82&#13;
3       42.3        29.0       25.4      23.7         23.4      28.7         25.2        22.9     29.7             .55         .93   .54   .80&#13;
4       37.7         27.8      22.7      20.8         20.7      24.1         24.7         21.4    28.1             .55         .84   .56   .89&#13;
1981  1       36.6         27.0      21.5      20.0         19.5      23.1         23.1         19.5    24.9            -.53         .84   .53   .84&#13;
2       35.2         27.       20.9      20.          19.5      21.7         22.1         19.5    27.7    17.03    .55         .88   .55   .89&#13;
3       34.7        27.        20.5      20.          19.5      21.6         21.6        19.5     22.9             .56         .90   .56   .90&#13;
4       33.6         26.4      19.6      18.1         18.6      21.6         21.6         19.0    27.0             .55         .86   .56   .88&#13;
1982  1       32.6         24.1      15.8      16.1         15.7      18.7         19.1         15.1    21.7             .48         .84   .42   .81&#13;
2       31.1         22.0      14.0      16.0         13.5      13.9         16.4         12.5    17.4    10.04    .43         .82   .40   .90&#13;
3       27.7         18.0      10.0      14.0         10.0      11.0         12.0         8.0     14.3             .36         .83   .29   .73&#13;
4       29.0         18.0      10.0      14.          10.       11.0         12.0         8.0     15.7             .34         .83   .27   .73&#13;
1983  1       20.3 (22.4) 18.        10.       14.          10.       11.0         12.0         8.0     14.8             .49 (.45)   .83   .39   .73&#13;
2       21.7 (23.2) 18.        10.       14.          10.       11.0         12.0         8.0     14.0             .46 (.43)   .83   .37   .76&#13;
3                                                               10.5         12.0         8.0     14.0&#13;
1/ Figures in brackets represent alternative UPM data.&#13;
UPN: Unorganized Financial Markets&#13;
Source: Bank of Korea&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
W-*i *3@. 5 oX .iw. t zs.*o ggg uwuL t ow 1W&#13;
201 Sim *J @2 eS JP 1 J_ *g*.fl IJOL s Si 4&#13;
gO*Z £L II 0 eX   f     a  *z.o '   N  J   if /&#13;
109-1 '2S*J  3 qS,WS *J SA C 10%11 *as"  e s2 t /#&#13;
ml 12          001         0-01            0-01                            10 (0 1I)0091                      (0-11)0-01&#13;
01 It (I U)O-Ise&#13;
1551SI 6 *zqt  S9l- S-CI   11- S-CI        S-CI                            -5l *                    1o;Sl) sn  (S-l)OtS&#13;
itni 9i *-r   s19- 'sL    0o91- 01o       .o 1                             o                        (s l)o.t   ly o1)1 LIV&#13;
Cojt)o 956  (031)OLt6s&#13;
Il 51 *"0     SUI- -a     09i- O-l        Otl                             0-S                     LS,I);;W    (SIMll91V&#13;
(O tl)09t3  (001)0511&#13;
Ski 4lo *-6   1C1- S-l     091- ° s1      0-5                             0o1                       (0t-)Liv   (s113o1n&#13;
(015)0g110  (01z)@ U0&#13;
Inl*     5     0S 1'" I- 5*lt  Otl- 091   09t1                            011                      o    nn    o o nnn,&#13;
o CIe      (s 4)ouu&#13;
t0ti *It -    S-SI- 5-01  o0t£- 091       ot                              O t            "IT        lilY      (0t 1)l &#13;
0313      rimgs      (1ZZ)1W1Z6&#13;
o*Z       00(6 o0 11 0   )0 t&#13;
oatl *o1 *tts  Sl- 0-OI    O-tl- oml      0o91      r,sO.T      0-01       0-010          sani     %s-n        (o nas CZY&#13;
ol 111    o an       (8 {MO 919&#13;
coa *1 *It tt     - o rou   051- OUtI       omi      iO-lt       ol         0O-            S     In"  sn        ( tz)s clv&#13;
olun      oun(       (O Lth)nn&#13;
0|*  1.        .t0-t      o*1 or        le- is l    i-1        o 1z       ooi 1          -n        s-ln      (1191HStz&#13;
OUS1 t 1r                                 gwul- *Z O*t 6   0L1  tz         Cri 1:         5111      ll*Iz      (9,11%zqv&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~*" .2O           *s11J      b;pn9 llt}"tuqds&#13;
e~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~                       si       0,° * &#13;
6161 It _30                               ,f0zz      0tT        0-11       0-wG           s-snl     s-n         s    s&#13;
o9(             (0io  1 )osza&#13;
oqsi *;1 *urn                            jo z        o*w        oi: lo n                 snn(o-1)wn&#13;
o *Ist    0'51        W0(iz0o1T&#13;
SAS1 It )s twotr                                      0191       o1        OSl            I I       SltY       (0zz)Log&#13;
oIt        ( (1) mISl&#13;
Sil'1It LOt0                                          UC        USI        0-0SI         e-it onZ)LO(v&#13;
0-511      (Sftu)OIta&#13;
Im I1t Ar                                 to9        0oo                   o il          omi        on61      (ou)O'l0&#13;
0*11  091i                                    (S3ln)0-&#13;
Lit  9 *i"O                                Ott       nfl        o-slYo                   O-Il       0-sn       (LUs-oWo-&#13;
O-Ltl      (IS-lO-UI,&#13;
US, 'I iar                                 o 11       o9 i       -         ONt           OSIt       o, nn ZV )al q&#13;
LIaa)w     *siacki  SOD)n0I oat   1XiISUi1 P   dUM"&#13;
-I SA)i*jJ                               £ I U    *dt joih   ISIiS t* Ssl _ 59'        iSIiStt   iUinttUlSSl   S1ISJ?J SO"&#13;
thSS t 154i@15151&#13;
13551 IU IItOUe ID SAIDWS tt Ilivi i3tl3m UO  (I)ZV alqe.L&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A2 (II):         MAJOR INTEREST RATES ON LOANS AND DISCOUNTS OF DEPOSIT NONEY BANKS&#13;
In Per Cent Per Annum&#13;
Snmll and Nedoim Industry&#13;
B a a k I   n a r u n d                 G o v e r na  e n t F u n d              F o r e    n   L o a n F u n d&#13;
Nedim          Equipment      Cooperative                  Cooperativem&#13;
Effective From      Industries      of Nedium        Business     Equipment       Businese      Operation        AID            XPW           PAC&#13;
1977.  7.  1       A 16.0         16.0 - 17.0         16.0          13.5           13.5            17.0           8.0           9.0           8.0&#13;
s 17.0&#13;
10.  4       A 15.0         15.0   16.0         15.0          13.5           13.0            14.0           8.0           9.0           8.0&#13;
B 16.0&#13;
1978. 6. 13        A 18.5         18.5 - 19.5         18.5          13.5           13.0            14.0           8.0            9.0          8.0&#13;
a 19.0&#13;
1980.  1. 12       A 24.5         24.5 - 25.0         24.5          19.5           19.0            20.0           8.0            9.0          8.0&#13;
5 25.0&#13;
1980. 6.   5       A 23.5         23.5 - 25.0         23.5          21.0           21.0            21.0           8.0            9.0          8.0&#13;
B 24.0&#13;
9. 16       A 21.5         21.5 - 23.0         21.5          20.0           20.0            20.0           8.0            9.0           8.0&#13;
5 22.0&#13;
11.  8       A 19.5         19.5 - 21.0         19.5          18.5           18.5            18.5           8.0            9.0           8.0&#13;
B 20.0&#13;
1981. 11.  9       A 18.5         18.5 - 20.0       -               17.5           17.5            17.5           8.0            9.0          '8.0&#13;
819.0&#13;
11. 30       A 17.5         17.5 - 19.0       -               17.5           17.5            17.5           8.0            9.0           8.0&#13;
B 18.0&#13;
12. 29       A 16.5         16.5- 18.0        -               16.5           16.5            16.5           8.0            9.0           8.0&#13;
B 17.0&#13;
1982.  1. 14       A 15.5         15.5 - 17.0       -               16.5           16.5            16.5           8.0            9.0           8.0&#13;
B 16.0&#13;
3. 29       A 13.5         13.5 - 15.0       -               14.0           14.0            14.0           8.0            9.0           8.0&#13;
B 14.0&#13;
6. 28         10.0                10.0       -               10.0           10.0            10.0           8.0            9.0           8.0&#13;
Source: Economic Statietice Yearbook BOK&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 72 -&#13;
TABLE A3: INTEREST RATES OF DEPOSIT MONEY BANKS BY MATURITY (%)&#13;
A         B       C       D          E            F          G&#13;
&lt;1 Yr    1-3 Yrs   B/A   &gt;3 Yrs       D/A       Average    4 Quarter&#13;
-Date                                                             D/A for    Average of F&#13;
Quarter&#13;
1974    12.7      15.5      15.5     1      15.5        1&#13;
1975                                                              1.000&#13;
4.17     15.0     15.5     1.033   15.5                  1.027&#13;
1.033      1.015&#13;
10.1      15.5     15.5     1       15.5       1          1.000&#13;
1976                                                                1&#13;
8.2      17.0      17      1        18       1.059       1.039      1.025&#13;
1.059&#13;
1977                                                               1.059&#13;
1.059      1.052&#13;
7.1     16.0       16      1        17       1.063       1.063&#13;
10.4      15.0      15      1        16       1.067       1.067&#13;
1.067&#13;
1978     6.13     18.5     18.5             19.5       1.054      1.064      1.060&#13;
12.7      18.5     18.5             19.5      1.054       1.054&#13;
1.054&#13;
1979      1.12    18.5      18.5            19.5       1.054      1.054&#13;
1.054      1.054&#13;
1.054&#13;
1980     1.42     24.5     24.5             25.5       1.041      1.042&#13;
6.5&#13;
8.1      23.5     23.5      1      25.5      1.043       1.042&#13;
9.16    21.5      21.5     1       22.5      1.047       1.044     1.045&#13;
11.8     19.5      29.5     1       20.5      1.051       1.051&#13;
1981     4.4      19.5      19.5     1'     20.5       1.051      1.051&#13;
11.9      18.5     18.5      1      19.5      1.054       1.051&#13;
11.30     17.5     17.5      1      18.5      1.057       1.051      1.052&#13;
12.29     16.5     16.5      1      17.5      1.061       1.054&#13;
1982     1.44     15.5     15.5      1      16.5       1.065      1.065&#13;
3.29    13.5      13.5     1       14.5      1.074       1.072     1.034&#13;
6.28      10       10      1        10        1           1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 73 -&#13;
TABLE A4:    COMMERCIAL BANK CREDITS BY MATURITY&#13;
(X)&#13;
Total&#13;
(amount in&#13;
Up to 1 year     1-3 years        over 3 years    billion won)&#13;
City Banks&#13;
1975         70.9               14.5            14.6            100.0&#13;
(1,378)&#13;
1976         75.1               11.3            13.6            100.0&#13;
(1,851)&#13;
1977         67.9               17.2            14.9           100.00&#13;
(2,356)&#13;
1978         64.7               21.8            13.5            100.0&#13;
(3,386)&#13;
1979         66.8               21.1            12.1            100.0&#13;
(4,596)&#13;
1980         69.4               20.5            10.1            100.0&#13;
(5,908)&#13;
1981         68.0               18.7            13.3            100.0&#13;
(7,720)&#13;
1982         69.9               14.3            15.8         (9400.8)&#13;
Local Banks&#13;
1975         88.8                6.7             4.5            100.0&#13;
(267)&#13;
1976         82.8               12.3             4.9            100.0&#13;
(349)&#13;
1977         81.8               11.4             6.8            100.0&#13;
(439) -&#13;
1978         73.2               18.5             8.3            100.0&#13;
(593)&#13;
1979         70.2               21.8             8.0            100.0&#13;
(744)&#13;
1980         63.9               29.9             6.2            100.0&#13;
(952)&#13;
1981         64.6               28.5             6.9            100.0&#13;
(1,295)&#13;
1982&#13;
Note:   Figures for 1975, 1976 relate to end September; for 1977-81 relate to&#13;
end December.&#13;
Source: BOK.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE      A5:         R E D I S C O U N T   R     A T I O  O F  B   A N K   OF  K O R E A&#13;
During Quarter&#13;
01/06/79   01/12/79   June-Sept. 79    07/03/80     1981    02/19/81±1   06/03/81   07/08/81   05/20/82   06/10/82   02/24/83   06/08/83&#13;
Comrcial Bills&#13;
Smel medius Induatry         Y                          2I                     70                     60         70          80       80                     80&#13;
Heavy Industry                                                         ?/      70                     60         60          60       60                     60&#13;
Export                        70           80&#13;
Others                              From 70t to SOZ                            60                     50         40          60       40                     40&#13;
Loans&#13;
Finance of Export Support                                                      100 (7)                                                80         80          70&#13;
Fund for Knergy                                                                100                                                   100         80          70&#13;
Conservation Facility                                                         80&#13;
Defense Industry                                                                                                                      80         70&#13;
Fishery Sector                                                                 50-60                                                  60         50&#13;
Small &amp; Medium Enterprises                                                                                                            30(7)      30          20&#13;
(+ 50 of excess&#13;
over 35S)&#13;
0 BOK set guidelines for special financial support to SKI     amount to be supplied during the year - 300 Billions Won&#13;
of which 30 Billion Won low-interest loans; 30 Billion Won special fostering funds; 240 Billion Won general loans.&#13;
(Medium Industry bank exclusively handles special low-interest loans and special fostering loans). (Citizens&#13;
National Bank, Five Nation-Wide City Bank and ten local bank can offer general loans). More than 302 of loans may&#13;
be lent on credit or on guarantee by the Korea Credit Guarantee Fund.&#13;
]/ Rediscount ceiling on comercial bills received by small and medium industry raised from 0.3 to 0.4 Billions for&#13;
prim enterprises and from 0.2 to 0.3 billions for enterprises vtth ordinary rating.&#13;
]/ Increases of the rediscount ceiling on commercial bills received by eligible heavy and chemical enterprises from&#13;
1.5 Billions Won to 2 Billions for prim enterprises; from 1.0 Billion to 1.5 Billions for ordinary enterprises.&#13;
r/ lonetsry Board abolished old regulation on handlitng discount and sales of commercial bills. BOK automatic&#13;
rediscount system abolished. Rediscount ceilLng were set for each banking Institution.&#13;
Source: BOK&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE A6: PRIVATE CORPORATIONS: STRUCTURE OF FINANCIAL ASSETS (A) &amp; LIABILITIES (L) (%)&#13;
1982            1981            1980           1978           1975&#13;
A      L       A       L       A      L       A      L       A     L&#13;
Money                8.2     -      6.7     -      7.5     -       9.1     -      9.4    -&#13;
Deposits T &amp; s      7.5     -      12.1     -     15.6     -      19.0    -      20.7    -&#13;
Interest &amp; Finance  3.7     -       2.9     -      2.9     -      3.1     -       1.4    -&#13;
Ind. Papers         4.5    10.1     3.4    9.3      -      -       -      -        -     -&#13;
Securities          9.4    37.3     8.3   37.0     9.5   40.1     9.6    36.9     9.1  36.1&#13;
Debentures         1.6   13.5     1.5   12.0     1.4   11.6     0.8     6.2     0.5   1.7&#13;
Stocks            5.2    24.1     4.6   25.0     5.8   28.5     5.7    30.7     7.7  34.4&#13;
Loans&#13;
Trade Credit       39.7    18.3    37.9   19.7    33.1   18.1    23.1    15.7    21.3  18.9&#13;
Bank                 -     52.4      -    53.5      -    53.8      -     52.0      -   58.9&#13;
Investment &amp;&#13;
Finance Cos.       -      6.6      -     6.3      -     5.7      -      6.4      -    5.3&#13;
Others               -     24.7      -    23.3      -    22.8      -     17.7      -   13.9&#13;
Source:  Flow of Funds Tables, Economic Statistics Yearbooks (various issues).&#13;
Note  : The assets/liabilities listed on the left are not exhaustive, so that&#13;
numbers in each column do not add up to 100%.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 76 -&#13;
TABLE A7: INDIVIDUAL PORTFOLIO COMPOSITION (%)&#13;
1982            1981           1980            1978           1975&#13;
Assets&#13;
Money              9.5            9.2            12.7           16.9            19.9&#13;
Deposits&#13;
Time &amp; Savings    41.7           39.8            38.9           37.3            35.9&#13;
Investment &amp;&#13;
Finance Cos.      1.7            2.2             2.8            3.6             3.4&#13;
Insurance          7.0            5.9             5.4            4.0             3.7&#13;
Trust              3.95           4.3             4.4            3.0             3.6&#13;
Ind. Papers        4.1            5.1              -&#13;
Securities        30.4           31.6            32.1           31.3            29.4&#13;
Debentures       3.2            3.3             3.3            1.7             1.1&#13;
Stocks          15.94          18.0            21.0           24.1            24.8&#13;
Beneficiaries      7.8            5.2             3.4            1.9             0.3&#13;
Other Loans        0.7            0.8             1.3            2.4             2.3&#13;
Liabilities&#13;
Bank Loans        25.7           24.3            25.9           24.4            28.8&#13;
Other Loans        9.1            9.0             8.1            5.6             4.7&#13;
Trade Credits     17.4           15.9            13.2            5.7             2.0&#13;
Equities                                            0.5            0.5             0.6&#13;
Other than Stock&#13;
Source: Flow of Funds tables from Economic Statistics Yearbooks.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE As PRWPORTION OF INSTITUTION'S ASSETS TO TOTAL ASSETS OF FIANIAL INSTITUTIONS 1X&#13;
COURCIAL BANKS       SPECIALIZED BANKS     DEVELOPMENT INSlITUTIONS    SAVING INSTIIUTIONS    INVESTMENT INSTITUTIONS   LIFE INSURANCE CONPANIES&#13;
1972                                      42.3                  35.1&#13;
1973                                      45.6                  37.6&#13;
1974                                      47.6                  30.0&#13;
1975                                      49.4                  26.3                        13.1                     5.7                        4.3                       1.6&#13;
1976                                      45.5                  25.5                         13.3                    6.2                        5.1                       1.5&#13;
1977                                      42.7                  27.0                         13.2                    6.7                        5.9                        1.7&#13;
1978                                     6q.1                   26.8                         12.9                    6.9                        7.3                        1.9&#13;
1979                                      42.6                  27.2                         13.8                    7.0                        7.5                        2.5&#13;
1980                                      40.0                  27.9                         13.6                    9.2                        7.9                        2.6&#13;
1981                                      38.7                  26.7                         14.6                    8.1                        8.9                        2.8&#13;
1m                                        37.1                  27.0                         13.8                    8.1                       10.6                        3.3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE A9: FINANCIAL SYSTeN: SoUBRCS OF FINANCE (Billion Won)&#13;
1982       S of      1981   2 of     1980     % of     1979      S of      1978    l of     1977     S of     1976      S of       1975      l of      1974    S of&#13;
Tot a 1-2Y       Tota1-/           Total               Total             Total            Total               Total-/             Total-            Total&#13;
A - Loans a Credits               69.8             70.7              72.3               71.6              69.4              70.4                72.1                                  73.9&#13;
(70.6)2k         (71.4)            (73.6)                                (70.6)                                (73.2)&#13;
rtant Loans         23,93R.9    43.8   19,003.5  44.2   14,462.9   46.7 10,818.7      48.4   7,678.7     50.3  5,265.4    49.1     4,249       53.0  3,338.524    (55.6)   2,619    55.01&#13;
Insurance Loans-     1,409.4     2.6     890.5    2.1     603.0     2.0    407.0       I.R     179.4      1.1   105.7      0.9     0,051                40.250            0,148      3.1&#13;
Investment &amp; Finance&#13;
Coupany Loans      1,813.4     3.3    1,467.4   3.4      997.3    3.2    901.5       4.0     637.9      4.2   393.5      3.7     0.303        4.0     192.693   ( 3.2)     -&#13;
Other Loans (includes&#13;
Dew. Banks)       11,195.8    20.5    8,650.1  20.1    6,294.3   20.3 4,183.2        18.7  2,901.6     19.0  1,969.0    18.4     1,326       16.0   1,007.632   (16.8)   0,919    19.4&#13;
Covernment Loans     4,721.1     8.7    3,741.1   8.7   :2,604.5    8.4  2,016.4       9.0   1,433.7      9.4   961.5      9.0     0,712               502.662    ( 8.4)   0,431     9.1&#13;
Trade Credits         11,505.6    21.1   9.273.0   21.6   5.999.8    19.4  4.028.9      18.0   2.441.3     16.0  2,020.4    18.9     1,397       17.0    918.487    (15.3)  0.643     14.0&#13;
Sub-Total         54,586.8    100    43,025.6  100    22,355.7   300  15,272.8       100    8,038      100 10,715.5     100      8,038      100.0   6,000.248  (100.0)   4,735    100.0&#13;
a - Securitles        20,967.3    26.8   15,778.3  25.9   11,846.4   27.7  8,853.6      28.4   6,724.7     30.6  4,504.3    29.6     3,103.5     27.9&#13;
mon Flnancial       20,195.7   (26.1&gt;3/15,179.9 (25.2)  11,093.4  (26.4)                     6,355.5    (29.4)                     2,942.6    (26.8)&#13;
C - Industrtal Papers  2,644.5     3.4   2,030.3    4.4&#13;
D - Totol (A + 1 + C)             200              100               100                100                100              100                  100&#13;
00&#13;
A S Rank Loans            25.97             31.34            33.56            41.02               80.7                                  62.24                                             1&#13;
A S Interest &amp; Finance    8.76              67.19             10.63           41.32              110.53&#13;
Company&#13;
A S Other Loans           29.43             37.38            50.51            44.17              118.8                                  44.29&#13;
A S Trade Credit          24.08             54.56            48.92            51.39               20.50                                117.26&#13;
I/   Insurance loans + trust loans.&#13;
2/   For different types of loans, 'total  refers to total loans and credits or the&#13;
tow titled 'sub-total'. For different methods of ftntncing (loans, securities,&#13;
Industrial Papers), 'total" refers to total of these.&#13;
For 2 In brackets only mn-financial securities are constdered.&#13;
Sources: Yearly Statistical Pook - 801&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
rABLE AlO: FINANCIAL INTERMEDIATION: ASSET PROPORTIONS (Z)&#13;
Commercial  Special   Comercial    Life    Development    Savings      Investment          Financial&#13;
Date    Banks      Banks    + Special  Insurance  Institutions  Institutions  Institutions Total Institutions&#13;
'Total Assets&#13;
1982    37.1       27.0        64.1       3.3       13.8           8.1         10.6       99.9      38.30&#13;
1981    38.7       26.7        65.4       2.8       14.6          8.1           8.9      99.8       37.64&#13;
1980    40.0       27.9        67.9      2.6        13.6          8.2           7.8     100.0       37.4&#13;
1979    42.6       27.2        69.8      2.5        13.8          7.0           7.5     100.6       36.77&#13;
1978    42.1       26.8        68.9       1.8       12.9          6.9           7.3      97.8       37.07&#13;
1977    42.7       27.0        69.7      1.7        13.2          6.6           5.9      97.2       35.46&#13;
1976    45.5       25.5        71.0      1.5        13.3          6.2           5.1      97.1       34.00&#13;
1975    49.4       26.3        75.7      1.6        13.1          5.7           4.3      100.4      33.83&#13;
1974    47.6       30.0        77.6                                                                 36.37&#13;
1973    45.6       37.7        83.3                                                                 34.85&#13;
1972    42.3       35.1        77.4                                                                 34.14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE All: Distribution of Securities Trade Credit and Commercial Paper by Holders (%)&#13;
FINANCIAL ASSETS AND LIABILITIES OUTSTANDING AT END OF YEAR 1982&#13;
Commercial      Specialized    Other Financial           Private        Govt. Invest.&#13;
Banks            Banks         Institution           Corporations      Corporation        Individual      T 0 T A L&#13;
A    L          A    L          A     L                 A    L            A     L          A    L          A      L&#13;
Securities           11      3       8       1       23      19              12     46         1       8        45      -      100      77&#13;
Govt. Bonds        28      -      21      -        21       -              9       -       0.1      -         15      -    94.1       -&#13;
Debentures          9      -       3      -        57 il    -              9      75         -      25        22      -     100      100&#13;
Stocks              3      8       2    0.5         9       7             17      77         3      7         63      -      97    99.5&#13;
Trade Credit          -      -       -      -         -       -              90     42         7       4         -     49      97       95&#13;
Industrial papers     -      -       -      -         5       -             45     100       0.2      -         49      -      99      100&#13;
(C.P.)           -       -       -      -         2       -             13     100         1      -         84      -     100     100&#13;
0-&#13;
FINANCIAL ASSETS &amp; LIABILITIES OUTSTANDING AT END OF 1981&#13;
2&#13;
Securities           11      3      10       1       20      13             11      50         2      10        46      -     100       77&#13;
Govt. Bonds        26      -      17      -        16       -              8       -         I      -         27      -      95       -&#13;
Debentures          6      -       2      -        55       -              11     89         -      11        26      -     100      100&#13;
Stocks              3      7       2    0.4         9       5             13      72         3      16        57      -      87     100&#13;
Trade Credit         -       -       -      -         -       -             89      46         9       6         -     41      98      93&#13;
Industrial papers    -       -       -      -         4       -             36     100       0.3      -         60      -    96.3     100&#13;
(C.P)              -       -       -      -       0.1       -             17     100         -      -         83      -     100     100&#13;
FINANCIAL ASSETS AND LIABILITIES OUTSTANDING AT END 1978&#13;
Securities            7      4      11      -         -      10              13     52         2      14        45      -      78       80&#13;
Govt. Bonds         5      1      28      -        15       -              11      -         -      -         11      -      70        1&#13;
Debentures          7      -       2      -        53       -              13     95       0.0       5        25      -      100     100&#13;
Stocks              5      6     0.4    0.1         9       3              13     70         3     21         55      -    85.6      100&#13;
Trade Credit          -      -       -      -         -       -              89     61         8       7         -     23      97       91&#13;
1/   Mainly Investment Institutions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 81 -&#13;
TABLE A.12: COMMERCIAL BANKS: GuaraLtee on Bonds&#13;
A                      B                          C&#13;
Loans from                Bond                      B/(A+B)&#13;
Banking Funds             Guarantees&#13;
1973               987.1                  .30                          .03&#13;
1974             1,534.1                 5,37                         0.35&#13;
1975             1,847.2                22.47                         1.20&#13;
1976             2,332.3                91.88                         3.79&#13;
1977             2,867.1               205.82                         6.70&#13;
1978             4,050.8               374.42                         8.46&#13;
1979             5,401.8               664.49                        10.95&#13;
1980             7,209.8              1,234.1                        14.62&#13;
1981             9,544.4             1,595.65                        14.32&#13;
1982            11,800.6             1,987.84                        14.42&#13;
1983-9          13,062.8             2,613.60                        16.67&#13;
Source: Monthly Review, Securities Supervisory Board&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 82 -&#13;
TABLE A13: SIZE OF INDUSTRIAL PAPER MARKET (BI-WON, 5)&#13;
Industrial Papers           Industrial Papers (%)     Industrial Papers (%&#13;
Flow          Stock           Loans &amp; Credits             Securities&#13;
(Total)&#13;
1974                       43.3                                        2.6&#13;
1975        40.4           83.7                1.4                    4.0&#13;
1976         56.1         139.8                 1.7                    4.5&#13;
1977         95.5         235.3                2.2                     5.2&#13;
1978         65.7         301.0                2.0                     4.5&#13;
1979       209.4          510.4                2.3                     5.8&#13;
1980        576.2       1,086.6                3.5                     9.2&#13;
1981        943.7       2,030.3                4.7                    12.9&#13;
1982        614.1       2,644.5                4.8                    12.6&#13;
Source: Economic Statistics Yearbooks&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 83 -&#13;
TABLE A14: INVESTMENT AND FINANCE COMPANIES (BI-WON)&#13;
Assets &amp;             Resold Bills           Presold Bills&#13;
Liabilitiesl/                                    Assets&#13;
1975              220.9                  73.8                 .334&#13;
1976               345.6                137.5                 .398&#13;
1977              471.5                 226.7                 .484&#13;
1978               685.3                280.4                 .409&#13;
1979               931.2                479.6                 .515&#13;
1980             1,214.4              1,025.9                 .845&#13;
1981            1,610.5               1,972.0                1.225&#13;
1982            2,150.2               2,327.5                1.083&#13;
1983-9          2,824.5               2,973.0                1.053&#13;
1/   Does not include Resold Bills.&#13;
Source: BOK Monthly Statistical Bulletin,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE  A15:    AMOUNTS AND RATIOS OF DIFFERENT TYPES OF BONDS OUTSTANDING&#13;
(in billion Won or %)&#13;
A               B             C             D            E               F           G&#13;
Gov't.&amp;          Gov't.      Corporate    Guaranteed   Non-Guaranteed      C/A         D/C&#13;
Corporate          Bonds         Bonds       Corporate       Bonds&#13;
Bonds                                       Bonds&#13;
1972                                                      3.60            6.33                    36.26&#13;
1973                                                      5.30            8.08                    39.62&#13;
1974                                                     15.87           15.75                    50.19&#13;
1975        121.52          60.22           61.32        38.12           23.20         50.5       62.17&#13;
1976       268.19          139.96          128.23       117.53           10.70         47.8       91.78&#13;
1977       419.88          133.82          286.06       285.51             .55         68.1       99.81&#13;
1978       848.21          257.81          590.40       562.90           27.50         69.6       95.34&#13;
1979       1393.87         283.72         1109.95     1,051.45           58.50         79.6       94.73&#13;
1980      2196.04          356.87         1839.17      1838.67              50         83.8       99.97&#13;
1981      3109.20          532.93         2576.28     2,512.48           53.80         82.9       97.52&#13;
1982      4126.55          714.80         3411.75     3,321.95           89.80         97.0       97.40&#13;
1983-9    5127.17          693.42         4433.75     4,395.75           38.00         86.5       99.14&#13;
Rate of&#13;
Growth    65.5            42.4             77.6          89&#13;
1975-82&#13;
(compound)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE A 16: ANNUALISED YIELDS ON DIFFERENT TYPE OF BONDS&#13;
A          B              C              D&#13;
Government Bonds         Public        Corporate&#13;
Grain     Housing      Industrial&#13;
Finance                        A/D          B/D          C/D&#13;
1975       -       21.4            21.1           20.1         -            1.06         1.05&#13;
1976       -       22.4            21.4           20.4         -            1.09         1.04&#13;
1977    18.2       22.6            21.0           20.1       0.91           1.12         1.04&#13;
1978    20.1       22.9            22.6           21.1       0.95           1.09         1.07&#13;
1979    24.3       26.7            25.7           26.7       0.91          1.00          0.96&#13;
1980    27.7       30.1            28.3           30.1       0.92           1.00         0.94           1&#13;
1981    21.1       23.6            24.6           24.4       0.86           0.97         1.01           X&#13;
1982    16.5       17.2            17.7           16.8       0.98           1.02         1.05&#13;
1983       -        13.0           15.2           14.2          -            .92         1.07&#13;
2/&#13;
Mean -  21.3        23.4           22.8           22.5&#13;
Std.     4.10       3.78           3.30            4.30&#13;
Cov.  19.24%      26.19%         14.46%           19.14&#13;
Corr.                .97            .99            1.0&#13;
Std.  =  Standard Deviation&#13;
I                                                 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~Cov.  =  Coefficient of Variation&#13;
I   1983 data are for first nine months only.                        Corr. =  Correlation Co-efficient&#13;
2/ Column A statistics are for 1977-82 rest are for 1975-82.&#13;
Source - BOK Monthly Statistical Bulletin&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A17:      COMPPOSITION OF THE SECONDARY AND TERTIARY MARKET&#13;
(Unit million won)&#13;
Year&#13;
or                                    Value of                            Value of Repo&#13;
Month                                 Stock Sales                       Sales and Repurchase&#13;
1978                                   1,741,506                                238,682&#13;
1979                                   1,327,813                                523,270&#13;
1980                                   1,134,019                                889,876&#13;
1981                                   2,534,160                             1,410,523&#13;
1982                                   1,973,469                             6,247,548&#13;
1983.6                                 1,072,527                             2,119,800&#13;
Source: Korea Stock Exchange.&#13;
Table A 18:  BOND TRADING UNDER REPURCHASE OR REVERSE REPURCHASE AGREEKENTS&#13;
(In mll. won)    0&#13;
11. Repo&#13;
8. Secondary                      utsndtng&#13;
Year       Under Reverse     3. Outstanding     Under Repurchase    6. Outstanding                Harket    9. Tertiary           Listed&#13;
or     Repurchase Agreement    at Year or          8eeeent           at Year or    7. Total     Activity    Activity   10. D&#13;
onth     1. Purchase 2. Sales   Month End    4. Sales 5. Repurchase   Month End    Outstanding    (1+4)        (2+5)    Balance  ofCiBnda&#13;
1977         15,418       13,5      li18         500           -          500          2,318       15,918       13,500    15,283    0.68S&#13;
1978        201,759    178,848      24,729        861         990          372         25,1U1      302.620      382,458    22,911    5.84X&#13;
1979        324,906    337,079      12,556      1,021       1,392            -         12,566      325,927      664,398   -12,173    2.331&#13;
1980        284,758    278,402      18,912        500         500            -         18,912      285,258      564,160     6,358    2.112&#13;
1981        313,365    306,981      25,295      5,105       5,105            -         25,295      318.470      630,556     6,384    1.653&#13;
1982 Jan.    34,812    46,347       13,760          -           -&#13;
Feb.    36,099     30,281      19,577          -&#13;
Mar.    54,787     62,546      11.818          -           -            -&#13;
Apr.    56,867     40,571      28,114          -           -            -&#13;
may     26,751     46,129       8,736          -           -            -&#13;
June    32,618     19,995      21,358          -&#13;
1982 1-6    241,934   245,869      21,358           -           -            -         21,358      241,934            -         -    -&#13;
Source:  Introduction to the Korean Securities Market, 1982.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A19:    BOND TRADING UNDER REPURCHASE AGREEMENTS&#13;
Repo Transactions&#13;
Unit: Mil. Won&#13;
Repo Sales                  Repo Purchase                                             Repo Outstanding&#13;
Secondary                  Bonds&#13;
Total      Market    Tertiary      Outstanding&#13;
Year &amp; Month     Sale     Repurchase  Balance   Purchase  Resale   Balance   Outstanding  Activity   Activity         (M)&#13;
1981    12                            185,592                       45,245      230,837                               7.42&#13;
1982     1       161,829    124,162   223,259    41,634    22,827   64,052            -     203,46D    146,989&#13;
2      160,393     116,147   267,505   62,065     34,181   91,936&#13;
3      236,270     190,704   313,071   87,840     70,416  109,360&#13;
4       190,690    161,685   342,076   83,433     66,650  126,143&#13;
5       190,049    172,041   360,084   59,786     72,495  113,434&#13;
6      240,838     177,826   423,096  100,755     70,990  143,199&#13;
7      216,369     172,890   466,575  103,181     98,174  148,206                                                    1&#13;
8      216,686     178,717   504,544   66,429     78,534  136,101                                                    X&#13;
9      253,338     260,821   497,061   72,917     93,226  115,792     612,853&#13;
10      211,834     242,621   466,274   67,797    89,769    93,820&#13;
11-     279,752     235,978   510,048   48,749     56,485   86,084&#13;
12      345,925                         33,795&#13;
1982          2,703,973   2,322,325   567,240  838,381    806,195   67,429     634,66.9   3,532,351  3,128,706       15.38&#13;
1983     1      327,772     250,638   647,072   87,556     89,408  115,559&#13;
2      334,477     256,038   725,511   75,919     96,780   94,697&#13;
3      359,045     320,444   764,112   49,544    105,737   38,504&#13;
4      32i,922     283,512   802,522   41,430-    36,711   43,223&#13;
5      362,812     312,865   852,469   84,402     73,291   54,334&#13;
6      343,705     330,551   865,623   84,465     86,998   51,801&#13;
7      253,608     217,365   901,866   75,991     76,575   51,217&#13;
8      272,533     227,151   947,248    79,417    86,209   44,425&#13;
9      303,724     272,320   978,652   76,648     81,295   39,778   1,018,430                               19.86&#13;
Rate of  81-12 to 82-12                 205.6%                       49.0%       174.9%&#13;
Growth   82-9 to 83-9                                                             63.9%&#13;
Source:  Monthly Review, Securities Supervisory Board, Korea.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A20:    NET PURCHASE AND SALE OF REPO BY INVESTOR&#13;
Unit: Mil. Won&#13;
Sold                                      Purchased&#13;
Other                 Balance   Listed     Securities  Other   Balance&#13;
K.S.F.C.   Bank    Corps.  Individuals  = Total   Companies    Firms     Corps.  = Total&#13;
End of&#13;
1982   1      5,844     668    25,134    191,613     223,259    62,994                1,058    64,052&#13;
2     13,222     668    29,910    223,705     267,505    90,378                1,558    91,936&#13;
3     11,841     569    35,009    265,651     313,071   107,914                1,446   109,360&#13;
4     28,342       -    26,425    287,310     342,076   124,093                2,050   126,143&#13;
5      8,591       -    29,204    322,288     360,084   111,961                1,473   113,434&#13;
6     16,752       -    31,609    374,736     423,096   140,726                2,473   143,199&#13;
7     31,820       -    34,164    400,591     466,575   142,753               5,453    148,206&#13;
8     42,283       -    37,525    424,735     504,544   131,678                4,423   136,101&#13;
9     47,247       -    37-,097   412,717     497,061   114,370                1,422   115,792&#13;
10     45,242      -     32,377    388,655     466,274    93,071                  749    93,820&#13;
11     51,944      -     69,753    388,351    510,048     85,133                 951     86,084&#13;
12&#13;
1982         49,981       -   118,665    398,594     567,240    67,033          -       396    67,429&#13;
1983   1     46,808       -   137,390    462,874     647,072    65,102     46,811     3,646   115,559&#13;
2     39,196       -   184,863    501,452     725,511    55,297     39,199       201    94,697&#13;
3      5,238       -   220,605    538,269     764,112    32,621      5,240       643    38,504&#13;
4     22,773       -   233,913    545,836     802,522    19,956     22,773       494    43,223&#13;
5     31,507       -   264,655    556,307     852,469    19,888     31,507    2,939     54,334&#13;
6     34,936       -   269,307    561,380     865,623    12,457     34,936    4,408     51,801&#13;
7     32,493       -   280,778    588,595     901,866    12,353     32,493    6,371     51,217&#13;
8     32,703       -   289,529    625,016     947,248     6,101     32,703     5,621    44,425&#13;
9     31,321       -   302,335    644,996     978,652     4,684     31,321     3,773    39,778&#13;
Note:  1)  Repo Sales of the banks are included from Oct. 1982.&#13;
2)  Repo Transactions of the K.S.F.C. are included from Jan. 1983.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE A21:       SECONDARY MARKET ACTIVITY:            STOCKS    (MI WON)&#13;
A                 B            C                D               8                    F           G                H             I&#13;
During            Sale Value of      Corporate      Trade in         Total          (A-B) x 100             C-D     f of old shares Av. hold of       G/H&#13;
Listed Stocks      Funds Raised    Exist        Market Value   Average Karket Value        A      Sold-FxSV       listed shares     (M)&#13;
1969              42,030.17          6,099          35,931.17         86,569.42        47.6               85.47         84.176     127,95 822        .07&#13;
1970              42,873.78          7,151          35,722.78         97,922.55       38.73               83.32         65.968    150,003 478        .04      1&#13;
1971              34,376.36          2,940          31,436.36        108,706.13       30.43               91.45         46.202    164,588.432        .03     Co&#13;
1972              71,050.05         14,813          56,237.05        245,980.70       31.71               74.15         67.032     189,983.38        .04&#13;
1973             160,642.18         51,098         109,544.18        426,246.66       32.59               68.19         88.694    295,646.000        .03      1&#13;
1974             179,427.74         46,417         133,010.74        532,826.81       27.74               74.13        116.646    396,328.129        .03&#13;
1975             333,906.16        122,806         211,102.16        916,054.11       29.14                63.2        196.334    656,293.007        .03&#13;
1976            628,677.62         175,946         452,731.62      1,436,074.01       38.50               72.01        426.158   1204,166.226        .04&#13;
1977          1,375,267.77         185,973       1,189,294.77      2,350,835.36       62.81               86.48       1099.577   1850,257.876        .06&#13;
1978          1,741,506.35         326,722       1,414,784.35      2,892,511.78       53.96               81.24       1111.726   2538,278.000        .04&#13;
1979          1,327,813.14         216,712       1,111,101.14      2,609,414.22       40.39               83.68       1305.933   3233,067.252        .04&#13;
1980          1,134,019.25         171,148         962,871.25      2,526,552.58        37.5               84.91       1397.020   3691,193.227        .04&#13;
1981          2,534,160.15         306,041       2,228,119.15      2,959,057.13       81.24               87.92       2703.255   3962,035.506        .07&#13;
1982          1,973,468.67         276,867       1,696,601.67      3,300,494.23       54.21               85.97       2469.413   4376,890.723        .06&#13;
1983!l       1,253,150.06         263.657         989,493.06      3,213,376.85           31&#13;
1/   1983  data is from January to August only.&#13;
Sources: Korea Exchange Stock&#13;
Introduction to the Korean Securities Market 1982 - KSE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 90 -&#13;
TABLE A22: RATES OF RETURN IN THE EQUITY MARKET (%)&#13;
p /Pt-1/          Yield       Rate of Return     Corporate&#13;
Bond Yields&#13;
1974&#13;
1975                                 15.0&#13;
1976                 1.16            14.0              30              20.4&#13;
1977                 1.32            14.4              46              20.1&#13;
1978                 1.06            19.8              26              21.1&#13;
1979                 0.82            15.7             -23              26.7&#13;
1980                 0.90            23.9             13.9             30.1&#13;
1981                10.97            24.5             21.5             24.4&#13;
1982                 0.95            16.3             11.3             16.8&#13;
1983&#13;
Mean                                                  22.8             20.9&#13;
Standard Deviation                                    15.376            4.527&#13;
Variance                                              67.4%            21.7&#13;
1/   Ratio of stock market index at end of period     t   to the index at end of&#13;
period t-1.&#13;
Source: Securities Statistics Year Book&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE A.23: DISTRIBUTION OF SHAREHOLDINGS&#13;
(A)  No. of Holders           (B)3Value.of Shares&#13;
No. of Holders                                       Shares in (Thou.)&#13;
Size of Holding     Dec. 1981     June 1982     Dec. 1982      June 1983    Dec. 1981     June 1982      Dec. 1982   June 1983&#13;
De. 19.       Jue18_2                                                                             ue1&#13;
Less than 100         169,775        156,683       158,875        147,219      6.536          5,968         5,948       5,378&#13;
(0.2)          (0.1)        (0.1)        (0.1)&#13;
100-999               277.476        276,356       276,641        237,290    114,371        113,732       115,366      93,197&#13;
(3.0)          (2.6)        (2.4)        (1.9)&#13;
1.000-9,999           196,215        193,272       191.367        192,570    635,087        599,899      649,247      705,619&#13;
(15.0)         (13.7)       (13.7)       (14.3)&#13;
10,000-99,999          48,252         49,318        50,281         49,126  1,306,701      1,352,042     1,376,152   1,226,037&#13;
(30.5)        (30.8)        (29.0)       (27.0)&#13;
100,000 &amp; sore          4,558         4,995          5,011         5,172   2,181,387      2,320,064    2,606,577    2,804,076&#13;
(51.3)         (52.8)       (54.8)       (56.7)&#13;
T 0 T A L          696,276        680,624       682,175        631,377   4,244,802     4,391,705     4,753,-290  4,944,307&#13;
(100.0)        (100.0)      (100.0)      (100.0)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 92 -&#13;
TABLE A24: OW.fERSHIP OF LISTED STOCKS BY TYPE OF HOLDERS&#13;
Type of Holders           Shares hold (In thou.)         Shares hold (in thou.)&#13;
Dec. 1981      June 1982       Dec. 1982      June 1983&#13;
Government &amp; State            86,710        86,765           35,636        16,876&#13;
Corporations                (1.8)         (2.0)            (0.8)        (0.3)&#13;
Banking Institutions         239,860       249,838          246,102      281,172&#13;
(5.7)         (5.7)            (5.2)        (5.7)&#13;
Securities Companies          95,612        112,952         167,183       150,111&#13;
(2.3)          (2.6)           (3.5)         (3.0)&#13;
Insurance Companies &amp;      1,001,563     1,048,152        1,293,451     1,402,450&#13;
Other Corporations         (23.8)         (23.9)          (27.!)        (28.4)&#13;
Individuals                2,737,902     2,804,212        2,914,027    2,996,245&#13;
(64.5)        (63.9)           (61.3)        (60.6)&#13;
Foreigners                    83,155        89,786           96,891        97,453&#13;
(1.9)         (1.9)            (2.0)         (2.0)&#13;
T O T A L            4,244,802     4,391,705           96,891       97,453&#13;
(100.0)       (100.0)          (100.0)       (100.0)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 93 -&#13;
Table A25: RATIO OF BOOK VALUE OF CAPITAL STOCK&#13;
TO REAL CAPITAL IN STEADY STATE&#13;
Gross Investment to Real Capital Stock (I/K)&#13;
.05        .1        .15        .2         .3&#13;
Depreciation         .10       .64        .75        .79       .82        .84&#13;
Rate                          (.08)      (.13)     (.19)      (.24)      (.36)&#13;
.12        .49       .62        .69        .73       .83&#13;
(+50%)      (.10)     (.16)      (.22)      (.27)     (.36)&#13;
.14        .39       .54        .61        .66       .72&#13;
(.13)      (.19)     (.25)      (.30)      (.42)&#13;
.16        .32       .47        .54        .60       .66&#13;
(+100%)      (.16)     (.21)      (.28)      (.33)     (.45)&#13;
Figures in parenthesis give the ratio of gross investment&#13;
to book value of capital stock.&#13;
TABLE A26: RATIO OF BOOK VALUE OF CAPITAL&#13;
STOCK TO ACTUAL CAPITAL&#13;
6           .05        .1        .15-       .2        .3&#13;
.07            .58        .70       .76        .79        .83&#13;
(.09)      (.14)     (.20)      (.25)      (.36)&#13;
.08            .54        .67       .4-        .77        .80&#13;
(.09)      (.15)     (.21)      (.26)      (.38)&#13;
.09            .51        .64       .70        .74        .78&#13;
(.10)      (.16)     (.21)      (.27)      (.38)&#13;
6 /6  '   1.4  or  a - 40%&#13;
Figures in parenthesis give the ratio of gross investment&#13;
to book value of capital stock.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE A27: DEPOSIT MONEY BANK'S BANKING FUND LANS (PERCENTAGE)&#13;
Equipment/             Term Loans/             Term Loans/                Medium Industry/&#13;
Total Loans             Total Loans             Total Loans            Total Loan with Banking&#13;
end of          with Banking Funds      wtth Banking Funds      vith Banking Funds           Funds + Loan with&#13;
+ Loans with NIF                   NIF&#13;
1972                  10                       3                         3                    1962     6&#13;
1973                  14                       2                        2                     1963     5&#13;
1974                  12                       1                         1                    1964     5&#13;
1975                  13                       1                        1                     1965     4&#13;
1976                  13                       1                         1                    1966     5&#13;
1977                  13                       2                        2                     1967     5&#13;
1978                  14                       3                        2                     1968     3&#13;
1979                  15                       3                        3                     1969     2&#13;
1980                  14                       4                         3                    1970     2&#13;
1981                  14                       4                         4                    1971     3&#13;
1982                  15                       4                         4                    1972     4&#13;
1983-9                15                       4                        4                     1973     3&#13;
1974     3&#13;
1975     3&#13;
General Funds/          Export/Total Loans                                        1976      3&#13;
Total Loans            with Banking Funds                                        1977      4&#13;
+ Loans with NIF                                         1978      4&#13;
1979     4&#13;
1972                  31                      10                                              1980     5&#13;
1973                  29                      15                                              1981     6&#13;
1974                  32                      16                                              1982     6&#13;
1975                  31                      12                                              1983-9   6&#13;
1976                  27                      13&#13;
1977                  31                      13&#13;
1978                  32                      14&#13;
1979                  28                      14&#13;
1980                  30                      15&#13;
1981                  29                      14&#13;
1982                  31                      12&#13;
1983-9                29                      12&#13;
Sources:  Nonthly Statistical Bulletin - BOK&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A28: DIRECTED LOANS OF DMBs&#13;
(in billion won, X)&#13;
1978                  1979                 1980                 1981&#13;
Amount    %           Amount    2          Amount    X          Amount     2&#13;
1. Banking Funds&#13;
A. Total loans                     6,019.1 100.0         8,267.7 100.0       11,295.2 100.0       15,350.6  100.0&#13;
All Equtpment                    818.8  13.6         1,208.6  14.6        1,544.9  13.7        2,615.7   17.0&#13;
B. Directed Loans                  1,965.8  32.7         2,786.2  33.4        3,966.8  35.1        5,612.4   36.6&#13;
BI Equtpment                     628.3  10.4           852.3  10.3        1,172.2  10.4        2,047.7   13.3&#13;
BI/B(X)                                 32.0                  30.9                 29.6                  36.5&#13;
BI/Al(X)                                76.7                  70.5                 75.9                  78.3&#13;
Exports (short-term) 1/          883.2  14.7         1,227.2  14.8        1,720.8   1.2        2,197.2    14.3&#13;
Export Industry Equipment 2/      57.0                  42.7                 26.2                179.9&#13;
Machitm Industry Promotion 3/     26.1                  15.1                  10.2                 6.2&#13;
Special Equipment                 35.0                  30.1                 22.5                 15.0&#13;
Industrial Rationalization         7.8                   7.5                  6.3                  5.4&#13;
Medium Industry                  242.1   4.0           371.5   4.5          642.9   5.7        1,000.1    6.5&#13;
Agriculture                      175.3   2.9           234.6   2.8          313.7    2.8         331.2    2.2&#13;
Fishery                           66.8   1.1            81.0   1.0          106.1   0.9          138.3    0.9&#13;
Housing                          381.4   6.3           626.9   7.6 -        938.6   8.3        1,455.1    9.5&#13;
Equipment for Energy&#13;
Conservation  4/                  -                     -                   2.0                 94.7    0.6&#13;
Others                           222.6   3.7           124.6   1.5          177.6   1.6          204.1    1.3&#13;
2. Government Funds&#13;
A. Total                             302.1 100.0           347.4 100.0          503.9 100.0          643.9   100.0&#13;
B. Equipment                         256.3  84.8           324.4  93.4          469.7  93.2          598.9   93.0&#13;
3. NIF Funds&#13;
A.  Total                            287.7 100.0           362.7 100.0          405.3 100.0          487.2   100.0&#13;
B. Equipment                         273.8  95.2           348.4  96.1          375.6  92.7          421.5   86.5&#13;
4. Foreign Currency Loans              1,098.9                1,722.9              2,596.1             2,775.0&#13;
Total DBM Loans                7,707.8 100.0         10,707.7 100.0      14,800.5 100.0       19,256.7   100.0&#13;
(1+2+3+4)&#13;
Total Directed Loans           3,654.5  47.4         5,194.2  48.5        7,472.1  50.5        9,518.5   49.4&#13;
(11+2+3+4)&#13;
Directed Loans (excluding&#13;
Exports-Short Term)            2,771.3  36.0         3,967.0  37.1        5,751.3  38.9        7,321.3    38.2&#13;
I/   90 Day.&#13;
2/    8 Years.&#13;
3/ 3-8 Years.&#13;
_/    5 Years.&#13;
Source: Bank of Korea&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table A29: NATIONAL INVESTMENT FUND NIF RATIO&#13;
CUMULATED REPAYMENT ON CUMULATED NEW LOANS&#13;
1974            1975            1976              1971             1978            1979                 t980                1981               1982&#13;
Loan   Rep.    Loan    Rap.     Losn    Rep.     Loan     Rep.  LIsn       Rep.    eoan    Rtp.       Loan      Rep.      Losn      Rep.      Loan     Rep.&#13;
Purchase of domestic    3,693   26     9.006    274     28.787   1.114   54,184  4.314   68.737  10,198   123,187  20,919    164.200   44,450    228.019   74.142   385,147   107.921&#13;
machineries&#13;
RATIO  S          1              3                 2                8               11               17                27                   33                  28&#13;
Constructlion of        7,055 861     16,166  3.287     30,748   4,137   61,228   5,777  106,753  8,711   155,676   16,241   173,335   31,354    194,854  46,836    234,235    60,423&#13;
wchinsry factories&#13;
2&#13;
RATIO S          12             20                13                9                8               10               18                   24                  26&#13;
Planned Shipbuilding     -      -      3,052     -      138,03     -     29,520    -     49,610   2,830   88,074    6,315    142.658   13,242   239.724   30,042    362,066   47,355&#13;
RATIO I          -              -                 -                 -                6                7                9                   13                   13&#13;
Defense Industries      1,944   38    12,419    380     25.006   1.323   38,438  3.721   71,384   9,735   102,364  23,822     141,703  44,054   211,857   72.591    253,049   116,120&#13;
RTIO   S          2              3                 5               10               14               23                31                  34                  46&#13;
Otber beavy &amp;          2,681    -     48,002   1.451    93,669   2,534  141,261  8,509  259,466   14,274  408,805  28,566    522.914   53,287   603.803   96,408    688,313   159.147     0&#13;
chemical Industrites&#13;
RATIO  2          -              3                 3                6               6                 7                 0o                 16                  23&#13;
Electronic                920   -      1,689     50      2,734     181    3,645    491   10,129    1,037   17,848   2,164     22,936    4,489    24,341    7,623     29.961    11,386&#13;
RATIO  S           -             3                1                3                10               12                 20                 31                  38&#13;
Power Industry         17,000   -    60,200   -        100,200          1 340,200  1,700  242,200  8,600  342,200  24,100    462,200   44,680    622,200  79,720    762,200   136,460&#13;
RATIOS             -             -                    -             I               4                 7                 30                 13                  l8&#13;
Unit Billion Won&#13;
Source: Natioaal lnvestaent Fond Statistics&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 97 -&#13;
TABLR A30: LOANS AND DISCOUNTS OF DEPOSIT MONEY BANKS BY INDUSTRY (Z)&#13;
Metal Products&#13;
Date   Construction    Manufacturing     Textiles    Chemicals    Machinery&#13;
(et.al)     (et. al.)     &amp; Equip.&#13;
1978        9.5            57.8            17.8         8.4            12.2&#13;
1979       11.6            56.8            16.3         8.1           13.4&#13;
1980       12.5            56.7            15.3         9.0            14.0&#13;
1981       12.8            54.2            14.2         9.1            12.5&#13;
1982-6      9.9            53.4            13.0         8.3            11.4&#13;
1982       10.6            50.3            12.3         8.4           11.9&#13;
1983-9     11.7            48.0            11.4         7.8           11.9&#13;
Table A31: Land Price Tndex (Rate of Growth)&#13;
1975    1976     1977    1978    1979    1980     1981    1982    1983&#13;
(est..&#13;
Total    26.99   26.60   33.55   49.98   16.63    11.68    7.51     5.4       20&#13;
Major     4.87   21.04   46.67   79.08    21.96   17.02    7.11      5.6      40&#13;
Cities&#13;
Small    25.84   28.62   34.65   58.78   14.49    14.37    8.63     7.9       18&#13;
Cities&#13;
Rural    25.92   24.43   25.72   26.69   12.46     8.19    7.12      5.0      13&#13;
WPI       19.6     9.4    10.1    12.2    23.8     42.3    11.3     2.4     -0.2&#13;
Deflator   24.4   17.9    16.5    20.3     19.3    23.8    18.1     8.0      2.8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 98 -&#13;
FOOTNOTES&#13;
1/      If one were to speculate on precise numbers, the appropriate ratio of&#13;
the general bills (or prime) rate, representing the base choice with&#13;
which the rate differentiation is to be built to the curb rate is not&#13;
likely to be significantly different from 0.5.&#13;
2/      Virmani (1982), Section 4.5 or Virmani (1983).&#13;
3/      See Virmani (1982), section 3.2 and 4.7, and Appendix.&#13;
4/       See Virmani (1982), Section 3.2.&#13;
5/      Overdue loans are a special category of low expected return or high&#13;
risk loans. The premium for these loans has ranged from 67% in the&#13;
third quarter of 1977 to 21% in the second quarter of 1982. For the&#13;
10 quarter period before and after first quarter 1980 it was 25% and&#13;
32% respectively. Finer differentiation into a B and C categories&#13;
(say), could have interest ceilings which were higher than the A&#13;
category by 15% and 30% respectively. Overdue loans of one category&#13;
could then be subject to the loan ceiling of the next higher category.&#13;
6/       I have shown elsewhere (see 1982 &amp; 1984 papers) that this is an&#13;
efficient form of intervention if market failure exists.&#13;
7/      See my 1982 and 1984 papers (op. cit.), for why a direct interest loan&#13;
subsidy (not a ceiling) or a collateral subsidy is an efficient way of&#13;
affecting credit allocation.&#13;
8/       1982 paper, op. cit., Chapter 15.&#13;
9/       See subsequent discussion on loans with and without collateral.&#13;
10/      1982 Paper.&#13;
11/     Op. cit., Sections 6.2 and 7.3.&#13;
12/      1982 paper, Section 3.4.&#13;
13/     Inflation is ignored.&#13;
14/     See Policy Analysis in Virmani (1982) Section 4.5, Virmani (1983) or&#13;
Virmani (1984).&#13;
15/     Wijnbergen (1983).&#13;
16/     Virmani (1982)   Section 7.3.   Also see analysis in Appendix.&#13;
17/     Virmani (1982),   Section 7.2, 7.3 on Adverse Selection.&#13;
18/     Figure 7 is in Virmani (1982) Section 2.3.     Figure 6 can also be found&#13;
in A. Virmani, "Contractual Equilibrium in Competitive Loan Markets",&#13;
DRD Discussion Paper No. 43.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 99 -&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
1. Park, Yungchul, Korea's Experience with Industrial Adjustment in the&#13;
1970's, Korea University Mimeo, 1983.&#13;
2. Virmani, Arvind, The Nature of Credit Markets in Developing Countries: A&#13;
Framework for Policy Analysis World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 524,&#13;
World Bank 1982.&#13;
3.             , Contractual Equilibrium in Competitive Loan Markets, DRD&#13;
Discussion Paper No. 43, World Bank, 1982 (b).&#13;
4.             , Loan Market Imperfections and Optimal Policy Intervention,&#13;
Mimeo, June 1983.&#13;
5.             , Evaluation of Financial Policy:    Credit Allocation in&#13;
Bangladesh, Staff Working paper No. 672, World Bank, 1984.&#13;
6. Wijnbergen, Sweder, "Interest Rate Management in Developing Countries,&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 524, World Bank, 1982.&#13;
7. Yang, S.K., "Shift in Development Strategy and Government Finance", in&#13;
J.K. Park and K.F. Lee (eds.), National Budget and Policy Objectives,&#13;
KOI, 1982.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Wolid Bank                               An Analysis of Developing                    NEW&#13;
Country Adjustment&#13;
PUblicAtions                             Experiences in the 1970s: Low-           Compounding and Discounting&#13;
of Related                               Income Asia                              Tables for Project Analysis&#13;
Christine Wallich                        (with a Guide to Their&#13;
Interest                                 Staff Working Paper No. 487. 1981. 43    Applications)&#13;
pages (including references).            Second Edition, Revised and&#13;
Stock No. WP 0487. S3.                   Expanded&#13;
Adjustment Experience and                Aspects of Development Bank              l. Price Gittinger&#13;
Growth Prospects of the Semi-            Management                               Project planners and analysts will find&#13;
Industrial Countries                     William Diamond and V. S.                this book a convenient and time-san-&#13;
Frederick Jaspersen                      Raghan                                   ing reference for the preparation and&#13;
StaffeWorkig Paspers No.R477.1981.132eaghavan                                     analysis of development projects. Six-&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 4771. 132         Deals exclusively with the manage-      decimal tables for I percent through 50&#13;
pages (including 3 appendixa).           ment of development banks. The book      percent show the compounding factor&#13;
Stock No. WP 0477. $5.                   is divided into eight sections, each     for I and for I per annum, the sinking&#13;
dealing with one aspect of manage-       fund factor, the discount factor, the&#13;
Adjustment in Low-Income                 ment of its problems, and of the var-    present worth of an annuity factor,&#13;
Africa                                   ious ways of dealing with them.          and the capital recovery factor. The&#13;
Robert Liebenthal                        EDI Series in Economic Development. The  first edition of this book underwent&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 486. 1981. 62    Johns Hopkins University Press, 1982.    seven printings in ten years and was&#13;
pages (including bibliography).          2nd printing, 1983. 311 pages.           translated into Arabic, Chinese,&#13;
Stock No. WP 0486. $3.                   LC 81-48174. ISBN 0-8018-2571-7, Stock   French, and Spanish. This new edi-&#13;
No. IH 2571, $29.95 hardcover; ISBN 0-   tion-with narrow-interval compound-&#13;
Aggregate Demand and                     8018-2572-5, Stock No. IH 2572, $12.95   ing tables added for higher interest&#13;
Macroeconomic Imbalances in              paperback.                               rates, updated project examples, a&#13;
guide to using simple electronic calcu-&#13;
Thailand: Simulations with the           Capital Accumulation in                  lators to perform the computations&#13;
SIAM   I Model                           Eastern and Southemn Africa: A           discussed, and an annotated bibliog-&#13;
Wafik Grais                              Decade of Setbacks                        raphy increases the proven usefulness&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 448. 1981. 132   Ravi Gulhati and Gautam Datta            of its predecessor, both in the class-&#13;
pages (including 3 appendixes).          Analyzes the magnitude of the setback    room and at the project site.&#13;
Stock No. WP 0448. $i. In capital accumulation in eastern and                     May 1984. About 208 pages.&#13;
southern Africa. This phenomenon is      ISBN 0-8018-2409-5. Stock No. BK 2409.&#13;
examined in twenty-eight statistical ta-  $10.95.&#13;
NEW                                  bles. The authors sample sixteen coun-    Translations of this new edition will be&#13;
tries and rely on expert observations to  awilable in 1985. Still available are the&#13;
explore the proximate causes of the      following translations of the first edition:&#13;
Alternative Mechanisms for               setbacks.                                 French: Tables d'interets composes et d'ac-&#13;
Financing Social Security                World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 562.  tualisation. Economica, 4th printing,&#13;
Parthasarathi Shome and Lyn              1983. 74 pages.                           1979.&#13;
Squire                                   ISBN 0-8213-0169-1. Stock No. WP 0562.    ISBN 2-7178-0205-3, Stock No. 1B 0542,&#13;
Reviews, clarifies, and evaluates theo-  $3.        ,                              $6.&#13;
retical literature about the effect of so-&#13;
cial security on capital accumulation    Capital Market Imperfections              Spanish: Tablas de interes compuesto y de&#13;
and labor supply. Analyzes empirical     and Economic Development                  descuento para evaluacian de proyectos.&#13;
studies using U.S. data, the impact of   Vinayak V. Bhatt and Alan R. Roe          Editorial Tecnos, 1973; 4th printing, 1980.&#13;
pay-as-you-go financed and fully         Staff Working Paper No. 338. 1979. 87     ISBN 84-309-0716-5, Stock No. IB 0526.&#13;
funded social security schemes, and      wages (including footnotes).              $6.&#13;
characteristics of optimal social secu-  Stock No. WP 0338: $3.&#13;
rity systems. This study provides a&#13;
starting point ferof exstoing theories for  The Changing Nature of Export          A Conceptual Approach to the&#13;
financing social security in developing   Finance and Its Implications             Analysis of Extemal Debt of&#13;
countries.                               for Developing Countries                  the Developing Countries&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 625. 1983. 62     Albert C. Cizauskas                      Robert Z. Aliber&#13;
pages.                                    Staff Working Paper No. 409. 1980. 43    Staff Working Paper No. 421. 1980. 25&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0292-2.Stock No. WP 0625.     pages (including 3 annexes).             pages (including appendix, references).&#13;
$3.                                       Stock No. WP 0409. $3.                   Stock No. WP 0421. $3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NEW                                  Staff Working Paper No. 632. 1984. 144  Growth and Structural&#13;
pages.                                  Adjustment in East Asia&#13;
Development Finance                      Stock No. WP 0632. $5.                  Parvez Hasan&#13;
Companies, State and Privately                                                   Staff Working Paper No. 529. 1982. 42&#13;
Owned: A Review                              NEW                                 pages.&#13;
David L. Gordon                                                                  ISBN 0-8213-0102-0. Stock No. WP 0529.&#13;
An informative guide to the function     Economic Liberalization and             $3.&#13;
and design of development finance        Stabilization Policies in               Interest Rate Management in&#13;
companies as they are set up in devel-   Argentina, Chile, and                   Developing Countries: Theo&#13;
oping countries. Case histories high-    Uruguay: Applications of the            and SiultonRgut fry&#13;
light the diffierences among these com-  Monetary Approach to the                     Simulation Results for&#13;
panies-their institutional structure,                                            South Korea&#13;
management style, financial perfor-      Balance of Payments                     Sweder van Wijnbergen&#13;
mance, and other features. Looks at      Edited by Nicolas Ardito Barletta,      Examines the claim that higher time&#13;
the problems of resource mobilization    Mario 1. Blejer, and Luis Landau        deposit rates raise output and lower&#13;
and strategies to overcome them.         Twenty-eight leading international      inflation in the short run, and increase&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 578. 1983. 84    economists and regional specialists re-  growth through their favorable impact&#13;
pages.                                   view the salient characteristics of the  on savings rates. It concludes that this&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-02264 Stock No. WP 0578.     monetary approach to the balance of     theory depends heavily on the as-&#13;
$3.                                      payments, examine the variations in     sumption that portfolio shifts into time&#13;
its application, and evaluate its suc-  deposits come out of unproductive as-&#13;
Development Prospects of                 cesses and failures. Emphasizes the     sets, providing less intermediation&#13;
Capital Surplus Oil-Exporting            empirical evidence and dynamic as-      than the banking system. Impact of&#13;
Countries: Iraq, Kuwait, *Libya,         pects and costs. Provides an important  changes in time deposit rates on infla-&#13;
Qountar   ies: Araq, Kuwait, Libya,      examination of economic policies and    tion, capital, capital accumulation and&#13;
Qatar, Saudi Arabia, UAE                 their effects in a region that looms    medium term growth are discussed,&#13;
Rudolf Hablutzel                         large in current deliberations about in-  and empirical relevance is demon-&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 483. 1981. 53    temational indebtedness and finance.    strated through simulation runs with a&#13;
pages (including statistical tables).    June 1984. About 240 pages.             macroeconomic model of South Korea.&#13;
Stock No. WP 0483. $3.                   ISBN 0-8213-0305-8. $17.50 paperback.   World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 593.&#13;
1983. 52 pages.&#13;
Developments in and Prospects            Energy Prices, Substitution,            ISBN 0-8213-0188-8. Stock No. WP 0593.&#13;
for the External Debt of the             and Optimal Borrowing in the            $3&#13;
Developing Countries: 1970-80            Short Run: An Analysis of&#13;
and Beyond                               Adjustment in Oil-Importing             International Adjustment in&#13;
Nicholas C. Hope                         Developing Countries                    the 1980s&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 488. 1981. 70    Ricardo Martin and Marcelo              Vijay Joshi&#13;
pages (including 2 annexes, references).  Selowsky                               Staff Working Paper No. 485. 1982. 57&#13;
Stock No. WP 0488. $3.                   Staff Working Paper No. 466. 1981. 77   pages.&#13;
pages (including footnotes, references).  ISBN 0-8213-0062-8. Stock No. 0485. $3.&#13;
Stock No. WP 0466. $3.&#13;
Exchange Rate Adjustment                    NEW&#13;
Domestic Resource                        under Generalized Currency              Links between Taxes and&#13;
Mobilization in Pakistan:                Floating: Comparative Analysis          Economic Growth: Some&#13;
Selected Issues                          among Developing Countries              Empirical Evidence&#13;
Nizar Jetha, Shamshad Akhtar,            Romeo M. Bautista                        Eincarsden&#13;
and M. Govinda Rao                       Staff Working Paper No. 436. 1980. 99   Keith Marsden&#13;
Fouses on the relationship between       pages (including appendix).             Reviews the experience with growth&#13;
taxation and the three main compo-       Stock No. WP 0436. $3.                  developed countrienty developing and&#13;
form with a view to raising addiional    A General Equilibrium                   spectrum of incomes. Do countries&#13;
revenues and encouraging household       Analysis of Foreign Exchange            with lower taxes experience more&#13;
and business savings. Proposals for tax  Shortages in a Developing               rapid expansion of investment, pro-&#13;
reform take account of equity consid-    Economy                                 ducbtvity, employment, and govern-&#13;
erations and the need to keep tax-in-.   Kemal Dervis, Jaime de Melo, and        ment services? This provocative paper&#13;
duced distortions in the allocation of   Sherman Robinson                        questions gseily        yeat odvl&#13;
resources to a minimum. Highlights       Stan W   o  bin son                     questiopm especially relevant to devel-&#13;
appropriate policies on current ex-      Staff Working Paper No. 443. 1981. 32   opment economists. It also examines&#13;
penditures, subsidies, user charges,     pages (including references).           the mechanisms by which fiscal poli-&#13;
public enterprise pricing, self-financing  Stock No. WP 0443. $3.                cies may affect growth rates.&#13;
of investment by public enterprises.                                             Staff Working Paper No. 605. 1983. 48&#13;
Includes three annexes that examine                                              pages.&#13;
direct taxes, indirect taxes, and tax     Prices subject to change without notice  ISBN 0-8213-0215-9. Stock No. WP 0605.&#13;
changes in Pakistan's 1983/84 budget.     and may vary by country.               $3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NEW                                   The Policy Experience of                 Private Bank Lending to&#13;
Twelve Less Developed                    Developing Countries&#13;
Municipal Accounting for                 Countries, 1973-1978                     Richard O'Brien&#13;
Developing Countries                     Bela Balassa                             Staff Working Paper No. 482. 1981. 60&#13;
David C. Jones                           Staff Working Paper No. 449. 1981. 36    pages (including appendix, bibliography).&#13;
This manual is based on British prac-    pages (including appendix).              Stock No. WP 0482. $3.&#13;
tices and terminology of municipal ac-   Stock No. WP 0449. $3.                   Private Capital Flows to&#13;
counting, modified to suit-the needs of&#13;
other countries, especially those lack-  The Political Structure of the           Developing Countries and&#13;
ing a core of appropriately trained ac-  New Protectionism                        Their Determinations:&#13;
countants. Provides the basic princi-     Douglas R. Nelson                       Historical Perspective, Recent&#13;
pies of municipal accounting for those                                            Eprec,adFtr&#13;
with littie or no bookkeeping experi-     Staff Working Paper No. 471. 1981. 57   Experience, and Future&#13;
ence and proceeds through successive     pages (including references).            Prospects&#13;
levels of difficulty to some of the most  Stock No. WP 0471. $3.                  Alex Fleming&#13;
advanced concepts currently in use,                                               Staff Working Paper No. 484. 1981. 41&#13;
including the pooling of loans. An im-                                            pages.&#13;
portant feature is the multitude of          NEW                                  Stock No. WP 0484. $3.&#13;
practical applications and examples of&#13;
forms and records.                                                                Private Direct Foreign&#13;
A joint publication of the Chartered      Price Distortions and Growth            Investment in Developing&#13;
Institute of Public Finance and Ac-       in Developing Countries                 Countries&#13;
countancy and the World Bank.             Ramgopal Agarwala                       K. Bilerbeck and Y. Yasugi&#13;
June 1984. About 900 pages.               Sixteen informative tables trace the    Staff Working Paper No. 348. 1979, 101&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0350-3. Stock No. BK 0350.    distortion in prices of foreign exchange  pages (including 2 annexes).&#13;
$30.                                      and other factors affecting the growth  Stock No. WP 0348. $5.&#13;
of developing countries. Based on sta-&#13;
The Nature of Credit Markets             tistics from thirty-one developing&#13;
in Developing Countries: A                countries.                                  NEW&#13;
Framework for Policy Analysis             Staff Working Paper No. 575. 1983. 78&#13;
Arvind Virmani                            pages.                                   Savings Mobilization through&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 524. 1982. 204   ISBN 0-8213-0242-6. Stock No. WP 0575.    Social Security: The Case of&#13;
pages.                                    $3.                                      Chile, 1916-1977&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0019-9. Stock No. WP 0524.                                             Christine Wallich&#13;
$5-                                       Pricing Policy for Development           Describes the savings mobilization po-&#13;
The Newly Industrializing                 Management                               tential in Chile and in five Asian pro-&#13;
Developing Countries after the            Gerald M. Meier                          grams. Some sort of social security&#13;
Oil Crisis                     ~~~~~~~Presupposing no formal training in  program functions in almost all devel-&#13;
Oil Crisis                                economics, it explains the essential     oping countries. Programs are often&#13;
Bela Balassa                              elements of a price system, the func-    costly, whether measured in relation&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 437. 1980. 57    tions of prices, the various policies     to GNP, government expenditure,&#13;
pages (including appendix).               that a govemment might pursue in         government revenue, or the wage bill.&#13;
Stock No. WP 0437. $3.                    cases of market failure, and the princi-  This paper compares the successful&#13;
ples of public pricing of goods and      systems.&#13;
Notes on the Analysis of                  services provided by government en-      Staff Working Paper No. 553. 1983. 109&#13;
Capital Flows to Developing               terprises. It also provides the would-be  pages.&#13;
Nations and the "Recycling"               practitioner with an appreciation of the  ISBN 0-8213-0123-3. Stock No. WP 0553.&#13;
Problem                       ~~~~~~~~underlying logical structure of cost-  5&#13;
Problem                                   benefit project appraisal. To give sub-&#13;
Ralph C. Bryant                           stance to the applied and policy di-    Short-Run Macro-Economic&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 476. 1981. 67     mensions, many of the readings are      Adjustment Policies in South&#13;
pages.                                    drawn from the experience of develop.   Ajsmn           oiisi       ot&#13;
Stock No. WP 0476. $3.                    ment practitioners and relate to such   Korea: A Quantitative Analysis&#13;
important sectors as agriculture, in-   Sweder van Wijnbergen&#13;
Notes on the Mechanics of                 dustry, power, urban services, foreign  Staff Working Paper No. 510. 1981. 182&#13;
Growth and Debt                           trade, and employment. The principles   pages (including 3 appendixes).&#13;
Benjamin B. King                          outlined are therefore relevant to a    ISBN 0-8213-0000-8. Stock No. WP 0510.&#13;
A pratica modl to xploe th  wayhost of development problems.             5&#13;
A practical mpodel to explore the way     The Johns Hopkins University Press. 1983.&#13;
in which capital nflow from abroad af-    272 pages (including bibliography and in-&#13;
fects economic growth.                    dex).&#13;
The Johns Hopkins University Press, 2968.  LC 82-7726. ISBN 0-8018-2803-2, Stock&#13;
69 pages (including 4 annexes).           No. IH 2803, $35 hardcover; ISBN 0-&#13;
LC 68-8701. ISBN 0-8018-0338-1, Stock     8018-2804-X, Stock No. IH 2804, $12.95   Prices subject to change without notice&#13;
No. IH 0338. $5 paperback.                paperback.                               and may vary by country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
State Finances in India&#13;
A three-volume set of papers that ex-&#13;
plores a range of issues relating to the&#13;
nature of intergovemmental fiscal rela-                                                                          l&#13;
tions in India.                              46The primary source for                   W oArld Debt Tables&#13;
Vol. 1: Revenue Sharing in India             medium- and long-term                        l                      l&#13;
Christine Wallich                                                                                                I&#13;
Vol. II: India-Studies in State Fi-          external debt of many&#13;
nances                                       developing countries."&#13;
Christine Wallich&#13;
Vol. III: The Measurement of Tax Ef-                Suhas Ketkar, Asia-Pacific&#13;
fort of State Governments, 1973-1976                Economist and Vice President,&#13;
Raja J. Chelliah and Narain Sinha                  Marine Midland Bank, N.A.&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 523. 1982. vol.&#13;
1, 85 pages, vol. 11, 186 pages, vol. 111, 85&#13;
pages.                                        66Often the only reliable&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0013-X. vol. 1, Stock No.&#13;
WP 1523, $3, vol. II, Stock No. WP           source of information for&#13;
2523, $5, vol. III, Stock no. WP 3523, $3.    countries for which data&#13;
_ _ _ _ __   is hard to come by ... Used quantitatively for&#13;
macroeconomic detail as well as qualitatively in&#13;
Structural Adjustment Policies                reports discussing the debt picture. I find the&#13;
in Developing Economies                      projected servicing payments a strong feature.99&#13;
Bela Balassa                                                                         Jonathan Kayes, International&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 464. 1981. 36                                                Economist, Republic&#13;
pages.                                                                               National Bank of New York&#13;
Stock No. WP 0464. S3.&#13;
Structural Aspects of Turkish                 World Debt Tables, 1983-84 Edition&#13;
Inflation: 19501979                          The World Bank's invaluable reference Also available for the first time&#13;
M. Ataman Aksov                               guide to the external debt of develop-  , ayRpr&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 540. 1982. 118       ing countries. Essential planning tool  umry     P&#13;
pages.                                        for economists, bankers, country risk  Debt and the Developing&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0098-9. Stock No. WP 0540.       analysts, financial consultants and all  World: Current Trends&#13;
$5.                                          those interested in-the global system&#13;
of trade and payments. Provides data  and Prospects&#13;
on the extemal debt of 103 developing Includes an overview and summary ta-&#13;
Thailand: An Analysis of                     countries augmented by information,  bles from the 1983-84 edition.&#13;
Structural and Non-Structural                where available, on major economic   1984. 64 pages.&#13;
Adjustments                                  aggregates plus indicators used to ana-&#13;
Arne Drud, Wafik Grais, and                  lyze debt and creditworthiness. Shows Stock No, BK 0319, $6.50.&#13;
Dusan Vujovic                                statistical tables by counitry, including  Companion computerized data&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 513. 1982. 93figures for external public debt out-        base&#13;
standing, commitments, disburse-&#13;
pages (including appendix).                   ments, service payments, and net bor- Includes all debt information given in&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0023-7. Stock No. WP 0513.       rowings. Reports on private         the unabridged volume, and, where&#13;
$3.                                           nonguaranteed debt of 19 countries.  available, offers continuous historical&#13;
Gives aggregate position of 13 major  series for 1970-82 and projected debt-&#13;
borrowers-countries with disbursed  service payments for 1983-92. Write for&#13;
Trends in Rural Savings and                  and outstanding medium- and long-    sample purchase agreement.&#13;
Private Capital Formation in                 term total debt in excess of $13.5 bil-  (9-track, phase-encoded, recording&#13;
India                                        lion at the end of 1982. Includes peri-  densitv 1600 bpi)&#13;
Raj Krishna and G.S.                         odic supplements as fresh data are re- Stock No. IB 0500, $5,000 (service bur-&#13;
Raychaudhuri                                                                      eaus for reselling to their clients); Stock&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 382.      1984. 328 pages.                     No. IB 0667, $2,000 (banks and commer-&#13;
1980. 43 pages (including 2 tables, 3 ap-    Stock No. BK 0315 $75 (annual subscrip- cial corporations); Stock No. IB 0666, $500&#13;
pendixes, references).                       tzon)                                (universities and libraries).&#13;
Stock No. WP 0382. $3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
*      The World Bank&#13;
Publications Order Form&#13;
SEND TO: YOUR LOCAL DISTRIBUTOR OR TO WORLD BANK PUBLICATIONS&#13;
(See the other side of this form.)        P.O. BOX 37525&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C. 20013 U.S.A.&#13;
Date&#13;
Name                                                Ship to: (Enter if different from purchaser)&#13;
Title                                               Name&#13;
Firm                                                Title&#13;
Address                                             Firm&#13;
City              State      Postal Code     .      Address&#13;
Country            'Teephone I      )               City            State  -   Postal Code_&#13;
Purchaser Reference No. .                           Country             Telephone (   )&#13;
Check your method of payment.&#13;
Enclosed is my a Check a International Money Order O Unesco Coupons O International Postal Coupon.&#13;
Make payable to World Bank Publications for U. S. dollars unless you are ordering from your local distributor.&#13;
Charge my E VISA O MasterCard O American Express O Choice. (Credit cards accepted only for orders addressed&#13;
to World Bank Publications.)&#13;
Credit Card Account Number           Expiration Date                    Signature&#13;
E Invoice me and please reference my Purchase Order No.&#13;
Please ship me the items listed below.&#13;
Customer Internal&#13;
Stock Number  Author/ Title                                     Routing Code  Quantity  Unit Price  Total Amount S&#13;
All prices subject to change. Prices may vary by country. Allow 6-8 weeks for delivery.&#13;
Subtotal Cost  $&#13;
Ibtal copies      Air mail surcharge if desired ($2.00 each)  $&#13;
Postage and handling for more than two complimentary items ($2.00 each)  $&#13;
Total  S&#13;
taRDO0053                                                        Thank you for your order.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Distributors of World Bank Publications&#13;
ARGENTINA                          GERMANY. FEDERAL REPBLIUC           KUWArr                             SRI LAN"   AND THE MALDVS&#13;
Carlos Hus-h. SRL                    OF                                MEMRB                              Lake House Bookhop&#13;
Galena Guemes                      LNO-Ve"S                            P0 8Ox S465                        P0 Box 244&#13;
Flonda 165. th Flocr-Otc. 45465    Di300 Bonn I                        Kuwait                             100. Sr Chittunpalam A. Gardiner&#13;
1333 Buenos ASoesSi                      stns                                                               MawatUh&#13;
AUSTRAA, PAPUANEW                  GREECE                              University olfalava Coopentve      CoSn  oo2&#13;
GUINEA. FII. SOLOMON             MEMR3                                 Bocokhop. Linuted                Sn Lanh&#13;
ISLANDS, AND VANUATU             24. Ippodamou Street                P 0 Box I17. 1u an Pantiu BanS     SWEDEN&#13;
Info-Lne                           Athens-11635                        Kuala Lumpur                       For single titl:&#13;
Oveneas Document Deliveryv         HONG KONG MACAU                     MEXIC                              ABCE Fntz, Kung. Hovbokhandel&#13;
Sydne. Gw O                        Asia 2000J Ltd.                     NT4OTEC                            Rgnp       t    2  o  &amp;5&#13;
Aus0Xa ;06.GP6 Fl. 146 Pnnce Edward Road. W,                           San Lorenz 153-11 Col del VaDle    5.10327 Stock6o1m&#13;
Austnalia                          Kowloon                              'Deeg Senito Juarez               For suruitim or&#13;
BAHRAIN                            Hong Kong                           03100 Mexico Cit                   Wennerr-Wti        Ai3&#13;
PEoMR                              INDIA                               MOROCCO                            bOm 30004&#13;
P 0 Box Z21W3                      UBS Publishers' DLstnbutors Ltd.      EMRSB                            5.104 25 Stockholm&#13;
tanama Town 317                    Post Box 7015                       2 Rue Mobere RaSZneErm                        N&#13;
BANGLADESH                         New Delh 110002                     Casablanca                         Libr     Pivot&#13;
MiAo sndusst es Development        10 First Matn Road                  THE NETHERLANDS                    6 Rue Grcnus&#13;
GPss Box 800                     Gandhi Nagar                        Medical Books Europe. BV (MBE)     Cane p-     381&#13;
GDP    Bo ka                        Bangalore 560009                   Noorderwal 38.                     CH 1211 Gene 11&#13;
BELGILM                            Apeetay Chambemn P0    Box 736      741 8L Lochem                      TANZANIA&#13;
Pubbaturuides  atins  nws  5 Waillae Stret                    NIGERIA                             Oxiatd IUniVuu  Pres&#13;
Publicabona des Nationts Lne       Bombav 40001                        University Pre  Limuted            P 0. BOX 5299&#13;
1060 Brussels                      8/-B. Chownnghtt Li                 Three Crowns Buidig Jertho         Dar es Saum&#13;
SRAZIL                             Cutta                               Private Man Bag 5DqTHAILAND&#13;
Pubbcacoes Teaucas Intemacionas    7138, I(CA)i Swarup Nagar           CNORWAY                             306 Stbtm R      S&#13;
Ltda.                             Kampu 200                          Tanum Kad [ohan. AS                 Bangk&#13;
Rua Peuxoto Gosude. 209            Sivagang Road                       P 0. Box 1177                       TRIAD &amp; TOBAGO&#13;
01409 Sao Paula, Sp                Nungambakkai                        Sentmum                             Svstmatna Sbsiads Unit&#13;
CANADA                              Madras 604                         Osl '                                 Eo tem M1m Road&#13;
Le Ddtuirser                       INDONESIA                           PAKISTAN                            Curepe&#13;
C P 85. 1 501 Ampere Stre          Pt Indua Lunuted                     Muia Book Agency                   Tnidad West India&#13;
Boucherville. Quebec 14B E6        Jl Sam Ratuiangi 37                 63. Shahrah-e-Quaid-e-Azam          TUNISL&#13;
CHILE                              lakiars Pusat                       P 0. Box No. 729                    Societe Tunmne de Dluon&#13;
Editoral Renacuruento              PO BOx Idl                          Lahore 3                            ; Avenue de CArtue&#13;
Mlrtiagor  354                     IRELAND                             PANAMA                              Tunis&#13;
S^ntag  TDC Pubbshen                Edicm Lbrerna Cuturai              TUBRKEY&#13;
COSTA RICA                         12 North FredencL Stret               Panamena. S.A                    FHaset rutpm A.S.&#13;
Lbreoa TMos                        Dublin I                            Av 7. Espana 16                     469 Ioiklal Caddes&#13;
CAvFe 11-13  GTALY                                                     Panamu Zone I                       Bevoglu-lsanbul&#13;
San Jo"                            Lscoa Commsnnazr Sarou SPA          PERU                                UGANDA&#13;
'A   B iox                         Via LLmamora45 Rtor l Desarroo SA                                       Uganda Bookhop&#13;
CYPRUS                             50121 Florece                       Apartado 3824                       Attn Mr    aiUan-Luthea Gabwango&#13;
Po BOX2O98                         JAPAN                                                                   P 0. Sox 7145&#13;
Nicosia                            Eastern Book Servce EBS)            PHIUPPINES                          Kampa&#13;
37-3 Hongo 3{Chome. Burkvo-ku       National Book Store                LNITED ARAB EMIRATES&#13;
DENMARK                              113                               :01 Rizal Avenue                     MB&#13;
SamhhndsLtteatur                    Tokvo                               Meto MInila                        P 0 Box 6097&#13;
Rosenoems Alle 11                  JORDA                               PORTUGAL&#13;
DK-197t3 Copenhagen V               'IEMRB                             Lbvrana Portuga                     LNMTD KINGDOM AND&#13;
EGYr ARAB REPUBUC OF                PO Soa 3143                        Rua Do Camro 70-74                    NOlRTHERN IRIELAND&#13;
Ui Ahram                           labai                               1200 Lsbon                         .Uicmfo Ltd.&#13;
Calaa Street omman                                                      SAUDI ALABIA                       P 0 Box 3&#13;
Cairo                               KE.YA                              lamr Book Store                     Alton, Hampshwre GU 34 2PG&#13;
FINLAND                             Atnca Book Sevice (E.A ) Ltd.       P 0. Box 3196                      Urited Kingdom&#13;
Akateemtnen KLrakauppa              P 0 Box 45243                      Rivadh 11471                        VEt-EZELA&#13;
SF4B101                             Nairobi                            SINGAPORE, TAIWAN. BURMA            Lbrnna del Este&#13;
Helsink 10                          KOREA. REPLBLIC OF                 Worrnation Pubbcatons Prvate. Ltd.  Aptdo 60.337&#13;
Pan Korea Book Corporation          02-06 Lst Fl. Pe-fu Industra Blg,  Caracas 1060-A&#13;
FRANCE                              P 0 Box 101, Kwangwhamun           24 New bndus nl Road                WESTERN SAMOA&#13;
Wodd Bank Publations               Seoul                               Singapore                           Wesev Boobhop&#13;
66 Avenue d'lena                                                       SPAIN                               Apia&#13;
75116 Parms                                                            Mundt-Prensx Libros. SA.&#13;
Castello 37&#13;
M01 .Vadrtd&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters                         European Office              Tokyo Office&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                 66, avenue d'lena             Kokusai Building&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.       75116 Paris, France          1-1 Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234            Telephone: (1) 723-54.21     Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK           Telex: 842-620628            Telephone: (03) 214-5001&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK                                          Telex: 781-26838&#13;
Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0587-5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554705">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/08/1554705/government-policy-development-financial-markets-case-korea
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/08/1554705/government-policy-development-financial-markets-case-korea</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1985/08/1554705/government-policy-development-financial-markets-case-korea</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/12/000178830_98101903432511/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/12/000178830_98101903432511/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-07-12T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1985-08-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Government policy and the development of
            financial markets : the case of Korea
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Direction and control of the financial
            system has had a significant role in the government's
            development strategy. The paper shows how this influenced
            the evolution of the Korean financial system, and how the
            latter responded to shocks during the 1980's. Review of
            the Korean experience also suggests two important
            hypotheses: that subsidy policies (not interest ceilings)
            directed solely at promoting market and economic efficiency
            are more likely to be successful, and that forced lending
            policies (often combined with interest ceilings) directed at
            social, political and other non-economic goals are likely to
            weaken the financial system and be much less likely to
            succeed. Given the nature of this study, however, its
            conclusions, like that of other similar studies, should be
            considered only tentative in the absence of rigorous
            empirical testing.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Government policy and the development of
            financial markets : the case of Korea
        </docna>
        <display_title>Government policy and the
            development of financial markets : the case of Korea</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1985/08/1554705/government-policy-development-financial-markets-case-korea</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Economic Theory &amp; Research,International Terrorism &amp; Counterterrorism,Financial Intermediation</subtopic>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>Korea, Republic of</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Virmani, Arvind</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Asia!$!80460</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903432511</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Other public sector management</subsc>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 747</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Public Administration, Law, and Justice</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0587-5</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Banking systems; Capital markets; Credit
            policy; Financial incentives; Financial institutions;
            Government policy; Interest rates; Lending policy; Subsidies
            Accelerated Depreciation,affiliated
            organizations,affiliates,agriculture,Assets,autonomy,balance
            of payments,Bank of Korea,Banking System,Banks,base
            rates,Bonds,Book Value,borrowing,checking,checking
            accounts,commercial bank loans,Commercial Banks,cost of
            capital,Coverage,Credit
            Markets,Debt,decentralization,depositors,deposits,development
            strategy,discount rate,economic conditions,economic
            efficiency,elasticity,excess demand,Expected
            Returns,Financial Assets,Financial institutions,financial
            intermediaries,Financial Intermediation,financial
            markets,financial regulation,financial sector,financial
            structure,financial systems,inflation,INSURANCE,Interest
            Rate,Interest rates,Land Prices,liberalization,LIFE
            INSURANCE,loan maturity,marginal cost,Monetary
            policy,Portfolio,profit
            margin,Profitability,reserves,Savings,Savings
            institutions,securities,securities
            markets,Shareholdings,specialized banks,Transaction costs
        </keywd>
        <owner>EAC</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP747</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Carreer Guidance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Job Fairs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary and Exchange Rate Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Intermediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Interest Rate Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Intermediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Securities Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Intermediaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Terrorism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Equity Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>