<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>The Newly-Industrializing Developing Countries&#13;
After the Oil Crisis&#13;
SWP437&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 437&#13;
October 1980&#13;
Prepared by: Bela Balassa, The Johns Hopkins University&#13;
and the World Bank&#13;
Copyright ( 1980&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
'7 N  9l-St-r, N.W.&#13;
igtGn, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
iws amd interpretations in this document are those of the author&#13;
Olud n ot be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated&#13;
!ations, or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretation in this document are those of the author and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations,&#13;
or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 437&#13;
October 1980&#13;
The Newly-Industrializing Developing Countries&#13;
After the Oil Crisis&#13;
Abstract&#13;
This paper examines the experience of the newly-industrializing&#13;
developing countries during the period following the quadrupling of oil prices&#13;
in 1973-74 and the world recession of 1974-75. Developing countries with per&#13;
capita incomes in excess of $1100 in 1978 and a manufacturing share of 20&#13;
percent and higher in GDP in 1977 have been classified in this group. The&#13;
investigation also covers Colombia that is on the borderline of becoming a&#13;
newly-industrializing country and India that has an industrial sector larger&#13;
than any developing country other than Brazil and Mexico.&#13;
The paper provides estimates of the balance-of-payments effects of&#13;
external shocks, in the form of the deterioration of the terms of trade and&#13;
the slowdown in world export demand, for twelve newly-industrializing&#13;
countries. It further analyses policy responses to external shock in these&#13;
countries and estimates the balance-of-payments effects of policy responses in&#13;
the form of additional external borrowing, export promotion, import&#13;
substitution, and reducing the rate of economic growth. Finally, the policies&#13;
followed by the individual countries are evaluated in a comparative framework.&#13;
There is a high correlation between reliance on export promotion in&#13;
response to external shocks and the rate of economic growth. This result&#13;
reflects the success of countries that continued to follow outward-oriented&#13;
policies (Korea, Singapore, and Taiwan) and those that newly adopted such&#13;
policies (Chile and Uruguay) during the period under consideration. These&#13;
countries had relatively low incremental capital-output ratios as they&#13;
achieved more efficient resource allocation and more rapid technological&#13;
change than their inward-looking counterparts, such as India.&#13;
The adoption of realistic exchange rates and interest rates also&#13;
contributed to economic growth. Overvalued exchange rates adversely affected&#13;
the growth of exports and output in Colombia, Israel, Mexico and Yugoslavia&#13;
during much of the period under consideration. In turn, negative real&#13;
interest rates appear to have had adverse effects on savings in Argentina,&#13;
Brazil and Israel. Brazil also relied to a considerable extent on foreign&#13;
borrowing, using the proceeds largely to increase consumption and to carry out&#13;
investments in highly capital-intensive industries, whereas Yugoslavia&#13;
utilized the proceeds of foreign borrowing to increase the rate of investment&#13;
although the efficiency of some of these investments is open to doubt. For&#13;
the group as a whole, reliance on foreign borrowing and the rate of economic&#13;
growth are negatively correlated.&#13;
Prepared by:                                          Copyright  c  1980&#13;
Bela Balassa, The Johns Hopkins University           The World Bank&#13;
and the World Bank                                    1818 H Street N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
THE NEWLY-INDUSTRIALIZING DEVELOPING COUNTRIES&#13;
AFTER THE OIL CRISIS&#13;
Bela Balassa&#13;
October 29, 1980&#13;
The author is Professor of Political Economy at the Johns Hopkins&#13;
University and Consultant to the World Bank. He is greatly indebted to Gholam&#13;
H. Azarbayejani for developing the computer program used in the calculations&#13;
to Dominic Li and Robert E. Therriault for data collection and to Robert E.&#13;
Therriault for undertaking the calculations.&#13;
The author bears full responsibility for the opinions expressed in the&#13;
paper; they should not be interpreted to reflect the views of the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Introduction&#13;
In recent years, much attention has been given to the emergence of the&#13;
newly-industrializing countries on the world scene-     The present paper will&#13;
examine the experience of the newly-industrializing developing countries&#13;
during the period following the quadrupling of oil prices in 1973-74 and the&#13;
world recession of 1974-75. It will focus on the policy responses of these&#13;
countries to external shocks and analyze the economic effects of the policies&#13;
applied.&#13;
As an introduction to the discussion, Section I will briefly review the&#13;
incentive policies followed by the newly-industrializing developing countries&#13;
during the 1960-73 period and the effects of these policies on exports and on&#13;
economic growth. Next, the methods employed to estimate the balance-of-&#13;
payments effects of external shocks and of policy responses to these shocks&#13;
will be described (Section II).&#13;
In Section III, estimates will be presented on the balance-of-payments&#13;
effects of external shocks, in the form of the deterioration of the terms of&#13;
trade and the slowdown of world demand for the exports of the newly-&#13;
industrializing developing countries. Section IV will analyze policy&#13;
responses to external shocks in the individual countries, including increased&#13;
reliance on foreign financing, export promotion, import substitution, and&#13;
lowering the rate of economic growth, and provide estimates on the balance-of-&#13;
payments effects of these policies. In the conclusion, the policies followed&#13;
by the newly-industrializing developing countries during the 1973-78 period&#13;
will be evaluated in a comparative framework.&#13;
1/ Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development, The Impact of the&#13;
Newly Industrializing Countries on Production and Trade in Manufactures&#13;
Paris, OECD, 1979.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
I. The Newly-Industrializing Developing Countries&#13;
in the 1960-73 Period&#13;
For purposes of the analysis, the newly-industrializing developing&#13;
countries have been defined to include developing countries that had per&#13;
capita incomes in excess of $1100 in 1978 and where the share of the&#13;
manufacturing sector in the gross domestic product was 20 percent or higher in&#13;
1977.1/ The countries in question are Argentina, Brazil, Chile, Mexico, and&#13;
Uruguay in Latin America; Israel and Yugoslavia in the Europe-Middle East&#13;
area; and Hong Kong, Korea, Singapore, and Taiwan in the Far East.&#13;
With the exception of Hong Kong and Uruguay, these countries were the&#13;
subject of an earlier study by the author of incentive policies, exports, and&#13;
economic performance which dealt with the period preceding the 1973 oil&#13;
crisis.3/. The study also covered Colombia that is on the borderline of&#13;
becoming a newly-industrializing country and India that has an industrial&#13;
sector larger than any developing country other than Brazil and Mexico, which&#13;
co-exists with a very large and backward agricultural sector.&#13;
For comparability with the earlier study, Colombia and India have been&#13;
retained in the present investigation. Also, the earlier study has been&#13;
1/ The data have been derived from the World Bank, World Development Report&#13;
1979 (Washington, D.C., 1979), and World Atlas (Washington, D.C., 1979). --&#13;
The newly-industrializing developing country category overlaps with the upper&#13;
ranges of the group of middle-income countries as defined in the World&#13;
Development Report, that also includes newly-industrializing countries which&#13;
are members of the OECD, the international economic organization of developed&#13;
countries (Greece, Portugal, Spain, and Turkey).&#13;
2/  The findings of the study have been reported in the author's "Export&#13;
Incentives and Export Performance in Developing Countries,"&#13;
Weltwirtschaftliches Archiv 114 (1979), .24-61; "Exports and Economic Growth:&#13;
Further Evidence," Journal of Development Economics, 5 (1978), 181-89; and&#13;
Development Strategies in Semi-industrial Countries, Baltimore, Md., The Johns&#13;
Hopkins University Press, 1981, Chapter 3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3 -&#13;
extended to include Uruguay but not Hong Kong that offers characteristics&#13;
little different from those of Singapore, another city-state.&#13;
Correspondingly, the analysis of the pre-1973 and post-1973 periods in&#13;
this paper will cover altogether twelve countries. In accordance with the&#13;
scheme of classification applied in the earlier study, the countries have been&#13;
divided into four groups on the basis of the policies applied in the period&#13;
preceding the oil crisis.&#13;
The countries of the first group, Korea, Singapore, and Taiwan, adopted&#13;
outward-oriented strategies, providing similar incentives to sales in domestic&#13;
and in foreign markets, after the completion of the first stage of import&#13;
substitution that entailed replacing the imports of nondurable consumer goods&#13;
and their inputs by domestic production. The second group, Argentina, Brazil,&#13;
Colombia, and Mexico, moved to the second stage of import substitution,&#13;
involving the replacement of the .imports of intermediate goods and producer&#13;
and consumer durables by domestic production, but subsequently reformed their&#13;
incentive system by reducing the bias against exports. In turn, the countries&#13;
of the third group, Israel and Yugoslavia, started export promotion at an&#13;
early date but their efforts slackened somewhat afterwards. Finally, India,&#13;
Chile, and Uruguay, classified in the fourth group, continued to pursue&#13;
inward-oriented strategies throughout the period preceding the 1973 oil&#13;
crisis.&#13;
Incentives and Export Performance&#13;
The first group of Far Eastern countries established a free trade regime&#13;
for exports and their domestic inputs. Some additional subsidies were also&#13;
provided, equalizing the treatment of exports and import substitution in the&#13;
manufacturing sector, without introducing substantial interindustry&#13;
differences in export incentives. At the same time, there was little&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
discrimination against primary activities;- incentives were granted by-and-&#13;
large automatically; realistic exchange rates were established; and stability&#13;
in the system of incentives was ensured over time.&#13;
The early application of outward-oriented policies explains that, in the&#13;
1960-66 period, the countries of the first group experienced more rapid&#13;
increases in manufactured exports than any of the other nine countries and had&#13;
the highest share of exports in manufacturing output. They also showed the&#13;
best export performance in the 1966-73 period, when their export promotion&#13;
efforts intensified. Increases in manufactured exports were accompanied by&#13;
the rapid growth of primary exports, again surpassing all the other countries&#13;
under consideration in 1960-66 as well as in 1966-73.&#13;
Unlike the first group, the second group of countries began their export-,&#13;
promoting efforts after having embarked on second-stage import substitution.&#13;
They also differed from the first group in that, with few exceptions, the use&#13;
of imported inputs in export production was limited to cases when comparable&#13;
domestic products were not available.   To compensate exporters for the&#13;
resulting high costs, and for the effects of continued import protection on&#13;
the exchange rate, the countries of the second group provided subsidies to&#13;
nontraditional exports. Export subsidies lessened, but did not eliminate, the&#13;
bias against exports, which remained particularly pronounced in the case of&#13;
traditional primary products. And, while the adoption of the crawling peg&#13;
imparted considerable stability to the system of incentives, incentives to&#13;
value added continued to vary greatly among industries and several of the&#13;
incentive measures were subject to discretionary decision making:&#13;
Within this group of Latin American countries, in the 1966-73 period&#13;
manufactured export growth rates were the highest in Argentina and Brazil that&#13;
introduced considerable export incentives in the mid-sixties. As a result,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
between 1966 and 1973, the share of exports in manufactured output rose from'&#13;
0.9 percent to 3.6 percent in Argentina and from 1.3 percent to 4.4 percent in&#13;
Brazil. Nevertheless, this share remained substantially lower than in the&#13;
countries of the-first group; in 1973, Korea exported 40.5 percent, Singapore&#13;
42.6 percent, and Taiwan 49.9 percent of its manufacturing output.&#13;
Having extended to a considerable extent the scope of export-promoting&#13;
measures in the mid-sixties, Colombia increased the share of exports in its&#13;
manufacturing output from 3.0 percent in 1966 to 7.5 percent in 1973. The&#13;
corresponding figures were 2.9 percent and 4.4 percent in Mexico that&#13;
benefited from the proximity of the United States but, apart from the&#13;
establishment of a free trade zone in the border area, did not provide export&#13;
incentives until early 1971.&#13;
With continued discrimination against traditional primary exports, the&#13;
four Latin American countries saw their world market shares'dwindle in&#13;
practically all of these commodities. Three of these countries, Argentina,&#13;
Brazil,, and Colombia, however, experienced gains in nontraditional primary&#13;
exports that benefited from export subsidies, thereby raising the rate of&#13;
growth of primary exports after 1966.&#13;
As a result of their early export promotion efforts, Israel and&#13;
Yugoslavia surpassed the second group of countries, while falling behind the&#13;
first, in terms of the share of exports in manufacturing output in 1966. But,&#13;
as their export promotion efforts slackened, this share increased relatively&#13;
little, from 12.8 percent to 14.1 percent in Israel and from 13.8 percent to&#13;
16.9 percent in Yugoslavia, between 1966 and 1973. In the same period,'the&#13;
share of exports in the'increment of manufacturing output declined in Israel&#13;
and hardly changed in Yugoslavia, Israel, however, gained in both traditional&#13;
and nontraditional primary exports which suffered little discrimination while&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6-&#13;
smaller increases were observed in Yugoslavia where a bias against primary&#13;
exports existed.&#13;
The fourth group of countries continued to apply an inward-oriented&#13;
strategy, entailing considerable discrimination against primary as well as&#13;
manufactured exports, during the period under consideration. As a result, they&#13;
lost market shares in traditional primary exports, did poorly in&#13;
nontraditional primary exports, and also suffered losses of market shares in&#13;
manufactured exports. India's share in the combined exports of manufactured&#13;
goods of the twelve countries under consideration decreased from 50.4 percent&#13;
in 1960 to 31.0 percent in 1966 and to 10.7 percent in 1973; Chile s share&#13;
declined from 1.9 percent to 1.5 percent and, again, to 0.5 percent; while&#13;
Uruguay's share never reached 0.5 percent. of the total.&#13;
Exports and the Growth of Output&#13;
Exportation provides advantages over import substitution by contributing&#13;
to resource allocation according to comparative advantage, greater capacity&#13;
utilization, the exploitation of economies of scale, and improvements in&#13;
technology stimulated by competition in foreign markets. To the extent that&#13;
exports give rise to more rapid increases in output than import substitution,&#13;
the indirect effects of export growth, too, will be larger in countries where&#13;
resources are not fully utilized.&#13;
These considerations explain that exports and output are highly&#13;
correlated in an intercountry context. In the 1960-73 period, the Spearman&#13;
rank correlation coefficient between the growth of exports and that of output&#13;
was 0.67 for agriculture, 0.71 for manufacturing, and 0.89 for the national&#13;
economy taken as a whole. In the same period, the coefficients obtained in&#13;
correlating exports with output net of exports were 0.74 in the case of&#13;
manufacturing and 0.77 for the gross national product, presumably reflecting&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
the indirect effects of exportsi/&#13;
Alternatively, one may introduce exports, in addition to labor and&#13;
(domestic and foreign) capital, as an explanatory variable in a regression&#13;
equation designed to explain intercountry differences in GNP growth rates. The&#13;
inclusion of exports in such a production function-type relationship reflects&#13;
the assumption that outward-orientation enhances the productivity of labor and&#13;
capital. In estimates made by pooling data for the 1960-66 and 1966-73&#13;
periods that were available for ten out of the twelve countries (excepting&#13;
Singapore and Uruguay), adding the export variable to the regression equation&#13;
raised the coefficient of determination from 0.58 to 0.77. The export&#13;
variable was significant at the 1 percent level; all other variabies (labor,&#13;
domestic capital and foreign capital) were significant at the 5 percent level.&#13;
At the same time, the method applied tends to underestimate the effects&#13;
of export growth on the growth of output by failing to account for the impact&#13;
of exports on other variables in the equation. Yet, there is evidence that&#13;
exports and domestic savings are positively correlated. Also, the improved&#13;
balance-of-payments situation attendant on the expansion of exports increases&#13;
the attractiveness of the country concerned for foreign capital.&#13;
II. Estimating the Balance-of-Payments Effects of External&#13;
Shocks and of Policy Responses to these Shocks&#13;
The Analytical Framework&#13;
The world economic situation changed with the quadrupling of oil prices&#13;
in 1973-74 and the world recession of 1974-75. In examining the policy&#13;
1/ All coefficients are significant at the one percent level. Results&#13;
obtained by the use of alternative methods and for the subperiods 1960-65 and&#13;
1966-73 are reported in the publications cited above. Correlations for output&#13;
net of exports have not been calculated in the case of agriculture. All the&#13;
calculations exclude Uruguay.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
responses of the newly-industrializing developing countries to these external&#13;
shocks, the following analysis will consider reliance on foreign financing and&#13;
the use of macroeconomic policy measures aimed at reducing the rate of&#13;
economic growth, together with incentives to exports and to import&#13;
substitution.&#13;
The balance-of-payments effects of external shocks in the form of the&#13;
deterioration of the terms of trade and the slowdown of world demand for the&#13;
exports of the newly-industrializing developing countries will be estimated by&#13;
postulating a situation that would have obtained in the absence of external&#13;
shocks. The same procedure will be applied in estimating the effects of&#13;
policy responses to external shocks.&#13;
In developing the analytical framework, designed to estimate the effects&#13;
of external shocks, and of policy responses to these shocks, the point of&#13;
departure is the balance-of-payments identity. This is defined in terms of&#13;
the resource gap that equals the deficit in merchandise trade, non-factor&#13;
services and private transfers combined; the resource gap is financed by the&#13;
net flow of external financing.&#13;
The resource gap is shown in equations (1) and (2) for years 0 and 1,&#13;
respectively. In the equations, M and X denote merchandise imports and&#13;
exports valued in base year (0) prices; p01m and p01X represent percentage&#13;
changes in import and export prices between years 0 and 1; and S and R refer&#13;
to the balance of non-factor services and private transfers and to the&#13;
resource gap, respectively, valued in terms of current prices.&#13;
(1)       Ro = MO - XO      SO&#13;
(2)       R1 = Ml(1+POl m) - Xl(l+POx) - Si&#13;
it Taking the difference between equations (2) and (1) and rearranging&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
terms, we express changes in the resource gap between years 0 and 1 in&#13;
equation (3) in terms of changes in import and export prices for the volume of&#13;
imports and exports in period 1 (p 1    m  _ p     x X1); changes in the volume of&#13;
imports (M1 - MO); changes in the volume of exports (X1 - XO); and changes in&#13;
the balance of non-factor services and private transfers (SI-so)-.&#13;
(3)    R1-RO = (PolM1 - Pol x X1) + (Ml-MO) - (X1-XO) - (SI-SO)&#13;
Equation (3) is modified if we examine the effects of policy actions&#13;
taken at home and abroad. As a first step, we introduce hypothetical exports&#13;
(X1h) that would be reached if the country in question maintained its base-&#13;
period share in world markets. Now, differences between actual and&#13;
hypothetical exports (X1 - X h), shown on the left-hand side of equation (4),&#13;
are taken to have resulted from domestic policy actions'as'regards exports.&#13;
(4)     (Ro-R0) + (XX1h h     (P0  M1 - P1 xX1) + (M -MO) - (X h-X0) - (SI-So)&#13;
Next, we introduce the effects of changes in foreign demand.      For this&#13;
purpose, we calculate the trend value of exports (X t) on the assumptions that&#13;
the trend of foreign export demand remained the same as in the base period and&#13;
that the country under consideration maintained its export share unchanged.&#13;
The difference between trend and hypothetical values (X t - X h),. shown on the'&#13;
.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~                                 1&#13;
right-hand side of equation (5), thus represents the effects of the external&#13;
shock due to changes in foreign demand for the country's export products.&#13;
(Since this export shortfall adds to the deficit, it is shown with a positive&#13;
sign.)&#13;
(5)    (R1-RO) + (Xi-Xi h     (POM1 - P       Xxl) + (X t_X h)&#13;
+ (Mg-MO) - (X1t-Xo)     (S- So)&#13;
In turn, hypothetical imports (M h) are calculated for the actual growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
rate of GNP in the country concerned on the assumption that the income&#13;
elasticity of import demand remained the same as in the base period.&#13;
Differences between hypothetical imports (Mlh) and actual imports (M1), shown&#13;
on the left-hand side of equation (6), are taken to reflect the effects of&#13;
import-substituting policies.&#13;
(6)    (R1-RO) + (Xi-xih) + (Mlh_M) = (polmM     - POQXXl)&#13;
+ (X t_X h) + (Mh_-MO) - (X t-Xo) - (Sl-So)&#13;
Furthermore, we calculate the trend value of imports on the assumptions&#13;
that the income elasticity of import demand and the rate of growth of GNP&#13;
remained the same as in the base period (i.e. no change in the rate of growth&#13;
of imports).   Differences between the trend value of imports and hypothetical&#13;
imports (M t - M h), shown on the left-hand side of equation (7), are assumed&#13;
to reflect the effects of changes in the rate of growth of GNP on imports.&#13;
(7)    (R1-RO) + (XI-Xih) + (Mlh_Md) + (Mt-Mh) = (polmM       - PO1XXl)&#13;
+ (X.t-X h) + (M t_MO) - (Xlt-Xo) - (SlSo).&#13;
The difference between the trend values for imports and exports, adjusted&#13;
for the actual balance of nonfactor services and private transfers, equals the&#13;
amount of net external financing that would have been necessary in the absence&#13;
of external shocks and policy reactions to these shocks (the trend value of&#13;
the resource gap, R t).   In turn, the sum of the differences between trend&#13;
values and actual values of imports and exports equals the difference between&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
the trend value of the resource gap and its actual value in the base year.&#13;
Introducing the trend value of the resource gap and rearranging terms, we&#13;
show the excess of the actual resource gap over its trend value on the left-&#13;
hand side of equation (8). This is taken to represent the additional inflow&#13;
of external funds associated with the balance-of-payments effects of external&#13;
shocks (additional net external financing).&#13;
(8)    (R -R t) + (X -X h) + (M h-Ml) + (M t-M1 )&#13;
= (P mM..P    xX) + cx1t_X h) + (MOt M) - (Xlt-Xo) - (SI-So) - (R1t-R0)&#13;
The last term on the right-hand side of equation (8) equals the sum of&#13;
the previous three terms and indicates the amount of additional net external&#13;
financing that would have been necessary in the absence of external shocks if&#13;
past trends continued, over and above the inflow of external funds in the base&#13;
year. The term is shown with a negative sign, so that the last four terms add&#13;
up to zero and can be omitted.&#13;
Under the assumption that the country in question is a price-taker in&#13;
world markets, the right-hand side of equation (8) is taken to indicate the&#13;
effects of external shocks on the balance of payments.     This is decomposed&#13;
into effects on the terms of trade (Po01M1-P01Xl) and on export volume (X t-&#13;
x h). The former is further decomposed into a pure terms of trade effect&#13;
calculated on the assumption of balanced trade in base year prices, (p01m&#13;
p01x) X1, and the effects of increased import prices on unbalanced trade,&#13;
(Ml-X1) Polm-&#13;
In turn, the left-hand side of equation (8) consists of terms&#13;
representing policy   responses to external shocks, including additional net&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
external financing (R1 - RIt), increases in the country's export. share in&#13;
world markets (X -X h), import substitution (M h - M1), and the effects of&#13;
lower GNP growth rates on the country's imports (M t - M h).&#13;
In the case of manufactured exports, the effects of lower growth rates of&#13;
GNP abroad and the effects of changes in the foreign income elasticity of&#13;
demand for these exports have further been distinguished. This has involved&#13;
calculating the constant-income-elasticity exports of manufactured goods from&#13;
developing countries to developed countries, developing countries, and&#13;
centrally planned economies that would have been obtained if the income&#13;
elasticities of import demand in in the base period were combined with the&#13;
actual GNP growth rates (Xmlc).&#13;
Assuming further that the country in question maintained its share in the&#13;
manufactured exports of the developing countries unchanged, the difference&#13;
between the trend value of manufactured exports-and the constant-income-&#13;
elasticity exports of manufactured goods (Xml - Xmlc) is taken to reflect the&#13;
effects of changes in GNP growth rates abroad. In turn, the difference&#13;
between constant-income-elasticity exports and hypothetical exports (Xmlc _&#13;
Xmlh) represents the effects of changes in foreign income elasticities of&#13;
demand for the manufactured exports of the developing countries. Again, a&#13;
positive sign denotes an export shortfall.&#13;
Estimating the Effects of External Shocks&#13;
In the practical application of the analytical framework, the average for&#13;
the years 1971-73 has been taken as the basis for;estimating terms of trade&#13;
effects. It may be objected that, due to the effects of the world boom of&#13;
1972-73, the terms of trade of the developing countries were particularly&#13;
favorable in 1971-73. However, the differences as compared to the nineteen-&#13;
sixties are small, and the terms of trade of the developing countries in 1971-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13&#13;
73 were in fact slightly less favorable than in the nineteen-sixties!/ if we&#13;
exclude fuel, the price of which started to rise in late 1973.&#13;
Changes in the terms of trade as compared to the 1971-73 base period have&#13;
been attributed to external shocks. The underlying assumption is that the&#13;
country in question is a price-taker in world markets. Such an assumption&#13;
applies grosso modo to the principal exports of the countries under study, the&#13;
principal exception being coffee in Brazil and in Colombia. Nevertheless, in&#13;
the absence of the explicit modelling of the world coffee market, the&#13;
assumption has been retained in this case also.&#13;
Terms of trade effects have been decomposed into a pure terms of trade&#13;
effect, calculated on the assumption of balanced trade in terms of "1972"&#13;
prices, and the effects of the rise in import prices on unbalanced trade (the&#13;
deficit or surplus in the balance of merchandise trade) expressed in "1972'&#13;
prices. In the event of unbalanced trade, then, the expressed terms of trade&#13;
effects include the impact of increases in import prices on the trade deficit&#13;
(surplus). This estimate reflects the assumption that, in the absence of&#13;
external shocks, import prices would have remained unchanged during the period&#13;
under consideration. The assumption of unchanged import prices has the&#13;
following rationale.&#13;
While primary product prices were rising rapidly during the 1971-73 world&#13;
boom, historical experience indicates that such price increases were followed&#13;
by a decline or, at the least, by a flat price trend. Primary product prices,&#13;
in turn, influence the prices of manufactured goods and it may not be&#13;
1/ The index numbers reported in United Nations, Monthly Bulletin of&#13;
Statistics (December 1971 and June 1977) are 103 including, and 93 excluding,&#13;
fuels in 1971-73 on a 1970 basis; the comparable averages for the 1961-70&#13;
period are 101 and 98 respectively.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
unreasonable to assume that the world economy would have experienced a return&#13;
to the noninflationary situation of the nineteen-sixties if the quadrupling of&#13;
petroleum prices did not occur. At any rate, the rapid rise in petroleum&#13;
prices accounts for a substantial part of the increase in import prices during&#13;
this period.&#13;
In order to indicate the impact of the quadrupling of petroleum prices on&#13;
the terms of trade, the balance of payments effects of changes in the prices&#13;
of fuel and nonfuel imports are separately shown. On the export side,&#13;
distinction has been made between traditional primary exportsl/, taken&#13;
individually, fuels, nontraditional primary exports other than fuels, and&#13;
manufactured goods.&#13;
The trend value of exports that would have occurred in the absence of&#13;
external shocks has been estimated on the assumptions that the world exports&#13;
of the country's traditional primary export products, taken individually, and&#13;
the developing countries   exports of fuels, nontraditional primary products&#13;
other than fuels, and manufactured goods grew at the same rate as in the 1963-&#13;
73 period and that the country concerned maintained its "1972" market share in&#13;
these exports. The underlying assumption is that a developing country&#13;
competes against all suppliers in the world market for its traditional primary&#13;
exports while its nontraditional exports compete against those of other&#13;
developing countries.&#13;
The effects of changes in foreign demand in the country.s exports have&#13;
been derived as the difference between trend and hypothetical values of&#13;
1/ Traditional exports have been defined to include commodities that&#13;
accounted for at least 1.5 percent of the country's merchandise exports in the&#13;
years 1971-73, on the average. Manufactured goods have been defined as SITC&#13;
tcategories 5 to 8 less 68; fuels as SITC category 3; nontraditional primary&#13;
'exports other than fuels include the remainder.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
exports, both expressed in "1972" prices. Hypothetical exports have been&#13;
estimated on the assumptions that the country's exports of traditional primary&#13;
products rose at the same rate as world exports and that its exports of fuels,&#13;
nontraditional primary products other than fuels, and manufactured goods&#13;
increased at the same rate as developing country exports, from a "1972"&#13;
basis. It thus again reflects the assumption that the country maintained its&#13;
"1972" market share during the period under consideration.&#13;
Estimating the Effects of Policy Responses to External Shocks&#13;
Among policy measures taken in response to external shocks, the amount of&#13;
additional net external financing has been estimated as the difference between&#13;
the actual resource gap or net external financing and the trend value of the&#13;
resource gap. The latter has been calculated on the assumption that the&#13;
country's imports and exports, expressed in "1972" prices, rose at the same&#13;
rate as in the 1963-73 period, taking further the actual net balance of&#13;
nonfactor services and private transfers as a datum. In turn, total external&#13;
financing has been defined as the sum of actual net external financing,&#13;
interest payments, and dividends.&#13;
The effects of export promotion have been represented by increases&#13;
(decreases) in exports, expressed in "1972" prices, that.were associated with&#13;
changes in the country's "1972" market shares. Separate calculations have&#13;
been made for traditional primary products, taken individually, fuels,&#13;
nontraditional primary products other than fuels, and manufactured goods.&#13;
Import substitution has been defined as savings in imports associated&#13;
with a decrease in the country's income elasticity of import demand as&#13;
compared to the 1963-73 period, again expressed in "1972" prices. Separate&#13;
calculations have been made for fuel and for nonfuel imports.&#13;
The effects on imports of lower economic growth rates in the country&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
concerned have been derived by applying income elasticities of import demand&#13;
for the 1963-73 period to GNP growth rates observed in the 1963-73 period and&#13;
to actual GNP growth rates during the period under consideration. Again,&#13;
separate calculations have been made for fuel and for nonfuel imports.&#13;
It should be noted, however, that changes in export market shares and in&#13;
the rate of economic growth may have been due to circumstances outside the&#13;
country's control. A decrease (increase) in the country's export market share&#13;
may have occurred because of an acceleration (deceleration) of the growth of&#13;
exports by competing suppliers.    In turn, a fall in foreign demand for the&#13;
country's export products may have contributed to a decline in its rate of&#13;
economic growth.&#13;
Changes in export market shares, in import demand, and in the rate of&#13;
economic growth may also have been due to internal events. In particular,&#13;
domestic policy changes may have occurred independently of external shocks and&#13;
may themselves constitute an "internal" shock. The methodology applied does&#13;
not permit separating the balance-of-payments effects of policy changes taken&#13;
in response to external shocks from the effects of autonomous domestic policy&#13;
changes; such distinctions become a matter of interpretation.&#13;
The estimates reported in this paper have been made for the years 1974 to&#13;
1978, taken individually.-     Averages for the 1974-78 period are also shown.&#13;
This permits considering changes over time and indicating the results for the&#13;
entire period.&#13;
III. The Balance-of-Payments Effects of External Shocks&#13;
This section will present empirical evidence'on the balance-of-payments&#13;
1/ Estimates of balance-of-payments effects p.ertaining to individual years&#13;
are shown on a "1972" basis. Changes between individual years can be derived&#13;
as the difference between the reported estimates for consecutive years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
impact of external shocks, in the form of terms of trade effects and export&#13;
volume effects, in the twelve newly-industrializing developing countries.&#13;
Under each heading, the discussion will proceed by separating countries into&#13;
four groups according to the scheme of classification described in Section I.&#13;
This will be followed by an comparative analysis of the relative importance of&#13;
the sources of external shocks in the twelve countries.-&#13;
Table lA. reports the estimated terms of trade effects and export volume&#13;
effects on the balance of payments of the newly-industrializing developing&#13;
countries; more detailed results are shown in Appendix Table 1 for the years&#13;
1974 to 1978, on the average.   Table lB relates terms of trade effects to the&#13;
average of exports and imports (average trade) and to the gross national&#13;
product, and export volume effects to exports and to the gross national&#13;
product,-all expressed in 1972" prices. Export volume effects are shown in a&#13;
four commodity group breakdown in Appendix Table 2.1/&#13;
Terms of Trade Effects&#13;
Among the first group of Far Eastern countries, Korea suffered the&#13;
largest terms of trade loss in 1974, equivalent to one-half of the average&#13;
value of its exports and imports. The quadrupling of petroleum prices&#13;
accounted for two-thirds of this loss.   Higher petroleum prices adversely&#13;
affected also Taiwan, where the terms of trade loss equalled one-third of the&#13;
average value of trade in 1974.&#13;
1/ More detailed estimates of the balance-of-payments effects of external&#13;
shocks, and of policy responses to external shock s in three Latin American&#13;
countries (Brazil, Mexico, and Uruguay) are contained in the author's "Policy&#13;
Responses to,External Shocks in Selected Latin American Countries," paper&#13;
presented at the NBER/FIPE/BE,BR Conference on Trade Prospects Among the&#13;
Americas: Latin American Export Diversification and the New Protectionism,&#13;
held in Sao Paulo, Brazil on March 24-26, 1980. Detailed results for the&#13;
other nine countries covered in the paper are available from the author.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE IA&#13;
BALANCE OF PAYMENTS EFFECTS OF EXTERNAL SHOCKS AND OF FOLICY RESPONSES TO THESE SHOCKS&#13;
($ millions)&#13;
Average                                                   Average                                                  Average&#13;
1974     1975     1976     1977    1978     1974-78      1974     1975     1976     1977     1978     1974-78      1974    1975     1976     1977     1978     1974-78&#13;
BALANCE OF FAYMENTS EFFECTS&#13;
A R GEN T INA                                                B R A ZIL                                                  CH IL E&#13;
I.  External Shockcs&#13;
(1)  Terms of Trade Effects                -180     ot622     194      193    -524       61         3143     3306     2635      805     1977     2373           45     710      478      932     1130      659&#13;
(2)  Export Volume Effects                    18      113     -59       38      54       33           168     529      341      787      793      523            52     87       74       98      175       76&#13;
(3)  Together-11                                      75       15      21      40        94         3311     3835     2976     19        70      29                     9        5       00      10         3&#13;
II. PolicyjResponses&#13;
(4)  Additional Net External Financing       156    1523     -241     -732   -1680     -195         4568     2749      823    -2327    -1857      791         -563     225     -430       50      505      -43&#13;
(5)  Increase in Export Market Share       -209     -739     -386      565     327      -89           108     793      341      524      445      442          288     249      447      462      538      397&#13;
(6)  import Substitution                      90       32     710      350     631      363         -742      625     2335     3491     3945     1941          202      18      218      248       84      154&#13;
(7)  Effects of Lower GDP Growth Rate      -198       481       52      49     252       15         -624     -381     -524      -95      237     -278            66    309      318      270      177      227&#13;
(8)  Together                               -11       75       15      21     -7          4         31        85      27        52      27        897            -7    79       552     1030     130       735&#13;
CO0LO0M BI A                                                M E X ICO                                                UR UG UA Y&#13;
I.  External Shocks&#13;
(1)  Terms of Trade Effects                  47       159    -139     -710    -511     -231           662    1073      525     -114       90      447          117     183      176      213      176      173&#13;
(2)  Export Volume Effects                    62j    101       02      230     205      136           925     247      -17-9    363      402      257           31      31       10       11     ..Jj     320&#13;
(3)  Together                               .109     260      -58     -479    -306      -95           758    1320      704      249      492      705          148,    214      186      224      194      193&#13;
II. policy Responses&#13;
(4)  Additional Net External Financing      213      108        93    -227     122       62         1979     2508     1533      336      856     1442          121     196       71      161      135      137&#13;
(5)   Increase in Export Market Share         39      110    -126     -118       4      -18           -93    -235     -507     -301      148     -198           11      48      124       81       86       70&#13;
(6)   Import Substitution                   -133      46      -23     -134    -417     -132        -1136    -1031     -533      -80     -813     -719            17    -18        8       11       16        7&#13;
(7)  Effects of Lower GDP Growth Rate       -10        4       -1       -1     -15       -6             8      78      211      293      302      178           -1     -11      -17      -29      -43      -20&#13;
(8)  Together                                109     260      -58     -79     -06       -95           75     F32       70       24       49       7518                 24       16       24       14       13&#13;
I N DIA                                                I SR A EL                                             YU GO SLAV IA&#13;
I.  Efternal Shocks&#13;
(1)  Terms of Trade Effects                1116     1919      872      396     962     1053         1054     1079      745      757     1116      950         1653    2009     1479     2387     2159     2009&#13;
(2)  Export Volume Effects                 3....4    342      322              85.2  22  42922         12     217      119      318      409      215          134     443      608      800     1247      646&#13;
(3)  Together                              1150     2260     1194      991    1815     1482         1066     1296      864     1075     1525     1165         1787    2452     2087     3187     3765     2665&#13;
II. Policy Resoonses&#13;
(4)  Additional Net External Financing 1587         2529      994     1723     3128    1992         1209       952     362      338      459      664         2044    1817      518     1979     2072     1686&#13;
(5)   Increase in Export Market Share      -328       -79        1    -362     -677    -289         -278     -206     -321     -205     -161     -234         -321     -28        73    -580     -440     -259&#13;
(6)   Import Substitution                   -173     -165     202     -302     -546    -197            49      282     287        86     180      177          -216    -28      573      933     1166      486&#13;
(7)  Effects of Lower GOP Growth Rate         63      -25       -3     -68      -91     -25            87     267      535.     856     1047      558          279     691      923      855      968      743&#13;
(8)  Together                              1150     2260     1194      991     1815    1482         1066     1296      864     1075     1525     1165         1787    2452     2087     3187     3765     2655&#13;
KOR E A                                              S I N GA PO0RE                                               TAI WA N&#13;
I.  External Shocks&#13;
(1)  Terms of Trade Effects                1712     1806     1203      623    1247     1318          678      911      602      433      997      724         1208     836      191      -72     -348      363&#13;
(2)  Export Volume Effects                   45      493      254      673     791      451             3     297      163      398      557      284          -14     581      237      813      992      522&#13;
(3)  Together                              1757     2299     1456     1296    208       769           681    1208      76       83      154       08194                46       42       72       64       85&#13;
(4)  Additional Net External Financing      486     -296    -2141    -3291   -2906    -1630         1011     1042      587      139      630      682         1556     520     -987    -1499    -2955     -673&#13;
(5)   increase in Export Market Share       445       934    1658     2211    2625     1575           211      -15       4      300      636      227         -343    -302      243      199      666       93&#13;
(6)  Import Substitution                     795    1412     2272     3395    4082     2391         -742     -193     -402     -304     -524     -433         -509     107       -7      523     1432      309&#13;
(7)  Effects of Lower GDP Growth Rate         31     248     -333    -1019   -1762     -567           202     374      576      697      812      532          491    1093     1179     1520     1501     1157&#13;
(8)  Together        1757     2299     1456     1296    2038     1769~~~~~~-T   6C81   1208     7T65-    8-32     1554     1008         1194    1416      428      742      644      885&#13;
Sources: See Appendix Table 1&#13;
Gross National Product - World Bank date bank.&#13;
Note: Numbers may not add up due to rounding.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE lB&#13;
BALANCE OP PATYENS TO EFFECTS OP EXTERNAL SHOCKS AND OP POLICY RESPONSES TO THESE SHDCKS&#13;
(per cent)&#13;
1974    1975    1976     1977   1978    1974-78     1974    1975     1976    1977    1978    1974-78     1974   1975     1976    1977    1978    1974-78&#13;
A R GE NT INA                                         B R A ZIL                                            C HIL E&#13;
(13)  Taco  of Trade Effects/Average     -7.7     29.1     9.0     6.6  -19.3.      2.5       49.0    52.2    43.2    13.6    31.3      38.2        3.9   65.2    41.6    76.6     80.0     54.8&#13;
Trade&#13;
(14)  Termss of Trade Effects/OFF         -0.4     1.3     0.4     0.4    -1.1      0.1        3.3     3.3     2.4     0.7      1.7      2.2        0.5    8.6     5.5     10.0    11.0      7.2&#13;
(15)  Export Volneo, Effects/Exports       0.8     5.7    -2.2     -1.0    1.4      1.1        3.4     9.6     6.1    13.7     13.0      9.4       -3.6    6.5     4.6      5.9    10.1      4.9&#13;
(16)  Export Voi1-  Effects/ONP            0.0     0.2    -0.1     0.1    0.1       0.1        0.2     0.5     0.3     0.7      0.7      0.5       -0.5    1.0     0.9      1.0     1.7      0.8&#13;
(17)  Externa  Shocka/GNP                 -0.3     1.5     0.3     0.5    -1.0      0.2        3.5     3.9     2.8     1.4      2.3      2.7       -0.1    9.6     6.4     11.0    12.7      8.0&#13;
II.  policy Responses      &#13;
(18)  NetExternal Financtig/AveraEe        6.7    71.2   -51.3   -25.1  -61.9      -8.0       71.3    43.4    13.5   -39.3    -29.4     12.7      -49.0   20.7   -37.5     4.1     35.7     -3.6&#13;
Trade&#13;
(19)  Net External Fiosnclng/GNP           0.3     3.2    -0.5    -1.5    -3.5     -0.4        4.8     2.8     0.8     -2.1    -1.6      0.7       -6.0    2.7    -5.0      5.0     4.9     -0.5&#13;
(20)  Increase Is Export Shares/Export    -8.7   -37.8   -14.4    15.1     8.8     -3.0        2.2    14.4     6.1     9.1      7.3      7.9       19.8   18.7    27.9     27.9    31.3     25.5&#13;
(21)  Ioport Substitotion/Ioports          4.0     1.4    44.2    16.9    37.2     18.2       -9.3     9.5    35.5    57.3     60.4     28.3       24.0    2.1    31.4    31.9      7.6     18.1&#13;
(22)  Lover OFF Growth Effects/Isports    -8.7    -3.5     3.2     2.4    14.9      0.7       -7.9    -5.3    -8.0    -1.6      3.6     -4.0        7.9   36.1    45.7    34.7     16.1     26.7&#13;
COLOM BI A                                            M EX ICO                                            IROG UA Y&#13;
I. External Shocks&#13;
(13)  Term,s of Trada Effects/Average      4.4    15.5   -14.0   -69.1  -39.2     -21.3       21.5    35.6     18.9   -4.2     2.6      14.8       48.2   62.6    51.8    64.1     51.0     55.7&#13;
Trade&#13;
(14)  Terms, of Trade Effects/OHP          0.4     1.2    -1.0    -5.1   -3.4      -1.7        1.3     2.0      1.0   -0.2     0.1       0.8        3.9    5.9     5.6     6.5      5.2      5.4&#13;
(15)  Export Vol,sem Effects/Exports       6.2     9.3     8.7    26.2   18.4      13.5        5.3    14.6     10.6   18.9     15.5     13.3       12.6   10.5     2.5     2.9      4.6      5.9&#13;
(16)  Export Volom  Effecta/CNP            0.5     0.8     0.6      1.6    1.3      1.0        0.2     0.5      0.3    0.6      0.7      0.5        1.1    1.0     0.3     0.3      0.5      0.6&#13;
(17)  Exteral Shocks/OFP                   0.9     2.0    -0.4    -3.5   -2.0      -0.7        1.4     2.4      1.3    0.4      0.8      1.3        5.0    6.9     5.9     6.8      5.7      6.1&#13;
II.  Policy Respoonses&#13;
(18)  Net Externa  Financ.ing/Average     20.1    10.5     9.4   -22.1    9.3      5.7        64.3    83.3     55.2   12.4    24.4     47.8        30.0   66.9    21.0    48.4    39.0      44.0&#13;
Trdae&#13;
(19)  Net External Pin...clig/ONP          1.7     0.9     0.7    -1.6     0.8      0.5        3.8     4.6      2.8    0.6      1.4      2.6        4.1    6.3     2.2     4.9      3.9      4.3&#13;
(20)  Incease In Export Shars/Export       3.9    10.1   -13.4   -13.4    0.4     -1.8        -5.2   -13.9    -30.2  -15.6     5.7     -10.2        4.3   16.2    30.4    21.5    22.0      20.4&#13;
(21)  Import Ssbstitation/Imports        -11.8     4.8    -2.2   -11.4  -28.0     -11.4      -26.1   -23.8    -13.8   -2.3   -18.4    -17.5         7.1   -6.4     2.8     3.7      5.4      2.4&#13;
(22)  Lover ONP Growh Rffects/Inports     -0.9    -0.4    -0.1    -0.1   -1.0      -0.5        0.2     1.8      5.5    8.3     6.8      4.4        -0.3   -3.9    -6.2   -10.1    -14.1     -7.3 &#13;
I N DIA                                            I SR AE L                                       Y UGOS L A VI A&#13;
I. External Shocks&#13;
(13)  Term  of Trade Effects/Averaga      40.9    65.5    29.1    12.6    29.0     34.7       55.1    57.6     37.4   34.7    47.7      46.1       47.4   56.1    41.3    68.0     67.3     56.1&#13;
Trade&#13;
(14)  Term,s of Trade Effects/GNP          1.8     2.8     1.3     0.5     1.2      1.9       11.1    11.0      7.7    7.8     11.0      9.7        5.3    6.4     4.5     6.7      6.7      5.9&#13;
(15)  Export Vol1-  Effects/Exports        1.3    11.7     9.5    18.7    27.6     14.1        0.9    16.7      7.9   19.0     21.2     14.1        5.5   16.0    19.7     30.0    43.8     23.4&#13;
(16)  Export Volmn  Effects/CNP            0.1     0.5     0.5     0.8     1.1      0.6        0.1     2.2      1.2    3.3     4.0       2.2        0.4    1.4     1.8     2.2      3.3      1.9&#13;
(17)  External1 Shock./GNP                 1.9     3.3     1.7     1.3     2.3      2.1       11.2    13.2      8.9   11.1     15.0     11.9        5.7    7.8     6.3     8.9     10.0      7.8&#13;
II.  Policy Resoosnes                                                                                                                                                                                  -t&#13;
(18)  Net External Fi-naning/Average      58.1    86.3    33.2    53.8    94.3     65.6       63.2    50.9     18.2   15.5     19.6     32.2       58.6   50.7    14.5    56.4     55.4     47.1&#13;
Trade&#13;
(19)  Net Externl Pinan..ing/GNP           2.6     3.7     1.4     2.3     4.0      2.8       12.7     9.7      3.7    3.5     4.5       6.8        6.5    5.7     1.6      5.6     5.5      5.0&#13;
(20)  Increase In Export Shares/Export   -12.3    -2.7     0.0   -11.4   -21.9     -9.5      -22.6   -15.9    -21.4  -12.2     -8.4    -15.3      -13.1   -1.0     2.4   -21.8    -15.5     -9.4&#13;
(21)  Import Subntitmtion/Imports         -6.2    -5.6     7.8    -9.1   -15.4    -6.5         1.9    11.5     11.6    3.2     6.5       6.8       -4.8   -0.6    14.1    21.4     25.1     11.0&#13;
(22)  1.oer 0CNF Growth Effects/Imports    2.3    -0.9    -0.1    -2.1    -2.6     -0.8        3.3    10.9     21.6   31.9    38.0      21.6        6.2   15.7    22.6    19.6     20.9     16.9&#13;
I.  External Shocks&#13;
(13)  Term  of Trade Effects/Average      51.8    50.6    25.6    11.3    18.4     27.6       16.8    23.5     13.8    9.2     18.6     16.1       31.9   23.4     4.0    -1.4    -6.0       7.9&#13;
Trade&#13;
(14)  Terms of Trade Effects/GNP           8.3     8.2     4.8     2.2    3.9       5.1       18.1 .22.8       14.2    9.4     19.8     16.7       10.4    7.0     1.4     -0.5    -2.1      2.7&#13;
(15)  Export Vol1m  Effects/Exports        1.5    14.6     5.3    12.5    12.6      9.9        0.1     0.1      4.8   10.4     12.7      8.0       -0.4   15.9     4.6     13.4    15.5     10.8&#13;
(16)  Export Vol1m  Effects/CGNP           0.2     2.2     1.0     2.4     2.5      1.8        0.1     7.4      3.8    8.6     11.0      6.6       -0.1    4.9     1.8      5.6     6.1      3.9&#13;
(17)  External Shocks/ONP                  8.5    10.4     5.8     4.5     6.4      6.9       18.2    30.3     18.0   18.0    30.8      23.3       10.2   11.9     3.2      5.1    4.0       6.5&#13;
II. Policy Resoonsen&#13;
(18)  Net ExternalI Financing/Averge      14.7    -8.3   -45.6   -60.0  -42.8     -34.2       24.4    26.9    13.5     2.9     11.8     15.2       41.1   14.6   -20.5    -30.1   -51.1    -14.7&#13;
Trade&#13;
(19)  Net External Finan.cing/OFF          2.3    -1.3    -8.5   -11.5    -9.1     -6.3       27.0    26.1    13.8     3.0     12.5     15.8       13.3    4.4    -7.4     -10.4  -18.1     -5.0&#13;
(20)  Increase In Export Shares/Export    15.0    27.7    34.8    41.0   41.9      34.6        6.6    -0.5     0.1     7.8    14.5       6.4       -9.4   -8.3     4.7      3.8    10.4      1.9&#13;
(21)  Import Substitotion/Imports         21.8    37.5    49.1    60.8   55.7      47.9      -14.6    -4.0    -7.6    -5.4     -8.3     -8.0      -13.0    3.1    -0.2     11.1    27.9      7.1&#13;
(22)  lower OFF Growth Effects/Imports     0.8     6.6    -7.2   -18.3  -24.1     -11.4        4.0     7.8    10.9    12.4    12.9       9.8       12.5   31A.4   26.6     32.4    29.2     26.7&#13;
Sourcs:    Table IA and World Bank data hank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
In the same year, the terms of trade loss amounted to one-sixth of the&#13;
average of exports and imports in Singapore, where the export value of&#13;
petroleum products nearly equalled the import value of petroleum. Neverthe-&#13;
less, with the average value of trade exceeding its gross national product,&#13;
the ratio of the terms of trade loss to GNP was the highest in Singapore; 18&#13;
percent in 1974. It was followed by Taiwan (10 percent) that also had a&#13;
relatively high trade share and by Korea (8 percent).&#13;
In Korea and in Taiwan, the terms of trade improved in subsequent years&#13;
when the rise of petroleum prices decelerated. In Korea, the terms of trade&#13;
loss was equivalent to 4 percent of GNP in 1978, with the pure terms of trade&#13;
effect accounting for two-thirds of the total. In Taiwan, the terms of trade&#13;
effects turned positive in 1978 as the gain from higher import prices on its&#13;
large trade surplus in terms of "1972" prices more than compensated for the&#13;
loss due to the negative pure terms of trade effect. In turn, the unfavorable&#13;
impact of higher import prices on its trade deficit was offset only in part by&#13;
the favorable pure terms of trade effect in Singapore, resulting in a-terms of&#13;
trade loss equivalent to one-fifth of GNP in 1978.&#13;
In 1974, the terms of trade loss equalled one half of the average value&#13;
of exports and imports in Brazil that was the only major petroleum importer in&#13;
the second group of Latin American countries. The corresponding ratio was&#13;
one-fifth in Mexico that experienced unfavorable trends in the prices of its&#13;
traditional primary exports; it was 4 percent in Colombia and -8 percent in&#13;
Argentina that gained from increases in cereal prices. Expressed as a&#13;
proportion of GNP the terms of trade loss was 3 percent in Brazil, 1 percent&#13;
in Mexico, and practically zero in Colombia and in Argentina.&#13;
Owing largely to increases in coffee prices, Brazil and Colombia&#13;
experienced considerable improvements in their terms of-trade in subsequent&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
years. By 1978, the terms of trade loss declined to 2 percent of GNP in&#13;
Brazil, with the pure terms of trade effect accounting for three-fourth of the&#13;
total, while Colombia had a terms of trade gain amounting to 3 percent of its&#13;
GNP.&#13;
As a result of higher prices on its rising petroleum exports, Mexico's&#13;
terms of trade loss disappeared by 1977, with the favorable pure terms of&#13;
trade effect compensating for the adverse impact of higher import prices on&#13;
the trade deficit. In turn, the favorable impact of higher import prices on&#13;
its trade surplus slightly exceeded the unfavorable pure terms of trade&#13;
effects in Argentina.&#13;
In the third group, Israel and Yugoslavia suffered the consequences of&#13;
the quadrupling of petroleum prices that resulted in a terms of trade loss&#13;
equivalent to one-half of the average value of their trade in 1974. Given&#13;
differences in trade shares, the corresponding ratio with respect to GNP was&#13;
11 percent in Israel and 5 percent in Yugoslavia. These figures changed&#13;
little in subsequent years. At the same time, in both countries, the-effects&#13;
of higher import prices on the trade deficit expressed in "1972" prices&#13;
exceeded the pure terms of trade effect by a large margin.&#13;
The quadrupling of petroleum prices adversely affected the balance of&#13;
payments of all three countries of the fourth group, although Chile benefited&#13;
from high copper prices that continued during much of 1974.     The terms of&#13;
trade loss expressed as a proportion of average trade and the gross national&#13;
product, respectively, was 48 percent and 4 percent in Uruguay, 41 percent and&#13;
2 percent in India, and 4 percent and 1 percent iD Chile in 1974.&#13;
Subsequently, however, copper prices declined precipitously, leading to a&#13;
terms of trade loss equivalent to 11 percent of Chile's GNP in 1978. In the&#13;
same year, the fall in beef prices contributed'to a terms of trade loss equal&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
20 -&#13;
to 5 percent of GNP in Uruguay. Finally, increases in tea prices contributed&#13;
to a decline in India's terms of trade loss that amounted to one percent of&#13;
GNP in 1978.&#13;
Export Volume Effects&#13;
Export volume effects were negligible in the first group of Far Eastern&#13;
countries in 1974 as foreign demand continued to be strong during much of the&#13;
year. These effects increased in subsequent years, however, with year-to-year&#13;
changes paralleling the world business cycle. By 1978, the shortfall in&#13;
exports due to the slow growth of world demand reached 13 to 16 percent of&#13;
export value in the three countries. With differences in export shares, the&#13;
ratio of the export shortfall to GNP was 11 percent in Singapore, 6 percent in&#13;
Taiwan, and 3 percent in Korea in 1978.&#13;
A similar pattern was observed in Brazil, Colombia, and Mexico, with the&#13;
export shortfall reaching 18 percent of the value of exports in Colombia, 16&#13;
percent in Mexico, and 13 percent in Brazil in 1978. Given the relatively low&#13;
share of exports in the gross national product, the ratio of the export&#13;
shortfall to GNP did not exceed one percent in any of the three countries,&#13;
however. And, this ratio was practically zero in Argentina that benefited&#13;
from the rise in world demand for beef and maize.&#13;
Israel followed the time pattern observed in the above mentioned&#13;
countries, with the ratio of the export shortfall to export value exceeding 21&#13;
percent in 1978. In turn, the export shortfall rose uninterruptedly in&#13;
Yugoslavia, reaching the highest level (44 percent of the value of exports)&#13;
among all the countries under study in 1978, largely because of unfavorable&#13;
developments in centrally planned economies whose 1978 imports from the&#13;
developing countries were below the "1972" level. Finally, the export&#13;
shortfall, expressed as a proportion of GNP,' increased from practically nil in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
1974 to 3 percent in Yugoslavia and to 4 percent in Israel in 1978.&#13;
India also exhibited the pattern observed in most other countries, with&#13;
the ratio of the export shortfall to export value rising from 1 percent in&#13;
1974 to 28 percent in 1978, and that calculated with respect to GNP increasing&#13;
from nil in 1974 to 1 percent in 1978. The pattern was similar in Chile,&#13;
except that strong demand for copper gave rise to a gain in 1974; the export&#13;
shortfall equalled 10 percent of Chile's exports and 2 percent of its GNP in&#13;
1978. By contrast, owing to the rise in world demand for beef and wool, the&#13;
ratio of the export shortfall to export value declined from 12 percent in 1974&#13;
to 5 percent in 1978 in Uruguay, with a parallel decline shown with respect to&#13;
GNP.&#13;
Terms of Trade vs. Export Volume Effects&#13;
The results indicate the relative importance of terms of trade effects in&#13;
newly-industrializing developing countries that rely on imported petroleum.'&#13;
In 1974 and 1975, on the average, the ratio of the terms of trade loss to the&#13;
export shortfall ranged between 4 and 6 in Taiwan, Singapore, Uruguay,&#13;
Yugoslavia and Korea; it was between 8 and 10 in India,Brazil and Israel; and&#13;
it reached 22 in Chile,. The corresponding ratios for the remaining countries&#13;
were 1 in Colombia, 3 in Argentina, and 5 in Mexico.&#13;
With the exception of Chile and Uruguay, the ratio of terms of trade&#13;
effects to export volume effects declined during the period under&#13;
consideration. For one thing, apart from Chile and Uruguay that experienced&#13;
unfavorable changes in the prices of their principal traditional exports,&#13;
there was a tendency for terms of trade losses as a percentage of GNP to&#13;
decline over time due largely to the slowdown in the rise of petroleum&#13;
prices. For another thing, export volume effects showed an increasing trend,&#13;
with fluctuations around the trend parallelling the business cycle, except&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
that Uruguay benefited from increased world demand for beef and wool.&#13;
Still, terms of trade effects continued to exceed export volume effects&#13;
by a considerable margin in all the petroleum importing countries other than&#13;
India where increases in the price of tea reduced terms of trade losses&#13;
towards the end of the period and Taiwan where high import prices on its trade&#13;
surplus measured in "1972" prices gave rise to a terms of trade gain. In&#13;
1978, the ratio of these effects was 2 in Brazil, Korea, Singapore and&#13;
Yugoslavia, and 3 in Israel; it was 6 in Chile, and 10 in Uruguay. In the&#13;
same year, terms of trade effects were negative in Argentina and Colombia and&#13;
practically nil in Mexico.&#13;
The results show the importance of the quadrupling in petroleunm prices in&#13;
1973-74, the effects of which were fully felt by January 1974. They conflict&#13;
with conventional wisdom that gives emphasis to the unfavorable effects of the&#13;
world recession and the subsequent slow recovery in the developed countries on&#13;
the balance of payments of the developing countries. Also, the results do not&#13;
support the view that the exports of manufactured goods from the developing&#13;
countries were adversely affected by increased protectionism in the developed&#13;
countries.&#13;
Thus, data available in a geographical breakdown show an increase in-the&#13;
apparent" income elasticity of demand for the imports of manufactured goods&#13;
in the developed countries, calculated as the ratio of the rate of growth of&#13;
their imports. to that of the gross national product. For the period as a&#13;
whole, increases in the income elasticity of demand offset one-fifth of the&#13;
export shortfall due to lower GNP growth rates in the developed countries.&#13;
At the same time, in intra-LDC trade, the favorable effects of higher GNP&#13;
growth rates and income elasticity of import demand cumulated, with favorable&#13;
effects for countries, such as those of the second group, where a large share&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
of manufactured exports was sold in developing country markets. By contrast,&#13;
in centrally planned economies, the decline in the income elasticity of demand&#13;
aggravated the adverse effects of lower GNP growth rates, importantly&#13;
contributing to the large export shortfall observed in Yugoslavia.&#13;
IV. The Policies Applied and their Balance-of-Payments Effects&#13;
Section III of the paper analyzed the impact of external shocks, in the&#13;
form of terms of trade and export volume effects, on the balance of payments&#13;
of the newly-industrializing developing countries classified into four&#13;
groups. Section IV will examine the policies applied in the four groups of&#13;
countries and indicate the balance-of-payments effects of these policies.&#13;
The balance-of-payments effects of the policies applied are shown in&#13;
Table IA while Table 1B relates the results to the volume of exports, imports,&#13;
average trade, and the gross national product, as the case may be, all&#13;
expressed in "1972" prices. More detailed estimates are shown in Appendix&#13;
Tables 1 and 2. In turn, Table 2 provides information on the financing of the&#13;
resource gap, Table 3 on nominal and real interest rates, the government&#13;
budget and the money supply, Table 4 on nominal and real exchange rates vis-a-&#13;
vis the U.S. dollar, Table 5 on debt service and the external debt, and Table&#13;
6 on expenditure shares, incremental capital-output ratios, and rates of&#13;
economic growth.&#13;
Korea, Singapore, Taiwan&#13;
In 1974, the combined balance-of-payments effects of external shocks&#13;
equalled 18 percent of the gross national product in Singapore, 10 percent in&#13;
Taiwan, and 9 percent in Korea. The effects of these shocks increased in&#13;
subsequent years in Singapore, reaching 31 percent of GNP in 1978. After a&#13;
small increase in 1975, the ratio declined to 6 percent in Korea and to 4&#13;
percent in Taiwan in 1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 2&#13;
Fietnetee the Eat.rnel Recenre G..&#13;
1971    1972    1973   '1972"   1974   1975    1976    1977    1979   1974-78         1971    1972    1973  '1972"   1974    1975    1976    1977    1978   1974-79         1971   1972    1973   "1972'   1974'   1975    1976    1977   .1979  1974-78&#13;
A RGE NT I NA                                                                               B RA ZI L                                                                               CH IL E&#13;
letre-    Nece ipte                   16       7      26      16     128.     55      50     128     333      139           43     131     327     167     718     364    282     358     640      672            12       1       5       6     24        5     10      18      39       19&#13;
Icteret Peyceece                    -226    -279    -343    -293    -625    -467    -515   -509    -719     -523          -374    -544    -908    -609  -1448   -1865   -2091   -2460   -3334    -2239          -100    -124   -114    -113    -286    -292    -320    -300    -454     -340&#13;
EaDeed                               -4      -61     -77     -61     -36     -16     -23    -211    -324     -122         -612    -319    -530    -417    -554    -532   -790   -1330   -1538     -949           -30     -23       0     -18      -8     -7      -2     -23     -30      -14&#13;
Other Fader 1'yeeete                 -33       -8    -33     -25     -39     -15      -5     -27    -143      -59            8       8      19       9      -1     -75    -120     -33    -44      -35           -13       5      12       1     -26    -11     -47     -54     -34      -34&#13;
OffEi.1T-Iref-t                       -3      -4      11       1       9      -1      -5       9       9       -1           29      23      16      20      -2     -19      -4       5       3      -2             4       2      10       5       8     13      16      16       0       11&#13;
Birere Ieaee     .e                    11      10      10     10      19       0       9      82     273       73          336     570    1341     816    1268   .1090    1212    1678   1880     1426           -66      -1      -5     -24   -337       s0     -1      21     182      -61&#13;
PetflM       Cpia                    -94     112      56      25     -78     203    -221     137   -503       -92         1393    3115    2768    2493    5371   4956    6988    4540    9486     6268           134     342     470     316     761    257     167     776    1496      691&#13;
Snare Ica'd Ou.leea                    29     40   -  69      46   -26       - 4     486     324     297      227           -9     438     355     261     -64     -35    1024    -614    298       122         -109       0     -86     -65    -117    -19       -3    -33     -68      -48&#13;
Cban9ee Ge ERear-.                   444       65   -845    -112     -76    1080    -921  -1837   -2269      -805         -485   -2431   -2307   -1749     989    1016  -2883    -495   -4646    -1164           239     130    -109      90      90    277    -333    -210    -720     -179&#13;
Net Entered    Fiiacan                *98   -118   -1126    -302    -510     843   -1136   T190    -3055    -1156          924    1000    1072     999    6277   4913    3818     1649   2745     3090            71     330     192     198   -111     283    -513     151     411       4&#13;
Tawl Entere       FL-inac             370    220    -706     -38     -49    1326    -616   -1193  -2012      -509         1710    0054    2210    2923    0279    7396    6699   3439    7617     7068           201     479     306     329     183     572   -190     334     893      399&#13;
CO0LOMEXB IA                                                                            HMEX I CO                                                                             UR UG UA Y&#13;
I-    acetEe...ipte                     9     18      24      17      65      56      65      65     123       75           65      80      97      81     153     117     124     168    345      161             1       1       6       3       5      4       7      12      18        9&#13;
IcarePeyenae                   -114    -135    -168    -139    -201    -230    -269   -232    -269     -248          -3019   -341    -513    -389    -886  -10984  -1675   -1978   -2550    -0621           -22     -23     -31    -26     -43     -71     -79     -77     -93      -73&#13;
Dlald.ede                            -71     -70     -70     -70     -35     -68    -109     -86    -114      -86         -359    -435    -581    -458    -794    -840    -866    -400   -400     -636             0       0       0       0      -4      -4       0     -2       9       -2&#13;
Other Feeer Payenete                  -32    -33     -23     -30     -23     -18     -17      -2      -3      -13           133    149     157     146     182     109     233     260     279      232           -1      -1       4      -1      -4      35      -3    -10      -6       -6&#13;
Offli.el1T- ef-r                       31      24     23      26      32      17      13       8       6       15             7     10      8a       8      22      27      27      16      18       22            8       8       7       8      17       3       0       0      0        4&#13;
Elret Invecemee                        43      18     24      28      41      40      25      64      73       49          307     301     657     352     678     610     628     556    532      691             0       0       0       0       0       0       0     66     129       39&#13;
B'.rfa,La Cap"Ita                     303    228     123     218     231     142     171     -91     149      120          629     134    1324     769    3122    4872    52.33   1616   2916     3360           102      40      20      54     160    163     060     238     -31       130&#13;
One   , ned 0,ecciae99                       103      69      87     -17     .19     211     is9     138      100           34     651    -411      91    -845  -1349   -3646       53   -557    -1129           -31     -62     -30     -48     -82    -38     -13      31     118        12&#13;
Ch.ag:e i    BR.,ve                     1   -178    -161    -113      91    -112    -633    -586    -528     -353         -134    -199    -154    -159     -79    -178     295   -375    -428        93           13     -36     -27     -17      40      62    743    -179    -129      -56&#13;
Net Eaterel Ficnleg                  269     -25    -161      25     168    -183    -543    -723    -423     -341          373     375     584     444    1633    2451    1473      84      iS    1098            50     -75     -16     -27      89     1t8      -1     83      4        67&#13;
TYawl Extend     Fieniag              445    180      77     234     424     131    -165    -385     -40       -6         1841    1153    1678    1291    3233    4381    3814   2294    3045     3354            72     -58     -25      -1     136     193      78    163     139      142&#13;
I ND IA                                                                             I8E RAEBL                                                                     YUGO0S L AVIA&#13;
Interact Rece ipts                    48      43      31      47      94     130     195     274     448      232          120     137     238     165     335     322     363    370     496      377            17      17      50      28      93     62      90     122     139      184&#13;
Inarnat PeY-t.tt                    -310    -310    -391    -364    -304    -184    -347    -413   -338      -358         -177    -240    -334    -210    -126   -652    -663    -711    -939     -699          -147    -165    -222   -178    -283    -343    -364    -381    -415     -366&#13;
Bi=deed                                 0       9      0       9       0       0       0       0       0        9          -29     -20     -42     -30     -13     -49     -38     -44     -48     -47             0       0       0       0       0       0       0       0      0        0&#13;
0O6cr Teeter FPymete                    8-     10     13      10      42      79     -29     -67       0        6          -68    -114    -198    -127    -233    -242    -222    -193   -218     -222             0       0       0,      0       0       0       0       0      0         0&#13;
Otfieiel T-cfer                       144     163    110     139    2094     194     401     394     993      815           240    344    1050     343     999    1092    1436    1277    1560     1253           -1      -1      14       4       1      -1       0      -1       0        0&#13;
BireetlI    ecBt                       -1       3    -13      -4      -6     -11      -8       0       o       -s           17     113     148     106      81      42      47      81    154        78            9       0       0       0       0       0       0       0      0        0&#13;
FeatfaiGa Capital                     717    271     482     505    -937     958     921     437       0      276          533     411     835     593     985    19091   1024     232   1345     1007           428     147     168     248     947   1067     909    1544    1267     1141&#13;
En-r. ed On.iecce                    -95    -254     -42    -130    -298    -433    -296    -134     199     -195            58     53      -4      36    -183     149      22    430     391      162             0       0       0       0       0       0       0     -0       0        9&#13;
Ch.ee    Ge Re.er-e                   -22     129    108      72      20    -362   -2214   -2425   -1692     1335         -224    -519    -532    -425     815     197    -64     -237   -860      -26           -70    -166    -646    -427     243     -63  -1063     -1     -250     -229&#13;
Net Eatereal FienecGe9.      333~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~_8  -19  31l8  72-73  311l  1147  1 7-7  -193  -370  n311     515      161   1161     612    2209    2673    1925    1199    1861     1973          27     -6       66     -2        9       2     49     17        1 &#13;
Yawl Eaterel Fteenie8-               839     369     700     629    1020     333   -1030   -1521     -12     -200          716     425    1537     093    2788    3374    2624    1960   2848     2719           374    -403    -414    -148    1264   1065      -75   1615    1167     1019&#13;
KO0R EA                                                                        S ING A PORE                                                                               T A I WAN&#13;
aterese R .ceipte                      23      21     41      28      82      47      70     134     282      123           83      96     137     103     182     211     208     273    383      251            40      46     III      66     164    149     134     212     376      211&#13;
letee-t Fejenete                    -109    -150    -192    -110    -294    -424    -4-80   -675    -968     -168          -30    -128    -298    -152    -371    -295   -349     -374   -454     -369           -56     -24     -43     -41     -82   -142    -261    -313    -400     -248&#13;
DivIdeat                               -3    -23     -10     -13     -30     -25     -37     -51     -10      -39        -    0       0      0       0       0       0       0       0       0        0          -21     -25     -49     -32     -65     -90    -.1     -67     -75      -72&#13;
Other Felr      eut                   236    229     176     214     150     125     182     310     328      219           117     61      so      86      82      69      52      32      38       51           20      48      -2      22      11      11     -51    -19    -106      -30&#13;
Offt  .  eTreeafer                     63      50     36      10      67      67     102      53      38       71            11       4      11      9       1       0      -3      -3      -4       -2            2       2      -5       0      -2      -6      -1      -2     -7        -4&#13;
Direct leecmt                         42      64      95      67     119      57      81      93      89       88          116     191     389     232     597     611     651     331    517      542            53      27      62      47      83      15      72     49     114       67&#13;
Partfelia Capital                     741    425     509     138    1624    2399    1782    1300    2006     1823          171     205     334     237     -99     -32     199     272    274       123         -162     -29    -485    -225    1019    532      266  -1000    1633     -175&#13;
Errn    ead Odleeoan                  24      21      41      31     107    -226    -232     -63    -327     -148          711     451     262     489     902     433     152     180    630      459           -24     -21    -116     -55      13     -5    -243    -141    -135     -183&#13;
- theegee Re Enaerves        ~39    -141    -348    -150     171    -376  -1314   -1372    -707     -720          -319    -337    -411    -316    -295   -408    -298    -313    -665     -396           -41   -514      -60   -203     -41     -12    -413     244      -6      -45&#13;
Net EatenI Pinceieg                  1018    494     352     635!   19      163      264    -266     691      854          904     -543    3M     -650    -999    -589    -592     442     719     660          -189    -494    -587    -43     1109    472    -58     115     170     t3&#13;
Yawl SEterel Fieeecie                1170    669     554     798    2320    2092     721     440    1709     1441          934     671     802     8092   1370     884     941     776   1173      1029         -112    -445    -495    -351    1247     704   -216    -735   -1391      -79&#13;
learce:     llereti-aI H-ntar FPed,           aleac af FPve-te Y-ebek, leteratiani Fineecta              Statistics, -ere-e ieee..&#13;
Yageelevice data fie Wand Beak Repait.          Far ladle, 1970/79 fiacal ye-      ace a..ed fee 1978, ftre   Wand Beak Rap-rt.&#13;
Nate:. Yawl Entered      Finaning L. cte. nm      atee   entrea    fieenia, ineeres      pay-ete and dialdnde..&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 3&#13;
RNaod1 and Real Interet Rates, the Coe-       t Budnat and the Haney Sanaly&#13;
1971  1,972   1973  "11972e 1974   1975   1976   1977   1978       1971   1972   1973  "1972  -1974    =1T   .1972  1977   1978       1971   1972   1973  '1972'  1974   1975   1976   1977   1978&#13;
AR CEN T I A                                                            B R AZI L                                                           C HI LE&#13;
Onela Interet 0t14'                           23.2   30.1   26.2   26.5   26.5   94.5  115.3  121.8  142.8       20.0-  20.0   18.0   19.3   18.0   18.0   28.0   38.0   33.0       15.8   20.0   50.0   28.3     -   267.3  197.9   93.8   63.2&#13;
Real Iner-t R.tneb                           -11.3  -24.7  -17.3  -17.     7.9  -33.9  -64.1  -11.1   -1.3        0:.0   1.:2   1.:1   0.8   -8.6   -7.3  -10.7   -8.7   -3.3      -14.7  -51.1  -73.3  -46.4     -   -22.7:  -4.5    1.1   16.3&#13;
R-M--                    ~   ~~~~6.6  5.7  5.2  5.8    6.0    3.9    5.3    6.2               9.    10.5   10.7   10.3   108     9.6   10.8   10.6   10.4       18.2   15.9   16.9   17.0   24.3   18.9&#13;
Ooveet Ependturs'    -                    8.     8.5   10.7     .4   1.3    16.1    1.8   10.               10.1   10.6    10.   104     02     96    10.8   10.6   10.3       26.1   26.1   29.8   23.7   34.9   17.8-&#13;
Budget Surplus (DefIlLt)5'          d         -2.3   -2.8   -5.5'   3.5   -8.3  -12.2   -8.5   -4.2              -0.2   -0.1    0.1   -0.1    0.6    0.0    0.0    0.0    0.1       -7.9  -10.2  --7.9   -8.7  -10.6    1.1&#13;
Change in the Mony Supply -        Ld         35.9   67.   103.6   68.81  71.6  196.5  297.7  148.7  133.3       20.:2  40.    49.1   39.4   33.6' 39.2    38.5   36.6   41.0      120.0  145.3  316.7  194.1  272.4  257.4  193.7  100.2   68.6&#13;
-             ~~~~~-52.2  -5.5O  22.7   8.  44    0.8  -33.6   -0.3   -5.2        77    18.1   27.7    17.8   3.5    9.4   -3.3   -4.1    2.3       63.1    0.0  -23.8   12.4  -15.2  -24.0   -3.9    8.7   20.4&#13;
COLO M BIA                                                             ME XI CO                                                         OR U       UA Y&#13;
ONeinl Inteee    RfeI14.0                            14.0   14.0   14.0   16.0   16.0   20.0   20.0   22.0        4.     455  4        435 4.         43     .5     .5     .5                                                 45.6   65.2   59.7&#13;
RootereMt R     tvene                          2.2   -3.7  -10.9    4.1   _14.7  -7.5   -2. 4  -5.3    2.7        0.6    1.7   -8.8    _-2.2  -14.7  -5.4  -14.6  -26.0  -9.7                                            -     3 3    9.9    7.5&#13;
9.7    8.9    0.4    9.1    81      .     9.     9.0    9.5        0.5    9.7   10.19   9.7   11.4   13.2   13.1   11.6   19.4        -      -     21.9    -     20.1   18.5   20.9   22.0   23.2&#13;
Ooveant tepanditureS'    .        1~~~~0.5  109    .4   190.31  9.0'  98     85      8.    8.8          .3   11.6   1.     157    13.0   16.7   16.5   14.9  24.1        -2 3.1               -     23.8   22.9   23.1    22.9  23.6&#13;
Budget SnrplnC'(DfiCtttS1          Id         -0.8   -2.0   -1.0   -1.3   -0.9   -0.3    0.9    0.8    0.7       -0.8   -1.9   -3.2   -2.0   -3.6   -3.5   -3.4   -3.3   -4.7        -      -     -1.2    -     -3.7   -4.4   -1.2   -0.9   -0.4&#13;
Change in the Mony Supply :-euN."  A/         11.0   27.1   30.7   23.2   17.8   20.1   34.7   30.4   25.0        7.6   17.9   22.4   16.0   20.7   21.4   29.1   26.0   31.1       53.9   46.9   80.0   60.3   64.2   64.0   66.1   38.1   79.7&#13;
a.l              0.3    7.4    2.2    3.3  -13.4   -4.3    9.6    2.0    6.3        3.6   14.7    5.7    8.0   -1.5    9.9    5.6  -10.7   13.2       27.5  -22.6  -16.3   -3.8   -8.1   -4.8   10.3   -8.2   20.9&#13;
INDI A                       -IS R                                           AEL                                               YSUGOOSL A VIA&#13;
SNel-1 Internt -v     '-                       6.0    6.0    7.0    6.3    9.0    9.0    9.0    9.0    9.0&#13;
Real Internt Rat~                              0. -          73     32-1.                 73    30     1.&#13;
_osrt paR-       l                            .9     33     73    -32   -52      4.      .      .;1.                                                             . 9.9  9.6  8.4  9.3  9.0  10.3  10.6  10.6  39.6  34.3~ 38.:5  57.5  42.4  49.2  55.5  37.5  20.9  23.8  20.3  21.7  22.2  22.1  22.4  13.4&#13;
_aert Opnirel12.1                                  11.6    9.9   11.2   10.6   12.5   13.4   13.2        -      5.0   47.2   67.3   56.5   66.1   70.3   76.6   78.5              25.3   24.1   20.7   23.4   24.9   24.2   24.3 -25.1&#13;
Budget Surplus (SefLalt)S      &#133;     -        -2.2   -2.0   -1.5    1.9   -1.6   -2.2   -2.8    2.6             -15.4  -12.9  -28.8  -19.0  -23.7  -21.1  -11.1  -21.0              -4.4   -0.3   -0.4   -1.7   -2.7   -2.1   -1.9   -1.7&#13;
Chang  tn the Money Supply N-i8ag7ld         13.6   12.8   16.    14.4   10 .2   9.3   24.9   16.8   21.6       28.2   28.7   32.3   29.7   18.0   21.7   27.1   38.8   45.0   -   15.9   41.7.  38.4   32.0   23.2   32.8   60.2   16.8   20.4&#13;
- -                                         _8- -  2,        3         _43     48    ;~9    10.4   22.9-      16.3   16.3- 11.2    14.6  -22.1  -13.6   -2.8 ~02       53          .     65    2.      72     3858                       1.&#13;
KORE A                                                       S.1 NGA POEER                                                           T AIVWARN&#13;
ONena Interes.t R.)-'/                        16.    11.0   11.0   12.7   11.0   14.0   24.0   14.0   15.0         8.0    7.5    9.0    6.2   10.3    7.1    6.8    7.0    7.7      12.0- 11.3    13.3   12.2   14.8   13.3   12.0   10.8   10.8&#13;
Real Interet Rat_k                             6.9,  -2.47   3.8    2.8  -21.9   -9.79   1.7    4.     3.0        6.0    5.3   -13.7  -0.8    -9.9   4.3     9.0    3.6    2.8      11.8    6.6   -7.7    3.6  -18.3   19.3    8.9'   7.9    7.0&#13;
G    -eat ReveueS                             17.2   15.4   13.4   16.1   16.0   17.    20.7   19. 7  20.3       22.3 -23.1    21.5   22.3   22.2   23.5   24.2   23.5   23.7                -         -        14.4   16.4   19.1   16.5   16.0&#13;
G_ent        aeu.dttsrk--                   - 17.8   20.1 -16.6    18.2 -17.8    19.4- '20.3 -19.4 -19.8-.       18.1   16.3   15.1~  16.5  -15.2-  17.3 .18.8-   19.6   20.5-    -    -       -10.0                   12.1   12.4   13.2   12.9&#13;
Budge   otSrplns (Deflaltg    &#133;    -          -0.6   -4.5   -1.2   -2.1   -1.8   -1.7    0.4    0.3    0.5               6 .  .0  6.4  5.8   .7.0    8.2    3.4    3.9    2.2-                                   4.4   *4.3- 3.7      3.2    3.9&#13;
Cage  nteMnySpl             Nnhld/           1.      51    4.      41    295    2.      07    4..2.              7.92   3.    10.4   17.9    8.    21.5   13.2   10.3   11.7       24.6   37.9   49.3   37.3    7.0   26.9   23.1   29.1   34.1&#13;
1-nRelk            7.2   257.5  31.5   23.    -8.9   -1.    16.6   29.1   11.8        6.0  .32.7  -2.7     8.7  -13     18.3   17.6    6.8    6.6       24.4   32.1   21.6   26.0  -23.9   33.6   19.7   25.7   29.5&#13;
Sonat:   Inteasti-al Monetary Puad, Iet.rntlo-I Pioanatal Otetletla..&#13;
N.t.:   (a  DIs-o-n rota,....ept far.. taneies noted hel; (b) Deflated by the hba1e..l     pr ice.des; (atpre...ed asep-p-rtian at the g-s         national p-d-at. The date do ant inlude grats. lending, sad repay-ts; (d) Sun at privat&#13;
etta  deoud depoalts end aurreny   -ntede the banks (Ml).&#13;
ArgenIna, anetnl interest rat, Slanap-r and Uruguy. tbs prine rot       a.d'f- Chile 35 day tIne dapolta rates at -om       itl bank. nun ned.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 4&#13;
9N.dl and Real Raahaca   Rate. 1971-1978&#13;
1971    1912    1973  "1972"   1974    1975    1976    1977    1979     1971    1972    1973   "1972'   1974    1975   1976    1977    1978      17      92     17     "1972"           1974 93 17.     __      17&#13;
A ROCE NT I           A                                                     B RA Z IL                                                                 C OI L &#13;
Exchang  Rafte . teon1 Cureny&#13;
par US doIlla                       4.6     8.2     9.4     7.4     9.9   36.6   140.0   407.6   795.8     5.288   5.954  6.126   5.783   6.790   8.129  10.675  14.144  18.070    0.012   0.020   0.111  0.048   0.832   4.911  1.3.054  21.529  31.456&#13;
Inex of Enchane Rates                62.2   110.8   127.0   100.0   120.3  494.6  1991.9  5508.2 10754.1      91.4   102.6   105.9  100.0   117.4   140.6   104.6   244.6  312.5      25.2    42.0   232.9  100.0  1746.0 10303.0 27394.0 45166.0  66411.0-&#13;
lestle Wholesale Pric    Index       53.0    95.1   143.5   100.8   171.2   503.4  30115.5  7520.9 18505.3    94.1    99.7   116.4  100.0   150.4   191.3   274.3   590.6  537.3      17.4    42.7   239.9   100.0  1054.0  5000.0 15623.0 29945.0  41956.0&#13;
Ine  f Relative ftLes&#13;
vIea-iad, 0                   60.6   102.6   136.8   100.0   137.5   369.0  2117.2 4975.1 11244.9      90.4   103.1   106.4  100.0   115.7   154.6   194.3   247.6  516.4      18i.7   44.0   2l8S    100.0  809.0 35827.0 10471.0 18916.0  24554.0&#13;
laden ef Real RhaoBe Rat&#13;
va-a-via the US dollar             102.6  109.0    92.8   100.0    97.6   133.9   89.4   110.8    94.6     100.9    99.5    99.5  100.0   101.5   104.5   100.2    98.8   98.8     134.8    95.5   104.6   100.0  216.1   248.5   261.5   2.38.9   270.5&#13;
CO0LO0M BI A                                                               MEX I CO                                                               UR U GUA Y&#13;
incheag  Rau.~ atmeal Currency&#13;
per 00 dollar                    20.080  22.018  2.3.815  21.970  27.109 51.202  34.976 36.9723  39.252   12.500  12.500 12.500  12.500  12.500  12.499  15.426  22.575  22.767    0.260   0.563   0.075   0.566   1.216  2.299   3.395   4.750    6.125&#13;
Index of Enchant Rates               91.4   100.2   108.4   100.0   12.3.4  142.0  1.59.2  160.1   178.7     100.0   100.0   100.0  100.0   100.0   100.0   1253.4  180.6 -182.1      41.9    99.5   194.6   100.0  214.0   409.2   599.8   939.2   1082.2&#13;
DestLe Wholesal PrIce Icda           81.1    96.1   122.9   100.0   167.1   209.6  237.8   326.5   384.0      93.2    95.8   111.0  100.0   136.0   150.2   185.7   259.5  300.1      43.0   91.6    175.4   100.0  513.5   540.4   813.7  122312   1817.4&#13;
Lad=   of ReIlatv  prices&#13;
v-svethe US                   07.7    99.7   112.6   100.0   120.9   147.9   173.9  207.5   226.0     100.5    98.7   101.1   100.0  104.2   105.4   123.3   163.8   176.1     47.8    00.9   165.3   100.0   248.6  391.9   564.5   799.2   1105.5&#13;
Index of Ral Enchant Rat&#13;
veavethe US d.11ai            194.2  100.5    96.3   100.0    95.7    96.0    91.5   77.2    79.8      99.7   101.3    98.9  100.0    94.0    94.9   100.1   110.5   105.4     96.0   114.5    93.5   100.0    86.4  103.6   106.5   105.0     89.1&#13;
I N DIA                                                                ISR A EL                                                            YOOOOSL A V IA&#13;
Eaesag   RaM. Rationa   Currenc y&#13;
per US dollar                     7.501   7.594   7.742   7.612   8.102   8.376  8.980   8.739   8.193     0.375   0.420  0.420   0.404   0.450   0.639   0.798   1.046  1.747    14.959  17.000  16.189  16.049  15.915  17.396  19.193  18.298  10.644&#13;
Index of Raah-ge Rates               98.5    99.8   101.7   100.0   106.4   110.0  117.7   114.9   107.6      92.3   105.9   10519  100.0   111.5   158.0   197.4   250.7  432.1      93.2   105.9   100.9   100.0   99.2   100.5   115 4   114.0    116.2&#13;
Dentin Wholesal Pria loden            89.3   97.8   112.9   100.0   145.2   151.4   133.9  162.9   161.1      95.1    97.1   109.9  100.0   150.5   142.7   149.2   158.5   170.5     09.8    99.4   111.9   100.0   145.6   177.5  189.3   207.7    251.9&#13;
Indx of Relative Price&#13;
va-a-fl. the us                     96.0  100.7   102.9    0.      1.     106.2   103.1i  102i.8  94.3      94.4   100.1   105.4  100.0   134.2   172.9   214.4   282.5  401.0      95.5   102.5   101.9   100.0   111.7  124.6   126.3   151.3    130.5&#13;
Indan of Roa1 Rachao   Rat&#13;
vie-a-vi  the US do1llar           102.6   99.1    90.9   100.0    95.6   105.6   114.2  111.7   114.1      97.9   103.9    98.6   100.0   82.9    91.4    91.2    91.6   107.5     97.6   103.5    99.0   100.0    88.8   91.0    89.8    96.8     89.2&#13;
OB R RA                                                             OIONOCA PO0RO                                                               TAI WA N&#13;
Exchang Ratn. Raticl Cureny&#13;
p.0.US dollar   -                300.80  595.97  398.32  591.03 405.97  484.00  484.00 484.00 484.00      3.0478  2.0092  2.4436  2.7669  2.4569  2.3715  2.4708  2.4394  2.2740  40.000 40.033   38.265  59.432  30.000  39.000 38.0D0  38.9000  37.054&#13;
ndex of Rnchao9o Rates               92.1   103.4   104.5   100.0   106.5   127.0  127.0   127.0   127.0     110.2   101.5   88.3   100.0    00.1    85.7    89.3    88.2   82.2     101.4   101.5    97.0   100.0   96.4    96.4    96.4    96.4     94.0&#13;
leslie Wholesale f.Plie  Index       90.0   101.5   100.5   100.0   134.3   195.6  218.9   238.7   246.6      90.3    92.4   117.0  100.0   145.0   146.9   144.0   148.7   153.7     90.2    94.1   115.6   100.0   162.5  114.3   158.6   165.0    108.7&#13;
Index of Ralntiv  Prin-&#13;
yin-s-v   the US                   94.7   194.3   98.8    100.0   118.2   137.0   146.7  150.6   156.3      97.6    95.5   104.9   100.0  110.0   103.2    96.8    94.1    91.7     97.3    97.5   105.6   100.0   124.9   100.6  106.7   103.5     99.5&#13;
,.d. of Rel Exhange Rate&#13;
vie-a-ne the 00S dollar            95.2    98.9   105.8   100.0    90.1    92.7   86.6    84.3    01.3     112.9   106.3    82.7  100.0    80.1    83.0    92.5    95.7    89.6    104.2   194.2    91.9   100.0    77.2   88.8 .90.3      93.5     94.7&#13;
Sourc: Itleontlonl M-ontac Pued. Iooolna            lsnLal Stetiatice *vrosjs, *U-I. . World Bctk Reports.&#13;
Be.tel Per ChLIl end Blogppre the Don-tie C    -,   Pni.o Ondec -a used.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table &#13;
Debt ServIce ed     xterna  Debt&#13;
(In U0$ niios.crrt price)&#13;
jfJ,     1972     1973   "1972"    1974    1975     1976     1977    1978        1971     1972    1973    "1972"   1974     1975     1976    1977     1978        1971    1972     1973   '17'      1974     1975    1976     1977    1978&#13;
A R CENTI NA                                                                          BR A ZIL                                                                          C HI LE&#13;
Cros   Debt ServIc                     502     528      744      395    1000     1051     122.3   1284     3161        1467    1942     2654    2021     3371    4031     5084    6511     8606         283      591     522      399     888      805      985    11353    1416&#13;
Eel Debt Servic                        486      531     718      578     872      956     1175    1156     2826        1424    1811     2327    1834     2653     3665    4802     6153    7966         271      390     517      393     864      800      975    1137     1377&#13;
-hctadiea Expots                      1760    1941     3266     2316    3931     2961    3912     5642     6483       2984     3991     6199    6365     7951    8670    10128   12120    12659         981      855    1249     1022    24-81    1552    20813    2190     2408&#13;
Gros   Debt Service Ratio             18.9    27.7     22.8     25.7    23.4     34.1     31.3    22.8     49.4       50.5     48.7     42.8    46.3     42.4    68.5     50.2     53.7    68.0        29.4    45.7     41.8     39.0    33.8     51.9    47.3     52.6     58.8&#13;
at, Debt Derric   Relle               27.9    27.4     22.0     25.0    22.2     32.3    30.3     20.5    44.2        49.0     45.4     37.5    42.5     33.4    42.3     47.4     50.8    62.9        28.2    45.6     41.4     38.4    34.8     51.5    48.8     51.8     57.2&#13;
C_nt Satern      Debt                                  3323             3641     3450.   5055     5890     7290       6622     9521    12372    9572    17165   21171    25985   32000    43500                         4048             4774     5263    5195     5434     6911&#13;
a.t Eaternl Debt                                       2215             2406     3286    3970     2977     2143       4899     5338     8154    5465    11893   17135    19441   24764    31608                         3964             40868    5840    5201     5315     6109&#13;
Orne   Nationl Produt                37907   45400    48138   43145    56115    60939   628,47   70018    72752      64340    74871    90227   76479   1008664  125212  143198   128556  108024        9275     9708    9851     9811   11398    10980    12010   13819    18442&#13;
re. External Debt MaCle                                 6.               65       5.7     8.9      8.6     10.0        10A3    12.7     13.9    12.5     15.8    18.9     18.1    20.2     24.2                         41.1             41.9     47.9    43.3     39.3     42.02&#13;
Net Exenal Debt RatIo                                   4.6              4.3      3.4      6.3     4.3      2.9         7.6     7.1      6.8     7.1     10.9     13.7    13.6     15.6    17.6                         40.2             42.7     50.3    43.3     38.5     37.2&#13;
CO0LO0M BI A                                                                        ME9X I CO0                                                                     UR UGUA Y&#13;
G-n    Debt S.e-ICe                    285     3153     338      319     485      471     488      484      351         788     874     1390    1018     1398    1929     2925    4398     7840          46       71     108       74      63      138      140     149      207&#13;
Net Debt Servic                        276     297      334      502     400      415     421      419      428         723     796     1293     937     1245    1812     2809    4230     6795          45       79     108       72      58      154      133     137      189&#13;
Ie-ad-iaa Exports                      489     863     1176      909    1417 -1445        1785    2643     3010        1363    1665     2871    1708     3850    2861     3316    6418     6217         208      214     322      247     382      384      547     608      680&#13;
Gros   Debt Seric   Ratle             41.4    36.5     30.4     35.1    32.8     32.2    27.9     19.8     18.3       57.8     52.6     67.1    59.9     49.1     67.4    88.4     98.5   113.2        22.3     33.2    32.9     30.1    16.5     35.9    23.6     24.0     38.1&#13;
Net Dbt Servic     tall               48.1    54.4.    28.4     33.2    28.2     28.3    24.1     17.2     14.2       53.0     47.8     62.4    55.1     43.7     63.3    84.7     95.7   189.3        21.8     22.7    31.1     29.0    15.2     34.9    24.3     22.5     27.5'&#13;
tosEtrnal Debt                                         2102             2370     2693    2806     3019     3541                         8310            12389   17263    228080  26785    32622                          268              557      667      758     791      866&#13;
abt Etrnal Sebt                                        1568             1921     2172     1648    1198      905                         6955            109 96  15724    20,973  25366    30675                          168              403      302     405      168       17&#13;
Ones NatLnl Product                   9447   10613    12078    10713   14124    16030   57615    19645    22993      41284    46192    52391   40592    68478   60624    73139   88402    81914        282.3    2828    3927     2893    5430     3905    4212     4629     3137&#13;
Gre    Exte-1a Debt Retio                              17.4             16.8     16.8     15.9    15.4     14.6                         15.9             20.5     235.2   50.1     33.3    35.5                         12.2             16.2     17.1     17.8    17.1     16.8&#13;
at Externl Debt Bale                                   13.0             13.6     13.5     9.4      6.1      3.9                         13.3             18.2     22.9    28.7     31.5    33.4                         56              11.7     10.0     9.6      3.8      0.3&#13;
I ND IA                                                                         I 8R AE9L                                                                TYU GO          LA VI A&#13;
* rossDebt Servic                      644      605      784     678     2717      789     760      661     908         493      557     612      524      797     838     1102    1141     1449         485     672      838     685     1014     1338    1267     1431    1855&#13;
a.t Dbt Servic                         596      562     735      639    2623      659     574      687      448         285     420      574     359      662     516      739      771     953         468     855      708      637     921     1296     1177    1508     1705&#13;
Merch-edisx Expert                    2037     2415    2961     2471    3889     4355     5523    5908     6232   -     980    1149     1509    1206     1823     1941    2416     5083    3924        1838     2237    3038     2364    3085     4072    4896     4896     54688&#13;
tees DObt ServIce Blie                31.6    25.1     26.5     27.4    69.7     1.       14.4    16.1     14.5       42.0     48.5     48.6    43.   4   5. 7   43.2     45.6    57.0     56.9        26.4     30.0    27.7     28.1    26.6     53.3    25.      29.2     32 337&#13;
not Dbt Service Retle                 293-2.            48      25.5    67.'3    15.     10.8     11.5      7.0       29.5     38.4   .2.8      29.8     25.3     266     306      25.0    24.3        25.5     29.3    26.      26.9    34.2     51.     24.      26.7.    38.1&#13;
* GasSanox       Debt                                  11252            12306    13178   14263    15554    16432       5395     4081     8095    4190     6210    7373 -   9040   10760    12529                         2443             3193     5476    6896     8589    10223&#13;
a.t Extrnl Debt                                       19181            11743    12703   11738    10579     9764       2698     2862     3278    2944     5849    6635     7998     9535   10284                         1131             2216     4784    5215     6748     8106&#13;
Cees Extione    Productt             27001    58950   64786   602.32   71374    85327- 91516    184309   117520       70       8559     9 412   8426    10968   130      12854    13692   15332       34392   26595    29224    26738   58100    39882   43679    50137   573&#13;
fnsEtetnl Debt bRie                -                17.4             17.4     15.4    15.6     14.9     14.0       46.9     47.3    54.1     49e-0    58.6    19.7     70.3     78.8    81.7                          8.4              8.8     13.7    15.8     17.1     18.1&#13;
a.t Exenal Debt Satto      -   --                      15.7             16.5     14.9     12.8    10.1      8.3        36.9    33.4    354.8    34.9     46.0     52.1    62.2     69.8    66.6                          3.9              6.1     12.0     11.9    13.4     14.2&#13;
KOR EA                                                                     SI NG APO0RE                                                                         T A IWA R&#13;
Mee     Debt Service                   332     481      531      421     751      958     1359    1868     2581         4       156      316     172      389     522      377     408      711         138      178     230      108     256      540     624      659      855&#13;
at Debt    evc                         309     380      490      593     849      911     1289    1714     2278      -3-9        60      179      87      207      ill     189      153     328          98      130     139      122      92      211     470      47       479&#13;
re4ds    orte-                 1060     1618     3215    1984     4453    5071     7693     9986   12654        1755     2181    5810     2515    5785     5377    6584     8342    10134        1998    2914     4575    3095     5518    5302     8156    983449  12644&#13;
GM. Debt.Ssrvoce Belie                31.3    24.8     16.5     21.5    16.9     18.9     17.7    18.5     20.2         2.5     7.2      8.8     6.0      6.7     6.0      5.7      4.9     0.0         6.9      6.0     5.7      6.1     4.6      6.8      7.7     7.0-     6.8&#13;
akt Debt -Sevc    Salle               29.2    235.     10.2    20.0     15.9     18.0     18.8    17.2     18.0       -2.2.     2.8      5.0     2.7      3.8     2.1      2.8      1.6     3.2         4.9     4.5      3.2      4.0     1.7      4.0      5.8     4.8      3.8&#13;
Ge     Externl Debt                                    3556             6693     6847     7379    0622    11992                          459              558     800      772     1089    1120                         1281             1535     2252    3030     3521     3903&#13;
abt Exteral Debt                                     -2667              4546     5515     5746    5989     9441                        -1827            -2254   -2407    -2592    -2769   -4183                          158              346     1083     1428    2074     2394&#13;
tee   Natloex   Prodct               15989    16416   20139    17208   23775- 27884     33316    40070    47998        2739    3209     3686    3211     4384    5028     5620    4478     7597        8793    10250   12138    10394   53391- 15033     17636    20266    24527&#13;
Gra    External Debt SatIn                             17.6             19.7     21.7     22.0    21.5     23.9                         12.5             13.0     11.9    13.7     16.8    14.7                         10.6             -11.5    15.0     17.2    17.6     15.9&#13;
at Externa    Debt Satin                               13.2             19.1     19.8     17.1    14.9     19.7                        -49.6            -32.4   -47.9    -46.1   -42.7    -55.1-                         1.3              2.6      7.2      8.1    10.2      9.8&#13;
9-ercs I Bnds, Internt PeYntot          end Receipte   Table 1.&#13;
Anttieetion Ssrre Bldirg: Infteratonl             o-tar   Pond, Interntinol Pi      Lsoal Otatitice,.   -L-.c 8-canoe&#13;
GNP In Curret Price.: Wend Bank det bent.&#13;
OronaEntirel Dets NaionalPeregn Asac-et Canter        o-PClits          xenl      etPste,WOnehigton D.C., Jscnr             1900.&#13;
Note:   Crosa ceterl debt Ionle'Se     public xe all ne    rivte debt; cet rsveandefined an the an              of lcrei9   orch.ege ho1ldto;&#13;
geld crere     a  nmd by nationl aetbeitire, 108 holdOnge. ron-o            poeitin ntb lbs Internti-nl Monear          Pod, lose toe of Putd credit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
EDOiSTIC EKPENDITURN ERAaE. INI(NAI         AIA-GUrPUT RATIOS AND GN        ME RSAES&#13;
1964-73      1971-73     1974-76      1977-79     1974-79           1964-73      1971-73     1974-76      1977-79     1974-79          1964-f3      1971-73     1974-76      1977- 79    1974-79&#13;
DOMESTIC  EP1TURIAEAR R GENT!I N Ad                                                                                               B RAZ IL                                                           CHLE&#13;
PrIvate Coosuputtoc            ~~~~63.5     52 .5       48.6         45.4         47.4              71.4        67.6         67.2        68.5         67.9            73.6         73.5         78.5        77.6         79.:2&#13;
Publc Co-uptioo                           13.7         22.9        2B.5         27.4        26.:1             10.6          96          9.3          959.3                       12.2        14.1         13.2         12.4        12.89&#13;
Total Co.s.optien                         79.2         75.5        77.2         72.9        75.5              92.0         77.:4       76.6         77.59       77.2             86.0        B7.6         91.6        8999         909&#13;
Irs.. Onetic Fixed 1ovestoot              20.3        24.0          22.7'       27.4        24.5              1B.0         22.6        23.4         22.1        22.0             14 .0       12.4         10.4         10.1         9.1&#13;
locretoco io Stock                        -0.5         0.5     ~    0.1        -0.2          0.0               N/A         N/A          N/A         N/A          N/A              NIA        9R/A          N/A         N/A          N/A&#13;
Gross De-tis 1ovotast                     20.8        24.5         22.8         27.2-       24.5              18.0         22.6        23.4         22.1        22.8             14.0         12.4        10.4         10.1         9.1&#13;
INVESTMENT CAPITAL-IUTPU7I RATIOS          4.3         5.5         20.4          9.9        13.0               2.3         1.7          3.1         4.3          3.6              6.2         6.7      j 15.3          1.2          2.8&#13;
GROWTHRAWnS (coos.taut prices)&#13;
Gross Naticul Product                      4.7          4.9         0.9          1.9          1.2              8.0         12.1         7.3          3.3         6.3              3.7          1.6        -2.4          9.0         3.6&#13;
Populttiso                                 1.4         1.3         8.3     3      1          1.                29          2.28                      2.          2.               1.9         1.7          1.7          1.7         1.7&#13;
Per CapIta GEP           3.3   -      3.5        ~~~~~        ~~~~         ~~~-0.4  0.6  -0.1  5.    .2H45                          .          3.1.8                        -0.1        -4.1          7.3          1.9&#13;
DOMESTIC ESPENIITIMRE ENARES&#13;
(is correctpico&#13;
PiaeCoosuoptico                       73.2        72.3         72.3        66.          70.6              72.3        72.1         65.1        64.5         64.9             75.5        73.5         73.6        73.3         73.4&#13;
Public   osoto                             7.2         8.1          7.2          7.19        7.2               7.8          8.5        10.6         11.6        11.0             13.7        14.2         14.2         12.6        13.5&#13;
Total Cooouoptlou                         80.4         80.3        79.5         76.0        77.8              90.1         80.6        75.7         76.1        75.9             89.2         87.7        87.7        95.9         87.0&#13;
Groso D-toeic Flood 1sveotmet             18.0         18.7        18.9         20.5        19.7              19.9         19.0        21.3         21.2        21.3             10.8         10.0        12.1         14.2        12.9&#13;
locroase to Stock.                         1.6         1            2.6          3.5         3.0               N/A         0.4          2.9         2.7          2.9              N/A         2.3          0.2        -0.1          0.1&#13;
Groe.. D-utic 1-vet-set                   19.6         19.7        20.5         24.0        22.2              19.9         19.4        24.3         23.9        24.1             10.8         12.3        12.3         14.1        13.0&#13;
INCRENENTAL CAPITAL-OUTPUff RATIOS         3.6         2.8          3.8          2.9         5.2               3.1         3.0          3.8          5.5         4.1              9.6       -11.0          3.6         3.3          3:4&#13;
QBRflHI.RATES (co...tast prico.)&#13;
Growth Natloosi Product                    5.6          7.0         4.6          6.6         5.5               6.4          6.0         3.3          5.9         4.2              1.2        -1.5          3.3          5.0         3.9&#13;
PopulotiL..                                2.7          2.3         2.3          2.2         2.3               3.2         3.2          3.3          3.3         3.3              0.8         0.2          0.2          0.7         0.&#13;
Per CaPita GNP                             2.9         4.7          2.3          4.4         3.2          -    3.2          2.7         0            2.5         0.9              0.4        I1.6          3.1         4.3          3.4'&#13;
IN DI A                                                            I SR A EL                                                     Y0UG 0 SLAV I A&#13;
DINtESIC.~ EEENIT      SNARES&#13;
(is curet priceT&#13;
Privote Cosocoptiso                       73.1         72.7        69.6         68.0        68.9              52.8        45.6 -       45.7        49.7         47.6             53.2        55.5         53.6         50.0        52.2&#13;
Public Cosocopliss                         9.2         9.4          94           9.7         9.5              24.4        28.5         31.3         29.5        30.5             16.9        15.9         16.6         16.6        16.6&#13;
Total-Cos...qwtios                        82.3         82.1        798.9        77.7        79.4              77.2         74.0        77.1         79.1        78.1             70.1        71.4.        70.2         66.6        69.7&#13;
Groso lomatic Fined 1ovetosot             17.7         15.3        17.0         20.0        18.2              22.9         24.8        21.9         19.5        20.8             29.9        26.7         27.7         31.4        29.2&#13;
Cb.sge Io Stocks                          NIA'          2.6         4.2          2.3         3.5              N/A           1.3         1.0          1.4         1.2             NIA          19           2.3          22          2.2&#13;
Groee loeteric Investoent -    .17.7  -     17.9       - 21.1   -    22.2         21.6              22.8        26.0         22.9  -  -  20.9-179     21.9 22.3 21.629.98         229.62.29.9.33.4.931.3&#13;
INCREMENTL CAFITAL-OTrPUT RATIOS       I   5.8         9.9          4.4          5.3         4.9               2.7         3.2         11.0          7.1         9.8              5.3         3.9          4.3          4.4         4.4&#13;
GRO           (cosoES tost price)&#13;
Growth Natlosal Product                    3.4          1.5         4.2          3.7         4.3               8.2          8.9         2.6          3.3         2.3              6.2          5.6         5.1          6.5         5.7&#13;
_,. Pplotioo-.                               2.3         2.1          2.0         2.0          2.0               3.1         3.2          2.5    -    2.2          2.3 -1.0                     1.0          0.     09                0.9     -&#13;
Per Capita GNP                                                                               230                                                                                 521.1  -0.6  2.2  1.7  235.1  5.7  0.1  1.2  00 - 5249  4.2  5.6  4.&#13;
ICIETICEXPNDIURESNARES&#13;
Private Cossuptios                        69.8        67.2         63.3         59.1        61.2              69.9         55.4        54.9         56.6        55.7             57.9        54.6         52.9         52.6        52.&#13;
PublIc Coseuputiso                         92          9.        - 00           10.9        10.4              10.8         10.2     -   9.4         10.1         9.7             17.5        16.91.51.                             15.&#13;
Totol Cosesoptios                         79.0         77.0       '73.2         70.1        71.6      -       79.7         65.6        64.3         66.8        65.5             75.4         71 .5       67.2         6,8.9       69.2&#13;
Groos D-etic Fixed 1ovestiset             19.4         21.2        23.6         28.9        25.7              20.3         30.9        32.1         31.4        31.7             24.6        25.3         29.6         27.9        28.:2&#13;
Iscrese. is Stocks                         1.6         1.8          3.2          19          2.               N/A           3.4         3.6          1.9         2.7             N/A          3.4          4.2         3.3          3.9&#13;
Grs    sisi     ooto  est                21.0         23.0         26.         29.9         29.4              20.3        34.4         35.7        33.2         34.5            24.6         285         3.31-                     31.9&#13;
IINCREOENTAL. CAPITAL-GI7rPUr RATIOS       2.1          2.4          2.7         3.1          2.9              1.9          2.6          5.5         3.4          4.2          -  2.5          1.8        .4.1          2.7          3.1&#13;
GROWTN RATES (cotast prices)&#13;
Growth Naticol Product                     9.1          8.9        -89          10.1        10.1              10.5         10.4         6.3          8.8  -      7.5              9.6         11.2         4.4   -      9.6         7.6&#13;
Pupulotiun                                 2.2 -       2.           1.9          1.8         1.9               1.9          1.7         1.3          1.1         1.3              2.3  -      2.1          1.9          1.9         2.0&#13;
Per Capita GNP                             6.9         6.08         7.0          8.3         9.3     -         8.6          8.6         4.8          7.6         6.1              7.3         9.1          2.5          7.7         5.5&#13;
Sourc:   World Bask data bass.&#13;
Nstse: 9/1979 data oct ovtllableo        espeodltu-   shre..&#13;
of  -scrwetal capital output   rto     bwsbees calculated by ssuos9a        s   year  lag hotwon tnvestset andloutput; the&#13;
rati .sr 1971-73, for esol, hoe bees derived by dividlog the s- of gross fixed capital fo-ustios is 1970. 1971. 1972&#13;
-by the  incresest is GNP, batwees -1970 sod 1973, both a-urd Lo cos..tost price..&#13;
/Grouch rtes have bees calculated by regressIo      sua lysis froc the Year pre...dioB  tbor iudicated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
All three countries continued with outward-oriented policies in the years&#13;
following the quadrupling of petroleum prices and the world recession. In&#13;
Korea, quantitative import restrictions were liberalized and tariffs were&#13;
lowered in 1973 and in 1977. The resulting reductions in import protection&#13;
appear to have been greater than reductions export subsidies which occurred&#13;
through the elimination of tax benefits on income derived from exports and&#13;
decreases in wastage allowances on imported inputs used in export&#13;
production. Also, new facilities were established for medium-term and long-&#13;
term export credits.!'&#13;
Import liberalization proceeded more rapidly in Taiwan than in Korea&#13;
while reductions in tariffs were smaller in magnitude. In turn, Singapore had&#13;
practically no import restrictions and further reduced its already low&#13;
tariffs. And, both Singapore and Taiwan instituted new facilities for medium-&#13;
term and long-term export credit.&#13;
At the same time, there are differences among the three countries in&#13;
regard to the macro-economic policies followed as well as the course of the&#13;
real exchange rate. Korea increased reliance on foreign borrowing in order to&#13;
overcome the adverse effects of external shocks it suffered in 1974. At the&#13;
same time, it ensured that the incremental inflow of capital was invested&#13;
rather than consumed by providing investment incentives, reducing the&#13;
government deficit, and re-establishing positive real interest rates. These&#13;
measures contributed to the increase in the share of investment in aggregate&#13;
expenditure from 23 percent in 1971-73 and to 27 percent in 1974-76.&#13;
1/ Exporters continued to benefit from the duty free entry of these inputs.&#13;
While officially the prior exemption system on imported inputs was transformed&#13;
into a drawback system, involving the payment and subsequent rebate of duties,&#13;
in practice payments were not made.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 5 -&#13;
With the rapid rise of investment, Korea expanded production for export&#13;
as well as for domestic markets. Notwithstanding the appreciation of the&#13;
exchange rate vis-a-vis the U.S. dollar from its undervalued "1972" level,&#13;
increases in exports and import substitution, taken together, offset the&#13;
adverse effects of external shocks on Korea's balance of payments in 1975,&#13;
eliminating the need for additional net external financing.&#13;
Following the liberalization of imports, export expansion assumed&#13;
increased importance relative to import substitution while the two effects&#13;
combined came to exceed the adverse balance-of-payments effects of external&#13;
shocks by more than four times in 1977. Although higher GNP growth rates added&#13;
$1.0 billion to the import bill, and Korea continued to suffer the effects of&#13;
adverse external shocks, additional net external financing reached $-3.3&#13;
billion as a result.&#13;
The increase in the share of investment in aggregate expenditure from 27&#13;
percent in 1974-76 to 30 percent in 1977-79 importantly contributed to the&#13;
acceleration of economic growth in Korea. Notwithstanding the increased&#13;
investment effort, however, export shares did not rise further and negative&#13;
import substitution (i.e. an increase in import shares) occurred in 1978,&#13;
largely as a result of the continued appreciation of the real exchange rate&#13;
and the domestic expansionary measures applied that maintained rapid rates of&#13;
economic growth at the cost of increased inflationary pressures.      These&#13;
influences, combined with credit allocation favoring large, capital-intensive&#13;
investments in intermediate products, led to a decline in the volume of&#13;
exports in 1979.&#13;
1/ The real exchange rate vis-a-vis the U.S. dollar was 84 percent of its&#13;
"1972" level in 1977 and 81 percent in 1978; in the two years, the real value&#13;
of the money supply increased by 29 percent and 12 percent, respectively.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
Additional net external financing was nearly offset by the trend value of&#13;
the resource gap in 1977,!/ so that actual net external financing was&#13;
practically nil. With unfavorable developments in trade, net external&#13;
financing reached $0.7 billion in 1978 while total external financing was $1.7&#13;
billion. Also, Korea's gross debt service ratio (interest payments and&#13;
amortization expressed as a proportion of the value of merchandise exports)&#13;
increased from 17 percent in 1973 to 20 percent in 1978 while the ratio of the&#13;
(gross) external debt to GNP rose from 18 percent to 25 percent 2/&#13;
Taiwan let its real exchange rate appreciate by 23 percent in 1974 as&#13;
compared to its "1972" level, leading to a decline in export market shares and&#13;
to negative import substitution. These unfavorable changes in trade flows&#13;
aggravated the effects on economic growth of the deflationary policies&#13;
applied, involving a decline in the real value of the money supply by 24&#13;
percent in 1974. As a result, economic growth came practically to a halt&#13;
whereas the 41 percent increase in wholesale prices in 1974 was followed by a&#13;
5 percent decline in 1975.&#13;
Savings in imports associated with the decline in the rate of economic&#13;
growth did not fully offset the adverse balance-of-payments effects of losses&#13;
in export market shares and negative import substitution in 1974.&#13;
Correspondingly, Taiwan's additional net external financing requirements&#13;
1/ The high value of the resource gap reflects the fact that the "1972" trade&#13;
deficit would have increased further if import and export trends observed in&#13;
the preceding decade continued.&#13;
2/ Table 5 also provides information on the net debt service ratio, derived&#13;
by deducting interest receipts from debt. service obligations, and the net&#13;
external debt ratio, obtained by. adjusting gross external debt for the net&#13;
value of reserves. These ratios will be referred to in cases when they show&#13;
results substantially different from the gross ratios.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
exceeded the negative effects of external shocks, necessitating large foreign&#13;
borrowing. The situation changed in subsequent years as the policies applied&#13;
encouraged new investment and improved Taiwan's competitive position.&#13;
To begin with, real interest rates rose to 19 percent in 1975 when&#13;
wholesale prices declined and it remained in the 7-9 percent range in the&#13;
following years. Also, increased investment incentives were provided through&#13;
amendments to the Statute for Encouragement of Investment and there was a&#13;
surplus in the government budget. Finally, Taiwan's real exchange rate&#13;
depreciated from year to year, exceeding the 1973 level, and approaching the&#13;
"1972" average, towards the end of the period.&#13;
As a result, the share of gross domestic investment in aggregate&#13;
expenditure increased from 28 percent in 1971-73 to 33 percent in 1974-76,&#13;
with a decline to 31 percent in 1977-79 due largely to the decline in the rate&#13;
of inventory accumulation. The rise in the rate of investment and&#13;
improvements in its competitive position, in turn, contributed to increases in&#13;
export shares and import substitution in Taiwan. At the same time, in&#13;
conjunction with the liberalization of imports, export promotion assumed&#13;
greater importance vis-a-vis import substitution.&#13;
These influences contributed to the acceleration of economic growth in&#13;
Taiwan. Its gross national product grew at an average annual rate of 10&#13;
percent after 1975 while it hardly changed in the previous two years. Still,&#13;
due to the slowdown in earlier years, Taiwan continued to experience import&#13;
savings. All in all, the balance of payments impact of domestic economic&#13;
policies affecting exports, import substitution, and the rate of economic.&#13;
growth exceeded the adverse effects of external shocks more than five times in&#13;
1978.&#13;
Correspondingly, additional net external financing became increasingly&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
negative and amounted to $-3.0 billion in 1978. Adjusted for the trend value&#13;
of the resource gap, actual net external financing was $-1.9 billion, and&#13;
total external financing $-1.4 billion, representing largely the repayment of&#13;
foreign debt. In the same year, the gross debt service ratio was 7 percent,&#13;
only slightly exceeding the 6 percent ratio in 1973 while the gross external&#13;
debt ratio was 16 percent as compared to 11 percent in 1973.&#13;
The real exchange rate in Singapore fell by 20 percent between '1972" and&#13;
1974 and increased only slightly in 1975. While exports continued to benefit&#13;
from subsidies, reductions in import tariffs aggravated the effects of the&#13;
appreciation of the real exchange rate giving rise to negative import&#13;
substitution, and a slowdown in economic growth. Growth was further slowed by&#13;
deflationary policies, although these were much less far-reaching than in&#13;
Taiwan, with the real value of the money supply declining by 11 percent in&#13;
1974.&#13;
In 1974 and 1975, taken together, the net balance-of-payments effects of&#13;
domestic economic policies added slightly to the adverse effects of external&#13;
shocks in Singapore, thus raising external financing requirements. Financing&#13;
took the form of the acceleration of the growth of foreign direct investment&#13;
and the clandestine inflow of portfolio capital that shows up in the errors&#13;
and omissions item. Political stability in Singapore was attractive to&#13;
foreign investors and direct investment was further motivated by increased&#13;
incentives through the extension of the tax-exempt status of pioneer&#13;
industries from five to ten years and the establishment of the Capital&#13;
Assistance Scheme to furnish capital to skill-intensive industries. At the&#13;
same time, the inflow of foreign capital permitted maintaining gross&#13;
investment at over one-third of aggregate expenditure.&#13;
The real exchange rate depreciated in subsequent years, surpassing the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
1973 level by one-tenth, although falling short of the "1972" average in about&#13;
the same proportion. Improvements in Singapore's competitive position were&#13;
translated into rising export shares while negative import substitution&#13;
continued during the period under consideration as tariffs were further&#13;
reduced. With the effects of export pomotion exceeding negative import&#13;
substitution, and high investment shares being maintained, the rate of&#13;
economic growth accelerated. Nevertheless, Singapore continued to experience&#13;
import savings due to the slowdown in the rate of economic growth in the early&#13;
part of the period.&#13;
Given the positive net balance-of-payments effects of domestic economic&#13;
policies, additional net external financing requirements were considerably&#13;
lower than the balance-of-payments effects of external shocks. With the trend&#13;
value of the resource gap being small, actual net external financing was $0.7&#13;
billion while interest and dividend payments raised total external financing&#13;
to $1.2 billion. Much of external financing continued to take the form of&#13;
direct investments, and the gross debt service ratio declined from 9 percent&#13;
in 1973 to 7 percent in 1978. And while the ratio of the gross external debt&#13;
to GNP rose from 13 percent to 15 percent, Singapore's net reserves continued&#13;
to exceed its gross external debt nearly three times.&#13;
Argentina, Brazil, Colombia, and Mexico&#13;
In 1974, the balance-of-payments effects of external shocks represented 4&#13;
percent of GNP in Brazil, 1 percent in Mexico and Colombia, and practically&#13;
nil in Argentina. After increases in 1975, when adverse changes in the terms&#13;
of trade reinforced the impact of the world recession, these ratios declined&#13;
until 1977, with a small deterioration occurring in 1978, Argentina&#13;
excepted. The relevant ratios for 1978 were: Brazil, 2 percent; Mexico, 1&#13;
percent; Argentina, -1 percent; and Colombia, -2 percent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
The four Latin American countries did not continue with reforms towards&#13;
greater outward orientation during the period under consideration. Brazil and&#13;
Colombia, in fact, increased the bias against exports through greater import&#13;
protection and reduced export subsidies, respectively. Furthermore, Colombia&#13;
let its real exchange rate to increasingly appreciate vis-a-vis the U.S.&#13;
dollar. In the early part of the period, the exchange rate was overvalued&#13;
also in Argentina and Mexico while there was little change in relative&#13;
incentives to exports and to import substitution in the two countries.&#13;
At the same time, there were differences among the countries of the&#13;
second group in regard to the macro-economic policies applied. In Brazil, the&#13;
immediate response to external shocks was to increase foreign borrowing for&#13;
the sake of maintaining a high rate of economic growth. In the years 1974 and&#13;
1975, taken together, the deterioration of the balance of payments resulting&#13;
from external shocks was fully financed from abroad; increases in export&#13;
market shares were offset by the rise in imports associated with higher GNP&#13;
growth rates; and import substitution was practically nil.&#13;
Apart from permitting continued increases in domestic consumption, the&#13;
amounts borrowed were employed to finance large investments in infrastructure&#13;
and in highly capital-intensive industries producing intermediate goods for&#13;
the domestic market. In turn, private investments in machinery industries&#13;
were promoted through the increased application of credit preferences while&#13;
real interest rates turned negative.&#13;
Measures aimed at reducing imports included increases in tariffs, advance&#13;
deposit requirements, and import restrictions. Notwithstanding the&#13;
introduction of some new export incentives, the net effects of the measures&#13;
applied was to increase the bias against exports and in favor of import&#13;
substitution. At the same time, the real value of the cruzeiro in terms of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
the U.S. dollar changed relatively little.&#13;
The application of these measures led to considerable import substitution&#13;
that came to exceed the combined balance-of-payments effects of external&#13;
shocks after 1976, when additional net external financing turned negative.&#13;
This result should, however, be considered in the light of the increased&#13;
burden of interest payments and dividends that rose from $1.0 billion in&#13;
"1972" to $2 billion in 1974, approached $3 billion in 1976 and was nearly $5&#13;
billion in 1978, raising total external financing requirements to $7.6&#13;
billion.&#13;
With the amortization of foreign loans adding to the debt service burden,&#13;
the gross debt service ratio rose from 43 percent in 1973 to 68 percent in&#13;
1978 whereas the gross external debt ratio increased from 14 percent to 24&#13;
percent. In turn, the rate of growth of GNP declined after 1976, reflecting&#13;
the effects of investments in capital intensive industries, the decline in the&#13;
rate of domestic saving associated with the maintenance of negative interest&#13;
rates, the distortions due to accelerating inflation brought about by&#13;
expansionary policies, and the deflationary policies followed between mid-1977&#13;
and mid-1978.&#13;
In Mexico, additional net external financing exceeded the balance-of-&#13;
payments effects of external shocks by a considerable margin throughout the&#13;
period under consideration. This result obtained as savings in imports&#13;
associated with lower GNP growth rates did not suffice to offset the&#13;
deterioration of the balance of payments resulting from losses in export&#13;
market shares and negative import substitution.&#13;
Decreases in export market shares and negative import substitution show&#13;
the direct and indirect effects of expansionary pblicies followed by the&#13;
Echeverria Administration from 1972. These policies entailed rapid increases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
in government expenditures without corresponding increases in revenues. As a&#13;
result, the budget deficit, expressed as a proportion of GNP, increased from 1&#13;
percent in 1971 to 4 percent in 1974; it was between 3 and 4 percent of GNP in&#13;
the following two years.&#13;
The budget deficit was financed by money creation!.   and by foreign&#13;
borrowing. Money creation gave rise to rapid inflation and to the&#13;
deterioration of Mexico's competitiveness that is not fully reflected by real&#13;
exchange rates calculated by reference to relative prices. This is because,&#13;
in Mexico's relatively open economy, increases in wages could not be fully&#13;
translated into higher prices.&#13;
The decline in Mexico's competitiveness was not offset by a devaluation&#13;
until September 1976. The devaluation, and the restrictive monetary policies&#13;
adopted by the Administration of Lopez Portillo in 1977, with the real value&#13;
of the money supply decreasing by 11 percent, led to reductions in import&#13;
shares. However, increases in fuel exports apart, there was little&#13;
improvement in export performance as the abolition of export subsidies largely&#13;
offset the effects of the devaluation.&#13;
Expansionary policies were adopted again in 1978, when the real value of&#13;
the money supply increased by 13 percent and th e-budget deficit approached 5&#13;
percent of GNP. With pressures on domestic capacity and the,appreciation of&#13;
the real exchange rate, the extent of negative import substitution increased&#13;
to a considerable extent in 1978. This increase was only partly offset by the&#13;
rise of petroleum exports and improvements in market shares .for manufactured&#13;
exports, reflecting the effects of the re-introduction of export subsidies.&#13;
1/ Apart from a small decline in 1974, the real value of the money supply&#13;
increased at rates ranging from 4 percent to 15 percent between 1971 and 1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
As a result of these changes, Mexico's additional net external financial&#13;
requirements increased again in 1978. This increase was largely offset by the&#13;
rise in tourist earnings and private transfers, so that actual net external&#13;
financing was practically zero in 1978. Interest payments on debt contracted&#13;
after 1971 and, to a lesser extent, dividend payments, however, gave rise to&#13;
total external financing of $3.0 billion that was largely met by additional&#13;
foreign borrowing.&#13;
With continued foreign borrowing, Mexico's gross external debt ratio&#13;
increased from 16 percent in 1973 to 36 percent in 1978. In the same period,&#13;
the gross debt service ratio rose from 67 percent to 113 percent. And while&#13;
adding tourist revenue to merchandise exports would lower the latter ratio to&#13;
72 percent, tourist revenue in Mexico is in large part offset by tourist&#13;
expenditures abroad.&#13;
In Colombia, the adverse effects of external shocks were aggravated by&#13;
negative import substitution in 1974 as the real exchange rate appreciated by&#13;
4 percent as compared to the "1972" average. In the following year, however,&#13;
import shares declined in response to the deflationary policies followed, with&#13;
the real value of the money supply falling by 13 percent in 1974 and by 4&#13;
percent in 1975. Colombia also experienced increases in export market shares&#13;
in 1975, due to the release of coffee from stockpiles as coffee prices rose&#13;
towards the end of the year.&#13;
With the rapid rise of coffee prices, the balance-of-payments effects of&#13;
external shocks turned positive in 1976 and increased further in 1977, with a&#13;
small decline in 1978. The opportunities provided by improvements in the&#13;
balance of payments were not utilized, however, to accelerate the rate, of&#13;
economic growth in Colombia. Rather, the policy measures applied adversely&#13;
affected the competitiveness of the noncoffee sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34&#13;
To begin with, the authorities limited the rate of crawl of the exchange&#13;
rate, notwithstanding the acceleration of inflation occasioned by the rise in&#13;
the money supply as the credit measures taken did not suffice to offset the&#13;
effects of the increase in foreign exchange reserves on domestic money&#13;
holdings.1/ After remaining unchanged in 1975, the real exchange rate&#13;
appreciated vis-a-vis the U.S. dollar by 5 percent in 1976, 11 percent in&#13;
1977, and 2 percent in 1978, bringing it one-fifth below the "1972" level.&#13;
The adverse effects on exports of the appreciation of the exchange rate&#13;
were aggravated by reductions in subsidies while only modest measures of&#13;
import liberalization were taken. With the increased bias against exports,&#13;
Colombia's export market share in manufactured goods declined by nearly one-&#13;
half. Furthermore, fuel exports increasingly gave place to imports,&#13;
reflecting the effects of the policies applied in earlier years that were&#13;
inimical to new exploration. At the same time, little change was shown in&#13;
traditional and in nontraditional primary exports except that releases from&#13;
stockpiles raised the volume of coffee exports again in 1978.&#13;
The appreciation of the real exchange rate also led to negative import&#13;
substitution in Colombia after 1975. The adverse balance-of-payments effects&#13;
of declines in export shares and negative import substitution offset the&#13;
favorable effects of external shocks in the years 1976 to 1978, on the&#13;
average, while the maintenance of past GNP growth rates did not have&#13;
differential effects on imports.&#13;
Correspondingly, additional net external financing was practically zero&#13;
in Colombia in the years 1976 to 1978 combined. Due largely to smuggling that&#13;
1/ The money supply increased by 10 percent in 1976, 3 percent in 1977, and 6&#13;
percent in 1978 in real terms.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
is included under non-factor services, there was nevertheless a surplus in the&#13;
actual resource gap that was only partly offset by interest and dividend&#13;
payments. With continued small borrowing abroad, Colombia accumulated nearly&#13;
$2 billion of reserves between 1975 and 1978, reducing its net external debt&#13;
ratio from 13 percent to 4 percent. In the same period, the gross external&#13;
debt ratio decreased from 17 percent to 15 percent while the gross debt&#13;
service ratio fell from 32 percent to 18 percent (there was little change in&#13;
these ratios between 1973 and 1975).&#13;
In Argentina, internal shocks predominated during the period under&#13;
consideration. As a result of the expansionary monetary and fiscal policies&#13;
followed,.the real value of the money supply rose by 33 percent in 1973 and by&#13;
46 percent in 1974 while the budget deficit increased from 2 to 3 percent of&#13;
GNP in the early seventies to 5 percent in 1973 and to 6 percent in 1974.. The&#13;
government attempted to offset the inflationary effects of these policies on&#13;
the trade balance by successive devaluations, but it only succeeded to&#13;
accelerate the wage-price spiral as labor unions and other interest groups&#13;
were able to maintain, and even to increase, their real incomes.&#13;
Correspondingly, the real exchange rate appreciated by 14 percent in 1973 and&#13;
6 percent in 1974; it was 12 percent below its 1972" level in the latter&#13;
year.&#13;
Further devaluations in 1975 were accompanied by price and wage controls,&#13;
giving rise to the depreciation of the real exchange rate in that year-. This&#13;
proved temporary, however, as prices and wages rebounded once the controls&#13;
were lifted. The increase in the ratio of the governmental budget deficit to&#13;
12 percent of GNP in 1975 further contributed to inflation, with the wholesale&#13;
price index rising at an average annual. rate of 300 percent between the fourth&#13;
quarters of 1974 and 1975 and approaching 1000 percent in early 1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
Rapid inflation caused considerable dislocation, leading to the fall of&#13;
GNP in 1975 and, again, in the first quarter of 1976. With declines in export&#13;
market shares aggravating the effects of external shocks, Argentina also&#13;
suffered large losses in foreign exchange reserves that raised questions about&#13;
its creditworthiness. The new government, which came to power in March 1976,&#13;
attempted to remedy the situation by introducing a policy package including&#13;
deflationary monetary measures, increases in interest rates, reductions in the&#13;
deficit in the government budget, wage control, and devaluation accompanied by&#13;
reductions in export taxes on traditional primary exports.&#13;
Reductions in export taxes and the depreciation of the real exchange&#13;
rate, attendant on the doubling of the peso-dollar rate in the last quarter of&#13;
1976, had their full impact on exports only in 1977. The expansion of exports&#13;
was concentrated in traditional and nontraditional primary commodities, while&#13;
Argentina continued to lose market shares in manufactured goods where export&#13;
incentives were below their pre-1973 level. It also experienced continued&#13;
import substitution as reductions in tariffs had little effect, given the high&#13;
level of tariff redundancy.&#13;
Increases in exports and import substitution, together with the rise of&#13;
investment activity reflecting greater confidence, contributed to economic&#13;
expansion in 1977. But, the government was unable to restrain wages and it&#13;
continued to run a budget deficit, albeit at a reduced rate. Following a&#13;
four-month "price truce," in which the largest industrial firms participated,&#13;
prices responded to the rising cost of labor. While earlier rates of&#13;
inflation were not again reached, wholesale prices rose at an average annual&#13;
rate of 150 percent in both 1977 and 1978.&#13;
The distortions caused by high rates of inflation contributed to the fall&#13;
of GNP in 1978, thereby lessening import requirements. With reduced pressure&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
on domestic capacity, import shares also declined but this was offset by a&#13;
fall in export shares as the real exchange rate appreciated again. At the&#13;
same time, Argentina benefited from favorable external shocks in the form of&#13;
improvements in its terms of trade and increases in foreign demand for its&#13;
traditional exports. As a result of these influences, additional net external&#13;
financing increasingly turned negative. With the negative trend value of the&#13;
resource gap, reflecting the assumption that earlier trade surpluses&#13;
continued, actual net external financing became even more negative, giving&#13;
rise to considerable reserve accumulation and the repayment of loans.&#13;
Loan repayments explain the high gross debt service ratio in 1978 (49&#13;
percent) that followed a decline from the peak reached in 1975 (34 percent) to&#13;
23 percent in 1977, when it equalled the 1973 figure. In turn, the gross&#13;
external debt ratio increased from 7 percent in 1973 to 10 percent in 1978&#13;
while the net external debt ratio declined from 5 percent to 3 percent,&#13;
reflecting the accumulation of reserves.&#13;
The accumulation of reserves facilitated the task of the government to&#13;
introduce a new economic program. This was done at the end of December 1978,&#13;
involving a slowdown in increases in wages, public utility prices, money&#13;
creation, and the depreciation of the exchange rate, together with the opening&#13;
of capital markets to foreign transactions and a five-year tariff reduction&#13;
plan. The effects of this program were not apparent, however, until the end&#13;
of 1979.&#13;
Israel and Yugoslavia&#13;
In 1974, the combined balance-of-payments effects of external shocks&#13;
amounted to 11 percent of GNP in Israel and 6 percent in Yugoslavia. In both&#13;
countries, the adverse effects of these shocks increased in 1975, declined in&#13;
1976, and increased again afterwards.    In 1978, they equalled 15 percent of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
the gross national product in Israel and 10 percent in Yugoslavia.&#13;
The Israeli economy further suffered the shock of the 1973 Yom Kippur war&#13;
that was followed by increases in the importation of military equipment from&#13;
$0.5 billion in 1972 to $1.9 billion in 1975, approaching one-half of&#13;
nonmilitary imports in that year. Military imports represented about one-half&#13;
of total defense expenditures that amounted to three-tenths of the gross&#13;
national product in 1975.&#13;
Israel as well as Yugoslavia raised the level of import protection,&#13;
thereby increasing the bias against exports, and let the real exchange rate&#13;
appreciate. In Israel, the real exchange rate vis-a-vis the U.S. dollar&#13;
declined to 83 percent of the "1972" level in 1974 and stabilized at 91&#13;
percent in subsequent years. In Yugoslavia, a 10 percent appreciation&#13;
occurred.&#13;
Israel also adopted deflationary policies in response to the shocks it&#13;
experienced. Following increases of 16 percent in 1972 and 11 percent in&#13;
1973, the real value of the money supply fell by 22 percent in 1974 and by 14&#13;
percent in 1975, declining further by 3 percent in 1976. And, after increases&#13;
from 13 percent in 1972 to 29 percent in 1975, the government budget deficit,&#13;
expressed as a proportion of the gross national product, declined to 24&#13;
percent in 1974 and to 21 percent in 1975 and 1976.&#13;
The policies applied led to losses in exports, a fall in the rate of&#13;
investment, and the deceleration of economic growth. Israel's export market&#13;
shares decreased by 21 percent between 1972" and 1976; the share of&#13;
investment in aggregate expenditure declined from 26 percent in 1971-73 to 23&#13;
percent in 1974-76; and the growth rate of GNP fell from 8.2 percent in 1963-&#13;
73 to 2.6 percent in 1973-76. Lower GNP growth rates, in turn, resulted in&#13;
import savings amounting to 3 percent of total imports in 1974, increasing to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
investment while the resulting distortions raised incremental capital-output&#13;
ratios.&#13;
With the gross national product remaining substantially below the level&#13;
it would have reached if earlier trends continued, import savings amounted to&#13;
nearly two-fifths of actual imports in 1978. Increased import savings,&#13;
together with higher export shares and import substitution, offset in large&#13;
part the increase in the balance-of-payments effects of adverse external&#13;
shocks in that year. But, with military imports more than doubling between&#13;
1977 and 1978, actual net external financing reached $1.9 billion in that year&#13;
while total external financing was $2.8 billion. Furthermore, with increased&#13;
indebtedness, the gross external debt ratio rose from 54 percent in 1973 to 82&#13;
percent in 1978. In turn, the gross debt service ratio was maintained below&#13;
40 percent only because Israel could obtain long-term loans in the United&#13;
States.&#13;
Yugoslavia responded to the external shocks it suffered in 1974 by&#13;
adopting deflationary monetary policies that gave rise to a 4 percent decline&#13;
in the real value of the money supply in 1974 after increases of over 20&#13;
percent in the preceding two years. However, the external shocks were not met&#13;
by a devaluation; rather, the nominal exchange rate appreciated vis-a-vis the&#13;
U.S. dollar and the real exchange rate fell by 11 percent.&#13;
The appreciation of the real exchange rate led to losses in export market&#13;
shares and to negative import substitution in Yugoslavia. The adverse impact&#13;
of these changes on the balance of payments was not fully offset by import&#13;
savings associated with the decline in the rate of economic growth resulting&#13;
from the application of deflationary policies. Correspondingly, additional&#13;
net external financial requirements exceeded the balance-of-payments effects&#13;
of external shocks in 1974 and, despite increases in workers' remittances,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
Yugoslavia had to borrow $1.0 billion to finance its resource gap. Borrowing&#13;
requirements changed little in 1975, when import savings at low GNP growth&#13;
rates and reductions in import shares due to the application of import&#13;
restrictions approximately offset the increase in the adverse balance-of-&#13;
payments effects of external shocks.&#13;
In response to the slowdown of economic growth, expansionary policies&#13;
were adopted in 1976, entailing a 51 percent rise in the real value of the&#13;
money supply. These policies were accompanied by further restrictions on&#13;
imports. The resulting decline in import shares, together with decreases in&#13;
the adverse balance-of-payments effects of external shocks, lowered additional&#13;
net external financial requirements to a considerable extent and Yugoslavia&#13;
accumulated reserves in 1976.&#13;
Reserve accumulation remained temporary, however, and Yugoslavia had to&#13;
borrow $1.5 billion in 1977 and $1.3 billion in 1978 as the adverse balance-&#13;
of-payments effects of external shocks increased. At the same time, with the&#13;
acceleration of the rate of economic growth, further import savings did not&#13;
occur while import substitution due to import restrictions was offset by&#13;
declines in export market shares. These declines occurred as the exchange&#13;
rate remained overvalued and there was increased discrimination against export&#13;
activities through import protection and preferential credit allocation to&#13;
import-substituting industries.&#13;
The loss in market shares occurred in traditional primary exports as well&#13;
as in manufactured goods. Within the latter category, the losses were&#13;
concentrated in developed country markets where Yugoslavia's export share&#13;
declined by one-half between "1972" and 1978. This compares with a gain in&#13;
market shares in exports to the centrally-planned economies.&#13;
Yugoslavia-s poor performance in developed country markets led to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
increased indebtedness in convertible currencies. The gross external debt&#13;
ratio rose from 8 percent in 1973 to 18 percent in 1978 while the gross debt&#13;
service ratio increased from 28 percent to 33 percent. The gross debt service&#13;
ratio is raised further if it is compared to merchandise exports in terms of&#13;
convertible currencies alone while it is reduced if workers remittances are&#13;
added to merchandise exports. With these adjustments, the gross debt service&#13;
ratio was 30 percent in 1978. At the same time, a substantial part of foreign&#13;
borrowing went into investment, increasing its share in aggregate expenditure&#13;
from 29 percent in 1971-73 to 30 percent in 1974-76 and 33 percent in 1977-79.&#13;
India, Chile, and Uruguay&#13;
Among countries that followed inward-looking policies during the&#13;
preceding decade, the combined balance-of-payments effects of external shocks&#13;
equalled 2 percent of the gross national product in India, and 5 percent in&#13;
Uruguay in 1974, it was practically nil in Chile. In India, the ratio&#13;
increased in 1975, declined in 1976 and 1977, and returned to approximately&#13;
the 1974 level in 1978. These adverse effects were more than offset, however,&#13;
by increases in workers remittances from the Middle East and in tourist&#13;
receipts.&#13;
In turn, adverse balance-of-payments effects of external shocks increased&#13;
to a considerable extent in Chile and in Uruguay. The rate of these effects&#13;
on GNP reached 10 percent in 1975 in Chile and, after a slight decline in&#13;
1976, increased further in subsequent years, reaching 13 percent in 1978. The&#13;
increase was smaller in Uruguay, where the ratio fluctuated between 6 percent&#13;
and 7 percent, with the former figure applying in 1978.&#13;
India and the two Latin American countries of the group also had&#13;
contrasting experiences as far as incentive policies are concerned. While&#13;
substantive changes in the system of incentives were not made in India, Chile&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
and Uruguay introduced major reforms during the period under consideration.&#13;
These reforms involved substantially reducing the bias against exports,&#13;
raising real exchange rates and real interest rates, reducing budget deficits&#13;
and increasing the role of market forces in general.&#13;
In response to the external shocks suffered in 1974, India adopted&#13;
deflationary policies, with the real value of the money supply falling by 14&#13;
percent in that year. Nevertheless, inflation continued at a higher rate than&#13;
in the United States and it was not fully offset by a devaluation. The&#13;
appreciation of the real exchange rate vis-a-vis the U.S. dollar contributed&#13;
to losses in export market shares and to negative import substitution, the&#13;
adverse balance-of-payments effects of which were offset only in part by the&#13;
import savings associated with the decline in the rate of economic growth&#13;
resulting from the deflationary policies applied. Correspondingly, additional&#13;
net external financing requirements exceeded the adverse balance-of-payments&#13;
of external shocks by a considerable margin.&#13;
This situation continued in subsequent years, except for 1976 when a&#13;
substantial devaluation in real terms led to import substitution in India.&#13;
However, the actual resource gap was much smaller and it turned into a surplus&#13;
of $1.4 billion in 1976 and $1.9 billion in 1977, largely because of the rise&#13;
in workers remittances and tourist receipts. The surplus was translated into&#13;
reserve accumulation in 1976 ($2.2 billion) as well as in 1977 ($2.4 billion)&#13;
that continued at a slightly reduced rate of ($1.7 billion) in 1978. Although&#13;
preliminary data indicate that the surplus in India's resource gap declined to&#13;
$0.4 billion in that year, this was in part offset by increases in official&#13;
grants. With the accumulation of reserves, the net external debt ratio&#13;
declined from 16 percent in 1973 to 8 percent in 1978; in, the same period, the&#13;
gross external debt ratio decreased from 17 percent to 14 percent and the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44&#13;
gross debt service ratio from 27 percent to 15 percent.&#13;
The conservative policies of reserve accumulation were not conducive to&#13;
the acceleration of economic growth. Nevertheless, GNP growth rates rose&#13;
somewhat compared to the 1963-73 period as the performance of agriculture&#13;
improved and the rate of domestic savings increased in response to the rise of&#13;
real interest rates.   There was also negative import substitution in response&#13;
to the trade liberalization measures introduced towards the end of the period.&#13;
Import liberalization was, however, limited to noncompeting imports.&#13;
This benefited, in particular, production for domestic markets through the&#13;
easier availability of imported inputs while exporters already had such&#13;
privileges beforehand. Also, the practical application of export promotion&#13;
measures continued to be plagued by administrative difficulties and the&#13;
incentives actually granted fell far short of the rates of import protection&#13;
as domestically-produced goods faced practically no foreign competition. In&#13;
particular, labor-intensive manufactures received few export incentives,&#13;
although they conform to India's comparative advantage. Correspondingly,&#13;
India continued to lose export market shares, especially in manufactured&#13;
goods, where actual exports fell to 70 percent of hypothetical exports,&#13;
calculated on the assumption of unchanged market shares, in 1978.&#13;
Chile, in turn, abandoned its inward-oriented strategy in favor of&#13;
outward orientation. It abolished all import restrictions and reduced tariffs&#13;
over a five-year period to 10 percent in June 1979, the only exception being&#13;
the automobile industry. Tariff reductions were part of a package of economic&#13;
policies that included a substantial devaluation in real terms, the abolition&#13;
of price control, the establishment of realistic prices for public utilities,&#13;
the. elimination of budget deficits, the establishment of positive real&#13;
interest rates, and the liberalization of financial markets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
The course of the economy in the years immediately following the fall of&#13;
Allende in September 1973 was, however, determined by the deflationary&#13;
policies of the newly-installed Pinochet government. These policies aimed at&#13;
lowering the rate of inflation that reached 500 percent a year; they became&#13;
even more severe in 1975 in response to the terms-of-trade loss Chile suffered&#13;
in that year.&#13;
The policies applied led to a decline in the real value of the money&#13;
supply by 15 percent in 1974 and by 25 percent in 1975 while the government&#13;
budget deficit gave place to a surplus. The continued indexing of wages held&#13;
back the decline in the rate of inflation, however. As measured by the&#13;
adjusted consumer price index prepared by the World Bank, December-to-December&#13;
price increases were 405 percent in 1973, 376 percent in 1974 and 341 percent&#13;
in 1975.&#13;
With the indexing of wages, the brunt of the adjustment fell on the&#13;
unemployed. In conjunction with the 7 percent fall of GNP between 1973 and&#13;
1975, unemployment rose from 5 percent of the labor force in December 1973 to&#13;
14 percent in December 1975 in the Greater Santiago area. Unemployment rates&#13;
fell to 10 percent in December 1976 but declined slowly afterwards as much of&#13;
the subsequent rise in the gross national product was attained through&#13;
increases in the productivity of labor and capital.&#13;
The gross national product rose by 13 percent between 1975 and 1977 and&#13;
by 20 percent between 1977 and 1978, although investment rates remained&#13;
unchanged, reflecting a decline in incremental capital-output ratios. At the&#13;
same time, inflation rates, measured from December to December, fell from 341&#13;
percent in 1975 to 174 percent in 1976, 63 percent in 1977, and 30 percent in&#13;
1978. The decrease in the rate of growth of the money supply was smaller, so&#13;
that real money balances held by firms and individuals were replenished.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
The policies applied further involved substantial increases in the real&#13;
exchange rate, although the extent of appreciation is overstated by the use of&#13;
the (adjusted) consumer price index used in the calculations, by reason of&#13;
declines in retail margins. Still, this index has been utilized because it&#13;
incorporates adjustments for suppressed inflation in the early seventies that&#13;
have not been made in the wholesale price index.&#13;
The depreciation of the real exchange rate led to rapid increases in&#13;
export market shares, with the resulting expansion representing 31 percent of&#13;
total exports in 1978. Increases in market shares were particularly&#13;
pronounced in manufactured goods; in 1978 these exports reached three times&#13;
the level that would have been attained if Chile maintained its "1972" market&#13;
shares. There was also considerable import substitution in response to the&#13;
depreciation of the real exchange rate, but this came to a standstill in 1977,&#13;
and declined afterwards, as tariff reductions increasingly weighed upon&#13;
import-substituting industries. Import savings associated with lower GNP&#13;
growth rates also declined as economic growth accelerated.&#13;
At the same time, the balance-of-payments effects of external shocks&#13;
increased to a considerable extent, necessitating additional net external&#13;
financing. Nevertheless, with rapid increases in GNP, the gross external debt&#13;
ratio hardly surpassed the 1973 level in 1978 (42 percent) while its peak&#13;
level was 48 percent in 1975. The improvement was even greater in terms of&#13;
the net external debt ratio as Chile accumulated reserves. The rise in the&#13;
gross debt service ratio from 42 percent in 1973 to 59 percent in 1978, in&#13;
turn, is fully explained by increased loan repayments that are included under&#13;
amortization.&#13;
In response to the quadrupling of oil prices, deflationary monetary&#13;
policies were adopted in Uruguay, with the real value of the money supply&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
falling by 8 percent between 1973 and 1974. The high rate of inflation also&#13;
led to reductions in the real value of government revenues, however, and the&#13;
budget deficit increased. Also, Uruguay failed to devalue pari passu with&#13;
inflation, and the real exchange rate vis-a-vis the U.S. dollar appreciated by&#13;
8 percent.&#13;
With the fall in the real exchange rate, there was little change in&#13;
export shares and in import substitution, so that Uruguay had to rely on&#13;
foreign borrowing, complemented by reductions in reserves, to finance its&#13;
rising resource gap. Rather than attempting to remedy its external situation&#13;
by deflating further the economy, however, the government opted for a "fuite&#13;
en avant" by introducing reforms that represented a break with the policies&#13;
followed in the preceding decades.&#13;
The policy changes introduced in July 1974 included decontrolling&#13;
domestic prices, eliminating import restrictions, reducing tariffs, and&#13;
abolishing minimum foreign financing requirements for imports, with exceptions&#13;
made for capital goods in the latter case. Also, interest rates were raised,&#13;
foreign capital movements liberalized, and the system of minidevaluations&#13;
adjusted.so as to depreciate the peso in real terms.&#13;
The real exchange rate increased by 20 percent in 1975, rose further in&#13;
1976 and 1977 and, notwithstanding a decline in 1978, it remained 5 percent&#13;
above the 1973 level and only slightly below the "1972" average. And while&#13;
tariff reductions remained limited in scope, nontraditional exports received&#13;
tax and tariff rebates, preferential credits, and tax relief, thereby reducing&#13;
the longstanding bias against exports.&#13;
The measures applied gave impetus to the rapid expansion of exports.&#13;
Increases were especially large in manufactured exports that exceeded the&#13;
hypothetical level, calculated on the assumption of unchanged market shares,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
more than three times in 1978. Improvements in the system of incentives,&#13;
together with the establishment of positive real interest rates and reductions&#13;
in the budget deficit, further contributed to increases in incremental&#13;
capital-output ratios, a rise in the share of investment in GNP, and&#13;
ultimately to the acceleration of economic growth. The gross national product&#13;
increased at an average annual rate of 3.3 percent between 1973 and 1976 and&#13;
5.0 percent between 1976 and 1979, following a decline in the early seventies&#13;
and virtual stagnation in the previous decades.&#13;
While the rise in imports associated with the acceleration of economic&#13;
growth in part offset increases in export shares, and there was little import&#13;
substitution, the net effect of domestic economic policies was to reduce&#13;
external financial requirements attendant upon external shocks.&#13;
Correspondingly, the rise in the gross debt service ratio from 33 percent in&#13;
1973 to 36 percent in 1975 was followed by a decline to 25 percent in 1977.&#13;
And while increases in external shocks and the fall in beef exports due to the&#13;
imposition of restrictions in the Common Market%/ occasioned a rise in this&#13;
ratio to 30 percent in 1978, the 1973 level was not again reached.&#13;
Uruguay's external debt increased to a considerable extent following the&#13;
oil crisis, with the gross external debt ratio reaching 16 percent in 1974.&#13;
It remained at this level afterwards while the net external debt ratio&#13;
declined from 6 percent in 1973 to nil in 1978. The latter figure takes&#13;
account of increases in the national valuation of gold holdings; the ratio was&#13;
percent if such an adjustment is not made.&#13;
Conclusions and Evaluation&#13;
1/ Under the methodology applied, the latter appears as a loss in market&#13;
shares in traditional exports that in part offset the gains Uruguay made in&#13;
nontraditional exports.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
Among newly-industrializing developing countries in the years 1974 to&#13;
1978, on the average the ratio of the balance-of-payments effects of external&#13;
shocks to the gross national product was the highest in Singapore (23&#13;
percent). The same ratio is obtained in relating the effects of external&#13;
shocks to the average value of exports and imports, which provides an&#13;
indication of the adjustment in trade flows necessary to offset the adverse&#13;
balance-of-payments impact of external shocks. The corresponding ratios were&#13;
7 percent and 37 percent in Korea and 7 percent and 19 percent in Taiwan&#13;
(Table 7).1/&#13;
The three Far Eastern countries did not modify their outward-oriented&#13;
strategies in response to external shocks and, correspondingly, experienced&#13;
further increases in export market shares during the period under considera-&#13;
tion. These countries also provided increased investment incentives and re-&#13;
established positive real interest rates, leading to a rise in the rate of&#13;
domestic saving and investment.&#13;
The policies applied enabled the three Far Eastern countries to maintain&#13;
rates of economic growth higher than any other newly-industrializing&#13;
developing country. This was the case notwithstanding the fact that Taiwan&#13;
and, to a lesser extent, Singapore accepted reductions in the rate of economic&#13;
growth in the years 1974 and 1975 for the sake of limiting their foreign&#13;
indebtedness and lowering the rate of inflation.&#13;
Korea, in turn, increased reliance on foreign capital so as to maintain&#13;
rapid rates of economic growth following the external shocks it suffered in&#13;
1974. Correspondingly, Korea-s external debt reached 25 percent of GNP in&#13;
1/ It should be recalled that, in calculating these ratios, the gross&#13;
national product and the average value of exports and imports (average value&#13;
of trade) have been expressed in "1972" prices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
1978, although rapid increases in exports made it possible to limit the gross&#13;
debt service ratio to 20 percent, substantially below the levels observed in&#13;
the early seventies. The situation deteriorated in 1979, when exports&#13;
declined as the exchange rate became increasingly overvalued and some large,&#13;
capital-intensive investments were undertaken.&#13;
In the second group of Latin American countries, the balance-of-payments&#13;
effects of external shocks were negligible in Argentina and in Colombia, which&#13;
did not suffer from increases in petroleum prices. Colombia further enjoyed&#13;
the favorable effects of increased coffee prices. The opportunities provided&#13;
by improvements in the balance of payments were not utilized, however, to&#13;
accelerate the rate of economic growth. Rather, Colombia let its real&#13;
exchange rate appreciate and reduced export subsidies, with adverse effects on&#13;
exports as well as on import substitution.&#13;
Brazil also increased the bias against exports by raising the level of&#13;
import protection and favoring import-substituting industries in the&#13;
allocation of credits. Furthermore, it substantially increased foreign&#13;
borrowing, with a view to maintaining high rates of economic expansion in the&#13;
face of the adverse balance-of-payments effects of external shocks that&#13;
equalled 3 percent of GNP and 47 percent of the average value of trade in the&#13;
1974-78 period. Given the high capital intensity of import-substituting&#13;
industries, however, incremental capital-output ratios increased to a&#13;
considerable extent, leading to a slowdown in economic growth as Brazil failed&#13;
to utilize the proceeds of foreign credits to raise the share of investment in&#13;
GNP. At the same time, the gross debt service ratio increased from 43 percent&#13;
to 68 percent, and the ratio of external indebtedness to GNP from 14 percent&#13;
to 24 percent, between 1973 and 1978.&#13;
The application of expansionary fiscal policies led to the deterioration&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
of Mexico's competitive position, necessitating foreign borrowing far in&#13;
excess of the balance-of-payments effects of external shocks that averaged 1&#13;
percent of GNP and 23 percent of the average value of trade during the period&#13;
under consideration. As a result, Mexico's gross external debt reached 35&#13;
percent of its GNP in 1978, notwithstanding large increases in oil earnings,&#13;
and the gross debt service ratio surpassed 100 percent. At the same time,&#13;
with decreases in (non-oil) export shares and negative import substitution,&#13;
the rate of economic growth did not reach the levels observed in the 1963-73&#13;
period and growth involved a high cost in terms of investment inasmuch as the&#13;
incremental capital-output ratio nearly doubled after 1973.&#13;
In Argentina, expansionary policies led to rapid inflation as resistance&#13;
to a decline in real incomes on the part of labor unions and other groups&#13;
generated a wage-price spiral. Rapid inflation, in turn, caused considerable&#13;
dislocation and the rate of economic growth declined from 4.7 percent in 1963-&#13;
73 to 1.2 percent in 1973-79. But, import savings at lower GNP growth rates&#13;
and favorable external shocks at the end of the period led to reserve&#13;
accumulation that facilitated the introduction of economic reforms in December&#13;
1978.&#13;
In the third group of countries, the balance-of-payments effects of&#13;
external shocks averaged 12 percent of GNP in the years 1974 to 1978 in Israel&#13;
and 8 percent in Yugoslavia; the corresponding ratios with respect to the&#13;
average value of trade were 57 percent and 74 percent, respectively. In&#13;
response to these shocks, Israel and, in particular, Yugoslavia increased the&#13;
bias against exports through higher import protection, resulting in losses in&#13;
export market shares.&#13;
During much of the period under consideration, Israel applied&#13;
deflationary policies and let the exchange rate appreciate, resulting in a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
decline in the rate of economic growth from 8.2 percent in 1963-73 to 2.3&#13;
percent in 1973-79. And while the devaluation of the exchange rate towards&#13;
the end of the period led to the expansion of exports and GNP, this was&#13;
accomplished at the cost of accelerating inflation. Also, the ratio of the&#13;
gross external debt to GNP increased from 54 percent in 1973 to 82 percent in&#13;
1978, and the gross debt service ratio was maintained below 40 percent only&#13;
because Israel was able to obtain long-term loans in the United States.&#13;
In Yugoslavia, the gross external debt ratio rose from 8 percent to 18&#13;
percent, and the gross debt service ratio from.28 percent to 33 percent,&#13;
between 1973 and 1978. Much of the inflow of capital went into investment,&#13;
permitting the maintenance of relatively high GNP growth rates (5.7 percent&#13;
between 1973 and 1979). Yugoslavia's poor export performance in developed&#13;
country markets, however, creates dangers for the future, and the efficiency&#13;
of some of the capital-intensive import-substituting investments is open to&#13;
doubt.&#13;
The average balance-of-payments effects of external shocks equalled 2&#13;
percent of India's GNP and 49 percent of the average value of its trade during&#13;
the 1974-78 period, but these effects were largely offset by earnings derived&#13;
from workers' remittances and tourism. By contrast, the balance-of-payments&#13;
effects of adverse external shocks equalled 8 percent of GNP and 61 percent of&#13;
the average value of trade in Chile and 6 percent and 62 percent in Uruguay.&#13;
And, whereas the two Latin American countries adopted outward-oriented&#13;
policies in response to these shocks, India did not substantially modify the&#13;
system of incentives and chose to accumulate reserves. As a result, India&#13;
experienced further losses in export market shares and its GNP growth rate did&#13;
not substantially rise above the level experienced in the previous decade,&#13;
notwithstanding the improved performance of agriculture and increases in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
rate of domestic savings.&#13;
The turn towards outward orientation was accompanied by severe&#13;
deflationary policies in Chile that was not the case in Uruguay where tariff&#13;
reductions also proceeded at a slower rate. The effects of the differences in&#13;
the policies applied are apparent in the pattern of economic growth in the two&#13;
countries. In Chile, as average rate of GNP growth of 1.6 percent between&#13;
1971 and 1973 was followed by a decline of 2.4 percent between 1973 and 1976&#13;
and an increase of 9.0 percent between 1976 and 1979; in Uruguay, the&#13;
corresponding growth rates were -1.5 percent,3.3 percent, and 5.0 percent,&#13;
respectively.&#13;
The acceleration of economic growth in the two countries was associated&#13;
with a substantial decline in incremental capital-output ratios. They also&#13;
experienced a fall in the ratio of external debt, net of reserve accumulation,&#13;
to GNP. Finally, the debt service ratio fell in Uruguay while the increase in&#13;
this ratio in Chile is explained by the repayment of foreign loans that is&#13;
included under amortization.&#13;
The findings point to the advantages of outward-oriented policies for&#13;
export performance and for economic growth in the face of external shocks.&#13;
Countries applying such policies experienced increases in their export market&#13;
shares while losses in market shares occurred in countries characterized by&#13;
inward orientation (Table 7) 1/ Reliance on export promotion in response to&#13;
external shocks under an outward-oriented strategy, in turn, favorably&#13;
affected economic growth.&#13;
1/ The only exception was Brazil where the share of exports increased,&#13;
notwithstanding the rise in the anti-export bias due to higher protection.&#13;
But, export shares declined towards the end of the period and a number of&#13;
industrial firms were subject to contractual export obligations, giving rise&#13;
to exports below cost.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54 -&#13;
In the group of twelve newly-industrializing developing countries, the&#13;
rank correlation coefficient between the extent of reliance on export&#13;
promotion in response to external shocks, defined as the ratio of the&#13;
increment in exports associated with increases in market shares to the&#13;
balance-of-payments effects of external shocks, and the rate of growth of GNP&#13;
was 0.48 during the 1973-79 period. ! This result is statistically&#13;
significant at the one percent level'2/&#13;
The extent of correlation between the two variables is reduced by reason&#13;
of the fact that in the two countries, Chile and Uruguay, which adopted&#13;
outward-oriented policies during the period under consideration, the favorable&#13;
effects of these policies on economic growth were observable with a time&#13;
lag. To allow for this lag, the extent of reliance on export promotion in&#13;
response to external shocks was also correlated with the rate of GNTP growth in&#13;
the period 1975-79; a Spearman rank correlation coefficient of 0.70 was&#13;
obtained in this case.&#13;
The favorable experience of countries applying an outward-oriented&#13;
development strategy may be explained by the efficient use of resources and&#13;
rapid technological change under such a strategy that provides similar&#13;
incentives to exports and to import substitution. This proposition receives&#13;
support from the observed high correlation between the extent of reliance on&#13;
export promotion and the incremental capital-output ratio. Using the&#13;
1/ External shocks and ratios of policy responses to external shocks,&#13;
including additional net external financing, increases in export market&#13;
shares, import substitution, and lowering the rate of economic growth are&#13;
averages for the years 1974-1978, calculated on 1971-73 basis.   The relevant&#13;
data are shown in Table 7.&#13;
2/ Extrapolating the value of statistical significance calculated for ten&#13;
observations, a Spearman rank correlation coefficient of 0.29 or higher will&#13;
be significant at the one percent level in the case of twelve observations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
reciprocal of the incremental capital-output ratio in the calculations, the&#13;
Spearman rank correlation coefficient between the two variables was 0.75 in&#13;
the 1973-79 period. Practically the same result, a coefficient of 0.77, is&#13;
obtained if incremental capital-output ratios for the 1975-79 period are used&#13;
in the calculations, in order to allow for the possibility of lags in the&#13;
adjustment.&#13;
The introduction of lags will affect the results, however, in attempting&#13;
to explain intercountry differences in GNP growth rates in terms of the&#13;
incremental capital-output ratio and the domestic savings ratio. Thus, in&#13;
replacing data for 1973-79 by data for 1975-79, the Spearman rank correlation&#13;
coefficient increases from 0.43 to 0.82 if the reciprocal of the incremental&#13;
capital-output ratio, and it declines from 0.59 to 0.46 if the domestic&#13;
savings ra-tio, is correlated with the rate of growth of GNP _/ The results&#13;
obtained for the years 1975-79 closely correspond to estimates for the 1960-73&#13;
period in a 113 country sample where rank correlation coefficients of 0.72 and&#13;
0.40 were obtained in the two cases, respectively.2/&#13;
In order to separate the effects of the incremental capital-output ratio&#13;
and of the domestic savings ratio on economic growth, multiple regression,&#13;
techniques have further been applied. The results shown in equations (1) and&#13;
(2) indicate that the rate of economic growth is affected by both variables,&#13;
which are highly significant statistically and explain about four-fifths of&#13;
1/ The results are not appreciably affected if the share of gross domestic&#13;
investment, or that of gross domestic fixed investment, is used in the&#13;
calculation in the place of the domestic savings ratio. (Data on the share of&#13;
investment in aggregate expenditure are shown in Table 6.)&#13;
2/ Michael Hopkins and Ralph van der Hooven, ''Basic Needs and Economic&#13;
Theory," Geneva, International Labor Office, August 1980 (mimeo).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
intercountry variations in GNP growth rates.1/ It is also apparent that, in&#13;
an intercountry context, a 10 percent increase in the reciprocal of the&#13;
incremental capital-output ratio is associated with a 9-10 percent increase in&#13;
the GNP growth rate and a 10 percent increase in the domestic savings ratio is&#13;
associated with a 3-4 percent increase in the GNP growth rate.&#13;
2&#13;
(1)  1973-79:  log y = 1.806 + 0.972 log AY/I + 0.385 log S/Y   R   = 0.782&#13;
(2.594) (4.866)          (1.973)&#13;
(2). 1975-79:  log y = 1.935 + 0.852 log LY/I + 0.311 log S/Y    R= 0.872&#13;
(4.145) (7.454)          (2.157)&#13;
The importance of policy choices is further indicated by the lack of a&#13;
negative correlation between the balance-of-payments effects of external&#13;
shocks, expressed as a proportion of GNP, and the rate of economic growth. In&#13;
fact, the correlation between the two variables was slightly positive, 0.19,.&#13;
statistically significant at the 10 percent level. This result is cominatible&#13;
with the hypothesis that external shocks provided inducement for policy&#13;
improvements as was the case in Chile and Uruguay.&#13;
There was no significant statistical relationship between reliance on&#13;
additional net external financing in response to external shocks and the rate&#13;
of growth of GNP, with the Spearman correlation coefficient between the two&#13;
variables being -0.08. The result reflects the fact that the effects of&#13;
foreign borrowing on economic growth depend on the uses to which the proceeds&#13;
of foreign loans are put. In Brazil, for example, where the proceeds were&#13;
used largely for raising consumption levels and for investment in high-cost&#13;
1/  Explanation of symbols:  Y = Gross National Product; I = gross domestic&#13;
investment, S/Y = gross domestic savings ratio; t-values are shown in&#13;
parenthesis.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE 7&#13;
REPRESENTATIVE RATIOS OF RALANCE PAYMENTS EFFECTS OF EXTERNAL SHOCKS AND POLICY RESPONSES TO ThESE SHOCKS&#13;
(averages for years 1974 to 1978)&#13;
External Shocks     Terms of Trade   Exp-rt Voloe       Additiosal Net    Iacrosse is Export       Iport        Effects of Lower       Gras, Debt      Grovth Rats      Capitel-Oltpat      Doaatt&#13;
Effects          Effects        Ext-eral PF.aaoo..    Markot Sh-res         Subhtitution     GNP G-roth Rate     Servite Ratio      of ENP            Ratio          SeeSags REtie&#13;
as a perreotage of          as a percertage of                                      as a perceotage of                                      percent     1973-79  1975-79  1973-79  1975-79  1973-78 1975-78&#13;
GNP       Average&#13;
Trade             Exteroal Shorks                                        EterseI Shorke&#13;
ARGENTINA          0.2        3.8           65               35               -207                  -95                  386              16                 33.6          1.2     1.3      13.0     16.6     24.6     26.9&#13;
BRAZIL             2.7       46.6           82               18                 27                   IS                  67              -10                 53.6          6.3     5.8       3.6      3.9     20.9    21.4&#13;
CHILE              8.0       61.1           89               11                 -6                   54                   21             31                  49.0          3.6     8.0       2.8      1.4     10.3      8.9&#13;
COLCMBLA          -0.7       -8.8          243             -143                 65                  -19                 -139             -7                  24.4          5.5     6.1       3.2      3.1     22.1     23.2&#13;
MEXICO             1.3       23.4           63               37                205                  -28                 -102             25                  90.0          4.2     4.7       4.1      4.0     22.2     22.7&#13;
URUGUAY            6.1       62.2           90               10                 71                   36                   4             -11                  26.7          3.9     4.3       3.4      3.6     12.1    12.5&#13;
INDIA              2.1       4B.8           71               29                134                  -20                  -13             -2                  23.8          4.3     3.7       4.9      5.7     20.9    21.9&#13;
ISRAEL            11.9       56.6           82               18                 57                  -20                  15              48                  40.4          2.3     2.2       8.8     10.8      6.6     6.1&#13;
YUGOSIAVIA         7.8       74.2           76               24                 64                  -10                   18              28                 29.7          5.7     6.1       4.4      4.7     26.5     28.3&#13;
KOREA              6.9       37.1           74               26                -92                   89                  135             -32                 18.8         10.1    11.0       2.9      2.8     23.6     24.0&#13;
SINGAPORE         23.3       22.5           72               28                 68                   23                  -43             53                   6.1          7.5     8.2       4.2      3.6     27.6     28.2&#13;
TAIWAN             6.5       19.3           41               59                -76                   10                   35             131                  6.7          7.6     9.8       3.2      2.6     32.6     32.3&#13;
Soaroe: See Table 1, 5, sd 6.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPP3EIIX TABLE S&#13;
BALANCE OP PAYMENTS EFFECTS OF EXTERN6AL NIECES A2ND OP POLICY RESPONSES TO SOUESE SIECKS (1974-78 ho-rge)&#13;
(0U.S. million)&#13;
A00ENTIN&amp;           BRAZIL           CHILESi        COLfOEIA          PMOICO            URUrUATY         I0DTA           ISRAEL         EIEOSIAVIA           KOREA           SINGAPORE          TAIWA0N&#13;
S.EXTERNAL SHECES&#13;
Effects of Increase d Impor t Pices                    1727              7102            1248               780              2442             351             3)68             2061             3913              4742               4393            3720&#13;
of which, Pods.                                    351              3257             233                63               210             1314            1224              518              814              1388               1909             995&#13;
Noo Fools                                    1376             3845             1014               717             2232              217             1945             1543             3099              3356               2484            2725&#13;
Effeci of Increase d Enpocft icoo                      1665              4729             589              1011              1993             178             2115             1111             1904              3424               3669            3357&#13;
of bhich, T-aditio,cs Primac                       624              2345             235               740               473              31              365               44               26               154                  0               0&#13;
Pods.                                          28              150                3                79              617                0               24               5                64                79               1559              94&#13;
Oth-r Ns-T-sdiisoal. PImary                   566              1113             182                26               264              73              636             221               447               333                847             403&#13;
Mansf-cocd                                    456              1121             170               156              440               75             1090             845              1287              2856               1244            2860&#13;
Difference (Torn' of Trade Effocts)                      61              2375              659             -231               447              175            1053              958             2009              1319                724             363&#13;
of which, Poc- Term of Trade Effects              1067              1203            1707              -354              -794             265             1077              136              559               890               -762             847&#13;
of which, U.bhol--ced nods Effeci                -1006              1170           -1048               123              1242             -92              -24              815             1651               429               1484            -484&#13;
Tred Pains of Enpor-, In "1972" prices                 3026              3658             1233             1159              2393              294            3765             1976              5669             3424               5612             3266&#13;
Hypothetical Esp-rt, in '1972" prices                  2993              5134             1157             1023              2136             274             3336             1742              3022             2973               3328             4764&#13;
Dlfer-c     (aport Vo1-    Efforts)                      33               523               76              136               257               20             429              213               446              451                284             522&#13;
of which, T-edfittIeto Pimar                       -23               324              56                99               105               9               80                3               23                19                  0               0&#13;
Fuels                                           2                14               1                18                 2               0                6                0                6                 6                158               3&#13;
Sihbr Not-Tr-dficiol PrImacy                   47                93              20                 4               41                a               60               29               65                24                104              60&#13;
Masfactoed                                      6                93              -1                15               105               4              283              183              532               402                 21             458&#13;
of which, Ermth Effect                    68              192                6                42              195                7              306             264               342               571               178              762&#13;
Enor   Elasticity Effect                -61               -99               -7              -26               -90               -3             -23              -81               211              -169              -157             -304&#13;
S.POLICY 80070801&#13;
Actal Reo-    -c  Gap, io Cocret Prices               -1156              3880               44             -341              1090               67            -564             1973               644              854                660            -390&#13;
Tred V.Io. of ERsm.--. Gap, in "1972" Pric..           -962              3089               87             -403              -345              -70           -~2356           -1309             -1032             2483            -   -21              283&#13;
Diffe--c    (Additional Net Ectr-1 FEc-nd90)           -195               791             -43                62              1442              137            1992              664              1686            -1635                682            -673&#13;
A--oI Enports in "1972" Prices                         2955              5577            1534              1005              1938             344             3847             1527             2763              4548               3556            4837&#13;
Nyppthecfcal Enpoct, In "1972" Prices                  2993              5134            1157              1823              2136             27h             3336             1762             3023              2973               3329            6744&#13;
08ff-.eo.e (Iscr-s    So  cp-rn Market Shares)          -89               442             397               -10              -198               70            -209             -234              -259             1575                227               93&#13;
of which, T-aditina    Pr.Imary-                  -100              -168             294               102              -154              -3                7               -5              -98                69                  0               0&#13;
Pools                                          -2               -8-1                              -47               148               0              -17               0                -4                 1                 19              14&#13;
Other Non Tr-dinion1 PrImay                   134               332              38                81              -00                5              165              -26              -34               142                121             181&#13;
Maofattoced                                  -1 20              207             157                00               111i             40             _644             -203             -123              1363                 07            -102&#13;
Hppothetital Imports, Is 019720 Prices                 2360              8798            1007              1029              3380             283             2827             2768             4001              7301               4986            4660&#13;
A_toel Iports, in "1972" PrIce                    1997              6057             853              1161              4098             277             3026             2391             4395              4990               3419            4331&#13;
Diffecoocs (Import Ouhtitotion)                    343              1941             134              -132              -719               7             -197              177              484              2391               -433             309&#13;
of which, Fools                               -40              250              -51               -14               134               9               -8              -26               41               188                102             -77&#13;
Non pOols                               403              1191              205              -118             -852               -3             -189             203               445              2203              -535              386&#13;
Tr-d Va1se of aports, to "1972" Prices                 2374              8520            1234              1022              3550             263             2803             3326             5624              6841               3519             5797&#13;
mypothetlaI Inp-tE, En "1972" Prices                   2360              8798            1007              1029              3380             283             2827             2740             4881              7381               4986            4640&#13;
Differenc   (IPort REtorts of mI-e GNP)                  15              -278             227                -6               178             -20              -25              558              742              -567                532             1137&#13;
of which.F, Poe6                                                     -39              35                -1                24             -11               -1               26               73               -40                 79              46&#13;
Non Fools!                                      9             -239              192                -7               153              -9               24             532               670              -527               454             1111&#13;
oon:I--rntio.1l sad M.tiloo.I Statistics&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX TABLE 2&#13;
TRADE EFFECTS OF EXTERNAL SHOCKS AND POLICY RESPONSES TO THESE SHCOKS&#13;
Commodity Groups (1974-78 Average Ratio)&#13;
ARGENTINA    BRAZIL     CHILE    COLOMBIA     MEXICO    URUGUAY    INDIA     ISRAEL    YUGOSLAVIA     KOREA    SINGAPORE    TAIWAN&#13;
EXPORTS&#13;
Traditional Primary Products&#13;
Hypothetical/Trend              101.3        89.9      94.0       85.8        87.2       95.1     89.8      97.0          93.2       83.9&#13;
Actual/Hypothetical          94.3        94.2    123.0       117.0       78.4       98.2     100.9     94.0           69.2     168.3&#13;
Fuels&#13;
Hypothetical/Trend               79.6        79.6      79.6       79.6        79.6        0       79.6      79.6          79.6       79.6        79.6       79.6&#13;
Actual/Hypothetical          77.9        84.4     46.0        34.0      624.3        0        30.4     35.3           83.7     103.6       103.1       213.0&#13;
Non-Traditional Primary Products&#13;
Hypothetical/Trend               90.3        90.2      90.2       90.2        90.2       90.2     90.2      90.2          90.2       90.2        90.2       90.2&#13;
Actual/Hypothetical         130.6       138.7    119.9       122.0       78.5      107.1     129.8     90.1           94.4     165.3        112.5      132.6&#13;
Manufactured Goods&#13;
Hypothetical/Trend               99.2         93.5    101.2       95.5        90.7       90.7      87.9     88.5          79.0       86.7        98.8       90.1&#13;
Actual/Hypothetical          84.6       121.5    292.8        74.9       89.1      288.3      78.4     85.6           94.1     151.8       105.0        97.6&#13;
Total&#13;
Hypothetical/Trend               98.9        90.7      93.8       88.3        89.2       93.1      88.6     89.1          82.4       86.8        92.1       90.1&#13;
Actual/Hypothetical          97.0       109.6    134.3        98.2       90.7       125.6     91.3     86.7           91.4     153.0       106.8       102.0&#13;
IMPORTS&#13;
Fuels&#13;
Hypothetical/Trend               96.0       103.5      70.7       90.1        88.5      126.5     100.2     84,1          82.8      107.6        89.2       83.4&#13;
Actual/Hypothetical         131.0        77.9    160.5       437.8       26.9       82.5     102.3    118.8           88.3      66.7        84.2       133.3&#13;
Non Fuels&#13;
Hypothetical/Trend               99.6       103.2      82.7      100.7        95.4      104.2     101.0     83.2          87.1      108.4        90.5        79.9&#13;
Actual/Hypothetical          81.9        77.9     77.8       111.5      126.6      101.1     107.6     92.3           90.2      67.7        112.3       91.2&#13;
Total&#13;
Hypothetical/Trend               99.4       103.3      81.6      100.6        95.0      107.6     100.9     83.2          86.8      108.3        90.4       80.0&#13;
Actual/Hypothetical         84.6         77.9     84.7       112.9      121.3       97.7     107.0     93.6           90.1      67.6       108.7        93.3&#13;
Sources: International and National Statistics&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
import-substituting industries, the rate of economic growth declined while&#13;
foreign debt increased.&#13;
At the same time, servicing the foreign debt entails a cost for the&#13;
national economy, lowering the rate of economic growth under ceteris paribus&#13;
assumption. In fact, in the twelve newly-industrializing developing&#13;
countries, the correlation between the gross debt service ratio and the rate&#13;
of growth of GNP, as measured by the Spearman rank correlation coefficient,&#13;
was -0.59 during the 1973-79 period.&#13;
The experience of the newly-industrializing developing countries during&#13;
the period under consideration also provides evidence on the responsiveness of&#13;
exports and of import substitution to changes in real exchange rates as well&#13;
as on the effects of changes in real interest rates and investment incentives&#13;
on domestic savings and investment.   It further appears that overvalued&#13;
exchange rates and negative real interest rates, as well as large budget&#13;
deficits and the resulting rapid inflation, tend to depress the rate of&#13;
economic activity.&#13;
These findings have implications for the policy measures that may be&#13;
taken in response to recent increases in oil prices. They indicate, first of&#13;
all, the need to lessen the bias in the system of incentives against exports&#13;
and in favor of import substitution. They further point to the need to&#13;
maintain realistic exchange rates and interest rates, limit the budget&#13;
deficit, and avoid using the proceeds of foreign borrowing to increase&#13;
consumption and to carry out investments in industries that do not correspond&#13;
to the country's comparative advantage. More generally, the findings suggest&#13;
the need to reduce distortions in product and factor markets and to increase&#13;
reliance on the market mechanism.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
RECENT PAPERS IN THIS SERIES&#13;
No.                       TITLE OF PAPER                               AUTHOR&#13;
419       Employment Patterns and Income Growth:                    J. Stern&#13;
An Application of Input-Output Analysis                   J. Lewis&#13;
420       The Evaluation of Human Capital in Malawi                 S. Heyneman&#13;
421       A Conceptual Approach to the Analysis of External         R. Aliber&#13;
Debt of the Developing Countries&#13;
422       Estimating Total Factor Productivity Growth in            A. Krueger&#13;
a Developing Country              .                       B. Tuncer&#13;
423       Rethinking Artisanal Fisheries Development:               D. Emmerson&#13;
Western Concepts, Asian Experience                        (consultant)&#13;
424       Transition toward More Rapid and Labor-Intensive          B. de Vries&#13;
Industrial Development: The Case of the Philippines&#13;
425       Britain's Pattern of Specialization in Manufactured       V. Cable&#13;
Goods with Developing Countries and Trade Protection      I. Rebelo&#13;
426       Worker Adjustment to Liberalized Trade:    Costs and      G. Glenday&#13;
Assistance Policies                                       G. Jenkins&#13;
J. Evans&#13;
427       On the Political Economy of Protection in Germany         H. Glismann&#13;
F. Weiss&#13;
428       Italian Commercial Policies in the 1970s                  E. Grilli&#13;
429       Effects of Non-Tariff Barriers to Trade on Prices,        C. Hamilton&#13;
Employment, and Imports: The Case of the Swedish&#13;
Textile and Clothing Industry&#13;
430       Output and Employment Changes in a "Trade Sensitive"      J. Mutti&#13;
Sector:  Adjustment in the U.S. Footwear Industry         M. Bale&#13;
431       The Political Economy of Protection in Belgium            P. Tharakan&#13;
432       European Community Protection Against Manufactured        E. Verrydt&#13;
Imports from Developing Countries:   A Case Study         J. IWaelbroeck&#13;
in the Political Economy of Protection&#13;
433       Agrarian Reforms in Developing Rural Economies             A. Braverman&#13;
Characterized by Interlinked Credit and Tenancy            T.N. Srinivasan&#13;
Markets                                                    (consultant)&#13;
434       How Segmented is the Bogota Labour Market?                 G. Fields (consultant)&#13;
435       Pirate Subdivisions and the Market for                     A. Carroll&#13;
Residential Lots in Bogota&#13;
436       Exchange Rate Adjustment under Generalized Currency        R. Bautista&#13;
Floating&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
W57 vW6l no*"43~*&#13;
BGa8Bssa Bela N. Ializing&#13;
- BalaSsaI-idustt t i   after&#13;
-  Ve. newlYOp" co&#13;
AzelOPlfl9 OU1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1554990">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1980/10/1554990/newly-industrializing-developing-countries-after-oil-crisis
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1980/10/1554990/newly-industrializing-developing-countries-after-oil-crisis</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1980/10/1554990/newly-industrializing-developing-countries-after-oil-crisis</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/12/000178830_98101903405991/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/12/000178830_98101903405991/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-07-12T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1980-10-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The newly-industrializing developing
            countries after the oil crisis
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The paper provides estimates of the
            balance-of-payments effects of external shocks, in the form
            of the deterioration of the terms of trade and the slowdown
            in world export demand, for twelve newly-industrializing
            countries. It further analyzes policy responses to external
            shock in these countries and estimates the
            balance-of-payments effects of policy responses in the form
            of additional external borrowing, export promotion, import
            substitution, and reducing the rate of economic growth.
            Finally, the policies followed by the individual countries
            are evaluated in a comparative framework. There is a high
            correlation between reliance on export promotion in response
            to external shocks and the rate of economic growth. This
            result reflects the success of countries that continued to
            follow outward-oriented policies (Korea, Singapore, and
            Taiwan) and those that newly adopted such policies (Chile
            and Uruguay) during te period under consideration. These
            countries had relatively low incremental capital-output
            ratios as they achieved more efficient resource allocation
            and more rapid technological change than their
            inward-looking counterparts, such as India.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The newly-industrializing developing
            countries after the oil crisis
        </docna>
        <display_title>The newly-industrializing
            developing countries after the oil crisis</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1980/10/1554990/newly-industrializing-developing-countries-after-oil-crisis</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Free Trade,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Achieving Shared Growth,Trade Policy</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Balassa, Bela</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903405991</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Macro/non-trade</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 437</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Export policy; Export promotion; External
            shocks; Import substitution; Incentives; Allocation of
            resources; Oil crises
            adverse effects,agricultural
            sector,agriculture,average trade,balance of payments,base
            year,centrally planned economies,comparative
            advantage,comparative analysis,decision making,developed
            countries,developing countries,developing
            country,Development Economics,Development Report,Development
            Strategies,dividends,domestic production,domestic
            products,domestic savings,economic effects,economic
            growth,economic performance,economic situation,economies of
            scale,elasticities,elasticity,elasticity of demand,empirical
            evidence,exchange rate,exchange rates,exploitation,Export
            Diversification,export growth,Export Incentives,export
            market,export market share,Export Performance,export
            prices,export promotion,export share,Export subsidies,export
            volume,exporters,exports,external financing,external
            shocks,foreign financing,foreign markets,free
            trade,fuels,GDP,GNP,gross domestic product,gross national
            product,Growth Rate,growth rates,import prices,import
            protection,import substitution,imports,income,income
            elasticities,income elasticity,income elasticity of
            demand,index numbers,individual countries,industrial
            sector,interest rates,intermediate goods,M1,macroeconomic
            policy,market share,market shares,negative sign,of
            Trade,oil,oil prices,Overvalued exchange,Overvalued exchange
            rates,per capita incomes,policy changes,policy
            measures,Political Economy,price increases,primary
            products,production
            function,productivity,Protectionism,rapid growth,real
            interest rates,relative importance,resource
            allocation,savings,technological change,Terms,terms of
            trade,terms of trade effects,terms of trade loss,trade
            deficit,trade effect,trade regime,value added,value of
            exports,value of imports,value of trade,world markets
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP437</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Free Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Incentives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Balance of Payments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>