<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Prospects for Traditional and Non-Conventional&#13;
Energy Sources in Developing Countries&#13;
SWP346&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 346&#13;
July 1979&#13;
FILE COPY&#13;
Prepared by David Hughart&#13;
Energy Department&#13;
Central Projects Staff&#13;
Copyright () 1979&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N W&#13;
Washington, D C 20433, U S A&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the auth'   __&#13;
and should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated  L   E   [     f &#13;
organizations, or to any individual acting in their behalf   X-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations,&#13;
or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
r1, . .. L    I.7&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
L[ i 1 u 1985&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 346&#13;
1;, ;Z-tC,W.0AtL Dl-!- . .oa&#13;
July  1979                       Crtc,i. i).C. 2Al- i&#13;
PROSPECTS FOR TRADITIONAL AND NON-CONVENTIONAL&#13;
ENERGY SOURCES IN DEVELOPING COUNTRIES&#13;
A Background Study for World Development Report, 1979&#13;
This paper reviews the prospects for traditional and non-conventional&#13;
energy sources in the developing countries through 1990. The evidence cited&#13;
indicates widespread shortages of the traditional fuels on which an estimated&#13;
one-half of the world's population relies for cooking and other energy needs.&#13;
Collection of these fuels, which include firewood, charcoal, dung, and the&#13;
inedible portions of agricultural crops, has become in some areas an important&#13;
demand on the labor and cash resources of low-income groups as well as a threat&#13;
to the soil resources on which agricultural development depends. Estimates of&#13;
traditional fuel supply and demand are presented, but the data base in this&#13;
field is too weak to allow much confidence to be placed in them. Non-conventional&#13;
energy technologies, including biomass conversion, solar, wind and small-scale&#13;
hydro are surveyed. It is suggested that many developing countries could&#13;
usefully consider programs to increase fuelwood production, improve charcoal&#13;
production techniques, raise cooking equipment efficiencies, survey and exploit&#13;
wind and small-hydro resources, and utilize combustible residuals from&#13;
agro-industrial and forest-industrial plants.&#13;
Prepared by:                                               Copyright  J   1979&#13;
David Hughart, Energy Department                           The World Bank&#13;
Central Projects Staff                                    1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433&#13;
With material prepared by:                                 U.S.A.&#13;
Meta-Systems, Inc. and the Overseas&#13;
Development Council&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
NOTE ON UNITS .......................................................            ii&#13;
I.   INTRODUCTION .................................................            1&#13;
II.   ENERGY SOURCES AND USES IN TRADITIONAL SECTORS              .     .       8&#13;
A.   Generalizations ..........................................           8&#13;
B.   Case Studies        .................................               17&#13;
III.   NATIONAL AND REGIONAL STATISTICS AND PROJECTIONS             .    .      34&#13;
IV.   TECHNOLOGICAL ALTERNATIVES .................................,.           44&#13;
V.   RECOMENTNATIONS ..............................,.,.,.                     55&#13;
A.   Substantive Programs        ........................                55&#13;
B. Research Needs .,                                                     58&#13;
UNNXES&#13;
I. STATISTICS AND PROJECTIONS,...,,,,,,,,,,,,,,,,               ..        . 62&#13;
II.   NON-CONVENTIONAL ENERGY TECHNOLOGIES ......................... 110&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-ii-&#13;
NOTE ON UNITS&#13;
The energy unit used in the paper is the gigajouleD abbreviated GJ0&#13;
A joule is one watt-second9 and a gigajoule is one bill-ion (10 ) joules. The&#13;
gigajoule is approximately equivalent to:&#13;
280 kwh,&#13;
0O95 million btu,&#13;
0O24 million kcal,&#13;
34 kg of coal,&#13;
0O17 barrels of crude oiL,&#13;
26 liters of kerosene,&#13;
67 kg, 150 lbs, 0O093 m3 or 3.3 cu0ft. solid or O0,4 3 or 5.0 cu.ft.&#13;
stacked air-dried wood, 34 kg or 75 lbs of charcoal, or&#13;
the energy required to llft 1000 tonnes 100 meters,*&#13;
that needed to bring 3000 liters of 200C water to a boll,* or&#13;
to boil away 440 liters of water at 1000C.*&#13;
* At 100% efficiency.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. INTRODUCTION&#13;
1.        This paper discussed the prospects for traditional and non-&#13;
conventional energy in the period to 1990 under three general headings:&#13;
(a) energy and basic needs, (b) energy and modernization, and (c) non-&#13;
conventional energy sources for the modern sector and developed countries.&#13;
2.        Heat for cooking is the most important energy requirement at the&#13;
basic needs level. The traditional fuels, including firewood, charcoal, dung,&#13;
and crop residues, are used for cooking by over half the world's population.&#13;
A widespread pattern of local and regional problems in the supply of these&#13;
fuels has developed. Scarcities of these fuels have increased the share taken&#13;
by fuel collection and purchases in the time and cash budgets of many of the&#13;
world's poorest people. Perhaps more important in the long run is that fuel&#13;
scavenging has in some areas contributed to deforestation and/or desertification&#13;
which degrade the resource base on which agriculture depends. Projects and&#13;
programs to increase the supply of and decrease the demand for woodfuels (firewood&#13;
and charcoal) are especially important in the mountainous catchment areas of&#13;
agriculturally important river basins and in arid and semi-arid zones.&#13;
3.        Modernization virtually requires the use of electricity and mechanical&#13;
energy from machines, yet the cost of these technologies is too high to permit&#13;
their rapid extension through the developing world. The only simple resolution&#13;
to this dilemma is to deny the possibility of providing modern means of&#13;
production and amenities to most of the world's population in the foreseeable&#13;
future by continuing to rely solely on conventional electrification and internal&#13;
combustion engines. At least three alternative approaches should be pursued:&#13;
making more effective use of draft animals, developing technologies that may&#13;
permit economic use of locally-available wind, hydro, and solar energy in some&#13;
areas, and improving the return on electrification projects by attaining a better&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
understanding of the circumstances under which they can contrib:'.-e _o increasa3&#13;
in incomes sufficient to justify the investimer't requiredc and &amp;ss-gn-i.g ar;c&#13;
implementing them accordingly,&#13;
4.        Developed economies and the modern sectors oc developf- economies&#13;
need to move away from dependence on petroletm over the cominVCig 6.cadesL  Tnhe&#13;
prospects, however, for non-conventional energy sources playing an importavr. rolc&#13;
in this transition appear poor at least through 1990   Developing countries can&#13;
expect to share in the use of technolpg-ies developed in the industr-ialized&#13;
countries for the use of solar and wind energy, but probably need to take the&#13;
lead in evaluating and developing mcans of tapping the enormous potential of&#13;
humid tropical areas to produce biomass fucls.&#13;
5.        The energy forms most used in the traditional sectors of developing&#13;
countries, both rural and urban, are ofteD refer.red to as `non-comnercial,"&#13;
although in fact they are widely bought and soldc   The most impo-trant forms are&#13;
firewood, charcoal, plant and animal residues, human and animal effort, and solar&#13;
energy. Wind and hydro power are also used in tsraditional sector-s !rn some areas.&#13;
Many of these same energy sources are also cailed "'non-conventioalt17 in the&#13;
context of discussions of alternatives for the supply of energy to the modern&#13;
sectors of both developed and developing countries. The differe.ces between&#13;
traditional and non-conventional enexgy are moire in the techno1og i es used for&#13;
energy collection and transformation T.han in the nature of the ietrgy source.&#13;
60        Developing countries vary widely in their degree of re_-°ance on&#13;
traditional energy sources. It has bszn estimated tha'; non-cormlrirciaL energy&#13;
forms supply over ninety percent of total energy demand i.i such countr-ies as&#13;
Nepal, Tanzania and Mali. In Africa (e'xcluding South Af-rica) m      ao&gt;e than&#13;
sixty-five percent of toal energy consumed is non-commercaia; so0,'2 ten per-&#13;
cent is agricultural residues while ove.r fifty-five percent is r.:.zlwood. In&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
the Far East, excluding Japan, energy use is probably divided about equally&#13;
between modern and traditional energy forms. In Panama, however, traditional&#13;
fuels make up only an estimated 20 percent of the total energy sources.&#13;
7.        Our working hypothesis is that in late 1981, when the world's popu-&#13;
lation is expected to be 4.5 billion, about two billion people will be eating&#13;
food cooked with commercial energy, one and one-half billion will rely prin-&#13;
cipally on woodfuels, and one billion will be eating food cooked with agricul-&#13;
tural residues including dung. These figures are based on the estimates by&#13;
geographic region and population group shown in Table 1.&#13;
8.        Traditional energy supply and demand patterns are frequently integ-&#13;
rated into complicated agricultural and socio-economic systems. In many&#13;
agrarian ecosystems, virtually no agricultural product is wasted in the sense&#13;
of not being put to some productive use, and fuel is produced either jointly&#13;
or as an alternative to other valued outputs. The right to collect fuel in&#13;
a given area is sometimes separate from rights to grow crops or build there,&#13;
and fuel-collection rights are sometimes lost in the transition from tradi-&#13;
tional to modern land tenure systems. Fuel-gathering is typically women's&#13;
work, and women are generally responsible for using it in cooking as well.&#13;
9.        In many of the most densely populated parts of the developing world,&#13;
forests have been reduced to insignificance as a result of land-clearing for&#13;
agricultural purposes and scavenging for fuelwood. This leads not only to&#13;
the use of dung and crop residues to meet basic energy needs, but also to&#13;
shortages of wood for other essential purposes such as housing, and, in some&#13;
areas, environmental damages that compromise the soil and water resources on&#13;
which future food production depends.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
.-4-4&#13;
TABLqE 1&#13;
World Population   by Princi4pal Caokin- Fuel, 1976&#13;
(millions)&#13;
Commezcial                       Dung anet&#13;
Total         Energy          Woodfuels      Crop Wastes&#13;
Afriea South of Sahara        340              35              215             90&#13;
Urban non-poor                 30             25                 5&#13;
Urban poor                     20                               20&#13;
Rural                         290             10               190             90&#13;
India                         610             60               290            260&#13;
Urban non-poor                 60             40                20&#13;
Urban poor                     70              -                40             30&#13;
Rural                         480             20               230            230&#13;
Rest of South Asia            205             25                95             85&#13;
Uzban non-poor                 20             15                 5&#13;
Urban poor                     15                               10              5&#13;
Rural                         170             10                80             80&#13;
East Asia-Developing          265             95               110             60&#13;
Pacific&#13;
Urban non-poor                 55             40                15&#13;
Urban poor                     30             15                15&#13;
Rural                         180             40                80             60&#13;
Asian CPEs                    855            1i90              435            230&#13;
UrDban                        205            150                55&#13;
Rural                         650             40               380            230&#13;
M-'Lddle East - North Africa  200            105                35             60&#13;
Urban non-poor                 70             70&#13;
Urban poor,                    20             10                10              -&#13;
Rural                         110             25                25             60&#13;
Latin America &amp; Caribbean     325            230                85             10&#13;
Urban non-poor                145            145&#13;
Urban poor                     50             25                25&#13;
Rural                         130             60                60             10&#13;
North America - OECD Pacific 365             365                 0              0&#13;
Western Europe                400            400o                0              0&#13;
European CPEs                 340            340                 0              0&#13;
¶lotal                    3905           1845              1265            795&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
10.       Deforestation and desertification are destroying the resources on&#13;
which large numbers of people depend for food as well as fuel. In some&#13;
cases, mountain slopes are cleared of trees for fuel and other uses as demand&#13;
exceeds regrowth. The soil is then exposed to the elements and often washes&#13;
away quickly. The loss of the soil not only makes it more difficult or&#13;
impossible to re-establish forest production on the areas affected, but may&#13;
cause problems downstream as well. The eroded soil may be deposited in&#13;
reservoirs (shortening their lives), irrigation canals (raising maintenance&#13;
costs) or riverbeds (increasing the flood level associated with any given&#13;
volume of water). 1/ In addition, the upland water storage capacity of the&#13;
eroded soil is lost, so runoff becomes more irregular, which both decreases&#13;
useable water resources and increases flood potential.&#13;
11.       Desertification occurs when the carrying capacity of arid or semi-&#13;
arid areas is exceeded and vegetative cover is reduced to meet forage and&#13;
fuel needs. The soil may then be carried away by the wind.&#13;
12.       Fuel gathering is an important contributor to deforestation, but&#13;
clearing of land for agricultural purposes and browsing by animals are at&#13;
least as important. Whatever the causes, deforestation forces people to spend&#13;
as much as a fourth of their time and/or income obtaining the fuel they need&#13;
to cook their food. Fuel scarcity also complicates efforts to re-establish&#13;
forests by making it difficult to prevent seedlings from being uprooted to&#13;
meet immediate needs.&#13;
1/   Controlling floods by building levees without at the same time dealing&#13;
with siltation can result in the riverbed being built up above the level&#13;
of the surrounding countryside. The classic example of this is the Yalu&#13;
River in China.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
130       Fuel scarcity can also affect agricultural productivity by £orcing&#13;
people to stop using animal dung and crop residutes as fertilizers and soil&#13;
conditioners. In some areas this may be of minor importance, wh:'ne in areas&#13;
where poor soil is cropped it reduces productivity markedly.&#13;
140       We do not know the magnitude of these environmental costs with any&#13;
precision, but we do know that they are serious and that the inc-:easing&#13;
pressure of population on resources will prevent the simple continuation of&#13;
fuel gathering and usage practices that have evolved over centuries and form&#13;
an integral part of the socio-econcmic-'agricultural structure of many com-&#13;
munities. At the current rate of deforestation, the tropical forests of&#13;
developing countries, which now cover half of their aggregate la-Ld area, would&#13;
disappear in about 60 years0&#13;
150       While meeting household energy needs in a manner that is consistent&#13;
with maintaining and increasing food production is perhaps the most serious&#13;
energy problem facing many countries, it is not always seen as sucho This&#13;
is partly because the supply of non-commercial energy is generally taken&#13;
for granted, and in any case does not have an easily measured effect on&#13;
variables such as GDP or the balance of paymentso On the other 'nand, there&#13;
is a clear link between modernization and the use of inanimate forms of&#13;
mechanical energy,-/and the goal of development in the sense of introduction&#13;
of modern technologies and means of production often takes precedence over&#13;
that of maintaining and improving the viability of traditional systems in the&#13;
interim0&#13;
- Per capita horsepower of mechanical prime-movers was sometimes used as an&#13;
index of economic development before national accountsvcice invented and&#13;
estimated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
16.       The increased price of petroleum and other modern sector energy forms&#13;
has made the process of modernization generally more expensive and hence more&#13;
difficult. In order to increase food, fiber, and fuel production and to increase&#13;
non-agricultural employment opportunities, more energy in the forms of fertilizer,&#13;
water lifting, seed and crop drying, and mechanical power is required. Although&#13;
we often assume that this means more electrification, chemical fertilizer,&#13;
diesel and electric pumps, and tractors running on petroleum products, the&#13;
time period that would be required to provide these things to the vast numbers&#13;
of people who must otherwise depend on themselves and on animals for mechanical&#13;
power and fertilizer may prove to be so long that it is worth considering alternative&#13;
technologies. There are perhaps 0.3 billion households without electrical service.&#13;
It may be technically feasible to provide connections to these households at&#13;
an average cost of $1,500 but the cost would be $450 billion. It may prove more&#13;
practical in some cases to improve the utilization of locally available energy&#13;
resources, including the sun, wind, and running water. While costs restrict&#13;
the present economic usefulness of these non-conventional technologies to a&#13;
relatively narrow range of conditions, they are already cheaper than conventional&#13;
power supply alternatives in some areas. Thus, it seems safe to say that when&#13;
inanimate mechanical energy does come to many areas, it will be provided by&#13;
small-scale solar, wind and hydro systems or by engines running on locally produced&#13;
fuels rather than by an electric grid or a diesel generator operating on "imported"&#13;
fuel. In the meanwhile, there may be scope for making more and better use of&#13;
draft animals through improvements in animal breeding and health and with improved&#13;
equipment. The use of rubber tires too worn for further use on automobiles&#13;
has already reportedly multiplied the load-carrying capacity of an ox-cart by a&#13;
factor of four in some areas.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
1IL  ENERGY SOURCES AMD USES -M.N 7'ADITIONAL SECTORS&#13;
A. GER1EIAIZAEIONS&#13;
170       Demand for traditional fue:ls is neav°est in rural areas and&#13;
dominated by household uses, primar7Ly cookignc  but there is also consider-&#13;
able use in urban areas and by a number of ladus-ries, some on G large scale.&#13;
180      iHost rural communities in developing countries are largely closed&#13;
systems with respect to energy0   A se: of estiuates constructed for rural&#13;
India, for example, indicates that apz.oxcimatcly ninety percent oc the energy&#13;
used is from local sources: human (ten percent)    and animal (fe;:-.teen) work,&#13;
wood (forty) crop residues (ten), and cattle dung (sixteen). Only ten percent&#13;
of rural Yndia's energy is "imported   f.Mom the modern sector as petroleum,&#13;
coal, or electricity. Table 2 presen.s est;hates of hors each of these energy&#13;
forms is used. Estimates constructed for a pzoto-typical v:.llage in Northern&#13;
Nigeria indicate it derives about one percenat cf its total energy (including&#13;
animal and human labor) from commercial so-zrces  and xwoodfuel provides some&#13;
80 percent of the total, essentially all c'- w.hich is used in household activi-&#13;
ties. Agriculture accounts for some _5 pezcent of energy demand Lnd domestic&#13;
uses Zor\eighty percent.&#13;
19o       Table 3 summarizes a set of estimates £or energy balances of six&#13;
such proto-typical communities represeeting important regions in the develop-&#13;
ing world0  It is important to note, however, that these estimates were&#13;
constructed from a variety of secorda/y sou,ces supplemented Wi^t-- educated&#13;
guesswork0 Very little reliable quai'titative data exists in this field0&#13;
20       Household activities account for -he Largest amounts of- traditional&#13;
energy demands0  The chief use is for cooking (including the boiling of water,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9-&#13;
l~ Ln  1-H  Cl)  cn  11  ,n4  '4t  C'J 4  ft L  ILIn  C  C&#13;
C)      u*          s I  *  *       *  r   N sru Ic.  0 o&#13;
'4   4   I~~CC)               1r4   CD   C&#13;
4i ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~~ &#13;
CO  Co  &lt;  o4  C  C  IC Co  If  -4  C O '  1    °&#13;
44  *  *  *    *  I &#13;
0  -4 ,4 -  -  -4  \C       C~  C;  C;  C  1- &#13;
H                                   V &#13;
CO  CJ02c            I 1r&lt;&#13;
4J '0 0)&#13;
0CO         *           I &#13;
%~~~~~ &gt;  U) aq 0                               er&#13;
P. SCo   Co IC                                    C    c- &#13;
Ea 0  P &#13;
.0  a)~'.&#13;
4-i 444&#13;
E-4  .4                                V  V &#13;
CO                                                             c)&#13;
C~~~~~~C&#13;
P     0                  C;&#13;
4-    HCo &#13;
I-4-) -,q &#13;
coW&#13;
C -     r  . ..            I  ..&#13;
o                    *co   I          oo&#13;
w                                                             :&#13;
0     1     Cn             IC oo  n         O      I         C-&#13;
C  4 o              I JH   o  oo&#13;
¢ 0                                                      to&#13;
4        o4-                          CE &#13;
Co  C             o~0 @            C   i&#13;
-42C b42C  *H                OI ZI fX           )                C&#13;
CW  o o XC C                        C   C    C   C4  a)4&#13;
~20O      rO  3w                                              C IUOgO H &#13;
X   t  ,q  ac  to   :   X   O   sd ^'   al~~~cq &#13;
0)~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~2~~~~~~~~~ ~ ~ ~ 0&#13;
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~4~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~~~~~~~'4&#13;
S  C  o  3  1   &gt;  c)  o    *      Eq gi &lt;a)     F.&#13;
44  *r-4,-4  ~ ~ ~ C          N0)&#13;
02  444~~~)  '4  '4     Co  -  rH   4         I -I  CP&#13;
C0,-4  *  &lt;  @    I o *        v  O       I. o  * co&#13;
cn°  C      '.0   I'.H)        C          IC    C-  '4 H  0  o&#13;
=                                                '.0 P   Z  4  &gt;4  E  0  0c&#13;
04-' ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ -P                   - &#13;
4-4  0   a                                              0)0 i4&#13;
'.0  ci  0       I0 co  If  -     C  4  I'0   '4&#13;
P.                                                     0)-U 04iE44&#13;
:j  cti  1-i  I 0  P        u       I 0   CO  PL~~~~~~~  ~ 4&#13;
0  ~   4  i  0 0     .4'H           -4 0a)          4-i&#13;
Eni   :J -H Ca24       a)4-  0      04  0)             0)&#13;
0)    4)       00 )  )  104  En  &gt; w   En           44 E&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-10-&#13;
TABLE 3&#13;
Hypothesized Energy Budgets of Six Agricultural Settlements&#13;
(GJ per person per year)&#13;
BIhar, Hunan,     Plateau,   Northern    Northern   Ances,&#13;
India   China     Tanzania   Nigeria    iiexico     Bolivia&#13;
Sources                    15.2    32o4       2601       1904       56C2       48M7&#13;
Woodfuels                1.0               23.0       15.7                  34.8&#13;
14o9&#13;
Crop residues            1.0    20.9        -&#13;
Dung                     2. lj &#13;
CQal, oil products     40.05     301        --       z0.05        9o9        -w&#13;
Electricity              --                 -          --        203         -&#13;
Human energy             301     301        301        3.0         3,7       305&#13;
Animal energy            7.9    52         --         0.8         704      10.4&#13;
Uses                       15.2     32,4      26,1       19.4        56,3      48,7&#13;
Domestic                 4,2    23,9       23.0       1507        17.8      3408&#13;
Agricultural             7,4     8,2        2,4        2.9        34,7      7/0&#13;
/1&#13;
Other                    3,5     3,3        0.8        0.8        3,8        6,9&#13;
Detail may not add to total due to rounding errors,&#13;
'/&#13;
Includes transportation and crop processing.&#13;
Source: Makhijani and Poole, 1975,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-11-&#13;
baking and brewing of beverages). Cooking was found in surveys in The Gambia&#13;
and Thailand to account for about 75% of total woodfuel consumption. Cooking&#13;
fuel in rural areas is almost always derived from biological sources, such as&#13;
wood, dung and crop residues. In fact, aside from kerosene, which is used&#13;
fairly widely in Latin America and less frequently elsewhere, wood, dung and&#13;
crop residues constitute virtually the only sources of household fuels acces-&#13;
sible to the non-rich in rural areas of developing countries.&#13;
21.       An important factor in the choice among biomass fuels is their&#13;
relative accessibility. According to an Indian survey, 1/ a pattern which&#13;
appeared typical of many areas is that where forests are no more than 10 km&#13;
from a village, between 70% and 100% of fuel requirements will be obtained&#13;
from them. Beyond a distance of 15 km however, fuelwood use virtually stops.&#13;
Crop residues and dung are then gathered locally or charcoal is brought from&#13;
more distant areas, or kerosene is used when available and affordable.&#13;
Similar patterns have been reported in Bangladesh, Northern Nigeria, Sudan&#13;
and Nepal, although people in some areas go much further for wood. Other&#13;
food preparation tasks often make use of solar and wind energy. A variety&#13;
of crops, species and fruits are sundried in order to preserve them. The&#13;
wind is widely used to help separate grain from chaff and sometimes also for&#13;
drying meat and hides. Space heating, where practiced, has traditionally&#13;
relied on biomass fuels in combination with architectural adaptations. Use&#13;
of thick stone or adobe walls and roof overhangs are the most common examples&#13;
of the latter. The household use of wood, dung and crop residues is often&#13;
1/   R. Mathur, 1975 cited in J.E.M. Arnold, 1978 World Forestry Congress&#13;
Paper.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
*12-&#13;
much greater in the mountainous areas of cievQic'iThg countries t17,= in tropical&#13;
lowlands0  One recent study 1/ fo-und Lhat household fuelwood requ rements&#13;
differ between lowland and highland areas by as much as a factor of 4. The&#13;
bulk of this variation is presumably due to space hestingc&#13;
22.       Hauling water and gatherinig fuel az,e essential domestic tasks re-'&#13;
quiring considerable arduous labor Palost altmays done by women and children0&#13;
Agricultural tasks in traditional ruz1al settTigs awe usually performed using&#13;
animate energy. Numerous country studies end cbservations indicate that most&#13;
of the human and animal labor available to rural families is used in 'these&#13;
tasks and that outside of parts of La-in America and South Asia, mechanization&#13;
is uncommon0  Soil preparation, chiefly by plowing, is done wherever possible&#13;
with bullocks. In some areas, especially in shifting tropical forest agricul-&#13;
ture, soil preparation is done by hand6 arTd -includes tasks such as tree-felling&#13;
and stumping. Both men and women (the lattez especially in Africa) perform&#13;
this task.  Planting and cultivating is almosi: universally done by hand0o iT;is&#13;
includes the application of fertil-°ze£s a2no pesticides where used0  Irrigatio-n&#13;
generally relies on gravity or commercial onecgy. Traditional energy forms&#13;
are less often used for irrigation, but in some countries technol-ogies such as&#13;
the animal-powered Persian wheel, the hand- owered counter,balancz "'shadoof"&#13;
of North Africa and West Asia, windmills in scattered sites and, occasionally&#13;
water wheels are used to provide mechanf caci pownro&#13;
23.       Fertilizing is not a universal practice in the poorer developing&#13;
countries, though it is far from uncommon0   On mocern farms commercial ferti-&#13;
lizers may be used. On small, traditional, end subsistence farms fertilizer,&#13;
1/   K. Openshaw, Tanzania&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-13-&#13;
if used, usually takes the form of animal wastes. Harvesting and initial&#13;
processing, such as grain threshing or sugar cane crushing and other tasks&#13;
such as husking, shucking, shelling or grinding, typically involve great&#13;
outlays of human and draft animal labor. Again, the proportion of animal&#13;
labor depends largely upon how much is available. Draft animals are uncommon&#13;
in Central and West Africa because of the prevalence of the tsetse fly. In&#13;
much of Asia, most draft animals are owned by the better-off village residents&#13;
and not available to the bulk of the rural population. In any event, harvest-&#13;
ing requires mostly human labor since animal-drawn harvesting equipment is&#13;
not available or is very costly. Marketing of foods that may be surplus to&#13;
the farmer's needs takes energy. In some areas cash crops are carried to&#13;
market on foot. More often it is brought on the backs of animals or in carts&#13;
drawn by them. Rural industry and commerce employ primarily human labor and&#13;
wood fuels. Some of the most important of these activities in terms of&#13;
energy use include metal working, commercial food preparation, brickmaking,&#13;
and drying and curing of food and crops such as tobacco, tea, and coffee.&#13;
Tobacco curing in Malawi is estimated to account for 17% of that country's&#13;
total energy consumption.&#13;
24.       In some rural areas, but more typically in larger towns and urban&#13;
areas, community services such as schools, clinics, local government, reli-&#13;
gious centers, public markets, transportation, communication, and electric&#13;
power enter into energy demand. Most of these needs are met with commercial&#13;
forms of energy. Public transportation is probably the most important of&#13;
these services in terms of numbers of users and quantities of energy used.&#13;
It is highly dependent on petroleum fuels. Electric service reached as of&#13;
1970 about 10-15% of the population of low-income and about half of the&#13;
households of middle-income developing countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-14-&#13;
25.       Much of the above description of energy needs and tasks applies to&#13;
urban areas as well, particularly for domestic needs and communit:y-related&#13;
services. However, the density of demand and hence pressure on resources is&#13;
much greater. Urban dwellers typically rely less on fuelw^ood tikan their&#13;
rural counterparts, but consume more charcoal and commercial fuels than rural&#13;
populations.&#13;
26.       Charcoal is a widely-used fuel in the households and informal/small&#13;
business sectors in many urban areas because it is more easily transported&#13;
than an equivalent amount of wood and is more convenient to use. As the&#13;
urban component of developing country population grows, charcoal use can be&#13;
expected to increase in importance. While 70-80% of the energy value of wood&#13;
is lost in traditional charcoal productions this is generally roughly compen-&#13;
sated for by the much higher efficiency of charcoal stoves.&#13;
27.       Where demand is high and supplies tight, wood fuel depzndency can&#13;
lead to hardships. Fuel purchase was estimated to take 20-30% of the average&#13;
worker's family income in Ouagadougou, Upper Volta and Niamey, Niger in the&#13;
early 1970so&#13;
280       Traditional fuels are not used exclusively by the poor0   Among the&#13;
highest income group in a Thailand study, comprising 6% of the population,&#13;
more than 70% of households are predominantly wood fuels0 Tne fraction of&#13;
households using woodfuels has been estimated from survey data to be 99% in&#13;
The Gambia, 98% in Tanzania, and 97% in Sudan and Thailand0 However, among&#13;
the middle and upper classes, a gradual transition to petroleum-based fuels&#13;
or electricity is evident, though tradition continues to favor charcoal for&#13;
cooking in some areaso Because overall consumption increase with income,&#13;
a positive income elasticity of demand for wood fuels has been found by some&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-15-&#13;
studies, so that with gradual rises in income, more wood fuels rather than&#13;
less may be consumed.&#13;
29.       A major element in the choice of cooking fuels is the cost of an&#13;
appropriate stove. Wood is often used without a stove of any sort and simple&#13;
braziers produced by artisans are frequently used for charcoal, whereas LPG&#13;
or electric stoves represent substantial investments. Investment costs re-&#13;
quired for the use of various fuels in Ouagadougou, Upper Volta have been&#13;
estimated as follows:&#13;
Fuel                           Investment Required                 Cost (US$)&#13;
Fuelwood                           some stones                            0.00&#13;
Charcoal                           stove                          0.80 - 4.00&#13;
Kerosene                           stove                          10.00 - 14.00&#13;
Butane or Propane (LPG)            stove + bottle                ca. 52.00&#13;
Electricity                        stove + utility deposit       ca. 120.00&#13;
30.       Fuel prices vary greatly from area to area.   Kerosene, the most&#13;
internationally traded of the fuels listed above, was sold in world markets&#13;
until recently at about US$0.10 per liter, or about US$7.50 per capita per&#13;
1/&#13;
annum for basic household requirements.    If crude oil prices settle around&#13;
$20/barrel, kerosene can be expected to cost about $0.15 per liter in major&#13;
export refinery markets, bringing the foreign exchange cost of cooking with&#13;
kerosene to about $11 per capita per annum.&#13;
31.       Lighting, another essential domestic need, is met by a variety of&#13;
sources, including kerosene lamps and candles. Most of the urban poor&#13;
cannot afford the high cost of electricity even when available.&#13;
1/ Retail prices were less than half the figure quoted in mid 1977 in the&#13;
capital cities of Indonesia, Bolivia, Ecuador, Mexico, Peru, and&#13;
Venezuela and more than US$0.20 per liter in those of Brazil, Ethiopia&#13;
and Uruguay. The prices in twenty-five other developing country capitals&#13;
was between US$0.05 and US$0.20 per liter.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
320       Other household activities such as food preparation and clothes&#13;
making and washing are done by hand; irons zaL' neated with fuel u'fhare electri-&#13;
city is not used.&#13;
33.       A host of cottage industry End s:maDl-scale enterprises employ&#13;
traditional fuelso   Small bakeries, cafe-baco. streets-de food vzacdors,&#13;
blacksmiths9 and briclmakers all ccmmonly use toodfuclso As in the uLban&#13;
household sector, charcoal is a preferred fuel. These same enterprises often&#13;
employ a great deal of semi-skille6 ½bDor.    la Afr ca, it is not uncommon to&#13;
find open air shops operated by semri-killed entrepreneurs.   These wsorkers&#13;
may use wood or charcoal fires to recycle scrap rnotal into items such as&#13;
bicycle parts or kerosene lanteens wh'nch can be sold directly to the public&#13;
(usually the urban poor) or to other small: businesses for resale.&#13;
34.       Other informal sector activ`;ties substitute labor for activities&#13;
thaL in the more developed countries would take modern energy0   1,.cusehold&#13;
members and domestic servants make the frequent trips to market (partly in&#13;
lieu of refrigeration), do the manual clothes washing and house^work', the&#13;
carrying of water and fuels, and nunerous other essential daily tasks by&#13;
hand0&#13;
35.       Some formal sector enterprises utilIze traditional fuels50   3efore&#13;
the oil price increases of the seventi_es this was decreasing steadily0   Indi-&#13;
cations are that for some industries this trend &amp;ay have halted or even&#13;
reversed. One example of using traditional fue '6s in the modern sector is&#13;
the use of charcoal for steel making in the PhiXippines, Brazil and other&#13;
countries. The Ugandan tea industry uses wood fo- curing and Thailand's&#13;
railroads are starting to revert back to their earl-ier use of wocd fuels0&#13;
Wood fuels are also used to brew beer, dry fisb, tobacco and lumber, make&#13;
bricks, and manufacture cemento&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-17-&#13;
36.       The case studies that follow are intended to illustrate the point&#13;
that traditional energy supply and usage patterns cannot in most cases be&#13;
understood except in the context of the eco-agricultural and socio-economic&#13;
systems of which they are a part.&#13;
B. CASE STUDIES&#13;
(1) Rural Energy in the Context of Agricultural Systems: Dhanishwar,&#13;
Bangladesh&#13;
37.       Traditional energy systems are difficult to analyze not only for&#13;
lack of data but because they are often part of complex agricultural systems.&#13;
In terms of output, high technology agriculture in developed countries is&#13;
often much simpler than traditional subsistence agriculture in developing&#13;
countries. While the only valued ouput from a corn field in a developed&#13;
country may be grain, each crop in Bangladesh typically fulfills multiple,&#13;
explicitly-recognized purposes.&#13;
38.       Another characteristic of this agricultural ecosystem's that vir-&#13;
tually nothing is wasted.   The term    "crop wastes" is inappropriate since&#13;
virtually every product of cultivation is put to use in some way. In a&#13;
materials sense subsistence economies are "tight." 1/&#13;
39.       This complexity and "tightness" makes the process of understanding&#13;
the energy system contingent on an appreciation of the agricultural and live-&#13;
stock systems. The high degree of "connectedness" between different sectors&#13;
means, for example, that an intervention in the agricultural sector (such as&#13;
1/   FAO Soils Bulletin  40, China: Recycling of Organic Wastes in Agriculture&#13;
(Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations; Rome 1977)&#13;
also illustrates this tightness.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
the introduction of high.yielding crop varieLies which produce a Jower ratio&#13;
of straw to grain) will also affect the energy and livestock sec^crs and&#13;
vice-versa.&#13;
40.       The intricacy of fuels supply and usage patterns in a nearly-closed&#13;
agricultural system is illustrated in Figure 1, an energy-related resource&#13;
flow diagram for the village of Dhanishwar in Bangladesh.              Food and&#13;
fuel balances for the village of 422 people are shown in the lowcr left corner&#13;
of the figure. The village economy is approximately balanced at a subsistence&#13;
level. Energy flows in Dhanishwar are related to the production of cash&#13;
crops, livestock, food and materials for home building.&#13;
410       A single crop may perform several complementary functicns0   An&#13;
example of this type of crop is doinshah, a leguminous plant which is sown&#13;
before the monsoon on the small ridges which separate individual plots. As&#13;
the fields become flooded by monsoon waters, doinshah fulfills the first of&#13;
its tasks by preventing water hyacinth from entering the plot and damaging&#13;
the growing paddy. At the same time the plant is enriching the soil by&#13;
fixing atmospheric nitrogen, a function   hinch is explicitly recognized by the&#13;
farmers. The leaves of the doinshah plant are harvested for cattle fodder.&#13;
Finally, at the end of the monsoon the fibrous stem is pulled out of the&#13;
ground and provides an excellent source of fuel0 This fuel is particularly&#13;
valuable since it becomes available during the period of acute fu2l shortage&#13;
preceding the amon harvest0&#13;
42.       Not only do most crops produce multiple complementary products, but&#13;
there are often alternative, competing uses to which each product may be puto&#13;
This is best illustrated by the most important crop in the area, deep--water&#13;
amon paddy0 This crop is sown before the monsoon, grows in four to nine feet&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
0 ~ ~ ~ ~~~~1-C .        1 &#13;
.0 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ t     ,80 &#13;
C~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
E &#13;
0  U,     C        0)~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~oU&#13;
C    c  . n      OG&#13;
C'4H1  ~ IC N   f&#13;
0 W  0               U'w E -  04&#13;
U]                               C-~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~U&#13;
to  CE                              -C&#13;
a)                          .~~~~~~~o  -.0~~~c   (&#13;
--   C  00    .C   'C&#13;
_                                    U,  0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
LO                 0C &#13;
a  CL. ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~         a &#13;
0~~~~~~~&#13;
00          .                           0 &#13;
N                                  C  *~  U,  U, C  C&#13;
-O~~~~~ 00 cc      .&#13;
a)                                        N       -. &#13;
a)    U]J  C-E&#13;
'C  C- .0 &gt; &#13;
"I                                 0        0~~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
CN                          C%j~~~~~~~&#13;
0                                0~~~~~~~~~~~~~.-  &#13;
0          0      OL~~~&#13;
U)  0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
'a~~~~~~~~~       )C    U,0 &#13;
t        C',  -  N   &gt;~~~~~~~~C  U &#13;
G~~~  0  ON  Ul ~ ~ ~ ~ O N &#13;
1-f  .2  U') o..-  -W 'n  =  0 ~ ~ ~ ~ 0 ..  0  . '&#13;
cu  Cj CL  o  v  .0 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ,~C &#13;
E       a) 0 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~a) o  &#13;
tn  0 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~I  n0 Ii&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
of water and is harvested after the monsoon waters recede. The wost signi-&#13;
ficant purposes served by the cultivation or amca paddy can be iJ_ustrated&#13;
as follows:&#13;
Use&#13;
Product            Human food    Fodder   Fuel   Fertilizer   Construction&#13;
Leaves&#13;
Grain&#13;
Husk&#13;
nara 1/ straw&#13;
kher 2/ straw&#13;
(Legend. **   predominant use; ** used commonly but not frequently; 8 used&#13;
but uncommonly).&#13;
1/   nara is the tough straw which remains in the field after the paddy is&#13;
harvested o&#13;
2/   kher is the more tender straw which is carried from the field with the&#13;
harvested paddy and which remains alter the threshing of the grain.&#13;
43.       All village activities depend on so1ar energy0   Total s-,nlight&#13;
falling on the cultivated area can be considered constant from year to year&#13;
at about 60OOO GJ/year while the efficiency of photosynthetic utilization&#13;
may increase or decrease depending on varietal, soil, and cultivation changes0&#13;
44.       Seventy-two percent of the labor available for agricultural work&#13;
is utilized in cultivation and crop processing0 During peak seasons this&#13;
becomes 100 percent. A shift to more intensive agriculture may be prevented&#13;
unless more power can become available through mechanization of agricultural&#13;
activities or shifting of labor from alternative occupations such as fuel&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-21&#13;
collection. Alternatively, as fuel becomes scarce and more time is required&#13;
for its collection, agriculture may suffer.&#13;
45.       Draft animals provide between one-half and two-thirds of the over-&#13;
all mechanical energy input to agriculture as well as being used in transpor-&#13;
tation. A change in livestock numbers would thus affect crop production&#13;
operations as well as alter the balances of straw and dung.&#13;
46.       Chemical fertilizers contribute little to crop production at pre-&#13;
sent. Most of the fertilizer applied to this village's fields is cow dung.&#13;
It is estimated that in this village 62 percent of all dung produced is used&#13;
to fertilize cultivated land and 13 percent is used as fuel. Twenty-five&#13;
percent is not collected and probably uncollectable. If dung use for fuel&#13;
were to increase, its availability for fertilizer would decrease and crop&#13;
production would suffer unless a replacement source of nutrients and soil&#13;
conditioners is provided.&#13;
47.       Agricultural outputs are processed and supplied to the homesteads&#13;
and to the cash economy outside the village. This village is close to a&#13;
balance between local food supply and demand with a modest sale of cash crops&#13;
suffucient to pay for the barest necessities of clothing, taxes, and small&#13;
amounts of food (salt, spices, sugar) from outside the vi4lage.&#13;
48.       Food and cash come from agriculture together with three other&#13;
essential products: animal feed, cooking fuel, and material for house cons-&#13;
truction. It is estimated that about one-half of the jute sticks (materals&#13;
left after the fibrous "cash crop" is removed) is currently used as construc-&#13;
tion material. Where competition is keen for jute stick as fuel, housing&#13;
suffers. This has already been reported to be happening in some parts of&#13;
Bangladesh.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
49.       Rice is the staple food of Bangladesh. Rice straw is zn important&#13;
source of cattle feed and provides three-quarters of the fuel used for cook-&#13;
ing. Jute sticks provide another 15 percent of cooking fuel. Clearly any&#13;
decline in the amount of rice straw produced, whether because of production&#13;
or varietal changes, will force (1) a cooking fuel shortage, (2) pressure on&#13;
jute stick supply for fuel9taking them away from construction, (3) pressure&#13;
on the few trees from which fuel-wood can be taken, and/or (4) reduced use of&#13;
rice straw for animal feed with animals as a res-ult producing less draft&#13;
power and dung. Fuelwood in Dhanishwar supplies only about seven percent of&#13;
household fuel requirements.&#13;
50.       Poor landowners head      20 out of the 77 familiesp xeitil 100 out of&#13;
422 peopleo  They work 6o5 of 60 hectares of land and own six of the 101 cows&#13;
and bullocks. Another 12 families are landlesso Table 4 shows the distribu-&#13;
tion of population and principal resources among households by income levelo&#13;
Table 5 shows the resulting food and fuel balances0&#13;
51.       The poor use no chemical fertilizer and have a supply of dung of&#13;
only 6 tonnes per year: less than their demand for fertilizer alone0 The&#13;
richest 10 percent of families have , however, a relative surplus of dung,&#13;
part of which they use for cooking0&#13;
52.       Furthermore, the poor have a food deficit and insufficient rice&#13;
straw to meet cooking needs0 The poor and landless gather twigs, leaves, and&#13;
firewoods and obtain food and fuel from the rich in exchange for labor at&#13;
times of peak demand0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-23-&#13;
Table 4&#13;
Distribution of Population and Resources&#13;
by Income Group in Dhanishwar&#13;
Class             Landless        Poor        Middle        Rich       Village&#13;
Total_________                         ____________  Totals&#13;
Total&#13;
Population          40            100         222           60          422&#13;
Numbers of&#13;
Families           12             20          37            8           77&#13;
# of persons/&#13;
family              3-1/3           5           6            7-1/2&#13;
Available&#13;
Agricultural          1               1-3/4      2            2-1/4&#13;
Work Unit/Famil&#13;
Farm Resources&#13;
Per Farm:&#13;
Land (acres)                    .8         2.25         6&#13;
Labor (agricultural work&#13;
units, in days/year)'      315         360          405&#13;
Bullock2                        .3         1            3&#13;
Cows3                          0            .5          2&#13;
By Class&#13;
Land(acres)                   16          83.25        48          147.25&#13;
Labor(agricultural work&#13;
units/year)'                35          74           18         1394&#13;
Bullock2                       6          37           24           67&#13;
Cows3                          0          18.5         16           34.5&#13;
1Each agricultural work unit is assumed to represent 180 days of ten&#13;
hours/day work. This figure is the one used by Revelle in Science article.&#13;
2Each bullock is available in 1,000 hours of work per year (Makhijani and&#13;
Poole). Each one also produces six pounds of dry dung daily (BES) and eats&#13;
26.0 GJ.&#13;
Each cow produces 4.5 pounds of dry dung daily (BES) and eats 19.3, GJ&#13;
of straw yearly. Cows are assumed not to perform any agricultural work.&#13;
4Includes landless workers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
w              -l LOi N         r;&#13;
91      ri:     °  &gt;         (7\      vD  fco            t9    2) r-&#13;
X   S     tS                            cDtDtDe     tO Vo (t)t)~~~~~~~~o  r&#13;
O               [  (:      tn  67      )   t ,-(CO          f (I  L)&#13;
rD           _                  -o                               :3  .S J  ,&#13;
aSl          C.                                         C 1r4C   1   XC y  .&#13;
m         u      v9 ~~0  N              kg O               *   &#13;
rQ       ;~~~~A4  f 4        en  co&gt;°9                      n .  s s YJ Z  p&#13;
0                                                 vl C)  3n      Z    : IV&#13;
o.               6     ,            °     ')  F-4   z    h  ;d cm  34J &#13;
=    O  fd   O            (d       vi          j  U  tv  S l *~~~~~~~Ai &#13;
(  4gDa&gt;        F4  4;a                        n  o  3J  C) &#13;
co~~~~ 'F               _   9t4 C4 n          Ho'4           -   :&#13;
pq ~ ~ ~ ~  ~   f  OD     F4 F4(a sS               fj    &gt;  t° g=  f&#13;
B   O   V 4 144   fE   &lt;   h  .fCl red V-   C~~~~U)  ,l (&#13;
P14 ~ ~  ~    a  0                   °     r   OOOQ       .3 C  &lt;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-25-&#13;
(2) Energy in the Contest of Traditional Socio-Economic Systems:&#13;
Fatehpur, Bangladesh&#13;
53.       All the important energy sources in village Fatehpur, Bangladesh,&#13;
are derivatives of either crop production, tree cultivation, or animal hus-&#13;
bandry. Over 40 percent of the village population is landless, perhaps 80&#13;
percent have no cattle, and significant numbers of trees are owned only by&#13;
the more wealthy villagers. In short, the command of energy resources in&#13;
the village is highly skewed, with perhaps 50 percent of the population&#13;
commanding virtually no fuel-generating resources. When we look at energy&#13;
use rather than production, however, we know that all families do cook their&#13;
food despite the fact that so many command so few fuel resources. This dis-&#13;
tribution of fuels is mediated by a system of social relationships. These&#13;
relationships are central to the distribution of energy resources within the&#13;
village, the probable reaction of different groups to attempts to introduce&#13;
new energy technologies, and to the effects that adoption of such technologies&#13;
would have on the various groups within the village.&#13;
54.       Social equilibrium in the Indian-subcontinent has historically been&#13;
maintained through communal organizations and through vertical relationships&#13;
between powerful patrons and peasants. Since the introduction of private&#13;
ownership of land by the Permanent Settlement Act of 1793, patron-client&#13;
relationships have stemmed directly out of the possession of differential&#13;
rights in land. All those who worked for a landownever, either directly&#13;
as tenants, servants or laborers or indirectly as artisans or service sup-&#13;
pliers, tended to become clients. Landowners leased out land to tenants&#13;
and sharecroppers in part to reduce their management problems and in part to&#13;
ensure a supply of labor during planting and harvesting when labor shortages&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-25-&#13;
are common. A client was also a loyal follower in village affairs, adding&#13;
to the patron's power in the endemic factionalism characterizing village&#13;
politics, and as a helper on ritual occasions and times of crisis.&#13;
55.       The distribution of scarce energy resources is governed by the&#13;
social mechanisms which control the distribution of food and othor valuable&#13;
commodities. Thus, after meeting his ot-n needs for fuel, a traa-tional land&amp;&#13;
owner may neither compost all residual rice straw nor burn the straw _n the&#13;
fields -- the ash is a valued fertilizer -- but may allow clients to clear a&#13;
prescribed area of the harvested paddy field. Similar privileges may be&#13;
extended for the collection of cow dung from the cattle of the rfch.&#13;
56.       These systems persisted because t'ie patron-client relationship was&#13;
the only vehicle which satisfied the objectives of both rich and poor. The&#13;
system acquired an apparent stability, with the regulations governing the&#13;
appropriate behavior of patron and client embedded in the social norms of the&#13;
community. Now, these once stable systems are changing rapidly in Bangladesh,&#13;
India, and other parts of the world0&#13;
57.       Among the causes of this change in Bangladesh are the adoption of&#13;
high-yielding crop varieties and the mechanization of agriculturc, the in-&#13;
creased importance of non-agricultural sources of income (includ:tng govern-&#13;
ment employment), a decline in the availabiliLy of certain resources (such as&#13;
fisheries) and the consequent forcing of groups depending on these resources&#13;
in other pursuits, a reduction in the demand for agric-ultural labor, and an&#13;
enormous increase in the supply of agricultural labor0&#13;
580       These social changes manifest themselves in several ways in the&#13;
energy system of the village0   Farmers who have acquired land through recent&#13;
purchases, who farm their own land and who pay exclusively money tiages&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-27-&#13;
frequently burn the crop residues which they cannot use themselves. Ten&#13;
years ago no villagers had difficulty in obtaining sufficient crop residues&#13;
from a landed person. Today the procurement of sufficient fuel is a critical&#13;
problem for many families. While there are instances in which families simply&#13;
cannot cook their food for lack of fuel, these are still uncommon. What is&#13;
common, however, is a complete breakdown in the distributive mechanisms.&#13;
Many families in the village collect rice straw from others' paddy fields at&#13;
night when they cannot be detected. Disputes between landlords and share-&#13;
croppers over crop residues are frequent and often vehement. The number of&#13;
village trials resulting from disputes over fuel is rising rapidly.&#13;
59.       An awareness of these distributive mechanisms is essential for&#13;
successful planning. A program for the utilization of dung from a farmer's&#13;
cows and the straw from fields may not be attractive to a traditional farmer&#13;
since benefits may be insufficient to warrant the risk of damaging customary&#13;
relationships on which he depends for labor or other services.&#13;
60.       Where new technologies are adopted and the use of organic resources&#13;
improved in a thermodynamic sense, the adoption of these technologies may&#13;
hasten the deterioration of the resource base of the poor. This is apparently&#13;
the case with the biogas program in India. The average gas-plant owning&#13;
family in Gujarat has twenty-six acres of land and ten head of cattle. The&#13;
poor can no longer, as in the past, collect much of the cow dung from the&#13;
cattle of the rich.&#13;
(3) Deforestation and Energy Needs in a Mountainous Area: Nepal&#13;
61.       Examination of one of the world's best known environmental problems&#13;
provides insight into the difficulties of intervention in a village ecosystem&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
28-&#13;
without sufficient attention to socia;. 'ealiies; in this case the desperate&#13;
condition of the poor.&#13;
62.       Tne slopes of the HimalayEc- aze zin wiany areas -being vmshed away0&#13;
By some estimates,  it will only take anothez decace ox two befce    these mouzn-&#13;
tains will be so completely stripped oF the'ir tree cover that erosion, already&#13;
severe, will be virtually unrestrained0   fkhie irplicztions of such? a develop-&#13;
ment for both the Nepalese and for the populations dowunstream in Bangladesh&#13;
and India are appalling.&#13;
63.       Just a day's walk north ir..o the hIlls above the Kathmandu Valley,&#13;
the effects of deforestation on soil quality, erosion, and water supply are&#13;
strikingly visible. The trail benesth trees is rich, moist, dgrk earth full&#13;
of humus and spongy. But where trees bave b2en cut aw-ay, the soil is dry and&#13;
sandy, crumbling underfooto   Whole mozintainsides can be seen to have fallen&#13;
away in landslides0   Stream beds are dry or run £ bare trickde between down-&#13;
pours as there is little soil to sto:re moisture, Where slides hLve started,&#13;
there is no vegetation to stop the eazth, xAhich smothers any trees below^ and&#13;
increases the bare surfaces0   Nowhere can thiere oe seen a tree o-: bush un-&#13;
scarred by axes, knives, or browsing domestic an5imals0  The imprint of people&#13;
searching for fuel and fodder is to be seen everywinere0&#13;
64.       There are three main causes of the deforestation which follows&#13;
people into the hills: expansion of agricultural land, demand for f-odder to&#13;
feed domestic animals through the winter months, and demand for -irewocd0    In&#13;
the search for agricultural land on which 'to groW food, people are clearing&#13;
hillsides and practicing the traditional terracing used in the lower valley&#13;
areas0 Many terraces are narrow and sloped outware, inviting lardsilides&#13;
which can subject whole mountainsides to erosion,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-29-&#13;
65.       Although much of the fodder needed by the dense population of&#13;
domestic animals in Nepal is provided from pastureland grazing, there are some&#13;
months during the winter when animals must be brought from the high pastures&#13;
to the villages for safekeeping. During these months, fodder gathered from&#13;
trees is fed to the animals.&#13;
66.       All domestic space heating and cooking in hill households is with&#13;
wood. It is estimated that firewood consumption is three-quarters of a ton&#13;
per person per year. As fuel becomes scarcer, it takes more hours per day to&#13;
collect the household's supply, and areas of the forest never before exploited&#13;
are now subject to the woodcutter's axe.&#13;
67.       Combined, agricultural expansion, fodder and fuel gathering are&#13;
removing Nepal's forests at a rate that could be sustained only twelve to&#13;
thirteen more years. As more forest is removed for farming, the potential for&#13;
regrowth   reduced even further.&#13;
68.       Figure 2 outlines energy flows in a typical Nepal hill village.&#13;
Land use in such a situation would divide approximately as follows if&#13;
forests were harvested at their sustainable yield rates:&#13;
Cultivated           29 ha&#13;
Pasture              43 ha&#13;
Fuel Woodlot          73 ha&#13;
Forest Fodder         50 ha&#13;
Total            195 ha   =  0.78 ha/person,&#13;
which is approximately the per capita land availability for all of hill Nepal.&#13;
69.       Clearly a village is in difficulty if its per capita share of land&#13;
in forests is not available because of physical or political conditions, de-&#13;
forestation, or inaccessibility and it therefore has to exploit its forests&#13;
at a rate that cannot be sustained. This is unfortunately the case for a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Figure 2&#13;
Farm System in the Hills of Nepal&#13;
con-i4una:lly                                     Fam fami&#13;
owiied                                           @OK@&#13;
resouXcCs      183 tons&#13;
73ha woodlot for 1                   materialsl 250 people in &#13;
sustained produc Lion                                  48&#13;
FOREST LAND                                       HOMESTEAD&#13;
and&#13;
WATERSItED                                      C .         _&#13;
-+5Oha forest fort9           n2&#13;
~ &gt;5  28.7 ha&#13;
CUJLTIVATED&#13;
LAND&#13;
- '%              | (valley and&#13;
hill terraces)&#13;
s50 tons rice and&#13;
maize&#13;
~~~       _E &#13;
~Wa~ur       _______e _&#13;
Hy&gt;'   &gt;S rs ~~ fi O d      U     04&#13;
&lt;S 9                           14 7 cows        oe '&#13;
~~~~~~~~~~55 bulLso&#13;
H  n   e             ~~~~~85 tons           0O9CTC&lt; &#13;
rAST£UE          Qs      2   _   f;tI^#H            cattle and        o&#13;
.AZ ND                    e            a &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-31-&#13;
Notes on Figure 2&#13;
Village population: 250 persons; 48 households, 5.2 persons per&#13;
household.&#13;
Cultivated area: 28.7 ha; 8.7 persons per cultivated ha.&#13;
Cattle and buffalo population: 202 (147 females and 55 males or&#13;
bullocks).&#13;
Argicultura]. production: 50 tons (net) of maize (or rice as&#13;
maize equivalent) per year; about 1.75 tons/ha/yr.&#13;
Average diet: caloric intake (at 3.5 x 106 kcal/ton):&#13;
50 x 103kg        yr            1&#13;
yr          365 days  x 250 capita   = 0-548 kg/cap/day&#13;
1920 kcal/cap/day&#13;
About 40 percent consumed by children and 60 percent consumed by adults.&#13;
Dung production: About 180,000 kg/yr on a dry basis. (Approxi-&#13;
mately 2.5 kg dry dung/animal/day.)&#13;
Fertilizer Value: Assume 50 percent of dung recovered. At 1.7&#13;
percent N this amounts to about 1530 kg N. On 28.7 ha this would be&#13;
53 kg N/ha/yr.&#13;
Fuelwood: About 2 kg/cap/day or about 183 tons/yr. On a sustained-&#13;
yeild basis (2.5 tons/ha/yr), this would require about 73 ha. (Note&#13;
the current practice does not rely on sustained yield. Extensive&#13;
"tree mining" is practiced.)&#13;
Cattle food: About 1.2 tons/animal/yr of total digestible nutri-&#13;
ents (dry basis) are required; about 242 tons/yr total. At 1.75 tons&#13;
of straw, etc., per tone of foodgrain, of which 65 percent is digest-&#13;
ible, about 57 tons/yr of TDN come from farm fields. The deficit of&#13;
185 tons/yr must be made up from pasture during the snmmer (say 85&#13;
tons/yr) and the forest (say 100 tons/yr), each producing two tons/-&#13;
ha/yr.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
great many villages in hill Nepal where the forests are rapidly disappearing&#13;
and time spent wood collecting is rapidly escalating0&#13;
70.       The urgency of this problem cannot be overstated.   The traditional&#13;
answer to deforestation -- planting trees -- will not wJork if people are&#13;
forced to cut them down prematurely as a matter of survival. Unless refores&#13;
tation is begun sufficiently early that the existing stock of trees will last&#13;
long enough to allow the newly planted, higher-yielding varieties to reach the&#13;
proper size for cutting or unless it is backed up by other measures which&#13;
produce results quickly, giving the forest time to be reestablished and begin&#13;
producing, it will be a formula for failure.&#13;
710       One response to the need for agricultural land wsould be to increase&#13;
production on the better farmlands rather than expand agriculture into in-&#13;
creasingly unsuitable areas. This is a difficult task since most subsistence&#13;
farmers cannot afford to buy fertilizers, which is carried laboriously up the&#13;
steep hillsides on trails to the few who can afford to purchase iL0    Irriga-&#13;
tion would also be needed to produce second crops on the better farmland&#13;
during the dry season0&#13;
(4) Poverty and Deforestation: The Woodcutters of Bara, Sudan&#13;
72.       It is the poor who appear at the cutting edge of energy-related&#13;
environmental deterioration in many cases0 The poorest people in Bara9 Sudan&#13;
are landless0  With no stake in the land or the trees (which are often, if&#13;
not usually, cut illegally) the poor cut, maim, and burn for their own sur-&#13;
vival0 Cash from the crude charcoal they produce and sell is sometimes their&#13;
sole means of subsistence0 The poor use less fuel than the rich, but impact&#13;
on the land more severly0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-33-&#13;
73.        One such woodcutter explained the situation to Turi Digernes, a&#13;
Norwegian geographer studying fuel use in the Sudan as follows:&#13;
Never ever do we ask anyone any permission. We take trees&#13;
belonging to other people. We cut them when they are too&#13;
young. We never pay any tax. Everything is in a mess for&#13;
us now. We are in a miserable state after our animals&#13;
starved to death during the drought. We must live from&#13;
something. What else can we do?&#13;
What else can they do? They have no access to land for cultivation or tree&#13;
farming. They have no alternative employment. The demand for wood or char-&#13;
coal is there -- in the town where wood and crop residues are not available&#13;
to meet cooking and other fuel needs. So the poorest in the Sudan serve a&#13;
useful market-determined function: they collect and produce charcoal for&#13;
themselves and for others.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
III NATIONAL AND REGIONTAL STATISTICS AND PROJECTIONS&#13;
74.       "Energy", in most statistics, usually includes only tlhcse forms&#13;
marketed on a large scale by a centralized distribution system: coal, oil,&#13;
natural gas, electricity, nuclear, geothermal and hydro. These are generally&#13;
referred to as "commercial" energy forms.&#13;
75.       Energy collected and used in the traditional economic sectors&#13;
is not generally shown in national accounts unless it enters formal marketso&#13;
Much "non-commercial" energy is bought and sold, however0&#13;
76.       Estimates of availability and use of fuels derived from crop and&#13;
livestock residues and comparisons with commercial fuels on an energy basia&amp;&#13;
face a number of difficulties. The major ones are as follows:&#13;
(a) estimation of crop production levels and numbers of livestock&#13;
(unmarketed production is especially difficult to estimate);&#13;
(b) coefficient relating residue production to production of&#13;
primary products (the ratio of straw to grain varies by a&#13;
factor of 4.5:1 among varieties of rice grown in Bangladesh,&#13;
for example);&#13;
(c) energy content of residues (values used for energy content&#13;
of cow dung range from less than 9 to 18 GJ/tonne dry weight);&#13;
(d) availability of residues for fuel use (collection problems,&#13;
alternative uses of combustible materials, distribution of&#13;
ownership);&#13;
(e) differential efficiency of application of fuels in end-uses0&#13;
77o       The  same categories of difficulties arise when making estimates&#13;
for fuelwood. Primary production data for woodfuel is often even less&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-35-&#13;
reliable (or available) than agricultural production statistics. Because&#13;
fuelwood is not a direct by-product of roundwood production, as rice straw&#13;
is of rice grain, roundwood statistics, which usually are available, are&#13;
of limited use in estimating woodfuel consumption.&#13;
78.       Another difficulty for statistical analyses is that much fuelwood&#13;
in many developing countries comes from trees and shrubs in open country,&#13;
around houses and village common areas, along roads, or other areas not&#13;
classified as forests and therefore not included in official statistics.&#13;
79.       On the other hand, the FAO and some national forestry agencies&#13;
have attempted to estimate woodfuel consumption from survey data and incorpo-&#13;
rate the results into timber balances, whereas efforts to estimate use of&#13;
agricultural and animal residues have not been attempted in more than a few&#13;
countries.&#13;
80.       Survey data is not always reliable, however.   In most cases&#13;
enumerators do not actually measure use but rely on users' estimates and&#13;
recollections. Sometimes they measure use in terms of headloads or other&#13;
unit whose magnitude is not adequately measured. There are sometimes reasons&#13;
for respondents to exaggerate or minimize their reported use; there are few&#13;
reasons for them to remember correctly. One survey of rural fuel use extra-&#13;
polated from data gathered from households purchasing wood to all households,&#13;
ignoring the bias thus introduced. Finally, fuelwood comes in many species,&#13;
moisture contents, and includes leaves and twigs so that it is difficult to&#13;
accurately estimate heating values.&#13;
81.       As a consequence of the above difficulties, fuelwood production&#13;
and consumption estimates must be treated with great caution; FAO statistics&#13;
show numerous anomalies but are generally considered to be the best available&#13;
data.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
820       A number of projections of traditional fuels availability and&#13;
usage to 1990 have been prepared and appear on a country-by-country basis in&#13;
Annex Io  A summary of the woodfuels consumption projections is shown in&#13;
Table 6. They were prepared by extrapolating FAO statistics covering the period&#13;
1961-75. No attempt was made to (a) adjust the 1975 figures to account for&#13;
woodfuel use not reflected in the oficial statistics relied on by the FAO, (b)&#13;
distinguish between actual increases in consumption over the period 1961-75&#13;
and adjustments in data coverage and estimation teclhniques, or (c) take into&#13;
account differences in population density and discribution, incomes, and&#13;
increasing scarcity of wood that will make growth rates in woodfuel consump-&#13;
tion different in the period 1975-90 from what they were 1961-75. Thus, the&#13;
projections should not be considered as valid in all their details, but we&#13;
believe they present a roughly correct global picture and can sezve as a&#13;
consistent set of baseline estimates from which adjustments can be made&#13;
to take account of additional information and special circumstances in&#13;
individual cases.&#13;
830       In most cases, the projections for developing countries shoe^w&#13;
woodfuel consumption increasing but at a rate lower than the increase in&#13;
population. The most populous exceptions are Argentina and Mexico with&#13;
declining absolute consumption levels and Bangladesh, Burma, Indonesia,&#13;
and PR China with increasing per capita consumption. 1/&#13;
1/ Declining consumption is projected for Malawi, Sierra Leone, Ivory&#13;
Coast, Mauritius, Reunion, Jordan, Iraq, Fiji, Bolivia, Chile,&#13;
Colombia, Cuba, Guyana, Mexico, Argentina, and Trinidad and Tobagoo&#13;
Increasing per capita consumption is projected for The Gambia,&#13;
Swaziland, South Africa, Lebanon, Bangladesh, Burma, Indonesia,&#13;
Costa Rica, Uruguay, PR China and Mongolia.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
TABLE 6&#13;
WOODFUELS CONSUMPTION PROJECTIONS 1976-90&#13;
(million GJ)&#13;
1976     1980     1985     1990&#13;
Africa South of Sahara                       3011      3250    3527      3805&#13;
Ethiopia                                   250       271     289       306&#13;
Kenya                                      125       133     143       154&#13;
Tanzania                                   399       428     475       523&#13;
Ghana                                      115       131     151       172&#13;
Nigeria                                    699       763     849       935&#13;
Sudan                                      228       227     233      238&#13;
Uganda                                     148       164     177       190&#13;
Zaire                                      128       143     149       156&#13;
Others                                     919       990    1061      1131&#13;
North Africa and Middle East                   91        96     106       116&#13;
Asia and Pacific excl. OECD                  5627      6152    6744      7346&#13;
Vietnam                                    177       195     209       223&#13;
Afghanistan                                 63        67      73        79&#13;
Nepal                                       95       101     107       113&#13;
Pakistan                                    92       103     115       126&#13;
India                                     1285      1359    1483     1606&#13;
Bangladesh                                 152       191     231       271&#13;
Burma                                      207       258     305       363&#13;
Indonesia                                 1207      1344    1485     1625&#13;
Republic of Korea                           80        81      77        73&#13;
Malaysia                                    61        65      69        74&#13;
Philippines                                250       274     307       340&#13;
Thailand                                   175       186     201       216&#13;
PR China                                  1544      1667    1794      1924&#13;
DPR Korea                                   50        5.6     61        66&#13;
Others                                     189       209     227       247&#13;
Latin America and Caribbean                  2455      2584    2686      2788&#13;
Colombia                                   218       211     200      189&#13;
Peru                                        62        69      76        83&#13;
Mexico                                      89        87      83        78&#13;
Brazil                                    1522      1635    1721     1806&#13;
Argentina                                   87        82      76        70&#13;
Venezuela                                   80        89      98      107&#13;
Others                                     397       411     432      455&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
TABLE 6 (Continued)&#13;
1976     1980    1985     1990&#13;
Southern and Western Europe                 419      362     307       272&#13;
Turkey                                   114      139     147       157&#13;
Others                                   305      223     160       115&#13;
North America and OECD Pacific              225      132       86       55&#13;
USSR and East Europe                       1034       941     857      780&#13;
WORLD                                     12863     13516   14312    15163&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-39-&#13;
84.       Per capita woodfuel consumption levels in 1976/77 ranged from&#13;
0.0 to 25.2 GJ per annum. Table 7 shows woodfuel consumption data for 28&#13;
large, Bank member developing countries in "adjusted" per capita terms&#13;
(computed on the basis of total population less the urban non-poor, considered&#13;
to be an approximation of non-commercial energy using population). 1/ Table 7&#13;
also shows woodfuel consumption as a percentage of estimated sustainable&#13;
yield.&#13;
85.       Most (58%) of the population of these 28 countries is found in&#13;
the eight whose annual adjusted per capita consumption rates are below 3 GJ.&#13;
These are all countries in which forest resources are either quite limited&#13;
or else located in relatively less populated areas: India, Bangladesh,&#13;
Pakistan, Mexico, Egypt, Iran, Morocco and Algeria.&#13;
86.       Four countries with 8% of the aggregate population make up a&#13;
second group with adjusted consumption rates ranging from 4.1 to 6.5 GJ/&#13;
person-year. Twelve more with 25% of the population have adjusted consumption&#13;
rates from 8.0 to 10.3 GJ/person-year. In two of these, Ethiopia and Kenya,&#13;
fuelwood group comprises five countries with 11% of the aggregate population&#13;
and adjusted consumption rates in excess of 16 GJ/person-year.&#13;
87.       Four of the 28 countries consume over 100% of their estimated&#13;
sustainable forest yields as fuelwood and two others consume over 50%.&#13;
Among the developing countries covered in Annex I (over 100), estimated&#13;
woodfuel use is currently greater than estimated sustainable forest yields on&#13;
a national basis in at least twelve developing countries with an aggregate&#13;
1/ Countries shown are all Bank borrowers with 1975 total populations over&#13;
10 million except Afghanistan, Turkey and Romania, for which the&#13;
necessary data is not available.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
0  .   0  c',41&#13;
-4             -&#13;
Ci ro Cn llo C)N &#13;
00 u2~~~~~~&#13;
o    Jc  l co-4&#13;
N rs 0 0  u wr cs&#13;
M  cs rs ^  )  H&#13;
,-o  -4122&#13;
Cd -4 .0 c,&#13;
Cd  0)4  Cd  N 4 -4 4  c&#13;
PW                en S &#13;
a)~~~~~~~&#13;
Cd  (0  Cd&#13;
'0   0X  X  ~  4  ~ '   - O &#13;
-44&#13;
O)&#13;
02  *ad( &#13;
H ~ ~ ~ a- ai                  go_ _&#13;
0   0 f    c Y  -  . rs 0r&#13;
W   ;R  _  0w4   W _  _ __&#13;
0)  4U)  ~t~1 C =l.t(C   '.&#13;
X ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ l 2; _1 __&#13;
O   X&#13;
t0  v&#13;
o   43  U) O FZ o ^ eo s0 sO &lt;  O&#13;
o   0.  eoo      |N %C&#13;
sn~ ~ ~~- 0e A4&#13;
~~~~  0.~~~~~~~~~&#13;
~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
o    C.)   +   c  f&#13;
O)                0&#13;
4.4         0) C              Cd &#13;
Cd0)       C1CO dCd&#13;
00.  '14 4  4  d,4 &#13;
C0.  C02-4.&#13;
Q~~~ Y   r°c NslJ*&#13;
12-'      U&#13;
bCd  0021.4CdCdN.e 0O&#13;
~02   .CdCd00  00.40..  4.4     0. Q&#13;
.2.)      Cd'-401..A43A0)0 _     U&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0&#13;
0)&lt;       C) C'C-.)-  U'       C&#13;
b2  .          -1 &lt;0      -&#13;
0)C.~~~~~~~~~~~~  .0~~~   w  4&#13;
O-  *I n                    0)  0&#13;
.,     so            C         0 o &#13;
3d 0)  _ _ _ ._ C _ _        co0&#13;
O.  CD  O-.4  *.  _          0 2&#13;
0)04  '- _   '_I   C-        Cd 6&#13;
_     _  t _   0              0&#13;
-C  Vd 0 . ..t            0 &#13;
1-'                  E          X&#13;
CO U C  °O  &#13;
~~ X X  v W 1J   )   n&#13;
,-4 &lt;CdzCd  o           ) &#13;
6  ) ) 0      0 &#13;
0  a t  W  X&lt;°  X  &#13;
m440~                    Cd0)l&lt;  :  &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
1975 population of about 150 million.l/ Under present trends, the list will be&#13;
joined by 1990 by four more countries with an aggregate 1975 population of&#13;
about 170 milion. 2/ This does not mean, however, that deforestation is not a&#13;
problem in most of the remaining countries. Rather, deforestation often&#13;
occurs because extraction is geographically concentrated in those forests&#13;
areas most accessible to populated areas rather than being evenly distributed&#13;
across the forested areas. Thus, Zaire consumes only about 2% of its sustain-&#13;
able yield but experiences serious deforestation problems around Kinshasa.&#13;
88.       The picture that emerges from these data and other sources indicates&#13;
that there are two types of problem areas in terms of woodfuel availability.&#13;
In the first, wood is already scarce and other fuels are being used. These&#13;
areas include most of the drier areas of Africa, much of South Asia, PR&#13;
China, and some areas of Latin America. In a second group of countries, wood&#13;
is now widely used but receding forest areas will force a change in this&#13;
situation. This is primarily true in densely populated rural zones and around&#13;
cities with large populations where incomes do not permit the use of kerosene.&#13;
89.       Estimates of per capita resources of wood (sustainable yields),&#13;
animal dung, and crop residues for the year 1990 also appear in Annex I&#13;
and are summarized in Table 8 for the larger developing countries. The&#13;
estimates are subject to a variety of objections (forest yields are based on&#13;
1976 forest area, dung production is estimated without accounting for diffe-&#13;
rences in average animal size and nutrition from country to country, crop&#13;
1/ The countries are Burundi (4 million), Ethiopia (28), Kenya (13), Rwanda (4),&#13;
Sierra Leone (3), Uganda (12), Swaziland (0.5), Togo (2), Tunisia (6),&#13;
Pakistan (69), El Salvador (4) and Haiti (5).&#13;
2/ Upper Volta (6), Ghana (10), Nigeria (75) and Bangladesh (79).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
TABLE 8&#13;
ESTIMATED ORGANIC RESOURCES9 1990&#13;
(GJ per capita per year)&#13;
1/&#13;
Sustainable        Dung             Crop&#13;
Forest                          Residues&#13;
Yield&#13;
Ethiopia                               3               6SH             3&#13;
Kenya                                  1               7CS             4&#13;
Tanzania                              54              11 CS            3&#13;
Ghana                                  8               2CS             2&#13;
Nigeria                                8               3CS             2&#13;
Sudan                               148               18 CS            5&#13;
South Africa                           2               8CS            13&#13;
Algeria                                3               3SC             1&#13;
Egypt                                  0               1CH             6&#13;
Morocco                                6               5CS             5&#13;
Iran                                  22                 SC            7&#13;
Iraq                                   1               5CS             2&#13;
Vietnam                               12               1CP             6&#13;
Afghanistan                            6               8CS             7&#13;
Nepal                                 15              li CS            6&#13;
Paki tan                               1               6CS             7&#13;
India                                  6               5CS             6&#13;
Sri Lanka                             11               2CS             4&#13;
Bangladesh                             2               4CS             4&#13;
Burma                                 82               4CP             6&#13;
Indonesia                             63               1CS             6&#13;
Rep. of China                         n.a.             n.a.           n.a.&#13;
Rep. of Korea                          9               1 CP            7&#13;
Malaysia                             114               2CP             7&#13;
Philippines                           12               3CP             7&#13;
Thailand                              22               3CP             9&#13;
Chile                                 71               7CS             4&#13;
Colombia                            180               16 CH            4&#13;
?Gru                                 245               7CS             2&#13;
Mexico                                39               9CH             9&#13;
Brazil                               229              15 CP            9&#13;
Argentina                            104              45 CS           33&#13;
Venezuela                            211              11 CH            4&#13;
PR China                              11               3CP             8&#13;
DPR Korea                             24               1C P           13&#13;
1/ Primary sources indicated by letter codes:&#13;
C = cattle, buffalo, camel&#13;
S = sheep, goats&#13;
H = horses9 mules9 asses&#13;
P = pigs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
residues are based on similarly fixed ratios to product yield and only grains&#13;
and jute are included, no adjustment is made for crop residues used as fodder)&#13;
and they do not differentiate between resources that are readily available for&#13;
use as fuel and resources that are too widely distributed to be economical to&#13;
collect or which have higher-value alternative uses. They do, however,&#13;
indicate at least the general magnitudes of organic fuel availability in&#13;
different countries.&#13;
90.       The figures have interesting implications for the potential useful-&#13;
ness of proposed technical solutions in various contries. They indicate&#13;
for instance that in many developing countries the resource base does not&#13;
1/&#13;
exist to make biogas a major contributor to rural energy supplies.    Biogas&#13;
may become important in some areas of these countries or it may be widely used&#13;
for the treatment of human wastes and to make a contribution to energy require-&#13;
ments, but it will be limited by its resource base to a minor role in the&#13;
energy balances of Ghana, Nigeria, Algeria, Egypt, Vietnam, Sri Lanka,&#13;
Indonesia, Republic of Korea, Malaysia, Philippines, Thailand, PR China, and&#13;
DPR K.z:ea. It is much less clear which countries are good candidates for&#13;
biogas because the data do not distinguish between animals according to the&#13;
time they are kept in enclosures or grazed near a fixed point.&#13;
1/ Assuming no breakthroughs in the production of biogas from vegetable&#13;
matter.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 .&#13;
IV~ TECHIWOLO,1GM,'C_ JiC,ERaNAT'fVES&#13;
91.       It is important to keep inr m-ncl -_ f^- discuss-on of .--Chnologies&#13;
for the utilization of renewable enezgy thaL `2-ergy` is Lnot a IrDnogeneous&#13;
commodity and that the difficulties of Lraiskornmiing it from one :fo.m to&#13;
another are an important aspect of t12 su,pply V3oblem. An histoica-l example&#13;
of the importance of innovations i71 fn:=gy fCr2ns?o-i'aj Ion technology as&#13;
opposed to primary supply is the rolz- olayed by t-^ s'ee*m ^ngine in the&#13;
industrial revolution.    Steam engfi--te_ aXlowed for the transfoLn'at!cn of wood&#13;
and coal energy into mechanical energy. M-chanical energy for traqspor4i-ation,&#13;
industry, and agriculture had previouuiy come from human and animal muscles&#13;
and from wind and water power where _,iese could be harnessed.&#13;
92.       The fact that energy cannot- always be frceely and easily converted&#13;
from one form into another makes it necesszry to distinguish forms or kinds&#13;
of energy. Six of the many kinds of energy e-re important in either supply or&#13;
demand: fuels (chemical energy), higlh' 'traztatue !'eat, lov-tempezatuZe heat&#13;
solar radiation, mechanical energy, and electricity0  Some energy conversions&#13;
are inexpensive and efficient, others dciffcult and inefficient0  For example,&#13;
fuels are typically burned to produce high-zemoprature heat which may be&#13;
in effect diluted to produce low-temperature heat or converted, a:t an effi-&#13;
ciency seldom exceeding 35%, to mechanical energy in a heat engiPe of some&#13;
sort. Conversion of mechanical energy to e1-i-ricity and vice-versa is rela-&#13;
tively simple and efficient. Conversion of mechaMIcal or electrcai energy to&#13;
heat is not difficult or expensive, but it wouwd generally be a poor use of&#13;
resources.&#13;
93.       Solar radiation can be converted to lots-temperature bear- J-'Lth&#13;
simple devices, or to high-temperature heat wIl.h f:ocusing lenses cr mirrors,&#13;
or directly to electricity with a photo-volItaic cello&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
94.       Energy forms differ in their handling properties and the ease&#13;
with which they can be transported and stored as well as physical classifi-&#13;
cation. These differences are perhaps most important for the limits they&#13;
impose on the suitability of various alternatives for supplying mechanical&#13;
energy. Mechanical energy itself cannot generally be transported economically&#13;
any to significant distance, 1/ so it is usually produced where needed by a&#13;
heat engine, a wind or water-power device, or an electric motor. For mobile&#13;
mechanical energy requirements such as those of a vehicle or tractor the&#13;
choice is further restricted: wind is too inconsistent to use on land,&#13;
water-power is available only in fixed locations, and the use of electricity&#13;
requires either a portable power plant, a heavy investment in distribution&#13;
systems or the use of batteries, any of which are practical solutions in&#13;
special cases only. It is hard to suggest practical alternatives in most&#13;
cases to the use of fuel-burning heat engines for        vehicles and tractors,&#13;
and liquid fuels are generally preferable because they can easily be carried&#13;
and metered out to the engine at controlled rates to meet fluctuating power&#13;
requirements.&#13;
95.       These considerations make it convenient to group technological&#13;
alternatives according to the type of energy they produce. Four categories&#13;
are important:&#13;
(1) High-temperature heat and fuels not appropriate for&#13;
vehicle/tractor use;&#13;
(2) Low-temperature heat;&#13;
(3) Mechanical energy and electricity, and;&#13;
(4) Fuels appropriate for vehicle/tractor use.&#13;
1/   Pipelines provide perhaps the most significant exception.     The force&#13;
needed to move a fluid through a pipeline may be provided by a pump&#13;
station tens of kilometers away.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-46 -&#13;
96.       Technologies of the first group are the most directly t30zfL for&#13;
dealing with cooking energy requirements and most of the enviror-iental&#13;
problems related to traditional energy use. Low-temperature hiieai. sources can&#13;
also contribute to this goal by subst4tuting for fuels use where water heatirg,&#13;
drying and curing are important demands and for reducing food losses in the&#13;
drying processo Mechanical/electrical energy producing systems .iould replace&#13;
human or animal effort or investments in diesel sets or electric systems.&#13;
High Temperature Heat/Fuel Technologies&#13;
97.       The principal alternatives in this category are:&#13;
(a)  improved stoves (reduction in cookilg fuel requircinents)&#13;
(b) increased wood production&#13;
(c)  biogas (production of methane by anaerobic digestion)&#13;
(d)  pyrolysis (production of charcoal , producer gas, and&#13;
liquid fuel from wood)&#13;
(e) solar cookers,&#13;
These alternatives all show promise of being useful in a wide variety of&#13;
situations to supply the basic fuel needs of low income populations both urban&#13;
and rural.&#13;
98.       Improved stoves. The wide-spread technique of cooking over an open&#13;
fire is estimated to achieve 5-10% efficiency, and many traditional stove&#13;
varieties are not much better. The atoves illustrated in Figures LII1 and II--2&#13;
can be made of an appropriate mixture of widely available clay and sand,&#13;
simple hand tools, and as little as US$5 worth of sheet metal (or completely&#13;
from local materials if a pottery chimney is subscituted). Tnis type of stove&#13;
is reported to be capable of cutting firewood consumption by at least half&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
104.      Biogas has been produced and used for years at some installations,&#13;
but generally in a modern sector setting and with human or pig wastes as raw&#13;
material. To have an important effect on the ability of low-income communities&#13;
to obtain the food and fuel they need from limited soil resources, biogas&#13;
plant designs need to be developed that are cheap, operate reliably without&#13;
sophisticated management or maintenance, and are capable of making efficient&#13;
use of cattle dung and/or vegetable material. Work on at least three basically&#13;
different designs is being carried out in a number of countries. Construction&#13;
of biogas plants numbering in the thousands has been reported in PR China,&#13;
India, Republic of Korea, and Republic of China, and at least a hundred in&#13;
each of Thailand, Nepal, Philippines, and Pakistan.&#13;
105.      Economies of scale in biogas plant construction and operation are&#13;
important enough that the technology may be viable only on a community basis&#13;
or for relatively wealthy families with 4-5 cattle and land sufficient to&#13;
utilize the sludge produced. Community plants virtually require village-scale&#13;
public utilities, which will often be difficult to organize and maintain. Use&#13;
of the gas produced in a community plant also requires either communal cooking&#13;
facilities or an expensive distribution network. An Indian program subsidizing&#13;
the installation of biogas plants by those relatively well-off families who&#13;
could use them had to be dropped when it was found that one result was to&#13;
increase the effective price of dung, causing hardships for the poorest&#13;
segments of the population, who depend    on dung     from other people's&#13;
animals for their fuel.&#13;
106.      Pyrolysis.  Charcoal is traditionally produced by controlled partial&#13;
combustion of piles of wood covered with dirt. The resulting charcoal has&#13;
only about 25% of the fuel value of the original wood. The charcoal yields can&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
be raised to 40-50% with steel or ma&amp;onry ki-as, vinick-. alsc pzoLcZ a 3ette&#13;
quality product0  Most of the remaining eiergy is -re"leased in ll ustile&#13;
gasses and liquids whicn in some inst-alle' ±oixs can be captu-eL ac  ecusaO  n&#13;
order of increasing sophistication, three ap-poaches ihich ap,2E.ea  p.o,AsirG&#13;
are: (1) Portable steel kilns costing perhaps $1000 rjhic. wouid &amp;i3e&#13;
charcoal yi'elds to about 40% and redace labor cequirementso  Un:c.ate1y9&#13;
the cost of these units puts them out oL zeach of independent cbafcoal producecs&#13;
and appears to be justified only wihen a credit 'Is made for wood savz6 or laf.d&#13;
cleared. Use of these kilns is thus probably only feasible wh;ea access to &#143;&#13;
wood supply can be controlled or when the landowner is willing &lt;o pay ,o have&#13;
land cleared for replanting with hfgher value '6ze2s or other uses0   (2) Large,&#13;
immobile kilns have efficiencies closer to 50% ae1d much lower uoiL costs of&#13;
operation and amortization, but typically require a supply of wc2d of about&#13;
40 thousand m  annually at a fixed location, about the output of 20 km    of&#13;
high-yielding plantation. They are thus useful only wnhere tzaaGport costs&#13;
are low or where volumes of wood wastes are available as byproducLs from&#13;
other operations. (3) Retorts, which are heated from outside rvIher than by&#13;
burning part of the contents, enable the gasses a-nd liquids prodeced by&#13;
pyrolysis to be captured and used. Retorts were used for wood `d:'stil.lation-&#13;
on an industrial scale as late as the 1940s and have been sugges:ed as tihe&#13;
best use of processing plant residues such as rice hulls where   -      sre -s&#13;
an in-plant use for the gas and oil and a local market for chaic0al for&#13;
domestic purposes0&#13;
107.      Solar cookers. While mary designs have been developed that can,&#13;
give sufficient sunlight, boil water and cook food, tihey have noL in t'he past&#13;
been widely adopted due to the unacceptability of limiting cooki-ng to unshaded&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
areas during the brightest, hottest hours of the day. Storage of heat and&#13;
transport from the focal point of a collector to a separate stove are both&#13;
technically feasible, but not at an acceptable cost. The prospects for&#13;
development of successful solar cookers are thus not very promising, but&#13;
the value of even a partial reduction in cooking fuel requirements is high&#13;
enough that continued efforts to develop solar cookers seem well justified.&#13;
108.      Other technological alternatives for producing fuels or high-&#13;
temperature heat that may have promise, but for large-scale modern sector&#13;
applications, are:&#13;
(a) increased recovery and use of processing and milling&#13;
residuals, including sugarcane bagasse, sawdust, peanut&#13;
shells, rice hulls, etc.;&#13;
(b) reduction of forest harvesting waste to more easily&#13;
transportable forms such as chips;&#13;
(c) large focussing solar collectors.&#13;
Low-Temperature Heat Sources&#13;
109.           Simple solar devices requiring neither focussing collectors&#13;
nor expensive materials can be used for a variety of processes requiring&#13;
low-temperature heat. Water heating, heating of buildings, driers for crops&#13;
and fish, and distillation of water are the principal applications.&#13;
110.      Solar Water Heaters are widely used in Japan, Israel and Australia.&#13;
They appear to be economic alternatives to electric or fuel-buring water&#13;
heaters in many areas and manfacture is within the capability of many develop-&#13;
ing countries. Their use requires a willingness to pay for hot water, however,&#13;
so the major markets would be among industrial users, hotels, relatively&#13;
high-income households and institutions such as hospitals and clinics. Use&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
of solar water heaters in community oaTP%ic En  cnr. 'aouses -ay al -- oe feas o.--&#13;
in some areas and some ruzal industzr:2s soCo az '   im- nn:   ana dy&amp;  ' ±,y f--&#13;
them profitable to use where traditCval fuelss    £-c apansive.&#13;
111o      Solar Driers  can provide covC-o'ke6 r.ea-t to reduce a-, ng -LLe&#13;
and reduce losses due to rotting, inszc-s, rr36 rcuenLs. Fcotlcmi   'ers:t'bli,y&#13;
depends in many cases on designing fo   -ocEL p-codTctlo' and mflai-a.-LateriE:&#13;
cost.&#13;
1120      Solar Water Distillation.  `I sLi 1 .ation of airty5 infe;:._c, or brac1C sh&#13;
water is one of the earliest known ue3s of' direct SOIEenc-fgy :° a2vet op_n&#13;
countries. It was used in Chlie betweeza 132 Fau 1920 for po.ab*    Tater for&#13;
miners and work mules at a mining ope,ai.ion.  Since that Lime, solar distillers&#13;
have been used in the U.S.9 USSR9 Austalia, Carei-ooean, and is:lards tihere o&amp;-y&#13;
brackish, unfilterable water exists a-nd effo ts to find and develop undergroundc&#13;
sources of sweet water prove futile. 'ae-ne is also a simall markel for distilled&#13;
water for health clinics and vehicle 'battere's that in somae isolated areas car&#13;
best be served with solar distillati°on equipment.&#13;
Mechanica . nd e2ctrica21 Energy&#13;
1130      High temperature heat produced ay concentrating solar znergyD by&#13;
burning fuels, or from some other souL:cc can be converted zo mec lan- cal or&#13;
electrical energy through the use of heat engines0 Biogas reportz-C-Ly u crks&#13;
well in internal combustion engines and prccrcer gas has been usnl, i'n some&#13;
situations. Wood and other solid fuels can be used by externli zcmoustion&#13;
engines such as the steam engine0   A1ternat:ivzs with Eopzrent L-    nesS in&#13;
developing countries include:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
(a) micro-hydro turbines and waterwheels,&#13;
(b) windmills, and;&#13;
(c) photo-voltaic cells.&#13;
1140      Micro-hydro.  Waterwheels designed and built by traditional artisans&#13;
are used in several countries. Modern turbine systems with capacity of less&#13;
than 50 kw have been installed in at least two dozen developing countries.&#13;
Most micro-hydro systems require a head of at least about 3 meters to operate.&#13;
To provide a typical rural household connection with 300 watts for 5 hours per&#13;
day with a 3 meter head would require about 300 m /day of water;&#13;
enough to 5-10 ha of land. The volume of&#13;
water required varies in approximately inverse proportion to the head, but it&#13;
would seem clear from the volume and head requirements that only a small&#13;
fraction of the rural population of developing countries can be electrified&#13;
with micro-hydro. The most promising areas of micro-hydro are probably&#13;
middle-income countries with populated high-rainfall mountainous areas. A&#13;
number of Latin American countries fit this description.&#13;
115.      Windmills of both traditional and advanced design exist.    Developing&#13;
country applications have mostly been for water pumping. Wind energy varies&#13;
with the cube of wind speed, so their economic viability varies greatly&#13;
according to location. The coastal areas in many developing countries appear&#13;
to have enough wind to make windmills worth considering. The most interesting&#13;
areas are those with adequate winds and poor rainfall. Among these appear&#13;
to be parts of northern Mexico, Peru, Chile, Argentina, northeastern Brazil,&#13;
the African coast from about Senegal clockwise around to Somalia, Namibia,&#13;
Yemen PDR, India, and Pakistan.&#13;
116.      Photo-voltaic cells reportedly cost about $15 per peak watt (watt&#13;
produced under near optimum conditions) with an additional expenditure of&#13;
about the same magnitude required for structural supportj auxiliary electrical&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54 -&#13;
equipment, and a typical amount of bat.ery storage. 'Ae cel.sies t   cvee a:_&#13;
declining in cost and are projected to reach $i/peak wat.I by khe    d .SOso&#13;
such a cost reduction would widen the ran-age of opportun,tLes for      -,&#13;
of photo-voltaic cells, especially in applicatio,s th-at do not recJ-r storage&#13;
and where the necessarily structural support can be mulT-Ati-purpOSe2  iCouo1n:!c *useCs&#13;
are presently limited to cases such as telecommunications equipme,l: and&#13;
navigational lights that require small amounts of electricity in 1cca,:Lo&#143;1s&#13;
where alternative sources are extraordinarily expensive.&#13;
Vehicle and Tractor Fuel s&#13;
117,      An average adult human is reportedly able to perform tashs requiring&#13;
to about 75 watts or 001 horse--power on a sustaired basis and oxen four to&#13;
eight times as mucho   Mechanized vehicles allow agdiculturpl and t:arsport&#13;
tasks to be performed much faster than is possible wi^-th hiuman and animal&#13;
power. They have fuel requirements, however; thmt are difficult to meet&#13;
cheaply from sources other than petroleum0 Stea-m engines are heavy and&#13;
inefficient. Internal combustion engines requirc lilqufd or gaseous fuels.&#13;
Carrying useful quantities of gaseous fuels requires pressurized s1orage- 'The&#13;
principal candidate alternatives are biogasg pyroly3is gas (genera2zd or board&#13;
the vehicle) and alcohol.&#13;
118.      Biogas is a useable engine fue2l but cannot be pr'oducead e.t ac'equate&#13;
rates in any generator that can be carried on a vzeicle0   CMpCCesse'3n 0: Lhe gas&#13;
would be expensive and the containers b-ulky and heavy0&#13;
119.      Pyrolysis gas has been used in vartIme to allow veof:cle .o run on&#13;
w-ood fuels0  The difficulty of filtering che gas suffic½fantly well -o protect&#13;
the engine appears to be the major problem with this technoiogy ia z eas with&#13;
adequate wood supplies to support vehicle fuel deemands0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
120.      Alcohol is probably the most promising candidate.   It is most&#13;
efficiently produced on an industrial scale, however, and is still consider-&#13;
ably more expensive to produce than petroleum fuels. It can also be sold for&#13;
industrial uses for more than it saves in gasoline costs when used in vehicles.&#13;
For these reasons, use of "gasohol" does not appear economical at current&#13;
prices (although financial viability is provided in some countries where&#13;
the gasoline component of the mixture is exempted from normal taxes).&#13;
V. RECOMMENDATIONS&#13;
A. SUBSTANTIVE PROGRAMS&#13;
121.      No one program of action can be recommended that will be uniformally&#13;
appropriate for all developing countries. The discussion below focuses on a&#13;
number of measures that we feel could usefully be taken in a number of countries,&#13;
without a long R&amp;D/Survey/Study process. The alternatives to be discussed are:&#13;
(a) increasing forest cover and fuelwood production,&#13;
(b) improved charcoal production methods,&#13;
(c) improvements in cooking stove efficiencies,&#13;
(d) exploitation of small-scale hydro and wind resources; and&#13;
(e) full use of presently unused or under-utilized milling wastes.&#13;
122.      The formulation of a program for a specific country should be&#13;
based on at least a general analysis of the problem to be addressed. A basic&#13;
group of indicators to consider in orienting a traditional/non-conventional&#13;
energy program toward the most important among the various goals that might be&#13;
set would include:&#13;
(a) types of fuel commonly used by households and general&#13;
pattern of variation geographically and by income level,&#13;
(b) cost of household fuels in money and/or time,&#13;
(c) ability to pay for electrification,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(d)  apparent pace of dJ-O           '-S 2ati^  .cZs O:&#13;
fuelwood gatlheri.nig 9 _F,a  C Jc.cai7pg and a:lil 'brcP.' -Lg&#13;
in causing it; scroous"ass l`n -evn  ol e rosiori; E&#13;
(e)  types, scale and loce.ion o' p--ocessing elLnts, .'v   -I g&#13;
large quantities of uwod aad opian.. iatezL:.' BG &amp;   I&#13;
sugar anLa lumber mil1s.&#13;
With even a general knowledge of these .LQJezLs ;E should oe posciboe to&#13;
judge the relative importance of var::o.s gcalo sach au&#13;
prevent erosion in zone xS9&#13;
-    reduce the time spent gai-!ling F-jel in aceae y;&#13;
-    develop an inoxpensivc scs,,ze of fuel four lo. !azc -le&#13;
households in city z,&#13;
bring the amenities an,. developEant boostin-tg Jene. -s&#13;
of electrification to x% of villages a',: 2n a£.forsC..3e&#13;
cost; and&#13;
-    substitute domestic sGurces fo.f i-ported pet3olz9%&#13;
123.      Afforestation and reforestation programs can yie±d h:- s_ re-urns I4&#13;
they are carefully managed and if appr.opriate lands are ava"labk0    "Careful&#13;
management" in this context refers botb to t7he technical package used and&#13;
to the organization to care for and regulate th'_ use of *oodlotsl   7"Appropriat:&#13;
lands" are those which need tree cover _o7 soi- consezvac-Jon pu-oposes aend/ox&#13;
are of high enough agricultufal qualicy ts grow L-ees but not so ;ood. that iL&#13;
is better to use it for crops. Under: favoreole condcitiois a xioo'_..   growing&#13;
program would cost about $200 per hectare and begin to yieeld 10 '-onifes of&#13;
fuelwood per hectare per year after 5-10 years, 'he investmenLt costs are&#13;
about $4 per tonne 1/ or $2 per person per yea,, at average rates o, corsux'3&#13;
tion.&#13;
124.      Charcoal production efficiencies can be inc.reased s&amp;ubsic&lt;alty ove-&#13;
those obtained by traditional methods ulta either smat, portcble 'cilos or&#13;
large stationary unitso The portable steel kilr.s conse.wve woiod zzlative&#13;
to traditional earthkiins at an equipment cost of abouL $405/¢oL:e 2/ and&#13;
1/ Compounded at 10% p.a. for 7 years0&#13;
2/  Escalating 1972 equipment costs along urit, zahbon steel prices 'Lc a&#13;
1977 basis and assuming a 3-year life0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
stationary steel furnaces do so at a much lower cost in equipment (perhaps&#13;
$0.25/tonne of wood saved) but require a much greater cost in collecting wood&#13;
to a central point. The choice among these and other alternative technologies&#13;
would have to be made on the basis of local conditions, including the role of&#13;
traditional charcoal production as a form of self-employment requiring very&#13;
little capital and as a way of "poaching" forest resources. Where these&#13;
considerations are important, the major difficulty will not be technological&#13;
but one of devising and implementing an organizational scheme that will offer&#13;
employment using modern charcoal techniques on terms more attractive than&#13;
those on which an individual can go into charcoal production using traditional&#13;
means.&#13;
125.      Measures to increase the efficiency of cooking stoves can produce&#13;
rapid reductions in demand for fuelwood, dung, and crop wastes for use as&#13;
cooking fuel, at low cost. An effective program requires careful design&#13;
adaptation to produce a stove which can be easily constructed from locally&#13;
available materials and which will conform to the intended users' require-&#13;
ments. It also requires a well-organized extension effort to train people to&#13;
be stove-builders and to demonstrate to the population at large the possi-&#13;
bility of reducing substantially the need to collect or purchase fuel by&#13;
adoption of an improved stove. If a stove program costs $10 per stove and&#13;
reduces fuel consumption by one-half, then the effect is as if cooking&#13;
fuel were provided to half the population with an investment of $20 per&#13;
household or about $4 per person, or under $1 per person per year.&#13;
126.      Small-scale hydro and wind systems should be considered as alter-&#13;
natives to conventional rural electrification and water pumping technologies.&#13;
The cost of small hydro installations will not be low enough in many instances&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 58 -&#13;
to allow the to be used for cooking , but they nay oc fo-znd coitp' .',_  i&#13;
the cost of bringing power to an arez f'3om an established elec&gt;  :a' grid o:&#13;
generating It locally with small diesel setso   S-in milarIy2 , idnl  s w  : b&#13;
found competitive with conventional pumps in many areas w-'nece avz:ag2 e  Jnd&#13;
speeds are at least 15 kcm/h and costs o' electricIty or diesel c:: gcassline&#13;
fuel and maintenance are relatively iilgh.&#13;
127.      Mill wastes include sugarcane  bagasse, sawdust a&#156;d ti'. shellsD&#13;
pulp, husks and other materials that are often byproducts of ooc; ana crop&#13;
processing operations. In many cases these materials are used p.^sductively&#13;
and efficiently while in others they are dumped, incinerated or inde&#13;
utilized. Countries in which these industri-es are importantt shcd consider&#13;
investigating the possible uses of byproducts as fuels, Includi-3 possibi-&#13;
lities such as driers to raise the fuel value of bagasse, pyrolysis units thaL&#13;
produce gas and char oil for in-plant use and charcoal for sale, r-evision cf&#13;
electricity tariff terms to encourage cc generation, and machines to producc&#13;
briquettes or pellets from loose material in order to produce a .-uel suitable&#13;
for domestic uses.&#13;
B. RESEARCH MEEDS&#13;
128.      The recommendations outlined below include research of oroblem&#13;
identification and analysis, technical research, development anad demonstration&#13;
of promising technological approaches, and research and trial of prfloject desigsi&#13;
and implementation techniques.&#13;
129.      In problem identification and analysis three general a.es are&#13;
especially important:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 59 -&#13;
(1) Surveys of traditional energy supply, trade, and use are needed&#13;
to establish base-year numbers and the order of magnitude of response to&#13;
increasing scarcity, price and income changes. We feel that investigation of&#13;
survey methodology and possibilities for cross-checking and inferring figures&#13;
from agricultural and forestry data and remote sensing techniques is needed as&#13;
well as sample surveys of households and other users.&#13;
(2) Estimates are needed of environmental damages associated with&#13;
alternative levels and patterns of traditional energy use. Much of the concern&#13;
for this subject stems from the apparently serious consequences of deforestation&#13;
(erosion, siltation and flooding downstream, desertification) and burning of&#13;
crop and animal wastes (loss of soil conditioners and nutrients) in many areas.&#13;
Sufficient research needs to be done on the cost in terms of agricultural&#13;
production of these damages and the role of fuel collection in producing them&#13;
to establish priorities.&#13;
(3) Identification of policy and investment priorities might also&#13;
be improved through research into the role of electricity and inanimate mechanical&#13;
energy in rural development. Mechanization and electrification are widely&#13;
identified with development by governments and the argument is made that&#13;
evaluation criteria such as those used by the Bank do not give credit for&#13;
the dynamic effects on the development process of projects such as rural&#13;
electrification. Studies to date have indicated the issue is a valid one but&#13;
have not developed the tools needed to adequately quantify these effects to&#13;
allow an accounting for them in project assessment.&#13;
130.      Technical research.   Most of the technical research and development&#13;
being done on renewable energy is directed toward the major energy problem of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 60&#13;
developed countries': finding alternatives for limited petroleum resources.&#13;
Developing countries with their growing urban-modern-industrial'sectors stand&#13;
to benefit from this research as the technologies are improved and conventional&#13;
energy prices rise.  However, the ecological differences between the tropics&#13;
and temperate zones give many developed countries significantly different&#13;
possibilities than those being studied for developed country use, especially&#13;
in terms of biomass production. Much of the technical R&amp;D on small scale&#13;
technologies for developing country environments is focused on providing&#13;
inanimate mechanical power and/or electricity for stationary applications. We&#13;
feel that much emphasis should be placed on the problem of cooking, including&#13;
fuels, stoves, utensils, and solar cookers. Improved use of draft animals&#13;
also appears to be a relatively neglected field.&#13;
131.      International cooperation in R&amp;D efforts can help to avoid duplica-&#13;
tion of effort and provide for cross-fertilization and cross-checking of&#13;
ideas. The form of cooperation that is most appropriate for a given technology&#13;
or'group on technologies varies from case to case. Basic research may not need&#13;
to be repeated in a large number of countries, although such replication may&#13;
be a worthwhile means of transferring technology. Adaptation of designs to&#13;
local materials and requirements is almost necessarily done in local institu-&#13;
tions, although the process may be accelerated by improving communication&#13;
among workers in different countries. Work on some technologies such as solar&#13;
cookers might usually be concentrated in a relatively small number of institu-&#13;
tions because to date designs have not been developed that could serve as the&#13;
basis for successful adaptation efforts in many countries. In general, the&#13;
number of centers working on a.given technology should increase as progress is&#13;
made from theoretical understanding of first principles to engineering of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 61 -&#13;
equipment and as a function of the need to develop different design approaches&#13;
and make different materials choices in different countries.&#13;
132.      Project design and implementation trials will be needed to learn how&#13;
and how not to attempt to move technologies out of laboratories and into homes&#13;
and communities. Improved woodstoves appear to be a technically simple, low-cost&#13;
solution or partial solution to fuel shortages in many areas. They have been&#13;
adapted to local conditions in a number of countries, but successful extension&#13;
techniques have not been proven on a large scale.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX X&#13;
-62-&#13;
STATISTICS AND PROJECT&amp;XO&#142;S&#13;
1.   As the discussion in the main text indicates, there is con- d:e2ble&#13;
uncertainty regarding both the demand and supply sides of the ,-e of&#13;
traditional fuels. Although potential supply can be estimated from&#13;
aggregate forestry, agriculture and livestock information, basic fuel&#13;
needs are strongly influenced by cultural, nutritional and enviyormental&#13;
factors.  Actual utilizvtion or demanad for traditional fuels is strongly&#13;
influenced by access to supplies, and to a lesser extent by incoyri level.&#13;
Consequently, neither the overall utilization nor the compositicn of&#13;
fuels can be estimated accurately from information on the nation-lal level.&#13;
Firewood may be available on the national level, but If the nearest&#13;
woodstand is 100 km away, a shift to cereal siraw and/or dung is quite&#13;
likely. Site specific surveys and measurement are necessary ano. for most&#13;
countries such information is lacking. The available survey data is&#13;
summarized in Table I-lo&#13;
2.   Nevertheless, in order to estimate the magnitude of traditional&#13;
fuel use and availability in all countries and to indicate pro^olsm areas,&#13;
baseline figures and projections were constructedo The results of thls&#13;
exercise must be viewed keeping in mind the data difficulties described&#13;
above, as yell as the masking of regional, economic class and seasonai&#13;
variations in traditional fuel use and availability involved in wYorking&#13;
with data at the national level0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-63-&#13;
TABLE I-1 HOUSEHOLD USE OF TRADITIONAL FUELS: SURVEY DATA&#13;
(GJ/capita/yr)&#13;
Percent of&#13;
Total       Firewood                 Agri-         National       National&#13;
Traditional        and       Animal     cultural      Population        Average&#13;
Fuel Use       Charcoal     Residue     Residue     Using Tradi-     Traditional&#13;
Country            Locale        Year       -    (For Traditional Fuel Users Only               tional Fuels      Fuel Use I/&#13;
Bangladesh 2/     national      1973/74         2.56           .41         .77       1.38           91%              2.32&#13;
Gambia 3/         national       1972          17.3         17.3                                    99%             17.3&#13;
India 4/            rural        1970           7.16         4.38         1.77       1.02&#13;
Kenya 5/                         1960          10.9         10.9&#13;
Nepal 6/          national      1974/75         8.5           8.2          .1         .2            99%              8.5&#13;
Nigeria 3/        northern,      1972          10.5         10.5                     n.a.&#13;
urban&#13;
Peru 7/            national      1976          17.7          15.1             --2.6--               60%             10.8&#13;
Sudan 3/          national       1964          14.2         14.2                                    99%             14.2&#13;
Tanzania             rural 8/    n.d.          29.9          29.9&#13;
national 9/   1961           12.3         12.3&#13;
national 10/  1970           23.2         23.2                                    99%            23.2&#13;
Thailand 3/       national       1972          14.2          14.2                                   97%             14.7&#13;
Uganda 5/                        1959          10.9          10.9&#13;
Upper Volta 11/      rural       1977           4.2           2.3                    1.9&#13;
Note:  Conversions to energy units were made as needed assuming wood fuel specific gravity of 0.725 and energy&#13;
content of 15 GJ/metric ton, agricultural residues at 13 GJ/ton at 20% moisture, and dung at 15 GJ per dry ton.&#13;
1/  The relationship between the national average for per capita traditional fuel use and the traditional fuel&#13;
user average is based on the percent of the total population which uses such fuels.    Specifically the national&#13;
average is the product of actual use estimates and the percentage of users.&#13;
2/ Data are from Bangladesh Energy Study.&#13;
3/ Information is from a study referenced in K. Openshaw, Wood Fuel -- A Time for Re-Assessment (stencil) 1977,&#13;
p.4.&#13;
4/ Roger Revelle, "Energy Use in Rural India, "Science," vol. 192, no. 4243 (1976), p. 973. Of the animal&#13;
residue use 0.71 GJ per capita is for cottage industrial use (brick making, pottery, etc.). Many other&#13;
Indian energy studies have been undertaken; however, some of the best recent work was only on a regional&#13;
basis. The Revelle paper was used because it conveniently presents India-wide results.&#13;
5/ FAO-assisted study quoted in J.E.M. Arnold, Wood Energy and Rural Communities, Eighth World Forestry&#13;
Congress, 1978, p.6.&#13;
6/ Energy Research and Development Group, Tribhuvan University, Nepal -- The Energy Sector, November 1976, p.15.&#13;
7/ Meta Systems Inc., Traditional Energy and Rural Development Issues and Recommendations for Peru, prepared for&#13;
Brookhaven National Laboratory and the U.S. Department of Energy (September 1978).&#13;
8/ p. and A. Fleuret, Fuelwood Use in a Peasant Community.&#13;
9/ An FAO study quoted in FAO, Present Consumption and Future Requirements of Wood in Tanzania, based on the&#13;
work of K. Openshaw, Rome, 1971, p.21.&#13;
10/ The results of a more recent FAO study on Tanzania, Ibid.&#13;
11/ Elizabeth Ernst, Fuel Consumption Among Rural Families in Upper Volta, West Africa, July 1977.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
30   Estimates of animal and agricultur&amp;aj rc       '`u-- s uzl use are  Il E bls I .f'z&#13;
a few countries. These are shown     -i TlDbe  -2, l'otuntt'.l SUpp-y C',s, imates&#13;
aan, however, be developed for mos_ LotzntLi`s,&#13;
4.   Fuelwood and charcoal product:on   -nfoLA.t-   is avalilaolc  .om t^&#13;
FAO Yearbook of Forest Products althouga th2 accuracy of suc'- c--£         De&#13;
questioned. The figures are generally offKci-K.     g-s from 'fi' ons &gt;&#13;
governments, and in some cases they :    d     1.t.y productiox fro- 'laniagzo.&#13;
forests.&#13;
5.   Nevertheless, the FAO informatico will be used as the bas§t fo:. the&#13;
estimates of present and future tradiui.ov.l fuel use.    Besi6es '.;'e &amp;.ovs&#13;
difficulties, however, it must be not_a ': at .'27O ooes not eisagg._zgci:e&#13;
industrial and domestic fuelwood and chiarcce'L use.&#13;
60   Unlike agricultural and livestoc:c sa,      . nPatistics coverin8 FoTsst,&#13;
woodlot and tree stand inventories and yicIds sre rarely availa&amp;L.e.&#13;
In addition, accessibility factors Etre clific. t to ascert.       *Torest&#13;
and woodland area data are presented in the, )TAC Production Year'Dooo.t&#13;
but the data are approximate and do not usi.aliy iDclu6s such wco6 sources&#13;
as small woodlots, fruit trees, trees alc.sg roies, v*cd sc&amp;.tereL  : .:r-es.&#13;
Furthermore, the FAQ figures sometilires include lan.d WtliIch may b'o  c:sforssted&#13;
in the future and does not always caoture the reduc-:4on of foree- 1 E-6d due&#13;
to wood use and land clearing.&#13;
7&gt;   The projections presented here ofov56c ar) i'tJdicatf o-ft of ';9_ poLentiai&#13;
of residues as an energy source, bu: clo 'no' 1ae 3eo eCCOUnf: i'-: Qegi8ee to&#13;
which residues are required for use as fori.iliZe:, ft,dd£r9 or cC%SZL:UC`ion&#13;
Burning these residues can bring a'ocut several proBle,-!,s concez.ni-.ng, for&#13;
example, soil fertility, farm yielcds, andl 'ivestock he,lth.   T'n efore   the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-65-&#13;
TABLE I-2. ESTIMATES OF AGRICULTURAL AND ANIMAL&#13;
RESIDUE FUEL USE (million GJ)&#13;
Total Agri-            Total&#13;
Total Animal          cultural            Residue&#13;
Country           Year               Residue Use          Residue Use          Fuel Use&#13;
1/&#13;
Bangladesh       1973/74                  53                  95                  148&#13;
P.R. ChinaZ/      1970                                       960                  960&#13;
India (rural)3/   1970                   779                 448                 1227&#13;
Nepal4/          1974/75                   1                   2                     3&#13;
Pakistani/       1973/74                 106                  81                  187&#13;
Peru&amp;/            1976                          --25--                              25&#13;
Upper Volta7j     1977                                         9                     9&#13;
TOTAL                                                                            2559&#13;
Notes: Bagasse is not included in these estimates. Unit conversions as necessary were&#13;
made using same assumptions as for Table I-1.&#13;
1/ Bangladesh Energy Study, 1975.&#13;
2/ V. Smil, China's Energy (Praeger:   New York, 1976), p. 101 estimates agricultural&#13;
residue fuel use by netting out fodder from potential supply and then assuming that&#13;
one-half of the remainder is used as fuel. All animal residues appear to be used&#13;
as fertilizer.&#13;
3/ R. Revelle, "Energy Use in Rural India," Science, vol. 192, no. 4243 (1976).&#13;
4/ Energy Research and Development Group, Tribhuvan University, Nepal -- The Energy&#13;
Sector, 1976.&#13;
5/ Brookhaven National Laboratory, A Preliminary Analysis of Energy Supply and&#13;
Consumption in Pakistan, Draft, December 1, 1977, p. 19 referencing a survey by&#13;
the Energy Resources Cell of the Ministry of Fuel and Power in Pakistan.&#13;
6/ Meta Systems, Inc., Traditional Energy and Land Development Issues and&#13;
Recommendations for Peru, prepared for Brookhaven National Laboratory and the&#13;
U.S. Department of Energy (September, 1978).&#13;
7/ Elizabeth Ernst, Fuel Consumption Among Rural Families in Upper Volta, West&#13;
Africa, July, 1977.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-66-&#13;
energy potential of residues must be considered in light of thz Competing&#13;
uses and potential damaging effects.&#13;
8.   The traditional fuel use and availability estimates and project-ions&#13;
required a range of agricultural, Livestock and forestry statisss:.c  and&#13;
projections as well as a set of residue and wood yields and sne: y&#13;
content factors. There is little consensus in published literature as to&#13;
the precise value of most of the required information0&#13;
9.   Before presenting the complete table of traditional fuel setimates&#13;
and projections, it will be useful to presenS an expanded form of the&#13;
table for a few countries as well as some figures which illustrate several&#13;
points concerning this exercise. Table Y-3 presents rough estimevtes of&#13;
present and future use and potential supplies of the types descr3bed&#13;
above; in addition some estimates of traditional fuel consumptio-" are&#13;
presented other than the FAO fuelwood and charcoal figures, The domestic&#13;
demand range entries reflect judgements based on the literature about&#13;
the level of traditional fuel consumption by that fraction of    h'--&#13;
population which primarily uses such fuel0 Tnis range is based oa rural&#13;
consumption studies, and the relationship between this range and &amp;iational&#13;
averages is primarily a function of the availability and relative cost&#13;
of commercial fuels (primarily kerosene and electricity), the degree of&#13;
urbanization and the accessibility of traditionai. fuel supplies,&#13;
10.  These effects can be clearly seen in the case of Peru. Baseci or a recent&#13;
survey of traditional fuel use and estimates of the number of trEditLonal fuel&#13;
users, actual annual use of fuelwood and charcoal and of small auiounts of&#13;
residue was estimated to be about 18 gigajoules per traditional fuel user0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-67-&#13;
1-4 ~&#13;
C U&#13;
4r -r- o             0     oa o .  0&#13;
5- : H                O l -( o  N        U I N  X&#13;
a)OU)&#13;
-W.I1-H  a)         Ifl Lf  LAL   LA    (LA &#13;
o .O@t                       S    S     N&#13;
0P40&#13;
HO  ~~~~  CU~~~~fl  04(1  0~~~~C)-4  WLfl  C'4n&#13;
4J 4J r         o    a) 1-4  kD k0  CS O 4  U'  a L&#13;
a  u)  C      LACUn        I-T  o  - fo&#13;
o -4 Q~&#13;
I a)-&#13;
004 r CUv         )    oc (li  ~o   fLA&#13;
0  4J     IN U1  -4 -4  L A1  OLAcof) O-O&#13;
on     la  .1 *Wf    t            °s     \     HO     u&#13;
v)     i0 *    4             C4 34  0 U&#13;
0           -)-  ~ 0  N-4CO  1001  OLA  01     -Q     A&#13;
o4     3W    u              44&#13;
OH  O   - W-&#13;
or  4i  coU  N&#13;
o  0   4.W ||        LO Ln  00)   000          C0     00&#13;
4-4  3  °)-4   . -&#13;
P4     :J0  N4-n LO        LALA   LA Lt  -4     L     A V  I U)&#13;
a)  E&#13;
4- -W  &lt;I0 7                      00           00&#13;
co  0       4&#13;
00 &#13;
4.  U&#13;
~  4.)            'D C-H&#13;
444i      r- e   O co kl  D m   (-N  .N     . c&#13;
04   4  n  o  s el)  °-     In     IT      m &#13;
&gt; ~ ~   ~  ~   N o;  a      o~&#13;
C4UC&#13;
0         04                 ( ~  6 1 14  NN  0401 C  C&#13;
CA a)      00O&#13;
CU4  .0 4  HC) 0     nI&#13;
-4  04      (.4&#13;
0  CU    mH&gt;,m)&#13;
1      0 &#13;
4-     (a           L&#13;
~~-4 '4-,&#13;
a) u    )C &#13;
.14~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
U) i *HW ON        -4&#13;
tO  LA  0)~~~~~~~~~~LnL&#13;
to                      *     LA     a'    LA&#13;
CU-      NtO   N-4    NCCONN NUA&#13;
A           co IV  co~~~~~~~L  CUILA  co &#13;
040  1.4    0            Ln     rn~~~~~~~-  .-'&#13;
Q)            ~~~~~~~~~~~~~0I&#13;
Q)  (a 0)m  (3)O'~  0) 0oll  -  ')O  J()ON  CON)&#13;
CU     Na'~~~- -4 - -a' )4a  a'-0-a     Ua&#13;
a)  a'0C  0a'a'  U)a'O'  a'a'  0a'a' ~~~~~~~~~a'O L&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
__68=&#13;
NOTES FOR TABLE Y3&#13;
1,   The ranges are based on supply, geog.raphical and cultual. factors&#13;
and were assumed constant over time. The survey est:i':Utes indicate&#13;
rural domestic use estimates fron published suzveys.  These demand&#13;
figures represent per capita use f7or tcaditional fue3. Users. As&#13;
a result, there is an inconsist.ency between the dema.d zanges and&#13;
the fuel wood consumption and residue supply :Ugures A.n t'hat these&#13;
figures are per capita potential avai biU.ties based on total&#13;
population not the population of kraditiona' fuel use,.s. The&#13;
number of traditional fuel users is rarely available ancd in most:&#13;
cases does not equal only the rural popula'tion.&#13;
2.   These figures generally zepresent the fuel.wood portion of the&#13;
consumption estimates from survey wor]k present in tho Oomestic&#13;
Demand Range column.&#13;
3.   The figures are based on the differeAce between total zound wood&#13;
production and fuelwood and charcoal production in the FAQ&#13;
Yearbook of Forest Products 19760&#13;
4.   Increments were based on forst types and yields in fi.gure 4-2 and&#13;
Table 4-3 of D. E. Earl, Forest Xnerqy &amp; Economic_Development&#13;
(Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1975) pages 44-460&#13;
5.   These figures are from the Bangladesh Energy Study.&#13;
6.   These figures are tentative f:i.gures f:o.r 1976 fzom the UtNDP&#13;
Peruvian National Energy Balance P3roject.&#13;
7.   These figures are from Ei2abeth Ernst Fuel Consumption Among&#13;
Rural Families in Uppe-r Volta, West Africa.&#13;
8.   The 1990 projections for agricultural. residues includes bagasse&#13;
projected at 2.0 percent per annum for Bangladesh and at&#13;
106 percent per annum for Burma.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-69-&#13;
However, due to the relatively high degree of urbanization in Peru and the&#13;
availability of subsidized kerosene, only about 50-60 percent of the total&#13;
population uses traditional fuels for domestic purposes. Therefore when a&#13;
national average for fuelwood and charcoal is calculated, the per capita use&#13;
becomes about 9.2 gigajoules annually. The disparity between these figures is&#13;
particularly high due to the particular situation in Peru; most Third World&#13;
countries have much lower degrees of urbanization and non-subsidized or&#13;
unavailable commercial fuels for domestic use.&#13;
II. For Upper Volta and Bangladesh the difference between domestic demand&#13;
estimates and non-FAO fuelwood and charcoal use estimates is less a function&#13;
of the fraction of the population which uses traditional fuels and more a&#13;
function of the use of agricultural and livestock residues in addition to wood.&#13;
In Bangladesh significant amounts of       these residues are used, and they&#13;
are the largest energy sources for domestic purposes. In Upper Volta, millet&#13;
straw appears to be the most readily available fuel and fuelwood is used&#13;
only when millet straw is not available. Unfortunately even this gross&#13;
breakdown of traditional fuels consumption is available for only a few&#13;
developing countries; thereby forcing most general work to rely on FAO figures.&#13;
12. The Peruvian information also illustrates the point concerning the&#13;
questionable accuracy of the FAO charcoal and firewood use figures. The FAO&#13;
figure is approximately 'the same as official Peruvian forestry statistics but&#13;
is about one-third of the estimate from the household consumption survey. A&#13;
disparity between FAO figures and other survey results is also apparent in&#13;
the case of Bangladesh where FAO figures are many times higher than the results&#13;
of the special study undertaken for the Bangladesh Energy Study, even taking&#13;
into account industrial use.&#13;
13. An additional example of problems evident in the FAO fuelwood and&#13;
charcoal statistics is a comparison of the results for Burundi and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Rwanda. It is difficult to explain the nearly fouz fold diJfxtErenc-.&#13;
in suchtraditional fuel consumption in light o£ the geographic-'&#13;
proximity and thecultural similarity of these two countries. -x:.on,h&#13;
some of the variations in fuelwood use can be attr:Lbuted to d .:erent&#13;
levels of industrial use, urbanization, and wood availability, e.:.16 'to&#13;
differences in diet and climate, it is sti.l hard to 32Cp; 'ei&#13;
comparisons of some of the FARObased resu2.ts.&#13;
140 Another  point which can be made using ,he Peruvian inforziacLion is&#13;
the one regarding the inadequacy of national averages due to, in this&#13;
case, regional disparities in resource endon^tmenL,W  The potentiFl. sustain-&#13;
able forest yield for Peru is extremeiy high reflecting the facL that&#13;
over half the land area is forested. However due to Peru:s geogradhy and&#13;
climatology, the spatial distribution of wood and population hardly&#13;
coincide. This results in local wood shortaqas, increased foraging&#13;
time requirements, use of animal dung, and to acological dm.age due to&#13;
&amp;eZoieestation.&#13;
15. One final point is that it is wisleading to directly comp;eFr the&#13;
potential agricultural and livesto&amp;z residue avai.bi.ities and the&#13;
levels of domestic demand. This co-aIqarison does *lot tF_kc2 into aconnt&#13;
the magnitude of competing non-fuel uses .or these resources. .'n&#13;
Bangladesh these non-fuel residue requiretments resulL in neari.Y total&#13;
utilization of residues and are significantly larger than the fuel use&#13;
of residues. This situation underlines the need to explore al.' resource&#13;
flows and requirements in a unified systematic rcinner.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-71-&#13;
16. Figure I.1 presents a view of the traditional fuel situation in&#13;
Bangladesh, a country for which there is relatively more information&#13;
on traditional fuels and in which traditional fuels provide about&#13;
70 percent of the overall national energy input. The estimated range&#13;
of utilization indicates that energy use is quite low in Bangladesh. In&#13;
fact, the best information available suggests that utilization is most&#13;
likely at the lower side of the worldwide range -- that is, less&#13;
than three gigajoules per capita annually. Comparison of this&#13;
utilization with supplies illustrates a number of points. First,&#13;
Bangladesh is clearly a situation where it isn't possible to rely on&#13;
firewood for domestic use; other traditonal fuels must be utilized. The&#13;
Bangladesh Energy Study (BES) estimated that firewood provides a small&#13;
percentage of domestic fuel requirements. Curve 1 is an estimate of&#13;
actual firewood consumption and is based on particular survey and study&#13;
information used in the BES.    It also points out the errors that can&#13;
evolve from use of more widely available data. In this case, the fire-&#13;
wood supplies that are implied by curve 1A based on FAO statistics&#13;
suggest that firewood is potentially available to meet most traditional&#13;
fuel requirements in Bangladesh; however, based on detailed study of&#13;
this issue, this is clearly not possible.&#13;
17. Curves 2-4 indicate potential agricultural and livestock residue&#13;
supplies. Utilization requirements are being met by use of these&#13;
residues but the extent is somewhat unclear. Although overall supply&#13;
potential is in excess of utilization, significant residue use can create&#13;
serious problems because these residues have fodder and fertilizer value&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-720&#13;
V&#13;
oU a)  -&#13;
U) *r                1&#13;
+,  +  -4i   : +                 4 -- &#13;
-                        O4 1 4  W -h&#13;
[ .   ' J .   -1   ;   V C   H   ' VP   0   _o   U  )&#13;
04- 'J  *                   )U'C*,\-'-  0&#13;
L  ~~~~~I  CJ0     .~~~~~~~~~~~~CV~~~~0  -4~~~~-&#13;
s_, s, V:  -o  h  V.  tuJ   3  it _  C&#13;
G         Co OOlQ.J                    O&#13;
I                             I&#13;
~~~~~~~-4  ct~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
I          0                 _&#13;
:~~~                                      H &#13;
$.~~~~~~~~~~~~-                    H &#13;
_6.  _  n l~~~~C4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-73-&#13;
and are being utilized. One of the reasons fuel utilization is low may&#13;
be a supply restriction reflecting fodder and other competition for&#13;
the traditional fuel sources. Furthermore, overall per capita potential&#13;
supplies are decreasing; therefore conditions will be getting worse&#13;
especially for the landless poor. There will be less fuel, less&#13;
construction material, less fodder, and less fertilizer (and subsequently&#13;
less production) based on present population and production projections.&#13;
18. Figure I-2 presents similar information for Burma, however, significantly&#13;
different inferences can be drawn. The estimated range of traditional&#13;
fuel use is more uncertain than in Bangladesh since no Burma-specific&#13;
information is available and the range was estimated from information&#13;
elsewhere. The fuelwood and charcoal consumption estimate based on FAO&#13;
statistics (no others available at this writing) suggests that wood may&#13;
be meeting most if not all of the domestic utilization. However, two&#13;
points should be noted regarding the FAO consumption estimates:&#13;
(i) some of this is undoubtedly going to industrial use, but likely a&#13;
small percentage, hence, most utilization is likely domestic and&#13;
(ii) if these estimates understate actual wood and associated branches,&#13;
twigs and leaves use, then firewood may be supplying all of the domestic&#13;
fuel requirements. Overall, potential supplies, curves 2-4, seem to&#13;
allow for any requirements not met by firewood to be easily met from&#13;
residues. In addition, Burma, clearly differs from Bangladesh in that&#13;
overall potential supply is much greater and that the per capita&#13;
availability of agricultural residues are increasing over time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-74--&#13;
U .4i  *u+   U&#13;
.0  "1  .~ :  O r  :En        .  .. &#13;
c.J  ',1 '-.  U +*&#13;
W- Q)  0r  u  x'- la u 1  l  _j&#13;
+C     , En c  +          0      w&#13;
-4 +  We) cC  ) &#13;
r      o L  1-  p H eo                  * H C&#13;
CIj'  *  3   Ue      0  CC a) &#13;
"   a)         r::  -4 W,         r-  -A E   Cr:&#13;
u    m- 0) D C1-  Q) w  &lt;   U     E~&#13;
_ 1      H  0)  00   3          -4      0&#13;
fn ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~~~~L Wa  4&#13;
F "g  &lt;   G  : FU&#13;
IO O                                              q&#13;
/O&#13;
e'J  .-4 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~~~~~(7  -&#13;
CH 0~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-75-&#13;
19. Tables I-4 and 5 show traditional fuel supply and demand estimates&#13;
by country. Due to the lack of domestic demand estimates on a widespread&#13;
basis, these tables focus primarily on the availability and use of wood&#13;
and on the potential availability of agricultural and livestock residues.&#13;
Table 1-4 shows estimates of sustainable forest yield, use of wood for fuel&#13;
and other uses, and availability of livestock, jute and cereal crop residues&#13;
/1&#13;
and bagasse on a per capita basis for 1976/77     and 1990.   Table 1-5 shows&#13;
woodfuel consumption estimates and projections for 1976, 1980, 1985, and&#13;
1990 by country.&#13;
20.        The agricultural residue figures are divided into two parts:&#13;
one for cereal and jute residue, the other for bagasse. These two groups&#13;
were separated because bagasse is rarely, if ever, used as a domestic fuel&#13;
whereas the cereal straw and jute stick are commonly used as such. These&#13;
estimates of agricultural residues are very conservative in that they do not&#13;
reflect the fact that in large segments of the developing world tubers,&#13;
vegetables and fruits are major crops. Cotton was not included in the calculated&#13;
residue availabilities because it rarely forms a major portion of a country's&#13;
agricultural residues. In one major producing country, Sudan, it is legally&#13;
mandated that cotton bushes be burned in the field as a method of pesticide&#13;
control.&#13;
1/ Wood and forestry figures refer to 1976, residue and bagasse estimates&#13;
to 1977.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-76-&#13;
21.  Table E4 permits a comparison o, toL_ ,_zsd uses, bo;h fuel and&#13;
non-fuel related, with an estiinpae      ;s5: '-X   forest wood yields for&#13;
1976 and 1990,   It must be noted agE.-Xl .'L' is comparison on &amp; national&#13;
level does not capture the regional .d eoo7iu ic c:lasc variatiois in&#13;
accessibility to these fuel resources       :hu-etharnore the very appcoximate&#13;
and uncertain basis oF these figures 'ist- be Yxzall:ed, 7-owever bsased on&#13;
this comparison, some qualitative hyoo'9`rv- c:£s be suggested concerning&#13;
the extistence of a firewood crisis   1f T:hi sustzi,able forest yield is&#13;
much larger than the wooce. use such  -   Av   h : Yi;  neroojo.. or Zaire, then&#13;
except for regional distribution i3suco, x     - so e 'n  can  grow at i ts present&#13;
rate or even expand.   Where the sustiYnxbie'j o ,77.d is fa`rly close to&#13;
present or projected wood use, it becomes U7skLZ  in as to whether projected&#13;
use levels are attainable.   In these cas^s  'Lh~z issues concerning&#13;
accessibility and accuracy become 7nsr^ lt'uor; t in determining the actual&#13;
situation. For those countries wheyr p-ere     o  projected use exceeds&#13;
sustainable yields then it seems likzely -:het L,-ere exists a serious and&#13;
widespread firewood proolem0.&#13;
22.       This diagnostic procedur^ -   et ',^  E vary cruce too:l for&#13;
assessing the traditional fucl situat-on.   P msre r2e2labi e and meaningful&#13;
examination of this situation would 'cequ,r- a maucn ~more sxtensive research&#13;
effort.  For countries falling into the lati:tez tw'o groups where the sustainable&#13;
yield is approximately less than twicz.e the wxo6 asz- t:he figures are marked&#13;
by a set of asterisks. The asterisks ind')ra,s^  a range of possible to severe&#13;
fuelwood shortages. In these cases -he projec.-foos n7ist be viewed with&#13;
greater uncertainty.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-77-&#13;
23,       Overallit appears that at least twenty-five percent of all&#13;
developing countries are presently or will be experiencing fuelwood&#13;
availability problems. This estimation is most likely conservative.&#13;
In Nepal)for example, the deforestation problem is clearly severe, but&#13;
the results of this exercise indicate only a possible problem. In&#13;
this instance, the national averages cover up the severity of regional&#13;
deforestation and the geographical inaccessiblity of much of Nepal's&#13;
forests. A similar situation exists for some of the Sahelian countries&#13;
where a low national population density disguises the fuelwood availability&#13;
problems around population centers. In addition, a significant portion&#13;
of fuelwood use is unreported or unrecorded if actual consumption surveys&#13;
are not undertaken. On the other hand, there are cases such as Kenya,&#13;
where the magnitude of the problem seems overestimated.&#13;
24.       The results also indicate the significant role played by population&#13;
growth in affecting resource availability. For a majority of countries&#13;
the forest and woodland areas projections did not significantly change;&#13;
this is more a function of information gathering problems than of actual&#13;
land use trends. As a result the often large decreases in per capita&#13;
sustainable forest yields are due to projected population increases.&#13;
25.       Finally, although the per cgpita use estimates are declining,&#13;
national fuelwood use is increasing though generally at a rate less than&#13;
population growth. However these per capita fuelwood decreases are in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
many cases not large and could reflect numerous trends such as urbanization&#13;
or an industrial shift to commercial fuels as their availability becomes&#13;
more reliable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
rb                         - 79_&#13;
U)    I&#13;
W)  (  I                              0  (3 &#13;
pi  o   i    I  I  I  I      I  I  I               r&#13;
|n   U   k  l  l   v   v   s   v     s      v     v~~~* &#13;
o)         rnJ o                                        NJI  U  nX&#13;
1)    I tT                                         " U  c &#13;
'U W  ~4  R   mI  S D  -  -     Ln  Ln O  0z  LI)&#13;
*4  51  I    CY)   U            0  r) rl U   U -  OD U) L&#13;
U)  Q&#13;
4       rn D0 U)  Is   UD Ur)                               U r O H N K   - N&#13;
Cd      ~~ ~~u -.  I&#13;
U)         0 *   I      C  tO  'J  LI tO  t  0 _1C   C     NI&#13;
U)~ ~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~U&#13;
04&#13;
&gt;1        WH ,~ o  Cu&#13;
*4             0 S rs      sk        vx&gt;*-*B4c &#13;
H         'd&gt; (U        Cl (D|D n N)  O  OI  N  a  N  N_  H  H  H  CO  N  t&#13;
'M ~ ~ C          H   N OO  LI  CO  0)  H  LIH  O     0      ) L&#13;
d         C) cn               H _          H  N            N&#13;
U       O    i                c4J  L 0  O O  c C  oN CO Dl  A r  H   %&#13;
S~~~~~4     r. oN o  !r (3) o) o' o  o  N      k. t  O- ON OOO  OD&#13;
,-1  0    U)Q  0     0               H  H&#13;
U)            4-))r  *0~&#13;
X 'aO °q H      VI****H &#13;
:        3)      I  C:  (J iN  0) N-  v  0)  0 GI  O  O  0  °I  tO  H&#13;
4J        ,             0  0     0                      0 &#13;
a)          I~~~~~~4I&#13;
bh     St _ L l &#13;
0^(ad   I     CO  tO  0) ^  @  (NJ  0n &gt;   t  CN L  G O  Co  N  N  0  H |nJ&#13;
co       r  * -H           N4           H °l  N  tO &lt;   CO NN  (N  CO&#13;
0        zO 4    _      CO N  4  e  J  L  i (NJ 0  0  |  CO  O ( N I  OO   LI | &#13;
UQU)~l4H &#13;
0       I  0  40  I 4&#13;
&gt;q  z   -  -  --  Co)         Dt    or     DI    ob  ° ul- °  or&#13;
Vo       0C0&#13;
Hco  (D      LI|  t G I  CO  Cl  ( j  CO  C l  H G rI I  N)  &gt; 0  r.  O&#13;
&gt; 0    H   C IO )  (  COCO 1 GI  0   H G I 0o G'. I G LO  C  I  O as  Go&#13;
Q-I      04.-4  I {  H 1         o   4  N r  0k  1   o I   o   o&#13;
|)                                              (NJN |  o  I&#13;
H&#13;
,0       L&#13;
' ~ 7 ji 4)  NO tON   0  tO -i m r0 LO OtO OtO   01  tN  0o&#13;
_        II&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
:3 Q 4 _] , 4|- &#13;
l   i                  ) C  fu ~&#13;
1a  o  8  Il u&#13;
(H  0       o     0 &#13;
0n  0       -     - i  U                             I&#13;
O D tlN 40 ,~ u)  j  I  n0  LI) 0 1  l) t N   ) 20 0N&#13;
o   8 in      U        L   O  c ro &#13;
*H  08     U      oo    o:    c   oHH&gt;x,o&#13;
r)  0  !                h4           r0 4  bB    N 0&#13;
Q                          CC  Co  H  H  N  '~'  .-: .CA&#13;
ia  :J O   X     =     ffi   z      x ao         O&#13;
rl  Oj      0.                      00 U0 U. U:l   U)   U?z   C   i&#13;
0   Ic                      r-I C  NL         CJ2l  l&#13;
X  U l     O     U      U     U     O     t) U&#13;
0  ~JJ     m)  Ooi  1-  '  O'  O  CC  Oo  (N  tj  o  H  uLA  LA i&#13;
4J  C  &gt;   N  o~    o'j  o  CC  '  Co  o(  4^N  m  O  LA&#13;
OJ  0  Q) I 0    fo a.-4  .  (N  N  (N  LA  H  (Y  CII&#13;
,&gt;   S \&gt; yO     H 1    H  H        H  ( i&#13;
V   04 ~~&#13;
H  0  4 0      I&#13;
4H                   H   I I  .(     NL             CC&#13;
0    (d  to  c    CV- 0                             O I  0  0  0t0  0  0&#13;
0  (  U)i  0.  04 (   IH       NI  0  ' H  CC14C     A  m&#13;
c4 o  o &lt;'                  (   (  H  H     m&#13;
0  U)~ 4  &#13;
°I                          H  C)  C  0  0  )   1&#13;
cl)  C)           it-   °   ) &#13;
HC U)8       Hl          0o  |   s 1  LA  LA)  CC  ON  (  LO  Hi&#13;
0  9    I  .a-1        4 I&#13;
i  I 0  i  I           1 °; °~ |; Ln u| v   &gt;   I &#13;
0                                  0&#13;
H            jaitDD | r-lO  NP  0  o| N1v  NQ nl'  mJ rt 4fio  o   HJ &#13;
0 0     El~&#13;
00  8l~~~~~~~~~~~~~00O&#13;
:J0U)~  8 &#13;
|~ ~~~~L                                          'n  r,  ; Zv -  i t! *{  O &lt;)1unlu   -l*  n °)  - t|Sl&#13;
8r4I 0 I  i 11    1    1     1      1     1           i&#13;
0" 'r n  H~'I0 -  m in  N a' (  Ctl )&#13;
:     |  9  11  XDor-  ol  MolF  o  to  o  mo  r- oo  0o00  o1 0 0 0 0 0 0   j 0-&#13;
04d  H      '0  (N r-  O  t-   H  oiC t- ON Li  N  t- L A   CC   0)  t-N N  0&#13;
e) o  n N  C)  0 OI  01   in ~ N  C  )  N a )  O N N0   0   C  i n i N   in N  051&#13;
u               11I4  1 1                        1-1      &#13;
Ci                 NN  0 0 1i o N§ 0o  NN  0"  NN  *,1 NN  S4i  N '  N  Col&#13;
0&#13;
m        I   O   "   I   W   I   C   I   4   I   iI   b   . to&#13;
rH   3  Q  ll  a)  |  w   |  r3   |  rG   |  4   |  &lt;   |  &amp;   i~~~~~Oll  ~&#13;
r'I          ~~~~~~~~~~~~~(a 6)  0&#13;
Nj    0        U)  r                 i&#13;
U  ai   (1C)                rd (d&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-81-&#13;
U) r               I      *  I ', r )  * |  NJ  *  rNJ r  n r&#13;
(U  0  Il        I   *      *: .   *      * &#13;
a)  _U  I&#13;
U)  °  I                   U             rn U&#13;
ci &#13;
-   0                              4  rn )   Or&#13;
a &#13;
Cr)  _ -X                   W4     &gt;: &#13;
O)  O~ I     N       v 0  CO  Xf  H  O 0XLA     (&#13;
L)  0  I     L             *r&#13;
;   U)  I    U)     U)            UU&#13;
O  ~-4  I                                        o S&#13;
W    I             Us    U)      U) rN  rNUrr)nrN &#13;
0     It      -                    S 1  Ln  co       s&#13;
n ~ ~~~4 rnl _l ,o i           0  a   I&#13;
U) O)  a ,                 U &#13;
o)  4r  I     ' 0  r-   ,   -n   L  N  LA  r  r  rN  0&#13;
&gt;    _1&#13;
In           a _.    NJ  00  L' O U CO rn  (NJ  H  H rO&#13;
o  3  o   I    N 0' H   nN      Hn rn   LA ,  r-&#13;
0:        Sk  1   k0 r-  O  xD t t  O  v9 r-  o  v9 r-  o co'L.  r-  O 91 &#13;
4i  (L)  (0           ')  H &#13;
U)  rZ44  -&#13;
0r                                                 I&#13;
0)             ('     a   O  LA  C  '       )  O1'    '&#13;
la  Q  I                               Ik&#13;
-  4   4  I     rI  %&#13;
o         )    .- 4n        r  n  OD .I a  W         &gt;     N&#13;
r-) -'U   0 tn  I         N~  CO  LA        H         H&#13;
:J  0  U) rz  1 0 &#13;
U)X4  '-o0   U&#13;
o             0~&#13;
U)               H   H&#13;
.14           0     M  M  M~0  L   O")   H,  H  LA  (UM'M 0) M0 a  CAON  M&#13;
U              *H~~~~~11-   -&#13;
H        I            '0    0   0  0 &#13;
VQ)  -  I~~~~      Z                     ) -&#13;
~  *-44~ 0 g  )0 N   A  C      0  0   a  a' 1 r     C'&#13;
HH~~~ )   Iqa               f       1c&#13;
U)(U4JU)  9  0)~E  -lO  En  CO  L  H  N  0  ~  N  LA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CD      co  i L n  UN&#13;
~~~~iH~~~~~~~&#13;
I__  ~ ~~1.~, &#13;
05     -V  m  0  ~   ~~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ M  0--0  '-  0-&#13;
0)     l;Q  0~~j  crl) ,  0  .1  n en :  0  n  in  C&#13;
C)         c'   ()  N Cl  o'            \ , H (&#13;
o)  C)  INI                    &#13;
in            ,.I-0*&#13;
Cj  El  I)U               I 1e   -  T&#13;
0      kJo  0  L~~~~n  en %  en  U 14  V&#13;
U)  U,           I             4 &#13;
C)    r-  Lo  m  n ( m   N-C%  en  n H!w e&#13;
&gt;C            II &lt;&#13;
&gt;4     v ~ ~ ~ in  r-  CC  I)    0 inen)&#13;
-44J   I'.&#13;
~~,  (N  H   0LO (N  ICN e o   n N&#13;
0             Cl)  m  Ln (0        CI&#13;
0    ml  HN  C)  ;  (  -.o  en  0   nm&#13;
00  I&#13;
0 ~ ~ ~  &#13;
-  (N  0            en  en~~~~~~N  r&#13;
0 ~0&#13;
4i 0~I            &#13;
o H   I~     -0:          .-I-&#13;
3                  I~~~~~~0(&#13;
~~~~~X4 U ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~)U&#13;
001; ~ ~ CN .;  R  f   .  I0 O  n ;, c  n r&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
|   - _ 1 |  i   O   fj   |    -83-&#13;
a)  4i  I &#13;
tJ    O        0l  . d  I  I  ND  fNI | l f ()  '   I  I  in  C&#13;
Cd  0  I     0 &#13;
ED  _J  I                                      fJ &#13;
l t ~~~~~~~O                 U     N I_f  C Nf4fZt -tO &#13;
fQa  t                          G   &lt;) 0  3   I  f) L &#13;
Ca   1                      cow  N(N 1 H  1  fO  f   -  I&#13;
_i  i&#13;
0d  4 0  I&#13;
U)  I  IXX&#13;
u)~ ~ ~~~C  (N  r-  r- m II fC')     I'  r-  11  0)  1- &#13;
4L)  -  I&#13;
H  f         0   C fN 0         fN rl          1 fN ,'  N fN fO  a' H &#13;
a)  E                                                     _&#13;
a)  .a  I  0 &#13;
U      t     fd   f'I&#13;
N~~~~~~~~~~~~~J        rq4  &gt;  4     P4     04     P4     4 4&#13;
l  I      -      =    fN             E  f&#13;
U)  0 °  °           - C          -      - I&#13;
a)  U)  I    COUUUUco                                 CO&#13;
0  43  I     N                    C H  N  a f  (N  N  N  rN   (N  N  LO&#13;
O~~~~~L :Jc  _ o &#13;
*n4~ &lt;              Cl l. &lt;                  ' ~   i   l~ O  H  a&#13;
U)  0  Cd        . fd      *                   l&#13;
&lt; ~a       0  a)    Cl O(N N  CO  (Nl  H  HN  (  H  .I  .l  CL  (N  in &#13;
14~~C                    Cl               w   nl, t   &lt;   O f  H  H f   f   f   f &#13;
fN     NL                                                 '&#13;
-    Cd id *              t   *        ,O f &#13;
4~4 &#13;
O4 4&#13;
U     a)3   -1   Cd l   N f   _ &lt; [   N  fl f             S   N&#13;
1-4  Ha)  H  N.  0&#13;
Oft  f4  &#13;
41             N -  r i co  fD)  OC  a)  r- fN  00  ( N o|fN &gt; v a  f   D&#13;
0   4-  C)C~                 r~C;          4 i  *..  U      0&#13;
En D 4         'In  N  CO  Cl  C  a '  H  in  H  fN CO   Cl  ,  0  H&#13;
d4J        (N5  ,  N  ,N  i  a   i  cO  CO  CO  '4  H  H  L4l  i&#13;
(dU)  - 4          o 4    o  *  o   *  o   .  O&#13;
:3~ ~ ~~~: tD    I  r-  &gt;                        co&gt;1  8 zr  c  l  n tl  c  1  n [-1  -&#13;
,f  fN    I   0  N  () f N f                       lIn  fn CCl  N  (N  (&#13;
0           H      H   H               H   H         HC)0 &#13;
0 0&#13;
C      Ha)      I                                c  0&#13;
,~~:  -,0   (N  Cl  (N  a'  H-  (N  ON  N' * * i  n  C  .&#13;
19 ~'            i     '. gI  fd  (N  H4  H , a' N d  rd  '.    . O i&#13;
rl  J4         -4 -,4  C4  4- Q- ,4                     --I&#13;
w      I&#13;
0     1  5  1 I      -,            EP&#13;
FQ ~H~U                (N  H  Cl     ( 0 9' z      Cd  Cd  HD  H  '&#13;
_                        C4 C)i&#13;
I'.0  ~'  H-  co  Na Q  N  (  0(E   N 1O  a'  COI  CO&#13;
Q   H  "  *,     k                              -i  n  0  uz  &#13;
a)                '.CjN  0  '.olr-  0  '.~N  0  ~N  0  t)&#13;
0&#13;
4.)    4.3                 *'4U&#13;
~~~4  .14 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ .       .4    a&#13;
0  ~ ~ ~ 4  ~ ~ 4   00      C&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
r)  4  ,)                   -84-&#13;
C                I                I  LA  *      (N&#13;
U.    I      II      *     0 r    I   I  *          *&#13;
ril  I                                 C))&#13;
Cl7)  1)  I                u      u &#13;
hD  O         N  (   v  U 3l   U1 n      D   1&#13;
U  I&#13;
H0  0  Og                     U)         U&#13;
U)  h)       U I,      0   v  .   '  co&#13;
4-.I)  I       C N  Cl  0  Ul  Cl  N  0  N-  LI)  (N  CN&#13;
Cl)  o  I        *      *          )C&#13;
I4       (N  (N   J   A L   A   l C   f  &#13;
Cl)  0  1&#13;
U &#13;
:3  44                                   PCO&#13;
la  2                   &lt;  S4a        s &#13;
&gt;    I &#13;
§~~~~L    -1                                   Cl A  &amp;z .t&#13;
*&gt;  O *4  I    -      S      S     * &#13;
aU)               Cl     U)  5    N_  1ZO &#13;
.1 f  0  Oi   -          .  S      S      S&#13;
H  &lt; &lt; r   l ~~I 09&gt;mOSN           t   S  OSH        H &#13;
I                         U~~~U &#13;
4J °         N-  0o  Cl) HO  LA  a,  a O O  .0  aO  a . D&#13;
U)N   (      H  LA  '.  N  C      UL  a,  N  (N   LA  LA&#13;
0  )  0  C)                       *         _&#13;
&gt;I*H  h 1  ;1  I  O'H  a,  0  CD  Cl  (N  LA '0 V&#13;
.H            1° N C            H (N  H&#13;
4.) &#13;
04 '-&#13;
HO   H      U'N&#13;
U'            &gt;" :                                    11&#13;
-,4 4J            '.D                             Cl ) N H  LA)  N&#13;
rdU]    |    ~      a  0   N  Cl 0           ||    X A0&#13;
O      4-i  0z C .N&#13;
U)~  ~  4         C&lt;a    a, O  0  (N  H  a  N~  H  Cl  0 (  LA&#13;
::  L                  v l H *)         Cd  Cd    C N  a,&#13;
U)~ 4                 (N                  LA  Cl)  0  Cd  ON&#13;
o)  14.4                                     Cl  N&#13;
o  Cl~~~~~~~~~~r                                   C,0 -1 ri m C  r  r  '&#13;
Cl)  HC)~~1     0 iU)iU           N  I  k   0  L)  -      N  %&#13;
c.w     I   H~                                  'H&#13;
CZ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
0  th -4  I~H            Cl (N  N  '.  d' ~   LA a&#13;
00I- ~  g I      0    H      C LA .0 r  0)  0D  0o  0l  0&#13;
0   (Z  4)                C  LACl)                ClI&#13;
HH 0  L)  g    0  '.  L  (N  '.  a~  LA  '.0  a,  C     0&#13;
E0 n               Cd' 0         C&#13;
S"     -4 N  H-  O0 -  . On  (N  C'LA  C  .C  (NC1 0lr 0n&#13;
-i    uc H(N,~ H9  '.00- H,-  LAIn N '  NCl Cl  HC l~  0; LI  .&#13;
0  4i-  H-               - &#13;
Cl)              '.0N ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0 '. 0N 0) CD 0l CDN~ 0 CON ol  CDN0 0)&#13;
4~~~~~~~~~~C~ ~ ~ ~&#13;
C.)~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
H        &gt;1~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
0      TI     co~ ~~~~~     C&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Ij~~~~~~ ~-85-&#13;
02 - &#13;
'.0  w~~~~~~~~~~~co 0 0&#13;
0)  1)  I                    C&#13;
~4  $4  I                4&#13;
*H   0 &#13;
a)&#13;
1- 4  I                '&#13;
C)  U)  I&#13;
-     It&#13;
Gd)  0) 4&#13;
(n  0    I       -       - &#13;
0)  U)  I)&#13;
&gt;)      &gt;0           02   N   (&#13;
4-0)&#13;
4.)-     z&#13;
.1.   -4     0&#13;
U)    .~~~~~~.d&gt;  $4  1 0&#13;
0    ru~~~~~~~~(&#13;
4-IC   00~4 &#13;
0        0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~o 0&#13;
HO)        H~~~~~~~~~~0  02  02&#13;
0                      C~  0    .0  I&#13;
0  ri  -I I     0.           cJ&#13;
v0 ) 'o-  I02                  2&#13;
OCOHO  ~~~~~I ,-         c    3&#13;
-4r~             '.  N   02)  dl&#13;
d   H4-i  I)     '0   0    m  &#13;
$4V'0    I&#13;
I1                m  IID&#13;
:30   0                   '~ &#13;
~~~14~~~&#13;
"fl  0) '.D   0&#13;
4-)             ~~~~~~~~&gt;4&#13;
0&#13;
4-4              ~~~~~~~~&gt;1&#13;
4.)4&#13;
0~~~~~~&#13;
04-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-86-&#13;
t,~~~~~i &#13;
'X             J        _gi_   I&#13;
I  vo  W  1, f   O   t   m   |  u   u   l  mI  I&#13;
| )    I _   II*            nr&gt;U &#13;
|   68  0  I  j             U) Ui L   ) L   o t  r   n n L  n&#13;
H.  0  i  Nkx&gt; &#13;
a~  ~~ v-~ i I ~  cl u ~   u          N  r&#13;
|  V  o ~ ~ ~ c~ O  7 sS  7n     O _ G   X G  LA  LO  oA  o&#13;
LA  Ii~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~p&#13;
sU         / C)            ON  C, al)&#13;
U) 0                               U&#13;
C)  U  I      Or&#13;
6~~~~~~~C J °N                co  00  00 hn Ln e O O O  nn v &#13;
Ho~~~- a                         _ _-4S&#13;
r-' a  N fI  (  aO  t N IC)   0 O  tN4  LA  ' 0  d&#13;
C) 0  e)  ('  4N H H ,4 H U   A ~ ~ L   ' 0 C&#13;
I~ ~r N. iiH &#13;
H EI4          0"  0  0 t  N    0" (N            -4 G|  U  0'&gt; dLi&#13;
Z  n))     LAON   0  O  r0LO  N  U)  N  CO l  |  °t  °o&#13;
4)1 0     fA  I C)  I  °      I 0&#13;
'jj1   LA  n  0  0  0  k        I&#13;
H  Ho                           LA (   H H4 &#13;
r~~~~~~~~~~~o  Imco         cI  nr&#13;
00    '~~~~~~  0  0 ~~~~~ 0  0)  0  0  0 0 0 0 0 &#13;
La &#13;
00 ~5dN       N C)C) 0  O  0  N  N  A C0&#13;
i  *d4  J  I&#13;
HHNU)o    CO  N  0  0    0  '0  ti  0  0  (n H  (&#13;
I           ,  &#13;
_                4     '0&#13;
'.0o  o1,1  r- I C-) u  0  NO  C',  (N LrA  H  Ln CO &#13;
(N C)  ;3  .0T'i r  col  r 0  rX  H  nCI  O  Lr)C  cN  &gt;co  co  rON  N&#13;
ol .11  -4 LO   LA4  COO' 'm  O '  NN L-JA N ) &#13;
0  0D 0,  (NC&#13;
HH(N o', IC'N) LA 0  HH  (N  H j   ) () (   ) m (10  1&#13;
0  LON  C)  AN  0  U)N~~-  0  U)Nr  0  '0N  0  WI  0&#13;
0&#13;
.44)  H      (el   0)En&#13;
0                  0)&#13;
E-4            9          I-.I ~ Q . j)   E-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-87-&#13;
:: o   i   I   -' ('  !C   c~   I  I  I  I  I &#13;
Id  0            *   I ,&#13;
_ , I      Ii         c&#13;
GI  3  I&#13;
Q)  U &#13;
ta ~ ~ ~ ~ c       N  co  Ol U: ;4  m&#13;
3  uI  13&#13;
4  0  I&#13;
u &#13;
~  4.  IULl 0i''0   ~ N C           c &#13;
t   I&#13;
a)  C.  I  u    :         - ,    U&#13;
*,  2  I  2        c U  U   m      c    a&#13;
-4  =1C r50        m 0 I         -    -- ' &#13;
KO  0o          (1)       U      hU&#13;
W  ul  I                             (ci C X ,d O &#13;
E-4~- &#13;
Eq ~ ~   -,   I                -  -   - &#13;
o °d 4O.,)  O  1  4J&#13;
4.)  'i  °  0  '                      '&#13;
H-q  4n         0  O 0  '  -  0  0  N  2  0&#13;
t2) ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ c NJ Ot  '.  Lf  H  Hi Hl  it -   O O O O O )  tN&#13;
V  ; 4  r -d  | i&#13;
rK ~ ~ U r ~   U'  CN  Lf c   d *n N I) )  IV  0N  r-   0  r -A  t-&#13;
,&lt;~~~a R~ 3                                 C|t C C 2 rdO &#13;
'0&#13;
WH«   *-a   Ct | .&#13;
a)  &lt;.) r-d  0&#13;
r3°  0d SJ  Ul) In     0 .i .   HD    CN _  t.0 N*&#13;
E-4D  O  4: -J  :       O O O  O OC       -&#13;
Wl  0   C &#13;
PI,  00H                    C~ .  0&#13;
4-            a)     O '0 N '0  ~ 0 '' L  c &#13;
I  o  3 !   I   r-d r-d  N  it)  |. HJ  )   cd! d r-   N   0 q   - 0  H (N(&#13;
a- I O)  0  I&#13;
DZD (aciI        H    H-  0  0  0 H  0  0 |  N&#13;
-4 4-) 1       w ST N  H 1 Ci   c N&#13;
-A~ - a  040&#13;
U         |- V. |4   0     S&#13;
EQ~~     ~~ ~~ H   H1             CO 4   4 |&#13;
CO             .4-  )  ciU-&#13;
-        4~~1   ci   *~  ci  It  N-  i) ia )  N 0  0 cq 0  *z  r  LN  Cc&#13;
:% 0    -0 CO4  '00  Cc  n O   H O  CO0  CO~ Nr~  '.0 1&#13;
ID4 -H   - i    '  ' H 0 N  N*     * Cc N&#13;
WCO4-)W I    c0     0 0 0  0 0ci    c H  H&#13;
iI~~  rci~~  H  Hu~.  H  olo  r 0  c   o r- ':' o   wlr  N&#13;
ci       NN 4it)  HO  ) - LAIcW   r N  0   0) N-  00  N - L'0)&#13;
i         (1Hci  *   -*  -I&#13;
4-3044   HCcCi'H            H&#13;
0~~~~0-&#13;
Ia4~~~~~~&#13;
C.)  -  ~~~~.J                       4-l  O   0. I O. N   'fN 0 0  &#13;
~4C         &gt;111 &#13;
0 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~0r&#13;
.4 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~4P&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Cla)  H  I             j &#13;
d   0  I&#13;
,l  z4  &amp;#21;lI &#13;
to I&#13;
I)  w   I     o0*&#13;
5~~~: U      I          s,     , &#13;
WN3~  ' 1@  ,               l )&#13;
_ 0           O&#13;
U)  U)&#13;
4             OD U      Lf OU SS&#13;
414          0       0'  0  l&#13;
Qr)&#13;
O ,  Atx &#13;
&gt; 1 -  tD|&#13;
'0   NiV &#13;
F-q   U)    I&#13;
L4    oo4 p  _&#13;
40  C        10 C)&#13;
-I       I ) &#13;
H               4J              4 .QH  1I&#13;
m~~~~     C     U      OU (U   D  I|D 0   (U&#13;
H           I 1  "I&#13;
0CU)I&#13;
00i 4   Ii "&#13;
'U En  -.  I&#13;
w  -H1J  I&#13;
~~o~~~0  I~0 &#13;
(U ~~~~~r D       mzirl on  o&#13;
~0 0i&#13;
04.&#13;
a4~~~~~$&#13;
0)                I~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~O lC l '  -I&#13;
IDN     0  ON   0  1O r- 0&#13;
1~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~',&#13;
a)            0~~~~~$                a)~e&#13;
Ui4&#13;
H~~~~~~~;                    - 1    )f&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-89-&#13;
tn   I                                          - * i  I ,  .  I  I  I .N  .1  co  .&#13;
I.U  D       H   (9   I  I  H  U     I  I  I   I  -4  (1  CO  C&#13;
m~~~~~ -                 *     II I I&#13;
I t                                                    H o&#13;
C)  O    ~~~~ ~~LO)  L')  L1n D t  Ln  1-  1_  OD  1  1-  WD  Lo  W&#13;
ru   i&#13;
:5 I.  I                                 -&#13;
'0 l L                              u       P     4     u) 1o :&#13;
En-  0  I&#13;
U)  U)  I&#13;
4      4 S         (N   L 0  Ct n   'N  L(N  LO  LA  Ln  H  CI  H&#13;
C)  )  XI    N)  _  CO  tH  OD      c CO   N C D O H   00  0  Ln&#13;
&gt;     I      L  L  LA  CO  C  L     N  N       N    C O  L  C&#13;
.r  __4&#13;
- IA&#13;
U ~  :   0                O                                 U )0&#13;
H    w'    W  I&#13;
U~~~             U     U                      U             U , &#13;
.1 4J 00            O-  0 tD  ml rSl  rd  ds  rd  r4  R  rI  - &#13;
f ~U)  I0  I d V  - -   I            mr               0  -I 1-&#13;
)i O)   _&#13;
U)n   :5      C   H  H  CO  CO  cd'  al   0  ( Aq  .1  CO  t  L^,&#13;
.)      a     C   q Cl  CN  N                   'A Ld  L  LA |O  L  C  C  0&#13;
0 _     .r  °  °   °  °  °   °  '      °°           °  °   °&#13;
-4 C)~~~~C&#13;
&lt;7B q   1                     OD  L   a               r  OD  rl  &#13;
t~~~~~~~f    a     n  r     Wm        L)  (d   I    1  I &#13;
'0~~~&#13;
rr )H.  -.  Cd          ~    C     0C               ~&#13;
a a   1 1; !L}  v  a         o                          q  r&#13;
O H )  H                                               I&#13;
_, 4J  II 3      nr        qNr&#13;
Cd&gt;4 Cd~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
CdU)  -    Cd  A  N -  LH  LClr-'   C o   Ln r-  CO  H|m  H 'D NI,  CO  ID  Hr&#13;
115 4          L  co ) f Jl0 )  |  r-  W   O9   C  04 |  |o  | ri *  |  rC&#13;
Q *  O   0    |~ 14Cd  r '  |            CH  N  | H  r | L  |   q | 0  0) H&#13;
0   4J  _        rQ'  0  CO  ND (N  HQ   r.  LA  H  |  H|&#13;
ra        kDIz ol tDIz o kDIz o   tDIt- o s11~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~o o - ol ksor ol DI- o&#13;
J          I  S  |I~~~~~~~$  r-Ir-  a5  r, r a  WN vrI- v  r  &gt;  -r VlrI &#13;
Cl~~~~~            H  H  Cl (N            4         H He           i&#13;
HO)     UIU        |  z     Q)        &lt;      J   l &#13;
H            H                      H1  IC  I~~~&gt;1  c&#13;
Cl)           d  N   O  CO H   C   LA   d' 4N            CO N   L&#13;
CO  Cd'  LA  N   LA  CO  CO  C   Cd' C  0  0&#13;
'00)  -~~~ I2a                      p0&#13;
OCOHO  I                             IC           IC  IC 44  C&#13;
0~~rd'H~~ I        O      d CO         H            0   4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-90-&#13;
zl*                          r'U (U (N  ( Ua&#13;
-   II2  &#13;
Zco                         m               Ln &#13;
C)  .&#13;
(Q)&#13;
,&gt;~~~~~~~L   m  r- m         IV Ln CN I       C ) &#13;
r4  0&#13;
U)  U)  I&#13;
&gt;- 7 ! sq sH     s       N   O            U  (N t&#13;
&lt;  o°  !&lt; t t |C 4 O  t ese &#13;
(U    -tolrI      in  (N  O           Cl  IO(N     (&#13;
I)   (U  'q|$                      1  2|I ||  t 0i|r  c n|r -,&#13;
|  h  o  a -o  I~ 11  Nl ,| t tli |l °f  in cA o   n &#13;
C)  0  I                                 .&#13;
- W C   4       Ln 0) C) Io I      CN             I&#13;
C I      -&#13;
0            |&#13;
41~ ~     Q  11        {3   l3rd      l|          r&#13;
_ )                cn cI        | Un    l   H&#13;
C-)&#13;
a4  GI o  4.)  cI,4C;                       1   ~  C  1 &#13;
U ) rX4   Cd'  (N C   C   A   -: 0   Y  H &#13;
C) 0 C)l            'I &#13;
*'-I  (U                  CD&#13;
0) &#13;
HC   H                         - &#13;
H   H4        C)t'      0   O  U  l  A   '  0     H&#13;
C:::  .4JC)~-  40  I  *  0                         4 &#13;
1-1  -i  ~4 En  I  0  H  .i        CO  0   CO-  '.o&#13;
HC) pi  'i'VH&#13;
C)  U)                                      0C C&#13;
( ,J  0  d *1-(            -&#13;
0   O r         N  l:  I             ~          L &#13;
Jt04  0  C)               C) CCD)5) CL  ,oPIrl&#13;
*~~~~~~~C)   -LO C   0L       L1 C&#13;
HH0 )            O   IV  00   C  .oC  Nq  r4  H  Ln&#13;
( r4 '-I   Im0                  0   r)c         l&#13;
0   4 U)l    (N   H  Cl 'A  -     (   '  C'O I&#13;
0)  ON  C,  c  m  C~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ C")  ON  o') U%  m  Cl  ON  O,,~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~'~l  ~ COA  l  A&#13;
0' i       In               f Clj&#13;
:3  ..14            AHH    iHH&#13;
(U~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~U&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
_~   C |  l|  t   *  G            N1 *|'    * .| rN .j  H  U)  0 &#13;
rri  O  l  |   u   rU (N     I  rN  r C  r&#13;
W    l                 3)  U)      U      U&#13;
Ca  C)  I   I  v                      I U' ) &#13;
7s 0 4  I1          -     -&#13;
'C  E  I'    k                  tvs&gt;* &#13;
*d  0  I&#13;
)  U)                                                I&#13;
n   -E  I&#13;
a)  I~C~                                         r&#13;
°~~      ~         H  Hd W     t'l                 ~&#13;
a)  0                       O&#13;
-u  I&#13;
~~~~ u~~~~&#13;
U)  0  I&#13;
a)  U)  I&#13;
4)  (r*('                U)  ()  (N      co U  0m  H IT  (N&#13;
H)  0l             C~ 0  rr  r(  rn  O  U)  U)  9)  (n  ND  rn  r  rN&#13;
a) 0  a)'&#13;
&gt; r1CLf               r            HN           m !   r'&#13;
4.)&#13;
'0 $4 t l04&#13;
u     fo Ua) '-4  -  (d                      'T 00  m  I  r &#13;
Ha)  H C)~~~~~~~~~~~~~C  ~   ~    C&#13;
C)     U~ ~4       - UH _' &#13;
H ~~~ .,H.   ,&gt; 1a  *    {|N  N  (N |  tn V  NO c'1   s H N  lO U)  U)  H l h&#13;
I)     - :.  N O0 (       0  0*1  U 0   09  U)  0 rn  N  n&#13;
0 0               H      Hrn       H H   H &#13;
I               1- &#13;
Ha)D  _  I- OO                           0              a)&#13;
C        0.o       0  (N  U)  o    N '   ON  U)  0&#13;
_            1  0}  11  0 5  , r ,&lt;  W 0I c N   W  W IO Cy o   n   " . O  e  r s'  )  rs  U)  (N I r Jl&#13;
D-4             55     .'C 0  55 1    4 1 1     -  514&#13;
0  0 a              0      I  U      '  H  tN      O a. (&#13;
)   4j                  0 11  U  U   V  t  t  U)&#13;
t  D  -  1     4           o 0 10           | H  H&#13;
1-   ri'   I&#13;
nJW  I O) N1           (N   U) rl   0  US  H  OH  N 1U  Ur&#13;
!1 0D tn  .:  I              2    r0      D 1 5&#13;
'40 0  0 &#13;
'0    _ _ _ _ _~~ (a&#13;
4.)~~~~~~~~~7&#13;
:5 0  0    .10  -      0~                  a)C ~ C~1  ~ 14 1  41&#13;
co -4     C      r,      C &#13;
H                    *H~~~        *H    *d           04 C4 .,&#13;
4.)  H~~) m   -, 0  H)  U n m )  I*        m 040&#13;
0    ~~~04-E            H&#13;
C)                     Ca    raw~~~.1  ()  :&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-92-&#13;
a  0   0    X&#13;
la  ::  . &#13;
-   id I      I&#13;
&gt;  3 U           N&#13;
0:: 4  J  C  ' :4O4  Ol  O&#13;
Z ~~~~U          kD  LO  0' O  |&#13;
-14  0&#13;
(5   q)s   t  11  4&#13;
-H °&gt; 4j  jn          CN0 &#13;
U)   U)&#13;
U)   -       e 0&#13;
aH      Ij       i    o&#13;
H     'I :DI      H   o o&#13;
&lt;1  I    I&#13;
0     u1'&#13;
-'-  0  I    0&#13;
0U)  0I&#13;
C Z)  U)3 -&#13;
o   -i _           C  IfI&#13;
Q  4-J  0) &#13;
l  U)  Ei  ID  L'  '  ~&#13;
U)4( :  0       0&#13;
-4&#13;
V     0&#13;
14'-   4 N&#13;
H            ,  u4  LI'  C 'J  t~ &#13;
0    4J&#13;
HO)~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
C:~ ~ ~ ~ 'DI&#13;
0~~~~&#13;
UN~~~~~(&#13;
~~          0  0  0 40&#13;
0  U)H  U ~ I.&#13;
00U)~~     ~ 0000&#13;
$4'd'd  I~~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
|   Ul   I   t            i   n .,             m   co&#13;
. ) rs  3   |   as I      O   n m    nS~ rt N OL  I  LN  O 1  I&#13;
m  _           m            N l3           l CO(N &#13;
cn _n                                   CN (      N r&#13;
o  o    I                 U)     U)         U         m)&#13;
C)   i                   -             - &#13;
a) 3  l I    u      U&#13;
*H 0 &#13;
U)  U  I       )  L) L)c                         i~&#13;
a) _- II&#13;
H  --  I     Co  to  N  in  in  to  w  '  (N  i  H  CO  H  (N&#13;
AS  4W  I  |i       in  in LC  t  H  m  H  H   CO  .-I  C~3  0&#13;
C)  C~~~~~~~~~~~~~  I                 .4r,)4 C4 C &#13;
Ua)  0 1&#13;
in      I&#13;
O -O  l I  P     1h     4PU)                U)     A4&#13;
-a  C  O I    *     -             -                    - &#13;
.^  3C  I                  U)=zu &#13;
'0  1-  I  I  u                          -n=U         f&#13;
X   5  I     U   )                U                   U)&#13;
&gt;)  0  I     co     *                    - r-  O&#13;
e)  0)  l)   U 1 -     t &#13;
&gt;I                      *&#13;
&lt; ~ ~~~~~~ U)                                          U ° @ L &#13;
O )       r&#13;
2 ~ ~~-  (  1- ma  t  | ~ °~ r°m (N   in) Nt  ,o  H  m  to o   S&#13;
H ~   U O ) og        N  (N O  O   )   O  tO  0  Oi  O  O  CO  in  n  m&#13;
'0&#13;
CO    Ha)  H  C&#13;
CO   O~  1- _  N&#13;
O.-44J  1)     N  in  O  .;r  to  N  N  in  co  H  (N ,  I)  CD&#13;
U  U) -,   co  t.o  N  (N  0 ,N  0-  N  H    in  H  in  H  in&#13;
.4iae)  Q 0 &#13;
La  ( 4 4  J   0  0   1  H      01  m  N _~  in NF  H   - ,&#13;
;j  0    3  (N4  (N CN co    N  0)  in        H  H'IT&#13;
Ott  .) E -o  0   00  in       (N  Hi                      (N  H-&#13;
&gt;4      0   O   4 &#13;
0)      H _&#13;
a  I        f I&#13;
I  r  9 0  °  tN-i      '  H  COD ° 1r  t°1   m  * o   to&#13;
o       !o  g  0  N  CO  0  (N  I  0    H         0   d  (N  CO&#13;
H     00         0 0 0     tO  C      0 0  N  i    0    0  .&#13;
ia   I&#13;
o  U)H  C) &#13;
. *4-        in  m  mn  in)  ml  0'n    mn  ml  H4  kto  m&#13;
IH1-4U)  (N  H  H4 -1  O     CO  CO 4  O. nS  CO  0  to&#13;
::s     U 4    'i  I               --I&#13;
0  i t                             H  &#13;
CO(CN  H-  ICn  0  0lC r  - N  HN q (N o r0  H T oD  H-  NO  (N&#13;
oO~ 0~  1To  HO      C! O  ~O  ~  COO  (N 1  O'( &#13;
0 .0  C           r- N Ole)  CT  (N  (N "  (N  )ONO  V  O  &#13;
O1-4-4  H'           HI   H  N N  Cl'-&#13;
'0                            I                a to&gt;           tON~0 .&#13;
C)  - ______  --  ~~~~~~~~~ON  C  toiN  o  toNe  ~~~lr- o  , NN r-  oo  &#13;
4)~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
0&#13;
H        14~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
C)                      '~~~~~~~~~~0&#13;
0                0                          co&#13;
U                    --I8 &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-94.-&#13;
C  I           *  W Y           L      LAn    L      n&#13;
.9n  o:       r-     co ,°                               r&#13;
1                           ur&#13;
_C)    ILA                                        U      L&#13;
lIt4&#13;
HO  O          LA  LA  LA:  n   A C    in   A  t in nA rt &#13;
nd  o  I      v          LA  0)  CI.)     in N&#13;
0)  ,  I       *            U&#13;
4J Gi  S     I  |   n  i- _n  n  r  co  L  UN  O  co  rq  j O  co&#13;
r0)  0  I  ']  -   t   t   in°  Ln  i  9  0  -  co  o  &#13;
a  4        Pt &#13;
sS~~~~~~1 ° 3 uc  u 1&#13;
i~~~~~~-1     Sn       .S   O',  -     co            co  #   # 1c&#13;
,a  -^  I             LA| co  ON r   LA  A  L An  rLO  t - 0.&#13;
,a~~~~~0  a) °  I  r- #                                  -;#&#13;
C.) (a_)4i#&#13;
U                                             U) Uu&#13;
U,  0              .~~~~~~m  1  0 c  C..co  -  -  -   - &#13;
O  )  U)               U O  r&#13;
U   iqStn  tU nL)°|r                 OS     n;            mc&#13;
;I .  C -'      L0 co             co  (0    Cd  LA  0   - iA&#13;
&lt;  ~  U2 CL4   Cd    L      C'  0   LA NcLA       0  i   (      a   --I&#13;
!~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~1 ' iJ            LI  I   W  01 In.&#13;
0)  0  a)'                                 0 CO  t0 ' C  in I OA   O  | Ln  r | Cn O)&#13;
|  0                C  L   L   N   in  iO  LA    H     cn (0  |N Si'  t&#13;
IP 0  f   II    &#13;
UC "h t                                            H              H  H-1lGolHsl&#13;
H             I        0   0 in              0  0    I     0 I  -  3z&#13;
H ij4-)(       C'  L~     in C  LA  (  LA   Cd;  H~  (0 N &#13;
0  ri     00 z                           (NI            N &#13;
U ~~~!rol&#13;
:5  0  0     0  * &#13;
0   4(0         i   (     0   0  L   H  i   C   0 &#13;
L o r-   o! r-   o   )r   LA   %' H  (0 0    H&#13;
I  *'-~~~~~~~~~~~~~  0  .  *      0~~~~~~~~~~~I'Dr  0  0i, :&#13;
40,:     I~~~~~~&#13;
Ca~~~~~~~~~~~~~~dC&#13;
LA  LA L   A          A   f  23              ' i&#13;
04 -H0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-95-&#13;
tO  o         iii  Cd  in  LA  Cl  LA   0   i .n nA   LA  C  d&#13;
r ~ 0  I           .         .&#13;
5p   I      N ii   N  N1     N  N      LA ur     N   Cl  in  $.1 :&#13;
LA,  5-  i,j;I                                    1~  r4&#13;
: - ~   II--0                                    AL&#13;
D~~~~5 --                   - 3   l &#13;
01  I            LA                            0      U&#13;
i h                                  U . m  X   CN  o  u&#13;
a)~~~~~~~~L C7                a) Cu u ~        u'14&#13;
*H  0  I             -         -m&#13;
-  I                                  U~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~U&#13;
H   -         cn LA  |l  cn  in   H      N  N         N  LA  in&#13;
Cd  4.  I    LA  O  LA  Cd    LA  H     H;  i.    0   H  Ns  LA&#13;
h4  O  t     LA  i  NS  N     N  LA     LA  LAI   LA  Cl  v  C&#13;
-, 0   a            07N                               Ol V&#13;
Y l- I&#13;
(d O  aN      r7)  0L7  0D r-  r     C.  c            Ln&#13;
L    A _ &#13;
0)  0)  I _&#13;
&gt;  UV   I           LA NA               C ON&#13;
K4    ~~-,-  ~ 4  I         /        0          A         AL&#13;
| ,  0 \                                   - N  O   0O* 1 C   vt   ~ O N N HI&#13;
rI H&gt;g |  o  0l t   o r|N U      O|r  o   o|H w &#13;
w   wtD 01 0                                             Ul N|N m  0l  N  |O|&#13;
o 0n 0J             0 _   ll   H   C H  N   wo l  Co cn  | (N |   in   N  L  0 &#13;
e    ~~4-' C)4             C   n1                    ~   1&#13;
U         4,  I     Cd  N    cl  vib  cnn  'O  n  I r  LN cn   0)  LA  'Tc&#13;
C )            Ln 0   r!)  cn S            *         .N +  c , &#13;
La            0                0 A  N in0 LALA Cd        L   C  &#13;
4            1  11        1                 I         I 4e    I0&#13;
H~~~C/        IO    H &#13;
$4 | N  ||   h   T  z      X    l    h    t    Cn   |  &lt;&#13;
Cd&gt;-'  Cd  ~~~~0                    00&#13;
X4  La    I ~  ~ *             A &#13;
0  tn~l        d      ALA      L      n  L      C   I  N  L&#13;
0 C L  a" in o  0~ If  CN  AmCd    0  0)  0N  LA  %d&#13;
rti -1    LA  Cl C             ~C                  H~  H  H&#13;
0  r  O                    00 &#13;
U                H                H         H~f-4U &#13;
~~  Cl  ~~Cl  0  %LA  LnH  N  ~ l I-  0 LA  N N  d&#13;
r~~~~~g   0~~~~~C          0      *U)  O  0    00C&#13;
z         I                    0)~~~~~~~~~~~~~      L)C&#13;
O~~)CdH  I  N  LA  in  LA  Cd'~~~~~~~~~~  N  Cd  Cl  LA N1   0  in&#13;
~  H4-)     Cd'  Cd'  LA  in Cr'  LA  LA  N     Cl  C  A  C&#13;
HH$4C0~~~$ I         *            *&#13;
NO HI LAO in  HLA LA ~~~~~~~~m 0 in N  O  N NHaN N&#13;
0~~~~~~0&#13;
'0   _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _~~~~~~4         04-&#13;
0)                inN  OWN 0       in1N 0~~~~~~~~~Z3  WN 0  NOW&#13;
H             C)     HIH H HH H      HIH H      HH H      HH)  H HH H&#13;
H          &gt;1     &gt;1                                 0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~L  zm0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
H - &#13;
|   !  .1 tc ) o,   v  U   -96-&#13;
uD  ^lCI               v &#13;
-4   En I  fX&#13;
.,  o  ,  I   z   z BI:-&#13;
Z)  )U  I&#13;
Fo W  U   O i   |  U   .   o   o   .   o   o  O  m&#13;
|~~~~- 0 Cg IO00 &#13;
C~~~~~~  U)  B ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ U&#13;
0) &#13;
ft 4.   ij  0  (Ii&#13;
H) O             I     I i&#13;
03  I 0 $          ifl  N 04&#13;
0)  0 Vo&#13;
. , o _  . &#13;
&gt; I:i   f  I&#13;
&lt; ~ ~ ~ 0  0)  O   -  ) &gt;|   ) &gt;|N G &#13;
C~~~I                m  m~~IP.   Cq )   Ul)  l&#13;
U)  0 4.&#13;
a ) V.,     UU &#13;
P4 &gt;   -  I&#13;
UO        , ~~~~I      O.&#13;
o     t.)          E&#13;
E-4 ~ U  :          0   ~    C ~ ~ - &#13;
0   V)  -4  r-)  IN  -  i  4I  d&#13;
ID  (a-         -  H  - .-I  m  0&#13;
*?-, 4  ft  '1  ro      N  N  4 -&#13;
,-I  i   ~4 LI) I  &#13;
0)  (Z 4)  . &#13;
- 0 U)  -4 OI&#13;
D04 u:l &#13;
(0 4  ft&#13;
r4 0)  I ) &#13;
0&#13;
1-4  I  t  t  f  U  C') o-4  UT )  in  in&#13;
I  0     *~~~~~-   r-  *  O OD C   -&#13;
0 0 -,I              0  -  - &#13;
Z            r&#13;
'do  -.~a I4    ,,-   i-     - &#13;
0 U) C) B~~~~C)'D0'or,   0r,C&#13;
4i ~   0~0   &#13;
rZ ~ ~ Z  4) j*             '  )i       '&#13;
'-~H&gt;4U)  I      -4 ra  N  4 &#13;
0)ft.1~~~~)0)  4I0&#13;
Cz~~~O~ 0 I39&#13;
1-4             c mu ~  t '  c4  (' nm&#13;
Hft  w~~~~~~~~~-    = &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
N)                      I&#13;
tyl~.  C  I  C1   H    I   I  ,1&#13;
U)  o i      N I  o  o     I l l&#13;
m01                 I1 &#13;
V  I  I                U ) &#13;
tn  c4  I           -&#13;
U4            co N   W   =&#13;
QH  0  I &#13;
U)  U )      U'     U4u&#13;
J)  C I$4    CO  tD  v  kS  O &#13;
En     I     A   )  N  U   j  H&#13;
U  H   N     0 r&#13;
C)  0               H  H&#13;
&gt;     I  -          -&#13;
&gt;~~~~ UD     I 1°          - &#13;
I -!&#13;
0          coU)  I &#13;
O)   U H              I)  I&#13;
o1 4- -i  CIV)                 cl&#13;
4-i C   5-l    0  .  sr  k  L n&#13;
U) ~4 f    l  -     r)  C &#13;
0   0  0 J  O    H      H  a- 0&#13;
U)   &gt;44 a,LA&#13;
*-4  Cd  N  4&#13;
U)      4 o  -i&#13;
H      '~~~~~~~~ &#13;
oa       HO)  H U      ° oHe&#13;
O               _~- c)r      v      v &#13;
C                   m   U)  LA Or  0  flO &#13;
40~ ~   dU   1&gt;2   H  0      H  Nq LA C.&#13;
OOQ         0 QVNL&#13;
0  c 0 n&#13;
&lt;~~~~~~                 ~~~ coi  114 00 0&#13;
p4   HO)~~~~~~~~~4 E  I H&#13;
4-)  )  I  i&#13;
&gt;4             I k     N  H 0   C.  N &#13;
|4  C    C     K      C&#13;
I  0  0   0~~~~~Z)  0:  c   N  C.&#13;
I-q ~ I &#13;
U             I~~~~~~ &#13;
P4               I I&#13;
03 ~    0~C-   I            %o   ) &#13;
H H~~~~~~~~U)  I%   )  '~o&#13;
~~  .c~~~~ *H1&#13;
0                 0~~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-98-&#13;
Notes for Table I-4&#13;
n.a. - not available&#13;
* - indicates possible fuelwood problem&#13;
1.  The population figures are from the World Book, Population Projections:&#13;
1975-2000 (April 1978).&#13;
2.  These figures are based on the 1976 Yearbook of Forest Products.   The baseline&#13;
per capita estimates are for 1976. The 1990 figures are trend projections&#13;
based on a linear regression of the historical data in the 1976 Yearbook,&#13;
except in a few cases where an exponential growth model was used. Projected&#13;
figures in parentheses are the result of regressions which explain less than&#13;
half of the variance (r2 A. 0.5).&#13;
Original data converted to energy units assuming wood density of 0.725 kg/m3&#13;
and energy content of 15 GJ per metric ton.&#13;
These per capita use estimates were based on FAO fuelwood and charcoal&#13;
production estimates. As a result there is some distortion because imports&#13;
and exports were not taken into account, however, this error is small since&#13;
international trade of fuelwood and charcoal involves less than one half of&#13;
one percent of total production. Furthermore, the FAO figures pose a problem&#13;
in that imports and exports do not balance: total world imports are 80 percent&#13;
larger than world exports.&#13;
3.  These figures are based on the difference between total roundwood production&#13;
and fuelwood and charcoal production in the 1976 Yearbook of Forest Products.&#13;
The baseline per capita estimates are for 1976. The 1990 figures are trend&#13;
projections based on the per annum growth rate from 1970 to 1976.   In some&#13;
cases where this procedure lead to a very high or low growth rate for non-fuel&#13;
wood use, total roundwood production was linearly regressed. Then the difference&#13;
between projected roundwood and projected fuelwood and charcoal was taken to&#13;
be the projected non-fuel wood use.  This procedure was used for Ivory Coast,&#13;
Liberia, Malaysia, Nicaragua, Papau-New Guineau, Peru, Swaziland, Tanzania, and&#13;
Uruguay.&#13;
,4. The sustainable forest yields are above ground annual wood increments&#13;
based on (i) forst types and yields in Figure 4.2 and Table 4.3&#13;
of Derek E. Earl, Forest Energy and Economic Development (Oxford:&#13;
Clarendon Press, 1975) and (ii) forest and woodland area from&#13;
1977 FAO Production Yearbook.&#13;
5. the baseline figures are based on the 1977 FAO Production Yearbook;&#13;
the 1990 figures are based on FAO projections of the number of&#13;
cattle and sheep and goats. The sources are listed in order of&#13;
decreasing residue contribution. The sources and ranking are constant&#13;
between 1977 and 1990. The source codes and the annual residue&#13;
(0% moisture content) produced per animal used are as follows:&#13;
Animal               Code    Annual Residue (ton/head)&#13;
cattle, buffalo, camel         C                1.00&#13;
horses, donkeys, asses         H                 .75&#13;
sheep, goats                   s                 .15&#13;
pigs                            p                .30&#13;
chicken, fowl                  F                 .005&#13;
The energy content of dry dung was taken to be 15 GJ per metric ton.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-99-&#13;
For projecting livestock residues, the basic projection in FAO Commodity Projections&#13;
1985, Meat: Supply; Demand and Trade Projections 1985 (June 1978) was utilized.&#13;
In this source cattle numbers and sheep and goat numbers are projected to 1985 for&#13;
geographical and other groupings: Latin America, Africa, Near East, Far East,&#13;
Asian centrally planned economies, and other developed regions. Based on these&#13;
figures two sets of projected annual growth rates were determined: for cattle&#13;
and for sheep and goats. These rates were used to calculate 1990 livestock&#13;
residue total availability by selecting for each country a livestock residual growth&#13;
rate equal to that of the animal group which produced the most dung in 1977. This&#13;
procedure was not changed when either cattle or sheep and goats were not the largest&#13;
dung producers, although this was rarely the case. In nearly all countries cattle&#13;
(including buffalo and camels) were the largest dung producers.&#13;
6. The baseline figures are based on the 1977 FAO Production Yearbook); the 1990 figures&#13;
are based on World Bank, International Food Policy Research Institute and FAO&#13;
projections. The sources are listed in order of decreasing residue contributions.&#13;
The sources and ranking is constant between 1977 and 1990. The source codes and&#13;
the residue (at field moisture content) to grain ratio used are as follows:&#13;
Grain                      Code                 Residue-grain ratio&#13;
rice                        R                          2.00:1&#13;
corn/maize                  C                          2.50:1&#13;
sorghum                     S                         2.50:1&#13;
wheat                       W                          1.75:1&#13;
barley                      B                          1.75:1&#13;
millet                      M                          2.00:1&#13;
rye                         Ry                         1.75:1&#13;
oats                        0                          1.75:1&#13;
jute                        J                          2.00:1&#13;
The energy content of agricultural residues was taken to be 13 GJ per metric ton.&#13;
Jute sticks were included only for Bangladesh. In all other countries, jute&#13;
production is less than 2 percent of total cereal production.&#13;
Cereal residues are only a fraction of total agricultural residues produced. In&#13;
most parts of the Third World, roots and tubers, vegetable, fruit, nut, pulse,&#13;
cotton production is very significant. However, the extensive residues from these&#13;
crops are not included in this table.&#13;
For projecting cereal crop residues, several sources were used. If availal-ie from&#13;
Price Prospects for Major Primary Commodities (Report No. 814/78, June 1978), country&#13;
specific growth rates for wheat, rice or coarse grains were applied to the 1977 FAQ&#13;
based production figures. These growth rates were only available for certain crops&#13;
for twelve developing countries. For the majority of countries, cereals production&#13;
were projected to grow at the rate implied by the International Food Policy Research&#13;
Institute report, Food Needs of Developing Countries: Projections of Production and&#13;
Consumption to 1990 (Volume 3, pages 129-136; December 1977). For the remaining&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
countries, approximately 15, not covnrnd by these sources, FiAO bo:5sic proJ2ct&#143;%O8;)&#13;
growth rates for cereals for differest geogrzprz-ical reg-tons fro.. ''AO Comno6 Ity&#13;
Projections 1985, Cereals:   Sygk    Demand and 'frade ?roJection_  985 (Juy y978)&#13;
were used.  For all of the countries except those for whlich som. 3trnk project:ons&#13;
were available, it was implicitly assumed that the miA of diffeen.c cerea.- crops&#13;
produced, residue-product ratios and energy contents remained constanat.&#13;
7. The baseline figures are based on 1977 FAO Production Yearbook; th-e 1990 f:igt.-zs&#13;
are based on projected growth rates from World Bank,   The ratio of bagasse to&#13;
sugarcane harvested at field moisture (sbout 50 percent) uned Wc So5 with a&#13;
corresponding energy content of 9.5 CJ per metic ton,&#13;
Bagasse availability was forecasted for only those major sugarcane producers&#13;
for which the Bank makes country specific projections of sugar production growth&#13;
rates.  The document used was Market Prospects for Sugar (June 1978) by Ezriel&#13;
Brook of the Economic Analysis and Projections Department.&#13;
8. In the 1976 Yearbook of Forest Products, the data for fuelwood, charcoal and&#13;
non-fuelwood use for Lesotho and Nam-lbia are included under those for South Africa.&#13;
Therefore the per capita results for the3e tWo categories (fuelwood and charcoal and&#13;
non-fuelwood use) for South Africa are based on the total populLtion of the three&#13;
countries. The population figures presented for South Africa are for that country&#13;
only.&#13;
9. The potential availability of agricultural residues for the Republic of China&#13;
(Taiwan) are based on 1976 agricultural oroduction levels from the U.S. Depar:ment&#13;
of Agriculture, Indices of Agricultural Production for Asia and Oceania, StatistiLcal&#13;
Bulletin No. 606 (June 1978),&#13;
lOo The 1977 population figure for Puerto Rico is an estimate from the New York City&#13;
office of the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico (telephone call),&#13;
11. In both the 1977 FAQ Production Yearbook and the 1976 Yearbook o' Forest Products,&#13;
the data for China include both China PR (m.ainland and the provioce of Taiwan (the&#13;
Republic of China). As a result the per capita igures for woo6 use, forest yield&#13;
and agricultural and livestock residiues are based on the total populatlon of China PR&#13;
and Taiwan.  The population figures presented for Chiina PR are only for that country,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-101-&#13;
TABLE I-5    Fuelwood and Charcoal Use -- 1976-19901&#13;
AFRICA, SOUTH OF SAHARA&#13;
(million GJ)&#13;
FAO             Projections based on FAO historical data&#13;
Country             1976              1980            1985              1990&#13;
Regional Group 1&#13;
Benin                25.77            27.42           30.63              33.83&#13;
Burundi              9.59             10.52           11.40              12.25&#13;
Central African&#13;
Empire            19.58            (22.78).        (24.16)            (25.55)&#13;
Chad                 37.63            38.78           42.14              45.48&#13;
Ethiopia            250.24           271.22          288.84             306.34&#13;
The Gambia            2.63             2.94            3.39               3.85&#13;
Guinea              28.81             31.35           34.18              36.97&#13;
Kenya              125.08            133.22          143.47             153.68&#13;
Lesotho             n.a.              n.a.            n.a.               n.a.&#13;
Madagascar           52.90            60.08           68.18              76.23&#13;
Malawi              33.05            (28.20)         (24.16)            (20.15)&#13;
Mali                 30.34            33.24           36.38              39.54&#13;
Niger                25.26            28.02           30.55              33.11&#13;
Rwanda              42.11             47.18           51.32             55.48&#13;
Sierra Leone         27.20            26.93           26.61              26.30&#13;
Somalia             34.52             37.42           40.87             44.33&#13;
Tanzania            398.69           427.49          475.02             522.55&#13;
Uganda             147.87            163.73          176.70            189.70&#13;
Upper Volta         42.64             46.82           50.31             53.80&#13;
Zaire              128.36           (142.66)        (149.28)           (155.94)&#13;
Regional Group 1&#13;
Totals          1462.27           1580.00         1707.59           1835.08&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
102 -&#13;
&gt;&#142;B3L2 I-5  (continued)&#13;
2zFRXCA, SO`15 Of.? SAIR.-\&#13;
FAQ            ),.).ojecJ- ons bpased on FAQ histori cal data&#13;
Country             1976             . .980          1985              1990&#13;
Regional Group 2&#13;
Angola              73..90           7'/53           04-1.2            9G071&#13;
k3otswana            7.,51           0O;.17           0,,85             9 55&#13;
tIu.eroon           76.55            820,,65         89029             95,o96&#13;
Congo               19.32            22oK .0         2,5,20            28.69&#13;
Ghana              114,59           131 026         15138            17Lo53&#13;
Gmin.ea-Bissau       4068             4.90            5012              5.34&#13;
XV0ory Coast        5 3 ..I         25225)          (51,,41)          (5006;)&#13;
Liberia             14,84            1$5o87          17,43             l9o00&#13;
kituxitania          5 .72            6018            6.66              7.o1&#13;
P£auitius             .24            02; .             1)  t             10&#13;
Mozambique          89.59            9 7 L 65        04. o  88 a      1252.3&#13;
Mamibia             n.a.             n, a.           n.a.             nXa. P-&#13;
k\!igeria          699.24           762 097         848882            935o22&#13;
Rhodesia            58,69            5'f.97          70.20             75.44&#13;
Seneceal            25,,96           28321.          30.79             33.35&#13;
Sudan              227059          (226096)        (232,62)           238019&#13;
Swaziland            4,o89           53 59            6,25              7 00&#13;
Togo                10,33            10 ,54          11.23             11,95&#13;
Zambia              40.56           (47,70)         (49,35)           (51.18)&#13;
X9gional Group 2&#13;
Yota2s          1525.31          :64i5,36        1793,77           19430.1&#13;
Regional Group 3&#13;
Gabon               11.96           O3,ll9 0        (12.00)           (12.08)&#13;
R°unJ. on             °34               I'5           °09               °05&#13;
South Africa        1099            12_39           !3.55             J.4 81&#13;
Regional Group 3&#13;
Totals            23.29            2444            25064             26094&#13;
AFRICAk, SOUTH CF&#13;
SAHARA- TOTALS   30i0o87          3249.80         3527000           3805013&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-103-&#13;
TABLE I-5 : Fuelwood and Charcoal Use -- 1976-1990 1&#13;
NORTH AFRICA AND MIDDLE EAST&#13;
(million GJ)&#13;
FAO             Projections based on FAO historical data&#13;
Country              1976             1980             1985              1990&#13;
Regional Group 4&#13;
Algeria              14.08            15.75            17.70             19.65&#13;
Egypt                 1.22             1.35             1.50              1.62&#13;
Jordan                 .03              .02              .01                .005&#13;
Morocco              29.63            32.45            36.01             39.56&#13;
Syria                  .54              .54              .54                .54&#13;
Tunisia              18.76            20.68            22.71             24.73&#13;
Yemen A.R.           n.a.             n.a.             n.a.              n.a.&#13;
Yemen PDR            n.a.             n.a.             n.a.              n.a.&#13;
Regional Group 4&#13;
Totals            64.26             70.79            78.47             86.11&#13;
Regional Group 5a&#13;
Iran                 21.83            19.94            -1.89             23.87&#13;
Iraq                   .16              .12              .09               .06&#13;
Lebanon                .65              .86             1.01              1.16&#13;
Regional Group 5a&#13;
Totals             22.64            20.92            22.99             25.09&#13;
Regional Group 5b&#13;
Kuwait               n.a.             n.a.             n.a.              n.a.&#13;
Libya                 4.36            (4.43)           (4.64)             (4.86)&#13;
Oman                n.a.              n.a.             n.a.              n.a.&#13;
Saudi Arabia         n.a.             n.a.             n.a.              n.a.&#13;
UAE                  n.a.             n.a.            n.a.               n.a.&#13;
Regional Group 5b&#13;
Totals             4.36              4.43            4.64               4.86&#13;
NORTH AFRICA AND&#13;
MIDDLE EAST TOTALS: 91.26             96.14           106.10            116.06&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-:104-&#13;
TABLE I-5 z Fuelwood azid CbercoF2 Use* 1976 3cX)&#13;
Asx), AND AX5C&#13;
(mi,.ilion CJ)&#13;
FAO            Pzojections based on FAC 7- .stoxicat. c u.&#13;
Country             1976             3.980          3.S85              9 2t&#13;
.egiona1 Group 6a&#13;
Cambodia            44.10            A84.8          53 3 2?9           .&#13;
Laos                32.33            35.44           38,6'            a,,&#13;
Vietnam            177.26           194.73          208.70            22206S&#13;
Regional Group 6a&#13;
Totals           253.69           2,78.63         300,o3            322~51&#13;
Regional Group 6o&#13;
Afghanistan         62.91            67020           73.23            -i &gt;2f&#13;
Bhutan              nOa.             n O a.          n.a, o 2             I&#13;
Nepal               94o61           101.47          107Jo0           1&gt;2o7,.&#13;
Pakistan            92.09           103.48           14 o61          i 2?,) o 7x'&#13;
Regional Group 6b&#13;
Totals           249.61           272015          294, 94           31 7 dg3&#13;
Regional Group 6c&#13;
India             1285.19          1359,27        14A2J10           L606Os. 3&#13;
Sri Lanka           45o95            410S 50 52,28                    5..,&#13;
Regional Group 6c&#13;
Totals          1331014          j./08,37        :t p334,f        1661958&#13;
Regional7 Group 6d&#13;
Bangladesh         152038           I90,89          231o03           2ViS&#13;
Burma              206.62           2:i7.69         304,8:3          3632.,3&#13;
Regional Group 6d&#13;
Totals           359.00           4i48,58         533,86           6 3, 4 43&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-105-&#13;
TABLE I-5 (continued)&#13;
ASIA AND PACIFIC&#13;
FAO             Projections based on FAO historical data&#13;
Country             1976             1980            1985              1990&#13;
Regional Group 6e&#13;
Indonesia         1207.12          1344.04         1484.76           1625.49&#13;
Regional Group 6e&#13;
Totals          1207.12          1344.04         1484.76           1625.49&#13;
Regional Group 7a&#13;
Republic of China&#13;
(Taiwan)          n.a.             n.a.            n.a.              n.a.&#13;
Fiji                  .12              .07             .05               .03&#13;
Republic of Korea   79.93            81.00           76.88             72.74&#13;
Malaysia            61.04            64.53           69.32             74.08&#13;
Papua-New Guinea    51.69            56.73           62.00             67.26&#13;
Philippines        249.69           274.42          307.46            340.50&#13;
Thailand           174.99           186.35          201.00            215.63&#13;
Regional Group 7a&#13;
Totals           617.46           663.10          716.71            770.24&#13;
Regional Group 7b&#13;
Hong Kong           n.a.             n.a.            n.a.              n.a.&#13;
Singapore           n.a.             n.a.            n.a.              n.a.&#13;
Regional Group 7b&#13;
Totals             0.0              0.0             0.0               0.0&#13;
ASIA AND PACIFIC&#13;
TOTALS          4018.02          4414.89         4867.88           5332.10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-106-&#13;
BBLE I-5 . Fuelwood and Chnarcoal Use -- 1975-1990 &#13;
XATXN AMERXCA AND CARIBBEAN&#13;
(million GJ)&#13;
FAO            Projections based on FAO h:.storical data&#13;
Country             1976             198C            1985              1990&#13;
3g9xona1 Group 8&#13;
Bo1livia            38.61            36016           32055             28094&#13;
Caile               32063            32032           32019             32005&#13;
Colombia           217.50           211007          200,24            189,40&#13;
Costa Rica          23.85            27.24           3Co33             33.42&#13;
Cuba                16.31            14.2S           12269             11.09&#13;
Dominican&#13;
Republic          18089           (20010)         (20.36)           (20.63)&#13;
Ecuador             21010           (22o70)          (26o02)           (29.34)&#13;
El Salvador         34.58           %31,C5)         (33021)           (35.37)&#13;
Guatemala           55o68            61o29           69o06             76o81&#13;
Guyana                o17              o08             .04                0 C2&#13;
Haiti               40/78            44.,44 1        47.46             50.48&#13;
Honduras            32.62            35.00           35.90             36S82&#13;
Jamaica               .01              .1      00101                     oOl&#13;
Nicaragua           23022            23033           24.29             25.27&#13;
Paraguay            32,62            35,84           39.82             43.79&#13;
Peru                62,50            69o12           76013             83013&#13;
Regional Group 8&#13;
'.Iotals         651.07           664,04          680,30            696,56&#13;
Regional Group 9a&#13;
Mexico              88,85            87.26           82.53             77,81&#13;
Regional Group 9a&#13;
Totals            88085            87.26           82.52             77,81&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-107-&#13;
TABLE I-5 (continued)&#13;
LATIN AIERICA AND CARIBBEAN&#13;
FAO             Projections based on FAO historical data&#13;
Country             1976              1980            1985              1990&#13;
Regional Group sb&#13;
Brazil            1522.50           1635.32         1720.85            1806.39&#13;
Regional Group 9b&#13;
Totals          1522.50           1635.32         1720.85           1806.39&#13;
Regional Group 9c&#13;
Argentina           87.00             82.00           75.86              69.74&#13;
pana a              15.22            (15.73)          (16.42)           (17.11)&#13;
Puerto Rico         n.a.              n.a.            n.a.               n.a.&#13;
Trinidad and&#13;
Tobago               .11             (.10)            (.07)             (.04)&#13;
Uruguay             10.33             10.90           12.20              13.50&#13;
Venezuela            79.69            88.56           97.85             107.16&#13;
Regional Group 9c&#13;
Totals           192.35            197.29          202.40             207.55&#13;
LATIN AMERICA AND&#13;
CARIBBEAN TOTALS 2454.77           2583.91         2686.08            2788.31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
--1O8-&#13;
TBLE I-5          Fuelwood and  Charcoal Use    197' 199O-&#13;
SOUTHERN EUROPE, WESTERN EUROPE, NORTH AMERICA &amp; OCJIANIA&#13;
(million GJ)&#13;
FAO            Pxojections based on FAO historical dat'&#13;
Country             1976             1980            1985             3990&#13;
SOUTIHERN EUROPE                Regional Group lOa&#13;
eizkey            ll1l9            D(i38.86)       (4 7,44s          ( l56,56&#13;
Regional Group lOb&#13;
Cyprus, Portugal&#13;
Yugoslavia          49.35            30o80           19.84&#13;
Regional Group lOc&#13;
Greece, Israel,&#13;
Spain               42,87            33vS4           21L27            13.34&#13;
SOUTHERN EUROPE&#13;
TOTALS             206.41           203060          18O8855          18205'!&#13;
WESTERN EUROPE                  Regional Group 11&#13;
Austria, Belgium-&#13;
Luxembourg, Denmark,&#13;
Finland, France,&#13;
Germany FR, Ireland,&#13;
Italy, Netherlands,&#13;
Worway, Sweden,&#13;
Switzerland,&#13;
United Kingdom&#13;
WESTERN EUROPE&#13;
TOTALS             212077           157.57         118.32             88085&#13;
WORTH AMERICA &amp;                 Regional Group 12&#13;
OCEANIA&#13;
Australia, Canada,&#13;
Japan, New Zealand,&#13;
United States&#13;
WORTH AMERICA &amp;&#13;
OCEANIA TOTALS     225.01           132.44           85059            55030&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-108a-&#13;
TABLE I-5.: Fuelwood and Charcoal Use -- 1976-19901&#13;
CENTRALLY PLANNED ECONOMIES&#13;
(million GJ)&#13;
FAO             Projections based on FAO historical data&#13;
Country             1976             1980            1985              1990&#13;
Regional Group 13a&#13;
China PR          1544.25          1663.11         1793.61           1924.00&#13;
Korea DPR           50.46            55.75           61.06             66.38&#13;
Mongolia            14.68            18.16           20.92             23.69&#13;
Regional Group 13a&#13;
Totals          1609.39          1737.02         1875.59           2014.07&#13;
Regional Group 13b&#13;
Albania, Bulgaria,&#13;
Romania&#13;
Regional Group 13b&#13;
Totals            82.01            72.83           64.08             56.38&#13;
Regional Group 13c&#13;
Czechoslovakia&#13;
Germany DR, Hungary,&#13;
Poland, USSR&#13;
Regional Group 13c&#13;
Totals           952.37           868.17          793.08            724.49&#13;
CENTRALLY PLANNED&#13;
ECONOMIES T\OTALS  2643.77         2678.02         2732.75           2794.94&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-109,&#13;
Notes for Table T-5&#13;
n.a.    not available.&#13;
1.     This table is based on pages 17 and 18 of the 1976 Yearbooke of&#13;
Forest Products. The 1983, 1985 and 1990 figures are trend&#13;
projections based on regressing historical data from &gt;She&#13;
1976 Yearbook. Projected figures in parentheses are the result&#13;
of regressions which explain less than one half of the variance&#13;
(r2 &lt; 0.5).&#13;
These per capita use estimates were based on FAO fuelwood and&#13;
charcoal production estimates. As a result there is some&#13;
distortion because imports and exports were not tciken i.nto&#13;
account; however, this error is small since international&#13;
trade of fuelwood and charcoal involves less than one half of&#13;
one percent of total production. Furthermore, the FAO figures&#13;
pose a problem in that imports and exports do not balance:&#13;
total world imports are 80 percent larger than world ecnorts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-110-                                -ANNEX II&#13;
NON-CONVENTIONAL ENERGY TECHNOLOGIES&#13;
CONTENTS&#13;
Page&#13;
(Biomass Conversion)&#13;
A. IMPROVED STOVES ...,                                 ,       ,,. 111&#13;
B. BIOGAS ..                                                      114&#13;
C. PYROLYSIS AND RELATED PROCESSES         .      .............. 117&#13;
D. ALCOHOLS            ...             .119&#13;
(Direct Solar).&#13;
E.  PHOTOVOLTAIC CELLS .........................-.-.-.--.-.120&#13;
F. SOLAR COOK ERS.121&#13;
G.  SOLAR DRIERS ..        ...............               .      . 125&#13;
H.  SOLAR STILLS ........................................... 126&#13;
I. FLAT PLATE SOLAR WATER HEATERS .. 127&#13;
J.  CONCENTRATING SOLAR WATER HEATERS................            128&#13;
(Wind and Water Power)&#13;
K. WINDMILLS.                                                    129&#13;
L. MICRO-HYDRO............................................ 130&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
A. IMPROVED STOVES&#13;
1        Most people who cook with wood use "stoves" that accomplish little&#13;
more than holding the pan, pot or other cooking vessel at an apprcoriate&#13;
height above an essentially open fire. Many improvements are possible in this&#13;
system. Generally, they involve enclosing the fire, regulating t'le flow of air&#13;
into the stove, and adding a chimney. These measures can increase efficiency&#13;
by a factor of 4 to 5 in laboratory tests; a halving of fuel requiirements for&#13;
household use has been claimed for a variety of designs. In some designs, the&#13;
stove is given a large thermal mass, so that much of the heat which is lost for&#13;
cooking purposes is released over an extended period after a meal is cooked and&#13;
is thus useful for space heating.&#13;
2.        The primary purpose of the chimney is to improve the stove's draft.&#13;
In effect, this allows for a greater exi:raction of heat from the combustion gases&#13;
by increasing the efficiency with which their buoyancy is used to pull air through&#13;
the stove. The chimney can also be used to conduct the exhaust gases out of the&#13;
home, which helps improve eye and respiratory system health. in some areas,&#13;
however, smoke in the home is considered beneficial because it cr&gt;ves away insects&#13;
that attack not only people but also roofing materials,&#13;
3.        Two general types of improved stoves have been developec0    The type&#13;
illustrated in Figures II -l and II-2 'is sometimes referred to as r, "mud" stove,&#13;
but is in fact made from a mixture of sand and clay wi-th enough sand to prevent&#13;
excessive cracking and enough clay to hold the stove together0    The clay should fire,&#13;
producing a hard surface in the firebox and flues0 Similar stoves have also&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-112-&#13;
FIGURE II-1&#13;
IMPROVED STOVE (GUATEMALA)&#13;
K'          H&#13;
t:~      ~      - !-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-113-&#13;
CL) I                      FIGURE 11-2&#13;
IMPROVED STOVE (INDONESIA)&#13;
*1&#13;
(Section)&#13;
Wood Storage&#13;
(Complete Stove)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-114-&#13;
been built with mixtures of clay and ashes, and fibrous material such as&#13;
straw may be added for strength. The chimney may be made from metal stovepipe,&#13;
bamboo, lengths of ceramic pipe, or built up with bricks of stove material.&#13;
4.        The second type of improved stove is made with a metal shell,&#13;
usually a used can of 5-gallon or larger capacity. An inner liner of&#13;
ceramic or other material may be used to separate the fire from the shell,&#13;
reducing heat losses and prolonging the shell's life. The cooking vessel&#13;
and food may be placed on top of the shell for frying or inside it for stewing&#13;
and higher efficiency. Some stoves of this type are designed to be packed&#13;
with sawdust, rice hulls, or other loose fuels rather than for use with wood.&#13;
B. BIOGAS&#13;
5.        A mixture of gases containing 55-65% methane is obtained from the&#13;
anaerobic decomposition of organic materials. It occurs in nature (e.g.&#13;
swamp gas) and has been produced in controlled environemtns for many years,&#13;
as a by-product of certain types of sewage treatment plants. When produced&#13;
for use as a fuel, it is often referred to as biogas.&#13;
6,       There is currently considerable interest in many countries in the potential&#13;
use of family or village scale biogas plants to provide fuel, improve sanitation,&#13;
and increase the fertilizer and soil-conditioning value of animal dung and other&#13;
organic wastes. The theoretical advantages of biogas production are especially&#13;
great in areas in which firewood is unavailable and animal dung is used as a&#13;
household fuel because it allows the use of a given quantity of dung as both fuel&#13;
and fertilizer. It does this by separating the fuel-valuable carbon from the&#13;
nitrogen in the dung. Most pathogenic organisms can be destroyed in a biogas&#13;
digester, so the technology can be used for the treatment of human wastes as well.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-115-&#13;
7.       Biogas can be produced in controlled environments, but the process&#13;
involved is a biological one involving several types of bacteria and is not fully&#13;
understood. The process is sensitive to temperature, acidity-alkalinity, and to&#13;
the type of feedstock used. Most digesters are operated at 30-35°C, although the&#13;
process can be maintained at temperatures down to about 10°C. At temperatures&#13;
well above the normal range, a different type of bacterial culture dominates&#13;
("thermophilic" as opposed to "mesophilic") and the process of methane production&#13;
is greatly accelerated. However, a thermophilic digester must be kept at 50-600C&#13;
and the cost of maintaining these temperatures is generally considered to exceed&#13;
the cost of using the larger digester required to obtain the same production from&#13;
a mesophilic system.&#13;
8.       A biogas digester consists basically of a sealed container filled with&#13;
water and the material to be digested. Gas produced rises to the top of the&#13;
container and is extracted through a tube or pipe. In most designs, an upper&#13;
portion of the container is reserved for gas storage. Raw materials are generally&#13;
added through an inlet at one end of the digester and the digested "sludge"&#13;
withdrawn via an outlet at the opposite end. At least three families of designs&#13;
are under development. They are distinguished by the means used to cope with&#13;
variations in the quantity of gas in storage.&#13;
The "Indian" design approach is to construct the digester in two telescoping parts&#13;
with a system of guides and counterweights to adjust the volume. The "early&#13;
Chinese" solution is to let accumulating gas push the liquid contents of the digester&#13;
up the outlet (which is covered but not pressure-sealed) and to minimize&#13;
fluctuations in water level by providing a large surface area between collected&#13;
gas and liquid. "Bag" digesters are made from a flexible material and easily&#13;
adjust to changes in the volume of their contents by changing shape. "Recent&#13;
Chinese" biogas units are built to withstand pressures of up to about 100 cm of&#13;
water, and so accomodate fluctuations in gas quantity by allowing pressure to&#13;
build up within a fixed volume.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-116-&#13;
9.       Biogas is usually produced under low pressures (5 to 10 cm water) and often&#13;
contains small amounts of hydrogen sulfide, which may cause corrosion problems in&#13;
any exposed metal parts with which the gas comes in contact. However, with suitable&#13;
adjustments to the burners, most appliances made for natural gas or LPG can be&#13;
adapted for use with biogas. Biogas can also be used to run internal combustion&#13;
engines, but to use it in vehicles would require compressors and pressurized tanks.&#13;
10.       India and China have both launched large-scale biogas programs at various&#13;
times. The Indian program involved technical assistance and subsidies on construction&#13;
costs and reportedly resulted in the construction of some 37,000 plants. The program&#13;
was criticized and cut back on income-distribution grounds: benefits went to&#13;
the relatively wealthy who had the cattle, land, and credit needed to build and use&#13;
a biogas plant and, apparently, introduction of the plants induced an increase in&#13;
the value of dung, so that the program had a negative impact on the real income&#13;
of the poorest groups, who cook with dung obtained from others.&#13;
11.      Biogas was one of the technologies promoted in the Chinese "Great Leap&#13;
Forward" program of 1958-60, but was reportedly not used on a widespread basis&#13;
until the 1970s. According to some reports, there were "well over" four million&#13;
biogas digesters in China by 1977. Many of these are apparently family-sized units.&#13;
12.      Most Asian developing countries appear to have between ten and a few&#13;
hundred biogas plants in operation. They appear to be most successful in the&#13;
Republics of China and Korea (where they are not operated during the winter).&#13;
In both of these countries, as in PR China, the primary feedstock is pig manure,&#13;
which has technical advantages over cow dung.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
117&#13;
C. PYROY.LSS ABD RE LAT:TD PTR J1I S IS&#13;
!3Aher tiood is neated su"ff ici )  S'n 2n oXygen I-ree env.i.:'onment,&#13;
a di!:tSJltI`or- process  occurs   AWOiS-:u0'e -'Vd &gt;ola.i-le  -e-e-a½ In the woo&amp;&#13;
are eva9,o.-ated, les v:-9 zcrbon and.    ci. meritlS :n the fo:-m c5 churcoa).&#13;
Ar ambieni. tempera.ure ancl pressare conditions, soiae o' the volp&lt;Jles will&#13;
coxndevse t-o form iiqui-ds ;-iile others  2mArin gases.&#13;
140 .     71r 'o-isLure erci ilinited -ftou,r.sn ) air are ava:labi3c  &lt;oe water and&#13;
carbon will react to forn carbon mLpcn-,m  n  and hydrogen in a com'ousible gaseous&#13;
rTIxtu.v_- -krown as "produrcr g-as  Pro)ucer gas typicallly conta_in-, about 25%&#13;
carbon Linonoxide an-d 10% Vnyerrgeni  g !iv. xi. a flue value abo.ut o e-s-xth that&#13;
of natur 2l1 gas.&#13;
15.       `.rater gas" is made by passing stegm Lhrough a bed of carbon heated&#13;
to ove_r lOUC0   Wi0%, Ut the additioni of' air-,  The ch.inicai reactions involved&#13;
are si,"ila- to those in thc producer g,.s cEs-z bu. as no alr is 'seS the&#13;
procuct is undilut2d by -ait.,ogen acQ haz,e  7a : gas has a fue-l value about&#13;
twIyce rhat of producer gas. Hovyavsr, t:ce pOocess requires a greaf: deal of&#13;
heat to mnaintafn the _--r,p2rature, so that,r i-t 5s generally altercyate-d with&#13;
a combustion cycle in w-S-c-h neacly hElf of Lhe czr:bon is used up,&#13;
16.       These procZs-E--  al be a'   sd 'o L'   ciats oLl -r thEr ,jood. Straws&#13;
nrut shells, coe-sL bark  id Lice hu-I-lls --a  isas ESWZ119 the primary constraints&#13;
appear to be moisture and -c h i Ine:L ma-eshla  co.._-nt,&#13;
17.       CharcoEl is 1mup -ant -,n souz             : ldL-t)tr  I 3.cessas, as 3c_ial ly steel&#13;
planss whnere lt can substitute foSr     more caol-ly usea cokS     Charcoal ls also&#13;
a w-`s-±y used household fal i?n aze-i_ at scin o stance from sou-zes of wood&#13;
because itL is much more economically rraasportrcl and i!ancled th.ao an equivalent&#13;
amourt of xvood,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-118-&#13;
18.      Charcoal is traditionally produced with no more capital equipment&#13;
than an axe and a shovel; earthen kilns are made by digging a pit, piling wood&#13;
into it, and covering the wood with a layer of dirt. In these kilns, some of&#13;
the wood is burned to provide the heat needed to reduce the remainder to charcoal.&#13;
The gases and liquids produced are not captured, and the charcoal can be&#13;
separated only imperfectly from the dirt.&#13;
19.      This process can be improved in several steps.    First, small portable&#13;
steel kilns can be used. This allows for better control of the process, so&#13;
the fraction of wood burned is reduced closer to the theoretical minimum and&#13;
the problem of contamination with dirt is avoided.&#13;
20.      A second level of improvement is to use a large, permanently constructed&#13;
masonry kiln. The lower surface:volume ratio and better insulation reduce&#13;
loss of heat and thus further improve yields. However, use of these kilns requires&#13;
supplying a flow of wood to a fixed point over a period of years.&#13;
21.      Finally, an externally heated retort can be substituted for the internally&#13;
heated kiln. This makes it practical to recover and use the gases and liquids&#13;
given off.&#13;
22.      Producer gas is a serviceable fuel for internal combustion engines,&#13;
and is produced on a commercial basis from rice hulls, cotton gin trash, saw mill&#13;
residues (principally bark in at least one case), and presumably from wood and&#13;
coal as well. It can be used to fuel vehicles either by using a small, portable&#13;
generator or by compressing the gas into cylinders. These practices have&#13;
apparently been restricted to wartime and similar shortage situations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-119-&#13;
D. ALCOHOLS&#13;
23.                        Alcohol can be produced from certain types of&#13;
organic material. While there is an energy loss in the process, it upgrades&#13;
the fuels in terms of handling and combustion properties to the point that&#13;
they become useful as motor fuels. Alcohol is also a convenient fuel for&#13;
lamps, but its advantages are less distinct for uses such as cooking in&#13;
which solid fuels are practical.&#13;
24.       Two distinct types of alcohol are often promoted as renewable&#13;
alternatives to petroleum fuels. Methanol, also called "methyl alcohol" or&#13;
"wood alcohol," can be produced by distillation of wood or synthesized from&#13;
carbon monoxide and hydrvdan which In turn may be obtained from ndatiral gas&#13;
or coal. Ethanol (ethyl alcohol or "grain alcohol") is produced by fermentation&#13;
of carbohydrate materials or synthesized from petrochemical feedstocks. Either&#13;
type of alcohol can be used to power vehicles either by itself or blended to&#13;
15-20% with gasoline, but there are important differences between them.&#13;
25.          Methanol has about one-half of gasoline's fuel value per unit volume&#13;
or weight. Operation of a gasoline-type engine on methanol is possible but&#13;
requires a redesign of the fuel system and starting may be a problem in cold&#13;
weather. Use of methanol-gasoline blends can reduce the need for changes in the&#13;
engine but would require a distribution system that could keep water out of&#13;
the fuel much more effectively than is necessary in handling straight gasoline.&#13;
26.       Ethanol has about two-thirds the energy content of gasoline per unit&#13;
volume or per unit weight. Like methanol, it requires minor alterations in&#13;
the design of gasoline engines if it is to be used straight and can be used&#13;
in a gasoline blend without engine modifications. Ethanol blends do not, however,&#13;
impose the stringent requirements on handling and storage that methanol blends&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-120-&#13;
do, and adding ethanol to gasoline raises the octane number, so that energy&#13;
savings can be obtained in refining and/or by using higher-compression engines.&#13;
The octane-raising effect appears to give ethanol an effective fuel value about&#13;
equal to that of gasoline when used as a blend.&#13;
E. PHOTOVOLTAIC CELLS&#13;
27.       Today's most widely used solar or photovoltaic cells are made of&#13;
silicon (the second most abundant element in the earth's crust but very expensive&#13;
in the extremely pure form required for photovoltaic cells) and created by blending&#13;
controlled amounts of special impurities with the silicon to produce what is known&#13;
as a p-n junction. When the cell is exposed to sunlight, the p-n junction creates&#13;
an internal electric field that results in positive and negative charges being set&#13;
up on metal grids attached to opposite sides of the cell. The charged grids can be&#13;
connected through an external circuit, with the resulting flow of electricity&#13;
performing useful work. The cells are arranged in arrays and encapsulated for&#13;
protection. Photovoltaic devices can be extremely rugged and require very little&#13;
maintenance. The voltage produced is relatively constant, while the amperage&#13;
increases directly with increasing solar insolation.l/&#13;
28.       Solar cells are generally sized in terms of their peak power, that is,&#13;
the power achieved by the solar cell array under nearly optimum terrestrial&#13;
conditions. Cells in good sites produce 4-6 watt-hours daily per peak watt.&#13;
29.       Solar cells resembling those now in use were first developed in 1954&#13;
and later further developed for use in space programs throughout the 1960s up to&#13;
the present. Commercial terrestrial applications began on a small scale in 1973 and&#13;
have been expanding rapidly. Production of solar cells in 1977 amounted at 750 KW&#13;
peak and world cumulative production up to 1977 totalled some 2MW peak. Uses&#13;
include battery charging at remote forestry stations, military installations and&#13;
1/ However, photovoltaic performance generally decreases with temperature, so&#13;
concentrating systems require cooling as well as tracking mechanisms. It is&#13;
generally preferred to use photovoltaics in fixed, flat arrays and increase the&#13;
area rather than add cooling and tracking systems.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
cf fihore dr4':ling rigs. They are usen iLcc sfg-aL  !uoy  water 'Pri f_cation&#13;
plants, educatio-o&amp;. TV xeceivers, anc N:elc *coaic_ JccaC i.ons systeTi1s on an&#13;
economic basis and to powez refrigarato-rs and Ywctz_ pumps on a subsidized&#13;
demonstration basis, Figt1re YLI.3 ncnovirs c photo--voltaic vLllaga Power system0&#13;
30.       Due ^o advances tn techno½o-y adrl specci alty markets, 5srices of solar&#13;
cells have fallen from $300-$5000/peak :sa.i (-Jp- ) in the ea.rly -i370s to $14 WTIpk.&#13;
The U.S. Departinent of Energy nas e3; iiateE t ,-at the cost of ?hotovoltaic celLs&#13;
will drop to $0O50 per peak watt by 1:55   So "al½e ;balance of system'7 costs&#13;
including structural suaports, electrfical ci rcztity, batteriies anaa installation&#13;
presently cost about $15/IsWpk for maiy .p -cat-ions, however, ano there is no&#13;
immediate prospect that thie cost o, thesco components wil1l be re-tuced as rapidly&#13;
as that of the cells0  As the cost o f ceis ' 5 Cl:nes the numbezr E'd variety of&#13;
economic uses will increase.  The Cost decrease will be -especial`ly important&#13;
to uses which require lower than average "balance of system" costs. This would&#13;
include cases such as water pumpi-ng wh-re Lattery sto-age and much of the&#13;
electrical equipment can be dispensed wi..Ln ar oases in Ahich structural support&#13;
can be integrated into a building siLI; othnr  sZes-&#13;
7. SOLAR COOWCERS&#13;
31        Most solar cookers cons-sti ofT a oarabolic reflector toughly one meter&#13;
in diameter, a mechanism for aiming the, rcl-1fctor at the sun, and a support for&#13;
holding the cooking vessel at. :he l-ocai poiut0  Their posiLtion must be adjusted&#13;
every 15-30 minutes to follow the sun,&#13;
32.        Solar ovens require mo-re time .o prepare a meal because they do not&#13;
concentrate the sun as greatly as the parEbaloid reflector varieties.   However,&#13;
precisely because of this factor, they can be 12f, uDattended for longer periods&#13;
of time and can prepare meals even on days of variable cloudiness and occasional&#13;
haze.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-122-&#13;
OVWN a MU-{ - TUOW                V34 A&lt; - TinOow&#13;
Samo ls Mgygl 'AisnlONi I EVIw&#13;
saed~~~~~~~ z                       as  s usnnl&#13;
2 0               - @            E                        C =&#13;
R~~~~~~&#13;
R~~~~~~~~~~uJ                             4 L  .   i &#13;
.- ,-                              I&#13;
20                         2~~~~~ &#13;
H-&#13;
H4&#13;
H&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-123-&#13;
33.       Both the solar cooker and solar oven are amenable to local production,&#13;
but require reflective material such as mylar or aluminum.&#13;
34.       The solar cookers listed in Table II-1 range in cost from under $10 to&#13;
$100.&#13;
35.       Solar cookers and ovens have never been adapted on a large scale for a&#13;
variety of technical, economic, and cultural reasons. The key problem is that&#13;
cooking must be done in mid-day and outdoors. This inconvenience and their&#13;
initial cost has outweighed the fuel savings in attempts to popularize solar cookers.&#13;
This may suggest that the earliest market for solar cookers may be commercial&#13;
users (e.g., makers of beer and bread).&#13;
36.       If solar cookers and ovens were to be developed to the point where they&#13;
were routinely used to supplement or replace traditional fuels, the impact on&#13;
village life could be significant.   Time and energy normally spent searching&#13;
for fuel could be used in other ways.&#13;
37.       If a variety of standard solar cooker and oven designs were developed&#13;
which could be purchased cheaply or built locally and if they were locally acceptable,&#13;
then solar cooking could certainly serve a large number of developing country&#13;
families either as the chief cooking fuel or as a supplement. Solar radiation, in&#13;
either direct or diffuse form, is distributed generously around the globe, although&#13;
it varies from being in great abundance in areas such as the Sahel, where cookers&#13;
could be used most of the year, to areas of high tainfall and heavy cloud cover&#13;
such as in the Bight of Benin in tropical West Africa, where solar cookers would&#13;
be of much lower utility.&#13;
38.       Table 11-1   adapted from "A State of the ArtSurvey of Solar Powered&#13;
Irrigation Pumps, Solar Cookers, and Wood Burning Stoves for Use in Sub-Saharan&#13;
Africa" by Georgia Institute of Technology (January 1978) describes various&#13;
features of a number of solar cookers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-124-&#13;
TABLE II-1&#13;
COMPARISON OF SOLAR COOKER DESIGNS&#13;
0 0 4 N&#13;
.4 0.0  0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~                                        a01&#13;
'     -4                              C1 0                                      0&#13;
U)~~  ~~ /J b ItPXf    O       b1  b4  m1  b4 e    e0 &#13;
Cd  A. &gt;  ;  X &gt; a   e  o  e   e    &gt;a  e  z    40      c3                 40  40  40  41&#13;
41  U _  O 'C  J  C  0   0&#13;
&lt;..i  C 0_0 C0 b      0 D                  0    a&#13;
u  1-             I..  IN CO X                                                            Cl 0 0&#13;
C  u  X  I  .0                &gt;                     I 4&#13;
14         ¢~ 41  Q CJ- &gt;Ut1C                                                     C&#13;
C  -0 4  .&#13;
.'   0-   01441.0.o~~~~~  IN  0    '.4  410                               41 ~~to0 &#13;
0     411.  1.I. 4., .  IN  _0  .0     C        41   014           . b  214  e         o14  o 0  U&#13;
e   14 -4                              0   IN 1   1.*.. a c1                                a1&#13;
O w  0 la                                  4           4.4 4         0 4     4 C  O O   aa&#13;
0  0  .-4  ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~41M                                         41~~~~~~~~0'&#13;
cg 0 CO                               Z °  e                                   4°  &gt;   z &gt;   o 4&#13;
U 0 ,.     4                                                       .   ,&#13;
_I~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ Q  1 &#13;
N   0    0 l...v0 U 4 0 CN Q40                      41                                    0  .&#13;
14.  .40  0  41  41.-1410&gt;,o  '.  I  *  0  M ~~~~~~~~~~~0  U*I-.  14  .0  .0  14 ~~~~~~~0  41  U  403-&#13;
CZ   U   o    &gt; 4o.     0'   0     0               0    4 0     0     0  0   ..e 0X  1      . 0u&#13;
0L 0 41  ' -'* 0 1 0  0             0       -                   0   0     4  0     14 0   11. &#13;
!50                                   0    1 6      N c0  4- 0s&#13;
co Z ) cn   X   Oc &#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~4&#13;
4 0  C.&#13;
0  014  41 0     3                                                                  0&#13;
cn44                                                             1 C                        0 NO&#13;
1 4e  &lt;   =  e  0  0 4.4  0 144  0   4   o   ,%  0  4) 0&#13;
40                     a c&gt;                 0      Z1 &#13;
ca  ::                               co       00 4) ¢^  4c         49 cc c                  0 a p   o&#13;
41 &#13;
.41  0~~~~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
40     -   *ow                                                                             41n &#13;
40 4  A.0  414Ca 1410  41                                                                     4&#13;
,4 10                       C:              -0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~&#13;
.0                                                                .41~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
40 0.                                            U &#13;
x              c c                               o &#13;
0  -    GJw                                                                            4 0 w u ~ U i 2 ^ _ X U &gt;&gt; + c a 8 ~ .&#13;
-  0  waw    IN~~~~C  C                  u   0 &#13;
z  40 u~~~~~~~~.                                                0    04&#13;
Z  .000   00.-.0                           11      00           0&#13;
In  r,  v                            4c~~~~~~~~~~~~~.  4.-4  . 4  0   4   0 4   4&#13;
C     .0  '.1                                              ~&#13;
0  41 41~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
'.4   .00  41'..'  0  410   *  40             lC)0u&#13;
0  4.0  U404j410  0~~ .&gt;  0   4   4     &gt;4     I      0 a--'              ae&#13;
.J     v144110     I   Ci                          0-                0                       0&#13;
41  U41   UU                       4~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-4  C  0m .04W1     d 410  410      0.&#13;
410   '~~~   '~~   a W     4 .0   410      .     1   4                     0.&#13;
W                0 :, ~    ~    1   &#13;
~~4 0   0   4 1.4   '0   .    .            .   .0   4 1 0   .0   14  &gt; W   W             *  4.I&#13;
040   0   144.  ~   4'1   14   14   l~ Q1   14   0 ,U0     0     .4 1.   4     114&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
G.  SOIAR DR3iRS&#13;
39        Experience over some twenty years in    S~  furkey, Canada, Australia&#13;
Brazil, India, and Trinidad demonstratc&#142;s the potenk:ial for using s:7-plI solar&#13;
equipmen'&gt; for drying or curing meats, fzuit, vegetables, grains, tobacco, and&#13;
timber ei'tier directly in the colleci.o z or xtith dry air heated in flat plate&#13;
collectors and transported 'o a sepa-fa'  6nry."3'lg chamber0  The collsctors&#13;
toemselves are generally either shallow boxes of gfood (painted bKck on the&#13;
inside) withn sloping clear glass or plastic covers aimed at the su-Ln0&#13;
40.       With advances in technology and the rising costs of fuel, it may be&#13;
feasible to 'narness solar energy for controlled food dehydration instead of&#13;
depending on the traditional sun dryliig.&#13;
41.       Under favorable climatic conditions, simple sun drying 1,c) feasible&#13;
at low cost and without complicated equipment5   L;ut sun drying has the&#13;
following disadvantages:&#13;
a.  The traditional process is ur,contn.rllable, as it is at the&#13;
mercy of the elements.&#13;
b. Good quality of the product cannot be guaranteed.&#13;
c.  A large area is requirea for -,:"e drying purposes.  Irn sun drying of&#13;
fruits, approximately one h,ectare of drying sa-r:ce is required per 20 hectares of crop&#13;
land with an average yield0&#13;
d.  Sanitary conditions caPnot be controlLed, as the food can often be&#13;
contaminated by dust, insects, birds, and rodents. The quality of the product is&#13;
often reduced by beetle iiifestation dv.ring 6rying,&#13;
s0  Sun drying is time consumhng,&#13;
1/  Adapted from "Utilization of Solar Energy in Food Preservation"' by ToW. i4aembe&#13;
in Workshop on Solar Energy for the Villages of Africa, an NAS/Tanzania National&#13;
ScientIfic Research Council publicet'on, 19/8).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-126-&#13;
42.        To avoid these problems, wood is often used for smoking and drying&#13;
of fish and high value crops. However, traditional fish smoking by using wood&#13;
is reported to produce a product of low quality, and in the Philippines, for&#13;
example, the cost of fuel for curing tobacco has doubled over the last three&#13;
years for all major sources -- oil, firewood, and LPG. Plans are under way to&#13;
test solar equipment to supplement or replace conventional fuels in the tobacco&#13;
curing process. Timber drying in Australia using flat plate collectors has&#13;
proven to be only slightly more expensive than conventional drying with fossil fuels.&#13;
43*       Solar driers could be used by either individual families or by coops&#13;
or entrepreneurs at the village level. If costs can be kept low enough, the&#13;
benefits from solar driers could be significant in light of the potential for&#13;
overall increased availability of food, reduced costs for curing tobacco and&#13;
similar products if substitution for fuelwood can be accomplished, and possibly&#13;
improved income to farmers and fishermen as a result of better quality products&#13;
available to consumers.&#13;
H. SOLAR STILLS&#13;
44.       A solar still was used to produce water for the mules that provided&#13;
mechanical power at a mining operation in northern Chile for about 20 years&#13;
after it was built in about 1870. Solar distillation has been used more&#13;
recently in the U.S., USSR, Australia, and various Caribbean and Mediterranean&#13;
islands to provide drinking water, water for livestock, distilled water for&#13;
automotive batteries and other uses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
45.        Though there are numerous designs, a so12a S.' ," .o' :&gt;&#13;
of a black bottomed tray filled with brackish water and coved-fe  £y £ repfg&#13;
roof of glass or plastic sheet. Sunlight evaporates t"e-        D&#13;
condenses on the underside of the transparent cover and _rickcler cc\J&#13;
into a trough running along the bottom edge of the covez     Suv,c, a.-  ca&amp;&#13;
yield five liters of fresh water per square mzter of collectoT ^ach Gacyc&#13;
Lifetimes of stills have exceeded 20--30 yeazs with maintenance and oieras-tng&#13;
costs that are generally very low, dependlng upon t',.e design a'1d materials&#13;
used. Potential problems involve removing the de'hydrated resiu.e of tle Feed&#13;
water, the durability of the clear cover, corrosion and siltiLng.&#13;
46.        Solar distillation units can reportediy 1bn bouilta fo-r between&#13;
$15 and $30 per square meter, which with a capital recovery ratze of 10 to 20&#13;
percent annually implies capital costs of $1 to $4 pser cubic me*.c (thousand&#13;
liters) of water distilled.&#13;
I. Flat Plate Solar Water 1-1eaters&#13;
47.        The prototypical flat plate collector solar water Ii_ter consists&#13;
of a glass covered box through which water moves iLn tubes from tne bottom of&#13;
the collector up the face and on to a storage tank0   Hovemeit -_.y be by&#13;
convection or a pump may be used.&#13;
48.        Solar water heaters are widely used :n J7?, f aoe r&lt;e s End Australia.&#13;
Use on a commercial scale in developing countries iS limited a' C scattered, out&#13;
some countries such as Niger are beginning to p&#143;oduce and marke- solar wate-&#13;
heaters for use in clinics, hotels, and private homes,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-128-&#13;
49.       Simple metal and glass flat-plate collectors with insulated tanks&#13;
costs about $100-130 per square meter of collector. Auxiliary electric heating&#13;
and other back-up and pump systems for dependable hot water on demand&#13;
increase the cost substantially. Australian models average 1-1.5 square meters&#13;
of collector with 310 liter tanks, yielding up to 200 liters of hot water each&#13;
day, and are actively being marketed as exports, but are much more costly.&#13;
The typical Japanese solar hot water systems are more modest by comparison.&#13;
Water is both heated and stored          in wide, long, clear plastic tubes&#13;
covered with glass, yielding between 80-200 liters of warm water at the end&#13;
of the day for about $100-$150.&#13;
50.       Widespread use of solar water heaters   in developing countries need&#13;
not depend upon imported commercial devices.    Most developing countries&#13;
could manufacture their own solar water heaters from sheet metal, glass&#13;
and insulation materials. Solar water heaters have been developed in most&#13;
*countries where there is interest in solar energy technology, but the market&#13;
continues largely to be limited to commercial enterprises such as hotels,&#13;
affluent urban dwellers, and occasionally, rural clinics.&#13;
J . CONCENTRATING SOLAR WATER HEATERS&#13;
51.      Parabolic trough concentrating collectors reflect sunlight onto a&#13;
linear collector running along the focal line and moved on one axis to track the sun.&#13;
They are becoming commercially available to provide heat in the 100°C - 300°C range.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
.129-&#13;
in the US, solar generated process heat is being investigated for use in&#13;
factories in the canning, textile and bu".lding m-ateria'ls industrics, Prices&#13;
of systems range from as low as $50 pez square mete-.: of collector area to&#13;
as high as $240.&#13;
K. WIRThMILLS&#13;
52.       Windmills were widely used in fhs Netherlands, the UnitZd States&#13;
and elsewhere before being displaced oy ruzal se'ctrificetion based on&#13;
centralized generating systems.   Windvills can b2 used to pump water for&#13;
drinking, drainage or irrigation, to gr:nd g-, or to generate electricity&#13;
which can be used for a wider variety of appjlicatJons.&#13;
53.       Wind driven electric generacors are now available commsccially with&#13;
1/&#13;
up to fifteen kilowatts of rated power.    Larger i.vfits of up to tuo hundred&#13;
kilowatts are entering the demonstration 3tage in the United Stat-es.&#13;
54.       Wind power systems produce energy in a ti-me pattern determined by&#13;
the rise and fall of windspeed rather than oy de,mland. Practical applications&#13;
thus require one of (,- a batitery or other energy storage system, (b) inter-&#13;
connection with other generators whose cutput can ba controlled to meet the&#13;
discrepancy between fluctuations in demand and windmf11 output, cnd (c)    applications&#13;
which do not require a predictable or rellab'e supply, Included in the last groups&#13;
are applications such as water pumping in w'hicb an intermediate product (e.g. pumped&#13;
water) can be stored to mediate betw2en variat-ions in uindmill output and demand.&#13;
1/  The power produced by a windmill increas2s wlvth witid speed between a minimum&#13;
speed needed to overcome friction, etc, and the design wind speed, beyond which&#13;
output is approximately constant at the rated power level up to a windspeed at&#13;
which the windmill must be stopped as a safety measure0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-130-&#13;
55.        Windmills have been designed and built with a range of materials&#13;
and manufacturing requirements including designs appropriate for construction&#13;
by artisans as well as equipment that would have to be produced in a modern&#13;
industrial setting.&#13;
56.        Windmill system costs per unit output depend critically on the&#13;
design and size of the windmill and other equipment, and also on the wind&#13;
regime at the location where the windmill is installed. Cost estimates&#13;
prepared for water pumping systems indicate that some of the "appropriate&#13;
technology" designs can pump water at a cost equivalent to $0.15-0.20 per&#13;
kwh in areas with steady 15 mph winds. If experience confirms these estimates,&#13;
windmills would be competitive with conventional pumping systems in areas&#13;
with exceptionally favorable wind regimes and relatively high cost electrical&#13;
service options.&#13;
L. MICRO-HYDRO&#13;
57.        Waterwheels have been used for thousands of years in many areas,&#13;
primarily to grind grain. They represent known, reliable technologies, and&#13;
can be constructed in many cases by traditional skilled craftsmen. Waterwheels&#13;
are reported in fairly wide use today in mountainous areas of Afghanistan and&#13;
central and eastern Turkey. The more sophisticated water turbines, which operate&#13;
at much higher speeds, are most often used in hydro-electric generation. Modern&#13;
turbine systems with capacities of less than 50 kw have been installed in over&#13;
two dozen developing countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
580       Use of micro-hydro systems is apparently mos. widesprea6 °n P1 Chiina,&#13;
with more than 50,000 installations renorted as of 1974.    Aggreg2cXt- production&#13;
:l/&#13;
from these units is however only about 10 kcwh per capita per yea.-&#13;
59D       Overall efficiencies of miero-hydrosystems are roughly `0%D which&#13;
implies that about 600/v cubic meters (thousand liters) of water aze SequireFC&#13;
per kwh of electricity produced, where v is the height of the hy&amp;:uulic headc&#13;
(vertical drop) utilized in meters. Household clients of rural e±ectrification&#13;
projects typically consume roughly 105 kwh daily, so that with a 'aead of five&#13;
meters the water requirement works oui: to about 180 m3/day, ThiE flou wffould&#13;
cover 6.6 hectares to a depth of one meter over the course of a year.&#13;
,ountries.&#13;
60.       Unit costs of micro-hydro installations can be expectedc to vary wIdely as&#13;
they depend on the head and flow available, the cost of the civil works requir,eci&#13;
to bring the water to the turbine, the distance over which the e"lectricity pro6uced&#13;
needs to be carried out and the sophistication of the electrical controls requAired.&#13;
Prices quoted for turbines and generators renge from about $500 2:o $2000 per kly,&#13;
They are built in India, Nepal, PR China, and possibly other developing couvi.r:ztes&#13;
as well as in industrialized countries. Waternwaeeals are much   cheapeT and simpler&#13;
than turbines, but systems cost are higher and efficiency lower with waterw^hen-Js&#13;
than with turbines if output is to be in the form of electric-.'ty because of t'he great&#13;
gap in speed of rotation between the power produced by a waterwheei and that&#13;
required for an electric generator.&#13;
1/   Per capita consumption of electricity in PoR. China in 1974 was 148 kwh/cap.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-132-&#13;
61.      Small hydro installations for rural electrification can be expected&#13;
to be technically and economically viable in a relatively narrow range of&#13;
situations bounded by availability of the physical resource, ability and&#13;
willingness to invest the sums required, and competition from conventional&#13;
electrification alternatives. Waterwheels appear to be an alternative within&#13;
the reach of some low-income communities where the needed resource exists&#13;
and there is an important energy requirement for tasks such as grain grinding&#13;
that can be performed by a stationary, low r.p.m. power source.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
RECENT PAPERS IN THIS SERIES&#13;
No.                    TITLE OF PAPER                  AUTHOR&#13;
318    Sources of Fertility Decline:   Factor        R. Faruqee&#13;
Analysis of Inter-Country Data&#13;
319    Educational and Economic Effects of           W.D. Haddad&#13;
Promotion and Repetition Practices&#13;
320    Small Farmers and the Landless in             I.J. Singh&#13;
South Asia&#13;
321    Fruit and Vegetable Exports from the          R.D. Hunt&#13;
Mediterranean Area to the EEC&#13;
322    Ability in Pre-Schoolers, Earnings,           R. Grawe&#13;
and Home-Environment&#13;
323    Priorities in Education:   Pre-School;        M. Smilansky&#13;
Evidence and Conclusions                       (consultants)&#13;
324    Tropical Root Crops and Rural                 T. Goering&#13;
Development&#13;
325    Costs and Scale of Bus Services               A.A. Walters&#13;
326    Social and Cultural Dimensions of Tourism     R. Noronha&#13;
(consultant)&#13;
327    Investment in Indian Education:               S. Heyneman&#13;
Uneconomic&#13;
328    Nutrition and Food Needs in Developing        0. Knudsen&#13;
Countries                                     P.L. Scandizzo&#13;
329    The Changing International Division of        B. Balassa&#13;
Labor in Manufactured Goods&#13;
330    Application of Shadow Pricing to Country      L. Squire&#13;
Economic Analysis with an Illustration        I.M.D. Little&#13;
from Pakistan&#13;
331    A Survey of the Fertilizer Sector in India    B. Bumb (consultant)&#13;
332    Monitoring and Evaluation in the PIDER        M. Cernea&#13;
Rural Development Project -. Mexico&#13;
333    Determinants of Private Industrial            A. Pinell-Siles&#13;
Investment in India&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NO.                    TXTLE OF PX?ER                 AUTHOR&#13;
334    The "Graduation" Issue in Trade Policy      :c0 .?rank&#13;
Toward LDCs                                   consult...&#13;
335    Balancing Trickle Dowrn and Basi.cs Needs    K. Selous:&lt;y&#13;
Strategiesg Income Distribution&#13;
Issues in Large Middle- -Income Counities&#13;
with Special Reference to Lat:in America&#13;
336    Labor Force, Employment and L&amp;bor Markets    XJC Sq3uire&#13;
in the Course of Econoomic Development&#13;
337    The Population of Tha:iXland- Xts Growth     S. Cochralx&#13;
and Welfare&#13;
338    Capital Market Imperfections and             V.V. Ahat&#143;&lt;&#13;
Economic Development                         A.A. Roe&#13;
339    Behavior of Foodgrain Production             if. SarmnF&#13;
and Consumption in India, 19606 '11&#13;
340    Electric Power Pricing Policy                M O Munasi.nghe&#13;
341    State Intervention in the Industrializa7-    A- Choks.&#13;
tion of Developing Countries-. Selected&#13;
Issues&#13;
342    Policies for Efficient and Equitable            Yi Unn&#13;
Growth of Cities in Developinc; Countr.ies&#13;
343    The Capital Goods Sector in LDCso  A Case    JO Datta ytitra&#13;
for State Intervention?&#13;
344    International Technology Transfer   Issues   F. Stewart&#13;
and Policy Options&#13;
345    Family Planning ProgramsO  An Evaluation     R. Cuca&#13;
of Experience&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG3881.5 .W57 W67 no.346 c.3&#13;
Hughart, David.&#13;
Prospects for traditional and&#13;
non-conventional energy&#13;
sources in developing&#13;
DATE    NAME AND EXTENSION     ROOM&#13;
NUMBER&#13;
I~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~. __________&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1555078">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1979/07/1555078/prospects-traditional-non-conventional-energy-sources-developing-countries
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1979/07/1555078/prospects-traditional-non-conventional-energy-sources-developing-countries</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1979/07/1555078/prospects-traditional-non-conventional-energy-sources-developing-countries</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/06/21/000178830_98101903403095/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/06/21/000178830_98101903403095/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1979-07-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-06-21T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Prospects for traditional and
            non-conventional energy sources in developing countries
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper reviews the prospects for
            traditional and non-conventional energy sources in the
            developing countries through 1990. The evidence cited
            indicates widespread shortages of the traditional fuels on
            which an estimated one-half of the world's population
            relies for cooking and other energy needs. Collection of
            these fuels, which include firewood, charcoal, dung, and the
            inedible portions of agricultural crops, has become in some
            areas an important demand on the labor and cash resources of
            low-income groups as well as a threat to the soil resources
            on which agricultural development depends. Estimates of
            traditional fuel supply and demand are presented, but the
            data base in this field is too weak to allow much confidence
            to be placed in them. Non-conventional energy technologies,
            including biomass conversion, solar, wind and small-scale
            hydro are surveyed. It is suggested that many developing
            countries could usefully consider programs to increase
            fuelwood production, improve charcoal production techniques,
            raise cooking equipment efficiencies, survey and exploit
            wind and small hydro resources, and utilize combustible
            residuals from agro-industrial and forest-industrial plants.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Prospects for traditional and
            non-conventional energy sources in developing countries
        </docna>
        <display_title>Prospects for traditional and
            non-conventional energy sources in developing countries</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1979/07/1555078/prospects-traditional-non-conventional-energy-sources-developing-countries</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Crops and Crop Management Systems,Energy and Environment,Engineering,Montreal Protocol,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Environment</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>HUGHART, D.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903403095</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Other fuels</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 346</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Environment</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Oil &amp; Gas</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Agricultural wastes; Biomass energy;
            Charcoal; Deforestation; Desertification; Draught animals;
            Dung; Electrification; Energy resources; Fuels; Fuelwood;
            Hydroelectric power; Land clearing; Soil erosion; Solar
            energy; Supply; Wind energy
            agricultural activities,agricultural
            crops,agricultural productivity,agricultural
            residues,Agricultural Systems,air,animal feed,animal
            wastes,animals,arid zones,biomass,Butane,carrying
            capacity,cash crops,chaff,charcoal,Chemical
            fertilizers,coal,coffee,combustion,commercial
            energy,commercial fuels,conditioners,corn,crop,crop
            drying,crop processing,crop production,crop residues,Crop
            Wastes,crude oiL,crushing,cultivated
            land,cultivation,deforestation,desertification,developed
            countries,dung,economic
            development,ecosystem,ecosystems,effective
            use,elasticity,elasticity of demand,electric
            power,electricity,electrification,employment,energy
            consumption,energy problem,energy resources,energy
            sources,energy supply,energy systems,energy
            technologies,energy use,engines,environmental
            costs,environmental
            damages,equilibrium,falling,FAO,Farm,farmer,farmers,farms,fertilizer,fertilizers,floods,food
            production,food supply,Forestry,fruits,fuel,fuel
            supply,fuels,fuelwood,grain,Harvesting,harvesting
            equipment,Heat,heating,hectares of land,household
            sector,hydro power,hydro
            resources,income,irrigation,irrigation canals,jute,land
            tenure,levees,meat,mechanical energy,nitrogen,nutrients,oil
            prices,Organic Wastes,paddy,pesticides,petroleum,petroleum
            products,Planting,plowing,pressure,produce,Propane,pumps,Recycling,refrigeration,reservoirs,Rice,Rice
            straw,river basins,runoff,rural communities,Rural
            Energy,salt,seed,seedlings,single crop,soil
            conditioners,Soils,solar energy,spices,straw,subsistence
            agriculture,sugar,sugar cane,tea,tea industry,tobacco,total
            energy demand,trees,tropical forests,vegetative cover,water
            storage,wind energy,windmills
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP346</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Demand</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock and Animal Husbandry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Integrated Pest Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pest Control</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pesticides</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forest and Forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Electricity Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Windpower</ml:concept><ml:concept>Degraded Lands</ml:concept><ml:concept>Desertification</ml:concept><ml:concept>Dry Lands</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drylands &amp; Desertification</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops and Crop Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Communities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Animal Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forests</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pest Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Solar Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wind Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drylands</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>