<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Shadow Prices for Project Appraisal FILE COPI&#13;
in Turkey&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 392                                     SWP392&#13;
May 1980&#13;
- Prepared by: Afsaneh Mashayekhi (Consultant)&#13;
Country Programs Department II&#13;
Europe, Middle East and North Africa Region&#13;
Copyright e 1980&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the&#13;
authors and should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its&#13;
affiliated organizations, or to any individual acting in their behalf.                   aw Li  LF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations,&#13;
or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 392&#13;
May 1980&#13;
SHADOW PRICES FOR PROJECT APPRAISAL IN TURKEY&#13;
This paper is a study of the shadow prices to be used for project&#13;
appraisal in Turkey. It arrives at estimates of various efficiency pricing&#13;
and social pricing parameters taking into account the Turkish import and&#13;
export regime and the objectives of the Government.&#13;
Prepared by: Afsaneh Mashayekhi (consultant)&#13;
Country Programs Department II&#13;
Europe, Middle East and North Africa Region&#13;
Coyright    J  1980&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
SHADOW PRICES FOR PROJECT APPRAISAL IN TURKEY&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
I.   INTRODUCTION ..........................................          1&#13;
II.    SUMMARY OF ESTIMATION RESULTS AND POLICY&#13;
IMPLICATIONS  ........................................        5&#13;
Conversion Factors ...................................          7&#13;
Marginal Productivity of Capital .....................          8&#13;
Social Pricing Parameters ............................          8&#13;
Shadow  Wage  Rates  ....................................       9&#13;
Policy Implications ..................................         10&#13;
III.   EFFICIENCY PRICING PARAMETERS IN TURKEY ....         ..........  11&#13;
Import  Regime  ........................................       13&#13;
Export  Regime  ........................................       15&#13;
Estimation of Conversion Factors .....................         16&#13;
Standard Conversion Factor ...........................         17&#13;
Conversion Factor for Consumption Goods ....        ..........  22&#13;
Conversion Factor for Intermediate Goods ....        .........  24&#13;
Conversion Factor for Capital Goods ....         ...............  26&#13;
Marginal Productivity of Capital .....................         29&#13;
IV.    SOCIAL PRICING PARAMETERS IN TURKEY ....        ..............  35&#13;
Government Objectives ................................         35&#13;
Consumption Rate of Interest, (CRI) ....         ..............  36&#13;
Value of Public Income ...............................         38&#13;
The Critical Consumption Level, (CCL) ....        ............  40&#13;
The Accounting Rate of Interest, ARI ....         .............  41&#13;
The Consumption Distribution Weights ....         .............  43&#13;
V.    SHADOW WAGE RATE ESTIMATES ...........................        47&#13;
Population, Labor Force and Employment ....        ............  47&#13;
Trends In Real Wages .................................         48&#13;
Social and Efficiency Wages ..........................         51&#13;
Estimations of Shadow Wages ..........................         54&#13;
This paper is a study of the Shadow Prices for Project Appraisal in Turkey.&#13;
I am grateful to Arshad Zaman who initiated and encouraged this study. I would&#13;
like to thank Shakil Faruqi for very valuable comments on the subject matter&#13;
of the paper and the methodological content and Adrian Wood for helpful&#13;
discussions on estimation procedures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. INTRODUCTION&#13;
1.        This paper describes the analytic and empirical basis for the&#13;
estimation of shadow prices which may be used for the evaluation of projects&#13;
in Turkey in the next five years. The fundamental ideas behind the methodology&#13;
adopted in this study were developed by Little and Mirrlees l/ and extended by&#13;
Squire and van der Tak 2/. Economic analysis of projects in order to assess&#13;
their likely impact on the relevant development objectives is carried out&#13;
through a comparison of the various ways in which scarce resources required by&#13;
the project might be used instead. The basic idea of project appraisal can be&#13;
set out briefly. The project is first analyzed into detailed commodity and&#13;
labor flows with numerical quantities assigned to them and each quantity&#13;
converted into a value through multiplication by a price. The total value of&#13;
outputs less the total value of inputs (discounting future values) is the&#13;
present value of the project. The application of the traditional efficiency&#13;
approach (TEP) essentially involves the steps mentioned above and translation&#13;
of all projects costs and benefits into domestic prices.&#13;
2.        The new methodology generally referred to in the literature as&#13;
the extended efficiency approach (EEP) uses conversion factors in order to&#13;
translate all costs and benefits into border prices. Thus it has the added&#13;
advantage of allowing for distortions in prices between the domestic market&#13;
and border prices. In the present context given that project analysis is&#13;
supposed to assess costs and benefits in the same unit a common 'numerairet is&#13;
used. The 'numeraire' adopted by Little-Mirrlees and Squire-van der Tak is&#13;
freely disposable, i.e., uncommitted, foreign exchange in the hands of the&#13;
government. It is basically a foreign exchange numeraire but expressed in&#13;
terms of units of the local currency (Turkish Liras) converted at the official&#13;
rate of exchange.&#13;
3.        In the idealized world of perfect competition the simple rule that&#13;
prices of goods and services should be set equal to marginal costs leads to an&#13;
efficient allocation of resources. This situation ensures optimality for a&#13;
given income distribution, when no one can be made better off without reducing&#13;
someone else's welfare. Moreover, given the compensation principle, as long&#13;
as aggregate benefits exceed aggregate costs, the efficiency criteria is met&#13;
and the beneficiaries of the project can (at least in theory) compensate the&#13;
losers 3/. However, in the real world, distortions occur in prices and income&#13;
distribution which are found objectionable in terms of efficiency and equity&#13;
considerations. Given the usual convexity assumptions, increasing shadow&#13;
prices exist although there are disagreements over the possibility of finding&#13;
1/   I.M.D. Little and J.A. Mirrlees, Project Appraisal and Planning for&#13;
Developing Countries, Basic Books, New York, 1974.&#13;
2/   L. Squire and H.G. van der Tak, Economic Analysis of Projects, World&#13;
Bank, John Hopkins Press, Baltimore, 1975.&#13;
3/   For a discussion of the welfare optimum in the context of shadow pricing&#13;
see: E.J. Mishan, Cost-Benefit Analysis, Praeger, New York, 1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
them mainly due to data problems. The technical literature on shadow prices&#13;
derives shadow pricing rules from the first order conditions from an optimiza-&#13;
tion model and this results in rules that link production to international&#13;
trade. While informational problems as regards tradable goods are surmount-&#13;
able given the small country assumption the case of non-tradable goods poses&#13;
serious practical problems 1/.&#13;
4.         Shadow prices are defined as the increase in welfare resulting from&#13;
any marginal change in the availability of commodities or factors of produc-&#13;
tion. According to the Little-Mirrlees rule the shadow price of a factor is&#13;
precisely the value of output forgone when this factor is marginally, that is&#13;
infinitesimally, withdrawn at the distorted market prices with the valuation&#13;
carried out at international prices. The shadow pricing methodology is based&#13;
on the premise that relative border prices correctly reflect relative shadow&#13;
prices--a result which is true for a wide class of general equilibrium models.&#13;
5.        Until recently, traditional methods of appraisal have emphasized the&#13;
growth objective and been mainly concerned with the national income parameter.&#13;
Many economists would agree that project analysis is intended to ensure that&#13;
the available resources yield the maximum increment in total national income&#13;
and other tools such as fiscal policy are to be used to bring about the&#13;
optimum income distribution. The problem, however, is first the well known&#13;
impossibility of optimal lump-sum taxation and more specifically in the case&#13;
of most developing countries the inefficiency and weakness of the tax system.&#13;
More recently, it has been argued that the operational assumption that all&#13;
units of income make the same contribution to growth may be untenable. The&#13;
World Bank and others advocate a more consistent and systematic estimation&#13;
method that takes explicit account of the impact of the project on the distri-&#13;
bution of income both between investment and consumption and among different&#13;
groups in the society. The validity of this new approach is to some extent&#13;
dependable on the extent to which the government is free to determine the&#13;
desired level of investment and affect income distribution by means of fiscal&#13;
and monetary policy. As already mentioned, the social economic and political&#13;
constraints in developing countries limit the use of these policies and social&#13;
pricing becomes a more useful concept. Mirrlees has argued that distribution&#13;
and efficiency can 1be operated in the social management of the economy 2/.&#13;
However, even in this framework he allows for some aspects of benefit-cost&#13;
analysis which can allow for distributional objectives by systematic applica-&#13;
tion of welfare weighting; both weighting private consumption relative to&#13;
public expenditure and the incomes of people in different income quintiles.&#13;
A point that needs to be emphasized is that the dichotomy between equity and&#13;
growth issues has been exaggerated. There is indeed evidence that extreme&#13;
1/   For an interesting exposition of the information problem refer to:&#13;
Peter Warr, "Shadow Pricing: information and stability in a simple open&#13;
economy", Quarterly Journal of Economics, Vol. XCII, 1978, pp. 95-116.&#13;
2/   J.A. Mirrlees, "Social Benefit-Cost Analysis and the Distribution of&#13;
Income", World Development, Vol. 6, No. 2, 1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
poverty and inequality may affect the growth objectives. The nutrition&#13;
studies carried out do show the positive link between nutrition (income) and&#13;
productivity of the labor force. However, the point made by Mirrlees is&#13;
well-taken; obviously wasteful projects should not be undertaken merely on&#13;
distribution grounds.&#13;
6.         Social pricing has the advantage of bringing all available informa-&#13;
tion from sector and other studies to bear on policy analysis. The shadow&#13;
pricing system used in this study constitutes an informal attempt to capture&#13;
general equilibrium effects and embody them in the particular national&#13;
parameters. In the context of a general equilibrium model, the shadow price&#13;
of a given input represents the change in the value of the national objective&#13;
function due to a marginal change in the availability of that input, subject&#13;
to a set of distorting constraints 1/. The lack of any estimates of these&#13;
numbers in earlier work has limited the significance and usefulness of the&#13;
parameters 2/. The estimation of shadow prices has also been shown to be&#13;
useful in reflecting areas where additional information or more refined&#13;
estimates are required 3/. Inclusion of estimates such as the social value of&#13;
public income which is an explicit attempt to capture some of the general&#13;
equilibrium effects of changes in public sector expenditure has made this&#13;
approach more useful.&#13;
7.        One further advantage of the more explicit approach now adopted by&#13;
the Bank is that by using efficiency prices parameters are derived that are&#13;
restricted to correcting for price distortions introduced by market imperfec-&#13;
tions. Social prices on the other hand provide a separate analytical frame-&#13;
work to incorporate social objectives such as the trade-off between growth and&#13;
equity. The efficiency pricing approach implicitly assumes certain drastic&#13;
value judgments (discussed in the main text) particularly regarding the&#13;
optimality of growth and income distribution. Social pricing, however,&#13;
1/   See P. Dasgupta and J. Stiglitz, "Benefit-Cost Analysis and Trade&#13;
Problems", Journal of Political Economy, Vol. 82, 1974, pp. 1-33.&#13;
2/   The partial equilibrium method used in project analysis has been critic-&#13;
ized on the basis on non-marginality, for its lack of simultaneity and&#13;
because of the judgment involved in choosing which linkages are to be&#13;
analyzed and which are neglected when the impact of some disturbance is&#13;
to be evaluated. While in principle these objectives can be met by an&#13;
iterative process of successive approximation, in practice this has&#13;
proved difficult to accomplish.&#13;
3/   This issue together with general equilibrium effects have been discussed&#13;
in an interesting fashion by L. Squire, I. Little and Durdag "Applications&#13;
of Shadow Pricing - Country Economic Analysis with an illustration from&#13;
Pakistan". They have incorporated shadow prices into a more general&#13;
study of country dates and insisted upon adoption of cost-benefit method-&#13;
ology to the particular country in such a way to call attention to&#13;
general equilibrium issues.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
allows systematic consideration of alternative sets of value judgments.&#13;
Within very wide limits, differences in value judgments make little differ-&#13;
ence to many aspects of social benefit-cost analysis. Of course, some assump-&#13;
tions are required, but only limited government rationality need be assumed.&#13;
The arguments concerning one method being objective and the other being&#13;
'subjective' are discussed below. It is enough to mention at this point that&#13;
given that few countries have shown optimal growth and income distribution&#13;
performances, the assumptions underlying efficiency prices would be overly&#13;
restrictive. 1/ In terms of Squire-van der Tak, these judgments imply setting&#13;
all the marginal distribution parameters, as well as 6 equal to unity, in&#13;
which case net social benefit equals net efficiency benefit. 2/ Moreover, the&#13;
efficiency approach assumes the economy does not face a foreign exchange&#13;
constraint. In the case of present day Turkey, this is obviously unrealistic,&#13;
and makes the approach more unsuitable than it would be otherwise. 3/&#13;
1/   This approach which is seemingly an objective one makes the implicit&#13;
judgment that at the margin savings and consumption are equally valuable&#13;
the existing income distribution is optimal, and there is no foreign&#13;
exchange constraint.&#13;
2/   0 is equivalent to the standard conversion factor and to the value of&#13;
public income.&#13;
3/   It is often asserted that efficiency prices are 'objective' measures&#13;
whereas social prices require the use of 'subjective' methods of analysis.&#13;
This does miss the fact that simple opportunity cost measure may mis-&#13;
represent the resource costs that result from changes in the patterns of&#13;
household expenditure. The absence of a social premium on savings&#13;
relative to consumption seems quite inconsistent with the interest of&#13;
people involved in choice of technique and project appraisal in the&#13;
magnitude of the savings premium. The claim that this is really a&#13;
distributional effect is mistaken since it implies that the social&#13;
discount rate should always be equal to the marginal rate of return&#13;
on new investment evaluated at efficiency prices which is at variance&#13;
with the results of the theory of planning and optimal growth. These&#13;
points imply that traditional efficiency prices do not represent a&#13;
consistent or appropriate basis for evaluating projects, even if one&#13;
wishes to abstract from distributional effects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 5 -&#13;
II. SUMMARY OF ESTIMATION RESULTS AND&#13;
POLICY IMPLICATIONS&#13;
8.        In this section, some methodological issues as well as the estimation&#13;
results are summarized 1/. Moreover, there is a brief discussion of their&#13;
interpretation and use which is of particular interest to the project analyst&#13;
though the generalist may also find it instructive. Some familiarity with the&#13;
work of Little-Mirrlees 2/ and Squire-van der Tak 3/ as well as the country&#13;
report, Turkey: Policies and Prospects for Growth 4/ is assumed. The recent&#13;
work done in the preparation of the report as well as the general equilibrium&#13;
model developed for Turkey have provided useful information for estimation&#13;
purposes 5/. In particular various market distortions which have always been&#13;
a major shortcoming in calculation of conversion factors have been quantified&#13;
in Turkey. Therefore, it can be claimed that the estimates derived for Turkey&#13;
are reliable due to the availability of information. Other sources used for&#13;
information on the balance of payments are the "Monthly Bulletin", published&#13;
by the State Institute of Statistics, and the 'Monthly Economic Indicators',&#13;
the Ministry of Finance. The recent IMF and World Bank mission reports have&#13;
also provided useful information. Moreover, the Turkish Fourth Plan (1979-1983)&#13;
has been valuable in particular as regards providing information on government&#13;
plans and objectives which are important factors used in social benefit-cost&#13;
analysis. In many instances the existence of additional data and use of dif-&#13;
ferent approaches have provided different values for the national parameters,&#13;
however, in many instances these are similar to previous estimates.&#13;
9.        It remains to be said that the policy recommendations derived from&#13;
the shadow prices prescribed in this paper should be regarded with some&#13;
reserve. There still remain major informational gaps and the existence of&#13;
additional data would allow many conceptual problems to be resolved and also&#13;
allow estimation of additional parameters such as conversion factors for&#13;
non-tradable goods, separate measures for the marginal productivity of capital&#13;
1/   A more thorough examination of the methodology and the estimation pro-&#13;
cedures occupies us extensively in Sections III, IV and V.&#13;
2/   I.M.D. Little and J.A. Mirrlees, (1974).&#13;
3/   L. Squire and H.G. van der Tak, (1975).&#13;
4/   Turkey:   Policies and Prospects for Growth, The World Bank,1980 (Forthcoming).&#13;
5/   K. Dervis and S. Robinson, "The Foreign Exchange Gap, Growth and Indus-&#13;
trial Strategy in Turkey: 1973-1983", World Bank Staff Working Paper&#13;
No. 302, 1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6-&#13;
in the public and private sectors and disaggregated shadow prices for major&#13;
inputs. However, it is necessary to point out that the parameters already&#13;
estimated do provide the basic structure and information required for the&#13;
purposes of project analysis. It also is the case that the methodology used&#13;
in this study makes it relatively simple to extend or even disaggregate the&#13;
set of shadow prices to meet the need of specific project appraisals. Finally,&#13;
it is important to stress that the shadow price estimates presented ought to&#13;
be updated at regular intervals particularly if there are major changes in&#13;
economic policy. The work of updating is also relatively simple and need only&#13;
focus on changes in areas of policy which have a direct impact on accounting&#13;
ratios.&#13;
Table 1: SUMMARY OF NATIONAL PARAMETERS&#13;
Parameters                                            Value&#13;
Standard Conversion Factor (SCF)                                   0.59&#13;
Conversion Factor for Consumption Goods (CF )                      0.79&#13;
Conversion Factor for Intermediate Goods (CF )                     0.55&#13;
Coversion Factor for Capital    Goods (CF )                        0.52&#13;
Marginal Product of Capital, q                                       12%&#13;
Elasticity of Marginal Utility, n                                     1&#13;
Rate of Pure Time Preference,                                        2&#13;
Consumption Rate of Interest (CRI)                                  4.5%&#13;
Value of Public Income, v                                           3.4&#13;
Critical Consumption Level:&#13;
Rural, 1973 TL                                               1,208&#13;
Urban, 1973 TL                                               4,524&#13;
Critical consumption level as a&#13;
ratio of national per capita&#13;
average income                                                      37%&#13;
Accounting Rate of Interest (ARI)                                    5%&#13;
The Summary Distribution Measure, D                                  1&#13;
Shadow Wage Rates (SP1): /1&#13;
Rural Sector                                                  0.56&#13;
Urban Informal Sector                                         0.55&#13;
Urban Formal Sector                                           0.57&#13;
/1   SP1 - see Section V for details.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
Conversion Factors&#13;
10.       Table I illustrates the estimates of the main national parameters&#13;
required for social benefit-cost analysis. The standard conversion factor and&#13;
the conversion factors for consumption, intermediate and capital goods were&#13;
derived using the c.i.f. border prices for imports, the f.o.b. border price of&#13;
exports after adjustment for import taxes, export rebates as well as 'domestic&#13;
user costs' 1/. The various methods used did give similar results but the&#13;
results quoted use the main Squire/van der Tak equation for conversion fac-&#13;
tors 2/. Following an extensive analysis of the Turkish economy, the premium&#13;
rate used in adjusting for the divergence of the c.i.f. and tariff price and&#13;
the domestic price of goods prior to the June 1979 devaluation was 90 per-&#13;
cent. The devaluation is expected to have a net positive effect but cannot be&#13;
depended upon to solve the structural problems of the economy on its own. The&#13;
stabilization and trade policies will be very important policy variables which&#13;
will also take time to become fully effective. The ambitious investment&#13;
plans, national income growth rate, and industrialization program outlined in&#13;
the Fourth Plan require continued large imports of intermediate and capital&#13;
goods. The present state of affairs which is expected to change slowly and&#13;
evidence on the recent past, however, imply that the above plans will lead to&#13;
some rationing and shortages although at a smaller scale. The previous rate&#13;
applicable to the results in (Table 1) is 60 percent and is consistent with&#13;
the projections of the general equilibrium model 3/. Sensitivity analysis is&#13;
carried out in Tables 5, 7, 9 and ll to show the results of no distortions as&#13;
well as a situation of extreme shortage similar to 1978.&#13;
11.       The standard conversion factor is 0.59.    If we allow for a premium&#13;
rate of 90 percent the shadow exchange rate of TL 47.2 to the U.S. dollars is&#13;
derived which is equal to the post (June 1979) devaluation rate and there-&#13;
therefore increases confidence in our results. The conversion factor for&#13;
consumption goods (CF ) is higher than that for intermediate and capital goods&#13;
(CFI, CFK). It does reflect the serious import rationing due to the supply-&#13;
1/   See the main text for a discussion on the domestic user cost which is&#13;
substantial in Turkey.&#13;
2/           (m +   x)             see Section III for details.&#13;
M(1 + tm + TM) + x(l - tx)&#13;
where M   - imports&#13;
X  - exports&#13;
tm - import taxes&#13;
tx - export taxes&#13;
TM - premium rate&#13;
3/   K. Dervis and S. Robinson, "The Foreign Exchange Gap, Growth and Indus-&#13;
trial Strategy in Turkey: 1973-1983", World Bank Staff Working Paper No.&#13;
306, 1978, (See T-1 run of the model).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
demand gap in the latter two markets. The conversion factor for consumption&#13;
goods is dominated by the export side which seemingly does not have the same&#13;
problems and therefore the border value and market value are not as widely&#13;
divergent as is the case in the intermediate and capital goods market.&#13;
Marginal Productivity of Capital&#13;
12.       Various methods were used to derive the marginal product of capital.&#13;
Turkey is one of the few developing countries with reliable data on capital&#13;
stock. It was, therefore, possible to use the production function approach&#13;
and run regression equations to derive the marginal product of capital&#13;
directly. 1/ There is a wide divergence of results depending on the methodology&#13;
used. The micro approach does give a rough range, however, given the seg-&#13;
mentation and imperfection of the capital market we based results on the&#13;
macro approach. In the case of Turkey, the macro data allowed estimation of a&#13;
value for the marginal product of capital equal to 12 percent. It is necessary&#13;
to point out that the provision of additional data to enable the estimation of&#13;
separate values of q for the public sector and the private sector would be&#13;
very useful given the particular structure of the Turkish economy.&#13;
Social Pricing Parameters&#13;
13.       The consumption rate of interest (CRI) was derived to be equal to&#13;
4.5 on the basis of the growth of consumption per capita, elasticity of&#13;
marginal utility and the rate of time preference. The latter two parameters&#13;
were based on the decisions and plans of the Turkish government as embodied in&#13;
the Fourth Plan. The accounting rate of interest (ARI) is an important concept&#13;
in social pricing since it provides the discount rate for public investments.&#13;
The value of 6 implies that public sector projects with a social rate of&#13;
return above 6 are justifiable given the growth objectives. The figure does&#13;
allow Turkey to be committed to its growth objective but also allows weeding&#13;
out inferior projects.&#13;
14.       The value of public income (v) was estimated to be 3.4 which is&#13;
quite high. It does, nonetheless, reinforce the 'etatist' position taken by&#13;
authorities in Turkey. It is also a reflection of the status quo position&#13;
which favors the state intervention in economic life 2/.     The estimates for&#13;
the critical consumption level and the consumption distribution weights are&#13;
all indicative of inequality and large scale poverty in Turkey. Poverty is&#13;
1/   The results do illustrate a high estimate of the marginal product of&#13;
capital, however, they were derived too late to be included in this&#13;
version.&#13;
2/   It is also consistent with the recent plans for increasing the share of&#13;
public investment in total investment which reinforces faith in the above&#13;
results and makes the social parameters more reliable from the project&#13;
analyst's point of view.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
more concentrated in rural areas. The consumption distribution measure for the&#13;
lowest quintile is equal to 8 and the weight attached to the lowest population&#13;
quintile is 3 which is indicative of the importance of undertaking more measures&#13;
as regards the distribution of income. The information on the spread of basic&#13;
needs programs indicates progress in fields such as education and health. The&#13;
value of consumption distribution measures for the second quintile also reinforces&#13;
the critical consumption level estimates 1/.&#13;
Shadow Wage Rates&#13;
15.       The shadow wages estimates in the table are based on social shadow&#13;
pricing procedures (SP1) that attaches a value of 1 to the marginal distribu-&#13;
tion measure, and disregards the disutility of effort and loss of leisure&#13;
arising from extra employment. Marginal productivity of labor is measured by&#13;
output forgone in alternative employment. The shadow wage for the urban&#13;
informal sector is based on the assumption that the urban rate of unemployment&#13;
remains constant because of its role as an equilibrating mechanism. We have,&#13;
therefore, estimated separate shadow wage rates for rural and urban sectors,&#13;
the latter being further disaggregated according to whether or not the labor&#13;
is employed in sectors where there is an element of wage control. 2/ The&#13;
tracditional efficiency approach has provided the lowest estimates, and the&#13;
extended efficiency approach by adding the consumption costs arising out of&#13;
employment has provided the highest estimates. Once the social benefits of&#13;
consumption are allowed for (through the use of social pricing), a reasonable&#13;
set of shadow wage rate estimates are derived. There is also very little&#13;
difference between the three sectors and the accounting ratios are in the&#13;
range 0.55-0.57. These results lend support to choice of labor intensive&#13;
projects and techniques of production.&#13;
1/   At the critical consumption level, d = v.CF     and therefore, v.CF /d = 1;&#13;
namely at the second quintile.               c                     c&#13;
2/   The rationale for this categorization is outlined in Section V.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
Policy Implications&#13;
16.       It is interesting to note the correspondence of the pattern of&#13;
national parameters estimated for Turkey and the classic import substitution&#13;
model developed by Little, Scitovsky and Scott 1/ and Balassa et al. 2/ The&#13;
Turkish Government's policy of adopting higher import duties, an overvalued&#13;
exchange rate, and substantial investment incentives which have been heavily&#13;
subsidizing capital costs relative to labor costs (consequently higher -&#13;
ratios) has been responsible for creating a distorted market. The 'signaling'&#13;
mechanism provided by the price system is no longer functional. Rationing in&#13;
goods and capital markets also implies that market prices no longer reflect&#13;
relative scarcities.&#13;
17.       The industrial sector has grown in response to market incentives&#13;
which bear little relation to the social value of producing different goods.&#13;
There has also been negative discrimination against export-oriented activities.&#13;
The Government incentive schemes e.g. tax rebates, are intended to encourage&#13;
development of manufacturing for exports. However, first the scale is rela-&#13;
tively small, secondly, the administration is based on a complex system. The&#13;
goods affected also change continually and there is some uncertainty regarding&#13;
rebate payments which has not been conducive to export oriented activities.&#13;
1/ Scott, et al., Industry and Trade in Some Developing Countries, 1970.&#13;
2/ Balassa et al., The Structure of Protection in Developing Countries, 1971.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
III. EFFICIENCY PRICING PARAMETERS IN TURKEY&#13;
18.       In this section we estimate the standard conversion factor (SCF),&#13;
and the conversion factors (CF's) for tradables as grouped into the categories&#13;
of consumption, intermediate and capital goods. 1/ These estimates provide&#13;
the multiplier used for conversion from the market values to values at shadow&#13;
prices which following the Little-Mirrlees methodology is measured by border&#13;
prices. Various distortions contribute to the divergence of domestic prices&#13;
from border prices. The import and export taxes account for some of the&#13;
market imperfections that affect the above estimates. Rapid growth and the&#13;
economic policies followed in Turkey have brought about non-tariff distortions&#13;
that by far outweigh the import taxes. During the years 1978 and 1979, the&#13;
"domestic cost elements" such as rent seeking activities and the cost of&#13;
rationing, have been more than three times the average import tax rate.&#13;
19.       The experience of rapidly growing developing economies indicates&#13;
that the unbalanced nature of growth and its speed create serious shortages in&#13;
the goods market. The formal import regime is not always a good indicator of&#13;
all the distortions that affect market prices.    In the case of Turkey consider-&#13;
able work that has been done in the preparation of the country report 2/ and&#13;
the general equilibrium growth and trade model, hereafter referred to 'is the&#13;
TGT model, 3/ have provided more information on various market distortions.&#13;
The conversTon factors that have been estimated have drawn upon the relevant&#13;
data on import/export taxes as well as other domestic cost elements and,&#13;
therefore, claim to be reasonable measures reflecting the divergence of&#13;
domestic prices from border prices in Turkey. In this section a brief review&#13;
of the import and export regimes will be followed by a study of other market&#13;
imperfections and their implications as regards the estimation of conversion&#13;
factors. Finally, the effect of devaluation on the conversion factors will be&#13;
studied. In the TGT model, total imports are set equal to total foreign&#13;
exchange earnings. Capital flows are given exogenously and total imports are&#13;
determined by total exports and are, therefore, not equal to desired imports. 4/&#13;
The model outlines a quantity adjustment mechanism that closely resembles&#13;
what took place in Turkey during the last few years and also takes into&#13;
account general equilibrium affects. The scarcity value of the imported goods&#13;
1/   The input-output information for Turkey does not provide a detailed break-&#13;
down of inputs that go into the production of non-tradable goods. Specific&#13;
conversion factors for major non-tradables, e.g., construction and trans-&#13;
portation cannot be calculated on the basis of available information and&#13;
the SCF can be used as a rough approximation.&#13;
2/   Turkey: Policies and Prospects for Growth, The World Bank, 1980 (Forthcoming).&#13;
3/   K. Dervis and S. Robinson, (1978).&#13;
4/   S. Robinson and K. Dervis; "The Foreign Exchange Gap Growth and Industrial&#13;
Strategy in Turkey: 1973-1983", World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 306&#13;
(1978).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
is generally much higher than the c.i.f. and tariff price. Import users are&#13;
off their demand curves at prevailing user prices and desired imports are&#13;
higher than actual realized imports. The import prices appear implicitly in&#13;
the profits made by producers and other license holders. A simple allocation&#13;
rule that is a reasonable approximation to the real situation rations foreign&#13;
exchange in proportion to desired imports. The model also assumes that&#13;
illegal or semi-legal means of resale exist and for certain intermediate&#13;
goods, very high premiums are being realized. The T-1 run of the model which&#13;
outlines the more pessimistic view namely that future performance will be&#13;
similar to the Third Plan period uses a premium of 90 percent for 1978 and&#13;
98.8 percent for 1979. Its projections for the rest of the plan period up to&#13;
1983 are within the range 55-60 percent. The country report 1/ also takes a&#13;
premium rate of 90 percent to be a reasonable adjustment. In the estimation&#13;
of conversion factors that follow, when allowance is made for the premium, the&#13;
shadow exchange rate derived is equal to the new official rate (post June 1979&#13;
devaluation rate) namely TL 47.2 to the US dollar.&#13;
20.       However, our choice of the premium rate depends on the trade and&#13;
stabilization policies followed by the Government. The rate to be used in&#13;
future project appraisal should allow for a consideration of the prospects&#13;
of the Turkish economy over the next five years. It is important to notice&#13;
that all projections of the premium are conditional upon the success of the&#13;
specific policy package followed by the Government. The recent devaluation&#13;
through its effects on resource reallocation, capacity utilization and capital&#13;
accumulation is expected to have a net positive effect. The high exchange&#13;
rate policy if successful will bring'about a real change in the economy and&#13;
reduce structural disequilibrium as well as the foreign exchange gap. The&#13;
Fourth Plan also calls for higher investment and savings rates. The above&#13;
together with a switch from import substitution to production for the export&#13;
market can go a long way in reducing the distortions in the foreign exchange&#13;
market.&#13;
21.       The wisdom of the above discussion is, therefore, that the pre-&#13;
mium will not be expected to remain as high as 90 percent. It is also not&#13;
realistic to expect deep-rooted structural disequilibrium in the Turkish&#13;
economy to disappear overnight. The key issue is whether the exchange rate&#13;
which has been adjusted recently will be changed again and often enough&#13;
to keep up with the domestic inflation rate. However, the lack of such an&#13;
adjustment will require the emergence of the premium rate to take into account&#13;
the effect of trade restrictions. A reasonable estimate that is consistent&#13;
with the projections of the general equilibrium model in Turkey is a premium&#13;
of 60 percent which will be used in all the following conversion factors.&#13;
However, sensitivity analysis is conducted to study the effects of differential&#13;
premia on the estimates of conversion factors. One more point that needs to&#13;
be made is that while present trends in the Turkish economy point to 60&#13;
percent as a reasonable estimate, any major economic change that affects the&#13;
premium rate should be considered by the project analyst using the conversion&#13;
factors. The methodology used is fairly flexible and the analyst should&#13;
carefully take into account major changes at future points in time.&#13;
1/ Turkey: Policies and Prospects for Growth. The World Bank, 1980 (Forthcoming)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
22.       In the case of Turkey, a devaluation to be effective will have to&#13;
bring about real price and income changes. Only in that case will the use of&#13;
different post-devaluation accounting ratios be relevant. Given that the&#13;
effects of the recent devaluation (June 1979) have not yet become fully&#13;
manifested, this issue will need to be resolved in the future.&#13;
Import Regime&#13;
23.       In March 1978 Turkey formally devalued its currency by 38 percent&#13;
to TL 25 to the dollar. The critical state of the Turkish economy and&#13;
its huge balance of payments deficit brought about a further devaluation,&#13;
setting the exchange rate at TL 47.5 to the dollar in May 1979. 1/ During the&#13;
late 1960's and early 1970's, successive Plans were mainly concerned with&#13;
rapid industrialization via capital-intensive technology, together with&#13;
a policy of import substitution financed largely by traditional agricultural&#13;
exports and processed raw materials. The import regime was therefore dominated&#13;
by a concern for protection of "infant industries" through imposition of&#13;
import duties and quotas and a licensing scheme. In the mid and late 1970's&#13;
the external trade balances of Turkey deteriorated rapidly as a result of&#13;
stagnation in export earnings (resulting from an overvalued currency, accele-&#13;
rating domestic inflation, increasing production costs and ad-hoc protective&#13;
policies), a fall in worker's remittances, together with a rising import bill.&#13;
Turkey's debt service ratio rose to 25.2 percent in 1978, leading to serious&#13;
consequences as regards the country's credit-worthiness. 2/ The import regime&#13;
in 1978 and 1979 has become more geared towards achieving a balance of payments&#13;
equilibrium and demand management aims. Thus, across-the-board economy-wide&#13;
import rationing has become an important tool in the present import regime.&#13;
We will first look at the formal import regime to be used in the estimation of&#13;
conversion factors. Next, it will be instructive to allow for effects of&#13;
import rationing and the "premium" rate, to get a better view of the real&#13;
import regime.&#13;
24.       In Turkey all commercial imports require import licenses.     These&#13;
are issued to registered importers, industrialists, State Economic Enter-&#13;
prises, and government departments and permit the necessary foreign exchange&#13;
payments to be made. Turkey's import regime relies on a positive listing&#13;
system. The basic essentials of the import program are fixed by the State&#13;
Planning Organization (SPO). It determines both the amount of projected&#13;
imports and their classification according to the necessity of demand for&#13;
imports in the implementation of development plans. All commodity imports are&#13;
classified, in the first instance into two major categories in terms of&#13;
1/   For most agricultural exports and for imports of petroleum and fertilizer&#13;
the exchange rate that is applicable is TL 35 to the US dollar.&#13;
2/   Turkey:   Policies and Prospects for Growth,    The World Bank,   1980&#13;
(Forthcoming).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
financing involved; programed imports financed by the country's own foreign&#13;
exchange resources and all self-financing imports financed with project&#13;
credits, private foreign capital and "imports with waivers". The programed&#13;
imports financed in convertible currencies are divided into Liberalized Lists&#13;
I, II, the EEC list, and global quota lists. The Liberalized List I com-&#13;
prises mainly raw materials for industrial products not produced domestically&#13;
and allows free imports of such goods without quantitative restrictions. List&#13;
II, composed mainly of raw materials produced in Turkey and semi-finished&#13;
goods for industrial production, requires prior approval of the Ministry&#13;
concerned when domestic production does not provide the required types of&#13;
goods in terms of quality or quantity. The quota list comprising investment&#13;
and consumer goods requires a more complex licensing procedure. The licensing&#13;
system consistent with the general import-substitution policy provides domestic&#13;
industry with a substantial degree of protection. A study by IBRD and the&#13;
Turkish Industrial Development Bank in 1972 found the median of effective rate&#13;
of protection to be 42 percent.&#13;
25.        Imported commodities are subject to the following different types&#13;
of taxation: 1/&#13;
(i)  Customs duty (30-60 percent of the value of imports).&#13;
(ii)  Stamp duty - previously at 9-9.5 percent of import value,&#13;
now raised to 25 percent applies to all imports following&#13;
waiver of GATT, article II.&#13;
(iii) Customs surcharge - 15 percent of applicable customs duty.&#13;
(iv)  Quay duty - 5 percent of import value.&#13;
(v)  Production tax - ranging from 10-75 percent when domestically&#13;
produced goods are subject to the same tax.&#13;
26.       Most of the imports consist of capital goods and intermediate goods,&#13;
and import of petroleum is almost one-third of total imports. Consumer goods&#13;
and food imports constitute less than 15 percent of total imports. The&#13;
analysis of structure of imports shows that the proportion of essential&#13;
imports has been rising partly in response to the long term changes in the&#13;
productive structure of the economy and reflecting the growth policy which&#13;
has favored sustained capital intensive investment requiring significant&#13;
capital imports. Thus a cut in imports has long term growth consequences.&#13;
The average tariff rate on imports is approximately 30 percent, varying&#13;
widely over sectors. Generally higher than average rates apply to capital&#13;
goods and some intermediate goods such as chemicals, and lower than average&#13;
rates apply to food and some consumption goods.&#13;
1/   When customs duties are equal to zero, other taxes on imports are not&#13;
payable. Also public sector imports are largely exempted from tariffs&#13;
and duties.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
27.       As already mentioned, however, pure import rationing has become&#13;
a prominent feature of the state policy. This has brought about a parallel&#13;
foreign exchange market due to rising demand for imported goods. The widen-&#13;
ing gap between supply of and demand for imported items, and the rationing&#13;
mechanism have added to the complexity of an already imperfect market. Thus&#13;
effective import costs (domestic prices) in a short market are much higher&#13;
than the c.i.f. price plus tariffs. For the period 1978-79 the TGT model has&#13;
estimated a premium rate of 90 percent to be added to import prices (c.i.f.&#13;
prices plus tariffs plus premium). 1/ The consequence of higher import costs&#13;
has been a bias towards more import substitution at the expense of other types&#13;
of policies. As the following tables and conversion factors show, given&#13;
the large magnitude of the premium rate (nearly three times the average&#13;
tariff rate in 1978) the conversion factors differ to a great extent depending&#13;
on the premium rate.&#13;
Export Regime&#13;
28.       Tax rebates are an important element of export policy established&#13;
in 1963 to encourage exports of non-traditional manufactured goods. These&#13;
were intended to offset the excise taxes paid by the manufacturers and&#13;
import duties and similar charges on the import content of exports. While&#13;
their impact has varied, textiles and the clothing industries have been major&#13;
beneficiaries. The average rate of export rebate, i.e., premiums of the&#13;
Turkish Lira per unit of foreign currency in transactions subject to rebates&#13;
is expressed as a percentage of the c.i.f. price of exports. While there is&#13;
no clear and direct relationship between export rebates and manufactured&#13;
exports, rebates can be justified as an additional short-term assistance to&#13;
industries that have an export potential but need time to develop export&#13;
markets. In principle the amount of rebate payment is limited to the actual&#13;
amount of taxes paid as well as export profitability considerations. Their&#13;
administration also has always been inefficient and on a piece-meal basis.&#13;
The share of exports subject to rebates increased from 30.6 percent in 1974&#13;
to 50 percent in 1977 and declined to 45 percent in 1978. The average rate&#13;
of export rebates fell to around 10 percent in early 1978 and rose to approxi-&#13;
mately 15 percent in the same year.&#13;
1/   It is interesting to observe the price of gold ingots in Turkey as&#13;
compared to that in the London market. The difference between the&#13;
parallel exchange market rate and the official rate in March 1979&#13;
was 190 percent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
Estimation of Conversion Factors&#13;
29.        In estimating conversion factors we will be mainly using the Squire&#13;
and van der Tak methodology as outlined in Economic Analysis of Projects. 1/&#13;
Given the following assumptions:&#13;
(a)  export demand and import supply are infinitely elastic; 2/&#13;
(b)  marginal changes in expenditure on non-tradeables can be&#13;
neglected; 3/&#13;
(c)  all income elasticities of spending are unity or the&#13;
relative size of the average propensities to spend on&#13;
importables and on exportables are approximately reflected&#13;
by the relative size of imports and exports. 4/&#13;
1/   The general formula for conversion factors is specified as&#13;
B      a, ,/p,     a.   1                (1)&#13;
.J  J  J  J     J&#13;
a. - proportion of marginal expenditure&#13;
devoted to the j   commodityth&#13;
-  is the shadow price of the j    commodity&#13;
J                                 .th&#13;
pj -  is the market price of the j     commodity&#13;
This requires information on the consumption patterns of different&#13;
income groups and expenditure elasticities which is not available.&#13;
2/   With respect to the elasticity of demand and supply, the assumption of&#13;
infinite elasticity seems advisable though it can be argued that the&#13;
elasticity of export demand is less than infinite for some major products.&#13;
3/   This assumption is justified if either a. for non-tradables is small&#13;
or if ./p. for non-tradables is approxiAately equal to the conver-&#13;
sion faatoL.&#13;
4/   In the case of Turkey the proportionality assumption (c) is to some&#13;
degree justifed in view of the fact that its economic structure and&#13;
trade composition are relatively diversified, i.e., import substi-&#13;
tution is reasonably advanced and export structure contains a&#13;
significant proportion of items which are domestically consumed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
(d) the existing extent and degree of protection is not likely&#13;
to change significantly. 1/&#13;
we can use          M + X          (2)&#13;
M(l+tm+TM) + X(l-tx)&#13;
M = c.i.f. value of imports&#13;
X = f.o.b. value of exports&#13;
tm = average tariff duty on imports&#13;
tx = average tax rebate (subsidy) on exports&#13;
TM = premium rate.&#13;
Standard Conversion Factor&#13;
30.       In project appraisal, there will usually be a number of inputs&#13;
whose weight in total costs is too small to justify the work which would be&#13;
involved in estimating specific accounting ratios for them. For tllis reason,&#13;
it is conventional to estimate a standard conversion factor (SCF) which is&#13;
used to convert expenditures on such items into values at shadow prices.&#13;
Tables 2 and 3 give the yearly values of the necessary export/import data to&#13;
calculate the SCF for the years 1974-78. The SCF using the three year&#13;
averages of trade and tax dates using equation (2) was estimated at 0.80. The&#13;
substantial non-tariff import restrictions, rationing and exchange controls in&#13;
Turkey constitutes an imperfect tax system. Addition of a "premium rate"&#13;
makes up the difference between c.i.f. plus tariff rate and the domestic&#13;
price of goods. After adjustment for the premium rate, (60 percent), the&#13;
standard conversion factor estimated for 1977-78 was reduced to 0.59.&#13;
1/   When these assumptions are abandoned, the marginal propensities to con-&#13;
sume exportables and importables have to be estimated and equation (1)&#13;
may be written as&#13;
Em.APCM     +   Ex.APCx&#13;
B  =  1 + tm          l-tx      (3) where m and x refere to importables&#13;
Em.ApCm         Ex.APCx        and exportables&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 2:   COMMODITY COMPOSITION OF IMPORTS 1974-78&#13;
(In millions of US dollars)&#13;
1974             1975            1976             1977            1978             Average&#13;
Value     %      Value     %     Value      %     Value     %     Value      %     Value     %&#13;
Consumption goods              510    13.6     501     10.6     28-     5.6     225      3.9     154     3.4      335     6.9&#13;
Intermediate goods                    54.6    2411     50.9  j2692     52.5    3395     58.6    2873    62.4     2607    55.0&#13;
Capital goods                 1204    31.8    1826     38.5   2150     41.9    2176     37.5    1572    34.2    1785     38.1&#13;
Total imports (goods)         3778   100.0    4739    100.0   5129    100.0    5796    100.0    4599   100.0    4808    100.0&#13;
Source:  Turkey:   Policies and Prospects for Growth, The World Bank, 1980 (Forthcoming); Statistical&#13;
Annex; Tables 3.1 - 3.4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 3:   COMMODITY COMPOSITION OF EXPORTS 1974-78&#13;
(In millions of US dollars)&#13;
1974             1975            1976             1977            1978             Average&#13;
Value     %      Value     %     Value      %     Value     %     Value      %     Value    %&#13;
Consumption goods             1225    79.9    1119     79.9    1679    85.7    1490     85.1    2003    87.5     1503    84.1&#13;
Intermediate goods             276    18.      254     18.      249    12.7     233     15.2     253    11.1      253    14.2&#13;
Capital goods                   31     2.0      28      2.0      31     1.6       30     1.7      31     1.4       31     1.7&#13;
Total exports (goods)         1532   100.0    1401    100.0    1960   100.0    1753    100.0    2288   100.0     1787   100.0&#13;
Source:  Turkey:  Policies and Prospects for Growth, The World Bank, 1980 (Forthcoming); Statistical&#13;
Annex, 3.1 - 3.4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
Table 4: ESTIMATION OF STANDARD CONVERSION FACTORS (SCF) 1974-78&#13;
1974      1975     1976      1977     1978      Average&#13;
Imports, c.i.f. (M)          3778     4739      5129      5796     4599        4808&#13;
Exports, f.o.b. (X)          1532     1401      1960      1753     2288        1787&#13;
Total (M + X)                5310     6140      7089      7549     6887        6595&#13;
Taxes on imports             1056     1392      1664      1760     1547        1484&#13;
Percentage (%)             28.0     29.0      32.0      30.0     33.0        31.0&#13;
Tax rebate on exports          67        96      196       192      138         138&#13;
Rebate/export ratio         4.3      6.9      10.0      10.9      6.0         7.6&#13;
Standard conversion&#13;
factor (SCF) /a            0.83     0.80      0.79     0.79      0.80        0.80&#13;
Premium rate (60%)           2267     2843      3077      3478     2759        2885&#13;
Standard conversion&#13;
factor (SCF*) /b           0.61     0.58      0.59     0.58      0.60        0.59&#13;
M + X&#13;
/a SCF = M(1 + tm) + X(1 - tx)&#13;
where: tm - import taxes&#13;
tx - export taxes&#13;
TR2 - premium rate (60%)&#13;
M + X&#13;
/b SCF* = M(1 + tm) + X(1 - tx + TM)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
Table 5:    STANDARD CONVERSION FACTORS&#13;
Sensitivity Analysis&#13;
1976       1977        1978       Average&#13;
Standard conversion&#13;
factor (SCF*) /a&#13;
SCF1  /b                          0.79        0.80       0.80          0.80&#13;
SCF2                              0.59        0.58       0.60          0.59&#13;
SCF3                              0.52        0.51       0.54          0.52&#13;
m+ X&#13;
/a  SCF*   M(1 + tm + TM    + X(l - tx)&#13;
/b   TM - premium rate (%)&#13;
SCFl:  TM   =0&#13;
SCF2:   TM  = 60&#13;
SCF3:  TM   = 90&#13;
Source:  Table 3, S. Robinson and K. Dervis "The Foreign Exchange Gap, Growth&#13;
and Industrial Strategy in Turkey : 1973 - 1983", World Bank Staff&#13;
Working Paper No. 306, 1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
31.       The SCF bears a close relation to the more familiar concept of&#13;
shadow exchange rate (SER). 1/ The precise relation is&#13;
SCF/OER  =   1/SER    (4)  OER = Official exchange rate&#13;
SER = Shadow exchange rate&#13;
Thus the SCF translates domestic prices into border prices expressed in units&#13;
of the domestic currency, and division by OER expresses the result in units&#13;
of foreign exchange. In the case of Turkey, using official tariff rates, the&#13;
SER is TL 30 to the dollar. Alternatively, the second approach allowing for&#13;
a rationing market leads to a shadow exchange rate which values the dollar at&#13;
TL 47.2. This is very close to the effective market rate during the past two&#13;
years and is a good measure of the overvaluation of the Turkish currency.&#13;
Conversion Factor for Consumption Goods (CF )&#13;
c&#13;
32.       The value of CF    is determined by estimating the increase in the&#13;
value of consumption at domestic prices if one more unit of foreign exchange&#13;
is committed to consumption.   The CF   is required to transform a marginal&#13;
increase in consumer expenditure into its equivalent value at shadow prices. 2/&#13;
This will be the ratio of the value of this consumption at border prices&#13;
to its value at domestic prices. From import and export data averaged over&#13;
the years 1973-79 (Tables 6, 7) the conversion factor for consumption goods&#13;
is derived. Since disaggregated urban and rural consumer expenditure data do&#13;
not exist it is not possible to derive any separate estimates although given&#13;
the inequal income distribution one could safely assume that there would be&#13;
a difference.&#13;
33.       Only a small proportion of consumer expenditures is spent on the&#13;
purchase of consumer goods that are imported and subject to restrictions.&#13;
The majority of consumer imports consist of essential items free of con-&#13;
straints although subject to customs duty at a rate of 30 to 40 percent. The&#13;
consumption conversion factor was estimated at 0.79.&#13;
1/   The relationship between SER and conversion factors is discussed in&#13;
detail in A. Ray "Shadow Exchange Rates and Conversion Factors" (CPN,&#13;
forthcoming).&#13;
2/   This means that the basket of commodities making up the consumer's&#13;
marginal consumption must be valued at shadow prices and the resulting&#13;
sum expressed as a proportion of the value of the same basket at market&#13;
prices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
Table 6:  ESTIMATION OF CONVERSION FACTOR FOR CONSUMPTION GOODS (CF ) 1974-78&#13;
(In millions of US dollars)                   C&#13;
1974     1975      1976     1977      1978    Average&#13;
Imports of consumption&#13;
goods, c.i.f. (M)         509.7     501.3    286.8     225.2    154.2       335.4&#13;
Exports of consumption&#13;
goods, f.o.b. X)         1225.3    1118.8   1679.2    1489.7   2002.8      1503.1&#13;
Total trade (X   + M )   1735.0    1620.1   1966.0    1714.9   2157.0      1838.5&#13;
C    C&#13;
Taxes on M                193.7     190.5    108.9      85.5     58.6       127.4&#13;
c&#13;
Tax rebate on X           122.5     111.9    167.9     148.9    201.0       150.0&#13;
c&#13;
Premium rate (60%)        305.8     300.6    172.1     135.0     92.4       201.0&#13;
Conversion factor (CF )     0.74      0.73     0.81      0.82     0.86        0.79&#13;
c&#13;
Table 7: ESTIMATION OF CONVERSION FACTOR FOR CONSUMPTION GOODS&#13;
Sensitivity Analysis&#13;
1974     1975      1976     1977      1978    Average&#13;
Conversion factor for&#13;
consumption goods&#13;
CFcl/a                   0.84      0.84     0.87      0.87     0.89       0.86&#13;
CFc2/                    0.74      0.73     0.81      0.82     0.86       0.79&#13;
CF c/3                   0.69      0.68     0.79      0.82     0.84       0.76&#13;
c 3&#13;
/a   CFcl - premium rate = 0.&#13;
/b   CFc2 - premium rate = 60%&#13;
/c   CF 3 - premium rate = 90%.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
Conversion Factor for Intermediate Goods (CF )&#13;
34.       The conversion factor for intermediate goods for Turkey using 1974&#13;
to 1978 import and export data was estimated at 0.55 (Tables 8, 9). Turkey's&#13;
main intermediate imports are petroleum products, chemicals, iron and steel&#13;
which are major inputs into industrial production. Intermediate imports&#13;
have been subject to varying degrees of tariff and non-tariff policies. The&#13;
premium rate on such imports in recent years has been very high and given the&#13;
rate of industrial growth together with recent foreign exchange shortage, the&#13;
official price plus tariff rate would not be a good guide of the user cost of&#13;
such imports to the private sector. The State Economic Enterprises and public&#13;
sector are major consumers of the import of intermediate goods and the premium&#13;
rate applying to the public and private sector also differ due to many complex&#13;
arrangements. 1/ Moreover, there is a special arrangement for resale of&#13;
foreign exchange earned by exporters which effectively allows them to make&#13;
black market profit on exchange rate transaction. An average tariff rate of&#13;
26 percent is used in the estimation of (CFI)      Recent changes in tax rebates&#13;
in May 1979 have reduced the maximum rebate rate and narrowed down its applica-&#13;
tion to manufactured goods. The average rebate used in the estimates is 18&#13;
percent. A more serious problem given the extent of the rationing in this&#13;
group and in particular given the differential treatment of public and private&#13;
sector and their relative shares in the economy of such imports is what would&#13;
be a reasonable value for the premium. The 90 percent premium rate would&#13;
reduce the CFI to 0.48 (Table 5). 2/&#13;
1/   Imports of petroleum and petroleum products and chemicals amounted to&#13;
about 35 percent of total merchandise imports in 1978. (IMF Report, July&#13;
1979).&#13;
2/   The important point to note is that the conversion factors derived reflect&#13;
the existing foreign trade policy, the values attached to various policies,&#13;
(e.g., existing import taxes) and the export and import regimes. Some&#13;
studies (Adrian Wood: Manufacturing Industry and Foreign Trade, The&#13;
World Bank, March 1979) show that in many manufacturing industries the&#13;
domestic resource costs are very high and production adversely affected&#13;
the foreign trade balance in the sense that earning or saving a dollar of&#13;
foreign exchange required another one dollar's worth of imported inputs.&#13;
Inefficient producers have benefitted from tax rebates and protection by&#13;
heavy tariff and non-tariff protective devices. Lack of competition, and&#13;
import substitution policies, and high trade barriers creating serious&#13;
shortages have led to a situation where foreign reserves are misallocated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
Table 8:  CONVERSION FACTOR FOR INTERMEDIATE GOODS (CF ) 1974-78&#13;
(In millions of Turkish liras)&#13;
1974     1975      1976     1977     1978    Average&#13;
Imports of intermediate&#13;
goods, c.i.f. (M I)        2063     2411     2692      3395     2873      2607&#13;
Exports of intermediate&#13;
goods, f.o.b. (X I)         276      255      249       233      253       259&#13;
Total trade (XI + MI)      2338     2665     2941      3658     3125      2866&#13;
Taxes on M   (26%)          563      627       700      823      642       678&#13;
Tax rebate on (X )           39       46        57       58       38        47&#13;
Premium rate (60%)         1238     1447      1615     2037     1483      1564&#13;
Conversion factor (CF )     0.56     0.55     0.55      0.55     0.56       0.55&#13;
Source:  Turkey:   From Crisis to Growth, 1979; S. Robinson and K. Dervis (1978).&#13;
IMF Reports on Turkey, 1979.&#13;
Table 9:  CONVERSION FACTORS FOR INTERMEDIATE GOODS (CF )&#13;
Sensitivity Analysis&#13;
1974     1975      1976     1977     1978    Average&#13;
Conversion factors for&#13;
intermediate goods CFI&#13;
CFI /a                    0.80     0.79     0.79      0.79     0.80      0.80&#13;
CF I2/b                   0.56     0.55     0.55      0.55     0.55      0.55&#13;
CF  /c                    0.49     0.48     0.48      0.47     0.48      0.48&#13;
13-~-&#13;
/a   CF11 - premium rate = 0.&#13;
/b   CF12 - premium rate = 60%.&#13;
/c   CFi3 - premium rate = 90%.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
Conversion Factor for Capital Goods (CF )&#13;
35.       The conversion factor for capital goods transforms a marginal&#13;
increase in expenditure on capital goods into its equivalent value at shadow&#13;
prices. Turkey's exports of capital goods are still relatively small. The&#13;
import of such items, however, has been increasing rapidly in the past few&#13;
years. Average tariff rate applicable is 33 percent but the rationing in this&#13;
market given the importance of capital intensive, technology and priority of&#13;
industrial projects has been quite fierce, particularly in the private sector.&#13;
The public sector, however, has fared better, at least up to 1978 when the&#13;
real credit crunch started. The CF estimated is 0.52 but when adjusted for&#13;
K&#13;
90 percent premium it is reduced to 0.45 (Tables 10, 11).&#13;
Table 10: ESTIMATION OF CONVERSION FACTORS FOR CAPITAL GOODS 1974-1978&#13;
1974     1975      1976     1977      1978    Average&#13;
Imports of capital goods,&#13;
c.i.f. (M K)              1204      1826     2150      2176     1572       1786&#13;
Exports of capital goods,&#13;
f.o.b. f. (X )              31        28       32        30       33         31&#13;
Total XK + MK)              1235     1854     2182      2206      1605      1817&#13;
Taxes on MK                  397      603      710       718      519        589&#13;
Tax rebates on XK              3.1      3.2       6.7      6t6      5.0        5.3&#13;
Premium rate (60%)           722     1096     1290      1306      943       1072&#13;
Conversion factor for&#13;
capital goods (CF K)         0.52      0.52     0.52      0.52     0.52       0.52&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
Table 11: CONVERSION FACTORS FOR CAPITAL GOODS&#13;
Sensitivity Analysis&#13;
1976      1977     1978     Average&#13;
Conversion factors for capital goods&#13;
CF  /a                                        0.75      0.75      0.75      0.75&#13;
K 1&#13;
CF  /b                                        0.52      0.52      0.52      0.52&#13;
K2'--&#13;
CF  /c                                        0.45      0.45      0.45      0.45&#13;
K3 3--&#13;
/a   CFKi - premium rate = 0.&#13;
/b   CFK2 - premium rate = 60%.&#13;
/c   CF K3 - premium rate =90%.&#13;
36.        The simple formula    +      (6) can be used when we assume that&#13;
all exportables are exported I/+anW that income elasticities for import com-&#13;
modities are all unity. In this case the results will differ to a large&#13;
extent for SCF and CF    but by a lesser amount for CFI and CFk'&#13;
Table 12&#13;
CF   l 11F                             Original Estimates&#13;
S+tm       CF     tm 0 T&#13;
SCF              0.77                 0.53                  0.59&#13;
CF               0.72                 0.50                  0.79&#13;
c&#13;
CFI              0.79                 0.53                  0.55&#13;
K              0.77                 0.52                  0.52&#13;
TM - premium rate.&#13;
37.        An interesting exercise using the T-1 run of the TGT model and&#13;
using the simple formula (6) for conversion factors and allowing for the&#13;
premia produces not very different results. The general equilibrium TGT model&#13;
projections for imports and exports as well as imports and exports as well as&#13;
import duty and export rebates that are expected to be relevant in the medium&#13;
1/   The use of the simple formula may not be justified given the fact that&#13;
the very serious import rationing and the fall in imports implies that&#13;
exportables were to a large extent directed to a booming domestic market.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
run (1979-1983). 1/ There is a 19 sector division of the economy and an&#13;
aggregated study of the consumer goods. (Table 13). On the basis of the&#13;
values provided by this model the estimates of conversion factors were slightly&#13;
lower than the original estimates. While using the simple formula is partly&#13;
responsible for this, some of the difference is due to the data based used.&#13;
Table 13: SECTORAL CONVERSION FACTORS 1978&#13;
(Domestic Price    CIF + Tariffs + 90 percent)&#13;
X =          1&#13;
tm (%)      tm + TM     1 + tm +TM       X&#13;
Agriculture                             23.1        103.1           2.03      0.49&#13;
Mining                                   6.8         96.8           1.97      0.50&#13;
Food                                    24.0        114.0          2.14       0.57&#13;
Textiles                                65.9        155.9           2.56      0.39&#13;
Clothing                                 7.2         97.2          1.97       0.51&#13;
Wood                                    14.9        104.9           2.05      0.48&#13;
Paper                                   47.1        137.1          2.37       0.42&#13;
Chemical                                41.4        131.4          2.31       0.43&#13;
Rubber &amp; plastic                        44.6        134.6          2.34       0.43&#13;
Petroleum products                      12.1        102.1          2.02       0.50&#13;
Non-mineral products                    47.1        137.1          2.37       0.42&#13;
Basic metal                             14.3        104.3          2.04       0.49&#13;
Metal products                          21.5        111.5           2.11      0.47&#13;
Non-electrical machinery                35.2        125.2          2.25       0.44&#13;
Electrical machinery                    20.2        110.2          2.10       0.47&#13;
Transportation equipment                36.0        126.0          2.26       0.44&#13;
Construction                            00&#13;
Infrastructure                          00&#13;
Services                                00&#13;
SUM&#13;
Agriculture                             23.1        113.1          2.13       0.47&#13;
Consumer goods                          37.9        127.9          2.28       0.43&#13;
Intermediate goods                      25.8        115.8          2.16       0.46&#13;
Capital goods                           32.7        120.7          2.21       0.45&#13;
Construction                            00&#13;
Infrastructure                          00&#13;
SUM                                     27.9        117.9          2.18       0.46&#13;
tm = Tariffs on imports.&#13;
TM = Premium.&#13;
1&#13;
1 + tm + TM&#13;
Source: Kemal Dervis and Sherman Robinson; T-1 Run of TGT Model.&#13;
1/   There is an implicit assumption that all values of the general equilibrium&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
The Marginal Productivity of Capital,q&#13;
38.       The marginal product of capital is the net return earned by a&#13;
marginal unit of investment at border prices when all inputs and outputs are&#13;
measured at efficiency prices. It indicates the marginal rate of transforma-&#13;
tion between present and future foreign exchange and is an objective parameter&#13;
that in principle can be observed. 1/ Estimation of q can be based on both&#13;
macro and micro data. For Turkey both sources are explored. Initially two&#13;
different macro economic estimation procedures will be used and a further&#13;
study of micro data will help to establish a reliable estimate of q. Moreover,&#13;
the availability of data allowed us to attempt regression analysis using labor&#13;
or capital stock and employment figures, dissaggregated in the agricultural&#13;
and non-agricultural sectors. 2/&#13;
39.       In the first procedure, the incremental employment/capital ratio&#13;
is multiplied by the marginal product of labor and the result subtracted&#13;
from the incremental output-capital ratio, to give an estimate of the mar-&#13;
ginal productivity of capital in domestic prices.     This is then multiplied by&#13;
the standard conversion factor over the conversion factor for capital goods&#13;
(CFK) to express it in foreign currency terms.&#13;
Formally,&#13;
0 -  AE  x   AW  SCF             (7)&#13;
q   hK    AK      AE  CFk&#13;
where,&#13;
0 = GDP at factor cost&#13;
K = Total fixed investment&#13;
E = Employment&#13;
W = Wages&#13;
The incremental output/capital ratio is the inverse of the conventional ICOR&#13;
(3.8 during 1973-77) 3/ and may be estimated from output and investment data&#13;
for Turkey adjusted by respective deflators.    When we allow for lagged effects&#13;
0                                   0&#13;
of investment - is equal to 0.30.    The value of K that will be used in these&#13;
K                         ~~~~~~~~K&#13;
will be 0.27 41 which is consistent with both the TGT model and the country&#13;
1/   Squire and van der Tak, Economic Analysis of Projects, 1975, p. 110.&#13;
2/   The results of the regression analysis using aggregate production&#13;
functions (Cobb-Douglas and C.E.S.) were derived too late to be&#13;
included in this version.&#13;
3/   K overestimates q because k is an average concept whereas q is a marginal&#13;
concept and also k neglects the contribution of other factors of pro-&#13;
duction and that of technical progress (See van der Tak, (1975), p.111).&#13;
4/   Source:   Turkey: Policies and Prospects for Growth, The World Bank,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
report estimates. The employment/capital ratio 1/ can be derived by using&#13;
the investment figures and employment figures during the 1974-78 period&#13;
(Table 14). The marginal productivity of labor is difficult to measure and&#13;
there is a wide gap between productivity in urban and rural sectors. A&#13;
weighted figure of marginal labor productivity is adopted as a rough approxi-&#13;
mation, w = 23,400. 2/&#13;
q = (0.27 - 23,400 x (0.0023 x 10 3)) 059    = *0.244&#13;
Given the above values, q is estimated to be 24 percent and allowing for&#13;
lagged investment effects will give a result closer to 28 percent.&#13;
Table 14: SECTORAL INCREMENTAL CAPITAL-LABOR RATIO&#13;
Labor Productivity (TL)                                 1973-77&#13;
Agriculture                                           722&#13;
Industry                                              672&#13;
Services                                              572&#13;
Average                                               432&#13;
Sources:  OECD; TURKEY; OECD Economic Surveys; November 1978.&#13;
40.        The second method estimates the Opportunity Cost of Capital using a&#13;
Cobb - Douglas type production function,&#13;
C = CertKaLB        O=utput                 (8)&#13;
C = Constant&#13;
r = rate of technical progress&#13;
k = Capital&#13;
L = Labour&#13;
1/   The inverse ratio can be interpreted as the macro index of the costs&#13;
of creating a job.&#13;
2/   The various sources that can be used are estimates of shadow wage rates&#13;
(Section IV), minimum wage laws and productivity measures in Turkey.&#13;
The minimum wage rates are not representative of the marginal product&#13;
of labor in the various sectors and provide a means of enforcing some&#13;
degree of social planning. Moreover, they cover only a small proportion&#13;
of the total working population. The figures used are based on marginal&#13;
productivity measures used in deriving shadow wage rates in Section V.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
The marginal change in output with respect to a marginal change in capital&#13;
gives the following:&#13;
do_         rt a-i B                        (9)&#13;
dO  -  a Ce   K   L&#13;
Multiplying through by k and dividing by k&#13;
dO  =  aCertKa1i B                         (10)&#13;
r&#13;
0&#13;
=aK&#13;
where - is the output-capital ratio (inverse of ICOR) and "a" is the share of&#13;
K                                  0&#13;
of profits in National Income. 1/ The K ratio has already been estimated to be&#13;
0.30 allowing for lagged effects of investment. Table 15 provides estimates&#13;
for "a" for the period 1978-80 using projections of labor income and capital&#13;
income taken from the T-1 run of the TGT model. The share of gross profit is&#13;
roughly 50 percent of National Income. 2/ However, when the share of profit&#13;
after rent and depreciation is taken into account it will bring "a" down to&#13;
35 percent of National Income. Compared to other middle income countries&#13;
(MIC) at a similar level of development, this is a reasonable estimate. The&#13;
resulting opportunity cost of capital is 10.5 percent which expressed in&#13;
border prices amounts to a rounded value of q of 12 percent which does seem&#13;
to be a more reasonable estimate.&#13;
Table 15&#13;
Share of Capital&#13;
Agriculture                     0.39&#13;
Industry                       0.63&#13;
Manufacturing                   0.61&#13;
Service                        0.43&#13;
Total                  0.50&#13;
Source:  Projections of the TGT model,&#13;
K. Dervis and S. Robinson (1978).&#13;
1/   The above can be derived directly since the marginal product of capital&#13;
is equal to the rate of profit, given assumptions of perfect competition&#13;
and constant returns to scale.&#13;
2/   61 percent for manufacturing sector, and 40 percent for agriculture.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
Table 16: OPPORTUNITY COST OF CAPITAL&#13;
(In millions of TL)&#13;
Total Net&#13;
National      Total      Total&#13;
Income       Income    Capital      K       /2    0        /1    q.SCF&#13;
Year         K + W        (W)        (K)      K+W     a*      K     OCC        CF&#13;
k&#13;
1978       1,069,465    533,125     536,346  0.50     0.35  0.30   0.11       0.12&#13;
1979       1,642,241    814,285     827,956  0.50     0.35  0.30   0.11       0.12&#13;
1980       2,482,790  1,238,741   1,244.049  0.50     0.35  0.30   0.11       0.12&#13;
/_   OCC = a 0.&#13;
K&#13;
/2   a* takes into account the estimate of rent and depreciation capital.&#13;
Source: Turkey: From Crisis to Growth, The World Bank, 1979; Statistical&#13;
Annex; K. Dervis and S. Robinson; TGT Model; T-1 Run.&#13;
41.        For the micro-economic estimation procedure two sources of inform-&#13;
ation on the marginal productivity of capital are available; the interest&#13;
rate structure in the economy and evidence on project-specific economic rates&#13;
of return. Criticisms have been made regarding the imperfections in the&#13;
capital market implying interest rates are not very meaningful measures of&#13;
the marginal productivity of capital and profit rates would provide better&#13;
guidance on q. Evidence on rate of profit in the private sectors, however,&#13;
is a useful parameter but difficult to obtain.&#13;
42.        Looking first at the interest rate structure, Table 17 presents&#13;
various rates in force during 1973-74 and 1978-79. In February 1978, the&#13;
government increased the legal ceiling on term loans to industry to 16 percent&#13;
per annum and in May 1979 to 20 percent. In addition borrowers pay 25 percent&#13;
transactions tax on interest. Moreover, commercial banks charge 2 percent&#13;
per annum commission on collateral held. The effective cost to borrowers&#13;
is now 26 to 28 percent. However, once we allow for the inflation rate&#13;
measured by the index of wholesale prices the real cost to borrowers of short&#13;
term local currency loans is negative 1/. The situation, however is different&#13;
in the case of individual long-term local currency loans since the real cost&#13;
1/   The inflation rate increased from 16 percent to 24 percent in 1977 and&#13;
to 51 percent in 1978 and is projected to go down to 40 percent during&#13;
the present fiscal year and fall to 10 percent by 1982 if the Govern-&#13;
ment stabilization policy is successful.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
of loans should be measured over their maturity when the rate of inflation is&#13;
expected to decline. 1/&#13;
Table 17: LENDING INTEREST RATES IN TURKEY&#13;
_ __ ___  1973  1974     1978    May 1979&#13;
General interest rate                             10.5    11.5      1.6       20.0&#13;
Medium-term credits                               12.0    14.0     16.0       20.0&#13;
Medium- and long-term credits                      9.0    10.5     10.5       16.0&#13;
43.        Further information may be obtained from Bank financed projects.&#13;
The following list summarizes the estimated internal economic rate of return&#13;
for some recent Bank projects;&#13;
Erdemir Steel Project, 1978                        8-17%&#13;
Ports Rehabilitation Project, 1979                20-37%&#13;
Grain Storage Project, 1979                       21%&#13;
Southern ANTALYA Tourism Project, 1976            17.2%&#13;
Moreover, the World Bank has used a rate of 8% to lend money for various&#13;
projects.&#13;
44.        The micro data provides a wide range (8-20) percent for q.      The&#13;
Eurocurrency rates can be taken as a reasonable estimate of the marginal&#13;
productivity of capital. The other interest rate and economic rate of return&#13;
figures, however, cannot be relied on. First, they provide a very wide range&#13;
which is not helpful from the project analyst's point of view. Second, these&#13;
rates loose their significance in a capital market which is as segmented and&#13;
imperfect as the Turkish one. In a market where capital is rationed, interest&#13;
rates may no longer be meaningful estimates of marginal productivity of&#13;
capital. Third, there is reason to believe that the rates applicable to the&#13;
1/   If the stabilization policy is successful, a typical 7 year loan&#13;
at the end of 1979 with a 2 year grace period would have a zero cost&#13;
in real terms over its entire life if the borrowers paid nominal&#13;
financial charges of about 19 percent per annum. As a result, the&#13;
prevailing interest rate implies a real cost to the borrower of&#13;
7 percent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
private and public sectors differ. The public sector and State Economic&#13;
Enterprises have often had access to cheaper and more readily available&#13;
sources of capital. The poor performance of the latter is a clear sign of&#13;
misallocation of resources resulting in inefficient operations. Given the&#13;
limited measure of capital available to the Turkish economy there has been a&#13;
crowding out effect which has influenced the private sector.&#13;
45.        Of the macro results the second approach is adopted and a net figure&#13;
of q = 12 percent is a reasonable estimate to be used in project appraisal.&#13;
However, several points need to be made. First, given the market imperfections&#13;
it will be useful to estimate the marginal productivity of capital in the&#13;
public sector and the private sector separately. Presently the data available&#13;
does not allow such work to be undertaken, but it remains an important issue&#13;
as long as the public sector is given certain preferences and advantages in&#13;
the capital market which affects investment decisions. Second, as already&#13;
mentioned the capital market segmentation should not be overlooked.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
IV. SOCIAL PRICING PARAMETERS IN TURKEY&#13;
46.        In this section we describe the methods and data sources underlying&#13;
our estimates of consumption and accounting rates of interest, the value of&#13;
public income, the consumption distribution weights, the summary distribution&#13;
measures and finally the critical consumption level. First, we present a&#13;
brief assessment of the Government's social objectives from which we deduce&#13;
the likely range of values for the consumption rate of interest (CRI). A&#13;
careful specification of the Government's preferences with regard to growth&#13;
and income distribution objectives is important. What matters is to bring the&#13;
objectives of the Government to bear on production decisions because their&#13;
objectives are related to possibilities. The objectives that are incorporated&#13;
in the analysis do play a role in the estimation of shadow prices. The&#13;
important point to note when moving from efficiency to social pricing is that&#13;
whether the benefits of a project will accrue primarily to those already rich,&#13;
or to the poor, is highly relevant to decisions about it. But the way in&#13;
which this view can and should influence project appraisal is the important&#13;
fact in social benefit-cost analysis. 1/&#13;
47.        Ideally, production decisions should be left to seek efficiency&#13;
and the government ought to correct the maldistribution of income by using the&#13;
tax system despite the fact that optimal lump-sum taxation is impossible.&#13;
Moreover, naive applications of distributional ideas has to be avoided. It is&#13;
necessary to observe, however, that a systematic application of welfare&#13;
weighting can allow for distributional objectives. The objectives can be&#13;
expressed by means of a social welfare function which assigns to all possible&#13;
allocations of income to individuals a numerical value. Relating the weights&#13;
to basic needs may be a practical solution to the weighting problem. We,&#13;
therefore, describe recent trends in public income and expenditure and present&#13;
estimates of the value of public income. Based on the preceding results we&#13;
make an estimate of the accounting rate of interest (ARI).&#13;
Government Objectives&#13;
48.       Turkey's Fourth Plan calls for improvement in income distribution&#13;
patterns and states that amongst the basic assumptions concerning political&#13;
and social choices, "the most important of these...are concerned with the&#13;
mechanisms for the distribution of income and resources, and the allocation&#13;
of the means of production". 2/ The planners have been concerned with a&#13;
1/   See J.A. Mirrlees, "Social Benefit-Cost Analysis and the Distribution of&#13;
Income", World Development, 1978, Vol. 6, No. 2 for a more detailed dis-&#13;
cussion. The argument is that the chief impact of distributional con-&#13;
siderations is on the costing of labor, measurement of benefits from&#13;
public goods, and pricing of non-tradables. The last is in principle&#13;
important but in practice the correct way of adjusting prices is compli-&#13;
cated and difficult to assess.&#13;
2/   Source:   Fourth Plan, and Turkey:   From Policies and Prospects for&#13;
Growth, 1980 (Forthcoming).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
more equitable and just income distribution to eliminate the past social&#13;
and economic imbalances resulting from rapid growth. There is an emphasis&#13;
on issues such as unemployment, and quality of urban and rural life. The&#13;
elaborate treatment of social problems does indicate interest in social&#13;
planning principles. Nonetheless, it is important to notice that the critical&#13;
economic situation in Turkey resulting from a huge external deficit, high&#13;
inflation rates and structural imbalances in the employment and capital&#13;
markets and breakdown of the price mechanism - presents more pressing problems&#13;
that might outweigh the social aspects of the Plan. This point will have to&#13;
be taken into account by choosing subjective parameters that are close&#13;
to the government objectives as pronounced in the Plan. Over the period&#13;
1973-77 the growth rate of Gross National Product has been 7.1 percent which&#13;
given a 2.5 percent population growth rate implies a per capita income growth&#13;
rate of 4.6 percent and a per capita income close to $1,100. 1/ Moreover, the&#13;
priority given to import substitution and industrialization led to a growth&#13;
rate of the industrial sector at the rate of 9.3 percent compared to 3.5&#13;
percent growth rate in agriculture. Despite industrial growth, Turkey's&#13;
agricultural base accounts for about 62 percent of the labor force and 24&#13;
percent of GDP. Investment, on the other hand, has increased from 17.9&#13;
percent of GDP to 26.1 percent between the years 1972 and 1977. The inade-&#13;
quacy of saving mobilization efforts (savings ratio = 16 percent of GDP) in&#13;
financing investment has led to heavy reliance on short and medium-term&#13;
foreign sources which have subsequently caused a large external deficit. The&#13;
present plans for heavy industrial investment and export-oriented growth and&#13;
projected GDP growth rate of 8.2 percent (1979-83), increase in the share of&#13;
industrial output to 32 percent in 1982 and a fall in the share of services&#13;
from 52 to 49 percent, require investment to increase by 12.5 percent annualy&#13;
in real terms rising from 20 percent to 24.4 percent of GNP in 1983. Given&#13;
that the sectoral distribution of investment shows a significantly large share&#13;
(27.4 percent) devoted to manufacturing of intermediate and capital goods,&#13;
reducing the relative shares of housing and transport and a modest allocation&#13;
to social sectors, it is obvious that the government objectives indicate a&#13;
very low consumption rate of interest (CRI). The lower this rate the less one&#13;
discounts future relative to current consumption, and hence the greater the&#13;
premium attached to resources which promote growth.&#13;
Consumption Rate of Interest&#13;
49.        The consumption rate of interest (CRI) is a discount rate defined&#13;
as the rate of fall over time in the value of the marginal utility of con-&#13;
sumption, at the average level of consumption (consumption is the numeraire).&#13;
Its purpose in project selection is to ensure that the government's preferences&#13;
concerning future consumption and current consumption are adequately reflected&#13;
in shadow prices. It is estimated as the sum of the rate of pure time&#13;
preference (p) or the degree of "impatience" of a community, and the product&#13;
of the growth rate of real per capita consumption (g) and the social elasticity&#13;
of the marginal utility of consumption, (n).&#13;
CRI  = ng + p                    (11)&#13;
1/   Turkey:  Policies and Prospects for Growthi 1980 (Forthcoming), Statistical&#13;
A -   --   _'  I  &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
Of the three elements of the CRI, only (g) can be estimated objectively. For&#13;
the period 1974-1978 total private consumption at constant prices grew at an&#13;
annual rate of 4.95 percent, implying an average growth rate of real per&#13;
capita consumption of 2.5 percent.&#13;
50.       As has been shown elsewhere, 1/ (n) can be linked to the Government's&#13;
attitude toward the degree of inequality in the distribution of income.&#13;
The larger the value of n, the faster the decline in income weights, as the&#13;
household income increases and hence the greater the social benefit accorded&#13;
to distributional changes in favor of the lowest income groups. Turkey's&#13;
Fourth Plan makes it quite clear that growth is the major objective in the&#13;
medium run though considerations of equity and social planning are not com-&#13;
pletely ignored. The Turkish government has already stated its desire to&#13;
improve income distribution. However, given the present tax structure,&#13;
although wages have been raised recently to match the inflation rate,&#13;
nonetheless the tax system is such that it bites heavily into the new high&#13;
nominal wages of lower income groups (although one may infer with some confi-&#13;
dence that n&gt;o since Turkey employs a progressive tax structure). For the&#13;
main part of the analysis a value of n=l will be used, meaning that increased&#13;
household incomes by a certain percent will reduce the income weight by the&#13;
same percentage. In sensitivity analysis, n=0.5 is used to show consequences&#13;
of assuming that the government attaches less priority to distributional&#13;
improvements relative to other objectives.&#13;
51.       The objectives also imply a very low value for the rate of pure time&#13;
preference (2 percent) because an increase in this parameter reduces, other&#13;
things being equal, the extent to which the weighting system favors growth.&#13;
The low    reflects the government's preference for future compared to present&#13;
consumption.&#13;
Table 18&#13;
Range of CRI&#13;
Rate of Pure Time Preference&#13;
0           1          2&#13;
Social elasticity of the&#13;
marginal utility of con-          0.5        1.25        2.25       3.25&#13;
sumption (n)&#13;
1           2.5        3.50        4.50&#13;
Within the resulting range (1.25% &lt; CRI &lt; 4.50%) our best estimate for the CRI&#13;
is 4.50. This measure, however, has to be seen within the limitations on con-&#13;
sumption following the Ecevit Austerity Plan and demand management aims.&#13;
Moreover, the higher CRI, the higher will be the accounting discount rate&#13;
(ARI).&#13;
1/   M. Scott, Project Appraisal in Practice (1976), p. 30.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
The Value of Public Income,v&#13;
52.       The value of public income is estimated in terms of the consumption&#13;
stream generated by a unit of public investment assuming optimal allocation&#13;
of public funds. While public income is expended for many purposes, since&#13;
public investment is probably a major component of marginal public expenditure,&#13;
it would seem important to attempt some estimate of its value. The results&#13;
can be checked later by relating them to estimates of the critical consumption&#13;
level. If we neglect the reinvestment of the returns to the public sector,&#13;
v can be estimated using the simple formula; 1/&#13;
v = q/CF     . CRI                                (12)&#13;
when;      q    =  Marginal product of capital in the public sector&#13;
CRI = Consumption rate of interest&#13;
CF   =   Conversion factor for consumption goods.&#13;
If we let q = 8 percent and CRI = 3.5, v will be 2.89. For the central value&#13;
of q = 12 percent, and CRI = 4.5 we estimated v to be 3.37 (3.4). This means&#13;
that marginal social value of foreign exchange in the public sector is worth&#13;
3.4 times the marginal social value of private consumption at the average&#13;
level of consumption. If we allow for the range of q to be 8 to 24 percent&#13;
and CRI to be between 1.25 and 4.5, the range of v will be between 2.25 and&#13;
24.30 (Table 19). The results depend largely on q and public sector profit-&#13;
ability. If n = 0.5, with q = 8 percent, the value of public income will be&#13;
approximately equal to 4 illustrating the priority given to growth. 2/&#13;
Table 19:  VALUE OF PUBLIC INCOME v = q/CF     . CRI&#13;
q                  1.25    2.25     3.5    4.5&#13;
8                  8.10    4.50     2.89   2.25&#13;
12                 12.20    6.75     4.30   3.37&#13;
24                 24.30   13.50     8.68   6.75&#13;
1/   Squire and van der Tak (1975), p. 106.&#13;
2/   The limitation of complex formula is due to the underlying assumptions:&#13;
(a) All variables q, CRI, S, SCF remain constant over time so that&#13;
v also remains constant which generally implies that equation&#13;
(13) overestimates v since it can be expected that the divergence&#13;
between q and i will decrease over time, reducing v.&#13;
(b) All project benefits augment either average private sector&#13;
consumption or public investment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
53.        In the more complex case, where it is assumed that the government&#13;
and private sector save and reinvest some of the returns for public&#13;
investment, v may be estimated by using the following equation:&#13;
q -sq      I                     13&#13;
v   i  sq     CF                     (13)&#13;
This method was applied despite the limitations cited below. The results&#13;
were, however, suspect due to the very large inaccuracy in the marginal&#13;
propensity to save where various sources have provided a range as wide as&#13;
0.08 - 0.33 and resulting unreliable values of v. The present Plan calls for&#13;
a marginal propensity to save of 35 percent by the public sector. If the&#13;
marginal propensity to save is taken to be 0.25 and q to be 12 percent the&#13;
value of v is 6.5. Despite the overestimation problem, allowing for savings&#13;
out of investment gives a much higher estimate of v.&#13;
Table 20:   PRIVATE SECTOR MARGINAL PROPENSITY TO CONSUME, 1974-1979&#13;
(TL millions)&#13;
Private&#13;
Consumption                   AGDP&#13;
Year            GDP          AGDP            (C)            AC           AC&#13;
1973          150429                       105349&#13;
1974          163238        12809          116387         11038        0.861&#13;
1975          177761        14523          123812          7425        0.511&#13;
1976          192783        15022          133701          9889        0.65&#13;
1977          201267         8484          138172          4471        0.52&#13;
1978          208235         6968          144061          5889        0.84&#13;
Ave.                        0.67&#13;
Av.                         0.67&#13;
Source:   Turkey: Policies and Prospects for Growth, The World RAnk, gtptistical&#13;
Annex; Ministry of Finance; Annual Statistics, 1979.&#13;
MPS = 1 - MPC             MPS = Marginal Propensity to Save&#13;
MPS = 0.33                MPC = Marginal Propensity to Consume&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
The Critical Consumption Level (CCL)&#13;
54.       The critical consumption level is defined as that level of per&#13;
capita consumption at which the government regards private consumption just&#13;
as valuable as public income. 1/&#13;
We can derive CCL(c*) implied by the value of v previously computed&#13;
from the public investment approach:&#13;
at  c*, d = v.CF                     (14)&#13;
c&#13;
d  =      c     n                    (15)&#13;
Given n = 1, an existing level of consumption equal to 35 percent of the&#13;
average level of consumption would result in the required value for d. Rela-&#13;
tively small differences in n and v can lead to large differences in CCL. it&#13;
follows that if we can obtain an independent estimate of CCL which matches the&#13;
estimates from n, and v we have significantly increased the reliability and&#13;
acceptability of the estimated set of distribution weight. The 1978 average&#13;
consumption level c was TL 3,350. 2/ The estimate of c* is TL 1,247. Given&#13;
a GDP per capita level of TL 4,886, the ratio of CCL to real per capita GNP&#13;
c*&#13;
is 26 percent, and c=37 percent.&#13;
55.       An independent estimate of the CCL can be derived from the govern-&#13;
ment's fiscal policy by determining the point on the income scale at which the&#13;
government stops taxing or starts subsidizing private consumption. In&#13;
the 1978 tax reform bill of the Ecevit cabinet the minimum alllowance for&#13;
wage earners is rearranged based on the minimum wage. The bill has increased&#13;
the "special deductions" that apply only to State employees and workers by 19&#13;
fold. 3/ Thus, the current deduction of TL 5 will rise to TL 95 a day meaning&#13;
that TL 2,850 of income will be tax free. The general deduction will apply to&#13;
all income so that a family of four will enjoy a tax exemption on TL 360 of&#13;
1/   The CCL may be calculated from the formula&#13;
I&#13;
c(v.CF   )              (16)&#13;
c&#13;
where c is average per capita consumption and CF     is the consumption&#13;
conversion factor.   The CCL is that point at which d/v = CF .&#13;
2/   The gross private consumption and population information are derived&#13;
from Turkey: Policies and Prospects for Growth, 1980 (Forthcoming),&#13;
Statistical Annex.&#13;
3/   Source:   Weekly Special Survey, EBA, April 1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
this income and for a worker or a state employee, this will be added to his&#13;
special deduction, bringing the total to TL 3,210 (equivalent to an annual&#13;
income of TL 38,500). This, however, bears little relation to the subsistence&#13;
level and does not apply to the agricultural sector but is, nonetheless,&#13;
indicative of the government's estimate of a minimum acceptable net income.&#13;
Using current 1978 prices,              c*        =   11.2% and&#13;
GNP&#13;
Per capita&#13;
c*&#13;
-*        =   16.2%&#13;
c&#13;
56.       In summary, one finds that although in the case of Turkey no&#13;
reliable precise estimate of the CCL is possible, the evidence supports the&#13;
previous conclusion that parameter values of n=l;O, CRI=4.5%, reflect approxi-&#13;
mately current government value judgements and -     value of 37 percent is&#13;
c&#13;
is a reasonable estimate. The CCL is 26 percent of the national per capita&#13;
average which is consistent with other results in MIC's where the CCL is&#13;
between one quarter and one half of the per capita average. 1/&#13;
The Accounting Rate of Interest (ARI)&#13;
57.       The Accounting Rate of Interest (ARI) plays a critical role in&#13;
the general application of social benefit-cost analysis because it is the&#13;
principal parameter reflecting the opportunity cost of public income used&#13;
both for projects and to finance other policies such as income used either&#13;
for projects or to finance other policies such as income transfers, consump-&#13;
tion subsidies. Ideally, the ARI should equal the real rate of return&#13;
on marginal investment in the public sector when they are evaluated using&#13;
accounting prices. Alternatively, if the government is borrowing heavily&#13;
from abroad and we accept the assumption that the volume of such borrowing&#13;
and the use of funds are 'rationally' determined, then ARI should equal&#13;
the marginal real cost of such borrowing.&#13;
1/   The CCL can be used as a cross-check on the distribution weight d,&#13;
derived later. But the use of the cross check is based on the assump-&#13;
tion that at the margin, the social value of different types of public&#13;
expenditure, e.g., investment, consumption subsidies, etc., is roughly&#13;
the same. It follows that an independent estimate of the CCL may be seen&#13;
as a test of the initial judgment concerning the subjective parameters,&#13;
given the assumption of an optimal allocation of public resources, or&#13;
as a test of the assumption of an optimum allocation of public resources&#13;
given the initial judgment concerning the judgment parameters.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
58.       Very little work has been done in Turkey on the appraisal of public&#13;
projects using a consistent set of shadow prices. Recent World Bank appraisals&#13;
of Turkish projects have used border prices and only sometimes shadow wages&#13;
have been used. But the implicit conversion factor has varied largely&#13;
from project to project and does not seem to have been based upon systematic&#13;
analysis of the social costs and benefits of employing labor. Subject to&#13;
these qualifications the economic rate of return estimated for World Bank&#13;
appraisal projects have varied between 8-30 percent. But given the low social&#13;
rate of return on import-substituting projects, it is unlikely that the real&#13;
marginal social rate of return on public investment will exceed 10% and will&#13;
probably be near 8 percent.&#13;
59.       If we look at the ARI as the rate of fall overtime in the social&#13;
value of uncommitted public sector income measured at border prices, since&#13;
v is the relative value of public income in terms of consumption, it follows&#13;
that:&#13;
ARI  =   sq + (1-s) q/v CF   1/            (17)&#13;
Table 23 shows the alternative values for ARI computed from equation (17).&#13;
Table 23: THE ACCOUNTING RATE OF INTEREST&#13;
S=0.20       S=0.25       S=0.30&#13;
q =  8%        4.03        4.27          4.58&#13;
q = 12%        6.04        6.40          6.78&#13;
q = 24%       11.95       12.80         13.56&#13;
Taking the combined value of q = 12 percent and a marginal propensity to&#13;
save of 0.30 (Table 23), the ARI will be equal to 6.8. On the other hand,&#13;
the T-1 run of Dervis and Robinson model provides an S = 0.25 which would&#13;
give a value of 6.4. Thus the range of 6.0 &lt; ARI &lt; 6.8 seems a reasonable one.&#13;
This, however, supports the existing evidence that discounting using social&#13;
rates makes more projects acceptable than use of private rates of return. It&#13;
also reflects the high priority on growth through public income expenditure.&#13;
1/   Alternatively we can examine the rate of fall of v;&#13;
ARI = CRI - -     -&#13;
dt   v&#13;
if we assume that the marginal allocation of public income between&#13;
current expenditures and investment remain constant which is questionable&#13;
in the case of Turkey.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
60.       Finally, we can examine this problem in the light of the Turkish&#13;
government's policies towards foreign borrowing. The government and the State&#13;
Economic Enterprises which until recently preferred not to borrow abroad,&#13;
during the latter part of 1970's borrowed heavily on international capital&#13;
markets. It is possible that the Eurocurrency markets represent the marginal&#13;
source of funds. The rate of interest on Eurocurrency loans varies with the&#13;
general market interest rate and with the premium charged on the specific&#13;
loan. It has been recently about 1 3/4 percent points above the LIBOR&#13;
(9-10 percent). Given the rescheduling of Turkish debts and the fact that the&#13;
debts will have to be rolled over on terms which cannot be predicted creates&#13;
an extra source of uncertainty as regards the behavior of the LIBOR and&#13;
exchange rates. Allowing for a risk premium the marginal cost of such borrow-&#13;
ing is pushed up to 11 3/4 percent. If we deduct the expected rate of infla-&#13;
tion for traded commodities we will get a value of 5 percent (+ 0.5) per annum&#13;
for this parameter. 1/   This provides another estimate which we should use&#13;
carefully, given the present standing of Turkey in capital markets. The ARI&#13;
rate of 6.0 will be used in future estimates as a reasonable estimate.&#13;
The Consumption Distribution Weights, d&#13;
61.        The consumption distribution weight, d, for a particular beneficiary&#13;
group will usually have to be estimated in the specifc project context, where&#13;
non-marginal changes are the rule. These weights refer both to the relative&#13;
valuation of consumption changes accruing to different beneficiaries at a&#13;
given time and to consumption over time. 2/ Only in those cases where it may&#13;
be assumed that the project results in marginal changes for people with&#13;
comparable levels of per capita income/consumption can the marginal consump-&#13;
tion distribution weight be applied.&#13;
62.       The d's for different household groups in the population have been&#13;
calculated using;&#13;
w = d/v CF               (19)&#13;
c&#13;
1/   In addition, it is useful to build up an estimate of the ARI through&#13;
an examination of the internal social rate of return of accepted IBRD&#13;
project.&#13;
2/   If there is not interdependence of utility functions;&#13;
Social Welfare (W) = W (d UId U ...),.&#13;
where the d's are social weights on individual consumption and the U's&#13;
are individual utility levels.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
where d is the ratio of national average household consumption and the&#13;
average household consumption in each group, the v value used is 3.4 and&#13;
n = 1, CFc = 0.79.&#13;
63.       The major point that emerges is that consumption accruing to the&#13;
lowest 30 percent of the population is considered substantially more valuable&#13;
than public income. This does reflect the very skewed income distribution&#13;
in Turkey. While per capita GNP has increased, more than 40 percent of the&#13;
total income accrues to the top 10 percent, leaving the bottom group much&#13;
below the national average. There is very little difference with the 1963&#13;
study of income distribution.&#13;
64.        Income distribution on a regional and urban/rural basis is also very&#13;
skewed giving a much higher income to urban sector. The Robinson-Dervis study&#13;
points to some interesting facts. 1/ They found that in their classification&#13;
of the society into 11 socio-economic groups what was obvious was great&#13;
inequality within sectors. The top ranking farmers in their study had high&#13;
incomes comparable to the highest incomes in the urban sector. However,&#13;
poverty was also more concentrated in the rural sector. Thus, average con-&#13;
sumption level gives no indication of welfare levels within the rural sector.&#13;
They also found evidence of large regional inequality and increasing poverty&#13;
as they went towards South East Turkey. Given the degree of poverty in&#13;
Turkey, the pragmatic use of a weighting system that is concerned with the&#13;
issue of poverty rather than inequality may be called for.&#13;
1/   S. Robinson, K. Dervis, "The Sources and Structure of Inequality in&#13;
Turkey (1950-1973)," Princeton - Turkey Project, 1977.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
Table 24: INCOME DISTRIBUTION BY INCOME BRACKET&#13;
% of                     Cumulative&#13;
Income Bracket          Households      % of NI        % NI&#13;
0 -    2,500          4.1             0.3           0.3&#13;
2,500 -     5,000         8.1             1.2           1.5&#13;
5,000 -    10,000        17.8             5.4           6.9&#13;
10,000 -    15,000        20.0            10.1          17.0&#13;
15,000 -    25,000        22.5            17.9          34.9&#13;
2,500 -    50,000        18.1            25.4          60.3&#13;
50,000 -   100,000         6.8            18.6          78.9&#13;
100,000 -   200,000         1.9            10.8          89.7&#13;
200,000 +                   0.7            10.3         100.&#13;
Source: S. Robinson, K. Dervis, (1977).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
Table 25:   MARGINAL CONSUMPTION DISTRIBUTION WEIGHTS, d&#13;
Percentage Average Per Capita&#13;
Population    of Tota h       Income in    /2        Marginal      /3&#13;
Percentile     Income-    Percentile Group    Distribution Weights-      W = 1/CFV&#13;
(%)          (%)       (TL 1968 Prices)   (n = 0.5)   (n = 1.0)    n=0.5   n=l&#13;
0-20         2.5            557             1.24         8.0       0.46   3.03&#13;
21-40         7.0          1,670             0.71         2.66      0.27   1.01&#13;
41-60        15.0          3,342             0.50         1.33      0.18   0.50&#13;
61-80        21.0          4,678             0.42         0.95      0.16   0.36&#13;
81-100       55.0         12,252             0.26         0.36      0.10   0.14&#13;
Total&#13;
Population     100.0           4,455&#13;
/1   This column was derived from K. Dervis and S. Robinson, "The Sources&#13;
and Structure of Inequality in Turkey (1950-1973)", (Princeton-Turkey&#13;
income distribution project, 1977).&#13;
/2   This column was derived by dividing income share of a particular income&#13;
group in total income by the proportion in total population of that&#13;
group.&#13;
/3   The distribution weights were estimated by using d = (-/c)n where c&#13;
is the national average per capita income level and c is the average&#13;
per capita income level in the particular percentile group.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
V. SHADOW WAGE RATE ESTIMATES&#13;
65.       The estimation of shadow wage rates has been carried out in accord-&#13;
ance with the principles adopted in previous studies and the Squire and van&#13;
der Tak methodology has been applied throughout this study. However, given&#13;
the variety of data sources available, it has been possible in this study&#13;
of Turkish national parameters to derive some additional interesting results&#13;
on the basis of the assumptions made. It, nevertheless, remains the case&#13;
that additional information would be of considerable value in refining the&#13;
estimates and reducing uncertainties.&#13;
66.       For the present discussion, we will concentrate on the estimation of&#13;
shadow wages for labor in the following three sectors; rural, urban informal,&#13;
and urban formal. 1/ The rationale behind this categorization is that it does&#13;
correspond to the segmentation of the labor market in Turkey and provides&#13;
a meaningful division into categories for which parameter values relating&#13;
to income weights, expenditure levels, etc., have been estimated. We have,&#13;
therefore, estimated separate SWR's for labor in rural and urban areas, the&#13;
latter being further disaggregated according to whether or not labor is&#13;
employed in sectors where wages are controlled by the government. The cate-&#13;
gorization adopted here is also consistent with that used in the TGT model. 2/&#13;
Clearly a more disaggregated approach dividing labor by skill variation and&#13;
allowing for inter-regional differences will be very enlightening and warrants&#13;
the development of a more detailed data base.&#13;
Population, Labor Force and Employment&#13;
67.       Estimates of Turkey's population cited by the Bank is 43.14 million&#13;
in 1978 with a growth rate around 2.5 percent. The labor force participation&#13;
rate (LFPR) in Turkey has been falling and now stands at 66.29.        Although&#13;
there are some doubts as regards the reliability of the figure there is no&#13;
question that participation rate is unusually low. This is attributable&#13;
partly to the structural changes that have been taking place as the country's&#13;
industrial sector has grown relative to the agricultural sector. However, the&#13;
1/   It is important to realize that strictly speaking the marginal product of&#13;
labor is measured as output foregone in leaving alternative employment&#13;
which in the case of formal urban sector labor is marginal product when&#13;
employed in the rural or informal urban sector. However, indications&#13;
of scarcity of certain kinds of skilled labor in the formal sector and&#13;
the possibility of obtaining better paid jobs (there is a difference&#13;
between public sector and private sector wages in the formal sector),&#13;
through search activities within the formal sector justifies the esti-&#13;
mation of a separate shadow wage rate for this sector.&#13;
2/   K. Dervis, S. Robinson, (1978).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
phenomena of "discouraged workers" also seems to affect the labor force&#13;
participation rate to some extent. This is not surprising given that surplus&#13;
agricultural labor was 4.6 percent of labor supply in the peak season which is&#13;
a lower bound to the actual surplus labor. 1/ The unemployment figure is put&#13;
between 15-25 percent. Turkey despite its Plan does have an unusually high&#13;
agricultural base for a middle income country, with 62 percent of its worker&#13;
force in agriculture. Future increases of employment in this sector are&#13;
considered small and the Plan forsees a fall in agricultural employment. The&#13;
non-agricultural sector has to absorb the entire labor force of 300,000 jobs a&#13;
year. External migration which was a major absorber of employment has been&#13;
falling and does not absorb more than 10,000-15,000 workers per year. The&#13;
high capital intensity resulting from subsidized capital and the drive for&#13;
industrial growth does not help the employment problem either. Increasing&#13;
labor costs to employers and labor unrest are other factors that influence the&#13;
choice of a more capital intensive technology when it is possible.&#13;
Trends in Real Wage Rates&#13;
68.       Minimum wage legislation and unionization are important aspects of&#13;
the urban labor market in Turkey. Legislation pertaining to minimum wages&#13;
has been present for more than forty years. They have reflected government&#13;
statements concerning social justice. However, instead of being a guide for&#13;
the rest of the economy, in practice minimum wages have followed actual market&#13;
wages and have been the dependent variable. The minimum wage applies mainly&#13;
to the 2 million public sector employees (12 percent of the labor force) 2/,&#13;
but the State Economic Enterprise wages are above the minimum wages. Although&#13;
most of the unionized workers get more than the minimum wage, the wage laws&#13;
provide insight into the rate of change of market wages, and are also used in&#13;
union negotiations. The nominal wages rose from TL 18 in 1970 to TL 180 in&#13;
1979, although after tax real wages show very little change. The extent of&#13;
unionization in the urban formal sector has grown to 57 percent of the indus-&#13;
trial labor force and the unions strength and activity has been increasing.&#13;
The evidence of union activity does have certain implications as regards the&#13;
imperfections in the labor market.&#13;
69.       The labor market in Turkey has been very disturbed in recent years.&#13;
Nominal wages as well as the wage cost to employers have been rising rapidly.&#13;
For 1977 average daily wages were about 70 percent higher than official data&#13;
due to employers' contribution to the social security system, yearly bonuses&#13;
and other fringe benefits. The tax system also has favored the fringe bene-&#13;
fits (taxed at 10 percent) agai:nst nominal wages (taxed at 30 percent). In&#13;
fact according to the private sector surveys, the fringe benefits/nominal wage&#13;
1/   Turkey: Policies and Prosnects for Growth. The World Bank. 1980&#13;
(Forthcoming).&#13;
2/   Turkey: Policies and Prospects for Growth, The World Bank, 1980&#13;
(Forthcoming).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
ratio has risen to 90 percent. 1/ This does make the nominal wage an unreal-&#13;
istic figure to use in the estimates and we will need to allow for this&#13;
divergence. However, the inflation rate has been very high and it rose to&#13;
about 50 percent in 1978. The wage rises have always been behind price rises&#13;
and once adjustment is made for the inflation rate, the 1978 real wage repre-&#13;
sents only a 6 percent gain over the observed wage in 1970. 2/ Moreover,&#13;
since the tax system is based on nominal wages the increases in nominal wages&#13;
have been taxed away. 3/ The real after tax earnings during 1970-1977 rose by&#13;
only 1 percent. Moreover, if we allow for the increase in average labor pro-&#13;
ductivity in the non-agricultural sector, (productivity growth rate was 28&#13;
percent in 1970-76) it is obvious that workers have not reaped the benefits&#13;
of higher productivity and have not achieved higher real wages despite the&#13;
increase in wage costs to employers.&#13;
70.       Wage levels for Government workers comprising 15 percent of the non-&#13;
agricultural labor force (830,000 civil servants) shows that the real wages&#13;
in 1977 are only 70% of their 1970 level, but the estimates are not clear as&#13;
regards inclusion or exclusion of fringe benefits, bonuses, etc. Most public&#13;
sector employers, however, receive wages in excess of the minimum wage. In&#13;
1978 the average nominal increases in wages and salaries of the State Economic&#13;
Enterprises employees were around 48 percent which implies a reduction in real&#13;
disposable income as increases in wages have been eroded by rapidly accelerat-&#13;
ing inflation and higher marginal tax rates on income.&#13;
71.       Given the large agricultural base of the economy (62 percent) there&#13;
is a great problem regards wage trends in this sector. The recent Plan does&#13;
not mention employment effects in this sector and there is a projection of&#13;
a fall in employment that further reflects the surplus labor problem. The&#13;
minimum wage legislation has set TL 90 as the relevant figure in the agricul-&#13;
ture sector. This, however, is not a very good guide to agricultural wages.&#13;
The peak agricultural wage observed by Bhalla in 1978 was TL 125 which is&#13;
consistent with the figures used in the Forestry Project in 1977.        The&#13;
report used a slack season wage rate of TL 40 and a peak season rate of&#13;
TL 120. Given the large seasonal variations in different regions, disaggre-&#13;
gated regional data would allow far greater insight into real agricultural&#13;
wages in Turkey.&#13;
1/   "The Turkish Economy:   Prospects for Growth Within Stability," TUSIAD,&#13;
1978. Their results are based on a survey conducted in 429 plants.&#13;
2/   Turkey: Policies and Prospects for Growth, The World Bank,     1980 (Fortncoming)&#13;
3/   In our analysis of shadow wages, this may not cause a problem if private&#13;
and public incomes are considered equally valuable and in fact public&#13;
income may be valued more highly in the case of Turkey. However, this&#13;
depends on the value of v and income distribution objectives.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
72.       In view of the considerable degree of variation in wage rates&#13;
within the informal urban sector it is worth emphasizing certain aspects of&#13;
our treatment of urban labor markets. Additional employment in the urban&#13;
sector generated by a project is filled directly by new migrants from rural&#13;
areas as well as moving up the job scale. Therefore, increases, in the number&#13;
of jobs available will be matched by a decline in the number of unemployed or&#13;
underemployed urban dwellers plus a flow of rural migrants. The total flow of&#13;
migrants induced by additional employment is likely to be substantially larger&#13;
than the number of jobs occupied by migrants since there will also be a flow&#13;
of dependents over a certain period of time.&#13;
Table 26: WAGE STRUCTURE /a&#13;
(TL per day)&#13;
1970      1972        1976       1977      1979&#13;
Minimum wage               15.5-19.5   22-25       60.0 /b   110 /c     180&#13;
Real Minimum Wage /d         18.0       17.0       21.7       19.-       20.7 /e&#13;
Nominal Wages&#13;
Public Sector             38.7        48.7     132.2       178.1&#13;
Private Sector            33.0        41.3     105.9       128.7&#13;
Real Wages&#13;
Public Sector             38.7        35.5      47.9        51.3&#13;
Private Sector            33.0        30.1      38.3        37.1&#13;
Labor Costs /f                          88.1 /g   119.4      306.0&#13;
Source:  Turkey:   Policies and Prospects for Growth, The World Bank, 1980&#13;
(Forthcoming).&#13;
/a   Based on data of Social Insurance Institute.&#13;
7W   Prevailing on June 1976.&#13;
Tc   January 1978.&#13;
Td   Deflated by Istanbul CPI, 1970 = 100.&#13;
7e   Deflated by June CPI for Istanbul (870, 1970 = 100).&#13;
7T   Costs of hiring a worker including wages, premia, and benefits.&#13;
Tg    1973.&#13;
73.       A class of migration models has been developed to explain the co-&#13;
existence of high levels of urban unemployment and rural-urban migration.&#13;
These models are characterized by an inflexible wage differential between the&#13;
rural and urban sectors and by intersectoral labor transfers that continue&#13;
until there is equality between the expected urban wage defined as the pro-&#13;
duct of the probability of being employed and the prevailing urban wage and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
the rural wage. 1/ At the core of these models is a migration function with&#13;
urban employment probability as well as rural and urban wages as determining&#13;
variables. One characteristic common to many of these models is that they&#13;
imply a constant rate of urban unemployment, which in turn implies that the&#13;
migration response M, namely, the number of migrants who will come to the city&#13;
as one additional job is created, can be expressed as the ratio of total&#13;
urban labor force, L, to total urban employment, N:      M = L/N 2/     (20)&#13;
The precise formulation of the shadow wage rate depends upon tFe nature of&#13;
the labor market and behavior of migrant workers. Since information on these&#13;
issues in Turkey is scarce, one has to adopt a very simple model. This remains&#13;
an area that merits deeper investigation, the results of which could be used&#13;
to improve the estimates.&#13;
Social and Efficiency Wages&#13;
74.       It is usual in project appraisal to distinguish between shadow&#13;
prices calculated on an efficiency basis and social shadow prices. The dis-&#13;
tinction between them is due to the different approaches adopted in the treat-&#13;
ment of the consumption and distributional effects of income payments. The&#13;
traditional efficiency prices (TEP) measure simply the opportunity costs of&#13;
various types of labor in their alternative forms of employment; in effect the&#13;
marginal output of labor forgone elsewhere because of its use in the project.&#13;
The extended efficiency prices (EEP) also incorporate allowances for the&#13;
social cost and benefits of income payments or transfers. Commitment of addi-&#13;
tional resources to consumption as a result of wage payments will have a net&#13;
social cost, when there is judged to be a premium on public savings relative&#13;
to private consumption. The Social Prices (SP) incorporate distributional and&#13;
other considerations (mainly of externalities) by introducing income weights&#13;
which vary according to the real income of the recipient. The differences&#13;
between (EEP) and (SP) is that the former treats all income recipient as if&#13;
they were at the average consumption level c, whereas the latter takes&#13;
account of costs and benefits associated with the transfer of income to&#13;
households with below average consumption levels. In this study, three sets&#13;
of shadow prices have been calculated:&#13;
(i) Traditional Efficiency Prices.&#13;
(ii) Extended Efficiency Prices.&#13;
(iii) Social Prices.&#13;
1/   S. Harris and M. Todaro, "Migration, Unemployment and Development:&#13;
A Two Sector Analysis"; American Economic Review, March 1970, Vol.&#13;
60; S.E. Stiglitz, 'Alternative Theories of Wage Determination and&#13;
Unemployment in LDC's: The Labor Turnover Model' Quarterly Journal&#13;
of Economics, May 1974.&#13;
2/   Mazumdar, D. "The Rural-Urban Wage Gap, Migration, and the Shadow Wage",&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Papers No. 197, 1975.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
In terms of the TEP system, if we assume the market for the type of&#13;
labor concerned is reasonably efficient, then the marginal product of labor&#13;
(m) in its alternative use is taken as a measure of forgone output. To obtain&#13;
its value at border prices requires adjustment by means of an accounting&#13;
ratio (SCF). 1/&#13;
Shadow Wage = SCF.m      (21)&#13;
75.       In terms of our categorization of labor we can measure the marginal&#13;
productivity of labor in the different sectors with varying degrees of&#13;
difficulty. It is necessary given the importance of (m) to examine the issue&#13;
briefly. Generally, the market wage is taken as the measure of (m). This is&#13;
a good approach when the relevant labor markets are active and market forces&#13;
work so that the wage level is equal to the value of the marginal product of&#13;
labor at the margin. Labor markets for unskilled labor may be sufficiently&#13;
active even in rural areas to permit the use of this method. The market price&#13;
for labor is determined by the interaction of demand and supply curves with&#13;
the private demand curve being the marginal labor productivity curve and the&#13;
private supply curve determined by the opportunities for alternative work and&#13;
private disutility of effort. It is only within the framework of a neoclassical&#13;
model that perfect labor markets exist with no rigidities, flexible wages, full&#13;
employment, maximizing behaviour information.&#13;
76.       In Turkey there is evidence of large surplus labor (4.5 million at&#13;
peak season) and large unemployment (15-25 percent). Marginal product of&#13;
labor particularly in the agriculture sector is likely to be low but not equal&#13;
to zero as in the Lewis model.   As Sen has pointed out, .       even if the&#13;
marginal product of labor could fall to zero for some total amount of labor,&#13;
that would not be a point of work equilibrium unless the peasants had no dis-&#13;
utility of effort, the work equilibrium would be a positive marginal product&#13;
of labor". 2/&#13;
77.       In the case of Turkey, given the imperfection in all labor markets&#13;
in serious, careful studies are required to get reasonable measures for (m).&#13;
In the rural sector the problem is the existence of surplus labor as well as&#13;
open unemployment. The minimum wage legislation decreed TL 90 to be the rele-&#13;
vant wage in the rural sector. The existence of open and disguised unemploy-&#13;
ment would indicate that marginal product of labor would be lower than what&#13;
the wage level represents. The Northern Forestry Project Appraisal Report&#13;
estimated the marginal product of labor in peak season to be equivalent to&#13;
TL 120 and in the slack season to be TL 40. Marginal product of labor can be&#13;
estimated using a weighted average of wages that uses seasonal employment as&#13;
1/   This approach is not suitable when a project has an excess migration&#13;
effect.&#13;
2/   Amartya Sen, Employment, Technology and Development, 1975, p. 37,&#13;
Clarendon Press, Oxford.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
weights. 1/ The marginal product of labor in the agricultural sector is&#13;
estimated to be equivalent to TL 60.&#13;
78.       The marginal product of labor in the informal urban sector poses&#13;
some estimation and specification problems particularly given the variation in&#13;
skill level in this group. The surplus labor and disguised unemployment&#13;
measures are very difficult to measure in this sector and there is no way of&#13;
deriving labor utilization ratios. However, it is reasonable to take the&#13;
appropriate (m) in this sector to be very close to the marginal product of&#13;
labor in the rural areas. The observation of the Dervis-Robinson estimates&#13;
also gives very similar measures. Thus it is reasonable to assume that at the&#13;
margin the (m) of labor in the informal urban sector is close to that in the&#13;
rural sector. We will take (m) to be equal to 60 within this sector. Sen-&#13;
sitivity analysis is carried out using M = 70 as well. The urban informal&#13;
sector wage figure is difficult to estimate. Unfortunately, Turkish and other&#13;
data do not provide any conclusive measure of the wage level in this sector.&#13;
It is, nonetheless, true that the wage level would be at least marginally&#13;
higher than rural wages to make up for migration costs. The wage level for&#13;
this sector is estimated to be TL 110 which is lower than the present minimum&#13;
wage legislation but higher than the average wage level in the rural sector.2/&#13;
This figure is also consistent with the estimate derived from TGT model.&#13;
79.       To derive a reasonable value for the marginal product in the urban&#13;
formal sector the minimum wage and average wages are useful statistics. The&#13;
1/   Formally M =EDj   Wj       (22)&#13;
Sj&#13;
E j=l&#13;
M   =  value of forgone marginal product of labor&#13;
Wj  =  monthly observed wage rate&#13;
Dj  =  monthly utilization of labor&#13;
Sj  =  monthly availability of labor&#13;
where, j=l, ...12&#13;
Given the above method is costly and time-consuming a short-cut might&#13;
be to assume that m = w during peak seasons and estimate labor utiliza-&#13;
tion during slack periods. The weighted average of peak and slack&#13;
seasons estimated for Turkey was TL 59.&#13;
2/   Sabot in his study of migration has concluded that the marginal urban&#13;
resident, given the prospect of eventually finding a high wage job will&#13;
accept an urban income equivalent to his marginal product in the rural&#13;
areas during his search period. (Sabot, 1977).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- EL -&#13;
minimum wage has been raised to TL 180. 1/ Average daily wage is higher due&#13;
to fringe benefit and bonuses, etc. If the ratio of fringe benefits to&#13;
nominal wages is taken to be 90 percent then taking into account the differen-&#13;
tial tax structure the average income in the formal sector will be TL 270 in&#13;
1978 prices. This is the figure we will use as the market wage rate. However,&#13;
it is necessary to point out to large variations partly dependent on relative&#13;
union strength. The weighted average of the market wages in the urban formal&#13;
sector is a reasonable basis but it obviously overestimates the marginal pro-&#13;
duct of labor. The market wage is upward bias and marginal product of labor&#13;
in the formal urban sector is taken to be equivalent to TL 200 in 1978.&#13;
Estimation of Shadow Wages&#13;
80.      -The shadow wages for the three sectors are estimated according to&#13;
the following equations. Applying the (TEP) approach, the shadow wage rate is&#13;
equal to labor's forgone marginal product at accounting prices.&#13;
SWR    SCF.m&#13;
(SWR   SCF.m.M if we allow for migration effects)      (23)&#13;
The (EEP) approach also takes account of the social cost of increased&#13;
consumption:&#13;
SWR     SCF.m + (w-m) CF   1/    (24)&#13;
c -&#13;
which is appropriate if the government's sole aim is to maximize growth.&#13;
If SCF = CF   then SWR = SCF.w.   The (SP) is used to allow for government&#13;
c&#13;
1/   There is a conceptual problem as regards the relevant measure to be&#13;
used for (m) in the formal sector. The rural-urban migration model&#13;
assumed together with the existence of large surplus labor and unemploy-&#13;
ment in the other two sectors may be used as an agrument for using the&#13;
output foregone in the rural or informal urban sectors as the relevant&#13;
measure for (m) in the formal urban sector. However, there is evidence&#13;
of relatively high marginal productivity of labor in non-agricultural&#13;
activities and in particular in industry. Also despite unionization and&#13;
government social planning objectives which increase the degree of&#13;
imperfection in the urban formal labor market, the latter sector in&#13;
Turkey does approach the neoclassicial model more closely than the other&#13;
two sectors. Obviously, the average wage overestimates the marginal&#13;
product of labor in this sector. It does indicate, however, that the&#13;
marginal product of labor in the urban formal sector is much closer to&#13;
the formal wage level than to the marginal product of labor in the rural&#13;
sector.&#13;
2/   Squire and van der Tak (1975), p. 84.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
objectives including growth and income redistribution.     In the simple case&#13;
where increased effort has zero social cost (O = 0).&#13;
SWR = SCF.m + (w-m) (Cf   - v )                    (SP1) (25)&#13;
c   v&#13;
In this case the shadow wage rate will be higher the more important the growth&#13;
objective as reflected in the value of v.    A more complete method allows for&#13;
O to vary and also takes into account the social cost of reduced leisure as&#13;
well as differential consumption weights d:&#13;
d             ed&#13;
SWR = SCF.m + (w-m) (CF   -   ) + (w-m)  O0)       (SP2) (26)&#13;
c   v              v&#13;
where e = ratio of the private value of forgone leisure to&#13;
the market value of increased consumption.&#13;
When 0 &gt; 1, the government considers increased private effort less of a&#13;
cost than output forgone on consumption (and conversely if 0 &lt; 1). We also&#13;
experiment with different values of d by setting d initially equal to 1. Then&#13;
we allow for a difference in the weighing system applied to the rural and&#13;
urban informal sector by using a d value equal to 3.03 derived from our income&#13;
distribution anaylsis Table 25 and leave the d value for the urban formal&#13;
sector to be equal to 1.&#13;
81.       The results differ depending on which approach is used.     However,&#13;
given the discussion that went on before, and the critisms to the implicit&#13;
value judgment underlying the efficiency approach and there is reason to&#13;
consider the results of SPI as reasonable. 1/ More interesting work can be&#13;
done if the consumption weights for rural and urban sectors are estimated&#13;
separately, but this will have to wait for a more disaggregated data base.&#13;
The results derived in Tables 27 and 28 do confirm the expectation that (TEP)&#13;
gives the lowest shadow wage rates while the (EEP) provides the highest&#13;
estimates. Moreover, the accounting ratios for the three sectors are very&#13;
close. The accounting ratios would lend support to projects which are of a&#13;
more labor intensive nature both in the rural sector. The migration effects&#13;
reinforce rural employment possibilities by raising the SWR in the formal and&#13;
informal urban sectors (Table 29). The figures estimated, although based on&#13;
the assumptions made about the Turkish labor market, do provide a useful basis&#13;
for the project analyst to value labor in project appraisal.&#13;
1/   SP1 is chosen rather than SP2 on the grounds of practicality and not&#13;
any other criteria. Estimations of 0 and e needed for SP2 may be very&#13;
difficult and are more meaningful when disaggregated data is used to&#13;
derive project specific shadow wages.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
Table 27: SHADOW WAGES IN TURKEY&#13;
(In Turkish Liras)&#13;
TEP_,       EEPL2      SML       SP2ML&#13;
Rural Sector                35         59         50       55&#13;
Urban Informal          (i) 35         75        60        68&#13;
Sector /5            (ii) 41         73        61        67&#13;
Urban Formal Sector        118        173        153      163&#13;
/1  TEP    Traditional Efficiency   SWR = SCF.m&#13;
Prices&#13;
/2  EEP - Extended Efficiency       SWR = SCF.m + (w-m) CF-&#13;
Prices&#13;
/3  SP1 - Social Prices             SWR = SCF.m + (w-m) (CF - d)&#13;
_                                             ~~~~~~~~~~c  v&#13;
/4  SP2 - Social Prices              SWR = SCF.m + (w-m) (CF   - v) + (w-m) 0 ed/v&#13;
c   v&#13;
/5  (i)-     m  = 60&#13;
(ii) -   m   = 70&#13;
Table 28: ACCOUNTING RATIOS FOR LABOR&#13;
TEP        EEP     SP1       SP2&#13;
Rural Sector                  0.39      0.65    0.56      0.60&#13;
Urban Informal Sector    (i)  0.32      0.66    0.55      0.61&#13;
(ii)  0.37      0.68     0.55     0.61&#13;
Urban Formal Sector           0.43      0.64    0.57      0.60&#13;
Table 29:   SHADOW WAGE RATES&#13;
(In Turkish Liras)&#13;
TEP*     EEP*  SP1*    SP2*&#13;
Urban Informal Sector          44      84     69      76&#13;
Urban Formal Sector           148     203    183     192&#13;
*Include migration effects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
Table 30: SHADOW WAGE RATES&#13;
(In Turkish Liras)&#13;
SPI       SP2&#13;
Rural Sector                   32       145&#13;
Urban Informal Sector   (i)    31        53&#13;
(ii)   37         55&#13;
Urban Formal Sector           112       143&#13;
Take d = 3.30 for the Rural and Urban&#13;
Informal Sectors.&#13;
d -1 for the Urban Formal Sector&#13;
Table 31: ACCOUNTING RATIOS FOR LABOR&#13;
SPI       SP2&#13;
Rural Sector                 0.36       0.50&#13;
Urban Informal Sector   (i)   0.28      0.48&#13;
(ii)  0.34       0.50&#13;
Urban Formal Sector          0.41       0.53&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
II&#13;
(  HG3881.5 .W57 W67 no.392 c.3  I&#13;
i Mashayekhi, Afsaneh. &#13;
I Shadow prices for project &#13;
a -1I   aDDraisal in Turkey'/ I/&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1555043">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1980/05/1555043/shadow-prices-project-appraisal-turkey
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1980/05/1555043/shadow-prices-project-appraisal-turkey</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1980/05/1555043/shadow-prices-project-appraisal-turkey</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/12/000178830_98101903404544/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/12/000178830_98101903404544/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-07-12T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1980-05-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Shadow prices for project appraisal in Turkey
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The analytical and empirical basis for
            the estimation of shadow prices, which may be used for the
            evaluation of projects in Turkey in the next five years, are
            described. Shadow prices are defined as the increase in
            welfare resulting from any marginal change in the
            availability of commodities or factors of production. Until
            recently, traditional appraisal methods have emphasized the
            growth objectives of a project and have been concerned
            primarily with the national income parameter. More recently
            however, it has been argued that the operational assumption
            that all units of income make the same contribution to
            growth may be untenable. The World Bank and others advocate
            a more consistent estimation method that takes explicit
            account of the impact of the project on the distribution of
            income, both between investment and consumption and among
            different groups in society. Estimates of various efficiency
            pricing and social pricing parameters are generated, taking
            into account Turkish import and export strategies and
            government objectives.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Shadow prices for project appraisal in Turkey
        </docna>
        <display_title>Shadow prices for project
            appraisal in Turkey</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1980/05/1555043/shadow-prices-project-appraisal-turkey</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Access to Markets,Markets and Market Access</subtopic>
        <teratopic>International Economics and Trade</teratopic>
        <count>Turkey</count>
        <authors>
            <author>MASHAYEKHI, A.</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Eastern Europe!$!107233</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe!$!80461</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Middle East!$!80463</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903404544</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Macro/non-trade</subsc>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 392</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>International Economics and Trade</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Economic growth; Income distribution; Income
            levels; Price policy; Pricing; Project appraisal; Project
            evaluation; Shadow prices; Social prices
            Accounting,balance of payments,Benefit
            Analysis,border price,Capital flows,Capital Goods,capital
            markets,consumption patterns,cost analysis,debt,demand
            curves,demand management,devaluation,discount
            rate,disequilibrium,Distribution of Income,domestic
            market,Economic analysis,economic change,economic
            life,economic policies,economic
            structure,economists,Efficiency
            Wages,elasticities,Elasticity,elasticity of demand,empirical
            basis,equilibrium,equilibrium models,exchange
            payments,exchange rate,excise taxes,expenditures,export
            markets,exports,fiscal policy,foreign exchange,general
            equilibrium model,growth policy,growth
            rate,imports,Income,income distribution,income
            groups,industrialization,inefficiency,inflation,inflation
            rate,Intermediate Goods,international trade,labor
            costs,Labor Force,leisure,marginal costs,Marginal
            Product,Marginal Productivity,Marginal Utility,market
            distortions,market incentives,market prices,market
            value,monetary policy,national income,opportunity
            cost,perfect competition,Political Economy,present
            value,price distortions,private
            consumption,producers,production costs,production
            function,profitability,quotas,rapid industrialization,rate
            of exchange,Real Wages,rebates,rent seeking,savings,savings
            rates,scarcity value,Shadow prices,shadow pricing,Social
            prices,social pricing,spread,state
            intervention,substitution,taxation,total costs,trade
            policies,unemployment,valuation,value judgments,value of
            output,Wage Rates,Wages
        </keywd>
        <owner>ECS</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Eastern Europe</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Middle East</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP392</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Formulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Implementation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Productivity-Led Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition  Community Based Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition  Raising Awareness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition  Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Employment and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Improving Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Market Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets, Job Creation and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Minimum Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Balance of Payments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Turkey</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>