<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>FILE COPY&#13;
European Community Protection Against&#13;
Manufactured Imports from Developing&#13;
Countries: A         Case     Study     in  the   PoiticaITERNATYONAL "M(ARt u,&#13;
Economy of Protection                                        SWP432&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 432&#13;
October 1980&#13;
Prepared by: E. Verreydt and J. Waelbroeck (Consultants)&#13;
Economic Analysis and Projections Department&#13;
Copyright ® 1980&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the autho&#13;
and should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated a   r  XU .&#13;
organizations, or to any individual acting in their behalf.  X&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the authors&#13;
and should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated&#13;
organizations, or to any individual acting in their behalf.'&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 432&#13;
October 1980&#13;
EUROPEAN COMMUNITY PROTECTION AGAINST MANUFACTURED IMPORTS FROM DEVELOPING&#13;
COUNTRIES; A CASE STUDY IN THE POLITICAL ECONOMY OF PROTECTION&#13;
This work in progress report is part of an inquiry being undertaken&#13;
by the World Bank in conjunction with scholars from twelve industrial countries&#13;
into the penetration of the markets of industrial countries by exports of&#13;
manufactures from developing countries. The project seeks to establish the&#13;
shares of industrial country markets held by the developing countries, changes&#13;
in such shares in the 1970s, and why they vary among industry groups and countries.&#13;
The aim is to assist developing and industrial countries to improve their policies&#13;
through a better understanding of trade patterns and protectionist pressures.&#13;
This paper focuses on the institutional aspects of decision-making&#13;
in the market for protection in the European Community. After a brief&#13;
discussion of the protectionist instruments available, it focuses on the&#13;
interrelationships among the four decision levels involved in thei formulation&#13;
of trade policies.  It then turns to the,general- goals of't'hese policies:&#13;
efficiency, income distribution, avoidance of retaliation, and provision of&#13;
public goods, in particular creating a stable political and economic framework&#13;
for future growth of the Economic Community. The last section describes the&#13;
objectives of interest groups and the Community's policy responses to their&#13;
demands.&#13;
We are grateful for comments from the participants at the NBER conference&#13;
on Import Competition and Adjustment: Theory and Policy held at M.I.T. in May&#13;
1980 where this paper was first presented.&#13;
Prepared by: E. Verreydt and J. Waelbroeck (Consultants)&#13;
Economic Analysis and Projections Department&#13;
Copyright c 1980&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H St. N.W.&#13;
Washington D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INTRODUCTION&#13;
In recent years the European Community (EC) has been torn&#13;
between its original mandate as an institution set up to promote free&#13;
movement of goods and production factors, and the strong pressures&#13;
for protection resulting from the mid 1970s recession and the sharp&#13;
accompanying difficulties experienced by a number of industries. By&#13;
agreeing to the Tokyo Round package, the Community committed itself&#13;
to participate in an unprecedently wide ranging package of multilateral&#13;
trade liberalization, the precise significance of which still remains&#13;
to be hammered out in the GATT committees which will implement the&#13;
newly agreed codes of behavior. The Lome agreement has been renego-&#13;
tiated, and the Generalized Scheme of Preferences (GSP) is to be&#13;
renewed soon.  Both are basicaly      ate      greements concluded&#13;
before the recession. On the other hand, there have been sharp&#13;
turns of the protection screw especially for textiles, clothing&#13;
and steel, and the EC has found itself involved in trying to moderate&#13;
a subsidy war in shipbuilding.&#13;
The aim of this paper is to review these developments from&#13;
the point of view of the political economy of protection.    This''&#13;
approach, developed by a number of recent authors, focuses on the&#13;
political motivatTions for protection, and leads to conjet-ures which&#13;
may be verified econometrical y.   Here, however, we take a non&#13;
economeitric approach.  It appears worthwhile to look at the recent&#13;
nistory of protection in the EC in the spirit of a case study, to&#13;
try to explain recent events using this new approach to international&#13;
trade theory. This may also be a useful way"of verifying its validity,&#13;
and may help to put flesh on abstract ideas. Finally, the case study&#13;
approach may point out aspects of the problem which have been under-&#13;
researched.                                   ,&#13;
The paper is organized as follows.' We first discuss the&#13;
institutional aspects of decision making in the market for protection.&#13;
The instruments available - tariffs and import quotas, trade adjust-&#13;
ment assistance subsidies, and cartels - .are;presented. This is&#13;
complemented by a description of the interrelations among the four&#13;
decision levels involved in the formulation of trade policies. The&#13;
paper then turns to the general goals of these policies: efficiency,&#13;
income distribution, avoidance of retaliation, and provision of&#13;
public goods, in particular creating a stable political and economic&#13;
framework for future growth of the EC. Theliast section describes&#13;
the objectives of interest groups and the ECIs policy responses to&#13;
their demands.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
I.  DECISION MAKING IN THE MARKET FOR PROTECTION&#13;
It is useful to organize the discussion of EC protection&#13;
policies around the concept of a political market for protection,&#13;
where special interest groups seek to pressure policy makers to supply&#13;
desired measures. The description should recognize the way in which&#13;
national interests perceived by voters may block the measures sought&#13;
by intepst groups through the "adding machine" of democratic decision&#13;
making.&#13;
Unlike the usual presentations of the political economy of&#13;
protection which are not specific about the institutions through which&#13;
the political market operates, because their authors are concerned&#13;
with general hypotheses, this case study discusses the institutional&#13;
aspects of trade policy making in the EC at length.&#13;
The institutional framework&#13;
Under the Rome Treaty, the EC is responsible for the establish-&#13;
ment of trade policies. To an academic economist, used to considering&#13;
trade theory as a separate subJect, this looks like a clear mandate,&#13;
but in practice, the range of government policies which have an impact&#13;
on trade is extremely wide, including for instance social legislation,&#13;
safety and health regulations, and other policy areas which at first&#13;
sight would not seem to be relevant.&#13;
Tariffs and Import quotas&#13;
Even for decisions which are clearly related to trade, govern-&#13;
ments of member countries retain significant residual powers. Thus&#13;
while tariffs are under the control of the EC, customs regulation are&#13;
not.  This is important in enabling countries to engage in "off-shore"&#13;
processing to carry out labor intensive stages of fabrication in low&#13;
wage countries. The transfer of import quotas to EC control is not&#13;
complete: France and Italy in particular continue to impose quotas 2&#13;
on imports of automobiles and electronic goods from Japan for example.-&#13;
A broad penumbra of quotas is operated through market sharing arrange-&#13;
ments at the business level (for example imports of Japanese cars into&#13;
the UK), backed by governments and carefully designed not to run foul&#13;
of EC anti-cartel regulations. Finally a third country (usually a&#13;
developing country) may receive a sharp warning that it should restrict&#13;
exports of a good to an EC country "voluntarily" for the sake of good&#13;
1/&#13;
2/ See Enzo Grilli&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
commercial relations it (usually) decides to obey. No visible measure&#13;
is taken by a public authority in the EC, but imports are clearly&#13;
restricted. Even quotas which are formally run by the EC may be&#13;
allocated between member countries, and the reshipment of the imported&#13;
goods across frontiers within the Community is then controlled as&#13;
provided for under Article 115 of the Treaty. Such quotas are formally&#13;
decided by the EC, but it is clear that the country affected has a good&#13;
deal to say about their management.&#13;
In a slow, and in principle irreversible process, the residual&#13;
import quotas of member countries have been gradually transferred to&#13;
Brussels. Progress in this direction is embodied in a "liberalized&#13;
list" of goods over which member countries have given up the right to&#13;
impose import quotas. It is important not to lose sight of the fact&#13;
that Community institutions have no enforcement power against national&#13;
governments. But in the context of a philosophy of "I am your leader,&#13;
I must follow you" these institutions' actions may be dictated by a&#13;
concern to forestall or to take over illegal trade restrictions by&#13;
member governments. This was quite obvious at the time of the 1977&#13;
renewal of the Multi Fibre Agreement (MFA). The very tough negotiating&#13;
stance of the EC was in part motivated by France's introduction of&#13;
quotas on textiles and clothing in violation of Community rules, and&#13;
clear indications that other member countries might introduce illegal&#13;
restrictions if the EC did not act to restrict imports sharply.&#13;
The EC itself is subject to the rules of the GATT, and thus&#13;
does not fully control the trade policy instruments which are in&#13;
principle available to it. Governments do - though fairly rarely -&#13;
violate EC rules and - much more frequently - fail to observe or&#13;
implement them. The Community, whose only power resides in the legal&#13;
superstructure created by the Treaty of Rome, has to be narrowly&#13;
legalistic in respecting GATT treaties. This in practice deprives&#13;
it of any control over normal tariffs though imposition of anti-&#13;
dumping and other temporary tariffs is of course possible. As the&#13;
implementation of the Tokyo Round leads to the establishment of agreed&#13;
codes of behaviour the freedom of actions of the Community is becoming&#13;
further restricted. Conceivably, indeed, implementation of the Tokyo&#13;
Round may be so successful that GATT rules might regulate aspects of&#13;
national policies over which the EC has not succeeded in establishing&#13;
control.&#13;
Trade adjustment assistance and subsidies&#13;
Eronomic theory has tended to regard adjustment assistance&#13;
more and more as a trade policy instrument which is as important as&#13;
tariffs and other measures of restriction. The pressures of interest&#13;
groups, to the extent that they cannot be controlled, can either lead&#13;
to market distorting measures of import restriction, and hence to a&#13;
waste of resources, or the interest groups can be bribed by offers of&#13;
assistance which reduce their losses and give them time to find other&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
employment.  These two ways.of dealing with protectionist pressures are&#13;
sometimes termed "negative" and "positive" adjustment.&#13;
The concept of trade adjustment assistance is clear in trade&#13;
theory for this is concerned with a clearly defined and distinct area&#13;
of investigation. The idea is much more difficult to apply to the real&#13;
world., in which agents are continually subjected to shocks of all types&#13;
and origins. Trade adjustment assistance is a workable policy concept&#13;
only if a way is formed of "tagging" agents whose problems are caused&#13;
by trade, but such tagging is extremely difficult to carry out fairly&#13;
and accurately. To the extent that agents whose misfortune is due to&#13;
trade are better treated than when misfortune has other causes a problem&#13;
of equity arises; inev-itably there is pressure to extend the scale of&#13;
trade assistance benefits across the board, and this can prove very&#13;
costly.&#13;
Finally it is very difficult to distinguish trade adjustment&#13;
assistance from subsidies.   The difference between these is that at&#13;
some point in the future, the beneficiaries of the first will shift&#13;
their production resources to a new type of activity which does not&#13;
require public aid to be viable. If they do not, they are relying on&#13;
a subsidy to continue an inefficient productive activity, as wastefully&#13;
as if they were protected by a tariff. 1   Indeed economists have some-&#13;
times used the term "domestic protection" to describe the economic&#13;
impact of subsidies. The gift of prophecy is needed to distinguish&#13;
between the two types of aid, and this is a second reason to doubt&#13;
that the theoretical concept of "trade adjustment assistance" is useful&#13;
for analysis of the real world.&#13;
It is probably fortunate that lack of funds prevents the EC&#13;
from engaging in the dubious business of allocating trade adjustment&#13;
assistance on a major scale. Two special funds were set up initially:&#13;
the European Social Fund, and the ECSC reconversion and readaptation&#13;
fund, set up under the Rome and ECSC Treaties respectively. In 1975,&#13;
an European Regional Fund was created to provide resources for regional&#13;
reconversion, ,but this fund is a good deal smaller than initially&#13;
envisaged. The European Investment Bank and the Ortoli Facility can&#13;
also be useful to create jobs in regions affected by trade adjustment.&#13;
Existing studies however suggest that these various funds are not very&#13;
effective. The sums which they can distribute are not large; more&#13;
importantly, it seems difficult for potential beneficiaries to use&#13;
the system effectively.&#13;
What this means is that the EC has little ability to compen-&#13;
sate individuals in member countries for losses suffered from changes&#13;
1/ Adjustment assistance will of course also cause some waste,&#13;
unless it takes the form of lumps sum transfers. But this waste&#13;
is likely to be small and is temporary.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
in international trade. This is probably as it should be, as the&#13;
Brussels Eurocrats have enough to do not to become heavily involved&#13;
in compensating individuals, industries, or regions in every member&#13;
country. It might perhaps be thought desirable that they should have&#13;
funds to compensate countries for trade losses - to shift funds to&#13;
France if French wine producers suffer from the entry of Spain into&#13;
the Community, subject to the French government redistributing the&#13;
money as it sees fit. In practice, EC negotiating sessions haggle&#13;
over so many issues that there is ample scope to buy off one country's&#13;
objections to a measure by offering it satisfaction on another issue.&#13;
Adjustment assistance is therefore a national responsibility,&#13;
and adjustment to trade is carried out under the same schemes as&#13;
adjustment to other disturbances.l/ The operation of such assistance&#13;
in member countries has been bewilderingly complex, and subject to&#13;
much grassroots improvisation as politicians and bureaucrats at all&#13;
levels sought to reduce the social and economic costs of the 1970s&#13;
recession. Bureaucrats and politicians have used instruments ranging&#13;
from delays in payment of taxes and social security contributions to&#13;
permission to violate pollution regulations, from interest rebates to&#13;
wage subsidies, from tax relief and preferential access to "off-shore"&#13;
processing licenses to subsidies and nationalization, from government&#13;
purchases of the products of an enterprise to pressures on other&#13;
producers to inject capital into ailing firms and to encouraging cartels.&#13;
These instruments can take a wide range of legal forms, be justified by&#13;
a great diversity of pretexts, and be decided at any level or in any&#13;
part of the administration. Ministries of Foreign Affairs have directed&#13;
aid projects to help particular enterprises, Ministries of Health have&#13;
tried to save others by forgetting anti-pollution regulations, Minis-&#13;
tries of Education have pushed schools to purchase equipment from&#13;
enterprises in difficulty. Most of these interventions have required&#13;
lengthy efforts and numerous contacts on the part of those concerned,&#13;
leading to a vast expenditure of efforts inspired by a laudable sense&#13;
of public duty. The result has, however, mostly been to push unemploy-&#13;
ment around by destroying jobs in enterprises which compete with those&#13;
obtaining assistance.&#13;
From this point of view, the Treaty provision which empower&#13;
the EC to eliminate market distorsions have been one of the most important&#13;
policy instruments it wields. The Directorate General for Competition&#13;
monitors inter alia government aids and subsidies. Controversies are&#13;
brought before the Court of Justice if agreement cannot be otherwise&#13;
reached. It is of course not possible to monitor all schemes (there are&#13;
1/ The scheme introduced by the Dutch government to help adjustment&#13;
by enterprises affected by import competition from developing&#13;
countries was a failure. It was little used, and has in practice&#13;
been abandoned.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
more than 1200 laws in force in the 9 member countries) but the&#13;
Commission can control the larger, more visible ones. The Rome&#13;
Treaty binds governments, but individuals can challenge aids which&#13;
have,been granted to their competitors before the courts. Civil&#13;
servants tend to forget to notify the Commission of aids which they&#13;
have contrived to help countrymen to beat foreign competitors.&#13;
These foreign (and sometime national) competitors often cannot find&#13;
the evidence required to bring a case before the courts. Many&#13;
trade distorting interventions therefore escape the watchful eye&#13;
of Community institutions. There is no doubt, nevertheless, that&#13;
the Commission's control of government interventions has been an&#13;
important element of trade policy, and has been useful to firms&#13;
outside the EC as much as to EC firms in making markets more&#13;
accessible and transparent than they would otherwise be.&#13;
Regulation of cartels&#13;
The Rome Treaty anti-trust provisions have likewise developed&#13;
into- an important instrument of trade policy. Forming a "recession&#13;
cartel" is a classic reaction to enterprise problems in concentrated&#13;
industries. These cartels may have as large an effect in restricting&#13;
trade as import quotas. They may cause price distortions through&#13;
dumping and other means. European governments have been generally&#13;
inclined to support these cartels to safeguard production resources&#13;
which they fear might otherwise be destroyed.&#13;
In fact the ECSC Treaty explicitly grants to the EC the power&#13;
to regulate in time of crisis production and prices of coal and steel,&#13;
that is to run a recession cartel. This power has not formally been&#13;
invoked but it provides the background for the Davignon Plan for the&#13;
steel industry.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
II. LEVELS OF TRADE POLICY DECISIONS MAKING&#13;
Decision making with respect to trade policy making is&#13;
obviously not concentrated in the hands of one "government", or even&#13;
of a group of "politicians" as envisaged in formal presentations of&#13;
the political economy of protection. Reality is a good deal more&#13;
complex. In practice it is useful to think of a four tier apparatus&#13;
of decision making, where each tier is subject to a different degree&#13;
of control by interest groups and voters.&#13;
A.   At the bottom, an enormous number of decisions which are.&#13;
individually small but important in the aggregate are taken&#13;
at the level of the bureaucracy. The decision level is&#13;
here what Messerlin (1979) has called the bureaus; it is&#13;
decisions at this level which are alluded to when econo-&#13;
mists try to explain why Japan has such low imports, or&#13;
claim rightly or wrongly that Germany's liberal trade&#13;
policy stance does not correspond to its real behavior.&#13;
These decisions are almost invisible, and thus represent&#13;
an ideal area for exertion of pressures by special&#13;
interest groups. Indeed because complaints are bad&#13;
for the careers of bureaucrats and because they come to&#13;
be sympathetic to the people whom they administer, it is&#13;
frequent to find agencies within the administration which&#13;
have become as devoted to the interests of special&#13;
interest groups as the lobbies financed by these groups.&#13;
By the same token, the Ministry of Foreign Affairs is&#13;
commonly the most free trade oriented body within the&#13;
administration, because of its unique exposure to the&#13;
points of view of other countries.&#13;
B.   What elected politicians do is more visible than what&#13;
is done at the level of the bureaus, and the influence&#13;
of the general voters is correspondingly larger. This&#13;
is the decision level which advocates of the political&#13;
economy of protection have in mind in their analysis&#13;
of decision making in the market for protection. Perhaps&#13;
the theory would become more realistic if a way was&#13;
found to recognize that governments are only one&#13;
echelon in a ladder of decision makers. They have&#13;
only a dim understanding and cognizance of what is&#13;
decided-by the bureaus, and on the whole respect the&#13;
restraints on their freedom which are imposed by&#13;
treaties to which they have subscribed.&#13;
C.   The views of interest groups and of voters filter up&#13;
to government via a complex system of parties,&#13;
lobbies and institutions for co-operation among&#13;
socio-economic groups which in Europe sometimes have&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
significant influence. Distortions may take place,&#13;
and it is often clear that (sometimes to their costs)&#13;
governments have misread the strength of the political&#13;
forces which are affected by a particular decision.&#13;
The accuracy of what filters up to 'the Economic&#13;
Community level is even' more questionable. Indeed,&#13;
most of the activity of the Brussels bureaucracy is&#13;
concerned with remaining in contact with the politico-&#13;
administrative base in member countries, to be able to&#13;
strike compromises which balance interests nationally&#13;
and internationally. Because legitimacy is the only&#13;
source of its influence, the Community must be even&#13;
more careful than governments in respecting the&#13;
Treaties under which it was established, and the&#13;
GATT agreements which it helped to negotiate.&#13;
D.   The GATT is the top tier of the system.   Its operation&#13;
has tended to be rigidly formalistic though this may&#13;
change as the Tokyo Round codes of behavior are&#13;
implemented. Initiatives at that level have been&#13;
dominated by the US, Japan,and the EC. Developing&#13;
countries, in particular, have tended to feel that&#13;
the GATT forum was not a forum in which they could get&#13;
their views across effectively.&#13;
A key property of this edifice is the changing balance -&#13;
between special and general interests as one moves up from one-tier&#13;
to the next.  There are good theoretical reasons to believe that a&#13;
completely open and general negotiation between economic agents will&#13;
lead to a "point in the core of the economy" which coincides with a&#13;
situation of free trade. This idea, indeed, appears to be more than&#13;
a theoretical construct. As the progress of air transport and inter-&#13;
national communications has facilitated international contacts, the&#13;
creation of such forums as the GATT and the Economic Community has&#13;
operated visibly in favour of a free exchange of goods and services&#13;
across countries.&#13;
Another property of this edifice is the extent to which the&#13;
discretionary decision making which is so important at the level of&#13;
the bureaus gives way to the operatiqv of formal rules at higher levels.&#13;
Economists have been very interested- in analysis of the advantages of&#13;
stable decision rules as a framework for the operation of a market&#13;
economy, freeing agents from the need to out guess or influence&#13;
government decisions and allowing them to concentrate on using' resources&#13;
efficiently. From this point of view also, the postwar tendency to&#13;
shift decisions from lower to higher decision levels has probably&#13;
contributed to efficiency.&#13;
1/ In particular in the recent spate of work on rational expectations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
_ 9.-&#13;
European institutions and their relations to lobbies&#13;
and general voters&#13;
Theoretical analysis glosses over the practical difficulties&#13;
of reconciling conflicting interests, or of obtaining agreement on&#13;
stable formal decision rules. In practice achieving these goals is&#13;
far from a trivial task, as the evolution of Community institutions&#13;
in dealing with this problem illustrates.&#13;
The core-of the system of EC institutions is the Commission,&#13;
which directs the work of the Secretariat and is controlled by the&#13;
Council of Ministers. The function of these bodies is to implement&#13;
the Treaties which have formed the European Community. The Court of&#13;
Justice in Luxemburg decides on cases bearing on the interpretation of&#13;
the Treaties. It has turned out to be an important component of the&#13;
system, tending quite systematically to give a broad interpretation of&#13;
the authority granted to the Community by the Treaties. The Court can&#13;
hear cases submitted to it by governments and individuals as well as by&#13;
the Commission, so that it provides a link with the political base of&#13;
the Community.&#13;
The European Council brings together heads of States, and its&#13;
agenda is not restricted to items which fall under the scope of the&#13;
Treaties. This is a new organ which as yet has not found a stable role -&#13;
if it has to have one. Its summit meetings have sometimes sounded as&#13;
shrill as an opera performance where several prima donnas compete for&#13;
the role of Carmen. Hopefully creation of the Council will broaden the&#13;
sphere of European cooperation. The EMS is a first result.&#13;
The European Parliament - 500 kilometers away from Brussels&#13;
in Strasbourg - is now elected, but has limited powers. It can reject&#13;
the budget and revoke the Commission - and then what. Its main function&#13;
appeai, to be to act as a sounding board for the views of political&#13;
parties, which are one of the main political forces which the Community&#13;
must understand to orient its decisions correctly.    The Economic and&#13;
Social Council, also a weak body, brings together representatives of&#13;
economic and social groups. To speak in the language of the political&#13;
economy of protection, it represents lobbies. In spite of their some-&#13;
times sizeable staff the Brussels lobbies have little power. They&#13;
serve mainly as yet another (two way) channel of information between&#13;
the Community and political forces in member countries. On key issues&#13;
they are often by-passie by national lobbies or by large firms.&#13;
The main channels through which both lobbies and general&#13;
voters influence the Community are the governments of member countries,&#13;
through the Council of Ministers. The Commissioners are usually them-&#13;
selves politicians. It is perhaps not sufficiently recognized by&#13;
outsiders that the Secretariat is a political intelligence agency,&#13;
whose function is not to go to the bottom of problems and map solutions,&#13;
but to run a complex and often apparently pointless system of committees&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
and working groups (in six languages with simultaneous interpretation)&#13;
primarily to keep the EC in close contact with government thinking in&#13;
member countries. The extent to which important decisions are prepared&#13;
by personal contacts between the Commissioners or members of their&#13;
s,taff, and influential politicians, civil servants, businessmen, and&#13;
trade union leaders (in 9 countries) is simply not known.&#13;
The genesis of trade policy&#13;
The formulation of trade policy by politicians strikes a&#13;
balance between the pressures exerted by lobbies, and more general&#13;
objectives accepted by voters. The role of lobbies can on occasions be&#13;
extremely crude. For example the lengths to which France went to sustain&#13;
the import ban on British lamb were widely understood to be directly&#13;
related to the importance of sheep raising in the constituency of the&#13;
leader of one of the majority parties.&#13;
As in the US, such juggling for the support of interest&#13;
groups is tempered by the need of politicians to convince voters that&#13;
they are dealing effectively and responsibly with the country's general&#13;
problems. How voters form their judgment is something that even&#13;
politicians do not know very well. Voters know little about trade&#13;
policies. There is an astonishing contrast between the accuracy and&#13;
timeliness of the lobbies' knowledge of trade related measures even&#13;
before they are announced, and the vague information about them that&#13;
can be gathered from serious newspapers. The diffusion of decisions&#13;
between four interdependent levels of decision making also makes it easy&#13;
for politicians to claim credit for popular measures, and to shift to&#13;
others the onus for the unpopular ones.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
III. POLICY GOALS&#13;
Though Eurocrats do not confront voters directly, there is&#13;
no reason to believe that their keenness to satisfy public opinion&#13;
differs in a fundamental way from that of politicians and civil&#13;
servants in national governments. Oversimplifying somewhat, we&#13;
shall first describe their perception of the EC's general interest,&#13;
as they may sense it to be understood by voters. We shall then describe&#13;
the concerns of interest groups which have played a key role recently,&#13;
and the EC's response to their demands. We will finally describe how&#13;
the Community has sought to use its trade policy to achieve a number&#13;
of more general objectives.&#13;
Efficiency&#13;
Efficient use of resources, the basic goal of trade, is the&#13;
first of these general objectives. At present there is a marked&#13;
inconsistency in EC policy making between the remarkable scaling down&#13;
of most external trade barriers, which was not interrupted by the mid&#13;
1970s recession (in contrast to the conclusion of the Tokyo Round), and&#13;
the parallel consolidation of extremely restrictive import policies&#13;
for agriculture and for textiles and clothing. It is too early to say&#13;
how other recently erected barrier's for example for shoes, steel and&#13;
artificial fibers will evolve.&#13;
The high.barriers ou textiles (and agriculture) affect,large&#13;
sectors and accordingly generate considerable waste. The extent of&#13;
this is not widely appreciated. The growing criticism of the Common&#13;
Agricultural Policy has focussed on its budget implications, and has&#13;
largely disregarded the invisible transfers implied by price distortions.&#13;
It has furthermore hardly dealt with the resource misallocation which&#13;
it causes. The MFA has largely escaped such public criticism because&#13;
it does not have a budget impact.&#13;
An important aspect of debates in Europe about the efficiency&#13;
impact of protection is the widely accepted view that the free play of&#13;
competition may lead to a wasteful destruction of resources in a&#13;
situation of unemployment. It is argued that keeping enterprises&#13;
afloat by government intervention is better than allowing the resources&#13;
which they employ to lie unused. In effect what is argued is that there&#13;
is a special type of market failure. As usual, of course, the enter-&#13;
prises and groups which ask for protection or other types of assistance&#13;
claim that *the light is at the end of the tunnel, so that all that is&#13;
needed is a temporary boost.&#13;
Public opinion has however moved perceptibly to a more&#13;
realistic view of things. "I am not a naive believer in perfect&#13;
competition" remains the standard way of starting a statement on&#13;
market intervention. However, there is growing realization that&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
the assistance given out since the beginning of the recession has been&#13;
costly and ineffective, that much of it has gone to firms which did&#13;
not really need it, and in particular, to a few large groups which&#13;
have enough skilled staff to understand how the system works, and&#13;
that milking the assistance and subsidy system has become so profitable&#13;
that it is absorbing valuable productive resources.l/&#13;
"But I don't think that lame ducks should be coddled" has&#13;
accordingly become the quasi-automatic follow up of expressions of&#13;
disbelief in the efficiency competition, reflecting growing understanding&#13;
that there are considerable dynamic economies to be reaped by letting&#13;
workers and employers understand that they have to confront competition&#13;
through greater efficiency rather than by securing subsidies, or even by&#13;
allowing bankruptcy to detach workers and capital goods from inefficient&#13;
managers. Recent elections, and the evolution of the stock language of&#13;
politicians, have provided clear indications that the shift in attitude&#13;
has a broad base in public opinion.&#13;
Income distribution&#13;
As indicated above, the EC's concern for income distribution&#13;
within countries is essentially symbolic. The activity of such bodies&#13;
as the European Social Fund is not a major component of the Community's&#13;
trade policy. Distribution of income between countries is another&#13;
matter because negotiators clearly understand the costs and benefits&#13;
of trade diversion.&#13;
Trade diversion is the Achilles heel of customs unions. As&#13;
it is acceptable to losers only if external protection is low, customs&#13;
unions between developing countries have failed up to now. The sharp&#13;
tensions concerning the Common Agricultural Policy illustrate this&#13;
danger. As discussed below, similar disputes may arise in the not so&#13;
distant future over textiles and clothing protection. Hopefully the&#13;
EC will understand the risk which maintenance of the present very high&#13;
barriers to this trade poses for the future cohesion of the Community.&#13;
Fear of retaliation&#13;
The fear of retaliation has been one of the main reasons why&#13;
interest groups have found it difficult to obtain support for protective&#13;
measures from the public. One of the main achievements of the Rome&#13;
Treaty has been the constitution of a trading block with enough power&#13;
to persuade US officials and the US public that protectionist measures&#13;
1/ This type of rent seeking is associated with significant dead-&#13;
weight costs (Krueger).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
will bring forth meaningful retaliation. Japan's inability to obtain&#13;
normal treatment of its exports by the EC to a significant extent&#13;
arises from the lack of balance of its trade with the Community.&#13;
From this point of view a striking aspect of trade of developing&#13;
countries with the EC (and other industrial countries) is their inability/&#13;
unwillingness to retaliate against the strongly discriminatory protection&#13;
to which they have been subjected. There are several reasons for this:&#13;
(a) A very large fraction of their exports comes from a&#13;
few countries which have very little bargaining&#13;
power. Hong Kong is a colony of an EC member; a&#13;
trade war would be disastrous both to its and to&#13;
Singapore's trade. Taiwan's international situation&#13;
also argues for caution, as does South Korea's need&#13;
for US military support.&#13;
(b) Voluntary export restrictions (VERs) which are the&#13;
main means of protection against developing countries&#13;
generate significant rents, which are appropriated&#13;
to a large extent by exporting firms in those&#13;
countries (Jenkins 1980). The effortless profits&#13;
yielded by such rent in effect creak bribes to&#13;
exporters not to press their governments too&#13;
strongly to complain about protection.&#13;
(c) Despite very low wages, most developing countries&#13;
are not capable of meeting the competition of the&#13;
large developing manufactured goods exporters.&#13;
A surprising number do not reach the low textile&#13;
and clothing quotas allocated to them by the EC.&#13;
They have a deep and probably exaggerated fear&#13;
of what they perceive to be China's enormous&#13;
competitive potential. Why should they press for&#13;
the suppression of a system of complex and detailed&#13;
import controls which protects them against these&#13;
competitors? Likewise why should the present large&#13;
exporters desire the abolition of a system which&#13;
grants them the lion's share of exports of sensitive&#13;
goods from developing to industrial countries, the&#13;
existence of which has in the past years deterred so&#13;
effectively potential exporters like India from daring&#13;
to undertake the transition to an export oriented&#13;
strategy?&#13;
(d) The strongly protectionist policies pursued by almost&#13;
all developing countries have excluded most consumer&#13;
goods from their imports. They therefore cannot&#13;
afford the import cuts required to implement retaliation&#13;
policies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
(e)  The developing countries have been unable to constitute&#13;
effective bargaining units. The group of 77 is an&#13;
instrument for the dramatized expression of dreams;&#13;
apart from OPEC, developing countries have not been-&#13;
able to form groups with enough interests in common&#13;
:  and- large enough in size to extract trade concessions&#13;
from the EC, the US, or Japan.&#13;
The EC as a producer of public goods&#13;
The function of governments is not only to create conditions&#13;
conducive to the maximum production of market goods, but also to&#13;
produce a number of "public goods" such as national security, access&#13;
to culture, national prestige, which the market cannot provide. The&#13;
EC has sought to fashion its trade relations with developing countries&#13;
to create a number of such goods.&#13;
Maintenance of good regional relations&#13;
The EC maintains a four tiers system of agreements with developing&#13;
countries, granting them different degrees of preferential treatment.   The&#13;
strongest preference is granted to new entrants, under agreements&#13;
preparing for accession to the Community. A complex system of regional&#13;
and national treaties regulates relations with Mediterranean countries;&#13;
the most important concession is that these countries' exports to the EC&#13;
are not regulated by the MFA, but by bilateral agreements which have turned&#13;
out to be more favorable than the MFA.   The Lome countries, mostly Europe&#13;
is former African colonies, benefit from a slightly better treatment of&#13;
manufactured exports than that provided for by the EC's GSP. (Their&#13;
exports were exempted from quantitative controls by the Lome I Convention,&#13;
but this advantage did not survive in Lome II). Other developing countries&#13;
benefit from the tariff quota system defined by the GSP.&#13;
This system is intended to promote stability in the region to&#13;
which the EC belongs, and to prepare for the enlargement of the Community.&#13;
It also maintains cultural and other ties which are valued by member&#13;
countries, such as consolidating the "community of francophone countries".&#13;
Stabilizing future markets and raw materials supplies&#13;
This system of agreements has also a more directly practical&#13;
value in helping businessmen to retain the commercial advantages acquired&#13;
when Western Europe dominated the Mediterranean and Africa. The EC has&#13;
tried to go.further by having developing countries agree to guarantee&#13;
its-access to their raw materials, and to undertake not to nationalize&#13;
its investments. This policy has not been successful.&#13;
Finally - also unsuccessfully up to now - the EC has sought to&#13;
promote a process of integration of the more advanced developing countries&#13;
into the constitutional framework through the "graduation principle" of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
world trade, by having them accept gradually the obligations imposed on&#13;
the developed signatories of the GATT.&#13;
Diversification of developing countries' exports of&#13;
manufactured goods&#13;
The exports of developing countries were initially concentrated&#13;
in a narrow range of goods. Greater diversification makes it easier for&#13;
producers in industrial countries to adjust to the expected large growth&#13;
of these export. Promotion of such diversification is a "public good"&#13;
to which public opinion in developed countries attributes a good deal of&#13;
value. This goal is pursued by both a very weak and a very strong&#13;
instrument; the weak one works in favour of developing countries, but&#13;
the strong one is probably quite costly to them.&#13;
The weak instrument is the GSP, which establishes duty free&#13;
quotas for manufactured goods exported by developing countries. The&#13;
scheme distinguishes three categories: highly sensitive, sensitive,&#13;
and non sensitive goods, which are offered preferences scaled according&#13;
to the degree of sensitivity.!'   The scheme, like the analogous schemes&#13;
enforced by the USA, Japan, Sweden, and other countries seems in principle&#13;
to be an ingenious way of fostering "infant expoLts" in developing countries,&#13;
while safeguarding the interests of the weaker sectors in the EC. For&#13;
several reasons the scheme has made only a small contribution to the&#13;
achievement of its stated goal. Its provisions are complex, and subject&#13;
to yearly revisions, leading to an uncertainty and opaqueness which&#13;
reduce its impact on investment in developing countries. Most of the&#13;
easily produced goods which are the mainstay of the early phase of&#13;
developing countries' export-drives are "highly sensitive goods",&#13;
poorly treated under the scheme, and subjec-t to the threat of MFA&#13;
discrimination. Tariffs in developed countries are anyway low and&#13;
have been getting lower. The evidence, econometric and otherwise, is&#13;
that the EC's GSP scheme, like the schemes designed by other trading&#13;
nations, has had little impact on exports of manufactured goods from&#13;
developing countries.&#13;
The negative instrument is the Sword of Damocles hung over&#13;
export oriented investments of developing countries by the threat of&#13;
discriminatory import quotas imposed as selective safeguards. Imposition&#13;
of such quotas is possible under the EC MFA regulations, authorized as&#13;
an exception to Article XIX of the GATT. The Community has pressed&#13;
strongly in the Tokyo Round and subsequently to extend this exception&#13;
to other goods under an appropriate code, and threatened to impose&#13;
selective safeguards even if agreement on such a code was not possible.&#13;
1/ For non sensitive goods, there is no quota; however if exports&#13;
grow substantially these goods are transferred to the "sensitive"&#13;
or "highly sensitive" categories for which the amounts which can be&#13;
sold free of duty are limited.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
This ill defined threat to future exports represents a&#13;
powerful instrument of preventive protection, by discouraging not+-&#13;
only marginal investments but even timid (prudent ?) developing&#13;
countries from undertaking the sweeping and politically costly&#13;
policy changes required by a switch from an import substitution&#13;
to an export oriented trade strategy. It is likely that this threat&#13;
has a considerable impact on the level and pattern of ex Yrts of&#13;
developing countries, in the direction sought by the EC._     To&#13;
the extent that- as is highly probable - developing countries have&#13;
felt driven to promote the export of goods for which their comparative&#13;
advantage is less than for their traditional exports, the result is a&#13;
.(probably large) waste of resources.&#13;
Textiles&#13;
From the point of view of the political economy- of protection,&#13;
it is not immediately clear why lobbying for protection plays so large&#13;
a role in the industrial strategy of the textiles and clothing sector.&#13;
This industry has a,very elastic long run supply curve, so that&#13;
protection has less impact on unit earnings of capital and labor than.&#13;
in most other industries. Entry is relatively easy. Because of the&#13;
sharp separation between the textile machinery, textiles, and clothing&#13;
sectors, and because of well developed training programs for workers&#13;
and staff, technology is available to anyone willing to enter the&#13;
industry. Exit is easy too. A large number of firms obtain a very&#13;
low return on assets even when the latter are valued at liquidation&#13;
prices. There is a market for textile machinery and much capital is&#13;
tied up in inventories. The owners of such firms must be tempted to&#13;
invest their money elsewhere, and indeed government administered schemes,&#13;
in the UK in particular, designed to bring about a shrinkage of&#13;
productive capacity, have readily enough identified producers who were&#13;
willing to be bribed to cease production.&#13;
The mobility of labour is debatable. The industry tends&#13;
to recruit its labour force in "pockets" of the labour market containing&#13;
workers with low mobility, who are willing to accept low wages: women&#13;
in regions where female employment is low, young girls between high&#13;
school and marriage, illegal imigrant workers sheltered from the police&#13;
by the anonymity of big cities. But labour turnover is typically high,&#13;
so that the work force can be reduced by attrition with less social&#13;
tensions than in most other industries. Wages are very low, so that&#13;
if other jobs can be created by market forces or "adjustment policies",&#13;
or by widening job opportunities through better education, the&#13;
workers who shift out of textiles will gain significantly. The&#13;
industry requires few skills so that little human capital is lost&#13;
by workers who move to other sectors.&#13;
1/ And other industrial countries which have pursued similar policies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
It is thus the elasticity of supply which accounts for the&#13;
strong unity of the industry in support of protection. Textiles and&#13;
clothing producers are deeply afraid of the competition of low wage&#13;
countries, with their huge labor reserves, and proven ability to&#13;
expand output very quickly. Their only hope for survival is to deny&#13;
low wage countries entry into markets in industrial countries. This&#13;
explains the paradox that an industry with an elastic supply curve,&#13;
where the large number of producers and their diversity makes it&#13;
difficult to reach a common view, should have lobbied so hard for&#13;
protection. What has welded the industry together is the feeling that&#13;
producers in low wage countries can destroy most of the textiles and&#13;
clothing industry in the EC. It is not only marginal producers who&#13;
feel threatened; even prosperous firms are afraid of going out of&#13;
business.&#13;
This fear is excessive, because it does not allow for the&#13;
great diversity of the industry. Large subsectors, mostly those&#13;
producing the "highly sensitive goods" of the MFA agreement regulations,&#13;
would indeed disappear. But the fact that EC exports and imports are&#13;
in rough balance shows that there are subsectors which can meet open&#13;
competition. Clothing is competitively much weaker than textiles, but&#13;
it should be remembered that effective tariffs on clothing are of the&#13;
order of 20% in the EC, so that domestic producers would retain&#13;
substantial protection even if MFA quantitative controls were relaxed.&#13;
Technology is becoming more and more capital intensive, reducing the&#13;
impact of wage costs on output. For certain types of weaving one&#13;
worker can tend some 100 looms, and microelectronics are beginning to&#13;
make automation of key operations in the clothing industry possible.&#13;
Specialization is often an asset. German industrial textiles and&#13;
carpet making on the "carpet freeway" in Flanders, are strong and&#13;
expanding subsectors. That adjustment to competition from low wage&#13;
countries is possible is also shown by the example of the Swiss&#13;
textile industry. Despite very high wages, specialization has enabled&#13;
this industry to survive, although that country has not introduced&#13;
quotas on imports from developing countries.&#13;
However exaggerated the fears of the industry, it is what&#13;
it believes which has led it to wield its considerable power to force&#13;
policy makers to supply the protection which it believes is needed.&#13;
This power results to a significant extent from its size. The textile&#13;
and clothing vote is worth competing for by any political party, and&#13;
the regional concentration of the industry provides it with the assured&#13;
and loyal support of a number of members in Parliament.&#13;
The weakness of trade unions does not handicap lobbying, for&#13;
it reflects close personal contacts between owners and workers in the&#13;
typically fairly small plants which characterize the industry. The&#13;
resulting climate of cooperation has facilitated the formulation of&#13;
common worker/owner demands to government.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
This lobbying proved decisive in 1977, a year of slow growth,&#13;
when developing countries were expanding their market shares in the&#13;
Community rapidly. The EC drastically reinforced controls on textiles&#13;
and clothing imports-from low wage countries, through VER agreements&#13;
imposed under the second MFA. The new system proved very effective,&#13;
curbing import growth from 25% per year in volume in 1973-6 to 4% in&#13;
1976-9 for MFA countries. Rates of growth of imports from preferential&#13;
countries were marginally higher.&#13;
Similar measures taken by other industrial countries strengthened&#13;
discriminatory import controls against developing and East European&#13;
centrally planned economics. Industrial countries thus formed a kind&#13;
of textiles and clothing common market to which developing countries&#13;
only had limited access. In equivalent tariff terms the external&#13;
barriers are highly variable ranging from 100% for some articles of&#13;
clothing to only a few percent for many textiles. They are therefore&#13;
very wasteful.!l The welfare cost of these barrier to consumers is&#13;
obviously high, particularly for low income groups, as the comparative&#13;
advantage of developing countries is greatest for the cheapest types of&#13;
clothing..&#13;
Trade diversion was striking consequence of this system. In&#13;
the EC,. Italy has improved its net exports rapidly at the expenses of&#13;
its Northern neighbours. US producers have likewise registered sharp&#13;
gains, reflecting an edge in technology and marketing techniques, the&#13;
fall of the dollar, and the availability of pockets of low wage black&#13;
and Hispanic labour.Z/ Northern EC countries have gained a respite for&#13;
those producers that would have had to contract output more rapidly if&#13;
protection had not been tightened. But as production and employment&#13;
shrinks, this gain is diminishing. Two of these countries, Germany and&#13;
the Netherlands, seem to have achieved the purported goal of the MFA&#13;
of shifting output to products which do not need protection. For these&#13;
countries the advantage of continuing protection are shrinking, but the&#13;
extra cost to consumers of buying from high cost sources is a permanent&#13;
loss.&#13;
One of the sources of strength of the textiles lobby in the&#13;
EC has been that the net exports of the various member countries were&#13;
not too different. As Italy continues to gain, and as Greece, Spain&#13;
and Portugal join to form a low wage EC "sunbelt", producers in the&#13;
Northern countries will have to concentrate more and more on special&#13;
articles and capital intensive products which can meet competition from&#13;
lower wage countries. Their interest in protection will decrease. At&#13;
the same time the shift to export oriented policies by a number of&#13;
developing .countries, in particular the influential countries of South&#13;
Asia, could strengthen the hostility of the Group of 77 to the MFA.&#13;
1/ Assuming linear supply and demand curves, the welfare cost is&#13;
proportional to the squre of the rate of protection. It is&#13;
therefore desirable to avoid sharp tariff disparities in policies&#13;
of trade restriction.&#13;
2/ And, for synthetic fibers, low energy costs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
There are therefore hopes that the balance of negotiating forces which&#13;
has generated the present system of protection will shift in favour of&#13;
freer trade.&#13;
The synthetic fibers sector is undergoing a severe crisis in&#13;
EC countries, and has resorted to a cartel to deal with the situation.&#13;
The Community at one time was inclined to give its blessing to this&#13;
cartel, but decided to avoid so blatant a violation of the Treaty of&#13;
Rome.  The cartel came into being anyway, and the Commission is&#13;
watching and trying to moderate its actions with obviously ambiguous&#13;
feeling.&#13;
There was no "external component" to the original Davignon&#13;
proposal of support to the cartel. As always trade distortions generate&#13;
demands for government intervention, and synthetic fibers producers&#13;
have recently been fighting hard for the external protection required&#13;
to stabilize their cartel, arguing that energy price distortions in the&#13;
US give producers in that country an unfair competitive advantage.&#13;
These demands benefit from a favourable political climate, because of&#13;
EC resentment over the threatened imposition of anti-dumping duties on&#13;
steel. This story of incipient escalation of distortions, intervention,&#13;
and retaliation has lessons for those developing countries which are&#13;
or are becoming exporters of synthetic fibers and yarns for it provides&#13;
a striking contrast between the interplay of effective threats and&#13;
counterthreats between the US and the EC, and their own inability to&#13;
put up a fight in 1977 for fair treatment under the MFA.&#13;
The producers of synthetic and artificial fibers have played&#13;
a key role in the relevant lobbies in support of protection of the&#13;
textiles and clothing industry. These provided much of the basic&#13;
analysis and data required to present a convincing case to policy&#13;
makers. To some extent therefore producers in the higher stages of&#13;
the industry, where output is not concentrated, have been free-riding&#13;
on the lobbying effectiveness of a few highly concentrated producers&#13;
who wish to help the downstream producers who absorb their output.&#13;
Shoes&#13;
The EC shoe industry includes Italy, one of the low cost&#13;
producers in the world, and will probably include Spain, which can be&#13;
expected to recover a competitive strength has been sharply reduced by&#13;
the social problems which have accompanied the move to democracy.&#13;
Special quota protection is therefore not necessary. The shoe lobby&#13;
is also much weaker than that in textiles and clothing. In the wake&#13;
of the 1977 MFA negotiations, European governments and the EC have&#13;
however moved to impose VER agreements on the main shoe exporters in the&#13;
world.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
Steel&#13;
The steel industry is almost a textbook illustration of.the&#13;
forces which bring about demands for protection. The elasticity of&#13;
supply is low except in the long run, so that the industry can easily&#13;
hold on to gains secured as a result of protection. The supply of&#13;
capital is unresponsive to prices. Almost none of the capital stock&#13;
can be retrieved once production stops, as there is little variable&#13;
capital and as most equipment cannot be moved. Prices would have to&#13;
be a good deal higher to justify construction of new mills.&#13;
Labour is not mobile. Much of the employment is for life, so&#13;
that it is hard to reduce the workforce by attrition. Work practices&#13;
are rigid, for technical reasons, and because of union resistance.&#13;
Steel workers are well paid, and often owe part of their income to&#13;
special skills and seniority which would be lost if they changed jobs.&#13;
As in the textiles and clothing sector, the industry is&#13;
welded together in its lobbying by realization that the adjustment&#13;
effort which is required is large and unpleasant. Production fell&#13;
by 20% from 1974 to 1975, and has hardly recovered since EC countries&#13;
like the US in earlier years, seem to have reached a stage of develop-&#13;
ment where growth has little impact on demand for steel. At the same&#13;
time, technological progress is strongly biased towards equipment with&#13;
a very large unit capacity. As a result, modernization tends to&#13;
increase capacity. This tendency is reinforced by the efforts of trade&#13;
unions and regional politicians to maintain employment, which leads them&#13;
to,press for plans which increase capacity. It is therefore very&#13;
difficult to close the gap between a slowly increasing demand and a&#13;
capacity growth which is hard to curb.&#13;
The prospect for closing this gap is worsened by the fact&#13;
that in the long run the EC will probably not be able to maintain the&#13;
level of its net exports. Japan's steel industry has lower costs than&#13;
EC producers.  In the last decades there has also been a marked shift&#13;
in comparative advantage in favour of developing countries some of&#13;
which have now had some 30 years of production experience. Some have&#13;
low fuel and iron ore costs in addition. Production in these countries&#13;
is growing very fast, and a few are now exporters.&#13;
Rationalization of the EC steel industry requires a major&#13;
geographical shift.   This industry consists in reality of two very&#13;
'different parts.  The older and larger component was built up close&#13;
to sources of coal and iron ore which have vanished, or are now more&#13;
costly than imported materials. These plants, which were built at a&#13;
time when the optimal scale of output was far smaller than today, have&#13;
crowded plants which are not as conveniently laid out as those built&#13;
on more recent sites. Productivity is in many instances held back by&#13;
work practices to which trade unions have been clinging in spite of&#13;
the evolution of technology.   During the long postwar years of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- .21 -&#13;
prosperity they were well placed to resist technological changes which&#13;
would have eliminated jobs. Opposition to rationalization has thus&#13;
continued in the recession, albeit, with less success.&#13;
Costs are lower in the modern and efficient plants built on&#13;
the seacoast which e7body the latest technology and process low cost&#13;
imported materials.!   These producers seem to have weathered the&#13;
recession successfully. A broad long term shift of the industry to&#13;
coast would however cause considerable political resistance in the&#13;
older steel making areas, except in countries such as Holland or Italy,&#13;
where the industry is of recent origin.&#13;
The steel lobby has a remarkable record of achievement in&#13;
milking governments for special benefits. Steel making is a highly&#13;
concentrated industry, with very strong unions, and concentration of&#13;
employment in limited areas. It enjoys a peculiar prestige as a symbol&#13;
of industrialization. These advantages have enabled the industry in&#13;
postwar years to enjoy privileged access to low interest loans and&#13;
grants to nationalized companies. When the recession started some&#13;
governments, for example, in Beligum and France, virtually opened&#13;
their pockets to steel makers to enable them to cover their losses,&#13;
ultimately nationalizing them and thus granting them the ultimate&#13;
subsidy.&#13;
The main limit steel industry's drive for protection is the&#13;
opposition of the much larger metal working industry. It obviously&#13;
makes no sense to shelter steel from a needed adjustment,,at the&#13;
expense of losses of jobs and exports in the automobile, shipbuilding,&#13;
and other large steel using sectors which also have difficulty in meeting&#13;
outside competition. Steel users understand these industries' need&#13;
for access to low price raw materials, and have enough lobbying power&#13;
to moderate protection for their customers by subsidies. It is not&#13;
!surprising, for example, to find that Germany, the largest exporter&#13;
of metal products, has been insisting on a strong link between the&#13;
renewal of the current steel protection scheme and continuing progress&#13;
in rationalizing output.&#13;
The EC's response to these pressures has been to back a&#13;
recession cartel. Under the Davignon plan, producers have been pressed&#13;
to respect minimum price and production guidelines.   The plan, which&#13;
is supported by VER agreements with other steel producers,. including&#13;
some in developing countries, is in practice part of a worldwide&#13;
recession cartel. As in the case of textiles, there is growing inter-&#13;
national interest in such protection by the industrial countries.&#13;
1/ The prices of which have however been distorted by input levies&#13;
designed to protect domestic coal against foreign competition.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
Whether the Davignon Plan becomes permanent is uncertain at&#13;
present. The EC may find that it has fathered a third highly restrictive&#13;
system in addition to its common agricultural and textile policies,&#13;
holding up domestic prices and dumping surpluses world markets.    This&#13;
would not only be disadvantageous to developing countries but also to&#13;
the EC metal using industry.&#13;
Ending the DP.g:zr.Plan hinees on successful rationalization&#13;
of the industry.   In fact rationalizatLon has made creditable progress.&#13;
Governments and employers have in the last two years not hesitated to&#13;
confront trade unions on the issue of productivity and production cut-&#13;
backs, forcing through employment cuts in spite of major strikes in the&#13;
Federal Republic of Germany, France, and the UK. It appears that there&#13;
is a definite possibility that the Common Market steel industry will&#13;
not follow the pattern of gradual permanent isolation from world&#13;
markets which seems to be establishing itself in the US. The main&#13;
uncertainty lies in the EC's ability to force through the cuts in&#13;
production capacity which are required to reestablish balance between&#13;
supply and demand, and so end the Plan. Marked progress can be expected&#13;
in the most few years from scrapping uneconomic plants, increasing&#13;
productivity in others through rationalization, eliminating excess&#13;
capacity and reducing energy costs. In the longer run a change in the&#13;
regional balance-of the industry is required, with a shift of basic&#13;
steelmaking processes to the coast and perhaps even to countries with&#13;
cheap energy. However, this will be difficult to achieve in a declining&#13;
and politically powerful industry.&#13;
Shipbuilding&#13;
Shipbuilding like steel is an example of an industry which&#13;
can gain significantly from protection, and has natural advantages in&#13;
pressing the government for favours.&#13;
The industry is not capital intensive. Unlike steel there is&#13;
appreciable freedom of entry. The inelasticity of supply results largely&#13;
from the need to keep production going to keep together a crucial core&#13;
of engineers and skilled workers.&#13;
Some shipyards are in large harbour cities like Hamburg,&#13;
Rotterdam, and Antwerp, where alternative employment opportunities are&#13;
numerous, but a large fraction of the capacity is in depressed areas&#13;
of the United Kingdom and Brittany.&#13;
Demand for ships fell sharply after 1973 with the decline&#13;
in the volume growth of trade, particularly of shipments of oil. For&#13;
a time activity was sustained by order backlogs, but the ships thus&#13;
launched added to the excess supply which had to be absorbed before&#13;
recovery became possible.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
The industry confronts-the most unpleasant adjustment of all:&#13;
extinction. Apart from a few specialized yards, notably those building&#13;
warships, it appears that shipbuilding in the Community will be reduced&#13;
very considerably. In spite of generous subsidies, and of creditable&#13;
efforts to overcome the rigid work practice rules which prevented&#13;
modernization of the industry especially in the UK, EC shipbuilders&#13;
only won a small fraction of the increased orders generated by the&#13;
recovery in demand in the lat 1970s. Japan is the dominant shipbuilder&#13;
today by an overwhelming margin, but a number of developing countries&#13;
such as Korea, Brazil, and India, have shown themselves capable of&#13;
exporting ships at competitive&amp;prices. Developing countries have a&#13;
comparative advantage in a sector where the capital output ratio is&#13;
low. To the extent that Japan loses part of the market it will be to&#13;
developing countries, not to Europe.&#13;
The shipbuilding industry has organised very effectively to&#13;
win favours from governments. Like steel it is endowed with a mysterious&#13;
prestige, which has helped to persuade the authorities to set up&#13;
intricate schemes to promote construction of merchant ships in home&#13;
shipyards. Union strength has been important.&#13;
Like steel, the action of the shipbuilding lobbyists has to&#13;
take account of the countervailing demands of their client, the shipping&#13;
industry. In fact the structure of the shipping industry makes it&#13;
almost impossible to promote shipbuilding by tariffs or quotas, for&#13;
shipping is a world market activity. There is little point in protecting&#13;
domestic shipbuilders by tariffs as national shipping firms would simply&#13;
buy elsewhere. Forcing them to buy at home would be pointless, given&#13;
the case with which capital can emigrate and escape government control&#13;
through foreign flags of convenience. Protection to shipbuilding has&#13;
thus been extended largely through subsidies rather than through tariffs&#13;
and quotas. The subsidies were sometimes quite indirect. For example&#13;
US aid had to be carried on ships flying the American flag to channel&#13;
business to national shipping and shipbuilding firms.&#13;
Protection of shipbuilding has therefore been the responsibility&#13;
of Community member governments. The Community, in contrast, has&#13;
regulated aids and subsidies and limited mergers to some extent at&#13;
least, thus curbing the absurdly generous aids granted by member&#13;
countries somewhat. The Commission has nevertheless proposed a&#13;
Community scrap and build scheme to bring about a resurgence of demand.&#13;
the response of governments to this plan has not been enthusiastic, and&#13;
it is doubtful that it will get off the ground. The discussions of this&#13;
plan illustrated the difficulty of obtaining support for protection in&#13;
the EC when the costs and benefits are not balanced among countries.&#13;
In this instance the proposal was killed by objections of Germany -&#13;
where the shipbuilding industry has almost vanished - and Denmark.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
CONCLUSIONS&#13;
We embarked on this case study as a way of verifying the&#13;
empirical validity-and usefulness of the political economy of protection&#13;
approach to the study of trade policy. Our feeling is that the experiment&#13;
was successful. The approach was able to classify facts and events to&#13;
suggest that it is able to illuminate reality convincingly. Its main&#13;
weaknesses appear to be that:&#13;
A.-  It neglects complications resulting from the fact that trade&#13;
policy decisions are made at several levels, that many&#13;
decisions may be taken jointly, rather than by the govern-&#13;
ment setting one tariff. In fact it would be worthwhile&#13;
to rigorously analyse from a theoretical-point of view&#13;
why decisions taken at higher decision levels and&#13;
simultaneously-tend to be more liberal than the blow&#13;
by blow decisions of the bureaus.&#13;
B.   Trade adjustment assistance is not a useful concept&#13;
empirically, because of the tagging problem involved&#13;
in distinguishing agents whose difficulties arise&#13;
either from trade or other forces, and because it&#13;
is so easy to use adjustment schemes to grant subsidies.&#13;
C.   It may be worth stressing even more than is done by the&#13;
- political economy of protection the enormous difference&#13;
in accuracy and timeliness of the information on&#13;
protection which is available to lobbies and to general&#13;
voters. The EC has made a-laudable effort to explain the&#13;
reasons for its decisions. The performance of the US'&#13;
government in this respect is markedly better. The&#13;
information distributed by governments on subsidies&#13;
and protection is abysmally poor. Even members of&#13;
the administration find it wellnigh impossible to&#13;
keep track of what is decided.&#13;
B.   We have been surprised to realize to what extent, from&#13;
the Davignon Plan to the Tokyo Round, from the GSP to&#13;
the MFA, trade policy is made today at the world&#13;
rather than at the national or EC level. This also&#13;
is a fact which the political economy of protection has&#13;
overlooked.&#13;
The most important policy conclusions are not unexpected:&#13;
A.   The study of the record confirms the fear that with the&#13;
MFA tightening and the Davignon Plan, the EC is sliding&#13;
into permanent- support of an increasing number of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
"Common Restrictive Policies". Experience with the&#13;
Common Agricultural Policy illustrates the way in which&#13;
distortions lead to remedial measures and thence to&#13;
further distortions, leading to disputes which under-&#13;
mine European unity. Hopefully the dan-ger will be&#13;
perceived in time.&#13;
B.   The revised MFA "Common Textile Policy" embraces most of&#13;
the industrial world. Developing countries rightly&#13;
perceive that the EC insistence on selective safeguards&#13;
aims at legalizing this way of organizing world trade&#13;
under the GATT. De facto the selective safeguards&#13;
discrimination against developing countries is of course&#13;
already widely applied, without significant resistance&#13;
from the group of 77.&#13;
C.   There are, however, hopeful signs that public opinion is&#13;
becoming less receptive to proposals for intervention in&#13;
favour of particular industries, because it has seen that&#13;
the measures which were adopted in recent years did not&#13;
lead to the hoped for results, and that not adopting&#13;
other proposals did not lead to the announced catas-&#13;
trophes. In a nutshell, voters'-instincts-are becoming&#13;
reassured about the flexibility of the economic system.&#13;
If this evolution of thinking continues, and if growth&#13;
does not deteriorate catastrophically, there may be&#13;
hope of easing MFA controls and discarding the Davignon&#13;
Plan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MARKET PENETRATION RESEARCH PROJECT--WOT&lt;K-IN-PROCRESS REPORTS&#13;
425      Britain's Pattern of Specialization in Manufactured Goods      Vincent Cable&#13;
with Developing Countries and Trade Protection                Ivonia Rebelo&#13;
426      Worker Adjustment to Liberalized Trade: Costs and              Graham Glenday&#13;
Assistance Policies                                           Glenn P. Jenkii&#13;
John C. Evans&#13;
427      On the Political Economy of Protection in Germany              H.H. Glismann&#13;
F.D. Weiss&#13;
428      Italian Commercial Policies in the 1970s                       Enzo Grilli&#13;
429      Effects of Non-Tariff Barriers to Trade on Prices,&#13;
Employment, and Imports: The Case of the Swedish&#13;
Textile and Clothing Industry                                 Carl Hamilton&#13;
430      Output and Employment Changes in a "Trade&#13;
Sensitive" Sector: Adjustment in the U.S. Footwear            John NTutti &amp;&#13;
Industry                                                      Malco]mi Bale&#13;
431      The Political Economy of Protection in Belgium                 P.K.M. Tharakax&#13;
432      European Community Protection Against Manufactured             Eric "erreydt&#13;
Imports from Developing Countries: A Case Study in&#13;
the Political Economy of Protection                           Jean Waelbroecl&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1555008">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1980/10/1555008/european-community-protection-against-manufactured-imports-developing-countries-case-study-political-economy-protection
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1980/10/1555008/european-community-protection-against-manufactured-imports-developing-countries-case-study-political-economy-protection</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1980/10/1555008/european-community-protection-against-manufactured-imports-developing-countries-case-study-political-economy-protection</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/12/000178830_98101903405887/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/12/000178830_98101903405887/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-07-12T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1980-10-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            European community protection against
            manufactured imports from developing countries : a case
            study in the political economy of protection
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The project seeks to establish the
            shares of industrial country markets held by the developing
            countries, changes in such shares in the 1970s, and why they
            vary among industry groups and countries. The aim is to
            assist developing and industrial countries to improve their
            policies through a better understanding of trade patterns
            and protectionist pressures. This paper focuses on the
            institutional aspects of decision-making in the market for
            protection in the European Community. After a brief
            discussion of the protectionist instruments available, it
            focuses on interrelationships among the four decision levels
            involved in the formulation of trade policies. It then turns
            to the general goals of these policies: efficiency, income
            distribution, avoidance of retaliation, and provision of
            public goods, in particular creating a stable political and
            economic framework for future growth of the Economic
            Community. The last section describes the objectives of
            interest groups and the Community's policy responses to
            their demands.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            European community protection against
            manufactured imports from developing countries : a case
            study in the political economy of protection
        </docna>
        <display_title>European community protection
            against manufactured imports from developing countries : a
            case study in the political economy of protection</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1980/10/1555008/european-community-protection-against-manufactured-imports-developing-countries-case-study-political-economy-protection</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Trade and Regional Integration,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Trade Policy,Free Trade</subtopic>
        <teratopic>International Economics and Trade</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>VERREYDT, E.</author>
            <author>WAELBROECK, J.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903405887</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Trade</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 432</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>International Economics and Trade</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Import quotas; Income distribution;
            Industrial diversification; Protectionism; Tariffs; Trade
            liberalization; Trade policy
            adjustment assistance,adjustment
            policies,agriculture,bankruptcy,bargaining power,bilateral
            agreements,capital goods,cartel,cartels,coal,common
            market,comparative advantage,consumer
            goods,consumers,country markets,customs,customs
            unions,decision making,developed countries,domestic
            producers,dumping,Economic Analysis,Economic
            Community,economic impact,economists,elasticity,elasticity
            of supply,employment,export
            restrictions,exporters,exports,external barriers,external
            protection,external trade,external trade barriers,foreign
            competitors,free trade,human capital,Import
            Competition,import controls,import policies,import
            quotas,import substitution,imported
            goods,imports,income,income distribution,income
            groups,interest groups,international
            trade,inventories,legislation,liberal trade policy,market
            forces,market shares,member countries,member
            country,multilateral trade,multilateral trade
            liberalization,national policies,national security,net
            exports,OPEC,perfect competition,POLICY DECISIONS,policy
            instruments,policy makers,political
            economy,pollution,preferential access,preferential
            treatment,process of integration,producers,productive
            capacity,protectionist measures,protectionist
            policies,protectionist pressures,public good,public
            goods,public opinion,quota system,rational
            expectations,recession,rent seeking,social security,social
            tensions,Specialization,supply curve,Trade adjustment
            assistance,trade assistance,trade barriers,trade
            concessions,trade diversion,trade liberalization,trade
            losses,trade patterns,trade policies,trade policy,trade
            policy instruments,trade policy making,trade policy
            stance,trade relations,trade restrictions,trade theory,trade
            union,trade war,unemployment,VER,voters,wages,world trade
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP432</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Funds</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Funds and Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Zero Pillar</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Policy, Strategy and Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Cartels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Horizontal Agreements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Price Fixing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Political Economy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Political Economy Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Judicial Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Justice Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal and Judicial Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Care Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Laws and Regulations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Free Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textiles</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Unions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Anticartel Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Political Economy of Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>