<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Determinants of Private Industrial Investment in India&#13;
SWP333&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 333&#13;
June 1979&#13;
Prepared by: Armando Pinell-Siles&#13;
South Asia Programs Department&#13;
Copyright © 1979&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
; H Street, N.W.&#13;
kington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
iews and interpretations in this document are those of the authMon                      g&#13;
hould not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated&#13;
izations or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations,&#13;
or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 333&#13;
June 1979&#13;
DETERMINANTS OF PRIVATE INDUSTRIAL INVESTMENT IN INDIA&#13;
This paper analyses the behavior of private industrial investment in&#13;
India over time and some of the factors that have influenced it, such as&#13;
sales, profitability, taxation, financial resources, and others. Financial&#13;
data compiled by the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) from large samples of predo-&#13;
minantly manufacturing companies for the period 1960/61 to 1975/76 are the&#13;
basis for the analysis. Financial data are transformed into meaningful econo-&#13;
mic magnitudes, as illustrated by the transition from the historical cost of&#13;
fixed assets to their replacement value. The divergence between financial&#13;
depreciation and 'economic depreciation' as well as its implications for&#13;
profitability and taxation are also explored.&#13;
The analysis reveals that there has been a significant deceleration in the&#13;
rate of growth of the fixed capital stock since the middle 1960s. Contributing&#13;
to this deceleration are the inadequate growth of industrial demand and the&#13;
related decline in real rates of return on non-financial assets. The paper&#13;
briefly discusses recent investment developments and prospects in the light of&#13;
the previous analysis.&#13;
Prepared by: Armando Pinell-Siles&#13;
South Asia Programs Dept.&#13;
Copyright   ®   1979&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                            TEBMATIONAL MONETARY FUND&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433 U.S.A.                      JOINTLIBRARY&#13;
OCT 1 9 198.4&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BAll. FOR&#13;
RECOiGSTRU O'i.1 AND DEVLOpIlET&#13;
WASHINGTONi D. C. 2,0421&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
LIST OF CONTENTS&#13;
Page No.&#13;
SUMMARY        .....................................................  i-viii&#13;
I.   INTRODUCTION            ..........................................  1&#13;
II.   CAPITAL STOCK ESTIMATES AND INVESTMENT PATTERNS ....       ....    5&#13;
II.1  Capital Stock Estimates ..........................           5&#13;
II.2 Replacement and Accounting Values of the&#13;
Fixed Capital Stock ............................          9&#13;
[II.   NOMINAL AND EFFECTIVE TAXATION IN THE PRIVATE&#13;
CORPORATE SECTOR .....................................         12&#13;
III.1   Nominal and Effective Corporate Taxation ....     ....    12&#13;
III.2   Incidence of Corporate Taxation ....        .............  17&#13;
III.3   Indirect Taxation ...............................         23&#13;
IV.   PRIVATE CORPORATE INVESTMENT AND ITS DETERMINANTS         ......  26&#13;
IV.1 Definition and Trends of Some Invesment-&#13;
Related Variables ..............................         26&#13;
IV.2  Statistical Analysis of Investment Determinants ..         40&#13;
V.   CONCLUSION .............................................          47&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
LIST OF TABLES&#13;
Page No.&#13;
Table 1:  INDIA - Real Capital Stock and Investment Patterns in&#13;
Samples of Firms in the Private Corporate&#13;
Sector, 1961/62-1975/76                               7&#13;
Table 2:  INDIA - Replacement and Accounting Values of Fixed&#13;
Capital Stock in Samples of Firms in the&#13;
Private Corporate Sector, 1960/61-1975/76            11&#13;
Table 3:  INDIA - Nominal and Effective Taxation Rates in the&#13;
Private Corporate Sector, 1961/62-1975/76            13&#13;
Table 4:  INDIA - Incidence of Corporate Taxation                       20&#13;
Table 5:  INDIA - Regression Results for Assessing the&#13;
Incidence of Corporate Taxation                      22&#13;
Table 6:  INDIA - Indirect Taxation in Samples of Firms in the&#13;
Private Corporate Sector, 1971/72-1976/77            24&#13;
Table 7:  INDIA - Investment Patterns and Some Determinant&#13;
Factors in Samples of Companies in the&#13;
Private Corporate Sector, 1961/62-1975/76            30&#13;
Table 8:  INDIA - Investment Patterns and Related Factors               31&#13;
Table 9:  INDIA - Regression Results on Investment and its&#13;
Determinants in the Private Corporate Sector         44&#13;
Table Al: INDIA - Market Value of Non-Financial Assets and&#13;
Valuation Ratio in Samples of Firms in the&#13;
Private Corporate Sector, 1960/61-1975/76            49&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
DETERMINANTS OF PRIVATE&#13;
INDUSTRIAL INVESTMENT IN INDIA&#13;
(SUMMARY)&#13;
1.        This paper analyses the behavior of private industrial investment&#13;
in India over time and some of the factors that have influenced it, such&#13;
as sales, profitability, taxation, financial resources and others. From the&#13;
analysis of large RBI samples of predominantly manufacturing firms in the&#13;
private corporate sector over the period 1960/61 to 1975/76, it is possible to&#13;
conclude the following. There has been a significant deceleration in the real&#13;
rate of growth of the fixed capital stock in the private corporate sector&#13;
since the mid 1960s. Whereas the fixed capital stock increased at an average&#13;
growth rate of 9.2% p.a. between 1961/62 and 1965/66, the corresponding&#13;
increase was only 4.8% p.a. from 1966/67 to 1970/71 and 4.0% p.a. from 1971/72&#13;
to 1975/76. Central Statistical Organization (CSO) data seem to indicate that&#13;
these trends have continued after 1975/76. The analysis of RBI samples of&#13;
firms can throw light on some of the present constraints on investment.&#13;
2.        Several factors account for the relative deceleration in investment&#13;
activity over time. Perhaps the most important one has been demand: whereas&#13;
the volume of sales (in constant prices of 1960/61) increased at an average&#13;
growth rate of 6.1% p.a. in the period from 1960/61 to 1965/66, it only&#13;
increased by 4.7% p.a. from 1965/66 to 1970/71 and by 2.9% p.a. from 1970/71&#13;
to 1975/76.&#13;
3.        Associated with this decline and partly as a result of it, there&#13;
has been a decline in the rates of return on the replacement value of non-&#13;
financial assets, most evident with respect to the rates'prevailing in the&#13;
period from 1961/62 to 1965/66. The average rates of return before and after&#13;
corporate taxes were respectively 11% and 7% during the period 1961/62 to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 1.2. -&#13;
to 1965/66, declined to 7.4% and 5.2% respectively, from 1966/67 to 1970/i;&#13;
and fell slightly further to 7.2% ad 4.8% respectively, over the next five&#13;
years (1971/72 to 1975/76). In the more recent period, the annual after-tax&#13;
rate of return on non-financial assets has progressively declined from 5.7%&#13;
in 1971/72 to 4.7% in 1974/75 and then sharply to 3.2% in 1975/76. The&#13;
decline in 1975/76 may have had an influence on the subsequent private&#13;
corporate investment fall in 1976/77.&#13;
4.        After-tax rates of return have fallen more extensively than before-&#13;
tax rates of return, as a result of increased levels of taxation. The effec-&#13;
tive tax rate in profit-making companies increased from 44.0% in 1971/72 to&#13;
56.8% in 1974/75 and 67.9% in 1975/76 (Table 3). Higher effective corporate&#13;
tax rates in recent years are the result of two factors.      First, taxable&#13;
income has been overstated as a consequence of inadequate accounting depre-&#13;
ciation provisions which fail to compensate for the economic value of depre-&#13;
ciation in current prices. The divergence between accounting and replacement&#13;
values of fixed assets has progressively increased as a result of inflation.&#13;
Whereas in 1960/61 the replacement value of net fixed assets (net of accumu-&#13;
lative economic depreciation) was 77% and 129% respectively of the book value&#13;
of gross and net fixed assets, the corresponding percentages in 1975/76 were&#13;
139.5% and 269.1% respectively. In fact, most of the increase in effective&#13;
corporate tax rates between 1971/72 and 1975/76 can be imputed not to in-&#13;
creases in the nominal rates, but to overstatement of current income for&#13;
tax purposes. In profit-making companies, actual taxable income as percentage&#13;
of corrected taxable income 1/ increased from 106.5% in 1971/72 to 113.2% in&#13;
1/   I.e. adjusted to reflect the economi-c depreciation of fixed assets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- iii -&#13;
1973/74 and accelerated to 122.2% in 1974/75 and 138.8% in 1975/76 due to&#13;
higher inflation rates. Secondly, nominal tax rates have increased also,&#13;
partly as a. result of higher statutory rates and surcharges and partly on&#13;
account of the lower utilization of fiscal incentives for investment. In&#13;
effect, significantly higher corporate tax collections in very recent years&#13;
do not seem to be primarily the result of higher statutory tax rates, but a&#13;
consequence of the lower investment activity in the corporate sector (which&#13;
induces lower tax deductions and hence higher overall tax liability) together&#13;
with inadequate depreciation provisions which inflate the corporate tax&#13;
base. _1/&#13;
5.        There is evidence that suggests that the burden of the corporate&#13;
income tax is not shifted significantly to other economic areas (Table 5).&#13;
In other words, higher effective tax rates do contribute to depress after-tax&#13;
rates of return and to that extent may have reduced the willingness to invest&#13;
in recent years.&#13;
6.        A similar pattern seems to have developed with respect to indirect&#13;
taxes. An ICICI sample of firms indicates that the burden of indirect taxa-&#13;
tion has also increased over the 1970s. Indirect taxes as a percentage of&#13;
sales have progressively increased in recent years: from i2.6% in 1972/73&#13;
to 14.1% in 1974/75, to reach 14.9% in 1976/77. As percentage of value&#13;
added the burden of indirect taxation increased from 43.0% in 1972/73 to&#13;
1/   For instance, corporate taxes in 1977/78 were 31.6% higher than in&#13;
the previous year, even though prices (as reflected by changes in the&#13;
wholesale price index) rose only 5.1% over the same period. Probably&#13;
less than half of the real increase in corporate taxes can be attributed&#13;
to higher overall corporate income (the tax base); the rest reflects&#13;
higher effective taxation rates due to lower investment activity in&#13;
this period and inadequate depreciatian accounting.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- iv -&#13;
45.6% in 1974/75 and reached 55.8% in 1976/66. It is not possible to test&#13;
adequately the extent to which indirect taxes are shifted to customers through&#13;
higher prices. However, given the relatively large burden of indirect taxes&#13;
on sales and value added, it can be presumed that only a fraction of these&#13;
taxes is passed on, especially in the context of generally weak demand condi-&#13;
tions faced by companies in recent years. If similar patterns to those of&#13;
ICICI's sample are applicable to broader segments of the private corporate&#13;
sector, part of the decline in profitability observed in recent years in RBI&#13;
samples of firms may be attributed to their inability to raise prices to the&#13;
extent required to compensate fully for higher indirect taxes.&#13;
7.        Lower profitability and inadequate provision for depreciation have&#13;
reduced the savings capacity of the corporate sector. The proportion of&#13;
cash flow (defined as the sum of accounting after-tax profits and depreciation&#13;
provision) to the replacement value of the non-financial assets of the firm&#13;
(comprising fixed capital stock and inventories) has declined over time,&#13;
from an average rate of 9.2% between 1961/62 to 1965/66 to 7.1% in the period&#13;
1966/67 to 1970/71 and 6.8% in the subsequent five-year period. This decline&#13;
represents a reduction in the private corporate sector's ability to finance&#13;
internally a given percentage growth rate of its real capital stock, a factor&#13;
which may very well have contributed to the corresponding deceleration in the&#13;
the growth rate observed since 1965/66 (Table 8).&#13;
8.        The real (after-tax) rate of return on invested capital is only&#13;
one of two critical elements on the investment decision. The other one is&#13;
the real cost of capital to the firm. The differential between these&#13;
variables is one factor determining whether an investment is worth undertaking&#13;
or not. The valuation ratio attempts to measure such a differential, and is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- v -&#13;
defined as the ratio of the (imputed) market value of the firms' real capital&#13;
assets to the replacement cost of those same assets. The implications of the&#13;
valuation ratio for investment are summarized as follows:&#13;
"Investment is stimulated when capital is valued more&#13;
highly in the market than it costs to produce it and&#13;
discouraged when its valuation is less than its replace-&#13;
ment cost." 1/&#13;
9.        Table 7 presents estimates of the valuation ratio for RBI samples&#13;
of companies. There has been a decline in the valuation ratio: from an&#13;
average rate of 65.7% from 1961/62 to 1965/66, to 62.4% from 1966/67 t,o&#13;
1970/71 and 56.0% in the subsequent five-year period. This decline coincides&#13;
with the deceleration of the growth rate of the fixed capital stock. 2/&#13;
10.       In addition to the broad comparisons of trends in variables over&#13;
five-year periods, statistical analysis of yearly variations in investment&#13;
rates and their determinants, has been undertaken. This analysis shows that&#13;
the annual rate of fixed capital formation is very highly correlated with&#13;
sales per unit of fixed assets, the after-tax rate of return, and cash flow&#13;
relative to the replacement value of non-financial capital stock, and to a&#13;
1/   W.C. Brainard and J. Tobin, "Pitfalls in Financial Model Building",&#13;
American Economic Review, May 1968, pp. 99-149. (p. 103).&#13;
2/   The decline in the valuation ratio has not been uniform, especially&#13;
as a result of downward shifts in expectations about profitability&#13;
in periods of severe droughts and other unfavorable economic condi-&#13;
tions (e.g. 1973-75). During these periods, the proportional decline&#13;
in the valuation ratio has been less acute than the relative fall in&#13;
the after-tax rate of return, indicating that the real cost of capital&#13;
has also declined (but to a smaller extent than the rate of return).&#13;
The main explanation for the decline in the cost of capital is the&#13;
following one: in periods of unanticipated inflation (as were to a&#13;
large extent the periods from 1966 to 1968 and from 1973 to 1975),&#13;
the nominal rate of interest attached to previously contracted debt&#13;
fails to adjust to inflationary conditions, inducing a transfer of&#13;
real resources from lenders to borrowers. Under these conditions&#13;
the rate of return fails to incorporat? the gains that accrue to&#13;
the firms as a result of having a lower real value of debt.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- vi -&#13;
lower extent with the valuation ratio. Regression results confirm the import-&#13;
ant role of demand on investment patterns in the private corporate sector. Not&#13;
only have sales influenced investment activity directly but also through profit-&#13;
ability and cash flow. Variations in the after-tax rate of return are explained&#13;
to a large extent by demand conditions and by changes in effective corporate&#13;
tax rates.&#13;
11.       The analysis of RBI samples up to 1975/76 can throw light on some&#13;
of the present constraints on investment. If ICICI data on companies are&#13;
indicative of the overall behavior of the private corporate sector, it seems&#13;
that profitability suffered a further decline in 1976/77, beyond the fall&#13;
observed in 1975/76 (Table 6). Such a fall seems to have resulted primarily&#13;
from inadequate demand growth, and from rising effective corporate tax rates&#13;
due to inadequate depreciation provisions that failed to adjust taxable income&#13;
for inflationary conditions on the one hand, and lower investment activity&#13;
itself on the oth.er. 1/ In addition, real interest rates were substantially&#13;
higher due to much lower price increases in the context of constant nominal&#13;
interest rates in this period. A lower real rate of return accompanied by a&#13;
higher real cost of capital implies a decline in the valuation ratio. Such a&#13;
decline may explain to a large extent the significant fall in private corporate&#13;
investment in 1976/77.&#13;
12.       The prospects for private industrial investment have improved&#13;
since the second half of 1977/78. Better demand conditions have improved&#13;
capacity utilization and profitability. Equity prices, which to a large&#13;
extent reflect profit expectations, have risen substantially during 1978.&#13;
1/   Consult p. iii above.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- vii -&#13;
Nominal interest rates charged by scheduled commercial banks were reduced from&#13;
14-15% to 12.5% effective June 1977. All these factors point to an increase&#13;
in the valuation ratio during 1978. Consequently, private industrial invest-&#13;
ment activity can be expected to improve broadly in the near future, provided&#13;
some uncertainties in the political and economic spheres do not provoke reti-&#13;
cence on the part of prospective investors. 1/&#13;
13.       Many factors that influence investment are not amenable to&#13;
quantitative analysis; among the most important of these are the regulatory&#13;
framework embodied in investment licensing and MRTP restrictions, and uncer-&#13;
tainty. The extent to which the regulatory system influences investment&#13;
patterns is difficult to assess; it appears, however, that in its present form&#13;
such a system - through delays if not by actual rejection of investment&#13;
applications - tends to decrease the expected rate of return on prospective&#13;
investment, and limits the elasticity of investment response to changing&#13;
economic circumstances. But these topics are outside the scope of this paper.&#13;
14.       In addition to analyzing some determinants of private industrial&#13;
investment in India, this paper has studied several variables that are of&#13;
interest in themselves. For instance, the replacement value of non-financial&#13;
assets (and its relation to accounting data), as well as the rate of return&#13;
(before and after taxes) on non-financial assets, are preliminary steps in&#13;
the calculation of the social rate of return to private investment, an&#13;
important datum for social cost-benefit analysis. Similarly, the taxation of&#13;
corporate income and its trend reveal some of the distortions induced by lack&#13;
of inflation clauses in accounting measures.&#13;
1/   An example of these is the recently discussed issue of nationalization&#13;
of certain industries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- viii -&#13;
15.       This paper has concentrated on aggregate trends in the private&#13;
industrial sector. Undoubtedly, there have been differences in performance&#13;
among specific industries; as illustrated by the cement and traditional&#13;
textile industries where until recently profitability and investment patterns&#13;
had been conditioned by the operation of restrictive pricing policies. A&#13;
natural extension of this paper is the disaggregation by industries or groups&#13;
of industries, to ascertain the extent to which there are underlying varia-&#13;
tions in the trends observed before.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
DETERMINANTS OF PRIVATE&#13;
INDUSTRIAL INVESTMENT IN INDIA&#13;
I.   INTRODUCTION&#13;
1.01      This paper analyses the behavior of non-financial private industrial&#13;
investment in India over time and some of the factors that have influenced it,&#13;
such as sales, profitability, taxation, financial resources and others. The&#13;
analysis relies extensively on financial data from RBI 1/ samples of companies&#13;
covering the period 1960/61 to 1975/76. The large size of the samples ensures&#13;
their representativeness of a broad segment of the private corporate sector,&#13;
especially as regards manufacturing activities.&#13;
1.02      The structure of this paper is a follows.    Section II presents&#13;
estimates of the fixed capital stock, in constant prices and replacement&#13;
values, and derives investment series for the period 1961/62 to 1975/76.&#13;
The relation between accounting and economic measures of the fixed capital&#13;
stock is explored in section II.2.&#13;
1.03      Section III studies nominal and effective tax rates in the private&#13;
corporate sector and relies on some of the results of the previous section.&#13;
Specifically, accounting measures of profits are adjusted to the extent that&#13;
accounting depreciation provisions fail to reflect the economic depreciation&#13;
of fixed assets in an inflationary context. 2/&#13;
1/   The Reserve Bank of India.   Detailed references are listed in the&#13;
bibliography at the end of the text.&#13;
2/   Between 1961/62 and 1975/76 the index number of wholesale prices more&#13;
than trebled, reflecting an average annual inflation rate of 8.2%.&#13;
Whereas this rate is lower than in several other less developed&#13;
countries, it cannot be considered negligible..&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
1.04      Section IV links the behavior of private corporate investment over&#13;
time to several factors including the rate of return from capital, 1/ the&#13;
valuation ratio, 2/ the degree of utilization of installed capacity, 3/ and&#13;
others. The first part of this section compares trends in these variables,&#13;
while the second one studies the importance of some of these variables in&#13;
explaining investment patterns, using multiple regression methods to that&#13;
effect.&#13;
1.05      Section V is the concluding part of the paper.     Before entering&#13;
Section II, it is important to analyze the nature and some of the limitations&#13;
of the data. There are three RBI samples of companies, each covering a period&#13;
of six years. The first series covers 1333 companies and extends from 1960-61&#13;
to 1965-66. The second one includes 1501 companies and covers the period from&#13;
1965-66 to 1970-71. The third sample comprises 1650 companies and extends from&#13;
1970-71 to 1975-76. One of the main advantages of these samples is that for&#13;
1/   For the analysis of investment in physical assets, the relevant rates&#13;
of return from capital in manufacturing are those with respect to non-&#13;
financial assets. Consequently, both the income derived from financial&#13;
assets and these assets themselves are to be excluded from the calcula-&#13;
tions. (Non-financial assets include the fixed capital stock and inven-&#13;
tories.) Another adjustement consists in considering interest payments&#13;
and managerial remuneration as part of the return from capital. On these&#13;
and other related issues, consult: Jenkins, G. "The Measurement of Rates&#13;
of Return and Taxation from Private Capital in Canada", reprinted in&#13;
W.A. Niskanen et al. (eds.) Benefit-Cost and Policy Analysis 1972 (Aldine&#13;
1973): and Harberger, A. "Investment in Men Versus Investment in&#13;
Machines" (1965) reprinted in D. Wall (ed.) Chicago Essays in Economic&#13;
Development, U. of Chicago Press, 1972.&#13;
2/   The valuation ratio measures the relationship between the market valua-&#13;
tion and the replacement cost of non-financial assets, and provides a&#13;
relative measure of the real return from capital vis a vis the real&#13;
cost of capital.&#13;
3/   As measured by the ratio of sales (in current prices) and the replace-&#13;
ment value of fixed assets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
any adjacent samples, there are two sets of data for the overlapping years;&#13;
namely, for 1965-66 and 1970-71. This permits proper adjustment for the chang-&#13;
ing size of the samples.&#13;
1.06      The RBI samples cover medium and large non-financial, non-government,&#13;
public limited companies. Only those companies with paid-up capital of at&#13;
least Rs. 5 lakhs are included in the samples. These companies account for&#13;
48.9% of paid-up capital in the private corporate sector in 1964-65, although&#13;
in number of companies their representation is smaller. 1/&#13;
1.07      The enlargement of the RBI samples over the years has extended their&#13;
representativeness. The sample of 1650 medium and large, non-financial, non-&#13;
Government, public limited firms accounted for about 80.4% of the paid-up&#13;
capital in all non-Government, public limited companies in 1971/72. 2/ This&#13;
represents approximately 63% of the paid-up capital in the private corporate&#13;
1/   The private -corporate sector consists of "public" limited and "private"&#13;
limited companies; the distinction is based on whether stocks are widely&#13;
held by the public or not. Out of a total number of 6450 public limited&#13;
companies in 1964-65, 37.5% had at least Rs 5 lakhs of paid-up capital,&#13;
but they accounted for 95.4% of the total paid-up capital in public&#13;
limited companies. The sample of 1333 firms in series I accounts for&#13;
20.7% of the total number of public companies but includes 62.8% of their&#13;
total paid-up capital in 1964-65. Private limited companies, although&#13;
more numerous (19588 firms against only 6450 public limited companies in&#13;
1964-65), represent only a small fraction of assets in the non-financial&#13;
private corporate sector (their total paid-up capital was only 22.1% of&#13;
the total paid-up capital of private and public limited firms in 1964-65).&#13;
Further details on the composition of samples I and II are included in&#13;
RBI, Financial Statistics of Joint Stock Companies in India, 1960-61 to&#13;
1970-71, pp. 1-7.&#13;
2/   RBI Census of public limited companies for 1971/72.    The unadjusted&#13;
Census results lead to 86%, but it is stated that only 94% of the&#13;
paid-up capital of these companies was actually counted in the Census.&#13;
(RBI Bulletin, June 1978, p. 413).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
sector. 1/ Most of the firms in the RBI sample of companies are engaged in&#13;
manufacturing. Approximately 86.5% of sales and 83.5% of gross fixed assets&#13;
in the sample of 1,650 companies corresponded to manufacturing activities in&#13;
1975/76. In conclusion, the large size of the RBI samples and their coverage&#13;
indicate that the information is highly representative of the non-financial&#13;
private corporate sector, especially as it relates to manufacturing activities.&#13;
1.08      The investment undertaken by new firms is not reflected in these&#13;
data. However, the importance of this omission does not appear to be serious&#13;
with respect to medium and large companies. Most of the investment activity&#13;
in medium and large firms in the private corporate sector in India is con-&#13;
centrated in established firms, as follows from a census of public limited&#13;
companies undertaken by RBI for 1971/72. 2/&#13;
1/   To obtain this estimate it is assumed that the share of non-Government&#13;
public limited companies in the paid-up capital of all private corporate&#13;
firms is the same as in 1964/65, namely 77.9%.&#13;
2/   The increase in gross fixed assets in medium and large, public limited&#13;
firms under construction during 1971/72 was only 15.4% of the increase&#13;
in gross fixed assets in medium and large, public limited firms that&#13;
had been operating at least since 1970/71. RBI Bulletin, June 1978,&#13;
p. 424.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 5 -&#13;
II. CAPITAL STOCK ESTIMATES AND INVESTMENT PATTERNS&#13;
II.1      Capital Stock Estimates&#13;
2.01      Table 1 presents estimates of the real stock of fixed capital for&#13;
samples of firms in the private corporate sector. Starting from an initial&#13;
value of the stock of fixed assets for 1960/61, subsequent values (in constant&#13;
prices) are calculated following the perpetual inventory accumulation method;&#13;
i.e. by adding the real gross investment in fixed assets during year t+l to&#13;
the existing stock at the end of year t, and substracting the real economic&#13;
depreciation during year t+l, a measure of the fixed capital stock at the end&#13;
of year t+l is obtained.&#13;
2.02      Real gross investment is calculated by deflating nominal gross in-&#13;
vestment in fixed assets by the implicit price deflator of gross fixed capital&#13;
formation (base 1960/61, derived from National Accounts). 1/ Nominal gross&#13;
investment in fixed assets is derived from company accounts and is composed&#13;
of: (1) nominal iincrease in gross fixed assets, (2) adjustment for retired&#13;
assets, 2/ and (3) repairs to building and machinery. 3/&#13;
2.03      Real economic depreciation of fixed assets during year t is assumed&#13;
to be a constant fraction (6%) of the real fixed capital stock at the end of&#13;
1/   The use of the price index of investment goods to estimate the value of&#13;
the capital stock follows Jorgenson, W.D. and Z. Grilliches, "The explana-&#13;
tion of productivity change", Review of Economic Studies, vol. 34, 1967,&#13;
pp. 249-83.&#13;
2/   Following Harberger, op. cit., it is assumed that expenditure on new&#13;
fixed assets exceeded the increase in the book value of gross fixed&#13;
assets by the same amount by which depreciation allowances exceeded the&#13;
change in accumulated depreciation during the year (on the presumption&#13;
that assets are generally fully depreciated before they are retired).&#13;
3/   Repairs to building and machinery are expenses that prolong the life of&#13;
fixed assets and as such should be included as part of gross investment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
year t-l. 1/ The uniform rate ot 6% is applied to an aggregate value composed&#13;
of land, buildings, "plant and machinery" and "others", representing approxi-&#13;
mately 4%; 19%; 69% and 8% respectively of the book value of gross fixed assets&#13;
in 1960/61. This depreciation rate implies that after 10, 20 or 30 years, only&#13;
53.9%; 29% and 15.6% respectively of a starting bundle of fixed assets will&#13;
remain in operation. Since land is not likely to depreciate in real value over&#13;
time and buildings have a longer life than plant and machinery, the implied&#13;
average length of life of real fixed asets is deemed adequate. 2/ 3/&#13;
1/   If the aggregate capital stock is composed of goods with a wide dis-&#13;
tribution of average lives, the number of machines being retired from&#13;
production in any given year approaches a proportion of the existing'&#13;
capital stock, independent of changing patterns in annual investment.&#13;
(Consult Jorgenson, D.W. "Anticipations and Investment Behavior" in&#13;
J.S. Duesenberry et al (eds.), The Brookings Quarterly Econometric Model&#13;
of tne United States, Rand McNally, pp. 35-92, p. 51) However, the&#13;
assumption that a fixed percentage of the outstanding capital stock&#13;
is withdrawn from the production process each year, ignores the fact&#13;
that the retirement of fixed assets is not uniquely conditioned by&#13;
the length of life of these assets but depends also on price and profit&#13;
conditions (e.g. economic obsolescence). For a more general treatment&#13;
of depreciation, consult Wright, F.K. "Towards a General Theory of&#13;
Depreciation", reprinted in Parker, R.K. and G.C. Harcourt (eds.)&#13;
Readings in the Concept and Measurement of Income, 1969.&#13;
2/   Alternative depreciation rates have been studied and the estimates&#13;
of the fixed capital stock do not seem to be too sensitive to these&#13;
assumptions. For instance, real fixed assets in 1975/76 would be&#13;
only 13.8% lower if a depreciation rate of 8% is used instead of 6%.&#13;
3/   Except for the implied length of life of fixed assets, it is not&#13;
possible to test directly whether the assumed depreciation rate of&#13;
6% is adequate or not. R.N. Lal, Capital Formation and its Financing&#13;
in India, 1977 presents estimates of the annual consumption of fixed&#13;
capital in the entire private corporate sector in current prices. By&#13;
applying the implicit price deflator for gross fixed capital formation&#13;
(from the same source) to these series, it is possible to derive the&#13;
value of depreciation in constant prices of 1960/61 for the private&#13;
corporate sector. Then it is possible to test whether the implied&#13;
depreciation (in constant prices) from RBI samples of companies for&#13;
specific years bears the same proportion to the total depreciation&#13;
for the private corporate sector (as derived from R.N. Lal's book),&#13;
as the size of the samples relative to the entire private corporate&#13;
sector for the sarne years. (As measured by paid-up capital).&#13;
(cont'd)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INDIA: Real Capital Stock and Inventment Patterns in Samples of Firms in the Private Corporate Sector. 1961/62 - 1975/76&#13;
(Constant prices 1960;61 - 100, Rs million)&#13;
YEAR          Real stock of        Real increases in 2/      Adjustment for 3/     Repairs to Building   Real gross&#13;
fixed capital        gross fixed assets-       retired assets  -    and machinery    S/    investment in 6/   Real economic L/     Real net        Groas invest,cent    Net investment&#13;
fixed assets        Depreciation        investment           rate   8            rate !I&#13;
SERIES I&#13;
1960-1                  14000&#13;
61-2                  15586                 1800                    86                     540                   2426               840              15865                17.3                11.3&#13;
62-3                  17086                 1781                    120                    534                   2435               935              15000                15.6                 9.6&#13;
63-4                  18864                 2073                   108                     622                  2803               1025              17788                16.4                10.4&#13;
64-5                  20388                 1924                   155                     517                   2656              1132              15244                14.1                 8.1&#13;
65-6                  21722                 1860                   140                     558                  2558               1223              13355                12.5                 6.5&#13;
SERIES 1I&#13;
4,&#13;
65-6                  23653                                                                                                        1332&#13;
66-7                  25349                 2410                   155                     549                   3114              1419              1695                 13.2                7.2&#13;
67-8                  26783                 2246                   140                     570                  2956               1521             1435                  11.7                5.7&#13;
68-9                  27954                 1976                   209                     593                  2778               1607              1171                 10.4                4.4&#13;
69-70                 29012                 1956                   138                     641                  2735               1677              1058                  9.8                3.8&#13;
70-71                 29863                 1817                    146                    629                  2592               1741               851                  8.9                2.9&#13;
SERIES III&#13;
4/&#13;
70-71                 31934                                                                                                        1862&#13;
71-72                 33083                2150                     163                    752                   3065               1916             1149                 9.6                 3.6&#13;
72-73                 34567                2517                     151                    801                   3469               1985             1484                10.5                 4.5&#13;
73-74                 36052                2537                     185                    837                   3559               2074             1485                10.3                 4.3&#13;
74-75                 37481                2635                     148                    809                   3592              2163              1429                10.0                 4.0&#13;
75-76                 38771                2581                     120                    838                   3539              2249              1290                 9.4                 3.4&#13;
Source:  RBI, Samples of medium and large non-financial, non-government, public limited companies.     R8I Monthly Bulletin, several issues.   Series I. II and III are not strictly comparable&#13;
sinee they involve different number of firms.    Nonetheless, adjustments have been made in relation to the changing size of the samples, so that consistent estimates of gross and&#13;
net investment rates are derived in the last tw columns.&#13;
1/   Real fixed capital is estimated each year by net accumaulation. I.e. Kt+l - RCTt+l - Dt+l +Kt     d Dt+l - (.06) Kt where Ktis ral fixed capital stock at end of year t, RClt+l - real&#13;
gross investment taking place durlng ysr t+1 and Dt+l - mal depreciation during year t+l, which by assumption is a fixed proportion (6%) of the outstanding real capital stock&#13;
at the end of year t. The initial stock of capital (1960-61) in series I has been estimated at Rn 14000 million at prices of 1960/61. This value is approximately the average between&#13;
the book values of gross and net fixed assets in 1960-61.    It is believed that accounting depreciation rates were quite liberal over the period prior to 1960-61 (even in relation&#13;
to inflation) so that the net value of fixed assets would in effect underestimate the true value.&#13;
2/   The nominal increase in gross fixed assets (as reflected in the sources-and-uses-of-funds table) deflated by the implicit deflator for gross fixed capital formation (column 2,&#13;
Table 2), represents the real increase in gross fixed assets.&#13;
3/   Retired assets can be expected to be fully depreciated before they are retired.     The excess of depreciation allowances (from Income Statement) over the change in accumulated&#13;
depreciation (from Sources and Uses of Funds Table) represents the required adjustment.     It has been deflated by the implicit deflator for gross fixed capital formation.&#13;
4/   To correct for the changing site of the samples, the real stock of fixed capital for a new sample was expanded in the same proportion by which gross fixed assets in the new sample&#13;
exceeded the corresponding value in the old sample for the same year.    Thus in 1965/66 gross fixed assets in series II exceeded the corresponding value for that same year in the&#13;
old sample by 8.89.; consequently the expansion factor for the real capital stock was 1.0889.     Similarly for 1970/71 the expansion factor was 1.0693.&#13;
5/   Repairs to building and machinery are taken from the annual income statement and converted to 1960/61 prices using the implicit deflator for fixed capital formation.       Series I&#13;
(1961/62 to 1965/66) does not contain this information.    It has been estimated that Repairs to Building and Machineryinater years amount to about 30. of the increase in gross fixed&#13;
assets; this percentage has been used to calculate the unavailable data in order to derive a consistent time series.&#13;
6J   Comprises real increase in gross fixed assets. adjustment for retired assets and repairs to building and machimary.It is implicitly assumed that the cost of repairs to building&#13;
and machinery is directly equivalent to the increasea value of repaired fixed assets.&#13;
7/   Real economic depreciation during year t is assumed to be 6% of the real value of fixed assets remaining at the end of year t-1.      This deprecintion rate implies that after 10, 20&#13;
or 30 years only 53.9%, 29%. and 15.67. respectively, of a starting bundle of fixed assets will remain in operation.    Since buildings are included, the implied length of life&#13;
of reel fixed assets is deemed adequate.    Alternative depreciation rates (e.g. 87.) have been studied and the estimates of fixed capital stock do not seem to be too sensitive&#13;
to these assumptions.   For instance, real fixed assiets in 1975/76 would be 13.8% lower if 87. is used instead of 6%. The depreciation rate of 67. may understate the true economic&#13;
depreciation of fixed assets, especially of machinery and equipment.    An 87. depreciation rate would imply that after 10, 20 and 30 years, only 43.4%, 18.97 and 8.27 resps-ctively.&#13;
of a starting bundle of fixed assets would remain in operation. The impact of assueing depreciation rates other than 6% on profitability and tax rates vill be analyzed in Section 111.1&#13;
8/ Gross (net) fixed investment during year t as a percentage of the real stock of fixed capital at the end of year t-l.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -.&#13;
2.04      To correct for the changing size of the samples the real stock&#13;
of fixed assets has been expanded in the same proportion by which gross fixed&#13;
assets in the first year of the new sample exceeded the corresponding value&#13;
(for the same year) in the old sample. For 1965/66 the real capital stock&#13;
of the sample firms was expanded by nearly 9% whereas for 1970/71 it was&#13;
increased by about 7% (Table 1).&#13;
2.05      Annual real gross investment in fixed assets minus economic&#13;
depreciation represents net real investment in fixed assets. The percentages&#13;
of gross or net real fixed investment during a year to the real value of the&#13;
fixed capital stock at the end of the previous year, provide measures of gross&#13;
and net real growth rates of the fixed capital stock. These rates are labeled&#13;
gross and net investment rate, respectively. The main advantage of these&#13;
(footnote 3/ cont'd)&#13;
Percentage of Sample's Depre-              Approximate Share of&#13;
ciation to Total Depreciation            Samples in Paid-up Capital&#13;
6% rate   8% rate                   (percentage)&#13;
Series I:     1964/65    47.3        60.2                        48.9&#13;
Series II:    1971.72    68.4        81.0                        63.0&#13;
The above table seems to indicate that the depreciation rate of 6%&#13;
is within the expected ranges and is to be preferred to the 8% depreciation&#13;
rate. For 1971/72 the share of the sample in the depreciation of the entire&#13;
private corporate sector is larger than that implied by the share in paid-up&#13;
capital, but the latter estimate may itself be subject to some error. In&#13;
addition, Lal's implied depreciation in the private corporate sector may be&#13;
underestimated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
measures is that they are independent of size and may be taken as representa-&#13;
tive of broader segments of the private corporate sector than the actual&#13;
samples of companies on which they are based. 1/&#13;
2.06      The main result that follows from Table 1 is the deceleration in the&#13;
rate of growth of the fixed capital stock, at least compared to the period&#13;
from 1960/61 to 1965/66, in which the average (net) rate of growth was 9.2% per&#13;
annum. 2/ In contrast, the average (net) growth of the fixed capital stock&#13;
was 4.8 % p.a. between 1965/66 and 1970/71 and only 4.0% p.a from 1970/71&#13;
until 1975/76.&#13;
11.2 Replacement and Accounting Values of the Fixed Capital Stock&#13;
2.07      Table 2 establishes the relationships that exist between accounting&#13;
and economic values of the fixed capital stock. To obtain the replacement&#13;
value of fixed assets the implicit deflator for fixed capital formation is&#13;
applied to the constant-price series of the capital stock. 3/&#13;
1/   Changes in inventories are part of capital formation but are excluded&#13;
in the above calculations because of the larger uncertainty surrounding&#13;
their measurement. For instances, in years of high rotation of inven-&#13;
tories, their book value may reflect adequately their replacement cost,&#13;
but the extent to which this is true depends on the accounting practices&#13;
followed for valuation. (See footnote 1 on page 27).&#13;
2/   Unless it is indicated otherwise, the average growth rates are the&#13;
annual geometric growth rates calculated between the initial and final&#13;
values of a given variable.&#13;
3/   This procedure may overstate the replacement value of fixed assets&#13;
in later years if the implicit price deflator does not adequately&#13;
reflect the qualitative changes (i.e. technological progress) incor-&#13;
porated in the more recent generations of machinery and equipment.&#13;
As J.F. Helliwell has pointed out: "...if embodied technical progress&#13;
is identified with price reductions in capital goods, then the constant&#13;
price measure of the capital stock is the right measure of productive&#13;
potential, for any given rate of capacity utilization. If the price&#13;
index is otherwise defined, then comparability is obtained by writing&#13;
down earlier vintages by the appropriate rate of obsolescence."&#13;
J.F Helliwell "Survey of Issues" in J.F. Helliwell, (ed.) Aggregate&#13;
Investment, Pengiun, 1976, p. 28.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
2.08      Columns 6 and 7 list the extent to which gross fixed assets and&#13;
net fixed assets as they appear in firm's accounting sheets differ from the&#13;
replacement value of the fixed capital stock over the period 1960/61 to 1975/76&#13;
The following points need to be stressed: (a) After 1969/70, inflation has&#13;
created an increasing disparity between accounting and replacement values; (b)&#13;
the progressive underestimation of fixed capital in recent years is much more&#13;
serious in the case of net fixed assets than gross fixed assets. In 1975/76&#13;
the replacement value of the capital stock was nearly 40% higher than gross&#13;
fixed assets and almost three times larger than net fixed assets; (c) the&#13;
underestimation of the replacement value of fixed capital depends not only on&#13;
inflation but on the time pattern of investments. 1/ It depends not only on&#13;
current inflation rates but also on past investment and inflation rates; e.g.&#13;
currently low inflation rates do not seem to be sufficient to compensate for&#13;
the distortions induced by high price increases a few years ago.&#13;
2.09      The next section analyses taxation patterns in the corporate sector.&#13;
In this context, the economic depreciation in current terms (derived in the&#13;
last column of Table 2) has to be contrasted with the accounting depreciation&#13;
allowed for taxation purposes. It will be shown that, similarly to the valua-&#13;
tion of fixed assets, inflation induces an increasingly large discrepancy&#13;
between accounting and economic measures of depreciation, a fact which has&#13;
broader repercussions not only on taxation but on profitability as well.&#13;
1/   If it can be presumed that the sample's investment pattern is repre-&#13;
sentative, then the percentages of replacement value of fixed assets&#13;
to gross fixed assets can be used as "conversion factors" for trans-&#13;
forming accounting figures into replacement values of fixed assets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 2&#13;
INDIA - Replacement and Accounting Values of Fixed Capital Stock in Samples of Firms&#13;
in the Private Corporate Sector, 1960/61 - 1975/76&#13;
(Rs million)&#13;
1                      2                     3                4                     5                6             7              8                  9&#13;
Real value of         Implicit deflator                                                                                                             Annual Economic&#13;
fixed assets         for fixed capital                1/     Gross fixed  2/     Net fixed   2/     RFK as % of    RFK as % of               3/     Depreciation in 4/&#13;
Year       (1960/61 prices)     formation (1960/61=100)   RFK(t)       assets (GFA)        assets (NFA)          CFA             NFA          RFK(t-l)        Current prices&#13;
SERIES I&#13;
1960-1       14000                     100.00             14000           18130               10880              77.2          128.7&#13;
61-2       15586                     104.10             16225           20000               11800               81. 1        137.5            14574               874&#13;
62-3       17086                     107.46             18361           21910               12720               83.8         144.3            16749              1005&#13;
63-4       18864                     112.42             21207           24250               13870               87.5         152.9            19208              1155&#13;
64-5       20388                     115.94             23638           26480               14810               89.3         159.6            21871              1312&#13;
65-6       21722                     123.97             26929           28860               15840              93.3          170-0            25275              1516&#13;
SERIES II&#13;
65-6       23653                     123.97             29323           31430               18360               93.3         159-7&#13;
66-7       25348                     137.51             34856           35740               21020               97.5         165.8            32525              1951&#13;
67-8       26783                     143.78             38509           38970               22480               98.8         171.3            36445              2187&#13;
68-9       27954                     149.33             41744           41900               23590              99.6          177.0            39995              2400&#13;
69-70      29012                     156.36             45363           44980               24520              100.9         185.0            43709              2622&#13;
70-71      29863                     167.47             50011           48060               25220              104.1         198.3            48586              2915&#13;
SERIES III!&#13;
70-71      31934                     167.47             534800          50770               28140              105.3         190.0&#13;
71-2       33083                     175.84             581733          54610               29220              106.5         199.1            56153              3369&#13;
72-3       34567                     186.56             644888          59560               31150              108.3         207.0            61720              3703&#13;
73-4       36052                     207.42             747799          65020               33500              115.0         223.0            71699              4302&#13;
74-5       37481                     262.18             982688          72750               37710              135.1         260.6            94521              5671&#13;
75-6       38771                     289.45            1122233          80440               41700              139.5         269.1           108489              6509&#13;
Source:  RBI Samples of medium and large non-financial, nion-government, public limited companies.  RBI Monthly Bulletin, several issues.   Column I is derived from Table&#13;
1/   Replacement value of fixed assets at the end of year t, valued at prices of year t.&#13;
2/   Accounting measures taken from Balance-Sheets.&#13;
3/   Replacement value of fixed assets corresponding to the stock at the end of year t-1 but valued at prices of year t.    Conceptually, it is equivalent to the&#13;
replacement value of fixed assets at the beginning of year t, valued at average prices of that year.&#13;
4/   Equivalent to 6% of the stock of capital at the beginning of the year.   Consult Table 1,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
III. NOMINAL AND EFFECTIVE TAXATION IN THE PRIVATE CORPORATE SECTOR&#13;
II1.1     Nominal and Effective Corporate Taxation&#13;
3.01       In assessing the extent of corporate taxation it is necessary to&#13;
consider not only the taxation rates but also the bases to which those rates&#13;
pertain. In particular, it is widely known that inflation will distort the&#13;
meaning of conventional accounting measures, such as depreciation based on&#13;
the historic cost (book value) of fixed assets. To the extent that accounting&#13;
depreciation in inflationary periods may fail to reflect the "economic"&#13;
depreciation of fixed assets (i.e. the compensation for "wear and tear" that&#13;
would enable the firm to replace a fixed asset when its life comes to an&#13;
end), the measure of corporate income for assessing tax liability will also&#13;
be distorted.&#13;
3.02      Table 3 presents data on corporate taxation at the company level,&#13;
from 1961/62 to 1975/76. The "economic" depreciation of fixed assets in&#13;
current (replacement) terms is derived in Table 2 from a consistent series&#13;
on the fixed capital stock in a large sample of firms in the private corporate&#13;
sector. 1/ The taxation data apply to the same group of firms. 2/&#13;
3.03      In order to calculate an economic measure of taxable income over&#13;
time, the actual taxable income (ATI), as defined for accounting purposes,&#13;
is corrected by the excess of accounting (AD) over economic (ED) depreciation.&#13;
1/   It is assumed that economic depreciation in year t is equivalent to 6% of&#13;
the outstanding real fixed capital stock at the beginning of that year.&#13;
2/   Table 3 distinguishes between profits before tax (as listed in the income&#13;
statement) and "other income". The latter refers primarily to income from&#13;
holdings of financial assets. Since at a later stage the rate of return&#13;
on non-financial assets will be calculated, the corresponding breakdown of&#13;
profits and taxes (exclusive of "other income") has been carried out in&#13;
Table 3. It is being assumed that tax rates on "other income" are similar&#13;
to those on operating profits, thereby;xdisregarding the existence of some&#13;
minor incentives for holdings of financial assets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 3&#13;
_/&#13;
IN1A: Nominal and Effective Taxation Rates in the Private Corporate Sector. 1961/62 - 1976&#13;
(Current prices in Rn million)&#13;
1 I              2                3              4                  5               6                  7               8                 9               10               1\                 12&#13;
Nominal                                                                                 Accounting                                          Actual taxable&#13;
tax rate on      Profits before                      Accon-         9Eonomic            Depreciation    Corretetd       Effective tx.      inco     as t&#13;
Profit            Other            Total         eccounting      tax minus         Adjusted      3/   ting           Depreciation in    ainus Econ.     Taxable         rate on             of corrected&#13;
before tax        income        tax provision   taxable incose   other income       tax provision     Depreciation   Current prices 3./ Depreciation    Incomne 5/       corregjd incoma    taxable income&#13;
SERIES I&#13;
1961-2            2330             352             1018             43.7            1978              864             1040             874              166             2144               40.3             92.3&#13;
62-3            2557             398             1338             52.3            2159             1129             1129            1005              124             2283               49.5             94.6&#13;
63-4            2899             459             1479             51.0            2440             1245             1297            1152              145             2585               48.2             94.4&#13;
64-5            2996             487             1514             50.5            2509             1267             1478            1312              166             2675               47.4             93.8&#13;
65.6            2971             562             1515             51.0            2409             1229             1524            1516                8             2417               50.8             99.7&#13;
SERIES II&#13;
66-7            *489             844             1668             47.8            2645             1263             1871             1951             - 80            2565               49.3             103.1&#13;
67-8            3001             805             1483             49.4            2192             1083             1967             2187             -220            1972               54.9             111.1&#13;
68-9            3051            928              1510             49.5            2123             1051             2128             2400             -272            1851               56.8             114.7&#13;
69-70           3974            1069             1735             43.7            2905             1269             2363             2622             -259            2646               48.0             109.8&#13;
70-71           4686            1221             2151             45.9            3465             1590             2625             2915             -290            3175               50.1             109.1&#13;
2/                                                                                                                                  4/&#13;
SERIES III     A       B         A       B                        A     B        A       B        A        B        A       B        A       B          A      B       A       B         A      B         A       B            -&#13;
71-2       5461     5986      1439   1239        2477         45.4   41.3     4023    4744      1826    1961     3045    2728     3369    3018      -324   -290     3690    4457      49.5   44.0      108.8   106.5&#13;
72-3       5832     6320      1571   1401        2697         46.2   42.6     4261    4919      1969    2095     3297    2865     3703    3218      -406   -353     3855    4566      51.1   45.9      110.5   107.7&#13;
73-4       7299     7790      1805   1608        3382         46.3   43.4     5495    6182      2554    2683     3487    3077     4302    3796      -815   -719     4680    5463      54.6   49.1      117.4   113.2&#13;
74-5      14213    10732      2063   1844        4991         48.9   46.5     8155    8888      3985   4133      3893    3537     5671    5152     -1778  -1615     6372    7273      62.5   56.8      127.9   122.2&#13;
75-6       8001     9585      2609   2125        4723         59.0   48.9     5392    7460     3181     3648     4046    3426     6509    5512     -2463  -2086     2929    5374     108.6   67.9      184.1   138.8&#13;
Source  R181, Samples of medium and Iarge non-financi.l, son-governent., public limited companies.    RB1 Honthly Bulletin, several issues. SErie. 1, II and III are not strictly comparable since they involve&#13;
different number of firms .    Nonetheless, meaningful comparisons are possible in the case of certain ratios.   Similarly, some adjustments hove been made in relation to the changing site of the&#13;
samples.  For instance,   consistent series on fixed capital stock and economic depreciation have been estimated by using adequate expansion factors. (Table I&#13;
1/   Only direct tanes are included in the folloving data.   For trends in excise taxes refer to Table 6.&#13;
2/   Column A refers to the total sample of 1650 companies.   Column 8 refers only to profit-making companies.&#13;
3/   Taxes paid on profits exclusive of "other income". "Other income" refers primarily to non-operating profits and is excluded in col.5 in order to calculate later the returns on non-financial assets.&#13;
3a/  Economic depreciation is assumed to be 67. of the outstandieg capital stock at the beginning of year t, valued at prices of that year. (Derived in Table 2). The Implicatio,. of aG-i-n6&#13;
different depreciation rares are discussed below.&#13;
4/   Economic depreciation in profit-making companies hba  been calculated un the assumption that it bears the same proportion to the total as the percentage of accounting depreciation in profit-making&#13;
firms relative to the accounting depreciation in all firms&#13;
S/   Actdal tioable income   1us accounting depreciation minus economic depreciation. i.e. "profits before tax minus other income" (column 5) adjusted by the excess of accounting over economic&#13;
deprecintion (column 9).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
The resultant measure is labeled Corrected Taxable Income (CTI) and reflects&#13;
the level of income that would be consistent with adjustments for inflation&#13;
that take into account the replacement value of assets in deriving the eco-&#13;
nomic depreciation of fixed assets. I.e. CTI = ATI + AD - ED. If T reflects&#13;
the income taxes paid on profits, then the effective tax rate (t*) with&#13;
respect to corrected taxable income can be shown to be:&#13;
t* =  T   =    T    ATI  = tB,&#13;
CTI     ATI    CTI&#13;
where t = nominal tax rate on accounting taxable income (T/ATI) and B =&#13;
(ATI/CTI) is the tax base ratio. 1/ The effective tax rate will be higher&#13;
(lower) than the nominal tax rate only if accounting taxable income (ATI)&#13;
exceeds (fall short of) corrected taxable income (CTI); in other words, only&#13;
if accounting depreciation is lower (higher) than economic depreciation.&#13;
From 1960/61 to 1965/66 accounting depreciation provisions exceeded economic&#13;
depreciation and consequently the effective tax rate was lower than the&#13;
nominal tax rate.   Compared with later years, this meant an implicit fiscal&#13;
subsidy in the form of a lower corporate tax base (lower B). These circum-&#13;
stances have been reversed since 1965/66.&#13;
3.04       From 1965 to 1970 the effective tax rates were generally higher&#13;
than in the previous five years (with the exception of 1961/62). This took&#13;
place even though nominal tax rates were somewhat lower than in the previous&#13;
five years (with the exception of 1960/61). In effect, the increase in the&#13;
tax base, on account of the larger discrepancy between accounting and economic&#13;
depreciation, more than compensated the decline in nominal tax rates.&#13;
1/   I.e. column II in Table 3 can be shown to be the product of column 4&#13;
and column 12.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
3.05      For the period up to 1970/71 no data are available on the taxation&#13;
of profit-making companies. The fact that companies that incur losses pay no&#13;
taxes tends ,to distort the meaning of nominal and effective tax rates since&#13;
the tax base may be unduly reduced because of the lumping of losing companies&#13;
with profit-making firms. For the period 1971/72 to 1975/76 the results for&#13;
the total sample of firms are presented under column A of Table 3, whereas&#13;
column B refers only to profit-making companies. The latter is a more reli-&#13;
able guide to effective tax rates, but the former is included in order to&#13;
enable comparability with estimates for previous years. During this period,&#13;
both nominal and effective taxation rates have increased, but the latter have&#13;
increased faster in view of the growing inadequacy of accounting depreciation&#13;
to reflect the economic depreciation of fixed assets.&#13;
3.06      The relation depicting effective tax rates as the product of nominal&#13;
tax rates and the ratio of accounting to corrected taxable income (tax base&#13;
ratio), can be used to ascertain the sources of the increase in tax rates.&#13;
Obviously if both nominal tax rates and the tax base ratio remain the same,&#13;
effective tax rates will not change. On the other hand, if either of these&#13;
remains constant, any change in effective taxation rates can be imputed to&#13;
changes in the other. If the tax base ratio had remained constant, effective&#13;
tax rates in profit-making firms would have gradually increased from 41.3%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
in 1971/72 to 48.9% in 1975/76; instead they increased to 67.9% in 1975/76. 1/&#13;
Most of the increases in effective tax rates since 1971/72 can be imputed to&#13;
changes in the tax base ratio (B), which increased from 106.5% in 1971/72 to&#13;
113.2% in 1973/74 and accelerated to 122.2% in 1974/75 and 138.8% in 1975/76.&#13;
Inadequate depreciation provisions in the context of fairly high inflation&#13;
rates in some of these years (e.g. 20.0% in 1973/74 and 25.2% in 1974/75) are&#13;
thus primarily responsible for the substantial increases in effective taxation&#13;
during this period; although increases in nominal tax rates have also been a&#13;
contributing factor, albeit a much smaller one. 2/&#13;
1/   The fact that losses in 1975/76 were substantially higher than in&#13;
previous years is responsible for the much larger increase in nominal&#13;
and effective taxation for the total sample of companies in that year&#13;
(Column A). Losses, as a percentage of profits-before-taxes in profit-&#13;
making companies, increased from 8.3% in 1974/75 to 27.7% in 1975/76.&#13;
Since higher losses depress net profit levels, the tax rates in&#13;
Column A apply to a unduly deflated measure of profits. Similarly,&#13;
the higher e'fective and nominal tax rates for 1966/67 and 1967/68&#13;
are partly a reflection of the larger losses that took place in the&#13;
Indian econdmy in that period. Larger losses are indirectly confirmed&#13;
by lower profitability rates in these years, as shown in Table 7.&#13;
2/   Some of the above results are contingent on the assumption that the&#13;
economic depreciation of fixed assets in any given year is approxi-&#13;
mately 6% of the outstanding stock of fixed assets at the beginning&#13;
of the year. As was pointed out earlier, this depreciation rate may&#13;
be lower than the "true" rate. Consequently, the implications of&#13;
assuming a higher rate (e.g. 8%) have been explored. If anything,&#13;
the main results seem to be strengthened with a higher depreciation&#13;
rate. Some of the main differences are listed below. Firstly, cor-&#13;
rected taxable income would be lower the higher the assumed rate of&#13;
economic depreciation. Secondly, effective tax rates on corporate&#13;
income (adjusted for economic depreciation) would be higher the&#13;
higher the assumed rate of economic depreciation. In effect, the&#13;
discrepancy between accounting and economic depreciation would be&#13;
larger the higher the assumed economic depreciation rate. Thirdly,&#13;
and related to the previous point, the tax ratio (i.e. the ratio of&#13;
accounting to corrected taxable income) would be higher the higher&#13;
the depreciation rate. Finally, the upward trend in the effective&#13;
corporate tax rate during the 1970s would be steeper the higher the&#13;
assumed economic depreciation rate; basically as a result of the&#13;
enlargement of the corporate tax base.in view of the increasing&#13;
inadequacy of accounting depreciation provisions in an inflationary&#13;
context.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 1 7 -&#13;
3.07      The nominal tax rate depends inter alia on the value of deductions&#13;
that firms are allowed to avail themselves in computing their (accounting)&#13;
taxable incdme. In spite of fiscal incentives for investment, nominal tax&#13;
rate-s of profit-making companies have risen since 1971/72 partly due to&#13;
surcharges and other rate increases over this period.&#13;
3.08 -     In the case of fiscal incentives for investment, the value of these&#13;
deductions will depend not only on the rate of exemption of investment in&#13;
fixed assets, but also on the volume of investment. Ceteris paribus, low&#13;
investment years will entail higher tax liability than years of high invest-&#13;
ment activity. In effect an important part of the increase in corporate&#13;
taxation in recent years is itself the result of lower investment activity. 1/&#13;
For instance, corporate tax collections increased by 31.6% in 1977/78, even&#13;
though wholesale price index rose only 5.1%. Probably less than half of the&#13;
real increase in corporate taxes in 1977/78 can be attributed to higher&#13;
overall corporate income (the tax base); the bulk of the increase reflects&#13;
higher effective tax rates due to lower investment activity in this period and&#13;
inadequate depreciation accounting.&#13;
111.2   Incidence of Corporate Taxation&#13;
3.09      The subject of corporate taxation cannot be closed without a dis-&#13;
cussion on tax incidence. If private firms were able to increase the prices&#13;
of their outputs, or reduce the prices they pay for their inputs to compensate&#13;
1/   Corporate tax collections in recent years have increased sharply from&#13;
Rs 8,617 million in 1975/76, to Rs 9,692 million in 1976/77 and&#13;
Rs 12,750 million in 1977/78. Budget estimates project an additional&#13;
increase to Rs 14,421 million in 1978/79.    (RBI, Survey of Currency and&#13;
Finance 1977/78, Vol. II, p. 98). These increases have occurred despite&#13;
the fact that the rate of investment allowances for tax deductions has&#13;
been increased.since 1976/77.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
fully for higher taxation imposed by the government, the incidence of taxation&#13;
on these firms would be nil, they would in effect shift the tax burden to their&#13;
customers or to their input suppliers. The available evidence does not provide&#13;
support to the contention that the burden of the corporate tax is shifted&#13;
significantly to other economic spheres.&#13;
3.10      To analyse the incidence of the corporate tax, two partial equili-&#13;
brium tests are performed. The first consists in testing whether gross profit&#13;
margins (or before-tax rates of return) increase as a result of tax-rate&#13;
increases. The second one analyzes whether net profit margins (or after-tax&#13;
rates of return) are maintained in spite of tax-rate increases. In either&#13;
test, a proper comparison for analyzing tax incidence should involve not the&#13;
actual profit margins (or rates of return) in two different periods, by the&#13;
levels which they would have attained under comparable circumstances with and&#13;
without the tax increase. It is not always possible to define a satisfactory&#13;
set of comparable circumstances and the number of different scenarios in which&#13;
the tax influence is to be measured can become vary large. In order to&#13;
simplify the analysis, it is assumed that gross and net rates of return as&#13;
well as profit margins are determined primarily by demand conditions and that&#13;
consequently the net effect of tax rates on these variables can be assessed&#13;
only after discounting the impact of those demand conditions. Multiple&#13;
regression methods in which the tax rate and sales per unit of fixed assets&#13;
are the independent variables are used in the following discussion as main&#13;
vehicles for the analysis of tax incidence.&#13;
3.11      The main hypotheses of the analyses are basically two:     Firstly,&#13;
if after discounting the influence of demand on before-taxes rates of return,&#13;
or on gross profit margins, it were to be found that higher tax rates have a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
significant and positive influence on those gross profit rates, there would&#13;
be a prima facie case to support the view that the corporate tax is at least&#13;
partly shifted. In other words, the positive and independent influence&#13;
wouid mean that higher tax rates lead to higher before-tax rates which at&#13;
least ameliorate (i.e. "shift") the negative impact of higher taxation on&#13;
net profits.&#13;
3.12      Secondly, as it relates to after-tax rates of return or net profit&#13;
margins, if after discounting the influence of demand on there rates, it were&#13;
to be found that net profit rates remain constant in spite of changes in tax&#13;
rates (i.e. no independent influence of taxation on net profit rates), this&#13;
would be additional evidence to suggest that in effect the corporate income&#13;
tax is shifted and places no burden on profitability.&#13;
3.13      The regression results presented in Table 5 provide no basis for&#13;
*supporting either of these two hypotheses. Firstly, the coefficients of the&#13;
tax variable in the first two regressions (respectively for before-taxes rate&#13;
of return and gross profit margin) are statistically not significant. 1/&#13;
Secondly, the third and fourth regressions (for after-taxes rate of return&#13;
and net profit margin respectively) show that the tax rates do have a statis-&#13;
tically significant influence on after-tax profit rates. Higher tax rates&#13;
have an independent influence in depressing these rates. In other words,&#13;
contrary to the initial hypothesis, net profit rates are not maintained&#13;
irrespectively of the prevailing tax rates.&#13;
3.14       In all regressions, the demand variable has the expected influence&#13;
on profitability: higher sales per unit of fixed assets, increase both&#13;
1/   In addition, and contrary to expectatipn, the sign of the coefficients&#13;
is negative, although the numerical value of the coefficients is very&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 4&#13;
INDIA: Incidence of Corporate Taxation&#13;
Before-tax frpte        After-tax                                        Effective        Gross profit   Net profit&#13;
of return -             rate of return i/           Sales/RFK 2/         tax rate -/     margin   4      nar-in&#13;
(1)                       (2)                        (3)                  (4)            (5)              (6)&#13;
SERIES I&#13;
1961-2                  11.96                    8.14                        1.81                 40.3           10.27            6.99&#13;
62-3                  11.31                    6.92                        1.72                49.5            10.08            6.17&#13;
63-4                  11.50                    7.18                        1.68                48.2            10.29            6.43&#13;
64-5                  10.90                    7.00                        1.61                47.4            10.05            6.45&#13;
65-6                   9.26                    S.97                        1.54                50.8             8.91            5.75&#13;
SERIES II&#13;
1966-7                   8.53                    5.87                        1.40                49.3             8.87            6.10&#13;
67-8                   7.04                    4.97                        1.35                54.9             7.48            5.28&#13;
68-9                   6.49                    4.65                        1.34                56.8             6.93            4.97&#13;
69-70                  7.30                    5.27                        1.36                48.0             7.67           5.54&#13;
70-1                   7.68                    5.37                        1.38                50.1             7.86           5.50&#13;
SERIES III&#13;
1971-2                   7.98                    5.71                        1.40                49.5             8.17            5.84&#13;
72-3                   7.57                    5.35                        1.41                51.1             7.70           5.44&#13;
73-4                   7.47                    4.99                        1.32                54.6             8.12           5.43&#13;
74-5                   7.73                    4.73                        1.25                62.5             8.70           5.33&#13;
75-6                   5.34                    3.18                        1.21                74.0 3/          5.98           3.57&#13;
Source:  Table 1, 2, 3 and 7.   Original data from RBI samples of medium and large non-financial, public limited companies.&#13;
1/ These rates are derived from Table 7.      2/ Sales per unit of fixed assets.   Current value data are used in calculating this ratio.&#13;
3/ To enable comparability with previous years, from 1971/72 onwards the tax rates in column A (for all companies) from Table 3&#13;
are transcribed here, except for 1975/76 in. which due to the extent of losses the tax rate was clearly overestimated. For this&#13;
year the tax rate reflects the following adjustment: starting from the effective tax rate on profit-making companies (67.9%),&#13;
it was assumed that losses as a percentage of profits in profit-making companies were 8.3% (as in 1974/75) and not 27.7%&#13;
(as in 1975/76), leading to an overall (inflated) tax rate on profits (net of losses) of 74.0% (Table 3).&#13;
4/ Gross and net profit margins are respectively the percentages of gross return before taxes and gross return after taxes to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
GRAPH 1&#13;
INDIA - Corporate Taxation and Rates of Return           1961/62-1975/76&#13;
1-4 4&#13;
H H F1&#13;
-. .-.4  .-4&#13;
0    Cd   0d              Before-tax &#13;
" ~~~rate of &#13;
return         \-S &#13;
80   11&#13;
Tax rate&#13;
Sales per               A&#13;
fixed ssets&#13;
70  10     1.8&#13;
60    9    1.7&#13;
After-tax \&#13;
rate  f return&#13;
50    8    1.6&#13;
Tax ra~ ~ ~      ~      ~~~~~.- &#13;
40    7    1.5                  Ta  r&#13;
30    6    1.4&#13;
I Before-tax rate of&#13;
20    5    1.3                                                                                                      return&#13;
10    4    1.2        Source: Table 4                                                                               Sales per fixed assets&#13;
Scale I     : Tax rate&#13;
Scale II : Rates of return&#13;
\ After-tax rate of return&#13;
0    3    1.1        Scale III:     Sales Rer ugit of fixed aqets-                                                      Year&#13;
_4   cn   _     in   O _au _% _      _          _         _     _&#13;
'0 0    %O %O %o  %     %0  %0    %O    r    r-   r-   r-     ,   r~r&#13;
H    e4         -    IA   '0    -    Co   0%   0     H    N    C     -r   IA&#13;
'0  '0    '0    %0   %0 'o %'       '0    '0 _t     t1. _      r. -   .   r-&#13;
a,  a. a' 0 0%    0%      0%    0%   0%   0%   0%    0%   0%   0%    0%&#13;
H  H   H    H~   H4   Hq    H4   H4    H4   q    H4   H4   H     H &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 5&#13;
INDIA: Regression Results for Assessing the Incidence of Corporate&#13;
Taxation -&#13;
Independent variables:                                        Dependent variables.&#13;
Before-taxes          Gross              After-taxes       Net profit&#13;
rate-of-return        Profit margin      rate-of-return    margin&#13;
(1)                    (2)              (3)               (4)&#13;
Constant                                                          2.138                2.539             4.616             4.989&#13;
Sales per unit of Fixed Assets                                    1.681                0.937              0.994            0.252&#13;
(6.27)                (3.35)            (5.32)           (1.25)&#13;
Effective Tax Rate                                               -0.161               -0.191             -0.826           -0.850&#13;
(-0.52)              (-0.59)            (-3.82)          (-3.65)&#13;
R2                                                                0.89                 0.73              0.94              0.85&#13;
N  of Observations                                               15                   15                 15               15&#13;
Source: Table 4 presents the data and the definition of variables.&#13;
1/   The method of estimation used in these regressions is ordinary least squares applied to the logarithm of the respective&#13;
variables, i.e. log y = a + b, log xl + b2 log x2 + e where the estimated parameters bi represent the (partial)&#13;
elasticities of y with respect to xi.   The numbers in parenthesis under the coefficients are t statistics.   An asterisk&#13;
indicate that the respective coefficient is statistically significant.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
before-tax and after-tax profit measures. Except for the last regression,&#13;
the coefficients are statistically very significant in explaining variations&#13;
in profit measures, confirming the strong role of demand in the performance&#13;
of the private corporate sector.&#13;
III.3     Indirect Taxation&#13;
3.15      Indirect taxes are an important source of Government Revenue&#13;
and represent a much higher share of total tax collections than corporate&#13;
taxes. In a sample of companies assisted by ICICI 1/, indirect taxes paid&#13;
by these firms were more than four times as large as their corporate taxes&#13;
(Table 6).&#13;
3.16      Corporate tax rates and indirect tax rates share the feature of&#13;
having increased significantly in recent years. Indirect taxes as percentage&#13;
of sales have progressively increased from 12.2% in 1971/72 to 14.0% in&#13;
1974/75 and 14.9% in 1976/77. As percentage of value added, indirect taxes&#13;
rose from 41.1% in 1971/72 to 45.5% in 1974/75 and reached 55.8% in 1976/77&#13;
(Table 6).&#13;
3.17      It is not possible to test adequately the extent to which indirect&#13;
taxes are shifted to consumers through higher prices or to input suppliers&#13;
through lower prices. However, given the relatively large burden of indirect&#13;
taxes on sales and value added, it can be presumed that only a fraction of&#13;
these taxes is passed on, especially in the context of generally weak demand&#13;
conditions facing companies in recent years. In fact, it can be conjectured&#13;
that part of the decline in profitability observed in recent years in RBI&#13;
1/   The Industrial Credit and Investment Corporation of India Limited (ICICI).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 6&#13;
INDIA - Indirect Taxation in Samples of Firms in the Private Corporate Sector. 1971 72 - 1976-77&#13;
(Current prices, Rs million)&#13;
1975/76 Sample of 421 Firms                                               1976/77 Sample of 417 Firms&#13;
1971/72       1972/73      1973/74       1974/75      1975/76             1975/76      1976/77&#13;
Sales net of excise taxes               39060        43780         47250        60200         68420              68540         75890&#13;
Value added                             11600        12820         14560        18450         19060               19420        20280&#13;
Excise taxes                             4770         5540          6240         8400         10230              10220         11310&#13;
1/&#13;
Profits before income tax                2970         3020          3630         5310          4250               4630          4590&#13;
Provision for income taxes               1310         1350          1650         2520          2340               2410          2550&#13;
Profits after taxes                      1660         1670          1980         2790          1910               2220          2040&#13;
Depreciation                             1780         1950          2070         2550          2410               2420          2580&#13;
Income tax provision as % of&#13;
profits before income tax               442          448           455          474          551                 521           555&#13;
Excise taxes as a % of sales&#13;
(net of excise)                        122           126          1321          140          149                 149          149&#13;
Excise taxes as a % of value added        411          432           429          455           537                526           558&#13;
Depreciation as a % of value added        154          152           142          122           126                125           127&#13;
Depreciation as a % of sales               46           45            44           97            35                 35            34&#13;
Source:   ICICI, Financial Performance of Companies, ICICI Portfolio 1975/76,     Table I-A pp. 24-25, Bombay, August 1977.&#13;
ICICI, Financial Performance of Companies, ICICI Portfolio 1976/77, Table II-A , pp. 38-39, Bombay, August 1978.&#13;
All firms in these samples are "public limited companies" and are mostly "large", i.e. their paid-up capital is&#13;
at least Rs. 1 crore).&#13;
1/ Net of excise taxes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
samples of firms was a result of their inability to raise prices to the extent&#13;
required to compensate fully for higher indirect taxes. 1/&#13;
3.18      ICICI data confirm some of the trends that have been highlighted&#13;
earlier in RBI samples. Nominal tax rates on corporate income have increased&#13;
in the 1970s, from 44.2% in 1971/72 to 47.5% in 1974/75, 52.1% in 1975/76 and&#13;
55.5% in 1976/77. 2/ At the same time, accounting depreciation provisions&#13;
apparently have failed to keep up with inflation: for instance, as a percent-&#13;
age of value added, they declined from 15.4% in 1971/72 to 14.2% in 1973/74&#13;
and further to 12.7% in 1976/77. This seems to confirm trends in RBI samples&#13;
and to indicate that effective corporate tax rates have increased at an even&#13;
faster rate than nominal tax rates, due to the overestimation of taxable&#13;
profits in the absence of inflation clauses for depreciation charges.&#13;
1/   RBI samples of medium and large firms in the private corporate sector&#13;
are much larger than ICICI samples, and comprise most of the firms&#13;
included in the latter. It is presumed that the higher indirect tax&#13;
rates observed in recent years in ICICI's sample of firms, also reflect&#13;
the trends in RBI samples.&#13;
2/   In RBI samples, nominal tax rates on profits increased from 45.5% in&#13;
1971/72 to 48.9% in 1974/75 and 59.0% in 1975/76. It can be verified&#13;
that money-losing enterprises are less significant in ICICI samples&#13;
than in RBI samples (Table II-A.2, p. 42-43 in ICICI, op. cit. Port-&#13;
folio 1976/77), a factor that accounts for the higher tax percentage&#13;
for 1975/76 in the latter. (Consult p45)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
IV. PRIVATE CORPORATE INVESTMENT AND ITS DETERMINANTS&#13;
4.01       The purpose of this section is to analyse the investment behavior&#13;
of a representative group of medium and large firms in the private corporate&#13;
sector over the period from 1961/62 to 1975/76 and relate their investment&#13;
activity to several factors, such as sales, profitability, taxation, level&#13;
of internally-generated financial resources, and others. As was pointed&#13;
out earlier, the net rate of growth of the fixed capital stock has deceler-&#13;
ated since 1965/66. Whereas the fixed capital stock increased at an average&#13;
rate of 9.2% D.a. from 1961/62 to 1965/66, the corresponding rates for the&#13;
periods 1966/67 to 1970/71 and 1971/72 to 1975/76 were respectively 4.8% p.a.&#13;
and 4.0% p.a. There follows a brief discussion of some of the contributing&#13;
factors, starting with profitability.&#13;
IV.1      Definition and Trends of Some Investment-Related Variables&#13;
4.02       In order to analyze profitability, it is necessary to adjust the&#13;
accounting data for known biases. A starting premise of the analysis is t'hat&#13;
the rate of return from real capital cannot be assessed by relating current&#13;
profits to such accounting concepts as "net worth" or "gross (or net) fixed&#13;
assets." First of all, these concepts do not provide an adequate measure of&#13;
the replacement value of fixed assets, since they represent successive addi-&#13;
tions of rupees which do not have equivalent or comparable purchasing power&#13;
over capital goods. Secondly, as was demonstrated earlier, in recent years&#13;
the divergence between accounting measures and the replacement value of fixed&#13;
assets has increased. Finally, accounting measures of profits may fail to&#13;
reflect actual earnings since the depreciation allowed for tax purposes may&#13;
not reflect the economic depreciation of fixed assets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
4.07      Table 7 presents estimates of the yearly rates of return from non-&#13;
financial assets in the private corporate sector. For calculating these rates&#13;
of return, tapital income is defined as the sum of profits (exclusive of&#13;
depreciation and non-operating income), managerial remuneration 1/&#13;
and interest payments, plus an adjustment that reflects the excess of economic&#13;
over accounting depreciation. 2/, 3/ Thus, capital income is defined net of&#13;
economic depreciation of fixed assets, but inclusive of interest payments&#13;
and managerial remuneration. Capital income measures-before and after taxes-&#13;
are in current prices. In order to calculate real rates of return, it is&#13;
necessary to have a measure of the stock of real capital 4/ (fixed assets&#13;
1/   Managerial remuneration in the private corporate sector in India is only&#13;
a small fraction of capital income. For instance, in 1975/76, it repre-&#13;
sented only 1.9% of capital income before-taxes.&#13;
2/   The distortions introduced by inflation into accounting valuations and&#13;
depreciation based on historical costs have been removed by calculating&#13;
the replacement value of the capital stock and the corresponding economic&#13;
depreciation. Consult G. Jenkins, op. cit. and A. Harberger, op. cit.&#13;
on these and other issues related to the concept and measurement of&#13;
capital income.&#13;
3/   A further adjustment may be necessary if capital gains on fixed assets&#13;
are considered a part of the return from capital. Capital gains take&#13;
place if the appreciation in the value of fixed assets is higher than&#13;
the overall inflation rate. There has been a slight relative apprecia-&#13;
tion of fixed assets in India. The implicit deflator for gross capital&#13;
formation was respectively 10.9; 6.9 and 7.5% higher than the correspond-&#13;
ing GDP deflator in 1975/76, 1976/77 and 1977/78 (base 1970/71 = 100).&#13;
However, unless this appreciation is fully anticipated, it cannot have&#13;
any influence on the expected return from investment. For these reasons,&#13;
no adjustment for capital gains has been included in the calculations.&#13;
4/   I.e., excluding financial assets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
plus inventories) in comparable prices. For this purpose, the replacement&#13;
value of fixed assets and the current value of inventories at the beginning&#13;
of year t, valued at prices of that year, are shown in Table 7. 1/ The rate&#13;
of return is defined as the percentage of capital income (in current prices)&#13;
during year t, relative to the replacement value (at prices of year t) of&#13;
the real stock of capital available at the beginning of year t. 2/ Columns&#13;
13 and 14 in Table 7 present respectively the before-taxes rates of return&#13;
and the after-taxes rates of return, over the period from 1961/62 to 1975/76.&#13;
There has been a decline in rates of return, most remarkable with respect&#13;
to the rates in 1961/62 to 1965/66. The average rates 3/ of return before&#13;
and after taxes were respectively 11% and 7% during the period from 1961/62&#13;
to 1965/66, declined to 7.4% and 5.2% respectively from 1966/67 to 1970/71,&#13;
and fell slightly in the next five years (1971/72 to 1975/76) to 7.2% and&#13;
4.8% respectively.&#13;
1/   The book value of inventories at the end of year t is assumed to reflect&#13;
the current value of inventories at prices of that year. It would be&#13;
difficult to adjust these values for inflation since accounting princi-&#13;
ples of valuation are not uniform: some firms use the first-in-first-&#13;
out (FIFO) principle, while others use the first-in-last-out (FILO) prin-&#13;
ciple. (Consult R. N. Lal, op. cit., p. 13.) In defense of the above&#13;
assumption, it can be claimed that the undervaluation of inventories in&#13;
accounting figures is probably not serious: The proportion of the book&#13;
value of inventories to the replacement value of the fixed capital stock&#13;
is clustered around 50%, with only a slight downward trend over the&#13;
fifteen-year period. The book value of inventories at the end of year&#13;
t-1 has been revalued at prices of year t in order to obtain a measure&#13;
of stocks at the beginning of year t at prices of that year. The whole-&#13;
sale price index of manufactures has been used to revalue inventories.&#13;
Manufactures accounted for 86.5% of sales in the sample of 1,650 firms&#13;
in 1975/76.&#13;
2/   The rate of return so defined is thus unrelated to the internal rate&#13;
of return calculated on the basis of streams of cash flows.&#13;
3/   Denotes simple arithmetic averages of-the corresponding annual data&#13;
within five-year periods.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
4.04       The decline in rates of return is partly attributable to demand&#13;
patterns. 1/ Whereas the real volume of sales (in constant prices of 1960/61)&#13;
increased at an average rate 2/ of 6.1% p.a. between 1960/61 and 1965/66, the&#13;
corresponding rate was 4.7% p.a. from 1965/66 to 1970/71 and only 2.8% p.a.&#13;
from 1970/71 to 1975/76 (Table 8).&#13;
4.05       The decline in profitability has also implied a lower savings capa-&#13;
city for the private corporate sector. Cash flow - defined as the sum of&#13;
accounting after-tax profits and depreciation provision- as a percentage of&#13;
the replacement value of real capital has declined over time: from an average&#13;
rate of 9.2% for the period from 1961/62 to 1965/66, to 7.1% in the following&#13;
five years and 6.8% in the period from 1971/72 to 1975/76. This means that&#13;
the private corporate sector's ability to finance a given percentage growth&#13;
rate of its real capital stock has declined sharply compared to the period&#13;
from 1961/62 to 1965/66, a factor which may very well have contributed to the&#13;
corresponding deceleration in the growth rate observed since 1965/66 (Table 8).&#13;
Valuation Ratio&#13;
4.06       The real (after-tax) rate of return on invested capital is only&#13;
one of two critical elements on the investment decision. The other one is&#13;
the real cost of capital to the firm. The differential between these variables&#13;
is one factor determining whether an investment is worth undertaking or not.&#13;
The valuation ratio attempts to measure such a differential, and is defined&#13;
as the ratio of the (imputed) market value of the firms' real capital assets&#13;
1/   As was, shown in Table 5 in the context of the analysis of tax incidence.&#13;
2/   Annual geometric growth rate between initial-year value and final-year&#13;
value.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 7&#13;
INDIA - Rates of Return and Profitability Trends in Smples of Companies&#13;
in the Private Corporate Sector. 1961/62 - 1975/76&#13;
(Current prices, Re million)&#13;
1       2         3        4         5           6         7           8        9         10          11           12        13         14       15         16       17&#13;
_~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
a                                                                  a.ak        a     ~    ~~~~~~                       ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ a  U &#13;
. a                                                           a  c                0                                 n                     a&#13;
0ER115 1           - M L L - 1         0          XL              |j|                           Sl                      j        lXl                        t&#13;
4)   4          NI      'fli                                                                      -    0 a     -&#13;
1960-1  1862  371  129I                                                        . 26  1                                 1 &#13;
634   a4   5          0      31715                                0     oa 1245  1926  145  336  2                                                  a&#13;
64-50209 .73  134   374     127        210         166       540       273       2181        1065        3246        10.0 S.                       62,       645&#13;
a  ap  50                                      ...5.                '.- ~~~Ca       .0       ua.          0&#13;
SERIES I&#13;
1960-1       1862      371      129      2362        719       1643                                                                                             16530      75.6&#13;
61-2       1978      437      124      2539        864      1675        166      2705       1841       14574       8043        22617      11.96      8.14     18600     74.5       6.99&#13;
62-3       2159      494      131      2784       1129      1655        124       2908      1779       16749       8958        25707      11.31      6.92     19760     71.1       6.17&#13;
63-4       2440      591      140      3171       1245      1926        145      3316       2071      19208        9637       28845       11.50      7.18     20350     64.8       6.43&#13;
64-5       2509      731      134      3374       1267      2107        166      3540       2273      21871       10615       32486       10.90      7.00     21610     62.0       6.45&#13;
65-1       2409      916      130      3455       1229      2226          8      3463       2234       25275      12133       37408        9.26      5.97     22290     56.3       5.75&#13;
SERIES II&#13;
1965-6      2605      1017      183      3805      1302       2503                                                                                              26510     61.5&#13;
66-7      2645     1288      194      4127       1264      2863        -80      4047       2783      32525       14910       47435        8.53      5.87     3173       63.0      6.10&#13;
67-8      2192     1541      175      3908       1083      2825       -220      3688       2605      36445       15930        52375       7.04      4.97     33530      60.4      5.28&#13;
68-9      2123     1678      181      3982       1051      2931       -272      3710       2659      39995       17204       57199        6.49     4.65      37180      62.9      4.97&#13;
69-70     2905     1733      187      4825       1269      3556       -259      4566       3297      43709       18812       62521        7.30      5.27     40760      63.6      5.54&#13;
70-71     3465     1979      130      5574       1590      3984       -290      5284       3694      48586       20239        68825       7.68      5.37     44360      62.3      5.50&#13;
SERIES III&#13;
1970-71      3906     2216      149      6271       1644      4627                                                                                              492WD      64.9&#13;
71-2      4023      2578      136      6737       1826      4911       -324      6413       4587      56153       24179        80332       7.98      5.71     5095)      60.9      5.84&#13;
72-3      Z4261     2721      133      7115       1969      54         -406      6709       4740      61720       26898       88618        7.57     5.35      54430      59.5      5.44&#13;
73-4-      5495     2866      147      8508       2554      5954       -815      7693       5139      71699       31339       103038       7.47      4.99     63390      59.9      5.43&#13;
74-5       8150     3747      157     12054       3985      8069      -1778     10276       6291       94521      38435       132956       7.73      4.73     71710      52.2      5.33&#13;
75-6       5392     4796      152     10340       3181      7159      -2463      7877       4696     108489       38995       147484       5.34      3.18     72790      47.5      3.57&#13;
Source:  RBI Samples of mediurm and large non-financial, non-government, public limited companies.       RBI tonthly Bulletin, several issues.&#13;
1l "Other income" reflects non-operating income end is excluded from profits in order to assess the rate of return on productive (non-financinl)essets.&#13;
2/  Managerial remuneration is largely a participation in the profits of the company and is thereby included as part of the return to capital.          In 1975/76 it&#13;
accounted for only 1.9, of capital income before taxes.&#13;
3/ Gross profit is defined inclusive of interest payments and managerial remuneration but exclusive of accounting depreciation.&#13;
4/ Adjusted taxes, i.e. taxea on "other income" are excluded.       only corporate taxes are included in the present table; RBI samples do not provide date on&#13;
indirect taxes paid by firms.&#13;
s! Capital income is equal to gross profits plus accounting minus economic depreciation. This adjustment intends to deduct from gross profits (inclusive of&#13;
depreciation provision) the "true" economic depreciation of fixed assets.       I.e. capital income is net of economic depreciation but gross of interest&#13;
payments anid managerial remuneration.&#13;
6; Replacement value of fixed assets at the beginning of year       , valued at prices of thet year.    Similarly, the book value of inventories at the end of&#13;
year t-I has been revalued according to the increase in the price index of manufactures in year t, so as to reflect their value at prices of year t.&#13;
7/ ;.orprises fixed capital stock plus inventories at the beginning of year t, valued at prices of yBar t.&#13;
S/ Rate-of-return estimates are based on capital income (see footnote 5) as a percentage of the replacement value of non-financial assets at the beginning of the year.&#13;
TThe value imputed to reel assets by the market Is calculated in Table Al.&#13;
Ihe valuation ratio is the percentage of the market value of the firms' real assets, relative to their replacement value; both measures are end-of-year values&#13;
(Table Al).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 8&#13;
INDIA - Investment Patterns and Some Determinant Factors in Samples of Companies&#13;
in the Private Corporate Sector. 1961-62/1975-76&#13;
Gross Investment     Net Investment      Sales per Unit of     Real Growth in         After-Tax Rate         Valuation    Cash Flow&#13;
Rate 1/              Rate           Fixed Assets 2/        Volume of Sales  /     of Return  /            Ratio 5/     Ratio 6'&#13;
SERIES I                                                                         (7)                   M)                    (Z)         (1)&#13;
1961-2             17.3               11.3                 1.81                   7.92                  8.14               74.5          10.40&#13;
62-3             15.6                9.6                 1.72                   6.69                  6.92               71.1           9.14&#13;
63-4             16.4               10.4                 1.68                   9.37                  7.18               64.8           9.42&#13;
64-5             14.1                8.1                 1.61                   5.15                  7.00               62.0           9.11&#13;
65-6             12.5                6.5                 1.54                   1.77                  5.97               56.3           7.97&#13;
SERIES II&#13;
1966-7             13.2                7.2                 1.40                   3.60                  5.87               63.0           7.78&#13;
67-8             11.7                5.7                 1.35                   5.06                 4.97                60.4           6.65&#13;
68-9             10.4                4.4                 1.34                   7.23                  4.65               62.9           6.41&#13;
69-70             9.8                3.8                 1.36                   2.80                  5.27               63.6           7.36&#13;
70-1              8.9                2.9                 1.38                   4.62                  5.37               62.3           7.50&#13;
SERIES III&#13;
1971-2              9.6                3.6                 1.40                   3.88                  5.71               60.9           7.51&#13;
72-3             10.5                4.5                 1.41                   4.95                  5.35               59.5           7.26&#13;
73-4             10.3                4.3                 1.32                  -6.57                  4.99               59.9           7.19&#13;
74-5             10.0               4.0                  1.25                   0.73                  4.73               52.2           6.85&#13;
75-6              9.4                3.4                 1.21                  12.18                  3.18               47.5           4.97&#13;
1/ Gross investment rate is the annual gross growth rate of the fixed capital stock in real terms (gross of depreciation), whereas net investment&#13;
rate is the actual annual growth rate of the fixed capital stock (i.e. net of economic depreciation).   Annual economic depreciation is assumed&#13;
to be 6% of the outstanding fixed capital stock at the end of the previous year.   Consequently gross and net rates differ by 6 percentage points.&#13;
2/                                   Both sales and fixed assets are valued in current prices for calculating this ratio.&#13;
3/  Value of sales has been deflated by the wholesale price index of manufactures to obtain volume of sales in 1960-61 prices.    Annual percentage&#13;
growth is calculated on that basis.&#13;
4/ Refers to operating profitq inclusive of interest payments and managerial remuneration but net of economic depreciation, as percentage of the&#13;
sum of the replacement value of fixed assets and the current value of inventories.&#13;
5/ Valuation ratio is the percentage of the market value of firms' real assets to the replacement cost of those assets.&#13;
6/ Cash flow ratio is the percentage of accounting profits after tax (i.e. exclusive of interest payments and managerial remuneration) plus&#13;
accounting depreciation provision in relation to the replacement value of fixed assets and inventories. It measures the level of internal&#13;
financial resources in relation to the value of existing productive assets.&#13;
Source: RBI samples of medium and large non-financial, non-government, public limited companies. RBI Bulletin, several issues. Consult Tables&#13;
1, 2, 3, 4, 7,   and Al for the derivation of the data in this table.   Series I, II and III are not strictly comparable since they involve&#13;
different number of firms. However, the different samples have been adjusted for their changing size, setting them on a comparable basis.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(%)           GRAPH 2        INDIA - Investment Patterns and Related Factors&#13;
11.5&#13;
10.5    \         Net investment rate&#13;
9.5    \   &#13;
8.5\\'&#13;
7.5..&#13;
6 5  ' &lt; z  /t   &lt;  /                      \ Cashflow&#13;
6.5                     V&#13;
After-tax     \&#13;
rate of return&#13;
5.5&#13;
4.5                                                         A&#13;
After-tax&#13;
3.5  s   /  _ _  rate of return&#13;
3.5/&#13;
Net investment rate&#13;
2.5 L                                                      --                     Year&#13;
*-4  cot  st   } - *Z          co 0  C O  0%  0     14  (4         t U  I&#13;
'0   '0   '0   '0   *0   '0    'D   '0   *0   #-    1    rI-.-  l  r-   t-&#13;
cn   0%   0'    0%   0%   0%     0%    0% % o%      0s  0%    0 o   0%  ON&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
0&#13;
0&#13;
0&#13;
x&#13;
k4~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~4&#13;
o                  o4.4 -c&#13;
o H&#13;
co                                                  U 1f L L6T&#13;
0           t                                  cL/ZZ61~ ~ &#13;
a  1                   ''              I~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~L/TL6T&#13;
OH       0WO&#13;
8U                 4 'OL/696T&#13;
&gt;               \                                   69/896T&#13;
i   /                  }               8~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~99L96T&#13;
U               /               /                   19/9961&#13;
/  ?                          89,s~~~~~~~~W961&#13;
- - '/  ~  C9/Z961&#13;
0                                  -~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
_TUDS aC                                      Z/196T&#13;
*IIIII                       &#13;
I                                                  tt/: XL6o &#13;
0oXNv                      N&lt;nf&#13;
_  _ 0  &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 &#13;
to the replacement cost of those same assets. 1/ The implications of the&#13;
valuation ratio for investment are summarized as follows:&#13;
"Investment is stimulated when capital is valued more&#13;
highly in the market than it costs to produce it and dis-&#13;
couraged when its valuation is less than its replacement&#13;
cost." 2/&#13;
4.07      Under simplified conditions, the valuation ratio can be construed&#13;
as the ratio of the real (after-tax) rate of return on productive assets and&#13;
the real cost of capital. 3/ The higher (lower) the real rate of return on&#13;
investment vis-a-vis the real cost of capital, the higher (lower) the valua-&#13;
tion ratio, and consequently, the larger (smaller) the net profitability&#13;
of the investment and thus the larger (smaller) the willingness to invest.&#13;
4.08      Under long-term competitive conditions, investment in physical&#13;
assets would proceed up to the point where the rate of return equals the&#13;
cost of capital, and the valuation ratio would approach unity. In the short&#13;
run or in the absence of competitive conditions, however, the valuation&#13;
ratio may systematically differ from unity. The most important reason for&#13;
this is the fact that investment decisions require time to be implemented.&#13;
If such a process were instantaneous, new investment would promptly eliminate&#13;
1/   The imputed market value of the firms' real assets is calculated as&#13;
follows: First the current value of stock is estimated by multiplying&#13;
the number of outstanding ordinary and preference shares by their respec-&#13;
tive market prices and adding up the two values. To obtain the imputed&#13;
market value of the firms' physical assets, the market value of shares&#13;
is added to borrowings and short term liabilities, and the value of&#13;
financial assets is subtracted from this total. (Consult Table Al,&#13;
Annex 1 for further details). The replacement cost of the firms' non-&#13;
financial assets has been calculated before and is listed on Table 7.&#13;
2/   W. C. Brainard and J. Tobin, "Pitfalls in Financial Model Building,"&#13;
American Economic Review, May 1968, pp. 99-149 (p. 103).&#13;
3/   Consult J. Tbbin and W. C. Brainard, "Asset Markets and the Cost of&#13;
Capital," in R. Nelson, et al. (eds.).--&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
any divergence between the rate of return and the cost of capital, and ful-&#13;
fill an "arbitrage" function of equalizing marginal returns and marginal&#13;
costs. 1/&#13;
4.09       Imperfect capital markets in which only a small fraction of the&#13;
shares of a company is traded and the remainder is in the hands of very&#13;
few owners, may underestimate the financial valuation of the firm and hence&#13;
the valuation ratio. For instance, the current price of shares may be sub-&#13;
stantially below the marginal cost of acquiring shares. 2/&#13;
4.10       The expectations of private investors regarding the future are&#13;
partially reflected in the valuation ratio through the market quotation of&#13;
shares. This is an important feature but it may also be a drawback, if for&#13;
instance, the valuation ratio is unduly influenced by swings of optimism or&#13;
by political events which are not germane to the underlying investment condi-&#13;
tions.&#13;
4.11       Ideally, the relevant determinant of investment is the marginal,&#13;
not the average, valuation ratio; i.e., the ratio between the increased&#13;
market valuation of a firm (or group of firms) that would result from an&#13;
investment and the cost of that investment. It has been argued, however,&#13;
that "the forces of continuity in the economy are strong," so that marginal&#13;
and average valuation ratios can be expected to move simultaneously. System-&#13;
atic differences in their levels can, nevertheless, remain. For instance,&#13;
the marginal valuation ratio may be expected to be higher than the average&#13;
1/   J. Tobin and W. C. Brainard, op. cit.&#13;
2/   E.g., the reservation price of larger-owners' shares may be substan-&#13;
tiallv hiaher than the Drevailinz market Drice.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
because of the significance of fiscal incentives for investment in India,&#13;
that effectively reduce real investment costs. 1/&#13;
4.12      Table 7 presents estimates of the valuation ratio for RBI Samples&#13;
of companies. There has been a decline in the valuation ratio: from an&#13;
average rate of 65.7% from 1961/62 to 1965/66 to 62.4% from 1966/67 to 1970/71&#13;
and 56.0% in the subsequent five-year period. This decline coincides with&#13;
the deceleration of the growth rate of fixed capital stock.&#13;
4.13      The decline in the valuation ratio has not been uniform, especially&#13;
as a result of downward shifts in expectations about profitability in periods&#13;
of severe droughts and other unfavorable economic conditions (e.g., 1973/75).&#13;
During these periods, the proportional decline in the valuation ratio has&#13;
been less acute than the relative fall in the after-tax rate of return, indi-&#13;
cating that the real cost of capital has also declined (but to a smaller&#13;
extent than the rate of return). The main explanation for the decline in&#13;
the cost of capital is the following one: in periods of unanticipated infla-&#13;
tion (as were to a large extent the periods from 1966 to 1968 and from. 1973&#13;
to 1975), the nominal rate of interest attached to previously contracted&#13;
debt fails to adjust to inflationary conditions, inducing a transfer of&#13;
real resources from lenders to borrowers. 2/ Under these conditions, the&#13;
1/   Estimates of average valuation ratios presented in Table 8 are system-&#13;
atically lower than unity and tend to confirm this; although in prin-&#13;
ciple, monopoly power or diminishing returns to scale could mean that&#13;
the average valuation ratio is higher than the marginal ratio. Consult&#13;
J. Tobin and W. C. Brainard, op. cit., p. 243.&#13;
2/   To a certain extent, borrowings by firms can be considered a hedge&#13;
against unanticipated inflation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
rate of return fails to incorporate the gains that accrue to firms as&#13;
a result of having a lower real value of debt. 1/&#13;
4.14      The analysis of RBI samples up to 1975/76 can throw light on some&#13;
of the present constraints on investment. First of all, if ICICI data on&#13;
companies are indicative of the overall behavior of the private corporate&#13;
sector it seems that profitability suffered a further decline in 1976/77,&#13;
beyond the fall observed in 1975/76. 2/ Such a fall seems to have resulted&#13;
from inadequate demand growth and from higher effective tax rates caused on&#13;
the one hand by inadequate accounting depreciation provisions that failed to&#13;
adjust taxable income for inflationary conditions and, on the other hand, by&#13;
lower investment activity itself. 3/ In addition, real interest rates were&#13;
substantially higher due to much lower price increases in the context of&#13;
constant nominal interest rates in this period. A lower real rate of return&#13;
accompanied by a higher real cost of capital implies a decline in the valua-&#13;
tion ratio. Such a decline may explain to a large extent the significant&#13;
fall in private corporate investment in 1976/77.&#13;
4.15       The prospects for private industrial investment have improved since&#13;
the second half of 1977/78. Better demand conditions have improved capacity&#13;
utilization and profitability. Equity prices, which to a large extent-&#13;
reflect profit expectations, have risen substantially during 1978. Nominal&#13;
interest rates charged by scheduled commercial banks on long-term loans were&#13;
reduced from 14-15% to 12.5% effective June 1977. All these factors point&#13;
1/   Conversely, the real value of assets of official lending institutions,&#13;
may be strained in periods of unanticipated inflation.&#13;
2/   Consult Table 6.&#13;
3/   Consult para. 3.08.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
to an increase in the valuation ratio during 1978. Consequently, private&#13;
industrial investment activity can be expected to improve broadly in the near&#13;
future, provided some uncertainties in the political and economic spheres do&#13;
not provoke reticence on the part of prospective investors. 1/ In the field&#13;
of private industrial investment, any factor that increases the uncertainty&#13;
surrounding future operations -- be it inadequate supply of power, labor&#13;
relations problems or others -- tends to decrease the expected return from&#13;
investment and hence reduces the willingness to invest. 2/&#13;
Investment Licensing and the MRTP Act 3/, 4/&#13;
4.16      The system of investment licensing and the MRTP Act regulates the&#13;
flow of private industrial investment, at least in the case of large compa-&#13;
nies, and is, in principle, an important investment determinant. The extent&#13;
to which this system has effectively reduced investment (i.e., below the&#13;
levels it would have reached otherwise) is difficult to assess. On the one&#13;
hand, at a minimum the process of securing an investment license and other&#13;
1/   An example of these is the recently discussed issue of nationalization&#13;
of certain industries.&#13;
2/   Private industrial firms bear a large part of the adjustment costs under&#13;
uncertainty. For instance, if output demand were to fall drastically&#13;
and unexpectedly, the firm retains the responsibility of maintaining its&#13;
labor force constant. Similarly, there is no compensation to the firm&#13;
in the event of inadequate supply of power. On the other hand, unex-&#13;
pected benefits are subject to taxation. The asymmetry in the treatment&#13;
of costs and benefits under uncertainty and the fact that a large part&#13;
of the former are borne by the firm, tend to diminish the expected return&#13;
from investment and may be important in explaining the investment per-&#13;
formance of private firms, especially in recent years.&#13;
3)   Monopolies and Restrictive Trade Practices Act in effect since 1969.&#13;
4/   For a broad discussion of industrial investment policies, consult&#13;
S. Bhoothalingam, "Review of Industrial Policy Since Independence."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
necessary clearances involves time. 1/ This process is eventually reflected&#13;
in longer gestation periods for specific investment projects; longer with&#13;
respect to the time they would otherwise have needed to develop (i.e., in the&#13;
absence of such clearances), and longer by international standards. To the&#13;
extent that longer gestation tends to decrease the expected rate of return of&#13;
a given investment, the regulatory system can be expected to reduce the&#13;
willingness to invest and the actual flow of investment.&#13;
4.17      On the other hand, the regulatory system has also been used to pro-&#13;
tect firms from potential competition; within certain bounds, those firms that&#13;
received a license could count on the exclusion of new investment in the in-&#13;
dustry if their installed capacity was not being fully utilized. In this&#13;
sense, the regulatory system for investment, by reducing uncertainty as to&#13;
the prospective returns from investment, may have increased investment beyond&#13;
the levels it would have reached otherwise. However, the importance of this&#13;
effect has declined over time. It was relevant in the earlier stages of&#13;
import-substitution industrialization (i.e., up to the middle of the 1960s).&#13;
At present, it is generally agreed that having a license does not guarantee&#13;
markets, 2/ especially in the context of a more open import policy which&#13;
introduces some measure of foreign competition into the economy. 3/&#13;
4.18      Consequently, in its present form the regulatory system for invest-&#13;
ment has primarily a negative role; it can restrict the flow of investment&#13;
1/   In recent years the procedures have been streamlined.&#13;
2/   S. Bhoothalingam, op. cit.&#13;
3/   However, recent import liberalization measures do not affect all the&#13;
industrial sector; e.g., imports of most manufactured consumption goods&#13;
are still not allowed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
in certain directions but it cannot encourage or stimulate it in others. 1/&#13;
In addition to inhibiting investment, perhaps the most significant features&#13;
of such a system are that it tends to reduce the elasticity of investment&#13;
response to changing economic circumstances and constrains the operation&#13;
of competitive forces within the industrial sector. 2/ Needless to add,&#13;
it may be nearly impossible to quantify the impact of such a system in terms&#13;
of foregone opportunities or inefficiencies generated, which is not equiva-&#13;
lent to saying that is impact is negligible.&#13;
IV. 2     Statistical Analysis of Investment Determinants&#13;
4.19      The assessment of trends in specific variables and their relation-&#13;
ship with investment trends are important in identifying broad patterns but&#13;
they are not a substitute for studying yearly investment variations and&#13;
their determinants. The latter is accomplished by means of multiple regres-&#13;
sion analysis.&#13;
4.20      One of-the basic problems in trying to identify those variables&#13;
that have an independent influence on investment is the high degree of multi-&#13;
collinearity among the variables. To the extent that several variables tend&#13;
to move together over time, it may not be possible to separate the influence&#13;
of individual variables. This is reflected in the correlation matrix&#13;
presented below.&#13;
1/   S. Bhoothalingam, op. cit.&#13;
2/   It should be stressed, however, that in recent years the extent of the&#13;
regulatory system has been reduced significantly: annual investments&#13;
of up to Rs 30 million have been exempted from licensing requirements;&#13;
nevertheless, MRTP restrictions are still in effect.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
Correlation Matrix 1/&#13;
S/FK     r       C     q&#13;
I                  0.91   0.87   0.86    0.68&#13;
S/FK                      0.95    0.78   0.94&#13;
rN                               0.99    0.82&#13;
C                                        0.80&#13;
where I - gross investment rate; S/FK - sales per unit of fixed assets;&#13;
N&#13;
r = after-tax rate of return; C = cash flow ratio; and q -,valuation ratio.&#13;
4.21      An important result is the high correlation between sales per unit&#13;
of fixed assets and the real rate of return from capital. 2/ Causation can&#13;
be presumed to run from sales to profits. Sales can also be expected to&#13;
influence cash flow and the valuation ratio. In addition to its indirect&#13;
effects on investment - via changes in profitability, cash flow and the&#13;
valuation ratio - the level of sales per unit of fixed assets has a dis-&#13;
cernible impact on fixed capital formation.&#13;
4.22      Given the high degree of multicollinearity among some of the&#13;
independent variables it was considered inadvisable to include more than two&#13;
independent variables in the regression. In some instances, the inclusion of&#13;
two highly correlated variables led to unsatisfactory results. 3/ For this&#13;
reason, a single explanatory variable and a time trend variable were intro-&#13;
duced in some instances; the latter in order to capture, at least partially,&#13;
the impact of excluded variables.&#13;
1/   Consult Table 8 for the definition of the variables.&#13;
2/   This result was anticipated ear±±er in Lne analysis of tax incidence,&#13;
and will be explored further.&#13;
3/   For instance, when sales per unit of fixed assets and the valuation&#13;
ratio were included jointly as explanatory variables, the investment-&#13;
response coefficient of the latter vatiable had the wrong sign.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
4.23       Before proceeding to analyze the regression results it is necessary&#13;
to list some additional limitations of the estimates and methods used. First,&#13;
investment processes involve time and there may be significant lags between&#13;
the formulation and implementation of an investment decision. On the other&#13;
hand, an investment may also be made on the anticipation of future events;&#13;
e.g., large growth in sales. The observed level of investment is certainly&#13;
the result of decisions made in the past, but to the extent that those&#13;
decisions were based on projections of future events, it may happen that&#13;
current values of observed variables may have a strong (or stronger) effect&#13;
on current investment (than lagged values of the same variables), especially&#13;
if anticipations have been proven correct. Consequently, the optimal speci-&#13;
fication of the lag or lead structure of specific variables in investment&#13;
functions remains unclear 1/. In the following regressions the current real&#13;
gross investment rate is related to current values (i.e., without lags) of&#13;
the independent variables.&#13;
4.24       Secondly, as mentioned earlier, there may be errors of measurement&#13;
in some of the variables, especially in the case of the valuation ratio.&#13;
This may systematically distort the results.&#13;
4.25       Finally, the time series are constructed on the basis of three&#13;
samples of different sizes.   Given the large size of each of the samples and&#13;
the correspondence that exists in relative values in adjacent years, it is not&#13;
likely that the samples reflect different structures, although some regression&#13;
results may be slightly affected by this. Since the variables used are either&#13;
1/   Unfortunately, graphs 2 and 3 do not provide sufficient guidelines on&#13;
this issue.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
annual growth rates or ratios of variables, they are independent of the size&#13;
of the samples. 1/&#13;
4.26      The main regression results are presented in Table 9.     The method&#13;
of ordinary least squares has been applied throughout. Column 1 presents&#13;
the regression results relative to the time trend of gross investment rates.&#13;
The deceleration in the gross rates of fixed capital formation is confirmed,&#13;
the relevant coefficient is negative and statistically significant. 2/&#13;
4.27      Among alternative specifications of the investment function, the&#13;
second regression presents the best statistical results. Sales per unit of&#13;
fixed assets has a positive and statistically highly significant coefficient.&#13;
The implied elasticity of gross investment with respect to sales is about&#13;
1.1, 3/ indicating that a 1% increase in sales would eventually trigger&#13;
about a 1% increase in gross investment.&#13;
1/   Heteroskedasticity and autocorrelation problems may have been circum-&#13;
vented by these means.&#13;
2/   As was pointed out earlier, the results are contingent on the assumption&#13;
that the annual economic depreciation of fixed assets is 6% of the&#13;
outstanding fixed capital stock at the beginning of each year. If&#13;
instead of 6%, a depreciation rate of 8% were assumed, the regression&#13;
results would not differ significantly, as the following shows:&#13;
G     16.414 - 0.4418*t                  R= 0.72&#13;
8             (-5.77)&#13;
2&#13;
G  =  16.351 - 0.5464*t                  R = 0.79&#13;
6             (-7.08)&#13;
where G   and G  are gross investment rates under depreciation rates of&#13;
8 and 6 respectively. (Numbers in-parenthesis are t statistics.) The&#13;
average gross investment rates during the fifteen-year period are 12.88%&#13;
and 11.98% under 8% and 6% depreciation rates respectively (Table 9).&#13;
3/   Evaluated at the mid-point values of the sample data, Column 10 in&#13;
Table 9.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 9&#13;
INDIA- Regression Results on Investment and its Determinants in the Private Corporate Sector&#13;
Regression on some explanatory variables&#13;
Average values     Variance&#13;
After-tax-rate    Valuation  Cashfo&#13;
Resresaions on GrosB Investr4ent Rate                   |     Afeer-eax-rate    ratio      Cash flcyw  $of independent      of independent&#13;
Repressions on Gross Investment Rate             f return        ratio        ratio       variables IL_      arabe&#13;
(1)        (2)        (3)        (4)       (5)        (6)                 (7)           (8)        (9)&#13;
fUDEPENDENT VARIABLES:&#13;
Constant                     16.351    o.498      10.004    9.145     17.644      -5.580             -3.326        44.086       0.733&#13;
Sales per unit of fixed assets         9.112**                                                       6.279**       15.225*                j        1.452             0.0297&#13;
(59.39)                                                       (110.79)      (6.39)                 l&#13;
After tax rate of return                          0.835*                                                                       1.186**              5.687            1.4179&#13;
(5.70)                                                                       (66.98)&#13;
Cash flow, ratio                                            0.739*                                                                                  7.701            1.7318&#13;
(5.59)&#13;
Valuation ratio                                                       -0.018       0.286*                                                          61.393           39.937&#13;
(-0.14)      (3.36)&#13;
Time trend                   -0.546*   -0.219     -0.347   -0.358     -0.567*                        -0.013        -0.60      0.028                 8.0             18.667&#13;
(-7.08)   (-0.06)    (-0.65)   (0.82)    (-6.42)                        (-0.01)       (-0.01)    (0.434&#13;
R2                            0.79      o.86      o.83     0.83        0.79        0.47              0.91           0.65      0.99&#13;
Number of Observations       15        15         15      15          15          15                 15            15        15&#13;
Soutee: Table 8. The first six regressions are alternative forms explaining the behavior of the gross investment rate. The following three regressions explain the behavior of&#13;
some investment deteminants. All regressions are linear regressions. The numbers in parenthesis under the coefficients are t statistics.  One and two asterisks&#13;
indicate that the coefficients are statistically significant at the 5 and I percent probability levels, respectively.&#13;
If The average value of the gross investmant rate is 11.98 and its variance is 7.0176&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
4.28      The level of sales is also an important determinant of profitability.&#13;
Regressions 7 and 8 show that sales per unit of fixed assets influence sig-&#13;
nificantly the after-tax rate of return and the valuation ratio, especially&#13;
the former. 1/&#13;
4.29      Profitability, as measured by the after-tax rate of return, influ-&#13;
ences investment patterns directly (Regression 3). However, given the high&#13;
correlation between profitability and sales, it is difficult to separate their&#13;
impact on investment. 2/&#13;
4.30       It was mentioned earlier that the empirical measurement of the val-&#13;
uation ratio was subject to several deficiencies. Undoubtedly, these account&#13;
for its poor explanatory power in regression 5. 3/ In regression 6, the time&#13;
trend variable is excluded and the coefficient of the valuation ratio becomes&#13;
positive and significant, although its explanatory power is still relatively&#13;
weak.&#13;
4.31      Regression 9 confirms the close relationship between the after-tax&#13;
rate of return and the cash flow ratio. 4/ In effect it means that in order&#13;
to increase cash flow it is necessary to increase profits as well. An unfor-&#13;
tunate consequence of such a close relation is the inability to disentangle&#13;
1/   In effect, regression,2 can be characterized as a "reduced form" equa-&#13;
tion which captures the indirect effects of profitability on investment,&#13;
via the dependence of the rate of return on the state of demand.&#13;
2/   In effect, a regression on investment including jointly these two inde-&#13;
pendent variables led to unsatisfactory results (e.g., the coefficient&#13;
of the rate of return was negative). Consult the previous footnote.&#13;
3/   The coefficient of this variable is unexpectedly negative, although it&#13;
is not statistically significant.&#13;
4/   Such a close relationship is not a result of the way in which the&#13;
variables have been defined.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
the effects of availability of financial funds on the one hand and of the&#13;
rate of return on the other, on investment patterns.&#13;
4.34       In conclusion, the downward trend in the gross investment rate can&#13;
be explained primarily by the relative performance of sales, which as men-&#13;
tioned earlier, have grown at lower rates than the fixed capital stock in&#13;
recent years. 1/ The state of demand has also influenced profitability;&#13;
the decline in the latter in recent years is a result of the lower rate of&#13;
growth of sales.&#13;
1/   Not only has the volume of sales grown at lower rates in recent years,&#13;
but there seems to have been wider fluctuations in the level of demand&#13;
than in the 1960s.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 7&#13;
V.         CONCLUSION&#13;
5.01      This paper has analyzed some determinants of private industrial&#13;
investment in India. A by-product of such an analysis has been the estimation&#13;
of several variables that are of interest in themselves. For instance, the&#13;
replacement value of non-financial assets (and its relation to accounting&#13;
data), as well as the rate of return (before and after taxes), are prelimi-&#13;
nary steps in the calculation of the social rate of return to private invest-&#13;
ment, an important datum for social cost-benefit analysis. Similarly, the&#13;
taxation of corporate income and its trend reveal some of the distortions&#13;
induced by lack of inflation clauses in accounting. In other instances, some&#13;
of the measurements require additional refinements, e.g., the valuation ratio.&#13;
5.02      Among the most important results of this study has been the decel-&#13;
eration in the rate of growth of the fixed capital stock. The forces behind&#13;
such a deceleration are difficult to disentangle but it seems conclusive that&#13;
the trend in sales has .been an important element. Not only have sales in-&#13;
fluenced investment activity directly but also through profitability and&#13;
cash flow. The decline in the after-tax rate is explained to a large extent&#13;
by demand conditions and by tax increases.&#13;
5.03      The analysis of investment patterns during the period 1961/62 to&#13;
1975/76 can shed light on some recent developments. The decline is profit-&#13;
ability in 1976/77 1/ and the increase in real rates of interest have un-&#13;
doubtedly contributed to the sharp fall in private corporate investment in&#13;
that year. The fall in profits seems to have resulted primarily from inade-&#13;
quate demand growth, and from rising effective corporate tax rates due to&#13;
inadequate accounting depreciation provisions that failed to adjust taxable&#13;
income for inflation.&#13;
1/   ICICI, op. cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
5.04      Investment prospects have improved substantially since the second&#13;
half of 1977/78. Sales have increased widely and this has improved the finan-&#13;
cial performance of companies. Interest rates have been reduced. Apparently&#13;
the valuation ratio has risen after its sharp fall in 1976/77. Direct evidence&#13;
on this is provided by the substantial increase in share prices during 1978 --&#13;
leading to higher market valuation of firms -- unaccompanied by a correspond-&#13;
ing increase in the replacement cost of real capital. 1/&#13;
5.05      The extent to which better opportunities will be translated into&#13;
actual investment depends partly on the operation of Government regulations&#13;
on investment, and on the perceptions of investors. It seems clear, however,&#13;
that the availability of fiscal incentives that reduce the tax liability of&#13;
investing companies has acquired special significance in the context of&#13;
improved demand and rising profits, 2/ and may provide a substantive stimulus&#13;
to investment.&#13;
5.06      This paper has concentrated on aggregate trends in the private&#13;
industrial sector. Undoubtedly, there have been differences in performance&#13;
among specific industries; as illustrated by the cement and traditional&#13;
textile industries where until recently profitability and investment patterns&#13;
had been conditioned by the operation of restrictive pricing policies. A&#13;
natural extension of this paper is the disaggregation by industries or groups&#13;
of industries, to ascertain the extent to which there are underlying varia-&#13;
tions in the trends observed before.&#13;
1/   The wholesale price index of machinery and equipment was only 5.1% higher&#13;
in December 1978 than in December 1977.&#13;
2/   In periods of depressed demand and profits (e.g., 1975-77), the avail-&#13;
ability of such investment incentives may not be sufficient to bring&#13;
about more investment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
80E1X I Table Al&#13;
DWIA.:   Market Value of RNo-Financil Ansets nod Valuation Ratio io S   Imsle. of Firma in th@&#13;
Private Cnrpormte Sector. 1960/61 to 1975/76&#13;
(current prices., R. illion)&#13;
Market Valu, of     Repl.cnt ywlue&#13;
Indeo  nsbern of                                                                                                                Finoocial   Short tcr,     FirV non-fi en-    of noo-flnancial    Valrtion&#13;
Security Price. 1/          Ordinary Share.           FPrfere.ce Share             Mrke     Valu of Share.         Borxmivnma     On        Liabilitisa    etal a*sets           t. at -ad of     Ratio (1)&#13;
Paid up   Market nolie of    Pid-up    Market value as                         5/                                                                         Yrt   7/&#13;
Orditary Prefermne     COpital    shares  of paid    CApital   2 of paid-up       Ordinary   Fraference   Total&#13;
up capital 2/                 capita1 3/&#13;
(1)       (2)           (3)         (4)              (5)         (6)              (7)         (8)        (9)       ,(10)         (1i)         (12)            (13)                (14)            (15)&#13;
SERIES I&#13;
1960-1       88.5      80.3       6014         152.5            1149        64.2              9171        737       9908        7280          6670         6010           16530               21870            75.6&#13;
61-2       94.7      76.6       6429         163.2            1145         61.2            18492        iOI      11193        7950          7230         6690           186C0               24960            74.5&#13;
62-3       92.5      74.9        6810        159.4            1152         59.8            10855        689      11544        8870          8000         7350           19760               27790            71.1&#13;
63-4       86.1      75.2        7118        148.3            1172         60.1            10556        704      11260        9870          8690         7910           20350               31410            64.8&#13;
64-5       84.5      93.5       7299         145.6            1198         74.7            10627        895      11522       11130          9610         8570           21610               34840           62.0&#13;
65-6       75.3     107.9       7554         129.7            1243         86.2             9798       1072      10870       12470         10150         9100           22290               39580           56.3&#13;
SERIES 71&#13;
1965-6       75.3     107.9       917o         129.7            1326         86.5            11893       1147      13040       14590         11020         9900           26510               43130           61.5&#13;
66-7       78.7     102.9      10362         135.6            1372         82.5            14051       1132      15183       17930         12410        11030           31730               50350           63.0&#13;
67-8       75.3      99.5       10984        125.7            1445         79.8            13807       1153      14960       19970         13100        11700           33530               55510           60.4&#13;
68-9       e0.2      98.2       11474        148.2            1519         78.9            17004       1198      18203       21170         14790        12600           37180               59140           62.9&#13;
69-70      90.9     100.1       12092        163.4            1598         80.3            19758       1283      21041       22290         16430        13860           40760               64110           63.6&#13;
70-1      100.0     100.0       12583        172.3            1626         79.9            21681       1299      22980       23680         17920        15620           44360               71260           62.3&#13;
SERIES 111&#13;
70-1      100.0     100.0       13729        172 3            1789         79.9            23655       1429      25084       26860         19110        16450           49280               75890           64.9&#13;
71-2       95.1      96.8       14207        161.8            1792         78.9            22987       1414      24401       28250         20500        18800           50950               83610           60.9&#13;
72-3       96.4      94.3       14718        169.2            1801         78-4            24903       1412      26315       28710         21630        21040           54430               91420           59.5&#13;
73-4      114.6      94.1       15313        196.5            1799         78.1            30090       1405      31495       31020         24900        25780           63390              105830           59.9&#13;
74-5      112.5      90.9       16313        193.8            1769         75.4            31615       1334      32949       34460         28380        32680           71710              137490           52.2&#13;
75-6       97.3      84.3       17209        167.6            1785         70.0            28842       1250      30092       38830         32100        35970           72790              153210           47.5&#13;
1/ The inden of security pricen is derived by aplicing dte, indicee coverinB the years 1960/61 to 1964/65 (bane 1952/3). 1964/65 to 1970/71 (baee 1960/1) and 1970/71  to 1975/76 (beec 1970/1), acing 1970/71 as tho&#13;
coen bane.     2/ The market valoe of shares as  percentage of paid-op capital for the yearo 1967/68 to 1973/74 is obtained directly from R81 B todlen on the t-rket vdloation of a lrge n&amp;pl of joint etock&#13;
co.pane.i, bhich contaIn oeparate information on ordinary and preference bharen. For the remining yearo thin percentage  is calculated by ootng the price inde, of ordinary oharen to deflote the 1970 71 ratio.&#13;
For instance. if in 1963 64  the price indee of ordinary sharee tas 86.1 (1970/1 - 100) then the relevant ratio is that of 1970/71 (i.e. 172 3) muitiplied by (.861) - 148.3.  3/ A siiler procedore to that&#13;
applied to ordinary ehare. Va followed in the cane of preferene shares. See footmote 2.    4/ Total paid-up capital (col. 3) i.  ultiplied by the ratio of the market naloe of shares to paid-op capital (col.4)&#13;
in order to derive col. 7.    5/ Col.7 is the prodoct of coimao  5 and 6 ( i 100).  6/ To obtain the mrket value of the finm   phy.ical .nnto. the mrket value of oheren in added ti berro-n.gs and ahort teers liabili-&#13;
tien nd 4he value f financil ansnets is oubstracted froe this total. The lost three terem   are derived directly from balance oheeto. Only a emali fraction of the debt of these copnio  is marketed. Further-&#13;
mare, the market value of the marketed debt is only slightly belov par volue. For inotance in March 1974, out of ootctandieg debenture. of Rn 2000 9011100 of cempanle quoted in tock e.change.. the -rk.t&#13;
value of thene debentures vn 94.37 of par value. (RBI Bulletin., Dc. 1974 p.228 ).  Conanquently, no adjunt.ent hbn been made in the bok value of debt.  7/ Sun of the replcne.t value of fined aseets (RFl(t)) and&#13;
the book value of inventorica (an reflected in BSlance Sheets). §/ The valuation ratio is the percentage of the narkat value  of ficou  phyical assets (eol. 13) to the replacent coat of those . .aet. (c.l. 14).&#13;
Source: RBI. Seoplee of medium and large non-financial,  n.goversmmnc. public limited companien. RBI Monthly Bulletin., everal i        Suen.  larie. I. II and III ore not atrictly comparable dnee they involve different&#13;
number of fin.    Nonethelean. the nariatitno  from s,aple to sample amc net large and proper co.parisona are possible iR6 nma djoatmtnr  ore made in reLation to the changing sie of the sample.. as e.g. in col. 14&#13;
derived in Table 7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
List of References&#13;
Bhoothalingam, S. "Review of Industrial Policy Since Independence,"&#13;
reprinted in C. N. Vakil (ed), Industrial Development of India -&#13;
Policy and Problems, 1973.&#13;
Brainard, J. and J. Tobin, "Pitfalls in Financial Model Building,"&#13;
Ame"rican Economic Review, Vol 58, May 1968.&#13;
Feldstein, M. and L. Summers, "Is the Rate of Profit Falling,"&#13;
Brookings Papers on Economic Activity, 1:1977, pp. 211-27.&#13;
Harberger, A. "Investment in Men Versus Investment in Machines"&#13;
(1965), reprinted in D. Wall (ed.) Chicago Essays in Economic&#13;
Development, Univ. of Chicago Press, 1972.&#13;
Helliwell, J. F. (ed.) Aggregate Investment, Penguin, 1976.&#13;
ICICI, Financial Performance of Companies, ICICI Portfolio 1975/76,&#13;
Bombay, 1977.&#13;
ICICI, Financial Performance of Companies, ICICI Portfolio 1976/77,&#13;
Bombay, 1978.&#13;
Jenkins, G. "The Measurement of Rates of Return and Taxation from&#13;
Private Capital in Canada," reprinted in W. A. Niskanen, et al.&#13;
(eds.) Benefit-Cost Policy Analysis, 1972 (Aldine, 1973).&#13;
YJorgenson, D. W. and Z. Grilliches, "The Explanation of Productivity&#13;
Change," Review of Economic Studies, Vol. 34, 1967, pp. 249-83.&#13;
Lal, R.N. Capital Formation and its Financing in India, Allied Publishers,&#13;
Bombay, 1977.&#13;
Government of India - Central Statistical Organization (CSO), "Quick&#13;
Estimates," January 8, 1979.&#13;
Reserve Bank of India (RBI)&#13;
-    Finances of Medium and Large Public Limited Companies:&#13;
(a) Financial Statistics of Joint Stock Companies, 1960/61 to&#13;
1970/71, Bombay, 1975.&#13;
(b) RBI Bulletin, September 1975.&#13;
(c) RBI Bulletin, September 1977.&#13;
(d) RBI Bulletin, July 1978.&#13;
-    Market Value of Share Capital of Joint Stock Companies:&#13;
(a) RBI Bulletin, September 1970.&#13;
(b) RBI Bulletin, February 1973&#13;
(c) RBI Bulletin, October 1973&#13;
(b) RBI Survey of Currency and Finance, Several issues&#13;
-    Survey of Currency and Finance 1977/78, Vol. I and II, Bombay&#13;
1978&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
List of References (continued)&#13;
Tobin, J. and W. C. Brainard, "Assets, Markets and the Cost of Capital in&#13;
B. Belasse and R. Nelson (eds.), Economic Progress, Private Values&#13;
and Essays in Honor of William Fellner, 1977.&#13;
von Furstenberg,. G. M. "Corporate Investment: Does Market Valuation&#13;
Matter in the Aggregate?" Brookings Papers on Economic Activity,&#13;
2:1977, pp. 347-408.&#13;
Wright, F.K. "Towards a General Theory of Depreciation", reprinted in Parker,&#13;
R.K. and G. C. Harcourt (eds.) Readings in the Concept and Measurement&#13;
of Income, 1969.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
RECENT PAPERS IN THIS SERIES&#13;
No.                        TITLE OF PAPER                            AUTHOR&#13;
310        Teacher Training and Student Achievement          T. Husen, L. Saha&#13;
in Less Developed Countries                       R. Noonan (consultants)&#13;
311        Optimum Economic Power Supply Reliability         M. Munasinghe&#13;
M. Gellerson (consultant)&#13;
312        Intra-Industry Trade and the Integration of       B. Balassa&#13;
Developing Countries in the World Economy&#13;
313        Export Promotion Policies                         B. de Vries&#13;
314        The Changing Composition of Developing            H. Chenery&#13;
Country Exports                                   D. Keesing&#13;
315        Urban Growth and Economic Development in the      M. Cohen&#13;
Sahel: Prospects and Priorities&#13;
316        World Trade and Output of Manufactures:           D. Keesing&#13;
Structural Trends and Developing Countries'&#13;
Exports&#13;
317        Cuba:  Economic Change and Education Reform       M. Carnoy, J. Wertheim&#13;
1955-1974                                         (consultants)&#13;
318        Sources of Fertility Decline:   Factor Analysis   R. Faruqee&#13;
of Inter-Countty Data&#13;
319        Educational and Economic Effects of Promotion     W.D. Haddad&#13;
and Repetition Practices&#13;
320        Small Farmers and the Landless in South Asia      I.J. Singh&#13;
321        Fruit and Vegetable Exports from the              R.D. Hunt&#13;
Mediterranean Area to the EEC&#13;
322        Ability in Pre-Sch6olers, Earnings, and           R. Grawe&#13;
Home-Environment&#13;
323        Priorities in Education:   Pre-School;            M. Smilansky (consultant)&#13;
Evidence and Conclusions&#13;
324        Tropical Root Crops and Rural Development         T.J. Goering&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
No.                       TITLE OF PAPER                             AUTHOR&#13;
325        Costs and Scale of Bus Services                  A.A. Walters&#13;
326        Social and Cultural Dimensions of Tourism         R. Noronha (consultant)&#13;
327        Investment in Indian Education:   Uneconomic?     S. P. Heyneman&#13;
328        Nutrition and Food Needs in Developing            0. Knudsen&#13;
Countries                                        P.L. Scandizzo&#13;
329        The Changing International Division of            B. Balassa&#13;
Labor in Manufactured Goods&#13;
330        Application of Shadow Pricing to Country         L. Squire&#13;
Economic Analysis with an Illustration           I.M.D. Little&#13;
from Pakistan                                    M. Durdag&#13;
331        A Survey of the Fertilizer Sector in             B. Bumb (consultant)&#13;
India&#13;
332        Mbnitoring and Evaluation in the PIDER           M.M. Cernea&#13;
Rural Development Project - Mexico&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG 3881.5 .W57 W67 NO.333 c.3&#13;
PINELL-SILES, ARMANDO, 1946-&#13;
DETERMINANTS OF PRIVATE&#13;
INDUSTRIAL INVESTMENT IN&#13;
DATE  NAME AND EXTENSION  ROOM&#13;
NUMBER&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1555091">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1979/06/1555091/determinants-private-industrial-investment-india
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1979/06/1555091/determinants-private-industrial-investment-india</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1979/06/1555091/determinants-private-industrial-investment-india</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/23/000178830_98101903402683/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/23/000178830_98101903402683/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-09-23T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1979-06-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Determinants of private industrial
            investment in India
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper analyzes the behavior of
            private industrial investment in India over time, and some
            of the factors that have influenced it, such as sales,
            profitability, taxation, financial resources, and others.
            Financial data compiled by the Reserve Bank of India (RBI)
            from large samples of predominantly manufacturing companies
            for the period 1960/61 to 1975/76 are the basis for the
            analysis. Financial data are transformed into meaningful
            economic magnitudes, as illustrated by the transition from
            the historical cost of fixed assets to their replacement
            value. The divergence between financial depreciation and
            economic depreciation as well as its implications for
            profitability and taxation are also explored. The analysis
            reveals that there has been a significant deceleration in
            the rate of growth of the fixed capital stock since the
            middle 1960s. Contributing to this deceleration are the
            inadequate growth of industrial demand and the related
            decline in real rates of return on non-financial assets. The
            paper briefly discusses recent investment developments and
            prospects in the light of the previous analysis.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Determinants of private industrial
            investment in India
        </docna>
        <display_title>Determinants of private
            industrial investment in India</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1979/06/1555091/determinants-private-industrial-investment-india</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Settlement of Investment Disputes,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Economic Theory &amp; Research,International Terrorism &amp; Counterterrorism,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>India</count>
        <authors>
            <author>PINELL-SILES, A.</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903402683</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Business environment</subsc>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 333</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Private Sector Development</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Capital stocks; Corporation taxes; Income
            taxes; Indirect taxation; Industrial investments; Private
            investments; Profitability; Savings
            Accounting,accounting practices,accumulated
            depreciation,affiliated organizations,assets,benefit
            analysis,book value,capacity utilization,capital
            goods,commercial banks,corporate taxes,cost of
            capital,current prices,debt,depreciation,depreciation
            allowances,economic circumstances,Economic
            Development,economic value,elasticity,financial
            assets,Financial data,financial resources,Financial
            Statistics,fixed assets,fixed capital,gross fixed capital
            formation,growth rate,income,inflation,inflation
            rate,inflation rates,interest payments,interest
            rates,inventories,inventory,less developed countries,Market
            Value,net value,net value of fixed assets,nominal interest
            rates,outstanding capital stock,price
            increases,productivity,profitability,regulatory
            framework,Reserve Bank of
            India,retirement,savings,Statistical Analysis,surcharges,tax
            rates,taxation,Taxation Rates,technological progress,time
            series,Valuation,value added,wholesale price index,wholesale prices
        </keywd>
        <owner>SAR</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP333</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education Reform and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teacher Professional Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Owned Enterprise Restructuring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Econometrics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Settlement of Investment Disputes</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textiles</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teacher Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Machinery and Equipment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Terrorism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprises</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>India</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>