<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>f sS"i    /7S7 3      &#143;&#13;
A Dynamic Simulation Model of the&#13;
World Jute Economy                                                           SWP-391&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 391&#13;
May 1980&#13;
Prepared by: Jock Anderson, Development Research Center&#13;
Charles Blitzer, Development Research Center&#13;
Tom Cauchois, Development Research Center&#13;
Enzo Grilli, Economic Analysis-and Projections&#13;
Departmeiit&#13;
Development Policy Staff&#13;
Copyright 0 1980&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the&#13;
authors and should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its&#13;
affiliated organizations, or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the authors&#13;
and should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organi-&#13;
zations, or to any individuals acting in their behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANlK&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 391&#13;
May 1980&#13;
A DYNAMIC SIMULATION MODEL OF THE&#13;
WORLD JUTE ECONOMY&#13;
Jute and jute products have been steadily losing markets to syn-&#13;
thetic substitutes since the 1960s. One of the causes of this loss in mar-&#13;
ket shares has traditionally been identified in the supply instability of&#13;
raw jute; large market price fluctuations have stimulated the search for&#13;
domestically produced substitutes for jute in consuming countries. Price&#13;
stabilization for jute has been intensely discussed in international fora,&#13;
within the framework of the UNCTAD Integrated Program for Commodities.&#13;
This paper investigates both the sources of jute supply instability and&#13;
the potential impact of an internationally managed buffer stock to stabi-&#13;
lize market prices.&#13;
The analysis is carried out utilizing a rather simple dynamic&#13;
model of the markets for raw jute and jute goods. The model combines&#13;
econometric estimates of the relevant parameters with a priori informa-&#13;
tion derived from industry studies. It integrates the behavior of jute&#13;
farmers in the principal jute growing countries with that of jute goods&#13;
manufacturers and consumers using a series of region-specific demand and&#13;
supply functions. Expected price variance is an explicit factor in&#13;
determining jute acreage.&#13;
This simple modelling approach should be quite useful in study-&#13;
ing commodity price stabilization. By focusing on the dynamics of supply&#13;
and demand, the adjustment to the stabilization policy itself can be&#13;
examined. By reducing the number of parameters to the minimum, it is&#13;
possible to identify the important ones and, therefore, those which need&#13;
more careful estimation. This methodology may also offer considerable&#13;
promise for medium-term analyses of other commodity markets.&#13;
Prepared by:  Jock Anderson, Development Research Center&#13;
Charles Blitzer, Development Research Center&#13;
Tom Cauchois, Development Research Center&#13;
Enzo Grilli, Economic Analysis and Projections Department&#13;
Development Policy Staff&#13;
Copyright Q 1980&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS&#13;
The authors wish to thank their former colleagues in the Develop-&#13;
ment Research Center and the Economic Analysis and Projections Department&#13;
of the World Bank who commented on this paper. They also wish to express&#13;
their appreciation to the participants in the Seminar on Planning Issues on&#13;
National Resources, held at the World Bank in December 1977, and in the&#13;
Commodity Modeling Seminar, held in Aarhus, Denmark, in December 1979, who&#13;
reviewed this paper. Finally they wish to acknowledge the usefulness of&#13;
the comments received from three anonymous referees who reviewed the paper&#13;
before its publication in the World Bank Staff Working Paper series.&#13;
None of the authors of this paper is any longer employed by the&#13;
World Bank. Mr. Jock Anderson is with the University of New England, Armi-&#13;
dale, Australia, Mr. Charles Blitzer is with the U. S. International Develop-&#13;
ment and Cooperation Agency, Mr. Tom Cauchois is at the Massachusetts Insti-&#13;
tute of Technology, Mr. Enzo Grilli is with the General Confederation of&#13;
Italian Industries in Italy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Introduction&#13;
1.        One of the key objectives of the New International Economic Order&#13;
has been to strengthen the position of developing countries in markets for&#13;
traded primary products. In international fora these countries, often&#13;
speaking as the Group of 77, have demanded increased stability, equitable&#13;
prices, and meaningful control over their resources. As the principal in-&#13;
ternational mechanism for achieving at least market stability a Common&#13;
Fund financing a series of buffer stock programs,was proposed. 1/&#13;
2.        During drawn-out discussions during the past five years, technical&#13;
discussions have been carried out for a core group of commodities, jute&#13;
among them. Jute and jute products have been steadily losing markets to&#13;
synthetic substitutes since the 1960s and the accepted wisdom is that over&#13;
time supply instability has generated,large market price fluctuations,which&#13;
have stimulated the search for domestically produced substitutes in the in-&#13;
dustrialized countries. 2/ In this paper, we investigate both the sources of this&#13;
supply instability and the potential impact of an internationally managed&#13;
buffer stock to stabilize prices.&#13;
3.        In particular, alternative buffer stocking rules are examined in&#13;
terms of their impact on:&#13;
- export revenue;&#13;
- direct costs and benefits of the buffer stock operation;&#13;
- required maximum funding to insure acceptable risk-targets.&#13;
1/ UNCTAD, "An Integrated Program for Commodities: The Role of International&#13;
Buffer Stocks". (Report by the Secretary General of UNCTAD), Docs.&#13;
TD/B/C.7/166 Supp. 7 and TD/B/C.7/Add. 7, December 1974.&#13;
2/ See Grilli and Morrison [1974] and IBRD World Jute Economy Report [1973].&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
In addition, we make some comparisons of alternative policies which might&#13;
also achieve similar stability objectives. These include:&#13;
- compensatory financing;&#13;
- tariffs and taxation;&#13;
- acreage limitations.&#13;
4.        The analysis is carried out utilizing a rather simple dynamic model&#13;
of the markets for raw jute and jute goods. It is our view that any meaning-&#13;
ful stabilization policy would affect the whole dynamic behavior of jute mar-&#13;
kets by altering expectations. With reduced risks, supply can be expected&#13;
to expand more than demand leading to increased price pressure, and ulti-&#13;
mately to further instability. Given the various ways that farmers, manu-&#13;
facturers, and customers react, some of the objectives of stabilization may&#13;
not be feasible except at unreasonable cost.&#13;
5.        The model has expected price variance as an explicit factor determin-&#13;
ing jute acreage. In addition, the specific functional forms were chosen to&#13;
allow maximum flexibility in terms of dynamic adjustments. The model inter-&#13;
grates the behavior of jute farmers in the principal jute-growing countries&#13;
with that of jute goods manufacturers and consumers using a series of region-&#13;
specific demand and supply functions. The model has been kept as simple as&#13;
possible for two reasons. First, the underlying data base is not extensive,&#13;
especially regarding the markets for jute goods. Since, data did not allow&#13;
econometric estimation of behavioral parameters in that set of markets, in-&#13;
formal estimates were required. These were derived from industry-wide studies&#13;
previously conducted at the World Bank and referred to previously. Only by&#13;
keeping the model simple could this be meaningfully done. Second, with a&#13;
simple model, having specific theoretical, behavioral properties-it is re-&#13;
latively easy to understand what is important in determining the characteristics&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
of simulated policy scenarios. It would be rash to claim that any model&#13;
could predict with great accuracy the'impact on the jute (or other) mar-&#13;
kets of a buffer stock operations. 'Nonetheless models can and should, be&#13;
able to isolate which factors will play the important roles and how they&#13;
inter-relate.&#13;
6.        The paper is divided into four sections.   We begin with a brief&#13;
review of the jute markets, highlighting those "stylized" facts which are&#13;
later included in the model. Section I describes the supply response of&#13;
jute farmers; econometric evidence is presented showing the importance of&#13;
risk in the planting decision. The rest of the model is outlined in&#13;
Section II.   In SectionIII results from the numerical simulations are&#13;
reviewed. Our conclusions are in SectionIV.&#13;
I. WORLD JUTE ECONOMY -- A REVIEW&#13;
7.        Jute fiber is produced in Asia, South America and Africa.   The&#13;
plant -- which grows annually -- requires high temperature, deep soil, and&#13;
rainfall distributed in such a way as to assure adequate moisture to the&#13;
young plant and more abundant moisture during its growth. Commercial pro-&#13;
duction of jute fiber is concentrated in the Asian Sub-Continent; India&#13;
and Bangladesh account for over 80% of the volume of world trade. Thailand&#13;
is the third largest producer, 1/ followed by Burma, Nepal and Brazil.&#13;
8.        Jute is mostly used to manufacture cloth (hessian or burlap) for&#13;
bags and sacks (including woolpacks and cotton-bale covers), backing for&#13;
tufted carpets and industrial wrapping material. Jute yarn is also used in&#13;
woven carpet backing and cordage. Sacks and bags are by far the most&#13;
1/ Thailand produces mostly a jute-like fiber, kenaf, which is coarser than&#13;
jute and it is only suitable in sack-making. Substantial amounts of&#13;
this fiber are also produced in India where it is known as mesta.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
important end-use for jute in all major consuming areas. In industrialized&#13;
countries, however, backing for both tufted and woven carpets is a very&#13;
important market for jute.&#13;
9.        Practically all the jute fiber grown in India is processed&#13;
locally and about 60% of it is exported in manufactured form. Bangladesh,&#13;
on the contrary, processes only about 45% of its annual jute production.&#13;
The remainder is exported as raw fiber. Until very recently, Thailand&#13;
exported production in fiber form well over 50% of its production. Burma&#13;
and Nepal are almost exclusively raw jute fiber exporters. Bangladesh&#13;
dominates the jute fiber export market: its exports account for 85% of&#13;
total world export of jute and for 60% of total world exports of jute and&#13;
jute-like fibers. Despite the growth of Thai kenaf exports during the mid-&#13;
and late 1960s, the traditional quasi-monopoly position enjoyed by Bangla-&#13;
desh in world jute export markets has not been seriously challenged. Burma&#13;
and Nepal are too small as exporters to influence the raw jute market to&#13;
any considerable extent. The world market for jute manufactures -- tra-&#13;
ditionally dominated by India -- is now almost evenly shared by India and&#13;
Bangladesh. Thailand only very recently became a sizeable exporter of jute&#13;
manufactures.&#13;
10.       Industrialized countries account for about 30% total world jute&#13;
consumption, developing countries for about 40% and centrally planned&#13;
economies for the remainder. However, while the latter are largely self-&#13;
sufficient in jute, 1/ industrialized countries do not have any indigenous&#13;
supply and are, therefore, the main importers of raw jute (about 60% of&#13;
1/ The centrally planned economies of Europe import some raw jute as well&#13;
as finished products. China is totally self-sufficient.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
world total) and manufactures (55% of world total). Among developing coun-&#13;
tries, India is the largest single consumer of jute (over 60% of the total).&#13;
Among the industrialized countries, both Western Europe and Japan have a&#13;
sizeable jute industry that relies on imports from Bangladesh and Thailand.&#13;
The US and Canada, on the contrary, have practically no domestic processing&#13;
industry and rely almost exclusively on imports of finished products from&#13;
India and Bangladesh. Imports of raw jute are duty free in all industria-&#13;
lized countries. Imports of manufactures are duty free in the US, but sub-&#13;
ject to tariff and some quantitative restrictions in Japan, Western Europe&#13;
and Oceania.&#13;
11.       The position of jute as the dominant fiber input for basic cloths&#13;
and cordage products began to be challenged in the mid-1960s by textile poly-&#13;
olefins. Polypropylene, a synthetic resin obtained by the polymerisation of&#13;
propylene, soon emerged as the most important substitute for jute. It had&#13;
very desirable technical properties -- high tensility stiffness, impact&#13;
resistance, and low weight, as well as low production costs, since its basic&#13;
raw material -- propylene -- was a by-product of oil refineries. Polypropy-&#13;
lene could easily be extruded into tapes and filaments from which suitable&#13;
cloth for bags and carpet backing was made. Economies of scale and tech-&#13;
nological improvements progressively reduced polypropylene resin costs (and&#13;
prices) in the 1960s. The polypropylene cloth industry expanded rapidly in&#13;
Western Europe, Japan and the US and penetrated very successfully almost all&#13;
the traditional jute markets (bags, sacks, carpet backing and cordage).&#13;
12.       Polypropylene resin is now almost a perfect substitute for jute&#13;
fiber in most uses. Its supply is abundant in all industrialized countries&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
and its processing technology is well established and readily available. Jute&#13;
prices, relative to those of polypropylene resin are the most important&#13;
factor affecting the substitution process between these two textile materials.&#13;
Jute (and for that matter polypropylene) demand, however, is for the most&#13;
part derived demand. Substitution, in response to changes in relative prices,&#13;
takes place slowly. Technical constraints -- as well as price expectations --&#13;
slow down the substitution process. Demand for jute as an input in textile&#13;
manufacturing is, therefore, price inelastic in the short term. In the&#13;
longer run, as capital stock is replaced, substitution takes place quite&#13;
easily and jute demand is very sensitive to relative price changes. 1/&#13;
13.       In developing countries, the demand picture is more varied.   In&#13;
the main jute producing countries -- India, Bangladesh and Thailand --&#13;
synthetic substitution is virtually non-existent. In Latin America, other&#13;
Asian countries and to a lesser extent in Africa, polypropylene resin is&#13;
available, but it is often imported and subject to import duties and other&#13;
restrictions. The processing technology, moreover, is less accessible and&#13;
the structure of demand for end-products (absolute dominance of demand for&#13;
sacks and bags) is such that price elasticities -- in both the short and&#13;
the long run -- are much lower than in industrialized countries.&#13;
14.       Raw jute supply -- which is geographically very concentrated --&#13;
depends to a large extent on jute prices and on those of alternative crops.&#13;
In both Bangladesh and West Bengal jute competes for land with rice and the&#13;
annual planting decisions is strongly influenced by expected (relative)&#13;
1/ There are very few recent econometric studies of jute and even fewer&#13;
econometric estimates of price elasticities of demand, given the novelty&#13;
of the substitution process and the enormous difficulties that are en-&#13;
countered by researchers in getting the necessary consumption and price&#13;
data by end-use. The little econometric evidence that is available --&#13;
particularly for the US market -- indicates that jute demand is quite&#13;
sensitive to relative price changes. See Grilli and Morrison [1974].&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
prices. In the Northeast of Thailand, where most of the fiber is grown,&#13;
kenaf competes for land with cassava, sugarcane, groundnuts and maize.&#13;
Cassava has become in recent years the single most important substitute&#13;
crop in kenaf growing areas. Jute yields are notoriously subject to weather-&#13;
induced random fluctuations.&#13;
15.       Jute and jute goods prices fluctuate considerably from year to&#13;
year. 1/ The accepted wisdom is that supply instability has generated&#13;
over time large market price fluctuations that have stimulated the search&#13;
for and development of substitutes for jute in consuming countries. This&#13;
diagnosis has added impetus to the request made by jute producing countries&#13;
for market price stabilization measures. While the two countries most de-&#13;
pendent on jute exports (Bangladesh and India) did in the past call for&#13;
price stabilization on familiar macro.economic grounds, in recent times&#13;
they have stressed the importance of a greater degree of price stability for&#13;
jute and jute products as a disincentive to further synthetic substitution.&#13;
II. SUPPLY OF RAW JUTE&#13;
16.       There have been many studies addressed to the question of the re-&#13;
sponsiveness of jute (and kenaf) producers to changing prices. Fortunately,&#13;
most of these studies have been reviewed recently by Askari and Cummings&#13;
[1976]. Producers have been shown (in the fraipework of the Nerlove adap-&#13;
tive expections model) to be strongly, but generally inelastically, re-&#13;
sponsive to changing observed, real or relative prices of jute.&#13;
1/ Raw jute accounts for at least 50% of the production costs of hessian&#13;
and carpet bgcking cloth whose prices are directly affected by varia-&#13;
tions in the costs of the fiber. This applies to both jute producing&#13;
and jute importing countries. Jute mills in India, Bangladesh and Thai-&#13;
land compete with overseas mills for their fiber supply. See Grilli and&#13;
Morrison [1974]&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
17.       The available results are generally deficient in treating the&#13;
producer's responsiveness to changing risk -- a consideration intuitively&#13;
important in an exploration of stabilization. Exceptions are the studies&#13;
of Behrman [1968] on Thai kenaf and the preliminary investigation of&#13;
Sengupta and Sen [19691 on Indian jute. These studies employed, respec-&#13;
tively, arbitrary moving-average standard deviation variables, and a port-&#13;
folio selection model to grapple with the issue of farmers' adjustments&#13;
to risk.&#13;
18.       The recent work of Just [1974, 1975, 1977] has provided a fresh&#13;
general methodology for dealing with supply behavior under risk. His&#13;
methodology seems the one available that is pertinent to the present study.&#13;
Accordingly, we have attempted to glean a consistent set of data bearing&#13;
on jute and kenaf supply and have applied the Just methods to these data.&#13;
19.       Essentially, the Just approach is to add second moments of ex-&#13;
planatory variables (such as prices) to the first moments that feature in&#13;
the traditional Nerlove model of adaptive expectations (i.e. geometrically&#13;
distributed lag functions). The first moment, or subjective expected value,&#13;
E, in this model depends on a stable adjustment parameter a and can be viewed&#13;
as a geometrically weighted sum of past observations on a random variable&#13;
X as in&#13;
(la)          Et(a)                  k aC (-a)xt--&#13;
t  ~   kOt-1-k&#13;
or as an exponentially weighted moving average, as in&#13;
(lb)          Et(a)= a X       +  (1 - a) E     (a)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
20.       The analogous second moment, or subjective variance, V, depends&#13;
not only on a (and E(a)) but also on a further stable adjustment parameter&#13;
$ for the geometrical weighting of past "observations" on variance&#13;
(squared deviations from means) as&#13;
co&#13;
(2a)        Vt(a,a)  =       (1 -   k) k(Xt-lk     Et-l-k)2&#13;
or equivalently,&#13;
(2b)        V (a,c)  =                 E(X  _  2 +    (1 2        (a,O&#13;
Covariances can be formulated in an identical way. Such first and second&#13;
moments can then be used as explanatory variables in estimating equations&#13;
which relate a decision variable to previous observed values of influential&#13;
variables.&#13;
21.        For example, suppose for the moment that planned jute output&#13;
is represented by acreage planted, Ht, and that producers are influenced in&#13;
this decision only by the mean and variance of "jute" (kenaf in Thailand) price&#13;
A&#13;
P.   Then one   simple model for a jute supply function is&#13;
(3a)        H    =  a   +   a1  Ejt (a)  +  a2 Vjt (   ) + ut&#13;
where E   and V.    represent observed means and variances of&#13;
jt      Jt&#13;
the price of jute and ut is a well-behaved disturbance term. This par-&#13;
ticular equation is linear in the parameters   ai  and so, for given   a&#13;
and a, can be estimated by ordinary least squares (OLS) regression analysis.&#13;
Indeed, one estimation method is to search the feasible space, 0 &lt; a&#13;
6&lt; 1, for those values of the adjustment parameters that give the minimum&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
sum of squares in the OLS equation.    If ut  is assumed to be normally dis-&#13;
tributed, this is a maximum likelihood search procedure. More generally,&#13;
non-linear least squares regression analysis can be used to estimate&#13;
a 1,   and the   ai  simultaneously.&#13;
22.       However, there is another difficulty to be confronted in empirical&#13;
work. Sample data will only be available for a finite (probably all too&#13;
brief) series of observations whereas the above equations implicitly in-&#13;
volve infinite series. Just has investigated several methods of dealing&#13;
with this difficulty. We review only that one we used empirically&#13;
to derive estimates for the base-year means and variances. There is no&#13;
way to avoid assigning some years as "prior" and later ones as     "for regres-&#13;
sion".  The prior year observations give the initial estimates of mean, E , as&#13;
r N              1-_lNk&#13;
k           ~~~k&#13;
(4)  E                  (1-              (1-)       X (+k)&#13;
K=O                K=O&#13;
where the N observations are   X 1  X     2    X-(N+1)&#13;
used as "priors"   on the observed explanatory variables.&#13;
23.       It is best to estimate the prior variance in the process of estimat-&#13;
ing the other parameters and this can be accomplished by adding an additional&#13;
variable to, for example, (3a), namely&#13;
(3b)    Ht =a   + a   E. (ax)  +  a  V  (cx,~)  +  a (l -  t +  t&#13;
(3) t  O  1  jt          2  jt            3&#13;
where Ejt now depends on Eo , and the additional coefficient may be inter-&#13;
preted as embodying the prior variance, since a    =    V . The estimation is&#13;
similar to Dhrymes' [1971, p.98] truncation remainder procedure.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
24.       This approach was applied to data from Bangladesh, India and&#13;
Thailand 1/ in several variants depending on: the surrogate assumed for&#13;
the decision variable (i.e. quantity supplied or area harvested since&#13;
neither planned output nor area sown is available); the particular series&#13;
of prices; the periods taken as "observation" and "prior to observation";&#13;
and the functional specification of the supply equation.&#13;
25.       The specification finally selected is about the simplest one&#13;
consistent with the objectives of this study. It recognized substitution&#13;
with the major competing crop, "rice", (rice in Bangladesh and India, sugar-&#13;
cane, maize and cassava in Thailand -- designated by the subscript r in&#13;
what follows), while restrictively focusing on the price variability of&#13;
jute growing. However, preliminary results suggested that variance of&#13;
"rice" price and covariance of jute and "rice" prices were unimportant in&#13;
determining jute supply. The chosen specification also minimizes problems&#13;
associated with the failure to deflate the observed prices to account for&#13;
inflation. The dependent variable, is acreage of jute. The key exploratory&#13;
variables are the ratio of subjective expected prices (which avoids infla-&#13;
tion accounting), and the dimensionless measure of variability that depends&#13;
on first and second moments of jute price. Specifically the acreage equation&#13;
is :      (4)    t   a0 + a1 (E jt/Ert) + a2 Cjt + a3(1-)  + ut&#13;
where, for brevity, the adjustment parameters and regional subscripts are&#13;
dropped, and C.   is the coefficient of variation of jute price, C + (V )     /E&#13;
21t                                                  t     t     t&#13;
1/ Supply of raw jute from the smaller producers is considered as exogenous&#13;
in this model. Lack of data prevented its explicit modeling.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
26.         The econometric estimates are summarized in Table 1. 1/     For all&#13;
three countries, the coefficients have the expected signs. Acreage responds&#13;
positively to expected price of jute relative to "rice" and negatively to&#13;
increased variance in jute prices. In terms of adjustment speeds, the mean&#13;
time lag is longer for price variance than for relative expected prices in&#13;
each country.&#13;
27.         The separate modeling of yields leads to a multiplicative risk&#13;
specification which, as argued by Hazell and Scandizzo [1975], is a most&#13;
natural and appropriate specification for a risky supply function. For un-&#13;
known reasons, jute yields early in the observation period exhibit irregular&#13;
patterns that seem of dubious relevance to present-day production. The pat-&#13;
tern of the most recent 14 years of yields (up to 1974/75) is summarized by&#13;
a small positive trend and a disturbance term, N(S), that is normally and&#13;
independently distributed with zero mean and standard deviation S. Thus,&#13;
defining YEAR as the calendar year of the first half of the crop year minus&#13;
1900, we estimated the following yield equations:&#13;
(5a)   ylt  =   1.100  +  (2.75)  10     YEAR  +  N(0.109)      (India)&#13;
(5b)   y2t  =   0.779  +  (6.67)   10    YEAR  +  N(0.117)   (Bangladesh)&#13;
2t ~ ~ ~  ~  ~~-&#13;
(5c)   y3   =    .199  +  (.7)  10     YEAR  +  N(O.0121)    (Thailand)&#13;
where  Yit    is yield in tons/hectare of raw jute.&#13;
28.       In implementing them in the model, the residual variation in the&#13;
price response functions was also modeled explicitly by assuming the dis-&#13;
turbance term, ut, in (4) to be normally distributed with mean zero and&#13;
standard deviation equal to the standard error of the estimate of the&#13;
respective equations.&#13;
1/ Data on production and prices used in estimating the supply equations for&#13;
the three jute exporting countries are given in Tables 6, 7, and 8.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
Table  1      Estimated Parameters of .Jute Acreage Response Equations&#13;
INDIA        BANGLADESH      TIIAILAND&#13;
Dependent Variable                             Acreage         Acreage        Acreage&#13;
Number of Observations&#13;
Pre-observation sample size-/                2               2              4&#13;
(years)                            (1950/51-      (1950/51-       (1953/54-&#13;
1951/52)       1951/52)       1956/57)&#13;
Observation sample size                     23              23             19&#13;
(years)                            (1952/53-      (1952/53-       (1956/57-&#13;
1974/75)       1974/75        1975/76)&#13;
Estimated Coefficients and&#13;
(Standard Errors)&#13;
Mean adjustment         a                   .793           .372           .708&#13;
(.104)         (.078)          (.331)&#13;
Variance adjustment                         .287           .081           .133&#13;
(.077)         (.051)          (.113)&#13;
Coefficients            a                   422             612           2425&#13;
0                 (107)           (243)         (1009)&#13;
a1                  275            670             411&#13;
(71)          (244)           (234)&#13;
a2                 -992          -2742           -7200&#13;
(276)         (1139)         (5552)&#13;
*3                  -22           -602           -3222&#13;
3                  (77)           (272)         (1211)&#13;
Coefficient of determination                .72             .72            .74&#13;
Standard error of estimate                   73             100            511&#13;
Durbin-Watson Statistic                    2.34            1.79           2.18&#13;
Final Values of Variables Used as&#13;
Starting Values in Simulations&#13;
Mean of jute prices                       128.7          122.3          3529.5&#13;
Mean of competing crop prices             109.3          121.8          2093.4&#13;
Ratio of-means                             1.178           1.004           1.686&#13;
Variance of jute prices                  266.2           441.6        453285.0&#13;
Coefficient of variation of                  .1268          .1718           .1908&#13;
jute prices&#13;
1/   Used inl estimating the prior mean.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
III. THE MARKETS FOR JUTE AND JUTE'GOODS&#13;
29.       Manufacturers of jute goods represent both the demand side of the raw&#13;
jute market and the supply side of the goods market. Ideally, we would con-&#13;
sider separately each class of jute goods. But, since the source data are&#13;
not available at this level of detail, we were forced to aggregate all jute&#13;
goods into one. Data was available to differentiate country-specific in-&#13;
put ratios, y's defining the quantity input of raw jute per unit of aggregate&#13;
jute goods.&#13;
30.       Since jute goodsmanufacturing has been a competitive industry, it is&#13;
reasonable to postulate a supply function relating prices to manufactured&#13;
quantities of jute goods. Here, we are concerned with prices of raw jute,&#13;
p and jute goods, P. For simplicity, we assume a linear form which treats&#13;
the two prices symmetrically. 1/ Thus defining X as output of jute goods&#13;
and using the subscripts "i" and "t" to denote regions and time,&#13;
(6)  Xi        O a   +  a (P (1+t)        P^ (1'+^ )&#13;
In each region,relative domestic prices of raw jute and jute goods differ&#13;
from the "world" price by fixed wedges which can be a combination of taxes&#13;
and tariffs.  In equations (6), ti and   ti represent the implied ad valorem&#13;
rate on goods and raw jute respectively. 2/&#13;
1/ The linear form used is implied whenever variable costs (other than raw&#13;
jute) are a quadradic function of total production volume, and the y's&#13;
remain constant.&#13;
2/ The region breakdown and indexing scheme is:&#13;
i =   1  India&#13;
2 Bangladesh&#13;
3 Thailand&#13;
4 North America&#13;
5 Western Europe&#13;
6 Japan&#13;
7 Rest of World (excluding the centrally planned economies)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
31.        As with any industry-wide supply function, scale is determined&#13;
by implicitly holding some factor of production fixed. In our model, capital&#13;
stock is fixed in each region, a convenient simplification based on the ob-&#13;
servation that net investment in this industry has been effectively nil for quite&#13;
a few years, a trend likely to continue. Since investment decisions are not being&#13;
modeled, it is reasonable to assume rapid adjustment of production to prices,&#13;
and in (6), no distinction is made between long- and short-run response.&#13;
32.        Demand for jute goods is also modeled on a regional basis.      The&#13;
main determinant of demand (given future economic growth rates) is the&#13;
relative price of jute goods and their synthetic substitutes. As noted in&#13;
Section I, the short-run relative price elasticity is low in comparison with the long-&#13;
run elasticity. The central reason is that demand is embedded in installed&#13;
capital, only part of which turns over in any one year. Here, we assume&#13;
linear demand functions whose short-run position relative to the origin is&#13;
determined by past investments and by long-run expectations. That is,&#13;
P (1+t )&#13;
(7)        D     =   A    (a+tib&#13;
it ~ ~ ~ ~   ~~~i&#13;
Ai        scale of demand,   region i , year t&#13;
it&#13;
Pi   =    price of synthetics,   region i , year t&#13;
it&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
33.       In modeling the dynamics of the demand functions, we assume that&#13;
in each year there is exogenous growth in the market for fibers in general&#13;
(jute and the synthetics), related to expected general economic growth. In ad-&#13;
dition, a certain proportion of lute good consumers-is faced'with an investment&#13;
decision -- whether to re-invest in jute-using equipment or not. The pro-&#13;
portion of these users who opt for jute goods (and thus shift the future&#13;
demand schedule) depends on the expected future relative price of jute to&#13;
synthetics. For simplicity, we assume the growth rate of the'demand func-&#13;
tion to be a linear function of the growth rate in demand for fibers in&#13;
general and the expected future price structure. That is,&#13;
(8)            i,t+l    i,t    2   g  (i,l i-    t&#13;
Ai t             i  pil    pi,2&#13;
where gi represents the expected growth in total fiber demand in region i.&#13;
This functional form makes use of two benchmarks, Pi l    and  P i2 '&#13;
which we have independently estimated for each region.    Pi 1  represents an&#13;
upper bound on relative prices (between jute goods and synthetic substitutes),&#13;
such that demand will shrink if the expected relative price Pit, is above&#13;
this benchmark.  On the other hand,   Pi,2 represents a neutral expected price at&#13;
which jute's share of the i'th market would remain constant. We use a&#13;
adaptive expectations formulation to represent how these are formulated over&#13;
time.' 1/&#13;
1/ A similar formulation of dynamic change has been used for a model of&#13;
world oil markets by Blitzer, Meeraus, and Stoutjesdijk [1975].&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
e ~    (iX     e             P (1+t)&#13;
g9)         Pi t  =    (J-X) pi,tl    + Xi     i&#13;
34.       In the numerical simulations, we take the price of synthetics&#13;
as exogenous and do not explicitly consider the competitive reaction of&#13;
synthetics producers to jute goods stabilization policy. Lack of data&#13;
prevented a more sophisticated treatment.     However,   synthetics are pro-&#13;
duced in process industries where costs of production generally determine&#13;
price. The price of oil is thus likely to have a more crucial impact on&#13;
the price of polypropylene than buffer stock action in jute markets.&#13;
35.        In closing the model there are two world markets which must be&#13;
considered -- those for raw jute and jute goods. Within a reasonable&#13;
degree of approximation, buffer stock operations occur in the market for&#13;
raw jute only. Thus, equilibrium in the raw jute market implies:&#13;
(10)     LSt +y     X~ +    E.     =  -&#13;
(10) A t  ZL Yi Xit  +Ej t  = 4_ Qi t  where&#13;
E.      represents the exogenous exports of raw jute to centrally&#13;
j,t   planned economies and&#13;
ASt , stands for stocks purchases of raw jute in year t,&#13;
Similarly, equilibrium in markets for jute goods requires that&#13;
(11)    ZDit+    Eg,t       it&#13;
Where E       represents the exogenous exports of jute goods to centrally&#13;
g,t    planned economies in year t.&#13;
36.        Equations (6) - (11) define a complete dynamic system given&#13;
values for ASt, and Qi t. The latter are provided by the stochastic supply&#13;
functions (4) and (5). That is,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
(12)      Qit     ~ Yit Hit    '&#13;
where the bars above the right-hand symbols signify the actual randomly&#13;
selected values.&#13;
37.       Traditionally, stocking behavior has been difficult to&#13;
model. In most econometrically estimated commodity models, some function,&#13;
often with price as the dependent variable, is estimated on the basis of&#13;
goodness-of-fit.   This procedure would not work for this study. In the first place,&#13;
we are concerned with a 10-15 year horizon, and in that period it is quite un-&#13;
likely that any estimated stocking parameters would remain constant. More-&#13;
over, past data yields behavioral information on a period without pre-&#13;
known outside intervention. Introduction of an international stabilization policy&#13;
would almost certainly affect significantly private stocking behavior.&#13;
38.       There is no  entirely satisfactory way out of this dilemma.&#13;
The procedure chosen in our simulations is to introduce buffer stocking&#13;
rules which generally take the form:&#13;
(13)      p   C p^  &lt;_&#13;
t -   t -    t&#13;
where the upper and lower bounds are determined by past prices and pre-set policies.&#13;
With this formulation, stock changes take place only if one of the inequalities&#13;
in (13) is binding. While admittedly this is a mechanical procedure, so are&#13;
most internationally negotiated stabilization rules.&#13;
IV. SIMULATION RESULTS&#13;
39.       A base case simulation, covering a fifteen year horizon for a deterministic&#13;
situation (no uncertainty in yield or acreage response) was first conducted to assess&#13;
at least qualitatively the behavior of the model against existing expectations&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
concerning the future of the world jute economy. 1/ The results for the&#13;
deterministic base case are summarized in Table 2 and details are found&#13;
in Tables 9, 10 and 11. 2/ They broadly conform to the current IBRD assess-&#13;
ment of the future of jute: total demand for jute goods is likely to grow&#13;
at only 1% per year in the medium-term and almost 70% of the increased demand&#13;
comes from the producing countries themselves. The long-run average price&#13;
for jute fiber ($298/ton in real terms), though roughly competitive with&#13;
that of polypropylene resin, still implies a loss in jute's share of the&#13;
world fiber market on both technical and non-price economic grounds (e.g.&#13;
self-sufficiency and import substitution).&#13;
40.       Somewhat more surprising is the need for some price stabilization&#13;
even in the deterministic simulation. Although the magnitudes involved&#13;
are relatively small, it seems clear that, quite apart from stochastic dis-&#13;
turbances, the dynamic adjustment process of the market is a source of price&#13;
instability (Table 2). This is generally the case with adaptive expecta-&#13;
tions. If all expectations were rational, the cause of instability could be&#13;
put more exclusively on the stochastic variables.&#13;
1/ This requires that equation (13) be modified to reflect existing sta-&#13;
bilization behavior. Indeed, the inelasticity of supply and demand in&#13;
the short-run necessitates that some stock adjustment exist -- and in&#13;
reality stock trading and holding does occur. Rather than try to esti-&#13;
mate a complex function, we merely try to replicate the observation&#13;
that prices rarely vary more than 15% per year.&#13;
2/ The simulation results highlight an interesting aspect of raw jute trade&#13;
between India and Bangladesh: the unrecorded imports of raw jute into&#13;
India. A comparison between Indian needs of raw jute for the manufac-&#13;
turing of jute goods -- as shown by Table 9 -- and the domestic supply&#13;
of fiber -- shown in Table 10 -- well illustrate the order of magnitude&#13;
of the "informal" trade between the two sides of Bengal.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
41.       The major elements of the picture are changed very little when&#13;
the stochastic elements are introduced (see Table 2). Here, dynamic simu-&#13;
lations are calculated for 100 sets of random disturbances. Not surpri-&#13;
singly, considerably more stocking activity is required to maintain the&#13;
bounds on yearly price movements. On average, traders remain net sellers,&#13;
obtaining some discounted profits after deducting discounted costs. More-&#13;
over, the values of stocks-on-hand implied are numerically consistent with&#13;
known initial conditions. On balance, uncertainty leads to slightly higher&#13;
average prices, slightly lower production levels, and marginally higher dis-&#13;
counted revenue.&#13;
42.       The mean prices and quantities are calculated by averaging the&#13;
average of each of the 100 stochastic simulations. As one welfare measure,&#13;
the discounted export revenues are calculated for the three main producers.&#13;
Yearly revenues are discounted by 10% annually, noting that inflation is&#13;
not otherwise counted.&#13;
43.       During each dynamic simulation, no checks are made on whether&#13;
the buffer stock of jute has been emptied. After the last year's simula-&#13;
tion is run, the model calculates using a backward recursion what the year&#13;
0 stock would have to have been to avoid ever reducing it below zero. Using&#13;
this initial value, the time path of jute stock is calculated. The means&#13;
of these across each experiment are shown in Table 2. Starting from fairly&#13;
high initial stocks, sales are made to reduce to the mean simulation stock&#13;
size, which is the average value of stocks in all periods in each simulation.&#13;
44.       The model can be used to simulate almost any buffer stock policy.&#13;
In the context on any international agreement on jute price stabilization&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
Table  2       Summary Results of Deterministic and&#13;
Stochastic Simulations of the Model&#13;
Deterministic        Stochastic&#13;
Mean world price of raw jute      ($/MT)                       298                307&#13;
(24) /1            (38)&#13;
Mean world price of jute goods ($/MT)                          613                620&#13;
(27)               (40)&#13;
Mean raw jute production          ('000 MT)                   2429               2404&#13;
Mean goods production             ('000 MT)                   2130               2107&#13;
Total discounted revenue of       ('000 $)              10,533,998        10,862,855&#13;
exporters&#13;
Mean initial buffer stock size    ('000 MT)                    868               1169&#13;
(44)&#13;
Mean simulation stock size        ('000 MT)                    191                631&#13;
(227)              (490)&#13;
Mean change in stocks             ('000 MT)                    -56                -57&#13;
(120)              (271)&#13;
Mean absolute change in stocks    ('000 MT)                     72                199&#13;
(111)              (193)&#13;
/1 Standard deviations in parentheses where applicable or computed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
based on an internationally held and financed buffer stock, the stabiliza-&#13;
tion bounds as well as the secular trend around which prices are to be&#13;
stabilized become a matter of producer-consumer bargaining and group nego-&#13;
tiations. The potential impact of a range of reasonable stabilization rules&#13;
that an international agency might try to adopt is examined here. The alter-&#13;
natives are:&#13;
Case 1 -- Stabilize world price of raw jute within + 10% of&#13;
prior year's price;&#13;
Case 2 -- Stabilize world price of raw jute within + 7.5% of&#13;
$300 per ton;&#13;
Case 3 -- Stabilize world price of raw jute within + 7.5% of&#13;
$330 per ton;&#13;
Case 4 -- Stabilize world price of raw jute within + 7.5% of&#13;
the trend price (Pt = $315 (1.05 ).&#13;
45.       Case 1 would simply represent an attempt to reduce the amplitude&#13;
of fluctuations by following, in essence, the dynamics of the jute market&#13;
without trying to interfere with it. Case 2 can be viewed as an attempt to&#13;
stabilize prices around a long-term average of $300 per ton. The rationale&#13;
of this alternative rests, on the fact that without continued increases in&#13;
crude oil prices driving up polypropylene costs, the long term competitive&#13;
price for raw jute is likely to remain fairly constant in real terms. Cases&#13;
3 and 4 represent possible examples of stabilization together with higher&#13;
prices that are advocated by primary commodity exporting countries and&#13;
endorsed -- at least in principle -- by UNCTAD. The first can be viewed as&#13;
stabilization around a long term average price 10% above trend, while Case 4&#13;
is an attempt to stabilize prices around a moderatly increasing long-term&#13;
trend. The results of these stochastic simulations are compared with the&#13;
basic case in Table 3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
46.       In addition to the previous calculations, in each experiment&#13;
the profits of the buffer stocking operation, net of initial financing,&#13;
are determined. Letting r denote the discount rate, cl, the transactions&#13;
cost of buying or selling jute, and c2 the annual storage costs, discounted&#13;
profits = N                ^&#13;
t=  (l+r) (tl)E[_P  tASt-C 2AStl-C   St]&#13;
47.       Case 1 illustrates quite clearly the fact that lower price vola-&#13;
tility (with respect to the basic case) induces a higher and more stable&#13;
average supply of raw jute despite the slightly reduced market prices. Pro-&#13;
duction of jute goods is only marginally affected. The export revenue of&#13;
India, Bangladesh and Thailand taken together remains virtually unchanged&#13;
with respect to the basic case, but is it more stable. The buffer stock&#13;
operation is marginally profitable as on average a net seller of jute.&#13;
48.       The simulation results of Case 2 are similar, because the long-&#13;
term average price around which market prices are stabilized is very similar&#13;
to the mean price that prevails under Case 1 rules. Production of both raw&#13;
jute and jute goods and discounted total export revenue are substantially&#13;
the same as in Case 1 and so is buffer profitability; a smaller volume of&#13;
transactions reduces gross revenue, but a lower stock carryover reduces&#13;
costs by almost the same amount. The only substantial benefit that arises&#13;
to the producers is the reduction in revenue instability. The coefficient&#13;
of variation drops to 6.2%, as compared to 8.8% in Case 1 and 9.5% in the&#13;
Basic Case.&#13;
49.       Cases 3 and 4 show clearly that stringent limits exist in the&#13;
jute market to "strong" UNCTAD-type stabilization rules, i.e. price sta-&#13;
bilization accompanied by attempts to raise average prices. The simula-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
T.hle   3       S!n,ulated ITMaet of Different St.bilfration Rules&#13;
CASE   I                   CASE   2                   C'SZ  3                 CASZ   4&#13;
STABLIZA11ON                                                                                                              7.ST  5 75%StbiSztinu.5il.bltatoation&#13;
MI:                                                       %~~~~~~~~~~~~~~17 Saiiain  .7  tbl Stabil izatiStbiiztn                       arc-nd .n initial&#13;
SATISTI              '          :          5         CASE             around prior           around a co..tant          arourd a constant        i3      . '   Arng.t'&#13;
veer's price        ~~~$300/NT                  $330/MT                  5Z A,,i1y&#13;
I   Wor1d Price Ran Jute      (S/1IT)              307                295                       299                      316&#13;
P.^:CES         2                                .(38)                                (28)                     (33)                      (26)                      :65)&#13;
3   World Price Jute          ($/MT)               620                611                       613                      626                      651&#13;
4       Goods                                       (40)              (40)                      (25)                      (28)                     (29)&#13;
S    InitIl. Sirc             ('000 MT)           1169               1142                       950                      535                       549&#13;
6                                                  (44)               (60)                      (40)                      (44)                     ('.3)&#13;
7   Mean Si=ulation Size      ('000 Mr)            631                572                      442                       673                      1058&#13;
3':-F'R   3                                       (490)              (464)                     (314)                    (599)                    (1037)&#13;
STOCK        9    Chanrge In Stocks        ('000 MT)            -57                -47                       -30                        98                      23S&#13;
:0                                                 (271)              (262)                     (223)                    (248)                     (34')&#13;
11   Absolute Chan3e in        ('000 Mr)            19'i               196                       164                      201                       326&#13;
12       Stocks                                    (193)              (ISO)                     (154)                    (176)                     (253)&#13;
13   Tot.1 DIscouoted          ('000 MT)         151921             119522                   114726                   -372260                  -997701&#13;
Er.ol6ts&#13;
14   Supply of Rav Jute        ('000 UT)            917                940                       932                      955                       99S&#13;
i15                                                 (IZ6)              (119)                     (115)                    (122)                     (141)&#13;
16   Su.plv of Jute Goods      ('000-ET)           1079               1095                      1090                     1063                      1051&#13;
*ID:D'A     I 17                                                   (30)               (33)                      (2.9)                    t21)                      (10)&#13;
13    -Nrxrt Rcrox,e           ('000 S)          302205             309797                   306098                    311600                    333933&#13;
15                                    ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~(4i91)  (367221)                                          12)                     (141)&#13;
19                                                (4991)            (36722)                   (32694)                  (35456)                   (39'79)&#13;
20  Total Disceunted  ('002 S)         3738747            3823675                  3776975                   3340895                  4052051&#13;
-ot - --&#13;
21    S-nny of R.. Jute        ('00  i ME)        1118               1121                      1137                     1180                      1232                        -&#13;
- :2                                               (187)              (188)                     (14)                    (196)                     (233)&#13;
23 I S_;'ly of Jute Coods      ('000 MT)            475                403                       484                      462           j4 t9&#13;
':;0'"DES :     I                                                (26)               (25)                     (21)                      (17)                       (9)&#13;
25    Ex-,ort Reverue          ('000 S)          465018             458998                   465062                    488820                    5237!3&#13;
'61                                              (60799)            (58359)                   (52965)                  (59167)                   (87972)&#13;
27   Total Di,counted          ('000 S)         5670508            5593884                  5663808                   5952411                   6326131&#13;
E'~pott Raevene &#13;
| 2  | SJnply of Rn. Jute        ('000 mET)           369                385                       384                      390                       413&#13;
29                                                  (92)               (94)                      (91)                     (92)                      (93)&#13;
30    Supply of Jute Goods     ('000 ME)            158                158                       158                       158                      159&#13;
T`'), .UND     31                                                   (4)                (3)                       (3)                      (3)                       (3)&#13;
32    Ex'ort Revenue           ('000 5)          118435             120113                   120340                    127655                    140889&#13;
33                                               (27795)            (263SI)                   (24123)                  (25647)                   (33149)&#13;
|34   E'ota  rt Di  e-teue     (000 5)          1453599            1469023                  1471847                   1560004                   1703197&#13;
35   Su-, ?y of Raw Jute       ('000 MT)           2404               2446                      2453                     2525                      2640&#13;
36    Supplv of Jute Goods     ('000 MT)           1712               1741                      1732                      1683                     1659&#13;
TOtALS-      i37    Total Revenue             ('000 S)          885659             888909                   891502                    928076                    995534&#13;
383                                              (84218)            (78400)                   (55601)                   (67050)                 (120567)&#13;
39   Ceefficient of                               (.095)             (.088)                    (.062)                    (.072)                   (.121)&#13;
j VarIation                                                                                          1 _   _&#13;
40 f Total       5;ocverue       ('000eI       10Z955             10886583                  10912631                 11353310                  12031330&#13;
Standard dev,atlrns ln parentheses.&#13;
: oer all  3   cr-ntr:Cs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
tions indicate that the price-induced higher supply of jute is not readily&#13;
absorbed by the market either in raw form or as manufactured goods, unless&#13;
synthetic prices were to rise significantly. Price stabilization in Case 3&#13;
turns the modest bufferstock agency profit shown under the previously exa-&#13;
mined rules into a substantial loss. The agency turns from an average&#13;
seller to an average buyer and loses about $370 million over the period,&#13;
in addition to required initial capital. The losses to the buffe. stock&#13;
authority are almost exactly equal to the increment in the discounted value&#13;
of the export revenues of the three major producing countries. Bangladesh&#13;
and Thailand appear to gain relatively more than India in terms of export&#13;
revenue from this type of price intervention, mostly on account of greater&#13;
responsiveness of jute supply to the higher market prices sustained through&#13;
the action of the bufferstock authority.&#13;
50.       Stabilization of raw jute prices,even around a modestly rising&#13;
trend (1.5% per annum), implies staggering losses to the buffer-&#13;
stock authority -- almost $1 billion over the period due to heavy stock ac-&#13;
cumulation. Again the producer gains,in terms of joint export revenue,are&#13;
almost exactly equal to the losses that the bufferstock agency would incur.&#13;
This type of stabilization with rising prices appears totally un-&#13;
feasible in the jute market, unless, of course, consumers accepted should-&#13;
ering the cost and considered it a vehicle for transferring resources&#13;
to jute producers or if synthetic prices changed dramatically. 1/&#13;
51.       In addition to bufferstock policy, stochastic simulations    were&#13;
conducted to assess the effects of alternative production and trade policy&#13;
options open to the jute producers and to the international community. These&#13;
alternatives are:&#13;
1/ These runs were made in 1978; the recent oil price increases indicate&#13;
that revisions in polypropylene prices would change these results some-&#13;
what.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
Case 5 -- Raw jute costs to the mills lowered by 20% in&#13;
Bangladesh;&#13;
Case 6 -- Positive exchange rate differential of 20% granted&#13;
to jute goods in Bangladesh;&#13;
Case 7 -- Jute acreage restrictions in Bangladesh;&#13;
Case 8 -- Compensatory financing applied to jute exporters.&#13;
The results of the stochastic simulations for Cases 5, 6 and 7 are compared&#13;
to those of the Basic Case in Table 4. Simulations of Case 8 are summarized&#13;
in Table 5.&#13;
52.       Case 5 implies a subsidy of 20% to Bangladesh jute mills on their&#13;
raw jute costs. Such input subsidy stimulates production of jute goods in&#13;
Bangladesh and lowers their prices in world markets. Production of jute&#13;
goods is reduced substantially in India and marginally in Thailand. On a&#13;
world basis, however, supply of jute goods is increased. Higher overall de-&#13;
mand for raw jute in producing countries reduces export availability and&#13;
raises prices. In terms of export revenue (which increases by about $300&#13;
million over 15 years), producers as a group would gain marginally from such&#13;
a policy implemented by Bangladesh. India, however, would lose competitive-&#13;
ness in the market for jute goods and suffer a loss in export revenue, while&#13;
Bangladesh would reap almost all the benefits. The effects on Thailand are&#13;
small; her revenue position remains virtually unchanged with respect to the&#13;
Basic Case.&#13;
53.       Case 6, which is a variation of the previous one, can be thought&#13;
as an atteuptby Bangladesh to subsidize even further its production of jute&#13;
goods, and at the same time to exploit to some extent its near monopoly&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 4A      Sieulated Im&gt;act of Different Productlon and Trade Policies&#13;
CASE  5                         CASE  6                       CASE  7&#13;
POLICY                            ZtASZ              Raw Jute Cost to                 20.  Positive&#13;
S'.'.VOARY STATIS                                             CASF            Mills LoercEd 207 in           Differential Exchange          Ac-nage Re,t, 7tic.&#13;
B-gladesh           ~~Rate for Goods in              In Bangla.!,ch&#13;
W.orld Price Raw Jute    (S/.MT)                  307                      316                            320                            34&#13;
PRICES                                                           (38)                     (38)                           (38)                           (SI)          I&#13;
W.orld Price Jute        (S/l-T)                  620                     610                            603                            65i&#13;
Goods                                          (40)                     (38)                           (37)                          (5S'&#13;
Supply of Rae Jute       (000 MT)                917                     929                            934                            982&#13;
(126)                    (129)                          (187)                          (14:)&#13;
Supply of Jute Coods     ('000 MT)               1079                     996                            950                           1039&#13;
INDi'A                                                           (30)                     (42)                           (44)                           (31)&#13;
Export Revenue           ('000 $)             302205                   273028                         257264                         3279F4&#13;
(4891)                  (42003)                        (41964)                        (4829'3)&#13;
Total Discounted         ('000 5)            3738747                  3374713                        3179483                        4037438&#13;
Export Revenue&#13;
Supply of Raw Jute       ('000 MT)               1118                    1152                           1168                            93'&#13;
(187)                    (191)                          (192)                          (132)&#13;
Supply of Jute Goods     ('000 MT)                475                     626                            710                            43c&#13;
BLACSLADESH                                                      (26)                     (21)                           (29)                           (32)&#13;
Export Revenue           ('000 5)             465018                   520695                         549061                         425771&#13;
(60799)                  (64458)                        (64753)                        (45903)&#13;
Total Discounted         ('000 5)             5670508                 6348718                        6694344                        5524819&#13;
Export Revenue&#13;
Supply of Raw Jute       ('000 Mr)                369                     379                            384                            395&#13;
(92)                     (91)                           (90)                           (96)&#13;
Supply of Jute Goods     ('000 Ki)                158                     152                            149                            159&#13;
T!:.% Z W7                                                        (4)                      (3)                            (3)                            (4)&#13;
Export Revenue           ('000 S)              118435                  120700                         121442                         139722&#13;
(27795)                  (28812)                        (28781)                        (35857)&#13;
TotEa t Discounted       (000 5)              1453599                 1482967                         1493533                       1698042&#13;
Supply of Raw Jute       ('000 iE)               2404                    2460                           2486                           2309&#13;
Supply of Juta Goods     ('000 K?)               1712                    1774                           1809                            1536&#13;
Total Revenue            ('000 $)              885659                  914423                          927768                         893479&#13;
TOTALS*                                                       (84218)                  (88055)                        (87220)                        (79130)&#13;
Coefficfent of                                  (.095)                   (.096)                         (.094)                         (.OM9)&#13;
Variation&#13;
Total Discounted&#13;
Export levenue        S 0=2.e2           108678559                                               1137361                        109503e2&#13;
*    Standard deviations in parentheses.&#13;
Totals over all   3  countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
position in raw jute exports.iI The overall impact of such a policy is&#13;
not very different from Case 5: total discounted export revenue is raised&#13;
only marginally since the fall in jute good prices almost completely off-&#13;
sets the increase in raw jute prices. The distribution of revenue gains,&#13;
however, is further changed in favor of Bangladesh and against India.&#13;
Thailand remains virtually unaffected.&#13;
54.       Case 7 showsthat jute acreage restrictions by Bangladesh 2/ would&#13;
increase the prices of both raw jute and jute goods without raising the&#13;
joint revenue of the three major producers with respect to that of the Basic&#13;
Case. Bangladesh would shoulder the cost of such a policy, with its ex-&#13;
port revenues decreasing as a result of reduced raw jute exports. India&#13;
and Thailand, on the other hand, would both gain in terms of revenue since&#13;
their production and exports of raw jute and jute goods increase in response&#13;
to the higher prices caused by acreage restrictions in Bangladesh.&#13;
55.       In Case 8, a compensatory financing scheme for jute exporters is&#13;
tested. Here the producing countries borrow from some lender (presumably&#13;
the IMF) whenever their export revenues fall short of the average revenue&#13;
of the Basic Case by more than 10%, and pay back in years when export re-&#13;
venue is above average. As shown in Table 5, at a modestly subsidized in-&#13;
terest rate of 3% the total discounted cost-of the plan would be very small&#13;
requiring total financing of $235 million and average drawings of $85 mil-&#13;
lion. Bangladesh would be the likely heaviest and India the likely lightest&#13;
user of the facility. At an interest rate of 8% the facility would become&#13;
self-financing, but the total financing required would increase to $275 million&#13;
1/ A differential exchange rate in favor of goods exports implies a&#13;
"tariff" on raw jute exports.&#13;
2/ Acreage is held to the 1972-75 average.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- .29 -&#13;
Table  5      Compensatory Financing for Jute Exporters&#13;
(Million $)&#13;
Rate of Interest&#13;
.03                            .08&#13;
Percent                        Percent&#13;
Men Change                 Men     Change&#13;
Mean      Main     in Mean     Mean     Man      in Mean&#13;
Maximum                        Maximum   Renu&#13;
Debt      Debt     Revenue     Debt      Debt    Revinthe&#13;
with                           wt&#13;
Respect to                     Respect to&#13;
Basic Case                     Basic Case&#13;
INDIA            15.3       61.6       1.2      16.9      68.8        1.2&#13;
BANGLADESH       47.9      110.8       -.12     64.9     133.4        -.3&#13;
THAILAND         22.2       62.6       1.3      27.7       72.5       1.1&#13;
TOTAL             85.4     235.0        .5     109.5      274.7        .4&#13;
Average&#13;
Profits of                  -4.88                           1.13&#13;
Finance&#13;
Facility&#13;
Before&#13;
Coefficient of   Compensatory                 .095                           .095&#13;
Variation of     Scheme&#13;
Mean Export&#13;
Revenue of&#13;
Jute Exporting   Compensatory                 .063                           .061&#13;
Countries        Scheme&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
and average drawings to $110 million. The impact of the scheme on total&#13;
export revenue is on balance positive, but while India and Thailand would&#13;
marginally benefit from it, Bangladesh would experience a marginal loss&#13;
over the period. There is no straightforward way to evaluate the benefits&#13;
from increased revenue stability. If this is considered important, com-&#13;
pensatory finance would seem to be the cost effective strategy. 1/&#13;
IV. CONCLUDING REMARKS&#13;
56.       In this study, we sought to investigate international policy to&#13;
stabilize jute markets using a simple and easily estimatible dynamic model.&#13;
Since the model has not been exhaustively tested, our conclusions are ten-&#13;
tative but we feel encouraging and reasonable.&#13;
57.       Since risk plays a quantitatively significant role in determin-&#13;
ing the acreage that farmers plant, it is important in analyzing price sta-&#13;
bilization policies to explicitly model this part of farmer reaction. As&#13;
expected, price variance carries a negative coefficient in all cases.&#13;
While further econometric improvements can be made and alternative expec-&#13;
tations behavior tested, the variance factor will likely remain an impor-&#13;
tant endogenous variable in modeling commodities like jute. The simple&#13;
formulation represented by equation (4) has worked satisfactorily for our&#13;
simulations in terms of reproducing past behavior. 2/&#13;
1/ We hasten to note that these calculations are based on particular&#13;
stochastic assumptions. If the underlying probability distributions&#13;
are much different from these, the results could be different. Spe-&#13;
cific numbers reported here should be interpreted cautiously, being&#13;
expected values of random variables.&#13;
2/ Details available from authors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
58.       Jute is seen as a classic example of markets with low short-&#13;
run and high long-run elasticities. The internal dynamics are never in&#13;
complete equilibrium, as demonstrated in the deterministic version of&#13;
the base case, because the expectations of buyers, manufacturers, and&#13;
farmers differ and adjust at different speeds to new prices. 1/ Not&#13;
only will a jute buffer stock agency have to deal with agricultural&#13;
uncertainties and business cycles, but also with the internal cycles of&#13;
the jute markets themselves. This implies that a complete market model&#13;
is needed to calculate the costs and benefits of any proposed policy.&#13;
59.       Cases 1 and 2 clearly indicate that a certain amount of sta-&#13;
bilization is feasible and might even be profitable for the buffer stock&#13;
agency. However, the net financial gains to the major jute producers is&#13;
quite modest, especially when viewed in light of the high level of buffer&#13;
stocks which would be required as an up-side risk hedge. It would seem&#13;
more difficult, and perhaps impossible, to both stabilize and raise prices&#13;
above the comparable synthetic substitute price. The effects of reduced&#13;
price risk and higher actual prices can easily lead to much over-production.&#13;
Moreover, jute goods would begin to lose their share of the total fibers&#13;
market quite rapidly. While the specific numbers would change if redone&#13;
at 1979 oil prices, the qualitative conclusion remains.&#13;
60.       In terms of alternative forms of policy, the choices are in-&#13;
numerable. The cases we chose for illustration indicate that there is modest&#13;
scope for collective action in reducing output a bit, but the total effects&#13;
1/ We do not wish to debate whether a perfectly rational speculator could&#13;
achieve stability, nor why this has not occurred. We take for granted&#13;
that it has not.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
are hard to measure, since higher prices lead eventually to reduced mar-&#13;
ket shares. From the narrow point of view of export revenue, compensatory&#13;
financing appears cost-effective when compared with direct market inter-&#13;
vention.&#13;
61.       While far from being fully satisfactory, we feel the simple&#13;
modeling approach used here, combining econometrics with industrial exper-&#13;
tise and bit of mdoel builders' glue, is a useful way to approach commodity&#13;
stabilization. By focusing on the dynamics of supply and demand, the&#13;
adjustment to the stabilization policy itself can be examined. In reduc-&#13;
ing the number of parameters to the minimum, we were able to see which&#13;
were important and in need of more careful estimation. Since a model like&#13;
this can be developed from existing statistics in only a brief time and&#13;
easily can be updated and modified, we feel the methodology offers great&#13;
promise for medium-term analysis of other commodity markets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
Table  6      Production and Prices in India&#13;
(2)            (3)            (4)             (5)&#13;
Agricultural       Area         Quantity       Harvest       Harvest Aus     Jute/Paddy&#13;
Year         Harvested     Ilarvested    Jute Prices     Paddy Prices   Price Ratio&#13;
Units:         ('000           ('000       (Rupees Per    (Rupees Per&#13;
Hectares)    Metric Tons)     Quintal)        Quintal)&#13;
1950-51          561.4          586.6         99.55           38.32           2.6&#13;
1951-52          762.2          829.8        114.12           37.93           3.0&#13;
1952 53          701.0          810.6         56.99           35.18           1.6&#13;
1953-54          484.0          567.6          59.42          29.91           2.0&#13;
1954-55          470.1          508.4         58.73           25.80           2.3&#13;
1955-56          684.5          749.3         60.36           30.24           2.0&#13;
1956-57          772.2          756.7         61.81           31.08           2.0&#13;
1957-58          705.0          734.9         61.37           35.71           1.7&#13;
1958-59          732.9          935.8         57.18           34.23           1.6&#13;
1959-60          681.5          825.3         58.06           34.32           1.7&#13;
1960-61          618.6          726.9        104.65           33.23           3.1&#13;
1961-62          923.3         1144.0         89.25           35.11           2.5&#13;
1962-63          852.8          982.4          73.94          36.44           2.0&#13;
1963-64          867.6         1090.9          82.59          39.07           2.1&#13;
1964-65          838.5         1083.6         94.97           44.19           2.1&#13;
1965-66          753.3          803.4        110.69           56.65           2.0&#13;
1966-67          796.7          964.2        114.31           70.76           1.6&#13;
1967-68          885.2         1146.4          98.53          88.26           1.1&#13;
1968-69          527.6          531.5        131.23           73.51           1.8&#13;
1969-70          762.0         1009.0        127.50           71.88           1.8&#13;
1970-71          743.2          879.9        145.22           73.90           2.0&#13;
1971-72          818.1         1027.9        130.37           77.86           1.7&#13;
1972-73          700.2          896.1        146.27           81.45           1.8&#13;
1973-74          792.8         1119.7        124.82          116.82           1.1&#13;
1974-75          664.3          804.7         --              --              --&#13;
1975-76          586.8          803.1         __               _              _--&#13;
Sources:  (1)    Indian Jute Manufacturers Association.&#13;
(2)    Intcrnational Jute Manufacturers Association.&#13;
(3)    IBRD (Weighted by State Jute Acreage).&#13;
(4)    IBRD (Weighted by State Jute Acreage).&#13;
(5)    Column (3) * Colulmn (4).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
Table  7      Production and Prices in Bangladesh&#13;
(1)            (2)           (3)            (4)            (5)&#13;
Agricultural       Area        Quantity       Farm Gate       Paddy        Jute/Paddy&#13;
Year     |larvested       Harvested      Jute Prices      Prices      Price Ratio&#13;
Units:         ('000          ('000        (Tk. Per       (Tk. Per&#13;
Hlectares)   Metric Tons)    Quintal)       Quintal)&#13;
1950-51          692.4         807.8         50.91          34.28           1.5&#13;
1951-52          719.9        1148.7         69.00          39.12           1.8&#13;
1952-53          771.6        1401.5         27.45          37.14            .7&#13;
1953-54          390.6         454.0         41.53          27.19           1.5&#13;
1954-55          503.1         845.9         41.91          19.46           2.2&#13;
1955-56          661.5        1014.6         50.56          36.59           1.4&#13;
1956-57          497.9        1000.4         64.55          55.82           1.2&#13;
1957-58          632.4        1034.3         53.75          46.76           1.2&#13;
1958-59          618.5        1088.7         42.87          44.99           1.0&#13;
1959-60          556.5         973.0         56.00          46.90           1.2&#13;
1960-61          614.2        1020.5        106.27          43.40          2.4&#13;
1961-62          833.3        1264.3         66.66          44.91           1.5&#13;
1962-63          697.3         928.5         58.81          47.95           1.2&#13;
1963-64          688.0         997.8         60.34          42.18           1.4&#13;
1964-65          671.0         976.1         84.32          44.32           1.9&#13;
1965-66          845.8        1154.6         73.39          52.46           1.4&#13;
1966-67          875.6        1161.1         96.54          68.52           1.4&#13;
1967-68          970.9        1242.7         73.90          61.27           1.2&#13;
1968-69          878.2        1043.9         91.13          68.20           1.3&#13;
1969-70          997.2        1301.0         79.79          67.49           1.2&#13;
1970-71          917.8        1242.6         94.18          66.43           1.4&#13;
1971-72          694.0         777.9        103.96          83.99           1.2&#13;
1972-73          896.3        1172.5        140.88         120.27           1.2&#13;
1973-74          888.9        1088.6        141.50         175.32            .8&#13;
1974-75          607.0         720.0         --             --             --&#13;
1975-76          526.0         816.0         __             __             __&#13;
Sources:            1950 to ].960; Statistical Abstract of East Pakistan&#13;
(1)&gt;.(2);  1960 to 1970: Statistical Digest of Bangladesh&#13;
1970 on:      IBRD&#13;
(3):   Pakistan Jute Board&#13;
(4):   IBRD&#13;
(5):   Column (3)  Colunin (4)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
Table  8:    Production and Prices in Thailand&#13;
(1)           (2)            (3)           (4)           (5)&#13;
Average        Composite     Ratio of&#13;
Agricultural      Area         Quantity     Price Good     Competing      Kenaf to&#13;
Year        Harvested     Harvested    Grade Kenaf     Crop Price    Composite&#13;
Bangkok__                    _ _ _ _ _ _&#13;
('000        (BAHT Per      (BAHT Per&#13;
Units:       ('000 RAI)   Metric Tons)  Metric Ton)    Metric Ton)                l&#13;
1954-55          --             __          2850.0         569.6          5.0&#13;
1955-56          __             __          3040.0         542.9          5.6&#13;
1956-57          __             __          2590.0         509.9          5.1&#13;
1957-58          --             --          2300.0          596.9         3.9&#13;
1958-59         127.5           32.0        2243.0          630.8         3.6&#13;
1959-60         278.3           55.0        3195.7          679.4         4.7&#13;
1960-61         877.0          187.0        3592.5          764.7         4.7&#13;
1961-62        1720.4          351.0        2342.6          654.0         3.6&#13;
1962-63         711.7          148.0        3732.6          695.0         5.4&#13;
1963-64         957.5          220.0        2849.8          621.0         4.6&#13;
1964-65        1365.4          310.0        3018.3          650.4         4.6&#13;
1965-66        1870.0          374.0        3311.0          701.7         4.7&#13;
1966-67        3314.1          672.0        1974.6          885.4         2.2&#13;
1967-68        1400.0          280.0        2525.8          809.0         3.1&#13;
1968-69         750.0          150.0        3040.0          971.8         3.1&#13;
1969-70        1931.5          350.0        2966.7         1023.6         2.9&#13;
1970-71        1500.0          300.0        3427.6         1106.5         3.1&#13;
1971-72        1750.0          350.0        4690.1         952.3          4.9&#13;
1972-73        2950.0          590.0        4111.9         1296.4         3.2&#13;
1973-74        2205.0          441.0        3270.0         1967.2         1.7&#13;
1974-75        1800.0          360.0        4064.7         2237.0         1.8&#13;
1975-76        1250.0          250.0        4230.5         1973.3         2.1&#13;
Sources:&#13;
(1)  : IBRD.&#13;
(2)  : IBRD.&#13;
(3)  : National Bank of Thailand.&#13;
(4)  : Composite of Maize and Cassava weighted by acreage in&#13;
Northeastern Thailand -- IBRD.&#13;
(5)  : Column (3) - Column (4).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table    9       Results of Deterministic Simulation          (Basic Case)&#13;
Supply of               Supply of               Supply of              World Price              World Price&#13;
Simulation          Raw Jute in              Raw Jute in             Raw Jute in            of Jute Goods            of Raw Jute&#13;
Year                 India               Bangladesh                Thailand&#13;
('000 MT)               ('000 MT)                ('000 MT)                ($/MT)                  ($/MT)&#13;
1                  940                      935                     463                     556                     260&#13;
2                  835                      911                     264                     611                     299&#13;
3                  889                      982                     311                     654                     344&#13;
4                  955                    1088                      361                     623                     314&#13;
5                  946                    1132                      368                     592                     282&#13;
t- - - - - - --- - -   -    -    -  -   -    -    -    -   -  -    - -    -    -   -  -    -    -  -   -    --   -    - -    -  -&#13;
6                  888                    1106                      348                     636                     324&#13;
7                  954                    1174                      386                     588                     276&#13;
8                  876                    1132                      360                     631                     317&#13;
9                  945                    1193                      394                     584                     269&#13;
10                   869                   1145                      367                     627                      310&#13;
11                   939                    1202                     400                     612                      293&#13;
12                   948                    1220                     408                     598                      278&#13;
13                   936                    1209                     406                     643                      319&#13;
14                   993                   1274                      433                     595                      271&#13;
15                   912                    1236                     406                     639                      312&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
Table  10      Rcsults of Deterministic Simulation    (Basic Case)&#13;
Manufacturing of Jute Goods by Region&#13;
(' 000 rr)&#13;
Simulation     INDIA       BANGLADESH    THAILAND       WESTERN       JAPAN         USA&#13;
Year                                                 EUROPE&#13;
1          1032          459          149           290           78            13&#13;
2          1078          476          157           300           80            14&#13;
3          1052          446          160           297           78            13&#13;
4          1062          462          158           298           79            14&#13;
5          1078          482          156           299           80            14&#13;
6          1065          460          159           299           79            14&#13;
7          1090          491          156           301           81            14&#13;
8          1079          472          160           301           79            14&#13;
9          1105          502          156           304           81            14&#13;
10          1097          485          160           304           80            14&#13;
13.         1110          499          160           306           81            14&#13;
12          1124          512          159           308           82            14&#13;
13          1117          495          163           308           81            14&#13;
14          1142          525          160           311           83            15&#13;
15          3.135         509          164          311            82            14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
Table    11        Results of Deterministic Simulation           (Basic Case)&#13;
Demand for Jute Goods by Region&#13;
('000 MT)&#13;
Simulation         INDIA        BANGLADESH        THAILAND         WESTERN           JAPAN           USA&#13;
Year                                                            EUROPE&#13;
1             447             34                64             365              203            416&#13;
2             452             34               63              372              217            463&#13;
3             458             35               63             356               208            410&#13;
4             470             37               65              354              211            407&#13;
5             482             38               67             356               216            408&#13;
______~          -' ___     ____ -___ --__ -___ -_____-----_ ---            -----           --- &#13;
6             488             39               67             346               211            371&#13;
7             503             41               70             351               219            383&#13;
8             509             41               70             341               213            349&#13;
9             524             44                73             347              222            360&#13;
10             530             44                73             338              217            330&#13;
______--_____--_____--_____.-_______-______. ______&#13;
11             543             46                74             338              220            325&#13;
12             555             48                76             338              223            321&#13;
13             562             48                76             328              217            291&#13;
14             578             51                79             332              225            299&#13;
15             585             51                79             322              219            272&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
References&#13;
1]   Askari, ll. and J.T. Cuilmings. [1976].  Agricu7-tural Szupply&#13;
Response: A Survey of the Econometric Evidence.&#13;
Praeger: New York.&#13;
[ 2]   Belrman, J.R. [1968]. Surp?y Response in UnderdeveZoped Agri-&#13;
culture. Norti llolland:  Amsterdam.&#13;
3]   Blitzer, C.; A. NIeeraLls; and A. SLoutjesdijk. [1975]. "A&#13;
Dynamic Model of Opec Trade and Production." JournaZ&#13;
of DeveZopment Economics, 2(4) , pp. 319-336.&#13;
[ 4]   Dhrynies, P.J. [1971]. Distributed Lags: Probleems of Estimation&#13;
and Formulation. Holden Day: San Francisco.&#13;
5]   Grilli, E. and R. Morrison. [1974].  "Jute and the Synthetics."&#13;
Weorld Bank Staff Working. Paper, No. 171.  Washington,&#13;
D.C.&#13;
[ 6)  HIazel1, P.B.R. and P.L. Scandizzo. [1977).  "Market In.ervention&#13;
Policics when Production is Risky."  American JournaZ&#13;
of Agric!ultural Economics, 59(l), pp. 204-9&#13;
1 7)   Just, R.E. [1974L. Econometric Analysis of Production Decisions&#13;
wit-h Governient interviention: The Case of CaZifornia&#13;
Fi,eld Crops.  Giannini Foundation Monograph No. 33,&#13;
Berkeley, California.&#13;
[ 8)   _          [1975].  "Risk Response Models and Their Use in&#13;
Agricultural Policy Evaluation," American Journal of&#13;
Agricultural Economics, 57(5) , pp. 836-43.&#13;
[ 9]  __    _     [1977].  "T'e Existence of Stable Distributed Lags,"&#13;
Econcmetrica  45(6) , pp. 1467-1480.&#13;
[10]   Sengupta, J.K. and A. Sen [1969].  "Econometric Supply Functions&#13;
for Rice and Jute,"  Arthaniti  12(1 &amp; 2), pp. 1-40.&#13;
[11]   UNCTAD, [1974). "An Integrated Programme for Commodities: The&#13;
Role of 'thnternational Buffer Stocks."  (Report by the&#13;
Secretary General. of UNCTAD.) Documents TD/B/C.7/166&#13;
SupplemT!ent 7 and TD/B/C.7/Addecdum 7&#13;
[12)  \lorld Bank [1973]3. To. rVWor2id Jute Economy. Volumes I and II.&#13;
Confidentia1 Report 114-BD, Washingzon, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1555042">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1980/05/1555042/dynamic-simulation-model-world-jute-economy
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1980/05/1555042/dynamic-simulation-model-world-jute-economy</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1980/05/1555042/dynamic-simulation-model-world-jute-economy</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/11/28/000178830_98101903404543/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/11/28/000178830_98101903404543/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1980-05-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2002-11-28T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            A dynamic simulation model of the world
            jute economy
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Jute and jute products have been
            steadily losing markets to synthetic substitutes since the
            1960s. One of the causes of this loss in market shares has
            traditionally been identified in the supply instability of
            raw jute; large market price fluctuations have stimulated
            the search for domestically produced substitutes for jute in
            consuming countries. Price stabilization for jute has been
            intensely discussed in international fora, within the
            framework of the UNCTAD Integrated Program for Commodities.
            This paper investigates both the sources of jute supply
            instability and the potential impact of an internationally
            managed buffer stock of stabilized market prices. The
            analysis is carried out utilizing a rather simple dynamic
            model of the markets for raw jute and jute goods. The model
            combines econometric estimates of the relevant parameters
            with prior information derived from industry studies. It
            integrates the behavior of jute farmers in the principal
            jute growing countries with that of jute goods manufacturers
            and consumers using a series of region-specific demand and
            supply functions. Expected price variance is an explicit
            factor in determining jute acreage.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            A dynamic simulation model of the world jute economy
        </docna>
        <display_title>A dynamic simulation model of the
            world jute economy</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1980/05/1555042/dynamic-simulation-model-world-jute-economy</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Crops and Crop Management Systems,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Access to Markets,Markets and Market Access</subtopic>
        <teratopic>International Economics and Trade</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Anderson, J.</author>
            <author>Blitzer, Charles</author>
            <author>Cauchois, T.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903404543</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Trade</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 391</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>International Economics and Trade</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Buffer stocks; Jute; Price policy;
            Production; Simulation; Stabilization; Supply &amp; demand; Synthetics
            adaptive expectations,alternative
            crops,alternative policies,average
            prices,benchmark,benchmarks,cassava,centrally planned
            economies,commodity,competitive
            price,consumers,cordage,cotton,crop,crop prices,demand
            functions,discount rate,econometric estimates,Economic
            Analysis,economic growth,Economic Order,Economies of
            scale,equations,equilibrium,expected value,export
            markets,exports,farmers,fibers,finished products,functional
            forms,groundnuts,growth
            rate,imports,inflation,jute,kenaf,maize,market
            prices,oil,oil prices,oil refineries,planting,price
            changes,price elasticities,price elasticity,price
            expectations,price fluctuations,price stability,Price
            stabilization,producers,production costs,regression
            analysis,sales,Stocks,substitutes,substitution,sugar,sugarcane,supply
            equations,supply functions,taxation,variable costs,world markets,yields
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP391</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Policy, Strategy and Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops and Crop Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Econometrics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textiles</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Refineries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Competitive Industries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>