<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Economic Motivattion Versus City Lights:&#13;
Testing Hypotheses About Inter-Changwat&#13;
Migration in Thaiiland&#13;
SWP416&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 416&#13;
September 1980&#13;
Prepared by: Fred Arnold (consultant)&#13;
Susan H. Cochrane&#13;
Development Economics Department&#13;
Development Policy Staff&#13;
Copyright © 1980&#13;
The World Bank                                                         I                fl11&lt;ID&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W. &lt;&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
?UB      lws and interpretations in this document are those of the authors&#13;
iG       I)uld not be attributed to the Worli Bank, to its affiliated&#13;
3881.5    ations, or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
.W57&#13;
.q767                                                                     RDti- E         0&#13;
no. 416&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretation in this document are those of the authors and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations,&#13;
or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 416&#13;
ECONOMIC MOTIVATION VERSUS CITY LIGHTS:&#13;
TESTING HYPOTHESES ABOUT INTER-CHANGWAT MIGRATION IN THAILAND&#13;
This paper is an expansion of the migration analysis done as part of the&#13;
Basic Economic Mission to Thailand and contained in Working Paper No.337. In&#13;
that paper net and gross, in and out migration were studied. In the current&#13;
paper the analysis is extended to include the direction as well as level of&#13;
migration flows between provinces (changwats) and this analysis is integrated&#13;
with that of others who have done migration research in Thailand.&#13;
The models tested here are of the gravity flow variety. They are tested&#13;
in two basic forms. The first is based on the assumption that it is only&#13;
the characteristics of the destination relative to the origin that matter.&#13;
The second is unconst-.ained and allows one to examine the characteristics&#13;
of origin and destinations separately.   While a number of questions remain&#13;
unanswered it is very clear from this analysis that:&#13;
(1) economic factors predominate over the non-economic attraction of urban&#13;
areas;&#13;
(2) the economic condlitions (income per capita, unemployment, and land scarcity)&#13;
in destinations relative to origins have significant relationships' in&#13;
the hypothesized direction;&#13;
(3) male and female migration streams respond to per capita income and unemploy-&#13;
ment in the same way. Males, however, are more responsive than females&#13;
to the scarcity or availability of farmland;&#13;
(4) migration to and from Bangkok tends to respond in a very similar manner&#13;
to relative income and the availability of farmland as migration to and&#13;
from other areas;&#13;
(5) in the unconstrained model, conditions in the area of destination all&#13;
have significant relationships of the hypothesized signs;&#13;
(6) conditions in the areas of origin play a far more complex role, since&#13;
conditions at l:he area of origin determine not only the push to migrate,&#13;
but also the ability to afford to migrate. For example, in all specifica-&#13;
tions the higher the per capita income in the sending area, the higher&#13;
the outflow of migrants;&#13;
(7) the sign and significance of other economic variables in the origin&#13;
vary depending on the specifications.&#13;
The major conclusion of policy relevance from this paper is that the&#13;
level of migration will increase as economic development proceeds, but the&#13;
direction of movement will depend on the relative economic opportunities in&#13;
various changwats. It: is the latter that might be most susceptible to policy&#13;
manipulation.&#13;
Prepared by:  Fred Arnold (consultant)                Copyright  @  1980&#13;
Susan H. Cochrane                       The World Bank&#13;
Development Economics Department        1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Development Policy Staff                Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Acknowledgement&#13;
We would like to 2xpress our appreciation .to Anuri Wanglee,&#13;
Deputy Secretary-General of the National Statistical Office,&#13;
for her cooperation and advice.   We would also like to thank&#13;
Daniel Suits, Qey Ileesook, Jed Shilling, and Gershen Feder&#13;
for their comments on-an earlier draft of this paper and Erwin&#13;
Chou and Kalpania-Nindwani for their assistance in the analysis&#13;
of the data..&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
I.  Introduction .             .......... ...   ........              1&#13;
II.  Theoretical Models of Migration  . . . . . . . . . . . .          4&#13;
III.  Previous Research on Inter-changwat Migrationi Flows&#13;
in Thailand.. ........                                          8&#13;
IV.  The Analysis .... .      .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .  15&#13;
V.  Summary and Policy Implications  . . . . . . . . . . . .          30&#13;
Footnotes  ....   .    .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .  36&#13;
References   ....   .    .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .  39&#13;
List of Tables&#13;
Table :L 'Regresstonw-Rpspilts for the Relative Model . . . . . .       19&#13;
Table 2   Rerpsslron wKesuits for the Expanded Model . . . . . .       21&#13;
Table 3   Kegress.1nn --R-qhilts tor the Relative Model for Bangkok&#13;
and Non:--,Wahngkok Migration (1965-1970) . . . . . . .    27&#13;
Table 4   RegressibnJwesults for the Expanded Model for Bangkok&#13;
and NiuE Ban'gkok MigratiULL. (1965-1970) . . . . . . .    28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I. INTRODUCTION&#13;
Although Thailand's population cannot be described as highly mo-&#13;
bile, both the upward trend in migration rates and the rapid growth in&#13;
the urban population have become a cause of some concern in the last two&#13;
or three decades.  Between 1955-1960 and 1965-1970 the rate of migration&#13;
between changwats (provinces)-/ increased by almost two-thirds.   Even&#13;
though both of these periods were characterized by a high degree of resi-&#13;
dential stability, particularly in rural areas, over three million per-&#13;
sons changed their place of residence (village or municipal area) at least&#13;
once in the latter per-iod, and about half of them moved across changwat&#13;
boundaries (Arnold and Boonpratuang, 1976).&#13;
The single most popular destination for inter-changwat migrants&#13;
continues to be Bangkok, which has grown rapidly to a metropolis of&#13;
more than four million residents. With over half of the country's urban&#13;
population and a population size more than forty times that of the next&#13;
largest city (Chiang Mai), Bangkok provides one of the most striking ex-&#13;
amples of urban primacy in the world (Piampiti, 1979). The rapid in-&#13;
crease in Bangkok's population has exacerbated a whole range of social&#13;
and economic problems in the capital city and has put a severe strain&#13;
on the government's ability to provide adequate public services to Bang-&#13;
kok's residents. In addition, the large influx of seasonal migrants&#13;
who augment Bangkok's permanent population during the agricultural slack&#13;
season further complicates government planning in this area.&#13;
Most urban population growth in Thailand is attributable to natural&#13;
increase, but Goldstein and his colleagues (n.d.: 692) have estimated&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
that about forty percent of urban growth between 1970 and 1975 was due&#13;
to migration. As fertility rates continue to decrease, and as the urban&#13;
population of Thailand continues to expand, migration will continue to be&#13;
a major component, if not the major component, in the expansion of Thailand's&#13;
cities for the rest of this century.&#13;
Although migration to Thailand's cities, especially to Bangkcok, was&#13;
undoubtedly the factor that initially aroused an awareness of migra-&#13;
tion problems among policy makers and the public (Prachuabmoh and Tirasa-&#13;
wat, 1974), urbanward migration constitutes only a minor proportion of&#13;
all migration in Thailand. In fact, in the period 1965-1970, 72 percent&#13;
of all changes of residence took place entirely between nonmunicipal&#13;
areas (Arnold and Boonpratuang, 1976: 9). In the past, migration of this&#13;
type was often motivated by a search for new agricultural land, as rapid&#13;
population growth put increasing pressure on previously cultivated land.&#13;
Farmers have been faced with the prospect of cultivating more and more&#13;
marginal, inaccessible land. The vanishing frontier has become a mat-&#13;
ter of major concern in Thailand because the population continues to&#13;
grow rapidly (at over two percent per year) despite an impressive&#13;
decline in fertility rates throughout the country during the 1970s.   Un-&#13;
der these circumstances, if migration rates continue to increase in&#13;
Thailand (as most theoretical migration models and our analysis sug-&#13;
gest), population movement will become-an increasingly important con-&#13;
sideration in development planning.&#13;
The importance of internal migration has been explicitly recognized&#13;
in the Fourth National Economic and Social Development Plan (1977-1981),&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
which is the first plan to include programs on population redistribu-&#13;
tion and human settlements. The plan seeks to redirect migrants to ur-&#13;
ban "growth poles" and to encourage migrants to move out of the Bangkok&#13;
Metropolitan Area by:&#13;
(a) controlling urban land use on the periphery of Bangkok;&#13;
(b) developing urban infrastructure (public utilities, educational&#13;
and health services, housing) in urban centers outside Bangkok;&#13;
(c) creating urban employment opportunities outside Bangkok by of-&#13;
fering monetary incentives to attract industries, commerce,&#13;
and services to regional centers and by establishing industrial&#13;
estates and export-processing zones; and&#13;
(d)  accelerating regional and rural development so that regional&#13;
urban centers will have local sources of raw materials and&#13;
marketing outLets for their products (Piampiti, 1979).&#13;
These policies are designed to affect: primarily the pull of urban areas&#13;
rather than the factors pushing migrants from rural areas. Similar&#13;
programs have met with only limited success in some settings, and it is&#13;
too early to assess the:ir impact in Thailand (Rhoda, 1979). But, as&#13;
in many places, the programs were formulated in the absence of satisfac-&#13;
tory information about either the causes or the consequences of inter-&#13;
nal migration.&#13;
This paper attempts; to shed some additional light on the determinants&#13;
of internal migration by means of a regression analysis of economic,&#13;
social, and demographic factors that are related to migration flows&#13;
at the changwat level. Data are taken primarily from the 1970 Popula-&#13;
tion and Housing Census. It is hoped that this analysis, together with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
the results of microlevel studies, will assist policy makers in design-&#13;
ing migration-related policies and programs.    First, the results should&#13;
help in predicting future migration flows. Inputs of this type are cru-&#13;
cial for population projections on which economic and social development&#13;
plans are based.2- Second, findings on the determinants of migration&#13;
can be used to formulate plans for altering migration streams according&#13;
to the goverrnent's goals.&#13;
The next section of the paper reviews some of the major theoretical&#13;
models of migration and the hypotheses that are derived from them. It&#13;
is followed by discussions of previous research on migration in Thailand&#13;
and the methodology and results of the current study. The final sec-&#13;
tion interprets some oE the major results in the Thai context and out-&#13;
lines some policy implications that follow from the analysis.&#13;
II. THEORETICAL MODELS OF MIGRATION&#13;
Migration can be studied from several perspectives and at different&#13;
levels of analysis. One can examine migration at the aggregate or the&#13;
individual level. At t:he aggregate level, the characteristics of the&#13;
region can be studied, whereas at the individual level, the characteris-&#13;
tics of the individuals who actually move may be analyzed. Although it&#13;
is possible to analyze the regional factors affecting migration choices&#13;
of individuals, it is much riskier to use regional data to make assump-&#13;
tions about the individuals who migrate.3/&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
In the present context, we shall focus on aggregate migration flows&#13;
rather than individual migration. This focus is quite useful both for&#13;
predictions of the magnitudes of the migration flows and for policy, but&#13;
it cannot be used to determine the characteristics of the individual&#13;
migrants or therefore the compositional changes of sending or receiving&#13;
areas. In addition, we shall concentrate our analysis and thus our dis-&#13;
cussion of models on gross migration from one region to another.-/ This&#13;
approach involves the study of the volume of movement and the charac-&#13;
teristics of both the sending and receiving regions.&#13;
The most elementary model of gross migration between areas is based&#13;
on a simple analogy to the law of gravity.   That is, the flow (gravity)&#13;
between two areas (bodiLes) is directly proportional to the size of the&#13;
two regions (mass of the two bodies) and inversely proportional to the&#13;
distance between them (Zipf, 1946).&#13;
a1 a2,&#13;
M. . = k P  j&#13;
ij     ~a&#13;
(D ij) 3&#13;
where Mij is gross migration from area i to area j; Pi is the population&#13;
of area i; P. is the population of j; Dij is the distance between i and&#13;
j; and a and kc are constants. One major advantage of this simple formu-&#13;
lation is that it is multiplicative and can be estimated by a simple&#13;
log linear equation:&#13;
log Mij.   log k + a1 log Pi + a. log P. -     og D&#13;
~~.  2      a3logD..&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
The gravity model is, of course, largely devoid of behavioral con-&#13;
tent and does not explain which decision or policy variables affect the&#13;
volume or direction of migration. Since these factors alone are quite&#13;
powerful in explaining migration, however, it is necessary to include&#13;
this mechanistic core in any behavioral model of gross migration to avoid&#13;
spurious results. A mtmber of models have been developed that attempt&#13;
to modify the gravity model to incorporate more interesting causal fac-&#13;
tors. Before examining these models, we shall review the theories of&#13;
the behavioral factors that determine gross migration.&#13;
Ravenstein's laws of migration, published in 1885, represent the&#13;
first attempt to describe migration in terms of demographic, social,&#13;
economic and geographic. characteristics of the flow. Ravenstein did&#13;
not attempt to develop a behavioral model of the factors determining&#13;
migration, but he did identify the variables that probably should be in-&#13;
cluded in such a model. He observed different behavior for urban and&#13;
rural residents and for males and females. He also stressed the impor-&#13;
tance of distance, level of development, and economic motivations for&#13;
migration.&#13;
In his 1966 paper, Lee developed a schematic model of the factors&#13;
determining the flow of migrants from i to j. This schema identifies&#13;
the important factors in the area of origin and the area of destination&#13;
and the intervening obstacles between the two. Factors characteristic&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
of the sending region are high unemployment, low wages, poor climate and&#13;
topology, and lack of :recreational, educational and community facilities.&#13;
Factors associated withl the area of destination are high wages, low&#13;
unemployment, good clirnate, and so forth. Intervening variables include the&#13;
distance and the costs of moving. Various researchers have added inter-&#13;
vening opportunities between i and j as determinants of the flow be-&#13;
tween i and j (Stouffer, 1966).&#13;
Although all these factors characterize regions, a large number&#13;
of factors determining the migration of particular individuals have also&#13;
been discussed in the literature. Some of these are age (or stage in&#13;
the life cycle), sex, individual knowledge about the area of destination,&#13;
and personality traits. Whether these factors have aggregate counter-&#13;
parts is less certain. Human capital models of migration have concen-&#13;
trated on the cost and returns to individuals, but the variables used&#13;
do not differ substantially from those used by demographers and sociolo-&#13;
gists (Sjaastad, 1962).&#13;
A major alteration of the individual model of migration decision&#13;
making is Toda:ro's postulate that migration responds to differences in&#13;
expected rather than actual earnings (Todaro, 1969; Harris and Todaro,&#13;
1970). Expected gains are measured by the difference in real incomes&#13;
between work opportunities in sending and receiving regions and the&#13;
probability of the new rnigrant's obtaining a job in the area of destina-&#13;
tion. At the regional Level, this would imply that emphasis needs to&#13;
be given to both unemployment and wage or income levels. The exact&#13;
specification of the int:eraction of t.hese two variables would depend&#13;
on how expectations are formed by different individuals and how such&#13;
individuals are distributed in the two populations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
The primary impori;ance given to economic factors is common to most&#13;
theories of migration. The major exception is the role of cities per&#13;
se in attracting migrants. It has often been hypothesized that this ef-&#13;
fect is important independent of the economic opportunities offered by&#13;
cities. This is referred to as the "city lights" hypothesis.-/&#13;
As Lowry (1966) and others have shown, economic characteristics of&#13;
sending and receiving areas can be introduced into the gravity model in&#13;
al a2  a4&#13;
several ways.   A simple formulation might be M..    k  i     Ei  where E.&#13;
13     a3    a5&#13;
represents a summary measure of economic               D  3   E.5&#13;
opportunities in the i    region.  This could be estimated in one of two&#13;
ways, either as:&#13;
logij = log k + a1 log P. +     2 lg       -a3 log D.j + a4 log (E./Ej), if&#13;
a4 = -a5 or alternatively as:&#13;
log M.= log k-i-a1 log Pi + a2 log Pj + a3 log Dij + a4 log E      + a  log E&#13;
where there is; no restriction that a4 = -a5.&#13;
In the relative formulation, it is assumed that economic conditions&#13;
in the sending region relative to those of the destination affect the&#13;
flow of migrants; the alternative specification allows for separate&#13;
and possibly different effects of origin and destination characteristics.&#13;
The second specification makes it easier to assess the separate impor-&#13;
tance of push and pull factors in determining migration.    In our analysis&#13;
we shall test both models.&#13;
III. PREVIOUS RESEARCH ON INTER-CHANGWAT MIGRATION FLOWS IN THAILAND&#13;
It is only within the last two decades that an active interest has&#13;
been taken in documenting migration flows in Thailand and in examining&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9.-&#13;
the characteristics of migrants and the determinants of migration. Some&#13;
specialized surveys of migration from Northeastern Thailand to Bangkok&#13;
were published in the early 1960s (Textor, 1960; Meinkoth, 1962), and&#13;
the 1954 National Demographic and Social Survey provided some information&#13;
on the characteristics of migrants (Wichiencharoen, 1960). However, a&#13;
substantial amount of migration research was not undertaken until the&#13;
1960 census data became available.&#13;
Ng (1969, 1970) noted the complexity of the spatial pattern of mi-&#13;
gration streams in Thailand and pointed out the inadequacy of using the&#13;
normal four regional designations to study migratory movements. He there-&#13;
fore developed a set of ten "migration regions" based on 1960 census&#13;
data to describe clusters of administrative units that were characterized&#13;
by a substantial mutual. exchange of migrants. Within each region, the&#13;
population tended to move away from the center of high population den-&#13;
sity into more sparsely populated areas. This pattern led Ng to con-&#13;
clude that intraregional moves in the 1950s were determined largely by&#13;
the availability of agricultural opportunities. Our results show that&#13;
the availability of land is still an important determinant of migration.&#13;
Goldstein (1973) used a sample tape from the 1960 census to study&#13;
the characteristics of migrants, particularly the fertility behavior&#13;
of migrants and nonmigrants. Data on migration from the 1960 census&#13;
were also used in a stLLdy of migration patterns by Chapman and Allen&#13;
(1965), in a report to the Thai government by the International Labor&#13;
Office (1965), and in EL succession of masters' theses written by Thai&#13;
students (e.g., Siripal;, 1965; Chamratrithirong, 1973). Many of these&#13;
studies were mainly descriptions of migration patterns and the charac-&#13;
teristics of migrants, but some also attempted to identify the major&#13;
determinants (or at least the correlates) of migration flows.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-10-&#13;
Prachuabmoh and Tirasawat (1974) reviewed migration studies from 1947&#13;
to 1972 and summarized the major results of those studies. The au-&#13;
thors concluded that economic factors were the most important motives&#13;
for migration in Thailand and that push and pull factors were both im-&#13;
portant determinants oi migration.&#13;
The National LongiLtudinal Survey of Social, Economic, and Demogra-&#13;
phic Change also spawned several migration publications (Goldstein et&#13;
al., 1974; Goldstein and Pitaktepsombati, 1974; Tirasawat, 1977).&#13;
In addition, several st:udies focusing on particular aspects of migra-&#13;
tion, such as migration to Bangkok or other specific locations (Thai-&#13;
land, National Statistical Office, 1979; Sternstein, 1977; Piampiti,&#13;
1976) and female migration (Arnold and Piampiti, 1979; Piampiti, n.d.),&#13;
have appeared in the last few years. But more general studies of the&#13;
areal determinants of miigration on a national basis have relied mostly&#13;
on 1970 census data. At least four Ph.D. theses by Thai students have&#13;
explored the determinants of migration on a macrolevel with 1970 cen-&#13;
sus data (Prasartkul, 1977; Srisawas, 1977; Chamratrithirong, 1976;&#13;
Garnjana-Goonchorn, 1974). These studies differ substantially in a&#13;
number of key respects, including the type of model proposed, the mea-&#13;
sures of migration used, the provinces included in the calculations,&#13;
and the method of analysis applied to the data. These variations have&#13;
resulted in substantially different findings and somewhat different&#13;
conclusions.&#13;
The study by Garnjana-Goonchorn covers migration to the Bangkok&#13;
metropolitan area, whereas the other three studies include all 71&#13;
changwats (except for Bangkok and Thon Buri in some cases). Srisawas&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-.11-&#13;
used the life table survival method to estimate net migration rates for&#13;
1960-70; the other three studies are based on five-year migration data&#13;
for 1965-70. All the authors used multiple regression to study inter-&#13;
changwat migration flows except for Chamratrithirong, who employed cor-&#13;
relation analysis. Because the census publications include only limited&#13;
information on the types of independent variables that are hypothesized&#13;
to influence migration., and because the scope and quality of alterna-&#13;
tive data sources are inadequate for this purpose, the researchers had&#13;
to be quite resourcefujl in finding data that were suitable for testing&#13;
their models. The three studies that used regression analysis all in-&#13;
corporated the standarcl gravity variables in their models; they also&#13;
included some economic variables, although the precise economic variables&#13;
selected were quite diverse (unemployment, income, population or land&#13;
pressure, socioeconomic development).&#13;
The gravity variabtles were generally found to be highly significant,&#13;
and the relationships were in the expected direction. The effect of dis-&#13;
tance, however, does nct appear to be linear. Both Chamratrithirong&#13;
and Prasartkul found support for the "critical distance" thesis, at&#13;
least in the case of migration to and from Bangkok. The negative ef-&#13;
fect of distance on migration was strong up to about 250-300 kilometers&#13;
from Bangkok but insignificant beyond that point. In addition, there&#13;
was a slight decrease in the significance of the distance effect on&#13;
migration to Bangkok between 1955-60 and 1965-70, probably due to the&#13;
availability of better transportation in the latter period (Prasartkul,&#13;
1977; Chamratrithirong, 1976).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-.12-&#13;
The significance of economic factors in migration varied con-&#13;
siderably from one study to another. Overall, the weakest results were&#13;
obtained by Srisawas (1977), who found that the level of development,&#13;
educational attainment of an area, and degree of accessibility were&#13;
all unrelated to the volume of migration. The only significant effect&#13;
found was a negative eiffect of density on net migration, and the level&#13;
of explanation for the complete model was relatively low (R2 = .199).&#13;
The author attributes 1:he poor results to weaknesses in measurement&#13;
procedures and suggests that it would be better to use a measure of&#13;
population pressure on arable agricultural land or land in cultivation&#13;
than a simple density measure. Chamratrithirong (1976), on the other&#13;
hand, found the level of socioeconomic development to be highly correlated&#13;
with migration flows. His measure of development (the proportion of the&#13;
economically active population in the primary sector) was posivively related&#13;
to in-migration, out-migration, and gross migration for both females and&#13;
males. He stressed the importance of physical and cultural facilitating&#13;
factors rather than "push" factors in explaining migration flows:&#13;
On the one hand, it is clear that push factors account for&#13;
a great number of out-migrants from the poorer provinces.&#13;
However, when the analysis shifts from the numbers of mi-&#13;
grants to migration rates, the characteristics of the more&#13;
developed provinces seem to facilitate moves. This is par-&#13;
ticularly visible in the case of out-migration to Greater&#13;
Bangkok. It appears that areas which have the more modern&#13;
characteristics, also have populations which are more likely&#13;
to migrate to the capital city (pp. 173-5).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
These results support Davisks thesis of "relative deprivation" since&#13;
migration does not seemn to be directly stimulated by poverty.&#13;
Prasartkul (1977) emphasized the effect of "pull" factors on mi-&#13;
gration. In general, conditions at the destination gave a better fit&#13;
than conditions at the origin. Population pressure was found to be more&#13;
important at the destination than at the origin.   Migrants tended to move&#13;
from changwats with low employment rates to those with high employment&#13;
rates, and more migrant:s moved to changwats with high rates of business&#13;
investment and a low degree of social structural disequilibrium. The&#13;
results, however, were highly dependent on the particular model tested.&#13;
The additive model explained only 25 percent of the variance and almost&#13;
all characteristics were insignificant. The multiplicative model, on&#13;
the other hand, explained 60 percent of the variance, but even with this&#13;
model, the socioeconomic and demographic variables by themselves were not&#13;
2&#13;
very effective (R = .08).&#13;
The best overall level of explanation was obtained by Garnjana-&#13;
Goonchorn (1974) for migration to the Bangkok Metropolitan Area.    Once&#13;
again, the choice of models is crucial. The log linear form explained&#13;
2                                2&#13;
more of the variance (R   = .85) than the linear form (R   = .61), and&#13;
the explanatory power was slightly better for females than for males in&#13;
both cases. The neoclassical economic variables (average monthly earn-&#13;
ings and unemployment) were significant in the linear model but not in&#13;
the log linear form. Finally, a set of variables added to measure in-&#13;
tervening opportunities was found to be insignificant in the linear&#13;
model and onlY Dartlv successful in the lo2 linear model.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The present study builds upon the work summarized above, makes modi-&#13;
fications to overcome some of the problems identified in those studies,&#13;
and expands the analysis into new areas. Our analysis differs from some&#13;
or all of the previous studies in the following important ways:&#13;
(a)  All nonzero inter-changwat migration streams are included in&#13;
the analysis. Other studies rely on the published census&#13;
volLumes which do not print data for small migration streams.&#13;
The present study is based on complete data for all migration&#13;
flows from the unpublished 71 x 71 matrix of migration for&#13;
Thailand. (Since Bangkok and Thon Buri are combined, the analy-&#13;
sis uses n 70 x 70 matrix.)&#13;
(b) The analysis is conducted for all changwats together and for&#13;
Bangkok and non-Bangkok migration separately.&#13;
(c)  Female and male migration streams are analyzed separately and&#13;
the data are also pooled.&#13;
(d) Interaction effects are included in the equations.&#13;
(e)  Both the relative and expanded gravity models are tested.&#13;
(f) Some of the key variables are measured differently from other&#13;
studies. In :particular, land pressure is measured by propor-&#13;
tion of land farmed rather than simply density and unemploy-&#13;
ment includes those waiting for agricultural employ.ment at the&#13;
time of the census.&#13;
Probably the greatest departure from the previous studies is the choice&#13;
and measurement: of variables included in the model. A detailed description&#13;
of the variables in the model and the results of the analysis are presented&#13;
in the next section.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-15-&#13;
IV. THE ANALYSIS&#13;
The data for this analysis were obtained primarily from the 1970&#13;
census of population. Interprovincial migration is measured by the num-&#13;
ber of people who had lived in their 1970 place of residence for less than&#13;
five years and whose previous place of residence was a different changwat.-&#13;
The study includes all combinations of origin and destination in which&#13;
there was at least one person who migrated from one changwat to another.&#13;
It is necessary to exc:Lude those combinations where there were no migrants&#13;
in order to use a log specification. It is unlikely that this exclusion&#13;
will cause serious bias since only 1.6 percent of the possible combina-&#13;
tions have no migration.  Other studies, however, which have relied on&#13;
published data may be subject to serious bias, since published data ex-&#13;
clude migration flows cf less than thirty persons which results in the&#13;
delet:ion of forty percent of the flows.&#13;
In this paper, the economic variables included in the analysis are&#13;
those most relevant to the Thai environment. To adapt the model to the&#13;
Thai context, it is necessary to recognize the importance of rural-to-&#13;
rural migration. Therefore, the availability of farmland has been added&#13;
to the standard economiz variables of income and unemployment. In ad-&#13;
dition, the proportion of population living in urban areas was added&#13;
to test the city lights hypothesis. Ideally, we would wish to measure&#13;
our independent variables at the beginning or middle of the 1965-70&#13;
period since we want to examine their causal effect on migration and&#13;
ignore the possibility that migration may have in fact affected the&#13;
level of the independent variables.  For income and proportion of land&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-16-&#13;
fanmed, it was possible to obtain figures for 1967 and 1961/62, respec-&#13;
tively, but measures oF unemployment and urbanization were obtained from&#13;
the 1970 census.- This might lead to a bias in the coefficients of these&#13;
8/&#13;
variables,-   but given the relatively small magnitude of migration overall&#13;
we do not expect this b)ias to be large.-/&#13;
Thus the model to be tested is:&#13;
aL  a2     a4 a  6 a8 aR &#13;
M.    k    pi    .    Ii u.   F.8 UR'0&#13;
lj                    1 &#13;
a3       a Ia  7 a9     11&#13;
D.  ~  I.   U.  F.  UR.&#13;
:Lj       j   j   j     J&#13;
where Ii and I. represent per capita. income in area of origin i and area&#13;
of destination j, Ui and Uj represent unemployment (including those wait-&#13;
ing for agricultural work), F. and Fj represent the proportion of land&#13;
farmed, and URi and URj represent the proportions of the population&#13;
urban.     For the relative model we restrict the coefficients so that&#13;
a4    a5, a6     a7, a8     a9 and alo    a11&#13;
The log linear formulation of the relative model implies that:&#13;
(a)  the.coefficient on Ii/I. should be negative, since the higher&#13;
the income ir! the sending area relative to the receiving&#13;
area, the less attractive migration should appear.&#13;
(b)  the coefficient on Ui/U. should be positive, since higher&#13;
unemployment in the origin than the destination should en-&#13;
courage migration;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-17-&#13;
(c)  the coefficient on Fi/F. should be positive, since the more&#13;
land already farmed in i relative to j, the greater the oppor-&#13;
tunities for homesteading new land in j relative to i (a major&#13;
factor in rural-to-rural migration);&#13;
(d)  the coefficient on URi/UR. can be expected to be negative if&#13;
urbanization per se is attractive to migrants independent of&#13;
its effects on economic opportunities;&#13;
(e) Pi and P. should have positive coefficients equal to 1;&#13;
(f) D.. should have a negative coefficient.&#13;
In the expanded model, the coefficients are unrestricted and their&#13;
signs are less certain. If only the relative values and not the absolute&#13;
values of the variables matter, then all variables in i will have the same&#13;
sign as in the relative model, and all variables in j will have the oppo-&#13;
site sign since they appear in the denominator of the ratio.    For example,&#13;
I. would have a negative sign and I. would have a positive sign. These&#13;
1                                  J&#13;
are the coefficients hypothesized by Todaro in a recent paper (Todaro, 1980).&#13;
If the origin and destination variables play independent roles, the signs&#13;
need not follow this simple pattern.&#13;
As suggested by Ravenstein, the importance of these factors may dif-&#13;
fer for male and female migrants. Therefore, the above models were&#13;
tested for differences in the behavior of males and females with respect&#13;
to these variables. In addition, in the context of Thailand, Bangkok&#13;
plays a very unique role, and the migration flows involving Bangkok may&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-18-&#13;
exhibit behavior quite different from those of the other regions. There-&#13;
fore, the models were also tested separately for Bangkok and non-Bangkok&#13;
migration.&#13;
The Relative Model&#13;
The simple formulation of the model to be tested is specified by&#13;
log M. = log k + a log P. + a log P    + alog Dij + a+&#13;
Uj            1     1     2g    i                           Iag.  a4o  ''*&#13;
a6log (U./U.) + a,3log (Fi/F1 ) 4 a10log (URi/UR.)&#13;
The results of this specification for total gross migration from i to j&#13;
are given in the first column of Table 1, and the results for females,&#13;
males, and a pooling of males and females are given in columns 2, 3, and&#13;
4.1-/ The first four c:olumns show that the model explains approximately&#13;
60 percent of the variation in each group, and that all variables are&#13;
statistically significant and of the hypothesized sign with the exception&#13;
of urbanization, which has the opposite sign. This would imply that ur-&#13;
banization per se is nct an attracting force once one controls for the&#13;
economic attractiveness of the changwat. This point will be explored more&#13;
fully later.&#13;
The gravity variables of population size and distanceL-J have the&#13;
greatest explanatory power as measured by beta coefficients (not shown),&#13;
followed by relative income, relative unemployment and relative proportion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-19-&#13;
Table 1. Regression Results for the Relative Model&#13;
(t Values in Parenthesis)&#13;
(2)         (3)        (4)               (5)&#13;
Variable             Total     Females      Males      Pooled    Pooled with interaction&#13;
0.675*      0.640*       0.658*     0.646*            0.648*&#13;
Population I                  (25.47)      (24.12)     (24.59)    (34.17)           (27.07)&#13;
0.912*      0.871*       0.901*     0.886*            0.878*&#13;
Population J                  (34.48)      (32.85)     (33.72)    (46.96)          (36.76)&#13;
-1.341*     -1.323*      -1.318*    -1.320*           -1.320*&#13;
Distance                      (67.11)      (65.29)     (65.75)    (92.23)           (67.52)&#13;
Income I                     -0.385*     -0.351*      -0.391*    -0.373*           -0.351*&#13;
Income J                      (10.41)     (9.32)       (10.54)    (14.08)           (9.33)&#13;
Unemployment I                0.163*      0.143*       0.161*     0.157*            0.143*&#13;
Unemployment J                (6.76)       (5.80)      (6.92)     (9.35)            (5.80)&#13;
% of land farmed in I         0.112*      0.090*       0.135*     0.114*            0.090*&#13;
% of land farmed in J         (9.02)       (6.94)      (10.98)    (12.76)           (6.95)&#13;
Urbanization I                0.160*      0.126*       0.174*     o.154*            0.126*&#13;
Urbanization J                (4.77)       (3.69)      (5.30)     (6.52)            (3.69)&#13;
Population I * S                                                                    0.015&#13;
(0.51)&#13;
Population J * S                                                                    0.003&#13;
(0.08)&#13;
Distance   * S                                                                     -0.001&#13;
(0.05)&#13;
Income I  *                                                                        -0.040&#13;
Income J                                                                            (0.75)&#13;
Unemployment I   * S                                                                0.018&#13;
Unemployment J                                                                      (0.54)&#13;
% of land farmed in I   *S                                                          0.045**&#13;
% of land farmed in J                                                               (2.55)&#13;
Urbanization I   *  S                                                               0.048&#13;
Urbanization J                                                                      (1.01)&#13;
-2                   0.62        0.60         0.60       0.60              0.60&#13;
Note : S = 1 for males,   i = significant at 0.01    **   significant at 0.05&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-.20-&#13;
of land farmed in that order.    The perverse urbanization variable has the&#13;
least explanatory power. Thus the purely economic variables perform at&#13;
a level between that oF the simple gravity model and the more impression-&#13;
istic taste for (or distaste for) urbanization.&#13;
Separate equations for male and female migration appear to be re-&#13;
markably similar in explanatory power and the size of the coefficients.L2/&#13;
Only for the relative availability of farmland is there much difference.&#13;
This is confirmed in column 5, where an interaction dummy variable for&#13;
which male equals 1 was multiplied by each of the explanatory variables.&#13;
None of the interactiorL terms is significant except that for farmland.&#13;
This coefficient indicates that males are significantly more likely than&#13;
females to migrate from areas of relatively high proportion land farmed&#13;
to areas of greater availability of farmland.&#13;
The Expanded Model&#13;
In this section, we shall address the question of whether conditions&#13;
in origins and destinations play a symmetrical role in determining migra-&#13;
tion. A first test of this question can best be addressed by running a&#13;
less restricted test of the basic model:&#13;
log Mij1 = log k + alog P   +           + aog Dij + a        I  + alog &#13;
1  1     2'g   j    3140 &#13;
a6log U  + a7log U. + a8log Fi +                        1+ a10 lg URi + al,log UR&#13;
The signs of the coefficents that would prevail if the variables have a&#13;
symmetrical role in origin and destination are shown in the margin of&#13;
Table 2. The columns of Table 2 replicate the analysis of Table 1 with&#13;
the expanded model.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-21-&#13;
Table 2. Regression Results for the Expanded Model&#13;
(t values in parenthesis)&#13;
Signs Im-&#13;
plied by&#13;
-he Rela-      (1)        (2)       (3)         (4)              (5)&#13;
Variable        tive Model    Total     Female     Wale       Pooled    Pooled with interaction&#13;
).971*     0.927*     0.955*     0.939*           0.903*&#13;
Population I          ()        (36.22)    (34.47)    (35.31)    (49.38)           (36.20)&#13;
1.207*     1.157*     1.200*     1.180*           1.133*&#13;
Population J          (+)      (5.07)      (43.05)    (44.29)    (62.00)           (45.52)&#13;
-:L.386*   -1.350*    -1.400*    -1.373*           -1.360*&#13;
Distance              ()        (69.73)    (67.93)    (68.96)    (97.16)           (70.62)&#13;
).099**   0.173*     0.008      0.094*            0.121*&#13;
Income I                        (2.03)     (3.45)     (0.16)     (2.70)            (2.69)&#13;
0.862*    0,870*     0.780*     0.834*            0.819*&#13;
Income J              (+}        tl7.66)  (17.46)    (15.86)    (23.83)           (18.19)&#13;
-3).489     0.017     -0.113*    -0.059*            0.010&#13;
Unemployment I                  (1.53)     (0.52)     (3.63)     (2.81)            (0.32)&#13;
-.3.378*   -0.270*    -0.443*    -0.378*           -0.276*&#13;
Unemployment J                  (11.79)    (8.31)     (14.23)    (17.88)           (8.54)&#13;
-0.070*    -0.102*    -O.D41**   -0.074*           -0.279*&#13;
% of land farmed I    (         (4.21)     (5.95)     (2.49)     (6.25)            (5.88)&#13;
-.).295*   -2.80*     -0.314*    -0.302*           -0.100*&#13;
Z of laad farmed J              (17.90)    (16.26)    (19.15)    (Z5.52)           (16.21)&#13;
0.083      0.104**    0.074      0.080*            0.126*&#13;
Urbanization I                  (1.91)     (2.32)     (1.72)     (2.61)            (2.88)&#13;
-.0.232*   -0.146*    -0.270*    -0.226*           -0.124*&#13;
Urbanization J                  (5.31)     (3.26)     (6.32)     (7.39)            (2.82)&#13;
Population I * S                                                                   0. 075**&#13;
_______ _ _(2.29)&#13;
Population J * S                                                                   0.087*&#13;
_      ,                              _~~~~~~~~~~~~~-0.027&#13;
Distance * S                                                                       (1.030&#13;
10.063&#13;
Income I * S                                                                      -0.02)&#13;
0.013&#13;
Income J * S                                                                       (0.23)&#13;
Unemployment 1 * S                                                               -0.115*&#13;
(2.58)&#13;
Unemployment J * S                                                               -(3.1585*&#13;
% of land farmed I r S                                                            0.059**&#13;
(2.50)&#13;
% of land farmed J ' S                                                           -0.035&#13;
(1.49)&#13;
Urbanization I * S                                                               -0.072&#13;
(1.21)&#13;
Urbanization J * S                                                               -0.168*&#13;
(2.83)&#13;
-2                     '3.68    | 0.66      0.67       0.66              0.67&#13;
Note: S = L foT males&#13;
* = Significant at 0.01&#13;
** = Significant at 0.0',&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-22-&#13;
In the expanded model, the adjusted R2's are slightly higher than&#13;
those in the relative model.  The gravity variables are all significant&#13;
(as in the relative model) and have the predicted signs. In addition,&#13;
the population coefficients are all close to one, as hypothesized. The&#13;
economic variables (income, unemployment, and farmland) are all signifi-&#13;
cant and of the hypotlhesized s'igns onl' in the areas of destination.&#13;
Urbanization in the destination is significant but has a negative sign,&#13;
opposite from that hypothesized by the city lights theory.&#13;
The coefficients of the economic variables in the regions of origin&#13;
are not all significan1., but when they are they have signs opposite to&#13;
what would be implied by the relative model. The signs for urbanization&#13;
in both the sending and receiving regions, when significant, are opposite&#13;
to those hypothesized. The interaction terms indicate that males are sig-&#13;
nificantly more likely than females to avoid destinations of high unem-&#13;
ployment and urbanization and more likely to leave areas with a high&#13;
proportion of land farmed and high unemployment.&#13;
A possible interpretation of the effect of the economic conditions&#13;
in sending and receiving areas is that while migrants flow to areas of&#13;
relatively better econcmic circumstances, more of those in changwats&#13;
with better than average economic circumstances can afford to move. 5/&#13;
This hypothesis has been suggested for Thailand by Chamratrithirong (1976)&#13;
and by researchers who have studied migration in other countries. -/&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-23-&#13;
This would imply that economic development will increase the overall level&#13;
of migration while differential levels and differential growth rates will&#13;
determine the direction of flow.&#13;
Push and Pull Factors in Migration&#13;
The gravity model of flows from i to j makes it somewhat difficult&#13;
to assess the differential importance of factors at origin and destination,&#13;
because it implicitly assumes that a joint decision is made about whether&#13;
or not to migrate and where to go. It may be, however, that these de-&#13;
cisions are more or less separate. Conditions at the origin might well&#13;
push people from a region, and it is only after such push factors trigger&#13;
migration that conditions in various destinations are reviewed to determine&#13;
where people go.&#13;
To further explore the effects of changwat characteristics at origin&#13;
and destination, two separate regressions were run. The total migration&#13;
to a changwat from all others was regressed on the characteristics of&#13;
that changwat. Then the total migration from a changwat was regressed on&#13;
the characteristics of that changwat.&#13;
The results for in-migration are as follows: -/&#13;
log M. = -9.39 + 1.02 log P. + 0.93 log I. -0.04 log U. -0.11 log Fj&#13;
(8.71)     3  (4.44)     J (0.29)      J (1.56)&#13;
2&#13;
-0.34 log UR.; r   = .54, N = 70&#13;
(1.77)      J&#13;
Of the economic variables, only income has a significant effect in&#13;
determining the total volume of in-migration. These results are virtually&#13;
identical for males and females.&#13;
The results for the province of origin are more interesting and have&#13;
2&#13;
a much higher R&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-24-&#13;
log M. = -4.24 + 0.78 log P. + 0.25 log I. + 0.29 log U. + 0.32 log F. +&#13;
1          (12.33)    1   (2.23)     1  (4.21)     1  (8.82)&#13;
0.12 log URi; -2    .87, N = 70&#13;
(1.17)&#13;
The economic variables all have a significant relationship with out-&#13;
flow, and the signs are extremely interesting. Income is positively as-&#13;
sociated with outflow supporting the ability to afford migration hypothe-&#13;
16/&#13;
sis.-Unemployment, however, has a sign that conforms to the initial&#13;
hypothesis and has more explanatory power (a higher beta value) than in-&#13;
come. Thus the higher the unemployment in an area, the greater the out-&#13;
flow of migration. Even stronger is the relationship of farmland to out-&#13;
migration: the greater the proportion of land farmed, the greater the out-&#13;
flow. Again, the results are virtually identical for males and females.&#13;
Thus, the ability to afford migration hypothesis and the push fac-&#13;
tors of high unemployment and especially limited farmland explain the&#13;
level of out-migration from a changwat, whereas income seems of primary&#13;
importance in explaining the level of inflow.&#13;
It is interesting to note that the relative model of the specific&#13;
flows from i to j yields the best prediction of signs, while the absolute&#13;
model yields expected signs for the destination variables only but gives&#13;
slightly higher adjusted R2 's. But wvhen total levels of migration to&#13;
or from a changwat are examined, the characteristics of the origin have&#13;
a much higher explanatory power. This would seem to imply that migra-&#13;
tion levels are more a push than a pull phenomenon, but once in motion,&#13;
it is the characteristics of the potential destination relative to the&#13;
origin that determine where migrants will go.   This gives a clear policy&#13;
implication: if one wants to reduce migration, one must concentrate on&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-25-&#13;
the conditions at the origin, but if the only problem is where the mi-&#13;
grants are going, one must alter the characteristics of alternative des-&#13;
tinations.&#13;
Bangkok as a Special Ca_e&#13;
Although the anomalous effect of the characteristics of origin on&#13;
migration flows has a tentative explanation, the perverse behavior of&#13;
urbanization is more d:ifficult to explain. As mentioned earlier, if mi-&#13;
gration causes higher urbanization in the destination and lower in the&#13;
origin, any simultaneous equation bias that exists would tend to strengthen&#13;
the coefficients in the hypothesized direction and thus cannot explain&#13;
the perverse results.&#13;
Part of the explarnation for the unexpected behavior of urbanization&#13;
may result from the fact that Bangkok plays a unique role in migration be-&#13;
havior in Thailand. The Longitudinal Study has shown differences in the&#13;
characteristics of those who migrate to Bangkok and those who migrate to&#13;
other urban areas (Goldstein et al., 1974). These differences might well&#13;
be reflected in different relationships between origin and destination&#13;
characteristics in migration to Bangkok and to other areas. Bangkok&#13;
may cause statistical problems as well because it is very much an outlier&#13;
on urbanization. In 1970, for exampLe, 81 percent of its population was&#13;
urban, whereas Phuket, the next most urban area, was only 34 percent&#13;
urban.-/&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-26-&#13;
Therefore, to separate the effect of Bangkok from that of other&#13;
areas, the previous an,alysis was replicated first for all migration flows&#13;
in which neither origin nor destination was Bangkok, then for flows in&#13;
which Bangkok was either the origin or destination.&#13;
Table 3 shows the results for the relative model. The results for&#13;
the non-Bangkok areas are essentially the same as those for the total&#13;
sample, but the coefficients are less significant owing at least in part&#13;
to the smaller sample size (138 cases for Bangkok versus 4,556 cases for&#13;
non-Bangkok). In particular, unemployment and urbanization are not signi-&#13;
ficant. The interaction terms show that in Bangkok males are signifi-&#13;
cantly more likely thanl females to respond to the relative scarcity of&#13;
farmland.&#13;
In the expanded model, the non-Bangkok results are again identical&#13;
to those for the total sample in both sign and significance. In Bangkok,&#13;
in addition to the gravrity variables, unemployment and income at destina-&#13;
tion have significant coefficients with the hypothesized signs, but farm-&#13;
land at destination is not significant, contrary to all other results.&#13;
It seems reasonable that few people migrate to Bangkok for its farming&#13;
opportunities, but this result also implies that those leaving Bangkok do&#13;
not tend to go to areas of high farming opportunities.- v&#13;
It is also interesting to note that the proportion of land farmed&#13;
at origin has a significantly positive effect on migration. Although this&#13;
was hypothesized to be the case, the coefficient for this variable for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-27-&#13;
Table 3.  Regression Results for the Relative Model for Bangkok and Non-Bangkok Migration (1965-1970)&#13;
(t values in parentheses)&#13;
TOTAL                     FEMALE                      MALE                        POOLED&#13;
Non-                       Non-                       Non-                        Non-&#13;
Bangkok       Bangl;ok     Bangkok       Bangkok      Bangkok       Bangkok       Bangkok      Bangkok&#13;
P1                       0.659*         0.602*      0.679*         0.569*      0.636*         0.578*      0.681*         0.579*&#13;
(6.62)        (20.46)      (6.65)        (19.31)      (6.35)        (19.50)       (8.03)       (21.59)&#13;
Pi                       1.034*         0.E;25*     0.996*         0.765*       1.066*        0.817*       0.998*        0.776*&#13;
(10.38)        (28.14)      (9.75)        (25.98)     (10.65)        (27.62)      (11.77)       (29.93)&#13;
D'                      -0.654*        -1.35*      -0.65*         -1.33*       -0.664*       -1.33*       -0.651*         1.328*&#13;
(13.38:)       (66.53)     (12.79)        (64.82)     (13.45)        (64.99)      (13.14)       (66.38)&#13;
Income I                -0.373**       _0.383*     -0.402**       _0.344*     _0.344**       -0.391*      _0.402**      o0.349*&#13;
Income J                (2.40)        (10.32)      (2.46)         (9.11)       (2.24)       (10.51)       (2.53)        (9.11)&#13;
Unemployment I           0.141          0.163*      0.133          0.142*       0.141         0.161*       0.133         0.142*&#13;
Unemployment J          (1.38)         (6.77)      (1.25)         (5.79)       (1.45)        (6.95)       (1.28)         (5.79)&#13;
Farmland I               0.159*         0.110*      0.124**        0.088*      0.190*         0.134*      -0.124**       0.087*&#13;
Farmland J              (3.06)         (8.89)      (2.25)         (6.78)       (3.75)       (10.85)       (2.31)        (6.78)&#13;
Urbanization I           0.161          0.154*      0.125          0.138*      0.188          0.174*       0.125         0.138*&#13;
Urbanization J          (1.20)         (4.74)      (0.87)         (3.94)       (1.45)        (5.11)       (0.89)        (3.94)&#13;
PI x S                                                                                                     0.048         0.117&#13;
(0.50)         (0.35)&#13;
Pj x S                                                                                                    -0.652         0.303&#13;
(0.68)         (0.90)&#13;
D x S                                                                                                     0.012          0.003&#13;
(0.18)         (0.09)&#13;
Income I                                                                                                  0.058         -0.047&#13;
Income J x S                                                                                              (0.26)        (0.88)&#13;
Unemployment I                                                                                             0.008         0.019&#13;
Unemployment J x                                                                                          (0.05)        (0.57)&#13;
Farmland I x S                                                                                            0.065          0.046*&#13;
Farmland i                                                                                                (0.87)        (2.59)&#13;
Urbanization I                                                                                            0.064          0.036&#13;
Urbanization J x S_                                                                                       (0.33)        (0.73)&#13;
-2&#13;
R                         .74            .59         .75            .57          .73           .57          .74           .57&#13;
Note: S = 1 for males&#13;
* = Significant at 0.01&#13;
** = Significant at 0.05&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 4. Regression Results for the Expanded Model for Bangkok and non-Bangkok Migration (1965-1970)&#13;
(t values in parentheses)&#13;
POOLED WITH&#13;
____________________  ___________TOTAL                             FEMALES                     MALES                      POOLED                  INTERACTION&#13;
Signs lIm-&#13;
plied by &#13;
thve Ren-Na-                                                                       Non-                        Non-                        Non-&#13;
Variable                      mdl            tankk         Bngon-agkk                 Bago Bangkok         Bangkok      Bangkok              Bangkok-      Bangkok       Bangkok&#13;
Population i                      ~~~~~0.945*   0.998*        0.979*        0.951*       0.90s*       0.967*         0.938*        0.956*       0.960*        0.923*&#13;
Population I                     (10.33)       (32.28)      (10.37)       (30.49)        (9.87)       (31.07)      (14.19)       (43.49)       (11.74)       (32.23)&#13;
Population J         (+)  ~~~~l.320*            1.218*        1.297*        1.147*        1.336*       1.206*        1.324*        1.178*        1.277*       1.119*&#13;
(39.56)  (13.73)  (3~..78)     (1.57)        (.30.82        0.3         (b.bo t)      (15.62)       (39.16)&#13;
0 ~.466*          -1.427*       -0.449*     ~1.387*         -0.481*      -1.440*       -0.467*       -1.412*       -0.455*      -1.396*&#13;
Distance                                     (9.81)       (69.75)       (9.15)       (67.79)        (9.99)       (68.79)      (13.52)       (96.93)        (9.78)       (69.66).&#13;
Income I                         ~~~~~~0.230    0.107**       0.240        0.183*        0.224         0.009         0.225         0.100*       0.205         0.136*&#13;
Income 1                         ~~~~~~~(1.31)  (2.16)       (1.30)        (3.62)        (1.27)       (0.18)        (1.75)        (2.83)        (1.2S)       (2.96)&#13;
Income J  ~     ~         ~        .97          086*          104*          0.6*         0.913*        0.781*        0.979*        0.833*       1.009*        0.820*     OD&#13;
IncOme J                         ~~~~~~~(5.59)  (17.49)      (5.63)       (17.14)        (5.22)      (1S.66)        (7.61)       (23.48)        (6.14)      (17.83)&#13;
Unemployment I                               -0.023        -0.058       -0.019         0.009        -0.023        -0.121*      -0.027        -0.066*       -0.021         0.004&#13;
(0.20)        (1.79)       (0.16)        (0.28)        (0.21)        (3.86)        (0.37)       (3.08)        (0.18)        (0.12)&#13;
Unemployment J                               (272         (11.96        (244          (841          (284         (1.8          (45)         (79)            25)9&#13;
% of Land Farmed I   ~0.303*                   -0.077*        0.260*       -0.110*       0.3S3*       -0.047*        0.307*       -0.081*       0.260*       -0.108*&#13;
% of Land Fanned I   (*           (4.96)~       (4.62)       (4.03)        (6.33)        (5.88)        (2.84)       (6.92)        (6.74)        (4.14)       (6.22)&#13;
-0.014        -0.302*        0.011        0.284*       -0.026        -0.319*       -0.013       -0,307*        0.012    ~    0.283*&#13;
% of Land Farmed J                           (0.24)       (18.01)       (0.18)       (16.26)        (0.44)       (19.20)       (0.29)       (25.54)        (0.18)      (16.18)&#13;
-0.154         O.100**       0.167        0.119*        0.180         0.079         0.173        0.091*        0.178         0.134*&#13;
Urbanization I                   ()(1.00)                  (2.19)        (1.02)       (3.32)        (1.21)        (1.74)        (1.58)       (2.83)        (1.13)        (2.90)&#13;
Urbanization J                   ~~~0.168      -O.229*       -0.082         0O.l55*     -0.196     ~   0,268*       -0.171        -0.228*      -0.071        -0.140*&#13;
Urbanization J  ~ ~ ~ ~           (1.09)        (4.91)       (0.50)        (25)          (1.32)       (5.94)        (1.56)        (7.10)        (0.45)       (3.04)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 4 (cont.)&#13;
POOLED WITH&#13;
TOTAL                   FEMALES                  MALES                   POOLED                INTERACTION&#13;
Signs Im-                                                                                          r&#13;
the Rela-&#13;
tive                      Non-                    Non-                     Non-  :                                          Non-&#13;
Variable                   Model        Bangkok      Bangkok   | Bangkok     Bangkok      Bangkok     Bangkok     Bangk.k      Bangkok     Bangkok      Bangkok&#13;
Population I * S                                                                                                                           - .  -0.037  0.069&#13;
I                                    i           I __________    (0.35)      (1.86)&#13;
Population J * S                                                                                               I                            0.077       0.113*&#13;
_______________________  .___________  __________  ___________  __________  ______________________ I __________ [  (0.74)  (3.04)&#13;
Distance * S                                                                                                                I l  l         -0.021      -0.034&#13;
I  I        I               (0.32)      (1.22)&#13;
Income I * S                                                                                                                                0.054      -0.081&#13;
I  (0.26)      (1.41)&#13;
Income J * S                                                              j            0                       l                        |  -0.061       0.007&#13;
1            1 __________                                     |(0.30)        (0.12)&#13;
Unemployment I *S                                                                                                                           0.002       -0.1U8*   Ir&#13;
(0.00)      (2.62)   1   O&#13;
Unemloyment j *                                                                                         ~~~~~~~     ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-0.013  -0.164*&#13;
Unemployment J * S- _ _ _ _ _                                                                                                              (0.08)       (3.63)&#13;
I % of Land Farmed I * S |           l            l           |           l            *           l           l           l            |   0.093       0.060**&#13;
% of Land Farmed                                          I *                                                              i               (1.06)       (2.49)&#13;
% of Land Farmed J * S                                                                                                                     -0.037      -0.037&#13;
(0.43)      (1.56)&#13;
Urbanization I * S                                                                                                                         -0.006      -0.068&#13;
(0.03)      (1.06)&#13;
Urbanization J * S                                                                                                                          0.133      -0.140**&#13;
(0.61)      (2.20)&#13;
-2R                                      0.85         0.65        0.85        0.63         0.84        0.63        0.84         0.63        0.85        0.63&#13;
Note: S = 1 for males&#13;
* Significant at 0.01&#13;
Significant at 0.05&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-30-&#13;
the total and the non-.Bangkok sample is significantly negative. This re-&#13;
sult might mean that migration to Bangkok, more so than to other areas,&#13;
is the result of diminishing agricultural opportunities in the rural sec-&#13;
tor. Alternatively, it may be a statistical artifact resulting from com-&#13;
bining migration to and from Bangkok in the same analysis.&#13;
We can test these alternatives by separating the analysis of the&#13;
two migration streams to Bangkok. The following relationship is found&#13;
between the inflow and the characteristics of the sending areas.&#13;
Mib   -5.71 + 1.01 log P. -0.43 log D. + 0.28 log I. -0.02 log U. +&#13;
(9.68)     1(6.71)         (1.59)      1 (0.16)&#13;
0.31 log F. + 0.21 log UR.; R = .83&#13;
(4.94)     1  (1.3'S)     1&#13;
Of the economic variables, only the proportion of land farmed in the send-&#13;
ing area is significant. This is further evidence of the role of scarcity&#13;
of agricultural opportunities in stimulating migration to Bangkok.&#13;
These results are quite similar to those found for in-migration for&#13;
all areas combined. One major difference between Bangkok and the total&#13;
sample, however, is that for the total sample there was no difference&#13;
between the determinants of in- and out-migration for males and females.&#13;
Separate equations for male and female migration into Bangkok, however,&#13;
show that although scarcity of land is significant for both males and&#13;
females, the effect of such scarcity on males is significantly greater.&#13;
The coefficient for females is 0.26; for males, it is 0.37. For the&#13;
total sample, the coefficient was 0.32 (.31 for females and .32 for&#13;
males).&#13;
V. SUMMARY AND POLICY IMPLICATIONS&#13;
As fertility rates continue to decline in Thailand, attention is in-&#13;
creasingly being turned toward an examination of migration as an impor-&#13;
tant feature of demographic change and one that will undoubtedly have&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31-&#13;
a major impact on the individual and collective welfare of Thailand's&#13;
population in the fut:ure. The rapid and unplanned growth of Bangkok&#13;
has highlighted some of the major problems associated with large-scale&#13;
migration and stimulated the government to include explicit population&#13;
redistribution policies and programs in the Fourth National Economic&#13;
and Social Development Plan (1977-1981).&#13;
The multivariate analysis undertaken in this paper has identified&#13;
some important factors that were associated with migration to Bangkok&#13;
and to all other provinces in Thailand in the 1965-1970 period. The&#13;
analysis presented above indicates that:&#13;
(a) The usual gravity variables (population at origin and destina-&#13;
tion and distance between (hangwats) are of paramount impor-&#13;
tance, but ecDnomic determinants of migration are also highly&#13;
significant.&#13;
(b) Economic factors predominate over the attraction of urban areas&#13;
per se as determinants of migration.&#13;
(c) The economic conditions in areas of destination relative to&#13;
those in areas of origin have significant effects in the direc-&#13;
tion hypothesized: the higher the per capita income, the lower&#13;
the unemployment, and the lower the proportion of land farmed&#13;
in the destination relative to the origin, the greater the flow&#13;
of migration between areas,holding population size and distance&#13;
constant. The expanded model also indicates that migrants&#13;
move to areas of relatively high income, low unemployment and&#13;
easy availability of farmland.&#13;
(d) Male and female migration streams seem to respond to per capita&#13;
income and unemployment in the same way. Males, however, are more&#13;
responsive than females to the scarcity or availability of farmland.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-32-&#13;
(e) Migration to and from Bangkok, and migration to and from other&#13;
areas respond similarly to relative income and the availability&#13;
of farmland. In addition, the coefficients for relative&#13;
unemployment are very similar for Bangkok and non-Bangkok migra-&#13;
tion streams, but the significance level is lower, probably be-&#13;
cause of the smaller number of cases in the Bangkok sample.&#13;
Thus, it is clear that the relative model predicts significant signs&#13;
very well, and that economic factors are far more important than the at-&#13;
traction of city lights. The separate roles of push and pull factors&#13;
are less clear.  Characteristics in the areas of destination have signi-&#13;
ficant effects in the direction implied by the relative model, but charac-&#13;
teristics in the areas of origin play a more complex role. Although higher&#13;
income in areas of destination served as a drawing card-for migrants,&#13;
higher income in areas of origin served as a stimulus to out-migration,&#13;
because people in the poorest changwats may not have had sufficient finan-&#13;
cial resources to support a move. This implies that the ability to afford&#13;
migration plans an important role in mobility in Thailand.&#13;
The scarcity of farmland in the region of origin has an unclear ef-&#13;
fect except in migration streams involving Bangkok, where it is an impor-&#13;
tant push factor, especially for males. For migration streams not involv-&#13;
ing Bangkok and for the sample as a whole, farmland in the province of&#13;
origin shows different signs depending on the specification used. If&#13;
one looks at the total migration from a province, scarcity of farmland&#13;
is a highly significant push factor. However, in testing the expanded&#13;
version of the gravity model where the dependent variable is the flow be-&#13;
tween two provinces, weD find a greater flow of migrants from areas of&#13;
less land scarcity.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-33-&#13;
This anomalous result for farmland may result either from measure-&#13;
ment problems (farm opportunities are not well captured by the proportion&#13;
of land farmed) or from the fact that our modeling has not captured the&#13;
essence of the decision-making process. Unfortunately, to test more so-&#13;
phisticated models of migration decision making, individual rather than&#13;
aggregate data are needed.&#13;
These findings suggest several implications about the future course&#13;
of migration in Thailand and possible policies to cope with any undesirable&#13;
effects of population movements. There is reason to believe that Thailand&#13;
will continue its pattern of increasing migration as development proceeds.&#13;
The impetus for migration to Bangkok and other urban areas is likely to&#13;
increase as uncultivated arable land becomes more and more scarce. Over-&#13;
all, inequalities in the income distribution among changwats will continue&#13;
to draw migrants to more prosperous areas of the country.&#13;
Our analysis indicates that the usual recommendation of&#13;
rural development projects may not dliscourage migration to Bang-&#13;
kok or other relatively developed areas of Thailand. The effects of&#13;
rural development projects on migration are by no means unambiguous. -/&#13;
For example, mechanization of agriculture can result in an increased&#13;
standard of living for some rural residents, but it may also provide an&#13;
impetus to out-migration by simultaneously reducing the number of farm&#13;
jobs and augmenting the ability of farmers to afford migration. This&#13;
does not mean that the government should not pursue rural development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-34-&#13;
policies,, but it is important to consider the possible differential effects&#13;
of employment: creationi versus income generation on migration.&#13;
In fact, measures to restrict further expansion of income and em-&#13;
ployment opportunities in areas of destination may be more effective&#13;
in curtailing undesirable population flows than efforts to develop rural&#13;
areas. This end could be accomplished, for example, by limiting increases&#13;
in minimum wages in Bangkok and other crowded areas and restricting de-&#13;
velopment of factories in congested areas. Measures of this type are&#13;
likely to be only part:ly successful, however, since a large proportion of&#13;
jobs available to migrants are in the service sector and are often not sub-&#13;
20/&#13;
ject to minimum wage regulation or other types of government controls.-O&#13;
Whatever migration-related policies and programs are ultimately&#13;
adopted, both the number of migrants and migration rates will probably&#13;
continue to increase. Therefore, it would be wise to try to project the&#13;
direction and magnitude of migration flows in order to adjust for such&#13;
changes in development plans. The relationships established in the mi-&#13;
gration regressions above can be useful in constructing population pro-&#13;
jections at the changwat level. Such projections can help in long-range&#13;
planning for the provision of public services and in establishing the need&#13;
for government programs for migrants.&#13;
The trend in migration in Thailand also highlights the neecl for&#13;
studies of the effects of migration on both origin and destination&#13;
areas. Present policies take into account some of the disadvantages of&#13;
migration, such as the strain on urban public services and the brain&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-35-&#13;
drain from rural areas.  But little is known about the possible advan-&#13;
tages of population movements. To what extent do migrants act as cata-&#13;
lysts for the dispersal of modern ideas? Are remittance flows from mi-&#13;
grants a major factor in aiding rural development? This paper has con-&#13;
tributed to an understanding of the causes of internal migration in&#13;
Thailand, but much more must be known about the consequences of migra-&#13;
tion to reach a more complete understanding of population movement and to&#13;
provide more effective input into the policy-making process.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-36-&#13;
FOOTNOTES&#13;
1/  In 1970, there were 71 changwats in Thailand with an average population&#13;
of about 500,000 persons.&#13;
2/ Although the National Economic and Social Development Board has often&#13;
expressed the need. for population projections for individual changwats,&#13;
the production of such projections has been hampered by a lack of&#13;
reliable and timely data on fertility, mortality, and especially&#13;
migration at the changwat level.&#13;
3/  For example, it may be that areas of very low educational attainment&#13;
may be the ones with the greatest out-migration. But within those areas&#13;
it might be the most educated individuals who migrate.&#13;
4/ Net migration between regions is more difficult to incorporate in the&#13;
gravity models presented below since the dependent variable can take&#13;
on negative as well as positive values, and the gravity model requires&#13;
taking the log of the dependent variable.&#13;
5/ The importance of the "bright l:Lghts" hypothesis is stressed, for&#13;
example, in May and Skeldon (1977).&#13;
6/ These data include very little temporary migration, since the census&#13;
was a de Jure one and permanent residence was recorded as current&#13;
residence.. People away from home for several months were not counted&#13;
as migrants.&#13;
7/  Ihe measures of land farmed and unemployment are not ideal.    Theoretically&#13;
we would want to include a measure of land quality as well as availability,&#13;
but an adequate measure of quality could not be found. The unemployment&#13;
variable :Lncludes those waiting for the farm season. This variable is&#13;
highly negatively correlated with urbanization, but standard unemployment&#13;
rates are extremely low.&#13;
8/  For urbanization, which we expect to increase inflow and reduce outflow,&#13;
if the city lights hypothesis is correct, we would anticipate that if&#13;
migration is focused on urban areas, then migration would increase&#13;
the proportion urban in 1970 and the observed relationship between&#13;
migration and urbanization would overstate the effect of urbanization&#13;
on migration. For unemployment, which should reduce inflow and increase&#13;
outflow, if migrati:on increases unemployment at the destination and&#13;
reduces unemployment at the origin, the unemployment coefficients would&#13;
underestimate the effect of unemployment on migration.&#13;
9/ Between 1965 and 1970 only five percent of the population five years of&#13;
age and over moved across changwat boundaries.&#13;
10/ The "total," "male," and "female" regressions have 70 x 69 observations&#13;
on gross migration (less any migration streams that equal zero). The&#13;
pooled sample has twice as many observations, since both male and female&#13;
flows are included as separate observations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-38-&#13;
urban migration." If the projects are employment creating, they may&#13;
reduce migration out of an area, but this possibility is only supported&#13;
in the total outmigration formulation and not in the directional analysis&#13;
of Tables 2 and 4.&#13;
20/ According to the Survey of Migration in Bangkok Metropolis (Thailand,&#13;
NSO, 1979), 43 percent of recent migrants working in Bangkok were employed&#13;
in service industries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-39-&#13;
REFERE.NCES&#13;
Arnold, Fred, and Supani Boonpratuarig. -1970 Population and Housing Cen-&#13;
cus: Migra1ion. Subject Report No. 2, National Statistical Office,&#13;
Bangkok, 1976.&#13;
Arnold, Fred, and Suwanlee Piampiti. *Research and Policy Review of Fe-&#13;
male Migration in Thailand. Paper prepared for Women in the Cities&#13;
Working Group. East-West Population Institute, Honolulu, March, 1979.&#13;
Chamratrithirong, Apichat.   "Fertility, Nuptiality and Migration in Thai-&#13;
land, 1970 Census: Multiphasic Response Theory," Brown University,&#13;
Ph.D. thesis, 1976.&#13;
Chamratrithirong, Apichat.   "Migration in Greater Bangkok, 1960 Census,"&#13;
Brown University, M.A. thesis, 1973.&#13;
Chapman, E. C., and A. C. B. Allen. Internal Migration in Thailand. Paper&#13;
presented at ANZAAS Conference, Hobart, Australia, 1965.&#13;
Connell, John, et al. Migration from Rural Areas: The Evidence from Vil-&#13;
lage Studies, Oxford University Press, Delhi, 1976.&#13;
Garnjana-Goonchorn, Savitri. "Internal Migration into the Bangkok Metro-&#13;
politan Area," University of Pittsburgh, Ph.D. thesis, 1974.&#13;
Goldstein, Sidney. "Interrelations between Migration and Fertility in&#13;
Thailand," 'Demography, 10, 1973, pp. 225-41..&#13;
Goldstein, Sidney, and Pichit Pitaktepsombati. Migration and Urban Growth&#13;
in Thailand: An ExpLoration of Interrelations among Origin, Recency,&#13;
and Frequency of Moves. Paper No. 24, Institute of Population Studies,&#13;
Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 1974.&#13;
Goldstein, Sicdney, Vis-d Prachuabmoh, and Alice Goldstein.  Urban-Rural&#13;
Migration Different`als in Thailand.   Research Report No. 12, Insti-&#13;
tute of Population Studies, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 1974.&#13;
Goldstein, Sidney, et al. "Report submitted to the Center for Population&#13;
Research," National Institute of Child Health and Human Development,&#13;
Washington, D.C.&#13;
Harris, J., and M. P. Todaro.   "Migration, Unemployment and Development:&#13;
A Two-Sector Analysis," American Economic Review, 60 (March 1970),&#13;
pp. 126-42.&#13;
International Labor Office. Report to the Government of Thailand on In-&#13;
ternal Migration. 'ELO, Geneva, 1965.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-40-&#13;
Lee, Everett S. "A Theory of Migration," Demography, 3, No. 1, 1966,&#13;
pp. 47-57.&#13;
Lowry, Ira S. Migration and Metropolitan Growth: Two Analytical Models.&#13;
Chandler Publishing Co., San Francisco, 1966.&#13;
May, R. J., and Ronald Skeldon. "Internal Migration in Papua New Guinea,"&#13;
in Change and Movemrent: Readings in Internal Migration in Papua New&#13;
Guinea, R. J. May (ed.), Australian National University, Canberra, 1977.&#13;
Meinkoth, Marian R. "'Migration in Thailand with Particular Reference to&#13;
the Northeast," Economic and Business Bulletin, 14, 1962. pp. 3-45.&#13;
Ng, Ronald C. Y. "Recent Internal Population Movement in Thailand,"&#13;
A_nals of the Association of American Geographers, 59, 1969, pp. 710-&#13;
30.&#13;
Ng, Ronald C. Y.   "A Study of Internal Migration in Thailand," Journal&#13;
of Tropical Geography, 31, 1970, pp. 65-78.&#13;
Piampiti, Suwanlee. Policies and Programs for Female Migration in Thai-&#13;
land. Paper prepared for Women in the Cities Working Group, East-West&#13;
Population Institute, Honolulu, March, 1979.&#13;
Piampiti, Suwanlee. Effects of Migration on Urban Development-in the&#13;
Southern Region of Thailand. SEAPRAP Research Report No. 9, Bangkok,&#13;
1976.&#13;
Piampiti, Suwanlee.   Female Migrants in the Bangkok Metropolis.    National&#13;
Institute of Development Administration, School of Applied Statistics,&#13;
Bangkok, n. d.&#13;
Prachuabmoh, Visid, and Penporn Tirasawat. Internal Migration in Thailand.&#13;
Paper No. 7, Institute of Population Studies, Chulalongkorn University,&#13;
Bangkok, 1974.&#13;
Prasartkul, Pramote. "Patterns and Determinants of Internal Migration in&#13;
Thailand," Cornell University, Ph.D. thesis, 1977.&#13;
Ravenstein, E. G. "The Laws of Migration," Journal of the Royal Statis-&#13;
tical Society, 48 and 52, June, :1885 and-June, 1889.&#13;
Rhoda, Richard E. "Development Activities and Rural-Urban Migration: Is&#13;
It Possible to Keep them Down on the Farm?" Office of Urban Develop-&#13;
ment, Bureau for Development Support, Agency for International Develop-&#13;
ment, Washington, D. C., 1979.&#13;
Siripak, Wiwit. "Patterns and Correlates of Internal Migration in Thailand,"&#13;
University of Chicago, M.A. thesis, 1965.&#13;
Sjaastad, Larry A. "The Costs and Returns of Human Migration," Journal&#13;
of Political Economy, 70(October, 1962), Part 2, pp. 80-93.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-41-&#13;
Srisawas, Narong. "Factors Associated with Internal Migration in Thailand,&#13;
1960-1970," Pennsylvania State University, Ph.D. thesis, 1977.&#13;
Sternstein, Larry. "tnternal Migration and Regional Development: The&#13;
Khon Kaen Development Centre of Northeast Thailand," Journal of South-&#13;
east Asian Studies, 8, 1977, pp. 106-16.&#13;
Stouffer, Samuel A. "Intervening Opportunities and Competing Migrants,"&#13;
Journal of Regional Sciences, 1, No. 1, 1966, pp. 1-26.&#13;
Textor, R. B. From Peasant to Pedicab. Cultural Report Series No. 9,&#13;
Southeast Asia Studies, Yale University, New Haven, 1961.&#13;
Thailand, National Economic and Social Development Board. The Fourth Na-&#13;
tional Economic and. Social Development Plan (1977-1981). National&#13;
Economic and Social Development Board, Office of the Prime Minister,&#13;
Bangkok.&#13;
Thailand, National Statistical Office. The Survey of Migration in Bang-&#13;
kok Metropolis, 1978, Bangkok, 1979.&#13;
Thailand,National Statistical Office.    1970 Census of Population and Hous-&#13;
ing, Whole Kingdom, Bangkok, 1973.&#13;
Tirasawat, Penporn. Urbanization and Migrant Adjustment in Thailand.&#13;
SEAPRAP Research Report No. 10, Bangkok, 1977.&#13;
Todaro, Michael P. "Internal Migration in Developing Countries: A Survey,"&#13;
in Population and l.conomic Change in Developing Countries, Richard A.&#13;
Easterlin (ed.), University of Chicago Press, Chicago, 1980.&#13;
Todaro, Michael P.   "A Model of Labor Migration and Urban Unemployment in&#13;
Less Developed Countries," American Economic Review, 59 (March, 1969),&#13;
pp. 138-48.&#13;
Wichiencharoen, Adul. "Movements of Population within Thailand," Journal&#13;
of Public Administration, Vol. 1, No. 2, 1960.&#13;
Zipf, George Kingsley. "The P1P2/D Hypothesis: On the Intercity Movement&#13;
of Persons," American Sociological Review, 11, December, 1946, pp.&#13;
677-86.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PUB HG3881.5 .W57 W67 no.416&#13;
Arnold, Fred.&#13;
Economic motivation versus&#13;
city lights : testing&#13;
hypotheses about&#13;
PUB HG3881.5.W57 W67 no.416&#13;
Arnold, Fred.&#13;
Economic motivation versus&#13;
city lights : testing&#13;
hypotheses&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
mC)&#13;
.0T0 C) lmmv&#13;
I i&#13;
oz&#13;
rn-W&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1555013">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1980/09/1555013/economic-motivation-versus-city-lights-testing-hypotheses-inter-changwat-migration-thailand
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1980/09/1555013/economic-motivation-versus-city-lights-testing-hypotheses-inter-changwat-migration-thailand</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1980/09/1555013/economic-motivation-versus-city-lights-testing-hypotheses-inter-changwat-migration-thailand</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/01/08/000178830_98101903405269/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/01/08/000178830_98101903405269/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-01-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1980-09-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Economic motivation versus city lights :
            testing hypotheses about inter-Changwat migration in Thailand
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The models tested here are of the
            gravity flow variety. They are tested in two basic forms,
            one constrained and one unconstrained. It is very clear from
            this analysis that: (1) economic factors predominate over
            the non-economic attraction of urban areas; (2) the economic
            conditions in destinations relative to origins have
            significant relationships in the hypothesized direction; (3)
            male and female migration streams respond to per capita
            income and unemployment in the same way but males are more
            responsive to the scarcity or availability of farmland; (4)
            migration to and from Bangkok tends to respond in a very
            similar manner to relative income and the availability of
            farmland as migration to and from other areas; (5) in the
            unconstrained model, conditions in the area of destination
            all have significant relationships of the hypothesized
            signs; (6) conditions in the areas of origin play a far more
            complex role, since conditions at the area of origin
            determine not only the push to migrate, but also the ability
            to afford to migrate; (7) the sign and significance of other
            economic variables in the origin vary depending on the specifications.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Economic motivation versus city lights :
            testing hypotheses about inter-Changwat migration in Thailand
        </docna>
        <display_title>Economic motivation versus city
            lights : testing hypotheses about inter-Changwat migration
            in Thailand</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1980/09/1555013/economic-motivation-versus-city-lights-testing-hypotheses-inter-changwat-migration-thailand</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Municipal Financial Management,Drylands &amp; Desertification,Voluntary and Involuntary Resettlement</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>Thailand</count>
        <authors>
            <author>ARNOLD, F.</author>
            <author>COCHRANE, S.</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southeast Asia!$!80471</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903405269</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Labor markets and employment</subsc>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 416</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Social Protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Agricultural land; Land resources;
            Migrations; Per capita income; Unemployment
            cities,climate,decision making,economic
            conditions,economic opportunities,Farmers,farming,health
            services,housing,human settlements,income,internal
            migration,land
            use,laws,marketing,migrants,migration,migration
            patterns,migration rates,migration
            streams,motivation,personality,public services,public
            utilities,rate of migration,sparsely populated
            areas,transportation,unemployment,urban growth,urbanization,wages
        </keywd>
        <owner>EAC</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southeast Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP416</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Child Survival and Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Early Child and Children's Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative and Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Management and Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Capital</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing People</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Involuntary Land Acquisition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing and Land</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing and Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Housing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Land</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Land Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>In-Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Child Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Involuntary Resettlement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Land Supply and Markets</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Thailand</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>