<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>sZwy$ Ofeu0                        e2e                                           t&#13;
SWP318&#13;
Wog-P   Bank§~&amp;ffWarMig Papeir No. 318                                    WATIPKGTOTN. n C. 2:44S1&#13;
February 1979&#13;
The views and interpretations in this clocumert zre- th-ose of th n, a thors&#13;
and shou!d not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated&#13;
organizations or to any individual acting in their heha!f.&#13;
Prepared by: Rashid Faruqee&#13;
Population and Humar ResoL rces Div;s,on&#13;
Development Econo i&#13;
Copyright © 1979&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Wa    H Street, N.W. W 3  U. S                          X&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the&#13;
author and should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its&#13;
affiliated organizations or to any individual acting in their&#13;
behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 318&#13;
February 1979&#13;
SOURCES OF FERTILITY DECLINE:&#13;
FACTOR ANALYSIS OF INTER-COUNTRY. DATA&#13;
In recent times, a number of developing countries have experienced&#13;
a decline in fertility making it possible to study the factors inducing such&#13;
decline. This subject constitutes the core of a continuing debate between&#13;
those who advocate intensive family planning programs irrespective of the&#13;
level of socio-economic development and those who support the proposition&#13;
that "development is the best contraceptive." Although most people would&#13;
take a position in between these two extremes, a serious debate still&#13;
continues regarding the desired sequence and mix of the two. A crucial&#13;
policy aspect of the debate is the issue whether family planning programs&#13;
can be a useful trade-off for socio-economic development in a high fertility&#13;
population.&#13;
The present study takes our understanding about the relative&#13;
significance of family planning and development a step further. Studies&#13;
undertaken so far could not fully separate the influences of family&#13;
planning and development in the analysis of the effects of interrelated&#13;
variables representing those dimensions. The present study, using factor&#13;
analysis, collapses a set of interrelated variables in terms of a smaller&#13;
number of mutually independent factors, which make it possible to separate&#13;
out the effects of family planning program inputs and socio-economic&#13;
development.&#13;
The findings of this study confirm the significant role if family&#13;
planning, but socio-economic development clearly emerges as the mo:e impor-&#13;
tant of the two in influencing fertility decline.&#13;
Prepared ty: Rashid Faruqee&#13;
Population and Human Resources Division&#13;
Development Economics Department&#13;
Copyright 0 1979&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
1.   INTRODUCTION AND BACKGROUND     .   .................................          1&#13;
Sources of Fertility Decline:     The Debate.                             2&#13;
Demographic Transition Theory.                                            4&#13;
A Synopsis of Empirical Theory.                                           6&#13;
2. FACTOR ANALYSIS OF INTER-COUNTRY DATA.                                           8&#13;
The Motivation .......................--------.......                     8&#13;
Data and Their Sources ........................----.......               11&#13;
The Dependent Variable .14&#13;
3. MAJOR FINDINGS AND DISCUSSIONS .16&#13;
Factor Analysis of Independent Variables .16&#13;
Analysis with Fertility Variables .22&#13;
General Observations ....................       -   -   -   -  ..        29&#13;
Regression Analysis with Factors .30&#13;
SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS .39&#13;
BIBLIOGRAPHY ................................-----...                         42&#13;
APPENDIX A&#13;
List of Tables&#13;
Table 1   -   List of Variables ...................................           12&#13;
Table 2   -   Crude Birth Rates of Developing Countries, 1970 &amp; 1975          15&#13;
Table 3   -   Rotated Factor Matrix of 15 Independent Variables ....          17&#13;
Table 4   -   Rotated Factor Matrix of 15 Independent Variables&#13;
and % Change in CBR .24&#13;
Table 5   -   Rotated Factor Matrix of 15 Independent Variables,&#13;
% Change in CBR and CBR 1970 .26&#13;
Table 6   -   Rotated Factor Matrix of 15 Independent Variables.,&#13;
% Change in CBR and CBR 1975 .28&#13;
Table 7   -   Regression Results: Dependent Variable, % Decline&#13;
in CBR 1970-75 .............                                 -31&#13;
Table 8   -   Regression Results:    Dependent Variable, CBR 1975 ....        33&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
1. INTRODUCTION AND BACKGROUND&#13;
In recent times, many countries have experienced a decline in&#13;
their birth rates. This trend, which started in the mid-fifties in a few&#13;
developing countries, gained momentum in the sixties, and by the early&#13;
seventies could be observed in many more countries. Mr. McNamara in&#13;
his 1977 address on population to the Massachusetts Institute of Technology&#13;
noted that a decline in the crude birth rate (CBR) had occurred in 77 of 88&#13;
developing countries. 1/ Recent birth rate data for about 50 countries&#13;
show that it is in 1970-75 that the most pronounced and widespread decline&#13;
in fertility has taken place. Such a demographic trend makes it possible&#13;
to take a fresh look at the sources of fertility declines, with their&#13;
implications for population policy.&#13;
One approach to understanding the sources of fertility decline&#13;
is to identify the determinants of fertility behavior. Research on&#13;
fertility determinants has been done at various levels, the most obvious&#13;
1/ McNamara, Robert S. Address to the Massachusetts Institute of Tech-&#13;
nology, IBRD, Washington, 1977, p. 16, also Tables V and VI. See&#13;
also Burch, Thomas K. "Fertility in the Developing World: Trends,&#13;
Causes and Some Reflections on Policy." The Population Council,&#13;
1975 (mimeo).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
and relevant being the household. 1/ The present paper focuses on the&#13;
sources of fertility decline at the country level, and bears on the contro-&#13;
versy regarding the effectiveness of family planning (FP) programs in&#13;
reducing fertility. Though behavioral variables are not explicitly analyzed,&#13;
assumptions about them are integral to our consideration of socio-economic&#13;
factors as influences on fertility.&#13;
Sources of Fertility Decline: the Debate&#13;
Many authors, including those of a recent review (Hermalin and&#13;
Chandrashekaran, 1976), have attributed some part of the fertility decline&#13;
in selected countries to an FP program, after allowing for the trend that is&#13;
1/  Sezeral reviews of determinants research exist.    The most comprehensive&#13;
source of correlates of fertility behavior is the U.N. document, Deter-&#13;
minants and Consequences of Population Trends. The source, although&#13;
fairly exhaustive, is somewhat descriptive. Another review is by&#13;
McGreevey and Birdsall of the Smithsonian Institute. This source,&#13;
although limited in coverage, analytically evaluates the empirical&#13;
works. Another similar source is Mason, et al., a survey prepared&#13;
for AID/NESA (U.S. Agency for International Development/Near East and&#13;
South Asia Bureau). Other important surveys are Hawthorn (1969),&#13;
Williams (1973), Schultz (1971, 1973, 1974). These sources only&#13;
survey the correlates of fertility along with empirical results on&#13;
those aspects. There is no attempt, in these surveys, to present a&#13;
theoretical framework to underline the cause-effect relationships.&#13;
However, there have been surveys of the literature on economic&#13;
determinants presented in a purely economic framework. To name just&#13;
a few, these sources are Easterlin (1969), W. C. Robinson and Horlacker&#13;
(1971), Leibenstein (1974) and Turchi (1975). Two recent IBRD reviews&#13;
are also relevant, Birdsall and Faruqee (1977), which treats the subject&#13;
in the overall framework of population-development relationships and&#13;
Cochrane (1977), which reviews the literature in relation qo one&#13;
specific determinant, education.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
already evident. Freedman and Berelson (1976) attempted to evaluate&#13;
the contention that FP cannot succeed unless a certain socio-economic&#13;
level is attained. Th- concluded, after analyzing inter-country data,&#13;
that both program efforts and social setting affect performance. l/&#13;
Their results seem to suggest that FP can be effective regardless of&#13;
the social setting, but despite their strong and elaboraie defense&#13;
of the record of family planning programs, controversy still persists&#13;
as to which factor plays a greater role in inducing a decline in&#13;
fertility - an intensive FP program or general socio-economic&#13;
development. 2/&#13;
1/ At the time of the first draft of this paper, the Freedman-Berelson&#13;
piece was the most important work, in my opinion, on the subject.&#13;
However, there have been a number of studies since then; the most&#13;
important being an update of the paper by Mauldin &amp; Berelson (1978)&#13;
which is briefly reviewed later. There has been also a recent paper&#13;
by Tsui and Bogue (1978).&#13;
2/ Although most people would accept the roles of both the factors,&#13;
gene:-alizations are not uncommon where one or the other is given&#13;
full credit for the observed decline in fertility. For the a3sertion&#13;
that recent fertility decline is primarily due to large scale family&#13;
planiiing programs, see T. V. Ravenholt and John Chao (1974). The&#13;
othei: extreme view ascribing the cause of fertility decline to&#13;
large-scale social reform with strong elements of redistribution&#13;
of income is expressed in Rich (1973) and Kocher (1973). Among&#13;
those who accept the roles of both, there is a wide spectrum of&#13;
views pertaining to the relative significance of socic-economic&#13;
development and FP program efforts as well as to their sequence&#13;
and mix. This paper reviews, somewhat selectively, these views&#13;
as well as presents further analysis made possible from recent&#13;
inter-country data.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
The above controversy dominated the World Population Conference&#13;
at Bucharest in 1974. The fear that FP could inhibit economic development&#13;
by diverting funds from investment for development must have contributed&#13;
to the debate. 1/ Strong advocates of socio-economic development have&#13;
increasingly turned to official adoption of FP programs, but the debate is&#13;
far from over. At the policy level the question is whether government&#13;
delivery of FP is desirable; at the operational level, the issue is how&#13;
to measure the fertility impact of FP programs. 2/&#13;
Demographic Transition Theory&#13;
Based on the experience of industrialized countries, the demo-&#13;
graphic transition theory, in its simplest form, asserts that with the&#13;
process of economic development first mortality and later fertility&#13;
decline. Developing countries where mortality has already fallen are&#13;
thus expected to go from a stage of low mortality and continued high&#13;
fertility to a state of low mortality and low fertility, as in the&#13;
developed countries.&#13;
1/ It should, however, be noted that in most countries FP claims less&#13;
than one percent of the total budget of the government.&#13;
2/ We have characterized the debate in the most commonly perceived form.&#13;
Analytically, (and also from the policy point of view), the more&#13;
significant issue is whether family planning programs, by motivating&#13;
prospective clients and changing their behavior, can be a useful&#13;
(effective) trade-off possibility for socio-economic development in&#13;
high fertility populations. Obviously, the issue in this form focuses&#13;
more narrowly on the relative profitability of using resources in&#13;
family planning and socio-economic development at the margin and&#13;
stresses the demand creation component (in comparison to mere&#13;
delivery of services) of family planning. However, an understanding&#13;
of the points regarding the common debate (as characterized in the&#13;
text) is helpful for the more analytical issue outlined in this&#13;
footnote.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
Related to the theory of demographic transition is "the threshold&#13;
hypothesis" which asserts, among other things, that a threshold level of&#13;
development has to be reached before fertility will decline. It may be&#13;
inferred from these theories that a family planning program cannot be&#13;
effective below a certain level of development. Sociologists have&#13;
referred to this point as closely linked with the level of "modernization,"&#13;
and economists have attempted to associate it with a certain standard of&#13;
living. 1/ The theory of demographic transition has taken various forms,&#13;
and one analysis (Coale, 1973) demonstrates several exceptions to the&#13;
predicted pattern. Coale concludes, after noting these exceptions, that&#13;
the power of the theory lies in its ability to predict fertility and&#13;
mortality given "sufficient" modernization, while its weakness lies in&#13;
the difficulty of defining exactly what is sufficient. 2/&#13;
Caldwell (1976) has argued that the transition theory needs to&#13;
be re-examined, since in all societies, at every stage of development,&#13;
actual fertility behavior is the result of a rational choice. Caldwell&#13;
asserts that fertility in a particular society is high or low because&#13;
of the differential economic benefits accruing from it to potential&#13;
l/ Many economists have approached the analysis of fertility behavior&#13;
at the household level, by applying essentially micro-economic theory&#13;
framework to explain household decisions as regards family size.&#13;
Income is an important variable in that framework. See footnote on&#13;
page 1.&#13;
2/ Coale adds three preconditions for a sustained decline in fertility&#13;
to occur as demographic process is predicted by the theory:&#13;
(1) Fertility must be within the calculus of conscious choice.&#13;
(2) Reduced fertility must be advantageous.&#13;
(3) Effective techniques of fertility reduction must be available.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
parents and their families. 1/ He emphasizes the need to do more research&#13;
on family level variables.&#13;
Although there are variations in the formulation of the demo-&#13;
graphic transition theory its central point is that at a sufficiently high&#13;
level of economic development, fertility begins to decline, leading&#13;
eventually to a relatively low population growth rate.&#13;
A Synopsis of Empirical Evidence&#13;
Broadly speaking, the studies on sources and processes of&#13;
fertility decline fall into three categories: first, those which aim at&#13;
proving or disproving the demographic transition theory or the threshold&#13;
hypothesis; second, those which focus on measuring the impact of family&#13;
planning programs; last, and most related to our purpose, those which aim&#13;
to quantify the relative significance of socio-economic development and&#13;
FP program inputs in explaining FP performance or fertilitv decline.&#13;
The findings of the studies in the first category are not&#13;
conclusive; many of these point out the exceptions to the pattern that is&#13;
predicted by the demographic and threshold theories. Some studies in&#13;
this category (e.g., Kirk, 1971) attempt to identify the level of develop-&#13;
ment at which rapid fertility decline would start to occur.&#13;
1/  Caldwell's basic thesis is contained in the following iines:     "There&#13;
are only two types of fertility regime, with the exceptional situation&#13;
at the time of transition: one where there is no economic gain to&#13;
individuals from restricting fertility; and the second when there is&#13;
often or eventually economic gain from such restriction."    His theory&#13;
is that between the extremes of maximum and minimum family sizes,&#13;
society's social or psychological reasons and not economic ones affect&#13;
the actual family   size pertaining to that societv.   He argues that the&#13;
movement from a society characterized by economically unrestricted&#13;
fertility to a restricted regime is essentially the product oF social&#13;
rather than econcmic chan2e.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Country-specific studies seeking to establish how much fertility&#13;
decline can be ascribed to family planning have generally found that its&#13;
impact has been significant; the quantitative measurement of the impact&#13;
in terms of the percentage of the total decline explained by family&#13;
planning, however, has been varied, lying between 20 to 60 percent. It&#13;
is also found that in countries where fertility is already declining,&#13;
family planning has been most effective.&#13;
The third category of research, in which the present study would&#13;
fall, consists of cross-sectoral studies in an inter-country or inter-region&#13;
framework. These studies aim at analyzing quantitatively the relative&#13;
significance of socio-economic development and family planning program&#13;
inputs in explaining family planning program performance or fertility&#13;
decline. The most comprehensive study so far is by Mauldin and Berelson&#13;
(1978). The results obtained by them are very similar to the findings of&#13;
most of the studies in this category and confirm that family planning has&#13;
a significant effect on fertility decline independent of the socio-&#13;
economic factors, which, of course, have a substantial relationship with&#13;
fertility decline. In comparison to earlier results, this study finds&#13;
stronger evidence then before that socio-economic development and family&#13;
planning efforts go together most effectively - there seems to be a&#13;
synergetic effect of the combination of the two. Another recent study,&#13;
Tsui and Bogue (1978), not nearly as rigorous as the other paper, seeks&#13;
to establish a far more significant role of family planning in explaining&#13;
fertility decline than most other works in this category.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
2. FACTOR ANALYSIS OF INTER-COUNTRY DATA&#13;
(a) The Motivation. A review of cross-sectional studies would high-&#13;
light some of their limitations. First, none of them has effectively&#13;
addressed the issue of inter-relatedness of the dimensions represented&#13;
by the explanatory variables. Some of the early studies have simply&#13;
ignored this problem. A few others, notably Srikantan (1977), and King,&#13;
et al. (1974), have employed stepwise regression; Srikantan uses both&#13;
path and regression models. Both the sources admit that their approaches&#13;
did not fully solve the problem of interdependence of explanatory variables.&#13;
The recent work by Mauldin and Berelson (1978) also addresses the problem&#13;
of interdependence of the socio-economic indicators and family planning&#13;
effect variables, but does not fully disentangle their effects on fertility&#13;
decline. These results, again using stepwise regression, show that the&#13;
most important determinant of fertility decline is the joint effect of&#13;
social setting and family planning program effect.&#13;
Second, excepting a few recent studies (Freedman and Berelson,&#13;
1976, Mauldin and Berelson, 1978, Tsui and Bogue, 1978), most of the&#13;
studies only analyzed fertility levels and not changes in fertility.&#13;
The operational significance of using fertility decline, rather than the&#13;
fertility level itself, as a dependent variable, is obvious. If the&#13;
research results show that the level of fertility is e-xplained by a host&#13;
of factors, we cannot still be sure that fertility decline can be triggered&#13;
by those factors within a given time framework.    Using fertility decline&#13;
as the depen-dent variable gives a better indication of how and whv&#13;
.ertility decline can be expected to occur.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
Third, in all the studies reviewed, variables used as proxies&#13;
for living standards have indicated only the level of development, rather&#13;
than changes in living standards over time. 1/ This makes it necessary to&#13;
assume that if a relationship between fertility and level of development&#13;
is established, then a decline in fertility can be achieved through a&#13;
change in level of living. Normally if two variables are associated, a&#13;
change in the level of one may be used to predict the direction and magni-&#13;
tude of change in the other; but the dynamics of socio-economic development&#13;
may not be at all adequately represented by static cross-sectional analysis.&#13;
In the transition to a higher level of living, certain sociological or&#13;
psychological factors, e.g., aspirations, may have pronounced effects on&#13;
fertility attitudes and behavior. It is, therefore, important to include&#13;
variables representing the rate of economic progress in addition to level&#13;
indicators.&#13;
Last, early studies were confined to a rather limited data base,&#13;
the number of observations being not more than 20. Recently the data base&#13;
has been widened substantially, creating another kind of problem. Some of&#13;
the recent studies (e.g., Mauldin and Berelson, 1978) use data on about 90&#13;
countries, which are by anybody's standard far more than they can support&#13;
with reliable estimates on the kinds of variables used in the study. In&#13;
our study we have carefully chosen those countries on which dependable&#13;
data, especially on demographic variables, are available.&#13;
1/ One should, however, note that Mauldin and Berelson emphasize the need&#13;
of "change analysis," but refrain from doing it on the grounds of data&#13;
availability. Moreover, they mention the need of using change in&#13;
socio-economic variables over time in place of "state at a given time,"&#13;
whereas we have included both state and change variables in our study.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
The form of the present study is designed to overcome the above&#13;
limitations. First, it uses factor analysis to identify a few underlying&#13;
dimensions, which are extracted so as to be independent of each other. l/&#13;
Condensation of variables into a few distinct factors or dimensions is also&#13;
highly relevant for inter-country analysis, since any single socio-economic&#13;
indicator in isolation may present a serious problem of comparability&#13;
between countries, whereas a cluster of allied indicators may smooth out&#13;
the variations arising from a use of divergent definitions. 2/ The study&#13;
1/   The purpose of factor analysis is to collapse the set of variables&#13;
linearly in terms of a smaller number of factors. This is done (in&#13;
this study) by a technique called principal component method, which&#13;
transforms a given set of variables into a set of composite variables&#13;
(principal components) that are orthogonal to each other (see Harman,&#13;
1967 and Rummel, 1970). The factors extracted are then rotated, in our&#13;
case by using varimax criteria. The emerging factors after rotation&#13;
will have the following properties: (a) the factors are linear com-&#13;
binations of the original variables, each successive factor being&#13;
chosen in a way that maximizes the percentage of the total variance in&#13;
the data ascribable to the factor after the previous factor was taken&#13;
care of, (b) those variables which are highly inter-related will have&#13;
high loading (correlation) with the same factor, (c) the variables&#13;
aligned to a given factor are those that are most independent of the&#13;
variables close to the other factor, (d) the factors are independent of&#13;
each other, (e) the number of factors initially extracted and subse-&#13;
quently rotated is smaller than the number of variables in the data;&#13;
the exact number depends on the size of the eigen value arbitrarily&#13;
selected to limit the number of factors. Factor analysis, thus, helps&#13;
in condensing the variables in distinct dimensions.&#13;
2/   It should be noted that although the factor analytical technique mini-&#13;
mizes the problems of inter-country comparison of single variables by&#13;
deriving a few dimensions out of the variables, quantitative comparison&#13;
of derived statistics should still be done with caution. However,&#13;
inter-country data have been studied quite extensively, some of which&#13;
are noted in our short review. Many inter-country analyses have been&#13;
done in other areas. Factor analysis was first done in an inter-&#13;
country setting by I. Adelman and C. T. Morris; Society, Politics and&#13;
Economic Development - A Quantitative Approach (Baltimore, The Johns&#13;
Hopkins University Press, 1967).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
also uses a multiple regression model to analyze how much of the variation&#13;
in fertility decline over a period or the level of fertility at a point in&#13;
time can be explained by the extracted factors, representing socio-economic&#13;
and family planning input variables. Second, the study uses variables&#13;
depicting fertility decline and economic change, rather than just static&#13;
values of dependent and independent variables.&#13;
Data and Their Sources&#13;
Table 1 lists the variables used in the analysis. The dependent&#13;
variable in our study is the percentage decline in the crude birth rate&#13;
(CBR) during the period 1970-75. Change in the CBR is chosen because data&#13;
on birth rates are more widely available and more reliable than those on&#13;
fertility. The total fertility rate would have been a better measure&#13;
because it takes account of the population's age structure. The study&#13;
concentrates on fertility decline, rather than changes in the contracep-&#13;
tive user rate, because the former captures a wider spectrum of a change&#13;
in fertility behavior and attitudes. Fertility decline and increasing&#13;
contraceptive practice are naturally related but never exactly coinci-&#13;
dental: fertility decline can and does take place without contraceptives,&#13;
e.g., through changes in age at marriage, marital rates and increased use&#13;
of traditional methods of avoiding pregnancy. 1/ Moreover, data are&#13;
available for more countries on fertility decline than on contraceptive&#13;
practice.&#13;
1/ It should be noted that the high fertility rate in developing countries&#13;
is still below the biological maximum, indicating there must be some&#13;
control practiced in avoiding pregnancies (e.g., abstinence, coitus&#13;
interruptus, etc.) in addition to infertility associated with physical&#13;
conditions (e.g., malnutrition).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
Table 1&#13;
LIST OF VARIABLES&#13;
POPURBN         Urban Population as Percent of Total Population (1970-75). 1/&#13;
CDR             Crude Death Rates ('70-75). 2/&#13;
PCGNP           Per Capita Gross National Product in US$ ('72). 3/&#13;
PRI4GNP         Percentage of Gross NationaL Product from Primary&#13;
Sector ('74). 3/&#13;
POPDOC          Population (in thousands) per Doctor ('74). 1/&#13;
LIFEXPCT        Life Expectancy ('70-'75). 2/&#13;
GDIGDP          Gross Domestic Investment as % of G.D.P. ('73). 3/&#13;
GROGDP          Average Annual Real Growth Rates of G.D.P. ('65-'73). 3/&#13;
E.XPNtLTH       Government (Current) Expenditures on Health as % of G.N.P.&#13;
('73).3/&#13;
EXPNEDU         Government (Current) Expenditures on Education as % of&#13;
G.N.P.('73).3/&#13;
TOTEXPN         Total Government Expenditures as % of G.D.P. ('73). 3/&#13;
CONSGDP         Total Government Consumption as % of G.D.P. ('73). 3/&#13;
FPPERFa1        Family Planning Personnel per million Females 15-44 ('74). 4/&#13;
FPFAFEM         The Number of Family Planning Facilities per million Females&#13;
15-44 ('74). 4/&#13;
YRSGVFP         Number of Years Government FP Program in Operation. 1/&#13;
CBR 1970        Crude Birth Rate 1970. 1/&#13;
CBR 1975        Crude Birtli Rate 1975. 1/&#13;
CHNG CBR        Percentage decline in CBR during the period 1970-75. 1/&#13;
Sources:        1/  Population Council - Factbook&#13;
2/  U.N. - Selected World Demographic Indicators&#13;
3/ World Banlk - World Tables (Parts II and III).&#13;
4/  World Bank Estimates (based on above sources)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
The list of explanatory variables includes three which relate to&#13;
the family planning delivery system. No measure of FP expenditures was&#13;
used because of the problem of comparing cost estimates between countries;&#13;
instead, we included a variable indicating family planning facilities and&#13;
personnel per million women in the reproductive age group and the number of&#13;
years that the government program has been in operation.&#13;
Most of the socio-economic variables included in our study have&#13;
multiple dimensions. The variable, POPURBN (urban population as a percen-&#13;
tage of total population) also reflects, or at least will be highly cor-&#13;
related with, the level of development of the country. One can ascribe&#13;
other dimensions to this variable, for example,the delivery of health,&#13;
family planning and other services has lower cost per capita in an urban&#13;
environment. The crude death rate is a variable that represents the health&#13;
status of the people and is clearly associated with the level of development,&#13;
but it also reflects, to some extent, the effectiveness of health services,&#13;
especially of public health measures.&#13;
Population per doctor and life expectancy at birth, reflect&#13;
public expenditure in the health sector and its impact, and also reflects&#13;
the general level of living. Government expenditures on health and on&#13;
education as percentages of GNP indicate not only the scope of government&#13;
efforts in providing social services, but also the general priority given&#13;
to human resource development. Gross domestic investment as a percentage&#13;
of GDP and average real growth rates of GDP have been included to represent&#13;
the dynamics of socio-economic growth. Variable definitions and data&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
sources are given in Table 1. Data on 62 countries is available for all&#13;
variables (presented in Appendix A).&#13;
The Dependent Variable: The dependent variable in our analysis&#13;
is the percentage decline in CBR during the period 1970-75. The source of&#13;
CBR data is the Population Council, which makes these estimates on the&#13;
basis of vital statistics sources for individual countries. The period&#13;
1970-75 has been chosen for analysis because, as noted already, more&#13;
developing countries have experienced a decline in fertility rate during&#13;
this time than before, and because more reliable data on fertility and&#13;
on the independent variables are available for this period. 1/&#13;
Table 2 shows the movement in the CBR between 1970 and 1975 for&#13;
56 developing countries, with data on the fertility trend in the oreceding&#13;
ten-year period, for 23 of those countries. Only four of the 55 countries&#13;
experienced an increase in CBR; CBR has remained more or less constant&#13;
for another ten countries (the percentage decline is zero to less than&#13;
3 percent), while 20 countries experienced a decline in fertility of&#13;
10 percent or more.&#13;
1/ In most macro studies of fertility determinants, the question of&#13;
time sequence is not explicitly considered. Although our knowledge&#13;
of time lags in this field is extremely limited, almost non-existent,&#13;
it is important to specify the independent variables corresponding&#13;
to the same time period as or proceeding to, the dependent variable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
Table 2&#13;
CRUDE BIRTH RATES OF DEVELOPING COUN'TRIES, 1970 AND 1975&#13;
CBR             CBR            2 Decline       2 Decline in&#13;
1970            1975           in CBR          CBR in Preceding&#13;
1970-75         10 Years - 1960-70&#13;
Afghanistan              50              49              2.0                 N.A.&#13;
So. Africa               40              44           -10.0                  0.23&#13;
Algeria                  49              48             2.04                -1.87&#13;
Bangladesh               47.5            43.0           9.47                 N.A.&#13;
Barbados                 20.5            19             7.32                 N.A.&#13;
Benin                    51              50             1.96                 N.A.&#13;
Bolivia                  44              47            -6.82                 N.A.&#13;
Botswana                 44              46            -4.55                 N.A.&#13;
Brazil                   42              37.5          10.71                 N.A.&#13;
Chile                    28.5            23.4          17.89                24.65&#13;
Colombia                 45              31            31.11                 N.A.&#13;
Costa Rica               39              29.3          24.87                28.54&#13;
Cuba                     29              20.7          28.62                 N.A.&#13;
Dominican Republic       47.5            36            24.21                 N.A.&#13;
Egypt                    40              35            12.5                 12.22&#13;
El Salvador              41              39.3           4.15                16.97&#13;
Fiji                     32.5            29            10.77                 N.A.&#13;
Gambia                   47.5            45             5;26                 N.A.&#13;
Ghana                    51              49             3.92                 N.A.&#13;
Guatemala                43              42             2.33                16.16&#13;
Haiti                    47.5            42            11.58                 N.A.&#13;
Honduras                 49              49             0.0                  N.A.&#13;
Hong Kong                20.1            17.7          11.94                45.56&#13;
India                    41              35            14.63                 0.98&#13;
Indonesia                42.5            38.5           9.41                 N.A.&#13;
Iran                     48              39            18.75                 0.21&#13;
Iraq                     50              48             4.00                -1.04&#13;
Jamaica                  34.4            30            12.79                 5.65&#13;
Kenya                    50              49             2.0                  N.A.&#13;
Korea                    31              24            22.58                 N.A.&#13;
W. Malaysia              33.5            30.3           9.55                 3.67&#13;
Mlali                    50              47.5            5.00                N.A.&#13;
Mauritius                25.9            25.6           1.16                 N.A.&#13;
Mexico                   44              40             9.09                 5.65&#13;
Mlorocco                 50              46             8.0                 -0.43&#13;
Nepal                    45              45             0.0                  N.A.&#13;
Nicaragua                48              48             0.0                  N.A.&#13;
Nigeria                  55              50             9.09                 N.A.&#13;
Pakistan                 47.5            40            15.79                12.40&#13;
Panama                   38.5            32            16.88                 8.82&#13;
Philippines              45              37            17.78                 4.35&#13;
Puerto Rico              24.8            22.3          10.08                 N.A.&#13;
Rhodesia                 48              49            -2.08                 N.A.&#13;
Singapore                22.1            18.8          14.93                42.89&#13;
Sri Lanka                32              27.2          15.0                 17.76&#13;
Sudan                    50              48             4.0                  N.A.&#13;
Tanzania                 48              44.5           7.29                 N.A.&#13;
Taiwan                   27.2            25.9           4.78                 N.A.&#13;
Thailand                 41              37             9.76                 5.22&#13;
Trinidad                 24              23             4.17                 N.A.&#13;
Tunisia                  38              35.3           7.11                 N.A.&#13;
Turkey                   40              32            20.0                  0.50&#13;
Uganda                   50              45            10.0                 -6.52&#13;
Venezuela                42.5            36            15.29                 N.A.&#13;
Zaire                    45             45              0.0                  N.A.&#13;
NA - Not available.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
In several countries 1/ experiencing significant fertility&#13;
decline during 1970-75, the process of decline had already begun in 1960-70&#13;
(e.g., Chile, Costa Rica, Panama, Hong Kong, Sri Lanka and Singapore). A&#13;
few other countries (Egypt, Pakistan, Jamaica) seem to display a declining&#13;
trend gathering momentum after a mild decrease in the 1960s. For some&#13;
countries (e.g., Iran, India, Philippines and T_rkey) fertility decline&#13;
appears to have been noticeable only since 1970.&#13;
3. MAJOR FINDINGS AND DISCUSSIONS&#13;
Factor Analysis of Independent Variables&#13;
We have already noted the relevance of factor analysis in&#13;
combining interdependent variables into factors, which are by definition&#13;
independent of each other. Factor analysis is also useful in a preliminary&#13;
exploration of data where there is no precise model to specify relationships.&#13;
In an interdependent system of relationships, the technique can throw some&#13;
light on the nature of clustering of variables and the pattern of their&#13;
association. 2/ Table 3 records the results of factor analysis of the 15&#13;
independent variables. The variable is presented bv assigning each vari-&#13;
able to the factor with which it has the highest correlation.3/ Each&#13;
1/ The scope of comparison is rather limited, because of lack of dependable&#13;
data for many countries before 1970.&#13;
2/  In an interdependent system, regression analysis can be done by using&#13;
a structural equation model. In future extension of an inter-country&#13;
study of fertility decline, use of a structural equation model will&#13;
be desirable.&#13;
3/ We should note here that our extraction of factors has been based on&#13;
an eigen value of one as the cut-off point.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
Table 3&#13;
a/&#13;
ROTATED FACTOR MATRIX OF 15 INDEPENDENT VARIABLES&#13;
Factor       Factor        Factor        Factor        h&#13;
1            2             3             4&#13;
POPURBN              .91943        .01449      -.04084       .06618      .85162&#13;
CDR                 -.81457        .04279      -.43355     -.13777       .87230&#13;
PCGNP                .85997        .08958       .00914       .24446      .80742&#13;
PRIMGNP             -.79097      -.30455        .02447      -.32486      .82452&#13;
POPDOC              -.78029        .09356      -.31125       .03180      .71549&#13;
LIFEXPCT             .80899        .01467       .46393       .13746       .88880&#13;
EXPNHLTH             .28838        .58435       .51429       .03884      .69062&#13;
EXPNEDU              .10967        .79669       .00821       .33699      .76037&#13;
TOTEXPN              .12674        .87739       .07601      -.09010      .79977&#13;
CONSGDP             -.21272        .88346       .05524     -.15973       .85431&#13;
YRSGVFP              .20249      -.23137        .53800      -.06122      .38773&#13;
FPFACFEI             .14195        .23665       .80912       .17872      .76277&#13;
FPPERFEI             .02364        .18220       .83111       .02777      .72527&#13;
GDIGDP               .09874        .09989       .13250       .90017      .84759&#13;
CROWGDP              .30609      -.12164       -.00438       .78833      .72997&#13;
Cumulative %&#13;
of Variance&#13;
Explained b/           30.0          49.0         64.0          77.0&#13;
a/ As noted in footnote on page 10, we have used varimax criteria to rotate the&#13;
initially extracted factors.   The rotation is an important step in the factor&#13;
analysis and is necessary to derive a meaningful patt_-nlng of variables (See Nie&#13;
et al. Statistical Packaging for the Social Sciences, McGraw Hill 1975, p. 482).&#13;
b/ This reflects the percentage of the total variance in the data set explained&#13;
cumulatively by successive factors. In factor analysis the variables are&#13;
normalized and hence the variance for each variable is 1. The total variance&#13;
in the data set is equal to the number of variables. The proportion of total&#13;
variance accounted for by a given factor is estimated by summing of squared&#13;
values of factor loadings by the column for the factor and dividing the sum&#13;
by the number of variables.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
entry of the matrix in the table represents the relative effect of&#13;
factor r on the ith observed variable and is referred to as factor&#13;
loadings. 1/ Squaring any entry gives the proportion of variation in&#13;
variable i accounted for by factor r. Since the factors are by definition&#13;
uncorrelated, it is possible to sum the squared factor loadings across&#13;
rows to get the communality (h ) of the variable in question. (This is&#13;
closely related to R   (see Harman, 1967)). 2/   Thus,the last column&#13;
represents proportion of variation in a variable that is related to the&#13;
factors identified.&#13;
Factor 1, which explains the 30% variation in the data set, is&#13;
highly correlated with the following variables: POPURBN, CDR, PCGN?,&#13;
PRIMGNP, POPDOC and LIFEXPCT. Itthus appears that this factor represents&#13;
the level of development. For example, the percentage of population&#13;
living in urban areas has a loading of 0.91, which actuallv represents the&#13;
correlation coefficient between the variable (POPTRBN) and Factor 1. 3/&#13;
1/  These are the rotated factor loadings, air.&#13;
2/  The comnunality (h ) of a variable measures the proportion of the&#13;
variance in that variable accounted for by all the faccors and in a&#13;
regression framework to measure the proportion of the variance in a&#13;
dependable variable explained by independent variables. Besides&#13;
the difference between factors and variables, it should also be&#13;
noted that in the case of factor analysis there is no dependent&#13;
variable.&#13;
3/ The entry recorded in a row against a variable also represents the&#13;
regression coefficient of factors to describe that variable. This&#13;
is because the factors are orthogonal to each other (see Harman, 1967).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
This also means that 80 percent of the variance in this particular variable&#13;
is explained by Factor 1. In the inter-country context, urbanization,&#13;
which represents to a large extent the relative size of the industrial&#13;
sector in the economy, is expectedly highly correlated with development.&#13;
This is supported by the observed factor loading of the variable, measuring&#13;
the percentage of GNP coming from the primary sector (PRIMGNP) with Factor 1&#13;
(0.79). The sign of the factor loading of the crude death rate is also nega-&#13;
tive, indicating a negative relationship between level of development and&#13;
CDR. About 65 percent of the variance in CDR is explained by Factor 1.&#13;
Life expectancy is positvely related with the factor and 65 percent of&#13;
the variance in life expectancy is explained by Factor 1.&#13;
As expected, Factor 1 is highly correlated with per capita income -&#13;
almost three-fourths of the variance in per capita income is explained by&#13;
this factor. One can thus argue that Factor 1, constructed out of a&#13;
number of socio-economic variables, is a more comprehensive indicator of&#13;
the level of development than is per capita income, and a more dependable&#13;
one to use for an inter-country comparison.&#13;
Table 3 shows that four variables all connected with the govern-&#13;
ment sector, have high positive loadings with Factor 2. These are EXPNHLTH,&#13;
EXPNEDU, TOTEXPN and CONSGDP. Two variables definitionally close, namely,&#13;
total expenditure in the government sector as a percentage of GDP and total&#13;
government consumption as percentage of GDP, have loadings of almost equal&#13;
size, around 0.88. This factor seems to represent the relative size of the&#13;
public sector in the economy. Government expenditure on health as a percen-&#13;
tage of GNP and government expenditure on education as a percentage of GNP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
are also represented in this factor because of their relationship to the&#13;
overall size of the public sector. This factor explains about 19 percent of&#13;
the variance in the data.&#13;
Factor 3 correlates highly with three variables related to the&#13;
family planning delivery system, and can therefore be characterized as the&#13;
FP input dimension. Two variables, namely family planning facilities per&#13;
million female population of 15 to 44 years (FPAFFEM) and family planning&#13;
personnel per million female population 15-44 (FPFERFE4) seem to be most&#13;
highly correlated (0.80 and 0.83 respectively). The other variable, one&#13;
would expect, to be related to the family planning input dimension is the&#13;
number of years the public sector family planning program has been opera-&#13;
tive. This variable has a correlation coefficient of 0.53 with the factor.&#13;
It can be seen from Table 3 that a number of health-related&#13;
variables have fairly high correlation with the family planning input&#13;
(0.33), and expenditure on education as a percent of GNP (0.33). For&#13;
example, public sector expenditure on health as a percent of GNP has a&#13;
correlation coefficient of 0.51. This is reflective of a widely prevalent&#13;
mode of health-based FP delivery system. FP facilities and personnel, two&#13;
important components of thle FP input (Factor 3), are closely associated with&#13;
the health infrastructure in the public sector and this is borne out by the&#13;
data. Two other variables reflecting the general impact of health services&#13;
-- life expectancy and crude death rate -- also have moderately high cor-&#13;
relation coefficients with Factor 3 (0.46 and 0.43 respectively). Obviously,&#13;
the link of the family planning input dimension with those variables is via&#13;
health services. It is also not surprising to find that, of the remaining&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
variables, the population/doctor ratio has some relationship with FP input&#13;
dimension (0.31). Factor 3 explains an additional 15 percent of the total&#13;
variance in the data set, making the total variance explained by the first&#13;
three factors 64 percent.&#13;
Factor 4 includes two variables which are inter-related and&#13;
represent the actual and potential rate of growth of an economy. These&#13;
variables are GDIGDP (gross domestic investment as percentage of GDP) and&#13;
GROWGDP (average annual growth rate of GDP). Eighty percent of the variance&#13;
in GDIGDP is accounted for by Factor 4 and about 58 percent of the variance&#13;
in average growth rate of GDP is explained by this factor, which can be&#13;
characterized as representing economic growth. The variables which have&#13;
some relationship with this factor are per capita income (0.23), proportion&#13;
of GNP from the primary sector (0.33), and expenditure on education as a&#13;
percentage of GNP (0.33). The correlation of per capita income with the&#13;
growth factor may be explained by the effect of per capita income on the&#13;
saving rate and hence on investment. The negative relationship between the&#13;
size of primary sector and economic growth reflects the observed association&#13;
of economic growth with the size and pace of industrialization. The observed&#13;
relationship of the education expenditure variable (EXPENDV) with Factor&#13;
4 is compatible with the positive role of human resource development in the&#13;
process of economic growth.&#13;
At least two general points can be made from Table 3. First,&#13;
it is possible to extract and identify a few broad dimensions, mutually&#13;
independent by definition, from a number of interrelated variables.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
Second, the observed values and signs of correlation of variables with&#13;
factors (loadings) indicate that the inter-country data are consistent&#13;
with expected relationships.&#13;
Analysis with Fertility Variables&#13;
Next, we did a factor analysis of 15 independent variables and&#13;
the fertility variables. The relationships hypothesized in this analysis&#13;
can be schematically presented as follows: 1/&#13;
Figure I: Analytical Framework of the Hypothesized Relationships&#13;
Initial Fertility                   Change in Fertility                  Terminal&#13;
Conditions            b         during the period          d         Fertility&#13;
(CBR:     1970)                     (percentage change                   Condition&#13;
in CBR between 1970-                 (CBR 1975&#13;
1975&#13;
Ia&#13;
Extracted Factors (per-&#13;
taining to the period&#13;
c                1970-75                           e&#13;
1.  Development Level                    .&#13;
.. 4   2.  Size-of Public Sector&#13;
3. Family Planning Inputs&#13;
4.  Economic Growth&#13;
l/ Although factor analysis does not need a priori specification of the&#13;
relationships to be probed, the emerging pattern of clustering can&#13;
still be helpful to show the nature of association between the&#13;
variables.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
Table 4 presents the results of factor analysis of the fifteen&#13;
independent variables along with decline in fertility, that is, it focuses&#13;
on the relationship denoted by 'a' in Fig. I. Inclusion of the fertility&#13;
variable causes only minor changes in the results in Table 3. The fifteen&#13;
independent variables are clustered exactly as in Table 3 with only slight&#13;
changes in the value of correlation coefficients. (Such changes are ex-&#13;
pected because the factors extracted are linear combin-ations of the vari-&#13;
ables and there is an additional variable in Table 4.) The total variance&#13;
explained by the four factors extracted in Table 4 is 74 percent, slightly&#13;
lower than that explained by the four factors generated by excluding the&#13;
variable, CHANGCBR, in Table 3 (77 percent).&#13;
Since the factors in Table 4 include one fertility variable, the&#13;
interpretation of the dimensions corresponding to the factors cannot be&#13;
strictly the same as in Table 3. However, clustering as well as loadings&#13;
being stable, it is reasonable to treat the factors in the same fashion as&#13;
we did in Table 3.&#13;
Keeping the preceding qualification in mind, Table 4 makes it&#13;
possible to review the relationship between decline in CBR and the extracted&#13;
factors. The highest correlation coefficient of decline in CBR is Factor 1,&#13;
which reflects the level of development. This factor explains about 23&#13;
percent of the variance in the change in birth rate. The next important&#13;
factor is family planning inputs (Factor 3), although the relationship is&#13;
not very strong (12 percent). The other two factors seem to be negatively&#13;
but weakly related with the decline in CBR.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
Table 4&#13;
ROTATED FACTOR MATRIX OF 15 INDEPENDENT VARIABLES&#13;
AND PERCENTAGE DECLINE IN CBR&#13;
Variables                    Factor 1      Factor 2      Factor 3     Factor 4       h2&#13;
CHNGCBR                      .48292       -.22699        .34589      -.29266       .4°003&#13;
POPURBN                       .91820       .03112       -.05050        .07736      .85263&#13;
C D R                       -.81867        .01961      -.42584       -.14524       .87305&#13;
POGNP                        .83924        .11315      -.01401        .28852       .80057&#13;
PRLkMGNP                    -.76584       -.32492        .05073      -.36545       .82821&#13;
POPDOC                      -.77950        .06574      -.29796        .01362       .70092&#13;
LIFEXPCT                     .81347        .03708        .45660       .14442       .89245&#13;
EXPENHLTH                    .27060        .60528        .49189       .07249       .68680&#13;
EXPNEDU                      .09926        .78677        .00127       .32961       .73751&#13;
TOTEXPN                      .12848        .87104        .07229      -.11211       .79302&#13;
CONSGDP                     -.22478        .87982        .04300      -.15746       .85125&#13;
YRSGVTFP                      .21243      -.21410        .53828      -.06131       .38447&#13;
FPFACFE4                      .12828       .26276        .79015       .21095       .75433&#13;
FPPERFEM                     .02940        .19799        .82797       .02695       .72633&#13;
GDIGDP                       .09129        .08744        .13607       .89453       .83469&#13;
GROWGDP                      .32254       -.14203        .01615       .74251       .67579&#13;
Cumulative % of&#13;
Variance Explained          29.0          47.0         62.0           74.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
Table 5 includes one more variable in the factor analysis, CBR&#13;
1970, to probe the hypothesized relationships 'b and 'c' in Fig. I. A&#13;
comparison of national fertility data for different countries is expected to&#13;
reveal a consistent pattern of relations between fertility level and its&#13;
determining factors (income, education, etc.). How rapid the decline in&#13;
fertility is likely to be depends largely on where the country's fertility&#13;
level stands in relation to that which would be normal for, say,its level of&#13;
living and family planning efforts. If the initial fertility level is high&#13;
in relation to the norm, the process of decline is expected to be rapid. 1/&#13;
The relationship embodied in 'c' is not expected to be substantial.&#13;
Initial fertility level, measured by CBR 1970, would not significantly affect&#13;
the extracted factors pertaining to the period 1970-75. However, if we&#13;
consider the variables which go into the formation of the factors, CBR, 1970&#13;
is expected to be associated with certain development indicators (e.g.&#13;
POPURBN PCGNP, etc). CBR 1970 cannot be an important determinant of the&#13;
size of the public sector in 1970-75 (represented by Factor 2). As for&#13;
Factor 3, change in the birth rate is more likely to be a consequence,&#13;
rather than a determinant, of family planning inputs. There exists con-&#13;
siderable evidence 2/ that high fertility adversely affects economic&#13;
growth. But the time horizon in our analysis is unlikely to be long enough&#13;
to capture that.&#13;
1/   In our formulation, the variable CHANGCBR is the percentage decline of&#13;
CBR between 1970-75, and, therefore, is corrected for the size differ-&#13;
ences in the inter-country comparison.   However, the initial level of&#13;
fertility still appears to be an important factor in determining the&#13;
rate of decline in fertility.&#13;
2/   See Nancy Birdsall and Rashid Faruqee, Population-Development Relation-&#13;
ships: Approaches to Analysis, World Bank, Development Economics&#13;
Department, 1977, mimeo.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
Table 5&#13;
ROTATED FACTOR MATRIX OF 15 INDEPENDENT VARIABLES,&#13;
PERCENT DECLINE IN CBR AND 1970 CBR&#13;
Variables                    Factor 1      Factor 2     Factor 3      Factor 4       h2&#13;
CHNGCBR                      .47583       -.24171        .29863      -.29312       .45994&#13;
CBR1970                     -.59988       -.15813      -.53866       -.10971       .68706&#13;
POPUREN                       .91920       .02651       -.04957       .07972       .85444&#13;
C D R                       -.82041        .03851      -.42004       -.13932       .87040&#13;
POGNp                        .84170        .10781        .00149       .28834       .80323&#13;
PRIMIGNP                    -.76555       -.32110        .04099      -.36752       .82592&#13;
POPDOC                      -.77428        .08137      -.27126        .01491       .67992&#13;
LIFEXPCT                     .81805        .01759        .45797       .13723       .89808&#13;
CONSGDP                     -.21784        .87951        .06808      -.16007       .85125&#13;
EXPNEDU                      .09579        .78495        .00791       .33135       .73517&#13;
TOTEXPN                      .13619        .86791        .09409      -.11413       .79369&#13;
EXPENhLTH                     .28124       .58759        .52421       .06064       .70283&#13;
YRSGVTFP                     .21614       -.23283        .53818      -.07202       .39575&#13;
FPFACFa1                     .13654        .23732        .80515       .19544       .76141&#13;
FPPERFa1                     .02841        .17051        .81298       .01393       .69101&#13;
GDIGDP                        .09343       .08396        .16112       .89108       .83576&#13;
GROWGDP                       .31497      -.14380        .00282       .74606       .67650&#13;
Cumulative % of&#13;
Variance Explained           29.0          46.0         62.0           73.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
Part of the effect of the birth rate in the initial period on the&#13;
rate of change in the birth rate as hypothesized in Fig. I, is hierarchical&#13;
-- the relationships denoted by 'c' and 'a'.    Since factor analysis does not&#13;
need a priori presumption about the direction of the relationship, and its&#13;
results are not affected by the choice of sequence of effects, the rotated&#13;
factor matrix in Table 5 can shed light on all three relationships, 'a', 'b'&#13;
and 'c', denoted in Fig. I.&#13;
The most important finding from Table 5 is that the inclusion of&#13;
initial fertility situation, CBR 1970, does not alter the nature of the&#13;
relationship of the decline of fertility with the extracted factors.     CHNG-&#13;
CBR still remains most strongly loaded with Factor 1. Inclusion of CBR 1970&#13;
does not increase the explanatory power of the factors. It appears that the&#13;
effect of the initial.fertility level has no significant influence on the&#13;
subsequent nature and rate of fertility decline.&#13;
Table 6 covers the hypothesized relationships denoted by 'd' and&#13;
e' in Figure I, that is,the expected effects of the extracted factors on&#13;
the terminal fertility (CBR 1975),either directly or via change in fertility&#13;
during the period 1970-75. It appears that CBR 1975 has strong negative&#13;
correlations with Factor 1 (-.66) and Factor 3 (-.63), indicating that the&#13;
level of fertility at the end of the period under review is significantly&#13;
(inversely) affected by the level of development as well as by the level of&#13;
FP inputs. The factors together explain 83% of the variation in CBR 1975. The&#13;
variable CHNGCBR also has a comparatively higher correlation coefficient with&#13;
Factors I and 3, although not as high as the respective loadings of CBR&#13;
1975 with those factors. These findings are consistent with the expected&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
Table 6&#13;
ROTATED FACTOR MATRIX OF 15 INDEPEjiDENT&#13;
VARIABLES, % DECLINE IN CBR &amp; CBR 1975&#13;
Variables                    Factor F      Factor 2      Factor 3     Factor 4       h&#13;
CHNGCBR                      .48493       -.23056        .36724      -.29748       .51167&#13;
CBR 1975                    -.65863       -.05068      -.62346       -.00835       .82571&#13;
POPUREN                      .91912        .02772      -.04036        .07945       .85350&#13;
C D R                       -.81428        .02176      -.43256       -.15045       .87327&#13;
PCGNP                        .83872        .11026      -.00703        .29095       .80031&#13;
PRLM!GNP                    -.76261       -.32356        .05452      -.37212       .82772&#13;
POPDOC                      -.76549        .06442      -.27722       -.00394       .66699&#13;
LIFEXPCT                      .81088       .03452        .46732       .14799       .89902&#13;
CONSGDP                     -.21937        .87984        .04646      -.16107       .85034&#13;
EXPNEDU                      .09636        .78752        .00929       .33348       .74076&#13;
TOTEXPN                      .13521        .86935        .08330      -.11643       .79454&#13;
EXPENHLTH                    .26887        .60440        .49688       .07362       .68990&#13;
YRSGVTFP                     .20894       -.21568        .54930      -.06330       .39592&#13;
FPFACFEM                      .12056       .26381        .78701       .21693       .75057&#13;
FPPERFE&#142;                     .01276        .20185        .80396       .04205       .68902&#13;
GDIGDP                       .09334        .08537        .14914       .88739       .82571&#13;
GROWGDP                       .31852      -.14270        .01432       .74440       .67615&#13;
Cumulative % of&#13;
Variance Explained           30.0          47.0          64.0         75.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
relationship between CBR 1975 and decline in CBR during 1970-75. Inclusion&#13;
of CBR 1975 increases the power of the factors in explaining the variation&#13;
in CHNBCBR by about five percentage points. (46 to 51 percent).&#13;
A comparison of Tables 5 and 6 shows that the terminal fertility&#13;
level is associated more closely with the variables included in our analysis&#13;
than with the initial fertility level. Only 68 percent of the variation in&#13;
CBR 1970 is explained by the factors extracted, as against 83 percent in&#13;
the case of CBR 1975. Moreover, the total variance in the data set explained&#13;
by the four factors also increases nearly two percentage points in Table 6.&#13;
General Observations&#13;
Based on the factor matrices in Tables 3 through 6, a few general&#13;
observations are in order. First, in Tables 3 through 6, the most important&#13;
factor in explaining total variance in the data set is the one that repre-&#13;
sents the level of development. This factor accounts for about 30 percent&#13;
of the total variance in those tables. The next most powerful factor (17.0-&#13;
19.0% of the total variance) represents the relative size of the public&#13;
sector. The family planning input factor explains 15 to 17 percent of the&#13;
remaining variance in the different matrices. In all the factor matrices in&#13;
Table 3 to Table 6, variables reflecting economic growth, actual and poten-&#13;
tial, have clustered into an independent factor, which explains around 11&#13;
percent of the remaining variance in all cases.&#13;
Second, although the broad dimensions as above are identifiable in&#13;
the data set by factor analysis, certain variables which have bearing on more&#13;
than one dimension, as expected, are evident from the size of factor loadings.&#13;
This is confirmed by the results in Tables 3 through 6. For example, some of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
the variables which have clustered in Factor 1 and Factor 2 seem to have mod-&#13;
erately high loading with the FP input dimension (Factor 3). We have noted&#13;
this happening with expenditure on health as a percentage of GDP, population&#13;
per doctor and CDR. Also, some of the development level variables, notably&#13;
per capita income and the proportion of GDP coming from the primary sector,&#13;
have some effect on the economic growth dimension, as one would expect. We&#13;
have also found that expenditure on education as a percentage of GNP seems&#13;
to be significantly positively related with rate of economic growth.&#13;
Third, inclusion cf fertility variables (CBR 1970, decline of CBR&#13;
1970-75 and CBR 1975) in the various factor matrices shows that both develop-&#13;
ment and FP inputs affect fertility decline. In contrast to the terminal&#13;
fertility rate, the initial fertility rate seems to have little effect on the&#13;
observed relationships. The influence of development and F? inputs pertaining&#13;
to the period 1970-75 on CBR 1975 also increases the power of the extracted&#13;
factors in explaining the variation in fertility decline in CBR during the&#13;
period 1970-75.&#13;
Regression Analvsis with Factors&#13;
Factor analysis does not treat any variable as a dependent variable.&#13;
Thus, the relationship of a particular variable with the emerging factors is&#13;
somewhat affected by inclusion of that variable in the same rotated matrices. We&#13;
shall, therefore, further the analysis using multiple regression, using the four&#13;
factors extracted out of the independent variables in multiple regressions with&#13;
fertility variables, mainly the percentage decline in CBR during 1970-75 and&#13;
CBR 1975. Table 7 presents the results of regression-with the decline in CBR as&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
841&#13;
o-0                  (N  .4  Ln  0&#13;
W4 L              ON  o  UL)  m  N&#13;
4 .o Gz            ko  co  ON  ON  r&#13;
*)         (J )   .   .   CN  r4&#13;
CD ionN .N            -,  N  .-4&#13;
Ln                ~~~N vr 'V  h &#13;
W                   H4  D  q  rn  o.&#13;
0                  (N  'D  a  LA  r%&#13;
N    v s mr N    O&#13;
-4  44 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ -4 N  .4  A L&#13;
o~~~~~~~         a, c-i G ,  oo &#13;
z                        0  '4 . .  N  N&#13;
W                         .  .&#13;
:&gt; ~~~~~~~~ o       ONW &#13;
NO         0s          -4 a   t&#13;
o  )                 o     &gt;&#13;
4-41    Ht     &#13;
z  -J(N~~~~-4  4~-40'           c&#13;
o~~~~~~a bq  Xq .% W &#13;
tr ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~L Cv  N &#13;
o~~    ro &#13;
W =   LA       n on&#13;
&gt;                 0N ' q  t  LA&#13;
Cc    0  0  in  (N !n i&#13;
U       U     ( &#13;
4-4&#13;
N   L a_%  0&#13;
zi~~~~~d |              a,C L&#13;
H4                       'I  co)  o &#13;
X~~~~~~~~~L         r- o vo C U &#13;
R~~~~~~~~~~L ').0 .4 *J * &#13;
8            0%~~~~~U  LA  Cl  -40&#13;
00    (N  0%  a,&#13;
'0t  N   Nv  a co&#13;
E¢4                       Kr  m  0%   0&#13;
Z      &gt;                  W  r-  r-  m &gt;  O&#13;
X   5         4m   S~~~~~~L csi m o r&#13;
aZ      O  .,' e    I 4-4  v  v  H;  o&#13;
0  um         U4*  O  -  -  0 O -.&#13;
:4'                Cl  0  L &#13;
a4       -4       . &#13;
WH                  fl 0&#13;
U,                           a        a 3 , n&#13;
'.0  N.-4     0~~1-  IV  rN  r4 0~&#13;
Lr  in  CD  ro  % &#13;
E-  .   *   * b                 -4  0  0  0&#13;
N                   a fi @4  ,4   n   a O  a $&#13;
0~~ co LOi co o) cn N B &#13;
Ln~~ N       r     .e eq  Ln cn %D     s&#13;
V4     F4 :&gt;  N    [4  Q 4)&#13;
$4 $  4 C&#13;
&gt;    0     -C4U&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
dependent variable and all the four factors and CBR 1970 as independent&#13;
variables. As recorded in Table 7, the regression equation is significant&#13;
at the 99 percent level; the total variation explained is about 28 percent.&#13;
The results show that Factor 1, which represents the level of devel-&#13;
opment, has the highest explanatory power and is significant at the 99 per-&#13;
cent level. Factor 1 alone explains nearly 14 percent of the variation in&#13;
the dependent variable, and has almost double the explanatory power of the&#13;
family planning inputs, Factor 3, which is significant at 95 percent level.&#13;
This finding suggests that the level of development has a stronger influence&#13;
on fertility than most of the empirical literature (using single variables&#13;
to indicate the level of development) has revealed. One reason for this&#13;
difference is that factor analysis makes it possible to isolate the effects&#13;
of development and family planning inputs among a set of variables. If&#13;
these dimensions are not thus isolated, the effect of development tends to&#13;
be underestimated, because among other things, family planning inputs would&#13;
embody an efficiency factor that is influenced by the level of development.&#13;
Factor 2, which represents the relative size of the public sector,&#13;
is not significant at t'ne 95 percent level; the observed relationshi? is&#13;
negative, that is, the higher value of Factor 2 is associated with a lower&#13;
rate of fertility decline during 1970-75. A large government sector appears&#13;
to be the consequence of, rather than a contributing factor to, a sustained&#13;
high rate of fertility.&#13;
The regression results in Table 7 show no significant relation&#13;
between the initial fertility level and the subsequent rate of decline; nor&#13;
between the rate of economic growth and the rate of fertility decline. The&#13;
latter is inconsistent with the conventional wisdom that fertility will start&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
ini&#13;
0  I'D'&#13;
in        CDN   N  N&#13;
I. cD          r-    r0  C&#13;
0                '.0&#13;
tn ~  ~   0N &#13;
4ji  g-  in  co&#13;
.n  rn  rl  V&#13;
V-   e Le&#13;
0          '.~~~~%  co  co  co&#13;
tn      4  .        4-4&#13;
r,  010 C;     0 .-4  0 0 &#13;
a,        Co'       I-i 1&#13;
Ci2~~~~~~~~~Ci o)-&#13;
&gt;0&#13;
0'.0         H   C~4'. I 0&#13;
N  C~~~~4  H   0U  t   %O  H&#13;
cn  0          CD   tnHC0&#13;
01  N  IA        .Y   .  .&#13;
0           H C~~~~~~~~0&#13;
IA~~~~~~~~~m t&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
falling only after a certain level of development has been reached. In other&#13;
words, fertility cannot be expected to decline, even with high rate of&#13;
economic growth, if the current level of living is low. This is shown by&#13;
the relative strength of Factor 1 and Factor 4 in explaining the variation&#13;
in percentage decline of CBR.&#13;
Our results are ccmpatible with the argument that a higher level of&#13;
living, operating through changes in aspirations about and family constraints&#13;
on the number of children (that they would like to have-or can have) triggers&#13;
fertility decline. The actual process of decline or the relative significance&#13;
of the forces operative in the process, remain to be analyzed by in-depth&#13;
country-specific studies. Since national fertility rates reflect what happens&#13;
at the household level, our results are consistent with various theories of&#13;
household behavior. Liebenstein's (1974) economic th1eory of fertility decline&#13;
states that "Economic development implies and is accompanied by conditions&#13;
that induce fertility decline." Essentially, his theory is based on the argu-&#13;
ments that with economic development a greater proportion of people achieve&#13;
"higher socio-economic statuses" and that the consumption decisions of the&#13;
household depend on the status group to which it belongs. His analysis dis-&#13;
tinguishes between ordinary consumption and expenditure for "status goods."&#13;
An upward movement from one status to another involves an increase in the pro-&#13;
portion of household income spent on status goods, implying that the relative&#13;
utility costs of nonstatus goods, including children, become higher. There&#13;
are other theories relating this process of decline in the preferred and&#13;
actual family size, as the family goes to higher socIal status and income&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
levels. Explanations are provided either in terms of quality and quantity&#13;
aspects of the demand for children (as the family goes to higher income, it&#13;
demands better "quality" but fewer children) or in terms of the increasing&#13;
cost of children (opportunity cost of time needed by parents to rear&#13;
children). Our results are consistent with such theories which provide a&#13;
rationale for expecting a declining trend in fertility as a higher level of&#13;
living is reached by households.&#13;
The above analysis relates to a fertility trend over time. But can&#13;
fertility behavior at a point of time be predicted from a given level of&#13;
living and other factors in our analysis? We investigated this by regressing&#13;
the level of fertility in the terminal period (1975) on the factors extracted&#13;
from the independent variables. Table 8 presents the results. This regression&#13;
is a much better fit than the earlier one; the total variation explained is&#13;
about 70 percent. It appears from Table 8 that the factors extracted out of&#13;
the independent variables prove to have strong predictive power for the&#13;
fertility level that is attained at the terminal point. Factor 1 explains&#13;
nearly 42 percent of the variation; the family planning input factor is also&#13;
very strong and explains nearly 28 percent of the variation, and the two other&#13;
factors are insignificant in the equation. Again, the role of development&#13;
is much stronger than that of family planning, although the relative differ-&#13;
ence is not as large as in the other equation (Table 7). The results in&#13;
Table 8 are consistent with the hypothesis that the norm of small family&#13;
size is associated with higher level of living. Tables 7 and 8 read&#13;
together show that a high level of development is associated with a low&#13;
level of current fertility, and also is likely to encourage a downward&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
trend in fertility. Family planning helps to maintain a lower level of&#13;
fertility than the potential level, but has a rather weak role in triggering&#13;
decline in fertility over time.&#13;
We also find that the rate of economic growth as reflected by&#13;
Factor 4 has no role in either explaining current fertility or causing a&#13;
decline in fertility over time. Such a finding is consistent with the&#13;
threshold hypothesis (that unless the level of living improves beyond a&#13;
certain point, fertility will not start declining), as well as with theories&#13;
which aim at explaining household behavior, including fertility, in a choice-&#13;
theoretic framework, of economic costs and benefits that are largely&#13;
influenced by the level of living.&#13;
An obvious policy implication of such a finding is that rising&#13;
family income will not of itself help in lowering fertility unless living&#13;
standards have become fairly high. In other words, fertility decline is&#13;
associated with level of living and not with the rate of income growth.&#13;
It should also be stressed again that the development indicator&#13;
in our analysis covers not only per capita income but also the extent of&#13;
urbanization, proportion of production from primary sector, namely popula-&#13;
tion per doctor, life expectancy, and the death rate. This also indicates&#13;
that aspects other than income are significant in affecting fertility&#13;
behavior. Such a finding supports the argument that a strategy emphasizing&#13;
a broad dispersion of benefits from development, rather than average income&#13;
growth alone, is relevant to reducing fertility.&#13;
Our findings have a direct bearing on the controversy of relative&#13;
importance of family planning delivery system versus development. We find&#13;
that the level of development is much more important, both in explaining&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
the variation in current fertility as well as in the decline in fertility&#13;
over time, though family planning also has a significant effect. Rela-&#13;
tively, FP is more effective in maintaining a lower level of fertility&#13;
than in inducing a declining trend.&#13;
Our results indicate a much more significant role of development&#13;
than what was found by other studies. King et al. (1974) analyzed the&#13;
relative importance of family planning program inputs and socio-economic&#13;
levels in explaining family planning performance for 19 countries by&#13;
running a number of regressions. The total variation explained by these&#13;
regressions is then decomposed into three parts: the first part exclu-&#13;
sively by socio-economic variables, the second part by program input&#13;
variables and the rest by the interaction of the two sets of variables.&#13;
Roughly speaking socio-economic variables account for less than one-&#13;
third of the total variance explained, somewhat more than one-third is&#13;
accounted for by the program inputs and the rest is assigned to inter-&#13;
action.&#13;
The study by Srikantan (1977) shows that the direct effect on&#13;
fertility of the demo-socio-economic factors is 35 percent, and the&#13;
combined effect of family planning program input and output is 48 percent.&#13;
The recent study by Mauldin and Berelson (1978) which updates&#13;
the earlier study of Freedman and Berelson (1976) finds that social setting&#13;
alone explains 66 percent of the decline of the CBR and program effort alone&#13;
explains 78 percent but when the effects are separated out, the "net" effect&#13;
of social setting becomes only 5 percent and the "net" effect of program&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
effort is 17 percent, which implies that the joint effect is the most&#13;
important factor (61.5 percent).&#13;
The recent study by Tsui and Bogue (1978) concludes that family&#13;
planning has a far more significant role in explaining fertility decline&#13;
than Mauldin and Berelson's. Their results, however, are based primarily&#13;
on correlation rather than multivariate techniques which allow several&#13;
factors to be examined together. Family planning has a correlation -&#13;
.681 with change in TFR, which is substantially higher than the correla-&#13;
tions of the dependent variable with any one of the socio-economic&#13;
variables; per capita income, percentage of urban population life&#13;
expectancy, etc.&#13;
A comparatively more significant role of family planning is&#13;
arrived at in these studies by a failure to fully separate the influences&#13;
of family planning anddevelopment in the analysis of the effects of inter-&#13;
related variables indicating those dimensions. The use of factor analysis&#13;
collapses a set of variables in terms of a smaller number of mutually&#13;
independent factors, which make it possible to fully separate out the&#13;
effects of family planning program inputs and development. The finding&#13;
confirms the significant role of family planning, but development clearly&#13;
emerges as the more important of the two in influencing fertility decline.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS&#13;
There is by now a broad consensus of opinion as to the positive&#13;
role of a family planning delivery system in a strategy of overall develop-&#13;
ment, although opinions differ about the relative importance of that role.&#13;
Among the empirical studies of the determinants of fertility are some&#13;
cross-section analyses of inter-country or inter-region data to assess&#13;
the relative contributions of socio-economic developtnent and family&#13;
planning programs to fertility decline. Among the methodological limita-&#13;
tions of these studies is their lack of an effective means to deal with&#13;
the problem of multi-collinearity among variables describing socio-&#13;
economic development and FP program output. Factor analysis has been&#13;
employed in the present study because it permits variables to be grouped&#13;
into dimensions which are by definition independent of each other. Factors&#13;
representing development level, size of government sector, family planning&#13;
input and economic growth are used to explain the relative significance of&#13;
the family planning delivery systems and level of socio-economic develop-&#13;
ment in reducing fertility.&#13;
We chose the percentage decline in crude birth rate (CBR) over&#13;
the period 1970-75 as the dependent variable, because reliable data on this&#13;
were available for a large number of developing countries. Factor analysis&#13;
shows that this variable is most highly correlated with the level of develop-&#13;
ment. In a series of rotated factor matrices the change in CBR is coupled&#13;
with the initial birth rate (CBR 1970) and then with the terminal birth&#13;
rate, (CBR 1975) along with the independent variables. The results&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
indicate that the initial birth rate has very little significance for the&#13;
relation of the change in birth rate to the extracted factors. However,&#13;
when the terminal birth rate is added with the change in birth rate, two&#13;
of the extracted factors-development level and family planning inputs--&#13;
appear to be very strongly (negatively) correlated with that variable.&#13;
This implies that the birth rate at a point in time is negatively related&#13;
to the level of living and family planning input availability. In all of&#13;
the results the level of development is found to be a-far stronger influence&#13;
on birth rate than is family planning. Neither the relative size of the&#13;
government sector nor the rate of economic growth emerges as a significant&#13;
factor.&#13;
Since in a factor analysis of the independent variables and the&#13;
fertility measures, the extracted factors contain elements of the fertility&#13;
variables, further analysis is done in a regression framework using the&#13;
factors extracted only out of the independent variables. Again it is found&#13;
that the level of development is a much stronger influence on the rate of&#13;
CBR decline during 1970-75 than the family planning inputs, although the&#13;
latter factor is also significant.&#13;
The rate of economic growth does not seem to affect the birth&#13;
rate, although the level of living does so. The policy implications of&#13;
this finding are important. First, there seems to be a considerable lag&#13;
between the process of economic growth and the lowering of birth rates;&#13;
even if the current rate of economic growth is rapid, birth rates only&#13;
decline significantly once a fairly high level of development has been&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
reached. Second, the level of living indicator, as extracted in our study,&#13;
is strongly related to, but not coincidental with, per capita income, since&#13;
it also reflects certain aspects of social development, especially health&#13;
(e.g., population per doctor, life expectancy and death rate). This lends&#13;
further support to those who argue that fertility is more likely to be&#13;
reduced through a planning strategy to ensure a better quality of life for&#13;
the vast majority of the population than through rapid growth of average&#13;
income alone.&#13;
The factors representing the development level and family plan-&#13;
ning inputs prove strong predictors of the birth rate, which means that a&#13;
country's birth rate, reflecting what happens at the household level, is&#13;
strongly associated with its level of living. The availability of family&#13;
planning inputs is also significant, but the predictive power of this&#13;
factor is not as strong as that of the level of development. Development&#13;
is thus not only instrumental in making the norm of small family size&#13;
widely acceptable, but it also contributes towards a decline in the birth&#13;
rate over time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
6. BIBLIOGRAPHY&#13;
Anker, R. "An Analysis of Fertility Differentials in Developing Countries".&#13;
Population &amp; Employment Working Paper #16 (April 1975).&#13;
Balakirishran, T.R. "A Cost-Benefit Analysis of the Barbados Family&#13;
Planning Program", Pcpulation Studies (London), July 1973.&#13;
Birdsall, Nancy and Rashid Faruqee. "Population Development Relationships:&#13;
Approaches to Analysis". (mimeo.), World Bank, 1977.&#13;
Blancly, R. "The Welfare Analysis of Fertility Reduction". Economic&#13;
JournaU Vol. 84 (March 1974).&#13;
Caldwell, J.C.   Study of Fertility &amp; Fertility Change in Trooical Africa&#13;
(Voorburg, London, International Statistical Institute, World&#13;
Fertility Survey, 1974).&#13;
.  "Toward a Restatement of Demographic Transition Theory",&#13;
Population and Development Review, Vol. 2, 1976.&#13;
Cernada, Geo. P., Ed. Taiwan Family Planning Reader. Chinese Center for&#13;
International Training in Family Planning. Taichung 1970.&#13;
Coale, The Demographic Transition. International Union for Scientific&#13;
Study of Population. International Population Conference. Vol. #1,&#13;
1973.&#13;
Cochrane, Susan H. "Education and Fertility: What Do We Really Know?"&#13;
(mimeo.) World Bank, 1977.&#13;
Encarnacion, Jose.   Effects of Family Income and Education on Fertility:&#13;
Cross-Section Results, Philippines, 1968. (Quezon City) Institute&#13;
of Economic Development &amp; Research, School of Economics, University&#13;
of the Philippines, 1972.&#13;
Easterlin, Richard A. "Towards a Socioeconomic Theory of Fertility: A&#13;
Survey of Recent Research on Economic Factors in American Fertility".&#13;
In Fertility and Family Planning, eds. J.J. Behrman, Leslie Corra, Jr.,&#13;
and Ronald Freedman. Ann Arbor, University of Michigan Press, 1969.&#13;
Expert GrouD Meetings on Social &amp; PsycholoRical Aspects of Fertility&#13;
Behavior. Asian Population Studies Series (Bangkok 1974).&#13;
Fawcett, J.T., Psychology and Population: Behavioral Research Issues&#13;
in Fertility and Family Planning (New York Population Council 1970).&#13;
Freedman, R. and Berelson, B. "The Record of Family Planning" Studies in&#13;
Family Planning, January 1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
Freedman et al. "Fertility Trends in Taiwan" 1961-70, November 1971.&#13;
University of Michigan Population Studies Center and Taiwan Committee&#13;
on Family Planning. Taiwan Population Studies Working Paper #15,&#13;
Ann Arbor.&#13;
Haney, C. Allen, et al. "The Value Stretch Hypothesis: Family Size&#13;
Preferences in a Black Population". Social Problems 21:206-220,&#13;
Fall 1973.&#13;
Harman, Harry H. Modern Factor Analysis. Chicago, The University of&#13;
Chicago Press, 1967.&#13;
Hawthorn, Geof.    The Sociology of Fertility (London, Collier-MacMillan,&#13;
1969).&#13;
Han, Sung Hyun. Correlations Between Fertility Rates and Family Planning&#13;
Acceptance Rates: Preliminary Tabulations of Data from 1971&#13;
Fertility Survey. Korean Institute for Family Planning (Seoul)&#13;
Family Planning Quarterly, Vol. 1, July 1972.&#13;
International Planned Parenthood Federation, Survey of World Needs in&#13;
Family Planning. (London, 1974).&#13;
Jain and Sarma, "Some Explanatory Factors for Statewide Differential&#13;
Use of Family Planning Methods in India"(mimeo.), 1974.&#13;
Karim, Mehtab S. "Fertility Differentials by Family Type". Pakistan&#13;
Development Review (Islamabad) 13(2) Summer 1974.&#13;
Kim, K.S. and Kim,D.Y. "The Effects of Household Size, Structure and&#13;
Income on Expenditure Patterns", Population and Emplovment Working&#13;
Paper #21 (May 1975).&#13;
King, Timothy and other World Bank Staff. Population Policies and&#13;
Economic Development, Baltimore, Johns Hopkins University Press, 1974.&#13;
Kirk, Dudley, 1971, "A New Demographic Transition"in Rapid Population&#13;
Growth, prepared by National Academy of Sciences, Baltimore.&#13;
Kocher, James. Rural Development Income Distribution and Fertility&#13;
Decline. New York City: The Population Council, 1973.&#13;
Kogut, E.L. "The Economic Analysis of Fertility". Population and&#13;
Employment Working Paper #7 (September 1974).&#13;
Leibenstein, Harvey. "Socioeconomic Fertility Theories and Their&#13;
Relevance to Population Policy". International Labour Review&#13;
109 (May/June 1974).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
Loebner, H. and Driver, Edwin D. "Differential Fertility in Central India:&#13;
A Path Analysis", Demography, Vol. 10.3, August 1973.&#13;
Marckwardt, Albert M. "Findings from Family Planning Research: Latin&#13;
American Supplement", Population Council Reports on Population/Family&#13;
Planning, New York, June 1974, No. 12.&#13;
Mason, K., David, A., Gerstel, E., Lindsey, Q., and Rubison, M. Social and&#13;
Economic Correlates of Family Fertility: A Survey of the Evidence.&#13;
Research Triangle Park: The Center for Population Research and&#13;
Services, Research Triangle Institute.&#13;
Mauldin, Parker W. and Berelson, B. "Conditions of Fertility Decline in&#13;
Developing Countries", Studies in Family Planning, Vol. 9 #5, The&#13;
Population Council, May 1978.&#13;
McGreevey, William P. and Nancy Birdsall. The Relevance of Recent Research&#13;
on Fertility. Washington, D.C., The Smithsonian Institution, 1974.&#13;
Nayar, P.R. and Copinathan. "A Decline in Birth in Korea: A Hypothesis&#13;
About Inter-relationships in Demographic Variables, Health Services&#13;
and Education", Economic Political Weekly, February 1974.&#13;
Preston, Samuel H. "Health Programs and Population Growth", Population&#13;
Development Review, Vol. 1, No. 2.&#13;
Ravenholt, T.V. and Chao, John. "World Fertility Trend". In Population&#13;
Reports, Series J. Published by George Washington University&#13;
Medical Center, Department of Medical Affairs, Washington, D.C. No. 2.&#13;
Reynolds, Jack. Studies in Family Planning, Population Council, Vol. 4 #11.&#13;
Rich, William. Smaller Families Through Social and Economic Progress.&#13;
Washington, D.C., Overseas Development Council (mimeo.), No. 7,&#13;
January 1973.&#13;
Robinson, Warren and Horlacker, David. "Population Growth and Economic&#13;
Welfare". Reports on Population/Family Planning, 6 (February 1971).&#13;
Rodgers, G.B. with Kirandana, T. "Fertility and Desired Fertility:&#13;
Longitudinal Evidence from Thailand". Population and Employment&#13;
Working Paper #11 (February 1975).&#13;
Rummel, R.J. Applied Factor Analysis. Evanston, Northwestern University&#13;
Press, 1970.&#13;
Schultz, T. Paul. "An Economic Perspective on Population Growth". In&#13;
National Academy of Sciences, Rapid Population Growth. Washington, D.C.,&#13;
National Academy of Sciences, 1971.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
Schultz, T. "Economic Factors Affecting Population Growth: A Preliminary&#13;
Survey of Economic Analyses of Fertility". Minneapolis Center for&#13;
Economic Research, Department of Economics, University of Minnesota,&#13;
1973.&#13;
Schultz, T. Fertility Determinants: A Theory, Evidence and Application&#13;
(Santa Monica, Rand, 1974). Rand Report R-1016-RF/AUD.&#13;
Simmons, Alan B. "Ambivalence Toward Small Families in Rural Latin&#13;
America". Social Biology 21(2): 127-143, Summer 1974.&#13;
Srikantan, R.S. "Fertility Impact of Family Planning Programs in the&#13;
Context of Social Change and Economic Development" (mimeo.).&#13;
Draft paper for PAA 1976.&#13;
Srikantan, R.S. "The Fertility Impact of Family Planning Programs in&#13;
the Socioeconomic Context: General Survey of 75 Countries from a&#13;
Long Term Perspective". New York Population Council (mimeo.).&#13;
Sun, T.H. "An Intensive Effort to Reduce Fertility in Taoyuan County,&#13;
Taiwan: 1973 Intermediate Report". Industry of Free China (Taipei)&#13;
42:6-15, August 1974.&#13;
Sweezy, Alan. "Socioeconomic Development and Fertility" - pp. 41-56,&#13;
American Universities Field Staff. Population: Perspective 1973.&#13;
Edited by Harrison Brown et al. San Francisco, Freeman, Cooper&#13;
&amp; Co., 1973.&#13;
Tsui, Amy 0. and Bogue, Donald J.    Declining World Fertility:   Trends,&#13;
Causes, Implications, Population Reference Bureau, Inc., Vol. 33&#13;
#4, Washington, 1978.&#13;
Thein, Tin Hyaing. Some Variables of Fertility Decline in Trinidad and&#13;
Tobago. New York, Columbia University, International Institute for&#13;
Study of Human Reproduction, 1970.&#13;
Thein and Reynolds. "Female Sterilization in Costa Rica, 1959-1969".&#13;
University of Costa Rica, Center of Social Studies and Population&#13;
1973.&#13;
Turchi, Boone. "Microeconomic Theories of Fertility: A Critique".&#13;
Social Forces, 54 (September 1975): 107-125.&#13;
U.N. Population Division, Report on Monitoring of Population Trends&#13;
E/CN.9/XlXCRP, December 1974 (mimeo.).&#13;
Welch, Finis. Sex of Children: Prior Uncertainty and Subsequent Fertility&#13;
Behavior (Rand Report) R-1510-RF. Santa Monica, Rand Corporation,&#13;
August 1974.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
William.s, Anne D. "Fertility and Infant Mortality". Thesis prospoctus&#13;
Univeristy of Chicago, October 1973.&#13;
Wolfers, D.   "Problems of Expandizg Population".   Nature (London' 225&#13;
(5233):593-597, February 14, 1970.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Io              -       .. N    -   - &#13;
01~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
0 10 0  0 0  0 a,  o I  !: =   o  M  o w M 0 &#13;
1 °°°°°°0°°°°^ooIT  t  M0o  M   'I&lt;rN oo&#13;
1 °:°°0,   °M ° o       M&#13;
a. a. .:r  _ o  _ o  M  _     o  Inv c o v-_&#13;
a In o     Nal   Vl In  0 M" o In  .0o  N M  C la&#13;
~~~. .~~~~~~~Mn     0 'O  a, -" M la&#13;
-  -,                  In .-o _ w o, o N ^ N | N &lt; § oO Y - N  w  o  M T  _&#13;
3.. &#13;
8  0I~l O _I l  _  N  a, N _   M -   M------ o M  0 aoM&#13;
In 10~~ e o 0n  01 In I  N rI  I! -  i N  N vi -&#13;
cn&#13;
U)~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~1&#13;
Cd    U  I0               ..   .........&#13;
¢ .:r     eW esZ -T   -Z .1  o 1 IT  o In la la   la  %  In  vt &#13;
-I  2    0 * 0.VIN 4M  M .2  ON  I 00 ~ l000,&#13;
o           N      N  N  N  N  ..N   -  -&#13;
9 on.0 aaIII0'aa    IN  _ _Ina.a.In_IN o I oa. u C@&gt;o &#13;
EC  InIflNN__NN^_ N  I -  NNMal -_  ___&#13;
I  a.OO0-In0Ma.8Ou,0-I00rN-..7O0unc.a.0&#13;
0   !  i      99  ~ 1.  NNg.  N..4  &#13;
j Nt In 0t 0t 0 I  0 0  In In '0 I  0  In sO.  In 0  - - 0  Na ^  0 e a. 0 In a. In a.&#13;
00.1.-sON  InNN  011.95~0,:O  N  0;-I0a. M.I~&#13;
Iai   o o.   M N.TN  5,  M    M.  M  MN M.-.&#13;
.J  * 0 &lt;^ Co.4CflN  NNa   -  O1.9.M  195001 T t.- 0.M l&#13;
M  M00        *n0M -350  boNe0&#13;
IMNorOOo                            o-_ ooo t  N  tos &#13;
U . NI.3n0-N              It-.--. _  I0Ins ...&#13;
.....................&#13;
I '=501T    0NnN.0O .0  0 1t _  o O s 0.t fo  o.S orr *  : N- C&gt;&#13;
t InInItINIn  _  ~ .-NslIUn  -  7_ N  1.4N  ~. J &#13;
3.  C    J C &gt;&lt;         ;  -       :&#13;
=| Q 'D _ .0 0 X _ X ^ S X * X X * t C _ C _ X e r 4 | _ ^ * 3.0&#13;
r ;n  3; A 2. O 3 3  , s  &gt; °  m Q  Q Q  ~, * * _  $   0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
51 -  - -  -  -  S  CC 0.s  _   ( _e7_N&#13;
_ 0( M -' 0( (N.0 0( uf (N0 (N  M  (NO  7.et  70  O  I   &lt;0   7f _  O0&#13;
g1.1  ( eN (N    a N  I n  10  (N 0 0   1  0 1. (t&#13;
-  r~~I  ..(NM  (N  .701(NlaM   .0(M  N   . &#13;
z                               -&#13;
D          o           o r. I. 7   (0  _  01 1071.0 (I n nCt   M-7.0(-&#13;
a l     a  a,   0 1         (&#13;
X Y " Z 100101(^N(^N4 0 N N   MIO  _  ( 07'(N_&#13;
_ _ w C14""_!_2_MN _" -_ -&#13;
I 7(NC _-  -'     ' _O O D  - - -  -&#13;
-I0   w_@Ne0  "os&gt;XoNe  O_eObe_NVI &#13;
o  a                           -~~~~~~o&#13;
413~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~2&#13;
..NM  M10   la71   I.I770 n0(0In(0&#13;
.0~~~~~~~~~~0&#13;
(N(N0(N .~..  ~  0  0  l.7C.  7...0 0( (N   l1  01&#13;
(N0  0.C  ...... (.0(N-(0l0((N0N....   .(...... .......... ......&#13;
z -   a. r00. o I N 0 -_ ,        0o -&gt; &#13;
-~~~~~-' -'u -mu (  01 &#13;
Q2     s &#13;
_~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0&#13;
C     0 O . ( ( 0 . C O 41 I " 7 I - ( ( ( 0&#13;
...0...........................((&#13;
I .000000000000000000000e0r 0000&lt;00 Xr &lt;o oe &#13;
_  __  __  _N  f ¢^ o  __ _flfsO . 70e M00 _ _ ( N  -eo &#13;
.01  000-0C&gt;I41C(_  r(N .00D  1-C ,- 0-  _ D . 0100. O  t0 0   - &#13;
(.1 .00 .7. .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  . . .0.0.  . .C0.  .  .&#13;
.0 &#13;
| ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ - 0"              ' _ _aY0 &lt; w _Z ~ 0 @&#13;
o1   0      41     41  6     .0mo ^&lt; Sw _N &gt;0&#13;
'7  OO_;_ O74  g OO  U  I.  6 _041 O" &lt;O  - -&#13;
P  1   4 .. . .. . .................6.....&#13;
X ~ ~ ~ ~ ~  67s o41_e__r0r_ v0_ "_0r Ue_e&#13;
Z ....................... 6.....&#13;
N   se  00  'a0  '7.6  .00 000  I. 006   00&#13;
_'C41        _ &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
RECENT PAPERS IN THIS SERIES&#13;
No.                      TITLE OF PAPER                             AUTHOR&#13;
290    Major Reforms of the Swedish Education System        A. Heidenheimer (consultant)&#13;
291    Industrialization, Technology and Employment -       T. Rawski (consultant)&#13;
China&#13;
292    Development and Income Distribution   -  Zambia      C. Blitzer&#13;
293    World Potash Survey                                  W. Sheldrick, H. Stier&#13;
294    The Economic Dimensions of Malnutrition in           M. Selowsky&#13;
Young Children&#13;
295    The Technology of Rural Development                  J.P. McInerney (consultant)&#13;
296    The Financial Cost of Agricultural Credit:           C.D. Datey (consultant)&#13;
A Case Study of Indian Experience&#13;
297    Agricultural Sector Planning Models:                 A.C. Egbert&#13;
A Selected Summary and Critique&#13;
298    Textbooks and Achievement:  What We Know             S.P. Heyneman.&#13;
J. Farrell,&#13;
A. Sepulveda-Stuardo&#13;
(consultants)&#13;
299    An Economic and Social Analysis of the               C. Bruce&#13;
Chao Phya Irrigation Improvement Project II          Y. Kimaro&#13;
300    Two-Studies of Development in Sub-Saharan Africa     S. Acharya&#13;
B. Johnston (consul;ant)&#13;
301    The Intermediate Sector, Unemployment, and The       W.F. Steel&#13;
Employment-Output Conflict:   A Multi-Sector Model   Y. Takagi (consultant)&#13;
302    The Economic Theory of the Household and Impact      D. Chernichovsky&#13;
Measurement of Nutrition and Related Health&#13;
Programs&#13;
303    Trade Restrictions and International Price           M. Bale&#13;
Instability                                          E. Lutz&#13;
304    Intergovernmental Fiscal Relations in Developing     R. Bird (consultant)&#13;
Countries&#13;
305    A Programming Approach to Fertilizer Sector          A. Choksi&#13;
Planning                                             A. Meeraus&#13;
306    The Foreign Exchange Gap, Growth and Industrial      K. Dervis&#13;
Strategy in Turkey:   1973-1983                      S. Robinson&#13;
307    The Importance of Risk in Agricultural Planning      P. Hazell, R. Norton&#13;
Models                                               M. Parthasarathy.&#13;
C. Pomareda (consultant)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
RECENT PAPERS IN THIS SERIES&#13;
No.                       TITLE OF PAPER                            AUTHOR&#13;
308        Guidelines for School Location Planning            W. Gould (consultant)&#13;
309        Growth and Poverty in Developing Countries         M. Ahluwalia, N. Carter&#13;
H. Chenery&#13;
310        Teacher Training and Student Achievement in        T. Husen, L. Saha&#13;
Less Developed Countries                           R. Noonan (consultants)&#13;
311        Optimum Economic Power Supply Reliability          M. Munasinghe&#13;
M. Gellerson (consu.tani&#13;
312        Intra-Industry Trade and the Integration of        B. Balassa&#13;
Developing Countries in the World Economy&#13;
313        Export Promotion Policies                          B. de Vries&#13;
314        The Changing Composition of Developing             H. Chenery&#13;
Country Exports                                    D. Keesing&#13;
315        Urban Growth and Economic Development in the       M. Cohea&#13;
Sahel: Prospects and Priorities&#13;
316        World Trade and Output of Manufactures:           D. KeeEing&#13;
Structural Trends and Developing Countries'&#13;
Exports&#13;
317        Cuba:  Economic Change and Education Reform        M. Car-noy, J. Wertheim&#13;
1955-1974                                          (consultants)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG3881.5 .W57 W67 no.318 c.3&#13;
Faruqee, Rashid, 1938-&#13;
Sources of fertility decline&#13;
factor analysis of&#13;
inter-country data /&#13;
DATE    NAME AND EXTENSION    ROOM&#13;
NUMBER&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1555102">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1979/02/1555102/sources-fertility-decline-factor-analysis-inter-country-data
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1979/02/1555102/sources-fertility-decline-factor-analysis-inter-country-data</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1979/02/1555102/sources-fertility-decline-factor-analysis-inter-country-data</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/23/000178830_98101903402168/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/23/000178830_98101903402168/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1979-02-28T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-09-23T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Sources of fertility decline : factor
            analysis of inter-country data
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In recent times, a number of developing
            countries have experienced a decline in fertility making it
            possible to study the factors inducing such decline. This
            subject constitutes the core of a continuing debate between
            those who advocate intensive family planning programs
            irrespective of the level of socio-economic development and
            those who support the proposition that development is the
            best contraceptive. Although most people would take a
            position in between these two extremes, a serious debate
            still continues regarding the desired sequence and mix of
            the two. A crucial policy aspect of the debate is the issue
            whether family planning programs can be a useful trade-off
            for socioeconomic development in a high fertility
            population. The present study, using factor analysis,
            collapses a set of interrelated variables in terms of a
            smaller number of mutually independent factors, which make
            it possible to separate out the effects of family planning
            program inputs and socio-economic development. The findings
            of this study confirm the significant role of family
            planning, but socioeconomic development clearly emerges as
            the more important of the two in influencing fertility decline.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Sources of fertility decline : factor
            analysis of inter-country data
        </docna>
        <display_title>Sources of fertility decline :
            factor analysis of inter-country data</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1979/02/1555102/sources-fertility-decline-factor-analysis-inter-country-data</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Statistical &amp; Mathematical Sciences,Poverty Assessment,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Reproductive Health</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>FARUQEE, R.</author>
            <author>DEDPH</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903402168</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Primary health, including
            reproductive health, child health and health</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 318</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Health, Nutrition &amp; Population</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Birth rate; Economic growth; Fertility
            decline; Mortality; Per capita income; Population movements;
            Public expenditures; Regression analysis; Social
            development; Urbanization; Family planning programs
            air,annual growth rate,average growth
            rate,birth rate,calculus,contraceptives,country
            context,country level,data availability,data set,death
            rate,Dependent Variable,determinants of fertility,developed
            countries,developing countries,Development
            Economics,economic development,economic growth,economic
            progress,economic theory,Empirical Evidence,expenditure
            variable,factor analysis,families,family planning,Family
            Planning Personnel,family planning
            programs,fertility,fertility decline,fertility
            determinants,GDP,GNP,Government Expenditures,Gross National
            Product,growth rate,health services,health status,household
            level,income,Independent Variables,individual
            countries,industrialization,infertility,isolation,Life
            Expectancy,living
            standards,malnutrition,Matrix,mortality,Motivation,parents,per
            capita income,policy level,population
            growth,pregnancy,public expenditure,public health,public
            sector,Regression Analysis,regression models,social
            services,socio- economic factors,socio-economic
            factors,socio-economic indicators,total fertility rate,urban
            areas,Urban Population
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP318</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographic Transition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Birth Spacing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographic Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Family Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contraceptives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Credit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>