<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Inter-Country Comparison of "Real (PPP) Incomes:.&#13;
Revised Estimates andUnresolved Quest'ions&#13;
World Bank Staff Workilng Paper No. 358&#13;
Sepemer1979&#13;
Prepared bv: Paul Isenman&#13;
Policy Planning &amp; Program Review, Department&#13;
Copyright ©O 1979&#13;
The Worl d saiik&#13;
1 81 8 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
The views and initerpretations in this document are thiose of the author&#13;
anid Should not be attributed to the World Bank, toits affiliated&#13;
organizations, or to any individlual acting in their behalf.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations,&#13;
or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 358&#13;
September 1979'&#13;
Inter-Country Comparison of "Real" (PPP) Incomes:&#13;
Revised Estimates and Unresolved Questions&#13;
Adjusting for purchasing power parities of national currencies makes&#13;
a significant difference to inter-country income comparisons.   However, PPP&#13;
estimates require detailed price data which are not readily available for&#13;
most countries. Kravis, Heston and Summers have used regression analysis to&#13;
extend their PPP estimates from the sixteen countries for which they have&#13;
detailed prices to any country for which data are available on the share of&#13;
trade in GDP and on inflation. The first part of this paper argues that a&#13;
variant of this "short cut" approach, one which relies on measures of human&#13;
resource development rather than on trade and inflation, is preferable on&#13;
theoretical and statistical grounds. The second part of the paper raises a&#13;
more fundamental issue. It argues that the treatment of services in their&#13;
detailed analysis, and hence in any short-cut approach derived from it, is&#13;
biased. This bias tends to exaggerate the PPP incomes of countries with&#13;
relatively good human resource development, and so produces misleading esti-&#13;
mates of relative incomes among poor countries and of the gap between poor&#13;
and rich countries.&#13;
Prepared by: Paul Isenman&#13;
Policy Planning &amp; Program Review Department&#13;
Copyright    1979&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
INTER-COUNTRY COMPARISON OF "'REAL" (PPP) INCOMES:&#13;
REVISED ESTIMATES AND UNRESOLVED QUESTIONS*&#13;
Introduction&#13;
There is now fairly widespread awareness of the inadequacies of&#13;
comparing per capita incomes without making adjustments for the purchasing&#13;
power parities (PPPs) of national currencies. In general, use of officia.&#13;
exchange rates tends to understate incomes in poor countries, even though&#13;
they often have overvalued exchanige rates. This is because price levels tend&#13;
to be lower in these countries. Kravis, Heston and Summers have been working&#13;
for a number of years on a major project to collect and analyze detailed price&#13;
data in countries at all income levels. The results of "Phase 2" of their&#13;
work, reporting PPP incomes for sixteen countries, indicate, for example, that&#13;
use of PPP rather than nominal prices causes incomes of poor countries to&#13;
increase by 100% to 200% in relation to that of the US (ICP, 1978).&#13;
A major difficulty in using PPP prices is the time, expense and&#13;
political and administrative problems of gathering detailed price data for&#13;
every country for which PPP income estimates are desired. Therefore, to&#13;
develop a set of PPP incomes that can be used for cross-country analysis,&#13;
Kravis, Heston, and Summers have used regression analysis to develop a "short-&#13;
cut" method of predicting PPP incomes for over one hundred countries (KHS,&#13;
1978, thereafter referred to as KHS).- They derive a set of regression co-&#13;
efficients which fairly faithfully (R2= .99) reproduce the PPP incomes of&#13;
the sixteen countries for which detailed estimates for 1970 were available,&#13;
They then use the coefficients to predict purchasing power parity incomes&#13;
for any country for which aggregate trade and inflation (GDP deflator) data&#13;
are available. No price data for individual goods and services are required&#13;
for these short-cut estimates.&#13;
The first par.- of this paper suggests an alternate approach to&#13;
short-cut estimates, The second considers the need to address an apparent&#13;
bias in the detailed ICP approach -- a bias which would affect conclusions&#13;
reached on such key questions as the extent and distribution of world poverty,&#13;
or the impact of income level on consumption patterns.&#13;
I.   Revised Estimates:&#13;
KHS argue persuasively that the main reason for the difference&#13;
between PPP and official exchange rate estimates of GDP is in services and&#13;
other non-1.raded goods. "In summary, if traded goods prices are pressed&#13;
toward equality by international trade, but non-traded goods prices vary&#13;
with the level of income, the overall price level for GDP will also vary&#13;
*    I would like to thank, without implicating, John Edelman, Frances Stewart,&#13;
Robert McPheeters and Sultan Ahmad for their suggestions and encourage-&#13;
ment, and Irving Kravis for comments on an earlier draft. Also, Satish&#13;
Mannan provided helpful assistance in the regression analysis.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
directly with real per capita income...   The real (PPP) per capita GDP of&#13;
the low-income country consequently will be higher relative to that of a&#13;
comparison of their nominal GDPs per capita" (KHS, p. 220). This importance&#13;
of non-. ½aded goods is apparent from the "full-information" PPP estimates&#13;
reported in the ICP study. For their four lowest income countries, Kenya,&#13;
India, Philippines and South Korea, non-traded goods were revalued upward&#13;
by an unweighted average of 341%, while for traded goods the increase was&#13;
only 78%.  In the case of India, the inrrease for non-traded goods was 646%&#13;
while that for traded goods was 102% yielding a weighted average for GDP of&#13;
234%. Using the ICP terminology, the "deviation index" -- the ratio of PPP&#13;
to conventional incomes -- for India was 7.46 for non-traded goods, 2.02 for&#13;
traded goods, and 3.34 for total GDP.&#13;
KHS seek to explain inter-country differences in the deviation&#13;
index for GDP in terms of variables affecting or measuring the extent of&#13;
international trade, arguing that a country "more exposed to the world econ-&#13;
omy is likely to have its non-traded goods prices pulled up closer to (those)&#13;
of high-income countries" (p. 221). In their regression analysis KHS use&#13;
three independent variables: conventional GDP; an index of "openness" --&#13;
imports plus exports as a percentage of conventional GDP; and "price isola-&#13;
tion" -- the (square of the) difference in inflation from that of their esti-&#13;
mated "world" average. Although there is a plausible case that the latter&#13;
two variables have an impact on the deviation index, KHS themselves niote that&#13;
there is room for question about the expected direction of that impact.    In&#13;
particular, one might well think that (with constant exchange rates) the&#13;
greater a country's price isolation -- i.e., the higher its inflation* --&#13;
then the higher its internal prices in relation to international prices, and&#13;
the lower its PPP income. The KHS hypothesis is, however, the opposite --&#13;
that "the greater the price isolation the less a country's non-traded goods&#13;
price will be pulled up ... and the larger will be real income" (KHS, p.&#13;
223).&#13;
KHS summarize the evolution of thinking on why the prices of non-&#13;
traded goods, which are largely personal services, tend to vary with income&#13;
level. Implicit in their summary is that there are constraints on the inter-&#13;
national mobility of labor, including the financial and psychic costs of&#13;
migration and restrictions on immigration into high wage countries. These&#13;
constraints keep the prices of services from being bid up, through trade, to&#13;
international levels. To the extent that there are constraints on interna-&#13;
tional labor mobility, then the price of services should be determined by&#13;
supply and demand within relevant segments of the domestic labor markets.&#13;
This approach appears to have a less unambiguous basis in theory than that&#13;
put forward by KHS.&#13;
*    While the mean squared deviation from "world" average inflation could&#13;
reflect inflation either above or below thaL average, in practice the&#13;
high "price isolation" values (p. 216) were all associated with above-&#13;
average inflation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-3-&#13;
The specific hypothesis pursued here is that the supply of labor&#13;
of various skill categories (relative to average incomes) is a key determinant&#13;
of the deviation index for non-traded goods, and hence that for GDP as a whole.&#13;
Conventional per capita income, which is already included as an independent&#13;
variable in the KHS i:egression analysis, would serve as a proxy for inter-&#13;
country differences :in the wage for unskilled and semi-skilled services (as&#13;
well as for differences in the price of traded goods). However, it cannot&#13;
serve as a satisfactory proxy for the wage for skilled services, in view of&#13;
the substantial differences in the labor supply for skilled services (e.g.,&#13;
the supply of teachers) among low-income countries, due to cultural, his-&#13;
torical and political factors. The difference between India and Kenya in&#13;
this regard, for example, is well known. India has a much greater supply,&#13;
in relation to demand, of highly trained manpower, and because of its well-&#13;
developed educational system can increase 4his supply relatively cheaply.&#13;
In the following regression analysis, two approaches are used. One&#13;
is a pure "short-cut" method, which relies only on published international&#13;
data series and does not require price data per se.   The other is a combina-&#13;
tion short-cut and limited-information approach, which like the short-cut&#13;
method makes use of regression analysis, but which also includes selected&#13;
observed price data. The short-cut approach has the advantage of quickly&#13;
yielding estimates fdr any country for which even minimal data are available,&#13;
and is potentially useful as a substitute for conventional income data in&#13;
cross-country analysis. However, it is too crude a tool to be aicepted as a&#13;
firm basis for setting an income level for any given country. Limited infor-&#13;
mation approaches, which require gathering consistent price data on, for&#13;
example, forty commodities, are likely eventually to provide superior and&#13;
more generally acceptable results to those of short-cut analysis. However,&#13;
collecting a consistent series of prices for well over one hundred countries&#13;
is a formidable task, even for only forty commodities. Thus, it may be that&#13;
the hybrid short-cut limited-information approach, which would require a very&#13;
small number of prices for each country covered, may be the best available&#13;
approach for the next several years.&#13;
The independent variables tried, in the short-cut analysis, were&#13;
rates of literacy, secondary enrollment, and university enrollment. Coeffi-&#13;
cients of any of the three would be expected to be positive, since the supply&#13;
of trained manpower for which they are a proxy would be negatively related to&#13;
the price of services and hence positively related to PPP incomes and devia-&#13;
tion indexes. The choice among these variables would depend on the relative&#13;
importance of the differing skill levels they represent in explaining inter-&#13;
country differences in the price of services. (Because of colinearity, only&#13;
one among them would be expected to be significant in any given equation.) The&#13;
price variables tried were the wages, at official exchange rates, for teachers,&#13;
skilled workers and white collar workers. Here expected signs would be nega-&#13;
tive; higher wages for services would be related to lower PPP incomes and&#13;
deviation indexes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
Conventional per-capita income was included as a variable in both&#13;
the short-cut and combination equations. Following both KHS and the labor-&#13;
supply hypothesis advanced here, its sign would be negative, and the devia-&#13;
tion index would decrease as conventional incomes increase. Various specifi-&#13;
cations of the variables were tried, including that of KHS (double-log with&#13;
quadratic treatment of income). "Stepwise" analysis was used to choose the&#13;
best statistical fit among alternate plausible explanatory variables. Since&#13;
the human-resource approach used here is not necessarily inconsistent with&#13;
the KHS trade-related approach, separate regression runs were carried out&#13;
which also included "openness" and "price isolation."&#13;
The specification of the dependent variable differed from that of&#13;
KHS. Their dependent variable was the ICP estimate of PPP per capita GDP,&#13;
expressed as a percent of US per capita GDP. A difficulty with this speci-&#13;
fication is that since both series grcei roughly in parallel, conventional&#13;
income alone explains 98.6Z of the variance (in their log quadratic specifi-&#13;
cation). This does not leave much room to distinguish among other explana-&#13;
tory variables. The best result obtained by KHS explained 98.9% of the vari-&#13;
ance, or only .3% more than with income alone. To distinguish among other&#13;
plausible variables is particularly important for those interested in com-&#13;
parative incomes or poverty incidence in low-income countries. To deal with&#13;
this problem, the deviation index was used as the independent variable. In-&#13;
come explains a still high but slightly smaller percent of the variance (92%&#13;
in a log quadratic specification). The deviation index also gives more stat-&#13;
istical weight to the low-income countries, since its variance is much greater&#13;
at lower incomes.&#13;
Results for 1970&#13;
Results of the regression analysis for the KHS 1970 data are shown&#13;
in Table 1.*&#13;
*    The countries for which the "full information" PPP estimates were avail-&#13;
able were Kenya, India, Philippines, Korea (Rep. of), Colombia, Malaysia,&#13;
Iran, Hungary, Italy, Japan, U.K., Netherlands, Belgium, France, Germany&#13;
(F.R.), and U.S.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-5-&#13;
Table 1&#13;
Dqeternlnants of the I'PP Deviation Index - 1970&#13;
Pi       Op    1 EACIH-&#13;
Lrnbln i              (n I  LnLn In    -i-pi            I.P  n LnSEC0ND1i Constant  R E.&#13;
(1) Short Cut         Ln DEV     -0.5302   -0.0475     -        -       -    +0.1804    -0.8221  0.946&#13;
(-6.46) a/ (-2.39)                           (3.01)    (-2.93)  (0.0856)&#13;
(2) Lv-il'ted Iniormal.ion       -0.3334               -        -     -0.1268          + 0,1806  0.960&#13;
- Slhort Cut       Ln DEV   (-17.26)                              (-4.76)            (5.04)  (0.0738)&#13;
(3) KIIS Short-Cut               -0.4618   -0.0551 +0 .0263  -0.0597    -       -      + 0.0459  0.929&#13;
(Thcir Eq. D)      Ln DE'    (-3.93)   (-1.92)  (1.57)   (-1.23)                     (0.65)  (0.0962)&#13;
(4) Combination of 2 &amp; 3 L n DEV  -0.3096  + 0.0059  +0.0106  +0.0625  -0.1417         +0.11.68  0.963&#13;
(-3.25)    (0.22)  (0.82)    (1.25)  (-3.38)            (2.13)  (0.0701)&#13;
(5) Combination of 1 &amp; 3 Ln DEV  -0.5164   -0.0522  +0.0179  -0.0377         +.0.1437   -0.6269  0.948&#13;
(-S.03)   (-2.13)   (2.22)  (-0.89)           (2.29)   (-2.09)  (0.083!,)&#13;
a/    t-statistics&#13;
Dependent variable:       DEV = Ratio of PPP to conventional GDP.&#13;
Independent variables:    n   = conventional (exchange rate converted) GDP per&#13;
capita as ratio of US GDP per capita.&#13;
PI = price isolation (mean squared deviation of&#13;
implicit deflator from "world" implicit&#13;
deflator, 1963-70).&#13;
OP = openness (ratio of exports plus imports to&#13;
GNP, 1965-73).&#13;
TEACH = teacher salaries at conventional prices,&#13;
in US dollars.&#13;
SECOND = secondary school enrollment, ratio.&#13;
Sources:   DEV, n, PI and OP from KHS; TEACH from ICP, Appendix Table 4.3;&#13;
SECOND from UNESCO Statistical Yearbook, 1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6-&#13;
The best statistical fit in the case of the sho5t-cut approach was with income&#13;
and enrollment in secondary education (Eq. 1, R = .95); the signs for both&#13;
variables were as expected. Enrollment in secondary education, relative to&#13;
per capita income, is an indicator of the supply of middle-level manpower.&#13;
The best fit in the case of the combined limited information and-hort-cut&#13;
approach was with income and the teacher-wage variable, (Eq. 2, R   =.96)*&#13;
again -7ith the expected signs.&#13;
The reestimation of what KHS identified as their best equation is&#13;
seen in Equation 3. Equations 1 and 2 are preferable to it, partly because&#13;
of their slightly higher R s and lower standard errors. The human resource&#13;
variables in Equations 1 and 2 are statistically significant at .01, while&#13;
neither price isolation nor openness was significant at .05. When the human&#13;
resource and KHS variables are combined, in Equations 4 and 5, not only do&#13;
the human resource variable continue to have much better "t" values, but in&#13;
Equation 4 the sign of the openness variable shifts from negative to posi-&#13;
tive. More importantly, as noted above, human resource variables have a&#13;
less ambiguous theoretical base.&#13;
Also, the country-specific deviation indexes derived from the human&#13;
resource short-cut equation appear to fit better with the "spirit" of the full-&#13;
information KHS estimates than does their own short-cut equation. Appendix&#13;
Table A presents an alternate set of PPP estimates of GDP per capita using&#13;
the coefficients from Equation 1, and compares them to the KHS estimates.   The&#13;
countries in which the human-resources short-cut approach led to the largest&#13;
changes in the est:mated deviation index are shown in Table 2.&#13;
*    The log of teacher wages (Lq TEACH) could be substituted for TEACH/n&#13;
with only a small loss in R . Since there was no a priori behavioral&#13;
reason to say that one specification or the other better described the&#13;
impact of teaiher wages on the log of the deviation index, the one with&#13;
the highest R is reported here. Experimentation with other wage var-&#13;
iables, or perhaps addition of prices of 2key traded goods, such as&#13;
grains, might well produce even higher R s.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
Table 2&#13;
Comparison of Human-Resource and KHS&#13;
Estimates of the PPP Per Capita GDP&#13;
Highest Increase                                 Highest Decrease&#13;
Increase over                          Decrease from&#13;
Human-Resource      KHS                  Human-Resource      KHS&#13;
Short-Cut       Short-Cuilt              Short-Cut      Short-Cut&#13;
Country        Estimate       Estimate      Country     Estimate      Estimate&#13;
(US$)         (Percent)                  (US$)        (Percent)&#13;
Sri Lanka       546             20       Niger            154           34&#13;
Barbados      1,381             20       Upper Volta      107           33&#13;
Philippines     559             18        Burundi         135           31&#13;
Burma           243             16       Mauritania       285           29&#13;
Guyana          935             17       Rwanda           122           25&#13;
Two points are apparent from this table (and from Column 5 in&#13;
Appendix Table A): the human resources approach can result in substantial&#13;
differences from the KHS approach in inter-country comparisons; and the human-&#13;
resource approach generally reduces income in Africa relative to those in&#13;
other regions. Let us compare the cases of Burma and Niger, both of which&#13;
had approximately equal conventional per capita incomes ($80-90) in 1970.&#13;
KHS estimates show Niger with a higher PPP income than Burma ($234 vs. $210),&#13;
while the human resource estimates show Burma to be much higher than Niger&#13;
($243 vs. $154). Recall that, for the sixteen countries on which detailed&#13;
price data were available, services of low-income countries were revalued&#13;
much more than traded goods; services were so inexpensive in India that&#13;
they were revalued up by 646%. The labor force in Burma, though, has a&#13;
substantially higher level of educational attainment than that in India and,&#13;
barring market failure, would be expected to have even lower prices of ser-&#13;
vices. Quite the opposite is true for Niger.* Thus, the KHS estimates -&#13;
which say in effect that, if detailed price information were also avail-&#13;
able for Niger and Burma, Niger's GDP would be revalued upward by more&#13;
than Burma's - seem implausible.&#13;
*    Literacy rates for Burma, India and Niger were 70%, 33% and 5% respec-&#13;
tively; their secondary enrollment rates were 25%, 30% and 1%.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
Reconciliation with Clague and Tanzi (1972)&#13;
One previous study (Clague and Tanzi, 1972) used a human-resource&#13;
(education) variable to explain the deviation index and came up with results&#13;
apparently quite different from those reported here; in one of their two&#13;
country samples the education variable had a negative sign, contrary to what&#13;
the discussion above would have suggested. However, this education variable&#13;
in fact serves as a proxy for a key excluded variable -- conventional per&#13;
capita income.* Rerunning their data with both education and income in the&#13;
same equation causes the sign of the educational variable to shift back to&#13;
positive. Results are reported in Appendix B.&#13;
II. Unresolved Questions:&#13;
The previous section developed an alternate set of short-cut PPP&#13;
income estimates for 129 countries, which it argued were more reliable than&#13;
those of KHS as proxies for the information ICP estimates. This section&#13;
raises some questions, though, about the full information estimates themselves.&#13;
We have seen that the KHS deviation index is highly dependent on the relative&#13;
price of services. In the ICP approach to international comparisons, PPP&#13;
prices for services are those wvhich one would have to pay in the (expenditure&#13;
weighted) "world" average country - i.e., in a relatively high-income country.&#13;
But how is that international price determined? KHS state "internal factor&#13;
mobility will lead to high wages also in non-traded goods in higher produc-&#13;
tivity countries" (KHS, p. 219). In other words the "international" price&#13;
of services (or other non-tradables) is measured essentially by the oppor-&#13;
tunity cost of the labor and other resources used to produce them in a rela-&#13;
tively high-productivity (income) country. How useful is it to measure the&#13;
price of services in this manner?&#13;
Let us consider the implications for resource allocation, taking&#13;
the example of primary and secondary education. Numerous studies have shown&#13;
positive (social and private) returns to education in India. But if we value&#13;
education in India at "international" prices, we would revalue it upward by&#13;
about fifteen times. In contrast, the value of the agricultural and indus-&#13;
trial traded goods produced by those educated would at international prices&#13;
only be doubled. With costs revalued upward by fifteen times, and benefits&#13;
doubled, returns would turn negative and so there would be little economic&#13;
justification for expenditures on education in India.** Similarly, if fac-&#13;
tories, and their leasing costs, are revalued upward by 900% but their output&#13;
*    The correlation between the Clague and Tanzi education variable and&#13;
conventional per capita income was .66 for the relevant sample of&#13;
thirteen OECD countries; the correlation between conventional per capita&#13;
income and the deviation index was .91.&#13;
**   To argue against this point on grounds that education should be valued&#13;
purely as a consumption good, rather than as a human capital investment,&#13;
would not be credible, particularly for low-income countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-9&#13;
is revalued by only 100% (i.e., the average for traded goods), there would&#13;
be little justification for building factories. This problem is a serious&#13;
one, since many or most services (or other non-traded goods) are, in essence,&#13;
intermediate (or investment) goods rather than consumption goods per se.&#13;
The obverse side of this problem is that output maximization at&#13;
ICP prices would call, for example, for huge increases in middle and higher&#13;
education, in spite of educated unemployment, and in factory construction,&#13;
more or less irrespective of demand. More generally, output maximization&#13;
would be achieved by shifting toward those expenditures which would be&#13;
revalued by high multiples (i.e., those with a high deviation index).* For&#13;
example, from 1970-76, Sri Lanka attempted to address some of its unemploy-&#13;
ment problem by increasing public sector employment more rapidly than the&#13;
(low) growth in output in either agriculture or industry. At ICP prices,&#13;
though, this growth in services would be revalued upward by a large multiple,&#13;
and thus GDP growth at ICP prices would seem misleadingly high. In sum, ICP&#13;
prices do not appear useful either for resource allocation, or for measuring&#13;
or comparing income growth rates.&#13;
In much the same manner, ICP prices have weaknesses as a guide&#13;
to measuring consumption per se. For example, how meaningful is it to say&#13;
that, if an Indian farmer hires an agricultural laborer, the farmer's ICP&#13;
income would go up by less than a tenth of the increase that would have&#13;
occurred if he had hired the same individual to work as a housThold servant?**&#13;
The ICP approach does have an understandable appeal, tbough. There is some-&#13;
thing rather democratic in saying, for example, that an hour of a nurse's&#13;
time is worth the same amount no matter what the cost of her training or&#13;
the incomes of those she treats. However, as noted previously, the "inter-&#13;
national" price of the nurses' services is determined by the opportunity&#13;
cost of these services (in terms of traded goods) in a relatively high-pro-&#13;
ductivity country. It is not at all a "pure" consumption price.&#13;
*    This would be true to some extent in the long run as well as the short&#13;
run. The opportunity cost, such as decreased food output, that would&#13;
be incurred from 'excessive' expenditures on services with a high&#13;
deviation index would be sharply reduced by present-value discounting.&#13;
**   The point here is not that the same set of prices need necessarily be&#13;
used for all purposes. In this case, however, the examples illustrate&#13;
not only the problems of using ICP prices for intra-country resource&#13;
allocation or consumption comparisons, but the reason why inter-country&#13;
comparisons based on the assumption of equal marginal productivity of&#13;
services are misleading.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
The above problems arise because the ICP treatment of services is&#13;
saying, in effect, that if there were perfect international mobility of labor&#13;
and if, therefore, the marginal productivity of services were the same in&#13;
India as in a relatively high-income country, then services in India would&#13;
be grossly underpriced in relation to traded goods.* But the assumptions&#13;
are incorrect and so, therefore, is the implication that the international&#13;
price is the "real" price for services in poor countries.&#13;
Put another way, to assume equal prices for (identical) services&#13;
is to assume equal availability (and "X" efficiency) of the complementary&#13;
factors of production that determine the marginal productivity of those ser-&#13;
vices. In a private communication Kravis indicates that ideally the ICP&#13;
comparisons for, e.g., doctors should take account of the effect on their&#13;
productivity of complementary capital inputs, such as expensive medical equip-&#13;
ment.  However, if this is true, then the same should apply to the whole range&#13;
of services (e.g., barbers, extension agents or engineers) and to other non-&#13;
traded goods (e.g., building rents).&#13;
What options are there that are consistent with the ICP general&#13;
approach, but which can deal with the problems of pricing non-traded goods?&#13;
First, weighting could be by population rather than by income. As indicated&#13;
in the discussion above, the ICP "international" price is, in essence, the&#13;
price faced by a person with the (relatively high) average per capita income&#13;
of the non-S' ialist countries. The person with the per capita income (or,&#13;
more precisely, expenditure) of $2,000 gets, on the average, 20 price "votes"&#13;
for every one of a person at $100 per capita. Kuznets (1972) has shown how&#13;
this principle produces estimates of country per capita income growth that&#13;
greatly overstates the growth enjoyed by the majority of the population. To&#13;
correct this, he proposed weighting per capita income growth by population&#13;
rather than income; average income growth would be measured by the average of&#13;
individual income grow.h rates, with the growth rate of the poor weighted as&#13;
much as the growth rate of the rich. Chenery and Ahluwalia have applied this&#13;
same principle to intra-country income weighting (Chenery et al., 1974). Why&#13;
not apply it also to determining international prices for PPP comparisons?**&#13;
*    The same general argument also applies in the case of other non-traded&#13;
goods, primarily construction; here the implicit KKHS assumption is that&#13;
productivity of investment in buildings and other non-traded goods is&#13;
as high in India as in a relatively high-income country.&#13;
**   A simplified expenditure-weighted index would be      (Q P )/ ;Q., where Q&#13;
is quantity, P price and i the country subscript.    The comparaile popu-&#13;
lation-weighted index would be     (Pop.P.) ,Pop..   For example, let us&#13;
take two countries.   The first has a population of one million and con-&#13;
sumes ten million haircuts at an average cost of $5. The second has a&#13;
population of ten million and consumes one million haircuts at an average&#13;
cost of $1. Conventional expenditure weights would put the average price&#13;
of $4.64, while with population weights the average price would be only&#13;
$1.36.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Second, non-traded goods could be set at a price to retain their&#13;
ratio to the average price of traded goods (which would be revalued in PPP&#13;
terms).* This would follow from the point noted earlier about the effect&#13;
of the %ack of international mobility of labor on actual marginal produc-&#13;
tivity (vs. the ICP use of hypothetical international marginal productivity).&#13;
Either of these two approaches would be relatively easy to compute, using the&#13;
detailed ICP data. As with other aspects of the index number problem (e.g.,&#13;
the choice between Paasche and laspeyeres indices), there is no reason that&#13;
one single method of valuing services needs to be adopted to the exclusion&#13;
of all others. For example, in comparing incomes among low-income countries&#13;
it might well be argued that prices in middle and upper income countries&#13;
are irrelevant and should not be used if - as is likely - they would mate-&#13;
rially change relative incomes among the low-income countries. In practice,&#13;
it would not be feasible to have more than one published PPP income level&#13;
(or at most two) for each country. Nevertheless, the marginal cost of car-&#13;
rying out special PPP income comparisons among particular groups of countries&#13;
is quite modest, given the availability of relevant country data and computer&#13;
programs. When "Phase 3" of the ICP is completed, there will be "full-infor-&#13;
mation" estimates available for about fifteen developing countries; the exact&#13;
number would depend on one's definition of a developing country. This would&#13;
be enough to allow use of regression analysis to develop short-cut estimates&#13;
for other developing countries.&#13;
Needless to say, the short-cut and limited information regression&#13;
approaclhes discussed above would have to be substantially revised if the&#13;
treatument of services is revised.&#13;
III. Conclusions&#13;
This paper has suggested the importance of human resource supply&#13;
in determining PPP incomes and has demonstrated its impact on short-cut and&#13;
combination short-cut limited-information estimates. Hopefully, the evolution&#13;
of research in this area will carry PPP income estimates well beyond what is&#13;
proposed here. It may be, for example, that there are some variables which&#13;
will serve as proxies for human-resources supply but add additional informa-&#13;
tion; or, as suggested above, the human-resource and KHS approaches may be&#13;
reconcilable. The availability of "full information" price data for thirty-&#13;
four countries under the ongoing third phase of the ICP project will help&#13;
to broaden the basis for short-cut, limited information and comtination&#13;
approaches.&#13;
*    Prof. Kravis has pointed out that reducing international income compari-&#13;
sons on the basis of only a few prices would defeat much of the purpose&#13;
of the comparisons. However, the ICP category of traded goods is quite&#13;
broad, so this problem (rather than the disputed problem of how to treat&#13;
services) should not arise.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
However, we have also seen that the ICP treatment of non-traded&#13;
goods, which is the key determinant of variance in the deviation index at&#13;
any given income level, has major limitations. This is not to say that the&#13;
ICP treatment is "wrong." It follows the accepted practice for international&#13;
price comparisons* (which grew from initial attempts to compare incomes among&#13;
relatively similar European economies). The problem, rather, derives from&#13;
the well-known theoretical problem of making cardinal comparisons of inter-&#13;
personal utility. There is no unique "correct" set of weights (prices).&#13;
Those that best answer questions relating to how much an international&#13;
traveler would have to pay for a given basket of goods and services may not&#13;
be those that best answer questions relating to inter-country comparisons.&#13;
Specifically, the ICP approach appears to overstate the PPP incomes both of&#13;
poor countries in relation to those of rich countries and, among poor coun-&#13;
tries, of those whose services have been revalued upward the most. In other&#13;
words, it understates the relative poverty of low-income countries, particu-&#13;
larly of those in South Asia. Also, it would overstate the growth rates of&#13;
countries with rapid growth in public sector employment or other services.&#13;
These problems suggest caution in use of the KHS estimates for international&#13;
income comparisons, at least for low income countries, until they can be&#13;
resolved.&#13;
There are also a few problems with the ICP data. It is even more&#13;
difficult, for example, to control for the quality of services (and thus&#13;
to compare like "quantities" of a given service among countries) than in&#13;
the case of commodities. For instance, the ICP data shows that dental&#13;
services in Kenya cost 100 times those in India; this raises the question&#13;
of whether the Kenyan data may not be more middle-class oriented than the&#13;
Indian data.&#13;
In spite of these problems, though, the landmark work of the ICP&#13;
project provides an important tool to improve our understanding of relative&#13;
prices and incomes. With some change in the treatment of services, their&#13;
PPP estimates would become more directly useful as a partial substitute for&#13;
conventional income estimates. The other data problems do not appear major&#13;
and can probably be handled effectively as more experience is gained in&#13;
implementing the ICP approach.&#13;
Also, in spite of the arguments above, the KHS PPP estimates may&#13;
be a relatively utseful index of welfare, or of meeting "basic needs," in&#13;
poor countries. In particular, the supply of trained people tends to be&#13;
related not just to PPP incomes, but to the cost and coverage of education&#13;
and health programs and to education and health status. Thus, the second-&#13;
ary enrollmer-t ratio used in the regression analysis presented here is&#13;
closely correlated with literacy, which is a determinant, along with per&#13;
capita income, of infant mortality and life expectancy. For example, while&#13;
*    See Sen (1979) for a wide-ranging review of economic issues relevant to&#13;
international price comparisons.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
the ICP treatment of services is argued here to overstate India's PPP income,&#13;
in so doing it provides a useful, if inexact, indicator of the differences&#13;
between sub-Saharan Africa and India in death and birth rates and in liter-&#13;
acy. The KHS PPP estimates may thus serve as an unintended halfway house&#13;
between traditional GDP estimates and direct measures of meeting basic&#13;
needs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX TABLE A&#13;
Page 1 of 4&#13;
ALternate -stimates of GDP Rer Capita in 1970 (US$)&#13;
Short Cut&#13;
Human     Krav i s&#13;
Kravis   Resources&#13;
Country   Conventional af     Short   Short      Col.4&#13;
-- C u                                SI         .     --&#13;
( I )          (2)           (3)     i 4 )     (S)&#13;
------------ -------- ---------------- ---P--- ---- ------ -&#13;
I Y, t NYA             143           350     334      0.96&#13;
2  INDI)It              99           291     308       1. 06&#13;
3  PI,ILIPPUIES        185           475     559       1. 18&#13;
4  KOR;A               258           630     702       1.11&#13;
5  COLOMB IA           347           939     778       O. 5&#13;
6  1 ALAYSIA           388           826     905       1.09&#13;
7  IRAM                401           892     8S2       1.00&#13;
8  HUUNGA,Y           1035          2018    1935      0. 9&#13;
9  ITALY              1720          2321    2598       1. 12&#13;
10  dAPAN              1906          274     2935       1 . 0&#13;
I t U. PI .           2 189          2999    3061       1.02&#13;
12  NETHERL,'JIDS     2.433          29'33   3265      1.09&#13;
13  .ELGI ;UM         2639           2982    3464       1. 16&#13;
14  PRANCE            ,278.          34,29   3508       1.02&#13;
15  GERMANY           3070           3562    3603       1 01&#13;
16  USA               4790           4790    4750      0.99&#13;
17  BiU I U1           47             --      87        --&#13;
18 MALI.                54            140     120      0.86&#13;
19  UPPER VOLTA\        59            160     106      0.66&#13;
20  RWANDA               60           162     122      0.75&#13;
21  BURUtID              67           195     135      O.69&#13;
22 BANGLADESH            69           191     208       1.09&#13;
23  1.L1 [O  6t           9            --     149         --&#13;
24  F.TriIOPiA           72           1930    163      0. 86G&#13;
25  Ci4AD                74           186     148      O.SO&#13;
26  L[S01 Hl3            74           181     185      1.02&#13;
27 (AALAWI               74           193     14p8     0.7G&#13;
28  YEMEN AR             7*3           --     133        - -&#13;
29 N4EPAtL               77            - -    200&#13;
30  B3URM1A              78           210 O    4        1 .1i6&#13;
31  1 DOCNESIA           79           2- 4 5  224      0.91&#13;
32 GUIINEA               E2           205     22V       1.A0&#13;
33  BENI N               82          :209     190      0.91&#13;
3 4  AFGHtANI S- NtJ     83            35     209      0.89&#13;
35  ZAIP.E               88           237     224     O.95&#13;
,3 6  S0MALI A           &amp;9           22 1     1 96    0.89&#13;
37 NIGER                 90           234     154      0.66&#13;
38  MALDI V ES;          92            -- --&#13;
39  1HAITI               97            --     225        --&#13;
40  YF'.1EN PCU'R        99            --     253        - -&#13;
41 T A N;.:f            I00           ;:252   205      0.81&#13;
42  GAMBI A             101           258     24 C     0.96&#13;
43  Ci C0).D5;          1 0:           --     236        --&#13;
44  C. TfNUL)P          108            --     179&#13;
a/   Source:   KHS, 1978&#13;
b/   Source:   Table 1, Eq. 1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Page 2 of 4&#13;
Alternate Estimates of GDP Per Capita in lD70 (US$)&#13;
Short Cut&#13;
Human     Kravis&#13;
Kravis RcsouLrces&#13;
Country   Conventional /      Short   Short       Col.4&#13;
---------------------------------               t--             -&#13;
( )(2)                   (3)     ¢4)y&#13;
--------   ---------o----------------------- -----------------&#13;
45  KHM,1ER REP.        126           351      --         --&#13;
46  CEN1.AF,REP.        127           319     273      0.8G&#13;
47  MADAGASCAR          133           334     328      0.98&#13;
48  TOGO                134           339     304      0.90&#13;
49  UG, 3ANDA           i35           330     297      0.90&#13;
50  SUD)AN              139           347     312      0.90&#13;
51  NIlGERIA            145           357     293      0.82&#13;
52  DOTS'WANA           150           343     340       0.99&#13;
53  TO;;GA              165            -.      - -        --&#13;
54  V'AU2 r TANI A      165           399     286      0.72&#13;
55  SIERRA LEONE        167           420     379      0.90&#13;
56  PAKISTAN            t76           434     427      0.98&#13;
57  SAMOA               177            --      --         --&#13;
58  SRI LANKA           179           457     547       1.20&#13;
59  Tli1A ILAND         180           443     451       1.02&#13;
60  CAMEROON            185           446     410      0.92&#13;
Gi SO J'MONU I S.       200&#13;
62  BOLIVIA             206           461     5 19      1.13&#13;
63  SENEGAL             216          5r21     4.79     0.92.&#13;
64  EGYPT               217           514     583       1.13&#13;
65 MAOROCCO             224           540     508      0.94&#13;
66  MOZARBIQUE          228            --     433         --&#13;
67 MAURITIUS            233           547     632       1.15&#13;
68  S1. VINCEINT        234            --      --&#13;
69  S.VIET NAM          235           628      --         --&#13;
70  CONGO               238           545     57 0      1.04&#13;
71 PARAGUAY             249           598     578      0.97&#13;
72  JORDAM              255           578     662       1.15&#13;
73  GHANA               257           629     546      0.87&#13;
74  GUIIiEA-fI5.       261            --     496         --&#13;
75  S T  KI1TS          26t            --      --         --&#13;
76  EQ. GCUINEhA        264            --     603         --&#13;
77  ECUADOR             268           628     659       1.05&#13;
78  LJBEfIA             268           604     544       0.90&#13;
79  SYRIA               269           616     711       1.15&#13;
80  SWAZILAND           270           554     626       1.13&#13;
81  PAPUiA              280           639     550       0.86&#13;
82  TUISIST             231           658     668       f.01&#13;
83  RHODESIA            283            .       --         --&#13;
84  HONDURA S           285           618     600       0.97&#13;
85  DOM INICA           286            --      --         -&#13;
EG  EL SALVADOR         231           672     679       1.01&#13;
87  A N'GCOLA           297            --     587         --&#13;
88  Sf. LJCIA           308            --      --&#13;
89  ALGEFRIA            324           716     648       0.91&#13;
-                                           ..... --.... . --... ... -.- .... --.--.......-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Page 3 of 4&#13;
Alternate Estimates of GDP Per Capita in 1970 (US$)&#13;
Short Cut&#13;
Human     KravIs&#13;
Kravis   Resources&#13;
Country    Conventional af     Short   Shor        Col.4&#13;
- - - -t - - - ------------------------------SL~ -J a&#13;
( I )           t 2)          (3)      4)         5&#13;
--                                          - - -   - - - - - - -&#13;
90  PERU                332            780     82 1     1 . 05&#13;
91  IVORY COAST         347            739     081      0.92&#13;
92  GRENADA             349             --      --        -&#13;
93  ANT GIJA            349             --      --&#13;
94  TURKEY              36 5           880     836      0 .5&#13;
95  DON. REPUB.        366            820     781      0.95&#13;
£6  GUYANA              371            797     935      1.17&#13;
97  GUATEM4ALA          373            847     718      0.85&#13;
98  OMAN                380            809       - -&#13;
99 I fAQ               382            807     841      1.04&#13;
100  ZA,'IATt.           421            926     794      0.86&#13;
101  BEILIZE             422             --                --&#13;
102  FIJI                4-23          880      961      1.09&#13;
103  NJI CAPAGUA         453           956      899      0 94&#13;
104  COOK IS.            465             --      --        --&#13;
105  BRAZIL.             493           1100    1026      0.9?&#13;
106  MAONTSFRRAT         498             --      --        --&#13;
107  SAUDI ARABIA        498           10O1     847      0.85&#13;
108  COSTA PICA          565           1113    1133      1.02&#13;
109  LEBANON             604           1165    1262.     1.08&#13;
11O  BARBADOS            604           1147    1381      1 .20&#13;
111  MEXICO              661           1243    1203      0.97&#13;
112  GABON               671           1247    1134      0.91&#13;
113  JAMAA ICA           685           1288    1472     1t14&#13;
t14  MAALTA              690           1311    1440      1.10&#13;
115  PORTUGAL            709           1290    1496      1.16&#13;
16  CHiLE               714           1477    1/03      0.95&#13;
117  GUADELOUPE          723             --    1485        --&#13;
118  PANAMA              733           1341    1434      1.07&#13;
119  S. AF'RICA          752           1293    1262      0.Sc&#13;
120  REUNION             77S             --    1501        --&#13;
121  HqONG KONG          '771          1303    1489      1.14&#13;
122  SUR r1NAM           795             --      --         -&#13;
123  URUGUAY             848           1713    i678      0.92&#13;
124  MARTINi1 QUE       8G2             --    t596        --&#13;
125  CYP'RUS             862           1509    ;G368     1.06&#13;
126  TRInIJDAD           877           1560    16iS       1.04&#13;
127  SINGAPORE           915           151°    1;694     1.12&#13;
128  ARGENTINA          1054           2013    1778      0.88&#13;
129  SPAIN              1087           1903    1953       1.03&#13;
130  AFARS &amp; ISS.       1102             --      --         -&#13;
131  VENEZUELA          1126           2004    1815 1    0.92&#13;
132  GFEECE             1135           1862    2082       1  2&#13;
133  BA HPA.            1135             --      --&#13;
134  VIRCIN IS.         1250             --&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Page 4 of 4&#13;
Alternate Estimates of GDP Per Capita in 1970 (US$)&#13;
Short Cut&#13;
Human     KravIs&#13;
KravIs    Resources&#13;
Country    Conventional a/     Short    hor      ' Co.4&#13;
( I)            (2)          (3)      j4)        (5)&#13;
--------    ------   ----------------------------------- -    --&#13;
135  IRELAND            1336           2045    2352       1.15&#13;
I3G  N. AtJTILLES       1375             --      --        --&#13;
137  BRUNE I            110              -       '-- I&#13;
138  LIBYA              1868           2559    2246       0.88&#13;
139  ISRAEL             19.30          -703    2482      0.92&#13;
140  AUSTRIA            1930           2490    2857       1.15&#13;
141  PUERTO RICO        2055             --    2935         --&#13;
142  FR. POLYNES.       2108             --      --         --&#13;
143  NEW LFALAND        2237           3037    3135       1.02&#13;
144  F INL. AND         2251           3017    3146       1.04&#13;
145  ICELAND            2.424          3224    3318       1.03&#13;
146  NORWAY             2874           3276    3 37       t.11&#13;
147  AUSTRALIA          2946           3329    3556       1.07&#13;
148- LUXEMBOURG         3137             --    3525         --&#13;
149  DENMARK            3157           3504    3766       1.07&#13;
150  SWITZERLAND        3195           3482    3677       1.06&#13;
15$  N. CALEDGCNIA      3243&#13;
152  C(UW]AIT           3593           3736    3868       1.04&#13;
153  CANADA             3885           3924    4031       1.03&#13;
154  SWEDEN             411O           4151    4232       1.02&#13;
155  QATAR              4354             -        -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
APPENDIX B&#13;
Reestimation of the Clague and Tanzi Data for&#13;
Thirteen OECD Countries in 1960&#13;
Reestimated Results&#13;
1.  Inverse Specification                                                                       -2&#13;
(to replicate that in        l/Dev.  =  59.076 +  .0197Y                  -0.0567EDUC      R    =   .937&#13;
Eq. 3, below)                          (28.35)b/   (11.22)               (-2.75)           s.e. = 2.70&#13;
831+l.4nY-2                                -2&#13;
2.  Log Specification            Ln D    =  -8.313 +   1.324LnY   0.116(Lnn) + .0872Ln(EDUC)    R    =  .924&#13;
(-3.76)    ( 2.17)        (-2.63)          (2.23)   s.e. = 0.037&#13;
Comparable Clague and Tanzi Result&#13;
3.  Clague and Tanzi                                                                            -2&#13;
Eq. 1 (in their Table 3)    l/Dev      69.08 +   0.0196DY   +  0.0967 EDUC    (6.28)       R    =  .937&#13;
c/       (11.20)                                       c/&#13;
a/   t statistic&#13;
b/   Not reported in Clague and Tanzi&#13;
Dependent variable: DEV = Ratio of PPP to conventional GDP&#13;
Independent variables: Y = Conventional per capita GDP in 1960&#13;
EDUC    (5 x Seccndary enrollment + 1 x higher enrollment)/6&#13;
DY  =  Residual from regressing Y on EDUC&#13;
Source of data:  Clague and Tanzi, p. 16.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
References&#13;
Ahluwalia, M.S. and Chenery, H.B., "Tle Economic Framework," in H.B. Chenery,&#13;
et al., Redistribution with Growth, London: Oxford University Press,&#13;
1974.&#13;
Clague, Christopher and Vito Tanzi, "Human Capital, Natural Resources and&#13;
the Purchasing Power Parity Doctrine: Some Empirical Results,"&#13;
Economia Internazionale, Vol. 25, No. 2 (February 1972).&#13;
Kravis, I.B., Heston, A., and Summers, R., United Nations International&#13;
Comparison Project: Phase II; International Comparisons of Real&#13;
Product and Purchasing Power, Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University&#13;
Press, 1978.&#13;
Kravis, I.B., Heston, A., and Summers, R., "Real GDP Per Capita for More&#13;
Than One Hundred Countries," Economic Journal 88 (June 1978), 215-242.&#13;
Kuznets, S. "Problems in Comparing Present Growth Rates for Developed and&#13;
Less Developed Countries," Economic Development and Cultural Change,&#13;
20 (Jan 1972), 185-209.&#13;
Sen, Amartya, "The Welfare Basis of Real Income Comparisons: A Survey,"&#13;
Journal of Economic Literature, XVII (March 1979), 1-45.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
RECENT PAPERS IN THIS SERIES&#13;
No.                   TITL E OF PAPER                         AUTHOR&#13;
322    Ability in Pre-Schoolers, Earnings, and              R. Grawe&#13;
Home-Environment&#13;
323    Priorities in Education: Pre-School;                 M. Smilansky&#13;
Evidence and Conclusions                             (consultant)&#13;
324    Tropical Root Crops and Rural Development            T. Goering&#13;
325    Costs and Scale of Bus Services                      A.A. Walters&#13;
326    Social and Cultural Dimensions of Tourism            R. Noronha&#13;
(consultant)&#13;
327    Investment in Indian Education: Uneconomic?          S. Heyneman&#13;
328    Nutrition and Food Needs in Developing               0. Knudsen&#13;
Countries                                            P.L. Scandizzo&#13;
329    The Changing International Division of               B. Balassa&#13;
Labor in L-nufactured Goods&#13;
330    Application of Shadow Pricing to Country             L. Squire&#13;
Economic Analysis with an Illustration from          I.M.D. Little&#13;
Pakis tan&#13;
331    A Survey of the Fertilizer Sector in India           B. Bumb (consultant)&#13;
332    Monitoring and Evaluation in the PIDER               M. Cernea&#13;
Rural Development Project - Mexico&#13;
333    Determinants of Private Industrial                   A. Pinell-Siles&#13;
Investment in India&#13;
334    The "Graduation" Issue in Trade Policy               I. Frank&#13;
Toward LDCs                                           (consultant)&#13;
335    Balancing Trickle Down and Basic Needs               M. Selowsky&#13;
Strategies: Income Distribution Issues&#13;
in Large Middle-Income Countries with&#13;
Special Reference to Latin America&#13;
336    Labor Force, Employment and Labor Markets            L. Squire&#13;
in the Course of Economic Development&#13;
337    The Population of Thailand:  Its Growth               S. Cochrane&#13;
and Welfare&#13;
338    Capital Market Imperfections and Economic            V.V. Bhatt&#13;
Development                                           A.R. Roe&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
No.                   TITLE OF PAPER                          AUTHOR&#13;
339    Behavior of Foodgrain Production                     J. Sarma&#13;
and Consumption in India, 1960-77&#13;
340    Electric Power Pricing Policy                        M. Munasinghe&#13;
341    State Intervention in the Industrialization          A. Choksi&#13;
of Developing Countries: Selected Issues&#13;
342    Policies for Efficient and Equitable                 J. Linn&#13;
Growth of Citites in Developing Countries&#13;
343    The Capital Goods Sector in LDCs: A Case             J. Datta Mitra&#13;
for State Intenrention?&#13;
344    International Technology Transfer:  Issues           F. Stewart&#13;
and Policy Options&#13;
345    Family Planning Programs:  An Evaluation             R. Cuca&#13;
of Experience&#13;
346    Prospects for Traditional and Non-                   D. Hughart&#13;
Conventional Energy Sources in&#13;
Developing Countries&#13;
347    National Urbanization Policies in Developing         B. Renaud&#13;
Countries&#13;
348    Private Direct Foreign Investment in                 K. Billerbeck&#13;
D.eveloping Countries                                Y. Yasugi (consultants)&#13;
349    Adjustment Policies and Problems in                  M. Wolf&#13;
Developed Countries&#13;
350    Energy Options and Policy Issues in                  T. Byer&#13;
Developing Countries                                 D. Fallen-Bailey&#13;
351    Growth and Equity in Semi-Industrialized             J. Bergsman&#13;
Countries&#13;
352    Capital Flows and Developing Country Debt            J. Katz&#13;
353    Trade Policy for Developing Countries                D. Keesing&#13;
354    Development Problems of Mineral-Exporting            G. Nankani&#13;
Countries&#13;
355    The Global Framework                                 R. Cheetham, S. Gupta&#13;
A. Schwartz&#13;
356    The Distribution of Income in Brazil                 G. Pfefferman, R. Webb&#13;
357    Estimating Shadow Prices for Colombia in             W. Schohl&#13;
an Input-Output Table Framework&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1555089">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1979/09/1555089/inter-country-comparison-real-ppp-incomes-revised-estimates-unresolved-questions
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1979/09/1555089/inter-country-comparison-real-ppp-incomes-revised-estimates-unresolved-questions</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1979/09/1555089/inter-country-comparison-real-ppp-incomes-revised-estimates-unresolved-questions</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-12T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-12T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/10/14/000178830_9810190340347/Rendered/INDEX/SWP358000Inter0unresolved0questions.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/10/14/000178830_9810190340347/Rendered/PDF/SWP358000Inter0unresolved0questions.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1979-09-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2002-03-30T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Inter-country comparison of
            "Real" (PPP) incomes : revised estimates and
            unresolved questions
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Adjusting for purchasing power parities
            of national currencies makes a significant difference to
            inter-country income comparisons. However, PPP estimates
            require detailed price data which are not readily available
            for most countries. Kravis, Heston and Summers have used
            regression analysis to extend their PPP estimates from the
            sixteen countries for which they have detailed prices to any
            country for which data are available on the share of trade
            in GDP and on inflation. The first part of this paper argues
            that a variant of this short-cut approach, one which relies
            on measures of human resource development rather than on
            trade and inflation, is preferable on theoretical and
            statistical grounds. The second part of the paper raises a
            more fundamental issue. It argues that the treatment of
            services in their detailed analysis, and hence in any
            short-cut approach derived from it, is biased. This bias
            tends to exaggerate the PPP incomes of countries with
            relatively good human resource development, and so produces
            misleading estimates of relative incomes among poor
            countries and of the gap between poor and rich countries.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Inter-country comparison of "Real"
            (PPP) incomes : revised estimates and unresolved questions
        </docna>
        <display_title>Inter-country comparison of
            "Real" (PPP) incomes : revised estimates and
            unresolved questions</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1979/09/1555089/inter-country-comparison-real-ppp-incomes-revised-estimates-unresolved-questions</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>General Technology,Transport Security,Educational Technology and Distance Education,Information and Records Management,Information Technology</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Education,Information and Communication Technologies,Transport</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>ISENMAN, P.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_9810190340347</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other Public Sector Management</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 358</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Education,Information and Communication Technologies,Transport</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Public Administration, Law, and Justice</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Gross domestic product; Human resources; Per
            capita income; Prices; Purchasing power parity; Regression
            analysis; Allocation of resources
            HTML,HTTP,Port,server,URL
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP358</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Policy Making Policy Coordination</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Birth Spacing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Educational Technology and Distance Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Radio, Television Instruction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Distance Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education for the Knowledge Economy</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT and Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Capital</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing People</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Employment and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Improving Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Market Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets, Job Creation and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Policy Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Family Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education and Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Reconciliation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Secondary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education and ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>